Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to Apple Park.
My name is John Tegtmeyer,
and I'm an engineer working on AppKit.
Later today, I'll be joined
by my colleague Jeff Nadeau,
and we're both really excited
to walk you through the new look of macOS.
As you may have seen,
macOS has an all-new design...
which includes a dramatic update
to the appearance and structure
of Mac apps,
including full-height sidebars
with colorful icons
and updated symbol iconography.
An all-new toolbar with inline title,
big bold controls
and integration
with the split-view sections below.
And an updated appearance
for lists of content,
featuring a new inset selection style.
Now, this is a big change,
and you might be wondering
what it means for your app.
The great news is that many of these
design changes happen automatically.
With the frameworks
doing the heavy lifting,
your native Mac app will look great
on macOS Big Sur out of the box.
But with a bit of adoption,
you can go the extra mile
and really shine.
And that's what we're here
to talk about today.
This new design is broken down
into three main sections.
First, updates to the structure
of your window,
elements like the sidebar and toolbar,
which will set your app up for success.
Next is some great new features
in the line of controls.
And finally, symbol images,
which have come to macOS.
Let's start things off with the updates
to sidebars and toolbars.
Perhaps one
of the most eye-catching updates
is the beautiful new full-height sidebar,
seen here in Mail.
Your app may get this for free
just by building on Big Sur,
and that's because it takes advantage
of existing APIs.
Specifically, make sure
your sidebar is built
using an NSSplitViewController,
and the SplitViewItem is configured
using the sidebar behavior.
The second piece of API
is the fullSizeContentView window mask.
This will allow content to be laid out
under the space
normally reserved for the title bar.
If you're not already taking advantage
of the fullsizeContentView style,
it's even easier to adopt
in macOS Big Sur.
NSView now exposes several different ways
to find the safe area of your View.
These new safe areas
are also available to you
through Interface Builder.
Just check the new box
in the Size Inspector
for Safe Area Layout Guide.
Then you'll find a Safe Area Layout Guide
in your View, ready to use.
If you're creating a new Mac app
in Interface Builder,
there's a neat object in the Catalog
that creates a preconfigured sidebar.
This will set up a split view controller
with a sidebar
and automatically adjust your window
for the fullsizeContentView.
No extra configuration is required.
In rare circumstances,
you may not want a full-height sidebar.
There's a new property
on NSSplitViewItem
which will allow you to opt out.
You may consider this
if your sidebar is typically collapsed
or if your toolbar is crowded
and you need more space.
But please note that this property
only affects items
with the sidebar behavior.
The sidebar has also gained
a splash of color
with new colorful icons.
By default, all sidebar icons
are colored with the accent color,
but there's a new
NSOutlineViewDelegate method
that you can use to customize it.
The delegate method returns
an instance of NSTintConfiguration,
which offers a few different
types of tint.
The first is the default configuration,
which uses the accent color.
The monochrome option
provides a colorless appearance
similar to the sidebar icons in Catalina.
PreferredColor allows you
to specify a color
that should be used
with the default accent color,
but should change to follow
the accent color if it's customized.
For example, Mail's teal folders
complement the default accent color
of blue nicely,
but would clash with a red accent.
Finally, fixedColor specifies
a color that never changes.
A great example is Mail's VIP folder,
which is always a yellow star.
You can use this feature to distinguish
the sections of your sidebar
in whatever way makes sense for your app.
You can also use it to strongly associate
a color with a particular item,
or use the monochrome option
to de-emphasize
the secondary groups in your sidebar
in order to draw focus
towards what's important.
Next, I'd like to call your attention
to the toolbar.
Toolbars have a brand-new design
in Big Sur.
Notice how there's no longer
any visible material behind the items.
Instead, it looks uniform
with the content of the window.
This is something
you'll get automatically.
In addition to the new
visual appearance of the toolbar,
there are also
many new styles of toolbars.
Each has been purpose-built to either
make an impactful presence in the window
or scale back
and allow the content to take focus.
There's a new property on NSWindow
called toolbarStyle,
which controls these new looks.
First is a unified style,
which is the new standard look
of toolbars.
This style emphasizes
the controls in the toolbar.
See how they're larger
and the icons are bold.
It also supports the new inline title,
which is placed at the leading edge
of the toolbar, next to the sidebar.
As this is the new standard look
of the toolbar,
it's a good choice for most windows
that don't meet requirements
from the other styles.
Its larger controls and streamlined title
can help your app look great
in the new look of macOS.
A variation of the unified style
is the unified compact style.
This style has a more compressed layout
with regular-sized controls
and a smaller toolbar height.
This is the look
that's been used in the past
if your window was configured
to hide the window's title.
In Big Sur, this style now supports
an optional inline title.
You may choose to use this style
when the user's focus is primarily
on the content of the window
and your toolbar isn't heavily populated.
The new preference style
is specifically designed
for the preference window of your app.
It complements
the selectable icons in the toolbar,
giving them similar sizes
and centering them,
which gives a nice,
uniform look to the window.
Now, what's really cool
is that this preference style
will be used without any adoption
if you're using an NSTabViewController
with the toolbar TabStyle.
Start using this class for your preference
window, if you aren't already,
because it makes switching tabs
really easy
and gives you this new look for free.
The expanded style
is one you may be familiar with
because it used to be
the standard layout of the toolbar.
Notice how the title of the window
is placed on top of the toolbar
and the title can expand
across the window if necessary.
This style is recommended
when your window title is long
or your toolbar
is heavily populated by items.
It's also a good choice
if you need to maintain compatibility
with your existing toolbar construction.
Finally, we have the automatic style,
which will use your window structure
to determine which style to choose.
This is the default value
and will maintain existing layout
for your pre-Big Sur linked apps.
Controls in the toolbar
also have a brand-new design
requiring absolutely no adoption.
Notice how they no longer show a border
behind them during normal usage.
But when the mouse is hovered
over the control,
we see the border pop back in,
giving some nice visual feedback.
While most controls
won't have any border around them,
controls with text
will have a stroke border
surrounding the edge of the control.
This helps define which areas
of the toolbar are empty
and will allow dragging the window.
Another change affecting controls
is the new large size used
by the unified toolbar style.
You'll find both the control,
as well as the icon,
to be larger and use a heavier weight.
Because of this new control size,
you may find some of your buttons
to have clipping on one or more sides.
This is likely because
the min and maxSizes
defined on the ToolbarItem
are now too small.
These properties are being deprecated
in favor of letting AppKit
measure your views automatically.
This has been possible since Mojave,
so in most cases,
you can remove those calls entirely.
It's the easiest kind of adoption.
Of course, you can use constraints
if you need more control
over the size of the items.
You may have already noticed
another enhancement
to the inline title and the toolbar.
Mail has displayed
the unread message count
right under the window title,
in a smaller font.
This is made possible
by the new subtitle property on NSWindow.
This is a great way to display
secondary text, like an unread count.
In the unified toolbar style,
you will see this text
placed below the primary title,
which saves a lot of space.
Using this in the expanded style
will place the subtitle
next to the primary title,
separated automatically.
And speaking of the window title,
if your toolbar contains controls,
such as back and forward,
these items belong
to the leading edge of the window.
With the new navigational property
on NSToolbarItem,
you can specify these items
and the system will take care of the rest.
Navigation items have special behavior
when customizing the toolbar as well.
These items can be customized
into and out of the toolbar,
but they can't be moved
out of this title-leading position.
One specific control in the toolbar
which is getting an all-new experience
is the search control.
When the window is large enough,
the full search field is shown as normal,
but when the window is compressed down,
the search field
is collapsed down into a button.
Clicking this button
will expand the search field back out.
This ensures
that search is always available
no matter the size of the window.
Now, to accomplish this behavior,
a new item has been added,
called the NSSearchToolbarItem.
This item has been designed
to make adoption as easy as possible,
allowing you to keep
your existing search field.
Here's some existing code
you may have in your app.
Adoption of the new search item
can be done in as little as two steps.
First, change the class of the item
to be an NSSearchToolbarItem.
Next, rather than setting
the item's View property,
instead set the item's
searchField property.
And with those two small changes,
you have a brand-new search experience.
In Interface Builder,
you'll find that a search item
has been added to the object Catalog.
The really amazing part is that this
object maintains backwards compatibility.
When your app is run on an older system,
a standard search field will be used
just as it is today.
There's no need to do any run-time checks.
And with just a few code changes,
you've adopted full-height sidebars,
a brand-new toolbar style
and adjusted the layout of the items.
Many of these features
require no changes at all.
But you can take adoption
to the next level,
making your window take full advantage
of the new look of macOS.
Consider the Mail app.
Notice how there are items in the toolbar
that align with sections of content
in the window.
The dividers of the split view
reach up to the top of the window,
creating these beautiful
full-height sections.
As the dividers are resized,
the toolbar items follow.
This gives useful context to the controls,
showing what content they will act on.
Now, just because adoption of these
toolbar sections goes the extra mile
doesn't mean it requires a lot of work.
They're created using the new
NSTrackingSeparatorToolbarItem.
Each item is configured
to track a specific divider,
and the toolbar does the rest.
During customization,
these sections are not removable,
but the content of the sections
can be customized.
Creating one of these items
requires just one line of code.
Create the item using the constructor
and assign it a split view to track
and specify which divider
of that split view
it should be aligned with.
If you don't have access to the split view
during the item's creation, that's okay.
Just assign it before the window is shown.
You can also use this new tracking item
to place controls
over a full-height sidebar.
To make this easier, AppKit has added
a new standard item identifier,
which will discover
the full-height sidebar automatically.
Toolbar items placed before the separator
will appear over the full-height sidebar.
You may have noticed that the toolbar
doesn't have a divider below it anymore.
But that's not always true though.
A shadow will automatically appear
between the toolbar and scrolled content
to create a visual pocket
where the content trails off.
This happens in each section of the window
with a scroll view.
In order to see this behavior,
make sure your scroll view
completely fills the frame of the section.
You'll also need to be using
the full-size content mask
that we talked about earlier.
Otherwise, you'll see a separator
regardless of whether or not
content is scrolled.
If you'd like to explicitly request
a separator instead of the scroll shadow,
or maybe have no separator at all,
you can do that
using the titlebarSeparatorStyle
on each split view item.
This will allow you to specify
which sections get the scrolling pockets
and which should not.
Or you can specify a style
on the window as a whole.
Note that the style on the window
will supersede any styles
defined by split view items.
If you want control of the style
to be in the hands of the items,
make sure the window style
is set to "automatic."
Now, we've talked about some
really striking window-level features
of the new design.
These features have been baked directly
into NSToolbar
and NSSplitViewController.
If you aren't already taking advantage
of those classes,
now is a great time to let the system
start doing the heavy lifting for you.
And that's it
for setting up your window for success.
Next, Jeff Nadeau will guide you through
some exciting enhancements to controls.
Thanks, John.
Now that you've refined
your window structure,
let's look at what macOS Big Sur brings
to the controls inside your app.
System controls have taken on
a new and modern design in Big Sur,
and AppKit provides all of these updates
to your app automatically.
But there are a few control updates we
think you'll be especially excited about,
and the first is an update
to accent colors.
You're probably familiar
with the family of accent colors
that are available on macOS.
These colors affect all kinds
of UI elements, including controls,
selection backgrounds, focus rings
and more.
In macOS Big Sur,
we're adding a new choice of accent color,
and it's any color you want.
If there's a color
that's special to your app,
you can designate it
as your app's custom accent color.
And when this multicolor option is chosen
in persistent preferences,
your custom accent will apply
in all of the places that you'd expect.
And that includes controls,
list selections, sidebar icons,
menus and focus rings.
This is a great way for your app
to express its unique personality.
Setting up a custom accent color is easy.
It's all done in the asset catalog.
First, create a new named color
in your app's asset catalog.
For newly created apps,
Xcode will even add this for you.
Set up your color however you'd like.
You can alias one of the existing
system colors, or you can pick your own.
And don't forget that you can also choose
a different shade for Dark Mode.
Once you're happy with your color choice,
you can specify your accent color's name
in the project editor
so that Xcode's build system
can identify it.
And that's it.
Build and run your app on Big Sur
and you'll see your custom color
throughout the UI.
Now, remember, your custom accent color
applies only when the system preference
is set to multicolor.
We still want to support
a level of personalization
when it comes to accent colors
so that people have the option
to choose their favorite
and use it everywhere on their Mac.
For that reason, you should continue
to draw using the named system colors
instead of hard-coding your custom accent.
These colors follow the accent preference
automatically
and will make sure that you match
the rest of the system as needed.
We think that's gonna be a really fun way
for apps to express some personality.
Next, I want to talk about a new control
style we think will be pretty popular--
large controls.
The idea behind large controls is that
sometimes you just need a bigger button.
These are really common
in onboarding flows like this one
where there's a single call to action
right in the middle of the window.
This type of UI is increasingly popular,
and we know that a lot of apps
have had to build custom buttons
just to get this type of control.
Well, I'm happy to say that large controls
are now a standard control size,
so you'll be able to get a large button
just by setting the control size to large
and have the confidence that it will
always match the system theme.
It's not just buttons though.
While the large size is available
for most styles of button,
including both pop-up and pull-down,
it's also available for segmented
controls, text fields and search fields.
In fact, the most prominent place
where you'll see these
is in the new unified style of toolbar
that we looked at earlier,
which uses the large control size
for all of the items in the toolbar.
You'll also see large buttons
in system alerts,
where they prominently display
the available actions on the alert.
Next up, I want to talk
about one control in particular,
and that's sliders.
Sliders have a new look on macOS Big Sur.
In this new style,
tick marks appear inline on the track,
unifying the layout between sliders
with and without tick marks.
This new look is applied automatically
when you build against the new SDK,
so there's a couple things
you'll want to know about it.
For one, it might have an impact
on your layout.
If you previously had a configuration
where you've manually aligned a label
to the track portion of the slider,
once your app is opted into the new style,
you might find
that your label doesn't line up anymore
since the track and tick marks
now sit differently
within the frame of the control.
The solution here is to baseline
align your label to the slider.
Slider calculates a baseline offset that's
appropriate for any adjacent label text.
This technique works on Catalina, too,
so you can configure your constraints once
and get clean label placement
on both versions.
Next up, let's take a look
at some of the updates to table views.
You might have noticed
this new look for table selections
in some of our screenshots.
This is the new inset style
that we've added to NSTableView.
The inset style applies some extra
horizontal padding around your cell views
and vertical padding
around the top and bottom rows.
It also has
a slightly taller default row height
and wider spacing in multicolumn tables.
You can control this styling using
the new style property on NSTableView.
There are four options built in.
The first, automatic,
is the default value,
and it chooses a style
based on the configuration of the table.
The fullWidth style displays
the selection edge-to-edge in the table,
just like it did on Catalina and previous.
Inset is the new inset style
that we just looked at,
and sourceList is specifically for the
new appearance of sidebar source lists.
The style property allows you
to configure which style you'd like,
and effectiveStyle
is a read-only property
which can tell you
how the automatic style is being resolved.
The automatic style resolve is based
on the configuration of the table view.
If it's in a sidebar,
it'll choose the sourceList appearance.
If the table is embedded
in a bordered scroll view,
it'll use the fullWidth style.
And, otherwise, it defaults to using
the new inset style.
Since the inset style
might affect your layout,
it's only used for apps that are built
using the new SDK.
However, sidebars always use
the new sourceList style.
The new style property completely replaces
the old sourceList selection
highlight style.
So, when you're setting up a sourceList,
you should prefer the new style property,
and so we've soft-deprecated
the old highlight style.
Now that your content lists
are looking great,
let's take a turn
and talk about the typography in your app.
The big news here is that text styles
have come to macOS.
You might have seen this hierarchy
of typographic styles on other platforms,
and now it's available
for your text content on macOS as well.
The sizes and weights have been adjusted
to fit the Mac design,
centering around
our standard body font size of 13 points.
It's important to remember that
this isn't the same thing as dynamic type,
so there's no slider that's going
to adjust these sizes system-wide.
Here's how you access
these system text styles and code.
You can either get an NSFont instance
using the preferredFontforTextStyle
options method,
or, if you'd like a font descriptor,
you can use preferredFontDescriptor
forTextStyle options instead.
And, of course,
the font picker and interface builder
has also added support for text styles.
Now that your controls
and typography are looking great,
let's focus our attention to iconography.
Those of you with keen eyes
might have noticed refreshed iconography
all across the system in macOS Big Sur,
and that's because
we've brought SF Symbols to the Mac.
That means that you have access
to our repertoire
of over 2,500 built-in symbol images
and also the option
to design your own symbols as well.
Symbol images are great
for building out iconography
that complements your app's typography
since they scale for the font size
and they adapt
to suit various font weights as well.
This makes them a natural partner
to the system text styles
that we looked at a moment ago.
It also means that symbol images can
easily adapt to different configurations.
For example, remember the large icons
in the new unified toolbar?
These icons are actually symbol images
set at a 13-point size, medium weight,
and using the large symbol scale.
Toolbar controls automatically configure
their symbol images
to match the size and style
of the toolbar.
So, if you use symbols,
you'll get a clean and consistent look
for any style of toolbar.
But that's not the only place
where we take advantage
of symbol images' versatility.
Symbols make for great sidebar icons,
and here we can see that NSOutlineView
automatically scales both the text labels
and the symbol images
to match the preferred sidebar size
in system preferences.
This makes it really easy to support
all three sizes in your sidebar.
You can access system symbols
using the new
init with systemSymbolName initializer.
When you create a system symbol,
you also have the opportunity
to provide an accessibility description,
which we strongly encourage.
You can also specify system symbols
in Interface Builder.
The menu provides a preview of each symbol
so you can find the exact one
that you're looking for.
When it comes to using symbol images
in your own UI,
the best method is to use NSImageView.
It knows how to properly resolve
the symbol image
against your preferred
typographic properties
and other factors like the display scale,
and it knows how
to most efficiently display symbol images.
We've added two new properties
to NSImageView
to help you configure your symbol image:
the symbol font and scale.
Image view also handles the unique
alignment properties of symbol images,
most importantly, the baseline.
When you use a symbol image
in NSImageView,
you can use auto layout to baseline align
the image to an adjacent label
so that they line up perfectly.
Symbol images typically resolve
their size, weight and scale
from the context that they're placed in.
So, for example,
a symbol image in a button
always matches the font of the button.
However, if you need
to manually specialize
some aspect of your symbol image,
you can use the new
withSymbolConfiguration method
to create a new NSImage
that embeds the relevant configuration.
You can create a symbol configuration
using a size, weight and scale,
or you can reference
one of our newly introduced text styles.
If you need
to manually draw a symbol image,
here's some important information
on how to align the geometry.
In the image's own coordinate space,
the glyph sits inside a bounding box
that's the same size
as the NSImageSize property.
Within that bounding box
is the alignment rect
which, for symbol images,
spans from the baseline to the cap height.
If you need to manually align
against one of these typographic features,
you can use the alignment rect
to adjust your drawing accordingly.
You should especially avoid using NSImage
directly in layer contents.
This has been problematic
for many versions of macOS,
but it's especially bad for symbols.
Once an image is set as layer contents,
it loses all of its context sensitivity,
and it won't be able to adapt
to things like display scale.
It's also difficult to properly size
and position the layer in this scenario,
which makes this a recipe
for blurry symbols.
It's better to just use NSImageView.
One final note on symbols.
We've updated
most of the existing named system images
to map directly to symbol images.
So, for example, if you ask
for NSImageNameShare template,
you'll get the square and arrow-up symbol.
This change might affect the drawing
or layout of these images in your app,
so we only do this mapping for apps
that are built against the new SDK.
This is something to keep an eye out for
once you've rebuilt your app for Big Sur.
Now, there's a lot of cool stuff here,
so let's review your next steps.
Once you've got your app building
against the new SDK,
start by making sure that you're getting
the full-height sidebar
so that you match
that modern window construction.
Then take a look at your toolbar
and consider which style
is right for your app.
If your window is based
on a split view construction,
you might also want to add split tracking
to your toolbar
so that you can divide it into those
clean, distinct sections that you see
in apps like Mail.
Next, consider defining a custom
accent color in your asset catalog.
This is a great way for your app
to express its personality.
And then, finally,
start using symbol images.
You now have access to a huge library
of high-quality, Apple-produced symbols,
which provide a lot of versatility
and go hand-in-hand with
the surrounding typography in your app.
macOS Big Sur is a huge update
to the design of macOS,
and we look forward to seeing
where you take this new design direction
in your own apps.
Thanks for watching.