Hello and welcome to WWDC.
-Hey, everyone. I'm Joe.
-And I'm Michael.
And we're both designers
on the Game Center design team.
We're here today to talk to you
about the new Game Center experience
and a whole lot of enhancements we've made
to make it more engaging and beautiful
for players.
This session will give you an overview
of how to design your game
to make the most
of Game Center's features.
[Joe Phillips] There are a number of
reasons to add Game Center to your game,
including social features,
where players can add friends
and manage their gaming identity.
Achievements and leaderboards
to encourage competition within your game
and keep your players
coming back for more.
And a rich multiplayer experience
for real time and turn-based games.
To help you take advantage of all of this,
we'll be talking in detail
about a number of things,
starting with the access point,
a consistent and recognizable way
for players to access Game Center
from within your game.
Let's take a look at this feature
by launching a game.
This is The Coast, an indie game
where you have to carefully direct ships
away from the shore
so they don't crash
and lose their precious cargo.
When your game launches,
the first thing you'll see
is the Game Center welcome banner.
When this goes away,
you'll notice a new UI element appear.
This is the access point,
a clear and easy way for players to access
their Game Center information on any game.
The player's avatar serves
as the access point for Game Center.
Tapping or clicking it at any point
will launch the new Game Center dashboard.
It's where players can check out
their profile, achievements, leaderboards
and other useful information
related to your game.
But we'll get to that in a minute.
You can choose to present
just the player's avatar
or pair it with bits of helpful
information we call "highlights."
These highlights surface
a player's Game Center data,
like achievement progress
and leaderboard positions.
The access point is pretty flexible.
You can place it in any corner of
the screen that works for your game's UI.
However, we'd recommend
placing it at top left, if possible.
And it works with how your game's designed
in both landscape and portrait.
You'll just want to make sure
none of your game's UI
encroaches upon the area
the access point takes
at its maximum size.
On iPhone 11 Pro,
the access point on portrait games
is 62 by 335 points.
We'd recommend leaving a safe area
of 114 points
from the top or bottom of the screen
that spans the full width.
And for landscape games,
it's 62 by 280 points.
It's best to leave a safe area
of 91 points
from the top or bottom of the screen
that spans the full width.
The access point is available
across other platforms.
You can find full details
on safe areas for other devices
in the Human Interface Guidelines.
Whenever possible, display your
access point at your game's main menu.
Placing it here gives players quick access
before they dive into your game.
Just be sure it appears at the right
moment within your game's launch sequence.
Let any splash screens
or cinematics finish
before displaying the access point,
along with your game's main menu.
If you can't place the access point
on your main menu,
you could find another place for it
that players return to in your game,
like on a level select screen
or in Settings.
As you can see, the access point
is designed to adapt to your game,
but think about how to design
your game's UI
to feel complementary
and fit naturally into the experience.
When the game starts,
it's a good idea to hide the access point
so players can focus on game play
and allow space
for any critical in-game controls.
The access point is the best,
most consistent way
for users to access Game Center
from within your game.
However, you can also link to Game Center
using your own custom UI.
We've provided different icon options
to be used within your game--
full color, white and black variants
in a variety of formats,
all of which you can find
in the Apple Design Resources.
Please use the iconography as provided
and don't alter it in any way.
If your custom deep link includes text,
please use the correct terminology,
Game Center,
and don't localize this term.
And that's the new access point.
Just a few things to remember:
Place the access point on your main menu
where possible.
Find the best corner
to display your access point.
Surface player information
with highlights.
And ensure safe areas
around your access point.
Joe, you're up.
Thanks, Michael.
Now let's move on
to the dashboard and profile.
Tapping the access point
will reveal the dashboard,
a jumping-off point
into each of the key areas
that make up
the new Game Center experience.
The dashboard is presented as
a transparent layer on top of your game,
and it shows through the color
of the screen behind it.
We recommend that you pause your game
or minimize
any overly distracting animations
when the dashboard is presented.
The dashboard, along with
the rest of the Game Center UI,
supports both landscape
and portrait orientation,
to respect the way
your game has been designed.
It has also been designed
to feel consistent across iOS,
iPadOS, macOS and tvOS.
On tvOS, you can also optionally
display artwork on the dashboard.
This really helps brand the experience
and makes it feel more integrated
into your game.
When choosing the artwork to display here,
please make sure that it comfortably
contrasts with the Game Center UI.
Consider using transparency
to let the background show through.
Make sure that the artwork
is simple, clear
and reads well at a distance.
The artwork you use here
shouldn't be your app icon.
Instead, use something different.
For example,
your game's logo or word mark.
Dashboard artwork is not focusable.
Here are the specifications
for uploading your dashboard artwork.
It must be a TIFF or a PNG file
to support transparency.
The image size should be
923 by 150 pixels at 1x...
1846 by 300 pixels at 2x,
at least 72 DPI
and in the sRGB color space.
The first section of the dashboard
provides access to the profile.
Tapping on this shows players a holistic
overview of their Game Center profile--
their friends, friend suggestions
and the ability
to access their achievements
across all of the games they have played.
The profile is always accessible
from the dashboard.
However, you can also optionally
provide a button inside your game
to link players directly
to the profile page.
This could be useful if you want to
encourage players to add more friends
so that they can better enjoy your game's
leaderboard or multiplayer experience.
If you want to provide a link
directly to the profile,
please use this icon.
You can style it to work with your game,
but do not alter the shape in any way.
To avoid confusion
with the design of the access point,
please don't use the player's
Game Center avatar for this purpose.
If pairing the link with text,
please use the correct language--
Game Center Profile
and not "profile" on its own,
"account" or anything else.
And as mentioned before, the term
Game Center should not be localized.
However,
you can localize the term "profile."
The accompanying tech session
for Game Center will go into detail
about how to link to the profile.
And that's the new dashboard and profile.
Let's review what we just talked about.
Remember to pause your game when
the Game Center user interface is open.
You can optionally provide
dashboard artwork for tvOS.
And if needed, you can link directly to
the Game Center profile from your game.
Now over to Michael for the next section.
And now on to my personal favorite update
to Game Center,
achievements,
which you'll find in the second section
of the dashboard.
I used to love collecting trading cards.
You just want to get them all,
and there's nothing like getting the ones
that are hard to find.
That's exactly why
we've redesigned achievements
as a collectible card format.
Here,
in the redesigned achievements section,
players will see a lineup of these cards,
representing your game's achievements,
which are now grouped
by "completed" and "locked."
There are different kinds of achievements.
Standard, which are earned straightaway
once the requirements are met.
Progressive, which give players
a sense of how far away they are
from unlocking an achievement.
And hidden,
in which the details remain a mystery
until the moment they're unlocked.
Think about how to make the most
of these achievement types
to improve the experience
of playing your game.
And when a player completes
any achievement,
an image appears
in the top portion of the card.
Make sure these images look awesome.
The Coast has all these great lighthouses
from around the world.
I got this one in Level 5.
The Passage Lighthouse is
in the Great Lakes near Mackinac Island.
This should be eye-catching,
complement your game's look and feel,
and make players feel rewarded
by getting something special.
It's a big step in keeping players
engaged in your game.
Stay away from using text
inside your artwork
and upload custom images
for each achievement.
Players love earning unique achievements
that remind them of each accomplishment.
And provide an opaque image
for each achievement.
The system automatically
crops the image into a circle,
so make sure
any primary content is centered.
Achievement images are for display only,
so they're not focusable.
Order your achievements in a way that
reflects the progress of your game play.
You're allowed up to 100 achievements
in a game.
Be selective about how many you provide.
It's good to only use what you need
to make your game challenging,
so earning every one feels rewarding.
And rather than offer all 100
in version one of your game,
leave room to add more in later releases
to give players a reason to come back.
There's just a few rules to consider
around achievement images.
It must be a JPEG, TIFF or PNG file,
512 by 512 pixels at 1x,
1024 by 1024 pixels at 2x,
at least 72 DPI
and in the sRGB color space.
You'll also need to include a title
and description text
for each of your achievements.
Make sure they're
as clear and succinct as possible
so players understand
how to earn an achievement at a glance.
And since achievement cards show
two lines of your title and description
before truncating,
try to keep your text under 30 characters
to guarantee it will work well
across devices.
Keep your titles initial caps,
your description sentence case
and avoid using all caps.
And for those final touches to copy,
include a second description
for when an achievement's been completed.
And make sure all copy is localized
depending on the country or region.
You can also choose to present
in-game achievement notifications
that give your players
an immediate sense of accomplishment.
We definitely recommend
you work these into your game.
Time these to display right
at that moment of completion.
Like here, in The Coast,
as soon as players clear the level.
If you'd like to give players
more direct access,
you can also provide a custom link into
the achievement section of Game Center.
If you'd like to use iconography,
use this,
which features the card representation.
You can style it to work
with your game's UI,
but don't alter the shape in any way.
Also just be consistent
in how you refer to them,
using the term "achievements"
and not "trophies" or "awards"
or anything else.
That's the new achievement experience.
Let's recap.
Use achievement types
to work with your game.
Design unique, eye-catching images.
Keep those descriptions
clear and succinct.
And incorporate in-game notifications
for some of that immediate reward.
Back over to you, Joe.
Thanks, Michael.
The next section of the dashboard
features your game's leaderboards.
A great place to encourage a player
to compete with their friends
and keep them coming back for more.
Tapping into this section
provides an overview
of all the leaderboards in your game.
We recommend that you create leaderboards
that best represent the core mechanics
of your game play.
They could be tied
to a specific score in your game.
For example, the longest distance traveled
or the total number of coins collected,
or alternatively, like in The Coast,
each of the leaderboards are tied to
a specific geographic region in the game.
Let's focus on the first leaderboard,
Crater Lake.
When designing your leaderboard imagery,
you should provide unique,
eye-catching artwork
that is recognizable at a glance.
Ensure that you use different artwork
for each leaderboard
so that players
can differentiate between them.
And also consider how your leaderboards
look alongside each other,
so that they feel complementary as a set.
For leaderboard image specifications,
images must be a JPEG,
a TIFF or a PNG file,
at 512 by 512 pixels at 1x,
1024 by 1024 pixels at 2x,
at least 72 DPI
and in the sRGB color space.
On tvOS, leaderboards
have a 16-by-9 aspect ratio.
They're also focusable and support
between one and three multilayer images
to provide a parallax effect.
During focus on parallax,
content around the edges of some layers
may be cropped or difficult to see clearly
as the image scales and moves.
To ensure that your primary content
is always visible,
please don't place it close to the edges.
tvOS leaderboard images
have different upload specifications.
Images must be a PNG file,
at 659 by 371 pixels at 1x,
1318 by 742 pixels at 2x,
at least 72 DPI
and in the sRGB color space.
You can find a more detailed overview
of how to design focusable layered images
for tvOS
in the Human Interface Guidelines.
Leaderboards can only show
a maximum of two lines before truncating.
We recommend keeping your
leaderboard titles under 30 characters
to guarantee that it will work well
across all devices
and accessibility settings.
Keep titles for your leaderboards
initial caps
and please avoid using all caps.
Tapping into one of these reveals
the scores for the specific leaderboard.
We have redesigned leaderboards
to be focused on friends,
the players you care about
competing with the most.
Speaking of which, Michael,
you've got a bit of catching up to do.
You can also embed the information from
your leaderboards directly into your game
to give players visibility
when it matters the most.
For example, you can give your players
a chance to see their position
before they start a level,
or at the end
after they beat their friends' top score.
The Game Center tech session
will go into detail
about how to embed leaderboard data
into your game.
You can also choose to link directly into
the leaderboard section of Game Center,
or even directly into
a specific leaderboard if you want to.
If you'd like to do this,
please use the icon that we have provided.
You can style it to work
with your game's UI,
but please do not alter the shape
in any way.
If accompanying the icon with text,
please use the correct language--
"leaderboards," and not "rankings"
or "scores" or anything else.
And that's leaderboards.
As a summary of what we just covered,
please design unique, eye-catching artwork
for each leaderboard.
tvOS requires a custom
16-by-9 layered artwork.
Keep your descriptions short and succinct.
And you can optionally embed
leaderboard data into your game
and also provide direct links
to specific leaderboards.
Now back to Michael.
Let's touch on multiplayer.
Game Center lets you easily take advantage
of its robust set of multiplayer features
for real time and turn-based games.
All you'll need is a button as a clear way
for players to open the multiplayer lobby.
The new, redesigned lobby
makes it simple and easy
to jump into a game.
When the lobby opens,
you may want to pause any distracting
animation in the background
so players can focus on inviting friends.
Tapping "add" reveals the player picker.
From here, you can see
nearby players, friends,
recent players and contacts.
Tap a player to add them to the lobby.
And when you're ready,
just tap "Invite and Start."
And if you'd like, you can also
implement our multiplayer features
without using our UI
by building it directly into your game.
Check out the tech session
for more details.
Back over to you, Joe.
Thanks, Michael.
And now on to the final section.
Game Center is now closely integrated
into the App Store.
Visitors to the store will now be able
to access their Game Center profile,
see their achievements, add friends
and browse the games
their friends are playing.
Your friends' avatars
will now show up on app icons
and feature prominently in the game's tab.
Friends playing will also be highlighted
on your game's product page.
You can see them here
at the top of the page
and also in more detail further down.
All of this will be enabled by simply
integrating your game with Game Center,
giving your game a great chance
to be featured on the App Store.
And that takes us to the end.
Now back to Michael for a summary
of everything we've just talked about.
Thanks, Joe.
And that's the new Game Center experience.
A new way to access Game Center
with in-game highlights,
the fully redesigned dashboard,
our beautiful collectible achievements,
our engaging leaderboards
and a whole lot more.
Please remember that everything
we discussed can be found in more detail
in the Human Interface Guidelines.
We're looking forward to see
what you do with Game Center,
and we can't wait to play
all the games you design.
Thank you.
Thanks a lot.