Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to WWDC.
My name is Frank Doepke and together
with my colleague David Hayward,
we're going to explore
Computer Vision APIs.
So why would you talk
about Computer Vision?
Computer Vision can really
enhance your application.
And even if it's not
at the core of your business,
it really brings something new
to your application.
Let me give you an example.
Banking applications allow
you to deposit checks.
They use Computer Vision for the camera
to actually read the check for you,
so you don't have to type
in the information anymore.
And clearly Computer Vision is not
at the core of the banking industry.
But by doing this you really can save
a lot of steps for your user.
They don't have to type
anything in anymore.
Another thing might be that you want to
just, for instance, read a QR code,
or when you read a receipt.
All of that may not be at the core
of what you wanna do for your application,
but it really makes it much easier for
your users to do this by using the camera.
So what APIs do we have available
for Computer Vision?
At the most high level part,
we have VisionKit.
It's the home of the VNDocumentCamera
that you might have seen
in Notes, or in Messages, or Mail
to actually scan the document.
Then we use Core Image to actually do
the image processing of images,
Vision for the analysis of images,
and last but not least, Core ML
to do the machine learning inference.
Today we're gonna focus just on
Core Image and Vision.
But I wanna make sure
that you don't just think of them
as pillars that stand side by side.
They can actually be nicely intertwined.
I might actually want to do
some image preprocessing,
run it into Vision, take the results
from there, feed them into Core ML,
or back into Core Image
to create some of the effects.
Now to talk about how we
want to use Core Image
to preprocess images for Computer Vision,
I would like to hand it over
to my colleague David Hayward.
Thank you, Frank. I'd like to take
this opportunity to describe
how you can improve your Computer Vision
algorithms using Core Image.
If you are unfamiliar with Core Image,
it is an optimized, easy-to-use image
processing framework built upon Metal.
For a deep dive on how it works,
I recommend you watch our WWDC
2017 presentation on the subject.
There are two primary reasons why your
app should use Core Image with Vision.
Using Core Image to preprocess
an input to Vision
can make your algorithms faster
and more robust.
Using Core Image to post-process
the outputs from Vision
can give your app new ways
to show those results to your users.
Also, Core Image is a great tool
to do Augmentation
for Machine Learning training.
There's some great examples of this
in our presentation from WWDC in 2018.
One of the best ways
to prepare an image for analysis
is to downscale it for best performance.
The scaler with the best overall quality
is CILanczosScale.
It is very easy to use this filter
in your code.
All you need to do is import
the CIFilterBuiltins header,
create a filter instance,
set the input properties,
and then get the outputImage.
It's that easy.
But that is just one of several
resampling filters in Core Image.
Depending on your algorithm,
it may be better to use the
linear interpolated CIAffineTransform.
Morphology operations
are a great technique
to make small features
in your image more prominent.
Performing Dilate using
CIMorphologyRectangleMaximum
will make brighter areas
of the image larger.
Performing Erode using
CIMorphologyRectangleMinimum
will make those areas smaller.
Better still, is to perform Close using
CIMorphologyRectangleMinimum
followed by CIMorphologyRectangleMaximum.
And this is very useful for removing
small areas of noise from your image
that may affect the algorithm.
Some algorithms only need
monochrome inputs,
and for these, Vision will automatically
convert RGB to grayscale.
If you have domain knowledge
about your input images,
you might get better results
using Core Image to convert to gray.
With CIColorMatrix you can specify
any weighting you want
for this conversion.
Or with CIMaximumComponent,
the channel with the greatest signal
will be used.
Noise reductions before image analysis
is also worth consideration.
A couple passes of CIMedianFilter can
reduce noise without softening the edges.
CIGaussianBlur and CIBoxBlur
are also a fast way to reduce noise.
And consider using
the CINoiseReduction filter too.
Core Image also has a variety
of edge detection filters.
For a Sobel edge detector,
you can use CIConvolution3X3.
Even better is to use CIGaborGradients,
which will produce a 2D gradient vector
that is also more tolerant of noise.
Enhancing the contrast of an image
can aid in object detection.
CIColorPolynomial allows you to specify
an arbitrary 3rd degree contrast function.
CIColorControls provides
a linear contrast parameter.
Core Image also has
some new filters this year
that can convert your image
to just black and white.
For example, CIColorThreshold
allows you to set the threshold value
in your application code,
while CIColorThresholdOtsu
will automatically determine
the best threshold value
based on the image's histogram.
Core Image also has filters
for comparing two images.
This can be useful to prepare for
detecting motion between frames of video.
For example, CIColorAbsoluteDifference
is a new filter this year
that can help with this.
Also, the CILabDeltaE
will compare two images
using a formula designed to match
human perception of color.
These are just a sampling of the more
than 200 filters built into Core Image.
To help you use these built-in filters,
this documentation includes
parameter descriptions,
sample images, and even sample code.
And if none of these filters
suit your needs,
then you can easily write your own
using Metal Core Image.
And we recommend that you
see our session on that
that we also made available this year.
With image processing and Computer Vision,
it is important to be aware that images
can come in a wide variety
of color spaces.
Your app may receive images in spaces
ranging from the traditional sRGB,
to wide gamut P3,
even to HDR color spaces,
which are now supported.
Your app should be prepared
for this variety of color spaces,
and the good news is that Core Image
makes this very easy.
Core Image automatically converts inputs
to its working space,
which is Unclamped,
Linear, BT.709 primaries.
Your algorithm might want images
in a different color space though.
In that case, you should do the following.
You will want to get a variable
for the color space
that you want to use from CGColorSpace.
And you will call
image.matchedFromWorkingSpace.
Apply your algorithm in that space,
and then call image.matchedToWorkingSpace.
That's all you need to do.
My last topic today
will be using Core Image
to post-process the outputs from Vision.
One example of this is using Core Image
to regenerate a barcodeImage
from a Vision BarcodeObservation.
All you need to do in your code
is create the filter instance...
set its barcodeDescriptor property
to be that of the Vision observation,
and lastly, get the outputImage.
And the result looks just like this.
Similarly, your app can apply filters
based on Vision face observations.
As an example, you can use
a vignette effect very easily using this.
The code is actually very simple.
One thing you need to be aware of
is that you will need to convert
from Vision's normalized coordinate system
to Core Image's
Cartesian coordinate system.
And once you create the vignette filter,
you can then put that vignette
over the image using compositing over.
You can also use Core Image
to visualize vector fields,
which Frank
will be demonstrating later on.
That concludes
my part of this presentation.
Here's Frank to talk more about Vision.
All right. Thank you, David.
So, now I'm gonna talk about how we
can understand images by using Vision.
We have a task, the machinery,
and the results.
The task is what you wanna do.
The machinery is what actually
performs the work.
And the results is, of course,
what you're looking for--
what you want to get back.
The task could be in our compiler,
the VNRequests.
Like a VNDetectFaceRectanglesRequest.
The machinery is one of two.
We have an ImageRequestHandler
or a SequenceRequestHandler.
And the results that we get back
is what we call VNObservation.
And these depend
on which task you performed,
like a VNRectangleObservation
for detected rectangles.
We first perform the request
on the ImageRequestHandler.
And from there, we get our observations.
Let's look at a concrete example.
We want to read text, so we use
the VNRecognizeTextRequest.
Then I create an ImageRequestHandler
with my image.
And out of that, I now get my
observations, which is just a plain text.
So, what do we have new in 2020 in Vision?
First, we have Hand and Body Pose.
To see more about that, please look
at the "Hand and Body Pose" session.
Then you might have seen
our Trajectory Detection.
And more about that, you can see
in the "Exploring the Action
and Vision Application."
Today, we're just going to focus on the
Contour Detection and on Optical Flow.
What is Contour Detection?
With Contour Detection,
I can find edges in my image.
As we saw here, the red lines now show the
contours that we found in this graphic.
So we start with an image, and then we
create our VNDetectContourRequest.
We can now set the contrast on the image
to enhance, for instance,
how some of the contrast may come out.
We can switch between,
do we want to run it
on a dark background
with this light background,
which may separate the foreground
versus background?
Last but not least, we can insert
the maximumImageDimension.
That allows you to trade off
the performance versus the accuracy.
That means,
for instance, if you look at it
at a lower resolution
you will still get your contours
but they might not follow the edge
as closely,
but it runs much faster
because it can run at a lower resolution.
In comparison,
when we use a higher resolution,
which you might want to do
in some post-processing,
we actually get
much more accurate contours
but it's gonna take a little bit longer
because it has to do more work.
Let's look at the observation
that we get back.
Here we have a very simple image
of two squares with a circle in it.
We are getting back a
VNContoursObservation.
The topLevelContours
are our two rectangles that we see.
Inside of those we have childContours.
They are nested and those are the circles.
Then we get back the contourCount
which I can actually use
to walk through all of my contours.
But it's much more easier,
for instance, to use the index path.
As you can see,
they are nested in each other
and I can now traverse my graph.
Last but not least,
I also get the normalizedPath.
And this is a CGPath I can use easily
for rendering.
Now, what is a VNContour?
In our example we get a VNContour here...
and that is the most Outer Contour,
our Parent.
Nested inside of it are childContours.
These are the Inner Contours.
My contour has an index path
and, of course, with that
every childContour has the index path,
which I can use again
to traverse my graph.
Then I get the normalizedPoints
in the pointCount.
Now, that is actually the real meat
of the contour
because it describes each
of the line segments that we discover.
Because we didn't just discover pixels,
we really get a contour which is a path.
We also have an aspectRatio.
I'm gonna talk about that
on the next slide.
And then we have the normalizedPath
to render.
When we want to work with contours,
there's a few things
we need to keep in mind.
Let's look at this image
that we have here.
It is 1920 by 1080 pixels,
and we have a circle in the middle
that is exactly 1080 pixels high and wide.
But Vision
uses a normalized coordinate space.
So, our image is 1.0 high and 1.0 wide.
Therefore, the circle now has a height
of 1.0,
but a width of 0.5625.
So, if you wanna take the geometry of the
shapes that you've detected into account,
you need to look at the aspectRatio
of the original image
from which it was computed on.
Now, contours really get interesting
when we can analyze them,
and we have a few utilities
for that available for you.
The VNGeometryUtils provides some API.
For instance, we have the boundingCircle
which is the smallest circle
that completely encapsulates
the contour that you detected.
It's great for comparing contours
with each other.
Then we can calculate the area.
And we can calculate the perimeter.
Now, the next part that
you might want to do with contours
is actually simplify them.
When we get contours from an image
they tend to be noisy.
Let's look at our example here.
We have a rectangle
that we've photographed.
But it has little kinks in it
and as you can see,
the contour actually followed
those little kinks.
So, now I actually
do not have all the points
on just the corners,
but even, like, on the middle.
I can now use the approximation
of a polygon by using the Epsilon.
Now, Epsilon means I can filter out
all the little noise parts around an edge,
so that only the strong contour edges
will actually stay.
And now, I get, again,
a perfect rectangle.
And with that I just have four points.
So, if I need to analyze shapes
it's very simple for me,
because I can simply say, "If
it has four points, it's a quadrilateral,"
and I detected what kind of shape I have.
Let's look at a concrete example
of how we can use all of this.
Let's say we need to save the world
by resurrecting very old computer code
that is done on punch cards.
So, our task is to identify the dimples
on the punch card
because nobody has
a punch card reader anymore.
So, we search the web
and find a Computer Vision blog post
that talks about how to do this.
But it's written in Python.
Our task, of course,
is to bring it natively onto our platform,
so that we can run it
in the best way possible.
So, now we have here
a section of Python code.
Don't worry
if you don't understand Python.
I'm just going
to walk you quickly through it.
The concept is very often always the same.
We do some image processing first...
then we do some image analysis...
and we get some results back
that we need to visualize.
Now, there's one part,
even if you don't understand Python
that I would like to highlight
here in the very beginning,
the first three lines that you see.
You see that we actually needed
to import a few libraries.
Now, they don't come with Python.
These are third-party libraries
that you need to actually include.
So, how do we do this natively?
For the image processing part,
we need to load the image.
And you know how to do that already.
You use CGImageSource,
get a UI Image from it,
load it into CIImage...
You name it.
Then you have the way of using Core Image
to process the image by using CIFilters,
like in the CIAbsoluteThreshold
or many others
as David has already explained.
Now we're doing the image analysis.
For that we create our ImageRequestHandler
from the CIImage that we just processed,
and then we perform our request
like the VNDetectContourRequest.
Now, the beauty of this request is
we might not even have
to preprocess our image.
And then we visualize our results.
Again, we can use Core Image to do this,
which allows us to composite it right over
the image that we actually have
right into the same context.
You might use the CIMeshGenerator,
or the CITextGenerator.
But I can also use CoreGraphics
or UIKit to render it into a layer
on top of my image.
All right, now, after all these slides,
let's look at a real demo.
Let me go over to my demo machine.
What I've prepared here
is a little playground.
And what you see is I've loaded my image.
I created my contourRequest...
and then I simply perform it.
And there, voilà.
I can see all the contours, including
the dimples that I was looking for.
Now, notice that I found 387 contours.
So, this may be a bit more
than actually I want.
So, we need to filter out
all these contours.
Well, I was a little bit prepared here,
and I've hidden a little bit of code.
Let me uncover this piece of code.
And all that is...
I use my domain knowledge
of knowing that my contours are actually
on a blue background.
So, I use now some CIFiltering
to first blur out all the noise...
then I use my color controls
to really bring out the contrast.
And then I use
my filtered image afterwards
and run it through my Contour Detection.
And you see now, I only find 32 contours,
which is really just the dimples
that I care about in the first place.
All right, let's go back to our slides.
Normally, I would talk about
what I did in my demo,
but it's more important, actually,
what I didn't have to do.
You noticed, I did not load
any third-party packages,
because this is all part of OS.
All I used was UIKit,
Core Image, and Vision.
I also never left our image pipeline
while using our most optimal processing
path because I stayed in our pipeline.
There was no conversion of the images
into matrices,
and with that,
I really saved all my memory,
and also a lot of computational cost.
So that was Contour Detection.
Next, let's go to Optical Flow.
So, what is Optical Flow?
We want to analyze
the movement between two frames.
Traditionally,
we might have used registration.
That has been a part of Vision
for quite a while.
It gives me the alignment
of the whole image.
Let's look at an example here.
We have these two dots,
and let's see if we take this
as a picture with our camera,
and then we shift our camera.
Now, these two dots
moved to the top and to the right.
The registration will give me
the alignment between the two images
by telling me how much the image
has moved up and to the right.
Optical Flow, on the other hand,
is different.
It gives me a per pixel flow
between X and Y,
and that is new in Vision this year.
In our example, again,
we have our two dots...
but now, they've actually moved apart.
So, the image registration
is not going to pick this up correctly.
But I can use the Optical Flow,
because it's going to tell me,
for each pixel, how they have moved.
Let's look at the results of Optical Flow.
From the Optical Flow,
I get the VNPixelBufferObservation.
It's a floating point image.
It has the interleaved X and Y movement.
So, when we have a video like this,
you can imagine that perhaps
just looking at these values on its own
will be really hard to visualize
what's going on.
Because they're really just meant
for processing in later algorithms.
But if I want to check it out,
I can actually use Core Image
to visualize our results.
And as David was teasing on
earlier in our session,
there is a way of doing this.
We created a little custom kernel,
and now, you can see how everything moves.
I have a color-coding that shows me
the intensity of the movement
and the little triangles actually show me
the direction of the movement.
Let me quickly show you how we did this.
So, we wrote a custom filter.
I need to load the kernel,
which we'll make available
in the slide attachments to you,
and then, all I have to do
is basically apply this kernel
with the parameters for the size
of the arrow that I want,
and run it as a filter.
Now, in my Vision code,
all I'm going to do is,
I run my VNGenerateOpticalFlowRequest,
I get my observations to pixelBuffer,
which I can just now wrap into a CIImage,
and then,
I simply feed that into my filter,
and get the output image back.
So, let's wrap up
what we've talked about today.
Computer Vision doesn't have to be hard,
and it really enhances your application.
Our native APIs
make it fast and easy to adopt.
And by combining these things together,
you really can create
something interesting.
I'm looking forward
to all the great applications
and great innovations
that you're going to bring out.
Thank you for attending our session,
and have a great rest of the WWDC.