Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi and welcome to this session
on "What's New in WatchOS Design."
I'm Jennifer Patton, and I'm
a Watch designer on the Apple Design Team.
In this session, I'm going to talk about
some of the ways
that we added new functionality
to native apps on the Watch this year,
and how you can bring some of this
same functionality to your watchOS apps.
I'm super excited to share with you
some of the things
we learned along the way,
so let's get started.
We'll start with a few guiding principles.
When designing your Watch app,
keep in mind that
Watch apps should be lightweight.
Like in this example
from the Sleep Cycle app,
limit lengthy interactions and be choosy
when it comes to functionality.
Ideally you can get all the information
from your Watch app at a glance.
When adding functionality to your app,
keep it actionable.
Wikiloc offers a filter option
in their list view.
Filtering is a great way to make
user interactions relevant to you
in the moment
you're interacting with your app.
And finally, once you've decided
that an action is critical
to the experience of your Watch app,
make it discoverable.
Here's a great example
from the Watch app, Bear,
that shows a clear visual button
to interact with.
This year on watchOS,
we did a complete audit
of all the gesture-based contextual menus
across the entire operating system
and native apps.
In previous watchOS versions,
actions were placed
in a gesture-based contextual menu.
In watchOS 7, we have moved
all of these actions into the apps
in an effort to make the experience
more intuitive for every user.
In the process, we've created
some great new interactions on Watch
that didn't exist before,
and we're excited to see
how you'll develop these new patterns
in your watchOS apps.
During the design process,
we had these three goals in mind.
First, interactions should be
both discoverable and predictable.
Secondly, relevant actions
should always be visible in the app.
And thirdly,
eliminate gesture-based contextual menus
without removing functionality.
As we brought these sensibilities
into our designs,
we learned that many of the actions
we wanted to display
really fall into the category
of secondary actions.
The interactions
I want to talk about today
are not the primary reason
you're using a Watch app.
Instead,
they add or increase functionality,
provide a secondary,
but still important action,
or provide a way to filter, sort,
or otherwise interact with
the primary actions already in the view.
Once you've narrowed down
the actions in your app
to just what is essential
for a delightful Watch experience,
here are some ways
to show secondary actions in your app.
We'll talk about commonly-used actions
like sort and filter menus
that can help make long lists
easier to navigate.
We'll talk about swipe actions
that can make a few key secondary actions
easily accessible.
We'll talk about
where to put more options,
the value of adding actions
to the bottom of a scrolling view
and a new toolbar button for suggesting
essential actions in a long list.
We'll also talk about when to use
a hierarchical navigation model
for changing destinations within an app.
Let's start with sort and filter.
A long scrolling list can become
much easier to use, and more personal,
if you have the ability to sort and filter
to just the information
relevant to you in the moment.
In watchOS 7, we added this button
to the top of the Activity Sharing list
in the Activity app.
I share my activity
with a long list of friends and family,
and maybe I'd like to see
who's done the most exercise today.
I simply tap on that sort button
at the top...
and I get a modal view,
with a linked table view that allows me
to sort my list with a single tap,
selecting Exercise instead.
Dang, Molly. It's not even 11:00 a.m.!
Here's one more example,
and we call this a view switcher,
slightly different
from filtering content out.
We're just viewing a different set of data
in this one.
In my Stocks app,
I can view all the stocks I'm following
at a glance in the list view.
But what if this information
just isn't quite relevant to me right now?
Let's tap on the button
at the top of the list
and choose Points instead.
There, that's better.
Now I'm viewing points
instead of percentages in the list,
which is just the information
I was looking for.
Sort and filter menus
are a lightweight and actionable way
to narrow down any long list
and make it easier to navigate
and more relevant to you in the moment.
To create a menu for sorting, filtering,
or view switching,
simply nest a picker in a list in SwiftUI.
Another API you can use in a list
is a swipe action.
We use these actions all the time in iOS,
and we're starting to use them
more and more in watchOS
for displaying actions in a list view.
World Clock has a perfect example
of a secondary action in a list view.
In my list of cities,
I can swipe a table row from right to left
to reveal a clear and recognizable prompt
to remove this city
from the list immediately.
I can always re-add it again easily
with the "Add City" button
at the bottom of the list.
The swipe action API is called
the onDelete modifier
and is currently available in SwiftUI.
We've talked
about adding functionality to a list.
But what if your Watch app
has more options
that you need to surface
in a glanceable view that doesn't scroll?
In this Maps example,
the entire screen is an active area.
I can move the map with my finger
to pan around
or tap the current location button
to snap back to my current location.
But we also have
a couple of additional actions
that we need to show
in this non-scrolling glanceable view.
So, we've added another button
in the bottom right
with the ellipsis glyph
in the app's key color
that can present these actions.
This is known as a More button.
By tapping this More button,
I can now search this area of the map,
or toggle between transit
and standard views.
The options in this contextual menu
add functionality
to the viewable area of the map.
It's pertinent to what I'm doing
in this moment,
and it's discoverable and reliable.
Inside the modal, you can show
a simple set of actions like this one,
or a more complex list of actions,
like the one in the Camera app.
If I open my Camera app on my Watch,
I can use my Watch as a remote
to take a picture with my iPhone camera.
Incidentally, we switched to
the three-second shutter as the default,
so I don't get caught in the picture
looking down at my Watch,
which I think is a great improvement.
And now, let's say
I have my iPhone all set up
and ready to shoot
another awesome full-length selfie
and I decide I want to change
my flash settings,
toggle Live Photo on or off,
or take some other common actions
right from my Watch.
Tapping on the More button
on the bottom right of the screen
gives me a modal table view
full of options for my camera settings.
This is an example of a sheet API
with a pretty robust list of options.
Let's focus on the design
of the More button for a minute.
You can create your own More button
using a simple circular container element
with the SF symbol "ellipsis"
centered inside.
Refer to Apple's
Human Interface Guidelines
for the recommended hit regions
for each Watch screen size,
and add transparent padding
around your button if needed
to ensure that your button
is comfortably tappable.
Now the Camera app has quite
a few options beneath the More button,
but what if you have a single secondary
action that you need to provide,
like this example in the Photos app?
In watchOS 7,
we added a button to the lower left
so that I can create a Watch Face
directly from the Photos app on my Watch.
Since there's really
only a single action here,
instead of the ellipsis symbol,
we designed an Apple Watch Face glyph.
You can design a glyph that families well
with the glyph language for your own app,
or utilize the glyphs available to you
in SF Symbols.
This More button needs to work on
a very dark and a very light background.
In order to make this button legible
on any background,
we used a white circular container
at 85% opacity
with a 1 point black outer glow
at 50% opacity.
The More button is a perfect way
to get to a menu of secondary actions
that are pertinent to the content
you're currently viewing.
It's especially important to separate
primary from secondary actions
when you think about using a More button.
Never put primary actions
inside a More menu
and be sure to be very choosy
about which secondary actions
you offer there, too.
Use a More button
in a glanceable full-screen view
or in a carousel list,
like this example in the Workout app
when you need to provide
contextual options,
but you don't have a lot of space.
Action buttons
at the bottom of a detail view
may be the most discoverable
and intuitive way
to show actions in your app.
Here's an example from the Calendar app.
In this calendar event
that I've been invited to,
we've added a button
to the bottom of the event detail
that allows me to e-mail
the sender of the invitation.
The actions in the bottom of a detail view
should always apply to the content
of the view above it.
Here's another calendar event.
This is a calendar event
that I've created.
At the bottom of any self-created
calendar event detail,
we've added a button
so that I can delete this event
from my calendar easily from my wrist.
To avoid confusion,
the information in this event detail
that's not actionable
sits directly on the black background.
Only the action button at the bottom
sits in a container and looks tappable.
Use a red text label on the button
to indicate a destructive action.
And add a confirmation alert
if the information being deleted
is not easily retrievable.
Next, I want to introduce a brand-new API
called the toolbar button.
We designed this button to solve
a specific interaction need on Watch,
the Compose buttons
in Messages and in Mail.
Wait, where is it?
It's tucked beneath the navigation bar
for the moment when I need it.
I likely did not open Messages on my Watch
to compose a new message.
Instead, my primary reason
for navigating here
is likely to read a new message
that just came in.
But if I did open my app
to start a new messages thread,
the compose button is there
waiting for me,
and I can tuck it back away
when I'm not using it.
You can find this toolbar button API
in SwiftUI.
Only use it in a scrolling view.
Scrolling is what makes
this button discoverable.
And use it judiciously,
only for actions that are essential
to the functioning of your app,
but may not be
the primary action for the view.
So far, we've been talking
about simple ways
you can add functionality
to your Watch app
with various types of buttons.
In watchOS 7, we had another case
that we needed to solve
where a button just couldn't do the trick.
It needed a different navigational model:
hierarchical navigation.
In some cases, it makes sense to land
one level in when you open a Watch app.
An example is what we do here in Mail.
When I open my Mail app,
I'm already in my All Inboxes view,
ready to read my most recent e-mail.
But if I tap the back button
in the navigation bar,
I'm at the top level of the app,
and I can change my destination
to visit my Apple e-mail inbox
or my personal e-mail inbox.
Let's check my Apple e-mail.
The title in the navigation bar
lets me know
which inbox I'm currently reading,
and the back button is still right there,
so I can jump back and switch anytime.
In a hierarchical navigation model,
the app should remember
the destination I chose
the next time I open the app.
If your interaction doesn't call
for that level of permanence,
then this is probably
not the right model to use.
Another example that we added
to watchOS this year is in the Home app.
Now when I open my Home app on my Watch,
I land here in my device list
for my house.
But tapping back in the top left
takes me to a top level list
of destinations.
From here, I can simply switch
to my design studio,
and now I can see and interact
with the devices that I have there.
The title in the navigation bar
has changed
to indicate the destination
that I am currently in,
and tapping back will always
reliably take me right back
to that same list of destinations.
I truly hope this session
on "What's New in WatchOS Design"
helps you bring useful functionality
to your Watch apps.
When designing or updating your Watch app
for watchOS 7, remember,
with so many different ways
to improve navigation in your app,
be extra particular about
what you put inside contextual menus.
Choose actions that are essential
to a delightful Watch experience.
And, once you've decided
on which actions to offer,
steer clear of gesture-based menus
and instead, offer a clear visual button
or predictable interaction pattern.
By keeping these simple design goals
in mind,
you'll make your app relevant
and easy to navigate
for everyone who wants to use it.
For additional information,
be sure to check out
the resources listed below this video
in the Apple Developer app.
Thank you.