Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, and thanks for joining.
My name is Jacob.
I'm a program manager
for the Enterprise and Education team,
and I'm here to talk with you
about deploying custom apps
with Apple Business Manager.
Apple builds products
to enrich people's lives.
This principle extends to business
and education customers as well.
Custom apps can make it easy for you
to reach this audience
and provide tools for them
to be productive,
engage with their employees and staff,
and reach their customers.
Whether you're a developer
considering custom apps,
a business customer purchasing
and distributing apps to your employees,
or an end user who just wants to know more
about the process,
I'll cover the benefits
of custom apps for you.
When you see these icons
throughout the session,
I'm covering a topic
of particular interest to that audience.
These three groups interact with
and influence each other,
so it's important to understand
how all the elements fit together.
This is a continual cycle, as developers
add features and sell to new customers,
businesses expand and offer more apps
to their employees,
and users transition to different roles
within the organization.
First, let's do a quick review.
There are multiple ways
to distribute your apps to customers.
Enterprise app distribution allows
for customization,
but is intended only
for internal deployment
to your own company's employees.
Historically, Enterprise app distribution
was the only approved path
for internal deployment.
The Custom app process includes
the benefits of TestFlight and App Review
and is now the preferred path
for internal deployments
in countries where Apple Business Manager
is available.
Public App distribution lets you leverage
the App Store infrastructure
and makes apps readily available
for your customers to purchase,
but this method is intended
for a broad audience
and doesn't allow for any customization.
We're gonna focus on custom apps,
which provide you as the developer
the ability to build apps
with features specific to your customers
while making it easier for them
to purchase and deploy the apps.
Custom apps allow you the developer
to distribute to a select customer
or group of customers.
This is essentially a private App Store,
where you determine the audience
who can purchase your app.
It allows you
to provide specific features,
branding, or other customization.
Customers purchase these apps
through Apple Business Manager.
They are not exposed
to the public App Store
and only visible
to the organizations you allow.
And now, we're excited
to extend custom apps support
to Apple School Manager customers as well.
I'll refer primarily to Apple Business
Manager throughout this session,
but the two programs have the same support
for custom apps.
Everything here that applies
to Apple Business Manager
also applies to Apple School Manager.
If you're a third-party developer,
you can build and sell these apps
to customers.
If you are part of a company
or organizational's
internal development team,
you can create and distribute custom apps
to your employees and staff.
This extends the scope of custom apps
to companies that want to develop
yourselves and deploy internally.
Customers purchase a custom app
using Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager.
This is the same purchase flow
as other volume licenses
of public App Store apps.
The only differences
are that you as a developer
explicitly allow which organizations
will see your custom apps,
and custom apps show up
in a separate collection
in Apple Business Manager.
After purchase,
customers manage licenses and distribution
the same as other volume-purchased apps.
Connect an MDM server
to Apple Business Manager
for license distribution
and other management tasks.
This connection allows MDM
to manage devices
on behalf of the organization.
Once the license is distributed
to the device,
the device downloads the custom app
from the App Store infrastructure.
Custom apps represent a private App Store.
You authorize organizations or specific
purchasers who can buy your apps,
and those apps only show up
for those customers.
So zooming in a bit,
we're gonna focus on how
this process works for the developer.
There are advantages to you
as a developer:
private distribution of a custom-built app
to the customers you specify.
You can create apps
with the features and functions
that might not be relevant
for the general public,
and provide these apps exclusively
to your customers.
You are able to provide custom features
for your audience
while leveraging the App Store
infrastructure for distribution.
And because your apps go through
the same app review process,
you get feedback from Apple and confidence
that your app meets our quality standards.
You get access to App Store Connect tools
for submitting your app,
viewing app analytics and crash logs,
and managing payment and pricing.
Apple takes care of payment processing,
taxes, and other overhead.
And if you're currently using
App Store Connect,
the process for submitting apps and using
these tools is already familiar to you.
Another important benefit
with App Store Connect
is the ability to use TestFlight
for beta testing with select users.
You can send invitations via e-mail
or a public link
and collect feedback before launching
your app for general availability.
If you're developing apps
for internal use,
you can also distribute internally
to your employees and associates.
This is a big improvement
because it greatly simplifies the process
of getting your apps to your staff.
And because these apps come
from the App Store,
the distribution certificates
don't expire.
This is an important distinction
for developers who are familiar
with Enterprise distribution
and the requirements to renew distribution
certificates on a regular basis.
With custom apps, you can focus
on enhancements and features
for new versions of your app,
not certificate management.
It all starts with inspiration.
You have a great idea for a custom app,
or a customer has reached out to you
and wants you to modify
an existing App Store app for them.
Let's say this developer has a popular app
called Forest Explorer
for exploring parks and open spaces,
and a business contacts them
and wants a custom version
to help their employees navigate
the corporate campus
and find local green spaces.
We'll call this custom app
Campus Explorer.
The first thing you need to do
is get your team together.
Enroll in developer programs if necessary.
If you already have an account, great.
You're ahead of the game.
Use the same
Organization Developer program
that you do for the apps you publish
to the App Store.
If you're setting up a new program,
be aware that you need
an Organization Developer program,
and this requires a DUNS number.
If you charge for your app, you'll also
need to provide banking information
and accept the paid apps agreement.
If you are an internal development team,
the same rules apply.
Get added to your company's
existing developer program,
invite third-party contributors...
If you're the account holder or admin
for your developer program
and want to include external developers,
grant them access to the apps
they are working on
and maintain control
of the app submission process yourself.
Once you're enrolled,
App Store Connect is where you manage
aspects of your developer account,
including inviting new members
to your team,
signing necessary agreements,
providing payment information,
and submitting your app.
Let's go through this together.
Under Users and Access,
we can see everyone associated
with our developer account
and their roles and app privileges.
For this project,
we're going to hire a contracted developer
to help with some of the work.
We're adding Lucinda Yang as a developer
with access only
to the Campus Explorer app.
When we select invite,
Lucinda will get an invitation
to join our developer account.
Once we have our team together
and our app is ready to go,
the next step is to submit it for review
and distribution in App Store Connect.
Provide metadata for your app,
like screen shots, description,
keywords, and other information.
Set the price and regions
where your app will be available.
We recommend making your app
available globally,
because this allows you
to reach the broadest possible audience.
This is also the point
where you'll choose the distribution type:
available as a public app on the App Store
or available for specific business
and education customers.
For more information, refer to the
"What's New in App Store Connect" session.
Okay, so we're ready to submit
our custom app.
First, we create a new app entry
by selecting the "plus" icon.
Then we provide the name, app preview,
screen shots, and other metadata.
We set a price for our app,
select the countries or regions where
our app will be available for purchase...
and we provide the org details
for our customer, Pretendco,
which will allow them to purchase our app
from their
Apple Business Manager instance.
We're almost ready to submit our app.
Our app requires sign-in
using a corporate account,
so we're providing a demo credential
that will help the App Review team
access the app.
We're also providing notes
with additional details,
and we have the option to submit
screen shots or other attachments.
When we're ready,
we submit the app for review.
And here's our app,
back from review and ready
for customers to purchase.
App Review gives you direct feedback
from our review team
and gives your customers the confidence
that your app has been vetted
and approved by Apple.
While Custom App Review differs slightly
from public apps,
to make sure your app goes through
this process smoothly,
provide a demo account and credentials
if your app requires authentication.
This demo account should be able to access
all the functions of your app.
Or you could build a demo mode
into your app and supply sample data.
The intent is to make sure the review team
is able to inspect all the functionality
and features of your app.
Submit good metadata, such as description,
keywords and screen shots
that show details about your app.
If you're providing your app
to a specific audience or market segment,
describe it in the notes review.
The more details the App Review team has
about your app,
the easier the process will go,
especially if this is your first time
submitting an app.
If you're updating an existing app,
provide details about the new enhancements
and features.
If the update is a maintenance release,
add notes with specific information
about what is fixed in the new version
beyond just "bug fixes."
Make sure you account for App Review time
when planning your deployment schedule.
Also, be aware of times
when there is increased traffic,
such as holidays and product launches,
when it might take longer
to get through the process.
And be mindful of deadlines when your app
is required to support the latest SDKs.
Use only public APIs,
and make sure your app runs
on the currently shipping OS.
This is covered in the guidelines,
but it's worth a call-out here.
Using documented APIs
and phasing out deprecated frameworks
ensures your app is stable
and continues to function.
Apple changes and modifies private APIs
without advance notice.
If your app relies on these,
it could stop working
or cause unexpected issues
for your end users.
If your app requires
additional entitlements
for hardware resources or user data,
make sure you adhere
to Apple's privacy guidelines
for collecting and storing user data.
Refer to the privacy and legal section
in the App Store Review Guidelines
and developer documentation.
As you expand your customer base,
you might create a new instance
of your app--
for example, if you're selling
to a new customer or market segment
or selling your app in a new region
with different regulatory requirements.
If possible,
keep these variations to a minimum.
This avoids the complexity of managing
separate build trains and release cycles.
If you need to provide specific branding
or other minor modification,
use App Configuration
or rules based on user authorization
to deliver this content.
All customers get the same app,
but you can fine-tune the experience
based on these settings.
If you do need to create
a completely new app,
collect common code into frameworks
so you can reuse it
across your different apps.
If you're creating a new app,
each instance requires a new Bundle ID,
a new submission,
and a separate App Review,
and you'll need to maintain these
as separate build trains.
Your development and release cycle
will be different
than the deployment cycles
for your customers.
It's important to take this
into consideration
when planning major releases.
Here, you release Version 1.1
in the middle
of your customer's deployment wave one.
This means that half the employees
will be on Version 1 of the app,
but devices that go out to employees
after this date
will have a Version 1.1 installed.
There are ways to mitigate this
with MDM commands,
but it's best to coordinate ahead of time,
especially when planning around
new product launches or OS releases.
Once you publish a new version
of your app,
your customers cannot deploy
the previous version.
This process usually goes smoothly.
But if you do run into problems,
make sure your customers have enabled
custom apps in Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager.
The org name and org ID you specify
in App Store Connect must match exactly,
including punctuation.
Apps can take time to show up as available
on a customer's
Apple Business Manager org.
If you authorize a new customer
to purchase an existing app,
allow up to 24 hours
before that app shows up
in their Apple Business Manager instance.
If you're modifying a consumer app
for a business customer,
you need to create a new Bundle ID
and submit it as a new app.
You can't convert an existing consumer app
into a custom app or vice versa.
If you do run into problems,
we're here to help.
Contact the App Review team
using your developer account
for issues like appealing a rejection
or providing additional information
about your submission.
You can submit
a Developer Technical Support case
for code-level technical assistance,
and your customers can contact AppleCare
if they experience issues
purchasing or deploying your app.
Now we're gonna transition
from our development track
and go back to our app life cycle
and focus on what this looks like
from the perspective
of a business buying the app.
For the administrators managing devices
and deploying apps to your employees,
this is your section.
Custom apps give you the benefit
of deploying and managing apps
like you're doing right now
with volume-purchased apps
through Apple Business Manager.
You purchase and manage licenses
the same way you would for other content.
IT teams can leverage the same
distribution model as App Store apps,
including device-based assignment
and managed-app capabilities.
You can assign, revoke,
and reassign licenses
as your needs change.
Since the custom app
has gone through App Review screening,
you can be confident that it meets
Apple's quality and security guidelines.
And you can work with the developer
to provide the level
of customization you need,
such as security features
for sensitive corporate data,
company branding, or specific
functionality for your workflows.
Apple Business Manager is the service
that makes this all possible.
There are three main functions
of Apple Business Manager:
deploying and managing devices,
purchasing and assigning content,
and managing accounts and privileges.
Apple Business Manager makes it easy
to deploy devices at scale
using automated device enrollment
and configure them
with your security policies and content.
You can automatically enroll
organization-owned devices
into your MDM solution without having
to prep each device individually.
You can simplify the setup process
by removing specific steps
in Setup Assistant
so users are up and running quickly.
You can delegate privileges
for certain functionality,
like managing devices or content.
And with Federated Authentication,
it's easy to use
existing corporate credentials
to reduce the number of accounts
employees need to maintain
and to give IT a central point of control.
Last year, we introduced User Enrollment
as an option for organizations
who want to enable their employees
to use their own device
while giving the corporate IT organization
lightweight control.
Companies can provide custom apps
and other managed content to the device.
Check out the "What's New
in Managing Apple Devices" session
for the latest updates.
Okay, let's set up Apple Business Manager
together.
As an IT administrator,
the first thing you need to do to support
custom apps is enable it under Settings.
You also need to provide
your organization details to the developer
so they can authorize you
to purchase the app.
This name and ID must match exactly as
it's displayed in Apple Business Manager.
Mobile device management is required
to make this all work.
You purchase content, manage locations,
and assign devices to MDM servers
in Apple Business Manager.
MDM does the heavy lifting
of assigning and revoking licenses
as well as ongoing device management.
So now,
we'll configure the connection between
our Apple Business Manager instance
and our MDM server.
First, we'll add a new MDM server.
We're using Profile Manager,
Apple's reference MDM.
In Profile Manager,
we've generated a public key,
which we upload here.
Then we download
the Device Enrollment token
and upload it to Profile Manager.
This creates the trust connection.
And now we can see that our devices
have been assigned
and are managed by Profile Manager.
Next, we download the location token
for apps and books
and save it to Profile Manager.
This allow license distribution.
In addition to license management
for volume-purchased content,
MDM handles management functions
like enforcing policies
to manage app updates centrally,
and restrict employees
from updating apps on their own.
This is useful
if you want to keep employees
on a specific version of an app until
you're ready to update to the new version.
Custom apps adhere to the same rules
as managed apps,
so you can remove a license,
push a new license to a deployed device,
or initiate an update to a deployed app
and enforce a policy to defer OS updates
for up to 90 days after release.
For more information, refer to
the Mobile Device Management Settings
for IT Administrators documentation.
Going back to Apple Business Manager,
last step:
We'll purchase the custom app now
and assign it to a location.
Then, MDM will be able to assign
that license to end users and devices.
Administrators can create separate groups
in Apple Business Manager
called Locations,
and use these to delegate
license management
to specific users in their organization.
If you have regional offices, for example,
you can purchase licenses
from the main corporate location,
then assign them to each regional office
to manage on their own.
If you're migrating from the legacy
volume purchase program,
Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager
provide better flexibility
for managing licenses.
You'll need to plan your migration
to ensure deployed apps continue to work
without an interruption.
See the support article
on Migrating to Apps and Books
for more information.
And as a reminder,
the volume-purchase program
will no longer be available
starting December 1, 2020.
If you need to keep users from updating,
use MDM restrictions to allow IT control
over initiating app updates.
And like other
managed license distribution,
you can assign apps to device or to users.
If you're new to Apple Business Manager
and just getting started,
make sure your MDM solution
supports these features for managed apps.
Custom app support allows the MDM
to manage licenses for custom apps.
If you want to manage
app updates centrally,
restrict end users from updating the app
on their own...
and initiate the app update
when you're ready to update
the entire organization
to the new version.
Deferring OS updates
can be a good technique
for keeping your devices
on the previous version of the OS
for compatibility or other reasons.
OS updates can be deferred
for up to 90 days.
Wrapping up for the business segment,
and finally, our app life cycle,
we'll look at the end-user perspective.
As an end user,
you get the benefits of using an app
that's been designed
to fit your specific needs.
When activating your device
for the first time,
MDM takes over initial configuration
and allows you to skip through
the setup process.
Your apps are automatically installed,
and company accounts like Mail and network
access are configured automatically.
Your company can publish an App Catalog
to make it easy to discover other optional
or recommended apps,
including other managed apps
or App Store apps.
And iCloud can help keep data in sync
across multiple devices
while giving IT the ability
to restrict content
flowing from managed sources
to unmanaged sources.
As an end user,
we'll take the device out of the box
and activate it for the first time.
We'll start the Setup Assistant,
choose a location, language,
and a Wi-Fi network.
And we'll see that our organization
is managing our device for us
to skip the rest of the setup process,
and our custom app is automatically
installed on the device,
and we're ready to go.
Last step: back to our cycle.
This is a continuous process.
As end users or organizations
have enhancement requests
and new feature ideas,
they communicate those to the developer.
The developer releases new versions
and enables more customers
to purchase their app.
Let's do a quick recap.
As a developer,
custom apps are a great way
for you to reach business
and education customers
and provide them an easy way
to distribute apps for their employees,
staff and students.
Businesses can benefit
from easy deployment using existing tools,
and they can get apps
with specific features built for them.
Internal teams can use custom apps
to easily deploy to their employees,
and Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager
make all this possible.
Thank you for your time,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.