Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to
"What's New in SiriKit and Shortcuts."
My name is Daniel Hsu,
and I'm an engineer on the Shortcuts team.
Today, I'm excited to be joined
by my colleague, Natalia,
to tell you about
the latest updates to Shortcuts.
SiriKit is our suite of developer APIs
for bringing enriched Siri
and shortcut support into your app.
It's a great way to make the things people
do with your apps easier to accomplish
by surfacing them
outside of the boundaries of your app
and letting them out
into the operating system.
This enables several key experiences.
Users can perform these actions
with their voice,
through suggestions that appear
on the lock screen and Spotlight,
and of course, through shortcuts
and the Shortcuts app.
The Shortcuts app, which comes built in
on iOS, iPadOS and watchOS,
is how we make it easy for people
to make using the device faster,
more automatic, and more personal.
Using the editor,
you can drag and drop easily
to piece together actions
from all of your favorite apps,
which can then be run
with just a single tap,
by asking Siri, or from many other
places in the system,
like from a widget on the Home screen,
or even automatically with automations.
There are practically
endless possibilities
for the kinds of shortcuts you can create
and how you use them,
from asking Siri to order your coffee,
to changing the lights and temperature
in your HomeKit-enabled home
as you're leaving work.
We're putting all the power in your hands.
Getting started with shortcuts
can be as simple as tapping
an "Add to Siri" button,
which you may have already seen
in many of your favorite apps.
It's important for you as a developer
to make setup easy and discoverable.
Make sure to include
an "Add to Siri" button
in a contextually relevant place,
not just in a nested settings view.
That way, the people that perform
those actions in your app every day
can set up a shortcut that makes executing
that action even faster in the future.
And, they can even give it their own
personalized trigger phrase,
like "soup time."
Now that I have that set up,
I can quickly reorder my favorite soup
from anywhere on my phone.
Siri is an intelligent assistant
that offers a faster, easier way
to get things done with your voice.
And this year, in iOS 14, Siri comes
with this beautiful, new, compact design.
We redesigned Siri from the ground up
to focus only
on the most essential information,
minimizing disruption, while still
allowing you to quickly get things done,
no matter what you're doing on your phone.
Your Siri UI should really feel
like an extension,
both functionally and aesthetically,
of your app.
To illustrate, let's take a look
at the Weather app.
Checking the weather in the Weather app
is the complete experience.
At a glance,
you're able to see the weather
for all of your favorite cities,
and you can drill down into
a specific city to see more details,
like air quality,
sunrise and sunset times, and much more.
In iOS 13, asking Siri for the weather
shows you the current forecast,
the upcoming hourly forecast,
and a few other details.
Updating this experience
for the compact UI in iOS 14
was an exercise
in choosing the most essential things.
In the new compact UI,
we focused on just the most succinct
and helpful answer possible.
This meant eliminating things
that weren't directly relevant.
But this doesn't mean minimalism
for minimalism's sake.
It's really about getting to the heart
of what the user intention is.
Now, in iOS 14, if you ask
for the weather, you'll get exactly that.
In iOS 14, we brought the same great
compact UI experience over to Shortcuts.
If your shortcut needs input from you,
a new compact UI will appear.
This works for entering text,
numbers, dates and more.
You can even compose messages and emails,
pick a photo, or choose a song.
We also extended the same UI treatment
everywhere you can run a shortcut.
Before, you may have needed to jump into
the Shortcuts app to complete a task.
Now your shortcuts will run seamlessly
in the background,
and will only prompt you
if the shortcut needs input from you.
This makes a lot of sense,
because after all,
shortcuts has always been about
getting the user
to what they want to do even faster.
We want to help you understand
how to apply this new design principle
in your intents.
There are a few cases
you should be aware of.
The first is disambiguation,
when you're asking follow-up questions
to clarify the user's intent.
The second is Intents UI,
which is how your app UI
shows in Siri and Shortcuts.
Let's talk about disambiguation.
With conversational shortcuts,
you have the opportunity
to ask follow-up questions.
If you're taking advantage of this
for your intents,
you should consider adopting the new APIs
for customizing how the list is presented.
New in iOS 14, you have the option to add
images and subtitles to your option list.
This can help people visually
differentiate between similar options,
which can be important, for example,
when ordering soup.
But use these judiciously,
and use your best judgment.
Imagery can help someone
make the right choice,
but it can also end up
feeling overwhelming
with too much information onscreen.
Now, let's talk about Intents UI.
Your Intents UI now appears
in this new compact UI,
whether you're running from Siri
or Shortcuts.
When designing your Intents UI
for this new environment,
consider what your intent
is supposed to do,
and what is actually important to show
when using it.
Because the compact UI appears
on top of whatever the user is doing,
the less vertical space
your Intents UI takes up,
the more lightweight
the experience will feel.
Consider providing a shorter snippet
where possible,
to minimize disruption
to the user's current context.
In order to help the snippet UI defer
to the context it's being presented in,
Intents UIs now use
a consistent background material
whether they're run from Siri
or from Shortcuts.
If you'd like, you can take advantage
of the new material
by keeping the background color
of your Intents UI view transparent.
If you do choose to use
a transparent background material,
make sure to test your UI
on a variety of different backgrounds
to ensure readability.
In summary, choosing the essential
is a key principle
for designing for the new compact UI.
We can't wait to see what you build.
That's the new Siri
and Shortcuts experience in iOS 14.
Now over to my colleague, Natalia,
for more exciting updates to shortcuts.
When Shortcuts became an built-in app
in iOS 13,
it gained a whole new audience.
From people using simple shortcuts
to set a laundry timer or calculate a tip,
to power users with hundreds of shortcuts.
Shortcuts allow people
to find new, creative ways
of interacting with your apps.
And in iOS 14,
we're making it easier to organize
shortcuts by introducing folders.
With new ways
to create and manage shortcuts,
people will find and keep track
of shortcuts from your apps faster.
To get started,
there are a few smart folders
that help people easily identify
which shortcuts appear in the share sheet
or on the watch.
That's right, people can now run shortcuts
on the watch
with the new Shortcuts app on watchOS.
In addition to running shortcuts
from within the app,
people can set shortcuts as complications
and run them right from the watch face.
That means that you can bring
the functionality of your apps
to the watch face just by using Shortcuts.
The watch app works seamlessly
with Shortcuts on iOS.
People can add or remove shortcuts
available on the watch
with the new Apple Watch switch
in Shortcut details.
To learn more about how to make
your shortcuts work great on the watch,
check out the session,
"Create quick interactions
with Shortcuts on watchOS."
Now sometimes,
people want shortcuts to run automatically
on their behalf
when certain conditions are met.
And for this, in iOS 13,
we introduced Personal Automations.
Personal Automations let people
run actions based on events,
such as time of day,
arrival at a location,
or the opening of an app.
People already build routines
around your apps,
and automations allow them
to do it faster.
For example,
we've seen people automate
their journaling routines
with the Open App trigger.
Whenever a journaling app is open,
the event gets logged
in a habit-tracking app,
the device is put
into Do Not Disturb mode,
and a focused writing playlist
starts playing.
This is just one example.
There's so much more
people are doing with automations.
And in iOS 14,
we're taking automations even further
by introducing new trigger types.
People will now be able to run shortcuts
when they receive an email or a message,
when they close a certain app,
when their battery hits a certain level,
or when they connect to a charger.
And more trigger types can now run
automatically without asking people first.
A great place to find inspiration
for shortcuts is the gallery,
and in iOS 14, we've added
automation suggestions to the gallery.
They provide catered automations
that people may find handy
based on how they use their device.
Your actions are the key
to great automations.
To learn more about enabling people to
interact with your app through shortcuts,
watch the video on featuring your actions
in the Shortcuts app.
As you can see,
shortcuts are great for taking
the guesswork out of everyday tasks.
No matter how complex your routine is,
you can easily automate it with shortcuts.
Our routines may differ,
but one thing we all have in common
is our need for a good night's sleep.
So this year, we're enabling developers
to help people manage their sleep routine.
If your app involves mindfulness,
journaling, music,
or any of the other
supported sleep categories,
your action can be featured
in the Wind Down setup experience.
All you need to do is mark
your shortcut donations as good for sleep
with the new
INShortcutAvailabilityOptions API.
If your app is even remotely
sleep-friendly,
make sure to watch the session
on integrating your app with Wind Down.
This year, we have so many
exciting improvements to SiriKit
that we have a separate SiriKit session.
We encourage you to check out
"Get the most out of Siri,
Shortcuts and SiriKit"
to learn all the details.
There are a lot of new features
in SiriKit and Shortcuts in iOS 14.
We're introducing a brand-new
shortcut-running experience and folders.
We're bringing the Shortcuts app
to the Apple Watch.
For automation, we're adding
automation suggestions to the gallery,
and providing more triggers.
And finally, we're supporting
the new Wind Down experience.
There's even more that we didn't get
to talk about in detail.
To dive deeper into what's new
in SiriKit and Shortcuts,
make sure to watch the sessions
linked to this video.
Thank you for watching.