Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everybody.
I'm Rishi Verma from the Core Data team.
This session,
we'll show you how to harness Core Data
to best fit the needs of an application.
To start,
we'll investigate how to populate
and maintain your persistent store quickly
and efficiently with batch operations.
Then we'll go over
how to tailor a fetch request
to match the needs of an application.
Lastly, a few tips and tricks
on how an application could react
to changes in the persistent store.
Let's start with a look at our sample,
Earthquakes.
It is a Swift application
that has a view context to drive the UI
and a background context
to ingest the data
provided by the US Geological Survey.
Our sample has a local container
for our application
and gathers quake data
from the USGS's JSON feed.
Here, we send the JSON feed
to our JSON parser,
which in turn sends the data over
to our background context
to be turned into quake managed objects
and saved to our local store.
Our view context then merges changes
to magically update our UI.
Now, our background context
could be working
with a large number of managed objects
that are created or fetched only to be
discarded shortly after the save.
But this is where batch operations shine.
Batch operations allow developers
to do inserts,
updates and deletes with ease,
while being as minimal as possible.
Due to the minimalist nature
of these operations, a few caveats.
There are no save notifications posted
because, well,
obviously we're not doing a save here.
And because we did not manifest
the managed objects,
we do not get any callback
or accessor logic for our changes.
But wait.
You can work around these two caveats
with persistent history.
Enable persistent history,
and your batch operations are captured
so that a notification
can easily be acquired,
and now we've worked around
that first caveat of the batch operations.
As for the callbacks and accessor logic,
we can accommodate that
by parsing our persistent history
for the relevant changes
to our application's current view.
How about we dive deeper
into batch operations?
The first thing
our applications generally do
is load data into the persistent store,
which in turn drives our UI.
When we introduced NSBatchInsertRequest,
it gave developers
the power of a batch operation
for data ingestion.
It streamlined the ability
to ingest a ton of data,
and now we have expanded the abilities
of NSBatchInsertRequest.
Initially, we gave developers the ability
to pass an array of dictionaries
for a batch insert.
The array of dictionaries represented
the objects to create
with the keys as attribute names
and their assigned values.
And we have a new addition,
an initializer that allows developers
to give a block to fill out
a given dictionary or managed object.
This greatly reduces the peak memory
of an ingestion
while also reducing the number
of objects allocations even further.
How about we see an example?
In this snippet of code, we're creating
managed objects for our quake...
and populating them with values
for our quake data provided by the USGS.
Then we save.
Let's see how this code would look
if we adopted NSBatchInsertRequest.
First, we gather a dictionary
of all the quake data
and add it to our array.
We create a batch insert request
and execute.
Simple. Now let's see this block variant
of batch insert request.
We create the batch insert request
with a block
that will assign values
to a given dictionary.
We then execute the request,
and this block is called
until it returns "true"
as the indicator to stop and save.
But how do these three different ways
perform?
Let's look at how our application performs
when we ingest
a large number of earthquakes.
When we save the context
with managed objects,
we see it takes over one minute
and idles out
with roughly 30 megs of memory usage.
The initial peak is the JSON data,
and most of that first minute
isn't actually the ingestion,
but the merging of change notifications
since we did a huge number
of transactions.
But we don't have that issue
with batch inserts.
When we use the NSBatchInsert
with an array of dictionaries,
we finish the same operation
with 25 megs of idle memory
and are able to save the same number
of objects in only 13 seconds,
a fraction of the time needed
for a traditional save.
But we can do even better.
Let's use the new block ingestion,
and we're able to ingest
all of the objects in 11 seconds.
Now that we've optimized
our data population,
let's learn a neat trick
about batch inserts.
Here, we have our managed-object model
from the Earthquakes Sample,
and I have the quake entity selected.
On the right-hand side
is the data model inspector
for our quake entity.
Let's take a closer look.
We can see that the attribute "code"
is a unique constraint.
This means that only one object
can have a specific value for "code"
in the persistent store.
No other quakes
can have the same value for "code."
How does this come into play
with our Earthquakes Sample?
Well, our JSON feed gives us
all of the quakes for the last 30 days,
and every time
our user hits the reload button,
we ingest all of the data
from the JSON feed,
which is mostly the same data
except for a few quakes
that have happened recently,
and updated data on past quakes.
Here we have a quake with code 42
coming from our JSON feed into our parser.
Then it is passed
to our background context,
which saves quake 42 into the store.
The first time it is ingested,
we create a new row in our store.
However, on subsequent attempts
to insert the same quake,
we don't want to delete the old one
and insert the new one.
We would really like to update
any data that has changed,
and in SQL that's called an UPSERT.
UPSERT is an SQL term
that is easier to understand
if you see the SQL at the same time.
So, here we have our insert
of our quake object,
and while inserting,
if we have a conflict on code,
update these properties
instead of inserting.
How do you get this behavior?
Simply set the mergePolicy on the context,
executing the batch insert request
to NSMergeByPropertyObject-
TrumpMergePolicy.
But there is a simpler way to do updates,
and it couldn't be simpler
with batch updates.
With the NSBatchUpdateRequest,
there is no need
to execute the fetch request
only to update the managed objects
and save.
An NSBatchUpdateRequest
can quickly and efficiently
update the properties in our objects
that meet the search criteria
defined in the fetch request.
Let's check out a quick example.
Using our Earthquakes Sample app,
we could mark all of the quakes
as validated
if we were able to confirm them
with another source.
Well, let's imagine our source
only validates earthquakes
if they have a magnitude greater than 2.5.
Well, we can build
a batch update for this.
This code creates a batch update request
for "Quake"
and then sets the propertiesToUpdate
"validated" equals "true"
and sets our predicate,
magnitude greater than 2.5.
Then we execute our batch update,
and we're all done.
It's just that simple.
So we've covered inserts and updates.
Let's do batch deletes.
Batch deletes are very powerful
and can be used to easily delete
large portions of the object graph.
Relationship rules are observed,
so deletes will cascade
and relationships will be nullified.
The general use case we have seen
is from expiration code
that determines the time to live
for objects
and cleans up those objects
that have reached their expiration.
This is a great use of this API.
However, what seems like a simple
operation can have complex ramifications.
How about an example?
Here, we have an example
where our earthquake data
expires after 30 days.
And since this is a clean-up task,
we have it dispatched asynchronously
with a background priority.
Our block kicks off
on the managed object context
and determines the expiration date.
Then we build our fetch request
and set our expiration predicate...
create a batch delete request
with our new fetch request, and execute.
Hmm. But what if we had
a large number of objects
that matched
our batch delete search criteria?
The request would take
a write lock on our store for,
uh-oh, possibly some
unbounded amount of time.
But wait. We can fix this.
Let's set a fetch limit.
This way our task doesn't go unbounded,
and we've saved our user
from a lot of frustration.
Now that we've avoided this pitfall,
let's see how we can improve
how to fetch data.
Now that we have this rich object graph,
we need to investigate and display
what we have in our store.
When fetching data, the data we get back
can drive a lot of views and computations.
But do we always need that much data?
And how can we do
these complex computations
without the entire object graph?
Well, first, the managedObjectResultType
provides the easiest way
to traverse the object graph
to the fullest extent.
This is great when we're using the results
to batch a fetchResultsController.
As our managed objects are updated,
our fetchResultsController
magically responds and applies the diffs.
Let's see this in action.
Here's our Earthquakes Sample
without any data, and then we fetch.
As the objects are fetched,
our fetchResultsController is adding rows.
And as we update these objects,
our view is also updated.
But if you notice here,
our view only shows about 15 earthquakes.
We fetched a lot more than that.
We have some room for improvement here.
By setting the batch size
on our fetch request,
the results will only have the first batch
of a given number of objects
fully hydrated with data.
And when our user scrolls,
the remaining objects will be hydrated,
but only as far as the user needs.
The batched array is special
and behaves differently
than a traditional array.
Let me show you.
Here, we have a regular result array.
All our managed objects are hydrated,
and as we iterate over them,
all is as expected.
Now we have a batched array.
Notice that we do not have managed objects
but ObjectIDs
that will turn into managed objects
upon iterating over the array.
And as I move on, the batches are released
and only the ObjectID is retained
for the results.
Let's see this in action.
Here's our Earthquakes Sample
fetching data,
and it shows the idle memory
at roughly 17 megs.
Well, what if we turn on batch fetch?
When we set the batch size,
we only use roughly 12 megs of memory
to do the same task,
and we've saved almost five megs,
nearly a third
of our application's memory usage.
How else can we improve our fetches?
We can trim down what data
the fetch fetches.
If we know the result will need
certain attributes or relationships,
we can tailor our fetch
to these requirements.
For the known attributes
that will be accessed,
we can set propertiesToFetch.
When we work with managed objects,
the default behavior is to have
the relationship set as "false,"
and the first traversal of a relationship
will trigger the fetch
of the related object.
This is great if few relationships
are traversed, or none at all.
But if it is known that a relationship
is highly likely to be traversed,
we recommend setting that key path
to be prefetched,
thus avoiding having to fetch the data
at a later time
and inefficiently, as the faults
are loaded on each traversal.
Here is our baseline fetch,
which sits idle at 17.6 megs.
But if we set the propertiesToFetch
to only those attributes
visible in our UI,
we can reduce our idle memory
to 16.4 megs.
Now let's talk about ObjectIDs.
Managed objects are large
and rich with data,
but these are not ideal
to pass between threads,
so ObjectIDResultType comes in handy.
When we want to do the work
and identify the objects
that meet a certain criteria,
these simple identifiers can be passed
to other threads for further processing,
avoiding that lookup cost
on the processing thread.
But what if we need something in between
a full managed object and ObjectIDs?
Like dictionary results,
which are very handy as they provide
a lightweight, read-only data set
that can be passed to other threads.
Dictionary results can also be tailored
to do complex data aggregation
that can help reduce large computations
that would normally require
pulling in the relevant object graph...
such as groupBy with aggregate functions
on the entities and their properties.
Let's look at an example.
Average magnitude grouped by place.
First, we determine
our key path expression for magnitude,
then our function expression
to get the average.
Then we make an expression description
of our average magnitude.
And lastly, we set up our fetch request
for quakes with properties to fetch,
our expression description and the place,
grouped by the place,
and set the result to "dictionary."
And this leads to these results,
which show us the average magnitude
for earthquakes in the designated places.
Our last result type to cover
is the countResultType.
It's simple, elegant and optimized.
Need I say more?
We've optimized ingestion and fetching.
Now let's look at how we can improve
our application's reactions
to changes in our persistent store.
Core Data is rich with notifications
that let you know when stores
have been added or removed,
or objects have been saved or changed.
But we want to focus on two in particular
that are really useful.
This year,
we've introduced ObjectID notifications
that are available in addition
to the traditional save notification.
The ObjectID notification
is a lightweight counterpart
to the managed object save notification
you're already familiar with,
and this convenient notification is vended
from persistent history transactions.
Let's look at these new additions
in Swift.
The managed object context now has
modernized notifications for Swift.
We've updated some oldies but goodies
to be friendlier in Swift
and added these two new notifications
that allow you to drive your application
with ObjectIDs
rather than managed objects.
But that's not all that we've modernized.
As part of our efforts to modernize,
we've also added notification keys
that make notification processing
much easier in Swift.
We've also added some new keys
to go with the ObjectID notifications.
And the other notification
we want to discuss
is the remote change notification.
Remote change notifications
are very informative
because they're posted for all operations
that are done in and out of your process
by any Core Data client.
This allows your application
to avoid polling for changes
and be able to drive that same logic
with notifications.
And when persistent history is enabled,
the userInfo
of a remote change notification
contains a persistent history token
which can be used to get
an ObjectID notification.
Let's see this in the works.
Here we have our container and application
and a table showing our persistent history
that has been captured so far.
The JSON feed from the USGS comes online,
and the background context ingests
the JSON data into the persistent store.
And persistent history captures
the operation with great detail,
much more than we can show you here.
Previously, though,
our application would need
to poll the store for new changes.
But not with remote change notifications.
Instead, we're notified
that changes have been made,
and the userInfo payload
for the remote change notification
has a history token so I can see
the exact operation in persistent history.
Let's see how this works
as our application evolves.
Our application has some new additions:
a share extension, a second application
that harnesses the same data,
and a handy Photos extension.
When one of these new additions
makes a change to the persistent store,
the operation is recorded
in persistent history.
However, when an application
comes to the foreground,
it needs to poll for history,
which is really expensive.
But if we have
remote change notifications enabled,
we get notified when our app
is brought to the foreground...
and on subsequent changes
by our Photos extension...
and our second application...
and our share extension.
When our app relaunches,
it is notified and can easily see
what has changed with persistent history.
These two features make it really easy
to know who, what, when, where,
and how the persistent store has changed.
Lastly, a quick tip on persistent history.
A rather handy tip for persistent history
is the same we told you earlier
for fetch requests.
Make sure to tailor the request
to your application's needs.
Here, we have an example
of how to tailor the change request
so that we can find all the changes for
a specific ObjectID after a given date.
First, we start off
by getting our entity description
for the persistent history
change object...
so that we can use it
to build our fetch request
and set the entity.
Then we set our predicate here,
looking for changes
to a specific ObjectID,
and then we create our history request,
and set the fetch request.
And voilà, execute.
Our results will only be those changes
for the given ObjectID
after the specific date.
That's all we have for this session.
A quick recap:
batch when possible,
tailor your fetches to the intended use
and harness the power of notifications
and persistent history.
Thanks to all of you
and to the Core Data team.
It's been an honor.