Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name's Andy.
I'll be talking to you about how
to "Safely Manage Pointers in Swift."
This session builds directly
on "Unsafe Swift" also from WWDC 20.
In that session,
we defined unsafe operations
as having undefined behavior
on some input.
In this talk,
I'll delve deeper into some details
of programming Swift
outside the usual safety zone.
These aren't the kind of details
that application programmers
typically need to worry about.
Managing pointers safely means knowing
all the different ways they can be unsafe.
I'll spend most of our time here
on type safety.
This is a source of undefined behavior
in C that tends to be poorly understood.
I'll explain the APIs that give Swift
the same low-level capabilities
and explain how to use them
to avoid that undefined behavior.
Pointer safety can be looked at
as a series of levels.
Each level down,
you take more responsibility
for the correctness of your code.
So it's recommended that you write code
at the highest safety level possible.
The first level is safe code.
A major goal of Swift
is providing new ways of writing code
that don't require any unsafe constructs.
Swift has a robust type system
that provides a lot of flexibility
and performance.
Swift's collection APIs,
slices and iterators
provide much of the functionality
you may have wanted from pointers.
And not using pointers at all
is a great strategy for code safety.
But another important goal of Swift
is performant interoperability
with unsafe languages.
To do that, Swift needs to provide
low-level expressibility
in the form of unsafe APIs.
These are denoted by the prefix "Unsafe"
in their type or function name.
Swift's UnsafePointer
lets you take responsibility
for some of the dangers of using pointers
without worrying about type safety.
If you need to work with raw memory
as a sequence of bytes,
Swift provides UnsafeRawPointer.
Loading and storing values with raw memory
gives you the responsibility
for knowing the layout of types.
At the deepest level,
Swift provides a few APIs
for binding memory to types.
It's only by using
one of these lowest level APIs
that you take full responsibility
away from Swift
for managing the safety of pointer types.
Let me explain
what I mean by levels of safety.
Safe code isn't necessarily correct code,
but it does behave predictably.
In most cases, if a programming error
could lead to unpredictable behavior,
then the compiler catches it.
For errors that can't be caught
at compile time,
runtime checks guarantee that the program
crashes immediately with a diagnostic.
It won't continue past
an incorrect assumption.
So safe code is really
about error enforcement.
If you don't use any Swift types
or APIs that are marked unsafe
and you take care to manage thread safety,
then you know that predictable behavior
is fully enforced.
In unsafe Swift code, predictable behavior
is not fully enforced,
so you take on extra responsibility.
Testing still provides
helpful diagnostics.
But the level of diagnostics depends
on the level of safety you've chosen.
Unsafe standard library APIs
have assertions in debug builds
that catch certain kinds of invalid input.
Adding your own preconditions
to verify unsafe assumptions
is also good practice.
You can test with more runtime checks
by enabling sanitizers,
like the address sanitizer.
Sanitizer diagnostics are a great
time-saver by pinpointing bugs
but they don't catch
all undefined behavior.
When errors are not uncovered
during testing,
they can lead
to unexpected runtime behavior.
That could be a hard to debug crash
that occurs
far from the source of the problem.
Or worse than a crash,
your program could do the wrong thing,
even corrupting user data.
A crash is a bad experience,
but corrupting or losing data is worse.
The further down you venture
into unsafe territory,
the harder it is to find those mistakes,
and the more confusing
the symptoms may be.
Symptoms may not even show up
until long after the bug was introduced.
Let's look at pointers to understand
some of the ways that code can be unsafe.
Swift is designed to be programmed
without using pointers,
and looking at why they're unsafe
will make it clear
why avoiding them is a good strategy.
But if you do need to directly
access memory using low-level APIs,
it's also useful to know how to manage
different aspects of safety yourself.
You may need to
point to the storage for a variable,
to the elements of an array,
or to memory that you allocated directly.
Before you can point to that object,
it needs a stable memory location.
The stable storage that you point to
has a limited lifetime,
either because it goes out of scope
or because you directly
deallocate the memory.
However,
your pointer value has its own lifetime.
When the pointer's lifetime
exceeds the storage lifetime,
any attempt to access it is undefined.
This is the primary reason that pointers
are unsafe, but not the only one.
Objects can be composed
of a sequence of elements.
Pointers are allowed to move
to different memory addresses
by adding offsets to the pointer.
That's an efficient way
to address different elements.
But adding or subtracting
too large of an offset
points to memory
that doesn't belong to the same object.
Accessing a pointer that has exceeded
its object's boundary is undefined.
For this talk,
we'll focus on another aspect of safety
that's easily overlooked.
Pointers have their own types,
distinct from the types
of values in memory.
How do we ensure those types
are consistent,
and what happens if they aren't?
When we ask for a pointer
to storage of type Int16,
we get back a pointer to Int16.
So far so good.
As we'll see, it's pretty hard to get
a pointer to the wrong type in Swift.
Now let's say we manage to overwrite
the same memory with a different type,
now Int32.
At that point, we'll have a pointer
to the correct Int32 type,
but our Int16 pointer
could still be hanging around.
Accessing the old pointer of type Int16
is undefined behavior
because the pointer type and
the in-memory type are now inconsistent.
You might be wondering,
"How can undefined behavior
be worse than a program crash,
and why would pointer types cause that?"
To understand,
let's look at some very unsafe code.
I don't expect anyone
to write code like this,
but you may be surprised
at what Swift code can look like
when it's ported from C,
and still calls parts of the old C code.
Code that does scary things
is supposed to look scary,
but we don't need to understand all these
low-level types yet to see the problem.
Imagine we have a collage struct
that holds a stand-alone pointer
to some image data in memory
and another property for the image count.
Maybe this type was imported from C.
We also have a function, addImages,
that writes image data into memory
and increases an image count.
When we call addImages,
we want it to update the image count
in our collage struct,
but there's a mismatch between
our struct's imageCount type, Int,
and the function argument's
pointer to UInt32.
The safe thing to do would be to create
a new count variable of the correct type
and use Swift's integer conversions.
Instead, this complex line of code creates
a pointer directly into our struct.
Later, the code needs to read the image
count again to pass it to saveImages.
The problem is, at runtime,
this count could be zero,
meaning that the program
has silently lost all the images.
By giving the count property an Int type
and the pointer a UInt32 type,
we've signaled to the compiler
that those values reside
in different memory objects.
The compiler does not see
any updates to an Int object,
so it could just reuse
the initialization value of zero.
In practice, the compiler is forgiving,
so such a small example
probably won't go wrong.
But we can't predict what will happen.
To the compiler, type information
is a fact that assumptions are based on.
Once the compiler makes a bad assumption,
that can percolate through the compiler's
pipeline and show up in surprising ways.
So, two versions of the compiler
can cause different program behavior.
Pointer type bugs
can cause your program to misbehave
in ways that are worse than crashing.
But what makes them more insidious
is that it's rare for them to be observed.
So, a program may appear to work fine
while a bug lingers in the code for years
without anyone noticing.
Someone might later make a safe
and seemingly innocuous change
to the source that exposes the problem.
Or it may show up
after a regular compiler update,
so your program starts
behaving differently
without anyone changing the code.
The challenge of pointer type safety
predates Swift.
Knowing how to use
pointer types correctly in C
requires deep knowledge
of the language spec.
You can find those discussions
under the terms "strict aliasing"
and "type punning."
Fortunately, you're not expected
to understand those rules
to be able to use Swift pointers safely.
It is common to pass pointers
from Swift into C though,
so Swift pointers need to be at least
as strict as C to safely interoperate.
Swift's UnsafePointer
gives you most of the low-level
capabilities of C pointers.
In exchange, you need to manage
object lifetime and object boundaries.
The "Unsafe Swift" talk
explains how to do this.
But you do not need
to take responsibility for type safety.
UnsafePointer's generic type parameter
is enforced at compile time,
making it a type-safe API.
Let's look at Swift's rules
for pointer type safety
to see why this works.
UnsafePointer's type parameter indicates
the type of value expected
to be held in memory.
We call this a typed pointer.
In Swift, the rule for typed pointers
is strict and simple.
Conceptually, the memory state includes
the type
that a memory location is bound to.
That memory location
can only hold values of that type.
As a type-safe API, UnsafePointer only
reads values of that type from memory,
and UnsafeMutablePointer only reads
or writes values of that type.
It may be natural to think
that pointer types won't matter,
as long as the bytes are laid out
in memory correctly.
And in C, it's not uncommon
to cast pointers to different types,
with both pointers continuing
to refer to the same memory.
Whether that's actually legal in C
depends on various special cases.
In Swift, accessing a pointer
whose type parameter does not match
its memory location's bound type
is always undefined behavior.
To guard against this,
Swift does not allow casting pointers
in the familiar C style.
This way, pointer types are enforced
at compile time by Swift's type system.
There's no need to store
extra runtime information,
extra type information in memory
or perform extra runtime checks.
Let's look at how memory is bound to
a type and where typed pointers come from.
If you declare a variable of type Int
and ask for a pointer
to the variable's storage,
you'll get back a pointer-to-Int
consistent with the variable declaration.
Array storage is bound
to the array element type.
And of course, asking for a pointer
into array storage
gives you a pointer
to the array's element type.
You can also allocate memory directly
by calling the static allocate method
on UnsafeMutablePointer.
Allocation binds memory
to its type parameter
and returns a typed pointer
to the new memory.
This is different from pointers
to variables and arrays
because, as the state diagram shows,
memory is already bound to a type
even though it doesn't hold
any initialized values yet.
You can use the typed pointer
that allocation gives you
to initialize memory
only to the correct type.
In the initialized state,
memory can be reassigned.
Assignment implicitly deinitializes
the previous in-memory value
and reinitializes memory
to a new value of the same type.
You can deinitialize memory
using the same typed pointer.
At that point,
memory is still bound to the same type,
but it's now safe to deallocate.
With variable and array storage,
these steps are automatically
handled by Swift.
With direct allocation,
you take responsibility
for managing memory's initialized state,
but Swift still ensures type safety.
Since typed pointers
follow simple, strict rules,
you generally
won't have two active pointers
to the same memory location
that disagree on the type.
But let's see what happens
with composite types.
In this example, we have a block of memory
that contains values of type MyStruct.
We can either get a pointer
to the outer struct
or a pointer to its property,
and those pointers are both valid
at the same time.
We can access either one without changing
the type that memory is bound to.
This still obeys the same basic rule
for pointer safety
because when memory is bound
to a composite type,
it's also effectively bound
to the members of that type,
as they're laid out in memory.
Swift's typed pointers
give you direct access to memory,
but only within the confines
of type safety.
You can't have two typed pointers
to the same memory
that disagree on the type.
So, if your goal is to reinterpret
bytes of memory as different types,
then you need use a lower-level API.
UnsafeRawPointer lets you refer
to a sequence of bytes
without specifying the type of values
they may represent.
You take control over memory layout.
With a raw pointer,
you interpret bytes as typed values
when you load them from memory.
Consider a block of memory
that's initialized to Int64
using a typed pointer.
It's always possible
to cast from a typed pointer
down to a raw pointer.
Operations on that raw pointer
only see the sequence of bytes in memory.
The memory's bound type is irrelevant.
You can ask that raw pointer
to load any type.
It does that by reading
the required number of bytes
and assembling them
into the requested type.
For example, when we call load as UInt32,
four bytes are loaded from the current
address generating a UInt32 value.
It's even okay to load a smaller type,
as long as you account
for the target platform's endianness.
You can also use a raw pointer
to write a value's bytes into memory.
Storing bytes is asymmetric with loading
because it modifies the in-memory value.
Unlike assignment using a typed pointer,
storing raw bytes does not deinitialize
the previous value in memory.
So it's now your responsibility
to make sure the memory doesn't
contain any object references.
In this example,
calling storeBytes on a raw pointer
extracts four bytes from a UInt32 value,
writing them into the upper four bytes
of an in-memory Int64 value.
When the bytes are written to memory,
they're reinterpreted
as the memory's bound type.
So the typed pointer that already points
to the in-memory value
can still be used to access it.
We cannot cast a raw pointer
back into a typed pointer
because doing that would conflict
with the memory's bound type.
In this case, we would end up
with both a pointer to Int64
and a pointer to UInt32
to overlapping memory.
Casting from a typed pointer
is not the only way to get a raw pointer.
The withUnsafeBytes API
exposes a variable storage
as a raw buffer
for the duration of its closure.
UnsafeRawBufferPointer
is a collection of bytes,
just like UnsafeBufferPointer
is a collection of typed values.
Here, the buffer count is the size
in bytes of the variable's type.
The collection index is a byte offset,
and reading the indexed element
gives you a UInt8 value for that byte.
You can also modify
a variable's raw storage.
withUnsafeMutableBytes
gives you a collection of mutable bytes
so you can store UInt8 values
at specific byte offsets.
And just like array
has a withUnsafeBufferPointer method,
it also has a withUnsafeBytes method
that exposes the raw storage
for the array elements.
The buffer size will be the array's count
multiplied by the element stride.
Some of those bytes could be padding
for element alignment.
Foundation's data type is often used
to pass around a collection of bytes.
Data also has a withUnsafeBytes method
that exposes the underlying raw pointer
for the duration of a closure.
Here, we use that
to read a specific element type, UInt32,
at a chosen byte offset.
You can allocate raw memory directly
by calling the static allocate method
on UnsafeMutableRawPointer.
Here you take on the responsibility
to compute the memory size
and alignment in bytes.
After raw allocation,
the memory state is neither initialized
nor bound to a type.
To initialize memory with a raw pointer,
you need to specify the type of values
that memory will hold.
Initialization binds memory to that type
and returns a typed pointer.
The transition to initialized memory
only goes in one direction.
To deinitialize memory,
you need to know the type
of in-memory values.
So there's no way
to deinitialize with a raw pointer.
You can deinitialize using the typed
pointer returned by initialization.
We already saw the memory state diagram
for typed pointers.
You can use the raw pointer
to deallocate the memory
as long as it's in an uninitialized state.
Deallocation doesn't care
if a memory is bound to a type or not.
Memory allocation with typed pointers
is safer and more convenient,
so that should be preferred.
But here's an example of why you might
want to allocate raw storage instead.
Let's say we want to store unrelated types
in the same contiguous block of memory
with variable length.
After computing the total size
in bytes and the alignment,
we call the raw version of allocate.
That gives us a raw pointer
to a contiguous block of bytes.
Now we can initialize part of that memory
as the header,
giving us a pointer to the header type.
After adding the header's byte offset,
we can initialize
the remaining bytes to integers.
That gives us a separate typed pointer
to the region of memory
holding only integers.
This storage allocation technique is great
for implementing standard library types
like Set and Dictionary,
but not usually something
you want to reach for.
In general, raw pointers
are a kind of power tool
that are good for implementing
high performance data structures,
but we don't want to expose them too much.
Fiddling with byte offsets
and data alignment is very tricky.
The more likely case
where you'll want to use a raw pointer
is when you have a buffer of bytes
that's externally generated,
and you want to decode those bytes
into Swift types.
Using UnsafeRawBufferPointer's
load API,
we first read a descriptor
to determine the sizes and types
of subsequent data.
We follow up with more calls to
the load API at increasing byte offsets,
each time specifying whatever type
we want to decode from the stream.
Raw pointers retain
an important level of type safety.
You take responsibility for memory layout
at the point that they're used,
but they don't affect when its legal
to use typed pointers,
so using raw pointers
does not make it more dangerous
to use the same memory and typed pointers.
At the deepest level, Swift provides APIs
that expose memory's bound type.
When you use these APIs,
you're taking all the responsibility
for pointer type safety.
Before jumping into these,
see if you can use one
of the higher-level APIs instead.
You'll know when you're circumventing
the enforcement of pointer types
because you'll need
to explicitly call an API
that refers to memory's bound type.
The danger of circumventing type safety
is that you can easily introduce
undefined behavior
somewhere else in the code
where typed pointers are used.
There's still just one rule to follow:
access to a typed pointer needs to agree
with the memory's bound type.
It is a simple rule,
but it's not easy to follow
because different parts of the code
all need to agree on memory type,
and the compiler
won't be able to guide you.
Let's look at some of the reasons
you might use such a dangerous API,
and pay attention
to why each of these uses is safe.
In rare cases,
code may not preserve a typed pointer.
What if we just have the raw pointer,
but we know with certainty
what type the memory is bound to?
We should be able to tell Swift
we know what we're doing
and get back our typed pointer.
In this example, we have a container
that holds raw memory,
but we also have a variable,
pointsToInt,
telling us whether the memory
can only hold integer values.
Calling assumingMemoryBound-to
on our raw pointer
and giving it the Int type as an argument
gives us back a typed pointer to integers.
We know this is safe because
when we allocated the memory,
it was bound to type Int.
Only call assumingMemoryBound-to
when you can guarantee the memory
will already be bound
to the type you want.
It's not checked at runtime.
It's just a way to ask the compiler
to make an assumption,
so you're on the hook
for the correctness of that assumption.
Here's another example
where we need assumingMemoryBound-to.
This time we're calling the C API
pthread_create.
First we initialize a context pointer
with our custom ThreadContext type.
When we call pthread_create,
we pass it our context pointer.
But when pthread_create calls back
to our start routine in a new thread,
it only gives us a raw pointer.
The C function declares
a void star argument to the callback,
which gets imported
as UnsafeMutableRawPointer.
That sort of thing happens in C sometimes,
and there's no way
to make it generally type-safe.
In this case, we do know it's safe
to recover a typed context pointer
by calling assumingMemoryBound-to
because that's the type
we just bound memory to
when we allocated it a few lines above.
In the last couple examples,
the original pointer type was erased.
Sometimes we have a typed pointer,
but it's at the wrong level
in a composition of types.
Here we have a function
that takes a pointer to integers.
If we have a tuple of Ints,
we should be able to pass a pointer to
the tuple's elements into that function.
To get a pointer into the tuple's storage,
we need to call withUnsafePointer.
But that gives us back a pointer
to the tuple type,
which is incompatible
with our function type.
Memory can only be bound
to one type at a time,
but since the tuple type
is a composite type,
binding memory to a tuple type
also binds it to the element types.
So, we know using a pointer to integers
for the tuple's storage is type-safe,
but we need to use a type-unsafe API
to get that pointer type.
First we construct a raw pointer,
deliberately erasing the type
of our tuple pointer.
Then we can use assumingMemoryBound-to,
just like we did before,
to create a pointer to integers.
Lowering a pointer down
to a member type like this
requires knowing the layout
of the composite type.
Swift's implementation does guarantee
that tuples whose elements
are all the same type
are laid out in a standard pattern,
one value after another,
according to the stride
of the element type.
Let's look at how this applies
to struct properties.
Once again, we have a function
that takes a pointer to integers.
This time, instead of a tuple,
we have a struct with an integer property.
withUnsafePointer gives us
a typed pointer to our outer struct.
Using the MemoryLayout API,
we compute the byte offset
of the value property.
By casting the struct pointer
down to a raw pointer
and adding that byte offset,
we get a raw pointer
to the value property.
A property's memory is always bound
to the property's declared type,
so it's safe to call
assumingMemoryBound-to
to get a pointer to an integer.
In general, the layout
of struct properties is not guaranteed,
so when you get a pointer
to a struct property,
you can only use it to point
to a single value for that property.
Pointing to struct properties is common,
so, fortunately,
there's an easy alternative
that avoids unsafe APIs.
When you pass the property
as an inout argument,
the compiler implicitly converts it
to the unsafe pointer type
declared for that function argument.
assumingMemoryBound-to
tells the compiler
to make an unchecked assumption
about the memory's bound type.
The bindMemory API actually lets you
change memory's bound type.
If the memory location
was not already bound to a type,
it just binds the type for the first time.
If the memory is already bound to a type,
then it rebinds the type,
and whatever values were in memory
take on the new type.
Say we allocate a block of memory
to hold two UInt16 values.
Then we ask for a raw pointer
to that block of memory.
By calling bindMemory
on that raw pointer,
we change the type in place
to a single Int32 value.
This is just a bitwise conversion,
so you don't get any of the safety checks
that happen with normal type conversion.
In fact,
nothing needs to happen at runtime.
bindMemory is really a declaration
to the compiler
that the type has changed
at that memory location.
bindMemory returns an Int32 pointer
that should be used
to access the memory now.
Accessing the old UInt16 pointer
is undefined.
At any single point in the program,
a memory location
is only bound to a single type.
Changing the memory's bound type
doesn't physically modify memory,
but you should still think of it
as changing a global property
of the memory state.
This isn't type-safe for two reasons.
First, it reinterprets
the raw bytes in place.
So, just like
when you're using a raw pointer,
you're taking responsibility
away from Swift
for the layout of types in memory.
But rebinding memory is more dangerous
than using raw pointers
because it also invalidates
existing typed pointers.
Their pointer address is still valid,
but accessing them is undefined
while memory is bound to the wrong type.
When you have a pointer into storage
for an object with a declared type,
like variables, arrays,
and other collection types,
using that pointer to rebind memory
can invalidate the object itself.
The bindMemory API is really
a low-level language primitive in Swift.
It's not intended for regular code.
In reality, though, there are situations
where you want to rebind the memory type.
This happens when you have
multiple external APIs
that disagree on the type of some data,
and you want to avoid
copying the data back and forth.
It's something that tends
to come up with C APIs
where pointer type safety
was not carefully considered.
Here we have a function
that takes a UInt8 pointer,
and we have pointer
into memory of type Int8.
Swift enforces pointer types,
so it won't let us pass that pointer
into that function.
We could allocate a new block of memory
with the correct type and copy the data.
That's safe
with regard to pointer types but slower.
Since we only need to reinterpret memory
for the duration of a call,
we can use Swift's
withMemoryRebound to API.
Just like with UnsafePointer,
withMemoryRebound to
gives you a pointer that's guaranteed
to be valid for the scope of its closure.
We know it's safe to rebind memory
within the closure
because our Int8 pointer
isn't used anywhere inside the closure.
When the closure returns,
withMemoryRebound to rebinds memory
back to the original Int8 type.
This makes it independent of typed
pointer access in surrounding code.
We can prove it's safe to use
just by reasoning about the code
within the closure.
The withMemoryRebound to API
makes binding memory safe
with respect to surrounding code,
but it has some strict limitations.
Because of these, you still may
need to call bindMemory directly.
When you do that, use the same
technique to reason about safety.
Only use bindMemory to get a pointer
within a controlled scope
where you know the code isn't accessing
the same memory with an old pointer.
When the scope ends, make sure
to rebind memory back to the original type
before other code
can access the same memory
using a previously obtained pointer.
Let's recap the memory-binding APIs.
assumingMemoryBound-to
is the intended way
to recover a typed pointer
from a raw pointer.
It's dangerous because you need to know
the memory is already bound to that type.
bindMemory is a low-level primitive
that changes the memory's
bound type state.
It's especially dangerous
because it can cause undefined behavior
when typed pointers are accessed
elsewhere in the code.
withMemoryRebound to is a much safer way
to temporarily bind memory
when it's necessary.
It's useful for calling C APIs
that disagree on types
without copying the underlying memory.
The most common misuse
of the bindMemory API
is simply to read a different type
from memory.
This code calls bindMemory to get
a pointer of the type it wants to read.
That typed pointer
is only needed to read a value.
But in the process
of creating that pointer,
we've changed memory state
and probably invalidated other pointers.
When you just want to reinterpret a type,
UnsafeRawPointer's load API
is a solution
that avoids the pitfalls of pointer type.
You only need to take responsibility
for memory layout.
The solution works wherever you need it,
so if you have a typed pointer to the
memory, you can cast it to a raw pointer.
And if you have a variable,
an array, or a Data object,
the withUnsafeBytes method
directly gives you access to a raw buffer.
Let's say you want to view
a region of memory
as sequence of elements
with a specific element type,
but the underlying storage
is exposed as a raw pointer
and may be viewed as different types
by different parts of the code.
You could easily create a wrapper
around that raw pointer
to preserve your element type.
Let's call it a BufferView.
We'll add the Unsafe prefix to the name,
so we don't need to
automatically manage memory
and we'll limit boundary checks
to the debug build.
To create a BufferView over a raw buffer,
we compute the number of elements
that fit in the buffer
based on the element stride.
And of course,
we add preconditions to verify
the buffer has the correct number
of bytes and alignment.
Now, to read an indexed element,
we just compute its byte offset
and ask the raw buffer
to load our element type.
Since loading from raw memory
is safe with respect to pointer types,
we don't need to worry about
how other code views the same memory.
Our BufferView lets us reinterpret
the sequence of bytes safely,
while retaining the element type,
so there's no need to use a typed pointer.
To end, let's review our strategies
for handling pointer types.
The best strategy is to avoid
using pointers whenever you can.
In the rare case you need to reinterpret
the same memory location
as a different type,
you should choose carefully.
Since typed pointers always need to match
the memory's bound type,
it's best not to use them
to reinterpret types.
This can be hard to remember though
because C code often handles this
by casting pointer types.
Instead, Swift provides APIs based
on raw pointers for that purpose.
These are useful APIs
even in pure Swift code.
For example, you may need to
decode values from a byte stream.
Or you might implement
a container like Set or Dictionary
that holds different types
in contiguous memory.
I hope you enjoyed hearing
about pointer type safety in Swift
and can see
it's not as mysterious as it may look.
Thanks for watching.