Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Thalia,
and together with Paolo, we're here
to go through what's new in SF Symbols.
Today, we're going to have a recap
of what SF Symbols is in the basics.
We're going to look
at some new additions and refinements.
We will talk about localized symbols
and how you can make your apps
awesome with them.
We will see how to deal with
old and new symbols
when targeting different OS versions.
We will talk about colors.
And lastly, we're going to talk
about layouts when using SF Symbols.
So, let's get started.
At Apple, we design interfaces
for apps and devices
that millions of people use
around the world.
When we design at this scale,
it is essential to have a visual system
that embodies ideas,
giving more substantial meaning
to representations of actions, objects
and even more abstract concepts
like language.
That's why we designed SF Symbols,
a consistent and flexible library
of iconography we introduced last year
that is designed to seamlessly integrate
with the system font, San Francisco.
All the San Francisco families:
SF Pro, SF Pro Rounded, SF Compact
and SF Compact Rounded.
When symbols appear next to text,
they are vertically centered
with a cap height.
Still, there are other typographic
guidelines we need to consider.
Let's look at the baseline.
The baseline is the imaginary line
upon which the text rests,
and all typographic elements
are related to it.
While text always sits on the baseline,
that's not necessarily true for symbols.
The relationship of the symbols
with a baseline
works in a bit of a different way.
Indeed, symbols are designed
to work next to text,
but we take the baseline
as a flexible guide when creating one.
Some can sit above the baseline,
like the infinity symbol.
And some symbols can descend below it,
like the folder symbol.
This is intended,
and it's meant to optically balance
the shape of the symbol
with San Francisco,
so consider this
when designing your own symbols.
All symbols come in three scales:
small, medium and large,
with medium being the default scale.
The symbol scales can be used
to vary the emphasis of a symbol
relative to the text it sits adjacent to
while remaining weight-matched
and vertically centered with text.
Let's take a look at the scales
in more detail.
Small symbols are approximately
20% smaller than the medium scale.
And large symbols are about 30% larger
than the medium scale.
But as we can see, only scaling the symbol
will make them appear
to have different weights.
Of all the symbols,
the small scale looks lighter,
and the large scale looks bolder.
It's a very subtle difference,
but we make some weight compensations
which allow us to maintain
the same stroke thickness,
making the symbols look weight-matched
not only between the scales
but also with text.
Here are some examples.
Different scales may be appropriate
based on the amount of vertical space
surrounding a symbol in a container.
Remember, the point size
of all these symbols
is the same relative to the text.
It's just the scale of the symbol
that changes.
You've seen SF Symbols
in the user interfaces since last year
throughout the system
and the apps we make,
but also from you.
These are only some of the examples
of what you have made.
The response has been truly amazing.
Let's look at how to use SF Symbols
with an example.
We're going to see how to do this
in design tools and in code.
We're going to use
the SF Symbols app and Xcode.
The SF Symbols app has been updated,
and a better version is available
for download
from the Apple Developer website
like before.
It comes with a version
of the system fonts
suitable for design tools.
And these fonts have symbols in them.
So, here's the app I'm working on
for our example.
This is a great opportunity
to use symbols.
With symbols, we can make
the Play and the Shuffle button
more distinctive and recognizable.
To do that, let's look at it
in a design tool like Sketch.
Here's my document
with the interface I'm working on.
I have installed the SF Symbols app
and the fonts that come with it.
We now need to add
the Play and the Shuffle symbols.
To do that,
let's go to the SF Symbols app,
go into the search field and look for it.
Here it is.
Now, I just copy the symbol
with the usual shortcut, command-C,
or using the Edit drop-down menu.
Then I'll just paste it in my artwork.
That's it. That's all I need.
See here that I have my text
set out to 17 points
for the text and for the symbol.
I can then do the same
for the shuffle symbol.
I'll go back to the app, search for it,
then I'll just copy and paste it.
Nothing changes.
This is a good spot
to learn how to do this in code.
To do that, here's Paolo to show us how.
Here we have the same view
implemented in UIKit.
I construct my image
with UIImage(systemName
and set it to my view.
The initializer takes a symbol name,
so I look for the symbol name in the app.
I go to the app, search for "play"
and here it is.
It's called "play.fill."
Good. One down.
For the next one,
Thalia tells me it's called "shuffle."
So I go back to the app,
search for "shuffle"
and, indeed, here it is.
Pro tip: I can copy the symbol name
with shift-command-C
and paste that directly into Xcode.
Careful here.
I copied a symbol name,
not the symbol itself.
If you copy the symbol, it will not work.
Now, we're ready to build and run.
And our symbols are showing up.
That's cool,
but in this instance, we can do better.
If we look at the relationship
between the text and the symbol,
the symbol appears too big.
We can actually select a different scale
for the symbol.
And remember,
we are not changing the point size.
In Sketch, we can do this by selecting
the small scale stylistic set
from the Text menu.
Now, let's do the same
for the shuffle symbol.
Again, let's select the small scale.
Also notice here how,
when I change the scale,
the symbol remains optically centered
and weight-matched with the text.
And to change the symbol scaling code,
we are going to use
the symbol configuration for that.
So, I just construct
my UIImage.SymbolConfiguration
with a scale, and I'm done.
I could be done here,
but there's a better way.
Let's take it up a notch
and configure a symbol
with the same text style as the font,
so the symbol can resize well
with Dynamic Type.
We can do that by passing the textStyle
argument to our SymbolConfiguration,
in this case, we have a headline.
If we build and run now,
we can see that symbols
follow the selected text size.
If I have it set to large size,
text and symbols go big.
If I pick a small size,
text and symbols resize accordingly.
This is the kind of behavior
we can only get if we use textStyles.
If you've been using SwiftUI instead,
then using symbols looks like this.
Call Image with systemName
to get an image of the symbol back.
Change its scale
with the imageScale modifier
and change other parameters
of the configuration
like point size, font weight
or, as we've seen,
textStyle via the font modifier.
New this year,
we have the very convenient label,
which lets us construct
a very common UI element all in one go.
And we also have a handy way
to do text attachments
by combining text and image.
For more information,
make sure to check out
the "What's New in SwiftUI" session.
This is all great,
but this app also works on macOS,
and it is not a Catalyst app.
Here's what it looks like in Big Sur.
We're thrilled to announce
that starting from macOS Big Sur,
SF Symbols are also available
on the Mac natively.
Now, for the first time, old platforms
can benefit from this unified iconography.
In design, nothing changes.
The way I use symbols
is identical to the other platforms.
In code, we can use symbols
with the new NSImage API,
which can take
an accessibility description
in the constructor.
So, here we have it,
our Music app in its full glory
using SF Symbols on macOS.
As part of the UI redesign for macOS,
not only did we bring SF Symbols
to the Mac,
we also have
some additions and refinements.
In iOS 13,
we shipped more than 1,500 symbols.
Now we have more than 750 new ones.
We have some devices,
some for transportation,
some symbols related to game controllers
and even some human-related symbols.
And all these are neatly organized
in the app with categories.
And not only does the app come
with some predefined categories,
but you can also create
your own collections now.
For example, if I'm designing an app
related to sounds and music,
and I want to have all the symbols I want
to use in one easy, accessible place,
I can create a collection
based on my selection,
name it "Music," in this case,
and even add or delete
more symbols as I go.
Another improvement is
for when symbols are laid out vertically.
This is especially true for symbols
that have variants with badges.
For instance, if we focus on folder
and folder-related symbols,
you can see how more often than not
we want to align the symbols
so that the badge
extends beyond the folder itself.
This is an optical alignment,
so you should use your best judgment
if you're creating your own symbol.
This is a great opportunity
to have another look at the template.
If you're not familiar with the template,
it is that artifact
that is a design source file
that I can export from the SF Symbols app,
modify and directly import
into Xcode as is.
There are three rows, one for each
symbol scale, small, medium and large,
and nine columns, one for each weight,
from ultralight to black.
Each one of the symbols
is in its own layer
with a unique, descriptive identifier.
These layer names are vital
to the integrity of the file,
so make sure that if you customize
the template, you maintain this structure.
We have a new version of the template now.
It is labeled as version 2.
It's pretty much identical to version 1,
especially in terms of structure,
but if we zoom in,
there's one important difference.
The margins are not rectangles anymore,
but lines.
This is what lets us set positive
or negative margins.
In this case,
the margin on the left is positive,
and the one on the right is negative
because it tucks in, overlapping
with the outlines of the symbol.
The color is not important here,
it's just a visual indicator.
It's their name and position that matters.
In code, nothing changes.
I still call my symbol as before.
But when I go use the symbol,
the margins produce the correct alignment
that Thalia was just describing.
So, let's talk about localization.
As we know,
English uses the Latin alphabet,
which is a left-to-right writing system,
but in other locales, the writing system
is right to left, like Arabic or Hebrew.
We've had localized symbols
since last year.
Now we have more.
Remember that these
localize automatically,
so there's no need to call out
the localized variants in your spec.
If a symbol is localized, the app
will show you what these variants are.
To implement this for your custom symbols,
there's nothing new.
Remember to localize your asset catalog
and assign a locale to each SVG template.
In some cases,
we do need a different design
that properly responds
to the design sensibilities of the locale,
but in some other cases,
in right-to-left locales,
we can just flip the symbol as is.
To achieve this, set the direction
of the symbol to "mirrors."
This is also a good spot for a quick word
on how to handle deprecated names
and new symbols
when it comes to targeting
previous versions of the OS.
SF Symbols naming system
is designed to have internal consistency.
And the repertoire keeps growing
as we introduce new symbols this year.
Let's look at this example.
In the case of the bin symbols,
we have bins with X marks
and arrows pointing up,
we have filled variants
and circled variants too.
We strive to keep consistency
in the naming scheme.
That's why what was called
"bin.xmark" is now "xmark.bin."
The shape that we named "bin" moved
to preserve coherence with the system.
So how should you deal with that
when targeting different OSes?
First of all,
this information is available to you
when browsing symbols
in the SF Symbols app.
So if your app minimum deployment target
is iOS 13,
you should be looking for symbols
available in that version of the OS.
Those symbols may have a different name
from the latest version of the OS,
so if you're backwards deploying
to iOS 13, you have to use the old name.
The new name will not be available there.
But if your minimum deployment target
is iOS 14, instead,
then you should use the new name.
Xcode is aware of these name changes
and will warn you accordingly
if you're using storyboards.
If you're not careful about this,
people using your app will likely see
no symbol, or worse, even get a crash,
which is definitely not
a great experience.
Okay, next, let's talk about colors.
Symbols can be colored.
As of last year, by default,
they take the tint color of the app.
As a reference,
here's how Calendar does it.
But there are some cases
where we want one symbol
to come with more than one color,
like in the Weather widget.
The symbols related to the weather
are way more effective
if they come in multiple colors.
And sometimes we want both.
We want part of the symbol
to reflect the tint color,
but also come with some pre-tinted parts.
We're happy to announce that all of this
is possible now with multicolor symbols.
A set of predefined colored symbols
to use in your UIs.
You can access them
by the color mode preview in the app,
through the "Toolbar" button
or with the multicolor category.
You can also choose between
the two preview modes:
"monochrome" for the black and white
version of the symbol
and "multicolor" for the colored version.
In my specs, I will just make sure
to annotate symbols with "multicolor."
These colors adapt dynamically
with appearances, just like system colors.
In code, this is done by asking
for a version of the symbol image
with a different rendering mode.
Pass true to setTemplate
for the monochrome, tintable symbol,
and this is the default behavior,
by the way,
and pass false
to get the multicolor version.
Speaking of specs,
let's have a refresher of the benefits
of using symbols in layouts.
Here's an example of a spec.
In this case, it is for Mail.
We have a pretty standard
macOS sidebar layout,
with symbols and text next to each other.
The symbols here specify
a scale and a point size,
the same point size as the text.
Symbols and text are baseline aligned.
There should be no surprises here by now.
On the vertical axis,
the labels are leading aligned,
and my column of symbols
is center aligned.
This may be different
from what you're used to
if you're coming from a pre-symbols world.
Notice here, I do not specify frames.
Symbols are not designed to be constrained
in frames with a specific size.
It's the typographic nature of symbols
that really makes it easy to spec
as if they were text.
This frees you from having to
specify frames and alignments
that would make it really hard,
if not impossible,
to leverage all the features
of SF Symbols.
Symbols have their own size.
They will occupy a different amount
of surface on the screen,
but they're coherent
relative to each other,
so don't force them into a frame.
Be wary of anything that uses
sizeThatFits and symbols.
As long as symbols have the same
text style or point size,
you will be good.
Also make sure to use center alignments
rather than aspectFit or scale to fit,
and check your content gravity is set
to "centered" if you're using CALayers,
especially when symbols are enclosed
in a well-defined area.
When laying symbols next to text,
remember to align them to the baseline,
not to align them to their center.
And vertically, use alignment guides
to make the symbols and text
grow harmoniously when text gets resized.
Okay, so let's recap what we've covered.
We have a new version of the app
and new features.
We have hundreds of new symbols.
Some of the existing symbols
got new names,
and we saw how to deal with them.
Remember to use the oldest name
for the minimum OS you're targeting.
We also saw how to use SF Symbols on macOS
with the new NSImage API in AppKit.
We saw how to deal with localized symbols.
And we have new multicolor symbols now
and how to use them
with the different rendering modes.
And lastly, we had a refresher
on how to spec for symbol images
by not specifying frames
but symbol configurations and alignments.
I hope you enjoyed learning about
all the new features of SF Symbols,
and we are looking forward
to seeing what you will do.