Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome
to "Port Your Mac App to Apple Silicon."
My name is Kuba Mracek,
and I will be guiding you,
Mac app developers,
through the journey of transitioning
your apps to Apple Silicon.
We will start with an overview
of what the transition means for you
and your apps.
Then,
we'll discuss building universal Mac apps
and what problems you might hit there.
I will show running, debugging,
and testing on Apple Silicon,
and we will talk about
implications for plug-ins.
Finally, I will mention a few tips
for working with universal apps.
So, let's jump in.
The Mac is transitioning to Apple Silicon.
You're probably wondering what exactly
that means for you and your apps.
Let's start with the basics.
The native CPU architecture
on Apple Silicon Macs is called arm64,
which will sound familiar
if you're developing for iOS.
iOS devices use the same architecture.
Apps can, of course, be built
as native ARM code and run natively,
but existing Intel apps continue to work
on Apple Silicon Mac computers.
The Rosetta translation
will seamlessly run them.
Arm64 is the primary topic for today
because that's the new CPU architecture
that your apps will use.
And not just your GUI code.
All user space programs will now be using
arm64 as their CPU architecture.
In this session,
we will cover how to use Xcode 12
to compile all your code to arm64
to get it to run natively.
So, I have an Apple Silicon Mac here,
and I'm going to launch Xcode
and open an existing project
called Solar System.
Let's focus on this area in the toolbar
that contains the active Run Destination.
It says "My Mac," but if I open it,
it reveals more options.
I can choose to run under Rosetta
or to build a universal app
for both Apple Silicon and Intel.
Let's stick with building natively,
and let's just build and run the app.
And there it is. Without any code changes
or project settings tweaks,
the app builds and runs natively with just
a press of the "run" button in Xcode.
In Activity Monitor,
I can verify the process type.
So, under Solar System Mac
in the Kind column,
it shows as Apple CPU architecture.
That means it does run natively.
Xcode 12 handles
the necessary project settings for you.
You don't have to change build settings
to select CPU architectures.
And, as we've just seen, for apps
that don't have portability issues,
building a native version
is often as simple
as clicking the "run" button in Xcode.
So, I recommend you just go ahead
and try that.
If your app works and runs correctly,
your job is done.
In case you do run into issues,
I will be describing some common pitfalls
later in this session.
We're also publishing
an extensive porting documentation
at developer.apple.com/documentation.
And you can start
with the page called Apple Silicon,
and from there,
you can navigate to other articles
that cover many of the topics
from this session in greater detail.
The documentation is an excellent resource
that will answer
many of your porting questions.
Let's discuss some basic concepts
around Mac apps.
Your apps,
and basically all executable code,
are stored in a file format called Mach-O.
These files can either be targeting
a single CPU architecture,
let's say 64-bit Intel,
or they can be universal.
That means
"Supports multiple CPU architectures."
To examine a file on disk,
you can use the "lipo" command,
and I'll be showing how to do that later.
Starting this year,
Mac apps should be built and distributed
as universal apps,
built for both Apple Silicon
and 64-bit Intel CPU architectures.
If you have any existing Intel-only apps,
or if, for some reason,
you can't start building your app
natively right away,
Apple Silicon computers have Rosetta,
a translation environment
that can seamlessly run these.
In Rosetta,
the entire process is always translated.
You cannot load native code
into a translated process or vice versa.
You also cannot use Rosetta
for kernel extensions,
AVX vector instructions or virtualization.
Xcode fully supports building
and running apps for Rosetta.
Let's look at how that works.
As we've noticed before,
the Run Destination in Xcode
allows you to target Rosetta.
Pressing "run"
will build the code for Intel
and then run it in Rosetta.
In Activity Monitor,
the app shows as Intel CPU,
so it is running in translation.
All aspects of development from Xcode,
including testing, debugging,
and profiling are supported,
and it's all translated on the fly.
So if you perhaps
happen to use the debugger
to look at individual CPU instructions,
you'll notice
that they are Intel instructions.
Don't be surprised by that.
They're all being transparently translated
by Rosetta.
Let's now focus on getting your apps
ported over
to run natively
on Apple Silicon Mac computers.
And the first step here
is building your apps as universal.
Let me start by explaining why I think
building your apps for Apple Silicon
is actually going to a very easy task.
First of all, the endianness
of arm64 is the same as x86.
So if you remember
the PowerPC-to-Intel transition,
you will not have to deal with any
byte order swapping problems this time.
Second, if you have any shared code
with iOS apps,
that code is almost certainly
already fully ported to arm64
because iOS uses the same CPU architecture
as Apple Silicon Mac computers.
And third,
you can use any Mac that you already have
to build apps as universal.
Xcode 12, the SDK,
and the entire toolchain
fully support cross-compilation.
That is, it's able to produce code
for a different architecture
than the one you're using Xcode on.
I'm going to demonstrate
some possible porting issues
on this little utility app
that I've been working on
called NetworkBenchmarking.
I have a copy of this app from last year,
so it's Intel-only,
and we see
that in the Info Dialog in Finder,
it shows as application Intel.
But, as you can see, I can still run it,
and it will run under Rosetta.
The app lets me create
a TCP server and a client.
And I can start a benchmark.
And while it's going,
it's measuring the data throughput.
The app is also showing
a bunch of system information,
like current CPU and memory usage.
All that's pretty much all it does.
Now, let's actually open the app
in Xcode 12...
and let's start bringing it over
to be a native app.
Let me briefly describe
the overall structure of this project.
It has a few targets inside,
like this first one,
which is the actual GUI of the app.
And it's mostly high-level AppKit code,
so I have things like an AppDelegate
and a ViewController, et cetera.
But then I also have
a few more low-level components,
like this TimeTools package
and some networking libraries,
and I even include a plug-in.
Generally, you should expect
that the high-level AppKit code
shouldn't have any portability problems.
But for the more low-level parts,
we might need to make some fixes.
So let's start building.
Step one is to verify that the app still
builds correctly for Intel with Xcode 12.
So let me select My Mac Rosetta
as the Run Destination and hit "build."
In my case, the app will build fine.
Generally,
this shouldn't produce any errors,
but there's one case I want to point out.
Native page size is different between
Intel machines and Apple Silicon systems.
If you use the PAGE_SIZE macro,
it's no longer a compile-time constant,
so you might see a build failure
because of that.
The fix is very easy.
Either use PAGE_MAX_SIZE
for a compile-time upper bound,
or vm_page_size
to read the value at runtime dynamically.
Also note that Rosetta will be
fully matching the Intel environment.
The CPU on Apple Silicon Macs
will support four-kilobyte pages
for translated processes.
Now, on to step two.
Switch to build
for the native architecture,
and let's resolve errors.
In Xcode, I will open
the Run Destination menu again
and select My Mac
and perform another build.
This time, I do get a compile-time error.
Let's look at it.
It looks like that there's something wrong
with this function
called GetDefaultTimerClass,
which is using preprocessor macros,
these #if lines, to switch behavior
between different platforms.
This is a pretty common pattern.
It's called target conditionals.
But it looks like I've made a mistake
when I wrote this code.
For this branch here,
I wanted to target macOS and simulators,
but instead, my condition says x86_64.
That is, Intel CPUs.
Which used to be okay,
but it's no longer correct.
The right way to use
target conditionals here
is to express them in the right terms.
If I want to target macOS and simulators,
I should use TARGET_OS_OSX
or TARGET_OS_SIMULATOR.
This problem is pretty common
even in portable code.
You should use
the semantic target conditionals
based on what
you actually want to express.
Here's a table
with some common target conditionals.
When you want to
conditionally compile code for the Mac,
use TARGET_OS_OSX,
or #if os(macOS) in Swift code.
Don't assume a CPU architecture
implies the platform.
When you want to
conditionally compile code for Intel,
use TARGET_CPU_X86_64,
or #if arch(x86_64) in Swift.
And similarly for the other cases.
Don't assume that a platform
or running in the simulator
uses a specific CPU architecture.
Related to this is any usage
of CPU-specific code and assembly,
either in-line in your Objective-C code
or stand-alone assembly files.
All such code needs
to be properly guarded with #ifs
and the right target conditionals
I just mentioned.
If you only have Intel implementations
for some functions like this,
you will need to provide
a second implementation for Apple Silicon.
However, in a lot of cases,
you can just rely on
OS-provided functionality instead.
Use the Accelerate
and Compression frameworks
for high-performance
optimized implementations
of math functions
and compression algorithms.
Now that the code is fixed,
let's build it again.
This time,
I receive a different build-time issue.
It's not a bug
in any of the source code that I wrote,
because the error message
doesn't actually point to any source file.
And if I click it,
it only takes me to the Build Log.
This time,
it's the linker that's emitting the error.
That leads us to step three:
resolving link-time issues.
The problem here
is that my app fails to link.
Let me switch to Errors Only
so we can focus
on what the linker is trying to tell me.
"Undefined symbols
for architecture arm64."
And I see the symbol name,
but it doesn't look familiar to me.
This is not a symbol or class name
from my code.
The important part of the error message
is actually the yellow warning
right above it.
Let's look at it.
The linker says, "ignoring file
when building for macOS-arm64
but attempting to link
with file built for macOS-x86_64."
What this error means is that
I'm depending on a binary framework
that's not universal.
This output also provides details.
It mentions the offending framework name,
and it prints the symbol name,
in this case
it's a Objective-C class name,
and also the referencing object file.
In my app, it's the AppDelegate file
that uses this class.
This is useful to know,
because you might want to try
to remove the dependency to make progress.
So, to do in my app, I would go edit
the AppDelegate source code.
But again, in short,
the problem here is that I have
a pre-compiled binary framework
in my project.
Having pre-compiled binaries
in your project will require some work.
All static and dynamic libraries
that you depend on
will need to first be built universal
before you can actually build your app.
You'll need to contact vendors
of those binaries
and ask them to provide
universal builds of them
that contain both the Intel code
and Apple Silicon code.
Then you can replace your old binaries
with the universal ones,
and the linker will be actually able
to link your app.
To make incremental progress,
you can consider temporarily removing
that binary dependency,
but don't forgot to put it back once you
have a universal build of that library.
What I also recommend doing right away
is to scan your source code
and do a search for anything
that's not being built from source code
but is pre-compiled by someone else.
Typically, that's files and bundles
with extensions of .a, .dylib,
.framework, and .xcframework.
You can use the "lipo -info" command
to inspect any binary and see
whether it's already universal or not.
So let's do that on our demo project.
I will open the project's directory
in Finder...
and I will also open Terminal.
Then I will drag Sparkle.framework
into Terminal to get its full file path
and use the lipo -info command
on the binary inside the framework.
And once I run this command, lipo will say
that it is really an Intel-only binary.
So what I need to do
is update the version of this framework
with a new one that's universal.
Here, you would typically reach out
to the vendor and ask for a new version
or go to the vendor's Web site
and download a universal binary
if it's published already.
But I have a new universal version
of this framework already.
My teammate was actually able
to provide it for me.
Because the framework is open-source,
and building it universal was literally
just a matter of rebuilding with Xcode 12,
we did not hit
any portability issues at all.
Let me replace the old version
with the new one...
and let's inspect this new version
of the framework.
Indeed, it is universal now.
Lipo says it's now a fat file
that contains both the x86_64 code
as well as arm64 code.
And if I build my app in Xcode
one more time...
this time, it will build successfully.
Step four: There is no step four.
I now have a native build of my app.
In this example project,
we've seen a few typical problems
when building universal apps.
Please see the documentation
on the Apple Silicon page
on developer.apple.com,
which covers many of the porting problems
that we've run into.
If you prefer building on command line
with xcodebuild,
it's important to select
the right Destination for building.
Use the -showdestinations option
to get a list
of available Run Destinations.
And then you can use
the -destination flag to select one.
Here's two examples
how to target either arm64 or x86_64.
Let me summarize the steps we went through
to build our app as a native app.
First, we verified that the app
still builds correctly for Intel CPUs.
Then, we switched to build natively,
and we fixed code issues.
This is the case where the code itself
was not correctly portable.
And third, we fixed link-time issues,
which are typically caused
by having binary dependencies.
And that's it.
As a reminder,
building universal apps works on any Mac.
You can use your Intel Mac computer
for that too.
Now that we have our app building,
let's move on
and talk about running and debugging
your native build of your app.
I know what you're thinking:
The app builds, so let's ship it.
Right? Well, no.
Your native app
still definitely needs runtime testing.
Don't assume that if the app builds,
that it's going to work flawlessly.
For this part,
you will need an Apple Silicon Mac.
Things like debugging, running unit tests,
profiling, using sanitizers
all need to run native code,
and that can only happen on Apple Silicon.
Please plan to do full runtime testing,
validation, and profiling
of both CPU architectures
before you ship your app.
Let's do some runtime testing
on our demo project.
Now that the app builds,
I can finally run it natively.
It seems to launch fine. The UI shows up,
and the system information table
seems to be accurate.
Let's try to start
the client-server data transfer.
Notice that there's some problem
with the transfer statistics
and the progress bar.
It seems to refresh
with some wrong frequency.
It's supposed to update
every 100 milliseconds,
but instead, the progress bar
just makes these weird large jumps.
So, let's look into this problem.
Based on the benchmark values, I think
the benchmark is actually running fine.
It's just the UI
that's not refreshing fast enough.
So let me set a break point
into my ViewController
into a method called
updateClientProgressUI,
and let's run the benchmark again.
We will eventually hit this break point,
but notice that it takes a while,
more than a couple seconds.
So I think there's something wrong
with the timer that's calling this method.
Let's look a few Stack frames below,
where I have an implementation
of this custom timer.
It seems to be measuring
a MonotonicTimestamp
using an API called mach_absolute_time.
So I think
that's the source of the problem.
Whoever wrote this code
assumed that mach_absolute_time
is always returning values in nanoseconds.
That's why the code right below it
is dividing by 1,000 three times
to convert it into seconds.
However, that's not correct.
I can Option-click the API...
to peek into the documentation for it,
and it says that it returns values
in tick units.
So assuming these tick units
are one nanosecond is incorrect.
The timebase for this API is different
on different CPU architectures.
Probably the best solution here
would be to avoid writing custom timers
using low-level APIs.
Foundation and GCD have implementations
of timers that often work better.
But if we really need to use time stamps
to measure time,
we can either query the timebase
dynamically
or switch to another API.
There's a variant of the clock_gettime API
that always returns the time stamp
in nanoseconds.
So let's use that in our demo.
The documentation pop-up
conveniently mentions this other API,
so I can copy it right from here.
Let's run the app one more time,
and let me disable the break point
I've put in earlier.
This time, if I run the benchmark,
the progress bar will update fluently.
This problem is actually quite common,
and the typical effect of this bug
is that something is running
roughly 40 times slower,
or an event is occurring
40 times less often than it should.
If you observe something like this,
search your codebase
for mach_absolute_time.
The best way to test software is,
of course, with automation.
In this project, I have most of the code
covered with unit tests.
So let's run them.
Luckily, all my unit tests are passing,
but notice that the entire test suite
only ran once.
In this case, in the Run Destination menu,
I have the native mode selected,
so all my tests and the code under test
were run in native mode.
If I want to run the tests
as Intel code under Rosetta,
I have to switch the Run Destination
and re-run my tests.
In my project, they all appear to pass
for both architectures,
but if you see a test failing
only under one of the two destinations,
that again indicates
some non-portable code.
Similarly to building on the command line,
when testing with xcodebuild,
think about the destination
that your tests are using.
If you want to run your tests as "native,"
specify "arch=arm64"
inside the destination flag.
This also is the default,
so if you don't use any destination,
your tests will run as native code.
To run your tests as Intel code
under Rosetta, use "arch=x86_64."
You might also want to set up
your CI systems
to run tests in both these modes
to catch any non-portable code
causing test failures.
Let's look at one particular test I have,
because it's a performance benchmark.
I'll select the "native" destination again
and run the test...
which is just measuring how long it takes
to transfer ten megabytes of data
from a local server.
The result is that it takes
21 milliseconds.
If I switch to Rosetta
and run the test again,
we'll get a different result.
This time it takes 29 milliseconds,
which is slower than native,
but the translated code
still performs very well,
and the result is very close
to native execution.
When profiling and benchmarking
on Apple Silicon Mac computers,
native code
generally has the best performance,
and you should aim at optimizing
native execution.
If you see a performance degradation
in native mode,
watch out for any Intel-specific
code optimizations that you might have:
for example,
optimized assembly using SSE or AVX.
To achieve best performance,
you might need to provide
a matching implementation
for Apple Silicon
using the ARM instruction set.
But in general, you should try using
Apple-provided APIs whenever possible,
like Accelerate.framework,
because those will provide
high-performance implementations
for all supported CPUs.
Apple Silicon Macs use
asymmetric CPU cores,
and that might have an effect
on your high-performance code.
There's two types of CPU cores:
high-performance, also called P Cores,
and energy-efficient, called E Cores.
All of them can be active at the same time
for maximum performance
on parallel workloads.
In Instruments,
this distinction is visible
in the CPUs view of the timeline.
The individual CPU cores in the list
have labels telling you
which ones are Efficient
and which ones are Performance cores.
Don't be surprised
if you see a graph like this,
where almost all the work is scheduled
only on the P Cores
or only on the E Cores.
The system is dynamically choosing
the best way to perform work
to make the right performance
and battery life trade-off.
One important pattern to avoid
on asymmetric CPU systems
is using spinlocks and busy-waiting code.
In this example,
the first function is using a spinlock
and the second example is busy-waiting.
That means actively spending CPU time
to check in a loop
whether a new job is available in a queue.
This is something that's generally wrong
to do on any computer system.
A much better alternative
for the first function
is to use some blocking type of lock,
for example, os_unfair_lock.
And instead of checking a condition
in a spinning loop,
use condition variables, which will block
until the condition is met.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
busy-waiting can have the effect
of pointlessly occupying the P Cores,
causing an overall delay
in completion of the entire work.
You should prefer
synchronization primitives that block
when they can't make progress.
NSLock, os_unfair_lock, pthread mutexes,
are all examples of blocking locks.
NSCondition
and pthread condition variables
provide a way to wait
until a specific condition occurs.
In general, use GCD when possible
and avoid splitting your work
based on number of available CPUs,
and instead prefer splitting tasks
into smaller-size units.
For details about GCD,
please watch a video from WWDC 2017.
And if you're using threading
for audio processing,
the "Meet Audio Workgroups" session
from this year
will help you fine-tune
your audio apps and plug-ins.
So when you're debugging,
testing and profiling your app,
remember that you can build on any Mac,
but running native arm64 code
needs an Apple Silicon Mac.
When running your tests, try to run them
under both native and translated modes
to discover non-portable code
in your tests.
And watch out for any
Intel-specific code optimizations
and any code that is using busy-waiting
instead of blocking.
The next topic I'd like to talk about
is plug-ins,
because these need some special
considerations on Apple Silicon computers.
Plug-ins are a way to dynamically load
and execute code.
Using plug-ins that just implement
standard system extension points
via NSExtension
is going to just work.
Both native and translated plug-ins
are supported.
However, if your app is a plug-in host,
and if it's using
a custom plug-in loading mechanism,
you'll need to consider how plug-ins work
on Apple Silicon Macs.
Your app's process at runtime
will contain the code that you wrote
and also code from system frameworks.
If your app supports plug-ins,
it will typically discover them at runtime
and then load them when needed.
That's called an in-process plug-in model,
and typically the app uses a call
to dlopen or Bundle.load for this.
Alternatively, the plug-ins can be spawned
as new processes,
and we call those out-of-process plug-ins.
The app and the plug-in process
then use some inter-process
communication mechanism like XPC.
Loading another plug-in
typically spawns another process.
While out-of-process plug-ins generally
provide better security and stability,
in-process plug-ins are still very common.
If your app is using in-process plug-ins,
you need to consider that
on macOS on Apple Silicon,
all code in one process must always have
the same CPU architecture.
Let's look at typical use cases
for plug-ins.
As I've mentioned, there's out-of-process
and in-process plug-ins.
What's also important
is whether the plug-in is first-party,
which means you are building it
from source code
and ship it inside your app...
or whether it's a third-party plug-in
that some other software vendor
distributes in pre-compiled binary form.
If your plug-ins are first-party,
and you can rebuild them,
make sure to build them as universal
plug-ins, and everything will work.
For third-party plug-ins
using the out-of-process plug-in model,
you can make some small changes
in your loading code
to support both CPU architectures.
If you make sure to load
the plug-in executable
as the right CPU architecture,
your app will be able to load
both native and translated plug-ins.
In-process third-party plug-ins
have some restrictions.
Native apps can only load native plug-ins,
and Rosetta-translated apps
can only load Intel-based plug-ins.
If your plug-in vendor hasn't updated
the plug-in to be universal,
it might affect your users.
Let's look at what happens
if we have a plug-in CPU mismatch.
In my NetworkBenchmarking app,
I am using a plug-in
to implement TLS support,
and it gets loaded
the first time I switch to the TLS mode,
so let me do that.
The plug-in loading fails,
so let's inspect the console.
The dynamic linker explains what happened.
We tried to use dlopen
to load a plug-in with this name,
and the file was found on disk,
but it had the wrong CPU architecture.
Let's verify this.
I'll copy the full path of this file...
and open Terminal,
and I will paste the path into Terminal
and the lipo -info again.
And indeed, this binary is Intel-only.
If this was
a third-party pre-compiled plug-in,
the right solution would be
to contact that third party
and urge them to publish a universal build
of the plug-in as soon as possible.
But let's go back into Xcode,
because in this case,
I do have the source code of this plug-in,
and I should be able to rebuild it
as universal.
Let's go into my project
and open the TLS plug-in target
and inspect its build settings.
It looks like I have
some unusual configuration here.
I'm forcing architectures
to always be x86_64.
This is probably some leftover
from when I wanted to drop 32-bit support.
But hard-coding x86_64 is incorrect now.
We should instead be using
standard architectures everywhere.
But an even better option is to avoid
setting architectures altogether.
So I will just select the build setting
and hit the "delete" key.
This way, Xcode will use
the correct default settings.
Let's build and run the app again...
and this time,
if I switch to the TLS mode,
the plug-in will get loaded correctly now.
A typical pattern to load a plug-in
is to use dlopen with a file path.
It's very important to always check
the return value from dlopen,
and if it's null, the full error message
explaining what's wrong
is provided by calling dlerror.
When running this code with
a mismatching plug-in CPU architecture,
you'll get an error explaining that
the file on disk has a wrong architecture.
That indicates that the plug-in
is not universal.
I'd like to point out
that the out-of-process plug-in model
doesn't have this restriction.
If you're using in-process plug-ins,
I encourage you
to explore XPC as a solution.
You can have one process per plug-in,
but also one process per CPU architecture.
In this case, you'll only ever use
up to two extra processes.
Out-of-process plug-ins provide better
stability and security for your app,
and for details about XPC,
I recommend watching
a WWDC session from 2013
called "Efficient Design with XPC."
If your users are stuck
with an Intel-only plug-in,
they can still force the app
to run in Rosetta,
which will allow loading those plug-ins.
For universal apps,
the Info dialog in Finder
has a checkbox
called "Open using Rosetta" to do that.
This checkbox can disallowed
with an Info.plist key.
Details are explained
in the Apple Silicon documentation,
so please refer to it
if you'd like to know more.
Let me finally share a few tips
when working on apps
that run on both Intel-based Macs
and Apple Silicon Macs.
Once your app is building, running,
and it's tested and verified
to work correctly on each architecture,
you're going to start
distributing your app,
either on the App Store,
or perhaps by a download link
on your Web site,
in which case you'll need your entire
software package to be notarized.
Please watch a WWDC session from 2019
called "All About Notarization"
for details.
In Xcode, your distribution process
starts with an Archive build,
which now by default
produces universal apps.
In Xcode, the Archive action
is available in the Product menu.
If your primary development work flow
is to use only one type of Mac computer,
doing an Archive build
might actually be the first time
that your code builds universally.
So if your debug iterations build fine
but your Archive build fails,
that indicates
you have some portability issues
that we've covered
earlier in this session.
Once your Archive build succeeds,
you can find your package for distribution
in the Organizer window of Xcode.
In Xcode 12,
it now shows which CPU architectures
are included in your Archive builds.
The Organizer also provides access
to crash statistics
and individual crash logs
from the users of your app.
For details about crash logs and how to
investigate root causes of crashes,
please watch a video from WWDC 2018
called "Understanding Crashes
and Crash Logs."
With universal apps,
you should now watch out
that you'll be receiving
three different kinds of crash logs:
x86 crash logs from Intel Macs,
native arm64 crash logs
for Apple Silicon Macs,
but also translated x86 crash logs
when running under Rosetta
on Apple Silicon Macs.
If you select a particular crash log
in the Organizer,
the Details section now shows
what CPU architecture
the crash originated on
and whether the process
was running translated or not.
If your app relies on a kernel extension,
or if you provide drivers for hardware
using DriverKit,
there's some special considerations
that you should understand
when porting these types of software.
In particular,
more types of kernel extensions
are now deprecated or disallowed
on Apple Silicon Macs,
and you'll have to use DriverKit
for those instead.
Please refer to the macOS
porting documentation for details.
One more thing to watch out for
is multithreading bugs.
Intel CPUs and Apple Silicon implement
a different memory ordering model.
For correct multithreaded code,
this doesn't matter.
It will always run correctly.
But bugs like race conditions
and data races
might have slightly differently behavior
on each of these architectures.
Specifically, a data race on Intel CPUs
might have worked fine
and appeared to be benign,
but the same bug could be causing crashes
on Apple Silicon instead.
Note that running under Rosetta
fully supports the Intel memory ordering,
so you will not see
a difference in behavior there.
Whether you do see crashes
in multithreaded code or not,
I highly recommend using Thread Sanitizer
as a tool
to detect and prevent data races.
We have presented this tool
in a WWDC session in 2016
called "Thread Sanitizer
and Static Analysis."
You can enable Thread Sanitizer
in the scheme editor of your project.
In the Diagnostics tab, you can find
a checkbox called Thread Sanitizer.
But remember, this is a runtime tool.
You have to run your app
and exercise code at runtime to find bugs.
So this concludes the tips that I have
for working with universal apps.
Let me now wrap up the session
and summarize
what we have talked about today.
Mac apps should from now on
be built as universal apps,
and you can start bringing them
to Apple Silicon today.
Scan your source code
for non-universal binaries.
You will need to get them updated
as universal to run your app natively.
Use Xcode 12 to build your app universal.
Identify and fix any portability issues
you discover on the way.
And don't forget to run and test
the native build of your apps.
Watch out for any of the platform
differences we have discussed today.
Finally, I would like to remind you that
developer.apple.com/documentation
contains many more details.
The article called "Apple Silicon"
provides guidance and answers
to questions you might have
about porting your app.
Thank you for watching.