Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, my name is Stacey Abrams,
and I'm an engineer
on the Wallet and Apple Pay team.
I'm excited to share
what we've been working on this year,
so let's get started.
First,
we'll cover incoming API enhancements.
Then we will talk about how Apple Pay
and App Clips work together.
Finally,
we will cover platform enhancements
that will improve the experience
of Apple Pay.
So, let's get into the API enhancements.
When we first launched Apple Pay,
we started out with payment
in its traditional form:
credit and debit cards.
But we've come a long way since then,
and now we have so much more
than just credit cards.
You can use Apple Pay
to get onto public transit
in the United States, Japan and China,
just to name a few.
You can add your student ID badge
to Wallet
and use your iPhone or Apple Watch
to get into dining halls
and academic buildings.
Historically,
the class used in conjunction
with these features on-device
has been PKPaymentPass,
but what these scenarios really have
in common from a device standpoint
is that they all require the backing
of the Secure Element.
The payment in PKPaymentPass was
starting to feel a little too specific,
given our continuously expanding
feature set.
Because of that, today we are introducing
PKSecureElementPass
in order to accurately unify
the uses of this class.
PKSecureElementPass
has all the same properties
to encourage new and existing developers
to adopt this class moving forward.
PKPaymentPass will be deprecated
in the future.
One class that's not shedding
its payment character
is our very own PKPaymentButton.
This is our main entry point for payment,
and that isn't changing.
What is changing
is that we have a comprehensive slate
of new button types coming this year.
Our users are doing so much more
than outright purchasing these days.
People are using Apple Pay to rent bikes.
They are adding money
to their transit cards.
We wanted to enable
anyone adding support for Apple Pay
to have the purchasing granularity
they desire in the button that they add.
So now you can rent with Apple Pay,
tip with Apple Pay and more,
all in the button you surface
to your users.
This is how you would currently declare
a PKPaymentButton with a white outline
on the Web and natively on iOS.
While type controls
the content of the button,
the style controls its appearance.
We have Light and Dark modes
for PKPaymentButton.
But wouldn't it be great
if it automatically switched
based on if your app is in Light
or Dark Mode?
Well, now it can.
We're introducing a new style
that handles this:
PKPaymentButtonStyle: .automatic.
This button's style
will automatically switch
based on the system theme.
If you're an iOS or macOS developer,
you can use this automatic button style.
If you have more specific requirements
or want to respond
to backgrounds differently,
then you can still use the regular
Light or Dark styles accordingly.
We hope this automatic style makes it
easier to enable Dark Mode in your apps.
We think you're going to love
all these new button options,
and they'll go far in helping you to
integrate Apple Pay into your app clips,
a feature that we're really excited about.
First, a small review
on what app clips are.
App clips are a way to build quick
transactional experiences from the Web
while leveraging native iOS technologies.
Without needing
to fully download your app,
users can complete small, focused tasks.
And with App Clips,
users gain access
to a seamless checkout experience
with Apple Pay natively.
So, you could tap and pay to park.
You could tap and pay
to rent a scooter or rent a bike.
You could tap and pay for food
at a restaurant or café.
And so much more.
You could tap and pay to rent a car,
you could tap and pay in-store
while having the item delivered home,
or you could tap and pay
to fill your car with gas.
The potential is really tremendous
for easily and quickly unlocking services
with App Clips and Apple Pay.
So, let's cover the best practices
when adding Apple Pay to your app clips.
We recommend
that you use Apple Pay when possible
because it's designed to be fast,
easy, and secure.
Making it your default payment option
will save your users time.
We also suggest allowing guest checkout
because it reduces friction
by postponing account creation
until after the purchase is complete.
Use "Sign in with Apple"
to make this process as easy as possible.
And app clips work best
when they are simple and focused.
Keeping this in mind
when designing your app clip
helps maximize conversion.
And finally,
keeping your app clip lightweight
lets users purchase faster.
By loading assets
such as maps and routes on-demand,
rather than with the initial download,
you reduce overhead
and make your app clip experience
more instantaneous.
App Clips is going to bring
even more people
into the Apple Pay ecosystem.
It's fitting to talk about
what we are doing to collectively enhance
the Apple Pay experience
across all of our platforms.
So, let's begin with Mac.
Today, Apple Pay on the Mac
is primarily experienced through Safari.
And we have seen developers adding support
for Apple Pay on the Web everywhere
by leveraging WebKit,
which simplifies the payment process
for e-commerce websites.
Speaking of WebKit,
I wanted to discuss a couple features
we introduced last year:
custom corner radius
and redacted billing address support.
You can now modify PKPaymentButton's
corner radius on the Web.
So, while the button comes
with rounded corners by default,
you can increase the rounding further
to achieve a pill shape
or decrease it to have a square shape.
And when the user presses that button,
you can present our payment sheet.
In order to compute line items like taxes,
merchants need simple locale information.
Historically, the shipping address
would be used for this,
but shipping address isn't applicable
to all purchases,
as shown in this screen for a purchase
involving a digital certificate.
Now, merchants on the web can receive
a redacted version of billing address
in order to compute variable line items.
This feature is ideal for purchases
involving digital goods and services.
It results in a lower risk of charge-backs
for merchants and higher conversion rates
because users get a complete price picture
before authenticating
to approve the transaction.
But what about experiences
outside of Safari on Mac?
We haven't provided a truly native option
for our Mac users.
However, today that changes,
with Apple Pay coming to Catalyst
and native Mac apps.
With Catalyst, you can have
your amazing iPad apps come to the Mac
with the full fidelity
of the Apple Pay experience.
We're going further than Catalyst too
in adding native support,
so if you had a photo book app
or any other app
that takes payments on Mac,
it can now accept Apple Pay.
This will bring
our great payment experiences
to more Mac apps across the board.
This also means
that PKPaymentButton is coming to Mac,
including the new types
and new automatic style
that I just announced.
So, how do you complete a payment on Mac?
It's very similar
to how you do it on the Web.
To quickly recap,
you need to establish a merchant session,
and you do so
by WebKit telling you which URL to hit.
Then you validate that URL
against a published list
of Apple hostnames
and send a post request to it.
Apple Pay server returns the session
for the client to consume.
If you'd like to get more information
about this,
you can find it in our "Apple Pay
on the Web" talk from 2016.
A native app might not need
to use WebKit though,
so we made things really easy here.
You hit this one static URL,
and you don't have to worry
about where it's coming from anymore.
In fact, this works for Web payments too,
so you should stop using the old way
and transition to this new way.
In a future release,
the old way will be removed completely.
Now, a couple more notes
about implementing Apple Pay on Mac.
First, when using
the PKPaymentAuthorizationController,
it needs to know the window
upon which to present the payment sheet.
Your delegate must implement
the presentationWindow method
and return
the UIWindow requesting the payment.
Typically, you'll return
yourViewController.view.window.
Of note, if you're using
the PKPaymentAuthorizationViewController,
the hosting window is determined by
the presentation of that view controller.
And as I just mentioned,
Catalyst uses the same security model
as a Web page implementing support
for Apple Pay.
Your delegate should implement
the didRequestMerchantSessionUpdate method
to request a merchant session
from your server
which securely obtains it from Apple.
The result of that request
is then passed back
through the provided handler.
On Catalyst, this takes the place
of supplying your merchant IDs
within your entitlements.
Many developers have
their native apps load Web pages
as a method of accepting Apple Pay.
They do this
by implementing support for WebKit.
With the introduction of Tiered WebKit,
I wanted to touch on its implications
for Apple Pay.
To further protect user privacy,
WKWebViews will now work
more like the SafariViewController.
Apps displaying WKWebViews will
be restricted in the APIs they can invoke
outside of a set of app-defined domains.
This means limitations
to JavaScript injections.
Now, nothing really changes for Apple Pay
from an implementation standpoint.
It was previously the case
that you could not perform
Apple Pay transactions
if script was injected
into a WKWebView instance on iOS.
What this does mean for Apple Pay
is that there will now be more WKWebViews
blocked from injecting script.
This means more loaded pages on iOS
will be allowed to perform
Apple Pay transactions now.
With Apple Pay making its debut
on Catalyst and native Mac apps,
we wanted to discuss what we're doing
to make the contact information
and checkout experience more seamless
on iOS, macOS, and the Web.
People have been using Apple Pay
for a while.
In fact, for six years,
which is incredible.
This is meant that, over time,
users have accumulated
a lot of Apple Pay contact information
on their devices.
And everyone knows what this feels like.
Some users would see this,
and that was for a few reasons.
To this point,
we haven't formatted our contact data.
You could insert any character you want,
including emojis.
While fun, these pose problems
for address-validation systems
that merchants employ.
And even if the merchant cleaned up
the address separately,
future transactions with Apple Pay
wouldn't reap the benefits
of that corrected information.
So, we set a goal for ourselves:
establish consistency
and make it easier on users and merchants.
While the ultimate responsibility
of address validation
for billing and shipping
lies with the merchant,
we want to ensure that the data
that the merchant gets is more consistent.
This way, when contact data comes
from Apple Pay, it will be standardized,
so you'll see less variation
and more predictability in the experience.
So, how are we achieving this?
We will now provide basic formatting
for contact data through the payment sheet
beginning with the latest iOS and macOS.
Merchants can now begin
to expect better formatted data.
Street and city fields
will only contain alphanumeric characters,
punctuation and whitespace.
The state field
will be a two-letter state code.
In the US, for example, the ZIP code will
be a five- or nine-digit numeric code.
If applicable, the ISO country code will
be an uppercase two-letter country code.
We're also improving the user experience
by raising formatting errors
in the UI earlier in the payment flow
so that the user can address them
before they authenticate
with Touch ID or Face ID.
For example, in this screen,
the incomplete ZIP code is highlighted.
And here we surface
that the phone number is not valid
so the user knows
to fix that specifically.
Use our error APIs
to help your users understand
what information needs correcting.
By doing so, they combine with the power
of these new contact formatting rules
to elevate the accuracy
of stored data on-device.
We will initially be supporting
addresses from Australia, Canada,
United Kingdom and the United States
while rolling out support
to other countries soon.
Address formatting differences
across countries, such as postal code,
will be accounted for
on a per-region basis.
These enhancements
to our contact data formatting
will make it simpler for users
to use Apple Pay at checkout.
But before you can check out,
you need to have a card in Apple Pay
to begin with.
We wanted to make it easier
for users to know they can use Apple Pay.
There are few ways new
and existing users can add cards today.
You can scan a card,
which uses our stellar
camera-recognition technology,
but you do need to be in possession
of your physical card to do this.
You can add the card
from within an issuer app,
which works well, but you need
to intentionally already be there
and have the goal of adding that card.
We wanted to make it easier for our users
to know they can add a card to Apple Pay
by improving discoverability
from within Wallet.
Today, we are introducing support for
Issuer Extensions to facilitate that goal.
For an issuer, this gives them the ability
to have that in-app experience
of adding a card, but inside of Wallet.
The issuer app needs to be installed,
and the user needs
to have signed into the app at least once
so Wallet knows there are cards
to surface.
Wallet can prompt for re-authentication
when adding if the app requires it.
This feature is extension-based:
apps will need a non-UI extension.
It will report the status
of the extension,
the passes it has available,
and then perform the card data lookup,
just like when adding cards to Apple Pay
from within an app.
It must subclass
PKIssuerProvisioningExtensionHandler,
and your extension will need
an entitlement.
If the non-UI extension reports
in its status
that authentication is required,
then a UI extension is also needed
to handle that re-authentication.
Your extension view controller
should conform
to PKIssuerProvisioningExtension-
AuthorizationProviding.
This UI extension also requires
a separate entitlement.
If you are interested in supporting
issuer extensions, please reach out to us.
We will help you determine
if issuer extensions make sense
for your app and get your app entitled.
We've covered a lot of changes today,
and I wanted to quickly review them.
I introduced a new style
and new button types for PKPaymentButton.
We talked about App Clips
and how you can leverage Apple Pay
even when your app isn't downloaded.
We are now providing full Mac support:
native and Catalyst.
Mac support
and App Clips will benefit greatly
from our new standardized
contact information formatting by region.
The experience of using Apple Pay
will be more consistent
as more users
are onboarded onto the platform.
And finally,
we introduced extensions for card issuers.
We're really excited for you
to leverage these changes in your apps.
We encourage you to add support
for App Clips and Apple Pay
to build even better commerce experiences.
Use our new buttons while you're at it.
Use the new static URL
for your Apple Pay sessions
natively and on the Web.
Take a look at our code sample
for supporting Apple Pay on Mac
found in our resources.
And finally, adopt our error APIs for
an all-around better checkout experience.
Thanks for attending today,
and I hope you've had a great WWDC.