Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to "Explore Packages and Projects
with Xcode Playgrounds."
I'm Chris Miles, an engineering manager
on the Xcode team.
Developers love using Xcode Playgrounds
to quickly try out new ideas and to learn
and explore APIs and frameworks.
Today, I'm excited to tell you about
enhancements we've made to Xcode 12
to make Playgrounds work seamlessly
with Swift packages and frameworks
in your projects.
In Xcode 12,
Playgrounds is fully integrated
with Xcode's modern build system.
That integration brings with it
a lot of improvements
to how Playgrounds works with packages,
projects and resources.
First, I'll show you how Playgrounds
now works well in Swift packages
and makes a great option for package
documentation containing runnable code.
Then I'm going to demonstrate improvements
for Playgrounds importing project targets,
like frameworks and package dependencies.
In the final part of the presentation,
I'm going to demonstrate working with
resources that need build support,
like ML models and asset catalogs,
in a playground.
So, let's get started
by looking at how Xcode Playgrounds
works with Swift packages.
Here I have a Swift package checked out
called NutritionFacts.
I'm gonna open it in Xcode
by double-clicking "Package.swift."
NutritionFacts provides accurate
nutritional information
for many common types of food.
It's a really handy package to use
in recipe and food apps.
What's great about NutritionFacts
is the authors have included
rich documentation
explaining how to use the API,
and, even better, the documentation
was written as a playground.
Playgrounds are great for documentation,
and they now work seamlessly
with packages in Xcode 12.
So, let's take a look.
In the navigator,
I'm gonna open the Playgrounds folder
and select the NutritionFacts playground.
Here, we see a description of the package
followed by detailed documentation
about how to use the API,
along with example code snippets.
And being a playground,
we can run that code.
Let's do that now by hitting "execute"
in the toolbar.
The playground will execute,
and on the right, we see a live view.
That is a view provided by the package.
It shows NutritionFacts
in a familiar format.
In the editor, we see an example
of looking up an item by identifier
and fetching nutritional information
about it.
The playground helps us
understand the code
by showing the result of each statement
in the results bar on the right.
As you can see, Playgrounds in Xcode 12
work seamlessly with packages.
This was made possible
because of Playgrounds' integration
with the modern build system,
which knows how to build packages
and make them available
for importing into playground code.
I recommend making use of a playground
the next time you need
to write documentation
or a tutorial for your Swift package.
Don't forget to take advantage of the fact
that users can run the example code
and see live results in the playground.
Next, I'd like to show you how Xcode 12
makes it easier for Playgrounds
to use framework and package dependencies
from a project.
I'm gonna use a project called Fruta,
and let's open it in Xcode
and run the project in the simulator.
Fruta is an iOS and Mac app
for browsing and ordering smoothies.
You can even purchase smoothie recipes
with Apple Pay
so you can make
your own smoothies at home.
Let's take a look at the app
in the simulator.
We see a list of some
of the smoothies available,
and if we select one, we can see an option
to buy it with Apple Pay,
and scrolling up, we see some of
the ingredients that are in the smoothie.
Let's select one to see a detailed image,
and tap the "I" button to see
nutritional facts about that ingredient.
Now, you may recognize this as the view
provided by the NutritionFacts package.
This project has a dependency
on that package,
as you can see in the left
in the navigator.
Even as a project dependency,
any playgrounds in that package
will still be available.
Let's take a look by opening the package
and opening the NutritionFacts playground
that we opened earlier.
Here, we see the same content,
and, like before, we can execute
the playground to see the results.
So, playgrounds in packages are available
whether you open the package directly,
like we did at the start,
or whether it's part of your project
as a package dependency, like it is here.
Just remember that, like all files
in a package dependency,
the playground will be read-only.
This project also contains a framework
called UtilityViews.
Let's take a look at the project editor
where we can see the UtilityView's
framework target.
It is now easier than before to use
your frameworks in Playgrounds,
as long as they are in the same workspace.
Let me show you an example.
In the navigator,
I'm gonna open the Playgrounds folder,
and we see a playground
called SmoothieLab.
Let's open SmoothieLab.
Notice some build activity at the top.
This was due to a new playground option
in Xcode 12 called Build Active Scheme.
Let me show you by opening the inspector,
and here we see in the playground settings
the new option
at the bottom of the settings.
When "Build Active Scheme" is enabled,
it tells Xcode
to automatically build all targets
in the currently selected scheme
and make any modules importable
to the playground.
So, that's why when
we opened the playground,
Xcode built all of the targets
for the currently selected scheme,
and the playground could import
the UtilityViews framework
and the NutritionFacts package.
SmoothieLab is a utility playground
that we use to design new smoothies.
We can select some raw ingredients,
combine them in various quantities
and then inspect their nutritional values.
We can even chart a calorie breakdown
using a chart view
from the UtilityViews framework.
Let's run the playground to see
the calorie breakdown for this smoothie.
In the live view, we see a chart
of the calorie breakdown.
Now, we usually like to keep
the fat content to be less than about 25%,
so let's tap the chart
to take a look at the percentages.
It's about 33% in this case,
so perhaps we could lower
the amount of peanut butter,
but I'll work on that later.
As you can see,
this playground is a handy tool
for helping us to combine ingredients
to design well-balanced smoothies,
at least from a nutritional perspective.
We haven't designed an algorithm
for calculating how good
a smoothie might taste,
but I'm fine with that as tasting is
my favorite part of smoothie design.
Playgrounds can now work seamlessly
with project targets,
such as frameworks and packages.
Xcode will take care of
building those targets
so that they can be imported
into your playground code.
Just make sure to enable
"Build Active Scheme."
The good news is that this option is
enabled by default for new playgrounds.
Also make sure that the module you want to
import is either part of the active scheme
or a dependency on another target
built by that scheme.
Another great enhancement in Xcode 12
is the availability of full build logs
for playgrounds.
Let's take a look at the build log
for SmoothieLab.
We'll switch to the report navigator,
and at the top, we see the build log
for the SmoothieLab playground.
So, let's select it
to open the build logs.
In the build logs,
we see all of the build details
for the targets that were built
as part of the active scheme,
as well as the module that
was built to support the playground,
containing compiled sources and resources
from within the playground.
Build logs are invaluable
for diagnosing build issues,
and we're happy that they're
available for playgrounds.
Another benefit
of Playgrounds' integration
with Xcode's modern build system,
is that all resource types
supported by the build system
are now supported in Playgrounds.
Let me show you an example
of using some resources in a playground
that require build system support.
Returning to the Fruta project,
I'd like to add a feature to Fruta
where the user can point their
iPhone's camera at their favorite fruit,
and Fruta would magically
suggest smoothies
that match the fruit that it could see.
To do this I'd like
to use machine learning
to perform object detection
and image classification.
There are a number
of classifiers available,
so I'd like to try one of them
with a few sample images
to see if it would be suitable
for the task,
and I'm going to do that using
a playground in Xcode.
First, let's get some sample fruit images
to test with,
and I think we happen to have some
already available in the Fruta project.
Let's switch back to the simulator
and navigate back,
and remember we saw the image
of some oranges before?
And if we dismiss that,
we see images of the other ingredients.
So, let's find these in the project.
I'm gonna hide the simulator,
as we don't need that anymore,
expand the Shared folder,
and let's take a look
in the asset catalog.
We see an app icon, some color sets,
and in the Ingredients folder,
we see all the images
representing the ingredients
that we put in our smoothies.
I think this will be a good sample set
for testing our machine-learning model.
So, let's make a copy of this by
Option-dragging this out to the desktop.
And now we don't need the project open,
so we'll close that,
and instead create a new playground
with "File," "New Playground."
We use an iOS blank playground.
And let's call it ML Fruta,
and store it on the desktop.
I'm gonna expand the size of the window
to give us some more working space.
Now, let's drag in the asset catalog into
the resources folder of the playground.
Notice that Playground compiles
the asset catalog for us
so that we can access the resources
from our code.
We can do that using UIImage(named.
Specify the name of the folder
within the asset catalog
and the name of an image.
And now let's execute the playground
to see the results.
In the results,
we see the width of the image,
and if we QuickLook the image,
we see a preview.
That looks great. So, we have access
to images from that asset catalog.
Now we just need a machine-learning model.
I'm gonna switch to Safari
where I've been browsing
the machine learning section
of the Apple Developer website.
In the Core ML Models page,
we see a number of image classification
and object detection models.
I'd like to try out this model
called YOLOv3,
which is able to detect multiple objects
in a scene and classify each of them.
I think that'd be good for pointing
the camera at a bowl of fruit
and having it identify all the fruit
that it could see.
So, let's click "View models,"
and we can download
the full-precision model at the top.
To save us time, I've already done this,
so let's minimize Safari.
And I'll drag in the model
from the desktop
into the resources section
of the playground.
Xcode will automatically compile
the model for us,
and while it's doing that,
let's select the model
to see details about it in the editor.
An important detail is the model class
up near the top here.
It tells us the name of the class
that will be automatically generated
by the build system
for use in our Swift code.
So, let's make use of that now.
Returning to the playground,
let's add the code to import CoreML.
Then I'll call my variable yoloModel,
and we'll use the class that was
automatically generated for us, YOLOv3,
to create a new instance
with a default configuration,
and we'll fetch the model property.
Let's run the playground
to see the results.
We get back a model description,
which we can preview here,
and see details about the inputs,
outputs and other properties.
So, that's great.
We now have a machine-learning model,
and images to test with,
we just need to combine them together.
An easy way to do that is using
the Vision framework.
I'm gonna replace this code
and instead import the Vision framework.
I'll define an array with
three ingredients to start testing with,
and then we can use our yoloModel
to create an instance of
the Vision framework's CoreMLModel.
And with that, we can create
a CoreMLRequest
that we can use to make
machine-learning requests on images.
Now, I'd like to visualize the results
of these requests by showing each image,
and drawing a rectangle around
any objects detected in the image.
To help do that, I've got some code
that I've used in the past.
Let me QuickLook it for you.
It defines a couple of structs to hold
the results of our object detection
and some SwiftUI views
that we use to show the images
and draw rectangles around any objects
detected in the image.
We won't go into detail about this code,
but we'll make it available
on our session website.
So, after dragging the support code into
the sources section of the playground,
Xcode will compile that,
and now we can make use of the code.
We'll iterate over the ingredient names,
fetch an image for each one
from the asset catalog,
and then we'll create
an image request handler with that image.
We can use that to perform
our machine-learning request.
Then we just need to pass the results.
Each result is
a RecognizedObjectObservation.
We'll enumerate the observations,
we'll fetch the label
with the highest confidence
and the bounding box of that object
within the image,
and return that as a RecognizedObject.
Finally, for each image, we'll return
the results as an ObjectDetectionResult,
and let's preview the results
that we get at the bottom.
Xcode will iterate over the three images,
and then we can preview the results.
Indeed we have a result for each image,
so let's visualize them.
We can do that by setting
a playground LiveView
to the RecognizedObjectVisualizer,
and pass it the results.
Let's continue running.
On the right, we see the results
of our object detection.
The first image we passed in
was of a banana,
and the orange indicates that a banana
was detected with 100% accuracy.
So, that's a pretty good result.
The second image was of three oranges,
and we can see that all three oranges
were detected with high confidence.
So, that worked really well.
The third image was of
a bottle of almond milk,
and we can see that the machine-learning
model detected a bottle
with pretty high confidence, although it
didn't classify it specifically
as a bottle of milk or almond milk.
And that would be because this model
has been trained to detect bottles
but hasn't been specifically trained
to detect bottles of milk or almond milk.
And I think that's fine.
For what this model's been trained for,
it performed really well.
I think this would be the model
to use for our app.
The next step would be to go ahead
and train that model even further,
with the types of ingredients
that we wanna detect for our use case.
To find out more about
how to train your ML models,
I suggest watching
the WWDC 2019 session called
"Training Object Detection Models
in Create ML."
So, that was an example of using resources
that require build system support
in Playgrounds.
Let's summarize what
I've covered in this presentation.
In Xcode 12, Playgrounds is fully
integrated with the modern build system.
When the new option "Build Active Scheme"
is enabled,
all targets in the currently selected
scheme will be automatically built
and made importable into playgrounds
that are in the same workspace.
Any frameworks or Swift packages can then
be imported into your playground code.
All resource types the build system knows
about can now be used in Playgrounds.
For example, asset catalogs and ML Models,
like I demonstrated.
Full playground build logs are
now available in the report navigator,
making it much easier
to diagnose playground build issues.
Playgrounds are great for documenting
packages and frameworks
with runnable code.
And don't forget that playgrounds are
a handy tool
for quickly coding up new ideas
or writing utility code.
I look forward to hearing
how playgrounds are able to help you
make your packages
and projects even better.
Thank you for watching.