[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is James,
and together with my colleague Luming,
I'm here to take you on a journey
of discovery in exploring App Clips.
In today's session, you'll be introduced
to App Clips, an exciting new technology
which will help more people
connect with your app.
We'll go over some example App Clips
to help you envision
what experiences to create.
We'll cover the basics of creating
an App Clip using Xcode.
And wrap up with a technology overview
to help you go from here.
Before we start designing or building
an App Clip,
it's important to understand
what an App Clip is.
And to do that,
I want to introduce three concepts to you.
The first is your app.
This is important
because App Clips are an additive feature,
and you'll need an app
before you can get started with App Clips.
Next is what we're calling
App Clip Experiences.
These are URLs that when opened on iOS 14
are handled by an App Clip
instead of a web browser.
And finally,
we need to talk about the App Clip itself.
This is what enables people
to use your native App experiences
without ever needing to install your app.
Let's cover these two new concepts
in more detail now...
starting with experiences.
These experiences form the basis
for how people will discover
and launch App Clips,
and you can think of them
as new entry points into your app.
Under the covers, we're using URLs
to identify these experiences.
And if you've adopted
Universal Links previously,
you should find the process for
handling App Clip URLs very similar.
A key difference is that
App Clip URLs are not defined
by your Apple-App-Site-Associations file
but are registered
using App Store Connect.
For everything you need to know
about creating
and customizing these experiences
be sure to check out the session,
"Configure and Link Your App Clips."
Once you've registered
an App Clip experience
and your App Clip is live in store, it'll
be surfaced anytime that URL is opened.
From QR codes to NFC tags,
links in Safari and Messages,
to business details and Maps.
No matter how someone uses their device,
we'll make sure that your App Clip
is given the spotlight.
And the best way to discover App Clips
will be with a new Apple designed
App Clip code, coming later this year.
When you see one, you'll know
there's an App Clip waiting for you.
App Clip codes combine the ease of NFC
and visual codes,
so you can tap them or scan them
and always know
that you'll get a great user experience.
Next, let's talk about App Clips.
As developers,
I'm sure some of you are very curious
about how we're gonna
just run part of your apps on demand.
Well, there's no magic.
An App Clip requires you to create
a second application target in Xcode.
This App Clip target will then contain
all the necessary code and assets
to handle your App Clip Experiences.
While an App Clip target is built
much like an app,
it still requires
a corresponding application,
which it will then be built
and submitted for review alongside.
You cannot upload an App Clip or its app
independently of one another.
Once your app and its App Clip
are live in the App Store,
they become mutually exclusive.
Your App Clip is downloaded
if someone encounters
your App Clip experience
but doesn't have your app installed.
Otherwise, your app is preferred.
This is important to remember,
because when someone installs your app,
they will expect those experiences
to continue working.
And last,
because App Clips are focused on providing
fast and in-the-moment experiences,
you should make them as small as possible
so that they download
and launch instantly.
Your App Clip must be less than
ten megabytes after thinning.
And you wanna strike a balance
of including enough assets
to be immediately usable after launch
and download other data
only as needed by the user.
I've talked a lot about experiences,
and I think it's time
to show some examples.
Let's consider this flowchart
where we have boxes
representing screens in an app
and lines showing how
the user moves between them.
This maps to how
a lot of apps are structured.
On the left,
we start with some high-level choices,
such as a Start Page or a Tab bar.
And as we move to the right,
we drill in through
navigation stacks towards some goal.
Hierarchies like this are great
because they help people navigate
complex applications.
But when designing experiences
for App Clips,
I want to challenge you
to radically rethink this flow.
Start by only including
the pieces of your app
that play to the strengths of App Clips.
App Clips are encountered in context
and at the moment someone needs them.
When thinking about
what helps users in the moment,
staple app features
like directory listings
or profile screens
may no longer make sense.
Next, consider how the URLs you use
for your App Clip Experiences
can be deep links into these flows.
App Clips should generally
omit top-level navigation elements,
like Tab bars.
Instead, use separate URLs
for any distinct experiences.
For example, you may want one experience
for when someone orders a product
that will be shipped to them,
versus if they're at an in-store checkout.
And if your business has
multiple physical locations,
you should use a URL
that identifies the store they're at.
This lets you skip showing a store-chooser
and go straight to the content
they care about.
At the end, what you want to have
are focused user flows
that guide someone to their goal.
This isn't to say that
an App Clip can only do one thing.
Quite to the contrary, a well-designed
App Clip can do many things.
However, it focuses on one at a time.
But that's enough theory.
For a demo of putting this all together,
I'd like to welcome Luming
to explain how to get started
with App Clips in Xcode.
Thanks, James, for your great introduction
on exploring App Clips.
I'm Luming,
an engineer from the App Clips team.
Today, I'll be demoing how to create
an App Clip from your app.
So here I am in my app Fruta.
Fruta lets you browse
an entire menu of delicious smoothies,
place orders,
keep track of your favorite smoothies,
get reward points,
and explore smoothie recipes.
While all these functionalities
are great for the full app,
we really want to focus on providing
a streamline ordering experience
for our App Clip.
So that is basically
all the functionalities in the Menu tab.
So let's create an App Clip.
I've opened the smoothies Xcode project,
and I'll create a new target.
I'll choose to create
a new App Clip target and click Next.
I'll call it Fruta Clip.
And it's automatically embedded
in our full application.
You'll notice that Xcode has automatically
populated the name
and the bundle identifier
for our App Clip as well.
Let's run the Clip on device.
Momentarily, the App Clip
should build and run.
Our App Clip has built and run.
Of course, the App Clip is
just an empty boilerplate right now.
So, "Hello, world!" Here we are.
Let's add some code
and resources to the App Clip.
Since the Fruta app has a dependency,
Nutrition Facts,
I'll need to add that
to our App Clip as well.
I'll go to the App Clip target
and choose to add a new dependency.
I'll choose to add
the Nutrition Facts dependency.
Next, let's create an asset catalog
to share assets
between the full app and the App Clip.
I'll choose to create a new file.
Then I'll choose to create
a new asset catalog
and name it Shared Assets.
I'll add it
to the Fruta Clip target membership.
Now, let's view these two asset catalogs
side by side.
Because we need the app icon
in both the app and the App Clip,
I'll drag the app icon
from the asset catalog
to the Shared Asset catalog.
The same applies for colors,
ingredient and smoothie.
So I'll drag all of them over as well.
Since our App Clip won't include recipes,
I'll leave it as is.
Most of my code is organized into groups.
So let's go through every group
and only add the Swift source files
we need to the App Clip target.
Model we definitely need,
so I'll go to the target membership
and tick the App Clip checkbox.
Store is for unlocking additional recipes,
so we can leave it out.
Orders, we definitely need it
in our App Clip, so I'll tick it as well.
But since our App Clip
doesn't need a tab bar
and focuses on ordering smoothie
just from the first tab,
which is the Main Menu of the full app,
we can let go of the navigation code.
Smoothies. We definitely need them,
so I'll check it.
Recipes we can leave out.
Ingredients. That's a must.
And so is Components and Styles.
I'll also include
the VisualEffectView wrapper
and check the Fruta Clip checkbox.
I think that's all
the code we need in the Clip.
Let's build it.
Huh. It looks like there's a build error.
Why is that?
Well, it turns out because
OrderPlacedView.swift references Store,
which we have excluded from the App Clip
in the previous step,
our App Clip won't build.
We need to conditionally compile out
the references to Store
in OrderPlacedView.swift.
I'll go back
to the App Clip target's build settings.
There, I'll find the Swift Compiler -
Custom Flags section,
and I'll define a new custom condition,
APPCLIP, in all caps,
for both the debug scheme
as well as the release scheme.
Now, we can come back
to OrderPlacedView.swift
and conditionally
compile out references to Store.
Finally, we need to bring up
Smoothie Menu in our App Clip.
In our App Clip's FrutaClip.swift file,
I'll instantiate a new Fruta model
as its data store object.
And pass it to the ContentView
as its environment variable.
In the body of ContentView
I'll remove the default placeholder,
"Hello, world!"
and create a new NavigationView.
In the NavigationView,
I'll include a SmoothieMenu.
Then we can build and run.
Voilà. We got our App Clip running.
The Clip looks and works great.
I can browse the smoothie menu...
find my favorite and place an order.
It looks like my smoothie's ready.
Time to enjoy my smoothie.
Back to you, James.
Thanks, Luming. That was awesome.
And I really like how that demo captures
just how simple it can be
to share code and assets
using existing Xcode features.
Shared asset catalogs
and source files are also great
if you're developing for multiple
platforms like Apple Watch and macOS.
And it highlights another theme
I want to touch on.
And that is how we've reused
existing technologies
to make building App Clips a breeze.
App Clips are built
using the same UI frameworks as apps.
This includes support for either UIKit
or the new SwiftUI app lifecycle.
When launched, your App Clip or app
will receive an NSUserActivity.
And if your App Clip
supports multiple App Clip Experiences,
you'll use the web page URL
on this activity
to know which experience you're handling.
This should feel very familiar if your app
already handles Universal Links.
And unlike extensions,
an App Clip is able to use
any API in the iOS SDK.
This makes sharing code between
your app and your App Clip so easy.
However, from your App Clip,
access to sensitive user data is limited.
But there's nothing special
you need to do here.
Just be sure to check for access to data
before you request it.
As an example, you can share source code
that uses the HealthKit framework.
But be prepared for
HKHealthStore isHealthDataAvailable
to always return false
when running in your App Clip.
And because of this,
you won't find any isAppClip API.
Just follow the best practices
for the frameworks you use.
To help you build
a frictionless experience from tap to tap,
we've added
a new location confirmation API.
Instead of prompting
for the full access to someone's location,
which they may not feel comfortable giving
to an App Clip they've just encountered,
use this API to confirm they're where
you think they are
while respecting their privacy.
To learn how to adopt this
and other great tips,
be sure to check out
the "Streamline Your App Clip" session.
Finally, to continue
that seamless experience,
we're providing API that allows you
to migrate data from your App Clip
if someone installs its corresponding app.
This is done
using a shared data container,
and I'll talk about it more in a bit.
Developing an App Clip
should feel instantly familiar
and just like working on an app.
However, when developing an App Clip,
there are some special considerations
to keep in mind.
To start, App Clips aren't something
people need to manage.
An App Clip is run when needed,
but if it is never used again,
iOS will delete the App Clip and its data.
Additionally, App Clips are not included
in iOS backups.
With App Clips, we want users to feel safe
running app code on demand.
As such, we're putting an even
higher focus on the privacy of App Clips
and outright restricting access to some
sensitive data such as health and fitness.
If your corresponding app
makes use of these types of data,
you can encourage people to install it
for even more functionality.
An App Clip is focused
on providing App Clip Experiences,
and it cannot be launched
for other reasons.
Because of this, it cannot register
for custom URL schemes,
document types or Universal Links.
This is very important if you're using
a custom URL scheme as a callback
for a federated sign-in service.
In this case, you should instead use
ASWebAuthenticationSession,
which does not require you to register
the URL schemes you use for callbacks.
And as you may have guessed,
this also means that App Clips
cannot include bundled extensions,
like content blockers.
Now that you know
some of the similarities and differences
between apps and App Clips,
I wanna cover how these two interact
on a single device.
Say, for example, someone finds a QR code
for an App Clip and scans it.
Because there is no app installed
to handle the experience,
iOS will automatically locate, download
and launch an App Clip for the user.
The App Clip gets to run while in use,
and then the user moves on.
After a period of time,
if the App Clip has not been revisited,
iOS will delete the App Clip,
its data container and its Keychain data.
If the user encounters
the experience again,
the entire process repeats,
just as before.
This illustrates an important point.
While App Clips can store data
on the device,
treat it more like a temporary cache,
because it may be deleted
at the system's discretion.
Now let's rewind and consider what happens
when someone repeatedly uses
the same App Clip experience.
Perhaps this is an ordering App Clip
at their favorite coffee shop,
and they visit it every day.
In this case, the App Clip's lifetime
will be extended,
and it may never be cleaned up
because iOS notices
that it's used frequently.
So, if the App Clip caches the last order,
it could show this as a recommendation
to speed up ordering next time.
Of course, if someone loves
your App Clip that much,
they'll probably want to install your app.
When they do this, iOS will automatically
migrate authorizations for camera,
microphone and Bluetooth access.
If your App Clip also has data to migrate,
you can do so using a new type
of group data container,
which is automatically made available
to both your App Clip
and your corresponding app.
For this to work, your App Clip should
store data that you want to migrate
in this shared data container,
rather than
the App Clip's standard container.
If the user then installs your app,
iOS will still delete the App Clip
and its data just like before.
But this group container will stick around
until your app has a chance
to copy the data out before going away.
A great App Clip is built
using the same best practices
and technologies as a great app.
That includes supporting Apple Pay
for payments,
which allows people
to quickly make purchases
without fumbling for their credit cards.
Notifications to alert someone
when their smoothie is available
or their parking meter is about to expire.
SwiftUI is a great fit for App Clips
because of its focus
on small and reusable components,
which can easily be shared
between an app and its App Clip target.
And new this year is SKOverlay...
or if you're using SwiftUI,
the App Store overlay modifier.
This API is the best way
to lead people to your full app
after they've had a great experience
using your App Clip.
You can learn more about it by watching
"What's New in In-App Purchase"
from WWDC 20.
Last, if your App Clip would benefit
from associating users with an account,
say, to keep reward points on a purchase,
you should use ASAuthorizationController
from authentication services.
ASAuthorizationController allows users
to easily sign in
to their existing password-based accounts
or create a new account
using Sign in with Apple.
For more information, check out "What's
New in Authentication" from WWDC 19.
In summary, App Clips represent
a new type of user experience.
These experiences can be invoked on demand
without someone
even having your app installed
via a dedicated App Clip binary.
However, once your application
is installed,
it will take over
and also handle these experiences.
These App Clip binaries are built
using the same technologies as apps,
so you can transfer knowledge from writing
apps directly to writing App Clips.
And App Clip Experiences
are streamlined and linear,
focused on achieving a specific task.
Features such as reward programs
should be presented as optional steps
after someone has completed their goal.
Thanks so much for watching
and have a great WWDC.
[chimes]