Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name is Ayaka,
and I'm here to show you
how to get your app's actions
featured in the Shortcuts app.
In this session,
we're gonna focus on two things.
First, we're gonna talk about
automation suggestions.
Specifically,
we'll talk about how your app's actions
can be featured as a part of automations
that are suggested by the system.
Next, we'll briefly talk about
how your actions can be surfaced
in the Shortcuts Gallery
and the Shortcuts Editor
so people can more easily discover
and create their own shortcuts with them.
Before we talk
about automation suggestions,
let's talk about automations.
In iOS 13,
we introduced personal automations.
Personal automations
allow you to run shortcuts automatically
based on a specific condition.
For example, one of my simplest
and favorite automations I have
is one that opens my reading list
when I arrive at my local bookstore
so I know exactly what I should look for.
Alongside automations in iOS 13,
we also introduced automation suggestions
in the Shortcuts Gallery,
which are centered around daily routines,
like going to and from work.
In iOS 14,
we extended it to support all actions,
including user activities, system intents
such as INPlayMediaIntent,
and custom intents that your app defines.
By having your app donate interactions
when a person does something in your app,
the system will learn and make suggestions
for things
that they might want to automate.
Here, because I use Duolingo
a lot in the evening,
I'm getting a suggestion to practice
my French every weekday at 9:00.
I think that's a pretty useful automation,
and something that could help
strengthen my habit.
I'm gonna tap on the suggestion to add it.
And then all I have to do is tap
"Add Automation"
to add it to my collection.
And here it is in my automations list
along with my other automation.
We think it's a great, simple experience
for people,
especially for those
who are just getting their feet wet
in the world of automations.
As I briefly mentioned earlier,
these suggestions are made possible
through donations of interactions
when a person does something in your app.
In fact, donating is the only thing
that you need to do
in order for the system to learn
and make these suggestions.
Let's see what that looks like in code.
Let's say I have a soup delivery app,
and I want to donate a order.soup intent
when a person, well, orders a soup.
First, I'm gonna initialize the intent,
which I've named PlaceOrderIntent.
Next, I need to know what I'm ordering,
specifically which soup,
so I'm gonna get my soup
from this order object I have.
Then I'm gonna set
the intent's soup property
to an INObject that represents the soup.
Next, I'm gonna set some images
for my parameters,
one for the soup
and one for the delivery location.
And then I'll wrap the intent
in an INInteraction.
And finally,
I'm gonna call donate on the interaction
to tell the system
that someone ordered a soup.
The types of actions that are supported
by automation suggestions
include system intents,
as well as custom intents
and user activities.
Because intents can run in the background
without having to open the app,
we recommend using intents here.
If you want to learn more about
how your app can adopt intents,
you can check out
some of these past talks.
The first one
is "Introduction to Siri Shortcuts,"
which shows you the fundamentals
of how shortcuts work with intents.
And the second one
is "Introducing Parameters for Shortcuts,"
which shows you how to make your shortcuts
even more powerful
by supporting
user-configurable parameters.
By the way, we support
many different automation types.
We have automation types
ranging from time of day
to when you arrive at a location
to when you connect
to a particular Bluetooth device.
As someone who turns on
my reading lights every evening,
I might get a suggestion for setting
my "reading time" home scene
every evening at 8:00.
Or as someone who calls in
to a lot of meetings on my phone,
I might get a suggestion for dialing in
to my conference room
every time I connect my AirPods.
The types of automations
that the system could suggest
are as endlessly unique
as people's habits and routines.
Going back to this list of suggestions,
another thing I want to explore
further today is Daily Routines.
Daily Routines are a special type
of automation suggestion
that we introduced last year.
These are centered
around a person's routine,
and there is a personalized,
step-by-step flow
that guides people through the process
of setting up a multistep automation.
Specifically, we have three of them.
One for going to work, one for going home,
and another for when you're at the gym.
There are several opportunities
for your app to be a part of these flows.
For example, if you're a media app
that plays music, podcasts or audiobooks,
you can be a part of all three
of these flows in the "Play Media" step
by adopting INPlayMediaIntent.
If you're a workouts app,
you can be a part of
the "At the Gym" routine
by adopting INStartWorkoutIntent.
Let's walk through what it looks like
to set up a daily routine.
I'm gonna tap on the first suggestion here
to set up a "Going Home" routine.
There's a step-by-step flow
that guides me through the process
of setting up this automation.
For example, for "Going Home,"
it first asks me
what media I want to play.
If your app plays media,
your app can show up on this list as well.
You can do this by adopting and donating
INPlayMediaIntent
to inform the system
that someone played some media.
Over time,
if that person does this consistently
and the predictions model
correlates this action with their commute,
the Shortcuts app will start suggesting it
as a part of this flow.
Once I choose my playlist,
I can choose to include
getting directions home.
After that, I get an option
to send a contact of my choice
an ETA for getting home.
For example, something like,
"I'll be home at 6:30."
And finally, I can choose
if I want this to be an automation
or a shortcut that I run manually.
I'm gonna select
"Show Automatically" here.
And once I do that,
it gets added to my automations list here
to run ten minutes
before leaving for home.
And this is the full shortcut
that got added to my library.
It first starts playing some music,
then gets driving directions to my home
in the Maps app,
followed by the estimated driving time
to get home,
and finally,
it sends a message with my ETA.
I was able to set up
this personalized multistep shortcut
with just a few taps
thanks to Daily Routines.
So, if you're a media app,
be sure to adopt INPlayMediaIntent,
and if you're a workouts app,
be sure to adopt INStartWorkoutIntent
to be a part of the Daily Routines flow.
That wraps up automation suggestions.
Now let's talk
about the Gallery and Editor.
Specifically, we'll take a look
at the "Shortcuts from Your Apps" section
in the Gallery, and the Shortcuts Editor.
This is what
the "Shortcuts from Your App" section
looks like in the Gallery.
If I tap on "See All,"
I see even more shortcuts.
Today I want to demystify
how these shortcuts are being curated.
One way to show up in this list
is by setting shortcut suggestions
using INVoiceShortcutCenter.
In code,
it might look something like this.
First, I'm gonna take my OrderStatusIntent
and wrap it in an INShortcut.
I'll do the same
for my TopSoupsUserActivity,
put them all in a suggestions array,
and finally, call setShortcutSuggestions
with those suggestions.
In addition,
similar to automation suggestions,
we can be more intelligent about
what shows up by relying on donations,
which I showed you how to do earlier.
These are suggestions based on
how people interact with their apps,
including things
that they have done recently.
So, those are the two ways
that you can get your app's actions
to show up in the Gallery.
In addition to the Gallery,
these same actions
will also surface in the Shortcuts Editor.
Here, the suggestions are based
on donations for things a person has done.
For example, I'm getting some suggestions
for music I might want to play
based on my playback history,
along with some suggestions
for streaks I'm trying to maintain.
A person can also tap on
the "Apps" button, which is up here,
to see a list of all their apps
that support shortcuts.
For example, I can look at all the actions
that the Streaks app is offering me.
There are a lot of actions here,
so let's break it down.
This is based on a combination of things.
First, the actions down here
are shortcuts that were suggested
using INVoiceShortcutCenter, or donated.
Also, if the action supports
key parameters,
it shows up
with a row of parameter options
like what we see here
under "Complete Task,"
like "Run Five Miles" or "Study French."
Second, the actions up here come from
intents that are marked "configurable."
If your intent is configurable,
it will show up
even if you don't donate or suggest it.
If you want to make sure a particular set
of actions always shows up,
we recommend using INVoiceShortcutCenter
to set suggestions in addition to donating
user interactions in your app,
just like what we talked about
for the Gallery.
In addition to suggesting shortcuts,
donating actions,
and making intents configurable,
there's also one more way
to include your actions
in the Shortcuts Editor.
That is, some system intents will show up
in the Shortcuts Editor
without having to suggest shortcuts
or donate actions.
Specifically, those system intents
are SendPayment, RequestPayment
and RequestRide.
So, let's talk about next steps.
First, consider providing
your app's actions to the system
using INVoiceShortcutCenter's
setShortcutSuggestions API.
Second, please donate your intents
during regular app usage
so the system can learn
to feature your app in the Gallery
as a part of automation suggestions,
and in the editor as suggested actions.
There are more opportunities than ever
to be featured in the Shortcuts app.
Thanks for watching,
and we can't wait to see what shortcuts
people create with their app's actions.