Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Dan, and today
we're gonna talk about how to create
a seamless speech experience in your apps.
In this talk, I'll go over
when to leverage AVSpeechSynthesizer
and when you might wanna consider
other APIs instead.
Then, I'll go over some of the API basics,
before jumping
into some more advanced topics,
like how to route speech
through an outgoing call
or how to opt speech audio out of
your application shared audio session.
Let's start by taking a look
at a couple different examples
of when you might be considering
using speech in your apps.
If you are trying to use speech
for everyone in your app,
AVSpeechSynthesizer
is likely a good choice.
Perhaps your app is designed
to be used without looking at the screen,
like how the Maps app uses speech
to provide spoken directions.
If you're trying to provide speech
only for people using your app
with a screen reader
or other assistive technology,
AVSpeechSynthesizer
may not be the right choice.
All of our devices ship with VoiceOver,
a built-in screen reader
with a rich feature set.
So there's no need for you
to create your own screen reader
that's local to your app
using AVSpeechSynthesizer.
Instead, make your app accessible
using the UIAccessibility APIs.
If you need help
getting started with this,
we have some great talks
from past WWDCs that can help.
For the cases where you want to provide
infrequent additional speech to VoiceOver,
such as describing
an event that has occurred,
you can do so by posting
an announcement notification.
Use UIAccessibility.post and pass in
a notification type of announcement
and a string
that you'd like to have spoken.
This will delegate the speech request
to VoiceOver so it can manage it for you.
If you're building an app that has
an experience centered around speech,
AVSpeechSynthesizer
might be able to provide you
with some additional flexibility
even if your app is going to be used in
conjunction with an assistive technology.
Augmentative Alternative Communication,
or AAC, apps are one example
of this kind of experience.
And Proloquo2Go
is an AAC app that does a great job.
It's a tool for people who are nonverbal,
and it uses pictures and other visual cues
to help people construct sentences
that are spoken aloud
via AVSpeechSynthesizer
so they may communicate with others.
Apps designed for people
who are blind or low-vision
might also have experiences
centered around speech.
Seeing AI is an app that helps people
interact with the world around them
by describing objects
in their environment.
Notice that Seeing AI is still
completely accessible to VoiceOver,
and all of its UI is properly labeled.
AVSpeechSynthesizer can still help
by being used to describe the objects
in the viewfinder
and gives the app additional control
over how and when
those speech requests are spoken.
Now that we know when it's appropriate
to use AVSpeechSynthesizer,
let's dive into some of the API.
To get started, it's pretty simple.
All you need to do is create
an AVSpeechSynthesizer object.
Make sure that this object is retained
until speech is concluded.
Next, create an AVSpeechUtterance,
passing in the string
you'd like to have spoken.
Finally, call the speak method
on your synthesizer,
passing in the utterance you've created.
Getting started is that simple.
If you're trying to provide basic amounts
of speech for everyone using your app,
this is likely all you'll need to do.
By default, AVSpeechSynthesizer
will configure your utterance
using the settings on your device
in Accessibility Spoken Content.
Keep in mind
that although Siri voices are available
to be selected in Spoken Content Settings,
they are not available
through the AVSpeechSynthesizer API.
In the case that a Siri voice
is the selected voice,
we'll automatically
configure your utterance
using an appropriate fallback voice
that matches the same language code
as the selected Siri voice.
People using your app with
an assistive technology like VoiceOver
likely have other speech settings
configured specifically
for that technology.
Until now, it hasn't been possible
to request that AVSpeechSynthesizer
respect those settings instead of the ones
on your device in Spoken Content.
Well, this year we're changing that
with the new
prefersAssistiveTechnologySettings API.
Setting this property to "true"
on your AVSpeechUtterance
will request that AVSpeechSynthesizer
apply the settings
from the currently running
assistive technology to your utterance.
This includes speech properties
such as the selected voice,
speaking rate and pitch.
It's important to note
that these properties will take precedence
over any properties you are
explicitly setting on the utterance.
If no assistive technology is running,
we'll continue to use
the settings from Spoken Content
or whichever properties
you are setting on the utterance.
We encourage you
to set this on your utterances,
especially if your app
is likely to be used
with an assistive technology
like VoiceOver.
However, this API may not be appropriate
for all apps, like AAC apps,
so make sure you evaluate
your use case accordingly.
Let's take a look
at how this API affects speech.
In this app,
tapping on each of the buttons
will speak the string "Hello, world."
The first button uses
the default settings,
whereas the second uses the
prefersAssistiveTechnologySettings API.
On this device, VoiceOver is running
with a non-default voice
and a higher speaking rate.
Let's listen to how the speech sounds.
[male electronic voice]
Speak "Hello, world" button.
[female electronic voice] Hello, world.
[male electronic voice]
Speak "Hello, world" button. Hello, world.
Notice how the second speech request
used the same voice
and speaking rate as VoiceOver
so that speech fit in much more seamlessly
with the VoiceOver experience.
Meanwhile, the first button
spoke the string quite differently,
and it may not be what the person
who is using this app would've expected.
Sometimes, you might want
to customize speech within your app
rather than respecting
the settings on the device.
For example,
an AAC app might wanna provide people
with a list of voices to choose from
and the ability to customize
other speech properties
so they can create a voice
that sounds more unique to them.
You can set a voice on your utterance,
choosing one using
either a language code or an identifier.
You can also get a list of voices
available on the system
by calling the Speech Voices method
on AVSpeechSynthesisVoice.
This list will be updated as new voices
are downloaded in Accessibility Settings.
You can further customize speech
by setting additional properties
on your AVSpeechUtterance,
such as speaking rate,
a pitch multiplier and a volume.
The AVSpeechSynthesizer talk from WWDC18
covers all of these properties
in more detail,
so I encourage you to watch that
if you'd like to learn more.
An API to consider if you're building
an app centered around speech
is the mixToTelephonyUplink property.
Setting this property to "true"
on your AVSpeechSynthesizer
will route speech
through the current active outgoing call,
such as a phone call or a FaceTime call.
If no call is active,
we'll continue to route speech
through its default audio route.
This is a really powerful API
for apps like AAC apps
as it can empower people who are nonverbal
to communicate using
more traditional methods.
Another API to consider
if you're building an app
that has an experience
centered around speech,
or if your app uses a lot of other audio,
is the usesApplicationAudioSession API.
By default, this is set to "true"
on your AVSpeechSynthesizer,
and speech audio will use
your application shared audio session.
You can set it to "false"
to delegate away the management
of speech audio to the system.
This way,
we'll take care of certain things for you,
such as handling audio interruptions
and setting your audio session
to active or inactive.
Additionally, speech will duck and mix
with the other audio coming from your app,
so you don't have to worry
about it interfering
with things like sound effects,
music or video.
That's an overview of some
of the AVSpeechSynthesizer API.
Remember,
AVSpeechSynthesizer is not a replacement
for the UIAccessibility APIs
and, instead, should be used
in conjunction with those APIs
to create a great experience.
Use the
prefersAssistiveTechnologySettings API
to request that AVSpeechSynthesizer
apply the speech settings
from the currently running
assistive technology to your utterances.
And if you're building an experience
centered around speech,
consider whether the mixToTelephonyUplink
or usesApplicationAudioSession APIs
can improve the experience
for people using your app.
Speech can be a really powerful tool for
people that use assistive technologies,
so I really encourage you to take a look
at how you can incorporate speech
into your apps
to empower those people
to do some incredible things.
Thanks for watching, and enjoy WWDC.