Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Lizi,
and I'm a machine learning manager
on the Create ML team.
Today I'm thrilled to introduce
a set of new APIs
for checkpointing
and asynchronous training in Create ML.
To make sure we're all on the same page,
let's talk about the Create ML app
and the Create ML framework.
The Create ML app is great.
If you want to easily create models
without a single line of code,
I encourage you to start there.
Under the hood, the app is powered
by a rich and easy-to-use API:
the Create ML framework.
For macOS Big Sur, we're bringing you
a set of powerful and flexible APIs
for controlling your training workflow.
These will enable you to customize the way
you create machine learning models
and leverage all the same technology
that powers the app.
With that, let's start by reviewing
the training process.
If you want to train a model,
the first thing you have to do
is collect some data.
You also want to look at
all the training options available to you.
If you are using Create ML,
you can always accept
the default parameter settings,
but it doesn't hurt to understand
what the options mean.
Next, preprocessing.
Some tasks require extracting features
or transforming data
into the right structure.
For example, raw audio may be transformed
by taking its spectrogram
or video may have keypoints
extracted from every frame.
Then, training. This is the fun part.
And we'll spend some time
looking at this in depth,
so let's leave it at that for now.
Next, we evaluate the model
by presenting it with new data.
Here, it's important to use
a different set of data
that the model hasn't seen
during training.
This will help you determine
if your model is generalizing
instead of memorizing training examples.
At this point, you may realize that
your model is not quite what you expect.
Maybe it needs more data.
Maybe it needs a different set
of training parameters.
Or maybe it just needs
to train a bit longer.
Model development is an iterative process,
so you can return to setup or train
until your model meets your needs.
Once you are satisfied,
you can use your trained model
to perform predictions.
At this point, you're ready to deploy.
With the training process in mind,
let's talk about control.
Training control is mainly
having the ability to pause and resume,
but also the ability to observe and alter
the training process while it's happening.
And you can stop training at any point.
Why is this important?
Training a machine learning model
takes time.
In particular, training an object
detection model can take five hours.
Imagine you were training
and after several hours, training stops
because it reached
the maximum number of iterations.
But then you realize
that the loss was still decreasing,
and there was still room
to converge to a better model.
Without training control,
you would have to start from scratch
and choose a larger number
of maximum iterations.
But now you can continue
from where training stopped.
Another reason this is important
is results are specific
to what you are trying to achieve.
Using a built-in mechanism
to evaluate the model
will not necessarily give the best results
for your specific use-case.
This is particularly true
in Style Transfer
where the quality of a model
is subjective.
For instance, here, the model is applying
the fish mosaic style
to the photo of the dancers.
It's up to you to decide
when this is good enough
and stop training.
Also, choosing when to stop
is specific to your needs.
Maybe you need a model for a prototype
and don't want to spend
too much time on it.
Or maybe this is an important model
and you are willing
to spend extra time training
to achieve the best result possible.
Using training control,
you can define custom stopping criteria,
meaning you are not limited
to the number of iterations.
You may have a target accuracy
for an image classifier,
or you may have a specific amount of time
you can allow for training.
Training control is available
in the Create ML app.
But with the API, you can customize
this behavior to your needs.
Let me show you.
Before, you would call
a model constructor, time would stop,
and a trained model would be returned.
With the new asynchronous API,
you can now call the train method
which returns a job.
The train method
takes the usual training parameters
as well as a sessionParameters argument
which lets you specify
the cadence of reports
and total number of iterations.
You can always omit the arguments
to use the defaults.
The first argument to sessionParameters
is the sessionDirectory.
This directory will be created
if it doesn't already exist.
In subsequent invocations,
the contents of the directory
will be used to resume a previous session.
If you want to start a new session,
simply delete the directory
or choose a new location.
The next two arguments control the cadence
of progress reports and checkpoints.
Smaller intervals
will give more frequent updates,
but may come at a performance cost.
The last argument
is the total number of iterations.
Training will stop
at this iteration number.
But don't worry,
you can always increase this number
in subsequent calls to train,
and you can always stop before
this number of iterations is reached.
The job returned from train
is an instance of MLJob
which represents an active training job.
It contains a progress publisher,
a checkpoint publisher
and a result publisher.
These leverage the Combine framework,
which you can learn more about
in "Introducing Combine"
and "Combine in Practice" from WWDC19.
MLJob also provides a cancel method
so you can stop training easily
at any point.
To give you an idea, here is how
you would use the result publisher
to get a trained model.
First, you register a sink
on the result publisher.
Its first closure is invoked on completion
and receives a success or failure result.
It also receives an error
in the failure case,
so you should handle errors here.
The second closure
receives the final model
when training is complete.
Finally, you store the subscription
until you are done with it.
You can observe progress
such as the fraction completed,
the current training iteration,
total number of iterations,
and custom metrics such as
the current loss or accuracy value.
For example,
you can observe and print progress
by accessing the progress publisher
on MLJob.
Note that this is the standard instance
of Progress from Foundation.
To access custom metrics,
we first register a sink closure.
As a precaution, we capture the job weakly
to avoid retain cycles.
Next, we ensure the job still exists
and create an instance of MLProgress.
The MLProgress helper type
allows us to access custom metrics
from an instance of Foundation Progress.
Note that there may be cases
where an instance of MLProgress
cannot be initialized yet,
such as when a new session is just created
or a new phase is starting.
We handle that by returning early.
Then we can access
all progress information
like the current item
and total number of items.
In feature extraction,
the item refers to the current file
or record being processed.
For training, it refers to
the current iteration number.
And finally, we can get training metrics.
Metrics are only available
in the training phase,
and are specific to each task.
Some tasks have accuracy
while others have loss or other metrics.
If you provided validation data,
you may also be able
to access validation metrics.
Now let's take a look
at how you can train a model
using the new asynchronous APIs.
I've been really interested in training
a few Style Transfer models
after watching "Build Image and Video
Style Transfer Models in Create ML,"
so I've started setting up
my model creation workflow in Playgrounds.
Here, I have a few different styles images
I can use in my resource bundle
and I also have some validation images
of different artists
that I'd like to stylize.
Back in my Playground,
I first specified URLs
to the style image and validation image
that I want to use.
One nice thing about Playgrounds
is it allows me
to visualize my data inline as I go.
For example, I can see the style
that I've designated
and validation image that we'll use.
The next thing I'll do is specify
a dataSource to define our training data
and I'll pass list the styleImageURL
and contentDirectory
and then proceed to initialize parameters
we need to set up our session.
I'll first initialize
MLTrainingSessionParameters
that takes a sessionDirectory.
I can also provide a reportInterval
to specify the number of iterations
between progress reports,
a checkpointInterval to specify the
number of iterations between checkpoints,
and iterations to extend training.
Next, I'll set up my model parameters.
Now we're ready to begin training.
To start the training process,
I'll call the train method
on the type of model I want to create.
Here, I'll provide my dataSource,
trainingParameters...
and sessionParameters.
This returns an instance of MLJob.
MLJob contains a results publisher.
We can use the results publisher to
receive errors that occur during training
and access the model once we're done.
I can also use the job to control
and observe training while it's happening.
For example, if I want to access
progress programmatically,
I can do so
by using the progress publisher.
And since this is an instance
of Foundation Progress,
I'm going to specify
that we want the fractionCompleted
by providing a key path to that property.
Next, I'll call sink
which will return a cancellable
that we can later use
to terminate the subscription.
Beyond the fractionCompleted,
I can also access metrics specific
to the ML model I am trying to train.
To do this,
I'll initialize an instance of MLProgress
from the instance of Foundation Progress.
I can then access specific metrics
such as the style loss
and content loss across iterations.
And with the power of Xcode Playgrounds,
when I hit "train,"
I can visualize progress
as it's happening.
And in Playgrounds, I can view this
as the latest value or a graph
as it trains across iterations.
Pretty cool.
New this release is also the ability
to control the training process
with pausing, resuming and extending.
To stop, all I need to do
is call cancel on the job.
To resume, it's as simple as calling train
with the same session directory
as I used before.
It's almost automatic.
Now that you've seen how to train a model
using the new asynchronous APIs,
I want to introduce checkpoints.
With checkpoints, you can capture
the state of your model over time.
You can use them to see
how training progressed
and easily compare
against previous results.
Also, if you decide that a checkpoint
needs a bit more training,
you can use it to resume
where you left off.
MLCheckpoint is the struct that represents
either a training
or feature extraction checkpoint.
Unlike in other frameworks,
MLCheckpoints are created automatically
when using the new asynchronous APIs,
and they're easy to resume from.
All you need to do
is provide a sessionDirectory
where you are starting a new session
or continuing an existing one.
This is great in environments
such as Playgrounds
so you can iterate
without losing progress.
Let's go back to the training process
for a moment.
I want to zoom into two of these phases:
preprocessing and training.
These are the two phases
where checkpoints are generated.
Let's start with preprocessing.
In this phase, we take data elements,
such as individual files
or rows in a table,
and process each one of them.
Progress is measured by how many
of these elements have been processed.
Every few elements,
we store the current progress
as a checkpoint.
We only keep
the last preprocessing checkpoint
since this phase is strictly additive.
The training phase
is also an iterative process.
The model improves in discrete steps
called iterations.
An iteration consists of running
a batch of data through the network,
computing the loss
and updating the weights.
A training checkpoint is the state
of the model at a particular iteration.
Unlike preprocessing, training preserves
all checkpoints you create.
As training progresses,
we also get metrics
such as loss or accuracy.
These metrics are stored
along with the checkpoints
to help you identify them.
Let's look at some code.
Here is an example of how you would use
the checkpoints publisher.
All checkpoints are automatically saved
to the session folder.
But this publisher gives you a chance
of generating custom metrics,
generating a model,
or stopping training altogether.
It's a chance for you to act
on new checkpoints as they are created.
For instance, this is how you can generate
a model from a checkpoint.
Once you have a model,
you can save it to disk
or use it to make predictions.
Note that you can only create
a model from training checkpoints,
not feature extraction checkpoints,
so you should check its training phase.
You can make checkpoints
during the feature extraction phase
for image classification,
sound classification
and action classification.
Training checkpoints are available
for action classification,
object detection, Style Transfer
and activity classification.
Now let's talk about sessions.
Think of a session as the aggregate
of all checkpoints and their metadata.
This is represented
by the MLTrainingSession type.
It lets you query details
like when the session was created,
the current training phase,
and the current iteration number.
If you want to access
the session directly,
you can use the restoreTrainingSession
method on a model type.
From that, you can do things
like access the loss values.
You can also remove checkpoints
that you don't need anymore,
freeing up disk space.
Now let's take a look
at checkpoints in action.
We already saw how you could observe
progress and results
from an instance of MLJob
while training a Style Transfer model
in Playgrounds.
Back in our same Playground,
we can see that MLJob contains
a checkpoints publisher
that we can use
to observe checkpoints over time.
For Style Transfer, I can access
the stylized validation image
on each checkpoint
to help us visualize how our model
is progressing as it trains.
To do this, I can use compactMap
to transform the checkpoint
into a form we need
and then map the image URLs into NSImages.
I'm then going to call sink
to attach a subscriber
to the checkpoints publisher
and store the AnyCancellable
return type to our subscriptions list.
And now we can see
our stylized validation image
over time as the model trains,
directly inline.
But wouldn't it be great
if we could take things even further?
Well, now, using SwiftUI,
we can easily render more
in the Xcode Playgrounds Live View.
The first thing I'll do
is to find a new view object
and pass it images of our style image,
stylized validation image
and original validation
so we can compare
how our model is performing over time.
And since we're using UI,
I'll receive this on the main queue
and then I'll set the Playground Live View
so we can populate the results there.
And the Live View comes to life!
Now we can visualize our model
as it trains
along with our reference style
and the validation image,
thanks to the new checkpointing
and asynchronous training APIs.
Let's recap what we saw in this session.
We learned how to train a model
using the new asynchronous APIs
available in Create ML.
We learned about checkpoints
and how to use them
to generate models and resume training.
And lastly,
we saw how to use Combine publishers
to get progress reports
and handle results.
So where do you go from here?
I encourage you
to leverage these new tools
if you need to customize
your training workflow.
Training control allows you to control
not just your model quality,
but the entire training process,
whether you are developing models,
automating workflows
or creating models on demand
in your macOS apps.
Thank you, and enjoy the rest of WWDC.