Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hey, everyone.
I'm David, a machine learning engineer
from the Create ML team,
and in this session,
we're going to talk about
building style transfer models
in Create ML.
Style transfer
is a new machine learning task
available this year in the Create ML app.
It can be used to blend
a style and content image together.
Let's see what happens when we apply
style transfer to this pair of images.
Wow. That's pretty cool.
The stylized result looks great.
The model has transferred the colors,
shapes, and textures
from the style image to the content image.
The color of the style image
is very important.
The white background
and black paint strokes from this style
are transferred by the model
to create a black-and-white result.
Paintings aren't the only source of style.
The model can learn and transfer the tiles
from this mosaic as well.
Express your creativity
by using different patterns from nature.
For example, the ice cracks in this style
can be transferred by the model
to produce a pretty compelling result.
These are just a few examples
of what you can do with style transfer
in Create ML.
But wouldn't it be great
if we could do even better?
What if you could apply style transfer
to more than just a static image?
Amazing.
Each frame is stylized fast enough
to maintain
a smooth stylization experience.
You can use a style transfer model
in real time for your video apps.
Using the A13 Bionic chip,
we can achieve a processing speed
up to 120 frames per second.
To train a style transfer model,
we need to provide some training data:
a style image
and a directory of content images.
The model learns the balance between
content and style from your images.
For optimal results,
the content images used for training
should be similar to what you expect
to stylize at inference time.
In this example, I have a directory
of natural content images.
You can use model parameters
to optimize the behavior
of a style transfer model.
You can configure your model behavior
with style strength and style density
model parameters.
Let's explore style strength first.
With a style strength parameter,
you can tune the balance
between style and content.
With low style strength,
only parts of the background
adopt the style image qualities,
and the people dancing have adopted
only a small amount of blue color.
Now, with high style strength,
the background is even more stylized,
and the people dancing completely adopt
the style image colors and ice cracks.
Notice the difference
when I put them next to each other.
Next, let's explore style density.
With the style density parameter,
coarse details
can be learned by the model.
Here, I've drawn a grid
on top of the style image.
Let's zoom in on a region.
The model focuses
on high-level details in this region,
such as the bird,
and learns these coarse qualities.
Here's an example of coarse stylization.
Fine details
can also be learned by the model
by setting the style density parameter
to a higher setting.
With a fine grid, the zoomed-in region
contains mostly color and brush strokes.
This produces a different stylized result.
Let's compare the coarse and fine results
side by side to visualize the difference.
You can use the style density parameter
to explore a wide range
of such stylizations.
Let's train a style transfer model
together in the Create ML app.
I'll open the Create ML app...
and create a new document.
I'll select
the new style transfer template.
I'll name the project...
Dance Stylizer...
and fill in a short description.
The app has already selected
the Settings tab
and is ready for my training data
and model parameters.
I have this style image
that you saw earlier in the session.
I'll drag it into
the Training Style Image datawell.
I also have an image of people dancing.
I'll use that for validation
in order to visualize the model quality
throughout the training process.
Lastly,
I need a directory of content images
to learn the balance
between content and style.
I can either download a set
of a few hundred natural content images
directly from the app,
which works
in a wide variety of use cases,
or I can use my own folder
of content images.
I'll drag in a folder
of 600 natural content images.
I have the option to optimize
for image or video use cases.
I'll choose video, since I'm interested
in real-time style transfer apps.
And I'll train for 400 iterations.
I can use the style strength slider
to control the balance
between content and style.
And I can also use
the style density slider
to explore coarse or fine stylization.
The default parameters
work pretty well in most cases.
Now that I'm finished
configuring my training settings,
I'll click the Train button
in the toolbar.
The app processes
the style and content images
and immediately starts training the model.
Every five iterations,
a new model checkpoint
stylizes my validation image.
I can use this to visualize
the model stylization interactively
through the training process.
At any point, I can take a model snapshot
by clicking the Snapshot button
in the toolbar.
A snapshot is an ML model
that I can use later in an app.
My model snapshots are saved
under Model Sources.
Style loss and content loss graphs
help me understand
the balance between content and style.
The style loss decreases
as my model learns to adopt
the artistic qualities of my style image.
The model has completed training
400 iterations,
and it looks like the style loss
has converged.
I can train my model for more iterations
by clicking the Train More button
in the toolbar.
I'm happy with my model stylization
on the validation image,
so let's go to the Preview tab.
I can navigate to the Preview tab
to test out my model with some new data.
I'll drag in a test image.
I can toggle back and forth
between the stylized image
and the original content,
so that I can clearly visualize
the stylized effect.
I can compare the stylized result
from different model snapshots.
Since this model was optimized for video,
I'll try dragging in a test video.
Now this is really getting interesting.
At this point, I can choose to download,
share with a colleague,
or open the stylized result
in the QuickTime Player app.
In the Output tab, I can find out
more information about my model.
The size of the model is quite small,
under one megabyte,
which makes it really convenient
to bundle with my apps.
I can see the OS availability of my model
to ensure compatibility.
And by selecting "Predictions,"
I can find out even more about my model,
such as input and output layer names.
At this point,
I can get the model to use in my apps
by clicking the Get, Open in Xcode,
or Share button in the toolbar.
And that's how easy it is
to train a style transfer model.
As you just saw in the demo,
training a model takes only a few minutes.
Let's recap some important concepts
from the demo.
We learned about training checkpoints
and how to interact
with the model training process
in a new and exciting way.
We compared model snapshots
at different training iterations
and discovered a new ability
to extend training
to improve the quality of a model.
For more finite control,
be sure to check out the session
"Control Training in Create ML
with Swift."
To show you some amazing experiences
style transfer can bring to your apps,
I'd like to introduce Geppy.
Hello. I'm Geppy Parziale.
I'm going to show you how to combine
style transfer with ARKit.
I got several style transfer models
from David,
and I decided to create
a new virtual world with them.
Let me show you how.
ARKit captures the surrounding
real-world environment,
and each style transfer model allows me
to stylize the scene.
Cool.
Let me show how to do it.
Here, I'm using ARKit to capture
the surrounding real-world environment
and stylizing it with one of our models.
ARKit generates ARFrames.
Each ARFrame contains a CVPixelBuffer
that I rescale to the input size
expected by my style transfer model.
Then the rescaled CVPixelBuffer
is stylized using the Core ML model
and rendered on the screen using Metal.
I can use ARKit
to add a virtual object to the scene.
And here she is. Michelle.
Oh, and she's a very good dancer.
To add a 3D object to the scene,
I can define an ARAnchor
to specify its location in the real world.
The virtual object is then rendered
seamlessly in the scene using Metal.
But I can do more.
Here it is.
And it seems
she really likes her new look.
Here, I stylized off-line the virtual
object texture with a different style.
But I want to do even more.
Using the power of the Apple Neural Engine
and these optimized style transfer models,
I can run multiple styles concurrently
in real time.
Combined with ARKit person segmentation,
I'm executing two style transfer models:
one for the background environment
and one for the segmented person.
The stylized results
are blended together using Metal.
Pretty cool, huh?
These highly optimized style transfer
models generated with Create ML,
combined with ARKit
and the hardware acceleration
of the Apple Neural Engine and Metal,
allow you to unleash
all the power of iOS 14 for your apps.
I can't wait to see
all the cool experiences you will build
with style transfer models
trained with Create ML.
And now,
I'll hand it back to David for a recap.
Thanks, Geppy.
Your app looks really amazing.
Let's summarize.
With style transfer in Create ML,
you can train models
for both image and video use cases.
The video style transfer model
is extremely performant
and can be easily combined
with other Apple technologies,
such as ARKit.
The model size is small,
which makes it convenient
to bundle with your apps.
Reduced training time makes the training
experience interactive and fun.
You can train a model in a few minutes
and quickly iterate with different styles
and model parameters.
We can't wait to see what you come up with
using style transfer in Create ML.
Thank you.