[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Mohammed, a UIKit engineer.
Later, I'll be joined by my colleague Joey
from the iOS System UI team,
and this is
"How to Build for the iPadOS Pointer."
In 13.4, iPadOS added general
pointing device support to the iPad.
This is a brand-new input method for an OS
that has been primarily touch-based
since its inception.
Rather than just bring over the exact
interaction model that exists on a Mac,
we thought about what value
a pointer can add to iPadOS
and how it can coexist
with a touch-based interface.
The result is a system
built on a fluid adaptive pointer
that morphs into controls when
hovering over them to adapt its accuracy
and provide a clear indication
that you're about to interact with them.
In other contexts, the pointer changes
its shape and motion characteristics
to provide contextual hints.
When hovering over text, for example,
the pointer changes into a beam
and snaps to lines
to make interacting with text easier.
In this video,
we'll discuss the strategy we followed
to update iPadOS for pointer
and how you can use the same strategy
when updating your app.
In the course of the discussion,
we'll talk about
the pointer customization APIs
introduced in iOS 13.4,
and we'll talk about some
of the best practices to keep in mind
while updating your app.
We'll also touch
on some of the basic design principles
behind the pointer UI.
For a more detailed discussion
of these principles
and some of the thought processes
behind the pointer design,
check out the session
on "Design for the iPadOS Pointer."
When you use an iPad
with a pointing device connected,
you'll notice that a lot of things work
with the pointer automatically
without any additional adoption from apps.
This is because a lot of system components
have pointer support built in.
Controls like UIBarButtonItem,
UISegmentedControl
and UIMenuController, to name a few,
have built-in pointer effects
and behaviors.
Scroll views respond to scrolling
with two fingers
as well as mouse wheels
and pinching to zoom on the trackpad.
And in addition
to these scroll view basics,
collection and table view now support
two-finger panning for swipe actions.
UITextView and other components
that use UITextInteraction
support a suite of new
quick text selection and editing gestures
that should be familiar
to anyone who's used a Mac.
UIDragInteraction now allows you
to drag quickly via a click-and-drag
instead of requiring a long press
as it does with touch.
And UIContextMenuInteraction
lets you invoke its menu
in a new, compact appearance
via a secondary click.
So, how do we go about updating an app
for pointer?
We found that it's best
to take a top-down approach.
Start with the higher-level APIs.
They'll offer you
the most polished experience
with tuned behaviors and visuals
that are consistent with similar UI
in the rest of the system.
There are a number of pointer-related APIs
available to you
at different levels of the stack.
Many controls
have built-in pointer effects.
Some,
like bar buttons and segmented controls,
have their effects enabled by default,
while others, like UIButton,
offer API that allows you to enable
and customize their effects.
With UIPointerInteraction,
you can make your custom UI react to
and interact with the pointer
in a way that feels consistent
with the rest of the system.
Using the interaction,
you can choose from one of a collection
of system-vended effects
to apply to your views.
Or you can change the pointer's shape
within an area of your app.
UIHoverGestureRecognizer lets you respond
to the pointer's motion more directly.
This is great for any custom behavior
that doesn't involve applying
hover or highlight effects
or modifying the pointer's appearance.
For more details on this gesture
and other pointer-related additions
to gestures and events,
check out the session
on handling trackpad and mouse input.
When updating your app,
you want to aim for an experience
that makes it feel consistent
with the rest of the OS.
When deciding
where to add pointer support,
take your cues from the Human
Interface Guidelines and built-in apps.
To that end, a good starting point
is ensuring that controls in your app's
chrome have the appropriate effects.
By "chrome," we mean the application's
top and bottom bars,
so start with any bar buttons in the app.
UIBarButtonItems created using
the system item, image or title APIs
get appropriate pointer effects
automatically.
If you're using the custom view API,
you'll have to implement
the pointer behavior yourself,
either using the view's convenience API,
if it has one,
or by installing a pointer interaction
and managing the effect yourself.
UIButtons that have been placed in bars
via the custom view API
have their built-in interactions enabled
by default
and are given an effect that the system
has deemed appropriate
for that button in its containing bar.
You'll be able to tweak this effect
using UIButton's convenience APIs.
To make this really easy, UIButton
has a two-stage convenience API.
To enable the automatic effect,
simply set the button's isPointer-
InteractionEnabled property to "true."
After enabling the effect,
you may customize it
using the button's pointerStyleProvider.
In this closure, the system offers you
a proposed effect and shape
that have been determined
based on the appearance,
size and contents of the button.
Here, you can customize either of these
or replace them entirely
and construct a new style.
Before we look at some examples,
let's take a brief detour
and talk about pointer styles.
All APIs that modify
the appearance of the pointer
use UIPointerStyle
to describe the modifications they apply.
Styles fit into two categories.
The first is what we call
a content effect.
Content effects usually cause the pointer
to morph into a view in the app
and apply some visual treatment to it.
A common example of this
is the highlight effect
applied to bar buttons
where the pointer morphs
into a rounded rectangle,
slides under the button
and applies
a subtle parallax effect to it.
This style consists of a UIPointerEffect
which describes the visual treatment
applied to the view...
and a UIPointerShape
which describes the shape
to which the pointer will change.
To specify this effect,
we construct a UIPointerStyle
with the highlight effect
and roundedRect as the pointer shape.
The second category
is shape customizations,
which are expressed via a UIPointerShape
and a UIAxis mask.
When applied,
the pointer morphs into the shape
and is constrained along the specified
axes within the current region.
A good example of this
is the pointer behavior in text views
where we use a verticalBeam as the shape
and specify "vertical"
as the constrainedAxes
to make the pointer feel as if it's on
a horizontal rail along the line of text.
So, with that basic overview of
the control APIs and the pointer styles,
I'm going to hand it over to Joey
to demo how they can be applied
to an existing app.
Joey?
Thanks, Mohammed.
Today we're going to take a look
at an app that I've been working on
called Quilt Simulator.
I'm not much of a quilter myself,
but I've been learning about quilting
as I built this app.
Let me build and run
to see what we've got so far.
The first thing we want to take a look at
is this button in the lower right corner.
It toggles a straight-line guide mode
on and off
to make stitching in a straight line
easier.
You can see that it uses the highlight
effect, but it doesn't seem right.
The effect isn't the right size.
Let's switch back to Xcode
and see what we can do to improve it.
Here we can see
that the pointer interaction
has already been enabled for the button
which gives up the default effect.
We can add a pointerStyleProvider for
this ruler button to improve the shape.
First we create a rect
that is outset from the button's bounds
by a suitable amount...
then convert that rect
to the coordinate space
of the target of the preview
of the proposed effect.
And finally, return a style
that uses the proposed effect
but with an improved pointer shape
based on that rect.
Let's take a look at the change.
Much better. This button looks right
and feels more comfortable.
Next, let's turn our attention
to the thread selector button
in the upper right corner.
This button changes color
with the currently selected thread color.
I already customized this bar button
to use the lift effect
because it has an intrinsic shape.
You can see here
it doesn't look quite right.
When the pointer approaches the button,
we see a diffuse blur under the button.
This is distracting and incorrect.
Let's switch back to Xcode
to address this problem.
Since it is a UIBarButtonItem,
it already gets an effect by default.
Again, we modify the pointerStyleProvider,
this time to change the default effect
to a lift effect.
This implementation isn't correct though,
so let's fix it with the correct shape.
In this updated implementation,
we create a new UITargetedPreview
that's suitable to be used
with the lift effect.
It's created with the view, target
as well as preview parameters
which we create above.
The parameter's shadowPath property
is set to be the path
which matches the outline of the button.
Finally,
the closure returns a pointer style
using a lift effect
created with this preview
and a pointer shape
that matches the button.
And now back to the iPad
to see the improvement.
Now things are looking good.
That spool of thread just comes alive
as we approach it with the pointer.
Mohammed, back to you.
Thanks, Joey.
Now that we've seen
how to enhance controls,
let's talk about custom UI.
When considering
adding pointer behaviors to custom UI,
focus on areas where you think
they'll add utility and unique value.
Our Quilt Simulator app
has this large area in the middle.
You click on it once to begin a stitch,
and then you click again
in a different location to complete it.
By implementing
some custom pointer behaviors,
we can do some things
to improve the experience.
Let's add two enhancements.
First, let's change the pointer's shape
when hovering over the quilt area
to make it clear that clicking
in a location starts a stitch.
And let's add a guided mode
for beginner quilters
where the pointer is constrained
along the vertical axis
to make it easier
to make perfectly horizontal stitches.
Since this is an entirely custom view,
we'll use UIPointerInteraction directly
to achieve our goals.
As with other UI interactions, we create
an instance of UIPointerInteraction
and attach it to the view.
Unlike others, however,
this interaction's delegate is optional.
As we did with the controls in our app,
we'll be using UIPointerStyles
to specify the effects or shape changes
we'd like to apply to the pointer.
Since we want fine-grained control
over where the styles are active,
we'll also be defining
custom UIPointerRegions
to indicate to the interaction
where to apply the styles we provide.
By default, the interaction uses a region
that covers the entire view.
If the delegate doesn't provide
any styles,
the interaction applies the automatic
pointer effect to the entire view.
This is really convenient in simple cases
where we want to apply an effect to a view
and be done with it.
But our scenario's a bit more specialized.
Since we want to define behavior
within specific subregions of our view,
we're going to implement
UIPointerInteractionDelegate's
regionFor request method.
This method is called
to request new regions
as the pointer moves
within the interaction's view.
For our implementation,
we'll provide it with regions
that correspond to our guides.
As soon as the pointer enters a region,
the interaction calls
its delegate's styleForRegion method
to request a style,
so we'll need to implement the method
and return a shape customization style
that provides this crosshair shape.
Now I'm gonna hand it back to Joey
to see what this looks like in practice.
Thanks again, Mohammed.
Let's take another look at Quilt Simulator
to see how we can improve it.
Once the quilter has selected a thread
color, it's time to start quilting,
which is easily done
by clicking for each of the stitches
on the patchwork area.
First I'll select some yellow thread.
I can zoom in with two fingers, leveraging
the capabilities of UIScrollView...
and I'll make a few stitches here
to get started.
This is a great opportunity
to take advantage
of the laser precision
the pointer is capable of
by specifying a custom pointer shape
and assist the user with custom regions.
The first thing we want to do is add the
custom pointer interaction to the view.
This creates a new UIPointerInteraction
with "self" as the delegate
and adds it to the quilt view.
I already implemented
the styleForRegion delegate method.
The first line creates
a UIPointerShape object
with a custom Bezier path
we get from helper method.
The second creates and returns
a UIPointerStyle
that uses the pointer shape.
Let's see what it looks like.
Much better. This feels more natural
with such fine thread.
Let's return to the straight-line guide
I mentioned earlier.
If I turn it on
by clicking the ruler button...
then make a few stitches...
it's plain to see how much easier it is
to produce excellent results.
This feels a little disorienting though.
The pointer is moving around freely,
but the stitches are showing up
only on the grid lines.
Let's see what we can do about that.
We can modify
our delegate method implementations
to restrict pointer movement vertically
so the pointer is constrained
to each of the rows.
First, I'll add
a regionFor request implementation
to supply different regions per guideline.
If we're using StraightLineStitch mode,
then provide a separate region that's
the height of one of our grid lines.
Otherwise, return the default region.
Next, we'll constrain the pointer's
movement on the vertical axis.
If we're using the guide,
return the crosshair with
the constrainedAxes set to "vertical."
Otherwise, the same as before.
As you can see, we've really enhanced
the app for stitching straight lines.
As I toss the pointer,
it lands on horizontal guidelines,
and the cursor is almost magnetically
attracted to where it's supposed to be.
And that's it for the demo.
Back to you, Mohammed.
Thanks again, Joey. That looks great.
Now let's talk
about a few extra steps you can take
to tailor the pointer experience
to your app.
There are a few little things you can do
to really polish
the pointer experience in your app.
One such enhancement is providing
expanded padding around views
to amplify the pointer's magnetism
and make it easier to interact
with important elements in your UI.
As you can see here,
the pointer snaps to this button
well before it reaches its edge.
This is done by providing a pointer region
that extends the pointer style's
effective area.
It's important to note
that any regions you provide
must be contained within a hit-testable
area of the interaction's view.
If you provide a region
larger than the view,
you must also ensure
that this area hit-tests to the view
by overriding its hit-test method.
By tuning pointer regions,
we can control exactly when and how
the pointer transitions between effects.
In this example from the Reminders app,
we can see that even though
these views are visually separate,
the pointer transitions between them
seamlessly
without dropping back to the system shape
in the gaps.
This was achieved
by providing the interaction
with contiguous pointer regions.
When coordinating multiple pointer regions
or styles,
it often makes sense
to take your interaction
up to a higher level in the view hierarchy
where you have a more complete picture
of the UI and can reason more globally.
In this example, the interaction
is attached to the entire view,
and its delegate provides regions
for the individual subviews.
Another great thing you can do
is coordinate additional animations
with the pointer interaction's animation.
This is a great way
to show useful information
or hide extraneous chrome
to reduce clutter during the effect.
Here we see how UISegmentedControl
hides its separator
as the pointer shifts between segments
for a cleaner, less cluttered look.
To coordinate animations,
just implement
UIPointerInteractionDelegates willEnter
and willExitRegion methods
and attach animations
to the provided animator object.
In this example,
we'll fade out a separatorView
when the pointer enters the region,
and fade it back in when it exits.
For more guidelines and polish tips,
check out the Human Interface Guidelines
and developer documentation.
Also, please check out the sample
related to this video
as it has some great examples
for you to try out.
Take these simple guidelines to heart
and build iPad apps
with first-class pointer experiences.
Prefer using higher-level APIs
for a more native look and feel.
Add pointer effects
to controls and custom UI
to make them feel responsive.
And finally, take some small steps
to polish your implementation
and infuse your UI
with surprise and delight.
Thank you for watching.
I can't wait to use all the amazing
pointer-capable apps
you're going to build.
[chimes]