Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Loïc Sander.
I'm a type designer
on the Apple Design Team.
In this session, with my colleague Jiang,
we'll introduce you to the details
that matter for great UI Typography
and the tools that will allow you
to achieve that for your app.
Overall, all the topics we'll cover
are really about understanding
the dynamic behavior of text
on our platforms.
So first, I'll talk about about fonts
and their aspects
that are relevant to UI design.
Then Jiang will show you
around useful APIs
and best practices when dealing
with typographic styles and layout.
For most people,
dealing with type is
as simple as picking a font
and choosing a point size,
and it's really how it should be.
But with our first topic,
I'd like to show you
how changing the size of text
actually has many subtle consequences.
Learning about optical sizes is key
to a better understanding of legibility,
which is something
you should always try to care for.
Right after optical sizes,
I'll talk a bit about variable fonts.
This is a format that's letting us refine
the behavior of text on our platforms
and can improve the typography
of your apps too.
Then I'll get into a topic
that affects UI Design directly:
tracking and leading.
They're essential parts of text layout,
so it's definitely worth taking time
to become more familiar with them.
Last but not least, Jiang will delve into
Text styles and Dynamic Type.
Two of our core typographic tools
to achieve great UI design.
It'll be a refresher,
since some of those APIs are not new,
but we do also have
some updates on the topic.
So let's get started.
To describe what optical sizes are,
I'd like to go back a few years
when our main system font, San Francisco,
was first designed.
Our team put a lot of effort
in making sure that SF
would look great at any point size.
And we achieved that
by introducing two variants
that you're probably familiar with.
We designed SF Text for small sizes
below 20 points
and SF Display for 20 points and above.
These variants
are what we call optical sizes.
They allow us to better control
the details that affect legibility.
For instance, the space between letters
in SF Text and Display
is adapted to the fact that
one design will be used small
and other one large.
The vertical proportions between
the two designs also differ slightly,
so that SF Text can appear
a little bit bigger
at the same point size,
and therefore being more legible
when used small.
When we introduced this design,
it felt like a small revolution,
but there's something amusing I find
about the word "revolution."
We usually assume
it means forward motion or progress,
when essentially
it means "going back to the start."
Because, you see,
optical sizes have been a thing
ever since typography was invented,
and remained a printing process
involving physical objects
that barely changed for centuries.
It is true that digital technology gave us
a lot more flexibility in handling text,
but in one way, it made typography
a bit more crude than it used to be.
So to make my point,
I'd like to show you optical sizes
in their natural habitat.
As a type and history nerd,
I happen to have this old book
from the 18th century at home.
This is what we call a type specimen.
It contains samples of typography
at various sizes,
of which I want to show you two examples.
In these pages, we have
the same design at a different size,
which is to say, two different fonts,
a bit like SF Text and Display.
They're about eight and 42 points
in today's printing units.
Now I'd like you to picture that
for each letter you see here,
there was a metallic stamp
of the exact same size
that was made by hand.
These so-called stamps
were designed through a process
that involved cutting letterforms
on punches of steel.
And these punches of steel were then used
at the start of the molding process,
that resulted in a sort,
which is what
these metallic stamps are actually called.
Looking at the details
of these letterforms
reveals how much this manual process
was influenced by physical scale.
The eight-point letter looks rough
because of its smaller dimension,
and that says something
about optical sizes:
they're entangled with resolution.
Which, for people cutting punches,
meant designing against the challenges
of printing with metal and ink
on paper fibers,
while for us,
it means dealing with the challenges
of vector graphics being rasterized
on a pixel grid.
But regardless of the kind
of output you design for,
the changes in optical sizes are meant
to balance legibility and detail.
And I say this
as if they were independent,
but legibility is defined by the details.
As with SF Text and Display,
the key detail here
is the space between letters.
When type becomes smaller,
letters tend to need more
space between them,
so that they eye can
more easily tell them apart.
But there are more meaningful details
in the letterforms themselves, of course,
like the thinner parts of the letters
that sometimes need to become sturdier,
as the letters become smaller.
Then, some details might strike you
as accidents,
like the position of the dot
on the letter "i," for instance.
But that's intentionally done to make sure
an "i" won't be confused
with an "l" at small sizes.
Because the smaller a gap gets,
the easier it is to fill,
be it with ink or pixels.
So since relative size is relevant here,
let's observe our two initial words
at their intended scale ratio.
The difference between the two designs
now feels much less pronounced,
which is the purpose of optical sizes,
they balance legibility
with aesthetic qualities
to make the design feel comfortable
and consistent across scales.
And for people making font centuries ago,
adapting a design to its scale
was a fairly direct process,
since they always worked at actual size.
But on the other hand,
digital type design has been faced
with an unfortunate challenge.
Because you can scale
vector graphics infinitely,
virtually, all digital fonts only contain
a single drawing for each glyph.
So type designers have to pick
an ideal size to design for.
And that means that most fonts you use
were really meant to perform best
around a certain size.
Of course,
type designers can always decide
to create multiple fonts
adapted to multiple sizes,
but it's not a decision we take lightly,
because it's a lot more work,
and more importantly,
it becomes a font family
that's less convenient to use.
So when SF was initially designed,
we considered that very carefully,
and we eventually decided on having
optical sizes but just two of them.
For us, this decision
was a bit easier to make,
because the OS could switch
between designs automatically.
Then we embraced the need
to teach everyone about the existence
of SF Text and SF Display.
And for years now, that's pretty much been
the state of the art on our platforms,
but we kept wishing
we could refine this behavior more.
After all, wouldn't it be great
if a single font would automatically adapt
to each size you picked
without you having to switch
between Text and Display?
Well, that's exactly what became possible
a few years ago.
Variable fonts were introduced in 2016,
as an evolution
of the OpenType specification.
The spec was updated in response
to the increased popularity of web fonts,
and the fact that this technology
was really testing the limits
of existing font formats.
The format fundamentally changes
the way glyphs are stored in a font.
A glyph is no longer limited
to being a single static drawing,
it can also describe
the way each point moves
to produce a related but different glyph.
Each of these motions, or deltas,
are tied to design axes
that let software control their behavior.
Among these axes, there is one
that is of particular interest to us,
because it is dedicated
to the implementation of optical sizes.
This has allowed us to update SF Pro
and refine our existing optical sizes,
but this new dynamic behavior
really shows its potential
with our system serif, New York,
where the different adaptations to size
are much more noticeable.
Thanks to variable optical sizes,
we're now able to design typefaces
that can adapt to scale perfectly.
And coming full circle, we're recovering
what was good about physical type.
This is why, this year,
we're starting to move away
from optical sizes as separate fonts.
And it's not just optical sizes that are
now merged together but weights too.
This means that from now on,
most of our system fonts will be
downloadable as single variable fonts.
This being said,
we'll still publish Text and Display fonts
this year to ease the transition.
In design tools, you should expect
to find new controls for variable fonts.
Mostly in the form of sliders
that will expose a font's public axes.
But note that
they are an optional control.
You can still use that font the usual way
through its predefined instances.
In fact, when you're working
with our system fonts,
it's usually best
to keep to these predefined instances.
If the variable font you're using
supports optical sizes,
you can look for a dedicated slider
that will cover
a specific range of point sizes.
In principle, design apps should take care
of keeping the value of that slider
in sync with the point size you're using.
But it's not always the case,
and depending on the app,
changing the point size
may not automatically update the control.
So if you notice the point size you use
doesn't match the value on the slider,
then you need to set the slider yourself.
And it's totally okay
if the point size you're using
is out of range of the slider.
Just set the slider
at the closest value you can.
If you're using a design tool
on a previous OS,
it is possible that variable fonts
won't work as expected.
In that case, it is safer to revert
using the separate optical sizes
we still provide,
like SF Text and Display.
In code,
this behavior is entirely automatic.
We take care of keeping the optical size
and point size values in sync.
This applies to our system fonts,
of course,
but also to any custom
variable font you might use,
as long as it has an optical size axis.
So after catching up
with the latest developments
in size-specific typography,
I'd like to touch on two fundamentals
of UI text layout:
tracking and leading.
Tracking is an essential part of how
we achieve great size-specific typography.
I've just discussed optical sizes
at length,
but there is one thing I didn't mention,
and that's the fact
that optical sizes work better
when you pair them with tracking.
But first, what do I mean by tracking?
Well, let's start by looking
at the glyphs of a font first.
They already incorporate
a certain amount of space in them.
And that space
is what we call "side bearings."
It is designed as the glyphs are drawn
and defines the default spacing of text.
But as I pointed out earlier,
text requires letter-spacing to vary
so it can always look good
at any point size.
And when you do that,
and compensate that initial space,
that's what we call "tracking."
It is somewhat synonymous
with letter-spacing, as in CSS,
but tracking specifically
refers to the action of adding space
between glyphs in text layout.
Now, I'm sure some of you were puzzled
by what I just said,
and thought,
"Wait, I thought this was kerning."
The confusion is common, but tracking
and kerning are different things.
Kerning is a micro-correction of spacing
that is only applied
between certain pairs.
Kerning is also created by type designers,
and the vast majority of times,
you shouldn't need to modify it at all.
But back to tracking,
let me show you how and why
we use it with SF.
Even when you're designing fonts
with size-specific spacing
like we did for SF Texts and Display,
it's still good to use tracking
if you want to achieve fine-tuned results.
With no tracking,
the difference in native spacing
between SF Text and Display
would have been an issue when we switched
from one font to the other at 20 points.
Notice how the last blue
and first orange lines
are almost the same length,
in spite of their difference
in point size.
That's because of
their default spacing being different,
and that abrupt change is the reason
why we use tracking
with our optical sizes.
It really is an essential part
of the behavior of system fonts
and the reason
why we publish tracking tables
as part of the Apple Design Resources.
Because if you want to accurately
reproduce a system font's behavior,
you need to know how much tracking
to apply for each point size.
This year, with SF Pro
becoming a variable font,
there is no hard break
around 20 points anymore
and the design now transitions from Text
to Display between 17 and 28 points.
Because of that underlying change
in behavior,
we've had to update the tracking tables.
So note that when you're using
the new SF Pro in your design comps,
you'll need to apply
a new set of tracking values
between 17 and 28 points.
But while we're looking
at tracking curves,
there's one last thing
I'd like to point out.
A font can actually contain
multiple tracking tables,
and we've used that to add tracking values
that can help with the tightening
of strings, for instance.
So say you were in that tricky situation
with a truncated string.
You might reach
for this very common solution
using the kerning API,
but as I pointed out earlier,
using kerning here is not ideal.
It would be better
to use the tracking API,
because it's semantically correct,
for one,
but more importantly, it allows the OS
to deactivate typographic features
that can clash with tracking,
such as ligatures.
Because if you're tracking out a word that
contains ligature, with a kerning API,
that ligature remains
and breaks the rhythm of the word.
On the other hand, with the tracking API,
we take of de-assembling
that ligature for you,
which makes that word spacing more even.
However, the best and preferred solution
to make a string fit
is to allow it
to be tightened automatically.
And that's when we use
the tight tracking table.
With this API, the system
will try to make a string fit
within a range
that's reasonable for legibility,
because there is such a thing
as too much tracking.
And for those cases, it's just better
to let things truncate.
One last reason to use this API
is that it applies size-specific tracking,
which you would have to implement manually
if you applied tracking on your own.
Okay, so let me wrap up
on the topic of tracking
with a little announcement.
This year, we're enabling tracking
for third-party fonts.
This means that font vendors
can start adding tracking tables
to their own fonts.
That embedded tracking
will be applied on our platforms,
provided that the font
also contains a STAT table.
Such fonts can also be used
with their tracking data on older OSs
if you apply
the CTFont optical size attribute.
All right, so we've looked
at the space between glyphs,
but let's now consider another kind
of typographic space: between lines.
Here again, I'd like to propose
a vocabulary interlude
to disambiguate two terms.
So let's first talk about line height.
By default, line height
is the height of font's vertical limits.
You can also measure it
as the distance between to baselines,
but regardless of the approach,
the distance remains the same.
Now when the distance
between two lines increases,
the space between them
is referred to as "leading."
And if trivia helps your memory,
the name comes from the days of metal type
when this gap corresponded
to an actual piece of lead
between two lines of text.
One important thing to note here is that
when there is leading between lines,
the line height includes the leading.
So the two concepts are dependent.
If you change one, you change the other.
Most of the time,
you don't need to concern yourself
with leading or line height,
because we've already defined them
in most of our UI components.
But let me show you two examples
in which we do modify leading.
The Arabic script is a writing system
that can feature a lot
of ascending and descending parts.
And on a given line, they can encroach
on the visual space of surrounding lines,
So it's usually beneficial
to add some leading in such situations.
For that reason, we're made our platforms
apply more leading
for Arabic and other locales
that benefit from a taller line height.
On the other hand, it's sometimes helpful
to tighten the leading,
and make things more vertically compact.
On watchOS, for instance,
we apply tight leading in many places,
to maximize the amount of information
that can be shown onscreen.
Such modifications are done
through the use of text styles
that Jiang will be covering next.
These two examples provide
a good closing demonstration
of how we strive to design our APIs
and typographic features.
By using preexisting system APIs,
you'll benefit from
the design improvements
we're making each year.
As for the new ones,
we try and make it easy for you
to consider adopting them,
which allows your app
to become better with time.
This gives me the perfect opportunity now
to hand off to Jiang.
He will show you more about
the powerful font and text APIs
we have for you to use.
Thank you, Loïc.
Okay, after an excursion
into the finer details of typography,
let's talk about text styles
and Dynamic Type,
two important system tools
that will help you create beautiful
and consistent typography in your apps.
Text styles are at the core
of how we build great UIs at Apple.
They provide a framework that enables
flexible and consistent typography
with a clear hierarchy
and enough stylistic range
to cover most UI needs.
Text styles are
a set of predefined combinations
of a system font weight,
a point size value and a leading value.
They are built in a system
that provides typographic hierarchy
and makes it easier for you to achieve
clear and legible layouts in your apps.
First of all,
while the text styles defined
offer a wide range of font sizes
to represent the information hierarchy,
sometimes the sizes alone are not enough
to highlight more subtle differences.
Like here, the header of the year
and month in Calendar.
You can see they are using
a heavier weight
from the standard text styles.
Emphasized text styles like these
allow you to use the same text style sizes
with a different weight.
This is widely used by our system apps.
And of course, you have seen this,
the large title navigation bar in Mail.
This is using
the emphasized large title text style.
Now I'm going to show you
how to use it in your own app.
Let's say we have a label
using the title1 font.
I've found the title needs
a little bit more punch,
so why not use a bold weight?
Well, emphasized title1 is exactly that.
Here, instead of using the UIFont
preferredFont(withTextStyle:) API,
we are using the UIFontDescriptor API
to get the descriptor
with title1 text style,
and then we apply
a bold symbolic trait to it.
With the bold trait, you are getting
emphasized title1 text style,
which maps to SF Pro Bold.
You can apply bold symbolic trait
to any NSFont, UIFont or SwiftUI font
While the name of that symbolic trait
is "bold,"
but the actual weight of the variant
depends on the text style.
It can be medium, semibold, bold,
or heavy.
As we talked about earlier,
text styles come with line heights
that we found to be appropriate
for most of the cases.
However, sometimes you are working
with a more constrained space,
so saving spaces between lines
can increase the information density.
An example here is the Fitness app.
Or when presenting a large amount of text,
you might want to give the content
a bit more breathing room
to improve the reading experience,
like here with Maps.
In those cases, you can use the tight
and loose leading variants of text styles.
In iOS and macOS, tight leading
decreases the line height by two points,
while loose leading
increases the line spacing by two points.
In watchOS,
the adjustment is reduced to one point.
Now, in this case,
we have a long paragraph of text
like this,
and it is using the body text style.
For now it has 22-point line height,
and let's just say we want to experiment
and see how it would look like
with a tighter line height.
I think you're now getting the hang of it.
Once we apply
the tight leading symbolic trait,
the text will look like this.
There we go.
Now it has 20 points of line height.
But that does seem to be too tight
for such a long paragraph of text.
So, what about loose leading?
How would that look?
Now let's try the loose leading trait
to get 24 points of line height.
Okay, that does look much better.
So it is actually very similar
to what we just covered
with the emphasized variants.
Only this time,
we are using the tight leading
and loose leading symbolic traits.
And new in this year,
you can do leading adjustments
for text style fonts in SwiftUI as well.
Throughout the system,
we have used New York
and SF Pro Rounded in our apps,
like here with the Books
and Reminders app.
But it is worth noticing that they
don't just work as stand-alone typefaces,
they work really well
with our text styles too.
Now, let's say we want to build a label
just like Reminders.
Let's combine what we just learned
about emphasized text style.
We start with a text such as "Today,"
and using
emphasized large title text style.
For now it's using SF Pro Bold.
Let's try to apply rounded design
using the fontDescriptorwithDesign API.
You can see now the font has switched
to SF Pro Rounded.
So, we have introduced
a really flexible API
to allow you to apply these designs
to any system UI fonts.
For AppKit and UIKit,
the fontDescriptorwithDesign API
can be applied to any UI font.
For SwiftUI,
the API is a little bit different.
You should pass the design
when constructing a font to begin with,
instead of using a modifier
to convert an existing font.
When picking a text style with a design,
everything else besides the design
stays the same,
including font size, weight
and line height.
I know many of you work with web pages
or have web views embedded in your app.
A few years ago,
WebKit introduced
the -apple-system font family
so that you can use it
to use San Francisco font in CSS.
This has been widely adopted.
Now the -apple prefixed version
has a standard name: system-ui.
And earlier this year, we're bringing
a new set of CSS font family names,
like ui-rounded, ui-serif
and ui-monospace to Apple platforms.
I'm happy to announce that this year
text style is a fully supported API
in macOS.
We are introducing a new set of API
to AppKit for all Cocoa apps.
This AppKit API will support
a full range of text styles,
just like on iOS.
The font sizes are optimized
to match macOS control sizes.
Although there is no Dynamic Type support,
you do get all the other benefits
of text styles we have just covered.
Last year, we shared this chart
for Catalyst app text style sizes,
which is really iOS sizes scaled at 77%.
And this year, the Catalyst apps
with interfaces optimized for Mac,
you will get a new set
of text style sizes like this.
You see, they are pretty well aligned
so that your app should only require
minimal change to adapt.
If you pick
"Scale Interface to Match iPad,"
it will continue to follow
the iOS sizes at 77%.
But if you want the new behavior,
picking the "Optimize Interface for Mac"
option in Xcode will give you that.
As you may already be aware,
in iOS, there is another dimension
to text style: Dynamic Type.
The font you picked
will scale automatically
according to preferences.
Dynamic Type lets people control how large
or small text styles should be for them.
It makes text easier to read
for a lot of people,
so you really should consider
supporting Dynamic Type in your apps.
By using the system font APIs
and text styles together,
you are opted in to this behavior
automatically on iOS.
But you can also support Dynamic Type
when using custom fonts,
and I will cover how to do that
in this part of the talk.
All right. The chart we have just shown
is a lot to take in,
and one thing I would like you to notice
is that the different text styles
may have different scaling behaviors.
And here we can see how body,
title1 and footnote text styles
scale with Dynamic Type.
When you are working on
Dynamic Type support with custom fonts,
you should also pay attention to this.
As we know,
typography is critical for brand identity,
and many of you are building apps
that are using custom fonts
designed for your app and brand.
But you still want to support Dynamic Type
as that is critical for accessibility.
You want your app to react accordingly
when text size preferences change,
just like iOS system apps do.
How would you do that?
We have covered this in past talks,
but it still deserves a revisit
as it is such a common question
throughout the years.
Since iOS 11, we introduced
a new UIFontMetrics class
that captures the Dynamic Type capability
from text styles,
and lets you apply it
to any arbitrary font.
To use it, let's look at this example.
First, I start with a custom font as usual
with the standard UIFont API,
and then I can create a UIFontMetrics
from body text style.
With that bodyMetrics object,
the font generated by scaledFont API
will scale just like how body text scales
when text size preferences change.
And it is worth noticing
that you can also use it
to scale a constant value
for custom layout,
like here the spacing
between the two labels.
We have received great feedback
from our SwiftUI developers
since the release last year.
And this year in SwiftUI,
we are making it possible for you
to do the same font scaling as in UIKit.
To understand this,
let's start by having a piece of text
in our SwiftUI ContentView.
So far so good.
Everything scales accordingly
when text size preference changes.
Now let's say I want to use Avenir font,
medium weight, 34-point for this text.
I know how to do that,
and as you can see,
it is using the font we intended.
However, in iOS 13,
the problem is that once you start
using a custom font,
it stops supporting Dynamic Type.
In iOS 14, it will automatically scale,
but just to make sure it has
the correct scaling behavior as title,
I'm going to set the relativeTo parameter
so that it will scale relative
to title text style.
As you can see, the title text
is scaling automatically now.
Let's move on to add the body text.
Similar to how we add the title text,
we declare a paragraph of text
and assign it to text in a VStack.
And I don't even need to use
the relativeTo parameter,
since custom font will scale relative
to body text style by default
now in iOS 14.
Both the title and body text
are scaling automatically now,
but it looks like we can benefit
from some padding around the body text,
because the text is just too close
to the edges and to the title.
Let's add some padding.
We start with a fixed padding
of 20 points first.
Much better.
Now, wouldn't it be nice if the padding
can also scale
in relative to text size changes?
Here we can leverage
the new ScaledMetric property wrapper,
to define a padding with value "20"...
but it can also scale relative
to body text style.
Let's see if that did the trick.
You can see the padding around the text
are scaling in proportion to the text size
instead of a fixed size.
Okay, here's a recap
of what we've just shown.
The font(.custom API has
a new optional parameter, relativeTo,
to specify which text style
you want it to scale relative to.
If you skip that,
it will scale relative to body,
and this is a behavior change in iOS 14.
You can still create a custom font
that is fixed size
and doesn't scale at all
with the fixedSize parameter.
In addition to that,
you can also scale a constant
just like what UIFontMetrics does
with the ScaledMetric property wrapper.
Well, we have covered
a lot of ground today,
and here are some of the basic principles
I want to remind you.
We have offered a wide range
of carefully designed system fonts
in a variety of styles,
such as SF Pro, SF Pro Rounded,
SF Mono, and New York.
We encourage you to give them a try.
For good typography,
hierarchy is important,
and text style is a great tool
for building such hierarchy.
Even when working with custom fonts,
you should have plenty of options
to support Dynamic Type,
which is great for accessibility.
We've covered many important details
of typography,
such as tracking and leading.
You should only override
the default system behavior
in exceptional cases,
and let the system
do the right thing for you
for the rest of them.
If you have to work with custom tracking
in your UI,
remember that it should be size specific,
otherwise a tracking you provided
for small sizes
may not look good on large sizes.
I hope you now have a better understanding
of the behavior of text on our platforms
and the text and font APIs
at your disposal
to achieve great typography in your apps.
Thank you.