Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello everyone.
I'm Jiewen from the WebKit Team.
Today I'm going to talk about Face ID
and Touch ID for the Web.
This session is tailored
for Web developers
looking to add this cool new feature
to their websites.
Let's get started.
There's a user experience in
a few apps on my phone that I really like,
which is the experience of using
Face ID or Touch ID
for re-signing into an app.
Let me show you
with my favorite demo application, Shiny.
Shiny is an app
that you can use every day,
and it shows you
a picture of something nice.
The first time I sign in to Shiny,
I will need to enter
my user name and password,
and since I care deeply about security,
I have enabled
two-factor authentication for Shiny.
In this case, I need to wait
for an SMS second-factor code to continue.
And once I've submitted the SMS 2FA code,
I'm signed in,
and I can see this adorable dog.
iOS makes signing in a better process
with AutoFill,
but even then, there are several steps
and a lot of thinking for me to do.
Shiny has a policy
of wanting me to re-sign in
after being inactive for a few hours.
You will see a policy like that
in lots of high-security contexts,
like signing into a bank.
But this time, when I sign in,
rather than go through a password
and SMS 2FA flow,
instead I just Face ID, like that.
Boom. I'm signed in.
It is both much faster and more secure.
This session is about bringing
the same user experience to your website.
Here is a quick overview.
I click the "sign in" button,
Safari prompts me for confirmation,
then, boom, Face ID, I'm signed in.
Now, let's dive into
how to add this to your website.
Face ID and Touch ID on the Web
is powered by a standard
called Web Authentication.
I'll start by talking a little
about that standard,
then Apple's implementation
of what's called a platform authenticator.
Next, I'll cover the basics
of what it takes
to adopt this awesome new feature.
Finally,
end on some important best practices.
Now, let's talk about
the Web Authentication standard.
Web Authentication is a JavaScript API
to allow you, Web developers,
to use public key-based authentication
on the Web.
This API is built
on top of public key cryptography
and brings many unique features
along with it.
Let's start with some high-level concepts.
First, you need to get used to
this strange yet familiar concept
called relying party,
which essentially means your website.
Second, the API generates
and makes use of a JavaScript object
called public key credentials,
which contains
all the necessary information
to perform your authentication.
Third, all private keys are managed
by devices called authenticators
instead of the user's directory.
An authenticator could be a security key,
which you might have heard about,
or the iPhone we just saw.
Web browsers manage the interface for
users to interact with an authenticator
and bridge the responses
from the authenticator to the website.
Fourth, authenticators can, if necessary,
prove their properties cryptographically
via a process called attestation.
These concepts may be new to many of you,
but this session should explain
everything you need to know
to get started
using them on your websites.
Let's take a look
at why you want to do that.
First, Web Authentication provides
strong authentication
through public key cryptography,
which is much stronger than passwords
and can't be reused or breached.
But more importantly,
it is phishing-resistant.
Safari will only allow
public key credentials created by this API
to be used
within the website they were created,
and the credentials can never be exported
out from the authenticator
they were created as well.
This means that
once a public key credential
has been provisioned,
there is no way for a user to
accidentally divulge it to another party.
Cool, right? This is the overview
of Web Authentication standard.
I will talk about the actual API later.
Now let's talk about
some unique features Apple does
to enable Face ID and Touch ID
under the Web Authentication standard.
An authenticator like the iPhone
is called a platform authenticator,
because the authenticator is a feature
built into the platform.
There are two important properties
that Apple builds into the authenticator.
The first one, as we saw,
is the Face ID and Touch ID,
which is used to verify users' identity.
The second one is Secure Enclave,
which is a processor that manages
all the private keys
and guarantees
that they cannot leave the device.
By combining both, each sign-in performed
with the Face ID or Touch ID
is essentially
a multi-factor authentication.
The response the device sends back
to the websites encapsulates two factors:
something you have, the iPhone,
and something you are, the biometrics.
And the sign-in only takes a single tap.
This is amazing.
However, websites like a bank
could be regulated to enforce
multi-factor authentication.
Information stored in the response
might not be sufficient.
They want some extra proof
from the manufacturer
that the device really,
really preserves those nice properties.
You do this with an optional
security feature called attestation.
Attestation is basically a secure way
for you to ask a device manufacturer
that the device is real and really has
the capabilities it says it does.
This is great for the specific-use cases
like the one that I just mentioned.
However, it can be implemented
in a way to violate user privacy.
For example, a device can be instructed
to use a single,
unique attestation certificate.
Then the unique certificate
becomes an easy tracking vector
to link all of a user's attested accounts
across the Web.
Apple cares about users' privacy.
Therefore, Apple has built
its own attestation service.
It generates unique certificates
for every credential,
and therefore websites can no longer
use them to track users.
That is called
Apple Anonymous Attestation,
which is coming soon.
With this rich set of features,
Apple's platform authenticator
is truly amazing.
Now let's walk through
how to adopt it in your website.
There are three different methods
your website will need to use.
All of them are promise-based API.
First, you should check if
the current device supports this feature.
You can do this by calling
PublicKeyCredential.isUserVerifying-
PlatformAuthenticatorAvailable.
Then,
when getting a user set up to use it,
you will need to call
navigator.credentials.create
to create a PublicKeyCredential object
that contains
the necessary authentication information.
Finally,
when a user wants to sign in to your site,
call navigator.credentials.get,
which returns a credential object
that you can verify on your server
to authenticate the user.
These are the entry points
to the Web Authentication API.
Now let's take a look at how to use them
to get Face ID and Touch ID
on your website.
To do feature detection, it is super easy.
Just call PublicKeyCredential.isUser-
VerifyingPlatformAuthenticatorAvailable,
which will simply return a Boolean
to tell you whether or not
the feature can be used.
Now it's time to onboard the user.
To do that, you might need to
first let your users sign in
with their old-school password credential.
Then you could show a notification
to the user, saying,
"Hey, we got this cool new feature
to let you use Face ID or Touch ID
to bypass the user name and password
next time when you sign in.
Would you like to enable that?"
The notification could be a full Web page,
a banner or a floating pop-up,
depending on the style of your website.
In this Shiny website that I built,
I decided to use a full-page notification.
Here is the notification.
Most users at this point
will probably press "OK."
Then you should prepare your website
with the following script
to enable Touch ID
with Web Authentication API.
First things first, let's construct
the options to pass to the method.
It looks scary.
However, after I break it down for you,
you'll see that it's actually pretty easy.
First, you need to tell the browser
what website you are.
Then, some information about the user.
And then you get to specify
what crypto you want to use.
Now, good old-school challenge
for our beloved crypto.
And then tell the browser you want to use
the platform authenticator.
This is the key option here.
Finally, this is completely optional.
Since Shiny has
some special security requirements,
it decides to opt in for attestation.
You see? That's simple.
Now, you pass these options
to navigator.credentials.create,
and then Safari will handle the UI
and give you back a PublicKeyCredential.
It's important to call this method
within user-activated events, though.
Let's see a demo
of how everything comes together.
First, let me sign in to Shiny
with my primary credential.
Then I get the notification.
I mean, why not?
Safari will then show a confirmation UI.
Click "OK" and then Touch ID. I'm done.
So that's the full user
onboarding experience.
Beautiful. But we are just halfway done.
What you just saw
is the front-end user experience.
We still need to do something
in the back end to process the response.
Let's take a look
at an overview of the response.
To begin with, it contains an ID
that you should save to refer to
this particular credential in the future.
Second, it contains a response
that is for enrollment.
In that response, you'll get some metadata
that is generated by the browser
for you to validate.
Then it is the meat of the response:
an attestationObject
that contains the public key data
and attestation certificates.
If you didn't opt in for attestation,
you will instead get back a "none"
attestation statement as shown here.
So that's the overview of the response.
Depending on your server's configuration,
code could be very different.
However, here is a checklist
you should follow in this order.
First, validate all metadata: the client
data and the authenticator data.
Second, if you opt in to attestation,
you should validate
the attestation statement.
Third, save the credential ID
and the public key data,
which you will use for future sign-in.
Lastly, you can optionally set
a server-side cookie to indicate
Face ID or Touch ID is enabled for
this particular account on this device.
This will make the re-authentication
process a lot easier.
So that's all you need to do
for onboarding users.
Now let's move to sign in.
If you have saved a cookie
about the Touch ID-enabled account
during enrollment,
then now you could list it
as a fast path for sign-in.
To use Touch ID for your fast path,
you will need the following script.
This is a very similar formula,
like the enrollment, to do sign-in.
The must-have field here is the challenge,
just like any other public key crypto.
Then it is helpful for you to tell Safari
the exact credential
you are planning to use,
so that Safari can offer
the most optimized UI for the user.
Most importantly,
you need to specify the transports.
Now you pass these options
to navigator.credentials.get,
and then Safari will handle the UI
and give you back a PublicKeyCredential,
just like the enrollment.
Also, same as the enrollment,
it's important to call this method
within user-activated events.
Let's see a demo
of how everything comes together.
Let me click the "sign in" button.
Safari will then show a confirmation UI.
Click "continue" and then Touch ID.
I'm in.
So that's just how easy it is
to use Touch ID to sign in.
Now let's focus on the back end.
In the sign-in case,
the returned PublicKeyCredential
is slightly different.
The type of the response
is now AuthenticatorAssertionResponse.
The meat of the response here
is the signature.
Yes, the old-school signature you need
to verify for every public key crypto.
So that's the response.
The checklist here for sign-in
is much simpler than the enrollment part.
First, you need to validate that
the user ID is indeed one of your users,
and then check if the credential ID
is associated with that user ID.
Once you've done that,
you then validate all other metadata.
Finally, you verify the signature.
Then you can log the user in,
and you are done.
That is everything you need to do
to enable Face ID and Touch ID on the Web.
Let me recap those three things.
First, you need to detect
the existence of the feature.
Then you should show a notification
to ask users to enable the feature
right after the user has signed in
with traditional mechanisms.
And then you are ready to go with
Face ID or Touch ID for future sign-in.
Face ID and Touch ID for the Web
is available in Safari
as SFSafariViewController
and ASWebAuthenticationSession
in macOS, iPadOS and iOS.
Finally, some best practices.
The most important one
is to use this feature
as an alternative way to sign in,
not the only one.
Since the private key is tied to a device,
if this is the only way
to sign in to your website,
your users will be
forever locked out of their accounts
if they lose their devices.
Use feature detection instead of
user-agent strings to detect this feature.
Call navigator.credentials.create and .get
within user-activated events.
If you ever need to set a flag
to indicate if this feature is enabled
for an account on a device,
use a server-side, secure,
HttpOnly cookie,
which should give you
the longest-term storage.
Finally,
for websites that have already enabled
security keys with Web Authentication,
you should consider whether it makes sense
to present this feature
along with security keys to your users,
because the end-to-end user experiences
are quite different.
In summary, today I introduced
Face ID and Touch ID for the Web,
which provides
a frictionless user experience
and yet a strong
multi-factor authentication mechanism.
It can be easily integrated
into your website
to streamline
your user's sign-in experience
without having to change the way
you manage your user session state.
Please start testing this feature today
and file any potential bugs
on Feedback Assistant or bugs.webkit.org.
Thanks for watching.