Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. Welcome to WWDC.
My name is Eryk Vershen.
I'm an engineer on the streaming team.
This talk is about HLS Tools
and HLS Authoring.
In particular, it's about new stuff
we have for you this year.
There's three main topics to cover.
First of all, I want to tell you about
changes that we've made in HLS Tools.
Then I'll tell you about
how to use some of the tools
to make a Low-Latency HLS stream.
And last, I'll give you some advice
about creating master playlists.
Let's get started with the first topic.
Last year, the Low-Latency HLS Tools
were in a separate package.
Since Low-Latency HLS
is coming out of beta,
we've gone back
to a single tool distribution
that includes those tools.
When you're validating a stream
with Media Stream Validator,
the tool waits until it's completely done
to report most errors.
In the case of a live stream,
where you might run the validator
for half an hour or even an hour or more,
this can be a problem.
With the new immediate option,
the validator will report errors
as soon as it detects them.
The other part of validation
is HLS Report.
That used to be a Python script.
We've changed it into a compiled binary.
We did drop one old deprecated option,
but all the other functionality
is still there.
We've added support
for some new audio codecs.
While I'll mention a few things
in this talk,
you should watch our other talk,
Delivering a Better HLS Audio Experience,
for more details.
Let's move on to the Low-Latency Tools.
Instead of one very long talk
about Low-Latency HLS,
we've split it into several smaller talks
this year.
You should definitely watch
the overview talk,
Low-Latency HLS Updates.
And you may find it helpful to review
the talk about Low-Latency HLS
from last year's conference.
Let's look at the specific tools
for Low-Latency HLS.
We added TS recompressor.
As the name implies,
it can modify transport streams,
but it can also generate video and audio.
That's what we're going to use it for.
Media Stream Segmenter was modified
for Low-Latency HLS
to be able to produce partial segments
and their associated tags.
And we added two scripts that implement
what we call
the Delivery Directives Interface,
which is the interpretation and response
to some query parameters.
I'll talk a little more about those later.
Here's how the flow works.
Any particular variant
of your Low-Latency HLS stream
is going to use Media Stream Segmenter
to break up its input.
That's going to be a transport stream
coming out of TS recompressor via UDP.
The segmenter will produce
a media playlist and media segments.
And that playlist will point
at the media segments.
Now, the playlist
is going to be periodically updated
because it's a live playlist.
And the media segments are dynamic.
That is, we add segments over time
and delete them
when they're no longer needed.
Low-Latency HLS requires the server
to interpret some query parameters,
so we have an interface script
that handles that,
and it returns a modified playlist,
which points at the same media segments.
Since we have multiple variants,
we need a master playlist
to reference them,
which is just a static file that uses URLs
that activate the interface script,
rather than the raw media playlists.
Here's what the TS recompressor
command line looks like.
We tell it
we want to generate input for us,
and use the hardware encoder if possible.
Then we tell it to output three versions:
a preview at 500 Kbps,
a lower-quality video at 2 Mbps,
and a main output at 4 Mbps.
These are sent to the listed UDP ports.
Each output port needs to have
its own copy of Media Stream Segmenter.
For example, this one is processing
the low-quality output
from TS recompressor.
Now the first option,
part-target-duration-ms,
activates the generation
of partial segments.
The next three should be familiar:
target duration, how many parent segments
to have in the playlist,
and delete segments
after they are no longer needed.
"Date-time" is a new option that adds
an EXT-X-PROGRAM-DATE-TIME tag
to the playlist.
And then, of course, you have to tell it
where to put the output files.
As I said earlier, we need to implement
the Delivery Directives Interface.
The first form is a script
written in the Go language.
It creates its own HTTP server,
so you pass it a directory
to tell it where the segmenter output is,
and it serves up synthesized playlist
when certain URLs are requested.
The other form is a PHP script.
This uses your existing HTTP server.
In this case, you need one copy
of the script for each variant.
The Delivery Directives Interface requires
returning the EXT-X-RENDITION-REPORT tag,
which gives information
about the other variants.
To make that easier
for both of these scripts,
they expect that
all the variants are written
to sub-directories
of a single parent directory.
That way they can simply search
relative to the parent directory
to find the other variants.
Let's talk about the new audio codecs
and how you can use them.
Here are the codec tags.
USAC or xHE-AAC
is an MPEG-4 audio variant.
Apple Lossless has
a very straightforward CODECS string.
Please note that the CODECS attribute
for FLAC, that's not a typo.
It really does have
that odd case structure.
When you're building up a master playlist,
it can be a bit complicated.
First you need to choose
your video resolutions and codecs.
These are your basic variants.
Then you have some some set
of audio languages.
For example, English and Chinese.
You'll have some codecs,
say, AAC, FLAC, AC-3.
Maybe some of these are in stereo
and some in 5.1 sound, or both.
You'll want to make one audio group
for each codec/channel count pair.
Each group must have every language in it.
Then you replicate the variant entries
for each group, with some exceptions.
When you're making audio groups,
there are some things to remember.
First, you should always have
a stereo AAC group.
This is good fallback,
since it's something all devices can play.
If you have multichannel
in a lossless audio codec,
then we suggest you have
a multichannel AAC codec as well.
Lossless requires a high bit rate.
You want something available
that has a lower bit rate.
Remember, we don't want to switch
the number of channels.
If you're in multichannel,
we want to stay in multichannel.
Generally speaking,
we don't switch between audio codecs,
but there are two notable exceptions.
We will switch among the AAC variants:
AAC-LC, HE-AAC, HE-AACv2,
and USAC or xHE-AAC.
And we will switch between
lossless codecs and AAC codecs.
As I said earlier,
once you have your audio groups,
you replicate the variant entries
for each group, with some exceptions.
If the codecs are switchable between,
like the AAC codecs,
then you can spread the groups
across the variants
using the low audio bit rate group
with the low video bit rates
and the high audio bit rate group
with the high video.
But, if the codecs are not switchable,
like AC-3 and lossless,
then you want them to be associated
with every variant.
Remember, this doesn't create
new variant playlists,
it just creates new entries
in the master playlist,
which associate a video playlist
with an audio group.
Now, some of you may have hit a problem
where the variants you want to favor
aren't being chosen.
The default behavior
is to choose the highest bit rate
among what's currently playable.
With USAC and with Dolby Digital Plus,
this can cause an inversion
where the chosen variant
is not what you would prefer.
To get around this,
we've added the SCORE attribute.
This is on variants and I-Frame variants.
The value is a floating-point number.
The feature is already in
so you can try it without upgrading.
It allows you to set an ordering
on all the variants.
You have to put it on all the variants.
If you want to set an order,
it has to be complete,
otherwise we'll have situations
where we wouldn't be able to choose.
The way it works is
we'll do all our usual filtering
to get down to a set of variants,
any of which could be played.
At that point, we use SCORE to decide
and the highest SCORE wins.
Let's see an example.
This is a very cut-down master playlist.
I've left out a lot
so it would fit on one slide,
and I've fiddled with the spacing.
We have two audio groups here.
One is USAC, the other is HE-AAC.
They have the same set of languages.
We have two video variants,
a 720p and a 1080p,
which makes for
four video variant entries.
Even though these are compatible audio,
I've put all the possible entries in.
These are in order by BANDWIDTH.
So notice, we would end up choosing
the HE-AAC variants to play.
This is not what we want,
since the USAC is going to sound better.
We really want to choose the HE-AAC
only if we are on some device
that can't play the USAC.
We fix this with the SCORE attribute.
We give the USAC variants higher scores,
so they are preferred.
This allows the USAC to function
like a mutually exclusive codec.
Let's wrap up.
Remember, we've made changes to the tools.
And you want to take a look
at how you're using audio groups.
So download the latest version
of the tools.
Read the Read Me files and manual pages
and explore what you can do.
That's all. Thanks for watching.