Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name is Phil Azar.
And I'm a software engineer
on the Power and Performance Tools team.
Today I'm delighted
to be able to share with you
what's new in MetricKit on iOS 14.
Your apps are a pivotal part
of the software experience,
and your apps are being used
more than ever before.
When your app is great for battery life
and has good performance,
it delights your users
and contributes to the overall health
of the software experience.
Our team is committed
to providing you powerful tools
to improve the battery life and
performance footprint of your application.
Last year we introduced a number
of these tools to help you do this,
including MetricKit,
an on-device framework for collecting
battery life and performance metrics.
Today I'm excited to share with you what's
coming in the next version of MetricKit.
We'll start with a quick recap
on how to use MetricKit.
Then, we'll move into a discussion of
some powerful new metrics and diagnostics,
followed by a deep dive
into those new interfaces.
Then, we'll wrap up with a quick summary.
Let's get started with some review
on how to use MetricKit today.
MetricKit as a framework
was designed from the ground up
to provide you data
in phases of the development cycle
where you typically do not have
direct access
to the users
or devices that are running your app.
These phases include
during an external beta like TestFlight
or once you've shipped to the App Store.
This means, for you as a developer,
MetricKit is a powerful tool
when leveraged in these phases,
as it provides you real access
to performance data about your application
from a large audience
and can help you find trends and patterns
in performance regressions.
In order to use MetricKit,
you need to follow three easy steps.
The first is to link and import
the MetricKit framework into your code.
The second step
is to instantiate a shared instance
of what we call the MetricManager,
which is a class that serves as
your point of contact with the framework.
Finally, you need to implement
a provided subscriber delegate protocol
to start receiving
metrics from the framework.
Here's an example
of the previous steps in code.
For this example, we've implemented
a custom class called MySubscriber
to help keep your code clean.
After we link the MetricKit framework,
we'll conform this new class
to our subscriber protocol,
instantiate an instance
of our shared MetricManager
and add a reference
to the new custom class to the manager.
We recommend you remove that reference
to the custom class on deinitialization.
Once you've done that,
the final step is to implement
the didReceive protocol method.
This will allow you
to receive metric payloads.
Let's review how the system aggregates
and deliver these payloads
to your application through MetricKit.
Over the course of the day,
the operating system is passively
aggregating performance data for your app
as it is used.
This data is anonymized
and designed to protect user privacy.
At the end of the day, that data
is bundled into a 24-hour payload
which we know as the MetricKit payload.
Metric payloads are strongly typed
by the MetricKit interface.
Let's take a look into what sorts of data
that payload contains.
MetricKit payloads
contain a wide variety of data,
including launch times,
CPU time, memory and more.
Here, we've taken a MetricKit payload and
converted it to a human-readable format.
This makes it easier for us to see
that the data is split up
into three types of aggregation--
cumulative, averaged and bucketized data.
Post-process,
this data is extremely useful
in identifying performance regressions
build-to-build in your application
and can be used
in conjunction with local context
to tackle challenging problems.
In some areas, however,
the metrics we have today
may not be enough
to fully characterize a regression.
Let's take a look
at a common example of this--
our launch performance data.
We see here
that the number of cold launches,
i.e. when our app is being launched
from scratch with no resources in memory,
far exceeds the number of resumes.
In a typically well-performing app,
we would expect our resumes to be
much more prevalent than our launches.
Something seems to be amiss here.
Another common case
is our cumulative CPU time.
Notice how
our cumulative CPU time is far smaller
than our cumulative foreground time.
This might seem like a good thing,
but it isn't clear
if this level of work is indicative
of a performance regression or improvement
because the CPU time
is bound by clock frequency.
As developers, our first instinct might be
to quantify this more precisely.
And as it stands right now,
that's not a straightforward problem.
There's a clear area for growth here.
We need more details
to dig deeper into these problems.
This year, with MetricKit 2.0,
we're going to be providing you
some new metrics
that we think will help you dig deeper
into these common problem cases.
Our team has worked hard
to expand a subset of metrics
to provide further clarity
into application workload,
performance and stability.
These include CPU instructions,
scroll hitches and application exits.
Let's start by reviewing
CPU instructions first.
CPU instructions in MetricKit are
a new addition to the MXCPUMetric class.
This metric summarizes
daily cumulative instructions
retired by your application.
CPU instructions are an absolute metric
for the work
that your application does on the CPU.
It is both hardware
and frequency independent.
This is going to enable you
to more precisely quantify
the total workload of your application.
Next up, let's talk about scroll hitches.
Scroll hitches are a new metric
we're providing you this year
to help you give insights into
your application's graphical performance.
A scroll hitch is when
a rendered frame does not end up on screen
at its expected time during scrolling.
This usually causes frames to be dropped,
causing a user-perceptible interruption
of animation smoothness.
In MetricKit,
we'll be providing you a ratio
of time that your application spends
hitching to the time spent scrolling
with UIScrollViews.
To dive deeper into
the technical details of hitches,
I encourage you to watch our talk
this year covering scroll hitches
and how to measure them
using XCTest metrics.
Last but not least,
we have application exit reasons.
This year, we're providing metrics
around application exits and terminations.
You'll receive a daily summary
of reasons and counts
of why your application exited
in both the foreground and the background.
We think this is going to be helpful
in assisting you track down
common problems associated with app launch
and using background runtime frameworks.
For a deeper dive
into how you can leverage these metrics
and employ best practices,
I encourage you to watch our talk
on app terminations this year,
entitled "Why Did My App Get Killed?"
And so those are our new metrics
this year.
We think they're gonna provide you
an extra degree of certainty
when looking for regressions
in your MetricKit data.
Let's look back at our metric payload
more closely and focus on one area
where we still weren't able to determine
what's going on.
In our application
hang duration histogram,
we see some entries that are alarming
and could be a serious interruption
in your user's experience.
As it stands right now,
this is definitely a regression.
But we can't determine
the root cause from metrics alone.
We need some additional diagnostic data,
like a backtrace at the time of the hang,
to figure out what happened.
That brings us to our next big feature
this year for MetricKit
that's going to help you get to the bottom
of another class of regressions--
MetricKit diagnostics.
MetricKit 2.0 is going to be providing
a new interface
that enables you access
to targeted diagnostic information.
This diagnostic information is actionable
for various types of regressions,
including hangs, crashes,
disk write exceptions and CPU exceptions.
To start receiving
diagnostics in MetricKit 2.0,
all you need to do is implement a new
MetricManagerSubscriber protocol method.
That's it!
This new protocol looks almost identical
to last year's didReceive metric payloads
delegate method,
and we expect that many of you
will be able to use the same pipelines
you've already built for MetricKit.
This protocol, however,
doesn't just look the same.
It also functions the same.
Semantically,
MetricKit diagnostics functions
almost identically to MetricKit metrics.
If we take another look
at our timeline from earlier,
as your app is used throughout the day,
in addition to metrics,
the MetricKit system will now
passively collect diagnostic information
about regressions that occur during use.
Then, the system bundles them
into a parallel daily diagnostic payload
that can be used
alongside your daily metric payload.
Now, when you see
a regression in a metric like hangs,
you'll be able to reference, if present,
the associated diagnostic payload
that came at the same time
as the metric payload.
This diagnostic payload
effectively maps one-to-one
to its companion metric payload.
Let's switch gears and take a deeper look
into this new interface
and get familiar with its capabilities.
The new diagnostic interface
mirrors the old metric interface
insofar that we have
a few new base classes--
MXDiagnostic, the base class
that all diagnostics inherit from,
MXDiagnosticPayload,
the carrier class which contains
all diagnostics at the end of the day,
and MXCallStackTree,
a new data class that encapsulates
regression time backtraces
for off-device use.
MXDiagnostics, which are contained
within MXDiagnosticPayloads,
contain metadata of the application
at the time a regression occurred,
such as the specific build version
and diagnostic-specific data.
Diagnostic-specific data
is a unique subset of data
for each diagnostic subclass
that we're providing this year.
One part that's consistent across all
of them, however, is MXCallStackTree.
MXCallStackTree is a new data class
that we're providing
that encapsulates backtraces
at the time a regression occurs.
These backtraces are unsymbolicated
and designed for off-device processing.
And they're going to provide you
a rich set of information
that will help you diagnose
and capture the essence of regressions.
Here's an example
of what these call stack trees look like
after they've been converted
to a human-readable JSON.
We can see that everything needed
to symbolicate individual frames
with a tool like ATOS is present.
That includes binary information,
such as the UUID, offset and name,
and the frame address.
These new call stack tree data structures
are highly portable
and can be found in other performance
tools we're shipping this year.
To learn more,
I encourage you to watch our talk
on the new Power and Performance API.
As we said earlier,
we're shipping a set of four new
subclasses of MXDiagnostic this year--
hangs, CPU exceptions,
disk write exceptions and crashes.
Let's take a look
at the unique data contained
within each of these
new diagnostic subclasses now,
starting with hangs.
Hangs are regressions that occur
when your application is unresponsive
to user input for long periods of time.
This is due to your application's
main thread being blocked or busy.
Hang diagnostics provided
through the MetricKit interface
are gonna be providing you
the time the application's main thread
was unresponsive
and the backtraces of the main thread.
Next up is CPU exceptions,
or energy logs
as they're called in the Xcode Organizer.
These diagnostics are going to contain
CPU time consumed,
total time sampled
during the high CPU usage
and the backtraces of the threads
consuming CPU time.
CPU exception diagnostics
used in conjunction with metric payloads
can be extremely useful
in identifying regressions
that may not be easy to reproduce.
Next, we have disk writes.
Disk write exception diagnostics
are fairly similar
to CPU exception diagnostics.
Each diagnostic will contain
the total number of writes caused
that generated the exception
and a backtrace of the threads
causing excessive writes.
These diagnostics are generated
whenever a one-gigabyte daily threshold
is breached by your application.
Last but not least,
we have crash diagnostics.
This year, we're excited to share
that MetricKit is going to be providing
you a diagnostic for application crashes.
Each time your application crashes,
an MXCrashDiagnostic containing
the exception information,
termination reason,
virtual memory region information,
in the case of a bad access crash,
and the backtrace will be provided to you
via the MetricKit diagnostics interface.
And that wraps up MetricKit diagnostics,
a powerful new tool for you
to get to the root cause of regressions
in real customer use cases.
Let's wrap up with a summary
of what we talked about today.
MetricKit 2.0 is packed with new features
that are going to help you take your
optimization efforts to the next level.
We're providing new metrics for you to
dive deeper into understanding regressions
that occur in your customer
and beta populations.
We're also providing you
targeted diagnostics
to enable you to catch
harder-to-reproduce regressions
in those populations.
And finally, we're doing this
all at very little cost to you
by providing these new features
through easy-to-implement interfaces
and existing interfaces.
We have a ton of great new content
this year
and useful older content
that I encourage you to check out.
Thanks again for tuning in,
and enjoy the rest of your WWDC 2020.