[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Radhika, and I work on the
Proactive Intelligence team here at Apple.
As JP just mentioned
in the previous video,
it's clear that
the intelligent system experience
provides a lot of value for the developer.
Now, we'll look
at how this benefits users.
To do this, let's walk
through how system intelligence
can actually help people,
even before they download an app,
and how it can help
through every step of the way
from someone
who's just starting to use an app
to becoming a power user.
To illustrate this,
we'll use something relatable,
like breaking up the workweek
by doing some exercise.
I'll tell this story from the perspective
of someone that's just starting to learn
how to take advantage
of all the cool stuff on their phone.
Let's say this person
always works out with a friend.
That friend might text them
with the address
of a new gym they're going to today.
And before they even
type the address in Maps,
there's a suggestion
to get driving directions to that gym
that's just a tap away
right there in Maps.
So again, no gym app installed yet,
but Maps is smart enough to pick up
on the location of the gym from Messages.
Pretty cool, right?
Let's say she arrives with her friend
at this gym
and they decide they want to do
a workout class together.
They don't really know
what classes are available at this gym,
so they're looking
for the gym's class schedule.
Starting with iOS 14,
there'll be an App Clip for that.
She could walk past
the same reception desk every day,
but this time, there could be an NFC tag
for an App Clip at the register.
By just holding her phone
close to the tag,
she could see the schedule
just like it would appear in the gym's app
but without needing to hunt down
and download something.
What's really cool is that if she finds
this particular App Clip useful,
there's a way to download
the full app right there.
Now, this imaginary gym rat has gone
from going to the gym without an app
to realizing how the App Clip
can help her plan out her week.
In fact, she might want to start picking
the day she wants to go to the gym
based on what classes are scheduled.
So, she ends up downloading the app.
Now, she's starting to plan ahead.
Discovering this app
helped her solve a problem
she didn't even know she had.
Our new app user
is now being far more proactive
in building healthy habits
and creating an intentional schedule.
She's started planning out her week
on Sunday mornings,
which is a very responsible thing to do.
In fact, she's gotten even faster
at opening her apps
by pulling down to reveal Search.
And lo and behold, when she pulls down,
even before she starts typing,
the app is waiting for her
right there in Siri Suggestions.
That's because Siri
can actually learn and predict
what app she wants to launch
based on how she uses her phone.
So, she has the app on her device,
and she's starting to use
the various features within the app,
like looking at the yoga schedule
and finding new classes she can try out.
She's pretty familiar with the app,
and can get to the information she needs
most of the time.
She's really into yoga.
So even though she has her week planned,
she's always trying to squeeze in
an extra yoga class.
She usually checks the yoga schedule
after work by going into the app,
but recently, she's been using
the timely shortcut suggestions.
She can jump right to the yoga schedule
by tapping on it in Search.
It ends up saving her a couple of steps,
and most importantly,
she can probably get in
some extra yoga time.
So, our friend is now
pretty accustomed with the app
and is really loving her new gym routine.
There have been some hiccups, though,
so she's looking for ways
to make things even easier for herself.
She ended up missing
a group class recently
because she didn't notice
a schedule update.
With a busy workweek, she didn't end up
checking the app frequently enough.
Luckily, this year, with the new widgets,
there's an intelligent experience
available right on her Home Screen.
With a few quick taps,
she can create a Smart Stack
with all her favorite widgets,
including Mission Gym,
and add it to her Home Screen.
Thanks to system intelligence,
the stack will rotate automatically
to show the most relevant
and timely widget.
So, in her case,
if the class schedule changes,
the stack will automatically rotate
to the gym widget,
giving her enough time
to react to any changes.
This way she'll never miss a class.
More importantly, in the future,
she can browse upcoming class times
directly on her Home Screen
by glancing at the widget
and picking a time that works for her.
If she wants to learn more,
she can always tap on the widget
to jump to the right place in the app.
So instead of looking for the app
and then navigating through it,
she can find everything
right on her Home Screen.
Our friend has been working out
pretty frequently now.
She did notice, however,
she has been repeating the same few things
right before she works out.
She always checks the bus schedule
before starting the workout,
and she uses the Mission Gym app
to track her exercise.
This is where Shortcuts
is bound to come in handy.
She can set up a Shortcut automation
that will run when she arrives at the gym.
So when she gets there,
she can see the bus schedule
and start her workout.
So, as you can see
through this user's journey,
system intelligence
can help people discover new apps
and accelerate them every step of the way
after that.
By leveraging
these intelligence touch points,
you can work with the system
to deliver better,
more holistic experience for your users
at the right time and place.
Now, I'm going to hand it over
to my colleague Sufiyan
who will talk about
the underlying technologies
that power all of these experiences.
[chimes]