Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Nishant,
and I'm a Streaming Media Engineer
at Apple.
If you are looking to let your users
download and play
your HLS content while off-line,
you've tuned in to the right session.
We introduced the ability
to download HLS back in 2016.
Over the years
we have added new functionality,
and in this talk
we'll cover everything you need to know.
Many of you already have media content
authored as HLS for streaming.
You can reuse the same for downloads.
Along with that, you can use
FairPlay Streaming content protection.
And finally, off-line HLS
allows your users to download
the content in the background.
So, first question first,
should I use off-line HLS?
Yes. Use it when your user
explicitly requests media downloads.
They may want to download, say,
when they are about to get on an airplane,
or they may be on some
expensive cellular data plan
and they may want to download on Wi-Fi.
In all these cases,
it's appropriate to use off-line HLS.
Let's see how we can get you started.
Off-line HLS starts with the creation
of a download task.
The download task represents
the entire life cycle of a media download,
such as a movie.
Later on,
you need to monitor the download task
and update any progress in your app.
And finally,
once the download is complete,
you can play it off-line.
So let's take a look at the download task.
Download tasks are defined on URLSession.
What is a URLSession?
URLSession is an object which coordinates
all network-related tasks
such as upload and download tasks.
The download tasks specifically inherit
certain features from it.
The important ones to remember are
the download tasks are scheduled according
to availability of system resources.
So in certain cases, you may see that
the download does not start immediately.
For example,
if the network connectivity is poor,
the download starts
when the network improves.
Another important thing to remember is
the downloads are automatically retried.
For example, if you hit network timeouts,
AVFoundation retries the downloads
for you.
Before we dig in,
let's take a look at typical HLS assets
we all are familiar with.
This particular asset has bunch of video,
audio and subtitle renditions.
We will be using this as an example
going forward.
Coming to download tasks,
there are two variants.
The first one we're gonna look at
is AVAssetDownloadTask.
Using it, you can download one combination
of video, audio and subtitle renditions.
To create one of these download tasks,
you need to set up a URL session,
specifically AVAssetDownloadURLSession.
You create it with a session configuration
using an identifier.
And then, once you have the URL session,
you can call makeAssetDownloadTask.
Here in this example,
I'm downloading a movie at two megabits.
When you create AVAssetDownloadTask,
automatic media selection will be used.
What does that mean?
Automatic media selection
chooses renditions
based on device region
and localization preferences.
For example,
if the device region is set as France,
French audio and French subtitle
renditions will be downloaded.
Moving on,
after creating one of these things,
the next thing you may want to do
is monitor it for progress.
To do this, you need to use
AVAssetDownloadDelegate protocol.
I would like to highlight
two of the interfaces we have here.
The first one can be used to monitor
the progress of your download.
It provides you with the time ranges
that have been downloaded,
rather than the bytes,
so as to correlate better
with media interfaces.
We also have didCompleteWithError,
which informs you
when the download is complete.
You can use these interfaces
to build a progress UI in your app.
Here is an example of how you can do it.
I won't go into detail,
but it's here for your reference.
Some of you may be wondering,
"What if I want to download multiple audio
and subtitle renditions?"
We have another API called
AVAggregateAssetDownloadTask.
Using AVAggregateAssetDownloadTask,
you choose what renditions
you want to download.
Going back to our earlier example,
using aggregate download task,
you can download English audio
and English subtitle,
followed by Spanish audio and Spanish
subtitle and French subtitle renditions.
This API is appropriate
when you want to let your users choose
which audio and subtitle renditions
they want to download.
To create one of these, first you need
an array of media selections
which you want to download.
You can create a media selection
by obtaining
a mutable AVMediaSelection from your asset
and choosing an appropriate
media selection option.
Once you have your media selections,
you create the AVAssetDownload
URLSession as we did before.
Later, you call aggregateAssetDownloadTask
with the media selections
you want to download.
Since aggregateAssetDownloadTask
involves multiple media selections,
monitoring it is a bit different
compared to AVAssetDownloadTask.
The first thing to do is
split the download progress
between your various media selections.
You can do this by assigning weights
to each one of the media selections.
The first media selection
will typically involve downloading video
and hence will take a longer time.
We have observed that this accounts for
approximately 70% of the download time...
but this may vary depending on
how your content is authored.
Then you split the remaining weight
between your other media selections.
Keep in mind that downloading audio
takes more time
compared to downloading subtitle tracks.
Going back to our earlier example,
you can assign 70% of the download time
to the video rendition,
10% of the time
to each of the audio renditions.
Here, I've split the time
for the audio rendition
between stereo
and multichannel representation.
Finally, we can assign the remaining time
to the subtitle renditions.
In order to get you started,
let's look at some of
the download delegate interfaces.
To monitor progress, you still use
the LoadedTimeRanges callback
similarly to AVAssetDownloadTask.
But here,
in addition to loaded time ranges,
you'll be informed
about the media selection
for which the time range was loaded.
Another interface to look at is
didCompleteFor mediaSelection.
You can use this
as a synchronization point
while estimating your download progress.
In case of audio rendition,
expect the calls twice.
One for stereo representation, followed by
once for multichannel representation.
Another thing that might happen
during your download is
your app may get backgrounded.
Download tasks still run
when your app is in background.
When your app is relaunched, you need to
restore your existing download task.
You can do this by creating a URL session
with the same configuration identifier
you used previously.
Then you can restore your existing tasks
and then query the tasks to get
the latest status of your downloads.
You can also get your original AVAsset
from the download task and reuse it.
So now you know how to create
and monitor the download task.
Let's see how you can play them.
First, let's take a look at where
your download is deposited on the disk.
In case of AVAssetDownloadTask,
you get the location
once the download is complete.
And in case of aggregateAssetDownloadTask,
you get the location via willDownloadTo
delegate callback.
You may want to store this location.
We'll see the reason in a bit.
Now let's see how we can play
your download.
Here is how we created
a download task earlier.
For playback, you reuse the AVAsset
to create your playback item.
An advantage of reusing
the same AVAsset is...
it allows AVFoundation
to optimize resources
between playback and download.
This will be useful in cases
where the playback happens
before the download is complete.
We call this scenario as play
while download is in progress.
Any media resources
fetched during playback
will be stored to the disk
and will not be refetched again
for the download.
Another scenario you may encounter is
your user is trying to play
long after the download is complete.
In that case,
you may not have the original AVAsset
or the download task object lying around.
In such cases,
you can recreate an AVAsset
using the file URL.
This is the same URL you saved earlier.
Some of you may be wondering,
"All right, I have an asset here,
probably with a bunch
of audio and subtitle renditions.
How can I find out
what can be played off-line?"
We have an interface called AVAssetCache.
You can obtain the AVAssetCache object
from your AVAsset.
It tells you what can be played off-line
and also what media selections
are playable off-line.
Now you know how to download
and play media content while off-line.
Let's talk about how you can protect
your content using FairPlay.
FairPlay Streaming for off-line HLS
was introduced back in 2016.
Some of you
may already be using FairPlay Streaming
for protecting your streaming content.
You can do the same
for off-line HLS as well.
If you are new to FairPlay Streaming,
I would recommend
you check out our earlier talk
"AVContentKeySession Best Practices"
from WWDC 2018.
When streaming, you get your key
from your key server as needed.
But during off-line playback,
you may not be able
to reach your key server.
Instead you create something
called as off-line key during the download
and store it for later use.
Let's see how we you can get you
this off-line key.
You need AVContentKeySession
to start with.
Then you initiate key loading
as you would normally do
for the streaming case.
If you do not know
the key required for the download,
don't worry.
When you create a download task,
you will also receive
a key request from AVContentKeySession
if the key's already not loading.
Then you create a ServerPlaybackContext,
SPC for short,
by providing your FairPlay Streaming
application certificate.
You talk to your key server
and get back the key
in the form of Content Key Context,
CKC for short,
and provide the CKC
to AVContentKeySession.
You can later obtain
the off-line key from it.
You store the off-line key
for subsequent use.
During off-line playback,
when you receive a key request,
you can reply back
with the off-line key you created earlier.
One thing to remember is
FairPlay Streaming lets your key server
set expiration date for off-line keys.
If the key expires
during an existing playback session,
in order to have a good user experience,
the session continues to the end
rather than stop abruptly.
Finally, remember to create
a new off-line key before expiration.
In some cases,
you may want to securely delete
an off-line key before it expires.
For example,
when the user deletes the download.
Since iOS 12,
you can invalidate an off-line key
by providing it to AVContentKeySession.
You can use also
invalidate all your off-line keys
by providing your FairPlay Streaming
application certificate.
AVContentKeySession also allows you
to create off-line keys for movie rentals.
A typical rental scenario involves
having two expiration dates:
one which starts
when the user rents a movie
and the other one which starts
when the user starts playback.
FairPlay Streaming supports this
using dual expiry off-line keys.
For example, you can let your user
watch a rental within 30 days of purchase,
but once they start watching,
they have to finish within 48 hours.
Again, this is explained in more detail
in "AVContentKeySession Best Practices"
from WWDC 2018.
There is one more thing
you may find useful.
Your app may be using custom protocols
for URL resources when streaming.
What are custom protocols for URLs?
These are the URLs
which begin with a custom scheme.
For example, URLs beginning with myscheme
and URLs beginning with skd.
These are the resources
specific to your app,
and AVFoundation handles them using
AVAssetResourceLoader for playlists
and AVContentKeySession for keys.
If your app gets backgrounded
immediately after the download starts,
you can still answer
resource requests for custom protocols.
Starting from iOS 14, you have 30 seconds
to answer any resource requests
involving custom protocols.
Moving on, let's talk a few things
you can do to improve user experience.
First, let's talk about the download time.
Users prefer
downloads which complete faster,
but they also prefer downloads
which are of higher quality.
You need to find the right balance.
One best practice we recommend
is to allow your users
an option to do fast downloads.
This may be really helpful for those users
who are downloading
just before catching a flight.
And finally another option
for best quality download.
For either of these options,
you may want to restrict
the type and quality of the content
you want to download.
You can do this by using
various options on the download task.
Firstly, you can restrict media bitrate
using MinimumRequiredMediaBitrateKey.
For example,
if you specify minimum required
media bitrate as five megabits,
the bitrate variant just above five
megabits will be chosen for downloads.
Starting from iOS 14,
you can also restrict
based on presentation size as well.
Another quality restriction you can do
is to download HDR presentations or not.
By default,
the download task would prefer to
download HDR presentations if available.
Lastly, you may want to restrict
based on audio type.
Again, by default, AVFoundation downloads
both stereo
and multichannel audio renditions.
You can opt out of multichannel by setting
prefers multichannel option key to false.
Some you may be wondering,
"Why download both
stereo and multichannel representations?"
We believe that the stereo rendition
mixed at a studio
better reflects artistic intent.
For example,
the dialogue may be given more prominence
compared to other background noise.
You may want to experiment with these
options and choose them appropriately
depending on
how your media library is authored.
Moving on,
let's talk about storage management.
Another best practice we recommend is
you let the operating system manage
the storage for your off-line downloads.
By doing so,
it allows the operating system
to delete and reclaim storage
when your app is not running.
For example, during software updates,
the operating system
can automatically reclaim space
when the storage is running low.
It also allows your users
to delete media content
through the Settings app.
The asset image and title you provide
when you create the download task
will be displayed here.
Now let's take a look
at how you can opt in to this.
You start by getting
a shared storage manager.
Then you create a new policy by providing
a priority and expiration date.
Assets will be purged
based on expiration date
and then based on the priority.
Finally, you set the policy
on your downloaded content.
Remember to keep the downloaded content
at the same system-provided location.
And be prepared for the assets
to be deleted by the system.
So that is off-line HLS,
and we are really excited
for you to start using it.
To wrap up,
we went over two different download tasks
using which you can download HLS.
The first one is AVAssetDownloadTask,
which uses automatic media selection
to select media renditions to download,
and the second one is
the aggregate download task,
which lets you specify
the audio and subtitle renditions
you want to download.
Finally, we looked at
how we can use FairPlay Streaming
to protect your off-line content
and learned
some best practices on the way.
To get you started,
we have a sample app which you can obtain
from the resources below.
Thank you for joining,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.