Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Daisy,
and I work on the Xcode Previews team.
In this video, I want to show you
how you can use Xcode Previews
to help you quickly build SwiftUI apps,
whether you're new to SwiftUI or not.
To do so, I'll be building the row view
for our smoothie app.
The view has the smoothie's name,
ingredients, calorie count, and an image,
along with the star count
for its popularity.
To begin, I'm going to use a library
to add a new view to my UI.
The library has SwiftUI views
and modifiers,
allowing you
to keep your preview compiling
without additional modifications.
SwiftUI uses structural layouts
in order to make your app adaptive.
So your app looks great whether
it's running on an iMac or an iPhone.
Xcode Previews lets you insert
your content,
and get the right layout container,
all in one action.
Next, I can double-click
on my "Hello World" view,
which brings focus to the editor,
allowing me to quickly modify
the key component of my view,
whether this is an image or text.
The Xcode Previews canvas
and the source editor
have a tight integration.
The canvas and the inspector
help you write your Swift code faster,
and any changes you do to source
are immediately visible in the canvas.
[typing]
To help you build your structure
even quicker,
you can use Command-D
to duplicate your views.
Xcode Previews understands the structure
of your code,
so if you're duplicating a view
that isn't in a container,
it would insert one for you.
Next, we can double-click
on our third label to quickly modify it.
Double-clicking on a view not only helps
with replacing static content,
but also makes integrating
your model data a breeze.
[typing]
To insert my image,
I'm going to bring up the library
using the keyboard shortcut
Command-Shift-L.
The Xcode Previews canvas not only works
with SwiftUI views and modifiers,
but also your media,
allowing you to use your images
in your asset catalog with ease.
Our image is larger than expected.
This, however, makes sense,
since SwiftUI renders your images
in their true size.
To remedy this, we can use the inspector
to locate the appropriate modifier.
Clicking on "Add Modifier" brings down
a list of recommended suggestions
using your current context,
allowing you to quickly locate
what you're looking for,
and learn about modifiers
commonly used with the view.
The image is now resizing,
though its size is not up to spec.
In the inspector,
I can add and edit common modifiers,
allowing you to try various values
without having to know
the modifier's signature.
This immediately updates your code
and renders in the canvas.
Next, I want to add the star view
that indicates the smoothie's popularity.
Using your project's custom SwiftUI views
and modifiers in the canvas
is just as easy as using
those provided by the library.
To see how to do this, see the session
"Adding Custom Views and Modifiers
to the Xcode Library."
To repeat the star horizontally,
Xcode Previews provides actions
that embed the selected view
in various containers.
The actions can be brought up by holding
Command and clicking on the view.
In our case, we click "Embed in HStack"
to embed in a horizontal container.
To repeat the star view,
we can bring up the same menu
and click "Repeat."
I'd like to make my smoothie title pop.
Using the inspector,
I can quickly try various font
and weight values on my view,
and preview the results immediately
in the canvas.
That doesn't look exactly how I want.
To clear the modifier,
I can click on the circular blue indicator
next to the control.
Clearing the modifier returns it
to its inherited value.
In this case, the font returns
to the default SwiftUI font.
Next, I would like to edit
the other labels,
which, with the inspectors,
is only a few clicks.
I can use the inspectors not only
to edit properties of the modifiers,
but also edit those of the view.
Screen real estate is a hot commodity,
so Xcode Previews has
an in-canvas inspector
allowing you to close your side panel
without losing any functionality.
To bring up the canvas inspector,
hold Control-Option
and click on the view you wish to inspect.
To help you preview
across different configurations,
in Xcode 12 we have introduced various
preview-centric capabilities.
For example, we can now duplicate
a preview with one click.
And since previews are just views,
we can inspect them too.
In summary, some of the ways
Xcode Previews helps you visually edit
your SwiftUI views is through
tight source editor integration,
the inspector, and the library.
Thanks!