Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Peter Raffensperger, and I'm
gonna tell you how you can record stereo
from the built-in microphones.
AVAudioSession is how your app
communicates to the system
how you intend to use audio in your app,
including configuration
for audio recording.
New in iOS 14 and iPadOS 14
is the option to record stereo audio
from the built-in microphones
on supported hardware.
That's right,
you asked for stereo recording,
and now you can have it.
The benefit of stereo is that you can tell
what direction a sound comes from.
Let's say I'm recording with your app.
My listeners could be my friends,
family or fans,
and stereo lets me bring them closer
to my expression, my art and my life.
So we recommend that you write your app
to take advantage
of the option to record stereo
whenever possible
so that you get the most immersive
audio recording experience.
In this talk, I'll explain how you
can adopt this new API feature
and also how to address
the new special consideration
for stereo recording
that we call "inputOrientation."
But first,
we need to go back to the basics
of AVAudioSession's microphone
and beam selection.
Many Apple devices
have multiple microphones,
and our fantastic acoustics design team
works hard
to optimize the microphone arrays
on each product.
AVAudioSession lets you choose
which of those device microphones
you want to record from.
Actually, in the API,
we say that you can choose different
data sources, not different mics,
because you can choose a polar pattern
that gets you
a kind of virtualized microphone.
So, say you select
that upper front data source.
You can either get
that individual microphone
by selecting the omni polar pattern,
or you can choose
to get a cardioid beamformer.
Let's have a closer look
at how this works.
When you record from the upper front data
source with the cardioid beam pattern,
actually you're using both of those
upper microphones and in tandem
to get a better directional response.
So that when a sound wave arrives
from the front
and arrives at that front microphone
before it arrives at the back microphone,
we can make that sound wave louder
than if it comes from the other direction.
So we get a kind of pattern like this--
it's louder in the forward direction,
quieter in the back.
Okay, so if we swap the roles
of those two microphones around,
we can get upper back subcardioid,
and that lets us listen more
in the other direction.
It's not quite the same shape,
because we don't want to null out
the user if they talk.
This is great.
We can focus audio
in particular directions.
But it's mono.
To get stereo,
we actually record from
all the device microphones simultaneously.
And we apply a special modeling process
that results
in a binaural stereo experience.
And we apply some special processing
to that front direction
to make it a little bit louder
than the back direction,
similar to how a cardioid beam works.
The result is this.
Left and right are in distinct directions,
and the forward direction is in
the look direction of that back camera.
So you're gonna choose this data source
if you want to get stereo audio
with your recording made
on the back camera.
Similar to cardioid and subcardioid,
if we want to look in the other direction,
we can choose upper front stereo.
Notice that left and right
are now in the opposite direction.
Left is now the edge of the device
with the lock button.
And right is the edge of the device
with the volume buttons.
So you're gonna choose this data source
to go with videos you've made
on the front camera.
However, users can hold the device
in many different possible orientations.
And we can't do the same thing
in landscape
as we did in portrait
because if we did,
then left and right would be up and down.
So we're gonna actually repeat
this modeling process once
for each different way
the user can hold the phone.
And you have to tell the system
which of those you want.
And that brings us to the new property,
inputOrientation for AVAudioSession.
Now, there are four possible values here--
portrait, portrait upside-down,
landscape left and landscape right.
And there are two different data sources.
So there are a total
of eight distinct cases,
each with a unique combination
of that forward beam direction
and left and right directions
relative to the edges of the device.
Here's the first four
of those eight possibilities.
First, you're gonna choose
which direction is forward
based on your selection
of the data source.
And then, left and right are determined
by the new inputOrientation property.
Okay, here's the second four.
You need to design your app logic
to select that stereo input orientation
and data source
so that these directions match
what your users are expecting.
Now, you'll only need to do this
for stereo polar patterns
because for mono,
the input orientation makes no difference.
There are a lot of options here,
so let me help you out.
If your app records video,
then select the input orientation
that makes left and right in the audio
match left and right in the video.
Refer to the documentation for details
on how to match the input orientation,
camera direction and video rotation.
If your app doesn't record video,
then we think it makes the most sense
to match your stereo input orientation
to your UI orientation
because that's how users
are expecting the device to be.
The other thing is,
when you're recording to a file,
especially if it's a video file,
then you should keep
that orientation fixed
for the entire duration of the recording.
That ensures there are no strange changes
in the directions during your recording.
Ultimately, though,
the number one principle is
that you should anticipate
the expectations
of the end listener
of your users' recordings.
And one size doesn't fit all here.
You've gotta figure out the logic
that's right for your app.
Here's a bunch of principles,
and they all lead to getting audio
in the correct directions.
The main idea is
that the app audio directions
are related to the edges of the device
and the microphone placements.
And we need to know
how that relationship works.
First, you're gonna choose
that forward direction
with the data source selection,
and then you're gonna figure out
which way left and right are
based on the data source
and that input orientation in combination.
The other thing is that we recommend
you test your app comprehensively here.
So, record a sound coming from the left
and then a sound coming from the right,
and listen back.
Make sure that is how you expect it to be.
Then repeat that test for each orientation
and data source selection
that you intend to use.
Okay, so that's the basic principles.
Let's have a look
at how this appears in code.
Here's some code from a sample project.
You can look
at the sample project on line.
The first thing we need to do is record
from the built-in microphone.
So this is all existing use of the API.
First we're gonna find
that built-in mic port.
And then we're gonna set that
as our preferred input port.
Okay, here's the new stuff.
First, we're gonna choose
that stereo polar pattern.
You'll see this new pattern on devices
that support stereo recording.
But you need to be ready for the case
when the device doesn't support stereo.
So, size your buffers dynamically.
The right way to do that is,
activate your audio session
and check
that input channel count property.
Then we're gonna choose
what data source we want.
Remember,
there's two options for stereo here--
one for the front, one for the back.
You're gonna choose the direction that
focuses audio where you want it to go.
And here's the call
to the new inputOrientation property.
You'll notice that
it's the PreferredInputOrientation.
And that's because if there's some other app
that happens to be in control of routing,
you might not get what you prefer here.
To get the best chance at your preference,
choose a non-mixable option
when you set up your session.
Okay, so I talked about what values
that you should set.
Now I'm gonna expand a little bit about
when you should set the data source
and inputOrientation.
If your app records video,
then you should set the inputOrientation
before you start recording video.
But the sample app doesn't record video,
and your app might not,
so we're gonna listen
to when the UI is rotated.
You might also have your focus direction
based on user input,
for example, derived from
the camera that your user selected.
In the sample app, it's a little picker,
so that's what gets called here.
The other thing I mentioned before
is if you're recording,
then now is probably not the time
to be changing that inputOrientation
or the dataSource selection.
So, here we're just gonna call
the function from the previous slide
with the chosen data source
and the orientation of the window.
All right. At this point,
you're ready to record stereo
using any of our audio APIs,
like AVAudioRecorder or AVAudioEngine.
Take your time to study that sample app.
See how it applies in your use case.
So what can we take away from all this?
The main thing is, record in stereo.
That'll get you
the most immersive experience.
Choose that data source to match
where you want to focus audio.
And then set your inputOrientation
so that the sounds come from directions
that match the user's expectations.
And that's recording stereo
from the built-in mic.