[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Wil, and I work on testing
and automation in XCode.
In this session we're going
to learn about new APIs
and other improvements
to how you investigate
test failures in your projects.
Investigation of test failures
is the single most critical piece
of maintaining any active test suite.
Difficult to diagnose failures
cost you time.
They cost too much time.
At the wrong point
in your release schedule,
they can even lead
to bugs shipping in products.
With any growing project,
code changes
will sometimes cause tests to fail.
Either locally,
or in continuous integration.
And when they do fail,
you'll be considering
the following questions.
What failed?
How did it fail?
Why?
And perhaps, most of all,
where in my source code,
did the failure happen?
In Xcode 12, we've added new APIs,
and enhanced the UI
for test failure reporting
to make answering
these questions more efficient.
It's worth noting the answer
to these questions are so important,
that there's a whole session dedicated
to coding patterns you can use
to further improve this process.
For more about
that check out, "Write Tests to Fail."
We've organized the content
for this session in four sections.
Swift errors in tests,
rich failure objects,
call stacks for test failures,
and advanced workflows.
We'll explore each
of these topics in turn.
But first, let's take a look
at how failures are presented in Xcode 12.
I have here a little project
called PlayGarden,
that I've been working on
with my three-year-old daughter.
PlayGarden helps us keep track
of all the plants, toys
and furniture in our backyard.
Now even at age three,
my daughter has
fully embraced test-driven development.
So, it's not surprising we have tests
for all the view classes
representing elements in our garden.
We noticed recently there was a lot
of duplicated code in these tests,
so we refactored it into some utilities.
I'm going to run one of these tests now.
I've introduced an artificial failure,
so we can see
how that's presented in Xcode 12.
Right away, you might have noticed
that the test is marked as failing.
But the only annotation
we can see is gray.
This tells us the failure happened
in a call underneath the annotated line,
but not at that line itself.
We can explore this further
by switching to the Issue Navigator.
The Issue Navigator
shows the test failure here,
but it shows more than that.
Underneath the failure is a call stack
in your test code.
If I click on a frame,
the source editor takes me
to that location.
Here the annotation is red,
because this
is the actual point of failure.
Now if I move through the rest
of the frames,
the Issue Navigator and the source editor
take me on a tour of my code,
working back from the failure
to the point in the test
where it was triggered.
This helps me quickly understand
all the context around the test failure,
cutting down on the time needed
to fix the issue.
There's another way
we can explore this data.
Let's switch to the test report.
This is a great way
to investigate test failures,
particularly if you're working
with a result bundle
from a continuous integration system.
In the report for our most recent test run
we have the failing test here in red.
If we expand that,
we see the failure message along
with the file
and line where it was recorded.
But let's scroll down a little further.
Now we can see the same call stack we saw
in the Issue Navigator
giving us another way
to explore your code.
You'll notice as I hover
over a frame in the call stack,
that two buttons appear
to the right of the frame.
The first of these is the Jump button,
which navigates
to the source code location.
I'll go back to the report,
so that we can explore the second button.
New in Xcode 12,
the Assistant button opens
a secondary editor next
to the test report,
which shows the reference source location.
This lets us view the test report,
and the source code, side by side.
And we can explore the failure
of call stack
in the same way that we did
within Issue Navigator.
So, that's our look at how test failures
are presented in Xcode 12.
Now I'd like to talk about
using Swift errors in your tests.
One of the ways XCTest supports
idiomatic coding patterns in Swift,
is by making it possible
for test functions to throw.
When a test does throw, the error is used
to formulate the failure message.
This means, instead of having
boilerplate for handling errors
like this,
your tests can be written like this.
Much cleaner.
But, until recently, these failures could
not provide the source code location,
file and line, that was traditionally part
of test failures recorded by XCTAssert.
Because of this limitation,
some developers still use
error handling boilerplate.
Happily, improvements to the Swift runtime
and iOS, and tvOS 13.4 and macOS 10.15.4,
made it possible for XCTest to begin
reporting the source code locations
for thrown errors and tests.
This means that you get great context
for these errors
without any other extra handling code.
Along with
the source code location improvements,
we added APIs,
so the same level of convenience
is available in your test's setUp()
and tearDown().
These new APIs are variants
of the original setUp()
and tearDown() methods shown here.
The new setUpWithError() will run
before the original setUp() method.
And the new tearDownWithError()
will be called
after the original tearDown() method.
You'll see both of these methods
in the templates provided
for new test files.
It's possible to use both variants
of these APIs in the same test case.
But generally, we encourage you
to switch your tests over
to the new methods,
unless you need
to preserve the old methods
because of inheritance.
Now I'd like to switch gears
and talk about rich failure objects.
XCTest has always recorded failures
as four discrete values.
The failure message, the file path,
and line number,
where the failure was recorded,
and a flag indicating
whether the failure was expected.
Expected failures are
those recorded by XCTAssert.
Unexpected failures generally indicate
that XCTest has caught an unhandled
exception thrown by the test code.
These values were passed by XCTAssert
into the record failure API,
which ensures that failures are logged
and ratted to Xcode for display.
In Xcode 12 these disparate values
have been encapsulated
by a new object XCTIssue.
In addition, there are new kinds
of failure data.
An explicit type of numeration,
a detailed description,
an underlying error and Attachments.
XCTAttachment is an API for capturing
arbitrary data with test runs.
Attachments can either be added
to the test itself,
or to an activity created by XCTContext.
Attachments can also be added to XCTIssue,
making it possible
to associate custom diagnostics
with your test failures.
XCTestCase has new API
for recording test failures.
This API, record(_issue:),
is used by all XCTAsserts
and can be invoked directly,
or even overridden.
The record failure API,
that we've showed a few slides back,
has been deprecated.
If you're calling recordFailure directly,
or are overriding it
to customize failure recording,
we encourage you
to update to record(_issue:)
at your earliest convenience.
When using record(_issue:), you may need
to know how to modify XCTIssues.
In Swift, issues are immutable
when declared with let.
Declaring with var allows you
to modify them.
In Objective-C, XCTIssue
has immutable subclass
and also conforms to NS mutableCopy.
XCTIssue enhances failure triage
in many ways.
But it's call stacks may be
the most transformative.
At the beginning of this session,
I suggested that one
of the most important questions
to answer about a test failure is where?
This is why the core test failure data
has always included a file path
and line number
captured at bill time, using
compiler tokens like pound file path.
A single source code location
is great for simple tests.
But isn't as useful
when test code is factored
into functions shared
by more than one test.
Consider this example.
Here are two tests both calling out
to the same shared function.
When there's a failure, the annotation
appears next to the assertion.
The test method itself becomes confusing,
because it's marked as failing,
but has no further information to help
the developer answer the where question.
This can be mitigated
if the helper function
captures the source location
where it was invoked.
And explicitly uses that
in its XCTAssert calls.
That improves the presentation
and the test method,
but if the helper has more
than one assertion,
than the ambiguity
has simply been shifted.
Fortunately, XCTIssue captures
and symbolicates call stacks.
This means that
there's considerably more context
for failures in complex test code.
Here's how that same failure looks
when we capture the call stack.
Very much like what we saw
in the demo earlier.
Answering the where question
is a totally different experience.
A gray annotation
in the test method indicates
the line under which the failure occurred.
And a red annotation in the helper method
highlights the failure itself.
No extra code was required
to pass down a location
and you don't have to choose
which location is annotated.
You get the best of both worlds,
with no extra effort.
Finally, I'd like to show you
some more advanced workflows
made possible by these new APIs.
First, you can implement custom assertions
by creating XCTIssue instances directly,
and calling record(_issue:).
Here's an example of an assertion
that validates some data,
and includes it as an attachment
to the issue that it records.
In the initial creation of the issue,
I'm using var,
because the rest of the code makes
some modifications to the struct.
We could also pass all the information
up-front to a longer initializer.
But I think it's a bit easier
to read this way.
Next, I'm adding the data
as an attachment to the issue.
This means that the data will appear
with the failure in the Xcode test report,
enabling me to inspect it during triage
and determine why it failed validation.
Here, I'm capturing the location
where my custom assertion was called.
This isn't required,
but can result in clear presentation,
since the code you see here isn't likely
to be useful
in understanding the failure itself.
Finally we call record(_issue:),
which logs the issue,
and sends it to Xcode.
The other advanced workflow
I wanna show you
is how you can override record(_issue:)
to observe, suppress,
or modify failures recorded
in your test class.
This method is the funnel point through
which every failure passes.
Overrides have total control over
the output of your test class.
Our first example overrides
record(_issue:) for observation.
It's important to call super,
to ensure the issue continues
along the recording chain.
You can also observe issues
using XCTestObservationCenter.
But the approach here
is useful if you only want
to observe failures in one class.
If your override does not call super,
you will have suppressed the issue.
You will not continue
along the recording chain.
And nothing will be logged
or reported to Xcode.
Modification is the most common reason
for overriding record(_issue:).
This pattern makes it possible
to add attachments,
which can be great diagnostic aides.
Example here shows
adding a simple string attachment,
but the API can handle
a broad range of types.
And that wraps up our session.
A few key points I hope you take away.
Triaging test failures
is one of the most important parts
of caring for your test suites.
Having call stacks makes it easy
to track down the locations in your code
that are most relevant to a failure.
This, in turn, supports more
natural patterns in your test code,
freeing you up to focus
on code reuse and other good practices.
XCTIssue also supports attachments,
which lets you add custom diagnostic data,
helping you answer the how
and why of your test failures.
Thanks for watching.
[chimes]