Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Jason Cary,
and today, we'll be talking about
deploying Apple devices using Zero-touch.
Within this session,
we'll review remote deployment
and management practices
by looking at Apple's
internal Zero-touch deployments.
We'll start with setup
and infrastructure components,
review how we deploy devices to our users,
confirm how we identify
and secure our users
and share how we distribute content
to ensure users are able to perform
their duties as efficiently as possible.
Before we dive into the technical details,
let's take a second to reminisce.
IT admins of the past
were involved in every aspect
of the hardware provisioning process.
Fortunately, the days of device imaging
and sitting with users
for hours on end are long gone.
Our Zero-touch enrollment solutions
allow efficient provisioning of devices
for thousands of employees worldwide.
New devices are drop-shipped
from our supply chain
directly to our users
without IT needing to touch each device.
Our goal is to have our users online
and productive within minutes,
not hours of unboxing their new device,
and to provide our users
with a positive device set up experience.
Let's look at the macOS Catalina
set up process
for the Macs we're deploying today,
which will be updated to Big Sur
after it ships later this year.
As a user boots their new device
for the first time,
Setup Assistant activates
and begins the device enrollment process.
Within our Zero-touch model,
we have customized
the Setup Assistant process
to be more efficient.
We've removed several
Setup Assistant screens and options
to provide an optimal experience
to our users.
Devices are automatically enrolled
in our device management solution
during the first boot,
which allows us to push
critical applications
and security settings to the device
during the initial set up process.
One of the most important set up steps
is to have the user
create a local user account
and a secure password.
This is where a specific account name
and password restrictions can be enforced.
I'll talk about several of these settings
later on.
Users self-configure various settings
to their preference,
including light and dark mode
within mac OS.
At the conclusion
of the device enrollment process,
Setup Assistant completes
the remaining device set up tasks
and brings the user
to their desktop screen.
When the user arrives
at their desktop screen,
applications required
to complete their duties,
as well as critical security settings,
are already installed
and enabled on the device.
Through the use of Apple Business Manager
and our device management solution,
our team has achieved an astounding ratio
of 20,000 managed devices per MDM admin.
Recently, in response
to the ongoing health pandemic,
Apple sent many of our employees home
from their normal
brick-and-mortar locations
to perform their job functions remotely.
As a result of this quick decision
and the prompt actions that were taken,
many of our employees were unable to take
their primary workstations with them.
Apple drop-shipped each
of these particular employees
a new Mac device to their home
in a very short time frame.
Our users were able to power on
their new devices
and quickly become productive,
thanks to Zero-touch device management.
Without these capabilities,
the quick pivot
would not have been possible,
and affected employees would have been
idle for an extended amount of time,
impacting their work and Apple's ability
to continue to support our customers.
Let's dive into our Zero-touch environment
setup and infrastructure components.
So, how does this technology work?
Our remote management solution is
made possible by Apple Business Manager,
the device management framework
with a third-party
device management solution,
and core technologies in iOS
iPadOS, macOS and tvOS,
that enable management
of certain features.
Starting with the purchase,
the device details are sent
to Apple Business Manager
through Apple's reseller API.
Each Apple Business Manager account
is configured with a default MDM target,
which allows the device to be assigned
to an organization's preferred MDM server.
Devices are purchased
through the reseller channel.
Each reseller partners with Apple
to obtain access to our reseller API.
Upon a device being purchased,
the reseller API performs data validation
to ensure sales notification data
is accurate and unique.
Multiple device details are included
in the reseller API transaction,
including serial number,
purchase order details,
date of purchase and more.
Checks can also be performed to validate
the device is not currently enrolled
with another
Apple Business Manager account.
Once verified, the device purchase record
is transferred
into Apple Business Manager.
Pending receipt of the sales transaction
into Apple Business Manager,
the device is added to a specific
Apple Business Manager account
based on the reseller ID provided.
A device is associated
with its intended MDM server
based upon the previously mentioned
Apple Business Manager assignment.
Multiple MDM targets can be configured
for a single organization.
Communication between the MDM server
and the device
is established during
the device set up process using APNs,
including the device receiving its initial
configuration instructions.
The MDM is then able to apply
pre-stage profiles to the device.
Devices may be manually assigned
to an MDM service
which is not the default MDM target
for your organization.
Such assignments should be completed prior
to the user receiving their device.
As of macOS 10.15.4 and iOS 13.4,
APNs also now supports
proxy configurations.
Apple is making it easier
for organizations
to communicate with
the Apple Push Notification service
on proxy networks.
APNs allows communication
from MDM to your devices.
Organizations need to allow communication
from their network to APNs.
Apple Push Notification service traffic
will now use a web proxy
when it is specified in
a Proxy Auto-Configuration, or PAC, file.
This new feature will provide
improved support
for default-deny networks,
typical in regulated industries,
as all Internet-bound traffic
must traverse a proxy
that is configured by a PAC file.
APNs traffic is encrypted
and cannot be inspected.
APNs proxy support will provide
full MDM functionality
on proxy-enabled networks.
Work with your network teams
for how your devices discover the PAC URL:
automatically
or via a configuration profile.
Data traffic traversing APNs
cannot be inspected,
so the communications remain secure
without the threat of being intercepted.
Let's look at an example of an MDM profile
in macOS Catalina.
Apple's management approach
has always been
to make it really simple for businesses
to centrally manage
their Apple devices with MDM.
The process is fully secure, streamlined
and easy for the user.
And it is transparent,
so that users know everything
that happens to their device,
including how it's set up
and what has been deployed to it.
In this way, users are a part of
the process and have a role to play,
whether each device is enrolled
in Apple Business Manager or not.
So what can MDM do?
Here are just a few examples.
Through the use of configuration profiles,
you can enforce passcodes,
restrict various settings
or organize apps in the Dock.
You can also configure macOS devices
to automatically connect
to an enterprise Wi-Fi network,
set up e-mail accounts,
install applications,
and enforce encryption with FileVault.
The last step in deploying macOS
and a Zero-touch solution
is getting your infrastructure ready.
macOS supports a wide range
of standard technologies
for everything from networking
to accounts and identities.
Most of these are the same standards
that companies already support
for iOS devices.
As a result, IT teams only need
to configure a few additional things
to do basic integration
and support key infrastructure.
There will be additional considerations
as you build your own
remote management environment.
Infrastructure components may vary
based on your organization's needs.
The first significant decision
that needs to be made
is whether the environment will be
on-premise or cloud-based.
Utilizing multiple MDM environments
allows MDM administrators
to push and test new settings
without the risk of impact
to production users and devices.
A good multiple environment setup
includes Production,
Disaster Recovery
in a geographically separate location
from your production environment,
Test and Development.
For on-premise environments,
containers or virtual machines
can be used for low processing needs
such as web servers
and application servers.
High computing needs
such as database transactions
should be properly sized to ensure
efficient processing of such requests.
The use of bare metal servers
may be beneficial
for resource-intensive functions.
You should install and enable
firewalls and access control list
at each layer of your solution.
Load balancers may be beneficial
for larger organizations
to balance management traffic
from your users.
However, they may not be necessary for
smaller implementations and organizations.
Let's talk now about deployment.
Our Zero-touch solution allows devices
to be drop-shipped from the supply chain
directly to our users.
Remember, your organization might choose
to skip certain aspects
of the normal Setup Assistant process
to streamline the device set up process.
Each device
is automatically enrolled into MDM
upon Setup Assistant running
during the first boot.
Users receive a custom
MDM enrollment notification screen
during Setup Assistant
which confirms their enrollment.
In our case, a self-service application
is automatically installed on the device.
Commonly used applications,
including a single sign-on,
or SSO, authentication client
are automatically pushed to each device
upon MDM enrollment.
Additional applications
such as corporate and contact center tools
are also made available to the user
via a self-service portal
to install at their convenience.
You should intentionally decide
which apps are automatically pushed
and which you allow the user
to install for themselves.
Some apps may be best
pushed automatically, but not all.
Local admin rights
are provisioned for our users.
User experience is greatly enhanced
and fewer issues occur
when users are provided
local admin rights to their device.
Measures should be taken
to ensure devices are properly secured
based on your organization's needs.
There are many different types of payloads
that can be built and deployed
to managed devices using an MDM solution.
All these different payloads
allow different settings in macOS
to be set by administrators
and are fully customizable
to your organization's business
and security needs.
Apple pushes a number of payloads
to our users' devices
via our internal MDM solution.
Corporate and business
critical applications
are automatically installed
upon MDM enrollment.
Mail and Calendar settings
are also auto-configured
upon the user logging in
to our single sign-on application.
Additionally,
VPN and our internal wireless network
are also configured automatically
for our users,
allowing them to go online
and become productive
immediately after MDM enrollment.
Identifying all users
connecting to Apple's network
and using Apple tools
is extremely important.
Numerous security measures
and settings are used
to identify users
and secure their devices from compromises.
User information is pulled
by our MDM solution
through the SSO authentication client.
Functionality will depend
on the identity provider being used,
but most LDAP integrations will support
these identification functions.
We have the ability to scope
MDM profiles, policies,
applications, and settings
based on LDAP groups and user roles.
You may use one
of a number of identity providers
and your full identity solution
can take advantage
of many of the built-in
user identification functions
depending on availability within your MDM.
Where such functionality does not exist
within your MDM,
custom scripts can be used to perform
additional identification functions.
For more on enterprise identity
and authentication,
please see this year's identity session.
We have implemented numerous
industry best practice security settings,
as well as settings specific
to our own needs
and internal security requirements.
These settings ensure our users,
their devices,
and the data they access
remain safe and secure.
Settings in gray
are common baseline security settings.
Some or all of the listed settings
may be beneficial to organizations
setting up their own Zero-touch solution.
Settings listed in white
are specific settings
put in place by Apple
to further protect our users,
their devices,
and their data being accessed.
As we utilize very sensitive customer data
to support our customers,
additional settings are needed
to ensure that data remains safe.
If a device is found to be out of policy,
lost, or stolen,
or if an employee leaves the company,
an MDM server can take action
to protect corporate information
in a number of ways.
A device must have a network connection
to receive these commands.
An IT administrator can end
the MDM relationship with a device
by removing the configuration profile
that contains the MDM server information,
including the accounts and settings
the MDM was responsible for installing.
IT can also keep
the MDM configuration profile in place
and use MDM to remove
only the specific configuration profiles
and provisioning profiles
they want to delete.
This approach keeps
the device managed by MDM
and eliminates the need to re-enroll
once it is back within policy.
Both methods give IT
the ability to ensure that information
is only available
to compliant users and devices,
and that corporate data is removed
without interfering
with a user's personal data
such as music, photos, or personal apps.
To permanently delete
all media and data on a device,
MDM can remotely wipe a Mac.
If a user has lost their device,
IT can also choose to send
a remote lock command to the device.
This process locks the device
and requires a password
created by the administrator
to unlock and resume use of the device.
Providing our users
with the necessary applications
to perform their duties
is essential to the success
of our business operations.
Device-based app management
allows us to distribute apps
directly to our users' devices
with Apple Business Manager and MDM.
And the process
to get devices up and running is easy,
whether they're assigned
to a specific user or not.
We use VPP and MDM
to assign and distribute apps
directly to a device
instead of requiring the user’s Apple ID.
This includes installing apps
on MacOS devices
without first configuring an Apple ID
or sending an invitation to a user.
If your organization
has a large number of devices,
you may benefit from
enabling MacOS content caching
which locally caches apps,
operating system updates,
and other content from Apple.
Several new features
are forthcoming in macOS Big Sur,
which will further enhance
app distribution.
One of the key new features
is managed apps.
Managed apps will empower users
to install their previously used apps
via their Apple ID.
Managed apps will also provide IT admins
with the ability
to lock important applications
to prevent those apps from being removed
or used maliciously.
For additional details
on new features within macOS Big Sur,
please see these related sessions
and the previously mentioned
identity session.
Let's review.
Zero-touch enrollment is a real thing
and will make your life much easier.
User experiences
are significantly improved
through user-friendly approaches
to common problems.
Hardware deployment can be
a hands-off, efficient process
for users and admins alike.
The sky is the limit
with security settings.
They can be customized
based on business needs,
user roles, DS groups, and other criteria.
There is no one-size-fits-all approach
to device management.
Use what works best for your organization
and your goals.
Start small and expand
your device management solutions
and complexity over time.
Zero-touch enrollment allows
efficient provisioning of devices to users
without the need for IT
to touch or configure each device.
And finally, the ability to unbox and go
provides a great user experience.
Thank you very much
for attending this session.
I hope you enjoy
the rest of your WWDC 2020 experience.