Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Tommy Pauly.
Encrypted DNS is a key technology
for improving internet privacy.
And it's supported natively
on Apple platforms
as an underlying technology
that you as a developer
can enable for users.
If you provide a public DNS service,
you can write an app,
or a configuration profile,
to let people use
your encrypted DNS server.
You can also opt in to encrypted DNS
for specific connections
within your own apps.
Before we dive into how you use
encrypted DNS on Apple platforms,
let's talk about what DNS is,
and why it matters for privacy.
DNS is the domain name system.
It's what takes a name that you see
for a web page in Safari,
and turns it into the actual IP addresses
of servers on the internet.
Your devices are using DNS
every time you access the internet.
When your app accesses a website,
the system asks a question, a DNS query,
to turn that name into a set of addresses.
Generally, the question is sent
to a DNS server
configured by your local network.
So where does privacy
come into the picture?
One concern
is that DNS questions and answers
are usually sent over
an unencrypted transport, UDP.
That means that other devices
on the network
can not only see
what names you're looking up,
but they can even interfere
with the answers.
The other privacy concern
is that you may not trust the DNS resolver
on your local network.
If you've joined a public Wi-Fi network,
your internet usage could be tracked
or blocked.
So how does encrypted DNS
improve this situation?
Encrypted DNS, simply put,
is using encryption to protect
your DNS questions and answers.
And if you don't trust
the network you're on,
it can also involve sending your questions
to a DNS server that you do trust.
Starting this year,
Apple platforms natively support
encrypted DNS.
There are two supported protocols.
DNS over TLS, also called DoT,
and DNS over HTTPS, also called DoH.
Both of these use TLS
to encrypt DNS messages.
DoH additionally uses HTTP
to improve performance.
There are two ways that encrypted DNS
can be enabled.
The first way is to choose
a single DNS server
as the default resolver
for all apps on the system.
If you provide a public DNS server,
you can now write
a NetworkExtension app
that configures the system
to use your server.
Or, if you use mobile device management,
MDM,
to configure enterprise settings
on devices,
you can push down a profile
to configure encrypted DNS settings
for your networks.
The second way to enable encrypted DNS
is to opt in directly from an app.
If you want your app
to use encrypted DNS,
even if the rest of the system isn't yet,
you can select a specific server to use
for some or all of your app's connections.
Let's start by looking at how
the system-wide DNS settings work.
System DNS settings can be configured
either by a NetworkExtension app
that uses NEDNSSettingsManager,
or an MDM profile that contains
a DNSSettings payload.
Both of these methods allow you
to specify the same content.
A DNS server configuration
that identifies which server to use,
and which protocol the server supports,
and a set of Network Rules
that allows you to customize
when your DNS settings should apply.
Let's look at how you specify
the server configuration
using NetworkExtension.
Use the shared
NEDNSSettingsManager object
to first load in
any existing configuration.
Next, you can define settings
for either a DNS over HTTPS server,
or a DNS over TLS server.
In this example, we're using DoH.
You can provide
the server's IP addresses,
which are optional,
and the server URL, which is required.
You set this object
into the "dnsSettings" property.
You then call saveToPreferences
to apply the configuration to the system.
At this point,
a user can enable your DNS server
in the settings app.
Next, let's look at the Network Rules part
of the configuration.
Specifying Network Rules allows you
to ensure that your DNS settings
are compatible with different networks.
Encrypted DNS can be great for privacy,
but a public DNS server isn't able
to resolve private names
that are only known to local networks.
For example, only a DNS server
on an enterprise Wi-Fi network
can resolve certain private names
that are accessed by employees.
Some aspects of compatibility
are handled for you automatically.
For these, you don't need to specify
Network Rules.
Captive network detection,
like when someone logs on
to a café network
is automatically granted an exception.
Similarly, if a VPN is active,
resolution within the VPN tunnel
will use the VPN's DNS settings
and not your system-wide settings.
However,
handling cases like private names
on enterprise Wi-Fi networks
requires setting up Network Rules.
Your Network Rules can define behavior
for specific network types,
like Wi-Fi or cellular,
and specific Wi-Fi SSIDs.
On matching networks,
you can disable
your DNS settings entirely,
or only grant exceptions
for specific private domains.
Here's how to set up some Network Rules
in your app.
Your app should allow users
to configure these kinds of rules.
To create an exception
for a work network,
define a rule for a Wi-Fi network
with a particular SSID.
The list of connection rules
defines a domain,
in this case, enterprise.example.net,
that should not use your DNS settings.
Overall, this rule says
that your DNS settings
should be used on the work Wi-Fi network
for everything other than
the private enterprise domain.
You can also set up rules
to disable your DNS settings
on an entire category of networks
using a Disconnect rule.
Here, we're disabling DNS settings
on all cellular networks.
The last rule you should set
should always be a catchall.
In this case,
let's make sure your DNS settings
are on by default
by using a Connect rule.
You store your Network Rules
as an ordered list,
and then can save the configuration.
Now we're ready to see
a DNS Settings app in action.
Here's an example project that configures
the system-wide DNS settings.
In our app,
we use NEDNSSettingsManager.
Here, we can define
the server configuration,
and we can also set up the Network Rules
based on the user preferences.
This particular app supports enabling
or disabling
on both cellular and Wi-Fi networks.
Before we run the app,
we need to make sure that
the DNS Settings capability
is enabled in Xcode.
To check this,
go to your Project Settings,
and then over to Signing & Capabilities.
The DNS Settings capability is one
of the NetworkExtension capabilities.
And since we're configuring a protocol
that's supported by the system,
we don't need to implement
an extension point.
We only need to build an app.
Let's look at that app now.
When we run the app,
the configuration is installed,
but not active immediately.
We can enable or disable our settings
on Wi-Fi or cellular,
and then enable the entire configuration
in the settings app.
We go to Settings, General,
and look at VPN & Network.
Here, there's a section for DNS
where your app will show up
once you've installed your configuration.
If you select your settings,
they will be automatically applied
to the whole system.
And if you go back to your app,
you can now see that the configuration
is active.
That's all you have to do.
At this point, your DNS settings
will apply to all apps on the system.
Be aware that some networks may block
using your encrypted DNS server
by policy.
These networks might be trying
to filter traffic
by looking at DNS queries.
If this occurs, a Wi-Fi network is marked
with a privacy warning.
Connections in apps will fail
rather than compromise your privacy.
If you don't provide a DNS service
that the entire system can use,
but you still want to use encrypted DNS
in your app,
you can enable encrypted DNS
throughout your app,
or for specific connections.
This approach works
no matter what system APIs you use:
URLSessionTasks,
Network framework connections,
or POSIX APIs like getaddrinfo.
Let's take a look
at enabling encrypted DNS
with Network framework.
You select your options
with a PrivacyContext.
You create one PrivacyContext
for every set of connections
that share DNS settings.
When you require encryption,
you can provide a DNS server
configuration to use as a fallback.
That means that any system-wide
DNS configuration will take precedence,
but your app's fallback
will kick in otherwise.
Here, we use the URL of a DoH server.
When you create parameters
for your connections,
set the PrivacyContext
you created earlier.
Then, start your connections,
and they will use encrypted DNS.
You can also check
whether encrypted DNS
was used on a given connection.
Once a connection is ready,
request an EstablishmentReport.
This report has a list
of resolution steps.
You can check which protocol
was used for DNS:
HTTPS, TLS, UDP, or TCP.
Note that answers that came from a cache
may not have any protocol set.
If you want to use encrypted DNS
throughout your app,
you can configure
the default PrivacyContext.
This applies your configuration
to every DNS resolution initiated
by your app,
either when you use URLSessionTasks,
or when you use lower-layer APIs
like getaddrinfo.
Now you're ready
to try out encrypted DNS.
If you provide a public DNS service,
write an app
that uses NEDNSSettingsManager
to deliver your settings.
If you have an enterprise MDM solution,
use profiles to enable encrypted DNS
on your networks.
And if you want to opt in directly
from your app,
adopt PrivacyContexts
in Network framework.
For more information on this topic,
please visit the following session URL.
And thanks for watching.