Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Drew Haas, and I'm an engineer
on the accessibility team.
Today, I'm going to talk about how
you can make your app visually accessible.
When you think about visual accessibility,
you might think about VoiceOver,
the built-in screen reader on iOS.
And you'd be right, because VoiceOver
speaks the items on-screen.
It also allows you to navigate
and interact with your device
without you needing to look at it.
But there's so much more
to visual accessibility.
Vision loss is best described
as a broad continuum.
That's because people experience
a wide range of visual impairment.
Some people have full sight,
partial sight or low sight,
and some have no sight at all.
And there's a lot in between,
like color blindness,
light sensitivity,
motion sensitivity and more.
Since each person's experience
with vision loss is unique,
iOS offers a range
of visual accessibility settings
so that everyone can get the most
out of their device
in a way that works best for them.
Today, I'll talk about
some of the great ways that your app
can provide a visual experience
that is inclusive to everyone.
First, I'll talk about the use of color
and shapes in your app,
which are a great way for you to add
a personal touch, like branding.
Next, I want to break down what it means
for text to be readable.
You can leverage different text attributes
and layout changes in your app
to make sure everyone has
a great reading experience.
And last, in accessibility settings,
users can customize
their display preferences,
which may alter
the appearance of your app.
I'll make sure you know
just what to look out for
as you make your app visually accessible.
When designing an app,
sometimes you may ask yourself,
"How can I make
this particular UI element stand out?"
Using color is often a great way
to create emphasis,
but we don't want to rely on color alone.
That's because for people
that are color-blind or have low vision,
using color only to create emphasis
can get lost.
There are extra steps you can take
to achieve good design,
and I'll give you a hint:
It's shapes.
I'm searching for a new game to play
in Apple Arcade.
Sneaky Sasquatch looks like fun.
In the App Store,
buttons use the color system blue,
and some use shapes
to help them stand out...
like the "start playing" button,
which is using color,
and it has a shape around it.
This really helps it stand out,
and lets a viewer know
it's not just a standard label.
The extra visualization
captures my attention and draws me in,
but I'll have to save this game for later.
Let's talk about another example.
Although tab bars only use color
by default to indicate the active tab,
you can enable
the Button Shapes accessibility setting
to get additional visualizations.
If you want your buttons
to really stand out
while the button shapes setting
is enabled,
we're bringing new API to iOS 14
to help you accomplish this.
If you can't fit button shapes
in your default design,
you should provide an alternate appearance
for people with this setting enabled.
To check this setting, you can call
button-Shapes-Enabled on UIAccessibility,
or you can observe the button-Shapes-
Enabled-Status-Did-Change-Notification
to run some code on the fly
when this setting is changed.
Last year in iOS 13, we added new API
for Differentiate without Color,
and this is a great way
to extend these ideas beyond just buttons.
You should apply this design practice
to things like status icons,
text with distinguishing colors,
or anything else that relies
on color alone to convey meaning.
If you aren't sure where to start,
try using SF Symbols.
We provide over 1,500 consistent,
highly configurable symbols
you can use in your app.
There are so many to choose from,
but if you don't find something
that fits perfectly,
you can create your own by expanding on
icons provided by SF Symbols.
Fun, right?
SF Symbols are really powerful because
they look great at any weight and scale.
This means
not only are you getting great symbolism,
but you can configure the symbol
to scale with text size and style.
Let's dive in to some of my own UI,
where I'm just getting started
designing the visual experience
with color and shapes.
I'm working on
a constellation tracking app, Starstruck.
Early stages of development
are the best time
to start thinking about
visual accessibility accommodations,
but it's really never too late to dig in.
I have a list of zodiac constellations,
and I'm distinguishing between them
by choosing a custom color for each.
If you're color-blind,
these might not stand out like I'd intend.
Since I'm already working toward
making these stand out,
I don't want to stop at using just color,
so I designed symbols to use in my app,
giving each constellation
a distinct visual experience
by using color and shapes.
This way, more people get to have a fun
viewing experience when they use my app.
I'm also using bold text optionally
to improve readability here,
and I'll touch more on that later.
When we do use color in our apps,
it's important to keep in mind that color
contrast plays a huge role in readability,
and it can be the difference between
someone being able to see an element
or having it completely blend in.
The Increase Contrast accessibility
setting makes elements stand out
by updating colors
to high-contrast appearances.
iOS offers a range of system colors
that automatically adapt to settings
like Increase Contrast.
If you're not using system colors,
you'll need to be aware of this setting
to improve the visual experience
in your app.
As a general rule,
colors should get darker in Light Mode
and lighter in Dark Mode.
I know that might sound confusing,
so here's an example.
In default contrast, my zodiac symbols
are using colors I designed them with,
but when Increase Contrast is turned on,
I need something a little bit darker here.
Now, I want you to keep an eye
on the symbols in each cell
as I enable Increase Contrast in settings.
Ready?
Okay.
I know that might have looked subtle,
but this is a really big deal.
For some people, having this boost
in contrast can make a huge difference.
If you are using custom colors
and symbols like this in your app,
you'll need update the tint color
or provide alternate assets
for high-contrast appearances.
In my project's asset catalog,
I can configure the appearance
of my symbol
by making changes
in the Attributes Inspector.
Under Appearances,
you can check the High Contrast box
to provide alternate versions
of your symbols.
The High Contrast appearance will be used
when Increase Contrast is on.
The Accessibility Inspector in Xcode has
a super-handy Color Contrast Calculator.
You can use this tool to calculate
the contrast between any two colors.
Here, I'm calculating the contrast
between my white symbol,
which is in the foreground, against
my custom purple color in the background.
This gives me a ratio of 4.5-to-1,
which is generally the lowest acceptable
ratio for most cases.
And here's my symbol's
high-contrast appearance.
I'm darkening the background color
to really make that symbol pop,
and my ratio is way better, at 7.5-to-1.
All right. Now that I've provided
all of these variations, the work is done.
iOS will automatically switch between them
based on anyone's display preference.
And a shout-out to Smart Invert Colors,
which, like Dark Mode,
darkens bright white UI elements.
The difference is that Smart Invert
Colors generally has higher contrast,
so people with light sensitivity
may prefer to use it.
And whereas Dark Mode support
in your apps is recommended,
Smart Invert Colors is a system setting
that asserts an inverted UI over any app.
So it's great to keep in mind,
someone using your app
might prefer to use Smart Invert Colors.
You should specially flag certain views
in your app so they don't get inverted,
like photos, videos and app icons.
You can do that by setting
accessibility-Ignores-Invert-Colors
on any UIView subclass.
So when designing with color and shapes,
you should take a variety of approaches
to create visual emphasis.
Doing this adds a lot of character
to your app-- Hello, branding--
while also making sure that
the rich visual experience in your app
is inclusive.
And be sure to observe
and respect people's preferences
if your default design
is not accommodating.
Next,
I want to talk about text readability.
iOS provides support for changing
the size of text on your device.
Smaller text can provide a higher content
density by fitting more words on-screen,
and large text can make things easy
on the eyes.
Some people, however,
rely on larger text sizes
in order to read the content
on their device.
When designing your app, keep text size,
weight, and layout in mind
for clarity and readability.
My biggest tip is to think about these
early on in the design process.
This is a great way to ensure
your app looks good,
not only for every content size,
but also across many devices
with different display sizes.
So design with large text in mind.
You should avoid truncating text
as the content size increases
so that the user doesn't miss out
on anything.
Instead, wrap labels and use
all of the available display width.
Remember those symbols
I talked about earlier?
Well, those also should scale with text.
You can override the function
trait-Collection-Did-Change,
which gets called when display traits
are adjusted on the device.
And UITraitCollection lets you get the
device's preferred content size category.
And, yes,
you can use a comparison operator
to perform comparisons on this enum.
It's my favorite thing ever.
In Starstruck,
when the user changes their text size,
I want to calculate
whether it's a default font size
or a large accessibility font size.
For default font sizes, my stack views
containing the cell's symbol and label
are set to the horizontal axis
with center alignment.
When an accessibility font size
is enabled,
I'm flipping the axis
and choosing leading alignment.
This lets my label take advantage
of the full width of the display
instead of sharing some of it
with the symbol.
I'm also always setting this label's
line count to zero instead of one,
so that if it were longer,
it would wrap for as long as it needs.
Remember how I mentioned
that I'm using bold text optionally
to improve readability?
Using Bold Text
not only lets labels stand out
when they're up against symbols,
but also lets them stand out
when they're with other text as well.
Did I mention Starstruck
lets users geek out about star stats?
Here, I'm using bold text optionally
to create visual distinction
between the title and detail label.
Creating emphasis
with bold text is awesome.
In fact, system-provided font styles
lets you really change up
your text weight,
which means we handle the heavy lifting,
and you don't need to lift a finger.
The Bold Text accessibility setting
is for people that need this emphasis
on all text in the system.
Sometimes thin and even default
font styles are hard to read.
If you aren't using system font styles
for text labels in your app,
then it may not respond well
to the Bold Text setting.
You can check the setting
by calling is-Bold-Text-Enabled
on UIAccessibility and make updates
to your text styles manually.
Last, I want to talk about
a few other display preferences
which may alter
the appearance of your app.
In my app, I've set up a parallax effect
on my constellation view controller.
A parallax effect is a UIMotionEffect
that helps me create a perception
of depth between stars in the foreground
and the vastness of the universe
in the background.
As I gently move my device,
the stars in the foreground shift
against the artwork in the back.
Another example of parallax
you might be familiar with
is on the Home Screen.
These effects are a lot of fun
to use and experience,
but for some people,
this can be disorienting
and cause motion sickness.
There is a collection
of display accommodation settings
that people can enable
if they're sensitive to motion.
While these display settings are on,
the user will expect adjustments
to motion on their device,
like suppressing small idle animations,
parallax or other motion effects,
auto-playing videos or GIFs,
and even slide transitions.
We love using effects like this
to bring the software experience to life,
but it's also our duty
to listen and respect the setting
for users that have it enabled.
If you are using dramatic
or frequent animations in your app,
check is-Reduce-Motion-Enabled
on UIAccessibility before performing them.
And you should observe the reduce-Motion-
Status-Did-Change-Notification
to make adjustments if the setting changes
while your app is open.
I want to tell you a little more about
the Reduce Motion setting
Prefer Cross-Fade Transitions.
As I move through
these navigation controllers,
push segues are performed
with sliding animations.
The next view controller slides into place
to cover the previous one.
When the Prefer Cross-Fade Transition
setting is on,
we replace the sliding transitions
for something a little more subtle.
And now you can too.
In iOS 14, we are introducing new API for
the Prefer Cross-Fade Transition setting.
If you're already using UIKits,
UINavigationController,
this work already comes for free.
But if you've implemented
custom slide transitions in your app,
this API is for you.
You can check if you need to cross-fade
your transitions
by calling prefers-Cross-Fade-Transitions
on UIAccessibility
or observing the notification.
Last is the Reduced Transparency setting,
which sets blur effects
to become completely opaque.
One big benefit of this
is text readability,
because a blurry background
might have varying levels of contrast,
making things hard to read.
While my users are geeking out
about star stats,
I added a visual effect
to blur some artwork in the background.
This helps me create an experience
that is immersive and feels unique,
but this isn't suitable for everyone.
Some blur effects can cause the background
to have varying levels of contrast.
When up against text, some readers
will have a hard time seeing this.
Or it can make them feel dizzy.
So when Reduced Transparency is on,
system blur effects and vibrancy effects
are adjusted to become
a single solid color.
For some,
this makes it much easier to read.
If you're not using system visual effects
for blurs or vibrancy,
UIAccessibility also provides API
free to use
to check the display preference
for Reduced Transparency.
By accommodating these display settings,
you can be sure your app looks great
on anyone's device.
All of this is so important
because being able to use an app
that is inclusive and accommodating
is, simply put,
empowering for our customers.
Thank you for all of your work
in making your app accessible
for everyone.
Now, I'm inviting you
to go in accessibility settings,
find some of the settings
I talked about today
and turn them on,
so you can see what your app looks like.
You'll be surprised
by what already looks great,
and this will be the perfect place
to start figuring out
what you can work on next.
Thanks, everyone.