Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Hannah Gillis,
and I’m here to show you how to declare
that your high-performance app
or game requires advanced capabilities
unlocked by the latest hardware.
To get started,
let’s begin with a refresher
of the required
device capability settings in Xcode.
We’ve had settings here for a while,
but you might not be familiar
with using them.
Required device capabilities
is a list of device-related features
your app requires to run.
You add entries to this list
in your app’s Info.plist using Xcode.
Entries in this list
indicate the specific capabilities
of certain device families
that your app requires.
This list informs the App Store
which device-related features
your app needs in order to run.
And it prevents customers
from installing apps on a device
that doesn’t have the necessary features,
and an app will simply
not launch on devices
that don’t satisfy
your device-related feature requirements.
There are a few existing
device capabilities
to enable high-end games
and pro applications on our devices.
One is the Metal key,
which means your app or game
requires the Metal Graphics API.
Metal advanced graphics was enabled by
the capabilities of the A7 chip and GPU.
Another key is for ARKit,
which indicates that your app
requires devices that support AR,
typically using an A9 chip or higher.
In iOS 14, we are introducing a new key
specifically for performance,
which requires devices
using an A12 Bionic chip or above.
Specifying your need for A12 performance
can help bring console and PC-quality
games and pro applications to iOS.
Here’s the name of the key value
to indicate an A12 Bionic requirement,
and it’s provided in iOS 14 and Xcode 12.
It indicates that your app
requires a device
with the capabilities
of an A12 Bionic chip,
which include a 6-core CPU and 4-core GPU,
the second-generation Neural Engine,
support for ARKit 3,
which brings people occlusion
and motion capture to your AR experiences,
and Metal GPU Family Apple 5.
Here are some of the latest iOS devices
using an A12 chip or higher
that support your application.
iPhone 11 and 11 Pro.
iPhone SE 2nd Generation.
iPad Mini 5th Generation.
And iPad Pro 4th Generation.
You define this
performance level using Xcode.
Navigate to your Info.plist, add an item
and choose the A12 requirement
from the drop-down menu, as shown here.
Now, when should you require A12 Bionic
or later for your application?
First, remember that we encourage you
to make applications
that scale across as many devices
as possible for all customers.
We work to ensure that iOS runs great
on both older and newer hardware
to help enable this.
In rare occasions, however,
the experience you are creating
is going to require the very latest
hardware to deliver the best gameplay
or cutting-edge graphics.
So here’s what we recommend checking.
Most importantly,
do your performance optimization.
Make sure you’ve made the effort
to bring your app
to all devices that support iOS 14.
We provide various tools to help tune
the performance of your applications,
and we highly advise utilizing them.
With this in mind, you can be confident
when determining that your app needs
the additional processing power
of an A12 Bionic chip or higher.
Lastly, remember that your app
should be aligned with iOS 14
to take advantage of this new key.
We encourage you to check out
our other sessions
around optimizing graphics,
games and memory usage
to ultimately delight as many customers,
all with various devices, as possible.
When an app declares
this performance capability,
that information
is also reflected in the App Store.
In specifying this key,
customers are informed
whether or not their device
supports the application.
It even prevents users from
downloading apps on unsupported devices,
so you can be sure your customers
always have clear communication.
I’m really excited to share this
new performance capability with you.
By specifying that your application
requires devices
with the minimum of an A12 Bionic chip,
we can ensure that high-end games
and desktop-quality apps
are brought to iOS and supported
for the best user experience.
Finally, I invite you
to try this new key for yourself,
using iOS 14 Beta and TestFlight
for validation.
And that wraps up
the new device performance key.
As always, I’m looking forward
to seeing the apps you build.
Take advantage of these unique
capabilities on iPhone and iPad.
Thanks!