Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to "Design Great Widgets."
My name is Mac and I'm joined later
by my colleague, Christian,
and we both work on the Human Interface
Design Team here at Apple.
We're really excited
to talk through the process
of how you can design amazing widgets
for your own apps.
But before we get started,
let's take a quick look at what's new.
In iOS 14, the entire widget experience
has been completely redesigned.
At its foundation
is an entirely new visual aesthetic
and powerful new capabilities.
The information
your widget chooses to surface
can be more up-to-date
and contextual than ever,
and drag and drop editing gives people
direct control over their widgets
in an intuitive and flexible way.
One of the things
we're really excited about
is that people can now
add these new widgets
directly onto their Home Screen pages.
This enables an all-new way
for users to experience widgets
and, likewise, a whole new
set of considerations to think about
as you approach designing them.
Another feature we've created
is Smart Stacks.
These let you add several
different widgets into a single location
and quickly flick between
the different widgets inside.
But what is really powerful
is that Smart Stacks
dynamically change and adapt
to how you use them.
Based on your behavior and context,
a Smart Stack will automatically rotate
to show you the most relevant widget
at a given time.
So the information you are looking for
is already there
before you even have to lift a finger.
For example, when I wake up,
I like to know what the weather
is going to be for the day.
When I'm on my way to work, I always play
some of my favorite recent music.
Later, in the afternoon,
I often check how much traffic there is
and how long it might take me to get home.
And in the evening,
I like to catch up and read through
some of the top news stories from the day.
These are just some examples
from my own widget stack,
but the widgets and behaviors
of the Smart Stack
are different for each person
based on the way they use their device
and the information
that matters most to them.
This was a super quick look
at some of what's new,
but it's important to remember
all of these different ways
someone can interact with your widget,
and we'll revisit certain features
more deeply
as they pertain to different sections
of the design process.
When designing a widget, there are
two main parts of the process to focus on:
ideation and creation.
In this first section,
we're going to cover some principles
to help guide your ideas
and also look at some of the new features
that are important to consider
at this step in the process.
Starting with design principles.
The new widget system
is all about content.
To create a great widget,
you need to understand
what the most useful information
and experiences are
that people return to your app for.
Three useful principles
we've found to focus on
when thinking about ideas
is to look for things
that are personal,
informational and contextual.
We want to look for things
that are personal
because it can allow for
a deeper emotional connection
with a piece of your app or
an experience that it enables for someone.
Widgets provide a great way
to see a top-level overview of information
from a variety of sources
on someone's device.
Surfacing the right information
can save people from doing
commonly repeated actions in your app.
People have their devices with them
throughout the day,
and there are tons of signals
to infer a person's circumstances.
Context helps surface
the right information at the right moment
and allows for a better experience
that, at its best,
feels like is magically predicting
someone's needs and next steps.
Let's take a look
at how some of these principles
informed our decisions and ideas
while designing some of our own widgets.
For Calendar, just like the app icon,
it shows the day of the week
and the current date.
Your next meeting or event was
the most important piece of information
to surface from within the app.
Glanceable details like the start time
and event location
save people a potential step in
opening the app to find this information.
If you have a busy schedule
with lots of events,
it collapses
some of the less relevant information
and prioritizes the single
most important piece of information
from each event.
When your day is almost over
and there's no more events,
rather than just showing a blank widget,
when possible,
we instead start telling you
about what is coming up next
and happening in your day tomorrow.
This is a great example of thinking beyond
just the context of the current moment
and broadening the scope
of contextual relevance
by the hour, day or even week.
A more personal detail
is the holiday calendar
for the country that you live in.
It adds a nice reminder
on special holidays.
And when it's a contact's birthday,
we show a present glyph
and elevate it at the top,
so right from your Home Screen,
you can feel a personal connection to them
during their birthday.
The Photos widget is a great example
of just how personal
a widget experience can be.
We found that
the most delightful experience
was to surface the best photos
instead of just the most recent ones.
In addition to photo memories,
we also surface featured photos,
and another way
of taking advantage of context
was to show you photo memories
from the current day in years past.
In the Weather widget,
we surface the city name,
current temperature,
including the high and low,
and what the forecast will be
for the rest of the day
in your current location.
Weather is a really great example
of how contextual a widget can be.
We display unique weather events
such as high wind, thunderstorms
and if and when
it's going to start raining.
And if it does, we contextually increase
the resolution of the next hour's forecast
so you can see up-to-the-minute detail
of when there might be a break in
the downpour or when it will stop raining.
For Maps, it's useful
to be oriented geographically
and see what's around you.
But we build on top of
this base spatial awareness.
When you're not at home
and you've driven somewhere,
we show where your parked car is.
And if you have a scheduled event,
we show how long it will take to get there
and contextualize the map
so you see the route you will take
and what's on the way.
When you're not at home, we show the ETA
for how long it will take to get back.
You can see how, in all of these examples,
the widgets are very dynamic
and informative,
and the contextual details
make the experience feel very personal
and adaptive to a person's needs.
One of the new capabilities
is the ability for people to edit widgets.
This is an important concept
to think about in the ideation phase
because it might change
how much information
you try to put into a single widget.
Let's take a look at how editing works
for the Weather widget.
In iOS 14, your widgets will jiggle
just like apps do in edit mode,
and you can tap on a widget here
to flip it around
and see what it allows for you to edit.
Here, the Weather widget lets me change
what location it's displaying
the weather conditions for.
By default,
it adapts to your current location,
so that when a person adds a widget,
they don't have to do any additional work.
If I tap on the location field,
I get a list
of all of my Favorite Weather cities,
as well as the ability
to search for other locations.
I'm going to change the location display
on this widget to Tokyo.
And when the widget flips back around,
it's now displaying the weather conditions
and information for that city.
But what is really cool
is widgets in iOS 14 let you add
as many additional widgets as you want
and edit each one to show
a different set of information.
Here, I'll add a second Weather widget,
and change this one
to show San Francisco's conditions.
One of the best parts of this feature
is that it eliminates the need
to create complex widget layouts
that represent
different entities of information
combined into a single widget,
and instead, lets a person choose how much
information they want to see from your app
by adding several widgets
and editing them to show
just what they want to keep track of.
Now, I can have both cities side by side.
Most of the new widgets in iOS
support editing like this,
and it's a great experience to add
and choose different Reminders lists,
Stocks, Notes
and world clocks, as shown here.
This is one of the main use cases
of configuration,
but there can be others too.
Consider what options
you could offer to people
that would maximize
the utility and flexibility
that people might get out of your widget.
Another thing to consider
in the ideation process
is deciding on
if you should offer multiple widgets.
For Stocks, we had two different ideas:
to offer a widget that shows
a glanceable compact summary
of your watch list information,
but also the ability to add
a single stock symbol as a separate widget
to keep track of it at a higher resolution
just like Weather did for cities
in the previous example.
Several other apps in iOS 14
offer multiple widgets,
including News, which lets you follow
top news from a specific topic,
and Notes,
that lets you pin a favorite note
or add a Shared Note Folder.
Now that we've taken you through
some important principles
and considerations to think through when
coming up with ideas for your widgets,
in the next part, Christian is going to
talk through the process
of how to take these ideas
and form them into beautiful widgets
that express
all that your app has to offer
in an elegant and consistent way.
Thanks, Mac. My name is Christian,
and I'm excited to take you through
how to make your widgets come to life.
Let's jump into the details
of creating your widget.
There's three things we're going to cover
as part of creation.
The first is sizes and interactions.
The new system supports three sizes
that you can design with:
small, medium and large.
We designed the small widget
to be all about the most useful
piece of content from your app
in a size that constrains
how much content can actually fit in it.
The small widget supports
a single tap target.
Tapping it should deep link
to the content that's on the widget.
Where you deep link to
will depend on how your app is structured.
Let look at some examples.
For our small Calendar widget,
since the widget is always showing
what event is coming up next,
we thought it made the most sense
to bring you to the latest event
in the app's day view.
When you tap on the widget,
the day view scrolls to the latest event
and gives you a nice glimpse
of the rest of your day around it.
For our small News widget,
since it previews a rich news story
that you might be interested in reading,
tapping it brings you
directly to that news story in the app.
Our medium and large widgets
are familiar shapes.
Both sizes fit more content
and support multiple tap targets.
Tapping a piece of content
in a medium or large widget
should also deep link you to the displayed
content that's on the widget,
like here in this News example.
Tapping either article brings you directly
to the news story you tapped on.
There's three different tap styles
supported in the widget system.
Fill style is best
for when you're deep linking
into a single piece of content.
Every small widget uses fill style
since it only supports one tap target.
Cell style is best
for when you're selecting
a piece of content in a widget
that lives in its own shape,
like here in our Files widget.
And content style is great for when
you're selecting a piece of content
that lives uncontained in a widget.
Next is all about content and personality.
The most important part
about making your widget come to life
is what lives in it.
You should think about content
and personality together
when you're designing your widget.
Ask yourself questions like,
"What are people looking for
when they launch my app?"
Also find distinct items of information
that people find useful in your app.
Let's look at a few examples of thinking
about content and personality together.
When designing our widget set,
we looked at finding personality
through how our apps look.
For Weather, we used the familiar
weather condition background,
as well as the iconography from the app.
For News, we took inspiration
from the rich story images
that you see in news stories.
And for Calendar, we took inspiration
from its simplistic look
and familiar red tint color,
focusing all on what events
are coming up next.
Another approach for finding personality
is taking inspiration from your app icon.
Like Notes, where we took on
the icon's notepad illustration style,
Podcasts, where we used
the icon's purple gradient,
and Tips, where we used
the icon's yellow gradient.
When it comes to
laying out content in your widget,
there were two patterns we found
when designing our widget set.
The first is a layout
that expands across all three sizes,
like Weather, where we add
additional information across each size.
The second is a layout
that is completely unique across sizes,
like News here.
The small widget prioritizes rich content
that fills up the whole space,
while the medium widget
focuses on showing more news stories.
When you're designing for each size,
make sure not to scale up your
smaller widget into your larger widget.
Think about the information
you're working with
and what makes the most sense
for each size.
For the large Screen Time widget,
since we had more useful information
that we could include and more space,
we increased the size of the chart
and also included category
and app details.
If you don't have more information to show
in your larger sizes, though,
it's fine to only support
specific sizes of your idea.
All sizes for an idea aren't required.
You might come up with an idea
like these examples here
where you want to pack a summary
of information in a small widget.
We recommend only including
a max of four pieces of information
in the small widget size.
Now, let's go into some more detail
about widget patterns.
As we designed our widgets,
there were several common layout patterns
that emerged.
Here they are across the different
small, medium and large sizes.
There are a mix of single-item
and denser multi-item summary layouts.
These patterns serve
as a helpful starting place
and a good way to try out an idea
in a format that already works well.
When designing your own custom layouts,
follow the default 16pt layout margins
across all sizes to make sure the content
in your widget feels consistent
when it's placed next to other widgets.
For layouts with graphical shapes
like circles and inset platters,
use tighter 11pt margins across all sizes.
Shape corners that sit
close to the edges of your widget
should appear concentric
with the widget's corner radius.
Since the widget's corner radius
changes across different device sizes,
we provide a SwiftUI container that
you can assign to shapes in your widget
that will make them concentric
with the widget's corner radius
without needing to manually specify
corner radius values.
For type, you should use SF Pro,
or other variants of San Francisco
that are available
like SF Mono and SF Pro Rounded.
If a custom font is important
to how your widget
represents its brand or personality,
make sure it's applied in a way
so that your widget still feels at home
alongside other widgets.
A widget should look great
in both Light and Dark appearance modes.
For Calendar, the whole widget changes
between Light and Dark appearances
just like its app does.
For Podcasts,
since the whole background is a gradient,
it already works nicely in both modes.
And for Notes,
it has a mix of bold colors and white,
so we adopt the note contents
for the darkened appearance mode
to reflect how the note appears
in the app.
Every widget must provide a placeholder
which is shown when the system has no way
of displaying your widget's data.
You should show
the base graphical elements in this state
and block-in areas of text where
your information is shown in the layout.
This way, when the system
goes from placeholder to the proper data,
the content can replace
the static elements
without having the layout or color
shift around.
The last thing we want to go over
are a handful of tips to keep in mind
when you're designing your widgets.
You should only use a logo in your widget
if your app is an aggregator of content
from different sources,
like these examples here.
To keep this treatment consistent
across different widgets,
your logo should always sit
in the top right corner.
Avoid using wordmarks in this space
and anywhere else in your widget.
Another thing to avoid
is putting your app icon in your widget.
Also avoid putting your app name
in your widget
as it will feel redundant
with the app label
that already appears underneath of it
on the Home Screen.
Don't put text that instructs a user
or talks to them.
Instead, if you feel there is
something important to communicate,
do it in a graphical way.
When displaying
chronological information on a widget,
don't use language like "last updated"
or "last checked."
We've talked through
where to start with your idea,
how you should surface
the most useful information from your app
and all the details about
how to bring your ideas to life.
We're really excited to see
what experiences you create
with the new widget system in iOS 14.