Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Sean James,
and I'm a GPU Software Engineer.
In this session, we're going to talk about
the brand new ray tracing API
we've added to Metal this year.
This new API allows you
to perform intersection testing
directly from within any compute kernel.
It also allows you to write
intersection functions
to customize the intersection process.
Ray tracing applications are based on
tracing the paths that rays take
as they interact with a scene.
Ray tracing has applications
in a lot of domains
such as audio and physics simulation,
but one of the most popular applications
is photo-realistic rendering.
In rendering, ray tracing is used to model
individual rays of light,
so we can simulate effects
such as reflections, soft shadows,
indirect lighting, and more.
Let's first review how ray tracing works,
then we'll look at
the new Metal ray tracing API.
We start by generating rays
which are emitted from the camera
into the scene.
We then test those rays for intersection
with the geometry in the scene.
Each intersection point
represents light bouncing off a surface.
How much light bounces,
and in what direction,
determines what objects look like.
So we'll compute a color for each
intersection point and update the image.
This process is called shading,
and it can also generate additional rays
which bounce further into the scene.
We test those rays
for intersection as well
and repeat this process
as many times as we'd like
to simulate light
bouncing around the scene.
For the last two years, we've talked about
how you can do this using
the Metal Performance Shaders framework.
We start by launching a compute kernel
which generates the initial set of rays
and writes them into a Metal buffer.
We can then use
the MPSRayIntersector class
to intersect those rays with the scene.
The intersector writes the intersection
results into another buffer.
We can then launch a final compute kernel
which reads those intersections
and does the shading.
Additional rays can be written
back into the ray buffer,
and we can launch
these two compute kernels in a loop
to simulate light bouncing.
This works great,
but it requires us to split up our code
into three separate compute kernels.
It also requires us to pass rays
and intersections through memory.
In contrast,
in the new Metal ray tracing API,
this intersector object is now available
directly from the shading language.
This allows us to combine
all three kernels
into a single compute kernel.
Since we don't need to pass ray data
between kernels anymore,
we can also eliminate
the ray and intersection buffers.
This removes the need to read
and write memory
to pass rays and intersections around.
This is also a much more flexible
programming model.
For example, instead of launching
compute kernels over and over,
the outer loop can be represented
by a simple loop in the shading language.
Let's see how
a basic ray tracing kernel works.
We'll launch
a two-dimensional compute kernel
with one thread per pixel.
We start by generating a ray.
This is just some math which produces
the initial ray for the given pixel.
We then create an intersector object.
This object is responsible
for finding intersections
between rays
and the geometry in the scene.
We can set various properties
on this object to customize its behavior.
For example, we can speed up cases
such as shadows and ambient occlusion
by accepting the first intersection
rather than exhaustively searching
for the closest one.
We then pass the ray to the intersector
and get back an intersection result.
Finally, we can use the intersection
result to perform shading.
Keep in mind that the intersection step
needs to do a lot of work,
so if you combine it
with complex shading code,
you may end up with a compute kernel
that runs at lower occupancy.
You'll need to profile your application
to find the best way to divide up work
between kernels for your application.
That's all we need to do
for basic intersection testing.
The other argument
to the intersect function
is an acceleration structure.
Acceleration structures
are data structures used to speed up
the ray tracing process.
These data structures
recursively partition space
so that we can quickly eliminate triangles
which could not
possibly intersect a given ray.
Like MPS, Metal takes care
of building this data structure for you.
All you need to do
is provide your geometry.
Here's how that works.
First, we need to create
a descriptor object
which describes
the acceleration structure to build.
Next, we need to allocate memory
to store the acceleration structure.
And finally,
we build the acceleration structure.
Let's start with the descriptor.
Metal supports
two types of acceleration structure:
primitive and instance
acceleration structures.
For this example, we'll create
a primitive acceleration structure.
As the name implies, these contain
primitives such as triangles.
Primitive acceleration structures
are composed of
individual pieces of geometry.
Metal also supports two types of geometry,
but for now, we'll focus on triangles.
Each piece of triangle geometry
can have its own vertex buffer,
index buffer, triangle count, and so on.
We start by creating a primitive
acceleration structure descriptor.
Next, we'll create a geometry descriptor.
In this example, we'll just create
a single triangle geometry descriptor.
Then we'll attach our vertex buffer
and specify the triangle count.
The triangle data will be embedded
into the acceleration structure,
so it's not necessary
to keep the vertex buffer around
once we've built
the acceleration structure.
We then simply add the geometry descriptor
to an array on
the acceleration structure descriptor.
Now that we've created the descriptor,
we can allocate memory
for the acceleration structure.
These are potentially
large memory allocations.
One of the improvements we've made
in the new Metal ray tracing API
is that Metal gives you full control
over when and where
acceleration structures are allocated.
This means you can reuse memory
or allocate it at a time
that's convenient for your application.
We start by calling a method
on the Metal device
which returns a struct
containing the sizes we need
to allocate the acceleration structure.
Next, we'll actually allocate
the acceleration structure
from the Metal device.
Finally, we'll also need to allocate
a scratch buffer.
This buffer will be used by Metal
as temporary storage
while building the acceleration structure,
and we can throw it away once we're done.
We won't need access to the data
in this buffer,
so we'll use
the private resource storage mode
to get the best performance.
We've now allocated memory
for the acceleration structure,
but it hasn't actually been built yet.
So, the final step
is to build the acceleration structure.
We've also made some improvements here.
Building acceleration structures
can take some time,
so Metal now gives you full control
over when they are built,
including which GPU command queue
and command buffer they're built on.
First, we'll create a command buffer
and, from it, one of the new
AccelerationStructureCommandEncoders.
Like the other Metal encoders,
this object is used
to schedule work on the GPU.
In this case, we'll encode
the actual build command,
providing the descriptor,
acceleration structure and scratch buffer.
Finally, we end encoding
and commit the command buffer.
This allows the GPU to get started
building the acceleration structure.
Acceleration structure builds
now run entirely on the GPU timeline
with no CPU synchronization,
so it's safe to schedule intersection work
on the GPU after this command buffer.
We've actually already seen
how to use an acceleration structure.
We simply pass it to the intersector.
As you can see,
acceleration structures bind
to normal Metal buffer binding points.
And there's a corresponding method
on the compute command encoder
and argument encoder
to bind acceleration structures
to these binding points.
So that's it for the basic building blocks
of the new Metal ray tracing API.
There are a few more advanced topics
we didn't have time to cover today,
so I'd encourage you to check out
our documentation and sample code.
I'd also like to encourage you to review
the previous two ray tracing talks
since many of the concepts are the same.
For example, like MPS,
Metal acceleration structures
support two-level instancing
of primitive acceleration structures,
which can be used to reduce memory usage.
Metal also supports refitting
existing acceleration structures,
which can be combined with instancing
to support dynamic geometry.
Finally, Metal acceleration structures
also support compaction,
which can be used to reclaim
significant amounts of memory
once an acceleration structure
has been built.
Next, we're going to talk about how
you can customize the intersection process
using intersection functions.
But first, let's see a demo
of everything we've covered so far.
This is an application
built by our Advanced Content Team
which demonstrates
the new Metal ray tracing API
applied to a complex scene.
What we're looking at now
is an interactive preview of the scene
recorded on a Mac Pro
with the new AMD Radeon Pro W5700X GPU.
The interactive preview is noisy
because we're only using
a single sample per pixel,
but it starts to converge
when the camera stops moving.
This is the way an artist
would see the scene while editing it.
For high-quality off-line rendering,
we would give each frame plenty of time
to converge to a noise-free image.
To give you a sense of
what the final result would look like,
we've rendered out
a fly-through of the scene
using 400 samples per pixel.
Special thanks to Quixel
for the use of their Megascans library.
This scene was assembled
from Megascans assets
and has over 32 million triangles.
The application works very similarly
to the outline I described earlier.
Using a rendering algorithm called
path tracing to simulate advanced effects
such as soft shadows, depth of field,
and indirect lighting.
We've now seen
the new Metal ray tracing API
in both an interactive application
and a full off-line renderer.
Next, let's move on
to one of the most exciting new features
of the new Metal API:
intersection functions.
So far, our programming model has been
that rays go in to the intersector
and intersections come out.
But the intersector
has always been a black box.
But there are actually a few cases
where you would want to customize
how the intersector works.
One example is alpha testing.
This is a common technique
with rasterization,
where we use a texture to mask off
parts of a triangle
that should be transparent.
This can be used to add
a lot of geometric detail
without increasing
the actual triangle count.
In this example,
the leaves get a lot more detailed
when we turn on alpha testing.
It's pretty easy to implement this
with rasterization,
where we can simply discard
the fragment from a fragment shader.
But with ray tracing,
it's a little more tricky
to implement this efficiently.
Each time we cast a ray, the intersector
will return the closest intersection.
However, in this case,
the intersection point
is actually transparent,
so we should ignore it.
So, we now have to cast a whole new ray
starting at the first intersection point.
Finally, we hit an opaque surface
and we can stop and move on to shading.
But each of these rays requires
a whole new trip to the intersector.
This is very inefficient
because we are constantly restarting
acceleration structure traversal
from the root of the tree structure.
A more efficient way to implement this
is with a triangle intersection function.
To understand how this works,
we'll need to look at
how the intersector works internally.
We start by traversing
the acceleration structure
until we find an intersection
between the ray and a piece of geometry.
We then check if the intersection
is closer than
the previous closest intersection.
If it is,
we make it the new closest intersection.
Then, we go back to traversing
the acceleration structure
Eventually, we will finish
and return the closest intersection.
Intersection functions
plug directly into this process.
These functions are called
each time we find an intersection.
The intersection function can then choose
to accept or reject the intersection.
If it accepts, then this becomes
the new closest intersection as usual.
But it can also reject the intersection,
in which case we go back
to traversing the acceleration structure,
discarding the intersection.
So, for our alpha testing example,
we can move the alpha testing logic
into an intersection function.
We will then only need to traverse
the acceleration structure once,
which is much more efficient.
Here's what a basic intersection function
looks like.
First we declare the function.
"Triangle" means
this is a triangle intersection function
and "triangle_data" means we want access
to the barycentric coordinates
of the intersection point.
The function returns a Boolean
indicating whether to accept
or reject the intersection.
We receive information
from the intersector
such as the primitive index,
geometry index,
and barycentric coordinates
of the intersection point,
along with other data
that isn't used here.
We can also bind our own resources
which we'll use
to access the alpha textures.
First, we'll look up
the alpha texture for this primitive.
Next, we'll use
the barycentric coordinates
to interpolate the texture coordinates.
This is exactly the same as
what you would do for the shading step.
Then we'll do the actual texture lookup,
and finally, we'll return true or false
depending on whether
the intersection point
is transparent or not.
But intersection functions
are not just limited to triangle geometry.
Metal also allows you to write
bounding box intersection functions.
These functions are invoked
when a ray intersects
a bounding box that you provide,
which can be used
to model custom primitives.
In this scene, the sphere is implemented
using a bounding box
intersection function.
Rays are tested
against the sphere mathematically
rather than modeling it with triangles.
This is a very simple example,
but bounding box intersection functions
can also be used to model
more complex surfaces such as curves.
In this example, we used
bounding box intersection functions
to render hair.
Each hair strand
is a custom cubic Bézier curve primitive,
and we used 10,000 of them
to give the hair its overall shape.
Although intersecting each curve primitive
is more expensive,
using curves instead of triangles
allows us to render
perfectly smooth hair strands
with no triangulation artifacts.
We can also use less memory
since each curve
needs just a few control points
instead of numerous triangles.
This efficient use of memory is important
for characters with a lot of hair.
Let's say we had a scene
made of sphere primitives.
We start by providing axis-aligned
bounding boxes enclosing each sphere.
Then, just like with triangles,
Metal builds an acceleration structure
over the boxes.
Later, when we provide a ray,
Metal searches for intersections
between bounding boxes and the ray.
Just like with triangles, Metal invokes
the bounding box intersection function
each time it finds
a potential intersection.
We only need to make
a couple of small changes
to build this acceleration structure.
We will create a primitive acceleration
structure descriptor
just like before.
However, this time, instead of
creating a triangle geometry descriptor,
we'll create
a bounding box geometry descriptor.
This descriptor simply provides
a place to attach a buffer
containing our bounding boxes
as well as the bounding box count.
Like triangle intersection functions,
bounding box intersection functions
return true or false to indicate whether
to accept or reject the intersection.
But they're also responsible
for computing the closest distance
from the ray origin
to any intersection points
on the custom primitive.
Metal will use this distance to
compute the overall closest intersection
across all the different triangle
and bounding box primitives in the scene.
The declaration changes slightly
to show that we're now writing
a bounding box intersection function.
Since we need to return multiple values,
we'll return a user-defined struct.
In this example, we've created a struct
which contains a Boolean
indicating whether to accept
or reject the intersection
as well as a float which contains
the intersection distance.
Like triangle intersection functions,
we receive ray data
such as the ray origin and direction
as well as information
about the intersection
such as the primitive index.
Again, we can also bind our own resources,
which we'll use to pass
an array of spheres.
We start by checking mathematically
whether the ray intersected the sphere
enclosed in the bounding box.
If not, we can return false right away.
Next,
unlike triangle intersection functions,
we have one more responsibility,
which is to check
if the intersection function
is within the acceptable range.
If it is,
then we can accept the intersection
and return the intersection distance.
But what if we want to return
additional data?
For example, we may want to return
the surface normal
at the intersection point for shading.
We can do this using the ray payload.
This is a small piece of data which can be
passed from an intersection function
all the way back to the compute kernel
that started the intersection process.
We simply declare a reference
to our payload type
as an argument
to the intersection function.
Then, we can write to it
to modify the payload.
Keep in mind that changes to the payload
will be visible
whether you accept the intersection
or not,
so in most cases,
you will only want to modify the payload
if you're going to
accept the intersection.
To retrieve the payload value, we simply
modify our call to the intersector
to pass the payload by reference.
Any changes to the payload
from an intersection function
will be visible
once the intersector returns.
So far, we've talked about how to use
a ray intersector from a compute kernel.
We've also talked about
how to write intersection functions.
Next, we'll talk about
how to combine the two.
In order for the intersector
to actually be able to call
our intersection functions,
we need to link them together
in a compute pipeline state.
We'll start by loading
the intersection functions
out of a Metal library.
This is done
just like any other Metal function.
Next, we attach the intersection functions
to the pipeline descriptor
using an MTLLinkedFunctions object.
Finally, we'll compile
the pipeline state as usual.
The compiler will link the code
for the compute kernel
and intersection functions together
so that the intersection functions
can be called from a ray intersector
inside the compute kernel.
Now that we've linked
all the intersection functions
into our compute pipeline state,
we need to map
these intersection functions
to individual pieces of geometry.
We do this using what's called
an intersection function table.
This table contains pointers to the actual
executable code in the pipeline state.
Just like each piece
of acceleration structure geometry
can have its own vertex buffer,
they can also each have
their own intersection function.
And if you're using
an instance acceleration structure,
each instance can have its own
set of intersection functions as well.
Both acceleration structure geometry
and instance descriptors
have individual
Intersection function table offsets.
When a ray hits a piece of geometry,
these two values are added together
to determine which
intersection function table entry to call.
To create an intersection function table,
we start by creating a descriptor.
In this example,
we create one with enough space
for all of our intersection functions.
Next, we allocate
the intersection function table.
This table points to
actual executable code
in a specific compute pipeline state,
so it's also created
from that pipeline state.
Furthermore, it can only be used
with this pipeline state
or a pipeline state derived from it.
Next, we'll get a handle
for each intersection function
from the compute pipeline state.
This handle represents the address
of the function's executable code
which has been linked
into the pipeline state.
We then insert this handle
into the intersection function table.
This is also where we bind the resources
used by the intersection functions
in the table.
For example, we'll bind our sphere buffer
to buffer index 0.
Using an intersection function table
is very similar to how we use
an acceleration structure.
We again simply pass it
to the intersector.
Intersection function tables also bind
to normal Metal buffer binding points.
And again,
there's a corresponding API method
to bind an intersection function table
on the compute command encoder
and argument encoder.
And that's everything we need to do
to set up intersection functions.
intersection functions are a powerful tool
which gives you much more control
over the intersection process.
To summarize, we first talked about
the new Metal ray tracing API,
and the ray intersector object
which is now available
directly from within any compute kernel.
This is a much more flexible
programming model
which allows you to divide up work
in the best way for your application.
We also talked about how the new API
gives you more control
over when and where
acceleration structures
are allocated and built.
Finally, we talked about
how you can write intersection functions
to customize the intersection process.
There's actually a lot more we could say
about intersection functions.
In fact, we've also made
the underlying mechanism
available for use in other applications.
For example, since a ray
could hit any surface at any time,
the shading step needs to be able
to execute code
for arbitrary materials on demand.
So, I would encourage you
to watch the function pointers talk,
which accompanies this session,
to learn about another powerful tool
which will allow you to do this.
We only had time to cover the basics
of the new ray tracing API today,
so I'd also recommend that you check out
the sample code and documentation
attached to this session.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.