Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to Explore Logging in Swift.
I am Ravi Kandhadai Madhavan,
an engineer at Apple.
In this talk, I will show you how
to make your apps easier to debug
using Apple's unified logging APIs,
also known as os_log.
I will talk about how to collect logs
from a device you have access to.
I will demonstrate the tools available
to analyze logs in order to understand
and fix problems with your app.
I will cover how to control performance
of log calls
and improve readability of log messages
using formatting options.
Bugs are important to fix.
Users expect quality apps to be reliable
and have few bugs.
Even minor bugs can lead
to a poor user experience.
However, some bugs are more difficult
to fix than others.
Often, the most elusive are those that
are hard to reproduce during development.
Logs are a valuable tool for finding
and fixing hard-to-reproduce bugs.
They provide a trail of clues
that you can follow to understand a bug
without even having to reproduce it.
I will now show you a hard-to-reproduce
bug in an app that I'm developing.
I will later show how I can add logging
to help understand and fix this bug.
My app, called Fruta,
lets users purchase smoothies.
I can browse through these smoothies,
tap on a smoothie, and also purchase one.
I've recently added a "Gift Cards" feature
to my app.
I've created a new tab
for browsing through gift cards.
I can tap on a card to purchase it
using Apple Pay.
When I scroll through the cards
and reach the end,
my app will start loading more cards
by communicating with a server.
When I select a card by tapping on it,
my app will stop the loading of cards
and any ongoing communication.
However, I can go back
and continue looking at more cards.
This works most of the time.
Unfortunately, sometimes I see a bug.
When my app is loading more cards,
if I tap on a card,
the loading occasionally fails
with an error.
This is frustrating because it doesn't
happen near my development machine.
It happens very rarely,
so I am not able to reproduce this
under the debugger.
Adding logging to your app can help you
understand errors like this one
without needing to reproduce them
at your desk.
In Xcode 12, we have introduced
new Swift APIs for unified logging.
You can use these APIs to record important
events happening in your app as it runs.
These logs are archived
by the operating system
so you can retrieve them later
from the device.
Because these new APIs are very efficient,
they can be widely used
without slowing down your app.
All it takes to add logging to your app
is three simple steps.
First, import the "os" module
which defines the new logging APIs.
Second,
create an instance of the type "Logger,"
passing it a subsystem and category.
These will be attached to every message
logged by the Logger.
Subsystem is typically a bundle identifier
which helps identify a message
coming from your app.
You can use the category
to further distinguish messages
coming from different parts
of your program.
Here, I've used the "Gift Cards" category
for my Logger.
Third, add logging to interesting places
in the code
by calling a method
on the logger instance.
Here, I've added a log every time
my app downloads data from a server.
With Logger, you can add runtime data
to the log message
using string interpolation.
For instance, here I'm adding
a task identifier to the log message.
This is similar
to calling the print function.
However,
log messages are different in a key way.
Unlike with print,
the log message is not fully converted
to a string, as that would be too slow.
Instead, the compiler
and the logging library work together
to produce a heavily optimized
representation of the log message
that leverages the type
of the logged data.
With the optimized representation,
you pay the cost of converting to a string
only when the log message
is actually displayed.
Log messages can contain
a wide variety of data types.
You can log numeric types
like Int and Double, Objective-C objects,
as well as any type that conforms
to Swift's
CustomStringConvertible protocol.
This means to add your own type
to a log message,
all you need to do is make it conform
to CustomStringConvertible.
When adding runtime data to a log message,
you should be aware
that a non-numeric type,
like a string or an object,
will be redacted in the logs by default.
This is done to ensure
that after your app ships
and is running on your user's device,
the logs do not show
any personal information.
For instance, here I'm logging a message
along with the bank account number
of a user
which is represented by a string.
In the output logs, the account number
will be redacted as private.
However, data that does not handle
any sensitive information
can be made visible in the logs.
When you log runtime data,
pass a value .public to an optional
parameter privacy, as shown here.
Now the logs will display
the contents of the data.
Here, it's the name of a smoothie.
I will say more about privacy later.
When your app logs a message,
the operating system stores it on device
in a compressed form.
You can use the "log collect" command
on your Mac to retrieve those logs.
First, connect your device to your Mac.
Next, run the "log collect" command
from the terminal with the device option.
Provide a start time
from when you need the logs,
typically,
a few minutes before you first saw a bug.
Also, provide a file name
for storing the log archive.
You can open log archives in Console app
by double-clicking on them.
This app makes it easy to browse logs
and filter them.
Let us see how I can use logging
to understand
the hard-to-reproduce bug
in the Fruta app I showed previously.
I have already added logging
to the source code of the gift cards view.
I imported the os module to get access
to the logging APIs
and created a logger
with a bundle identifier
and "Gift Cards" category.
I have added logging to record interesting
events performed by this view.
For instance, when the app starts a task
to communicate with the server,
it now logs a UUID
that uniquely identifies the task.
Since the identifier does not contain
sensitive information,
I made it public
so that it's visible in the logs.
Using log collect, I've extracted the logs
of the Fruta app to a log archive.
Now I will open it in Console app.
There are lots of log entries here.
This is because the log archive
contains messages
logged by all processes in the system.
I can use the "search" and "filter"
features of the Console
to narrow down on the logs
I am interested in.
First, I'll filter by subsystem--
in this case, my app's bundle identifier--
to limit the display
to only messages from my Fruta app.
I will click on the search field
at the top right,
enter the subsystem...
and select "subsystem"
from the drop-down list.
I can scroll through just my app's logs
and find the message that corresponds
to the failure.
But since my app is logging so much,
there are still too many entries for me
to understand what else has gone wrong.
What I really need is a way
to narrow down on the problem.
My logged task identifiers
provide the solution.
I can filter by the task identifier
of the failed task
to see only logs
that are relevant to the failure.
I will do that now
by adding the task identifier
as another keyword to the search field.
Now there are only a few logs.
I can read through them
and understand the error.
The first entry shows that the app is
starting a task to fetch more gift cards.
Then I see that the task is completed
due to a network error
and is waiting to retry after a timeout.
The next entry shows that in the meantime,
the user has selected a gift card,
which attempts to stop the task.
But since there is no active task
at this point,
the app finds itself
in an inconsistent state and fails.
This is enough for me to reconstruct
what has actually happened.
By selecting a card,
I attempted to stop a task
from loading more gift cards
at a time it had already stopped
due to a network error.
This explains why this bug
was so hard to reproduce.
It's dependent on the timing of events
and a network error.
Thanks to the logs, I am now able
to understand the bug and fix it.
We saw that using "log collect" command,
you can collect logs
after your app has finished running.
It is also possible to stream logs
while your app is running.
If your device is connected to your Mac,
you can stream log messages
as they happen in Console app.
If your app is launched from Xcode,
you will also see them in Xcode's console.
This is a helpful alternative
to "printf" debugging
with more structured output
that can be easily filtered.
You might have noticed when I was
browsing through logs in Console app
that the "failure" message
was highlighted.
This is because I logged it
with the fault log level.
The logging APIs provide five log levels
for indicating importance of messages.
In the increasing order
of their importance,
they are debug, info, notice,
which is also the default level,
error, and fault.
Use the debug level for messages
that are useful only during debugging.
The info level is for messages
that are helpful
but not essential
for troubleshooting errors.
Notices indicate that the message is
absolutely essential for troubleshooting.
You can use the error level to record
errors that happen during execution.
The fault level is the most severe.
You should use it to record situations
that arise due to a potential bug
in the program.
For example, to record that an assumption
that the program expects to hold
is violated at runtime.
The error and fault levels are highlighted
with yellow and red bubbles
in Console app.
The Logger type has methods
for each log level.
For example, to log a debug message,
call the debug function on a logger.
While choosing a log level,
an important thing you must consider
is persistence.
That is, whether a log message is archived
and can be retrieved later
after the app has finished executing.
The logs that aren't persisted can only
be streamed while the app is running.
Whether a message is persisted or not
depends on the log level.
Persistence increases
with the method's importance.
Debug level messages are not persisted,
which means they cannot be retrieved
after the app has completed execution.
Info error messages
are mostly not persisted,
except when they are generated a few
moments before a log collect command.
Messages logged at every other level
are persisted,
and you can retrieve them later.
There is, however, a storage limit
on how many messages are archived.
Once that limit is exceeded,
the older ones are purged
and become unavailable.
The error and fault level messages
are persisted even longer
than notice level messages.
Typically, the messages will be persisted
for a few days.
However, it depends on the storage space
on your device.
The log levels also affect performance.
Even though logging in general
has low overhead,
the log levels have different performance
relative to each other.
The levels that are less important
are faster.
The fault level is the slowest,
and the debug level
is the most performant.
Logging at the debug level is so fast
because debug messages
are not persisted at all.
They are discarded when the logs
aren't being streamed.
Further, the Swift compiler uses
sophisticated optimizations
to ensure that the code that creates
the messages is not even executed
when the debug messages are discarded.
This means that you can log
verbose messages at the debug level
and call expensive functions
to construct messages.
Your users won't pay the cost for them.
As I showed with my Fruta app,
including runtime data,
such as task identifiers,
in a log message made it more useful
for debugging.
However,
raw data such as numbers and strings
can be hard to understand and interpret.
The Logging APIs offer many ways
to format data for readability
with no runtime cost.
Let us return to the Fruta app
to see how formatting of log messages
can help with debugging.
I see a performance problem
in the gift cards view.
Sometimes loading cards takes too long.
The app uses multiple servers
to load gift cards.
I suspect that the performance problem
is related to which servers are chosen.
To investigate this,
I've added some logging
to gather some statistics
about the communication with servers.
For each task, I log the task identifier,
the identifier of the gift card
that was fetched,
the server that served the request,
and the total duration
the task took to complete.
Now I will plug in my iPhone to my Mac
and run the app from Xcode
and view the logs in Xcode's console.
Unfortunately,
the logs are very hard to understand,
as they are not aligned well.
I will now use the formatting options
to make this look better.
First, let me make
the gift card identifier fixed-width
by displaying the maximum number
of characters a card identifier can have.
I will also round off the duration
to two decimal places,
since I don't need that much precision.
Let me relaunch the app
and view the logs again.
Now you see that
the logs are much easier to read.
In fact, since they are aligned well,
I can even hold down the option key
and copy the fields using "column select."
I will paste them in Numbers
and visualize the data.
With this graph, I can immediately notice
that the slow tasks
are all served by server three,
so I will take that server off-line
for maintenance.
To recap, you can use the optional
"format" and "align" parameter
to format data.
Since formatting data
using the Logging APIs
doesn't add to the cost of a log call,
you can use formatting as much as you like
to make your data look pretty
and easy to understand.
The Logging APIs
provide many formatting options,
of which I only showed you a few.
You can see the full range of options
using Xcode's code completion,
including formatting numbers
as hexadecimal,
octal, exponential, and others.
As we saw before,
you can use privacy options to control
the visibility of data in the logs.
It is really important to take seriously
the privacy of the logged data.
This is because logging happens
all the time,
even after your app has shipped
and is in the hands of your users.
Logs can be collected by anyone
who has physical access to the device
and also its passcode.
Therefore,
it is important that the log messages
do not mark
any personal information public,
which could expose it in the logs.
You can get a lot of the same benefits
as using public without actually doing so
by using an equality-preserving hash.
This does not reveal
the content of the data
but still allows you to know
when the logged values are the same,
which can help in filtering logs.
For example,
here I'm passing a mask parameter
to the .private privacy option
in order to log a customer's
bank account number with a hash.
This lets me find out when
two log messages refer to the same account
without revealing the account number.
The Logger APIs I described are available
in iOS 14.
If your app targets prior releases,
you can use the os_log function
that accepts printf-style format strings.
Starting in this release,
string interpolations can also be passed
to the os_log function,
just like with Logger.
To summarize, you can take advantage
of new Swift logging APIs
to debug problems that would otherwise be
almost impossible to understand and fix.
This is possible because you can
retrieve logs from your development device
and drill down into them
without even having to reproduce the bug.
The logging APIs offer you both
high performance
and at the same time rich formatting.
Therefore,
you can log informative messages,
secure in the knowledge that you won't
make your apps slow for your end users.
Thanks for watching.