Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Guillem Vinals Gangolells:
Hello and welcome to this session.
I am Guillem Vinals
from the Metal Ecosystem team.
Today I will talk about
how to optimize your game or app
using GPU performance counters.
This talk will walk you through
the architecture of modern Apple GPUs
and explain its performance metrics.
We will start with an introduction to both
our GPUs and the performance counters.
Then we will cover several groups
of GPU performance counters.
We'll talk about performance limiters,
memory bandwidth,
occupancy, and hidden surface removal.
All of these GPU performance counters
will help us understand
the Apple GPUs much better.
We will start with an introduction
to the GPU and its performance counters.
The GPU is a central part
of Apple processors such as A13.
So let's do a quick recap
of Apple GPUs first.
Apple GPUs
are part of the Apple processors,
which are very power efficient.
Apple processors
have unified memory architecture
where the CPU and the GPU
share System Memory.
The GPU has on-chip Tile Memory.
Notice that the GPU does not have
dedicated Video Memory,
so bandwidth could be a problem
if the content has not been tuned.
To be fast and efficient
without Video Memory,
our GPUs are TBDRs,
or Tile Based Deferred Renderers.
This diagram shows
the Apple GPU rendering pipeline.
We have covered the pipeline
in more detail in other talks,
so I will just provide a quick overview.
The rendering pipeline
has two distinct phases:
First, Tiling, where all of the geometry
will be processed.
Second, Rendering,
where all of the pixels will be processed.
So let's recap both phases,
starting with the Tiling Phase.
During the Tiling Phase, the GPU will,
for the entire render pass,
split the viewport into a list of tiles,
shade all of the vertices,
and bin the transformed primitives
into tiles.
Now, the GPU is going to shade
all of these tiles separately.
Each GPU core will shade
at least one tile at a time.
For each tile in the render pass,
the GPU will execute the load action,
rasterize and compute the visibility
for all of the primitives,
shade all of the visible pixels,
and then execute the store action.
This is how our design can scale so well.
The more GPU cores we have, the more tiles
we can shade at the same time.
Before concluding this overview,
let's have a closer look
at the GPU configuration.
Apple GPUs have multiple cores.
A GPU core contains a Shader Core,
a Texture Unit, and a Pixel Backend,
as well as a dedicated pool
of Tile Memory.
Notice that Tile Memory
is just part of the hierarchy.
Both the ALU and the TPU
have dedicated L1s.
All of the GPU cores
share a last level cache.
And then, of course, there's System Memory
which is basically DRAM.
This talk will assume some familiarity
with the Apple TBDR architecture
as well as the Metal Best Practices.
Check out these two talks
to brush up on both topics.
I would actually recommend you to start
with "Harness Apple GPUs with Metal"
and then look at the Best Practices.
So, let's build up some context
around GPU profiling first.
In order to render a frame,
the GPU needs to process
multiple render passes.
Each render pass will be executed
across multiple GPU cores.
And each GPU core will, in turn,
process different tasks,
such as shading or texturing.
All of those tasks will be executed
on different hardware units,
such as the ALU or the TPU.
And of course, every single one
of these units has a different throughput
which uses different metrics.
For example, we will use FLOPS
to measure the ALU throughput
or megabytes per second
to measure the TPU throughput.
So, there's multiple metrics to look at.
What metrics should we look at then?
Well, enter GPU performance counters.
GPU performance counters will measure
how the GPU is being utilized.
Will help us find
if the GPU doesn't have enough work,
or if the GPU has too much work.
Will help us identify
performance bottlenecks,
and also help us optimize the commands
that take the longest.
Cool, so let's review
the GPU performance counters
for our Apple GPUs.
Well, that's actually quite a list.
There's over 150 GPU counters to look at.
Maybe at this point,
there's just far too much data to parse.
So how can we make sense
of all those numbers?
The answer is tooling.
Our GPU tools
will help you navigate all that data,
starting with Metal System Trace,
which is part of Instruments.
You will want to use Metal System Trace
for performance overview.
You will see both
the CPU and the GPU timelines.
Your workload will be affected by thermals
and dynamic system changes.
Metal System Trace is already part of
the Game Performance template
in Instruments.
You can also enable
GPU performance counters
which can be used to identify
potential GPU or memory bottlenecks
at different points during the frame.
Of course, there's also the Metal Debugger
which is part of Xcode.
You will want to use this tool
for a deep performance investigation.
You will see both a detailed GPU timeline
as well as
the Metal API usage of your game.
And your workload will be unaffected
by thermals or dynamic system changes.
Xcode also supports
GPU performance counters
and exposes every single one of them
at encoder granularity.
There's also a large subset of counters
available per draw call.
Xcode is where
all of the counters are listed,
so it's definitely the right tool
to correlate metrics.
So what exactly do those values mean?
By now you know that
there are a ton of counters,
and that the tools will help you
focus on the important ones.
The rest of the talk will walk you through
different groups of counters
and explain them in more detail.
We will start with performance limiters,
arguably the GPU counters
you should always look at first.
Limiters are very important
due to the parallel nature of GPUs.
The GPU can execute
a ton of work in parallel:
arithmetic, memory accesses,
as well as rasterization tasks.
The limiter counters will measure
the activity of multiple GPU subsystems.
They will help you find
work being executed,
as well as find stalls
that prevent work from being executed.
Remember, the GPU is only as fast
as the slowest part.
Limiters will point you to that part
for you to investigate.
Time for a demo. Please welcome Sam
for a cool demo of Metal System Trace.
Thanks, Guillem. I've got my iPad Pro,
and I'm playing Respawnables Heroes,
a game by our friends
over at Digital Legends.
It looks great. It's got reflections,
beautiful dynamic lighting with shadows,
and many more post-processing effects.
But to get a sense
of how well it's running,
I'm going to show you how to record
the performance limiters in Instruments.
Let's switch back to my computer
where I've already got Instruments open.
First, I'll select
the Game Performance template.
Then, I'll make sure
that my device is selected and the game.
I'm gonna long-press on the Record button
and click on Recording Options.
Then, I'll switch to
the Metal Application recording options
and make sure that Performance Limiters
is selected under the GPU Counter Set.
I'm also going to enable
the new Shader Timeline,
and you'll see why in a sec.
But for now,
let's click on the Record button.
Instruments is now recording the game,
and when we're done, we can click Stop.
The Game Performance template
gathers a lot of information
about the state of the system,
but for now, we're interested in the GPU.
So I'm going to disclose the A12Z track
to see what was running.
I'm going to hold Option and left-click
and drag to zoom into a frame.
We can now see a timeline
of all of the command buffers and encoders
that were running, color-coded by frame.
We can see that Respawnables Heroes
first renders a shadow map.
This is then followed by
a Deferred Phase Encoder
where it looks roughly 50-50 split
between the vertex and fragment shader,
but the fragment shader
is a little bit longer.
In this case, 1.29 milliseconds.
After this is a bunch
of post-processing effects.
Now, I'm going to take a close look
at the Deferred Phase Encoder
because it's taking the longest time.
So I can disclose the fragment track
to see the new Shader Timeline...
which shows me which shaders are running
at certain sample times
during the execution
of my command encoder.
This fine-grained detail
makes it really easy
to see and identify
longer-running shaders,
and helps to explain why a given encoder
is taking a certain amount of time.
If I select the track and a region,
I can actually see which shaders
were running in the table below,
along with how many samples
they were running for
and an approximate GPU time.
We can also see
the performance limiters in Instruments.
So, the first track
is the top performance limiter track.
Now, if I scrub my mouse over this track,
we can see that during the deferred phase,
the ALU Limiter is the highest.
And during the post-processing,
it's the Texture Sampler.
Now, this makes a lot of sense.
But don't worry
if you don't know what they mean.
Guillem will later explain each limiter
and what to do if you see a high value.
Below the Top Performance Limiter tracks
are the individual limiters themselves,
such as ALU, Texture Sampler,
and many, many more.
Now, back to Guillem.
Excellent. Thank you, Sam.
Now we know where to find
the GPU performance limiters.
So, let's focus on some of them.
We will talk about Arithmetic,
Texture Read and Write,
Tile Memory Load and Store,
Buffer Read and Write,
GPU Last Level Cache,
and Fragment Input Interpolation limiters.
As we go through the list,
we will also be putting them
in the context of the Apple GPU.
Also, I will show you
how to find them in Xcode,
starting with the ALU limiter.
Before looking at the limiter,
we will build some context first.
The ALU is part of the shader core.
It processes arithmetic operations,
both bit-wise and relational operations.
It is optimized for both
floating-point arithmetic
and coherent execution.
So, let's review that.
Let's review the relative throughput
of the different operations first.
At the top, we can see
16-bit floating point operations,
which are run at double rate.
Then, we also have
32-bit floating point operations,
which are run at full rate.
Finally, we also have 32-bit integer
and complex operations,
which are run at half rate or less.
For example, we should prefer
F16 over F32 when possible.
Also, watch out for complex operations.
The best case is shown here.
Some complex operations
such as a square root
will have an actually lower rate.
Great. So let's talk about
the execution model of our shader core.
Each shader core has multiple SIMD units,
as well as dedicated Tile Memory
and a pool of Register Memory.
Each SIMD unit has 32 threads,
and each thread in the SIMD
executes the same instruction.
This is very important
when it comes to authoring shaders.
Each SIMD lane has 32 threads
but a single program counter.
This is ideal when all of the threads
execute the same instruction.
In this case, the condition "a"
is equal for all of the threads.
That's what we call coherent execution.
All of the threads
will execute the same instruction.
And the total time
to execute this program will be 40 cycles.
There is no penalty for the "if" branch
other than the extra temporary registers
required and not utilized.
In this case, we have divergent execution.
Some of the threads
will evaluate "a" to "true."
All of the SIMD lane
has to execute all of the instructions.
The threads that don't take the branch
will mask out the execution,
but still spend the cycles.
In this case,
the total cost will be 70 cycles.
Notice that we have the extra 30 cycles
from the "if" condition.
One last note on execution model.
There are some cases
where only a few threads of a SIMD
will actually need to run.
This will, of course,
have an impact on performance,
since most of the threads
are wasting cycles.
Okay, so with that in mind,
we can now look at the limiter.
So what can we do
if we are actually limited by the ALU?
Well, in most cases,
we may want to celebrate.
That's exactly what we want:
the GPU is crunching numbers,
and that's exactly what the GPU is for.
But what if we actually want
to reduce the ALU load?
In which case, we will want to replace
complex calculations
with either approximations
or lookup tables.
Also, try to replace floats,
full-precision by half-precision.
Try to avoid implicit conversions.
Avoid FP32 inputs
such as textures or buffers.
And also make sure that all of the shaders
are compiled
using the Metal "-ffast-math" flag.
Notice, though, that a high limiter value
does not mean
that the workload is efficient.
It's a great step though.
For example, we can be 100% ALU limited
but only stay at 50% utilization
if all we are doing are FP32 operations.
Xcode is the ideal tool to find out about
what is causing a limiter
to be high or low.
For example, we can filter by ALU
in order to see
all of the arithmetic-related counters.
Great. So let's move on
to Texture Read and Write.
Before we talk about the limiter,
we should understand Metal textures first.
Metal textures
are backed by Device Memory.
They are always read by the Texture Unit,
which does have a dedicated L1,
as well as support for multiple filtering
and compression modes.
Textures, on the other hand,
are written by the Pixel Backend.
Notice that the Texture Unit
and Pixel Backend
are different hardware blocks,
so we should review them separately,
starting with the Texture Processing Unit,
or TPU.
The TPU reads texture data.
When the render pass executes
the LoadActionLoad for an attachment,
or when we are explicitly reading
or sampling from a shader.
It is optimized for gather operations
as well as regular pixel formats.
The pixel format has a direct impact
on the sampling rate.
Particularly, watch out
for 128-bit formats such as RGBA32Float,
since those are sampled at quarter rate.
Oftentimes, these high precision
pixel formats are used for noise textures
or lookup tables for post-process effects.
The pixel filtering rate is also important
and should be kept in mind.
It could be a problem when we have
very high levels of anisotropy.
Now, let's talk about compressed formats.
Apple GPUs support
both block-compressed pixel formats,
such as PVRTC or ASTC,
as well as lossless compression
of conventional pixel formats.
In this diagram, we see an example
of a block-compressed HDR environment map.
The small Cube Map would require
three megabytes if left uncompressed.
Using ASTC HDR,
which is supported by A13 GPUs,
allows us to massively reduce
the memory footprint
and bandwidth, of course,
for these assets.
So what can we do
if we see a high Texture Sample limiter?
Well, you will want to use mipmaps
if minification is likely occurring.
Also, consider changing
the filtering options.
Try to use lower anisotropic sample count,
for example.
Consider using smaller pixel sizes.
And of course, make sure
you are leveraging texture compression.
Use block-compression
such as ASTC for assets,
and lossless texture compression
for textures generated at run-time.
Same as we did before, we can use Xcode
to find more about texture reads.
In this case,
we can select the "Texture" group
to see all
of the texture-related counters.
Great. Now let's move on to texture write.
Textures are written into Device Memory
by the Pixel Backend.
The Pixel Backend will write texture data
when a render pass executes
the StoreActionStore for an attachment.
Or when we explicitly write into a texture
from a shader.
It is also optimized for coherent writes,
so you should avoid
all kinds of divergent writes,
such as writing to different array indices
or different tiles.
There really is not much to say
on the write rates themselves.
Try to keep a small pixel size
and potentially watch out for MSAA.
The most important thing to bear in mind
is that the Pixel Backend
and Texture Processing Units
are different hardware blocks,
so they have
different throughput altogether.
You may want to make sure
that the lower texture write rate
is not actually
the main limiter for your shaders.
So what can we do if we see
a high texture write limiter value?
Based on the rate,
you should watch out for the pixel sizes,
as well as the number of unique
MSAA samples per pixel.
Also, try to optimize for coherent writes.
Xcode is a great tool
to narrow down the search.
We can also use more complex filters
such as "Texture" and "Write"
to get all of the texture-write counters
found across different groups.
Great. So, moving on to the next limiter:
Tile Memory Load and Store.
To understand this limiter,
first, we need to understand Tile Memory.
Tile Memory is a set
of high-performance memory
that stores Threadgroup
and Imageblock data.
Tile Memory is accessed when reading
or writing pixel data from the Imageblock,
such as when using tile shaders.
It's also accessed when reading
or writing data from Threadgroup Memory,
for example,
when you're using compute dispatches,
and it is also accessed
when reading or writing
to render pass color attachments,
such as when using programmable blending,
or even when enabling blending
on a rendering pipeline.
So what can we do if we see a high value?
This may be the case
when writing complex compute shaders
that explicitly leverage
threadgroup memory.
If such is the case, you will want to
reduce the number of threadgroup atomics,
consider using
threadgroup parallel reductions,
or SIMD lane operations instead.
Also, make sure to align
threadgroup memory allocations
and accesses to 16 bytes.
Finally, consider reordering
your memory access patterns
for higher efficiency.
Tile Memory is referred to in the tools
as Imageblock and Threadgroup Memory.
This is the case for both
our tools and documentation.
So in this case,
typing "Imageblock" in Xcode
will reveal
all of the Tile Memory counters.
On to the next limiter,
which is Buffer Read and Write.
Same as we did with Textures,
we should first understand Metal buffers.
Metal buffers
are also backed by Device Memory.
But Metal buffers are accessed
only by the Shader Core,
which does have a dedicated L1
as well as support
for different address spaces.
Address spaces for buffer data
are device for read-write data
or constant for read-only data.
For example, you will want to use
the device address space
for data which is indexed per fragment
or per vertex,
and use constant address space
for data that is utilized by many vertices
or fragments.
So what can we do
if we are limited by Buffer Read or Write?
You may actually want to pack data
more tightly.
Try to use smaller types.
Also, try to vectorize load and store,
and, if possible, avoid device atomics
and register spills altogether.
Another interesting optimization could be
to use textures to balance the workload
since both the ALU and the TPU
have different caches.
Xcode can also help us find
whether Buffer Read or Write is a problem.
By typing "Buffer" in the filter,
you will see
all of the Buffer Read and Write counters,
as well as the limiter, of course.
Great. So let's talk about
GPU Last Level Cache or GPU LLC.
The GPU Last Level Cache
is shared across all GPU Cores.
It caches both texture and buffer data,
as well as storing device atomics.
It is optimized
for spatial and temporal locality.
This is a great opportunity to review
the relative peak rates
of the memory hierarchy of a GPU core.
Based on these rates, we should actually
favor Tile Memory over the GPU LLC
and also watch out for atomic operations.
So what can we do if we are being limited
by the GPU Last Level Cache?
Well, if texture or buffer limiters
also show a high value,
try to optimize this first.
Potentially consider reducing the size
of working sets.
If your shaders are using device atomics,
try to refactor code
to use threadgroup atomics instead.
Also, make sure to access memory
with better spatial and temporal locality.
Typing "Last Level Cache"
will, very unsurprisingly,
reveal all of the GPU LLC counters,
including the limiter, of course.
Great! On to the last limiter,
Fragment Input Interpolation.
Same as we did before,
we should first understand
Fragment Input Interpolation.
Fragment Input is interpolated
during the rendering stage
by the Shader Core.
The Shader Core has a dedicated
Fragment Input Interpolator,
which is both fixed function
and full precision.
Due to the fixed function nature
of the Fragment Input Interpolation,
there's not much we can do
if we see a high limiter value.
We can only remove vertex attributes
passed to the Fragment Shader.
You can find the Fragment Shader
Interpolation Limiter in Xcode, of course.
Now it's a great time to point out
to some of our documentation
on the topic of both limiters
and developer tools.
Notice that I have also included here
some articles about memory bandwidth
and occupancy, which we will cover next.
This next section is about understanding
memory bandwidth.
This is a very important GPU counter
since many of the TBDR optimizations
have something to do
with saving bandwidth.
Remember that Device Memory
is backed by System Memory
on Unified Memory Systems such as the A13.
It will store both Metal resources
as well as the output
from the tiling phase.
Also, it will be cached
by the GPU Last Level Cache.
The Memory Bandwidth GPU counter
measures transfer from System Memory
to the actual GPU itself.
For example,
when we read buffer or texture data.
Notice, though, that there's also
System Level Cache, or SLC.
This means that oftentimes
you may see bursts of data transfer
at a higher rate
than the actual DRAM throughput.
So what can we do if we see
a high Memory Bandwidth GPU counter?
Well, if texture or buffer limiters
show a high value,
you should try to optimize those instead.
Also, make sure that the load and store
instructions are efficient,
so only load data needed
by the current render pass,
and only store data
needed by future render passes.
Of course,
this is a great moment to remind you
that you should always leverage
texture compression.
Use block-compression, ASTC, for assets
and lossless compression
for textures generated at run-time.
Texture compression really has
a big impact on the memory bandwidth.
Great. Moving on.
Another good set of counters to look at
is occupancy.
Occupancy measures
how many threads are executed
out of the total thread pool.
Latency, in this context, is the time
it takes for a task to be completed.
For example, the left diagram shows a GPU
where only half of the thread pool
is executing.
The diagram to the right
shows a case of 100% occupancy
where the GPU runs
as many tasks as it can.
So, why is occupancy important?
Well, GPUs do hide latency
by switching between available threads.
GPUs will, of course, create new threads
when there are enough internal resources
to do so
or when there are commands
scheduled to run.
So, if a task has high latency,
for example, due to memory transfers,
the GPU will switch between
available threads to avoid stalling.
Of course, all of that
while creating new threads when possible.
Occupancy will depend, in large part,
on some static properties
of the compute or rendering pipeline.
So you may want to query those.
You may want to query the maximum number
of threads per threadgroup,
the execution width of a SIMD lane,
and also,
the length of the threadgroup memory
that needs to be statically allocated.
So let's talk about
the occupancy GPU counter.
This GPU counter
will measure the percentage
of the total thread capacity
being used by the GPU.
This counter is actually
the sum of other counters.
It's the sum of Compute, Vertex,
and Fragment Occupancy.
Notice also that
neither high or low occupancy
are indicative of a problem.
For example, low Vertex Occupancy is fine
if there is enough Fragment Occupancy.
Low occupancy is also fine
if the GPU resources
are being fully utilized.
Overlapping work in different subsystems
may increase occupancy.
For example, the diagram below
shows high overlap
between tiling, rendering, and compute.
So what can we do if we see
a high occupancy GPU counter?
Well, we will want to correlate
occupancy measurements
with data from other counters or tools.
And if overall occupancy is low,
this means that shaders may have
exhausted some internal resources,
such as tile or threadgroup memory.
It could also be that
threads finish executing faster
than the GPU can create new ones.
Also, it may be that your app
is rendering to a small area
or dispatching very small compute grids.
Great. So now let's talk about
Hidden Surface Removal, or HSR.
Hidden Surface Removal, or HSR,
is an early visibility pass.
It is important to use the GPU counters
to measure its efficiency for your game.
Let's recap HSR first.
HSR allows the GPU to minimize overdraw
by keeping track of the front-most
visible layer for each pixel.
HSR is both pixel perfect
and submission order independent
for opaque meshes.
Notice the pixels are processed
into two stages.
First, Hidden Surface Removal,
and then, Fragment Processing.
For example, even if you draw
two triangles back to front,
HSR will ensure that there is no overdraw.
So how can we measure
Hidden Surface Removal efficiency?
We will actually want to use
GPU counters for that.
We can use GPU counters to measure
the number of pixels rasterized,
the number of Fragment Shader invocations,
the number of pixels stored,
as well as the number of Pre-Z test fails.
Overdraw, in this context, is the ratio
between Fragment Shader invocations
and Pixels Stored.
Of course, we can minimize overdraw by
reducing the number of full-screen passes,
as well as reducing blending.
But what else can we do?
We should use HSR efficiently.
You will want to draw meshes
sorted by visibility state.
First opaque meshes,
then alpha test, discard,
and depth feedback,
and finally, translucent meshes.
You should avoid interleaving
opaque and non-opaque meshes,
as well as avoid interleaving
opaque meshes
with different color attachment
write masks.
Awesome. So please welcome Sam again
for another demo.
Guillem's just walked us through
all the limiters,
what they mean,
and what to do if you see a high value.
So let's look at
Respawnables Heroes again,
specifically an older build
running on my iPhone,
but this time in the Metal Debugger
with all of the GPU performance counters.
I've already captured the frame in Xcode,
and I'm looking at the summary.
We can see the GPU time
in the performance overview
is about 12.82 milliseconds.
But I want more detail,
so I'm going to click
on the Show Counters button
to jump right into
the GPU performance counters.
We can now see
a detailed view of the counters
for each command encoder or draw call.
As Guillem showed you earlier,
there are a ton of counters
for Apple GPUs.
So we've made a bunch of improvements
to the tool
to help you find and organize them.
To begin with, we've reorganized
the counters into groups.
For instance, if you want to see
all of the counters related to memory,
simply click on the Memory group.
You can also filter for things.
So, if I want to see every counter
related to the ALU, I can filter for it.
One of the cool things about groups
is that you can also create your own.
So after filtering, a Save button
will appear on the top right,
which you can click
to create your very own group.
There's also a new detail table
at the bottom,
which is strongly linked with the graph.
So, I can select something here,
and it also selects it in the table,
and vice versa.
It also selects it in the navigator.
You can also sort the table
by different counters.
For example, to quickly find
the most expensive encoder,
those most bottlenecked by ALU.
In this case, it's the deferred phase.
The performance limiters group
shows us all of the limiters.
We can see that the deferred phase
is mostly limited by the ALU.
If we look
at the floating-point 32 utilization,
we can see that it's higher
than the floating-point 16 utilization.
As Guillem mentioned earlier,
floating-point 16 is twice as fast.
So we really want to reduce that usage
of floating-point 32
as much as possible
to make the game run faster.
What else can we look for?
Guillem mentioned that memory bandwidth
is pretty important.
So let's focus on that
and see if we can reduce it.
I want to show you how easy it is
to pick a limiter
and use the counters to really drill down
into the fine details.
So let's switch back to the memory group,
and this time I'm going to sort the table
by Bytes Read From Main Memory.
Once again,
it's our Deferred Phase encoder.
But we really want to find out
why we are reading so much memory.
Since an encoder is just a container,
what we really want is to find out
which draw is using the most memory.
So let's click on the Draw button
to switch the graph
to Per-Draw Counters mode.
There are thousands of draw calls
in this frame.
But since we already knew
that we're interested
in the Deferred Phase encoder,
we can filter the table to only show
draw calls in this encoder.
Let's sort by texture, L1, by thread,
which gives us the draw call
that has the most L1 bytes transferred.
Since clicking in the table
also highlights it in the navigator,
it's really easy to find the draw call.
Since it's right here,
disclosing the draw call,
we can click on Bound Resources.
This view shows us which resources
the draw call has bound,
and in this case,
it looks like the draw binds and reads
from an RGBA16 floating-point
cube map texture.
Let's check the flags.
Storage mode is shared. Ah.
In this case, since we're sampling,
we could change the texture storage mode
to private,
which would automatically enable
lossless texture compression
to reduce the memory bandwidth.
We could even consider block compression
to further reduce the bandwidth,
not to mention the footprint.
If private storage mode isn't an option,
we can still explicitly optimize it
for the GPU
with a Blit Command Encoder.
I encourage you to check out
the "Delivering Optimized Metal Apps
and Games" talk
from last year's WWDC to learn more.
So just like that, we've been able to use
the performance counters
in the Metal Debugger
to drill down and discover
some optimizations that can be made.
If you pick a limiter
and focus on optimizing it,
you can use the tools to really increase
your game's performance.
In this case, Digital Legends were able
to make these changes amongst others,
significantly increased
their floating-point 16 utilization,
and reduced their memory bandwidth
by block-compressing texture assets.
The game now runs
at a steady 120 FPS on iPad Pro.
It's been a pleasure. Now back to Guillem.
Thank you, Sam, for this great demo.
Okay, so it's time to wrap up.
Today, we have reviewed a bunch of
really important GPU performance counters
and put them into the context
of modern Apple GPUs.
So the next step, of course,
are for you to profile your game.
Use what we have learned.
Use the GPU performance counters
to understand
how the GPU is being utilized
and also find the bottleneck.
You should also learn more
about GPU tools.
Please check the talks below,
and thank you for watching.