Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to this year's WWDC.
My name is Roger Pantos,
and I'm going to tell you about
HLS Blocking Playlist Reload.
To start with,
what is Blocking Playlist Reload?
Well, a fundamental aspect of HLS
is that clients are discovering
new segments constantly
by reloading the Playlist.
The original approach was just to
reload the same Playlist URL
every Target Duration.
Now, that's nice and simple,
but it doesn't work well with Low-Latency.
Because if a client
just misses a Playlist update,
it'll take another Target Duration
before it finally notices it.
And so, for Low-Latency HLS
we introduced the notion
of Delivery Directives,
which are a way for the client
to ask the server
to perform some kind of service for it
by adding query parameters
to its get requests.
For Blocking Playlist Reload,
clients can use a Delivery Directive
to tell the server,
hold on to this Playlist request
until the Playlist you see
contains a segment
that I haven't seen yet.
Once that Playlist updates
with that segment,
the server will unblock
and send it to the client.
So let's take a look
at how that works in detail.
First of all,
Blocking Playlist Reloads are optional,
so the server needs to indicate
that it supports them.
And it does that by adding
a CAN-BLOCK-RELOAD attribute
to its server control tag.
Next, a client will load a Playlist
for the first time.
It doesn't supply any query parameters
because at this point it just wants
whatever's current on the server.
As soon as it gets the Playlist,
it will immediately turn around
and issue a reload request.
And now it will use
the HLS_msn Delivery Directive
to specify the first new segment
that it hasn't seen yet.
And if it's a Low-Latency Playlist,
then it will also specify the next
Partial Segment that it expects to see.
The server will then
hold on to that request
until it has a Playlist that's new enough.
Now let's see how that looks graphically.
Here we have an HLS client to the left
and a server to the right.
The client asks for a Playlist that
contains Partial Segment 2, for example.
The server doesn't have
Partial Segment 2 yet, so it blocks.
Eventually Partial Segment 2 will appear
and will get added
to the Playlist.
Now the server can unblock
the client request
and send it the updated Playlist
as the response.
Let's take a look at an actual example.
We'll start with a regular Playlist,
not a Low-Latency one.
Here is a regular live HLS Playlist.
The first thing to notice
is that the server is advertising
that it supports Blocking Playlist Reload
in its server control tag.
Next, the Media Sequence Number is 19,
and that refers to the first segment
in the Playlist, which here is Segment A.
Now, if you count four segments down,
all the way to the bottom to Segment E,
you'll see that it has
a Media Sequence Number of 23,
and that means that the next time
a Playlist is updated with a new segment,
that new segment
will be Media Sequence Number 24.
So to ask for that update,
the client will use
the HLS_msn=24 Delivery Directive.
When it receives this request,
the server will block
until the Playlist is updated,
and then it will return
the newer version of the Playlist.
And at the end, it now contains Segment F,
also known as Media Sequence Number 24.
So that's the flow
of Blocking Playlist Reload
for regular segments.
Now let's see what happens
for Low-Latency.
In this example, we'll see
how the client asks for the next Playlist
when it contains partial segments as well.
So, here we have
a live Low-Latency Playlist.
You can see that the segments
have a Target Duration of six seconds,
while the partial segments have
a part Target Duration of two seconds.
At the end of the Playlist
are the first two parts of Segment 7--
part zero and part 1.
Given that the last thing in this Playlist
right now is Media Sequence 7 part 1,
to get the next Playlist
the client will need to ask
for Media Sequence 7 part 2.
And so that request looks like this:
The server will hold on to it
until the Playlist updates again
and then send back this response.
And now we can see
that there's a new partial segment
which has Media Sequence Number 7 part 2.
Now, you may be wondering,
if the client is always asking
for the next part
of the current media sequence number,
what happens at the end of the segment?
Well, let's go back
to our earlier Playlist.
Here the next Playlist request
will be for Segment 7 part 3.
Now, the server will translate
any request for a part
that goes beyond the end
of the parent segment
into a request for part zero
of the segment that follows it.
So in this case the server will block
until it returns this Playlist,
where it now contains
part zero of segment 8 at the end.
There are a few other exceptional cases to
know about for Blocking Playlist Reload.
First, the Media Sequence Number
and part Delivery Directives
only apply for live Playlists.
That means they're ignored
if a Playlist has an ENDLIST tag.
Next, if a client asks
for a particular Playlist update
and the server already has it,
it returns the latest Playlist right away.
That's also true even if the Playlist is
newer than what the client has asked for,
if it's advanced ahead
by a couple of Partial Segments.
And in fact,
to take it to the greatest extreme,
if the segment the client asks for
has already rolled out
of the Playlist completely,
the server will still unblock immediately
and return the current Playlist.
The rule is that the origin always returns
to the current version of the Playlist
as long as it's new enough.
Finally, if the server has to wait
too long for the Playlist to update--
if it has to wait
more than three Target Durations--
it will return an error.
Now, that should only happen
if there's a serious problem
with the back-end production.
Another interesting area to talk about
is how Blocking Playlist Reload
interacts with CDNs and other HTTP caches.
The good news here
is that Blocking Playlist Reload
actually works a lot better with caches
even than traditional live HLS.
A big reason for that
is having a unique URL
for each individual Playlist update
allows each request
to be cached independently.
So the update request and response
for MSN 23, for example,
can live in the same cache
alongside the request and response
for MSN 24.
Now, this has a couple
of useful consequences.
First, a new request will effectively
bust through the cache
because it will present
a combination of query parameters
that the cache has never seen before,
so the cache knows to send the request
right along to the origin.
Second, each response has
a longer useful lifetime in the cache
because it doesn't have to
compete with itself.
You no longer have to expire
every Playlist response
in a half-Target Duration,
the way you do
with regular live HLS Playlists.
And in fact, we recommend
a lifetime of six Target Durations
for successful Playlist responses.
The other thing worth saying
is that with Blocking Playlist Reload
and other Delivery Directives,
you have to configure your CDN
to coalesce duplicate edge requests
into a single request to the origin,
because when you have an active origin
you'll want to do everything you can
to help reduce its load.
So, to summarize Blocking Playlist Reload,
it's a new mechanism in HLS
that allows clients
to discover new segments
as soon as they become available
on the server.
Clients request them by using
the msn and part Delivery Directives.
Blocking Playlist Reload
works better with CDNs,
both in a positive sense
of enabling more caching
and also in the negative sense
of explicitly busting that cache
for new requests.
This helps out
with regular live HLS streams
and it's required for Low-Latency streams.
We encourage you to adopt
Blocking Playlist Reload
to improve the delivery of HLS
to your users.
Thank you very much.