Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, I'm Jon Davis,
Web Technologies Evangelist
for the Safari and WebKit teams.
I'm so excited to get to tell you
about all of the new features
and improvements
for web developers this year.
If you develop websites,
web apps saved to the Home Screen
or web content used in apps,
and want to learn
about all of the latest technologies
available in Safari and WebKit,
this session is for you.
In this session, I'll give you a tour
of the new features
and enhancements in WebKit
and shipping in Safari 13.1 for macOS,
Safari on iOS and iPadOS 13.4
and coming to Safari 14
on macOS, iOS and iPadOS.
But first, there's some really great news
I wanna share up front.
We made a really big effort this year
to improve Safari's interoperability
with other browsers.
One way to measure that
is web platform tests.
It's a set of tests used by browser makers
to ensure interoperability
so your web content operates
the way you expect across browsers.
So I'm pleased to announce
improved interoperability
for service workers,
XHR and Fetch, pointer events,
CSS, SVG, WebAssembly and many more areas.
Safari passes 140,000
new interoperability test cases this year,
and you can look forward
to continued progress in this area.
But there's so much more
to talk about this year.
In this session, I'm going to go
over performance improvements,
lots of new web API, CSS updates,
media enhancements,
including some great image updates,
new JavaScript features
and finally, new platform
integration capabilities.
So let's get started with performance,
and specifically browsing performance.
Page load performance is foundational
to our browsing experience feeling fast,
and I'm pleased to report
Safari 14 is 13% faster
clicking a link to an unvisited site,
and up to 42% faster clicking a link
for a recently visited web page.
Typing a URL
into the Search and Address bar
for a recently visited web page
is 52% faster.
We improved instant back
by caching up to 34% more pages.
PDFs show the first page
60 times faster while downloading.
And outside of page load performance,
closing unresponsive tabs
is down from three-and-a-half seconds
to just 50 milliseconds.
All of these improvements
help users and developers
have a faster browsing experience
in Safari.
And there's performance improvements
for developers too.
CPU usage while scrolling
is three times less.
It's buttery smooth
with zero dropped frames.
IndexedDB operations
are up to ten times faster.
Reduced overhead makes for-of loops
up to five times faster,
based on microbenchmarks.
Promises are twice as fast
in the JetStream 2 benchmark's
async-fs test,
and optimized JavaScript delete operations
are up to 12 times faster.
Safari and WebKit are faster than ever.
But now, I'm going to show you
the new web API
added in WebKit and available in Safari.
First up is the Web Animations API.
It's long-awaited and new in Safari 13.1.
It's an API available in JavaScript
to directly create
and control the playback
of CSS animations and transitions.
You no longer need to manipulate
element properties.
And you can query
the animations on the page,
seek directly to a specific time
in the animation playback cycle
or even change the speed
and direction of playback.
So I've been experimenting
with a loading animation
of the WebKit logo for an internal website
where my colleagues enjoy
discussing their pets.
And after it's animated in,
the compass needle spins
and it's a really fun element.
So I'd like to let folks
interact with it a bit
by clicking on the logo
to give the needle another spin.
And with the Web Animations API
it's really easy.
So in the logo's click handler,
we use the element.animate method.
It takes a KeyframeEffect parameter
that allows us to set up
the keyframes for the animation,
a nice easing function
so the needle starts spinning quickly
with a softer ending,
and then a reasonable duration
in milliseconds.
And here it is.
And clicking the logo
keeps the needle spinning.
That's more fun than I thought it'd be.
And Web Inspector's Graphics tab
now shows you the animation instances...
including the animations created
each time I click the logo.
It also visualizes the easing curves.
And to help with timing, it gives you
a perspective of the animation delay
compared to its duration.
There are lots of updates
to Web Inspector you can learn about
in the "What's New
in Web Inspector" session
available in your Developer app.
So that's the Web Animations API.
JavaScript control of animations
with all of the power and efficiency
of CSS animations and transitions.
Next in our tour is ResizeObserver.
It's newly available with the release
of Safari 13.1 earlier this year.
It's a JavaScript API
that reports element size changes.
It allows elements to respond
to the size changes of other elements,
not just the viewport.
With ResizeObserver, your content
can react to elements
that change their size
both when the viewport changes,
like when the window gets resized,
but more importantly,
when other changes to size occur,
like changing the display property
or when new child elements are appended.
My colleagues on the WebKit team
love discussing their pets,
so I've been maintaining
an internal website
where they can share pictures
and comment on them.
And, of course, it uses responsive design
so that when you resize the window
and things start to get a little cramped,
the controls shrink to just show
the icon and save space.
But some folks said
they wanted a flexible editor
because they like having
the extra space while commenting,
and you can see
it resizes well for the window,
but it doesn't work
when resizing the editor.
This hasn't been easily achieved before,
but ResizeObserver
is a great tool for this
because it can detect when the size
of the container changes and react.
Let me show you what I've been working on.
So to address this,
I'll create a new ResizeObserver
in the site's JavaScript that detects
when the container's width
goes below a certain size,
then toggle a CSS class on the container.
The style rules for our formatting buttons
can pick that up
and hide the label to use less space
and collapse the size of the buttons
so they always fit.
To get it working,
I just pass the container element
to the Observer method
of my newly constructed ResizeObserver.
Let's check it out.
With the code in place,
resizing the editor
causes the buttons to hide the labels
and resize the way you'd expect.
That's ResizeObserver.
If you wanna learn more,
there's a blog post
on the WebKit blog with more details.
Now, another feature I need to get working
on the WebKittens website
is the Paste button,
and I've got just the thing,
the Async Clipboard API.
It's also new this year
and available in Safari 13.1.
You can read data
from the system clipboard
for paste operations or write data
to the clipboard for copying.
It's asynchronous,
to avoid blocking the page
while you're accessing the clipboard.
And there's no need to fake a selection
or have element focus
to copy data into it.
It supports multiple items and item types
like images and rich formatted text,
but needs a secure context over HTTPS
and calls must be invoked
in response to user interaction.
Now, if you're working
with just plain text,
it has shortcut methods
to make it even easier.
Copying plain text is as easy
as using the clipboard.writeText method
to write a string of text.
And pasting plain text uses
the clipboard.readText method.
But for the WebKittens website,
the team wants
rich HTML-formatted text when pasting.
Inside the click handler,
the clipboard.read method
is called asynchronously
to get an array of clipboardItems back.
The clipboardItems are iterated
to find the HTML data.
The data gets returned as a blob object.
Then, FileReader is used
to get the HTML data back,
which is collected
and appended to the editor.
I copied a comment
from another post earlier to test with,
so I'll click the Paste button
and post it.
And there you have it, a functional
Paste button that handles rich text.
The Async Clipboard API is powerful
and this just scratched the surface.
You can learn more about it
on the WebKit blog.
Now, if you're a developer of a library
or framework, this next news is for you.
Safari 13.1 now supports
the EventTarget constructor.
EventTarget is used by objects
that can receive events.
For example, DOM elements
extend EventTarget,
but now your own objects can too,
without all the extra element behaviors.
Library authors can use
native event functionality
to create their own object interface
for dispatching custom events
for non-DOM objects.
While we're talking
about library developers,
a lot of libraries are simply providing
a custom component
for web authors to implement,
so that leads us to an update
on web components.
We've had support for web components
in Safari for a long while now
and they keep becoming
more and more powerful.
It's actually another feature I took
advantage of on the WebKittens website.
Everything from the posts to the comments
and even the formatting buttons
are implemented as web components.
But for a simple example, let's look
specifically at the formatting buttons.
Some simple template markup is used
to set up the component
as a custom element.
The id attribute is used to reference
this template in JavaScript.
Then, in JavaScript,
it's registered as a custom element.
The id attribute value is repurposed
to serve as the custom element hook.
Our custom element class
extends a generic HTMLElement
and in the constructor,
clones the template content
to modify the template fragment
with our text label and icon.
It then appends our modified DOM fragment
to the shadowRoot of the custom element.
Then, the page markup
can create those elements
using the custom element's
registered name as the tag name.
Each of the format buttons
can be customized
for bold, italic, underline and so on.
Now, as a component author,
you provide a generic component
that can get used in many ways,
so you wanna give the page author
some control
over how these elements are styled.
In this case, as a component author,
we don't know what kind of button
each one will end up being.
In the example,
component styling handles the layout
of a larger text icon
to the left of the button label,
but in order to give the bold button's
"B" icon a bold style,
and an italic style for the "I" icon,
the page author, who knows
what kind of button they're implementing,
needs to be able to customize
that part of the component.
With Safari 13.1
released this spring they can,
using CSS Shadow Parts.
It allows web component authors
to specifically expose
parts of their components
to content authors
to style with their own CSS.
You don't need to know
all of the underlying markup structure
of the component to style it.
Just the parts of the component
the author exposed
through the part attribute.
Component layout is protected
and content authors
can customize the components
to fit the use case or better match
the style of their website.
Looking back at our example,
this was the original template markup.
By adding the part attribute
to the elements inside the component,
they're now exposed to the page's CSS.
Now, the page author
that's implementing the buttons
can use the part pseudo-element selector
and easily decorate the buttons
to provide an extra visual hint
about their function.
So this turns into this.
And that's CSS Shadow Parts
for web components.
Speaking of visual hints,
WebKit added support
for another visual hint.
The HTML enterkeyhint attribute.
It's supported on Safari,
on iOS 13.4 and iPadOS.
It allows you to declare an action label
for the Enter key on virtual keyboards
of a touchscreen device.
You can set the label
to give your users a hint
about what action the Enter key will take.
Instead of just Enter, it could be
Done, or Go, or Send, for example.
Before I wrap up the new web API,
there's one more API to mention...
the Web Authentication API.
It supports logging into websites
beyond usernames and passwords
and it was introduced in Safari 13
and Safari on iOS 13.3
with support for hardware security keys.
And with the latest Safari,
WebKit has added support
for Touch ID and Face ID
in Safari on macOS, iOS and iPadOS.
You can learn all
about the security and convenience
of implementing it for your users
by watching the "Face ID
and Touch ID on the Web" session
in the Developer app.
And that's a look at the new Web API
in Safari this year.
Web Animations, ResizeObserver,
the Async Clipboard API,
the EventTarget constructor,
CSS Shadow Parts, HTML enterkeyhint
and Web Authentication.
I can't wait to see what you do
with these new capabilities.
But we're not done yet.
Let's take a look
at several CSS improvements
that give content authors
more fine-grained control
over styles and layout.
This year, WebKit added support
for system font families.
They work in WebKit
across all of Apple's platforms.
They each map
to a system-appropriate font.
The system-ui font family
is a generic alias for ui-sans-serif
and on the system
it maps to San Francisco...
ui-serif uses the New York font family...
ui-monospace uses SF Mono...
and ui-rounded uses SF Rounded.
They're useful when developing a web app
that you wanna make feel
more familiar to the system.
And the different font families
allow you to create
an easily identifiable difference
between content and user interface,
such as on the WebKittens website.
It uses ui-serif for the content areas...
and ui-sans-serif for the user interface
when adding a comment.
So beautiful new font families
for your web apps.
Another CSS feature
that can help your content layout
is support for "line-break: anywhere."
It breaks to a new line at any opportunity
before the content overflows.
This can be particularly helpful
with long words that can overflow
narrow containers,
especially technical jargon, like code,
where hyphenation might change
the intended meaning of the word.
And it can protect your content
from unexpected layout issues.
The simplest way to understand it
is to see the behavior
of the default line-break rule.
WebKit uses a default line-break heuristic
that's based on language-specific rules,
while taking into account
other CSS that might apply.
With roman-based written languages,
the line-break heuristic
hyphenates the text when it can,
but take a look at the first word
on this page
from the Web Inspector
Command Line API Reference.
The long queryInstances syntax
doesn't break at all.
It's breaking right before the long word,
making a blank line after the bullet.
Then, it still overflows the container
and the viewport.
"Line-break: anywhere"
makes it possible to fix this.
With "line-break: anywhere," it breaks up
the character just before the overflow,
making it possible
to see all of the content
without breaking the layout.
Now it's possible to see the entire line.
Next up is another powerful CSS tool.
The "is" pseudo-selector.
It's newly supported in Safari 14.
It matches a list of selectors
just like the "matches" pseudo-selector.
In fact, "is" aliases
our "matches" pseudo-selector behavior
that's been part of Safari for years.
The matching element gets the specificity
of the most specific selector.
It's really useful
for avoiding repetitive selectors.
Here's an example.
Here, a 3em top margin
is added to all of the headings.
Then, this rule removes the top margin
when a heading is immediately followed
by a heading of the next level down.
But, of course, if this is used
in a content management system,
page authors may not adhere
to strict rules
of an h1 followed by an h2.
They're not technically prevented
from using an h1 followed by an h3,
so this isn't enough
to cover all of those cases.
To do that, you'd need
a really repetitive selector.
Like this.
That's pretty awful-looking.
But with "is," we can simplify
writing all of that out.
And it becomes this. That's so much nicer.
To go along with "is,"
WebKit also supports
the "where" pseudo-selector.
It works the same way as "is"
in that it matches a list of selectors,
but the big difference
is that the CSS specificity
of any matching element is always zero.
So it can act as
a kind of specificity reset.
Here's another example,
and I'll start by comparing "is" first.
Looking at this example, the "is"
selects an intro class, pullquote
or element with a hero id
and styles the paragraph tag
that immediately follows it
to use uppercase text
and give it an eye-grabbing look.
Later in the styles, the page author
is trying to specifically override
the heading levels two through six
followed by a paragraph
to use normal text.
Seems like they only want this
to work for paragraphs
following level one headings.
But using "is" means
that it won't work as expected.
This is where
the "where" pseudo-selector comes in.
Using "where" instead makes this possible.
Now, the elements matched by "where"
are reset to a specificity level of zero,
making the follow-up rules
able to override as expected.
From CSS, we move on to media.
But included in media is a fair number
of image updates as well.
And I'm pleased to announce support
for an entirely new image format...
WebP images.
WebP is an open-source image format
that provides smaller file sizes
and lots of advanced bells and whistles.
It supports a lossy format
comparable to JPEG
and a lossless format like PNG.
It even supports transparency
and animation across both.
In your markup,
you can use the picture element
to add WebP images with a fallback.
And on the server side,
you can look at the Accept header.
But a big reason web developers
are excited for this format
is the file size savings.
This sample JPEG
encoded at 80% quality is 5.1 megabytes,
but the WebP lossy encoding
at the same quality settings
gives us a 41% file savings
with visual quality
that's nearly the same as a JPEG.
This high resolution PNG
weighs in at 817 kilobytes,
but the lossless WebP encoding
preserves the transparency
and saves us 33%.
WebP image support is available
in Safari 14 and Safari for iOS 14.
While we're talking about images,
there are a couple of new
default image behaviors in WebKit.
The first is a change that will improve
the way your web pages load.
We've all seen what happens
when we load a web page
where the images load in
and cause the layout to jump around.
I'm going to show you
how easy it is to fix this
with WebKit's new behavior for calculating
the default image aspect ratio.
In Safari 13.1 and in Safari on iOS 13.4,
WebKit now calculates
the image aspect ratio
from an image tag's
width and height attributes.
All you have to do is make sure to add
the width and height attributes
to your image tags.
Let's see what happens
when the attributes are added.
There's no jumping around at all.
The space is reserved for the image
and it just loads right in.
Beautiful.
The other new default behavior
is for image orientation.
We've supported respecting
EXIF image orientation on iOS
for a long time.
This update aligns
our support on iOS and macOS
through the standard
image-orientation: from-image value.
The from-image value tells Safari
to respect the image-orientation flag
encoded into images
that support EXIF data.
This JPEG image is encoded
with an EXIF orientation flag of six,
meaning the camera was rotated
90 degrees counterclockwise.
And now you can override this default
by setting image-orientation value
to "none,"
to display the image directly as encoded,
without rotation correction.
From images, we move on to video.
With system support
for High Dynamic Range videos
and web content with Safari 14 on macOS.
You can use media queries to detect
High Dynamic Range display support.
In CSS, you can query support
with "dynamic-range: high" like this.
Or you can use the window's
matchMedia method in JavaScript
so you can deliver
progressively enhanced content
to users with HDR displays.
Continuing with video updates,
WebKit has added support
for the Remote Playback API.
We've always had an API
for doing AirPlay before,
but the Remote Playback API
is a standards-based way
of adding remote playback
of audio or video
to your custom web-based media player
and sending it to a variety
of other remote playback devices,
like connected TVs, audio-only speakers
and any AirPlay-capable devices.
To use it, you'll set up a custom button
on your video player controls
and in response to user interaction,
call the videoElement's
remote.prompt method.
Then, you can handle
updating remote playback state
in your callback handler.
It's really that easy.
Then, on your device,
users can tap on the control
to get a menu of available
remote playback devices.
When selected,
the video is sent to that device.
Supporting the Remote Playback API
gives your users the flexibility
to enjoy media on all of their devices.
And another way to help users
enjoy your media
is the picture-in-picture API.
Adding a picture-in-picture control
to your web player
allows users to play videos
in a pop-out window
while they continue doing other tasks.
Like remote playback,
WebKit has supported
picture-in-picture for a while,
but the standards-based
picture-in-picture API is now available
and it works across iOS, iPadOS and macOS.
Similar to using the Remote Playback API,
you setup a custom control element
and call the videoElement's
requestPictureInPicture method
in response to user interaction.
That's it.
Then your users can enjoy videos
in picture-in-picture mode on their device
while doing other tasks.
In other news related to video,
Safari 14 includes support
for timed metadata in HLS.
It's new in Safari 14.
And this is metadata synchronized
to the media time stamps
in the video stream.
It can be used to provide
program information like episode details
or live sports data
like inning boundaries or scores.
There are two approaches supported.
The HLS #EXT-X-DATERANGE tag
is available in the DataCue
and carries the metadata
to the HLS Media Playlists themselves.
The advantages of using these tags
is their immediacy and scope.
All metadata in Media Playlists
is available to the video player
as soon as it's loaded.
It doesn't require waiting
for the specific segment to load
or for the playhead to pass over it.
And event message boxes
are now available in fragmented MP4s.
These are compatible with ID3 storage
and other formats,
like MPEG-2 transport streams,
to carry the same metadata
in fragmented MP4 containers.
This is especially important
for codecs like HEVC and Dolby Atmos,
which Apple platforms only recognize
inside fragmented MP4s.
The last update is an enhancement
for developers of video sites
that provide subtitles and captioning.
This is a short, but sweet update.
It's an enhancement to TextTrackCue
that allows you to use
your own captions format,
but use native caption rendering.
Developers can use
existing caption formats
without needing to convert them all.
And because the user agent is responsible
for displaying the captions,
they get first-class
accessibility treatment.
Plus, they render in both full-screen
and picture-in-picture
without any extra work.
Those are our media updates,
with support for WebP images,
new defaults for image aspect ratio
and orientation,
Mac HDR video, timed metadata in HLS,
Remote Playback
and picture-in-picture APIs
with natively rendered
subtitles and captions.
Now it's time for new JavaScript features.
Starting with BigInt.
BigInts are a new data type in JavaScript.
They're integers
that are arbitrarily large
and most commonly used in cryptography,
but are useful wherever you need numbers
larger than the MAX_SAFE_INTEGER
in JavaScript.
But there are a few things
to keep in mind.
You can't use number operations
or mix operations
with the regular number data type.
You also can't use JSON.stringify
to serialize a BigInt
for backwards compatibility reasons.
You'll need to build your own
serialization functionality
to ensure the decoding process
matches your serialization format.
And be aware
that when using the division operator,
BigInts will drop any decimal values.
That's BigInt available in Safari 14.
But WebKit also supports
some powerful new operators
to help with null or undefined values.
The nullish coalescing operator
works like other logical operators,
but it checks for existence.
Let's look at a quick example.
So I have a Person class
where the constructor takes
a firstName, lastName and age argument.
The nullish coalescing operator
is used to check
if an argument's value is provided.
If it's null or undefined,
the result of the right-hand side
of the operator is used instead.
Here, without any arguments,
the right-hand side defaults,
as I like to think of them, are used.
But passing Boolean values,
regardless of what they are,
pass the existence check
and are set as the properties
on the Person object.
Passing a filled in string
or empty string, or even zero for the age
still evaluates to set the fields
to the passed-in arguments.
And finally, passing the full data
sets the properties.
And that's nullish coalescing.
Building on nullish coalescing,
and also new this year,
is optional chaining.
It's a new JavaScript syntax
that gives you a shortcut
for property access.
And it even works
for indexes and methods too.
Take a look at this example.
Here, we add a name property to include
both the first and last name.
And when a Person is registered,
we want to see the first name.
This is how you might typically
add some guards
to make sure you can access
the firstName property.
Passing no arguments to the Person
when calling "register"
gives us an undefined result.
And passing strings
for the firstName and lastName
gives us the expected firstName.
But with optional chaining,
we can replace this approach
with new syntax that uses
the optional chaining operator.
And it works in the exact same way.
It also works with indexes,
like checking for the first entry
in an array of a person's children.
Using optional chaining here
avoids the TypeError
and it even works for methods.
Trying to call an undeclared method
triggers an error,
but with optional chaining
you can avoid the error.
So that's optional chaining.
Sticking with the operators theme,
there are even more
newly available operators in Safari 14.
Logical assignment operators.
And they come in three flavors.
Logical and assignment,
logical or assignment...
plus a nullish assignment operator.
Logical assignment operators are nice
in that they only evaluate
the left-hand side expression once.
And it isn't as destructive
in that it doesn't always reassign.
Take this example
using the nullish coalescing operator
where it always reassigns innerHTML.
With a nullish assignment operator,
it only destructively assigns innerHTML
if it is null or undefined.
Switching gears
back to objects for a moment,
WebKit in Safari 14 includes support
for public class fields.
Public class fields are a new syntax
to declare member properties
that are part of the object,
regardless of them being set up
in the constructor.
Looking at the Person example earlier,
they could be set up like this.
Now, children, for example,
will still be available
when a new Person object is created,
even though it isn't set
in the constructor.
By not having it in the constructor,
you can focus on the logic
instead of worrying if variables are set
as public class fields
are guaranteed to always be added.
And a final utility in JavaScript
to look at is String replaceAll.
Finally, String replaceAll
is new in Safari 13.1
and it does what it promises,
replacing all instances of a string.
Previously, the String replace method
would only replace
the first occurrence of the string.
You'd have to iterate
over the words in the string
or use a global regular expression.
With replaceAll, you can replace
all the instances of the string.
And those are the powerful
new JavaScript features
available in Safari this year.
BigInt, nullish coalescing,
optional chaining,
logical assignment operators,
public class fields and String replaceAll.
That's our JavaScript updates.
And finally, I'm going to share
a few exciting platform integration
capabilities new this year.
First up is AR Quick Look on iOS.
These are experiences launched from Safari
that can be customized
with web technologies.
And new with iOS 13.3,
these experiences can include
a banner for users to buy products.
You can customize
individual elements of the banner
or provide a completely custom banner
with a simple HTML page.
To learn more, I encourage you
to check out the "Shop Online
with AR Quick Look" session
in the Developer app.
Another platform technology
in Safari updated this year
is Apple Pay.
Apple Pay on the web has been updated
to add new button types
with custom rounded corners
and the ability to request
redacted billing details.
This is great for merchants
that calculate tax
based on a customer's location,
but have no use for the shipping address.
To learn more,
see the "What's New
in Wallet and Apple Pay" session
in the Developer app.
Finally, another experience
new this year is App Clips.
It gives users a focused, fast
and frictionless experience
without waiting for downloading
and installing an entire app.
On your website, you can let users know
that an App Clip interaction is available
by adding the apple-itunes meta tag
to your website's HTML
and include your AppStoreID
and the new app-clip-bundle-id parameter
to add a banner to your website.
You can learn more about App Clips
by watching
the "Explore App Clips" session
in the Developer app.
That wraps up our platform integration
with customizable AR Quick Look,
Apple Pay updates
and the all-new App Clips experience.
And it also wraps up our tour
of the new features and improvements
of Safari and WebKit.
There's a whole lot new
in Safari this year
powered by changes in WebKit
and I encourage you
to try these features out
and share your feedback.
Now is the perfect time to test it.
And we'd love to hear how it goes,
especially if you run into bugs.
For Web API, CSS or JavaScript bugs,
you can file issues
on the WebKit bug tracker
at bugs.webkit.org.
For Safari bugs or issues specific to iOS,
Home Screen web apps
or Apple platform integration features,
you can use Feedback Assistant.
If you wanna stay on the leading edge
of what's coming,
you should download and use
Safari Technology Preview.
It's a separate version of Safari
that works right alongside of Safari
and it's shipped every two weeks
with a sneak peek of new
and experimental features,
as well as new Web Inspector tools.
So as a web developer, you can be using
the latest developer tools
every two weeks.
You can also stay informed
by keeping tabs
on the WebKit website at webkit.org.
It features blog posts,
Safari Technology Preview release notes
and a fantastic library
of reference guides
for using Web Inspector.
You can also follow WebKit on Twitter
for new announcements
about the WebKit project
along with tips and tricks
for Web Inspector.
And check out the links
related to this session,
including "Safari Web Extensions,"
"What's New in Web Inspector"
and more web technologies.
Thanks for joining me, and enjoy WWDC.