Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Devin,
and I'm thrilled to be able to show you
some of the many improvements
and new features
added to Web Inspector in the last year.
To start,
let's enable Web Inspector in Safari.
First, click on the Safari menu bar item
and select "Preferences"
to show Safari's Preferences.
Go to the Advanced tab
and enable
"Show Develop menu in menu bar".
In the now-visible Develop menu,
click "Show Web Inspector".
And there it is.
Web Inspector is your one-stop shop
for all introspection
and debugging tools for Web content,
whether that be in Safari,
a WKWebView in an app
or even a JSContext.
Before we dive into individual features,
let's take a look at some of the changes
that have been made
to the overall interface.
We've merged the toolbar and dashboard
into the tab bar
to save on vertical space.
Additionally, we've tightened the spacing
around many controls
throughout the interface,
allowing you to see more content
in Web Inspector
without having to sacrifice
on visibility of content
in the inspected page.
These changes also are not limited
to when docked to the bottom
as they also apply
when docked to the side,
and even when undocked
into a separate window.
We've also improved accessibility support
for navigating around Web Inspector
when using a screen reader.
For those of you that prefer Dark Mode,
we've created Dark Mode variants
for all of the icons
throughout Web Inspector,
as well as added a way to toggle Dark Mode
independently from the rest of the system
in the Settings tab.
Because there's no longer a dashboard,
the Network tab now shows
the inspected page statistics
below the main table,
and has been expanded to include
the number of unique domains,
the total transfer size,
and a count of all redirects.
This year, we've added new features
to almost every tab,
as well as adding a few entirely new tabs.
So, let's go through each,
starting with the new Sources tab.
For those of you who've used
Web Inspector in the past,
the Sources tab takes
all of the best features
of the Resources tab and the Debugger tab,
and combines them into a single tab.
The Sources tab lists all resources
loaded by the inspected page
since Web Inspector was opened,
including long-lived things
like WebSockets,
or more ephemeral things
like XHRs or Fetches.
The Sources tab is also the primary place
for JavaScript debugging,
containing all of the JavaScript debugger
stepping controls
and many
of the breakpoint-adding capabilities
provided by Web Inspector.
And new this year,
the Sources tab is home
to the network-overriding capabilities
provided by Web Inspector,
which we'll see in a minute.
So, let's take a look.
When viewing resources in the Sources tab,
Web Inspector will provide
alternate representations
for applicable content,
giving you another way
to explore and examine the content
to understand what's going on,
or fix any issues.
Right now, we're looking at
the response content of this resource,
which we can see is HTML text.
In this case, the head is filled
with a lot of meta and link tags,
meaning that we'd have to scroll down
to see any of the content of the body.
Additionally, it's harder to see
where tags begin and end
when they're all scrunched up
like this in the text.
It would be a lot easier to navigate
if we could visualize
this response content
as a DOM tree instead,
just like in the Elements tab.
Clicking on the Response breadcrumb item
will show a drop-down
with all of the alternate representations
Web Inspector provides for this resource.
Selecting the response "DOM Tree"
will visualize the response content
as a DOM tree, just like we wanted.
Similar alternate representations
are also provided
for when the content is valid JSON,
showing an object tree
as if it were logged in the Console.
These alternate representations
are also available
when content is sent as part of a request.
In situations that you do find an issue
in the resource's response,
it's not always easy to make a change
to the source code
that the resource was loaded from
as it may exist on a faraway server,
or involve complicated
preprocessing steps.
I am very excited to tell you
that this year
Web Inspector has added a new feature
to solve this exact problem.
We call them "local overrides".
Creating one is as simple as clicking
the "Create Override" button
when viewing any resource,
which will automatically copy
the current contents of that resource
into a new local override
for that resource.
They are fully editable
and are preserved by Web Inspector
across sessions of both the inspected page
and Web Inspector itself.
So, let's try making a simple change
to see a local override in action.
Scrolling down in the content area,
we can see the WebKit text in the header.
We can change this WebKit text
to something like "Hello WWDC" instead.
If we take a look at the inspected page
and reload,
we can see that the WebKit text
in the header of the inspected page
changes to match the edits we just made.
Even better, local overrides support
more than just modifying
the response's content.
If you right-click on the local override
in Web Inspector
and select
the "Edit Local Override" action,
it's also possible to modify
the HTTP status code
or any HTTP headers.
When the inspected page
loads anything over the network
that matches any local override's URL,
the entire response,
including the HTTP status code
and any HTTP headers,
will be completely replaced
by the local override
as it's been configured.
Whenever this happens, the icon
of the overridden resource will change,
indicating that it was replaced.
And this overridden icon is shown anywhere
that the resource can be seen
throughout Web Inspector.
As further proof,
if we select the overridden resource
and scroll down,
the same modifications we made
to the content are also present.
All resources, including
the main resource like we just saw,
and even non-text resources like images,
can be overridden and fully configured
from within Web Inspector.
Sometimes, however,
it's not necessarily a particular resource
that you wanna change,
but really a JavaScript API
provided by WebKit.
In these cases, you'll want to use
the new Inspector Bootstrap Script,
which can be added
from the "Add Resource" button
in the bottom corner
of the navigation sidebar
in the Sources tab by selecting
the "Inspector Bootstrap Script" action.
Similar to how local overrides
allow you to modify resources
loaded over the network,
the Inspector Bootstrap Script
can be thought of as a way to modify
the JavaScript API surface itself.
The contents
of the Inspector Bootstrap Script
are guaranteed to run before anything else
in the inspected page,
hence the "bootstrap" name.
This allows you to do things
like swizzle built-in functions
to see where they get called,
or set up some global state
that causes your code to log
additional debugging information.
Just like local overrides,
the Inspector Bootstrap Script
is preserved by Web Inspector
across sessions
of both the inspected page
and Web Inspector itself.
Speaking of debugging JavaScript,
we've also added a number
of new global breakpoints.
The Debugger Statements breakpoint
controls whether or not
JavaScript execution
is paused at debugger statements.
Previously, the only way to control this
was to completely disable all breakpoints.
We felt that this was
unnecessarily restrictive,
so we created this separate control
to allow you to use
other types of breakpoints
while simultaneously disabling
debugger statements specifically.
The other new breakpoints,
since they relate to specific APIs,
must be enabled by clicking
on the "Add Breakpoint" button,
which will show a menu with actions
that each enable
one of these new different breakpoints.
So, let's go through each of them
one by one.
The All Microtasks breakpoint
will pause JavaScript execution
whenever any microtask
is about to be executed,
such as from Promise objects
or the queueMicrotask global function.
Along these lines,
the All Animation Frames breakpoint
does the same
for requestAnimationFrame callbacks,
the All Timeouts breakpoint
does the same for setTimeout callbacks,
and the All Intervals breakpoint
does the same for setInterval callbacks.
Lastly, the All Events breakpoint
will pause
before any callback is invoked
for any eventListener,
even those unrelated to the DOM.
But sometimes these global breakpoints
are almost too global
in the sense that they pause
more often than desired.
Let's take a look at an example
using the All Events breakpoint.
I have a simple page that uses jQuery
to add an EventListener
to a button element.
Because I've enabled
the All Events breakpoint,
I would expect to pause
inside this EventListener.
But in reality, jQuery wraps
my EventListener callback
with its own logic,
so instead we pause
in jQuery's EventListener wrapper,
which is not really ideal
as none of this is my code.
Really, what I want to do
is have this breakpoint pause in my code
after all of jQuery's code has run.
Script blackboxing is a new feature
that allows you to do just that,
instructing the JavaScript debugger
to defer any pause
that would occur in a script
to pause at the first expression
to execute outside of that script.
We can do this to jQuery
by hovering over the jQuery resource
in the navigation sidebar
and clicking on the button that appears.
Now, if we trigger this breakpoint again,
we should pause
in our EventListener instead.
If, for some reason,
you still do want to dig
into the library or framework code,
Web Inspector will still show
any call frames from blackboxed script,
graying them out
to indicate their blackbox nature.
For larger libraries and frameworks,
it's also possible to blackbox
multiple scripts at once
by configuring regular expression patterns
to match against the script's URL
in the Settings tab.
In addition to some
of the global breakpoints
we've seen so far, Web Inspector
also allows you to set breakpoints
on specific lines of JavaScript,
even after pretty-printing.
Clicking on any line
in the gutter area of the content preview
will add a JavaScript breakpoint
that will pause right before
that line executes.
Because JavaScript is so flexible
with its syntax, however,
it's not uncommon to see
lots of operations combined
onto a single line,
using a mix of various operators.
In this case, the logical "or" operator.
Previously, if I wanted to pause
inside the "c" function call
and I didn't know where "c"
was declared to set a breakpoint,
the only way to do this
would be to use the Step In
JavaScript debugger action
to step in to "a"
and then step out to move past "a",
then step in again to go inside "b"
and finally, step back out again
to arrive at "c".
This is a very tedious process
with lots of opportunity for mistakes,
which can be incredibly frustrating,
especially in cases
where the starting state is hard to reach.
This has led us to introduce
a new JavaScript debugger action
which we call "Step".
Unlike the Step Over
JavaScript debugger action,
which resumes and re-pauses execution
before the next statement
in the current call frame,
which, in this case, would be after
the entire foo variable declaration,
this new Step debugger action
will resume and re-pause
JavaScript execution
before the next expression
in the current call frame.
And just like that, we've resumed,
executed "a" and re-paused
on the same line
without ever having
to step in or step out.
Once more, we can Step to resume,
execute "b",
and re-pause,
arriving at the call for "c".
The Step JavaScript debugger action
provides more fine-grained control
over how the JavaScript debugger
execution head moves through the program,
allowing for fewer stepping mistakes,
and even less actions in total.
But sometimes scripts
are inlined into HTML.
In the past, there was no way
to pretty-print
this inlined script content,
or even any of the surrounding HTML.
As a result, it was often difficult
to set breakpoints,
or even step through code
in a nicely readable way.
I'm very happy to say
that in the latest Safari,
Web Inspector now supports formatting HTML
and other XML-like content,
including inline scripts and style sheets,
allowing support for all of the existing
JavaScript debugger
and stepping capabilities too.
Simply click on the "Pretty-Print" button
in the top right
of any text-based content preview
to toggle between the original content
and the pretty-printed version.
Web Inspector will also attempt to detect
when HTML has been minified
and automatically toggle pretty-printing,
just like it has always done
for JavaScript and CSS content.
So, speaking
of Web Inspector functionality,
there's so much more
than just viewing resources.
So, let's move on
to some of the other powerful
or more specialized features,
starting with the Timelines tab.
The Timelines tab contains
the majority
of performance-profiling tools
offered by Web Inspector.
It captures activity in the inspected page
during what we call "a recording",
which organizes and plots the data
into one of a handful
of different timelines
based on the type of data.
Timeline recordings can also be
exported and imported,
allowing you to share them with others,
or save them for later use.
The main change this year
in the Timelines tab
is an introduction
of an entirely new timeline,
which you can activate by clicking
the "Edit" button in the main graph area.
This will put us in Edit mode,
where we can enable or disable
any of the various timelines.
The new timeline we've added this year
is the Media and Animations timeline,
which captures events related
to media elements, like video or audio,
and also captures the life cycle
of CSS animations and CSS transitions.
After checking the checkbox to enable
the Media and Animations timeline,
and clicking the "Done" button
to leave Edit mode,
if we reload the inspected page,
we can see a list of all media elements,
CSS animations and CSS transitions
that have had any activity
during the recorded interval.
Each individual media element,
CSS animation or CSS transition
has its own row in the table,
with links to any related DOM node,
or information about
the CSS animation name,
or CSS transition property.
The Media and Animations timeline
can also be used to correlate activity
captured in other timelines
with state changes in any media elements,
such as a video being paused,
or the creation or destruction
of any CSS animations or CSS transitions,
to figure out what's going on
and understand why.
And that's a quick look
at the Media and Animations timeline
in the Timelines tab.
Let's move on to the Storage tab.
So, the Storage tab
contains a list of all of the data
stored by the inspected page
in the browser,
via things like cookies
or localStorage or IndexedDB.
This year,
we've added filtering capabilities
for all storage types,
and improved editing
and deleting capabilities,
especially for cookies.
The new filtering capabilities
take the form
of an always-visible filter bar
shown at the top of most storage views.
As an example,
filtering cookies is as simple
as typing some text into the filter bar,
which is compared
against the various fields of each cookie,
hiding any rows that had no matches.
The second major feature
is the ability to edit cookies.
Double-clicking on one of a cookie's cells
will show a popover with inputs
for each field of that cookie.
All modifications made in this popover
will be applied
as soon as the popover is dismissed.
It is also possible
to add entirely new cookies
by clicking on the "Add Cookie" button,
which will show a similar popover,
but this time
all of the inputs will be empty.
Note that a name is required
in order for a cookie to be added.
Just like HTTP cookies
or those set by document.cookie,
they will persist beyond Web Inspector,
so be careful what you add.
But many other features of the Web
are not persistent,
so let's take a look at tooling
for some of those,
starting with the all-new Graphics tab.
For those of you who've used
Web Inspector in the past few years,
you may remember using the Canvas tab.
The Graphics tab expands the scope
and functionality of the Canvas tab,
still showing all
canvas contexts and shaders,
and supporting taking recordings
of JavaScript API calls
made with canvas contexts,
but now also listing all Web Animations,
including those created
by CSS animations and CSS transitions,
providing in-depth information about each.
The previously available information
about all canvas contexts
in the inspected page
is still shown
in the Canvases section at the top,
followed by the new sections
for the various types of animations
created by the Web Animations API,
separated by how they're created,
such as from JavaScript,
CSS animations or CSS transitions.
Clicking on one of these animations
will expand the Details sidebar,
which contains all of the information
about the selected animation,
such as the ID, which can be
thought of as the animation's name,
the associated node of the animation,
the configured timing parameters,
like the number of iterations
or the total duration,
the keyframes list,
each item containing
a list of CSS properties and values
that are interpolated between
as the animation progresses,
and finally, for animations
that are created by the JavaScript API,
a backtrace for how the animation
was created.
Clicking the "markup" icon
in the header of any animation
will show a context menu
with a number of utility actions,
such as "Log Animation",
which will save the JavaScript object
for that Web Animation
in a temporary variable in the Console,
in this case "dollar sign one",
allowing us to have easy access
for manipulating it
using the powerful Web Animations API.
For more information
about the new Web Animations API,
be sure to check out
the "What's New for Web Developers"
session
in your Developer App.
But sometimes
animations are configured incorrectly,
which causes performance problems.
So, let's take a look
at the new Layers tab
to see how it can help.
The Layers tab shows a live view
of the layer tree of the inspected page,
listing the memory cost
and the paint count for each layer.
While it's not exactly one-to-one,
it's generally a good idea
to keep the number of unintended layers
as low as possible,
as a greater number of layers
can be associated
with increased memory use
and worse performance.
The key word there, though,
is "unintended,"
which really requires you,
the developer, to know your layout
and when things should
and should not create a layer.
To assist with this, clicking on a layer,
either in the visualization itself
or in the Details sidebar,
will show information about that layer,
such as why it was created.
In the case
of the currently selected layer,
it was created because the associated node
was being animated by CSS
and had a CSS willChange property.
The entire layer tree visualization
can also be manipulated
using common orbit controls,
such as rotating vertically
by clicking and dragging up and down...
rotating horizontally
by clicking and dragging left and right...
zooming by scrolling in and out...
and panning by right-clicking
and dragging,
making it easy to find layers visually
to find out more about them.
So, now let's move on to our final tab,
the Console.
The Console tab lists
all of the various messages
logged by the inspected page,
and allows arbitrary JavaScript evaluation
in the inspected page.
Special functionality is also exposed
while evaluating JavaScript,
intended to make inspecting
and debugging JavaScript easier
by providing more information
previously known only to WebKit.
There are a whole bunch of these
Console-only, specially-exposed bits
of functionality that are new this year,
but there are two
that are particularly noteworthy.
The first is called QueryInstances.
So, let's imagine a simple
JavaScript class hierarchy
of an Animal base class
with a Pet subclass.
Now, let's say that we want to find
all instances of this Pet subclass.
One way to do it would be
to examine a captured heap snapshot
in the Timelines tab,
but that includes
a lot of other information
that is likely not relevant.
So instead, QueryInstances,
when given a constructor,
will scan the entire JavaScript heap
for instances of objects that inherit
from that given constructor,
returning them all in an array
that can be further manipulated
in the Console.
As we can see here,
there is one instance of this Pet class,
which is held in the variable
with the name "Buddy".
Note, however, that due to the nature
of JavaScript inheritance,
the term "instance" also applies
to subclass objects as well.
As an example,
if we call QueryInstances
with the Animal constructor,
we will not only see
the previously seen "Buddy" variable,
but we will also see an instance of Animal
held by the "cat" variable,
and even the entire Pet class,
as it also inherits from the Animal class.
For more flexibility, it's also possible
to provide a prototype
instead of a constructor,
which will have the exact same result
we saw earlier
with the related constructor.
The second noteworthy function
is called queryHolders.
So, again, let's imagine
a simple JavaScript class called Person.
Similar to reality,
each Person can have a Parent.
This is represented in JavaScript
as a Parent property,
whose value is the other Person object.
This is called a strong reference
and is a common cause
of memory leaks in JavaScript programs.
If we wanted to find all objects
that have a strong reference
to a given object,
we could examine a captured heap snapshot
in the Timelines tab,
but again, this may include
other information
that is likely not relevant.
Instead, we can use the queryHolders
Console function,
which, when given an object,
will scan the entire JavaScript heap
for all other objects
that have a strong reference
to that given object.
As we can see in this example,
Alice has a strong reference to John
through its Parent property,
which is why Alice appears in the array
returned by queryHolders.
Now let's talk
about our last feature for today.
I'm very happy to announce
that in the latest Safari,
so long as Web Inspector is already open,
enabling "Intelligent Tracking Prevention
Debug Mode"
from Safari's Develop menu
will cause all debug logging
from Safari's
Intelligent Tracking Prevention
to also appear
in the Web Inspector Console,
as well as in the macOS system
Console.app.
Additionally, logs
for Ad Click Attribution Debug Mode
will also be shown
in the Web Inspector Console,
which can be enabled
from the Experimental Features submenu
of Safari's Develop menu.
This way, you'll never
have to switch away from Safari
to see all of the logs
you might find useful.
And with that, we've reached
the end of our feature highlights.
There is so much more
coming in the latest Safari,
including a ton of bug fixes
and minor tweaks throughout Web Inspector.
Before we finish up,
there's a few general tips
I'd like to leave you with.
Tooltips are your friend.
If you're unsure of what something does,
simply hover over it with your cursor
for a few seconds
and voilà, the answer will appear.
Every icon in Web Inspector has a tooltip.
All links have a tooltip.
In fact, almost every component
of the interface has a tooltip.
Web Inspector makes heavy use
of iconography
as there's a ton of varying functionality
that has to fit into
a very limited amount of space.
As such, it relies on tooltips
to provide additional explanation
and description
where there isn't enough room.
For a similar reason,
context menus are everywhere
and they often contain
additional functionality
that can't be accessed anywhere else.
Many icons have a context menu.
Every link has a context menu.
Again, almost every component
of the interface has a context menu.
And, in fact,
most of what we've done so far
could've also been done
via a context menu action.
For much of the same reason as tooltips,
Web Inspector puts a lot of functionality
into context menu actions
as there isn't enough room for each action
to have its own component
in the interface.
For more tips like those,
there's an all-new section
of the WebKit website
that talks specifically
about Web Inspector.
It contains a bunch of reference pages
that each explore
both the breadth and the depth
of various features,
parts of the interface and more.
In fact, many of the features
we talked about today
already have reference pages,
and we're working on writing even more
for many of the others.
Also, be sure to follow @webkit on Twitter
as we post weekly tips
about various features in Web Inspector.
And I'd also highly recommend
using Safari Technology Preview
for your daily development
as it gets biweekly updates
with bug fixes and new features
both to Web Inspector
and to the rest of WebKit.
Be sure to check out
this session's related resources
or other sessions
about some of these new features,
as well as links to our documentation.
I really hope you've enjoyed learning
about what's new in Web Inspector,
and I hope you find
the things we've discussed useful
for understanding and debugging
Web content in the future.
Thank you so much for listening,
and I hope you have a wonderful WWDC.