[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name's Tina.
I work on SwiftUI.
Today I'm going to talk about building
apps supporting documents with SwiftUI.
First off, what is a document?
People have been managing their files
with the Finder and Files app
on macOS, iPadOS and iOS.
They can use features like tags,
cloud file providers
and external storage devices
to organize their projects as they need.
They expect to be able to use apps
that allow them to seamlessly open
these files in place, view and edit them.
This includes being able to make changes
on the original document,
where the change is accessible to all apps
that support opening files in place.
This is in contrast to apps
that import those files into some database
that is then managed by the app.
When you edit an imported document,
you're editing a copy
of the original document,
and the original is unchanged.
Professional apps like Pixelmator
not only allows users
to do openInPlace file management,
but also enable powerful
editing capabilities,
including opening multiple files at once.
Almost all of the functionality in apps
like Pixelmator,
Keynote and Final Cut Pro
is focused on allowing users
to do this management of documents.
We often call these "document-based apps"
as an indication of that behavior.
But opening documents
is a feature your app can support
without being entirely document-based.
Apps like Xcode
have additional UI and features
outside of its document support.
And apps like Mail and Console
primarily present
a non-document-based appearance,
but support opening additional documents,
like EML files or crash reports.
A SwiftUI application
is composed of apps, scenes and views.
Adding support for documents
is done compositionally
using another scene type,
called DocumentGroup.
A simple text-editing app looks like this.
When you use DocumentGroup in your app,
you're declaring that your app supports
opening and managing
this type of document in place.
As shown in
the "App Essentials in SwiftUI" talk,
the structure of our code matches
the hierarchy of ownership of an app.
In this case, our app contains
a single DocumentGroup scene,
able to open multiple windows
of that document content.
And of course, as a compositional element,
it could support multiple DocumentGroups
for different types,
or a WindowGroup and a DocumentGroup.
You can compose these scenes
into your app,
and SwiftUI automatically gives your app
the expected platform behaviors
for those scenes.
That includes standard UI elements
specific to document apps.
State Tracking and Handoff on Mac,
and Document Browser
and the Navigation Bar
with search field
and sharing functionality on iOS.
You get all these with very minimal code.
Now let's build something
using DocumentGroup API.
So I was prototyping a drawing app
with SwiftUI on my iPad Playground.
I currently have a canvas
where I can add shapes of different colors
and change their shapes.
I think it's working quite well,
so I want to make it into an app
where I can save and manage my drawings.
Let's see how to do this.
Let's open Xcode
and create a document-based app.
I want to have it run on both macOS
and iOS,
so I'm going to choose
the multi-platform template.
I'm going to call it "ShapeEdit."
This already comes with some templates.
Let's try building and running this.
We now have a text-editing app
that has all
the document-supporting features
we mentioned before.
Now, before we dive in,
let's have a look at the project settings.
I'm going to focus on
the macOS target for now,
but the configuration we're going to use
applies to both the iOS and macOS targets.
Let's take a look at the Info.plist.
Xcode adds the "Document Type" section
for document-based apps.
The value in this identifier field
is a uniform type identifier.
The system uses this identifier
to associate files with your app,
so it knows to open this type of document
in your app
when it sees one on the system.
This identifier is declared
as an imported type down here.
It's imported because the plain text type
was declared by another party,
and we import this type declaration
to tell the system
that the app knows about it.
For our app,
we're going to declare a type of our own,
so let's come back here...
and create one.
[typing]
Since it's a type we invented,
we need to export the type declaration
to tell the system that we are
the authoritative owner of this type.
We do this by filling out
the "Exported Type Identifier" section.
Let's give it a description.
We're going to store
the drawing app's binary data,
so make it conform to public data...
and public content.
I'm also going to assign it an extension.
So this is all we need to change here.
Let's have a look at the main function.
Our document type ShapeEditDocument
is declared for us already.
Both the type of document
and the base document to use
when creating new documents
are passed to DocumentGroup.
The document property
of the closure's argument is a binding
that provides us with read-write access
to the underlying data model,
which is the text
in this text-editing app.
DocumentGroup supports opening place,
and the binding lets SwiftUI know
when the text is updated
so it takes care of registering undo
and dirtying the document state.
Let's take a look at ContentView,
which is the default view
for presenting the document.
It consists of a TextEditor.
Since we're going to do
a shape-drawing app,
we're going to replace it with a canvas
where users can draw.
But we'll come back to that later.
Let's have a look at a ShapeEditDocument.
It is a value type that conforms
to the file document protocol,
which is the representation
of a document on disk.
First, we are going to define
readableContentTypes.
It's an array of UTType,
the uniform type identifier.
SwiftUI uses this to identify
the type of a document
that your user wants to open,
and only those defined here are allowed.
exampleText is defined here.
This should match what we put
in the "Document Types" section
of the target's Info.plist earlier,
so let's change this.
Notice the difference
between the two declarations.
Here, we're using
the exportedAs constructor,
while previously we were using
the importedAs constructor.
The imported type is a computed variable
because it's imported.
That means its value can change over time
as apps are installed or uninstalled.
Here, we're using an exported type,
so it can be declared a constant.
For more information,
see the documentation for UTType
on the Developer website.
Now let's change this...
to our own type.
Next, let's implement
initializing our document,
giving the FileWrapper
and the contentType.
We don't need this code,
so I'm going to remove them.
The contentType argument
is always the type supported by the app.
And there are a few ways to do this.
Here, we're going to use a JSONDecoder.
And to use a JSONDecoder,
the type needs to conform to "Codable."
We also need to implement
writing out the document to a file
for our specified type.
We don't need these either,
so I'm also going to remove them.
FileWrapper is the destination
of the serialization.
It's an inout argument,
and we can either create
the new FileWrapper or update it.
Again, there are a few ways to do this,
and we'll use a JSONEncoder.
So that's all we need to do
to conform to the file document protocol.
Notice that we are working with
a value type here.
This means that you get all the benefits
of working with this struct,
including copy-on-write behavior,
and that the app can start saving
while the user is still drawing.
Now, with document support in place,
let's add our prototype canvas code
into the project.
We have a graphic type
that defines the attributes of the shapes
and a Canvas View to display the shapes.
Let's change the data type in the document
from text to our graphic type.
Let's also add some initial shapes.
Let's also swap out the TextEditor
with our canvas.
And we're all set. Let's run it.
We have a drawing app
that supports documents.
I can save the drawings
and revisit them later.
So, this is how easy it is
to add document support
to your app in SwiftUI.
Thank you.
[chimes]