Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. My name is Abhi,
and I'm a software engineer here at Apple.
Thanks for joining our session.
Today, we'll take a look at USD
as it's used around the world,
new workflows enabled by Reality
Composer's new USD export functionality,
and then take a peek behind the curtains
at the new AR USD schemas
helping make these workflows possible.
Last year, we introduced
Reality Composer for macOS and iOS,
with the goal of making
interactive AR content creation
intuitive and easy for developers.
Reality Composer allows you to import
your own USDZ content
or get started with a great built-in
library of static and procedural assets
and bring them to life with interactions,
physics, anchoring, and more.
This year, we've made it even easier
to bring content
from a Digital Content Creation tool,
or a DCC, into Reality Composer
with the introduction
of Reality Converter.
We've also added support to export content
from Reality Composer as a USDZ,
which enables new workflows between
Reality Composer and a variety of DCCs.
To make this possible,
we've worked in collaboration with Pixar
to develop new preliminary AR USD schemas,
which we'll take a look at in-depth
later in this session.
For those unfamiliar with USDZ,
USDZ is the compact,
single-file distribution format for USD.
It is optimized for sharing
and is deeply integrated into iOS,
macOS and tvOS
in applications like Messages, Files,
Safari and more.
If you're interested to learn more
about USDZ as a distribution format,
including more about
its underlying technology, USD,
and relevant concepts such as schemas,
composition,
the stage, prims, and properties,
we encourage you
to check out last year's session,
"Working with USD,"
in the "related talks" section.
Over even just the last year,
we've seen an exciting growth
in the adoption of USD
and the USDZ file format.
USD is being used everywhere,
from films to gaming to AR to DCCs.
A few examples include Pixar,
which uses USD for its films,
and Maya, Houdini, Unity, Unreal Engine,
and Adobe Aero,
which support USD interchange,
either as export or import or both.
So, why USD?
Let's take a high-level look
at other formats out there today.
The most basic format is .obj,
which essentially contains
a single 3D model.
It has limited material support
and no support for animations.
Then there's a large group
of more modern file formats.
They usually support multiple models
that can be laid out in a scene graph
and usually support
material definitions and animations.
USD supports all of this,
and is additionally designed
to be scalable.
Pixar developed USD for use in its films.
USD also allows for collaboration,
allowing for many artists
to work on a single scene
without getting in each other's way.
USDZ is the archive package
and inherits most of these features
and is optimized for sharing.
Next, we'll take a look at new workflows
enabled by Reality Composer's
new USDZ export functionality
and then take a peek behind the curtains
at the new AR USD schemas
that make this possible.
When Reality Composer launched last year,
it supported the import of USDZ content
and the export to Reality File.
This year,
we've expanded the artist workflow
with the introduction
of Reality Converter,
which makes it easy to convert content
from DCCs to USDZ
for import and use in Reality Composer.
New this year as well
is the ability to export
content created in Reality Composer
to USDZ.
This enables not only new artist workflows
between Reality Composer and DCCs,
but creates an ecosystem
of content creation tools
all speaking the same language: USD.
So, for example, we can start
by creating custom content in a DCC
and use Reality Converter
to convert it to a USDZ
and import it into Reality Composer.
Or we could import a USDZ we found online
or exported from another application
directly into Reality Composer.
And the third option
is we can start with any of the great
built-in content inside the asset library.
Next, we can add functionality
specific to Reality Composer,
such as interactions or physics
to bring our content to life
and anchoring
to help place it in the world.
We can then export our creation
as a Reality File or as a USDZ.
Last year,
with the export of only Reality Files,
we would have been able to
share our content online
with family and friends,
view it in AR Quick Look
or use it in an application.
However, this is where
our content creation story would've ended.
This year, the journey continues.
We can take our USDZ
and continue making edits in any DCC
that supports the USDZ file format.
For example,
we could scatter our content in Houdini,
export it, pick it up in Maya,
make a few more edits, export it again,
and bring it back into Reality Composer
to make a few final additions.
We've designed the new AR USD schemas,
which we'll take a closer look at
later in this session,
so that they are compatible with DCCs
and viewers that haven't yet adopted them,
allowing you to make edits
without losing information
and view content
as accurately as possible.
So let's take a look
at an artist workflow.
So here I'm in Reality Composer,
and I've brought in some USDZ assets
from a variety of different sources.
For example,
here we have a plane and a toy car
from the AR Quick Look gallery
available online.
I've also worked with artists
to create some really nice assets,
including this sun asset
and this cloud asset.
And finally,
I've also worked with our artist
to create a nice wooden flag asset that
fits well with the rest of our content.
We've already brought it
through Reality Composer
and added a few behaviors.
So when I tap on this flag,
we'll see that it performs a behavior
and then displays some additional content.
So let's go ahead and preview that.
Again, this is a single USD.
So we'll see our content move
and additional content show up.
That looks pretty awesome.
So what I want to do in this demo now
is take all of my USDZ assets,
export them, bring them into Houdini,
and make them race against each other
with the beat of some music
that I made in GarageBand.
So the first thing we'll want to do
is export this content to USDZ,
and we can do that
by first going into our preferences...
and selecting "enable USDZ export."
Now when we go to export our content,
we'll see two different options.
We'll see the USDZ option
and our existing
Reality File export option.
Let's go ahead and export to USDZ.
And I've already done this
and brought it into Houdini,
so let's jump over to our prebaked scene.
So here we have our USDZ assets
in Houdini now.
We can see our toy car and our toy plane,
and I've worked with my artist
to position them
to create this racing scene.
So we can see we've instanced some of our
road assets and placed them along,
and we've also animated all of our content
to some additional music
that I made in GarageBand before.
We can see the full setup of our scene
right here in the Houdini editor,
and we can also get a preview
of our content right here.
So we'll see in our scene
I've also placed our flag asset.
Houdini doesn't yet
understand the behavior schema,
so we won't actually see our flag animate
and additional content show up.
However, it's still an asset,
so we can still place it.
When I go to export my content,
these behaviors are still
inside of the USD,
so when we bring it back
into Reality Composer
or another RealityKit-based application,
we should see our behaviors show up again.
So this is looking pretty good,
and what I want to do next
is export my content
so I can bring it back
into Reality Composer
and add a few final behaviors
like a play animation and some audio.
So, let's go ahead and export
our content from Houdini.
And I've already done that
and brought it into Reality Composer,
so let's jump over to our final scene.
So here in Reality Composer,
we have our baked asset from Houdini.
We can see it comes in
as one big asset together.
So we have our instance road,
our toy car and our toy plane
and some instance clouds as well.
And we'll notice that it has a behavior.
I've already gone ahead
and set up a couple of behaviors here.
Specifically, a Tap Trigger,
a USDZ Animation and a Play Music action.
The USDZ Animation targets our baked scene
and will play that animation
that we built in Houdini,
which moves the plane and the car
to the beat of some music.
So let's go ahead and preview our scene.
We can see that when I tap on the flag,
our original behavior comes through.
It's gone all the way through Houdini
and now comes back in Reality Composer.
And now...
[lively music plays]
...we'll see that our content animates,
and we hear some audio.
That looks pretty sweet.
I think I'm ready to export this now
as USDZ
and bring it into my RealityKit
application
and publish it to the App Store.
So we've seen how we can start
with some content in Reality Composer
that we've brought in
from various different sources,
including the AR Quick Look Gallery
and other DCCs.
And we saw how, for example,
the flag asset kept the behaviors
that we imbued from Reality Composer
through a full import, export,
and import flow
between Reality Composer, Houdini,
and again, Reality Composer.
So that's a look at the new workflows
and USD-based content creation ecosystem
enabled by Reality Composer's
new USDZ export functionality.
Next, let's take a closer look
behind the scenes
at the new AR USD schemas
making the export of Reality Composer
content to USDZ possible.
Reality Composer enables you to create
many different kinds of experiences
with features like scenes, AR anchoring,
interactions, physics, 3D text,
spatial audio, and more.
We've worked in collaboration with Pixar
to create new preliminary schemas
and structures for all of this
to enable the export
of Reality Composer content to USDZ.
As a reminder,
schemas are USD's extension mechanism,
allowing you to specify new types
in the Library.
In this section, we want to give you
an overview of these new schemas
so you can gain an intuition
of their design
to adopt into your own content
or editor applications.
We encourage you to also check out
our in-depth documentation
available on the Developer site
for more information and examples.
So let's start with scenes.
Scenes are a fundamental part
of Reality Composer.
A single scene can contain multiple models
and specify scene-wide properties,
such as gravity, ground plane materials
and where in the world
our content would like to be anchored.
You can create multiple scenes
in a single Reality Composer project
and load each individually
in an application
or stitch them together
with the change scene action
to create a larger overall experience.
The scene structure in USD defines
multiple scenes in a single USD file,
with scenes being targetable by behaviors.
You can also load a scene by name
in a RealityKit-based application
just like you can for a Reality File.
Let's take a look at the scene structure
in a USD.
Here we're taking a look
at the plain-text version of USD,
known as a USDA, for readability.
Scenes are structured
under a scene library,
which is specified using a new type
of "kind" metadata called sceneLibrary,
on the root prim.
Each Xformable prim under this root prim
is considered a scene,
and it can contain its own tree of prims
defining meshes, materials, behaviors,
anchoring, and more,
just like in a single-scene USD.
Scenes can be marked active
by using the "def" specifier
and inactive
by using the "over" specifier.
This also allows DCCs and viewers that
haven't yet adopted the scene structure
to still be able to view
all active scenes.
So if we want to swap
the "def" and "over" for our scenes,
we'll now see the sphere
instead of the cube.
In addition,
each scene can be given a readable name.
This name can be used
to load a particular scene
from the USDZ
in a RealityKit-based application,
just like you would for a Reality File.
Note that RealityKit, AR Quick Look,
and Reality Composer
only support a single active scene
in a scene library
and don't yet support nested scenes.
Next, let's take a look at anchoring.
Anchoring helps specify where content
should anchor in the real world.
For example, one scene can anchor
to a horizontal plane,
like a table or a floor,
and another scene can anchor to and follow
an image or a face.
The AR anchoring schema
is an applied schema
that supports specifying
the horizontal plane, vertical plane,
image, and face anchoring types.
Note that ARObject and GeoLocation anchors
aren't yet supported in USD.
Let's take a look at how to add
anchoring information to a USD.
Here we have a basic cube in our USD.
We want to anchor this cube
to an image in the real world.
We can do this by first applying
the anchoring schema to the prim...
and then specifying the anchoring type.
In this case, because we're aligning
our content to an image,
we use the "image" type,
and then specify
our related image reference prim.
The image reference prim
contains a reference to the image,
which can be a JPG or a PNG,
as outlined in the USDZ specification,
and then define its physical width.
This property is defined in centimeters
to avoid unit changes due to composition
or edits made by a DCC
that hasn't yet adopted the schema.
Next, let's take a look at behaviors.
Behaviors in Reality Composer allow you
to easily bring your 3D content to life.
A behavior in Reality Composer
contains a single trigger
that can target multiple objects,
such as a tap, collision,
or proximity event,
and can contain one or more actions
targeting multiple objects,
such as Emphasize, Play Audio,
and Add Force.
Here, we have an example of a tap trigger
with a bounce action.
The behavior schema follows
this same structure,
but also pulls back the curtain
and allows for more complex nesting
and composition of triggers and actions.
The schema defines
only three new prim types:
a behavior, a trigger, and an action.
Specific triggers and actions are defined
with data schemas
similar to UsdPreviewSurface,
which allows the behavior schema
to be much more flexible
beyond the initial triggers and actions
we've added support for this year.
Let's add a behavior to our scene.
Here, we've defined a single behavior
defining a tap trigger and a bounce action
as seen in the video
in the previous slide.
The behavior contains an array
of trigger relationships
and another array of action relationships.
Nested in the behavior,
we've defined a trigger,
which is our tap trigger.
The trigger defines itself
as a tap trigger
using the "info:id" property...
and the objects that are observed
for tap events
which invoke this trigger.
In this case, our tap trigger targets
our cube prim from the previous examples.
We also have a nested action
and have related our behaviors trigger
and action properties
to their object paths.
The action defines itself
as a bounce action
using the info:id property
and motionType properties.
The motionType property is defined
as a property in the emphasize actions
in the behavior's data schema,
and the bounce action's target is defined
with the affectedObjects property,
which, again, is our cube.
Together with the trigger,
we've defined a behavior
that bounces the cube when it is tapped.
In the previous example,
we only had one trigger and one action
for this behavior,
but multiple triggers and multiple actions
can be related to these properties.
When multiple triggers are defined,
the satisfaction of any of them
will invoke the related actions.
When multiple actions are defined,
they each run serially,
one after the other.
We have also encoded the concept of
group actions in our action data schema,
which allows for serial
or parallel execution of related actions.
Also, behaviors are automatically loaded
as part of the scene.
If behaviors are defined
in a multi-scene USD,
they will be scoped to the scene
in which they're defined.
In this example, we have three behaviors
which are all loaded
as part of the "My Cube Scene."
Next, let's take a look at physics.
Physics in Reality Composer
helps make your AR content
feel at home in the real world.
In Reality Composer, you can define
the physical properties of an object,
such as its physics material,
like rubber, plastic or wood,
its collision shape,
such as a box or a sphere,
and motion type,
as well as scene-level physical properties
like the ground plane material
and gravity.
The physics schema allows you
to set up a physics rigid body simulation.
It does this with schemas
for the physics material,
colliders, rigid bodies and forces,
specifically gravity.
Here we have a wooden ball
that we want to make participate
in the physics simulation
as a dynamic object.
To achieve that,
we're applying the collider API
and the rigid body API to our prim.
We're using the prim's own geometry
in this case
to define its convex collider shape.
This property comes from the collider API.
We're then giving our wooden ball
a mass of ten kilograms.
This property uses kilograms to avoid
unintended scaling due to composition,
similar to the anchoring API.
Next, we can apply a wood physics material
to our wooden ball.
Here we're defining a wooden material.
The physics material schema
is an applied schema,
so we first apply it
to our wood material prim.
We've opted for an applied schema
so that these properties can be applied
to an existing material in the scene
without having to create a brand-new prim
and then define various properties
about the material,
such as its restitution and its friction.
We can then apply the material
to our wooden sphere.
Next, let's make sure
our content doesn't fall into infinity
by adding a ground plane collider
to our scene.
We can do this
by specifying an infinite collider plane
and then marking it
as the scene ground plane.
For maximum compatibility,
we're putting this into
the custom data dictionary for the prim
so that older versions of USD
that do not have this registered
can still open the file.
We can then specify the plane's position
and normal...
and we can also apply a material
to our plane.
In this case, let's reuse
our wood material from earlier.
Let's take a look at the scene
we've just created.
Finally,
let's define the gravity in our scene.
For fun,
let's put our wooden ball on the moon.
We can do this simply
by creating a prim in our scene
with a gravitational force type.
We recommend that there
only be one gravitational force per scene.
We can define the gravitational force
in stage units per second using a vector.
Together we have a scene
that looks like this.
Next, let's take a look at audio.
[whinnies]
Audio in Reality Composer is driven
by behaviors,
specifically the Play Audio action.
This allows audio to be played
at the start of a scene
or after a supported event,
such as the tap of an object.
The audio schema, which is distinct
from the behavior schema,
allows for the embedding of audio content
in a USD.
Audio specified in this way
will be played back
alongside the stage's animation track
and can be configured
with various playback options,
such as aural mode,
playback offset and volume.
When a USD containing the audio schema
is brought into Reality Composer,
its audio will play
alongside the USD's animation.
This can be invoked
with the "USDZ Animation" action,
which now supports audio controls as well.
If you're working with an editor
that doesn't yet support
the spatial audio schema,
you can use the USDZ Python tool,
available on the Developer website,
to add it to your USD.
Let's take a look at the audio schema
in the USD.
Here we have a model
that specifies audio to be played back
alongside the animation in a USD.
First, we're defining a brand-new
prim type named "SpatialAudio."
We specify the audio file itself
using the filePath property.
We can also specify the auralMode,
which is how the audio
will be played back.
Spatial audio will emit audio
from a specific transform,
and non-spatial audio will play the audio
without taking transform into account.
In addition, you can set the start time
and media offset of your content,
which will begin your audio clip
at a specific point
and after a specific time respectively.
Since the spatial audio prim inherits
from the xformable prim schema,
it can be placed in space.
By default, it will inherit
the transform of its parent.
However,
we can set our own local transform
to offset our audio
to play it from a specific location.
In this case, we want to play
our horse neigh from the horse's mouth.
Next, let's take a look at 3D text.
3D text in Reality Composer allows for the
addition of readable content in the scene.
Text can be configured
with a variety system fonts and weights
and additional options
such as alignment, depth,
bounding volume, wrap mode, and more.
The 3D text schema defines
all of these properties an IsA schema.
Let's take a look at the text schema
in a USD.
Here we're defining 3D text
with a content "#WWDC"...
with the font Helvetica
and a fallback font of Arial.
If we chose a different main font,
our system will use that if it has it.
We can also define additional properties,
such as the wrap mode and alignments.
Finally, let's take a look
at the new metadata options.
These options allow
for the specification of a playback mode,
whether the animation
and audio automatically plays
or is paused upon load,
and scene understanding metadata
that specifies if a scene's content
interacts with the real world,
as generated
by the new scene understanding feature
in RealityKit and ARKit
on the new iPad Pro with LiDAR scanner.
This allows objects to not only fall
on content in your scene
but also interact with real-world objects
in your environment.
Let's take a look
at the new playback metadata in a USD.
Here we have a USD with an animation
and are specifying that it should loop
and not start automatically.
This is a hint to a viewer
that it should display a play button,
so the user can initiate the animation.
Auto-play is also disabled for all content
coming out of Reality Composer,
so they can be driven explicitly
by behaviors.
Next, let's take a look at the new
scene understanding metadata in USD.
Here we have a USD with some objects that
have physics properties applied to them.
In our scene, we're specifying
that all content in the scene
will interact with the environment
as generated by the scene understanding
capability in RealityKit.
As next steps, we encourage you
to check out the schemas in depth
through new documentation available
on the Developer website,
send us feedback through Feedback
Assistant or the Developer Forums,
check out Reality Converter
in the related talks,
and finally,
begin adopting the new AR USD schemas
in your content and editor applications.
So that's an overview of the new workflows
in USD-based DCC ecosystem
enabled by USD export in Reality Composer
and the new AR USD schemas.
We've seen how we can start
with content in Reality Composer,
bring it to life with interactions,
physics and anchoring,
export it, modify it in a DCC
and re-import it
into Reality Composer or a DCC,
continuing the content creation story
and creating an ecosystem
of content creation tools
that all speak the common language of USD.
We've also taken a closer look
at the new AR USD schemas,
making USDZ export
in Reality Composer possible.
With this new functionality and schemas,
we're excited to see what amazing
creations you will continue to create.
Thank you,
and enjoy the rest of your WWDC.