Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. I'm Kevin Milden,
and I'm on Apple's Device Management team.
At Apple,
our team spends our time focused
on making devices easier to manage
across our platform apps
and services that you use.
Whether you're assigning sixth-graders
activities using Schoolwork on an iPad,
setting up iPhones in your organization
for the first time,
or using Apple Business Manager
to purchase apps and books
for your organization,
it's Apple's hardware,
software and services
that are at the center of your deployment.
And this year,
we've made some significant strides
in bringing numerous crucial
device-management features to the Mac.
Today, we're gonna start by reviewing
how you can deploy, manage and secure
macOS Big Sur.
Setting up and deploying Macs
has never been easier.
With essential services from Apple,
your organization can quickly deploy
and support Macs at scale.
Our vision of enrollment
requires nothing more than unboxing a Mac
and booting it up.
And we're delivering on that promise
with Automated Device Enrollment.
All the user needs to do is select
their language and connect to Wi-Fi.
It automatically enrolls
organization-owned devices into MDM,
so you don't have to touch them
before you hand them out.
Enrollment Customization allows you
to add branding, consent text,
and use modern authentication
during the setup process.
It provides a better experience
while using new auth vendors,
such as Microsoft Azure Active Directory,
Okta, Ping, and more.
Using the credentials
from your identity provider
in Enrollment Customization,
you can pre-populate the user's full name
and short name.
We are also introducing
the ability to choose
if the account can enable
user-channel management too.
After creating a user account,
you can customize the setup process
to meet your organization's needs.
Choose which steps to hide and show,
such as Siri, Touch ID, FileVault,
Analytics, Location, and more.
With Automated Device Enrollment,
there's no step three.
You land at the desktop.
Automated Device Enrollment enables you
to automate MDM enrollment
and simplify device setup.
You can supervise devices
during activation without touching them,
as well as lock MDM enrollment
for ongoing management.
A few years ago,
we introduced a new feature
that makes it easy
to set up Apple TVs at scale.
It's been very successful
and we're bringing it to the Mac.
All that you do is plug in power
and connect Ethernet.
And then boot it up...
and all of the setup screens
are automatically skipped.
You land right at log-in.
It's the fastest way to set up a Mac,
and we think you're gonna love it.
Auto Advance
for Automated Device Enrollment
makes it easy to set up a Mac.
It requires you to manage your devices
using Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager.
Only power and Ethernet are required,
but your network must support DHCP.
Skip all the Setup Assistant steps
and reach log-in within seconds,
or customize the setup to meet your needs.
And if you use encrypted disks,
you will be required
to enter your password.
Now, I've got one more
deployment feature for the Mac
that I really want to tell you about.
And yes, it's for the new Mac Pro.
It's called Lights Out Management,
and will enable admins
to deploy Mac Pros at scale.
You can start up, shut down, and reboot
one or more Macs remotely
even if they're unresponsive.
This is accomplished
by sending a command from your MDM server
to the MDM-enrolled controller
on your Mac network.
Lights Out Management
requires macOS Big Sur,
and your Mac Pros must
be on the same subnet.
And you're going to want to install
the Lights Out Management payload too.
Here's how it works.
You'll need to enroll a Mac
to act as the controller
on your local network.
And you'll need all the Mac Pros
to enroll as well.
Then connect all the Mac Pros
to the enrolled LOM controller Mac.
Send the command to your MDM server.
Your MDM vendor will need to support
the new Mac commands
in order for this to work.
The LOM controller Mac
receives the command
and distributes them
to each of the Mac Pros.
Lights Out Management for the new Mac Pro
is an awesome new feature,
and we hope
that you'll take advantage of it.
These terrific new enhancements
to deployment
will help you set up Macs at scale
faster than ever before.
But once you have your Macs deployed,
what about ongoing management?
Let's start with Supervision.
Supervision gives admins greater control
of how devices operate.
We're making a change this year
that you've been waiting for.
Previously, User Approved MDM
didn't have the same capabilities
as Automated Device Enrolled Macs.
Not anymore.
Any Mac enrolled in a User Approved MDM
will now be considered supervised.
Admins have the same special abilities
such as controlling activation lock
and leveraging bootstrap tokens,
just as they do if the device was enrolled
using Automated Device Enrollment.
You can query and list local users
and choose to delete them,
as well as replace or remove profiles
and install supervised restrictions,
using MDM commands, and...
schedule software updates.
We've learned a lot from
Managed Software Updates on iOS and iPadOS
and we want to bring that same experience
to the Mac.
There's a number of new MDM commands
for Software Update,
including forcing client Macs to accept
software updates and then restart.
Major releases of macOS and non-OS updates
can now be deferred up to 90 days.
And we've made a few changes
to increase security,
such as the removal
of the software update catalog,
as well as the Ignore Flag
for major updates only.
Now, that's the story
for Managed Software Updates,
but what about apps?
Managed apps have been a terrific feature
on iOS for many years,
and we wanna bring it to the Mac too.
You can now remove apps
using MDM commands,
or they can be removed
on device un-enrollment.
Managed app configuration
and feedback are supported,
just as they are on iOS and iPadOS.
And if eligible, you can convert
unmanaged apps to managed using MDM.
User enrolled devices
that have managed apps installed
do not support conversion.
Apps have always been the cornerstone
of the macOS experience,
but as cool as they are,
large apps can include
additional components
that need to be downloaded
to each of your clients.
Doing that can slow things down
and use up valuable time.
Which is why we hope you're using
content caching to reduce Internet usage,
while speeding up the rate
of downloading of apps,
books, iCloud content, GarageBand music,
software updates,
Xcode components and so much more.
There are over two dozen data types
supported by content caching.
We've added support for Internet Recovery.
The initial boot image isn't included,
but the full six-gigabyte recovery image
is cached,
which will restore Macs on your network
faster than ever.
When we integrated content caching
into macOS a few years ago,
we included a new tab in Activity Monitor
that displays key performance metrics
to help you understand
how your content is being used.
We're now making those metrics
available to you
using the new
"Content Caching Information" MDM command.
They help you determine if content caching
is turned on, working,
and helping your clients
download content faster.
It gives you the information
about registration state,
cache pressure, bytes served
and so much more.
As a developer,
please resist the urge to set this command
repeatedly at high frequency,
as it really wasn't intended to be used
like it is in Activity Monitor.
There's a bunch of great new features
for content caching,
and we hope that you'll
take advantage of them
to speed up downloading of content
to the devices on your network.
Now, just as we have
with deployment and management,
we're also bringing a number of
security improvements from iOS to the Mac.
At Apple,
we strive to strike the right balance
between improving security
and preserving
effortless deployment workflows.
Today, we are introducing more things
you can do with bootstrap tokens.
A bootstrap token
is a reserved encryption key
provided by your MDM server that
enables macOS to create admin accounts
without needing to authenticate
with an admin password.
Historically, admins would need to create
complicated workflows
to create accounts on the system
and then add individual user accounts.
Not anymore.
Bootstrap tokens enable users
to get a secure token
and boot a Mac that uses FileVault.
This is a really useful feature
if you used networked accounts.
Bootstrap tokens improve
the log-in workflow for mobile accounts.
Once implemented,
admins can take advantage
of authorized software updates
and kernel extensions.
Bootstrap tokens are supported
on the latest Macs
with the Apple T2 Security Chip.
Please review developer documentation
to learn more about
bootstrap tokens in your deployment.
Now let's talk about how
we took measures to protect users.
You might be asked to install a profile
that was sent to you in an e-mail,
or one that was downloaded in a web page.
Since profiles can configure your device,
we need to make sure that
we don't install them accidentally
from people that you don't trust.
In iOS and iPadOS,
we introduced Downloaded Profiles.
This is where we isolate a profile
that's been downloaded.
We have you install it manually
by paying a visit to Settings.
It's designed to help protect customers.
We're bringing Downloaded Profiles
to the Mac
to offer the same security benefits.
When you download a profile,
you'll receive a notification
that you can review it in Settings.
Visit System Profiles pane
and you'll see a new group
labeled "Downloaded Profiles".
Here you can preview the profile
and click "Install."
Confirm that you actually
want to install it,
and enter your password
to complete the installation.
Profiles can modify the way
your device is configured,
and we want users to take
an informed decision when installing them.
As an MDM developer, you're going to want
to consider the challenges
that Downloaded Profiles poses
to your deployment workflows.
Once a profile is downloaded,
it remains in the System Preferences
for eight minutes
before it is removed
from the System Preferences pane.
As we informed you previously,
we've continued to make
security enhancements
that impact several command line tools
that you may be using
in your deployment workflows.
As of macOS Big Sur,
you will no longer be able to completely
install profiles using Terminal.
When you attempt to install a profile
via the command line,
it will treat it as if it was downloaded,
and you'll have to complete the install
in the Profiles System Preferences pane
manually.
All other features of
the profiles command line tool
will remain the same
and continue to work as expected.
In addition to changes
to the profiles command line tool,
macOS Big Sur also includes a tool
called networksetup
that makes it easy to view and edit
your network settings using Terminal.
The problem is that admins
and standard users
had the same abilities
to view and modify network settings
from the command line.
We've now imbued these account types
with different abilities
when using the networksetup tool.
We've also hardened security
by honoring the setting
that requires your admin password
when modifying system-wide preferences.
Here's some detail around
networksetup tool.
Admins and standard users now have
different capabilities.
Standard users can only
read network settings,
turn on and off Wi-Fi,
and change the access point.
They no longer have the same
unbridled capabilities that admins do.
Tick the checkbox to require your password
when modifying settings
in Security and Privacy,
but admins can
get around this by using sudo.
There's one more significant
security enhancement
that you should be aware of.
Automated Device Enrollment
uses device serial numbers
to know which devices
to enroll at activation.
Serial numbers contain
bits of identifiable information,
like where and when the device was built.
These 12-character numbers
help Apple target devices made
at the same time in the same place
to maintain quality.
To address identifiable information
being used maliciously,
we're going to start issuing
completely random
10-character serial numbers
across our product line.
As an MDM vendor, you depend
on Automated Device Enrollment
and serial numbers to identify devices.
You'll need to take
the new serial number format change
into account within your products.
Third-party solutions must be capable
of handling both the current
product serial number formats
and the newly updated format
at the same time.
There are a number of
other new device management features,
restrictions and commands
that MDM vendors can now
take advantage of in macOS Big Sur.
Please consult
our updated configuration profile
and MDM protocol reference documentation
at developer.apple.com to learn more.
It's a big year for the Mac,
but the latest release of iOS and iPadOS
have tons of great device-management
features included this year too.
From Shared iPad for Business
and Temporary Session
to Shortcuts now supporting
Managed Open-In,
iOS and iPadOS
have a ton to offer administrators.
Just like with Mac,
we're going to focus on how admins
can deploy, manage,
and secure iOS and iPadOS too.
Let's start with deployment.
And when time is of the essence,
Apple Configurator
helps you mass-configure iPhones, iPads
and Apple TVs fast using a USB cable.
Apple Configurator now supports
Apps and Books Locations
that are provided by Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager.
Locations are different places
where devices are kept.
For example, an institution may use
a completely different set
of apps and books
at an elementary school
than they do at a high school.
With this new feature,
admins can now go to the Account menu
and select the Location
they'd like to use.
That displays an entirely different set
of apps and books for each Location
that has been configured in
Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
This is a critical feature
for our customers
and we're excited to introduce it.
In addition to Locations,
cfgutil is now more scalable
and can restore larger numbers of devices
than ever before.
And if you didn't notice,
Apple Configurator sports a brand-new look
in macOS Big Sur.
Now let's turn to a few more additions
in iOS deployment.
Automated Device Enrollment enables you
to customize the Setup Assistant
to simplify MDM enrollment
and device setup.
It enables you to get to the Home Screen
without needing to use
the Setup Assistant.
And we're adding new skip keys
for the new Getting Started
and Update Completed panes in iOS 14.
We've now brought
the Setup Assistant payload to iOS,
although it works a little differently
than on macOS.
Using the payload,
you specify the same skip keys
you use with Automated Device Enrollment,
and then they will take effect
during future upgrades.
The payload offers two benefits.
First, it allows you to skip
Setup Assistant panes during an upgrade
that you didn't know about
when initially setting up the device.
And second,
skipping the setup panes during upgrade
is now possible on all supervised devices,
not just those enrolled using
Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager.
I would now like to discuss
one of my favorite
device-management features:
Shared iPad.
It allows students to have
a personal experience on a shared device.
Shared iPad gives schools the ability
to provide each and every student
with a personalized experience,
and their own data
even if the students are sharing iPads.
Earlier this year,
we added some great new features
to expand the ways
in which Shared iPad can be used
in different types of organizations,
not only schools.
Shared iPad for Business can be configured
using Apple Business Manager,
just as you do to configure it
for students in Apple School Manager.
Employees can sign in to a shared iPad
using their Managed Apple ID.
This is a great feature for
service businesses such as restaurants,
where you can deploy shared devices
to take orders from customers.
If you use
Microsoft Azure Active Directory,
your users can now sign in
using federated authentication.
And Shared iPad now supports
the new Single Sign-on Extension too.
But wait, there's more.
Shared iPad now supports
dynamic numbers of cached users,
which allows you
to set the amount of storage
for each user,
instead of a fixed number of users.
You can also now delete all users
from a shared iPad at once,
and we have added queries
for estimated resident users
and quota size.
And a highly requested feature
called Temporary Session.
A Temporary Session further expands
the way a shared iPad
can be used in different organizations
by allowing a user
to sign in temporarily
without needing an account.
When you sign out,
all the data the user created
during the session will be deleted.
It's a quick and easy way
for people to start using a shared iPad
without a Managed Apple ID.
Those are all the new deployment features
we've introduced in iOS and iPadOS 14.
Now let's review what we're going to do
to make managing iPhones
and iPads even better.
First up is non-removable managed Apps,
a great new feature that admins
will be excited about.
Previously, admins could completely lock
the Home Screen
and prevent the deletion of all apps,
which constrained the user's ability
to manage their own apps.
Now users can continue to rearrange
their apps and install new apps,
and delete other apps
that they've installed.
And admins can mark
only mission-critical managed apps
as non-removable.
When your users try to delete
or off-load a managed app,
it prevents it and displays an alert.
Non-removable managed apps
ensures that your users
always have the apps they need
on their devices.
You can now mark specific managed apps
as non-removable,
which will prevent the user
from removing or off-loading them.
Just like organizations want to be able
to have some control
over their apps
on their employees' devices,
they also want to keep a tight control
over their proprietary data.
And this year, we've added several
new ways to maintain that control.
Let's start with a great new
iOS productivity feature, Shortcuts.
Shortcuts deliver a quick way
you can get things done
with your apps,
or with just a tap by asking Siri.
By Shortcuts supporting Managed Open-In,
when a shortcut triggers an action
where data flow is not allowed
because of the device policy...
the shortcut will immediately
stop running.
We do this by controlling the flow of data
to make sure that managed data
does not get shared
with unmanaged apps and services,
and vice versa.
This makes certain
that your organization's data
does not fall into the wrong hands.
Building on preventing sensitive data
from being shared,
let's turn to notifications.
Organizations want to ensure
that sensitive information
cannot be revealed without user intent,
so we've added a setting
to control notification previews to help.
It's a new key
in the Notification Settings payload
called "Preview Type,"
which controls when previews
are shown in notifications:
never, always, or only after the user
has unlocked their device.
The new key is only respected
on supervised devices,
and will help your organization
keep your data private and secure.
Now, I have just one more
management feature
I would like to share with you
before we move on
to our security features.
Managing remote devices around the world
is something that
we are all becoming more familiar with.
Let's say you have employees
that are located across multiple countries
and some of them don't use Location.
It really doesn't make a lot of sense
for their devices to be configured
to use the time zone
of your MDM server by default.
Time management of endpoints
is a critical function of key services.
If set incorrectly,
it could cause serious problems,
such as authentication issues.
So, we're introducing
the new Set Timezone MDM command
that allows you to choose the time zone
for each device.
And it's not dependent
on Location Services whatsoever.
Make sure you review
developer documentation to learn more
about how you can take advantage
of this new command.
And those are just some
of the new management features
we are bringing to iOS
and iPadOS 14 this year.
But what can we do to continue to improve
the security of your devices?
In this section, we will cover
some changes coming this year
that will impact deployment workflows,
as well as
some new management capabilities
you can use to secure iPhones and iPads
in your organization.
VPN, or virtual private networks
let people send and receive data
across public networks.
There are three types
of VPN that iOS supports:
full tunnel,
which all traffic can flow through,
split tunnel, which chooses
which traffic can flow through it,
and we've added support for per-app VPN,
which only lets certain apps' data
flow through it.
Today, we're going to add support
for you to choose
which VPN your accounts should use.
This is called Per Account VPN for iOS,
and it allows you
to choose a replacement VPN
for Contacts, Calendars and Mail domains.
You can associate
an individual account with VPN,
just like you can the traffic of an app.
Developers only need
to replace the keys in the domain payload
to take advantage of this new feature.
Since we're on the topic
of encrypted traffic,
you can now encrypt your DNS too.
Most of our traffic is encrypted
when we talk to a server,
but when we talk to a DNS server,
those connections aren't secure.
So, in addition to Per Account VPN,
we're also introducing
encrypted DNS settings.
Encrypted DNS
allows you to enhance security
without needing to configure a VPN.
iOS already supports
the standard for secure DNS,
now we're providing the ability
to manage it via MDM as well.
Let's talk about
just one more new security feature
we've included this year.
Beginning in iOS 14, whenever a device
associates with a Wi-Fi network
it will use a random MAC address
instead of the device's
true hardware MAC address.
For enterprise networks
that use captive portals or filtering,
the new feature may cause
an unexpected behavior,
as the device
may not be identified when it joins.
If the device fails to join the network,
it will fall back
to using its real MAC address.
While users can disable
this feature in Settings,
we've also made it possible
to disable it using the Wi-Fi payload.
As there were for macOS Big Sur,
there are a number of other new
device-management features,
restrictions and commands
that MDM vendors can now take advantage of
in iOS, iPadOS and tvOS.
Please consult
our updated configuration profile
and MDM protocol reference documentation
at developer.apple.com to learn more.
Thanks for joining me to learn what's new
in managing Apple's devices at WWDC 2020.
We hope you'll take advantage
of the great new features
across our platforms this year.
Thanks.