Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome. I'm Eric Dudiak,
an engineer on the UIKit team.
And I'll be joined by David Duncan.
We're going to be talking about
some great new features of UIKit
with a focus
on standard controls and menus.
So, let's get started.
Here's a quick overview
of what we're going to be covering
in this session.
We'll take a brief look at some of
the recent changes in control appearances.
After that, we'll go over
the new color picker and how to use it.
Then we'll take a look
at the updated date picker.
We'll also look at how menus have changed
and added more options.
Finally, we'll go over improvements
around UIActions
that can significantly simplify your code.
So let's get started with the appearance
updates to some common controls,
and these apply across iOS and iPadOS,
in both UIKit
and their SwiftUI counterparts.
UISlider and UIProgressView
have both received minor updates
to make them more consistent
across all of the platforms.
First, you'll notice the thickness
of the track has been increased,
bringing the appearance
more in line with macOS.
Along with the appearance changes,
UISlider now adopts the macOS behavior
of being able to tap or click on the track
to adjust the value.
Here we see the matching visual change
on UIProgressView.
When using these and other UIKit controls
in an optimized Catalyst app,
they will further adopt
the macOS appearance.
This further adoption will limit some of
the customization APIs of these controls,
and they will have no effect.
For more information
about the considerations
when making an optimized Catalyst app,
check out the "Optimize the Interface
of your Mac Catalyst App" session.
The next control
to receive an appearance update
is UIActivityIndicatorView.
The new design features fewer petals
and is consistent across all sizes,
along with some timing adjustments
on the animation.
Now, it is important to always use
the built-in UIActivityIndicatorView
when showing indeterminate progress.
This ensures consistency.
Now, to ensure it works
in all possible scenarios,
use the modern styles
that adjust for Dark Mode
and optionally allow
setting a custom color via the API.
Similar appearance changes have also
been made in the pull-to-refresh control.
And here we see the optimized
Mac Catalyst version of these
and a few other standard controls.
Notice that they match the appearance
of standard Mac controls.
UIPickerView has also received an update
in its appearance.
It should be noted, however, that menus
may be an appropriate replacement
in many contexts.
We'll discuss them a little bit later
in this session.
On Catalyst apps on macOS,
menus are almost always the best choice
when you're presenting a selection
from a number of choices.
The last control we'll go over
is UIPageControl.
Now, it has received both
appearance changes
and some functional changes.
The new appearance allows the page control
to support an unlimited number of pages
within a fixed size.
Now when the number of pages
exceed the space available,
the control allows for the scrubbing
and scrolling of those pages,
making the control more ideal
for scenarios
where user customization
may dictate the number of pages,
such as on the Home Screen.
Additionally, the page control features
new API to customize its appearance.
The indicators themselves
can now be set to custom images
either for individual pages
or all of the pages.
This can be useful if a certain page
has a special function,
such as the first page
in the Weather app shown here,
which shows the current location icon
for the weather.
The presentation and interaction
of the control can also be customized,
such as setting the control to display
in a more prominent mode
when it is the main control
of an interface.
So, let's take a look at
how we use these customizations.
Here we go ahead
and create our pageControl.
We can then set the backgroundStyle
to prominent,
so that it'll stand out better
in the context of our app.
This will make the background area
always show,
instead of just
when we're interacting with it.
We can also set the default image
for all the indicators
if we don't want the normal circles.
In this case, setting the bookmark image
for a case where we are browsing
pages of bookmarks.
We can also further customize
individual pages.
Here we're doing that
with the heart image on the first page
to indicate that it is for favorites.
All of the other API surface
of the pageControl
remains completely unchanged.
Next up, let's take a look
at the new color picker in iOS 14.
For those already familiar
with the macOS color panel,
the new color picker in iPadOS and iOS 14
will feel very similar.
The color picker is a view controller
that can be easily presented
as a sheet or popover
from your application.
In addition to typical delegate callbacks,
it has a color property that can be set
and read to configure it.
Once presented,
it allows selecting a color
through a number of different methods,
such as picking from a grid...
selecting a color from
the entire spectrum gradient
or manually specifying an exact color
with red, green and blue components.
Or even a hexadecimal code.
Frequently used colors
can also be favorited
and reused across applications.
So Pro Apps can allow users
to easily select something important,
like a brand color, in one context,
and use it in many.
Finally, just like the macOS panel,
the color picker supports grabbing colors
from anywhere on the screen
using an eyedropper tool.
This is especially powerful on iPadOS
when running multiple apps.
The color can be easily selected
anywhere on the screen,
matched and then reused.
On macOS, the picker uses
the standard color picker panel,
allowing the same familiar functionality.
So, let's take a look at setting up
and using the color picker.
In this case, we have
a ColorPickerViewController property
on our existing viewController.
When the color button is pressed,
we go ahead and set the color
on the viewController
to the current color being used
and then present
the ColorPickerViewController.
If the user finishes selecting a color,
we go ahead and set it in the app.
If the user canceled selecting a color,
we can safely ignore the color.
At no point do we have to worry
about how the color was selected
or supporting the eyedropper tool.
All of that is handled automatically
by the color picker.
The date picker in iOS and iPadOS
is not a new control,
but we have made
some really big improvements
to the versatility
and user experience of it.
New in iPadOS and iOS 14,
the compact style
is available and supported.
Just like the macOS version
introduced earlier,
the compact style in iOS
shows the time and date
as fields that can be tapped
to bring up a modal selection.
This is especially useful
when space is limited in the UI,
such as in a table view
or form with several fields.
When selecting from the date side,
a modal calendar is displayed
allowing for the easy selection
of any given day.
This also allows for far more rapid
selection of distant dates
than the traditional wheel styles allowed
and is better optimized
for pointer interaction on an iPad.
When tapping on the time,
the keypad is used
for selection of the time.
As mentioned earlier, the compact style
is supported on macOS Catalina
and later in the iOS 13.4 SDK and newer.
This can help make your optimized
or unoptimized Catalyst app
better support showing a date picker
on a Mac.
When using it, the date picker control
is sized similarly to a UILabel.
Clicking on components of the date
bring up a modal calendar presentation
for selecting the date.
The date and time can also be set
by typing in values to the field.
Additionally, if only the time
or only the date are required
for a given context,
the app can limit the picker
to just that part of the field.
Additionally, iOS 14 introduces
the inline style for the date picker.
This is particularly useful
in circumstances where selecting a date
is the primary function of a UI
and the addition of the modal step
is simply unnecessary.
This can be useful on iPad apps
migrating from the wheel style
where more screen space
is readily available.
The presentation itself matches that
of the modal one
presented from the compact style,
just filling the contents of the control
rather than being presented from it.
The great part about all three new styles
is that all the API of UIDatePicker
remains exactly the same.
So the new styles can be easily adopted
or even adjusted,
depending on the context,
with only the layout of the app
being affected.
So now let's take a look
at using these new styles.
Here we see creating a date picker
and setting the initial date
has not changed at all on iOS 14.
We can also set minimum and maximum dates
for the selection.
All we have to do to use one of the
new styles is just set a preferred one.
And here we'll set that to
the compact style.
We can also customize the locale and
calendar of the date picker if necessary.
And the new styles will show
the appropriate content.
In this case,
we'll show the Japanese calendar.
And we can see how the era is now
displayed where the year was previously.
We can also limit the selection
to just the date
if the time isn't relevant
to this context.
The date picker is still just a UIControl.
So it's easy to be notified
when the value has changed
and then read in the new date.
The new date picker styles provide
an improved experience
when selecting dates in an application
without the application having to handle
many of the inherent complexities
of different calendars or interactions
across platforms.
Now I'd like to hand it over
to my colleague, David Duncan.
Thanks, Eric.
I'm David Duncan,
and I'm going to talk about enhancements
to menus and UIAction.
Let's start with how iOS 14 brings quick,
lightweight interactions with menus
to more parts of your UI.
Any app in iOS 14 can easily add menus
to UIButtons and UIBarButtonItems.
This example shows how Safari uses menus
to put more power at your fingertips.
Let's dive into this interaction.
Tapping on the tab switch button
performs the default action,
showing the Safari tab switcher.
On iOS 14, long pressing on this button
presents a menu with more options.
Immediately, you can slide your finger
to select an item and lift to activate.
Let's see how to add a menu like this
to your app.
UIButton and UIBarButtonItem
directly support menus,
and adding one couldn't be easier.
Just assign a menu to the menu property
of either class,
and UIKit will take care of displaying
that menu on long press.
But in some cases, you don't want to wait.
Let's take a look at that interaction.
Reminders uses a More button
to group several actions together.
Unlike our Safari example,
the menu presents immediately
when you touch the button.
Just like before,
the user can then slide their finger
and quickly select an action
in one smooth gesture.
How you select this interaction differs
between UIButton and UIBarButtonItem.
For UIButton,
setting showsMenuAsPrimaryAction to true
causes the button to present its menu
immediately on touch down.
For UIBarButtonItem, providing a menu
but not setting a primary action
indicates the menu should present
on touch down.
On iOS 14, you'll also see menus
automatically provided
by the navigation Bar Back button.
This menu creates a standard accelerator
for jumping back in the nav stack
in any application.
Menu titles are automatically chosen
considering customized back buttons
where appropriate.
If you use a custom title view
but don't set a title
of a navigation item,
consider setting backButtonTitle
to ensure a good experience.
The new menu support you've seen so far
is provided by UIControl.
You've already seen
showsMenuAsPrimaryAction
which determines if the menu triggers
on long press or touch down.
UIControl provides access
to its contextMenuInteraction
and a property to enable that interaction.
To support custom menu-based UIs,
you can subclass UIControl
and override its implementation
of ContextMenuInteractionDelegate.
To take action when the menu gesture
has been recognized,
you can register for
the menuActionTriggered control event.
Now let's take a look
at powerful new features in menus
to complement the new places
where you can use them.
UIDeferredMenuElement adds the ability
to asynchronously provide menu items.
As our example shows,
UIKit presents a standard loading UI
while waiting for the final menu items
to be provided.
Once provided, these items are cached
should the menu be displayed again.
UIDeferredMenuElement is also useful
for generating complex menus,
as the items won't be requested
until they need to be displayed.
Next, let's focus on two new features
of UIContextMenuInteraction.
UpdateVisibleMenu allows you to update
the menu currently presented to the user.
You receive a copy of that menu,
and you return a menu
to present in its place.
To make this API super easy to use,
UIMenu has changed behavior to no longer
force its children to be immutable,
allowing you to update and return
the menu passed to your block
instead of creating a new one.
UIContextMenuInteraction now provides
a query for the interaction's appearance.
This property may return rich
when displaying a preview,
compact for menu-only interactions
or none.
While controls always use
the compact appearance,
your own interactions may display rich
or compact based on how they're triggered.
That's some of the new capabilities
in iOS 14 to bring menus to more places.
Next, let's see how improvements
to UIAction can make it easier than ever
to act on user input.
In iOS 13, UIKit introduced UIAction to
make sharing event handling code easier.
For a refresher,
see "Modernize your UI for iOS 13"
from WWDC 2019.
iOS 14 expands where and how
you can use UIAction in your app.
UIBarButtonItem adds new initializers
to create items with actions and menus.
They make it easy to create BarButtonItems
that react to taps, present menus or both.
And nearly every parameter is optional,
so you only need to specify
those that you need.
Let's take a look.
Here we configure the toolbar items
of our viewController
using new API in iOS 14.
First, we create a system item
that triggers an action when tapped
and a menu when long pressed.
Next, we add a fixedSpace,
using the new fixedSpacewidth API.
Then we add a custom item,
configured to display an image
and present a menu on touch down.
Now, a flexibleSpace, also using new API.
And finally, an item that will use
the primaryAction's title or image
and trigger the handler on tap.
Like BarButtonItems, all controls
can be constructed with a UIAction,
but two controls,
UIButton and UISegmentedControl,
have additional behavior.
UIButton adds a new initializer accepting
the button type alongside a UIAction.
The type defaults to system,
and the primary action's title and image
are used to configure the button
when appropriate.
Like other controls created
with a primaryAction,
that action is registered to handle
the primaryActionTriggered control event
causing the action handler to be called
when the button is tapped.
Before we look at Segmented Control's
support for UIAction,
let's see how you might configure one
prior to iOS 14.
First, create the control
with an array of strings.
Next, add a handler to call a method,
located elsewhere in your code.
That method then has to switch over
the selected segment
assuming a mapping that may change.
And when the mapping does change,
the compiler can't help you
catch the problem.
iOS 14 makes this much easier.
With UIAction, creating segmented controls
looks like this.
Create the control with an array
of UIActions,
each defining the title or image
for one segment.
But unlike before,
we don't need to add an event handler.
UIKit automatically calls
the action's handler
when that segment is selected
and only that segment.
No more need for a switch statement.
No more default case
to try to catch problems.
The handler is right there
next to control creation.
And the compiler can help us keep
configuration and response
to user input in sync.
Here we use an enum
to generate our actions.
Which means we can just add
a new enum case,
and our segmented control's behavior
updates automatically.
And you can still combine this
with control event handling
for the best of both worlds.
UISegmentedControl's adoption
of UIAction starts with a new initializer
and adds new methods for adding, removing,
updating and finding segments.
As we've already seen,
segments associated with a UIAction
will have that action's handler called
only when that segment is selected.
iOS 14 has a lot to offer
to enhance your application
for iPhones, iPads and Mac Catalyst.
Refresh your UI by taking advantage
of new appearances on stock controls,
new customizability on UIPageControl
and new styles for UIDatePicker.
Adopt ColorPickerController
for all your color picking needs,
making it easy for your users
to select any color they can see.
Make your application easier and faster
to use with menus,
where a quick slide of the finger
can begin any task.
Support rapid navigation through your app
by making sure back button menus
are clear and correct.
And take action on UIAction to simplify
and share code to handle user input.
I can't wait to see how you enhance
your applications.
And thank you for watching.