Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Elliot Garner,
and in this video,
I'm going to be discussing
push notifications.
Let's begin with an overview
of push notifications,
what they are and why you might use them.
Then, I will be discussing
how you can add them to your application.
Push notifications allow applications
to be engaging and interactive.
They provide you the ability to deliver
updates to your application in real time.
This allows for a more dynamic experience
when it comes to
updating your application.
So, what exactly are the advantages
to adding push notifications
to your application?
First, they do not require
your application to be in the foreground.
Push notifications are delivered
to your application
regardless of the app state
and, if necessary,
your application will be launched.
Push notifications are power-efficient
and are a great way to engage
with your customers.
There are two types of push notifications:
Alert notifications
and background notifications.
Alert notifications allow you
to deliver visible alerts
that can be interacted with
in ways that your app can customize.
Background notifications allow
your application to receive runtime
while it is not in the foreground
in order to keep your content up-to-date.
Now, let's talk about alert pushes first.
Alert pushes allow you to deliver
a visible alert
to give an update about your application.
This alert should be used
to inform about new information
that can be interacted with.
This alert does not require
your application to be running
and will be displayed
regardless of app state.
And, most importantly,
it's entirely customizable.
How the alert looks,
and its interact-ability, is up to you.
Let's look at how you would begin
setting up your application
for alert notifications.
The first thing you need to do
is register for remote notifications.
This will register the device for
Apple Push Notification system, or APNs,
and will return a device token
to your application.
This token is used to identify the device
and lets you target it for notifications.
Next, you will need to declare
your AppDelegate
a UNUserNotificationCenterDelegate.
Once you have done that,
you will assign your AppDelegate
as a delegate of the Notification Center.
This will let your application be notified
when your alert gets opened.
Once you have called
registerForRemoteNotifications,
you will receive a callback
on one of these two methods.
If you failed to get a token
for the device,
didFailToRegisterFor
RemoteNotificationsWithError
will be called with the error
describing why registration failed.
If you succeeded in getting a token,
you need to send that token
to your back end push server
so you can deliver notifications
to this device.
Let's take a look at an example of that.
The device token is delivered
to your application as a data object.
So, in order to send it to your server,
it needs to be converted into a string.
You can do that by separating the data
into its components,
converting those components
into a hexadecimal string,
and then joining them back together
into a single string.
You then append that string
to your URLQuery
to make your fully qualified endpoint.
Then, you perform a URLSession
to send that token to your server
to register it in your database.
Lastly, before the device
can receive any notifications,
you need to ask for permissions
for your application to display alerts.
Calling requestAuthorization
results in a prompt being displayed
asking if your application
can display alerts.
The result of that decision
will be passed to the completionHandler
and is set in device settings.
Any successive calls to this method
will return the status in device settings
and will not result in a prompt.
As you can see, this function is asking
for permissions to display an alert,
play a sound, and present a badge
on the application icon.
Only request authorization in response to
an action when there is context.
You are much more likely to get
permissions with this context.
Before discussing how to handle
a notification payload,
let's look at an example payload.
Let's say that you're building
an application for a restaurant
that wants to be able to alert users
whenever there is a new special.
As you can see, this alert is telling us
that the Avocado Bacon Burger
is now on sale.
Let's step through this payload
piece by piece
to make sure that it's understood.
First is the aps dictionary.
This aps dictionary tells the device
how to render the notification.
Inside of the aps dictionary
is the alert dictionary.
This tells the system what text to use
for the notification.
Inside of that
are the title and body fields.
The title field is a short string
describing the purpose
of the notification.
This needs to be short
and easy to understand.
The body field is the full descriptive
text of the alert message.
Next is the sound field.
This field is optional
and should be included
when you want the device to play a sound
when the alert is received.
If you wanna use the default sound,
simply use default like this.
However, you can also provide
custom sounds for your application.
Next is the badge field.
This is an optional field which is used
to modify the badge of your app icon.
This is an absolute value
which will be displayed on the app icon.
This value can be modified
programmatically,
so once the alert has been opened,
set this value to zero
when handling the notification.
Outside of the aps field,
you have any custom data
that you might wanna provide
alongside the notification.
Here, it's telling the application
what the special is for today,
and how much it costs.
Now that we know
what our payload looks like,
let's examine how to handle
receiving a notification.
This method is the UNUser
NotificationCenterDelegate method
that is called
whenever your notification is opened.
This method has a completionHandler
that must be called
before returning from the function.
The payload that was delivered
to the application
can be extracted from the userInfo
property of the notification's content.
Once you have the payload, parse the data
from the dictionary representation
of the JSON.
If the data isn't there as is expected,
call the completionHandler
before returning.
This lets the system know
that you have finished handling
the opening of the notification.
Once you have the data, you can perform
any updates necessary to your application.
You should be opening the part of your
application relevant to the alert.
In the example of the restaurant,
when the alert is tapped,
the item is added to the cart
and the cart is displayed.
Once you're done,
call the completionHandler
to tell the system that you finished.
And that's it.
That's all that you need to do
to set up your application
to handle and receive alert notifications.
Now that we've examined
implementing alert pushes,
let's discuss background pushes
and how you can use them
in your application.
Background pushes
are similar to alert pushes
but there are some crucial differences
that are important to remember.
Background notifications
allow your application to fetch data
from the background
upon receiving push notifications.
These should be used
to keep your application up-to-date
even if the application isn't running.
The system will launch your application
and give you necessary runtime
in order to perform
your background update.
However, there are some limitations.
The system limits applications
to so many background operations a day,
and background updates
will not be performed
if the device
is under certain constraints.
For example,
if the device is in a low battery state.
So, what do you need to do
in order to set up your application
to register for and handle
receiving background pushes?
Like with alert pushes,
you need to register your application
for remote notifications
in order to obtain a device token
for your application.
However, unlike alert pushes,
you do not need to make your application
a UNUserNotificationCenterDelegate
or assign it to
the UNUserNotificationCenter.
That's because
the UNUserNotificationCenterDelegate
is only used
when handling alert notifications.
And since background notifications
are all that's being implemented here,
it's unnecessary.
Because registerForRemoteNotifications
was called,
you still need
to handle receiving a device token,
and you still need to send that device
to your push server
for your own registration.
This is exactly the same as what needs
to be done for alert notifications.
Now, let's examine the payload
for a background notification.
As you can see,
background notification payloads
are much more simple
than alert notifications.
The only field required
for background notifications
is the content-available field
inside of the aps dictionary.
This field tells the system
that this is a background notification
and that your application should be
launched to perform your updates.
Just like alert notifications,
the outside of the aps dictionary
can be used for custom data.
Now, let's look at
how you would handle a background push.
When the device receives
any remote notification,
didReceiveRemoteNotification is called.
Use this method
to handle your background notification.
This function
also has a completionHandler.
However, unlike the completionHandler
when handling alert notifications,
this completionHandler has one parameter.
This parameter is an enum
which tells the system whether
your background update failed...
received no data...
or received new data.
This allows the system to be smart
about when to launch your application
in the future.
So, in the case
of the restaurant application,
background notifications are being used
to fetch the menu every day
in order to make sure
its content is up-to-date.
If the URL for the current version
of the menu fails to be made,
call the completionHandler
and tell it the background update failed.
Once the URL is created,
a URLSession needs to be created
in order to fetch the data
for today's menu.
If no data was received,
call the completionHandler
and tell it that the background update
finished successfully with no data.
Otherwise, now that the updated menu
has been fetched,
the application can use
that data to update its contents.
And once that has been finished,
the completionHandler can be called
to tell the system
that the background update has succeeded
and retrieved new data.
And that's all it takes
to get your application
to handle background notifications.
Now that you know
what push notifications are,
how they can be used,
and how to implement them,
it should be no problem
to add them to your application.
All that you need to do is enable
push notifications in the developer portal
and follow these steps to add
push notifications to your application.
Download the sample app.
It has all of the codes
shown in this video.
Look through it,
and use it as a jumping-off point
for adding notifications to your apps.
Once you have done these things,
you are well on your way to creating an
enriched experience for your applications.
Thank you.