Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. I'm Jiten Mehta,
and today we're gonna take a look
at some of the important things
you should be doing
on both your app and your server
to provide the best user experience.
We're gonna touch on ways
to maximize the performance
of your networking operations.
Take advantage
of rock-solid security capabilities
built into all Apple platforms.
Deliver a robust mobility experience as
devices move between different networks.
And protect your users' privacy.
A brief note as we begin.
Many of the things we're gonna talk about
involve technologies
that must be supported
both on the client device
as well as on the server
that it's talking to.
On the client, you're all set
if you're already using
the modern networking APIs
on Apple platforms,
URLSession and Network.framework,
as you'll get support
for all these technologies automatically.
Let's dive right in
starting with performance.
First step, IPv6, the newest version
of the Internet protocol,
the fundamental protocol
that supports the Internet.
Apple platforms have had
native IPv6 support for a number of years,
including support for IPv6-only networks.
Connections using IPv6 on the network
observe lower latency
and are generally more performant
than IPv4,
in part because of fewer NATs
and more modern networking equipment.
Test that your app works
on IPv6-only networks
with the NAT64 support
in Internet sharing on your Mac,
as it's an App Store
submission requirement.
The good news is that if you use
the modern networking APIs,
it should just work.
There has been a growing trend
of IPv6 usage on the Internet.
If you look at the last month
of connections made worldwide
by Apple devices,
we see that IPv6 now accounts
for 26% of all connections made.
Twenty percent of the time,
the connection could have used IPv6,
but the server didn't have it enabled.
And when IPv6 is in use,
the median connection setup
is 1.4 times faster than IPv4.
This is primarily due to reduced NAT usage
and improved routing.
Make sure your app is taking advantage
of the improvements IPv6 offers
by using URLSession
or Network.framework on the client
where you'll get the support
built right in.
We've done our part. Now it's up to you
to check the box on the server side.
So make sure
you have enabled IPv6 on your server
to ensure the best experience
for your users.
Next, URLSession provides
built-in HTTP/2 support,
which improves load performance.
It multiplexes several requests
to the same server
onto a single connection.
This saves you time by not having to wait
for the end of each response
before sending your next request.
HTTP/2 also provides performance
improvements via connection coalescing.
The system detects that different requests
can be served by the same server
and reuse an existing connection,
saving you connection setup costs.
Header compression support
allows for better bandwidth utilization
as extraneous bytes can be eliminated
on both request and response headers.
To learn more about how HTTP/2
can benefit your app,
check out "Optimizing Your App
for Today's Internet"
from WWDC 18.
If we look at the HTTP usage in Safari,
we see that 79% of requests
in the past month
are using HTTP/2,
and the median duration
of the URLSession tasks
for the requests that use HTTP/2
is 1.8 times faster
as compared to the requests
that use HTTP/1.1.
Using URLSession on the client
will negotiate HTTP/2 by default
if it is enabled on the server.
So double-check your server settings
to make sure HTTP/2 is enabled.
Next, let's talk about some advances
in securing your network transactions.
TLS 1.3 is the latest and greatest version
of TLS,
providing reduced connection setup times
by removing one round trip
from the handshake.
It provides improved security
through formal verification
and by reducing the potential
for misconfigurations.
In iOS 12 and macOS Mojave,
we provided a preview where you
could enable preliminary versions
of the TLS 1.3 standard
and test them
against your server deployments.
Now the standard has been finalized,
and TLS 1.3 has been enabled by default
since iOS 13.4
for URLSession and Network.framework.
Over the past month,
we've seen roughly 49% of all connections
use TLS 1.3
on devices running the latest iOS.
And connections that use TLS 1.3
are established 1.3 times faster
than those using TLS 1.2.
Our modern networking APIs
will negotiate TLS 1.3 by default
if it's enabled on the server.
So turn on TLS 1.3 on your server today
to take advantage of this faster
and more secure experience.
Let's take a look at how you can provide
a seamless experience
as a device transitions
between different networks.
Multipath TCP allows a single
TCP connection from your app to continue
as the device changes networks.
This prevents your app
from needing to start all over
when the connectivity is flaky
or if the user
is moving in and out of networks.
On the client,
you can opt into Multipath support
by setting
the multipathServiceType property
on your URLSessionConfiguration
or on your NWParameters object
if using Network.framework.
We have had great success
with Multipath TCP for our own services.
Last year,
we announced that in addition to Siri,
we'd also enable Multipath TCP
for Apple Music.
Since then, we've seen
a 13% reduction in Music stalls.
And in the event that a stall occurs,
there has been a 22% reduction
in the stall duration.
You can opt into Multipath protocols
easily on Apple platforms
by setting
the multipathServiceType property
on your configuration or parameters.
You need to do a little bit more work
to enable it on the server,
so visit multipath-tcp.org
to find instructions for enabling
Multipath TCP on your server deployment.
Next, my colleague Eric
is going to walk us through some
important new privacy features in iOS 14.
Thank you all.
Thanks, Jiten.
iOS 14 improves user privacy
by introducing new privacy protections
for the local network.
This helps to prevent apps
and third-party libraries, or SDKs,
from using the presence
of other devices on the network
to locate or fingerprint your users.
Built-in system services
that interact with the local network,
such as AirPrint, AirPlay and HomeKit,
don't give the app any private information
about the network.
However, directly accessing
any local network resources,
including the use of multicast
and broadcast,
now requires explicit user permission.
To help your users understand
how your app uses their local network,
you need to provide a reason string
in the Info.plist for your app.
For more information
about what to expect when testing your app
and how to make sure that you're ready
to provide
a more privacy-protecting experience,
make sure you check out "Support
Local Network Privacy in Your App."
Also new in iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur
is support
for secure domain name resolution,
including both DNS-over-TLS
and DNS-over-HTTPS.
Instead of providing
individual resolution services
for each app or browser,
this support comes to the system resolver
so that once you've configured secure DNS,
all apps on the device will benefit.
In addition to writing an app
using NetworkExtension
to deliver these system-wide settings
for encrypted DNS transports,
you can also require
encrypted resolution in your app.
See the "Enable Encrypted DNS" session
for details on how to take advantage
of these new APIs.
You can deliver system-wide settings
for encrypted resolution
by writing an app using
NetworkExtension on the client,
and ask your DNS provider
to offer a DNS-over-HTTPS option
if they don't already.
We'd also like to share a sneak peek
of some upcoming technologies
that you can start preparing for today.
Even if you've enabled encrypted DNS
to make name resolution more private,
every TLS handshake you do with a server
includes a cleartext
server name indication, or SNI,
that can be observed by a third party
on the network.
We're currently working with the IETF
to standardize methods
for encrypting even more
of the TLS handshake
so that third parties cannot snoop
on your traffic.
This, especially in combination
with encrypted DNS,
will be a major step towards ensuring
that your network communications
stay between you
and the server you're talking to.
For another sneak peek,
HTTP/3 is the next generation of HTTP,
which is built on top
of the new QUIC transport protocol.
This transport protocol
has TLS 1.3 security built right in
and provides all the same
multiplexed stream support as HTTP/2,
but with further reductions
to head-of-line blocking
so that losses of any individual request
or response
won't hold up
other potentially unrelated messages.
HTTP/3, using QUIC,
also has higher fidelity information
to provide improved congestion control
and recovery of lost packets.
It also brings built-in mobility support
such that network transitions don't cause
in-progress operations to fail.
They can instead seamlessly continue
on the new network without interruption.
HTTP/3 is still
an in-progress specification at the IETF,
where we continue to actively collaborate
to help make HTTP/3 ready
for worldwide deployment.
As an important first step
in that direction,
iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur
include an experimental preview
of HTTP/3 support for your apps
that use URLSession,
which you can enable
in developer settings.
You can also try out
the same HTTP/3 support in Safari
via experimental settings.
Similarly, for macOS Big Sur,
you can enable experimental HTTP/3 support
for apps using URLSession
by setting the CFNetworkHTTP3Override
user default,
and you can use the develop menu to enable
it under experimental features for Safari.
Please try out HTTP/3
and file bugs for any issues
you might encounter.
We're really looking forward
to your feedback.
Today we talked about how taking advantage
of IPv6, HTTP/2,
TLS 1.3, Multipath TCP and encrypted DNS
can provide performance, security,
mobility
and privacy benefits for everyone.
All of these technologies
are currently supported
by the modern networking APIs
on Apple platforms,
so make sure you're using URLSession
or Network.framework in your application.
Next,
take a look at your server deployment
to make sure everything is up to date
and these features are enabled
so you can fill in
the right-hand side of this list.
Finally,
enable experimental HTTP/3 support
and test with your server deployment
to provide feedback on the next
generation of networking protocols.
Thanks for watching.