Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Philip Simmons,
a designer here at Apple.
Thank you so much for taking the time
to tune in for my talk
on the artist's AR toolkit.
So today my talk is gonna focus on
the artist's journey
of creating compliant USDZs
for use in Reality Composer.
This will cover what file formats
you should export from your DCC,
how to bring those assets
into Reality Converter,
and make them into USDZs.
Later, we'll look at using our assets
inside Reality Composer
and setting up some complex behaviors
to create rich experiences.
Lastly we'll send all this data to device
and view our newly created AR project.
So what does all this look like?
So from a high level,
this is the journey we're gonna take.
It is a straight line from your DCC
of choice into Reality Converter,
then Reality Composer, and, lastly,
onto device for viewing and sharing.
So Reality Converter is a major step
in this process,
and we need to know a few things before
we can begin pushing data through it.
So the primary things to note are gonna be
geometry types that can be imported
and the texture types that are supported.
So for geometry, we're gonna have
FBX, OBJ, USD and GLTF.
For textures, we have PNGs and JPEGs.
So these inputs combined allow
Reality Converter to output a valid USDZ.
Since Reality Composer
only accepts USDZ files,
Apple has provided the tools necessary for
developers to generate and inspect USDZs.
So last year, Apple offered
a suite of Python-based tools
so developers could get started
making their own content.
This year, we're proud to be including
Reality Converter
as a next generation in that tooling.
So both Reality Converter
and the USDZ tools are available today
through the developer.apple website.
All right. So let's get started
generating some content.
We're going to look at a few examples
in different DCCs
and send all that data over
to Reality Converter.
So here, we're gonna begin by taking
a look at an asset inside Houdini
and exporting it out as a USD for use
in Reality Converter.
Now Houdini is known for
its powerful simulation tool set,
and in this demonstration,
I will be scratching the absolute surface
of that toolset
to show you how we can take one asset,
instance it around,
and export those instances out
as individuals in a hierarchy.
Now this is an important distinction,
because later I'm gonna show you
how to reach into that USDZ hierarchy
and apply behaviors
directly to individuals
instead of the asset as a whole.
So let's take a look at
what I've set up here.
Here I have the cloud geometry.
You can see it in the viewport
as we tumble around.
Now when we jump into the geometry node,
you can see what I've actually created.
Here I'm bringing the geometry
on the left,
and down the right-hand side
I've built a graph.
Now this graph is essentially
building a volume,
scattering particles throughout it,
and then instancing our cloud
at each one of those points.
So if we look further down the chain
what our combined result is,
I have clouds scattered
through this volume.
Now this is a live graph,
so I can jump back in
and update the scatter node
to have more or less points.
Here I'll drop the count
from ten to eight.
So, all together,
we can go ahead and start exporting.
So for export,
I'll jump over to the staging area.
Here I've set up a USD rot node.
This is being fed our instance geometry
and our particles.
Now I'm combining these in such a way
that keeps the instances in a hierarchy,
as opposed to merging it
as a solid piece of geometry.
So with my rot node set,
I can go ahead and save this to disk.
So with our newly-exported asset,
now is the perfect time to fire up
Reality Converter and get to know the app.
We will go ahead
and begin with our cloud asset
and get a feel
for how Converter's gonna work,
and then we'll loop back and gather
the other asset types for conversion.
So here we are with Converter loaded up.
In Converter,
it starts with a blank scene,
and it's asking you to drop the files.
So let's do that.
We'll navigate on disk
and find our cloud USD that we've created.
Now we can simply drag and drop this
into the viewport
and Converter will load up our asset.
And here we are.
With this asset loaded up,
now is a great time
to take a tour through the software
and get a feel for everything
it has to offer.
So first and foremost,
we're in the 3D viewport.
You can rotate, you can pan, you can zoom.
Now down the left-hand side,
we're gonna have the Models tab.
The Models tab will fill up
as you drag in more geometries.
So once we fill this in
with our other geometries later on,
you'll see how we can toggle between them.
Now this is a 3D viewport, and sometimes
you can lose where you're at.
So if you're playing around and you happen
to zoom away from where you want to be,
we've given you a framing icon
to give it back.
Now down the right-hand side is where
you're gonna do most of your work.
Now the Environments tab is the tab
where we're giving you preloaded IBLs.
That's image-based lighting.
This is the lighting environments
that make your image look how they do.
You can simply toggle between them,
and find ones that suit your needs.
Now if they're too light or too dark,
we're giving you exposure controls
down the bottom
where you can
make adjustments accordingly.
In addition, we're giving you
grid and environment views.
Grid is perfect for knowing
how large your asset is
in relation to a certain scale.
So, example,
our grid units here are set to one meter.
You can see that each checkbox
is going to be a meter large.
You can also see the environment.
This is representing what the IBL is.
So the IBL looks like this,
and in the 3D viewport,
it's gonna look like this.
If you find that distracting,
you can simply turn it off
and get back to a solid color.
The Materials tab is where you're gonna
hook up all your materials and textures.
Here you can see
we have two materials noted,
but only one of them
I actually assigned to my DCC.
Converter is giving you a default material
as a fallback nicety,
so if you download something or you build
something and forget to assign a material,
we've given you the fallback material
that will automatically assign on import.
Now I've set up a material,
so I know I'm ready to go.
We can simply add our textures
by dragging them from disk as well.
So if we navigate the disk,
we can find our base color
and drop it on our base color input.
There we have it.
We can go ahead
and fill in the rest of them.
We have a normal map,
and we also have an ambient occlusion.
And that's it. Our material is set up,
and our textures are added.
So let's go ahead
and look at our last tab.
Our Properties tab is important.
This is where you're gonna add
your copyright information
and also set up your base units.
So for copyright information,
you want to let the world know
who made this asset.
So we'll go ahead and tell them
Apple made it.
Now base units is an important feature.
I know because this asset came
from Houdini, it was built in meters.
So I want Converter
to also export it in meters.
Later on, we'll see assets
that were constructed in centimeters,
and we'll go ahead and change it here
to be centimeters for export.
So with that all set,
we can jump back to our DCCs
and grab the rest of our assets.
So now let's take a look at
an animated asset inside Maya
and export it out as an FBX.
So here we have a taxi.
This asset has been modeled, textured
and animated inside Maya by an artist.
So we accept both transform animation
as well as skinned animation.
So this particular animation has been done
by keyframing directly on the geometry,
so no rig or skin is actually needed.
There we have it. We can hit play,
and we can see it
bumbling around the viewport.
Now let's take a moment
to talk about materials.
Here in my viewport, you can see
I have assigned a shader with textures.
We can look at the graph and see
where I've actually put that all together.
Reality Converter doesn't care about
your texture inputs here.
It cares about material names
and material assignments.
So that I've hooked up textures here
is just a nicety for me in my own DCC.
So long way of saying you don't need
to set up textures in your viewport
to get a valid build in Converter.
So with all this set
and we're happy with our asset,
we can go ahead and export
as an FBX to disk.
So on a quick technical note,
when using FBX you will need two things.
So first you're gonna need
to have the FBX plug-ins enabled
in your Maya plug-in preferences,
and second, you're gonna have to have
the FBX Python bindings
installed to your machine.
Now those bindings are available for free
on the Autodesk website, seen here.
So jumping back to our DCCs,
next we're gonna look at a static asset.
Static assets are the most common
type of asset you will encounter,
and OBJ is a very popular file format
to save static assets to.
So nearly every DCC
is going to export to OBJ.
And that's why you will often find this
as the available file type
when downloading from online sources.
So here inside Blender
we can take a look at a static asset.
This school asset is comprised of
geometry, materials, and textures.
So here in the viewport,
we can see the geometry.
Down below, we can see I have a material
hooked up with my texture inputs.
And lastly, here are the UVs
that the textures are being powered by.
So all that combined gives our final look
in the viewport.
So, happy with our asset,
we can go ahead and export this as an OBJ
and save it to disk.
GLTF is our final geometry format
that we accept.
More and more DCCs are starting
to pick it up as an export option,
and KeyShot is one such app.
So for our off-line render community,
you can now easily move your data to
a real-time format through GLTF and USDZ.
So here in KeyShot,
you can see the clock tower.
Now like the OBJ example,
this is a static asset.
So it'll have the same geometry,
materials and texture setup as before.
Here we can select the geometry
in the hierarchy
and see further down
I've assigned the material.
So this material,
I have base colors and roughness assigned.
Now if we inspect the material itself,
you can see where
I've plugged in those textures,
and all of this combined
is what's giving us our final render.
So, happy with our asset again,
we can go ahead and export this out
as a GLTF and save it to disk.
So last topic before we go back
to Reality Converter
is about downloaded content.
As you can see, using DCCs is a complex
and specialized skill set.
So for developers
that don't want to learn a DCC,
or don't want to make their own art,
online resources are available.
Some have even started offering USDZs
as a downloadable file type,
which is perfect for use
in Reality Composer,
Sketchfab being one such site.
But for those times that you find
an asset online,
and it's not offered in USDZ format,
you now have the capability
to make it one yourself.
So with our new content,
let's get back into Reality Converter
and make some USDZs.
So Converter's still up,
loaded and waiting for us.
We can go ahead and navigate on disk
and find our assets.
Now, the first time we did this,
we dragged in the geometry
and in the texture separately.
That was the long way.
I'm gonna show you a faster way
to get through this software
and get it done.
So if you select at the folder level,
you can see I've exported out our geometry
and our associated textures.
Now if we just grab things
at the folder level,
we can drag and drop that
directly into Converter,
and it'll hook it all up for us.
So let's do that.
So here we can see, we have our taxi,
our clock tower and our schoolhouse.
You can see down at the Models tab here
that we've given affordance
for animated assets.
So if you bring in an asset
that has animation,
it's gonna get
this little running man icon.
That's how you'll know at a glance
which one has animation.
So to that end, in the viewport,
we're gonna give you the ability to play,
pause and stop the animation.
So if you hit play,
it'll simply loop endlessly.
Now same as before, you can toggle through
your environment lightings
if you want to view it
in different lighting setups.
You can show the environment and grid.
That also works. Same as before.
So over to the important part,
we'll look at our properties.
Properties, like we spoke about before,
is where you add copyright information
and you set your base units.
Now this important because we exported in
centimeters from our last DCC packages.
Here in Converter,
we need to have that reflected.
So we'll go ahead
and change him to centimeters,
and we'll do the same
for the clock tower and the schoolhouse.
Perfect.
So there we go.
All our assets are in Converter,
materials are hooked up,
textures are applied,
all our units are set
and our copyrights are set.
We can go ahead and export.
Now you could export one at a time
and save it out to disk,
but there's a faster way.
We'll give you the affordance
to simply go file, export all,
and you can do it all in one big push.
So we'll find a nice place on disk
and hit export.
Now once the export is complete,
you'll get a little check mark
next to each one of the icons,
and you'll know that
that process has been done.
We can verify that by jumping to Finder,
and we can now see our assets
here on disk.
So with all our content in USDZ form,
we're now good to go
with Reality Composer.
We can simply spin up a project,
drag in our assets to be used.
So let's start.
Jumping over to Reality Composer,
we can bring up Finder and drag in
those assets that we just created.
So here's where you would know immediately
if your unit scales
were not set correctly in Converter.
Everything is sitting nicely
with each other,
and it's the right scale and proportion
to each other.
If it wasn't exported at the right scale,
some would be larger by 100X
or smaller by 100X.
Here we can visually see
that everything is working fine.
Now our schoolhouse and our clock tower
are static assets.
So all we have to verify for them
is that they look nice.
So we can go ahead and view them,
scroll around, and everything looks great.
Now for our taxi, if we remember,
this is an animated asset.
Now as we saw in Converter,
you can hit play,
or in preview you can hit space bar,
and it'll automatically animate.
In Composer,
we don't automatically animate for you.
You tell it when you want it to animate.
So let's take a look at how that works.
We zoom in to our taxi.
We'll make it a little bit larger
so we can see it.
With our taxi,
we're gonna need to use behaviors.
So let's make a new behavior.
So there's a plus sign, go to Custom.
We'll give it a trigger.
So I'm gonna tell it,
on Scene Start, do something.
So we'll select Scene Start,
and in our sequence,
we'll tell it to use a USDZ animation.
Now we need to target it.
Since I already had the taxi selected
when I built this behavior,
it automatically applied it
to the behavior.
So we don't even really need to target it.
Now we can hit space bar and simulate,
and there we have our taxi moving.
Now, by default, it goes one time
through the animation and stops.
I want this to loop endlessly.
So I'm gonna go ahead up here
at the action sequence,
and tell it to loop endlessly.
Now, if we simulate again...
our taxi's running, endlessly animating.
Perfect.
So let's take a look at our clouds.
Our cloud asset, if we remember,
we set up specifically
so we could get
at the individual entities.
So let me show you how to do that.
If you select your clouds,
you can right-click
and get at Hierarchy Select.
Here's where you can expand the USD scene
that we've created.
And this is how you can get at
the individuals inside
and do individual things.
So with right-clicking
and doing Hierarchy Select,
I can move things around,
I can scale them,
and, more importantly,
I can apply behaviors to them.
Great.
So with that understanding,
let's take this all over and use it
in context of a real AR experience.
So if we go to our scenes,
I've already put one together.
So here's a little town I put together
using our assets,
in a more contextual way.
If we hit simulate, you can see I've
already given it some ambient behaviors.
So let's take a look at our taxi asset
to begin with.
This particular taxi asset
is slowly approaching,
driving down the street,
and then disappearing.
Now, what's really happening
under the hood
is what this other one is doing.
This other taxi is moving
from point A to point B,
and then rewinding and doing it again.
But that doesn't look so great.
So let me show you
how to add those extra niceties
to make this look
like a real smooth transition in,
transition out, and a loop,
so as if it were ambient taxis
coming and going through your scene.
So let's jump down to the Behaviors
and take a look.
In our sequence,
you can see I'm doing a move-to.
This is moving a taxi
from point A to point B.
Now, after that,
I'm simply giving it another move-to
to tell it to go back
to where it started from.
So we need to add a couple more cards here
to smooth out that transition.
So if we hit the plus sign,
we can pick a Show,
we can also pick a Hide.
Now, behaviors are evaluated
left to right.
So we're going to need to
move these cards into position
so that they function correctly.
So I'll select my Show card,
and move it to the beginning,
'cause that's the first thing
I want it to do.
Of course, we'll choose our asset
that we want it to be triggered at.
We're also going to want to hide it.
So our Hide is not the last thing we do.
It's actually the third to last thing.
So we're going to put it in place.
Then again, choose,
and assign it to the taxi.
Now, let's take a look
at what that did for us.
Fades in, it drives,
and once it gets to the end
it's going to fade out,
and rewind itself.
But it doesn't quite
look like the other one.
That is because Show and Hide cards
have different ways of showing and hiding.
And that's an important distinction.
So let's scroll down a bit further
and check out their options.
If we give it a motion type,
we can tell at what direction
we want it to appear from.
So let's try Move from Front.
Now, I don't actually know
what direction that's going to go,
so that's why we have
these little play buttons.
And we can check and see
what this card does in context.
So I hit Play.
And it got lucky.
So let's take it.
So we can change the duration for how long
we want it to take to show up.
Let's say two seconds.
We can also tell it how far
we want it to go to show up.
So let's say something
like 25 centimeters.
And again, we can preview it
to see if that looks about right.
And perfect.
So last note on the card,
we're going to want to change
the animation type.
We don't want to ease in
and come to a stop
before the next card takes over.
We want it to ease in and then continue on
into the next animated card.
So we're going to change its easing type
to simply be Ease In.
And then, we're going to let the next card
have no easing type.
So it just smoothly transitions
across the whole thing.
For the Hide Out,
we're going to do the exact same thing.
Whereas this one was Move to Front,
this one will be Move to Rear.
We'll change it to have the same time.
And the same distance.
There we go.
And on this easing type,
we'll do Ease Out,
since it's slowly leaving the scene.
Now if we hit Play, we should have
something a little more similar
to what the other taxis are already
set up and doing.
It gets to the end.
It will smoothly drive off and disappear.
It will then rewind itself,
and begin again.
Perfect.
So that's the basic concept
of making something show,
move, hide, and repeat itself.
We can build on these basic concepts to
make something a little bit more complex.
Let's take a look at this police car.
This police car shows up, and moves.
Exactly how we did our taxi.
Now, when we get to the end of the street,
he's going to make a turn.
This turn is a little bit more complex
to set up
than just telling it to go
from point A to point B,
because that would be a linear move,
and we want it to do an arc.
So let's check it out.
If we scroll down here
to the police car's sequence,
we can see I'm doing a show, a move,
just like we had before,
now, I'm going to do an orbit
and another move.
Now, what am I orbiting?
I'm orbiting a tiny piece of geometry
that I have hidden inside another area.
So an Orbit card is going to require you
to have an affected object,
and a center object.
So if I move this building,
you can take a quick look,
I have a pill hidden inside this building.
That is what I'm using
as its area to orbit.
Let's go ahead and put our building back.
And you can see how that works.
The car drives,
once it gets to the end of the street,
he's going to then orbit that pill .25,
because I don't want to do a full circle,
just a simple turn.
And then, another Move To card
is going to take over.
And we'll have a Hide card at the end
to make it disappear, same as the taxi.
So that's an easy way
to take a simple behavior
such as, like, showing,
and moving, and hiding,
and giving a couple extra cards
in the middle
to create a more rich
and convincing environment.
So let's take a look at our clouds.
Like we did before,
we can select individual clouds
and make them do different things.
This would look a little funny
if all the clouds simply moved
on their own.
So let's check out what I've built.
In this behavior, I'm using
the same gimmick of Show and Hide
where I'm telling it to show a cloud,
come in on a slow transition,
and then hide out on a slow transition.
And if we view this sequence,
we can see our clouds are doing just that.
Now, that's great
and looks very convincing.
But I want them all to do it.
So let's hit Stop,
and let's apply more behaviors.
Now, where I want them all to do it,
I want them all to do it
at different rates.
So instead of building a new behavior
over and over again,
we can simply duplicate a behavior...
and re-target the cards
to different clouds.
So let's go ahead and do a Choose,
and instead of targeting these again,
we'll pick this guy here in the back.
And of course,
we'll do it again for the Hide.
And we can change its timing
to be something a little bit longer.
Maybe 15, and 15.
And let's simulate and see what that did.
So now you can see my groups of clouds
coming and going.
I have three different cloud behaviors
targeting different groups of clouds,
and they're moving and going
at different rates.
Perfect.
So with all that set up,
now's a good time to talk about context.
Viewing AR is great in context.
So we need to know how big are things?
Are things moving quickly or slowly
in your actual world?
So this is where we have the iOS Handoff.
So here, on Mac OS, I can hit Edit on iOS
and I can drop this project to my iPad.
Then, on my iPad, make edits in context
and drop it back to my Mac OS.
So let's give that a shot.
So here on the Mac OS,
we can simply do Edit on iOS...
and with Reality Composer launched,
you'll see our iPad show up.
Now, we can do the Handoff.
So we'll simply click ourselves,
and Accept on the iPad.
Now, it's transferring the project
all the way over to my iPad
for me to make edits.
So we'll simply wait for it to sync,
and we'll be good to go.
So here we go.
We've transferred our file
over to our iPad.
Now, we can view
and edit things in context.
So here on iPad, we can see
we have the Reality Composer app running,
and our project loaded.
We can simulate here in the View port,
and we can see everything
that we had set up on the Mac
is working here on the iOS.
Now, the power of working on iOS
is that we can drop this into our world,
and edit in real time.
So let's go ahead and hit
the AR affordance here in the corner.
And we can target our table
and drop our scene down.
Now, with our scene placed
in the real world,
we can hit Play again,
and we can view things in context.
There goes our little police car.
And here are our clouds coming and going.
And there's our taxis moving.
Now, let's say I'm not happy
with the rate something is moving.
I can simply hit Stop,
and I can jump over to the Behaviors tab.
Let's grab our taxi here.
And we can change
the rate at which things show up.
And let's say on taxi number two,
I would like it to show up
a little bit slower.
I can change that from two to five.
And we're set. We can hit Play again.
And we'll view that that takes now
five seconds for it to show up
at a very slow pace.
Now, happy with the changes
that we've made,
we can stop simulating,
drop out of AR mode,
and simply hit Done in the top corner.
That passes the project back
to your Mac OS.
Once back in Mac OS,
we can view that our behavior is updated
with the changes that we made
on our iOS project.
So if we navigate here,
and see that that five-second change
translated across for us smoothly.
Once happy, you can save it
and export it all out.
Let's hit one more topic
before we export all this.
I want to teach you how
to make a splash page
for your AR experience.
Now, when using AR Quick Look,
there is a load time
while it syncs and anchors.
While that's happening,
you view a scene of your content.
I'm going to teach you how to make
a nice scene there
for people to see
while they wait for it to load.
Now, the fastest way in Reality Composer
to do that
is to duplicate everything,
and remove what you don't want seen.
Let me show you how that works.
Here, we can do a Select All.
And Copy.
Now, on our Scenes tab,
we'll go ahead and make a new scene.
So we'll go ahead and remove this one.
We'll build a new one.
There we go.
Now, with a clean scene,
we can just Paste,
and all our geometry is coming
from our other scene into this one.
Now, what did not come along
is the behaviors.
So if we look at the behaviors,
everything is gone.
We simply have a static scene.
And that's fine. That is what we want.
So here,
I'm going to give it one behavior.
So let's go ahead and do a Custom,
On Scene Start...
and we're going to give it a Change Scene.
We'll choose our completed scene,
and we're good to go.
So what this is doing is,
when the scene is loading,
this is what you view.
But when it drops down on your table,
and the scene actually starts,
it immediately jumps over to our scene
with the animated traffic,
and the moving clouds.
So this, in a sense,
is making a splash page
for people to look at
while your content is loading.
So while we're here,
if we don't want to view certain things,
like I don't want to view the taxi,
or I don't want to view the clouds,
you can simply remove them,
and that comes off the splash page.
But when we simulate,
it immediately jumps to the page,
that has all the actual behaviors
and animations.
Perfect.
So our project is essentially done.
Now, let's talk about exporting
and sending to device.
New to Reality Composer,
we're going to give you the option
to export out as a USDZ.
Now, where before we were only giving you
the Reality Export,
this is a new option for you
that you'll need to enable
in your preferences.
So if we open our Preferences tab,
you can see Enable USDZ Export
as an option.
Now, you're asking,
"What's the difference?"
The difference is going to be contextual
based on what you want to do
with your project.
So if you're looking to embed it
in a website,
or put it in a News article,
you're going to want to use a USD export.
Now, if you want to use it
in an Xcode project,
or you want to use it with AR Quick Look,
you're going to want to
stick with the Reality export.
Now, I want to view this in AR Quick Look,
so I'm going to stick
with the Reality export.
Let's do a File.
Export,
and we'll save this to disk
as a Reality File.
So with our new exported file,
we can go ahead and AirDrop that
onto our device for viewing and sharing.
So let's do that.
I can select my Reality export,
I can right-click and do Share,
AirDrop.
Now, once our device comes up,
we can send it to ourselves.
Great.
So we see it pop up here on our iPad.
We can go ahead and accept it,
and save it to our files.
Now, with it saved in our files,
it'll automatically launch
in AR Quick Look,
and drop it onto our desk.
And once it loads,
our town should be here.
Perfect.
So that's the overall workflow using
Reality Converter and Reality Composer.
We have seen how we can take geometries
from a variety of DCCs
and using Reality Converter
make them into USDZs.
We then took those USDZs into Composer
and created an AR experience
with simple behavior set ups.
From that, we sent it all over
to AR Quick Look
to view, enjoy, and share.
Now, this is all in service
of building great AR experiences
that are lightweight and easily shareable.
So with these tools,
you now can create
even more compelling content
for your experience.
Moving forward from this talk,
you might find yourself with questions,
or wanting to know more
on topics that I touched on.
Here are some great resources
to help you dive deeper
on the topics we discussed.
If you are new to Reality Composer,
I encourage you to check out
the Apple YouTube video
that gives an overview of the software.
Now, for Reality Converter,
you can download the app
from the developer's site
and check out the documentation.
And for Xcode projects
that leverage Reality Composer
you can view the samples
under the RealityKit section.
Thank you so much
for taking the time to view my talk today.
I really hope you found it fun,
informative, and inspiring.
So I look forward to seeing
all the great content
and experiences Reality Converter
and Reality Composer
will enable you to create.
I am Philip Simmons,
and this has been a look
at the Artist AR Toolkit.
Thank you. Bye-bye.