Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Ellie Epskamp-Hunt.
I work on Safari.
Today I'm going to introduce
a new type of Safari extension,
Safari web extensions.
Before I go into more detail,
let's cover Safari's
existing extension ecosystem.
First there are Content Blockers.
These are available for iOS and macOS,
and are designed for speed
and user privacy.
Safari 13.1 can even run
your Content Blockers
delivered with apps
built with Mac Catalyst.
Next up, share extensions.
These are also available
on both iOS and macOS.
Once invoked by the user,
they are able to run JavaScript
on the webpage
and return data to your app extension.
And third, Safari App Extensions,
available on macOS.
These are great
if you are a native app developer
already familiar with Swift or Objective-C
who wants to extend
your app's functionality into Safari.
These extensions are all built
using native technologies
like Swift or Objective-C.
But what if you aren't familiar
with this style of development,
but are instead a web developer
familiar with JavaScript, HTML, and CSS?
Maybe you even have an extension
written for another major web browser
and you don't want to re-write it
in native code.
This year, we are thrilled to announce
that Safari is adding support
for web extensions on macOS.
These are built primarily using
JavaScript, HTML, and CSS,
similar to Legacy Safari Extensions.
But this type of extension
brings along significant improvements.
You can use
the same extension model and APIs
that you are already familiar with
in other browsers.
And web extensions also provide
improved user privacy controls
along with the ability
to sell through the App Store.
Today we're going to show you
just how easy it is
to bring your extensions
from other browsers to Safari.
We will walk you through
using our conversion tool.
We will review
our privacy-centric permissions model
to show how users will grant capabilities
to your extension.
Finally, we will cover tips and tricks
for debugging
and show how to message
your extension's native app.
Before we create
our first Safari web extension,
let's talk about
how these extensions are packaged.
Just like other Safari extensions,
Safari web extensions
are packaged with native apps.
When that native app is installed,
the extension is also installed in Safari.
It's up to you, the developer,
if the containing app
should play any role beyond this.
The containing apps
for Safari web extensions
will be distributed through the App Store.
And because these extensions
are packaged with apps,
you'll need to download Xcode 12 or higher
to build and run that app.
We've built a command-line tool
that ships with Xcode
to help you convert existing extensions
to use in Safari.
This tool will package your extension
into a native app.
This tool only needs to be run once
to create a default Xcode project
using information
from your extension's manifest file.
That project will build and run
the native app containing your extension.
If there are keys
that appear in your manifest
that are not supported
by the current version of Safari,
the tool will let you know.
The largest icon
you declare in the manifest
will be used as your app's icon,
so you'll want to declare
a larger icon size in your manifest.
We recommend that you add
a 512 by 512 icon and a 1024 by 1024 icon.
For more information
on designing great Mac app icons,
check out the macOS
Human Interface Guidelines.
Finally, if you add more files
while developing your extension,
these new files must be added
to your Xcode project.
And note that when you modify
your source files through Xcode,
your changes will appear
in the original file.
Now let's see how this tool works
in practice.
I have my unconverted extension here.
Sea Creator is an extension that replaces
aquatic animal names in webpages
with their corresponding emoji.
This folder contains
all my extension's resources.
In Terminal, I'll run
the safari-web-extension-converter command
and provide the path
to the extension folder.
Here it's asking if the information
it gleaned from the manifest is correct.
If I saw an issue with anything here,
I could type "no"
and the tool would allow me
to make changes.
But everything looks good,
so I'll press Enter
to use the default option
in the brackets, which is "yes."
We've got a warning from the tool.
Let's minimize Xcode for a second.
I declared that I wanted to use
the notifications API in my manifest,
but that isn't supported
in this version of Safari.
Since notifications aren't a critical part
of this extension's functionality,
I can continue converting.
Now let's run the app
and see the extension appear in Safari.
Click the Run button to build and run.
Here's the app that was created
by the converter tool.
It has the extension's icon,
some text indicating
if the extension is turned on or off,
and a button to open up
Safari's Preferences pane.
It's up to you
if you want to customize this app further.
Okay, let's open up Safari's Preferences.
Note that our extension isn't here.
Because I am just trying this tool out,
I don't have a developer certificate yet,
so the parent app is ad-hoc signed.
By default, Safari won't show extensions
from ad-hoc signed apps.
To show these extensions,
we need to first turn on the Develop menu.
Click in Advanced,
and then "show Develop menu in Menu bar."
Then in the Develop menu,
allow unsigned extensions
and authenticate.
Coming back to the extension pane,
there's our extension installed in Safari.
Below the extension description
is an explanation
of the privileges this extension has.
This extension's permissions mean
it can only access
the current tab's webpage
after the user interacts
with the toolbar icon,
a context menu item
or a keyboard shortcut.
All right, let's turn this extension on
and see it working.
The extension has a toolbar button now,
but its icon is grayed out.
This indicates that the extension
is not active on this current page.
Now let's find an article about fish.
When I click on the toolbar button
to use the popover,
the extension icon lights up.
The first thing you might notice here
is this broken image.
We will come back and fix that
during the debugging portion
of this session.
Now let's replace all the fish words
on this page with a cool emoji.
Great! We converted an existing extension
and used it in Safari.
For more information
on this converter tool,
consult the documentation
linked in the resources section.
Now what if you don't have an extension
made for another browser?
You can create one from scratch
using the Safari Extension App template
in Xcode
with "Safari web extension" as the type.
But it's possible that you have a Mac app
that you'd like to add
a Safari web extension to.
Let's cover how to do that now.
Here's my existing Mac app.
It's an app that lets me browse
and save recipes.
Maybe we want to create an extension
that lets me save recipes right in Safari.
Let's explore how to do that.
We're going to add a new target.
Select File, New, and Target.
Make sure you have the macOS tab selected
and filter by "Safari."
Select the "Safari Extension" option.
You'd use
the "Safari Extension App" option
if you wanted to create both the extension
and the containing app
completely from scratch.
Let's give this extension a name
and then make sure
you have "web extension"
as the selected type.
So the new target was created,
which we can see here.
And there's a new folder
here in the sidebar
with some default extension files.
For those who are unfamiliar
with this type of development,
let's go over what's here.
The information I'm about to cover
is applicable to all browsers
that support web extensions.
First, let's look at the manifest file.
The manifest file defines
the overall structure of your extension.
For example, you name your extension
by giving a value for the name key.
Here, the value of the name key
is a special string
that allows the extension's name
to be localized.
It's further defined in the Locales folder
in the messages.json file.
There are three main parts
of an extension:
the background scripts, content scripts,
and a popover.
There's a special API
that lets an extension communicate
between these three parts,
as well as create keyboard shortcuts,
access cookies, and more.
The background key defines which scripts
make up the background page.
These scripts have no visible UI
and can contain the logic
that drives your extension.
Let's take a look
at the background script.
Here we have a snippet of code
that receives a message
from another part of the extension
and sends out a response.
Next up, content scripts.
Content scripts are injected into webpages
and can modify their appearance
and function.
These scripts execute
in an isolated world,
meaning they won't conflict
with the webpage's JavaScript.
The "matches" keyword here
defines which domains you want
your content scripts to be injected into.
If we take a look at this content script,
we can see it using the sendMessage API
to send out a message
which we saw being processed
by the background page.
And finally, a popover.
Here, the browser_action key
defines a popover
that appears when the user
clicks the toolbar button.
This is an easy way for your users
to interact with your extension.
Another important part of the manifest
is the permissions key.
The permissions key defines privileges
your extension has in Safari.
You can put API names here,
like "cookies,"
which lets an extension read
and set browser cookies.
You can also have URL match strings
to define which websites
your extension has access to generally.
There are lots of online resources
to learn more
about developing web extensions
and you can look at the information
on developer.apple.com
for content specific
to Safari web extensions.
And that's how you create
Safari web extensions,
either from scratch
or by converting an existing one.
Now let's talk about extension permissions
in greater detail.
Apple takes user privacy very seriously.
Our browsing experience,
including which websites we visit
and what we do on those websites
can be highly personal.
So when we install an extension,
we want to make sure
only the data we are comfortable sharing
with that extension gets shared.
To show how users will control
their privacy in Safari
when it comes to extensions,
let's make some modifications
to the Sea Creator extension.
Let's say I've really enjoyed
using my extension on Wikipedia
and I just want it
to always work on that site
without any action on my end.
Previously, my extension made use
of the activeTab permission
which is what allowed it access
to the current tab I was on.
The "Replace words" button
injected the content script dynamically.
Instead, we want to declare
our content script in the manifest.
First we'll go into the manifest
and remove that activeTab keyword
from the permissions array.
Then we will add a content_scripts key
to inject content.js into wikipedia.org.
Let's build and see
what this experience looks like in Safari.
I'll use the product menu
and select "build."
Let's go to that article about fish.
The first thing that we notice
is that our toolbar button
is badged with a warning icon.
This lets the user know
that the extension wants access
to one or more sites.
If we click on the button,
we get this dialog in the popover
explaining what website
the extension wants access to.
We can go ahead and allow for one day.
And then our content script is injected.
Notice that if we visit
another Wikipedia page,
our choice is remembered
and the content script
is injected immediately
without me having to interact
with the toolbar button again.
The toolbar button
still remains highlighted,
letting me know that the extension
is able to run code on this page.
Now let's say I want to add a share button
for Shiny the social network
to my extension.
This is a good chance
to use optional permissions.
Optional permissions
are used for permissions
that aren't critical
to your extension's functionality.
To use optional permissions,
we first name the URL
or API name in the manifest,
and then request it
in our JavaScript code.
First, let's add a URL match pattern
for shiny.com in the manifest.
In our popover code,
I've already added a share button.
Let's add the code that requests
the optional permission I added
in the shareOnShiny function.
I'm calling browser.permissions.request
with the particular origin
I want access to.
Then I could add more code here
that would share information
about the extension.
Let's see what this looks like in Safari.
Use the product menu to build again.
Back in Safari...
when I click this share button,
I get this dialog that asks me
if I want to allow my extension access
to shiny.com.
I can allow for one day
and then I would be able to tell the world
about the Sea Creator extension.
All right, so maybe
I'm just loving my extension so much
that I just want it to work everywhere.
To do this, I'll modify the manifest again
and use the "all_urls" keyword
in the matches section
to indicate I want this content script
to be injected onto every webpage I visit.
Let's build again.
Now if I come back
into the Preferences pane,
I can see that my previous choices
were remembered.
If I go to another webpage about fish,
this time there's no warning badge.
The warning badge won't appear
every time a user visits a new site.
We put the warning badge there
the first time your extension
wants to inject into a webpage
as a way to educate users
about activating an extension
from the toolbar item.
When we click the popover,
we get a similar dialog
about giving access to a website.
This time I'll allow on all websites,
but this prompt appears to make sure
that the user is completely aware
of the access they are giving.
Back in the Preferences pane,
the list of websites
where your extension has access
has disappeared
and has been replaced by this message,
letting the user know
the capability that this extension has.
And that's how extension permissions
work in Safari.
Now let's talk about some best practices
when it comes to these permissions.
The best way for an extension
to respect user intention
when it comes to privacy
is by using the activeTab permission.
With this permission,
your extension is only granted access
to know things about a tab, like its URL,
and inject script into the webpage,
when your user expresses intent
to use your extension
with that tab very clearly,
by using the toolbar item,
keyboard shortcut, or context menu item.
Optional permissions are another great way
to respect user privacy.
These permissions are also declared
in the manifest
and represent permissions
that your extension would like to have,
but that aren't critical to
the core functionality of your extension.
For some extensions, you will want to
not require a user gesture to take action.
For example, you might have an extension
that inserts a useful toolbar
on certain domains.
You might have a manifest
that looks something like this,
where a script is injected onto
all domains that match to apple.com.
But this doesn't mean that your extension
will automatically be given access
to inject on those domains.
Instead, the user will see
your extension's toolbar icon badged
the first time they visit a website
that matches what's declared
in the manifest.
Some extensions ask
for access to everything
by using the "all_urls" permissions key
in the manifest.
If your extension doesn't actually
need access to all webpages,
scope your webpage access requests
more appropriately.
In summary, activeTab is a great way
to respect user privacy.
If activeTab isn't compatible
with your extension,
request the minimum access you need
for your extension to work.
And use optional permissions
to request more access
for noncritical features
of your extension.
And that was an overview
of privacy and permissions
for Safari web extensions.
Now let's talk about some tools we added
to make debugging your web extensions
easier in Safari.
I can right-click in the popover
to inspect.
Well, there's an error.
It looks like I've hard-coded
my extension resource URLs
to use the moz-extension scheme.
That's not going to work in Safari.
Let's go back to Xcode and fix this.
One approach might be
to change the scheme of this URL
to be safari-web-extension.
This isn't going to work, though,
because the host of your extension URL
changes across every launch of Safari
to prevent users of your extension
from being fingerprinted.
Instead, we need to use an extension API
that forms extension URLs.
It's called browser.runtime.getURL.
Let's see if that fixes our bug.
Great, now our beautiful
wave image appears.
Our issue was in the popover this time,
but you might also want to inspect
your background page.
I'll use the Develop menu,
web extension background pages,
and click on the name of my extension.
You might also run into bugs
in your content scripts.
Let's take a look at how to debug those.
First, let's go to a webpage
where my content script is injected.
Then let's right-click on the page.
Here in the Sources tab,
you can see all the extension scripts
that are injected into a page.
Any injected style sheets
would also appear here.
Maybe I want to print out the contents
of a variable in my content script.
If I do that now, it won't work.
That's because Web Inspector
is currently targeting
the page's JavaScript world.
Again, content scripts execute
in an isolated world
to avoid conflicts
with the webpage JavaScript.
We need to switch
to the extension's isolated world.
I can do that using this menu
in the bottom right.
Now if I print out the variable,
I can see its contents.
Those are some developer tools we added
to help you debug your web extensions.
If you want to learn more
about Web Inspector,
check out the session
dedicated this topic.
Let's quickly discuss
some common bugs you may encounter
while converting your web extension
to use in Safari.
First, if you perform user agent checking,
think again about this approach.
Using feature detection
is the more reliable way
to determine what's available
in the browser
your extension is running in.
Second, bugs can come
from making assumptions
about your extension's resource URLs.
For example,
if you check for a particular scheme,
like Chrome extension,
or assume the host of your URL
will be same across launches of Safari,
this might cause bugs.
Third, your extension
may have problems in Safari
if it has content scripts
that depend on being injected immediately.
Remember, the user may navigate to a page
and then allow your extensions
to inject scripts.
So in this case,
if you have a script that listens
for when the DOM content has loaded
and then performs an action,
that code won't be called
and your extension will appear broken
to the user.
Finally, it's possible that there are
slight implementation differences
between browsers
for an API your extension uses.
Consult online documentation like on MDN,
the Mozilla Developer Network,
for more detailed information.
And those were some tips and tricks
for debugging your web extension
in Safari.
Let's discuss how to communicate
with your native app
using the native messaging API.
Native messaging allows apps
and extensions to communicate.
Unlike in other browsers,
your extension is only allowed
to communicate with its container app.
Let's discuss how to send messages
between the different components
of your extension:
the app, the app extension,
and the background page running in Safari.
Communicating from the background page
to your app extension's native code
uses the same API found in other browsers.
Use browser.runtime.sendNativeMessage
or browser.runtime.connectNative
and make sure you request
the native messaging permission
in your manifest.
You don't need to provide
the application IDs to these APIs
as Safari securely guarantees
that the message will be relayed
to your app extension.
If we want to go the other way
and send a message
from the app extension's native code
to the background page,
use the completion handler
on the NSExtensionContext object
passed in to SafariWebExtensionHandler.
beginRequest.
To send a message from your app
to the extension's background page,
you can use SFSafariApplication.
dispatchMessage.
Before using this method,
it's a good idea to check
that your extension
is actually turned on in Safari.
You can do this by calling
SFSafariExtensionManager
getStateOfSafariExtension.
If you've written
a Safari app extension before,
these APIs are the same ones you've used.
To receive the message
in the background page,
you must have opened a port
using browser.runtime.connectNative.
And to communicate between the different
components of your App Group,
use NSUserDefaults or an XPC connection.
That's how you send messages
between the different components
of your app and extension.
Now that we've got an idea
of how to communicate
between our native app and extension,
let's see how it works in practice.
Let's add a feature
that reports how many times
our word replacement script
ran in the native app UI.
To achieve this, we will send a message
from our extension to our app extension,
write the value to NSUserDefaults
and then read that value
and display it in the app's UI.
First, we need to add the nativeMessaging
permission to our manifest.
Next, let's add a message
from the content script
to the background page
to indicate that
some replacement of text has happened.
Then, in our background page,
we can call sendNativeMessage
to send a message
from our app extension's native code.
Now let's handle that message
in SafariWebExtensionHandler.
The code that's here was provided by Xcode
when we converted our extension.
Using the NSExtensionContext object,
we can grab the contents of that message
and then write to NSUserDefaults.
Make sure you specify a particular suite.
The bundle identifier here
matches the ID I used
to group my app and app extension
in the Capabilities section
of the targets.
I added the App Group capability here...
for each target,
and gave them the same identifier.
Now that we've written to our defaults,
we can read that value in the parent app.
I've already created a button
that will update the text in our app's UI.
So we need to read and then set the text.
Let's build and see it in action.
I navigate to the page,
and the script works.
I click this button, and great,
this updated based on information
from the extension.
And that was an overview
of how to communicate
between your extension and app.
We've gone over a lot today.
First we showed how to convert
an existing extension for use in Safari
or how to create ones from scratch.
Then we covered Safari's permission model
developed with privacy in mind.
We explored tools added in Safari
to help you debug your extension
and common pitfalls.
And finally we learned how to communicate
with your extension's parent app.
Now that you've seen
Safari web extensions work in practice,
try it out yourself.
Start by downloading
the sample code project
that builds and runs
the Sea Creator extension
that you saw in this session
and play around with it.
We are very excited to see you
bring your web extensions to Safari,
so try using our converter tool
to bring over an extension
you've made for another browser.
We are just getting started
with web extensions in Safari
and you might find that some APIs
you need are missing.
We are depending on your feedback
to make web extensions in Safari
even better,
so tell us which APIs
are the most important
to help you provide the best experience
for your users.
Reach out through Feedback Assistant
or on the Safari developer forums
to let us know what you think
or of any bugs you find.