Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hey. My name's Matthew,
and I'm on the Security Engineering
and Architecture team.
Today, we're going to talk
about the Endpoint Security Framework.
The Endpoint Security Framework was first
introduced last year in macOS Catalina.
It is intended to be used as a replacement
for the Kauth KPI,
the unsupported Mac kernel framework,
and the OpenBSM audit trail.
Kernel extensions, or KEXTS,
can be difficult to develop
and even more difficult to debug.
Further, KEXTS pose
a maintenance nightmare,
as kernel interfaces frequently change.
They can also degrade
overall system security and stability
as even minor bugs
often lead to kernel panics.
With the EndpointSecurity Framework,
you no longer need to develop
a kernel extension,
and you can instead focus on
the real goals of your products.
Products that use EndpointSecurity, or ES,
are able to tap into a rich event stream
from a normal application.
Right now, ES supports roughly 100 event
types, and we're constantly adding more.
There are two categories of event types.
We have NOTIFY events, which inform you
of an operation taking place,
and AUTH events,
which allow you to control
whether or not an operation
should be allowed to continue.
We'll be discussing how
the EndpointSecurity subsystem works,
how your products
can best utilize the event stream,
as well as some more advanced features
available to you.
While it's possible to distribute your
ES application as a stand-alone product,
we believe there are a lot of benefits
to delivering your product
as an EndpointSecurity based
system extension.
System extensions were also introduced
last year in macOS Catalina.
Several types of extensions are supported,
including Network Extensions
for writing applications
such as VPNs and content filters,
DriverKit for controlling hardware,
and EndpointSecurity targeted at products
like endpoint detection and response.
We're not going to cover system extensions
in detail here,
but you should check out last year's
WWDC 2019 session
titled "System Extensions and DriverKit"
for more information.
First, when the extension is installed,
it becomes protected
by System Integrity Protection,
preventing accidental or malicious
tampering of you extension and assets.
We're also able to provide a greater
level of protection for you daemon
similar to that of system daemons.
This means that we prevent even root users
from being able to unload
your launchd job.
Also, there are some EndpointSecurity
features that products can only use
if they are a system extension,
such as during system start-up,
the ability to execute
and set up an event stream
before other third party applications
are able to execute.
I always like starting with an example,
so let's take a quick look
at the key components needed
to get started with EndpointSecurity.
One thing to note,
this framework is provided as a C library,
which is a little different
than many other Apple frameworks
you might encounter.
Using C allowed us greater control
over some memory
and performance characteristics.
Also, our goal was to be able
to provide a library
that would be quickly adoptable
by existing products.
By using C, this library is callable
from many languages
including Swift, Objective-C and Rust.
First off, in this example, you can see we
start by initializing a new event stream
using the ES new client API.
This function returns
an ES client T handle as an out parameter,
but, importantly, is also defines
the event handler block.
The block passed here
will be invoked whenever there is
an event ready to be processed.
In this example, you can see the block
simply prints out the event type.
Next, we set up the subscriptions
for the event stream
using the es_subscribe API.
In this example, we have a single event
in the array, the NOTIFY_EXEC event.
Also in this example, we see
the es_delete client API being used,
when something went wrong
setting up the subscriptions,
and this API can be used
to clean up resources
previously obtained
from a call to es_new_client.
Finally, we call dispatch main
which will allow the program
to continue executing
and process events via
the event handler block submitted above.
To help you all get an understanding
of how EndpointSecurity works,
let's take a look
at a high-level architecture design.
When your process connects
to the EndpointSecurity subsystem
using the es_new_client API,
a channel is set up through which messages
will be enqueued for processing.
In this diagram here, there are
two different ES-based applications.
One has set up two event streams
using multiple calls to es_new_client,
and the second one has a single channel.
We typically refer to these channels
as ES clients.
Each ES client is able to have
its own set of subscriptions
to control which events it receives.
When an event is triggered in the kernel,
and assuming our client
is subscribed to that event,
EndpointSecurity intercepts
and enriches this event
with information that is typically helpful
for ES clients performing analysis.
We'll discuss the information collected
in more detail in a second,
but once collected, this data
is then wrapped in a message envelope.
Next, that message is then sent
to all appropriate ES clients,
enqueueing the message
for the event handler blocks to process.
The message is enqueued
for all clients simultaneously.
So for those of you
already familiar with EndpointSecurity,
this is a slight change in behavior,
where before,
events were delivered to clients serially.
Some events require a response,
which we'll talk about shortly,
in which case the original operation
is held up in the kernel
until a response is received.
For normal notification events, or after
receiving a response for AUTH events,
the operation is immediately unblocked
in the kernel and allowed to continue.
Last thing to note in this diagram,
is that EndpointSecurity
attempts to cache as much as possible
in order to reduce the number of messages
that are required to be delivered
for AUTH events.
We have a lot more information
about the cache later on.
The message envelope I just mentioned
refers to the es_message_t structure,
which is the wrapper for all ES events
delivered to ES clients
via the event handler block.
Each message contains three
primary categories of information.
First, message metadata.
This includes things like the event type,
message generation time,
whether it's an AUTH or a NOTIFY event,
and a message version number used for
compatibility, which we'll touch on later.
Next, all messages include information
about the process that caused the event
to be triggered in the first place.
Process information includes information
about the executable file,
including full stat info,
code signing information, process ID and
user ID information, and a whole lot more.
Last, each message contains information
specific to the event that occurred.
For example,
the SIGNAL event includes information
about the process being signaled
and the signal number.
The exec event includes information
such as the file that will be executed
and the executable arguments,
and the OPEN event includes information
about the file being opened
and the open flags.
Time-of-check time-of-use issues
are extremely important
for you to be aware of
when developing your ES products.
Quickly, for those
who may not be familiar,
this refers to a class of bugs that occur
when a program makes assumptions
about some state that were previously true
but may no longer be true.
Classic example here
is first checking if a file exists
and then opening the file
as a two-step process.
If someone on the system
maybe deleted the file
after your program checked its existence,
but before your program opened it,
and your program
didn't handle open failures correctly,
it could lead to unexpected behavior.
The information provided in ES messages
reflects a snapshot in time.
The system continues to process
multiple threads simultaneously,
and those threads may do things
that can change system state
before your application has an opportunity
to inspect a message.
This means, in some cases, parts
of the message may have different values
than if you were to query that information
on your own.
Products need to be cautious of things
like time-of-check time-of-use issues.
This is no different
than those issues faced
by kernel extension-based products today.
One last thing to note
before diving in to a demo,
EndpointSecurity
has a handful of runtime requirements
that programs must satisfy in order to
successfully establish an ES event stream.
First, an application must have
the proper EndpointSecurity entitlement.
This is a restricted entitlement,
and you can request a provisioning profile
via the link shown here.
If your application is bundled
as a system extension,
there is an additional entitlement
required for the containing app bundle
in order to install the extension.
This information can be found
within the system extension documentation.
Also, system extensions require approval
from the user to complete installation.
Once an extension
begins the installation process
by using the system extension API,
the user must approve the installation
from the Security and Privacy Preferences
dialogue on the General pane.
Next, in order to increase user privacy,
we require that your applications
obtain user consent
in the form
of Full Disk Access permissions,
which is found on the Privacy pane of the
Security and Privacy Preferences dialogue.
If you deploy as a system extension,
on installation, we pre-populate
your extension in this dialogue
to make it easier on users
to enable these permissions.
If your product is being deployed
on managed devices,
there are two MDM payloads available
to aid distribution.
First, there's payload
to define extensions
that will be automatically
allowed to install without user approval.
And second,
there is a privacy preferences payload
that can automatically enable
Full Disk Access permissions.
All right.
Now, let's just into our first demo
where we're going to look at
notification messages
and expand upon an existing ES extension.
So over here we're looking at
our main function for a NOTIFY demo,
and we can see right away
this code looks very similar
to the example code
that we saw a few slides back.
We start by setting up our new client
event stream with es_new_client,
and our handler block here just calls
our handle_event function,
which we'll look at in a second.
Next, we set up our subscriptions here
and call es_subscribe.
Right now we have the NOTIFY_EXEC
and NOTIFY_FORK event types.
Then, once the subscriptions are in place,
we call dispatch_main
to allow our program to continue
executing and processing these events.
So let's jump up in the handle_event.
Up here, you can see we use a switch
statement on the message event_type,
and then we have a case for each one
to just log message to the screen.
So this extension is already installed
and running and approved on the system,
so let's go take a look
at what's happening.
So we're going to
set up our log stream here first,
and there's a predicate involved
that allows us to just focus on
the executions that I'm doing right now.
Next, I'm gonna use the ps utility
as an example.
So now, when we execute ps,
we see two messages come through.
We first see that our Z shell
is forking a new child process,
and then from that forked process,
it wants to execute the new
executable /bin/ps.
All right. Now let's expand upon this demo
and add the EXIT event to get
full process life cycle information.
So here in our event array, we're going to
add the ES_EVENT_TYPE_NOTIFY_EXIT
to our list of subscriptions.
In our handle_event function,
we need to add this new case.
So I'm gonna go ahead
and add the break statement
so I don't forget to do that later,
and now we want to log this information.
So I'll set up some of the boiler plate
code for the OS log function here,
and for the format string,
let's go ahead and add
the instigating process information
like we did above, along with the pid.
And then next, I know that the EXIT event
includes some event specific information
related to the exit status.
So let's get that as well.
All right.
So now, to fill in the data
for this format string,
we need to first look for
the instigating process,
and we can do that looking at the process
member of the message structure.
From there, we can look at the executable,
and then finally grab the path.
Next, we need that pid
for that process, and for processes,
EndpointSecurity provides audit tokens
for that information,
which includes things like the user ID
and the process ID.
So you can use the lib BSM function,
audit_token_to_pid, to extract that.
So, once again,
we'll dive into the-- the process field
and pull out the audit token.
And finally, we want the event specific
information free at the EXIT event,
which is the exit status code.
So to do that, we'll look at
the event member of the message.
From there we can pull out the EXIT event
and then, finally, the stat field
for that status code.
All right. So we're going
to build this extension,
and now we need to install it.
A quick note that I've set up a system
extension developer mode on this system,
and that just allows us
to more quickly deploy test extensions.
The other thing to note here
is that system extension requires
that the containing app bundle
live in /Applications
to be able to install the extension.
So we're gonna drag this containing app
we just built over to /Applications.
And then, once there, we can run that
app and finally install the extension.
So this is now
just performing the upgrade,
and the new extension is now running
and live on the system.
So, once again,
let's use the ps utility as an example.
Now you can see
we get a third exit message,
that includes the status code of zero,
indicating the process
exited successfully.
As a quick example,
we could pass an invalid flag to ps
and we can see now the status code is 256
indicating there might have been an issue
with the process.
Now that we've seen notification events
in action,
it's time to talk about AUTH events.
A major feature of EndpointSecurity
is the ability to authorize operations
on the system.
AUTH events are synchronous,
which means after we enqueue
the message for the ES clients,
the operation is held up in the kernel
and unable to resume
until a response is received
or a deadline expires.
Each AUTH message received
has its own deadline field
contained inside the message structure.
Your ES clients must inspect this value
for each message
and ensure that the work it performs
is completed before the deadline expires.
If a client fails to respond
before the deadline,
the application will be terminated.
If your application is a system extension,
the launchd job we submit for you
will be automatically restarted.
It's important to emphasize that each
individual message has its own deadline,
and there is no guarantee
that each message
allows for the same amount
of response time.
These values can
and will change over time.
When a deadline is missed, an implicit
ALLOW is applied as the response,
but the result will not be cached,
allowing future operations
to be reevaluated.
There are two APIs available
for responding to AUTH events.
Most event types require a simple
ALLOW or DENY response
using the es_respond_auth_result API.
The second response API,
es_respond_flags_result
is used when an event has a range of
options that may be permitted or denied,
such as being able
to allow a file to be opened
with read-only permissions
instead of read/write.
You should look at documentation to know
which API to use for each event type,
however as of today, only the AUTH OPEN
event uses the flags result API.
If there are multiple clients on a system
that subscribe to the same AUTH event,
the responses
from all the clients are combined
by applying the most restrictive response,
so if you have four clients respond
to an event with ALLOW
but one wants to DENY, the overall result
is to deny the operation.
Similarly for flags responses,
only the subset of flags
set by all clients will be allowed.
You should also be aware that ES
does not send introspective AUTH events
as this would lead to trivial deadlocks.
The events will be implicitly allowed.
We will, however, send NOTIFY messages
for events instigated by your process.
One quick caveat to call out
with the flags result API
is that your ES client process
should respond with
all the flags it will ever permit,
not necessarily only the flags requested
for an individual event.
This has to do with caching, and we'll
discuss this in more detail soon.
With muting, ES clients are able to
prevent receiving messages
from processes that may not be
of interest to the application.
There are two main ways to do this.
First, with es_mute_process,
the ES application provides an audit token
that uniquely identifies a process.
Typically, the client will obtain
the audit token from a previous message.
The EndpointSecurity subsystem
will automatically track process exits
and remove them from your client's set
of muted processes.
There is no need to manually use
the corresponding es_unmute_process API
unless your client
wants to start receiving messages again
from a process that it previously muted.
ES also supports muting by path literals,
that is complete paths,
with es_mute_path_literal as well as
path prefixes with es_mute_path_prefix.
As the names suggest,
this mechanism will prevent messages
from instigating processes
which match the provided paths.
We recommend that ES clients use caution
with these last two APIs here.
While we employ data structures
with fast lookup operations,
adding a large number of paths
can potentially have
an adverse affect on performance.
Muting by process audit token
is generally a better way to mute events
without as much overhead.
Many of the AUTH events can cache
the combined result
from the ES client responses,
and this is stored in a single global
cache shared across all ES clients.
The cache strategy used
by EndpointSecurity is best effort,
and entries may expire at any time.
EndpointSecurity tracks
several operations,
and will automatically
invalidate cached entries,
for example, if a file is written,
truncated, deleted and many more.
While we don't guarantee responses
will be cached,
if an ES client sets the cache flag
in the response APIs to false,
ES will guarantee
not to cache that result,
even if another client
does request that it be cached.
Some reasons that an ES client
may want to deny caching
might be for the EXEC events
when the executable is very dependent
upon the executable arguments
or environment variables,
such as interpreters
where you may want to inspect the script
that the interpreter will execute.
ES applications are able to clear the
entire cache with the es_clear_cache API,
however we do not support
invalidating individual cache entries.
Also note that ES
will automatically clear the cache
when a new client connects
or an existing client disconnects.
This allows for various scenarios
where the remaining clients
might respond with a different result
than the previously combined cache result.
A few slides back I mentioned
an important caveat
that you need to be aware of when using
the es_respond_flags_result API.
While at first it might sound unintuitive,
the response must contain all flags
an ES client might ever allow
for an operation.
This is because the cache
for flags responses
operates the same way as AUTH responses.
When a future event occurs,
the cache is first consulted.
If a cached entry exists,
the flags from that entry
are compared against the requested flags
for the new operation,
and the result is applied
without generating an AUTH message.
So consider the case where a process
opens a file with read-only flags set,
and suppose the file being opened
isn't a concern to your application.
That is, your application wants
to allow that process
to manipulate the file however it needs.
When your ES client process
responds with the flags result,
it should set all appropriate flags,
including the WRITE flag,
even though it wasn't requested
for this particular event.
Because what would happen
if you did not set the WRITE flag?
Well, if the process opened
the same file for writing in the future,
and the cached result still existed,
the operation would be
automatically denied
without generating an AUTH message,
even though that wasn't
what your product intended.
Now that we've gone over the two,
let's look at a quick comparison
between AUTH and NOTIFY event types.
NOTIFY events are always asynchronous.
We enqueue the message for the client,
but the operation immediately continues
and could be completed
before the ES client
has an opportunity to see the message.
AUTH events, as previously stated,
are synchronous
and the operation is held up
until a response is received.
Regarding delivery, NOTIFY messages
are always delivered.
However, AUTH messages are only delivered
if there is no cached result
and the message isn't being delivered
to the same process
that instigated the event.
Neither AUTH
nor NOTIFY messages are delivered
if the instigating process is muted.
Finally, there is a slight difference
in message structure between the two.
NOTIFY messages contain the result
as applied by EndpointSecurity.
That is, the ALLOW or DENY result
from the corresponding AUTH message.
If there were no ES clients
subscribed to the AUTH variant,
or no AUTH variant exists for the event,
the result is implicitly allowed.
For AUTH messages, no result information
exists yet, obviously.
However, a message will have
a deadline value
and also requires a response
from the ES client process.
Now, let's do another demo,
this time looking at AUTH event types
and seeing how we can write a client
to handle and respond to these messages.
So, once again, we're looking
at our main function here.
You'll notice right away it looks very similar
to the previous demo setup that we had.
One slight difference here,
we're going to be performing
some asynchronous work
on an asynchronous dispatch queue.
So, we're going to go ahead
and set up that queue first.
But afterwards, we'll go ahead and
initialize our new client event stream
with the es_new_client.
And our handler block will once again
call our handle_event function.
For this demo, we're going to be looking
at AUTH_EXEC and AUTH_OPEN event types.
And after subscribing,
we once again call into dispatch_main
to allow our program to continue
executing and processing these events.
So, let's look at
the handle_event function.
Once again, we see a switch statement here
where we call
an appropriate handle function
for each individual event type.
Let's start with EXEC.
First thing to note here is that we call
the es_respond_auth_result
with ES_AUTH_RESULT_ALLOW for all EXECS.
But we've left a TODO for ourselves
to deny new EXECs matching the signing ID.
Now, we typically expect most products
will want more restricted polices,
such as matching on CD hashes,
but for demonstration purposes,
this is a little more clear
to see what we're trying to block.
So, how can we do this?
Well, one way, we could just use
a simple string comparison
on the new process that we'll be executing
then compare that signing ID
to the one that we want to block.
So, because we're looking at
the event-specific data,
we'll dive into the event union.
And then from here,
we can look at the target process
and pull out the signing_id data.
So, now we'll compare that
to the signing_id_to_block,
and if they're equal,
we want to deny that.
So, we can do that
with the es_respond_auth_result API.
We need to pass our client
and message argument here.
And next we need to, define our result
which is simply the AUTH_RESULT_DENY.
Go ahead and allow this to be cached.
And to complete this out,
we'll put this previous existing response
here in the else statement.
So, now, if our new executable
matches the signing ID we want to block,
we will respond with a "deny" result,
and everything else will be allowed.
So now let's look at the open case.
So in handle_open,
this may look a little less familiar,
and there's some concepts
we need to introduce
that we haven't quite talked about yet.
It is recommended that your ES clients
perform as little work as possible
in their event handler block.
This typically means
that you shouldn't perform a lot of I/O
or large CPU-intensive tasks.
And the goal here
is that your event handler block
should be as quick as possible
so that they can return
and continue dequeuing messages
in order to keep
that message queue size small,
and that will help prevent
with dropping messages.
So in this function,
you see we copy our message
with the es_copy_message API,
and we'll discuss that more later on.
After we've copied our message,
we asynchronously call
our handle_open_worker function,
and then once that's complete, we then
go ahead and free that copied message.
So, what does our worker function do?
We have three cases
that we're concerned about.
Our first case
is a test for an EICAR file,
and for those not familiar,
an EICAR file is a test file
that antivirus products typically use
to test their operation
without needing to introduce
real malicious code on the system.
So, it's not important what this function
does for this demo purposes.
Just know that it needs to open
and inspect the file contents,
and it was a big driver for why
we're doing this work asynchronously.
So, assuming this is an EICAR file,
we will use
the es_respond_flags_result API.
And you can see we've defined
a mask of zero.
And this essentially clears all bits
and will deny all open operations
for that file.
Next, you can see
we left a TODO for ourselves.
So, what's going on here?
In this if statement,
you can see we're inspecting
the open event specific data
for the file that is being opened,
and we compare that against
the read only prefix
here defined as /usr/local/bin.
So we want to prevent anybody from
manipulating files on these directories.
So, to do that, we can once again use
the es_respond_flags_result API.
We'll also pass
our client and message arguments.
Now we need to define the flags.
We know that the only operation
that we want to deny here
is the write operation.
So we can define the mask
that is first with all bits set
and then use some bitwise operations
to clear the right flag.
One thing to note here you might notice
is that EndpointSecurity
provides flags for the open event
that are the kernel versions of flags,
not the oflags that you might be
familiar with from the open system call.
This is documented in the open event,
and you should check that out.
Last, we'll allow this to be cached.
And then the final case here
already written,
is that for all other open operations, we
have our mask set here with all bits set
and will allow all those open operations
to continue successfully.
So, let's recap what we've done.
So, the three things that our program
was intending to do
was first to deny
the text edit application to open.
We haven't installed the extension yet,
so we can see all this working now.
So text edit can successfully open.
We also wanted to deny writing to files
in /usr/local/bin.
So, as an example here,
we have set up a script called hi.sh
that simply prints "hi" to the screen.
And just to see that running,
we can execute it.
It does
exactly what you'd expect it to do.
Finally, in our home directory,
I have an EICAR file.
So, we'll print that out here,
and we can see
the standard EICAR test file definition.
All right, so, now let's go over,
build our extension.
We once again need to install
the system extension,
so we're gonna drag it over
to /Applications.
Now we'll launch the containing app bundle
and install that new extension,
and now our AUTH demo
is now live and running.
So, we can first try now to open
the text edit application.
We can see the icon bounces,
but nothing's able to launch anymore.
Next we want to try and modify a file
in usr/local/bin.
So, here we can see I'm trying to modify
the contents of the hi script
to say "Bye" instead.
However, this is now no longer allowed.
But you can see this file is still allowed
to be opened for read-only purposes,
and the script is able to still execute.
And finally we have the EICAR file
that we want to prevent all operations on.
So we can see even trying
to read that file is no longer permitted.
After seeing how easy it is to write
in ES client to handle AUTH events,
let's dive into some more advanced topics.
The message structure contains
a version field
that will allow your ES-based applications
to maintain compatibility
when deployed across
different operating system releases.
New fields can be added to the various
EndpointSecurity structures over time,
allowing us to provide
additional information to your ES clients.
The version number
is a single integer value,
and all messages in an OS release
will share the same version number.
If an OS release modified structures
in a way that could affect compatibility,
the version number will be increased.
Clients using newer fields
must first check the message version
to ensure the field is available.
Failing to do so
will result in undefined behavior.
Please pay close attention
to the header docs for the ES structures
as they indicate in which version
new fields were added.
As a quick example, let's take a look
at the acl field for the create event.
This field didn't exist
in the initial release,
and, when it was added,
we bumped the message version to 2.
In the small example here,
we have the handle_notify_create function
that operates on NOTIFY_CREATE events.
We see that before accessing
the acl member,
the function first checks
that the message version
is greater than or equal to two.
The so-called early boot feature is
a powerful mechanism of EndpointSecurity.
And, as a reminder,
this feature is only available
to ES-based products
that are system extensions,
not to stand-alone ES applications.
An extension opts into this feature
by setting
the NSEndpointSecurityEarlyBoot key
in the extensions input/out plist.
When there are registered
early boot clients on system start-up,
the system still comes up normally.
However, no additional third-party
applications will be allowed to execute
until all of the early boot extensions
are ready.
To signal readiness, your extension
needs to make at least one call
to the es_subscribe API.
Once all early boot clients
have made their first subscriptions,
the third-party applications
are finally allowed to execute.
This means that your client
should be prepared to subscribe
to all necessary events
in a single call to es_subscribe.
If you split your events
across multiple calls,
third-party applications
may begin executing
before the additional subscriptions
are in place
and your client can miss events.
It's also important to note
that there is a deadline enforced
by EndpointSecurity subsystem
by which all early boot clients
must signal readiness.
Once the deadline expires,
all third-party executions
are automatically allowed to continue.
Your extensions should be careful
not to perform long initialization steps
before making a subscription
to prevent missing events.
We do not consider the deadline value
to be API
and is subject to change over time,
but we believe the value is suitable for
your products to come up and become ready
without having a large impact
on end users.
Those of you who have already worked
with the EndpointSecurity framework
have likely noticed
that we do not provide events
related to networking operations.
This is intentional
as these are better covered
by the NetworkExtension framework.
There's a small exception
related to UNIX domain sockets,
and ES does provide events for these.
You should also know
that it's possible to use
both the EndpointSecurity
and NetworkExtension frameworks
from a single combined system extension.
For these products,
you should use the system extension APIs
and install flow as you normally would
for extensions
that are of a single extension type.
Additionally, it is safe to combine keys
in your extension's info.plist
that are specific to either network
extensions or EndpointSecurity extensions
and the system will take care
of applying those values as appropriate.
ES provides messages to clients in the
same order as they occurred on the system.
For example, if a client subscribes
to FORK and EXEC events,
in the common scenario,
when a new process is spawned,
the client's handler block
will always receive the fork event
before the corresponding exec.
Also note that message ordering applies to
subscriptions on an individual ES client.
If your application
creates multiple ES clients
and splits subscriptions across them,
the order of the events are only sequenced
relative to the subscriptions
for each ES client.
If desired,
you can reconstruct global ordering
by using the message generation time
contained in the message struct.
Messages are delivered to ES clients
one at a time,
and messages are delivered only when
the ES client's event handler block
returns from processing
the previous message.
The message structure received
by the handler block has a lifetime
that is only guaranteed to be valid
as long as the invocation
of the handler block for that message.
Once you return from the block, you
should not continue to access the message
as doing so will result
in undefined behavior.
If you need to extend
the lifetime of the message,
as we needed to do in the demo,
you can do so using
the es_copy_message API.
This will return a handle to the message
that will live until the corresponding
es_free_message API is called.
An important feature this implies
is that AUTH events
do not necessarily need to be replied to
before the handler block returns.
It also means that AUTH events
need not necessarily be responded to
in the same order
as presented to the ES client.
It might be important for your application
to first inspect future messages
in order to make a decision
on a previous message.
In this case, the ES application
can first copy the message
and return from the handler block
to begin inspecting additional messages,
and then later reply to that copied
message with the appropriate response.
Don't forget to finally free the message
when it's no longer needed.
If you need to do some sort
of asynchronous message processing,
such as using
an asynchronous dispatch queue,
be sure you initialize the dispatch queue
with a quality-of-service class
appropriate for your application.
This will likely be dependent
on many factors,
such as whether or not you subscribe
to AUTH events, expected event volume
or how much CPU or system resources
you wish to consume.
Next, we wanted to share some various tips
that we think will help you develop
great EndpointSecurity-based products.
One field you might've noticed
in the message structure
is the is_es_client Boolean member.
ES applications are not able
to authorize their own actions
as these introspective events
are automatically allowed.
However, there might be
multiple ES clients on a system,
and ES clients do have the ability to
authorize the actions of other ES clients.
For both AUTH and NOTIFY messages,
the is_es_client field
will be set to "true"
if the instigating process contain
the EndpointSecurity client entitlement.
ES client should inspect this field
and take appropriate action
to ensure they don't inappropriately
interfere with those clients' actions
or perform actions
that could create feedback loops.
Path muting is a fantastic way
to prevent your client
from being inundated with messages.
It also helps keep
the overall system more performant
by reducing the number of messages
that need to be processed or authorized.
For instance,
if your client isn't concerned
about the Spotlight service
on Mac OS indexing files,
muting the appropriate indexing processes
can greatly reduce the number
of messages received for some event types.
Applications
that take advantage of the cache
should be aware that caching should
be used for performance purposes only,
and caching should never be used
for policy.
This is because, as stated earlier,
cache entries may expire at any time.
For example, if your application decides
to deny a process from opening any files
and allows the response to be cached,
you should then not mute the process.
Consider what happens if the cache entry
is later invalidated or otherwise removed.
If that process attempts to reopen files,
no AUTH events will be generated
because your ES client
has muted the process
and those open operations
would be automatically allowed.
The next tip is to be careful
when debugging your ES application
when subscribed to AUTH events.
There is no way to disable
or otherwise extend the response deadline.
If an AUTH event is enqueued
while your application hits a break point,
you're still required to respond
before the deadline,
or your process will be terminated
as per the normal rules.
Finally, it is possible
for EndpointSecurity to drop messages
without delivering them to clients
if the message queue is full.
Client can determine if this has happened
by inspecting the sequence number field
in the message structure.
This is a per-client
and per-event-type sequence number
so you can determine exactly how many
of each event type may have been missed.
Clients that see higher drop rates
are encouraged to take advantage
of more advanced
EndpointSecurity API usage patterns
such as muting, asynchronous processing
and splitting subscriptions
across multiple ES clients.
This year we're announcing that
the audit subsystem is being deprecated.
This mainly refers to functionality
related to audit events
such as events written
to audit trail files,
typically those found
in the /var/audit directory,
as well as events
sent to the Auditpipe pseudo-device
for applications that wanted
a live event stream.
This does not apply to things
like audit tokens and audit sessions,
which will continue to be
a core part of the system.
Products that rely on audit events
should migrate
to using the EndpointSecurity framework.
So what's new in macOS Big Sur?
First up, there is some new
event-specific API for the EXEC event.
ES now provides the list of
file descriptors and file descriptor types
that a newly executing process
will begin with.
We also provide unique identifiers
specifically for Pipe file descriptors
that will allow you to track how multiple
processes might be communicating
via the Pipe interprocess
communication mechanism.
Due to performance limitations,
not all file descriptors may be provided.
The main focus was for standard in,
standard out and standard err descriptors,
but we also provide several more
if they exist,
and we expose to clients
if there are additional descriptors
we may not have enumerated.
Regarding performance, we think early
adopters of EndpointSecurity framework
will have a lot to look forward to
in macOS Big Sur.
We've rewritten many of our data
structures to reduce memory allocations
and increase event throughput.
We've tuned the caches
to eliminate invalidation bottlenecks
and improved
our overall memory performance.
Combined, these enhancements have led
to better system performance
and fewer drops.
We think this will provide
much better performance characteristics
for your EndpointSecurity products
as well.
There were also several new event types
that were added in macOS Big Sur.
Some of these are additional AUTH variants
for previously existing NOTIFY events
and some are brand new.
I wanted to call out a couple here.
First, we added the trace event
that was widely requested.
This will notify your client
when a process is being debugged.
Second, we're excited to introduce
the CS_INVALIDATED event.
As many of you know,
as a signed process executes,
the kernel is constantly validating
that the code it pages in
matches the individual page hashes
of that binary.
If a mismatch is found, the process has
its code signing flags updated
to clear the CS_VALID bit.
Previously, ES clients
had to wait for future messages
and inspect the code signing flags
of the instigating process
to determine if it went invalid.
However, with this event,
clients can get an immediate notification.
One thing to note, binaries that use
hardened run-time features,
such as those that have
the CS_KILL code signing flag set,
will still automatically be terminated
by the system
if a hash mismatch is encountered.
So, where do you go from here?
First, you can use the top link shown
to begin the process of requesting the
restricted EndpointSecurity entitlement.
Next, you can begin reviewing
the official EndpointSecurity
and System Extension API documentation
on the Apple developer website.
I want to also encourage you to carefully read the
EndpointSecurity header docs in the SDK.
We've added a lot of comments and detail
that may not be on the websites
that we think answers common questions
and will help you build great products.
Lastly, we'll be making sample code
available largely based on today's demos
to help you get started working
with the EndpointSecurity framework.
With that, thanks for joining us, and we
look forward to seeing what you build.
And enjoy WWDC 2020.