Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Michael Rojas,
and I work on the Shortcuts team.
Today, we're going to talk about
how you can feature your app's shortcuts
with Wind Down,
which is part of our new Sleep experience.
First, we'll go over how the new Wind Down
experience works with shortcuts.
Then we'll explain
how you can use some new APIs
to integrate the actions from your app
with Wind Down.
And finally, we'll go over
how to use some existing APIs
to make sure it's super easy
for people to add your action
when they set up and personalize
their Wind Down experience.
So let's dive in.
So, what is Wind Down?
At its core, we built Wind Down
to help you meet your sleep goals.
Sometimes that means focusing
on the things that will relax you
or give you some space
and mindfulness after a long day.
For some of you,
it might mean getting a heads-up
on what is most important for tomorrow
before going to bed.
We built a way to quickly get
to your favorite things in Wind Down mode,
and it's called "Wind Down Shortcuts."
Here are some Wind Down Shortcuts
that I can run with just a couple of taps.
For example, I have a shortcut
from Ten Percent Happier
that starts a sleep meditation.
I also have a custom Sleepy Time shortcut
that plays relaxing music
and adds an entry to my night journal.
And I have a shortcut
to set my "Relax" home scene
that dims all of my lights.
You can create
your own Wind Down Shortcuts
in the Health app's new sleep setup flow.
During this setup flow,
you'll be given the option
to add shortcuts you want to see
on the lock screen during Wind Down.
Let's take a look
at how you can add a shortcut.
After tapping on "Set Up Shortcuts,"
you can choose from the list
of suggested shortcuts shown here.
I'm getting a suggestion
to open Day One for journaling
and some meditation apps for mindfulness.
I'm going to select Ten Percent Happier.
As you can see, this shortcut was added
to my list of Wind Down Shortcuts.
You can edit these or add more
straight from the Health app.
In addition, all of these shortcuts
can be accessed from the Shortcuts app
in a new Sleep Mode collection
that will appear once you've added
a Wind Down shortcut.
You can get any existing or new shortcut
to show up in the Sleep Mode collection
by simply flipping on
the "Show in Sleep Mode" switch
in the shortcut's detail view.
We've also built some new APIs
that allow you to feature shortcuts
from your app in the Wind Down setup flow
so they can be run
with just a few taps from the lock screen.
The main way your app can expose
its actions is through intents.
Your app can adopt
one of the built-in intents
such as INCreateNoteIntent
or define its own custom intents.
We have a great video about
how to choose the right Siri technology.
Make sure to check it out.
Once you've built out your intent,
you can take advantage of a new property
called shortcutAvailability.
Let's take a deeper look
at this new property.
We added a new property
called shortcutAvailability to INIntent,
which you can use to tell us
which of your app's actions
should appear in the Wind Down setup.
We also added the same property
on NSUserActivity,
if that's what you're using
to represent your action.
Now let's take a look
at the different options that you can set.
Here are the different
shortcut availability options.
These options match the categories
in the Wind Down setup flow.
For example, if you're a meditation app,
you might want to mark your
start meditation intent or user activity
with the mindfulness option.
This will allow your app's meditation
to quickly be accessed
from the lock screen when in Wind Down.
If you're an app that helps people
get ready for tomorrow,
such as a Notes app or Weather app,
you should use
the Prepare for Tomorrow option.
Here's what those categories
look like in code.
Now, let's take a look at an example.
This sample app,
which, naturally, we've named Bedtime,
helps people fall asleep
by playing soundscape stations
such as "Sleepy Dinosaur Sounds"
and soothing "Cooking White Noise."
Maybe not for everyone, but for me,
this sounds like a great candidate
for the "sleep music" option.
So let's go for it.
To get started,
I'm going to create my intent.
In this case,
I'm using the system INPlayMediaIntent
because that allows me
to start audio sessions.
Then I'm going to set the shortcut
availability options to sleepMusic.
Next, I'm going to wrap my intent
in an INShortcut.
Grab the shared property
on INVoiceShortcutCenter.
And finally,
I'm going to provide it to the system
by calling setShortcutSuggestions.
It's as easy as that.
Now my bedtime action
will show up in the Music section
when someone sets up
their Wind Down experience.
It's important to keep in mind
that not every action from your app
will actually help people
reach their sleep goals.
For example, starting yoga for relaxation
would be perfect
for the yoga and stretching category.
But starting a warm-up run
probably wouldn't be the best way
to get ready for bed.
So not a good candidate.
Likewise, it's easier to wind down
to a relaxing soundscape
than it is to a wake-up mix.
And clearly, starting a meditation
is better for getting a good night's sleep
than starting a meeting.
So you'll need to choose
only the right actions from your app,
and ultimately,
you'll be the best judge of that.
Just always keep
the user experience in mind.
What helps people fall asleep?
Now let's take a look
at what you need to do
once you've chosen
the right actions from your app.
There are two things you can do
to enable the system
to suggest your app's actions
during Wind Down setup.
First, as I mentioned earlier,
you can suggest shortcuts to the system
that you want to feature
by calling setShortcutSuggestions
on INVoiceShortcutCenter.
If your app's actions
change at some point,
make sure to set it again
so only the most relevant actions appear
in Wind Down setup.
Another thing you should do is donate
the intent or user activity to the system
when someone performs the action
in their normal, everyday use of the app.
This helps the system understand
what the most important actions are,
so we can do our best to surface them
prominently in Wind Down setup
and even in other places
like search and lock screen suggestions.
Now let's talk about how to decide
between suggesting and donating.
You should both suggest shortcuts
to the system and donate,
as they each have benefits.
One benefit of suggesting shortcuts
through INVoiceShortcutCenter
is that it will ensure
that these actions from your app
will be featured in Wind Down.
For example, I have an action
to play the soundscape of the day
that I always want to be easy to find,
so I'm going to set that as suggested.
Here's how to do that in code.
First, initialize the INPlayMediaIntent.
Next, make sure to set
the shortcut availability if it applies.
In this case, I'll set it to sleepMusic.
Don't forget to set
the suggested invocation phrase.
This will be the phrase
someone can say to Siri
to execute this action with their voice,
and it's also the phrase displayed
on the Wind Down screen
to describe the shortcut.
Then create a shortcut from the intent.
And finally, suggest the shortcut
on INVoiceShortcutCenter.
Now let's take a look at donating.
When an action is performed in your app,
such as playing a track,
you should donate that action
to the system
so it can learn
from the person's behavior.
Let's take a look at this in code.
To donate an intent
when actions are performed in your app,
you first initialize the intent.
Next, make sure to set
the shortcut availability.
Again, I'm going to make sure
to set the suggested invocation phrase,
this time to the name of the track.
Wrap it in an INInteraction.
And finally,
call donate on the interaction
to tell the system
that a track was played.
And to donate a user activity,
first initialize the user activity.
Make sure it's eligible for search
and also for prediction.
Set a title.
Set the suggested invocation phrase
and the shortcut availability.
And finally, set the view controller's
user activity property to donate it.
As you saw in the code samples just now,
you should be sure to set
the suggested invocation phrase
on your intent or user activity,
as this is what's used
for naming the shortcut from your app
and also what's displayed
on the lock screen during Wind Down.
A suggested invocation phrase
should be short and concise,
since it has to fit in the small screen
real estate on the lock screen
and should allow users to be able
to uniquely identify the shortcut
based on the name.
Let's take a look
at how to choose a good phrase.
For example, if you're a white-noise app
such as Bedtime,
a good phrase to use
would include the name of the track,
such as "Play Counting Sleepy Dinosaurs."
This name is descriptive enough to
stand out from your app's other actions,
while being short enough
to fit on the lock screen.
A phrase such as "Play sound"
is too generic
and doesn't have any information
about the actual sound,
making it hard to identify.
Make sure to also limit
the length of the phrase
by omitting unnecessary information
to avoid truncation in places
with limited space.
Now that you know how to choose
a great suggested invocation phrase,
let's see how to do this in code.
You can do this by simply setting the
suggested invocation phrase on the intent
before donating
or suggesting the shortcut.
As you can see, this phrase is displayed
on the lock screen during Wind Down
and is used to name the shortcut,
so it's important
to choose this carefully.
To wrap up, we talked about
the new Wind Down experience
and its integration with the Shortcuts app
and how you can use new APIs
to make it super easy
for actions from your app
to be a part of this experience.
Thank you for watching, everyone.