>> LISA JACKSON: Hi.
I'm Lisa Jackson and I
lead Environment, Policy,
and Social
Initiatives for Apple.
Thank you so much for
joining us for today's
WWDC conversation
on race in America.
I am so honored to be here
today and beyond excited
to be joined by my dear
friend and former cabinet
colleague, former Attorney
General of the United
States, Eric Holder.
Now, before we get
started, I want to say a
few things about Eric.
There's the obvious.
He was the very first
Black Attorney General of
the United States and one
of the longest serving
AGs, a tough job
in a tough town.
He came to the
administration with a
remarkable record as a
successful attorney both
in government and in
the private sector.
But the most notable
attribute I want to call
out is his unwavering
commitment to equal justice.
In fact, Time Magazine
noted this when they named
him to their list
of one hundred most
influential people.
And that's a big part
of what we're going to
talk about today.
So, Eric, welcome
to your first Dub-Dub.
Thanks for being here.
>> ERIC HOLDER: Well,
thanks for having me, Lisa.
It's always
good to see you.
>> LISA JACKSON: Now,
s we're talking about
justice now in a time
where we're surrounded
by gripping and
painful reminders that
the fight continues.
For many of us, this has
been a reality of our life.
But for others, this seems
to be a new realization.
So, what do you make
of what feels like an
all-time high in public
awareness around this
set of issues?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Well, you
know, I think we're in the
throes of a generational
racial awakening.
I think that these happen
every so often in American
history and I think
we're on the verge of
another one here.
What people saw in
Minneapolis with the
death, the killing of
George Floyd, coupled with
other videos that people
have seen, coupled with
just, I think, a general
unease about things racial
in the United States, I
think we've seen people
get into the streets,
express concerns not only
about what we see in our
criminal justice system,
but more generally about
the condition of people of
color in the
United States.
I think we are as I
said, at the beginning of
something that I think
ultimately is going to
lead to some
positive change.
I'm actually cautiously
optimistic about where
this movement is
going to take us.
>> LISA JACKSON: Wow.
That's great to hear
because there's definitely
a lot of energy out in the
streets and there's also
energy in places
across the country, in
boardrooms, in
companies, in schools.
In 2009, you famously
called this country a
nation of cowards for our
failure to talk openly
about racial issues.
And you took some
heat for that comment.
Now look at us.
So, how many people have
called to apologize?
>> ERIC HOLDER: I'm still
waiting by the phone to
get those apologies or you
know, some indication that
maybe I called something
right back in 2009.
The point of that speech
was, and it's still true,
I think, today, here in
the United States, we are
experts at avoiding
conversations about race
and in a lot of ways,
that's understandable.
These are painful, awkward
conversations but they're
necessary conversations.
If we want to get to a
better place when it comes
to racial things, we've
got to discuss our
history, we have to be
cognizant of what the
present is all about,
and we have to talk about
where we want to
go in the future.
Now, this means that
we have to ask tough
questions of one another.
We have to face some
hard historical truths.
But if we don't engage in
these conversations, we're
not going to make the kind
of progress that we want.
So, that was the
point of that speech.
I think the speech has
actually held up pretty
well and what I said back
then, you know, about
Americans being reluctant,
hesitant to talk about
racial things, I think is
unfortunately still true,
but I think those people
in the streets, those
people in the streets are
going to force this nation
into a very needed - a
very needed conversation.
>> LISA JACKSON: Something
we can no longer avoid and
that we shouldn't avoid.
>> ERIC HOLDER: I think
that's just, you know,
that's the beginning.
We have to have the
conversation but then we
have to use that
conversation and that
necessary interaction
to come up with concrete
steps to take us to that
better place, change
policies, put in place
measures that will
alleviate the unfairness,
the injustice that still
exists in this country.
>> LISA JACKSON: So, that's -
that's interesting.
Let's talk about policy
because I know you're an
expert on the
police system.
You were our nation's top
law enforcement official
and so much of your
career centered on law
enforcement at all levels.
How do you contextualize
the fight for justice with
the glaring injustices
we're seeing carried
out by police?
And what do you see from
a policy perspective about
moving forward?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Well,
firstly, I think people
need to understand that
you know, people find
racism in the criminal
justice system.
Well, that shouldn't
be shocking.
We are still a nation that
is dealing with racism
throughout our society.
And so, if you look at any
component of that society,
you would expect
to find racism.
Now, that's particularly
troublesome when it comes
to the criminal justice
system where property,
where life can be
taken by the state.
And so, you want to make
sure that we have as
neutral a system
as we possibly can.
I mean, there are concrete
steps that can be taken.
We need to, you
know, ban chokeholds.
We need to have
better training.
We need to be better
in our selection of who
serves as police officers.
We can investigate
police departments.
All of those things are
important, extremely
important, but we've
really got to deal with
those larger societal
issues if we want to move
our criminal justice
system to a better place.
And that gets back, again,
to facing our history and
dealing with these larger
issues, the fact that we
don't have an educational
system that works for
everybody in this country,
that fair employment is
not necessarily something
that everybody enjoys
here, that housing in the
United States of America
is not necessarily made
available to everybody on
an equal basis.
You have to deal with
these core issues in
addition to dealing with
those things that are
manifest in the criminal
justice system if we want
to get to that
better place.
>> LISA JACKSON: To these
systemic issues, the ones
that are sort of embedded
in how we run and how we
live our daily lives.
>> ERIC HOLDER: Exactly.
I mean, it's - you can't
divorce the criminal
justice system from the
society that it is apart of.
And you know, this sounds
like a daunting task, you
know, talking about
systemic changes of things
that have been in place
for hundreds of years, but
at the end of the day,
we're talking about
manmade problems that are
susceptible to manmade and
womanmade solutions.
And that's what makes
me relatively, you know,
relatively confident here.
We've got this
new awakening.
We've got people
in the streets.
We have a new level of
civic engagement, a new
level of interest, a new
willingness, I think, to
confront those
hard issues.
If we can maintain this,
this moment that we have
can be turned
into a movement.
So, that's what I
think can be done.
I think it's going to
probably be led by young
people as social change
in the past has tended to
be as well.
So, as I said, I'm cautiously -
cautiously optimistic.
>> LISA JACKSON: Now, you
know, Apple just announced
our new Racial Equity
and Justice Initiative.
So, at the heart of it is
Apple using our platforms,
our voice, our resources
to challenge systemic racism.
I know a lot of times,
inequalities are hidden
in the system.
They're not always
directly able to be seen.
Can you share some
examples of how this has
shown up maybe in your own
life or in your career,
the inequities
you've seen?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Well, as
an African American man in
the United States of
America, you know, we all
have stories, you
know, that we can tell.
I remember going to run
to a movie in Georgetown
which is a neighborhood
in Washington, D.C., very rich
neighborhood, a predominantly
white neighborhood.
It was evening, dark, so
I was running to a movie
along with my cousin.
Stopped by the police
because they saw two Black
men running in a white
neighborhood and assumed
that something must
have gone wrong here.
It must be something
inappropriate.
Stopped us, put the
spotlight on us, asked us
what were we doing.
I said well, you know,
going to see a movie.
What they didn't
understand, the police
officer didn't understand
is that they had stopped
my cousin, a Vietnam
veteran and me.
At the time, I was a
federal prosecutor.
I was an employee of the
United States Department
of Justice who worked with
police officers and FBI agents.
But they didn't see that.
They just saw two Black guys
and so you know, a story.
And you know, my story is
not different than others
that - other Black men -
that other Black men can share.
So, that's, you know, a
very visible, personal thing.
But then there are
systemic things that tend
to be a little
more hidden.
When you look at the
ways in which people are
refused mortgages - red
lining is what we call it
in the United States.
You know, areas
are forbidden.
Certain areas are
forbidden for people of
color to locate in.
So, you go to a bank, you
fill out an application,
and your application
is rejected.
You don't really
know why but it's a
result of discrimination.
We've brought lawsuits
against banks when I was
the Attorney General to stop,
you know, to stop that practice.
If you look at the Fortune
500, if you look at law
firms, people of color are
simply not represented to
the degree that you
would expect as leaders
of those organizations.
And these are people who
are, you know, there are
significant numbers of
people of color who are
qualified, who should have
opportunities to lead, but
they simply don't get
those opportunities and as
a result, we have again,
these silent barriers,
these silent glass
ceilings that keep people
away from positions of
leadership that they
otherwise should have.
>> LISA JACKSON: Yeah.
When I'm explaining it to
people, I sometimes remind
them of something I'm
sure you heard from your
parents, which is my
mother and father used to
say, you have to be three
times as good to get you
know, a third as much.
So, I think, you know,
this idea of striving.
We're not afraid of doing
the work but if the system
is stacked against you,
it leads to frustration.
It leads to anger.
>> ERIC HOLDER: Yeah.
You know, it's interesting
because I've heard certain
people say it's an
exhausting thing to be an
African American and
have to deal with these
stereotypes, to deal with
the prejudice, to deal
with the discrimination.
And I thought to
myself, you know what?
It really isn't exhausting
because we train for this
from the day that
we leave the womb.
It's something that
on a day to day basis,
we get used to.
It's something that we -
it's almost like training
for a marathon. You know?
Day after day after day,
you have to put up with this.
You have to figure
out ways in which you
deal with it.
And after a while,
it becomes almost unconscious.
It's just kind of the way
you think that you have to
lead your life.
But you know, if you're
a person of color and you
can imagine a world where
you wouldn't have to deal
with all of those things,
boy, it would be a much
better existence.
And I think that hidden -
that hidden thing that we
have to deal with really
does have a pernicious
effect both on our psyche
and I think research
shows, on our
bodies as well.
High levels of tension
that leads to all kinds of
health problems.
But again, it's not
something that you're
conscious of on a day to
day basis because you deal
with it all the time
and you just accept it,
unfortunately, for the
way life has to be.
And that - that
has to change.
>> LISA JACKSON: You know,
I'm going to change the
subject a little bit.
I'm going to let that sit
there for a second but
then I'm going to change
the subject just a bit.
I was thinking back on
the drive this morning, to
inauguration day in 2009.
You and I, we were next
to each other with our
spouses that morning.
The weight of history,
the pageant of it all.
We were both the first
Black heads of our
respective
cabinet agencies.
I am immensely
proud of that.
I always say I was
the first Black EPA
Administrator for the
first Black president.
But it says something
about our country and our
progress or lack thereof.
Is it something you think
about and you know, how
does that hit you?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Yeah.
I mean, it's
certainly something that
I thought about then.
It's certainly something
I reflect on now.
It's clear.
I wasn't the first Black
lawyer who was qualified
to be Attorney General
of the United States.
I mean, I'm very grateful
for the fact that I was
given that opportunity.
I hope I did a good job.
You know, there's kind of
a dual pressure that you
feel being the first.
You don't want to
disappoint people who have
sacrificed and supported
you and made it possible
for you to become the
first head of the EPA, the
first head of the
Justice Department.
People sacrificed.
People died.
People committed
themselves so that other -
next generations would
have opportunities to
which they were denied.
And so, there's
that pressure.
Then there's also that
pressure that you want to
make sure that you perform
for the larger world and
so that the stereotypes of
lack of ability, of lack
of performance, you dispel
those and you feel that
pressure as well.
You know, it's - it's a
lot of this stuff is about
pressure, as I
talked about before.
But again, you know, given
those opportunities, I
think I felt and I'm sure
you felt a real duty to
perform as best we could,
to move the needle, to
open the doors for people
who would come - who would
come after us.
You know, it was great to
serve with you, to serve
with President Obama.
I remember that day in
2009 and the hope that I
felt and I think the hope
that the nation felt.
I think actually, the
hope that the world felt.
And I think, you know, we
had a good eight-year run.
There have been some
reversals since that
period of time but I think
as I said, the United
States, and I think the
world, is really on the
verge of a new era,
a new and better era.
>> LISA JACKSON: One thing
we worked on together was
environmental racism or
to fight environmental
racism, to bring about
environmental justice.
And you know, if we're
talking, environment is
going to come up.
We know that
communities of color are
disproportionately
impacted by a range of
environmental ills,
whether it's climate
change, air quality, water
quality, drinking water
quality, land use
decisions about what land
we are even able to - to
consider developing in
terms of housing
or schools.
Is there space for an
issue like that in the
conversations that we're
having in this moment?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Oh,
there's not only
space for that.
That is a necessary part
of the conversation.
We're really talking about
life and death issues there.
I mean, we can put in
place all kinds of new
structures, change
attitudes, make
opportunities available,
but you need to have
people live and live in a
way that enables them to
use the God-given
talents that they have.
I mean, we have seen, you
know, the negative impacts
of environmental racism
shortening lives,
negatively impacting
lives, curtailing peoples'
ability to reach all that
they are capable of doing.
Environmental racism is
something that I think for
too long has not
been front and center
and needs to be.
I mean, it has to be
because you're talking
about you know, the way
in which a society treats,
you know, its people.
And locating things next
to communities of color
that are going to cause
high rates of cancer, high
rates of asthma, you know,
the kinds of things that
curtail, again,
peoples' abilities.
These are the kinds of
things that people in
government have to stop,
that societies have to say
this is unacceptable, and
we have to be, I think,
more conscious of our
environment and the impact
that environment has
on all of our people.
>> LISA JACKSON: So agree.
I even like to point out
to younger people, even
the roads we're driving
on oftentimes cut a swath
right through the heart of
Black prosperity and the
Black community.
I grew up in New Orleans
where Claiborne Avenue
became an
underpass, right?
And it has a huge impact.
So, New Orleans.
I'm also going to
talk about music.
It is Black Music Month.
I know music is in
your blood as well.
We just celebrated
Friday, Juneteenth.
We talked about Black
music as the soundtrack
for protest and you're
no stranger to protests.
You were even on the
ground with activists in
Ferguson, Missouri.
What has been the
soundtrack of your
struggles through
the years?
And follow-up question;
what's the music that's
giving you life right now?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Well, when
I think about protests and
music that I like,
there is one album.
What's Going On,
Marvin Gaye, 1971-1972.
It was a great album then.
I think it's the greatest
album that's ever been made.
With, you know, all due
respect to the Beatles and
other artists.
It was great back in the
early 70's and it still
resonates in the
21st Century.
You know, What's Going On.
You listen to Marvin sing
in that song, over the
course of that whole
album, you know, both sides.
It's - he talks about
the problems that he
confronted, his brother
confronted in Vietnam, but
it speaks also to
issues that we have here
in the 21st Century.
You know, and so, I
still listen to that.
I still love that.
But now, you know,
it's interesting.
You know, what am
I listening to now?
I mean, 21st Century, this
is a turbulent time and I
look for peace in my music
and so I've gone back.
I'm kind of hanging
out in the 70's.
So, Marvin Gaye, Luther
Vandross, Aretha Franklin,
Earth, Wind, and
Fire, the Stylistics.
All - this is the
music of my youth.
A turbulent time but a
time that we got through,
a time that gives me hope,
makes me think that you
know, as turbulent as the
late 60's and early 70's
were, we got through it
and we made a better America.
We have turbulent times
now in the early part of
the 21st Century and again,
I'm cautiously optimistic.
I think we'll get through
it again and music helps
me have that optimism.
>> LISA JACKSON:
Yeah. Me too.
I'm going to bump Living
Just Enough for the City
up on that playlist too.
I always - Innervisions.
I think that's the reason
I actually became an
environmentalist,
listening to the story of
this brother getting off
the bus in New York and
what happened to him, you
know, in those decades after.
>> ERIC HOLDER: If you
look at What's Going On,
you've got to remember
Mercy, Mercy Me, the Ecology.
I mean, Marvin covered
everything, you know?
He covered protests,
demonstrations, Vietnam,
the Ecology.
It's a - it's
a masterpiece.
>> LISA JACKSON:
It is. It is.
Alright, let me take it
to the tech community.
This is a wonderful
audience listening to us,
dynamic, talented
developers who - who are
interested in this fight,
interested in the fight
for change, and I've heard
from so many people across
Apple, throughout our
network, who are looking
for ways to help.
What are some ways that
tech and developers, app
developers specifically,
can help tackle racism in
the work that
they do every day?
>> ERIC HOLDER: Well,
tell you, you know, this
is an unbelievably
creative community and I
think using the skills
that you have to - to
aggregate, to massage, to
work with data and then to
share information, I think
that's - I mean, that's
the core of what it is
that developers do, I
think, at their best, you
know, simplifying things,
making things accessible
to people around the world.
So, I would say that you
know, I am not as creative
nor technically proficient
as people are in this
audience, but using those
- those skills, those
really special skills to
come up with ways in which
you make available to
people the possibilities
that they have,
opportunities with regard
to how they can make
their lives better,
opportunities in which
they can you know, monitor
things that are being done
in their societies, ways
in which the information
can be shared across borders.
This is all the kinds of
stuff that you all do so
extremely well.
I would ask you to think,
you know, about maybe
turning your focus from
the things that are more
traditionally have been
expected of you and think
about new ways that you
can look at this, this
other frontier, this
racial frontier that is
not only in the United
States but in other
countries as well, and
think about ways in which
you can focus that
creativity, those skills
on this problem of
race and ethnic strife.
What are the things that
you can do there that can
alleviate those problems?
I'm really confident.
Again, if this community
focuses on those issues,
coupled with great
companies like Apple, you
all could have a really
meaningful impact for the
good on the issues that
we have been discussing.
>> LISA JACKSON: Alright.
We will take that.
Eric, it is always such an
honor to talk to you, such
time well spent,
so much to take away from
our time together.
I just want to thank you
so much for joining us,
for all you do, for all
you've been in service to
equality to our community.
Just huge thank you.
And thanks to all of
you for tuning in.
Enjoy the rest of Dub-Dub.