Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to
Explore Numerical Computing in Swift.
My name is Tim Kientzle.
I'm with the Swift Runtime team,
and I'd like to talk to you
about recent improvements
to floating-point numerics support
in Swift.
I'll start by introducing
the Swift Numerics package.
Among other features,
this package includes
a protocol called "Real"
and a fully-functional
Complex number type.
Then I'll describe the new
high-performance Float16 type
that we've added to the Swift Core
language and standard libraries.
Let's start by looking at
the Numerics package as a whole.
The Swift Numerics package
is an open-source Swift development effort
hosted on GitHub.com.
It's designed to make it easy
to implement numeric algorithms
that work with any standard
floating-point type.
It does this by making
the standard floating-point types
usable with Swift's generic
programming facilities.
To see how this works, let's assume
you're working on some project
where you discover you need to use
the common logit or log-odds function
from probability theory.
You start by defining a logit function
that takes and returns a Double.
To implement this function,
you import the log and log1p
functions from the Darwin module.
This code works,
but there's one small wrinkle.
This is written to only support Double.
Some day you might want to
use it with Float or maybe Float80.
With a one-liner like this,
it's no big deal
to just make another copy of it,
but what if a new floating-point type
gets added in the future?
How do you handle types like Float80
that are only available
on certain platforms?
And of course, if this function
were hundreds of lines,
then duplication would create problems.
Someone might correct a bug in one copy
but fail to correctly edit the other copy.
This could get to be quite a mess.
So let's instead try to define logit
as a generic function
that can work with
any floating-point type.
Here's a reasonable first attempt.
Unfortunately, this won't compile.
The problem is
that we've told the compiler
that this function works for any type.
But of course the log and log1p
functions aren't defined for every type.
They only make sense
for a handful of floating-point types.
So we need some way
to constrain the type T
to only the types
that are actual floating-point types
with actual log functions available.
Instead, let's import the Numerics module.
By importing the Numerics module,
we get access to the Real protocol,
which provides all the necessary support
for this kind of programming.
Using that,
we can define our logit function
so it works for any fully-functional
floating-point type.
We also need to use the generic forms
of log and logonePlus
that are exposed by the Numerics module.
This implementation of logit works
for every standard floating-point type.
If new floating-point types
get added in the future,
this code will support them
without requiring any changes.
This even works for Float80,
on the platforms that support Float80,
without you having to figure out
the magic conditionals.
The key to this is the Real protocol.
Let's take a closer look at that.
Types that conform to the Real protocol
support all the standard
floating-point capabilities.
Real does this
by combining several other protocols,
as you can see in the definition here.
This definition, by the way,
is exactly the one that you can see
in the Numerics source code.
The FloatingPoint protocol
from the standard library
is one key component here.
Two other protocols,
AlgebraicField and RealFunctions,
are new protocols
defined by the Numerics package.
But before I dive into details of those,
I want to reiterate
that the Real protocol
is the one you should actually use.
I'm going to describe how these
other protocols fit together
because I think it helps
to better understand
the range of capabilities
that Real brings to the table.
And of course, if you ever need
to define a new numeric type,
you'll probably want to decompose
your implementation along these lines.
But for most of you, the Real protocol is
the only one you'll routinely work with.
With that in mind,
let's review the protocols
that are already present
in the Swift standard library.
The Swift standard library
defines a lot of protocols
that apply to the standard
floating-point types.
This diagram shows just a few
of the more important ones.
For this talk,
I'm only interested in three of these:
AdditiveArithmetic, SignedNumeric
and FloatingPoint.
AdditiveArithmetic applies to types
that support addition and subtraction.
This covers almost anything
that can reasonably claim
to be some form of number
and corresponds nicely
to what mathematicians refer to
as an "algebraic group."
SignedNumeric extends that
with a concept of multiplication.
Finally, FloatingPoint
adds various notions
that are needed for any practical computer
floating-point number implementation,
including comparison functions,
a way to decompose numbers
into exponent and significand,
as well as useful constants,
like the largest and smallest value,
infinity, pi and so on.
The Numerics package
builds on these core concepts.
The first protocol here augments
SignedNumeric with a notion of division.
Mathematicians refer to number systems
that support all four basic operations
as "algebraic fields",
which inspired the name.
The ElementaryFunctions protocol
specifies a large collection
of common floating-point functions,
including core trig functions,
as well as logarithms,
exponentials, roots and powers.
The RealFunctions protocol
extends this even further
with many less-used functions,
such as the gamma and error functions,
as well as variations
of the common trig functions.
The Real protocol combines all of these
into a single unifying concept
that neatly defines
the common capabilities
of the standard floating-point types.
Any type that conforms to the Real
protocol is a floating-point type...
that supports all
the standard arithmetic operations...
and has a full repertoire
of common mathematical functions...
which is how the Numerics package
makes the standard floating-point types
more usable than ever.
Fundamentally, the Real protocol
is a simple concept
that is very powerful in practice.
It lets you use generic
programming techniques
to define your floating-point code
in a way that automatically supports
every standard floating-point type.
And it's built on top of
a set of interlocking protocols
that should make it easy to define
new numeric types.
Now, let us turn to the complex number
support provided by the Numerics package.
The Complex type
in the Swift Numerics package
is a fully-featured implementation
of a standard complex number type.
To use it, just import
the Numerics package into your program.
Because the Complex type
is generic over the Real protocol,
it works for any floating-point type.
In this example, the constants
1.0 and 2.0 default to Double,
so "Z" here is a Complex Double.
As always, Swift infers the type for you
so you generally
can just omit the type annotation.
The Complex number type
is useful in itself,
but it's also a great example
of how the Real protocol
enables generic numeric programming.
The basic type is defined a lot like this.
A complex number has both real
and imaginary components
and a way to create new complex numbers
from those components.
Those components can be any NumberType
that conforms to the Real protocol.
To make complex numbers fully functional,
we need to define
the standard arithmetic operations.
Here are the basic addition, subtraction
and multiplication operations
as required by the SignedNumeric protocol
we discussed a little while ago.
Complex numbers are often
expressed in polar coordinates--
that is, in terms of a length
and a phase angle.
Because the real and imaginary components
are floating-point types
that conform to the Real protocol,
we automatically get everything we need
to expose those length
and phase properties.
The length is defined in terms
of the standard hypotenuse function,
the phase in terms of
the standard arctangent function.
Other common trig functions
let us create new complex numbers
with a specified length and phase.
This complex type is a plain struct
holding two floating-point values.
As a result, its memory layout
precisely matches
that of the C and C++
complex number types.
So complex numbers in memory look
exactly the same in all three languages.
You can create a buffer
full of complex numbers in Swift
and pass a pointer
to that buffer to a C or C++ library
that expects the corresponding
C or C++ complex type.
To see how this works,
let's look at an example
using Accelerate's implementation
of the Basic Linear Algebra Subroutines.
The first part of this example
just creates an array
of 100 Complex Double values
using a common Swift idiom.
Now we can use the ampersand operator
to pass a pointer to this array
directly into the Accelerate API.
This particular function accepts
an array of Complex Doubles,
computes the Euclidean 2-norm
and returns a Double.
Especially when
porting code from C or C++,
you may need to be careful
when dealing with infinity or NaN values.
There have been different styles
over the years for how these should work.
It's not surprising that C and C++
use the same style as each other.
After all, their complex number support
was standardized at about the same time.
Swift however uses
a slightly different convention
that is simpler
and significantly more performant.
To see the difference,
here's a basic benchmark program
that just performs a bunch
of complex multiplications and divisions.
With this program,
multiplication is about 1.3 times
faster in Swift than in C.
Division is almost 4 times faster.
And if you can arrange your work
so that you are dividing by a constant,
then you'll find that division in Swift
can be over 10 times faster.
I hope the previous sections
have given you a taste
of what we're trying to accomplish
with the Swift Numerics package.
This is a work in progress.
The package is being developed
as a community effort on GitHub,
and there are active discussions
about where to take it in the future.
New features are added regularly.
This has recently included
improved handling of integer powers
and some new tools
for dealing with approximate equality.
There are also active discussions
about how to extend the library
with support for
arbitrary-precision integers,
shaped arrays and decimal floating-point.
If you would like to participate, please
check out the project on GitHub.com
or join the discussion
in the Swift Forums.
Now, let's turn to the core Swift language
and standard library
and the new Float16 data type.
Float16 is an IEEE 754 standard
floating-point format
that is new to Swift.
It's already available in Swift
on ARM-based platforms,
and we're working with Intel to finalize
the correct calling convention
before we land this on x86.
Float16 is in every way a standard
and fully-supported floating-point type.
It conforms to the core protocols
from the standard library,
including things like SIMDScalar.
It conforms to the Real protocol
that I discussed earlier in this talk.
As you recall, this means that it supports
all of the standard floating-point
operations and functions.
So our earlier diagram that shows
the types that conform to Real
now has a fourth type.
In the months
since Swift Numerics was released,
there are already a number
of projects using the Real protocol
to write algorithms that work
across all standard floating-point types.
Without any source code changes at all,
those projects already work with Float16.
Like any actual numeric format,
there are trade-offs to using Float16
instead of some other type.
Most of those trade-offs
relate simply to its size.
Since it's a smaller data type,
you can fit more of them
in a SIMD register or in a page of memory,
which directly translates
into improved performance.
However, as a smaller data type, it also
has a more limited precision and range.
Let's take a careful look at that.
As the name suggests,
a Float16 takes just 16 bits or two bytes,
as opposed to four bytes
for a single-precision float
or eight bytes
for a double-precision value.
The smallest value it can represent
is around 10 to the minus 8,
which is generally not a concern.
However, the maximum value
that a Float16 can represent
is a little more than 65,000.
This can be a problem
for many applications,
and it's something you should be
careful with when translating code
that was originally implemented
for Double or Float to work with Float16.
On the hardware side,
Float16 is already well-supported.
Apple GPUs have used this for a long time,
and Apple CPUs have direct support
beginning with A11 Bionic.
On older CPUs, we support Float16
by simulating the operations using Float.
The results are exactly the same,
only a little slower.
As I mentioned before, on hardware
that does fully support Float16,
you can fit twice as many values
into the same SIMD registers,
which generally translates
into a doubling of performance.
To see how that plays out in practice,
let's look at a simple benchmark
that compares a BNNS convolution
computed in single-precision Float,
where we get about 49 gigaflops,
to one computed with Float16,
which achieves 119 gigaflops,
even more than twice the performance.
This talk has discussed
the Swift Numerics package
and shown how the Real protocol
provides a way to write floating-point
algorithms generically
so they work with
all floating-point types.
I've also talked about a new complex type
that provides
full interoperability with C and C++.
And finally, I've introduced
the new Float16 type
that improves our support
for high-performance numerics.
To get involved, you can visit
the Swift Numerics project on GitHub,
take a look at the existing
issues and pull requests
to understand what work is ongoing
and contribute your own ideas
to the group.
You can also visit
the Swift Forums at forums.swift.org
and look in
the "Related Projects" category
to find discussion
specifically about Swift Numerics.
I appreciate you joining me
for this look at Swift Numerics,
and I hope you enjoy the conference.