Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to the session
on handling
the new Limited Photos Library.
My name's Matt Dickoff,
and together with my colleague,
Adam Swift,
we'll be walking you through
this new PhotoKit feature
that allows users to better control
the access that apps have
to their Photos Library.
We'll start with a feature overview
so you can familiarize yourself
with what this looks like in iOS 14.
Then, we'll cover
what new APIs are available
to determine if your app
has been put into this mode.
And finally, we'll discuss some UI changes
that you might need to make in your app.
So, first, let's go over
what Limited Photo Library means.
As a reference,
here's what full Photos Library access
looks like to your app.
In this scenario, your app has access
to nearly all of the assets
in the user's Photo Library
through PhotoKit APIs.
You app can make PhotoKit requests
to either write or read from the database.
In limited mode, we introduce this concept
of the user's limited library selection.
You can think of this as a filter
for the PhotoKit APIs that you call.
You will only be able
to fetch assets and resources
related to what the user has chosen
for you to have access to.
When a user modifies their selection,
your app will automatically be notified
so that it can update its UI
to reflect the user's actions.
It's important to note that
Limited Photo Library access
will affect all apps that use PhotoKit.
Even the apps that you've already shipped
will be able to be put into
this mode in iOS 14.
To demonstrate this,
let's look at an example app.
This demo will show what a user will see
when using a third-party app that hasn't
adopted any new APIs or functionality.
Upon first launch of a photos application,
the user will often be faced with a prompt
asking them to grant the app
access to their Photo Library.
The user now has an additional option
which says Select Photos.
After selecting this,
the user is presented
with the limited library management UI.
This is allowing the user
to individually select
what photos or videos the app
will have access to via PhotoKit.
Now, let's select some photos.
After tapping "Done,"
the app is back in the foreground.
As you can see, the app is only able
to fetch the assets selected by the user.
The app is still able
to see photo metadata,
such as whether it was favorited.
However,
this is limited to the user's selection.
So, if we turn the Favorites on for this,
we can see it's only the selected assets.
Now, you may be wondering
how a user would be able to modify
the selection of photos for this app.
The first way is by going to Settings,
where alongside the option to change
the overall access level this app has,
the user can manage their selection.
So if I add a new photo...
and go back to our app...
you'll see that it refreshed
its view of the library.
The second way is specific to apps
that haven't made any changes
to accommodate this new mode.
For these apps, like this one here,
once per app life cycle,
when they first fetch assets via PhotoKit,
the user will be prompted to either
keep their current selection or modify it.
Let me show you what that looks like.
This allows the user to modify
the selection within all apps
without app adoption.
Later on in the presentation,
I'll show you new APIs that you can adopt,
which will allow you
to take control over when and where
this management UI is presented from,
as well as suppressing
that prompt that comes up
the first time your app
calls PhotoKit APIs after launch.
Before we dive into the technical details,
I wanna first talk about
why we built this feature.
The primary motivation was to give users
more control over their data.
Over the years,
we've seen personal Photo Libraries
grow from tens to hundreds of thousands
of photos and videos.
In nearly all cases,
users do not want to give third parties
access to their entire library.
Given this big push for user control,
this is a great year to take a step back
and ask yourself if your app
even needs to ask the user
for access to their Photo Library at all.
For most apps, the answer is no.
Today, users see this prompt
way more often than they really need to.
Many of you don't need to request
this level of access
and could provide a simpler and better
experience for your users without it.
To accentuate this point,
let's look at some features
that can easily be built
without needing to request
access from the user.
Uploading a profile picture
is a prime example.
Often, this is the only
photo-related feature in an app.
Or maybe you support sending photos
in a message or social media post.
Or maybe your app supports
embedding photos
into a document that it creates.
All of these features can be built
very easily with the new PHPicker
without requiring
any Photo Library access.
PHPicker is a great replacement
for the UIImagePickerController
you may be familiar with.
It has multi-select and built-in search
and users will expect that your app will
be able to use features like I just showed
without ever granting your app
Photo Library access.
For more information on implementing
these workflows with the new PHPicker,
please see this session
that my colleagues put together.
I haven't talked about all the features
you possibly could build with PhotoKit,
so what is left?
The simple addition
of being able to save an image
then accounts
for a large percentage of apps.
If your app falls into this category,
you are now to explicitly ask the user
for add-only access
to their Photos Library.
In the API slides coming up,
we will show exactly how you can do that.
Of course, there are apps that provide
a very photocentric experience
that require full access.
For example, browsing apps, editing apps,
camera apps or data backup apps.
These types of apps
will need to do the most work
to handle limited library access.
Now I'm gonna hand
the presentation over to Adam,
who will walk you through
the new APIs we've introduced this year.
Adam?
Thanks, Matt.
As you just heard,
Limited Photos Library access
can be enabled by the user in every app
that requests access to the Photo Library.
So, as a developer,
we wanna help you provide
the best app experience for users
that choose to enable limited access.
First, I'm going to walk you through
the APIs you can use
to know if the user
has granted your application
limited photos access.
Then we'll look at what has changed
when requesting access.
After that,
I'll be handing it back to Matt
to talk about UI considerations
like how to present
the limited library management UI natively
and prevent the automatic prompt.
Let's start with a look at how you query
for authorization status.
We've added a new value
to the existing
PHAuthorizationStatus enumeration
to indicate that your app
is authorized for limited access,
and introduced a new enumeration
called PHAccessLevel.
This can be add-only or read/write.
These levels correspond
to the two different
photos usage privacy prompts
that you should be familiar with.
The authorization status query
and request APIs
have been updated to take an access level.
This means that now you can check
if your app is authorized for read/write
or just add-only access.
Limited library doesn't affect
add-only access,
so to check if the user
has granted limited access,
you need to pass
the read/write access level
and check for the limited
authorization status return value.
Let's look at
how you can do that in detail.
Since we want to know if the user
has authorized our app for limited access,
we'll need to specify
the read/write access level.
Then, we'll call
the new authorizationStatus API
for that access level.
And the last step is
to check the return value
for the new limited authorization status,
usually to set up your UI in a way
that works best in limited access mode.
Now, let's see how requesting access
is impacted by limited library.
When your application wants to access
Photo Library data,
we still recommend that you allow
a user action to drive that request.
Ideally, when some UI activity
initiated by the user
requires you to fetch photo data
or add to the camera roll,
calling the PhotoKit APIs
to perform that work
will trigger the request for access
and make it clear to the user
why your app is requesting access.
But there are some cases
where you want to control
the timing of that request.
And we've updated
the request authorization API
to support access level
and limited authorization status.
Let's take a look at a request example,
keeping in mind that
requesting authorization
only prompts the user
if the status isn't already determined.
Just like when querying the status,
you'll want to declare
the access level your application needs.
In this case again,
we are requesting read/write access.
Then, call to request authorization
for that access level from the user.
This will put up the system prompt
for Photo Library access.
After the user makes their choice,
in the call back to this function
you will be provided with
the authorization status value
that aligns with their response.
This is where you want to check
for the new authorization status,
"limited",
that indicates that the user
has granted your application
limited photos library access.
The old authorization status
and request APIs
are not limited-library
or access-level aware
and are marked for future deprecation.
It's important to note
that for compatibility reasons,
these APIs will not return
the new "limited" authorization status.
Instead, they will return "authorized"
even if the user has granted Limited
Photos Library access to your application.
Generally, you should expect PhotoKit APIs
to act the same whether your app
has full authorization
or limited access
to the user's Photo Library.
However, there are a few exceptions
that are intentional and worth noting.
When your app creates new assets,
they will automatically be included
as part of the user's selection
for the application.
User albums, however,
cannot be fetched, nor created.
If your application relies on being able
to create an app-specific album,
you will need to change
your app's behavior.
Also, there is no access
to cloud-shared assets or albums.
All right, with that in mind,
I'll hand it back to Matt
to talk about UI considerations
and how you can natively present
the selection UI in your app.
So now that you can determine
if your app is in limited library mode,
let's talk about what UI changes
you'll need to make.
First, I'll cover how you can present
the selection UI natively.
And second, I'll mention how you can stop
the automatic system prompt
from happening for your app
the first time that it does
PhotoKit API calls after launch.
Presenting the management UI
is as simple as calling
this new PHPhotoLibrary API
presentLimitedLibraryPicker,
passing in the view controller
you wanted to present from.
You should monitor any changes
that happen to the user's selection
through the existing
PHPhotoLibraryChangeObserver API.
By doing this, you will be robust
to changes that happen in this picker,
in system preferences
or existing scenarios,
such as asset deletions
that may have synced
through iCloud Photo Library.
You may want to tie the presentation
to a button or action within your app.
For example, in the demo app
I showed you in the beginning,
some sort of affordance
in the browsing experience
would be a good way to allow
the user to easily modify
their Photo Library selection
for your app.
As you can see here, we added
a button to the browsing experience
that pulls up
the limited library selection UI.
You can suppress
the automatic prompting from the system
by setting this key to yes
in your app's Info.plist.
This is found in the same place
where you set your Photos
usage description strings in Xcode.
This is represented by the Prevent
Limited Photos Access alert key.
This exact string will be
in an upcoming version of Xcode.
In summary, these are the steps
that you should go through
when updating your app to handle
the new limited library mode.
First, reconsider if your app needs
to use Photo Library access at all.
The new PHPicker improvements this year
are a great way to implement
many of your features.
Second, adopt the new authorization APIs
so you will know if your app
is in limited library mode.
Third, update your app designs
to give an affordance for users
to modify their limited library selection
in a way that makes sense
in the context of your app.
And finally, be sure to set
the Info.plist key in Xcode
so the system prompt
stops coming up for your app
the first time it makes
PhotoKit API calls after launch.
And that's everything
you need to know about
the new Limited Photos Library feature.
Thank you.