[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to
"Stacks, Grids and Outlines in SwiftUI."
I'm Cody, an engineer working on SwiftUI.
And later in this talk,
I'll be joined by my colleague Curt.
SwiftUI has a variety
of built-in layout primitives
for arranging collections of views
in horizontal and vertical sequences.
These primitives can be used on their own
to address basic layout needs,
or they can be combined together
to build out complex views
with custom behavior.
The new Notification Center in macOS
was implemented with SwiftUI,
and it serves as a great example
of this compositional process at work.
Simple Stacks and Grids work together
using hierarchy, alignment and spacing
to organize a lot of information,
and the result is both
beautiful and usable.
When developing your own apps,
I encourage you to think in similar terms.
SwiftUI's layout primitives
were designed with composition in mind.
Generally, when a simple type doesn't do
everything you need it to do,
the path forward involves combining it
with another simple type
that has complementary behavior.
In this talk, I'm going to cover
some new additions to SwiftUI's
family of layout primitives.
I'll start with a review
of the most basic types,
horizontal and vertical Stacks,
and introduce a new pair of types
for creating grid layouts
that grow lazily.
Then I'll look at a new feature
of the existing Lists type
that allows for the presentation
of hierarchical data.
And finally, Curt will do a deep dive
into Outlines and Forms
and show some techniques
for the progressive display
of user interface controls.
I'll begin with Stacks,
which are the simplest
layout primitives in SwiftUI.
But first, in order to talk about Stacks,
I need to talk about sandwiches.
If you caught
the "Introduction to SwiftUI" talk,
you'll know that my friend Jacob
has been hard at work
on an app for making sandwiches.
I fancy myself something
of a sandwich connoisseur,
and I thought it would be fun
to put together
a gallery view for Jacob's app
to showcase photos
of especially memorable lunches.
The data model I'm going to use
is pretty simple,
just an ID, a name, a star rating
and a heroImage for the gallery.
The view for displaying an individual
sandwich in the gallery is equally simple.
It displays a resizable heroImage.
And it adds an overlay
containing information about the sandwich.
The BannerView that overlays
each heroImage uses a VStack
to arrange the sandwich's title
and star rating indicator.
And the star rating is just
a horizontal stack of images.
My initial implementation
is pretty straightforward.
I'm presenting my gallery
using a vertical stack of sandwich views.
My sandwich list is going to grow
dynamically as I take more pictures,
so I need to include a ForEach view
that will enumerate every sandwich
and make a view for each one.
Also, Stacks don't scroll on their own,
so I need to wrap everything
in a ScrollView.
I'm pretty happy with this so far,
but as I go about loading
in my back catalog of sandwich photos,
I start to notice a problem.
The more photos my gallery
needs to display,
the longer it takes for the screen
to become responsive when presented.
What I want is a Lazy Stack
that builds itself out incrementally,
so that initially only the first
screenful of images need to be rendered.
The rest can be loaded on demand
as the user scrolls through the gallery.
We are introducing
two new SwiftUI stack types
that address this problem directly:
LazyVStack and LazyHStack.
Lazy Stacks are just like
their VStack and HStack counterparts,
except that they render their content
incrementally as it becomes visible.
This is perfect for my needs.
The view won't block the main thread
loading and measuring every single image
and the app's memory footprint
won't grow unnecessarily large.
All I need to do is replace
my VStack with a LazyVStack...
and now my gallery loads incrementally.
There's one other point
I want to make here.
If you recall from the definition
of "rating view,"
the vertical stack that defines
the gallery of HeroViews
isn't the only stack on screen here.
Each HeroView has its own horizontal stack
to lay out the star rating indicator
as well as a ZStack to overlay
the rating on top of the heroImage.
So, it's worth asking,
since I made my outer stack lazy,
should these stacks be lazy too?
In this case, the answer is no.
While I want the vertical stack
to be lazy,
specifically because it scrolls,
I don't want to spend the time
it takes to render everything up front
when most of the content
can't be seen without scrolling.
On the other hand, making the stacks
within a given HeroView lazy
doesn't actually confer any benefits.
The content is all visible at once
as soon as the view lands on screen.
So, everything has to be loaded at once,
regardless of the container's
default behavior.
As a rule, if you aren't sure
which type of stack to use,
use VStack or HStack.
Adopt Lazy Stacks as a way
to resolve performance bottlenecks
that you find after profiling
with Instruments.
Now I'd like to talk about
a new set of types, Lazy Grids.
Let's return to my sandwich gallery.
I'm liking how this looks on iPhone,
but how does it fare on a bigger screen?
Let's move it to an iPad and find out.
It's the same thing, just bigger.
Not exactly the look I'm going for.
With all this extra screen real estate,
what I really want is to get
more sandwiches on the screen.
If I could change this
from a single column of images
to a grid with multiple columns,
I'd be able to increase my overall
sandwich density quite a bit.
Sounds like a job for two new types
we're adding to SwiftUI's
family of layout primitives,
named LazyVGrid and LazyHGrid.
As the names imply,
these types build out grids of content
and are similar in use to Stacks.
Using a LazyVGrid, I can easily
implement a multi-column layout
to increase the sandwich density
of my view.
Let's take a look at how this works.
Here's the same Lazy Stack we saw earlier,
scaled up for iPad.
I'll update it to make it three columns
of sandwiches instead of one.
The main difference
from the earlier example
is my layout container.
I'm using a LazyVGrid
instead of a LazyVStack
and I'm passing in a collection
of values that tells SwiftUI
how to compute the width
of the columns in my grid.
More on that in a second.
Apart from the column descriptions,
I define my grid
just like I would define a stack,
by passing in a view builder
to generate the individual views
that comprise the grid.
To describe my grid's columns,
I create an array of GridItem values.
Each item specifies how
an individual column's width is computed.
Here, I'm defining three columns.
Grid items are flexible by default,
so this arrangement will fill the grid
with columns of equal width.
And here's the same thing
in landscape orientation.
The number of columns is the same,
they're just wider.
Grid layouts can also adapt
to the space available
to create a variable number of columns.
Here, for example,
I've declared an adaptive GridItem
which produces as many
equally wide columns as it can
while maintaining
a specified minimum column width.
It's great for landscape mode
where there's room for additional columns.
Adaptive grid items
are also great on macOS
where windows can be resized arbitrarily.
I'm really excited about the expressive
power of these new primitives.
The last topic I wanna cover
before handing off to Curt is Lists.
Lists are more than just
basic layout primitives.
They are interactive, with support
for selection management and scrolling.
List contents are always loaded lazily.
Now, I don't know about you,
but at this point, I've pretty much
had my fill of sandwiches.
Let's take a look at a cool new app that
Curt's been working on called "ShapeEdit."
ShapeEdit is a document-based app
that runs on macOS, iPadOS and iOS.
If we zoom in, we can see
the window sidebar view in ShapeEdit,
where we've used a List
to enumerate the shapes on the canvas.
We have an array of the graphics
currently on the canvas,
and we use our graphics array
to populate rows of content
in the sidebar,
producing a flat list of shapes.
Super cool.
I've been having a lot of fun
playing around with this app,
so much so that I was inspired
to add a feature
to collect shapes into groups.
Groups can also contain other groups,
so our flat list now needs to represent
an arbitrarily deep tree of elements.
We've added a new feature to Lists
that's perfect for this,
and I'm really excited to talk about it.
To turn my list into an outline,
I just need to tell the list
how to traverse the data tree.
I'll use a new initializer
to provide the children key path
on the graphic model,
and SwiftUI will do the rest.
With this one change, my sidebar now shows
the complete shape hierarchy.
Awesome.
As you might imagine,
there's a lot of interesting work
happening under the hood
to automate the creation of this outline.
I'll now hand off to Curt
who will show you how to use
the same tools List uses
to implement progressive disclosure
in your own UI.
Curt?
Thanks, Cody.
Converting a list to an outline
like that is super cool.
I'd like to dive into how that works.
I think the details are pretty great,
and you can use some of the pieces
in your own apps too.
Cody showed us how ShapeEdit
can display an outline of the graphics
in the sidebar
by passing the children key path
to the List.
I've been thinking it would be cool
to support multiple canvases in our app
and sketched a mock-up.
This mock-up uses a different section
for each canvas
and has a separate outline
inside each section.
Let's see how we can implement
a custom outline like this.
As Cody mentioned,
Lists are a high level structure
that help manage selection.
So, we keep that bit.
Then, inside the List,
we use a ForEach to iterate
over the canvases.
For each canvas,
we use Section to add a header
showing the name of the canvas.
And finally, the content of the Section
is a view new to SwiftUI:
an OutlineGroup.
An OutlineGroup is similar to a ForEach,
except that instead of iterating
over a flat collection,
OutlineGroup traverses
tree structure data.
Here, it takes an array of graphics
and the children key path.
The OutlineGroup generates an outline
where each item is a GraphicRow.
Let's switch to Xcode
and see how this works live.
Here's our outline of graphics
showing in preview.
Not only do SwiftUI outlines work
on macOS, they work on iOS too.
It's great to have powerful, built-in
outline capabilities on iPad and iPhone.
Let's go to Live Preview
and see how these groups work.
I can tap the disclosure indicators
to expand and collapse the groups.
Let's update this view
to show all the canvases.
First, we'll add an OutlineGroup
inside our List, wrapping this GraphicRow.
Then I'll move these first two arguments
from List to the OutlineGroup.
Notice how our preview hasn't changed yet.
An OutlineGroup directly inside a List
is the same as a List
that uses the children parameter.
Next, let's change our view
to use canvases instead of graphics.
I'll wrap this OutlineGroup in a ForEach
by Command clicking and choosing Repeat.
Then I'll replace the argument
with the canvases from my model.
And rename this parameter.
Finally, I'll change the OutlineGroup
to iterate over the graphics
from a single canvas.
Now we see the graphics from all
our canvases, but they all run together.
Let's add some section headers.
I can hit Shift+Command+L
to open the Library,
then filter to Show Section.
I can just drag the Section in,
then make the header show the canvas name.
Notice that because we're using
a SidebarListStyle,
we get these beautiful bold headers
introduced in iOS 14.
We can expand and collapse these too.
I think this is so cool.
With hierarchical Lists and OutlineGroups,
SwiftUI provides two great new tools
on mac and iOS
for progressive display of information.
Sometimes an app calls
for hiding and showing controls
or other information that doesn't
follow a regular hierarchy,
like this Inspector popover.
For cases like this,
I'm happy to introduce
a third new tool: DisclosureGroups.
A DisclosureGroup provides
a disclosure indicator,
a label and content.
When your user taps or clicks
on the disclosure indicator,
the content is revealed.
When they tap or click it again,
the content is hidden.
Let's see how we can use it.
Here's our Inspector.
We have controls for adjusting the fill,
shadow and text properties.
All this is wrapped in a Form,
which is a perfect choice
for collections of controls like this.
You can use Forms in your new
Settings Scenes on macOS too.
Let's take a quick look
at how the Inspector works in the app.
ShapeEdit works great on iPad.
I can select a shape
and then open the Inspector.
I can change the color, add a shadow...
and even change the shape.
Let's go back to the code.
This Inspector works great,
but it's a little busy.
Let's see if we can tidy things up a bit.
First, I'll wrap all these fill controls
in a DisclosureGroup.
I'll grab a DisclosureGroup
from the Library.
And set the title to Fill.
Notice that the fill controls are now
collapsed together in the Inspector.
Just like with Outlines,
we can expand and collapse
the disclosure group.
This group could really use an icon.
We can use a label for that.
We just remove this convenience property
and add a trailing closure for the label.
I can put any view here,
but the new Label type is a convenient way
to semantically combine
a title and an icon.
I can use one of the great
SF Symbol images here.
One of my favorites
is rectangle.3.offgrid.fill.
That's looking great.
Let's give the shadow and text controls
the same treatment.
With that done,
this Inspector is looking pretty good.
There's just one more thing
I'd like to change.
I think my users will adjust
the fill settings a lot,
so I'd like them to be visible
when they open the Inspector.
Let's do that now.
Disclosure groups in SwiftUI
can take a binding to a Boolean property
that controls expansion.
I'll add Boolean state
to act as the source of truth.
And make it default to true.
Then I'll configure the DisclosureGroup
to take a binding to our new state.
Now our fill controls default
to expanded. Nice.
We've seen how you can use
Outline and DisclosureGroups
to manage progressive disclosure
of information in your apps.
Before I wrap up,
let's look at how OutlineGroup
actually works.
It's a great example of the principle
of composition that Cody mentioned.
It's not necessary to understand this bit
to use Outline and DisclosureGroups,
but I think it's pretty cool
and hope you will too.
Here we have an OutlineGroup
over a collection of graphics.
SwiftUI expands the OutlineGroup
into a ForEach over that
same collection of graphics.
The body of that ForEach
is a DisclosureGroup.
Notice that the label
of each DisclosureGroup
is generated with a single element
of the original collection,
while the content of each DisclosureGroup
is another OutlineGroup,
this time over the children
of that single element.
This unwinding process continues
until we find a graphic with no children.
But because SwiftUI only evaluates
the content of a DisclosureGroup
after someone opens it,
only the minimum amount of the process
is actually executed.
As I mentioned,
you don't need to understand
this unwinding
to use Outline and DisclosureGroups,
but I just love the combination
of recursion and composition
that makes OutlineGroup possible.
Practically, I hope this tour of
SwiftUI's tools for displaying your data
has been helpful.
We saw that HStack and VStack
are the right tool
for controlling the placement
of a fixed set of items.
The new Lazy Stacks work great
inside a scroll view
for displaying variable,
potentially large sets of items.
Lazy Grids provide a convenient new way
to display your collections in a grid.
Lists are a powerhouse,
giving you support for selection,
scrolling, lazy loading of content
and, new this year,
display of hierarchical data.
Use Forms for settings
and other lists of controls
like we saw in the Inspector example.
And finally, the new Outline
and DisclosureGroups
give you the power to tailor
the progressive display of information
that's just right for your app.
To learn more about how best
to show data in your app,
you can download the code for ShapeEdit
from developer.apple.com.
Also be sure to check out
"App Essentials in SwiftUI"
for more on creating
Settings Scenes in your apps
and "Data Essentials in SwiftUI"
for the details on connecting
your model to your views.
And for more about sandwiches,
check out "Introduction to SwiftUI"
from WW 20.
Thanks for watching. Be well.
[chimes]