Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is James Magahern.
I'm from the iOS Keyboards team,
and I'm here to give you a brief primer
on how to make your app a first-class app
on devices with hardware keyboards.
iOS applications have always embraced
user interfaces designed all around touch,
which is a truly excellent way
to interact with content.
Discovering UI in your application
is as easy
as just showing something on the screen.
iPad users
with hardware keyboards attached, however,
have become quite common.
Embracing hardware-keyboard support
in your application
allows your users
to become more productive
and navigate your UI more quickly
and ergonomically.
They can leverage muscle memory
to execute functions
without even thinking about it.
Also, by implementing
standard system shortcuts,
novice users can approach your application
with a familiar, consistent interface
armed with expectations
brought from the Mac.
To be a first-class app
on a next-generation computing platform
like the iPad,
your application should excel at both
touch and hardware-keyboard interactions.
Here's a quick setup for what
we're gonna be talking about today.
Let's jump right in
and talk about keyboard shortcuts.
To go briefly over
how keyboard shortcuts work on iOS,
let's first talk about UIKeyCommand.
UIKeyCommand is an object
that represents a custom keyboard shortcut
in your application.
It has all the properties
that you might expect,
such as the discoverability title
shown to the user,
what keyboard input is required
to invoke it,
and optionally, a set of modifierFlags
defining which modifier keys
should be held.
This fits together with your UI
by returning an array of key commands
via an overridable property
called keyCommands on UIResponder,
where you return an array
of all the commands
for that particular responder.
Most common UIKit widgets
are subclasses of UIResponder already,
so in most cases, extending your
application to include these key commands
should be as simple
as just overriding this one property
and returning whatever key commands
are relevant
for that particular part of your UI.
The way this all fits together
in your application
is via the responder chain.
The responder chain loosely follows
the view hierarchy of your application,
with the UIApplication instance
at the very end
and the responder the user is currently
interacting with at the beginning.
Your application's first responder
is the UIResponder object
in which all keyboard events
first funnel into.
If a responder in the chain isn't able
to handle a particular event,
the event goes further up the chain.
UIViews, for example,
have their designated next responder
in the chain as the view's superview.
Key commands are then collected
by the application from each responder
via the keyCommands method
that you override,
starting with the application's
first responder
and ending up
at the top-level UIApplication instance.
Once all of your key commands
are collected by the system,
users will be able to discover them
via the discoverability heads-up display,
which is accessible by holding
the Command key anywhere in the system.
This is great, not only for your users
to be able to discover keyboard shortcuts,
but it's also handy during development
to be able to test and inspect all of them
in one place.
Now let's take a look
at how all this fits together in practice.
Let's take the Music app as an example.
When the Music app is in the foreground,
the user can press the space bar
to easily toggle the playback
of the currently playing song.
This works consistently across all apps
that do media playback of any kind,
such as when playing videos
in the Photos app
or for QuickTime videos in Safari.
Following
the model-view-controller pattern,
the ideal place to define this behavior is
in your custom view controller subclass.
In this example,
we have a player view controller
subclass of UIViewController,
which manages playback in our application
and whose view contains things
like the play button.
Because all UIViewControllers
are UIResponders,
all I need to do
is override a few methods here
to allow this
to start accepting keyboard shortcuts.
First, override canBecomeFirstResponder
and return true.
Then, override viewDidAppear
and call becomeFirstResponder
to make sure this view controller
is first responder when it first appears.
Lastly, override the keyCommands property
to return
our custom space-bar keyboard shortcut.
Here you can see
we provide a localized string
to show in the discoverability HUD
which action to perform when it's invoked
in the form of a selector
and which input is required.
In this case,
a string just containing space
to indicate this is for the space bar.
You're getting really excited
right about now,
thinking about adding some commonly used
keyboard shortcuts to your app
that your users are expecting
from other apps.
For example, if you're working on
a music library application,
you'll want to add a few shortcuts
that would make it faster
to interact with songs and playlists,
such as select all, copy, and paste.
Or if you're working on
an illustration app, for example,
you'll want to have things like
Command-Plus for zooming in
and Command-Minus for zooming out.
Well, fortunately, for many
of these commonly used keyboard shortcuts,
you don't even need to create
a single UIKeyCommand.
All you need to do
is override a couple of methods.
Every UIResponder subclass
conforms to a protocol
called UIResponderStandardEditActions,
which can respond
to any method listed here.
All you need to do
is override the relevant method.
You don't have to create
a single UIKeyCommand.
Here's a quick example.
In your UIResponder subclass,
our UITableViewController subclass here,
we just need to override
the same two methods that we did before
to make sure
it can become first responder.
As always, this will be required
if you decide to implement this
inside of your view controller subclass.
Then you can override any of the methods
mentioned on the previous slide,
such us select all, copy, paste,
and a few others,
all without creating
a single UIKeyCommand.
Check out the documentation
on UIResponderStandardEditActions
for more commands
and for more information.
UIKeyCommand was designed
with Catalyst in mind.
Making all these new key commands work
with the macOS Menu bar is extremely easy.
For the UIResponderStandardEditActions
I mentioned on the previous slide,
you get those for free.
But for custom UIKeyCommands,
luckily, UIKeyCommand is a subclass
of UICommand,
which means this is easily integrated
into the command-builder API
that we introduced for macOS Catalina.
For more depth and for more information
about how the command-builder API works,
check out the "Taking iPad Apps for Mac
to the Next Level" session from WWDC 2019.
The next thing I want to talk about
is how hardware keyboards interact
with table views and collection views.
If you have a list of files,
like in the Files app,
your users will expect
some common shortcuts from the Mac
to also work on their iPads.
For example, holding Shift
and tapping on two list items
to select a contiguous list of files
should work.
And secondly, holding Command
and tapping multiple items in a list
should extend the user's selection
without having to enter edit mode first.
Fortunately, it's extremely easy
to implement this behavior
your users expect in your application
if you're already using UITableView
or UICollectionView.
All you need to do is implement
shouldBeginMultipleSelection
InteractionAt indexPath and return true.
The system will then automatically
put your table view into editing mode
or your collection view
into multiple selection mode
and extend the user's currently selected
set of index paths
based on which modifier key has been held.
Likewise, implement
didBeginMultipleSelection
InteractionAt indexPath
to adapt your surrounding UI to the fact
that it was automatically placed
into editing mode.
To find out what else
the multiple selection API can offer you,
check out the "Modernizing Your UI
for iOS 13" session from 2019.
Now, on to some new things for iOS 14,
starting with some additions that we made
to gesture recognizers.
To start with another example,
let's take a look at Numbers.
One of the ways Numbers leverages
the hardware keyboard on iPad
to provide advanced functionality,
is by allowing users to hold the Shift key
while resizing a shape
with their finger or the trackpad
to constrain the scale
of the selected shape to its aspect ratio.
In addition, Numbers allows users
to hold the Command key
to select multiple objects
by tapping on them,
so you can move them all at once,
for example.
This is all possible because in iOS 13.4,
when we introduced the new Magic Keyboard,
we added a property on UIGestureRecognizer
called modifierFlags,
which allows any application
to implement this kind of behavior.
This property will be set
to whatever modifier keys
the user had been holding down
when the gesture recognizer's
state changes.
So, if we're implementing something like
what Numbers did in our example,
all we need to do is consult this property
when out gesture-recognizer callback
is fired
and do the appropriate action
based on which modifier key is held.
For more information
about what else is new
with events and gesture recognizers,
check out the "Handle Trackpad
and Mouse Input" session.
The last thing I want to talk about
is a new API
for responding to raw keyboard events.
Embracing hardware-keyboard interactions
within your application
can give your users
much more fine-grained control
over certain aspects of your app.
Back to Numbers as an example.
Numbers leverages the accuracy
of the hardware keyboard
and matches expectations
to allow users to be able
to make small adjustments
to shapes or layers using the arrow keys.
This requires you to respond
to a key-down event
to start moving the object
and a key-up event
to stop moving the object.
Both things are not possible
with UIKeyCommands,
which are only fired once
after invoked by the user.
Well, new in iOS,
we've added the ability to respond
to all key-down and key-up events
from an attached hardware keyboard.
Back to our friend, the responder chain,
all this is done via UIResponder methods
called pressesBegan and pressesEnded.
You only need
to override these two methods
on your view or view controller
to start getting notified
as soon as a key goes down or is released.
Again,
using the model-view-controller pattern,
we override pressesBegan and pressesEnded
on something like
our canvas view controller, for example.
In pressesBegan,
which is called when a key goes down
on a hardware keyboard,
we can check the key code
to see which arrow key was pressed
and perform the appropriate action
in our app
to start moving a shape continuously
while the key is down.
Then, in pressesEnded,
simply perform whatever action in your app
stops moving the shape.
It's as easy as that.
Likewise, similar to what we added
for gesture recognizers,
you can also check the modifierFlags
for every key event
and make adjustments as necessary.
For example,
allowing the user to hold Shift
to select while moving something.
In addition, we'll also notify you
about key-down and key-up events
with just the modifier keys as well.
So finally, what you need to do next.
Make sure your app works
with all the common keyboard shortcuts
your users expect.
Enhance the functionality of your app
with completely customized
keyboard shortcuts
to make your users more productive.
Create menu items
so your app feels right at home on macOS.
And finally,
use the new hardware-keyboard APIs
to complete the awesome
keyboard experience in your app.
Thanks for watching.
Be sure to like, comment and subscribe.
I've completely lost it. I'm sorry.