Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. My name is Brett Keating.
I hope you are all enjoying WWDC 2020.
Let's continue your journey
and talk about some new APIs
in Vision this year.
Let's hear all about how to obtain Body
and Hand Pose using the Vision framework.
One of the major themes
of the Vision framework
is how it can be used
to help you understand people
in your visual data.
Back when Vision framework
was first introduced,
it came with a new Face Detector that
was based on deep learning technology.
And since that time,
it had been improved upon
with a second revision
that could detect upside-down faces.
Also arriving with the debut of Vision
was Face Landmark detection,
which has also seen improvements
with new revisions.
Last year, we started giving you a new,
richer set of landmarks
that infer pupil locations.
Also new last year
is human torso detection.
And now, I'm excited to show you
what's new in the People theme
for Vision framework this year.
We will be providing hand pose,
and we will be providing human body pose
from Vision framework.
Let's begin by talking about hand pose.
Hand pose has so many exciting
possible applications.
I hope you will agree
and find amazing ways
to take advantage of it.
Look at how well it's working
on this video
of a child playing the ukulele.
Let's go through a few examples
of what can be done with hand pose.
Perhaps your mission as a developer
is to rid the world of selfie sticks.
The Vision framework can now help
with hand pose estimation.
If you develop your app
to look for specific gestures
to trigger a photo capture,
you can create an experience like the one
my colleague Xiaoxia Sun has done here.
Maybe you'd like to be able
to overlay fun graphics on hands,
like many developers
have already done with faces.
In your app, you can look at
the hand poses Vision gives you,
and if you write code to classify them,
you can overlay emojis
or any other kind
of graphic that you choose,
based on the gestures you find.
So how do you use Vision for this?
As we've promised since the start,
all of our algorithm requests generally
follow the same pattern as the others.
The first step is to
create a request handler.
Here, we are using
the image request handler.
The next step is to create the request.
In this case, use
a VNDetectHumanHandPoseRequest.
The next step is to provide the request
to the handler
via a call to performRequests.
Once that completes successfully,
you will have your observations
in the requests' results property.
In this case,
VNRecognizedPointsObservations
are returned.
The observations contain locations
for all the found landmarks for the hand.
These are given in new classes meant
to represent 2D points.
These classes form
an inheritance hierarchy.
If the algorithm you're using
only returns a location,
you will be given a VNPoint.
A VNPoint contains a CGPoint location,
and the x and y coordinates
of the locations can be accessed directly
if desired as well.
The coordinates use the same lower left
origin as other Vision algorithms
and are also returned
in normalized coordinates
relative to the pixel dimensions
of your image.
If the algorithm you are using
also has a confidence associated with it,
you will get VNDetectedPoint objects.
Finally, if the algorithm
is also labeling the points,
you will get VNRecognizedPoint objects.
For Hand Pose,
VNRecognizedPoint objects are returned.
Here's how you access these points
from a Hand Pose observation.
First, you will request a dictionary
of the landmarks
by calling recognizedPoints(forGroupKey
on the observation.
I will go into more detail
about group keys in a minute,
but know that if you want all the points,
you will use
VNRecognizedPointGroupKeyAll.
We provide other
VNRecognizedPointGroupKeys,
such as for only those points
that are part of the index finger.
You can access the landmarks
by iterating over them,
or as in this example,
access a particular one
for the tip of the index finger
by specifying its VNRecognizedPointKey.
Here I am showing you a quick overview
of the hand landmarks that are returned.
There are four for each finger and thumb,
and one for the wrist,
for a total of 21 hand landmarks.
As I just mentioned,
we have a new type this year
called "VNRecognizedPointGroupKey."
Each of the hand landmarks belong
to at least one of these groups.
Here is the definition for the group key
for the index finger,
and here are the landmarks
that are contained in that group
displayed visually on the hand.
Also, in the code example shown before,
I showed you one
of the VNRecognizedPointKey
that you can use
to retrieve the tip of the index finger.
Let's see what this looks like
for the remaining parts of the finger.
Going down towards the hand,
the first joint
is the distal interphalangeal joint,
which we abbreviate as DIP.
Notice that
the VNRecognizedPointKey type
uses this abbreviation
to distinguish itself.
Continuing along, the next joint
is the proximal interphalangeal joint,
which we abbreviate as PIP.
Finally, at the base of the fingers
is the metacarpophalangeal joint,
which for fingers we abbreviate as MCP.
All these four points I mentioned
are retrievable
by the index finger's group key.
The pattern repeats for each
of the fingers.
As an example, here's the group key
and associated landmark keys
for the ring finger.
The thumb is a bit different.
The thumb also has a tip.
The first joint
is the interphalangeal joint,
which we abbreviate as IP.
The next joint
is the metacarpophalangeal joint,
which for thumbs we abbreviate as MP.
The next joint for the thumb
is the carpometacarpal joint,
abbreviated as CMC.
Below, for reference,
the corresponding group keys
and landmark keys for the thumb are shown
to contrast against what we provide
for fingers.
And then, there's the base of the wrist,
which also has its own landmark.
The wrist landmark falls
on the center of the wrist
and is not part of any group
except for the "all" group.
In other words, it's not part
of any finger or thumb group.
Combined with the landmarks
for the fingers and thumbs,
this forms the set of landmarks
we identify for hands.
Now, let me show you
our sample application for hand pose.
So with this sample,
I'm using my hand to draw on the screen.
When my finger and thumb
are close together,
I'll start drawing.
And here I'm using that
to write the word "hello."
And that's it.
So I'll see what that looks like
in the code.
Here I'm going to start
in the camera view controller...
in our capture output where
we are receiving CMSampleBuffers
from the camera stream.
The first thing we do
is we create a VNImageRequestHandler
using that sample buffer.
Then, we use that handler
to perform our request.
Our request...
is a VNDetect human hand pose request.
If we find a hand,
we will be getting an observation back,
and from that observation
we can get the thumb points
and the index finger points by using
the VNRecognizedPointGroupKey
by calling
recognizedPoints(forGroupKey.
With those collections,
we can look for the fingertip
and the thumb tip points.
And we do that here.
We ignore any low confidence points.
And then, at the end of this section,
we convert the points
from Vision coordinates
to AVFoundation coordinates.
One thing I want to draw your attention to
up here is that we have set up
a separate queue to process these points.
So let's go into processPoints.
Here we're just checking to see
if nothing's going on. If so, we reset.
Otherwise, we convert our thumb
and index points
into AVFoundation coordinates here.
Then, we process these points.
We have another class
called "gestureProcessor."
And in that we call "processPointsPair."
So here, in processPointsPair,
we're looking at the distance between
the tip of the index finger
and the tip of the thumb.
If the distance
is less than a threshold...
then we start accumulating evidence
for whether or not we are in a pinch state
or a possible pinch state.
The threshold that we have is 40.
And how much evidence we require
is three frames of the same pinch state.
So once we've collected three frames
of the pinch state,
we move from a possible pinch state
to a pinch state.
We do the same thing for the apart state.
If the fingers
are not meeting the threshold,
we consider them apart.
Until we've accumulated enough evidence,
we are in the possible apart state.
Once we have enough evidence,
we transition to the apart state.
Going back
to the CounterViewController file,
these state changes are handled
in handleGestureStateChange.
Here we're looking at which case we're in.
If we're in a possible pinch
or a possible apart state,
we want to keep track of the points
that we have found
in order to decide later
if we want to draw them or not,
and we collect those here.
If, ultimately,
we end up in the pinch state,
then we go ahead and we draw those points.
Once we've drawn them, we can
remove them from our evidence buffer,
and then go ahead and continue drawing.
If we end up in the apart state,
we will not draw those points.
We will still remove all of those points
from our evidence buffer,
but then, we will update the path
with the final point
and indicate that with the Boolean
isLastPointsPair set to "True."
One last thing I'd like to mention
in the sample
is that we have also set up
a gesture handler
that looks for a double tap
in order to clear the screen.
And that is how you use
our sample for hand pose
to use Vision framework
to draw on the screen with your hand.
Vision provides a couple additional things
in the API that you should know about
which are meant to deal with the fact
that there could be many hands
in the scene.
Perhaps you're only interested in the one
or two biggest hands in the scene
and don't want results returned for any
smaller hands found in the background.
You may control this by specifying
maximum hand count on the request.
The default is two,
so if you do want more than two,
it's important to adjust this parameter.
Suppose you want all the detected hands
which aren't too blurry or occluded.
You may set this as high as you want,
but know that setting this parameter
to a large number
will have a latency impact,
because the pose will be generated
for every detected hand.
If the parameter is set to a lower number,
pose will not be computed
for any hands detected
beyond the maximum requested,
which can help with performance.
It is, therefore, recommended
that you tune this parameter
for your application needs
with performance in mind.
While using hand pose in Vision,
it might help to take advantage
of the VNTrackObjectRequest.
VNTrackObjectRequest is potentially
useful in hand analysis for two reasons.
First, if all you want to do
is track the location of the hands
and care less about the pose,
you may use a hand pose request
to find the hands,
and then use VNTrackObjectRequest
from that point forward
to know where the hands are moving.
Second, if you want to be more robust
about which hand is which,
a tracking request may help you.
The Vision tracker is good
at maintaining object identifiers
as things move offscreen
or become occluded temporarily.
For more information
about the object tracker,
please have a look at our WWDC session
on the matter from 2018.
I'm sure you're completely sold
on hand pose by now
and can't wait to start implementing
the apps you've already begun dreaming up,
but before you do,
there are a few accuracy considerations
to keep in mind.
Hands near the edges of the screen
will be partially occluded,
and hand pose is not guaranteed
to work well in those situations.
Also, the algorithm may have difficulty
with hands that are parallel
to the camera viewing direction,
like those in the image
of this karate chopper.
Hands covered by gloves
may also be difficult at times.
Finally, the algorithm will sometimes
detect feet as hands.
It is good to keep all
of these caveats in mind
when designing your app,
which may include instructions
to your users
to make the best of the experience
you plan to provide them.
And that is hand pose.
Moving on, let's now discuss
human body pose in Vision.
New this year, Vision is providing you
with the capability
to analyze many people at once
for body pose as shown in this video.
So like we did for hand pose,
let's go over some exciting ideas for apps
you can develop with body pose.
How about taking better action shots?
If you have the body pose available,
you can identify interesting parts
of the action,
like the apex of this jump.
That is probably the most interesting shot
of this sequence.
Or creating Stromotion shots?
Here we use human body pose
to find the frames
where the basketball player
doesn't overlap with himself.
And we can create this cool-looking image.
Having a look at body pose
for work and safety applications
might be interesting
to your application domain.
Perhaps it can help with training
for proper ergonomics.
Human body pose can be used as part
of another new feature this year as well--
Action Classification through CreateML.
Maybe you'd like to create
some fitness apps
that can classify an athlete
as performing the action you expect,
like this man performing jumping jacks.
Or perhaps you want to know if these kids
are having any success
in attempting
what is properly considered "dancing".
This technology was used
in the Action and Vision application.
So check out the session on that
for a more in-depth look
on how to bring everything together
into a really cool app.
To analyze images for human body pose,
the flow is very similar
to that of hand pose.
As with any use of Vision,
the first thing to do
is to create a request handler.
The next step is to create
a VNDetectHumanBodyPoseRequest.
Then, use the request handler
to perform the requests.
The difference between this example
and the hand pose example
is that we use the word "body"
instead of "hand", and that's it.
Looking at the landmark points
is also analogous
to what is done for hand pose.
Getting all the points is done
exactly the same way
by calling
the recognizedPoints(forGroupKey
with VNRecognizedPointGroupAll.
Or you can get a specific group
of landmarks
as we do for the left arm here.
And then, you may request
a particular landmark by key,
as we do here
to get the left wrist landmark.
Let's go over the landmarks
for the human body.
There are VNRecognizedPointGroupKeys
for each group.
Here we start with the face.
The VNRecognizedPointKey values
for the face include the nose,
the left and right eye,
and the left and right ear.
Let's have a look
at the right arm group next.
Note that this is the subject's right arm,
not the one on the right side
of the image.
There are three landmarks in this group,
for the shoulder, the elbow and the wrist.
The subject's left arm also has a group
for the shoulder, elbow and wrist,
with associated keys listed here.
The torso is next.
Note that is also contains the shoulders.
So then, the shoulder landmarks appear
in more than one group.
Also included is a neck point
between the shoulders,
the left and right hip joints,
and a root joint
between the two hip joints.
The subject's right leg comes next.
And note that the hip joints appear
in both the torso group
and each leg group.
Also in the leg group
are the knee and ankle landmarks.
And finally, same with the left leg,
the hip, knee and ankle landmark.
There are some limitations
you ought to be aware of
regarding body pose in Vision.
If the people in the scene are bent over
or upside-down,
the body pose algorithm will not perform
as well.
Also, the pose might not be determinable
due to obstructive flowing clothing.
Also, as you may have noticed
in the dancing example,
if one person is partially occluding
another in the view,
it is possible for the algorithm
to get confused.
Similar to hand pose,
the results may get worse
if the subject is close
to the edges of the screen.
And finally, the same considerations
that applied to hand pose for tracking
also apply to body pose.
As you may be aware,
Vision is not the first framework
in our SDKs to offer body pose analysis.
Since last year,
ARKit has been providing body pose
to developers within the context
of an ARSession.
Here, we contrast that to Vision,
and when it makes sense
to use one versus the other.
You will get the same set of landmarks
either way,
but Vision provides a confidence value
per point,
while ARKit does not.
In general, the Vision framework
is capable of being used
on still images or camera feeds,
so just like anything else
Vision provides,
human body pose from Vision
can be used offline
to analyze whole libraries of images.
ARKit's solution is designed
for live motion capture applications.
Also, due to its specific use case,
ARKit body pose can only be used
with a rear-facing camera
from within an ARSession
on supported iOS and iPadOS devices.
Vision's API can be used
on all supported platforms
except the watch.
The idea behind providing this API
through Vision
is precisely to make available
Apple's body pose technology
outside of an ARKit session.
However, for most ARKit use cases,
especially motion capture,
you should be using ARKit
to get body pose information.
As mentioned earlier in this discussion,
you can use body pose in combination
with CreateML for action classification.
Let's go over a couple tips for how
to best train your action classifier
with body pose data.
If you use videos directly for training,
you should understand that Vision
will be used
to generate body poses on your behalf.
If there is more than one subject
in the video,
then by default,
the largest one will be used.
To avoid having this default behavior
applied to your training videos,
it is best to ensure only the subject
of interest is in the frame.
You can do this by cropping
your training videos
so that only a single actor is present.
If you are not using videos,
you may also use MLMultiArray buffers
retrieved from Vision's
keyPointsMultiArray method.
With this method, you exactly control
which body poses are used for training.
Since Vision is used during training,
it should also be used for inference.
Attempting to use ARKit body pose
as an input to a model trained
with Vision body poses
will produce undefined results.
Finally, please be aware that once you get
to the point of performing inference,
you will need to pay attention to latency
on older devices.
While the latest and greatest devices
might be able to keep up
with the camera stream
while performing inference
for action classification,
older devices will not.
Suppose this is your image sequence.
You will still want to retrieve body pose
for every frame,
because the classifiers will be expecting
the body poses to be sampled at that rate.
But do be mindful of holding on
to camera buffers for too long,
otherwise you may starve the stream.
But your application will perform better,
especially on older model devices,
if you space out
the classification inferences.
Recognizing an action
within a fraction of a second
is pretty quick for most use cases,
so doing inferences only a few times
per second should be okay.
The Action and Vision sample
is a great example
of how to use Vision and CreateML
to classify human actions.
Here is a short demonstration clip
of the Action and Vision sample in action.
In this clip, we see my colleague Frank
tossing some bean bags
at a cornhole board.
He tosses the bags
using a few different throwing techniques,
which are classified in the app
using CreateML.
So let's have a look at the code
in the Action and Vision sample
to see how this is done.
We'll start in the game view controller.
Here in the camera view controller,
we are getting our CMSampleBuffers
from the camera.
And we provide those
to an image request handler here.
Later on, we use that image request
handler to perform our request.
Here it is,
a VNDetectHumanBodyPose request.
If we get a result,
then we call humanBoundingBox.
Let's go into humanBoundingBox
to see what this is doing.
In humanBoundingBox,
we're trying to find
the humanBoundingBox around the person.
We'll start by getting all the points
out of the observation
by calling
recognizedPoints(forGroupKey: all.
Then we can iterate
over all the points here.
We look here to see
if the point has enough confidence.
And if it does, we add it
to our normalizedBoundingBox.
Here, we're doing something where
we're trying to find the body joints
for the right-hand side of the body
so we can overlay them on the screen.
But since we're talking about
action classification,
I'll skip that for now.
Later on, we're going
to be storing these observations.
Let's look at what's happening
in storeObservation,
and why we're doing it.
In storeObservation,
we have a buffer of observations
that we call "poseObservations."
What we're going to do is use that
as a ring buffer.
If this buffer is full,
we will remove the first one,
and either way we're going
to append the next one.
We use this later on
when a throw is detected.
A throw is detected when
the trajectory analysis detects a throw.
And then we call this function
"getLastThrowType"
to find out what kind of throw was made.
We're going to use our action classifier
for this,
but we need to put all of our observations
into the correct format.
So we will call
prepareInputWithObservations
in order to do that.
Let's look at what that function's doing.
In prepareInputWithObservations,
we see that we need 60 observations,
and we need to put them
in a multiArrayBuffer
of type MLMultiArray.
Here in this loop,
we iterate over all the observations
that we have in our buffer.
And for each observation
we call keypointsMultiArray.
And we put that into our buffer.
If we don't have 60,
then we'll pad with zeros.
Notice the MLMultiArray(shape
and data type that's expected.
And then we can catenate those
and return them.
Going back to getLastThrowType...
we provide that input
into PlayerActionClassifierInput,
which is our ML feature provider.
Once we have that,
we provide it to our action classifier
by calling prediction with the input.
Then, once we have the output,
we look over all the probabilities
to see which of the possibilities
are the most likely,
and then, we return the Throw Type
that corresponds
to that maximum probability.
And that is how you do
action classification
using body pose from Vision framework.
Now that you've had a closer look
at the code
in the Action and Vision application
for body pose,
congratulations!
Along with everything else
you've learned in this session,
you are prepared to go create
amazing applications.
Applications that do more
when it comes to analyzing people
with computer vision
with the Vision framework.
And that is hand and body pose in Vision.
Have a great time continuing
your WWDC journey.