Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Ally. I'm the engineering
program manager for Game Center.
I'm super excited to talk to you
about not only what's new,
but to also walk you through
some updates to existing features
that we think you and your players
are really gonna love.
Throughout both sessions,
we'll touch on all the core features
of Game Center.
At the end, we hope you walk away
equipped with the tools you need
to add Game Center support to your game.
But before we get to details,
let's take a minute
to talk about what Game Center is
and what it offers you and your players.
Game Center
is Apple's own social gaming network.
It offers a single identity for players
to use across all their games.
And once signed in,
they can instantly access
their Game Center network of friends.
As a developer,
you can implement as many or as few
Game Center features as you'd like.
It's really about
what makes sense for your game.
Leaderboards are a good place to start
if you're new to Game Center.
They let your players see
how they stack up against friends
and other global players.
And as players progress through your game,
why not reward them along the way?
Achievements are a great mechanism
to do just that.
They also encourage players
to come back and keep playing.
And if your game is more fun
when played with others,
you can also use Game Center
to create rich multiplayer experiences.
Most of Game Center's functionality can be
added within your own custom-built UI.
Or you can take advantage
of the native Game Center offering,
which has been completely refreshed
this year.
That's what I'd like
to walk you through now.
To do that, let's jump into a game.
Upon launch, the Game Center
welcome banner will still appear.
But once it rolls away,
a new element appears.
This is the Game Center Access Point.
At a glance, I see some useful highlights,
like how many achievements I've earned
and where I stand in the leaderboards,
all without any action on my part.
Once the highlights finish displaying,
the Access Point collapses
into my player avatar.
This element is meant
to remain on your title screen
as a consistent way
for players to access Game Center.
To add Access Point functionality
within your game
you'll need to adopt the Access Point API.
This lets you choose
what corner to position it in
and whether or not you want to display
highlights to the player.
Christy will cover Access Point
implementation in depth a little later.
But for now,
let's tap on my player avatar.
This takes me to the in-game dashboard--
a centralized location for players
to browse and interact with Game Center.
From here you have quick access
to existing features,
like Leaderboards and Achievements.
But as you've probably already noticed,
the biggest change is
the addition of a new section
that offers in-game access
to your Game Center player profile.
But before we dig into that,
let's talk about the main dashboard
for just another second.
To give your players access
to the top-level dashboard,
you can adopt the Dashboard API.
Your player will then be able to choose
what section they want to explore.
If you already link to specific sections
of the dashboard in your game,
don't worry--
those will continue to work as well.
For example,
if you link to an individual leaderboard
somewhere within your UI,
we'll still take you directly to it.
Top-level highlights within the dashboard
are also new in iOS 14.
These are little bits of information
that are meant
to offer useful stats at a glance.
You'll see similar highlights
throughout each section of the dashboard,
so let's continue to drill in.
Tapping on the first section
of the dashboard
brings me to my own player profile.
Right away I get some useful stats
about my overall game play.
I can view and edit my friends list
or see a list of players
I've recently been matched with.
I'm also offered
some friend suggestions here.
And if I see one I like,
I can tap on "invite"
and send that person a friend request.
All of this can be done
without having to leave the game.
Scrolling further,
I now have a way to view the achievements
I've earned across all my games.
And if I want to change something within
my profile, like my nickname or avatar,
I could tap on Profile Settings.
I'm pretty happy with my profile, though,
so let's go back to the dashboard.
Next up is Achievements.
Right away, I'm greeted by
the achievements I've already completed.
This is a great way to let the player feel
a sense of accomplishment.
Scrolling a little further,
here are the achievements
I've yet to earn.
And if the game has implemented
in-progress achievements,
like this one has,
I can tell how close I am to earning it.
Notice that the artwork you choose to use
for achievements is prominently displayed.
We'd encourage you to check out
the "Design for Game Center" session
as well the Human Interface Guidelines
for guidance on how to create
great achievement art.
Both will cover best practices
for creating all kinds of assets
for your game.
And later on, Dersu will walk you through
exactly how to set up
different kinds of achievements
within your game.
Let's move on to Leaderboards.
Just like achievements, the artwork
associated with your leaderboards
is now the center of attention.
So it's a great idea to use
different assets for each one.
This is an opportunity to help the player
better recognize
which leaderboard they're looking for.
The design session I referenced
just a second ago
also has details
on creating great leaderboard art.
Tapping into an individual leaderboard,
the most obvious difference
is the addition
of a friends-only leaderboard.
This is now the default
and makes it much easier
for players to see
how they rank amongst their friends.
I could also view global
and recent leaderboards if I want
by changing views at the top.
But while we're on the topic of friends,
I can also tap on a friend
within a leaderboard.
This brings up their player card.
And if that friend has chosen
to share their info,
I can see what they've recently played
as well as their achievement progress.
The best part is player cards are
accessible in lots of new places.
I can see this same information
in my friends list
and even while browsing the App Store,
which we'll talk more about in just a bit.
Returning to the leaderboard,
perhaps the largest change is the option
to create a recurring leaderboard.
This leaderboard is set to recur
every 15 minutes,
and I'm currently only in fourth place.
That's okay-- scores will reset shortly,
and I'll have another chance
to come out on top.
Notice that I can see my standing
not only in the current leaderboard,
but in the last iteration
I played in as well.
Recurring leaderboards can be set up
within App Store Connect,
similar to classic leaderboards.
Later on, Udayan will be walking you
through how to configure both types.
Returning to the dashboard one last time,
the final section to check out
is actually an optional one,
and that's Challenges.
We only made one change this year,
but it's one worth calling out.
The Challenges feature now lives behind a
new opt-in flag within App Store Connect.
By default,
the Challenges section of the dashboard
will not appear within your game.
However, if this is a feature you support
and would like your players
to continue to have access to,
simply check a box in App Store Connect
and you're good to go.
Now, let's move on to a different area
of Game Center, and that's multiplayer.
Game Center can be used to create
both real-time and turn-based
multiplayer experiences.
During implementation, you can choose
the one that fits best within your game.
The other choice to make is whether
you want to use your own multiplayer UI
or the default Game Center one.
To help you decide, let's take a look
at the native experience.
Choosing the multiplayer option
from the main menu brings up the new UI.
As you can tell, the colors of
the game underneath really show through.
This is meant to make the design
feel at home within any game
with no additional work
from the developer.
Now let's set up a game
the way a player would.
At the top, I can adjust
how many players I want to add
up to the developer-specified limit.
For this example, let's choose three.
Within each slot,
I can tap on "Add Player."
This will bring up the player picker.
This is where I choose
the people I want to play with.
If nearby players exist,
they'll appear at the top.
Or what I tend to do most often--
I can choose to play
with an existing Game Center friend.
We'll also offer suggestions based
on people you've recently played with
or recently contacted on your device.
Coming back to the main screen,
I don't have to fill all these
player slots in if I don't want to.
Any slots I leave blank
will automatically be auto-matched.
And now I'm ready to start the game.
Look how easy that was.
No join codes, no friction--
just set up and play.
And that's a quick overview
of the new multiplayer UI.
A little later on, Christy will
walk you through in more detail.
Now that you've seen an overview
of what Game Center has to offer,
I want to spend
just a few minutes talking about
some new ways we think Game Center
can help players discover new content.
And there's no better place to start
than within the App Store.
Now, when browsing popular areas
of the store,
like the Arcade and Games tabs,
players can better discover what
their Game Center friends are playing.
We're also integrating
this same information
right into your game's product page.
I can even view a friend's player card
right within the App Store.
From there, I can check out
more of their recently played games
and download any of the ones
that look interesting to me.
We think this will give players
a convenient way to discover new games
they may have otherwise missed.
Now, let's start diving into details.
Here's a look at how
the rest of the sessions will break down.
To get started,
Udayan is going to show you
how to implement the Dashboard API
within your game.
After that, Christy will cover
adding Access Point functionality...
followed by players and friends,
where Jon will show you
not only how to enable Game Center,
but also how to properly interact
with the local player and more.
And this will bring the first session
to a close.
To kick off part two,
Udayan will be returning to show you
how to set up
both classic and recurring leaderboards.
In the achievements section,
Dersu will walk you through the different
types of achievements, how to set them up,
and how to ensure
they're reported accurately.
Finally, Christy will talk about
multiplayer functionality
and what's new there.
But to get you started with Dashboard,
I'd like to now turn it over to Udayan.
Thank you, Ally, and hello, everyone.
My name is Udayan Kale.
I'm on the Game Center engineering team.
In this part of the session,
we will take a deeper look
at the Game Center dashboard.
Ally just showed you
the new Game Center dashboard.
I will now show you ways
to invoke the main dashboard
and each dashboard section
from within your game.
The new Game Center dashboard
is a consistent, one-stop UI
for many Game Center features.
It allows you to access
the local player's profile, leaderboards,
achievements and challenges.
All these features are provided to you
through the familiar
GKGameCenterViewController class.
Here is an example of using the dashboard.
It uses the same
GKGameCenterViewController class
that you are probably using today.
The main difference
is how you initialize it.
For most games, we recommend
using the main dashboard view.
You can see here,
when I initialize the view controller,
I'm specifying the dashboard state.
This gives you the main view
that you see here on the right.
Another option is to go directly
to a specific section of the dashboard.
You can go right into the leaderboards,
achievements, challenges
or the local player's profile.
All you need to do
is set the state to the one you want.
So here is the Achievements section.
You can see I have earned
three achievements so far,
and I can browse through the achievements
to see which ones are remaining.
Or here, I have chosen to go
straight to the player profile view.
I can look at friends,
people I have played with,
and access my profile settings.
All of this is up to you.
You can also deep-link
directly to a specific leaderboard.
For this, you just provide
the leaderboardID
along with the playerScope,
global or friends,
and the timeScope,
all time, this week or today,
and present the view controller.
And regardless of which section
you start them in,
your players will be able to navigate
to any available section on their own.
So that's all it takes
to adopt the new dashboard.
We wanted to make it easy for you
to move your apps onto this right away.
Now let's talk about the new Access Point.
And for that, let me welcome Christy.
Thank you.
Thank you, Udayan.
Today I want to talk about Access Point--
a great new way to let your players view
and manage their Game Center data
right within the game.
As you can see,
there is now a small button
in the upper left with your avatar in it.
Tapping this button will take the user
to the in-game dashboard.
This button can be placed
in any corner that you choose.
Additionally,
there are options to show highlights,
including the number
of achievements earned
or your rank on the default leaderboard.
Ally has already showed you what this
looks like from the player perspective,
so now let's take a look at how to adopt
Access Point within your game.
So first,
I will cover some configuration options
that let you specify position,
content and so forth.
Then I will talk to you
about how to display Access Point
as well as some behaviors around this.
Next, there are some properties
you can observe
to know when you are presenting
Game Center and to adjust your layout.
And finally,
we will cover some considerations
for Apple TV and game controllers
and how to trigger the Access Point
programmatically.
So, let's talk about positioning.
By default,
Access Point is placed in Top Leading,
which is the upper-left corner.
However, Access Point is flexible,
so you can place it
in any corner of the screen
that best suits your game's UI.
The positioning of Access Point
will depend on your language setting.
So in languages like Arabic and Hebrew,
Top Leading will appear on the top right,
Top Trailing on the upper left,
and so forth on the bottom
from right to left.
Access Point allows you to choose
which highlights you wish to display.
You can choose to show just the avatar
or show highlights,
including the number of achievements
you've earned
or your rank on the default leaderboard.
So here's how to configure
and show the Access Point.
Typically you want to display Access Point
while you're on your main menu.
So first,
I want to set the location to be top left.
Now, I set Access Point
to showHighlights,
and finally, I set isActive to be true
in order to activate it.
Please notice that all of these calls
are to a shared singleton
off of GKAccessPoint.
As I just showed in the code,
we recommend
that you show your Access Point
when presenting your main menu.
You should hide the Access Point
in situations like cinematic intros,
game play or your Settings screen.
Our design team
has put together some best practices
for when to show and hide Access Point,
so I suggest you check that out.
Now, if the player taps Access Point,
they will be taken into the dashboard.
While that is happening,
you may wish to pause
your menu animations or whatever.
We provide a property,
isPresentingGameCenter,
that you can use for this.
So here, I'm setting up an observer
to keep an eye on that.
And based on this property,
I'll pause or un-pause my game.
In this case, the Access Point
overlaps the moon in our sample app.
So we provide a property,
frameInScreenCoordinates,
which can be used to adjust
the layout of your UI.
In this case, we use the frame
to shift the artwork out of the way.
This can also be observed
as the Access Point progresses
through each of its highlights.
Let's show you
what this looks like in code.
Here I am observing the property,
and when a change happens,
I grab the frame from our singleton,
convert it to my view's local coordinates
and adjust the layout.
Another use
for frameInScreenCoordinates
is for games using controllers
or on Apple TV
where you track the remote directly.
As you can see, as the user navigates
through the menu of our game,
the game draws its own custom feedback.
Here you can use
frameInScreenCoordinates
to draw focus feedback
when the user navigates
to the area behind the Access Point.
Here's what this looks like in code.
The first part's similar
to our previous code
where we get the screenFrame
for the Access Point
and convert it to myView coordinates.
Then I toggle focusFeedback
based on whether or not
the tracking position
is inside the frame of the Access Point.
To finish this,
we need to do one more thing.
When the user selects
the accessPointElement,
they call our programmatic API,
triggerAccessPoint,
to show the dashboard.
In closing,
I've given a quick tour of Access Point
and gone through the API
used for adoption,
including configuration, activation,
observable properties
and programmatic activation.
Now let's hand it off
to Jonathan Ellenbogen.
Thanks, Christy. I'm Jonathan Ellenbogen.
I'm on the App Store team.
I'm going to talk to you
about players, friends,
and getting started with Game Center.
Let's start with players.
Just like in a game,
Game Center refers to users as players.
Game Center uses players
to track scores, achievements,
build leaderboards
and start multiplayer games.
Players have one avatar and nickname
that is used across all Game Center games.
This gives your users a consistent
and familiar look right from the start,
which is good
for both users and developers,
saving you the time and trouble
of implementing this yourself.
The fact that players
have just one account
means they only need to sign in
once per device,
and can start playing your game
even faster.
And this year, with all the new
redesigned Game Center features,
players are more accessible than ever.
From leaderboards to friends lists,
users can access player profiles
for themselves and their friends.
Before using Game Center
for the first time,
users will create a single account
which will identify them
across all Game Center games.
In code, players are represented
by two different classes--
GKLocalPlayer and GKPlayer.
A great way to think about these classes
is that the GKLocalPlayer
is the user playing your game,
while GKPlayers are everyone else.
Let's take a quick look and compare.
All players will have
an avatar and a nickname.
Both types of players
will also have scoped playerIDs,
which can be used for leaderboards,
game invites and challenges.
However, the local player
will have a persistent ID,
while GKPlayers have IDs that change
with every instantiation of your game.
Since the local player is used
to represent
the player that's currently signed in,
some additional information is needed.
The local player class exposes information
related to restrictions
which may need to be applied in your game.
The local player is also used
by Game Center services
to save states such as scores,
achievements and friends.
Now let's look at how you can start
using players in your game.
First, before we start
using players directly,
you'll need to enable Game Center.
To do this, add Game Center
as a capability in your Xcode project.
You'll also need to enable Game Center
in App Store Connect.
This is done in the Features section
under Game Center.
You'll be prompted to enable Game Center
if you haven't already.
After Game Center has been enabled
in Xcode and App Store Connect,
you'll need to authenticate
the local player
before accessing any Game Center APIs.
Authentication allows Game Center to
make sure there's a signed-in local player
and that the Game Center account
is ready to use.
Authentication also checks
whether your game has been configured
to make Game Center API calls
and talk to Game Center services.
Once authenticated, you'll be able
to turn on Game Center features
and receive notifications
such as game invites,
challenges and user changes.
Let's look at how authentication works
in your game.
Authenticating the local player
should be done
as early as possible
in the life cycle of your game.
This ensures your game is ready
to receive notifications
and make Game Center API calls.
First, you'll need to set
the authentication handler
on the shared instance of GKLocalPlayer.
This will kick off Game Center
authentication automatically,
and you'll receive callbacks when
authentication-related changes happen,
and you can respond accordingly.
It's likely that the local player
will have already been signed in.
In this case,
the authentication handler will be called
without any errors or UI to present,
which means you've successfully
authenticated and are ready to go.
There will also be cases where the player
hasn't yet authenticated with Game Center.
In these cases,
your authentication handler will be called
with a error and a view controller.
Your app should present
this view controller,
giving the user a chance to sign in
or continue their account setup.
Once the user has successfully signed in,
your authentication handler
will be called again,
this time without any errors
or UI to present,
and you're ready to start your game.
You'll also need to handle the case
where the user decides not to sign in.
When this happens,
your authentication handler will be called
yet again, but this time with an error.
You should disable Game Center
and start your game.
Once you've successfully authenticated
and have a signed-in local player,
you can start accessing Game Center APIs.
But I'm going to talk to you
about player profiles.
This year, player profiles have moved
beyond just settings
and are now a larger part of Game Center.
As a result, you have the ability
to present local player profiles
right from within your game,
and it couldn't be easier.
All you have to do is initialize
a GKGameCenterViewController
with the localPlayerProfile state.
Set yourself as the delegate, and present
it as you would any other view controller.
It's that simple.
From here,
players can see their achievements,
find friends
and see what their friends are playing.
There are cases where the local player may
have certain restrictions on their account
and it's your app's responsibility
to check these restrictions
and disable or hide relevant content.
As we can see here,
in addition to checking
whether the user is underage
and has access to multiplayer games,
I'm also checking the personalized
communications restriction.
This is new in iOS 14,
and when this restriction is turned on,
it means the user will not be able to use
voice or messaging features
in Game Center multiplayer games.
So if your app has
any custom communication features,
be sure to honor this flag
and disable them when necessary.
This restriction will always be true
if the user is underage.
This year,
as part of user management on tvOS,
Game Center has added support for
multiple Game Center accounts per device.
This means that as users switch accounts,
the GKLocalPlayer will change,
and your game will receive callbacks via
the authentication handler when it does.
This is all done transparently
to your game,
giving you the ability to easily support
multiple players with very few changes.
Any tvOS game
can easily opt into this feature
by adding the user management capability
in Xcode.
Refer to the tvOS multiuser session
for more information.
Now let's talk about Game Center friends.
Friends are an incredibly important part
of Game Center
and are used in leaderboards,
multiplayer gaming and challenges.
And through friend profiles,
you'll be able to see
which games friends are playing
and the achievements they've earned
in those games.
With local player profiles,
we now have one place where you can see
all your Game Center activity,
including achievements and games.
You can see all your friends
and invite new ones.
You will also have access
to your friends' profiles.
These are referred to as player cards.
From here, you can quickly see
what your friends are playing
and the achievements they've earned.
This year,
you'll notice player cards are accessible
from many different places
throughout Game Center.
And with player profiles
becoming a larger part of Game Center,
profile privacy and visibility
becomes even more important.
Players can choose
from three different privacy settings--
Everyone, Friends Only and No One.
This is all handled automatically
in the game,
showing and hiding profile information
depending on which setting
a player chooses.
You can see the difference between someone
with a profile visible to everyone...
and a profile visible to no one.
To wrap things up,
we've taken a look at the different types
of Game Center players,
the importance of authentication
and making sure that it's done
as early as possible,
the Game Center APIs
around presenting player profiles,
honoring player restrictions
and enabling multiuser support on tvOS.
We've talked about the new player cards
and how different privacy settings affect
what other players can and cannot see.
Earlier, Ally, Udayan and Christy took you
through what's new in Game Center,
the new in-game dashboard,
and how to enable Access Point
in your game.
In our next session,
you'll get a more in-depth look
at some of the cool new features
in leaderboards, achievements
and multiplayer gaming.
That's all for this session.
Thanks for watching.
Have a great rest of your day.