Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Rohith,
and I'm joined today
by my colleague Brandon.
Today, we're going to take you through
how we build trust with our users
through better privacy.
I'll walk through
our approach to privacy at Apple
and then go through
how we can apply our privacy principles
to mitigate user tracking
in our ecosystem.
So, what is our approach to privacy?
At Apple,
we have four fundamental privacy pillars
that guide the products and features
that we make.
On-device processing--
processing data locally,
without sending it to a server.
Data minimization-- requesting and only
using data that you actually need.
Security protections,
which enforce the privacy protections
on our platform.
And transparency and control--
providing the user understanding
and control over their data.
These four pillars help us build strong
privacy protections into our features
to continue building trust with our users.
Let's go through these one by one
as I showcase how each influences
changes that we've made this year,
starting with on-device processing.
So, what is the benefit
of operating on data
without sending it off a user's device
to a remote server?
When you send data to a remote server,
the user loses their ability
to control who can access it,
who the data will in turn be shared with
and what the data may be used for.
It additionally requires extra work
to secure customer data
against breaches or other threats.
But sometimes you need to collect data
to train a machine-learning model.
So we're creating more ways
to leverage Core ML
to build and train models on-device.
It's as easy as dragging and dropping
these models into your Xcode project.
And keeping data locally
automatically takes advantage
of the strong security protections
we have on our devices.
We've been leveraging on-device learning
for many of our features.
Since iOS 13, we have been using
private federated learning,
or PFL,
to build machine-learning models
on potentially sensitive data.
PFL works by having devices send
differentially private model updates
instead of sending the user data.
This way, we can build centralized models
on our servers
without ever having access to user data.
Last year,
we used this technology to improve models
for QuickType and Siri voice recognition
from users who opt in
to improve our products.
And this year, we're bringing new private
federated learning use cases.
We leverage the powerful Neural Engine
in our chips,
allowing us
to improve machine-learning models
without revealing user data
to Apple or any third parties.
To learn more about
using machine learning in your apps,
check out the following talks.
Additionally, we have brought dictation
locally to the device for many languages.
So when you dictate on your phone,
your voice data will be processed locally
right on your device.
And if you write apps that use dictation,
you should specify
to use the on-device dictation model
to take advantage of this new technology.
This year,
we also introduced a new HomeKit feature,
face recognition,
so that your cameras and video doorbells
can let you know who is there
based on the people that you've tagged
in your Photos app
or from recent visitors you identify
in the Home app.
If you opt in to this feature,
your home hub will leverage
on-device intelligence
to recognize people who walk by.
On-device processing is essential
to many of the new features
we are introducing this year.
You should look for new opportunities
to use on-device processing
and reconsider your existing features
as our devices continue
to become more powerful.
This is a great tool
to build trust with your users
by minimizing the data
that you send off the device.
Let me now hand it off to Brandon to
talk more about our next privacy pillar,
data minimization.
Thanks, Rohith.
Privacy is about building trust
with your users.
One of the best ways to do this
is use only the data you need
to get the job done.
You can think of this as a careful balance
between what data your app has access to
and what it will use
to deliver the feature.
Asking a user to share
lots of personal information
for features that will only
take advantage of a little
asks users to make a bigger choice
than they might be ready for
just to use that feature.
Trust is built over time,
and starting out
by showing respect for users' data
by asking for access
to as little as possible
is a great first step.
We know
it's not always simple in practice,
so this year we're introducing new tools
that will make it easier for you
to balance the amount of information
your app has access to
with a simple user experience.
Today we'll talk about three types of data
that are accessible in new ways in iOS 14:
Photos, Location and Contacts.
Let's look at these in the context
of a simple photo-sharing app.
The app needs access to Photos
in order to pick the photo
you want to share,
Location,
to find friends around you to share with,
and Contacts, if you want to pick a friend
to share with manually.
Let's see how this might
be implemented on iOS 13.
To select a photo to send,
the user will be asked
to give the app access
to their whole photos library.
The app will ask for location permission
to find friends in the area.
Or if a user wants to send the photo
to a specific friend,
the app will request access
to all of their contacts,
so the user can pick one to share with.
To look at the whole flow,
this is a lot of access
and a lot of user friction.
To share a photo,
the user had to answer three prompts,
and in the process gave access
to all of their photos,
their precise location
and all of their contacts.
This is not great
from a privacy perspective.
While the user did have control
over sharing their information,
they couldn't use the core functionality
of the app
without saying yes to a lot of sharing.
It's also not great
from a usability perspective.
But we can do better.
This year,
we're introducing a few new technologies
to help you improve
this experience in your apps,
starting with Photos.
For all apps that access
the photos library on iOS 14,
we're introducing
the "Limited Photos Library."
Users can give apps access to only
a limited selection of their photos
instead of their entire photos library.
When the user taps "Select Photos,"
they can pick just what they want
to share with the app.
This is the new prompt for all apps
that ask for photos access on iOS 14.
Please test your apps for compatibility,
and for more information, check out
the "Limited Photos Library" session.
But this still requires a prompt,
and we can do even better.
Most apps use only
a small number of photos,
like in this case, the photo
you want to share with a friend.
PHPicker is a new framework that
replaces UIImagePickerController
that you can adopt to avoid prompting
for photos access entirely.
It features search and multi-select
to help users
find what they're looking for
and doesn't require the user
to grant Photos Library access.
PHPicker runs in a separate process
from your app,
but is rendered on top of it.
Your app can't access the picker directly
or take screenshots of the picker content.
Only what the user actually selected
is passed back to your app.
Unless your app has a strong need
for access to all photos,
such as to provide a backup service,
you should use PHPicker.
For more details on PHPicker, check out
the "Meet the New Photos Picker" session.
So let's look at what that means
in practice for our photo-sharing app.
To pick a photo to share,
the user is presented with the PHPicker,
where they can select
just the photos they want.
This is a much faster user experience
than going through a prompt
and results in much better privacy.
Next, let's look at Location.
In iOS 14, we're adding the ability
for a user to share
only their approximate location
with an app.
Like Limited Photos Library,
this is the new access prompt for all apps
that ask for location on iOS 14.
When the user taps the pill,
the app will receive
only approximate location updates.
Many apps today have features that are
a natural fit for approximate location,
like this photo-sharing app
for finding friends in your area.
You can request approximate location
by default
when asking for location authorization
by setting the
NSLocationDefaultAccuracyReduced key
in your Info.plist.
And if your app has features
that really needs precise location,
like turn-by-turn navigation,
you can ask the user for a temporary
upgrade to precise location.
In this photo-sharing app,
we don't need it,
so we'll ask
for just approximate location.
You should take a careful look
at how your app will respond
to approximate location.
Respect the user's intent by keeping
as many features available as possible,
and where appropriate, consider asking
for approximate location only.
To learn more about
the Core Location API changes,
see "What's New in Core Location."
And for a thoughtful look at the design
choices Apple Maps made
to adopt approximate location,
see "Design for Location Privacy."
Finally, let's look at how access
to Contacts can be simplified in iOS 14.
This year, we've made
proactive keyboard even more intelligent.
QuickType will suggest contact details
from your on-device contacts database.
When a user starts typing a name
in the "Enter name" field,
the keyboard automatically populates
the correct information for that name.
You can annotate text fields
to give clues to the keyboard
about what type of contact information
should be suggested.
Most apps, like this photos app,
can have a great experience
without needing to ask for access
to all of the user's contacts
just to fill in a phone number
or e-mail field.
To learn more about how this works,
see the "Autofill Everywhere" session.
Now let's recall how we started here.
To share a photo,
the user had to answer three prompts
and grant a lot of access.
Not great for privacy,
and not great for ease of use.
But now with the new tools available
to your app in iOS 14,
you can provide
a significantly better experience.
It's seamless for the user
to share only the photos they want,
easy to help them find friends in the area
without sharing their precise location,
and simple to type in a friend's name
without granting access to all contacts.
Great for privacy and great for usability.
Regardless
of the individual design choices
your app might make with these new API,
it's important to remember
the principle behind them.
Data minimization is about asking
for only what you need, when you need it,
and using new tools
to build great functionality
with the minimum data possible.
It's a great way to start building trust
with your users,
from their first moments using your app.
Back to Rohith to talk about
our next privacy principle, security.
Thanks, Brandon.
Security is another fundamental pillar
that grounds and enforces privacy
in our ecosystem.
This year, we leverage security
to address the problem
of server-name tracking
in Internet protocols.
One way that server names are exposed
is with DNS queries.
When a device accesses a website,
the system sends a DNS query
to turn that name into an IP address.
The DNS server the device uses
is usually automatically configured
by the Internet provider,
wireless carrier,
enterprise or other network operator.
And since DNS queries do not support
either confidentiality or authenticity,
the queries and server addresses
can be read or even modified
by third parties or your network operator.
They can collect, monitor,
retain and share information
about the types of DNS queries
your device sends.
But with an encrypted connection,
third parties can no longer observe
DNS queries.
Starting this year,
Apple platforms natively support
two standard encrypted DNS protocols.
The supported
standard encrypted DNS protocols
protect both the confidentiality
and the authenticity of server names.
This will coexist with corporate VPNs
and MDM configuration profiles.
IOS 14 also supports
automatic DoH server discovery,
so that devices can automatically
use encrypted DNS protocols.
If you host web content,
you can direct devices
to resolve DNS queries
using your servers securely.
Apple server names will automatically
resolve DNS queries
using Apple's DoH server.
For more information
about enabling these protocols,
see the "Enable Encrypted DNS" talk.
Another way that server names
are revealed when you're browsing
is through the TLS session
establishment handshake.
TLS is a protocol that is used
to encrypt traffic on the web.
Even if you've enabled encrypted DNS
to make name resolution more private,
TLS session establishment
includes a plain-text
Server Name Indication,
or SNI.
Just like with DNS queries,
the SNI can be observed
by a third party on the network,
telling them the name of the server
you are making a connection with.
We're currently working with the IETF
to standardize methods
for encrypting even more
of the TLS handshake
so that third parties
can't snoop on your traffic.
With these updates, encryption prevents
network operators and third parties
from tracking your activity on the web.
This is just one of the many ways
that security enforces privacy protections
in our systems.
Users depend on your apps
to keep their data secure.
For more information about securing your
apps to maintain user trust in iOS 14,
please see the following talks.
We've now talked through
three of our privacy pillars--
on-device processing, data minimization
and security protections.
In addition to giving developers
better ways to request access
for only what they need,
we're adding transparency for users
to understand when apps access what data.
This year, we have updates
to help users better understand
what data is collected
by apps and on the web.
Starting with the App Store.
Today, we already require
that all apps have a privacy policy.
This year, we're going one step further
by adding more information
to help you easily pick out
the most important details.
Starting in fall 2020, when you
submit your app to the App Store,
you will need to fill out a questionnaire
to describe how your app uses user data.
The information you provide will be shown
to users directly on your store page.
This gives users the ability
to see what an app does
before they download it.
They will be able to see
if you collect a little data
or a lot of data
and if any of that data
is used to track them.
You should make sure to still provide
further details to your users
to explain your data usage,
such as in your privacy policy
or on your website.
This information will be readily available
on your App Store product page.
It will also be shown for apps
in the App Stores on all platforms.
If you have installed
any third-party code,
such as an analytics or advertising SDK,
you will also need to declare
what data they collect and how it is used.
Remember that SDKs
run in-process of your app,
so they have access to the same
permissions that your app does.
And as a developer, you are responsible
for the trust and handling
of user data in your app,
including any code that you include.
And, SDK developers, this would be
a great time to update your documentation
to make sure that developers understand
what your SDK does.
The developer documentation
and questionnaire will be available later.
In the meantime,
reach out to your SDK's developers
to make sure you understand
how they may collect and use data.
On the web,
we're making changes to let you see
how Intelligent Tracking Prevention,
or ITP, has been protecting you.
ITP has been protecting users
since iOS 11 and Safari 11.
Now you can see what known trackers
ITP is protecting you from
right from Safari's toolbar.
And you can also dive deeper
and view a full report
of tracking that Safari has prevented
across all browsing in the last 30 days.
We're also adding
increased transparency within apps.
Users may copy and paste
a lot of sensitive information,
like passwords, photos
or even their credit-card number.
This information should only be accessed
when a user wants to share
their clipboard data with an app.
You may not even realize that code
you include is accessing the clipboard.
In iOS 14, we're making it clear
to developers and users
when apps access pasteboard items
from another app.
This includes programmatic access
as well as when a user manually pastes
using the keyboard,
menu items or the callout bar.
This serves to provide user confirmation
when they paste an item
and also warn of apps
that may be excessively accessing
pasteboard information.
We're also bringing increased transparency
to the camera and microphone.
When an app turns on the camera or mic,
an indicator will appear in the status bar
so users always know
when apps are recording.
Control Center will additionally show
which app is currently
using the camera or mic
or which app has recently used it.
This transparency also applies
to websites' use of the camera
and mic permissions.
Make sure you understand how your app
uses the pasteboard or recording
to ensure that it's only accessed
when a feature requires it
and that a user expects it.
This could include pre-warming
the pasteboard, microphone or camera
to make your app more responsive.
A user may be surprised
if an app immediately
starts recording on launch.
Make sure to include UI clues
that make it clear
when and why your app will access
the pasteboard or start recording.
And remember that SDKs
are part of your app too.
You're responsible
for the code in your app
and the relationship with the end user.
If an SDK in your app uses the pasteboard,
mic or camera,
it looks as if your app did so
to the end user.
Maintaining transparency reinforces trust
the users have with your app
and its use of their data.
Control over data
that's shared with your app
goes hand-in-hand with transparency.
So let's go through the following updates
we're introducing this year,
starting with networking.
Devices on a local network
can observe and gather information
about network activity,
and apps can gather information
about users
from the networks that they use.
Every network is unique,
and it represents a user's
surrounding environment.
This means that apps and other observers
can get information
such as if they are at home
and who is around them.
They can also build a profile
based on connected devices,
such as TVs and other accessories.
This year, we're adding control
over access to the local network.
When your app tries to access
the local network,
such as with a Bonjour or mDNS scan,
it will prompt the user
to provide it access to do so.
You should declare which Bonjour services
your app requires in your Info.plist
so that the system knows which services
to provide information from.
As before,
make sure you provide a usage string
to explain why your app needs access,
and make sure to have UI clues
so that the prompt is not unexpected.
For more information
about local networking in iOS 14,
see the "Support Local Network Privacy
in Your App" talk.
MAC addresses are identifiers used to
address specific devices on a network,
but they were not created
for the purpose of tracking devices.
In iOS 8,
we introduced MAC-address randomization.
This prevents users from being tracked
from their MAC address
when they are not connected to Wi-Fi.
But when users connect to a network,
their physical Wi-Fi MAC address
leaves a trail of their connectivity
because the address doesn't change.
As they move around
from one network to another,
network operators can combine the data
from their Wi-Fi MAC address
to create a more complete user profile
which includes where they've been
and details about their network activity.
So this year,
we're introducing private Wi-Fi address.
iOS 14 will automatically manage
Wi-Fi MAC addresses when joining networks.
This way, the MAC address
will not tie to a user's identity,
and it can't be used to track them
from one network to the next.
A new MAC address will also be generated
for networks every 24 hours,
and the new private address will be used
when the user leaves
and rejoins the network.
Users are always in control
over this feature
and can adjust this
in their Wi-Fi settings.
So with private Wi-Fi addresses,
users get a per-network address
that is not linked to their identity,
generated daily.
And users are always in control.
We're also introducing
the Nearby Interaction framework this year
that allows you to take advantage
of the ultra-wideband ranging
we introduced with the U1 chip.
Nearby Interaction is a great way
to get distance and direction information
for interactive games
and other peer-to-peer use cases,
such as confirming that a nearby phone
is the one you are looking for.
When using this framework,
there is no need to prompt
for Bluetooth or network access.
Instead, your app will prompt
for a session-based access.
So the data will be available
while the app continues to be used
in the foreground.
Make sure to include a clear explanation
when you prompt the user for permission,
and prompt when there's context
for why your app is requesting it.
For more information,
see the "Meet Nearby Interaction" talk.
New in iOS 14, app clips are a great way
to introduce users
to experiences in your application.
We designed app clips from the ground up
to be private,
so users can feel at ease
when trying them.
If a user doesn't upgrade
from an app clip to a full app,
iOS cleans up any unused app clips
so they leave no trace behind.
We've also designed
new privacy-friendly location access
specifically
for app clips' unique use cases
to help you practice data minimization.
You can check to make sure
that a tag hasn't moved
or that a user is getting on the wait list
for the right restaurant.
Location confirmation reveals just enough
information to accomplish this
without the need for full location access.
Users can control this
in the app clip card.
When you ask the system if the app clip
was invoked at a specific location,
there is no extra prompt.
But a failed check may not indicate
that the user isn't nearby.
The user may simply
have location services turned off
or they may have declined
to allow location confirmation.
You should provide a way
for users to complete the action,
such as with additional confirmation.
For more information,
see the "Streamline Your App Clip"
and "Design Great App Clips" talks.
New in Safari 14, Safari web extensions
put users in direct control
over their extensions
and use of their data.
Users will be able
to select which websites
a Safari web extension gets access to
and customize it to their needs.
You should configure your extension to
request the minimum permissions necessary.
For example, the active-tab permission
allows you to run script
on the current web page
after the user invokes the extension
without additional user confirmation.
To learn more about
Safari web extensions and privacy,
check out
the "Meet Safari Web Extensions" talk.
And this year on the Mac,
we're bringing many of the technologies
and privacy protections
you're familiar with on iOS
to macOS.
Users can now control Bluetooth access
for macOS apps that use Core Bluetooth.
And if you use Catalyst
to build your apps,
users can also take advantage
of the Limited Photos Library,
HomeKit, which is available
with the same authorization model as iOS,
access to Media and Apple Music
and access to CNCopyCurrentNetworkInfo.
And just as in iOS,
you will need to provide a purpose string
to help users understand
why you need their data.
We've built great new tools this year
for you to practice transparency
and control in your apps.
It's important to explain and show users
how their data is used
and make sure that users
are always in control of their data.
These four privacy pillars put users
in charge of their data and their devices.
Each one continues
to build trust with your users,
starting from their first moments
in your app.
Back to Brandon to talk about
how these privacy pillars come together
to prevent user tracking.
Since the early days of Safari,
we've had tracking prevention built in
to protect users as they browse the web.
We've worked hard
to continually update these protections,
from blocking third-party cookies
by default
to this year's new transparency
in Intelligent Tracking Prevention.
This year, we're bringing this same
tracking prevention mentality to apps,
which is that we believe tracking
should always be transparent
and under our users' control.
Moving forward,
App Store policy will require apps to ask
before tracking users across apps
and websites owned by other companies.
Your app must display this prompt
and only track users
across apps and websites
owned by other companies
if they tap "Allow Tracking."
This includes tracking
for targeted advertising,
advertising measurement
or sharing with data brokers.
Let's take a closer look at what tracking
across companies means in practice.
For example,
if your app knows that I like bagels
and don't like grapes,
and then you share this with a data broker
who knows that I want to be an astronaut,
this counts as tracking.
Importantly, this counts
even if it isn't tied directly to my name,
but also if it's tied to an identifier
about a particular user,
such as a user ID,
identifier for advertising,
device ID, fingerprinted ID or profile.
There are a few specific circumstances
where calling the tracking API
isn't required.
For instance, if the linking is done
solely on the user's device.
That means the data
can't be sent off the device
in a way that can identify
that user or device.
Or if data is being shared
with a data broker,
but only for fraud detection or prevention
or for security purposes.
And regardless, the use
must be exclusively on your behalf,
not for the data broker's purposes.
To ask for permission to track a user,
call the AppTrackingTransparency
framework,
which will result in a prompt
that looks like this.
This framework requires
the NSUserTrackingUsageDescription key
to be filled out in your Info.plist.
You should add a clear description
of why you're asking to track the user.
The IDFA is one of the identifiers
that is controlled
by the new tracking permission.
To request permission to track the user,
call the AppTrackingTransparency
framework.
If users select "Ask App Not to Track,"
the IDFA API will return all zeros.
The AppTrackingTransparency framework
is only available in the iOS 14 SDK.
This means that if you haven't
built your app against iOS 14,
the IDFA will not be available,
and the API will return all zeros.
Additionally, users can choose to not be
asked by any app for tracking permissions.
Limit Ad Tracking
is migrating to this switch,
and as a user who is upgrading
would expect,
Limit Ad Tracking enabled
means apps on iOS 14
will continue to read the IDFA as zeros,
and the Request to Track switch
will be off.
Just like Limit Ad Tracking,
the switch will be off
and be disabled entirely
for child accounts, shared iPads,
and can be switched off and disabled
with an MDM profile.
Finally, you should keep in mind
that users can disallow
tracking permissions at any time.
Call the AppTrackingTransparency framework
every time your app is launched
before you want to use the IDFA.
As is the case today,
you shouldn't cache or store the IDFA.
And think about
what changes you should make
to stop tracking a user
if they switch tracking off.
We believe privacy
is a chance to innovate.
With this substantial change
to how tracking works,
we've put together an innovative solution
to help you answer a key question
that normally involves tracking--
advertising attribution.
For many developers,
tracking is a side effect
of trying to answer business questions
like "Which advertising campaign
is most effective?"
Apple's Search Ads attribution system
doesn't track users
across companies today,
but what about other attribution systems?
This year we're announcing
major improvements to SKAdNetwork,
a framework that gives you
a privacy-friendly way
to answer questions
about advertising performance.
SKAdNetwork is engineered
with privacy at its core.
It uses on-device intelligence
and aggregation
to provide conversion measurement
without users being tracked.
And because it's engineered
to not track users,
there's no need
to request permission to track.
Here's how attribution works.
You pay for an ad for your app
to appear in a news app.
If a user clicks on that ad,
they can see your app in the App Store,
decide to download it, launch it
and end up new users of your app.
SKAdNetwork can help you answer questions
like "Which advertising campaign
led to the most app installations?"
Here it looks like the orange background
is more effective,
so it's probably a good idea
to run more of Campaign 1
and less of Campaign 2.
It can also help you understand
which apps that the ad appeared in
led to the most new users of your app.
Here you should probably focus on
running more campaigns in the sports app.
So how does this work today?
When the user clicks on an ad,
the advertising SDK sends a message
to their ad network
with a campaign ID and an identifier
associated with the user, like the IDFA.
Then when the user has installed
and launched the app,
an advertising SDK in that app
sends up the same identifier
to tell the ad network.
The ad network puts these pieces together
and informs the developer
who bought the ad
that Campaign 89 in the news app
resulted in a successful conversion.
So what does the ad network learn?
They learn a lot.
They learn that this user has installed
both the news app and your app,
that they clicked on this ad,
and that the conversion was successful.
Now let's see what this would look like
without tracking.
If the user denies permission to track,
the user IDs here are gone,
so the ad network isn't able
to learn anything about the conversion.
This is a problem for conversion
measurement the traditional way.
But the ad network is only trying
to measure conversions,
which don't include
user-specific information.
We built SKAdNetwork to make it possible
to learn just conversion information
without user specifics.
Let's take a look
at how this works under the hood.
Instead of the ad SDK
calling the ad network directly,
let's have it call the StoreKit framework
on-device
and pass it the campaign ID.
This information is stored
by the App Store client,
which also records the app download.
When the app is launched,
the ad network inside your app
needs to tell StoreKit
that it has been successfully launched,
which in turn informs
the App Store client.
To prevent a unique combination
of the source and destination app
from identifying a user,
the conversion data is sent to Apple,
which checks if a sufficient number
of other users
have made this same conversion.
If the check passes,
the device is notified
so that it can send the conversion data
to the ad network,
reporting a successful conversion
from the news app to your app
via the campaign you ran.
And to ensure
the integrity of this information,
cryptographic signatures
are used throughout.
Now let's look at
what the ad network learns here--
only that Campaign 89 led a number
of users from the news app to your app,
which is what they were trying
to measure all along.
SKAdNetwork is a great example of
applying privacy engineering techniques,
building creative technical solutions
to bridge the gap
between features and privacy.
There are several groups of developers
that can take steps to adopt SKAdNetwork.
If you have advertising in your app,
or your app is advertised in another app,
pick an ad network
that supports SKAdNetwork
so you don't have to prompt
for permission to track
and will get conversion data
regardless of user tracking choices.
If you're an ad network,
go to developer.apple.com
to learn how to adopt SKAdNetwork.
Please check out the "What's New
with In App Purchases" session
to learn more
about SKAdNetwork and adoption.
To wrap up, we talked about
the four key privacy pillars
that guide product decisions at Apple
and described how they apply
to our new features this year,
including new tracking protections.
We hope this will inspire you
to treat privacy as a chance to innovate
and use some of the tools
we talked about today
to build trust with your users
through great privacy.
Thank you.