Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Gavin.
I'm in the Core OS group,
and my team have been working
on bringing macOS to Apple Silicon.
So I'm delighted to get to introduce
some of the changes
coming in these systems.
We're going to talk about new features
and how to take advantage of them
in your macOS applications.
We'll go over some security enhancements,
and we'll touch on
application compatibility.
Then I'll hand over to my colleague,
Anand,
who'll be taking you through
boot features and recovery.
Intel-based Macs contain a multi-core CPU,
and many have a discrete GPU,
and recent Macs also have a T2 chip
which enables features such as Apple Pay,
TouchID and Hey Siri.
Machines with a discrete GPU
have separate memory for the CPU and GPU.
Now, the new Apple Silicon Macs
combine all these components
into a single system on a chip, or SoC.
Building everything into one chip
gives the system
a unified memory architecture.
This means that the GPU and CPU
are working over the same memory.
Graphics resources, such as textures,
images and geometry data,
can be shared
between the CPU and GPU efficiently,
with no overhead, as there's no need
to copy data across a PCIe bus.
Using Apple Silicon in the Mac
also allows us
to bring unique technologies
developed for the iPhone and iPad
over to the Apple Mac.
Apple Silicon contains coprocessors,
including powerful and efficient
video encoders and decoders,
the Neural Engine
and matrix multiplication
machine learning accelerators.
The Mac has had a multi-core CPU
for years,
but for Intel-based Macs,
all cores have similar performance.
Apple Silicon Macs
have a mix of performance cores
for when your application needs
the maximum performance,
and more power-efficient cores
for less CPU-intensive tasks.
We call this asymmetric multiprocessing,
or AMP.
The cores support
the same architectural features
and command all the same software.
macOS will use
all these cores simultaneously,
and applications are scheduled
onto the appropriate cores
depending on
their current performance requirements.
So, how should your applications
take advantage
of these new capabilities from macOS?
You might be expecting us
to announce new APIs
for you to adopt in your applications.
But we've been working for years
to build a consistent set of APIs
across all our platforms
and to optimize those frameworks
for Apple Silicon.
To run work on the GPU,
you should be using the Metal API on both
Intel-based and Apple Silicon Macs.
On Apple Silicon,
you'll just see a significant speed boost
when running tasks that benefit
from the unified memory architecture.
To take advantage of the hardware
video encoders and decoders,
you can use the same AVFoundation
and VideoToolbox frameworks
that are in macOS today.
To get the very best performance,
you'll want to use the pixel formats
that the hardware is optimized for.
Apple Silicon is particularly efficient
at handling BiPlanar formats,
such as this one.
I'm not going to attempt to read that,
but just look out for the ones
with BiPlanar in the name.
Your same Core ML code can run on any Mac.
The functionality is available
on Intel-based Macs too,
but on Apple Silicon,
Core ML is much faster and more efficient,
and it takes advantage
of the Neural Engine
and the machine learning accelerators.
Your Core ML code
should just run on the Neural Engine
without you needing to make any changes.
You might want to check that you're not
explicitly configuring your model
to run on cpuOnly, or cpuAndGPU.
To be eligible to run
on the Neural Engine,
you want computeUnits set to "all,"
which is also the default.
On Apple Silicon, you can also leverage
the machine learning accelerators
more directly
using the accelerate framework.
And, of course,
everything in the accelerate,
compression and SIMD frameworks
all have highly tuned implementations for
both Intel-based and Apple Silicon Macs.
We have two key pieces of advice
when it comes to AMP.
First, make sure you're setting
the quality of service, or QoS,
on all of your work items.
These QoS properties
are an indication to macOS
of how work should be prioritized.
Whether an action needs to be completed
at the highest performance possible,
or whether the OS
should be prioritizing power efficiency.
Setting QoS correctly
is important on all our platforms,
but it's particularly important
on platforms with AMP,
as QoS is a factor in determining
which core a task will be run on.
My second piece of advice
is to use Grand Central Dispatch.
Again, this is just good advice
on all our platforms,
but, again, it's particularly important
on AMP systems.
Why?
Well, dividing up work across
multiple cores is particularly tricky
when those cores have very different
performance characteristics.
For optimal performance,
you need to distribute
the right proportion of the task
to each thread.
API in Grand Central Dispatch,
like concurrentPerform,
can help with the hard work
of distributing tasks optimally
to run in parallel across all cores.
When using API like this,
make sure you're breaking your task
over a large enough number of iterations.
This will help the system
to load balance effectively.
These frameworks
have been in macOS for years,
so there's plenty more documentation
if you'd like to learn more.
A great starting point
will be these WWDC sessions.
And the Metal team
have a couple of new sessions this year
that's all about Metal
on the Apple Silicon Macs.
Okay, so that was macOS on Apple Silicon.
Now let's move on
to talking about security.
Building our own Silicon
has enabled us to develop
awesome security features for the iPhone,
and we're excited to bring
these protections to the Mac
while making sure not to lose
any of the capability
that makes a Mac what it is.
These features include write XOR execute,
kernel integrity protection,
pointer authentication
and device isolation.
Apple Silicon enforces a restriction
called write XOR execute.
That means that memory pages
can be either writable or executable,
but never both at the same time.
Pages that are both
writable and executable
can be a dangerous security vulnerability.
However, many modern applications
embed just-in-time compilers
to support languages
such as Java or JavaScript.
These JIT compilers frequently rely
on memory being
both writable and executable.
So, we're adding new API
that allows memory to be quickly toggled
between writable
and executable permissions.
What's really cool
is that this works per-thread,
so two threads can see
different permissions for the same page.
This makes it easy to adopt
in multi-threaded JITs.
And it's going to enable JIT compilers
that are both fast and secure.
Apple Silicon has hardware support
in the memory controller
to make the OS kernel code immutable.
Once the kernel
has been loaded into memory,
kernel integrity protection prevents pages
containing kernel code from being modified
or additional pages
from being made executable.
This blocks attacks
that would inject new code into the kernel
while it's running.
Pointer authentication
prevents misuse of pointers,
and it can harden against attacks
such as return-oriented programming.
Unused bits in 64-bit pointers are used
to store a pointer authentication code,
which is then checked
when the pointer is used.
Right now,
we're enabling use of this in our kernel,
system applications and system services.
We're not yet ready for you
to start distributing your applications
with pointer authentication.
But if you're interested to experiment,
then there's a boot-arg that you can set
so you can try this out for yourself.
PCIe devices access system memory
through an IOMMU.
On Intel-based Macs,
macOS gives all devices
a shared view of system memory.
On Apple Silicon, all devices are given
separate memory mappings.
This restricts devices
to only accessing memory
that they were intended to.
And it prevents devices
from snooping on each other.
To set up a DMA transfer
in a PCIe device driver,
you should use the IOMapper
and IODMACommand API.
Make sure you're getting
the IOMapper from your device
and then passing that
when you're configuring an IODMACommand.
Some older drivers don't use this API
and just use getPhysicalSegment
on ioMemoryDescriptor directly.
That's not going to work,
and those drivers will need updating
to the newer API
before porting over to the new platform.
Now, you'd only be using this old API
in an IOKit driver
written with a kernel extension.
Kernel extensions are still supported,
but you're going to see
increased inconvenience
for both you, as a developer,
and for your users.
The last three security features
I introduced
all impact kernel extension development.
To be able to support
kernel integrity protection,
we had to change
how macOS loads kernel extensions.
Which means this now requires a reboot.
And point authentication.
If you develop a kernel extension,
you are going to need
to enable point authentication.
And as we continue
to improve the platform,
you should expect to see
more friction around kernel extensions.
We introduced DriverKit
last year in Catalina
to enable you to build drivers
that run in user space,
which improves system stability
and security.
If you're not already looking into
DriverKit for any drivers you develop,
then now's the time to do so.
Here are some resources
to help you learn more
and get started with DriverKit.
Okay, that was security.
Now, let's take a look
at application support on this platform.
Rosetta is our translator
to run existing x86_64 applications.
It runs all kinds of apps:
macOS apps, Catalyst apps, games
and complicated apps like web browsers
with embedded JIT compilers.
Apps using Metal will directly generate
the right commands for the Apple GPU,
and translated apps that use Core ML
get to run on the Neural Engine.
The performance and compatibility
of Rosetta
was only possible through Apple Silicon
and software teams
working closely together.
Now, Rosetta sets to work
right from the moment
your application is being installed.
Triggered by the App Store
or the package installer,
Rosetta will start translating
all the executable code
in your application.
If your application doesn't use
one of our installers,
then you may see an extra bounce or two
in the dock the first time it's launched,
as we'll start translating it then.
And security is deeply integrated
into this translation process.
Translations of your application
are all code-signed,
tied to a single machine, securely stored,
and get refreshed over OS updates.
When your application is launched,
we load our stored translation.
Rosetta then fully emulates
a x86_64 process,
right down to the system call interface.
Everything in the process is translated,
including all system frameworks.
If Rosetta newly encounters code that
haven't been translated at install time,
then we'll compile it on the fly.
And Rosetta maintains the security
you'd expect
with hardened run-time protections,
all fully enforced
on processes running in Rosetta.
Now, hopefully,
everything should just work,
but if you do need to debug
or profile your app,
well, that's all fully supported.
You can build and run translated apps
directly from Xcode,
and you can profile from Instruments.
You could also use command-line tools
like LLDB.
There are some differences
between processes
running on an Intel-based
and Apple Silicon Mac.
Page size, memory ordering rules,
the frequency of mach_absolute_time
and some details
of floating point behavior,
these all change.
For applications running in Rosetta,
we've made sure that everything matches
behavior on an Intel-based Mac.
Now, Rosetta does not support
the AVX vector extensions to x86.
Applications should already be checking
whether the machine supports AVX
before trying to use it.
There's a sysctl you can use
if you need to do so.
Also, you will see some limitations
running on the Developer Transition Kit,
as there are some compatibility
restrictions on that hardware.
The DTK release notes
have more information.
And finally,
if your application does need to know
when it's being run in Rosetta,
then we have added
a sysctl.proc_translated
to check for this.
Okay, that's Rosetta.
Of course, what your customers really want
is a native arm64 port
of your application.
We have a ton of great information for you
on porting
and optimizing your applications
on the developer documentation website.
And there's a whole session full of advice
around porting your applications,
so please go check that out,
and please get started on a native port.
And for the first time,
compatible iPad and iPhone apps
will also be available on the Mac.
Again, we have a whole session on that
for you to learn more.
I hope I've given you some useful insights
into macOS on Apple Silicon,
the new security enhancements
and application support.
I'll hand over now to Anand,
who is going to dive into
boot architecture of these systems.
Thank you.
Thanks, Gavin. Transition to Apple Silicon
has been a great adventure,
and boot process
is an essential part of it.
I'm excited to tell you all about it.
This part of the session will give you
an overview of the new boot process.
We will talk about changes
to the start-up and log-in experience,
changes to macOS Recovery Mode
and enhancements to Boot Security
and data protection layers of the system.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
the boot process is based on
Secure Boot architecture
of iOS and iPadOS.
Secure Boot ensures that
each start-up component
is cryptographically signed by Apple
and that the boot happens only after
the verification of the chain of trust.
This offers much stronger security
at boot time on macOS.
In addition, we have added support
to boot from multiple macOS installed
on internal or external volumes,
as well as enabled booting
any version of macOS signed by Apple.
This will allow future macOS
to continue booting older versions.
Lastly, we have introduced
new macOS Recovery flows.
So how does
start-up on Apple Silicon Macs work?
The start-up experience
is much simpler than before.
All of the start-up keys are now unified.
Just press and hold the TouchID button
on your Mac portable
or press Power button on your desktop
to launch Startup Options.
Startup Options
is part of the new macOS Recovery UI.
Once you are in Startup Options,
you can access features and tools
using the UI or shortcut keys.
Here's what it looks like.
This is macOS Recovery Startup Options UI
with integrated Startup Manager
on Apple Silicon Macs.
macOS Recovery is your one-stop shop
for all things related to startup
and recovery.
It's transformed with new user experience.
Two features worth highlighting
are Startup Disk and Mac Sharing Mode.
Let's start with Mac Sharing Mode first.
Mac Sharing Mode
replaces Target Disk Mode.
It uses SMB file sharing
to provide file-level access to user data.
User authentication is required
to enable this service.
Next, Startup Disk.
macOS Recovery Startup Disk
focuses on selecting the security policy
for each of the volume
with macOS installed.
You can choose from full
or reduced security, as shown here.
So, what are the security modes?
In full security mode,
new Apple Silicon Macs
enjoy the same
best-in-class security technologies
that exist on iPhone.
This mode is enabled by default.
In addition,
you can now boot from external disk
without downgrading
the security of the system.
We think this is great.
By contrast, reduced security
provides flexibility
and configurability of your Mac,
and it keeps the Mac what it is.
Reduced security allows you
to run any version of macOS,
including the versions
that are no longer signed by Apple.
In addition, users that want to install
notarized kernel extensions
must enable this mode in order to do so.
To enable reduced security, users must
authenticate in macOS Recovery first.
Using existing security configuration tool
CSRUtil,
you can also configure the security
of your Mac to support specific workflows.
For example, you might want to do this
if you develop kernel extensions,
or if you are a researcher or a hobbyist
exploring the Apple platform.
CSRUtil provides many norms.
Few of them are highlighted here.
Now, on Intel-based Macs,
the active security policy
applies to the entire system.
So, if you have macOS
installed on multiple volumes,
downgrading the security of one
affects all of the installations.
However, Apple Silicon Macs
maintain a separate security policy
for each macOS installation.
You can downgrade security for an OS
being used for development or testing
and still have a full security
macOS installation for daily use.
Let's move on and talk about new log-in.
This is gorgeous.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
macOS has a unified log-in experience.
It supports a richer UI
with accelerated graphics
that is also consistent
with macOS look and feel.
This experience is made possible
by fully booting macOS
without requiring the user
to unlock the system.
The unified log-in experience
allows the introduction of new features
even when FileVault is on.
For example, it now has built-in support
for authentication with CCID-
and PIV-compatible smart cards,
as well as VoiceOver support
for accessibility improvements.
Let's touch on data protection.
Similar to T2 Macs,
macOS on Apple Silicon Macs
supports full data volume encryption
by default.
When FileVault is on, this encryption
is tied to user's credentials.
Apple Silicon Macs
also support secure hibernation.
In addition to preserving
the desktop and applications
during a low-battery event,
secure hibernation provides full
at-rest protection of the memory contents
by offering integrity
and anti-replay protection.
Transition to Apple Silicon
made this feature possible.
Let's talk about how the recovery
of Apple Silicon Macs will work.
At a high level,
software is composed of two components:
macOS and macOS Recovery.
If macOS is not accessible,
you can use macOS Recovery
to reinstall and recover your system.
But what happens when macOS Recovery
itself is not accessible?
On Intel-based Macs,
you can use Internet Recovery.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
we are introducing System Recovery.
It's a minimal macOS environment
installed in a separate hidden container.
It enables you to restore your Mac
by reinstalling macOS and macOS Recovery.
Apple Configurator 2
will continue to be supported.
It will allow you to recover your Mac
when System Recovery itself
is not functional.
You can erase and reinstall macOS,
including System Recovery.
To wrap up, in this session,
we touched on Apple Silicon features,
including security enhancements,
and how macOS application
can take advantage of them.
We also went over
application compatibility
and introduced Rosetta.
And finally, we described
new boot features and recovery process.
Transition to Apple Silicon
brings significant improvements to macOS.
We hope this session provided you
with good insights into them.
We look forward to seeing
how you take advantage
of these improvements
in your own application.
Thank you very much for joining us.