Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Jacob,
and I'll be joined later by Kyle.
We're so excited to show you SwiftUI,
a great way to build better apps, faster.
We think the best way
to learn about SwiftUI
is to see it in action by building an app.
Using SwiftUI feels like magic,
but to make it clear
that I don't have anything up my sleeves,
I want to go through the entire process
of creating an app in SwiftUI
starting from scratch.
So, what kind of an app
are we going to make?
Let me set the stage for you.
Kyle and I love to eat sandwiches.
So we've been keeping a list
of the best sandwiches we can find.
And we want to make an app for it.
Let's jump to Xcode and start building it.
I'll start by creating a new project.
And using the multi-platform app template.
And I'll call it "Sandwiches."
And here's our new project.
Xcode has started us off
with everything we need
for iOS and macOS versions of our app.
We have a group for iOS-specific assets
and a group for macOS-specific ones.
But most of our code
is in the shared group.
We have a file here
that has all of our app code.
And this may seem too short to be the code
that sets up our entire app,
but this is all we need.
We'll come back to this code
a little later.
For now, let's start with the code
for our app's view.
The left side of our editor
shows our code,
and the right side shows a canvas
with a visual representation of that code.
In SwiftUI,
view definitions are just Swift code,
which means that the canvas
and the code editor
are just different ways of viewing
and editing that same code.
If we select something in the canvas,
that selection is reflected
in the code as well.
And if you change something in the code...
that change is reflected
in the canvas as well.
They work together seamlessly
so that you can move between them
whenever you want.
Let me tell you a little more
about how it works.
The canvas shows us previews
of our view code,
and it even helps us edit
and learn about that code.
Xcode shows these previews
by compiling our real code
and running it to generate a result.
But one of my favorite things
about previews
is that they're also created
using SwiftUI code.
And later on, we'll see how that gives us
a lot of power to customize our previews.
Now, our app is going to show
a list of sandwiches.
So let's make the cell for our list.
I'm going to add another piece of text
under this one
to show more information
about each sandwich.
And I'm going to add it
from the library...
by just dragging it out onto my canvas.
And Xcode even shows me what will happen
when I drag it into different locations.
When I drop it, the preview updates
to show the text added,
but even better, Xcode has actually
edited my code to add that text.
Xcode has embedded these views
into a VStack
to get the layout that I want.
A VStack, or vertical stack,
is one of the common layout containers
in SwiftUI.
It lets you stack views vertically.
There's also an HStack
that lets you stack views horizontally.
And these stacks are containers.
I can place any views that I want
inside of them.
I'm going to replace this placeholder
with the ingredients of a sandwich.
For now, let's just use a hard-coded value.
Next, let's add an image next to our text.
I can make edits in the code
just as easily as in the editor,
so let's embed our view
in an HStack right over here.
I'll command-click on my view
and choose "Embed in HStack."
And Xcode has added the code
to do just that.
Now, I can just add an image
next to our VStack.
We'll add some assets in a bit,
but for now, I'll use an SF symbol image
to get things up and running.
And already,
we have a basic version of our cell.
Now let's style the cell.
I can command-click on a view
and inspect it
to see some properties about that view.
Let's change the alignment for our VStack.
And Xcode has updated my code
to show that value.
Now, let's inspect our ingredients text.
This time, let's use the canvas.
Pro tip: You can control-option-click
to go directly to the inspector.
I'll change to a smaller font.
Let's use Subheadline.
One of the great things
about Xcode editing my code
is that it helps me to learn
how to use SwiftUI.
I can now see the code
to set the font for some text.
We call these kinds of methods
"modifiers,"
and they're used in SwiftUI to customize
the way your views look or behave.
I'll add another modifier in code
to set the foreground color
to a secondary color.
And now that I have my cell,
let's put it into a list.
To do that, I'll command-click on my cell
and choose "Embed in List."
This wraps my cell in a list
and makes five iterations of that cell.
And this code is all I need
to show a list.
No delegates or data sources,
just views inside a list.
Next, let's hook this up to some data.
I'm going to drag in some assets
and a model file that I created earlier.
My model has a few fields of information
that we'll use.
And to use this in a list in SwiftUI,
I just need to
make this type Identifiable.
This lets the list know
when new items are coming and going.
We already have an 'id' property,
which is all we need.
This model file also includes
some test data
that I can use for debugging my app.
Now, let's go back to our view
and pass in our data.
I'll add a property on my view
for the sandwiches.
And one of the great things about previews
is that they can use their own test data.
So I'll just pass in our test data
right here.
You may notice this banner
that's appeared above our preview.
When I make larger changes to my types,
like adding the sandwich's property,
Xcode pauses the previews until I'm ready
to have them resume updating.
I can click this button
or press command-option-P to resume.
Next, let's use our data
to drive the list.
We'll pass the sandwiches to the list...
and we'll update our text
to show the sandwich's name.
And we'll show
the correct number of ingredients.
And now that we have real images,
let's use our sandwich's thumbnail
for the image.
You may have noticed
a subtle change in our cells.
When we started,
they were the standard 44 points tall.
But when we changed
to these larger images,
the cells automatically expanded
to make sure those images fit
without any extra work.
And now that I have
those images in context,
they look a little sharp.
Let's apply a corner radius to our images
using another modifier.
If you're not sure
what modifiers are available,
you can view and filter a list of them
in the Xcode library right here.
We'll find the corner radius modifier,
and we can drag it onto our canvas.
Notice that for views
that are in our list cell,
Xcode even knows that these cells
share the same definition
so this modifier
will apply to all of them.
Let's drop it onto our image...
and tweak the value.
Now that our cells and list
are looking good,
the next thing we need
is to be able to tap on a cell
to see more details about a sandwich.
To support that,
let's wrap our list in a NavigationView.
A NavigationView enables navigating
between different parts of your app.
On an iPhone, it shows a navigation bar
And allows pushing onto a navigation stack.
Let's also set the navigationTitle
for our view
to show "Sandwiches" in the bar.
Then I'll set up our cell
to push onto the stack.
To do that, we can wrap our cell's content
in a NavigationLink.
A NavigationLink
takes a destination to push.
For now, we'll just use some text
that shows the sandwich's name,
and then we'll put our cell
as the contents of the NavigationLink.
And you'll see that the UI
has automatically updated
to show these detail indicators
in all of the cells.
SwiftUI automatically handles
details like this
so that our UI looks right by default.
Let's also check
that the cell behaves correctly.
And previews are great here as well.
I can click the play button on my preview,
which takes me live.
This lets me interact with my real code
right here in the canvas.
So I can tap on cells to make sure
that they push and pop as expected.
And if I swipe to pop,
you'll notice an advanced behavior
that SwiftUI has given me automatically.
Our cell stays highlighted
and interactively unhighlights as we swipe
with no extra work.
One last change
I'd like to make to this list
is showing the number of sandwiches
in a row in the list.
But our view code
is a little bit large now.
And I don't want to end up
with a single massive view.
So let's factor the cell out
to be its own view
to get some separation of concerns.
Xcode helps me do this
in one simple operation.
I can just command-click
the view that I want...
and choose "Extract Subview."
All of the view code gets moved
into this new view,
and I even get to choose its name.
Let's call it "SandwichCell."
Then I'll just add a property
for the sandwich...
and pass that sandwich in.
This is a fantastic workflow improvement.
And with SwiftUI,
views are very lightweight,
so you don't have to worry about
creating extra views
to better encapsulate
or separate your logic.
Now that our list code is slimmed down,
let's add the row
with the number of sandwiches.
Right now, we're using a single collection
to drive our entire list,
which is great for lists
that are purely data-driven.
But when I need more,
SwiftUI also lets me mix
static and dynamic content
in lists and other containers.
I can replace passing this collection
to the list
with a ForEach,
which creates a view
for each item in the collection.
Now I can add a static element
right alongside this data-driven one.
I'll just add another text
below this ForEach
and have it show the number of sandwiches.
And let's change its foreground color
to be secondary as well.
Let's also show the text centered.
To do that, we can embed the text
in an HStack...
and add some spacers.
A Spacer is a common layout element
in SwiftUI.
It behaves like a flexible space
in a toolbar,
expanding to fill
whatever space is available.
So these two spacers
divide up any available space,
which centers the text.
Next, let's build our detail view.
I'll create a new view
using the SwiftUI View template...
called "SandwichDetail."
Xcode automatically gave me a view struct
and the preview code to create it.
I want this detail view to show
more information about my sandwich,
so I'll pass that in as an input.
And just like before,
I use the preview code
to set up a version of this view
that uses our test data.
Now, to build our view,
I'll just use an image
with the sandwich's image name.
It's showing our image,
but that image is too large for our view.
By default, SwiftUI shows all images
at the size of their contents
to prevent visual artifacts
from scaling the image up or down.
But for photos like this one,
we want to be able to resize them down.
And we can use an image-specific
resizable modifier to specify that.
Now it's the size of our screen,
but I really want to maintain
the image's original aspect ratio.
I can do that with another modifier
to set the aspect ratio.
And this lets me choose between "fill,"
which expands the image
to take up its entire frame,
or "fit,"
which makes sure that the image fits
within the frame.
And previews let me really
easily see and understand
the difference between these.
For now, let's use "fit,"
so we can see our full image.
Now, let's go back to our list
and update our cell to push
our new detail view when we tap on it.
We'll create our SandwichDetail...
and pass in the current sandwich.
I'll switch my preview back to live mode.
And now I can tap on the cell
to see my image.
But now that I'm previewing it here,
I can see that I forgot to set its title
in the navigation bar.
Let's go back to our detail view
and fix that.
I'll just add
the same navigationTitle here
to set my title to be the sandwich's name.
But in the preview I have here,
we're only seeing the view itself,
and I'd really like to be able
to quickly verify my change.
Well, since previews have all the power
of SwiftUI's views available,
we can do just that.
I can set up my preview
to be in a NavigationView
just like I would anywhere else
in my SwiftUI code.
Now, my view's preview
has a navigation bar,
and I can see my title right there.
Now, when I'm picking a good sandwich,
there's one thing
that's very important to me.
The sandwich has to have
just the right amount of sauce.
No sauce, and it's too dry.
Too much, and it's drowning in sauce.
I can see that there's some sauce
on this sandwich,
but I want to make sure
that it's not too much.
Now, if this had an aspect ratio
of "fill"...
I could see the sandwich up close.
Looks like a good one.
What I'd really like
is to be able to change back and forth
between "fill," to see up close,
and "fit," to see the whole sandwich.
But how do I dynamically change
this aspect ratio's content mode
while the app is running?
To understand how to do this,
we really need to know more
about how views work in SwiftUI
and why.
I'm going to turn things over to Kyle
to talk about that.
Thanks, Jacob. Hi.
I'm Kyle, a member of the SwiftUI team.
SwiftUI might be a little different
from what you're used to,
so, before we go any further,
we're gonna step back and spend some time
talking about the way views work.
We left off implementing
the SandwichDetail view.
Note that in SwiftUI, a view is a struct
that conforms to the view protocol,
rather than a class
that inherits from a base class
like UIView.
This means your view doesn't inherit
any stored properties.
It's allocated on the stack,
and it's passed by value.
SandwichDetail just stores a sandwich,
so it's the size and weight of a sandwich,
no additional allocation
or reference counting.
Behind the scenes, SwiftUI
aggressively collapses your view hierarchy
into an efficient data structure
for rendering.
Because of this, we make liberal use
of small, single-purpose views in SwiftUI.
And you should too.
What I want you to take away from this
is that views are incredibly lightweight
in SwiftUI.
As Jacob mentioned earlier,
you should never hesitate
to re-factor your SwiftUI code
because extracting a subview
has virtually no runtime overhead.
A view in SwiftUI
and a view in a traditional UI framework
fulfill the same primary role:
they define a piece of UI.
The view protocol only requires
a single property: body.
Which is itself a view.
You build bigger views
by composing together smaller views.
We built the SandwichDetail view
by composing together
Image, a view of an image
at its native resolution...
resizable, a view that stretches an image
in either dimension...
and aspectRatio,
a view that proportionally
scales its child.
The rendering of any view you might build,
like SandwichDetail,
is just the rendering of its body.
If you set a break point
in the implementation of body,
and the debugger stops there,
its means the framework has decided
it needs a fresh rendering of your view.
Ta-da!
The framework knows
when to fetch a new rendering
because in addition
to defining a piece of UI,
a view defines its dependencies.
Let's extend SandwichDetail
to allow the user to tap,
to toggle between fitting into
and filling up the available space.
The first thing we'll need
is a state variable
that says whether or not
the image is zoomed.
When SwiftUI sees a view
with a state variable,
it allocates persistent storage
for that variable
on the view's behalf.
If we decide to fill or fit
based on that state variable,
we've got a view that renders like this
when it's zoomed
and like this when it isn't.
Now, all we need is a tap gesture
to toggle back and forth
between the two states.
Then on tap,
the image will zoom to fill...
and shrink to fit.
So, what's actually happening here
when we tap?
One of the special properties
of state variables
is that SwiftUI can observe
when they're read and written.
Because SwiftUI knows
that zoomed here was read in body,
it knows that the view's rendering
depends on it.
Which means...
when the variable changes,
the framework is going to ask
for the body again,
using that new state value
so it can refresh the rendering,
this time with a different content mode.
Traditional UI frameworks don't
distinguish between state variables
and plain old properties.
However, I found the distinction
to be incredibly clarifying.
In SwiftUI, every possible state
your UI might find itself in--
the offset of a scroll view,
the highlightness of a button,
the contents of a navigation stack--
is derived from an authoritative
piece of data
often called "a source of truth."
Collectively,
your state variables and your model
constitute the source of truth
for your entire app.
Earlier I mentioned that this call
to aspectRatio makes a view.
Its definition looks something like this,
where contentMode
is a plain old Swift property.
You can neatly classify every property
as either a source of truth
or a derived value.
The zoomed state variable
is a source of truth.
The contentMode property
is derived from it.
Recall, SwiftUI can observe
when state variables are read and written.
So when one changes,
it knows which renderings to refresh.
The framework refreshes a rendering
by asking for a new body,
making a new aspectRatio view
from scratch,
thereby overriding the contentMode
and any other stored properties.
This is the mechanism
by which all derived values
are kept up-to-date in SwiftUI.
We've seen that every state variable
is a read-write source of truth...
and that every plain old property
is a read-only derived value.
We're not going to see an example
in this talk,
but SwiftUI invents a tool
called "binding"
for passing read-write derived values.
And technically, any constant can serve
as a perfectly good
read-only source of truth.
The test data driving our previews
is an example of this.
Lastly, I mentioned earlier
that collectively,
your state variables and your model
constitute the source of truth
of your entire app.
Later on, we'll see Jacob use
observable objects
to teach SwiftUI how to observe changes
to a model object.
Don't worry if the difference
between these primitives
isn't crystal clear to you yet.
We've got an entire session dedicated
to developing your instincts
around when to use which
of these data flow primitives.
Okay.
Let's just step back and take stock here.
What we've seen is really different
from what you do
in a traditional UI framework,
where the views themselves persist
and you try your hardest to keep them
all up-to-date and consistent.
You may not think about it in these terms
when you use a traditional UI framework,
but every time a view
reads a piece of data,
it's creating an implicit dependency.
It's a dependency
because when that data changes,
the view needs to update
to reflect the new value.
When it fails to, that's a bug.
SwiftUI automatically manages dependencies
on your behalf,
recomputing the appropriate derived values
so this never happens again.
Of course, we don't just manage
a single dependency at a time.
The UIs we work on
are big and complicated.
When it comes to how much
you have to hold in your head
and how easy it is to make a mistake,
the way we manually manage
dependencies today
is really hard.
Despite my best efforts,
every update to every app
I've ever shipped
has had UI bugs.
Every one of these lines is a dependency.
And even after you understand all of them,
you still have to make sure
that your UI is in a consistent state
across all possible orderings
of event handler callbacks.
To clarify what I mean by that,
we're going to look at a bug
in an old version of the Sandwiches app,
which was implemented in UIKit.
Here's a sketch
of the view controller code.
When you zoomed in,
it had a snazzy enhance button.
So, if Jacob ever ended up
with a low-resolution image like this one,
he could still verify the sandwich
included a healthy dose of sauce.
Tapping the button would dispatch
a machine-learning operation
on a background thread
to enhance the image.
Ah, that's better.
I think I spy some spicy brown mustard.
There was only one problem.
We had a report
of a stray activity indicator
that never stopped spinning.
The bug was caused
by this unexpected ordering of events.
These kinds of mistakes are easy to make
when you mutate your subviews
directly in event handler callbacks
rather than updating a source of truth
and deriving your UI from that.
This is because we can't help
but code to the happy paths
that come readily to mind
and overlook the unhappy ones that don't.
The problem is,
as the number of events increases,
the number of unhappy paths explodes.
Assume we get all four events.
How many different possible orderings
are there?
There are actually 24 different orders
any four event handlers
could be called in.
In practice, it's even worse than this
because each of these events
can occur more than once.
Say, for example,
a user is mashing the enhance button.
The challenge of managing this complexity
should be familiar to anyone
who has tried to juggle
asynchronous callbacks
or implement interruptible animations.
These completion handlers can fire
at all kinds of unexpected times.
If I could tell myself from five years ago
one thing about my job,
it would be that UI programming is hard.
No one pretends synchronizing
multi-threaded code is easy.
It's taken me months to shake out the bugs
in some of the multi-threaded code
I've written.
And even then, I couldn't be
100% confident in its correctness.
A lot of UI code
is actually just like that.
I think we downplay how hard it is
because it often only manifests
as a view missing or in the wrong place.
But we shouldn't.
Race conditions and UI inconsistencies
share the same underlying
source of complexity –
these easy-to-overlook orderings.
Many of the views we all work on
have to handle way more than four events.
Model notifications, target-actions,
delegate methods,
lifecycle checkpoints,
completion handlers--
they're all events.
A view with 12 would roughly equate
to 12 factorial possible orderings.
That's almost half a billion.
You can think about this as kind of like
Big O notation for your brain.
You're human.
You can only fit so much in your head
at a time.
This dotted line?
That's your app.
What do you think the difference
between these points is?
That's right.
Bugs.
As we add features
the number of possible orderings explodes,
and the chance we overlook one
increases to the point
where bugs are inevitable.
I imagine many of you have discovered
when using a traditional UI framework
the simplicity that results from
collecting all of your view updates
into a single method.
When you do this, you break the back
of the curve we just saw,
because when there's only one method,
there's only one possible order
it can be called in.
You may not have thought about it
in this way,
but this pattern forces you
to define a source of truth
for every possible state
your UI might find itself in
and derive your view's properties
from that collective source of truth.
If this sounds familiar,
it's because SwiftUI was directly inspired
by this best practice.
We've codified it in the framework
by making "body"
the only entry point that is ever called.
And in doing so,
we've solved the tricky cases,
the ones that I, at least,
when using a traditional UI framework,
was never able to fit into this pattern.
Like removing subviews,
pushing onto a navigation stack
and performing updates to a table view.
This is why Views,
but also Apps and Scenes
and any other SwiftUI abstractions
with a body
work the way they do.
Because you're only human,
and this pattern
of simply fetching new instances
for the parts of the UI that changed
scales with your brain,
virtually eliminating UI inconsistencies.
Now let's get back to the demo
and finish the SandwichDetail view.
Jacob?
Thanks, Kyle.
To be able to look more closely
at our sandwich,
let's add a state property...
called "zoomed"...
and default it to "false."
And states should only be accessible
within a view's implementation,
so we'll make it private.
Then we'll use it
in our aspect ratio's content mode
to change between "fill" when we're zoomed
and "fit" otherwise.
And finally, we'll add a tap gesture
to toggle our zoomed state.
Let's try it out in a live preview.
Now we can change between these modes.
But you might notice
that when we're zoomed in,
there's some blank space at the bottom.
SwiftUI automatically lays out your views
in what we call the safe area.
This means that UI elements in your app
won't get clipped
by things like the corner radius.
But for an edge-to-edge image like this,
we actually want to expand
to the whole screen.
To do that, we can just add a modifier...
to ignore the safe area.
And specifically,
we'll ignore it on the bottom edge.
Okay, we're close,
but there's something missing here.
This needs an animation,
and with SwiftUI
animations are really easy to add.
I can just wrap my change
in withAnimation...
and now it animates
between its different states.
And not only that, the animation
is fully interactive and interruptible.
I can tap on it at any time,
and it always animates correctly.
I would add the enhance button next,
but it turns out
that the way Kyle trained the model,
it only ever worked
on that one image that he showed.
So I'm going to add something more useful.
Kyle loves spicy sandwiches,
like this one.
But I don't,
so I want to have a way to quickly know
if a sandwich is spicy or not.
Let's show an indicator for that
below our detail view.
I'll add a VStack
around our existing sandwich image.
And I'll move the more general modifiers
to apply to that VStack.
I want to show an image and text here,
and a great way to do that
is with a label.
A label takes a title to show--
we'll use "Spicy"
and it also has an associated icon.
We'll use a system image...
called "flame.fill."
The label shows the icon and title
together for us.
And it can also be used in other contexts,
like lists and menus,
where it will automatically
take on the correct appearance,
spacing and sizing.
I was kind of imagining
a bottom banner appearance for this,
where it's at the bottom of the screen
with a background behind it.
To move it down there
we'll just add a spacer...
which will move the banner to the bottom
and our image to the top.
And to keep our image centered,
let's add another spacer above the image.
Spacers automatically have a minimum size
to maintain some padding between elements.
But in this case, we want the image
to be able to go all the way
to the edges of its container.
So let's set a minLength of zero
for these.
Let's also add some padding in our banner
so it still has some space
when it's visible
and doesn't go up against
the edge of the screen.
In the inspector...
I can just click this button
to turn on padding for this view.
That's better.
And let's turn up the font size as well.
Notice that not only
did the text size increase,
the symbol image did as well.
Symbol images automatically use
the same font information as text
to size themselves appropriately.
Let's use a headline font.
Now, to really make this screen spicy,
let's give it a red background.
A background modifier lets me put any view
behind the view that it's applied to.
These are commonly used with solid colors
to give a solid color background
to a view.
Well, we have red behind our view.
But why is it just this small region?
In SwiftUI, views size themselves
to fit their content.
So in this case the image and text
are their natural sizes,
and there's also space
for the padding we applied.
And just like earlier,
we can make this expand edge-to-edge
by adding spacers and an HStack.
Now, for a few finishing touches,
let's turn the foreground color
to be yellow
to match our spicy theme...
and update our font to use small caps.
Looking good.
Now we have our banner,
but we only want it to appear
when a sandwich is spicy.
How do we do that?
The declarative syntax we're using
makes that really easy.
We can just use an "if."
We'll check if our sandwich is spicy...
and if so, we'll show our banner.
To check this,
we can change our preview data
to show a different sandwich
that isn't spicy.
But even better,
we can set up our previews
to show multiple versions of our view.
I can click the plus button
to add another copy of this preview.
And I'll update the data we're using...
to show different sandwiches.
Now, we can see one version of our view
with a spicy banner
and one without.
That way, as we make edits, we can be sure
that both versions of our view
work the way we want.
And notice that the way Xcode
added another preview
is just by adding
another instantiation of our view.
I like this banner, but I don't want it
taking away space from the sandwich image
when we're zoomed in.
So let's hide the image when we're zoomed,
which we can do
just by updating our condition.
Now the banner shows and hides as we zoom.
And it even animates...
fading in and out.
We can also customize
that animation behavior
by setting a different transition.
Let's use ".move" on the bottom edge.
Now it slides out and slides back in.
And if you look closely while I tap
when the animation is still going...
notice that it turns around
and comes back.
No matter what I do,
everything stays interactive
and it always ends up in the right place.
And that's our detail view.
Let's review what we just built.
Our detail view is configured
with the sandwich to show.
And remember, that's a derived value
passed in by the parent of this view.
We also have our state property
for whether we're zoomed or not,
which is persisted by the framework
and controls our aspect ratio's
content mode.
And we have our banner,
which is only visible for spicy sandwiches
and only when they're not zoomed.
We're also specifying a transition
to make it slide in and out.
And what's actually happening
during that transition?
When it's removed, the view is animating
to a new position offscreen...
and SwiftUI waits
until it finishes that animation
to actually remove the view
from the hierarchy.
And when it's coming back,
SwiftUI inserts it offscreen
and then moves it back in
with an animation.
It's pretty amazing to be able to add
and remove views from a hierarchy
with an animation so easily.
And recall that this animation is always
interactive right out of the box.
This is where being data-driven,
instead of event-driven, really shines.
All those events Kyle talked about
can happen while this is animating too.
And animations beginning and ending
are even more events.
It's incredibly difficult
to build something like this
in an event-driven world,
but in SwiftUI it's just one line of code.
Now let's go back to our list
of sandwiches and finish up this app.
When we started, we used
a multi-platform app template,
but so far we've only been looking
at an iPhone.
How much work do we need to do
to run this on other platforms?
Let's see.
I'll switch my run destination
from an iPhone to an iPad...
and go live.
SwiftUI has converted our navigation view
into a split view,
so I can choose sandwiches on the left...
and show them on the right.
The one thing
that I'm noticing in my preview
is that when I don't have
a sandwich selected,
I just see a blank area.
I'd like to improve that
to show a placeholder
saying to select a sandwich.
All we have to do for that is to add
a second view in our navigation view.
Just like you can add multiple views
to stacks,
you can add multiple views here.
But instead of those views being stacked,
they're given to the navigation view
to be shown in the most appropriate way.
In this case,
the first view is shown on the left
and the second view becomes
the placeholder for the view on the right.
And on an iPhone
the placeholder is automatically removed
since it's not needed.
Let's look at what happens on macOS.
It's working great here too,
and we get the same placeholder,
shown here, as on iPad.
We're able to use the same view code,
model code and app code
between all Apple platforms.
And we can make
platform-specific improvements,
like this placeholder,
to go even further.
Over time, we need to be able to
change our list of sandwiches.
So let's add some editing support.
And while we're at it, let's also
make our data model a little more real.
Right now, the data in our app
is completely static.
We have this array of sandwiches...
and whatever we start with
is what we'll always have.
Let's update our model
to have a root store object
that will contain our sandwiches
and will be able to change over time.
I'm going to drag in
a pre-built model file
with our sandwich store.
And just so you know,
that store as in data store,
not a place that sells sandwiches.
Notice that our store is a mutable object
that contains our sandwiches.
And we also have a singleton instance
of that store for testing.
Now all we need to do is tell SwiftUI
when our object changes.
To do that, I'm going to make it conform
to the ObservableObject protocol.
Then I can just mark any properties
I want to observe with @Published.
So, how can we use our new model?
Just like we used @State
to make a source of truth for a value...
we can use @StateObject
to make a source of truth
for a mutable object.
StateObject will automatically
observe the object
to update our view when it changes.
And we could add that StateObject
here in our view code.
But since this is our app-wide store,
there's an even better place to put it--
in our app code.
Let's go back to our app code
to look more closely
and see how we can link it to our model.
This is the code we started with.
And notice that it's very similar to the
view code that we were just looking at.
We have a struct that conforms
to the app protocol...
and it has a body property,
where we build up what we want,
just like a view.
In this case we have a WindowGroup
which lets us specify
what view we want to use
for all windows in our app.
And one thing that's special about our app
is that we also have this @main attribute.
This just tells Swift that this struct
should be the starting point for our app.
I'll add our store
and a StateObject right here.
Apps can use State, StateObject
and other special properties
just like views.
Next, let's pass the store
to our view code.
We'll pass it to the view's initializer.
And back in our view code...
we'll replace the constant sandwiches...
with a property for our store.
Then we'll tell SwiftUI that we want to
observe this object for changes
by making it an ObservedObject.
And we'll update our list
to pull the sandwiches from the store.
Finally, let's also update our preview
to use our test store.
Great. Now we're pulling our data
from the store.
Which means we're ready
to add our editing support.
I'm going to drop in
some convenience functions
for making changes to our store
from a snippet.
There's one to add a new sandwich...
one to move sandwiches around
and one to delete sandwiches.
In our lists ForEach,
we can add an onMove modifier...
that calls our "moveSandwiches" method.
And we'll also add onDelete...
to call "deleteSandwiches."
And with just that change,
we can go back to our app...
and we're already able to swipe
to delete rows from our list.
Whenever we swipe to delete,
SwiftUI will call our callback...
which will remove the sandwich
from the store.
And our UI will automatically update
to show that change.
On macOS, this is all we need
for editing support.
But on iOS, we should add a way
to explicitly go into edit mode
in addition to swipe to delete.
So let's add an edit button
as a toolbar item.
I can use a toolbar modifier...
which lets us add any SwiftUI views
as toolbar items.
Inside of it I'll just add an edit button,
which is a control
that automatically toggles edit mode.
I only want this to appear on iOS,
so I'll add "if os(iOS)"
around that button...
so that it's only added
to the toolbar there.
Now let's toggle edit mode for our list.
Notice that all of our data rows
have editing controls,
and the static element at the bottom
does not.
SwiftUI automatically
shows the editing controls
only on the rows that need them
and omits them from the rows that don't.
We can reorder items...
and tap to delete them.
Let's also add a button
for adding new sandwiches.
I'll just add another view
in our toolbar modifier,
and for this one
I'll just make it a button
with a label of "Add"...
and an action that calls
our makeSandwich method.
Now we can tap our button...
and there's our new sandwich.
Let's quickly review
what we've just added.
We saw how to quickly add
editing operations to our list...
with just these modifiers...
and some simple functions
to change our data.
And remember how we made
our sandwich type identifiable earlier?
ForEach automatically watches
for changes to its collection
and synthesizes the correct
insertions and deletions for us
so we no longer need to tell the list
to add and remove rows,
which means we no longer have to worry
about getting data source
inconsistency exceptions.
We also used a toolbar modifier...
to add toolbar items for editing our list
and adding new items.
And that's our list.
We made this whole sophisticated list UI
with just this really minimal view code.
We were able to build up this app
really quickly.
But you might be thinking that
there's still a lot more work we need
to get it ready for customers.
These days support for Dynamic Type,
Dark Mode, localization and more
are expected for an app.
But with SwiftUI you get a lot more
support for these behaviors automatically.
And we can use previews
to really quickly test all of these.
Let's go to our preview and take a look.
I'm going to add a second preview
by clicking the preview's "plus" button.
Then I can click this "inspect" button
to configure the new preview.
I'll set the Dynamic Type size
to be a much larger value.
And everything looks great automatically.
Let's look at the code that got added
to change this preview.
Xcode just added a modifier
that's setting a value
in the environment of our previews.
The environment is a way you can set
contextual information about your views
that flows down the view hierarchy
and changes aspects
of any contained views at once.
It's great for making cascading changes
to a view and its children.
Let's add another preview instance.
And this time, in our preview inspector...
let's set the color scheme to "Dark."
Once again,
everything looks great automatically.
And finally, let's see how our app works
with other languages.
I have some English string files...
that I'll drop into our app.
Then I'll tell Xcode
that we want to localize these files.
Then I'll go to my project file...
and import a localization into Arabic.
Now, back in our view code,
let's add one more preview.
If we set the environment's
layout direction...
to be "rightToLeft"...
everything just works already,
which is great.
And finally, if we set the locale...
to be Arabic...
our app is localized.
But even better,
if you look back at our code...
we didn't do anything special
to support these features.
To get our text localizable,
we didn't have to mark up which strings
should be localizable or not.
SwiftUI automatically infers the text
with string literals, like "sandwiches,"
should be localized by default.
But text that's created from strings,
like our model values,
should be used as is.
And you can even use string interpolations
and have them localized correctly.
We're really excited for you
to start building apps with SwiftUI.
When you get all of these behaviors
for free,
you can concentrate on
the unique parts of your app
and build better apps for your customers
even faster.
Let's take one last pass through our app
to review what we built
and make sure everything is working right.
Let's use the Dark Mode version
and take our app live again.
But this time let's do it on a device.
I have an iPhone plugged in,
so let's just click this button...
to send our view to the device
to preview it there.
We have our list of sandwiches,
and we can tap on one
to see more information.
In our detail view,
we can tap to zoom to full screen,
which hides the "spicy" banner
with a transition.
And that animation is always interactive.
And we can edit our list to make changes.
Let's move this up.
And I'm a purist.
I don't think a hot dog
counts as a sandwich.
And we can add our new sandwich.
So there's our app.
But there's one last thing
that I want to point out,
and it's something we didn't see.
We just built up this entire application
and tested all of these rich behaviors
without ever once
building and running our app.
Xcode previews let us view, edit
and debug our applications
much faster than was ever possible before.
Thank you for watching, and I hope
you enjoy using SwiftUI as much as we do.