Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Izzy. I'm an engineer
on the iOS System Experience team.
This is the last in our series
of widget code-alongs.
We'll cover using URL sessions
from a widget extension.
It should be familiar,
but there's some new API just for widgets.
We'll use SwiftUI's Link API
to make regions of a widget tappable.
We'll add a widget bundle.
We can provide multiple kinds of widget
from the same extension,
which is super convenient.
And we'll look at how to provide
a dynamic set of options
for a widget configuration.
This session's a code-along.
We're picking up from where we left off
in the widgets code-along session,
so if you've been following along so far,
you're in the right spot.
If not, don't worry.
You can pick from the part-three target
in the sample project.
Since we're covering a lot of subjects
in this session,
I made a checklist for us.
We're starting at part three,
so let's jump in.
I've actually gone ahead and added
another widget to this project:
the Leaderboard widget.
Let's take a look.
We can see that it gives us
a list of characters sorted by health.
Let's talk about how it's doing that
for a minute.
Making network requests
is one of the fundamental ways
that a widget can get data.
You may have already noticed,
but the timeline provider API
is built with completion handlers
instead of return values
specifically to make doing
asynchronous tasks,
like network fetches, easy.
Here we have a loadLeaderboardData
asynchronous request
on our CharacterDetail object.
Let's take a look at the implementation.
You'll notice that
this is a normal URL session
making a normal data task request.
We're simulating a remote fetch
with a local file,
but you'd typically call
a remote Web service here.
The key thing to note is that this is
the normal in-process URL session API,
and it works just the same
as you would expect.
But what about background sessions?
You may be familiar with
other extension types
where a background URL session will launch
the extension's hosting app
when it completes.
That's not true for widgets.
The widget responds to
all the URL sessions it creates,
including background session.
But there's no app delegate.
So how does a widget know what to do?
There's a modifier on widget configuration
called onbackgroundURLSessionEvents,
and that's analogous to
the application delegate method.
You're provided the sessionIdentifier...
and a completion block.
And you'd manage those just the same
as you'd manage them in an app.
That's URL sessions.
Let's add our Leaderboard widget
to the Home Screen.
So this is nice,
but like the Character Detail widget,
I want to be able to tap each character
to launch to their specific detail screen.
Like widget URL, this is super simple.
All we have to do
is use the SwiftUI Link API.
Our leaderboard widget uses
this AllCharactersView.
So let's jump to the definition of that.
I can see by clicking this HStack
and the blue outlines that are reflected
in the SwiftUI preview
that my rows are this HStack.
And all we have to do
is embed this in a link...
with a destination of our character's URL.
Now let's build and run.
And now when I click my widget...
you can see that it highlights
that specific row,
and when I tap, I go directly
to that character's information.
That was Spouty, and now Egghead.
So that's using Link.
One thing you may have noticed is that
when I pulled up the widget gallery,
I only have a Leaderboard widget.
And that's because
I moved the main attribute
from the Ranger Detail widget
onto the Leaderboard widget.
By definition,
there can only be one main per process,
so we can't just add it in both places.
But what we can do
is make a widget bundle.
So all we have to do is add
both of our widgets to the widget bundle
and move our main attribute
from the Leaderboard widget...
onto the bundle.
Now, when I build and run...
and go the widget gallery...
I have my Leaderboard widget
and my Ranger Detail widget.
Great.
That's widget bundles.
In our previous session, we made a widget
configurable using a hard-coded list.
But what if we don't know
all of the options up front?
Because our configuration is
a SiriKit intent,
we can provide a dynamic list of options
with an Intent Extension
the same way we would
for other intent-based features.
I've already added the extension
to this project, but here's how you do it.
First you go to File, New, Target...
search for "Intent"...
and add an Intents Extension.
Pick Swift as a language.
Make sure your starting point is "none."
And that's all you need to do.
Now let's look at our Intent Definition.
It looks very similar
to our previous static Intent,
but "type" is now a custom type
instead of an enum.
Let's take a look
at what properties it comes with.
It has two properties:
identifier and displayString.
These are the default properties
a custom Intent type has,
but now, where do these values come from?
They come from the IntentHandler.
Here is where we provide
our dynamic set of options.
Note that this is an asynchronous call
like our timeline method.
We're already returning
a default set of characters,
but CharacterDetail has
a remoteCharacters list as well,
so let's add that here.
This would be like fetching
more information from the network.
Now let's update our widget
to use the dynamic Intent.
We can Edit All in Scope
our character selection Intent.
Because we no longer have an enum value,
we don't need this method anymore.
And our selected character
is the characterFromName.
And the name is the Intent identifier.
Let's see what this looks like.
Now, when I go to configure
my Character Detail widget...
I have our original options
of Power Panda, Egghead and Spouty,
but you can see we also have Mr. Spook,
Cake and Octo.
So Cake...
Okay.
But I want to keep an eye on Mr. Spook.
So I'm gonna put him on my Home Screen.
So now we have a widget
that uses URL sessions,
uses the new SwiftUI Link API,
has a bundle
with two kinds of widgets in it,
and we support dynamic configuration.
For a design perspective
on how to build great widgets,
see the "Design Great Widgets" talk,
and for applying those design guidelines
in SwiftUI,
see the "Build SwiftUI Views for Widgets,"
both talks from this year's WWDC.
Thanks so much for joining me.
You now have all the tools you need
to build amazing widgets.
I can't wait to see what you come up with.