Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. My name is Eric,
and I'll be joined by my colleague Nathan
to talk about accessibility design
for Mac Catalyst.
Mac Catalyst
has been a huge success for Apple.
It is incredibly easy to use,
and the developer communities
absolutely love it.
And we already have some of the best apps
on the App Store
that are made of Mac Catalyst.
And with all that great work out there,
it is important to make your app usable
for all of your customers.
And this is what brings us here today
to talk about accessibility.
At Apple,
accessibility is one of our core values.
We have an array of assistive technologies
on all of our platforms
to help people with disabilities.
Our accessibility team
has been working so hard
to make sure that all the great work
you've done for iOS accessibility
are converted to Mac Catalyst.
So, if you make your iOS app accessible,
it is automatically accessible
when bringing it to the Mac.
This is so that you can continue
to think in terms of iOS
when working on Mac Catalyst apps.
We'll first talk about how to optimize
your app experience for keyboard usage
by improving focus behavior
and adding keyboard shortcuts.
Then we'll walk through what you can do
to enhance your app's navigation
efficiency for assistive technologies.
And finally, we'll give you some tips
to test accessibility
on macOS for Mac Catalyst apps.
So let's start with keyboard usage.
On macOS, the keyboard isn't just
a supplementary interaction method
like it is on iPadOS.
Instead, it's the primary medium
users will interact with your app.
So the goal is to make
as many functionalities of your app
accessible with the keyboard.
And the first thing you could do
is to check keyboard focus.
Keyboard focus determines which UI element
is currently receiving inputs
from the keyboard,
and we want to make sure
that all UI elements of app
that could be interacted by the user
can become focused.
To demonstrate this, we will look at
a sample app called Roasted Beans.
It is a spin-off of the Peanut Butter app
that we made accessible in previous years.
While our Peanut Butter app
was a great success,
many were asking for a way
to find the ideal cup of coffee
to enjoy with their peanut butter toast.
So having finished building the iOS app
and making it accessible,
we now want to bring it to the macOS
using Mac Catalyst.
Let's see how this app interacts
with the keyboard.
To test this,
we first need to turn on a system setting
that enables keyboard interaction
with controls.
It is located
in the System Preferences app...
the Keyboard section,
and under Shortcuts menu.
With the checkbox, use keyboard navigation
to move focus between controls.
So go back to our app,
and see what happens if we press tabs.
We'll see that the add button
on the right of the navigation bar
now has a focus ring around it.
This means that the add button
has the keyboard focus,
and if you press the space bar,
the button will be activated.
The next tab highlights
the first item of the sidebar.
The users could press
up and down arrow keys
to change the selection of the table view.
And subsequent tabs highlights
the rest of the interactable controls
of the app,
the Share button, the Favorite button
and the Gift button.
Wow, that is awesome!
Without us doing any work,
UIKit already makes all of our controls
accessible with keyboard,
with tab keys looping us
through the controls of the app
and arrow keys changing the selection
of the table view.
Now, if you have a UITableView
or a UICollectionView
elsewhere in your app,
you might notice that arrow keys
don't move the selection.
And all you need to do
for arrow keys to change the selection
is to set this new API
selectionFollowsFocus to true
on your UITableView or CollectionView.
In our sample app, because our tableView
is a sidebar of a UISplitView,
UIKit sets this to true for us
so we don't need to do this step.
To learn more about how to further
customize your keyboard experience,
please check out the sample app
and watch the session
"What's New in Mac Catalyst."
Now we've made sure
that all of the interactable controls
of the app can take focus.
We can talk about the next thing
you could do about keyboard usage.
Add keyboard shortcuts.
Right now, in order for our users
to add a new coffee or rate a coffee,
they can only do so
by clicking on the screen.
For people who use assistive technologies,
finding on-screen UIs to interact
can become tedious.
So it would be nice
if they are able to perform actions
through a quick keyboard shortcut.
So let's see what we need to do
if we were to add a keyboard shortcut
for sharing a roast with friends.
To do that, I first need to find out
the best keyboard combination to use
because we want it to be as intuitive
as possible for the customers.
You can first check out
the Apple guideline
for a list of commonly used
keyboard shortcuts.
If your app has similar functionalities,
you could consider using these
keyboard combinations for the shortcuts
because users
are already familiar with them.
For us, sharing isn't on the list here,
so another way is to check out
the existing apps on the Mac
to see if they have something similar.
So I checked out the Safari app on the Mac
that everybody loves.
It uses Command-I
as a shortcut for sharing.
And I've just decided to do the same.
To do this, we first need to override
the buildMenu function in AppDelegate.
We need to create a UIKeyCommand
that responds to the keyboard shortcut.
We assign a localized string as the title,
because this would show up
in the menu bar.
Then we assign the action
that gets triggered for the command.
We need to create a UIKeyCommand
that responds to the keyboard shortcut.
We assign a localized string as the title,
because this would show up
in the menu bar.
Then we assign the action
that gets triggered for the command
and set the input to letter "I"
for modifierFlags command.
Then we need to create a UIMenu
that takes the shareCommand
as the only child for the menu,
and insert this new menu item
to an appropriate place on the menu bar.
For this demo, I chose to insert it
at the end of the edit menu.
Now if you open the edit menu,
you would see that
our new keyboard shortcut, Share,
appears nicely under the edit menu,
and it can be accessed
by pressing Command-I.
And don't forget that all the great work
you are optimizing for Mac Catalyst
are also great optimizations
for full keyboard access on iOS,
which is a feature that allows users
to use the device with just the keyboard.
In addition,
your app can get the exact keyCode
from a UIPress object
starting in iOS 13.4.
This is useful if you're developing
a game, for example,
because this API gives you
the full control of the keyboard.
And don't forget to check out
our sample app for these usages.
For a quick recap,
a great app designed for the keyboard
is a great app for accessibility.
It is important to make sure
that interactable controls
are accessible with keyboard focus.
And we recommend you to add some
useful keyboard shortcuts for your app.
So that's it for keyboard usage.
Next, I will hand it over
to my colleague, Nathan,
to talk about how you can improve
navigation efficiency
for assistive technologies.
Thanks, Eric.
Hey, folks, my name is Nathan.
I'm a software engineer
on the Accessibility Team.
My team and I
have been working really hard
to improve
how our macOS assistive technologies
are going to interact
with your Catalyst apps.
Like Eric touched on earlier,
making your app accessible
is to make it usable for everyone.
Part of making your app usable
is to give users
an efficient way to access content.
Today we'll focus on VoiceOver.
It's a screen reader that exists
on all of our platforms,
and it allows users with low or no vision
to interact with your app
by reading out content on screen.
VoiceOver does this through interacting
with a tree of accessibility elements
based off of your user interface.
On macOS, you might be delivering
a more complex app
with a bigger user interface,
to take advantage
of the additional screen real estate.
With a more complex interface,
it means there's even more accessibility
elements for VoiceOver to navigate.
This means users need
an efficient way to navigate
or they could begin to feel overwhelmed.
That's why today, I'm very excited
to talk to you about accessibility groups.
It's a strategy you can use to improve
your app's navigation for VoiceOver users.
We've made it possible to use grouping
to deliver a more native macOS experience.
But before we can talk about
improving navigation efficiency,
it's important to first understand
how VoiceOver sees your app.
This is how VoiceOver sees your app.
It's what we call the accessibility tree.
It's a collection of elements
that are visible
by all of our assistive technologies.
Views that are accessibility elements
are determined
by the isAccessibilityElement property.
Each element is a leaf node,
which results
in a single-level tree of elements.
This model works great on iOS.
Users navigate with a touchscreen,
which means they can navigate elements
one by one
or quickly jump to them
by tapping them on screen.
However, on macOS,
VoiceOver users navigate using a keyboard.
Without a touchscreen,
they cannot quickly jump between elements.
So if we were to use the same model,
all accessibility elements
would have to be navigated one by one.
To illustrate this navigation challenge,
let's take a look
at the accessibility elements
in our Roasted Beans app.
Here you can see there are
26 visible accessibility elements.
That means there's at least 26 elements
a user would have to navigate through
at any given time.
Imagine if it took you
26 keystrokes in Xcode
to reach that Compile button.
You would probably find programming
quite a bit more challenging.
While a keyboard shortcut could be added
so that navigation
to a specific element isn't required,
it won't solve every use case.
So what can we do
to improve this experience?
What if we were to take inspiration
from a dinner menu?
Instead of the menu presenting
a long list of every dish,
they are categorized
into relatable sections,
such as salads, main course
and side dishes.
This would allow a VoiceOver user
to navigate between groups
before navigating individual elements
in a specific group.
We can apply this same idea
to the accessibility tree.
You can define a relation between elements
through the use
of accessibility containers.
When you set accessibilityContainerType
on an element,
our assistive technologies
will be able to use that information
to provide a better navigation experience
for the accessibility elements
it contains.
You may have already known
about the accessibility container API
and how it helps users on iOS navigate.
For example, it allows them
to perform a touch gesture
to navigate to the first accessibility
element in the next container.
VoiceOver would then focus
on elements like this.
Since our goal here was to improve
navigation efficiency for Mac Catalyst,
VoiceOver on macOS
will leverage this same API,
but adapt the behavior.
Accessibility containers on macOS
will behave as an accessibility element.
This means VoiceOver can navigate focus
to the container itself.
From here, users can choose to skip past
the container to the next element
or interact with a container,
allowing for exclusive navigation
of the containers' accessibility elements.
So when I say accessibility containers
will behave as an accessibility element,
this is because
when we build the accessibility tree
for a Mac Catalyst app,
the container becomes
its own node on the tree
and its accessibility elements
become their own subtree.
This structure closely aligns with
the accessibility API built around AppKit.
Its model works great for macOS
because it significantly reduces
the number of accessibility elements
a user needs to navigate
at any given time.
The key takeaway here
is that accessibility containers
are an accessibility element
on Mac Catalyst,
so ensuring you have
set standard accessibility properties
such as accessibility label
on your containers is essential.
Looking back to our Roasted Beans app,
what would we see
now that the accessibility containers
behave as an independent node
in the accessibility tree?
Here you can see
a dramatic efficiency improvement.
This reduces the number
of visible elements from 26 to 8.
Now that we've seen how much of an impact
accessibility containers
have on navigation,
let's take a few moments
to discuss the different types
and when you should use them.
Data tables are specifically
for when your container,
such as a graph,
adopts the UIAccessibilityContainer
DataTable protocol.
Lists are for ordered content.
These are primarily used in web pages
or in a PDF's table of contents.
Landmarks are containers
used specifically for web pages and tvOS.
Lastly, semanticGroups
are a general container type on iOS.
On iOS, their accessibility label
will be spoken the first time
VoiceOver users focus on an element
within that container.
On macOS, their label will be spoken when
VoiceOver focuses on the container itself.
So in our case, we want to be using
the semanticGroup type
to improve the navigation experience.
While grouping can greatly improve
the navigation experience,
I want to be sure that you understand
that too much grouping can overcomplicate
the navigation of your app.
Since each accessibility container
becomes a node in the accessibility tree,
elements within the container
are not discoverable
unless a VoiceOver user
explicitly interacts with the group.
So let's take a look at a few examples
to see when we should group elements.
To start things off, elements belonging
to the same functional section
should be grouped.
But how do we discover
these functional sections?
Let's take a look at Swift Playgrounds,
a recent Mac Catalyst app.
Imagine you have a friend
who just started learning how to code.
They open up Swift Playgrounds
and start one of their first lessons
and unfortunately, they get stuck
on one of the problems.
But luckily for them,
they have you to call upon.
Imagine yourself
talking to them over the phone.
How would you help them navigate the app?
You might ask, "Do you see
a list of chapters on the left?
Which chapter are you on?
In the world view on your right,
which tile
is your character byte standing on?"
Or maybe you're trying to teach them
more about writing code,
in which case you could separate
the middle into two functional groups,
the top being the editor
where you write code
and the bottom being
the auto-complete suggestions.
By walking through
how you might verbally describe your app,
you can more easily identify
these functional sections
that should be placed
into accessibility containers.
Another instance of when
you should use accessibility containers
are when they are related by type
or functional purpose.
For example, UINavigationBar,
UITabBar,
UICollectionView and UITableView
are some of the standard UIKit views
that are accessibility containers
of type semanticGroup by default.
So if you have created
your own custom UI elements
that act as tab bars or navigation bars,
please follow
the expected default behavior
by configuring it
as an accessibility container.
Now let's step through an example
in our Roasted Beans app
to see how easy it to improve the
navigation experience in your own apps.
Starting on the left,
we have a UITableView.
It's an accessibility container
of type semanticGroup by default.
Recall that accessibility containers
are an independent accessibility element
for our Mac Catalyst app.
Which means that just like
any other accessibility element,
we recommend giving the container
a localized accessibility label.
In this case,
"Coffee list" would be appropriate.
Since our UITableView
maintains some state
about which coffee is selected,
we could make this label even better
by adding which coffee is selected
to the label.
Here is a great time to take a moment
to pause and remind everyone
of the importance of adding
great accessibility labels to their apps.
To learn how to make
great accessibility labels,
we have a presentation from 2019
which I encourage for you to watch.
Coming back to our app,
what about the details view on the right?
It's a functional section
that holds all the information
related to the select coffee.
Because the details view
isn't already grouped,
because we did not use a UITableView
or UICollectionView,
we have to manually define
these accessibility containers.
Today I'll show you how easy it can be
to take something like our availability UI
and make it a container.
We implemented this
as a series of UILabels
in a vertical UIStackView.
This means a user would have to
navigate through each element.
We could make
this navigation experience better
by adding an accessibility container,
so the VoiceOver users can quickly
navigate past the entire list.
From here, in just a few lines,
we can make the UIStackView
an accessibility container
and give it an accessibility label
that describes the group.
These are some fantastic improvements
to our app.
By placing these related elements
into groups,
we can greatly improve how VoiceOver users
will navigate our Mac Catalyst app.
And so I hope you take away the importance
of adding accessibility containers
to your app.
It's a small change you can make
that will greatly improve
the navigation experience
on macOS and on iOS.
Please ensure
that your accessibility containers
have a concise localized label
that describes the group
and includes any important details
regarding the containers' state.
That's all I have for you today
regarding navigation efficiency.
I'll now pass things back to Eric,
where he will show you
how to test your Mac Catalyst app
for accessibility.
Thank you, Nathan.
With all the great work that you've done
to improve
your accessibility app experience,
now is a great time to talk about
testing on the macOS platform.
When bringing apps from iOS to the Mac,
you think of the app as an iOS app
from the inside,
but a Mac app on the outside,
because it is running
on the macOS platform.
As it happens, when you work
with accessibility APIs from UIKit,
our team automatically converts
your iOS accessibility code to macOS
without you having to do any work,
so that you can continue
to think about iOS.
To help you better understand
what's going on under the hood,
we've improved the Accessibility Inspector
for Mac Catalyst apps,
and now it shows you the iOS APIs
when running on macOS.
If you have not used
Accessibility Inspector before,
I highly recommend you
to watch these two videos,
"Auditing Your Apps for Accessibility"
and "Accessibility Inspector."
Together they will give you
a complete guide
on how Accessibility Inspector
can help you
find and fix accessibility issues
for your apps
across all Apple platforms.
So now let's see
how to use the Accessibility Inspector
to audit your app accessibility
on Mac Catalyst.
If we use the Inspector
to inspect the elements for the cell,
we can see the element has a proper label
that describes the title of the coffee
and a proper value
that describes the rating.
We also see
that there's a new Catalyst section
that shows accessibility traits,
container types from iOS.
If we then use the Command-Control-Up,
the Inspector would then inspect
the parent of the cell element,
which serves as the container.
We could verify that
this is the correct element to inspect
by checking the element class.
In this case, the class name shows
that this is the element
that we translated
for the tableView class.
All classes from UIKit
will be eventually translated
to a Mac platform element.
In addition, Inspector tells you
the view controller of the view
if it has one.
In this case, it is
the RBListViewController from the app.
To make sure that VoiceOver
reads the container,
we can make sure
that the tableView container
has a proper label
which is a localized coffee list.
It also has the correct container type
which is a semanticGroup.
And starting this year,
Accessibility Inspector would tell you
the automation type for all elements.
In this case, it is a table,
so that you know
exactly how to find it in XCUI tests.
So that's a brief overview
of some of the additional things
you can do with Accessibility Inspector
for Mac Catalyst apps.
We hope you enjoyed it.
So we've covered a lot today
for accessibility in Mac Catalyst.
To wrap up, we first discussed
how a great keyboard app
is a great app for accessibility
by making sure the controls of the app
is accessible by keyboard focus
and adding keyboard shortcuts.
Then we showed you
how you can improve navigation efficiency
for assistive technologies
for Mac Catalyst apps.
We learned how the existing iOS API
accessibilityContainerType
can make a much bigger impact on the Mac,
and how you should adopt it in your app.
And our last piece of advice
is to use the Accessibility Inspector.
This is a great tool that we created
to help developers like you.
So thank you for joining us,
and we hope this presentation
will help you create
a better accessibility experience
for Mac Catalyst apps.