Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to
"Synchronize Health Data with HealthKit".
My name is Netra,
and I'm a software developer
on the HealthKit team.
Our users store their most private
and personal information on our devices
in the form of health data.
On Apple platforms,
HealthKit is the foundation
that provides easy access to this data.
HealthKit also enables
all of the rich experiences
you have created in your apps.
As a result, we are all part
of this large health ecosystem.
The goal of this health ecosystem
is to empower our users.
Our users may access their health data
from any part of this ecosystem.
From Apple Watch,
from the apps released by Apple
all from all your amazing apps.
As such, we never want
to surprise our users
with the changes we make
to their health data.
While we all want to be good citizens
of this health ecosystem,
it can get quite challenging.
In this talk, we here at HealthKit
are going to help you do just that.
So let's remember that our goal
is to empower our users.
Users must always remain
in control of their data
and changes to health data
must always reflect user intent.
Today, we look at two important topics.
First, we look at monitoring changes
in HealthKit.
We know that data can be read or written
from any part of the health ecosystem.
This health data can be used
to power multiple types of apps
or data visualizations.
Our apps must be equipped
to react appropriately
to the changes in HealthKit.
We will then dive into maintaining
an external data store
in sync with HealthKit,
and we'll see how HealthKit
can make this really easy for you.
We'll begin with our first topic,
monitoring changes in HealthKit.
Let's build an app
to work through these concepts.
This is an app for patients
recovering from an injury.
This app let's patients track
their daily step count.
As time goes on,
they want to monitor
the progress in their daily step count.
Additionally, our patient also visits
the physical therapist
a couple of times a week
and completes certain walking tests.
The test is a six-minute
walking distance test.
It measures the distance
covered by a patient
while walking on a flat surface
for six minutes.
The physical therapist enters
the results of this test on their machine
and data is synced over
to the user's iPhone as a weekly report.
One of the best ways to monitor
such important data is via a graph.
A patient can easily see the uptrend
or downtrend in their steps count
with out being too concerned
with actual values.
Here we have a graph
that is of great interest to our patient
and the physical therapist.
It tracks the patient's total step count
over each day of the past week.
Now steps can be recorded
from both Apple Watch and iPhone.
We want to ensure that we get
an accurate count of steps taken in a day.
The first thing you do
when creating a graph like this
is to reach for
the HKStatisticsCollectionQuery.
This is the first query you should
reach for when creating most graphs.
You might have already learned
all about this query
in our previous talk,
"Getting Started with HealthKit".
If not, and if it is new to you,
you might want to go
watch that talk first.
In fact, we'll use the SmoothWalker app
created in that talk to build our app.
The graphs that we just created
need to be sent to the remote server
so that the physical therapist
who is interested in the user's progress
can read them as well.
How would this look like?
First, we'd send our initial
graph of the week to the server.
Next, if there are any changes
to the data for the week,
for instance, with more steps collected,
the new data for the week
would have to be sent over to the server.
For our purposes here,
we are considering the external data
to be a remote server,
but it might as well be
an external database
maintained locally on the device.
It could be using Core Data
or even a SQLite database.
Now we know that we can use
the HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
to load data,
we'd need to run the query
at a regular cadence to fetch new data.
This could be at app launch
and maybe every few hours after that.
But there are some downsides
to using it for reacting to new changes.
If data does not change often enough,
we would be running
the HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
multiple times,
leading to redundant calculations.
We would also be sending
all the data every single time.
This would be a waste
of network resources.
HealthKit has another tool
specifically for use cases like this.
It's called the HKAnchoredObjectQuery.
The HKAnchoredObjectQuery
allows us to monitor updates
to the health database.
It provides a snapshot of changes
in the health database.
This snapshot includes both
new samples and deleted samples.
Let's see how this query works.
As the name suggests,
an anchored object query
requires an anchor.
An anchor represents
a specific point in time
in the evolution of the health database.
Health data could have been added
or deleted after this point in time.
This anchor allows you to identify
all the samples you last received
from this query.
When you provide HealthKit
with this anchor,
HealthKit will only return
the changes since that point.
Now, initially, for the first query
our anchor will be nil.
HealthKit at this time
has samples A, B and C.
When you execute the query,
HealthKit returns all the data
based on the data type you specified.
In this case, you will receive
samples A, B and C in your updateHandler.
The anchor is updated,
and HealthKit gives you
the new anchor in the updateHandler.
It is the last point in time
that HealthKit returns samples
in the updateHandler.
Let's say there were more samples added
since your updateHandler was last called.
These include samples D and E.
Additionally, sample B
has since been deleted.
For every subsequent query run,
only the changes since the previous anchor
will be returned in the updateHandler.
These will include samples D and E,
the deletion of sample B,
but nothing about A and C.
When we use the HKAnchoredObjectQuery
or any query in HealthKit,
we must think a little
about the type of data
and use case we are dealing with.
In the case of steps, we don't really care
about the actual samples itself.
In fact, Apple Watch
was released five years ago now.
That's a lot of data
being generated by these devices.
That's a lot of data to sync up.
We just want a cumulative statistic,
not every single sample.
There are other cases where we might care
about the individual samples.
These could be samples
that are not generated very often.
Each data type can be treated differently.
We must spend some time
thinking about how we want to query
and sync our data.
The task we are trying to accomplish
drives the type of query we want.
Querying for the minimal amount of data
has its performance benefits as well.
For our current use case,
we just want the statistical graph
to be available to the physical therapist.
How do we do this?
We can always run over our samples
from the HKAnchoredObjectQuery
and compute the graph.
But why not make
the two queries work together?
With the anchored object query,
we can set our predicate and sample type
to exactly what we are looking for.
When the anchored object query
updates you with changes in HealthKit,
you can look at the dates
of the returned samples
and use that to create and run
the statistics collection query.
The statistics returned for those days
can then be sent to the remote computer
as updated graph data.
Now we just send
the new data to the server.
This, again,
might be a local Core Data model
or an NSURLSession for a remote server.
To understand this better,
we'll take a look at
how this would look like in code.
First, we'll set the parameters
for the anchored object query.
The sample type is step count.
We'll set the anchor parameter
using the PersistedAnchor.
Persisting the anchor
allows us to only retrieve
the changes in HealthKit
since the last query.
We need the same behavior
for the initialResultsHandler
and the updateHandler,
and so we'll set the same block
for the handler variable.
In the handler, we'll unwrap
the samples returned from HealthKit.
We'll create a predicate from the samples.
This might be the dates
for which the samples were retrieved.
This is the predicate we'll be using
to initialize
our statistics collection query.
Here we also need to update
the PersistedAnchor.
At the end of this block,
we can call the fetchStatistics method
that creates
the HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
using the predicate.
We'll initialize the HKAnchoredObjectQuery
with the parameters we set.
These include sample type,
a nil predicate, the anchor
and lastly, the resultsHandler
and the updateHandler.
Finally, we'll execute the query
on the healthStore.
Let's see how
the fetchStatistics method creates
the HKStatisticsCollectionQuery.
Once again, we set our parameters.
We want our statistics collection query
bucketed by days.
To achieve this, we'll set the anchor date
to Monday at midnight
and an interval parameter of one day.
The sample type
will once again be step count.
We can then initialize
the HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
with these parameters.
The options will be cumulativeSum
since we want a total step count
for each day.
As you can see, we have provided
the predicate created in
the anchored object query over here.
In our initialResultsHandler,
we unwrap the statisticsCollection
and then simply send over this data
to our remote server.
And as always, we only get our updates
after we execute the query
on the healthStore.
We just saw how you can send data
from HealthKit to an external server.
Now we need to get to the next step,
which is receiving data
from the external store
and saving it to HealthKit as well.
Like we saw earlier, our patient visits
the physical therapist's office
a couple of times a week
and completes six-minute walk tests.
The six-minute walk test
is the amount of distance
covered by an individual
while walking for six minutes
on a flat surface.
It is often used by physical therapists
to gauge their patient's
exercise capacity.
This year, we introduced a new set
of mobility types in HealthKit.
One of the data types
is the six-minute walk test distance.
These work perfectly
for the purposes of our app.
We can save test data
received from the physical therapist
as six-minute walk test distance samples.
In our app, the physical therapist
records these six-minute walk test values
and a weekly report is synced
to the patient's device.
The weekly report contains a graph
of the six-minute walk test distance
for each day of the week.
We also have the individual samples
from the graph displayed underneath it.
This is in case the physical therapist
or patient
wants to dig deeper
into each individual test result.
This takes us back to the idea
that each data type
needs to be treated differently.
We must think about the type of data we
are dealing with and what our use case is.
The sixMinuteWalkTestDistance
is not written to HealthKit
very frequently,
and the patient or the physical therapist
might be interested
in each individual test sample.
So, unlike steps, which we saw earlier,
in this graph
it is worth plotting each sample.
Earlier, we were syncing step samples
from the device to a remote server.
Now we have this weekly report
on the physical therapist's server.
We want to sync it from the server
to the patient's device
and save the corresponding samples
in HealthKit.
This will allow the patient to view
their sixMinuteWalkTestDistance graph
on their app
along with the individual test samples.
When saving changes to HealthKit,
there are a couple things to keep in mind.
We only want to save incremental samples
in HealthKit.
Simply removing
and then re-saving all the data
can result in an inconsistent state
of the user's health data.
New samples reflect new health data
about the user,
for instance, a new six-minute walk test
or new steps covered.
Maybe even the change in weight
recorded by the user.
When deleting a sample, you need
to ensure that it is actually a sample
that was previously written by your app.
You can't delete data
you didn't explicitly save yourself.
A good best practice here is to first
query for the sample and then delete it.
Adding or deleting a sample
should always reflect user intent.
If the user didn't mean
to delete a sample,
then you should probably
not be deleting it.
Now there are some challenges
that arise here.
What if the physical therapist
wanted to update a specific test?
For example,
for a test on the 18th of June,
the patient covered 400 meters
in a six-minute walking test.
This data was later updated
by the physical therapist
to reflect an error.
The distance covered
was actually 450 meters.
Now this can be a little tricky.
When you edit a sample, you need
to actually delete and add a new sample.
If you don't,
you could be saving duplicated samples.
This means
you have to query for the sample,
match it to the exact sample
the physical therapist had edited
and then save a new sample.
If there are no edits needed to be made
to the other samples,
you need to make sure
that during your changes
you are not saving a duplicated sample
for any of those either.
Health data is available
on all of the patient's devices:
their iPhones and their Apple Watches.
The change in samples need to be
reflected correctly across all devices.
If you have saved a sample on one device,
you need to make sure that you are not
saving the sample again on another device.
All this time, you have to ensure that
you're correctly reflecting user intent.
This may appear to be really complex,
but HealthKit actually makes this
really easy for you.
HealthKit contains two metadata keys
known as the HKMetadataSyncIdentifier
and the HKMetadataSyncVersion.
The sync identifier is a string,
and the version is a number.
The identifier allows us to recognize
a sample anywhere in the health ecosystem
across any of the user's devices.
The version helps us understand
when the sample has been updated.
When you set a sync identifier
on a sample,
HealthKit ensures
that duplicate copies of the sample
are not saved
in the user's health database.
A combination of the sync identifier
and the version
allows HealthKit to update samples only
when the version number has increased.
Additionally, all operations done using
sync identifiers are transaction safe.
That means if there was any error,
you can be rest assured that your data
is in a consistent state.
Health data is available
on all of the user's devices.
Sync identifiers
allow you to maintain samples
in a consistent state across devices.
In your remote server, you have a sample
with an identifier and a version one.
Your app syncs a sample from
the remote server to the patient's iPhone.
Considering that this is the first sample,
HealthKit saves it successfully.
Now when HealthKit realizes
a new sample has been saved,
it syncs this over
to all of the patient's devices.
If the patient had an Apple Watch,
it would sync it over to the Watch.
If your remote server were also
syncing data to your app on Watch
and you try to save the sample again,
HealthKit would see that the sample
already exists and ignore it.
Now if the physical therapist decides
to update the distance completed
in the six-minute walk test,
we would update the sample
by keeping the sync identifier consistent
but increasing the version number.
When this sample is synced
to the patient's device,
HealthKit notices
that the version number has increased.
It overwrites the previous sample
with the new sample.
The sample will again be synced
to all of the patient's devices.
If the remote server syncs the version two
of the sample to Apple Watch,
HealthKit would see
that the sample already exists
and ignore the sample.
As you can see, HealthKit will manage
all the conflict resolution
while saving and syncing.
The challenging task of versioning
and syncing has been reduced
to simply maintaining
consistent identifiers.
We saw the patient's weekly report
earlier,
but how do we go about
actually modeling this data?
One way to do this is by representing
the weekly report as a report class.
This report class can be identified
with a high-level sync identifier.
The report class will contain a list
of all the sixMinuteWalkTestDistance
samples from that week.
Each sample can then contain
a sync identifier metadata key
which is derived
from the high-level report identifier.
This way, each sample can be uniquely
referenced across different weeks.
Data can be synced from the remote server
to the patient's device
in the form of this report class model,
and individual HK samples from this list
can be saved to HealthKit.
Let's take a look at this in a demo.
We have already created this app,
SmoothWalker,
in our previous talk
"Getting Started with HealthKit."
This project is also available
for download as sample code
on the Developer website.
We want to create this weekly report
view controller in our app.
When you press the Fetch button,
we want to pull the six-minute walk
samples from the server
and populate our view controller with it.
Let's take a look at the
WeeklyReportTableViewController class.
When we select the Fetch button,
the didTapFetchButton method
will be called.
Here we want to pull the server response
from the network.
We then want to call
the handleServerResponse method
with the serverResponse.
Let's implement
the handleServerResponse method.
Here we want to pull the weekly report
from the serverResponse
and save the corresponding samples
to HealthKit.
The first thing we'll do is to pull
the weekly report from the serverResponse.
After this, we loop over all the samples
in the weekly report.
As you can see here, we are
looping over the weekly report samples
and returning an HKQuantitySample
for each of them.
In this loop, first we'll set
the parameters for HKQuantitySample.
We have a quantity which has a unit meter,
and the value is pulled
from the serverHealthSample.
The sampleType
is sixMinuteWalkTestDistance.
And finally, we have
the start and end date.
We'll then initialize our
HKQuantitySample with these parameters.
We have the sample type, the quantity,
the start and end date,
and, for now, the metadata is "nil."
The samples returned from the loop
need to be saved to HealthKit.
So now, we'll save the samples
to HealthKit.
As you can see, we have saved
all these samples using the healthStore,
and the completion handler
will load the new data from HealthKit
to the view controller.
Let's run this code
and see what it looks like.
When we select the Fetch button,
the view controller is populated
with the samples from the weekly report.
However,
when we select the Fetch button again,
we can see that duplicated samples
are saved to HealthKit.
This is incorrect.
We don't want duplicated data
in HealthKit.
Let's see how this changes
when we include metadata
in the HKQuantitySample.
We create a metadata dictionary
and add it to our list of parameters.
We'll pull the sync identifier
from the serverHealthSample
and add it to the key,
the HKMetadataKeySyncIdentifier.
Similarly, we'll also pull the
syncVersion from the serverHealthSample
and add it to the key,
the HKMetadataKeySyncVersion.
We'll then add this metadata dictionary
to our list of parameters
in the HKQuantitySample.
Let's run this code again
and see what it looks like.
For the purposes of this demo,
I've added code to delete
all the six-minute walk samples
in HealthKit on app launch.
However, let's remember
that when deleting samples,
always be careful and ensure
that we're reflecting user intent.
Now, on selecting Fetch,
the six-minute walk samples
are displayed in the weekly report.
On selecting Fetch
multiple times, however,
there are no duplicated samples.
As you can see, saving a sample
with the HKMetadataSyncIdentifier
and the HKMetadataSyncVersion
ensures that there are
no duplicated samples in HealthKit.
We have now modeled
the data backing this graph.
Synchronizing your external data
with HealthKit
is not as challenging
as it might appear to be.
HealthKit provides the tools that
allow you to efficiently monitor changes
in the health ecosystem,
as well as maintain your data consistently
across multiple devices.
Let me leave you with some best practices
when working on synchronizing
your health data.
When making changes to users' data,
ensure that you're always reflecting
user intent.
Users should not be taken aback
or surprised by the changes
to their health data.
Think about ways
in which you can run efficient queries.
Maybe you can consider combining queries
to fetch and sync minimal amount of data.
Finally, since health data exists
across multiple devices,
use sync identifiers and version numbers
to keep data consistent across devices.
We have only touched a small part of
the health ecosystem on Apple platforms,
but there is much more you can do here.
When working with health data,
think about the security and privacy
implications of what you are trying to do.
This is especially important
if we're maintaining health data
on an external data store.
Apple has a lot of resources
that can help you with this.
If you want to create the beautiful graph
visualizations we showed you today,
take a look at the CareKit framework.
CareKit is an open-source framework
for developing apps
specifically around managing your health
and providing care.
Finally,
HealthKit has multiple other features
that you can use
to create rich health experiences.
These range from workouts,
clinical health records
and high-frequency data types.
We are so excited to see the amazing apps
that you create
using all these HealthKit resources.
Thank you so much for watching.
I hope you have a great WWDC.