Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Dale Taylor,
and I'm an engineer on the tvOS team.
Today I'm going to talk to you
about Search.
In tvOS 14, we've made it even better.
Here's how Search looks in our TV app.
We've increased the size of the text
in the search field
so it's easy to see what you've typed.
And in many languages, we've optimized
the keyboard layout to one line.
That leaves more space
for your search results.
Some apps, like our music app,
take advantage
of our new search suggestions feature.
These suggestions
allow you to minimize typing
and find what you're looking for
even faster.
If you're already using
UISearchController,
you get most of what you've seen here
for free.
For those of you that aren't, let's review
how simple it is to add to your app.
Let me show you.
We have a simple tab-based app here
with photos and videos
from travel over the years.
As a reminder, tvOS apps work best
with a NavigationController
as the root view controller
that contains a UITabBarController.
Let's head to Xcode
and look at adding SearchUI to our app.
First, let's add a new view controller
to go in our tab bar.
We can call it "Search View Controller."
Then we'll set up
some basic functionality.
We can configure a tabBarItem.
We'll use the search SystemItem
because that's the platform convention
for indicating a search tab.
Now let's add our search controller.
Since we're adding this
as a child view controller,
we'll want to put this
in a UISearchContainerViewController.
First, let's set up some constants
to hold our variables.
Then we can create instances
of our SearchController
and SearchContainerViewController.
We'll want to add that as a child view
controller as well in viewDidLoad.
To show our search results,
we'll need a search results controller.
We have one already made
named "GridViewController"
with a simple collection view
and an items property.
Anything we set on the items property
will show up in our collection view.
Let's start by defining a constant.
[typing]
Then we can create an instance
of this view controller
and pass it to our UISearchController.
[typing]
We'll also want our search controller
to scroll along with our collection view
when we scroll through the search results.
The searchControllerObservedScrollView
in viewDidLoad.
We'll want to update the contents
of the results view controller
when our search results change.
Let's start by making our controller
conform to UISearchResultsUpdating.
[typing]
Then we can set ourselves as the
search results updater in viewDidLoad.
Then we can handle updates from our search
controller in UpdateSearchResults.
We can filter out the data,
and we can set those results
on our search results controller.
Finally, we can go to our app delegate
and we can add our new view controller
to our tab bar.
Let's give it a try.
If I swipe over to search,
you can see what we've built.
If we try searching now...
we can see it filter our search results.
Now let's talk about what we can do
to make it even better.
You may remember that I mentioned
search suggestions earlier.
Before I show you how easy they are
to implement in our sample app,
let me tell you a little bit
about how to use them.
We've added a new class,
UISearchSuggestionItem.
It's a model that represents
the search suggestion in the UI.
It supports an image, text
and a description for accessibility.
To display these, you just assign them
to the new search suggestions property
on your UISearchController.
If you have your own object,
feel free to use that as well,
as long as it conforms
to the UISearchSuggestion protocol.
Here's an example of how you'd use it.
You can just create
UISearchSuggestionItems
with the optional properties
and assign an array of suggestions
to the search controller.
Now that you know how to add search
suggestions to your search controller,
how do you make them update dynamically?
You'll use the UISearchResultsUpdating
protocol
that I mentioned earlier in the demo.
You'll recall this gets assigned
to the searchResultsUpdater property
on UISearchController.
In the demo, we used this protocol
to handle text input updates
with UpdateSearchResults
for SearchController.
We used the search term from
the search bar to query our data source.
We've extended this protocol in tvOS 14
to handle search suggestions.
When someone using the app
selects a search suggestion,
you can respond to it in
updateSearchResults for searchController
selecting searchSuggestion.
This is useful
because the search suggestion
can contain more information
than just the search term.
For instance,
you could use the suggestion's image
to differentiate between content types.
Now that I've given you a brief overview
of how search suggestions work,
let me show you how to add them to our
sample project where we integrated Search.
Our data source has the capability
of giving us suggested search results.
Let's start by making our SuggestedEntry
conform to UISearchSuggestion.
[typing]
We can define properties
for the localizedSuggestion
and iconImage.
And we'll fill out a description
for accessibility as well.
You'll notice that for our iconImage,
we're returning a different image,
whether it's a video or a photo,
that way we can see that
in our suggestion when it's onscreen.
Now we can go back
to our search controller
and display these suggestions
in our search UI.
All we have to do is assign them
to the search suggestions property
when the input changes.
We can fill in our empty parameter
for suggestions.
And then we can assign the suggestions
to our searchController.
[typing]
If no one's typed anything,
we don't need any suggestions,
so we'll assign an empty array.
[typing]
Now let's run our app
and see how it looks.
If we navigate over to the search tab
and start typing,
we can see the suggestions populate
as we type.
Let's see what happens
if I click a suggestion.
Hmm. I clicked on the suggestion
for videos named "Blue,"
so I shouldn't have any photos
in my search results.
No problem. That's an easy fix.
Let's head back to our search controller.
We can adopt the new method
in UISearchResultsUpdating
to handle the search suggestion
being selected.
Then we can check to see if our suggestion
was for a video suggestion.
If it was, we'll update our search results
accordingly.
We can navigate back to the search tab,
start typing "blue"
and select our suggestion
for "Blue" video.
You'll notice that now we only see videos
when selecting that suggestion.
That's exactly what we wanted.
We've worked hard
to make UISearchController
as easy to use as possible.
But here are a few suggestions
to help make sure people using your app
have the best experience.
Our keyboard is highly adaptable
to various languages and input methods.
You should consider this
when laying out your search results.
Here are a few examples
of alternate layouts.
For people using IR remotes,
we'll display a grid keyboard.
500 Internal Server Error
QTL_Cache/1.2.14
While typing, the search results
will only occupy some of the screen width,
and then they'll slide in
to fill the screen when focused.
When the system language is set to Thai,
we use a three-line keyboard layout
to provide the best input experience.
Keep this in mind
when sizing search results
because not as many will fit onscreen.
You should also try to avoid
covering the keyboard with your own UI,
even in the borders outside the safe area.
It'll likely lead to focus issues,
and we don't recommend doing it.
If you need to differentiate between types
of content in search suggestion items,
use a symbol image.
It's a great way to present
more information in limited space.
Our library of SF Symbols
will work great for these suggestions.
Today we've shown you
the improvements we've made
to UISearchController in tvOS 14
and how easy it is to adopt.
You saw how you can integrate search
suggestions to make searching even faster.
If you follow the best practices
we've shown you here,
your customers will have
a great search experience in your app.
Thanks,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.