Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Nat Brown,
and I work on the Game Technologies team
here at Apple.
This video covers adding
keyboard and mouse input support
to your games for iPadOS.
We've added specific support
for keyboard and mouse gaming
because we know games are often designed
around their main form of input.
For example, most iPhone and iPad games
are designed around Multi-Touch input.
Multi-Touch input is incredibly flexible.
Whole new genres of games
have emerged utilizing taps,
swipes, touches and gestures.
This is Ordia by Loju LTD.
It's one of the winners of last year's
Apple Design Awards, and it's super fun.
Some games have added on-screen controls
with thumbstick areas and buttons
similar to a game controller.
This has worked well for many
first-person view-oriented games,
as well as for driving games.
Here, I can play one of
our sample applications, Fox2,
using its on-screen controls.
On the left, is a touch area
that acts like a left joystick,
and on the right, I have two actions,
as well as a right joystick.
Still, many games and game genres were really
designed around the tactile feedback
and the precision of a game controller,
and they don't always translate well
to on-screen controls.
For example,
driving games can take advantage
of the analog triggers
and the shoulder buttons
to give finer control
to acceleration and braking.
And many gamers consider
this right thumbstick
more sensitive and accurate
to use for aiming and camera control.
Here in Fox2,
I find it more fun to play the game
with a game controller on an iPad.
It's more of a lean-back experience,
and I have additional control.
But we also know there are whole genres
of very popular games that
aren't a perfect fit for touch input and they're also
not a perfect fit for game controllers.
Multiplayer Online Battle Arena,
or MOBA games,
using precise mouse control
to select areas or to move units,
while also supporting
keyboard modifiers to those mouse actions,
they don't always translate well
to using touch input.
First-person perspective games
that use WASD keys for movement
and other left-hand adjacent keys
for actions and modifiers,
while the mouse precisely aims the camera
are another type of game
not always perfect for touch.
So we've added game-focused APIs
for keyboard and mouse input
for these types of games.
It's a coordinated effort between the
UIKit and the Game Controller framework
to give you the options you need
for creating your best game experience.
For the rest of this talk,
I'm going to first dive into the details
on the new keyboard and mouse APIs
in the Game Controller framework.
I'm gonna spend a moment
describing examples
of when you might choose to use
the Game Controller APIs
versus other pointer APIs
at the UIKit layer.
I'm gonna show
a quick example of adding support
in one of our classic
Game Controller samples, Fox2.
And, finally, I'll play a bit of the game
to show you the game in action.
So let's dive into the Game Controller
framework support
for keyboard and mouse input.
The Game Controller framework
this year introduces two new classes:
GCKeyboard and GCMouse.
Like the trusty GCController class,
you can find out when these new types of
input devices connect and disconnect,
register blocks to watch
for input changes asynchronously,
and, in some cases, you can poll to read
the current state of these input devices.
These classes conform
to the GCDevice protocol,
just like GCController.
They have a physical input profile,
which you can use to look at the specific
input surfaces they expose.
In the case of GCKeyboard,
you'll find a set of buttons.
And those buttons also appear
in the aggregate elements collection.
You won't find Dpads
or Axes on GCKeyboards.
In the case of GCMouse,
you may see zero or more Axes
and one or more buttons
depending on the type of physical pointing
device you have paired at the time.
It is exactly the point of physical input
profiles to let you tune your game
to the specific capabilities
of attached devices.
Now we're finally to the actual code,
which is my favorite part.
I'm gonna show you the types
of change handlers you can establish
on GCKeyboard devices.
And you'll also see how you can inexpensively
poll the keyboard key states.
We'll see how to get raw mouse delta
events delivered to your change handlers...
and how you use the companion
UIKit pointer locking API
in order to hide the system pointer
and avoid triggering system gestures
at the edges of the screen.
We'll also look at how to find out
if the keyboard and mouse devices
are connected and when they disconnect.
So it's pretty straightforward
with GCKeyboard
to get notified about key-down
and key-up events.
You first check to see
if there's a keyboard attached.
You'll notice that we're using coalesced
on the GCKeyboard.
That's because we merge
all the keyboard input together.
Then, as you are used to elsewhere
in the Game Controller framework
for watching events asynchronously,
you simply assign a change handling block
to either the whole keyboard
with a key-Changed-Handler,
or alternately,
assign a change handling block
to a specific keyboard button
using a value-Changed-Handler.
In this case,
notice I added a handler to just catch
what the space bar is up to or down to.
The other common way to read keyboard
input in games is through polling
to check the current up
or down state of a key
rather than through a changed handler.
Here we are at some point
in our game's update loop,
and we're polling the input
using this poll-Input function.
We are just checking the up/down state
of the W, A, S and D keys
and reacting by preparing to move our
character later in the game update logic.
So whether you choose callbacks or polling
is really up to you and your needs,
depending on how you are trying to align
your input and your rendering loops.
One nice thing about these polling APIs
is that they are Order(1)
and non-blocking,
they're non-yielding
and they're thread-safe,
meaning you can call these APIs
without worrying about interrupting
or stalling a critical input handling,
simulation or rendering thread.
Events coming from the GCMouse devices
are not too different from the keyboard.
Here you can see
how our mouse-Moved-Handler
is receiving just delta information
coming from the device.
This is the delta or change in input value
since the last input was received.
It is not the current X and Y position
of the mouse and screen coordinates,
and that's intentional.
With GCMouse, there is no way
to poll the current pointer position
because, well, you're using this API
because you're in charge
of defining how and where you want
your in-game pointer to appear, if at all.
And you are also in charge
of how you want its acceleration to work
and the behavior you expect
at the screen edges as well.
But what about system gestures,
like bringing up the dock,
or other multitasking gestures
that can happen
at screen edges and corners?
That takes us to the need to lock the
pointer to your application and to hide it.
If you're using GCMouse
for a full-screen game,
you almost certainly wanna do this.
Any game that draws its own pointer
or which sometimes shows no pointer,
a game that performs its own
input acceleration, yeah,
you'll also wanna lock the pointer
from the system's perspective.
This will both hide the pointer and it'll lock
it to just your full-screen application.
The pointer now
can't trigger those system gestures
that would otherwise break your game.
Telling the system you want
the pointer lock is very easy.
On your top level ViewController,
tell the system if you prefer
your pointer locking
by overriding the prefers-Pointer-Locked
getter to return your current state.
You can dynamically change your mind
about having the pointer locked and hidden
by simply calling UIViewController's
set-Needs-Update-
Of-Prefers-Pointer-Locked
and returning a new value from prefers-
Pointer-Locked when it gets called.
This allows you to, for example,
use a key to toggle
between a mouse-controlled camera mode,
where you are controlling
your character's viewpoint,
and having the system's on-screen pointer,
which can be used to interact
with user interface elements.
Finally, here's how you detect
the presence of a keyboard and mouse.
It's just the same as detecting when
game controllers connect and disconnect.
We keep some local state
to keep track of the mouse
and maybe whether we've seen a keyboard.
Then, if you wanna have special logic for
handling specific mice or multiple mice,
you can do so in the Connect-Notification
handling block.
You might simply set up button
and delta event handlers directly here
and effectively coalesce any attached
GCMouse devices.
That's up to you.
In the case of keyboards, you can't
differentiate multiple keyboards,
and all keyboard events from multiple
keyboards are instead coalesced for you.
So while you might use notifications
to notice when a keyboard disconnects
and perhaps pause the game
to prompt for different input,
in general, you'll find that just using
GCKeyboard-Device.coalesced
to check on the key state
when non-nil is the right path.
The coalesced keyboard input
is a little bit like
the GCController.current controller
in this respect--
a lot easier to use
if you don't really have any special needs
around seeing the device connect
or disconnect.
So, when should you use Game Controller
APIs for keyboard and mouse handling
versus the UIKit APIs
introduced in iOS 13.4?
The answer is, it really depends,
and you might find yourself
using a bit of a mix of the two.
If your game is almost always full-screen,
has mostly custom UI,
renders a custom pointer
or hides the pointer during gameplay,
wants delta mouse events to implement
custom input acceleration
and wants to avoid having system gestures
intrude on gameplay,
or if it needs to poll for the very latest
input in multiple time-critical threads,
you probably wanna make use
of GCKeyboard and GCMouse.
If, on the other hand,
your game is only optionally full-screen
and can be split screen
or multitasking aware...
if the standard system pointer
shape morphing and blending support
fits your interaction model,
and system gestures
at the edge of the screen or hot corners
do not intrude on your gameplay,
and the UIResponder delegate callbacks
on your main thread
are adequate for receiving keyboard
and mouse input,
you will have access
to all of the new key-up and key-down
and key modifier keyboard and mouse events
that games are looking for,
and you should be fine using UIKit.
The reality is that you may
find yourself using both
in different modes of your game.
During the match portion of a first-person
viewpoint game, for example,
you may have the pointer locked
and no cursor visible,
and then you'll be using
the delta mouse events.
After a match, it may then make sense
to unlock the pointer
and present standard system UI
and a pointer matching
the rest of the system.
So now let me show you how easy it was
to add keyboard and mouse support
to our Fox2 sample.
We already had a UIViewController
with a lot of functions we need for moving
the character, changing the camera
and performing actions
like jumping and attacking.
All we need to do is wire those up
to the keyboard and mouse
and to keep track of a bit of state.
We're adding a delta variable
to pick up the mouse motion
which we'll apply in the main game loop.
When we see a new mouse device attach,
we're going to call
this new registerMouse function
to attach our value change handlers.
Now, here where we had that comment
to set up our handlers,
we first set up the mouse-Moved-Handler
to capture those raw delta mouse events
we were just talking about.
We just store those in our ViewController.
We'll wire up the mouse's left button
to cause our fox
to fight with the enemies.
It's easy because
we already wrote those methods
for our Game Controller
and on-screen touch controls.
We're just wiring them
to a new input source.
Finally, in our change handlers,
we set ourselves up to read
from the mouse scroll wheel
to change the fieldOfView
of the main camera.
The camera's already automatically
following our character,
so we just wire up a fieldOfView change.
This is actually a new feature
for keyboard and mouse.
We didn't have a way to zoom in and out
of the touch screen
or the Game Controller version.
Last, but not least,
we made some small changes
in our main update loop.
This is the loop of code
that runs every frame of the game.
We use the most recent
delta mouse event data
to change our camera direction,
and then we clear the delta event variable
until the next delta event
comes in from the mouse.
For the keyboard, we didn't set up
any value change handlers.
We're just polling for the current key
press state right here in the update loop,
and we change the character's direction
based on the W, A, S and D keys,
like a good
little keyboard and mouse game does.
Finally, we allow the user
to hold the left Shift key
to cause our fox to run instead of walk.
That's a pretty common
keyboard and mouse game trick--
to use modifier keys
to modify motion or aiming.
And that's all it took.
Let's compile this new version
of the game and give it a play.
So, here I am playing Fox2.
I can use the keyboard.
And the W, A, S and D keys
allow me to move.
The space bar jumps.
I've got control with the mouse
of where my camera's looking.
I can use the scroll wheel
to zoom in and out.
And that's it for keyboard
and mouse gaming on iPadOS.
Now you know how to use
GCKeyboard and GCMouse
and when you might wanna use GCMouse
versus UIKit Mouse APIs.
You've also seen how easy it was
to add to a game that already had
controller and touch input.
If you're interested in more ways
to control games and game input,
you may also find
these two other talks useful.
And that's it for keyboard
and mouse gaming for iPadOS.
Thanks for coming to WWDC.