Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to
"Introducing StoreKit Testing in Xcode."
My name is Dana,
and I'm really excited to show you
all the great new features
we're introducing this year
that will make building and testing
in-app purchases better than ever.
But before we get into what's new,
let's quickly review
how developers work with StoreKit
to add in-app purchases
to their apps today.
Currently,
if I'm looking to update my app,
either to begin selling content
through StoreKit
or to add new content to sell,
one of the very first steps I have to take
is to sign into App Store Connect.
There, I need to register my app,
define my in-app purchases
and create my Sandbox accounts
for testing.
Only after I've taken those steps
can I go back to Xcode
and start writing the code
to integrate StoreKit within my app.
As I'm building up my app, I'll be working
with the Sandbox environment
to test my in-app purchases
using one of the Sandbox accounts
I set up in App Store Connect.
There, I won't be charged
as purchases are made during my testing.
Additionally,
when I hand off my app to be beta tested,
the Sandbox environment will continue to
be used by developers working with my app.
Only after I've verified
my app works as expected
will I release my app to the App Store,
where the production environment is used
to back all StoreKit calls.
This has worked well in the past,
but we think we can do better for you,
our developers.
I'm excited to announce this year,
with Xcode 12,
we're introducing
a new development and testing suite
dedicated to StoreKit
and in-app purchases.
This will allow you to start
right in Xcode
to build and test your app's
in-app purchase entirely locally.
This is all integrated right into Xcode,
so it works seamlessly
with your app's development workflow.
Additionally, we're introducing
a brand-new StoreKit test framework
that will unlock the full automation
testing for your StoreKit integration.
This changes the entire
development life cycle for StoreKit.
Now, instead of starting in App Store
Connect, you can start right in Xcode.
Build out your StoreKit integration
at the same time
you're building out the rest of your app.
Add in unit, UI and other automation tests
to make sure the quality of your app's
StoreKit integration remains high,
then sign in to App Store Connect
and begin using the Sandbox environment.
Working with Sandbox
is a critical step you need to take
to make sure your app is ready to be
released to your users in the App Store.
It's also the environment you need to use
to test out any server-to-server
functionality required for your app.
Additionally, we're adding
a number of great enhancements
to the Sandbox environment this year
that my colleague Chris will go
into more detail later on in the session.
Let's dive in and take a closer look
at StoreKit testing in Xcode 12.
The app I'm building, Fruta,
is all about fruit smoothies,
and the feature I'm working on now
is around selling recipes
for those smoothies.
StoreKit is the right technology to use,
as those recipes are digital content
I want to offer within my app.
I've already configured Fruta
to fetch and render those store products
for the recipes.
If I navigate to Store.swift, where I keep
most of the store content within my app,
you can see
I have a list of product identifiers
for all the different recipes
I want to sell.
Further down,
within the fetchProducts function...
I have a SKProductsRequest call
where I'm passing in
all the product identifiers
from those recipes.
Fruta should be ready to go
for fetching and rendering those products,
so let's launch it in the simulator
and see what happens.
As you can see,
none of my recipes are showing.
But this is expected
because I've not yet configured
my app or in-app purchases
within App Store Connect.
And by default,
StoreKit is using the Sandbox environment,
so I need to enable local testing
within Xcode.
To do that, I first need to define
my in-app products inside my project.
First, I navigate up to the file menu.
Create a new file.
There I'll type in "StoreKit" and select
the StoreKit configuration file template.
And I'll just create a new configuration
file right inside my project.
I now have a place to store the metadata
for all my in-app products,
the recipes that my app will offer.
In the bottom left-hand corner
of this editor,
I have the option
to add StoreKit items to this file.
As I select that, I'm given a choice
over which type of product to add.
The first option is for consumable,
which is a type of product
that you can buy over and over again,
such as lives or gems within a game.
The second is for a non-consumable,
which are purchased once and never expire.
Lastly,
we have auto-renewable subscriptions,
where users are charged periodically
for access to services or content.
I'm going to choose to create
a non-consumable,
as that makes the most sense
for purchasing digital recipes.
I now need to fill out the details
for the recipe I want to sell.
In this case, I'm gonna choose Berry Blue,
as it's my favorite smoothie.
The product ID is a unique identifier
for this specific product within my app,
and it needs to match the value that
my app will pass into the StoreKit APIs.
To make sure I get it right, I'm gonna
copy and paste it from Store.swift.
Next, I need to set a price.
Unlike in App Store Connect,
where I can choose from a price tier,
here I'm given the option
to enter in any decimal value.
This is because
for StoreKit testing in Xcode,
the price is simply used
for setting what value is returned
in the SKProduct
that is handed back to my app.
So here I have direct control
over the value, and I can easily change it
to make sure my app can handle
any possible value returned.
For now,
I'm going to leave it as 99 cents.
Additionally, I have the option
to enable Family Sharing.
This is a brand-new feature
we're releasing this year.
For the purposes of StoreKit testing
in Xcode, enabling Family Sharing
will update the is-family-shareable flag
on the SKProduct.
I'm gonna leave that unset.
Lastly, I need to give this product
a localized name within my app.
I can also set a description,
but for now I'm gonna leave that blank.
Now that I've set up
my StoreKit configuration,
I need to tell Xcode to use it
instead of Sandbox when launching my app.
Doing that is easy
as opening up the scheme editor...
and under "run options," selecting
that configuration I just created.
Now when I relaunch my app,
StoreKit is using
the local test environment...
and the SKProduct
returns the metadata I've configured.
Earlier, I skipped setting a description
for Berry Blue,
but I want a description to show up,
and Fruta's already set up
to take the localized description
from the SKProduct and display it.
StoreKit testing in Xcode
is entirely interactive,
meaning I can update the metadata
for my app's products
without recompiling or even relaunching.
I just need to update
the StoreKit configuration file
to have the description I want...
and have my app re-execute
the SKProduct request
to pull down the updated metadata.
My project already contained
a StoreKit configuration
that has all the recipes
I will be selling,
so I'm gonna quickly switch over
to that file and relaunch my app.
My app is already configured
to take the SKProduct that we fetched
and use it to create an SKPayment
and add it to the payment queue.
To exercise that code, I just need
to select one of the "buy" buttons.
Right here in the simulator,
I get a payment sheet
a lot like what my users will see.
The big difference here
is that I didn't need to sign in,
and there is no need to authenticate.
Since this is just for testing purposes
and I won't be charged,
I simply select "confirm,"
and the payment goes through.
Just like Sandbox or Production,
my app's payment transaction observer
is updated
as the transaction goes from "purchasing"
to "purchased."
I'm even given a receipt
that my app can verify.
Berry Blue is now unlocked,
and I can navigate in and see the recipe.
Let's say I had an issue where I needed
to purchase Berry Blue all over again,
possibly to fix a bug or to change
the experience around purchasing.
Xcode makes that really easy with the new
StoreKit Transaction Manager.
I see all of the purchases
I made in the local test environment,
and I have full control over them.
I'm able to delete this transaction...
and reset state
as if the purchase never happened.
I can now buy Berry Blue again
as if I'd never purchased it before.
In addition to being able to delete
previous purchases,
I have the ability to simulate a refund.
In the case of a refund, the transaction
remains in the transaction manager
but is marked as refunded.
The transaction also remains
in the app's receipt
but is updated
to contain a cancellation date
for when the refund occurred.
Again, my app is informed about the refund
and is able to respond immediately.
If you want to make sure your app
has a great experience for kids,
who need to get permission
before making purchases,
StoreKit testing in Xcode has full support
for Ask to Buy.
It's easy as going back
to your StoreKit configuration file
and enabling Ask to Buy
under the editor menu.
Now when I go to purchase a recipe
within Fruta,
I see the same "ask permission" dialogue
that'll be presented to any user who has
Ask to Buy turned on for their account.
When I select "Ask," the transaction
appears as "pending approval"
within the transaction manager.
And in code,
my app's SKPaymentTransactionObserver
is informed that the transaction
is now in a deferred state.
I can now approve or decline it.
Once I approve,
the previously deferred transaction
is updated to a purchased state,
and my app updates right away
to show the unlocked recipe.
I also have the option to enable
interrupted purchases.
This will allow me to simulate the case
where a user needs to take some action
on their account
before being able to complete a purchase.
For example,
they may need to update details
related to their account's
billing information.
In this case, the initial purchase
will come back as "failed."
But once the user's taken action
to resolve whatever issue
caused the interruption,
a new transaction for the same product
will be added to the payment queue.
I've been considering changing
the business model of my application
to be subscription-based.
For one monthly price, users will have
access to all the smoothie recipes
instead of needing to buy them
one at a time.
StoreKit testing in Xcode
makes it really easy
to build auto-renewable subscriptions
with StoreKit.
I've already created
a second StoreKit configuration file...
that contains two different subscriptions
I want to offer in my app.
First, Recipes Plus,
which is configured to renew
at a monthly price of 2.99.
To make it even more compelling,
I've set up an introductory offer
of 99 cents for the first month.
I've also created a Recipes Pro option,
which not only unlocks
all the recipes in my app,
but gives subscribers access
to advanced nutrition facts
for each smoothie.
The two subscriptions are contained
in the same Subscription group,
enabling my app to offer upgrade options
between Recipes Plus and Recipes Pro.
I've already built Fruta
to work with these subscriptions,
so to try out that business model,
I just need to switch
StoreKit configurations
and relaunch my app.
Here, my app is displaying details
about both the subscription offers,
including the introductory offer
on Recipes Plus.
I want to make sure my app
correctly handles
when my subscription auto-renews,
but I don't want to wait
a full month to test it.
With StoreKit testing in Xcode,
I have the power to speed up time.
In the Editor menu
of my Subscription Configuration...
I select Time Rate,
and I can set one second to be one day.
This will change it so I only have to wait
seconds for that renewal to occur
instead of an entire month.
Now that I've purchased that subscription,
all the recipes are unlocked.
And I won't have to wait very long
for the recipe auto-renewing subscription
to automatically renew.
Earlier, as I was working
with the Transaction Manager
to delete and refund purchases,
my app immediately updated
to revoke access to those recipes.
This was made possible in iOS 14
thanks to a new API we added
on SKPaymentTransactionObserver:
didRevokeEntitlements-
ForProductIdentifiers.
To learn more about this API
and all of the other new features
we've added to StoreKit this year,
I highly suggest you check out
"What's New with In-App Purchases."
To enable you to authenticate
the purchased content in your app,
the App Store provides
a digitally signed receipt.
The receipt is the trusted record
of purchases made by the user in your app.
It's stored on the device
and updated automatically by the system.
It is signed, so you know
that it came from the App Store
and was meant for your app on that device.
If you want to learn more on how to verify
the receipt, I recommend checking out
"Best Practices and What's New
with In-App Purchases" from 2018.
But I do want to highlight
some key differences
you need to keep in mind
when working with the receipts generated
by the local
Xcode StoreKitTest environment.
First, they're signed
with a different private key
than what is used
for the receipts generated
in the Sandbox or production environments.
That means you need to use
a different certificate when validating.
We provide a convenient way
to export that StoreKitTest certificate
into your project via the editor menu
of your StoreKit configuration file.
Lastly, the StoreKitTest certificate
is not part of a certificate chain.
To accommodate for those differences,
you should make use of the DEBUG macro
within your client-side validation code.
Here you can see where my code is choosing
between the StoreKitTestCertificate
and the AppleIncRootCertificate
based on that macro.
Additionally, if I use OpenSSL
for my client-side receipt validation,
I would pass in the PKCS7_NOCHAIN
argument,
but only when building for DEBUG.
StoreKit testing in Xcode 12
works great on all of the OS betas
that we just released,
both when building and running
in the simulator,
as well as on real devices.
I walked you through setting up
your project's StoreKit configuration,
enabling the local test environment,
using the Transaction Manager
to delete and refund previous purchases,
and making sure your app
has a great experience
for deferred or interrupted purchases...
and purchases that renew automatically.
But as critical as it is
for you to be able to build and test
your StoreKit integration manually,
it's just as important
for you to build automation
that continuously tests
your in-app purchases.
Which is why we're introducing
a brand new StoreKitTest framework
that enables you in code to control
the full local test environment.
All of the controls that you had manually
are exposed inside your tests.
StoreKitTest works with XCTest
for extending unit and UI test coverage
to your in-app purchases.
Additionally, with StoreKitTest,
you have the ability to disable
all of the sheets and dialogues
that would normally appear,
so your test can run to completion
without waiting for user interaction.
Lastly, you have the ability to trigger
the renewal of a subscription right away,
so your test can validate
your app's subscription features
continue to work across renewals.
StoreKitTest can be used
to cover a wide range of cases,
including your app's handling
of both successful and failed purchases,
interrupted and deferred purchases,
transactions that initiate
outside the running of your app,
as well as all sorts of cases
related to subscriptions.
Let's go back into Xcode
and run through an example.
In Fruta, I've already built out
a series of unit tests
covering cases
related to in-app purchases.
The first one is a basic test case...
that ensures my app correctly unlocks
the "That's Berry Bananas" smoothie recipe
when successfully purchased by a user.
The very first thing it does
is create a new StoreKitTest session
initialized with the NonConsumable
StoreKit configuration file.
It's important to remember to include
the configuration file in the test targets
so that it's referencable
by SKTestSession.
Next,
I'm disabling all dialogues on my session
so that my test can run to completion
without user interaction.
After that,
I'm clearing all previous transactions,
so I know that I'm starting
from a clear state.
Finally, my test buys the recipe
and confirms that it's available.
"Test succeeded,"
so I know I'm good to go.
At this point, I can begin the process
of getting my app and in-app purchases
ready to be available on the App Store.
The critical next step
is sign into App Store Connect,
set up everything the App Store needs
to support my in-app purchases,
and test that configuration
using the Sandbox environment.
To tell you about
all the great enhancements and features
we are bringing to Sandbox,
I'm gonna hand it off to Chris.
Thanks, Dana.
Hi. I'm Chris,
a program manager for the App Store.
We saw how StoreKit testing in Xcode
enables you to perform early testing
and debugging of in-app purchases
in a local test environment.
There are key differences
between StoreKit testing in Xcode
and testing in the Sandbox environment.
First, you set up in-app purchases
in App Store Connect.
This is the same product information
your app uses
when it's available on the App Store.
And you'll create a Sandbox Apple ID
to sign into your test device.
In Sandbox,
app receipts are signed by the App Store.
Sandbox also supports
server-side receipt validation
and App Store server notifications.
In iOS 12, we added a Sandbox
account section in App Store Settings...
for signing into a Sandbox account,
an account you set up
in App Store Connect.
In iOS 14,
it's easier to test your in-app purchases
and subscriptions in Sandbox.
A new Manage option leads you into the new
Sandbox Manage Subscriptions page...
where you can view and test
your subscriptions in Sandbox.
Tapping into our Fruta app,
we see all subscriptions
within the Subscription group.
You may have used this page on production
as a subscriber
for selecting a different subscription,
to upgrade, downgrade or cancel.
Now this page is available to you
as a developer
to test your subscription tiers
in the Sandbox environment.
We added the ability to reset introductory
offer eligibility for a subscription.
With this,
you can use the same Sandbox test account
to test free trials
or introductory offers.
You no longer need to set up
a new Sandbox Apple ID
each time you want to re-test
an introductory offer.
Here's an example
of a subscription life cycle.
With this new functionality in Sandbox,
you can test common subscription changes
which happen outside of your app,
including customer actions,
such as a downgrade,
an upgrade or a cancellation.
You can test server logic for subscriber
status change notification types,
such as Did_Change_Renewal_Status
and Did_Renew,
a new notification type
coming later this year in production
which you'll also receive in Sandbox.
To learn more
about server notification types,
please refer to the session
"What's New with In-App Purchase."
Coming soon to App Store Connect,
Sandbox accounts will be able to test
interrupted purchases on a device.
To use this,
select a row for a Sandbox Apple ID.
Selecting Cindy's account.
Check the box to enable
interrupted purchases, then save.
Now Cindy can test interrupted purchases
in Sandbox on an iOS device.
A scenario would be needing to agree
to updated terms and conditions
before completing the purchase.
Purchases on a device
will continue to be interrupted
for an individual Sandbox account
until you return to App Store Connect
and disable Interrupted Purchases
for each tester.
Let's review the new iOS 14 subscription
and in-app purchase testing functionality
in Sandbox.
On a device, you can now view
and manage subscriptions.
You can also test upgrades, downgrades,
cancellations,
and reset introductory offer eligibility.
Soon you'll be able to test on a device
how your app responds
to an interrupted purchase.
Lastly, in App Store Connect,
users with the developer role
will be able to create and manage
Sandbox tester accounts.
Testing in the Sandbox environment
is a great way to improve
your app's handling of in-app purchases
before releasing into production.
For a recap, here's Dana.
Thanks, Chris.
There's a clear path
for building and releasing
high-quality apps that use StoreKit.
Start in Xcode 12 and use
the interactive local test environment
to build out your StoreKit integration.
Use the StoreKitTest framework
to build tests and automation
to ensure the quality
of your app's subscription
and in-app purchase functionality.
Sign into App Store Connect,
set up everything the App Store needs
to support your in-app purchases,
and test that configuration
using the Sandbox environment.
Additionally, use Sandbox to test
all server-to-server functionality
required for your app.
Take advantage of TestFlight
to get beta testing coverage
of both your app and its subscription
or in-app purchase functionality,
and then make your app live
on the App Store.
Thanks again,
and we look forward to seeing
the great apps you're gonna release.