Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome, everyone.
My name is David Hayward, and I'm
an engineer on the Core Image team.
I'll be giving a short presentation today
that will show you everything
you need to do
to build Metal-Based Core Image kernels
in Xcode.
First off, why do you want to write
custom CIKernels in Metal?
In addition to the usual features
of CIKernels,
such as automatic tiling
and concatenation,
by writing them in Metal,
you will reduce runtime compile times
by shifting that work
to when your app is built,
give your kernels access
to high-performance features
such as gather-reads, group-writes,
and half-float math,
and make your life easier as a developer
by syntax highlighting as you type
and syntax checking when you build.
So now that you know these benefits,
let me show you step-by-step
how to add Metal Core Image kernels
to your application.
There are five simple steps.
First, add custom build rules
to your project,
then add .ci.metal sources
write your kernel,
initialize your CIKernel objects,
and apply your kernel
to create a new CIImage.
Unlike conventional Metal compute
and graphics shaders,
Core Image Metal code needs to be
compiled and linked with special flags.
I recommend adding two custom build rules
to your project targets
that will make
using these flags automatic.
First we'll go
to the project's target settings
and add a build rule
for files that end in .ci.metal.
For files with this extension,
we will run a one-line script
that calls the Metal compiler
with the required -fcikernel flag.
This build rule will produce
an output binary that will end in .ci.air.
Next, we will add a second rule
for files that end in .ci.air.
For files with this extension,
we will run another one-line script
that calls the Metal linker
with the required -cikernel flag.
This build rule will produce an output
in your apps resources directory
that will end in .ci.metallib.
Now that we have added
the custom build rules,
all we need to do is add
a .ci.metal source to your project.
To do that, all you need to do is go to
the file menu and select New, File,
and select
that you want to add a Metal file,
and then create a file name
that ends in .ci
so that the new file in your project
will end in .ci.metal.
For today's session,
I will demonstrate this
with a kernel that is shown
in another great presentation
on Edit and Playback HDR Video
With AVFoundation.
The kernel from that presentation
applies an animated zebra-stripe effect
that highlights the bright,
extended range portions of an HDR video.
To write a custom CIKernel for this effect
is really easy.
First, at the top of the source,
you will include CoreImage.h header
so that you get access
to all the normal Metal classes
as well as the additional classes
that Core Image provides.
Next you will declare the function
for the kernel, which must be extern "C".
The example is a CIColorKernel,
so the function must return a float4 pixel
and take some arguments.
Here, the first argument
is a Core Image sample_t
that represents a pixel
from an input image.
This pixel is a linear
premultiplied RGBA float4,
which is suitable
for either SDR or HDR images.
The last argument
is a Core Image destination
that provides the coordinate
of the pixel to return.
In the implementation of this kernel,
we use the dest.coord x and y values
to determine
which diagonal line we are on.
Then we use some simple math
to calculate
if we should be on a zebra stripe or not.
If we are on a zebra stripe,
and the current pixel sample is brighter
than the normal Standard Dynamic Range
white of 1,
then we will return a bright red pixel.
Otherwise we return
the input sample unchanged.
For detailed documentation on Metal Shader
Language for Core Image kernels,
I recommend you go to developer.apple.com
and download this reference PDF.
It documents
the Metal Core Image kernel classes
and also describes more advanced features
like gather-reads and group-writes.
The final steps I will describe today
are in the Swift code
that loads your kernel
and applies it to create a new image.
Kernels are typically used
by CIFilter subclasses
which will have input properties
such inputImage and other parameters.
We recommend that your filter
instantiate its CIKernel object
using a static property.
This way, the work of loading the compiled
metallib resource is done only once
when it is first needed.
Lastly, CIFilter subclass must override
the output image property.
In this getter, you will take the kernel
from the static property
and use its apply method
to create a new image.
So that concludes
my step-by-step description
on how to build
Metal Core Image kernels in Xcode.
I have shown you how to add
custom build rules to your project,
how to write a kernel
and add it to your project,
and how to initialize and apply
your kernel object to create a new image.
I hope this allows you to add great visual
effects to your app's images and videos.
Thank you very much,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC 2020.