Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome. My name is Steve Breen,
and I'm an engineer on the UIKit team.
And in this video,
we're going to chat a bit about
advances in Diffable Data Source
for iOS 14.
So, before we dive into our content,
I want to highlight a portion
of the companion sample project
for this video entitled "Emoji Explorer."
This sample has a lot of interesting
components baked right into its design.
Now, in this first section, there's
a horizontally scrolling grid of emoji.
This is a pretty common design element
in many of today's apps.
Okay, so, this section in the middle
of Emoji Explorer is especially novel.
It's an expandable-collapsible
outline-styled UI which is new in iOS 14.
And finally, in this last section,
there's a design that looks
suspiciously like a UITableView
right here in the middle
of our UICollectionView.
Okay, that's Emoji Explorer,
and we'll be referring back to this
throughout our video.
Okay. So, to review, Diffable Data Source,
which was introduced in iOS 13,
greatly simplifies
the management of UI state
through the addition
of a new snapshot data type.
Snapshots encapsulate the entire UI state
via the use of unique section
and item identifiers.
So, when updating a UICollectionView,
we first create a new snapshot,
populate it with the current UI state,
and apply it to the data source.
Diffable Data Source
computes the differences
and animates things automatically
without any additional work needed
from the application developer.
So we covered this API in detail
in the WWDC 2019 video,
"Advances in UI Data Sources,"
and I encourage you
to check out that video to learn more.
So, for iOS 14, we've built on
the foundation of Diffable Data Source
with two new features:
Section Snapshots
and first class Reordering Support.
Let's chat a bit about Section Snapshots.
For iOS 14,
we're adding a new section snapshot
right alongside the existing snapshot type
we call "section snapshots."
And as the name implies,
section snapshots encapsulates the data
for a single section
in a UICollectionView.
There are two reasons
for this enhancement.
First, to allow data sources to be more
composable into section-sized chunks.
And second, to allow modeling
of hierarchical data
which is needed to support
rendering outline-style UIs,
a common visual design
found all throughout iOS 14.
So let's go back to Emoji Explorer
and see how section snapshots are used
to build this out in our sample app.
First, in our
horizontally scrolling section,
we are using a single section snapshot
to completely model
the content found here.
Next, in our second section
where we see this
expandable-collapsible
outline-style section,
a second section snapshot is used
to model this hierarchical data.
And finally, in our list section,
we again model this section's content
with a third section snapshot.
So for Emoji Explorer,
we compose our Diffable Data Source
from three distinct section snapshots
each representing
a single section's content.
Let's take a look at some API.
So, here's a snippet
of the new Section Snapshot API,
and check out the SDK for the entire API.
So, please note
that we'll use the term "snapshot"
when we're referring to the original
snapshot type introduced in iOS 13,
which includes sections
and item identifiers.
And we'll use the term "section snapshot"
to refer to this new to iOS 14 type.
So, glancing at
this new section snapshot type,
we see that
it's generic over the item type.
Note there's an absence
of any kind of section identifier type.
section snapshots just inherently
don't know what section they represent.
To add content to our section snapshot,
we'll use the 'append' API.
Now, notice the optional parent parameter.
When supplied, this allows us
to create parent-child relationships
in the section snapshot
needed to model hierarchical data.
Now, we've added two new APIs
to UICollectionViewDiffableDataSource
to accommodate
the new section snapshot type.
First, we have a new 'apply' method
which takes a section snapshot
and a section identifier.
Our second new API allows us
to retrieve a section snapshot
representing
a particular section's contents.
So next, let's flesh out a code snippet
showing how to use snapshots
and section snapshots together
to build up our Collection View's content.
First, we'll add sections
in the order we desire
by applying a snapshot
to our Diffable Data Source.
And here we see, we have the sections
in a particular order:
'recent,' 'top,' and 'suggested.'
Now, after we have
the desired section order,
we're going to populate the items
for each of these sections
by applying section snapshots
directly to each section.
Let's take a look
at how to create hierarchical data
using this Section Snapshot API.
First, we'll append some root items
to our sections.
Smiley, nature, food, et cetera
using the 'append' API.
Recall the 'append' method
has an optional 'parent' parameter.
So when that's not supplied,
that means apply these items to the root.
So, to configure
our parent-child relationship,
we'll append some child items
into a parent item.
In this example,
the parent item is "food."
And that's it.
We've created a section snapshot
which models
our application's hierarchical data.
Okay. So, it should be clear by now,
section snapshots are capable
of representing hierarchical data.
Now, at times, it's very convenient
to reason about
just a portion of this hierarchical data.
So, in this code snippet,
we're interested in getting
all the children
related to a particular parent item,
optionally including the parent
in a resultant section snapshot.
Okay. So, next up,
let's chat a bit about expansion state.
So expansion state is managed
as part of a section snapshot's state.
And when building up a snapshot for display,
you can easily determine whether or not
a child content is initially visible
by setting that item's
parent expansion state.
You can also query a snapshot to determine
if an item is expanded or collapsed.
Note that if you mutate
a section snapshot's expansion state,
this won't apply until you actually
apply that to the Diffable Data Source.
Okay, so when a user interacts
with an outline-styled UI
which is configured with
the new Cell Outline Disclosure Accessory,
the framework will automatically update
the section snapshot
with the new expansion state
and apply that section snapshot
to the data source.
Now, often it's useful to be notified
about expansion state changes
caused by these user interactions.
For example, you may have a design
that requires
that a particular parent never collapse.
To support this,
Diffable Data Source has new APIs
for giving applications
programmatic control
over expansion state changes
caused by user interactions.
Okay, so here are these new APIs.
First, we notice that
Diffable Data Source has a new property
called "SectionSnapshotHandlers."
The new SectionSnapshotHandlers type
is a struct which is generic over item
and contains five optional closures.
To handle
our previously mentioned requirement,
we could provide
a shouldCollapseItem handler
which will return 'false'
for a particular parent
to avoid collapsing the outline.
Now, we also provide support
for lazy loading of expensive content
with the API
snapshotForExpandingParent.
So this is useful to minimize
the amount of content loaded
in the initial section snapshot
when getting that content is expensive.
So, you can load that content as needed
depending on
the current child snapshot's state.
So, that wraps up Section Snapshots.
One of the advances
Diffable Data Source brings
is the ability to model
our Collection View's data
with unique item identifiers.
With these unique item identifiers,
it is possible for the framework
to automatically commit reordering changes
on the application's behalf
based on user interactions.
But this isn't really enough.
Our application needs to be notified
that a user-initiated
reordering interaction took place
so that it can persist
the new visual order
to the application's backing store,
which is its final source of truth.
So, to support reordering,
Diffable Data Source now has
a new property: reorderingHandlers.
This a struct
which contains three optional closures:
canReorderItem,
willReorder, and didReorder.
So, to enable reordering via this new API,
you'll first need to supply
a canReorderItem closure.
This will be called when a user attempts
to start a reordering interaction.
If it returns 'true,'
the reordering interaction
is allowed to begin.
When the user is done
with the reordering interaction,
the didReorder closure is called
to allow your application to commit
the new ordering state
to your application's source of truth.
Note that you must provide
both the canReorderItem
and didReorder closure
to enable the reordering feature.
Okay. So, the didReorder closure
passes your application a new type:
NSDiffableDataSourceTransaction.
So, transactions supply
all the information needed
to reason about the update being performed
against the Diffable Data Source.
First, let's check out
the NSDiffableDataSourceTransaction.
This type supplies
four basic pieces of information.
First, we have the initialSnapshot.
This is the state
of the Diffable Data Source
before the update is applied.
Next, we have the finalSnapshot.
Now, this is the state
of the Diffable Data Source
after the update is applied.
And we can use these item identifiers
from this snapshot directly
to determine the new ordering
which we need to commit
to our application's source of truth.
Additionally, we can see
the Swift standard lib
CollectionDifference is also supplied.
And if your application has a data type
such as 'Array' for the source of truth,
we can apply that CollectionDifference
directly to that.
And, lastly, we see
a list of section transactions
that provide per-section details
about all the sections involved
in this reordering update.
Section transactions are quite similar.
They have one section transaction supplied
for each section
involved in the reordering update.
First off, we can inspect
the sectionIdentifier
this sectionTransaction
has been applied to.
And we also see we have
the initial and final section snapshots,
along with the CollectionDifference
specific to this section's update.
Okay. So, let's check out an example.
Here, our backing store
is an array of items
supplying the source of truth
for a single section Collection View.
Using the Swift standard lib
CollectionDifference
supplied with the transaction,
we'll create a new backing store
and update our source of truth directly.
Well, that wraps up our video today
covering all the advances we've brought
to Diffable Data Source for iOS 14.
Download the sample app.
It's full of examples
of how to use these new APIs.
And use this code as a starting point
to update your apps
to take advantage of these new APIs.
And watch the related videos mentioned
throughout this talk to go deeper.
Thanks for watching.