[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. Welcome to our session
on "What's New in App Store Connect."
My name is Daniel Miao,
and I'm an engineering manager
on the App Store Connect team.
So, as with every WWDC,
we have a ton
of exciting new features for you.
Today, I'll talk to you
about how to use App Store Connect
to configure and test app clips,
as well as how to take advantage
of new Game Center features
like Challenges
and Recurring Leaderboards.
I'm also gonna give you
some exciting updates
about both in-app purchases
and the App Store Connect API.
So, as you heard in the Keynote,
an app clip is essentially
a small part of your app
that's discoverable
at the moment you need it
and is focused on performing
a specific task.
From a technical standpoint,
an app clip is simply a binary
that you package alongside your app
and runs on-device just like an app.
The app clip binary is delivered
to the device when it's invoked,
and we limit the size of the binary
to make sure the invocation
of the app clip feels very fast.
Now, in order to deliver
a great app clip experience,
there are a few major areas
to think about.
First, you wanna beta test your app clip
to make sure you're providing
a solid user experience.
Then, when you're ready to release
your app clip to the rest of your users,
you'll set up app clip card metadata
to provide meaningful information
to your customers
about what your app clip does.
And finally, you'll need to properly
define domain associations
to enable your app clips to launch.
But before we get into these,
I wanna spend a few minutes
talking about a concept
that's foundational to all of these areas,
and that's what an app clip invocation is
and why it's important.
I'll start off with an example
of invoking an app clip from Safari.
Here,
we're on the forestexplorer.org website.
The first thing you'll notice
is this banner at the top of the page.
We call this the Safari app clip banner.
It appears when a website
is associated with an app clip.
In Safari, we invoke the app clip
by tapping the "Open" button
in this banner.
This brings up what we call
the app clip card.
This card contains more information
about the app clip
before it's launched on the user's device.
Tapping the "Open" button
on the app clip card
launches the app clip itself.
And once your app clip is running,
a link to your full app on the App Store
will briefly appear
at the top of the screen.
There are many ways to invoke an app clip.
As you just saw,
an app clip can be invoked from Safari.
But app clips can also be invoked
from Messages, Maps,
via NFC tags, and QR codes,
and based on a user's location.
But no matter how it's invoked,
almost every app clip invocation
will be associated with an invocation URL.
A simple example of an invocation URL
is the URL of the web page
that we just saw in our last example,
forestexplorer.org.
A second example
is a piece of functionality
that we're introducing to Forest Explorer.
Users will be able to use our app clip
to reserve camp sites from Apple Maps.
Here you see the invocation URL
camp.forestexplorer.org/reserve
and then the ID of the campground
for the reservation.
Now, users will also be able to check in
to the campsites that they reserve
by scanning an NFC tag at the campsite.
This URL contains the ID
of the campground,
along with the specific campsite number.
So, the invocation URL
serves two main purposes.
The first is when an app clip
is displayed,
the invocation URL is used to determine
what metadata is shown
on the app clip card.
Then, when the app clip is launched
on the user's device,
the invocation URL
is passed into the app clip
to deep-link the user
into a specific piece
of app clip functionality,
similar to how you can
deep-link into apps today.
So now that you're a bit more familiar
with how an app clip is invoked,
let's talk about how to deliver
and beta test your app clip.
So, after you finish developing
your app clip in Xcode,
you'll generate a build.
This build contains both your app
and your app clip together.
An app clip cannot be packaged
separately from your full app.
The build is then delivered
into App Store Connect.
You can find the build
in the TestFlight view
of App Store Connect.
And you'll know that it's a build
that contains an app clip
because it has an extra row
containing the same information
you're used to seeing with apps,
but specific to the app clip.
When you click into the build details
for this build,
you'll see a new app clip
invocation section on the page.
From here, you can configure
up to three invocation URLs
for your testers to test.
To do this, you provide a title,
which appears in the TestFlight app,
along with the invocation URL itself.
Now, once the app clip invocations
have been configured,
clicking "Save" will make them
available to testers immediately.
Now let's look at what testers will see.
In the App Detail view,
you'll see a new App Clips section.
Here, we see the list
of app clip invocations
that we just set up in App Store Connect.
Tapping the "Test" button
will launch the app clip
associated with the current build
and pass the configured invocation URL
into the app clip to support deep-linking.
Now, one thing to note is that TestFlight
is the only app clip invocation case
that does not show an app clip card
before launching the app clip itself.
If testers encounter
any issues with this app clip,
TestFlight Feedback will be available
to collect information from testers
just like it is for apps.
So, once beta testing is complete,
it's time to think about the metadata
that will display to your users
on the app clip card.
The app clip card contains a header image,
a title, a subtitle and a call to action.
Toward the bottom of the card,
you'll also see more information
about the full app
and a link to the app on the App Store.
The app clip card is part
of the overall app clip experience.
It's easy to get started with App Clips
by setting up a default set
of app clip card metadata
in App Store Connect.
In fact, the default metadata
is required for all app clips.
And of all the invocation methods
that I spoke about earlier,
this metadata will only appear
when an app clip is invoked from Safari
or from Messages.
And for many of you,
this is all you'll need to set up
before releasing
your app clip to the world.
To configure your default experience
in App Store Connect,
you'll start on the iOS version page.
Here you'll enter
the default experience metadata,
including the header image, subtitle,
and you'll choose a call-to-action verb.
When your app clip is invoked
from Safari or from Messages,
you'll see this metadata appear
on the app clip card.
Now, you might be wondering
how Safari knows
that a web page
is associated with your app clip
in order to invoke
your default app clip experience.
Well, to make this association,
you simply include a meta tag
on the web page itself
with the name "apple-itunes-app".
This is the same tag that's used
for Safari Smart App Banners today,
but with an extra attribute
for the app clip.
The app-clip-bundle-id attribute
identifies which app clip
to associate with this web page.
And for your customers who are on iOS 13
and earlier, who can't run app clips,
you can add an app-id attribute
that'll link them to your full app
on the App Store.
And that's how you set up
a default app clip experience.
Some of you may want more control
over your app clip experiences.
For example, you may wanna set up
customized app clip card metadata
for specific invocation URLs.
You can do this by creating
advanced app clip experiences.
Not only can you customize
app clip card metadata
with advanced experiences,
but you can also associate
these experiences
with places on Apple Maps.
Finally, advanced app clip experiences
support all of the invocation methods
I told you about earlier.
So now let's look at a few examples
of advanced app clip experiences
for Forest Explorer.
First is the ability to invoke
a campsite reservation experience
from Apple Maps.
When a user taps the button
on the Apple Maps place card
for this campground,
the app clip card
for this experience will appear.
We want this app clip card
to display a photo of the campground,
as well as a meaningful title
and subtitle.
In this case,
we set the title to "Reserve"
and the subtitle to the name
of the campground.
Next, let's take a look
at the campsite check-in experience.
Campers will be able to check in
to our high-tech campgrounds
by scanning on-site NFC tags
encoded with our campsite check-in URL.
Just like the reservation case,
we want this experience
to display the campground photo and name,
but this time we want
the title to say "Check-in."
Now, looking at the invocation URL,
you'll notice that this URL
is specific to each campsite,
but we want a single set of metadata
to appear for all campsites.
If we register metadata
for the URL as you see it,
we would need to register
the same metadata for every single site,
and this would get repetitive
very quickly.
So, instead, we'll only associate
the campground metadata
to the first part of the invocation URL.
Any URL beginning with this prefix
will display the same metadata.
And now we've configured metadata
for all of the campsites
with a single registration.
These are just a few ways to configure
advanced app clip experiences.
Now I'd like to show you
how to set up advanced experiences
in App Store Connect.
First we'll head back
to the iOS version page.
Next, we'll click on
the "Get Started" link
in the Advanced
App Clip Experiences section.
And then we land on this page
where you'll get some background
on what you'll be asked to provide
for the experience you're registering.
First, you'll need to specify
the app clip invocation URL
for your app clip experience.
In this case,
I'm gonna register the full URL
for the campground reservation experience.
Below the URL is the bundle ID
of the app clip itself.
After setting up your URL,
it's time to enter the metadata
for the app clip card.
First, we upload metadata
that includes the header,
image title and subtitle
for this app clip card.
And after entering the metadata,
we answer the question
of whether to associate this experience
with a place in Apple Maps.
The campground is represented
as a place on Apple Maps,
so we select "Yes"
for the place selection.
Then, we select a Maps action
that best fits the experience
by selecting "Open Reserve Room."
To complete setting up
the place association,
we select the campground
that we're creating the experience for.
In this case, Lakeside Campground.
And once we've chosen a place,
we're asked a few questions
about the relationship
between the app developer and the place.
Since Forest Explorer
does not own the campground,
but does have a relationship
with the campground,
we select "Authorized by Owner"
for the relationship.
And then, in response to
"What is promoted in this experience?"
we choose
"A different business or service"
since we're promoting the campground
and not Forest Explorer.
Generally, the answer to
"What is promoted?"
will fall into one of two main categories:
"Your business" and "Other businesses".
Most of you will set up experiences
promoting your own business
because your app clip represents
surface offerings
that your business provides.
But some of you will set up experiences
for other businesses.
This makes sense
when you represent other businesses,
for example, the way Yelp does.
Notice that the icon that displays
when the experience represents
another business
is a category icon and not the app icon.
This icon is displayed in History,
the Safari app clip banner,
and other parts
of the app clip experience.
Once you've completed the process
of setting up your experience,
you'll see all the experiences
you've configured
along with their statuses
on the App Clip Experiences page.
And that's how you set up
advanced app clip experiences
in App Store Connect.
Now, once this is done,
it's time to think about
domain associations.
Every invocation URL contains a domain.
Now, we need to make sure
you're authorized to use these domains
to invoke your app clips.
To do this, first you specify
which domains you wanna associate
with your app clips
by using
the Associated Domains Entitlement.
Next, you set up
Apple App Site Association files
to be served from those domains.
These need to contain a reference
to the app clip app ID.
If everything checks out,
then your app clip
can be invoked on-device.
If you wanna check
the validation status of your app clip,
go to the build details page
in App Store Connect.
From here, click the "View Status" link
in the App Clip section
and this will bring up a modal
showing domain validation status.
The cache status column
is what drives app clip invocations
on your customers' devices.
And if, for example, you're working
on your Apple App Site Association file
and you wanna find out
whether your changes are valid,
you can click
the "Load Debug Status" link.
By doing this, we'll reach out
to your servers in real time
and validate the app clip portions
of your file.
If there are any issues,
you can get more detail here.
There's a lot more to learn
about associating domains,
so for a full walk-through of the process,
be sure to check out
the "What's New
in Universal Links" session.
There are also a number
of other informative sessions
focusing on various aspects of app clips
that are linked in the resources
associated with this session.
And that's how you set up App Clips
in App Store Connect.
Next, I'd like to show you
how to use App Store Connect
to take advantage of the new features
in Game Center on iOS 14.
First, we have Challenges.
Now, Challenges enable players
to challenge other players
to complete an achievement
or to beat a leaderboard score.
To enable this feature for your game,
go to the Game Center landing page,
under Features.
From there,
you click the "Allow challenges
in this game" checkbox.
Once you save this change, your players
will be able to challenge each other.
Next, we have Recurring Leaderboards.
Recurring Leaderboards
are a new kind of leaderboard
that allow you to collect scores
for a predetermined period of time,
and that period is then scheduled
to repeat at specific intervals.
As an example, let's say you create
a recurring leaderboard
that begins for the first time
on October 13th at 6:00 p.m.
It lasts for four hours
and repeats every week.
This means that scores
are posted to this leaderboard
beginning on Tuesday the 13th at 6:00 p.m.
and the leaderboard
continues to collect scores
for four hours until 10:00 p.m.
And every week after the 13th,
from 6:00 to 10:00 p.m.
a fresh leaderboard opens up again
to take new scores.
This is the page where you set up
Recurring Leaderboards
in App Store Connect.
If you've set up leaderboards in the past,
most of these fields
will look familiar to you.
For Recurring Leaderboards,
we've just added a start time,
a duration and a field where you can
specify the recurrence rules.
We have two additional sessions
that cover the full breadth
of new Game Center features,
so be sure to check those out.
Next, I wanna give you an exciting update
about our subscriptions program.
Subscriptions are
one of the fastest growing business models
on the App Store...
and we know that customers love
our Family Sharing capabilities,
which let them share Apple services
like Music, Apple Arcade and TV+.
Which is why we're so excited
to announce that starting this fall,
Family Sharing for subscriptions
will be available to all app developers.
For the first time, everyone in the family
can have access
to great subscriptions from the App Store
with a single purchase.
Family Sharing will be available
for both auto-renewable subscriptions,
as well as non-consumable
in-app purchases.
Family Sharing is flexible enough
to adapt to your different business needs.
For example, if you would like to make
a family-shared subscription
an upgrade from an individual one,
you can do just that.
When you enable Family Sharing
for your subscription
or non-consumable in-app purchase,
all new customers will automatically
share the purchase with their family.
Be sure to update
your in-app purchase metadata
to appropriately communicate
that it is a shared purchase.
On the other hand,
if you have existing subscribers,
those subscribers will need
to take an action to opt in
to sharing the subscription
with their families.
To configure Family Sharing
in App Store Connect,
navigate to the In-App Purchase
detail page.
Once you arrive here,
you'll wanna think about your metadata
to make sure you're communicating
that this is a family-shared
in-app purchase.
When you're ready to enable
Family Sharing,
click the "Turn On" link
toward the middle of the page.
When you do this, we will ask you
to confirm your decision.
Please consider your decision carefully,
because once you enable Family Sharing
for a live in-app purchase,
you cannot turn it off again.
Once you confirm, Family Sharing
will go into effect immediately.
For more information about how to support
Family Sharing with StoreKit,
along with other updates to StoreKit APIs,
watch the "What's new
with In-App Purchases" session.
We've also added an exciting set
of testing features
that includes local testing
of in-app purchases
directly from within Xcode,
and we've made enhancements
to the Sandbox testing experience.
We'll take a deep dive into these features
in "Testing In-App Purchases."
And finally, if you wanna make
the most of subscription features
for your business, you'll wanna watch
"Architecting for Subscriptions."
And finally, we'd like to tell you
about our expanded App Store Connect API.
Two years ago,
we launched the App Store Connect API
with support for TestFlight,
user management,
provisioning and reporting.
Later this year,
we're exciting to be adding
two powerful new sets of APIs.
We'll be introducing a suite
of App Metadata APIs
that will let you manage
your presence on the App Store,
as well as a new Power and Performance API
that'll let you download
the same aggregate data
that drives the new power
and performance analysis tools in Xcode.
In fact, just between these two new
categories of API functionality,
we're adding over 200 new endpoints.
For App Metadata,
you'll be able to do things,
like create new App Store versions,
set pricing and availability,
edit app- and version-level metadata,
associate builds
to your App Store versions
and submit those versions for review.
Now, we can't even begin
to scratch the surface
of the new APIs in this session,
so be sure to check out
the new "App Store Connect API" session
for a deep dive into the new APIs
and walk-throughs of some common use cases
that you may encounter.
So, we've covered a lot of ground today.
We talked about using App Store Connect
to configure App Clips,
and new Game Center features,
like Challenges
and Recurring Leaderboards.
You'll soon be able to make
your subscriptions family-shareable,
and we're adding
a ton of new functionality
to the App Store Connect API.
We're very excited
about all of these new features
and we can't wait to see
what you'll do with them.
Thank you for watching this session,
and please enjoy
the rest of your conference.
[chimes]