Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Will Thimbleby.
We're going to take a look
inside PencilKit drawings,
at what they're made out of
and what you can do with them.
PencilKit is super easy to adopt,
provides beautiful,
realistic-looking inks,
the best low-latency drawing experience
and some great new UI improvements
in iOS 14.
For more information
about these improvements,
see the "What's New in PencilKit" talk.
In iOS 14, we're also letting you look
inside PencilKit's data model:
the drawings, the strokes,
inks, paths and points.
This will enable you to build some great
new features in your apps with PencilKit.
With access to the data model,
you'll be able to inspect the contents
of what your users drew,
react to what was drawn,
manipulate existing drawings
or dynamically create new drawings
from scratch.
To give an example of what's
newly possible with PencilKit,
let me jump straight into a demo.
This demo is also available
as sample code.
I've been working on an app
to help my seven-year-old son
practice his handwriting.
At the top of this app is a text field
with the words I want him to practice.
Below is a synthesized PencilKit drawing
of the same text.
I could change this text
with the keyboard,
but this is a Pencil demo.
I can use the great new Scribble feature,
which, by the way, also uses PencilKit,
to change this text
to what I want him to practice,
perhaps to something more appropriate
for a seven-year-old.
As I enter text,
the template PencilKit drawing below
is constructed from individual letters.
In the top right, I can also choose
the size I want him to practice
and the difficulty.
Now that I have a template,
we're set up to practice handwriting.
The next stroke to copy
is animated by this red dot
that shows how to write the next letter.
All I have to do is copy it.
If I write something
that's close to the template,
my handwriting changes to green
and we move on.
If I write something badly,
the stroke disappears
and the animation repeats.
My score is shown in the top right.
Let's see how I do.
We did well, so we get some fireworks,
a key motivational tool
for seven-year-olds.
But I've had a few years
to practice my handwriting,
so why don't we try
something a bit trickier?
I drew a PencilKit ligature,
and I've added that to the app.
Now we can practice our calligraphy.
The app is synthesizing
PencilKit drawings from text,
animating them and performing recognition
on what I wrote.
This is just a small example
of what you can now do
with access to the PencilKit data model.
So let's look inside a PencilKit drawing.
Here we have a simple drawing of a flower.
If we split it up,
we can see that the drawing is composed
out of many PencilKit strokes.
Each stroke represents
an individual line that the user drew.
These strokes are in the order
that the user drew them,
so you can see that the outline
of the flower was drawn first,
then the stalk, leaf,
and finally the whole thing
was colored in with a marker.
Here we have the data asset that I drew
that contains the lowercase letters
for the demo I just gave.
To be able to generate text,
we first want to split this drawing up
into individual letters.
Later, these letters are combined
to generate the template text
that users use to practice.
To split this drawing up,
we take the lowercase alphabet drawing
and get its strokes.
We slice this array to get the strokes
for each individual letter.
Then we can create new drawings
for each letter out of that slice.
This is repeated
for each letter in the alphabet.
If you want to inspect
or modify a drawing,
you do this by accessing
the drawing's array of strokes.
You can also use strokes
to create new drawings from scratch.
So, what about strokes?
What makes up a PencilKit stroke?
For a stroke,
the primary feature is the path.
This provides the shape of the stroke.
You also have an ink, which describes
the appearance of the stroke:
its color and type.
A transform gives the orientation
and position of the stroke.
Strokes can also have masks,
and we'll discuss those
later in this talk.
Another useful property of strokes
is the renderBounds,
and this is a bounding box that
encompasses the entirety of the stroke
when it is rendered.
The renderBounds accounts for the effect
of all the stroke properties
including the path, ink,
transform and mask.
Inks, which describe
what a stroke looks like,
contain the type of ink and a color.
Inks do not have a width.
The width of a stroke
is variable along the stroke path.
The stroke path describes
the shape of the stroke
and the appearance of that shape
as it changes along the path.
For example, the stroke path gives you
the width of the stroke at any point.
A PencilKit stroke path
is a uniform cubic B-spline
of PencilKit stroke points.
Now, that's quite a mouthful.
What does that mean?
It means that the contents of a path
are, in fact,
the control points for the B-spline.
So if we iterate
over the points in a path...
and draw each one in turn...
the resulting points
are not actually on the stroke.
These points
are the B-spline control points
and probably not what you want to draw.
To get points on the actual path,
we need to interpolate the spline.
To interpolate the spline,
we access the points
using interpolatedPoints strideBy.
This provides a sequence of points
that we can iterate over like before.
Drawing these gives us
a series of points on the path.
There are a couple of things
to notice here.
They're on the path,
there are more of them
and they have uniform spacing,
in this case, a distance of 50 points,
which is the stride argument
passed in to the method.
You might also notice that the spacing
of the last point is uneven.
This is because the last point on a stroke
is always generated
regardless of the stride.
You can stride by distance,
as in this example,
time or parametric value.
Distance and time are self explanatory.
Distance is points
in drawing coordinate space,
and time is duration in seconds,
which depends on how fast the user drew.
Parametric value relates to the parametric
interpolation of the B-spline.
To explain what the parametric value is,
let's bring back
drawing the control points.
This is the same code
that we used earlier.
If instead of drawing the control points,
we iterate over the indices of the path,
which go from zero
to the control point count,
and at each iteration we get the point
using interpolatedPoint(at,
for the parametric value
0, 1, 2, 3 and so on
and draw that...
we get the equivalent points
to the control points.
But these points are actually on the path.
Why is this useful?
Let's number the points
so you can see what's going on.
The parametric value is useful
because it is a floating point value.
That means you can ask for
the interpolated point for any value,
including non-integer values
between control points
like 2.4 or 4.8...
and so on.
This gives you the flexibility
to interpolate the stroke path
any way you want.
All the interpolation we've seen so far
has been interpolating the path
with a uniform step.
Using the parametric value,
PencilKit also provides the ability
to step along a path
by an arbitrary distance,
using parametricValue, offsetBy.
This function allows you to offset
a parametric value on a path
forwards or backwards
any step in time or distance.
One of the places
where non-uniform stepping is useful
is when animating.
The demo I gave earlier uses this ability
to animate the red marker dot
along the strokes.
Each frame,
the current marker position on a stroke,
is offset by the exact time duration
since the last frame.
Non-uniform stepping is necessary
because we're not always guaranteed
a uniform amount of time
between animation frames.
To animate in the demo,
first we get the delta time,
the time that has elapsed between
the current frame and the previous frame.
We use that to offset
the current animation parametric value
along the path by the same amount of time.
This animates along the stroke path
with the same velocity
as when the user drew it.
Finally, we update the marker position,
getting the new location on the path
from the new parametric value.
So that's the path.
Both the control points
and the interpolated points along the path
are PencilKit stroke points.
These are the atomic building blocks
of paths and strokes.
They capture both the appearance
and touch information of a stroke
at a particular location.
These points are stored
in a lossily compressed format,
so any points you create
will not capture the values you use
with perfect precision.
Let's take a closer look
at one of these points in a stroke.
A PencilKit stroke point
has several appearance attributes.
The first of those
is the location of the point.
A point also has a size,
which for marker strokes won't be square.
A rotation angle, or azimuth.
And finally, the opacity.
These attributes combine to describe how
a stroke appears at a certain location.
Stroke points
also have a couple of properties
that are not appearance attributes.
Force and altitude match
the same values from UITouch
when the stroke was drawn.
Time offset is the offset in seconds
from the creation date of the stroke path
that the point belongs to.
This provides timing information
for how the user drew the stroke.
We'll jump back now to talk about
the last property of PencilKit strokes
that we haven't covered...
and that is masking.
Masked strokes are typically created
when the pixel eraser is used
to erase only a portion of a stroke.
Most strokes are not usually erased,
but when they are,
the mask is used to clip
these strokes in rendering
and adjust how the user
can interact with them on the canvas.
Masks can have holes.
Or they can cut a stroke
into multiple pieces.
In this example, using the eraser,
the stroke has been split
into two separate strokes.
These become unique, independent strokes
and behave as such
to the user and in the API.
For example, each of these two new strokes
has its own separate transform and mask.
The user can select one of the strokes
and move it around
without affecting the other stroke.
PencilKit strokes are masked,
but stroke paths are not.
This means that if we take the code
we were using earlier
to draw a stroke path
and use that code
to draw a masked stroke...
we're going to get a much longer path
than we wanted.
Instead, we want to use
the maskedPathRanges property
of the stroke.
This is an array of parametric
value ranges on the stroke path
when it is clipped to the mask.
Here we iterate
over the maskedPathRanges...
and interpolate the points
in each of those ranges.
This correctly gives an interpretation
of the stroke path
in a way that makes sense
for a masked stroke.
Strokes can have zero masked ranges.
For example, if the user erases
all but a fraction of a stroke,
and that fraction does not
intersect the path spline,
then the resulting masked stroke
will have zero maskedPathRanges.
Strokes can also have
multiple masked ranges.
In this case, a stroke with holes in it
has four individual ranges.
Recognition is a building block
for many great features
that you can build with PencilKit.
Spline-based recognition can make use
of these maskedPathRanges
to provide a sensible interpretation
of masked strokes,
and this is what we do
for handwriting recognition in Notes.
When interpreting strokes,
you can use maskedPathRanges
to get a range of points,
interpolate them how you want
and use non-appearance attributes
like time and force
to supplement the shape of the path.
The demo you saw earlier
provides a simple example
of spline-based recognition.
It uses a matching algorithm
to compare and score the user
on the similarity between what they drew
and the template they're trying to copy.
If you want to do image-based recognition,
use the rendering API on PKDrawing
to generate images.
PencilKit provides a super easy way
to add great Pencil support to your app.
Now that you can look inside drawings
and access the strokes,
inks, paths and points,
inspect what the user wrote and drew
to build features
like the new Scribble experience
which uses PencilKit
to enable handwriting in text fields
across the whole of iPadOS.
Modify drawings to create
interactive drawing experiences
that respond to the user's actions.
And create new drawings procedurally,
like the sample code does to generate
handwriting templates for practicing.
Adding support for Pencil,
one of our most expressive input devices,
is a great addition to almost any app.
PencilKit has always been a fantastic way
to add drawing to your app,
and now that you can look inside drawings,
it's also
an incredibly powerful foundation
for new Pencil-focused experiences
that you want to build.