Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. I am Guillem Viñals
from the Metal Ecosystem team at Apple.
Today we will talk about our unique GPUs.
This is a talk about hardware so there is
not a single line of code,
but plenty of pipelines instead.
And, as we all know, pipelines are cool.
This talk has two parts.
First, we will talk about Apple TBDR GPUs,
which will cover the basics
of the rendering pipeline.
Then we will talk about modern Apple GPUs,
which cover some of the recent
enhancements to the pipeline.
So why are GPUs so important?
Well, they are at the heart
of our A Series processors.
Our Apple processors are powering
over one billion devices worldwide.
So that's a lot of Apple GPUs.
Apple processors are very power efficient,
and they have this unified
memory architecture,
which means that the CPU and the GPU
share System Memory.
Also, the GPU has a dedicated pool
of on-chip memory,
which we call Tile Memory.
Notice, though, that the GPU
does not have video memory.
So bandwidth could be a problem
if the content has not been tuned.
In order to be fast and efficient
without video memory,
our GPUs have a unique architecture
known as TBDR,
or Tile Based Deferred Renderer.
So let's talk about that.
Today, we will review
the rendering pipeline,
as well as some of the features
that make the GPUs so efficient.
We will talk about Vertex
and Fragment stage overlap,
Hidden Surface Removal,
Programmable Blending,
Memoryless Render Targets,
and also our very efficient
MSAA implementation.
So let's have a look
at the graphics pipeline
to understand this a bit better.
Our GPUs are TBDRs,
or Tile Based Deferred Renderers.
TBDRs have two main phases.
First, tiling, where all of the geometry
will be processed.
Second, rendering, where all of the pixels
So let's cover this pipeline
more in detail,
starting with the Tiling Phase
at the very beginning.
In the Tiling Phase,
for the entire render pass,
the GPU will split the viewport
into a list of tiles,
shade all of the vertices and, finally,
bin the transformed primitives
into a list of tiles.
Remember, our GPUs don't have
a large pool of dedicated memory.
So where does all this
post-transform data go?
It goes into the Tiled Vertex Buffer.
The Tiled Vertex Buffer
stores the Tiling phase output,
which includes the post-transform
vertex data,
as well as other internal data.
This data structure
is mostly opaque to you.
But it may cause a Partial Render if full.
A Partial Render
is when the GPU splits the render pass
in order to flush
the contents of that buffer.
So the takeaway is for you to know
that the Tiled Vertex Buffer exists,
but don't worry too much over it.
Okay. So far, so good.
Let's move on to the second stage
of our GPU pipelines, rendering.
This is where
most of the heavy lifting happens
and it's also where the TBDR architecture
shines the most.
In the previous stage, the GPU
split the viewport into a list of tiles.
Now we are going to shade
all of these tiles separately.
In the rendering phase, the GPU will,
for each tile in the render pass,
execute the load action,
rasterize all of the primitives
and compute their visibility,
shade all of the visible pixels
and, finally, execute the store action.
Most of this is also
opaque to the application,
it just happens to be very efficient.
What the application
can control very explicitly
are the load and store actions.
So let's review those
to make sure you got them right.
Load and store actions
are executed for each tile.
At the beginning of the pass,
where we tell the GPU
how to initialize Tile Memory,
and at the end of the pass, to inform
the GPU what to do with the final render.
The recommendation
is to only load the data that you need.
If you don't need any data,
don't load anything and clear instead.
This will save us all the memory transfers
required to upload
all the color attachments,
as well as depth and stencil buffers.
The same goes for the store action.
Make sure to only store
the data that you need,
like the main color attachment.
This is very important to improve
the efficiency of your render.
So let's look at the rendering phase
in a bit more detail,
starting with Hidden Surface Removal,
or HSR,
which happens before we render anything.
This is possible thanks
to the on-chip depth buffer.
This is also a key aspect of TBDR.
HSR allows the GPU to minimize overdraw
by keeping track of the frontmost
visible layer for each pixel.
HSR is both pixel perfect
and submission order independent.
So pixels will be processed
into two stages,
Hidden Surface Removal
and Fragment Processing.
For example, even if you draw
two triangles back to front,
HSR will ensure that there is no overdraw.
So let's assume we want to render
three triangles, submitted back to front.
First, the blue triangle at the back.
Second, orange triangle in the middle.
And, finally, a purple
translucent triangle in the front.
HSR will keep track
of visibility information.
Each pixel will keep the depth
and primitive ID
for the frontmost primitive.
Zero, in this case, means
that the background color should be used.
We have not yet rasterized anything.
We will rasterize the first primitive,
the blue triangle.
This primitive will populate the depth ID
for all of the pixels covered.
Notice that so far we haven't run
any fragment shader yet.
Then we will rasterize
the second primitive
and to exactly the same.
Since the orange triangle is in front,
we update the depth and primitive ID
of all of the pixels it covers.
Again, we rasterize the primitive
without running any fragment shader.
The GPU will first calculate
the visibility for each pixel
before shading anything.
Now we will rasterize
the translucent triangle.
HSR does only keep the frontmost
visible primitive ID for each pixel.
But now we have a primitive
that needs to be blended.
At this point, the HSR block
will need to flush
the pixels covered
by the translucent primitive.
In this context, flushing means
running the fragment shader
for all of the pixels covered.
The GPU cannot defer
fragment shading any longer.
Once the pixels have been flushed,
the GPU can now process
the blended primitive correctly.
This was the last primitive,
so the remaining pixels
in the Visibility Buffer
will also need to be flushed.
At the end of the pass,
all of the pixels are shaded.
Notice, though, that some pixels
have only been shaded once.
In spite of potentially having
multiple primitives overlapping,
these pixels have no overdraw.
In this context, overdraw is the number
of fragment shader invocations per pixel,
and we want to keep it low.
On a scene with non-opaque geometry,
overdraw will depend
on the HSR efficiency.
So you will want to maximize that.
You will want to draw the meshes
sorted by visibility state.
First, opaque.
Second, alpha test,
discard or depth feedback.
And third, and finally,
translucent meshes.
You should avoid interleaving
opaque and non-opaque meshes
and also avoid interleaving opaque meshes
with different color attachment
write masks.
Maximizing the efficiency of HSR
will help us reduce overdraw.
So let's review these with an example.
This time we want to draw
the same triangles as before,
but with a different order.
The translucent triangle
is now in between the other two.
If we just submit back to front,
we will mix different visibility states.
In this case, interleaving opaque
and non-opaque primitives is inefficient.
HSR will need to flush all of the pixels
covered by the translucent primitive.
Many of these pixels shaded
will soon be occluded
by the next primitive
and then shaded again.
To maximize efficiency,
render all of the opaque geometry first.
We don't actually need to sort
opaque meshes.
As long as we submit them
before the non-opaque meshes,
HSR will be very efficient.
After HSR, we move on to the actual
Fragment Processing stage.
Notice, though, that if we discard
or update the depth,
we will need to go back to HSR.
This stage is very efficient
thanks to the on-chip frame buffer.
Alpha Blending will always happen
on Tile Memory.
Also, notice that there is
no dedicated blending unit.
The only time while we read
or write any render target
is when the load and store actions
get executed.
In this example, in spite of blending,
the final render target gets written
only once at the end of the pass.
Sometimes, conventional Alpha Blending
may not be usable though.
This is the case
for some full screen effects
such as global fog or deferred lighting,
which requires some custom blending.
These algorithms are traditional
multi-pass techniques.
Many of these techniques
will store all of the attachments
just to sample from them in a second pass.
TBDR GPUs expose a feature
called Programmable Blending.
Programmable Blending
allows fragment shaders
to access pixel data
directly from Tile Memory.
This allows you to merge
multiple render passes into one
and drastically improve
the memory bandwidth.
In this example, we don't need to load
or store any intermediate render target.
But there is still some waste in here.
There are a couple of render targets
which are not being loaded or stored.
They are just being used
within the Tile Memory.
And those are potentially big textures
taking a large chunk
of your memory footprint.
TBDR's GPUs have a solution for that,
Memoryless Render Targets.
We can explicitly define a texture
as having memoryless storage mode.
This gets rid of all of these
unnecessary allocations,
saving us precious memory footprint.
There's another technique
which fits this design very well.
But let's talk about the problem first.
Aliasing. Aliasing, or Jaggies,
are the stair-shaped pattern
that we may see sometimes in games.
Aliasing is a common artifact
of rasterization.
The GPU will sample
the pixel at the center
and only shade the primitive
if it intersects with a sample point.
Multisample Antialiasing
is a very common technique
that consists of rasterizing
multiple samples per pixel.
This allows rasterization to occur
at higher resolution.
The pixel shader is run
once per triangle per pixel
and blended with the rest of samples.
This will smooth out
the edges of a primitive.
Apple GPUs have a very efficient
MSAA implementation.
Apple GPUs will track the primitive edges,
so pixels without edges
will blend per pixel,
and pixels that contain edges
will blend each sample.
But that is not all.
The multiple samples are stored
on-chip Tile Memory
and resolve once the tile is flushed.
This makes the store action
very efficient,
and you can also use
memoryless storage mode
to save some footprint.
So let's review this.
Trivially, this is how it would look.
We have a large multisample texture,
as well as a Resolve Texture.
At the end of the pass,
we store the multiple samples and resolve.
By using efficient Resolve action,
we can save all of the bandwidth required
to store the large multisample texture.
That is because MSAA Resolve
always happens from Tile Memory.
So there is no point
in storing the samples...
which makes the multisample texture
fully transient.
We never load it or store it.
This means that we may as well
make it memoryless
and save all that footprint too.
Awesome! So now let's take a step back.
Thanks to the efficient load and store actions,
Tile Memory and memoryless render targets,
we can write some awesome renders
which are impressively efficient.
Another characteristic of Apple TBDR GPUs
is that the tiling and rendering are
separate stages for each render pass.
This allows the tiling work
of a render pass to overlap
with the rendering work
of a previous pass.
And of course,
if there is no dependencies,
Compute will always overlap.
As you can see, Apple TBDR GPUs are great.
And thanks to Metal, it's very easy
to leverage the architecture.
Apple designed Metal to enable
rapid innovations in GPU architecture.
And in turn, the Apple GPU architecture
has informed the design of Metal.
Metal is designed for Apple GPUs.
It exposes a unified graphics
and compute architecture
as well as TBDR features
such as Programmable Blending
and Memoryless Render Targets.
It also exposes an explicit submission
model and explicit multi-threading.
This deep integration
of hardware and software makes it possible
to easily optimize advanced algorithms...
such as deferred rendering.
Deferred rendering is
a multi-pass algorithm
that decouples rendering the scene
properties from the actual lighting.
In its most basic form,
we can think of each of the algorithm
stages as a rendering pass.
This is considered bandwidth-heavy
because we need to write out
and then sample a lot of data
in order to produce the final lit render.
This requires a lot of memory footprint
to store these intermediate textures
or G-Buffer.
Of course, you know by now
that by using Programmable Blending,
efficient load and store actions
and memoryless render targets,
we can make this algorithm very efficient.
Both in terms of memory footprint,
but also in terms of memory bandwidth.
You can find a lot of documentation
on the topic of deferred rendering
and all of the TBDR features
in the following samples.
So go check them out.
Check the Deferred Lighting sample code,
which is actually written
in multiple languages,
and also optimized for Apple TBDR GPUs.
Now, let's move on
to the second part of the talk.
Modern Apple GPUs.
Starting with A11,
we introduced a major GPU redesign.
We redesigned and rebalanced the full GPU
in order to support
more modern rendering algorithms.
These algorithms may require us
to explicitly leverage
the Apple TBDR architecture,
potentially manage complex data structures
as well as greater numerical accuracy.
Since we also rebalanced the design,
we made several rate improvements
as well as increased
some implementation limits.
Cool! So let's review
the render pipeline changes.
This is the TBDR pipeline we've just seen.
And this is the new TBDR pipeline
of modern Apple GPUs.
Most of the changes occurred here.
We have now an on-chip Imageblock
as well as a new programmable stage
called Tile Compute.
So let's review that,
starting with the Imageblock.
An Imageblock is a 2D data structure
in Tile Memory.
It has width, height and pixel depth.
It can be accessed by both
fragment functions or kernel functions.
Using this structure explicitly
also has some efficiency gains.
Prior to Imageblocks,
you probably moved your textures into
Threadgroup Memory one pixel at a time.
But the GPU didn't understand
that you were operating on image data.
You also had to store the texture
one pixel at a time.
With Imageblocks, you can load and store
image data using a single operation.
This is much more efficient.
So far, so good.
But the Imageblock makes more sense
when we talk about Tile Shading.
Tile Shaders are the compute kernels
that we can dispatch
in order to access the Imageblock
mid-render pass.
Dispatches are interleaved with draw calls
executed in API submission order.
And they will barrier against
earlier and later draw calls,
so synchronization should not be an issue.
Tile Shaders and Imageblocks will also
help us with MSAA.
MSAA also got more efficient
On our modern GPUs.
Now, the GPU also tracks unique samples.
But so far, MSAA is fairly opaque
to your application.
You could enable or disable it
for a render pass
with no control
on how the samples are resolved.
Leveraging the flexibility of Imageblocks
and Tile Shading,
Imageblock sample coverage control
gives you access
to each pixel sample coverage
tracking data
for even more control
of your multisample render passes.
This allows you to leverage MSAA
where you would have not before.
Some applications render complex scenes
with lots of opaque geometry
and lots of translucent geometry,
like particles.
This would have a negative impact
on the performance
due to the high number
of small, translucent triangles
which will have a lot of samples
per pixel.
In this case,
you may want to resolve your sample data
with a tile pipeline
before the heavy blending phase.
With Imageblock Sample Coverage Control,
you can resolve the sample data
with a tile pipeline
after rendering the opaque geometry
to ensure that all of the pixels contain
a single unique color.
Also, the resolve is fully programmable.
You may actually want to implement
a custom resolve
for each type of render target,
such as HDR color or linear depth.
Tile Shaders and Imageblocks add
a great deal of flexibility to the GPU.
They also help you leverage the TBDR
architecture of our modern Apple GPUs.
You can learn more about Apple GPUs
in the following Tech Talks.
These Tech Talks also cover some
great features we haven't talked about,
such as raster order groups.
Now, let's switch back to Metal
for a second.
Metal makes it possible to leverage
the improved capabilities of Apple GPUs.
We will review an example of this
for these two major areas.
First, the explicit control
of Tile Memory,
and second, GPU-driven rendering,
starting with explicit control
of Tile Memory.
Metal allows you
to take advantage of Tile Memory directly.
Tile Memory is exposed
through Tile Shaders, Imageblocks
as well as Persistent Threadgroup Memory.
You can use this to improve the efficiency
of more complex algorithms,
such as tiled deferred rendering.
This is a more advanced version
of deferred rendering
which is considered to be more efficient
for a large number of lights.
This algorithm adds an extra step
to cull all the lights into a tile list
that is used by a later compute pass
to light the scene.
So, if we start from deferred rendering,
we need to add an extra compute stage
to cull the lights.
Potentially, we could also use compute
for the light accumulation.
But this would prevent TBDR GPUs
from merging the passes,
because Programmable Blending only allows
us to work on a single pixel at a time,
and this would make light culling
far too expensive.
But Tile Shading allows us
to work on a full tile.
By using Tile Shading,
we can interleave rendering and compute.
This allows us to merge the three
render passes into a single pass.
And of course,
this is much more efficient.
But Metal also exposes the capabilities
of the Apple GPUs
through GPU-driven rendering.
This is a fairly modern concept,
possible in Metal
thanks to Argument Buffers
and Indirect Command Buffers.
Traditionally, the render loop is driven
by the CPU.
This is because the data set
and the process required to traverse it
are complex.
We need several structures
to define the entire scene.
In this example,
our scene contains a list of meshes,
materials and models.
Each model will contain indices
to a parent mesh and a material.
So far, so good.
The actual real problem here
is when we have to decide what to render.
We just cannot render everything
every frame.
The CPU will need to decide
what geometry to render
based on the occlusion culling
from the previous frame
as well as the view frustum.
And of course, the CPU will also need
to select the appropriate LOD.
This requires
several synchronization points.
The CPU needs to read occlusion data
written by the GPU
in order to issue the draw commands.
So there are two problems
that we need to solve.
First, the traversal
of the scene description,
and then the encoding of draw commands.
Metal has the following building blocks
to help.
First, Argument Buffers, which make
the scene data available on the GPU
and also allow us to describe
complex data structures.
And then we also have
Indirect Command Buffers,
which will allow the GPU
to encode its own draw calls.
So this scene...
can be flattened to an array
of Argument Buffer arrays.
And these can be efficiently traversed
by modern Apple GPUs.
Thanks to Argument Buffers, the GPU
can now transverse the entire scene.
And by using Indirect Command Buffers,
the GPU can also issue draw commands.
In this example, we can see a GPU-driven
render loop.
This is how the GPU will manage
the render loop.
It will first traverse the scene
to render occluders,
then traverse the scene again to perform
culling and the LOD selection
and then render the scene one final time.
This requires no synchronization
between the CPU and the GPU.
You can learn
how to implement these algorithms
by studying the
"Modern Rendering with Metal" sample code.
This sample includes
a full GPU-driven render loop.
It is also written using modern constructs
such as Argument Buffers
or Indirect Command Buffers.
It also leverages
modern Apple GPU features
such as Tile Shaders, Imageblocks,
Sparse Textures
and Variable Rasterization Rate.
And this was just a summary.
You may actually want to follow up
on more Metal talks.
Also, do not forget to check out the
"Modern Rendering with Metal" sample code.
And that's about it.
Today we have talked about Apple GPUs and
what makes them so unique and efficient.
We've also revealed some use cases
in which you can use Metal in order
to accelerate rendering algorithms.
So the next steps are for you to follow up
on related talks about Apple GPUs
and also explore the best practices
for both Metal and Apple GPUs.
Thanks for watching.