Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Anton, and in this session
we are going to take some time
to talk about your SwiftUI views
and modifiers inside Xcode.
Since the very beginning,
Xcode Previews was built
to put your content front and center.
For example, your views are previewable
without doing any extra work,
and most user modifiers are inspectable
right out of the box as well.
In Xcode 12, we are taking a step further
by letting you add your SwiftUI views
and modifiers to the Xcode Library.
Let's take a step back and talk about
some benefits of the Xcode Library.
First, discoverability.
As your code base grows, it can become
hard for the users of your code
to know exactly what the key parts
of your API are.
The Library is a place where developers
look to discover available visual content,
and by placing your most important
and most reusable views there,
you make them easier to find.
But discoverability is just the beginning.
Since each asset in the Library
comes in a compilable form,
it can serve as an excellent way
of educating the users of your code
about how any particular view
or modifier was intended to be used
with a clear example that can often
serve as an excellent starting point.
And finally,
every asset in the Library can be
dragged and dropped into the canvas,
and inserting views and modifiers
from the Library
allows Xcode Previews
to continue rendering,
enabling rich visual editing
for your content.
So now let's look at what you need to do
to expose your content in the Library.
And this is where the Library takes
a page from Xcode Previews' playbook.
Since the view or modifier
you're adding to your Library
is defined in Swift code,
the most natural place to define
how to expose it in the Library
is also in Swift code,
right next to the view
or the modifier itself.
The big advantage of doing that
is that the compiler can help us ensure
that the Library items remain functional
as your API changes.
To extend the Xcode Library,
we need to declare a new type
that conforms
to the Library content provider protocol.
This protocol has two requirements:
the views property, which you can use
to extend the views Xcode Library,
and the modifiers function,
which you can use
to extend the modifiers Xcode Library.
There are some differences between the two
which we will discuss in a moment,
but for now notice that both of them
return an array of Library items.
Let's look at how to create
a Library item.
The minimum amount of data
that Xcode needs to create a Library item
is a completion that will get inserted
when the user picks that item
from the Library.
But you can also optionally specify
additional information,
such as that Library item's visibility...
a more descriptive title for the item,
or its category.
There's a lot to unpack here,
and the best way to discover this API
is with a demo.
So let's take a look.
So I am here in a Fruta app that
my team has been working on for a while.
This is an app that allows the user
to explore different kinds of smoothies,
and in particular,
I'm looking at a smoothie row view,
which is a view designed to showcase
a particular smoothie with information
such as its title, its ingredients,
its image and so on.
This view is used
in a couple places in our app,
so I'd like to add it to the Library
to make their use easier.
I'm gonna do that now.
We just scroll to the bottom of this file
and add a new type
that conforms
to the Library content provider protocol.
This type can be named anything,
but for the purposes of this demo,
I'm going to call it LibraryContent.
Since what I'm adding is a view,
I'm gonna add a views property.
And now I need to add a Library item.
To finish completing the Library item,
I need to provide a completion
that represents my view.
Since what I'm adding
is a smoothie row view,
I'm just going to instantiate
a SmoothieRowView here.
I'm going to provide
some default data here for my smoothie.
I'm gonna pick out of the list
of preexisting ones.
And I like lemonberry,
so I'm just gonna pick lemonberry here.
And that's really all we need
to create a Library item for this view.
I'm ready to use it.
I'm going to switch to the smoothie list.
As the name applies, this is just a view
that takes an array of smoothies
and shows them in a navigable list.
It's empty right now,
as you can see from the preview.
I'm going to populate it
with my smoothie row view.
To do that, I'm going to click
on the Library icon in the toolbar,
which is a little plus,
and I'm gonna search for "smoothie."
As you can see,
Xcode already discovered my Library item
and populated the Library with it.
It even gave it a category, Fruta,
which matches the name of my project.
This makes local items
from my project easier to find.
It also gave it a rich title,
Smoothie Row View,
which is based
on the completion I provided.
So now I can just drag this Library item
right into my code...
and my preview will update automatically
to reflect the change that I just made.
Notice that all of the rows in this list
right now are saying "lemonberry,"
and that's because Xcode inserted
exactly what I specified
with a lemonberry placeholder.
But there's a slight difference here.
The argument
for the smoothie row view here,
lemonberry, that I provided, is tokenized.
And that's because Library items
are meant to be a starting point
that can be customized
based on the insertion context
for the view that you are inserting.
So I'm going to select
the lemonberry token here
and replace it with the data
from the list--
in this case, just "smoothie."
So the preview updates
to show me the content of the list
with the different smoothies
provided from its preview.
That's exactly what I want.
So now let's talk about customizations
options for this Library item.
And for that, I'm going to go back to
the LibraryContent struct I'm working on.
First, let's talk about the category.
The project category is very useful
for projects that are small
and add a small number of items,
such as this demo.
But for a larger project
that adds a lot of items,
this category will become pretty unwieldy
pretty quickly.
If you've ever used
SwiftUI's Xcode Library,
you noticed that SwiftUI deals with that
by adding categories
that correspond to functionality,
such as controls, layout,
effects and so on.
We can do the same
for our Library items as well.
I'm going to go back to my code
and add an argument here
to specify the category.
I'm going to pick control
because this view is most like control.
It provides data
and allows me to interact with it.
Now if I bring up the Library
with a Command-Shift-L shortcut
and search for "smoothie,"
you'll see that the category
of this Library item was updated.
It's still prepended with Fruta,
so it's still easy for me
to find the local ones,
but now it's clearly indicated
that my view is a control.
The icon for the Library item
changed as well
to indicate that it's control
with the color blue.
So views don't have to correspond
to Library items one-to-one.
It is perfectly reasonable
to create multiple Library items
representing the same view
in different configurations.
In this particular case, smoothie row view
has another argument that lets me specify
whether I want to see local popularity
of a particular smoothie.
I'm going to add a Library item
for that configuration as well.
I'm going to go back to my views property
and add another Library item.
And it also creates a SmoothieRowView,
but now it also uses
showNearbyPopularity flag
and sets its default to "true."
If I bring up my Library again...
I can see that my Library item got added,
just like I would expect,
but there's a problem.
It's really hard for me to tell
which Library item
represents which instantiations.
I can fix that by adding another argument
to this Library item instantiation
that specifies its title.
In this case, I'm gonna say
"Smoothie Row View With Popularity."
And while I'm here,
I can also fix its category
to match the other smoothie row view
as well.
Now, if I bring up the Library,
I can see that my Library item
got updated,
and it's much easier for me to tell
which one is which.
So that's a quick intro in how to add
a view to the Xcode Library.
But what about modifiers?
It turns out the idea is very similar,
but has a little bit of a detail.
Let me set the stage for a second.
As I audited my code,
I found out that a lot of times
when we use an image,
we also use
these three modifiers in a row:
resizable, aspectRatio and frame.
And the result of these modifiers
is to resize an image to a particular size
while keeping its aspect ratio.
We use it enough that I actually separated
this functionality into its own modifier.
I created an extension on Image,
and I created a function
called resizedToFill,
which takes a width and height.
And this function just takes the image
and applies the three modifiers to it
and returns the result.
I'd like to add resizedToFill
to the modifiers Library.
To do that, I'm going to implement
the second requirement
of the Library content provider protocol,
the modifiers function.
And this is very similar
to the views property,
but it requires a base argument.
When figuring out what the completion
for the Library item should be,
Xcode needs a way to be able to tell
which part of the completion
is the modifier
and which part is the thing it modifies.
And the base is the way for us
to communicate that.
So since my modifier is declared on Image,
I'm going to set this type to Image.
And then I'm going to add my Library item.
Its completion is base
with resizedToFill called on it.
And I just need to populate this
with sample data.
And just like that,
my modifier item is ready to be used.
I'm going to scroll back to my image
and delete the three modifiers
I'm trying to replace.
I'm going to bring up the Library again,
but this time I'm going to switch
to the Modifiers tab
and search for "resized."
And here's my new modifier.
I can use it right now
by hitting "return,"
and what gets inserted
is exactly what I would expect.
Xcode stripped the base part
and just inserted the modifier itself
and tokenized the arguments.
So I can customize them here with size...
and size, like it was before.
And just like that,
I used my modifier from the Library.
You may have noticed that
at no point during this demo
we had to build or run our project
to populate the Library.
This is because Xcode can harvest
the Library definitions
by simply scanning your source
for Library content providers
and parsing their declarations.
There are several advantages to this.
First, it means that if your project
is not in a runnable state,
it can still contribute content
to the Library,
which is really handy when you are
in the middle of a UI rework,
your project doesn't run, but you
still want the content of the Library.
It also means that there's
no additional build configuration required
to enable this feature,
and since Library content provider code
is never actually executed,
the compiler will strip it when
your project is built for distribution.
So this approach works really well
for building a library of content
for your work space or project,
but since Xcode scans all source files
in your work space for library content,
including any dependencies you have,
it actually works really well
with Swift packages as well.
In our project, we have a dependency
on the nutrition facts we've packaged,
which provides facilities
for visualizing nutritional information.
I'm looking for a view
that will allow me to display
caloric information of a smoothie
in my row view.
I can use the Library to explore
the content of the nutrition facts package
for a view I want.
I'm going to bring up the Library again.
But this time I'm going to switch back
to the Views tab
and scroll down
until I find the nutrition facts category.
This is a category that Xcode created
for the content of the nutrition facts
Swift package.
I can see that there's
a Calorie Count View here,
which sounds like exactly what I want.
I'm going to hit "return" to insert it,
and my preview will update
to reflect the change that I just made.
This basically looks exactly
like what I want,
so all I need to do now
is to populate this view
with data from my model.
Fortunately,
I already have nutrition facts,
so I can just type
smoothie.nutritionFact here
and have my view updated.
And just like that,
I was able to discover and use
content from a Swift package
without ever opening its source code.
To summarize, in this session,
we've learned how to extend
the Xcode Library
by creating a type that conforms
to the Library content provider protocol,
implementing one or both
of its requirements
and returning instances of Library items
that correspond to the individual items.
Thank you, and have a great WWDC.