Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Nick Teissler,
and I'm a Cocoa Engineer.
Later, I'll be joined by my colleague,
Jake Carter.
Today, we're going to tell you
how to optimize the interface
of your Mac Catalyst app.
The next level of Mac Catalyst app
is what we call "Optimized for Mac."
Optimizing for Mac gives you
Mac-like visuals and controls
that aren't available to Catalyst apps
scaled to match the iPad.
Opting in to optimized for Mac
is a build setting change
that takes effect at launch time.
An app optimized for Mac
launches in the Mac idiom.
Catalyst apps scaled to match the iPad
launch in the iPad idiom.
This particular setting
won't have any compile time implications.
So you won't have build errors
or framework issues
if you're optimizing a Catalyst app
scaled for iPad.
And we recommend
you start with a Catalyst app
that has already gone some work
to bring it to the Mac.
There's a lot you should do
before optimizing for the Mac,
like adding menu bar actions
with keyboard shortcuts
or handling right clicks in your interface
with the UIContextMenuInteraction APIs.
See these sessions from WWDC 2019
that review features you can add
to your Catalyst app
before optimizing the interface for Mac.
So let's look at what we mean
when we say "Optimized for Mac".
What exactly is getting optimized?
Optimizing for the Mac
is all about more Mac-like visuals.
So, when you bring your iPad app over
as an optimized Catalyst app,
we render that content 1:1.
Compare that to the 77% downscale
when Catalyst apps are adjusted
to match your iPad views.
In that case, 100 points in your code
becomes 77 points onscreen.
When optimized for Mac,
100 points in your code is always
equivalent to 100 points onscreen.
Not scaling your content paves the way
for many more visual improvements
throughout an app.
If you use controls
like UIButtons, UISlider, UISwitch,
UIActivityIndicator and more,
these will all render
as macOS system controls.
Here, you see a system iOS button
that will render as a system Mac button
when optimized.
These new control appearances
will have sizes and metrics
matching controls on the Mac.
It's likely they won't be the same size
as your iPad appearance.
So your layouts might be
a little bit altered.
Catalyst Optimized for Mac
adjusts text style sizes
like body, title and callout
to match the Mac.
Unlike Catalyst apps scaled for iPad,
the rendered text is no longer scaled.
The text style sizes are different.
For example, the body text style
returns 17 points
on Catalyst apps scaled to match the iPad,
whereas it returns 13 points
on Catalyst apps optimized for Mac.
The true font sizes will look noticeably
sharper than the scaled font sizes.
This also means
if you have hardcoded font sizes,
these will not be adjusted,
and your UILabel or UITextField
might feel sad.
A small part of it, probably about 23%,
won't feel home when it's on the Mac.
A final more straightforward change
to be aware of
is that Auto Layout will use Mac spacing
if you're building constraints
with the system spacing methods.
The system spacing is typically larger
on the Mac than in iOS.
So these are the high-level features
that you will get
if you choose to optimize
your Mac Catalyst app for the Mac.
It may take a minute to mentally
position Catalyst optimized for Mac
in the growing set of options
available to you to bring apps to the Mac.
Catalyst Optimized for Mac
is an alternative
to Catalyst scaled to match the iPad.
You can't have both.
Let's compare the two more directly.
So, first, one doesn't obsolete the other.
Scaling to match the iPad might certainly
be a better fit for your app,
and we'll continue to see great apps
running in both idioms.
The scaled option
is a fast path to a Mac app.
It will get your app running on the Mac.
You shouldn't need to refactor
all of your app's views
to get a great version of your app
on the Mac.
And that's part of the philosophy
behind scaled apps.
So you make some trade-offs to get
your Mac app up and running quickly.
The trade-offs you make
might be more or less desirable
depending on the specifics of your app.
Optimizing for Mac
is a possible next step.
A scaled app
favors compatibility with your iPad app.
Catalyst does everything it can do
so you don't have to make
app-wide code changes
to get an appearance
that fits in great on the Mac.
An optimized app
favors an authentic Mac look and feel.
Catalyst swaps in Mac controls
and unscaled text sizes
to make an app's interface
look its absolute best on the Mac.
Because scaled apps favor
this compatibility
with the iPad version of your app,
your layouts are preserved
as much as possible.
Most times,
you don't have to make any changes
for your view
to lay out properly on the Mac.
But given that optimizing gives you
a completely different look for controls,
you'll need to do some layout work
where you've made implicit assumptions
of the sizes of controls.
Now that we understand what is optimized
and the differences between the idioms,
we should start thinking about which apps
can gain the most from opting in.
Which apps want to be optimized
to look their best?
Apps that show lots of text
can see noticeable visual improvements.
This is because
they get the true text sizes
instead of scaled text.
Swift Playgrounds is a Catalyst app
optimized for Mac this year on Big Sur.
The rich text editor in Swift Playgrounds
drives the app's visual appeal,
so it makes sense to undertake the work
and see these benefits.
Apps with certain emphases on graphics
have potential for improvements too.
Graphics intensive apps
that use Metal or SceneKit
saw significant improvement
in our experience.
Swift Playgrounds uses SceneKit
in their "Learn to Code" series.
After optimizing for Mac,
Swift Playgrounds saw higher frame rates
and lower power consumption
on Macs with both integrated
and discrete graphics systems.
Another type of graphics emphasis
is highly custom, detailed artwork.
The differences between
scaled Catalyst assets and optimized ones
is identical to the visual differences
you see
if you display a png
scaled to fit a particular size
rather than at its natural dimensions.
You can quickly evaluate
how your app will look
comparing the two versions side by side.
The artwork in MapKit
is a great example of this.
MapKit has literally a world's worth
of custom designs and icons.
Looking at the magnified versions
of the pixel-perfect iconography
created for place marks,
we can see the difference
between scaled and unscaled artwork.
On the left here is the scaled icon that
the California Academy of Sciences uses.
On the right is the unscaled image.
See how you can count the windows
and pillars at the front of the building.
Some of that fine detail
is lost in a scaled graphic.
Just down the road is the de Young Museum.
Here, too, the unscaled asset
and even the text is sharper.
Finally, the Guggenheim Museum.
The rounded architecture is represented
more fully in the unscaled MapKit asset.
Icons are rendered
much smaller on the screen,
so the visual differences
aren't as obvious to users
as we've displayed them here.
But this still generalizes
throughout MapKit.
In dense cities like Paris, at a low zoom,
having that resolution to show
detailed road networks
is a strong motivator
for optimizing your Catalyst app
if you use MapKit prominently.
Another trait that can make an app
a good candidate
is having many control views.
Like a popover
showing some adjustable value.
That view would likely fit in better
if optimized for Mac.
Maps takes advantage of this,
using the checkbox here,
which fits in better
than a sliding switch might.
Finally, the state
of your third-party dependencies
could be a limiting factor
for your apps' candidacy.
For all of you
framework developers out there,
supporting a Catalyst target
might not be enough.
Especially if your framework
is UI-focused,
you likely need to support
optimizing for the Mac,
so you don't limit your clients.
Jake will show you
how to make changes to your code
to support the Mac idiom later.
Now we'll look at how optimizing for Mac
affects a view
from an app scaled to match the iPad.
On the left is a simple view showing
the beginning of a recipe for a tart.
The layout is built with stack views
and contains five elements:
a button, a label, a slider,
an image and a text view.
Watch closely as I optimize this for Mac
without making any layout adjustments.
Phew, looks like our layout held up okay.
The first difference that jumps out to you
is probably the system iOS button
on the left
changing to the system Mac button
on the right.
This causes the button
to have a different size at run time
and, depending on how you layout
your views, possibly a different origin.
Let me draw your attention to the windows.
They're exactly the same size in points
on the Mac screen.
Remember, though,
the point sizes of the window on the left
and all of its contents
are actually 77% of the sizes
in your app's code.
This is the behavior from
the first release of Catalyst on Catalina,
but keep that in mind as we go through
the rest of the changes.
Next, take a look
at the leading edge of each window.
The space between the leading edge
of the window and the text view
is noticeably smaller on the left
than on the right.
As we saw before, system spacing values
are generally a bit larger on the Mac.
This means, though,
that there is more horizontal padding
on the view optimized for Mac.
This gives that view
less available width to lay out in.
And this is the reason
the text has wrapped an additional line,
and the reason the slider is more narrow.
Strangely, though,
even given less available width,
the image view has taken up more space
when optimized for Mac.
It's laid out with required width
and height constraints
matching its intrinsic content size.
Knowing that, you can guess
why it's wider when optimized for Mac.
The image has gone
from being 77% of its natural size
to 100% of its natural size.
You can handle this different ways
depending on your circumstances.
The optimal way is using Asset Catalogs
to provide a Mac or iPad-specific asset.
If you don't have a properly-sized asset,
you can use
Interface Builder's trait variations
to assign a different size
to either idiom.
This fully explains
the appearance of the slider.
The slider is configured
to take up the available space remaining.
The increased padding and wider image
have decreased the space
available to the slider.
In fact, the optimized for Mac slider
is shorter by the sum
of the increased padding
and the increased width of the image.
That's enough layout for now.
Let's take a look back at appearances.
The slider on the left
is a system UISlider
with no customizations.
On the right,
you see it's adopted the appearance
of the newly-designed macOS Slider.
Notice some subtle differences
in the track height and knob shadow.
The important part for you
and the people who use your app
is that this slider is identical
to other sliders on the Mac.
One thing that isn't obvious
from these screenshots
is the difference in text rendering.
The text view is using
the body text style.
On the left, that will be a font size
of 17 points, the iPad standard.
On the right, 13, the Mac standard.
As we know,
the fonts match visually in size.
However, since the view optimized for Mac
is using a true 13-point font,
the text is sharper.
Remember that the additional line of wrap
is because of the decreased
horizontal width available
and doesn't have anything to do
with the text rendering or sizing.
If you're inclined toward
concrete numbers,
I've annotated this slide
with the layout values
so you can convince yourself
that all of these changes make sense.
Taking all of this together,
you can see that you are committing to
a certain amount of work
refactoring even some simple layouts
when you elect to optimize for the Mac.
Let's tidy up this Mac layout.
That app is truly at home on the Mac.
So we just saw that it's less about
applying rules of thumb to your layouts
and more about understanding
which elements will be changing, and how.
The payoff is this wonderful app
that looks completely at home to users.
Before we leave this view behind,
take a look
at that "Get Cooking" button on the left.
Its tint color is set to systemTeal,
but on the right,
that tint color doesn't carry over
to the Mac appearance at all.
Tinted buttons aren't standard on the Mac
and users aren't accustomed to them,
so that tint color gets dropped
for the optimal Mac appearance.
In fact, there's a larger category
of control customizations
that are unavailable
when optimizing for Mac,
either because the customization
is typical to the iPad and not the Mac,
or because their usage isn't supported
with the Mac visual appearance.
It's common to attach a gesture recognizer
to a UIButton to detect a long press
and overload the button
with multiple actions.
Your gesture recognizers
on UIButtons will not get called
if you're using a system button
that has adopted the Mac appearance.
You can handle this in a number of ways.
First, make sure you aren't bringing
an iPad interaction over to the Mac.
This might be better handled
with a menu item in the app's menu bar,
or by attaching a menu to the UIButton
using the UIButton menu property
like Maps does here.
When optimizing your app,
we recommend auditing controls
customized at the event handling level.
This includes gesture recognizers
on controls like UIButtons,
and overrides
of UIControl event tracking methods
like beginTrackingTouchWithEvent.
If the gesture recognizer
is non-negotiable,
remember that the custom button type
is not rendered with the Mac appearance
and will maintain the same event tracking
as on the iPad
and your gesture recognizer
won't lose functionality.
Look at this customized slider
to the right, here.
I've really taken off with it.
It has a white minimumTrackTint color,
and blue maximumTrackTintColor,
and has replaced the circular thumb
with an airplane.
You might experience some turbulence
when you bring this to the Mac.
In the Mac idiom,
these customizations are unavailable.
An effective mental model here
is that when using system controls,
you are limited
to appearance customizations
where standard Mac appearances
overlap available UIKit API.
I'll now hand it over to Jake who will
take you through making some changes
to a scaled Catalyst app
to optimize it for the Mac.
Thanks, Nick. Hi, my name is Jake,
and I'm an engineer on the Xcode team.
Today I'd like to show you
a simple Mac Catalyst cookbook app
that some of us have been working on.
Let's jump right into a demo.
First, let me give you
a quick tour of the app
before we optimize it for the Mac.
On the left, we have a sidebar with
easy access to common areas of our app,
like "All Recipes" and "Favorites."
Next, we have a list of recipes,
and finally, the recipe itself.
We can add new recipes
by pressing this "New Recipes" button.
Here, we can add details of our recipe
along with a photo.
This app already feels pretty good
on the Mac,
but there are some things
that feel out of place,
like the iOS-style button
and the navigation bar.
Let's switch over to Xcode
and get started.
This is the target's general settings.
Here you'll notice this new pop-up button
next to the "Mac" checkbox.
By default, "Scale Interface
to Match iPad" will be selected.
New with Xcode 12 and Mac OS 10.16 is
the "Optimize Interface for Mac" option.
Let's choose that.
What this will do is tell UIKit that
we want our app to run with the Mac idiom
which will give it
a more Mac-like look and feel.
Let's Build and Run to see what's changed.
I've set this up so that we can view
both the "Scale Interface to Match iPad"
and the "Optimize Interface for Mac"
versions at the same time.
Immediately,
you'll notice that the window is larger.
But not only that, the contents
inside the window is also larger,
and that's because
it's no longer being scaled.
The next thing I'd like to point out
is this "Timers" button.
Just by making the change
to "Optimize Interface for Mac,"
we're automatically getting
a more Mac-like look for this button.
There's also something else going on here.
Not only does the button look bigger,
because it's no longer being scaled,
it's also using different metrics.
What do I mean by that?
What I mean is that some of the sizes
have actually changed.
For example, the font is bigger,
and there's more padding
between the text and the button border.
Because of these types of changes,
the frame of the button
is actually larger.
It's these changes in metrics
that you should keep in mind
when auditing your layouts
after making this change.
Okay, let's look a little closer
at this list of recipes.
We know that the recipe images on the left
and the "Favorite" icon on the right
are slightly bigger,
because they're no longer being scaled.
But if you look closer, you may notice
that the size of the text did not change.
And that's because
we've used a dynamic text style
which automatically adjusts
for optimal legibility.
The size of the text looks good,
but I think the list would look better
if the recipe images
and the "Favorite" icon
were a little smaller,
like they were before.
Let's head back into Xcode
and get this list looking better.
This is the view controller
that manages that list of recipes.
If we look through the code here
that creates the layout,
we can see that we're using
an absolute height of 100 points.
Because of the way I've set up
the Auto Layout constraints,
if this height were smaller,
it would cause the recipe images
to be smaller, too.
I was playing around with this earlier
and found that 80 points
looks really nice.
[taps keyboard]
So I'll update this line of code
to check the idiom.
If it's "Mac,"
we set the height to 80 points,
otherwise we leave it at 100.
Now for the Favorite icon.
For that I've specified an image here
in the Asset Catalog.
I've only filled in
the "Universal" version,
so it's getting used
everywhere the app can run.
In this case, on iPhone, iPad and Mac.
As we saw, this version of the image
looked too big next to the text
when running on the Mac.
Now that our app is running
in the Mac idiom,
it'll have access to the Mac assets
defined here in the Asset Catalog.
This will let us specialize the image
and use one that's been handcrafted
to the correct size.
To enable the Mac assets,
all we need to do
is click this "Mac" checkbox here
in the "Devices" section of the inspector.
Now we can drag in
the Mac versions of our icon.
That's it. Let's Build and Run
and take a look at that list again.
Now you can see
that our cell height is shorter,
which caused our recipe images
to be smaller also.
And that our Favorite icon on the right
is a more appropriate size for the text
because it's using
that specialized Mac asset.
Let's move on and take a look
at the "New Recipe" screen.
Okay, we got that new Mac style
for this "Choose Photo" button,
which is really nice.
But there are some things here
that feel out of place on the Mac,
like this top navigation bar.
Navigation view controllers
and their navigation bars
are really useful for transitioning
between child view controllers,
so that you can show more data
on small screens.
This type of interaction
feels out of place on a Mac, though.
It's also common to put frequently used
buttons in the navigation bar.
On a Mac, the toolbar,
up here where you see the window title,
is a better choice for this type of UI.
So, the "Save" and "Cancel" buttons
should be moved,
either up to the toolbar,
or down into the view
and the navigation bar
should go away completely.
Because the "Save" and "Cancel" buttons
are acting on the data
entered in this view,
and because both of them will end up
dismissing the window,
it would be more Mac-like
to move them to the bottom of this view.
I also see a bug.
Now that we're running in the Mac idiom,
the "Title" label is bigger
than the other two labels.
Let's go back to Xcode
and get these fixed up.
This is the RecipeEditorViewController
which is used in that "New Recipe" window.
What I'd like to do is hide the
navigation bar when running on the Mac.
To fix that, we'll check the idiom.
If it's Mac, we hide the navigation bar.
Pretty simple.
Next, let's take a look at the storyboard.
Now that our project supports
the Mac idiom,
you'll notice this new idiom chooser
in the device bar here at the bottom.
Watch the view above
as I switch it to the "Mac."
You'll notice the canvas has updated.
The controls are now more Mac-like,
and are using the Mac standard spacing
and metrics.
The first thing I'd like to fix here
is the "Title" label.
At run time,
it was bigger than the other two.
If we take a look at the "Font" attribute
in the inspector,
you can see that it's set up to use
a 17-point system font.
Like Nick mentioned earlier,
this was getting scaled down
to around 13 points.
But now that we've chosen
the "Optimize Interface for Mac" option,
it's getting rendered
at its unscaled 17 points.
So that's why this one is bigger,
but why haven't the other two changed?
If we select one of the other two labels,
we can see that it's set up to use
the "Body" text style.
Like I mentioned earlier,
these text styles are dynamic
and will adjust to be the appropriate size
for the platform they're rendered on.
We highly recommend using
these text styles when you can.
Let's go ahead
and update the "Title" label
to use the "Body" text style as well.
Next, let's address
the "Save" and "Cancel" buttons.
Remember that we've already hidden
the navigation bar in code,
so even though it does show up here,
it won't at run time.
Let's add new "Save" and "Cancel" buttons
to the bottom of this view
and set them up
to only show in the Mac idiom.
First, I'll resize this bottom text view
to make room for our new buttons.
When I do,
Interface Builder alerts me to the fact
that the frames in the canvas
no longer match
the frames computed by Auto Layout.
I'll leave this for now
so we have room for our buttons.
Now, I'll go ahead
and drag out a stack view...
and pin it to the bottom right.
I'll adjust its spacing
to use the system standard spacing...
and set its "Distribution"
to "Fill Equally"
so that the buttons are the same size.
Next, I'll drag out our buttons
and update their titles.
I only want these buttons to show up
when the app is running in the Mac idiom.
So I'll select
the containing stack view...
and I'll use this "Installed" attribute
here at the bottom
of the Attributes inspector.
For a view,
this attribute specifies whether or not
it will be added to the view hierarchy
at run time.
By having "Installed" checked,
this stack view will always be added
to the view hierarchy,
but we can add a trait variation
by clicking the plus button
down here on the left.
This will let us vary the attribute
based on these traits.
New in Xcode 12, we've added the ability
to vary the traits based on the Mac idiom.
I'll go ahead and add a variation
based on these traits.
We'll leave "Installed" checked
for this new Mac idiom variation,
but uncheck it for the "Default" case.
Now these views will only be installed
when running in the Mac idiom.
Next, let's make sure that our text view
doesn't cover up our new buttons.
To do that, I'll Control-drag from it
to the stack view.
When I hold the "Option" key
on the keyboard,
the top choice changes
from "Vertical Spacing"
to "Vertical Standard Spacing."
I'll choose that one.
The constraint was added,
but some of our other constraints
turned red.
This means we have
unsatisfiable constraints.
If we look at the red constraints
at the bottom,
you can see that we still have
that 20pt spacing
between the text view
and the bottom of its superview.
This is conflicting
with the new constraint we just added.
We can't just delete this old constraint,
because when running on the iPad,
our new buttons won't be installed,
and we'll need some other way
to specify the height of this text view.
There are a couple ways we could fix this,
but I think what I'll do
is change the constraint's "Priority."
Currently it's set to "Required,"
but let's change it
to "High Priority" instead.
This way it'll be ignored
when it can't be satisfied.
We're back to all orange constraints,
so all we need to do
is click the "Update Frames" button
down here in the bottom right.
Now the constraints work
in both Mac and iPad idioms,
and we can verify that using
the idiom chooser in the device bar again.
Now when I bring up
the "New Recipe" window,
you can see that the "Title" label
is the appropriate size,
the navigation bar is hidden,
and we have the "Save" and "Cancel"
buttons at the bottom.
This feels much more Mac-like.
Let's go back to slides and recap.
So, by choosing
the "Optimize Interface for Mac" option,
you're telling UIKit you want your app
to run in the Mac idiom.
As we saw, this gives your application
a more Mac-like look and feel.
But it also means layout changes,
because the Mac standard spacing
and control metrics are being applied.
This means that controls, image views
and font sizes will be different.
So you really need to audit your layouts
after making this change.
One tip would be to check
for "unsatisfiable constraint" warnings
in the logs.
This can help find issues caused
by the changes to control sizes.
We also looked at providing Mac assets
in the Asset Catalog
to help with
some of these kinds of issues.
One thing to keep in mind here is that
if Mac assets can't be found,
the system will fall back
through "Mac Scaled" and "iPad" assets
before using the "Universal" assets.
As we saw in the demo,
it's likely the sizes of these assets
won't be optimal,
so make sure to audit your images and
provide Mac versions where appropriate.
Lastly, we looked at some paradigm
differences between Mac and iPad,
like the navigation bar
and button placement.
You should keep
these kinds of differences in mind
when designing your Mac Catalyst apps.
I would highly recommend reading
our Human Interface Guidelines
for more insight into designing apps
that feel truly great on the Mac.
While it is possible to back deploy
a Mac Catalyst app
that has been optimized for the Mac,
there are some things
you should keep in mind.
When running on Catalina,
these apps will not get
the new Mac-like look and feel.
It also means supporting
both the iPad and Mac idioms.
We found that a majority of the work
when back deploying
is making sure that your layouts
can handle the metrics in both idioms.
You'll also need to continue guarding
uses of frameworks and API
that aren't supported on the Mac.
Consider checking the idiom
on traitCollection...
or using conditional compilation blocks
to help with these sorts of things.
Keep in mind that
the conditional compilation block here
will be true regardless of idiom.
And in some cases, it may be appropriate
to use both techniques.
That's it for me.
I'll hand it back over to Nick
to tell you about SwiftUI
optimized for Mac. Nick.
Thanks for the demo, Jake.
That Cookbook app
fits right in on the Mac now.
You may know that SwiftUI is available
to Catalyst applications
scaled to match iPad.
SwiftUI is also available to use
in applications optimized for Mac.
SwiftUI takes a similar approach to UIKit
in Catalyst optimized for Mac,
but you tend to get more for free.
Its declarative syntax and layout
allows it to do more for your views
when optimizing them for the Mac.
If you've worked with SwiftUI,
you've seen how it already adjusts
your views on a context-aware basis.
For example, changing a button's style
if it's in a form or a menu.
SwiftUI also knows if views are being used
in the Mac idiom.
Just like your controls
change their appearance
for where they are in an iPadOS view,
so, too, will they represent themselves
differently optimized for Mac.
You can still expect to do
some layout work
to optimize SwiftUI interfaces
for the Mac.
Your SwiftUI layouts
will by and large shift
based off the containers you use
to compose your views.
As always, you can build more flexible
and reusable layouts,
keeping your views modular
and making proper use of containers.
Let's take a whirlwind tour
through some SwiftUI controls
and how their appearances change
from "scaled to match the iPad"
to "optimized for Mac."
This year, GroupBox is new
on iOS and iPadOS.
GroupBox is used
for layering structured content
and automatically receiving
the right semantic colors
as backgrounds for that content.
In this code sample, I've used a GroupBox
in a VStack nested in another GroupBox,
and the views have rendered automatically
with different background colors.
Your SwiftUI GroupBoxes
will appear as Mac GroupBoxes
when optimized for Mac.
This comes with some automatic padding
and layout adjustments.
Here, I've set up a Toggle in code
that uses the variable completed
as its Bool binding.
You'll see that the default representation
of a Toggle in SwiftUI on iPadOS
is the sliding switch.
We've already seen
that Mac Catalyst and UIKit
make the Mac checkboxes available,
and so does SwiftUI.
In Catalyst Optimized for Mac,
the default Toggle appearance
is a checkbox.
You can use the ToggleStyle structs
and ToggleStyle modifier
to specify a style
if the default isn't right for your case.
Similar to UIKit, system iOS buttons
will adopt the native Mac appearance.
You can even place SF Symbols
alongside them.
These are both definitely
fantastic buttons.
I don't know about you, but one of these
looks more clickable to me.
DatePicker is a little different.
On the right, you see the DatePicker
in both idioms of Catalyst.
The DefaultDatePickerStyle
renders identically across Catalyst.
Remember that here, too,
there are, of course,
other styles available to you.
The DefaultDatePickerStyle
is compact in both idioms.
This content view sets up a picker to pick
from the small, medium and large sizes.
Its binding is set up
through the property sizeIndex.
You could also bind via string values
or an enum.
When you optimize for Mac,
the Mac picker becomes available to you.
This is a control
users are very familiar with on the Mac,
and offers a much more Mac-like experience
than the scrolling picker.
Remember, the segmentedControlStyle
is an option on both platforms too.
One last control to mention.
You know that the system buttons
are available to you,
however, you also aren't sacrificing
any customizability
on your SwiftUI buttons.
If you aren't using
the system button appearance,
then you're using some custom body.
Hopefully, you're using SwiftUI's
ButtonStyle API as I've done here,
to make your button styles
flexible and reusable.
SwiftUI and Catalyst
know not to render custom buttons
with the Mac appearance,
so your custom buttons come across
exactly as they are.
I've taken some time to write
a fully custom
throwback NinetiesButtonStyle.
You can see I've applied it
as a view modifier
to the button in my ContentView's body.
Thanks to Catalyst,
I can have this on iOS and Mac
without needing to write
any additional code.
So I, like some of you, maybe,
have been experimenting with SwiftUI.
And you may know that SwiftUI
can run seamlessly in UIKit apps.
It's really easy
to build up a content view
in the SwiftUI previews canvas,
and then drop that
right into my UIKit code
with the UIHostingController.
I thought that this text-only view
from the Cookbook app
Jake was showing earlier
could use a makeover.
So I made this interactive recipe view
completely with SwiftUI.
It lets the user check off their progress
as they work through the recipe.
You can select which units of measurement
to use with a picker at the top.
Each instruction is contained
in a GroupBox...
and can be marked complete with a Toggle.
I've used a custom blue timer view
and custom SwiftUI button
to control that timer.
Now let's see
how this new iPad feature work
carries over
to our Catalyst app optimized for Mac.
Here's the app
with the plain text directions view.
And here it is with my iPad SwiftUI view
dropped right in,
no code changes at all.
I am really happy with these changes.
The picker has adopted
the default Mac appearance.
The iOS style GroupBoxes
are now using the Mac style.
Notice how using the GroupBox
also achieved a more Mac-like layout
that I otherwise would have
had to do myself.
The Mac GroupBox uses Mac metrics,
so it's a little bit more snug
around the views,
and the label of the GroupBox
has moved outside the box
which also affects
what completed instructions look like.
The sliding switches
are all now checkboxes,
and the labels of those checkboxes
are to the trailing edge of the box.
Those labels are also clickable
to toggle the checkbox,
and this is different
from a sliding switch's label behavior.
And my custom views are untouched
and scaled correctly.
I'm very excited with how easily
I was able to bring SwiftUI
right into this app
and make following our recipes easier
and more interactive
on the Mac and the iPad.
Let's review all that we've learned today.
You saw what you to expect to change
when you optimize
your Catalyst interfaces.
We went over traits that might make an app
a good candidate
for optimizing for the Mac.
Jake showed you
how to optimize your app in Xcode
using Interface Builder's trait variations
and idiom checks in code.
Finally, we saw how SwiftUI
optimizes for Mac,
and how easy it can be
to integrate new SwiftUI views
into your UIKit app.
Thanks for watching.
Enjoy WWDC 2020.