Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Boris,
and today I'm going to talk about
distributing binary frameworks
as Swift packages.
In Xcode 11, we introduced support
for Swift packages,
offering a straightforward approach
to distributing libraries as source code.
We also introduced XCFrameworks,
which provided a better way to distribute
closed source binary frameworks
and libraries.
Now in Xcode 12,
we're bringing the advantages
of Swift packages for library distribution
to closed source libraries as well,
with support for binary dependencies.
In this video, I'm first going to cover
how to use a binary dependency in an app.
Next, I'll be talking about
how to distribute a binary framework
as a Swift package.
And finally, we're going to look at how
to create a binary framework with Xcode.
While many libraries
are available in source code form,
some developers choose to not make
the source code
of their library available,
and instead,
distribute them in binary form.
Using such a binary dependency
works just like adding
a source-based dependency.
Let's look at that in a demo.
We'll start with a simple iOS app.
You select File, Swift Packages,
Add Package Dependency.
We'll pick the BinaryEmoji package...
use version 1.0...
and link the binary with our app.
Now if we look at the project navigator,
we'll see a new group,
"Referenced Binaries,"
that contains an XCFramework.
Let's look at that in Finder.
We see that it has
a bunch of subdirectories,
each of which corresponds
to a platform and target environment
represented by a target triple.
Inside, you see a corresponding
framework for that particular triple.
Let's go back to Xcode.
We can now import the emoji module
in our app's code.
And if we jump to "definition,"
we'll see which API it provides.
There's an EmojiView type
that I want to use in my app.
If we now refresh the preview...
you see the EmojiView being used.
So, using a binary dependency
really works the same
as a source-based dependency.
If you're already familiar
with XCFrameworks from Xcode 11,
they are effectively handled the same way
as if they were added
directly to your app.
If you want to use that same library
as a package dependency,
it also works the same way you're used to.
In the package manifest,
you can add an entry
to the dependencies array,
which points to the repository
the package is using
and defines the version restrictions
that you chose for this dependency.
Now that we saw
how to use a binary dependency
that someone else authored,
next, let's look at
how we create such a package
that distributes
a binary framework ourselves.
Xcode 12 offers the new tools-version:5.3
which brings the new package manifest API.
This adds a new target type:
"binaryTarget."
It has a name which corresponds
to the module name of the XCFramework...
a HTTPS URL...
and a checksum so that
the downloaded archive can be verified.
There's also an option
to point to an XCFramework by path,
that's meant for development.
Note that larger XCFrameworks,
just as any large binary files,
shouldn't be committed
to your Git repository,
because they will slow down checkouts.
Products can reference binary targets
to vend them to clients,
just like regular targets.
Binary targets use XCFrameworks,
as we saw earlier,
are only supported on Apple platforms,
can be HTTPS or path-based where the path
can point to files inside your package.
If HTTPS is being used,
the binary artifact
will be downloaded separately
from the Git checkout of your package.
This means that you don't pollute
the history of your repository
with large binaries,
and that you can use
the same download location for other uses,
such as people downloading your framework
manually.
The name corresponds to the module name.
Names are unique across the graph,
so don't bundle
other people's binary frameworks.
There should be one canonical package
for each binary framework.
As you evolve the binary targets
of your package,
you should adhere to semantic versioning,
just like you would
for source-based targets.
For example,
breaking changes to your XCFramework,
such as renaming a method or type,
should lead to an increase
of the major version of your package.
Similarly, you also want to
version your framework itself
using the bundle version string setting
in the framework's Info.plist.
More information about
evolving binary frameworks
were covered in the WWDC 2019 session
"Binary Frameworks in Swift"
that I would encourage you to watch.
Let's see how we can create
our own binary dependency in another demo.
This time we start with a new package
using File, New, Swift Package.
We will call it "Emoji."
We delete the targets
that were added by the template...
and instead, insert a binary target.
The name will also be "Emoji."
Use a URL pointing to a local server
that has my XCFramework.
And now we need a checksum.
How do we generate that?
To compute the checksum
of a binary framework,
use the "swift package compute-checksum"
command.
This will print the checksum
to the terminal,
and you can copy it from there
and paste it into your package manifest.
When your package is being used,
Xcode will compute the checksum
of the downloaded file
and reject it
if it does not match the manifest.
This ensures that your clients
use the exact binary you expect.
Now we can insert that checksum
and build the package.
And that's how you can bundle
an XCFramework
into a Swift package for distribution.
Finally, let's look at how to create
binary frameworks themselves.
XCFrameworks were introduced in Xcode 11.
They bundle up multiple variants
of a framework for different platforms,
they support frameworks
as well as dynamic and static libraries,
and each XCFramework
contains a single module.
To create an XCFramework,
set the "Build Libraries for Distribution"
build setting
on your existing framework
or library target,
archive each variant
using the "xcodebuild archive" command,
and use the "xcodebuild
-create-xcframework" command
to bundle it up.
There's a lot more detail about this
in the WWDC 2019 session
"Binary Frameworks in Swift,"
so I'd recommend watching this before
creating binary frameworks with Xcode.
Now before we wrap up,
I want to talk about the trade-offs
of using binary dependencies.
You should always carefully consider
which third-party components
you bring into your projects.
With binaries specifically,
debugging becomes harder
and making your own fixes
won't be possible.
You will also be limited
to whatever platforms
are supported by the author,
since you won't be able
to rebuild a binary dependency.
Keep these points in mind before adding
new binary dependencies to your app.
To wrap up, you can now distribute
existing XCFrameworks as Swift packages.
Depending on them works the same way
as for source-based packages.
Thanks for watching.