Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, I'm Kurt. Welcome to WWDC.
I'm here to talk about "Build for iPad."
We're here to talk about
making your app work great on the iPad
using new features
and a new look in iOS 14.
We've redesigned our apps,
like Mail, Notes and Home
to take advantage
of the power of the iPad.
I'm going to point out
some specific UI features
that you can implement too.
Mail has a new look with multiple columns.
You can easily see just your e-mail
or all of your mailboxes.
With just a few simple gestures, you can
hide or show exactly what you want.
The sidebar list design
is simple and clear.
When I tap the edit button, now there
are a lot more controls available.
It's easy to build a simple list
and then add accessories to it.
In Notes, we've made it easier to get
work done without all of the extra taps.
For example, I brought up the color picker
to choose a color for my marker.
When I draw in the document,
it automatically dismisses
the color picker
without needing a tap.
Here's another example.
The new design of Home on iPad
has a sidebar with a list.
When you use Catalyst
to bring your app to the Mac,
all of these features work there too,
but they also use the new Mac design.
We'll tell you how you can do the same
with your app
using new functionality in UIKit.
Multi-column split view is now available.
We'll give you an overview.
We'll talk about how to implement lists
in those columns
and how to get the right look.
We'll talk about reducing modality
in your UI,
and we'll give a case study
how the Shortcut app did all those things.
So, let's begin.
The heart of a multi-column app
is UISplitViewController.
It's a container view controller
that provides the structure
around the content
that you provide in your view controllers.
In iOS 14, there's new API that makes it
easy to set up and work with.
Use this new initializer
that specifies a style.
Using this initializer enables
new behavior and more new API.
The style says up front
how many columns you want.
Use the double-column style
for two columns.
We call these primary and secondary.
Then you specify
which view controller goes in which column
by calling setViewController
for a specific column.
For example, Home can provide
one view controller for the primary column
and another view controller
for the secondary column.
Three columns is just as easy.
Use the triple-column style.
What goes between primary and secondary?
We call the new column in the middle
"supplementary."
Again, call setViewController
to provide the view controller
for the supplementary column.
For instance, here's how Mail sets up
their supplementary column.
That's all you have to do
to get double- and triple-column layouts.
We've said this before, but to emphasize,
we recommend you have one app
for iPad and iPhone.
If your app is structured into columns,
use UISplitViewController
as your window's root view controller.
It handles the columns for you
by showing the right view controllers
in the right places at the right time.
What happens is based on size classes.
There are cases
when there is a lot of horizontal space,
like iPad full screen
and large iPhones in landscape.
We call this the regular width size class.
Because there is so much room,
UISplitViewController
can show multiple columns side by side.
In other cases,
there's not so much horizontal space,
like iPad apps in slide over
and iPhones in portrait.
We call that the compact width size class.
There's clearly no room
to show multiple columns,
so what do we do?
You can choose to specify
a separate view controller
that's used when the width is compact,
and it can use
a different navigation scheme
that's tailored for the space available.
You give us another view controller
for that column
by calling setViewControllerForCompact.
That's all. We do the rest.
For example, here's Shortcuts.
They use a tab bar controller
to implement a different method
of navigation
that works in that smaller area.
To sum up, don't think of it as designing
an iPad app and an iPhone app.
Instead,
you're designing two experiences--
regular width, which has multiple columns,
and compact width, which doesn't.
Let's go back to talking
about multiple columns.
There are a lot of ways
we can lay out those columns
depending on how much space we have
and how big they are.
We call these display modes.
We can show the secondary column only.
That's when you're focusing
on your content
and you've hidden
all of the other columns.
You can show a single column
beside your secondary
or over, above the secondary.
If there are three columns,
there are even more choices.
You can have two columns
beside the secondary,
or over it, or they can even displace it,
pushing it aside.
To move between these display modes,
SplitViewController
automatically creates appropriate buttons
and makes them appear in the right places.
For example, here we're showing
and hiding the columns in Notes
by pressing buttons.
You can also swipe from the edge
to show more columns
and tap to hide all of the columns.
The buttons and gestures are enabled
by the property presentsWithGesture.
By default, it's "true,"
but set it to "false"
and those buttons and gestures go away.
The property showsSecondaryOnlyButton
enables an additional button
which hides all but the secondary column.
You just saw that in Notes.
The preferredSplitBehavior property
can be set
to determine what display modes
the buttons and gestures will use.
For example, if you prefer that
the columns are side by side in your app,
use the tile behavior.
Pressing the button
will move through these display modes.
The displace behavior is similar,
but when three columns are shown,
we push the secondary column
partially off-screen.
The overlay behavior, of course,
uses the overlay display modes.
At any time, you can request
that a column be hidden or shown.
Just say which column you want to change.
UISplitViewController
will automatically do a smooth transition
to fulfill your request.
Finally, if you know your app
always wants the same layout,
specify that with preferredDisplayMode.
For instance, an app like Reminders
that always wants to have two columns
side by side,
would set preferredDisplayMode
to oneBesideSecondary.
I said the buttons get added
automatically. How does that work?
Because each column
now has a navigation controller
that's automatically created for you.
And each navigation controller
has a navigation bar at the top
and an optional toolbar at the bottom.
That means that UIKit
can put buttons in those bars,
and so can you using the standard methods.
There are a lot more details.
We recommend
you check out the documentation
to learn more about new delegate methods,
ways of controlling the widths of columns
and also how to animate
alongside the transitions.
The Human Interface Guidelines
also explain
how split views are intended to be used.
Now let's talk about the contents
of each column.
Often, you want to show lists
in your primary and supplementary columns.
For instance, Mail shows
a list of mailboxes in the primary view
and a list of mail messages
in the supplementary view.
The modern way to show lists
is using UICollectionView.
It's very powerful and very flexible,
and it's what we recommend going forward.
There's an overview video that explains
all the new API--
"Advances in UICollectionView."
I'm going to focus on a specific topic--
getting the right appearance
for the primary and supplementary columns,
and I'll give you a recipe to follow.
Let's dive into how to set up
a collection view.
This will be similar for all lists,
but we'll work through an example
that has items that are kinds of weather.
Each item shows an image and a title.
We do this setup once
when we create the collection view.
To make the collection view,
we need a layout.
That specifies the details about how
the items are arranged in a vertical list.
And we make a layout
based on a list configuration.
That specifies the default appearance
of cells,
whether there are headers and footers
and other details.
When we write the code,
it's from the inside out.
First we make a list configuration.
That's
a UICollectionLayoutListConfiguration
using the sidebar appearance.
There are other appearances
and properties you can change,
but start with the defaults.
Then make the layout
a UICollectionViewCompositionalLayout
using the list method, which makes it
a simple, vertically scrolling list,
and it's based on that configuration
you already created.
Finally, create the collection view
and give it the layout.
We do all of this once,
and we don't have to touch it again.
Next, we connect your data
to the contents of the cells in the list,
and this is where the details
of your app come in.
In this example,
I have a simple structure called MyItem.
It contains a title and an image,
and my data store
is an array of these structures.
Here's one instance of it
where the title is "Sunny"
and the image is a system image
showing the sun.
Now we need some code
to take an instance of this structure
and show it in a cell.
There's a new simple method in iOS 14.
You create a CellRegistration.
That says that given a cell of a certain
type and data of a certain type,
here's the code to run
to put the data in the cell.
For a list, you want the cell type
to be UICollectionViewListCell.
There are a lot of possibilities
for how this cell can look.
It's very general.
The way we're setting up the content,
it will contain an image view
and a label next to each other.
I'm showing question marks right now
because we haven't filled them in yet.
The data type is up to you.
In this example, it's MyItem.
Now let's fill in the code.
We make a cellRegistration
with those types
and give it a closure to run.
The closure's given the cell, the index
path on the collection view and the item.
Next we use
the new contentConfiguration API
to specify the cell contents.
There are several
built-in content configurations
for different looking cells,
but usually you want to
use the default for the cell.
We just take our item's properties
and transfer them
into the content configuration
and then, finally,
apply that content to the cell.
When your code is called, it fills in
the cell, and you see the results.
Finally, we'll connect the last piece--
make a UICollectionViewDiffableDataSource.
This tells the collection view
what items to show,
and it's based on your data store.
You push items from your data store
into it.
Then the data source calls its closure
to create cells to display.
There's a lot going on here, but all
lists will follow the same pattern.
Create the data source
providing a type for the section
since collection views
can contain multiple sections.
Each section has items of type MyItem.
This data source is initialized
with a specific collectionView.
When the data source wants a cell,
this closure is called
with an index path and an item.
You need to return a cell.
You call dequeueConfiguredReusableCell
using the cell registration
you created earlier,
and it's responsible
for setting up each cell.
Everything else is handled for you,
including all the details of reusing cells
for good performance.
This code will be the same for most lists.
The interesting parts are the type
of your item and the cell registration.
Here are the results.
Nice lists with the right appearance.
Note that we automatically adjust
the background color for selected cells
to be different in each column.
All of this appearance is customizable.
Every one of those objects
we created earlier
has properties that you can change.
For example, when you're showing
a list of content, not navigation,
you want to use a slightly different
appearance in the supplementary column.
Use the appearanceSidebarPlain
when you set up the collection view.
You see the different look.
The background is white,
there are separators
and other subtle differences.
The Human Interface Guidelines say
that if you have a list of content,
like items in a collection or folder,
then use the sidebar plain appearance.
This is very common
in the supplementary column.
With Collection View,
you can do a lot more.
Here are some examples in Mail and Files.
You can add accessories like check marks.
You can reorder items by dragging them.
You can use the outline features
to collapse and expand
items in a hierarchy.
And you can add swipe actions to rows,
for example, to remove a folder.
If you're still using UITableView,
we highly recommend you switch
to UICollectionView.
That makes it easy to add
all these features
and get all the new styles
and appearances.
Last, let's talk briefly
about reducing modality.
In iOS 14, we tried to get
the interface out of the way
in some common scenarios.
This reduces the amount of tapping around
you need to do to get your tasks done.
In Notes, we've made
the interface more fluid.
I'm bringing up the color picker
to choose a color for my marker.
And then I just draw in the document.
It automatically dismisses
the color picker.
I didn't have to tap once
to dismiss the popover
and then touch again to start drawing.
All of those extra taps used to add up.
Here's another example.
I'm in Contacts and I press
a button to show a menu.
Traditionally, at this point,
we'd put up a dimming view.
But then we would require you
to tap outside the menu to dismiss it.
Now, in iOS 14, touching outside
the menu dismisses it
and you can keep scrolling
with that same touch.
We implemented that in UIKit,
so you get it automatically.
We encourage you to do
similar things in your app.
Every app is different,
so we don't have an exact recipe.
But we do suggest, watch for user actions
like incoming events or scrolling,
and use them as a signal to dismiss
any transient UI that might be in the way.
Now you know how to use
multiple columns and Lists,
and you understand
how we've reduced modality.
The Shortcuts app adopted all of these,
and we think it's a great example.
With that I'll hand off to Natalia
to explain how Shortcuts did it.
I'm going to tell you
about how the Shortcuts app
was redesigned for the iPad.
What you learn here today will help you
build a great iPad experience
for your users.
Let's dive right in.
This is Shortcuts on the iPad.
We redesigned it to take full advantage
of the large iPad display.
For better navigation,
we replaced the tab bar with a sidebar.
This enabled us
to provide more navigation options.
And since the sidebar is collapsible,
the display becomes customizable.
Let me tell you more about how we did it.
As Kurt said before,
the Split View Controller
is the driving force
behind the multi-column layouts.
So, first I'm going to tell you
how we redesigned Shortcuts
using the new Split View Controller API.
Then I'm going to talk more
about the sidebar.
You will see all the parts
that it's made of.
By the end of this talk,
you'll have a good idea
of how these new UIKit APIs
come together
to create a great iPad experience.
First, let's look
at the Split View Controller.
Split View Controller
is the backbone of Shortcuts.
It's the API that allows us
to have these two different
view controllers
coexist side by side.
On the left is what the Split View
refers to as its primary column.
In Shortcuts, that's the view controller
driving the navigation.
Whenever we tap on one of the cells there,
the view controller on the right changes.
And the view controller on the right
is known as a secondary column.
Let's see how to set up
this layout in code.
First, we initialize
a Split View Controller.
In iOS 14, we get access to this
new initializer that takes in a style.
That style describes how many columns
we want to show in the Split View.
We want our layout to have two columns,
so we're passing doubleColumn
into the initializer.
If we wanted to have
three columns instead,
we would simply pass in
a tripleColumn style.
Next, we need to set view controllers
that will show in each column.
In the primary column,
the one we saw on the left,
we want to see a sidebar,
and a sidebar is just a view controller
with a few specific styles.
That's what
our Sidebar View Controller is,
and we're going to use that
in the primary column.
We do that by calling
setViewController for primary.
Then the secondary column.
And this one's a bit different
since we want it to be dynamic.
Whenever we tap
on one of the cells in the sidebar,
we want to update the secondary column.
So, first we need to know when the cell
is selected so we can react to it.
And for that, we conform
to UICollectionView delegate
and implement didSelectItemAt indexPath.
Then, we show the DetailViewController
in the secondary column by calling
showDetailViewController.
So now we have the Sidebar View Controller
in the primary column
and the Detail View Controller
showing on demand in the secondary column.
Now, this is great for the iPad,
but we also redesigned Shortcuts
on the iPhone.
There we didn't have space
for two columns,
so we implemented
an entirely different layout.
In compact width,
we have a tab bar in the list view,
so the navigation options that were
in the sidebar in regular width
are split between the tab bar
and the list view in compact width.
Now, this is a very different layout.
But what we're looking at here
is using the same UISplitViewController
API that we just talked about.
Let's see how that's possible.
Aside from the primary column
and the secondary column,
UISplitViewController
also has a notion of compact column,
and that's the column that we see
when the device is in compact width.
And so, just like with the other columns,
we simply call
setViewController for compact,
and the compact layout is done.
This is really powerful
because we're free to establish
our own separate compact flow,
but we don't need to worry
about switching between layouts.
All of that is done for us
by the Split View Controller.
The one thing to know
about using this approach
is the fact that we are working
with two separate view hierarchies,
the one in regular width
and the one in compact width.
So while the Split View Controller
knows which hierarchy should be used
based on the current trait collection,
we need to make sure
that the user is in the right place
as the size classes change.
Let's look at an example.
Let's say we open the app
and navigate to the Apple Watch folder.
Then we decide to open another app
in side by side.
That causes the Shortcuts app to move
from regular width to compact width.
And without us doing anything,
the Split View Controller
displays the compact hierarchy,
which is great.
But that's not the hierarchy
we just navigated.
So by default, it will put us back
at the beginning of the flow.
So, we need to make sure
that these transitions are smooth.
Here's how we're doing it.
The Root View Controller is the parent
of the Split View Controller.
That's where all the navigation happens.
Each Detail View Controller
that can be displayed
in the secondary column
conforms to a protocol,
and that protocol
requires the view controller
to provide a method that re-creates it.
When the size class is about to change,
we look at
the current Detail View Controller
and re-create it
using the protocol method.
Once we do that, we plug it
into the new view hierarchy,
and that's how we make sure
the state is restored.
Let's talk more about the sidebar.
Now we know that the sidebar
is just a view controller
with a few specific styles.
But let's take a closer look.
Here's the sidebar.
You can clearly see there's a large title,
a left bar button
that let's us collapse the sidebar
and a right bar button
that toggles the editing mode.
But what's inside of the sidebar?
It's a collection view
filled with new list cells.
Let's look at the code,
starting with the collection view layout.
The Sidebar Collection View
is using compositional layout
with the default configuration.
The one thing that stands out
is the sectionProvider.
The sectionProvider allows us to configure
every section in the collection.
The section we are providing
is using the new ListConfiguration
with the sidebar appearance.
And that pretty much
sets up the layout for us.
The section itself is a new list section.
We pass in the configuration
and we're done.
This is the entire layout.
Now let's look at the cells.
First, we need to set up our cells.
We're used to registering the cells
for later dequeuing
by calling Register on the collectionView.
With the new cell registration API,
there's a new way to do that.
We can register and configure
the cells in one place
in a type safe way.
We don't need to worry about keeping track
of forUse identifiers anymore.
We just set up cellRegistration
and pass it directly into the data source.
So this is how we register the cells.
Let's see how we configure them.
In the past,
whenever we wanted to make
collection view cells nice and custom,
we would end up creating a subclass.
We don't need to do that anymore.
And that's thanks
to the new UIContentConfiguration API.
We can mix and match configurations
to get the cells exactly as we want them.
We can create
completely custom configurations
or we can take advantage
of existing premade configurations.
For example, here we're simply using
the predefined
defaultContentConfiguration.
This returns the default configuration
with sidebar cell styling
as the cell is contained
in a list with sidebar appearance.
So we're just setting
the title and the image,
and everything else is taken care of.
So that's it for Shortcuts on the iPad.
Great iPad apps allow users
to take full advantage
of the beautiful, large display.
So try adding a sidebar to your iPad app
and be creative.
If your content needs
more than two columns,
use a supplementary column.
Use collection views
with predefined configurations.
Collection views
are much more powerful than table views,
and predefined configurations
are an easy way to add functionality
and polish to your app.
And finally,
get the interface out of the way.
Lean on gestures and enable users
to move within your app freely
without the interruption of modals
that take up all this space.
And remember to check out
the links attached to this video.
There's so much more to learn
about these new APIs.
Thank you for watching.
We can't wait to see your apps
built for iPad.