Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, hello. My name is Gavi Rawson,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Apple Health team
working on the CareKit framework.
Later we'll be joined by
my colleague Erik Hornberger,
who works on the framework as well.
We're here to talk to you today
about the updates
that we've added to CareKit this year.
So, what is CareKit?
CareKit is an open-source framework
that helps you build beautiful care apps.
The framework is split up
into three parts.
We have CareKit, CareKitUI
and CareKitStore.
Each part is a framework in and of itself
and can be imported
using Swift Package Manager.
CareKitStore provides
health flavored data models
and a core data layer for persistence.
CareKitUI provides static views
that are perfect for displaying that data.
And CareKit ties the UI
and store layers together
by providing synchronization
between the two.
When data in the store changes,
the views are automatically updated.
Last year, we rearchitected the framework
using Swift.
We made sure to design the framework
in such a way
that it's easy to use for beginners
but also provides enough customization
hooks for more advanced developers.
This year, we focused
on strengthening the framework
and building out even more new tools
that make it easier for you
to create your care apps.
Instead of giving you a boring old agenda,
we've created this sticker pack
for all the new CareKit features,
because who doesn't love stickers?
By the end of the talk today,
we'll collect all the stickers
and tack them onto our MacBook.
So, let's kick things off today
in CareKitUI,
which provides different types of views
for visualizing tasks,
charts and contacts.
This year, we're adding even more
new views to the framework.
Let's look at these new views
in the context of a wellness application
built using CareKit.
Here we have my personal feed,
showing a list of cards relevant to me.
Each card here is a new view
that we've added to the framework.
The first is the SimpleTaskView,
reminding me to do my daily stretches.
If you've worked with CareKit before,
this view might look familiar to you.
We already have a UIKit API
for the SimpleTaskView,
and now we've added a SwiftUI API as well.
Let's look at that SwiftUI API in detail.
We start by importing
CareKitUI and SwiftUI
and we write some boilerplate
SwiftUI code.
Then we add the SimpleTaskView
to the body.
We initialized the view
with a title, a detail
and a flag that determines
if the task is complete or not.
But this view is just a starting point.
So, let's say you want to customize it
just a bit.
We'll take a closer look
at the title and detail parameters
that accepts SwiftUI texts
rather than a string.
This allows you to decorate
the title and detail
using custom view modifiers.
Notice how we changed the title
to a thin fontWeight
to provide less emphasis in the header.
We'll jump back to our default fontWeight
and check out another customization point
available to us.
SwiftUI encourages you
to build small view components
then compose them together
to create more rich and functional views.
This SimpleTaskView is built
from small view components as well.
We have a detail disclosure and a header.
If you'd like, you have the option
of injecting your own custom header
or detail disclosure into the view
in place of the default ones
we provide for you.
Let's try creating a custom header
for this view.
We'll go back to our code and use
another initializer available to us.
This one provides us a closure
where we can build our custom header,
and CareKitUI provides
a few small view components
to help us along the way.
In particular, we can use a HeaderView
to help us match the style
of other CareKitUI cards.
We pass a title and a detail to the header
and place it beside a custom accent bar
in an HStack.
With that, the view is already starting
to look custom,
but let's go even deeper
using another customization point.
We can attach custom views
to any side of the content here,
which allows us to extend the card
in any direction.
Let's look at some code to attach content
to the bottom of the view.
We'll start by creating a new view
just so that we have more space to work.
Then we wrap our SimpleTaskView
inside of a CardView
and place it beside
a divider and instructions text.
The CardView is another component
from CareKitUI,
and when wrapping one card
inside of another,
only the outermost card will be displayed.
This allows us to put all of our content
into a single card.
And with that, we're all done
building our custom view,
and you can see it looks very different
from when we started.
We started with the SimpleTaskView
that had just a header
and a completion button.
And now we have a custom accent bar
and detailed instructions for the task.
Let's go back to our wellness application
and look at some
of the other new views in CareKitUI.
The next new view
is the labeled value view.
This one is great for displaying a value
and its associated units.
Here we're showing my heart rate
measurement is 62 beats per minute,
which seems a bit generous.
We can create this view
by providing title and detail text
just like in the previous view.
We also provide the completion state.
If you'd like to customize
the view even further,
we provide identical hooks into the view
as the ones we saw
for the SimpleTaskView.
The next new addition to CareKitUI
is the NumericProgressTaskView,
which is helpful for displaying
my cumulative progress towards a goal.
Here you can see
that I've exercised for 22 minutes
in pursuit of my 30-minute goal.
Just a gentle reminder
to get back out there.
To create the view, we again pass a title
and a detail to display in the header.
We also provide instructions for the task
and the text for the progress and goal.
Lastly, we pass in a flag
that determines if the task is complete.
The next new view
is the FeaturedContentView,
and this one is great
for highlighting important information,
such as an article for me to read.
Here we have a great article
on easy and healthy recipes
that I can cook at home.
Creating the FeaturedContentView
is a bit different from before.
We start by importing CareKitUI and UIKit.
We then define the view,
then set the large image in the background
and the text on the bottom of the view.
When the FeaturedContentView is tapped,
we can display a new DetailView.
The DetailView supports HTML and CSS
in the content under the image,
allowing you to put
virtually anything in here.
Creating the view
is similar to the last one.
We start by importing CareKitUI and UIKit.
Then we define styledHTML,
which is a combination of HTML
and the associated CSS for styling.
We then instantiate the view
by passing in the styledHTML
and a flag that determines whether or not
to show the close button
in the top right corner.
Finally, we set the image,
just like we did before.
The last new view is the LinkView,
which is great for displaying buttons
that present new views directly inside
or outside of the application.
Here I have links to help me schedule
a physical therapist appointment.
We create the view by supplying a title,
instructions and the links to display.
Here we create a link button that opens up
a website inside of the app.
These link options are just a few
of the many that we provide.
We also provide options
like navigating to the App Store.
But if we don't address your use case,
there's an option to provide
a custom URL as well.
So, we've reached the end
of today's feed in the app.
And that finishes up
with all of the new views
that we're adding to the framework.
These are just a few new views,
but we're essentially laying a road map
for a UIKit and SwiftUI APIs.
We now look to all of you in the community
to build on top of what we have
and improve the framework
with new views for new use cases.
With that, we can get our first sticker
for CareKitUI views,
and we can tack that on
right next to our WW sticker.
So, we just saw how we can create
static views in CareKitUI,
but CareKit goes one step further
and wraps the static views
in a synchronization layer,
so that when data in the store is updated,
the UI will reflect the changes.
So now that we have
new SwiftUI views in CareKitUI,
we're adding synchronized
SwiftUI views in CareKit.
Let's look at how we can create
one of these views.
We start by importing CareKit,
CareKitUI and SwiftUI.
Then in the body we can create
the SimpleTaskView from CareKit
by providing a taskID, an eventQuery
and a SynchronizedStoreManager
that holds a reference
to the CareKitStore.
The view will use the taskID
and the eventQuery
to locate the task data in that store.
Once it's located,
it'll be automatically mapped to the view.
And after that,
the SynchronizedStoreManager
will ensure that the view is updated
when task data changes.
But you may want to customize the way
that the task data is mapped to the view.
To do that,
we can use another initializer.
In this one, we provide
the same parameters as before,
but we also provide a closure
where we can create the underlying view
from CareKitUI to display.
The closure will be called each time
SwiftUI recomputes the body of this view.
Inside of the closure
we have access to a controller
that holds a reference
to the task data and a view model.
The view model is a convenient struct to
help us instantiate the underlying view.
So, let's use that view model
to instantiate
the SimpleTaskView from CareKitUI.
Since we're creating the view
from CareKitUI,
we have access to all
of the customization points
that we saw earlier for CareKitUI views.
So with the help of the view model,
we've essentially created
the default SimpleTaskView.
To make things a little bit
more interesting,
let's try modifying this view to display
a ResearchKit survey when it's tapped.
To do that, we first add a state property
that determines whether or not
the survey is showing.
Then we change the displayed task
to the researchKitSurveyTask.
After that, we can modify the action
to set the isShowingSurvey flag to true
when the view is tapped.
And finally when that flag is true,
we can present a popover
with the ResearchKitSurvey.
We've seen a lot of you out there
using CareKit cards
to present ResearchKitSurveys,
so this should be
a really good starting point for you all.
All right. That finishes up our section.
Let's get our new sticker
for synchronized views
and build up our collection even more.
We've clearly embraced SwiftUI in our API,
and it's brought many advantages
to the framework,
including a simplified API
and many customization points.
But one of the biggest advantages
is that SwiftUI has allowed us
to bring CareKit to the Apple Watch.
You can now build CareKit, CareKitUI
and CareKitStore all for watchOS.
On the UI side, we currently support
the simple and instructions task views,
and each have been fine-tuned
for the Apple Watch screen.
Like we said before,
these are just a few new views,
and we're super excited to see you all
take them one step further
and build new views for the Apple Watch.
That finishes up our really short section,
so let's get a shiny new watch sticker.
Now, let's move on to some updates
to the CareKitStore,
which is perfect for storing health data
in your app.
But while the CareKitStore is useful,
we already have a store
on our devices today
that's storing an immense amount
of health data.
That store is HealthKit.
And now you can use data in HealthKit
alongside CareKit data
to create HealthKit-driven tasks.
The tasks can be stored in a CareKitStore
and can be auto-completed
based on data that comes out of HealthKit.
Before diving into the new
HealthKit architecture,
let's look at the current architecture
around the CareKitStore.
We have an OCKStore,
which is a core data implementation.
The store can be wrapped by a StoreManager
that powers synchronization in the views
by emitting notifications
when data in the store changes.
The StoreManager can be used
to create synchronized views in CareKit,
like the ones we saw earlier.
Now let's look at how HealthKit
integration fits into the picture.
We've created a new
HealthKitPassthroughStore
that sits beside the CareKitStore.
While the CareKitStore uses core data
as its source of truth,
the HealthKitPassthroughStore
uses HealthKit as its source of truth.
The two stores can be wrapped
with a new StoreCoordinator.
We can interact with the StoreCoordinator
in the same way that we interact
with the individual stores,
by calling create, update
and delete methods for CareKit entities.
So, let's dive deeper
into the StoreCoordinator
to see how it communicates
with its internal stores.
When we ask the StoreCoordinator
to fetch data,
it aggregates results
from its internal stores.
But if we ask the StoreCoordinator
to write data,
it only writes to a single store
at a time,
which helps ensure that writing data
is a transactional operation.
Let's take a look at some code
that actually sets up
this new HealthKit integration.
We'll start by importing
CareKit and CareKitStore.
Next, create both the CareKitStore
and the HealthKitPassthroughStore,
making sure to give each a name
that's unique for your application.
Then create a StoreCoordinator
and attach the two stores
that we've just created.
Finally, create a StoreManager
using the StoreCoordinator,
and this StoreManager can now be used
to create synchronized CareKit views.
Now that we have a store set up,
let's actually create an exercise task
to add to it.
We create a schedule for the task,
which specifies that the task occurs
at 8:00 a.m. every day.
It also sets a target value
of 30 exercise minutes,
which will be used by the views
to display the exercise goal.
Next we create a HealthKit linkage
to help us link the task
to a HealthKit quantity.
We can use the quantity identifier, type
and unit that corresponds
to the HealthKit data type.
Now that we have a schedule
and a HealthKit linkage,
we can create the new task
and add it to the store.
To display the task,
we can use some of the new views
that we've introduced in CareKitUI.
In this case, the NumericProgressTaskView
is a perfect fit
because it shows
a progress and a goal value.
The LabeledValueTaskView above it
is better for displaying tasks
that don't have a particular goal.
All right.
That finishes up another section.
We already have a lot of stickers,
but let's make room for one more
for HealthKit-driven tasks.
In addition to HealthKit,
there are many other storage systems
out there today
in the health care industry.
The vast majority of them
store their data in a format called FHIR.
And FHIR is used so that data
can be easily exchanged and parsed.
And to make it easier for you to interact
with these databases in your apps,
we're introducing FHIR compatibility.
To understand FHIR a little bit better,
let's look at a snippet of JSON
that's structured in the FHIR format.
This JSON represents data
for a medication order of Tylenol.
The JSON is formed
in a certain release of FHIR.
In CareKit, we support compatibility
with a few releases,
including DSTU2 and R4.
To enable FHIR compatibility,
we're introducing coders
that can map between
CareKit entities and FHIR data.
To accomplish this mapping,
we make use of
a new open-source Apple framework,
called FHIRModels.
For more information on the framework,
check out the session,
"Handling FHIR Without Getting Burned,"
which is one of the best-named
WW sessions out there.
When we're doing this mapping
of FHIR data to CareKit entities,
oftentimes a single FHIR resource
maps to a single CareKit entity.
A good example is a FHIR patient.
But sometimes FHIR resources
are more granular than CareKit entities,
and in those cases, a few FHIR resources
might map to a single CareKit entity.
It's important to take this into account
when doing the mapping yourselves.
Now that we understand the coders
at a high level,
let's actually create them.
We'll start by importing CareKitStore
and CareKitFHIR,
which is a new SPM package
that contains the coders.
We can then initialize the coder
that's responsible for mapping the data,
and here we have a coder that will map
JSON in the R4 release
to CareKit entities.
Using that coder,
we can take a CareKit patient
and convert it to FHIR data.
In the reverse direction,
we can take FHIR data
and map it to a CareKit patient.
Notice that in the process,
we first create a FHIR resource data.
This helps ensure that the binary data
is JSON in the R4 format,
so that it can be safely passed
to our R4 coder.
But the mapping between FHIR data
and CareKit entities
isn't always so perfect.
For example, it's possible
that a property on a CareKit entity
cannot be perfectly represented
by a FHIR resource.
In those cases, it's important
to define the mapping yourself,
so that data isn't lost in translation.
Here you can define the way
that a patient name
is mapped to the FHIR data.
In this closure, we're given a name
and a patient
from the FHIRModel's framework.
Our job is to actually map the name
to the patient.
In the reverse direction,
you can define the way
that a patient name is mapped
from the FHIR data.
Here we're given a patient
from the FHIRModel's framework,
but this time, our job
is to extract the name components
for the CareKit entity.
Notice that these closures
expose types from FHIRModels.
Like we mentioned before,
the framework is completely open-source,
and you can find all of the source code
on the CareKit GitHub page.
That finishes up the FHIR updates.
Let's see what our new sticker looks like.
Awesome.
And now, I'll pass it off
to my colleague, Erik,
who's going to go through some
more exciting updates to the CareKitStore.
On to you, Erik.
Thanks, Gavi.
And hello, everybody.
My name's Erik.
I'm also an engineer on the CareKit team,
and today I have the privilege
of introducing and demoing
an exciting new feature in CareKit.
Gavi's just talked to you a bit
about how CareKit helps keep your views
in sync with the data in your store.
What I'm going to talk with you about
is a different kind of synchronization:
synchronization with a server.
One of the most common questions
we've received
since CareKit was open-sourced has been,
"How do I synchronize the data
in my CareKit app with a server?"
We've put a lot of time and thought
into considering how to do that
and how to do it well.
And today, I'm happy to introduce
a new set
of CareKit remote synchronization APIs.
The new remote sync API defines a protocol
for communicating with CareKit.
Any server that observes these rules
can be used as a synchronization back end
for CareKit apps.
When a CareKit app
enables remote synchronization,
changes made locally,
such as completing a task,
will be synchronized to a remote server.
Other devices can interact
with the data on the server as well.
Here the other device adds a new task
for this user.
The next time our patient
synchronizes with the server,
the store receives the updates,
and it can be displayed to them.
There are two sides to the new APIs
that enable these interactions.
The first lives on an extension
to OCKStore and is for iOS developers.
The second is a new protocol
for adding support for CareKit to servers.
Let's start with the app developer
facing bits of the API.
We've added a new remote parameter
to OCKStore's initializer.
If you pass an argument
into this parameter,
CareKit will enable remote synchronization
with the object you provided.
If you leave the remote nil,
then CareKit will continue
to function entirely off-line,
as it did previously.
We've also added a new synchronize method,
and as its name suggests,
calling this method will prompt CareKit
to synchronize its local store
with its remote store.
The policy parameter's default value
is generally the one that you'll want,
but there are other options that allow you
to completely overwrite the data
on either the local or the remote
with the data from its partner.
Let's take a look
at how you'll use these in practice.
First you'll need to import CareKitStore
plus a VendorSDK.
We'll talk more about these packages
in a moment,
but let's assume that we have one for now.
The next step is to instantiate a class
that conforms
to OCKRemoteSynchronizable.
You'll need to pass that instance
into OCKStore's initializer.
And once you've done that,
just use the store as you normally would.
Many remotes support
automatic synchronization,
which means that CareKit will call
the synchronized method for you as needed.
Of course, you're always welcome
to call synchronize manually
to kick it off on your own.
So, we've just had a look at
the app developer facing side of the API.
The other side of the coin is the new
OCKRemoteSynchronizable protocol
that back end engineers
and cloud providers can use
to add support for CareKit
to their servers.
This protocol has five requirements.
You'll need to equip your class
with a delegate,
and it'll be your responsibility
to alert the delegate
when changes happen on the server
that CareKit needs to be aware of.
You'll also need to tell CareKit if you
want automatic synchronization or not.
It can be helpful to turn this off
for deterministic unit tests,
but typically,
you'll want this to be true.
You'll also need to provide a method
for fetching changes from the server.
CareKit will give you a knowledgeVector,
also known as a vector clock
in other contexts.
This is a specialized data structure
that allows the server
to know exactly what data already exists
on your device and what doesn't.
Your job will be to send this vector
to the server,
exchange it for a RevisionRecord,
pass the RevisionRecord
into the merger vision closure
and indicate when you're done
by calling the completion block.
The next requirement is pushRevisions.
CareKit will provide you
with a deviceRevision,
which documents all of the changes
that have happened on the device
since the last time it checked in
with the server.
It's your job to pass this RevisionRecord
to your server
and tell CareKit when you're done
by calling the completion closure.
Finally, chooseConflictResolutionPolicy
will be invoked
when conflicting edits are made
on the device and on the server.
The conflict description contains a copy
of both versions of the conflicted entity.
And your job will be to inspect both
and decide which one to keep.
By implementing this protocol,
plus the server side logic to support it,
it's possible to create
new integrations with CareKit.
Now, Apple does not provide
a bespoke server implementation,
but we have made it as easy as we can
for others to do so.
And we're thrilled to announce
that we already have one partner lined up.
IBM has become the very first
to add support for CareKit
to their IBM Cloud Hyper Protect offering.
In the spirit of CareKit,
IBM has even open-sourced their work
as part of the CareKit organization
on GitHub.
If you'd like to learn more
about their SDK,
you can follow their self-guided lab
to find out how to get started.
All right.
We've done a lot of talking now,
and I'm really excited
to get to the showing.
Today we're gonna go through
a demonstration
that uses the new sync API
we've just introduced
to do something
that we think is pretty clever.
Now, the remote sync API
is primarily intended for synchronizing
an iOS CareKit app with a server,
but I'm gonna show you
how we can use the very same API
to synchronize data between an iOS app
and its companion watchOS app.
The app we're gonna be creating today
will remind our user to stretch daily,
prompt them to report any muscle cramps
and show them a chart to illustrate
the relationship between the two.
Our goal is to get to a point where the
same tasks are displayed on both devices,
and completing them on one device should
automatically update them on the other.
Now the iOS application
is actually just a pruned-down version
of the very same sample app
that we built out
in our talk from last year.
If you haven't seen that presentation yet,
I'd highly recommend
going back and watching it
to learn how we got to where
we're going to be jumping in today.
All right, let's hop into Xcode.
As I mentioned a moment ago,
the iOS application
is actually complete already.
That means that we'll be able to focus
on creating a stellar watchOS experience.
Let's begin by setting up
the synchronization
between our Apple Watch app
and our iOS app.
We'll do that by leveraging a new class:
the OCKWatchConnectivityPeer.
This class conforms
to the remote synchronizable protocol,
and it makes it possible
for the Apple Watch and the iPhone
to act as remote stores for one another.
We'll need to pass this remote
into the store when we instantiate it.
Now, in today's demo, we're going to be
working with WatchConnectivity.
And when using WatchConnectivity,
all of the messages passed back and forth
between iOS and watchOS
get funneled through
the WatchConnectivity session delegate,
which is a class that's typically owned
and controlled by you, the app developer.
What that means
is that CareKit is going to require
a little bit of cooperation on your part
in order to get its messages
back and forth.
I'll walk you through what we need to do.
We'll need to set up and activate
our WatchConnectivity session.
That'll entail setting the delegate
and calling the activate method.
For our purposes,
we're gonna define a little helper class
to function as our delegate.
The WatchConnectivity session delegate
has two required methods.
The first, activationDidComplete,
seems like the perfect place to kick off
our very first synchronization.
The second method, didReceiveMessage,
will be triggered each time a message
from the iPhone lands on the Apple Watch.
And this is where we're gonna give CareKit
a bit of help.
Each time we receive a message,
we're going to show that message
to our CareKit remote
and give it an opportunity
to furnish a response.
We'll then take that response
and forward it back to the iPhone
on CareKit's behalf.
Now that that's out of the way,
we'll just need to create an instance
of our new class
and remember to set it
as the session delegate.
Now, typically, we would need to perform
this exact same setup
on the iOS side as well.
But because it really is
the exact same setup,
we've gone ahead and done some demo magic,
and we've taken care of that already.
We have our remote setup on watchOS.
We have our remote setup on iOS.
And our synchronization story is complete.
We're going to move on
and tackle the views next.
In order to keep the views up-to-date
with the latest data in the store,
we'll need to provide them
with a reference
to a SynchronizedStoreManager.
Let's create one right here.
We'll be building out our views
in SwiftUI today.
And when using SwiftUI,
EnvironmentValues can be a great way
to provide a reference
to your StoreManager to your views.
Here we're defining a new EnvironmentKey
that provides
a SynchronizedStoreManager.
For the default value,
let's use the instance owned
by our extensionDelegate.
We'll also extend EnvironmentValues
to define a new property: storeManager.
And we'll use this property
as an environment variable
inside of our TodaysTasksView.
Now that we have a reference
to the storeManager,
we can begin fleshing out our view.
We want to display two task cards
and we'll wrap both of them
inside of a ScrollView.
We'll also go ahead
and tint that ScrollView red
to match the theme of our iOS application.
Now on iOS we chose to use
the InstructionsTaskView
for the stretch task.
So we'll do the exact same thing here.
Similarly, we'll use the SimpleTaskView
for the cramps card.
And because reporting cramps
is sufficiently self-explanatory,
we'll demonstrate the use
of a secondary initializer
to hide away the detail label
and create a nice crisp view.
With our view complete,
our app is now finished.
Let's build, run and see how it looks.
Note that the very first time
we run our app,
we won't see any tasks appear
immediately on the Apple Watch.
This is because it will take a moment
for synchronization
between watchOS and iOS to complete.
But once it does, we should see our tasks
appear on the Apple Watch.
And we do.
Let's go ahead and try reporting
muscle cramps on the iPhone
to see if it makes it across
to our Apple Watch.
It does. This is looking really good.
Remember, all of the views in CareKit
are synchronized with the store.
What that means is that, in a moment,
when I check off our stretch task
on the Apple Watch,
we should see all the subscribed views
on the iPhone update simultaneously.
Keep an eye on the adherence ring,
the stretch task card
and the chart as I complete our task.
There is just something about that
that is really satisfying.
There's a bit more here
that we can tinker around with,
but I think that you all get the gist.
So I'm gonna go ahead
and wind down our demo right here.
Let's recap.
We've taken a look
at the new APIs in CareKit.
We've also looked
at how you can add support for CareKit
to existing servers or clouds.
Then we demonstrated
how these new APIs can be used
to synchronize an Apple Watch
with an iPhone.
We've worked really hard for this one,
so let's claim
our remote synchronization sticker.
I'm gonna hand things back to Gavi now.
And he's gonna cover
our very last topic for today:
community updates.
Take it away, Gavi.
Thanks, Erik.
We're really excited
about the new remote synchronization API,
and we can't wait to see how all of you
will use it in your apps.
Like Erik mentioned, next we'll go through
some community updates.
And each year,
there's amazing work that's done
by all of you in the community.
And I'm super excited
to share those updates with you today.
Erik just talked all about
our new remote synchronization API.
As a member of our community,
IBM has been one of the first adopters
of the API.
You can find all of their source code
on the CareKit GitHub page.
Setting remote synchronization aside,
each year we love to highlight
amazing apps
that are on the App Store today,
making great use of CareKit
and ResearchKit.
To call out a few, the OYM Athlete app
helps support athletes' nutrition goals
by providing daily meal tracking
and trends using our chart views.
The Health Connected app
makes it easy for you to share health data
with your doctors and family members
and makes use of contact views
and charts as well.
We've also seen apps leverage CareKit
and ResearchKit
to quickly respond to COVID-19.
The Stanford First Responder app
is helping responders
assess their risk for COVID-19
and quickly get them tested.
The University of Nebraska's
1-Check COVID app
is providing investigators
with greater awareness of the disease.
These are just a few of the apps
released this year,
but we'd love to hear
how you've been leveraging the frameworks,
and we'll show you how to do that
in just a bit.
Last year, we announced that
we'd be releasing a brand-new website.
It's out there now at researchandcare.org
and acts as a beautiful landing page
for the frameworks.
On our overview page,
you can get a snapshot of the features
in both CareKit and ResearchKit
and get insight into how the frameworks
can help you and your app.
To get more specific information
on CareKit,
you can navigate to the CareKit tab
where you can browse through
CareKit features,
and as you scroll more,
you can read case studies from programs
that are using the frameworks
to help people on a daily basis.
You can also check out
our Investigator Support Program,
which aims to support researchers
with Apple Watches for their studies.
And if you're interested
in applying for this program,
please reach out to us using
the e-mail address on this page.
And finally,
there are a lot of you out there using
ResearchKit and CareKit in your apps.
Like I mentioned before,
we'd love to hear all about your use case
and how you've been leveraging
the frameworks.
So, please reach out to us
using this submission form.
Now comes a bittersweet moment
where we get our last new sticker
for community updates.
It's been a long journey
and we've talked about everything
from a beautiful new UI
to enhancements to the CareKitStore.
I hope you're all as excited as I am
about all of the new updates.
I think it's about time
we earned our badge
for this year's new CareKit features.
To get started with the framework,
make sure to check out our GitHub page
and newly designed website.
And as you all know,
we're an open-source framework,
and we're made better by all of you
out there in the community
that put in the hard work
to build new features
and contribute them back.
So don't be afraid to open up
your first PR on GitHub
whether it's big or small.
And to finish things off today,
the team just wants to take a moment
to thank all of you for being
amazing supporters of the framework
and for improving health in the world.
We can't wait to see
what you all build next.
Thank you.