[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Matt Ricketson,
and I work on the SwiftUI team.
Later on,
I'll be joined by my colleague, Taylor.
Last year we introduced SwiftUI,
a powerful new way
to build great user interfaces
on all of Apple's platforms.
We're incredibly excited to show you
what's new
in SwiftUI's second major release.
As you'll soon find out,
there are a ton of new features this year,
much more than we can cover
in just one talk.
But we'll try to cover as much as we can,
and along the way,
we'll let you know about other sessions
that you can check out to learn more.
First up, we'll introduce
the new app and widget APIs.
We'll also talk about improvements
to displaying lists and collections.
We'll introduce new multi-platform APIs
for toolbars and controls...
and also show you
new kinds of visual effects
for styling your apps.
Finally, we'll discuss new ways
for your SwiftUI apps
to integrate with the rest of the system.
But let's start with apps and widgets.
For the first time, you can build
an entire app using just SwiftUI
instead of embedding your SwiftUI code
within a UIKit, AppKit or WatchKit app.
Let's take a look.
What you see here is a complete SwiftUI
app, a simple "Hello, world!" example.
That's right.
This is a 100% functioning app.
You can build and run this code.
In fact, it's so concise
that you can fit the entire app
into just 140 characters.
But don't let this deceive you.
SwiftUI packs a ton of intelligent,
automatic, but also customizable behavior
into a simple and flexible API
for declarative apps.
Here I've written an app
for keeping track of the books
I'm currently reading in my book club.
At the bottom, I've written a custom view
to represent my app's main user interface.
And at the top, I'm using that view
as the content of my app's main window.
The first thing to notice here
is how similar these two declarations are.
We designed SwiftUI's new app API
to follow the same declarative,
state-driven patterns
you're already used to in your view code.
In both cases, you define a struct
conforming to a protocol.
You can declare data dependencies
using properties,
and that data is used
within the body property,
which, for both apps and views, defines
their declarative user interface content.
However, you may notice one key difference
which is the return type
of the app's body property.
The body of an app returns a scene,
a new concept in SwiftUI that represents
pieces of an app's user interface
that can be independently displayed
by the platform.
We've prepared a whole talk
that goes into more depth
on what scenes are
and how they relate to apps and views.
For now, I just want to focus
on the scene we're using in this app
called WindowGroup.
That's because WindowGroup is a powerful
example of how scenes in SwiftUI
can provide intelligent, multi-platform
functionality out of the box.
In our iOS app,
WindowGroup is creating and managing
a single full-screen window
for our application.
But the same code can also run on watchOS,
also managing a single full-screen window.
Of course, our watchOS app looks different
than our iOS app,
but the core app structure is the same
on both platforms,
allowing them to share
a single app declaration.
In fact, my app will also work on tvOS
and on the iPad too.
And since iPadOS supports
multi-window apps,
we get some additional functionality
for free...
like being able to create
multiple instances of the app
that can appear side-by-side.
This also extends to macOS,
which also supports multiple windows.
I can create new windows
using the standard command-N shortcut
and gather them up
into a single tabbed window.
SwiftUI will even automatically add
a new window menu command
into my main menu.
And all of this is made possible
by this simple app declaration
using the new WindowGroup API
to define my interface.
SwiftUI supports other types of scenes
as well,
which can be composed together,
like views, to build more complex apps.
Like the new Settings scene
available on macOS
for adding a preferences window
to your Mac app.
The Settings scene
will automatically set up
the standard preferences command
in the app menu
and also give the window
the correct style treatment.
SwiftUI's scene APIs
also support document-based apps
like this app that I built
for drawing vector shapes.
New this year
is the DocumentGroup scene type,
which automatically manages opening,
editing and saving document-based scenes,
supported on iOS, iPadOS and macOS.
On iOS and iPadOS, DocumentGroup will
automatically present a document browser
if no other main interface is provided.
And on the Mac, DocumentGroup will open
a different window for each new document,
and also automatically add commands to
the main menu for common document actions.
Speaking of menu commands, SwiftUI
lets you add additional commands as well
using the new commands modifier.
For example,
here I've added a custom shape menu
for adding new shapes to the canvas.
macOS will automatically add custom menus
in the correct section of the main menu
and will show their keyboard shortcuts
which we assigned using
the new keyboardShortcut view modifier.
Commands API has a lot more to offer
than what we've shown here,
such as being able to target commands
based on user focus.
It's really fun to work with.
You can check out
our reference documentation to learn more.
There's a lot more to say
about apps and scenes,
and we've prepared a few other talks to
help you dig deeper into these new APIs.
"App Essentials in SwiftUI"
explains how views, scenes and apps
all work together in more depth.
And "Document-Based Apps in SwiftUI"
dives deep into how to open
and manage documents in your app.
To help you build these new apps,
we've also updated
the "new project" experience in Xcode
by adding new multi-platform templates
specifically for SwiftUI apps.
These new templates are optimized
for multi-platform code,
automatically setting up groups
for shared code
as well as platform-specific components
and assets.
Another part of the project experience
we're extending
is how you configure
your app's launch screen.
New this year
is the Launch Screen Info.plist key.
This allows you to declare
various combinations
of standard launch screen components
such as default images, background colors
and empty top and bottom bars
like I've configured here.
You may already be using a storyboard
for your launch screen,
which still works great,
and there's no reason to switch.
But for new SwiftUI projects
that otherwise don't use storyboards,
Launch Screen configurations
are a simple alternative.
Now let's talk about widgets, an exciting
new feature on iOS, iPadOS and macOS.
Widgets are built exclusively
with SwiftUI.
You build widgets just like apps and views
using a custom struct
conforming to the new Widget protocol.
You can make many different types
of widgets,
like this one that periodically recommends
a new album for me to listen to.
Widgets can also be configured with
other kinds of data such as Siri intents.
There's a lot to cover
when it comes to building widgets,
and we have several talks
to help you get started.
I'd recommend watching "Build SwiftUI
Views for Widgets" to learn more.
And finally, you can now use SwiftUI
to build custom complications
for Apple Watch.
You can build a full-color complication
like this weekly coffee chart I made
and also customize how it looks
within a tinted watch face,
like this cool blue tint
that I like to use.
To learn more, check out
"Build Complications in SwiftUI,"
or if you're new
to building complications,
I'd recommend starting with
"Creating Complications on Apple Watch."
Next, let's talk about improvements
to displaying lists and collections.
Lists are a vital component of many apps,
often representing the primary interface
that users interact with.
In this release,
lists are gaining some great new features.
I'm especially excited
about the new support for outlines.
Regular lists enable concise declarations
of dynamic, data-driven content.
By providing a children key path
to its initializer,
a list can now build out
recursive outlines of content.
By default,
this shows up using the expected
system-standard styling on macOS...
and on iOS and iPadOS.
We hope that easy-to-use outlines
can help reduce the need
for disruptive
push-and-pop navigation patterns
within content-focused apps.
Along with lists and outlines, it's also
common to show collections of content
in other kinds
of scrollable layouts such as grids.
This year, SwiftUI is adding support
for lazy-loading grid layouts
which can be composed with scroll views
to create smooth-scrolling grids
of content.
Grids are powerful layouts that support
a variety of different configurations,
such as adapting the number of columns
to fit the available space
like we see here
in both landscape and portrait.
Or forcing a fixed number of columns that
can each have their own sizing parameters,
like this example that sticks
with four columns in every orientation.
And, of course, SwiftUI also supports
horizontally scrolling grids.
We're also exposing lazy-loading versions
of the existing
vertical and horizontal stack layouts,
which are great for building
custom scrollable layouts
like this asymmetric gallery of images.
Let's take a closer look.
Here we're using a lazy vertical stack
containing all of our gallery content.
We're also using the new view
builder support for switch statements,
allowing us to easily alternate between
different image layouts within the stack
such as the single large image
shown at the top...
the asymmetric groups of three images...
and the shorter rows of smaller images.
Together, composed with
a lazy-loading vertically scrolling stack,
they form a seamless gallery.
Lists and collections
are powerful features of SwiftUI,
and we've only scratched the surface
of what they're capable of in this talk.
To learn more,
you should really check out our talk
on stacks, grids and outlines.
And now to talk about toolbars and
controls, I'll hand things over to Taylor.
Thank you, Matt.
It is so cool to see how easy it is
to have our app's model come to life
using SwiftUI
with things like the new DocumentGroup
and new collection views.
Now let's jump into
the powerful toolbar support in SwiftUI
and new ways to customize controls.
Toolbars and apps across our platforms
have some amazing new updates,
from their beautiful new look
in macOS Big Sur
to the updated iPad system experience
to the primary actions in watchOS.
And this year, SwiftUI has a new API
for constructing all of these
using the new toolbar modifier.
Toolbar items consists of the same views
you use throughout the rest of SwiftUI,
in this case, a button.
They'll be placed in idiomatic locations
by default
but can be explicitly customized
through the use of toolbar items.
In this case, the primary action
is the default placement on watchOS,
but there are other placements as well.
For instance, confirmation
and cancellation modal actions.
These are examples of semantic placements
where you're describing to SwiftUI
the role that these toolbar items have,
and SwiftUI automatically figures out
the right spot.
Another example is the principal placement
to give an item prominence in your app,
as you see here on iPad...
and on macOS.
Toolbar items
can have positional placements
where you want to have
that extra level of design control
over where your items are placed.
Particularly in narrow size classes, it's
common to have items in bottom toolbars,
and the literal bottomBar placement
allows you to explicitly specify that.
You've probably noticed
in a few of these examples
the use of a new label view in SwiftUI.
Let's take a closer look at that.
This is a combined representation
of a title and an icon
that can be used to label UI elements.
Here we have a string
used as a localization key for its title
and the name of a system image,
or SF Symbol.
And this year, not only
are symbols available on macOS,
but there are hundreds of new ones
available for your apps to use.
The "SF Symbols 2.0" talk
goes into more detail
on all the new enhancements
to symbols this year.
This construction of Label
is actually a convenience
for its full form,
which is using any view
for that title and icon.
And its power comes from the semantics
it provides for that title and icon,
so they can be treated appropriately
based on where they're used.
So, returning to our toolbar example,
in the context of a toolbar,
by default it'll just be the icon
visually presented as that button's label
and the title used
for accessibility purposes.
This behavior extends from toolbars,
to context menus, to lists.
Now, this list contains
multiple rows of labels.
The titles are perfectly aligned,
regardless of image size
and the power of Labels really shines
when using different dynamic type sizes.
This is showing the layout
for the default large size category
and as that changes to extra extra large,
both the icon and title
update automatically,
including nicely reflowing the text
and growing the list rows.
An even further specialization happens
at the larger accessibility sizes.
At those, the labels
have updated text wrapping
around the icon to maximize
the amount of visible text.
Now, with contexts
like toolbars having clean,
icon-only styles of labeling elements,
providing additional help
or context for those
is more important than ever.
With the new help modifier,
you can attach these descriptions
of what effect a control will have
and that will manifest
as Tool Tips on macOS.
What's really cool is that this modifier
is available on all platforms
as it also provides an accessibility hint
to provide an even better
voice over experience
for your app everywhere.
Here we can see a similar experience
for an app on the phone
for that same toolbar item.
[Siri] Progress button.
Record new progress entry.
It is so cool how our SwiftUI declarations
can naturally improve the experience
of our app for everyone.
Now, another new way of bringing
more flexibility and power
to how people interact with your controls
is using the keyboard shortcut modifier.
These are most often used
for scene commands
as it's critical for allowing
those commands to be accessible
via keyboard shortcut on iPad
and on macOS through the main menu,
like Matt showed earlier.
However, keyboard shortcuts
can also be used
for other controls
that are shown on screen,
such as creating Cancel
and default action buttons
that have keyboard shortcuts
of Escape and Return keys.
From keyboards, to TV remotes,
to the watchOS digital crown,
focus drives how these indirect inputs
are routed in your app.
And using the new default focus support,
your app can now control
where focus starts on screen
and how that default might change
alongside your app state.
The "SwiftUI for tvOS" session
goes into more detail
on using that new support,
as well as other tips for crafting
a great tvOS app using SwiftUI.
Last but not least,
there are a couple of new controls
that you can now use throughout your app.
First, there are progress views.
These can be used to display determinate
and indeterminate progress over time.
There are both linear
and circular style progress views,
the latter enabling everyone's favorite,
spinning style,
as a display of indeterminate progress.
A similar new control are Gauges.
Gauges are used to indicate
the level of a value
relative to some overall capacity.
Here I have a circular watchOS gauge
for tracking the acidity level
of my garden's soil.
Gauge has additional
optional customizations.
Tomatoes are finicky enough
to where I'd really like to see
the exact pH level at a glance.
So I can add a current value label
to allow that to be displayed.
Gauge can also have minimum
and maximum value labels.
In some cases, those might be image icons,
but here I'm just gonna display
those pH levels as text.
Now, this code snippet also highlights
the new multiple trailing
closure syntax in Swift.
It allowed the expression
of our gauge to grow naturally
as it gained additional complexity.
It is really nice having
a new, expressive way
of creating toolbars across
all of the platforms my apps support,
plus these new means of really fine-tuning
the behavior of controls
both in and out of toolbars.
Next up, let's take a look
at new ways of crafting
immersive and fun experiences
using SwiftUI.
macOS Big Sur has a gorgeous revamp
to Notification Center
and the new Control Center
in the menu bar,
both built using SwiftUI.
Control Center features
these smooth animations
in and out of its different modules
using a new feature in SwiftUI
that you can use in your own apps.
Here I built a little prototype of UI
to gather up my favorite albums.
It consists of a scrolling grid of albums
and a row of the selected ones.
Now, on selection, rather than
the albums just popping into that row,
I'd really like them to fluidly
transition from the grid.
And using matched geometry effect,
it's really easy.
I can apply the matched
geometry effect modifier
to the albums in both the grid
and the selected album row
using the album's identifier
as the identifier
to connect the two views,
as well as the namespace
that those identifiers are relative to.
In this case, it's the namespace
associated with the containing view.
And that's really all it takes
to create this effect.
As an album is removed from one section
and inserted to the other,
SwiftUI will automatically interpolate
their frames as a seamless transition.
Another fantastic new tool
is ContainerRelativeShape.
This is a new shape type
that will take on a similar path
of the nearest containing shape.
We can see the effect here
in a widget for our favorite album.
The clip shape on our album artwork
automatically took on
a concentric corner radius
relative to the shape of the widget
and so fits perfectly within it.
We can really get a feel
for how cool this is
by changing that padding,
which effectively changes the offset
to that outer container shape,
and thus the clipping of our view,
using ContainerRelativeShape,
reacts beautifully...
automatically maintaining
that concentricity based on its offset.
There are a few other enhancements
to refine the experience
of text related elements as well.
Custom fonts will automatically scale
with dynamic type changes.
Further, now that images
can be embedded within text,
they'll act
as a unified part of that text,
including reacting to dynamic type.
And for any custom non-text metrics,
such as for layout,
there's a new scaled metric
property wrapper
that automatically scales some base value
against the current dynamic type size.
All together, these make it so easy
to create responsive, custom layouts
that react well in these larger
accessibility sizes.
There'll be another talk
that goes into detail on this,
as well as other advanced
font and typographic features
that can be used
to really make your app shine.
Now, these were a few of the new tools
for building creative
and reactive custom views.
But the enhancements
to styling your app don't stop there.
Even when using system controls,
you can customize them to look
and feel at home on your app
and make your app stand out from the rest
by using a custom accent color.
New this year is the ability
to customize that accent color on macOS
and new support for customizing
that accent color
directly in the asset catalog in Xcode 12.
This lets you easily specify that color
for all of the platforms
that your app supports.
Now, this is great for applying
a broad theme color across your app.
But there are also cases
where you might wanna specifically
customize the tint of a single control.
Now, by default, cyber icons
on iPadOS and macOS
follow the app accent color.
With a new listItemTint modifier
you can customize the tint of those icons
per item or even for an entire section.
The same affect applies to macOS sidebars
where these modifiers
also react appropriately
for changes to the system accent color.
This same modifier also applies to watchOS
where it's used to tint
the standard platter background.
And we've brought this tinting support
to other controls as well.
Using new style customizations,
controls like buttons and toggles
can now be explicitly tinted.
Here, the switch fill is customized
to follow the overall themed accent color
rather than the default green.
Now, all of these new views
and interactions
enable even more polished
and fun experiences within your app.
And last, but certainly not least,
let's look at new ways your app
can integrate and take advantage
of functionality and services
provided by the system.
This year, SwiftUI has a first-class API
for opening URLs,
available on all platforms.
One form of this is in a new Link view,
which takes the URL to open
and the label of the link.
It does what you'd expect,
creating a visual element with that label
and opening that URL
with the default web browser.
But in addition,
it can also open universal links
directly into other apps.
In this case, News.
Links also even work within widgets,
where they can even link directly
back into content within your main app.
Now, in the context of apps,
there are cases where URLs
need to be programmatically opened.
For these advanced cases,
there's also an openURL action
in the environment,
which can be called with the URL to open
in an optional completion handler.
Because it's in the context
of a specific view,
SwiftUI automatically opens that URL
relative to its containing window.
In an update to iPadOS 13,
SwiftUI gained support
for enabling your app
to both drag to other apps
and receive drops from those apps,
making your iPad app
even more powerful and integrated.
In iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
this API is built
on top of a new framework
that enables stronger typed identifiers
for the contents being dragged,
using the new
Uniform Type Identifiers framework.
This has been adopted throughout SwiftUI,
allowing you to take advantage
of its features throughout your app,
from extending it with your app's
custom exported or imported types
to introspecting a type.
For instance, getting
its human presentable description
or validating its conformance.
The "Document-Based Apps in SwiftUI" talk
has more details,
such as the differences
between imported and exported types.
And there's also some great documentation
available on Apple's website.
One last example of enabling your app
to integrate with other services
is the Sign in with Apple button.
This is again a first-class SwiftUI API
provided by AuthenticationServices
and available on every platform.
What's really cool is that simply
by importing AuthenticationServices
and SwiftUI together,
you get these new APIs.
There's no new import or framework needed.
And this is just one example
of the many Apple frameworks
that are now providing
SwiftUI views and modifiers.
From video players, to maps,
to app clip overlays,
it's even easier to bring
these advanced features
into your SwiftUI app.
Many of these are fully multi-platform
including natively on watchOS,
meaning when you learn how to use
these frameworks for one platform,
you can apply that anywhere.
And that was a quick summary
of some of the new ways
your apps can integrate and take advantage
of the various system features
now available in SwiftUI.
We've run through
a lot of new features and APIs
and like Matt mentioned in the beginning,
there's just so much more
that we didn't have time to talk about.
But as one last callout,
throughout the talk
we came across a few examples
where our app's SwiftUI code
was made even better
from improvements to the language itself.
This year's "What's New in Swift"
goes into more details
on all of the awesome changes in Swift.
It has more examples of syntax refinements
like builder inference and support
for switch and if let inside of builders.
The compiler now has
even better diagnostics
that helps more quickly
pinpoint build errors in your code.
And finally, improved performance,
such as reductions of code size
for your SwiftUI apps
and faster code completion.
And these are the types of things
that make using SwiftUI
that much more enjoyable.
We are so excited to share
all this with you this year,
but lastly, thank you.
Thank you for the excitement
and passion we've seen from the community.
Thank you for the reports
on Feedback Assistant,
the commentary on social media,
the discourse on the forums,
the many days of tutorials,
and all of the amazing prototypes
and explorations people have built.
We were just blown away
by the excitement we've seen
and are really looking forward
to what's yet to come.
[chimes]