Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Caleb.
I'm a software engineer on the tvOS team.
Today, I'm excited to share with you
a great new way for your apps to support
multiple users on Apple TV.
Apple TV is designed to be used
by everyone in your home.
And we think it's really important
that everyone who uses Apple TV is able to
access all of their own content and data.
In tvOS 13, we made switching users easy
by adding fast user switching
right in Control Center.
We also added the TVUserManager API
so apps can link their own user profiles
with users on the device.
So if your app has its own user profiles,
I encourage you to watch
"Mastering the Living Room with tvOS"
from WWDC 2019
so you can learn how TVUserManager can
help take people right to their content.
But what if your app doesn't have
its own user profiles?
What if you want to store separate data
for each user instead?
Today, tvOS apps have access
to a single set of resources
for the entire device.
That means things like iCloud, Game Center
and Local Storage for your app's data
are the same
no matter who's using Apple TV.
But wouldn't it be great
if your app knew who was using it
so you could create a personalized
user interface
and access data from their other devices
using iCloud?
In tvOS 14,
we're making it really easy
for your apps to do exactly that.
Now, each person who uses your app
will have access
to all of their own data in iCloud,
Achievements and Friends and Game Center,
and even their own local data
and preferences.
And because your apps can access data
in each user's iCloud,
everyone using Apple TV will now be able
to start a game on their iPhone,
continue playing on Apple TV
and easily sync their progress
across all of their other devices.
Let's talk about how this works.
When your app declares support
for multiple users in tvOS 14,
it will be given access to accounts
and storage for the selected user.
When a new user is selected,
your app will be given a chance
to save any unsaved data,
then it will be terminated.
If your app was running in the foreground
when a new user was selected,
it will be automatically relaunched
for the new user.
So far, I've only mentioned iCloud
and Game Center by name.
But I'm happy to share that all of the API
we provide for storing data,
both locally on Apple TV and in the cloud,
support storing individual user data.
And the best part is
you don't have to make any code changes.
You can keep using all of the API you're
already using to read and write data,
and the system will take care of the rest.
By now you're probably excited to learn
how to enable this for your apps.
There are only three things you need to do
to support multiple users
in your tvOS apps.
I'm going to go over them with you now,
starting with User Management capability.
In tvOS 14 and Xcode 12,
we have a new Runs as Current User option
in the User Management capability.
This tells the system that you want your
app to be able to support multiple users.
You can add the User Management capability
by navigating to your app's
Signing and Capabilities editor in Xcode.
And when you add this to your app target
in Xcode 12,
the Runs as Current User option
will be selected by default.
Next, I'd like to talk about changes
to the application life cycle.
Earlier I mentioned that when the selected
user changes, your app will be terminated.
If your app is currently running,
make sure you save any unsaved data
before your process exits.
You can do that by implementing
applicationWillTerminate
in your app delegate.
And note, they're given
a limited amount of time to perform tasks
when this function is called,
so be sure to do as little work
as possible to save any user data.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here I implemented
applicationWillTerminate
in my app delegate.
First, I check whether my game has
any changes that need to be saved.
If not, it's best to return right away so
the system may continue switching users.
Next, I ask my game
to save any unsaved data
both locally and to CloudKit.
Once this function returns,
the system is free to terminate my process
and switch users.
So I'm using a semaphore
to keep it running long enough
to save data asynchronously.
There's one last change
you may have to make
if your app uses CloudKit
subscription notifications.
When your app supports multiple users,
it may get CloudKit notifications
for other users on the device
who have used your app.
To make your app more efficient,
you should check
the new subscriptionOwnerUserRecordID
property on CKNotification
and compare it with the RecordID
of the current CloudKit user.
If the notification was meant
for a different user,
it can be safely discarded.
In this example,
I implemented the application
didReceiveRemoteNotification function
in my app delegate.
I start by initializing
a CKNotification object,
fromNotification userInfo dictionary.
Next, I check the notification's
subscriptionOwnerUserRecordID
and make sure it's equal to
my game object's currentUserRecordID.
Once I know this notification
is meant for the current user,
I tell my game object
to handle the notification
and call the completion handler.
That's it.
That's all you need to do
to prepare your app
to support multiple users in tvOS 14.
And now, I'd like to show you a demo.
Here, I have a simple game
that I ran from Xcode.
This game syncs all of its data
with iCloud
using NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
The main menu allows me to resume the game
I started playing earlier
and to view my fastest solve times
from previous games.
Right now, my high score
is one minute and nine seconds.
If I select "Resume Game,"
you can see the current state
of the game board.
I can flip over tiles
to try to find matching Memoji.
Now my friend Felipe wants to play
and show off his high score.
He opens Control Center
and switches to his user.
But the game stayed the same.
That's not very exciting.
Let's see what we can do about that.
Here I have the Xcode project for my game.
I'm going to show you how easy it is
to add support for multiple users
to your tvOS app or game.
First, you'll navigate
to the Signing and Capabilities editor
of your app target.
Next, you'll add
the User Management capability.
And last, you'll make sure
the Runs as Current User option
is selected.
That's it.
Let's build and run
and switch back to Apple TV.
If I resume my game
or view my high scores,
you can see the same game data
that I showed you earlier.
But now, let's see what happens
when I switch users.
Notice that the game was terminated.
The system switched users,
and the game was relaunched for Felipe.
Now when Felipe plays the game,
he sees his own data.
He doesn't have an in-progress game yet,
so he has an option to start a new game
with no matches.
And notice, his high score of 39 seconds
is faster than mine.
Again, all this data is synced
with iCloud,
and it's kept completely separate
for each user.
And I didn't have to make any code changes
to support this.
We are really excited
for your games and apps
to take full advantage of multiple users
in tvOS 14.
To wrap up, the new
Runs as Current User option
in the User Management capability
allows your apps to easily support
multiple users in tvOS 14.
You can use existing API
to store separate data
for each person using your app
with no code changes required.
This allows you to take full advantage
of multiple users on Apple TV
and provide everyone
with a seamless experience
when they use your app
across all of their devices.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.