Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Gokhan Avkarogullari,
and I lead the graphics acceleration
driver teams for Apple Silicon.
Today,
my colleague Sam and I will tell you
how to bring your Metal-based apps
to Apple Silicon Macs,
and then how to make them faster,
more robust and ready for the future.
For many years,
Apple has designed the graphics processors
found in the amazing A series chips
used in iPhone, iPad and Apple TV.
For the first time, we're bringing our
deep expertise in GPU design to the Mac.
So, let's get started.
The Apple Silicon Mac
contains an Apple-designed GPU
that is designed to handle the workloads
found in desktop games and Pro Apps,
all while delivering new levels of speed
and power efficiency.
This is DiRT Rally from Feral Games.
This was recorded directly
from an Apple Silicon Mac
running the unmodified
x86-compiled binary,
translated using Rosetta.
You can see
all the modern rendering techniques
applied to high-quality game assets.
Complex shading, reflections,
particle effects, motion blur
and lush vegetation
make the game look great.
And, of course, the Apple-designed GPU
makes it run smoothly.
How do we deliver
this level of performance?
We do it using the same powerful
Tile Based Deferred Rendering architecture
used on iPhone, iPad and Apple TV.
If you are familiar with these devices,
then you know that there are several
important advantages to this architecture
that are exposed via the Metal graphics
and compute API.
Capabilities
such as Programmable Blending,
Tile Shaders and Local Image Blocks
are now available
to take your Mac app or game
to a whole new level of performance.
In fact, the GPU in the Apple Silicon Mac
supports a unified Metal feature set
that combines what was previously
available on both macOS and iOS.
And we've done our homework
to make this move as easy as possible.
This enables you to get the benefits
of the faster,
more power-efficient GPU
with more features
without having to retool your app or game.
However, it's really important for you
to follow the guidance in today's talk
to account for certain
behavioral differences
and really unlock
the full potential of the platform.
Before we get into the specifics,
let's take a look
at the path you will take.
On Intel-based Macs,
your app runs natively.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
your app will run out of the box
under Rosetta's
highly optimized translation layer.
Under translation,
your app will be automatically opted
into several Metal consistency features
that ensure your apps look great too.
Translation and consistency features
do have some performance costs,
so your next step will be
to recompile your app
for Apple Silicon's native architecture.
You will then find and fix
any Metal consistency issues.
And if you want optimal performance
on Apple GPUs,
check out the session
by my colleagues Michael and Dom,
"Optimize Metal Performance
for Apple Silicon Macs."
Let's look at today's agenda.
The first section is about adapting
your app for the Apple GPU.
I will start by reviewing
the GPU architecture of Intel-based Macs
and the differences with the Apple GPUs,
and I'll discuss the APIs
supported on the Apple Silicon Mac
and Metal features
you can use in your apps.
Different GPU families
will behave differently
when it comes to undefined behaviors,
programming errors
and performance characteristics.
So in the second section,
we will talk about a few common issues
we observed on some apps
coming form Intel-based Macs.
And finally, Sam will talk
about what we recommend you do
for consistent rendering
using Metal on the Mac.
So let's start with adapting your app
for the Apple GPU.
Let me highlight some of the major changes
from the Intel-based Mac
to Apple Silicon Mac
when it comes to the GPU.
Apple Silicon Mac
contains an Apple-designed GPU,
whereas Intel-based Macs contain GPUs
from Intel, AMD and Nvidia.
Apple GPU is built on the Tile Based
Deferred Renderer architecture,
whereas Intel, AMD and Nvidia GPUs
are known as immediate mode renderers.
I will cover the differences in a minute.
Apple-designed GPU combine
the feature set of iOS and macOS.
Both Mac 2 and Apple GPU family
feature set are supported.
Intel-based Macs
support only Mac 2 family.
Now, let me describe to you
how Tile Based Deferred Renderer
differs from immediate mode renderers.
Let us start
with an immediate mode renderer,
abbreviated here as IMR.
This is a logical view
of the architecture.
From left to right,
the hardware fetches vertex attributes,
executes the vertex shaders
and transforms geometry into screen space
with the help of fixed-function hardware.
Then, the fragment stage
rasterizes the triangles
and performs some early
depth testing for efficiency.
An important note here is that
triangles can span the entire screen,
or two triangles from the same draw call
might end up in widely different places
on the screen,
meaning that the hardware
needs the entire depth buffer
and only can cache a small subset of it.
Early depth test is followed by shading.
When early depth test cannot be done,
the depth testing is done
post-fragment shading.
There's also alpha test and blending,
where access to color buffers
are required.
Just like as it is for the depth buffer,
the color buffer is needed
in its entirety,
and only a small part of it can be cached.
Now that we reviewed IMR architecture,
I will move on
to the Tile Based Deferred Renderer
and highlight the differences
step by step.
The first change is tiling the geometry
in screen space
and creating a database
for all geometry in memory
that I'm going to refer to
as Tiled Vertex Buffer.
Since we have all the geometry information
for an entire tile,
we can rasterize it up front.
As a result, for each pixel in the tile,
we know for which opaque fragment
the shading will have to happen.
We also know which opaque fragments
will fail the depth test.
As a result,
the hidden surfaces are entirely removed.
We don't shade any fragment that
will later be occluded by another one.
We can do this with just
tile size depth buffer on the chip
rather than the entire depth buffer.
It does not matter
if a triangle is full-screen
or in the same draw call triangles
are widely distributed on the screen.
We get perfect testing
with just a tile size on-chip depth buffer
thanks to the Tiled Vertex Buffer.
Additionally, if we are not going to use
that depth buffer later,
we can use memoryless
render target feature
and not store the depth data
and not use memory for the depth buffer.
It's a win-win situation.
Not only that,
we also can do blending and alpha testing
without ever having to load
from the full color buffer in memory.
Because we process an entire tile at once,
we only need a tile's worth
of color buffer on the chip.
Please note that the arrow
for color buffer in memory is one-way.
We never need to access it
for alpha testing,
write mask or blending
or for anything else.
This architecture allows
for alpha test and blending operation
to be performed by the shader core
instead of fixed-function hardware.
It also allows you access to the contents
of the color buffer in your shader,
which you can use
for programmable blending,
custom MSAA resolve, and so on.
Obviously, feedback such as depth writes
between the depth buffer and shading
is covered by this architecture.
To recap,
Tile Based Deferred Renderers
have two main phases:
tiling, where all of the geometry
will be processed,
rendering,
where all the pixels will be processed.
Let us summarize.
On a TBDR GPU, a well-written app
uses a lot less memory bandwidth
than an IMR GPU.
Since processing is done for a full tile,
all blending happens in registers,
so it's really fast and power-efficient.
This is great for games,
Pro Apps and UI performance as well.
No reason to re-fetch color, depth
or stencil buffers over and over again.
As a result, memory bandwidth is saved,
performance increases,
power consumption goes down.
Now that we reviewed the architecture,
we can move on to app's view of the GPU.
With Apple Silicon Mac,
you get what you had before and more.
This new Mac supports everything
the Intel-based Macs support.
All the APIs we and you love,
such as Metal,
MPS, Core Animation, and so on,
are available.
All the other APIs that are also used,
such as OpenGL and OpenCL,
are also available on Apple Silicon Mac.
I will briefly talk about GL and CL first
and then move on to Metal.
OpenGL and OpenCL are still deprecated,
but they are not yet removed.
They are present
for backwards-compatibility purposes
with the library of existing Mac apps
that use these legacy technologies.
OpenGL is supported up to version 4.1
and OpenCL to version 1.1.
For features not in the core,
you should always use extension
or query checks before using them.
Note that Apple-designed GPUs
are engineered for Metal.
If you are still using OpenGL and OpenCL
in your app or game,
you should prioritize moving to Metal
as soon as possible.
Otherwise, you will continue to leave
performance and capability on the table.
Now, on to more exciting things.
Let's talk about those new features
that Apple-designed GPUs bring to the Mac.
Apple Silicon Macs have the feature set
defined by the Metal GPU Family Mac 2.
Additionally, for the first time ever,
the features that are specific
to Apple GPUs are coming to the Mac.
These features provide
tremendous upside for your apps
in terms of better performance,
lower poser consumption
and lower memory usage.
Through the use of the features,
such as Programmable Blending,
Tile Shaders and Local Image Blocks,
you can accelerate deferred, forward,
and all types of tiled rendering.
With memoryless render targets
and on-chip MSAA resolve,
MSAA feature shines on this system.
You can even use MSAA
with deferred rendering
because all the processing is done
on the chip in this architecture
without the cost of additional
memory bandwidth and storage.
There are many other features,
such as ASTC textures,
image block sample coverage control,
and so on
that open up opportunities
for new techniques and optimizations.
Let's recap.
Your app should work fine,
as all APIs are already supported.
Be aware of the underlying
Tile Based Deferred Renderer architecture
and use its best practices.
And don't stop there.
Take advantage of the new features
and the new architecture.
They will improve
your app's performance even more.
Now we are going to look into some issues
that we observed on Metal API misuse
on the Mac on some apps.
We will review what the right usage is.
I will start with Metal feature detection.
After that, Sam will take over
and will talk about a few
app-correctness issues that we observed
and how we can fix those,
such as load and store actions,
position invariance
and Threadgroup Memory synchronization
and sampling previous depth
while forming up new depth values.
Let us start with Metal feature detection.
Previously, we talked about
the unified feature set support.
So how do you go about finding
the availability of these features?
Applications should query
Metal GPU features directly.
Metal organizes features
into different GPU families
that can be queried for a given device.
Some individual feature queries
are also available.
Make use of those for features
that vary within the same GPU family.
One important note.
Querying the GPU name to know
if a particular feature is supported
is not the best practice.
The code is not future-proof.
Let's see an example.
Here is some code
basing feature usage on the OS,
differentiating between
macOS and iOS platforms.
Then, it uses the GPU name
to decide some other information,
such as SIMD group size
and if the device is marked as low-power.
And finally,
it assumes that Apple GPU features
are not available on macOS.
This is not true anymore
with Apple Silicon Mac.
Instead, applications should gather
this information using the Metal API.
The supportsFamily API can be used to know
if Apple GPU features are supported.
The SIMD group size can be found
using the method threadExecutionWidth
on a compute pipeline object.
And to know if a GPU needs to be treated
as integrated or discrete,
use the isLowPower API.
Note that for Apple GPUs,
isLowPower returns "false,"
which means
that you should treat these GPUs
in a similar way as discrete GPUs.
This is because the performance
characteristics of Apple GPUs
are in line with discrete ones,
not the integrated ones.
Despite the property name, though,
Apple GPUs are also way,
way more power-efficient
than both integrated and discrete GPUs.
Now that we reviewed
Metal feature detection,
it's time to review how to correctly use
load and store actions.
Sam will tell you all about it and more.
Sam?
Thanks, Gokhan.
Let's now talk about a common issue
related to Metal load and store actions.
First, a quick recap.
Load and store actions control the action
performed on an attachment,
either color, depth or stencil,
at the start and end of a render pass.
On Apple GPUs, they directly control
the state of the on-chip tile memory.
This memory is initialized
based on load actions
and flushed based on store actions.
An incorrect usage can cause
performance issues
if attachments are unnecessarily
loaded or stored.
Please refer to the video
"Optimize Metal Performance
for Apple Silicon Macs"
to know how to best use
load and store actions.
But in this section,
let's focus on correctness issues.
Here is an example showing
some incorrect usage on the left.
We had rendered the skybox
in an earlier pass,
and then drew the scene in the final pass.
However, we used a DontCare
load action for the final pass,
causing the skybox to not be uploaded
to tile memory,
generating graphics artifacts.
Setting the load action to Load
avoids this issue.
Let's take a look at a diagram
to understand what is happening.
We first start with a previously rendered
texture in system memory.
And if a DontCare load action is chosen,
Apple GPUs will not upload the textures
from system memory to tile memory,
leaving it uninitialized.
The scene will then be drawn
on top of this uninitialized data,
and if the drawing does not cover
the full frame buffer,
uninitialized data will remain,
creating correctness issues.
However, if loadAction load is chosen,
the tile memory is correctly initialized.
In this case, the scene is rendered
on top of the previous content.
Let's now look at store actions.
If a DontCare store action is chosen,
the tile memory
is not being flushed to system memory,
leaving it potentially uninitialized.
This is not the desired behavior
if this texture is consumed
by a later render pass.
However,
if a storeAction store is being used,
the rendering done in tile memory
is populated to system memory.
Let's summarize how to correctly use
load and store actions.
For load actions, make sure to only load
if the previous content
needs to be preserved.
This is the case when a draw
does not cover the full frame buffer
and accumulation is needed
on top of the previous rendering.
If you don't need accumulation,
do not use a loadAction load,
as it costs performance.
Similarly, choose to store
only if the content
will be consumed in the later pass.
Otherwise, make sure to not store
to avoid extra memory traffic.
Let's carry on with an issue
related to position invariance.
The results
of the same vertex position calculation
across different vertex shaders
can be slightly different.
This is because, by default,
the Apple GPU compiler
highly optimizes vertex shaders.
As a consequence, different optimizations
between vertex shaders
might lead to position value differences.
If an application relies on
position invariance without enabling it,
correctness issues might be observed.
So, in Metal, position invariance
is not guaranteed by default.
It has to be explicitly enabled.
This is exactly what is happening
in this image.
Due to position invariance being disabled,
position outputs are slightly different
between two passes,
causing many pixels to be discarded.
Here is the same image with
position invariance correctly enabled.
Let's illustrate this issue
with a diagram.
Let's assume that the first pass
of a multipass algorithm
has rendered some geometry
and stored the depth texture
in system memory for later usage.
Then comes Pass2
that loads this depth texture.
Also note that the tile memory
that is holding color values
is cleared at the beginning
of the render pass.
Pass2 then starts rendering
the same geometry as Pass1,
but this time
with the depth test set to EQUAL.
And due to position invariance
being disabled,
Pass2 generates slightly different
depth values than Pass1.
This causes some pixels
to fail the depth test and be discarded.
For those pixels, the cleared color
is populated to system memory,
causing correctness issues.
Let's now take a look at the code.
Here we have the two vertex shaders
used in the previous diagram,
vertexPass1 and vertexPass2.
As you can see, the position computation
is exactly the same
between the two shaders.
It calls computePosition in both cases.
But there is no guarantee
that it will actually produce
the exact same values for the position.
This is due to the code
around the position computation
that might trigger differences
in compiler optimizations,
affecting the position itself.
How can this be avoided?
First, make sure to pass
the preserveInvariance option
to the Metal compiler
when creating a Metal library.
Note that there is a similar option
if you use the off-line compiler.
And for all the vertex shaders
within this library
that require position invariance,
just add the invariant keyword
on the position output.
Note that you need to set these
two options to ensure position invariance.
And since position invariance comes
at a performance cost,
carefully enable these options
only for shaders that really require it.
We encourage you
to go through your application
and identify vertex shaders
that require position invariance.
This will likely be needed where the
depth-compare function is set to "equal,"
as it will require matching depth values
between different passes.
And to enable position invariance,
make sure to use the preserveInvariance
flag during compilation
and the invariant keyword on the position
output in your vertex shaders.
Now let's take a look
at Threadgroup Memory Synchronization.
This is an area
where you can get great performance
if you have a good understanding
of the underlying hardware architecture.
Let's first refresh the notion
of threadgroups and SIMD groups.
Compute passes launch a set
of individual threads
organized into threadgroups.
The threads within a threadgroup
execute together
and can share a common block
of threadgroup memory.
Access to this memory needs to be properly
synchronized for correct ordering.
Threadgroups are further organized
into SIMD groups
that execute concurrently on the GPU.
However,
the SIMD group size is GPU-specific.
It is 32 on Apple GPUs.
Knowing the SIMD group size can be very
useful to optimize your compute shaders...
particularly if there is
only one SIMD group per threadgroup.
There is no need to synchronize
between SIMD groups.
In order to ensure correct synchronization
on any GPU,
you should query the SIMD group size
through the Metal API at runtime.
And if an application does not use
the correct SIMD group size,
synchronization might be missing,
causing correctness issues.
Let's see an example.
The artifacts in this image
are due to the fact
that the application expects only one
SIMD group in a 64-threadgroup size,
omitting any kind
of threadgroup memory synchronization.
Here is the correct image
with proper synchronization.
Let's dig into the compute shader used
in this application.
This kernel
makes use of threadgroup memory.
It has also been launched
using a threadgroup size of 64.
You can also see
that the threadgroup memory
is first initialized
and read back later in the shader.
Note that there is
cross-thread communication,
as the buffer written from one thread
will be consumed on another thread.
However, nothing in the code
guarantees correct ordering.
Something is missing here.
You probably already guessed
what is missing:
memory synchronization.
Here is what the code looks like
when adding proper synchronization.
First, the application queries
the SIMD group size
using the built-in threads_per_simdgroup.
These can then be used
to inject the correct synchronization.
If there is only one SIMD group
per threadgroup--
in this shader,
it means that simd_size is 64--
then a simple SIMD group barrier
is required to guarantee memory ordering.
However, if there are several SIMD groups,
a full threadgroup barrier is required
to synchronize all the SIMD groups.
And even though extra control flow
is generally not a good practice,
in this particular case,
as simd_size is a constant,
the compiler is able to optimize out
the code path that will not be taken.
This code will ensure
correct synchronization on any GPUs.
For best performance,
you might want to rewrite your shaders
with a 32 SIMD group size in mind
to avoid threadgroup barriers,
as they are expensive.
Applications could have
different sets of shaders
optimized for a given SIMD group size
and would choose at runtime
which variant to use.
With that in mind,
go through your compute shaders
and ensure correct
threadgroup memory synchronization.
GPUs have different SIMD group size,
which will require
different synchronization.
Make sure to query the SIMD group size
either in your shader,
using the built-in threads_per_simdgroup,
or with the Metal API,
using threadExecutionWidth.
And for better performance,
write multiple versions of your shader
optimized for a given SIMD group size.
Let's now explore
a final issue that we observed
related to depth
and stencil texture sampling.
Applications should ensure correct texture
and attachment bindings.
More specifically,
a texture used as an attachment
cannot also be sampled
in the same render pass.
This might create a concurrent read-write
access to the same rendering texture
and trigger correctness issues.
This is exactly what is happening
in this image.
The current depth attachment is also
being sampled in the same render pass.
No artifacts are being observed
if the application avoids
this undefined behavior.
A diagram will help us understand
what is happening.
We first start with a depth texture
in system memory.
Then the first draw comes in
and starts accumulating depth.
Fragment shaders within this draw
execute and sample the depth texture
from system memory.
Then comes a later draw.
Same story here. It will accumulate depth
and sample the depth texture.
One important point in this diagram
is the fact that depth is accumulated
prior to fragment shader execution.
This will be the case for opaque geometry,
where fragment shaders
don't modify the depth.
At this point in the render pass,
all the depth information is finalized.
Apple GPUs will then start flushing
the on-chip depth and stencil memory
back to system memory.
This is where a concurrent read-write
access to the same depth texture
introduces correctness issues.
And note that this race condition can
happen on any draws in your render pass,
not only the last one.
In summary, ensure that your application
does not sample
the current depth and stencil attachments
in the same render pass.
This is undefined behavior on any GPUs.
Also, do not use texture or memory
barriers to work around this issue.
Those are very expensive,
especially on Apple GPUs using
a tile-based default render architecture.
Instead, if your application really
requires sampling the current attachments,
create a second copy for sampling.
Let's now wrap up with what you need to do
in order to get consistent rendering
using Metal.
In our application testing,
we observed three main issues
affecting graphics correctness.
That is why we developed
three Metal work-arounds
that are enabled
for backward compatibility.
These work-arounds are only applied
for applications compiled
with a macOS Catalina SDK or earlier.
The first issue is when applications
are using DontCare load actions
where it should have been a load.
In this case, Metal is remapping
all DontCare load actions
to actual loads
to avoid correctness issues.
The second issue
is related to position invariance.
Some applications rely on
position invariance without enabling it.
Metal is then forcing position invariance
for all vertex shaders.
And finally, if the same depth texture
is both sampled and rendered
in the same render pass,
Metal will snapshot the texture
prior rendering.
Again, these work-arounds are only enabled
for applications compiled
with a macOS Catalina SDK or earlier.
And as you probably suspect,
they also come at a performance cost,
so this is really not what you want.
To help you identify these issues,
we augmented the Metal API
validation layer to catch a few of those,
such as the misuse
of DontCare load and store actions,
as well as sampling the current depth
and stencil attachments.
Here is a recap
of the Metal best practices
to get consistent rendering
across different GPUs.
Go through your application
and make sure
that this is already what you are doing.
And if not,
just follow these simple recommendations.
Regarding Metal GPU feature detection,
make sure that it is API-driven by
querying the Metal GPU features directly.
Carefully choose
your load and store actions
to address both correctness
and performance issues.
Do not unnecessarily load
or store attachments,
as it will increase memory traffic.
Also consider using memoryless attachments
to lower the memory footprint
of your application.
These can typically be used
for depth attachments.
Enable position invariance where required.
Ensure correct threadgroup memory
synchronization
by querying the SIMD group size
and using the appropriate
synchronization primitives.
And finally, avoid sampling
the current depth and stencil attachments
by snapshotting the attachments
prior rendering.
We are very excited
to bring Apple Silicon to the Mac.
This means that your applications
will be more power efficient
and run faster out of the box.
We can't wait to see
how much faster they will run
once you start optimizing
for Apple Silicon.
This will also enable you
to use brand-new features on the Mac
that were not possible before,
such as programmable blending,
tile shaders,
memoryless frame buffers, and more.
And finally, this transition aligns
the technology used on Mac platforms
with existing Apple platforms.
That means that you can easily share
a common code base
across all Apple products.
And this makes it even easier to bring
all your iPad and iPhone applications
to the Mac.
Apple Silicon Macs
brings up new opportunities for you.
At the beginning of this session,
we showed how Games gets
amazing graphics performance
while playing DiRT Rally.
On Apple GPUs,
even the most demanding pro applications
will get great performance.
As an example, I would like to show you
a video of Cinema4D.
This is recorded live
on an Apple Silicon Mac.
Note that it is also running
the original x86 binary
and a Rosetta translation.
In this video, the application
is rendering a high polygon model
in real time
with realistic camera properties
such as user-specified aperture,
f-stop and focal point.
Enjoy how smooth it runs
on Apple Silicon Mac
while rendering
a graphics-demanding scene.
Where does this all fit in the transition
process to Apple Silicon Macs?
At this point,
your application should look great
without Metal work-arounds
running on new macOS SDK.
But your journey should not stop here.
To take your application to the next level
and greatly improve performance,
make sure to check out the session
"Optimize Metal Performance
for Apple Silicon Macs."
Thank you.