Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. My name is Tanu Singhal,
and I'm an engineer on the tvOS team.
Today, we'll talk about
building SwiftUI apps for Apple TV.
We'll introduce new APIs,
we'll discuss best practices,
and we'll go over some examples
that'll help you create experiences
that look and feel familiar to TV users.
First, we'll discuss button styles
and context menus that are new on tvOS 14.
Next, we'll talk about
managing focus in our apps.
And finally, we'll learn to create layouts
that look good
on the largest screen in the home.
There are some button styles
that are unique to TV.
Let's look at an example.
Say we're building an app
for streaming music on Apple TV.
Here's a mock-up that we received
from our design team.
They'd like us to create these buttons
that have a movement effect
when we drag on the Siri Remote,
just like the one you see
under "Albums" here.
To create such buttons in SwiftUI,
we can use the new Card-Button-Style.
A Card-Button creates a platter
that raises and looks highlighted
when it's focused.
It also adds
directional movement to the button
when you drag on the Siri Remote.
To create a Card-Button,
you simply add the button style modifier
to any button,
and set it to Card-Button-Style.
Card-Button-Styles can really
enhance the appearance of your buttons.
However, there might be times
when you don't want
the default highlighting and focus effects
that we offer
with the preexisting button styles.
In such a case,
you can create your own button style.
This adds no existing effects
for pressing and focused states.
And a custom button style
is really easy to configure and customize.
To create your own button style,
you first conform
to the Button-Style protocol...
then in the makeBody method,
you can leverage the configuration
to return any view.
Once the button style is set up,
it can be added to any button
using the button style modifier.
Now we've set up the buttons in our app,
but we've received
another feature request.
When we long-press on an album button,
we want to present some quick actions,
like the ones you see here.
These can be created easily in SwiftUI
using context menus.
Context menus can be added
to any button or view
and they're invoked
after the long-press gesture.
We can add actions to the context menu
using regular buttons.
Here's some code showing
how you can create a context menu.
We simply add the context menu modifier,
and then we can add
some buttons within it.
As you've seen, it's really easy to use
the new button styles and context menus.
We think these will look great
in your apps.
Next, we'll discuss focus.
Focus is the primary way
to interact with a TV app.
And it's incredibly important
to be able to focus on views,
as well as determine if a view is focused.
To learn more about focus, let's look at
another example from our music app.
Here we have the "Now Playing" screen.
We want to focus
on the currently playing song.
And for this focused song,
we would like to display
the name of the artist,
as well as the name of the album,
along with some music emoji.
For the songs that are not focused,
we simply display the name of the artist
without the name of the album.
To implement this, first, we need to
be able to focus on the Song-View.
One way to do this
is by using the focusable modifier.
The focusable modifier creates a focusable
wrapper on top of your existing view.
Note that this modifier is not meant
for intrinsically focusable views.
So, if you have a button or list,
or a UIKit view
that manages focus in UIKit,
then it's best to not have
a focusable modifier on that,
because this modifier will add
another focusable wrapper
on top of your existing view.
To manage the focused
and non-focused state, in tvOS 13,
you would have to use the onFocusChange
callback for the focusable modifier.
However, new in tvOS 14, we're introducing
the isFocused environment variable.
This lets you check
whether or not a view is in focus,
even if the view itself is not focusable.
The isFocused environment variable
will return true
if the nearest focusable ancestor
of your view is focused.
So now, we'll look at the code
for the Song-View that we saw before.
This just has an image
followed by some text labels.
We've refactored the text labels
into a Details-View.
Within the Details-View, we can simply use
the environment variable for isFocused
to check whether or not
this view is focused.
So if the Song-View that's the parent
of the Details-View is focused,
then our isFocused variable
would be true.
We'll use this isFocused variable
to display either the artist
and the album name, along with the emojis,
or simply the artist name
when the view is not focused.
Notice, in our Song-View,
we are using a button
so we don't need to use
the focusable modifier at all,
because the button is focusable already.
Using a button also has the advantage
of giving us
selection and accessibility for free.
We've added the button style
that's our own button style,
because we didn't want
the default highlighting and focus effect
offered by the existing button styles.
Now, at this point,
our app is mostly set up,
and it's ready to start streaming music.
But, we also want to add
a paid version of this app,
so users can listen to premium content.
To create this paid version,
we are first setting up a sign in screen.
This screen simply has
a username and password field
followed by a log in button.
Notice that the username field
is what's focused by default.
tvOS will geometrically compute
the view that should be focused on load.
This is typically the topmost
or leading focusable view on the screen.
In this case, it makes sense
for the username to be focused.
However, there are times when
we already know the username and password,
and we want to focus
on the log in button instead.
To implement this in SwiftUI,
we can use the new default focus APIs.
We're introducing
the prefersDefaultFocus modifier
that allows you to specify the view
that prefers to be focused by default.
Now, we want to make sure
that you don't accidentally change focus
for an entire global view hierarchy
when you're only working
on a small custom view.
To support this, we have created
the focus-Scope modifier,
which allows you to limit default focus
preferences just to a specific view.
We'll look at the code
for the log in screen that we saw.
This is simply a VStack
with a TextField, a Secure-Field
and a button.
Now I'll add some focus management code
to this.
Don't worry about reading
all of it at once.
We'll go over it line by line.
We have a state variable to figure out
if the credentials are filled.
Now, we add the prefersDefaultFocus
modifier to the username TextField,
and the first parameter of this modifier
is a Boolean that should be true
if this view prefers default focus.
In this case, the username prefers default
focus when the credentials are not filled.
We'll also add the same modifier
to the log in button,
but this prefers default focus
when the credentials are filled.
Next, we want to limit
our focus preferences
just to the VStack that we're working on.
To do this, we create a namespace.
The namespace is a dynamic property
that provides us with a unique ID
which can be used to identify any view.
We'll add this namespace
to the focus-Scope modifier
that we've added to our VStack.
Next, we'll pass the same namespace
to the prefersDefaultFocus modifiers
as the second parameter.
By doing this, we have set up
our default focus preferences
in a way
that they apply only to this VStack.
So if focus was meant to be
within the VStack,
then our username or log in button
would be focused
depending on whether or not
the credentials are filled.
However, if focus was supposed to be
somewhere else in the view hierarchy,
then our modifiers
will not impact global focus,
which is what we want.
In addition to setting default focus,
we also need to reset focus sometimes.
This can be done using
the new reset-Focus environment action.
This environment action
resets focus back to default
and, again, the focus updates stay scoped
to the namespace that you provide.
So, in the sign in screen example
that we saw earlier,
let's say we also want to add
a clear button,
which clears the username and password
and resets focus back to the username.
To implement that, we'll use
the reset-Focus environment action.
Then, when the clear button is triggered,
we call reset-Focus for the same namespace
that we had in our focus-Scope.
Since the credentials
have been cleared at this point,
our focus will get reset
back to the username.
In this section, we learned about
the isFocus environment variable,
as well as the new modifiers
and environment actions
that can be used to control default focus.
We think you'll find these really useful
as you create your SwiftUI apps.
Finally, we'll learn to build layouts
that are commonly seen on Apple TV.
Here's a view that we saw earlier
from the music streaming app.
You may have seen similar layouts
across various Apple TV apps.
This is made up of shelves
that scroll horizontally.
To implement this screen,
we can use the new Lazy Grids.
Lazy Grids arrange child views
in a grid container
that scrolls vertically or horizontally.
The grid items can specify properties
such as size, alignment, and spacing,
that help with building the layout.
To learn more about grids, you can
check out the following two sessions:
In this session, though,
we'll learn to leverage a Lazy Grid
to build the layout that we just saw.
In our Shelf-View, we have created
a Scroll-View that scrolls horizontally.
Within the horizontal Scroll-View,
we have added a Lazy-H-Grid.
Now, we can add a lot of items
to this Lazy-H-Grid,
and they won't all get initialized
at once.
They'll get loaded as and when
they're needed, while we scroll.
For the Lazy Grid,
we also set up Grid-Items.
Grid-Items can be a flexible or fixed size
and we can customize
the spacing between Grid-Items.
Within our Lazy Grid,
we simply add the content
that we want to present in our cells.
Now, our shelf is ready,
and we can stack together
multiple shelves in a VStack
along with a few text labels
to create the layout that we saw before.
It's as easy as that to create
beautiful Grid layouts on Apple TV.
So, to recap, we encourage you to try out
the new Card-Button Styles
and context menus on tvOS 14.
They're really easy to use,
and they will look great in your apps.
The new focus APIs can help you
manage focus better in your apps,
and we think you'll find them
really useful.
Finally, we hope
you'll leverage Lazy Grids
to quickly build layouts for tvOS.
We cannot wait to see
what you build next with SwiftUI.
Thank you, and have an amazing WWDC.