Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. Welcome to
"Get the Most Out of Sign in with Apple."
My name is Alfonso,
and together with my colleague, Jonathan,
we're going to talk about best practices
and some of the new features
we have worked this year
for Sign in with Apple.
As you know,
Sign in with Apple makes the experience
of signing into your application
fast and easy.
Users are really loving
how easy it is to use,
as well as the fact that there are
no more passwords for them to remember.
Its privacy features
have been embraced by our users,
with over half of them opting
to use private e-mail relay.
Because of Sign in with Apple,
users are now able to create an account
with your application with a simple tap.
If you haven't already,
be sure to watch last year's WWDC session
"Introducing Sign in with Apple,"
where you will be able to see a live demo
on how you can add this feature
to your application.
Today, we will go over several topics.
We will start by digging deeper
into the authorization request
and how to make it more secure.
After that,
we will talk about best practices
when handling credentialState changes
for your applications.
We will also introduce new
server-to-server developer notifications,
as well as some new additions and changes
to the Sign in with Apple Button.
And finally, we will talk about
upgrading to Sign in with Apple.
As you know,
security is very important for our users,
and it was one of the things we focused on
when creating Sign in with Apple.
When using Sign in with Apple,
you already get great security features
for your accounts,
like automatic two-factor authentication,
but there are also a few things you can do
to make your requests even more secure.
Today, we will review
some of the best practices
for creating your authorization requests,
as well as how to get the most
out of the security features
integrated into them.
This is an example on how to create
an authorization request using Swift.
If you have seen our previous session
or implemented Sign in with Apple before,
this will look very familiar.
This is the method where we will handle
the SignInWithAppleButtonPress
and the right place to create
your authorization request and controller.
As you know, you can modify
the properties of the request
to add things like requestedScopes,
in case your application requires
user information like name or e-mail.
But as we mentioned before,
the request also has some properties
that can help make
the authorization process more secure.
These are nonce and state.
These properties will allow you to verify
that the authorization and credential
you get after executing a request
are the ones you were expecting.
Let's start by talking about
what these properties are.
The nonce is an opaque blob of data
sent as a string in the request.
It is important
to generate one unique nonce
every time you create a new request,
as later on,
you will be able to verify this value.
In order to do that,
the nonce value will be returned to you
embedded in the identityToken property
of the authorization credential.
This will allow you to verify this value
in your server,
helping prevent replay attacks.
Like the nonce, the state value
is also an opaque blob of data
sent with the request.
One key difference
it has with the nonce value
is that the state will be returned
in the credential,
allowing you to locally match
a credential to a request
and verify this was generated
from your application.
Now that we have added these properties,
we're ready to tell the controller
to perform and present our request
to the user.
At this moment, the user will see
the authorization request,
which will look like this.
If you requested
the user's e-mail address,
the user will be presented with the choice
to share or hide their e-mail address.
If the user decides
to hide their e-mail address,
what you will receive
will be a private e-mail relay.
You might have
several questions about this, like,
"What is a private e-mail relay?
How can I verify this e-mail address?
What if I need a reply from a user?"
So let's try to answer
some of these questions.
E-mail relays are just like
a real e-mail address and are team-scoped.
This means
that they will be unique for you
but will always be the same e-mail address
for a user
across all of your applications.
E-mail relays route e-mails
to an e-mail address
verified by Apple
to be real and owned by the user,
so you don't have to worry about
verifying the e-mail address.
You can also be sure
that users will have the ability to reply
to your e-mails if a reply is needed.
There are no downtimes for this service,
so users are able to receive and reply
to your e-mails anytime.
As you can see, this makes the e-mail
relay a great choice for your users
while remaining a convenient communication
method between you and them.
If a user has chosen to use
a private e-mail relay,
be sure to respect their choice.
Once the user makes a selection,
the authorization will proceed.
When an authorization is successful,
you will receive a credential
in the delegate methods
for the authorization controller.
This is an example on how to get
a credential from an authorization.
Inside of this credential,
you will find properties
containing the user information
that you requested, like name and e-mail.
Along with this, you will also find
important properties that will allow you
to securely verify the request
and create a session with your servers.
These are the state,
identityToken and authorizationCode.
As you know, some of these parameters,
like name and e-mail,
will only be included on the credential
the first time a user
authorizes your application.
Because of this, it is important
to cache the objects you need
in case of a failure communicating
with your server due to poor connectivity.
That way, the important information
you need will not be lost.
Make sure you verify
the state value of the credential
to be the same state value
you previously generated.
As I mentioned before,
the response contains
an authorizationCode and an identityToken.
Send these values to your server,
where they can be decoded.
Once decoded,
verify the received information,
as well as the session with Apple servers.
Let's see how the identityToken will look
when decoded by your server.
As you can see, some of the values
you can get from it are:
the subject,
which is the userIdentifier that was
returned to you on the authorization
and will allow you
to create a session in your servers.
The nonce, as we mentioned before,
it's a very important value.
Verify this to be the same nonce
you generated previously in the request.
This will allow you to verify
the authenticity of the authorization
and help mitigate replay attacks.
If you requested
the user's e-mail address,
it will also be included
in the identityToken.
And finally,
the real_user_status will be returned
the first time that a user
authorizes your application.
Includes one of three states:
0 for unsupported, 1 for unknown,
and 2 for likely real.
As we just saw, the identityToken
is a JSON Web Token that contains
several pieces of information
related to the authorization.
Once you have this information,
it's time to verify the token
by using the public key
you can obtain from Apple,
and make sure the token has not expired.
You can exchange the authorizationCode
with the Apple ID servers,
and when this is successful,
you will receive a refresh token
and an access token for future calls,
as well as a new identityToken
that should be identical
to the one you already have.
You may verify a refresh token once a day
to confirm that the user's Apple ID
on that device is still in good standing.
By following these best practices,
you will not only make sure
your users have
a great and smooth sign-in experience,
but you can also be confident
that the authorization,
along with the information
contained in it, is valid and secure.
Now that we have covered
the authorization process,
let's cover
some of the best practices to have
when checking for the credentialState
of your application.
For this,
we use the getCredentialState API.
It allows you to verify
the current state of a credential
by sending
the currently stored userIdentifier.
This API will help you verify
that the user remains signed into
this device and to your application,
helping you make sure everything is okay
for you to continue with your session.
It is important that this method is called
every time your application is launched
or changes to the foreground.
That way, you will be able to react
on time to any changes in status
and present the appropriate screen
in your application to your user.
These are the already known states
you can receive when calling this API.
Let's quickly review those again
and what to do when encountering each one.
Authorized means
you can fast-track the user
directly to your application
and skip the log-in UI.
Revoked means that the user
decided to sign out of your application.
In this scenario, you should
sign the user out of your application,
close your session,
and present the log-in screen.
NotFound will be returned
when there was no credential
matching the userIdentifier.
Present the log-in screen so that the user
can authenticate to your application.
And finally, you will notice
there is a new credentialState...
Transferred.
Let's talk about this credentialState
and how we can handle it.
The Transferred credentialState
will only be received by applications
that recently were transferred
from one development team to another.
For example, after a company is acquired.
As we have mentioned before,
userIdentifiers are unique to a team,
so when transferring ownership
of an application,
the existing users
will need to be migrated
to a new userIdentifier
to match the new team.
This migration is handled silently,
that is, without any user interaction,
and can be triggered
by calling the same API
used to create a new account
or log in a user.
As you can see, this is the same code
for creating a new account
or signing into an existing account.
By adding the currently stored
userIdentifier to the request,
we can validate
the transferred state of the user
and generate the new userIdentifier
that will match the new team.
The response will be returned
in the AuthorizationController
delegate methods,
and the application can continue
to be used
without the user noticing a change.
Now, let's talk about a new feature
we're introducing this year
for Sign in with Apple:
server-to-server developer notifications.
Listening to these notifications
will allow you to monitor
things like credentialState changes
right from your server
as well as receive other types of events.
The process to start receiving
these notifications is simple.
First, you have to register
your server end point
on the Apple Developer's website.
Once you have completed this registration,
you are ready to start receiving events.
Events will be sent as JSON Web Tokens
signed by Apple.
Let's take a look
at how these tokens look like.
As you can see, the JSON Web Token
will contain important information,
like the issuer and the bundle identifier
of the application.
This is an example
of the e-mail-disabled event,
which you can get if a user has decided
to stop receiving e-mails
on their e-mail relay.
The e-mail-enabled event
means that the user opted back in
to receiving e-mail messages.
It is important to note that this event,
as well as e-mail-disabled,
will only be sent when the user
previously decided to use
a private e-mail relay for their account.
The consent-revoked event
will be sent to you
when a user decided to stop using
their Apple ID with your application,
and should be treated
as a sign out by the user.
One example on when you might receive
this notification
is when a user decides to disconnect
your application from Settings.
And finally, account-delete.
This event will be sent when a user
has asked Apple to delete their Apple ID.
When receiving this notification,
the userIdentifier associated
with the user will no longer be valid.
As you can see,
by listening to these notifications,
you will be able to react to these
four different scenarios in a better way
and directly from your servers.
Now, let's talk about another new feature
we're introducing this year:
a Sign in with Apple Button for SwiftUI.
With SwiftUI,
it is really simple to present
the Sign in with Apple Button
in your application,
but not only that, the SwiftUI API
will also help you create
the authorization request
as well as handle the response
within the same block of code.
As you can see,
the button is very simple to create.
On your view, you can just add
a SignInWithAppleButton object
and specify a label for it.
In this case, we have chosen "SignIn,"
but we can also choose "Continue"
or "SignUp."
After that, we have an onRequest closure
where we're able to create our request.
Just like we saw before in Swift,
this is the right place to add
the requested scopes like name and e-mail,
and the nonce and state values
we talked about before.
With the button,
we also have an onCompletion closure
where we will get
the result of the request
and handle the success or failure cases
just as you would on the delegate methods
for the authorization controller.
And finally,
we can also select the button style.
The available styles
for the Sign in with Apple Button
are black, white, and white outline.
And since we're talking
about styles for the button,
if you need to personalize
the Sign in with Apple Button more
to match the specific design
of your website or application,
we're also happy to introduce
a new online portal
where you will be able to do just that.
You can access this website at
appleid.apple.com/signinwithapple/button.
Here, you will be able to customize
many features of the button
like the label, the size,
and the position of the elements.
You will also be able to download
and get the button assets
so that you can import them
to your project or website.
And now, I would like to invite Jonathan
to talk about upgrading
to Sign in with Apple.
Thanks, Alfonso.
Last year, we launched Sign in with Apple,
and customer feedback has been phenomenal.
Users love being able
to sign in to your apps with just one tap.
But what about users
that are already using
a traditional username-
and password-based account
and don't want to fork
their current account?
This year, we're introducing a new API
to help your users upgrade
to using Sign in with Apple.
So why would you want your users
to upgrade their account
to Sign in with Apple?
First, it is secure
for both you and your users.
Upgrading to Sign in with Apple
is the easiest way
to convert your accounts
to two-factor authentication.
Sign in with Apple requires two-factor
and utilizes device trust
for local credentialState.
Account recovery
is also a lot less complicated
with Sign in with Apple.
Users forget their passwords,
and they also need to be verified.
You don't need to manage
your users' secrets
when you use Sign in with Apple.
That's all done for you.
Utilizing this API, you will prevent
the duplication of accounts.
Users love the convenience and security
of Sign in with Apple.
Those users that already have
a traditional username-
and password-based account
won't abandon their current account
to use Sign in with Apple
because now they can just upgrade.
So what is Upgrade to Sign in with Apple?
Upgrade to Sign in with Apple is a new API
designed to be a fast,
easy security upgrade for your users,
and it is available in multiple places
throughout iOS and iPadOS,
including your app.
To help you upgrade your users
to Sign in with Apple,
Authentication Services is utilizing
an extension-based API.
We call this extension
the Account Authentication
Modification Extension.
Using it, you can provide
a seamless experience for your users
to upgrade the way they sign in
to Sign in with Apple.
When a user upgrades to Sign in with Apple
from a weak credential,
that weak credential
gets removed from the system
once the flow is completed successfully.
We've also included support
for adding your own UI
in cases in which
security verification should be completed
prior to asking
for a Sign in with Apple credential.
This same extension supports both upgrades
to Sign in with Apple
and strong password upgrades.
For our session,
I'll be providing an overview
of the new
Upgrade to Sign in with Apple flow.
For all the details
about implementing this new API,
including strong password upgrades,
I invite you to check out
the WWDC 2020 session,
"One-Tap Account Security Upgrades."
Once implemented, there are three ways
your Account Modification Extension
can be invoked by users.
The first is when security recommendations
identifies a weak credential
in the new password manager in Settings.
The second is when a user
is interacting with your app,
utilizes password autofill,
and the selected credential
is a weak credential.
The last is when you invoke
the new Authentication Services API
via a user interaction
that you specify within your app.
Now that we know
where the extension is invoked,
let's take a look at how it works.
There are a few concepts
to the Account Modification Extension.
If you couldn't tell by its name,
let me clarify
that the ASAccountAuthentication
ModificationViewController
is a view controller.
Your subclass of it
will be the NSExtensionPrincipalClass.
The first call to your extension will
invoke a non-user interactive function
that serves as the first attempt
to upgrade the user to Sign in with Apple
with the existing credential.
We hope to see most upgrades occur here,
as it would require
the least work for our users.
Understanding there are cases that will
require additional UI to verify a user,
a step-up security view can be displayed.
We'll then pass the same credential
to the extension
via a separately defined function.
The last element
is the extension context property.
The extension context is used
for communication between your extension
and the extension hosting process
while within the user interactive
and step-up security functions.
Using the extension context,
you'll be able to tell
the extension hosting process
what happened
and what needs to happen next.
Here, you can see a stubbed-out version
of the ExtensionViewController subclass
named AccountModificationViewController.
As you can see,
it is overriding three functions.
The first, convertAccountToSignIn
WithAppleWithoutUserInteraction,
is called initially
by the extension hosting process
in an attempt to upgrade the credential
without user interaction.
The second is viewDidLoad,
which can be used to set up
an intermediary user interface
for the security step-up flow
if necessary.
Providing intermediary UI
to indicate progress
might help provide
the best user experience
if you expect there to be
network calls or delays.
The last, prepareInterface
ToConvertAccountToSignInWithApple,
is called just prior
to your view appearing.
It gets past the same ASPasswordCredential
provided in the non-user interactive flow.
This credential is to be used for actions
such as prefilling a username in a form
or kicking off
a two-factor authentication flow.
Tasks that will take a while
should be done asynchronously,
utilizing intermediary UI
to indicate progress.
Your step-up view is not shown
until this call finishes.
Now that we've completed an overview
of the AccountAuthentication
ModificationViewController,
let's take a closer look
at how it all works together by looking at
the ASAccountAuthentication
ModificationExtensionContext.
The extension context
is the integral property
of the account modification
view controller.
As mentioned earlier,
the extension context is used
to control the flow of the upgrade.
So, how does it control the flow?
First, it has a function to request
Sign in with Apple authorization.
This is similar
to calling perform requests
with an Apple ID credential,
as mentioned earlier by Alfonso.
This will display Sign in with Apple UI
specific to your app.
Then if you're evaluating the credential
or currently signed-in account
and determine that additional UI
is needed to verify the account,
the extension context is used to request
that the Step-Up Security UI is displayed.
The extension context is also used
to tell the hosting process
to complete the flow.
This removes the existing credential.
Last, the extension context
is also used in cases
in which you need to cancel
the flow entirely.
Let's take a closer look at the
extension context property in more detail.
GetSignInWithAppleAuthorizationWithState
displays the Sign in with Apple UI
with your app's information,
asking the user to authorize the upgrade.
Earlier, Alfonso mentioned
setting a state and nonce
on the ASAuthorizationAppleID request.
In upgrade flows, nonce and state
is passed as a parameter to this call.
Once the user authorizes the upgrade,
the completion handler will be called
with the Apple ID credential
after the flow completes.
Next, we have completeUpgrade
ToSignInWithApple.
This lets the extension hosting process
know that the authorization
completed successfully,
resulting in the removal
of the password credential.
Last, we have cancelRequest.
The API expects this to be called
with an ASExtensionError.
If your extension determines
that additional UI
needs to be shown to the user,
it is critical to call this
with the userInteractionRequired error.
If the user cancels
while within your UI flow,
utilize the userCanceled error.
All other failures can use
the failed error.
In our previous slides,
we did a brief overview
of the account modification
view controller.
Then we reviewed
the extension context property
and how it controls the flow.
Now, let's dive deeper
into implementation details
around converting the account without UI.
We begin the flow in the OS
when the user interacts
with a weak credential
and wants to upgrade that credential
to Sign in with Apple.
Your Account Modification Extension
is initialized
by the password managing process,
and the Convert without UI function
is called,
providing the password credential
intended to be upgraded
to Sign in with Apple.
The extension's job
is to evaluate the passed credential
to make sure it is valid
prior to upgrading to Sign in with Apple.
At this point,
checking to see if the username matches
the currently signed-in user
is a good first course of action.
Let's say the extension determined
that the state of the signed-in user
and the passed credential
requires a call to the server
to verify the account.
The server verifies the credential,
and the authentication is a success.
The server then replies back
to the extension
confirming that the account is ready
to be upgraded to Sign in with Apple.
Now that the account is confirmed
as authenticated and eligible for upgrade,
the extension context would be used
to request the Apple ID credential.
But before we jump into
that part of the flow,
let's take a look at what would happen
if there is an issue with the account
preventing an immediate upgrade.
As seen in our previous example,
the flow begins when the user interacts
with a weak credential
and wants to upgrade that credential
to Sign in with Apple.
Your Account Modification Extension
is then initialized
by the password managing process.
Then the Prepare to Convert
Without UI function is called
with the password credential.
The credentials are then verified
by the extension.
Let's take a moment to look at some
sample code for verifying the credentials.
As you can see,
the sample code defines an enum
representing a verification result.
There are three values
that represent the verification result:
success, failure,
and twoFactorAuthRequired.
When the existing credential is verified,
one of these three values
would get returned.
A failure result is for cases
such as when the server attempts
to validate the credential,
but the account or server state
is not appropriate
for converting the account at that time.
For this case,
the extensionContext would be used
to call cancelRequest
with the failed error.
This would end the flow.
Success indicates that the account
is ready to be converted right away,
as shown in our previous sequence diagram.
The extensionContext is then used
to get the Apple ID credential.
TwoFactorAuthRequired means
that we need to show some UI to the user.
The credential alone is not enough
to upgrade to Sign in with Apple.
This case is handled
by using the extensionContext
to call cancelWithError
with the userInteractionRequired error.
Back to our diagram.
The extension calls
the verifyCredential function,
which results in a call
to the extension's back end
to validate the credential.
The server will attempt
to verify the account with the request.
The server determines that this account
needs additional verification.
That reply comes back to the extension,
and the verifyCredential function
evaluates this
as a twoFactorAuthRequired
VerificationResult.
As shown in the sample code
for the verifyCredentials call,
this case is handled
by using the extension context
to call cancelWithError
with the userInteractionRequired error.
We have a recommendation
of requesting UI only if needed
to avoid users having to do extra work.
In most cases where a user
is already authenticated in your app,
we'd expect
that a non-user interactive flow
will be enough to complete the conversion.
However, as seen in this example,
there could be circumstances
where UI flows might be warranted.
Let's take a look at how this would work.
After the extension context canceled
with the userInteractionRequired error,
the password managing process
initializes a new instance
of the account modification
view controller...
and calls
the Prepare to Convert with UI function,
passing the ASPasswordCredential.
At this point, the extension's
view controller is presented
providing intermediary UI,
such as a spinning gear.
Utilizing the same credentials as earlier
with perhaps a slight change of context,
a request is made to the back end.
The server attempts to verify the account,
requires 2FA,
and sends a reply back to the extension.
The extension updates the view,
asking the user
for two-factor authentication.
The user provides the verification code,
which the extension would then verify.
If the user could not be verified
at this point,
the extension context would be used
to cancel the flow with the failed error.
Let's assume
the user provided a valid code
and verification is a success.
The extension is now ready
to request the Apple ID credential.
So now, we're back on the happy path
with an account that is authenticated
and eligible for upgrade.
Now that the account is ready,
let's request the Apple ID credential
and finish the flow.
As mentioned earlier by Alfonso,
it is important to secure your request.
To do so, your extension would generate
a state and nonce
and pass them as parameters
for the getAppleIDCredential call.
This results in
Upgrade to Sign in with Apple UI
being displayed to the user.
The user then authorizes using Face ID.
The Apple ID credential
is provided to the extension
in the completion block
of the getAppleIDCredential call.
The extension would then verify
the credential's state property
as being the same generated earlier.
The extension would then request
an upgrade of the account,
providing the necessary
account information
and the Apple ID credential
to the server back end
so the account can be converted.
The back end would then exchange
the authorization code with Apple servers,
verifying the value of the nonce
in the identityToken,
and if successful,
perform a conversion of the account.
After converting, it sends a reply back
with a success value.
It is important to note again
that if the server's operation failed,
the extension context should be used
to call cancelWithError
with the failed error.
This time,
the server is indicating success,
so the extension would perform
any required bookkeeping
and then call completeUpgradeToSignIn
WithApple on the extension context.
This results in the password manager
removing the existing credential,
and with that, the flow is completed.
The new Authentication Services
Account Modification Extension
is built specifically
to help improve users' security
by offering Sign in with Apple
in place of their weak credentials.
Because we remove the old credential,
users will not be confused
when they sign in to your app next.
Utilizing this API,
you can help your users implement
the best security practices
for their credentials
while avoiding duplicate accounts.
Upgrade to Sign in with Apple
offers a convenient API
for you to upgrade
your users' existing accounts.
We're incredibly excited to see how you
implement Upgrade to Sign in with Apple
and look forward to your feedback.
I hope you all enjoyed our talk today.
Thank you for joining us
and have a great WWDC.