Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, and welcome to ProRes Decoding
with AV Foundation and Video Toolbox.
Our goal today is optimizing the path
from a ProRes movie file,
or really any other video,
into your application.
So, you have an amazing video-editing app
in a really cool Metal rendering engine.
You want to ensure that users
have the best possible experience
working with ProRes content in your app.
Our goal is to make two things happen:
leverage available hardware decoders,
like Afterburner,
and make sure that you have
an optimized and efficient path
for the flow of compressed data,
as well as for the frames
coming out of the decoder.
So, first we're going to do an overview
of some of the concepts
around integrating video into an app.
Then we're gonna discuss
how AV Foundation can do it all for you.
But doing it all at the AV Foundation
level isn't right for everyone,
so next we'll talk a little bit
about how you can fetch or construct
compressed samples
if you choose to drive the decoder
yourself with the Video Toolbox.
Then we'll talk a little bit about
how to use a VTDecompressionSession.
And finally,
we'll cover some best practices
for integrating decoded video frames
with Metal.
All right, let's talk about some basics
for working with video on our platforms.
First, let's talk briefly
about video decoders.
Video decoders do a lot of parsing
of bitstreams
that can come from a wide range of sources
not always fully controlled by users.
This presents opportunities
for malformed media
to destabilize an application,
or even exploit vulnerabilities
and create security issues.
To mitigate these concerns,
the Video Toolbox runs decoders
out-of-process in a sandboxed server.
This both provides security benefits
by running the decoder
in a process with limited privileges,
but it also adds application stability.
If there is a crash in the video decoder,
the result is a decode error
rather than crashing
your entire application.
All right, let's talk about
the media stack on mac OS,
and for this talk,
we're going to be focused on video.
At the top, we have AVKit.
AVKit provides very high-level options
for dropping media functionality
into an app.
Since we want to integrate
with your existing render pipeline,
we aren't going to be looking at AVKit.
AV Foundation provides
a powerful and flexible interface
for working with all aspects of media.
We will be looking at a few interfaces
in the AV Foundation framework.
We have already, and will continue to talk
about Video Toolbox,
which provides a low-level interface for
working with video decoders and encoders.
The Core Media framework
provides many basic building blocks
for any media operations on the platform.
And finally, Core Video provides
basic building blocks
for working specifically with video.
So, we're going to be focusing
on interfaces from these three frameworks:
AV Foundation, Video Toolbox,
and Core Video.
In AV Foundation, we'll take a closer look
at AVAssetReader
as well as AVSampleBufferGenerator.
In Video Toolbox, we'll be looking
more closely at VTDecompressionSession.
And finally, in Core Video,
we'll be looking at integrating
CVPixelBuffers
and CVPixelBufferPools with Metal.
Let's talk a little bit
about some considerations
when working
at these different API levels.
First, in current versions of the OS,
all media interfaces will automatically
enable hardware decode when available.
This includes enabling Afterburner.
We'll talk later about how to selectively
enable and disable hardware decode,
but by default, it will always be used.
Earlier, we talked about how
video decoders run in a separate process.
If CMSampleBuffers
are created by AV Foundation,
they are automatically generated in a form
which optimizes them for transfer
over the RPC boundary.
When working with
VTDecompressionSession directly,
whether or not you get this optimized RPC
depends on how
the CMSampleBuffers are generated.
We'll talk more about this later on
as we talk about generating
CMSampleBuffers.
Next, I want to dive into
a little glossary.
First, let's talk about CVPixelBuffers.
CVPixelBuffers are essentially wrappers
around blocks of uncompressed
raster image data.
They have inherent properties
like pixel format, height, width,
and row bytes or pitch,
but they can also carry attachments
which describe the image data,
things like color tags.
Next we have CMBlockBuffer.
This type is defined
in the Core Media framework
and serves as a basic type
for wrapping arbitrary blocks of data,
usually compressed sample data.
Then we have CMSampleBuffers.
CMSampleBuffers
come in three main flavors.
First, a CMSampleBuffer
can wrap a CMBlockBuffer
containing compressed audio or video data.
Second, a CMSampleBuffer
can wrap a CVPixelBuffer
containing uncompressed raster image data.
As you can see,
both types of CMSampleBuffers
contain CMTime values
which describe the sample's presentation
and decode timestamps.
They also contain a CMFormatDescription
which carries information describing
the format of the data
in the SampleBuffer.
CMSampleBuffers
can also carry attachments,
and this brings us to the third type
of CMSampleBuffer,
a marker CMSampleBuffer which has
no CMBlockBuffer or CVPixelBuffer
and exists entirely
to carry timed attachments
through a media pipeline
signaling specific conditions.
Next we have IOSurface.
An IOSurface is a very clever abstraction
around a piece of memory,
often used for image data.
We talked about the raster data
in a CVPixelBuffer.
That raster data is usually
in the form of an IOSurface.
IOSurfaces can also be used
as the basis for the memory
for a texture in Metal as well.
IOSurface allows the memory
to be efficiently moved between frameworks
like Core Video and Metal,
between processes
like the sandboxed decoder
and your application,
or even between different memory regions,
such as transfer between VRAM
in different GPUs.
And our final stop in our glossary
is the CVPixelBufferPool.
CVPixelBufferPools
are objects from Core Video
which allow video pipelines to efficiently
recycle buffers used for image data.
In most cases,
CVPixelBuffers will wrap IOSurfaces.
When a CVPixelBuffer
allocated from a pool is released
and no longer in use,
the IOSurface will go back
into the CVPixelBufferPool
so that the next CVPixelBuffer
allocated from the pool
can reuse that memory.
This means that CVPixelBufferPools
have some fixed characteristics,
just like CVPixelBuffers:
the pixel format, height, width,
and row bytes or pitch.
All right, let's get straight into
how AV Foundation can do it all for you.
Let's go back to our original problem.
You have a ProRes movie file,
you have your awesome
Metal rendering engine,
and you want to get frames from that movie
into your renderer.
AVAssetReader can do it all for you.
It reads samples from the source file,
optimizing them for the RPC
that will happen in the Video Toolbox.
It decodes the video data
in the sandbox process,
and it provides
the decoded CVPixelBuffers
in the requested output format.
Creating an AVAssetReader
is pretty easy.
First we create an AVAsset
with a URL to a local movie.
Then we create an AVAssetReader
with that AVAsset,
but the AVAssetReader
isn't ready to use yet.
Requesting decoded data
from the AVAssetReader
involves configuring
an AVAssetReaderTrackOutput.
First we need to get the video track.
Here we're getting an array
of all of the video tracks in the movie,
and then selecting the first track
in that array.
Your logic for selecting tracks may vary.
Now we create
an AVAssetReaderTrackOutput
based on the video track we selected.
In this case,
I'm choosing to configure the output
to return 16-bit 4:4:4:4 YCbCr with alpha,
or Y416,
which is a great native format to use
when working with ProRes 4444 content.
Next, we're going to instruct
the AVAssetReaderTrackOutput
to not copy samples when returning them.
When setting this,
we will get optimal efficiency,
but it also indicates
that the returned CMSampleBuffers
may be retained elsewhere,
and we absolutely must not modify them.
And finally, we need to add this output
to our AVAssetReader.
Running an AVAssetReader
is pretty simple.
I'll show you it operating
in its simplest possible mode here.
First, we just start it reading.
Then we can loop over calls
to copyNextSampleBuffer,
and since we've configured it
to provide decoded output,
we check each output CMSampleBuffer
for a CVImageBuffer.
We will get some marker CMSampleBuffers
with no image buffers, but this is okay.
Using an AVAssetReader,
you can set time ranges
or do other more advanced operations
rather than this simple iteration
through the track.
Your video pipeline will be most efficient
if your renderer
is able to consume buffers
in a format that is native to the decoder.
AVAssetReader
will convert the decoder output
from the decoder's native format
to your requested output format
if you are requesting a format
that the decoder does not support.
But avoiding these buffer copies
will improve
your application efficiency immensely.
Here are some guidelines
on choosing an output pixel format
that will not result in a conversion.
In the previous example,
we configured the AVAssetReaderOutput
to return buffers in 16-bit 4:4:4:4 YCbCr
with alpha,
or Y416,
which is the optimal format
when using ProRes 4444.
For ProRes 422, 16-bit 4:2:2 YCbCr,
or v216,
is the most native decoder format
to request.
For ProRes RAW, RGBA half-float, or RGhA,
provides the most native output.
Sometimes there's reasons
why one doesn't want to rely
on AVAssetReader to do everything.
In these cases, you'll need to generate
CMSampleBuffers
to feed directly to the Video Toolbox.
There are three main options here.
First, you can use AVAssetReader,
much like we described a moment ago,
but you can request that it give you
the compressed data
without decoding it first.
This provides track-level media access,
with awareness of edits
and frame dependencies.
Second, there is
AVSampleBufferGenerator.
This provides media-level access
to samples,
with no awareness of edits
and frame dependencies.
And finally, you can construct
CMSampleBuffers yourself.
Letting AVAssetReader
generate your samples
provides compressed data
read directly from the AVAsset.
AVAssetReader
is doing track-level reading,
which means it will provide
all samples necessary
to display frames at the target time,
including handling edits
and frame dependencies.
Also, as noted earlier,
AVAssetReader will provide samples
which are optimized for RPC,
reducing sandbox overhead when the frames
are sent to the Video Toolbox.
In order to get raw compressed output
from the AVAssetReader,
you simply need to construct
the AVAssetReader as described earlier,
but when creating
the AVAssetReaderTrackOutput,
you'll set the outputSettings to nil
rather than providing a dictionary
specifying a pixel format.
AVSampleBufferGenerator provides
samples read directly from the media
in an AVAssetTrack.
It uses an AVSampleBufferCursor
to control the position in the track
from which it will read media.
It has no inherent awareness
of frame dependencies,
so this may be straightforward
to use with ProRes,
but care must be taken
when using this interface
with content
with inter-frame dependencies,
like HEVC and H.264.
Here's a brief code snippet showing how
an AVSampleBufferGenerator is created.
First you need to create
an AVSampleCursor
which will be used
for stepping through samples.
You must also create
an AVSampleBufferRequest
which describes the actual sample requests
you will be making.
Now you can create
the AVSampleBufferGenerator
with your source AVAsset.
Note that I'm setting
the timebase to nil here,
which will result
in synchronous operation.
For optimal performance
with AVSampleBufferGenerator,
you would provide a timebase
and run your requests asynchronously.
Finally, I'm looping over calls
to createSampleBufferForRequest
and stepping the cursor forward
one frame at a time.
Again, this shows the simplest possible
synchronous operation.
For optimal performance, one would use
async versions of these requests.
Finally, you can create
CMSampleBuffers yourself
if you're doing your own file reading
or getting sample data
from some other source, like the network.
It's important to note
that this sample data
will not be optimized for transfer
over the sandbox RPC.
Earlier, we talked about the components
of a CMSampleBuffer.
Once again,
there's the data in a CMBlockBuffer,
a CMFormatDescription,
and some timestamps.
So, first you need to pack
your sample data
in a CMBlockBuffer.
Then you need to create
a CMVideoFormatDescription
describing the data.
Here it would be important to include
the color tags
in your extensionsDictionary
to ensure proper color management
for your video.
Next you would create some timestamps
in a CMSampleTimingInfo struct.
And finally, create a CMSampleBuffer
using the CMBlockBuffer,
the CMVideoFormatDescription
and the CMSampleTimingInfo.
Okay, you've decided to do it yourself
and you've created a source
for CMSampleBuffers.
On to the Video Toolbox.
Let's take a look at the anatomy
of a VTDecompressionSession.
The VTDecompressionSession,
of course, has a video decoder,
and as described earlier,
this will be running
in a separate sandboxed process.
The session also has
a CVPixelBufferPool
which is being used to create
the output buffers
for decoded video frames.
And finally, if you have requested output
in a format which doesn't match
what the decoder can provide,
there will be a VTPixelTransferSession
to do the required conversion.
Before you get started,
if your application needs to access
the set of specialized decoders
distributed for Pro video workflows,
your application can make a call
to VTRegisterProfessional-
VideoWorkflowVideoDecoders.
This only needs to happen once
in your application.
The steps to use
a VTDecompressionSession
are pretty simple.
First, create a VTDecompressionSession.
Second, do any necessary configuration
of the VTDecompressionSession
via VTSessionSetProperty calls.
This isn't always needed.
Finally, begin sending frames using calls
to VTDecompressionSession-
DecodeFrameWithOutputHandler,
or simply
VTDecompressionSessionDecodeFrame.
For optimal performance, it's recommended
that asynchronous decode be enabled
in your DecodeFrame calls.
Let's look more closely at creating
a VTDecompressionSession.
There are three major options
that need to be specified.
First is the videoFormatDescription.
This tells the VTDecompressionSession
what codec will be used,
and provides more details
about the format of the data
in the CMSampleBuffers.
This should match
the CMVideoFormatDescription
of the CMSampleBuffers
that you are about to send to the session.
Next is
the destinationImageBufferAttributes.
This describes
your output pixelBuffer requirements.
This can include dimensions
if you want the Video Toolbox
to scale output to a certain size.
It can contain a specific pixelFormat
if your rendering engine requires it.
If you only know
how to consume 8-bit RGB samples,
this is where you would request that.
This can also be a high-level directive,
like a request to just provide
Core Animation-compatible output.
Next is the videoDecoderSpecification,
which provides hints
about factors for decoder selection.
This is where you specify
non-default hardware decoder requests.
Speaking of hardware decoder usage,
as mentioned earlier,
on current OS versions,
hardware decoder usage
is enabled by default
for all formats where it's supported.
This is a slight change from
a few years ago when it was an opt-in.
In current OSes,
all hardware-accelerated codecs
are available by default
with no opt-ins required.
If you want to guarantee
that your VTDecompressionSession
is created with a hardware decoder,
and want session creation to fail
if it isn't possible,
you can pass in
the RequireHardwareAcceleratedVideoDecoder
specification option set to true.
Similarly, if you want to disable
hardware decode
and use a software decoder,
you can include
EnableHardwareAcceleratedVideoDecoder
specification option set to false.
These two keys are awfully similar,
so once more,
the first key is
RequireHardwareAcceleratedVideoDecoder
and the second is
EnableHardwareAcceleratedVideoDecoder.
This sample shows the basics
of VTDecompressionSession creation.
The first thing that we need
is a formatDescription
to tell the session
what type of data to expect.
We pull this straight from
a CMSampleBuffer
that will be passed to the session later.
If we want a specific pixelFormat
for our output,
we need to create
a pixelBufferAttributes dictionary
describing what we need.
So, just like in the earlier
AVAssetReader example,
we're requesting 16-bit 4:4:4:4 YCbCr
with alpha.
Now we can create
the VTDecompressionSession.
Note that we're passing in NULL
for the third parameter,
the videoDecoderSpecification.
This NULL means that the Video Toolbox
will do its default
hardware decoder selection.
Once the VTDecompressionSession
is created,
the calls to DecodeFrame
are fairly straightforward.
As mentioned earlier,
for optimal performance,
the kVTDecodeFrame_Enable-
AsynchronousDecompression flag
should be set in the decodeFlags.
The block-based VTDecompressionSession-
DecodeFrameWithOutputHandler
takes the compressed sampleBuffer,
the inFlags,
which control decoder behavior,
and an output block which will be called
with the results of the decode operation.
As long as the VTDecompressionSession-
DecodeFrameWithOutputHandler call
doesn't return an error,
your output block will be called
with the results of the frame decode,
either a CVImageBuffer
or a decoder error.
A quick note about decompression output.
Decoder output is serialized.
You should only see a single frame
being returned from the decoder at a time.
If you block inside of the decoder output,
it will effectively block
subsequent frame output
and ultimately cause back pressure
through the decoder.
For best performance, you should make sure
that processing and work is done
outside of your session's output block
or callback.
Now let's talk a little bit about using
decoded CVPixelBuffers with Metal.
Before diving into this,
it's important to review
exactly how a CVPixelBufferPool works.
As described before,
when a CVPixelBuffer which was allocated
from a CVPixelBufferPool is released,
its IOSurface goes back
into the CVPixelBufferPool,
and the next time a CVPixelBuffer
is allocated from the pool,
the IOSurface will be recycled
and used for the new CVPixelBuffer.
With this in mind,
it's easier to understand
the pitfalls that one can encounter
working with CVPixelBuffers and Metal.
We need to ensure
that IOSurfaces are not recycled
while still being used by Metal.
There are two main approaches
to using CVPixelBuffers with Metal.
One is the obvious bridge
through IOSurface.
The CVPixelBuffer contains an IOSurface
and Metal knows how to use
an IOSurface for texturing.
But this path requires
a bit of extra care.
The second path is through
Core Video's CVMetalTextureCache.
This is less obvious, but generally
simpler to use in a safe manner,
and can provide some performance benefits.
Using the IOSurface backing
from a CVPixelBuffer
directly with Metal
appears straightforward,
but there's a trick to ensuring
that the IOSurface is not recycled
by the CVPixelBufferPool
while it's still in use by Metal.
To go this route, you first need to get
the IOSurface from the CVPixelBuffer,
and you can then create a Metal texture
with that IOSurface.
But you need to ensure that the IOSurface
is not recycled
by the CVPixelBufferPool
while it's still in use by Metal.
So, we use
the IOSurfaceIncrementUseCount call.
To release the IOSurface
back into the pool
when Metal has finished with it,
we set up a MTLCommandBuffer
completion handler
to run after our CommandBuffer completes,
and we decrement
the IOSurfaceUseCount here.
Using CVMetalTextureCache
to manage the interface
between CVPixelBuffer and MetalTexture
simplifies things,
removing the need to manually track
IOSurfaces and IOSurfaceUseCounts.
To use this facility, you need to first
create a CVMetalTextureCache.
You can specify the Metal device
you want to associate with here.
Now you can call
CVMetalTextureCacheCreateTextureFromImage
to create a CVMetalTexture object
associated with your CVPixelBuffer.
And getting the actual Metal texture
from the CVMetalTextureCache
is a simple call
to CVMetalTextureGetTexture.
And the last thing to keep in mind here
is that once again,
you must set up a handler
on your Metal command buffer completion,
or otherwise ensure
that Metal is done with the texture
before you release the CVMetalTexture.
CVMetalTextureCache also saves you from
repeating the IOSurface texture binding
when IOSurfaces
which come from a CVPixelBufferPool
are reused and are seen again,
making it a little bit more efficient.
Okay, so we covered a few topics here.
We talked about when you will get
hardware decode, and how to control it.
We talked about how
AV Foundation's AVAssetReader
can simply and easily allow you
to integrate accelerated video decoding
with your custom rendering pipeline.
We talked about how to construct
CMSampleBuffers
and use them with the Video Toolbox
if using AVAssetReader on its own
isn't a good fit for your use case.
And finally,
we talked about some best practices
around using CVPixelBuffers with Metal.
I hope that what we've discussed today
helps you make your amazing video app
a little bit more amazing.
Thanks for watching and have a great WWDC.