Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome back to Swan's Quest.
I'm Rob, your host,
as we go inside
the final chapter of our quest.
We hope you had a fun time so far.
For this last chapter,
we're going to move away from ToneOutputs
and talk about sampled instruments.
In the final chapter,
you meet with the Lizard one last time.
The chest from the Swan is a mystery,
and I don't want to spoil it.
Let's just say that sequencers
are going to play
a key role in solving this challenge.
We're gonna start
with an introduction to sequencers
and some tips
for constructing one in Swift.
Stephen's gonna return
to discuss the content SDK's API
for playing sampled instrument,
and a brief overview of the library
of instruments provided within the SDK.
He's also going to tell you
how we sampled them in GarageBand.
Finally, we'll wrap up
with a final side quest
for those who don't want the fun to end.
Let's talk about step sequencers.
At the end of the third challenge,
the Swan gave us a scroll
with two-part harmony.
Great one, Swan.
Unlike our previous challenge,
this will require multiple instruments
playing at the same time.
To play multiple parts at once,
we're going to show you
how to build a step sequencer.
Believe it or not,
you only need a single timer
for this sequencer.
And instead of a ToneOutput,
we're going to take advantage
of the sampled instruments
included in our content SDK.
A sequencer is a multi-track timing loop.
It is divided into equal chunks, or steps,
which play in sequence
over a predefined duration.
Each track represents an instance
of a pitched instrument.
Sequencers are also used with
non-pitched instruments like percussion.
Sequencers are very versatile.
They're great for creating
atmospheric background loops
or drum beats
which can sit underneath a melody.
Step sequencers allow one to layer
multiple tracks on top of another.
In the example shown here,
there is a horn track, a guitar track,
and a percussion track.
Each column in this sequence
is a quarter note in length.
What you see are eight beats,
or two bars of 4/4,
or, as we call it in the music biz,
common time.
Here's an example
of a sequencer's timing loop.
The timer's interval is determined
by dividing the total duration,
four seconds,
by the total number of beats,
eight, in the sequence.
We need add our tracks and code
to play the instruments
inside of each track.
Let's check in with Stephen.
Thanks, Rob. We include a rich API
and instrument library
with our content SDK.
We first introduced the Instruments API
in Sensor Arcade,
and included a template
called Sensor Create,
so you could write your own music.
Then, last year,
we released Sonic Workshop
and its companion starting point:
Sonic Create.
These both included seven instruments,
and samples for three octaves of notes.
The fundamental API
is the playInstrument method.
This API requires a reference
to one of the seven instruments
included in Playgrounds content SDK:
electric guitar, bass guitar, piano,
warm bells, seven synth, bass synth,
and the crystal synth.
The second item required
by the playInstrument method
is a MIDINoteProtocol value.
These MIDI notes include an 8-bit integer
which corresponds
to the appropriate MIDI code.
Here's an example implementation with
the second octave of encoded MIDI notes.
Note: we include a value, "rest".
This allows us to represent silent gaps
for instruments in the sequence.
Before we update our code,
we need to discuss tracks.
We've included another protocol for you
in Sequencer.Swift: the TrackProtocol.
This includes an instrument value,
the length of the track,
and a method which provides the MIDI note
for a given step in the sequence.
An example implementation
might look like this.
Remember to check
for the existence of the notes property,
and ensure the indexed step does not
exceed the boundaries of the sequence.
With all of the pieces now in place,
we can revisit our bare-bones example.
First we create our two tracks:
bass and piano,
and combine them into an array.
Once those are created, we need to assign
note patterns to each track.
Finally, we loop through
the selected tracks
and play the notes
for the assigned instrument.
Don't forget to call
the endPerformance method
after the first time
through your sequence,
so you get credit for your solution.
Let's update the code
that recycles the index
after we've completed
a loop of the sequence.
After we reset the index back to zero,
we can call endPerformance
and the Swan will know
we've finished their challenge.
Next, I'd like to talk about
sampling in GarageBand.
One way to create your own instruments
is to take your own samples
from GarageBand.
First, open GarageBand
and select Keyboard,
or another instrument
you're interested in sampling.
Within Keyboard,
there are many instrument options.
I've chosen the koto,
a traditional Japanese instrument.
You'll also notice that you can change
many other properties of the instrument,
such as the tone and the resonance.
You can also select
which scale the Keyboard uses.
This makes playing your desired notes
even easier.
Here, I'll select the major scale.
[timer button clicks]
[piano notes play]
Once you've recorded
your individual notes,
play them to make sure
they sound exactly as you want them to.
[paino notes play]
If you want, you can make modifications
within the GarageBand Editor
before you export.
Once you're all set, export your song.
The most lossless format
is an uncompressed WAV,
but you can also export
in compressed formats.
Once you've exported,
trim the individual notes
and import them into your project
to create your instrument.
Rob, we should do a really cool side quest
for our final one.
I agree, Stephen.
Is everyone ready?
Are you ready?
No spoilers this time.
For this final side quest,
we want you to combine
everything you've done
across the four chapters:
Add the ToneOutput as an instrument
for your step sequencer.
During this episode, we gave you tips
for completing the final challenge
in Swan's Quest.
You learned about step sequencers
and how they could be used
to create multipart harmony.
We introduced you
to the pre-sampled instruments
included in Swift Playgrounds,
and then gave you instructions
for sampling and creating
your own instruments.
We hope you've enjoyed Swan's Quest,
and learned more about Swift Playgrounds
and everything you can accomplish
with our embedded content SDK.
If you need a refresher,
or just want to
play through the fun again,
be sure to check our earlier episodes.
Good luck, have fun,
and join us in the forums to share
your solutions for the side quests.
We'd love to hear how you did.