Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, and welcome.
My name is Jad Osseiran,
and I'm a software engineer on tvOS.
In this session,
we'll begin with a high-level overview
of tvOS Picture in Picture.
We will then cover what it takes
to implement Picture in Picture
in your applications,
and I will then hand it off to Dan,
who will talk about how you can make
your existing applications
work great with Picture in Picture.
Finally, Dan will run us through a demo
that covers what we've learned
in this session.
Okay. So let's get started and have a look
at an overview of tvOS Picture in Picture,
or, more succinctly, PiP.
Here, we have an application
with two videos in its browse view.
Let's see how we can put these videos
in Picture in Picture,
and even swap between them.
First, let's bring a video full screen.
By bringing up the playback UI,
we can select the "start PiP" button,
bringing this video
into Picture in Picture.
Unique to tvOS,
we can start the other video
and have them play simultaneously
side by side.
At any time,
the playback UI can be brought up
to swap the full-screen video
with the content in the PiP.
If we now go back to our browse view...
we can see that the video in PiP
is the second video that we played.
We have effectively PiP-ed both videos
and swapped them.
So we have seen that tvOS PiP
brings a familiar experience from iPadOS
and augments it
by adding simultaneous video playback.
So how can your application
take advantage of this?
To find out, let's dive into how you can
implement Picture in Picture in tvOS.
The first step is to set up
your Xcode project.
Before you write any code,
you will need to add
the Picture in Picture capability
to your application in Xcode 12.
To do so, you select Background Modes
in the Add Capabilities window.
It is then as easy as checking
the Picture in Picture box
in the Signing and Capabilities tab
of your project.
Next up, you will need to configure
your audio session
by setting your application's
AV-Audio-Category to "playback."
Here is what this code might look like
in your application.
And that's it for project setup.
If you have previously implemented PiP
on iPadOS,
these steps should be very familiar
to you,
as they are the same across our platforms.
The second step in implementing tvOS PiP
is adapting your playback UI.
So let's see what that entails
for the standard playback UI.
Our standard playback UI,
or AV-Player-View-Controller,
will display the right UI affordances
for PiP.
This happens automatically
if you've configured your project
following the setup steps
we've just discussed.
To help you respond
to the PiP's life cycle,
your application will make use
of AV-Player-View-Controller's
delegate methods,
which are now in tvOS.
If this API is new to you,
or you would benefit
from a quick refresher,
here are some of the delegate methods
we will be seeing again in this session.
These methods cover the life cycle
for starting PiP,
stopping PiP,
and restoring PiP.
Now I'd like to call out the restore.
In this method, your application is given
the opportunity to restore its UI
so that it can accommodate the player
coming out of Picture in Picture.
When implementing this method,
keep in mind
that a fast restoration is ideal,
and that avoiding animations
is a great way to ensure the restoration
is quick for your user.
If your application takes too long,
the restoring player will be terminated,
leading to a poor user experience.
Getting started with a standard playback
UI is straightforward and very familiar
with the existing iPadOS implementation.
Later in this talk,
Dan will go into further details
on how you can get the most out of PiP
with AV-Player-View-Controller.
However, we recognize that some
of your applications
require a custom playback UI.
If this is true of your application,
then your second step
in implementing tvOS PiP
will be different
than what we've just covered.
So let's explore that now.
AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller
is now available on tvOS.
And just like on iPadOS and iOS,
your application will use it
to control the PiP.
AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller
now has a new tvOS API
to help you manage your custom UI.
So let's have a look at that API.
Your app will use
can-Stop-Picture-In-Picture
to help you display
the appropriate affordances
and provide the correct behavior
in your custom playback UI.
So let's dig into this a little more.
If can-Stop-Picture-In-Picture is false
for your full-screen player,
it indicates to your application
that your custom playback UI
should display a start-PiP affordance.
When your users select
the start PiP affordance,
your app should call
start-Picture-In-Picture
under managing
AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller
to programmatically start PiP.
Conversely,
when can-Stop-Picture-In-Picture is true,
your application should display
UI affordances
for swap and stop
in your custom playback UI.
It is worth noting that there is
no special call to initiate a swap.
Your application should call
start-Picture-In-Picture
when starting a swap,
and the system will take care of the rest.
If we think about this from the point
of view of the full-screen player,
it is starting PiP in both a simple start
and a swap case,
making start-Picture-In-Picture
the appropriate method in both scenarios.
To stop an existing PiP
from your full-screen player,
your application should call
stop-Picture-In-Picture
on the AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller
managing that full-screen player.
It is important that your app
only call stop-Picture-In-Picture
when the user has selected
your stop affordance.
Can-Stop-Picture-In-Picture
can change at any time.
For example, a user might stop the PiP
from the PiP window itself.
As such,
your UI must always be up to date.
To do so,
your application will need to observe
can-Stop-Picture-In-Picture for changes
and update your UI accordingly.
Here's a sample
of how that might look in your code.
We strongly encourage you to read
the latest Human Interface Guidelines,
which goes into detail about
how to best display these affordances.
Next up, let's talk about how tvOS 14
allows publishing to multiple
Now Playing info centers.
When two videos
are playing simultaneously,
their respective Now Playing information
should also be updated.
You can do this by tying AV-Players
to an MP-Now-Playing-Session.
Your application can have multiple
MP-Now-Playing-Sessions,
and in the case of PiP,
you would have a Now Playing session
for your PiP content
as well as one
for your full-screen content.
In fact, in order to use PiP on tvOS,
the same player used
in AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller
must be tied to an MP-Now-Playing-Session.
So let's have a look
at what that means in code.
Here is a snippet of what a custom
playback UI controller might look like.
We see that the player used to create
the AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller
is also used
in the MP-Now-Playing-Session initializer.
Later on, and when appropriate,
you can set the session's Now Playing
info center and make it active.
This tells MediaPlayer to start publishing
this information on your behalf.
Before we move on,
there are a couple of things to note
when using MP-Now-Playing-Session.
The first thing to note
is that updating to MP-Now-Playing-Session
will make the system ignore updates from
the default MP-Now-Playing-Info-Center.
As such, you should make sure
that when you implement PiP,
you switch over to MP-Now-Playing-Session
across your whole application.
Because there are now
multiple Now Playing info centers,
the system will decide which information
to display in the Now Playing system UI.
It is important, however,
to keep publishing
Now Playing information,
even if your session
is not currently shown in the system UI.
Your app will want to do this,
as the system may choose
to display your session at any moment.
So far, we have covered setup
and the two different ways you can
integrate your playback UI with PiP.
The last thing we want to cover
on implementing tvOS PiP
is the life cycle your application
should expect when performing a swap.
The first scenario is swapping
within your own application.
If we imagine that these videos come
from your application,
let's look at the lifecycle between
your sports PiP content
and your full-screen animated movie.
Here's a snippet of what
a player delegate object would look like.
First, your application will see
the will-Start delegate callback
for the player that is going into PiP.
Next, your stopping player will ask
your application to restore a UI
to accommodate it coming out of PiP.
Remember,
restoring quickly is essential here.
Once you have restored your UI,
you will get a will-Stop callback
for the stopping player.
And finally, your players will get
their respective did-Start
and did-Stop delegate callbacks
once the swap has completed.
The second scenario we will cover
is swapping across applications.
Here, your application
can either start Picture in Picture,
swapping with another application's PiP,
or your application can be the one
that is bringing its Picture in Picture
full-screen.
So let's first cover the case
of your application starting PiP.
Let's now imagine that your application is
providing the full-screen animated movie.
In this scenario, the PiP sports content
is provided by another application.
Now when we swap,
your content is going into PiP.
So taking our player delegate from before,
let's focus on the delegate callbacks
of interest.
You will get a will-Start callback
and as you might expect, a matching
did-Start once the animation is complete.
Your application
will then get backgrounded.
This is because as part of the swap,
another application
became the foreground app
to play their full-screen content.
If you have implemented Picture in Picture
in iPadOS,
this may look familiar to you.
It is the same sequence you would see
when your application
is automatically put into PiP
when the user returns to the home screen.
Lastly, let's cover the cross-app case,
where your application brings its PiP
full-screen.
For this last example,
let's imagine that your application
now owns the content in the PiP,
and that another application
is playing full-screen.
During a swap, your PiP content
will take over the full screen.
So let's again follow this
in our play delegate example.
First your application is brought
to the foreground.
Then you will get the opportunity
to quickly restore your UI.
It is then told that Picture in Picture
will stop.
And finally,
once the animation is complete,
you will be told that Picture in Picture
did stop for your player.
Okay. We've just covered what it took to
implement Picture in Picture from scratch.
After configuring your projects,
we explored the two approaches
to integrating your playback UI with PiP.
If your application uses
AV-Player-View-Controller,
the heavy lifting is already done for you.
However, if your needs require
a custom playback UI,
you can use
AV-Picture-In-Picture-Controller.
The last implementation step we covered
was the expectations your app should have
during a swap.
By following these steps,
you will find that getting tvOS
Picture in Picture up and running
is a breeze.
But what about your existing applications?
To tell you all about that,
I would like to hand it off to Dan,
who will show you how you can get the most
out of AV-Player-View-Controller.
Thanks, Jad.
AV-Player-View-Controller provides
the standard video playback experience
on Apple TV,
supporting a wide variety of remotes,
skipping, scanning, scrubbing,
Siri command, interstitial support,
and more.
And we encourage all tvOS apps
to adopt it for video playback.
For those of you who are already shipping
apps with AV-Player-View-Controller,
let's look at what you'll need to do
to get your application working
with Picture in Picture.
First,
let's talk about interactive overlays.
Interactive overlays display
custom application controls over a video,
such as a channel guide
or suggestions for further viewing.
In most apps today,
users get to these overlays
by swiping up on the remote.
Since tvOS 13, the swipe-up gesture
is reserved by AV-Player-View-Controller,
and this gesture is required for users
to reach the Picture in Picture controls.
So,
use the custom-Overlay-View-Controller
property of AV-Player-View-Controller
for your interactive slide-up controls.
This property was introduced last year
in tvOS 13.
If you haven't adopted
custom-Overlay-View-Controller already,
you will need to do so when you move
to the latest SDK,
because your custom swipe-up
gesture recognizer will stop working.
Users can access your custom overlay
by swiping up quickly on the remote
or by clicking an on-screen button
when the transfer bar is visible.
For an in-depth look at custom overlays,
see the presentation for "Delivering
Intuitive Media Playback with AVKit"
from last year's WWDC.
The button for the custom overlay controls
appears on the left
when the transport bar is visible.
Next, let's talk about Now Playing info.
Now Playing info is metadata,
static and dynamic, about your video,
relayed to the OS, other applications,
and remote devices.
AVKit publishes Now Playing info
on your application's behalf.
So if you need to augment this metadata,
use the external metadata property
of AV-Player-Item
rather than talking directly
to the MediaPlayer framework.
In tvOS 14, the old shared
Now Playing info center is no longer used.
So make sure you aren't still trying
to publish this info yourself
when you update your app
to the latest SDK.
This code illustrates
using a helper function
to create metadata
to put in the external metadata property.
Most of you are already using similar code
to provide title,
description, media content rating
and other information
to be displayed in the info panel.
As you can see here,
it can also be used
for non-displayed metadata
such as a service identifier.
Next, let's talk about how this affects
the architecture of your app.
The AV-Player-View-Controller delegate
receives and handles messages from AVKit
about user actions and other events,
including Picture in Picture.
In the past, you may have had the parent
or presenting view controller
act as the delegate.
However,
the delegate must continue to exist
and respond to messages
during Picture in Picture.
But at the same time, users can navigate
throughout your application.
So this means your delegate must not
be part of your view hierarchy.
It should probably be a separate object
that can persist
while your video is PiP-ed.
Let's think about what will happen
when the user swaps two videos.
So visually,
the two videos will trade places
on the screen with a smooth animation.
But you'll need to do a few things
to make this happen.
If you're simply presenting
the player view controller,
then you can implement swapping
by dismissing one view controller,
the one going to Picture in Picture,
and presenting the other.
Embedding AV-Player-View-Controller
in another view controller
poses additional challenges.
Do you want or need
to recreate the parent view controller
when a PiP video returns to full-screen?
And think about what should happen
to the navigational hierarchy
when this happens.
What part of your app should the users see
after they dismiss the video?
Should it be what the users saw
right before they started the last video?
Or maybe the landing page for the video
they just swapped to full-screen.
Perhaps the main screen of your app.
Depending on what you want to do,
there may be additional work to perform
when videos swap.
Don't overlook these details.
Be sure to allow time in your process
to properly design and implement
the right solution for your application
and your customers.
If you have a custom playback UI,
you may currently be pausing playback
when your app is deactivated.
But you should not do so
if the video is in Picture in Picture.
You do not need to do so at all
if you use AV-Player-View-Controller,
and we recommend that you don't.
So we've talked about implementing
Picture in Picture with AVKit.
Let's see what it looks like.
Okay. So here we've got a video playing.
Let's move this to Picture in Picture.
I'll swipe up to move the focus
to the PiP buttons.
And we click to go to Picture in Picture.
Now let's start another video in our app.
All right. Let's swipe up again
to bring up the PiP controls.
Swap and stop PiP are in the middle.
We can swap the videos like so.
All right. Let's try that one more time
in case you missed it.
We swipe up again, and we click,
and there it goes.
So let's look at the custom overlay.
The button for the custom overlay
is on the left.
And click, and here's our custom overlay.
The PiP window, you'll notice,
moves out of the way of the focus,
so your users don't have to move it
to a different corner of the screen
to see your controls.
Now let's stop Picture in Picture.
And there we go.
In summary, use AV-Player-View-Controller
to get the full tvOS playback experience,
including Picture in Picture,
with very little work in your application.
If your needs require
a custom playback UI,
be sure to follow
the Human Interface Guidelines
to ensure that users are as comfortable
using PiP in your application
as any other on Apple TV.
Do not install
a custom swipe-up gesture recognizer
for your own overlaid UI when
you're using AV-Player-View-Controller.
And be sure to allow time
to adjust your application architecture
to provide the best possible support
for Picture in Picture.
Thank you very much,
and enjoy the rest of your conference.