Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome to Handle Interruptions
and Alerts in UI Tests.
My name is Dennis,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Xcode team.
In today's session,
we'll define what a UI interruption is
and how to handle interruptions
utilizing interruption handlers.
Interruption handlers have been part
of XCTest for many years,
but it's not always clear
when they should be used.
In the second half of this session,
I'll demonstrate how to interact
with expected alerts.
For example, the ones that appear
when the app wants to get access
to protected resources such as Bluetooth
or location data for the first time.
And lastly, we'll talk about
how we can work with protected resources
and how we can reset
the authorization status
so that you can test these kinds of alerts
in a deterministic way.
Let's start
with what is a UI Interruption?
A UI Interruption is any element
which unexpectedly blocks access
to another element with which
a UI Test is trying to interact.
In the example on the right,
you can see a simple recipes app.
Imagine there's a UI Test that wants
to tab one of the recipes to view it.
Even though there's a banner at the top,
the banner is not considered
a UI interruption
because the banner's UI
does not cover the table view row
that the UI Test is going to tab.
Now that we're in the recipe's
detail view,
we make sure that we actually
navigated there
by asserting that the UI elements
appear as expected.
After that, we want to navigate back
to the list of recipes
to ensure that this part
of navigation works as well.
But now, the "Back" button is covered
by the banner notification.
So to be able to tap the button,
the UI Test needs to interact
with the banner first.
In this case, the banner is considered
a UI interruption.
Interrupting elements
are most commonly banners,
like we see in the example,
alerts, dialogs or windows,
but can be other types as well.
The important thing to remember is
that interruptions are unexpected
or at least not deterministic.
The appearance of an alert
in direct response to a test selection,
such as clicking a button,
is not an interruption.
Now that we understand
what a UI Interruption is,
let's go ahead and explore how we can use
UI interruption handlers
to handle these interruptions.
We've learned that interruptions
are unexpected
and appear nondeterministically.
Per that definition, there is no way
to handle interruptions efficiently
using the usual automation APIs.
Interruption handlers are closures
that are invoked by XCTest
when an interruption occurs.
There can be multiple interruption
handlers registered at anytime,
and the order in which they are added
is decisive of the order
in which they are invoked.
XCTest keeps a stack
of interruption handlers
and invokes them in reverse order
until one of them signals
that it handled the interruption.
You are free to use any of these handlers
as general or as specific as you wish.
Some handlers may just attempt
to find a "Cancel" button and press it,
others might make decisions
based on the UI
and contents of the interrupting element.
If an interruption handler
successfully handled an interruption,
it returns "True" and the iTest continues.
If it was not able
to handle the interruption,
it returns "False" and the next handler
on the stack gets invoked.
UI interruption handlers are automatically
removed at the end of the test
or can be removed manually at anytime.
At the lowest level in the stack
of UI interruption handlers,
XCTest provides its own implicit
interruption handler
that takes care of the most
common interruptions for you.
On iOS, XCTest handles
interrupting elements
if they have a "Cancel" button
or a "Default" button.
And new in Xcode 12,
XCTest also implicitly handles
banner notifications.
On macOS, XCTest implicitly handles
user permission dialogs
by clicking the "Don't Allow" button,
and the Bluetooth Setup Assistant,
which is well-known
for interrupting UI Test flows,
especially in CI
where no keyboard is attached.
Let's take a look at how all of this works
in action.
When I lived in Germany
and studied computer science,
my grandma not only helped me
with my homework for uni,
she also used to cook for me
almost every day.
Since I moved to the US,
she's been really worried about my health
and wants to make sure
that I eat healthy food.
She had this idea of having an app
that lists all her favorite recipes
she inherited and collected
over the years,
so that I could easily cook
the "good food" myself.
She's an exemplary programmer
and knows that she needs to have tests
that validate her app's behavior.
Here, you can see one
of the iTests she wrote.
She told me that this test
would sometimes fail,
but she has no idea why.
I promised her to take a look at this.
And sure enough,
after several runs of the test,
I was able to reproduce this.
The underlying issue here is
that sometimes the connection
to the server fails
and the app cannot update the recipes.
In that case, the app displays an alert,
letting the user know
that there was a problem
and gives them the opportunity to retry.
Now, for the purpose of this demo,
I've shutdown the web server
so that we can easily reproduce
the issue ourselves.
As you can see at the top,
I've already added
a UIInterruptionMonitor skeleton
to the test setUpWithError method
that we'll complete later.
Let's run the test step-by-step.
First, we create
and launch the application.
Then, we try to tap
one of the table view cells,
but the alert is in the way.
Since we're actually trying to interact
with an element,
the alert is considered interruption,
and XCTest invokes
our interruption handler.
In our skeleton implementation,
we just return "False"
indicating that we did not handle
the interruption.
This is where XCTest implicit
interruption handling kicks in.
Once I step over here,
you can see how XCTest
presses the "Cancel" button
to dismiss the alert and tap the cell.
Now, the test continues.
Great. You can see that XCTest
handled this interruption for us
by clicking the "Cancel" button.
But Grandma wants to make sure
that this test used
the latest relatable data,
so pressing "Retry" here
would be the better choice.
Let's modify our interruption handler
to press the "Retry" button instead.
Inside the interruption handler,
we check if the interrupting element
is an alert
and if it has a "Retry" button.
If it has, we tap it, and return "True"
to indicate that we handled
the interruption
and the test can continue.
Let's run the test one more time.
Great. Now, our test handles these
network interruptions by retrying
to fetch the latest set of recipes
instead of just canceling.
Now that we know how
to handle interruptions,
let's see how to best handle alerts
that are expected to show up.
Unlike interruptions, expected alerts
are often deterministic,
and the direct result of an action
performed by the UI Test.
The majority of alerts are expected,
and should, therefore,
not be handled as an interruption,
but as part of your test,
and should participate
in its validation process
using standard queries and events.
In the demo, the test did not explicitly
trigger the alert's appearance,
and we don't know beforehand
when it will appear.
The server will probably respond correctly
most of the time but not always.
That's why they had to use
a UI interruption handler.
Let's look at a different example to see
how it can interact with expected alerts.
Here, our test swipes left
on one of the recipes to remove it.
We know that after deleting a recipe
an alert shows up asking
if you really want to delete that recipe.
Since the alert is expected to show up,
we use traditional UI element query
and waitForExistence APIs.
Once it appears onscreen,
we validate that it contains
the text we expect.
Lastly, we dismiss the alert
by confirming the action
and validate that the row
does not exist anymore.
The expected alerts we've seen so far
have all been in our control.
This makes it straightforward
to get the app on our test
in the state we need
to validate these scenarios.
Protected resources, stuff like location,
Bluetooth or the microphone,
are very privacy sensitive,
and the system needs to make sure
that the user explicitly allowed each app
access to these resources
before letting the app access them.
Once the user interacted with the alert
asking for access,
their decision is stored by the system.
In a test, there are two or more
distinct branches that should be tested:
How does the app respond
to the user granting permission,
and how does the app respond
to the user denying permission?
However, the user response is stored
as system state,
so after the first such interaction,
the device is no longer in a clean state,
and it is difficult or impossible
to explore all the other branches.
For more information about
protected resources,
please watch "Better Apps
through Better Privacy"
and "Your Apps and the Future
of macOS Security"
from WWDC 2018.
In Xcode 11.4, and iOS and tvOS 13.4,
and macOS 10.15.4,
we introduced API on XCUIApplication
to reset the authorization status
of protected resources.
Resetting the authorization status
of protected resources
makes the app behave like it never asked
the user for permission before.
This allows you to retest
these authorizations
or initial launch experience workflows
in a deterministic way.
Note that these alerts did not originate
from your app but from the system.
Therefore, you need to make sure
to adjust your queries accordingly.
Also note that resetting
the authorization status
of a protected resource
may terminate the app process.
This behavior's not exclusive
to the iTesting, though,
and also happens when the user changes
the authorization status
in settings while the app is running.
Supported resources for all platforms
are, for example, context,
calendar, photos, microphone,
camera and location.
On iOS, we also support
keyboard network access,
Bluetooth, and new in Xcode 12
and iOS 14, health.
On macOS,
we additionally support researching
the access to various directories
like the user's downloads
or desktop folder.
Here's an example
of what a test looks like
that validates the flow of accessing
the user's photos for the first time.
First, we reset the app's
authorization status for "photos."
Resetting the authorization status
for photos terminates the app process,
which is why we launch the app
after the reset.
After that, we continue
with our usual test code,
where we find that the alert appears
after requesting access
to the protected resource
and dismissing the alert.
That's it.
Let's recap what we talked about
in this session.
We learned that UI interruptions
are unexpected,
or at least not deterministic UI elements
that block access to an element
which the UI Test needs to interact with.
We covered UI interruption handlers,
and when and how to use them.
And that XCTest provides
an implicit interruption handler
that can handle most interruptions
out of the box.
We talked about expected alerts
and how they're different
from interruptions.
And lastly, we saw how
it can work with expected alerts
that result from the use
of protected resources
by using new API in XCTest
to thoroughly test the initial
launch experience of your app.
Grandma and I want to thank you
for watching.