Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, and welcome to our session
on iPad app design.
I'm Grant Paul from the Apple Design Team.
Today, we want to show you
some of the new features and changes
in iPadOS 14,
what those mean for your apps,
as well as some general tips
on how you can make a great iPad app.
With technologies like Auto Layout,
Mac Catalyst and Universal Purchases,
many apps are continuing to expand
to more devices and more platforms.
People are getting more opportunity
to use their favorite apps
on all of their favorite devices
wherever it's most convenient for them.
And for us as designers and as developers,
this means we need to focus in
on what's best for each platform
to make sure
that every device and every platform
is creating a great experience.
So, on the one end, you have the Mac.
The Mac has the biggest screens,
it has the most precise input methods,
and Mac OS apps are there to support
all of the most advanced use cases
while still staying
accessible to everyone.
On the other side, you have the iPhone.
iPhone apps are all about
getting quick and easy access
to the most important functionality
while you're on the go,
and all through Multi-Touch.
So for both of these, the design direction
for your apps is pretty clear.
But what about the iPad?
Just because the iPad is in the middle,
that doesn't mean it's just
halfway between the Mac and the iPhone.
A great iPad app, it needs to be
just as dedicated to what's unique,
to what's great and special about the iPad
as apps are about what's unique and great
about the iPhone and the Mac.
And that's what
we're going to talk about today.
We're going to show you
some design principles
that we applied in our apps for iPadOS 14,
and we're going to talk about
how you can use
those same principles in your own apps.
So first, we're going to talk about
updating your app's layout
to take full advantage
of the iPad's large display.
After that, we're going to cover
how to best support
all of the different inputs on the iPad.
Then, I'll hand it over to Vince Lane
to talk in detail
about some of the new UI components
in iPadOS this year.
Things like our new Split Views
and the great new Sidebar navigation.
And finally, we'll cover some changes
in how to use toolbars
to position your buttons and your actions.
So the most important,
the most prominent feature of the iPad
is of course its big display.
So, if you're making an iPad app,
your first step should be
to take advantage of the display
to show your content
and your user interface
in the best possible light.
So, let's look at a few examples
from our own apps of how you can do that.
The first technique
that I'm going to talk about
is to flatten your app's navigation.
Avoid big full-screen transitions
in favor of updating
part of the screen at a time.
Let's look at an example of that.
So, here's part of the Photos app
from iOS 13.
You can choose an album or a media type
like your Portrait mode photos,
and it'll slide over the entire screen
to show that content.
It's simple, it's familiar,
and it works great on the iPhone.
And on the iPad, we had brought over
the same familiar navigation structure
with full-screen transitions.
But on the iPad,
that ends up leaving a lot of empty space
on the right side of the screen.
So, on iPadOS 14,
we've updated the Photos app
to use our new Sidebar navigation.
So instead of empty space,
it fills the display
with the content that you want to see,
your photos,
as well as your navigation controls
on the left.
It's using that space
to show you something useful.
But showing content
along with your navigation
also helps in other ways too.
For example, if you want to switch between
different parts of your photo library,
to your albums or to all of your photos,
it's now just a single tap away.
And it speeds up features
like Drag and Drop
since the drop targets, the albums
that you want to drop your photos into,
are already visible on the screen
as soon as you start dragging.
Now, the next principle
that I want to talk about
is showing more content.
Now, this one is a pretty simple idea.
You've got a bigger screen on the iPad,
so you need more content
in order to fill that up.
But getting that right,
it takes some intentional design choices.
So, back in iOS 12, here's what
the Home Screen looked like on the iPad.
You can see all the icons
are relatively far away from each other.
They're pretty spaced out.
In iPadOS 13, we added
an extra row and column of icons,
and now, in iPad iOS 14,
we've added in our new widgets.
So, the icons are still pretty big
and you can see more of them at once.
It's using the space in a better way.
Here's another example:
This is the Files app from iPadOS 13.
Now, this one is interesting
because the files are filling up
the entire right side of the screen.
There's no gaps between them,
and there's no big empty space.
But if you look,
it's only showing 12 icons at a time,
and we thought we could do better.
So, in iPadOS 14, Files now uses
significantly smaller icons.
Now, these icons are still plenty
big enough to see, to read, and to tap on,
so the app is just as usable,
but it's a great example
of how small tweaks to density
can make your app feel
so much more efficient, and more powerful,
just by making better use
of the available screen space.
Now this new layout here
means that Files is showing
almost 300% as many icons.
Can you believe that?
As long as your text is readable,
you should see if you can show
more on screen in your apps too.
So, that was showing more content.
Now, our next technique
is adding more context.
Now in iPhone apps, you're often
gonna focus in on a specific thing
because there's only so much room
to show things on the small screen.
But on an iPad, you have room to do more,
to show more than one thing at a time.
Let's see where that can apply.
In iPadOS 13, this is what it looked like
when you renamed a file in the Files app.
It's focused. You're not seeing anything
else but the file you're renaming,
but you're losing all of the context
of the files below.
In iPadOS 14,
we've brought file renaming in-line.
By staying in context, this lets
the rest of the screen stay useful
even while you're renaming
a specific file.
You can use the other file names
in the folder,
for example, as a reference
for the name that you're typing in.
So, wherever you have an overlay
or you're blocking out part of the screen,
see if you can keep people in context.
It'll make your app feel
both lighter weight
and more powerful at the same time.
Another example of this
can come with popovers.
Now, popovers are great
when you're showing context
of where something comes from.
For example, here,
when you're viewing or editing
a specific event in your Calendar,
the arrow on the popover
helps give you that context
of where that event is in your day.
But take a look at this popover
from Calendar in iPadOS 13.
Now, this one came from
us directly bringing over
the same screen from the iPhone.
The popover is the same width
as the iPhone screen,
so it's really easy to translate.
But look at this popover.
The arrow is just pointing
to a button called "Calendars".
It's not really giving you
any useful context.
So, in iPadOS 14,
we've moved the Calendars menu
to the same level as the Calendar events.
Now you can see and interact
with those Calendar events
even while you're changing the visibility
of your Calendars.
The results display instantly
on the right.
So, take a look at your apps.
See if you have any modal sheets
or popovers,
and see if those modal sheets and popovers
are giving people useful context
or if they're blocking
other parts of your app.
See if it would work better
if your controls are at the same level,
rather than an overlays.
And of course,
if your app works on Mac OS too,
avoiding models and overlays
works great there as well.
Now, modal UIs
are used even less often on Mac OS
than they are on iPadOS,
because Macs have bigger screens
and larger windows.
On the other hand,
with a compact device like an iPhone,
you might not have enough room
to show multiple things at a time,
and you shouldn't try and force it,
you shouldn't try and squeeze
multiple pieces of UI
onto a single screen.
modals are still a great choice to focus
in on a specific piece of content.
Finally, I want to talk about
going deep on a specific piece of content.
Some of the most magical iPad experiences
come from when the display
becomes more than a piece of glass.
When it feels like the entire device
is becoming a piece of content.
This is things like turning pages in Books
or watching a video on Apple TV
or sketching with the Apple Pencil
in Notes.
Here's another example of that
from the Photos app.
When you go in to edit a photo,
it uses a custom immersive layout
that's been designed specifically
for the iPad.
You can see all the controls are aligned
to the left and right sides of the screen
so that they're easy to use with two hands
when you're holding your iPad.
And on the big screen, you can both see
the photo really nice and big,
and none of the editing controls
have to cover
any part of the photo that you're editing.
And here's another example.
This one is new in iPadOS 14.
In Music, the Now Playing screen
takes over the entire display,
so you can focus on the music
and the lyrics that are playing.
Now compared to a Mac.
this ability to focus in
on a single piece of content
is something that's really unique
and special about the iPad.
The software can make it feel
like the hardware almost disappears.
Like it's become the piece of content.
It leaves your app feeling like
more than the sum of its parts.
So, that's how to fill the display.
The next key part of an iPad app
is all about interaction.
So, of course, the iPad
is a touch-first device,
but from the very beginning,
it's something that's supported
multiple kinds of inputs.
From the keyboard, originally,
to now the Pencil and the Trackpad.
And the best iPad apps
are going to have first-class support
for all of these different inputs.
They're going to use each input
for what it does best.
But, of course, you always should start
with Multi-Touch.
Everything in iPadOS
is built out of big, friendly tap targets
and fast and fluid gestures.
Your iPad apps should always start
with these touch interactions too.
Even if you're going to support
extra inputs on top of that,
you need to make sure that your app
has a great experience with touch
before you do.
Now, the next step after Multi-Touch
is using the built-in features in iPadOS
to support all of these other inputs.
For people who are using a Magic Keyboard
or other keyboards,
you should make sure
to add keyboard shortcuts
for all of the common actions in your app.
There are some people who really
use a lot of keyboard shortcuts,
and they're going to appreciate
any shortcuts that you add.
But those shortcuts won't get in the way
for anyone else using your app.
If you're on the fence about
whether you should add a shortcut,
I would recommend that you do it.
And if you bring your app to Mac OS
with Mac Catalyst,
all of these shortcuts
are gonna translate over there as well,
and people are gonna find them
just as useful.
Now, along with the keyboard,
the iPad now supports the Trackpad.
Most Trackpad support
is going to come automatically
because all of the built-in controls
in iPadOS support the Trackpad already.
You can also extend the pointer
to support any kind of custom controls
or custom interactions
that you want to add.
So, for more information
on the Trackpad behaviors
and the customizations you can make to it,
I would really recommend
checking out the session,
"Designing for the iPadOS Pointer."
Finally, you should make sure
to support Scribble with the Apple Pencil.
Like pointer support,
you'll get it automatically
when you use
the system text input controls.
But if you have custom controls,
you're going to want to make sure
that Scribble is supported in them too.
Because people who use Scribble
are going to expect it to work
in all of the apps on their device.
So, that's using the built-in features
from all of the inputs in iPadOS.
One thing that's really special
about all of these inputs
is that they can all work
at the same time.
And one really unique thing you can do,
one thing that's really special
and that can only exist on the iPad,
is that you can combine multiple inputs
into a single interaction.
It can make for
some really great interactions
that couldn't exist anywhere else.
One great example of that
is combining Keyboard with Touch.
For example, in Safari,
you can open links in a new tab
by holding the Command key
while tapping it,
or hold down "Option" and tap a link
to download a file,
or hold down "Ctrl" and tap
to get more options.
And in your apps,
you should support combining modifier keys
with all of the inputs,
like Touch and Trackpad.
You can support standard system behaviors,
things like holding "Option"
and dragging an item
in order to make a copy
or holding "Shift" and tapping items
to select them as a group.
Another great combination of inputs
is Pencil and Touch.
Here's the great animation app Loom.
So, Loom combines Pencil and Touch input
to make it really fast
to sketch out frames.
On the left, you can use this dial
with Touch
to select which frame it is
that you're drawing the animation for.
Then, on the right side of the screen,
I can use the Apple Pencil
to draw the actual frame of the animation.
So, I can switch between a frame
and then draw the next one.
You can see how fast it is
to draw a cool animation
by combining both Touch input
and the Apple Pencil
for a great interaction.
So those are some ways that you can make
your app's input more powerful.
The last technique I want to talk about
is making your app feel fast,
and one really key way
to make your app feel fast
is to make sure
that it's always responsive.
No matter what else is going on
on the screen,
animations or transitions or processing,
it should always be responsive
It means responding to input
all of the time.
Here's an example of that
in the new drop-down menus in iPadOS 14.
You can scrub to the item you want
in a single gesture,
even while the menu is animating up.
Imagine that if you had to tap,
wait for the menu to finish appearing,
and then tap an item to select it.
It would feel so much slower.
It would feel like
the device is not working
as fast as you can think about it.
Let's look at another example.
So when you bring up a drop-down menu,
tapping outside of that menu
has to dismiss it,
so it can't pass that touch through
to the app below.
But other gestures
don't necessarily conflict.
So in iPadOS 14, you can start scrolling
outside of a menu to instantly dismiss it
and scroll the content underneath
with a single gesture.
The app is staying as responsive
as it possibly can.
Now these kind of micro-interactions,
they can feel small.
But when you get them right,
it really adds up.
People can build confidence
that no matter where they are in your app,
when they interact with the screen,
when they go out of their way
to touch the screen or use the Trackpad,
that the app is going to respond
to the input that they're giving it.
You know, sometimes people complain
that animations feel too slow
or the transitions are taking too long,
and they have to wait for them to finish.
But when your app is always responsive,
these animations
can help give people context
rather than getting in the way,
because they can always interact
with your app at any time.
Now I'm gonna hand it over to Vince
to talk about sidebars.
Thanks, Grant.
To optimize iPad layouts,
one of the key new features in iPadOS 14
is the sidebar.
Let's take a look at some of
the new features built into the sidebar
and then later we'll discuss strategies
for implementing a sidebar in your app.
Now, this is Home in iPadOS 13.
And if we take a closer look
at the tab bar,
you'll notice
a lot of empty horizontal space.
It's not a great use
of this beautiful 12.9-inch display,
and navigating to a specific room
takes a few steps.
To get there,
you have to tap the Rooms tab,
then open the Rooms popover,
then find the room you're looking for,
and then, finally, hit the switch.
It's a little cumbersome,
especially if you're in the dark
trying to turn on the lights.
Now this is Home in iPadOS 14,
featuring the new sidebar
in place of the tab bar.
It's a much better use
of this large display.
You can now jump to any room in the house
with a single tap.
You can also easily rearrange rooms
by simply dragging and dropping.
Okay, let's see
some more sidebar examples.
The team's added a sidebar
to Music as well.
It allows for much quicker navigation
to your entire library.
And in Files, the new iPadOS 14 sidebar
makes navigation and customization
simpler than ever.
The new sidebar supports Edit mode,
making it easy to show, hide,
and rearrange content.
You can also easily create shortcuts
to your most important content
by dragging and dropping items
onto the sidebar.
And it makes it really easy
for people to dial in
the sidebar's content to their needs.
The sidebar even supports
spring-loaded folders,
so you can rearrange content
with a single finger.
We've added the sidebar to Photos as well,
making navigation simple and fast.
Content is organized
into collapsible groups.
You can collapse media types, for example,
to quickly jump to the other albums below.
And if you tap the sidebar toggle button
at the top,
the sidebar tucks away,
allowing your photos to fill
the full width of the screen.
To bring it back,
just swipe from the left edge.
Swiping from the left edge lets you
pull in the sidebar as an overlay,
and using the sidebar as an overlay
is great for fast, fluid interactions.
It means the sidebar is always there
when you need it,
but as soon as you start interacting
with the content area,
it re-hides,
so you can get right back to your photos.
And of course, if you don't want
the sidebar automatically hiding,
just tap the sidebar toggle button again
to bring it back
without the overlay behavior.
Now let's see how things work in Portrait.
The sidebar automatically switches
to overlay in Portrait,
and this is to ensure
enough horizontal space for your content.
But again, you can easily
bring it back into view anytime
with a tap, or a swipe from the left edge.
It works the same way
when you're multitasking on iPad.
With a split view like this one,
there isn't enough room for the sidebar
and your content,
so the sidebar switches
to overlay presentation.
Now let's take a look at Mail.
One of the great things about Mail on iPad
is that it supports three-column layouts.
It's super useful
for visualizing the hierarchy
of your mailboxes and messages.
But in iPadOS 13,
these three-column layouts
were only available
on our largest iPad Pro devices.
Smaller iPads were limited
to two-column layouts.
Well, the new iPadOS 14 sidebar
changes that.
We're bringing three-column layouts
to all iPads.
Just swipe from the left edge
to bring in the third column.
You can now see your mailboxes
and messages side by side.
Once you're done with the sidebar,
the layout collapses back down
to two columns
to make room for your content.
Three-column layouts even work
when the sidebar is presented
as an overlay.
Again, just swipe from the left edge
to bring in the sidebar.
And if you need to get
to that third column,
just keep on pulling, and there it is.
It really comes in handy,
and now it's available
on all iPads running iPadOS 14.
The sidebars you build in iPadOS
convert into sidebars on Mac OS,
so they're perfect for creating
the navigational structure
of your Catalyst app, too.
That's the all-new iPadOS 14 sidebar.
Let's recap the features
of the new sidebar.
It provides app layouts
optimized for iPad.
It supports both modal
and non-modal editing
so that your users can quickly navigate
to what's most important to them.
It supports drag-and-drop
for powerful multi-window
and multi-app interactions.
Its content can be organized
into collapsible sections.
It can be used as an overlay
so that it's always available
but never in the way.
And you can interact with it
using fluid swipe gestures,
so bringing it into view
or getting it out of the way
are fast and easy.
And, finally, it brings the benefit
of three-column layouts to all iPads.
Now let's discuss some strategies
for adding a sidebar to your app.
Let's start with a quick look
at two styles of app navigation
that are particularly well-suited
for the sidebar:
flat and hierarchical.
A flat navigation, as the name implies,
uses a relatively flat structure
of similarly weighted top-level content.
Even if one or two of those sections
has some depth to that content within,
the primary destinations
tend to be similarly weighted.
In apps like this, you generally use
a tab bar to navigate sections.
Think apps like Photos or Music.
A hierarchical navigation
is common in apps
that are more about
organizing and traversing
potentially deep layers of content.
Think apps like Mail or Notes.
Now, unless your app is
something immersive like a game,
it likely falls into
one of these two categories,
and both work great with the new sidebar.
Okay, so where do we begin?
Well, if you already have a tab bar,
it's the perfect place to start.
Tab bars are one of the most useful tools
for making navigation simple.
When you see one, you know right away
where you are and where else you can go.
And they're instantly familiar
to iPad and iPhone users,
so there's no learning curve for people
checking out your app for the first time,
and they clearly convey
the most important places in your app.
So no matter
how complicated your app gets,
tabs provide easy to understand
structure to your app.
So, as you start to think
about incorporating the sidebar,
we suggest taking existing tabs
and putting them at the top.
Think of this space
at the top of the sidebar
as a tab bar equivalent.
Whatever you put here will be interpreted
as the most important places in your app.
But don't get rid
of your tab bar entirely.
The sidebar
is only for regular-width layouts.
If you already have a tab bar,
you should continue to use it
in compact-width layouts,
and, likewise, on iPhone.
Make sure you have
the same top-level items
in both your sidebar and your tab bar.
This will ensure your app feels familiar,
regardless of size class.
Now you're ready to decide
what else should go into your sidebar.
Consider all of the content in your app.
We've found the things
most well-suited for sidebar placement
tends to be longer lists of content,
especially if that content
is user-generated in some way.
Think albums in Photos
or playlists in Music.
Put these items
below your primary navigation.
And, as you add content to the sidebar,
nest it under a collapsible header.
This will ensure
you maintain the correct hierarchy
between your top-level destinations
and the content below.
And it's okay if you end up creating
two ways to get to the same content,
maybe through one of the top-level items,
and also through a folder below.
That's totally fine.
Think of the items
you put into the sidebar
as shortcuts
to people's most important content.
You may choose to add additional content,
but resist the urge
to surface your entire app.
If the sidebar becomes overloaded
and requires a lot of scrolling
and uncollapsing sections to find things,
it's no longer serving its purpose
as a quick jumping-off point.
Finally, if your sidebar content
is user configurable,
it's a great idea to include add buttons.
Place them at the bottom
of each configurable section.
This enables people
to create content in-line
in the same place
they'll use that content.
If your app's navigation more closely
resembles the hierarchical model,
surface the top-level content
in the top of your sidebar.
You might have multiple top-of-tree items
to stack here, and that's fine.
Again, think of apps like Mail,
for example,
which could have multiple mailboxes
located here.
Then below that, add shortcuts
to the most important places in your app.
Keep in mind, however,
the sidebar is not suited for browsing
deep, nested levels of hierarchy.
This entire tree of content here
shouldn't be forced into the sidebar.
So if that's your app,
use the content area instead
for navigating hierarchy.
The sidebar should be reserved
as a jumping-off point
to the most important places
in that hierarchy.
Let's wrap things up
with a few quick tips to keep in mind
as you're implementing your first sidebar.
First, some don'ts.
Don't use sidebars in compact-width
size classes, including iPhone.
Instead, sidebars should convert
to tab bars
or standard table rows in compact.
And don't mix sidebars and tab bars
in the same view.
Sidebars and tab bars are meant to be
two different presentations
of the same content.
Mixing them creates
a confusing navigational structure.
And, finally, resist the urge
to surface your entire app in the sidebar.
Okay, now let's look over
a list of tips you should do
when implementing your first sidebar.
Keep primary navigation at the top.
This is the most visible place
in a sidebar app
and where your users will look
to navigate the key sections of your app.
Convert sidebars to tab bars
in compact-width layouts.
If your app has a tab bar
in compact-width,
your users will expect to find
the same key places
in both your sidebar and your tab bar.
We also suggest using outlined glyphs
in the sidebar,
though keep the filled in glyphs
for your tab bar.
As you consider additional content
to add to your sidebar,
be sure to start with the content
that's most important to your users.
Keep it below the primary navigation.
So list-style content
and anything user-generated
are both great options here.
And be sure to nest those items
under a collapsible header.
Support edit mode,
so that users can customize the sidebar
to their specific needs,
and make sure to support drag-and-drop.
Your users will expect
to be able to drag items
into folders in the sidebar,
and they'll also expect to be able
to drag content
directly into the sidebar itself
to create a shortcut.
Great. That wraps up sidebars.
Let's move on to a quick look at toolbars.
It's another way we've optimized iPadOS 14
to make better use
of the screen real estate on iPad.
Now, in iPadOS 13, we had some toolbars
that took up more space than needed.
Similar to some of our rather empty
tab bars we saw earlier,
this toolbar doesn't feel like
a great use of space,
so we've moved a lot of toolbar items
to the top in iPadOS 14.
The placement makes better use
of this large display.
However, when there's less room,
such as in compact-width,
these toolbar items stay at the bottom.
So just a couple quick tips
to keep in mind
as you're working on toolbars
in your iPad app.
Default to placing toolbar buttons
at the top in iPadOS.
Now, this isn't always possible,
but for one, two,
and three-button toolbars, it often is.
Use an alternate layout in compact-width
to move toolbar items to the bottom
when there isn't the room
to place them at the top.
Great. That was a look at the new
iPadOS 14 sidebars and toolbars.
Let's go back to Grant
to recap what we've discussed today.
Thanks, Vince.
You know,
if there's one theme from this talk today,
it's that making a great iPad app
doesn't come for free.
You need to design your app
specifically for the iPad.
The ways you can do that
are flattening your navigation,
letting your content fill the display,
showing more content
and giving users additional context.
It means supporting
all of the iPad's inputs:
Trackpad, Keyboard, Pencil,
and, of course, Multi-Touch,
and making them work together
for some great interactions.
It means using sidebars
for really fast navigation
rather than tab bars,
and including your top-level content
in the sidebar
to make it just a single tap away
from anywhere in your app.
And it means putting
your actions and your controls
into the top navigation bar
rather than in toolbars at the bottom,
to make best use of the iPad's display.
That's all we have.
If you're interested in more,
I'd really recommend
checking out the session
on the new controls in iOS 14.
Those new controls are gonna work great
in your iPadOS and your Mac Catalyst apps
in addition to on the iPhone.
You can also go deeper in how to build
all of these features into your apps
with the session "Build For iPad."
It'll show you how to use all of these
from within your code.
We're really looking forward to seeing
all of the great iPad apps that you make.
Thank you.