Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. Welcome to
"Discover WKWebView Enhancements."
My name is Brady Eidson, and I'm an
engineer on the WebKit Architecture team.
I'm genuinely excited to talk to you today
about new features of the WKWebView API.
At Apple, we love the Web.
We pay great attention to detail,
making sure that the WebKit framework
is fast, responsive, secure and efficient
so that our favorite browser, Safari,
can be all of those things.
But we don't only love
exploring the Web in a browser.
We love seeing web technology
used everywhere,
and our platforms enable
amazing integration of web content
with native experiences.
If you primarily need
an in-app web browser
and don't need deep customization
of that experience,
SFSafariViewController
is the best choice for you and your users.
It handles all of the things
you'd need to worry about
while implementing a basic browser
and beyond.
Your users get Reader, content blockers,
autofill and more,
and you get a browser in a box.
Add it to your app
and give it a URL to load.
SafariViewController is easy to use,
but powerful
because it is built on top of WKWebView.
When you need a higher degree
of configurability
or are using web content in ways
unrelated to browsing,
you can also build on WKWebView directly.
WKWebView automatically protects
your application's code and data
from the complexities of the web platform
by isolating web content
in a separate process.
This enables fast execution of web content
while also providing protection
against malicious actors.
SafariViewController uses WKWebView
because of those benefits,
and they are also why, for years,
we've strongly recommended WKWebView
over other alternatives.
Speaking of those other alternatives,
WebView and UIWebView were our
original APIs for embedding web content.
They've served us well,
but for all the benefits WKWebView has,
they tend to have the parallel drawbacks
which is why they've been deprecated
for a few years now
and why we are striving
to drive their usage down to zero.
The deprecated WebViews
work so differently from WKWebView,
it wasn't desirable or even possible
to make WKWebView APIs work
exactly the same.
This difference sometimes requires you
to rethink how you do things.
Other times, it requires us
to add new capabilities to WKWebView.
For those developers who have run into
challenges transitioning to WKWebView,
we are listening to you,
and the WKWebView API is still growing.
It has each year since its introduction,
and it will each year going forward.
On that note, I'm going to talk
about new features WKWebView has in iOS 14
and macOS Big Sur.
Some will make previously difficult tasks
much easier.
Some will bring back things missing
from the deprecated WebViews.
And some are brand-new capabilities.
We have a lot on our plate to cover.
First, I'm going to discuss new APIs
to help you isolate your app
and web content from one another...
then we'll talk about improvements
in how you interact
with web content via JavaScript...
we'll go over a few APIs to help you
fine-tune the rendering
of web content in your app,
we'll touch on ways to get more value
from web content
on the native side of things,
and finally, we'll touch on a topic
that is more and more important each day,
respecting privacy.
To help show off these new capabilities,
I'm going to tell you a story
that is probably familiar to many of you,
and that is the story of an app.
First, a little background.
Like most mature
software engineering organizations,
the Safari and WebKit teams have many
mission-critical internal tools
to keep the project going.
One of these critical tools
is our internal WebKittens website,
to notify team members
of the important updates
to the department's many cats.
The website has been with us
for longer than the iPhone.
But of course, once iOS was a thing,
somebody took it upon themselves to write
the WebKittens app using UIWebView.
Also like most mature
software engineering organizations,
our department has
a lot of duplicated effort
in its mission-critical internal tools.
The Pups on Safari website is one of those
to stay updated
on the department's many dogs.
And like with WebKittens, Pups on Safari
also has an aging iPhone app.
For such critical content,
having to check multiple places
throughout the day was kind of a drag,
so I decided to solve that problem
by writing Browser Pets,
a single feed
seamlessly combining both sites
natively managing
the interactions between them.
Since each of the original apps
evolved independently,
I started from scratch using WKWebView.
One of the first challenges I ran into
was isolating my application's logic
from the web content.
The "hello world" moment for my app
was showing the WebKittens' news feed
by itself.
And the first thing I noticed
while trying to scroll through the feed
was I couldn't.
As I scrolled through the page
with my finger, the page was fighting me.
My experience with the WebKittens website
is that it has a scrolling experience
heavily customized by JavaScript.
That's fine for the page in the browser,
but I'm doing deep customization
of the experience in my app.
I just want the kitties and nothing else.
The WKWebView API has always had a way
to disable JavaScript
by setting the javaScriptEnabled
property of WKPreferences to "false."
Unless you're writing
a general purpose web browser,
it's always good to ask yourself
if you can disable JavaScript
from remote sources,
especially those outside of your control.
With WKWebView,
this can become problematic
since most interaction with the content
inside the view
is by evaluating JavaScript.
So, we've deprecated
that setting this year
and we've added something new.
By using
the allowsContentJavaScript setting
on WKWebPagePreferences,
you disable only the JavaScript that comes
from the web page content itself.
In-line scripts,
remotely referenced JavaScript files,
JavaScript URLs, everything.
But your application's JavaScript
will continue working.
If you are not familiar
with the WKWebPagePreferences API,
it's pretty slick.
It's a recent addition,
and it allows configuring certain
behaviors on a per-navigation basis.
I'm already using the newer version
of the policy delegate
that lets me configure
web page preferences
so I can present as a mobile device
even when running on an iPad.
Here is where I can also disable
ContentJavaScript
while viewing the main news feed.
With that change,
scrolling works as expected.
Now that I can scroll
through the news feed at will,
I want to make sure
viewing the comments on a post works,
so let me tap this one here.
And this is the next problem I ran into.
I know from using the website
and app for years
that the bottom half of this page
should be full of comments.
Instead, it is blank.
I also know from experience
the comments are populated by JavaScript.
And before you say it,
I did not accidentally disable JavaScript
on these navigations.
It's time to hit up the Web Inspector.
The Web Inspector is a great way
to explore what's happening
with web content
in your WebKit application.
For years you've been able to attach
to any WebView or JavaScript context
in any app you're developing,
but we like to remind developers
at every opportunity
that you can do this,
and that it's awesome.
There are a lot of fantastic improvements
to the Web Inspector this year,
and I encourage you to check out
the session about them to learn more.
Back to our bug.
I can see here that there is an error
in the JavaScript console.
Let's take a closer look at that.
The web page expects the symbol
"commentDetails" to be a function,
but it isn't.
When looking at the page's JavaScript,
I can clearly see
they declare this function,
but the Web Inspector is telling us
that it's null.
I searched for the symbol in my app
and found this code.
Coincidentally, my application code
also has a JavaScript symbol
named commentDetails
injected into the web page.
And when I evaluate my JavaScript,
I overwrite their function
with an unrelated variable.
This type of conflict
is an ever-present concern
when working with WKWebViews.
Your application can accidentally conflict
with the web content.
The web content can accidentally conflict
with your app.
Malicious web content can conflict
with your application on purpose
by trying to change its behavior
or steal sensitive information from it.
These are all possible
as long as our JavaScript
and the web page's JavaScript run
in the same world.
To fix this, we'll need an isolated place
for our JavaScript to run
separate from the application JavaScript.
Our own global object.
And that is where
WKContentWorld comes in.
A WKContentWorld is an isolated sandbox
for JavaScript to run in.
If you are familiar with JavaScript,
it's like having your own separate
window object for the same page content.
There is a page world
representing the web content itself,
and then there are client worlds
representing one or more homes
for your application's JavaScript.
Your application's JavaScript
run in a client world
can still do things
like call built-in DOM APIs on the page
or change the DOM itself,
but it will never see the application
state set up by the page's JavaScript.
Likewise, the page's JavaScript
will never see yours.
To fix this in my application,
I'm going to use the default client world
for all of my evaluateJavaScript calls.
And now that my app's JavaScript and the
JavaScript on the page no longer conflict,
there's those comments. Great.
I showed you adopting WKContentWorld
with evaluateJavaScript,
but now you can also inject
WKScriptMessageHandlers
into a specific content world
to isolate them as well.
I think I've done a pretty good job
protecting my app and web content
from one another.
The next step in developing Browser Pets
involved a lot more JavaScript.
To help keep that under control,
I used some new ways
of managing the JavaScript
that my app uses.
The WebKittens website is rather static,
so it was a great starting point
for our combined news feed.
I injected some JavaScript
to clean up its look a little bit
and to prepare it to integrate
the Pups on Safari web content.
The Pups on Safari site has
a JavaScript API for fetching posts,
and that's what I've used to get
the combined news feed up and running,
and here's some of the hoops
I had to jump through.
When I wanted to reuse the same JavaScript
but with different values,
you know, kind of like calling a function
with parameters,
I needed to construct an entirely new
JavaScript string each time.
Another awkward thing was passing data.
These strings to represent zero?
Elsewhere in my application code,
they are natively integers,
but I have to convert them into strings
so I can build a JavaScript string
out of the string components.
Much worse than those
is how I manually add JavaScript strings
for each entry in this native dictionary.
What I'd love is for the ability to reuse
the same constant JavaScript string
as a function with named parameters,
and to not worry about those parameters
getting serialized
or deserialized incorrectly.
And those are just a few things that
the new callAsyncJavaScript API does.
Let's see what using it does to that code.
I can write JavaScript naturally
without having to construct
a string from arguments.
I can name whatever arguments I want
for my JavaScript string
and provide their values with the call
to callAsyncJavaScript.
Serialization and deserialization
of argument types happens automatically.
A Cocoa string
becomes a JavaScript string.
A number remains a number.
A Cocoa dictionary
becomes a JavaScript object
as I've highlighted here.
This little utility method I've written
can easily be reused
with different argument values like this.
You might notice in my example
that the JavaScript has
an explicit return value.
That's another difference between this
and evaluateJavaScript.
If I don't explicitly return a value,
then my completion handler receives
"undefined" as the result.
But there is another really important
trick hiding up its sleeve.
If your JavaScript returns a promise,
then your completion handler
is not called right away.
Instead,
it waits for the promise to resolve
and is called with the result
of that fulfillment.
This code returns the promise
that is returned
from calling the built-in fetch method,
which means
that my completion handler isn't called
until the bytes for that resource
have loaded over the network.
Just one tiny example
of how this makes working with modern
asynchronous JavaScript seamless.
CallAsyncJavaScript is a great addition
to evaluate JavaScript,
but there's more ways
my app uses JavaScript
besides my native code evaluating it.
The WebKittens folks
built in some cool features.
For example, if a new comment
is being added to a post server-side,
the page is notified and lets you know.
It even fires a comment event
for other JS on the page to listen to.
I wanted my native app
to listen for new comments too
so I can notify my native code,
and I do that using
WKScriptMessageHandler.
This API was originally designed
as a one-way communications channel.
To make it bidirectional
to handle a reply to your script message
requires some extra code.
For example,
tracking each message with an identifier
that can be used to look up a later reply.
The more sophisticated
your messaging system,
the more involved your message tracking
mechanism needed to be,
more code you have to write and debug,
and there's some race conditions
you may never be able to solve.
There's two new changes this year
to improve this.
First, postMessage
used to return "undefined" in JavaScript
as there is no meaningful return value
to be had.
Now it returns a promise.
Second, there's a new form
of the WKScriptMessageHandler protocol
that you can use which gets
a completion handler attached
to each message it receives.
When you call that completion handler,
the promise from the postMessage
is resolved.
That JavaScript code
waiting for a message reply
now boils down to this--
handling the reply to the message
through the resolution of the promise,
and that's a good thing.
At this point, I feel really great
about my application's JavaScript
and how well it cleaned up,
so I want to turn my attention
to making sure
the cats and dogs are all displaying
as they should.
I was able to apply
a few more new APIs that we have
to allow for more flexible rendering.
This is relatively old web content
from before when the phrase
"responsive design" had even been coined.
The original WebKittens app
looked pretty good on early iPhones
because the authors had tweaked it
for that specific purpose.
This is how viewing a comment
on the original iPhone looks.
This is how viewing a WebKittens comment
looks on a modern iPhone,
much larger than when the WebKittens app
was originally written.
You can see the beginnings
of a native UI I'm adding to Browser Pets
to allow returning from a post
to the news feed.
The web content itself looks passable,
but there's also lots of negative space.
It looks more like a 2005-era website
in a browser.
I think I can adapt the site as is
to make better use of the space
to make better use of the screen
and to fit in better with native UI.
I decided to see
if I could throw some CSS at the problem
to fill my users' screens.
The CSS zoom property has been with WebKit
for a dozen years,
and I think it might work here
applied to the entire body element.
As long as the zoom value is big enough,
it caps to take up
the entire viewport width
which is perfect in effect.
But the way I'm doing it here
is a bit clunky.
First, even though I'm evaluating
the JavaScript in my own client world,
that doesn't change the fact
that I'm changing the CSS
in ways visible to the page.
I don't know if it would cause issues
for WebKittens,
but you can easily imagine how it might.
Second, I chose to do this manually
on each navigation,
so I get into a bit of a race.
Will the content display before my
JavaScript-to-override-zoom is executed?
Unclear.
Fortunately, we have a solution for that
in the form of the new pageZoom property
on WKWebView.
This is actually the same property
that drives command-plus
and command-minus full-page-zoom
in Safari.
And I think a lot of developers
will find it useful in a lot of scenarios.
By using it on my WKWebView,
I can get the exact same effect
as changing CSS with JavaScript
but without any of the drawbacks
of doing so.
So much code removed
and more predictable behavior.
Next, let's take a look
at a Pups on Safari comment.
These headers and footers that you see
were meant for display on the website
as viewed in a browser.
They're not really what I want.
I have native UI to show,
not these artifacts from the site.
To explore my options for removing them,
I decided to learn more about them
in the Web Inspector.
I noticed the elements have these classes,
pup-header and pup-footer.
Let's dig a little deeper
and see where those are used.
So they match this custom media query
for a no-header-and-footer-device.
One usually sees
only a handful of media types in CSS,
"Screen," "Print" and so on,
and this is not one of them.
I did a little digging
amongst my colleagues,
and I found out that before there was
a Pups app for iPhone,
there was also a Mac app
that used the original Mac WebView.
WebView in the Mac had this great feature
where you could tell it to present itself
as a particular media type.
Commonly used to pretend to be a printer
when you were really a screen,
it could also be used for custom types.
So, depending on the context
within your app,
the same content
could have different presentation.
And we're bringing that feature forward
to WKWebView on all platforms this year.
By setting a custom media type
on my WKWebView,
I can easily get rid of those elements
and also adopt any other styles
that might come along
for a custom app like mine,
all without JavaScript,
and globally instead of per navigation.
Now that I've spent some time
fine-tuning how things look in my app,
I wanted to explore other features
I could add
that focus on the web content itself.
Fortunately, there's some relevant
new APIs this year for me to explore.
Looking back
at that last Pups on Safari post,
this was a popular post
with a lot of comments.
I remember Beth made this hilarious joke
in those comments,
but scrolling through to find it
seems cumbersome.
I'd rather have a "find in page" feature,
but how will I implement it?
There are some great
JavaScript find utilities out there
that might make sense if I needed
deep customization of the find experience.
But WKWebView now has an easy-to-use
find functionality
that behaves like others on the platform,
and that's just what I'm looking for.
I have a few things I can configure
about the find
like any find in AppKit and UIKit APIs--
the direction, case sensitivity, wrapping.
Or without any configuration,
it will just use sensible defaults.
If a result is found,
it is selected and scrolled into view.
Voilà.
That joke is just not quite as funny
as I remembered it.
Another thing a proper app needs to do
is share content.
And I can think of no content
more worth sharing
than the cutest web kittens
and the most adorable pups on Safari.
For a few years,
WKWebView has supported the ability
to take a bitmap snapshot of its contents.
This is useful in so many situations.
But it is limited to the on-screen content
no matter how much content
is actually there.
So if we add a feature to zoom in
on the full-resolution version
of this photo, for example,
we could only capture what's visible.
And this is not to mention,
depending on your goal,
bitmapped images might be a poor fit.
I think another great way of sharing
this content would be as a PDF,
and this year,
WKWebView will support just that.
You can configure a few things
about how you want to capture the PDF,
or if you just want a PDF
of all the content in the view,
including content
not currently visible on the screen,
call createPDF
with the default configuration.
This code... will share this entire post,
including all the comments
in a searchable text form
in one PDF document
that would look like this.
I told you it was a popular post.
Another type of content snapshot that I
often find useful when working with WebKit
is the WebArchive.
A web archive is an actual rich snapshot
of the current DOM of the web content
and the sub-resources
it would need to render.
In addition to being a file format
supported since the first public release
of the WebKit framework,
it is also the native pasteboard format
for web content on all of our platforms.
When I was first debugging issues with
the combined news feed in Browser Pets,
I wanted to leverage WebArchives
to help me.
While WKWebView has been able to load
WebArchive files since its first release,
it hasn't been able to save them.
Until now.
With createWebArchiveData, I can
now take that snapshot of web content
for later debugging and testing.
Like taking a bitmap snapshot
or creating a PDF,
it's a simple method of requesting
the WebArchive data
and getting the result
in a completion handler.
I can save this data off to disk
for later use,
put it on the pasteboard,
or even load it
into another WKWebView right now.
As I mentioned, WKWebView has always
been able to load WebArchive files.
I've heard from a few developers
that they thought that was not the case,
so I just wanted to share the code I used
to load a WebArchive, which is load(data
with the appropriate mimeType.
With bitmap snapshots,
PDFs and web archives,
we have a growing number of ways
to get stuff out of a WKWebView.
And there is one more important one.
As I mentioned before,
WebKittens and Pups on Safari
are mission-critical tools.
And some team members even rely on the
ability to print out their favorite pets
on actual paper
for proper motivation throughout the day.
Since Browser Pets is brand new,
I am of course using SwiftUI,
and I've been able to build
a Mac version of the app.
But I know printing is important
to these team members.
Printing WKWebViews has been possible
on iOS for a while,
but Mac developers have not been so lucky,
until macOS Big Sur.
If this interests you, go looking for it
in your SDK, and give it a whirl.
Before we get to a few more APIs
that help you on the app side of things,
I know many of you are also focused
on the web content itself.
We're always working on new Web-facing
features that can shine on our platforms,
and this year is no exception.
Once we're done here,
I encourage you to take a look
at the "What's New for Web Developers"
session.
Finally, I'm happy to share with you
exciting announcements
regarding user privacy
and how they affect developers
using WKWebView.
You might have heard Apple
say this before,
but just in case, I'll repeat it now.
We firmly believe
that privacy is a fundamental human right,
and that belief
is legitimately one of our core values.
We've designed iOS and the App Store
with this in mind.
We strive to prevent any native app
from using private information
without user consent,
not only at the policy level,
but also at a technical level,
and we get better at this every year.
The Web is different.
When users browse the wild web,
they are often being watched
by at least one party.
There is no curator, and some
web technologies seem to have evolved
to encourage tracking users
instead of preventing it.
We realized that with WebKit,
we could do something about this.
We started working on
Intelligent Tracking Prevention, or ITP.
ITP uses various client-side heuristics
and machine learning
to identify, classify and thwart trackers.
We've improved it continuously
since we added it to Safari in 2017,
and we won't stop.
Since we added ITP to Safari,
many WKWebView developers have been
asking us to use it in their apps.
And we're happy to announce that in iOS 14
and macOS Big Sur,
ITP is enabled by default
on all WKWebView apps.
Users have the control here.
For example, if you have
a general purpose web browser,
your users might need to disable ITP
for compatibility
with a website you don't control.
Most people
will not fall into this situation,
but there is API for you
to point users towards disabling it
just like we've seen with Safari.
Intelligent Tracking Prevention
has proven to be a powerful way
to protect user privacy in the Web,
but we didn't stop there.
While trying to think of other ways
to protect users on the Web,
we identified three common ways
web content is used in an app.
The easiest to understand, perhaps,
is the general purpose web browser
like Safari.
The primary purpose of these apps
is to show web content from any source
and to help their user manage
the things important to them
related to the task of web browsing.
On the opposite end of the spectrum
from a general web browser
is an app that stays in the confines
of only one or a few sites.
No matter their balance of native UI
and displaying web content,
the web content itself is part
of the core implementation of the app.
And then there's the in-app browser.
Often starting from a domain
specific to the app,
they aggregate content
from a lot of different sources,
usually allowing users
to start browsing from any of them.
A prime example
is a social media news feed,
much like Browser Pets.
For these last two types of app,
WKWebView has a new feature
called App-bound domains.
The idea is simple.
You specify which domains are the core
part of the implementation of your app.
This empowers you to design a secure app
by implementing the principle
of least privilege.
Deep interaction with the web content
not core to your app is disabled
for both the code you write
and any other code you might bring in
from frameworks or libraries.
This affects me with Browser Pets.
Comments on a post
can have links to other domains
to learn more about cats and dogs.
I want to allow these links,
and I can do so safely
as long as I limit my App-bound domains
to WebKittens and Pups on Safari.
It would become impossible for user data
to be accidentally compromised
on these other domains
where I don't have a deep understanding
of their structure or function,
or intentionally compromised if my users
run across a bad actor on the Web.
I don't necessarily know
what nefarious plans
the developers of this site might have.
Adopting it is easy.
You just need to add an entry
for WKAppBoundDomains
to your app's info.Plist,
and point it to an array of domains.
Here's how I adopted it in Browser Pets.
Loading any other domain still works,
but deep interaction with other domains
is prevented at a technological level.
It's even possible to disable deep
interaction with all domains in your app
by simply adding the key to your
info.Plist with an empty set of values.
If you load arbitrary content
but don't need any interaction
with the web content itself,
this is a best practice.
So, that was our journey.
We took two separate apps displaying
content from two separate websites
and integrated them into one news feed.
And the morale of the Safari
and WebKit teams has never been higher.
Along the way,
we made sure our app's JavaScript
was isolated from the web content itself.
We leveraged callAsyncJavaScript
and postMessageWithReplies
to greatly simplify our JavaScript logic.
We fine-tuned how the content displays
using new APIs that affect rendering.
We added an easy "find in page"
and a powerful "share as PDF" feature
as well as printing on the Mac.
And we respected our users' privacy
out of the gate
by embracing
Intelligent Tracking Prevention
and adopting App-bound domains.
All of these features were driven
directly by developer feedback.
We know we haven't gotten
to everyone's requests,
but remember, we're not done.
We can't wait for you to try out
these new APIs
and we genuinely want to keep hearing
what else you need in WKWebView.
In addition to feedback with Apple,
webkit.org has multiple ways to reach out,
including a link to our Slack
and to our many mailing lists.
WebKit is very open source,
so this is also where you can learn
to check out and build
as well as file bugs.
We're also on Twitter.
If you want to stay on top
of new Web-facing features,
Web Inspector enhancements and other
goodies you might see in future releases,
we usually update
Safari technology preview every two weeks.
Purple Safari deserves a home in your doc.
Thank you for watching, and I hope
you have a great rest of WWDC 2020.