Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Jess. I'm on the Siri team.
I'm a conversational interaction designer,
which is a fancy way of saying
that I think about the kinds of things
people should be able to do with Siri.
I'm going to talk about
these two things today.
So first, let's talk about
what you can do with Siri.
To get at the heart of it,
let's first dig into what we at Apple mean
when we refer to "Siri"
in the first place.
You may be familiar with this bit
from the Siri Human Interface Guidelines.
Siri makes it easy for people
to accomplish their everyday tasks quickly
using Voice, Touch or Automation.
This means that Siri should be equally
as powerful and enjoyable to use
across all these modalities
for all supported tasks.
As a conversation designer, I, of course,
want to focus today on Voice.
There are many parts
of the overall Voice experience,
including the assistant, Intents,
Shortcuts, Suggestions, Automations.
Siri is a lot of things.
First, let's look at Siri,
the conversational assistant available
on your Apple devices.
Siri helps you do all kinds of things,
including get information,
like the weather,
an answer to a math problem
or hours of a local business.
Complete tasks, like calling a loved one,
setting a calendar event
or checking important Reminders.
And pass the time
with all kinds of conversation
from asking for jokes to hearing a story.
All of us at Siri work hard
to make a great assistant,
but there are ways that you can help it
become even better.
Let's look at what you, as a developer,
can do with Siri.
It all starts with intents.
But what even are intents?
Conceptually, intents are how
we a speak a common language.
That definitely sounds like
something we want to do,
but what does it mean in practice?
Let's take a look at some examples.
An intent helps answer this question:
What is sending a message?
Well, think about what is
actually involved when a message is sent.
We need to know
who you want to send the message to.
And we definitely need to know
what you want to say in your message.
We've defined really powerful natural
language support for some key experiences
in what we call domains,
that group related intents
to do the things people do every day.
You'll see these groups referred to
as System Intents.
These intents come with the conversational
flow that's needed to complete a request.
Do you need to ask what music to play
or say a message has been sent?
Comes with. Just add your data.
Of course, there are still some things
you should think about
from the design perspective here.
While most of what Siri will say
has been written for you,
you should still make sure
that the dialogue sounds good
with your data in it,
both from a sentence structure perspective
and a text-to-speech perspective.
And error cases
are always really important,
so that people understand what's happened,
which means
you should pay special attention here
and make sure that the errors
or unsupported cases in your app
map to the dialogue that Siri provides.
But what about other stuff,
like what is it to order coffee?
Well, you tell us.
You're the expert on your use case.
That's where custom intents
come into play.
With custom intents,
the conversational flow isn't provided.
But as I said,
you're the expert on your use case,
so that puts you in an excellent position
to create this flow.
Just think through the logic
of your use case.
What steps does someone need to take?
What information do they need to provide?
And how would you talk them through it?
What words do you use,
what order do you ask for things?
In addition to intents,
we should also talk about Shortcuts.
Shortcuts is an umbrella term
for a lot of functionality.
Shortcuts are a great tool for developers
to make their functionality
even easier for people to access.
They also empower people to create their
own routines for things they like to do
and then share those routines with others.
Under the Shortcuts umbrella,
there's Suggestions.
Siri can suggest a Shortcut for an action
someone has done at least one time.
It can surface these suggestions
in a variety of ways,
making for a more personalized
Siri experience
and a quick and easy way
to access your app's functionality.
Siri can also suggest Shortcuts
for actions people haven't done yet,
but might want to do,
based on what they've done before.
The Shortcuts app.
In the app, people can find premade
Shortcuts for all kinds of actions,
both fun and useful.
They can also create Automations,
which can run directly
on a person's device
or can be used by everyone at Home.
Just set up the right conditions
to run the actions,
like time of day, location
or when a specific event happens.
Last, but certainly not least, Voice.
These Shortcuts are powered by the
custom intents we talked about earlier.
They enable people
to access your in-app functionality
without having to open the app
and allow people to add actions
from your app
into Automations
that they may want to set up.
Now that we've talked
about the ways you can add to Siri,
let's turn our attention
to what to add to Siri.
Voice shouldn't just be
about filling out forms.
That can be useful,
but speaking answers one by one
to a bunch of fields
isn't what makes
a great voice interaction.
Voice is great
for simplifying multistep interactions,
especially ones
that are completed frequently.
Think about playing music.
If you want to play
your favorite artist's newest album,
you first need to open the app.
Then you either need to know
the name of the album
or search through the band's whole catalog
to find it.
At last, you can play it.
With Voice, you can say,
"Play the latest album by DaBaby,"
and let the app do the heavy lifting of
figuring out what it's supposed to play.
It's less steps, which is great,
but there's also less required from people
to accomplish their goal.
Sometimes,
apps are laid out with several steps
before the actual task
people want to complete.
Imagine our old friend Soup Chef.
You have to look at the menu
before you can select a soup,
even if you know
exactly what you want to order.
That in-app hierarchy is important
to help people who are new to your app
know what there is to do.
But people who order your soup
all the time
don't need to see the menu to know
they want to order the tomato bisque.
Voice accelerates them past
the information they no longer need
and gets them right
to where they want to be--
ordering a delicious bowl of soup.
And maybe you have
some power users of your app
who frequently access something that's
not prominently featured in your UI,
like Settings.
This is a great fit for Voice.
People who love that feature
will be able to access it quickly.
And remember that people can use
their voice even when they're driving,
walking with AirPods or otherwise unable
to get to your app on their phone.
Voice is great for things people
want to do when they're multitasking.
In addition to having a great feature set,
you also want to ensure your experience
has great conversation.
Taking advantage of available modalities
is a great step
towards natural conversation.
Let's take a quick look at the two modes
Siri can use to communicate.
First up, silent mode.
In iOS 14,
if the iPhone ringer switch is muted,
Siri will be in silent mode by default.
As implied by the name,
Siri doesn't speak in silent mode.
Instead, the screen UI
and, where relevant, printed dialogue
work together to present
all the information people need
to complete their task.
And then there's Voice mode.
Here, while an available screen
will still show UI,
Siri speaks out all the information
people need to complete the task.
Siri:Your message to Eden says,
"Want to get coffee later?"
Ready to send it?
How you adopt these modes depends
on what solution you've implemented.
System intents have a lot of functionality
baked into them,
including handling
these different interaction modes.
You don't have to do anything
to get this working for people.
Custom intents do require a little work
to support this,
but the tooling makes it easy.
Just indicate what dialogue and UI
you want Siri to use
when people are looking at the screen
and what you want to use when they aren't.
Siri will ensure the right pieces are used
at the right time.
So, now that you know the modes
Siri can communicate in,
let's talk about what Siri actually says.
One of the things the Siri team works on
is ensuring Siri doesn't speak
more than it needs to.
So, where appropriate,
Siri will use shorter dialogue
once people are familiar
with a piece of functionality.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here, Siri provides more information the
first time you ask to change a setting.
The second time,
people don't need the same detail.
One of the places where Siri does this
is in attribution,
or letting people know
where information is coming from.
If you build a custom intent
and you do your job well,
people will use your shortcut a lot.
In that case, Siri will stop including
the attribution for your shortcut
when people access it.
But that means you have a responsibility
to have conversational dialogue.
And so, here are some things
to keep in mind to help you do that.
Questions are a great
conversational marker.
They let people know
you're expecting an answer,
so be sure to use them when people need
to provide information to continue.
Try to avoid jargon in your dialogue.
You're an expert on your use case,
but other people might not be.
Use best practices for spoken English,
not written English.
This keeps it feeling,
well, conversational.
And as much as possible,
keep dialogue short.
It's hard for people to remember
everything they hear.
Thanks for watching and enjoy WWDC.