Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi there. My name is Nahir,
and I'm a manager on
our iOS System Experience team,
and I'll later be joined
by my colleague Neil.
It's my pleasure to welcome you
to "Meet WidgetKit."
In iOS 14, we have a dramatic,
new Home Screen experience.
One that is much more dynamic
and personalized with a focus on widgets.
Our new widgets are designed
to be bold, highly glanceable
and be perfectly at home,
not just on the iPhone Home Screen...
but also our refreshed Today View...
pinned to your iPad Home Screen
and, finally, in the gorgeous new
Notification Center on MacOS Big Sur.
Now, before I dive deep into the API,
let's actually talk about
what makes a great widget experience.
When the team started to think about that,
we quickly came to three main goals.
A great widget is glanceable,
it's relevant and it's personalized.
What do we mean by
that a great widget is glanceable?
As we'll dive into later,
our new widgets can come in many sizes.
Especially at the smallest widget size,
you only have the space
of around four Home Screen icons,
so you really want
to make that space count.
People only spend a few moments
on their Home Screen
before they springboard off
to somewhere else.
They shouldn't need to interact with
or do anything more than take a quick peek
to get the most value out of your widget.
Take a look at some examples of widgets
in the small sizes.
You don't need to tap any buttons
or even spend time
trying to figure out a complicated UI.
The content is the focus.
This is very important,
widgets are not mini-apps.
Think of this as more projecting content
from your app onto the Home Screen
rather than full mini-apps
filled with tiny little buttons.
This can sometimes be tricky
to figure out.
Luckily, we have a great session
from our design team available
to help you think through
what parts of your app
would make really compelling
widget experiences.
Having a glanceable widget
is only one part of the story.
Having those widgets be relevant
is just as important.
For example, in the morning getting ready,
I care most about the weather,
but then, throughout the day,
maybe Reminders
so I don't forget any of my to-dos,
and then, at the end of the day, music,
so I can annoy my neighbors
with some loud party music. I'm kidding.
Especially on our mobile platforms,
where space is at a premium,
we really wanted a way
to make sure the right widget
is up and available as soon as you need.
This is where Smart Stacks comes in.
Smart Stacks are a collection of widgets
that will automatically rotate
to show the right widget at the top.
But you can also swipe through.
It's super fun.
We use on-device intelligence to help show
the right thing at the top of the Stack.
But as a developer, you can help
drive this using Siri Shortcuts donations,
the system that we've been building upon
in previous years.
There's also a specific WidgetKit API
to help the system figure out
when your widget will be more relevant
or when something else might be.
This is a really deep topic
that is broader than just widgets,
and we have an entire session
dedicated to this topic available
that I highly recommend you go check out.
A great widget
should let you personalize it.
Let's take a look at the Weather widget.
Yes, it's in Celsius.
I'm Canadian, and we use metric.
Right off the bat, you can have it
in three different sizes,
small, medium or large.
You're not required
to support all the sizes
as some experiences don't make sense
in all of them,
but I recommend supporting
as many sizes as possible.
Let's customize
the Weather widget further.
Just tapping on a widget,
while in edit mode,
flips around for quick configuration.
All the configuration options
are built using Intents,
which you may be familiar with
from Shortcuts.
Choosing a city
is a relatively simple example,
but this is a powerful system
full of possibilities.
Now, the awesome thing about WidgetKit
is that we can generate
this entire Configuration UI
from your Intent completely automatically
with no additional work from you.
It's pretty cool.
So, to recap,
the goals for a great widget experience
is one that is glanceable,
relevant and personalized.
With these goals in mind,
we designed WidgetKit.
So, let's dive in.
First of all, it was a goal
from the very beginning
for widgets to be multi-platform,
and to make it as easy as possible
for developers to have their learnings
apply across iOS, iPadOS and macOS,
so widget's user interface and WidgetKit
are built entirely with SwiftUI.
SwiftUI also makes it super easy
to support features
like Dynamic Type and Dark Mode
nearly automatically.
Next, there are some strong implications
with having widgets
on the main Home Screen.
The average person goes to
the Home Screen more than 90 times a day
and only spends a few moments there.
The last thing you want to see is
your Home Screen full of loading spinners.
When we designed complications on watchOS,
we had very similar goals
of having things be ready
and immediately glanceable,
so we took some inspiration
from how they were built.
What that means is WidgetKit extensions
are background extensions
that return a series of view hierarchies
in a timeline.
Using the declarative nature of SwiftUI,
we can package up these views
in this timeline
and then send them over
to the Home Screen,
which will present them at the
correct time according to the timeline.
This avoids the entire launcher process,
load and then present to view.
They are ready to go
and immediately glanceable.
The fact that we have your views
ready beforehand
means we can also reuse them
in other areas of the system.
For example,
we can have this super-fun experience
to add widgets from the Widget Gallery,
where people who use your app
can get a preview
of exactly what your widget will look like
right on the Home Screen.
You can refresh these timelines
from your main app.
So, for example, something changes in
your app, your widget can be up-to-date.
Or you can request schedule updates
right from your extension.
So, as an example, Calendar's widget
knows all my events for the day
and when they occur.
The extension can use this information
to render the right views
for when my next meeting is happening,
when I'm in that meeting
and the next one after.
You know what?
I think Neil and I should skip coffee
and go celebrate
at my favorite steak place in the city,
so I go into Calendar
and update the event.
Calendar will then use API
to reload the timeline.
What we mean by that
is that the extension wakes up
and returns a new timeline
with all the new updates.
Now that you have some idea
of how WidgetKit works,
let me hand it off to Neil who'll dive
deeper into actually building a widget.
Neil.
Thanks, Nahir.
Hi, everyone. My name is Neil Desai,
and I'm the WidgetKit engineering manager.
I am so excited to talk about
how to create a great widget today,
and to do so, I wanna talk about
four major things.
We're gonna talk about
how to define a widget
and learning about how to create
a glanceable experience.
We're also gonna discuss
the engine of our widget:
our views, timelines and reloads,
as well as the personalization
and intelligence aspects of widgets.
Widgets are simple
yet incredibly powerful.
And we're gonna talk about
all of the tools at your disposal.
So, first,
let's learn how to define a widget.
To define a widget, I wanna talk through
a few different concepts.
Those are: kind, configuration,
supportedFamilies and placeholder.
When we started this project,
we talked a lot about the different kinds
of widgets we wished to enable.
We wanted a mechanism
to allow a single extension
to support multiple kinds of widgets.
For example, a single Stocks extension
provides an experience
like the Stocks overview widget.
A great widget, which provides
glanceable information about a few stocks,
but also, that same extension powers
the Stocks detail widget,
which allows a user to show a single stock
on their Home Screen
or on Notification Center on macOS.
This is all done,
like Nahir had mentioned,
through the use of SwiftUI
and a multi-platform extension.
WidgetKit extensions can support SwiftUI,
AppKit and Catalyst-based macOS apps.
Kinds of widgets can also express
which type of configuration they support.
One is a StaticConfiguration,
and the other is an IntentConfiguration.
The Fitness widget doesn't really
make sense for configuration.
The widget doesn't need to allow the user
to configure it in any way.
The widget really is just,
"Hey, here's your activity for the day."
And mine happens to not look so hot.
So, I should get moving around,
but I digress. Anyways...
This widget has a StaticConfiguration.
Reminders, on the flip side,
can be personalized for a particular list.
This widget uses an IntentConfiguration.
A particular kind can also enable
one or many supportedFamilies.
By default,
widgets support all family types.
Weather's widget supports all families,
and so I can enjoy all my temperatures
in Fahrenheit
with any family type,
unlike Nahir's love of Celsius.
And these families look great on iOS...
and on macOS.
The last key component
of widget definition
is our placeholder UI.
Each kind of widget is required
to provide a placeholder UI.
Placeholder UI is the default content
of your widget.
It should be a representation
of your widget kind,
but nothing more than that.
There should not be any user data
in this UI.
The other important thing to note
is this UI is retrieved only sparingly,
and there are no guarantees
on when that will occur.
Typically we will only ask
for a new placeholder UI
on a device environment change.
For example, if the dynamic type setting
of the device changes.
Great placeholder UIs show representation
of what your kind of widget is.
I encourage you to think through
the best possible UI for your widget.
Ah, code.
All of those four key components
boil down to this widget definition.
Here we define a sample widget,
which conforms to the widget protocol
and we specify a kind.
We return some widget configuration,
which is composed of a few items
and within there we specify a provider
in our placeholder view.
We'll get to provider later,
but, really, that's how we set up
the engine of our widget.
We now know how to define our widget.
Let's talk about how to create
a glanceable experience.
Weather is a great example
of a glanceable widget.
Same with Nike Run Club's widget
and Calendar.
All three show me useful information
and invite me, as the user,
to tap to launch the app
and find out more information.
The first aspect of creating
a glanceable experience
is creating StatelessUI,
which SwiftUI is uniquely perfect for.
These interactions on the Home Screen
and on Notification Center are different.
These widgets are not mini-apps.
We do not support
scrolling within the widget,
interactive elements like switches
and other system controls,
nor videos or animated images.
These glanceable UIs can allow your user
to easily tap on the widget
and deep link into your app.
Let's take music as an example.
Here's music in systemSmall.
A user can tap
on the most recently played album
and deep link directly into that app.
systemSmall has a single tap target.
So the entire widget is a tap target
meant to take the user
directly into the app.
Music's widget also supports systemMedium.
There's great content which shows me
a bunch of different albums.
Each album is an individual link,
which can take you directly into that app.
The entire widget can be associated
with a URL link using the widget URL API.
If you wanna create sub-links
in systemMedium or systemLarge,
then you can use the new link API
in SwiftUI.
We've defined our widget and know how
to create a glanceable experience.
Let's now chat about the real guts
of your widget experience:
views, timelines and reloads.
Really, there are three types
of UI experiences you need to think about:
Placeholder UI,
which we discussed earlier,
and then there is snapshot and timeline.
Snapshot is where the system needs
to quickly display a single entry,
so the expectation is for your extension
to quickly return a view
as fast as possible,
because when you do so,
you'll see your real widget
in the gorgeous Widget Gallery on iOS.
This isn't a screenshot or image
we had to provide at design time.
This is your real widget experience
on iOS, iPadOS and macOS.
In most cases,
your timeline's first entry and snapshot
can be returned as the same entry.
So what you see in the Widget Gallery
is what you get when the user
adds it to their device.
And if we follow that thread,
if a snapshot is just a single entry,
then a series of multiple views
to be displayed at the right time
is just the timeline.
Timelines are a combination
of views and dates that are returned,
which allow you to say at what time
a particular view should be shown.
And by returning a timeline
is how we drive the widget experience.
Timeline's returns should be
for both dark and light mode.
And I wanna pull back the curtain
a little bit.
When a WidgetKit extension
returns an entry,
we will take that information
and serialize the view hierarchy to disk.
This means we just-in-time
render each individual entry.
This enables the system
to power numerous widgets
at the same time with numerous timelines.
I can't put this lightly.
This is some seriously cool tech.
Timelines should typically be returned
for days' worth of content.
There are times when your widget needs
to return more up-to-date information.
We do this through the concept
of what we call reloads.
Reloads are where the system will wake up
your extension and ask for a new timeline
for each widget placed on the device.
Reloads help ensure that your content
is always up-to-date for your user.
I don't know about you,
but I always find code to be the easiest
way to learn about a new topic.
So, let's dive in.
Here's the TimelineProvider protocol.
We have a TimelineEntry,
which consists mainly of a date,
a context, which provides
environment information,
and the context for which
the system is asking you for entries.
Then, in the snapshot function,
the system asks for a single entry.
And in the timeline function,
the system asks for a series of entries.
Here's an example of how I'd conform
to the TimelineProvider protocol.
I would create a provider.
In snapshot, I would create a single entry
and return it.
In timeline, I would return an array
of entries and attach a reload policy.
Baked into each timeline
is a reload policy.
It's where you can tell the system
when to ask for the next timeline.
You can ask for a reload
at the end of the timeline you provide,
after a particular date,
or you can explicitly tell the system
to not reload your timeline.
For example, maybe your widget
needs user data first
before returning a compelling timeline.
The system will take into account
your reload policy
and determine the best time
to reload your widget.
Widgets viewed frequently
will receive more reloads.
Widgets viewed infrequently
will receive fewer reloads.
The system will also force reloads
for whenever a device environment changes.
For example, if a significant
time change occurs.
The system will determine the best time
to reload your widget,
but there are also other events,
which may need you to ask
the system for a reload from your app.
For example, your app may receive
a background notification.
Or a user may make a change
in the app itself.
When receiving a background notification,
you can use WidgetKit API
via WidgetCenter to reload your timeline,
which will wake your extension.
And if your user makes a relevant change
in your foreground app,
you may also reload your timeline.
Be judicious with your
foreground app reloads.
Only reload your widget when a relevant
change in the app has occurred,
which should be reflected in your widget.
You can use the WidgetCenter APIs
from within your app process or extension
to reload your timeline.
You have the option to reload timelines
per kind or reload all timelines,
and you can retrieve the list
of current configurations.
There are also times when you need
to query your server for more information.
You can use background URLSessions
to kick off a task
and your payload will be delivered
to your extension
via the onBackgroundURLSessionEvents
modifier.
You should also be cognizant
of your networking usage.
Make sure and batch your requests
to your server
and only use as much networking
as you need.
Reloads when your app processor widget
is run in the background
are budgeted by the system.
Be efficient with how much processing
and networking your widget requires.
Widgets are not in every second operation.
Widgets are not about creating a live
running experience on the Home Screen.
There are many ways to drive reloads
to help keep your widget up to date.
Think through the right experience
for your kind of widget.
And keep in mind how to be efficient
with the different ways
to reload your timeline.
Lastly, let's talk about how to enable
your users to personalize your widget,
if it makes sense,
and help inform the intelligence
in the Stack.
Personalization and intelligence
are driven by two major concepts.
Intents, which are used as a mechanism
to allow a user to configure a widget,
and relevance,
which allows you, the developer,
to inform the intelligence in the Stack.
Intents are all powered
by the Intents framework.
Intents contain a set of parameters,
which are questions to ask the user.
For example,
Weather's configuration question
is the location
for which to return a forecast.
The Intents framework is already used
for integrating with Siri and Shortcuts.
And in iOS 14, it is now used
to power widget configuration.
Let's look at a concrete example.
The Stocks single symbol widget
asks someone which stock to show.
When the user tries to configure
the widget,
Intents can help answer this question
by allowing Stocks to return
the same list of stocks
that are presented in the Stocks app.
This is really powerful
and helps give your app the tools needed
to provide a great
configuration experience for your user.
Sometimes, though, that may not be enough.
What if someone wanted to show a Stock
that didn't already exist in the main app?
Well, thanks to the power of Intents,
we can drive this type of experience
using the Intents dynamic options
capability.
So, the user can search
in the configuration UI
and the system will fire up
the Stocks Intents Extension
which can then return a series of answers
in the form of stock symbols.
And new in iOS 14, Intents now support
in-app Intent handling
where your app can answer these questions.
If you want more information
about in-app Intent handling,
see the "What's New in SiriKit
and Shortcuts" talk.
Now, do you remember
that widget we defined earlier?
Here's how we change that
to support Intents.
Now, we specify an IntentConfiguration
instead of a StaticConfiguration,
and we specify an associated Intent.
Along the same lines,
here's that previous TimelineProvider
which now evolves into the provider
conforming to the IntentTimelineProvider.
You will be passed in an Intent object,
and based on the parameters in the Intent,
you can generate a specific timeline.
One of the coolest features of widgets
is not just having one widget,
but multiple in a Stack.
The system can intelligently rotate
the most relevant widget,
and your app and widget
can help feed this intelligence.
There are two primary ways to do so.
When users perform actions in your app,
your app can donate Shortcuts.
If your widget is backed by
the same INIntent,
then your widget may be rotated to
in the Stack
when the user would have typically
performed that action.
If you want to know more information,
I recommend checking out
the "Enable Widget Personalization
and Intelligence" talk.
Your widget extension also has the ability
to annotate timeline entries
with relevance values
via the TimelineEntryRelevance API.
When the time is appropriate, and you feel
your entry is the most relevant,
then you may return a score and duration
to inform the system
to rotate to your particular widget.
Score is a float value that you provide
relative to all entries
you have ever provided.
Duration is a time interval for when
that particular entry is relevant.
I want to make sure and stress this point.
This relevance value is relative
to all entries you have ever provided.
The system will take your relative values
and all other widgets' values
and determine the correct widget
to rotate to in the Stack.
Widgets are simple yet incredibly powerful
and we've only scratched the surface.
Widgets are not mini-apps,
so think through
a glanceable experience for your user
and use timelines,
the concept of reloads, and intelligence
to create the perfect experience
on iOS, iPadOS, and macOS.
On behalf of Nahir and myself,
we hope you have a great WWDC.
We can't wait to see what you'll build.