Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello there. I'm Ilya Veygman.
I'm a software engineer
with Core Location.
Today I'll be telling you
about all the cool new stuff
in Core Location this year.
We'll be primarily covering
location authorization,
and we will also discuss some new features
from this year's release,
App Clips and widgets.
Let's start with location authorization.
I want to begin by talking about
the state of the world in iOS 13.
As of the most recent major release,
there are basically three ways
a user can control the circumstances
under which an app
can access their location.
A user can respond to a location prompt
or go to Settings
and set one of these options,
which means that an app can get
their location information at no time...
only while it's in use
or at any time.
As user privacy is and has been
a major priority for Apple,
we thought, are there any other controls
we can give the user
which will allow them to regulate access
to their sensitive location data?
To do so,
we asked ourselves this question:
What does this app really need
to know about me in order to do its job?
A privacy-conscious user is likely
to ask themselves this same question.
And one way the user will ask this
is not just,
is this app getting my location
when I don't want it to?
They will also ask whether the app
needs to know exactly where they are,
as opposed to
approximately where they are?
There are certain classes of apps
where a user may not see the need
to give their exact location
and would be satisfied with the app
knowing just approximately where they are.
Does this dating app, for example, really
need to know anything other than my town?
Does this local events app
have to know what hotel I'm staying in?
Does this social media app
need to know exactly where I've been?
In fact, they might prefer to give only
minimal information and nothing more.
There are certainly use cases
where exact location is preferred,
if not necessary.
For example,
if you want to use a navigation app
to get turn-by-turn directions
from wherever you may be
to your destination,
you would need the app to know
exactly where you are.
But there are other classes of apps
where sharing just a little bit
of location information makes sense
for the app's expected functionality.
In the case of a dating app
or a local events app, for example,
it's certainly possible to make
hyper-targeted recommendations
or matches to a user
if you have their exact location.
This is a great feature for some,
but others may not be interested
in that level of detail
and would prefer
to not share location at all
rather than to access that functionality.
In cases like these,
approximate location might, in fact,
be good enough for many users.
In iOS 13, a user getting an initial
prompt for location authorization
would see something like this.
Starting in iOS 14,
and as you saw in the keynote,
a new option will appear
in the prompt for users, "Precise."
This option lets the user grant an app
only their approximate
rather than their exact location.
This will also be visible to users
under Settings.
By disabling the Precise Location switch,
the user can choose to grant
only approximate location to the app.
As a result of this,
the user now has two dimensions
upon which to specify how much location
access they would like to grant an app.
There's the "what circumstances"
of an app accessing location,
and there's now also the "how much"
dimension of location access.
Now, instead of just the one notion
of location authorization, we have two.
Users can do all sorts of things
with authorization now.
Initially grant while using
with reduced accuracy,
upgrade that to full accuracy,
and even do things like change
the authorization to "Always"
and then downgrade the accuracy
to "reduced" again.
Now, one thing that should be made
very clear before we continue--
apps cannot opt out of this new feature.
This functionality
is controlled entirely by the user.
It's another form of authorization,
after all,
and the user decides whether they grant
or revoke authorization at any time.
You, the app,
must adapt to this new world,
where users can decide not to give the app
exact location information at all times.
Given that, I think it's time to talk
about the tools we're providing you
to adopt this new feature.
First, we're deprecating
the CLLocationManager class method
for authorization status
and replacing it with a property that
delivers the app's authorization status
just like before.
We also introduce a new instance property
that indicates how accurately
the app can know user location.
There are two options for this enum,
full and reduced.
Full is the sort of default
from the pre-iOS 14 world,
while reduced is the new scenario.
To further accommodate these new notions
of location authorization,
we're further changing up the
authorization status delegate callback.
We're deprecating the old
didChangeAuthorization status callback
and replacing it with a new
locationManagerDidChangeAuthorization
callback method.
This new method is invoked
whenever either the authorization status
or accuracy authorization
property values change.
Here's how you might want to implement
the new delegate callback method.
You will need to check the values
of both the authorization status
and the accuracy
to determine how to proceed.
Now, a few notes
on how these are delivered.
Reduced-accuracy fixes are still delivered
to the didUpdateLocations delegate,
just like before,
and they're still expressed
as CLLocation objects,
with a CLLocation Coordinate 2D
center point
and a large value for horizontal accuracy.
These locations are recomputed
about four times per hour,
so if you have some time-out logic
in your application,
you should make sure to inform it
using the value of accuracy authorization.
Finally, while these are represented
as CLLocation objects,
you should not treat them like you would
a typical location with full accuracy.
Instead, you should consider them
to contain the user's true position.
Now, let's have a look at a case study
of a top-notch adoption
of this new feature in Maps.
The Maps team
have worked closely with ours
to bring you what you can see in iOS 14
and have done an amazing job of adopting
the new accuracy authorization API.
Please check out their talk
on designing for location privacy,
which will cover some topics that are very
relevant to what we will discuss here.
New, in iOS 14, when Maps, or any app,
asks for location for the first time,
they would see this prompt,
just like you saw before,
which will show an inset map
with their location on it.
Let's toggle the "Precise: On" pill
to see what happens.
This will show you
what the underlying app would get
if you gave it full
versus reduced accuracy.
This will be immediately obvious
by seeing the big circle
indicating the user's
approximate location in the app
rather than the familiar blue dot.
Let's see how this looks when you grant
authorization to the app and launch it.
As you'd expect,
the UI will show a large circle
indicating the user's approximate location
rather than the blue dot
that you're probably used to.
Again, this circle contains
the user's true position.
Maps also does a really good thing here
by placing a banner at the top of the UI,
which clearly indicates to the user that
they have reduced accuracy for this app.
This is a good thing to consider
when you're designing your own app
to adopt this feature,
how to reflect this reduced accuracy
authorization back to the user.
Now, looking at where we are
isn't the only thing we use Maps for.
We also like to use it
to navigate to places.
I'm going to look up directions
to my favorite museum after work.
Swipe up here,
tap on California Academy of Sciences,
and-- Okay, we see something new here.
Maps is informing us that getting
directions from where I am to the museum
needs my exact location
with full accuracy.
If you have a feature
that needs exact location,
but you don't have full accuracy
authorized, what do you do?
So let's pause and talk about that.
What do you, the developer, do
if the user is only sharing
approximate location with your app,
but you have a feature
that needs exact location?
Well, you've got two options here.
First, you can send the user to Settings
and ask them to upgrade you
to full accuracy permanently.
This may not be attractive to all users,
and some might prefer
to simply not use that feature
or even stop using your app entirely
rather than to grant you more access
than they want.
Fortunately, the other option is far more
attractive to these kinds of users,
temporarily granting full accuracy.
Here's how you would do that.
We have a new method on CLLocationManager
that allows you to prompt the user
for temporary full accuracy.
In this example, the user is prompted
to upgrade
their location accuracy authorization
if they do not have full accuracy.
After they respond,
this completion block is called,
which calls start navigation
if we got the needed response.
Now, we must set a purpose key
when requesting this temporary accuracy
authorization upgrade.
This is a very important point
to remember.
You have to explain to the user
why you need this upgrade,
and this purpose key will show them
what that reason is.
So let's talk about how to specify these.
To ask for temporary full accuracy,
you must specify a purpose key
like you just saw in the previous slide.
These strings must be within a dictionary
keyed off NSLocationTemporary
UsageDescriptionDictionary
in your Info.plist
like you see in this example.
Make sure you explain clearly to the user
why you want their exact location
to ensure
they grant you the access needed.
Following on the previous slide,
Core Location will select the string under
"WantsToNavigate" to display to the user.
It's important that you put these strings
under this dictionary,
as Core Location will only look
under this path for your purpose keys.
The prompt a user sees
will ultimately look something like this.
Note that the purpose key is shown
to the user just above the map inset
and explains why the app
wants their exact location.
Temporary location accuracy upgrades
work a lot like things do
with the "Allow Once" behavior
introduced in iOS 13.
That is to say, your user will be prompted
for an accuracy upgrade
the next time they relaunch your app
and trigger the feature that requires
a temporary accuracy upgrade.
This upgrade lasts as long
as a user keeps using the app.
So as long as they don't close it,
you won't have to ask for it again.
Okay, let's bring all this together
and see how it works.
Your user sees a prompt indicating
what location info the app would get,
were they to grant exact location.
Upon allowing this,
the app can now proceed
to give navigation instructions from
their exact location to their destination.
So, just a few takeaways to consider
before we move on.
You should make sure your app's
location-based features
are able to deal with not having
been granted full location accuracy.
Maps is a really good example of this.
They might seem like an app that would
always require full accuracy location,
but they deliver a great user experience
in both full and reduced
accuracy authorization.
When they lack full accuracy,
it's reflected in the UI to the user
with both the large position circle
and the status bar at the top of the UI.
This UI reflection is worth a strong
consideration when making your own app.
Sometimes, however,
full accuracy is needed,
and at that point, it's perfectly fine
to ask the user to grant full accuracy.
Maps does this well
by showing in the search bar
that it needs exact location
to navigate from the user's location
to their destination
and will then prompt for it
if the user selects this option.
Asking for full accuracy
only when it's actually needed
makes users more likely
to give you what you need.
It shows that you're not asking
for more information than is necessary.
Following on this,
you should also make sure
to use purpose strings
for accuracy upgrades
just like you would
with location authorization in general.
Explain to the user why it's necessary.
You can have more than one feature per app
that needs full accuracy,
so you can have as many such purpose
strings in your Info.plist as you need.
When asking for full accuracy,
it's often better to use
a temporary upgrade prompt,
rather than to send the user to Settings
whenever that's possible for you.
Now, let's talk a bit about how to
consider background location updates
in light of this new
accuracy authorization.
Let's start with significant
location change monitoring.
This monitoring adapts well
to reduced accuracy.
You'll get updates no more often than
you would didUpdateLocation results--
about four times per hour.
Similarly, we do not deliver
duplicate locations
if your position has not changed enough
to have also changed
your reduced accuracy location.
When accuracy authorization is reduced,
visit monitoring API
is still accurate in time.
It is only the spatial information
which is reduced in accuracy.
Let me explain what this means.
Let's say I arrive at work
bright and early in the morning.
If I have two apps monitoring for visits,
one receiving full accuracy,
one receiving reduced accuracy,
then the full accuracy app
will receive a visit notification
that I arrived at coordinates
within Apple Park at 10:08.
But the reduced accuracy app
will receive a visit notification
that I arrived at coordinates somewhere
within Cupertino, but still at 10:08.
Finally, beacons and regions.
Region entry and exit notifications
will not be delivered for apps
that are not authorized for full accuracy.
You will need to get full accuracy
to use this feature.
More on this in just a bit.
We know that there are many apps
which use region monitoring
to deliver features to users.
Let's look at one popular example,
Reminders.
As you probably know,
Reminders can deliver
location-based reminders to the user
by setting a perimeter
around some location.
Let's see how they adopted
the new accuracy authorization API.
I have a reminder set for myself
to buy some tuna for my cats,
and I want to be reminded of this
when I'm leaving work
so I don't forget
this incredibly important task.
Let's see how this works in the canonical
example with full accuracy.
Now, I can authorize, tap on the reminder,
and then go set a location
for this reminder.
Here, I'll be able to set a region
around my office
such that I'll be notified
when I leave work.
Okay. So, great.
I'll be reminded to buy some tasty tuna
for my cats as I leave work.
Let's see this again,
but this time with reduced accuracy.
You remember how I told you
that region monitoring
won't work in this configuration?
This time, Reminders prompts me to go
to Settings to turn on full accuracy.
It's correct for Reminders
to do this here,
rather than to ask
for a temporary upgrade,
because this app needs full accuracy
at all times
to deliver
timely location-based reminders.
Now, the user can choose
not to grant full accuracy here
and still set a location for the reminder,
but this location-based reminder
won't fire on any device
where the user has not granted
full accuracy access.
So a few key takeaways
for background location updates.
Region monitoring requires full accuracy,
so apps needing it will have to have
full accuracy granted to them.
While it might be tempting
to always check at launch
if your app has full accuracy
and then send the user to Settings
if you don't,
you should think carefully
about whether that's actually necessary.
Not every app needs the user
to grant them full accuracy at all times.
When it's possible,
design your app in a way
that will let the user interact with it
without having to increase
the authorized accuracy.
This will make for
an overall better user experience
and make the user more likely
to keep using your app.
As I mentioned at the start of this talk,
there exists a set of applications
that really do not need more
than reduced accuracy locations.
I previously talked about
how to get full accuracy
when you only have reduced.
So now let's talk about the inverse case.
Even though you might be authorized
for full accuracy,
it doesn't mean
you should get full accuracy locations
if you don't actually need them.
Luckily, you can set your location manager
to get only reduced accuracy locations,
when that makes sense.
We introduced
a new CLLocationAccuracy constant
that you can use to put
your location manager into this mode.
You can also change your app's behavior
to request reduced accuracy locations
by default
when asking for authorization
by setting this key in your Info.plist.
Note that there is no "Precise: On" pill
in the map this time.
This is another effect of this key.
It prevents the user from accidentally
giving more location access
than they intend.
In some cases, the user may want
to go back and change their mind
about having granted reduced accuracy
to their app,
and they can do so
simply by going to Settings
and toggling the "Precise: On" switch.
This is still going to be available
despite the mentioned Info.plist key
being set.
Let's have a look at an example app
that does request reduced accuracy
locations by default--
TV.
Many of us are familiar with
region-locking for streaming content
as well as television blackouts
for sporting events
and pairing with local affiliates.
With the proliferation
of content streaming services,
like Apple's TV app,
there is a legitimate business need
for video streaming applications
to know the locations of their users.
But, like we discussed before,
that doesn't mean the app needs to collect
more information about the user
than is actually necessary.
TV only asks for location
when it actually needs it,
and when it does,
it only asks for approximate location.
If I feel like watching some sports,
I would go to the Sports tab,
then find a game and tap it to watch.
If I click on one of these games,
TV verifies my location,
and after granting location access,
it only gets my approximate location.
By taking this approach,
TV still respects broadcast rules
while minimizing how much information
it has to collect about the user.
So, by now you've probably wondered
how exactly these locations work.
You're probably thinking that desired
accuracy was doing this for you all along.
So I'd like to talk about that for a bit.
Desired accuracy is a property
that we introduced to encourage you
to only use as much accuracy as you need.
There were many reasons for this,
but the foremost was
to allow iOS to save battery life.
Now, this is different from what we now
have with reduced accuracy in two ways.
First, there wasn't actually a guarantee
that you would get
the desired accuracy you asked for,
either because there was a lack
of a GPS signal
or because there could be another app
running simultaneously
which was receiving
more accurate locations
that we would then opportunistically
deliver to your app.
Second, there was not an effective way
to surface this information to the user.
That is, the user really had no control
over how much information
an app would get.
So, what does this new API actually do?
It might be tempting to think
that reduced accuracy locations
are simply your true location
with some noise added in,
but that is not the case.
Simply adding some random noise
on top of the user's true location
is actually not that secure
against someone who might wish
to disambiguate the true location.
Instead, it's better to think
of what happens under the hood
as a quantization of sorts.
Let me explain further.
Let's look at an example area.
Consider different users going on a drive
in the vicinity of El Paso, Texas
and Juárez, Mexico.
Note that this is near
an international boundary,
with the US being
in the northern half of the map
and Mexico being in the southern half,
bordered by this pink line you see here.
The true position of the user
is represented by the cars,
while their reported position,
that is to say, what an app would see
if it had reduced accuracy,
will be shown by a circle.
Again, as I mentioned earlier
in this presentation,
these reported locations
will contain the users' true location.
As these users drive down Interstate 10,
their location "snaps" to within different
quantized regions of varying sizes.
Both the red and yellow users
are going to be quantized or "snapped"
into the same regions
as they drive along the road,
but the amount of snapping will vary.
In denser urban areas,
this amount of quantization
can be a couple kilometers,
but in less dense places,
like rural areas,
it can be ten kilometers or a bit more.
A typical value for this quantization
radius is around five kilometers.
Note that, despite the cars
continuously driving along the road,
the region to which the true position
quantizes will not continuously update.
This is because reduced accuracy locations
are recomputed about four times per hour,
so depending on exactly
how fast these cars are moving,
there might be some lag
between quantized "snaps."
The actual semantics of the quantization
are intended to replicate
what the user would expect to hear
if they were to ask for an approximate
answer to the question, "Where am I?"
We try to ensure that the resultant
reduced accuracy location
is still going to be somewhere
that the user actually expects to be.
We use the location we have for you
to place your approximate location on
the appropriate side of the border here.
Again, though, remember
that the center point does not represent
the location of the user.
It only represents the center of a region
where they approximately are.
Approximate location snapping, however,
might put you in a neighboring city,
especially if there are cities
close together.
To reiterate the bit
about quantization around borders,
let's see what happens to someone driving
on the other side of the border in Juarez
and what they might expect to see.
Note that the blue car
is quantized into regions
whose centers are
on the Mexican side of the border.
This new reduced accuracy API
is available on iOS and watchOS.
An app's accuracy authorization status
is synced
between companion apps
on paired phones and watches,
just like the canonical
authorization status.
We've also made an improvement
to WatchConnectivity
for sharing
your app's authorization status.
We introduced this capability in iOS 9,
and we've made an improvement this year.
Now, you'll be able to share apps'
temporary authorization status,
as well as In-Useness state,
across both platforms.
This means that if a user selects
"Allow Once" on your companion watch app,
or does a temporary accuracy upgrade,
your phone app will be able
to benefit from that decision.
No more needing to ask for permanent
authorization when you don't need it.
In summary, this new API brings with it
a whole new dimension
of location authorization,
and with it you will need to consider
how your app should change
to accommodate the user
giving you only reduced accuracy.
If you have features
that do require full accuracy,
then think carefully about whether
you really need permanent full accuracy
or whether you can use
a temporary upgrade API.
Whether your app uses background location
updates will help to inform this decision.
Finally, consider whether your application
could utilize reduced accuracy by default.
There's no need to get more information
from the user than is actually necessary.
A few more things about CLLocationManager.
First, we'd like to address the changes we
made in iOS 13 for Always authorization.
For some apps, we made some
improvements in a recent release.
You may recognize this diagram
from last year's presentation,
and that it was not possible
to get Always authorization
without first going through
the provisional Always state.
The idea behind this was to help the user
understand Always authorization
by asking them to grant it
within the context
of where it was actually being used.
But for some apps,
this made it tricky to know
when location updates
would actually be delivered.
Asking for Always permission
when authorized WhenInUse
would put you
into the provisional Always state,
just like it would had you asked for it
from notDetermined.
We've changed this up
in the latest releases
to better balance
functionality and privacy.
Starting in iOS 13.4,
we slightly changed this state diagram
to provide a more deterministic path
to Always authorization.
An app which has previously asked
only for WhenInUse authorization,
and got it,
may now request Always authorization
and have the user immediately
be prompted to consider granting it,
without leaving the app's context.
If you need to know exactly
when Always authorization
has been granted to your app,
please consider this.
Don't ask the user for Always right away.
Instead, ask for WhenInUse the
first time they access location features.
Only ask for Always once the user
accesses a feature that really needs it.
If users better understand
why your app needs this authorization,
they're more likely to grant it.
One last thing.
We've had feedback from developers
that are using activityType in their apps,
and we wanted to rehash
some recommendations for you.
The activityType field
on CLLocationManager
helps inform
our underlying positioning algorithms,
give you and your users
a better experience,
and it's important to use them correctly.
Airborne should only be used for
actual airborne activities like flying.
Fitness should only be used if the user is
specifically intending a workout session,
like an outdoor run,
a swim or some other sport.
Automotive Navigation
has a special case of positioning
where you know the user
will definitely stay on a road,
like if they're driving a car.
Selecting best accuracy
for navigation here is also a good idea.
otherNavigation is when the user
is definitely moving,
but not necessarily going to be on a road.
This includes cases
like off-road vehicles, hikes,
boats, walking and so on.
Other should be used
when you don't have something
that will neatly fit
into one of these other buckets
or has no clear user intention,
like a workout.
Okay.
Let's talk about App Clips and widgets.
You probably heard about App Clips
in this year's keynote.
These are a great new feature
that will enable an entirely new
experience for your users.
I'm not going to spend too much time
rehashing exactly what these are,
and you can look at this talk
to get more information on that subject.
The key point for us to remember, though,
is that these are essentially
a lightweight subset
of a corresponding app.
This concept applies to using
Core Location within App Clips as well.
From our perspective,
App Clips are more or less the same
as their corresponding apps,
but with two very important distinctions.
First, they will not receive
Always authorization.
Second, instead of "While Using,"
they will see this--
"While Using Until Tomorrow."
This means that they get While Using
authorization only temporarily.
The authorization is automatically cleared
the following morning after being granted.
So, in terms of design considerations,
don't put any features into an App Clip
that would require Always authorization,
because you can't get it.
You should also remember that App Clips'
location authorization expires.
Cinderella can use an App Clip
to hire a pumpkin carriage
and a gorgeous dress for the night,
but just like her magical accoutrements,
the App Clip's location authorization
disappears by morning.
Finally,
I'd like to touch briefly upon WidgetKit.
This is an awesome new feature
in iOS 14 and the new mac OS
that you should definitely check out.
When making a widget that uses location,
you have to include
the NSWidgetWantsLocation key
in your widget's Info.plist.
You should also consider that widgets are
not able to show authorization prompts.
Their authorization will derive
from the parent app.
So, if you have an application
whose experience
will be primarily driven by its widget,
you'll need to consider how to prompt
for location access in the parent app,
should you need it.
Today we talked about some big changes
to Location Authorization,
a whole new conceptual dimension.
Giving the user more control over
their data privacy is important to Apple.
Users are increasingly conscious
of how different services use their data,
and location is a prime example.
When you design an app
to account for reduced accuracy,
you can deliver an amazing user experience
and build trust with your users
by showing them that you're not actually
asking for more information than you need.
We also talked about two new types
of apps entirely, App Clips and widgets,
and how to use Core Location
effectively in them.
These are great tools that were designed
by a group of amazing engineers,
and we hope you get the chance
to try them out.
If there's nothing else
you'll take from my talk,
then please just remember this,
Don't ask the users for more information
than they want to share with you
and that you truly need.
This isn't just for the users' benefit.
It's for your own too.
Users don't want to give away
more information than they have to,
and by minimizing what you ask for,
you can build trust with them
and give them a better user experience.
Think about your features,
think about what they do,
and think about what can work
with reduced accuracy.
Thank you.