Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Matt, and I'm the engineering
manager of the Swift Playgrounds team,
and today I'm going to be walking you
through the process
of using Swift Playgrounds
to prototype a SwiftUI view.
Many people know Swift Playgrounds as
a great way to learn to code using Swift.
What you may not know
is that it's a full-featured environment
for prototyping and coding in Swift
far beyond the end
of the "Learn to Code" series.
Today we'll start out by creating
a Playground that's compatible with Xcode
and showing a SwiftUI view
as the Playground's live view.
We'll take a tour of some of Swift
Playground's unique editing features
that can make prototyping
faster and easier,
and we'll look at how to move your code
into multiple source files
for building more complex Playgrounds.
Lastly, we'll look at a couple of tricks
for building custom, interactive previews
with more than one SwiftUI view at once.
So, as so many engineers do
at one point in their lives,
I'm working on building
a task-tracking app,
with tasks grouped into milestones
for a particular project.
One thing it's missing, though,
is a nice summary of my progress
through the project as a whole.
I want to do a little something like this.
Now, clearly my hand-drawn art
isn't quite ready for prime time,
so we're going to build this view
using SwiftUI,
and I'm going to do it in a Playground.
Today I'm using an iPad
with a Magic Keyboard attached,
but you can do this just as easily
using the on-screen keyboard
or using Swift Playgrounds on Mac.
Since I know I'm going to be bringing
my work into Xcode when I'm done,
I'm going to create
a blank Xcode Playground
rather than a blank Playground book.
I do that by tapping the "See All" button
in the bottom right-hand corner,
scrolling to the end
of the starting points,
and then tapping "Get"
next to Xcode Playground,
which will create a new, blank
Xcode Playground in the top left corner
of the My Playgrounds screen.
I'll give it a more interesting name
before we start,
which I can do by tapping and holding,
or in my case,
two-finger clicking on the Playground,
choosing "Rename,"
and then entering a new name.
We'll call it "My ProgressView."
I'll tap "Done,"
and then I can open
the playground by tapping on it.
And we're ready to start coding.
Since I'm building a SwiftUI view,
the first thing I'll do is import SwiftUI.
I'm also going to import
the PlaygroundSupport framework,
which is what you use to customize
the behavior of your Playground,
including showing live views.
Next, we'll create our view,
which is going to be a struct
called ProgressView.
It'll conform to the "View" protocol...
and it'll have a property called "body,"
which returns an opaque view type.
For now, let's just say "Hello world."
We're ready to show our view now,
so I'll move to the end of the document,
and I'll use the PlaygroundPage type
to access the current page
and then call the setLiveView method.
Now, you might have noticed
that while I've been typing,
I've been getting completion suggestions
at the bottom of the screen.
I can either tap those with my finger,
or in this case,
I'll click using the trackpad...
and then I'll create a new ProgressView.
To see what this looks like,
I'll tap the Run My Code button in the
bottom right-hand corner of the screen.
And voilà! Our first SwiftUI view.
Now, this text is just a placeholder,
and I think we want to get started
by building out the basic shape
of our live view,
which, if you remember
from my crudely drawn mock-up,
is kind of a circle-y type shape.
So I'll delete the text
that I've written here...
and replace it with a Circle view.
The arc in the mock-up has a blue stroke
on the outside of it,
so I'll use the stroke modifier...
and start typing "line width."
Then I can tap the first suggestion at
the bottom of the screen to complete it.
For now, let's say "25."
And since I like to indent my modifiers
below the view that they belong to,
I'm going to use the Command-Right
square bracket keyboard shortcut
to indent the code.
We'll also want to give this
a foreground color,
and we'll set that color to blue.
We can look at this by running it,
which this time I'm going to do using
the Command-R keyboard shortcut.
And there we have it. A blue circle.
I'll admit, it's a little bigger
than I thought it was going to be,
and that stroke isn't quite as heavy
as I imagined either,
but that's pretty easy to change.
For the stroke width, I can single-tap
or double-click on 25 to select it,
and we'll say maybe 40 instead.
And we can give the view a little padding
by adding a padding modifier of maybe 150.
If I hit Command-R again,
this time it looks a lot closer
to what I had in my head.
The next thing we'll build
is the text in the middle
that tells us how far we are
through our project as a percentage,
so I'm going to add a Text view
to contain that text
and then put it in a ZStack
with my circle.
I'll click above the circle,
type "ZStack,"
and create a pair of curly braces.
But rather than move my code
inside of those braces manually,
I can tap on the ending brace,
or in this case hover my pointer over it,
press and drag down
to encompass the circle and its modifiers.
Finally, we'll add a text view,
and for now, we'll just hard-code "25%."
If I hit Command-R...
Looking good.
We're really cooking now and making
great progress through this view.
-So it's time to get...
-[computer dings]
Oh. Well, I guess our designer
has actually already done
-all of the hard work for us.
-[computer dings]
It looks like
they've started their Playground
and put it in a shared iCloud folder.
So I'll close this document by tapping
the X button in the top left-hand corner,
and I can access files
outside the Playgrounds folder
by tapping the "Locations" button.
And there it is.
So I'll open that...
and then I'll tap the Run My Code button.
And you can see, yeah,
they got a lot further along than I did.
In fact, it looks so good, I'm not sure
what they want me to change about it.
-It's pretty perfect.
-[computer dings]
Oh. Okay. So it Looks like they want us
to try tweaking with the colors a bit,
so let's see if we can't make this look
a little snazzier.
It's really easy to play with colors
in Swift Playgrounds
because it has
an awesome built-in color picker.
So, you can see on this line here
at the top of the screen,
we have the two gradient colors, which
are the SwiftUI colors blue and purple.
The Color type actually has another
initializer that'll take a UIColor,
so I'll use parentheses to open that...
and if you look at the bottom
of the screen,
one of the options there is this gray
square that represents a color literal.
When I insert it, I get a color picker
with tons of options
provided by Swift Playgrounds.
I think we'll pick this
nice raspberry color for the first one,
and then for the second color,
we'll follow the same steps.
I'll open the parens,
insert a color literal,
and this time pick a nice deep purple.
And now if I hit Command-R,
you can see it looks a lot livelier
than it did before.
I think we're really
about done with this now
-and ready to wrap it up.
-[computer dings]
Unless, of course,
our designer has other ideas.
And they have a great suggestion,
as always.
We should see what this looks like
in Dark Mode.
Now, one of the great things about
working with SwiftUI in Swift Playgrounds
is that this entire live view area
is your canvas,
so if I want to show my view more
than once, I can do that really easily.
First, though, I want to give myself a bit
more breathing room in the main page,
so we're going to move ProgressView
to a file all of its own.
I can add a new file by tapping on the
"File" button in the top left-hand corner,
or on a Mac, by opening the sidebar,
and then tapping the "New File" button.
I'll give it the name "ProgressView,"
press "Return" to accept it,
and then I can tap outside the popover
to close it.
500 Internal Server Error
QTL_Cache/1.2.14
I'll switch back over to the main page,
and now what I want to do
is move this entire ProgressView struct
over into the file we just created.
I can do that by single-tapping
or two-finger clicking
on the "struct" keyword,
and then choosing "Cut."
I can then switch back over
to the ProgressView tab
with the Command-Shift-Right Brace
keyboard shortcut,
tap to enter code,
and then press "Command-V" to paste.
And there we have it.
It's in a file all its own.
Right away,
you can see it has some issues, though,
and the biggest one is that I haven't yet
imported SwiftUI into this file.
So I'll do that.
I'm also going to want to mark
my struct "public,"
since it's now in a separate module,
so I'll do that as well.
Now that I've done that, you can see
there's one new issue for us to address,
and if I tap on the "issue" dot,
it's reminding me that "body"
needs to be made public as well.
I'll tap "fix" to accept the fix-it.
And while I'm here, I'm also going
to mark the initializer as public,
because I'm about to use it
on the main page.
I can use Command-Shift-Left Brace
to switch back...
and if I hit Command-R...
you can see the live view is unchanged.
Now, I want to look at two of these
at the same time
so I can compare what it looks like
in Light Mode versus Dark Mode,
so to do that, I'm going to create
a new view to act as my preview.
We'll create a struct called "Preview"...
that conforms to the View protocol
like before.
And in this case,
the body is going to be a VStack.
We'll add a little bit of spacing...
and inside it,
we'll create two ProgressViews.
While we're at it, I'm going to
spruce it up a bit so it looks nice.
I'm going to get rid of the padding
we specified down below
using Option-Delete to delete by word...
and then I'm going to add some padding
to the VStack.
I'll also add a background modifier
so it's easier to see differences between
Light and Dark Mode variants of our view.
Here I'll use a color,
and I'll pass in the UIKit...
secondary system background color,
which I'll let code completion
fill in for me.
Lastly, we'll switch the ProgressView
initializer at the bottom of the file
to our new Preview initializer
by single-tapping or double-clicking
its name and typing "Preview."
I'll use Command-R to run,
and you can see that now I've got two
different previews of our ProgressView.
I did want one to be in Dark Mode, though,
so for the second one,
I can add an environment modifier,
and we'll set the color scheme...
to dark.
Now when I hit Command-R,
you can see we have one in Light Mode,
one in Dark Mode.
Looking great.
The last thing I want to do is take a look
at how this view feels in action
with different progress values
and with animation.
Since the live view is fully interactive,
I'm going to do that by adding a button
to step through different values
in 25% increments.
I noticed that the ProgressView accepts a
double as an argument to its initializer,
so let's wire that up in our preview.
I'll create a new State variable
called "Progress,"
and I'll set that to 25%.
I can then pass that into each
of our ProgressViews...
and when I hit Command-R,
the value updates.
With that in place,
we can now add our button.
I'll create a new method
called "Increment,"
which is just going to add 25%
to our current progress value.
And since I did promise animation,
we'll add a "with Animation" block
on top of it...
and like before, drag the closing brace
to encompass our incrementing statement.
Now I'll create a new button view
inside our VStack...
and I'll set its action
to the method that we just created.
Lastly, we'll give our button a label,
which is just going to be a Text view
with the message "Increment Progress."
If I hit Command-R now...
you can see we have a new button,
and if I tap it,
we have a working ProgressView.
And that's building a SwiftUI view
using Swift Playgrounds.
In summary,
Swift Playgrounds has loads of features,
like color literals, brace dragging,
and a full suite of keyboard shortcuts
that make it easier to edit complex code.
If you're going to be bringing your work
back to Xcode,
it usually makes sense to start with
the Xcode Playground starting point.
You can split your code
across multiple source files
to make it easier to understand.
This is especially useful
with SwiftUI views,
where you can put your view code
in a module
and use your main source file
for previews.
And remember,
you can customize your previews
and add interactivity by creating
your own views just for that purpose.
Thanks for watching, and enjoy
the rest of the awesome content from WWDC.