Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone.
Thank you for tuning in.
My name is David Lui,
and I'm excited to present to you
how to bring AR Quick Look
to commerce and retail workflows.
Starting in iOS 12,
we introduced AR Quick Look, our built-in
system-wide AR viewer for 3D content
where you can preview USDZ
and Reality File scenes
right with you in your world,
all without needing to download an app.
With iOS 13, we added new features
like launching straight into AR
the moment you tap the 3D model
from any application or website.
You can now share product links
instead of the 3D model
to bring users back
to detailed product pages from retailers.
We added support
for detecting vertical planes
along with horizontal planes
making it possible
to anchor picture frames or lights
on floors and walls in your space.
There's even support
for viewing face accessories,
like glasses and masks,
using the front camera
coupled with our automatic face occlusion
for that realistic try-on experience.
We gave a session last year
where you can learn more about
our other features and advancements
in AR Quick Look.
In the last year,
AR Quick Look was accompanied by
two new products in the AR family...
Reality Composer and Reality Converter,
and serves as a great visualization tool
for viewing and sharing
your 3D compositions.
And in support of those applications
and frameworks, like ARKit and RealityKit,
we've added new features
like instant AR placement
and object occlusion
that make the AR experience
more responsive and realistic,
especially on the new iPad Pro
with LiDAR scanner.
Now objects appear immediately
in your world
and can be anchored anywhere
from the flat surfaces of your floor
to the curved surface of your couch.
And together with object occlusion,
AR furniture could be placed in your space
between and behind
pieces of real furniture
for more realistic product visualization.
But one of the amazing things
we previewed last year
was our retail integration,
and we started with Apple Pay.
Our goal is to provide
a tighter integration
of AR technology and commerce
with retailers
in a really simple and easy way,
and AR Quick Look was a fantastic solution
to enable not only a richer and more
immersive experience for consumers,
but also for businesses
to sell their products in AR.
We've seen a lot of great companies
like Home Depot, 1800Flowers, and Wayfair
adopt this technology and integrate
AR Quick Look
as part of their shopping experience
with great feedback,
resulting in increased purchases.
And one of the most notable is
Bang & Olufsen,
where Jakob Kristoffersen, Senior Manager
of Customer Experience said,
"Users who engage with the AR experience
in our iOS app or on the website
are four times more likely to seek out
our Store Finder to visit a B&O store
and has aided our sales effort
to great extents."
So let's take a look at how this works.
We've added a banner at the bottom
of the AR Quick Look view
which provides a quick one-tap way
for the customer to immediately purchase
the item, like this alarm clock,
after seeing the product
in the world with AR.
The Apple Pay banner has
a very clean and templated layout
where the product information
is located on the left
and the Apple Pay button is on the right.
In addition to the Apple Pay banner,
there is a custom action banner
where retailers can provide
their own call to action text.
Our third banner style
is entirely customizable,
so you can completely configure the look
and feel of the banner using custom HTML.
These three banner styles
are available through the web
starting with iOS 13.3
on iPhone, iPad, and iPod touch.
Let's take a look how this experience
works from end-to-end
and discuss what's needed
to create the banner.
Suppose I run an online store
selling retro alarm clocks
and I want to add the Apple Pay button
to my AR experience
when customers visit each product page.
On my web page,
I can add a link to my USDZ model
so that customers can preview
the alarm clock on their nightstand
using AR Quick Look.
Last year, we introduced a way
to customize the AR Quick Look experience
through the web URL's fragment identifier.
We can use the same system
to provide the required information
for AR Quick Look to use to display
an Apple Pay banner.
These customization options
get passed to AR Quick Look
when the user taps on the link.
AR Quick Look then parses
the fragment identifier
and creates the appropriate banner style.
The last step for me
is to add an EventListener to my page.
This way,
when the customer is ready to take action,
tapping on the banner
will dismiss AR Quick Look,
and notify the EventListener
on my website,
which can then present
the Apple Pay prompt.
Now, let's go into more detail
about how to specify these customizations.
Before we jump in,
I'd like to first give you a refresher
on how to integrate AR Quick Look
with your website.
On my product page I've added an "a" tag
with a link to the USDZ model
of my retro alarm clock.
I've also nested an image tag
to show a thumbnail of the clock.
Adding the rel="ar" attribute tells Safari
that this is an AR experience
so it will draw an AR badge
and will present AR Quick Look directly,
instead of first navigating
to another page.
Next, we customize the experience
by passing in customization options
through the web URL's fragment identifier,
which appears after the hash mark.
To help with code readability,
I've separated each parameter
on its own line,
but in practice they should be separated
only by an ampersand
without any spaces in between.
Normally, tapping on the share button
allows the user to share
the current page that they are on.
However, specifying
the canonicalWebPageURL
overrides the default URL.
In my example,
users can share a direct link
to this fictitious product page,
even though they were
originally viewing it
on the Quick Look gallery page.
We also support disabling content scaling
through
the allowsContentScaling parameter,
so people can preview content
at the intended size.
In my example,
I always want the alarm clock viewed
at its true real-world size,
so I've provided a value of zero
to allowsContentScaling
which disables scaling.
So that's a quick recap on integrating
AR Quick Look on your website
and how to use the fragment identifier
to customize AR Quick Look.
Now let's talk in more detail about each
of the three available banner styles...
starting with Apple Pay.
If you're already accepting Apple Pay
as part of your business payment methods,
the Apple Pay banner is the simplest
and most convenient way to get set up
and allow customers to make purchases
right within the AR experience
with all the benefits of Apple Pay,
like being a fast and secure way to pay.
If this is your first time
incorporating Apple Pay on your website,
there's a lot of great resources online
including guidelines to help get set up.
As a reminder, AR Quick Look
is a system extension
and was built with security in mind.
So no payment information
is collected or stored
since the payment happens
after the AR experience dismisses
and the customer is returned back
to the retail web page.
Retailers have a wide selection
of button types to choose from
to best match with their business.
Specifically seven types.
The first four button types,
like Pay with or Check out with Apple Pay,
are focused on purchasing a product...
while the last three payment styles,
book, donate and subscribe are tailored
for specific use cases, such as travel
or subscription-based businesses.
Underneath each button type
is their corresponding value
for the Apple-Pay-Button-Type
parameter option,
which we'll talk about shortly.
Here's the code sample which will present
AR Quick Look with the Apple Pay button.
The first thing you might notice
is there's an additional
id="ar-link" attribute.
This specifies the unique identifier
for this link element
which we will use later
when we start listening for tap events.
There are four required parameters:
applePayButtonType, checkoutTitle,
checkoutSubtitle and price.
In our example,
I've chosen the plain Apple Pay style,
which is simple and compact.
The title and subtitle is where you can
supply the product information
to the customer.
Because URLs can't contain spaces,
the values in the fragment identifier
need to be percent-encoded such as
the spaces in the title and subtitle.
If your website supports
multiple languages,
you'll need to localize the string values
provided to the parameters
since AR Quick Look
will display them as is.
This is especially important
for the price parameter
when representing currency
for different locales.
And of course, you can also combine this
with other AR Quick Look
customization options
like allowsContentScaling.
Let me show you what the full Apple Pay
experience looks like.
Say I'm shopping
and I find an alarm clock that I like.
I can place it on my nightstand
and see it up close, right in my room.
Oh, this looks great.
I'll rotate and position it
to my preferred spot close to my bed.
Okay, I'm definitely going to
purchase this.
Since the banner's always visible
on-screen with the Apple Pay button,
I can immediately tap "buy" to start
the transaction.
AR Quick Look will then dismiss
and return to the web page
with the Apple Pay prompt brought up,
where I can then authenticate
and complete my purchase.
[app beeps]
Now let's look at the second style--
the custom action banner.
The custom action banner provides the same
intuitive layout of the Apply Pay banner
but provides the ability for supplying
your own call to actions
like "Add To Cart" or "Preorder"
to help move the customer one step further
in the purchasing flow.
This conveys the intention by the user
to proceed to follow-up questions
such as asking for an e-mail address to be
notified when the kids slide is released.
After AR Quick Look dismisses,
your website can then perform custom logic
such as adding to the item
to the shopping cart,
prompting for the product size,
or even opening Apple Maps
to help the customer
find the closest store near them.
The call to action
provides more flexibility
to enable additional retail use cases
besides purchasing,
providing more ways to integrate with AR.
The code is very similar to Apple Pay
except we need to specify callToAction
instead of the
Apple-Pay-Button-Type parameter.
Again, be sure to percent-encode
the URL parameter values
in the fragment identifier and localize
the strings for different locales
for both the call to action text
and price fields.
In addition, the price parameter is now
optional for the custom action in iOS 14.
This provides better flexibility
for products
which might have varying prices
depending on the product variant.
However, keep in mind that this field is
still required on previous versions of iOS
and should not be empty.
Let's take a look at a kids slide
from the AR Quick Look gallery page.
I'll go into object mode, where you can
see the custom action banner
is always visible for quick access.
Tapping on the custom action button
will dismiss AR Quick Look
and take me to the documentation page,
which is how I've defined and set up
the custom action.
Now let's look at the last style,
the custom banner.
This banner is the most customizable,
where you can supply your own custom
HTML file to fit your own unique use case.
This allows you to customize
the entire view
so you can use your own font,
layout and graphic
to match your business' branding
and style.
This banner supports three predefined
heights which can be used to communicate
additional information and contain
personalized messaging.
Like the custom action, it is up to you
to decide how to respond.
For example, you can start
a Business Chat conversation
by redirecting to your unique
Business Chat URL.
To comply with AR Quick Look's
security standards,
the HTML resource must be sent over HTTPS.
Otherwise, the banner will not display
and the request will be ignored.
To display the custom HTML banner,
you'll need to set just one parameter,
"custom,"
and provide the absolute URL
to the HTML file.
Like the other two banners, make sure
to percent-encode this value
before appending it as a URL parameter.
There's an optional "customHeight"
parameter available
if you want to set the banner height.
Supply a value of 'small' to set
the banner height to 81 points.
Or 'medium' to set the banner height
to 121 points.
And 'large' to set the banner height
to 161 points.
If you omit the custom height
URL parameter,
AR Quick Look uses a default small height.
Here's a great example of shopping
for a guitar from our fictitious store,
called Acoustic House.
I'll go ahead and tap on this guitar image
which will push me into AR Quick Look
where I can preview
the Stratocaster guitar in my room.
You can see Acoustic House is using
the custom banner style
and has presented the banner
for a conversational experience
with the immersion in AR.
On tap, AR Quick Look launches
a Business Chat conversation
in Messages,
where I can chat with a live agent
and ask questions
and eventually place an order.
This illustrates how AR Quick Look
provides a really powerful handoff
from the AR experience to applications
like Business Chat,
allowing customers to connect directly
with companies to learn more
and quickly get answers.
If you're not already familiar,
Business Chat allows consumers
to connect with brands
to ask questions,
schedule appointments and deliveries,
purchase goods and services
using Apple Pay and more
right from the Messages App.
Here, in this example, The Home Depot
is using AR Quick Look
to help consumers check out
home appliances
in an immersive and engaging way
as part of their buying process.
And with our new banner feature,
AR Quick Look
can then launch Business Chat
where consumers can start a conversation
with businesses like Home Depot
about the washer machine
and receive a USDZ file
of the companion dryer
where they can place it virtually
in their laundry room with AR.
This is a great way for customers
to learn more about a product
and really make an informed buying
decision in a private and secure channel.
And for businesses,
it is really easy to provide
this seamless customer experience
by using a Business Chat URL
as a custom action or custom banner event.
Here's a summary of the different
customization parameters
for each of the different banner styles.
As a reminder, the highlighted parameters
are optional for that banner style.
Now that we've gone over how to customize
AR Quick Look to show a banner,
let's go over how your website
can get notified
when users interact with the banner.
From earlier, we saw the code snippets
of how to use the fragment identifier
to specify which type of banner to show.
To listen for and be notified
of tap events,
we need to add an EventListener like this.
Remember the id="ar-link" earlier?
This is how the script is able
to retrieve the corresponding "a" tag
that we defined previously
and assign it
to the constant linkElement.
When WebKit invokes your listener,
check the data property.
A value of
"apple_ar_quicklook_button_tapped"
confirms the user tapped the banner
in AR Quick Look.
From here,
you can either invoke the Apple Pay sheet,
or perform some custom logic
like adding the item to the shopping cart
depending on the banner style displayed.
The AR Quick Look gallery
has been updated with new 3D models
and the banner examples
we've gone through together.
Visit the gallery page on your iOS devices
and try everything out.
It's really amazing to see how people
are taking advantage of AR
and integrating AR Quick Look
into their website
and iOS application workflows.
We love seeing all the many types
of content
people are sharing and experiencing
in AR Quick Look.
You saw the Apple Pay
and Custom Action banner
which are really simple
and easy templated styles
to quickly add purchasing options
to your AR experience.
With the custom HTML banner,
retailers have even greater flexibility
in customizing the view
to match their branding and colors.
There's lots of great documentation
available on developer.apple.com,
including how to add an Apple Pay button
or a custom action in AR Quick Look
that I've went through today.
We love to hear from you,
and you can send us feedback
on your Apple Pay
and custom banner integrations,
along with any requests you may have,
through Feedback Assistant.
Thank you, and thanks for watching.