Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Pascal,
and I'm here to talk about handling PHIR
without getting burned.
As you may know, since early 2018,
the Health app supports Fast Healthcare
Interoperability Resources,
better known as "FHIR,"
to download clinical data to your phone.
This is possible
thanks to the open standards
developed by HL7 and the SMART team,
which the Health app leverages.
To recap,
for us it all starts with the Health app.
Health establishes a secure connection
directly to the health provider's API...
and then downloads FHIR data directly
to the iOS device.
This data is stored securely in HealthKit,
which allows aggregation of data
from multiple institutions.
This data is then available to you
via the HealthKit API.
At the end of a download,
clinical data is presented
neatly laid out in the Health app.
Now let's see how your app can obtain
and work with this FHIR data.
First, your app will request authorization
from the user.
The user is guided through the
authorization process in three screens.
On the first screen,
general information about
what granting access entails is shown.
Next, the explanation text
that you provide in your app's Info.plist
is presented alongside a link
to your privacy policy.
And, yes,
we will review your privacy policy.
In this simple example
of a medication list app,
only access to medications is requested.
This follows our "proportional
to what you need" data use principle.
Finally, by default, only data already on
the device will be shared with your app,
so request authorization each
and every time you query for FHIR data
to ensure the user has a chance
to authorize access to new data
if applicable.
The sheet won't appear
if there is nothing to authorize for.
More details about this process are
available in our WWDC talk from 2018.
Now that your app has access
to clinical health records,
let's take a closer look at FHIR data.
This is a simplified FHIR
prescription resource.
There are a variety of field types:
simple strings, strings that can only be
of certain values, so-called codes...
date and times that come as strings
in an ISO-8601-like format,
other primitive types,
such as Booleans and numbers,
and complex nested structures
comprised of primitives.
Previously,
you had to write your own Swift Codable
if you wanted to work with FHIR data
in a native format.
This seems straightforward if you only
want to look at certain data elements,
and you know that the data is uniform.
In this example, you only want the status,
date and the medication of a prescription.
Soon, however, you start to realize
the depth, complexity,
and even just the sheer number
of FHIR resources.
Just indulge in this full definition
of a prescription resource.
Yes, you probably don't want to model this
all by yourself.
So, how can we help you work
with FHIR data?
Introducing FHIRModels.
FHIRModels is an open-source Swift package
available via GitHub
allowing you to file issues,
request features,
and to generally provide feedback.
There is support
for multiple FHIR releases,
and data models are provided
for all the resources in a release.
Resource integrity on encode
and decode is enforced,
preventing creation
of structurally invalid resources.
There is date/time parsing,
enums enforcing code fields,
enums enforcing value[x] polymorphic
properties, and much, much more.
And of course
we will keep the package up to date
with new FHIR and Swift releases.
The package comes with libraries for the
DSTU2, R4 and the latest build release.
We'll add support for new releases
as they emerge.
It is available via GitHub,
cohosted by our friends at CareKit.
Now, let's handle some FHIR.
Here's how you can get
a full-fledged FHIR data model
from clinical data
that you obtain via the HealthKit API.
First,
import HealthKit and the DSTU2 library
from the FHIRModels package.
Grab an HKClinicalRecord from HealthKit
and its associated HK fhirResource.
You can inspect HK fhirResource
to know its type.
Parse the resource's JSON data to receive,
in this case, a MedicationOrder instance.
You could then print the note.
Let's complicate things a bit
by presenting dosage instructions
with an associated date range
from a deeply nested structure.
First, write an extension on TimingRepeat,
a type provided by FHIRModels.
We want to pull out the start
and end dates of the bounds period.
In the real world, you would want
to make this far more extensive,
like check for nullability
and use a good old date formatter.
Then, map over all
the prescription's dosage instructions.
Use your new extension to prefix
the instruction with a date range
during which
these instructions were valid.
Another fun part of FHIR
is the fact that different releases
are in use out there in the wild.
In the fall of 2014,
the first draft standard for trial use,
DSTU1, was released.
It was followed
by three more major releases up to today.
Soon,
release 5 will be let out of the barn.
However, as I alluded to,
when a new release is published,
existing APIs aren't magically updated.
You'll likely want to support
the more popular releases,
especially DSTU2, for a few more years.
So, let's see how you can support
multiple FHIR releases with FHIRModels.
First, import the appropriate libraries
from FHIRModels.
Then, assuming you have a FHIRRelease enum
with values for all FHIR releases
you want to support,
switch over the release
and use the JSON decoder
with the appropriate model types.
Here, we use MedicationOrder for DSTU2
and MedicationRequest for R4.
Finally, walk the properties accordingly
to arrive at the values
you want to extract.
This, and much more,
is what you can do with FHIRModels.
To wrap up, FHIRModels helps you deal
with the complexity of FHIR resources
and even FHIR releases.
Use the package
when you are working with clinical data
obtained via the HealthKit API.
Also,
take a look at "What's new in CareKit"
to see how you can use FHIR
with CareKit to build care apps...
or, of course,
enhance your own independent FHIR apps
with the use of this package.
Here's what you can do from here.
Clone the library, add it to your project
and start exploring the code.
File issues, even if you just want
to provide feedback or ask questions.
Get our sample app which shows
how you can integrate FHIRModels
into an app that uses the HealthKit API.
And finally, you can learn more about FHIR
and chime in at chat.fhir.org.
Thank you, and happy coding.