Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Tom Doron
and today I'm thrilled to share with you
a set of technologies
that allow you to build and debug
serverless functions
written in Swift using Xcode.
Many systems these days
have client components
like iOS, macOS, tvOS
or watchOS applications
as well as server components.
The server components
enable the client applications
to extend their functionality
into the cloud, for example:
access data that is not available
on the device,
offload tasks
that can be done in the background,
or offload tasks
that are computational heavy.
Often, server components need to be built
using different tools
and different methodologies,
creating a separation between the server
and the client engineering teams.
Serverless functions offer
a programming model
that brings the two closer together.
Serverless functions are becoming
an increasingly popular choice
for running event-driven
or otherwise ad hoc
compute tasks in the cloud.
They resolve the need
in running dedicated resources
by replacing them with a more dynamic
resource allocation system.
In many cases,
serverless functions allow developers
to more easily scale
and control the compute costs
given their on demand and elastic nature.
AWS Lambda is an event-driven,
serverless computing platform
provided by Amazon
as part of Amazon Web Services,
and it is considered among
the industry leaders in this space.
When building systems
with serverless functions,
extra attention is given
to compute resource utilization
as it directly impacts
the overall cost of the system.
The combination of developer friendliness
and low resource footprint
makes Swift a fantastic choice
for building serverless functions.
Given how well these two go together,
we're happy to offer a Swift solution
for building and debugging
serverless functions in Xcode
and deploying them to AWS Lambda.
Let me show you what this looks like.
And this is it. Only four lines of code.
Let's review the API in detail.
First, we import
the AWS Lambda Runtime library.
Next, we call Lambda.run
and pass in a closure
that takes a context, an event payload
and a completion handler.
The function can call
the completion handler
when the work is done.
The closure will be invoked
as event payloads become available
for it to process,
and the runtime library
will manage the program's life cycle
and interaction
with the underlying platform.
There is also
a second protocol oriented API
that is designed
for performance sensitive use cases.
This API exposes
the SwiftNIO EventLoop underpinning,
which allow the Lambda function
to share the same thread
as the networking processing stack
and so to avoid context twitches.
This API is more powerful,
but it comes at a cost
of cognitive and technical complexity
as the Lambda function needs to take care
to never block the EventLoop.
In most cases,
closure based Lambda functions
are the right choice.
And in this example,
you may have noticed that
we're using a request and response struct
that conform to the Codable protocol,
providing easy serialization
to and from JSON.
In most cases,
Lambda payloads are JSON based,
so this represents
a more typical use of the library.
Now, let's see how to build
and debug a Lambda function,
and for that,
we will switch over to Xcode.
In this example,
which is included in the Swift
AWS Lambda Runtime library repository,
we have a workspace with two projects:
a Lambda and an iOS app.
The Lambda is a package manager project
with an executable product
and the dependency
on the Swift AWS Lambda Runtime library.
If we look at the Lambda main.swift,
which is the entry point for the program,
we can see a request struct
and a response struct
similar to the ones we saw on the slide.
The request struct
is a user registration form
with a name and a password field,
and the response is a message
with a simple greeting to the new user.
Switching over to the iOS app,
we can see a similar setup.
The SwiftUI registration form
with a text field for the username
and a secure field for the password
and a button that invokes
a register function.
The question, of course, is
how do we tie these two things together?
How does a register function cause
the Lambda function on the other side?
Let's try to run our Lambda function
and see what happens.
We hit "run"
on the Lambda target over here,
and we can see that it failed.
Looking at the error,
it could not fetch work
from the Lambda runtime engine
because the connection was refused.
This makes sense because
we're not running in AWS Lambda Runtime.
We're running in Xcode.
Luckily, the library comes
with a special mode
that enables a Simulator
that simulates the AWS runtime engine.
We can turn this on by editing the scheme
and setting an environment variable
called LOCAL_LAMBDA_SERVER_ENABLED
to true.
Let's do that
and try to run the Lambda again.
In this case,
we're getting much better results.
We're seeing that
the Local Lambda Server was started
and is listening on local host port 7000
and receiving events
on the invoke endpoint.
That's pretty sweet.
It also gives us a hint as to what
we can do on the iOS application side.
Let's switch over there
and try to write our register function.
For this, we will use a snippet
we prepared up front,
and this snippet uses URLSession
to the local host address
provided to us by the Lambda function
in sending the request form,
and then handle the response.
We can add a couple breakpoints,
maybe when we're constructing the request,
and as we are handling the response,
we can also add a breakpoint
on the Lambda function.
Let's run our iOS application
in the Simulator and see what happens.
We can see that
Xcode is managing two processes.
One for the Lambda function
and one for the iOS application.
We can also see that the Lambda
only takes 6.3 megabytes of memory.
That's pretty sweet.
Now, let's switch to the application
in the Simulator and try to register.
Put in our name and our password
and click the register button.
Then we hit the first breakpoint.
This is the construction of the request.
This all looks pretty good.
Let's remove this breakpoint and continue.
And now we hit the second breakpoint
on the Lambda function.
Here we can inspect, maybe,
the request that we got from the client,
and we see our username
and supersecret password.
That looks good as well.
Remove the breakpoint and continue.
And finally, we hit the last breakpoint
when processing the response.
We can use the LLDB debugger
to examine the response as well.
Finally, we get our greeting showing up
on the UI as expected.
Awesome, but how did this work?
We used Xcode to manage two processes
for our two executable targets:
the iOS application
and the Lambda function.
To make the Lambda function
available over HTTP,
we also started a local HTTP server
that simulates
the AWS Lambda Runtime engine.
We used a special environment variable
to turn this functionality on.
The iOS application
then used an HTTP call,
using URLSession
to submit work to the Lambda.
This setup only works locally
in debug mode.
To interact with a Lambda
deployed to AWS over HTTP,
you need to expose it first
through AWS API Gateway.
Now, let's see how to deploy
our Lambda function.
And for this,
we will switch over to the terminal.
To deploy our Lambda function,
we can use a variety of tools
provided by AWS,
such as SAM or AWS CLI.
In this example, which is also available
as part of the library code on GitHub,
we build a small script
that wraps the AWS CLI
and shows you the different steps required
to deploy the Lambda function to AWS.
Let's run scripts/deploy
and see what it does.
First, we create a Docker image
that is based on the Amazon Linux 2 image
published by Swift.org.
Next, we compile the Lambda function
in the Docker container.
Then we package the executable and
all of its dependencies in a .zip file,
which is the expected package format.
Finally, we upload the .zip file to AWS
and notify about the new code version.
With the code updated,
we can also test our Lambda function
using the AWS CLI wrapper script.
We're gonna call scripts/test
and see what happens.
We enter our username and password
and we get a greeting as expected.
Sweet!
But how did this work?
When we deploy the Lambda function to AWS,
the AWS Lambda Runtime engine
will control the program's life cycle.
The Lambda polls
the runtime engine for work,
and if such work is not available,
the compute resource will be hibernated
until work is available.
The iOS application,
command line tool or any other client
can use an HTTP call,
using URLSession or otherwise,
to interact with the Lambda.
To make the Lambda function available
as an HTTP endpoint,
you can use AWS API Gateway
which routes every request it receives
to the Lambda function queue.
There are also other ways
to invoke Lambda functions,
such as event based triggers,
which are covered by AWS's documentation.
In order to make all this possible,
we needed to create
two main pieces of technology.
The first part was getting Swift
to run on Amazon Linux,
a flavor of CentOS.
Starting May 2020,
Swift.org has begun publishing
Swift toolchains
for building and running Swift programs
on Amazon Linux 2.
The toolchain is useful in the context
of many AWS compute services,
including EC2 and AWS Lambda.
The second part was building
a Swift Lambda runtime library,
an implementation
of the AWS Lambda Runtime API.
The library provides a multitier API
that allows building
a range of serverless functions,
from quick and simple closures
to complex and performance sensitive
event handlers.
A program's life cycle is managed
by a lifecycle loop
provided as part of the library.
The program is designed
to serve traffic forever,
or until the process is terminated
by the AWS platform.
Long-lived processes
can serve traffic faster
by employing caching techniques
such as caching the connection.
The library also manages a state machine
representing the various stages
of the Lambda execution.
Polling work
from the runtime engine queue,
submitting the work
to the user provided function,
and submitting the results
back to the runtime engine.
An asynchronous HTTP client
that is fine tuned for performance
in the AWS Lambda Runtime context
is embedded in the library,
and compiling the Lambda program
produces an executable
that links the user provided code
with the underlying runtime library
and the Swift dependencies.
And they can be linked together
statically or dynamically,
depending on the need.
AWS Lambda can then be configured
to run as many copies
of the serverless functions as required,
and this elasticity means
that this simple programming model
can be scaled up
to meet even significant demand.
This also means that the serverless
functions are designed to be stateless
and care needs to be taken
to avoid global mutable state
or holding on to memory
for longer than required.
Finally, the runtime library
includes extensible integration points
to trigger serverless functions
based on events.
For example,
events from AWS systems
like S3, SQS and SNS,
triggers based on HTTP endpoints
exposed via API Gateway,
or custom events
that can be added by the user.
To wrap up, serverless functions
are a great way to extend
your iOS, macOS, watchOS, tvOS
or any other client applications
to the cloud.
Swift is a perfect match
for serverless functions.
It is fast, safe
and uses only little resources.
The tools you need to build, debug
and run Swift based serverless functions
are available today.
So, what are you waiting for?
Go build awesome things.
Thank you for listening, and enjoy WWDC.