Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name's Brian
and I'm an engineer
on the Apple Education team.
Today I'll be talking about what Apple's
been up to this year in education.
For more than 40 years
Apple's been working with educators
to help them create rich
and meaningful learning experiences.
More recently,
Apple's provided technologies
to support not just students and teachers,
but IT and school administrators as well.
And, of course,
none of this would be possible
without the apps and content
that developers provide.
Since we launched the App Store,
developers like you have built
thousands of amazing educational apps
for the iPhone, the iPad and the Mac.
We're committed to working with you
to provide the best
educational experiences for everyone.
With that in mind,
let's look at how education apps
fit into the Apple ecosystem.
There's a lot to cover.
So, I'll spend a few minutes
on the developer opportunities
in each of these areas.
Let's start with Schoolwork.
Schoolwork makes it easy for teachers
to share materials,
assign activities
and track student progress.
The latest version of Schoolwork
introduces a brand-new design.
It's now even easier to switch
between Handouts and Student views.
This is the App Activity Chooser.
It's where teachers
can assign the Activities
from your ClassKit enabled apps
to a Handout.
The Chooser now shows
richer metadata for your Activities
with the addition of thumbnails
and summary info.
Be sure to update your app to use
the new metadata fields in ClassKit.
The new Handout view
provides insights into overall class
and individual student progress.
This view is driven by the Progress data
that your app provides.
As you can see here, your app can report
time spent, percentage complete
and quiz scores.
Please see the ClassKit documentation
for a complete list
of status reporting options.
Schoolwork 2.0 has an all new design,
Handout Library and Handout detail view.
The Detail view is great for showing
progress from your app's Activities.
And there's also support
for the new metadata fields,
so you can show off the content
like never before.
If you want your app
to work well with Schoolwork,
you'll need to adopt
the ClassKit Framework.
Once you do, be sure to include
all the metadata that you can
and report any progress
on Activities back to ClassKit.
Schoolwork helps students
and teachers easily tap into
the ecosystem of apps that you create.
How do you do that?
You do it with ClassKit.
Let's dig into
the latest ClassKit details.
As you saw in Schoolwork,
ClassKit is a framework for iOS
that lets your app content
be assigned to a student.
And your app can then report progress
back to Schoolwork.
Student data is very sensitive,
and that's why ClassKit
only reports Activities
that have been assigned in a Handout.
And it's only available to certain people,
like the student's teacher.
Progress on any Activities
that weren't assigned
will not be shared or displayed.
For example, if a teacher
gives a student the reading assignment
"Fun with Science" in Apple Books,
the time spent and reading progress
will be reported for that item.
If that student then also reads
"Basic Arithmetic,"
no status will be reported
because that was not assigned
in a Handout.
In order for app Activities
to be displayed in the Activity Chooser,
your app must first publish that data
to ClassKit as a CLSContext.
Typically, this happens
after a teacher downloads your app
and browses to an Activity.
This works great for teachers that
are already familiar with your content,
and using your app,
but what about those that aren't?
That's why today we're introducing
something new for Schoolwork
called the ClassKit Catalog API.
The ClassKit Catalog is a central store
of your app's public Activities.
Assigning Activities from your app
is no longer limited
to the local context store.
Now the only requirement will be
that your app is installed
and all of your Activities
will be available from the Catalog.
Using a web API,
you can publish your Activities
and they will be available
from the Activity Chooser.
The Catalog also includes
new metadata fields
that'll make it easier for teachers
to find your content.
You can learn more
about working with ClassKit
and the new ClassKit Catalog API,
by checking out this year's session
"What's New in ClassKit."
To get the most from ClassKit, make sure
to report progress from your Activities.
Include the thumbnails
and other improved metadata,
and submit your data
to the ClassKit Catalog.
Schoolwork, ClassKit
and the new ClassKit Catalog API
are just the beginning
of what we have for you today.
Let's take a look at the service that brings
all of our educational apps together.
Apple School Manager,
our simple, web-based portal
for schools to manage accounts,
devices, and content,
all from one place.
With Apple School Manager,
IT administrators
can easily create classes
and manage login credentials
for teachers and students.
There are also several options
for streamlining this integration
with Student Information Systems, SFTP,
and federated authentication
using Microsoft Active Directory.
Enrolling devices
into Mobile Device Management is easy
and you don't have to physically
touch devices before distributing them.
Check out the session
"What's New in Managing Apple Devices"
to learn more about Apple School Manager.
The Apps and Books section
is where administrators
can purchase content for their schools.
As a developer, you'll want to make sure
it's easy to purchase
and deploy your applications.
To find out more about
how best to sell your app
to schools and businesses,
check out the 2019 session
"App Distribution -
From Ad-hoc to Enterprise."
Apple School Manager
is a great way to connect your school
to both Apple's ecosystem
of products and services
as well as the thousands
of educational third-party apps
for the iPad, the iPhone and the Mac.
And this year, it all works together.
Apple School Manager,
Schoolwork, and Classroom
are more integrated than ever.
Now classes created
in Apple School Manager
are automatically available
in both Classroom and Schoolwork.
And updates from Apple School Manager
are synced down as well.
When students sign in
with their Managed Apple ID,
they will automatically
show up in Classroom,
and they can see their Schoolwork classes.
In addition to better integration
with Apple School Manager,
Classroom is getting
a number of new features too.
With Classroom, teachers
can easily launch your app
on every student's iPad at the same time.
Or launch a different app
for each group of students.
Teachers can also easily see
what students are up to
by viewing their iPad screens
and even take a closer look
using pinch to zoom,
which is new this spring.
And if your app is ClassKit enabled,
teachers can even launch your app
with the right Activity already open.
If you're a teacher, and you create
your class in Classroom,
you start your class
and invite your students to join
with a four-digit code.
Now you can just tap
the AirPlay Class Code button,
and all your class info
is instantly shared
with your students on your Apple TV.
New this year, classes created
using Apple School Manager
and Schoolwork will now show up
instantly in Classroom.
This fall, teachers will also be able
to create their own classes in Classroom
for use in Apple School Manager
and Schoolwork.
Classroom added
a bunch of new features this year
with Apple School Manager
class integration,
AirPlay class invitations
and pinch to zoom.
You'll want to make sure
that your app is ClassKit enabled
to get the most
from Classroom integration.
Now that we've covered
classroom management,
how about the student login experience?
That brings us to Shared iPad.
With Shared iPad, students
can quickly log into an iPad
and use it as if it were their own device.
Your app should behave on a Shared iPad
just like it would on a personal device,
except the data
must be synced from the cloud.
When a student signs into a Shared iPad,
you shouldn't expect that
any of that user's data to be present,
as the data may not be available
after the student logs out.
And new this fall, Shared iPad
will offer Temporary Session.
Shared iPad Temporary Session
enables schools to deploy devices
with standard configurations that students
can use without sign-in credentials.
Imagine that you're a student
on your first day at a new school
and your accounts aren't ready yet.
With Temporary Session, you can still
grab an iPad and join the class.
When you sign out, all the data created
during that session will be deleted.
With Temporary Session,
no Apple ID is required to sign in
and no data is retained
after the end of the session.
By default, Temporary Session
is turned on.
If you're an MDM developer,
we've introduced
a new supervised restriction
for customers to choose to opt out
of using Temporary Sessions.
Remember, for your app to provide
a good student experience,
all data must be synced from the cloud.
And when a student is done
with the Shared iPad and logs out,
your app needs to be ready
to sync in the background.
Using longLived CKOperations
and UIBackgroundTasks
will make this possible.
That brings us to the topic
that all students love, taking tests.
New in macOS this year
is the Automatic Assessment
Configuration Framework.
We introduced the ability
for iPads to be used
in standardized testing in 2016.
And we wanted to bring
this feature to the Mac as well.
The new Automatic Assessment
Configuration Framework
enables educational institutions
to leverage the power of the Mac,
while at the same time preventing students
from using features that could give them
an unfair advantage.
The Automatic Assessment
Configuration Framework
allows you to provide a secure environment
for your applications
to deliver tests to students.
The Framework is available on iOS,
macOS and supports Catalyst as well.
Test takers are locked
into the testing app
and features, such as Screen Sharing,
Universal Clipboard or Dictation
are automatically disabled
for the duration of the test.
To find out how your app
can take advantage
of the new Assessment Framework,
see this year's session,
"What's New in Assessment."
If you're developing a testing app
on iOS or the Mac,
you should consider adopting
the Assessment Framework.
You'll need to apply for a new entitlement,
so check out
the Automatic Assessment Configuration
documentation for more information.
On iOS, the old UIKit Assessment mode
has been deprecated,
so please be sure to switch
to the new framework.
Also on iOS, you can use
configuration options to customize
which system features
are available during testing.
And that's what's new
in Apple Education this year.
Now that you've heard
of all of our updates,
it's time to figure out where you fit in.
If you create apps
for use in the classroom,
you should be using ClassKit.
You'll want your app's content
to be easily available
for teachers to assign as Activities.
So be sure to submit all of your
app Activities to the ClassKit Catalog.
If you create apps for testing,
be sure to check out
this year's Assessment session
on how to deploy your app
on iOS and the Mac.
And all education apps should be ready
to work well on a Shared iPad.
Whether you make an MDM system
to help IT manage thousands of devices
or an app that helps
third graders study vocabulary,
every piece of technology
built by developers like you
creates a better learning environment
for future generations.