Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. Thank you for viewing
"Architecting for Subscriptions."
My name is Michael Gargas,
a technical advocate
on the App Store Commerce team,
and I'm excited to introduce
some new concepts
around how to build and maintain
a subscription service
on the Apple platform.
We want to structure this to be helpful
not just for business and engineering,
but also for your server-side teams
and data analysts.
Whether you've been offering
subscriptions within your app for years
or are just getting started,
this session will provide
valuable information
for constructing
your system's entitlement architecture.
From there, you'll see ways to build
or reconstruct your server-side systems
to take full advantage of the new features
which Apple will provide over time.
To build a successful
subscription platform,
it's important to understand
the journey a subscriber can take.
We can then define
subscription entitlement,
craft custom logic,
and put it all into practice by utilizing
an entitlement engine
to provide a tailored experience
for those subscribers.
So let's take a deeper look
at the subscriber journey
and the different complex states that can
result from different subscriber actions.
In the past, access may have been granted
based on one or two receipt fields,
such as product ID
and expiration date, determining:
Is this user or subscriber active or not?
As we've launched new features
like Billing Retry and Grace Period,
these combinations of receipt fields
have become more and more complex,
and understanding them requires
deep knowledge of the app receipt itself.
Let's take a look at an example
subscription in a calendar view.
Here, we have a one-month product
which was purchased on May 1st.
Let's take a deeper look
and see how different subscriber actions
can affect subscriber states.
For a basic subscription
that was purchased on May 1st,
Apple will send you, the developer,
a server-to-server notification
signifying an initial buy has taken place.
If no subsequent actions are taken
by the subscriber,
we will continue to renew the subscription
on the 1st moving forward.
But let's say that the subscriber elects
to cancel their subscription.
Here, we see the example subscription
purchased again on the 1st.
However, the subscriber has navigated
to the App Store
Manage Subscription setting
and elected to cancel.
It's at this point that Apple
will send you, the developer,
a server-to-server notification
letting you know that that subscriber
has disabled their auto-renewal status.
If no subsequent actions are taken,
this user will voluntarily churn
from your subscription product.
This will be signified via the
expires_date and expiration_intent fields
in the receipt response.
In this example,
what if Apple is unsuccessful in charging
the user's card for a subsequent renewal?
Here again, we see
the initial buy notification on the 1st,
but Apple was unsuccessful
in charging the card
on the subsequent anniversary date.
The user, however, navigated to the
App Store's Payment Information settings
and updated their payment method on file.
It's at this point that Apple
will deliver you, the developer,
a server-to-server notification signifying
that the subscriber has renewed,
and we will continue to renew that
subscriber on the 15th moving forward.
However, what if you, as a developer,
have Grace Period enabled?
In this example, again we see
the subscription purchased on the 1st,
and we were unable to renew the card
on the subsequent renewal date.
However, with Grace Period enabled,
any recoveries which happen
within a 16-day period
will keep billing date continuity.
So as you can see,
Apple will continue to renew
that subscriber on the 1st moving forward.
It's important to understand
that each subscriber journey is unique.
It's for this reason that we need
to understand all of the receipt fields,
the signals Apple sends
as a result of customer actions
and the different states
that may be a result
of those specific customer actions.
These examples illustrate how quickly
a subscription state
becomes more than active versus inactive.
Basic actions like upgrading
or downgrading, and even crossgrading,
and other complex billing states,
like Billing Retry and Grace Period,
also present messaging opportunities
or actions
which can help provide
a better customer experience,
reduce churn and maximize conversion.
In previous sessions, we've highlighted
a wide range of tools and features
that can be used to enhance
your subscription service.
Whether it's the StoreKit framework
that helps process payments,
server-to-server notifications
or even enhanced receipt data,
each of these lay the groundwork for
building an engaging subscription service
on the Apple platform.
I highly recommend that you check out
these additional sessions
to ensure you are up-to-date
on all the existing and new features
which will be available for integration
in your applications.
So in order to respond
to customer actions accurately,
it's imperative that we take
a deep dive into the subscriber state.
Here we see that identifying
the subscriber state
is a key step in the purchase process.
This helps you, the developer,
best understand the experience that
you want to provide to your end users.
Whether it's presenting
a subscription offer
or un-entitling service for the user
because they've been refunded,
understanding the subscription state
is key.
When we think about subscription state,
it's important to know
where the subscriber has been,
where they are at, and what event
may take place in the future.
Deep knowledge of the data
within the app receipt
is key to understanding
subscription states.
Each renewal event in the receipt is
a static entry
showing that subscriber's state
at that moment in time.
State can then be inferred
by looking at combinations
of these different receipt field values.
Using these states, you can then decide to
tailor your experience for that subscriber
and take any relevant actions
within the app experience.
Taking a deeper look, it is obvious that
there are many different states
which a subscriber can land in.
These states are a combination
of different receipt values,
such as an expires-date value
being set in the future
and auto-renew status being a value of
one, representing active, auto-renew on.
For each of these states,
we've also defined relevant substates
to show what type of offer
the user is consuming,
such as a free trial
or even a subscription offer.
Now that we've established
a better understanding
of the complexity behind
subscriber state and substate,
let's see how these can manifest
in the real world for subscribers
and what relevant type of actions
or messaging
you, as a developer,
may want to take as a result.
So let's walk through these five different
examples of complex states
and the resulting actions to take.
When looking at a subscriber
and trying to decipher the state,
we have to look at
the most recent receipt data.
At the surface, we may only see "active"
if we're only looking at expiration date.
When looking at a subscriber state
and trying to decipher that state,
you, as a developer, have to look at
the most recent receipt data.
On the surface, you may just see "active"
if only the expiration date is used.
However, if we look even just
a little bit deeper,
we can see an opportunity
for a retention subscription offer
based on that user's auto-renewal status
and the current subscription product.
In this case, the subscriber is currently
on a subscription offer.
As a developer,
you may want to attempt to retain them
with a follow-up subscription offer.
Using that same logic,
if we dive deeper here,
we can see a user who has expired,
but is in actuality
in a Billing Retry state,
signifying that we, Apple,
are still attempting to collect payment
for a subscription renewal.
In this example, as a developer,
you may want to surface a persistent
banner which deep links the subscriber
to the App Store's account
to update their payment information.
When using the Grace Period example,
we can see another opportunity
to identify the user is in a grace period
via these specific receipt fields,
and offer maybe a countdown
of days remaining for available service.
This can also deep link
to that subscriber's payment information
in the App Store
so that they're able to update
and recover their subscription.
Another opportunity to provide
a tailored experience
is to win back users
who have already expired.
In this example, we're looking
to see how the user expired,
what product
they were initially subscribed to,
and providing a push notification
merchandising a current win-back
marketing offer.
It's important to note that
this push notification
will still need to deep link that user
to an appropriate payment screen
within your application.
And lastly, as a developer, you may want
to provide subscribers a better experience
by merchandising potential
upgrade opportunities.
In this example, you may notice
the user has purchased a monthly product
and renewed for multiple
consecutive periods.
By offering an upgrade
to an annual subscription,
you can provide a discount
and reward your most loyal subscribers.
Now we have identified five states
and substates,
but as you can see, there isn't just
one state for active versus inactive.
There are many more potential outcomes
based on subscriber actions.
Understanding this is a key factor
in defining subscription entitlement.
To walk you through
the details of entitlement,
I'd love to welcome my colleague Garrett.
Hi, my name is Garrett Cox, and I'm
a solutions engineer for the App Store.
Michael described the subscriber journey,
and as we've seen,
there are many potential states
a subscriber can encounter.
The entitlement process needs
to account for these potential states.
Let's start by defining the components
that make up subscription entitlement.
While access to content is the fundamental
basis of subscription entitlement,
the scope of access
will inevitably be broad.
Rather than just unlock content,
access might vary
based on geographical availability,
billing states
and unique levels of service.
Before we present products to the user,
we must determine whether they qualify.
This also applies to the upgrade
and downgrade options we might present.
How and when you display products
changes based on the user's eligibility
for discounted pricing
like free trials or offers.
The App Store determines
certain eligibility criteria,
such as for free trials,
but you can control eligibility
for subscription offers
based on your business needs.
Lastly, your messaging to the user
can be more meaningful
than simply communicating
an expiration date.
A tailored experience means
timely communication
of promotional messaging
or critical billing issues
which change throughout
the subscriber journey.
Given this definition
of subscription entitlement,
you're going to need to build
the server-side logic
which digests all of the subscription data
encompassing the subscriber journey.
For now, we'll be referring to this
as the entitlement engine.
This digested data is then used to
calculate the user's service entitlement.
The engine needs to support changes
to your subscription offering
as well as the billing states
a user might encounter.
So more specifically, our engine takes
receipt data and any other app insights
to calculate and respond
with correct entitlement info.
So before I walk through how we,
as subscription developers,
actually need to code
this entitlement engine,
I want to let you know that we will be
providing sample code in Node.js
in an article with this session
to represent the parts of this process
and help you get started
in building your entitlement engine.
For now, I'll be addressing these steps
as if we're building
this entitlement engine together.
Here's a more detailed overview
of what the entitlement process
looks like using our engine.
Subscription data, including receipts
and server notifications,
are passed into the engine.
The output is a simplified JSON payload
that you use to entitle service
and update your user database.
The app receipt is our source of truth
for inspecting transactional data,
so it's only fitting
our first step is to validate
the authenticity of each receipt.
This phase should include fetching
the newest receipt info
from the App Store's
verifyReceipt end point
if the receipt we are starting with
is out-of-date.
We want to ensure
we're making entitlement decisions
using up-to-date information
that isn't outdated.
Optionally, we can fetch from our systems
other relevant data or contextual details
unique to the subscriber
not found in the receipt.
If you're providing a subscription
across multiple apps or platforms,
this phase should include passing in
the subscriber's status
that exists outside of the app receipt
to ensure they aren't locked out
or presented with another subscription
to purchase.
Next, we'll synthesize the relevant data
we have gathered.
This phase is really
the powerhouse of the engine
because we want to condense
and convert the information we have
into actionable insight.
Given that information is interspersed
across multiple arrays and fields
in the in-app receipt,
like the latest_receipt_info array
and the pending_renewal_info array,
we want this process to thoroughly check
all of the relevant fields
that shape entitlement.
We want our logic to iterate
over the data,
building data objects that we will
eventually include in our final response.
Our focus here is to produce
and attach any key details
that will aid in determining where
in the subscriber journey a user might be.
So for example, we'll want to organize
the response by subscription product
and include essential information.
This key data is valuable
to any subscription service
like product ID, trial consumption
or expiration date.
We'll revisit the entitlement code
for now.
Additionally we can add insights
outside of the receipt
that still might influence
the entitlement process.
For example, hours watched
or an upcoming event
the subscriber might be interested in.
We've now condensed the data down
to the meaningful details
to distinguish one unique cohort
of subscribers from another.
At first the cohorts should be defined
to cover all the general subscription
billing states.
These separate cohorts
of subscriber states
will allow us to craft unique experiences
based on the location of the subscriber
in the journey.
As we organize the subscriber journey
into varying states,
we want to distinguish subscribers
within the states Michael enumerated.
So for this example, I'm simply assigning
unique values to each of those states.
These could be modified or enhanced
to fit the needs of your subscription.
And then I also do the same
with the substates
to add uniqueness
to the specific subscription products
by assigning them a decimal value.
This way, the combination of the two
can be paired together to represent
a range of cohorts.
For a simple approach,
the positive values represent cases
where we would unlock access,
and the negative values
represent subscription states
where the service wouldn't be provided
for a given product ID.
Even though we define generic access
with positive and negative values,
we can enhance the entitlement process
to pay attention to unique cohorts.
Combining these values,
we now have an entitlement code
to represent the state of a product.
We can send this value to the client
or store it server-side.
The code can be treated as a simple signal
to unlock the service
since it is positive.
Or in this example, the value
could be handled as a custom action
since its unique insight
represents an active subscriber
that has disabled auto-renew
during the free trial period.
Now that we've identified the cohort
of a subscriber,
we'll use that to determine
the entitlement info we want to include.
In this phase, we focus on generating
and attaching added data
that suits the unique cohort
of the subscriber.
This phase can also include
taking specific business actions
that apply to each unique cohort.
Here's how.
We built our response object
to contain the essential keys
we'll need for entitlement
and populated those keys with the values
pertaining to subscription entitlement.
We can take this representation
and, with a few statements,
tailor the entitlement
to cover complex states
like the ones Michael had mentioned.
So for the retention example where
the subscriber just disabled auto-renew...
an if statement including the entitlement
code 4.0 and the specific product
can then be used to attach
a retention message or even an offer.
The nuanced state of Grace Period
Michael mentioned
must be used to unlock service
throughout the grace period,
but since we already have defined
this unique code,
we can use that state to add logic
covering the more niche action
to prompt the user to update
their billing information
in order to prevent
unwanted loss of service.
And since Grace Period is slightly
different than Billing Retry,
we can have a similar goal
of updating billing information
while providing limited access instead.
In this example,
we can use the entitlement info
to present a custom offer to the user
that has opted to cancel service.
Even for our loyal subscribers,
we can use this entitlement code,
the number of renewals
and the subscription group ID,
to suggest upgrading to an annual product.
So we've made it to the final step
and generated
all the necessary entitlement info.
We want to route this data
to update our database
so it accurately is synced
and representing the state of the user.
And if it was a user's device that
was requesting this entitlement data,
we should send this calculated data back
securely to the device.
Consider adding something
like a JSON Web Signature
to prove the data came from your server.
We just dove deep into crafting
the entitlement engine logic,
so now let's zoom out some
and get a sense of how to put the engine
to use within our system's architecture.
Let's keep in mind some essentials.
A highly available entitlement engine
will allow us to compute and respond
with the latest entitlement details
the moment a change happens.
This availability, paired with the
coverage of all the subscription states,
ensures we accurately entitle subscribers
with the proper experience.
While responding with accuracy
is the mission,
we want to position this process to be
fail-safe from unexpected circumstances.
And lastly, we've built our engine
in a manner
that we can leave room
to support future features
or changes to our subscription business
that may happen later on.
We've covered how to build the engine
to validate, authenticate
and properly entitle
for the subscription experience.
Here's an overview on how we can maximize
the engine in our server architecture.
This approach is really powerful,
even when just getting started
with subscriptions.
With just a basic implementation
that isn't using notifications or storage,
we can still support many of the
subscription features Apple has to offer,
like subscription offers.
Also, having this engine
running server-side
means any errors or updates
in our entitlement logic
can be fixed, tested with receipts
or mocked receipt data
and then quickly deployed.
That way, new inbound requests
will resolve to properly entitle access
without relying on a client update.
The catch here is that we need the devices
to be sending the receipts
to be processed in each request.
Without storing the receipt data,
we also won't have a way to support web
or other platforms,
but this approach is a promising start
and even a reasonable fallback
in the event that we have
some problems with our storage
or for some reason missed processing
App Store notifications.
But we can easily iterate from here.
By adding persistent storage,
it now becomes a matter of routing
the resulting entitlement info
and receipt data
to the persistent storage.
Getting over that hurdle means
we can then grant access
via the web and off-platform.
But at this point,
we should add an end point
to receive and process
the App Store Server notifications.
Our server can then be notified
the moment a change is made
to the subscription status
rather than status polling
the verifyReceipt end point.
With this implementation, we also have
multiple ways to support failure.
If notifications are missed
or not processed,
use the persistent storage receipt data
to maintain accuracy.
Even if our storage data is inaccurate,
we can update our entitlement logic.
That way we can route the data
directly to the entitlement engine
and entitle service until we resolve
the problems with our storage.
So if there's anything you take away
from this session,
it should be that building
a responsive entitlement process
will allow you to tailor to the complexity
of the subscriber experience.
From there you can then iterate
to better support the subscriber journey.
Thank you for attending this session,
and I hope you enjoy the rest of WWDC.