Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello.
Welcome to "Meet Scribble for iPad."
My name is Daniel Gobera.
I'm an engineer
in the Pencil and Paper team.
And I'll be joined later
by my colleague, Evan Long.
Scribble is a fantastic new way
of entering text on iPad
using Apple Pencil
through handwriting recognition.
In this video, we'll see an overview
on how Scribble works.
We'll look at the aspects that make
a great writing experience.
We'll take a tour of the APIs
that support Scribble,
and finally, we'll see some examples
on how to customize
the behavior of Scribble
so you're getting the best possible
experience in your app.
When bringing Scribble to the iPad,
we wanted to do it in a big way.
Centered around the Apple Pencil,
Scribble is deeply integrated
into the system,
which means you can just write directly
into any text field,
and not on a separate writing area.
Transcription happens on the fly
as you write.
There are no modes, no tapping.
You just write.
Scribble on iPadOS
is part of the system experience,
which means it's available
to all apps by default,
the same way the keyboard is.
It works anywhere
where you can enter text.
It is built on top of a best-in-class
handwriting recognition engine
that is fast, it's incredibly accurate,
and runs entirely on the device,
so it's always available
and completely private.
It recognizes handwriting in English,
Simplified and Traditional Chinese
and Cantonese.
So, let's see an overview of the aspects
that make up a great writing experience.
This will give you a set of guidelines
that you can use
to make sure your app is getting the best
possible experience with Scribble.
The first key aspect
is that Scribble makes text input
feel fluid and effortless.
Here we see an example
of searching in Maps.
Notice how you can just
start writing directly
without tapping on the field first.
If you notice that there are
any fields in your app
that don't accept
Scribble writing directly
and it's necessary to tap on them first,
you should adopt the APIs
that we're gonna show a little bit later.
Scribble is direct,
meaning that the position of the Pencil
tells the system
where the text should get inserted.
We see an example here of filling out
a form with multiple fields in Safari,
and notice how you can effortlessly jump
from field to field.
The strokes are ephemeral,
as the transcription happens on the fly
as you write.
Makes it feel almost like
you're dictating with motion.
The second design principle
is consistency.
Scribble needs to work everywhere where
you would expect to be able to enter text.
Here we see an example in Reminders,
where every item on the list
contains text that you can normally edit,
so naturally you can just start writing
on any of them.
Now, we noticed that
some people found it natural
to write on the blank area below the list
to create a new entry.
This is not normally a text input view,
so Reminders adopted the API,
that we'll describe a little bit later,
to allow writing in this area.
And this created a great new way
of adding a new reminder very easily.
There's also a small set
of editing gestures
that people need to learn only once,
and they work exactly the same anywhere
where you can edit text with Scribble.
We can see an example
when composing an e-mail.
You can draw a horizontal line
to select text
and perform the normal
text editing actions.
You can also scratch out some text
that you want to delete.
This all adds up to create a reliable
and familiar interaction model.
Our final design principle
is Pencil friendliness.
The iOS user interface
was designed primarily for Touch,
and it works really, really well
for Pencil input.
But you'll notice a few places
where we made some adjustments,
and I want to highlight some of them.
Let's start with reducing distractions.
A good example we see here
is placeholders in text fields.
When you start writing into a field
that has a placeholder,
it disappears
to avoid overlapping the strokes,
and that keeps the handwriting readable.
You get this behavior for free
with Standard Text Controls.
Stable layout means that the text field
and the text inside
should not move or scroll
while you're writing.
As an example, you might know
that some search fields
tend to shift their position
when they become focused.
This is great for a keyboard,
but it can be a problem when you're trying
to write into it with your Pencil.
So Scribble detects when you're writing
on a search field that moves,
and it waits for you to make a pause
before making it first responder
and inserting the text.
If you use the standard search controller,
you get this behavior for free.
But if you have a custom field
with a similar shifting animation,
you need to tell Scribble about this,
and you can request delaying
focusing of the field
to adopt the same behavior.
It's also really important that
there's always enough space to write.
A good example is the Messages app.
You'll notice that the message field
is near the corner of the screen,
so there's really not a lot of space
to write more than a few words.
So Messages detects
that you're using Scribble,
and it adjusts the size of the field
so it's much more comfortable to write -
even a longer sentence.
We know many apps have a similar layout,
especially messaging apps,
and we recommend
that you apply the same behavior
using the API
that we'll show a little bit later.
So let's see an overview of the APIs
that support Scribble,
some existing ones and some new ones.
Scribble relies on
existing Text Input APIs from iOS:
Standard Text Controls
and the UIKit Text Input infrastructure.
There's also two new APIs
that we're introducing in iOS 14
that allow customizing
the behavior of Scribble.
Let's talk about
the existing Text Input APIs first.
Standard Text Controls
are things like text fields, text views,
and search fields
that you can get from UIKit.
It also includes
standard editable web content
and forms in web pages through WebKit.
The great news is that
all of these work out of the box,
and they work really well with Scribble.
We recommend that you stick to these
as much as possible,
and they're highly customizable
to adapt to the look and feel of your app.
Now, it's worth noting that password fields
are not supported by Scribble,
because the recommended way
of entering passwords is through AutoFill.
Next is the UIKit Text Input
infrastructure.
If you have a custom
text editing experience,
there's a set of protocols
that you must implement
for your view to work with the keyboard
and with the iOS text input system.
Scribble relies on these same APIs
to talk to your text view.
In particular,
it's really important to have
a very good and complete implementation
of UITextInput.
This is how Scribble gets information
about the text content, the selection,
and how it's gonna make changes
to the text in your view.
We also recommend that you use
UITextInteraction
to get the standard cursor
and selection UI from the system,
so you don't have to implement your own.
If you're interested in more details
about these topics,
check out these great talks
from previous WWDC 2012 and 2017.
And now Evan's gonna give us an overview
on how to use the new APIs
to customize the behavior of Scribble
in your app.
Thank you, Daniel.
As Daniel mentioned,
when using standard UIKit text controls,
Scribble will just work.
But there are cases that may require
customizing the Scribble experience.
And to support those customizations,
we've introduced UIScribbleInteraction
and UIIndirectScribbleInteraction
in iOS 14.
First, UIScribbleInteraction.
Interactions are added to views.
Here, we've added UIScribbleInteraction
to a text field.
The interaction has a delegate,
and this delegate is where an app
can customize the Scribble experience.
For example,
disabling Scribble on the view,
delaying that view
from becoming first responder
until handwriting has momentarily paused,
or simply being informed
when Scribble handwriting begins or ends.
Now let's go through some practical cases
of how to use UIScribbleInteraction.
Some apps have added
in-line completion fields.
For example, Spotlight's search field.
This works well for keyboard input,
but would visually interfere
with handwriting.
By using a UIScribbleInteraction
previously added to this field,
it's possible to check if the view
is currently handling handwriting
and to update
the completion text accordingly.
In this case, simply by hiding it.
Now, in order to optimize UI layout
for Scribble,
we need to know if handwriting is likely,
or if it has completed.
One place to do this
is in the initial appearance
or setup of the UI.
Here, the app uses
UIScribbleInteraction's class property,
isPencilInputExpected.
When the property is true,
the app makes the text area
a little larger.
Rather than changing the UI
as part of view setup,
it is also possible to update it
after the user finishes writing
via the delegate method,
scribbleInteractionDidFinishWriting.
And it's worth noting,
in both of the approaches we just saw,
the UI is changed
while the user is not writing.
Some apps mix drawing and editable text.
In cases like this, it makes sense
to disable Scribble to allow drawing.
This can be done
with ScribbleInteraction's
shouldBeginAt delegate method,
by returning "false"
when the app is in a drawing mode.
Now let's look at
UIIndirectScribbleInteraction.
Just like UIScribbleInteraction,
UIIndirectScribbleInteraction
is also added to a view.
This interaction is used by Reminders
to allow writing below the list
of current reminders,
to create a new one.
This is also the interaction to use
for UI that would become editable
in response to a tap gesture.
And this interaction has a delegate.
This delegate provides
the system information about elements.
Elements are regions within the view
that can be written into.
There can be more than one element,
and the size of the elements can vary.
Let's take a closer look
at how UIIndirectScribbleInteraction
was used in our sample app.
Our sample app allows adding
an engraving to the back of a laptop.
This engraving element does not
become editable until it is tapped.
So I can tap with my finger,
a text field is installed
that becomes first responder,
and I can enter my name.
But if I remove the text,
and instead try to write
with Apple Pencil, it doesn't work.
That's because the engraving field alone
is not editable text input.
So let's add
a UIIndirectScribbleInteraction
to make this work with Scribble.
To surface the engraving field
as a writable area,
we install
a UIIndirectScribbleInteraction.
Next we need to implement
the delegate methods
describing the writable regions.
The first thing is to implement
the delegate method
that provides a list of identifiers
for all writable elements.
In this case, the engraving field
has a single writable region.
So we can call the completion handler
immediately with an identifier.
Next, we need to provide
the system information
about the element's location.
This is done with the frameForElement
delegate method.
It is possible to return smaller regions
that can be written into,
but we want to allow writing
into the whole view.
So, in this case,
we just return the bounds.
Next, we need to handle the case
where the system requests
we focus a responder
that supports text input.
This is done with
the focusElementIfNeeded method.
If a text field is not installed,
we'll create it
and add one to the view hierarchy.
Then we will ensure the installed
text field becomes first responder.
And finally, return that text field
with the completion handler.
The last piece of information
required by the system
is to indicate if a particular element
is focused.
We only have the one field in this case.
So if we have a field,
and it's first responder,
we'll return "true,"
otherwise, we'll always return "false."
Now if I try writing my name
in the engraving area,
I can do so.
So just to recap the APIs
that support Scribble:
Standard Text Controls in the system
from UIKit and WebKit will just work.
Scribble will also work
for custom text editors
that implement the text input protocols.
And to customize Scribble, this is done
via the two interactions added in iOS 14.
So grab your Pencil
and test your apps with Scribble.
See how you fit into the design principles
we covered earlier
and use Standard Text Controls
to get most of these behaviors for free.
And apply those Scribble interactions
for that final polish,
things like creating space to write
and allowing Scribble where expected.
Thank you for watching,
and we look forward to your app
Scribbling to success in iOS 14.