Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name's Saad,
and I'm from the RealityKit team.
Last year we released RealityKit,
an AR-focused 3D engine.
And since then, we've been working hard
to add many new features.
Today, I'm excited
to tell you about some of them.
To start off, we have Video Materials,
and Video Materials allow you
to use videos as materials in RealityKit.
Second is scene understanding
using the brand-new LiDAR sensor.
Thanks to ARKit processing data
from this new sensor,
we're able to bring the real world
into your virtual one.
As a result,
we have a huge set of features
that allow you to make your virtual
content interact with the real world.
Next is improved rendering debugging.
With rendering being such a huge pipeline,
we've added the ability to inspect
various properties
related to the rendering of your entity.
And the next two updates
are related to ARKit 4 integration.
ARKit has extended its face-tracking
support to work on more devices.
This means that now face anchors
will also work on more devices.
And ARKit has also added location anchors.
Location anchors
allow you to place AR content
at specific locations in the real world
using RealityKit.
With these new features in mind,
I want to now show you an experience
that you can now create using RealityKit.
This experience is built upon a problem
we face as developers every day.
When we code, what do we get?
We get bugs like this one.
And this is quite a simple-looking bug.
And in real life,
bugs are never this simple.
So, let's add some complexity to it
using our new Video Materials feature.
The bug now has a glowing body
as well as glittering in its eyes.
So what does a bug normally do?
Well, it hides.
As the bug runs to hide,
the tree occludes the bug.
But it can't hide forever.
You know you'll fix it.
But until then, you know
it's gonna try to run away from you.
And using scene understanding,
we can implement this logic.
Once you finally catch it,
you want to make sure you fix it for good.
So, let's pick it up and crush it...
into the pavement.
And because of scene understanding,
the bug disintegrates
when it collides against the real world.
And that's it for the experience.
Now let's take a deep dive into these
new features and see how you can use them.
We'll start with Video Materials.
We saw from the experience
that Video Materials
were used to give the bug a glowing effect
as well as glittering in its eyes.
Now let's have a look at the video.
On the left, you can see the video
associated with the texture on the bug.
You can see how the eyes map on,
and you can also see
how we're able to share
one portion of the texture for both eyes.
You can also see
how the body is mapped on.
As the glow pulses in the texture,
you can see it pulse through the body.
So in a nutshell,
Video Materials allow you to have textures
that change over time.
They get these textures from a video.
You can use this for a lot of things.
You can use it
to simulate the glow effect you saw.
You can also use it
to provide video instructions.
Simply create a plane
and map a video onto it.
You can even combine ARKit image anchors
with Video Materials
to bring images to life.
But that's not all.
Video Materials also play audio.
Spatialized audio.
When you apply a video material
onto an entity,
that entity becomes a spatialized
audio source for your video.
Spatialized audio is when the sound source
acts as if it's emitted
from a specific location.
In this case, from the entity.
This helps build
a more immersive experience.
Now, because all of this is done
under the hood,
when you apply the material,
you don't have to do extra work
like synchronization
or doing your own manual audio playback.
So now that you know what they are,
how do we use them?
The flow is quite simple.
First, we need to load the video.
RealityKit leverages the power
of AVFoundation's AVPlayer
to use as a video source.
You load the video using AVFoundation
and create an AVPlayer object.
Once you have an AVPlayer object, you can
then use it to create a video material.
This video material is just like
any other RealityKit material.
You can assign it on any entity
that you want to use it on.
So let's see how these steps map to code.
First,
we use AVFoundation to load the video.
Next, we create a VideoMaterial
using an AVPlayer object
and assign it to the bugEntity.
Once we've assigned the material,
we can then play the video.
Now, video can be controlled
as you would through AVPlayer,
and this is quite a simple example
of video playback.
However, since RealityKit's Video Material
uses AVPlayer,
you get all of the great functionality
and features that AVFoundation brings.
For example,
you can use AVPlayer to directly play,
pause and seek inside your media.
This allows you to use a video atlas
instead of having one video per texture.
You can use AVPlayer properties
to trigger state transitions in your app.
For example, when your video finishes,
you can use this
to go to the next stage of your app.
You can use AVPlayerLooper
to play one video in a loop,
and you can use AVQueuePlayer
to sequentially play a queue of videos.
And lastly, you can even play remote media
served using HTTP Live Streaming.
If you want to learn more,
see the "Advances in AVFoundation" session
in WWDC 2016 for more information.
This concludes Video Materials.
To summarize,
Video Materials allow you to use videos
as a texture source
and spatial audio source.
Let's move on to our next big feature,
scene understanding.
Scene understanding has one main goal.
Its goal is to make virtual content
interact with the real world.
To achieve this, we want to bring
everything in the real world
into your virtual one.
So let's see how we can do this.
We start in the ARView.
The ARView has a list of settings
related to the real world
under the environment struct.
These settings configure
the background image,
environment-based lighting,
as well as spatial audio options.
And we consider the real world
to be part of your environment.
As a result, we've added
a new scene understanding option set.
This new option set lets you configure
how the real world interacts
with your virtual.
It has four options.
First, we have Occlusion.
This means real-world objects
occlude virtual objects.
Second is Receives lighting.
This allows virtual objects
to cast shadows on real-world surfaces.
Third is Physics.
This enables the act of virtual objects
physically interacting
with the real world.
And last but not least, we have Collision.
This enables the generation
of collision events
as well as the ability to ray cast
against the real world.
One thing to know: Receives lighting
automatically turns on Occlusion,
and likewise,
Physics automatically turns on Collision.
Let's have a look at these options
in a bit more detail.
We'll start with Occlusion.
On the left, without Occlusion,
you can see that the bug
is always visible.
On the right, with Occlusion,
the bug is hidden behind the tree.
You can see how Occlusion helps
with realism
by hiding virtual objects
behind real ones.
To use Occlusion,
simply add .occlusion
into your sceneUnderstanding.options.
Our next option was Receives lighting.
On the left, without Receives lighting,
the bug looks like it's floating
because of the lack of shadows.
And now on the right,
with Receives lighting,
the bug casts the shadow
and looks grounded.
To use shadows, like Occlusion,
simply add .receivesLighting
into your options set.
These new shadows are similar
to the shadows that you're used to seeing
on horizontally anchored objects.
However,
because we're using real-world surfaces,
you no longer have to anchor these objects
to horizontal planes.
This means that any entity
that you have in the virtual world
will cast a shadow onto the real world.
It's important to note, though,
that the shadows imitate
a light shining straight down.
This means you won't see shadows on walls.
For those shadows, you still have
to anchor your entity vertically.
We can now move on to our third option,
Physics.
Previously, for AR experiences,
you were just limited to using planes
or various primitives
to represent your world.
This is unrealistic because the real world
doesn't conform to these shapes.
Now,
because of scene understanding physics,
you can see
that when the bug disintegrates,
the small pieces bounce off the steps
and scatter all around.
To use Physics,
you add the .physics option
into your sceneUnderstanding.options set.
There's a couple of specifics
you should know, however.
First, we consider real-world objects
to be static, with infinite mass.
This means that they're not movable,
as you'd expect in real life.
Second,
these meshes are constantly updating.
This means that you should never
expect objects to stay still,
especially on nonplanar surfaces.
Third, the reconstructed mesh is limited
to regions where the user has scanned.
This means that if the user
has never scanned the floor,
there will be no floor in your scene,
and as a result,
objects will fall right through.
You should design your experience
to make sure that the user
has scanned the room before starting.
And fourth, the mesh is an approximation
of the real world.
While the Occlusion mask is very accurate,
the mesh for Physics is less so.
As a result, don't expect the mesh
to have super crisp edges,
as you can see in the image on the right.
Lastly, if you do use Physics,
collaborative sessions are not supported.
Collaborative sessions will still work,
just with the other scene understanding
options.
Let's now look at our last option,
Collision.
Collision is a bigger topic.
But before we get into that,
to use Collision,
similar to the previous three options,
just insert .collision
into your sceneUnderstanding.options.
The reason Collision is a bigger topic
is because it has two use cases.
The first is ray casting.
Ray casting is a super powerful tool.
You can use it to do a lot of things,
such as pathfinding,
initial object placement,
line-of-sight testing
and keeping things on meshes.
The next use case is collision events.
We want to do some action
when we detect a collision
between a real-world object
and a virtual one.
So let's recap.
Let's see how we used the two use cases
in our experience.
We'll start by looking at ray casting.
You can see how the bug stays on the tree
and finds different points to visit.
Ray casting allows us
to keep the bug on the tree
by ray casting from the body
towards the tree
to find the closest contact point.
And ray casting is also used to find
different points for the bug to visit.
And let's look at the next case,
collision events.
By using collision events,
we were able to detect when the bug
is tossed and hits the real world.
When it does, we make it disintegrate.
So now that we've seen these two use cases
and how they helped build the experience,
there's still one more thing
you need to know about using them.
Ray casting returns a list of entities,
and collision events happen
between two entities.
This means we need an entity, an entity
that corresponds to a real-world object.
As a result, we're introducing
the scene understanding entity.
A scene understanding entity
is just an entity,
an entity
that consists of various components.
It contains a Transform component,
a Collision component
and a Physics component,
and these are automatically added
based on your scene understanding options.
There's still one more component,
and that is
the SceneUnderstandingComponent.
The SceneUnderstandingComponent
is unique to a scene understanding entity.
It is what makes a scene understanding
entity a scene understanding entity.
When looking for a real-world object
in a collision event
or ray-casting results,
you simply need to find an entity
with this component.
And similarly, with this new component,
we have a new
HasSceneUnderstanding trait.
All scene understanding entities
will conform to this trait.
It's really important to realize
that these entities
are created and managed by RealityKit.
You should consider these entities
read-only
and not modify properties
on their components.
Doing so can result in undefined behavior.
So now that we have scene
understanding entities in our toolbox
and we know how to find them,
let's look at how we can use them in code
for the collision use cases we saw.
We'll start with ray-casting.
In this sample,
we'll look at implementing some simple
object avoidance for our bug entity.
We start by figuring out
where the bug is looking
and get a corresponding ray.
Once we have this ray,
we can then do a RealityKit ray cast.
The ray cast returns a list containing
both virtual and real-world entities.
We only want the real-world entities.
Thus, we filter using
the HasSceneUnderstanding trait.
And with these filtered results,
we know that the first entity
into the results
is the closest real-world object.
Then finally,
we can do some simple object avoidance
by looking at the distance to
the nearest object and taking an action.
Maybe we go right, maybe we go left.
So now let's move on
to another code example,
a code example using collision events.
In this sample, we'll look at implementing
something similar to the bug
disintegration we saw in the experience.
We start by subscribing
to collision events between all entities.
When we get a callback for a collision,
we need to figure out
if it was with a real-world object.
We need to see if either entity
is a sceneUnderstandingEntity
by using
the HasSceneUnderstanding trait.
If neither of these entities
conform to this trait,
then, well, we know that we don't have
a real-world collision.
If, however,
one entity does conform to this trait,
then we know that we have
a real-world collision
and the other entity is the bug.
We can then make the bug disintegrate
by doing an asset swap.
This leads to one question
that I want to discuss.
We can react when objects collide
against the real world,
but what if we don't want them
to collide at all?
And to do this,
we need to use collision filters.
And collision filters
need collision groups.
If we want objects not to collide
with the real world,
we need to filter them out using
the collision group for the real world.
And as a result,
we're introducing a new collision group
called SceneUnderstanding
for real-world objects.
To use this group,
set your collision filter
to include or not include
SceneUnderstanding
to filter the collision appropriately.
And because RealityKit manages
scene understanding entities,
it automatically sets
the collision groups on them,
so you don't have to manually do this.
That covers all of the collision-related
aspects of scene understanding.
Using the all of the scene understanding
features I talked about,
you can now create a great app.
However, once you start building your app,
you might run into some issues.
And then you're not sure if it's the mesh
that's the problem or your logic.
So to help with this, we've added
the ability to visualize the mesh.
Let's take a look.
Here you can see a video with
the debug mesh visualization turned on.
This shows us the raw real-world mesh.
The mesh is color-coded
by the distance away from the camera.
You can also see how this mesh
is constantly updating
and the reconstructed mesh
is an approximation of the real world.
You can see how the mesh is not crisp
at the edges of the stairs.
To enable this visualization,
add the .showSceneUnderstanding option
into the ARView's debug options.
The colors you saw in the video
are color-coded using the chart below.
You can see that the color
varies by distance,
and past five meters,
everything is colored white.
It's important to note that this option
shows you the raw real-world mesh.
If you want to see the physics mesh,
then you just turn on the regular physics
debug view that's already available.
And that covers everything
scene understanding.
As you can tell, there's a lot of cool
stuff you can do with scene understanding.
I want to summarize some key takeaways.
The first is the goal
of scene understanding.
The goal of scene understanding
is to make your virtual content
interact with the real world.
And one set of these interactions
is through occlusion and shadows.
Real-world objects will occlude
and receive shadows from virtual ones.
Another set of interactions
is through physics and collision.
Physics lets objects
physically interact with the real world.
Collision, on the other hand,
lets you know
when objects physically collide,
and it also enables you
to ray-cast against the real world.
Real-world objects have corresponding
scene understanding entities.
These entities can be identified
using the HasSeenUnderstanding trait.
It's important to remember
that these entities
are created and managed by RealityKit
and they should be considered read-only.
And lastly,
we have debug mesh visualization.
This allows you to view
the raw real-world mesh.
And that's it for scene understanding.
We can now move on
to our next major feature:
improved rendering debugging.
Rendering is a huge pipeline
with lots of small components.
This includes model loading,
material setup,
scene lighting, and much more.
And to help debug
rendering-related issues,
we've added the ability
to inspect various properties
related to the rendering of your entity.
Let me show you an example of what I mean
by looking at our bug.
Let's have a look
at its base color texture.
How about its normal map?
Or its texture coordinates?
So, we can see these properties,
but how do they actually help us?
They can help us because you can
look at normals and texture coordinates
to ensure that your model
was loaded correctly.
This is especially important
if you find a model off the Internet
and are having issues with its rendering.
Maybe the model was just bad.
If you're using a simple material
on an entity
and setting the base color, roughness
or metallic parameter
and things don't look right,
you can inspect those parameters
to verify that they are set correctly.
And finally,
you can use PBR-related outputs,
such as diffuse lighting received
or specular lighting received
to know how much to tweak
your material parameters.
Now, to visualize these properties,
we've added a new component,
the DebugModelComponent.
To enable the visualization of a property,
simply choose a property,
create a DebugModelComponent
using the property,
and then assign it to your entity.
You can choose
from a huge list of properties.
Currently, we have 16.
These can be grouped as vertex attributes,
material parameters and PBR outputs.
Finally, one last thing to note:
The visualization only applies
to the targeted entity
and is not inherited by its children.
USDz files may have multiple entities
with varying hierarchy.
As a result, you need to add the component
to each and every entity
that you want to inspect.
And that's it.
Hopefully, with this component
you're able to iterate and debug
rendering problems much faster.
That covers everything related
to improved rendering debugging.
We've also covered all of the features
that are RealityKit-specific.
Let's move on to our next section:
integration with ARKit 4.
ARKit 4 has many updates this year.
There's two updates
that relate to RealityKit.
The first is Face Tracking.
Support for Face Tracking
is now extended to devices
without a TrueDepth camera,
as long as they have
an A12 processor or later.
This includes new devices,
such as the iPhone SE.
As a RealityKit developer,
if you were using Face Anchors before,
whether you created them using code
or Reality Composer,
your applications should now work
without any changes.
The second ARKit feature
is Location Anchors.
Location Anchors lets you create anchors
using real-world coordinates.
ARKit takes these coordinates
and coverts them to locations
relative to your device.
This means that you can now place
AR content
at specific locations in the real world.
As a RealityKit developer,
to use Location Anchors,
you create an anchor entity
using a Location Anchor.
Any virtual content
that you anchor under this entity
will show at the specific location.
And creating an anchor entity
is also super simple.
Since ARKit's new ARGeoAnchor class
is just a subclass of ARAnchor,
you can call the already existing
anchor initializer
to create an anchor entity.
Now, one thing to note
is that ARKit also introduced
a new AR geotracking configuration
for Location Anchors.
And since this is not
a world tracking configuration,
you need to manually configure
and start a Location Anchor session
in the ARView.
This also means certain features,
like scene understanding,
that I just talked about, will not work.
If you want to learn more,
I suggest checking out
the "Introducing ARKit 4" talk.
It will go over
how to set up your session,
how to create anchors,
and how to use them with RealityKit.
And that summarizes the main things
you need to know about ARKit 4
and its integration with RealityKit
for iOS 14.
This also concludes all of the features
I want to talk to you about this year.
And there were a lot of them,
so I want to summarize
everything we've learned so far.
We started with Video Materials.
Video Materials allow you to use videos
as a texture and spatial
audio source on your entity.
This can be used for a lot of things,
such as sprite-like effects
or instructional videos.
Next, thanks to scene understanding,
using the brand new LiDAR sensor,
we're able to bring the real world
into your virtual one
through many ways, such as occlusion,
shadows and physics.
You can now leverage ray-casting
to implement smart character behavior
to have it react with the real world.
And you can also use collision events
to implement collision responses
when your objects collide
with the real world.
And then our next update was an improved
ability to debug rendering problems.
With our new DebugModelComponent,
you can inspect any
rendering-related property on your entity,
such as vertex attributes,
material parameters
and PBR-related outputs.
We then had ARKit-related integrations.
ARKit extended Face Tracking support
on devices without TrueDepth camera.
This also means Face Anchors
will work on a lot more devices,
like the new iPhone SE,
without requiring any code changes.
And finally, ARKit added Location Anchors.
Location Anchors allow you
to place AR content
at specific locations in the real world
using RealityKit.
And that concludes my talk.
Thank you for your time.
I can't wait to see
what incredible content
you will make using these new features.