Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everybody, and welcome to
"What's New in ResearchKit."
My name is Pariece McKinney,
and I'm a software engineer
on the health team.
Later in the talk, we'll also be joined
by my fellow colleague
and software engineer, Joey LaBarck.
Thank you for taking the time to join,
and we're extremely excited
to show you all the new updates
ResearchKit has to offer.
There's quite a bit to cover,
so let's jump right in.
In order to make things
easier to follow this year,
we created a ResearchKit sticker pack,
where each sticker corresponds to
a particular topic of this talk.
At the end of each topic,
we'll collect the sticker
for that particular subject
and slap it on the back of our laptop,
which is pretty empty at the moment.
Now that everyone knows
how to follow along,
let's get started with our first topic:
community updates.
Each year,
we're excited about the new apps
that take advantage of our frameworks
to advance health and learnings
in various health areas.
To name a few,
the Spirit Trial app built by Hello Thread
was created in support of a clinical trial
on advanced pancreatic cancer.
Also, CareEvolution and the NIH
launched the All of Us app
to speed up health research
and breakthroughs
by building a community
of a million or more people across the US
with the aim
to advance personalized medicine.
We've also seen apps
utilize our frameworks
to build high-quality apps very quickly
in response to COVID-19.
The Stanford First Responder app
aims to help first responders
navigate the challenges of COVID-19.
And the University of Nebraska
Medical Center 1-Check app
aims to provide real-time situational
awareness of COVID-19 to investigators.
Last year, Apple also announced
and released the Research app,
which heavily utilizes ResearchKit,
while paving the way
for conducting large-scale studies
all through your iPhone.
Last year, we also announced
that we would release
a newly redesigned website,
and we're proud to share
that website with you,
which launched in late 2019,
at researchandcare.org.
On our overview page,
you can read about the frameworks
and their capabilities and features
before diving in to create your own app.
If you navigate to the ResearchKit page,
you can find even more information
about the models it provides,
as well as case studies
that showcase amazing examples of studies
and programs built in the community,
like the one you see here.
We also announced
our new Investigator Support Program,
through which researchers
can submit proposals for Watches
to support their studies.
You can now read about that
on our website,
and learn how to reach out to us
if you're interested in the program.
And lastly, we welcome all of you
to reach out to us through our website
so that we can hear about
all the amazing work you all are doing.
Now that we've collected
our community update sticker,
let's move on to the next topic,
which is onboarding updates.
For the vast majority of study-based apps,
the onboarding views
are usually the first thing
your participants will see
and interact with.
Knowing this, it's extremely important
to convey exactly what the study is,
and what the participant should expect
if they decide to join.
As you can see here,
we've moved towards leaning on
the instruction-Steps capability
to support custom text and images
so that you can have complete control
over the content you wish to display.
Let's take a look at the code
to create this step.
After importing ResearchKit,
the first thing we'll do
is initialize the instruction-Step
and pass in a unique identifier.
After setting the title and detail-Text,
the last thing we have to do
is set the image property
to the heath_blocks image
seen in the previous slide.
In the second step of our onboarding flow,
we're using Instruction-Step again,
but this time,
we also incorporate body items,
which is an extremely useful feature
to further educate your participants.
In this example,
we use SF Symbols for our icons,
but it's important to note
that everyone watching this video
has access to these icons and more.
So, if you're interested,
feel free to download the SF Symbols app
to find the icons
that match your use case.
Let's take a look at the code
to create this step.
Much like the previous code slide,
we initialize the ORK-Instruction-Step
and pass in our unique identifier.
After setting our title property,
we also set our image property again,
but this time
we pass in an informed_consent image
seen in the slide before.
Next, we initialize our first body-Item,
making sure that we pass in an image
and that we set our body-Item-Style
to dot-image.
The last thing we have to do
is append our newly-created body-Item
to the body-Items array
that sits on the Instruction-Step.
Now let's take a look at an enhancement
we've made to our Web-View-Step.
Previously, presenting the user
with an overview of the consent document
and collecting the signature for it
were handled by two different steps.
Now we've added
the signature capture functionality
to the Web-View-Step
so that you can present
the overview of the consent document
and ask for the participant's signature
within the same view.
Let's see how this step is created.
The first thing we have to do
is initialize the ORK-Web-View-Step,
passing in an identifier
and the HTML content you wish to display.
And the last thing we have to do is set
the show-Signature-After-Content attribute
to "true,"
and this will ensure
that the signature view
is shown below the HTML content
when the step is presented.
This year, we're also introducing
the Request-Permission-Step.
Previously, if you wanted
to request access to Health data,
you would have to do so
outside of the ResearchKit flow.
Which means you had to create
the necessary views to ask for access,
and maintain those views yourself.
Now all you have to do
is initialize the Request-Permission-Step
and pass in the HealthKit types
you want access to,
and we'll do the heavy lifting
of requesting the data for you.
Now you can do more with less code
while making the experience
and flow of your app much better.
Let's take a look at the code
to create the ORK-Request-Permission-Step.
We start off by creating
a set of HK-Sample-Types,
and these represent the types
you want to write access for.
Then we create a set of HK-Object-Types,
and these represent the types
you want to read access for.
Next, we initialize
the ORK-HealthKit-Permission-Type,
making sure that we pass in
the HK-Types-To-Write,
and HK-Types-To-Read sets created above.
And the last thing we have to do
is initialize
the ORK-Request-Permission-Step,
and pass in an array of permission types
that currently only has
our HK-Permission-Type within it.
That brings us to a close
for the onboarding update session,
so let's collect our sticker.
Now that we have our sticker,
let's keep moving forward
and talk about survey enhancements.
Before we show any questions,
we always want to give the user
some insight
on what the point of the survey is.
To do this,
we use an Instruction-Step again
to provide some brief context,
but this time,
we also provide an icon image
that is left-aligned to the screen,
which is all handled by ResearchKit.
In the second step
of the onboarding survey,
we use our ORK-Form-Step to collect
basic information about the participant.
But as you can see here,
we've made some UI improvements
by using labels to display errors,
as opposed to previously using alerts,
which didn't always make for
the best user experience.
Let's fix those errors and move on
to the next step in our onboarding survey.
In the third step,
we preview the new SES-Answer-Format,
which can help present
scale-based questions.
Much like the example here,
where we asked the user
to select the option
that they feel best depicts
the current state of their health.
Let's look at the code
needed to present this step.
The first thing we do
is initialize the SES-Answer-Format
and pass in the top-Rung-Text
and bottom-Rung-Text, as seen here.
The last thing we have to do
is simply initialize our ORK-Form-Item
and pass in the SES-Answer-Format
created above.
In this step,
we use a Continuous-Scale-Answer-Format
and a Scale-Answer-Format
to get information on the participant's
current stress level and pain level.
In the past, if the user wasn't
comfortable enough to answer the question,
or simply didn't know the answer,
they would either leave the question blank
or provide an answer that wasn't accurate
because the question might be required.
Now we've added the ability
to use the ORK-Dont-Know-Button
with select answer formats.
This will allow the participants
to select the "I don't know" button
when they don't want to answer
the questions presented to them.
You can also pass in custom text,
as seen here,
to replace the default
"I don't know" text.
Let's take a look at the code
for the second scaled question
to see how we added
the "Don't know" button
and added custom text.
First, we initialize
the ORK-Scale-Answer-Format
and pass in all the required values.
Next, we set
the should-Show-Dont-Know-Button attribute
to "true."
Then we set
the custom-Dont-Know-Button-Text
to "Prefer not to answer,"
and this will override
the default text "I don't know."
The last thing we have to do
is initialize the ORK-Form-Item
and pass in the Scale-Answer-Format
created above.
In the last question of the survey,
we use an ORK-Text-Answer-Format
to collect any additional information
the participant thinks we should know.
Previously, we supported
setting the maximum character count,
but there was no visual
to let the user know what their limit is,
or how close they were to approaching it.
Now we've added
a maximum character count label
so that the user can have
a much better idea
of how much information they can provide
and base their response off that.
We've also added a "Clear" button
so that the user can remove any text
that they've typed in.
Let's check out the code
to make this happen.
First, we initialize
the ORK-Text-Answer-Format.
Then we begin to set some properties
on the Answer-Format,
such as setting multiple-Lines to "true,"
setting maximum-Length to "280,"
and setting hide-Character-Count-Label
and hide-Clear-Button to "false"
to make sure
that both of these UI elements are shown
when this step is presented.
And the last thing we have to do
is initialize our ORK-Question-Step
and pass in the text-Answer-Format
created above.
After finishing the onboarding survey,
we present the participant
with the new ORK-Review-View-Controller.
One of the biggest challenges
for any study
is making sure that the data entered
by the participant is accurate.
As humans, making mistakes
in our everyday lives is very common.
So when participants fill out surveys,
it might be safe to assume
that a small mistake might have happened.
To help alleviate this problem,
ResearchKit now provides
a Review-View-Controller
that will allow the participant
to view a breakdown
of all the questions they were asked,
and the response they gave.
If they want to update
any of those questions,
they can simply click "Edit"
and update their answer.
Let's look at the code
to present the Review-View-Controller.
First, we initialize
the Review-View-Controller,
which requires us to pass in a task
and a result object,
which, in this case, we get
from the task-View-Controller object
passed back to us by the
did-Finish-With-Reason delegate method.
But keep in mind that you can
also initialize your task separately,
and also pass in a result that may have
been saved at an earlier time.
Next, we set ourselves as the delegate,
and this requires us to implement
the did-Update-Result
and did-Select-Incomplete cell methods.
Then, after setting
our review-Title and text,
we're done creating
our first Review-View-Controller.
Now that we've finished
reviewing our survey enhancements
and collected our well-deserved sticker,
let's move on to the next topic,
which is active tasks.
Let's first take a look
at the improvements we've made
to our hearing task.
For the Environment-SPL-Meter-Step,
we added a new animation
that clearly indicates if you're within
the set threshold for background noise,
as seen here.
We also made updates
to our dB-HL-Tone-Audiometry-Step
by tweaking the button UI,
adding better haptics,
changing the progress indicator to a label
to make it more clear to the participant
how far they've made it,
and we also added calibration data
to support AirPods Pros.
Let's collect our hearing sticker
before moving on.
Now that we have our hearing sticker,
let's chat about our next topic,
which is 3D models.
When running a study,
giving your participants
clear and informative visuals
to explain a specific concept
can be invaluable,
especially if they can
also interact with it.
Using 3D models to do this is, by far,
one of the best solutions
to educate your participants,
while also increasing engagement.
However, writing the code necessary
to present 3D models and maintaining it
can be cumbersome to say the least.
So, whether you're trying to present
something as simple as a human hand,
or something more complex
such as the human muscular system,
we've made the process of
presenting 3D models much easier for you
by creating two new classes.
Those two classes
are the ORK-3D-Model-Step,
and the ORK-USDZ-Model-Manager.
Using these two classes,
you can now quickly present 3D models
within your ResearchKit app by...
first, adding a USDZ file
to your Xcode project.
Second, creating
a USDZ-Model-Manager instance
and passing in the name
of the desired USDZ file
that was imported in your project.
And third, initialize an ORK-3D-Model-Step
with the USDZ-Model-Manager instance
and present it.
And just like that, you can now present
high-quality 3D models
that your users can interact with
and touch
without having to maintain
any of the code yourself.
Before moving on, we wanted to point out
that we're well-aware
that creating your own model
can take a good amount of time.
However, there are models
accessible to you online
that you can download for free
to practice with.
So, in the upcoming example,
we use a toy robot
and a toy drummer 3D model
that are both publicly available
at the URL seen here.
Let's get started.
In the first example,
we'll present the toy robot model.
Selection has been enabled,
and the user is required to touch
any part of the model before continuing.
In the second example,
we'll present the drummer model.
Selection is disabled,
but certain objects on the model
have been pre-highlighted
to draw the user's attention.
The user also has full control
to inspect the highlighted areas.
Let's take a look at some code to see
how simple it is to present a 3D model.
First, we initialize
our USDZ-Model-Manager,
passing in the name of the USDZ file
that we wish to present.
Next, we set a few properties
on the Model-Manager,
such as allows-Selection, highlight-Color,
and setting
enable-Continue-After-Selection to "false"
to ensure that the user
isn't blocked from moving forward.
Next, we pass in
our optional array-Of-Identifiers,
where each identifier
maps to a specific object
on the model we want to highlight
before we present it.
Then the last thing we do
is initialize the ORK-3D-Model-Step
and pass in the USDZ-Model-Manager
created above.
So, some of you might be wondering,
"Why create a Model-Manager class
instead of just adding that functionality
to the 3D-Model-Step itself?"
And the reason is to make the process
of creating a custom 3D model experience
much easier for any developer
interested in doing so.
To understand it further,
we need to learn about the parent class
of the USDZ-Model-Manager,
which is the ORK-3D-Model-Manager.
Let's take a look.
The ORK-3D-Model-Manager class
is an abstract class that we've created
which shouldn't be used directly.
The point of the 3D-Model-Manager
is to be a subclass
while requiring the subclass
to implement specific features
that we believe
every 3D model experience should have.
So, after creating your subclass
and making sure
that these features are handled,
you can then move forward to add
all the extra functionality you want,
as seen here with the USDZ-Model-Manager.
If the talk were to end here,
we definitely believe
that using the USDZ-Model-Manager
could create endless possibilities
for your ResearchKit app.
However, we are open source,
and we always encourage
members of the community to contribute
to help push ResearchKit forward.
With that being said,
we're excited to announce
that someone from the community
has also taken the opportunity
to create their own Model-Manager class.
BioDigital, an interactive 3D software
platform for anatomy visualization,
has provided
the ORK-BioDigital-Model-Manager class
so that their already powerful iOS SDK
can now be integrated easily
into any ResearchKit project.
Some of their features include:
presenting custom models
created via their admin portal,
programmatically adding labels,
colors and annotations
to any model loaded within your app.
And since all of our digital models
are loaded via the web,
you can dynamically add new models
to your project
without having to update any code.
Let's see a couple of examples in action.
In the first example,
we use an instruction step
to inform the user that we'll present
an interactive human model.
This could be used in many situations
that most of us have experienced,
such as visiting a physical therapy clinic
or an orthopedic physician's office
where you're usually given
a piece of paper to describe your pain,
or circle the area
on some kind of picture.
Now we can get rid of paper
and make the experience much better.
As you see here, we've loaded our model
while also being presented with a card
that contains useful information
that can be updated via
BioDigital's admin portal, or their SDK.
Users can also interact with the model
so that they can reach and view
the exact areas of interest.
After clicking on the muscle
where pain has been experienced,
we're also presented with a label
that can give us even more information
on that specific organ.
This can be updated
via BioDigital's admin portal,
or locally through their SDK.
In the next example, we imagine a scenario
where a patient has visited a hospital
for chest pain.
After receiving a CT scan,
the physician would like to give a visual
to show the patient the exact arteries
that are experiencing blockages.
To do this, we'll present
an interactive 3D human heart model
with dynamically-added annotations
to specific coronary arteries,
all done directly
through BioDigital-Model-Manager class.
As you can see here,
we presented our heart model
along with another card view
for additional information.
The user can then interact
with the heart model
and select
the programmatically added annotations
to find more information on the severity
of each individual blockage.
Let's take a look at the code
to present the animated heart model.
After importing ResearchKit and HumanKit,
which is provided by BioDigital,
we first initialize
the ORK-BioDigital-Model-Manager instance.
Then we set a couple of properties
that were inherited
from the ORK-3D-Model-Manager class,
such as highlight-Color
and identifiers-Of-Objects-To-Highlight.
Then we focus on some properties
and instance methods added by BioDigital,
such as identifiers-Of-Objects-To-Hide,
the load method, where we pass in the ID
of the model we want to present,
in this case, the heart model,
and the annotate method,
where we pass in the identifier
of the object we want to annotate,
in this case, the right coronary artery.
After setting the title and text,
the last thing we have to do
is initialize the ORK-3D-Model-Step,
and pass in the BioDigital-Model-Manager
created above.
To find out more information
about BioDigital and their SDK,
visit their GitHub page, seen here.
Now that we've collected
our 3D model sticker,
I'll hand things over to my teammate Joey
to talk about building
a custom active task.
Take it away, Joey.
Thanks, Pariece, for those awesome updates
coming to ResearchKit.
Today, I'm going to be showing you
how to create
your very own custom active task.
So, we've collected
a bunch of stickers already...
so to collect
our front-facing camera sticker,
we will walk through the process
of creating an active task in ResearchKit.
Then we will open Xcode
and implement a custom application
to show off our new task.
Our task is going to show the user
a preview of what they're recording
in real time.
We'll let the user control
when to start and stop recording,
and show a timer for how long
they have been recording for.
Additionally,
the user will have the opportunity
to review and retry the recording,
in case they want another take.
Before we get into it,
I want to give you a quick refresher
on the relevant classes and protocols
included in ResearchKit
to help you accomplish this.
First, your application needs to create
an ORK-Task object.
ORK-Task is a protocol
which your app can use
to reference a collection
of various step objects.
Most applications can use
the concrete ORK-Ordered,
or ORK-Navigable-Ordered-Task
included in ResearchKit.
The task object you create
is then injected
into an ORK-Task-View-Controller object.
This object is responsible for showing
each step in your task
as they are de-queued.
Your application has no need
to subclass ORK-Task-View-Controller,
so you can use it as-is.
Additionally, ORK-Task-View-Controller
is a subclass
of UI-View-Controller internally,
so you can present it in your app
as you normally would
any other View-Controller in UIKit.
Finally, the ORK-Task-Result is an object
which contains the aggregate results
for each step in your task.
The results that are collected
from the task
are then delegated
back to your application
upon completion of the task,
using the ORK-Task-View-Controller
delegate.
This is the essential round trip
from your application into ResearchKit,
and then back.
Since I'm going to be showing you
how to create your very own active task,
we need to dive one level deeper
with some coding examples
that will set up our active task.
So first, our application needs to create
a collection of ORK-Step
and ORK-Active-Step objects
to make up the data model of our task.
Since we will be creating
a Front-Facing-Camera-Active task,
we will really create a task
which includes an Active-Step subclass.
First, import the ORK-Active-Step header
from ResearchKit
and create a new subclass
of ORK-Active-Step.
We'll name this class
ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step.
I'm also going to add
three additional properties here
I would like to configure.
An NS-Time-Interval,
to limit the maximum duration
we want to record for,
and two Booleans for allowing the user
to review their recording,
as well as allowing them
to retry their recording.
Next, we will declare
the View-Controller type
to display when the step is de-queued.
In the case of an ORK-Active-Step,
this should be a subclass
of ORK-Active-Step-View-Controller,
which you can implement
similar to any UI-View-Controller
in UIKit.
The ORK-Task-View-Controller
presenting your task
is responsible for instantiating
the associated View-Controller
of each step in your task.
Here's a quick look at the interface
of our ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-
Step-View-Controller,
which subclasses
ORK-Active-Step-View-Controller.
In our ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step,
we will declare
the type of View-Controller
to associate with the step,
so we can override the step-View-
Controller-Class method of the superclass.
In this case, we will return
the ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-
Step-View-Controller class object.
You can use a custom UI-View
to represent the content of your step.
So here, our ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-
Step-Content-View
is a simple subclass of UI-View.
I've declared some View events here
which we can use to pass relevant events
back to our View-Controller,
as well as a block typedef.
Inside of our interface,
we have a method
to set the block parameter
to invoke when events are passed
from the content view.
Since we want to give the user a preview
of the recording in real time,
we will pass the AV-Capture-Session
to the content view,
and internally,
the content view will set up
an AV-Capture-Video-Preview-Layer.
And finally, we have added a method
to start our timer with a maximum duration
as well as a method to show certain
recording options before submitting.
We can now add this content view
into our View-Controller.
We already have a reference
to an AV-Capture-Session
which is initialized in another method.
We also have a property to reference our
ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step-Content-View.
By the time we reach view-Did-Load,
we are ready to initialize
our content view.
Next, we will handle events
coming from our content view.
We'll use weak-Self here
to avoid a reference cycle.
We will add our content view as a subview.
And finally,
we will set the Preview-Layer session
using our AV-Capture-Session from before.
After our step finishes,
ORK-Active-Step-View-Controller
asks for the ORK-Step-Result.
This is your View-Controller's call
to add the appropriate results
and any data you collect to be delegated
back to the application
when your step finishes.
In our case,
ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step-Result
is going to be a subclass
of ORK-File-Result.
We have also added an integer property
so we can keep track of how many times
the user deleted
and retried their recording.
If we revisit the View-Controller,
we override the superclass's result method
to append our custom
ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step-Result.
First, we create an instance of our
Then we set the relevant parameters,
such as the identifier, content-Type,
retry-Count, as well as the file-URL.
Finally, we append our new-Results
into the current-Results collection
and return.
This effectively completes
the implementation
of our custom active task.
Let's jump into Xcode and try it out.
So here I have a demo application
that I've been working on
which includes ResearchKit as a submodule.
So I'm going to go ahead
and I'm going to create a method
which allows us to construct
and present our task.
Inside of this method,
we're going to instantiate our steps
that are part of our task.
So I'm going to go ahead
and create an instruction-Step
which welcomes the user to the task.
Then I'm going to use
the ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step
that we just created.
We'll set the maximum recording limit
to about 15 seconds,
and we'll allow the user
to retry and review their recording.
Then we'll go ahead
and add a completion step,
thanking the user for their time.
So, now that we have all of our steps,
we'll go ahead and create
an ORK-Task object.
So here we have an ORK-Ordered-Task
and we'll include
all of the steps from before...
then create a task-View-Controller object
injecting our task as well.
Then we present this task-View-Controller.
In view-Did-Appear
we can go ahead and present
Front-Facing-Camera-Active-Task
and conform to the delegate,
the ORK-Task-View-Controller delegate.
Then we can make ourselves
the delegate for the task-View-Controller.
Then respond to the did-Finish-With reason
ORK-Task-View-Controller delegate method.
Inside of this method,
we're going to check to see
if the currently presented View-Controller
is the task-View-Controller,
and then dismiss it.
And we'll go ahead and try to extract
the ORK-Front-Facing-Camera-Step-Result.
And once we have that result object,
we can go ahead
and print the Recording File URL,
as well as the retry-Count.
So let's go ahead
and run this on the device.
Okay, so here we have
our instruction-Step that we created,
and we're "Welcome to WWDC!"
So here we have our preview-Layer session,
which we can see our recording
in real time.
We'll go ahead and click "Get Started."
So here we have
our Front-Facing-Camera-Step,
and I'll go ahead and create a recording.
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
So let's go ahead and review this video.
Okay, let's go ahead and just retry that
'cause I didn't like that.
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I think that one was good,
so I'll go ahead and submit.
Here's our completion-Step
thanking the user,
and we'll go ahead
and exit the task gracefully.
If we go back to Xcode,
we should be able to see in the console
that we have printed
the Recording File URL
as well as the retry-Count.
This concludes
our demonstration for today,
and we have implemented our own
custom Active-Step in ResearchKit
and constructed the task
in our application.
We then extracted the results object
to verify our result.
We hope you enjoyed. Thank you.
Pariece, back to you.
Thank you for that demo, Joey.
We hope everyone viewing enjoyed it,
and we're very excited to see
what you can do
with the new Front-Facing-Camera-Step,
or any task
that you decide to create yourself.
Now that we've collected
our Front-Facing-Camera-Step sticker,
that brings us to a close to
all of our ResearchKit updates this year.
But before moving on,
let's go over all the stickers
we've collected throughout our talk.
First, we talked about community updates,
where we mentioned a few apps
that have leveraged our frameworks
over the past year,
our new website at researchandcare.org,
and the new Investigator Support Program.
Then we moved on to onboarding updates.
We spoke about the new additions,
such as body items,
inline signature functionality
and the Request-Permission-Step.
Then we talked about survey enhancements,
where we previewed new error labels,
the "I dont know" button,
and the Review-View-Controller,
to name a few.
Then we talked about
hearing test UI updates,
where we previewed UI enhancements
to the Environment-SPL-Meter
and Tone-Audiometry-Step.
Then we moved on to 3D models,
where we went over and previewed
the 3D-Model-Step,
the USDZ-Model-Manager,
and the BioDigital-Model-Manager classes
to add 3D models to your app.
And last, but not least,
Joey walked you through the process
of building your own active task,
while also previewing the functionality
of the new Front-Facing-Camera-Step.
We have a pretty solid collection
of stickers here,
but it wouldn't be complete
without the final ResearchKit sticker.
For more information
on the topics discussed today,
feel free to visit
the resources shared here.
As always,
we want to remind everyone watching
that we are open source,
and we welcome anyone using
or interested in ResearchKit
to visit our GitHub repo shown here
and contribute to help the framework grow.
Thank you again for taking the time
to watch our talk,
and we're looking forward to seeing
the powerful apps and experiences
you will create with ResearchKit.
Thank you.