Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, folks! My name is Edith
and I'm a motion scientist
on Apple's software engineering team.
Today, I'm joined by Dan Trietsch,
a motion engineer,
to introduce a new set of metrics
now available on iOS and watchOS
that enable customers
to measure their movement
in groundbreaking ways.
In this session,
we'll introduce these metrics
and provide guidance for app developers
who want to go beyond simple step-counting
to create a rich understanding
of a customer's mobility.
Movement is a key indicator of health.
The way someone moves
can tell us about their short-term health,
like recovery
from a musculoskeletal injury,
and their long-term health,
like their ability to age
with independence.
Movement is affected
by a variety of health conditions
like neurological disease
and cardiopulmonary fitness.
One of the primary ways
that we measure movement
is observing how someone walks.
Walking is something
many people do every day
and might take for granted,
but it's actually pretty amazing how many
systems have to come together to do it.
Walking requires coordination,
strength and fitness.
Our muscles, brain and heart
are constantly working when we do it.
Measuring walking is a great way
to see changes in health,
but measuring how someone walks
is surprisingly complicated.
It requires trips
to in-clinic appointments
and extensive evaluation
with specialized equipment.
This is a hallway,
and it's a setting for one of
the most used clinical walking tests,
the six-minute walk test.
Patients are asked to walk back and forth,
to go as far as they can in six minutes.
The faster and more continuously
they walk, the higher the number.
The total distance covered
is a great indicator
in a wide range of health scenarios.
But to do this test properly,
it requires 30 meters of clear hallway
to make sure the person isn't spending
more time turning around
than they are walking.
How many of us
have this kind of space at home
to check in on our progress
between clinic visits?
Questionnaires are a less time-
and resource-intensive tool
to evaluate walking.
Asking a person to report
their level of difficulty or pain
when walking is helpful,
but questionnaires rely on memory
and perception.
There are systems for measuring movement
much more precisely.
Motion-capture technology
is a very precise method
to detect small changes
in a person's movement,
but it requires expensive equipment,
specialized cameras and markers
like you can see here,
and trained technicians
to gather, process and analyze the data.
Overall, even the best of these approaches
is only a rare snapshot.
It's a substitute for the question
that really matters--
how are you moving in your everyday life?
iPhone and Apple Watch,
devices people carry every day,
can now bring the motion lab
into the real world,
filling the gap between research and life.
New to iOS and watchOS,
Apple is introducing
a category of metrics to HealthKit
that capture the complex and important
elements of human movement,
all while a customer walks around
with their iPhone in their pocket
or their Apple Watch on their wrist.
Customers can view these metrics
in the Health app,
and developers can use them in their apps
through the HealthKit API.
Four of the new mobility metrics
are calculated on iPhone.
The first two metrics are walking speed,
how fast a person travels over ground,
and step length.
Is a person taking short, cautious steps
or long, confident strides?
These metrics are sensitive
to slow walking
and can detect small changes,
tasks that traditional pedometers
struggle with.
Two other iPhone metrics measure
walking quality--
double-support time,
which is the percentage of time
during a walk
when both feet are in contact
with the ground,
and walking asymmetry,
which is the percentage of time
that steps with one foot
are faster or slower
than steps with the other foot.
While step counters and pedometers
measure all walking in a day,
these new metrics intelligently gather
the most valuable bouts of walking
during consistent conditions,
over flat ground in a continuous segment,
resulting in precise measures
that resemble standardized walking tests.
The other four mobility metrics are
calculated only for Apple Watch wearers.
In addition to counting flights of stairs,
Apple Watch can now record
how fast a person goes
up or down a flight of stairs.
Two features synthesize together
multiple data sources
to make predictions of what a person
could do at their highest effort.
First, remember that standardized
walking test I mentioned?
The six-minute walk distance?
Apple Watch now uses activity clues
that happen naturally over a week
to estimate what a person
would have scored on that test.
And finally, VO2 max is not new,
but now it's more accurate
and it's better for people
with lower levels of fitness.
Instead of requiring running-level effort,
Apple Watch can now predict VO2 max
using slower walking speeds.
These metrics build on APIs
that measure movement
with iPhone and Apple Watch,
like CMPedometer,
which is used to track steps,
cadence, distance, pace,
and flights of stairs,
and HealthKit,
which aggregates these metrics
to add calories, exercise minutes,
and workouts from Apple Watch.
You can find more resources
on these technologies
in WWDC talks from 2017 and 2018.
That's a lot of new information
and there are
so many possible applications
for this new collection
of mobility metrics,
but today, we'll focus in on one scenario
where these data could be helpful--
recovery from a musculoskeletal injury.
We'll show you how to access
and use these data types
to create a rich user experience.
Imagine you have a customer named Jamie,
who just injured their ankle
while training for a 5K.
While Jamie is still able to walk around
and complete daily tasks,
they want to track progress
during rehab and recovery,
and how far there is to go.
Recovering from an injury
is often a slow process,
and it can be hard to recognize
and celebrate small increments of progress
to stay motivated in between visits
to the doctor and physical therapist.
What can you do to help fill in the gaps?
In the next few slides,
we'll use the mobility metrics
to show Jamie their progress
and help them put
their recovery in context.
For details about syncing data
with HealthKit
or making apps in CareKit,
check out these past WWDC sessions.
We're going to break today's work up
into three steps.
First, how to measure walking by querying
one of the new mobility data types.
Second, how to aggregate the data
to see changes over time.
And finally,
how to bring in other data types
to build and interpret
a holistic picture of walking.
First, what should you measure?
You'll start by showing Jamie
their walking speed
using the new HKQuantityType.
There are a lot of pedometers
out there already,
including one on iPhone and Apple Watch,
that measure walking quantity.
They're optimized to count
as much walking as possible.
But this measure is designed
to capture small changes
in how they're doing that walking,
so it works a little differently.
It doesn't need calibration against GPS,
making it consistent and easy
to compare values over time.
It's accurate at slow walking speeds,
so it works for people
with limited mobility
and can capture
even those early days of recovery.
It's sensitive to even small changes.
By design,
it doesn't count all the walking.
Instead, you'll see a start and stop time
for samples of continuous walking
on flat ground,
which makes walking bouts
easier to compare.
And because it's passively collected
on the motion coprocessor all day,
any time Jamie carries their iPhone
in a pocket or on their hip,
they can have measurements
dating back to before the injury happened,
which allows pre-
and post-injury comparison.
Now, Dan will walk through
how to use this metric.
First things first, since walking speed
is a HealthKit quantity type,
we will need to ask Jamie
for permission to read their data.
For our app, we are not planning
on writing new data back into HealthKit,
so we only request read access.
Next, we will construct a query
for walking-speed samples
around the time of Jamie's recent injury.
Let's assume that they have already
shared with us the date of their injury.
Let's set our query bounds
beginning 30 days before the injury
so we can establish a baseline speed,
and ending 60 days later,
so we can track their recovery progress.
Then, we specify the type of data
we're interested in, walking speed,
and how we want it to be sorted.
As soon as we execute this query,
our callback will receive
all of the matching HKSamples.
Be aware,
depending on Jamie's activity level,
this query could return
hundreds of walking samples.
Now that we have Jamie's query results,
we need a way to visualize the data.
Fortunately for us,
Apple has a pair of frameworks
to chart and graph our results,
CareKit and ResearchKit.
In today's example, we'll be using
ResearchKit's graphChartViews.
Specifically,
ResearchKit's lineGraphChartView
and discreteGraphChartView
will provide an excellent way for us to
visualize Jamie's query results over time.
For each sample, we append our results
to an array of ValueRange objects.
Then we have a function we added,
updatePlotPoints,
to our ChartViewDataSource object.
Finally, we have our graphChartView
reload our data in the UI
on the main queue.
In this graph,
we're presenting walking-speed results
in ResearchKit's discreteGraphChartView.
That's quite a bit of data!
Jamie's injury date is at day zero
on the x-axis.
Notice that because we're plotting Jamie's
full range of walking speeds by day,
it's difficult for us to know
where most of the data is distributed
within any particular day.
However, just from this plot,
we are starting to see the impact
of injury on Jamie's walking speed.
Edith, what's next?
All right, Dan got us started
with a straightforward visualization
of the raw values for walking speed.
However, you could probably see
that with a passively measured
all-day metric like this,
there's a lot of data to make sense of.
The next step toward
a simple but insightful experience
is to aggregate the raw data
into something more meaningful
for the recovery process.
In the first plot of all the daily data,
the injury was striking,
but it was harder to see
the more subtle recovery.
When working with
"all-day-every-day" data,
not all walking is going to have
the same meaning.
Think about the many things
that could impact a person's walking speed
other than their health.
Maybe they're rushing to a meeting.
Maybe they're walking a dog
that likes to stop and smell everything.
Maybe they spend some time walking with
a partner who is slower than they are.
As a developer, you,
and maybe some friendly domain experts,
like doctors, physical therapists
or biomechanists,
will need to find the right way
for your scenario
to aggregate and summarize the samples
to cut through that noise.
Here's a look at the data
underlying the plot Dan just showed
of Jamie's walking speed over time.
There are many samples
of walking during a day,
covering a wide range of speeds
with the occasional outlier.
You've consulted the domain experts
or your data-science team,
and they've identified
that faster walking speeds
are the most meaningful way to understand
if someone's on track for tasks
like hustling to make it across the street
before the light turns red.
So you decide to use the 95th percentile
of the metric
to track maximum walking speed,
without being too sensitive to outliers.
And since this recovery process is going
to be a matter of weeks, not days,
your product team doesn't want Jamie
to be too concerned
about the small day-to-day fluctuations,
so you decide to average over seven days.
But, of course, you don't want to blend
the pre- and post-injury values together,
so you reset the calculation
after the date of injury.
Now, Dan will walk through
how to do this same calculation
directly in your app.
Thanks, Edith.
As you recall, we had previously queried
all of Jamie's walking speeds
from 30 days before the injury
up to 60 days after.
As Edith demonstrated,
in order to measure maximum walking speed,
we will want to calculate and display
the top 95th-percentile speed per day.
Let's pick midnight as the starting point
and ending point for each day.
We will call enumerateDates
to iterate over each day
and find all the walking speed samples
contained within.
Notice that my output array
is made up of optional values.
We cannot assume that Jamie will have
a walking speed for every single day
in the range of our query.
Perhaps they left their phone
on their bedside table,
or maybe they just weren't
very active that day.
But, for the days when they do have
sufficient data,
we can calculate their 95th-percentile
walking speed.
First, we extract all of the walking speed
samples from the HKQuantitySamples.
Since we have been using miles per hour
in our plots,
let's select that
for the values we are calculating.
And just to finish it up,
let's sort the list
and find the 95th-percentile
walking speed.
Wow! Thanks to the analysis
of our scientists
and our code implementation,
Jamie can really see
the impact their injury had
and how they came back
stronger and faster than before.
Edith, back to you.
Now that you've aggregated walking speed
to create a meaningful chart,
let's talk about how to help Jamie
interpret the big picture.
Filtering all that data down
to something more digestible
will reveal daily and weekly progress.
But recovery from an injury
can take a long time,
and there will be other factors
that impact daily walking speeds.
They could be health-related
like decreased pain
or dropping off from physical therapy
or taking on a new exercise program,
and non-health-related,
like a brisk walking commute
that has become a morning stroll
while working from home.
Or a family vacation
that means spending several days
walking with an older relative.
Or maybe it's just too hot out
to walk very fast.
Luckily, Apple's mobility metrics
go further
to capture aspects of walking quality.
By combining multiple metrics together,
you can create
the whole picture of recovery.
We have a good understanding
of how Jamie's walking speed has changed
before and after their injury.
Now let's take a look
at their double-support time.
This is the percentage of time
during walking
when both feet are in contact
with the ground,
and a lower value is actually better
because it indicates
that the walker is spending less time
using both feet to stabilize themselves.
You can show Jamie that
even though their walking speed
slowed down during a heat wave,
when they didn't feel like going
on their brisk afternoon walk,
they continued to make steady improvements
in lowering their double-support time
back to pre-injury levels.
And it doesn't stop
with this rich record of daily walking.
Recall the occasional
six-minute walk tests
that are done in a physical therapy clinic
to provide snapshots
of the recovery process.
They might not be done very often
in a busy clinic,
and they can't tell us what
Jamie's baseline was before their injury.
But because Jamie wears an Apple Watch,
the movement signals from Apple Watch
and iPhone are combined
into a predicted six-minute walk distance
each week.
These values give insight
into what Jamie's movement was like
before the injury,
and the recovery process
in between physical therapy appointments.
Dan, what do developers need to do
to bring in these added dimensions,
like double-support time
and six-minute walk test, to the app?
Let's add double-support time
and six-minute walk distance
to the list of types
we would like to request.
We query double-support time
and six-minute walk
in much the same way
as we do walking speed.
Now is a good time to also filter the data
according to how it was collected.
As you know, data stored in HealthKit
can come from a variety
of different sources.
For example, six-minute walk data
could be predicted values
calculated on Apple Watch
or user-entered values in the Health app.
For a six-minute-walk graph,
let's aggregate both the predicted values
and the value Jamie had manually entered
after completing
a six-minute walk test in-clinic.
We can accomplish this
by checking the sourceRevision
and metadata of the HKSample.
First, we check
the source's bundleIdentifier
to see if the data was recorded by Apple.
Then, we check the metadata key
for the WasUserEntered key.
If this key is both present
and set to "true,"
then we will know that it was a sample
entered by Jamie into the HealthKit app.
Otherwise, it is a predicted value
from Apple Watch.
With these newly added dimensions,
Jamie gets more than just
the walking speed plot we made earlier.
They can see how their percentage
of double support
increased after their injury
and steadily decreased during recovery.
Typically, this type of data would have
required a specialized motion lab.
Now, these metrics are collected
right on their iPhone.
Let's graph two sets of data points
for Jamie's six-minute walk distance.
First, in red, we plot values
recorded from a test
at a physical therapy clinic
and manually entered in the Health app.
Second, in green, we plot predicted
six-minute-walk values
generated by iPhone and Apple Watch.
The automatic, in-system values give Jamie
a pre-injury baseline for comparison
and paints a fuller picture of recovery.
Back to Edith!
Thanks, Dan!
Developers, you've helped Jamie
own recovery from that injury
by measuring, aggregating
and interpreting changes in mobility
over time.
In today's scenario, we've gone deep
on the powerful new mobility metrics
available for iPhone and Apple Watch.
There are already some great examples
of groups exploring mobility metrics
for clinical use cases.
The Society for Vascular Surgery
will use these mobility metrics
to monitor patients
with peripheral vascular disease
as they work through
a home exercise program.
And Zimmer Biomet,
a leader in orthopedic devices and care,
will use them in mymobility,
an app that helps patients
and their doctors
prepare for and manage
knee-replacement surgery.
I want to close
with a few final pieces of advice.
Apple devices offer rich opportunities
for motion sensing, in a variety of APIs,
that round out the ways
to measure movement.
You can access inertial sensing signals
directly on the iPhone and Apple Watch
using CMMotionManager.
You can track changes in altitude
using CMAltimeter.
And new this year, you can now get
those same useful inertial sensor signals
in a new location, AirPods Pro,
with the Headphone Motion API.
Second, mobility metrics
have useful metadata,
like the start and end times
for each walking bout,
or the calibration status of a predicted
six-minute-walking-distance sample.
So check those out when considering
how to aggregate the data.
Next, remember that the mobility metrics
require particular conditions
for measurements to be recorded.
The iPhone values are recorded
when the user carries their phone
near their waist,
such as in a pocket,
and walks on flat ground.
Six-minute walk distance is recorded
with a week of Apple Watch wear.
And finally, work with domain experts
like physical therapists, doctors,
and biomechanists
to develop the strategies
for aggregating these metrics
to find the insights and meaning
that suit your use case.
There are so many health scenarios
beyond acute injury
when movement will change.
We're excited
for all the creative applications
you find for mobility metrics,
and we can't wait to see
what you come up with.
Thanks for being a part of WWDC 2020.