[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. Welcome to
"What's New in Universal Links."
My name is Christopher Linn.
We've talked about universal links
at WWDC before,
but we'd like to give you
a brief refresher.
Universal links are HTTPS or HTTP URLs
that represent your content
both on the Web and in your app.
They allow users to open your content
in your app instead of in a Web browser,
allowing you to provide
a richer experience.
You create them by adding
a special entitlement,
the Associated Domains entitlement,
to your app
and by adding a JSON file
to your Web server.
The entitlement mentions
your Web server's domain name,
and the Web server mentions
your app's application identifier.
This creates a secure two-way association
between your app and your website,
allowing your app to perform special tasks
on behalf of your website.
Where you are currently using
custom URL schemes,
you should migrate to universal links
as soon as possible.
Custom URL schemes are not recommended.
For more detail about what
universal links are and how to adopt them,
check out our session from WWDC19.
After that high-level review
of universal links,
let's get to the fun stuff:
support for new platforms.
The first and smallest platform
we're adding support for this year
is watchOS.
Universal links work the same way
on watchOS
as they do on our other platforms,
but there are some platform-specific
differences we want to share with you.
The first is that, when using WatchKit,
the API is different
than when using UIKit or AppKit.
And it's important to remember
that your entitlements,
including the Associated Domains
entitlement,
are applied to your WatchKit extension,
not the containing WatchKit app.
On iOS, or when using Mac Catalyst,
you implement
the UIApplicationDelegate method
"application: continue userActivity:
restorationHandler"
to handle incoming universal links.
We've shown how to use this
delegate method in previous sessions.
When you want to open a universal link
in another application,
you use UIApplication, openURL.
However, on watchOS,
you use WatchKit instead of UIKit,
so to adopt on watchOS,
we'll need to make some changes here.
WKExtensionDelegate's
handle(_ userActivity method
is responsible for handling
incoming universal links.
The body of this method
will be fundamentally the same
as on iOS and macOS.
To open a URL in another application,
you use WKExtension's
openSystemURL method.
Just like on our other platforms,
if you attempt to open a universal link
in an application that's not installed,
that link will fail to open.
Now, Safari is not available on watchOS
except in limited contexts
like Mail and Messages.
And this method does not return a value
or take a completion handler.
So, rather than leave the user
with no feedback,
we present UI to the user on watchOS,
and that looks like this.
Here you can see
an app we've been working on
that shows us the menus
for all our favorite restaurants.
It lets us select our favorite foods,
then order them in each restaurant's app
by invoking a universal link.
However, this Apple Watch doesn't have
this restaurant's app installed.
So when we tap the button to order,
we'll see this alert,
telling us to continue
on the paired iPhone.
So, to quickly summarize,
these are the methods you use
to handle and open universal links
when using WatchKit.
These are the equivalent methods
when using UIKit.
Note that when your app is configured
to use UIScene,
you need to implement
a different delegate method
than when using only UIApplication.
And AppKit is similar to,
but distinct from, UIKit.
In the end, the exact API you use
will depend on the platform
and SDK you're using.
But-- and we're very pleased
to tell you about this--
SwiftUI is adding support
for universal links this year too.
And that looks a little like this,
no matter which platform or SDK you use.
For more information about
the enhancements to SwiftUI this year,
please check out "What's New in SwiftUI."
It's really exciting that we now have
universal links on watchOS
and when using SwiftUI.
We also have new features available
across all our platforms.
We'd like to tell you about them now.
First, a quick refresher
about how pattern matching works
with universal links.
You can use the asterisk
and question mark characters
in your pattern strings
to specify wildcards.
Asterisk matches zero
or more characters and does so greedily.
It will match as many characters
as possible.
Question mark matches
exactly one character.
To match at least one character,
use question mark followed by asterisk.
For more information
about pattern matching
using wildcard characters,
please take a look at last year's video.
And now, on to the cool new stuff.
The first new feature
we'd like to announce today
is support for case-insensitive
pattern matching.
We've had a lot of requests
for this feature.
Let's say you have a pattern
like this one.
It will match any path that starts
with the path component "sourdough"
and at least one character afterward.
However, it can only match
the lowercase word "sourdough."
So, to support all possible mixes
of uppercase and lowercase letters,
you might want to add patterns
for each combination of characters.
But actually, you might not.
There's such a thing
as too much sourdough.
But you don't have to worry about
carb comas anymore,
because we are introducing a new key
in the components dictionary:
caseSensitive.
Set its value to "false" to disable
case-sensitive pattern matching
and to enable case-insensitive
pattern matching.
Case-insensitive pattern matching
is available today
with macOS Catalina 10.15.5 and iOS 13.5.
Next up, let's talk Unicode.
URLs are always ASCII.
When you encounter a URL
with non-ASCII Unicode characters,
what's happening behind the scenes
is that you're actually encountering
percent-encoded characters
like you see here.
The string is converted to UTF-8,
and then the hexadecimal representation
of each byte in the UTF-8 sequence
is emplaced in the URL.
This is the name of a tasty Szechuan dish
called "ants crawling on logs,"
but even a fluent Chinese reader would
have trouble telling that from this URL.
Wouldn't it be nice if this pattern could
contain actual Chinese characters?
Good news: Now it can.
Add the key percentEncoded
to your components dictionary
and set its value to "false."
This disables percent-encoding,
meaning that your pattern is matched
as a sequence
of 32-bit Unicode code points
instead of 7-bit ASCII characters.
Support for Unicode is available
in macOS Big Sur and iOS 14.
And, of course, you can use
both percentEncoded and caseInsensitive
in the same pattern.
We support case-insensitive
Unicode pattern matching.
But this can get a little repetitive,
as we have percentEncoded
specified twice here
and caseSensitive specified twice too.
You can now add "defaults,"
a dictionary containing values
to apply by default to all patterns
unless a pattern explicitly overrides it.
Once we add this key,
we can remove the percentEncoded
and caseSensitive keys
from each individual component.
That's a lot cleaner.
If it's a sibling of components,
it will apply to all patterns
in that components array.
If it's a sibling of "details,"
it will apply to all universal links
for this domain.
And the defaults key is available
for macOS Big Sur and iOS 14,
along with Unicode support.
Now let's look at a pattern-matching story
from the real world.
This is based on a true story.
My colleague Jonathan and I
are building a food-ordering app
that you briefly saw back when we were
talking about watchOS support.
Here's a URL that we would like to
pattern-match against.
It contains a locale code,
consisting of a two-letter language code,
an underscore
and a two-letter country code.
This is followed by a product name,
one of several food items
sold on our website
and in our corresponding app.
A simple pattern that would
reasonably match a URL like this one
looks like what you see here.
Remember, the question marks
match single characters,
and a question mark
followed by an asterisk
matches one or more characters.
But this pattern will match more URLs
than we want.
What about countries
where we don't operate,
languages we don't support,
and products we don't sell?
This pattern would match all of them.
Our first attempt at pattern matching
involved hard coding
the list of possible values
we wanted to match against,
and that might have worked
if we had a small number of regions
and languages that we supported
and just a handful of products.
But thanks to Jonathan's hard work,
we operate in over 100 countries
around the world.
Once we added the products we sell,
all heck broke loose.
If we just consider
every two-letter language code,
every two-letter region code
and four products,
we're already looking at 1.8 million
possible patterns to match against,
and they take up over 27 megabytes.
That's because pattern matching
has exponential complexity.
We took a look
at this apple-app-site-association file
and said, "Let's do better."
We're happy to introduce
a new feature of universal links
that we call "substitution variables."
What are they? In a nutshell,
they are named lists of strings
that can be matched against.
These variables appear
in your pattern-matching strings
and represent any and all of the values
you specify.
Their names can contain
almost any character.
In a moment, you'll see why dollar signs
and parentheses are restricted.
Variable names are always case-sensitive
when encountered in a pattern.
The values you specify, on the other hand,
can contain question mark and asterisk
for wildcard matching
but can't reference
substitution variables.
They don't recurse.
The values are case-sensitive
if pattern matching is case-sensitive,
which is the default behavior.
If you have enabled
case-insensitive pattern matching,
then values will be matched accordingly.
To get you started, we've built in
some common substitution variables.
The first is alpha,
which is all upper and lowercase
ASCII letters.
You can see here why the dollar sign
and parentheses characters are restricted.
They're part of a variable's name
when referenced in a pattern.
"Upper" and "lower" are the uppercase
and lowercase ASCII alphabets.
"Alnum" is short for "alphanumeric"
and matches all ASCII letters
and the digits zero through nine.
"Digit" is decimal digits,
and "xdigit" is hexadecimal digits.
These variables are equivalent
to the similarly-named character classes
in the standard C library.
Next we have "region,"
which is every ISO region code
recognized by Foundation's Locale type.
And finally, we have "lang,"
which is every ISO language code.
Let's take a look at
the apple-app-site-association file
that we were worried about
a few slides back.
Here are all those patterns
as they appear within the full file.
Equipped with substitution variables,
we're now ready to wake up
from this combinatoric nightmare.
The first thing we'll do is to add
a new key-value pair under "applinks"
named substitutionVariables.
The value for that key is a dictionary.
The keys in that dictionary
are variable names,
and the values are arrays
containing sets of substrings to match.
The variable we've added here
is named "food"
and has four possible values.
And now we're going to use this variable
in these patterns.
Watch me make 27 megabytes disappear.
Wow. That's an obvious improvement.
We accomplished this feat by using
three substitution variables.
"Lang" and "region"
are predefined variables,
so we didn't need to define them
ourselves,
and "food" is the variable
we defined above.
You'll note that when defining
the variable,
its name is in quotation marks.
That's because that's the syntax
for JSON keys.
In a pattern, it's wrapped
with a dollar sign and parentheses.
So, we could ship this,
but we do have one problem:
We can't sell our app or our products
in Canada
because we've been having a lot of trouble
securing a supply of maple syrup.
So we'll add another pattern
before the one we have
to match the ISO region code CA,
which corresponds to Canada,
and we'll mark this pattern as "excluded,"
which tells the operating system
that if a URL matches this pattern,
it should not be opened by this app
as a universal link.
This way, we can still exclude individual
combinations of variable values.
However, Jonathan was born in Canada,
and he really wants to do business
back home,
so let's say we secure
that maple syrup supply.
Of course, all that syrupy goodness means
that Canada needs a different menu
than the other countries where we operate.
How can we handle special cases
in his substitution variables?
It's not hard. We just add
another variable, "Canadian food,"
specifically for Canada.
You'll notice right away that there's
some overlap between the menus,
and that's okay.
You'll also notice
we kept the exclusionary pattern we had.
If we were to remove it, then the last
pattern would match all values
from the "food" variable in Canada,
which we don't want to do.
So, we're almost ready
to deploy this file.
But Canada is a multilingual country.
Not everyone there speaks English.
At a minimum,
we should support English and French,
so we'll add the French translations
of those Canadian food names.
Oh, that looks weird.
One of the French food names
has an accented letter,
which means we need to deal with
percent encoding.
Let's clean that up.
Ah, much better.
We can use the percentEncoded key
we are introducing this year.
It allows us to use accented letters
directly in our patterns and variables.
We're done. And now I'm hungry.
But I won't have to wait long
to order lunch with this app,
because substitution variables
are available today
with the macOS Catalina 10.15.6
and iOS 13.5 updates.
Now that we've spent some time
talking about the contents
of the apple-app-site-association file,
let's talk about how it gets on
to your users' devices
and how we can improve that flow.
Let's say we have an iPad,
and we want to download an app.
We open the App Store
and select the app we want to download.
There it goes.
After the app is downloaded and installed,
the system checks its entitlements
and sees that it needs data
from one or more
apple-app-site-association files.
The device opens a connection
to the Web server
where that file is hosted
in order to download it.
Now, devices have limited bandwidth,
so if multiple files need to be downloaded
from multiple Web servers,
the device needs to download them
a few at a time.
The apple-app-site-association file
makes its way
from the Web server to the device,
is parsed by the Associated Domains
daemon,
and the app's universal links
become active.
Then the device moves on
to the next queued server and so forth.
But what if there's a problem
with the download?
Let's go back a few slides here
and try downloading that file again.
The device attempts to establish
a connection to the server.
But let's say the Wi-Fi goes down
or the server crashes
or the server is simply unreachable
from the device.
How far the download can proceed depends
on the exact nature of the failure,
but the data won't make it to the device.
Eventually,
the device has to give up on the download
and move on to the next server.
This leaves the device
in an inconsistent state,
where the app is installed
but its universal links
and other Associated Domains data
are not available.
This state can persist for hours or days,
until the system next attempts
to update the data for that app.
But I think we can do better here.
Let's go back a few slides again,
but this time with an ace up our sleeve.
Once again,
we pick an app on the App Store,
and it's downloaded onto this device.
This device sees that the app has
the Associated Domains entitlement,
but instead of connecting
to the associated Web server,
it connects to a content delivery network,
or CDN,
that manages Associated Domains data.
A CDN is a powerful tool
and can cache large amounts of data,
so it might already have the data
from this Web server stored.
But let's say it doesn't.
It can connect to the server
on behalf of this device.
But again, CDNs are powerful,
so it can connect to all the servers for
all apps on this device simultaneously.
It can download
the apple-app-site-association files
for all of these domains concurrently,
cache them,
and send the data to the device
with a single network connection.
This device is looking much happier
than it was the last time we tried this.
There are a number of reasons
we want to use a CDN here.
We've built a CDN dedicated
to just Associated Domains
and apple-app-site-association files,
so we can fine-tune it to deliver
the best experience to users.
Because a CDN caches data
from multiple Web servers,
we can use a single HTTP/2 connection
to request all the data we need
instead of a separate connection
for every Web server.
Caching reduces the total load
on your server
from potentially millions of requests
per day to just a handful.
And, because the CDN has a known-good,
known-fast connection,
users' experiences with your apps
are overall more reliable.
Beginning with macOS Big Sur and iOS 14,
your Web server will only receive requests
for your apple-app-site-association files
from Apple's CDN,
which lives on the public Internet.
However,
not all servers are created equal.
What if your Web server cannot be reached
from the public Internet?
Perhaps it's a Web server you use
for pre-deployment testing
or one intended only for use by employees
connected to your internal network.
How can you continue to support
these scenarios?
We've designed a few features
into our CDN support
that are here to help you,
and we call them "alternate modes."
Alternate modes allow you to bypass
the CDN
and directly connect to a domain
you control.
There are two alternate modes
in macOS Big Sur and iOS 14,
and they're distinguished
by when you would use them.
The first alternate mode
is called "developer mode,"
and it's designed for use
when you're building and testing your app
before you deploy it to TestFlight
or end users.
The second alternate mode
is called "managed mode"
and is for use when your app is installed
using an MDM profile.
We'll be focusing today on developer mode.
For more information
about managing your devices
and configuring your MDM profile,
watch "Managing Apple Devices."
The first big difference with
developer mode is that, when enabled,
you can use any valid SSL certificate
on your Web server,
even if it is not trusted by the operating
system's built-in certificate store.
This is more powerful than it sounds,
because without precautions,
it could allow
for a man-in-the-middle attack
that could leave your users vulnerable
to a number of security issues.
We require that a user opt in
to developer mode
on any device that uses it.
On iOS, watchOS and tvOS,
opting in looks similar to this.
Open the Settings app
and select Developer Settings.
They'll appear after your device
is connected for the first time
to a Mac running Xcode.
Under Developer Settings,
enable "Associated Domains Development."
This device is now configured
for developer mode.
On macOS,
the process is a little different.
Open Terminal
and enter the command you see here:
swcutil developer-mode -e true.
You'll be prompted for
an administrator password or Touch ID.
After granting permission,
developer mode is enabled.
This is a per-user operation.
Because developer mode is a global switch,
we don't want to enable it for all apps.
Only the app you're developing.
So it only takes effect for apps that
are signed with a development profile.
Apps signed for distribution
on the App Store or TestFlight
or Mac apps that have been signed
and notarized
cannot be used with this alternate mode.
Finally, developer mode and managed mode
require that you host
your apple-app-site-association file
in the .well-known directory,
not at the root of your domain.
That's a great summary of alternate modes
and how you enable one on a device.
But how do you tell the system that
your app should use that alternate mode
for a given domain?
Let's take a look at our
Associated Domains entitlement.
This entitlement currently has support
for www.example.com.
Pretty typical.
Now let's enable developer mode
and managed mode for this app.
We've added separate entitlement entries
for these alternate modes.
The domain names we've selected
are examples only.
They don't need to be distinct from your
public-facing domain or from each other.
The domain names you use
will be specific to your organization.
These new entitlement entries include
a query item with the name "mode"
and a value specifying
the alternate mode to use.
The first entitlement value
we added specifies
that this domain can be accessed
when in developer mode.
The second says that it can be accessed
in managed mode.
And the third?
This domain can be accessed
when this device is in both
developer and managed mode
at the same time.
You might want to use this configuration
when building your internal applications.
We've gone through
a lot of new stuff today.
We have support for watchOS with WatchKit
and all platforms with SwiftUI.
We've added several new
pattern-matching features,
including substitution variables,
to help you build efficient,
effective universal links.
And we've introduced a new CDN
that speeds up and streamlines the process
for downloading
your apple-app-site-association files.
We're looking forward to seeing what
you're able to build with these new tools.
Thank you.
[chimes]