Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, I'm Matthias Lerch,
and today I'm so excited to talk about
the digital version of car keys
now available in iOS.
With car keys, people can unlock, lock,
and start their car
using iPhone and Apple Watch.
Keys are stored securely
on their personal Apple device,
and you can delete them via iCloud.
And because they're digital,
it's easy to share keys with friends
or manage them remotely.
It can work
with different radio technologies.
This week we introduce support for NFC.
In the future, Ultra Wideband technology
will provide even more convenience.
The car key system is designed to work
without a network connection.
And after a long day of hiking, people can
still get into their car and drive home
because the feature works
with power reserve.
This session is geared towards automakers
interested in supporting digital car keys.
To work with this system,
your car needs to support owner pairing,
transactions and server interfaces.
Owner pairing is the first step
and is required to set up
a digital car key on iPhone.
Owner pairing establishes a privileged
and secure association
between the owner's iPhone and the car
using a short-range radio channel
such as NFC.
First, the user must prove
that they own the car.
The requirements here are defined by you,
the automaker.
Next, they initiate pairing.
The easiest way is to use an automaker app
that you provide.
For new cars, you can also send a welcome
e-mail containing a link to start pairing.
When the car is ready,
the user places iPhone
onto the car's NFC reader
in the dashboard.
As a fallback, you should also
provide an option
to start owner pairing
from within the car.
In this case, placing iPhone
onto the car's NFC reader
allows them to manually enter
a pairing pass code.
The pairing process
runs for a few seconds,
then the car key appears in Wallet,
ready to use.
Next, transactions.
Transactions are the heart
of the car key system.
Transactions are used
to unlock or lock the car
and to authorize engine start.
Cars must provide at least one
NFC reader in the door handle
and one in the dashboard.
Simply place iPhone near the door handle
to unlock or lock the door.
[chimes]
Of course, the pass will be customized
to match your car brand
and will look great.
And in the car, place the device
on the tray reader in the dashboard
to authorize engine start.
[chimes]
Transactions are optimized
for security and performance
to ensure a smooth user experience.
Express Mode lets the feature work
without Face ID or a pass code.
It's turned on by default,
but users who want additional security
can turn it off.
In this case, user authentication
is required for each relevant transaction.
All transactions work fully off-line.
You don't need a network connection
to drive your car.
And because transaction information
is not sent,
Apple doesn't know when you use your car.
Some feature, such as key sharing
and key management
do require a server connection.
Key sharing works with Messages on iPhone.
The car doesn't need to be online
when sharing,
and private information is encrypted.
So when the owner shares a key
with family members or friends,
Apple doesn't know any of it.
As the automaker, you can provide
different access levels for shared keys.
In this example, the car supports
two access levels for each key.
"Unlock and Drive" is unrestricted.
"Access and Drive Restricted"
limits the car speed to 65 miles per hour.
Again, it's up to each automaker
to define access levels.
Users can mange all keys on iPhone.
Owners can remove their own key
or revoke shared keys,
and the car
can provide similar functionality too.
Keys removed from a device
stop working immediately,
even if the device is off-line.
Family and friends
can only manage their own keys.
iCloud lost mode and remote card deletion
are fully supported.
And device upgrades are simple.
When the owner buys a new iPhone,
all they have to do
is to pair their new device with the car.
The key on their old iPhone is removed,
shared keys continue to work,
and everything is automatically
transferred to the new iPhone.
Now that we've introduced the feature,
let's look under the hood
and examine the system architecture,
radio technologies,
server integration and automaker apps.
Let's start by looking
at the system architecture.
The core features, pairing,
sharing and revocation
are supported natively on iOS.
Automaker apps are not required, even when
you share your keys with friends.
Cryptographic keys are generated
in the Secure Element on the device
and are never exported.
All features use standard AES
and elliptic-curve algorithms
for higher security and easy adoption
on any platform.
The system is based on Public Key
Infrastructure for off-line use.
And for simple server integration,
a Trusted Service Manager is not required.
Let's take a closer look
at this new digital car key.
Our goal was to bind keys
to the user's device,
and not to Apple or the automaker.
Therefore, an elliptic-curve key pair
is created in the Secure Element
on the iPhone.
The private key always stays
in the Secure Element.
The public key is exported in an X.509
certificate for authenticity verification.
An applet in the Secure Element
implements the car key.
The applet stores the key pair
and binds it to the car.
It implements transactions
and manages secure mailboxes which store
key attestations and security tokens
the prevent a revoked car key
from being reactivated.
Mailboxes also support immobilizer tokens
for compatibility
with existing car architectures.
For memory efficiency, all car keys
are hosted in a single applet instance.
A typical car key system
has some standard components.
Of course, we have iPhone and the car.
They communicate directly via NFC.
iPhone and the car
each have associated back-end systems.
The back-end systems are connected,
and there are times when the automaker app
needs to communicate with its server.
Let's use owner pairing as an example and
see how these components work together.
The automaker server generates a verifier
which is provisioned into the car
at production
or over a telematics link.
A matching pairing password
is made available to the owner
via an automaker app.
With the pairing password
and the verifier,
we can create a secure channel
for the pairing transaction.
We have chosen an elliptic-curve based
PAKE protocol with augmented security
and low memory requirements on car side.
At first, the vehicle sends
its identity certificates to the device.
The owner iPhone creates the owner key
in the car key applet
after successful certificate verification.
It then returns the identity certificates
of the new key
back to the car for acceptance.
From now on, car and device
are cryptographically linked together.
To register the key,
the owner iPhone sends encrypted data
to the automaker server
and receives a confirmation attestation.
Then the Apple server activates the key
in the device
and loads the pass into Wallet.
To enable the key on car side,
the device provides the confirmation
attestation to the car over NFC
during the owner pairing transactions.
If the device was off-line
during the owner pairing,
the attestation can also be provided later
during the first usage of the key.
Once iPhone is paired with the car,
transactions occur fully off-line.
No information
needs to be provided to the servers.
Next, I'd like to walk you
through key sharing.
With key sharing, there are two devices:
the owner iPhone and friend iPhone.
The owner starts by sending an invitation
using Messages.
The invitation
specifies the key configuration,
such as the access level and car identity.
The friend iPhone creates a new car key
based on the invitation.
Then it sends
the new key's identity certificate chain
back to the owner
via the Apple Identity Service, IDS.
This is not visible to the user.
The owner device
verifies the certificate--
We'll see in a minute how that works--
and issues
a signed confirmation attestation.
Similar to owner pairing,
the confirmation attestation
allows the car to accept the friend key.
The owner iPhone sends the attestation
back to the friend via IDS.
This is also not visible to the user.
If the car is off-line,
the friends presents
the registered confirmation attestation
during their first transaction
using their phone with the car.
They can now unlock and drive the car.
Note that if the car is online,
the attestation can also be transmitted
to the car during key registration.
Before we dive into the cryptography
of pairing, sharing and transactions,
let's review the complete life cycle
of a car key.
A car key is created through owner pairing
or key sharing.
Transactions lock and unlock the car,
authorize engine start,
and exchange encrypted data with the car.
iCloud Lost Mode temporarily suspends
car keys on iPhone or Apple Watch
by locking the car key applet
on the Secure Element.
The owner can revoke shared car keys
from their device or from the car UI.
And, of course, every key holder can
delete the car key on their device
at any time.
Certificates are the backbone
of car key life cycle management,
so it's worth having a deeper look
to see how they work.
Let's start with the car certificate
embedded in the car
and the owner's key certificate
created on iPhone during owner pairing.
The automaker can issue car certificates
from a regional or brand-specific CA,
which is represented
by an optional intermediate certificate.
All intermediate certificates
should be trusted by a single
root certificate for an automaker.
The public key of this root certificate
is embedded in the owner key
during the owner pairing process.
The automaker public key
is required for key sharing,
as we'll see in a minute.
Each owner key is trusted by an instance
CA located on the Secure Element.
We create one instance CA per automaker.
Note that the subject name
of the instance CA
links the automaker app
to all car keys for this automaker.
The device is registered
with the automaker
using the instance CA identifier.
When the owner signs out of iCloud
or erases their device,
the instance CA is deleted,
and the automaker is no longer able
to identify the device.
This protects user privacy.
The instance CA is trusted
by the Apple root certificate.
For each automaker, Apple will provide
the root certificate in a trusted way.
The automaker creates
the external CA certificate.
This certificate contains
the Apple root key
and is signed by the automaker.
The owner key is now trusted
by the automaker root.
The car is not required
to carry Apple's root certificate.
The automaker root certificate
is sufficient
to verify the authenticity
of a car key in a device.
The same certificates allow sharing
between secure elements.
The owner's iPhone sends an invitation
with a template for the friend's device
to create a key.
The friend's key is trusted
by the friend's instance CA.
The external CA connects the device
chain of trust to the automaker root.
As you remember, the owner key
embeds the automaker root
since it was provided by the car
at owner pairing.
The owner is now able to verify
the authenticity of a friend key.
Now let's look into transactions.
Fast and standard transaction
are variants of the same flow.
The flow is designed to adapt seamlessly
to any situation.
The standard transaction is used
to start the engine.
It also creates the keys
for the fast transaction.
We recommend to use the fast transaction
to unlock a car.
When a friend key is used
for the first time,
the door handle extends the fast
transaction to a standard transaction
and adds an exchange command to read the
friend key attestation from the mailbox.
Let's see how that works in detail.
When a key is used for the first time,
the car executes a standard transaction
on the door handle reader.
For this, the car sends
its unique identifier
and an ephemeral key to the device.
The car identifier is created by you,
the automaker,
to extract the real car identity,
such as the VIN.
The device responds with an ephemeral key.
For privacy protection,
the device does not send an identifier.
To provide information about the new key,
the device
must authenticate the car first.
The symmetric keys for future
fast transactions on the door handle
will now be calculated by the device.
The device then sends
its encrypted key identifier
and its signature to the car.
At this moment
of the standard transaction,
the car would normally authenticate
the device and start the engine.
But as this is the first transaction
with an unknown key,
the car checks if an attestation package
is present in the car key mailbox.
If there's no friend attestation,
then the user has most likely tapped
the device to the wrong car.
But if there is a friend key attestation,
then it is a new friend key
that the car doesn't know yet.
The car will obtain the friend's public
key, access level, and the owner signature
from the attestation.
On successful validation, the car stores
all those elements and unlocks the door.
Let's summarize
the security properties of transactions.
In the fast transaction,
the car authenticates the device.
Device tracking is not possible due to
the absence of any device identifier.
All exchanged sensitive data
are encrypted.
The standard transaction adds mutual
authentication between car and device.
To protect the device against tracking,
device identifiers are sent encrypted
only to a known car.
Forward secrecy protects transaction data
against future compromise.
Now that we've reviewed
the system architecture,
let's talk about the radio technologies
used to communicate
between iPhone and the car.
NFC operates with a standard reader
in the door handle and inside the car.
In addition, Apple's
Enhanced Contactless Protocol, or ECP,
enables a truly magical experience.
Whether you approach an NFC reader
on the car or a payment terminal,
we'll automatically use the matching path
from Wallet.
ECP works by identifying the reader type
and the make of the car
before a transaction even starts.
And fast and efficient reader polling
enables a good user experience.
In the future, Ultra Wideband technology
will enable a truly passive entry system
by providing secure ranging.
Simply unlock and start your car
while iPhone stays in your bag or pocket.
And because
the car key system is radio agnostic,
everything we covered about key management
remains the same.
The specification is currently
in draft form and will be available soon.
Okay, let's move on
to talk about server integration.
Although car keys work off-line,
servers are required
for remote key management.
First, your automaker server needs to
establish a reliable and secure connection
to Apple's back end.
This needs to be done
for each server environment,
such as testing and production.
Apple will provide
our car key root certificate
to you, the automaker, for cross-signing.
You send us back
your external CA certificate,
root certificate,
and certificate for privacy encryption
and signature verification.
One set of certificates is required
for each server environment.
We have defined a small set
of server interfaces
that need to be implemented and tested.
They allow you to register a new key,
remotely revoke keys,
and send important device notifications.
Passes represent your car keys in Wallet,
provide logo and background artwork
to match your company brand.
We supply a template and a portal
to make this easy for you.
Wallet passes are created automatically,
so you don't need to write code here.
Finally, your automaker app needs to
retrieve the owner pairing password
from your back end.
If you support deletion of keys
in your app,
you will need to send
the termination request via your server.
Let's talk more about automaker apps.
With automaker apps,
you can provide custom features
using keys stored in Wallet.
Your automaker app is also
a great way to start owner pairing.
The APIs are available to automakers only
and require an app entitlement.
For more information,
see the PassKit documentation.
There are many details
we didn't cover today,
including communication protocols,
hardware features and more.
If you're an automaker
and want to learn more,
your first step is to enroll in
the Car Connectivity Consortium, or CCC,
and get the digital key specification.
The CCC is a cross-industry organization
that deals with phone-to-car technologies
including standards for digital keys.
The NFC feature we discussed today
corresponds to version 2.0.
The upcoming version 3.0 supports
Ultra Wideband for passive entry.
The CCC includes 26 automakers,
representing even more brands
and over 80 suppliers
and technology partners.
You'll also need details
on supporting iPhone and Apple Watch,
transaction and system performance goals,
and integrating with Apple servers.
This will be provided
through the Apple MFi program.
If you are not already enrolled
in the MFi program,
go to the "Contact us" form to express
your interest in the car key feature.
We are really excited about digital keys
and letting people leave
their physical car keys at home.
We look forward to seeing this
in your cars soon.
Thank you for watching.