>> DANA: I painted
this one last -
>> SPEAKER: I can't
watch anymore TV.
>> JO: If you don't think
that the toilet paper
industry started this,
then you're f*****g crazy.
>> POPPY: Hello.
>> IAN: There
she is. Hey, Poppy.
I waited for you.
I waited for you this
time in the meeting.
>> POPPY: Nice one, mate.
>> IAN: Looks like somebody
did find that shower.
>> POPPY: I wanted
to look fancy.
>> IAN: Did you
wash your hair?
>> POPPY: Yes, I
washed my hair.
>> IAN: All right.
I'll keep my eye on it.
>> POPPY: Okay. Okay.
Alright, alright.
Okay, okay, okay, okay. Fine.
You know what I
actually did -
>> LOU: Guys? G*d d***it.
Guys. F**k. Good. There. Jesus.
Now, remember, this only works
if we all do our part, okay?
We get one shot at this so
don't f**k it up, Rachel.
No one can hear you.
It's paradise.
All right.
It looks like we're
ready at CW but Brad has
a quick announcement.
Whatever. Fine.
Brad, go.
>> BRAD: Yeah.
Hey, everybody.
So, I had this bet with
David and well, he totally
sandbagged and lost on
purpose, but then we made
the stakes really high and
we played one final time and
well, I still beat his a**.
>> SPEAKER: Oh. David.
>> SPEAKER: David,
is that you?
>> DANA: You look weird.
>> SPEAKER: You
look like an egg.
>> DAVID: I know I
look weird, okay.
>> SUE: You look
like a baby turtle.
>> LOU: Wait, is that
David or Sandy Duncan?
>> DAVID: But it'll grow
back in like eight or
ten months.
I don't know.
Has anyone ever
shaved their eyebrow?
I don't know how
long that takes.
Does it grow back?
Whatever.
It doesn't matter.
I just - I feel bad that
I lost the $300,000
for charity.
>> BRAD: I already
donated it.
>> DAVID: What?
>> BRAD: Yeah, I was
always going to donate it.
>> DAVID: What?
>> BRAD: Ian doubled it.
>> IAN: Yo.
>> DAVID: But why?
I thought you were opposed
to giving away money?
>> BRAD: No, no, no.
I told you I need to get
something out of it
which I did.
Your dignity.
That's $600,000 for charity.
Way to go, David.
>> SPEAKER: Way
to go, David.
>> SPEAKER: Good job, David.
>> DAVID: Thanks, guys.
>> SPEAKER: It all
worked out, right?
>> RACHEL: Actually, since
we're all here, I think it
would be really nice to -
>> LOU: Oh, God.
Here comes some boring
SJW rant about -
>> RACHEL: You know what?
F**k you, Lou, okay.
You're being such a d**k.
Oh, s**t.
I think I started it.
>> IAN: Wait, what?
>> LOU: Go.
Go, go, go, go, go.
Oh, s**t. It's working.
>> DANA: Wait, where's CW?
>> SPEAKER: Where is he?
>> RACHEL: Come on, dude.
>> BRAD: C-dubs. Come on.
>> IAN: Come on, man.
>> JO: Where is he?
>> POPPY: Oh my God.
>> IAN: Come on.
>> JO: Come on.
>> CW: Huzzah.
>> LOU: Yes.
>> CW: I made it.
>> SPEAKER: C-dubs,
you the man.
>> CW: F**k you,
coronavirus.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Hey there, everybody.
Thank you for having a few
of us from the Mythic Quest
team here today in the
all-new WWDC virtual world.
Joining me are Charlotte
Nicdao who plays Poppy.
Imani Hakim who plays Dana.
Danny Pudi who plays Brad.
And Megan Ganz who
is the co-creator and
executive producer.
Okay. Let's jump in with
the first question.
This comes from Michael
from Phoenix, Arizona.
Michael says Mythic Quest is
absolutely my favorite show.
That's a great start.
That's a great start
to this entire thing.
>> BRAD: I'm loving
this question.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Mythic
Quest is absolutely my
favorite show
centered on development.
>> MEGAN GANZ: Oh.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: That
seems a little bit more -
that seems -
>> MEGAN GANZ:
We're the only one.
We're the only one, so.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Fine. We'll take it.
Michael, we'll take it.
It feels so true to life.
I'm curious how many
consultants you worked with
on creating the scripts?
Meg, you want to take that?
>> MEGAN GANZ: Yeah.
Well, our first and
foremost, like, our partners
in Mythic Quest are Ubisoft.
So, we had constant
communication with them.
They were in the
writers room with us.
They were guiding the whole
process, letting us know -
introducing us to the world.
On top of that, they also
facilitated people from many
different studios
coming to visit us.
We had programmers.
We had a
monetization expert.
We had writers.
We had all sorts of
different people come in
and talk to us.
My favorite of all of those
people was the first female
coder we spoke with who was
just as surly as I wanted
her to be.
She was suffering no fools
and not mincing words about
her experience and I
absolutely loved every
second of talking to her.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: That was
a really fun experience
because she
seemed very upset.
>> MEGAN GANZ: Yeah.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: She was
very upset, I think mostly
by the portrayal that she
had seen of programmers on -
on various television shows
or movies that we had seen
and she was like, you
guys better get it right.
So, I hope we got it right.
Okay. This comes from Patricia
from Oakland, California.
I freaking love watching
- I mean, two for two.
Two for two.
I freaking love -
it's a good start.
I freaking love watching the
dysfunctional relationship
between Poppy and Ian.
It's honestly so validating
to see conversations I
witnessed over my career
acted out on screen.
As you were developing these
characters, what's one thing
that struck you as truly
bizarro in tech culture?
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: You
know, one thing that did
feel bizarre to me,
especially with Ian and
Poppy's relationship, is
like, the - the fact that
she literally builds
everything and yet he's
considered to be the genius.
I enjoyed playing with that
in their relationship.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay.
This is a question that
comes from Valentin from
Mössingen, Germany.
As a fifteen-year-old that
is heavily inspired by
books, movies, and TV shows,
what are some of your tips
for getting into the
business of storytelling,
particularly through
movies and TV shows?
>> IMANI HAKIM: I would say
no matter where you are in
the world, to find your
community, find people who
are already involved in
the space that you want to
operate in, and read books.
Study.
Watch more movies like
you're already doing.
But I think mainly just find
the community where you can
learn and pick up new tools
from people who are already
involved in it.
>> DANNY PUDI: I
would say, yeah.
Practice telling your story.
I think that's
really important.
The more you work on
telling your story or just
storytelling in general,
whether that's working on
videos for your family or
practicing jokes in the
bathroom in front of your
mirror, not that I do that.
I have some
friends who do that.
But those things all help
you hone in on your voice,
so I think that's good.
And then yeah, like what
Imani said, is find
your people.
Find people who are working
on aspects of storytelling
that you're not, so
writers, directors.
Form a little crew and work
together to help each other
get better.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Next
question comes from Russia.
All right.
Ilya from Moscow, Russia.
Lots of love from Russia.
My question is, do any of
the cast members have any
coding experience
at all in real life?
Anybody?
>> IMANI HAKIM: No.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: When I
- when I got cast, I signed
up to a - to a - like an
online school, like free
coding school called Code
Academy, thinking like, I
would, you know, just learn
the basics and then I'd have
like a kind of understanding
that I could use in my
portrayal of the character.
And I think I tried to do
one lesson before I was
like, no. I can't do it.
And I still get emails from
them being like, pick up
where you left off.
And it makes me feel really
guilty and really stupid.
>> MEGAN GANZ: I learned
the words server/client
architecture.
I don't know what it means
but I know it's a thing that
I think
programmers care about.
We - we need to get better
about it because - because
we have partners in Ubisoft,
what we do is in the script,
whenever there are moments
where Poppy needs to
describe what it is that
she's actually doing, we
just write the word haptics
over and over because we
heard that word once
and we were like, oh,
that sounds techy.
So, we just write haptics,
haptics, haptics and then
the good people at Ubisoft
go through the scripts and
replace those with actual
language that you might use.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay.
Oh, here's a question
from Portugal.
From Viseu, Portugal.
This person's name is João.
And they would like to know,
which episode did you have
the most fun filming?
Imani, which episode did you
have the most fun filming?
>> IMANI HAKIM: Oh.
I would say all of the
episodes were really fun but
I think the one that stands
out to me the most obviously
is the - the
montage episode.
Was that number
two, I believe?
Episode number two.
Rachel and Dana, they have
this fun montage and it was
just really fun to
shoot and it's one of my
favorite memories.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Hey, Danny.
I have a question for you
and it - and it hails from
Melbourne, Australia.
And yes, Charlotte, you'll
get an opportunity to answer
it as well.
But I don't know.
>> CHARLOTTE
NICDAO: Melbourne.
>> DANNY PUDI: Charlotte,
you can take any Chicago
questions from now on.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: Good.
I've been studying up.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: If you
were to create an app or
a game, what would it be
and why, asks Yuma from
Melbourne, Australia.
>> DANNY PUDI: One app that
I actually use, I use this
app which is a plant
recognition app that I love
and it is - literally I just
ride my bike around the
neighborhood and I take out
my phone and I'm like, look
at that tree.
I wonder what kind
of tree that is.
And I like, snap a picture
of it and they're like, oh,
this is a pepper tree.
I'll be like oh, wow.
That's so cool.
And that's super
exciting for me.
So, I think something
dealing with like, plants or
maybe how to successfully
make plants live would be
really kind of
cool for me to do.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay, so,
Charlotte, it's clear that
Danny blew that opportunity
to take a question.
So, we're going to - we're
going to kick it to you,
being from
Melbourne, Australia.
We'll ask it again.
If you were to create an app
or a game, what would it
be and why?
And how would it be
different from Danny's
plant app?
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: Okay,
see, I actually have an
answer to this question.
And it's going to - it's on
record now that it's my idea
so if anyone steals it,
you know that it was me.
It's a dating app but
instead of like, answering
questions about
yourself, you get shown
a series of memes.
You decide which memes you
think are funny and then you
get matched with people who
also find those memes funny.
>> DANNY PUDI: Oh.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: And
it's called - I'm trying to
think of a pun on the fly.
It's called You and Meme.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
That's pretty good.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: It'll
have a better name than that.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay, so,
this comes from DJ from Ann
Arbor, Michigan.
What apps did you use to
shoot the quarantine episode?
I believe I can answer that.
We used - for our camera
app, we used something
called Filmic Pro version
6.10.9 I believe.
And it's just
incredibly easy to use.
But what you're seeing mixed
with the hardware of the
iPhone has created a
professional grade look that
you saw in the
quarantine episode.
And then the audio was - was
an app called MOTIV Audio
version 2.62.1 or something
like that which would just
be the most recent version.
And again, it worked
really seamlessly with the
camera package.
And a mic system - that
hardware there was called
Shure Mic MV88 Plus.
And that worked really
seamlessly with the hardware
as well and - and really,
that's - that's how we
achieved 99.9% of the -
of the technical elements
of the show.
So, that's the boring stuff.
Now moving on.
Well, it's Developers
Conference so you kind of
want the boring stuff.
So, we'll mix it
in a little bit.
This is a question from
Leonard from Singapore.
Charlotte, is there
a scene that you personally
really liked?
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: No.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Great. Moving on.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO:
Yes. So many scenes.
My top - my top scenes, I
loved shooting the mocap
stuff in the masked man
episode with you, Rob.
And I also loved
- you know what?
I'm realizing now all my
favorite scenes are when I
got to wear silly costumes
because I also loved
shooting at the streamer
conference, pretty much
anything where I got to wear
that masked man costume and
especially the scene where
I was sitting in a beanbag.
Like, I don't think I even
had any lines in that scene.
I just enjoyed sitting in
that beanbag in my costume.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: The next
question is from Henry from
Kensington, Maryland.
Danny, for the quarantine
episode, you had to be your
own lighting designer,
audio team, camera person,
et cetera.
Which crew role did you turn
out to be a natural at and
which one not so much?
>> DANNY PUDI:
Great question.
So, another app that I'm
working on is the best place
to take a picnic and it's
designed to look at -
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Okay. Moving on.
Thank you, Danny.
Thank you, Danny, for that.
Imani.
>> IMANI HAKIM: Yes?
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: For the
quarantine episode, you had
to be your own lighting
designer, audio team, camera
person, et cetera.
Which crew role did you turn
out to be a natural at and
which one not so much?
>> IMANI HAKIM: I would
say I was - I was the most
natural at maybe
sound and the glam.
I think because - I've had
more practice at doing my
own makeup so that came a
little bit more natural.
And the things that I wasn't
the most natural at is for
some reason we had to check
our settings multiple times
and it just - I
couldn't remember.
So, I applaud all of the DPs
and all of the hard workers
in the crew because it
was - it was weird for me.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Charlotte?
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: I'm
the opposite of Imani.
I was absolutely the bane of
our hair and makeup team's
existence, I think.
Even getting ready for
this today was just a
nightmare for them.
I don't know why.
I think - I was joking with
Thea, our makeup artist,
that my sister started
doing makeup when she was
a teenager so she's really
good at it and I started
doing makeup like since
quarantine started and I had
to start doing it myself
for stuff like this.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Imani,
this is a question again
from Australia and we're
just not going to let
Charlotte answer
any of these.
Jimmy in Sydney, Australia
asks, you used multiple
iPhones to shoot
this, right?
I'm curious on how to
control all of them at the
same time and how the
director was able to see the
shooting in
progress in real-time.
Imani, can you maybe just
walk us through from your
perspective, what it was
like and how we - how we
created the setup in
which we could work?
>> IMANI HAKIM: Yeah.
So, Apple sent over a ton of
equipment for the actors to
use, from iPhones to sound
equipment to lighting.
And the way that we were
able to have Rob direct the
episode and see everything
that's going on, we had - we
had all the crew members and
the actors in the scenes on
Zoom where we would have our
iPhones on this really cool
contraption and it would -
it would show the screen to
the people in the Zoom and
they were able to watch what
we were doing
through the iPhones.
It's a lot but it worked
really, really great.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: And from
your perspective, one of the
things I keep getting asked
about was because also we
were - we were communicating
through AirPods, and a lot
of - and we could barely see
each other because even in
the rig that we have setup
right now, we can't really
see each other because
we're blocked by so many
different things.
And people were asking, what
was it like to work with not
only your other
actors in a scene but
also direct people?
And I found that in some
ways, it was a little bit
more intimate because you're
so - obviously as actors,
we're trained to listen to
what other people are saying
and react to that.
But oftentimes what happens
is because of so much
nonverbal communication,
you're assuming what a
person is going to say or
you're feeling it before
they even say it and it
doesn't necessarily allow
for you to listen to the
extent that you could
or should be.
And when you're limited
by not being able to see
somebody but just hear them,
it almost opens up another
form of communication
because you have to really
pay attention to every
word and to the tenor
of their voice.
Did - did all of you guys
find something similar?
>> IMANI HAKIM: Yeah.
I think to your point, Rob,
I think it - like you said,
it really forces you to
sort of drop in and be more
connected than what - what
you would usually be.
Like, we're pretty - we're
pretty connected on set but
there was something about
this where we know that
we're counting on each other
through the scene to get
this story across, to get
this scene across in a way
with barriers that we've
never experienced before.
So, it's almost like it
forces you to have this
sense of camaraderie and
community and to show up for
each other in ways that you
didn't necessarily expect.
>> DANNY PUDI: Yeah.
I would say also, it does
make you listen a little bit
more to the rhythm of scenes
in terms of how lines are
coming through.
There is this sort of
delicate balance of making
sure that we're speaking in
a way that is natural but
also not overlapping too
much, not - I think there
was just a little bit
of a worry on my part of
sometimes the wi-fi signal
not being super strong and
worried that I either missed
the end of the line or
I jumped it.
And so, there's this like,
hyper listening but also
just sort of like, almost
like at times, I was just
relying on sort of like an
instinct of jumping in on a
line just when I felt like I
think this is the right time
to say this line.
But you're just hyper
aware of people finishing
thoughts, right?
And so, that was kind of
a really interesting game
within the game.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Great.
Meg, this one comes from
Tukwila, Washington.
A gentleman named Rick wants
to know what is the most
valuable lesson you've
learned about the industry?
>> MEGAN GANZ: I would say
like the presence of women
in the video game industry.
I - I had no - I kind of - I
had no idea that there were
such an equivalent amount of
women playing video games
and I guess you just don't
hear about it and it feels
like a lot, when I was
growing up, the marketing
was so directed towards
men that I guess I always
assumed that that
was who was playing.
And now, I'm being - my
eyes are being opened to an
entire world of women not
only playing these games but
also making them and - and
Ashly Burch who plays Rachel
on the show who is you know,
heavily involved in the
gaming community and has
done voice overs for a lot
of great games, has
introduced me to a couple
games that are just, I feel,
a little bit more feminine
oriented and that I just
sort of didn't understand
that there was that
space in gaming.
So, it's been
a real delight.
Also, just the narrative
that modern games, like,
their ability to tell
complex and meaningful and
deep stories.
I mean, we - my husband and
I are just playing The Last
of Us 2 now and it is,
I mean, breathtaking.
Like, I can't play it before
I go to bed because it has
that much of an effect on me
and I previously I guess,
only thought that that was
possible with movies and TV.
So, that's been
real eye opening.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: This
hails from Charlotte, North
Carolina which again, we
will not allow Charlotte
to answer.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: But -
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: From
Nick, the most unexpected
response you've gotten from
someone about the show.
And I'm kidding.
Charlotte, handle it. Go.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: Oh, I want
to think about it though.
Does anyone have an
answer quicker than me?
Wait, what was the question?
I was just thinking
about my name.
>> DANNY PUDI:
It's Charlotte.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY:
Your name is Charlotte.
>> DANNY PUDI:
It's Charlotte.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Yeah.
>> DANNY PUDI: It's
always - right?
It's always been?
>> CHARLOTTE
NICDAO: Yeah, yeah.
>> DANNY PUDI: Still is.
>> MEGAN GANZ: Danny,
can you make an app for
Charlotte that can remember
her name for her so that she
doesn't have to waste
valuable time remembering
what her name is?
>> DANNY PUDI:
Already on it.
Name rememberer.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay.
I'll repeat the question.
Nick from Charlotte, North
Carolina would like to know,
what's the most unexpected
response you've gotten from
someone about the show?
Anybody?
Anybody not named Charlotte
or named Charlotte?
>> MEGAN GANZ: My mom really
likes it which I wasn't
necessarily expecting
because the past shows that
I've worked on, she usually
says they talk too fast.
That's her major complaint.
And I feel like we talk
pretty fast on the show but
she still really likes it.
She's never played
video games and has no
interest in them.
So, I think she just likes
CW and she's just showing up
for that which is great.
We'll take it.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: I think
for - for me, I think it was
- I believe it was the same
day, I saw two tweets in
support of the show, one
from Elon Musk and one from
Barry Jenkins.
I thought that was a really
great day for the show.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: Yeah.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay. Megan
Ganz, we have a question
from Wilton, Connecticut.
John Paul wants to know what
was the most eye-opening
slash surprising thing
about shooting on iPhones?
>> MEGAN GANZ: Oh, well, I
had some experience shooting
on iPhones before because
I did an episode of Modern
Family that was shot about
half on iPhones and -
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: We're not
here to talk about your Emmy
winning endeavors, okay?
We're here to talk
about your Apple show on
Mythic Quest.
So - Meg likes - Meg likes
to bring up all of the shows
she won Emmys for except
for the ones that she works
with me on.
>> MEGAN GANZ:
All of them. One.
I - aside from that
award-winning show,
my experience, I mean, it's
kind of incredible, the ease
at which - the - how
easy they are to use.
I mean, I have zero idea of
what I'm doing as a director
of photography, even
maybe less than I know
about programming.
And the fact that with just
a few settings on the phone,
we can produce footage that
looks absolutely equivalent
to the footage that we get
from on set with the giant
cameras is just phenomenal.
You know, it's - it's really
- has removed all barriers
to the - to the
filmmaking process.
It's - if you would have
told people thirty years ago
that they would have gotten
this kind of quality out of
a phone that's in their
pocket, they just would have
never believed you.
So, I mean, it was a
fantastic experience for me.
I am actually planning at
the moment, of shooting some
more stuff on iPhones
that's not even - not even
necessarily when we're in
quarantine because I just
was so pleased
with the result.
So, I encourage anybody that
is thinking about making
something, especially if you
are looking at getting into
the industry, I don't think
you should wait to make your
mistakes once
you've gotten the job.
I think you should start
shooting things now, edit
them together, see
what they look like.
Shoot it again.
Reedit it.
Like, see where your
mistakes are because you'll
be developing skills and
making your mistakes when it
doesn't count and then
hopefully when you get the
opportunity to make a cool
episode like we did, you'll
have gotten some of those
mistakes out of your system.
>> ROB MCELHENNEY: Okay.
Well, that seems like a
great place to finish up.
Again, on behalf of the
entire Mythic Quest team,
thank you for having us
at the WWDC this year.
Have a great time.
>> DANNY PUDI: Thank you.
>> MEGAN GANZ: Bye.
>> DANNY PUDI: Bye everyone.
>> IMANI HAKIM:
Happy Dub-Dub.
>> CHARLOTTE NICDAO: Dub-Dub.