[Presenter] Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Lawrence and I work on
NFC software here at Apple.
Today we will go over the changes
in our existing APIs.
These changes follow some of the new
published Swift guidelines.
We have also expanded our APIs
for the ISO15693 tag
used in NFCTagReaderSession.
First, let's start with an overview
of Core NFC.
You may recall our creative salmon
from our last year WWDC presentation.
By the way, his name is Kevin.
Today I have brought Kevin with me
and here is the coupon tag.
Core NFC allows your app to read
this NFC tag using an iPhone.
[phone beeps]
NFC is also used in other places,
such as on parking meters, scooter rental,
electric car charging station,
ordering menu in restaurant, et cetera.
Core NFC allows an app to read an NFC tag
in a session lasting up to 60 seconds.
This has been supported on iPhones
since the iPhone 7.
Beginning on the iPhone XS,
tags can also be read in the background
while the screen is on, if the NFC forum
NDEF message contains a universal link.
Once the user has tapped
on the notification banner shown on screen
that NDEF message will be sent
to your application
as an NSUserActivity via
UIApplicationDelegate restorationHandler.
Texts may contain a NFC forum NDEF message
or other proprietary data set.
Core NFC supports NDEF reading and writing
as well as other native tag protocols.
The easiest path for tag access is to use
the NFCNDEFReaderSession.
Core NFC supports NDEF reading and writing
as well as other native tag protocols.
The easiest path for tag access is to use
the NFCNDEFReaderSession.
But Core NFC also supports raw tag
communication via ISO7816,
FeliCa, MIFARE and ISO15693.
Next, let's talk about some changes
to the Swift syntax
to make it easier to understand
your Core NFC code.
Core NFC now adopts the use
of the Result enum in our tag APIs,
specifically how parameters are returned
in our completion handler.
Let's look at the ISO7816-tag-send-command
as an example.
Before iOS 14, the method signature
accepts a closure with four arguments
as the completion handler.
Your application will need to check
the optional error object
to determine if an error occurs.
If the operation succeeds,
you may then parse the rest of arguments
to collect the results.
The new signature in iOS 14 returns
a Result enum
of either a NFCISO7816-Response-APDU
object on success,
which is the result of reading the tag,
or an error object on a failure.
The Result enum can be easily handled
using a switch statement as shown.
Now let me show you how it looks in Xcode.
I've opened the NFCFishTag sample project
from WWDC 2019.
Here, in CouponViewController,
the write function is shown
in its existing form.
Let's replace the send-MIFARE-command
using its new Result signature.
Here, in the new code,
the data object is handled in this section
of a switch statement.
An error is handled over here.
We have also made a few changes
to the existing enum values
to improve readability.
For example,
the ResolveFlag enum has been changed
to refer specifically to ISO15693.
Some other new enums
have been added as well.
Please refer to the documentation
for more details.
Now we will talk about new capabilities
we've added
to the NFC-ISO15693 tag protocol.
We have added the enhancement defined
by the ISO15693 specification
third edition 2019.
These functions are useful for tags
with larger memory sizes
and security operations.
We have also included
a new generic send command
if you would like to send arbitrary
data packets for your application.
Here is a complete list
of the enhancement function signatures
under the NFC-ISO15693Tag protocol.
We now support the following operations:
fast reading multiple blocks,
extended write multiple blocks,
authenticate, key update,
challenge, read buffer,
extended get multiple blocks
security status,
extended fast read multiple blocks
and send request.
That's what new in Core NFC this year.
We look forward to seeing
what you can make with it.