Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name's Mark Mikin,
and I'm the Siri Experience Evangelist
here at Apple.
I know this is WWDC,
but it wouldn't quite be WW
if we didn't have a session
about why you should build something
in addition to all the awesome videos
we've made about how to build it.
And this is one of those "why" sessions.
In particular, we want to talk about
something we call system intelligence
from a few different perspectives
and over the course of a few videos.
First we'll define it, and then
I'll talk about how it relates to design
and then how it's powered
by extensibility.
So now let's explain
what we mean when we say
"the intelligent system experience."
You've probably heard terms
at previous WWDCs
like "proactive,"
and being proactive is a key part of this.
Another piece of it is Siri,
which is why I,
the Siri Experience Evangelist,
am here talking to you.
So over the course
of the next several videos,
my colleagues at Apple, the ones
that actually work on these technologies,
will help me define
just exactly what we mean
when we say
"intelligent system experience"
and what you can do
to be a part of that system.
Let's get started
with the most basic definition,
which we'll build on
throughout these videos.
I found the simplest way to explain it
is that it's how the operating system
works with the apps
that people use every day
to make "the everyday" easier for people.
And that's intelligence.
Now, it's easy to view the features
we place under this umbrella,
like Voice and Siri Suggestions,
as a convenience.
It makes something easier,
and you could keep doing it
the hard way if you wanted,
but that's not quite the right way
to look at it.
Intelligence should be viewed
as a design practice.
In fact, it's a design that's, in a way,
alive.
So let's talk about this concept
of a living design.
What do we mean by that?
Well, ultimately,
what's the core job of a designer?
It's to help people accomplish something.
And one of the key ways
a designer enables this
is by leveraging the familiar.
Take this, for example:
the "share" button.
When someone using an app
wants to share something,
how is this capability conveyed
to the person using the app?
By using a signifier, or a symbol.
In the case of iOS,
someone can easily recognize this symbol
because it consistently gets used
across our apps and yours.
In other words,
it's a platform convention.
And guess what?
Intelligence is a platform convention too.
It's something enabled and reinforced
by its consistent appearance
on the platform.
But unlike other forms of design,
intelligence isn't a static glyph or icon
like the "share" button.
It's alive.
It manifests itself
by adapting to how the system,
the platform,
conforms to how people use their devices.
No two people's Siri Suggestions
or conversations with Siri are alike.
And what's needed or suggested
can change at any second.
The more we do that,
with the help of your apps,
the more people's expectations change.
People expect their devices and the apps
installed on them to be smart.
And "smart" is clearly a loaded term,
as is "intelligence."
We all know that people get frustrated
when their expectations aren't met.
When something doesn't feel as smart
or as helpful as they think it should be,
they don't care if it's the system
or the app's fault.
It just doesn't feel quite right.
So as an app developer,
you have a big responsibility.
After all,
apps are a key piece of this story
through something we call extensibility.
Before we go deeper on how intelligence is
powered by an app through extensibility,
let's first define what an app even is.
The simplest way to look at it
is that an app is an app icon,
and when I tap on it,
I get this awesome experience.
When I swipe away, I close the app,
and then I'm done.
The next time I want to use that app,
I tap on the app icon again,
and I'm right back in.
And for many people,
that's still how they use an app today.
But apps have actually been evolving
over time,
and that's something
that we've been working toward for years.
Like when we debuted the very first
app extensions six years ago
at WW 2014.
And when we debuted SiriKit at WW 2016,
we used that same foundation
of app extensions
to allow apps to work with Siri
for the very first time.
And then there were shortcuts,
and now we have the new widgets
and app clips.
And it's not like we've been building
a bunch of software features
just to make the operating system better.
A lot of the technologies that are
foundational to the intelligent system
were actually built to help
our growing ecosystem of devices.
Like with Handoff, which first started
with iPad, iPhone and Mac,
but was really crucial
for enabling Apple Watch.
And the next thing you know,
we have this intelligent glue
that ties together all of our devices
and apps and the operating system
to make everyday stuff easier for people.
And this intelligent system
we're building with your help
is built from the ground up
from a foundation
of respecting your privacy.
You'll hear more about that later,
but no intelligent system
is worth sacrificing
a fundamental human right for.
Now, in the following videos,
we'll try and cover system intelligence
from a few different angles.
First up,
we'll expand on this common theme
of how intelligence,
paired with extensibility,
allows for quick interactions
that save people time.
We'll also walk through how we measure
a successful intelligent interaction
and how there's a measurable impact
on the value people get out of your apps.
Then we'll walk you through how,
without even knowing it,
people can benefit from intelligence
features throughout their user journey
to help people become more proficient
at taking advantage
of their phones and their apps.
Sometimes
even before they download an app.
Then a few more of our colleagues
will talk you through
some of the underlying technologies
that power it.
There are three key concepts
that are consistent throughout,
and we'll show you
how you can use just a few APIs
to provide a lot of value to people.
So, without further ado,
check out the next video,
where my colleague JP
will talk about the opportunity at hand.
Thanks for watching.