Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, I'm Baskaran. I'm an engineer
on the Apple Education team.
Today, my coworker Daniel and I
would like to update you
on the latest changes to ClassKit.
First, I'll show you enhancements
we have made to ClassKit,
enhancements that will enable you
to provide rich details
about content in your apps.
Then I will go over
some recommended best practices
for adopting ClassKit.
After that, Daniel will introduce you
to a new way to report your content
using a service
called ClassKit Catalog API.
And finally, he will go over
some recommended best practices
for adopting ClassKit Catalog API.
Let me begin with a brief overview
of ClassKit.
It's a core component
of Apple education ecosystem.
It's a framework that enables you to
surface educational content in your apps
as activities that teachers can use
in assignments for their students.
ClassKit enables your app
to report progress
as students work on their assignments.
And most importantly, it does this while
protecting the privacy of the students
by only reporting progress
on assigned activities.
For example, if a teacher assigns students
to read a chapter from Fun with Science
and a student also reads a chapter
from Basic Arithmetic,
the student and the teacher
will see progress
only on Fun with Science
because that was assigned reading.
ClassKit was introduced in 2018.
Now it's also available on macOS
for creating native and Catalyst apps.
For more information on ClassKit,
check out our 2019 session
"What's New in ClassKit"
and our 2018 session
"Introducing ClassKit."
Before I go into the enhancements,
let's take a quick look
at how content in your app
appears as assignable activities
in Schoolwork.
Your app defines the content
and describes it as activities
using ClassKit,
which can be browsed using Schoolwork.
With Schoolwork,
it's easy to share class materials,
get students to a specific activity
in an app,
collaborate with students
and view student progress.
When you open Schoolwork,
you'll land on this view
which serves as home base for all content
teachers assign to their students.
You tap on the New Handout button
on the top right to create a new handout.
Let me zoom in to make it easier to see.
Now, tap on the App Activities
to show the app activity chooser.
The app activity chooser shows
ClassKit-enabled apps
with App Activities.
Here, we see three apps with activities.
I'm going to use the Book Reader app
as an example for this presentation.
Let's look at the activities
within Book Reader.
We see a book, Fun with Science,
with activities.
Let's browse the activities
in Fun with Science.
There are several activities
in Fun with Science
organized by chapters.
Let's see what's in the first chapter
titled "Inquiry."
This chapter has one activity,
Science Investigation.
Let's look at that activity.
At the end of the section
on Science Investigation, we see a quiz.
By the way, did you notice
the rich details shown for the activities?
We see here a thumbnail,
a summary describing the activity,
suggested age
and suggested completion time
and the types of progress
reported by the app for the activity.
These details help teachers to decide
if they want to use this activity
in an assignment or not.
Now let me show you
how we can add these details
to activities in our app.
Before we do that,
let's take a brief look at App Activities.
An app activity
is any assigned content in your app.
This could be a chapter in a book,
a media stream in a podcast,
a test, a quiz and so on.
They are defined by your app
and are structured hierarchically.
Let's look at our example.
We saw a hierarchy of activities
in a book titled Fun with Science.
At the top level of that hierarchy
is the book Fun with Science.
The children of the book
are the chapters in the book,
and their children are
the sections in the chapters and so on.
You may be wondering how we surface
these activities in Schoolwork.
We use the CLSContext class in ClassKit
and create an instance of CLSContext
to represent each activity.
ClassKit provides a root context
for your app
called the Main App Context.
This is the parent
of your activity hierarchy.
Get the Main App Context...
create a CLSContext
for the topmost activity Fun with Science
and add it as a child
of the Main App Context.
Then go down the activity hierarchy...
create a context for each activity
and add it to its parent's context.
Now I'm going to use the measurements
quiz activity as an example
and show you how to add rich details
to that activity.
As we saw earlier,
there are several details here.
Let me walk you through, in steps,
and show you how to add these details
to the quiz context.
So, first, let me show you
how you can add a thumbnail
and summary to the quiz context.
First, create a context for the activity.
In this case, it is a measurements quiz.
Then add a summary to the context.
You say what the quiz is about.
Then add a thumbnail.
Remember, ClassKit limits the size
of thumbnails to 330 by 330 pixels.
It will downsize if needed.
In this example,
we are creating a thumbnail
from an image asset,
measurements_quiz.jpg.
Notice that we are using a function,
thumbnailFromImage,
to get a thumbnail from a file URL.
Let's take a look at this function.
This function shows you
how to create a thumbnail
from a file URL in a memory-efficient way
using CoreGraphics.
First create an image source
from the file...
then set some options
for creating a thumbnail.
We are choosing
to always create a thumbnail from an image
with a maximum size of 330 pixels.
Then create the thumbnail and return it.
This is just one way
of creating a thumbnail.
If UIImage
is more readily available to you,
you can get its CGImage property
and use it as thumbnail.
But keep in mind, doing it that way
may significantly increase the memory
used by your app.
Okay.
Let's add some more properties
to the quiz context.
Let's add suggested age
and suggested completion time.
It is very simple to add these properties.
They are both expressed as ranges.
Let's set the suggested age
as nine to 11 years
and the suggested completion time
as 15 to 20 minutes.
Next we will add the type of progress data
reported for the quiz activity.
In this example, we see four kinds
of progress data being reported--
percentage of progress,
correct/incorrect score
for each question...
the number of hints used by the student
when taking the quiz
and an overall score.
I'm going to show you how to add
a couple of these to the quiz context.
First, create a capability
for reporting progress percent.
The CLSProgressReportingCapability
class has two properties--
"kind" and "details."
You set the kind to percent kind
and set the details to a descriptive text.
Next create a capability
to report the number of hints used
when taking the quiz.
You can see how simple it is
to create each reporting capability.
Finally, we add these capabilities
to the quiz context.
In this example, I have set
the capability details in English,
but these text strings
are visible to users,
so please localize them at run time
based on the current locale.
Remember, this is similar
to what you have been doing
when setting the user visible title
of the activity.
Okay.
Now you know how to add the new properties
to your app activities.
This is how
you make your app activities rich.
Now I would like to go over
some recommended best practices
for creating and managing context
for your app.
The newly introduced properties
on CLSContext
adds valuable metadata
that informs the teacher
about the rich set of activities
in your app.
So, when you create a context,
please create a full-featured context
with as much metadata as you can provide.
If you find context saved
by an older version of your app,
update any missing properties.
If your app no longer supports
an older context,
then delete the context
so it does not show in the list
of activities supported by your app.
If your app uses a context provider
app extension to create context,
please update that app extension as well.
I'm almost done here,
and Daniel is itching to tell you
all about
the brand-new ClassKit Catalog APIs.
However, I want to tell you
about a few more enhancements
we have added to CLSContext
that many of you requested.
Like a read-only property identifierPath.
This returns you the full identifierPath
of the context.
And a new context type "course,"
and a new context type "custom."
Use this
in case none of the predefined types
is suitable for your app's content.
And an optional settable property
to give a name to your custom context,
your new property to mark a context
as a nonassignable activity.
Let's see where this property
is very useful.
In our example,
we created context for a book.
You see the entire book, Fun with Science,
is an assignable activity
indicated by a plus.
But I don't think your teacher
would assign that entire book.
In fact, as a developer,
you did not intend to make a book
an assignable activity.
You were just using a CLSContext
for the book
as a container to hold its chapters.
Now, by setting the new isAssignable
property of the context to "false,"
you can make it clear that the book
is not an assignable activity.
I encourage you to review
the updated developer documentation
to learn about all the enhancements
we have made to ClassKit.
These are the latest enhancements
to ClassKit.
With that, let me invite Daniel
to introduce you to the new and exciting
ClassKit Catalog API.
Here you go, Daniel.
Thanks, Baskaran.
Today, we'd like to introduce
a new web service
called ClassKit Catalog API.
Our motivation behind this service
was to provide an even better experience
for our developers
who build ClassKit-enabled apps
and for the teachers who use them.
We built this to help you
with several things in mind.
First, we wanted to improve
your content's discoverability
within Schoolwork.
Consumers of your app should see
the rich repository of content
you've made available to them
without having to work
through each piece first.
Next, we wanted to give you support
to provide an even wider array
of ClassKit-enabled content
than otherwise possible,
using the native approach
of CLSContext creation.
Lastly, we wanted to decouple
the management of your content
from the management of your application.
Your content is subject to change,
and you should be able to make those
modifications without changing your app.
How do we achieve this?
Currently, the CLSContexts
are defined natively in your app.
As teachers use it,
it delegates to ClassKit
to generate the necessary contexts
that get saved on the teacher's device
and eventually
on the students' devices too.
ClassKit Catalog API prescribes
a different way to report your content.
To use this new service,
begin by translating your existing
CLSContext hierarchy
into a JSON structure.
Next, take the payload
and upload it
using the ClassKit Catalog API.
From there, using the data
that you've provided,
we'll handle the generation of CLSContext
on the teacher or students' devices
whenever your app
is referenced in Schoolwork.
Before I move on,
it's important to note
that ClassKit Catalog API
is intended for content you'd like
to display publicly in Schoolwork.
Private content,
such as dynamically generated
or user-specific CLSContexts
should continue to be reported
to ClassKit using the native API.
We have a new address
to which you can make requests:
api.classkit-catalog.apple.com.
This is suffixed with "v1"
in order to version our API
to support any changes
we may introduce in the future.
The API itself is comprised
of two main components,
one to manage contexts
and one to manage thumbnails.
Contexts are the fundamental unit
that describe your content
and that the catalog operates on.
You can think of them as the CLSContexts
that Baskaran presented earlier,
but with a couple of more
bells and whistles.
We'll take a closer look at them
a little later.
Thumbnails are images
you associate with your contexts.
In the first part of this presentation,
we saw how this is done natively
using ClassKit.
Well, with the API,
we'll use the thumbnail endpoint,
which we'll see later as well.
Today, we'll focus on the POST requests.
Let's begin
by looking at one for contexts.
Here's an example of a POST request
with the required fields
you'll be expected to provide.
First is a query parameter
labeled "environment."
It determines whether the changes you make
target a development environment
or are made live to production.
We'll see how to take advantage
of this a little later.
Next, a couple of headers are expected.
Content-Type and Authorization.
Content-Type describes
what sort of payload you'll be delivering.
For this endpoint,
it should be application/json.
Authorization describes the credential
with which you'll authenticate
with our service.
For ClassKit Catalog API,
we decided to adopt
the use of JSON Web Tokens.
This is an industry-standard approach
to authentication
that's used across several
of Apple's web services.
We'll detail how to generate these tokens
later in the presentation.
The body of this request
should contain a JSON-formatted list
of contexts to be created or updated.
These contexts represent
the CLSContexts in your application,
and in order
for your application's capabilities
to be properly represented,
the entire context tree
associated with your ClassKit-enabled app
will have to be reported.
A single context consists of two fields,
data and metadata.
Let's take a closer look
at how these two fields are constructed.
The data object is comprised of fields
taken directly from a CLSContext,
including the new fields
added to the latest update of ClassKit,
which Baskaran mentioned earlier.
When you create this data object,
use the values of the fields
from the CLSContext
that your app already creates.
Make sure that they match the contexts
your app natively creates,
so that your content can be
properly represented in the catalog.
The metadata field
is meant to capture info
that's not represented in CLSContext.
It contains three fields.
Locale, which is meant to distinguish
your content between different languages
and regions of your application,
minimumBundleVersion,
which acts as a hit for the client
to determine whether this context
is supported by a version of your app,
and keywords,
which represent tags that you believe
accurately describes your content.
Metadata is a sparse object,
but we expect it to grow
along with the API.
That was an example
of a POST request for contexts.
More details on this endpoint,
along with the GET and DELETE
methods for contexts,
will be available
in Apple Developer documentation.
For now, let me highlight
a couple of guidelines
on the context endpoint.
First, there's a limit
of 200 contexts per POST request.
If you have more, split them up
across multiple requests.
If you do, make sure
that the children contexts
are submitted after their ancestors.
Aside from your main app context,
child contexts are considered invalid
if their parent does not exist.
Lastly, should you decide
to delete a context,
be aware that any of its descendants
will be deleted as well.
This is done to ensure the integrity
of your app's context hierarchy.
Moving on,
let's take a look at the POST method
to upload a thumbnail.
Here's an example of one
with the fields expected in a request.
It begins with a thumbnail reference,
which is used to associate the thumbnail
to one or more contexts.
This is done by matching
against the thumbnail field
on a context object.
The rest of this request
should be similar to the first one we saw.
For instance,
we must also target an environment
using the "environment" query parameter...
provide credentials
using the Authorization header,
as well as a Content-Type
to describe the image being uploaded.
Unlike our previous POST request,
we have the addition of a Content-Length
to describe the size of the thumbnail
to be uploaded in bytes
and a body that consists of the bytes
representing the image.
During the Handout creation flow,
this image is used
to represent an Activity.
So keep that in mind as you decide
how best to represent your content.
That was a look at the POST endpoint
for a thumbnail.
The corresponding GET and DELETE endpoints
are structured similarly,
and more details can be found
in Apple Developer documentation.
Before I move on,
let me highlight some guidelines
for the thumbnail endpoints.
First, use PNG or JPEG
to represent your thumbnails.
Next, format your thumbnails
to be 330 by 330 pixels.
That's the resolution
we'll use for Schoolwork.
Lastly, upload your contexts first,
followed by your thumbnails.
This is to prevent thumbnails
to be orphaned.
Upload requests will be rejected
if the thumbnail isn't referenced
by any context.
This also means if the last context
to reference a thumbnail
were to be deleted,
then the thumbnail would be deleted too.
Before I move on,
let's talk about how the API
would respond when something goes wrong.
Here is an example of a response
you might get back
from trying to POST a thumbnail
that's reporting an error.
Aside from an expected HTTP status code,
a response reporting an error
should also contain a JSON body
to provide more details on the problem.
The ID field provides a unique identifier
which we can use to identify
and track this error.
We can tell from the code field that
there's a problem with authentication...
and upon inspecting the message field,
we find a human-readable explanation
of the problem,
as well as the way to resolve it.
A full list of error codes
and their respective messages
will be available
in Apple Developer documentation.
As for this authentication error,
how do we get past this?
As promised,
let's talk about authentication.
We mentioned earlier that authentication
in ClassKit Catalog API
is handled with the use
of JSON Web Tokens, or JWT.
This is an industry standard
that's used across several
of Apple's web services.
To begin,
log into the Apple Developer portal
and provision a ClassKit Catalog API key
for your team.
This private key will be used
to create the JWT
used to authenticate
with ClassKit Catalog API,
and must be provided
with all the requests you make
as part of the Authorization header
we mentioned earlier.
The JWT consists of three parts,
a header, a payload and a signature.
To form the header and payload,
provide the key ID and team ID
found in the Apple Developer portal.
This will associate the credential
to your developer team.
Additionally, generate a UUID
to identify this token
and two UNIX time stamps,
one to represent when the token was issued
and one to represent
when the token expires.
What we see here are the raw fields.
To form the eventual token,
these fields will have to be
Base64 encoded.
To complete the JWT,
a signature is required,
which is generated using
encoded header and encoded payload.
The algorithm to be used to sign this
is ECDSASHA256.
There are plenty of public libraries
across programming languages
that should make it easy to do so.
Altogether, the fully formed JWT
will look like this.
This token must be included
in the Authorization header
and prefixed with the word "Bearer."
Now that we have all the pieces,
how would you test the content
you've uploaded
before it's shown to your users?
We have two environments
to which you can push your content,
development and production.
To test your changes,
use the "environment" query parameter
to upload your content to development,
like we showed earlier
in the presentation.
Once you've done that, open Settings
and navigate to the Developer tab
on your device
that's running a development build of iOS.
Tap on ClassKit API to see more options.
Under ClassKit Catalog Environment,
select the Development environment.
Once it's set, ClassKit will change
where it pulls data from
and display the appropriate content
in Schoolwork
based on the environment you have chosen.
Take note that content
pushed to development
will be available
to all ClassKit Apple developers
who are also using
the Development environment.
To wrap up, I'd like to highlight
some best practices
to keep in mind while using the API.
First and most importantly,
as you define new content
or remove old content,
report this using ClassKit Catalog API.
This ensures that your app
and its Activities
are properly represented in Schoolwork.
Next, take advantage of locale support
provided for contexts.
Doing so helps your app reach
the widest audience possible.
Lastly, you'll want to provide
as much detail as you can
in the contexts you report
and have thumbnails associated with them.
This will provide more detail
to users in Schoolwork
as well as a more compelling reason
for them to assign content from your app.
That's all for ClassKit Catalog API.
It will be available
for ClassKit developers this summer.
This also concludes our presentation
of "What's New in ClassKit."
Thanks.