Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, and welcome back to Swan's Quest.
I'm Rob, your host as we go inside
the second chapter of our journey.
We hope you had a fun time
with the first challenge,
and learned a little bit
about accessible interfaces.
In the second chapter,
you returned to the Lizard,
who helps you uncover
the mystery of the Swan's scroll.
I don't want to spoil it for you,
but I can tell you
that to pass this challenge,
you need to play
a series of musical notes for the Swan.
In order to play notes, we're gonna
show you two pieces of API:
ToneOutput and Timer.
We'll cover both of them in enough detail
for you to impress our magnificent regent.
Finally, we'll end with a side quest
for those of you
in search of more adventure.
First, let's talk about how to play tones.
For that, we're gonna use
the ToneOutput type.
We introduced ToneOutput
in Sonic Workshop,
and included it in Sonic Create,
so you could use it in your own projects.
Let's take a closer look at ToneOutput.
Our ToneOutput type
has a straightforward API
for playing generated signals
from a tone value.
It produces 44,100 samples a second.
That's so your ears hear continuous sound
instead of discrete pulses.
The primary instance method, play(tone:)
is what you call to create a signal.
The definition for tone
is equally straightforward.
A pitch, which is a Double representation
of a frequency,
and a volume, also described as a Double.
And this is what it looks like in use.
In this example,
we create an instance of ToneOutput,
then pass it a 440 Hz frequency,
or middle A.
Run this code in your Playground
and you should hear a tone
reminiscent of
the Emergency Broadcast System.
If you don't stop running your Playground
code, that tone's gonna play forever.
Let's check in with Stephen
to see how to play more than one note.
Thanks, Rob.
As he mentioned, the ToneOutput sample
will play continuously
unless it is stopped.
To stop the ToneOutput instance,
we need to call stopTones
as highlighted here.
We can accomplish this in our example
by calling Dispatch_async_After,
which calls stopTones
after 400 milliseconds.
The note will play for a short
period of time and then stop.
This approach won't work
if you want to play more than one note.
We recommend using a timer.
It's a more straightforward API
and it's easy to repeat a loop
over a predetermined time interval.
Let's update our example
to play multiple notes.
Here, we have supplied the frequencies
for middle A, middle B and middle C.
To play them consecutively
after one another, we use a timer.
We iterate over our array of tones,
playing the next one
every 400 milliseconds.
When we get to the end of our array,
we call stopTones on our ToneOutput
and invalidate our timer
so it'll stop repeating.
Finally, you need to make a call
to endPerformance,
so that you get credit for your work.
You'll use this same call
on all of your remaining challenges
to signal to the Swan
that you've finished performing.
And that's how you can use a timer
to play multiple different notes
one after the other.
Thanks, Stephen.
Before we go any further,
I want to warn you.
This side quest will contain spoilers
for this chapter's challenge.
If you want to complete the challenge
first, hit pause on this video
and come back
after you've completed the challenge.
Good luck.
Okay, are you ready to do this side quest?
The Swan's challenge
was to play a C-major scale,
and they provided
all of the frequencies for you.
Let's see if you can adapt that code
to play an F-major scale.
If you think about it, you already have
many of the frequencies you need.
First, the F-major scale starts at F4.
You already have that note from the Swan.
Second, you should be able to reuse
your code from your C-major scale.
Finally, if you need to go up an octave,
just double the frequency.
That means to get an A5 from an A4,
you need to multiply 440 Hz by two
to get 880 Hz.
Right. You're gonna need
the frequency for B-flat too.
During this episode,
we gave you tips for completing
the second challenge in Swan's Quest.
We introduced you to ToneOutput
and how to use Swift Playgrounds
to play tuned pitches by frequency.
Then we discussed how to use timers
to change notes for a certain duration.
Tomorrow, we'll be back with a "note-able"
challenge. You're not gonna wanna miss it.
Good luck, have fun,
and join us in the forums to share
your solutions for the side quest.
We'd love to hear how you did.