Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Anil Katti
and I'm excited to share with you
some of the amazing new features
we've introduced this year in Core ML.
Core ML makes it easy for you
to seamlessly integrate machine learning
into your app,
unlocking the door to countless
amazing experiences for your users.
Your Core ML model is at the heart of
what makes all these experiences possible.
Today, we are introducing new features
that are centered around this model.
In this session,
we're going to cover a few topics,
from a new way to deploy your models,
to encrypting them,
and some enhancements in Xcode.
Let's get started.
We designed Core ML with
your app development workflow in mind.
Once you have a model,
you can integrate it into your app
by simply dragging and dropping it
into your Xcode project.
Xcode compiles your model
into an optimal format
for running on-device.
When you submit your app,
the compiled model
is bundled with your app.
Together, they go to the App Store
and then to your users' devices.
Bundling a model with your app works great
and we highly recommend doing it.
That way, the model is readily available
as soon as a user installs the app.
There are scenarios where you might need
more flexibility and control
over the model delivery process.
Today, we're introducing
Core ML Model Deployment
to give you that flexibility.
provides you a new way
to deliver models to your apps.
Using the Model Deployment dashboard,
models can be stored, managed
and deployed via Apple cloud.
Devices periodically retrieve updates
as they become available.
Model Deployment gives you
the ability to develop and deploy models
independent of the app update cycle,
a new way to group and manage
models that work together,
and the option to target models
to specific device populations.
We're really excited about these features,
so let's explore each one in more detail.
Let's start with independent development.
Typically, when you retrain your models,
you probably plan to bundle them
with your next app update.
But what if you're updating your models
at a different pace than your app?
In the past,
you'd have to push more app updates
just to get the newer models
in your users' hands.
Now, with Model Deployment,
you can quickly and easily
update your models
without updating the app itself.
Next up: model collections.
Model collections are a great way
to group one or more models
that relate to a feature in your app.
For example,
let's say you're working on a game
and one of its levels needs
a set of models to support a feature.
You can keep these models in sync
by grouping them
into a single model collection.
When you deploy a model collection,
that deployment keeps all the models
within a collection together
and atomically delivers them to your app.
I'm eager to show all this in action,
but before we jump into the demo,
let me describe how we would go about
adopting this feature.
So, there are three steps
in adopting Model Deployment.
The first step is to use
the new Core ML API
to opt-in for Model Deployment.
Next, prepare the model for deployment
by creating a model archive.
You can do this in Xcode.
The last step
is to upload the prepared model
and deploy
on the Model Deployment dashboard.
You will only need to repeat
steps two and three
every time you update your model.
Let's take a closer look
at these steps with a demo.
I have a simple app
that classifies flowers
and applies cool visual effects
when you double-tap on a picture.
It uses two Core ML models:
an image classifier
and a style transfer model.
I chose to integrate Model Deployment
so I could decouple updating models
from the app update process
and iterate on models independently.
So, the first step is to use the new API
to opt-in for Model Deployment.
Let's see how to do that in Xcode.
I have my Xcode project open.
Although this app does a couple of things,
for this demo, let's just focus
on the flower classification feature.
Here is the key method
we are going to implement today.
It classifies the flower in a given image
and updates the UI with the class label.
The first thing I want to do
when this method is invoked
is create an instance of FlowerClassifier
and store it in a variable.
This would allow me to access
the preloaded model in subsequent calls
and not have to load the model
every single time.
So, let me get started
by checking for the preloaded case.
Here, I check to see
if the variable is already set
and if so, use that to classify the image
and return immediately.
Next, let's implement the logic
to load the model.
Recall that models
are grouped into collections.
I will show how to create
and deploy model collections
on the new dashboard in a few minutes.
But here, I'm interested in accessing
the collection that was already deployed.
I can do that by simply calling
beginAccessing method
on MLModelCollection.
The first time this method is called
for a model collection with an identifier,
the system downloads all models
in that collection on a background queue
and registers for future updates
to those models.
You can monitor the download
using the progress object.
Here the model collection identifier
we are using is "FlowerModels."
Let's just keep a note of that
since this is required
while creating the model collection later.
This method also returns an instance
of MLModelCollection asynchronously
as a result type.
Let's see how we can access
the downloaded models from this result.
When this operation succeeds,
we get an instance of model collection
which contains model collection entries.
There's one entry per model.
I can access the model collection entry
for our FlowerClassifier model
using the model name as the key.
Inside the entry is a model URL
that points to the compiled model
which was downloaded and placed
in the app's container by the system.
Accessing a model collection could fail.
For instance,
if there is no network connectivity
the first time this is called,
downloading models will fail.
It is important
to handle the failure case.
In this example, we simply log the error
and fall back to using the bundled model.
Next, let's implement the logic
to load the model.
I implemented a simple helper method
It takes an optional modelURL as input
and uses that to load
the FlowerClassifier model.
If the URL is nil, it just falls back
and loads the model
that is bundled with the app.
The last step
is to use this FlowerClassifier
for classifying the image.
Here's the code for that.
When the model loading succeeds,
we use the loaded model
to classify the image
and also store it in the variable
for subsequent classification requests.
We have a separate method
to handle the model load failures,
which, in this case, displays
a suitable error message to the user.
This is all the code that's required
to prepare the app for Model Deployment.
Now, how can I prepare the model itself
for deployment?
Well, I can do that in Xcode.
If you click on the model in Xcode,
you'll see that we have introduced
a new utilities tab this year
which has a section for Model Deployment.
I can prepare a model for deployment
by creating a model archive.
Okay, Xcode created
FlowerClassifier.mlarchive
and saved it on the disk.
I can locate the file by clicking here.
It is placed
right next to our original model file.
The last step is to deploy this model
on the Model Deployment dashboard.
Xcode provides a button that takes you
right to the Model Deployment dashboard
in Safari.
The first thing you'll notice
on the dashboard
is that we have a way
to create a model collection.
I'll start by creating a new
model collection for our flower models
and name it "FlowerModels."
This should match with
what was specified in the app.
Next, let's provide a nice description.
Something like...
"collection of models
built for flower images."
And then specify the two models
that we plan to collect
in this collection,
the first being a FlowerClassfier.
And then we have a FlowerStylizer.
And then click on the create button.
Next, I can deploy the models
by creating a new deployment.
I will call it Global Deployment
since I intend to deploy these models
to my app on all devices.
I can upload the model archives I created
against each of these model names.
Let me pick the FlowerClassfier first
and then the Stylizer
and click on the deploy button
on the top right.
In the model collection page,
I can verify that the deployment
I created just now
is in the active status.
So this looks good.
These models are made available
on all devices
running the version of my app
that uses this model collection.
Let me launch the app
and try classifying flowers now.
I picked a dahlia and see
that it's being classified as dahlia.
Let me try a hibiscus this time.
The app seems to get that right as well.
The model that I used here was
only trained on three different classes
and rose was not one of them.
Let me try a rose image
and see what happens.
As expected,
the app does not seem to recognize rose.
Let's say I want to enhance my app
to classify rose.
Since I've already adopted
Model Deployment in this app,
I can easily add this feature
by deploying a model
retrained with rose images
using Model Deployment.
For the sake of this demo,
I've already prepared
the updated model for deployment.
Let's go to the deployment dashboard
and see how to update a model.
I can deploy the updated model
by creating a new deployment.
This time,
I will pick the improved classifier
and the same stylizer
and click on the deploy button.
Like before, these updated models
are made available to my app
on all devices,
but it might not happen immediately.
Each device figures out the right time
to download the model in the background
and makes it available to the app
on its next launch.
Let's see what will happen
when my app gets launched
after the OS has synced
the updated models to the device.
Picking the same rose image
that was not classified previously,
I see that it is getting classified
as a rose this time.
So without changing a single line of code,
we've enhanced the user experience
by improving the model,
and I think this is really cool.
Next, let's talk about
targeted deployments.
Typically, when your app is young,
it might have only one set of models
for all your users.
However, as your app evolves,
it might make more sense
for you to use specialized models
for different populations.
One solution is simply to bundle
all models in your app
and use the right one at the runtime,
but it's not very efficient.
And what if the models are large
and you want to keep
the app download size small?
With targeted deployments,
you can define rules
so that each user's device
only gets the model it needs.
Let's see how to set one of these up.
Recently, I made an improvement
to our FlowerClassifier,
but specifically made it for iPads.
It turns out the camera angle
and the light setting
in images taken on an iPad
are slightly different
from those on an iPhone.
Although I want to use
a new model on iPads,
the existing model works just fine
on all other devices.
Let's take a look at how we can target
the iPad-specific model to just iPads.
Back on the dashboard,
I can either clone an existing deployment
or create a new one.
For now, I'll create a new one
and call it Targeting iPads.
First, I get to pick the default models
for this deployment.
These models will be delivered
on all devices
that do not match the deployment rules.
After that, I can add
an additional targeting rule.
You can see
all the different criteria I can target.
I'll pick the device class
and select iPad.
So for this targeting rule,
I get to pick the iPad-specific models.
I can now deploy these models.
Devices pull the right model
based on the device class.
No additional change required in the app.
We showed you how easy it is
to use Core ML Model Deployment
to help with some interesting use cases.
Here are some things
that you should keep in mind
as you use this feature.
First, we strongly suggest
testing each model locally
before uploading it
on the Deployment dashboard.
This will ensure that your users
do not end up with models that don't work.
Next, be aware that the models you deploy
won't be available on devices right away.
Each device's system decides when to
download the model in the background.
Therefore, your app
should always have a fallback plan
when the deployed models aren't available.
Lastly, model collection provides
a convenient way to organize models.
We recommend
grouping your model collections
around each of your app's features.
So, to summarize what we've shown you:
Core ML Model Deployment is a new way
to deliver models to your users,
independent of app updates.
Model collections give you a new way
to group and work with your models,
and targeted deployments are super helpful
when you want to deploy models
to separate populations.
We think these features
will give you more flexibility
and make it more convenient
to deliver models to your users.
I'll hand it over to John Durant,
and he can tell us more
about some other exciting features
we have for you this year.
Thank you, Anil.
Hi, everyone,
and thank you for joining us.
We're really excited
to share these features with you,
and we can't wait to see
the amazing apps you'll build with them.
So far we've covered
some new and faster ways
to get your models to your users.
Now let's take a look
at how you can encrypt those models.
With model encryption,
you can distribute your models,
knowing that they are encrypted
at rest and in transit.
Let's take a look at what that means
and how it works.
Whether your model is bundled
with your app or deployed to the cloud,
what Xcode actually encrypts
is the compiled Core ML model.
This compiled model,
not the original .mlmodel file,
is what actually lives inside your app
on a user's device.
So, how do you encrypt
this compiled model?
Easy. With Xcode.
The first thing you'll need
is an encryption key.
I'll show you how to make a key
in a few minutes.
With the key, you can tell Xcode
to encrypt your model at build time.
Or you can use a key to encrypt
a model archive when you generate it.
Either way, the compiled model
stays encrypted in transit
and at rest on a user's device.
So, how do you use
an encrypted model at runtime?
Well, you use an encrypted model
just as you would a regular one.
Core ML automatically decrypts
the model for you,
but the decrypted model
only exists in memory.
The compiled model in the file system
remains encrypted at all times.
The first time you load
your encrypted model,
the OS securely fetches
and securely stores
the model's decryption key
on your app's behalf.
After that, your app won't need
a network connection
to load the same model again.
Let's jump in to Xcode
and see just how easy it is
to adopt model encryption.
I'll go back to the same app
that Anil was using before.
Let's say I want to encrypt
our image classification model.
The first thing I need to do
is create an encryption key.
To do that,
I'll open up the model in Xcode,
and I'm gonna go over here
to the utilities tab
and I'm gonna click on
"Create Encryption Key."
What we see here is that Xcode associates
the encryption key with a team,
and so it's important
to choose the same team account
that you use for building your app.
When I click on Continue,
Xcode sends a request to Apple cloud
which generates a new encryption key.
The server securely stores the key
and sends a copy back to Xcode.
So now we can see that Xcode generated
a new file with extension .mlmodelkey,
and it's dropped it
right next to my Core ML model.
So here we can see we have the .mlmodel
and the .mlmodelkey.
Okay, great. Now we have a key.
Now we can take this key and share it
on our team's secure key repository
so that other developers on our team
can use it.
Now that we have a key,
we can use it to encrypt our model.
First, let's look at the scenario
Anil showed earlier,
where he deployed the model
with the Core ML Model Deployment.
This time,
when I go create a model archive,
Xcode pre-selects the .mlmodelkey
sitting beside my model.
Let's click Continue,
and we'll see that Xcode generates
a model archive just like before,
but this time
it encrypts the contents of the archive.
The remaining steps
are exactly the same as before.
I can simply deploy
this encrypted model archive
by uploading it
to the Core ML Model Deployment dashboard
as Anil did earlier.
Okay, so that's great for deployments.
But what if I wanted to bundle the model
within the app itself?
Well, there's a way to encrypt
those models too.
In this app, I have a second model
called FlowerStylizer.
I'll run the app again
so we can see what this does.
When I pick an image
and then double-tap it,
we see that a cool style transfer effect
gets applied.
Looking good!
If you'd like to build
one of these models yourself,
you can check out the session called
"Build Image and Video Style
Transfer Models in Create ML."
Now this model is packaged
with my app bundle.
If I want to encrypt it,
I have to generate a key for it
and then tell Xcode
to encrypt the model at build time.
First, I'll generate a key for this model.
We see that FlowerClassifier.mlmodelkey
has been saved to disk.
Now what I need to do is tell Xcode to use
this key for encryption at build time.
I'm gonna go ahead
and grab these compiler flags.
I'm gonna go over
to my project properties,
Build Phases, Compile Sources,
and I'm going to look for my model.
There it is.
I've got FlowerStylizer.mlmodel.
And I'm gonna go over here
to Compiler Flags.
And I'm going to go ahead and paste in
dash-dash encrypt,
and then a pointer
to the .mlmodelkey file on disk.
Once we've done that,
we can go ahead and build again.
So now, each time when I build the app,
the Core ML Compiler
will compile the model
and then encrypt it
with the model's encryption key.
That means the app now has
this encrypted, compiled model built in.
Okay, so now let's look at
how we can load the encrypted model.
If we go over here, we see we have
a function called "Stylize the Image."
Now, since model loading needs
a network connection the first time,
we've introduced
an asynchronous model loading method.
That's right here. FlowerStylizer.load.
We're going to deprecate
the default initializer
and we strongly recommend
switching to the new .load method,
as it gives you an opportunity
to handle model load errors.
Load automatically fetches the key
from Apple cloud
and works just like you'd expect it to.
Even though Core ML needs network access
to get the key the first time,
it won't ever need
to fetch that key again.
For example, let's say you close your app
and later launch it again.
This time,
Core ML doesn't make a network request
because the OS
securely stored the key locally.
You can see we're getting back
a result of "T"
that contains the model,
and we can unwrap it in the success case,
at which point we have our model
and we can continue stylizing as before,
or we also have a failure case.
In the failure case,
we have a helper method
and you'll notice here we specifically
trap for a modelKeyFetch error.
And in that case,
we may want to let the user know
that they need network connectivity
or to try again later.
And that's it. Adopting model encryption
really is that simple.
So to recap, you can use model encryption
in three easy steps.
First, generate an encryption key
with Xcode.
Next, encrypt your model
with the encryption key.
And finally, load and use
the encrypted model on the device.
Create, encrypt, load. It's that simple.
Model encryption works seamlessly
whether you bundle a model in your app
or send one through a Model Deployment.
All you have to do is create a key,
encrypt your model, and call .load.
We'll handle the rest of it
so you can focus on making a great app.
Before we finish, we have a few more
exciting Xcode updates for Core ML
that we'd like to share with you.
During our demos, you may have noticed
that Xcode now shows you
a lot more information about your model.
At a glance, you can now see
which OS versions a model supports,
its class labels, and even
some internal neural network details.
Another new feature
we think is particularly useful,
not to mention fun,
is the interactive model preview.
Now you can interactively preview
and experiment with your model
directly in Xcode,
before you write a single line of code.
We support previews
for a wide variety of models,
such as image segmentation,
pose detection, depth estimation,
and many more,
including all the models you can train
with Create ML.
The full list of preview types
is listed here,
and we encourage you to explore the models
available on developer.apple.com.
We are also happy to announce
that Core ML models
are now first-class citizens
in Xcode Playgrounds.
Simply drag and drop a Core ML model
into your resources folder.
Now your Playground gets
the same auto-generated class interface
as an Xcode project.
This allows you to programmatically
experiment with your model
in a live, interactive coding session.
Playgrounds are also a great way
to share your model demonstrations
with friends and colleagues.
We've covered a lot of ground today,
so let's do a quick recap.
We introduced Core ML Model Deployment,
which allows you to deliver Core ML models
independently from your app.
This makes it really easy
to quickly distribute
and target your models
as you improve them.
We think this will greatly accelerate
the app development process
and how quickly
you can adopt machine learning.
We also introduced model encryption,
which protects your models in transit
and at rest,
without having to set up
your own hosting and key management.
Now you can encrypt Core ML models,
whether they ship with your app
or as part of a Model Deployment.
And finally, we added
some Core ML enhancements to Xcode,
making it easier for you to understand,
preview and interact with your models.
Thank you for watching our session
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.