♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Dani Chootong: Hello,
and welcome to
"What's new
with in-app purchase."
I'm Dani, and I'm an engineer
on the StoreKit team.
Today I'll be presenting
with my colleague Ian,
and we'll be going over
the new improvements
we're bringing
to in-app purchase this year.
Last year,
we introduced StoreKit 2,
a set of new APIs
designed from the ground up
to make it simple
to integrate in-app purchases.
StoreKit 2 uses
modern language features,
including Swift concurrency
using the async/await pattern.
On the server side,
we complemented these
new StoreKit features
with an entirely new set
of App Store Server endpoints.
These server endpoints
make it easy to retrieve
transaction information
and check subscription status
on your server.
We also released Version 2 of
App Store Server Notifications,
to make tracking
the subscription lifecycle
on your server easier than ever.
Today I'll be going over
these new APIs,
as well as
enhancements we're bringing
to the new StoreKit models.
Then, Ian will walk you through
some exciting new
server updates,
including App Store Server
API enhancements
and brand-new APIs for
App Store Server Notifications.
First, I'll go over
the new App Transaction API
for verifying
the purchase of your app.
Next, I'll dig into some
new properties we've added
to our StoreKit models.
I'll introduce you
to the new SwiftUI friendly APIs
for redeeming
subscription offer codes
and asking a customer
to review your app.
Then, I'll introduce you
to StoreKit Messages,
an API used to display
App Store messages
to your customers.
And finally, I'll go over
an enhancement we're adding
to preserve Application Username
when you're migrating
from the original
to the modern StoreKit APIs.
Throughout this presentation,
I'll be using my favorite app,
Food Truck.
In the Food Truck app, I manage
a pop-up donut food truck
that visits various cities
to make donut deliveries.
So, let's get started!
Meet App Transaction.
The App Transaction
is our new API
for verifying the purchase
of your app.
The App Transaction represents
the signed information
for the purchase of your app
for the device it's running on.
It's signed using JWS,
and it replaces the app detail
portion of the app receipt
from the original StoreKit API.
Just like
transaction verification,
StoreKit performs
automatic verification
of the app transaction for you.
However, if you wish, you can also perform
your own validation.
Validating a JWS signature
is a well-documented standard.
You can refer
to the public documentation
to implement
your own validation.
StoreKit takes care
of automatically updating
the App Transaction
when necessary.
However, in the rare case
that the user
thinks there's something wrong,
it can be refreshed.
You should provide
UI in your app
to allow your customers
to refresh the app transaction.
This should only be used
in response to user action,
as refreshing
the App Transaction
prompts the user
to authenticate.
Preventing fraud isn't the only
reason to love App Transaction.
If you're looking to switch
business models from a paid app
to a free app that offers
in-app purchases,
if you're curious about
which of your customers
preordered your app,
or even if you just want to know
when your app was purchased,
these are all situations you can
handle with App Transaction.
In the app receipt,
the receipt payload
combine the purchase data
about your application
along with all the in-app
purchases that have occurred.
These are now broken up
into two separate components
in StoreKit.
The first of these
is the Transaction History.
StoreKit's transaction APIs
give you insight
into the user's entire
in-app purchase history,
right on the device.
These APIs allow you to find
the exact information you need,
including the user's
latest transactions,
unfinished transactions,
and current entitlements.
If you prefer to perform these
calculations on your server,
you can also get
the user's purchase history
from the App Store Server API.
Ian will have some
exciting updates on this
later this session.
And the second component
is the App Transaction,
which contains the data
you need to make sure
that your app is valid
for the device it's running on.
It's easy to verify
the purchase of your app
using App Transaction,
and in just a moment,
I'll be going over an example
of how you can use it.
But first,
let me give you some background
about my favorite app.
With Food Truck, I'm able
to make donut deliveries,
check in on a basic social feed,
and visualize my sales history.
Keeping all this information
in a database
is an ongoing cost for my app,
so to help me cover the costs,
I'm going to turn
the yearly sales history chart
into a onetime purchase.
Additionally, I want to enhance
the social feed.
So instead of just seeing
what others are saying
about my food truck,
I want to provide the tools
so I can engage
with my customers as well.
This will be
a subscription service,
and I'll have a monthly
and a yearly plan.
Food Truck began as a paid app,
but I'm going to make the switch
to a free app that offers
in-app purchases.
But I don't want
my existing customers
who already purchased Food Truck
to feel left out.
So, I'll be using
the App Transaction
to make sure that the customers
who purchased Food Truck
continue to have access to the
premium content they paid for.
Here's the timeline
for Food Truck.
At the initial release,
Food Truck started out
as a paid app that cost $4.99.
Version 1.0 offered
donut deliveries,
a basic social feed,
and sales history charts.
Later, at the release
of version 8.0,
my business model changed.
Food Truck is now free,
but includes
a variety of in-app purchases
which unlock premium features.
The yearly sales history chart
is now a nonconsumable
onetime purchase,
and now there's
a new subscription service
for a premium social feed
that gives you
advanced engagement tools.
Now let's take a look at
two different types of customers
who might be affected by this.
Alice found out about my
Food Truck app in version 2.5,
and she decided she wants
to share her passion for donuts
in the digital world.
So, she purchased
my app for $4.99
and began her
donut delivery journey.
A second customer, Bob, finds
out about my Food Truck app
though a friend
and downloads it for free
in the App Store in version 8.2.
In this scenario, Alice,
who purchased my app
before it became free,
should still have access
to all the premium content
she already paid for.
She still has the option
to purchase the premium
social feed subscription,
but I don't want to deny her
the yearly sales history chart
that was initially included.
Bob, however,
got my app for free.
I know then not to unlock
features and content
until they complete
the in-app purchase.
So, let's see how
we can achieve this
with App Transaction in code.
I'll start off
by fetching the app transaction
by calling
AppTransaction.shared.
This call gets me
a VerificationResult
containing my app transaction.
Within the result,
the AppTransaction type
contains the JWS payload.
Next, I'll switch on the result.
If the result is unverified,
this would be a good time
to alert the user
that their app purchase
could not be verified
by the App Store,
and then, I can prompt them
to refresh the app transaction.
At this time, I'll offer
a minimal experience for my app.
If the result is verified,
I'm going to use this as
an opportunity to check whether
the user has purchased my app.
Customers
that purchased my app
should be granted
the services they paid for.
For this, I'll use the original
app version property.
This property lets me know
the app version in which
the customer had downloaded
my app for the very first time.
Version 8.0 is the version
in which my app became free
with in-app purchases.
I'm going to pass the customer's
original app version
to my function which checks
if the user purchased my app
before version 8.0.
And with that, I can make
an informed decision about
how I should go about providing
premium content to my users.
For customers like Alice,
who purchased my app,
I'm going to provide the content
the user is entitled to
that they had
at the time of purchase.
In my case, I'm going to unlock
the yearly sales history chart
for her deliveries.
Also, I want to check
any additional in-app purchases
they may have made
so I can provide that as well.
Otherwise, I can be confident
that the user downloaded my app
after I switched
my business model, like Bob.
This can be a good time
to check the user's
current entitlements
so I can unlock the features
and content they paid for.
And with just
a few lines of code,
I was able to verify
the purchase of my app,
check whether
the user downloaded
the paid version of my app,
and I can immediately start
providing my premium content,
whether the customer
purchased my app or not.
With App Transaction,
you can easily support
your customers
whether they're early supporters
or if they've just recently
downloaded your app.
Now I'd like to move on
to the new properties
we're adding
to our StoreKit models.
The first of these properties
is the price locale.
The price locale is now
included in StoreKit products.
You may already be familiar
with price locale
from interfacing with
our original purchase APIs.
Next, I'll dig into
the server environment property.
Now, you can tell
the server environment
a transaction
or renewal info occurred in.
Then, I'll move onto
the recent subscription
start date property.
You can use this as a tool
to make informed decisions
for your customers based
on their subscription patterns.
And lastly, I'll go over
some special considerations
for these properties
when you're using them
with StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
These properties return
sentinel values
in older operating systems,
and I'll explain what this means
in just a bit.
The StoreKit APIs were designed
with flexibility in mind,
so I'm proud to announce
that you can take advantage
of these new properties
on devices as far back as
last year's operating systems,
even though they did not
originally ship with them.
All you'll need to make
this happen is to use
Xcode 14 to build your app,
and you'll have access
to these properties in
the previous operating systems.
This is possible
because the implementation
for these properties
are compiled into your app,
so when your customers
update to the new version,
they'll be able to get the
benefits of these enhancements
without needing to update
their operating system.
There is one thing
to keep in mind
when using these properties,
though.
These properties
will return sentinel values
when you're using
StoreKit testing in Xcode
in these older
operating systems.
When I say sentinel values,
I'm referring to
placeholder values that signal
that these are not real values
you should work with,
and I'll explain
why this occurs.
The sandbox and production
environments
make use of these properties
by extracting the values
from the App Store
server response.
StoreKit testing
in Xcode, however,
is a local testing environment
that operates independently
from the App Store server.
This means we're not able
to backport the value of these
properties to the previous
operating systems there.
You can easily
get around this limitation
by updating your test device
to a new operating system,
and you'll be all set
to test these values
in the local environment.
Let's discuss some situations
that demonstrate
how you can start using
these new properties,
the first of which
is price locale.
StoreKit products already have
a display price property
to label the purchase price,
but with price locale,
you can format numbers
deriving from
the product's decimal price.
If you have
a yearly subscription,
you might
use this as an opportunity
to show your customers how much
it would cost them per month.
In this example, you can see
that the yearly subscription
amounts to $4.17 per month.
Or perhaps
you'd want to show them
how much they would save if they
purchased your yearly service
over your monthly service.
With this information,
your customers can make
informed decisions
when they're considering
your purchase options.
Now, let's move on
to the environment property.
The environment property
is available
in the Transaction
and renewal Info.
This property tells you
the server environment
in which the transaction
or renewal info originated in,
which could be Xcode,
sandbox, or production.
Your app may communicate
transaction information
to your server after a customer
makes a purchase
for bookkeeping and analytics.
When your app generates
these transactions,
it could be from any one
of these server environments.
Like most of you,
I don't want to add noise
to my analytics
with irrelevant test data.
So, knowing the environment
can help you
filter out unnecessary
information from being sent up
to your server.
Finally, let's take a look at
the recent subscription
start date.
The recent subscription
start date is available
within a product's
subscription information,
and it represents
the most recent period
of continuous subscription.
A subscription is considered
continuous if there is no more
than a 60-day gap between
any two subscribed periods.
Keep in mind that this period
can contain gaps
where the customer was not
subscribed to your product,
so don't use this
as an indicator
for the number of days
a customer has been subscribed.
The recent subscription
start date can help you
determine a pattern of loyalty
between you and your customers.
For your loyal customers,
you might offer them a reward
as a way to keep them
engaged with your product.
Or if you notice that a customer
has unsubscribed
from your service,
you can use it as a chance
to win back a lapsed customer
by offering them an incentive to
start using your product again.
I mentioned earlier
that we'd take a closer look
at the sentinel values
for these properties.
As a reminder,
when I say sentinel values,
I'm referring
to placeholder values
that serve as an indicator
of the absence of a real value.
The sentinel values for these
properties are easy to identify.
When you're dealing
with price locale,
the sentinel value is a locale
with the identifier xx_XX.
For the environment property,
it'll be an empty string.
And finally, for the recent
subscription start date,
this value is Date.distantPast.
Luckily, the occurrence
of these sentinel values
are predictable --
you'll only encounter them
if you're using
StoreKit testing in Xcode
in older operating systems,
and you can get around this
by updating your test device.
So now you've seen
the enhancements
we've made
to our StoreKit models.
And my favorite part is,
they're backward compatible
all the way back
to the operating system
in which the models
were introduced,
so your customers can see
the benefits right away
just by updating your app.
When you perform arithmetic
with price values,
the price locale
helps you correctly format it
so that it matches
the App Store's locale.
For transactions
and subscription information,
the environment
tells you exactly
where they originated from,
so if you store this data
on your server,
you can act on it accordingly
depending on the environment.
The recent subscription
start date helps you understand
customer loyalty, so you can
tailor specific offers
to long-time customers,
or maybe you can provide
an incentive for customers
who have unsubscribed.
And in case you were wondering,
yes, the environment
and recent subscription
start date are also available
via App Store Server API and
App Store Server Notifications,
which Ian will discuss.
Now I'd like talk about the
new SwiftUI APIs we're providing
for redeeming offer codes
and requesting a review.
Offer codes can help
you acquire, retain,
and win back subscribers
by providing subscriptions
at a discount
or free for a limited time.
Now in App Store Connect,
you can create uniquely named
custom codes.
There, you can set
a maximum redemption limit
and you can choose whether
or not to set an expiration.
Let's look at the SwiftUI
implementation to present
an offer code redemption sheet
straight from your app.
Here, I've got a SwiftUI view
with a button to trigger
the offer code redeem sheet.
The offer code redemption sheet
now has its own
view modifier in SwiftUI.
The view modifier
is easy to use,
it just needs a binding Boolean
to start the process.
And once the offer code sheet
is dismissed,
you'll get a result
representing
whether or not the sheet
presented successfully.
When a customer redeems
an offer code for your app,
the resulting transaction
is sent
to the transaction listener.
So, be sure to set up
a transaction listener
as soon as your app launches
to receive new
and updated transactions
while your app is running.
The offer code view modifier
is available starting on iOS 16.
Next, I'd like to talk about
updates to request review.
Getting customer feedback
is important.
Potential new customers
might use reviews
as a deciding factor in their
decision to download your app.
Others might want to leave
a review as a way to provide
feedback or suggestions.
Either way, we want to give you
the tools to make it easy
for you to request
a rating from your customers,
so you can let them know
you're listening
and you can continue
engaging with them.
Let's review the code.
Here I have a very simple view
to demonstrate
the Request Review APIs.
In SwiftUI,
there's now an environment value
called requestReview.
You can use this value
to get an instance
of the RequestReviewAction,
and when you're ready
to request a rating,
simply call the instance
as a function
to request to display
the review prompt.
You can decide
the right time to request
a review for your app.
However, you should be aware
that the prompt will only be
displayed to customers
a maximum of three times
within a 365-day period.
And you shouldn't ask customers
to review the same version
of your app multiple times.
Avoid interrupting customers
with a review prompt.
A good time to ask for a review
could be after they've
had a positive interaction,
such as completing a purchase
on an e-commerce app,
or completing a level in a game.
Finally, customers can disable
requests from ever appearing
on their device,
so you shouldn't request
a review as a result
of a user action.
These APIs are really
going to come in handy
for your SwiftUI apps.
Next,
I'd like to introduce you
to our new API
for StoreKit messages.
A StoreKit message represents
a sheet that appears over
your app to display important
information to the user.
Messages are vended
by the App Store.
Each message has a reason,
which is included
in the message metadata.
StoreKit messages are retrieved
when your app
comes to the foreground.
As an example,
let's take a look at
one of the message reasons --
price increase consent.
When you increase
the price of a subscription
and it requires user consent,
the App Store will inform
affected subscribers through
email, push notification,
and an in-app
price consent sheet.
In this case, the App Store
requires that the user
agrees to the new price
of your subscription
before it renews
at the higher price.
So, if you decide to charge
more for your subscription,
a price increase consent sheet
may appear
when a user opens your app if
they haven't already responded
to your price increase.
By default, StoreKit messages
appear over your app
when the user brings
your app to the foreground,
and it may ask the user
to take some action
relating to your app.
Let's review this.
The entire process
starts with your app.
When your app
enters the foreground,
StoreKit knows to check
if there's pending messages
to display.
And if there are, StoreKit
checks in with the App Store.
The App Store returns
information about the message
to StoreKit.
At this time,
StoreKit checks whether your app
is set up to receive messages.
You can do this by setting up
a message listener in your app,
which I'll get into shortly.
If your app has set up
a message listener,
StoreKit sends information
about the message to your app.
Now's your chance to decide
whether or not it's a good time
for your app
to display the message,
or if you want to defer
the presentation for later.
If you don't set up
a message listener,
StoreKit displays
the message right away
by presenting the message sheet
over your app.
I'll go over
how to do this in code.
But before I do that,
I'll explain a situation
in which it would be useful
to control the presentation
of an App Store message.
In the Food Truck app,
I'm able to customize the donuts
I'm delivering
to different cities.
If a message gets delivered
to my app during this time,
it would be confusing
to the user if they're suddenly
interrupted by a message sheet,
so I'm going to be implementing
the messages API
to make sure this doesn't happen
by controlling when incoming
messages are presented.
Now let's get into the code.
Here, I have a simple view
for the donut editor.
As I mentioned earlier,
pending messages are sent
each time your app
comes to the foreground.
So, I want to set up
a message listener in each view
in which I want to defer
the presentation of a message.
I'll add a binding array
to collect all the messages
that are delivered to my app
while I'm in the editing view.
This is important, because if I
don't set up a message listener,
StoreKit is going to display
the message sheet right away
when my app
comes to the foreground.
As soon as the view appears,
I set up my message listener.
I'll do this by setting up
a task that iterates
over a static property
on the message type.
This property
is an async sequence,
and I'm able to receive messages
as they come in.
For my use case,
I'm going to save the message
in the pendingMessages array.
Since pending messages
get delivered each time
your app enters the foreground,
your app could receive
the same message more than once,
so I have this condition
to avoid adding
duplicate messages to my array.
Then, once the view dismisses,
I'll display the messages
in the parent view.
This is the parent view
which holds a navigation link
to the donut editor.
Here, I've collected
all the pending messages
I need to display
in this pendingMessages array.
So how do I display
these pending messages?
Well, now there's
an environment value
displayStoreKitMessage.
This gets you an instance
of a DisplayMessageAction,
which you can then use
to display a given message.
When the view appears,
I'll iterate through
the pending messages
and call displayStoreKitMessage
passing in the message
I want to display.
StoreKit takes care
of presenting the message sheet.
Earlier, I mentioned
that the same message
may get delivered to your app
more than once.
That's because a message
doesn't get marked as read
until it's presented
to the user.
So, StoreKit makes sure
that each unique message
is only presented once.
And that was
a quick implementation
of the Messages API.
Remember, StoreKit messages
are sent to your app each time
it comes to the foreground,
so you'll want to set up
a message listener in each view
in which you want to control
the timing of when
the messages are presented.
You can ensure customers have a
great experience by making sure
message sheets don't appear
at unexpected moments.
Or perhaps you want
to tailor your logic
for certain messages types.
With a price increase
consent message,
you may want to educate
your customer
about the additional value
you're providing
before the price increase
consent sheet appears.
Finally, let's review
how StoreKit preserves
the applicationUsername
as an appAccountToken
after a user makes a purchase.
If you have a user account
system on your server,
chances are
you're already making use
of the applicationUsername
property.
The applicationUsername
is a string that you create
to associate a transaction with
a user account on your service.
In the original API
for in-app purchase,
you set the applicationUsername
value when you add a payment
to the payment queue.
Although the applicationUsername
accepts any string,
we recommend that you provide
the string representation
of a UUID.
When you provide it
a UUID string,
StoreKit persists
the value and you'll see it
in the transaction
that the queue updates.
If you don't provide
a UUID string
for the applicationUsername,
StoreKit may not persist it.
There's no guarantee
the value will persist
between the time you add the
payment transaction to the queue
and when the queue updates
the transaction.
When you provide the string
representation of a UUID,
you can identify which of your
app's user accounts
began and completed
a transaction.
In the modern StoreKit APIs,
we implement this concept
as a purchase option
called appAccountToken
and it requires a UUID format.
Now, when you set
the applicationUsername
to a UUID string during payment,
the App Store server stores it
as an appAccountToken.
So you'll see its UUID appear
in the signed transaction info
returned by
the App Store Server API
and in V2 App Store
Server Notifications.
And as a UUID, it's compatible
with the appAccountToken
in the modern
StoreKit transaction APIs.
So, now you can be sure that
when you update your codebase
to the modern StoreKit APIs,
the UUID you used
for the applicationUsername
is preserved
as an appAccountToken
in the StoreKit transactions.
We touched on
a lot of things today.
Before moving on
to the server updates,
let's review this year's
StoreKit updates.
We discussed validating
your app's purchase
with App Transaction,
redeeming an offer code and
requesting a review in SwiftUI,
and controlling the presentation
of StoreKit messages.
We talked about
new price locale, environment,
and recent subscription
start date properties.
And, we went over
the importance of using
a string representation of a
UUID for the applicationUsername
to persist it
as an app account token.
I highly recommend
you check out our other session
"What's new
in StoreKit testing."
And if you need a refresher
on the StoreKit 2 APIs,
check out last year's session
"Meet StoreKit 2."
Now I'd like
to hand it over to Ian
to walk you through the updates
to the App Store server.
Ian Zanger: Thanks, Dani.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Ian,
and I'm an engineer
on the App Store Server team.
Now that you've heard the latest
about in-app purchase
with StoreKit,
I'm going to switch gears
and talk about the server.
First, I'll review some recent
developments from the past year
before moving on
to some exciting new updates
coming to
the App Store Server API
and App Store Server
Notifications Version 2.
Let's get started.
Last year was big.
We brought you an entirely new
suite of endpoints
with the App Store Server API
and App Store Server
Notifications V2,
including full
sandbox testing support
for all these new features.
We shared how you can use the
Get Transaction History endpoint
to get the full history
of a user's in-app purchases,
or the Get All Subscription
Statuses endpoint
to stay up to date
with the current state
of a user's subscriptions.
Both of these endpoints
conveniently key
off of a user's
originalTransactionId,
so you can access
this trove of data
by storing just
this one simple value.
We also covered how version 2
of App Store Server
Notifications
can simplify event processing
on your server
and complement
the App Store Server API.
With V2 notifications,
the App Store server
calls your server directly,
providing in-app purchase
updates as they happen.
The streamlined notification
type and subtype
make it easy to understand
what's happening.
You can use these
to track changes
related to in-app subscriptions
and other events.
With all of these data sources,
we wanted to make that data
as easy as possible to parse.
Receipts are now a thing
of the past,
as these new services
provide in-app data
in signed JSON format,
so you can easily parse it
and trust that it came
from the App Store server.
Last year was a big year
for the App Store server.
It may have been big
for you as well
if you worked to update
your server code
to leverage all
these new features.
Rest assured that effort
will continue to pay off
as we bring powerful new
enhancements and features
to App Store Server API and App
Store Server Notifications V2.
That's our year in review,
but if you'd like
more of a refresher
after hearing
this year's updates,
be sure to check out
the WWDC21 sessions titled
"Manage in-app purchases
on your server,"
"Meet StoreKit 2,"
and "Support customers
and handle refunds."
Now let's move on
to brand-new updates
coming to the App Store server
for WWDC22.
First I'll share
some updates to transaction
and renewal info fields.
Next I'll tell you about
new enhancements
to the App Store Server API.
And finally, I'll share
exciting new features
coming to App Store Server
Notifications V2.
Now let's dive in with
the first of our new topics:
new fields found in
transaction and renewal info.
Earlier, you heard from Dani
about a couple new fields
coming to the transaction
and renewal info
of in-app purchases.
These fields, environment
and recentSubscriptionStartDate,
are also coming
to the transaction
and renewal info payloads
you receive from
the App Store Server API
and in V2 App Store Server
Notifications.
Let's take a fresh look at the
data you can expect to receive
from the App Store server
with these new fields included.
First is the transaction
info payload,
which we can see here
after decoding.
Down at the bottom, you can see
our new field: environment.
You can use it to tell,
at a glance,
whether the transaction
took place
in the production
or sandbox environment.
Next is the renewal info
payload,
also seen here after decoding.
As you can see, the environment
field is also available here
for your reference.
Additionally,
recentSubscriptionStartDate
will now appear
in every renewal info payload.
This is the start date
of the user's first
subscription purchase in their
most recent string of renewals,
ignoring any gaps
of 60 days or fewer.
recentSubscriptionStartDate
is an easy way to get an idea
of a customer's loyalty
at a glance.
But if you'd like more detail,
including the timing and length
of any gaps in service,
you can call the
Get Transaction History endpoint
and examine the full history
of a user's subscription
renewal purchases.
Or for even more detail,
with App Store Server
Notifications V2,
the App Store server
automatically sends updates
about user subscriptions
to your server.
These notifications give you
maximum insight
into the timing of events like
renewal preference changes,
offer redemptions,
billing failures, and more.
As you can see,
recentSubscriptionStartDate
rounds out a suite of options
for determining
customer loyalty.
Use these tools to target offers
and reward your most
loyal customers.
Now let's move on to some
convenient new enhancements
to the Get Transaction History
endpoint.
With the Get Transaction History
endpoint,
you can fetch the full history
of a user's purchases
in your app.
The endpoint response
is paginated
so you can process this data
in reasonable chunks.
Each response contains a
revision token that you provide
in the next request in order
to get the next page.
And the pages are sorted
by modified date,
meaning each subsequent page
contains transactions
that are more recently modified.
Let's take a look
at how this works.
You call the Get Transaction
History endpoint,
and provide
an originalTransactionId.
The App Store server will return
up to 20 signed transactions
for that user.
It will also return
an updated revision value
that you will provide in your
next page request for this user.
You'll know there's
more data available
when the hasMore field
in the response is true.
Let's say in this case
that there's another page
of data available.
You make another request
to the endpoint,
and you include that revision
value from the first response.
You receive
the next page of data,
including an updated
revision value.
hasMore is now false,
so you know you're up to date
with the latest
transaction data.
Except this time,
you notice something
about the final transaction
in the response;
you've seen it before!
It was one of
the original 20 you received
in response to your first
request.
This means the transaction
must have been modified,
so it was put back at the top
of the sort order.
Now, you can examine
the data of that transaction
and take note of what's changed.
In this instance,
you notice the revocationDate
and revocationReason fields
are now populated,
meaning the transaction
was revoked.
You can take action
by revoking any content
associated with the purchase.
It's a good idea to store
the revision value
from this final response
alongside
the originalTransactionId
you used to identify the user.
The next time you call
the endpoint for this user,
you can provide
that revision and know
that you're getting back
only fresh transaction data
that has been modified
since your last request.
As you've seen, the
Get Transaction History endpoint
provides you a simple way
to retrieve a comprehensive set
of in-app purchase data.
But maybe sometimes it can be
a bit too comprehensive.
Some users have
lengthy purchase histories
dating back several years.
For these users,
this endpoint could return
hundreds of purchases
of a variety of types.
Even with pages,
this can be a lot to handle.
That's why this year,
we're enhancing this endpoint
with a variety of new sort
and filter options.
Now, you can tell us exactly the
data you want from the start,
saving processing time
on your server
and reducing the number
of network calls
needed to retrieve
all available pages.
You can sort
by descending modified date
if you're interested
in seeing the most recently
modified purchases
on the first page of results.
You can also filter
by several useful fields
such as product type,
product ID,
Family sharing status,
and more.
To apply these new
sort and filter options,
just append them as query
parameters to your request
to the Get Transaction History
endpoint.
Let's take a closer look
at how that works.
Here you can see all
the new parameter options.
These may look familiar,
since most are taken directly
from the transaction info
payload.
You can mix and match
these parameters
to get very specific results.
For example,
maybe we want to fetch
only the nonconsumable purchases
a user has made
since the beginning
of this year.
We also want to exclude
any revoked purchases.
We will build our custom request
by setting the productType
to NON_CONSUMABLE
and specifying the startDate
as the beginning of this year
represented in milliseconds.
Finally, we'll set
excludeRevoked to true.
And that's our request!
Since we did not specify
a sort order,
the response will default
to sorting
by ascending modified date.
Now even with a request
as specific as this,
there could be multiple pages
of purchases to retrieve.
For follow-up requests,
we should make sure
to include the exact same
query parameters,
in addition to the revision
from the previous response.
For even more flexibility,
three of the filter fields
support multiple values,
so you can filter
to only those purchases
that match at least
one of the provided values.
These fields are productType,
productId,
and subscriptionGroupIdentifier.
To provide multiple values
for these parameters,
simply define them
multiple times.
Next let's move on to App Store
Server Notification updates.
With App Store Server
Notifications V2,
you can take your server
to the next level.
V2 notifications
give detailed insights
about in-app purchase events
that you can't get
anywhere else.
These are especially useful
for tracking the lifecycle
of autorenewable subscriptions
offered in your app.
You can use these insights
to retain customers,
win back those
that have churned,
resolve customer support
requests, and more.
With all of these benefits, you
might wonder how to get started.
As with any new feature,
the sandbox testing environment
is the best place to start.
That's why last year,
we added the ability to set
a separate server URL
in App Store Connect
for receiving
App Store Server Notifications
in sandbox.
After registering
your server URL,
you'll want to confirm
your server
is receiving notifications
from the App Store server.
You might set up
a sandbox account
just to trigger a notification
through a user action.
For example, let's say you
perform a first time buy
of a subscription
using that sandbox account.
You should receive a V2
notification of type SUBSCRIBED
and subtype INITIAL_BUY.
But what if that notification
doesn't come?
You might wonder if there
was an issue with your server
or the steps you took
to trigger a notification.
This situation can generate
a lot of uncertainty
right as you're getting started.
We want to simplify this
experience and give you a way
to easily verify that App Store
Server Notifications
can reach your server.
That's why this year,
we're introducing the new
Request a Test Notification
endpoint.
By calling this simple
endpoint,
you can ask us to send
a V2 Notification of type TEST
to the server URL registered for
your app in App Store Connect.
The new TEST notification type
is used exclusively
for this endpoint.
You can call the endpoint
in sandbox or production
to test your saved URL
for either environment.
Use this new endpoint
to quickly test new server URLs
and configurations.
Let's see how this simplifies
first-time setup.
Now, if you're just looking to
trigger your first notification,
there's no need to set up
a sandbox account
or perform a purchase.
Just call the new endpoint
in whichever environment
you want to test
and you'll receive
an HTTP 200 response
confirming your request.
The response
will contain a new field,
testNotificationToken, which
identifies the test notification
your server will receive.
We will come back
to this field later.
Shortly afterward, your server
should receive a V2 notification
of type TEST at the URL
saved in App Store Connect.
Now let's see
how to call this endpoint.
Just send a simple POST request
to this new path
on the App Store server.
You'll receive
an HTTP 200 response
and know that your request
has been submitted.
The response will contain
that new field I mentioned,
testNotificationToken.
Take note of this for later.
Soon you'll receive
a signed TEST Notification.
Here's what that notification
will look like
once it's decoded.
You'll notice it contains
all the usual top-level fields
of a V2 notification,
including the new
notificationType, TEST.
The contents of the data object
are a bit shorter
than a normal notification.
Since this is just a test,
there are no transaction-related
data to include,
so we omit
transaction-specific fields,
most notably
the signedTransactionInfo.
When calling the new Request
a Test Notification endpoint,
keep in mind that App Store
Server Notifications
are sent asynchronously.
Your successful call
to the endpoint
will return an HTTP 200
but the actual test notification
will arrive separately,
a short while later.
Given that this endpoint
is all about
testing your server
configuration,
you might be wondering
what to do when that test fails.
In other words, what if the test
notification doesn't arrive?
To further enhance
your testing capabilities,
we're releasing the Get Test
Notification Status endpoint,
which you will use
in conjunction
with the Request a Test
Notification endpoint.
With this new endpoint,
you can check on the status
of a previously requested
TEST notification.
The endpoint response will tell
you if the App Store server
was able to reach your server
and successfully send
the TEST notification.
If the send failed,
it will give you an idea of why,
so you can better troubleshoot
your server configuration.
Let's check out how you'll use
this endpoint.
Send a GET request to this path
on the App Store server.
In the path, include
the testNotificationToken
you received from the Request
a Test Notification endpoint.
This will tell us
which test notification
you want to check the status of.
Now for the response.
The signedPayload field contains
the TEST notification payload
that the App Store server
attempted to send
to your server.
And the firstSendAttemptResult
field indicates the result
of that send attempt.
Here, SUCCESS indicates
that the send was successful,
meaning the App Store server
received an HTTP 200 response
from your server.
If the send was unsuccessful,
you'll instead see one of
several different error values.
These values indicate the error
the App Store server experienced
trying to reach your server
with the test notification.
With this information, you can
troubleshoot your server issue,
request new test notifications
as needed,
and get your server
running reliably.
Collectively, these test
notification endpoints
are simple to use and can
save you a lot of trouble
when setting up
or reconfiguring your server
to receive V2 App Store Server
Notifications.
Now with the help
of these endpoints,
you can set up your server and
confirm it's running smoothly.
But servers aren't perfect
and outages happen.
How do you recover
when your server goes down,
leading you to miss
App Store Server Notifications?
The current solution to this
is a retry system.
When the App Store server
fails to reach your server,
it initiates a retry process.
It will retry sending the same
notification up to five times,
with a longer wait
between each attempt.
These retries take place only
in the production environment.
Retries help you eventually
recover from an outage,
but they're not perfect
for every situation.
For example, some outages
can be extensive.
If your server
is down long enough
to miss the final retry attempt
from the App Store server,
that notification is lost.
Or more commonly,
your server could experience
a very brief issue,
during which it misses
only a handful of notifications.
But missing even
a single notification
means some of your customer
records are out of date
for at least an hour.
Yet you don't know which ones!
Clearly, server outages
are stressful,
and recovering from them
can be a complex task.
That's why we want to make it
as easy as possible
to recover missed
App Store Server Notifications,
so you can get your server back
on track as soon as possible.
That's why this year,
we are introducing the new
Get Notification History
endpoint.
With this endpoint,
you can fetch the history of V2
App Store Server Notifications
generated for your app.
Whether your server successfully
received a notification or not,
that notification will appear in
the response of this endpoint.
When calling this endpoint,
you'll specify a date range
of notifications to fetch.
With WWDC, we have started
recording this data,
and we will build up to the cap
of the latest six months
of rolling history
being available.
You can optionally filter your
request by type and subtype,
or fetch just
a single user's notifications
by providing
an originalTransactionId.
And the existing retry system
is still available,
so you can use it in tandem
with this new endpoint.
Let's take a look at how
you'll call this endpoint.
You'll send a POST request
to this new path
on the App Store server.
In the request body, you'll
include a startDate and endDate.
The response will contain
only notifications
we first attempted to send
in this window.
Keep in mind that the earliest
notifications available
will be those sent six months
before the date of your request.
Optionally, you can specify
a notificationType
and notificationSubtype.
If you do, the history will be
filtered to only notifications
that match both of these values.
Keep in mind that some
notifications have no subtype.
Alternatively,
you can provide
an originalTransactionId
of a user,
to fetch the notification
history of only that user.
Finally, you should provide
a paginationToken
as a query parameter
for every follow-up request
in order to get the next page.
Make sure you use
the same request body
for follow-up requests,
changing only
this paginationToken.
Now let's take a look
at the response.
The notificationHistory array
contains up to 20 notifications,
with the oldest
notifications first.
Each entry in this array
represents a notification
and inside you'll find
the signedPayload,
which you can decode as usual
to view the transaction data.
The data within
is identical to the payload
the App Store server sent
in the original notification.
You'll see that we've also
brought the new
firstSendAttemptResult field
to this endpoint response.
You can use this field to look
for sequences of timeouts
and other errors to better
understand why your server
missed notifications
in the past.
The response also contains
a paginationToken
if there are more pages
to retrieve.
You should provide this
in your next request
in order to get the next page
of notifications.
You'll know there are
more pages to retrieve
as long as
the hasMore field is true.
And that's everything
you need to know
about this useful new endpoint.
That concludes our App Store
server updates for today.
Every server feature
announced today is available now
in both sandbox and production.
We hope you'll take advantage
of these new features
to make your server
the best it can be.
For more great content on using
a server with in-app purchase,
including how to use
the latest features
while supporting legacy clients,
I encourage you to check out
another session at WWDC22,
"Explore in-app purchase
integration and migration."
Both: Thanks for joining us
at WWDC22!
♪