♪ ♪
Karthik: Hi, I'm Karthik,
an engineer on the Messages team.
In this video,
I'm going to introduce Shared with You,
and how to adopt it in your app.
Shared with You was announced in iOS 15.
It is designed to make it easier
for you to revisit links
that friends and family send you
in Messages.
System applications that have
adopted Shared with You are
Safari, News,
Music, Podcasts,
the TV app and Photos.
Shared with You meets you
where you're consuming content.
Many times content is received
when we are not ready to consume it.
For example, a friend sends
a recommendation for a TV show
while you are out grocery shopping,
and then it's forgotten
in the course of the day.
Shared with You makes it easier
to discover this TV show later on
when you are browsing
for TV shows to watch in the TV app
Shared with You makes it convenient to
pick up a Messages conversation
right from within the app,
allowing you to stay in context
of shared content
without leaving the app.
Your content can be pinned in Messages.
It elevates the content
in Shared with You and Search.
This is a signal
that content is important,
and starts the flow
of automatic sharing consent.
More on that later.
In iOS 16, Shared with You is extended
to include your apps, links, and content.
This takes the convenience of
Shared with You and puts it in your apps.
I'll first talk about the design
of Shared with You in your app,
then show you how it works,
and then walk you through
how to adopt Shared with You.
Starting with design.
There are two parts of Shared with You
that are part of your app experience:
The Shared with You shelf,
and the Shared with You attribution view.
The Shared with You shelf
is a dedicated space
in your app's browsing experience
that highlights content
that was shared in Messages.
For example, the TV app's "Watch Now" tab
has a Shared with You shelf.
So does the Listen Now tab
in Music and Podcasts.
The content provided by Shared with You
is a ranked and ordered list.
I'll go over that later in the video.
For each item
in the Shared with You shelf,
show a rich preview
along with an attribution view.
A rich preview has thumbnail, a title,
and a subtitle if applicable.
In this example, the rich preview
consists of podcast art,
episode name, and the show name.
There is also an attribution view
for each shared content
in the Shared with You shelf.
This is the all of the information
that allows context
to be gleaned at a glance.
Have a Show More element
that can expand the view
or navigate to showing all of your app's
Shared with You content.
The Attribution view
is an out of process view
that securely displays the names
and avatars of who shared it.
It also shows
if the content was pinned in Messages.
Show the attribution view
in the details view of your content.
This allows people to connect
content in your app
back to the Messages conversation
it was shared in.
For example,
when I'm browsing for a TV show to watch,
the attribution view helps me recall
that a friend had recommend it.
I can quickly tell my friend
that I'm about to watch the show.
All this happens right in app,
and after replying,
I'm right back at the content.
The attribution view is interactive.
Tapping on the view takes you
to the Messages conversation
right from within the application.
The attribution view also presents
contextual menu options
such as "Reply" and "Remove".
The "Reply" content menu option
functions similar to tapping the view.
The "Remove" context menu option
is a way to tell the Shared with You
not to surface a piece of content
going forward.
The same contextual menus
are made available to you
to add to your content's contextual menus.
The title for the Remove context menu
can be customized.
For example in Safari,
the contextual menu
for the web page shows "Remove Link".
I'll go over how you can do this
in your app later on in this video.
Now you know where to present
a Shared with You shelf
and where to show the Attribution View.
Let me show you how Shared with You works.
Links shared by friends and family in
Messages are surfaced in Shared with You.
Links in group conversations are surfaced
when at least one participant
is a contact.
Shared with You is based on the same
technology behind Universal Links.
Universal Links allows for
seamless linking to content in your app
or on your website.
Users have granular control
over Shared with You content.
They can choose what content is shared
outside of Messages
on a per conversation basis,
per app, or globally.
This permission doesn't need
to be requested in advance.
It happens organically.
Pinning links is implicit permission
to surface the content in Shared with You.
Pinned content is always available
to Shared with You in your app.
Based on heuristics when content
for your app is pinned in Messages,
an option to enable
automatic sharing is presented.
When automatic sharing is turned on,
further content is automatically available
to Shared with You in your app.
Content in Shared with You is ordered.
The first item in the Shared with You
shelf is curated by Siri Suggestions
based on various signals from the system.
This is followed by Pinned items
and the remainder of the list
is chronologically ordered.
Siri Suggestions uses signals
such as "Has the user viewed
or interacted with the content?"
Is the content Pinned?
In which context
is the content being presented?
Your app plays a part
in providing this feedback.
I'll go over in detail
a little later on in the video.
All this is done to ensure that content
is not too transient or stale.
In a conversation
when a link is shared multiple times,
Shared with You surfaces
only the most recent message.
When a link is shared in
multiple Messages conversations,
Shared with You visually represents
that via the attribution view.
For example,
both Enrique and Sarah have shared
the Top 25 Chicago playlist.
The attribution view shows
both their contact avatars.
Tapping on the attribution view
presents a disambiguation menu,
allowing you to choose which Messages
conversation to reply to.
Security and Privacy
was a primary consideration
and focus when designing Shared with You.
The attribution views
and disambiguation views
are drawn on your behalf out of process.
Shared with You protects
your app's content
via the Universal Links association
so it is accessible to only your app.
Apps do not have access to Messages
recipients and conversations.
Now you know how Shared with You works.
On to the most exciting part–
how to adopt Shared with You in your app.
First, adopt Universal Links.
Then, add the new Shared with You
Capability,
under the Capabilities tab in Xcode.
Then, put a Shared with You shelf
in your app,
and add attribution view
to your content.
Let me briefly talk about
adopting Universal Links.
Universal Links allows your users
to intelligently follow links to content
in your app or to your website.
Take the following steps
to support universal links.
First create a two-way association
between your app and your website
and specify the URLs
that your app handles.
You create them by adding the Associated
Domains entitlement to your app,
and by adding a JSON file
to your web server.
Next, update your app delegate
to respond to the user activity object
the system provides
when a universal link routes to your app.
For more information, please watch
the "What's new in Universal Links" video.
In iOS 16 we have introduced
a new Framework called Shared with You.
There are three main classes
in the Shared with You Framework:
SWHighlightCenter,
SWHighlight, and SWAttributionView.
SWHighlightCenter is the class that helps
you get Shared with You content
for your app.
SWHighlight is a model object
that wraps your app's shared content.
SWAttributionView is the view
that helps connect your content
back to a Messages conversation
and displays attribution information.
The highlight center is
a simple object that consists of:
Highlights,
which is an array of SWHighlight objects;
and a delegate property
by which apps get notified
when there is content added,
removed, or updated by Shared with You.
A highlight is represented
by the SWHighlight class.
It is used to pass the URL for your app's
content that was shared in Messages.
You use it to refer to your content,
render a rich preview,
and navigate to the content in your app.
Let me show you how to enumerate
Shared with You content in your app.
First create an instance
of SWHighlightCenter.
Then set the delegate property.
Implement the SWHighlightCenterDelegate
method.
Use the highlights property
on the highlight center
to access your app's Shared with You
content.
Apps can choose to keep
the previous list of highlights
in order to quickly diff that list
against the latest list.
Use the URL property on each highlight
to generate a Rich preview
of your app's content.
And it's as easy as that to enumerate
Shared with You content in your app.
Next, I'll show you how to add
and customize the Attribution View
to your app's Shared with You content.
SWAttributionView is the view
that shows the names and avatars
of who shared the content.
Each highlight has
a corresponding attribution view.
Setting the highlight Property
on the attribution view
triggers the out of process rendering
of the attribution information.
Specify a maximum width
the attribution view can take.
The attribution view will fill
or fit the space as needed.
Set the alignment of the attribution view
within the maximum space.
Let me show you an example.
Create an instance of SWAttributionView
and set the highlight property.
Set the preferredMaxLayoutWidth.
In this example it spans the bottom
of the shared content thumbnail.
Constrain this view's width anchor
or set its frame width to control
the maximum width of its contents.
Set the maximum AX content size category
for the view as necessary
using:
minimumContentSizeCategory
or maximumContentSizeCategory
properties on UIView.
Provide enough vertical space
around this view.
The view's height is dependent
on the preferredContentSizeCategory,
and the resulting font size.
If the view's height
is unnecessarily constrained,
then the view might be clipped
or not get drawn.
The horizontalAlignment is set
to leading in this case.
It can also be set to Center
or Trailing.
Next, let me show you how to customize
the Attribution view.
Setting a display context helps inform
the system
about how the user is consuming
the attributed content.
It also influences ranking of
Shared with You content for your app.
Set this before it's added to a window.
The background style of
the attribution view can be customized
based on the content's background
it is being used against.
Let me show you an example.
The default value for
displayContext property is summary.
This indicates that the content
is being shown for consumption.
Set the displayContext to detail
when the user is actively consuming
the content,
like watching a movie
or listening to a podcast.
Setting the displayContext
is the feedback your app can provide.
This'll help Siri Suggestions
rank content for you app.
Set the background style
for the attribution view to color
when placing the attribution view
over monochrome backgrounds
like in this example.
Use material when placing the attribution
view over multicolored backgrounds.
This sets a material background blur
for the view's contents.
In this example, Safari's landing page
has a background image.
The contents of the attribution view
are more visible
by setting the correct background style.
Next let me show you how to add Shared
with You Contextual Menus
to your app's content
and customize the title.
The existing contextual menu
attached to your app's content
can be supplemented
by the attribution view's menu.
This menu should be added inline with
or at the end of the contextual menu
it augments.
A custom title for the Remove contextual
menu option can be provided.
The string should include the word
"Remove", localized correctly.
In this example, Safari has customized
the Remove menu title to "Remove Link"
in its content's context menu at the end.
Let me show you how to do this
via an example.
First create an instance
of the attribution view
and set the highlight property.
Provide a custom title
for the Remove context menu
via the menuTitleForHideAction.
When configuring
your content's context menu,
get the menu from the attribution view
via the supplementalMenu property.
Then append them
to your content's context menu.
These easy steps allow your app
to add the context menu option
available on the attribution view
to your content's context menus.
Now you know all that is needed
to adopt Shared with You in your app.
Let's recap the three easy steps
Go adopt Universal Links.
Then add the new Shared with You
Capability in Xcode for your app.
Import and use the new
Shared with You framework.
I'm looking forward to sharing
your content in Messages
and using Shared with You in your app.
Thank you for your time and attention.