♪ ♪
Hi, my name is Vincenzo,
and I'm a type designer
on the Apple Design Team.
I'm part of the group responsible
for the design and expansion
of many of the font families
used in our platforms.
We focus on making functional
and expressive fonts
that are essential
in enabling great typography.
I'm here to share some awesome
updates on San Francisco
and tell you about all the latest
additions to the system fonts.
We'll start with an overview
of the San Francisco family of fonts.
I'll take you through
the various available families,
styles, and Optical Sizes.
Then I'll introduce
the new width styles in SF Pro:
Condensed, Compressed, and Expanded.
I'll also share a few examples
of how and why to choose these styles
while designing User Interfaces.
And to wrap up,
I'll talk about how we're bringing
many of the features of San Francisco
to other writing systems,
introducing SF Arabic
and SF Arabic Rounded.
Let's jump right in,
starting with a quick overview
of San Francisco.
San Francisco is a functional
and versatile family of fonts
designed by Apple
and used throughout our platforms.
Over the years San Francisco
has grown in parallel
with an eco-system of products
and experiences,
providing new styles and families
capable of adapting
to the various needs of UI design.
Today San Francisco includes
different font families
which share a common visual language
but with unique features designed
specifically for different environments
and applications,
such as SF Pro and SF Pro Rounded,
the main system fonts
used in many of our platforms,
like iOS, iPadOS, macOS, and tvOS.
SF Compact and SF Compact Rounded,
a variation of San Francisco optimized
for narrow columns and small point sizes,
also the default system fonts in watchOS.
And SF Mono,
the monospaced SF:
used in coding environments
like Xcode and Swift Playgrounds.
All of these font families, together,
provide great functionality
and range of expression
that allows text to be rendered
in a variety of contexts.
Most SF families come with
a comprehensive palette of weights,
spanning from Ultralight to Black,
providing enough stylistic variation
to create emphasis
and typographic hierarchies.
Also, most of the font families come
with Optical Sizes,
allowing the fonts to automatically adjust
certain design features
based on the point size of text.
For example, moving the dot on top of
the "i" further away from the base shape,
or opening up
the apertures of certain glyphs,
as well as progressively tracking out text
at smaller point sizes.
All of these adjustments optimize
the fonts generating unique designs
to fit different point sizes,
for both Display and Text typesetting,
typographic terms used in reference
to Large and Small text.
The San Francisco fonts offer control
and flexibility
to render clear and legible interfaces
consistently across all Apple platforms.
These are some of the highlights of SF,
but there's so much more.
If you want to dive deeper
into Optical Sizes, Variable fonts,
and Dynamic Type,
I encourage you to check out
Loïc and Jiang's session "The details
of UI typography" from WWDC 2020.
Now, today we're going to be focusing
on SF Pro,
which is already an incredible tool
to design User Interfaces.
However, while weights and optical sizes
already cover many designers' needs,
we identified a set of specific tasks
that couldn't be fulfilled by
just Weight and Optical axes.
For instance, in the Photos app,
where we expanded the stylistic variations
of the Titles in Memories.
Or in News, where SF serves
as the editorial voice in headlines,
with expressive
and space-efficient styles.
And lastly, in Maps,
where providing more stylistic options
increased typographic contrast
and legibility.
So we further expanded
the capabilities of SF
by designing a new axis.
With Weights and Optical Sizes
already available,
adding a Width axis was the natural
evolution of SF:
Joining the Regular Width
we have three more styles:
Condensed,
narrow and space-efficient;
Compressed, the most compact
style currently available in SF;
and last but not least, on
the other end of the spectrum, Expanded.
These are all the new available Widths
in SF,
which in combination with all the Weights,
add a tremendous amount of options,
bringing a whole set of new voices
and functionalities
to accommodate a broad range
of applications.
Some of these styles are more neutral;
others are more expressive.
Every style is functional
in its own right,
but depending on the design intent,
some will perform better than others.
There are no absolute rules in typography,
but you can expect the styles that
gravitate towards the center
of the stylistic map of SF
to have a more neutral voice,
while the styles
around the perimeter of the map,
which feature more extreme Weight
and Width proportions,
to be more expressive,
have a stronger voice,
attributes that can be useful
if you want to draw people's attention
towards a certain area of the UI
or strengthen a typographic hierarchy.
Let's explore the shared and unique
features of these styles
and learn how to make
more informed decisions
during the process of choosing
and pairing fonts.
First things first, all the styles provide
the same language support
and can be used to typeset
most of the languages
which use the Latin script,
from English to Vietnamese.
But also Greek and languages
based on the Cyrillic writing system.
Something else that all the styles
have in common is the vertical proportions
so that they can be used without any
visual scale discrepancies across Weight.
A feature that makes swapping
or mixing fonts predictable and easy,
so when using different Width styles,
the focus is solely on the Width itself.
In fact, only the horizontal proportions
of the glyphs change
and of course, as a byproduct,
the line length.
The progressively narrower proportions
highlight a defining aspect
that differs between the styles,
which is the relationship between
the stem thickness of each style, which–
albeit some optical adjustments–
remains fairly consistent.
Instead, the negative area
inside the glyphs,
which has a much more dramatic shift,
becomes much tighter or wider
depending on the Width style.
This balance has stylistic
and functional implications
in regards to the legibility of a font,
but also the personality.
So here are some considerations
regarding each style.
I'm sure it doesn't come as a surprise
that the Regular Width
is the most ubiquitous
and versatile style.
It features standard proportions,
making text easy to read.
You can stick to the Regular Width
when the functionalities offered
by the other Widths are not necessary.
Condensed, while looking narrower
compared to the Regular style,
still features a comfortable Width,
allowing itself to be used to fit
more text without being overly present.
Compressed features
very dense proportions,
with flat-sided shapes, which allow
the design to become much tighter,
making it very space-efficient
but also graphical and
ideal as a Display style.
And lastly, Expanded,
with a striking loose and open appearance
that can find use in Display typesetting
but also smaller labels,
and secondary content.
We can see them in action,
typesetting the same text
using the same Weight
but different Widths,
calls attention to one of the most obvious
use cases for these new styles,
which is space-efficiency.
In fact, we can notice how tighter
or wider SF looks at the same point size.
But also how we can typeset
Condensed or Compressed much larger
while still fitting in
the same line length,
which is very useful when
dealing with titles and headlines.
But it's not only about Display sizes.
In fact, the Width styles can
help control longer passages of text,
providing the ability
to fit more characters per line,
achieving a more ideal and comfortable
reading experience for narrow columns.
or just shortening
or lengthening a paragraph,
for filling or freeing space in a layout.
However, this example highlights
also how the Compressed style,
while still functional
for small single lines,
might be too tight for longer
passages of text, like you see here.
So always consider legibility
when opting for a non-Regular Width.
Now that we've seen the main features
of these new styles,
let me walk you through a few examples
of how they've helped us
improve and expand
the typography in our apps.
Let's start with Photos,
where the new range of Widths,
joined other styles
bringing even more visual interest
in the Titles of Memories
with text treatments that celebrate
and elevate the content
from the rest of the UI.
Taking a closer look,
we can see that the difference in scale
takes care of establishing
the typographic hierarchy,
telling us clearly
which is the primary piece of information
and which is the secondary.
Two contrasting Width styles,
like Compressed and Expanded,
take on the job of making the text
more unique and visually impactful.
Pairing the wide and condensed styles
of SF with different weights
can allow for a near-endless variety
of font pairings.
For instance, you can decide
to stick to just one Width style–
Expanded in this case–
and use contrasting Weights,
like Black and Light.
Or you can pick a single Weight
and use different contrasting Widths,
like Expanded and Compressed.
You can also combine both approaches
by mixing opposite Width and Weight,
for an even more decided contrast.
Together with the other
San Francisco families,
like SF Pro Rounded, SF Mono,
and also New York,
the serif system font,
the new Width styles open
a world of possible combinations.
In News, in addition to complementing
the editorial context of the app,
the Width styles provided
extra flexibility and practicality,
like in this example,
where using Condensed allows a long
Headline to be more space-efficient,
wrapping into four lines instead of five,
or even tighter, with Compressed,
which brings the title down
to three lines.
Opening up quite a bit of real estate
in the layout,
as well as making the Title stand up,
giving it more personality.
Notice also how the Expanded Widths,
used to contrast the Headline,
feel at home in captions and bylines.
We can see another specific but very
interesting use case for Expanded in Maps,
where the wide horizontal proportions
of this style
paired with loose tracking
work perfectly when used to represent
large geographical areas,
like mountain ranges.
But of course,
cartography's not just about mountains.
In fact, Maps adopted other Widths of SF
to create a rich typographic system,
with styles coherent between each other
but also diverse and contrasting,
making it easier to read
and tell apart all kinds of labels:
such as roads,
countries, continents, et cetera.
While, in most cases,
two or three styles are more than enough
to design an effective hierarchy,
this is a great demonstration
of how SF Pro can support
even the most elaborate graphic systems.
And those are just a few examples of how
to take advantage of the new Width styles.
The expanded functionality
and range of expression
make SF Pro an even more powerful
communication tool.
However, with great typographic power,
comes great responsibility.
Remember that fonts are design tools that
are meant to make interfaces beautiful,
but most importantly
legible and accessible.
Let's do a quick recap
with some of the considerations made
on the new Compressed,
Condensed, and Expanded styles.
First and foremost, the new Width styles
unlock an unprecedented level of control
in your layouts, giving you the ability
to make text wider or tighter
to efficiently design and arrange
typographic elements in your apps.
Also,
in addition to Weight, Size, and Color,
the new Width styles provide
more stylistic options
to create even more clear
and precise typographic hierarchies.
The fonts with more extreme
Weight and Width proportions
provide expressive styles that work great
at Display point sizes,
to elevate titles and headlines
from the rest of the UI.
All the SF Pro fonts cover most languages
using the Latin,
Greek, and Cyrillic alphabets.
However, if localization is
an essential aspect of your app
and you're looking to provide
a consistent experience
across multiple writing systems,
other than the aforementioned ones,
make sure you have a fallback plan,
by identifying alternative solutions
that can help you localize your app.
Okay, so we did go through many
of the new features of the system font,
but we're not done yet.
There is another way
the family is expanding.
At Apple, we design for a global audience.
Our devices are used by people
from all around the world
who read and write different scripts
and languages.
Fonts play a huge role
in designing interfaces
that are both stylistically
and functionally consistent
across multiple languages,
providing integrity to the many
graphical elements featuring text.
And text is everywhere,
like in the Large Titles and Table Rows
in these screens,
but also in Buttons,
Platters, Icon labels.
Text is in Widgets, Keyboards,
Tab bars and many more,
in many more languages!
One area where
we incorporate these principles
and we can achieve
the highest level of consistency
is with experiences
that are self-contained
and can use fonts we design
for the ultimate localized experience,
allowing your screensaver on the Mac
to greet you in Japanese
and many other languages with
the iconic "hello" cursive style.
or the iPhone to display the time
using Arabic,
Arabic-Indic, or Devanagari numerals
with the same consistent typeface.
Or on the Typograph watch-face,
which features
five different numeral sets,
including the new Chinese numerals.
We want to bring the same level
of consistency to the system fonts,
which have to work
for a much broader range of applications.
This requires extending
the linguistic coverage of San Francisco
and allowing other writing systems
to benefit from features
like Weights and Optical Sizes,
providing a reading experience that is,
at the same time,
visually engaging and comfortable,
for every script and language,
in any of our platforms.
This expansion started last year
when we introduced
the new Arabic system font,
SF Arabic.
We designed SF Arabic
to seamlessly integrate
with the rest
of the San Francisco families.
SF Arabic is a contemporary interpretation
of the Naskh style
with a rational and flexible design,
and it's the latest writing system,
after Latin, Greek, and Cyrillic,
to benefit from the most advanced
font technologies,
available on the Apple platforms.
Like the other San Francisco families,
it features the full gamut of weights,
Ultralight through Black,
and each of the nine weights has been
carefully designed to fit and combine
with the other scripts
and languages supported in SF.
Also, SF Arabic comes with Optical Sizes
tailored specifically
for the Arabic script.
Allowing the fonts to automatically adjust
the stroke contrast
and terminals and spacing,
adapting and scaling the design
between Display and Text sizes.
The Text styles are fine-tuned
for high Legibility and familiarity,
featuring a higher stroke contrast
and wider spacing.
While the Display styles morph into
a design with a simpler geometry,
blending with the clean
and contemporary look of San Francisco.
And all of this is automatically
and dynamically taken care of
by the system,
enabling a comfortable
reading experience at all sizes.
Like the Latin,
and Cyrillic writing systems,
the Arabic script is highly multilingual
and is used to write
not only the Arabic language,
but also a variety of other languages,
such as Persian, Pashto,
Sindhi, and many more,
all supported by SF Arabic.
Numerous vocalization,
tone, and poetic marks,
extended vowel signs, honorifics,
and Quranic annotations
complete the extensive character set
supported in SF Arabic.
And I'm excited to announce
that this year we're introducing
a new member to the San Francisco family,
SF Arabic Rounded.
Which packs the same great features
of SF Arabic,
coming with a full range of Weights,
and Optical Sizes.
The new Rounded design
enriches many apps and UIs.
Such as in Reminders and the Fitness app.
It expands the stylistic range
of SF Arabic,
and joins the rest of the system fonts,
making Arabic typography on Apple
platforms modern, clear, and refined.
If you want to see all the new
SF Arabic fonts in action
and want to learn more about the design
and optimization of apps
for the Arabic audience,
be sure to check out Mohamed's session,
"Design for Arabic".
The latest SF Pro,
SF Arabic, SF Arabic Rounded,
and all the other font families,
are available for download
on the developer.apple.com website.
And that's a wrap for this session.
I hope you enjoyed learning
about all the latest additions
to the system fonts.
Thank you for watching.
Ciao!