♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, my name is David Findlay,
and I'm an engineer
on the Create ML team.
This session is all about
Create ML Components,
a powerful new way to build
your own machine learning tasks.
My colleague Alejandro gave
an introduction in the session
"Get to know
Create ML Components."
He explores deconstructing
Create ML tasks
into components
and revealed how easy it is
to build custom models.
Transformers and estimators
are the main building blocks
that you can compose together
to build custom models
like image regression.
In this session, I want to go
way beyond the basics
and demonstrate what's possible
with Create ML Components.
Let's go over the agenda;
there's lots to cover.
I'll start by talking about
video data and go into detail
about new components designed
to handle values over time.
Then I'll put
those concepts to work
and build a human action
repetition counter
using only transformers.
Finally,
I'll move on to training
a custom sound
classifier model.
I'll discuss incremental fitting
which allows you
to update your model
with batches,
stop training early,
and checkpoint your model.
There's so much opportunity
with this level of flexibility.
I can't wait to dive in.
Let's get started.
At WWDC 2020, we introduced
Action Classification
in Create ML,
which allows you to classify
actions from videos.
And we demonstrated how you can
create a fitness classifier
to recognize a person's
workout routines,
such as jumping jacks,
lunges, and squats.
For example, you can use
the action classifier
to recognize the action in
this video as a jumping jack.
But what if you wanted
to count your jumping jacks?
The first thing
you need to consider
is that a jumping jack
spans consecutive frames,
and you'll need a way
to handle values over time.
Thankfully,
Swift's AsyncSequence
makes this really easy.
If you're unfamiliar
with async sequences,
you should check out the session
"Meet AsyncSequence”.
With Create ML Components,
you can read your video
as an async sequence of frames,
using the video reader.
And AsyncSequence provides a
way of iterating over the frames
as they are received
from the video.
For example,
I can easily transform
each video frame asynchronously
using the map method.
This is useful when you want
to process frames one at a time.
But what if you wanted
to process
multiple frames at a time?
That's where
temporal transformers come in.
For example, you may want
to downsample frames
to speed-up an action
in a video.
You can use
a downsampler for that
which takes an async sequence
and returns a downsampled
async sequence.
Or you may want to group
frames into windows,
which is important
for counting action repetitions.
That's where you can use
a sliding window transformer.
You can specify a window length,
which is how many frames
you want to group in a window,
and a stride,
which is how you control
the sliding interval.
The input is, again,
an async sequence,
and the output in this case is
a windowed async sequence.
Generally speaking,
a temporal transformer
provides a way to process
an async sequence
into a new async sequence.
So let's put
these concepts to work.
I don't know about you,
but when I'm working out,
I always lose count of my reps.
So I decided
to shake things up a bit
and build an action
repetition counter
with Create ML Components.
In this example, I'll go over
how to compose transformers
and temporal transformers
together.
Let's start with
pose extraction.
I can extract poses using
the human body pose extractor.
The input is an image
and the output is an array
of human body poses.
Behind the scenes,
we leverage the Vision framework
to extract the poses.
Note that images
can contain multiple people,
which is common
for group workouts.
That's why the output
is an array of poses.
But I'm only interested in
counting action repetitions
for one person at a time.
So I'll compose
the human body pose extractor
with a pose selector.
A pose selector
takes an array of poses
as well as a selection strategy
and returns a single pose.
There's a few selection
strategies to choose from,
but for this example,
I'll use the
rightMostJointLocation strategy.
The next step is to group
the poses into windows.
I'll append a sliding window
transformer for that.
And I'll use a window length
and stride of 90,
which will generate
nonoverlapping windows
of 90 poses.
Recall that a sliding window
transformer is temporal,
which makes
the whole task temporal,
and the expected input is now
an async sequence of frames.
Finally, I'll append
a human body action counter.
This temporal transformer
consumes a windowed
async sequence of poses
and returns a cumulative count
of the action repetitions
so far.
By now, you may have noticed
that the count is
a floating-point number.
And that's because the task
counts partial actions too.
It's that easy.
Now I can count my reps
in my workout videos
and make sure
I'm not cheating.
But it would be even better
to count repetitions live
in an app, so that I can keep
track of my current workouts.
Let me show you
how you can do that.
First, I'll use
the readCamera method
which takes
a camera configuration
and returns an async sequence
of camera frames.
Next, I'll adjust the stride
parameter to 15 frames
so that I get an updated count
more often.
If my camera captures frames at
a rate of 30 frames per second,
then I get counts
every half second.
Now I can workout and not worry
about missing a rep.
So far, I've explored
temporal components
for transforming
async sequences.
Next, I want to focus on
training custom models
that rely on temporal data.
In 2019, we demonstrated how
you can train a sound classifier
in Create ML.
Then in 2021,
we introduced enhancements
to sound classification.
I want to go even further
and train a custom sound
classifier incrementally.
The MLSoundClassifier
in the Create ML framework
is still the easiest way
to train a custom
sound classifier model.
But when you need more
customizability and control,
you can use the components
under the hood.
In its simplest form, the sound
classifier has two components:
an Audio Feature Print
feature extractor
and a classifier of your choice.
AudioFeaturePrint is
a temporal transformer
that extracts audio features
from an async sequence
of audio buffers.
Similar to
a sliding window transformer,
AudioFeaturePrint windows
the async sequence
then extracts features.
There are a few classifiers
to choose from,
but for this example, I'll use
a logistic regression classifier
and then compose it together
with the feature extractor
to build a custom
sound classifier.
The next step is to fit
the custom sound classifier
to labeled training data.
For more information about
collecting training data,
the "Get to know Create ML
Components" session
is a good place to start.
So far, I've covered
the happy path.
But building
machine learning models
can be an iterative process.
For example, you may discover
and collect new training data
over time and want
to refresh your model.
It's possible that you can
improve the model quality.
But retraining your model
from scratch is time-consuming.
That's because you need
to redo feature extraction
for all of your previous data.
Let me give you an example
of how you can save time
when training your models
with newly discovered data.
The key is to preprocess
your training data
separately from
fitting your model.
In this example, I can extract
audio features separately
from the classifier fitting.
And this works in general too.
Whenever you have
a series of transformers
followed by an estimator,
you can preprocess the input
through the transformers
leading up to the estimator.
All you need to do
is call the preprocess method
and then fit the model on
the preprocessed features.
I find this convenient
because I didn't need to change
the sound classifier
composition.
Now that I have the features
extracted separately,
I have the flexibility
to only extract audio features
for the new data.
As you discover new
training data for your model,
you can easily preprocess
this data separately.
And then append
the supplemental features
to the previously
extracted ones.
This is just the first example
of where preprocessing
can save you time.
Let's go back to
the model-building lifecycle.
You may need to tune
your estimator parameters
until you're satisfied
with your model's quality.
By separating the feature
extraction from the fitting,
you can extract
your features only once
and then fit your model with
different estimator parameters.
Let's go over an example
of changing
the classifier parameters
without redoing
feature extraction.
Assuming that I've already
extracted features,
I'll modify the classifier's
L2 penalty parameter.
And then I'll need to append
the new classifier
to the old feature extractor.
It's important not to change
the feature extractor
when tuning your estimator,
because that would invalidate
the previously
extracted features.
Let's move on to incrementally
fitting your model with batches.
Machine learning models
in general
benefit from large amounts
of training data.
However, your app may have
limited memory constraints.
So what do you do?
You can use Create ML Components
to train a model
by loading only a batch of data
into memory at a time.
The first thing I need to do
is replace the classifier
with an updatable classifier.
In order to train
a custom model with batches,
your classifier
needs to be updatable.
For example, the fully connected
neural network classifier,
which I can easily use
instead of the logistic
regression classifier
which is not updatable.
All right, now I'll write
a training loop.
I'll start by creating
a default initialized model.
You won't be able
to make predictions yet;
that's because this is just
the starting point for training.
Then I'll extract
the audio features
before the training starts.
This is an important step
because I don't want to extract
features every iteration.
The next step is
to define the training loop
and specify the number
of iterations
you'd like to train for.
Before I continue, I'll import
the algorithm's Swift package.
I'll need it for creating
batches of training data.
Make sure to check out
the session
"Meet the Swift Algorithms
and Collections packages"
from WWDC 2021
to learn more.
Within the training loop is
where the batching happens.
I'll use the chunks method
to group the features
into batches for training.
The chunk size
is the number of features
that are loaded
into memory at once.
Then, I can update the model
by iterating over the batches
and calling the update method.
When you train your model
incrementally,
you can unlock a few more
training techniques.
For example,
in this training graph,
after about 10 iterations,
the model accuracy
plateaus at 95 percent.
At this point,
the model has converged
and you can stop early.
Let's implement early stopping
in the training loop.
The first thing I need to do
is make predictions
for my validation set.
I'm using the mapFeatures
method here
because I need to pair
the validation predictions
with its annotations.
The next step is to measure
the quality of the model.
I'll use the built-in metrics
for now,
but there's nothing
stopping you
from implementing
your own custom metrics.
And finally, I'll stop training
when my model has reached
an accuracy of 95 percent.
Outside of the training loop,
I'll write the model out to disk
so that I can use it later
to make predictions.
In addition to stopping early,
I'd like to talk about
model checkpointing.
You can save your model's
progress during training
rather than waiting
until the end.
And you can even use
checkpointing
in order to resume training,
which is convenient
especially when your model
takes a long time to train.
All you need to do is write out
your model in the training loop.
We recommend doing this
every few iterations
by defining
a checkpoint interval.
It's that easy.
In this session, I introduced
temporal components,
a new way to build
machine learning tasks
with temporal data
like audio and video.
I composed
temporal components together
to make a human action
repetition counter.
And finally, I talked about
incremental fitting.
This will unlock
new possibilities for you
to build machine learning
into your apps.
Thanks for joining me
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
♪