♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hi, my name's Philippe.
Swift has a growing catalog
of open source packages.
I am pleased to introduce you to one
of the newest additions:
Swift Async Algorithms.
This package is
alongside the other packages,
like Swift Collections
and Swift Algorithms.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
is a set of algorithms
specifically focused on processing values
over time using AsyncSequence.
But before we get into it,
let's take a brief moment
to recap AsyncSequence.
AsyncSequence is a protocol
that lets you describe values
produced asynchronously.
Basically, it's just like Sequence,
but has two key differences.
The next function
from its iterator is asynchronous,
being that it can deliver values
using Swift concurrency.
It also lets you handle any potential
failures using Swift's throw effect.
And just like sequence,
you can iterate it,
using the for-await-in syntax.
In short, if you know how to use Sequence,
you already know how to use AsyncSequence.
Now, when AsyncSequence was introduced,
we added in almost all the tools
you would expect to find with Sequence
right there with the async versions.
You have algorithms like map,
filter, reduce, and more.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
takes this a step further
by incorporating more advanced algorithms,
as well as interoperating
with clocks to give you
some really powerful stuff.
This is an open source package
of AsyncSequence algorithms
that augment Swift concurrency.
Last year we introduced
the Swift Algorithms package.
To demonstrate the uses
of those algorithms,
we made a messaging app.
This was a great example of some
of the rich and powerful things
you can do with that package.
We decided there were a number
of really good opportunities
to take advantage of migrating the app
to use Swift concurrency.
To highlight just a few
of the asynchronous algorithms,
I'm gonna take you through some
of the things that we used
and how they work.
First off, we have a family
of algorithms for working
with multiple input AsyncSequences.
These are algorithms focused on combining
AsyncSequences together in different ways.
But they all share one characteristic:
They take multiple input AsyncSequences
and produce one output AsyncSequence.
One you might
already be familiar with is Zip.
The Zip algorithm takes
multiple inputs and iterates them
such that it produces a tuple
of the results from each of the bases.
Each of the inputs to Zip are the bases
that the Zip is constructed from.
The asynchronous Zip algorithm works
just like the Zip algorithm
in the standard library,
but it iterates each
of the bases concurrently
and rethrows errors if a failure occurs
on iterating any of them.
Now, accomplishing
that concurrent iteration
with rethrowing errors
can be rather involved.
But the Swift Async Algorithms package
took care of all of that
for us in our messaging app.
We previously had a lot of code
coordinating asynchronously
generating previews
of video recordings
and transcoding video
into multiple sizes for efficient storage
and transmission.
By using Zip we can ensure
that the transcoded video gets a preview
when we send it off to the server.
Since Zip is concurrent,
neither the transcoding
or the preview will delay each other.
But this goes a bit further.
Zip itself has no preference on which side
produced a value first or not,
so a video could be produced first
or a preview,
and no matter which side it is,
it will await for the other
to send a complete tuple.
We can await the pairs
such that they can be uploaded together
because Zip awaits each side concurrently
to construct a tuple of the values.
We came to the conclusion
that modeling our incoming messages
as an AsyncSequence
made a lot of sense.
So we decided to use AsyncStream
to handle those messages
since it preserves order
and turns our callbacks
into an AsyncSequence of messages.
One of the requested features
we needed to tackle is
that we wanted
to support multiple accounts.
So each account creates an AsyncStream
of incoming messages,
but when implementing this,
we need to handle them all together
as one singular AsyncSequence.
This means we needed an algorithm
for merging those AsyncSequences together.
Thankfully the Swift Async Algorithms
package has an algorithm for exactly that,
aptly named "Merge."
It works similarly to Zip in the regards
that it concurrently iterates
multiple AsyncSequences.
But instead of creating paired tuples,
it requires the bases
to share the same element type
and merges the base AsyncSequences
into one singular AsyncSequence
of those elements.
Merge works by taking
the first element produced by any
of the sides when iterated.
It keeps iterating until there
are no more values that could be produced,
specifically when all base AsyncSequences
return nil from their iterator.
If any of the bases produces an error,
the other iterations are cancelled.
This lets us take the AsyncSequences
of messages and merge them.
These combining algorithms work
concurrently on when values are produced,
but sometimes it is useful to
actually interact with time itself.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
brings in a family of algorithms
to work with time by leveraging
the new Clock API in Swift.
Time itself can be
a really complex subject,
and new in Swift (5.7) are a set of APIs
to make that safe and consistent:
Clock, Instant, and Duration.
The Clock protocol defines two primitives,
a way to wake up after a given instant
and a way to produce a concept of now.
There are a few built in clocks.
Two of the more common ones are
the ContinuousClock
and the SuspendingClock.
You can use the ContinuousClock
to measure time just like a stopwatch,
where time progresses no matter
the state of the thing being measured.
The SuspendingClock, on the other hand,
does what its name implies;
it suspends
when the machine is put to sleep.
We used the new clock API in our app
to migrate from existing callback events
to clock sleep function to handle
dismissing alerts after a deadline.
We were able to create the deadline
by adding a duration value
that indicated specifically the number
of seconds we wanted to delay.
Clock also has some handy methods
to measure the elapsed duration
of execution of work.
Here we have those two common clocks
I mentioned earlier,
the SuspendingClock
and ContinuousClock.
Below are displays showing
the potential elapsed duration
of work being measured.
The key difference
between these two clocks
comes from its behavior
when the machine is asleep.
For long running work like these,
the work can be paused,
just as we did here,
but when we resume the execution,
the ContinuousClock has progressed
while the machine was asleep,
but the SuspendingClock did not.
Commonly, this difference
can be the key detail
to make sure things like animations
work as expected
by suspending the timing of the execution.
If you need to interact with time
in relation to the machine,
like for animations,
use the SuspendingClock.
Measuring tasks in relation
to the human in front of the device
is better suited for the ContinuousClock.
So if you need to delay
by an absolute duration,
something relative to humans,
use the ContinuousClock.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
uses these new Clock, Instant,
and Duration types to build
generic algorithms for dealing
with many of the concepts of how events
are processed with regards to time.
In our messaging app,
we found these really helpful
for providing precise control over events.
It let us rate limit interactions
and efficiently buffer messages.
Perhaps the most prominent area
that we utilized time
was searching messages.
We created a controller
that manages a channel of results.
The channel marshals search results
from the search task back to our UI.
The search task itself needed
to have some specific characteristics
with regards to time.
We wanted to make sure to rate limit
searching sent messages on the server.
The algorithm Debounce
awaits a quiescence period
before it emits the next values
when iterated.
It means that events can come in fast,
but we want to make sure to wait
for a quiet period
before dealing with values.
When user input from a search field
is changed rapidly,
we don't want the search controller
to fire off a search request
for each change.
Instead, we want to make sure
to wait for a quiet period
when we're certain typing was likely
to be done.
By default, the Debounce algorithm
will use the ContinuousClock.
In this case, we can debounce
the input such that it awaits
a specified duration
while nothing has occurred.
Clocks and durations are
not just used for debouncing,
but they're used
for other algorithms too.
One area that we found
that was really useful
was sending batches
of messages to the server.
In the Swift algorithms package,
there's a set
of algorithms to chunk values.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
offers those,
but also adds a set of versions
that interoperate
with clocks and durations.
The family of chunking algorithms allow
for control over chunks by count,
by time, or by content.
If an error occurs in any of these,
that error is rethrown,
so our code is safe
when it comes to failures.
We used the "chunked(by:)" API
to ensure that chunks of messages
are serialized and sent off
by a certain elapsed duration.
That way, our server gets
efficient packets sent from the clients.
We were able to use this API
to build batches of messages
every 500 milliseconds.
That way, if someone's really excited
and typing really fast,
the requests sent
to the server are grouped up.
When working with collections
and sequence,
it's often useful and performant
to lazily process elements.
AsyncSequence works much
like how the lazy algorithms work
in the Swift standard library.
But just like those lazy algorithms,
there are often times where you need
to move back
into the world of collections.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
offers a set of initializers
for constructing collections
using AsyncSequence.
These let you build up dictionaries,
sets, or arrays
with input AsyncSequences
that are known to be finite.
The collection initializers
let us build in conversions
right into our initialization of messages
and keep our data types as Array.
This was really useful
since we had numerous features
that really could use some updating
to use Swift concurrency.
And by keeping
our existing data structures,
we can migrate parts
of our app incrementally
and where it makes sense.
So far,
we've just gone over just a handful
of the highlights
of Swift Async Algorithms package.
There are a whole lot more
than just what we've covered today.
We have algorithms ranging
from combining multiple AsyncSequences,
rate limiting by time,
breaking things into chunks,
but those were just the highlights
that we ended up
using extensively in our app.
This package has a lot more
than just those.
It ranges from buffering,
reducing, joining,
to injecting values intermittently,
and more.
The Swift Async Algorithms package
takes the set of algorithms
for dealing with things over time
and expands it to a wide range
of advanced functionality
that can help you in your apps.
Try it out.
We're really excited
to discover what you build with these,
and that excitement is shared.
This package is being developed
in the open with you.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪