Andreas: Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Andreas from the localization team
at Apple
and today I would like to share with
you some examples
about how to build high-quality,
localized apps.
Internationalization means
preparing your app
to run on devices all across the world.
When localization is done well,
everybody gets to enjoy the same
great experience and utility–
regardless of the language they speak.
Using the APIs that Apple offers,
most parts of your app
are internationalization friendly
right out of the box.
In this talk, you will learn
from our experience
making Apple's apps appealing
to a diverse audience,
including some challenges
and how we solved them.
I will start with declaring
and loading localized text.
It's easy to include formatted dates,
times, and more in our strings.
I will highlight some options, and we will
take a look at a sophisticated example.
Your Swift Package
might include localized text, too,
and you will learn about improvements
to the localization workflow.
Finally, I will talk about layout
and great new additions to SwiftUI.
At Apple, we make sure that our apps
are providing a great experience
to our international audience.
And the Weather app
is one example of this.
Millions of users open it up every day
to check the forecast–
and this is what the app looks like to
them, wherever they are in the world.
Notice how everything in the UI
is adjusted to their preferences.
We localize descriptions
of the current weather conditions
and we format numbers.
The UI is also adapted appropriately
depending on whether the language
is left-to-right or right-to-left.
Let's take a closer look
at one of the things we customize
by starting with translation.
This view here says "Wind is making
it feel cooler" in English.
And this is what it looks like
in other languages.
To support them properly,
all we have to do is declare
the string using String(localized).
Xcode discovers it
when exporting for localization,
and we can send the result
over our translators.
I will use the Mail app
on my Mac to do so.
And while we're there,
I want to show you something.
If I open the context menu of an email,
I can move it
to a special folder called "Archive.”
It is located in my sidebar.
Notice how both words
are "Archive" in English.
Other languages like Spanish, however,
have different words
for the action and the folder name.
Even though the English words
are the same,
when they appear in different contexts,
other languages might use different words.
You should use two strings in code
in this case.
And to do that, we added new API
to the string initializer this year.
It now takes a default value,
which we can use for our English string.
Then, we modify the localized string's key
to make the distinction clear
to translators.
This way, the same word is shown
when running the app in English,
and Spanish translators are able
to provide different words.
Last year's talk
"Streamline your localized strings"
helps you understanding the basics
of managing strings,
and it goes further
into the localization process.
I want you to take away from this example
that sometimes the same English word,
or even an entire sentence,
is shown in different contexts in the UI.
In these instances, make sure to use
two different strings in your code.
Weather is not just about the app.
It is also well integrated
into the system.
Here, we see a user activity,
suggesting to open the app
to check the weather
at the current location.
Let's take a look
at how that might be implemented.
The string could be declared
and loaded like this,
using String Interpolation
to insert any location name.
And this name could be a city
or a term for the current location.
The result works well in English:
"Show weather in Cupertino"
and "Show weather in my location,”
respectively.
In other languages however,
we might run into grammatical issues.
In German, for example,
the preposition works for a city name,
but is wrong when inserting a term
for the current location.
We need to have
a different translation instead.
The solution here is simple:
just use two different strings.
Inserting a city name
is fine in the first one,
and for the current location
we use another string.
This ensures that translators
are able to use the correct grammar
for their language.
And it works well in English, and German.
I made this example to show you
that inserting a variable had an impact
on the entire sentence.
Joining strings might have surprising
consequences in other languages:
they might need to inflect the grammar or
could have troubles with capitalization,
but knowing that beforehand
when writing the code is difficult.
Having people who speak the language
testing the app
is a substantial part of the workflow.
Keep that in mind when you're tempted
to construct a string programmatically.
Now that we share a good understanding
of how strings are declared in code,
let's talk about their comments.
Here's the string from our previous
example again, with a proper comment.
A comment is really, really important
for translators.
You should make sure to give them
the context they need to translate it,
keeping the same intention as you had
when declaring the string.
A great comment explains which interface
element the string is shown in,
like a label or a button.
It also explains the context of the UI
element and where it is shown on screen.
That could be a section header,
a context menu, or a user activity.
If the string contains variables,
make sure to explain their value
at runtime.
This is very important
for matching the grammar of the sentence,
as we have seen in the example.
Remember that translators
might not see the app at runtime
when translating your content.
But with these tips you should be able
to create a shared understanding
between declaration and translation
of a string
and which role it plays in your app.
Now, it might have never
occurred to you,
but the Weather app doesn't
actually control the weather.
Instead,
the data is downloaded from a server.
It can be located anywhere in the world
and it might not even know what language
to send the content in.
When content is downloaded
to a user's device,
it should always be presented
in the language that the user prefers.
Having just some parts of an app localized
can be very confusing.
Here, the Weather app shows
a severe weather alert,
which has been loaded from a server.
This looks really serious,
and if it was not translated into my
language, I might get into trouble later.
Let's take a look at what you can do
to make sure that your users
are always able to read remote content.
Your server can send a list
of supported languages to the app.
This should be an array of language IDs,
and the device has all the knowledge
about which languages the user prefers,
so you don't have to check
an compare them yourselves.
You can leverage Apple's Frameworks by
calling 'Bundle.preferredLocalizations'.
And this will do the match for you.
It returns an array
of candidate languages,
sorted by how closely they match
the user's language choices.
And the first one is usually the best fit,
so you will use this one.
That language then should be used
for any subsequent requests to the server.
It uses it to generate a response
with content in the language
that your user
will be able to understand.
With this technique you can be confident
that strings coming from the server
are ready for updating the UI
and for showing alerts to the user.
So to save your users
from a storm of frustration
when displaying remote content,
download the available languages,
match that against the user's preferences,
and use the result for any requests
that load user-facing content.
But let's come back to nicer weather now.
Rain or shine,
the Weather app is very rich in data
and many aspects of it
contain numbers and counts.
Let's focus on one of them.
Under "Precipitation"
it says "0 mm in last 6 hours.”
Let's assume that you want to build
something similar,
but spelling out "one hour" here.
This is how you can declare
the string in code.
In English,
you will need to use the plural form
if the number of hours is larger than one:
one hour, but two hours.
The rules when another variant
should be used
are even more complicated in Ukrainian.
You do not want to implement
that logic in your code,
and this is why you leverage
Apple's frameworks.
All you have to do is to declare
the string in code
and provide a stringsdict file,
which encodes the plural rule.
Another option is to make use
of Automatic Grammar Agreement.
You can learn more
about these two techniques
in last year's talk
"Streamline your localized strings.”
Even though it is easy,
you should not always apply
a plural rule to all of your strings.
For example,
if your sentence doesn't count anything,
and does not include a number,
you should not use a plural rule for it.
Here, "Remove this city
from your favorites"
doesn't need one
because there is no number,
and the same applies to multiple cities.
But if the string does include a number,
you should consider
having variations for plural.
The string of the previous example counted
how much rain will fall in the next hours,
and we just learned how easy it is to
make it adapt for numbers larger than one.
However, if there is a unit
in the sentence, like a duration,
a time, or percentage,
you should consider using a formatter.
So let's talk about formatters now.
Weather displays the current humidity
in percent in this view.
To do this in SwiftUI, it's just a matter
of a single line of code.
You just wrap your value in Text()
and specify how you would like
your number to be formatted.
And the equivalent Swift code
is simple too.
You just call .formatted on your value.
That really is all you need to do,
and the Formatter takes care
of everything else.
It does not only place
the percent sign in front of
or after the number and add spaces,
it also accommodates
for the user's preferred numbering system,
and that is something
that Arabic and Hindi users expect.
But that's really only the beginning
of what types of data you can format.
There are formatters
for almost everything,
and I encourage you to recap the session:
"Formatters: Make data human-friendly.”
As we have seen,
the weather is not always sunny,
and some days will have rain.
Of course, this highlight can't be missing
from Weather app.
Under "Rainfall" it says,
"50 mm expected in next 24 hours,"
and I'm really glad that it is not
that much where I am right now.
In English, the case is simple.
We say "50 millimeters expected
in next 24 hours.”
In Spanish however,
the matter is more complicated.
We need to vary the translation
when the amount of precipitation
is singular or plural.
We can solve this by combining
both a Formatter and a plural rule.
The string "2 mm" is produced
by a Formatter,
and it is embedded in a sentence that
needs to be varied for plural in Spanish.
All right, let's take a look
at how to do this in code.
We start by declaring a function
that takes a parameter
about how much the precipitation
will be in millimeters.
Probably it was downloaded from a server.
First, we ask the system
for a UnitLength,
which encodes the user's configuration,
and it will pick the right one
for our the case of showing rainfall.
If the user has not configured
their system to use metrics,
the Measurement type can be
easily converted to the preferred unit.
Next, the formatting API allows us
to produce a formatted string
for the value in a single line of code.
The preferredUnit already
has the information that we want
to display rainfall.
So when formatting,
we set the usage to asProvided.
If more than 1 millimeter or inches
of rain will fall,
we want to use the plural case.
We convert the value into an integer
so that we can check for that.
Next, we load a localized String
with a given key,
and we provide a default value, too.
There, we use String Interpolation
to include the integerValue,
the formattedValue, and the number 24.
The number is defined in code here,
because it will be always 24 hours.
Using String Interpolation
automatically makes sure
that the correct numbering system is used.
The key is declared in a stringsdict file.
Let's take a look at that.
The stringsdict starts with the key
that we have just used in our code.
In English, we don't need to vary
the string for plural,
so we use the category of "Other" for it.
The first parameter defines
which category is chosen at runtime.
Remember, it was the integer value.
Parameter number two and three
are present in the formatted string.
This defines what the sentence
will look like at runtime.
The Spanish stringsdict
has the same structure,
except that we provide a translation
in both singular and plural.
We have now formatted the data in code
and placed it in a sentence.
A stringsdict file
contains the plural rule,
so that the Spanish translation
is using the correct grammar.
Sometimes it's challenging
to provide a fully localized UI
that is working well for all languages.
Again, you learned that joining strings
can work for English
but might have surprising consequences
in other languages.
This might require
some comprehensive code to do,
but now you know how you can make it right
for all your users.
Sometimes
your strings are in a dependency,
or in a module that your app uses.
Or maybe you distribute your own code
to other developers, too,
using Swift Packages.
Let's take a look
at what's new for localization.
For defining a Swift Package
you declare the structure
and build configuration
by using Swift itself.
If you have user-facing content,
you can use the parameter
defaultLocalization to declare
that the content is using English
as primary language.
That is similar to specifying the
development language of an app project.
Xcode now reads that parameter
and recognizes that you are interested
in providing a localized experience.
Because of that, it will add the option to
Export Localizations to the Product menu.
You're probably used to using this feature
for your main app,
and now it also works for Swift Packages.
If you click "Export,” Xcode reads
your code and extracts all your strings.
They are placed in .xcloc files,
that you send to translators.
And to import your localized content
back into your package,
use Import Localizations,
and Xcode will place the files
at the correct file path in your package.
The workflow of localizing a Swift Package
is now identical to localizing your app.
But remember,
loading a string in a Swift Package
requires that you specify
the 'bundle' argument.
You can learn more about that
in the talk "Swift package:
resources and localization.”
If you are the author of a library
which is distributed as a Swift Package,
you now have an easy way
of keeping your project updated
and making localization
a regular part of your workflow.
You put a great amount of effort
and care into your project,
and having it localized is
a huge time-saver for all of your clients.
It can really make it stand out.
Make people aware
that you are going the extra mile
to provide the best experience
with your software,
so go ahead and tell them!
Be open about which languages
you support out of the box.
As an app developer,
you put special considerations
into your dependencies,
not only from a code quality perspective.
Components that you use
should support the same languages
and high-quality translations
as the rest of your app.
In the case that third-party code is not
localized to your required languages,
you can still create
a local copy of the package
and update the localizations there.
Make sure to test all parts of your app
in the languages that it supports.
This way you can make sure
that there will be no UI elements
that are not adapted
to the user's language.
Most of the time a translated string
is longer or shorter
than the English equivalent,
and that always affects
the layout of your app.
Let's look at what this means
for the Weather app.
This is the app running in English,
and on the right side
you can see it running in Arabic.
It is apparent that not only translations
are adapted to the language,
also the layout follows
the appropriate directionality.
If you want to learn more
about how to create a layout
that works for all languages,
which types of symbols
provide a localized alternative,
and what else to consider
for right-to-left languages,
make sure to watch the talk
"Get it right... to left.”
Here, the app is running in Hindi
on the right side.
Let's zoom in.
The script of that language
tends to be taller in general.
And if you look closely,
you see that the height of the labels
are adjusted to accommodate for that.
The system does this automatically.
All you have to do is to make sure
that you don't give UI elements
a fixed height.
Don't assume that everything
will fit within 44 points
just because it's tall enough
to fit the English string.
Please always expect your text to
be taller according to the circumstances.
Coming back to the main view
and scrolling it up,
Weather has a 10-day forecast view
which is great
for checking out the next week.
What stands out on this screen
is how it dynamically adjusts
the position of elements
according to the longest label.
In English, "Today" is longer
than all of the abbreviated weekday names.
In Spanish, however,
all of them are three characters wide,
and in Greek, the translation for "Today"
is almost double the size.
In all languages, though, the weather icons
are aligned vertically with each other.
Meaning they do not have fixed spacing
to their neighbor elements,
but flow according to
the longest weekday label.
When it comes to creating a layout
that works well with internationalization,
you should always keep in mind
that labels need to be flexible.
You have just seen how important it is
to make them flexible vertically,
but also expect labels to grow
horizontally with a longer translation.
It can be a challenge to accommodate
for that in certain layouts,
such as in this example,
but this year,
SwiftUI adds support for Grid,
which is a new view that helps you
to build this kind of layout more easily.
Let's take a closer look
at how to use Grid.
You start by declaring the Grid
with a leading alignment.
That means that UI elements start
on the left side of the screen
in a left-to-right language
and on the right side of the screen
in a right-to-left language.
Then, for each horizontal group,
you add a GridRow.
And lastly
you declare the content of the rows.
That's all it takes
to create this rather advanced layout.
When the label needs more space,
the Capsule can shrink in size
because it's the most flexible element.
SwiftUI does all the heavy lifting,
such as measuring,
sizing, and positioning the views–
completely automatic.
Another challenge is to make a view
with a longer translation
work with a limited amount of space,
like on Apple Watch.
Here, the German translation
of "Tip Function"
is too long to fit in one row.
To fix this, we do not remove the icon
next to the text to make more room.
The solution is rather to use
two or more lines of text if needed,
which is the default behavior.
We do not encourage you to change that
and hiding interface elements
if there is not enough space.
Usually there is a way
to adjust the layout,
so that it can accommodate
for the needs of the language.
The Mail app does this in a creative way.
In the sheet presentation, there are four
buttons to take action on this email.
When a translation
of one of the button titles is too long,
we do not clip the text
or wrap it onto a new line.
This would make the view look imbalanced.
Instead, the entire layout is transitioned
from a horizontal stack,
to a vertical stack of two rows.
This year, SwiftUI adds another great tool
that makes creating
this dynamic layout easier:
ViewThatFits.
In essence,
it lets you provide alternative layouts
if the space is constrained
and the view would not fit.
You simply declare your views
independently of each other,
and place them in ViewThatFits.
SwiftUI automatically detects
if a view does not fit without clipping,
and transitions to the next one provided.
Keep in mind that you should
only switch out the layouts.
Hiding a view just because the translation
is too long is a bad practice.
That makes it harder for the users
to orient themselves in the UI.
Try to make room for
all the interface elements first
by having a flexible layout.
This is not only helpful for localization.
This layout also works great
when the user prefers to have smaller
or larger text,
and uses different devices.
To learn more about the great new
layout features of SwiftUI this year,
I recommend you to watch the talk
"Compose custom layouts with SwiftUI.”
Having different accessibility preferences
and localized text can be a challenge
for your layout.
Interface elements can be
taller and wider.
Adapting the layout to accommodate
for that can be a challenge,
but with SwiftUI
it gets a lot easier this year.
I want you to take away from this talk
that constructing a string in code
can be challenging
when supporting other languages.
Listen to the feedback
that your international users
and testers give you to make sure
it works great for everybody.
Formatting values in Swift is easy
and it often just takes
a single line of code.
And doing that,
your formatted values respect
the user's preferences automatically.
When you are offering a Swift Package,
make use the new
Xcode localization workflow
to provide a fully localized experience
to your clients.
Now, with or without using SwiftUI,
your layout should be able
to accommodate for translated text
and accessibility settings.
Use your layout tools
to make the layout flexible,
without hiding interface elements.
In the end,
your users will be grateful for that
because they expect your app
to fit into their lives,
and that includes
respecting their languages.
Now, I'm looking forward to a very sunny week.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC,
and thank you for watching.