♪ ♪
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Ajay Singh,
and today I am excited to take you
on a journey
to explore SMS message filters.
These allow you to create
message filter extensions
which help people categorize incoming
SMS messages
from unknown senders.
First, I will describe how
SMS message filters work.
Next, I will talk about
what's new in iOS 16.
I will walk through an example of how
to build a message filter extension
using iOS 16 APIs,
then show you what people will see
in Messages
when they use your extension.
Finally, I will talk about enhancements
to Apple's SMS filter for India.
Let's talk about SMS message filters.
In many countries,
SMS messages are now used by businesses
to notify customers about transactions,
marketing campaigns,
alerts, and reminders.
In this example you
can see a mix of SMS messages
including short codes,
alphanumeric codes,
and standard phone numbers.
This results in a very cluttered inbox,
and it's really difficult
to find personal messages
from your loved ones.
iOS does provide an option
to filter messages from unknown senders,
but if you receive several messages
each day,
even the unknown sender folder
will quickly get filled
with unread messages.
Automated filtering of SMS messages
is important to many people,
and iOS provides a secure
sandbox-based extension model
that allow you to further classify
messages from unknown senders.
People can find and install
SMS filter apps from the App Store.
Once installed,
you can turn on message filtering
by going to Settings, Messages,
Unknown & Spam,
and turning on Filter Unknown Senders.
Then, you can select
your SMS filter of choice.
Here we have installed two SMS filters.
Note that only one filter
can be active at a time.
In iOS 14 and later,
new folders will appear in Messages
for Transactions, Promotions, and Junk.
These folders help people organize
and find messages
that are most relevant to them.
Regardless of which filter is chosen,
Messages provide
the same classification structure
consisting of Transactions,
Promotions, and Junk.
We have heard from you loud and clear,
that you would like to provide
more detailed classifications.
So in iOS 16
we are introducing enhancements
to the filter classification API.
Now your SMS message filter extension
can classify messages
into 12 additional sub-categories.
Here are the new sub-categories
that you can specify
in your SMS filter extension.
The new sub-categories fall under
the existing top level categories–
Transactions and Promotions.
Now you can further refine
incoming messages
and provide an even better experience.
For example, in markets like India,
it's common to receive
a large number of messages
related to financial transactions.
These include activities
in their bank account
and alerts for credit card spending.
These messages can now
be nicely organized
in the Finance sub-folder
under Transactions.
Let's see how the flow works
for SMS message filters.
We can divide the flow into two phases;
configuration and runtime classification.
In the configuration phase,
users select your message filter
in Settings.
This triggers a new API
introduced in iOS 16
to request the capabilities
supported by your filter.
You can now respond with a list
of supported categories
and sub-categories.
In this example,
the filter reports
that it supports the sub-categories
Finance, Orders, and Coupons.
iOS validates these capabilities
and updates the inbox in Messages
with the appropriate folders.
In the runtime classification phase,
every time an SMS message is received
from an unknown sender,
iOS queries your filter
to determine which category
and sub-category it belongs to.
You can also see the terms
action and sub-action used here.
Filters must respond with
one of the capabilities declared
in the configuration phase.
The SMS message will then appear
in the corresponding sub-folder
in Messages.
Let's build
a simple message filter extension
to see how the APIs are used
and what people will see in Messages.
In Xcode, you start by creating
a new Message Filter Extension target.
The Message Filter Extension target
appears as one of the options
when you create a new target
and go to template selection.
Select the Message Filter Extension
and click Next.
Now give your filter a name
and click Finish.
When the target is created,
MessageFilterExtension.swift
will be auto-populated
with all the required functions.
In iOS 16, we have a new API handle
called capabilitiesRequest.
Fill in the
ILMessageFilterCapabilitiesQueryResponse
structure with the transactional
or promotional sub-actions
that you support.
You can specify up to five sub-actions.
Here we are indicating support
for Finance,
Orders, and Health sub-actions
under Transactions,
and Coupons and Offers sub-actions
under Promotions.
Now build and install
your filter extension.
When you choose your filter in Settings,
the Message inbox will be updated
with the sub-actions we declared;
Finance, Orders, and Health appear
under Transactions,
and Coupons and Offers
appear under Promotions.
Now, we have confirmed
that our configuration works.
Let's define some simple logic
to return suitable categories to iOS
when an incoming SMS message is received.
First, we extract the message body text
from the queryRequest object.
If the message contains specific keywords,
we return a suitable matching action
and sub-action.
Here, we have added the code
where if the keyword is debited
then we will return filterAction
as Transaction
and filterSubaction
as transactionalfinance.
Similarly, when the message has
the keyword coupon,
then Promotion and PromotionalCoupons
will be returned.
You can also update the business logic
for other sub classifications within
Transactions and Promotions.
Note that if you return
an incorrect combination
for filterAction and filterSubAction,
iOS will discard the sub-action
and only honor the action.
For example,
if we return the action Transaction
and sub-action Coupons,
then the message will only go
to the All Transaction folder.
Here, we have an example
of SMS received from bank
with the keyword "debited"
and it has been classified
under Finance sub-folder by Messages.
Here is another example
where we have received a Black Friday Deal
with the keyword "coupon."
In Messages it has been classified
under the Coupons sub-folder.
In iOS 16,
you can choose sub-categories
that are the best fit
for your user demographics.
In the first example, the SMS message
filter shows folders
for Orders, Reminders, Health,
Public Services, and Weather
under Transactions,
while the second example shows
folders for Finance,
Reminders, Health, and Rewards
under Transactions
and Offers under Promotions.
Your filter extension can use
these sub-categories
to provide a differentiated experience
for your users.
Apple provides an SMS filter in India,
and we have updated it
using the enhancements in iOS 16.
The Apple SMS filter in India
now supports additional sub-folders
including Finance, Orders,
and Reminders under Transactions.
Your bank transactions appear in Finance,
your food
or commercial delivery messages
are organized under Orders,
while important events and to-do's
appear in the Reminders folder.
To wrap up, in this video
we talked about SMS message filters
and how they can classify messages
into Transactions,
Promotions, and Junk.
In iOS 16,
your message filter extension
can now classify messages
into 12 additional sub-categories.
To learn more, see the API documentation
in the link accompanying this video.
I look forward to seeing your new
and creative ideas
to help people organize SMS messages.
And as always,
we appreciate your feedback
to help us improve
SMS message filtering in future.