[spacey music]
Tyler: Hi, my name is Tyler,
and I'm an engineer on the WebKit
accessibility team.
In today's session,
we're going to take a tour
of modern web accessibility,
beginning with a brief overview
of assistive technologies
like screenreaders.
Then, we'll talk about ways you can build
rich, accessible web apps
with tools like custom controls,
speech synthesis markup language, or SSML,
in the Web Speech API,
and the dialog element.
So let's begin by talking
about assistive technologies.
Approximately one in seven people
worldwide have a disability that affects
the way they interact with the world,
their devices, and the web.
People can experience
disabilities at any age,
for any duration,
and at varying levels of severity.
Apple has built a variety of tools
to enable users to interact
with their devices in a way
that works best for them.
These tools include VoiceOver,
Switch Control, Voice Control,
and Full Keyboard Access, all of which
provide alternate means of device usage.
To learn more about these tools
and some others,
check out last year's session, titled:
"Support Full Keyboard Access
in your iOS app."
To get a feel for what this
is like on a real webpage,
let's use VoiceOver to navigate
a sample quiz assessment website.
On my iPad, I'll triple-press
the top button to activate VoiceOver.
Siri: VoiceOver on.
Safari, Show Sidebar, Button.
Tyler: And now, with VoiceOver active,
I'll tap the page heading to focus it...
Siri: Pop Quiz, Heading level 1.
Tyler: And swipe right to move
through the elements on this page.
Siri: One of six: How many slices are in
1/4 of a pizza with eight total slices?
Two slices, radio button, unchecked,
one of four,
Three slices--
Four slices--
Six slices--
Next question. Button.
Tyler: As a web developer,
you have many tools at your disposal
for making your pages accessible
to users of technologies like VoiceOver.
For example,
Safari has built-in accessibility support
for semantic HTML elements like button,
h1 through h6,
table elements,
list elements, and many more.
Using these semantic HTML elements
should be your default,
as this will guarantee a consistent,
accessible experience for your users
across all browsers.
However, sometimes you may have a need
not completely fulfilled by semantic HTML,
and need to create
custom components with JavaScript.
If this is the case,
you'll likely also need
to supplement your components
with ARIA attributes
so that their semantics are properly
conveyed to assistive technologies.
This brings us to our second topic
of the day, custom controls.
Let's say we wanted to make
the pizza quiz question more engaging.
One thing we could do is replace
the radio buttons with a custom control
that allows users to add and remove slices
from a pizza tray with a tap.
Our markup for this custom control
might start with a div and an ID .
In order to make this component operable
for users interacting with a tap or click,
we'll need to add a click event listener.
Let's create a new PizzaControl class
with a constructor
that accepts the ID of an element.
We'll get that element by ID, and then
add a click event listener for it.
This listener will compute the new number
of slices based on the tapped position
and then pass that value to a function
called update to re-render the control.
This will work great for some users,
but not all.
For example, what about our users
with visual disabilities,
who won't know where to click or tap?
When building custom components,
we must always consider how users
of assistive technologies of all types
will interact with our component.
With that in mind,
the first step to making our component
accessible is to give it a role attribute
with a value of "slider".
Our control maps quite nicely
to the model of a slider.
There is a minimum value, zero slices,
a maximum value, eight slices,
and a current value, four slices.
We'll also need to add a tabindex of zero
to ensure our component is focusable
for users of keyboards
and other non-touch interfaces.
We'll also need
to add a few ARIA attributes.
Aria-valuemin and aria-valuemax inform
assistive technologies
of the minimum
and maximum values for this slider.
These attributes are similar
to the min and max attributes
that you can use
on native range type inputs.
Next, let's add aria-valuenow to convey
the current value of the control.
We'll also use aria-valuetext
to provide a more useful description
of the current value,
which is four slices.
Now that we've established
our control as a focusable slider,
we need to handle updates
to the control's value
from assistive technologies.
On iOS, VoiceOver facilitates
the adjustment of sliders
with a single finger swipe up
to increment the slider,
and a swipe down to decrement the slider.
Safari provides an easy way
to handle these gestures.
When a VoiceOver user swipes up
with a slider in focus,
Safari automatically simulates
an arrow-key right event.
And similarly,
if a VoiceOver user swipes down
with a slider in focus,
an arrow key left event will be simulated.
These simulated events behave
the same as real keypresses,
meaning they can be handled
by key event listeners.
With this new knowledge in our tool belt,
let's add a keydown listener
to our pizza control.
If the activated key is
a right arrow or up arrow,
we'll update our control with
the current amount of slices plus one.
And similarly, if the activated key
is a left arrow or down arrow,
we'll update our control with
the current amount of slices minus one.
Adding this key event listener
not only benefits VoiceOver users,
but also users of Full Keyboard Access,
who may heavily or entirely rely
on your web app
being keyboard accessible.
With both
of our event listeners established,
we probably now also want
to define our update function.
First, we'll clamp the value we're given
to ensure it's within bounds,
between zero and eight,
and update our stored slice count state
to this value.
Next, we need to ensure we update
both the visual and ARIA representations
of our control.
When building custom components,
a good rule is that if you're updating
the visual representation of your
component,
you also need to think
about how you'll be updating
the ARIA representation.
In this case, we need to update
both the aria-valuenow
and aria-valuetext attributes
to inform users of assistive technologies
of the new control state.
We'll begin by setting aria-valuenow
to be the current slice count.
Next, we'll set aria-valuetext
to be the more human-friendly description
of the slice count,
plus either the word "slice" or "slices".
Okay, now that all that's in place,
let's go back
to our quiz assessment web app
to see what the experience is like with
VoiceOver.
I'll begin by tapping
the pizza control to focus it.
Siri: Four slices, adjustable.
Swipe up or down with one finger
to adjust the value.
Tyler: We heard that VoiceOver read
the initial value of the slider,
four slices,
and told us that it's adjustable.
Following VoiceOver's prompt,
we can swipe up to increase
the number of slices selected...
Siri: Five slices.
Six slices.
Tyler: And swipe down to decrease
the number of slices selected.
Siri: Five slices.
Four slices.
Tyler: With these changes in place,
our custom slider component
is now much more accessible.
Now, let's talk about how you can use SSML
in the Web Speech API
to build more rich experiences
for all of your users.
The Web Speech API is made up
of two primary JavaScript interfaces:
SpeechRecognition for audio input,
and SpeechSynthesis
for text-to-speech audio output.
Web Speech gives you the capabilities
to provide
a voice-assisted or voice-only interface
for your web app.
This can be beneficial for users
with motor disabilities,
who may have trouble using other means
of control,
like a mouse, keyboard, or touchscreen.
New to SpeechSynthesis on Safari
is the ability to use SSML
to manipulate the way your text is spoken.
SSML has tons of capabilities.
For example,
you can use the break element
to insert pauses in speech
with a time of your choosing.
You may want to ask your users
to breathe in... and breathe out.
Using the phoneme element,
you can control
the pronunciation of words,
like "tomayto" versus "tomahto."
The prosody element allows
you to manipulate the pitch,
rate, and volume of your spoken text.
And these only scratch
the surface of SSML's capabilities.
To learn more, check out
the SSML specification on w3.org.
Let's put our newfound knowledge
of SSML to use.
For the final question of our quiz,
we ask our students
to choose a radio button
with the correct Spanish translation
of the phrase, "the water."
We can make this question
more engaging by allowing users
to press a button to read the question
and answers with text-to-speech,
using SSML to read
the Spanish phrases
in a Spanish-locale voice.
Let's begin by creating our button,
ensuring to wrap the speaker emoji
in a span with aria-hidden set to true,
since this emoji's description
is not particularly useful here.
Next, let's create
a helper JavaScript function
called wrapWithSSML ,
which takes a phrase to speak
and a voice-locale to speak it in.
We'll begin building our SSML string
with the break element
to insert a short pause before each phrase
to build emphasis.
With the prosody element,
we'll specify that we want our phrase
spoken at 80% of the default rate.
And finally,
we can use the lang element to choose
the locale-specific voice
we want our phrase to be spoken in.
And now we'll add a click event listener
to our read question button
and build our SSML string inside.
We begin by wrapping
the entire string in a speak element.
Speak is important because it
indicates to synthesis processors
that anything within
should be considered SSML.
Next, we include our question:
How do you say "the water" in Spanish?
We can use
our wrapWithSSML helper function
to give emphasis
to the phrase being translated
and ensure it's read
in a U.S. English locale-voice.
We'll also use wrapWithSSML
for all four of our potential answers,
providing emphasis and requesting that
they be read in a Spanish locale-voice.
Finally, we can create
a new SpeechSynthesisUtterance object
with our SSML string,
and pass that to the window
SpeechSynthesis speak method
to read it out.
With all of that in place,
let's see what the experience is like
on our web app.
On the page with the final question,
I'll tap the "Read question" button,
and listen.
Siri: How do you say "the water"
in Spanish?
El agua.
La abuela.
La abeja.
El árbol.
Tyler: Thanks to SSML, we've created
a much more engaging experience
for our students.
Another common design pattern
on the web is the modal.
You may use this on your web apps
as a sign-in or sign-up form,
for confirmation dialogs, and more.
One way to provide
an accessible modal experience
is the aria-modal attribute.
With aria-modal="true",
Safari will consider
all accessible elements outside
the modal to be ignored.
Recently, Safari has also added support
for the dialog element.
Dialog makes providing
an accessibility-friendly modal experience
much easier
with standard focus interactions,
out-of-the box handling
of modal closing gestures,
like the Escape key and the scrub gesture
on iOS, and more.
To see this in action,
let's change the "Show score" button
on our quiz assessment web app
to open a dialog with our results.
First things first,
we'll need to create our dialog element.
The markup
could look something like this.
We give the dialog an ID so it can be
referenced later by our show score button.
We also wrap the dialog's contents
in a form with method dialog.
By doing so, any submit type controls,
like our button,
will cause the dialog to close.
We'll also need
a bit of JavaScript to open the modal.
Let's add a click event listener
to our Show Score button
that calls showModal()
on our dialog element.
And now we're ready to try this out.
With VoiceOver active, I'll tap
the "Show score" button to focus it.
Siri: Show score. Button.
Tyler: Then, I'll double-tap
with a single finger
anywhere on the screen
to press the button.
Siri: Show score. Web dialog.
Close button.
Tyler:
And now we have our modal.
I can swipe left to move through
the modal's contents to hear my score.
Siri: You got all six question correct.
Great work!
Tyler: And when I'm done, I can move
back to the close button
by swiping right...
Siri: Close button.
Tyler: And double tap to close
the modal.
Siri: Unchecked.
Tyler: As I mentioned previously,
the dialog element handles
the iOS scrub gesture
for modal closure out of the box.
To demonstrate, I'll re-open the modal
with a double-tap...
Siri: Show score, button.
Web dialog. Close, button.
Tyler: And then perform the scrub gesture
by quickly moving two fingers right,
left, and right across the screen.
Siri: Show score. Button.
Tyler: Okay, so we have
a functional modal,
but we can still do better.
Did you notice
that when we opened the modal,
VoiceOver only read "web dialog,
close, button"?
In this situation,
it would probably make sense
to use an aria-label
or aria-labelledby attribute
to provide more information for users
of assistive technologies.
Since our modal content is short,
simply informing users
of how many answers they got correct,
let's use that for our label.
First, we'll wrap the modal content
in a span with an ID.
Then, we can add
the aria-labelledby attribute
to our dialog pointing
to the modal-content ID.
Let's also explicitly set
the initial modal focus element
to be the close button
with the autofocus attribute.
While this was already the default
behavior for this simple modal,
that may not have been the case
if our modal had more content
or was more complex,
with lots of controls.
For example,
in a modal with a lot of content,
it may have made more sense
to place autofocus on a top-level heading.
As the modal author,
you'll know best as to what will provide
a great experience for your users.
With our new attributes in place,
let's again see
what the experience is like in VoiceOver.
I'll first tap the Show score button
once to focus it...
Siri: Show score, button.
Tyler: And then double-tap to press it.
Siri: You got all six questions correct.
Great work! Web dialog, close button.
Tyler: That's a much better experience.
A VoiceOver user immediately hears
their score thanks to aria-labelledby,
and is already focused
on the close button,
and therefore can double-tap
to leave the modal.
And with that,
it's time to wrap up today's session.
I hope you've learned some techniques
to build rich, accessible web apps,
ensuring you provide a great experience
to all of your users.
Please try these features out
in the latest Safari,
and file any bugs you find
to the WebKit bug tracker
at bugs.webkit.org.
Thanks for joining me on today's whirlwind
tour of modern web accessibility.
Have an amazing WWDC!
[spacey music]