♪ ♪
Susan Prescott: Welcome
to the Platform State of the Union
for WWDC 2022.
We're always excited for WWDC
because it's an opportunity
for us to connect with all of you,
share some news
about what we've been working on,
and better understand what you need
from our developer platforms.
What you do as developers is amazing.
You transform your ideas,
the stuff of imagination,
to take users' experiences
to another level.
And we want to help you
take your ideas even further.
In the Keynote, we already talked
about some new capabilities
across iPhone, iPad, Mac,
Apple Watch, and Apple TV,
and the incredible power
of Apple silicon
to help bring even the most ambitious
ideas to life.
We have a lot to cover today.
Let's start with some updates.
Earlier this year, we opened
the brand-new Apple Developer Center,
a place designed for you to connect
and collaborate
with Apple engineers and designers
right here at Apple Park.
And last fall, thousands of you
from all over the world
attended our new online Tech Talks,
with hundreds of live sessions
originating in 11 countries
and in five languages.
For us, one of the best parts
of the Tech Talk series
was one to one meetings,
which were a great opportunity
to hear about what you're up to
and share some advice and guidance.
Last fall, Swift Playgrounds 4 shipped
with the power to build apps and submit
them directly to the App Store
and support for SwiftUI,
making it an incredible tool for
experimentation and UI prototyping.
And of course, there's Xcode Cloud.
We built Xcode Cloud to help you
build better apps
faster and more easily.
It's a continuous integration
and delivery service
built right into Xcode
and hosted in the Cloud.
Xcode Cloud supports development
for all Apple platforms.
It integrates with TestFlight
and App Store Connect
as well as every major git based
source control provider.
It even has REST APIs
to help connect to other aspects
of your development workflow.
It's built with advanced security
to protect you and your projects.
And I'm delighted to say
that Xcode Cloud is available
starting today.
We think nearly every development team
can benefit from Xcode Cloud,
and we've priced it to be accessible
to developers of all sizes.
We're offering
the 25 hour per month subscription
free to all Apple Developer Program
members through the end of 2023!
And you'll be able to subscribe to any
of the Xcode Cloud subscription levels
in the Developer app later this Summer.
Today we're gonna talk
about three big topics.
First, we want to share more about our
vision for developing for Apple platforms,
where we are with our platforms,
and where we're headed.
Then, we'll share some compelling
new ways your apps can integrate
with the system experience
on Apple platforms.
And finally,
we'll discuss some powerful new APIs
and show you how they can enable you
to do even more ambitious things
with your apps.
Let's start with the vision
for our developer platform
and how it's been evolving.
Josh is here to tell you all about it.,
Josh Shaffer: A great developer platform
provides tight integration
between programming language,
frameworks and tools.
When all three
fully complement one another,
we can ensure that common things are easy,
and even uncommon things are possible.
Now, getting that right shortens the path
to building a great app,
and it benefits everyone.
Customers get a consistent experience,
like scrolling that always feels perfect.
And you're able to focus your time
and effort on what makes your app unique.
But designs evolve, hardware advances,
and what was once cutting edge
becomes the expected baseline.
The Objective-C language,
AppKit & UIKit frameworks,
and Interface Builder
have empowered generations of developers.
These technologies
were built for each other,
and will continue to serve us well
for a long time to come,
but over time
new abstractions become necessary.
For a while now, you've seen us
hard at work defining the next generation
of integrated language,
frameworks, and tools:
Swift, SwiftUI, and Xcode Previews.
Tight integration
in a development platform like this
requires that all three pieces
be designed and evolved together,
both driving and driven by one another.
Swift result builders were inspired
by SwiftUI's compositional structure.
SwiftUI's declarative views
were enabled by Swift value types.
And Xcode Previews was specifically
designed for, and enabled by, both.
Now, the result is the best development
platform that we have ever built.
And this year, Swift, SwiftUI, and Xcode
all have fantastic updates
that take this vision further,
and make it even easier for you to build
great apps for all of our platforms.
And it all starts with Swift.
Now Ben from the Swift team
is gonna tell you all about what's next.
♪ ♪
Ben Cohen:
Swift is fast, modern, and safe.
It combines the speed
of a strongly-typed language,
with an expressive syntax
that's easy to read and write.
And its design eliminates
entire categories of programming errors.
Swift is the absolute best language
for building apps across our devices.
Swift is also open source,
with an amazing community of contributors
organized at swift.org,
supporting one another through
initiatives like Diversity in Swift
and the Swift Mentorship Program,
and advancing the language
with working groups on topics
like Swift on server,
and C++ interoperability.
Over the last year,
Swift has gotten even better,
with enhancements in concurrency,
upgrades to make Swift code
easier to read and write,
tooling to help you
customize your workflow,
and amazing under-the-hood improvements.
It started last year,
with the introduction
of Swift Concurrency.
Swift Concurrency dramatically simplified
reading and writing code
that runs in parallel,
and has been a huge hit,
with more than 40,000 apps
in the App Store
adopting it in just the first year.
Because it's such a fundamental
and important improvement
to your app's code base,
it's now possible to deploy code
with Swift Concurrency
to all operating systems
released in the last three years.
Swift Concurrency also introduced
async sequences.
This year, there's a new,
open-source package
that brings concurrency to Swift's
rich set of existing sequence algorithms.
It's called async algorithms.
For example,
where Swift's sequence protocol
supports a zip algorithm
to combine two sequences,
async algorithms brings a version
for zipping together
two asynchronous sequences.
Because async sequences are integrated
directly into the Swift language,
they use familiar constructs
like 'for' loops
that, thanks to the async/await syntax,
looks like regular straight-line code.
You're also able to use
the familiar try/catch pattern
to handle things like network failures
from asynchronous data streaming
over the network.
A key thing about async sequences
is how they deliver data values over time.
Swift now includes a new set of
clock types for representing time units,
and async algorithms builds on them
to provide many time-based algorithms,
like throttle here,
which can help slow down updates
from a sequence.
Swift's concurrency model is designed
to make asynchronous code as easy
and safe to write
as your synchronous code.
A big part of that is Swift's actor model.
Actors allow you to isolate your data
using thread-safe,
concurrently-executing code.
Swift prevents you from
accidentally sharing that state
between parallel threads,
defining away a major source of bugs.
Communication between actors is
easy and efficient through async/await.
Now, Swift takes the idea
of actor isolation further
with distributed actors.
Distributed actors can communicate
across multiple processes or devices.
The "distributed" keyword
marks these actors
and methods that can be accessed remotely,
whether that's between
separate processes on your Mac,
peer to peer between different devices,
or from a device talking to your backend
written with Swift on Server.
Just as actors help Swift
protect your state data
from race conditions,
distributed actors help Swift make them
available outside your process,
using a pluggable transport mechanism.
The Swift compiler can then
perform checks that help guarantee
correct behavior
in a distributed environment,
allowing you to get back to working
on the features that you care about.
Distributed actors
and other concurrency features
show just how easy Swift code can be
to read and write
when enhancements
are crafted deep within the syntax.
To tell you more
about usability enhancements in Swift,
here's Ken.
Ken Orr: Strings are one
of the most important features
of any programming language.
But dealing with strings can
be a common source of frustration.
At some point in a developer's journey,
they may find themselves
needing to extract information
from a string like this.
Writing code to parse the string
is easy to get wrong,
with many details to track.
And the resulting code–
it's hard to read and modify.
Regular expressions are a powerful
solution to this challenge.
They allow you to describe the pattern
you expect to see in your string
and specify which pieces of information
you're interested in capturing.
This year, Swift is delivering a huge
improvement to the developer experience
around regular expressions,
starting with
a new regular expression literal.
They're built directly into the language,
allowing the Swift compiler
to check for correctness.
And they unlock the power
of Swift's type system
when you're extracting information
with a regular expression.
And they take full advantage
of Swift's best-in-class Unicode support.
Let's take a look.
I'm working on an app
called Food Truck
that organizes everything
from taking orders to tracking sales.
And some orders come in as strings,
packed with data.
Now, regular expressions are perfect
for extracting the details I want,
and there's no better place to experiment
with them than here in a Playground.
I'll start by creating a regex literal.
Now I'll type the expression,
and pull out who made the order,
the donut type,
and the number of donuts.
Now, as I type,
the regex is syntax highlighted,
which helps me confirm
my expression is correct.
Now I'll try it out.
Use the order string from above
and look for the first match of the regex.
Now, when I run the Playground,
I can see with the inline result
exactly what parts of the order string
the regex matches.
And here, it's finding
just what I was looking for.
Swift's new regex support
doesn't stop here.
As literals become more complex,
like this one
that matches parts of a log file,
Swift offers an even better way
to craft these patterns–
regex builders.
And it's easy
to convert a literal to a builder.
Now I have code,
and that makes it easier
to read and change.
I can simplify this one even more.
Here, where I'm looking for a hex digit,
I'll use the new .hexDigit CharacterClass,
helping making my intent even clearer.
Now, the builder syntax makes it
so much easier for me to create
and extend my expressions,
and get the results I'm looking for.
And that's the powerful,
new developer experience
around regular expressions in Swift.
Ben: Beyond string syntax,
Swift is also getting easier
to read and write through improvements
to a language feature known as generics.
Generics power features of Swift
you use every day,
like the Array type,
which holds any kind of element,
from strings to your own custom types.
Generic code uses the concept
of a placeholder type
to stand in for another type
to be determined later.
By removing assumptions
about specific types,
you can be more clear
about the intent of your code,
and make it easier to re-use.
But this can also make your code
harder to read.
For example, if you wanted to handle
a generic collection of songs
as a function parameter,
you'd have to write quite a bit
of code to express your intent.
Now in Swift, writing a function
that accepts some collection of songs
is as easy as using the 'some' keyword
to tell Swift about the parameter.
You get the same meaning,
but with less code.
In other cases,
you might need more dynamic behavior,
like with this music library's
array of playlists,
which might need to contain different
types of collections of songs–
sets of songs, or arrays of songs.
That's where the new 'any' keyword
can help.
The 'any' keyword
is built right into Swift,
and allows you to express a type
that can hold any collection of songs.
And it works seamlessly
with generic functions too.
By adopting familiar syntax
and using more natural keywords,
writing generic code in Swift
has never been easier.
Just as important as the features
built into the Swift language
are the tools built around it.
The Swift Package Manager makes it easy
to manage your app's dependencies
and take advantage
of the fantastic packages
published by developers around the world.
To date, those developers have
published thousands of Swift packages,
providing code to help with everything
from authentication and web services
to data management
and reusable UI components.
And this year, the Swift Package Manager
is amplifying the ways
you can create and build code
with all-new Package Plugins.
Plugins are Swift packages
you can add to your project
as easily as any other dependency.
They download and build
automatically on a fresh checkout,
except instead of being code in your app,
they're code that helps build your app.
Package Plugins can be invoked
from the command line or within Xcode,
either as part of your build phase
or on-demand.
They run in a sandbox environment
which prompts you for permission
before reading or modifying your code.
There are endless possibilities
for extending your workflow
with Package Plugins.
You could use them to lint
and format your code
to match the team style guide
with packages
like SwiftLint or SwiftFormat
or automatically generate source code
at build-time
with tools like Sourcery.
Anything that helps you get the job done.
Ken: Package Plugins are a great way
to extend Xcode,
just by writing a little Swift.
And you can do that in two ways.
With command plugins
that you use on demand,
and with build plugins
for whenever your project builds.
Now, back here in our Food Truck app,
here's the code for a command plugin
I created.
My team has a unique code aesthetic.
We like our imports
sorted in string length order.
Shortest to longest.
And since Package Plugins are
all about customization and control,
we created a command plugin that uses
SwiftFormat to take care of that.
It finds all the locally modified files,
and then it sorts their imports.
Now, here's a file I've been editing
with some unsorted imports at the top.
I'll use the command
on the entire project.
I can select any number of targets.
I'll run it on everything.
And I can review
the plugin's code if I want.
I'm all set.
I'll run the command.
And then, just like that,
the plugin goes to work on my files.
It finds all of the locally modified
source files,
and then it sorts them in length order.
With plugins,
you can go beyond just formatting.
You can generate source code,
work with git,
even surface your own custom errors
and warnings.
I have another plugin to make sure
my code is well documented.
It's a build plugin, and it's based on
the open source SwiftLint package.
So now when I build, I can easily see
all the places in my code
where I need to add documentation.
And build plugins extend
all the way to Xcode Cloud,
where they run as part of every build.
With Swift package plugins,
my team and I can create our own commands,
customize builds locally
and in Xcode Cloud,
and then share those plugins with others.
All using the power
of a few lines of Swift.
And that's a quick look
at the ways Package Plugins
can level up your development workflow.
Ben: Finally, Swift has some impressive
changes under the hood.
Building Swift projects
is quicker than ever.
Thanks to new parallelization efforts,
link time is up to twice as fast.
And the Swift concurrency runtime
is now more tightly integrated with the OS
to better ensure the priority
of your asynchronous tasks,
helping your apps
stay efficient and responsive.
Lastly, launch time for apps written
in Swift is dramatically faster on iOS 16,
with apps like Lyft or Airbnb
launching almost twice as fast
thanks to improvement
in the dynamic linker.
With these under-the-hood improvements,
new abilities in tooling,
an evolved syntax
that's easier to read and write,
and improvements in concurrency,
there has never been a better time
to develop in Swift.
Swift is the absolute best language
for building apps across our devices.
But a language is just part of what
you need to build your best apps.
You have to pair a language with
a powerful user interface framework.
And Eliza is gonna tell you more.
Eliza Block: A powerful UI framework
provides abstractions
that make it easy
to describe your interface,
to populate it with data,
and to keep it up to date.
It should scale well with complexity.
And it should be designed
for the platform you're targeting,
giving you full access
to the power of the device.
Your UI framework should help you make
your app feel familiar and intuitive.
It should make it easy to create
standard controls
and native interaction patterns,
with options for advanced customization.
And it needs to have an expressive API
that allows you to quickly prototype
your ideas
and see the results
across a range of devices.
SwiftUI offers all this and more.
Like Swift,
Swift UI is designed with strong opinions
about the best way to build apps.
It has a declarative syntax
that's easy to read and write.
You describe what your interface
looks like, instead of how to build it.
And this leaves room for SwiftUI
to provide intelligent defaults
for each platform.
SwiftUI automatically keeps your interface
up-to-date with changes
to the underlying data model,
so your app's UI never ends up
in an inconsistent state.
SwiftUI handles all these details for you,
so you can focus your time and energy
on what makes your app unique.
Writing a new UI framework
is a huge undertaking.
Since its introduction
we've been continually expanding
SwiftUI's API coverage,
guided by your feedback.
This year we've made it even easier
to adopt SwiftUI incrementally
in your existing apps,
and we've made some exciting enhancements
to its power and flexibility,
starting with app navigation.
With SwiftUI,
it has always been easy to create
the common kinds of navigation
hierarchies found in many apps.
And this year,
SwiftUI is expanding that support
with an all-new navigation API.
The new navigation API makes it easy
to express the style of navigation
that best fits the needs of your app.
With robust programmatic control
over the presentation of your app's views,
you can easily save and restore selection,
and even replace the full contents
of a navigation stack.
This is really useful
when handling important behaviors
like setting the launch state of your app,
managing transitions between size classes,
and responding to deep links.
SwiftUI also has huge improvements
when it comes to controlling
the layout of your app's interface.
The layout of many app interfaces
can be described using SwiftUI's model
of horizontal
or vertical stacks of elements.
And while this model works
for many common layouts,
sometimes
you need something more flexible.
This year, we're adding a new Grid API,
which makes it easier
to lay out a set of views
aligned across multiple rows and columns.
And you can take your layouts even further
with the all-new custom layout API.
The custom layout API
gives you the flexibility
to build any type of layout you want.
For example,
you could create a flow layout
where your views are arranged
like the content of a newspaper,
wrapping to the next column
when more space is needed.
Or you could create a radial layout
that draws your views in a circle,
like the numbers on a watch face.
The custom layout API makes it easy
to re-use your layout logic,
making your view code simpler
and easier to read.
SwiftUI continues to grow
to offer
many more types of interface elements.
Like half sheets,
which define secondary views
that slide above a main view.
These are great to provide quick access
to information on smaller screens.
And SwiftUI now supports Share Sheets,
so your app can easily leverage
all of the Share extensions available
on a user's device.
Share Sheet support is powered
by the new Transferable protocol,
which introduces a type-safe API
for transferring app data.
We've also made it easier to adopt SwiftUI
incrementally in your existing apps
with a special collection view cell
that can host SwiftUI views.
If you already have a collection view
in your UIKit app,
you can now write custom cells
using SwiftUI's declarative syntax.
These cells are tightly integrated
with UIKit, supporting swipe actions,
cell backgrounds, and all the other
features of UICollectionView.
Today we're also introducing
a brand-new framework
that complements SwiftUI
and will allow you to express
even more of your interface.
Here's Jo to tell you more.
Jo Arreaza-Taylor:
Today's world is filled with data.
Data to help understand, make decisions,
and see new perspectives.
A well-designed and accessible
data visualization
can communicate complexities to your users
in a way that feels clear and natural,
empowering them
as they move through the day.
Like helping to show
changing trends in their health,
highlighting their progress
towards personal goals,
and preparing them for what's to come.
Today, we're introducing a new framework
to help empower your users
to unlock the data within your apps.
Say hello to Swift Charts.
Swift Charts is a highly customizable
charting framework
built on top of SwiftUI
that makes it easy
to create gorgeous visualizations.
It uses the same declarative syntax
as SwiftUI to make it easy
to read and write code
which conveys visual information.
Swift Chart lets you customize
the presentation of information
to best fit the needs of your app
to create everything
from line and bar charts
to more sophisticated examples
like heat maps and stream graphs,
and many, many more types.
And because Swift Charts
is built on top of SwiftUI,
charts have great support
for accessibility features,
like a terrific, out-of-the-box
VoiceOver experience
that's easy to customize.
Being built on SwiftUI also means
you can animate your charts,
to help you give your app
just the right look and feel.
And of course, Swift Charts works great
across all our devices.
Eliza: Back in our Food Truck app,
here are the beautiful new Swift Charts
in Xcode's fully redesigned preview area.
I'm also using
the new multicolumn SwiftUI table view.
Let me show you how easy it is
to build this chart.
And as I scroll, check out
the awesome new structured headers
in the source editor.
They make it really easy
to see where you are in the file.
Here's the code for the chart.
Now, this is actually a stacked bar chart,
but you can't really tell.
Let's have each donut
use its own color.
Maybe it would be easier to see
how the donuts compare
if we position the bars side by side.
I love how I can make
all these big changes
with just a couple simple modifiers.
We can customize the styling, too.
Let's make the bars
reflect the donut colors.
And we can even add annotations
to the bars with another modifier.
Looking great.
Previews are now live by default,
so I can immediately interact
with my view.
I'm gonna change the sort order.
Watch how the bars animate beautifully,
with Swift Charts
doing all the heavy lifting.
Let's fetch more data.
The chart and table
both automatically update
as my model changes.
The chart even recalculates its Y axis
to reflect the new totals.
Let me show you one more chart.
I've stubbed out a line chart
which we can add to the view.
I'll jump to the implementation.
Line charts with Swift Charts
have some really cool options.
We can add symbols for each donut.
We can annotate the lines.
We can even smooth the curves
with a variety
of interpolation strategies.
Let's use catmullRom.
Finally, I'll override
the chart scale style
by providing my own mapping.
That will make my chart fit in better
with the app's color scheme.
Really nice.
The redesigned preview area
makes it easier than ever
to see how my view looks
in different environments.
By pressing this button
in the canvas,
I can see my view in Dark and Light mode.
I can even look at my layout
in every interface orientation,
all without adding
a single additional preview.
Let's zoom in on landscape.
It looks like my UI
isn't quite fitting here.
A few controls are offscreen,
and the charts have
an awkward aspect ratio.
Let's see where we're describing
this layout.
These views here are
in an implicit Vstack.
This year there are some powerful
new APIs in SwiftUI
that can create more flexible layouts.
Here, I'm going to use a ViewThatFits
to switch between a vertical
and a horizontal stack,
depending on the available space.
That looks much better.
Let's wire this up
so we can navigate to it
from the main screen.
I'm using SwiftUI's
new navigation split view,
which makes this really easy.
The split view has a sidebar
to track the selection
and a NavigationStack
that changes its content
as the sidebar selection changes.
I'll jump into the sidebar
and add a navigation link
for our Donut Champion view.
And then, we can try it out
in the interactive preview.
I'd like to see my split view
in landscape,
so I'll use the new canvas settings
to rotate the live preview.
Works great.
I'm happy with how this is looking
on iPad,
but now I'd love to bring it to Mac,
and it's only a few clicks
to do that.
I want to take full advantage
of the Mac SDK,
so I'm going to use native.
With just a single target backing my app,
I can share almost all my code,
and SwiftUI makes my app look great
on each platform.
I can also easily add
device-specific features.
For my Mac app,
let's add a menu bar extra.
Those are the little useful icons
on the upper right corner of your screen,
like Wi-Fi and Spotlight.
SwiftUI has a new API for this.
I just add it to the body of my app.
Now let's run this for Mac.
Our Donut Champion view looks great
on Mac right out of the box.
And here's that menu bar extra.
That'll be handy.
And that's a quick look at Swift Charts
and just a few of the enhancements
coming to SwiftUI and Xcode.
And now back to Josh.
Josh: We're continuing to expand
our adoption of SwiftUI
across our apps and system interfaces.
For example, iOS's new Lock Screen widgets
were designed from the ground up
using SwiftUI.
The new Font Book app was
completely rewritten with it.
And the modern, forward-looking design
of the new macOS System Settings app
was built using it.
Swift and SwiftUI were designed
from the start
to provide a single, native language
and API for all Apple platforms.
You can learn them once
and apply them everywhere.
Whether your vision is to provide
quick access to information
at a glance on Apple Watch,
productivity tools
on MacBook Pro and iPad,
new experiences on iPhone,
or a new way to relax with Apple TV,
Swift, SwiftUI, and Xcode
provide a next-generation integrated
development platform
to help you build apps
for all of our products.
Now, if you have an existing app,
it's easy to adopt
these new technologies incrementally.
And if you're new to our platforms
or if you're starting a brand-new app,
the best way to build an app
is with Swift and SwiftUI.
Now, of course
that's just the beginning.
We're also continuing to evolve
the user experience of our platforms
to give you more ways
to engage your users.
And to tell you more, here's Sebastien.
Sebastien Marineau-Mes:
Now, apps are about turning ideas,
code, and APIs into user experiences.
And the best apps
are the ones that can meet users
where they are in the moment.
We've created ways to help you take
user experience beyond your apps,
and build it into the system experience
on Apple devices.
This journey started with extensions,
integration with the Share Sheet,
and custom keyboards.
And more recently,
it's included the ability
to have your app display key information
on the Home Screen using widgets.
Now, this year,
there are a number of new ways
for your app to integrate with the system
experience across our platforms,
and it really starts with the Lock Screen,
which gets its biggest update ever.
It re-imagines how
the Lock Screen looks and how it works,
and it gives your ideas and your apps
another place to engage users.
And to tell you more, here's Robert.
Robert Dhaene:
In reimagining the Lock Screen,
we set out to make it
even more personal and beautiful,
while improving everyday utility.
As part of this,
we knew we needed to bring
the power of widgets
to the all-new Lock Screen.
Widgets have been an incredible way
to elevate key information
from your app and display it
where people can view it at a glance.
They make it easy to access
rich, timely information
right from the Home Screen.
The Lock Screen is the first thing you see
every time you pick up your iPhone,
and it's always been a place
to check the date and time
and look out for key messages.
When thinking about the best format
for displaying even more information here,
we didn't have to look far
for design inspiration.
Complications on Apple Watch
already provide glanceable, relevant,
and up-to-date information,
presented beautifully
right when users need it.
The design language naturally extends
to iOS and feels right at home
on the new Lock Screen.
So using WidgetKit,
we brought some of those same designs
to widgets on the Lock Screen,
including Circular,
which displays a small image,
gauge, or a few characters of text.
Circular widgets are great for displaying
whether you've been active enough today
or if you need to go out for a run.
Rectangular provides a large canvas
for displaying things
like the upcoming weather forecast.
Inline provides a powerful way
to convey information
with a tiny amount of text and SF Symbols
above the clock on iPhone,
next to a system-supplied date string,
such as Monday the 6th.
And by the way, all of these widgets
work on both iOS and watchOS
because starting in watchOS 9,
complications
are also powered by WidgetKit.
For the first time,
you can use the same code
to generate glanceable data
on both platforms.
WidgetKit manages platform differences
for you automatically,
using the appropriate system fonts
by default,
and tinting the widgets on
the Lock Screen for maximum legibility.
To show you how to use WidgetKit to create
widgets for the Lock Screen on iPhone
and complications on Apple Watch
using the same code,
I'll hand it over to Michael.
Michael Kent: Building widgets
on the iPhone Lock Screen
and complications on Apple Watch
is really easy with WidgetKit.
If you've made Home Screen widgets,
you're already most of the way there,
including how your data
and timeline are updated.
In our Food Truck app,
we already have a systemSmall widget
that users can add to their Home Screen
to see how many orders they've filled
out of their quota today.
This kind of information would be great
to show on the Lock Screen
or in a complication on the watch face.
Let's start by building out
the Circular family.
We'll first declare support for it
in our Supported Families array.
You'll notice that we're using
some platform conditionals here.
This is because we want this widget
to continue supporting macOS and iOS
with systemSmall, but that family
isn't available on watchOS.
Then, we'll add a case to define its view.
Let's use a gauge
that shows the current number of orders
from 0 to the daily quota
so the users can quickly see
their progress at a glance.
We'll display the current order count
as text in the center,
along with a donut symbol.
There.
Let's take a look at this
in Xcode Previews now.
Awesome!
That feels right at home
on the Lock Screen.
In order to show a bit more detail
at a glance,
we can also add support
for the rectangular family.
For this view,
we'll make a VStack,
starting with a title for the data
that's shown,
and that same donut symbol.
By using the Headline style for the font,
we'll get a treatment
that looks great on both platforms.
And we'll make sure it pops
with the widgetAccentable modifier.
Since the rectangular family gives us
a bit more space,
we'll show a cool custom segmented gauge
and display the current number of orders
out of the daily quota
for the gauge's label.
Looking back at the canvas,
we can see the rectangular widget
in previews as well.
I really love that gauge.
Now let's take a look at how this widget
would appear as a circular complication
on a watch face.
Well, all right, everything is there,
but for complications,
we also need to consider
the full color rendering mode,
which is the default in Xcode Previews.
Let's do that by adding a tint
to each of our gauges.
And a foreground color
to the rectangular headline.
For a bit of a pop in full color,
we can check the rendering mode
with an environment property
to replace the donut symbol
with a donut emoji
on both the circular
and rectangular views.
That looks really great!
With the new variants UI in previews,
we can change the color
we're previewing with no code at all.
Or even look at several at once.
And since we used default spacing,
system font styles,
and adapted to the rendering mode,
the same views look right at home
on both the Lock Screen and watch face.
It's that easy to make a widget
on the brand-new Lock Screen in iOS 16
and a great complication in watchOS 9,
all with the same code.
But this isn't the only way we've brought
the power of WidgetKit to the Lock Screen.
Here's Matt to tell you more.
Matt Shepherd: With WidgetKit,
you can give people access
to glanceable information.
But what about those moments
when they need live updates,
information tied to an activity,
or an event
that they care about right now?
For that, we are working on something new
we call Live Activities.
Live Activities makes it easier
to stay on top of things
that are happening in real time,
right from the Lock Screen.
Things like the latest score from a game,
the progress of a ride share,
or a workout,
right on the Lock Screen,
and always up-to-date.
Just like with widgets,
you create Live Activities with WidgetKit.
The difference is, you update
your Live Activity's presentation
and state in real time.
Since they're built with SwiftUI,
you can even animate your updates
from one state to the next.
These updates make sure
your Live Activities
has the most current information
when the user chooses to glance at it.
Live Activities will be available starting
in an update to iOS 16 later this year.
So those are the updates
to the all-new Lock Screen.
We think they're gonna be a great way
to help you give people
more information at a glance
in the moments they need it most.
Next, let's talk about a brand-new way
to enhance collaborative experiences.
To tell you more, here's Pierre.
Pierre de Fillipis:
Collaboration is an important part
of what people do
on iOS, iPadOS, and macOS.
And that's due in large part
to the incredible wealth of apps
that many of you have built,
to support teams who are collaborating
across any distance.
There's collaboration for work,
like a product road map in Airtable,
and there's also collaboration for play,
like finding your dream home in Redfin.
Whether it's for work or play,
collaboration often starts
with a conversation.
And with the new
Messages Collaboration API,
you can bring your app's
existing collaboration experiences
into Messages and FaceTime.
When users share a link
to content in your app,
the API makes it easy for you
to mark that link as collaborative,
enabling a seamless experience.
We provide the identifiers you need
so you can give access
to the recipients immediately
when they tap the link to join.
And of course,
this works without compromising privacy.
Messages identities and app identities
remain private and are not shared.
And the best part is, you can do this
with existing technologies
your app is most likely already using.
With one object,
your users can initiate collaboration
in two convenient ways
that they're already familiar with.
One, the Share Sheet,
which has been updated
to put collaboration front and center,
and two, drag & drop,
where you can share content
you want to collaborate on
by dragging it directly
into the Messages conversation.
And once the conversation is started,
you can even post notices
about content updates
right to the Messages conversation.
With a couple lines of code,
your users can get back to collaborating
in your app with a single tap in Messages.
And with the collaboration popover,
your users can get back to the
conversation in Messages or FaceTime
right from your app.
So with the Messages Collaboration API,
your app is truly woven into the fabric
of Messages and FaceTime.
We take care of giving your users
powerful communication tools
so you can focus
on the powerful collaboration tools
you deliver in your app.
So this is going to level up collaboration
on iOS, iPadOS, and macOS,
creating a consistent experience
that's deeply rooted
in the connection
between the people collaborating,
whether for work or play.
Next is Ari, who's going to tell you
about a new framework called App Intents.
Ari Weinstein: I'm excited to tell you
about the App Intents framework,
which makes your app's features
available to the system,
so people can use them automatically
through Siri and Shortcuts.
People love using Shortcuts
with their apps.
They let them get things done so fast,
just by asking Siri,
or by quickly tapping a shortcut
on the Home Screen.
And it's amazing
to see how people remix app capabilities
into totally new pieces of functionality
with custom shortcuts.
Today, people have to add shortcuts
manually before they can use them at all.
We're making this automatic in iOS 16
with the new App Intents framework.
App Intents works together with Shortcuts
to form App Shortcuts,
which people can use with Siri
right away,
without having to set anything up first,
like, "Hey, Siri, clean the kitchen
with Roomba."
But it's not just Siri.
App shortcuts give your users
a front-row seat
to your app's features
throughout the system,
like in Spotlight, where anytime
people search for your app,
your shortcuts show up, too,
and your shortcuts will be suggested
right below app suggestions
without needing to adopt
any additional APIs, like donations.
Your shortcuts also appear immediately
in the Shortcuts app,
where people can run them with a tap.
App Intents is the next step
for the SiriKit Intents framework
that we introduced in iOS10.
If you adopt Intents to integrate
with Widgets or domains
like media or messaging,
you should keep using
the SiriKit Intents framework,
but for developers who build
custom intents for Siri and Shortcuts,
you should go ahead and upgrade
to App Intents.
You can easily upgrade to App Intents
in Xcode
by pushing the Convert button
in your intent definition file.
Xcode will generate the equivalent
App Intents source code,
and then you fill in the blanks
with your intent handling code.
The App Intents framework is really easy
to develop for
because it's designed
from the ground up for Swift,
and it requires much less code.
The Swift code that you write
is the only source of truth,
There's no separate
intent definition files
or code generation to keep in sync.
And the code is easy to add
to your project.
You don't need to rearchitect
your codebase.
Even if you have Objective-C code,
you can use it with App Intents
by wrapping it with Swift.
An app intent represents something
people can do inside of your app,
and it makes it possible to do it
from outside of your app.
You can define an intent
and add an app shortcut
in just a few lines of code.
Let's give it a try together.
Back in the Food Truck app,
I have this great chart view
that lets me see the top five
best-selling donuts
over a given period of time,
like today or this week.
I want to expose this
to Siri and Shortcuts
so people pull it up super quickly,
so first, in Xcode,
I'll go to a new Swift file.
I'll import the App Intents framework
and SwiftUI.
Then I define the intent
by defining a struct
that conforms to the AppIntent protocol.
I'll give it a title.
And I'll add a parameter
for which time frame of trends to look at.
This uses the time frame enum
that's already defined in my codebase.
I need to extend it to conform
to the AppEnum protocol
so that we can extract
human-readable names
for each enum case,
like "today" and "this week."
Next, on the intent,
I'll implement the perform method.
Here, I return a result that includes
the SwiftUI chart view.
I could also include a dialogue
or output value.
I want people to be able to use
this intent automatically, without setup,
so I'll define an app shortcut.
This includes the phrase
that people can say to Siri
to use this intent.
The phrase has to include the app name
as a variable,
and I've included the time frame parameter
so people can say
"Food truck trends for today,"
or "Food truck trends for this week."
The last thing I need to do is make this
discoverable for my users.
People need to see the phrase
at some point,
so they know what to say to Siri,
so I'm going to switch to the file
for the Top 5 Donuts view
that we were looking at a second ago,
and I'll add a Siri tip.
Now I can build and run the app
and hop over to my phone.
Let's give it a try.
I can see the shortcut now appears
in the Shortcuts app,
with variants for each parameter value,
and I can run one
just by tapping on it.
And I can run them from Siri
just by saying the phrase,
"Food truck trends for today."
Or I could say,
"food truck trends for this week."
When people are in
the Top Five view of my app,
they'll see this tip we added
at the bottom,
so they know what to say to Siri
to ask for this feature.
Lastly, people can quickly access these
in Spotlight
when they search for the app, like this.
It's super useful.
App Intents will make it easier than ever
before to make your app's functionality
available throughout the system experience
on all of these platforms.
Next, Ricky will tell us
about some big updates
to authentication technologies.
Ricky Mondello:
For as long as we can remember,
we've been creating and using passwords.
But passwords have serious issues,
like phishing, reuse across accounts,
and website leaks.
The good news is that together
we can solve these issues.
And we can do this today with Passkeys.
Passkeys will streamline
your authentication flows
and address the top security issues
with passwords.
Passkeys were designed
to be incredibly easy to use.
The interface uses familiar
Autofill-style UI
and FaceID and TouchID
for biometric verification.
These elements create a seamless
transition away from passwords,
while delivering
a profound increase in security.
Let's check out Passkeys in action.
When setting up an account with a passkey,
I don't need to create a password.
I'll type a user name and save
the passkey to my iCloud Keychain.
This will securely sync this passkey
to all of my other Apple devices.
And if I sign out,
signing back in is a breeze.
Just Face ID, and I'm in.
Because passkeys are built
on open industry standards
that platforms are adopting,
I can use the passkey
I just created on my iPhone
to sign into the Food Truck website
on my friend's PC.
On the website,
I'll type my username, submit,
and choose the option to sign in
using a phone,
scan the QR code,
let the iPhone and PC securely connect,
and I'm signed in.
In Safari on my Mac,
it's even easier to sign in.
My passkey is already here,
thanks to iCloud Keychain,
and I can sign in directly
from the website's username field.
It's easy to integrate passkeys
into existing sign-in flows.
For example, this website's username field
lets me sign in with a passkey
or a password.
If I type a username
for a password based account,
I can quickly sign in.
With passkeys,
the device does the hard work,
and it's secure every time.
When creating a passkey,
the device generates a unique key
that is specific to the website or app
it was created for
and protects it behind biometrics.
It's impossible to have a weak passkey.
It can't be forgotten, reused, or guessed.
Passkeys are based
on public key cryptography,
which makes credential leaks
from servers a thing of the past.
Instead of storing salted,
hashed passwords,
that can leak and be cracked,
your server keeps only a public key.
Public keys are designed
to be truly public,
and not at all valuable to hackers.
This significantly reduces your risk
as a website owner.
With passkeys–
and this point is huge–
credential phishing as we know it today
is gone,
eliminating the number one
security vulnerability that users face.
Passkeys are intrinsically linked to the
website or app they were set up for,
so users can never be tricked into
using their passkey on the wrong website.
And unlike passwords,
it's not possible to type
or copy a passkey
into a convincing fake website,
or even give anything away to
someone looking over your shoulder.
When you put it all together,
what we're talking about here
is a new era of account security.
Bringing passkeys to your app
and website takes only a few steps.
First, you'll teach your account backend
to store public keys
and issue authentication challenges.
Then, on your website and in your app,
you'll offer passkeys to users
and adopt API to create
a new passkey and sign in with it.
Passkeys are based on the Web
Authentication, or WebAuthn, standard,
which has been a collaborative effort
across the industry
from both platform vendors
and service owners.
The standard itself is mature
and well documented,
and passkeys fit it like a glove.
All of this is ready
for you to build on right now.
Next generation security,
a seamless user experience,
and a design that works beautifully
alongside passwords during the transition.
Back to you, Sebastien.
Sebastien: You've just seen
a few of the newest ways
that you can integrate your apps with the
system experience on all of our platforms.
And beyond those integration points,
there are a ton of new APIs
and frameworks
across all of our platforms
that open up even more possibilities
for you and your apps this year.
And I'd like to walk you through a few
before diving into some others
in more detail.
Let's start with iPadOS.
With iPadOS 16, you'll be able to make
the most powerful iPad apps yet,
with a consistent,
desktop-like experience.
There's a seamless find-and-replace
experience for UI text views
that your apps get automatically,
as well as updates to the navigation bar,
toolbars, the document menu,
that make it easy for your users
to manage documents
and customize their experience.
To enable even more powerful applications
of iPad with connected hardware,
DriverKit comes to iPad,
helping to unlock
the incredible power of the M1 chip.
It's the same API
that's available on Mac today,
enabling you to easily deliver support
for your USB, audio,
and PCI devices
to an even larger audience.
Now, watchOS is creating new opportunities
for apps through deeper integration
with system services.
The CallKit framework in watchOS 9
includes a new
Voiceover IP background mode
that lets apps make voice calls
directly from Apple Watch,
with the same familiar user experience
as FaceTime audio and phone calls.
And Bluetooth-connected medical devices
get more robust connectivity
and data delivery,
allowing for timely alerts
when a critical condition is detected.
Now, tvOS 16 gives you new ways
to create connected experiences
between your apps on Apple TV
and iPhone, iPad, or Apple Watch apps
on nearby devices.
So a workout could use motion data
from Apple Watch,
or you could use iPhone or iPad
as a custom controller
for your turn-based games,
And tvOS manages device discovery
and connection for you,
so your app doesn't even need
to be running on the other device.
In fact, if your app isn't installed,
the user is automatically prompted
to download it
right from the App Store.
Now, for Phone and iPad,
there are new tools for advertisers.
We know that effective advertising
is important to a lot of your businesses,
which is why we created SKAdNetwork.
It's an API that helps ad networks
and advertisers
measure the performance of campaigns
without tracking users,
and we've been pleased to see
many third-party ad networks adopt it.
Now, we've heard feedback from
ad networks and developers,
and this year, we made a number
of improvements to SKAdNetwork
that reflect some of the biggest requests
and give you
dramatically more flexibility,
all without compromising user privacy.
Now, on iPhone and iPad,
there are new cool features
that use AR and LiDAR scanning
with ScanKit and RoomPlan.
These APIs let your apps create
rich 3D parametric room models
in USD and USDZ formats.
So you can create
a variety of workflows and experiences,
from architecture and design,
to retail and hospitality,
and the models include furniture
classification for categories
such as sofas, cabinets, TVs,
and yes, even kitchen sinks.
Now, last year, we introduced Focus
for iPhone, iPad, Mac, and Apple Watch,
and with it, ways for your app to manage
notifications based on a user's Focus.
And this year,
Focus goes further with Focus filters.
They're built on top of App Intents,
and Focus filters let you adjust
the content of your app
based on the user's current focus.
So, for example,
an app could create a Focus filter
to only show work accounts
when the user is in their Work Focus.
And those examples are really
just scratching the surface.
Across the board at every level,
there are new tools and APIs
with the power that you need
to take your apps further than ever
and to create entirely new apps
and experiences.
So next, let's go a little deeper
starting with Metal, a technology that's
really taking things to the next level.
And to tell you more, let's go to Sarah.
♪ ♪
Sarah Clawson: Metal is the powerful
graphics and compute API
that helps you create amazing games
and pro apps for Apple platforms.
Metal makes it easy to take advantage
of the groundbreaking Apple GPUs
and unified memory system
now spanning the latest iPhone,
iPad, and Mac lineups
shipping with Apple silicon.
And this year, we're introducing Metal 3,
with powerful new features that help you
render immersive graphics
with even higher frame rates
and enable new levels
of computational performance.
For instance,
you'll get huge performance gains
for the machine learning framework,
PyTorch,
which now uses the new Metal backend
to enable ML training with the GPU.
And the biggest focus area is on gaming,
starting with game loading,
a key element to the gaming experience
that can affect launch time
and loading new levels.
Modern games deliver
a rich gaming experience
by providing high-quality assets,
and loading these assets quickly from
storage to the GPU can be challenging.
Often, games will hide asset loading
behind a loading screen,
and one technique
to launch gameplay faster
is to load and draw
a lower quality version
until the high-quality visuals
are available.
This is not an ideal gaming experience
since the user sees
lower quality graphics for longer.
Metal 3 introduces fast resource loading
with the Metal IO API
that takes advantage of the Apple GPU's
unified memory architecture
to minimize loading overhead
and ensures
that the high-speed SSD storage
that ships with every Apple silicon Mac
has enough requests in its queues
to maximize throughput.
This new API provides faster
and more consistent performance
so that more time is spent
drawing at the ideal quality.
In addition to moving resources
from storage to memory,
game loading
is also about shader compilation.
Shaders always need to be compiled
for the user's unique
hardware configuration,
and with the wide variety
of PC hardware permutations,
this usually has to be done at runtime.
This in-game compilation can affect
the gamer's experience
causing dropped frames,
slower frame rates, and longer loading.
In contrast, Apple silicon and Metal 3
are designed together
to support all Apple devices.
And now, with offline shader compilation,
you can generate GPU shader binaries
at project build time,
enabling you to eliminate
in-game shader compilation
to reduce load times
and improve rendering performance.
Another important aspect to gaming
is providing rich, detailed assets,
and one way to increase the visual
fidelity of your game's graphics
is by generating much more sophisticated
geometric meshes.
Traditionally this is done
with a compute pass
that'll evaluate the surface
and generate geometry
to be used in a later render pass.
The challenge is that
this can introduce latency
and take an unpredictable
amount of memory.
Metal 3 introduces a new Mesh Shading API,
which gives you precise control over
an optimized geometry processing pipeline
from a single render pass.
The Object shader decides
how many meshes to generate,
and the Mesh shader
generates the actual geometry
to be sent directly to the rasterizer,
avoiding a trip to device memory
and increasing performance.
Gamers also want to see
these stunning visuals
at the highest possible frame rate,
but rendering advanced graphics
at ultra-high resolutions
can cost precious milliseconds.
MetalFX upscaling helps
you render immersive graphics
in less time per frame.
Here's how it works.
Previously, you would render
your full frame at native resolution,
but the GPU render time
might not hit the target frame time.
Now, you can render the same
complex scene at a lower resolution
to meet the target frame times,
and use MetalFX framework
to perform temporal antialiasing
and upscaling to the target resolution.
With Apple silicon and Metal 3's
optimized features,
gaming has never looked so good
on the Mac.
And developers agree.
Leading game studios have plans to bring
their titles to the Mac,
like Grid Legends,
taking advantage of Apple silicon
to help you reach maximum speeds.
Or Resident Evil Village,
using features like MetalFX upscaling
to deliver hauntingly beautiful scenes
at the highest resolution.
And No Man's Sky,
taking advantage of Metal 3
to explore rich, expansive worlds
on both Mac and iPad.
Metal 3 is incredible,
with features to boost the performance
of your apps
and provide an amazing gaming experience.
Now to tell us more about the direction
MapKit is headed, here's Kathy.
Kathy Lin: Whether you're navigating
to a favorite restaurant,
planning that next vacation,
or just checking where your favorite
food truck is parked on a map,
we rely on our devices more than ever
to help us explore the world around us.
MapKit is the best way to help users
discover and navigate the world
with rich and flexible mapping
and location services,
powered by Apple Maps
and available to developers for free.
With MapKit, you can display map
or satellite imagery in your app,
find and call out points of interest,
add annotations and overlays,
get directions, and more.
MapKit is powered by our all-new map,
built from the ground up by Apple.
It offers improved detail and accuracy,
and can bring useful mapping
and location services to your app.
With iOS 16,
we're building on this map
to introduce our biggest update ever
for MapKit,
starting with making the 3D City
Experience available to all developers.
Users of your apps will be able
to see incredible details,
like 3D elevation, turn lanes,
crosswalks and bike lanes,
and amazing handcrafted 3D landmarks
like the Golden Gate Bridge,
or the Ferry Building.
The additional detail of the map allows
you to provide context and precision
that was never before possible.
You can, for example,
show that a point of interest
is between the crosswalk
and where the bike lane starts.
No other digital map lets you do that,
and we've made it incredibly easy
to implement.
To show you more,
let's create an experience
that makes it easy for a user to find
where their favorite food truck is parked
using the details of the new map.
Map views like this one will automatically
get the 3D City Experience
where it's available.
Just select iOS 16
as the deployment target.
Next, I can utilize
the extraordinary detail of the map
to illustrate the exact location
of the food truck.
MapKit has powerful controls that allow us
to position the camera in 3D space
to create a precise view of the map.
Here, I can choose how far
we want to be zoomed in
by setting the distance of the center
coordinate of the camera to 600 meters.
By adjusting the pitch and heading
and tilting the camera into 3D,
you can see amazing
and useful details like turn lanes,
crosswalks, and even trees.
By default, elevation will be flattened.
In order to help users understand
the terrain they'll encounter,
I can specify a preferredConfiguration
with elevationStyle 'realistic'
to include 3D elevation.
When adding an annotation or a route line
sourced from MapKit's Directions API,
MapKit automatically handles elevation
and will adjust the annotation
or route line
by placing it on top of the 3D terrain.
Animating the camera heading
by adding a slow pan
really brings the map view to life.
When a user switches into Dark Mode,
the map will adjust together
with the rest of the UI.
We're very excited to make
this immersive experience available
to developers with iOS 16.
In addition, we're also bringing another
popular Apple Maps feature to MapKit,
Look Around,
which is a great way
to explore the world at ground level,
with high resolution 3D photography
and smooth animations.
Users can simply tap
to move down the street.
I can add a static Look Around preview
just below the map
by dropping in a View Controller
and specifying a MapItem.
The Look Around view automatically frames
the location correctly.
When a user taps on the preview,
I can choose to provide
a full screen Look Around view,
where users can see the address,
the date the imagery was collected,
and they can tap to move around freely
to get a better understanding
of their surroundings.
There's one more new,
highly-requested capability
we're introducing to MapKit in iOS 16–
Apple Maps Server APIs.
Maps Server APIs are RESTful
and support four of the most used
functions of MapKit:
Geocode,
which turns a lat/long into an address;
Reverse Geocode,
which does the opposite–
it turns an address into GPS coordinates;
Search;
and Estimated Times of Arrival.
Our new Maps Server APIs
are a great way
to make your own backend services richer
and more performant.
Of course,
MapKit is built from the ground up
on the same foundation of privacy
as Apple Maps,
and does not associate users' data
with their identity
or keep a history of where they've been.
And that's a quick look at
what's new with MapKit in iOS 16.
Now for the weather, or at least
how you can build it into your app,
here's Novall.
Novall Khan: We announced today that we're
bringing the Weather app to iPad and Mac,
and introducing powerful new features,
including severe weather notifications,
rich detail views,
and ten days of hourly temperature
and precipitation forecasts.
And there are all kinds of
other experiences across Apple devices
and platforms that get better because
of the weather data we provide–
from asking Siri for today's forecast,
to rerouting navigation around flooding.
All of that is built on
our Apple Weather service.
Apple Weather delivers
a world-class global weather forecast
using high-resolution
meteorological models
combined with machine learning
and prediction algorithms.
Apple Weather provides current weather,
10-day hourly forecasts, daily forecasts,
and historical weather
so you can evaluate trends in data.
Severe weather alerts
and minute-by-minute precipitation
are also available
for select countries around the world.
Forecasts feature 10 days
of hour-by-hour temperature,
precipitation, UV index forecasts,
and much more.
And all of this data is available to you
through WeatherKit.
WeatherKit is a native Swift API
for all Apple platforms,
and a REST API you can use from anywhere.
These APIs deliver accurate,
hyperlocal weather forecasts,
to help your users stay safe,
informed, and prepared.
Let me show you how easy it is
to get weather information
through WeatherKit's great Swift API
in a quick demo.
Let's revisit our Food Truck app.
To make sure my customers
don't get caught in the rain,
my app is set up to recommend
a parking spot with clear skies.
Let me show you how I can get the weather.
Here I have a list of safe parking spots.
I've already added the WeatherKit
capability in Xcode,
and all it takes is a few lines of code.
With Swift Concurrency,
requesting weather is simple.
We call weather(for:) on WeatherService,
and pass in a location.
Then I can get the relevant data
I need for my app, like condition,
precipitation,
and cloud cover.
Now that I have the data I need
for each of my parking spots,
when I run my app,
my custom view has updated to
recommend a location with clear skies.
There are all kinds of ways
you can use weather data
to make the experiences
in your apps better.
You might use weather forecasts
to help you with inventory,
predicting that
your ice-cream filled donuts
are going to be a popular order
on a hot day,
so you should stock up on ice cream.
That's all it takes
to get the weather for our food truck,
and there's so much more
to uncover with WeatherKit.
In keeping with Apple's commitment
to privacy,
location is used
only to provide weather forecasts,
is not associated with
any personally identifying information,
and is never shared or sold.
Privacy is a shared responsibility,
and through WeatherKit,
you can get accurate weather data
while protecting user privacy.
Because we want to make it easy for you
to get started with WeatherKit,
we're including 500,000
weather(for:location) API calls per month
in your Apple Developer Program
membership.
Those of you who need more will be able
to purchase additional tiers of service
right in the developer app,
starting this fall.
So that's WeatherKit,
accurate, hyperlocal weather forecasts
powered by the Apple Weather service.
We're starting with a beta,
and it's available now on all platforms.
There are so many creative ways
that you can use WeatherKit in your apps.
And now here's Ryan
to give us some perspective
on what your apps can see with Live Text.
Ryan Dixon:
Our users are loving Live Text,
and we have heard from many of you
that you want to bring it
to your apps too.
So this year,
we are expanding VisionKit
with two new APIs
that will allow you to do just that.
The Live Text API unlocks the ability
to analyze image content,
allowing users to interact with text
and QR codes
found in photos and paused video frames,
and it provides quick actions
so your users are just a tap away
from taking action on relevant data.
It's great for any app
that displays visual media,
like Apollo for Reddit or Vimeo.
And the Data Scanner API unlocks
the ability to analyze a live camera feed.
It dramatically simplifies text
and barcode ingestion for users.
All you need to do
is add any overlays or custom controls
that tailor the live camera experience
to the needs of your app.
This is especially useful for
consumer apps that rely on QR codes
or enterprise apps built for
back-of-warehouse inventory management,
pick-and pack delivery services,
and point of sale kiosks.
Both the Live Text and Data Scanner APIs
support automatic detection
of nine languages,
including this year's additions
of Japanese and Korean.
These VisionKit APIs will bring years
of computer vision innovation
to your app with just a few lines of code.
Here's Jenny to show you how.
Jenny Chen: To show you a demo, we're back
to our trusty pop-up Food Truck app.
We're doing a promotion where if
users post a picture to a social channel
holding a sign up with the hashtag
#freedonut and their address on the app,
we'll drive to their address
and deliver a free donut to them.
We'll head to our social donut feed.
We want to add Live Text to the images
so that drivers can extract the text
to get the addresses for delivery.
Here's where the new Live Text APIs
play in.
I can easily add an ImageInteraction
on top of my view,
and that will add the Live Text button
with quick action support to it.
While the Live Text button
normally sits on the bottom right,
I already have a heart button in my app,
so I can adjust the placement
using custom insets.
I can also set the button configuration
to customize the style of the button
so that it matches my app better.
Now that I've added it in,
I can tap the Live Text button,
select the text,
or use quick actions
to easily grab the address.
I love that users don't have to learn
a new interaction model,
as it provides the same ease of use
with the Live Text experience.
The UI is consistent and familiar.
It feels integrated with the OS,
but I can still adjust the placement
even when I have my own custom UI.
Of course, like any good delivery app,
we also want to provide
the best service to our customers
and make sure
we're giving people the right donuts.
So we track our donut orders via QR code.
Using the new Data Scanner APIs,
I can easily add that as the first step
of any customer interaction.
Right now,
that button doesn't do anything,
but I can easily instantiate
a new DataScanner object
that looks for text, QR codes, or barcodes
that I can then import into my app.
With just a few lines of code,
I can bring up the camera,
specify that I want QR codes,
and startScanning!
When the driver taps on the QR code,
I want to show that the scan is a success.
I'll add in the delegate handler
in Xcode...
...and on tap, show an alert to the user
that the scan was a success
so that I can go ahead
and get the donut order started.
Now when I run the app,
this brings up a view controller
with the camera view,
and I can see the guidance
and the reticle view
highlighting the QR code.
When I tap on the QR code,
I can see my scan was a success
and the donut order is confirmed.
And with that,
my #freedonut delivery is on its way.
With VisionKit,
the new Live Text and Data Scanner APIs
easily allow you to bring these
powerful vision capabilities to your app.
And now, back to Susan.
Susan: This is an exciting time
to be building apps.
Xcode Cloud is now ready
to help you build better apps faster.
With Swift and SwiftUI,
it's easier than ever
to transform your ideas into apps
that work across Apple platforms.
There are cool new ways for your apps
to bring your ideas
deeper into the system experience.
Lock Screen widgets and Live Activities
bring your app to the Lock Screen.
Messages Collaboration
makes it incredibly easy
for your users to connect and collaborate.
And App Intents
help integrate your app with Siri.
There are entirely new APIs
and major updates to existing APIs,
like WeatherKit, MapKit,
Live Text, and Metal.
And that's not the end of the story.
It's another big WWDC this year,
with 175 sessions,
hundreds of labs, and Digital Lounge
activities running all week.
We can't wait to connect with you
this week,
and more importantly,
this week is for you.
We're eager to see what you create next.
Thank you!
♪ ♪
.