♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Welcome to "Qualities of
great AR experiences."
I'm Alli Dryer, and I'm part of
the Apple Design team
working on augmented reality.
AR lets you deliver experiences
that blend virtual objects
with the real world,
creating the illusion that
these objects actually exist.
AR can be
surprisingly immersive,
and yet at the same time,
it's always grounded
in what's really happening.
It allows you
to visualize things
that would be impossible,
risky, or hard to do
from a practical standpoint.
Blurring the line between
imagination and reality,
an AR experience
really feels like magic.
You can completely transform
people's surroundings
through visuals and sound so
they experience something new.
You can also add new layers of
information to the environment
to enable quick and lightweight
interactions.
Designing for augmented reality
can be very different
from designing
for 2D applications,
but don't worry,
we'll break it down here.
Today I'm going to share
criteria you can use
to decide if AR is right for
the experience you're building,
along with tips for handling
some of the unique aspects
of augmented reality
when you're designing
your first AR experience.
OK. So you're designing
an app or feature
and wondering whether AR
makes sense for you.
Here are a few things
to consider.
AR can help you deliver
a true representation of things.
To show what I mean,
let's look at an example of
something AR does really well,
which is to present the
real-world size of an object.
Say you're trying
to educate people
about how big a dinosaur is.
You could just write it out,
or show a picture,
or you could unleash
a virtual T. rex on the scene.
In that case,
there's no need to imagine
how big the dinosaur is.
The AR experience
gives the viewer
an instant,
visceral sense of scale
in a way that's
truly immersive.
This example comes
from the app Monster Park,
a game that lets people
explore and control
the movement of animated
three-dimensional dinosaurs.
It's fitting that the entire app
revolves around this
large-as-life AR experience,
also emphasizing the creation of
photos and videos for sharing.
AR is at its most delightful
when it affects and responds
to what's immediately
around you,
involving physical space
in a meaningful way.
Say you're trying
to design an app
that helps with interior design,
and you want to help people
choose a paint color
for their walls.
You could use swatches
or stock photography,
but those aren't very accurate.
Even better,
you could show someone
how their very own
room would look
with freshly painted walls.
The Color Snap app
does just that.
It allows people
to choose a paint color
and then tap a wall
to preview the effect.
Because it's AR,
people can move around
to see how the new color
will affect their space
from different vantage points.
Next, augmented reality
allows you to create experiences
that visualize
virtual objects in 3D,
which makes it easier
to understand and evaluate them.
With AR, you can build features
that help people try on things
in a way that's virtual
yet realistic enough
for someone to make
a confident purchasing decision.
For example,
the Warby Parker app
lets people try on
virtual glasses
so they can place an order
knowing exactly
how their frames will fit.
It's faster to switch between
frame styles in AR
than it would be
to swap glasses in real life.
Grounding virtual objects
in the scene
is also really important.
The quality of lighting
and shadows in your experiences
can have a huge impact
on people's feeling
that things are really there,
even when an object
isn't very realistic.
The IKEA Place app
allows people to place
a piece of virtual furniture
in their home
and get a more accurate sense
of what the updated room
would look like.
IKEA Place takes advantage of
ARKit's built-in lighting
for realistic shadows
that really settle
the virtual furniture
into the room.
Visualizing in 3D
can refer to objects,
but don't forget about
using people's surroundings
as a canvas
for your experiences.
You can create new features
with advanced visual effects,
provide maps and 3D models
that fit your brand,
and even bring people's spaces
into the game you're building
with iOS's new RoomPlan API.
We've got a session
on creating 3D room scans
that goes into detail
about RoomPlan
if you want to learn more.
AR lets you streamline actions
by attaching digital
capabilities to physical things,
making your apps and features
more efficient.
You might have
already experienced
how using the real world
as input can speed things up
if you've ever scanned a code
to order at a restaurant.
You can use AR to build compact
yet incredibly useful features
that save people time.
In iOS's Measure App,
centering the camera on a person
automatically displays her
height in just the right spot.
The experience feels lightweight
because there's very little UI,
the interaction is based
on device movement,
and the measurement information
disappears after you've seen it.
This AR experience
would be too limited to offer
as an app on its own,
but it really complements
the other capabilities
of the Measure app.
So, now you know you can use
AR for your apps and features
when you want to deliver
a true representation,
involve physical space
in a meaningful way,
visualize in 3D,
and streamline actions
by making use of what's in
the environment.
And as you can see, there are
a lot of different ways
to incorporate AR into
the experiences you're creating,
whether it's as
the main focus of the app
or with a lighter hand as
a feature that reduces friction.
So, you've decided AR
is right for your purposes
and now it's time
to get started with design.
When you're designing for AR,
you'll need to consider
some of the aspects
that make it different
than traditional 2D interfaces.
AR is spatial.
AR is movement-based.
And AR is tied
to the physical environment.
You'll need to think about
how to blend virtual elements
into the scene,
about ergonomics,
and about working
with a limited field of view.
Now I'll go through tips
you can keep in mind
when designing AR experiences.
People using your app
might be in places
that are difficult for AR,
so what you can do
to help is coach them
through different ways
to get to a better experience.
The Mission to Mars app
does a great job
of getting people
set up for success
with a strong coaching sequence.
Let's take a closer look
at this example.
As you're getting started,
Mission to Mars highlights
three different requirements
you need in your environment
to have a great session.
First, there's a reminder
that AR can be immersive,
and it's wise to find
a safe place to engage with it.
This can be a particular concern
for experiences
that involve wayfinding,
where you'll need
to take extra care
not to draw people's
attention to the screen
for long periods of time.
Next, the app suggests
that AR performs best
on surfaces with texture,
rather than on glass or
smooth white featureless planes.
LiDAR can help overcome
some of these challenging
environmental conditions,
so you might be able
to omit this suggestion
for some devices.
And last, Mission to Mars
advises people
to find a bright space
because AR works best
in environments
that are properly lit.
What's great about this coaching
sequence is that it's quick,
easy to navigate,
and helps people understand
how to set up their environment
for the best AR experience.
The next tip is to take
advantage of screen space.
You'd be surprised
how large a role it can play
in AR experience design.
So, what is screen space?
Think of screen space
as a 2D layer
that sits on top of
the three-dimensional world
that's captured by
your camera view.
It's best to place text
and interactive elements
like buttons
here in screen space,
rather than in the 3D world
of the camera
to preserve legibility.
Here's a great example
from the Mission to Mars app
that illustrates how to handle
text in screen space.
High-contrast text and buttons
sit in a 2D screen space layer
on top of the 3D scene below.
The text updates as the camera
moves to help you understand
how it relates to the 3D objects
in the scene.
If you do need to lock your text
to something in the world,
try to keep it billboarded
or parallel to the screen
when possible.
Focus on increasing contrast,
bumping up type sizes
and putting text on a background
so you can maintain
accessibility.
Design for constant movement.
It's important
that people understand
how and when to move
their devices.
Sometimes they'll need
to move their bodies as well
in order to experience AR.
Try to provide
real-time feedback
with visual effects and sound
as people move,
so that even if the action
is taking place out of view,
people can still connect
with the experience.
Use simple, glanceable
instructions and animations
to coach people how to move.
It helps to place instructions
in screen space
and to show them on an as-needed
basis, rather than all up front.
It's great to leverage the
built-in coaching animations,
but you can also create your own
onboarding instructions
that relate to your app,
like this example
from the app DoodleLens
that shows an iPhone
panning back and forth
in front of a doodle.
Ergonomic considerations
are really important for AR.
It can be exhausting
to hold your arm out
for long periods of time,
and uncomfortable
to reach for buttons
that aren't positioned properly
for one-handed use.
Emphasize legibility at arm's
length for the entire interface.
Simplify interactions
so that they can be completed
with minimal effort.
Use oversized buttons
with high-contrast icons
that are easy to tap
one-handed with a thumb.
Here's a nice example
at the bottom of the screen
in DoodleLens.
People are viewing
AR experiences
with a limited field of view
offered through
a handheld device,
so there's a good chance
they might not be able to see
the full extent
of something large.
There's also a possibility
that a virtual object
might be located out of view.
Allow people to adjust
the scale of an object,
in case they're not
able to back up far enough
to see the whole thing.
This example from AR Quick Look
uses a pinch gesture
for direct manipulation.
There's also a haptic
so that you can feel it
when you scale something
past 100 percent.
When something is out of view
to the right or to the left,
use sounds and haptics
and provide simple indicators
or text instructions
in screen space.
It can also be helpful
to provide a map
or bird's-eye view
showing someone's orientation
and illustrating
that the object is located
in the opposite direction.
In this example
from the RoomPlan experience,
the small 3D model drawing
at the bottom of the view
helps you preview your results
and keep track of what has
been scanned so far.
It can be difficult for people
peering through a screen
to understand the location
of virtual objects in space
unless they're behaving
realistically.
Depth cues that help people see
how far away things are
can help with this.
The size of objects,
perspective effects
like diminishing
towards the horizon,
realistic shadows and lighting,
the proper amount
of detail in your textures,
and overlapping objects
create a feeling of depth
and help people perceive
spatial relationships.
I want to highlight one depth
cue that's tricky to work with
but can really
help people understand
where things are located
relative to each other:
overlapping,
also known as occlusion.
Here's an example of overlapping
you can see in AR Quick Look.
The virtual airplane
seems like it's positioned
behind the wooden blocks
on the desk
because the lower part of it
is hidden.
Finally, craft experiences
that last
no more than a minute or two.
This is for the ergonomic
reasons I mentioned earlier,
but also because AR is
a resource-intensive superpower
that has a big impact
on battery and thermals.
If you do end up creating
a longer experience,
make sure that you
build in breaks.
For All Mankind: Time Capsule
is an AR experience
that allows you to explore
the For All Mankind universe.
The app complements
the TV show,
telling stories through
interactive objects.
Time Capsule is
presented in chapters
that provide moments of rest
and a place to pause
then return to the experience.
Today I shared tips to help
overcome some of the challenges
with working on AR features.
You've learned to guide people
to the right environment,
to take advantage
of screen space,
to design for constant
movement,
to think about ergonomics
and a limited field of view,
to use depth cues, and to limit
the duration of the experience
to keep people
from getting fatigued.
Augmented Reality feels
like magic when it's useful,
delightful, and relates
to the physical world.
AR allows you
to see virtual objects
or even to transform
your environment.
You can attach digital
capabilities to physical things
to create a layer of useful
information and actions.
The AR features and apps
that you create
will transform how people work,
learn, play, shop,
and connect with the world.
I can't wait to see
what you'll build next
in augmented reality.
Thank you!
♪