♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hi, my name is Felipe.
I'm a software engineer on the tvOS team.
Today I'm excited to share with you
the improvements we've made in tvOS 16
to make it easier to support
multiple users in your apps.
Apple TV is designed to be used
by everyone.
We've been improving multiple users
on Apple TV since tvOS 13.
In tvOS 16 we have new features
that will make it easier
to support multiple users in all apps.
I'll start with an overview of
the multiple users features on Apple TV.
Showing how easy it is personalize apps
on a device used by everyone.
Then I'll demonstrate how simple it is
to store the profile selection
for each user of a streaming app.
Finishing with recommendations
for the best approach for your own app.
In tvOS 16 we are making it easier
to have the entire family on Apple TV.
When you press and hold the TV button
on your Siri Remote,
Control Center shows up.
At the top is the list of users
that are on this Apple TV.
New in tvOS 16,
the list of users includes
iCloud Family members
that haven't been added yet,
making it easier than ever
to have the entire family on Apple TV.
Here, Anne isn't on the Apple TV yet.
The plus icon indicates a suggested user.
To have Anne join,
we can simply select the suggested user.
All Anne needs to do is bring their iPhone
to the same room as the Apple TV,
and on the iPhone confirm
the connection.
And that is all.
Anne has now access
to their data on Apple TV.
Now let's go back to Anne's iPhone
for a moment.
Let's take a look at Anne's
favorite video streaming app.
The app is used by the entire family
and each person has their own profile.
When the app first launches,
it presents a profile picker,
Anne picks her profile.
The app, running on a personal device,
can simply store the preferred profile
in NSUserDefaults,
or even put in CloudKit
to have it synced to all devices.
The iPhone of each member of the family
remembers
that person's preferred profile.
There is no need to keep asking
which profile to use when the app opens.
Apple TV is a device shared
by the entire family,
and we think it is really important
that everyone who uses Apple TV
is able to access
their own content and data.
In tvOS 14 we introduced the ability
for apps to run as the current user.
With a single checkbox to add
the "Runs as Current User" entitlement,
and no code changes at all,
apps can access each user's own data,
just like on iPhone.
Your iOS code, calling those APIs,
can run as is on Apple TV,
behaving like each person
is using their own personal Apple TV.
When the app launches,
tvOS takes care of everything.
Privacy and security,
all handled by the system.
The "runs as current user" entitlement
is perfect for games
and any apps that are all
about individual progress.
Media apps with profiles, though,
need a little bit more.
In my example so far,
I skipped an important part: the sign-in.
We believe signing in needs to be
as easy and infrequent as possible.
In tvOS 15 we introduced a feature
that allows people to use their iPhone
or iPad to seamlessly sign in
on your tvOS apps.
It is a first-class sign-in experience,
where the devices work together
to offer the most convenient way
to sign in on Apple TV.
Features not directly available
on Apple TV,
like your passwords in iCloud Keychain,
are just a tap away.
To learn how to build
great sign-in experiences,
watch "Simplify sign-in for
your tvOS apps" from WWDC 2021.
And this year
we're introducing support for OAuth
and passkeys on tvOS.
Passkeys are an awesome
new authentication technology
for replacing passwords
in your apps and websites.
To learn more about passkeys,
watch the "Meet Passkeys" video.
But ease and convenience isn't all.
It is still important
to have sign-in happen only once.
To achieve this optimal user experience,
with "Runs as Current User,"
we're introducing
a simple new API in tvOS 16.
It is a new constant in Keychain Services
that allows apps to access
a user-independent Keychain.
Items stored using this new key are always
accessible by all users on Apple TV.
Let's look at an example.
Here is a method that saves
an item in the Keychain,
with username and password.
To save the item
to the user-independent Keychain,
all you have to do is add a new key to the
attributes dictionary
that is passed to the function SecItemAdd.
We simply pass true as the value for
the key kSecUseUserIndependentKeychain.
With the user-independent Keychain set,
the items you read and write
will be visible to all users.
The combination of both
the new Keychain API
and "Runs as Current User" entitlement
allows your apps to have the best
of iPhone and the best of Apple TV:
simple per-user data separation
on a shared device
while maintaining
the single sign-in experience on Apple TV.
In tvOS 16 we've deprecated
the methods to manually map profiles
to system users in TVUserManager.
There is no need for you to maintain
a map of users to profiles anymore.
The system will handle it for you.
The same APIs you use on iOS can be used,
as is, on Apple TV.
It is so much easier.
Let me show you it all
in action with a demo.
I'll walk you through a sample app
that represents media apps with profiles.
This is my streaming video app.
Currently it doesn't use any
of the features I talked about.
It doesn't run as the current user,
and it doesn't use the new Keychain API.
I'll go ahead and sign in to show you.
After sign-in
I'm presented with a list of profiles.
The current user is Mei,
so I'll pick her profile.
Picking a profile shows the personalized
contents Mei wants to see.
Later, Anne sits on the couch to watch TV.
They open Control Center
by long pressing the TV button
on the Siri Remote.
Here at the top in Control Center
is the list of users.
The green checkmark indicates
the current user.
I'm going to switch to Anne now
and open the app.
As expected,
the app presents the profile picker again.
So Anne can select their profile.
But watch what happens
when switching back to Mei.
The app stays in Anne's profile.
It doesn't remember that Mei
had picked her preferred profile before.
With the new features in tvOS 16,
the user experience can be much better.
I want people using the app to not
have to select again who is watching.
Let's go to Xcode,
and I'll show you how easy it is.
Making my app executes
as the current user is simple.
All I have to do is add one capability
to my app's target.
Here in my app's target,
I'll go over
to the Signing & Capabilities tab.
Just under the tab, on the top left here,
I'll click the Add Capability button.
It opens the list of capabilities.
The one I'm interested in
is called User Management.
So I'll type "user" to filter the list.
Now I just double-click the capability
I want to add to my app.
Down here
the "Runs as Current User" checkbox
is selected by default.
That is exactly what I need.
With this entitlement, my app's process
will always be launched
as the currently selected user.
The system will make sure
that the data for each user is distinct.
All of it, including the Keychain.
But for my app,
having a distinct Keychain per user,
would have an unexpected side-effect.
It would require
each user to sign in separately.
In tvOS 16 we can maintain the experience
of having a single account for all users
while running as the current user.
By using the new Keychain API
to access the user-independent Keychain.
I'll go now to
my KeychainController class,
I use it to read
and write to the Keychain.
Here I have the property baseQuery
which has the keys I need
to access the credentials
for my app in the Keychain.
To update it to use the new
user-independent Keychain,
all I have to do
is add a new element to the dictionary.
I'll add the new
kSecUseUserIndependentKeychain,
and set it to true.
And that is all I need to change
to make the app share its credentials
with all users.
Nothing else.
It is important to note, though,
all other data is still distinct per user.
Like UserDefaults,
which I'm going to use
to remember the profile selection
for each user.
Now let's open my ProfileData class.
This file is shared
between my iOS and tvOS projects.
In fact, the iOS version of my app
already stores the profile selection
in UserDefaults,
but only when running on iOS.
And that is because
iPhones are personal devices.
But now that my app runs
as the current user,
Apple TV can be as personal.
I can remove the iOS-check and have
the code work the same way on Apple TV.
The system will make sure to use
the correct UserDefaults for each user.
When I run the new version of the app,
it is launched as the current user,
which is Mei.
Mei signs in and pick her profile.
With the app running as the current user,
it behaves like Apple TV is,
at that moment, a personal device.
Mei's device.
Mei's profile selection
gets stored in her UserDefaults.
When it's time for Anne to watch,
they switch to their user
using Control Center.
The system will put up
a switching user UI,
while it gives time to your process
to finish any last tasks
before it is relaunched.
tvOS now relaunches the app as Anne.
Now Apple TV is Anne's device.
The sign-in prompt is skipped,
because the credentials are stored
in the user-independent Keychain,
accessible by all users.
But Anne doesn't have a profile selection
stored in their UserDefaults yet,
and the profile picker is shown.
Picking Anne's profile,
saves the selection in their UserDefaults.
Okay now, at this point Mei and Anne
both have selected their profile.
When switching users,
the app won't show
any interstitial prompts anymore.
It will always go straight to the content,
automatically selecting
the correct profile for each person.
Every time.
That is how, in tvOS 16,
we've made it much easier
to remember each user's profiles.
A simple new API to access
the user-independent Keychain,
with the system handling
separating each user's data.
Now that you've seen how to remember
each user's profile selection
without requiring everyone
to sign in separately,
let's review how apps work on Apple TV.
Apps without the runs
as current user entitlement
use the resources of the Default User.
You can think of it as being
the Apple TV's own resources.
Switching users have no influence
on the app's process.
Here are my recommendations
for when you do want to personalize.
This table shows
the available capabilities
depending on which features
you use on your tvOS apps.
If your app is a media app,
or like one,
shows personalized content
through profiles;
while having a single account shared
between everyone using the Apple TV,
you adopt
the Runs as Current User entitlement
and use the new user-independent
Keychain API.
If, like a game,
your app is all about individual progress,
all you have to do is adopt
the Runs as Current User entitlement,
tvOS will handle the rest.
And for all other apps,
apps that present the same content
to all users–
like for example, a recipe app–
you don't have to do anything.
Just create a new tvOS app project
in Xcode.
To learn more about
running as the current user,
watch our session from WWDC 2020.
We believe a streamlined direct-to-content
experience is the best one for a tvOS app.
I hope all these features help you
implement
great big-screen experiences in your apps.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the conference.