♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
[CLICKING]
Hi, there!
I'm Paul, and I work
on the SF Symbols app.
Today, we're going to talk about
a brand-new feature of SF
Symbols: Variable Color.
We'll be going over how to bring
symbols with Variable Color
into your projects,
and how the SF Symbols app
can help you with every step
along the way.
First, we'll take a look
at Variable Color
in system-provided SF Symbols.
We'll go over how it works
and when to use it.
Then, we'll go over
how to bring Variable Color
into your own custom symbols.
Before we get started,
if this is your first time
using SF Symbols,
or if you just want a refresher,
I recommend you watch
last year's session,
"Explore the SF Symbols 3 app,"
to find out more about
how to find and organize
symbols for your projects.
And if you haven't yet,
check out Thalia's talk,
"What's new in SF Symbols 4,"
for an overview
of the visual design
of SF Symbols
and the different rendering
modes we'll be showing today.
Now, let's talk
about Variable Color.
Variable Color is a new feature
of SF Symbols that allows you
to affect the appearance of a
symbol using a percentage value.
By changing
this percentage value,
you can easily create symbols
that reflect values
that can change over time, like
signal strength or progress.
I think the best way to see
how Variable Color works
is to jump into
the SF Symbols app
and let the system
speak for itself.
This year
in the SF Symbols app,
we added a new preview area
here in the rendering inspector
that allows you to see a symbol
in every rendering mode
at a glance.
You can also click on
the different representations
to switch between
rendering modes.
There's also a new Automatic
option here in the picker.
This option allows each symbol
to choose its own
preferred rendering mode,
which you can see selected
in the preview area here.
For example, this
square.and.arrow.up symbol
prefers Monochrome,
while these iPhone symbols
prefer Hierarchical.
Below the color controls,
you'll find a new set
of controls for Variable Color.
And there's a new category
for symbols that support
Variable Color,
which is a great place
to start experimenting.
Let's select this speaker
symbol, switch to Multicolor,
and switch to the gallery view
to get a closer look.
I'll start by clicking
this button
to turn Variable Color on,
and pull the slider
all the way down to decrease
the percentage we're using.
You can see pieces
of the symbol dimming
as the percentage value
decreases.
And as I pull
the slider back up,
those pieces of the symbol
regain all of their color.
If you keep an eye
on the preview area,
you can see this happening
in all four rendering modes.
And if I switch
back to grid view,
you can see all of the symbols
in the Variable category
are reacting to the changes.
So what did we just learn
about Variable Color?
First off,
Variable Color can be used
with every single rendering mode
available for SF Symbols.
Every system symbol
that supports Variable Color
supports it in Monochrome,
Hierarchical, Palette,
and Multicolor modes.
Second, there are no rules
for how many parts of a symbol
can be affected
by Variable Color.
Some symbols only have
one layer that's affected;
some have dozens.
Regardless,
because Variable Color
is controlled using percentages,
you don't need
to worry about this.
Just pass in a percentage
and you're good to go.
So how does the system
interpret those percentages?
How do we know
when a particular layer
is going to have
Variable Color applied?
Well, like the rest
of SF Symbols,
we designed Variable Color
to make your apps
feel right at home
on Apple platforms.
And that means that we took
inspiration from the behavior
of system-level indicators
that you might be familiar with.
Let's look at this microphone
symbol as an example.
The four dots on the left side
of the microphone are each
in a separate layer that
participates in Variable Color.
So, each dot will activate
when the percentage value
crosses a certain threshold.
Those thresholds
are spaced out evenly
between zero and 100 percent.
Zero percent is a special case
where no layers will be active.
Any value
greater than zero percent
will activate the first dot.
At 26 percent and greater,
the second dot
will also be activated.
Fifty-one percent and greater
will activate the third dot.
And 76 up through 100 percent
will activate all four dots.
So, Variable Color symbols
will only appear
visually empty
at exactly zero percent.
You can see this behavior
in system-level indicators
like Wi-Fi strength
and battery level.
Variable Color symbols will
start appearing visually full
at a value
less than 100 percent.
You can see this behavior
in system-level indicators
like brightness and volume.
Now, this next symbol has three
layers that use Variable Color,
which means that the thresholds
between layers might fall
at awkward values like
33.3333 and 66.6667 percent.
We didn't want rounding errors
to make symbols appear in
unexpected ways, and we didn't
want you to have to worry about
how many significant digits
you typed into your code.
So, thresholds between layers
are rounded to the nearest
percentage point,
and we don't activate
the next layer
until you're one full percentage
point above that rounded value.
So, for the first threshold,
33.3 percent rounds down
to 33 percent,
so the second layer
activates one percentage point
higher at 34 percent.
The final threshold rounds from
66.7 percent up to 67 percent,
so the last layer activates
at one percentage point
higher than that, at 68 percent.
Of course,
system-provided symbols
are only one half of the story.
With the SF Symbols app,
you can make and annotate
your own custom symbols,
and even better,
you can make your custom
symbols just as flexible
and just as powerful as symbols
provided by the system.
What do I mean
by flexible and powerful?
Well, system-provided
SF Symbols are available
in nine different weights, and
each one of those nine weights
is available at three
different scales.
Each one of those
27 variants is available
in four rendering modes
with and without Variable Color.
That's 216 possible
configurations.
Luckily, that doesn't mean
that you need to draw
your custom symbols 216 times.
Last year, to streamline
the process of drawing symbols,
we introduced
variable templates.
When using
this kind of template,
instead of drawing 27 different
combinations of weights
and scales,
you only need to draw three,
and the system can generate the
other 24 for you automatically.
After you've drawn
your custom symbol,
you can adopt
different rendering modes
through a process
we call "annotation."
Last year, if you wanted
your symbol to adopt
the Hierarchical
and Palette rendering modes,
you broke your custom symbol
into different layers
and assigned each layer
a hierarchy level.
If you wanted
your symbol to adopt
the multicolor rendering mode,
you broke your custom symbol
into different layers again and
assigned a color to each layer.
This meant that, to support all
the available rendering modes,
you had to manage
two separate layer structures.
This year,
we're streamlining that workflow
with unified annotation.
Unified annotation uses
a single-layer structure
for a symbol,
and shares that structure
across all rendering modes.
So, instead of having to break
your symbol into layers
multiple times,
you only need to do it once.
You now also have control
over how your symbol will look
in Monochrome rendering mode,
in addition to the previous
control you had
over Hierarchical, Palette,
and Multicolor.
And of course,
unified annotation allows you
to add Variable Color
to your symbols.
So let's work on annotating
a custom symbol
to get to know
unified annotation.
Last year, I was working
on an app
so my family could play
card games together,
even when we couldn't be
in the same room.
A few months after that,
I discovered a new obsession:
puzzle cubes!
So this year,
I want to make an app
that's going to help me
practice solving mine.
I've got a custom
puzzle cube symbol
that I've made
here on my desktop.
I'll drag it into the app
to make a new custom symbol.
I based this symbol off of the
system-provided cube symbol,
and notice how I've left
some of the details
of the puzzle cube out.
This helps the symbol
come across clearly,
even at small sizes
and different weights.
Now, remember this preview area
from before?
It's especially handy when
annotating custom symbols.
As I make changes
to the annotation,
I can see how
my custom symbol looks
in all the different
rendering modes at a glance.
And when I switch
rendering modes by clicking here
or picking a different
option in the picker,
the annotation controls
in the list change accordingly.
Monochrome looks pretty good,
but let's add some depth
in Hierarchical mode.
I'll switch to that mode
and pull the top
and the side of the cube into new layers.
You can see
that these new layers
automatically get switched
to the less-prominent
secondary and tertiary levels.
This gives my symbol
a little bit more depth
and visual interest.
And remember
that the Hierarchical annotation
that we create is also used to
support Palette rendering mode.
So I've just gotten
two new rendering modes
for the price of one.
Now, let's switch over
to Multicolor mode
to give this symbol some color.
Notice that when I switch
to Multicolor mode,
I still see the same layers
that I separated out
in Hierarchical mode.
Remember,
in unified annotation,
changes made to the layer
structure in one rendering mode
will carry through
to all the others.
Let's make the front face red,
the top face blue,
and the side face yellow.
All right,
this looks pretty great.
But the most important part of
learning to solve a puzzle cube
is practice, practice,
and more practice.
So, I would love to use
my cube symbol as a timer,
and have it fill up with color
as I spend more time practicing.
The solution for that
is Variable Color.
These separate pieces
in the front face
look like a great place
to add some variable color
for our timer.
Let's separate out
each of these pieces
into a different layer.
Notice the order
that I'm arranging these
in the layer list.
The layers that I want to
fill in first go on the bottom,
and the layers I want
to fill in last go on top.
Then, we'll select all of these
layers and click on this button,
which will enable Variable Color
on all of them.
And that's it!
Let's move the Variable Color
slider around
to see what happens.
Remember to keep an eye
on the preview area
to see what's happening in all
the different rendering modes.
You can see that,
as we change the percentage
used in Variable Color,
the front face adjusts its color
in every rendering mode.
That's the power
of unified annotation.
Because edits
in one rendering mode
can carry through
to other rendering modes.
In many cases, you only need
to do work once or twice
to get great results
in all four rendering modes.
And in situations where
things are a bit trickier,
the SF Symbols app
still has you covered.
Let's look at a more
complicated symbol.
Here's my cube symbol again,
but this time,
it's set inside of a circle,
like many of the .circle.fill
symbols in the system library.
Now, I've already started
annotating this symbol.
You can see here
that I've separated the circle
and the parts of the cube
into different layers.
My symbol looks great
in Multicolor
and Hierarchical modes,
but in Monochrome,
there's not much contrast
between the cube
and the circle behind it.
When all the paths in
the symbol were in one layer,
the cube paths created
holes in the circle path,
which looked great
in Monochrome.
But now that I've moved
the circle onto its own layer,
the cube paths
no longer create holes.
Instead, they create a solid
cube on top of a solid circle.
So we can't see it very well.
Luckily, there's a new feature
of unified annotation
that can help us here.
We can choose Erase
to make a layer create a hole
in the layers behind it.
That's looking much better.
Now, let's add
Variable Color again.
This time, I'll just select all
of the pieces of the front face
and choose
Split into New Layers
from the contextual menu.
Then I'll use this button
to turn on Variable Color again.
And I'm done!
And by the way,
the paths are split up
using the order that they appear
in your symbol template,
so if you pay attention to the
order of your symbol's paths
as you're drawing,
you can save some time later.
So that is unified annotation
in a nutshell.
It's a fast and powerful way
to annotate your custom symbols.
You create one layer structure
that applies across
all rendering modes.
You can now control
the appearance of your symbol
in Monochrome rendering mode.
You can add Variable Color
to individual layers
in your symbol.
The z-order of the layers
determines the order
that they will fill in as the
passed-in percentage increases,
and the thresholds used
for each layer are spaced evenly
between zero and 100 percent.
And because it's part
of the layer structure,
when a layer opts in
to Variable Color,
this setting is shared
across all rendering modes.
And there are two new layer
options in unified annotation
that make it easier to work with
the new shared layer structure.
Setting a layer to Erase
will use that layer's shape
to erase layers behind it.
This is really useful in
situations like Monochrome
and Hierarchical symbols
that have badges with a plus,
a minus, or some other shape
inside of them.
And finally, setting a layer
to Hidden will exclude it
from a particular
rendering mode.
If you're in a situation where
a layer truly can't be used
across all the rendering modes,
you can use this option
to only apply that layer
to certain modes.
All of these new features
are supported
by a new template format, 4.0.
When you're exporting a symbol
from the SF Symbols app
to import into Xcode, make sure
that you export a 4.0 template
to control Monochrome rendering
and use Variable Color.
If you already
have custom symbols
that you annotated last year,
they will be automatically
updated to use
unified annotation.
Your Hierarchical and Multicolor
annotations will be brought in
with no extra work
required from you.
And, if you need to support
earlier platforms,
the previous 3.0 and 2.0 formats
are still available for use.
Before we wrap up, there's
one more thing I want to do.
I've had a lot of fun learning
about how to solve puzzle cubes,
but the best part so far
is that my daughter
saw me solving them
and wanted to learn too.
So naturally, I also want her
to be able to use my app
to help her practice.
Now, she's starting
kindergarten this fall,
so we're going to start
her off a little slower.
But this is where symbols
with Variable Color truly shine.
We could design
our timer UI like this.
Text and numbers are
descriptive and helpful,
but they could be intimidating
for someone like her
who's still learning
or is unable to read the text.
But seeing a puzzle cube
that looks just like the one
she's holding,
and seeing it fill up
with color as time passes,
is friendly and intuitive.
I don't even need
to change my timer code;
all I need to do is change
the name of the symbol I'm using
and keep passing in the same
percentage values I used
for my bigger cube symbol,
and SF Symbols
takes care of the rest.
And that's the power of symbols.
They allow us to convey
ideas in a way
that transcends
language and text.
They give us a way to make
our apps more inclusive.
And Variable Color in both
system-provided symbols
and your custom symbols gives us
even more expressive power
for concepts like progress,
signal strength, and time.
All of that
from three drawings
and one unified annotation.
That's pretty amazing.
And, I might add,
it's way easier
than solving a puzzle cube.
♪