♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello, I'm Donghao.
In this session, we are going
to learn more about how to build
great data visualizations
with Swift Charts.
In other words,
we will raise the bar
of what you can do
with charts in your apps.
A great data visualization
makes your app more informative
and more engaging.
In order to build
a great chart in our apps,
there are many things
to consider.
Of course, we would want
our charts to faithfully
communicate the underlying data
and be accessible for everyone.
But charts in an app
don't live in a vacuum.
They are part of the app's
user interface.
We have to support localization
and OS features like Dark Mode.
A chart has to have a proper
layout that fits seamlessly
into the rest of the UI;
it should support Dynamic Type
and device screen sizes.
We'll also want charts
to work in all platforms,
and have great animation
for the best look and feel.
Swift Charts takes care of
a lot of these basic features
for you automatically,
so you can focus more
on building the best charts to
communicate your unique data
and make it accessible
for everyone.
Swift Charts achieves
this by providing you
with a declarative syntax
that feels just like SwiftUI.
You specify what you want
in a chart
with a small amount of code,
and Swift Charts will
automatically produce
a great chart out of the box.
Swift Charts also provides
a rich set
of customization options,
so you can style the chart to
match your unique application.
This session is about giving you
a deeper understanding
of Swift Charts.
We will start by covering
the basic building blocks
of the declarative syntax:
marks and the composition
of marks.
Here are some examples where
we use charts in Apple products.
As you can see,
there is a wide variety of data,
chart types, and styles.
Instead of providing
a prebuilt component
for each type of chart,
Swift Charts is built
on the idea of creating charts
by composition.
It provides a small number
of basic building blocks
by combining them
in different ways,
you can create
a wide range of charts.
Let me show you how it works.
To do that,
I'll need an example.
All of my teammates
love pancakes,
so we are having an app
to track orders for a food truck
selling various
kinds of pancakes.
Here is a chart showing
the number of pancakes delivered
over the last 30 days,
broken down by style.
This is widely known
as a bar chart.
In Swift Charts, we consider
each of the six blue rectangles
a mark.
A mark is a graphical element
that represents data.
This is a bar mark
showing the number of cachapas
sold over the last 30 days.
In this chart
we have six bar marks,
each showing a pancake style
and the corresponding
sales number.
Let's see how
this is written in code.
Here we have a SwiftUI view that
includes a descriptive title
like "Most Sold Style, Cachapa,"
and an empty chart.
The chart type here
is the top-level view
that defines a single chart.
You can add a chart
in your SwiftUI application
just like adding any other view.
For the rest of the talk,
we'll focus on the chart part.
You can add marks to a chart.
Here we have a single
BarMark showing cachapa
and its sales number.
This makes a chart
with a single bar mark.
As shown in the screenshot,
the chart fits nicely
into the rest
of the user interface
and has a great default style.
For example, nicely rounded
numbers in the X-axis.
If you add another bar mark
with different name and sales,
you'll get a second bar.
You can repeat this
to add more bars.
In a real app,
we'll probably generate
these marks programmatically.
You can do so by providing
an array of structs or tuples
to the chart,
and use a ForEach
to create the bar marks with
the values from each element.
If ForEach is the only content
in the chart, like in this case,
you can also put data
in the chart directly.
Many SwiftUI modifiers
are available for marks.
For example, you could set
the color of the bars
with the .foregroundStyle
modifier.
Here we are setting it
to a named color,
which can be created
in Xcode as a named asset.
It's very important
that the chart is accessible
for everyone.
By default, the chart will be
exposed to VoiceOver users
with automatically generated
accessibility elements.
You can customize these
with the .accessibilityLabel
and .accessibilityValue
modifiers.
Here for example,
we set the label to the name
of the pancake,
and the value to the sales
with the suffix "sold."
As a result, we get a custom
experience for VoiceOver users.
VoiceOver: Cachapa, 916 sold.
Injera, 850 sold.
Crêpe, 802 sold.
Donghao: Our app also tracks
pancake deliveries
over the days.
Here, we have a view showing
the number of pancakes sold
in the last 30 days.
The chart gives a detailed view
of each individual day.
Let's see how
to make this chart.
Here, we have a data array
with day and sales.
The day is represented
by a Date value
at the start of the day.
We visualize the data
with bar marks,
where x shows day,
and the unit parameter here
means that the Date values
represent the duration
of a calendar day,
and y shows the sales
of the day.
As you see on the right,
we get a bar chart
showing sales over the days.
Bar chart is not the only way
to visualize this data.
Let's try a line chart.
The only change we have to make
is to replace BarMark
with LineMark.
With a declarative syntax,
it is very easy to switch
between chart types
in Swift Charts.
The previous chart shows
total sales over time.
But the food truck service has
been operating in two cities,
and we would love to compare
the sales between the two cities
on each weekday,
to help us decide where to go.
The lines in this chart show
the sales from Monday to Sunday.
Each line represents a city.
Let's see how this is built.
Now suppose we have
two cities' data
defined here
with an array of tuples,
each contains city name
and the sales of the weekdays.
Then, we can wrap
the line chart we had before
with a ForEach that loops
over the series data.
In order to differentiate
the two cities,
we use the
.foregroundStyle(by:) modifier
to style the two lines
by the city name.
As you can see, Swift Charts
automatically picks two colors
for the two cities,
color the lines,
and then add a legend to
indicate what each color means.
The default colors are chosen
to be system colors
that are easy to differentiate.
To make the chart
easier to read
for people with color blindness,
we can add symbols to the lines
to further differentiate them.
This can be done by adding
the .symbol(by:) modifier
with city as the data.
Finally, to make the lines
look smoother,
we can use a curve
as the interpolation method
for the lines.
Even with the two series
line chart,
we can still go back to bar mark
and see how it looks like.
Changing the mark
type to BarMark,
and remove the modifiers
that aren't relevant to bars,
we get a stacked bar chart.
The bars are
automatically stacked
because we now have
two bars for each month.
While the stacked bar chart
is great for showing
the total sales value
for the two cities,
it's not very good for comparing
between the two cities.
To make it easier to compare,
we can turn this
into a grouped bar chart with
the .position(by:) modifier.
So far, we've seen
bar marks and line marks.
Swift Charts supports a couple
of other mark types
including point mark, area mark,
rule mark, and rectangle mark.
You can combine these marks
to build more complex charts.
Let's see an example.
Let's start with a line chart
showing the average daily sales
for each month.
While the average is useful,
we also want to see the minimum
and maximum daily sales
to get an idea
of the more extreme values.
Let's start by adding
these values to the data.
We introduce daily min
and daily max to each element
in the data array.
We can then visualize the min
and the max with an area mark,
where x is showing month,
and y starts at the daily min,
and ends at the daily max.
This way, we have a chart
showing daily average values
with a line,
and daily min and max values
with the area around the line.
A line plus area
isn't the only way
to visualize this kind of data.
You can easily switch
to other mark types
to explore more design options.
For example,
here we are using a BarMark.
However, the line doesn't seem
to fit very well with the bars.
Let's change the line mark
to a RectangleMark,
with a height of two points.
This way, the rectangle mark
creates horizontal lines
inside the bars
showing the average value.
You can also adjust
the width of these marks.
Here, for example,
we are setting width
to be with a ratio of .6
This means the width
of the bars and rectangles
will be 60 percent
of the width of a whole month,
as you can see
in the screenshot.
Finally, we'd like
to have an option
to show the average daily sales
among all the months.
To do so, we first set
the foreground style
to a fade gray color
to deemphasize them.
Then, we add a rule mark
outside the ForEach,
with y showing
the average value.
This adds a horizontal rule.
To make it clear that the rule
is showing the yearly average,
we can add
an annotation to the rule
using the .annotation modifier.
This adds a text label
at the top of the rule mark,
with leading alignment.
We've discussed
a couple of examples
of building charts
by composition.
There are many different ways
to use and combine
these basic marks.
Like a box plot, multi-series
line chart, population pyramid,
range plot, stream graph,
multi-series scatter plot,
heat map, or even a plot
of a vector field.
These are just some examples
of the wide variety of charts
you can build with Swift Charts.
Let's dive into the next topic.
Plotting data
with mark properties.
Swift Charts support
three major types or data:
quantitative,
nominal, and temporal.
Quantitative data
is a numerical value,
such as the number
of products sold,
the temperature of a room,
or the price of a stock.
Swift Charts treats
Swift numerical types such as
Int, Float, and Double
as quantitative data.
Nominal data,
or categorical data,
represent discrete
categories or groups.
For example,
the name of a person,
a continent,
or the type of a product.
You can use a string
or a custom string-valued enum
as nominal data.
Temporal data represents
a point or interval in time.
For example, the duration
of a particular day,
or the exact time
of a transaction.
Swift Charts treats
"Date" as temporal data.
A chart works
by transforming abstract data,
like sales value,
into the properties of marks.
Let's take a look at BarMark,
which can plot data with X, Y,
and Foreground Style properties.
In this example, we plot sales
value, which is quantitative,
with the x property,
and name, which is nominal,
with the y property.
The resulting chart
consists of horizontal bars,
each showing Sales on X,
and Name on Y.
If we swap Name and Sales,
such that Name is on X
and Sales is on Y, we get
a vertical bar chart instead.
As you can see,
the BarMark's behavior
depends on the data type plotted
with its X and Y properties.
The orientation of the bar
depends on where
the quantitative property is.
Now, let's look at another chart
with all three properties
used to plot data.
Here we plot Weekday,
which is temporal, with X,
Sales with Y,
and City with Foreground Style.
The resulting chart
is a stacked bar chart,
where X-axis shows Weekday,
Y-axis shows Sales,
and the bars
are colored by city.
Swift Charts has six mark types,
and six mark properties
that you can plot data with.
Remember that data
can be of the three kinds,
so there is a vast array
of possible combinations.
This is what allows Swift Charts
to support a wide range
of chart designs with a small
number of basic building blocks.
When you plot data
with a mark property,
for example, sales with Y,
Swift Charts creates a mapping
that transforms
the abstract data
into a proper value
of the property.
In this case,
it will transform Sales value
to Y coordinates
in screen space.
We use the term "scale"
to refer to the mapping
from abstract data, like sales,
to mark property,
like Y position.
You can think of Scale
as a function
that takes data value
and returns a property value.
For example, here is a yScale
function that takes sales
and returns the Y position
of the bar.
The name "scale"
comes from the fact
that for position properties,
we often scale the input value
by some factor to convert it to
a reasonable screen coordinate.
When you plot data
with mark properties,
a scale is created
to transform the data
into the corresponding
mark property.
For example, in this chart
we have three scales,
each transforming
Weekday to X, Sales to Y,
and City to Foreground Style,
respectively.
By default, Swift Charts infers
the scales automatically
from the data, so you get
a nice chart out of the box.
You can use the scale modifiers
to configure the scales
in a chart.
Let's take a look
at a few examples.
In this example,
the Y scale is automatically
inferred to be zero to 150.
However,
we'd like to fix the Y scale
so that no matter what
the current sales looks like,
we always have
a consistent Y scale.
Let's change it
such that the Y scale
always starts at zero
and ends at 200.
To do so, we can use
the .chartYScale modifier,
and set the domain
of the scale to be zero to 200.
Now, as you can see,
the axis goes from zero to 200.
Similarly, we can change
how the two cities
map to foreground style using
the .chartForegroundStyleScale
modifier.
Now we have new colors
for the two cities.
Now we know
how to compose marks
and plot data
with mark properties.
Let's dive into more
customization options
that Swift Charts provides.
A chart consists of axes,
possibly a legend,
and a plot area.
Axes and legends
help us interpret the chart.
The plot area is the area
between the two axes.
This is where we
plot data with marks.
All of these elements are
customizable in Swift Charts.
Let's first see a few examples
on how to customize
axes and legends.
Here is a chart showing
total monthly sales.
Without customization,
Swift Charts generates
a default axis that features
nicely rounded values.
Right now, the X-axis shows
a label for every quarter.
Let's change it to show
a label every month,
and use a single-letter
month label.
We'll start by adding
a .chartXAxis modifier
to customize the X-axis,
with AxisMarks as the content.
AxisMarks with no parameter
recreates the default axis.
Let's start by changing
the axis values.
Since we want to have
regular calendar intervals,
we can use stride(by:),
similar to the stride function
from the standard library.
Now we have a label
for each month.
However, the default labels
feel too crowded,
as you see in the screenshot.
Some labels get truncated
because we don't have
enough space for them.
Let's change the labels
to use a single-letter format.
To do so, let's build up
the axis marks
from the individual components,
including AxisGridLine,
AxisTick, and AxisValueLabel.
Let's set the format of the
label to use narrow month names.
Now we have one letter
for each month.
The value parameter passed
into the result builder
provides information
about the current axis value.
You can use this
to conditionally determine
the existence and style
of axis marks.
For example, here we have
a condition that tests
whether the value as a date
is the first quarter of a month.
If yes, we can highlight
the first month of each quarter
with a different
foreground style.
If not, we only display
a grid line,
without tick and label.
Since we are now
showing quarters,
we can change the format
to quarter style.
With the customizations
we just did,
we get a more unique
X-axis showing quarter data,
with subgrid lines
showing every month.
In addition to values,
axis marks have other properties
that allows you
to configure the general
appearance and style.
Suppose we'd like
to have the Y-axis appear
at the leading edge of the chart
instead of the default
trailing edge,
we can set the position
parameter to leading
to move them
to the leading edge.
Swift Charts provides a default
preset for the axis marks
based on the axis and the type
of data being visualized.
You can override the default
using the preset parameter.
For example, here we are using
the .extended preset
for the Y-axis to help
with visual alignment
with the rest
of the user interface.
In some charts, you may not
want the axis to be visible.
For example, the purpose
of the top sales chart here
is to give people
a brief overview,
so the axes aren't
really necessary.
You can pass in .hidden
to the chart axis modifiers
to hide an axis.
Legend configuration
is similar to axis.
For example,
in this chart that highlights
the best day and location,
we already use opacity
to highlight the best city,
so we can hide the
automatically generated legend.
To do so, we can add
the .chartLegend modifier
with .hidden as parameter.
Now let's talk
about the plot area.
You can use
the .chartPlotStyle modifier
to configure
the plot area of a chart.
In the trailing closure,
we will write a function
that takes original plot area,
and returns
a modified plot area.
Let's see a few examples.
In some cases,
we might want the plot area
to have an exact size
or aspect ratio.
For example, in this case,
we want the plot area's height
to be driven by the number
of categories in the chart.
To achieve this, we can apply
a .frame modifier
to the plot area, and return
the modified plot area.
This will set the height
of the plot area.
We can also use modifiers to
achieve a special visual effect.
For example,
in this Dark Mode chart,
we use the .background modifier
to add a pink background
with opacity of .2 to make the
chart stand out a little bit.
And then add a 1-pt border
with the same pink color.
This creates a unique
visual effect for the chart.
Earlier in the session
we mentioned scales,
which are functions
that map data values
to mark properties
such as X and Y.
Swift Charts provides
a ChartProxy that allows you
to access the X and Y scales
in a chart.
You can use the ChartProxy's
position(for:) method
to get the position
for a given data value,
or use the value(at:) method
to get the data value
at a given position.
This allows you to coordinate
other views with the chart.
Let's look at an example.
We are going to build
this interactive brushing view.
Here you can select
an interval from the chart
with a drag gesture,
and that interval
will then be used to filter
the rows in the details view.
We can get a chart proxy
object from the .chartOverlay
or .chartBackground modifiers.
These two modifiers
are similar to SwiftUI's overlay
and background modifiers,
but they provide you
with a chart proxy.
To build this example,
we'll start by defining
the base chart just like before.
We then add
a .chartOverlay modifier
that provides us
with the chart proxy.
Inside, we have a geometry
reader that gives us access
to the geometry
of the overlay view.
Then, we have a Rectangle view
that is configured to respond
to SwiftUI's DragGesture.
When the drag gesture happens,
we first find the x coordinates
of the start
and the current locations
inside the chart's plot area.
This is done by subtracting
the plot area's origin
from the locations
provided by the gestures.
Once we have these coordinates,
we can then use the chart proxy
to find the corresponding
Date values,
and finally set it
to a SwiftUI state
that keeps track of
the current date interval.
With the range state, we can
then define a rectangle mark
in the chart to visualize the
currently selected date range.
This state can also be used
to control other parts
of your application
for example,
to filter the contents
of the details view
below the chart.
This is a simple example
to illustrate how
chart proxy works.
You can use it to build
many interesting features,
for example,
this interactive chart
that shows the selected day
and sales value
with an overlay
that looks like a lollipop.
In this session,
we have discussed
how to create charts
by composing marks;
how to plot data
with mark properties,
and how to customize a chart.
You can go to the design
sessions to learn more
about how to design great
app experiences with charts
and how to design
an effective chart.
We think you will love
building data visualizations
with Swift Charts.
Thanks for watching.
♪