♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, welcome to
our session on iPad App design.
I'm Bryant Jow.
And I'm Grant Paul,
and we're from
the Apple Design Team.
Bryant: Today, we'll show you
some of the new UIKit
and SwiftUI updates
in iPadOS 16,
as well as some general tips
for incorporating these
into your app designs.
With iPadOS 16,
people can take advantage
of larger resolutions
with extended display support
and display zoom
and work with their apps
in a single view
by using Stage Manager.
So what does this mean
for iPad apps?
Your app design should always
embrace larger screens
and different window sizes,
as well as support all
the different inputs of iPadOS.
And now, your iPad apps
should consider
how to lean into
more advanced use cases
that come with using iPad
like a desktop.
So that's why we're introducing
a number of improvements
to help apps become
more powerful and easier to use.
Here's a preview
of the features we'll cover:
toolbars and customization,
document menu,
editing menus,
find and replace,
navigation,
search,
tables,
and selection.
Today, we're going
to show examples
of how you can
incorporate these updates
in designing two kinds
of experiences:
document editing
and content browsing.
We'll start with
document editing
and look at how these
improvements can help people
be more productive
when using your app.
Let's jump into toolbars.
Toolbars are a really important
component in app design
because they organize
your app's functionality,
and this impacts how easy it is
for people to go about
their workflows.
Here's the previous toolbar
in the Pages app in iPadOS 15.
In iPadOS 16, we're introducing
a new toolbar layout
that aligns titles
to the left side
and allows apps to offer more
toolbar items in the center.
Let's take a closer look.
Here's the leading section
of the toolbar.
It should contain items
that help people navigate within
and outside of the document,
like the back and sidebar
buttons.
And it displays the new
document title and menu,
which I'll come back to later.
With more space in the toolbar,
apps can elevate commonly used
actions in the center.
In iPadOS 16,
the Pages app shows actions
for inserting content.
You should consider
what are the most common
workflows in your app
where people could benefit
from one-tap access.
But be careful not
to pack your app's toolbar
with too many items.
Let's look at a couple more
tools to consider
if your app
has a lot of functionality.
In iPadOS 16, you can
enable customizable toolbars
so people can curate the items
that are most important
for their workflow.
If your app has
a lot of toolbar items
or advanced features
that not all people need,
you should consider
enabling customization.
Note how items
in the center section
can be added, removed,
or rearranged.
Items outside of this section
are not customizable
because these may include
navigation buttons
or important features that need
to be always accessible.
Toolbar items can also be
grouped or collapsed.
Use groups
to keep related actions together
in the toolbar
or the overflow menu.
In the Pages app,
similar actions
like inserting tables, charts,
shapes, and photos
are grouped together.
When there's not enough room
in the toolbar,
these actions collapse
into a plus button.
You can also
make wide toolbar items
collapse into a compact glyph
at smaller window sizes.
Now, let's take a look at the
trailing section of the toolbar.
This section may contain
a variety of items:
any button that invokes
nearby inspectors,
important items that should stay
visible at any window size,
and an optional overflow button
for people to access
hidden items
as well as toolbar
customization.
When people resize your app,
the toolbar items in the center
will automatically hide
into an overflow menu
when there's not enough room.
And when the window
is resized even smaller,
only the leading and trailing
sections remain.
So make sure to arrange
important items
in the trailing section
if you want them to be visible
at most window sizes.
So here's a quick recap
of toolbars.
Consider if there are
common workflows
that you can elevate
in the toolbar.
Arrange important toolbar items
in the trailing section
to avoid overflow
in smaller window sizes.
Enable customization if your app
has many toolbar items
and advanced use cases.
And wherever possible,
try to organize similar items
into groups.
Now let's take a look
at the new document menu
that we mentioned earlier.
To make it easier for people
to find document-related actions
in one place across apps,
we're introducing a new title
and menu in the toolbar.
This layout is intended for
document viewers like Quick Look
or document-editing apps
like Keynote.
Note, these apps may also
have a browser view,
which can appear
as a back button
near the document title.
If your app is primarily used
for editing or viewing
documents,
you should consider
using this new menu.
Let's open Keynote's
document menu
by clicking the title.
Here, you can see
there is a combined set
of standard document actions
as well as app-specific ones.
So, what should go inside here?
The menu should contain actions
that affect the document
as a whole.
Here are some examples
of standard actions
that should go inside
the document menu:
Duplicate, Rename, Move,
Export, and Print.
You can also add custom actions
for your app.
But not everything should go
inside in the document menu.
Actions that take content
outside of your app
should be placed under Share,
and actions that directly affect
content inside a document
should support
toolbar customization
and appear in edit menus
where appropriate.
Next, I want to talk about
a couple of features
that can help users work more
efficiently in your iPad app.
Let's look at edit menus.
These menus may appear
over selected text
and contain edit options
such as Copy and Paste.
In iPadOS 16,
edit menus have a new look
and are optimized
for touch and pointer.
When using touch,
the menu appears horizontally
and people can now scroll
back and forth
between the list of options
like this.
When using pointer,
the edit menu
shows a more comprehensive
list of options
in a vertical layout like this.
Your app should support
both styles
for touch and pointer
interactions.
When you incorporate
these edit menus into your app,
here are a couple of things
to remember.
Don't remove
the standard actions
like Cut, Copy, and Paste.
These editing tools are
important to many workflows
and should be always available.
And you should organize
custom actions
close to related system actions.
In iPadOS 16, the Notes app
groups formatting options
for checklists and text
in the same section.
Edit menus are not just limited
to text fields.
They can also apply to objects
on a document canvas.
Here's an example of selecting
layers in Keynote with touch.
And that same menu
when using pointer.
Try to integrate these menus
into any editable content
so that people can be more
productive when using your app.
So that's edit menus.
Now, let's dive into
find and replace.
In iPadOS 16, we're introducing
find and replace
into the system keyboard
so people can quickly search
for specific words, phrases,
and more within a document.
This also supports
advanced use cases
like matching specific parts
of a phrase
or replacing all matches
with a different word.
And when iPad is attached
to a hardware keyboard,
the find and replace interface
sits above the app
in this compact appearance.
To make find and replace
easy to access,
consider adding an item
inside the overflow menu
as well as the system keyboard
shortcuts.
So those are some
of the new features
we're introducing
for document editing.
Now I'm going to hand it off
to Grant Paul,
who will talk about
some more improvements.
Grant: Thanks, Bryant.
Next up, I'm going to talk about
improvements
for content browsing,
something that you do
in a lot of different iPad apps.
Content browsing experiences
are everywhere on iPad,
whether you're managing
in your photo library in Photos,
browsing Apple Music,
or choosing a document in Pages.
iPadOS 16 has
some great new features
and patterns
for content browsing.
I'm going to focus
on three areas
that are important
to this part of an app.
The first one is some updates
to app navigation.
iPadOS 16 has
a new style of navigation
that we call "browser-style"
navigation.
For example, the Files app
uses back and forward buttons
to let you easily
browse between folders
that might have come from
different places in the sidebar.
With browser-style navigation,
it's up to your app
to choose the buttons
that go to the left
of the title.
You should make sure to keep to
just those navigational buttons
like back and forward,
or maybe a sidebar button.
Browser-style navigation
works well
when your app
has a complex hierarchy
where people are often jumping
between different levels;
things like a file browser
or a web browser.
If your app has a shallow
or flat hierarchy, like Photos,
you might not need
browser-style navigation
because all of the destinations
in the app are already available
with a single tap
in the sidebar.
If you do use browser-style
navigation,
it goes great with another
new feature in iPadOS 16:
putting search in the top right
of the navigation bar.
Search in the top right
is great when your search bar
is used to filter the content
that you're looking at below
on the same screen.
And even though
it's in the navigation bar,
it supports suggestions.
Suggestions show up right off
the field as you're typing.
Your app can suggest
recent searches.
It can also suggest
recommendations
for what to search for.
And it can suggest filters
to narrow down your search.
Again, search in the top right
is meant for searching
the content
that's showing below.
If you want to search
your entire app at once,
it's better to keep that
in a search tab
so that people can get to search
from wherever they are
in your app.
That's what's new
for navigation.
Next up, I want to talk about
selection and menus.
iPadOS 15 introduced
band selection,
using the pointer to quickly
select multiple notes at once.
But you still have to use the
toolbar to act on the selection
and to leave edit mode
when you're done.
iPadOS 16 makes that
much easier.
If you use band selection,
iPadOS no longer enters
editing mode automatically.
You can now use
keyboard modifiers
like Command and Shift
to select and deselect,
also without going into
editing mode.
And once you have
the notes selected,
it's just a secondary click
to act on all of them together.
With touch, you can long press
to get a context menu
for those same actions.
And these interactions
work just as well with a list.
You can hold Command
to select multiple notes,
use drag-and-drop
to move them into a folder,
and bring up a context menu
to act on multiple notes
together.
Along with these
multi-item context menus,
iPadOS 16 also supports
context menus in empty areas,
which you can use
to create something new.
For example, you can make
a new folder in Files.
Or, you can paste
a copied event in Calendar.
OK. That's a lot of things
to keep in mind for selection.
Let's go through the checklist.
Your app should support
keyboard focus
to navigate around using
the arrow keys and with tab.
Support band selection
to quickly select
multiple items in a grid
by using the pointer.
Allow multiple selection
without entering editing mode
when using the pointer
or the keyboard.
Add context menus to act
on multiple selected items
together.
And in the empty area,
use a context menu
to create new items.
The next thing I want
to talk about is submenus.
On iPhone,
submenus open vertically.
Since space is limited
and they're an extra tap away,
it's best to use submenus
on iPhone
only when you really need one.
But on iPadOS 16,
submenus open horizontally
when they have space available.
This makes them much faster,
especially with a pointer.
For example,
Calendar uses a submenu
to really quickly move an event
into a different calendar.
And Reminders uses submenus
to quickly change the due date
and the priority.
So on iPad,
you should consider
including submenus
in your app's context menus
to make quick changes
just like these.
Along with submenus, iPadOS 16
also adds a new control
for pop-up buttons in lists.
Just like any other
pop-up button,
these show a menu
to let you choose an option.
Let's look at these in practice.
In the past,
editing a reminder's priority
meant pushing
into the detail view,
then popping back out.
It's a bunch of taps, and it
also took you out of context.
In iPadOS 16, you change
the priority right in place.
It's much faster, and you stay
right where you are.
So as you've seen here,
the main use for these
pop-up buttons in lists
is to replace navigation pushes
in popovers and in modals.
When you're using
a pop-up button,
choose places where you have
a well-defined set of options
to pick from.
Make sure to only
use a pop-up button
if your options really do
fit nicely into a menu.
If your option is better
as a switch, use a switch.
And if the options
really need more controls,
don't try and force it.
But if you only sometimes
need more controls,
a good choice can be to add
a Custom option into the menu.
When someone chooses Custom,
your app can reveal
the extra controls
without getting in the way
of the other choices.
And if your options
need an explanation,
you can put that underneath
the pop-up button in the list.
All right. That's what's new
for selection and menus.
Lastly, I want to talk about
tables.
Tables are a great new component
in iPadOS 16
to make your lists of content
more powerful.
Now, in the past, you may have
used a control called a table.
But that wasn't quite right;
it's not much of a table
if it only has a single column.
iPadOS 16 has a real table.
Tables in SwiftUI show
multiple columns of information.
And they let you sort
just by tapping a header.
Now, since iPad screens
are relatively small,
you'll only be able to show
the most important columns.
But you can swap
those columns out,
like replacing Size with Kind,
just by choosing
a different sort option.
And as makes sense
for something that's all about
having powerful access
to your content,
sortable tables also support
all of the selection features
I talked about earlier.
So tables are
a really powerful control,
but it's important
to use them correctly.
These tables built into iOS 16
are built to show
more information
about a list of content,
not to show
a spreadsheet of data.
You can think of them
as an extended version
of the list views that you
already have in your app.
In fact, when you resize an app
to a compact width,
tables will switch back
into being single-column lists.
And when they do,
we recommend
taking those details
from the secondary columns
and moving that information
into a secondary line of text
within each row
so all of that information
is still available.
And for sorting,
you can use a toolbar button
to quickly reveal
the sort options.
So those are the new components
and features in iPadOS 16.
Let's go back to Bryant
to recap everything
we talked about today.
Bryant: Thanks, Grant.
A lot of the features
we covered today
are aimed around helping users
be more productive with iPad.
As you think about how
these relate to your iPad app,
consider how you can
make your app more powerful
by offering more functionality,
better organization,
and make common editing and
browsing tasks more efficient.
Evaluate your app design
in resizable windows
and larger screens.
And ensure your app
works seamlessly
with touch and pointer.
Grant: And if you want
an overview
of what goes into designing
a great iPad app,
you should make sure
to check out our previous talk,
"Designed for iPad."
Bryant: Thanks for watching.
♪