[spacey music]
Yann Ly-Gagnon: Hi.
my name is Yann.
I'm a core Bluetooth engineer.
Today, I want to talk to you
about timely alerts
for your Bluetooth devices on Apple Watch.
First, we will review how to update
a complication
while your watchOS App
is in the background.
Then, we will dive into how to listen
for timely alerts on your watchOS App.
We will also see new ways
you can discover peripherals
on watchOS 9.
Finally, we will provide best practices
and recommendations
to help you design
your Bluetooth accessory.
Let's jump into our first topic:
how to update a complication
in the background for your watchOS App.
Last year, in watchOS 8,
we introduced a way
to update complications
with your Bluetooth accessory
during Background app refresh.
This is great for data
that can be updated periodically,
like in this example showing me
the current air temperature.
As a quick refresher, last year watchOS
allows you to update your complication
and use Background app refresh,
which runs periodically in the background.
Whenever Background app refresh happens,
it allows your app to reconnect
to your Bluetooth peripheral,
retrieves data,
and then disconnects from your peripheral.
For more details about this,
watch the video called
"Connect Bluetooth devices
to Apple Watch."
But what if a time-sensitive event
happens on your Bluetooth peripheral
that the user wants to know about?
In watchOS 9,
we are introducing a way to listen
for alerts from your Bluetooth
accessories in the background.
Here's how it works.
You will connect your device
when your app is running,
and start monitoring a characteristic.
When your app stops running,
Core Bluetooth maintains the connection
to your device on your behalf,
and continues
listening
for changes to your characteristic.
When your device changes
the value of that characteristic,
your app will get runtime
to process that event.
You could post a local notification
or send a network request, for example.
This is intended to provide users
with time-sensitive information
they care about.
Let's say I have a food thermometer.
I can set a desired cook temperature
to get alerted
when I should remove my food
from the oven.
As the temperature approaches
the desired temperature,
the thermometer changes
a characteristic's value,
and the app posts a local notification
that the food is almost ready.
When the food is done,
I receive the desired notification.
And if the temperature keeps rising,
I get one final notification.
First, let's review how
to configure the Background modes.
Add Bluetooth-central to UIBackgroundModes
in your Watch app's Info.plist.
In Xcode it's called
"Required background modes,"
and you should add
"App communicates using CoreBluetooth."
Note that those Info.plist entries
are the same as your app has for iOS
if you want to use
background execution as a central.
You will need to edit
your watchApp info.plist manually
and not rely on the iOS
"Signing capabilities."
Let's look at the code.
Assuming you're already connected,
you found a GATT service
and just discovered a GATT characteristic.
You will get
the didDiscoverCharacteristicFor callback.
Inside the callback,
you can decide to get notifications
every time the value changes.
This is the same API as in watchOS 8,
with the difference that it will also work
while your app is in the background.
Then implement the delegate method
to handle changes
to the characteristic's value
with didUpdateValueFor.
Once the characteristic changes,
you can post a local notification here,
send a network request,
or whatever makes sense for your app.
This method will be called both
in the foreground and in the background,
so make sure you perform
the correct action in both cases.
Now, let's talk about some situations
you need to consider.
First, on the topic
of Bluetooth reconnections.
If your device goes out of range,
the Bluetooth connection
will disconnect after a timeout.
If this happens, your app
will briefly get background runtime
to call "connectPeripheral"
in order to attempt reconnection.
This is the same as what happens on iOS.
As soon as the device is in range again,
Core Bluetooth will reconnect to it.
Now, let's talk about some limits.
These limits are important
to maintain optimal battery life
for Apple Watch users.
If your device is on the edge
of Bluetooth range
and repeatedly disconnects
while in Background BLE connection,
the reconnection range will be reduced.
This means only devices close
to the Apple Watch will reconnect.
Those limits are counted
on a rolling window of 24 hours
and are reset whenever
the user interacts on your App.
Another limitation is regarding the number
of background runtime opportunities
for timely alerts.
Only monitor characteristics
that will change
when something critical to the user
happens.
If you need to gather
periodical data from your device,
this should be done
with Background app refresh.
When your app is about to exceed
the limit, the notification
LeGattNearBackgroundNotificationLimit
will be posted.
It is a good practice for your app
to monitor that error
and realize that the user
isn't interacting with the watchOS app.
If this alert is important,
it might be the right time
to find another way to communicate
with your user,
such as through a network request
or UI changes
on your Bluetooth peripheral.
After the limit is exceeded,
the notification called
LeGattExceededBackgroundNotificationLimit
will be posted.
After this point, your app
will no longer receive background runtime
and will revert back to watchOS 8 behavior,
where there will be
no background connection
and only background app refresh.
You can retrieve those two notifications
in the error field
of the GATT Notification Update.
For background BLE connection,
we recommend using the error
to know when the limit is reached
instead of counting down.
For watchOS 9,
the background runtime limit is set to 5.
Both of these limits are reset
whenever the user interacts with your app.
They also reset 24 hours
after the limit was reached
in case there has been no user interaction
with your app.
Note: These limits only apply
to Bluetooth Background LE connections.
Background app refresh will continue
to happen if your complication
is on the active watch face,
regardless of these limits.
The amount of time you get
to process each event is very short.
There may not be enough time
to do extremely complex processing,
but enough to alert the user
something important is happening.
Finally, listening for timely alerts
in the background
requires Apple Watch Series 6 or later.
Listening for alerts isn't the only thing
you can do in the background.
In watchOS 9, you can discover peripherals
while your app is in the background.
Let's say
I have a Bluetooth medical device
and a watchOS app that detects
any timely alerts from it.
To conserve power,
the peripheral doesn't advertise
until it detects a serious condition.
Therefore, there's no connection
between the device and Apple Watch yet.
Here, the watchOS App will scan
for a unique Service UUID
from the medical device.
Now, when the medical device detects
something is serious,
it starts advertising.
The Apple Watch discovers this peripheral
and launches the app in the background.
The app can then alert
the user of the condition detected.
Here's how it works:
The Watch app will initiate
a scan for peripherals,
and Core Bluetooth will continue
scanning in the background.
Once the peripheral's
advertisement is detected,
the app is given background runtime
and can initiate a connection.
Let's dive into the code
to make this happen.
The API hasn't changed from watchOS 8,
but the scan will be honored
even the app is in the background.
Call "scanForPeripherals"
with the service UUID
you want to watch for.
You can do this while your app
is in foreground, and it will continue
while the app is in the background.
Note that if you ask for the option
"allowDuplicatesKey,"
it will only be available
when the app is in foreground.
Now, let's talk about some limits.
There is a limit on the number
of times your app will be given
background runtime between app launches.
This limit is combined
with the background runtime
we saw previously
when a GATT characteristic changes.
Also, scanning for peripherals
in the background
requires Apple Watch Series 6 or later.
In summary, we can now scan
for a limited number
of Bluetooth service UUID while
the watch is scanning in the background.
Now let's talk about how to design
your accessory
to make the most of these features.
There is a power tradeoff
you need to consider
when designing
your Bluetooth accessory.
If power consumption is a concern,
you should opt for a topology
where your device can go into deep sleep
and only advertise relevant information
when an alert happens.
The tradeoff is, you will have extra
latency with the Bluetooth discovery time
at every timely alerts,
but you will be able to save more power.
This is the topology provided
in the example with the medical device.
On the other hand,
if you need low latency
for your timely alerts,
but the power is not so much a concern,
you can consider using
Background LE connection
and send your alerts
with GATT indications.
Note that there is a limit
of two Bluetooth connections for each app.
This is the topology we saw in the example
for temperature sensor.
In order for your users to have
the best experience with timely alerts,
consider adding as much processing
and intelligence on your peripheral
to filter the data that is time critical
versus non-time critical.
Coming back to our temperature example,
instead of transmitting every temperature,
you can send only the relevant events
or when the temperature changes.
The benefit of this approach is,
if you properly separate
the time-critical events
from periodic data,
both your peripheral
and the Apple Watch user
will save on power,
thus an overall better experience.
When your device disconnects,
we recommend advertising
to re-establish the connection.
The advertisement interval depends
on the requirement
of your Bluetooth peripheral,
such as how fast it needs to reconnect,
battery life, et cetera.
In the accessory guidelines, we offer
a few different values you can use.
For example,
if your device is battery constrained,
you can use a value
of 1022.5 milliseconds.
Another example: if you advertise
at a rate of 20 milliseconds,
it should allow for a detection
within a second in ideal conditions.
You could design such that
this high advertisement rate can be used
only while a critical event happens.
Now let's talk about connection interval.
If you opt for a topology where your device
remains connected in the background,
we highly recommend using
a long connection interval,
such as at least 150 milliseconds.
This will allow to save battery
on your peripheral
and provides best user experience
on Apple Watch.
Bluetooth 5.3 is coming to Apple Watch,
along with connection sub-rating.
This would allow to increase
the connection interval
while the Bluetooth peripheral is idle
and quickly change
to smaller connection interval
when you need lower latency.
Here is a table showing
the differences between platforms.
These are the currently supported
configurations for Bluetooth Low Energy.
Last year we introduced
Background app refresh for watchOS
as a new background execution mode.
This year,
if you own a Series 6 and above,
we improved the background execution
with timely alerts as we described today.
Thanks for watching!
[spacey music]