♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hello and welcome.
My name is Alè Segovia Azapian
from the GPU Software team here at Apple.
And I’m Mayur,
also from the GPU Software team.
Alè: In this session we are going
to talk about bindless rendering.
The bindless binding model is a modern
way to provide resources to your shaders,
unlocking advanced rendering techniques,
such as ray tracing.
For today, I'll start with a brief recap
of how the bindless binding model works,
and how you can easily adopt bindless
in your games and apps with Metal 3.
Bindless rendering aggregates data,
which opens up new opportunities
to improve performance on the CPU and GPU.
I'll give you two specific tips today
to improve your CPU and GPU times.
Then I'll hand it over to Mayur,
and he’ll show you how the tools
can help you adopt a bindless model.
In the bindless model,
resources are aggregated
and linked together with argument buffers.
Conceptually,
this is what this looks like.
In this example, an array
aggregates all the meshes in a scene.
Unlike the traditional binding model,
where you bind each resource independently
to a specific slot in a pipeline,
in the bindless model, resources
are first linked together in memory.
This lets you bind a single buffer
that your shaders can freely navigate
and access the resources they need
to calculate elaborate surfaces
and lighting.
After the app goes bindless,
the ray tracing shaders can access
all the data they need
to beautifully shade the reflections.
The app makes the 3D models and textures,
including the floor, the trucks,
their materials, and even the sky,
available to the ray tracing shaders
by placing all its data
into argument buffers.
Even better,
when bindless rendering is paired with
other Metal features like Heaps,
apps and games enjoy better performance,
thanks to less pressure on the CPU.
I'll talk about four specific enhancements
in Metal 3
that you may find useful
for bindless rendering.
Argument buffers
are the fundamental Metal construct
that allows you to link
your resources together.
They reference resources
such as textures and other buffers.
Metal 3 makes writing
argument buffers easier than ever
because now you no longer need
an Argument encoder object.
And the same is true for unbounded arrays.
You can now allocate acceleration
structures
from a Metal Heap
and the Shader Validation Layer alerts you
when resources aren’t resident
in GPU memory.
Together, these four features
make it easier than ever to go bindless.
In particular, writing argument buffers
in Metal 3 is a joy.
To encode a scene into argument buffers,
you write into these buffers
the scene data,
such as instances, meshes,
materials, and textures.
In Metal 2, this is accomplished
with an argument encoder.
So first, I will recap
how these objects work,
and then I will show you
how Metal 3 helps simplify your code.
With argument encoders, the first step
is to create the encoder instance.
You do this via shader function reflection
or by describing
the struct members to Metal.
With the encoder instance,
set its recording destination and offset
to the target argument buffer.
And use its methods to
write data into the buffer.
Please check out the bindless session
from last year
for a detailed refresher on argument
buffers and argument encoders.
Now this mechanism is great,
but the encoder objects
can sometimes be challenging to manage.
Metal provides two mechanisms
for creating argument encoders.
It might not be clear
which one is appropriate for your app.
Additionally, using an argument encoder
from multiple threads requires care.
Developers, intuitively understand
how to write a C struct,
and with Metal 3, you can now do just that
for your argument buffers.
Metal 3 simplifies writing argument
buffers by allowing you
to directly write into them
like any other CPU-side structure.
You now have access
to the virtual GPU address
and Resource IDs of your resources.
When you write these directly
into your argument buffer,
Metal now understands
what resources you are referencing.
It is functionally the same
as previously encoding the reference
using an argument encoder,
except an encoder isn't needed anymore.
This capability is supported all devices
with argument buffers tier 2 support.
That is, any Mac from 2016 or newer,
and any iOS device with
the A13 bionic chip or newer.
If you are unsure whether
a device supports argument buffers tier 2,
there is a convenient feature query
in the MTLDevice object that you can use.
This is what the process
now looks like in Metal 3.
First, define your CPU-visible structs,
using a 64-bit type for buffer addresses,
and MTLResourceID for textures.
Then, allocate the argument buffer.
You allocate buffers either directly
from the MTLDevice, or from a MTLHeap.
You get the buffer's contents and cast it
to the argument buffer struct type.
And finally, write the addresses
and resource IDs to the struct members.
Take a look at how this is done
in the hybrid rendering demo.
Here is the code.
Notice how simple it is.
The host-side struct directly stores
the GPU address of the normals buffer.
This is a 64-bit unsigned integer
so I used uint64_t.
Now that there is no encoder object,
you simply use the size of the struct
for your argument buffer.
Metal guarantees that the size
and alignment of the GPU and CPU structs
match across clang
and the Metal shader compiler.
Next, allocate the buffer as usual.
And if a buffer’s storage mode
is Managed or Shared,
get a direct pointer to the buffer
and cast it to the struct type.
And finally, set the normals member
to the gpuAddress,
and optionally, an offset that you must
align to the GPU’s memory requirements.
One thing I want to highlight
is how the structure declaration changes
between the Metal Shading Language
and the C declaration.
In this example, these are kept separate,
but if you prefer, you can have a single
struct declaration in a shared header
and use conditional compilation
to distinguish between
the shader compiler types and the C types.
Here’s a unified declaration in C.
The __METAL_VERSION__ macro is only
defined when compiling shader code.
Use it to separate GPU and CPU code
in header declarations.
If your app targets C++,
you can take this further
and use templates to make
the declarations even more uniform.
Check out the argument buffer
sample code for the best practices.
Now that's how you write one struct,
but you can also write many structs
using unbounded arrays.
You could already implement unbounded
arrays in Metal using argument encoders,
but Metal 3 simplifies the process
even further
by bringing it closer to just filling out
an array of structs.
Here's what's different compared
to just writing one struct.
You now need to allocate enough storage
for all structs you want to store.
And then, iterate over the array,
writing the data for each struct.
Back to the code sample,
first, expand the size of the buffer
to store as many structs
as meshes in the scene.
Notice how this is exactly the same
you do for a CPU buffer:
multiply the size of the struct
times the mesh count.
I want to take a moment to note
how powerful this is.
This single variable completely controls
the size of the array.
The shader does not need
to declare this size
to the Metal shader compiler at any point
and it's free to index into any position.
This is part of the reason the bindless
model is so flexible in Metal,
because you write shaders that access
arrays of any size with no constraints.
It just works!
Next, allocate the buffer of this size
and cast the pointer to the contents
to the correct mesh struct type.
Now that the buffer is large enough,
walk it with a simple for loop,
straddling the size of the mesh struct.
And finally, directly set the GPUAddress
of each struct in the array,
and optionally, an aligned offset.
From the GPU side in the shader,
this is one way
to represent the unbounded array.
Here, I declare it as a mesh pointer
parameter that I pass to the shader.
This makes it possible to freely access
the contents directly,
just as you would for any C array.
Another option is to pull
all the unbounded arrays into a struct.
This helps keep shaders neat
by aggregating data in a single place.
In this example,
all the meshes and materials
are brought together in a scene struct.
Using the scene struct,
the scene is passed directly to the shader
by binding a single buffer,
instead of passing every unbounded array
separately.
And access is just like before,
but now, the mesh array is reached
through the scene struct.
And that’s how to write argument buffers
and unbounded arrays in Metal 3.
The completely revamped API
now makes it more intuitive
and matches what you do for CPU structs,
or arrays of structs.
With this year's ray tracing update,
ray tracing acceleration structures
can be allocated from Metal Heaps,
along with your buffers and textures.
This means they can be aggregated
together amongst themselves
and with other resource types.
This is great, because when you aggregate
all acceleration structures into heaps,
you can flag them all resident
in a single call to useHeap.
This is a huge opportunity
for significant CPU savings
in your application's render thread.
Here are some tips for working with
acceleration structures in heaps.
First, when allocated from heaps,
acceleration structures have
alignment and size requirements
that vary per device.
There is a new query to check
for the size and alignment
of an acceleration structure
for heap allocation.
Use the heapAccelerationStructureSize
andAlignWithDescriptor method
of the MTLDevice to determine
the SizeAndAlignment
for structure descriptors.
Keep in mind, this is different
from the accelerationStructureSizes
WithDescriptor method
in MTLDevice.
Now that acceleration structures
are in a MTLHeap object,
call useHeap: to make them
all resident in a single call.
This is faster than calling
useResource on each individual resource.
And keep in mind that unless
you opt your heap into hazard tracking,
Metal does not prevent race conditions
for resources allocated from them,
so you will need to synchronize
the acceleration structure builds
between one another
and with ray tracing work.
Don't worry though,
I will talk more about this in a moment.
For more details on this
and other ray tracing performance
advances in Metal 3,
make sure to check out
the "Maximize your Metal ray tracing
performance" talk this year.
Using heap-allocated acceleration
structures provides an opportunity
to reduce your app's CPU usage
when it matters the most.
Last but not least, here's one of my
favorite features this year:
Shader validation enhancements.
On the topic of useResource and useHeap,
it is very important that
apps flag residency to Metal
for all indirectly accessed resources.
Forgetting to do it means that the memory
pages backing those resources
may not be present at rendering time.
This can cause command buffer failures,
GPU restarts, or even image corruption.
Unfortunately, it is very common
to run into these problems
when starting the bindless journey,
because in bindless,
the majority of scene resources
are accessed indirectly,
and shaders make pointer navigation
decisions at runtime.
This year, Metal 3 introduces
new functionality
in the shader validation layer
that will help you track down
missing residency of resources
during command buffer execution.
I'll show you a concrete example.
During the update process
of the Hybrid Rendering app,
we encountered a real problem where
reflections sometimes looked incorrect.
I'll show you how the validation layer
helped diagnose and fix this problem.
To flag residency to Metal, the app stores
all individual resources
not backed by heaps
into a mutable set at load time.
The app adds buffers and it adds textures.
At rendering time, before the app
dispatches the ray tracing kernel,
it indicates to Metal that it uses
all resources in the set.
This is a simple process where
the app iterates over the set
and calls useResource on each element.
Metal then makes
all these resources resident
before starting the ray tracing work.
Here's part of the code where the app
collects the resources into this set.
The app does this as part of
its argument buffer writing process.
The app's loading function
iterates over each submesh.
It nabs the data it needs
to write to the argument buffer--
that is, index data and
texture data for materials--
then it stores the index buffer's
address in the argument buffer.
For materials,
it then loops over the texture array,
writing the texture GPU resource IDs
into the argument buffer.
And at the end,
it adds all individual textures
from the submesh materials
to the sceneResources set,
so it can flag them resident
at dispatch time.
Unfortunately, there is a subtle bug here.
The app would run the command buffer,
and in some cases,
reflections would be missing.
Previously,
it was hard to track this down.
Now in Metal 3, the shader
validation layer comes to the rescue.
These kinds of problems now produce
an error during command buffer execution,
indicating what the problem is.
The error message indicates
the name of the shader function
that triggered the problem,
the name of the pass,
the metal file and line of code where it
detected the access,
and even the label
of the buffer, its size,
and the fact that it was not resident.
As a pro tip, this is why it's always
a good practice to label Metal objects.
The tools use the labels, which is helpful
when trying to identify
which object is which
while debugging your app.
With all this
detailed information in hand,
it's now easy to find the missing resource
in the shader code.
What's even better is that
when the debug breakpoint is enabled,
Xcode conveniently shows
the exact line in the shader code
where shader validation
detects the problem.
In the case of the demo app, it is
the indices buffer that is not resident.
The fix is now straightforward.
Going back to the code,
the app now stores
the missing index buffer
into the resident resource set.
With these changes,
later at ray tracing time,
Metal knows to make the index buffers
available to the GPU, solving the issue.
This is an essential tool,
and a complete game changer,
that will potentially save you hours of
debugging time in your bindless journey.
So those are the enhancements
Metal 3 brings to help you organize
and refer to bindless resources.
Now I'm going to switch gears
and talk about how to maximize
your game's performance
when going bindless.
In this section, I will cover two topics:
unretained resources,
and untracked resources.
These tips will help you get
more performance out of both your CPU
and your GPU when you have
long-lived and aggregate resources.
Now, to talk about how to improve
CPU performance with long-lived resources,
I will first recap
the Metal resource lifecycle.
Objective-C and Swift handle
object lifecycles via reference counting.
Metal resources follow this model.
Resources start with a retainCount of 1
and the runtime deallocates them
when all strong references disappear.
Because the CPU
and GPU operate in parallel,
it would be a problem if
the CPU deallocated a resource
by allowing its retainCount to reach 0
while the GPU is still using it.
To prevent this, Metal command buffers
create strong references
to all resources they use,
ensuring their retainCount
is always at least 1.
Metal creates strong references for
resources you directly bind to a pipeline
with functions such as
setVertexBuffer or setFragmentTexture--
and this also includes render
attachments--
Metal heap objects you flag resident
via the useHeap API,
and indirect resources
that you make resident
via the useResource API,
even if they are part of a heap.
For more details
on Metal object lifecycles,
please check out the "Program Metal
in C++ with metal-cpp" talk this year.
Now, it's very useful that
Metal creates these references,
because as a programmer,
you never have to worry
that you might be deallocating an object
while the GPU is still using it.
This safety guarantee Metal gives you
is very fast to execute,
but it does comes with a small CPU cost.
Now, in the bindless model,
apps aggregate resources into heaps
and these tend to be long lived,
matching the application's domain.
For example, in a game, resources are
alive for the duration of a whole level.
When this is the case, it becomes
unnecessary for Metal
to provide additional guarantees
about resource lifecycles.
What you can do then
is recoup this CPU cost
by asking Metal command buffers
not to retain resources they reference.
To turn off Metal's
automatic resource retaining,
simply create a command buffer
with unretained references.
You do this directly
from the MTLCommandQueue,
just like you create
any regular command buffer.
You don't need to make
any other changes to your app,
as long as you are already guaranteeing
your resource lifecycles.
Keep in mind that
the granularity level for this setting
is the entire command buffer.
It will either retain all referenced
resources or none of them.
In a small microbenchmark,
we measured a CPU usage reduction of 2% in
the command buffer's lifecycle
just by switching to command buffers
with unretained references.
but this time was spent entirely
creating and destroying
unnecessary strong references.
In summary, unretained resources provides
an opportunity for some extra CPU savings
when you are already guaranteeing
resource lifecycles.
Similar to unretained resources,
untracked resources
provides an opportunity to disable
a safety feature
to obtain more performance.
Many visual techniques consist in
rendering to intermediate textures
and writing into buffers and then
consuming them in later passes.
Shadow mapping, skinning, and
post-processing are good examples of this.
Now, producing
and immediately consuming resources
introduces read-after-write hazards.
Additionally, when several passes
write to the same resource,
such as two render passes
drawing into the same attachment,
one after the other,
or two blit encoders
write into the same resource,
it produces write-after-write hazards
because of the way Metal schedules work
on the GPU.
When you use tracked resources,
Metal automatically uses
synchronization primitives to
avoid hazards on the GPU timeline.
For example, Metal makes the GPU wait
for a compute skinning pass
to finish writing into a buffer
before starting a scene rendering pass
that reads from the same buffer.
This is great,
and it's a big part of why Metal is
such an approachable graphics API,
but there are some performance
considerations for apps
that aggregate resources into heaps.
Consider this example.
Here, the GPU is busy,
drawing two frames
that do vertex skinning,
render the scene, and apply tone mapping,
one after the other.
As the app keeps the GPU busy,
Metal identifies opportunities
where render and compute work can overlap,
based on resource dependencies.
When there are no dependencies,
and the conditions are right,
Metal schedules work to overlap
and run in parallel.
This saturates the GPU and allows it
to get more work done
in the same amount of wall-clock time.
Now, when the app aggregates
resources together in a heap,
all of its subresources appear
as a single one to Metal.
This is what makes heaps
so efficient to work with.
But this means that Metal sees
read and write work on the same resource
and must conservatively schedule work
to avoid any race conditions,
even when no actual hazard exists.
This situation is called "false sharing"
and, as you might expect,
it increases the execution
wall-clock time of the GPU work.
So here's the performance tip.
If you know there are no dependencies
between the resources in the heap,
then you can avoid this behavior.
To avoid false sharing, you can opt
resources out of hazard tracking
and directly signal
fine-grained dependencies to Metal.
You opt out of resource tracking
by setting a resource descriptor's
hazardTracking property to Untracked.
Because this is so important,
it is the default behavior for heaps,
as it allows you to unlock more
opportunities for the GPU
to run your work in parallel
right out of the gate.
Once you start using untracked resources,
you express dependencies
using the following primitives.
Depending on the situation,
use Fences, Events,
Shared events, or Memory barriers.
Metal Fences synchronize access
to one or more resources
across different render
and compute passes,
within the context
of a single command queue.
This is a split barrier kind-of primitive,
so the consumer pass waits
until the producer signals the Fence.
The only requirement you need to
keep in mind when using Fences
is to commit or enqueue
your producer command buffers
before your consuming command buffers.
When you can't guarantee this order,
or need to synchronize across
multiple queues on the same device,
use MTL Events.
Using Events, the consumer command buffer
waits for the producer command buffer
to signal the Event with a given value.
After it signals the value,
it is safe to read the resource.
Use Events to tell a GPU to pause work
until a command signals an Event.
MTLSharedEvents behave very similarly
to regular Events,
but work at larger scope
that goes beyond a single GPU.
Use these to synchronize
access to resources
across different Metal devices
and even with the CPU.
For example, use Shared Events
to process the results
of a GPU calculation from the CPU.
Here is an example.
The GPU in this case
skins a mesh in a compute pass
and the CPU stores the pose to disk.
Because these two are independent devices,
use a Shared Event to have the CPU wait
until the GPU produces the resource.
In the beginning,
the CPU unconditionally starts to wait
for the GPU to signal the Shared Event.
When the GPU produces the resource
and places it into unified memory,
it signals the Shared Event.
At this point, the waiting thread
on the CPU wakes up
and safely consumes the resource.
The last primitive type
is Memory Barriers.
A Memory Barrier forces all subsequent
commands within a single render
or compute pass to wait
until all the previous commands finish.
The cost of a barrier is similar to the
cost of a Fence in almost all cases.
There is, however, one exception.
That exception is barriers after
the fragment stage in a render pass.
These barriers have a very high cost
that’s similar to splitting
the render pass.
Metal disables barriers after
the fragment stage on Apple GPUs
to help your apps
stay on the fastest driver path.
The Metal debug layer even
generates a validation error
if you add an after-fragment barrier
on Apple GPUs.
It is recommended to use a Fence
to synchronize resources
after the fragment stage.
Here's a short summary
of the synchronization primitives
and when to use them.
Prefer using Fences
for the lowest overhead
when committing or enqueueing work
to a single command queue
in producer, then consumer order.
Fences are great
for the majority of common cases.
When the submission order
can't be guaranteed,
or there are multiple command queues,
use Metal Events.
Shared Events allows synchronization
of multiple GPUs
between themselves and with the CPU.
Use them only in these specific
multi-device cases.
Use Memory Barriers for cases where
it's desired to synchronize within a pass.
Barriers are a fast primitive
in most cases,
such as concurrent compute passes,
and vertex stages between draw calls.
But friendly reminder, use a Fence
between passes instead of a barrier
for synchronizing
after the fragment stages,
because these barriers are very expensive
and Apple GPUs don't allow it.
Using untracked resources
and manual fine-grained tracking,
you can now have
all the advantages of data aggregation,
while maximizing GPU parallelism.
And those are the performance tips
to get the most out of the CPU
and GPU when going bindless.
I've talked a lot about how Metal 3
unlocks simplified
and efficient bindless workflows.
But writing code is only half
the equation.
The other half is how the available tools
can help you verify
how the GPU sees and executes work.
I am now going to hand it over to Mayur
to talk about what's new
with Metal 3 tooling for bindless.
Mayur: Thank you Alè.
Today, I'm excited to show you
some of the great new features
in the Metal Debugger that will help you
debug and optimize your bindless Apps.
I just took a frame capture
of the HybridRendering app
that Alè just showed you.
When you capture a frame in
the Metal Debugger,
you'll arrive to the Summary page,
which provides you
with an overview of your frame
alongside helpful insights on how
to improve your app's performance.
But today, I’m excited to show you
the new dependency viewer.
To open it, just click on
Dependencies here on the left.
Here is the new dependency viewer
and it features a brand new design
that’s packed with powerful new features.
The dependency viewer shows you
a graph-based representation
of your workload.
Each node in the graph represents a pass,
which is encoded by a command encoder,
and its output resources.
The edges represent resource dependencies
between passes.
New this year,
you can analyze your workload
by focusing on two types of dependencies.
data flow and synchronization.
The solid lines represent data flow
and they show you
how data flows in your app.
The dotted lines represent synchronization
and they show you dependencies
that introduce GPU synchronization
between passes.
To learn more, you can click on
any encoder, resource, or edge,
and the debugger will show you a lot of
detailed information in the new sidebar.
For example,
this edge adds synchronization
and also has data flow
between these passes.
By default, the dependency viewer
shows both data flow
and synchronization dependencies,
but you can use this menu
down here at the bottom
to focus on
just one of the dependency types.
Here, I will focus on just
synchronization.
As Alè said earlier,
false sharing is a common problem
when reading and writing
different resources from a tracked heap.
The dependency viewer makes it easy
to catch these issues.
This demo I captured is from
an early development version
that has this issue.
If I click on this heap,
the dependency viewer shows me
that this heap is tracked
and therefore adds synchronization
between these two passes.
The dependency viewer also highlights
the resources allocated inside the heap,
such as this render target texture
that the render encoder stores,
and a buffer that the compute encoder
reads and writes to.
The problem is this synchronization
between these two passes is not needed
because the compute encoder is not using
any resources from previous encoders.
To remove this dependency, I can modify
the app to use an untracked heap
and insert Fences
where synchronization is needed.
With that change,
these two passes can now run in parallel.
Another great improvement in Xcode 14
to help debug your bindless apps
is the new resource list.
I can navigate to a draw call
that I want to debug and open it.
When using bindless,
hundreds or even thousands of resources
are available to the GPU at any time.
This year, the Metal debugger gives you
the ability
to check which of these resources
a draw call accessed,
just by clicking on the
"Accessed" mode at the top.
Now the debugger shows me
only the handful of resources
that this draw call accesses
and the type of each access.
This is really useful for understanding
what resources your shader has accessed
from argument buffers.
Knowing what resources
your draw call uses is great,
but if it shows resources
that you weren’t expecting,
you can use the shader debugger
to figure out what’s going on.
To start the shader debugger,
just click on the debug button here
in the bottom bar,
select the pixel that you want to debug,
and hit the Debug button.
And now you are in the shader debugger.
The shader debugger shows
how your code was executed line by line,
including which resources were accessed.
For these lines, this shader reads
textures from an argument buffer.
I can expand the detailed views
on the right sidebar
to check which resources were read.
This can help identify issues
where your shader accesses
the wrong argument buffer element.
In this demo, I’ve shown you
how to use the new dependency viewer
to analyze and validate
resource dependencies,
how to use the new resource list
to understand what resources
a draw call accessed,
and how to use the shader debugger
to analyze, line by line,
how a shader was executed.
I can’t wait to see how you use
these new features
to create great Metal bindless apps.
Back to you Alè.
Alè: Thank you, Mayur.
That was an awesome demo.
To wrap up, Metal 3 brings a lot
to the table for going bindless.
With simplified argument buffer encoding,
acceleration structures from heaps,
improvements to the validation layer
and tools,
Metal 3 is an excellent API
to bring effective and performant bindless
to your games and apps.
With this year's enhancements, the hybrid
rendering app is looking better than ever.
We are releasing
this updated version of the app
with full source code
in the Metal sample code gallery.
You can download, study, and modify it,
and as an exercise, I challenge you to
take it even further
and add recursive reflections
to the mirror surfaces.
I can't wait to see what you do with it.
There has never been a better time
to go bindless with Metal 3.
Thank you for watching.
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪