♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Jaideep Joshi,
and I'm a GPU software engineer
at Apple.
In this session,
I will introduce
a new feature in Metal 3
that will simplify
and optimize resource loading
for your games and apps.
I'll start by showing you
how the fast resource loading
feature
can fit into your app's
asset-loading pipeline.
It has several key features that
harness new storage technologies
on Apple products.
Fast resource loading
has some advanced features
that solve interesting scenarios
your applications may run into.
There are a few best practice
recommendations
you should know about
that will help you
effectively use
these features in your apps.
As you add fast resource loading
to your apps,
tools like Metal System Trace
and the GPU debugger
can help profile and fix
issues you may run into.
At the end, I'll walk through
an example
that shows fast resource loading
in action.
So here's what you can do with
Metal 3's fast resource loading.
With Metal 3's
fast resource loading,
your games and apps
can load assets with low latency
and high throughput
by taking advantage
of the Apple silicon
unified memory architecture
and fast SSD storage
included with Apple platforms.
You will learn the best ways
to stream data
and reduce load times
to ensure that your game's
assets are ready on time.
A key aspect
of reducing load times
is to load only what you need
at the smallest
possible granularity.
The high throughput
and low latency in Metal 3
lets your apps stream
higher-quality assets,
including textures, audio,
and geometry data.
Now I'll walk you through
an example of asset loading
in a game.
Games typically show
a loading screen
when they first start up, or
at the beginning of a new level,
so they can load
the game's assets into memory.
As the player moves
through the level,
the game loads
more assets for the scene.
The downside is the player
has to wait a long time
while the game makes
multiple requests
to the storage system
to load assets up front.
Plus, those assets can have
a large memory footprint.
There are a few ways
to improve this experience.
Games can improve
this experience
by dynamically streaming objects
as the player
gets closer to them.
This way, the game only loads
what it needs at first
and gradually streams
other resources
as the player moves
through the level.
For example, the game
initially loads this chalkboard
at a lower resolution, but as
the player walks towards it,
the game loads
a higher-resolution version.
This approach reduces
the time the player waits
at the loading screen.
However, the player might
still see lower-resolution items
in the scene even
when they are up close,
because it takes too long
to load
the higher-resolution versions.
One way to deal with this
is to stream smaller portions
of each asset.
For example, your game could
load only the visible regions
of the scene with sparse
textures that stream tiles
instead of whole mip levels.
This vastly reduces
the amount of data
your app needs to stream.
With that approach,
the load requests get smaller,
and there are more of them.
But that's OK,
because modern storage hardware
can run multiple
load requests at once.
This means that you can
increase the resolution
and scale of your scene without
compromising the gameplay.
Along with issuing a large
number of small-load requests,
you also have the ability to
prioritize your load requests,
to ensure that high-priority
requests finish in time.
Now that I have covered the ways
to boost visual fidelity of
games while reducing load times,
I'll show you how Metal 3's
fast resource loading
helps you do this.
Fast resource loading
is an asynchronous API
that loads resources
from storage.
Unlike existing load APIs, the
thread which issues the loads
does not need to wait
for the loads to finish.
The load operations
execute concurrently
to better utilize the throughput
of faster storage.
You can batch load operations
to further minimize the overhead
of resource loading.
And finally, with Metal 3,
you can prioritize load
operations for lower latency.
Now I'll show you
the key features
that will help you build
your asset-loading pipeline,
starting with the steps
to load resources.
There are three steps
to load resources:
open a file,
issue the necessary
load commands,
and then synchronize these load
commands with rendering work.
Here's how you do that,
starting with opening a file.
You open an existing file
by creating a file handle
with a Metal device instance.
For example, this code uses
the Metal device instance
to create a file handle
by calling its new makeIOHandle
method with a file path URL.
Once you have a file handle,
you can use it
to issue load commands.
Here's a typical scenario
in an application,
where it performs load
operations and encodes GPU work.
With existing load APIs, the app
has to wait for the loading work
to finish before it can encode
the rendering work.
Metal 3 lets your app
asynchronously
execute load commands.
Start by creating
a Metal IO command queue.
Then use that queue
to create IO command buffers
and encode load commands
to those buffers.
However, as command buffers
execute asynchronously
on the command queue,
your app does not need to wait
for the load operations
to finish.
In fact, not only do
all commands
within an IO command buffer
execute concurrently,
IO command buffers themselves
execute concurrently
and complete out of order.
This concurrent execution model
better utilizes
faster-storage hardware
by maximizing throughput.
You can encode three types of
IO commands to a command buffer:
loadTexture, which loads
to a Metal texture
for texture streaming;
loadBuffer, which loads
to a Metal buffer
for streaming scene
or geometry data;
and loadBytes, which loads
to CPU-accessible memory.
You create IO command buffers
from an IO command queue.
To create a queue,
first make and configure
an IO command
queue descriptor.
By default, the queues
are concurrent,
but you can also set them
to run command buffers
sequentially and completely
in order.
Then pass the queue descriptor
to the Metal device instance's
makeIOCommandQueue method.
Create an IO command buffer
by calling the command queue's
makeCommandBuffer method.
Then use that command buffer
to encode load commands
that load textures and buffers.
Metal's validation layer
will catch encoding errors
at runtime.
The load commands are what use
the fileHandle instance
created earlier.
When you are done adding load
commands to a command buffer,
submit it to the queue
for execution
by calling the command buffer's
commit method.
Now that I've covered how
to create IO command queues,
command buffers,
issue load commands,
and submit them to the queue,
I want to show you
how you can synchronize loading
work with the other GPU work.
An app typically kicks off
its rendering work
after it finishes loading
resources for that rendering.
But an app that uses
fast resource loading
needs a way to synchronize
the IO command queue
with the render command queue.
You can synchronize these queues
with a Metal shared event.
Metal hared events let you
synchronize the command buffers
from your IO queue
with the command buffers
from your rendering queue.
You can tell a command buffer
to wait for a shared event
by encoding a waitEvent command.
Similarly, you can tell
that command buffer
to signal a shared event by
encoding a signalEvent command.
Metal ensures
that all IO commands
within the command buffer
are complete
before it signals
the shared event.
To synchronize
between command buffers,
you first need
a Metal shared event.
You can tell a command buffer
to wait for a shared event
by calling
its waitForEvent method.
Similarly, you can tell
a command buffer
to signal a shared event
by calling
its signalEvent method.
You can add similar logic
to a corresponding
GPU command buffer
so that it waits for
the IO command buffer
to signal the same shared event.
To recap, here are
the key features and APIs
that load resources
in your Metal apps.
Open a file by creating
a Metal file handle.
Issue load commands by creating
an IO command queue
and an IO command buffer.
Then, encode load commands
to the command buffer
for execution on the queue.
And finally, use wait
and signalEvent commands
with Metal shared events
to synchronize loading
and rendering.
Now, I'll go over
a few advanced features
that you might find helpful.
Here's a typical scenario
where a game can't fit
its entire map in memory,
which is why it subdivides
the map into regions.
As the player progresses
through the map,
the game starts preloading
regions of the map.
Based on the player's direction,
the game determines
that the best regions to preload
are the northwest,
west, and southwest regions.
However, once the player
moves to the western region
and starts heading south,
preloading the northwestern
region is no longer beneficial.
To reduce the latency
of future loads,
Metal 3 allows you to attempt
to cancel load operation.
Let's look at how to do that
in practice.
When the player is
in the center region,
encode and commit IO command
buffers for three regions.
Then when the player
is in the western region
and heading south,
use the tryCancel method
to cancel the loads
for the northwestern region.
Cancelling is at
the command buffer granularity,
so you can cancel the
command buffer mid-execution.
If at some later point,
you want to know
whether the region
was completely loaded,
you can check the status
of the command buffer.
Metal 3 also lets you
prioritize your IO work.
Consider a game scenario
where the player teleports
to a new part of the scene and
your game starts streaming in
large amounts
of graphics assets.
At the same time,
the game needs to play
the teleportation sound effect.
Fast resource loading allows you
to load all your app's assets,
including audio data.
To load audio, you can use
the loadBytes command
discussed earlier to load to
application-allocated memory.
In this example, texture
and audio IO command buffers
are concurrently executing
on a single IO command queue.
This simplified diagram
shows the requests
at the storage layer.
The storage system
is able to execute
both audio and texture
load requests in parallel.
To avoid delayed audio,
it is critical
that the streaming system
be able to prioritize
audio requests
over texture requests.
To prioritize audio requests,
you can create
a separate IO command queue,
and set its priority to high.
The storage system will ensure
that high-priority IO requests
have a lower latency and are
prioritized over other requests.
After creating a separate
high-priority queue
for audio assets,
the execution time
of the audio load requests
has gotten smaller,
while that of the parallel
texture load requests
has gotten larger.
Here's how you create
a high-priority queue.
Simply set the command queue
descriptor's priority property
to high.
You can also set the priority
to normal or low,
then create a new
IO command queue
from the descriptor as usual.
Just remember that you cannot
change a queue's priority level
after you create it.
As you add fast resource loading
to your apps,
here's some best practices
to keep in mind.
First, consider
compressing your assets.
You can reduce
your app's disk footprint
by using built-in
or custom compression.
Compression lets you trade
runtime performance
for a smaller disk footprint.
Additionally, you can improve
storage throughput
by tuning the sparse page size
when using sparse textures.
I'll go through each of these
in more detail,
starting with compression.
You can use Metals 3's APIs
to compress
your asset files offline.
First, create a compression
context and configure it
with a chunk size
and compression method.
Then pass parts of
your asset files to the context
to produce a single compressed
version of all your files.
The compression context works
by chunking all the data
and compresses it with the codec
of your choosing
and stores it to a pack file.
In this example,
the context compresses
the data in 64K chunks,
but you can choose
a suitable chunk size
based on the size and type
of data you want to compress.
Here's how you use
the compression APIs in Metal 3.
First, create
a compression context
by providing a path for creating
the compressed file,
a compression method,
and a chunk size.
Next, get file data
and append it to the context.
Here, the file data is
in an NSData object.
You can append data
from different files
by making multiple calls
to append data.
When you're done adding data,
finalize and save
the compressed file
by calling the flush and destroy
compression context function.
You can open and access
a compressed file
by creating a file handle.
This file handle is used
when issuing load commands.
For compressed files, Metal 3
performs inline decompression,
by translating the offsets
to a list of chunks
it needs to decompress, and
loads them to your resources.
You create a file handle
with a Metal device instance.
For example, this code uses
the Metal device instance
to create a file handle
by providing
the compressed file path
to the makeIOHandle method
I covered earlier.
For compressed files,
an additional parameter
is the compression method.
This is the same
compression method
you used at the time of creating
the compressed file.
Now, I'll go through
the different compression
methods supported
and the characteristics
of each of them,
so you can better understand
how to choose between them.
Use LZ4 when decompression
speed is critical
and your app can afford
a large disk footprint.
If a balance between codec
speed and compression ratio
is important to you,
use ZLib, LZBitmap, or LZFSE.
Amongst the balanced codecs,
ZLib works better
with non-Apple devices.
LZBitmap is fast
at encoding and decoding,
and LZFSE has
a high compression ratio.
If you need the best
compression ratio,
consider using the LZMA codec,
if your app can afford the extra
time it takes to decode assets.
It is also possible to use
your own compression scheme.
You may have cases
where your data benefits
from a custom compression codec.
In that case, you can replace
the compression context
with your own compressor
and translate offsets
and perform decompression
at runtime yourself.
Now that you have seen
how to use compression
to reduce disk footprint,
let's look at tuning
sparse page size.
Earlier versions
of Metal support loading tiles
to sparse textures
at a 16K granularity.
With Metal 3, you can specify
two new sparse tile sizes:
64 and 256K.
These new sizes let you
to stream textures
at a larger granularity
to better utilize
and saturate
the storage hardware.
Note that there is a tradeoff
between streaming
larger tiles sizes
and the amount of data
you stream,
so you'll have to experiment
to see which sizes work best
with your app
and its sparse textures.
Next, let's look at
how you can use
the set of Metal Developer Tools
to profile and debug
fast resource loading
in your app.
Xcode 14 includes full support
for fast resource loading.
From runtime profiling
with Metal System Trace
to API inspection and
advanced dependency analysis
with Metal debugger.
Let's start with
runtime profiling.
In Xcode 14, Instruments can
profile fast resource loading
with the Metal System Trace
template.
Instruments is a powerful
analysis and profiling tool
that will help you achieve
the best performance
in your Metal app.
The Metal System Trace template
allows you to check
when load operations
are encoded and executed.
You will be able to understand
how they correlate
with the activity that
your app is performing
on both the CPU and the GPU.
To learn how to profile your
Metal app with Instruments,
please check out
these previous sessions,
"Optimize Metal apps and games
with GPU counters"
and "Optimize high-end games
for Apple GPUs."
Now, let's switch gears
to debugging.
With the Metal debugger
in Xcode 14,
you can now analyze
your game's use
of the new
fast resource loading API.
Once you take a frame capture,
you will be able to inspect
all fast resource loading
API calls.
From the IO command buffers
created
to the load operations
that were issued.
You can now visually inspect
fast resource loading
dependencies
with the new
Dependency viewer.
The Dependency viewer
gives a detailed overview
of resource dependencies
between IO command buffers
and Metal passes.
From here, you can use
all the features
in the new
Dependency viewer,
such as the new synchronization
edges and graph filtering,
to deep dive and optimize your
resource loading dependencies.
To learn more about the new
Dependency viewer in Xcode 14,
please check out this year's
"Go bindless with Metal 3"
session.
Now, let's look at
fast resource loading in action.
This is a test scene that uses
the new fast resource loading
APIs to stream texture data
by using sparse textures
with a tile size of 16 kilobytes.
This video is from a MacBook Pro
with an M1 Pro chip.
The streaming system queries
the GPU's sparse texture access
counters to identify two things:
the tiles it has sampled
but not loaded
and the loaded tiles
the app isn't using.
The app uses this information
to encode a list of loads
for the tiles it needs
and a list of evictions
for tiles it doesn't need.
That way, the working set
contains only the tiles
the app is mostly likely to use.
If the player decides to travel
to another part of the scene,
the app needs to stream in
a completely new set
of high-resolution textures.
If the streaming system
is fast enough,
the player will not notice
this streaming occurring.
If I pause the scene,
you can observe the image
differences more clearly.
The left side
is loading sparse tiles
on a single thread
using the pread API.
The right side
is loading sparse tiles
using the fast resource loading
APIs.
As the player enters the scene,
most of the textures
haven't fully loaded.
Once the loads complete, the
final high-resolution version
of the textures is visible.
If I go back to the beginning
of this scene and slow it down,
it is easier to notice
the improvements
that fast resource loading
provides.
To highlight the differences,
this rendering
marks tiles the app has not
yet loaded with a red tint.
At first, the scene shows
that the app hasn't loaded
most of the tiles.
However, as the player
enters the scene,
fast resource loading
improves the loading
of high-resolution tiles
and minimizes the delay
compared to the single-threaded
pread version.
Metal 3's fast resource loading
helps you build a powerful
and efficient asset-streaming
system that lets your app
take advantage of the latest
storage technologies.
Use it to reduce load times by
streaming assets just in time,
including higher-quality images.
Use Metal's shared events
to asynchronously load assets
while the GPU renders a scene.
For assets that your app
needs in a hurry,
minimize latency
by creating a command queue
with a higher priority.
And remember,
keep the storage system busy
by sending load commands early.
You can always cancel
the ones you don't need.
Fast resource loading in Metal 3
introduces new ways
to harness the power
of modern storage hardware
for high-throughput
asset loading.
I can't wait to see
how you use these features
to improve your app's visual
quality and responsiveness.
Thanks for watching.
♪