♪ ♪
Owen: Hello, and welcome
to Bring your iOS app to the Mac.
My name is Owen,
and I'm a Mac Catalyst engineer.
Whether you ship your iOS app
on M1 Macs with no changes,
have started thinking about
going further with Mac Catalyst,
or already ship a Catalyst app you want to
make even better,
I'm excited to share new APIs
and techniques
to make your app the best it can be
on Mac.
But first, I'd love to show off
some of the amazing work
done by developers that showcases
what's possible with Mac Catalyst.
Craft is an incredible app
that makes it effortless
to start writing
and produce beautiful documents,
and is the App Store's
2021 Mac App of the Year winner.
And because of Mac Catalyst,
this great experience is available
across devices,
so it's always ready
when your next idea strikes.
Darkroom's smart AI editing tools
streamline your photography workflow,
and you can start your edits in the field
on your iPhone or iPad,
and finish at home
with their Mac Catalyst app.
It won an Apple Design Award
for outstanding design,
innovation, and ingenuity,
and has been an App Store Editor's Choice
app since 2018.
Night Sky is a stunning way to explore
the cosmos right from your computer.
You can learn about the constellations,
and get a closer look
with detailed 3D models of the moon,
planets, and satellites.
It has won multiple Webby and Lovie awards
for its design and breathtaking visuals.
Asphalt 9 - Legends is an exhilarating
high-octane racing simulation,
and the only racing game to ever win
an Apple Design Award,
and the action is even more exciting
on the big screen
with their Mac Catalyst version.
Now, I'll get into all the ways
you can create a great experience
on Mac for your app.
I'm going to start
with a couple of new options
for running your iOS app natively on M1,
the easiest way
to get your existing iOS app onto Mac.
Then I'll walk through adding
a Mac Catalyst run destination in Xcode,
and go over what changes.
I'll show off the new behaviors
your Catalyst app will get for free
when you adopt
the new Desktop-class iPad APIs.
Then dig in to Mac-specific refinements
made possible with new Mac Catalyst APIs.
I'll start with some new options
for native iOS apps on Macs with M1.
Your iOS apps are already available
on M1 Macs in the Mac App Store.
As long as you haven't opted out,
your app is found in a search
under the "iPhone and iPad Apps" tab.
And we have a couple new additions
that can improve your app experience
on Mac.
There are two new keys
you can add to your Info plist,
which allow you to specify
how your iOS app should launch on Mac.
These keys aren't bound
to any SDK version,
and are ignored on iOS and on Mac
prior to macOS 12.1,
so they're safe to add
to any app that would benefit.
The first key,
"UISupportsTrueScreenSizeOnMac,"
indicates that your app is prepared
for the wide variety of display
configurations it may encounter.
This way,
your app gets the true screen size
and pixel density,
rather than a compatible iPad size.
The second key,
"UILaunchToFullScreenByDefaultOnMac,"
tells the system that your app prefers
to enter fullscreen mode
as soon as it's launched.
These two keys work great together,
especially for games and multimedia apps,
delivering a pixel-perfect,
edge-to-edge, full screen experience.
These keys have been adopted
by the award-winning
Sky: Children of the Light
to provide an immersive experience
immediately.
As soon as the game is launched,
it pulls you in to its beautiful world
of exploration
by filling the screen with rich detail.
Another way to improve your app experience
on Mac is with Touch Alternatives,
which automatically converts keyboard,
mouse, and trackpad input
into iOS multitouch gestures
and device motion expected by your app.
We've already added built-in
touch alternative support
for many of the most popular games
on the app store.
When launched, they automatically show
a tutorial
explaining how their touch controls
translate to a keyboard and mouse
or trackpad.
For example, the arrow keys
can be used to simulate swipes
from the center of the window,
and the spacebar to perform a tap.
To opt into automatic Touch Alternatives,
create a new plist file in your app named
"com.apple.uikit.inputalternatives.plist".
First, add a key called
"defaultEnablement"
with a string value of "enabled",
which tells the system that Touch
Alternatives should be on immediately.
Below that, add another key
called "requiredOnboarding".
This is an array containing a list
of which controls
you've decided work best for your app.
You have the choice to onboard
for five different control options:
tap, tilt, drag, swipe,
and direct touch input from a trackpad.
Note that when
Touch Alternatives is enabled,
all of these controls will be active,
but you should still decide
which make the most sense for your app,
and only add the controls that you want
highlighted to your onboarding plist.
This is detected
when your app is run on Mac,
and on first launch, the onboarding sheet
is presented highlighting those controls.
In your app settings,
people can switch between displaying
the preferred controls specified
in the plist
and all controls.
Of course, the best option
is to implement keyboard and cursor support
directly in your app.
By doing this, you ensure
your app behaves well on all devices,
including iPads with an attached keyboard,
and on the Mac.
For more information, watch the videos
"Support hardware keyboards in your app"
and "Handle trackpad and mouse input".
Now I'll quickly cover the process
of becoming a Mac Catalyst app.
By adding a Mac Catalyst destination
in your project settings,
your app will automatically be converted
to a full Mac Catalyst app
capable of running on every Mac,
and allowing you to customize it further
using Mac Catalyst API.
You also have the choice
to optimize the interface for Mac,
which will give you
native AppKit styled controls,
and ensure your app content
renders at native scale.
I'll be using the Markdown demo app
that the team has been working on
to highlight the new iPad features.
When I first bring it to Mac, it's running
in "Scaled to Match iPad" mode.
When I switch to Optimize for Mac,
many changes happen automatically.
When compared side-by-side,
the differences are apparent.
When the app is optimized for Mac,
the UINavigationBar gets translated into
a rich NSToolbar,
providing native AppKit controls.
This translation happens
for other controls as well.
And the text size adjusts as well.
Text in the iPad idiom
renders at iPad size,
and then is scaled down
to 77% of its original size.
Text in the Mac idiom is handled
with native Mac font rendering,
which happens at pixel-perfect scale.
This is ideal for our app,
since it ensures
the text always looks crisp.
With the app opted into Mac Catalyst,
I want to check out how well it works,
and go deeper
into the new automatic Mac behaviors
provided by iPadOS 16's new API.
If you've already watched
"Meet desktop-class iPad"
and "Build a desktop-class iPad app",
you've learned about the many new tools
to enhance your app with iPadOS 16.
And these new APIs translate beautifully
into native Mac representations.
I'll take a tour of the markdown app,
and highlight some of these new behaviors.
Controls and navigation move
from UINavigationBar into the NSToolbar.
And if you don't already create a toolbar,
we give you one automatically.
If you already manage
your own NSToolbar in Catalyst,
we stay out of your way.
Center item controls
become NSToolbarItems.
For document based apps,
your window title shows the document name,
and if "Show window title icons" is
enabled in Accessibility System Settings,
the file proxy icon appears as well,
exactly how you would expect it on Mac.
And if you use a navigation controller,
the back button
and other navigation controls
are also brought into the toolbar.
Additionally,
you get new document-centric menu items
in the File menu:
Duplicate, Move, Rename, and Export As.
To enable these menu items,
ensure some object in your responder chain
overrides UIResponder's duplicate,
move, rename, and export functions.
If your app doesn't need
these File menu items,
they should be removed with UIMenuBuilder.
Implement the buildMenu method on your app
delegate to control your app menus.
The new Document menu items have
a UIMenuIdentifier value of .document.
If your app includes a search bar,
it gets automatically pulled
into the NSToolbar as well,
first showing as a search button
that expands into the bar on click.
The UISearchTextField that backs it
is hosted inside of an NSToolbarItem,
and this is available
for custom views as well.
The search suggestions menu
and search scope bar
also get converted
into native AppKit controls.
In addition to all the new Mac behaviors
you get for free
by adopting desktop-class iPad features,
we've also added several new
Catalyst-specific APIs
to improve multi-window
and toolbar behaviors.
I'll go through our Markdown app
one more time,
and add these Mac-specific features
using a mix of old and new API.
From the existing Mac Catalyst APIs,
I've chosen a few
that really enhance our App.
I've adopted the Mac idiom
to get native controls
and the automatic NSToolbar.
I added a custom pointer
so moving the mouse over the slider handle
in the middle of the custom split view
switches the pointer
to horizontal double-arrows
indicating that the split can be resized.
And I've added printing support
with the UIApplicationSupportsPrintCommand
plist key.
When considering your app,
don't feel like you need to add
every single one of these features.
Instead, think about
the type of app that you create,
and which features work best for it.
Check out the Mac and Mac Catalyst
Human Interface Guidelines,
and look for inspiration
in other apps you use.
With these features implemented,
the app is already in a wonderful spot.
And now with some new Mac Catalyst API,
I can do even more.
We've added new options for customizing
app window frame and controls,
for displaying UIView content
in the NSToolbar,
and for showing popovers
from toolbar items.
I'll go ahead and use these new APIs
to improve our app even further on Mac
starting with the windows.
Catalyst apps support multiple windows
using the existing UIWindowScene API.
And new in macOS Ventura,
we've added API to let you customize
your app windows even further
by setting the style
of the traffic-light window controls,
programmatically resizing
and repositioning your windows,
and disabling fullscreen
for specific scenes.
I'll use these tools
to add a feature to the markdown app
to show a helpful auxiliary panel
with markdown syntax.
This panel will be sized smaller
with the new geometry request API,
and have its minimize
and zoom buttons disabled.
At scene creation, in my Scene Delegate's
"scene willConnectTo session" method,
I create my desired frame.
It's good practice to always start with
the current frame from effectiveGeometry.
Before the scene is created,
this is initialized to CGRectNull,
whose values the system knows to ignore
for initial scene creation.
I modify the size,
then give my scene its new frame
by creating a new
UIWindowScene.macGeometryPreferences
object and passing the frame
as its systemFrame argument.
I then submit the update using
the scene.requestGeometryUpdate() method.
Because this is a request,
the system reserves the right
to reject the new geometry,
in which case it will call
the error handler callback with details.
When done in the scene
willConnectToSession method as shown here,
the request will apply to
your application's first launch,
but will be superseded by any
applicable state restoration
performed by the system on later launches.
And because this is a small helper panel,
I also disable the minimize button
from the new windowScene
windowingBehaviors object,
and the ability
to make the window fullscreen,
from the new property on sizeRestrictions.
When this new Markdown Hints
window is shown,
it appears with the size we requested.
The yellow minimize and green zoom
window control buttons are disabled,
leaving only the red close button.
These options aren't reserved
just for scene creation.
At any time in a scene's life,
you can check its current frame
from the readonly effectiveGeometry
property,
modify it however you need,
and request a new geometry update.
Here's another example showing
how to modify the origin of the window,
keeping its size the same.
There are two important aspects
of the geometry to keep in mind.
First, because systemFrame
dictates the frame of the window
on the Mac desktop,
the size of one point
for the systemFrame property
is always the size of one AppKit point.
If your app is optimized for Mac,
this is the same scale
as your UI elements.
However,
if your app is scaled to match iPad,
it will differ by the 77% scale factor.
Second, the origin of the coordinate space
is the upper-left corner
of the main display.
If you have multiple displays,
the main display is the one that shows
the Menu bar
in the system display settings.
With new Mac Catalyst API,
you can take control over the state
of each of
the three window control buttons.
The new windowingBehaviors object
on UIWindowScene has two properties,
closable and miniaturizable,
that will adjust these respective window
behaviors
and enable or disable the red
and yellow window buttons.
The green window button handles both
resizing your window on the desktop,
and taking the window into fullscreen.
You can disable fullscreen
with the new property on sizeRestrictions,
"allowsFullScreen"
or disable resizing
by using size restrictions
and setting the minimum
and maximum size to the same size.
And by doing both,
the green button also becomes disabled.
And you can check whether
your scene is currently fullscreen
with the new "isFullScreen" property.
Now, I'll focus on
refining the toolbar for Mac.
We've added new options
for toolbar customization,
whether you rely on the automatic
conversion from a UINavigationBar
or manage your own NSToolbar
in your app code.
New in Mac Catalyst,
UIViews can be added
as items to the NSToolbar.
I designed a custom UIView for our App
that shows the current word count.
And when clicked,
it presents a popover
with additional details
like paragraph and section counts,
reading time, and translation.
Because I'm using
the new desktop-class iPad API,
the customView property
on my UIBarButton item
is automatically wrapped
and added to the toolbar.
But if you manage
your NSToolbar independently,
we've also added
a new NSToolbarItem subclass,
called NSUIViewToolbarItem.
You can use NSUIViewToolbarItem
just like any other NSToolbarItem,
to instantiate a toolbar item
from your NSToolbarDelegate's
itemForIdentifier method.
The initializer takes a UIView to wrap,
which is then inserted into the NSToolbar.
NSToolbar expects
unique toolbar item instances
for toolbar customization mode.
If you are using automatic NSToolbar
hosting from your UINavigationBar,
your view is cloned by the system
for toolbar customization automatically.
However, if you manage your own NSToolbar,
your delegate will need to create
unique instances
of your UIView
for each NSUIViewToolbarItem instance,
rather than reusing
the same UIView instance.
With my new item in the toolbar,
I'll add the popover behavior.
In my toolbar item's action,
I create the popover view controller,
and set its source item
to be my toolbar item.
Then I present the popover.
With the popover code in place,
clicking on the toolbar item
presents additional detail
in a popover presentation
anchored on my toolbar item.
Like other controls in Mac Catalyst,
you can opt out of navigation bar
translation by using the new property
preferredBehavioralStyle
on UINavigationBar.
Its default value is automatic,
but you can set it to .mac
to explicitly request translation.
and by setting it to .pad,
your navigation bar
no longer gets automatically translated.
With these options,
you can add a new layer of customization
to your app's toolbar.
We're so excited to see how
you use these new tools
to make your apps even better.
With your iPad app
automatically on the Mac App Store,
it's available for a whole new audience.
When you upload your iPad app,
run it on the Mac and try it for yourself.
Or take it to the next level
by becoming a Mac Catalyst app,
and use the new API in iOS 16
and macOS Ventura
to make your app its best.
It's easy to bring your app to the Mac.
We love showcasing your hard work
and can't wait try what you build next.
Thank you.