♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello, I'm Alejandro.
I'm an engineer
on the CreateML team.
Today I'm going to talk about
a brand-new API
for building machine learning
models using components.
Create ML
provides a simple API
for training
machine learning models.
It is based on
a set of supported tasks
like image classification,
sound classification, and so on.
At WWDC 2021,
we presented two great talks
on the Create ML framework.
Make sure to check those out
if you haven't.
But I want to talk about
going beyond predefined tasks.
What if you wanted
to customize a task
to your particular problem
beyond what Create ML offers?
Or what if you wanted to build
a different type of task?
Using components,
you can now compose tasks
in new and creative ways.
Let's dig in.
I'll start by breaking up
an ML task
and explaining what
each component does.
Then, I'll talk about how you
can piece components together.
Followed with an example
of a custom image task.
Then, I'll talk about
tabular tasks.
And I'll end with
deployment strategies.
Let me start by exploring
the insides
of a machine learning task
so that you understand
what goes into it
and how it works.
This way, when we start
building custom tasks,
you know what I'm talking about.
I'm going to use an image
classifier as an example.
An image classifier
uses a list of labeled images
to train a model.
In this example,
I have images of cats and dogs
with their respective labels.
But let's explore how images
are transformed at each step.
To do that, I'll expand
the image classification task
to see what's inside.
Conceptually, an image
classifier is very simple.
It consists of a feature
extractor and a classifier.
But the important part
is that Create ML components
gives you access to these
components independently.
You can add, remove, or switch
components to compose new tasks.
I'm going to represent
components as boxes.
Arrows represent
the flow of data.
Let's zoom into the first step
of the image classifier:
feature extraction.
Generally, feature extractors
reduce the dimensionality
of the input by keeping
only the interesting parts --
the features.
In the case of images,
a feature extractor
looks for patterns in the image.
Create ML uses
Vision Feature Print,
which is an excellent
image-feature extractor
provided
by the Vision Framework.
Now, let's talk about
the second piece:
the classifier.
A classifier
uses a set of examples
to learn a classification.
Some common implementations
are logistic regression,
boosted trees,
and neural networks.
So training an image classifier
starts with annotated images,
goes to annotated features,
and ends with the classifier.
But why do we want
to break it into pieces?
The reason is we want
to expand the possibilities.
Maybe you want
to do some preprocessing
by increasing the contrast.
Or maybe you want
to normalize all images
so they have uniform brightness
before you extract features.
Or maybe you want to try
a different feature extractor.
Or maybe you want
to try a different classifier.
The possibilities are endless.
These are just
a few of the options.
That's why we've added
support for ML components
in macOS, iOS, iPadOS, and tvOS.
Our hope is that you can
compose new models
using some of the components
we provide
together with
your own components,
or even components built
by others in the community.
And you can leverage it
across all of our platforms.
Here are some of the components
built into Create ML Components.
But let me take a step back
and introduce some concepts.
There are two types
of components:
transformers and estimators.
A transformer is simply a type
that is able to perform
some transformation.
It defines an input type
and an output type.
For example, an image-feature
extractor takes an input image
and produces a shaped
array of features.
An estimator, on the other hand,
needs to learn from data.
It takes input examples,
does some processing,
and produces a transformer.
We call this process "fitting."
Great. With those concepts
out of the way,
let me talk about
how Create ML Components
lets you build
an image classifier
from its individual components
using composition.
This is an image classifier
using components.
It has ImageFeaturePrint
as the feature extractor
and LogisticRegressionClassifier
as the classifier.
Regardless of
whether a component
is a transformer
or an estimator,
you combine them using
the appending method.
And this is where components
provide unlimited possibilities.
You can use a fully connected
neural network as a classifier
instead of logistic regression
with a simple change.
Or you can use a custom feature
extractor in a CoreML model.
For example,
the headless ResNet-50 model
you can find
in the model gallery.
When composing two components,
the output
of the first component
must match
the input of the second.
In the case
of our image classifier,
the output of the feature
extractor is a shaped array,
from the CoreML framework.
Which is also the input of a
logistic regression classifier.
If you get a compiler error
when using the appending method,
this is the first thing
to check.
Make sure the types match.
But let me clarify an important
point around fitting.
I said before that fitting
is the process
of going from an estimator
to a transformer.
Let's look at this
from the perspective
of a composed estimator.
When your composed estimator
has both transformers
and estimators,
like in the case
of the image classifier,
only the estimator pieces
are fitted.
But the transformers are
an important part of the process
because they are used
to feed the correct features
to the estimator's
fitted method.
Here is the code.
The image classifier
needs a collection
of annotated features
where the features are images
and the annotations are strings.
We'll talk about
loading the features
when we go into the demo.
Once I have the data,
I can call the fitted method.
This returns the trained model,
a transformer.
And it's important to note
that the types used
when fitting are related
but different
from the types
of the resulting transformer.
In particular, the types used
in the fitted method
are always collections.
And in the case
of supervised estimators,
the features must include
the annotations.
Create ML Components
uses the AnnotatedFeature type
to represent a feature
along with its annotation.
Once I have the model,
I can do predictions.
It doesn't matter
if it's a model I just fitted,
or if I'm loading
the parameters from a disk.
The API is the same
in both cases.
Since I am training
a classifier,
the result is
a classification distribution.
The distribution includes
a probability for each label.
In this case, I'm just printing
the most likely label
for the image.
The fitted method
also provides a mechanism
to observe training events,
including validation metrics.
In this example,
I'm passing validation data
and printing
the validation accuracy.
Note that only
supervised estimators
provide validation metrics.
Once you train a model,
you can save
the learned parameters,
either to reuse later
or to deploy to an app.
You do this using
the write method.
Later, you can read
using the read method.
And that's composition.
This is where
it gets interesting.
Let me talk about
writing a new task,
something that Create ML
didn't support until now.
What if you wanted to train
a model to score images?
Let's say you have
photos of fruit,
but instead of
classifying the fruit,
you wanted to rate it.
Give it a score
based on how ripe it is.
To do this,
you need to do regression
instead of classification.
So let me write
an image regressor
that gives a score to images
of bananas based on ripeness.
I'll give each image a ripeness
value between one and 10.
An image regressor is very
similar to an image classifier.
The only difference
is that our estimator
is going to be a regressor
instead of a classifier.
As you may have
already guessed,
this is going to be easy.
To refresh your memory,
here is our image classifier.
And this is an image regressor.
I substituted the logistic
regression classifier
with a linear regressor.
This simple change
also changes the expected input
to the fitted method.
Before, it expected
images and labels.
Now, it expects
images and scores.
But enough about concepts.
Let me demo this
with some actual code.
Let me show you how to write
a custom image regressor.
I'll start by defining
an ImageRegressor struct
to encapsulate the code.
I have a folder
with images of bananas
at different levels of ripeness.
I'm going to start
by defining that URL.
The next step
is to add a train method.
This is where you use
training data
to produce a model.
I'm going to use the "some"
keyword on the return type
so that the return type
doesn't change
as I add or modify steps
in the composed estimator.
Now, I'm going to define
the estimator.
It's simply
the feature extractor
with the linear regressor
appended.
And now, I need to load
the training images
with their score.
I can use AnnotatedFiles,
which is a collection
of AnnotatedFeatures containing
URLs and string labels.
It provides a convenience
initializer that fits my needs.
My files consist of a name,
followed by a dash,
followed by the ripeness value.
So I'm going to specify
that the separator is a dash
and the annotation
is at index: 1
of the filename components.
I'm also going to request
only image files
by using the type argument.
Now that I have URLs,
I need to load the images.
I can use
the mapFeatures method
and the ImageReader to do this.
I also need
to convert the scores
from strings
to floating point values.
I can use the mapAnnotations
method to do this.
And with that,
I have the training data.
But I want to put some of it
aside for validation.
I can use the randomSplit
method to do this.
I'll keep 80 percent
for training
and use the rest for validation.
Now, I'm ready to fit.
And I'm going to save
the trained parameters
so that I can deploy to my app.
I'll choose a location
to save to.
And I'll call the write method.
Finally,
I'll return the transformer.
This is the essence
of defining and training a model
using components.
I defined
my composed estimator,
I loaded my training data,
I called the fitted method,
and I used write
to save the parameters.
But there are some things
I can improve.
For starters, I am passing
a validation data set
but not observing
the validation error,
so I'll do that.
The fitted method
takes an event handler
that you can use
to gather metrics.
For now, I'll just print
both the training
and validation
maximum-error values.
I also want the mean absolute
error for the final model.
I compute that by applying
the fitted transformer
to the validation features
and then passing that along
with the actual scores
to the meanAbsoluteError
function.
I ran this but I didn't get
a great model -
the error was high.
This is because I don't have
that many images of bananas.
I should get more images,
but before I do that,
I can try augmenting my dataset.
I can rotate and scale my images
to get more examples.
To do this, I'm going to write
a new method
that takes an annotated image
and augments it.
It returns an array
of annotated images.
The first augmentation
I'm going to do is rotation.
I'll randomly choose an angle
between -pi and pi
and use it to rotate the image.
I'll also do a random scale.
And I'll return three images:
the original, the rotated one,
and the scaled one.
Now that I have
my augment function,
I'll use it to augment my
training images using flatMap.
Each element of my dataset
will be converted to an array.
FlatMap flattens that array
of arrays into a single array,
which is what I need
for the fitted method.
Note that augmentations
only apply when fitting,
not when doing predictions.
OK, this increased my accuracy.
But let me talk about
one more improvement
that is going to make
my model even better.
I want to use
the Vision framework
to crop the images
to the salient object.
This is one of the images
in my training data.
Someone is holding bananas with
other fruits in the background.
The model may get confused by
the other objects in the photo.
Using the Vision framework API,
I can automatically
crop the image
to the most salient object.
To do this, please check out
the Vision talk from WWDC 2019.
I can easily apply this
transformation to all my images,
both when fitting
and when getting predictions
if I write a custom transformer.
Let me show you how.
The only thing I need to do
to conform to
a transformer protocol
is implement the applied method.
And in this case,
I want it to take an image
and return an image.
I'm not going to go
into this code,
except to say that if I don't
get a salient object,
I'll just return
the original image.
Now that I have
my custom transformer,
I'll add it
to my image regressor.
I just need to use
my custom transformer
before feature extraction.
Now that saliency is part of
my task definition,
it will be used to crop
every training image,
and it will also be used
when doing inference.
This is one of the advantages
of sharing the task definition
between training and inference.
Before we go on
to the next task,
let me highlight
some important points.
Using components,
I can now create custom tasks.
I did this by using
the appending method.
I used AnnotatedFiles
to load my files
with annotated file names,
but you can also load files
annotated by directories.
I mapped the URL to images
using ImageReader
and mapped the annotations
from strings to values.
I used randomSplit to set aside
a validation dataset,
and I saved the trained
parameters for use later.
Then I added augmentations
and defined a custom transformer
to improve my model.
But this works for more
than just images.
I'll switch gears and talk about
another type of task:
tabular tasks.
These are tasks
that use tabular data.
Tabular data is characterized
by having multiple features
of different types.
It can include
both numerical data
as well as categorical data.
A popular example is
house-pricing data.
You have things
like area and age,
but also things
like neighborhood,
type of building, et cetera.
And you want to learn
to predict a value;
for example, the sale price.
In 2021, we introduced
the TabularData framework.
Now you can use
the TabularData framework
together with
Create ML Components
to build and train tabular
classifiers and regressors.
I also recommend the tech talk
on TabularData.
It's a great introduction
to data exploration,
which you will likely need
when building a tabular task.
Let's dive in.
When dealing with tabular data,
each column of the table
will have a different
type of feature.
And you may want to process
each column differently,
based on what type of
information it contains;
the distribution,
range of values,
and other factors.
Create ML Components lets you do
this using the ColumnSelector.
Here is an example.
I mentioned house prices,
but those are ridiculous.
I'm going to use
avocado prices instead.
I have this table
of avocado prices.
I want to build
a tabular regressor
to predict avocado prices
based on this.
It contains columns
with numeric data
such as bags, year, and volume
and columns with categorical
data such as type and region.
Some regressors
benefit from having
a better representation
of these values.
For instance,
this is the distribution of
volume values in the dataset.
It is close to
a normal distribution,
but with large values
centered around 15,000.
I think this is
a great example of a dataset
that could benefit
from normalization.
So the first thing I want to do
is normalize these values.
To do this, I can pass the
column names I want to normalize
to the ColumnSelector
and then use a standard scaler.
Here is the code.
First I create
a column selector.
Then I pass the column names
I want to scale.
All columns must contain
the same type of element;
in this case, Double.
Then I unwrap optionals.
I can do this because I know
there are no missing values.
But I could also use an imputer
which replaces missing values.
And then I append
the StandardScaler
to the unwrapper.
So I started with this table
where bags numbers
were in the tens of thousands
and volumes were in
the hundreds of thousands.
And after scaling those columns,
I end up with values that now
have a magnitude close to one,
which could improve
the performance of my model.
To be more specific, my values
now have a mean of zero
and a standard deviation of one.
Here is a similar example,
but in this example,
I'm selecting the type
and region columns,
which are of type string and
performing a one-hot encoding.
One-hot encoding refers
to encoding categorical data
using an array to indicate
the presence of each category.
In this example,
I have three categories:
Bronze, Silver, and Gold.
Each gets a unique position
within the array,
indicated by a one
in that position.
An alternative is to use
an ordinal encoder,
which gives a consecutive
number to each category.
Use a one-hot encoder when
there are only a few categories
and an ordinal encoder
otherwise.
Now let me put all this together
and build a tabular regressor.
As before,
I'll start creating a struct
and defining the data URL
and the parameters URL.
I also want to define
a column ID
for the column
I want to predict: price.
I'll define my task separately
so that I can use it
both from the train method
and the predict method.
As I mentioned, I'm going
to normalize the volume.
Then I'm going to use
a boosted tree regressor
to predict the price.
It takes the name
of the annotation column --
which is also the column
of the resulting predictions --
and it takes the names
of all three feature columns.
I'll start with
these three columns.
Then I'll combine the pieces
using the appending method
and return the task.
Now that I have
my task definition,
I'll add a train method
as before.
And as before, I want to make
sure that the return type
doesn't depend
the specifics of my model.
The first step is to load
the CSV file into a data frame.
I'm using the TabularData
framework to do this.
And as before, I want to split
off some of the data
for validation.
I'll pass the training
and validation datasets
to the fitted method.
I'll also report validation
error as before,
and I'll save the trained
parameters for use later.
Finally, I'll return
the transformer.
Once I have
a trained transformer,
I can use it to make price
predictions on data frames.
I'm going to write
a predict method to do this.
I'll start by loading the model
from the task definition
and the parameters URL.
I need to make sure the data
frame I use for predictions
has the columns
I used as features:
type, region, and volume.
The predicted value
will be in the price column.
I'll use the column ID
I defined at the top.
And that concludes
my tabular regressor.
I have a train method,
that I only need to call once
to produce my trained
parameters,
and a predict method
that returns the avocado price,
predictions based on the type,
region, and the
volume of avocados.
That's all I need
to use this in my app.
Here are some things
to keep in mind
when working on tabular tasks.
You can use
ColumnSelector operations
to process specific columns.
It's worth noting that
tree classifiers and regressors
are all tabular, but you can
also use a nontabular estimator,
such as a linear regressor,
in a tabular task using
AnnotatedFeatureProvider.
Please refer
to the documentation.
When doing predictions,
build a data frame
with the required columns,
making sure to use
the correct types.
Now that you know
how to build a custom task,
let's talk about deployment.
So far, I've used the same API
for training and inference.
I want to point out that when
using Create ML Components,
your model is your code.
You need the task definition,
even when loading the trained
parameters from a file.
This is useful
in some situations,
but sometimes you may want
to use Core ML for deployment.
When using Core ML,
you leave the code behind.
The model is fully represented
by a model file.
If you are
all ready using Core ML,
this may be a good workflow.
And it has the advantage
of optimized tensor operations.
But there are
some considerations
you should keep in mind.
Not all operations
are supported in Core ML.
Specifically, custom
transformers and estimators
are not supported.
And Core ML only supports
a few types
like images and shaped arrays.
If you are using custom types,
you may need to convert
those in your app
when using the Core ML model.
This is how you can export your
transformer as a Core ML model.
If your transformer contains
unsupported operations,
this will throw an error.
If you'd rather stick with
deploying your task definition
along with
the trained parameters,
you should consider bundling
them in a Swift package.
This way, you can provide simple
methods to load the parameters
and perform a prediction.
For more information
on Swift package resources,
check out the Swift packages
talk from WWDC 2020.
That's all I have.
The main thing to remember
is that you can now create
custom tasks with composition.
The possibilities are endless.
I look forward to seeing
what you build.
For more advanced techniques,
including audio and video tasks,
check out
"Compose advanced models
with Create ML Components"
where my colleague David
will present
more advanced custom tasks.
Thank you and enjoy the rest
of WWDC 2022!
♪