♪ ♪
Hello and welcome.
My name is Kelvin Chiu from
the GPU Software team here at Apple.
Today, I'll talk about how to
boost your Metal application performance
with MetalFX Upscaling.
MetalFX is a new API that provides
platform optimized graphics effects
for Metal applications.
It enables high performance upscaling,
which will boost
your application performance
while retaining its rendering quality.
Rendering a frame
at high resolution costs GPU time.
To reduce that time,
rendering at a lower resolution will
usually do the trick.
However, the tradeoff is
a lower rendering quality.
With MetalFX Upscaling,
your application can now render frames
at a lower resolution,
reducing rendering time,
without compromising rendering quality.
MetalFX Upscaling is optimized
to run best on Apple devices.
and it is also easy
to adopt in your game.
MetalFX provides
two upscaling effects,
which I will describe in detail.
Spatial upscaling is simple to use
and gives a great performance boost.
Temporal anti-aliasing
and upscaling integrates information
from multiple frames
to produce a higher quality output.
I will then talk about best practices
for using these effects.
Finally, I will end the session
with demos showing them in action.
Let's start with Spatial upscaling.
MetalFX Spatial upscaling
analyzes the input’s spatial information
to produce new, upscaled samples.
Integrating Spatial upscaling is simple.
It only requires anti-aliased
input color to produce
a spatially upscaled color output.
In a typical game rendering pipeline,
there are various rendering passes
including anti-aliased render
and various post processing effects.
Add MetalFX spatial upscaling
right after
the game's tone-mapping process
is completed.
It will perform best if the input
has been tone mapped and is
in a perceptual color space.
Let’s checkout MetalFX
spatial upscaling in action.
This chess scene is produced
with a high quality reference renderer
in 4K resolution.
It is path traced,
with complex graphics effects,
like ray-traced reflections and shadows.
Here is a side by side comparison,
with 540p input on the left...
…and 1080p output with MetalFX
spatial upscaling on the right.
If I zoom in on the queen, on the left,
the image lacks details
and is low resolution.
On the right,
the spatially upscaled output
has sharper reflections
and more refined edges.
Next, I'll walk you through how
to implement MetalFX spatial upscaling.
In Metal, you would
normally create a command encoder
to encode commands into a command buffer
and produce input for the effect.
Similarly,
you can create a MetalFX effect object
to encode commands into a command buffer
and perform the effect.
Finally, create a third command encoder
to encode commands
that make use of the MetalFX output.
You should only create
a new spatial scaler object
when your application first starts
or when a display switches resolutions
because they are expensive to create.
First, create and configure
a MTLFXSpatialScalerDescriptor.
Then, create a scaler object
by calling the makeSpatialScaler() method.
In the initialization code,
start with the descriptor.
Fill both the width and height
of the input and output texture.
Then, set the texture format
for the textures that will be set later
on the scaler object.
Set the color processing mode.
This tells the API which color space
the input and output is in.
You can set the value
to be in either perceptual,
linear, or HDR color space.
Once the descriptor is filled,
create the scaler object.
Once the scaler object is created,
you can modify the properties
of the object as frequently as you want
and call the encode() method
to start the upscaling process.
In your per frame draw code,
make sure the correct input
and output textures are being set
on the scaler object
before encoding the scaling effect
into the command buffer.
Spatial upscaling offers
a simple way to boost performance.
And when you want
even higher quality rendering,
that's where
MetalFX temporal anti-aliasing
and upscaling comes in.
Temporal AA and upscaling
is a technique that uses data
from previous frames to produce
high-quality upscaled output.
This means, the output of upscaling
from the previous frame
will be used as one of the inputs
for the current frame upscaling.
To better understand why Temporal AA
and upscaling requires data
from the previous frames,
I'll first review the concept
of supersampling.
In supersampling,
multiple samples are calculated per pixel,
which is then integrated
into a single pixel value.
The more samples
that we integrate per pixel,
the better the result will be.
However, it comes at a great cost
to calculate multiple samples per pixel
within a single frame.
Instead of sampling multiple locations
per pixel in a single frame,
you can perform temporal sampling.
Temporal sampling
is the concept of rendering
a different sample location
for all the pixels in a given frame.
This enables you to achieve
supersampling quality
over multiple frames
at a significantly lower cost.
By accumulating samples
from multiple frames and accounting
for sample positions,
temporal AA & upscaling can
integrate samples appropriately
in target resolution pixels,
resulting in a high quality
anti-aliased upscaled output.
However, since content
often changes between frames,
it will require more input data
to detect these changes.
Besides the previous frame output,
Temporal AA and upscaling also requires
a color input that is jittered,
as well as motion
and depth data from the scene.
I'll go through each of them
to explain why they are required.
Let's start with the jittered color input.
Here is a red triangle rendered
without jitter.
The bright white outline represents
the triangle being rendered.
Each one of the small squares
represent a pixel.
And the gray dot in the middle
is where the pixel is sampled.
This is the output of the same triangle
when rendered with a small jitter.
The gray dots show
the sampling location for a given pixel.
The jitter offset should be unique
for a set number of frames
in order to fully gather
the desired number of samples.
I will cover the topic
of jitter sequence in detail later.
Next is the motion information
from the scene.
Motion data from the scene indicates
how much and which direction
the objects had moved
from the previous frame.
Temporal AA and upscaling uses
the motion information to back track
and find corresponding locations
in the previous frame
in order to correctly gather samples.
Another input is the depth information
from the scene.
Depth data from the scene
indicates what's in the foreground
and what's in the background.
This is important when prioritizing
foreground edge anti-aliasing
and provides clues on what
other objects might be newly exposed
when gathering samples
from previous frames.
The last piece of input data is
the previous frame’s output.
The previous frame’s output contains all
of the samples that have been
integrated previously,
and it will be blended with
the current frame’s jittered color input
in order to increase the number
of samples per pixel.
By combining information
from both the current and previous frame,
the resulting image now has more details.
MetalFX keeps track
of the upscaled output,
so you only need to pass the color,
motion, and depth
from the current rendered frame.
Going back to a typical
game’s rendering pipeline,
MetalFX temporal AA
and upscaling should run
before any post processing effects,
since these effects will interfere
with the result of the upscaling.
Here's the chess rendering again,
this time using
MetalFX Temporal AA and upscaling.
This is a side by side comparison
of 1080p input on the left
and 4K upscaled output on the right.
Zooming in closer to the queen,
the input is low resolution and aliased,
while the temporally upscaled output
on the right is high resolution
with a smooth outline and has
more fine details in the reflections.
Just as with spatial scaler,
creating a new temporal scaler
is expensive and should only be done
when your application first starts
or when a display switches resolutions.
First, you'll need to allocate and fill in
a MTLFXTemporalScalerDescriptor.
Then call makeTemporalScaler() method
to create the scaler object.
In your initialization code,
start with the descriptor.
Fill in both the width and height
of the input and output textures.
Then set the jittered color,
depth, and motion texture formats
for the textures that will be bound later
on the scaler object as inputs.
Finally, set the format
for the output texture
where MetalFX will store
the upscaled output.
Once the descriptor is filled,
create the scaler object.
On the scaler object,
set the motion scale properties.
This helps you scale the app's motion data
to what the API expects.
MetalFX expects motion data
in the render resolution pixel space
with direction that goes
from the current frame’s position
to the previous frame’s position.
As an example,
I'll use a render resolution of 1080p.
Suppose you have an object
that moves from clip space coordinate
(-0.75, -0.75).
to clip space coordinate (0.25, 0.25).
The motion data is stored as (1, 1).
Set the motion vector scale property
to (-960, 540)
so that MetalFX can interpret
your game's motion data correctly.
You can modify the properties
of the scaler object as frequently
as you want.
And call the encode() method
to start the upscaling process.
For your per frame draw code,
first set the resetHistory property.
Set this to true when your application
loads the first frame
or when there is a scene cut.
Then set the textures
that are inputs for the effect,
followed by the output texture.
Next, set the reversedDepth property
to indicate whether the depth values are
in reversed-Z mapping.
The last property to set
before encoding the scaling effect
is the current jitter offset.
Getting jitter offset correctly
is essential
to the quality of the output.
Let us take a quick look
on how to set jitter offset.
As an example, on the left
is a triangle rendered with jitter.
On the right
is a zoomed in view of a pixel.
The sample is located at (0.625, 0.78).
The pixel center is represented
by the orange dot.
It is located at (0.5, 0.5).
In this example,
the jitter offset is (-0.125, -0.28).
Note that jitter offsets are always
in the range of -0.5 to 0.5.
To verify that you are providing
the correct jitter offset,
render a scene
without camera and object motion
using a sequence
of different jitter offsets.
On the left is an example
when incorrect jitter offset is specified.
Static objects could shift,
and fine lines are fuzzy.
On the right is the output
when correct jitter offset is specified.
Objects stay in place,
and fine lines are resolved progressively.
The MetalFX
“temporal AA and upscaling” effect
boosts your application performance
and gives an upscaling quality
that’s comparable to the quality
of the native target resolution rendering.
In order to get optimal quality
and performance
when using both upscaling effects,
l’ll now cover
implementation best practices.
Starting with spatial upscaling.
For the best spatial upscaling quality,
the color input should be
anti-aliased and noise free.
This is because noise effects
and aliased images
prevent good edge determination,
which will worsen
the spatial upscaling quality.
For the best performance,
use the perceptual color processing mode.
This means,
your input color should be tone mapped,
with values from 0-1,
in the sRGB color space.
And finally,
set the appropriate negative mip bias
for higher texture detail.
The recommended mip bias calculation
for spatial upscaling is to apply log2
of the render resolution width,
divided by the target resolution width.
For example,
scaling each render resolution dimension
by 2x will result in -1 mip bias,
while scaling each dimension by 1.5x
will result in -0.58 mip bias.
Note that lower mip levels
might result in flickering for textures
with high frequency patterns.
You should adjust the mip bias
for certain textures
if you spot such artifacts.
I will talk next about TemporalAA
and upscaling best practices.
To get the best quality
from Temporal AA and upscaling,
it's important to choose
a good jitter sequence.
Look for a jitter sequence
that will provide
a good distribution of samples
across all the pixels
in an upscaled target resolution.
Usually, eight jittered samples
per output pixel
produces a high-quality
anti-aliased upscaled output.
In the case of 2x upscaling,
the recommendation is to use
a Halton (2,3) sequence with 32 jitters
to produce your jittered color input.
Here’s a plot
of the first 32 sample locations
from Halton (2,3) sequence,
producing approximately
eight samples per output pixel.
It's also important to set
the appropriate negative mip bias
for higher texture detail.
The recommended mip bias calculation
for temporal AA and upscaling
is to apply log2
of render resolution width,
divided by target resolution width,
subtracted by 1.
For example,
scaling each render resolution dimension
by 2x will result in a -2 mip bias,
while scaling each dimension
by 1.5x will result in a -1.58 mip bias.
Next, I will show you examples
of how mip bias affects your output
in different situations.
Here are MetalFX temporal AA
and upscaling outputs of the same scene
using mip bias of 0, -1, and -2.
Mip bias of -2 produces
the sharpest and clearest output,
while mip bias of 0 produces
the softest and most blurry output.
Here are three renderings
of a circuit board
that use the temporal upscaling effect.
From top to bottom,
the mip bias values applied
when sampling textures are 0,
-1, and -2.
Because the circuit board’s textures
have high-frequency patterns,
such as its tiny trace wires,
mip bias of -2 generates flickering
and moire effects.
However, mip bias of -1
greatly reduces these effects,
and mip bias of 0
completely eliminates them.
Lower mip levels
generally result in more details.
Use our mip bias suggestion
as a starting point,
but be mindful when choosing a mip bias
for textures with high-frequency patterns.
Follow these practices
to ensure an anti-aliased,
high-quality upscaled output
from MetalFX Temporal AA and upscaling.
Finally, I will cover
performance best practice
when using MetalFX Upscaling.
To get the best performance
with MetalFX Upscaling,
you should be careful
to avoid binding the same resources
for reading and writing
in two non-dependent render
or compute passes.
Doing so creates false dependencies.
In Metal, it's always a good idea
to avoid false dependencies.
But this is especially important
for MetalFX Upscaling,
as I will describe next.
In this example, there are two frames.
The shadow and the post processing passes
are completely unrelated
and have no resource dependencies.
Metal will overlap the next frame’s
shadow pass
with the current frame’s
post processing pass.
However,
if the post processing pass writes
to a Metal buffer while the shadow pass
also reads from the same buffer,
Metal will prevent the GPU
from running these two passes
in parallel in order
to avoid the potential hazard of reading
and writing to the same resource
at the same time.
False dependencies between frames
can negatively affect performance
of MetalFX Upscaling.
Notice that if there is no
false dependency between frames,
the next frame’s shadow pass
could have overlapped
with the previous frame's MetalFX Upscaling.
However, because of the false dependency
between frames,
the performance loss now
also includes the time
it takes for MetalFX Upscaling
to finish its process.
Ideally, you should ensure that
there are no false dependencies
between frames to allow overlapping
of workloads between different frames,
ensuring the most optimal performance
when using MetalFX Upscaling.
In this example,
you can instead create a separate buffer
for the post processing and shadow passes
to prevent the false dependency,
resulting in parallel execution
of independent passes.
Avoiding false dependencies
is something you always want
to keep in mind
when adopting MetalFX Upscaling.
When deciding which
of these two effects to choose,
there are some considerations
you should also keep in mind.
With ever-increasing shading costs
and pixel counts,
temporal AA and upscaling
is here to stay.
Amortizing pixels temporally
increases visual fidelity
and boosts performance.
If you don’t already have
a great temporal AA solution
and can render jittered color,
motion, and depth buffers,
MetalFX temporal AA and upscaling provides
a compelling platform-optimized solution
that you should consider.
If you don’t have the necessary inputs
or already have a well tuned AA solution,
consider using MetalFX spatial upscaling.
With that, hopefully you now
have a better understanding
of which upscaling effect to choose.
I will next show examples
of both of these effects running live
in Metal applications.
Here’s a side by side comparison
of the “Bistro” scene
from our “Modern Rendering with Metal”
sample code,
which features
real-time rendering algorithms,
like ambient occlusion and volumetric fog.
Native rendering at 1080p on the left
versus 4K output
with MetalFX Spatial upscaling
on the right.
Note that this sample has
its own temporal anti-aliasing solution,
which we use as input
for MetalFX spatial upscaling.
Zooming in more closely at the scooter...
On the left, the image is a bit blurry,
while on the right,
the spatially upscaled output results
in a sharper image with cleaner edges.
The straight line
on the handle bar is nicely antialiased.
The curve on the body
is also much smoother.
Let's do a performance comparison.
On the left is a native rendering at 4K.
On the right is the 4K output
from MetalFX Spatial upscaling.
As the camera moves,
the native rendering on the left
is running at a choppy frame rate,
while the spatially upscaled output
on the right is much smoother.
Next is a side-by-side comparison
of a ray-traced scene
with many reflections and shadows.
On the left is
a native rendering at 1080p.
On the right is the 4K output
with MetalFX Temporal AA and upscaling.
Zooming in more closely
at the chandelier...
The native output
on the left has an aliased look,
while the temporally upscaled output
on the right
has sharp edges with more fine details.
The shadow is nice and crisp
rather than fuzzy looking.
And fine details on the chandelier
can now be recognized.
Performance gains are also apparent
with MetalFX Temporal AA and upscaling.
On the left is native rendering at 4K.
On the right is the 4K output
with MetalFX Temporal AA and upscaling.
As the camera moves,
the native rendering on the left
is running at a very low frame rate,
while the temporally upscaled output
on the right is much smoother.
Leading game developers are excited
by the capabilities of MetalFX Upscaling
and will be bringing "Grid: Legends,"
"Resident Evil: Village,"
and "No Man’s Sky" to Mac later this year.
Next, I’ll show you some early work
using the framework.
[rumbling and impacts]
In this scene,
we can see the incredible visuals
and fluid gameplay of "No Man’s Sky"
using MetalFX Temporal AA and Upscaling.
[ship beeps]
[engine rumbles]
To recap,
MetalFX is a new API
with a focus on upscaling.
Spatial upscaling is easy to adopt
and delivers
substantial performance gains,
and you can use Temporal AA and upscaling
to deliver higher quality rendering.
Following the best practices
I talked about earlier will ensure
you get the most out of MetalFX Upscaling.
Thank you for watching.
♪ ♪