♪ ♪
Hello and welcome.
I'm Galo Avila,
engineering manager in GPU Software.
In this session,
Eylon and I are excited to share
how you can improve your app's GPU
binary generation with Metal 3.
First, I'll describe
how offline compilation can help you
reduce in app stutters,
first launch, and new level load times.
Then Eylon will explain how you can use
the optimize for size compiler option,
to tune code expanding transformations
and improve your compile times.
Offline compilation lets you move GPU
binary generation to project build time.
To fully understand the benefits adoption
can bring to your Metal application,
I'll start by reviewing the ways in which
you can already generate a GPU binary.
In your Metal app, GPU binary generation
happens both at build time and runtime.
For example, suppose you instantiate
a metal library from source.
This generates at app runtime
Apple's Intermediate Representation,
also known as AIR.
This can be a CPU intensive operation,
which you can move to app build time
by pre-compiling your source
to a Metal library,
and instantiating from a file instead.
Once your Metal library is in memory,
creating a Pipeline State Descriptor
containing state and functions
is a lightweight operation.
Until you create
your pipeline state object,
which can be another
CPU intensive operation,
where just-in-time
GPU binary generation takes place.
Since GPU binary generation at runtime
can be a CPU intensive operation,
Metal helps you speed up
pipeline state object creation.
When you instantiate a PSO,
Metal stores your GPU binaries
in its file system cache.
And every time a new PSO is created,
any newly generated functions are added.
So any previously generated binaries
that are referenced
will be loaded from the cache.
Metal also lets you explicitly control
when and where GPU binaries are cached
using Binary Archives.
Simply use a PSO descriptor
to cache a GPU binary in an archive,
as many times as you need.
Then your PSO creation becomes
a lightweight operation.
Binary archives enable
more flexible caching,
but they still have to be
generated at runtime.
In many cases,
what you really want
is to generate those archives
at build time,
and now you finally can.
With offline binary generation,
you specify a new artifact
at project build time
called Metal pipelines script,
along with Metal source
or a Metal library.
A pipelines script
is your compiler toolchain equivalent
to a collection of pipeline descriptors
in the API.
The output of your compilation process
is a binary archive.
No further GPU code generation
takes place at app runtime.
Merely load your binary archive built
offline to accelerate your PSO creation.
Offline compilation benefits your app
by reducing runtime CPU overhead,
which is at the core
of what makes Metal a low level API.
Further, adoption can improve your app's
experience in two noticeable ways.
First launch and new level load times
can become dramatically faster,
potentially resulting in greater
engagement and interaction.
Stutters or frame rate drops,
due to runtime compilation
can be removed at last,
without the memory
or CPU cost of pre-warming frames.
I'll explore these benefits
in more detail next.
Here you have your traditional
app runtime binary generation.
In this example, your app spends
roughly 2/3 of its time
compiling GPU binaries
behind a loading screen,
before you can begin interacting with it.
But with offline compilation your runtime
shader generation moves to app build time,
PSO creation happens
in a fraction of the time,
and you are able to interact
with your app sooner
instead of idling away at a load screen.
Offline compilation
also helps to reduce stutters.
With traditional
runtime binary generation,
you may have too many pipeline states
to create at load time,
so you might instead be creating
some just-in-time.
And when that happens,
you may experience frame drops
caused by compilation temporarily
interrupting your command encoding.
Offline compilation
removes those pesky bubbles,
because you can compile many more shaders
at app build time.
Next, I will share
a new developer workflow
to help you harness the benefits
of offline compilation.
In the following workflow you'll learn
how to use new toolchain features
to build GPU binaries offline.
I'll show you how to generate
your new pipelines script input artifact.
Then, how to invoke the toolchain
to generate a GPU binary.
A pipelines script artifact is
a JSON formatted description
of one or more API pipeline
state descriptors
and can be generated in many ways.
For example,
author them in your favorite JSON editor,
or Harvest them from binary archives
serialized during development and testing.
Here you have a snippet of Metal code that
generates a render pipeline descriptor
with state and functions
and its equivalent JSON representation.
First, your API metal library file
is specified as a libraries path property.
Then your API render descriptor function
names as render pipelines properties.
Lastly, other pipeline state,
like raster_sample_count
or pixel formats,
are also captured as script properties.
Look for further JSON schema details
in Metal's developer documentation.
You also may want to kickstart
JSON script generation,
and using the Metal runtime can help.
Simply generate
your binary archives at runtime,
and serialize them during your development
and testing process.
Now I'll show you how you can accomplish
this with the Metal API.
You begin the runtime harvesting process
by creating your pipeline descriptor
with state and functions,
adding it to an archive,
which generates GPU binary,
and serializing it
to the file system to import into
and load from your app's bundle.
The Metal 3 runtime stores your pipeline
descriptor alongside the GPU binary.
Now I'll show you how to extract them.
metal-source allows you
to extract your JSON pipelines script
from an existing archive.
This is handy for migrating your binary
generation from runtime to app build time.
Just invoke metal-source
with the flatbuffers
and output directory options.
The result is a pipelines script file,
which you can edit
to generate additional binaries.
Now, I'll show you
how to invoke the toolchain.
Generating a GPU binary from
an Xcode project build phase is easy.
Simply invoke metal as you would
from the terminal with your source,
pipelines script, and output file.
Your output metal library
now contains GPU binary,
and can be deployed across
any toolchain supported device.
And if instead of source,
you have a Metal library,
you can pass that to the toolchain too.
Generating a binary from
a pre-existing Metal library
is just as easy
with Metal translator tool.
Just call metal-tt as you would
in a terminal with your source,
pipelines script, and output file.
Your resulting Metal library
now contains GPU binary
for all toolchain supported devices.
Now that you know
how to create binaries offline,
I'll review how to load them.
Simply provide the binary URL
when creating an archive descriptor
and use it to instantiate an archive.
That's it!
For more information about
Metal's binary archive API,
please refer to our previous years' talks.
Finally, a note on how Metal handles
GPU binary compatibility
for offline generated artifacts.
To ensure your offline generated binaries
are forward compatible
with future OS versions and products.
Metal gracefully upgrades
your binary archives during OS updates
or at app install time.
It does so asynchronously,
and in the background.
I can't wait for you to harness
the benefits of offline compilation
to remove runtime stutters and reduce
first launch and new level load times.
Such improvements can be tangible
to others
and enhance their overall app experience.
Now, over to Eylon.
Eylon: Thanks, Galo.
Next, I'll introduce
the new compile option,
optimize for size.
The Metal compiler optimizes code
aggressively for runtime performance.
Some optimizations
expand the GPU program size,
which may introduce unexpected costs.
For example,
function inlining is an optimization
to avoid the overhead of a function call.
It works by inlining the body
of the called function into the call site.
This example kernel
doesn't look like a lot of code,
but after inlining,
it would contain a copy
of functions 'f' and 'g',
and potentially also of functions
called from 'f' and 'g',
such as helpers
and non-primitive library functions.
Another optimization is loop unrolling,
which inlines additional copies
of a loop body,
to expose parallelism across iterations
and to avoid branching overhead.
The compiler may unroll as few
as two iterations of the loop
or as many as all the iterations of a loop
that has fixed bounds.
When optimizations like these
create a very large program,
the compiler also has to spend
a lot more time compiling it,
and in some situations,
you may prefer to avoid those costs.
Xcode 14 introduces a new Metal
optimization mode: optimize for size.
This mode limits size-expanding
transformations,
such as inlining and loop unrolling,
when the compiler applies
performance optimizations.
The intended benefit
is to keep the GPU binary smaller,
and the compile time shorter,
in cases when default optimization
proves to be too expensive.
When optimizing for size,
it is possible for the result
to have lower runtime performance.
Whether that actually happens
depends on the program,
so you will need to try both
optimization modes and compare.
Optimize for size may not improve size
and compile time for all shaders.
It is most likely to have benefit
for large programs
with deep call paths and loops,
where inlining and unrolling are common.
The option is worth trying
whenever you encounter
an unexpectedly long compile time
from default optimization.
The option is available whether compiling
at project build time or at app runtime.
Here's a case where optimize for size
can make a difference.
Cycles is a an open source project
implementing a production renderer
for the Blender 3D design environment,
and was recently updated to support Metal.
Apple recently joined
the Blender Development Fund,
and one of the things we learned
was that Blender's path tracing algorithms
use large compute shaders,
with many helper functions and loops,
and its compile times
can add up to minutes.
It turns out those are exactly
the kind of shaders that can benefit
from Metal 3's
new optimize for size option.
When rendering these scenes
on an Apple Silicon GPU,
enabling optimize for size
improved Blender's Setup Time,
which includes compiling shader pipelines,
by up to 1.4x.
And it provided that speedup with
little or no degradation in Render Time.
Some renders slowed up to 4%,
and some did not slow at all.
So lower runtime performance is possible.
But in some cases, optimize for size
can also improve runtime performance.
Here's an example.
These are Render Time speedups
for the same scenes
from enabling optimize for size
on Intel GPUs.
The benefit was not just faster compiles,
but also some faster renders,
by up to 1.6x.
How?
Because a smaller GPU program
can avoid some of the runtime penalties
that come with large size:
it may enjoy
fewer instruction cache misses,
or need fewer registers,
which translates to fewer spills to memory
or even more threads in parallel.
Keep in mind, these results
are not typical of all shaders and scenes,
and a performance drop is possible.
For your project, you will need
to evaluate the actual impact
to both compile time
and runtime performance.
You can enable optimize for size
when compiling from Metal source,
in three different environments.
In the Xcode 14 user interface,
specify optimize for size
as a build setting.
Under "Metal Compiler - Build Options"
find the setting "Optimization Level".
Level "Default" optimizes for performance,
as Metal has done in the past.
Level "Size" enables optimize for size.
When compiling Metal source
by command line,
specify optimize for size
using option'-Os'.
The first example specifies the option
to a single compile-and-link command.
The second example
has two compile commands
and specifies the option
to just one of them
to enable it for only some shaders.
The option does not need to be passed
to the link command
or to any subsequent commands.
And you can use optimize for size
either with, or without,
generating a GPU binary using the commands
presented earlier in this talk.
Finally, when compiling Metal source
at app runtime with a Metal Framework API
such as 'newLibraryWithSource',
specify optimize for size
in a 'MTLCompileOptions' object
using property 'optimizationLevel'.
The optimization level
may be 'default' or 'size'.
I hope your project will benefit
from this new optimization mode
in the Metal compiler.
Galo: To wrap up,
I presented offline compilation,
a new workflow for generating GPU binaries
entirely at app build time,
to reduce in-app stutters,
first launch, and new level load times.
Eylon: Then I presented optimize for size,
a new Metal optimization mode
when compiling from source,
to reduce program size and compile time.
Galo: We hope these improvements
help your app or game
deliver an improved user experience.
Eylon: With shorter setup and load times,
fewer stutters,
and new workflows,
thanks to lower compile costs at runtime.
Thank you for watching.  ♪ ♪