♪ ♪
Prashant: Hey, everyone.
I'm Prashant.
I'm an AVFoundation Engineer,
and welcome to WWDC2022.
With the introduction of SharePlay,
you can provide people
with a connected viewing experience
that lets them navigate through
and interact with content in real time
all while staying completely in sync
with the SharePlay group.
However, some of you might have
targeted ads or other interstitials
scheduled in the content timeline,
making it a challenge
to coordinate playback
between participants that receive ads
of different durations
or say between a mixed set of participants
where some receive ads and some don't.
So if you're interested in scheduling ads
and other interstitials
for coordinated playback in SharePlay,
you've tuned in to the right session.
In this talk we'll start by going over
how coordinated playback works.
Then we'll go over the challenges
associated with ads
and other interstitials
in coordinated playback.
Following that, we'll discuss
the different viewing experiences
that are possible when watching ads.
We'll then see how one might achieve these
for stitched-in ads.
And we'll also see how HLS interstitials
work with coordinated playback.
And to conclude,
we'll go over some best practices
that you can use to provide people with
a really compelling SharePlay experience.
Lets see how coordinated playback works
in SharePlay.
So while participants are in
a FaceTime call,
the playback control commands originating
on one participant's device
are shared across group
so that they all play in sync.
While this works well
if all the participants
are watching the same content,
what would happen if some of them
have ads?
Now let's take a look at the case
where Alice and Bob are trying
to watch some program content.
Now what we see here are the presentation
timelines at their respective ends.
If it is only the program content
that they're watching,
then it should be pretty straightforward
to achieve coordinated playback.
You'd simply associate the groupSession
with the playbackCoordinator,
and you'd be good to go.
Now lets say each of them have
a program recap segment stitched in,
which is preceded by the studio
or network banner.
This is fairly typical,
and since the recap segments
and the banners match for Alice and Bob,
coordinated playback is still achievable.
But now,
let's say Alice's geography requires
that the service show some statutory
warnings before the start of the program,
and there might also be ads scheduled
at different points within the program.
It could be that these ads
are of different durations.
We can now see
how this might pose a challenge
when trying to get them to play in sync.
For Bob, the network banner might appear
at the very beginning,
but for Alice, it would appear
only after the warnings are shown.
And if we were to look at some arbitrary
time in the presentation timeline,
they would be watching completely
different portions of the content.
Now let's take a moment to think about
the user experiences
that would be possible
in scenarios such as these.
For this let's consider a simpler timeline
where each of them have
just the single ad stitched in.
In the ideal case,
the experience shouldn't be too different
from where they were watching
the program alone.
For that to be possible, we'd expect
the durations of the ads to match.
This would be
our preferred experience as well.
Now, after watching the ad, both
of them would resume playback in sync.
But sometimes they might get ads
of different durations,
or one of them may not have
any ads at all.
So now, if they were to play in sync,
one of two experiences is possible.
Once Alice finishes her ad,
she can then wait for Bob's ad to finish
before resuming together in sync.
Or she can continue with the main program
and Bob would then jump ahead to catch up
with Alice so that they stay in sync.
In this scenario, Bob would end up
missing some program content
when catching up with Alice.
Now how would you
enable these experiences?
You can specify these waiting policies
at the AVPlaybackCoordinator
by how you populate the
suspensionReasonsThatTriggerWaiting array.
The default behavior is for
the group to not wait
while some of the participants
are watching ads.
When these participants finish their ads,
they would miss some content
to catch up with the rest of the group.
Alternately, if you wish for the group
to wait while the participants watch ads,
you can simply include the
"playingInterstitial" suspension reason
as part of the
suspensionReasonsThatTriggerWaiting array.
With this policy,
when a participant is waiting
for the others to complete their ads,
their player's timeControlStatus would be
waitingToPlayAtSpecifiedRate
and the waitingReason would be
waitingForCoordinatedPlayback.
So going back to the content
described earlier,
how do we define these time ranges
that are to be left out
of the coordinated playback timeline?
For instance,
the statutory warning is something
that only Alice has and Bob doesn't.
And it's also possible that the ad breaks
are of different durations.
You might be aware that HLS offers
two ways of scheduling ads.
One of which would be to directly
stitch in the ad segments
into the primary content's playlists.
So for video on demand content
that has ads stitched in
using discontinuity tags,
you can set the ad time ranges
on the AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
using an AVFoundation API.
So we've added the following
delegate method to–
using which you can specify an array
of sample accurate time ranges
that represent ads
and interstitials in the content.
The AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
would then use this information
to coordinate playback across the group.
When a participant enters this time range,
playback would be coordinated
in accordance with
the waiting policy specified.
Also,
depending on the type of interstitial,
you might allow for someone
to navigate into these time ranges.
So if they were to seek into
these time ranges while in SharePlay,
the entire group would then
snap to the beginning of that time range.
This shows a playlist example
where the ad time ranges
are populated by summing up the times
reported in the EXTINF tags
of the playlists.
This assumes that the durations reported
as part of the EXTINF tags
accurately reflect the media durations
of those segments.
So, now what should the assets look like
for coordinated playback to work?
So if you were to look at this example,
Alice and Bob have different
duration ads stitched in,
resulting in different asset durations.
For these to be considered
SharePlay compatible,
we'd expect the actual content duration
of the assets to match.
Note that this applies only
to video on demand content,
for live content with stitched-in ads,
we'd expect the durations of the ad breaks
to match for all participants.
If you think that it might be a challenge
to obtain the sample accurate time ranges
or if you wish to dynamically schedule
targeted ads in live content,
then you can use
HLS interstitials to schedule ads.
In 2021, we introduced HLS interstitials
which offers a different,
more flexible approach to scheduling ads.
For more details, check out
the Explore dynamic pre-rolls
and mid-rolls in HLS talk from WWDC2021.
In short, ads and interstitials
are treated as separate objects
outside of the content timeline.
These objects can be directly referenced
via their multi variant playlist
and one can perform
Server Side Ad Insertion
simply by including
the multi variant playlist URI
as part of a date range tag
in the primary content's media playlist,
or you even schedule ads on
the client side using AVFoundation APIs.
If you use HLS interstitials
to schedule ads,
AVFoundation automatically takes care
of them during coordinated playback.
All you need to do
is to specify the waiting policy.
When using HLS interstitials
to schedule ads,
once again, we'd expect the primary
content durations to match
across all the participants
for the assets
to be considered SharePlay compatible.
Now let's go over some best practices
that you can use
to provide people with a really good
SharePlay experience.
SharePlay is meant to provide
a seamless connected viewing experience
where people interact with content
as though they were
watching it by themselves.
So with this experience in mind,
one should strive to minimize waits
and content skips as much as possible.
So to this end, it is recommended that
you try to align the ad break durations
such that the wait or skip times
are minimized.
When you have mixed participant groups
where some people have ads
and some don't
and all are watching live content,
you can use HLS interstitials
to schedule the ads
while using the default waiting policy.
Now, if you don't specify
the resume offset while scheduling the ad,
the content would resume at an offset
that equals the ad duration.
In such a scenario
the participant without ads
would continue to watch
the primary content
and the others would join that participant
once they've finished watching their ads.
Here we have Alice, Bob, and Charlie
watching some live content.
Alice being a premium subscriber
to that service does not have any ads,
while Bob and Charlie have ads
of different durations
all scheduled using HLS interstitials.
You can see how Alice continues
to watch the program
while Bob and Charlie sync up with Alice
when they come out of their ad break.
Now if this were a live sports game,
you can imagine how Alice might be
watching the live in-stadium feed
while Bob and Charlie are watching ads.
And when they come out of their ad break,
it would be just in time
for the start of play.
For Video on demand streams,
where participants can't afford
to miss any program content,
you can use the wait - waiting policy.
Now you can share the ad schedule
amongst the participants
using the GroupSessionMessenger.
And when someone is waiting for
the others to finish watching their ads,
you'd now know exactly how long
they would have to wait for
since you've already shared
the schedules.
So now while they're waiting,
you could perhaps use a different player
to show some interesting content,
like the upcoming attractions
in your service to keep them engaged.
To wrap up, in order to schedule ads
and other interstitials
during coordinated playback,
all you need to do
is specify the waiting policy,
and if you have stitched-in ads,
you can set the their time ranges
on the playback coordinator
using the AVFoundation API,
or you could use HLS interstitials to let
AVFoundation manage the playback of ads.
The ideal scenario would involve all
participants watching the same content.
As much we'd like for this to be possible,
this may not always be the case.
You could have a premium subscriber tier
that receive no ads
and you might also have participants
receiving ads of different durations.
In scenarios such as these,
your premium subscribers
don't have to be
staring at a waiting screen.
You could show them some
interesting content as we saw earlier
or you could even build other experiences
to keep them entertained.
For more ideas on how to build
custom experiences in SharePlay,
check out the
Make a great SharePlay experience talk.
Hope you found this session informative.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC.
Thank you.