♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Angela.
And I'm Becca.
Welcome
to what's new in Swift!
We're really excited
to talk to you today
about all of the great
new features in Swift 5.7.
Many of the things
we'll talk about today
demonstrate Swift's goal to make
your life as a developer easier.
We'll look at new tooling
to help you customize
your workflow
and some amazing
under-the-hood improvements.
Then we'll talk about the latest
in Swift's concurrency model
and the road to Swift 6,
including full-thread safety.
Then I'll finish up
by taking you through
some language improvements
that make Swift easier to read
and write, including cleaner,
simpler generics,
and powerful new
string processing facilities.
But first,
let's start by talking about
one of the things
that makes Swift so special --
all of you.
Your input and contributions
are what have enabled Swift
to expand so rapidly.
Community involvement
is at Swift's core.
This year, more of the Swift
project became available
to the community when docC --
the documentation generation
tool announced last year --
and the Swift.org website
were open sourced.
Open source works best
when you have an active
community shepherding it.
We've been using the workgroup
model for Swift on Server
and Diversity in Swift
to provide stewardship
and support
for community members
interested in specific areas.
This has been working
really well
so we've started
two new workgroups.
One for iterating
on the Swift website
and making it more
of a community resource,
and another
for C++ interoperability,
to shape the design of the model
between C++ and Swift.
As we venture into new areas,
we all need support
from members
within the community.
As a part of that, the
Diversity in Swift workgroup
introduced the Swift
Mentorship Program last year.
The program provides pathways
to contribute to all
of the workgroup areas
for folks who don't know
how to start
or are looking to deepen their
expertise in a particular area.
Last year's program
was a huge success.
There were a lot
of interested mentees;
and with that, we were able
to create 41 mentorship pairs.
This success is why the program
is being brought back
for year two.
The program would love
to include everyone
who's interested;
but to do that, we need you --
the excited and experienced
developers listening now
who are ready to share
their breadth of knowledge
and make new connections.
Because the mentorship program
is not just about the code
but about building relationships
within the community.
And a little guidance
can have a lasting effect.
Don't just take my word for it.
Last year, Amrit participated
in the mentorship program
and focused on compiler
and language design.
What started off
as intrigue for Amrit
transformed into
tangible contributions.
Diving into a new domain
is not easy.
Even so, she walked away
finding success
and feeling inspired
to contribute more.
Like many others,
this experience
opened a door for Amrit.
In addition to compiler
and language design,
last year there were a wide
range of available focus areas,
from technical writing
and testing
to contributing
to Swift packages.
This year,
we're adding even more
and there's always opportunities
for new topics.
If you don't see something
in this list that interests you,
you can still mention it
in your application.
Another addition is that
this year's program will offer
mentorship year-round
for starter bug contributions
to help accommodate anyone
who may have a lower capacity
to participate but is still
excited to get involved.
If you're interested
in applying,
or just eager to hear more,
check out the most
recent Swift blog post.
There, you can find links
to detailed reflections
from the highlighted mentees.
The mentorship program
is just one initiative
under Diversity in Swift
umbrella.
To learn more about
the mentorship program
and other Diversity in Swift
efforts,
you can visit
Swift.org/diversity.
To open the door even further,
we want to make it
as easy as possible to use Swift
with the resources you have!
We have streamlined the Swift
toolchain distribution process
for the Linux platform
by adding support
for Linux package formats.
With the new native
toolchain installers,
you can now download RPMs
for Amazon Linux 2
and CentOS 7
directly from Swift.org.
These toolchains
are experimental,
so be sure to share feedback
on the Swift.org forums.
Swift is primarily used
for building apps.
However, the vision has always
been for Swift to be scalable --
used from everything
from high-level scripts
down to bare-metal environments.
To encourage Swift to be used
where it's never
been used before,
Swift underwent some
major changes this year.
To make the standard
library smaller
for standalone,
statically linked binaries,
we dropped the dependency
on an external
Unicode support library,
replacing it with a faster
native implementation.
Smaller, faster binaries
are a huge benefit
when running on
event-driven server solutions.
You get static linking
on Linux by default
to better support containerized
deployments for the server.
This size reduction
makes Swift suitable
for even restricted
environments,
which allowed us to use it
in Apple's
Secure Enclave Processor.
Swift is useful
from apps to servers
all the way down
to restricted processors;
tying it all together
is the package ecosystem.
This year's new features
in Swift packages
will make your life better.
To start, Swift Package Manager
has introduced TOFU.
No, not the delicious snack.
TOFU is an acronym that stands
for Trust On First Use.
It's a new security protocol
where the fingerprint
of a package
is now being recorded
when the package
is first downloaded.
Subsequent downloads
will validate this fingerprint
and report an error if
the fingerprints are different.
This is just one example
of how trust and security
are built into the core
of the package ecosystem
to help you feel
confident using it.
Command plug-ins are a great way
to improve the workflow
for Swift developers.
They are the first step
in providing more extensible
and secure build tools.
Command plug-ins can be used
for documentation generation,
source code reformatting
and more.
Instead of writing your
automation in a shell script
and having to maintain separate
workflows, you can use Swift!
Think open source
formatters and linters.
Now, all of those open source
tools are available within Xcode
and Swift Package Manager.
Command plug-ins are the glue
between open source tools
and Swift Package Manager.
The Swift project
is embracing developer tools
in the open source community
to provide seamless integration
with your automated workflows.
docC is great tool
to integrate documentation
into your source code.
This year, it got even better
with Objective-C and C support.
Let's take a look
at what it would take
to create a plug-in
with docC.
Plug-ins are just
simple Swift code.
You can define a plug-in
by creating a struct
that conforms to
the CommandPlugin protocol.
And then you just add a function
that tells your plug-in
which tool you'd like to invoke.
Within this function
is where we want to call docC.
Once you've defined your
plug-in, it becomes available
through the Swift PM
command line interface
and Xcode as a menu entry.
Now, we can tell Swift PM
to generate documentation
and it knows to pass this action
to the docC executable.
It doesn't stop there.
There's a second plug-in
known as build tool plug-ins.
These plug-ins
are packages that allow you
to inject additional steps
during the build.
When you implement
a build tool plug-in,
that will create a command
for the build system
to execute in a sandbox.
They differ from
command plug-ins
which you execute
directly at any time
and can be granted
explicit permission
to change files in your package.
Build tool plug-ins can be used
for source code generation
or custom processing
for special types of files.
With build tool plug-ins, this
would be the package layout.
In this example,
the plugin.Swift
is the Swift script
that implements
the package plug-in target.
The plug-in is treated
as a Swift executable.
And you write the plug-in
in the same way
you write any
Swift executable.
You can implement
your plug-in by defining
a set of build commands
that tells the build system
what executable command to run
and what outputs are expected
as a result.
Package plug-ins
are secure solutions
that provide extensibility
in your packages.
You can learn more
about how plug-ins work
and how to implement your own
plug-in, in two sessions,
"Meet Swift Package plugins"
and "Create Swift Package
plugins."
As you expand
your use of packages,
you might have encountered
module collisions.
That's when two
separate packages
define a module
with the same name.
To solve this situation,
Swift 5.7 introduces
module disambiguation.
Module disambiguation
is a feature that allows you
to rename modules from outside
the packages that define them.
Here in our
Stunning application,
we're bringing in two packages
that define a Logging module,
so they clash.
To fix this for
our Stunning application,
you'll just need to add
the moduleAliases keyword
to the dependencies section
of your package manifest.
That way you can use
two different names
to distinguish between modules
that previously had
the same name.
Swift 5.7 brings some fantastic
performance improvements.
Let's start
by looking at build times.
Last year, we told you
about how we had rewritten
the Swift Driver --
the program that coordinates
the compilation
of Swift source code in Swift.
Last year's rearchitecture
unlocked some really
important changes
that speed up builds
significantly.
The driver can now be used
as a framework
directly inside
the Xcode build system
instead of
as a separate executable.
This allows it to coordinate
builds more closely
with the build system to allow
things like parallelization.
If you're someone who loves
the sound of quick builds,
you can get
more details in the
"Demystify parallelization
in Xcode builds" session.
To show you
how much faster builds are,
let's look at some examples
of how long it takes to build
some of the tools we use often
that are written in Swift.
On a 10-core iMac,
the improvements have ranged
from 5 percent
all the way up to 25 percent.
Next, there are improvements
to the speed of type checking.
This year, we improved
the type-checker performance
by reimplementing a key part
of the generics system --
the part that computes
a function signature
from things like protocols
and "where" clauses.
In the old implementation,
time and memory usage
could scale exponentially
as more protocols were involved.
For example, here, we have
a complicated set of protocols
that define a coordinate system,
with a lot
of generic requirements
on the many associated types.
Previously, this would take 17
seconds to type-check this code.
But now, in Swift 5.7,
this example is able
to type-check significantly
quicker, in under a second.
We also have some equally
impressive runtime improvements.
Before Swift 5.7, we've seen
protocol checking on app startup
take as long
as four seconds on iOS.
Protocols needed to be computed
every time we launched apps,
resulting in launch times
that got longer
the more protocols you added.
Now, they're cached.
Depending on how an app
was written
and how many protocols it used,
this can mean launch times
being cut in half in some apps
when running on iOS 16.
The session "Improve app size
and runtime performance"
will dive deeper
into how you can leverage
these improvements
in your own application.
Now, it's time for something
I'm sure a lot of you
have been eager to hear about.
Last year, we introduced
the new concurrency model,
bringing together actors
and async/await.
This had a transformative effect
on the concurrency architecture
of your applications.
Async/await and actors are safer
and easier than callbacks
and manual queue management.
This year, we further
fleshed out the model
with data race safety
at the forefront.
Because concurrency
was such a fundamental
and important improvement
to your app's codebase,
we made it possible
to back-deploy these changes
all the way back to iOS 13
and macOS Catalina.
In order to deploy
to older operating systems,
your app bundles a copy of the
Swift 5.5 concurrency runtime
for older OSes.
This is similar
to back-deploying Swift
to operating systems
before ABI stability.
Next, we've taken this model
in new directions.
We've introduced
language features
and supporting packages.
First, let's talk about
data race avoidance.
Before I jump into that,
I should probably
take a step back
and say that one of the really
important features of Swift,
is memory safety by default.
Swift users can't do things
with unpredictable behavior,
like reading a value
while you're in the middle
of modifying it.
In this example, we're removing
all of the numbers in an array
that match
the same array's count.
Initially,
the array's count is 3,
so we'll remove
the 3 from the array.
But once we've done that,
the count will be 2.
Do we remove the 3
and the 2 from the array,
or just the 3?
The answer is neither.
Swift will prevent you
from doing this
because it's not safe
to access the array's count
while you're in the middle
of modifying it.
Our goal is to do something
similar for thread safety.
We envision a language
that eliminates low-level
data races by default.
In other words, we want
to prevent concurrency bugs
that can cause
unpredictable behavior.
Here's another example.
Using the same number's array,
we create a background task
that appends 0 to the array,
and then we remove
the array's last element.
But wait, does removing
the last element
happen before or after
we append 0?
The answer, again, is neither.
Swift will block you from doing
this because it's not safe
to modify the array
from a background task
without synchronizing access
with something like an actor.
Actors were the first major step
towards eliminating data races.
This year we've refined
the concurrency model
to push us even further
towards the end goal.
You can think of each actor
as its own island,
isolated from everything else
in the sea of concurrency.
But what happens when
different threads want to query
the information stored by
each of the isolated actors?
This metaphor will be explored
in depth in the session
"Eliminate data races
using Swift Concurrency."
From memory safety
to thread safety by default;
that is the goal for Swift 6.
To get us there,
we first improved last year's
concurrency model
with the new language features
I just mentioned.
The second thing
I haven't mentioned yet
is the new opt-in safety checks
that identify
potential data races.
You can experiment with
stricter concurrency checking
by enabling it
in your build settings.
Let's take a look
at actors again.
We can take this notion
of actor isolation,
and take it further
with distributed actors.
Distributed actors put those
islands on different machines
with a network between them.
This new language feature makes
developing distributed systems
much simpler.
Let's say you want
to create a game app;
you can now easily write
the back end in Swift.
Here, the distributed actor
is like an actor
but it might be
on a different machine.
In this example,
we're looking at computer player
that will maintain state
during a game with a user.
The distributed keyword can
also be added to a function
that we expect
will need to be called
on an actor that might be
on a remote machine.
Let's add another function
called endOfRound.
It will loop over the players
and call makeMove on each one.
Some of these players
might be local or remote,
but we have the benefit
of not needing to care
about which is which.
The only difference
from a regular actor call
is that a distributed actor
call can potentially fail
because of network errors.
In the event
of a network failure,
the actor method
would throw an error.
So, you need to add
the try keyword
as well as the usual
await keyword that's needed
when you call a function
outside of the actor.
Building on these core
language primitives,
we also built an open source
Distributed Actors package
that is focused on
building server-side,
clustered distributed
systems in Swift.
The package includes an
integrated networking layer
using SwiftNIO and implements
the SWIM consensus protocol
to manage state
across the cluster.
The "Meet distributed actors
in Swift" session
will go into more details
on how to build
distributed systems
with these new features.
We also launched a new set
of open source algorithms
to provide easy out-of-the-box
solutions to common operations
when dealing with AsyncSequence,
which was released
with Swift 5.5.
Releasing these APIs
as a package
gives developers flexibility
in deploying across platforms
and operating system versions.
There are several ways to
combine multiple async sequences
and to group values
into collections.
These are just some
of the algorithms
included in the package.
Check out the "Meet Swift
Async Algorithms" talk
to see how you can use
this new powerful API.
But there's another aspect
of concurrency,
which is performance.
This year,
with actor prioritization,
actors now execute
the highest-priority work first.
And continuing
our deep integration
with the operating system
scheduler,
the model has priority-inversion
prevention built in,
so less important work can't
block higher-priority work.
Historically, it has been
really hard to visualize
the performance impact
of concurrency in your app.
But now, we have a great
new tool for doing exactly that.
The new Swift Concurrency view
in Instruments
can help you investigate
performance issues.
The Swift Tasks
and Swift Actors instruments
provide a full suite of tools
to help you visualize
and optimize
your concurrency code.
At the top level,
the Swift Tasks Instrument
provides useful statistics,
including the number of tasks
running simultaneously
and the total tasks
that have been created
up until that point in time.
In the bottom half
of this window,
you can see what's referred to
as a Task Forest.
It provides a graphical
representation
of the parent-child
relationships
between tasks
in structured concurrent code.
This is just one
of the detailed views
for the Swift Actor
Instrument.
To learn how to use
this exciting new tool,
you'll want to hop over
to the talk
"Visualize and optimize
Swift concurrency."
And don't forget to give
those new packages a try.
Don't be shy to let us know
how it's going on the forums.
Now, I'll hand it over
to Becca to talk about
the many improvements
to Swift language usability.
Languages are tools,
and there's a funny thing
about tools --
they can really affect
the things you build
with them.
When all you have
is a hammer,
you're going to build things
with nails instead of screws.
And even if you have
a full set of tools,
if your hammer has
a big, grippy handle
while your screwdriver
is plasticky and hard to hold,
you might still lean
towards the nails.
A language is the same way.
If Swift has a good tool
for expressing something,
people will use
it more often.
And this year, Swift's tools
for expressing what you want
your code to do
have improved in many ways.
Some of these changes
are simple conveniences
for things you do often.
For example, it's really common
in Swift to use if let
with the same name on both
sides of the equal sign.
After all, there probably
isn't a better name
for the unwrapped value
than the name you gave
the optional one.
But when the name
is really long,
that repetition starts
to get cumbersome.
You might be tempted
to abbreviate the name,
but then your code
becomes kind of cryptic.
And if you later rename
the optional variable,
the abbreviation
might get out of sync.
Swift 5.7 introduces
a new shorthand
for this common pattern.
If you're unwrapping
an optional
and want the unwrapped value
to have the same name,
just drop
the right-hand side.
Swift will assume
it's the same.
And of course, this also
works with guard, too,
and even while,
for that matter.
We also looked at places where
a feature suddenly stops working
when you make
a minor change.
For instance, Swift has always
been able to figure out
what type a call will return
based on the code
written inside
a one-statement closure.
In this compactMap call,
the closure returns the value
of parseLine,
and the parseLine function
returns a MailmapEntry,
so Swift can figure out
that entries should be
an array of MailmapEntry.
This now works for more
complicated closures
that have multiple statements
or control flow features.
So you can use do-catch,
or if...else,
or just add a print call,
without having
to manually specify
the closure's result type.
Another thing
we looked at is danger flags
that aren't really flagging
any actual danger.
Swift is very concerned
with type and memory safety.
To keep you
from making mistakes,
it never
automatically converts
between pointers
with different pointer types,
nor between raw pointers
and typed pointers.
This is very
different from C,
which allows
certain conversions.
For example, you can change
the signed-ness of the pointee,
or cast any pointer to char star
to access it as bytes,
without violating any
of C's pointer rules.
But sometimes these differences
in pointer behavior
will cause problems when
a C API is imported into Swift.
The original developer may
have designed their APIs
with slight mismatches
that are handled
by automatic conversions in C
but are errors in Swift.
In Swift, accessing
a pointer of one type
as though it were a different
type is very dangerous,
so you have to describe what
you're doing very explicitly.
But that's all pointless
if we're passing the pointer
directly to C,
because in C,
that pointer mismatch
is perfectly legal!
So in this case, we've treated
something really straightforward
as though it were dangerous.
This matters because, as much as
Swift values type safety,
it also values easy access
to C-family code.
That's why C
and Objective-C interop
are so rich and seamless,
and it's why the Swift project
formed the C++ working group
Angela mentioned earlier
to start building equally
capable C++ interop.
We don't want
using C functions like these
to be unnecessarily painful.
So Swift now has
a separate set of rules
for calls to imported
functions and methods.
It allows pointer conversions
that would be legal in C
even though they normally
aren't in Swift.
That way, your Swift code
can use these APIs seamlessly.
So far we've talked
about small improvements
to the tools
you already had.
But this year, Swift also
has a brand-new tool
for extracting information
from strings.
Here's a function
that parses some information
out of a string.
This sort of task
has always been
a bit of a challenge
in Swift.
You end up searching, splitting,
and slicing over and over
until you get what you want.
When people notice this,
they tend to focus
on the little things,
like how wordy it can be
to manipulate
string indices,
but I think that's kind of
missing the bigger picture.
Because even if we changed
this syntax,
it doesn't help you answer
the basic question you're asking
when you look at this code --
what does the line variable
that's passed into it
actually look like?
What sort of string is it
trying to take apart?
If you stare at it long
enough, you might realize
that it's parsing a simplified
version of a mailmap --
a file you put
in a git repository
to correct a developer's
name in old commits.
But extracting that information
by searching and slicing
is so involved that it's
hard to figure that out.
You get so lost in how
to slice up the string
that you kind of lose track
of what that string is.
The problem is not
these two expressions;
the problem is
the whole thing.
We need to rip
out all of this
and replace it
with something better.
We need a
different approach;
one where your code
sort of draws a picture
of the string you want
to match,
and the language figures
out how to do it.
A declarative approach,
not an imperative one.
In Swift 5.7, you can now
do that by writing a regex.
A regex is a way to describe
a pattern in a string.
For over 50 years,
languages and tools
have allowed developers
to write regexes
in a dense,
information-packed syntax.
Some of you already use them
in the Xcode find bar,
in command-line tools
like grep,
in Foundation's
NSRegularExpression class,
or in other
programming languages.
That syntax is now supported
by Swift's regex literals,
and it works just like it does
in any other developer tool.
But some of you haven't
used regexes before
and you're probably going,
"Is that real code
or did a cat walk
across her keyboard?"
And I don't blame you.
Regex literals are written
in symbols and mnemonics
that you have to memorize
in order to read them.
To someone who knows
the language,
even the gnarliest parts
of this regex,
like the part that matches
the developer's name
are just combinations of
several simple matching rules.
But that's a lot of behavior
to cram into 11 characters.
Regex literals are so compact
that even experienced developers
sometimes need a minute to
understand a complicated one.
But what if you could write
the same kind of matching rules,
just with words
instead of symbols?
That seems like it'd be
easier to understand.
In fact, put it
all together,
and you get something
that looks a lot like SwiftUI.
That'd be a great alternative
to a regex literal, wouldn't it?
So it's a good thing
Swift supports that!
The RegexBuilder library
provides a whole new
SwiftUI-style language
for regexes that's easier to use
and more readable
than the traditional syntax.
It can do the same things
a regex literal can,
but it describes its behavior
in words you can understand
or look up, instead of
symbols and abbreviations
you have to memorize.
Regex builders
are great for beginners,
but this is far from
a beginner-only feature.
It has powerful capabilities
that go way beyond
what a regex literal can do.
To start with,
you can turn a regex
into a reusable regex
component,
just as you can turn
a SwiftUI view hierarchy
into a view.
You can use these components
from other regexes
created with
the builder syntax,
and you can even
make them recursive.
Regex builders also support
dropping some Swift types
directly into a regex.
For example,
string literals just match
the exact text inside them --
no special escaping needed.
You can also use
regex literals
in the middle
of a regex builder.
So you can strike a balance
between the clarity
of a regex builder and the
conciseness of a regex literal.
And other types -- like this
Foundation date-format style --
can integrate custom parsing
logic with regex builders,
and even convert the data to a
richer type before capturing it.
Finally, no matter
which syntax you use,
regexes support a bunch
of useful matching methods
and strongly typed captures
that are easy to use.
Now, for the regex nerds
who have been squirming
in their seats,
Swift Regex uses a brand-new
open source matching engine,
with a feature
set comparable
to the most advanced
regex implementations.
The literal syntax is compatible
with the Unicode regex standard,
and it has an uncommon level
of Unicode correctness.
For instance, dot matches
a whole character by default,
not a Unicode.Scalar
or a UTF-8 byte.
To use Swift Regex, your app
will need to be running
on an OS with the Swift
Regex engine built into it,
like macOS 13 or iOS 16.
Swift Regex is
an entire language --
well, two languages, really --
so there's much more
to say about it.
These two sessions --
"Meet Swift Regex"
and "Swift Regex:
Beyond The Basics" --
will give you lots
more details about using it.
Finally, there's one place
where we took a comprehensive
look at the tools we have
and made a bunch of changes
to improve them.
That's in generics
and protocols.
To show you how these tools
have improved,
I'll need an
example protocol.
Let's say you're writing
a git client
and you have to represent
mailmaps in two different ways.
When you're displaying commits,
you use a type with a dictionary
to quickly look up names.
But when you're letting
users edit the mailmap,
you use a type with an array
to keep the entries
in their original order.
And you have a protocol
called Mailmap
that both of
them conform to,
so your mailmap parser can
add entries to either type.
But there are two ways
the parser could use
the Mailmap protocol.
I've written two
different versions
of this addEntries function
to illustrate them,
but it's actually
kind of hard to explain
how they're different,
because Swift is using the same
syntax for two different things.
It turns out that the word
"Mailmap" means one thing here
but it means something
subtly different here.
When you name a protocol
in an inheritance list,
generic parameter list,
generic conformance constraint,
or an opaque result type,
it means "an instance that
conforms to this protocol."
But in a variable type,
a generic argument,
a generic same-type constraint,
or a function parameter
or result type,
it actually means
"a box which contains
an instance that conforms
to this protocol."
This distinction is important
because the box
typically uses more space,
takes more time to operate on,
and doesn't have all
of the capabilities
of the instance inside it.
But the places where
you're using a box
look just like the places
where you aren't,
so it's hard to figure out
if you're using one.
Swift 5.7 fixes
this oversight.
When you're using one
of these boxes
containing
a conforming type,
Swift will now expect you
to write the any keyword.
This is not mandatory in code
that was valid before Swift 5.7,
but it is encouraged
and you will see it
in generated interfaces
and error messages,
even if you don't
write it out explicitly.
So the preferred way
to write all of those things
in the right-hand column
is with the any keyword.
If you do that,
you'll be able to tell
when you're using
one of these boxes.
Now that the any keyword
marks one of the parameters
in this example,
it's a lot easier to explain
the difference between
these two functions.
addEntries1 takes the
Mailmap as a generic type;
addEntries2
takes it as an any type.
And it's also easier
for error messages
to explain what's happening
when you hit one of
the limitations of any types.
For instance, this mergeMailmaps
function tries to pass
an any Mailmap to a generic
Mailmap parameter.
This used to
produce an error
saying that Mailmap
cannot conform to itself,
which always seemed
kind of paradoxical.
But now that we have
the concept of any types,
we can explain what's happening
more clearly.
The problem is
that any Mailmap --
the box containing a mailmap --
doesn't conform
to the Mailmap protocol.
But the box is what
you're trying to pass,
and it doesn't fit
into the generic parameter.
If you want to pass the instance
inside the box here,
you'd have to somehow
open up the box,
take out the mailmap inside
it, and pass that instead.
But actually,
in simple cases like this one,
Swift will now
just do that for you.
Open up the box,
take out the instance inside it,
and pass it
to the generic parameter.
So you won't be seeing
this error message
nearly as much anymore.
But there's an even more
exciting improvement
to any types than that one.
Previously, a protocol could
not be used as an any type
if it either used the self
type or had associated types,
or even just conformed
to a protocol that did,
like Equatable.
But in Swift 5.7,
this error is just --
poof --
gone.
A lot of developers
have struggled with this one,
so we're thrilled to have
fixed it at the source.
Now, that's exciting enough
just for protocols like Mailmap,
but this goes even further.
Because even very sophisticated
protocols, like Collection,
can be used as any types.
You can even specify
the element type,
thanks to a new feature called
"primary associated types."
A lot of associated types
are basically just
implementation details.
You usually don't care
which type a collection uses
for its index, iterator,
or subsequence;
you just need to use
the type it supports.
But its Element
is a different story.
You might not always care
exactly which Element type
a collection uses,
but you're probably
going to do something
with the elements,
so you'll need to constrain them
or return them or something.
When you have an associated
type like Element
that nearly every user
of a protocol will care about,
you can put its name
after the protocol's name
in angle brackets to make it
a primary associated type.
Once you do that, you can
constrain the protocol's
primary associated types
with the angle bracket syntax
pretty much anywhere you can
write the protocol's name,
including in any Collection.
Now, some of you might be
looking at this type and going,
"Wait a minute.
Isn't there already something
called AnyCollection,
just run together
and with the 'any' capitalized?"
And you're right, there is!
The old AnyCollection
is a type-erasing wrapper --
a handwritten struct which
serves the same purpose
as an any type.
The difference is that
the AnyCollection struct
is just line after line of
the most boring boilerplate code
you've ever seen in your
life; whereas the any type
is a built-in
language feature
that does basically
the same thing --
for free!
Now, the AnyCollection
struct will stick around
for backwards compatibility
and because it has
a couple of features that any
types can't quite match yet.
But if you have your own
type-erasing wrappers
in your code, you might want to
see if you can reimplement them
using built-in any types instead
of box classes or closures.
Or maybe even just replace
them with type aliases.
So Swift has dramatically
improved any types.
It's introduced
the any keyword
so you can see
where you're using them.
It allows you to pass them
to generic arguments.
It's abolished the restriction
that kept many protocols
from being used with them.
And it even lets
you constrain
an any type's primary
associated types.
But even with all
of those improvements,
any types still
have limitations.
For example, even though
you can now use any Mailmaps
when Mailmap conforms
to Equatable,
you still can't use the
equals operator with them,
because the equals operator
requires both mailmaps
to have the same concrete type,
but that's not guaranteed
when you're using
two any Mailmaps.
So even though Swift has
improved any types a lot,
they still have
important limitations,
in both capabilities
and performance.
And that's why a lot of the
time, you shouldn't use them --
you should use
generics instead.
So let's go back to the
two versions of addEntries
and apply that wisdom.
Both versions do exactly
the same thing,
but the one on the top
uses generic types,
and the one on the bottom
uses any types.
The generic version
will likely be more efficient
and more capable,
so you ought to use that one.
And yet, you're probably
tempted to use any types,
because they're just so much
easier to read and write.
To write the generic version,
you need to declare
two generic type names,
constrain them both,
and finally,
use those generic type names
as the types of the parameters.
That's just exhausting compared
to writing "any Collection"
and "any Mailmap."
So you'd be tempted to use any
types despite their drawbacks.
But that's the same thing
I was talking about earlier --
using your hammer
instead of your screwdriver
because the hammer
has a big, grippy handle.
You shouldn't have
to make that choice.
So Swift is making generics
just as easy to use
as any types.
If a generic parameter
is only used in one place,
you can now write it with
the some keyword as a shorthand.
And it even supports
primary associated types,
so you can accept all
collections of mailmap entries
with code that's a lot
easier to understand.
With that in your toolbox,
there's no reason
to avoid generics anymore.
If you have a choice between
generics and any types,
generics will be
just as easy to use --
just write "some"
instead of "any".
So you might as well use
the best tool for the job.
I've only scratched
the surface of these changes
to protocols and generics.
For an in-depth look,
as well as a great review
of all of Swift's
generics features,
we have two more talks
for you this year:
"Embrace Swift generics,"
and "Design protocol
interfaces in Swift."
Now, Angela and I
have talked about
nearly two dozen changes
to Swift,
but there are lots more that we
couldn't fit into this session.
Every one of these changes
was pitched, proposed, reviewed,
and accepted publicly
in the Evolution board
on the Swift Forums.
And all of them were shaped
and realized with the help
of community members
from outside Apple.
If you're one of those people,
thank you for making Swift 5.7
the great release it is.
And if you want to help
decide what comes next,
visit Swift.org/contributing
to find out how to participate.
Thanks for your time.
And happy coding.
[LAUGHS]
♪