♪ Bass-heavy electronic music ♪
It's time to review day four.
Roll the tape!
We checked in with Raj
on how you can
organize your iPad interface
with SwiftUI.
- Better support for
state restoration, deep linking,
and even richer
programmatic control.
- Cool.
- Then Sara showed us how
to bring the power of SwiftUI
to your UIKit apps.
- You can use
the hosting controller
anywhere you can use
a view controller in UIKit.
- Later on,
Brett took us through
the latest updates for Vision.
- Here we compute optical flow
for a short clip
of this dog fetching
a water bottle on a beach.
- And we discovered
how to create
compelling
SharePlay experiences.
- Think of SharePlay
like a portal,
transporting people
through their phones
and into the same space.
- We also got a lesson
in language
from Apple's interface writers.
- Writing for interfaces
begins with curiosity
for who's on the other side
of the screen.
- And now for the intel
on day five.
♪
Check back in tomorrow
for our final report.
♪