♪ Bass-heavy electronic music ♪
Serenity Caldwell:
Welcome to HQ.
I'm Serenity Caldwell;
here's your day one
debrief of WWDC.
iOS 16 is now mission-ready,
starting with
the reimagined Lock Screen.
Choose from countless fonts,
colors, and widgets
to personalize your iPhone.
Want to set boundaries between
work and home life?
Activate Personal Focus.
And if you've ever sent
an embarrassing message,
now you can fix that.
Or better still, erase it
before anyone spots it. [POP]
With SharePlay you can actually
watch movies and shows
with friends while messaging.
Ted Lasso: Oh, I like this.
Serenity: Want to send a picture
of your best friend
without the background?
Just touch, lift, and send.
[BARK]
Sharing photos with family
just got a lot easier with...
Craig Federighi: ...iCloud
Shared Photo Library.
Serenity: We also got a sneak
peek at the future of CarPlay.
♪
And arriving in Maps, at last,
the ability to plan
up to 15 stops.
Say hello to some new
Apple Watch features.
There are new Workout views
like heart rate zones.
We made it easier
to customize your workout
and added reminders
to take your meds.
And there's a range
of new watch faces:
Astronomy, Lunar,
Playtime, Metropolitan,
and of course,
we can't forget [BARK] Buddy!
The next generation
of Apple silicon is here.
Meet the mighty M2.
We took all this power
and used it to supercharge
the new MacBook Air.
It's thinner, lighter,
and faster than ever.
We're even bringing M2
to 13-inch MacBook Pro.
We launched
the newest macOS, Ventura,
with big upgrades to Spotlight
like Enhanced Image Search,
and we introduced...
Craig: ...Stage Manager.
Serenity: Now working between
different windows and apps
is faster and easier.
And you can Schedule Send
and Undo Send emails.
You asked, we delivered.
Introducing Continuity Camera.
Now you can use
your iPhone as a webcam
in ways that were
never possible before.
Don't look now, it's...
Craig: ...iPadOS 16.
Serenity: For the first time,
you can work on multiple
overlapping windows
with Stage Manager.
Craig: And it gets even better.
Serenity: We made collaborating
easier across different apps
and devices,
and coming later this year,
a new app
for live collaboration.
We added new APIs
to all Apple platforms,
brought in top-notch weather
data with WeatherKit,
gave developers more power
to build games with Metal 3,
Made SwiftUI
more powerful and flexible,
raised the bar
with Swift Charts,
Introduced Swift Regex,
and opened Xcode Cloud
to all developers.
And congrats to the 12 winners
of the Apple Design Awards
and all our finalists.
Here's a look at day two.
♪
That's all for now.
Be sure to report back tomorrow.
♪