♪ ♪
Hi. I'm Charles Ying.
Welcome to What's new in App Clips.
An App Clip is a small part of an app.
They're light and fast,
and easy to discover,
so you can quickly get what you need
right when you need it.
They can be found in Messages,
Maps, Spotlight, and Safari,
or out in the world with QR codes
and App Clip Codes.
One really cool example is Toast.
Toast's app clip lets you scan a QR code
to pay for your food right at your table!
Toast configured their App Clip to open
from an existing QR code
printed on a receipt.
The App Clip has resulted
in users checking out faster,
and more users
choosing to install the full app.
Building an App Clip into
an existing flow is a great way
to streamline your experience.
Today you'll learn about new features
that let your users do more
with your App Clip,
and make developing App Clips even easier.
Let's start with the App Clip size limit.
App Clips are light and fast,
and designed for speed.
To make App Clips feel instant,
they need to be small.
And since wireless networks
are faster than they were two years ago,
I'm happy to say that new in iOS 16,
App Clips can now be up to 15 MB in size.
This gives you more room
to build your ideal experience.
Set your App Clip's minimum version
to iOS 16 for the new limit,
or stay under 10 MB to be compatible
with iOS 15 and earlier.
Either way, you can always download
additional resources
after your App Clip launches.
Speed is still key to a great experience.
Your users won't always be
in locations with a fast network,
so optimizing your App Clip
is still as critical as ever.
To learn more
about optimizing your App Clip,
please watch,
"Build light and fast App Clips”.
Next, I'm really excited to show you
a simple new tool
that makes sure your App Clip experience
or universal link is set up correctly.
Here's how it works.
On your iPhone or iPad,
go to Developer Settings
and under App Clips Testing,
select Diagnostics.
Now, enter your URL.
You can turn on Developer Settings
by connecting your device to Xcode.
iOS will check your URL's configuration.
If everything is set up right,
you'll see these green checkboxes.
But, if there's something wrong,
you'll see a screen like this one
that tells you exactly what's happening.
This will help you fix problems
like Safari's banner not showing,
or navigating to a web page
instead of your App Clip.
Each diagnostic has a link
to documentation
to explain the configuration step further.
Now you'll be able
to see exactly what's wrong.
App Clip diagnostics checks App Clip
experiences that use physical codes,
Safari and iMessage,
and it will also check your universal link
associated domains configuration.
This simple new tool makes it so much
easier to get your configuration right.
Next, CloudKit.
CloudKit is a framework that lets your app
access data stored on iCloud.
Up until now, CloudKit has
not been available for App Clips.
Your App Clip might be using a server
to read data or resources.
New in iOS 16,
App Clips can also read data
and resources stored
in a CloudKit public database.
You can now share the same code,
access the same data
in both your app and App Clip
with all the power and scale
CloudKit provides.
An important difference between apps
and App Clips is that App Clips can read
from a public database
but can't write data to CloudKit.
App Clips also can't use cloud documents
and the key-value store.
This keeps the promise to users
that when an App Clip isn't used anymore,
iOS will delete the App Clip and its data.
To enable CloudKit
for your App Clip in Xcode,
open your App Clip target's
Signing and Capabilities tab,
and select the CloudKit container
you want your App Clip to use.
This CloudKit container can be a new
or existing container
shared with your full app.
Here's an example of how to read
CloudKit public data from your App Clip.
Create a CKContainer
with the container's identifier
and access
the publicCloudDatabase property.
Then fetch the record you want
from the public database.
Next, keychain migration.
Today, when you want to transfer
sensitive information,
like authentication tokens
and payment information
from your App Clip to your full app,
your App Clip would store this data
in a shared app group container.
iOS saves this data when a user upgrades
from your App Clip to your full app.
Your full app reads
the app group container
and stores that information
in the keychain.
However, the keychain is the ideal place
to securely store
this type of information.
New this year,
when a user installs your app,
items stored in your App Clip's keychain
are transferred
from your App Clip to your app.
Now your App Clip can simply store
secure items in the keychain
and they will be moved to your app
when it's installed.
Shared keychain groups
and iCloud Keychain are not supported.
This keeps the promise to users
that keychain information
won't stick around
when an App Clip isn't used anymore.
Here's an example of how to store and
read login information in the keychain.
The code is the same
for both app and App Clip.
You can add new items to
the keychain with SecItemAdd.
And fetch these items from the keychain
with SecItemCopyMatching.
And add a label to your items
to help your full app
identify that the items were saved
by your App Clip.
Finally, the App Clip experiences API.
As your app clip grows, you'll have more
and more advanced App Clip experiences,
each with their own information
or location.
You need an easy way to add
and update all of these experiences.
App Store Connect has
an App Clip experiences web API
that's designed to automate this workflow.
Let's look at an example
that uses this API
to add an advanced App Clip experience.
First, get the App Clip resource ID.
Next, upload your header image.
Last, create the advanced
App Clip experience.
First, let's find the resource ID
for the app clip.
Call the web API with your app's item ID
and App Clip bundle ID.
And from the response,
save the App Clip resource ID for later.
Next, upload a header image
for the advanced App Clip experience.
Save the header image's resource ID
for the next step.
Last, with your App Clip resource ID
and your header image ID,
we can now create
your advanced App Clip experience.
There are three dictionaries to fill in:
attributes, relationships, and included.
In the attributes dictionary,
add information like the action name,
which category and language,
and the link
for the advanced App Clip experience.
If your advanced experience is tied to
a Maps location, add a place dictionary.
In the place dictionary,
add the matching Maps business place name,
a map action, and the map coordinates.
In the relationships dictionary,
add the App Clip resource ID
and the header image ID.
And in the included dictionary,
add a localized title and subtitle
for the advanced App Clip experience.
And that's it!
With this App Store Connect API,
you can fully automate creating
advanced App Clip experiences.
To learn more about App Store Connect,
check out “Automating App Store Connect”
and “What's new in App Store Connect”
from WWDC 2020.
To wrap up, the new App Clip size limit
gives you more room
to build your ideal experience.
App Clip diagnostics tools are a great way
to understand your App Clip
and universal link configuration
end to end.
CloudKit and keychain can ease
your development
by sharing more code with your app.
And the App Clip experiences API
automates the workflow
for managing
your advanced App Clip experiences.
To learn more about developing App Clips,
please watch “What's new in App Clips”
from WWDC 2021
and “Design great App Clips” from WWDC 2020.
You developers have made
such great App Clips.
They're so creative!
We hope these new features help you build
your next great App Clip.
Thanks for watching!  ♪ ♪