♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hi, my name is Boris,
and welcome to the session
"Create Swift package plugins."
We introduced support for Swift packages
in Xcode 11
to offer a straightforward approach
to distributing libraries as source code.
In Xcode 14, we want to bring
that same great way to structure and share
components to development workflows,
such as generating source code
or automating release tasks,
with Swift package plugins.
First, a quick overview of the talk.
After learning the basics of plugins,
we'll build our first custom
command plugin in a demo.
Next, we'll look at more details
about creating plugins,
followed by building both an in-build
and a pre-build command plugin
in further demos.
A package plugin is Swift code
that uses the PackagePlugin API,
similar to a package manifest.
Plugins can extend
the functionality of Xcode
or the Swift Package Manager
through well-defined extension points.
How do package plugins work?
Xcode will compile and run your plugin,
which can use information
about available executables
and input files to construct commands
which it communicates back to Xcode
in order to execute them as needed.
Package plugins can contribute
custom build tasks
that run before or during the build,
for example, to generate
source code or resource files.
They can also add custom commands
to SwiftPM's command line interface
or menu items to Xcode.
For more information on the basics
of plugins, I would recommend watching
"Meet swift package plugins" first,
and in case you are new
to packages entirely,
you can watch the WWDC19 session
Creating Swift Packages.
Let's look at building
our first custom command plugin.
I'm working
on the tools-support-core package
from Swift open source,
and I'd like to add a text file
that lists
all the contributors to the project.
I also want to regenerate it as needed
from the Git history of the package.
Previously,
I might have written a shell script
or a makefile to do this,
but I'd like to create
a custom command plugin
so that I can re-generate
the file without having to leave Xcode.
First, we have to create
the directory structure for our plugin.
We open the context menu
on the package
and select New Folder
to create a top-level folder
called Plugins
similar to the existing Sources
and Tests.
Next, we will create another nested folder
for the plugin target,
called "GenerateContributors."
And inside there, we create a new file
and call it "plugin.swift."
Next, we need to make some changes
to the package manifest
to declare our new target there.
But first, we need to bump
the tools version for our package to 5.6
since plugins are only available
since that version.
Next, we can insert our plugin target.
Let's take a look
at the new manifest API here.
We are creating a plugin target
which corresponds to a folder
inside the Plugins folder,
similar to source module targets.
It gets a name that is both relevant
for naming the folder
as well as a menu
item in Xcode.
We specify the capability,
so what type of extension point
we want to use.
In this case, we are making
a custom command.
The intent can define a verb
for the SwiftPM command line
as well as a description
of what the plugin does,
and finally, we can declare permissions
that the plugin requires.
In this case, we want to write a new file
to the root of the package,
so we need permissions
to write to that directory.
The reason string will be shown
to the user of the plugin
so that they know whether
or not to grant the permission,
similar to how permissions
work in the OS itself.
Now that we have declared the plugin,
let's go back to actually implement it.
The plugin will shell out to Git
to get the commit history.
It will read the history from standardout
of the external Git command
and parse the results
and finally write them out to a text
file.
We'll open our plugin source file
we created earlier
and import PackagePlugin.
This is a built-in module,
much like PackageDescription,
that gives us access to the APIs
we can use to implement plugins.
We define a struct GenerateContributors
and conform it to CommandPlugin.
We'll accept the fix-it here,
to get the missing stubs for implementing
the protocol.
We also need to mark our struct
as @main
since it will be the main function
of the plugin executable.
performCommand is the entry point
for our command,
and we receive two arguments:
context, which gives us access
to the resolved package graph
and other information about the context
we are being executed in,
as well as arguments.
Since custom commands
are invoked by the user,
they can provide input
in the form of arguments.
We are creating a simple command,
so we won't actually provide any options
to the user at this time.
Since we want to shell out to Git
in order to get information
about the commit history,
we are importing Foundation
because we want to use the Process API
to do so.
Next, we'll define a process instance
and set it to execute Git log
with some formatting arguments.
We need to create a pipe to capture
the process output.
Then we can run it and wait
until it exits.
After the process has finished,
we read all the data from the pipe
and convert it to a string which will have
all the git log output.
We do some string manipulation to trim
the output down to a list
without duplicates,
and finally, we can write it
to a file called "CONTRIBUTORS.txt,"
and since the custom command is executed
in the package's root directory,
we'll store the file there.
Now, if we save and then
right-click on the package
in the project navigator,
there is a new entry for our command
in the context menu.
Let's execute it!
In the following dialog,
we can select the packages or targets
that should be the input
for our plugin as well as any arguments,
but since our plugin doesn't react
to these options, we can click Run.
Next we'll be asked for permissions,
as we defined in the manifest earlier.
Since we just wrote the plugin ourselves,
we can go ahead and run it,
but you should make sure that you only give
extra permissions to plugins you trust.
After running, the CONTRIBUTORS.txt
file shows up in the project navigator.
So now after we extended
Xcode with our first plugin,
let's go a bit deeper
into how plugins work
and what to look out
for when creating one.
Package plugins run in a sandbox,
similar to the evaluation
of the package manifest itself.
Network access and writing
to non-temporary locations
other than the plugin's own work directory
is prohibited.
Custom commands can optionally declare
that they'd like to write
to the package's root directory,
as shown earlier.
If you are wrapping
an existing third-party tool,
you may have to look into how
to confine it to the sandbox model,
for example, by configuring
where generated files get written to.
I talked about the different types
of plugins in the introduction,
and it should be clear whether a problem
is better solved
by a custom command or a build tool,
but let's take a look at the structure
of build tool plugins.
These plugins allow you
to extend the build system
by providing a description
on which executables to run during a build
and specifying their inputs and outputs
which helps with scheduling your work
at the appropriate time during a build.
You might be familiar with the basics here
if you have been creating
run script phases
in Xcode projects.
There are also two different types
of build tool plugins.
The distinguishing factor here is whether
your tool has a defined set of outputs.
If it does, you should create
an in-build command
which will automatically be re-run
by the build system
if your outputs
are out-of-date compared to your inputs.
If you don't have a clear set of outputs,
you can create a pre-build command
which runs at the start of every build.
Because of this,
you should be careful about doing
expensive work in pre-build commands
or come up with a custom strategy
for caching results
that's appropriate to your use case.
For our second demo,
I want to create a new library
that encapsulates icons I'd like to share
between different tools I am working on.
Let's get started and create
a new package from template
and call it "IconLibrary."
And I'm going to drag in some icon assets
I already have into my library's target.
Let's also add a basic SwiftUI view
and a preview to my library.
First, we need to add the required minimum
deployment targets to the manifest.
Next, let's actually add
that basic view and preview.
Here we can use our assets we dragged
in before.
I think it would be nice if,
instead
of having to deal with strings here,
we would have a type-safe way
to reference these images.
This seems like a great use case
for an in-build command plugin
which looks at asset catalogs
and generates some Swift code
based on them.
Let's take a look at an asset catalog
in Finder
to find out how we can extract
the information we need for the plugin.
Each image gets its own imageset directory
with the name of the asset...
And there's a JSON file
which describes the basic contents.
In-build commands work a little different
from custom commands
in that they're providing
a description of executables to run
as well as their inputs and outputs.
The executables
can be provided by the system,
third party packages, or you can create
one tailor-made for your plugin.
We want to take the third approach here.
Plugins get run
at the start of the build process
in order to participate in
computing the build graph.
Based on that, executables get scheduled
as part of build execution.
Now back
to the executable we're building.
We'd like to have a compile-time constant
for each image in an asset catalog
so that, instead of needing to remember
the correct strings for each image,
we'll get them autocompleted
as Swift symbols.
We want to loop
over the directory contents
of the asset catalog
to find all the image sets.
For each image set, we parse its metadata
to determine
if it actually contains any images
and should therefore get code generated
for it.
Then we can generate the code
and write to a file.
Since we declared those files as outputs
of our plugin,
they will automatically be incorporated
into the build of the target
the plugin is being applied to.
We'll need a way to deal with arguments
since that is how we communicate
between the plugin and the executable.
The first argument will be the path
to the asset catalog we are processing,
and the second one will be a path provided
by the plugin for our generated code.
Next we need some model objects
for decoding the contents.json files.
We use Decodable to take advantage
of Swift's built-in JSON decoding.
The only information we
are interested in are the list of images
and their filenames, which are optional
because there might not be
an image for each pixel density.
We'll generate code
in a simplistic manner here
by just building up a string.
We start it with imports
of the frameworks we need,
Foundation and SwiftUI.
We want to loop
over the directory contents
of the asset catalog
to find all the image sets
We need to parse the JSON next.
The filename uses the input parameter.
And we decode using
Foundation's 'JSONDecoder' API.
The main piece of information
we're interested in
is whether there is a defined image
for a given image set,
which we determine by checking
whether there's at least one image
with a non-empty filename.
If the given image set has an image,
we'd like to generate a SwiftUI image
which loads that image
from the package's bundle.
We do that by building a string
with the base name of each image
that loads the given image
from the module bundle,
which is the resource bundle
that the build system creates
for each package with resources.
We can wrap up the work of the executable
by writing the generated code to a file,
as given to us by arguments.
Let's go back to Xcode
and create the executable.
We call it "AssetConstantsExec"...
And add a main file.
Now we have to declare
it in the package manifest.
And we can add the code we just discussed
in its main file.
Now that we have
an executable that can generate code,
we can bring it
into the build system using a plugin.
Let's add the required target
and also add a usage of the plugin
from our library target.
As before, we're importing
the PackagePlugin library
and create a struct,
this time conforming it
to the BuildTool plugin protocol.
The entry point looks similar,
but instead of user arguments,
we are giving a target here.
This is the target that the plugin is
being applied to,
and the entry point will be called once
per target that uses the given plugin.
This plugin will care particularly
about source module targets,
which are any targets
which actually carry source files,
in contrast to, for example, a binary target.
To build up the array of build commands,
we loop over all xcasset bundles
in the target.
We'll extract a string
for the display name
that will show up in the build log,
as well as construct suitable
input and output paths.
We can also look up our executable here
using the plugin API
and then put our build command together.
With this, we're ready
to build the project again.
We can take a look at the build log
for the new build steps
that are happening.
The plugin is being compiled
and run at the start of the build,
from where it adds any generated
commands to the build graph.
Looking at the target,
our new build command ran.
And finally, the generated source file
shows up
as part of compiling Swift files.
Let's go back to our preview,
where we can replace the stringly typed
image construction with our new constants.
We also get autocompletion
for the other image names.
This is nice.
With relatively little code,
we have been able to improve our workflow,
all using familiar Swift APIs
and without having to leave Xcode.
So far, we have looked
into making plugins for our own use,
as part of libraries we were already
working on,
but another powerful attribute of plugins
is that we can share them
in a straightforward way,
similar to libraries.
For the next demo,
I'd like to automate
some pre-build processing
using the genstrings tool
that ships with Xcode.
The tool extracts localized strings
from your code
into a localization directory
for further use.
Since that seems generally useful,
I'd like to make the plugin
a separate package
so that it can be shared independently.
If you'd like to learn more
about resources and localization
in packages,
I would recommend
the WWDC20 session on that topic.
For more information
about localization in general,
check out Localize your SwiftUI app
from WWDC21.
For this plugin, we'll start
by computing the output directory
for localizations.
We'll compute the input files,
which are all the Swift or Objective-C
source files in a given target,
and then construct the pre-build command
for executing the genstrings tool
provided by Xcode.
Note that the biggest difference between
pre- and in-build commands
is that we don't declare
a well-defined set of outputs,
which means these commands run
on every build.
The tool will extract
all the localized strings
from the user's source code
and then write all those strings into
a localization directory,
which can be used as the basis
for the actual localization work
for the user's project.
To start, I have created
the scaffolding here already.
Now in the package manifest,
let’s add a target as before,
but we will also add a plugin product.
Similar to library products,
this is the way to make a plugin
available to clients of a package
instead of just privately.
We can write the code
That we discussed earlier...
Now that we have built our plugin,
we'd like to test it out
in a separate example package.
For that, let's create
a new package from template.
We'll add an API that provides
a localized string to the package...
And add a use of that
in the generated test.
As expected, the test works,
as our API returns the string "World."
Let's add a path-based dependency
on the plugin package...
and a use of the plugin
to the library target.
We can now run again...
and if we look at the build log,
our plugin gets executed
at the start of the build
and the generated files
get added to our target,
so we're getting a resource bundle built
and a resource accessor being generated,
just as if the resource was part
of our target from the beginning.
Now let's change our code to actually use
the resource bundle.
Finally, if we change the code...
and take a peek
at the generated bundle...
we can see the changes reflected here.
Now that we have a test bed
for the plugin,
we could flesh out the test suite
and eventually share
the plugin package with others.
To recap, plugins can be used
to automate and share developer tooling,
custom commands provide a way
to automate common tasks,
and build tools can be used
to generate files during
the build process.
Thanks for listening!
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪