♪ ♪
Mahesh Molakalapalli:
My name is Mahesh Molakalapalli.
I am an engineering manager on
the App Store and App Analytics team.
Our goal with App Analytics
is to help you grow your business
by providing you with the unique
insights about your app.
Today, I am going to introduce you
to an exciting new feature
called App Benchmarking
that will help you get better insights
than ever before.
We will begin with an overview
of benchmarking.
Then we'll talk about the metrics for
which you can see benchmarking data.
Next, we'll show you how we create
relevant benchmarks
while protecting the privacy of all apps.
And we will wrap up by showing you
how you can take action
on insights gained from benchmarking.
Let's get started.
Many of you may already use App Analytics.
In this tool, we share data with you
about your app's acquisition,
usage, and monetization.
Let's say that you are a developer
of an app called Mountain Climber,
which is a travel app
offering subscriptions.
The overview page shows how
Mountain Climber is performing over time,
across key performance metrics
that allows you to monitor results
in each stage of the customer lifecycle,
from awareness
to conversion and on to retention.
Since you're focused on growth,
let's say that one of your top
business priorities for your app
has been to improve your conversion rate.
Looking at the data,
you have been making steady improvement,
with a 5.5% increase
over the last 90 days.
But what is unclear
is how much more improvement
you might be able to achieve
with continued effort.
Do you have more opportunity to grow,
or should you focus your efforts
somewhere else?
That's where peer group benchmarking
comes in.
You can learn
about the performance of apps
that are similar to your app
in a privacy-friendly way,
and check how you are performing
relative to them.
Like your Mountain Climber app,
all the apps
on the right hand side are travel apps,
with a subscription business model.
Let's take a look at how your App is doing
compared to this group.
You can see the same apps,
arranged left to right,
from lowest to highest conversion rates.
So how does your app stack up
against all the others?
Although your conversion rate
has been improving over time,
you are still in the bottom half
of your peer group.
There's plenty of room for improvement.
Benchmarking provides insights like this
without revealing the performance
of any individual app in your peer group.
We do this by including enough apps
to provide meaningful results
in the aggregate
so that it doesn't reveal
any individual app's performance.
And in order to show
your relative position,
we show you what the distribution
of your peer group looks like
such as the 25th, 50th,
and 75th percentiles of your group.
You will then be able to see
how you are performing
relative to your peer group,
and understand
whether you have growth opportunity,
or whether
you're already beating the competition.
Now that you have an idea
of what peer group benchmarking is
and why it is so important,
let us talk about the metrics that you
will be able to use in this feature.
One of our goals with benchmarking
is to give you insight
into how your app is performing
throughout the customer lifecycle.
That's why we will be offering benchmarks
for metrics related to acquisition,
usage, and monetization.
To help you measure
your acquisition efforts,
we will provide you with
conversion rate benchmarks.
Conversion rate helps you understand
how often people download
or redownload your app
after seeing it on the App Store.
The higher your conversion rate,
the more efficiently
you are acquiring your customers.
To help you measure usage,
you will be able to see Day 1,
Day 7, and Day 28 retention.
Retention helps you understand
what percentage of people return
to your app one day after download,
seven days after download,
and 28 days after download,
and is a good indicator
of how engaging your app is
for your customers.
You will also be able to see
how your crash rate stacks up
against your peers.
If your app is prone to crashing
more often than normal,
it may negatively impact your engagement
and monetization metrics,
so it's good to keep this
as low as possible.
Finally, to help you evaluate
your monetization strategy,
you will be able to see benchmarks
around average proceeds per paying user.
This will allow you to see how much money
your peers take home
from each of their paying customers,
so you can see how you compare.
Now that you know what metrics
you will be able to see,
let us talk about relevancy and privacy.
Throughout the development
of this feature,
we have strived to create peer groups
that are highly relevant to you
and your business,
while also protecting the privacy
of each app within that group.
This helps us meet our goals
of providing you with helpful insights,
without revealing the performance
of any individual app.
Let us discuss two examples
of how we will make the peer groups
relevant to you,
no matter what kind of app
that you have on the App Store.
First, we will use a number of attributes
that we have on the App Store
to create your peer groups,
including the app's App Store category.
For example, if you have put your app
in the travel category,
we will group you with other apps
that also put themselves
in the travel category.
Second, we will also look at
how your app monetizes on the store.
For example, is it a free app,
freemium, paid,
paidmium, or subscription?
Since apps with different business models
have different expectations
about user behavior,
this is also a very important factor
for creating relevant peer groups.
Each attribute that we use to create
your peer groups
has been tested to ensure
it allows for meaningful comparisons
over time between your app
and its peer group.
Next, let's talk about privacy.
At Apple, we have significant experience
with building great products
that also have great privacy,
and we used that experience here.
In order to accomplish our privacy goals,
we use a technique called
differential privacy,
which is the gold standard
for ensuring that aggregated data
can remain both helpful
and private at the same time.
When we calculate your peer
group's overall conversion rate,
we add small amounts of noise
to each data point
we share about your peer group.
We also ensure
that enough apps are in your peer group
so that it is not possible to know
whether a particular app is in
or out of your peer group,
because the noise added to the data set
is large enough to obscure
the exact makeup of the peer group,
while still providing useful information
about your peer group in the aggregate.
This protects the privacy of your app
and all the other apps in the peer group.
Let us end by taking a look at
how you can use other tools
to take action on this information.
The App Store provides a number
of developer features
that enable you to optimize
and improve your performance
across the customer lifecycle.
For example,
to have a great conversion rate,
you need to have
a great App Store product page,
and the App Store offers you
tools to help.
With product page optimization,
you can test different app icons,
screenshots, and app previews
to find out which combination of features
works best with your customers.
And with custom product pages,
you can create unique product pages
for different audience
that focus on their specific interests,
rather than having one product page
for all customers.
Both of these features can help you
boost your conversion rate.
In order to improve your usage metrics,
you can utilize in-app events
and App Clips.
In-app events are timely events
within apps and games–
such as game competitions,
movie premieres,
or livestreamed experiences–
that you can showcase on the App Store
to engage new customers
and re-engage existing customers.
And an App Clip is
a small part of your app
that is discoverable
in relevant public places
so your customers can complete
a quick task from your app.
For example, whether ordering take-out
from a restaurant,
renting a scooter,
or setting up a new connected appliance
for the first time,
people can launch the App Clip
to easily start and finish the task.
And finally, to improve your monetization,
you can try out different pricing tiers
so that users can customize
their experiences
based on their preferences
and the amount they want to pay.
Or you can create
a promoted in-app purchase,
which lets users browse the items for sale
directly on the App Store,
even before they download your app.
To conclude,
by combining peer group benchmarking
with other App Store tools,
you can make meaningful progress
in the areas
where your app needs it the most.
We invite you to go to
developer.apple.com/app-store
to learn more.
Here is a quick summary
of what you've seen today.
Peer Group Benchmarking
is an exciting tool
that will let you compare
your App Store performance
against a group of similar apps
on the store.
We have designed Peer Group Benchmarking
using differential privacy
to provide relevant insights
without revealing the information
about any individual app.
By using Peer Group Benchmarking
in combination with other developer
features on the App Store,
you will have the ability to boost
your app's performance on the App Store.
You will be able to start using
Peer Group Benchmarking early next year.
Thank you.