♪ (Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music) ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Michael Sumner.
I'm a software engineer
working on Siri and App Intents.
In this session,
I want to talk to you
about creating app shortcuts
for your app,
using the new
App Intents framework.
I'll start with an overview
of what App Shortcuts are
and how they relate
to App Intents.
Then, I'll walk through creating
an app shortcut in Swift,
and adding a parameter.
Finally, I'll cover how to make
your app shortcut discoverable,
so users can benefit
from your hard work.
Let's get started with
the App Intents framework
and App Shortcuts.
People use shortcuts
to create multistep workflows
with your apps that can be used
from the Shortcuts app
and from Siri.
Until now, someone first
had to set up a shortcut
via an Add to Siri button
or the Shortcuts app
before they could use
your intent.
We're excited to introduce
App Shortcuts,
which require zero user setup.
This makes it easier than ever
for people to benefit
from your shortcuts.
By integrating
with App Shortcuts,
intents from your app
will be available
as soon as your app
is installed.
This makes it easy for someone
to discover and use
your app's functionality.
They no longer need
to head to the Shortcuts app
or use an Add to Siri button
to set anything up.
App Shortcuts,
like user-built shortcuts,
can be run from
the Shortcuts app,
Spotlight, and Siri.
This gives people multiple ways
to discover and interact
with your application from
various places in the system.
For example,
when searching in Spotlight,
your app shortcut
will be displayed
right in the search results
for easy access.
By implementing App Shortcuts,
your users will be able to
interact with your app in quick,
lightweight interactions
that make it easier for them
to complete their task
and be on their way.
My team is working on an app --
Meditation --
that helps users meditate
by guiding them
through a set of audio prompts
and sounds
to help them focus
on what matters.
Today, to start a meditation,
users have to launch the app,
log in, and find the meditation
session that they want to run.
By integrating
with App Shortcuts,
my users can quickly access
these features from anywhere
just by asking Siri.
And by making it faster
to start a session,
users can integrate meditation
into their daily routine,
either in the morning
before work
or in the evening to help
wind down after a long day.
Alright, let's dive right in
to the code needed
to create an App Intent and
turn it into an app shortcut.
Unlike previous shortcuts,
App Shortcuts are built with
the new App Intents framework.
App Intents is a new,
Swift-only framework
built from the ground up
to make it faster
and easier to build
great intents.
With App Intents,
everything is defined
right in your Swift source code,
instead of a separate
metadata file.
This removes any
code generation steps
and allows you to stay focused
without switching contexts
between the source editor
and the metadata editor.
They're also easier
to code review
and solve merge conflicts.
To build App Shortcuts,
you'll need to write
an AppShortcutsProvider
that lists the phrases
and other metadata needed
to turn your App Intent
into a full-fledged shortcut.
And note that because
these are set up
without any user interaction,
you'll need to include
your application's name
in the trigger phrase.
Intents are defined
as Swift structs,
that implement
the AppIntent protocol.
A basic intent has
just two requirements --
a title, which is used
to display your intent
in the Shortcuts app,
and a method called perform.
The perform method is where
you run your intent's logic
and return a result.
Additionally, you can trigger
prompts for the user
and await their response.
In this intent, I'll start
the default meditation session
using my app's
MeditationService.
Because the perform method
is async,
I can run asynchronous code
to start my session.
Once the session has started,
I'll return a dialog
that is shown to the user.
And if your app is localized,
you'll want to localize this
string in all of your locales.
So far, with what I've built,
the StartMeditationIntent
will appear in the Shortcuts app
when authoring a shortcut.
A motivated user
can take this intent
and create a shortcut
that will kick off a session.
In this shortcut,
I've also added a second intent
to enable a Focus.
By default, my App Intent
is rendered using the title
I specified in my source code.
To customize the rendering
for your action,
be sure to add a parameter
summary to your App Intent.
Parameter summaries
allow you to customize
the look of your intent,
as well as show values inline.
However, this intent works great
as a shortcut all by itself.
Ideally, someone would be able
to run my intent
without first having to author
a shortcut at all.
By creating an app shortcut,
I can perform this setup step
on behalf of the user,
so they can start
using my intent
as soon as the app is installed.
Now that I've written an intent,
I'll create
an app shortcut for it.
Similar to an intent,
App Shortcuts are defined
in Swift code,
by implementing the
AppShortcutsProvider protocol.
To implement the protocol,
I'll simply create
a single getter that returns
all the app shortcuts
I want to set up for the user.
Note that in total,
your app can have a maximum
of 10 app shortcuts.
However, most apps
only need a few.
So I'll create
a single AppShortcut
for my StartMeditationIntent.
To get started, I'll pass
an instance of my intent.
If my intent's initializer
took parameters,
I could specify values here.
Second, I'll create an array
of spoken phrases
that will invoke
my AppShortcut from Siri.
You'll notice that rather than
writing my application's name
directly in the string,
I used a special
.applicationName token.
This allows Siri to insert not
only my application's main name,
but also any app name synonyms
that I've configured.
Because users may say different
phrases to start meditation,
I'll provide a few more
alternative phrases here.
If your app is localized,
you'll need to localize
these phrases as well.
Great. So now when someone
wants to mediate,
they just stay to Siri,
"Start a meditation."
Siri will call
the StartMeditationIntent
and speak the dialog
that I returned.
Also, if someone searches
for my app in Spotlight,
they'll see the first
App Shortcut I've listed
in my code.
When the user taps the result,
the shortcut
will immediately run
without launching
the application.
It's important to note
that if your intent
does trigger an app launch,
it won't be shown in Spotlight.
So, with just a very small
amount of code,
I've now made it much,
much simpler for my users
to meditate with my app.
But right now, Siri shows
a default view
whenever running my intent.
This is OK, but I'd really
like to show the user
more information when they run
my app shortcut.
To do this, I'll need
to implement a custom view
that Siri can show whenever
my intent is run.
Views in the App Intents
framework are built
using SwiftUI and leverage the
same view technology as widgets.
This means you, as a developer,
don't need to build
a separate UI extension
for your custom view.
Instead, you can simply
return the view
when running your intent.
It's important to think about
the specific constraints
this brings for your views.
Just like widgets,
custom App Intent views
can't include things like
interactivity or animations.
Make sure to take this into
account when designing your UI.
App Intents supports showing
custom UI at three phases:
value confirmation,
intent confirmation,
and after the intent
is finished.
For my app, I'm going to return
a custom view
at the end of running my intent.
If you're using
these other prompts,
be sure to think about how
you can integrate custom UI
at those steps too.
Finally, as I mentioned,
displaying custom UI is easy.
You simply need to return
your view from your intent.
Alright, time to jump
into some code.
Adding a custom view is easy.
As I mentioned, I'll just return
the view alongside my dialog.
The App Intents framework
will take care
of presenting my view
inside the Siri snippet.
Keep in mind that your views
are going to be shown
alongside other Siri views,
like the snippet title
or confirmation buttons.
So you'll want
your snippet's design
to feel at home inside of Siri.
Up next, let's check out how
I can extend an app shortcut
to include parameters.
In my previous implementation,
I chose to start
the default meditation session.
But my app includes
many great session types,
and users will want to start
a particular session
they have in mind.
Ideally, my user would be able
to specify the session
they want to start
when running my intent.
To support these use cases,
I'll need to extend my intent
by adding a parameter
that captures the session
the user wants to run.
To add a parameter,
I first need to define
the parameter's type.
I'll create
a MeditationSession struct
that has the relevant
information for a session.
I'll include a name,
and I'll give it
an identifier field,
which can be a UUID.
To use this struct
as a parameter for my intent,
I also need to implement
the AppEntity protocol.
Implementing
the AppEntity protocol
tells the App Intents framework
about my type
and lets me specify
additional information,
like how the entity
is displayed.
The entity protocol requires
that my type has an identifier,
which I've already provided.
I could use other types as well,
like integers or strings.
I also need to provide
some information
on how to display my entity.
This will be used
in the Shortcuts app
and other places
where my entity is shown.
Finally, I need to wire up
a default query.
I'll call my query
the MeditationSessionQuery,
and I'll implement it next.
In order to work with my entity,
the App Intents framework
needs to be able
to look up my entities
based on their identifier.
To make this possible,
the EntityQuery protocol
defines just one requirement:
a function
that takes identifiers
and returns matching entities.
I'll implement this function
by looking up the sessions
in my SessionManager.
Next, I'll update
my StartMeditationIntent
to add a parameter.
Parameters are
straightforward;
they are just a normal
property on my struct.
But to tell App Intents
about my parameter,
I also need to add the
@Parameter property wrapper.
This property wrapper
lets App Intents know
that the session property
is part of my intent.
I can also specify
additional metadata
in the Parameter property
wrapper, like the display name.
Now that I've added
a parameter to my intent,
I need to ask the user which
session they'd like to run.
The App Intents framework
has robust support
for asking users
follow-up questions
to gather values
for my intent's parameters.
These prompts will be displayed
anywhere my intent is run.
When run from Siri, Siri will
speak out the questions,
and ask the user
to speak the answer.
In Spotlight
and the Shortcuts app,
the user will be presented
with the same prompt
in a touch-driven UI.
App Intents supports
three types of value prompts.
Disambiguations asks the user
to select from a fixed list.
Disambiguations are great
to present the user
when you have small
fixed set of options
for a parameter
in your intent.
Value prompts allow you
to ask the user
for an open-ended value.
These are great for types
like strings or integers,
which can take any value.
Finally, confirmation
asks the user
to verify a particular value
and can be helpful
if you want to double-check
with the user
that you understand
their intent.
Prompting for values is
a great way to make intents
more flexible and allows you
to gather more information
from the user.
But they also slow down
the conversation,
and can frustrate users
if you use them too often.
For more insight into
designing great intents,
check out the session titled
"Design App Shortcuts"
from Lynn.
All right, now that I've added
the session parameter
to the StartMeditationIntent,
I'll go ahead and add logic
to my perform method
to prompt for this value.
In my app, I have a small
fixed number of sessions
the user can run.
If the session
isn't already specified,
I'll retrieve the list
from my SessionManager
and present a disambiguation
to the user.
Using the display representation
for each of my sessions,
App Intents will format
sessions into list items
and display them
to the user.
When the user picks one,
the selected item
will be returned to me.
I'll pass the selected session
to my MeditationService,
which will start
the session.
I can then return a dialog
to let the user know
that the intent has started.
Since the user
provided a session,
it's a good idea to put the name
of the session
in the dialog so the user knows
we understood their request.
Great, so now when my users
say, "Start a Meditation,"
my app can prompt the user
for the particular session
they want to run.
However, as I
mentioned before,
users prefer Siri interactions
that are quick and to the point.
Ideally, I'd be able
to let my users tell Siri
the session they'd like
to run in the initial phrase,
rather than
in a follow-up question.
Well, I have good news.
App Shortcuts has support
for extending trigger phrases
with predefined parameters.
By implementing
parameterized phrases,
my app can support
utterances like
"Start a calming meditation"
or "Start a walking meditation."
Parameters are great
when you have
a fixed set of well-known
parameter values
that you can specify
to Siri ahead of time.
For my app,
I'll use my session names.
Parameters are not meant
for open-ended values.
For example, it's not possible
to gather an arbitrary string
from the user
in the initial utterance.
So, my app couldn't support
a phrase
like "Search my
diary for X,"
where X could be
any input from the user.
Instead, parameter values
are specified ahead of time,
when your app is running.
Let's implement
some parameterized phrases.
To implement parameterized
phrases in my app,
I need to make
a few changes.
First, I'll update the query
for my SessionEntity
to implement the
suggestedResults() method
to return the list of entities
for my parameterized shortcut.
Second, I'll need to notify
the App Intents framework
when the list of available
SessionEntities has changed.
This allows
the App Intents framework
to create new shortcut phrases
for use in Siri.
I'll do this by updating
my app's model layer
to notify
the App Intents framework
whenever my session list
changes.
Finally, I'll add some new
phrases to my App Shortcut
that reference
the session parameter
on my StartMeditationIntent.
So first, I'll update
the MeditationSessionQuery
by implementing the
suggestedEntities function.
The App Intents framework
uses the sessions
returned from this function to
create parameterized shortcuts.
It's important to note that
while this method is optional,
if I don't implement
this method,
I won't get any
parameterized shortcuts at all.
Second, I'll need to update
my app's model layer
to notify
the App Intents framework
whenever my list
of sessions changes.
In my app, I infrequently
publish new session types
that I fetch from the server
in the background.
I'll update my SessionModel
to call the
updateAppShortcutParameters()
method
any time I receive
new sessions.
This method is provided
by the App Intents framework;
you don't need
to implement it yourself.
When called, App Intents
will invoke your entity's query
to gather the list of parameters
for your shortcut phrases.
Finally, I'll add new phrases
for my App Shortcut
that include the session
keypath on my intent.
The App Intents framework
will combine this phrase
with all of the sessions
returned from my query.
The text used for each value is
pulled from the title property
on the SessionEntity's
display representation.
Just like before,
I'll want to include
a few different ways that users
might phrase my App Shortcut.
This ensures
a smoother experience
if the user doesn't remember
your preferred phrase.
All right, I now have a great,
full-featured App Shortcut,
and I can't wait for my users
to give it a try.
But in order
for that to happen,
I need to do some work to help
users discover my new Shortcut.
The first thing I want to talk
about is picking great phrases.
Great phrases for App Shortcuts
are short and memorable.
Users will have a lot
of apps on their phone
that support App Shortcuts;
and in practice,
users can have a hard time
remembering exactly how
to phrase their shortcuts.
So where possible, keep your
phrases short and to the point.
Along these lines,
if your app name
can be used
as a noun or verb,
consider using it that way
in your phrase.
In my app, I've used
Meditation like a noun,
so that the phrase
can be short and memorable.
Finally, app name synonyms
can help your users immensely.
If users call your app
something other than
your app's display name,
you'll want to consider adding
an app name synonym for it.
iOS 11 added support
for app name synonyms.
If you haven't created one, now
may be a great time to do so.
The next thing
I want to talk about
is the Siri Tip
and the Shortcuts link.
Because App Shortcuts
don't require any user setup,
discoverability is vital
for users to find
and use your App Shortcuts.
With App Shortcuts,
users no longer need
the Add to Siri button
to add your Shortcut.
It's already added!
However, we don't want to lose
the discoverability benefits
that the Add to Siri button
provided.
With that in mind, we've
created a new Siri Tip view.
This view works great
anywhere you may have used
the Add To Siri button
in the past.
The Tip view is available
in both SwiftUI and UIKit.
And we've provided
a number of styles
so that the Tip looks great
in any application.
Siri Tips are best placed
contextually,
when they're relevant
to the content onscreen.
If a user just placed
an order in your app,
consider showing a Tip
for your Shortcut
that provides
the order status.
Siri Tips should be
placed thoughtfully,
when you feel a user
is likely to engage
with your App Shortcut
in the near future.
The Siri Tip also
supports dismissal.
The view includes a dismiss
button and will trigger
a custom closure
in your code when tapped.
You'll want to remove
the view from your layout,
and consider
not showing it again
until you feel
it's relevant.
Finally, we've also included
a new ShortcutsLink
that will launch to a list
of Shortcuts from your app.
This new element is great
if your app has a lot
of App Shortcuts
and you want to let users
explore all of them.
Now, the great thing
about App Shortcuts
is they're available as soon
as your app is installed.
Even before the app
is first launched,
users can see and run
your Shortcuts
from Spotlight, Siri,
and the Shortcuts app.
You may need to take this
into account
when building
your App Shortcut.
For example, if your app
requires a log-in flow,
the user may not have logged in
before running your intent.
Your intent should fail
gracefully with an error message
explaining to the user
that they need to log in.
Second, parameterized phrases
for your App Shortcuts
won't be available until
your app has been launched
and notified
the App Intents framework
that you have new
parameter values.
If your App Shortcut
doesn't contain
any non-parameterized
phrases, the user won't see
your App Shortcut at all until
they first launch your app.
You may consider adding a
few non-parameterized phrases
to avoid this issue.
Additionally, Siri has added
support for phrases like,
"What can I do here?" and
"What can I do with Meditation?"
Siri will automatically
gather and recommend
any App Shortcut phrases and
present them on your behalf.
Your app doesn't need
to do anything additional
for this
functionality to work.
Finally, in both Siri
and the Shortcuts app,
the order your App Shortcuts
are displayed is determined
by the order that you list
your App Shortcuts
in your source code.
You'll want to consider putting
your best and most useful
App Shortcuts first, so that
they get the most attention.
Similarly, the first phrase
you list in the phrase array
will be considered the primary
phrase for that App Shortcut.
The primary phrase is used as
the label on the Shortcut tile,
and it's shown
when the user asks Siri
for help with your app.
OK, we covered a lot
about App Intents framework
and App Shortcuts.
I want to leave you
with two key thoughts.
First, App Shortcuts make it
easy for users to use your app
from anywhere in the system, so
think about the best use cases
in your app that fit
this more lightweight model.
Second, once you've
implemented an App Shortcut,
users will not know about it
unless you tell them!
Think hard about how to make
your App Shortcut discoverable.
Consider places in your app
where you can show
the Siri Tip, as well as
off-product locations,
like a website
or a sign in your store.
We can't wait to see
all the great App Shortcuts
that you create with the
new App Intents framework.
To dig deeper into design,
as well as
the App Intents framework,
be sure to check out
other talks this week.
Thanks, and have
a great WWDC.
♪