♪ ♪
Hi.
I'm Stephanie Angulo.
and I'm Marcus Jackson.
We're software engineers
on the Swift Playgrounds Content team.
Today, we will give you
the tools to create
engaging content for Swift Playgrounds.
Swift Playgrounds 4 introduced
app development on iPad and Mac.
It's the best way to learn
about building apps for the App Store.
Our team has released a number
of tutorial and sample code products
that help you learn the fundamentals
of app development.
We cover topics like
building dynamic SwiftUI apps
using observable data models,
customizing views with fun
SwiftUI animations and shapes,
and more advanced topics,
like asynchronous data fetching.
In today's session,
we'll provide an overview
of our new instructional system,
write content
using the project's guide module,
and build an immersive learning experience
with walkthrough and experiment tasks.
Let's get started.
Imagine a learner completing our tutorial,
"Keep Going with Apps."
They'll end up with an app called,
"Emoji App."
In this app, they can keep track
of all their favorite animals in a list,
change their color and size,
and tap on the animals
to watch them get their groove on
in "Creature Dance" view.
This dance view is fun,
but I want the vibe to be
more of an actual dance party.
So let's go ahead and add some extra
features we can show our learners.
Here, I added a bit more code
to "Creature Dance" view.
Every party needs a dance floor.
So I made a 10x10 grid
that I set as my view's background.
And each tile in the grid
updates its color randomly
using a custom view modifier.
Looks groovy huh?
I also wanted to make sure
our favorite animals can dance
without our help,
so I made a few more custom modifiers
that help animate the animals' scale,
position offset, and rotation.
In all of these custom modifiers,
these animations are set to repeatForever,
which means our animals can dance
all night on their brand-new dance floor.
And finally,
to really light up the dance floor,
I added an animated disco ball
at the top of our view.
Adding this final touch
really pulls it all together
for the ultimate dance party.
I've made quite a few changes
to this project,
and I didn't even to dive into the details
of custom view modifiers.
So how should we explain this
to our learners?
You could direct a learner
to Apple's documentation,
but now you also have
the option to teach these concepts
alongside your project's code
in Swift Playgrounds.
Our team has built
this new instructional system
that's designed to help authors like you
create engaging in-app experiences
for your learners.
Today, we'll walk you through
how to build the learning content
for this app in Swift Playgrounds 4.
Let me give you a sneak peek
of what you'll be walking away with.
When a learner first opens
your content on Swift Playgrounds,
you can introduce them to the project
with an optional welcome message,
as shown here from our friend Byte.
The welcome message sits at the top
of the project's source editor
on the left hand side of the screen,
while on the right hand side
of the screen is the learning center.
The learning center is a designated area
where you can add images
and instructional text that describes
your content to your learners.
In our welcome message
and our learning center,
we're letting our learners know that this
project will be pumping up the jams
with the help of SwiftUI colors,
shapes, and animations.
The learning center also contains
a section for tasks.
Tasks are coding objectives you the author
can write to help guide your learners.
They're a fundamental
building block for content.
By tapping a task button
in the learning center,
our instructional system will open up
a Swift file
and render a card with learning material
at the top of that file.
This card can contain a series of pages
with text, images, and code snippets.
Later, Marcus will go over
two tasks types:
walkthroughs and experiments.
At a high level, that's what
our instructional system has to offer.
With the right prose and the right tasks,
you can build a compelling
educational experience for your learners.
Now, in order to start
creating your own content,
we first need to talk
about the guide module.
By default,
the file structure of a swiftpm project
keeps all its source code at its root.
In order to upgrade your project
to take advantage
of the instructional system,
you'll need to change its file structure.
We first need to create an App module.
Once it's created, we need to move
all our project's source code
and assets into it.
The Package.swift file should be
left at the root of our project.
Then we need to create a guide module.
This module should be at the same level
as the App module and Package.swift file.
Inside the guide module,
you'll need a guide file.
This file will include all the prose
of your learning content.
I've already started on my guide file,
so let's check out the content
I've written so far.
The guide file contains a combination
of directives and markdown.
Directives are an extension of markdown
that can take in primitive types
as attributes, such as strings,
as well as more complex types,
like markdown elements
and other directives.
Directives can act as containers
for other directives,
but they can also represent UI elements
in our instructional system.
First in the guide file, I've added
the necessary guidebook directive
that's wrapped
around the entirety of the file.
It acts as the main container
for all our directives.
Its parameters include a title,
icon and background image,
and the file you first want opened
when you open the project.
Under the guidebook directive,
I've added a welcome message directive.
Welcome messages are optional
and as mentioned earlier,
they are presented to the learner
when they first open up the project.
Below the welcome message directive,
I've added a guide directive
that's wrapped around a step directive.
The guide directive acts as a container
for your steps
and steps map out to your content
displayed in the learning center
and tasks.
To start adding images and instructional
text in your learning center,
you'll need to include a ContentAndMedia
directive inside your step.
So I got this party started
by adding a dance floor,
a nice welcome message,
and the prose for the learning center.
Marcus,
do you wanna keep this party going?
Marcus: Definitely.
What a dope dance floor
for our creatures to party on.
While this effect is really cool,
I think it might be too much
for someone who is still learning.
To help explain this code,
we can use walkthrough tasks.
Let's start with a one-page walkthrough.
Later, I'll show you
how to fill out the rest.
Stephanie already showed you
the beginnings of our guidebook,
as well as a helpful welcome message.
We already have the first directive
you need to create tasks,
the step directive.
The step directive is where
our walkthrough content will live.
To make a step, you need to fill it
with two other directives.
Here, we've already added
a content and media directive.
This directive contains markdown
that goes into the learning center
on the right hand side.
The body of this directive can contain
any form of markdown text.
This is the place to put longer prose
and larger images
that might help cover your topic.
Here is the content and media directive
being displayed in Playgrounds.
While the area seems small
in this example,
this view can extend further down
and is contained in a scroll view.
This makes it a great place
to write longer bits of prose
and show complex content such as diagrams.
Once you have
your content and media written,
we can add in the second
required directive, tasks.
We add our tasks into another directive
called a task group.
Task groups are an optional directive
you can put inside of steps,
if you want to collect
a group of tasks together.
You might consider this if you have
content which covers the same topic
across multiple files
or different types of tasks.
Within the task group,
we can add a short bit of text.
This will be displayed
in the learning center as a subtitle.
Here is how a task group
displays in Playgrounds.
Now that I have
my task group and my subtitle,
I can start adding task directives.
Tasks have a few parameters
The first parameter is type.
This lets the instructional system know
what UI to generate
when displaying this task.
Next, every task needs an ID.
IDs are strings
that can be anything you want.
However, every ID in the guide
must be unique.
The title parameter is also a string.
This can also be whatever you want
and does not have to be unique.
This title will be rendered
by the task card UI.
Finally, the file parameter tells
the learning center
which file in the project to open
when the learner starts this task.
Here is how
a task displays on Playgrounds.
The title sits inside of a button,
and the file of the walkthrough
is listed above it.
Now we have our walkthrough task written.
Let's add our first page.
Page directives go
inside the body of a task
and have the following
mandatory parameters:
The ID parameter behaves
just like the ID for a task,
so they must be unique
for the entire guide file.
The title parameter behaves
a lot like the one for tasks.
However, when you leave
the title string empty on a page,
this lets the instructional system know
to use the task's title
when displaying this page.
Inside of a page,
you can add any markdown text,
similar to the content
and media directive.
However, the task view is
much smaller than the learning center.
Keep your text short and avoid
using complex images like diagrams
because they may be hard
for the learner to read.
This is the first page of our walkthrough
as rendered by Swift Playgrounds.
We're almost done
with our first walkthrough,
but first I need to show you
how to highlight the code
as shown in the last screenshot.
For that, we need to add some markers
to CreatureDance.swift.
When my walkthrough is shown,
I'd like to highlight
the first custom modifier,
the animatedScalingEffect.
To add highlights to a line,
I'll add a pair of comments on the lines
before and after the code.
We start with the multiline
comment syntax, /*
Inside the comment,
we write #-code
-walkthrough,
followed by a pair of parentheses.
Inside the parentheses, we write the ID
of the page directive
we want to highlight.
In this case, 1.modifier.
Now, let's test this out in Playgrounds.
Let's open the Emoji App project.
When you open the project,
you're greeted with the source editor
on the left and the preview on the right.
Above the source editor
is our welcome message,
where our buddy Byte gives you an overview
of what learning content there is to do.
I'll tap on the Learn More button.
The preview on the right
is swapped out for the learning center.
At the top is the prose we wrote
in the ContentAndMedia directive.
Below that is the task group,
as well as the button
with the title of our walkthrough.
Walkthroughs are denoted
in the learning center as buttons
with pictures of another one
of Byte's friends, Expert.
Tapping on this button does a few things:
First, the learning center is once again
swapped out for the preview.
Second, if it isn't already open,
the file specified
in the task's file parameter
is opened in the source editor.
Third, the task view drops down
above the source editor.
Finally, the source editor highlights
the code marked
in the code walkthrough comments.
If the content is not on screen,
the source editor will scroll
until the lines of code that need
to be highlighted appear.
And that is how you write
a walkthrough in Swift Playgrounds,
but I think it's fair to say
you're probably curious
what a walkthrough
with multiple pages looks like.
To do that, I'll open the project in Xcode
to fill out the rest of my walkthrough.
Now with the guide file open in Xcode,
I'd like to add a couple more pages
to my walkthrough.
I've explained a little bit
about what a view modifier is,
but I'd like to explain more
about how to build a custom view modifier.
I'll go ahead and add those pages.
Great.
Now we have our walkthrough
for custom view modifiers.
I think now is also a good time
to explain the ViewModifier protocol.
This way, learners can try to make
their own ViewModifiers if they want to.
To do this, I'll add another walkthrough
to our task group.
We now have
a fully fleshed out pair of walkthroughs.
I'll switch back over to my iPad
to see how it looks.
When we open our project,
there are now two walkthroughs
in the learning center.
I'll start by tapping
on the first walkthrough.
Just like before,
the line with the view modifier highlights
and our task view drops down
to explain what this code is.
Now I can tap the next button.
The source editor now scrolls down
to the modifier struct
and explains what this struct is for.
Tapping on the next button again moves
to the final page of this walkthrough,
which explains more about the body method
inside the modifier struct.
In the bottom corner of the task view,
there is a button marked Next Walkthrough.
Tapping on this automatically begins
the next walkthrough task.
This functionality is given to you
for free by the instructional system
as long as there is another task
to progress to.
Now that I am here, I will tap
through the rest of this walkthrough.
And that is how you build walkthroughs
in Swift Playgrounds.
Next, I'd like to show you how to create
a different kind of task
that will allow learners to try adding
code themselves and seeing what happens.
So at this point,
we have a good party going.
Our creatures are dancing, and they have
some lights in the background.
While it basically looks
like a nightclub in there,
I think we can do a little bit better.
I think it would be great
to add some colors to our creatures
so it looks like they're dancing under
the strobe lights of their little club.
But that's just me. What would you do?
This is where experiment tasks come in.
Experiments are optional bits of code
learners can add
if they are feeling extra curious
or if they want a way
of making the app unique to them.
Back in the guide file,
we can add our experiment task
to the same step
we were already working on.
I've created a new task group
to hold our experiments
which I've named "Experiments."
I've populated it with a subtitle
as well as the beginnings
of our first experiment task.
The first difference between
an experiment task and a walkthrough
is what goes into the type parameter.
The other parameters follow
a similar convention to walkthrough tasks.
Page directives work the same way
they do in walkthroughs.
However, for experiments, we add
one optional parameter, isAddable.
The isAddable parameter allows
experiment tasks to add code
directly into the source editor.
When isAddable is set to true,
an add button appears
in the learning task card
next to the code snippet.
The code in a page directive
must be wrapped in a code block
using the triple back tick
markdown syntax.
It's best practice to keep
your code blocks to ten lines or less.
While the task view can show
longer code snippets if need be,
it's better
if learners don't have to scroll.
Here is how the code view
displays in Playgrounds.
To the right of the code snippet,
is an add button,
since the isAddable parameter
was set to true.
That is almost everything we need
to write an experiment task.
But remember that isAddable parameter?
This allows the experiment task
to add code to the source editor,
but we need to tell Playgrounds
where in the code to add the snippet.
Here we are again in CreatureDance.swift.
I want learners to add the color modifier
right below the opacity modifier.
So that's where I'll add
my experiment task comment.
Experiment task comments are single line,
meaning they start with a double slash.
Then, we write #-
learning-task.
After, comes a pair of parentheses,
and inside we write the ID
of the experiment task.
Now we have everything we need
to test out our experiment task.
Once again, I have all this
already written in the swiftpm project
Stephanie and I are working on.
Let's check it out.
We're back once again
to the learning center.
This time I want to focus
on the bottom task group,
where our first experiment is.
Experiments are noted
in the instructional system
by another one of Byte's friends, Blu.
Let's tap on the experiment task.
What happens next should seem familiar.
The task view drops down.
However, this time,
the task view contains a code view.
On the right of the code view
is an add button.
Tapping on this adds the code
right to the source editor.
With the code now added,
I'd like to check out
what changes that made
to the CreatureDanceView.
Let's start this party!
Sweet.
Now we can see the lights
hitting our creatures.
This is pretty groovy, but I think
we can take it up one more notch
by using a timer to give the creatures
a random color every few seconds.
To do that, we'll need to add
another experiment,
so let's take this project back to Xcode
and add our new task.
Before we add in our second experiment,
I think it's a good idea to add a page
to the experiment that's already there.
For a learner,
it can be confusing to add a block of code
and not know why or what it does.
To help with that, I'll add a page
with some text before our code page.
Now, we are ready to add our second task.
Again, I want the learner
to add some code to their project,
so I'll add a page explaining the code
followed by an addable code snippet.
And with that, we have made
a new piece of content to teach learners
about some of the things you can do
with custom view modifiers.
Hey, Stephanie, you ready to show them
what we've built?
Stephanie: Yeah, let's do it.
I'll open the final version of our content
on my iPad
and check out how my changes
and Marcus' changes flow together.
When I first open the project,
the welcome message animates in,
introducing us to Creature Party.
When I tap on the Learn More button
in the welcome message,
it opens the learning center for me.
Awesome.
Our learning center does have
my description at the top
and the four tasks Marcus added.
Let's tap on the first walkthrough.
Here, Marcus used
my AnimatedScalingModifier
as an example to explain
how to use custom view modifiers.
When I tap on the Next Walkthrough Button,
the second walkthrough animates in.
Marcus used the View Modifier protocol as
an example to describe how protocols work.
After finishing the second walkthrough,
when I tap Done,
the first experiment task segues in.
The Dancing in the Strobe Light task
tells me
I can add some color to our creatures
by adding this code snippet
containing a colorMultiply modifier.
Let's remind ourselves
what this dance party looks like
before adding the code snippet.
All right, cool.
I'll add the code snippet by tapping Add
and tap Start the Party again
to check out the changes.
Nice, the creatures changed color.
I'll complete this experiment task now
and transition to the last one.
The Switch It Up experiment task
tells me I can customize the color
of the animals
with a tap gesture and a timer.
I'll add the code snippet
and start the party once more.
And now when I tap on the animals,
they change color.
Nice.
I'll complete this last task
and head back to the learning center.
Now, all tasks are marked as completed
in the learning center,
which means we've completed this sample.
And that's how you take advantage
of our new content features
in Swift Playgrounds 4.
We hope you enjoyed today's session
and we're so excited
to see what sorts
of learning experiences you'll build.
Don't forget to check out
the other Swift Playgrounds session,
Build your First App in Swift Playgrounds.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC.
Marcus: And now, if you'll excuse us,
we have a party to attend.