♪ ♪
Souvik Banerjee: Hi, and welcome
to "Bring your driver to iPad
with DriverKit."
I'm Souvik, and today I'll discuss several
exciting new developments in DriverKit.
We're going to discuss three topics today.
First, I'll give a brief overview
of DriverKit.
Then, I'll discuss some updates
to AudioDriverKit.
And I'll end with how to bring your
drivers to the iPad
Let's get started with an overview.
In 2019, we introduced DriverKit,
a replacement for IOKit device drivers.
DriverKit brought a new way
to extend the system
that is more reliable and secure,
running in userspace.
And it's easier to develop
since your process isn't in the kernel.
These driver extensions,
also known as dexts, are bundled in apps,
and you can easily distribute your apps
and drivers on the Mac App Store.
People can easily find your driver
with a search,
and if your driver is no longer needed,
you can just delete the app
to uninstall it.
Since introducing DriverKit, we have added
support for many new driver families.
We now support Networking,
Block Storage, Serial,
Audio, and SCSI controller
and peripheral drivers
in addition to transports
such as USB, PCI, and HID.
To learn more about the kinds of drivers
you can build with DriverKit,
please check out the "Create audio drivers
with DriverKit" session
from WWDC 2021
and the "Modernize PCI and SCSI drivers
with DriverKit" session
from WWDC 2020.
Next, we added several new features
in AudioDriverKit recently
that I want to highlight.
One of these features
is real-time operations.
We're excited to introduce
a new feature in AudioDriverKit
allowing you to register
a real-time callback.
This callback gets invoked
every time an IO operation happens.
You can use this callback if you need
to modify your audio buffers
on a real-time thread,
such as for signal processing.
To register a real-time callback
in AudioDriverKit,
we declare an IOOperationHandler block
to set on the IOUserAudioDevice.
This block will be called
from a real-time context
when an IO operation occurs
on the IOUserAudioStream buffers
for the device.
Inside the block,
we check what the operation is,
and we can modify the data as necessary.
Finally, we call SetIOOperationHandler
to set the block on the audio device.
Now let's talk about entitlements.
When we introduced AudioDriverKit,
you had to use
the allow-any-userclient-access
entitlement on your driver.
In macOS 12.1,
we introduced a new entitlement
specifically for AudioDriverKit.
Please update your audio drivers
to use the new audio family entitlement
instead of the
allow-any-userclient-access entitlement.
You can keep the
allow-any-userclient-access entitlement
if you want any app to be able
to communicate with your driver.
This new entitlement
is public for development,
so you can get started using this today
without filing a request.
In fact, all DriverKit family entitlements
are now available to use for development.
To request
this entitlement for distribution,
please visit the System Extension page
on developer.apple.com.
Now, I'm really excited to tell you
about DriverKit on iPad.
Professionals are increasingly
using iPad to do their best work.
But many rely on external hardware
that they couldn't use on iPad.
So today, we're excited to announce
that DriverKit is coming to iPad.
DriverKit on macOS has made it possible
to extend the system
in a safe and secure way,
and we're bringing
that same technology to the iPad.
In fact, if you've already created
a driver with DriverKit on the Mac,
you can bring that exact same driver
to the iPad
without any changes to your driver.
USB, PCI, and Audio will be
supported in iPadOS 16.
This will enable Thunderbolt audio
interfaces on iPad for the first time,
and many more devices.
This is made possible
with the power of the M1 chip.
All iPads with M1 will support DriverKit.
DriverKit on iPadOS
is the same as on macOS.
This means that you can build
one DriverKit driver
and have it work on both platforms,
no source changes required.
In addition ,
using the new multiplatform apps feature
in Xcode 14, you can easily create
a single app target
to deliver your driver
on both Mac and iPad.
For more information
about multiplatform apps,
please check out the "Use Xcode
to develop a multiplatform app" session.
Xcode also now supports
automatic signing of DriverKit drivers.
It knows how to handle DriverKit on iPadOS
and can provision for both Mac and iPad.
You no longer need to configure
manual signing for DriverKit drivers.
Your iPadOS app and driver
can be distributed on the App Store ,
just like on macOS.
This means that you can take advantage
of features like in-app purchases
and have your driver be
easily discoverable by users.
Let's see just how easy it is
to take an existing macOS driver and app
and bring it to iPad.
Here, I have an app
called DriverKitSampleApp.
It has a SwiftUI view
with a label and a button
allowing the user to install the driver.
Our driver is called NullDriver.
It prints a message when the driver starts
and starts a timer that fires every second
and increments a counter
called timerCount.
To make this an iPad app,
all I need to do is select
the DriverKitSampleApp target in Xcode...
And add iPad to Supported Destinations.
Now I can change my run destination
to the iPad I have connected to my Mac.
Let's try running this on the iPad.
Here's our iPad app.
We have the label and the button
from the view we saw in Xcode.
Tapping the Install Dext button
takes us to Settings,
where we see this new Drivers link.
We tap that link, and we see a list
of all drivers bundled in this app.
We can then enable our Null Driver.
So you might have noticed
several things in the demo.
Our Null Driver is bundled
inside our iPadOS app,
and it gets automatically discovered
by the system after installation.
On macOS , you would need to use
the SystemExtension framework
to prompt the user to install the driver.
On iPadOS, there is no
SystemExtensions framework.
Inside Xcode, you can see
that our driver is embedded
within our app.
Since drivers are low-level software
and are privileged,
they need to be approved by the user
before they can run.
On macOS, users need to go
to the Security & Privacy preferences
to allow system extensions.
On iPadOS, the driver approvals
are in the Settings app.
There are two options
for driver approvals.
If there is at least one app
with a driver installed,
there will be a menu
inside General Settings
with a list of all available drivers.
Each driver can be toggled on or off.
If your app contains a Settings bundle,
there will be a Drivers link
inside your app's Settings.
Your app should prompt the user
to enable the driver in Settings.
Let's start again
with our macOS driver project
and see how we can have our app
prompt the user to enable
the driver in Settings.
We start by adding iPad
to our supported destinations.
Our SwiftUI view has a button
to install the driver,
and our view model has a state machine
that interacts
with the SystemExtensions framework.
Since this project is going to build
for both Mac and iPad,
we want to keep our Mac view
and view model
but create a new view
that will be used on iPad.
Then, we can go to Build Phases
and Compile sources
and change the platform filter
for each file
to conditionally compile for iOS or macOS.
Now, let's add
a Settings bundle to our app.
We're going to use the default
example Settings for now,
but we can change these later
to real Settings that the app can use.
Now let's check the iOS view
we just created.
We can copy our macOS view
to our iOS view
to use as a starting point.
Our iOS view doesn't use a view model,
so we can remove that.
We also need to change our button action
to open our Settings bundle.
This will take the user into Settings,
so that they can enable the driver.
Finally, we change the button text
to make it clear
that the user needs to enable the driver
in Settings.
Let's see this in action.
We have the view we designed,
and tapping the button takes us
to our Settings bundle.
Then we go into Drivers
and enable the Null Driver.
It's important to keep in mind
that drivers launch on demand.
Although we've enabled the driver
in Settings,
the driver only starts running
when the hardware device is
plugged in to the iPad.
After the driver starts running,
I can attach a debugger to it
using Xcode wireless debugging.
To do that,
I go to the Debug menu in Xcode,
attach to process,
then select the NullDriver process.
Once attached, I can set breakpoints
or pause execution.
Here, I've set a breakpoint in our timer.
I'm going to print timerCount to see
how many times our timer has been called.
When you're done debugging,
detach from the driver process
using the Debug menu in Xcode.
So now we have a driver.
But a driver isn't very useful by itself.
It needs to communicate
with the rest of the system.
Some DriverKit frameworks
like AudioDriverKit handle this for you.
But if you need to do something
more advanced,
such as creating a custom
control panel app for your hardware,
you need to have your app be able
to communicate with your driver.
This is what user clients allow you to do.
They allow you
to define your own interface,
allowing app and driver communication.
Apps use the IOKit.framework
to open user clients.
For an example of how this works,
please see the sample code
on developer.apple.com.
So we know that apps can
communicate with drivers.
But it's important
to keep security in mind.
Since drivers are privileged,
we don't want to allow every app
to communicate with drivers.
On macOS, the app needs the driverkit
userclient-access entitlement,
and the value is an array
of allowed driver bundle identifiers.
On iPadOS, we added a new entitlement
called Communicates With Drivers.
It replaces
the macOS user client entitlement.
This entitlement grants your app
the ability to open user clients
to your driver.
If you want to add
the Communicates With Drivers entitlement
manually to your app,
here's the XML entitlement string.
We can also add
this entitlement from Xcode.
In Xcode,
we go to Signing and Capabilities,
then add a new capability.
Then, we can search
for "communicates with drivers"
and add the capability to our app.
Another use case for user clients
is to allow apps from other developers
to interact with your driver.
So in this case,
suppose you have an app and driver
and you want to provide a service
to other apps,
including those from other developers.
DriverKit user clients also support this.
Each app that needs to communicate
with drivers
needs the communicates
with drivers entitlement.
The driver needs the Allow Third Party
User Clients entitlement.
This allows apps
built with a different team identifier
to open a user client to the driver.
Without this entitlement,
only apps from the same team
can communicate with the driver.
If you want to add the Allow Third Party
User Clients entitlement
manually to your driver,
here's the XML entitlement string.
Or we can add this capability from Xcode
by going into Signing and Capabilities
for our driver.
These new user client entitlements
are public for development,
which means that you can get started
using this today without any approval.
To request these entitlements
for distribution,
please see our developer website.
DriverKit drivers also have
important implications for app update.
Automatic app update ensures users
always get the latest version of your app.
However, for apps containing drivers,
the update process works
a little differently.
Let's suppose you distribute version 1
of your app on the app store.
Then, you install that app
along with its bundled driver on your iPad
and enable the driver in Settings.
When you plug in the hardware device
for your driver,
the driver starts running,
and once the driver starts running,
your app can begin communicating
with your driver using user clients.
Now, suppose you find a bug in your app
and you submit version 2 to the App Store.
Because of automatic app update,
the version 2 app is downloaded
and installed on your iPad automatically.
The driver approval state is
maintained through updates,
so you don't need to approve
the driver again.
However, notice that the hardware
is still plugged in,
and our version 1 driver is still running.
Driver version 2 was downloaded
with the app update
but does not start running.
Since the old driver
still continues running,
your version 2 app may have to communicate
with the version 1 driver.
When the hardware device is unplugged,
the driver stops running,
so now driver version 1 is done
and we can update the driver to version 2.
Now, if you plug in the device again,
we start the version 2 driver,
and now your app is communicating
with the new driver.
To recap: Apps are updated anytime
with automatic app update.
Drivers are updated
after the device is unplugged.
And your app may communicate
with an old driver.
When your app and driver are ready,
you can submit them to the App Store.
Your drivers can only run
on devices that support DriverKit.
If you want to restrict
your app to those devices,
such as if your app
only installs a driver,
add DriverKit to your app's
UIRequiredDeviceCapabilities.
This will prevent users
from installing your app
on a device
that does not support DriverKit.
We also suggest submitting a video
to App Review
showing how your app and driver work
with your hardware device.
So that's DriverKit on iPad.
You can now bring USB, PCI,
and Audio drivers to iPad with M1
and deliver those drivers
inside apps on the App Store.
And if you already have a driver,
it's easy to bring that to iPad.
We encourage developers
to try using DriverKit on iPad
and provide any feedback
using Feedback Assistant.
Thank you for watching.