♪ ♪
Hi, I'm Richard,
I'm an engineer
on the Swift Standard Library team.
Today, let's embark on a journey
beyond the basics of Swift Regex.
Swift 5.7 is gaining powerful
new capabilities for string processing.
They start with the 'Regex' type,
a new type in the Swift Standard Library.
A language built-in Regex literal syntax,
which makes this powerful and
familiar concept even more first-class.
And finally, a result builder API
called RegexBuilder.
It is a domain-specific language,
or DSL,
that takes advantage
of the syntactic simplicity
and composability of result builders,
and pushes the readability
of Regex to a whole new level.
For background as to why Swift Regex
makes it easier to process strings,
check out the Meet Swift Regex session
by my colleague Michael.
Let's look at a very simple example
of Swift Regex.
Let's say I have a string of data,
and like to match and extract
the user ID from this string.
I can create a regular expression
from text
like I normally do with
'NSRegularExpression'.
It matches "user_id" colon
followed by zero or more whitespaces
followed by one or more digits
What's different this time
is that we are creating
a value of type Regex.
This is a new type
in the Swift Standard Library.
I can then use string's
'firstMatch' algorithm
to find the first occurrence
of the pattern defined by this Regex,
and print the whole match,
just like that.
Because my Regex string
is known at compile-time,
I can switch to using a Regex literal
so that the compiler would check
for syntax errors
and Xcode can show syntax highlighting.
But for ultimate readability
and customizations,
I can use the Regex builder DSL.
With Regex builder,
reading the content of a Regex
is as easy as reading native Swift API.
In this session I will show you
how Regex works
and how you can apply Regex
in your workflow.
A Regex is a program that is to be
executed by its underlying Regex engine.
When executing a Regex,
the Regex engine takes an input string,
and performs matching
from the start to the end of the string.
Let's take a look at a very simple Regex.
This Regex matches a string
that starts with one or more of letter "a"
followed by one or more digits.
I use one of the matching algorithms,
'wholeMatch',
to match input "aaa12".
The Regex engine will start
from the first character of the input.
First, it matches
one or more of character a.
At this point,
it reaches character "1"
and tries to match this character
against character "a".
But it doesn't match.
So the Regex engine moves
to the next pattern in the Regex,
to match one or more digits.
As we reach the end of the string,
matching succeeds.
In the rest of this session,
I will explain a bit more
about this execution model.
With Regex built on its underlying
Regex engine,
the Regex builder DSL
and Regex-powered algorithms expand
the power and expressivity of Regex.
Regex-powered algorithms
are collection-based APIs
that provide some of the most
common operations such as first match,
which finds the first occurrence
of a Regex in a string,
'wholeMatch', which matches
the entire string against a Regex,
'prefixMatch', which matches the prefix
of a string against a Regex.
Besides matching,
the Swift standard library also added APIs
for Regex-based predication, replacement,
trimming, and splitting.
Also, Regex can now be used
in Swift's pattern matching syntax
in control flow statements,
making it easier than ever
to switch on strings.
Finally, on top of Regex builder
and Regex-powered algorithms,
this year, Foundation introduced
its own Regex support
that works seamlessly with Regex builder.
The Regex support in Foundation is
none other than the formatters
and parsers
that you are probably already using,
such as those for Date and Number.
If you want to learn
more about these APIs,
watch the What's new in Foundation
session from WWDC21.
This year, Foundation is adding support
for formatting and parsing URLs as well.
With Regex support in Foundation,
you can embed the Foundation parsers
directly in Regex builder.
For example,
to parse a bank statement like this,
I can use a Foundation-provided
date parser with a custom format
and a currency parser
with a domain-specific parse strategy.
This is a really big deal
because you can create Regexes
out of existing battle-tested parsers
that take care of corner cases
and support localization,
and compose them with the expressivity
of the Regex builder DSL.
To show you how you can apply
Swift Regex to your workflow,
let's work out an example together.
I have been writing a script
to parse the logs
from running XCTest-based unit tests.
A test log starts and ends
with the status of a test suite.
Then XCTest runs every test case
and reports the status of the test case.
Today let's parse the first
and the last lines of the log.
It's information about a test suite.
First, I import RegexBuilder.
RegexBuilder is a new module
in the Swift Standard Library
that provides the RegexBuilder DSL.
Regex can be initialized
with a trailing closure
that represents the body of the Regex.
Let's look at an example log message.
There are three variable substrings
that we care about in this log;
the test suite's name,
the status,
whether it started, passed, or failed,
and the timestamp.
I can parse
other parts of this line verbatim,
while coming up with a pattern
to parse the three variable substrings.
The log message starts
with the word "test suite",
followed by a space and a single quote.
Then we parse the test suite's name.
The name is an identifier,
which can contain lowercase or uppercase
letters or digits,
but the first character
can never be a digit.
So we create a custom character class
to match a letter as the first character.
Then I match zero or more characters
that are either a letter
or a digit from zero to nine.
This is very clear and readable,
but it's a little cumbersome.
Many of you may be familiar
with the textual Regex syntax.
In RegexBuilder, I can actually embed
a concise Regex literal
directly in the body.
A Regex literal
starts and ends with a slash.
Swift infers the correct
strong type for it.
This Regex, for example,
matches the substring, "Hello, WWDC!".
So its output type is substring.
But what's really cool about
a first-class Regex literal
is strongly typed capturing groups.
For example, I can write a capturing group
to capture two digits as the year.
And give a name
to this capturing group, "year".
When I do this, another substring
will appear in the output type.
Later in this talk, I will show you
how you can use captures
to extract information from a string.
Besides standard Regex literals,
Swift also supports
extended Regex literals,
starting with pound slash
and ending with slash pound.
The extended literal allows
non-semantic whitespaces.
In this mode you can split your patterns
into multiple lines.
With a Regex literal embedded
in my RegexBuilder,
it's clean and yet familiar.
After I parse the test name,
I parse a single quote and a whitespace.
Now I reach the test status.
There are multiple types of test status:
started, failed, and passed.
To match one of these options,
we use 'ChoiceOf'.
'ChoiceOf' matches one of
multiple subpatterns
and it's exactly what we need.
Next we parse what comes
immediately after the status,
a space followed by
"at" followed by a space.
The rest of the string is a timestamp.
We can match this
as one or more of any character.
But as I look at some more examples,
a log message sometimes ends
with a period.
We still want to use 'Optionally'
to match the period when it exists.
To match an input against a Regex,
use one of the provided
matching algorithms.
Let's use 'wholeMatch', which matches
the entire string against a Regex.
With 'wholeMatch',
I match each of these log messages,
and print the matched content.
It matched!
But we don't just want to know
whether it matches the strings.
We also want to extract information
that we care about,
such as the test name,
the status, and the timestamp.
So let's go ahead and do this
with one of the coolest features of Regex,
Captures!
A Capture saves a portion of the input
during matching.
It is available as "Capture"
in RegexBuilder
and as a pair of parentheses
in Regex syntax.
Capturing appends the matched substring
to the output tuple type.
An output tuple type starts with
the whole substring
that matched the entire Regex,
followed by the first capture,
the second capture, and so on.
The matching algorithm
returns a Regex Match,
from which you can obtain
the output tuple.
The whole match, the first capture,
and the second capture.
Let me use captures
in my test suite log Regex.
I capture the test suite's name,
the status,
and the timestamp.
Let's again run this Regex
on some inputs,
and print the three things
that we captured.
That looks like a successful match!
It printed the name,
the status, and the timestamp.
But as I look closely,
something in the date is a little off.
It included the period in the input
as part of the capture.
So let me go back and check
the Regex for errors.
I want to focus on the timestamp Regex
and see what's wrong with it.
Then I realize, the pattern
"one or more of any character"
consumes everything from
the first digit of the timestamp,
all the way to the end of the line.
So the "Optionally period" pattern
below it never matched.
I can fix this by making this
OneOrMore reluctant.
"Reluctant" is a case
of repetition behaviors.
One or more, zero or more,
optionally, and repeat
are what Swift Regex calls repetitions.
A repetition is eager by default.
It matches as many occurrences
as possible.
Let me use the example from earlier.
When the Regex engine tries to match
OneOrMore of any character eagerly,
it starts with the first character,
and it accepts any character along the way
till the end of the input.
Then the Regex engine moves on
to match Optionally period.
There's no more period to match,
but it's optional anyway, so it succeeds.
Because we're running
the 'wholeMatch' algorithm,
and both the input
and the Regex pattern reach the end,
matching succeeds.
Although matching succeeded,
the period had already been captured
unexpectedly as part of the OneOrMore.
When we change
the repetition behavior to reluctant,
the Regex engine matches
the repetition a little differently.
It matches as few characters as possible.
So when the Regex engine matches
the input string this time,
It carefully marches forward
by always trying to match
the rest of the Regex first,
before consuming a repetition occurrence.
When the rest of the Regex doesn't match,
the engine backtracks to the repetition
and consumes an additional occurrence.
Let's fast forward to the last character,
the period.
Unlike eager behavior,
the Regex engine did not consume
the period initially
as part of the OneOrMore,
but tries to match
the "Optionally period" pattern instead.
This matches, and the Regex engine
reaches the end of the pattern.
So matching succeeds,
and it produces the correct capture
without a trailing period in it.
Because eager is the default behavior,
as you create your Regex
using a repetition,
you should think about its implications
on your intended match.
You can specify the behavior
at a per-repetition level,
by passing an extra argument,
or, you can use
the 'repetitionBehavior' modifier
to override it for all repetitions
that did not specify a behavior.
As we've modified the repetition behavior
for the timestamp to be reluctant,
Matching now extracts the right timestamp
without including the period.
Let's come back to the Regex.
As I use Capture to extract
the test status from the input,
its type is Substring.
But it would be much better
if I can convert the substring
into something more programming friendly,
like a custom data structure.
To do this,
I can use a transforming capture.
A transforming capture is a Capture
with a transform closure.
Upon matching, the Regex engine calls
the transform closure
on the matched substring,
which produces a result
of the desired type.
The corresponding Regex output type
becomes the closure's return type.
Here, by transforming the capture
with Int's initializer from String,
I get an optional Int
in the output tuple type.
To obtain a non-optional output,
TryCapture can help.
TryCapture is a variant of Capture
which accepts a transform
that returns an optional
and removes the optionality
in the output type.
Returning nil during matching will cause
the Regex engine to backtrack
and try an alternative path.
TryCapture is most useful
when you transform a capture
with a failable initializer.
A natural fit for storing the captured
test status, would be an enumeration.
So let's define one.
I defined a TestStatus enum
with three cases:
started, passed, and failed.
The raw string values makes
this enum initializable from a string.
In the Regex,
I switch to 'TryCapture' with a transform.
In the transform closure,
I call the TestStatus initializer
to convert the matched substring
to a TestStatus value.
Now the corresponding output type
is TestStatus.
Using a custom data structure like this
makes the Regex match output type safe.
Back to the Regex.
There is one additional improvement
I'd like to make.
Currently, I match the timestamp
using a wildcard pattern.
It's going to produce a substring.
This means that if my app wants
to understand the timestamp,
it'd have to parse the substring again
into another data structure.
Earlier in the session,
I mentioned that Foundation
now supports Swift Regex,
providing industry-strength parsers
as Regexes.
So instead of parsing the date
as a substring,
I can switch to Foundation's ISO 8601
date parser
to parse the timestamp as a date.
Now the inferred type shows
that this Regex outputs a Date.
As I run 'wholeMatch' on the inputs,
I can see that the date string was parsed
into a Foundation Date value.
Having access to
battle-tested parsers as a Regex,
like the Foundation date parser,
is incredibly handy
in day-to-day string processing tasks.
Next, I will show you an advanced feature,
re-using a pre-existing parser
defined elsewhere in a Swift Regex.
Let's look at an example where we want
to parse the duration of a test case.
Duration is a floating point number,
such as, 0.001.
The best way to do this is, of course,
using the Foundation-provided
floating point parser
with full support for localization.
But today, I want to show you
what's under the hood
and how you can hook
into the Regex engine yourself
to leverage an existing parser
to parse the duration
floating-point number.
'strtod' is a function
from the C standard library.
It takes a string pointer,
parses the underlying string,
and assigns the end position
of the match to the end pointer.
Let's parse the duration, the C way.
To do this,
I can define a parser type on my own,
and make it conform to the
CustomConsumingRegexComponent protocol.
I define a structure named CDoubleParser.
Its 'RegexOutput' is Double,
because we are parsing a Double number.
In the "consuming" method,
we make a call to the double parser
from the C standard library,
passing the string pointers to it,
and getting a number back.
In the method body,
I use the withCString method
to obtain the start address.
Then I call the 'strtod' C function,
passing the start address
and a pointer
to receive the result end address.
I then check for errors.
When parsing succeeds,
the end address is greater
than the start address.
Otherwise, it is a parse failure,
so I return nil.
I compute the upper bound of the match
from the pointer produced by the C API.
And finally, I return the upper bound
of the match, and the number output.
I can come back to the Regex and use
my 'CDoubleParser' directly in the Regex.
The output type is inferred to be Double.
When I call 'wholeMatch'
and print the parsed number,
it outputs 0.001, like I expected.
In summary,
today we talked about some common
and advanced use of Swift Regex,
a new feature in Swift 5.7
that enables you
to integrate the power
of string processing in your apps.
A good practice when using Swift Regex
is to try to strike a good balance
between concision and readability,
especially when you mix the RegexBuilder
DSL and Regex literals.
When you encounter common patterns
such as date and URL,
always prefer the industry-strength
parsers provided by Foundation,
as parsing these patterns
with custom code can be prone to errors.
For more information about Swift Regex,
check out the series
of declarative string processing proposals
on Swift Evolution.
I hope you'll enjoy
processing strings with Swift.
Thank you, and have a great WWDC.