♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I’m Nikhil and today, I’ll share with you
the changes coming to SKAdNetwork.
Before diving into the future,
let’s remember where we are
and how we got here.
At Apple, we believe privacy is
a fundamental human right
and protecting it is woven
into everything we do here.
Which is why we created SKAdNetwork.
SKAdNetwork is Apple’s privacy-preserving
install attribution system.
Attribution data is sent back
to the advertiser
while preserving the user’s privacy.
SKAdNetwork involves three actors:
ad networks, publisher apps,
and advertiser apps.
Let's also define some terms
used commonly within SKAdNetwork.
Impression:
an impression in the context
of this discussion is input
from the publisher app to SKAdNetwork.
Engagement:
an engagement happens when the user
interacts with the advertiser app.
The advertiser app captures
these engagements
in the form of conversion value updates.
And finally, conversions,
which are also called postbacks.
The postback contains attribution data
which is sent to the ad network.
The attribution data provides a signal
to the ad network
that this was a successful conversion
of the original ad.
The ad network generates a signed
impression for the advertiser app.
The publisher app uses this impression
and displays this ad.
The user then taps the ad
and installs the app.
When launched for the first time,
the app calls an API
to signal the conversion.
The app can then repeatedly call this API
to update the conversion value
and capture various levels of engagement
and return on ad spent.
Once the timer expires,
we send the postback
containing the attribution data
to the ad network.
Taking a quick look at the version history
for SKAdNetwork.
SKAdNetwork 2.0 introduced
privacy-preserving ad attribution.
2.2 enabled publisher apps
to show custom ads.
3.0 added postbacks
for non-winning impressions.
And in iOS 15.0, we introduced
postback copies for developers
for all versions of SKAdNetwork.
For more on the history of SKAdNetwork,
refer to the session
"Meet privacy-preserving ad attribution"
from WWDC 2021.
Now let’s talk about the future,
SKAdNetwork 4.0.
Let’s have a look at the new features.
We are going to start by looking at
a few changes to the API
designed to provide more data
to advertisers.
Following this, we will look at
the conversion side of things.
We will then move on to attribution
for ads on the web,
and wrap up by talking about
SKAdNetwork testability.
Hierarchical IDs and conversion values
are the first new feature
coming to SKAdNetwork 4.0.
Before diving into the new feature,
I would like to define crowd anonymity.
Crowd anonymity is the term we use
to refer to the privacy-preserving way
in which SKAdNetwork delivers
attribution data.
Counts of installs determine
the level of privacy
assured to the person using your app.
At the lower end,
we send less attribution data
to the advertiser in the postback.
When the install count is low,
we take extra steps to protect privacy
by limiting the trackable information
sent back.
As the count scales up
and the user’s uniqueness starts
to blend into the crowd,
we send more data back.
Finally, as the count reaches
the highest tier,
we are able to send the most data back
while still preserving privacy.
In SKAdNetwork 4.0,
we have a way to send more data
while retaining our privacy protections.
For this, we are changing
the campaign identifier field.
At present, this is a 2 digit field.
We will increase the range
of this field to 4 digits
and rename it to source identifier.
The new name reflects our way
of thinking about this field
as being capable of representing
anything you choose to use it for
and not solely for identifying campaigns.
Though this is a single number,
we encourage thinking about it
as three hierarchical numbers,
a 2, 3, and 4 digit number.
Thinking about the source identifier field
as a hierarchical set of numbers
is helpful
in ascribing meaning to
the different numbers.
As an example, the 2 digits
could represent the ad campaign,
the 3rd could represent
the bucketed location of the user,
and the 4th could stand for
ad placement on screen.
Alternatively, the 2 digits
could stand for treatments,
the 3rd digit could represent
bucketed time of day,
and the 4th digit could stands
for the size of the ad shown.
These are simply examples,
and ultimately, what we wanted here
was to open this field up to you
to use as best fits your need.
Continuing the theme
of providing more data,
the conversion value is also changing.
Currently this is a 6 bit value.
With SKAdNetwork 4.0,
we are introducing two conversion values:
a fine-grained value
and a coarse-grained value.
The fine-grained value is the same
as the conversion value today.
The coarse-grained value can assume
one of three values.
Considering a conversion value of high 42,
where high is the coarse value
and 42 is the fine value,
the install count required
to receive the coarse value
is lower than that needed
for the fine value.
Consequently, apps will receive the former
much faster than the latter.
Note however, that only one of these
will be sent back to the advertiser.
Let us take a look at how crowd anonymity
affects these new fields.
Using our earlier example of 5739
as the source identifier,
at the low end of crowd anonymity,
you can expect to receive the 2 digit
component of the source identifier,
which in this case is 39.
At the medium level, you can expect
to receive the 3 digit component.
And at the highest level,
you can expect to receive
the full 4 digit source identifier back.
As the crowd anonymity level increases,
more digits of the source identifier
are sent back.
And taking our earlier example of high 42
for the conversion value,
at the low end of crowd anonymity,
you will not receive a conversion value
in your postback.
At the medium level, you will receive
the coarse conversion value.
And at the highest level,
you will receive the fine-grained
conversion value in your postback.
As the crowd anonymity increases,
the conversion value returned changes.
Let’s take a look at the API changes.
If you are using instances
of SKAdImpression to show your ads,
you can set the new sourceIdentifier
property on the SKAdImpression instance.
If you are setting your impression
via a dictionary,
you can set the sourceIdentifier value
using the new source identifier key.
For advertised apps, you will call the new
updatePostbackConversionValue method
which has been changed to now take
a coarse-grained conversion value
in addition to the fine-grained
conversion value as shown here.
We recommend that you use the completion
handler to do any follow up tasks
after updating your postback’s
conversion values.
Here are some recommendations on adopting
the new hierarchical IDs
and conversion values API.
Different portions of
the source identifier will be returned
depending on
the privacy level of the install.
Consider this when composing
source identifiers for your impressions.
Coarse conversion values are at
a much lower granularity
than fine conversion values.
Consider this when ascribing meaning
to their values.
Conversion values can increase
or decrease.
And finally,
when making changes to your server
to process SKAdNetwork 4.0 postbacks,
make them capable of parsing
the new source identifiers
and coarse conversion values.
That wraps up our introduction to
hierarchical IDs and conversion values,
providing more data to advertisers
while retaining our privacy protections.
Let’s focus on another critical area
of the attribution flow, conversions.
SKAdNetwork today uses
a single conversion model.
From the time of install,
we update the conversion value
to capture various user engagements.
And after a certain amount of time
elapses,
we send the postback to the ad network.
Let’s have a look at an example.
Let’s use Food Truck.
Food Truck puts you in control
of your food truck.
Customize, control, and create
your own unique donut delivery experience.
As Food Truck’s developer,
I want to know the value
of my advertising spend.
As an example of this,
when the user starts Food Truck,
I will update the conversion value
to mark this.
Once they pick up their first batch
for delivery,
I update the conversion value again.
Due to this batch of donuts requiring
a certain amount of time to age,
the user waits.
Somewhere in the aging time,
the conversion is sent
in the form a postback to both
the ad network and optionally to me.
However, when the user finally delivers
the donut,
I will have no way of measuring this
or any further user actions
since the postback has already been sent.
In other words, re-engagement is lost.
This is what we are changing.
We are moving from a single postback
to three postbacks.
The postbacks are tied to
definite time windows
and are sent at the end of those windows.
Let’s revisit the earlier example.
As before, the user starts Food Truck
and proceeds to pick the first batch up
for delivery.
The first postback’s time window elapses
and we send it out.
The user delivers the donuts.
Whereas earlier,
this would not have been captured,
now we find ourselves in
the second postback’s time window.
We update the conversion value
to capture this.
The second postback’s time window
passes and we send it out.
Using the tools in the app,
the user creates a brand new donut recipe
and then heads out again
to deliver a fresh batch.
The third window elapses
and the third postback is sent out.
There are more opportunities to measure
the value of the conversion
and to receive these measurements
more often.
A few points to note about
multiple conversions:
Only the first postback will get
the fine conversion value.
The additional postbacks can carry
the coarse conversion value.
Only the winner and developer
will receive the additional postbacks.
Next, let’s review SKAdNetwork
attributions for ads on the web.
We know that publisher apps show ads
which open product pages in the App Store.
The App Store, in turn, works with
SKAdNetwork to attribute installs
while providing the privacy protections
that our users rely on.
We want to extend the same privacy
to ads shown on web pages.
Let’s take a look at how this will work.
The user taps on a link for an ad
in Safari.
Safari launches the App Store and lands on
the product page for the advertised app.
Two things happen here.
The App Store fetches the ad impression
from the ad network server,
and the user installs the app.
Following this, everything flows
as it does today,
and eventually,
SKAdNetwork sends the postback out.
Let’s have a look at
how the link is composed.
The href portion contains the App Store
link for the app being advertised.
The attributionDestination tells Apple
where to fetch
the signed ad impression from.
And the attributionSourceNonce
helps the ad network find
the exact ad impression to send back.
Note that this link can be served
on first party sites
and in embedded cross site iframes.
Let’s take a closer look at
the URL construction.
We extract the eTLD+1 component
from the attribution destination.
To this, we then add
the well-known qualifier
and two more path components.
This gives us the URL to which
we will make the HTTP POST request
to get the signed impression.
Note that the protocol and
highlighted path components are fixed.
You, the ad network, decide the value
of the host component.
SKAdNetwork will make an HTTP POST request
to the URL constructed as just discussed.
The POST body will be JSON.
You will recognize the source_nonce as
being the same as in the original ad link.
This value is what the ad network
will use to identify
the signed impression it wants to serve.
Let’s look at what we expect to receive
from this POST request.
This is a signed impression,
ready for consumption by SKAdNetwork.
Note the source domain field
in the impression.
This is the link analog
of the source app ID
in the app driven SKAdNetwork flow.
Looking at how to get started using this
new entry into the SKAdNetwork system,
ad networks have to do the following:
Create the uniquely identifiable parts
of the link and the link itself.
Expose an endpoint capable of serving
signed impressions
at the location constructed
as we discussed before.
Update your postback servers
to parse and understand
the new optional source domain field.
For webpages that want to use the links
to SKAdNetwork,
simply embed the ad links provided to you
by your ad network.
That was an introduction to SKAdNetwork
attribution for ads on the web.
We are incredibly excited to see
this feature being adopted
across the wider advertising ecosystem.
Next, we will go over how you can test
your SKAdNetwork implementations.
At a high level, SKAdNetwork deals
with impressions and postbacks.
From working with our developer community
we know that on the side of impressions,
signing and configuring
have been points of friction.
And with postbacks, receiving and
validating them in a test-friendly manner
has been an area for improvement.
To help improve the developer experience
with SKAdNetwork,
we released SKAdNetwork
testability changes in Xcode 13.3.
This is available as a unit testing
framework within StoreKitTest
that a lot of you have already been using
for testing various parts
of your StoreKit implementations.
Let’s take a look at
validating an impression.
You create and configure an instance
of SKAdImpression.
You supply the public key counterpart
of the private key
used to generate the signature,
and then you call the validate method
on the SKAdTestSession instance.
This will validate your impression and
throw an error
if either the impression is misconfigured
or the signature is invalid.
The other main area to test is
the receipt of postbacks.
There are 2 steps here.
Step 1: adding the test postback
to your test session.
You will create an instance
of SKAdTestPostback
and configure it with the values you want
in your postback.
Pay special note to the postback URL,
since this is where your postback
will be sent to.
This can point to
a remote or a local server.
You will then add this to
your test session
using the setPostbacks method
on SKAdTestSession.
Step 2 is to actually send
the postback out.
All you need to do here is to call
the flushPostbacks method
on SKAdTestSession
and your postback will be off on it’s way.
Note that SKAdTestSession will send
your postback over the network
to the server you specified
when composing your postback.
These are a few things coming to
SKAdNetwork testability later this year:
Support for the new
source identifier field.
Support for fine
and coarse conversion values.
Support for testing multiple conversions.
And that was a quick look at
the SKAdNetwork testability changes
that were first available in Xcode 13.3.
Today, we talked about hierarchical IDs
and conversion values,
aiming to get more data to you sooner.
And then we talked about
multiple conversions,
allowing you to measure re-engagement
over a longer period.
Then we talked about
link-driven attribution
and how we are adding
a bridge to SKAdNetwork,
bringing with it
the same privacy protections.
And we finished by talking about
SKAdNetwork testability in Xcode.
And that wraps up our journey
through SKAdNetwork 4.0.
In closing, everything we build is driven
by feedback
from our amazing community of developers.
It has been incredibly fulfilling
and humbling to hear about
your experiences building a privacy first
ad experience for our users.
Thank you.
♪ ♪