[upbeat music]
- Hi, and welcome to What's New
in TextKit and text views!
I'm Donna Tom, and I'm a TextKit engineer.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
we introduced TextKit 2,
a powerful new text engine
with improved performance,
correctness, and safety.
TextKit 2's viewport-based layout
architecture
delivers high performance text layout,
especially for documents
with large contents.
TextKit 2 provides a better text
experience for international audiences
by removing the unnecessary complexity
of working with glyphs,
and it has full support
for modern font technologies
like OpenType and Variable Fonts.
And TextKit 2's focus on working with
higher level objects
to control text layout
makes it easier for you
to customize the layout of your text
so you can
build cooler stuff with less code.
Moving forward, the TextKit 2 engine
forms the foundation of text layout
and rendering on all of Apple's platforms.
Future performance enhancements,
updates, and improvements
will all be focused
on the TextKit 2 engine.
By updating to TextKit 2,
your app can get the benefits
of these improvements
as we roll them out.
For an in-depth introduction
to TextKit2,
watch the Meet TextKit2 video.
That video covers the fundamentals
and how to build your own text
layout components using TextKit 2.
In contrast, this video covers
the latest advancements in TextKit 2
and how to get the most out
of TextKit 2-backed text views.
That's right, I said text views,
plural, because now,
as of iOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
all text controls in UIKit
and AppKit are using TextKit 2,
including UITextView.
So we're using TextKit 2 for layout
and rendering all throughout the system.
It's important that all apps transition
to TextKit 2 as soon as possible,
and we've added a number of tools
to make the transition easier for you.
For many apps,
this can be a zero code transition.
And we expect this to be true
for apps that don't make any special
modifications to their text views.
I'll tell you a bit more about that later.
But first, I'll start by going
over what's new in TextKit 2,
including some
of those tools I just mentioned.
After that,
I'll dive deep into the details
of the TextKit 1
compatibility mode for text views.
Then I'll finish with a discussion
of modernization strategies you can use
when preparing to transition
your code to TextKit 2.
So first up is what's new in TextKit 2.
TextKit 2 first came to UIKit in iOS 15
where UITextField was upgraded to use it.
In iOS 16, the UIKit transition
to TextKit 2 is complete,
with all text controls using TextKit 2
by default, including UITextView.
Most text views will be
automatically opted in to TextKit 2,
requiring zero adoption on your part.
There are just a few situations
where text views might not get opted in,
and I'll cover that in the
compatibility segment of this video.
And it's a similar story for AppKit.
TextKit 2 first came to AppKit
in macOS Big Sur.
In macOS Monterey, NSTextField
was upgraded to use it by default,
and it was available for
NSTextView by opting in.
In macOS Ventura, all text controls
use TextKit 2 by default.
Just like UITextView, most NSTextViews
get automatic opt in to TextKit 2
and require zero adoption on your part.
TextEdit, which is a thin wrapper
around NSTextView,
uses TextKit 2 everywhere
in macOS Ventura.
TextEdit has been using TextKit 2
in plain text mode since macOS Big Sur.
In macOS Ventura,
rich text mode uses TextKit 2 as well.
Since TextKit 2 is the new standard,
we've added some convenience constructors
for both UITextView and NSTextView.
Use these new constructors
to choose at initialization time
which text engine to use.
To create a text view that uses TextKit 2,
use the new constructor and pass true
for the "UsingTextLayoutManager"
parameter.
If the text view needs to use TextKit 1
for compatibility, pass "false" instead.
And there's a new Text Layout option for
text views created in Interface Builder.
This new option gives you control
of which layout system to use
on a per-instance basis.
The default setting is the system default,
which is TextKit 2.
You can also choose to explicitly
use TextKit 2 or TextKit 1.
TextKit 2 now supports
non-simple text containers.
Non-simple text containers
may have holes or gaps in them.
This allows text to wrap around
images or other inline content.
To create a non-simple text container,
use the exclusionPaths property
on NSTextContainer
to define the areas
where text should not be laid out.
For an example of how to do this, check
out the TextKitAndTextView sample code
from the resources
associated with this video.
You can find the related example
on the "exclusion path" tab.
We've enhanced the line breaking engine
in TextKit 2
to choose more even line breaks
for justified paragraphs.
This is a subtle change that's easier
to notice on longer paragraphs of text.
Here we have two versions of the
same text, laid out in the same area.
Notice the stretched out lines
and large interword spacing
with traditional line breaking.
There's much less of that going on
with the new even line breaking.
This makes the text easier to read,
and you get it for free with TextKit 2.
There's no adoption required.
And finally, we've added text list support
in TextKit 2 for all platforms.
With text lists,
you can programmatically create
numbered or bulleted lists
for display in a text view.
TextKit 2 uses NSTextList to represent
text lists, just like TextKit 1.
NSTextList
used to be available in AppKit only,
but in iOS 16,
it's available in UIKit too.
Use NSTextList together with
NSmutableParagraphStyle to specify
that a paragraph in your text storage
should be formatted as a list for display.
The text view is responsible
for picking up these attributes
from the text storage and reformatting
the paragraph content to look like a list.
While NSTextList itself isn't new,
there are a few new TextKit 2 additions.
Since lists can have nested items,
it's natural to represent them
as a tree structure.
In TextKit 2, we've enhanced NSTextElement
to support structuring them as trees
with properties for accessing
child and parent elements.
And we've added a new element subclass
called NSTextListElement.
When the content manager comes across
a NSTextList in the text content,
it will generate NSTextListElements
to represent the items in the list.
To get a more in-depth view of
how to create text lists and add items,
refer to the
TextKitAndTextView sample code.
You can find the related example
on the "list" tab.
And while
you're exploring the sample code,
don't miss the text attachment example
which shows how to use the text attachment
view provider APIs in TextKit 2.
These APIs let you use a UI
or NSView as the text attachment,
and events can be handled directly
by the attachment view.
This makes event handling with
text attachments a whole lot easier,
and it's only possible with TextKit 2.
All right,
that's it for what's new in TextKit 2.
Next, I'll get into the details of
the TextKit 1 compatibility mode.
Since TextKit 2 is such a radical
departure from the design of TextKit 1,
we understand that full adoption of
TextKit 2 may take some time
for apps that are heavily invested
in the TextKit 1 architecture.
We want these apps to continue to work
well until the transition can be made,
and that's why we've added
a special TextKit 1 compatibility mode
for UITextView and NSTextView.
When you explicitly
call an NSLayoutManager API,
the text view replaces its
NSTextLayoutManager
with an NSLayoutManager
and reconfigures itself to use TextKit 1.
This can also happen
if the text view encounters attributes
not yet supported by TextKit 2,
such as tables, or when printing.
If you encounter an unexpected runtime
fallback to TextKit 1 in UITextView,
check the log for a message
warning about the switch.
Set a breakpoint on the symbol underscore
UITextViewEnablingCompatibilityMode
to capture a stack trace
and other useful debugging information.
For NSTextView,
you can get more information
about unexpected runtime fallbacks
by subscribing to the willSwitch
or didSwitchToNSLayoutManager
notifications.
If you must drop back to TextKit 1,
it's best to opt out
at initialization time
with programmatically
initialized text views.
Do this by using your own text container
and a TextKit 1 layout manager.
Another option is to use the
new convenience constructor
to initialize a TextKit 1 text view
and pass false as the parameter.
This will
make your text view use TextKit 1.
And a third option
is to use Interface Builder
and set the new Text Layout option
to TextKit 1 on your text view.
Here's something to watch out for.
If you're swapping out your
text container's layout manager
during or after initialization,
then your text view
will fall back to TextKit 1 as designed.
It's inefficient to create all the TextKit
2 objects during initialization
only to throw them away moments later.
There's also potential user side effects,
depending on the timing.
If it happens during typing,
the text view could lose its focus
and interrupt input, requiring the text
view to be selected again to resume.
Avoid this by opting the text view out
at initialization time.
Now that you know
all about compatibility mode,
it's time to talk about how to avoid it
altogether by modernizing your app
and adopting TextKit 2.
And there's one really important
thing I want you to remember.
There can be only one
layout manager per text view.
A text view can't have both
an NSTextLayoutManager
and an NSLayoutManager at the same time.
Once a text view switches to TextKit 1,
there's no automatic way of going back.
The process of switching
layout systems is expensive,
and you will lose any UI state that
was present at the time of the switch.
So for optimum performance and usability,
the system will never switch a text view
back to TextKit 2 from TextKit 1.
It's a one-way operation.
This means it's really important
to avoid compatibility mode.
And there's a few different reasons
a text view will enter compatibility mode.
The number one reason for a
text view to enter compatibility mode
is accessing the text view's
layoutManager property.
The other reasons are much less common.
So an important strategy
is to avoid accessing
the text view's layout manager property.
Also avoid accessing the layout manager
through the text view's text container.
Audit your code
for uses of these properties,
and remove them or replace them
with TextKit 2 equivalents.
If you're deploying your app to older
OS versions that don't have TextKit 2,
you might not be able to entirely
remove your layoutManager code.
In that case, you should first check
for the text view's NSTextLayoutManager.
Put your TextKit 2 code in the if clause
and put the TextKit 1 code
in the else clause,
including the layoutManager access.
This way, the TextKit 1 code only runs
when TextKit 2 is not available,
and your layoutManager query won't cause
an unintended fallback to TextKit 1.
If you've followed all this
advice and you still encounter
an unexpected fallback to TextKit 1
coming from the system,
that's our problem, so please report
the issue with Feedback Assistant.
Include a capture of the stack trace
at the time of fallback,
which you can get from breaking on
underscore
UITextViewEnablingCompatibilityMode
in UIKit, or
willSwitchToNSLayoutManagerNotification
in AppKit.
Okay, now I'll get into the specifics
of updating code
related to TextKit 1 types,
starting with NSLayoutManager.
Once you've audited your code
for NSLayoutManager queries,
you'll need to figure out the TextKit 2
equivalents with NSTextLayoutManager.
Some layout manager APIs have
similar names between TextKit 1 and 2,
and the substitutions are straightforward.
Here's a few examples.
In TextKit 1, you call usedRect(for:
textContainer) on NSLayoutManager
to get the bounding rectangle for
the text inside a text container.
In TextKit 2, you get this from the
usageBoundsForTextContainer property
on NSTextLayoutManager.
In TextKit 1,
we used the name "temporary attributes"
for attributes that affected
only the rendering, and not the layout.
In TextKit 2, we more accurately
call those "rendering attributes."
But there are some TextKit 1 APIs that
have no direct equivalents in TextKit 2.
To understand why,
you need to understand
there is no correct
character to glyph mapping
for many words in Indic scripts
like Kannada.
In these scripts, glyphs can be split up,
reordered, recombined, or even deleted.
The glyph-based APIs
on NSLayoutManager
assume you can directly associate
a contiguous range of characters
with a contiguous range of glyphs,
and that's just not true for all scripts.
Using these APIs can result
in broken layout and rendering
for text written in scripts like Kannada.
That's why there are
zero glyph APIs in TextKit 2.
You can't just substitute a single
TextKit 2 API for a TextKit 1 glyph API.
Replacing these APIs
requires a different approach.
So here's how to update glyph-based code.
The first step is to identify
which glyph APIs you're using.
Next, look at how you're using those APIs
and define what you are trying to do
at a high level.
Glyph-based code is very low level,
and there are many details
that aren't relevant
to your high-level task.
Once you've defined the high-level task,
then examine the structures
available to you in TextKit 2
such as layout fragments,
line fragments, and text selections.
These can help you accomplish your task.
For example, consider this TextKit 1 code.
There's two glyph APIs used here:
numberOfGlyphs,
and lineFragmentRect(forGlyphAt: index) .
This TextKit 1 code is iterating
over all of the glyphs in the document
and counting the line fragment rects.
The high-level task is counting the number
of lines of wrapped text
in the text view.
Since this code is working with
line fragment rects,
the TextKit 2 structures to use
are NSTextLineFragment
and NSTextLayoutFragment.
And here's the code
rewritten to use TextKit 2.
Instead of iterating over glyphs,
it's enumerating the text layout
fragments in the document
and supplying a closure that counts
all of the text line fragments
within each layout fragment.
Keep that example in mind when
updating your own code for TextKit 2.
Now I'm going to shift gears and discuss
updating code that's based on NSRange.
TextKit 1 uses NSRange
to index into text content,
and NSRange
is a linear index into a string.
For the text "Hello TextKit 2!"
exclamation point,
the NSRange that represents
the "TextKit 2 exclamation point"
is location 6 and length 10,
since it begins at the 6th character
and it's 10 characters long.
This linear model is easy to understand,
and it works great
for indexing into strings.
But the linear model doesn't
work for indexing into any content
that has more structure than a string.
Here's an example.
HTML documents
are represented as a tree structure,
where each tag is a node in the tree.
If our Hello TextKit 2! text
is part of an HTML document,
there's no way for our NSRange to tell us
that the text is inside the span tag,
nested 3 levels deep.
The linear model isn't expressive
enough to store that information,
so we can't use it to index
into a nested structure like this one.
This is why TextKit 2 added new types for
representing ranges in the text content.
NSTextLocation is an object
that represents a single location
inside the text content.
NSTextRange
consists of a start and end location.
The end location
is excluded from the range.
These new types can represent the
nested structure of this HTML document
by defining a location as the
DOM node plus a character offset.
Since NSTextLocation is a protocol,
any custom object can be a location
as long as it implements
the NSTextLocation protocol methods.
This is crucial infrastructure for working
with different types of backing stores
that support structured data
in their models.
But text views are built on
NSAttributedString backing stores
that don't have this structure,
and we can't change that
without breaking lots of apps,
including yours.
So you'll continue to use NSRange
when using text view APIs
like selectedRange
or scrollRangeToVisible.
And you'll need to convert between
NSRange and NSTextRange
when communicating with the TextKit 2
layout manager or content manager.
To convert a text view's NSRange
to an NSTextRange,
define the location as the integer index
into the attributed string.
Use the NSRange location as
the start location for NSTextRange.
Use the NSRange location plus the length
as the end location of the NSTextRange.
Conceptually, that's how to map
from NSRange to NSTextRange.
In practice,
the code looks a little different
because NSTextLocations must be objects.
You need to go through the content
manager to compute the locations.
For the start location,
ask the content manager
for the location
of the beginning of the document,
then offset it by the NSRange's location.
Then offset the start location by the
NSRange's length to get the end location.
To go in the other direction,
use the text content manager
to get two different offsets.
The NSRange's location is the offset
between the beginning of the document
and the NSTextRange's location.
And the NSRange's length is the offset
between the start and end locations
of the NSTextRange.
UITextViews and UITextFields
conform to the UITextInput protocol,
which uses UITextPosition and range.
Most of the time,
you won't need to convert
a UITextRange
directly to an NSTextRange
when using UITextView or UITextField.
But if you do, use the integer offsets
as the intermediary
between the two range types.
On the other hand, if you're using
a custom view with UITextInput,
you have direct control
over the UITextPosition
and UITextRange subclasses
used with your view.
You can make your
UITextPosition subclass
conform to NSTextLocation,
implement the required method,
and use your subclass
to create NSTextRanges directly.
Finally, here's a reminder to avoid
reusing UITextPosition objects
across different views, even if the
content in both views is similar.
A UITextPosition is only valid
for the view used to create it.
All right, now you've got lots of
strategies at your disposal
for modernizing your code.
Apply these strategies,
and your app will be ready
to reap the benefits of TextKit 2.
And that's what's new
in TextKit and text views.
I covered a lot of great improvements
in TextKit 2
and shared some strategies
for updating your apps
while maintaining compatibility
for older OS versions.
Use TextKit 2 in your apps today to take
full advantage of the new improvements.
Check your text views to make sure
they aren't unintentionally
falling back to TextKit 1.
And finally,
employ the modernization strategies
to get your app on TextKit 2.
We can't wait to read what you'll create
with TextKit 2 and text views.
Thanks for watching!