♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hello, and welcome to
“Discover advancements
in iOS camera capture”.
I'm Nikolas Gelo
from the Camera Software team,
and I'll be presenting some exciting
new camera features in iOS and iPadOS.
I'll begin with how to stream depth
from LiDAR Scanners using AVFoundation.
Next, a look at how your app
will receive improved face rendering
with face-driven auto focus
and auto exposure.
Then, I'll take you through advanced
AVCaptureSession streaming configurations.
And lastly,
I'll show you how your app will
be able to use the camera
while multitasking.
I'll begin with how to stream depth
from LiDAR Scanners using AVFoundation.
The iPhone 12 Pro,
iPhone 13 Pro, and iPad Pro are equipped
with LiDAR Scanners capable
of outputting dense depth maps.
The LiDAR Scanner works
by shooting light onto the surroundings,
and then collecting the light
reflected off the surfaces in the scene.
The depth is estimated by measuring
the time it took for the light to go
from the LiDAR to the environment
and reflect back to the scanner.
This entire process runs millions
of times every second.
I'll show you the LiDAR Scanner
in action using AVFoundation.
Here on an iPhone 13 Pro Max,
I'm running an app that uses
the new LiDAR Depth Camera
AVCaptureDevice.
The app renders streaming depth data
on top of the live camera feed.
Blue is shown for objects that are close
and red for objects that are further away.
And using the slider,
I can adjust the opacity of the depth.
This app also takes photos
with high resolution depth maps.
When I take a photo,
the same depth overlay is applied
but with an even greater resolution
for the still.
This app has one more trick up its sleeve.
When I press the torch button,
the app uses the high resolution depth map
with the color image to render a spotlight
on the scene using RealityKit.
I can tap around and point the spotlight
at different objects in the scene.
Look how the spotlight
highlights the guitar.
Or if I tap on the right spot
in the corner of the wall,
the spotlight forms the shape of a heart.
Let's go back to that guitar.
It looks so cool.
API for the LiDAR Scanner was
first introduced in ARKit in iPadOS 13.4.
If you haven't seen the WWDC
2020 presentation “Explore ARKit 4”,
I encourage you to watch it.
New in iOS 15.4, your app can access
the LiDAR Scanner with AVFoundation.
We have introduced
a new AVCapture Device Type,
the built-in LiDAR Depth Camera,
which delivers video and depth.
It produces high-quality,
high-accuracy depth information.
This new AVCaptureDevice uses
the rear-facing wide-angle camera
to deliver video
with the LiDAR Scanner to capture depth.
Both the video and depth are captured
in the wide-angle camera's field of view.
And like the TrueDepth AVCaptureDevice,
all of its formats
support depth data delivery.
This new AVCaptureDevice produces
high quality depth data
by fusing sparse output
from the LiDAR Scanner
with the color image
from the rear-facing wide-angle camera.
The LiDAR and color inputs are processed
using a machine learning model
that outputs a dense depth map.
Because the LiDAR Depth Camera
uses the rear-facing wide-angle camera,
the Telephoto and Ultra Wide cameras
can be used in addition
with an AVCaptureMultiCamSession.
This is useful for apps that wish
to use multiple cameras at the same time.
The LiDAR Depth Camera
exposes many formats,
from video resolutions of 640 by 480
to a full 12-megapixel image
at 4032 by 3024.
While streaming,
it can output depth maps up to 320 by 240.
And for photo capture,
you can receive depth maps of 768 by 576.
Note, the depth resolutions are slightly
different for 16 by 9 and 4 by 3 formats.
This is to match the video's aspect ratio.
The LiDAR Depth Camera AVCaptureDevice
is available
on iPhone 12 Pro, iPhone 13 Pro,
and iPad Pro 5th generation.
iPhone 13 Pro can deliver depth data using
a combination of the rear facing cameras.
The AVFoundation Capture API
refers to these as “virtual devices”
that consist of physical devices.
On the back of the iPhone 13 Pro,
there are four virtual AVCaptureDevices
available to use:
The new LiDAR Depth Camera
uses the LiDAR Scanner
with the wide-angle camera.
The Dual Camera uses the Wide
and Telephoto cameras.
The Dual Wide Camera,
which uses the Wide
and Ultra Wide cameras.
And the Triple Camera,
that uses the Wide,
Ultra Wide, and Telephoto cameras.
There are differences in the type
of depth these devices produce.
The LiDAR Depth Camera
produces “absolute depth.”
The time of flight technique used allows
for real-world scale to be calculated.
For example, this is great for computer
vision tasks like measuring.
The TrueDepth, Dual, Dual Wide,
and Triple Cameras produce relative,
disparity-based depth.
This uses less power and is great
for apps that render photo effects.
AVFoundation represents depth
using the AVDepthData class.
This class has a pixel buffer
containing the depth
with other properties describing it,
including the depth data type,
the accuracy, and whether it is filtered.
It is delivered
by a depth-capable AVCaptureDevice,
like the new LiDAR Depth Camera.
You can stream depth
from an AVCaptureDepthDataOutput
or receive depth attached to photos
from an AVCapturePhotoOutput.
Depth data is filtered by default.
Filtering reduces noise
and fills in missing values,
or holes, in the depth map.
This is great for video
and photography apps,
so artifacts don't appear
when using the depth map
to apply effects on a color image.
However, computer vision apps
should prefer non-filtered depth data
to preserve the original values
in the depth map.
When filtering is disabled,
the LiDAR Depth Camera
excludes low confidence points.
To disable depth data filtering,
set the isFilteringEnabled property
on your AVCaptureDepthDataOutput to false,
and when you receive an AVDepthData
object from your delegate callback,
it will not be filtered.
Since ARKit already provided access
to the LiDAR Scanner,
you might ask,
“How does AVFoundation compare?”
AVFoundation is designed
for video and photography apps.
With AVFoundation,
you can embed depth data
captured with the LiDAR Scanner
into high-resolution photos.
ARKit is best suited
for augmented reality apps,
as the name suggests.
With the LiDAR Scanner,
ARKit is capable of delivering features
like scene geometry and object placement.
AVFoundation can
deliver high-resolution video
that is great for recording movies
and taking photos.
AVFoundation's LiDAR Depth Camera
can output depth up to 768 by 576.
This is more than twice as big
as ARKit's depth resolution of 256 by 192.
ARKit uses lower resolution depth maps,
so it can apply augmented
reality algorithms for its features.
For more “in-depth” information on how
to use AVFoundation to capture depth data,
watch our previous session
“Capturing Depth in iPhone Photography”
from WWDC 2017.
We're excited to see the interesting ways
you can use the LiDAR Depth Camera
in your apps.
Next up, I'll discuss how improvements to
the auto focus and auto exposure systems
help to improve the visibility
of faces in the scene for your app.
The auto focus and auto exposure
systems analyze the scene
to capture the best image.
The auto focus system adjusts the lens
to keep the subject in focus,
and the auto exposure system
balances the brightest
and darkest regions of a scene
to keep the subject visible.
However, sometimes
the automatic adjustments made
do not keep your subject's face in focus.
And other times,
the subject's face can be difficult
to see with bright backlit scenes.
A common feature of DSLRs and other
pro cameras is to track faces in the scene
to dynamically adjust the focus
and exposure to keep them visible.
New in iOS 15.4, the focus and exposure
systems will prioritize faces.
We liked the benefits of this so much
that we have enabled it by default
for all apps linked on iOS 15.4 or later.
I'll show you some examples.
Without face-driven auto focus,
the camera stays focused
on the background
without refocusing on the face.
Watch it again.
Look at how his face remains
out of focus as he turns around
and that the trees
in the background stay sharp.
With face-driven auto focus enabled,
you can clearly see his face.
And when he turns away, the camera
changes its focus to the background.
When we compare the videos side by side,
the difference is clear.
On the right
with face-driven auto focus enabled,
you can see
the finer details in his beard.
With bright backlit scenes, it can
be challenging to keep faces well exposed.
But with the auto exposure system
prioritizing faces,
we can easily see him.
Comparing side by side,
we can see the difference here again.
Notice that by keeping his face
well-exposed in the picture on the right,
the trees
in the background appear brighter.
And the sky does too.
The exposure of the whole scene
is adjusted when prioritizing faces.
In iOS 15.4, there are new properties
on AVCaptureDevice to control
when face-driven auto focus
and auto exposure are enabled.
You can control whether the device will
“automatically adjust” these settings
and decide when it should be enabled.
Before toggling
the “isEnabled” properties,
you must first
disable the automatic adjustment.
The automatic enablement of this behavior
is great for photography apps.
It's used by Apple's Camera app.
It's also great
for video conferencing apps
to keep faces visible during calls.
FaceTime takes advantage of this,
but sometimes
it's not best suited for an app
to have the auto focus and auto exposure
systems be driven by faces.
For example,
if you want your app to give the user
manual control over the captured image,
you might consider turning this off.
If you decide face-driven auto focus
or auto exposure is not right
for your app,
you can opt out of this behavior.
First, lock the AVCaptureDevice
for configuration.
Then, turn off the automatic adjustment
of face-driven auto focus
or auto exposure.
Next, disable face-driven
auto focus or auto exposure.
And lastly,
unlock the device for configuration.
I'll talk about how you can
use advanced streaming configurations
to receive audio and video data
that is tailored for your app's needs.
The AVFoundation Capture API allows
developers to build
immersive apps using the camera.
The AVCaptureSession manages data flow
from inputs like cameras and microphones
that are connected to AVCaptureOutputs,
that can deliver video,
audio, photos, and more.
Let's take a common camera app
use case for example:
Applying custom effects like filters
or overlays to recorded video.
An app like this would have:
An AVCaptureSession with two inputs,
a camera and a mic,
that are connected to two outputs,
one for video data and one for audio data.
The video data
then has the effects applied,
and the processed video
is sent two places,
to the video preview
and an AVAssetWriter for recording.
The audio data is also sent
to the AVAssetWriter.
New in iOS 16 and iPadOS 16, apps can use
multiple AVCaptureVideoDataOutputs
at the same time.
For each video data output,
you can customize the resolution,
stabilization, orientation,
and pixel format.
Let's go back
to the example camera app.
There are competing capture
requirements this app is balancing.
The app wants to show a live video preview
of the content being captured
and record high quality video
for later playback.
For preview, the resolution needs to be
just big enough for the device's screen.
And the processing needs to be
fast enough for low-latency preview.
But when recording,
its best to capture in high resolution
with quality effects applied.
With the ability to add a second
AVCaptureVideoDataOutput,
the capture graph can be extended.
Now the video data outputs
can be optimized.
One output can deliver smaller buffers
for preview,
and the other can provide
full-sized 4K buffers for recording.
Also, the app could render a simpler,
more performant version of the effect
on smaller preview buffers
and reserve high quality effects
for full-size buffers when recording.
Now the app no longer has
to compromise its preview
or recorded videos.
Another reason to use separate
video data outputs for preview
and recording is
to apply different stabilization modes.
Video stabilization
introduces additional latency
to the video capture pipeline.
For preview, latency is not desirable,
as the noticeable delay
makes it hard to capture content.
For recording,
stabilization can be applied
for a better experience
when watching the video later.
So you can have no stabilization applied
on one video data output
for low-latency preview
and apply stabilization
to the other for later playback.
There are many ways to configure
the resolution of your video data output.
For full-size output, first,
disable automatic configuration
of output buffer dimensions.
Then disable delivery
of preview-sized output buffers.
In most cases, however,
the video data output
is already configured
for full-size output.
For preview-sized output, again,
disable the automatic configuration,
but instead, enable delivery
of preview-sized output buffers.
This is enabled by default when
using the photo AVCaptureSessionPreset.
To request a custom resolution,
specify the width and height
in the output's video settings dictionary.
The aspect ratio of the width
and height must match the aspect ratio
of the source device's activeFormat.
There are more ways
to configure your video data output.
To apply stabilization,
set the preferred stabilization to a mode
like cinematic extended,
which produces videos
that are great to watch.
You can change the orientation
to receive buffers that are portrait.
And you can specify the pixel format,
to receive 10-bit lossless YUV buffers.
For more information
on selecting pixel formats
for an AVCaptureVideoDataOutput,
see Technote 3121.
In addition
to using multiple video data outputs,
starting in iOS 16 and iPadOS 16,
apps can record
with AVCaptureMovieFileOutput
while receiving data
from AVCaptureVideoDataOutput
and AVCaptureAudioDataOutput.
To determine
what can be added to a session,
you can check
whether an output can be added to it
and query
the session's hardwareCost property
to determine whether
the system can support your configuration.
By receiving video data
with a movie file output,
you can inspect the video while recording
and analyze the scene.
And receiving audio data
with a movie file output,
you can sample audio while recording
and listen to what is being recorded.
With a capture graph like this,
you can offload the mechanics
of recording to AVCaptureMovieFileOutput
while still receiving uncompressed video
and audio samples.
Implementing
these advanced streaming configurations
requires use of no new API.
We've enabled this by allowing you
to do more with existing API.
And lastly, I'll discuss how your app will
be able to use the camera
while the user is multitasking.
On iPad,
users can multitask in many ways.
For example, recording Voice Memos
while reading Notes in Split View
or with Slide Over,
write in Notes in a floating window
above Safari in full screen.
With Picture in Picture,
you can continue video playback
while adding reminders
to watch more WWDC videos.
And with Stage Manager new to iPadOS 16,
users can open multiple apps
in resizable floating windows.
Starting in iOS 16,
AVCaptureSessions will be able
to use the camera while multitasking.
We prevented camera access
while multitasking before
because of concerns
of the quality of service
the camera system can deliver
while multitasking.
Resource-intensive apps like games
running alongside an app using the camera
can induce frame drops and other latency,
resulting in a poor camera feed.
A user watching a video months
or years later that has poor quality
may not remember
that they recorded it while multitasking.
Providing a good camera experience
is our priority.
When the system detects video
from the camera was recorded
while multitasking,
a dialog will be displayed
informing the user about the potential
for lower quality videos.
This dialog will be presented
after recording has finished
with AVCaptureMovieFileOutput
or AVAssetWriter.
It will be shown only once
by the system for all apps
and will have an OK button to dismiss.
There are two new properties added
to AVCaptureSession to indicate
when multitasking camera access
is supported and enabled.
Capture sessions that have this enabled
will no longer be interrupted
with the reason “video device not
available with multiple foreground apps.”
Some apps may wish
to require a full screen experience
to use the camera.
This may be useful if you wish
for your app to not compete
with other foreground apps
for system resources.
For example, ARKit does not support
using the camera while multitasking.
You should ensure your app performs well
when running alongside other apps.
Make your app resilient
to increasing system pressure
by monitoring for its notifications,
and take action to reduce the impact,
like lowering the frame rate.
You can reduce
your app's footprint on the system
by requesting lower-resolution,
binned, or non-HDR formats.
For more information on best practices
of maintaining performance,
read the article “Accessing
the Camera While Multitasking”.
Also, video calling and video conferencing
apps can display remote participants
in a system-provided
Picture in Picture window.
Now your app's users
can seamlessly continue a video call
while multitasking on iPad.
AVKit introduced API in iOS 15
for apps to designate a view controller
for displaying
remote call participants in.
The video call view
controller allows you to customize
the content of the window.
To learn more about adoption,
please see the “Adopting Picture
in Picture for Video Calls” article.
And this concludes advancements
in iOS camera capture.
I showed how you can stream depth
from LiDAR Scanners using AVFoundation,
how your app will receive
improved face rendering,
Advanced AVCaptureSession streaming
configurations tailored for your app,
and lastly, how your app
can use the camera while multitasking.
I hope your WWDC rocks.
♪ ♪