♪ ♪
Nick Kledzik: Hi, I'm Nick Kledzik,
lead Engineer on Apple's Linker team.
Today, I'd like to share with you
how to link fast.
I'll tell you what Apple has done
to improve linking,
as well as help you understand
what actually happens during linking
so that you can improve
your app's link performance.
So what is linking?
You've written code, but you also use code
that someone else wrote
in the form of a library or a framework.
In order for your code to use
those libraries, a linker is needed.
Now, there are actually
two types of linking.
There is "static linking",
which happens when you build your app.
This can impact how long it takes
for your app to build
and how big your app ends up being.
And there is "dynamic linking".
This happens when your app is launched.
This can impact how long your customers
have to wait for your app to launch.
In this session I'll be talking about
both static and dynamic linking.
First, I'll define what static linking is
and where it came from,
with some examples.
Next, I'll unveil what is new
in ld64, Apple's static linker.
Then, with this background
on static linking,
I'll detail best practices
for static linking.
The second half of this talk
will cover dynamic linking.
I'll show what dynamic linking is
and where it came from,
and what happens during dynamic linking.
Next, I'll reveal what is new
in dyld this year.
Then, I'll talk about what you can do
to improve your app's
dynamic link time performance.
And lastly,
we'll wrap up with two new tools
that will help you
peek behind the curtains.
You'll be able to see
what is in your binaries,
and what is happening during
dynamic linking.
To understand static linking,
let's go way back to when it all started.
In the beginning, programs were simple
and there was just one source file.
Building was easy.
You just ran the compiler
on your one source file
and it produced the executable program.
But having all your source code
in one file did not scale.
How do you build
with multiple source files?
And this is not just because
you don't want to edit a large text file.
The real savings is
not re-compiling every function,
every time you build.
What they did was to split the compiler
into two parts.
The first part compiles source code
to a new intermediate
"relocatable object" file.
The second part reads
the relocatable .o file
and produces an executable program.
We now call the second part 'ld',
the static linker.
So now you know
where static linking came from.
As software evolved,
soon people were passing around .o files.
But that got cumbersome.
Someone thought, "Wouldn't it be great
if we could package up
a set of .o files into a 'library'?"
At the time the standard way
to bundle files together
was with the archiving tool 'ar'.
It was used for backups and distributions.
So the workflow became this.
You could 'ar' up multiple .o files
into an archive,
and the linker was enhanced
to know how to read .o files directly
out of an archive file.
This was a great improvement
for sharing common code.
At the time it was just called a library
or an archive.
Today, we call it a static library.
But now the final program was getting big
because thousands of functions
from these libraries were copied into it,
even if only a few of those functions
were used.
So a clever optimization was added.
Instead of having the linker use
all the .o files from the static library,
the linker would only pull
.o files from a static library
if doing so would resolve
some undefined symbol.
That meant someone could build
a big libc.a static library,
which contained
all the C standard library functions.
Every program
could link with the one libc.a,
but each program only got the parts
of libc that the program actually needed.
And we still have that model today.
But the selective loading from static
libraries is not obvious
and trips up many programmers.
To make the selective loading
of static libraries a little clearer,
I have a simple scenario.
In main.c, there's a function
called "main" that calls a function "foo".
In foo.c, there is foo which calls bar.
In bar.c,
there is the implementation of bar
but also an implementation of another
function which happens to be unused.
Lastly, in baz.c, there is a function baz
which calls a function named undef.
Now we compile each to its own .o file.
You'll see foo, bar, and undef
don't have gray boxes
because they are undefined.
That is, a use of a symbol
and not a definition.
Now, let's say you decide to combine
bar.o and baz.o into a static library.
Next, you link the two .o files
and the static library.
Let's step through what actually happens.
First, the linker works through the files
in command line order.
The first it finds is main.o.
It loads main.o
and finds a definition for "main",
shown here in the symbol table.
But also finds that main
has an undefined "foo".
The linker then parses the next file
on the command line which is foo.o.
This file adds a definition of "foo".
That means foo is no longer undefined.
But loading foo.o also adds
a new undefined symbol for "bar".
Now that all the .o files
on the command line have been loaded,
the linker checks if there are
any remaining undefined symbols.
In this case "bar" remains undefined,
so the linker starts looking at libraries
on the command line
to see if a library will satisfy
that missing undefined symbol "bar".
The linker finds that bar.o in the static
library defines the symbol "bar".
So the linker loads bar.o
out of the archive.
At that point there are no longer
any undefined symbols,
so the linker stops processing libraries.
The linker moves on to its next phase,
and assigns addresses to all the functions
and data
that will be in the program.
Then it copies all the functions
and data to the output file.
Et voila!
You have your output program.
Notice that baz.o was in the static
library but not loaded into the program.
It was not loaded because the way
the linker selectively loads
from static libraries.
This is non-obvious,
but the key aspect of static libraries.
Now you understand the basics
of static linking and static libraries.
Let's move on to recent improvements
on Apple's static linker,
known as ld64.
By popular demand, we spent some time
this year optimizing ld64.
And this year's linker is...
twice as fast for many projects.
How did we do this?
We now make better use of the cores
on your development machine.
We found a number of areas
where we could use multiple cores
to do linker work in parallel.
That includes copying content
from the input to the output file,
building the different parts
of LINKEDIT in parallel,
and changing the UUID computation
and codesigning hashes
to be done in parallel.
Next, we improved a number of algorithms.
Turns out the exports-trie builder
works really well
if you switch to use
C++ string_view objects
to represent the string slices
of each symbol.
We also used the latest crypto libraries
which take advantage
of hardware acceleration
when computing the UUID of a binary,
and we improved other algorithms too.
While working on
improving linker performance,
we noticed configuration issues
in some apps that impacted link time.
Next, I'll talk about what you can do
in your project to improve link time.
I'll cover five topics.
First,
whether you should use static libraries.
And then three little known options
that have a big effect on your link time.
Finally, I'll discuss some static linking
behavior that might surprise you.
The first topic is if you are
actively working on a source file
that builds into a static library,
you've introduced
a slowdown to your build time.
Because after the file is compiled,
the entire static library
has to be rebuilt,
including its table of contents.
This is just a lot of extra I/O.
Static libraries make
the most sense for stable code.
That is, code not being actively changed.
You should consider moving code
under active development
out of a static library
to reduce build time.
Earlier we showed
the selective loading from archives.
But a downside of that
is that it slows down the linker.
That is because
to make builds reproducible
and follow
traditional static library semantics,
the linker has to process static libraries
in a fixed, serial order.
That means some of the parallelization
wins of ld64
cannot be used with static libraries.
But if you don't really need
this historical behavior,
you can use a linker option
to speed up your build.
That linker option is called "all load".
It tells the linker to blindly load
all .o files from all static libraries.
This is helpful if your app is
going to wind up selectively loading
most of the content
from all the static libraries anyways.
Using -all_load will allow the linker
to parse all the static libraries
and their content in parallel.
But if your app does clever tricks
where it has multiple static libraries
implementing the same symbols,
and depends on the command line order
of the static libraries
to drive which implementation is used,
then this option is not for you.
Because the linker will load
all the implementations
and not necessarily
get the symbol semantics
that were found
in regular static linking mode.
The other downside of -all_load
is that it may make your program bigger
because "unused" code
is now being added in.
To compensate for that,
you can use the linker
option -dead_strip.
That option will cause the linker
to remove unreachable code and data.
Now, the dead stripping algorithm is fast
and usually pays for itself
by reducing the size of the output file.
But if you are interested
in using -all_load and -dead_strip,
you should time the linker
with and without those options
to see if it is a win
for your particular case.
The next linker option
is -no_exported_symbols.
A little background here.
One part of the LINKEDIT segment
that the linker generates
is an exports trie,
which is a prefix tree
that encodes all the exported symbol
names, addresses, and flags.
Whereas all dylibs need
to have exported symbols,
a main app binary usually
does not need any exported symbols.
That is, usually nothing ever looks up
symbols in the main executable.
If that is the case,
you can use -no_exported_symbols
for the app target to skip the creation
of the trie data structure in LINKEDIT,
which will improve link time.
But if your app loads plugins
which link back to the main executable,
or you use xctest with your app as the
host environment to run xctest bundles,
your app must have all its exports,
which means you cannot use
-no_exported_symbols
for that configuration.
Now, it only makes sense to try to
suppress the exports trie if it is large.
You can run the dyld_info command
shown here
to count the number of exported symbols.
One large app we saw had about
one million exported symbols.
And the linker took two to three seconds
to build the exports trie
for that many symbols.
So adding -no_exported_symbols
shaved two to three seconds
off the link time of that app.
I'll tell you more about
the dyld_info tool later in this talk.
The next option is: -no_deduplicate.
A few years back we added a new pass
to the linker to merge functions
that have the same instructions
but different names.
It turns out, with C++ template
expansions, you can get a lot of those.
But this is an expensive algorithm.
The linker has to recursively hash
the instructions of every function,
to help look for duplicates.
Because of the expense,
we limited the algorithm
so the linker only looks
at weak-def symbols.
Those are the ones the C++ compiler emits
for template expansions
that were not inlined.
Now, de-dup is a size optimization,
and Debug builds are about fast builds,
and not about size.
So by default, Xcode disables
the de-dup optimization
by passing -no_deduplicate to the linker
for Debug configurations.
And clang will also pass
the no-dedup option to the linker
if you run clang link line with -O0.
In summary, if you use C++
and have a custom build,
that is, either you use
a non-standard configuration in Xcode,
or you use some other build system,
you should ensure your debug builds add
-no_deduplicate to improve link time.
The options I just talked about are
the actual command line arguments to ld.
When using Xcode, you need to change
your product build settings.
Inside build settings,
look for "Other Linker Flags".
Here's what you would set for -all_load.
And notice the "Dead Code Stripping"
option is here as well.
And there's -no_exported_symbols.
And here's -no_deduplicate.
Now let's talk about some surprises
you may experience
when using static libraries.
The first surprise is when you have source
code that builds into a static library
which your app links with, and that code
does not end up in the final app.
For instance, you added
"attribute used" to some function,
or you have an Objective-C category.
Because of the selective loading
the linker does,
if those object files
in the static library
don't also define some symbol
that is needed during the link,
those object files won't get loaded
by the linker.
Another interesting interaction
is static libraries and dead stripping.
It turns out dead stripping can hide
many static library issues.
Normally,
missing symbols or duplicate symbols
will cause the linker to error out.
But dead stripping causes the linker
to run a reachability pass
across all the code and data,
starting from main,
and if it turns out the missing symbol
is from an unreachable code,
the linker will suppress
the missing symbol error.
Similarly, if there are
duplicate symbols from static libraries,
the linker will pick the first
and not error.
The last big surprise
with using static libraries,
is when a static library is incorporated
into multiple frameworks.
Each of those frameworks
runs fine in isolation,
but then at some point,
some app uses both frameworks, and boom,
you get weird runtime issues
because of the multiple definitions.
The most common case you will see
is the Objective-C runtime
warning about multiple instances
of the same class name.
Overall, static libraries are powerful,
but you need to understand them
to avoid the pitfalls.
That wraps up static linking.
Now, let's move on to dynamic linking.
First, let's look at the original diagram
for static linking with a static library.
Now think about
how this will scale over time,
as there is more and more source code.
It should be clear that as more and more
libraries are made available,
the end program may grow in size.
That means the static link time to build
that program will also increase over time.
Now let's look at how these libraries
are made.
What if we did this switch?
We change 'ar' to 'ld'
and the output library
is now an executable binary.
This was the start
of dynamic libraries in the '90s.
As a shorthand,
we call dynamic libraries "dylibs".
On other platforms
they are known as DSOs or DLLs.
So what exactly is going on here?
And how does that help the scalability?
The key is that
the static linker treats linking
with a dynamic library differently.
Instead of copying code out of the library
into the final program,
the linker just records a kind of promise.
That is, it records the symbol name
used from the dynamic library
and what the library's path
will be at runtime.
How is this an advantage?
It means your program file size
is under your control.
It just contains your code,
and a list of dynamic libraries
it needs at runtime.
You no longer get copies of library code
in your program.
Your program's static link time is
now proportional to the size of your code,
and independent of the number
of dylibs you link with.
Also, the Virtual Memory system
can now shine.
When it sees the same dynamic library
used in multiple processes,
the Virtual Memory system will re-use
the same physical pages of RAM
for that dylib in all processes
that use that dylib.
I've shown you how dynamic libraries
started and what problem they solve.
But what are the "costs"
for those "benefits"?
First,
a benefit of using dynamic libraries
is that we have sped up build time.
But the cost is that launching your app
is now slower.
This is because launching is no longer
just loading one program file.
Now all the dylibs also need to be loaded
and connected together.
In other words, you just deferred
some of the linking costs
from build time to launch time.
Second, a dynamic library based program
will have more dirty pages.
In the static library case,
the linker would co-locate all globals
from all static libraries into the same
DATA pages in the main executable.
But with dylibs,
each library has its DATA page.
Lastly, another cost of dynamic linking
is that it introduces the need
for something new: a dynamic linker!
Remember that promise that was recorded
in the executable at build time?
Now we need something at runtime that will
fulfill that promise to load our library.
That's what dyld,
the dynamic linker, is for.
Let's dive into how dynamic linking
works at runtime.
An executable binary is divided up
into segments,
usually at least TEXT, DATA, and LINKEDIT.
Segments are always a multiple
of the page size for the OS.
Each segment has a different permission.
For example, the TEXT segment
has "execute" permissions.
That means the CPU may treat the bytes
on the page as machine code instructions.
At runtime, dyld has to mmap()
the executables into memory
with each segments' permissions,
as show here.
Because the segments are page sized
and page aligned,
that makes it straightforward
for the virtual memory system
to just set up the program or dylib file
as backing store for a VM range.
That means nothing is loaded into RAM
until there is some memory access
on those pages,
which triggers a page fault,
which causes the VM system
to read the proper subrange of the file
and fill in the needed RAM page
with its content.
But just mapping is not enough.
Somehow the program needs to
be "wired up" or bound to the dylib.
For that we have a concept
called "fix ups".
In the diagram,
we see the program got pointers set up
that point to the parts of the dylib
it uses.
Let's dive into what fix-ups are.
Here is our friend, the mach-o file.
Now, TEXT is immutable.
And in fact, it has to be
in a system based on code signing.
So what if there is a function
that calls malloc()?
How can that work?
The relative address of _malloc
can't be known when the program was built.
Well, what happens is,
the static linker saw
that malloc was in a dylib
and transformed the call site.
The call site becomes a call to a stub
synthesized by the linker
in the same TEXT segment,
so the relative address is known
at build time,
which means the BL instruction
can be correctly formed.
How that helps
is that the stub loads a pointer from DATA
and jumps to that location.
Now, no changes to TEXT are needed
at runtime–
just DATA is changed by dyld.
In fact, the secret to understanding dyld
is that all fixups done by dyld
are just dyld setting a pointer in DATA.
So let's dig more
into the fixups that dyld does.
Somewhere in LINKEDIT is the information
dyld needs to drive what fixups are done.
There are two kinds of fixups.
The first are called rebases,
and they are when a dylib or app
has a pointer that points within itself.
Now there is a security feature
called ASLR,
which causes dyld to load dylibs
at random addresses.
And that means those interior pointers
cannot just be set at build time.
Instead, dyld needs to adjust
or "rebase" those pointers at launch.
On disk, those pointers contain
their target address,
if the dylib were to be loaded
at address zero.
That way, all the LINKEDIT needs to record
is the location of each rebase location.
Dyld can then just add
the actual load address of the dylib
to each of the rebase locations
to correctly fix them up.
The second kind of fixups are binds.
Binds are symbolic references.
That is, their target is a symbol name
and not a number.
For instance,
a pointer to the function "malloc".
The string "_malloc"
is actually stored in LINKEDIT,
and dyld uses that string
to look up the actual address of malloc
in the exports trie of libSystem.dylib.
Then, dyld stores that value
in the location specified by the bind.
This year we are announcing
a new way to encode fixups,
that we call "chained fixups".
The first advantage is that
is makes LINKEDIT smaller.
The LINKEDIT is smaller because instead
of storing all the fixup locations,
the new format just stores where the first
fixup location is in each DATA page,
as well as a list of the imported symbols.
Then the rest of the information
is encoded in the DATA segment itself,
in the place
where the fixups will ultimately be set.
This new format gets its name,
chained fixups,
from the fact that the fixup locations
are "chained" together.
The LINKEDIT just says
where the first fixup was,
then in the 64-bit pointer location
in DATA,
some of the bits contain the offset
to the next fixup location.
Also packed in there is a bit that says
if the fixup is a bind or a rebase.
If it is a bind, the rest of the bits
are the index of the symbol.
If it's a rebase, the rest of the bits
are the offset of the target
within the image.
Lastly, runtime support for chained fixups
already exists in iOS 13.4 and later.
Which means you can start using
this new format today,
as long as your deployment target
is iOS 13.4 or later.
And the chained fixup format enables
a new OS feature
we are announcing this year.
But to understand that,
I need to talk about how dyld works.
Dyld starts with the main executable–
say your app.
Parses that mach-o to find
the dependent dylibs,
that is,
what promised dynamic libraries it needs.
It finds those dylibs and mmap()s them.
Then for each of those, it recurses
and parses their mach-o structures,
loading any additional dylibs as needed.
Once everything is loaded,
dyld looks up all the bind symbols needed
and uses those addresses
when doing fixups.
Lastly, once all the fixups are done,
dyld runs initializers, bottom up.
Five years ago
we announced a new dyld technology.
We realized the steps in green above were
the same every time your app was launched.
So as long as the program and dylibs
did not change,
all the steps in green
could be cached on first launch
and re-used on subsequent launches.
This year we are announcing
additional dyld performance improvements.
We are announcing a new dyld feature
called "page-in linking".
Instead of dyld applying all the fixups
to all dylibs at launch,
the kernel can now apply fixups
to your DATA pages lazily, on page-in.
It has always been the case
that the first use of some address
in some page of an mmap()ed region
triggered the kernel to read in that page.
But now, if it is a DATA page,
the kernel will also apply the fixup
that page needs.
We have had a special case
of page-in linking for over a decade
for OS dylibs in the dyld shared cache.
This year we generalized it
and made it available to everyone.
This mechanism reduces
dirty memory and launch time.
It also means DATA_CONST pages are clean,
which means they can be evicted
and recreated just like TEXT pages,
which reduces memory pressure.
This page-in linking feature
will be in the upcoming release of iOS,
macOS, and watchOS.
But page-in linking only works
for binaries built with chained fixups.
That is because with chained fixups,
most of the fixup information will be
encoded in the DATA segment on disk,
which means it is available
to the kernel during page-in.
One caveat is that dyld only
uses this mechanism during launch.
Any dylibs dlopen()ed later
do not get page-in linking.
In that case,
dyld takes the traditional path
and applies the fixups
during the dlopen call.
With that in mind, let's go back
to the dyld workflow diagram.
For five years now, dyld has been
optimizing the steps above in green
by caching that work on first launch
and reusing it on later launches.
Now, dyld can optimize
the "apply fixup" step
by not actually doing the fixups,
and letting the kernel do them lazily
on page-in.
Now that you have seen
what's new in dyld,
let's talk about best practices
for dynamic linking.
What can you do to help
improve dynamic link performance?
As I just showed,
dyld has already accelerated
most of the steps in dynamic linking.
One thing you can control
is how many dylibs you have.
The more dylibs there are,
the more work dyld has to do to load them.
Conversely, the fewer dylibs,
the less work dyld has to perform.
The next thing you can look at
are static initializers,
which is code that always runs, pre-main.
For instance, don't do I/O or networking
in a static initializer.
Anything that can take more
than a few milliseconds
should never be done in an initializer.
As we know,
the world is getting more complicated,
and your users want more functionality.
So it makes sense to use libraries
to manage all that functionality.
Your goal is to find your sweet spot
between dynamic and static libraries.
Too many static libraries
and your iterative build/debug cycle
is slowed down.
On the other hand,
too many dynamic libraries
and your launch time is slow
and your customers notice.
But we sped up ld64 this year,
so your sweet spot may have changed,
as you can now use more static libraries,
or more source files directly in your app,
and still build
in the same amount of time.
Lastly,
if it works for your installed base,
updating to a newer deployment target
can enable the tools
to generate chained fixups,
making your binaries smaller,
and improving launch time.
The last thing
I'd like you all to be aware of
is two new tools that will help you peek
inside the linking process.
The first tool is dyld_usage.
You can use it
to get a trace of what dyld is doing.
The tool is only on macOS,
but you can use it to trace your app
launching in the simulator,
or if your app built for Mac Catalyst.
Here is an example run
against TextEdit on macOS.
As you can tell by the top few lines,
the launch took 15ms overall,
but only 1ms for fixups,
thanks to page-in linking.
The vast majority of time is now spent
in static initializers.
The next tool is dyld_info.
You can use it to inspect binaries,
both on disk
and in the current dyld cache.
The tool has many options, but I'll show
you how to view exports and fixups.
Here the -fixup option shows
all the fixup locations dyld will process
and their targets.
The output is the same regardless
of if the file is old style fixups
or new chained fixups.
Here the -exports option will show
all the exported symbols in the dylib,
and the offset of each symbol
from the start of the dylib.
In this case, it is showing information
about Foundation.framework
which is the dylib in the dyld cache.
There is no file on disk,
but the dyld_info tool uses the same code
as dyld and can thus find it.
Now that you understand
the history and tradeoffs
of static versus dynamic libraries,
you should review what you app does
and determine
if you have found your sweet spot.
Next, if you have a large app
and have noticed
the build takes a while to link,
try out Xcode 14
which has the new faster linker.
If you still want to speed up
your static link more,
look into the three linker options
I detailed
and see if they make sense in your build,
and improve your link time.
Lastly, you can also try building
your app, and any embedded frameworks,
for iOS 13.4 or later
to enable chained fixups.
Then see if your app is smaller
and launches faster on iOS 16.
Thanks for watching,
and have a great WWDC.