♪ ♪
Hi, I'm Slava
from the swift compiler team.
Welcome to Design
Protocol Interfaces in Swift.
I'm going to pick up where the Embrace
Swift Generics talk left off,
and show you some advanced techniques
for abstracting over concrete types
and modeling type relationships
using protocols.
This talk will cover both
existing language features,
as well as some of the new capabilities
introduced in Swift 5.7.
This talk has three main themes:
First, I'll show you how protocols with
associated types
interact with existential 'any' types,
by explaining
how 'result type erasure' works.
Next, I'll explain using
opaque result types
to improve encapsulation
by separating
interface from implementation.
For the final topic,
you will see how
same-type requirements in protocols
can model relationships between
multiple different sets of concrete types.
Let's start by learning
how protocols with associated types
interact with existential types.
Here, we have a data model
with a pair of protocols,
and four concrete types.
There are two types of animals,
chickens and cows,
and two types of food, eggs and milk.
Chickens produce eggs,
and cows produce milk.
To abstract over the production of food,
I'm going to add a produce() method
to the Animal protocol.
You might remember
from the 'Embrace swift generics' talk
that that the best way to abstract the
different return types
of produce() on Cow and Chicken
is to use an associated type.
By using an associated type,
we're declaring that:
given some concrete type of Animal,
calling produce() returns
some specific type of Food,
that depends on the concrete Animal type.
We can show
this relationship with a diagram.
The protocol 'Self' type stands in
for the actual concrete type
conforming to the 'Animal' protocol.
The 'Self' type has an associated
'Commodity' type,
conforming to 'Food'.
Let's look at the relationships between
the concrete Chicken and Cow types,
and the associated type diagram
for the Animal protocol.
The Chicken type conforms to the Animal
protocol with a CommodityType of 'Egg'.
And the Cow type conforms to the Animal
protocol with a CommodityType of 'Milk'.
Now, let's say we have a farm
full of animals.
The 'animals' stored property on Farm
is a heterogenous array of 'any Animal'.
In embrace Swift generics,
we saw how the 'any Animal' type
has a box representation
that has the ability to store
any concrete type of animal dynamically.
This strategy of using
the same representation
for different concrete types
is called type erasure.
The produceCommodities() method
maps over the array of animals,
calling the produce() method on each one.
The method looks simple,
but we know that type erasure
will eliminate static type relationships
to the underlying type of animal,
so it's worth digging deeper
to understand why this code type checks.
The 'animal' parameter in
the map() closure has type 'any Animal'.
The return type of 'produce()'
is an associated type.
When you call a method returning
an associated type on an existential type,
the compiler will use type erasure
to determine the result type of the call.
Type erasure replaces
these associated types
with corresponding existential types
that have equivalent constraints.
We've erased the relationship
between the concrete Animal type
and the associated CommodityType
by replacing them with 'any Animal'
and 'any Food'.
The type 'any Food' is called the upper
bound of the associated CommodityType.
Since the produce() method
is called on an 'any Animal',
the return value is type erased,
giving us a value of type 'any Food'.
This is exactly the type we expect here.
Let's take a closer look at
how associated-type erasure works,
which is a new feature in Swift 5.7.
An associated type appearing in
the result type of a protocol method –
on the right-hand side of the arrow –
is said to be in 'producing position',
because calling the method
will produce a value of this type.
When we call this method on 'any Animal',
we don't know the concrete result type
at compile time,
but we do know that it is a subtype
of the upper bound.
Here in this example,
we're calling produce() on an 'any Animal'
that holds a Cow at runtime.
In our case,
the produce() method on Cow returns Milk.
Milk can be stored
inside of an 'any Food',
which is the upper bound of the associated
CommodityType of the Animal protocol.
This is always safe, for all concrete
types that conform to the Animal protocol.
On the other hand, let's think about
what happens if the associated type
appears in the parameter list
of a method or initializer.
Here, the eat() method on
the Animal protocol
has the associated FeedType
in consuming position.
We need to pass in a value of this type
to call the method.
Since the conversion goes
in the other direction,
type erasure cannot be performed.
The upper bound existential type
for the associated type
does not safety convert
to the actual concrete type,
because the concrete type is unknown.
Let's look at an example.
Once again,
we have an 'any Animal' storing a Cow.
Suppose that the 'eat' method
on Cow takes Hay.
The upper bound of the Animal protocol's
associated 'FeedType' is 'any AnimalFeed'.
But given an arbitrary 'any AnimalFeed',
there is no way to statically guarantee
that it stores the 'Hay' concrete type.
Type erasure does not allow us
to work with associated types
in consuming position.
Instead, you must unbox
the existential 'any' type
by passing it to a function
that takes an opaque 'some' type.
This type erasure behavior with
associated types is actually similar
to an existing language feature
you may have seen in Swift 5.6.
Consider a protocol
for cloning reference types.
This protocol defines a single
clone() method, returning Self.
When you call clone()
on a value of type 'any Cloneable',
the result type 'Self',
is type erased to its upper bound.
The upper bound of the Self type
is always the protocol itself,
so we get back a new value
of type 'any Cloneable'.
So to summarize: you can use
'any' to declare that the type of a value
is an existential type that stores some
concrete type conforming to a protocol.
This even works with protocols
that have associated types.
When calling a protocol method with
an associated type in producing position,
the associated type is type-erased
to its upper bound,
which is another existential type that
carries the associated type's constraints.
Abstracting over concrete types
isn't only useful for function inputs -
it's useful for function outputs, too,
so that concrete types are only visible
from the implementation.
Let's take a look at how to abstract away
concrete result types
to separate the essential interface
of a piece of code
from its implementation details,
making static type assignments more
modular and robust in the face of changes.
Let's generalize the Animal protocol
to allow feeding Animals.
Animals get hungry,
and when they're hungry they need to eat.
Let's add an isHungry property
to the Animal protocol.
The feedAnimals() method on Farm will feed
the subset of animals that are hungry.
I've split off the computation
of this subset of hungry animals
into a hungryAnimals property.
This initial implementation of
hungryAnimals() uses the filter() method
to select the subset of animals
where the isHungry property is true.
Calling filter() on an array
of 'any Animal'
returns a new array of 'any Animal'.
Now you might notice
that feedAnimals()
only iterates over the result
of hungryAnimals once,
and then immediately discards
this temporary array.
This is inefficient if the farm contains
a large number of hungry animals.
One way to avoid
this temporary allocation
is to use the standard library's
lazy collections feature.
By replacing the call to 'filter'
with 'lazy.filter',
we get what is known as a lazy collection.
A lazy collection has the same elements
as the array returned
by a plain call to 'filter',
but it avoids the temporary allocation.
However, now the type of
the 'hungryAnimals' property
must be declared
as this rather complex concrete type,
'LazyFilterSequence
of Array of any Animal'.
This exposes
an unnecessary implementation detail.
The client, feedAnimals(), doesn't care
that we used 'lazy.filter'
in the implementation of 'hungryAnimals';
it only needs to know that it's getting
some collection that it can iterate over.
An opaque result type can be used
to hide the complex concrete type
behind the abstract interface
of a Collection.
Now clients calling 'hungryAnimals' only
know they're getting some concrete type
conforming to the Collection protocol,
but they don't know the specific
concrete type of collection.
However as written,
this actually hides too much
static type information from the client.
We're declaring that hungryAnimals
outputs some concrete type
conforming to Collection,
but we don't know anything
about this Collection's Element type.
Without the knowledge
that the element type is 'any Animal',
all we can do with the element type
is pass it around;
we can't call any of the methods
of the Animal protocol.
Let's focus on the opaque result type
'some Collection'.
We can strike the right balance
between hiding implementation details
and exposing a sufficiently-rich interface
by using a constrained opaque result type.
Constrained opaque result types
are new in Swift 5.7.
A constrained opaque result type
is written by applying type arguments
in angle brackets
after the protocol name.
The Collection protocol has
a single type argument, the Element type.
Now once 'hungryAnimals' is declared
with a constrained opaque result type,
the fact that it is actually
a 'LazyFilterSequence of an array
of any Animal' is hidden from the client;
but the client still has the knowledge
that it is some concrete type
conforming to Collection,
whose Element associated type
is equal to 'any Animal'.
This is precisely the interface
that we want here.
Inside the for loop in 'feedAnimals()',
the 'animal' variable
has the type 'any Animal',
allowing methods of the Animal protocol
to be called on each hungry animal.
This all works because
the Collection protocol declares
that the Element associated type
is a primary associated type.
You can declare your own protocols
with primary associated types
by naming one or more associated types
in angle brackets after the protocol name,
like this.
The associated types that work best
as primary associated types
are those that are usually provided
by the caller,
such as an Element type of a collection,
as opposed to implementation details,
such as the collection's Iterator type.
Often, you will see a correspondence
between the primary associated types
of a protocol, and the generic parameters
of a concrete type
conforming to this protocol.
Here, you can see that the Element primary
associated type of 'Collection'
is implemented by the 'Element'
generic parameter of Array and Set,
two concrete types defined by the standard
library that both conform to Collection.
'Collection of Element' can be used
with opaque result types
using the 'some' keyword,
as well as with constrained
existential types using the 'any' keyword.
Before Swift 5.7, you would've needed
to write your own data type
to represent an existential type
with a specific generic argument.
Swift 5.7 builds this concept
into the language
with constrained existential types.
If we wanted hungryAnimals
to have the option
of whether to compute
the hungryAnimals lazily or eagerly,
using an opaque Collection
of any Animal would result in an error
that the function returns
two different underlying types.
We can fix this by instead
returning 'any Collection of any Animal',
signaling that this API can return
different types across calls.
The ability to constrain primary
associated types
gives opaque types and existential types
a new level of expressivity.
This can be used with various standard
library protocols such as Collection;
you can also declare your own protocols
to have primary associated types.
Writing generic code using opaque types
must rely on abstract type relationships.
Let's discuss how to identify
and guarantee necessary type relationships
between multiple abstract types
using related protocols.
We're going to add a new associated type
to the Animal protocol
for the concrete type of animal feed
that this animal eats,
together with an eat() method that tells
the animal to consume this type of feed.
To make things more interesting,
I'm going to introduce
an additional complication:
before we can feed an animal,
we must grow the appropriate type of crop,
and harvest the crop to produce the feed.
Here is the first set of concrete types.
A cow eats hay,
so given a cow,
we first need to grow some hay.
This gives us alfalfa,
which is harvested and processed into hay,
that the cow can eat.
Here's the second set of concrete types.
A chicken eats scratch,
so if you bring me a chicken,
we first need to grow a type of grain
called millet
that we harvest and process
to produce chicken scratch,
which we feed to our chicken.
I want to abstract over these two sets of
related concrete types,
so I can implement
the feedAnimal() method once,
and have it feed both cows and chickens,
as well as any new types of animals
I might adopt in the future.
Since feedAnimal() needs to work with
the eat() method of the Animal protocol,
which has an associated type
in consuming position,
I'm going to unbox the existential
by declaring that the feedAnimal() method
takes 'some Animal' as a parameter type.
To start, I'll define a pair of protocols,
AnimalFeed and Crop,
using what we know about protocols
and associated types so far.
AnimalFeed has an associated CropType,
which conforms to Crop,
and Crop has an associated FeedType,
which conforms to AnimalFeed.
As before, we can look at a diagram
of type parameters for each protocol.
First, let's look at AnimalFeed.
Every protocol has a 'Self' type,
which stands for
the concrete conforming type.
Our protocol has an associated 'CropType',
which conforms to Crop.
The associated 'CropType' has a nested
associated 'FeedType',
which conforms to AnimalFeed,
which has a nested associated 'CropType'
conforming to Crop, and so on.
In fact, this back-and-forth
continues forever,
with an infinite nesting
of associated types
that alternate between conforming
to AnimalFeed and Crop.
With the Crop protocol, we have
a similar situation, just shifted by one.
We start with the 'Self' type,
conforming to 'Crop',
which has an associated 'FeedType',
conforming to AnimalFeed.
This has a nested associated 'CropType',
conforming to Crop and so on...
To infinity.
Let's see if these protocols
correctly model the relationship
between our concrete types.
Recall that before we can feed an animal,
we need to grow the crop
that is then processed into
the correct type of animal feed.
grow() is a static method
in the AnimalFeed protocol,
which means it must be called directly
on a type conforming to AnimalFeed,
and not on a specific value
whose type conforms to AnimalFeed.
We need to write down a the name of a type
conforming to AnimalFeed,
but all we have is a specific value,
of some type conforming to Animal,
a different protocol.
Well, we can get the type of this value,
which we know is some type
conforming to Animal,
and Animal has an associated FeedType,
which conforms to AnimalFeed.
This type can be used as the base
of the method call grow().
The grow() method on AnimalFeed
returns a value
whose type is the nested
associated CropType of AnimalFeed.
We know that CropType conforms to Crop,
so I can call harvest() on it.
But what do I get back?
harvest() is declared to return
the associated FeedType
of the Crop protocol.
In our case, since the base of the call is
(some Animal).FeedType.CropType,
harvest() will output a value of type
(some Animal).FeedType.CropType.FeedType.
Unfortunately, this is the wrong type.
The eat() method on (some Animal) expects
(some Animal).FeedType,
and not
(some Animal).FeedType.CropType.FeedType.
The program is not well-typed.
These protocol definitions, as written,
do not actually guarantee
that if we start
with a type of animal feed,
and then grow and harvest this crop,
we'll get back
the same type of animal feed
that we started with,
which is what our animal expects to eat.
Another way to think about it
is that these protocol definitions
are too general -
they don't accurately model
the desired relationship
between our concrete types.
To understand why,
let's look at our Hay and Alfalfa types.
When I grow hay, I get alfalfa,
and when I harvest alfalfa,
I get hay, and so on.
Now imagine I'm refactoring my code,
and I accidentally change the return type
of the harvest() method on Alfalfa
to return Scratch instead of Hay.
After this accidental change,
the concrete types
still satisfy the requirements
of the AnimalFeed and Crop protocols,
even though we violate our desired
invariant that growing and harvesting
a crop produces the same type
of animal feed that we started with.
Let's look
at the AnimalFeed protocol again.
the real problem here is that in a sense,
we have too many
distinct associated types.
We need to write down the fact
that two of these associated types
are actually the same concrete type.
This will prevent
incorrectly-written concrete types
from conforming to our protocols;
it will also to give
the feedAnimal() method
the guarantee that it needs.
We can express the relationship
between these associated types
using a same-type requirement,
written in a 'where' clause.
A same-type requirement
expresses a static guarantee
that two different,
possibly nested associated types
must in fact be the same concrete type.
Adding a same-type requirement here
imposes a restriction
on the concrete types that conform
to the AnimalFeed protocol.
In this same-type requirement here,
we're declaring that
`Self dot CropType dot FeedType'
is the same type as 'Self'.
what does this look like in our diagram?
Well, here is how we can visualize it:
Each concrete type conforming
to AnimalFeed has a CropType,
which conforms to Crop.
However, the FeedType of this CropType,
is not just some other type
conforming to AnimalFeed,
it is the same concrete type
as the original AnimalFeed.
Instead of an infinite tower
of nested associated types,
I've collapsed all relationships down
to a single pair
of related associated types.
What about the 'Crop' protocol?
Here, the Crop's FeedType
has collapsed down to a pair of types,
but we still have
one too many associated types.
We want to say
that the Crop's FeedType's Crop Type
is the same type as the Crop
that we originally started with.
Now that these two protocols
have been equipped
with same-type requirements,
we can revisit the 'feedAnimal()'
method again.
We start with the type of some Animal,
as before.
and we get the animal's feed type,
which we know conforms
to the AnimalFeed protocol.
When we grow this crop, we get
some animal's feed type's crop type.
But now, when we harvest this crop,
instead of getting yet another
nested associated type,
we get exactly the feed type
that our animal expects,
and the happy animal is now guaranteed
to eat() the correct type of animal feed
that we just grew.
Finally, let's look at an associated type
diagram for the Animal protocol,
which pulls everything together
we've seen so far.
Here are the two sets of conforming types:
first, we have Cow, Hay, and Alfalfa.
Second, we have Chicken, Scratch
and Millet.
Notice how our three protocols
precisely model the relationships
between each set of three concrete types.
By understanding your data model,
you can use same-type requirements
to define equivalences between
these different nested associated types.
Generic code can then rely on
these relationships
when chaining together multiple calls
to protocol requirements.
During this session,
we explored when type erasure is safe,
and when we need to be in a context
where type relationships are guaranteed.
Then, we discussed how to strike
the right balance
between preserving rich type information
and hiding implementation details
using primary associated types,
which can be used with both opaque
result types and existential types.
Finally, we saw how to identify
and guarantee type relationships
between sets of concrete types
using same-type requirements
across the protocols that represent
those related sets of types.
Thank you for joining me.
I hope you have a great WWDC.