♪ ♪
Hello, and welcome to WWDC 2022.
My name is Ben, and I'm an engineer
on the Xcode build system team.
Hi, my name is Artem, and I'm
an engineer on the Swift Compiler team.
In this talk we're gonna give you
a deep dive into Xcode's build process
to demystify parallelization
inside builds.
Ben is going to start with an introduction
of the core concepts about builds
and look at the available tools
that Xcode offers
to help investigate
build performance issues.
He will then explain how Xcode increases
parallelization while building a target.
Building on top of that,
I will explain how Xcode
parallelizes a build holistically
while building projects
consisting of many targets
and summarize the takeaways in the end.
Ben?
Let's re-iterate on what happens when
pressing CMD+B in Xcode to build an app.
The build system, as part of Xcode,
gets invoked with a representation
of the whole project,
including all source files, assets,
build settings, and other configurations
like the run destination.
The build system is the single source
of truth about how an app should be built.
It knows which tools to invoke
using which settings
and which intermediate files to produce
to eventually create an app.
In the next step,
the build system invokes the tools
to process the project's input files,
for example, the compilers.
Both compilers, Clang and Swift,
will produce object files
that the linker needs
to link the executable program
that represents the app.
While this order makes sense,
it's not obvious where it comes from.
So let's take a look
at one example of that process
and how the build system decides
in which order to execute all tasks.
Using the input source-files,
the Swift compiler captures
the programmer's intent and translates it
into a machine-executable binary,
checking the source code
for errors along the way.
This process can fail,
which would cancel the build,
but if it succeeds,
it creates an object file for each input.
Those object files are used
to invoke the linker
which combines them and adds references
to externally linked libraries
to produce the executable.
The two tasks have a dependency
based on what they consume and produce.
The object files produced by the compiler
get consumed by the linker.
This creates a dependency
on the build system graph.
The file contents itself
are not of interest to the build system,
but the dependency between the tasks is.
While executing the build,
it needs to make sure
that a task that produces another task's
input finishes before said task can start.
And since this core concept
is valid for all kind of tasks,
let's switch to
a more generic visualization
that shows a dependency
between Task A and Task B.
In this case,
A produces some or all of B's inputs.
Compiling and Linking are only
a few of many different task types
that need to be executed
to build a whole target,
so let's add some more generic tasks
to the graph
that represent other types
like compiling assets,
copying files or codesigning.
Together, they represent
building a Framework target.
Again,
those tasks have defined dependencies
based on their inputs and outputs.
So completing executing task A
unblocks running task B and C,
while finishing task B
unblocks task D and E.
Tasks that get unblocked
are called 'downstream'
and tasks that block 'upstream'.
Many projects contain
more than one framework target,
so let's add two more targets representing
an app and an app extension.
Targets define dependencies
between each other in the project
via explicit or implicit dependencies.
For example, by getting added to the
'Link Binary with Libraries' build phase.
In this case,
the app embeds the app extension
and links against the Framework.
The app extension
is not using the Framework,
so they don't have
a dependency relationship.
When executing the build graph, different
tasks take a different amount of time.
This comes down to the level of complexity
that is necessary to complete the work,
depending on the computation that's needed
as well as the size of the input.
Compiling many files takes usually much
more time than copying a few header files,
and taking this into consideration
will end up with something like this.
When the build system executes this build,
it starts by running tasks
that don't have dependencies.
And once those completed,
they unblock downstream tasks and so on,
following this process
until all planned tasks finished.
On following builds,
the build system is able to skip tasks
for which inputs haven't changed
while the output is still up to date.
If a task needs to re-run
due to a changed input,
like B of the App target in this case,
downstream tasks have to re-run too
if its output changed.
Skipping all other tasks allows
for very fast turnaround times
when iteratively working on the project.
This is called an incremental build,
but let's stick to full builds for now.
The dependencies and duration
of the task execution
defines the first possible time
a downstream task can start.
With this information it's possible
to calculate the critical path
which is the shortest time
the build needs to run
with theoretical unlimited resources.
A common pattern throughout this talk
will be to shorten this path
to create a highly parallelizable
and scalable build graph.
A shorter critical path
does not necessarily result
in a shorter overall build time,
but it ensures that the build scales
with the hardware.
The critical build path
defines the limiting factor
of how fast a build can be–
it cannot complete faster,
even if the hardware would allow it.
Shortening the critical path is done by
breaking up dependencies within it.
When looking at how a build performed and
to understand more about its execution,
the data needs to be plotted
based on the time they executed.
The width still indicates
the length of tasks.
Wide elements like these two
indicate a long running task
while narrow elements like these
represent fast finishing tasks.
The height of the graph shows the number
of parallel executing tasks
at a given time.
Be aware that this does not directly map
to CPU or memory utilization.
Empty space originates by tasks blocking
its downstream tasks
like in those two scenarios.
And finally, the color of the elements
represent their associated target.
I'm very excited to announce that
this visualization is new in Xcode 14
and will help understand
a build's performance after it finished.
The Xcode Build Timeline is
a great new addition to the build log.
It visualizes based on
parallelization,
rather than hierarchy
to understand the build's performance.
The number of rows at given time
represents the level of parallelism
during that time.
The horizontal length of individual tasks
represent the duration they needed
to finish their work.
Empty space in the graph
shows where unfinished tasks
blocked downstream tasks
from starting to execute.
Different colors applied
to the timeline elements
help distinguish the different targets
that were part of the build.
And on incremental builds,
the timeline will only contain tasks
that got actually executed,
allowing to spot long-running tasks,
especially ones which might not have
been expected to run during this build.
Here's a demo of the Build Timeline
in Xcode 14.
In this window I opened a copy
of the swift-docc project from Github
which builds the documentation compiler.
To get an overview about the targets
that are built for the scheme,
let's check out the scheme editor.
To open that I click on the scheme
and select "Edit scheme".
The 'build' tab contains a list
of all targets.
Targets can explicitly get added
to the scheme
or implicitly
by being a dependency of a target
that is already part of the scheme.
In this case I'm using a Swift package
with an automatically generated scheme
for the package, so all targets
from the manifest are explicitly defined.
This log represents a build of that scheme
that I executed earlier.
In contains entries for all tasks
that the build system executed.
The entries are organized in a hierarchy
based on the targets they belong to,
like the 'docc' target here.
To successfully build the executable
of that target,
Xcode ran all tasks that are represented
by the children of this node.
Since the build log is currently
in its 'All' state,
it also shows tasks from previous builds
that didn't need to re-run
in an incremental build.
Selecting 'Recent' only shows tasks
that got actually executed,
hiding all skipped tasks.
In addition to that,
the build log also supports filters
to only show tasks
that had issues or even failed.
To open the build timeline for this build,
I go to the editor options
and open the assistant.
The build timeline
opens next to the build log.
Like usual, the editor options
provide settings to show the assistant
on the right or bottom.
I'll stay with bottom for now.
The timeline visualizes the same data
as the 'recent' build log
based on the parallelization of the build.
Selecting an element in one
also selects it in the other.
This enables to see
a task's execution in context.
The timeline here gives a sense
about the tasks
that executed in parallel
to the selected task.
I'm using a pinch gesture
on the trackpad to zoom out again.
Selecting an element in the timeline
shows it in the build log.
And since the build log visualizes
based on the hierarchical structure,
it enables to view
which files were compiled
as part of this compiler invocation.
It also enables to view the whole
command line of that invocation.
Holding down Option while selecting
an area in the build timeline
adjusts the view port
to fit this timeframe.
Here we can verify
that linking of the target ArgumentParser
is in fact waiting for compilation
of the same target.
Holding Option while scrolling up
allows me to zoom out quickly.
The number of rows in the timeline
represents the number of tasks
that ran in parallel at that time.
An empty space like this indicates tasks
waiting for un-produced inputs.
Ideally, the timeline is vertically filled
and has as little empty space as possible.
This scales the build graph the best
and makes builds faster,
the faster the hardware.
To achieve this, Xcode comes with
many improvements this year
to shorten the critical path.
Next, let's check out how Xcode defines
and builds individual targets
as well as how
it can increase parallelization.
When configuring a target,
build phases describe the work
that needs to be done
to produce that target's product.
They are defined in the project editor
and can contain a set of source code files
and assets to compile,
files that need to be copied
like headers or resources,
as well as libraries that should be linked
or scripts that should be executed.
Many build phases describe
tasks with inputs or outputs
from other build phases,
creating dependencies between them.
For example, a target's source files
must be compiled before it is linked.
However,
this doesn't apply to all build phases.
Instead of running tasks from
each build phase in a linear order,
the build system will consider the inputs
and outputs of build phases
to determine if they can run in parallel.
For example, Compilation
and Resource copying can run in parallel
because neither depends
on any outputs of the other.
However,
linking must still follow compilation
because it depends on the object files
produced by that phase.
Now, let's consider a different target
which contains 'Run Script' build phases.
Unlike other build phases,
the inputs and outputs of script phases
must be manually configured
in the target editor.
As a result, the build system
will run consecutive script phases
one at a time to avoid introducing
a data race in the build process.
If the scripts in a target
are configured to run
based on dependency analysis
and specify their complete list
of inputs and outputs,
then the build setting
FUSE_BUILD_SCRIPT_PHASES
can be set to YES
to indicate the build system
should attempt to run them in parallel.
However,
when running script phases in parallel,
the build system has to rely
on the specified inputs and outputs.
So be aware that an incomplete list
of the inputs or outputs of a script phase
can lead to data races
which are very hard to debug.
To mitigate this, Xcode supports
user script sandboxing
to precisely declare the dependencies
of each script phase.
Sandboxing is an opt-in feature
that blocks shell scripts
from accidentally accessing source files
and intermediate build objects,
unless those are explicitly declared
as an input or output for the phase.
In this example,
neither input nor output.txt
are declared as a dependency
for that script phase.
The sandbox will block the script
from reading and writing
to both files when building the project.
When the script violates the sandbox,
it will fail with a non-zero exit code
causing the build to fail.
In addition to that,
Xcode will list all the paths
that the script phase was trying to access
without properly declaring them.
Adding both files as dependency
information to this script phase
fixes this issue.
This way the sandbox ensures
that the script is not mistakenly
accessing any file other than
its declared inputs and outputs.
Now, let's explore an example
with more than one script phase
and see how sandboxing prevents
data races and incorrect builds.
There are two script phases.
The first one reads a text file,
calculates a checksum of its content,
and writes that value to an intermediate
file in DERIVED_FILE_DIR.
The other script reads the same text file
as well as the produced checksum
and injects them into an html file
for later display in the app.
If the precise set of input
and output dependencies for these phases
is not declared,
Xcode will run the two scripts in parallel
when FUSE_BUILD_SCRIPT_PHASES
is on.
Let's inspect this problematic scenario
in detail.
Let's assume "Generate HTML"
is missing the input declaration
of "checksum.txt", but all other inputs
and outputs of both scripts
have been correctly declared.
Without sandboxing, this misconfiguration
might stay unnoticed,
causing problems in the build.
It means Xcode will fail to infer
the dependency relation
between both phases,
and schedule to run them in parallel
when FUSE_BUILD_SCRIPT_PHASES
is switched on.
There are a few hazards here.
Since checksum.txt is not listed as an
input dependency for "Generate HTML"
during a clean build
the script will attempt to read the file
without it being available
on the filesystem.
The other hazard is if checksum.txt
is available on disk
because of previous runs
of "Calculate Checksum",
"Generate HTML"
may pick up the outdated file
when the two scripts run in parallel.
This is a user error,
and executing the scripts in a sandbox
helps preventing this issue.
With sandboxing switched on,
"Generate HTML" will fail immediately
when it attempts to read "checksum.txt".
The error message will guide adding
the missing input for that build phase.
Having the inputs and outputs
correctly defined
guides Xcode to respect the dependency
relation between both phases
so that "calculate checksum"
runs before "Generate HTML".
While unrelated build phases
can still execute in parallel.
To enable Sandboxed Shell Scripts
for a target,
set ENABLE_USER_SCRIPT_SANDBOXING
to YES in the build settings editor
or an xcconfig file.
In summary, sandboxed shell scripts allow
having correct dependency information
to enable faster
and more robust incremental builds
since the build system has the confidence
to skip script phases
if the inputs haven't changed
and the outputs are still valid,
while re-running the script otherwise.
Enabling the build setting for
a script's target blocks access to files
inside the source root of the project
as well as the derived data directory
if they are not explicitly defined
as inputs or outputs of the script
in the project.
The sandbox will not prevent unauthorized
access to any other directory,
so don't consider this a security feature.
Using this feature helps to debug
missing inputs or outputs
of existing script phases
to ensure a valid configuration
And in combination with
the previously explained build setting
FUSE_BUILD_SCRIPT_PHASES,
script phases with correctly defined
dependency edges through sandboxing
can execute in parallel
to reduce the critical path of the build.
That's it for parallelizing
the steps of building a target.
Now Artem is going to
demystify parallelization
hen building many targets.
Artem: Thanks, Ben.
Now that we've covered the basics
of build system tasks
and phases that may go into building
a target in your project,
let's take a more global view
and explore how Xcode uses dependencies
between Swift targets
to extract the maximum amount
of parallelism out of your builds
and how the structure and organization
of your project can affect build times.
There are likely to be several levels
of hierarchy composing your project.
For example, an App target depending
on a collection of local libraries
broken up into targets
along semantic boundaries,
and in several frameworks.
Each target containing
many different build phases and steps,
producing and consuming file dependencies
to and from build phases in other targets.
As the size of your project grows,
these task graphs tend to increase in size
and complexity.
While the Xcode Build System
flattens these hierarchies,
breaking down the build
into a sea of tasks
that correspond to build phases
of all targets.
One kind of task that is special
for a Swift target is compilation.
Building a Swift target's source code
into binary product's
is a complex operation
that typically consists of many sub-tasks
for build planning,
compilation, and linking.
Coordination of these
tasks is delegated to a specialized tool
in the Xcode toolchain–
the Swift Driver.
The Driver has specialized knowledge
on when and how to construct
the required compiler and linker
invocations for the target's source code.
Any target that includes Swift code
also corresponds to a unit
of code distribution: a module.
A binary module file capturing
the public interface of this target
is a build product that is required for
downstream targets to begin a compilation.
Let's take a closer look at an example
of what Swift Driver does
to build one of the targets.
Your target probably consists of
a collection of several source files.
In release or optimized builds
the driver will schedule one compiler task
including all source files to maximize
opportunities for optimization.
This single compile task will also produce
the target's Swift module.
In debug or incremental compilation modes,
the Swift Driver breaks down
the required compilation effort
into smaller sub-tasks
which can run in parallel,
some of which may not need to re-run
on an incremental build.
Producing a Swift module then requires
an additional step
to merge together partial intermediate
products of each compile task.
If, like in this example,
the number of source files
in your target is high,
individual files may also be assigned
to batch compilation sub-tasks,
according to
the build-system's heuristics.
The build log highlights
which source files get assigned
to batch compilation jobs,
with a separate entry
for each file's diagnostics.
Being able to parallelize a target's build
across different source files is crucial
for both faster
and smaller incremental builds,
so make sure your Debug builds are using
the Incremental Compilation Mode setting.
Before Xcode 14,
because of the boundary
between the Xcode Build System
and Swift Driver,
orchestration of target build phases,
and compilation sub-tasks spawned by each
target's instance of the Driver
happened independently of each other,
with each component doing its best
to make the most
of available system resources.
Let's take this example build graph
and dive deeper
into what goes into scheduling
its compilation phases
with respect to each other.
As we've learned earlier,
Swift target dependencies are resolved
by having their dependents provide
a binary module file
that captures the dependent's
public interface.
Resolving these dependency relationships
leads us to the following ordering,
captured in a timeline showing
the top-level Swift Driver tasks
for each target,
as well as their individual sub-tasks.
With Xcode 14, thanks to an entirely new
implementation of Swift Driver–
itself now written in Swift–
the build system
and the compiler are fully integrated.
The Xcode Build System acts
as the central scheduler
for all tasks that must be performed
to compile your code.
This central planning mechanism
allows Xcode
to make fine-grained scheduling decisions
providing better guarantees
that building your project
will use only as much resources
as available,
without oversubscribing your CPU
and reducing overall system performance.
And what was previously a collection
of islands of sub-tasks
outside of Xcode Build System's purview
are now fully in a domain
of the build-system's scheduler.
With all the individual sub-tasks
in a central task pool,
it is important to consider the trade-offs
made by the build scheduler.
For example, on an 8-core machine
the scheduler's default
is to assign available tasks–
those tasks whose dependencies have been
satisfied and are ready to go–
to one of eight available execution slots.
As soon as one of the slots frees up,
the Build System attempts to fill it
with more outstanding work.
On a higher-core-count machine,
we're able to perform
more concurrent work.
But that means we're also more likely
to have idle cores
which are available to perform more work,
but all of the outstanding tasks
are still awaiting their inputs,
as produced by other tasks
that are currently in-flight or waiting.
The new integrated build system
allows the scheduler
to significantly reduce this idle time.
To see how, let's revisit how
a target's dependencies for compilation,
binary module files, are resolved.
As we've covered earlier,
the partial results
of compilation sub-tasks
are merged into a target's
final module product.
Once this product is available,
downstream targets may begin compilation.
New in Xcode 14 and Swift 5.7,
construction of a target's module
is done in a separate emit-module task
directly from all program source files.
This means a target's dependencies
can begin compilation
as soon as the emit-module task
is complete
without waiting for all of the other
compiler tasks of the dependency target.
Being able to unblock downstream
target compilation this much sooner
cuts down on the time spent waiting
for available work with idle CPU cores–
that empty space in between
spurs of activity in the build timeline.
Extending this to the rest of our project
shows that although we are performing
a similar amount of overall work,
the build system is able to use
the computer's resources more efficiently,
often completing
the build significantly faster.
Now, let's take a look at
a second cross-target optimization
the build system can perform
when building Swift–
Eager Linking.
Building on the previous example,
we've added the linker tasks
for each target,
which are both
on the build's critical path.
In this case,
because Target B links Target A,
Target B's link task must wait for
Target A's linked output to be produced
and its own compilation tasks
to complete before it can run.
However, with eager linking,
Target B's link task can depend on
Target A's emit-module task instead.
As a result, Target B can begin
linking earlier in the build,
running in parallel with linking Target A
and shortening the critical path.
How does this work?
Normally,
the dependency graph of two targets
with a linked product dependency
looks something like this.
Linking the dependent target requires
the linked product of its dependencies
in addition to the target's
own compilation outputs.
When linking eagerly,
this dependency is broken,
allowing the dependent target
to start linking earlier.
Instead of depending on a linked
product of the dependency,
it now depends on a text-based
dynamic library stub
produced earlier in the build process
by the emit-module task.
This stub contains a list of symbols
which will appear
in the linked product
for use by dependents.
You can enable this optimization using
the Xcode build setting shown on screen.
Eager Linking applies
to all pure Swift targets
that are dynamically linked
by their dependents.
To summarize, the Xcode Build System
is a sophisticated scheduling engine
that seeks to extract
as much parallelism as possible
by running build phases in parallel.
And features like Script Sandboxing
allow you to ensure your builds
are both maximally parallel and reliable.
Xcode and Swift are more integrated
than ever.
And project structure: its modularization,
the overall shape of the graph
made up of dependencies
between target products
and the number and complexity
of build phases within them,
combined with the available computational
resources of your machine–
all these are contributing factors
to the degree Xcode is able to parallelize
and speed up your builds.
With this knowledge, and powerful
new tools like the build timeline,
you are well equipped to examine your
project and gain insight into your builds.
And if you're curious to learn even more
of the behind-the-scenes
technical details,
many of the technologies we described
that are used by Xcode
are developed in the open-source.
You can find the repository for
Swift Driver on GitHub at the link below.
For more great sessions about Xcode,
check out all new features
and improvements from this year
in "What's new in Xcode".
And learn how Xcode 14's linker
improves link times up to two times
in the session "Link fast:
Improve build and launch times".
Thanks for following along.
We hope you learned some new insights
about Xcode builds.
We can't wait to see
what you're going to create.
Have a great rest of the conference.