♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello, and welcome to
"What's new in WKWebView"
I'm Alex Christensen,
an engineer on the WebKit team.
We've been busy, and we've added
a lot of new web technology
for you to use
in your apps this year.
Before we start, though,
let's make sure you are
using the right technology
for your application.
If you want a browser-like
experience inside your app,
and don't need
deep customization,
you'll definitely want to
use SFSafariViewController.
If your app still uses
the deprecated UIWebView,
now is the time to migrate
to the faster
and more responsive
WKWebView.
UIWebView will be removed
in a future release.
WKWebView is the API to use
to write an application
that interacts with web content.
You could be using it
for CSS-based UI
or writing some of your app
in JavaScript.
You might be interacting
with your own web content
using app-bound domains.
You may also be developing
your own browser.
Whatever your application is,
we are constantly adding
new capabilities
to allow you to make
richer web applications.
The new features available
to WKWebView this year
come in four categories:
new ways to interact
with web content,
new capabilities
for content blockers,
encrypted media,
and use of Remote Web Inspector.
First, we're going
to cover new APIs
for interacting
with web content.
There are three new ways
your app can interact
with web content in iOS 16:
using the full-screen API,
using new CSS viewport units,
and using find interactions.
Let's get started
with full screen.
For many years now,
JavaScript has been able
to make HTML elements,
like videos or canvas games,
full screen in browsers,
and now they can do
that in your apps too.
Here's what a simple example
looks like on a phone.
JavaScript can request
full screen,
then the user or JavaScript
can exit full screen.
All you need to do
in your app
is set WKPreferences
.isElementFullscreenEnabled
to true and load web content
that uses full-screen APIs
like webkitRequestFullscreen.
It works pretty well
out of the box,
but if you'd like to customize
the transitions in your app,
you can observe the value
of WKWebView.fullscreenState,
which will let your app know
when the web content
is becoming full screen
or returning.
And that's all there is to
using WebKit's full-screen APIs
in your app.
We also have new CSS units
to allow web content
to lay out according
to dynamic viewport sizes.
These new CSS units include
svh, lvh, dvh, and many others.
They allow web developers
to modify layout
based on the smallest, largest,
and dynamic viewport sizes.
Let's take a look
at what Safari does
to get an idea of how
this can be used in your app.
When you first open
a page in Safari,
you see the webpage host
and some buttons at the bottom.
As you scroll,
the viewport increases in size
when the buttons slide
out of the way.
Svh, lvh, and dvh
provide useful units
to measure these different
sizes of the viewport.
If your app changes the viewport
of your WKWebView,
then you should inform
WebKit up front
what the viewport
size ranges are.
In Swift, one function call
informs WebKit
of the maximum and minimum
edge insets
to allow this web content
to lay out correctly
in your app.
We are also introducing support
for Find interactions
in WKWebView in iOS 16.
Many WKWebView applications
load lots of text,
and users want
to search this text.
If you set WKWebView
.findInteractionEnabled
to true,
then your users will be able
to use familiar UI
and shortcuts like Command-F
to search the text
on the open page.
That one line of code
is all you need
to turn on the feature,
but you can also access
the UIFindInteraction object
through WKWebView
.findInteraction
to do things like present
and dismiss the Find panel,
or move to the next or previous
results programmatically.
Try it out and see
what it can do in your app.
For content blocking,
we added a new capability
to WKContentRuleList,
the API used to implement
content blockers in Safari.
Here, we have Wikipedia embedded
in an iframe on an example site.
Previously, you could run
regular expressions on the URL
being requested
and the top-frame URL,
to decide whether to block
a load or perform other actions.
Sometimes, though,
what you really wanted
was for a certain rule
to apply only to loads
inside certain iframes.
Now you can run
regular expressions
on the URL of the current frame.
We are going to write a rule
to block images
but only from frames
containing Wikipedia.
To do this,
we add if-frame-url
to the JSON like this.
You then compile the JSON
as you have before
and apply it to
a WKWebViewConfiguration.
The regular expression then runs
on the URL of the frame
that is making the request.
This blocking rule will now only
apply to requests from frames
that match the if-frame-url
regular expression.
Here we see that it has
blocked the image loads
inside the Wikipedia iframe.
If you're serious about
implementing content blockers,
you should check out the WWDC
session about Safari Extensions
which includes some
new possibilities
in declarativeNetRequest.
Another new capability
in WKWebView in iPadOS 16
is encrypted media.
If you have content that uses
the Encrypted Media Extensions
and Media Source
Extensions APIs,
you can now use it
in your apps on iPadOS.
This means that if you have
premium content like AppleTV+,
it will work on iPadOS
like it has in macOS.
If your app has
the web-browser entitlement,
then Remote Web Inspector
will just work
with your production app
like it has on Safari on iOS;
no need to add
or change any code.
To enable Web Inspector
in third-party browsers,
the process is the same
as with Safari.
You'll first need to turn on
Web Inspector
in Safari settings
on the iOS device,
then enable the Develop menu
in Advanced Settings
in Safari on your Mac.
Attach your phone to the Mac
and look for your device
in Safari's Develop menu
on macOS.
Web Inspector has many tools
for debugging web content.
You can explore the DOM,
run and debug
JavaScript execution,
view timelines
of your page-loading, and more.
If you have a website,
you can now inspect
and debug it yourself
in third-party browsers
on iOS,
using Remote Web Inspector.
Those are the main
new API additions
to WKWebView this year.
Try them out and see
what they can do in your apps.
Remember to use the best APIs
for your application,
and if there's something you're
unable to do with WKWebView,
please file a feature request
using Feedback Assistant.
We read the feature requests
we get
and prioritize our development
based on your input.
Don't forget to check out
"What's new in Safari
Web Extensions”,
and for more additions
to the web platform,
remember to check out
"What's new in Safari
and WebKit”.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
♪ ♪