[upbeat music]
- Hello all.
I'm Prashant, and welcome to WWDC.
In 2021, we introduced HLS Interstitials.
They offer a really simple way
to schedule ads and other interstitials
in your HLS streams.
This year, we've added features
that let you better optimize
your ad inventory
and also fine tune your presentation.
So come, let's find out
what's new in HLS Interstitials.
In this talk, we'll start with a quick
overview of how HLS Interstitials work.
And we'll follow that by discussing the
new ad cueing options that we've added.
After that, we'll see how you
can fine tune your ad experience,
especially in live scenarios
using the SNAP attributes.
We'll then go over some
of the new query parameters
that we've added to the HLS specification,
and finally we'll discuss the changes
to the AVFoundation APIs
that incorporate these new features.
But before we dive into the new features,
let's quickly refresh ourselves
with HLS Interstitials.
With HLS Interstitials,
ads are treated as separate assets
that can be scheduled
onto a program timeline.
They need not be stitched in with
discontinuity tags anymore.
Instead, they can be directly referenced
via their multivariant playlist.
This makes it really simple
to schedule ads, as you'd only need to
point to their multivariant playlist
from your primary content.
This is your typical media playlist
that shows a primary content timeline.
Say you want to schedule
two ads during playback.
You'd like for the first ad to appear
some 5 seconds into playback.
For that, you'd simply specify the start
time of the ad using a DATERANGE tag.
And you'd like for the second ad
to appear at 15 seconds.
For that, you'd add another
DATERANGE tag to the playlist.
It's as simple as that.
It could also be that your primary content
has some ads already stitched in.
You can even replace these ads
by specifying a resume offset
that equals the duration
of the stitched-in ad.
Apart from this,
HLS interstitials also lets you
specify navigation restrictions
for your ads,
and you can even schedule early return
in live scenarios,
among other things.
For more information,
you can check out
"Dynamically insert midrolls and prerolls
in HLS" from WWDC 2021.
While you can schedule ads
along the content's timeline,
this year we've added attributes
that force the placement of the ad
to the beginning
or at the end of playback.
For that we've added the following
new cueing options that you can specify
using the CUE attribute.
This attribute can take on one or
a combination of the following values.
A value of PRE would make the ad appear
before the presentation of
the primary content begins.
This is especially useful
in live scenarios
where you'd want to schedule
a premium ad spot
before tuning into the program.
A value of POST would indicate
that the ad should appear
after the presentation
of your primary content.
This might be useful for event streams
where you'd like to schedule end credits,
say, at the conclusion of a live event.
And a value of ONCE would
make the ad appear only once.
So if the user were to seek back
to before the ad,
they would no longer see the ad
play again.
A great application of this
would be for rating screens
which are typically shown just
the one time at the start of playback.
This shows a playlist example
where you have ads scheduled
as pre and post rolls.
Note that the preroll
is scheduled to play only once.
And we also have an ad
scheduled to play once
at some 10 seconds into playback.
Now, scheduling ads in live scenarios
comes with its own set of challenges.
For instance, your packager
might be using one clock
to set the program date time tags
in the playlist
while the encoder
that is producing the media
is driven by a different clock.
Now, these two clocks
need not necessarily be in sync.
For instance, in this example,
the difference in the date time tags
associated with segment 0 and
segment 100 is about 800 seconds.
However, the accumulated media
duration would be slightly less than that
as individual segment durations
are under eight seconds.
In such scenarios
where your packager clock
is slightly faster
than the encoder clock,
the actual mediatime where the ad starts
might fall somewhere inside the slate.
And if you're expected to rejoin
the main content
at an offset that equals
the ad duration as shown here,
you'd actually end up missing some of the
primary content that follows the slate.
You can now use the SNAP attribute
with the OUT value
to snap out of the primary content
at a segment boundary
that is closest
to the intended ad start time.
And similarly use the SNAP attribute
with the IN value
to snap back in the primary content
that is closest to the ad return time.
Note that we expect you to
use the SNAP attributes
only for live scenarios, as this notion of
clock drift shouldn't exist
when dealing with pre-packaged
video on demand content.
Here we see a live playlist where the ad
is scheduled to both snap-out and snap-in.
This year, we've also added
some query parameters
that will help you
optimize your ad inventory
as well as with session management.
Now, when you're tuning into a live stream
in the middle of an ad pod,
you'd be interested to know
how far that ad pod has progressed
so that you can show your most valuable
inventory in the time remaining.
For that, we've added the
HLS_start_offset query parameter.
The HLS_start_offset query parameter
will be supplied with the request
for the interstitials' Asset-list URL.
For live content, this would specify
the offset into the Asset-list
where playback would begin
when joining a live stream,
and for video on demand content,
it would be the offset
into the Asset-list
when seeking into a region
replaced by the interstitial.
In this sample, we have a live playlist
with a 15-second ad
scheduled to start at 5 seconds
from the top of the playlist.
The highlighted segments shown here
would be replaced by the interstitial.
Now during live join,
the client would typically be
some 3 target durations
behind the live edge.
At that point, the 15-second ad pod
that is scheduled
would've played out for 10 seconds.
So this is supplied as part of
the HLS_start_offset query parameter.
Now that the client only
has 5 seconds of ad time remaining,
the server can construct the Asset-list
such that it places its most valuable ads
in the last 5 seconds of that list.
At your server,
you might probably need a way
to track the same playback session
across multiple ad requests
so that you can avoid serving someone
the same ad over and over.
So to associate ad requests
with primary playback sessions,
we've added the
HLS_primary_id query parameter.
If a client sets the playback session
id request header for all http requests
of a particular playback session,
they can then supply this session ID
as part of the HLS_primary_id query
parameter
to the X-Asset-URI
and X-Asset-List requests.
Clients that do not set the session id
request header
should create a unique value
for every primary playback session
and use that as the
HLS_primary_id query parameter
for both primary
and interstitial asset requests.
You might recall that AVFoundation
offers the AVPlayerInterstitialController
and the AVPlayerInterstitialEvent objects
that let you schedule ads
on the client side.
Now we've added support for
the cue and SNAP options
to the AVPlayerInterstitialEvent
object as well.
You can specify the cueing options,
whether you want the ad to be scheduled
as a preroll or a post roll,
via the Cue property.
The play once option that is signaled via
the Cue attribute in the DATERANGE tag
is set as a Boolean
via the willPlayOnce property.
The option to snap out is signaled via
alignsStartWithPrimarySegmentBoundary
property
and to snap in, you'd set the
alignsResumptionWithPrimarySegmentBoundary
property.
As AVPlayerInterstitialEvent
continues to grow,
we figured it might be better to separate
the setting of the properties
from the creation of the object.
So we've now made the
AVPlayerInterstitialEvent object mutable.
You can now create the object
with just the primary item
and start time of the event.
And you can then specify
the different configuration options
by setting the relevant properties.
Note that once the event
is set on the controller,
any subsequent changes to the event object
will not be reflected at the controller,
since the controller
makes a copy of these objects.
For the changes to take effect,
you'd have to set the event
once again on the controller.
To wrap up, you can now schedule
your ads as pre or post rolls
using the X-CUE attribute.
You can also force your ads to play
only once by setting the X-CUE to once.
To manage clock drift in live scenarios,
you'd use the X-SNAP attribute.
For constructing your asset lists
during live join,
you can use
the HLS_start_offset query parameter
and you'd use the HLS_primary_id query
parameter
to relate interstitial requests
with primary playback sessions.
Did you know that if you use
HLS interstitials to schedule ads,
AVFoundation automatically
manages them while in Shareplay?
For more information, check out the
"Display ads and other interstitials
in SharePlay" talk.
That's it for me, folks.
Thank you.