♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Lynn,
a design producer
for Siri and Shortcuts.
And today, I'm going
to tell you a bit more
about the new App Intents
framework
and how you can use it
to design great App Shortcuts.
Here at Apple, we know
that people love using Siri
and Spotlight to accelerate
common tasks across devices,
like this.
Remind me to buy garlic.
Set a timer for 20 minutes.
These habitual tasks
can be easily completed
outside their respective apps,
and making them available
via Siri and Spotlight
gives people flexibility
in how they interact
with their device
and how they get things done.
Shortcuts are how you can offer
people that same flexibility
to accomplish key tasks
from your app throughout the OS.
And all shortcuts begin
with a fundamental component
called actions, which
represent an individual task
that people can complete
with your app,
such as creating a reminder
or sending a message.
This foundation can be used
in a couple different ways.
First, for custom shortcuts,
which people can create
using one or more actions
from apps;
that is, your app and others.
Or an action can be used
to create an App Shortcut,
created by
app developers like you,
containing one action
from your app.
And while in the past,
people needed to find and tap
the Add to Siri button
to enable each new app shortcut
you created,
now, with iOS 16,
the App Shortcuts
you create for your app
will be automatically available
as soon as your app is installed.
That means they'll be
available in Siri,
visible in Spotlight,
and featured
in the Shortcuts app,
making it easier than ever
for people to access
their favorite features
from your app throughout the OS.
Today I'm going to walk through
a few different areas
to help you create
unforgettable App Shortcuts.
I'll start with how to select
the right features
from your app
to turn into shortcuts,
and how to name them.
Then, I'll walk through
some best practices
for presenting your visuals
and for collecting
required information.
And finally, I'll let you know
how you can tell people
about your new shortcuts.
So let's jump in.
Now your app
has a wide range of features.
But we know that some things
lend themselves
better than others
to becoming great shortcuts.
So what should you look for?
Think about the features
people love in your app,
and then focus on tasks
that are self-contained,
meaning they can be completed
outside your app;
and straightforward,
in that they're efficient
to get through.
To give these principles
a bit more context,
let's take a look at
a sample meditation app.
We'll just call it "Meditation."
Now a great
App Shortcut is one
that actually doesn't require
your app in focus at all.
You're looking for a lightweight
task that can be completed
via Siri or via search
in its entirety.
For our new Meditation app,
that'd be something like this.
Start sleep meditation.
Voiceover: Take a deep breath,
close your eyes,
and leave the day behind.
It's easy to kick this off
without opening the app,
and it just starts playing.
You also want to make sure
the shortcuts you author
are straightforward.
They should feel effortless
to get through.
Tasks that require a lot
of input may be too tedious
and time-consuming
for a shortcut.
For example, a lengthy,
multistep survey like this one
wouldn't be appropriate
for an App Shortcut.
Instead, focus on
uncomplicated tasks
that people can succeed
at quickly,
and that they can remember even
when they're not using your app,
like this.
So the best features from
your app to turn into shortcuts
are self-contained
and straightforward.
They can be completed
without the app in focus
and are uncomplicated
to get through.
And all in all, there may not
be so many of these.
The maximum you can create
is 10, but in most cases,
the key features of your app
can be captured
in two to five
high-quality app shortcuts,
and we strongly recommend
keeping your set
as focused as possible.
Now, as important
as selecting the right features
to become app shortcuts,
is authoring a great phrase
to name them.
This name is really the hero
phrase for your shortcut.
It appears in the Shortcuts app
under your app's header,
it's how your shortcut will be
referenced in Spotlight
and it's what people will say
to Siri to invoke your shortcut.
So where to start?
The first important thing
to remember
when you're crafting that hero
phrase is to keep it brief.
You want your
app shortcut phrase
to be easy to remember
and to clearly communicate
its function.
As a requirement, you'll need
to include your app name.
But you can be
creative about it!
See if you can incorporate
your app name
directly into
the invocation phrase,
like here with Voice Memo
or here with Panera.
And the app name in this phrase
can be your official app name
or any of the alternative names
you submitted to the App Store.
In this case, Panera Bread
is the official app name,
but the Panera synonym feels
more natural in the phrase.
And here's how that could look
with our app, Meditation.
Let's dig a little deeper
with the Voice Memo example.
I'll turn on my transcriptions
so we can see my speech.
Remember that the name
you choose for your App Shortcut
is also what people will say to
Siri to invoke it, and you need
to provide thoughtful
natural language variations
to ensure it works
for whatever similar phrases
people might say.
For example, for this shortcut,
named Record Voice Memo,
I would need
to explicitly specify
"Start Voice Memo"
and "New Voice Memo"
as synonyms,
otherwise they won't work.
Be sufficiently thorough here.
You want to try to capture
all the alternative phrases
people might say.
But -- and this is
a bit of a judgment call --
make sure you're not straying
too far from the core purpose
of your shortcut
and entering into a new meaning
with these phrases.
In this case, the intent is
truly to create not to save.
And remember, you will have
to go through this exercise
of providing thorough synonyms
for every language
that your app is published
to ensure a robust experience
around the world.
So I've talked about
the importance
of keeping your app shortcut
name brief and memorable,
creative strategies
for incorporating your app name,
and the value of generating
thorough synonyms
and translating those synonyms
to other languages.
The last thing
I want to talk about
when it comes
to naming your shortcut
is how and when to use
a dynamic parameter.
You can now use
a dynamic parameter
directly in the name
of your shortcut
to create multiple variations
on the phrase
that people can say to Siri
or see in Spotlight.
Let's take a look at an example.
So for our Meditation app,
the dynamic parameter
could be different types
of meditation.
And you can see how
this provides the flexibility
to directly ask
for those different types.
But there are a couple things
to note about this parameter.
First, you can only have
one dynamic parameter
in your phrase,
and it can only be used
to select from a finite list.
You want to make sure
that other values in the list
are predictable since people
won't have this list of options
in front of them for reference.
This is a good example because
people are likely familiar
with the different meditation
types from using the app,
and it's also a small list.
Other good examples
might be recent restaurants
that are front of mind or
different rooms in the home.
A bad example would be
something with infinite options,
like a time value.
You don't want to use
a dynamic parameter here,
but instead, prompt
for additional information
as needed.
I'll talk more
about that in a bit.
Last thing to note
is that this list
of possible parameter values
can be updated any time
your app is open,
so you can ensure
it consistently contains
up-to-date and relevant values.
Now, each parameter value,
in combination
with the App Intent,
creates a unique variant
of your app shortcut.
So for starting a meditation,
you'd have this
unparameterized version
and each parameterized version,
like Start Sleep Meditation,
Start Gratitude Meditation,
and all the others.
These are automatically
generated
and displayed in the Shortcuts
app, as you see here,
and shown as individual rows
in Spotlight.
These parameters are also
visible in the Shortcuts editor
when you provide a parameter
summary for your action.
When someone taps
on the parameter,
your options will appear
in a menu like this.
To learn more about actions
and how they appear
in the Shortcuts editor,
check out this talk from last
year on designing great actions
for Shortcuts, Siri,
and Suggestions.
The last important consideration
when it comes
to including a dynamic parameter
is making sure it's clear
which part of the phrase
is a parameter.
As I mentioned, you can only
have one dynamic parameter
per app shortcut, but if you had
this as your app shortcut,
the second part of
the phrase -- "nature sounds" --
seems like a second parameter
that can be changed.
This could make people
think they can say
"gratitude meditation
with ocean sounds,"
when in fact, only
the first part of the phrase
can be changed.
The solution here
is to keep it simple.
If it feels too complicated
when you say it aloud,
it probably is.
And if that additional
information
is absolutely required,
you can ask for it
in a subsequent step,
and I'll provide some tips
on how to do that later.
Looking back at everything
I mentioned
about selecting features,
naming your shortcut,
and using dynamic parameters,
one theme stands out,
and that's to make it memorable.
Within your app,
people can explore,
get drawn into features,
and learn new flows.
But with shortcuts,
your main goal is to create
a few focused experiences
that people can quickly learn,
remember,
and grow to depend on.
Now let's take a look at
some visual considerations
for your app shortcuts.
Custom Snippets
and Live Activities
provide you with an opportunity
to present information,
request clarifications,
and surface your app identity,
and I want to share some tips
for making them as beautiful
and effective as possible.
Unlike most of your apps that
likely use opaque backgrounds,
snippets use
a semitranslucent material.
Place elements from your app
on top of this material
instead of filling the visual
with an opaque background.
You can see an example here,
with elements
from the Weather app
integrating seamlessly
into the Siri snippet.
And when you draw your text,
use vibrant label colors
to guarantee great contrast
over the translucent background.
Doing this ensures
that your text
will automatically look great
in Dark Mode too.
Now there are two ways
to show results in iOS 16:
Live Activities
and Custom Snippets.
If you're not sure
which one to use,
think about whether
people would benefit
from continuous access
to this information,
such as transit progress
for a food order
or a timer counting down.
If so, use a Live Activity.
This will make the content
continuously glanceable,
even on the Lock Screen,
until the event has ended.
If not, and the shortcut
is a self-contained action
or piece of information,
use a Custom Snippet.
Let's take a closer look
at the iOS snippet
and a couple
of the key elements it contains.
Here, you see
the supporting dialog.
This is what Siri speaks
and is intended to accompany
your custom visual.
Together, they communicate
all the necessary information
for this step of the shortcut.
Now by default, your custom
visual will consistently appear
with supporting dialog.
But in this example, you can
see that the supporting dialog
is fully redundant
with your visual response.
When that's the case,
you should suppress this dialog
in your source code
so that it won't be shown.
But the presentation of your
information goes beyond iOS,
and you'll need to think about
other devices in the ecosystem
as well.
For voice-only products,
like AirPods,
Siri will read out
the full dialog you provide.
For these platforms,
it's important
that your full dialog contain
all the critical information
from both your custom visual
and any supporting dialog.
Be sure to provide
both types of dialog,
so that people have access
to all the information they need
regardless of which device
they choose
to interact with your shortcut.
And for the first time,
Apple Watch now supports
Custom Snippets as well.
This means you should take
a look at your shortcuts
in watchOS 9
and make sure they look great
on that platform as well.
And know that this may
require you to make changes
to your layout.
Here you can see
how the Coffee app
repositioned the address line
on watchOS
to fall beneath the header
to help with readability.
Just to recap
these first few visual tips.
I walked through how
to integrate elements
from your app into
the translucent background,
the importance of using
vibrant label colors,
the appropriate time to use
snippets versus live activities,
and how to adapt
your dialog and visuals
for different platforms
and contexts.
Now, let's talk about Spotlight.
In iOS 16, your app's shortcuts
will also appear in Spotlight.
If someone searches for your
app name, one app shortcut --
the first one in
your App Shortcuts array --
will appear as a Siri Suggestion
below your app as a top hit.
They can also search directly
for the name of the shortcut,
and any app shortcut
that matches the search term
will appear.
Finally, if your app
is a Siri Suggestion
when someone
first launches Spotlight,
your top shortcut
will also appear here,
even before anything has been
typed into the search field.
This is all really exciting,
because it provides
an opportunity for people
to learn about your shortcuts
just by looking for your app
or by using their phone.
You'll also notice
that each unique app shortcut
is decorated with a symbol
on the right side.
Be sure to review
the SF Symbols library
and select one for each
of your app shortcuts
that accurately reflects
its intent.
Also, know that the order of
your actions and your parameters
will influence the order
your app shortcuts appear
in Spotlight.
Actions can only be reordered
with app updates,
but as I mentioned earlier,
the order of your parameters
is truly dynamic
and can be updated
any time your app is open.
This in turn impacts
how your shortcuts are shown.
Here, you see that
Reorder Coffee App Cappuccino
is first in the Shortcuts app
and takes the single slot
in Spotlight.
But maybe this customer ordered
a chai latte more recently,
and you want that to be
your suggestion in Spotlight.
You can make it the first item
returned by your entity query
or dynamic options provider,
and it will become first
in the Shortcuts app
and in Spotlight.
And as the number
of parameters increases,
this prioritization may become
even more important.
But be sure to pick
a meaningful heuristic --
such as recency or frequency --
to drive the order,
so that it doesn't feel
random or unpredictable.
And one last thing --
pick a color for your shortcuts
in the Shortcuts app.
We have a bunch of great colors
for you to choose from,
and all your shortcuts will use
this color in the app.
So pick one that complements
your app icon nicely
and don't just stick
with the default.
Now, as quick and contained
as your shortcuts aspire to be,
there may still be times
when you need
to collect some information
in order to see a task though.
I'm going to walk through
a few different ways to do that
and when to use each one.
Take a phrase like this one that
doesn't contain a parameter.
Sometimes, you can make
an informed decision
and assume a value and
then proceed with the action.
One example here
might be starting a meditation
that was already in progress.
But other times, in the face
of an ambiguous request,
you'll need to ask
for more information.
When possible, try to make
a meaningful assumption
and present it as an option
for people to confirm.
This is called
a Parameter Confirmation.
These assumptions could be based
on remembering a prior selection
or based on something
like the most popular option.
Parameter Confirmations
are a nice, efficient way
to be sure you have the detail
you need and continue on.
But let's say the person has
never gone through this shortcut
before and you don't have
a single parameter to offer.
Another option is
to provide a short list.
This is called a disambiguation
and helps people
that are unfamiliar
with the shortcut
learn the possible values.
Just keep in mind
that this is best for lists
of five values or less,
because in voice-only
modalities, such as AirPods,
Siri will read
this entire list aloud.
What kind of meditation?
Focus, Gratitude, Walking,
Compassion, or Sleep?
Sometimes, you need
to collect an open-ended value
that isn't compatible
with a short list,
like a number, a location,
or a string.
In these situations, you can
use an open-ended request.
This has the fewest
guardrails though,
since there are
no suggested values
and people can say
anything in response,
so make sure it's clear
what type of information
your app is expecting.
In this case,
it's apparent that the response
should be a time value.
The App Intent framework does
provide a set of common options
for these open-ended requests,
such as numerical values,
dates, or time values.
If your required parameter
aligns with one of these,
definitely select it.
This will allow you to benefit
from certain built-in dialog
and visual patterns,
as well as Siri's natural
language understanding
as it pertains to these types
of information.
If not, you can use
a custom entity.
For more information on how
to implement app entities,
check out this year's talk
called "Dive into App Intents."
Lastly, even if you have all
the information you require,
you may still want to do
one final confirmation --
what we call
an "intent confirmation" --
before proceeding
with your shortcut.
The guidance here is
to only use this step
for consequential actions,
be it a financial transaction,
a destructive action
like deleting content,
or an action that may
just feel high risk,
like sending a calendar invite
to a big group.
Use these appropriately
but sparingly,
as the goal of getting through a
shortcut as quickly as possible
always applies.
One last detail
on intent confirmations
is that they will always have a
pair of buttons in the snippet,
offering to either
proceed with -- or cancel --
the proposed action.
When confirming an intent,
buttons should contain a verb
reiterating the action
that is about to be taken
and not ambiguous words
like "confirm."
The App Intents framework
provides a really helpful set
of default verbs
with corresponding synonyms.
You can see
a few examples here.
If your intent maps to one
of these, go ahead and use it.
If you have a specific intent
that falls outside this group,
you can provide
a custom string instead
but be sure to provide
synonyms as well
so that Siri understands
all the similar phrases.
Last but not least,
once you've created
an awesome set of app shortcuts,
there are a few places
to surface them
for people to discover.
First, in place of the old
Add to Siri button
is a new tip for you
to feature in your app.
It's important that
you carefully select moments
within your app to surface
these tips, at a time
when people are likely
to benefit from the education,
such as immediately before
or after completing an action
that they may want to repeat
in the future.
And where appropriate,
make your tip dismissible.
Respect people's desire to
remove this helpful information
from their workflow.
We've also provided a button
that you can place in your app
to link to the Shortcuts app
directly to the landing page
that lists all
your app shortcuts.
It's an exciting year
for shortcuts,
with the introduction
of App Shortcuts,
created by you,
and seamlessly available
in Siri, Shortcuts,
and Spotlight.
With dynamic parameters
in the invocation phrase,
Custom Snippets on watchOS,
new tips, and more,
there's a lot to explore.
And with all the info
I walked through today
on selecting and naming
great app shortcuts,
refining your presentation
and flow,
and including tips
for discoverability,
you're well on your way
to an amazing
App Shortcuts experience.
We can't wait to see
what you create,
and have a great
rest of WWDC.
♪