♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Lais Minchillo:
Hi, my name is Lais.
David Silver: And I'm David.
And we will be presenting
this year's new features
in Wallet and Apple Pay.
We launched Apple Pay in 2014,
setting a new benchmark
for making fast, secure,
and private payments
in store, online and in-app.
Since then, we've expanded
Apple Pay across the globe.
Apple Pay is now available
in 72 countries and territories
and handles more than a million
transactions every day.
Today we're introducing exciting
new features and APIs
into Wallet and Apple Pay.
Lais will tell you more.
Lais: Thank you, David!
Let's take a look
at the main agenda for today.
First, we'll talk about
some quick updates.
We are adding support for
payments to multiple merchants
in a single transaction.
We are also greatly improving
support for automatic payments,
including subscriptions,
With order tracking,
you can enhance
the postpurchase experience
for your customers.
And finally, David will
talk about identity verification
with IDs in Wallet.
We have a few
exciting updates to share.
Tap to Pay on iPhone
was announced earlier this year
and launched
in iOS 15.4 in the US.
Tap to Pay on iPhone
provides a secure, private,
and easy way to accept
contactless payments.
You can easily integrate
this into your app
to seamlessly and securely
accept contactless payments.
This includes Apple Pay,
contactless credit
and debit cards,
and other digital wallets.
The transaction is completed
through a simple tap
to the iPhone,
removing the need
for additional hardware
or payment terminals.
Meanwhile, in macOS 13,
we redesigned
the Apple Pay experience.
The iOS payment sheet
redesign last year
was a great success
and this year we're bringing
a similar experience to macOS.
We used SwiftUI
to implement this,
which helped us
bring new features to macOS
at the same time as iOS.
All of the Apple Pay features
we are introducing today
are also supported on Mac.
We're introducing
new SwiftUI APIs.
Integrating Add to Apple Wallet
or Apple Pay buttons
in your SwiftUI app
will be much easier.
These new APIs will
significantly reduce
the amount of code
you need to write.
Let's take a look at
how you can add a button
to prompt the user
to add an airline pass.
First, create the pass.
You should handle the case where
it wasn't successfully loaded.
This could happen
if the pass data is malformed
or if it was not properly
signed, for example.
Next, call AddPassToWalletButton
with an array of passes.
In this example, we have
an array with only one element,
but you can have multiple passes
on the same button.
The result is passed
in as a Bool, and you can save,
log, or trigger other actions
in your app
based on whether the user
has added a pass or not.
In this example,
I'm saving that to a state var.
And that's it!
You can also customize
the button's size and style
within a set of minimum values.
This is the default size:
width 250 and height 50.
You could also make it
wider...
...or taller.
This wraps up how you can add
an Add to Apple Wallet button
in SwiftUI.
Now, let's see how you can add
a Pay with Apple Pay button.
First, create a payment request
using the PKPaymentRequest
class,
setting your usual
configuration on it.
Then, create an
authorizationChange method.
Now that we have
these two pieces ready,
let's add code
to show the button.
Add a call to
PayWithApplePayButton,
passing in the label,
the paymentRequest object,
and the authorizationChange
method.
To handle cases where
Apple Pay isn't supported
by the current device,
you can pass in a fallback view.
Just like the Add Pass button,
you can also customize
its size and style.
In total,
there are 17 different labels,
so you are able to customize
the pay button
to align with your use case.
These are available on iOS,
iPadOS, macOS, and watchOS.
Now, let's take a look
at multimerchant payments.
In iOS 16, we're introducing
the ability to request
multiple payment tokens
for different merchants
in the same transaction.
This is useful for things
like online marketplaces,
travel bookings,
and ticketing services.
Let's take a closer look
at an example.
Imagine Allison
is planning a trip.
She goes to a travel
agency's website
and they conveniently offer her
all of the things
she needs to book --
flight tickets, a hotel stay,
and a car rental.
Allison just needs to pay
a total of $500 dollars.
Allison provides
the travel agency
her full credit card
information.
Now, you might imagine
that the travel agency
will charge Allison's
credit card $500 dollars,
and then pay
the other companies involved.
But what typically happens
is the travel agency
simply passes along
the credit card information
to each company to make
their individual charges.
This works,
but it's not great
for Allison's
privacy and security
to have her credit card
information shared around.
Now, with the new
multimerchant payment API,
it's possible to request
a payment token
for each merchant involved
in a transaction.
Using these payment tokens,
the multiple companies involved
can each charge Allison
for the relevant amount
she authorized.
Allison can now book
and pay for her trip
while taking advantage of the
privacy and security benefits
that Apple Pay offers.
The payment sheet has been
updated to show customers
a breakdown of the submerchants
involved in a transaction.
Customers can tap
on the total field
to navigate
to the payment summary.
Here, the customer
can see a breakdown
of all the merchants involved
in the transaction,
along with the amount authorized
for each one.
Now, let's look
at how you can add
multimerchant payments
to your app.
First, create a payment request
using the PKPaymentRequest
class,
setting your usual
configuration on it.
Then add summary items for your
payment, including the total.
Next, create
a payment token context
for each additional merchant
involved in the transaction,
using the new
PKPaymentTokenContext class.
Provide details
for each merchant,
as well as the amount
to authorize for each.
Finally, set the payment token
contexts on the payment request.
Keep in mind that the sum
of the amounts
for all of your
payment token contexts
must be less than or equal
to the total amount
of the payment request itself.
Also, you should always use
the same external identifier
for the same merchant any time
you request a payment token
for that merchant in your app.
For adopting
multi-merchant payments
with Apple Pay on the web,
check out the Apple Pay JS API
documentation.
Now, let's take a look
at our improvements
to automatic payments.
In iOS 16, we're introducing
the ability for people to view
and manage automatic payments
they've set up with merchants,
right from the Wallet app.
In this release,
we're supporting two types
of automatic payments:
recurring payments,
which includes things like
subscriptions, installments,
or recurring billing;
and automatic reload payments,
such as store card
balance top-ups.
We're introducing new APIs
to allow you to request
to set up an automatic payment
when you make a payment request.
We're also introducing
Apple Pay merchant tokens,
a new kind of payment token
tied to a customer's Apple ID,
which can help you more reliably
charge your customers
on an ongoing basis.
Let's take a closer look
at Apple Pay merchant tokens
to see how
they can be useful.
Imagine Julie is paying
for a book club membership
using Apple Pay on her iPhone.
The book club makes
a payment request,
and when Julie authorizes
the payment,
the book club receives
a payment token,
and every month they can
use that to charge Julie
her membership fee.
This payment token is linked
to the device Julie used
to authorize the payment.
But what happens if Julie
gets a new iPhone?
With the new
automatic payments feature,
the book club
will instead receive
an Apple Pay merchant token,
if Julie's payment network
supports it.
This payment token is tied
to Julie's Apple ID,
rather than to her iPhone,
which provides better assurances
for ongoing authorizations.
This means that if Julie
upgrades her iPhone,
or resets her current phone,
the book club can continue
to reliably charge Julie
her monthly membership fee.
If you accept Apple Pay
for these types of payments,
it's a great idea to adopt
automatic payments to ensure
you can continue reliably
charging your customers,
as well as avoid any
interruption to their services.
The first type of automatic
payment we're supporting
in this release
is recurring payments.
Recurring payments have
a fixed or variable amount
that is charged on
a regular schedule,
such as weekly,
monthly, or annually.
These payments can end
on a certain date
or they can be ongoing
until canceled.
A trial or introductory period
is also supported.
Subscriptions,
installment plans,
and regular billing
are perfect uses
for this type of payment.
Let's take a look at how you can
set up a recurring payment
in your app using
automatic payments.
Start by specifying
the amount and duration
of the recurring payment,
using the
PKRecurringPaymentSummaryItem
class.
For recurring payments,
you can specify
both a regular billing period
as well as an introductory
or trial period.
You can use the startDate
and endDate properties
to indicate when
the trial period ends
and the regular billing period
starts.
Next, create a
recurringPaymentRequest
using the new
PKRecurringPaymentRequest class.
Provide a description
of the payment,
the regular billing period,
as well as a managementURL
to a web page
where the customer can update
or delete the payment method
for the recurring payment.
You can also optionally
provide a trial billing period
as well as
billingAgreement text
to help explain the terms
of the payment to the customer.
Finally, you can optionally
provide a tokenNotificationURL
where your server can receive
life cycle notifications
about the Apple Pay
merchant token for the payment,
if one was issued.
For example,
you can receive notifications
if the card issuer or the user
deletes the token.
For more information
about merchant token
life cycle notifications,
see the Apple Pay Merchant Token
Management API documentation.
Finally, set the
recurringPaymentRequest
on the paymentRequest object.
A quick note on summary items,
your recurring payment
will not be added to the payment
request's summary items
automatically.
So be sure to add items for it
to the summary items array.
The total for
the payment request
should be the first amount
that the customer
will be charged.
So in this example,
the total is set to display
the trial period amount,
as that's the first amount
the customer will be charged.
The payment sheet
will show details
of your recurring payment
to customers,
and they can tap
on the Billing Details section
to read further.
Now, let's take a look at the
second type of automatic payment
we're supporting
in this release:
automatic reload payments.
With this type of payment,
a balance is
automatically topped up
with a fixed amount whenever
the balance drops below
a certain threshold amount.
Automatic reload payments
are perfect for things like
store card top-ups
and prepaid balances.
To request to set up
an automatic reload payment,
start by specifying the reload
and threshold amounts,
using the new PKAutomatic
ReloadPaymentSummaryItem class.
Next, create an
automaticReloadPaymentRequest
using the new PKAutomatic
ReloadPaymentRequest class,
passing in a description
of the payment, the billing,
and a management URL,
just like for
recurring payments.
You can also optionally
provide billing agreement text
and a token notification URL.
Finally, set the automatic
reload payment request
on the payment request object.
Again, be sure to include
your automatic reload payment
in the summary items
and set the total of the
paymentRequest appropriately.
For adopting automatic payments
with Apple Pay on the web,
check out the Apple Pay JS API
documentation.
Here's how the automatic reload
payment appears
in the payment sheet
for your customers.
Finally, here's
a few things to remember
to help give your customers
the best possible experience
when you adopt
automatic payments in your app.
Remember to include
summary items
for your automatic payment
as these are not added for you.
The total amount of your
payment request should be
the first amount
the customer will be charged.
You should keep the billing
agreement text short.
The payment sheet will only show
the first 500 characters.
The billing agreement text
is not intended to replace
your normal billing
and legal agreements.
It's up to you to be compliant
with your local
recurring billing laws.
If you have a legal agreement
to show the customer,
that might mean
displaying it to the customer
before you present
the payment sheet.
You can only request
one type of automatic payment
in a single transaction.
Also, automatic payments
cannot be used
with multi-merchant payments.
Finally, if you want to receive
life cycle notifications
for the Apple Pay merchant token
issued for the payment,
be sure to provide
a token notification URL
and adopt the Apple Pay Merchant
Token Management API
on your server.
We think you'll love
these new APIs
and the benefits
of Apple Pay merchant tokens.
Here are just a few
of our partners
that will also be adopting
support for automatic payments.
Apple Pay merchant tokens
will be supported by
American Express, Discover,
Mastercard, and Visa,
with support for other payment
networks in the future.
We are excited to introduce
Order Tracking
to enhance the postpurchase
experience.
New in iOS 16, order tracking
allows users to track orders
placed with participating
merchants.
Wallet now provides
an intuitive overview
of active orders,
recently completed orders,
and past orders.
I currently have a single active
order for some bakery goods.
My order is still in processing;
I'll get back to that later.
For now, I want to buy some toys
and accessories for my cat
from Pet Avenue.
I choose to check out
with Apple Pay.
Shortly after
I authorize the payment,
I receive a notification
to track my order in Wallet.
Interacting with
that notification
takes me to the details
of my order
where I can check
the current status.
I can see the order status,
including shipping
and tracking information,
and the list of line items
I have ordered.
Further below, I have multiple
options to contact Pet Avenue,
check the payment information,
and go back to Pet Avenue's app.
Now, imagine
Pet Avenue is really fast
in processing incoming orders
and they just shipped my items.
As soon as Pet Avenue
shipped my order,
they have updated
the available information.
I can see the status changed
to "On the Way,"
with an estimated delivery date
of June 10th.
They also included
a custom message
and tracking information
for the shipment.
Oh, remember my baking goods?
I just got a notification
that they are ready for pickup.
Let's check it out.
I have ordered
my bakery goods for pick up.
They are ready for pick up,
that's great!
Bake My Breath Away
has provided my pickup window,
pickup instructions,
and a barcode
to present upon arrival.
We've seen that order tracking
works seamlessly with Apple Pay.
Let's have a look at how
you can integrate order tracking
into your customer experience.
To get started
with order tracking,
first, you must create
an Order Type ID
in your developer account.
An Order Type ID identifies
your organization as an entity
that provides order information.
You can register
multiple Order Type IDs --
for example,
to provide order information
on behalf of multiple merchants.
Also create an Order Type ID
Certificate.
You will use the certificate
to build order packages
and update orders.
Orders are distributed
as order packages.
An order package includes
all the metadata and information
for an order.
It can represent
a wide range of scenarios,
including shipping, pickup,
and multifulfillment orders.
An order package
also includes images,
like your logo
and line item images.
You can also add localizations
to support your diverse
range of customers.
Every order package must be
cryptographically signed
to verify its origin.
Once everything is in place,
order packages are compressed
for distribution.
Check out
the sample order packages
attached to this session.
And for more information
on order packages,
see the developer
documentation.
Adding an order to Wallet
works seamlessly with Apple Pay.
When your customer
authorized a payment,
your app or web page
receives payment information,
then sends it to your server
for processing.
If processing the payment
information succeeds,
your server creates an order
and some metadata.
Your server then returns details
about that order
to your app or web page
to include in the result.
The order details enable the
device to asynchronously request
the order from your server.
Your server then returns
the order package to the device.
When your server
creates an order,
assign an Order ID
that is unique
within the namespace
of your Order Type ID.
Your server must also generate
a secure authentication token.
This is a shared secret that is
part of the order details.
The device will use the token
to authenticate itself
when it requests the order.
Let's take a look at an example
for returning a payment
authorization result.
When your customer
authorized a payment,
your app sends the payment
information to your server
and asks it to create an order.
Check whether the server
result indicates success
and handle any error
returned by your server.
If the server result
does indicate success,
complete the payment
with an appropriate
authorization result.
To return a payment
authorization result
with order details,
first, extract them
from the server result.
Then create a
PKPaymentOrderDetails object
with the Order Ttype ID,
Order ID,
the URL to your server,
and the authenticationToken.
Assign the PKPaymentOrderDetails
object
to the new orderDetails property
on PKPaymentAuthorizationResult.
That's it!
You can complete a payment with
order details on the web too.
As before, extract the order
details from the server result.
Then include the order details
in the data you complete
the payment with.
To be able to update an order,
create an order package
that indicates support
for automatic updates.
When the order is added,
the device will register
for updates to it.
Your server must store
information about registrations.
Later on, when your server
updates the order,
use the registration information
to notify devices
that registered for updates
to it.
When the device receives
the push notification,
it will again request the order
from your server.
Your server then returns
the updated order package
to the device.
Only your customers and you
should know
what they have ordered.
We designed order tracking
with privacy in mind.
Order information
is exchanged directly
between devices and your server.
When orders are synchronized
via iCloud,
they are end-to-end encrypted.
Follow these practices
to provide
the best customer
experience possible.
Associate your app
with orders that you provide.
If your app delivers
notifications and is installed,
you can disable order tracking
notifications.
This helps to prevent
duplicate notifications.
Use the knowledge you have
about your customer preferences
to provide relevant
localizations only.
Be mindful of
the order package size.
Try to keep the size small
to reduce expensive
networking cost.
When you update an order,
promptly notify devices that
registered for updates to it.
Orders in Wallet should match
the actual state of the order.
Make sure to also check out
the HIG for order tracking.
Platforms can make your
integration of order tracking
much simpler.
We are happy to announce
Shopify, Narvar, and Route
will support order tracking
by fall.
Look out for more platforms
supporting order tracking
in the coming months.
Order tracking is
a great way to enhance
the postpurchase experience
for your customers.
With automatic updates,
your customers
will always be up to date
about the status
of their orders.
We believe your customers
will love this experience
and we look forward
to ordering with you soon!
Now, I'll pass over to David.
David: Thanks, Lais!
I'm super excited to talk about
the new functionality
we've added to IDs in Wallet
in iOS 16.
We launched IDs in Wallet
earlier this year in iOS 15.4.
It allows users
in supported US states
to add their driver's license
or State ID to Wallet.
IDs in Wallet are issued
by the same issuing authorities
as users' physical IDs.
in the US, that's their State's
Department of Motor Vehicles
or equivalent organization.
In iOS 16, we've added
a new API that allows apps
and App Clips to request
information from IDs in Wallet
in order to verify
a user's age or identity.
Your app will request
the information,
the user will review
and approve the request,
Then your app will send
the response to your server
for decryption and verification.
You can request
a number of data elements
from the user's ID.
These include their name,
their address,
their date of birth,
their photo --
known as the portrait --
the issuing authority
that issued their ID,
the number and expiration
date of their physical ID,
and the driving privileges
granted by their ID,
if there are any.
A very common use case for IDs
is to verify someone's age.
With a physical ID, that means
looking at their date of birth.
But the date of birth reveals
far more information
than is necessary
just to verify age.
If you're checking my age,
you don't actually need to know
the exact day or year
I was born,
or even how old I am.
You just need to know
if I'm old enough.
With IDs in Wallet, you can ask
that question directly.
Your app can request
a Boolean data element
indicating whether the user
is above a certain age,
providing a more
privacy-preserving way
to do age verification than
checking the full date of birth.
When your app invokes the API,
a sheet will show the user
what information
you're requesting.
It will also show
whether you intend
to store that information,
and for how long
you intend to store it.
This lets the user make
an informed decision
about whether to share
the information with your app.
No information is shared
until they give
their explicit approval
using Face ID or Touch ID.
The response you receive
contains just the elements
you requested.
Other identity verification
mechanisms,
such as scanning
a physical ID card,
share everything
that's on the ID.
By limiting the sharing
to just what you need,
IDs in Wallet is more
privacy-preserving for the user
and reduces the amount
of sensitive information
you need to keep secure
on your server.
The response is signed
by the ID's issuing authority,
making it straightforward
to verify
that the information
in the response is authentic.
Note that the issuing authority
creates the ID
but is not involved
at the time you invoke the API.
They do not learn when users
share their information
or to whom they share it with.
To use the API, you need
to request an entitlement
through your developer account.
You'll then need to set up
a merchant ID
and encryption certificate.
This process is very similar
to setting up in-app payment
with Apple Pay.
We'll talk more about how to use
the ID and certificate in a little bit.
For now, let's talk about
the verification flow.
At a high level,
it consists of four steps.
First, your app will invoke the
API in the PassKit framework
and specify the information
you're requesting.
The system will then display
a sheet
prompting the user
to approve the request.
Once they do,
your app will receive
an encrypted response.
Your app will then pass
that response to your server
for decryption and verification.
First, let's talk about
how to use the API in PassKit.
If your app uses SwiftUI,
you should use the
VerifyIdentityWithWalletButton
SwiftUI view.
This displays a button
that triggers
the identity verification
flow when pressed.
Just like the Pay with Apple Pay
and Add Pass to Wallet buttons,
the Verify Identity with Wallet
button provides a familiar,
consistent experience
across apps using the API.
You can choose between
four different labels
to display a button
that fits your use case.
It automatically switches
between single
and multiline versions depending
on the space available to it.
When creating the button,
you need to specify
a PKIdentityRequest object,
which describes the information
you want to request
and how it should be returned.
Let's take a look
at how to create it.
You begin by creating a
PKIdentityDrivers
LicenseDescriptor,
which describes
the data elements
that you're looking for.
Use the addElements method
to specify elements
you want to request,
along with whether you intend
to store them.
You can invoke the addElements
method multiple times
to specify different
sets of elements
with different intents to store.
In this example,
I'm calling it twice.
First, I add an
age(atLeast: element,
which is not going to be stored.
Then, I call the addElements
method again to request
the user's givenName,
familyName, and portrait,
all of which may be stored
for up to 30 days.
The descriptor then goes
into a PKIdentityRequest.
The next step is to specify
a merchantIdentifier to use.
The merchantIdentifier
indicates
the encryption certificate
to which the API response
will be encrypted.
You'll configure both
the merchantIdentifier
and its encryption certificate
through your developer account.
Finally, you'll need
to specify a nonce,
which will be tied
to the response you receive
from the API.
Its an important
security feature
used to prevent replays
of a response
and to bind it
to a specific user session.
Exactly how you manage the nonce
is up to you,
based on your own
security requirements.
Often, it comes from
your server, because later on,
your server will be
responsible for enforcing
that the nonce is valid.
With all of those
properties set,
you have your
PKIdentityRequest.
Now, let's get back
to the button.
If identity verification
is available,
the button will be displayed
in your app,
and tapping it will start
the identity verification flow
with your request.
If identity verification
is not available,
a fallback view you specify
will be displayed instead.
For example, this will happen
if there isn't an ID in Wallet
on this iPhone.
You can use
the fallback view
to offer other ways
to verify identity.
Let's assume identity
verification is available,
and the user taps the button.
The system will then show
a sheet with your request,
including the elements
you requested
and your intent to store them.
The user can approve the request
with Face ID or Touch ID,
or close the sheet
without approving.
Your code will then receive
a result object
containing the outcome
of the request.
If the request was approved,
you'll receive a success result.
This comes with
a PKIdentityDocument object
containing the
encrypted response,
which your app
will send to your server
for decryption and verification.
If the request
was not successful,
you'll receive a failure result.
The most common cause
of failure
is that the request
was not approved,
in which case you'll receive
a cancelled error.
That was
VerifyIdentityWithWalletButton,
the SwiftUI version of the API.
Use it to display a button
that launches
the identity verification flow
and requests information
from IDs in Wallet.
If you're not using
SwiftUI in your app,
you can also use
the PKIdentityButton
and PKIdentityAuthorization
Controller classes
to accomplish the same thing.
OK, so, now you've
requested the information,
the user's approved the request,
and your app has sent
the encrypted response
to your server.
Now, let's talk about
what your server needs to do
to decrypt and verify
that response.
I'm only going to skim
the surface on this topic,
so please check the developer
documentation for more details.
The response format uses
several international standards,
so I strongly recommend
familiarizing yourself
with those as well.
The response data you'll receive
is in a CBOR-encoded
encryption envelope.
CBOR is a data format
defined in RFC 8949.
It's similar to JSON
but uses binary data
to encode objects.
The encryption envelope
contains metadata
needed for
the decryption process,
along with the encrypted data
itself.
The data is encrypted
using HPKE,
an encryption scheme
defined in RFC 9180.
Your server will decrypt
this data using its private key.
Once decrypted, you'll get
an mdoc response object.
The mdoc response is defined
in ISO 18013 part five,
the ISO standard for mobile
Driver's Licenses and State IDs.
The mdoc response object
contains the data elements
that you requested.
It also includes a number
of security features
that your server
needs to validate
to ensure that the response
is authentic.
Note that your server
will perform the decryption
and validation itself.
Neither Apple servers nor
the issuing authority's servers
are involved.
Before we can talk
about decryption
and response validation,
we need to talk about
the session transcript.
This is a CBOR structure
that binds a response payload
to a specific request
from a specific app.
Your server will need to build
this structure and use it
during both
decryption and validation.
The session transcript contains
the same nonce and merchant ID
you used earlier in your
PKIdentityRequest,
as well as the team ID
of your developer team
and the SHA256 hash
of your encryption certificate's
public key.
When building
the session transcript,
your server should check
that the inputs you're using
are all valid.
That means the nonce shouldn't
have been used already,
and should be tied
to the current user.
The other values should
match what's expected
on your developer account.
Now let's talk about decrypting
the encrypted data.
You'll need the session
transcript you just created,
along with the metadata
from the encryption envelope.
You'll also need
your private key.
This is the private key
corresponding to the certificate
you setup earlier
in your developer account.
To protect the confidentiality
of user information,
you need to make sure
your private key stays private.
Store it securely
on your server
and never include it
in your app.
If your private key
is ever compromised,
revoke the certificate in your
developer account immediately.
After decrypting
the encrypted data,
you'll receive
an mdoc response object
containing two
cryptographic signatures,
plus the data elements
you requested.
You need to check both
signatures in the mdoc response
before you can use
its data elements.
First, you need to check
the issuer signature.
This is a signature
from the issuing authority
of the user's ID.
By checking this signature,
you're verifying that the data
in the response
came from the real
issuing authority
and wasn't tampered with.
You should check that not only
is the signature valid,
but also that it is signed by
an issuer certificate you trust.
Take a look at the documentation
for more details
about the issuer certificates
used by IDs in Wallet.
Next, you need to verify
the device signature.
This is a signature
created by a key
in the Secure Element
of the user's iPhone.
It proves that the response
you received
came from the same iPhone
that the issuing authority
originally issued the ID to.
Here, you'll need to use
your session transcript again,
along with some information
covered by the issuer signature.
Finally, you're ready
to use the data elements
that you requested.
You should never
use these elements
without first verifying the
issuer and device signatures,
because otherwise you don't know
whether the data you received
is authentic.
And with all those steps
completed, you're done!
Your app has requested
the information,
and your server has decrypted
and verified the response.
You might be wondering
how to test your implementation
if you don't have
an ID in Wallet.
We've provided a few mechanisms
to help you do that.
First, you can test
in the iOS Simulator,
where the API will return
a mock response.
This response is similar
to a real one,
but lacks real signatures.
Similarly, you can use
a test profile
to receive a mock response
on a real iPhone,
even If you don't have an ID
in Wallet on that iPhone.
See the documentation for more
details about how to do this.
Note that your server
should never treat
either of these mock responses
like a real one.
To help you with
your server implementation,
the documentation also
includes an example response,
along with everything you need
to decrypt and validate it.
And that's how you can perform
identity verification
with IDs in Wallet in iOS 16.
We discussed how to use
the API in your app,
how to process the response
on your server,
and how to test
your implementation.
Lais: This year, we introduced
many great new features
to Wallet and Apple Pay.
These include
multi-merchant payments,
improved support
for automatic payments,
order tracking,
and identity verification.
Please check out
the developer documentation
for more information.
David: Thank you for watching,
and have a great WWDC!
♪