[upbeat music]
- Hello, I'm Josh
and I'm a software engineer
on the Apple Business Essentials team.
As a small business,
you may find yourself managing
an increasing number of devices
as your team expands.
The IT demands that come with this
can be a lot to take on,
taking time away
from doing what you do best.
Apple Business Essentials makes this easy
with a subscription that seamlessly
brings together device management,
24/7 support, and cloud storage
so your small business can manage
every employee's iPhone,
iPad and Mac every step of the way.
And for your employees, it's simple.
All they need to do is sign in
with a Managed Apple ID,
and their devices are set up
with Apple Business Essentials.
Once they're signed in,
devices are automatically configured
with the settings they need,
including critical security settings
like FileVault and passcode policies
as well as all of the apps
they need to be productive.
Plus, the iCloud storage to store,
collaborate on,
and share documents in iCloud Drive.
They can even use iCloud backups
for their iPhones and iPads.
When something goes wrong, AppleCare+
for Business Essentials is there to help.
Repair credits are shared
across the entire organization
and can be used for any device
under a plan with coverage.
In fact, Apple Business Essentials
helps you with every step
of the device lifecycle.
In this session, we'll explore the ways
you can take advantage of
everything the subscription has to offer.
We'll review the first step: getting
an account in Apple Business Manager.
We'll start a new Apple Business
Essentials subscription,
add settings and apps,
and explore how the experience
looks for employees
as they enroll their devices.
Let's get started.
Apple Business Essentials exists inside
of Apple Business Manager
where you manage devices,
add users, and purchase apps.
To subscribe to Apple Business Essentials
as your device management solution,
you first need an
Apple Business Manager account.
Sign up by visiting business.apple.com
and entering your company name,
DUNS number, and contact information.
Once you have an account,
the next step is to add users.
You add individual users by
manually entering their information
or sync an existing list of users
from a Microsoft Azure Directory
or Google Workspace.
Many of your users share common needs,
like a sales department or field workers,
so you want them to get
the same settings and apps.
To prepare for this, make user groups
with the users you just created.
And save time using 'smart user groups'
which automatically creates groups
based on common attributes
like division, location, and role.
Now that I have
my Apple Business Manager account
and I've set up some users and groups,
I'm ready to enroll
in Apple Business Essentials.
Let's go to the Mac;
here's Apple Business Manager.
I find Subscription in the sidebar
and start a free trial .
I need to choose whether this is
an employee plan or a device plan.
Employee plans are just that--
plans for devices used by my employees.
Device plans are also available for things
like conference room devices,
kiosks, loaners, or other cases
where the device is not assigned
to a specific employee.
Next is the number of devices
per employee, either just 1 or up to 3.
I'm setting up a plan for my sales team.
I know they're on the road frequently
and usually have a work MacBook
as well as an iPhone and iPad,
so I'll set them up
with a three-device plan.
Next, storage.
With the subscription, my employees get
an iCloud account dedicated for work
so they can access their files
and folders across their devices.
I'll stick with 200 GB for now;
this should be plenty to start with.
But if my team's needs
change in the future,
I can update it at any time.
Last, I select AppleCare+
for Business Essentials for repair,
service and support; perfect for
my sales staff who are out in the field.
Next, I add user groups
and individual users.
Let's search for the sales team
and add them to this plan.
I've already entered
my payment information.
I review the pricing...
and add the plan.
As my business grows,
having multiple plans lets me cover
all the unique needs
of my employees and devices,
and when I make changes at any time,
I'll only pay for what I use.
My Apple Business Manager view
updates to reflect
that I'm subscribed to
Apple Business Essentials
and I now see Settings
and Collections in the sidebar.
Settings provides a list of configurations
I automatically push to a managed device.
Apps provides a list of apps to purchase
for my users to download on their devices
with the Essentials app.
Collections are a group of Settings
and Apps that I assign to users or groups.
We'll get started
by exploring the settings.
The Essentials category brings together
the settings I'm most likely to use.
But I have a number of options here,
so let's understand what they are
and then add the ones I need.
The security tab brings together
all your critical security settings
to one place so they're easy to configure.
For my iOS devices,
I want a password setting.
I'll do that shortly.
For my macOS devices,
I add the FileVault setting
to ensure my employee's Macs
encrypt their data.
I turn on Application Layer Firewall
to protect against threats
from incoming network traffic
to untrusted apps.
I turn on Gatekeeper to prevent
untrusted apps from running altogether.
Moving on to the network category,
I configure my devices with AirPrint
to automatically connect to my printers
and use the Wi-Fi setting
to configure trusted networks
so they're available automatically
when the user signs in to their device.
Personalization provides
additional settings that I can use
to customize the experience
for the devices in my fleet.
For example, I use conference room display
to restrict my apple TVs to airplay only.
For my macOS devices,
the login Window setting
allows me to display a message
on the login window,
which is great for showing things
like support email addresses
or phone numbers.
Let's go back to the essentials category
to add a few of these settings.
We'll create a new configured setting
and name it Password Policy.
The check boxes are on
for both macOS and iOS,
and let's leave on the switch on
for "password and security options"
to require my users
to create a strong password.
I select the "no" option
for "allow simple passwords"
to require my employees to choose
at least one special character
as part of their password,
and 'yes' for
"require alpha numeric password"
requires at least one letter and number
for their password.
Let's save this setting.
And here it is, added to my settings list.
Next, I configure Wi-Fi passwords
so my employees' devices
automatically join a known Wi-Fi network.
I'll name this setting
BetterBag Secure Wi-Fi.
I enter my company's Wi-Fi name...
and password.
I leave the "network visibility"
as visible,
leave "auto join" as "yes" and save.
Let's move on to apps.
The Apps page is where I get
apps, both paid and free,
that my users then install with
the Essentials app on their device.
Here I have the apps and books available
from the Apple App Store
as well as any Custom Apps
that have been made available
specifically for me to purchase.
I'd like all my users to have the Pages
app for iOS available to install,
so let's search for and get Pages.
When my users install Pages from the
Essentials app, the app is managed,
which means updates happen automatically,
and the app will be uninstalled
if the user signs out of the device.
I assign the app to my office.
I need 4 licenses, and I confirm
the price--free, in this case.
Let's get the licenses for the app.
Now that I have settings configured
and apps purchased,
let's group them together
into a Collection.
A Collection applies a combination of
settings and apps to users and groups.
This ensures that employees' devices
are configured correctly
and they have access
to the apps that they need
as soon as they sign in to their devices.
I create a new Collection
for my sales team and name it Sales.
I add apps to my collection
in the apps tab.
Let's add Pages.
Similarly, I add settings to
my collection in the settings tab.
Let's search for and add the Wi-Fi
and password policy settings.
Finally, I add my Sales team to
this collection in the User Groups tab.
I just search for the Sales User group
and add it.
Let's save, and I can now see
my newly created collection.
Okay. I have apps and settings,
and I've assigned them to my employees.
Now, I need to give the employees
a way to sign in to their devices.
In the User list,
let's find one of my employees,
Eliza...
And create a Managed Apple ID for her.
Either I download a file with
the user name and temporary password
or send Eliza an email with her
Managed Apple ID credentials directly.
Let's explore what this looks like
from Eliza's perspective.
She has a company iPad
and a personal iPhone.
She uses her Managed Apple ID
we created to enroll both devices.
Let's start with the company-owned iPad.
Because this iPad
was purchased specifically
for my organization through Apple
or an authorized reseller,
Eliza gets the Work sign-in
right when she sets up her device.
She enters the username and
password from the email I sent her.
Upon completing setup,
the device automatically joins the office
Wi-Fi network that I've set up
and the Essentials app is installed.
Next, she sets up her personal iPhone.
This device is already signed in
with her personal Apple ID
and has all of her personal apps and data.
With Apple Business Essentials,
Eliza can sign in to
her work account separately.
She goes to the settings app,
selects general,
VPN and Device Management,
and sign in with a work or school account.
Then she enters her username and password.
Now her iPhone is signed into
both her personal account
and her Apple Business Essentials account.
The best part is that these are
crytographically separated,
meaning her personal data stays private
while her work data
remains managed and secure.
Once enrolled,
Eliza has all the settings
automatically deployed to her device,
and the Essentials app is downloaded.
She uses it to install all the apps
I've assigned to her.
On the devices tab,
she has all her devices
and the Apple Support button.
If something goes wrong
with one of her devices,
she initiates a repair request
from inside the Essentials app
with the "Visit Apple Support" button.
Once approved, she requests
a repair technician to come to her
or she brings the device to an
Apple Authorized Service Provider.
I see the status in Service and Support,
where I approve or deny the request.
With Apple Business Essentials,
as your needs change,
you go back and revisit
your apps and settings.
The changes you make are automatically
pushed to your employees' devices.
If a device is lost or needs to be
re-provisioned, you select the device,
and either "sign out user",
"lock device" or "erase,"
and the action is taken on the device.
And that employee replacing
or upgrading their device
just needs to sign in to a new device
with their Managed Apple ID
to access their apps,
settings, and work data in iCloud.
Let's wrap up.
We reviewed how to get set up
in Apple Business Manager.
We subscribed
to Apple Business Essentials,
making a few key decisions along the way.
We added settings and apps
to collections
which we assigned
to a user group of employees
and explored how the experience
looks for employees on their devices.
Apple Business Essentials, currently
available to U.S.-based small businesses,
lets you get back to doing
what you do best, faster.
It's simple to manage the entire life of
your employees' devices
with easy set up and onboarding,
security and privacy,
storage and backup, support and repair,
and updates
with one flexible subscription.
To learn more about
Apple Business Essentials,
visit apple.com/business/essentials
Have a great WWDC.