♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi! My name is Adam Bradford.
I'm an engineer
on the VisionKit team,
and if you're looking to add
Live Text to your app,
you're in the right place.
But first, what is Live Text?
Live Text analyzes an image and
provides features for the users
to interact with its content,
such selecting and copying text,
perform actions
like lookup and translate,
providing data-detection
workflows,
such as mapping an address,
dialing a number,
or jumping to a URL.
Live Text even allows
for QR code interaction.
Imagine how you could
put this to use in your app?
You want to know more?
Well, you're in the right place.
For this session, I'm going
to start with a general overview
of the Live Text API.
Then I will explore
how to implement this API
in an existing application.
Next, I will dive into
some tips and tricks
which may help you when adding
Live Text to your app.
Now for an overview
of the Live Text API.
At a high level, the Live Text
API is available in Swift.
It works beautifully
on static images
and can be adapted to be used
for paused video frames.
If you need to analyze video
in a live camera stream
to search for items
like text or QR codes,
VisionKit also has
a data scanner available.
Check out this session from
my colleague Ron for more info.
The Live Text API is available
starting on iOS 16
for devices with
an Apple Neural Engine,
and for all devices
that support macOS 13.
It consists of
four main classes.
To use it,
first, you'll need an image.
This image is then fed
into an ImageAnalyzer,
which performs
the async analysis.
Once the analysis is complete,
the resulting
ImageAnalysis object
is provided to either
an ImageAnalysisInteraction
or ImageAnalysisOverlayView,
depending on your platform.
Seems pretty straightforward
so far, right?
Now, I'm going to demonstrate
how one would add it
to an existing application.
And here's our application.
This is a simple image viewer,
which has an image view
inside of a scroll view.
Notice, I can
both zoom and pan.
But try as I might,
I cannot select any of this text
or activate any
of these data detectors.
This simply will not do.
Here's the project in Xcode.
To add Live Text
to this application,
I'll be modifying
a view controller subclass.
First, I'm going to need
an ImageAnalyzer,
and an
ImageAnalysisInteraction.
Here, I'm simply
overriding viewDidLoad
and adding the interaction
to the imageview.
Next, I need to know
when to perform the analysis.
Notice that when
a new image is set,
I first reset the
preferredInteractionTypes
and analysis which were meant
for the old image.
Now everything is ready
for a new analysis.
Next, I'm going to create
the function we will use
and then check
that our image exists.
If so, then create a task.
Next, create a configuration
in order to tell the analyzer
what it should be looking for.
In this case, I'll go with text
and machine-readable codes.
Generating the analysis
can throw,
so handle that as appropriate.
And now finally,
I'm ready to call the method
analyzeImageWithConfiguration,
which will start
the analysis process.
Once the analysis is complete,
an indeterminate
amount of time has passed,
and the state of the application
may have changed,
so I will check that both
the analysis was successful
and that the displayed image
has not changed.
If all of these checks pass,
I can simply set
the analysis on the interaction
and set the
preferredInteractionTypes.
I'm using .automatic here,
which will give me
the default system behavior.
I think this is ready
for a test.
Oh, look at that!
I see the Live Text button
has appeared, and yep,
I can now select text.
Notice how these
interface elements
are positioned for me
automatically,
and keep their position inside
of both the image bounds
and the visible area,
with no work on my part.
OK, notice that tapping
the Live Text button
will both highlight
any selectable items,
underline data detectors,
and show Quick Actions.
I can easily tap this
Quick Action to make a call,
and even see more options
by long-pressing.
You have to admit,
this is pretty cool.
With just these
few lines of code,
I've taken an ordinary image
and brought it to life.
This simple application
now has the ability
to select text on images,
activate data detectors,
QR codes, lookup,
translate text, and more.
Not too shabby from just
this few lines of code,
if you ask me.
And now that you've have seen
how to implement Live Text,
I'm going to go over
a few tips and tricks
that may help you
with your adoption.
I'll start by exploring
interaction types.
Most developers
will want .automatic,
which provides text selection,
but will also highlight
data detectors if the Live Text
button is active.
This will draw a line underneath
any applicable detected items
and allows one-tap access
to activate them.
This is the exact same
behavior you would see
from built-in applications.
If it makes sense for your app
to only have text selection
without data detectors, you may
set the type to .textSelection
and it will not change with the
state of the Live Text button.
If, however,
it makes sense for your app
to only have data detectors
without text selection,
set the type to
.dataDetectors.
Note that in this mode,
since selection is disabled,
you will not see
a Live Text button,
but data detectors will be
underlined and ready
for one-tap access.
Setting the
preferredInteractionTypes
to an empty set
will disable the interaction.
And also, a last note, with text
selection or automatic mode,
you'll find you can
still activate data detectors
by long-pressing.
This is controlled by the
allowLongPressForDataDetectorsIn
TextMode property,
which will be active when set
to true, which the default.
Simply set to false
to disable this if necessary.
I would like
to now take a moment
and talk about these buttons
at the bottom,
collectively known as
the supplementary interface.
This consists of
the Live Text button,
which normally lives in
the bottom right-hand corner,
as well as Quick Actions
which appear on the bottom left.
Quick Actions represent any
data detectors from the analysis
and are visible when
the Live Text button is active.
The size, position,
and visibility
are controlled
by the interaction.
And while the default position
and look matches the system,
your app may have
custom interface elements
which may interfere
or utilize different fonts
and symbol weights.
Let's look at how you can
customize this interface.
First off, the isSupplementary
InterfaceHidden property.
If I wanted to allow my app
to still select text
but I did not want to show
the Live Text button,
if I set
the SupplementaryInterfaceHidden
to true, you will not see
any Live Text button
or Quick Actions.
We also have a content insets
property available.
If you have interface elements
that would overlap
the supplementary interface,
you may adjust
the content insets
so the Live Text button
and Quick Actions adapt nicely
to your existing app content
when visible.
If your app is using
a custom font
you'd like
the interface to adopt,
setting the
supplementaryInterfaceFont
will cause the Live Text
button and Quick Actions
to use the specified font
for text
and font weight for symbols.
Please note that
for button-sizing consistency,
Live Text will ignore
the point size.
Switching gears for a moment,
if you are not using
UIImageview,
you may discover that highlights
do not match up with your image.
This is because
with UIImageView,
VisionKit can use
its ContentMode property
to calculate the contentsRect
automatically for you.
Here, the interaction's view
has a bounds that is bigger
than its image content
but is using
the default's content rect,
which is a unit rectangle.
This is easily solved by
implementing the delegate method
contentsRectForInteraction
and return a rectangle
in unit coordinate space
describing how
the image content relates
to the interaction's bounds
in order to correct this.
For example, returning
a rectangle with these values
would correct the issue,
but please return the correct
normalized rectangle
based on your app's
current content and layout.
contentsRectForInteraction
will be called
whenever the interaction's
bounds change, however,
if your contentsRect
has changed
but your interaction's bounds
have not,
you can ask the interaction
to update by calling
setContentsRectNeedsUpdate().
Another question you may have
when adopting Live Text may be,
Where is the best place
to put this interaction?
Ideally, Live Text interactions
are placed directly on the view
that hosts your image content.
As mentioned before,
UIImageView will handle
the contentsRect
calculations for you,
and while not necessary,
is preferred.
If you are using UIImageview,
just set the interaction
on the imageView
and VisionKit
will handle the rest.
However, if your ImageView
is located
inside of a ScrollView,
you may be tempted to place the
interaction on the ScrollView,
however, this is not recommended
and could be difficult to manage
as it will have a continually
changing contentsRect.
The solution here is the same,
place the interaction
on the view
that hosts your image content,
even if it is inside
a ScrollView
with magnification applied.
I'm going talk about gestures
for a moment,
Live Text has a very, very
rich set of gesture recognizers,
to say to least.
Depending on how your app
is structured,
it's possible you may find
the interaction
responding to gestures
and events
your app should really handle
or vice versa.
Don't panic.
Here are a few techniques
you can use to help correct
if you see these issues occur.
One common way to correct this
is to implement
the delegate method
interactionShouldBeginAtPointFor
InteractionType.
If you return false, the
action will not be performed.
A good place to start is
to check if the interaction
has an interactive item
at the given point
or if it has an active
text selection.
The text selection check
is used here
so you will be able to have
the ability tap off of the text
in order to deselect it.
On the other hand,
if you find your interaction
doesn't seem
to respond to gestures,
it may be because
there's a gesture recognizer
in your app
that's handling them instead.
In this case, you can craft
a similar solution
using your gestureRecognizer's
gestureRecognizerShouldBegin
delegate method.
Here, I perform a similar check
and return false
if there is an interactive item
at the location
or there's an active
text selection.
On a side note.
In this example,
I'm first converting
the gestureRecognizer's location
to the window's coordinate space
by passing in nil,
and then converting it
to the interaction's view.
This may be necessary
if your interaction
is inside of a ScrollView
with magnification applied.
If you find your points
aren't matching up,
give this technique a try.
Another similar option
I have found to be useful
is to override UIView's
hitTest:WithEvent.
Here, once again,
similar story,
I perform the same
types of checks as before,
and in this case,
return the appropriate view.
As always, we want your app
to be as responsive as possible,
and while the Neural Engine
makes analysis
extremely efficient,
there a few ImageAnalyzer tips
I'd like to share
for best performance.
Ideally, you want
only one ImageAnalyzer
shared in your app.
Also, we support
several types of images.
You should always
minimize image conversions
by passing in the native type
that you have;
however, if you do happen
to have a CVPixelBuffer,
that would be
the most efficient.
Also, in order to best utilize
system resources,
you should begin your analysis
only when, or just before,
an image appears onscreen.
If your app's content scrolls --
for example,
it has a timeline --
begin analysis only once
the scrolling has stopped.
Now this API isn't the only
place you'll see Live Text,
support is provided
automatically
in a few frameworks across the
system your app may already use.
For example,
UITextField or UITextView
have Live Text support using
Camera for keyboard input.
And Live Text is also supported
in WebKit and Quick Look.
For more information,
please check out these sessions.
New this year for iOS 16,
we've added
Live Text support in AVKit.
AVPlayerView and ViewController
support Live Text
in paused frames automatically
via the allowsVideoFrameAnalysis
property,
which is enabled by default.
Please note,
this is only available
with non-FairPlay
protected content.
If you're using AVPlayerLayer,
then you are responsible
for managing the analysis
and the interaction but it is
very important to use the
currentlyDisplayedPixelBuffer
property
to get the current frame.
This is the only way
to guarantee
the proper frame
is being analyzed.
This will only return
a valid value
if the video play rate is zero,
and this is a shallow copy
and absolutely
not safe to write to.
And once again,
only available
for non-FairPlay
protected content.
We are thrilled to help bring
Live Text functionality
to your app.
On behalf of everybody
on the Live Text team,
thank you for joining us
for this session.
I am stoked to see how you use
it for images in your app.
And as always, have fun!
♪