♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Keyi Yu,
and I'm an engineer
from the Metal Ecosystem team.
Today, it's my pleasure
to introduce metal-cpp.
We created metal-cpp for anyone
who uses C++ and wants to build
Metal applications
for Apple platforms.
Metal-cpp is
a low-overhead library
that connects your C++
applications to Metal.
First, I'll start with
an overview of what metal-cpp is
and how it works,
and then I'll cover some details
about the lifecycles
for Objective-C objects.
C++ and Objective-C handle
lifecycles a bit differently,
and I'll show you how to handle
those differences.
Xcode and metal-cpp
have some great utilities
that can help you manage
the object lifecycles
in your apps.
And finally, I'll show you
how to integrate C++ code
with Objective-C classes.
So here's a look at metal-cpp
and how it works.
Metal is the foundation
for accelerated graphics
and compute on Apple platforms,
enabling your apps and games
to tap into the incredible power
of the GPU.
It was originally designed
using the powerful features
and the conventions
offered by Objective-C.
But if your code base is in C++,
you may need something to bridge
between your code
and Metal's Objective-C code.
Introducing metal-cpp!
It serves as a hub
between your C++ application
and Objective-C Metal.
With metal-cpp
in your application,
you can use Metal classes
and functions in C++,
and metal-cpp can help you
call Objective-C functions
in runtime.
metal-cpp is a lightweight
Metal C++ wrapper.
I say it's lightweight,
because it's implemented
as a header-only library
with inline function calls.
It provides 100 percent
coverage of the Metal API
by implementing a one-to-one
mapping of C++ calls
to Objective-C APIs.
To do this, metal-cpp wraps
parts of the Foundation
and CoreAnimation frameworks.
It's open source
under Apache 2 License,
so you can modify the library
and include it
to your applications, easily.
metal-cpp uses C
to call directly
into the Objective-C runtime.
This is the exact same mechanism
that the Objective-C compiler
uses to execute
Objective-C methods.
So this wrapper
introduces little overhead.
Since metal-cpp implements
a one-to-one mapping of C++
to Objective-C calls,
it follows the same Cocoa
memory-management rules.
I will discuss this
in more detail later.
This one-to-one mapping
also allows
all of the developer tools
to work seamlessly,
including GPU Frame Capture
and the Xcode debugger.
These are the series of calls
necessary to draw a triangle
with metal-cpp.
If you are familiar with C++,
it's a good time to learn Metal,
because you don't need to worry
about language syntax.
If you've already used Metal
with Objective-C,
in terms of function calls,
there's very little difference
between the Objective-C
interface of Metal
and metal-cpp.
I am going to demonstrate
how easy it is to use metal-cpp.
First, I create
a command buffer,
which I will fill with commands
for the GPU to execute.
I can simply use
the raw pointer in C++
as a mapping to ID
in Objective-C.
I can create a render
command encoder
and write render commands
with a command buffer.
The C++ function
renderCommandEncoder
and the Objective-C method
WithDescriptor are the same.
The only differences
are the name conventions
of the languages.
I then set a render pipeline
state object
which contains the vertex
and fragment shaders
and various other
rendering states.
Then I encode my draw call
to render a single triangle.
Then I indicate that
I've finished encoding
render commands.
I present the drawable, so the
triangle is displayed onscreen.
Finally, I commit
my command buffer.
This tells the GPU that it can
begin executing my commands.
Obviously, metal-cpp
and Objective-C Metal
are almost the same.
You don't need to worry
about language syntax now
with metal-cpp,
you can directly look into
the Metal documentation
to learn the concepts
and usage of Metal.
You may have already played
with this deferred lighting
sample before.
We now provide a new version
of this deferred lighting sample
which uses metal-cpp.
We hope this can help you learn
how to code with metal-cpp
in practice.
I'm also excited
to introduce a series
of incremental C++ samples
that introduces the Metal API
and shows you how to accomplish
different tasks with it.
So now that you know
a little bit about metal-cpp,
how do you actually use it?
We published
metal-cpp last year.
Here's the webpage where
you can find the downloads
and instructions.
Let me show you the steps
you will need to take.
After downloading metal-cpp,
you should tell Xcode
where to find it.
Here, I put metal-cpp
under the current project.
Then, you need to set
C++17 or higher
as the C++ language dialect.
Next, add three frameworks
to the project:
Foundation, QuartzCore,
and Metal.
Now there's only one thing
left to do
before using C++ interfaces
of those frameworks.
There are three headers
in metal-cpp.
Since metal-cpp is
a header-only library,
you need to generate
their implementations
before importing
the header files.
To do this, define three macros:
NS_PRIVATE_IMPLEMENTATION,
CA_PRIVATE_IMPLEMENTATION,
AND MTL_PRIVATE_IMPLEMENTATION.
If you are interested in what
metal-cpp does with the macros
under the hood,
please check out header bridge
files in the metal-cpp folder.
You can use
the headers separately
or put them in a single header.
You can import the header files
whenever you need them.
But remember,
do not define the NS, CA,
or MTL_PRIVATE_IMPLEMENTATION
macros more than once.
Otherwise, you may cause
duplicate definition errors.
To use metal-cpp effectively,
you'll need to know Cocoa's
memory management rules,
how to use the great utilities
that can help you
manage object lifecycles,
and how to design
your application architecture
when you interface
with other frameworks.
I'll start with object
lifecycle management.
During your application's
operation,
you typically need to allocate
and release memory.
You also need to manage
command buffers,
pipeline objects, and resources.
To help manage this memory,
Objective-C and Cocoa objects
include a reference count.
This is also present
in metal-cpp.
Reference counting helps you
manage your memory.
Using reference counting,
all objects contain
a retainCount property.
Components in an app
increase the count
to keep objects
they're interacting with alive
and decrease it
when they are done with them.
When the retainCount hits zero,
the runtime
deallocates the object.
There are two types of reference
counting in Objective-C.
One is called
Manual Retain-Release -- MRR;
the other is Automatic
Reference Counting -- ARC.
When compiling code
with the ARC feature,
the compiler takes
the references you create
and automatically inserts calls
to the underlying
memory-management mechanism.
metal-cpp objects are manually
retained and released.
So you need to understand
Cocoa's conventions
to know when to retain
and release objects.
Unlike creating objects in C++,
metal-cpp objects
are neither created with new
nor destroyed with delete.
With Cocoa's conventions,
you own any object you create
with methods starting
with the alloc, new, copy,
mutableCopy, or create.
You can take ownership
of an object using retain.
When you no longer need it,
you must relinquish ownership
of an object you own.
You can release it immediately
or release it afterwards.
You must not relinquish
ownership of an object
you do not own
as you risk a double free.
Next, I'll walk through
an example
of these Cocoa conventions.
In class A, a method uses alloc
to create an object
and init to initialize
this object.
Remember, never call init
on an object twice.
Class A takes the ownership
and is responsible
for deallocating it.
Now the retain count
for this object is one.
Next, class B uses retain
to get the object
and takes ownership
of this object.
So far, I have two objects
that share the ownership
of this object represented
by the orange cube.
The retain count
increases by one.
Class A doesn't need
this object anymore,
so class A should manually
call release for it.
As a result, the retain count
decreases by one.
Now, only class B
owns the object.
OK, finally, class B wants
to release this object too.
Now the retain count is zero,
so the runtime frees the object.
Here's a situation where
a method in class B
returns an object.
You still need this object
in the rest of the programs.
In other words, you want
to relinquish ownership
of an object in a method
in class B,
but you don't want it to be
deallocated immediately.
In this case, you should call
autorelease in class B.
The retain count is still one
after you call autorelease,
and thus, you can still use
the object later.
Here's the question:
since class B does not own
this object anymore,
who is responsible
for deallocating it?
The Foundation Framework
provides an important object,
called the AutoreleasePool.
The Autorelease API puts the
object into an AutoreleasePool.
Now, the AutoreleasePool takes
the ownership of the object.
The AutoreleasePool decrements
the receiver's retain count
when the AutoreleasePool
is destroyed.
You are not the only one who
can create autoreleased objects.
Metal creates several
autoreleased objects
as part of its operation.
All methods that create
temporary objects
add them to AutoreleasePools
by calling autorelease
under the hood.
It is the AutoreleasePool's
responsibility to release them.
In other words,
with an AutoreleasePool,
you can code
in a more elegant way.
You can have an AutoreleasePool
for the main application.
We also encourage you
to create and manage
additional AutoreleasePools
at smaller scopes
to reduce your program's
working set.
You also need AutoreleasePools
for every thread you create.
Here's an example showing
how to use an AutoreleasePool
and autoreleased objects.
In this sample,
an AutoreleasePool
is created by alloc, which
means you take the ownership
and it should be
manually released.
Now we have an AutoreleasePool.
As we discussed
in the beginning,
you should create
a command buffer.
It's not created
with alloc or create,
so you don't own it.
Instead, it's an autoreleased
object created by Metal.
This command buffer will be put
into the AutoreleasePool.
It's the AutoreleasePool's
responsibility to deallocate it.
You can use it as you wish
until you release
the AutoreleasePool.
Then you need to create
a RenderPassDescriptor.
This RenderPassDescriptor will
be put into the AutoreleasePool
as well.
Same to RenderCommandEncoder.
It's also an autoreleased object
created by Metal.
Don't forget
this currentDrawable object.
It will be put into
the AutoreleasePool too.
At the end of the piece of code,
I use pPool->release
to release the AutoreleasePool.
Before being deallocated,
the AutoreleasePool
releases everything
that it owns,
in this case, it releases
the CommandBuffer,
RenderPassDescriptor,
RenderCommandEncoder,
and currentDrawable.
Then the AutoreleasePool
is released.
So far, you got to know
Cocoa's conventions,
autoreleased objects,
and AutoreleasePools.
It's important to correctly
manage object lifecycles
to avoid memory leaks
and zombie objects,
and we have great tools
to help you avoid
and debug these issues.
I'll focus on two utilities:
NS::SharedPtr and NSZombie.
NS::SharedPtr is a new utility
that can help you manage
the object lifecycle.
You can find it under
Foundation framework
in the metal-cpp folder.
Notice that it is not
exactly the same
as std:shared_ptr.
So there's no dependency
on the C++ standard library
and no extra cost
on storing the reference count.
Here's what NS::SharedPtr
is like.
Transfer and retain functions
clearly express
the intent of consuming
an object.
Transfer creates a SharedPtr
without increasing
the pointee's referenceCount,
effectively transferring
ownership to the SharedPtr.
The retain function sends a
retain to the passed-in object.
Use this function
to keep alive objects
that are in AutoreleasePools
and to express
that the pointer's owner
has a vested interest
in the pointee's lifecycle.
You can access
the underlying object
as expected via get
and via the operator->.
SharedPtr copy,
move, construction,
and assignment work as expected,
with copy increasing
the retainCount.
Moves are fast and
do not affect the retain count
in the general case.
SharedPtrs always send
exactly one release
to the pointee
on destruction.
You can avoid this if you want
by calling
the detach function.
Going back to the top,
it's important to know
the differences between
creating a pointer
by transferring or retaining it.
So for TransferPtr,
suppose I have an MRR object,
with a reference count of 1.
After I pass it
to the TransferPtr function,
the SharedPtr takes
ownership of the object,
but its retainCount
doesn't change.
When the pointer
goes out of scope,
the SharedPtr's destructor runs
and calls release
on the MRR object,
which decrements
the retainCount to 0.
Another function
is NS::RetainPtr.
When you want to avoid
deallocating an object
because you want
to use it later,
you should use NS::RetainPtr.
Suppose we have this MRR object;
the retainCount is one.
After we pass it
to the RetainPtr function,
the retainCount increases
by one.
After running out of the scope,
this RetainPtr calls release
for this MRR object.
So the retainCount is one.
In general, NS::TransferPtr
takes the ownership
of an object for you.
But NS::RetainPtr
helps you retain an object
when you don't want it
to be deallocated.
When you pass an object
to these two functions,
NS::TransferPtr doesn't change
the reference count
but NS::RetainPtr increases
reference count by one
as it calls retain for you
under the hood.
The destructor
of these two functions
both call release
for the passed-in object
and, therefore, reference
count decreases by one.
If the reference count
hits zero,
the object will be freed
in runtime.
Here's an example
of NS::TransferPtr.
When I talked about
the render pass,
which drew a single triangle,
I needed this
render pipeline state.
Here are the calls to create
a render pipeline state object.
These are the attributes that a
render pipeline descriptor needs.
According to
Cocoa's conventions,
since these calls starts
with new and alloc,
I own these objects.
So I need to call release
for these objects.
With NS::SharedPtr,
I don't need to call release
for those MRR objects
because NS::SharedPtrs takes
the ownership of these objects.
So here, I pass raw pointers
to the TransferPtr function.
After doing that,
there's no need to call release
as I did in the previous slide.
If you are familiar with ARC,
you may find that MRR
used with NS::SharedPtr
is similar to using ARC.
You may encounter
use-after-free bugs
when handling memory manually.
They occur when you are trying
to use an object
which has been already released.
NSZombie is a good way
to check for those bugs.
When use-after-free
bugs occur,
it triggers a breakpoint and
provides you with a stack trace.
You can enable Zombies
very easily
with an environment variable.
Just set NSZombieEnabled
to YES.
Or If you're using Xcode,
you can enable Zombies
in a scheme.
Here's how it works.
I want to create a new
render pipeline state object
with the same
render pipeline settings.
So in this
newRenderPipelineState function,
I reuse the pDesc object.
After clicking on run,
Xcode triggers a breakpoint
and shows me the stack trace.
That means
I got something wrong.
Hm, what's the problem?
Maybe NSZombie can help here,
so I enable NSZombie in scheme.
When I run the program again,
NSZombie triggers a breakpoint.
I get something new
in the console output:
"message sent
to deallocated instance."
Oh, I reused an object
that I have already released.
And it's
the render pipeline descriptor.
So I need to use this
render pipeline descriptor
before calling release.
By doing that,
I fix the problem.
More tools and details
are covered in this year's talk,
"Profile and optimize
your game's memory."
For example, you can learn
how to track retainCount
in allocations in instruments.
Feel free to check out
other tools on Apple platforms.
You will find out that they
can help you debug your game
and improve performance.
Now you know how to manage
object lifecycles in metal-cpp.
But you may still need to
interface with other frameworks,
like game controller
and audio.
These are still in Objective-C.
How can you interface
with those APIs
and design an elegant
application architecture?
Say you wrote a ViewController
in Objective-C,
but you wrote a renderer in C++
with metal-cpp.
You need to call renderer
methods, like draw,
from the ViewController.
The challenge here is to nicely
separate the two languages
but have them work together.
The solution is to create
an adapter class
which calls C++
from Objective-C files.
By doing this, you can focus
on Objective-C or C++
in files where
you implement features.
For example,
I can create a RendererAdapter
class in Objective-C.
And down in the implementation,
I add an Objective-C method
so that I can call it
directly from
the ViewController.
Inside of the interface,
I declare a C++ pointer
to a renderer object.
Inside the body of the method,
I directly call
the renderer's C++ method.
This method needs to pass
the MTK::View
as a C++ object
into the draw method,
so it casts the view
as a C++ type
by using the __bridge keyword.
I'll talk more
about this cast later.
In contrast, you need to call
MTKView which is written
with Objective-C in Renderer
which is written with C++.
It's challenging as well.
Similarly, the solution
is to create an adapter class.
With this class, in C++ files,
you can call Objective-C methods
using C++ interface.
For example, I can create
a ViewAdapter class.
I write the interfaces in C++,
so in the Renderer class,
I can call those C++
view methods easily.
While in the implementation,
I call Objective-C methods
from MTKView,
including currentDrawable
and depthStencilTexture.
You may notice there're some
__bridge keywords here.
I use them to cast between
metal-cpp objects
and Objective-C objects.
As you learned in the beginning,
metal-cpp objects are manually
retained and released,
but objects created
by Objective-C
use automatic
reference counting.
You need to move objects
from MRR to ARC
and from ARC to MRR.
Here are three types
of bridge casting
which can help you cast
between Objective-C and C++.
They can also help you
transfer ownership
_bridge casting casts
between Objective-C
and metal-cpp objects.
There is no transfer of
ownership between them.
__bridge_retained casting
casts an Objective-C pointer
to a metal-cpp pointer and
takes the ownership from ARC.
__bridge_transfer casting moves
a metal-cpp pointer
to Objective-C and transfers
the ownership to ARC.
Going back to the problem,
you need to cast
between metal-cpp objects
and Objective-C objects.
If there's no transfer
of ownership,
you can use __bridge cast.
If you want to cast from
metal-cpp to Objective-C objects
and transfer
the ownership to Objective-C,
you should use
__bridge_transfer cast.
If you want to cast from
Objective-C to metal-cpp objects
and take the ownership
out of ARC,
you should use
__bridge_retained cast.
Here's a case when
I have to use MetalKit
to leverage
the asset loading code.
That means in my C++
application,
I need a texture
as a metal-cpp object,
but it is created
by Objective-C methods.
I need the ability to transfer
ownership out of ARC
so I can manually release it.
And in this case,
I need to pick
__bridge_retained cast.
I have this C++ function that
loads a texture from the catalog
and I want to return
a metal-cpp texture.
But inside, I'm calling
some Objective-C functions
in MetalKit.
I need to define the options
that a texture loader needs.
Then I create a texture loader
by calling an Objective-C method
from MetalKit.
With that loader,
I can create a texture object
and load a texture
from the catalog.
This method is also
an Objective-C method
from MetalKit.
Now I have
an Objective-C type texture,
I need to cast it
to the metal-cpp object
and take it out of ARC.
With these steps in mind,
it's time to code,
and I'll show you
how casting works in practice.
First step is to define
the texture loader options
that a texture loader needs.
I can safely cast the metal-cpp
storage mode and usage
to the Objective-C type,
as the metal-cpp type
defines them to the same values.
Here I create a texture loader.
I have a device that
is a metal-cpp object,
and I need to pass it
to the initWithDevice method.
Because the metal-cpp object
is an Objective-C object,
I can cast it
like a toll-free object.
There is no transfer
of ownership.
Now I use
the texture loader options
and a texture loader
to create a texture.
And I want to return the loaded
texture as a metal-cpp object.
So I need
to take it out of ARC
and cast it to the corresponding
pointer type.
This is done with
a __bridge_retained cast.
After this,
I can use this texture
as any metal-cpp object.
I am responsible
for releasing it.
In this section,
I provided an adapter pattern
which can help you handle
two different languages
in your program.
I also showed how to interface
with Objective-C and C++
with three types of casts.
To summarize,
metal-cpp is a lightweight
and very efficient
Metal C++ wrapper.
I talked about how to manage
object lifecycles
when using metal-cpp,
how to interface
with Objective-C
in an elegant manner,
and how our developer tools
can help you debug.
Download metal-cpp and play with
all the amazing samples now!
See what you can create
with Metal.
We look forward to seeing
your C++ applications
running across
all Apple platforms.
Thanks for watching!
♪