♪ ♪
Christian: Hi, my name is Christian.
I'm an engineer on the ARKit team,
and I would like to welcome you
to our session, Discover ARKit 6.
You'll learn how to make use
of the latest advancements
in our Augmented Reality framework.
We are delighted to see what you have been
creating over the last several years
with ARKit.
We are seeing some amazing apps
in interior design,
travel, virtual exhibitions,
games, and so many others.
Our team here at Apple has
paid close attention to your feedback,
and we have incorporated a lot of it
into ARKit 6.
Let's have a look.
We are introducing a new 4K video mode
that lets you run the camera stream
in the highest image resolution yet.
After that, I'll talk about some
additional camera enhancements we made
that give you more control
of the video backdrop.
We also have updates
on the behavior of plane anchors,
additions to the Motion Capture API,
and finally share new cities
where location anchors will be supported.
Let's start with 4K video.
Over the course of the past several years,
we saw a lot of demand
for high resolution content,
especially those apps which leverage
the power of Augmented Reality
for filmmaking,
are ever hungry for more pixels.
Let me show you how images are captured
and processed for ARKit.
This is the camera module
of an iPhone 13 Pro.
If we open it up, we can see its setup.
Let us talk about the Wide
and the Ultrawide camera.
Both these cameras can be used
for different computer vision tasks,
such as world tracking,
motion capture, or person segmentation.
The wide camera
has a special place in our heart,
since it delivers the images
for the rendering backdrop.
It's important to understand
how images are processed for rendering,
so let me zoom in to the sensor level.
When capturing images for ARKit,
we use a large part of the image sensor.
To be more precise,
it's an area of 3840x2880 pixels
on this particular model.
After capture,
we use a process called binning.
It works as follows:
Binning takes a region of 2x2 pixels,
averages the pixel values,
and writes back a single pixel.
This has two significant advantages.
First, image dimensions are reduced
by a factor of two,
in this case,
it downscales to 1920x1440 pixels.
As a result of this, each frame consumes
way less memory and processing power.
This allows the device to run the camera
at up to 60 frames per second
and frees up resources for rendering.
Secondly,
this process offers an advantage
in low light environments,
where the averaging of pixel values
reduces the effects of sensor noise.
We end up with a camera stream
that provides an image at HD resolution
roughly every 17 milliseconds.
After using the current frame
for various computer vision tasks,
ARKit surfaces the current frame
for rendering.
In case you are writing
your own Metal renderer,
you have access to it via
ARSession's currentFrame.capturedImage.
If you are using RealityKit, the image
is automatically processed further
for use as a backdrop.
It is scaled on-device to match
the screen width of 2532 pixels
and is cropped to match
the display aspect ratio.
RealityKit performs the task of rendering
and compositing the virtual content,
like this pirate ship,
on top of the frame and displays
the final result on screen.
Now, with the power
of our latest hardware,
we enable full 4K video mode in ARKit.
Your app can now take advantage
of a higher resolution image
by skipping the binning step and directly
accessing it in full 4K resolution.
In 4K mode,
an image area of 3840x2160 pixels is used
and you can capture video
at 30 frames per second.
Apart from these changes, your app
will work the same way as before.
If you use RealityKit,
it performs scaling, cropping,
and rendering for you.
You can enable the 4K mode
using a few simple steps.
Let's see how that looks in code.
'ARConfiguration' has a new convenience
function
'recommendedVideoFormatFor4KResolution'
that returns a 4K video format
if that mode is supported
on your device.
If the device or configuration do not
support 4K, this function will return nil.
You can then assign this video format
to your configuration,
then you run your session
with that adjusted configuration.
The 4K video mode is available
on iPhone 11 and up
and on any iPad Pro with an M1 chip.
The resolution is 3840x2160 pixels
at 30 frames per second.
The aspect ratio is 16:9,
for iPad that means that images have to be
cropped at the sides
for full screen display and the final
render might look zoomed in.
When using ARKit,
especially in the new 4K resolution,
it's important to follow some
best practices for optimal results.
Do not hold on to an ARFrame for too long.
This might prevent the system
from freeing up memory,
which might further stop ARKit
from surfacing newer frames to you.
This will become visible through
frame drops in your rendering.
Ultimately, the ARCamera's tracking state
might fall back to limited.
Check for console warnings
to make sure you do not retain
too many images at any given time.
Also consider if the new 4K video format
is indeed the right option for your app.
Apps that benefit from high resolution
video are good candidates,
such as video, filmmaking,
and virtual production apps.
Dealing with higher resolution images
takes up additional system resources,
so for games and other apps
that rely on a high refresh rate,
we still suggest using full HD video
at 60 frames per second.
On top of the new 4K mode,
there are some additional enhancements
that allow you to get more control
over your camera.
I will start by introducing the hi-res
background photo API
and show how to enable the new HDR mode.
Further, I will demonstrate how to get access
to the underlying AVCaptureDevice
for more fine grained control
and show you how to read EXIF tags
in ARKit.
Let's jump into the new
hi-res background photo API.
While running an ARSession,
you still get access
to the video stream as usual.
In addition, ARKit lets you request
the capture of single photos on demand
in the background,
while the video stream is running
uninterrupted.
Those single photo frames take
full advantage of your camera sensor.
On my iPhone 13 that means
the full 12 megapixels of the wide camera.
When preparing for WWDC,
we at ARKit had a fun idea
for a Photography app
that highlights what this new API
can help you create.
In our example,
we take you back in time
to April 1st, 2016,
when the famous pirate flag
was flying over
the Apple Infinite Loop Campus.
I asked Tommy,
the original photographer,
where exactly he shot that photo
six years ago.
Based on this coordinate,
we can create a location anchor
that guides you to the exact same spot
where Tommy stood in April 2016,
as indicated by the big blue dot.
Upon reaching that spot,
it helps you frame that perfect picture
by showing a focus square.
Finally, the app lets your take a photo
by tapping the screen.
That photo can be taken
in native camera resolution
while the current ARKit session
is running,
without the need to spin up
another AVCapture session.
We're excited to see which ideas you have
that combine the power of AR
and photography.
Another use case that will greatly benefit
by this API
is the creation of 3D models
using Object Capture.
Object capture takes in photos
of a real world object,
like this running shoe,
and using our latest photogrammetry
algorithms,
it turns them into a 3D model
ready for deployment in your AR app.
With ARKit you can overlay a 3D UI
on top of a physical object
and provide better capture guidance.
And now with the new high resolution
background image API,
you can take higher-resolution photos
of the object
and create even more realistic 3D models.
I'm a big fan of photogrammetry,
so I'd highly recommend
that you check out this year's
"Bring your world to augmented reality"
session.
Let me show you how you can enable
high-resolution photo captures in code.
First, we check for a video format
that supports hiResCapture.
We can use the convenience function
'recommendedVideoFormatForHighResolution
FrameCapturing' for that.
After we make sure
that the format is supported,
we can set the new video format
and run the session.
We further have to tell ARKit
when to capture a hi-res image.
In our earlier example,
the capture of a photo is triggered
by a tap on the screen.
In your own application, you might want
to react to different events
that trigger high-resolution
frame captures.
It really depends on your use case.
The ARSession has a new function
called captureHighResolutionFrame.
Calling this function
triggers an out-of-band capture
of a high-resolution image.
You get access to an ARFrame
containing the high-resolution image
and all other frame properties
asynchronously in the completion handler.
You should check
if the frame capture was successful
before accessing its contents.
In this example
we store the frame to disk.
Also keep in mind our best practices
on image retention
that I mentioned earlier,
especially since these images use
the full resolution of the image sensor.
Next, let's talk about HDR.
High Dynamic Range captures
a wider range of colors
and maps those to your display.
This is most visible in environments
with high contrast.
Here's a good example from my backyard.
This scene features both very dark areas–
for example, on the wooden fence–
and some very bright areas
like the clouds in the sky.
When turning on the HDR mode,
as on the right,
you can see that details in these regions,
like the fluffiness in the clouds,
are preserved much better in HDR.
Let's see how HDR is turned on in code.
You can query any video format
if it supports HDR
through its
'isVideoHDRSupported' property.
Currently, only non-binned video formats
support HDR.
If HDR is supported, set videoHDRAllowed
in the config to true
and run your session
with that configuration.
Turning on HDR
will have a performance impact,
so make sure to only use it
when there is a need for it.
In use cases where you prefer
manual control
over settings such as exposure
or white balance,
there is now convenient way
to directly access an AVCaptureDevice
and change any of its settings.
In our code example,
call 'configurableCaptureDevice
ForPrimaryCamera'
of your configuration to get access
to the underlying 'AVCaptureDevice'.
Use this capability to create custom looks
for your ARKit app,
but keep in mind that the image is
not only used as a rendering backdrop,
but is also actively used by ARKit
to analyze the scene.
So any changes like strong overexposure
might have a negative effect
on the output quality of ARKit.
You can also perform some advanced
operations, like triggering focus events.
For more information on how to configure
AVCaptureSessions,
please refer to the AVCapture
documentation on developer.apple.com.
Finally, ARKit exposes EXIF tags
to your app.
They are now available with every ARFrame.
EXIF tags contain useful information
about white balance,
exposure, and other settings
that can be valuable for post-processing.
That concludes all updates
on the image capture pipeline.
Let's see which changes we have
for Plane Anchors.
Plane anchors have been a popular feature
since the very first version of ARKit.
Many of you expressed the need to have
a cleaner separation of plane anchors
and the underlying plane geometry.
For that reason, we are announcing updates
on the behavior of the plane anchor
and the geometry of the plane.
This is an example of a typical
plane anchor in iOS 15.
At the beginning of the AR session,
it fits the plane
to this well-textured notebook
on the table.
When running the session,
the plane is gradually updated
to account for new parts of the table
that come into view.
Every time the plane geometry is updated,
the anchor rotation is updated as well
to reflect the new orientation
of the plane.
With iOS 16, we introduce a cleaner
separation between plane anchors
and their plane geometry.
Plane anchor and geometry updates
are now fully decoupled.
While the plane is extending
and updating its geometry
as the full table comes into view,
the anchor rotation itself
remains constant.
When contrasting with the old behavior
on the left hand side,
you can see that the plane anchor
in iOS 16 has stayed
at the same orientation,
aligned to the notebook,
throughout the whole AR Session.
All information on plane geometry
is now contained in a class
called ARPlaneExtent.
Rotation updates are no longer expressed
through rotating the plane anchor itself.
Instead, ARPlaneExtent contains
a new property, rotationOnYAxis,
that represents the angle of rotation.
In addition to this new property,
planes are fully defined
by width and height,
as well as the center coordinate
of the PlaneAnchor.
Let me show you how to create this
plane visualization in code.
First, we generate an entity
based on a plane mesh
according to the specified
width and height.
Then we set the entities transform
according to the rotation on y axis
and also offset it by the value
of the center property.
Every time the plane is updated, we have
to account for the fact that width,
height, and center coordinate and
the new rotationOnYAxis might change.
To make use of this new behavior,
set your deployment target to iOS 16
in your Xcode settings.
The next update is on MotionCapture,
our machine learning masterminds worked
hard to make further improvements.
There is a whole suite of updates,
both for the 2D skeleton,
as well as for the 3D joints.
For the 2D skeleton
we are tracking two new joints:
the left and the right ear.
We also improved
the overall pose detection.
On iPhone 12 and up,
as well as on the latest iPad Pro
and iPad Air models with the M1 chip,
the 3D skeleton, as shown in red,
has been improved.
You will experience less jitter
and overall more temporal consistency.
Tracking is also more stable
if parts of the person are occluded
or when walking up close to the camera.
To make use of the improved MotionCapture,
set your deployment target to iOS 16
in your Xcode settings.
Next, I would also like to announce
new cities and countries
where LocationAnchors will be supported.
As a small reminder,
Apple Maps uses the LocationAnchor API
to power its pedestrian walking
instructions.
In this example you can see that it can
lead you through the streets of London,
thanks to the power of LocationAnchors.
LocationAnchors are already available
in a growing number of cities
in the United States and in London, UK.
Starting today, they will be available
in the Canadian cities of Vancouver,
Toronto, and Montreal.
We are also enabling them in Singapore,
and in seven metropolitan areas in Japan,
including Tokyo.
As well as in Melbourne and Sydney,
Australia.
Later this year,
we will make them available in
Auckland, New Zealand,
Tel Aviv, Israel,
and Paris, France
If you are interested to know
if LocationAnchors are supported
at a particular coordinate,
just use the checkAvailability method
of ARGeoTrackingConfiguration.
And those were all the updates to ARKit 6.
To summarize, I presented how to run ARKit
in the new 4K video format.
For advanced use cases,
I demonstrated how to enable HDR
or get manual control
over the AVCaptureDevice.
For even more pixel hungry applications,
I demonstrated how to get high resolution
photos from an ARKit session.
We talked about the new behavior
of Plane Anchors,
and I presented the new ear joints
and other improvements in MotionCapture.
You also got to know
in which countries LocationAnchors
will be available later this year.
Thanks for tuning in.
Have a great WWDC 2022!