[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> I am Michael Diu from the
Interactive Haptics Team.
And I am forward to sharing the
many advances in haptics in iOS 13
with you.
Let's take a look at our agenda.
First, we'll find out where we
can use Core Haptics.
How it fits in with other audio
and haptic APIs.
And we'll talk about the two
groups of classes in the API.
And the basic dimensions and
descriptors that we will use to
describe our haptics and audio
content.
We're going to walk through the
basic recipe to start playing
out that content.
And then we're going to move on
to introducing dynamic
parameters.
And dynamic parameters are a way
that you can customize your
haptic patterns at playback time
in response to your user or your
apps behavior.
And we're going to explore a new
way to express, store, and share
your audio haptics content.
A new file format we're calling
the Apple Haptic Audio Pattern,
or AHAP.
So let's get to it.
First, what is Core Haptics?
We can think of it as an
event-based audio and haptic
rendering API.
Or synthesizer for iPhone.
We can continue to use our other
audio and haptics and feedback
API's like AVAudioPlayer and
UIKit's UIFeedbackGenerator in
parallel with Core Haptics.
You might be wondering, "Which
iPhones can I use this on?"
With one, just one API and one
file format, we will be able to
access hundreds of millions of
haptic engine-equipped iPhones
starting from iPhone 8 onward.
And we've taken care that your
haptic patterns will have the
same feel across all of these
products.
So much so that you're going to
be able to prototype and release
just using one product.
And these iPhones aren't
equipped with just any old
commodity actuator.
They all have the Apple-designed
taptic engine.
Which offers you that unique
combination of power, a wide,
expressive range, and an
unmatched precision and control
and subtlety.
Next, I'd like to talk about
those of you who have already
started adopting haptics on
iPhone with UIKit's
feedback-generated API's.
Now Core Haptics is not a
replacement for this API.
In most cases, you want to keep
on using FeedbackGenerator,
especially for UIKit controls
and adding haptics to that.
With that API, you indicate the
design intent for your event.
Whether that's a selection, an
impact, or a notification.
And you let someone else, Apple,
worry about developing a
vocabulary to express that and
mixing the right modalities like
audio haptics animation to
communicate that message.
Now, this API is also being
improved in iOS 13.
So please check out its
documentation for more details.
In contrast, Core Haptics is
good when you want to be your
own sound and haptic designer.
With it, you develop your own
patterns.
And you can have a lot more
control over exactly what time
it gets played.
So you can synchronize with
other API's like an animation
from Core Animation.
Or a sound event from
AVAudioEngine.
You have a much richer set of
playback and modulation
controls.
Now, UIKit is built on top of
Core Haptics.
So both API's share the same
low-latency performance
characteristics.
Now
designing your own haptic
patterns is going to take more
time.
But when it allows you to do
something that you couldn't
otherwise do and when it allows
you to differentiate your app,
then it's worth thinking about.
Now next, I'd like to talk a bit
more about those audio
capabilities.
So Core Haptics is also an Audio
API.
And so that allows you to play
short, synthesized or custom
waveform audio in
synchronization, tight sync with
your haptics.
This type of audio haptic
duality has been crucial to many
of Apple's own haptics
experiences.
Like the haptic home button in
iPhone 7, the haptic crown in
Series 4 Watch, and the
UIDatePicker, those scrolling
wheels that you use to select
dates and times and alarms and
calendars.
And you may not have realized
that.
You may not even have noticed
that there was audio in these
experiences.
But if you were to cover up that
audio once you take it away,
you'll realize that it's an
inseparable an integral part of
that experience.
So now, you can do the same with
Core Haptics in your own apps.
And I want to talk about some
categories of apps, one app -- a
huge category in particular
where you might want to think
about Core Haptics, and that's
games.
So imagine we are at the race
track.
We want to go into turbo mode.
Let's imagine.
[ Engine Sounds ]
When you've got that brute force
message to deliver, think about
using synchronized haptics and
audio in your app to generate
those visceral explosions and
rumbles.
Now another very nice
application is for to simulate
physical contact to make your
applications feel more
realistic.
Think about a tennis game.
You could have audio and haptic
components where the pitch of
your audio, the intensity of
your haptics are proportional to
how fast your swing is or how
centered the ball lands in the
middle of the racket.
And you can even control how
long the strings your racket
will resonate for after the
impact.
So another great area to think
about using Core Haptics is in
augmented reality apps.
And there, if you're working in
this space, you're already
familiar with the benefits of
having high visual fidelity
paired with 3D audio working in
concert.
Now we can reach for that next
level of immersion by
considering how custom haptic
feedback can ground our user
gestures,
or respond to app, device, and
AR object events.
For example, moving your device
around or moving your entire
users around.
As an inspiration this year,
we've enhanced the Swift Shot
sample code by using haptics
that are modulated based on how
fast you pull back the sling.
How fast you pull back your
phone.
You're going to feel the tension
building up as you stretch it
back.
And then a very satisfying thunk
as you release.
I'd like to show you a video of
this and I'm going to use audio
to represent just the haptics
that you're going to feel.
They're going to sound like
this.
[ Low-Pitched Noise ]
Now, we're going to see the
whole thing together.
Visuals and haptics, no regular
audio.
[ Low-Pitched Noise ]
So that was an example of how we
can use haptics, sound, and
visuals all synchronized
together to enhance our AR
experience.
Now these are just a few
categories of apps, games, and
AR that are ripe for creative
explorations, with haptics and
the corresponding sounds.
I'm sure you're going to think
of many, many more.
So now let's get into how we can
start expressing our content
with Core Haptics.
There are just two groups of
classes in Core Haptics.
There's those to represent your
content.
And those to playback that
Let's take a closer look at the
content side first.
The basic indivisible content
elements is in Core Haptics is
called a CHHapticEvent.
Now, each event has a type and a
time.
And optionally, parameters that
will customize its feel.
These events can overlap each
other and when they do, they
mix.
And all events are grouped into
a pattern.
Next, I'd like to talk about
those types of events that we
can have.
Our first type is called the
HapticTransient.
The HapticTransient, I think of
it as a gavel.
It's a striking motion.
It's momentary and
instantaneous.
And then we have two continuous
types.
We have HapticContinuous and
AudioContinuous.
And there I think of, for
example, bowing a stringed
instrument.
It is longer than a transient.
It can be, for example, used as
a background texture.
And you have a much richer set
of knobs that you can use.
For example, to modulate the
resonance of it.
Lastly, we have the AudioCustom
type.
And the AudioCustom, as we -- as
I mentioned earlier.
Is where you can provide your
own audio to be played back in
sync with the haptics.
Next, let's talk about some of
those optional parameters.
Our first event parameter is
called HapticIntesnity.
And it has an audio analog,
audio volume, which you're
probably already familiar with.
Now, with this parameter, you go
from no output as you turn, and
as you turn the knob from zero
all the way up to one, you go to
the maximum output of the
system.
Our next parameter is called
HapticSharpness.
Now HapticSharpness is a new
concept.
There's no physical analog to
this and there's also no audio
analog.
In this world, I want you to
instead think of moving along in
a perceptual space from a very
round and organic feel at zero,
all the way to a more crisp and
precise feel at one.
And to help ground that a bit
further, I'm going to use some
examples from iOS 12.
The flashlight button on your
lock screen is an example of a
very high sharpness haptic.
And the App Switcher, that swipe
up, that's an example of a more
round, a lower sharpness haptic.
As for the why.
Why were those two types of
experiences, you know, sharp and
not sharp?
I'm going to refer you to our
talk on Audio Haptic Design.
Now, we have several more types
of event parameters, for
example, that apply to audio,
like pitch and pan.
And for haptics, we have things
that let you change those
resonance and so forth.
But these two, intensity and
sharpness, will be enough to get
us going.
Now, to develop a feel for that
dynamic range and precision of
intensity and sharpness.
We've got a sample code, the
palette, which allows you to try
out these experiences for
yourself.
As you move, as you tap, or you
drag your finger around, you'll
be accessing the sharpness axis,
as well as the intensity axis.
And it's going to play out the
corresponding continuous or
transient haptic as you do that.
This will help you get that
intuition.
So that was an introduction
about where we can use Core
Haptics and also how to specify
our content.
Now, let's invite Doug Scott,
our Core Haptics architect, to
get us started with playing back
Core Haptics, playing back those
patterns, and integrating Core
Haptics into our apps.
Please welcome Doug.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Michael.
Good evening, everyone.
I am thrilled to be here to talk
to you about integrating the
Core Haptics API into your
applications.
Before I show a demo and dive
into the code, let's walk
through the basic steps that
your application will follow
when you want to play a haptic
pattern.
Creating your content is the
first good step because this can
be done at any point prior to
the point where you need to use
it.
In this example, we load an
NSDictionary into a haptic
pattern.
The dictionary might have been
something that we stored in our
application as part of our
resources.
As we will see later, patterns
can also be created right before
they are to be played if they
need to very interactively in
response to changes in your
application.
The next step is to create an
instance of the haptic engine.
This should be done as soon as
your application knows that it
will be making use of haptics.
Next, you create a haptic player
for your haptic pattern.
Each player is associated with a
single pattern and a particular
haptic engine.
Starting the haptic engine tells
the system to initialize the
audio and haptic hardware in
preparation for request to play
the pattern.
At the moment that your
application wants the pattern to
play.
You start the player.
This can be done in two modes.
The first is called -- which we
call immediate mode tells the
system that you wish this
pattern to play at the soonest
possible moment with the minimal
latency.
The second, in scheduled mode,
you hand it an absolute
timestamp which tells the system
that you want to synchronize
this event with some other
systems such as another audio
player or a game event or a
graphics event.
If you want to know when your
pattern is finished playing, you
can have the haptic engine
notify you via callback when
your player or players are done.
Here, the engine calls back to
the application.
And the application can now
choose to stop the haptic engine
or continue on with the next
haptic pattern.
Those are the basic steps.
Now let's see an example of an
application which uses this
system.
But before we do, we need to let
you in on a secret demonstrating
the use of an API which
generates tactile feedback
prevents -- presents a unique
problem.
You in the audience can't feel
it.
The way we handle this was by
adding an audio equivalent for
each haptic event into the
output which will let you hear
the effect of the haptics.
This application uses a simple
physics engine to move the ball
around the screen in response to
the accelerometer.
[ Knocking Sounds ]
It generates haptic and audio
feedback when the ball impacts
the edges of the screen.
The user has the sense they are
feeling the impacts through the
edges of the game wall as well
as hearing them.
The harder the ball hits the
edge, the more intense the
haptic and the louder the audio.
Okay, let's look at the code for
this example to see how to
integrate the Core Haptics API
into your application.
We'll see how event parameters
are used to produce changes in
the haptics and audio.
The example here, all this code,
is taken from the sample code on
the website.
But it's been edited down to
show the important points.
First, we import the Core
Haptics module.
Along with the other modules we
need for the application.
The CHHapticEngine is declared
as a member variable of our
ViewController because we want
to be able to control its
lifetime and have it exist for
the lifetime of the application.
As discussed in our flow chart
earlier, we set up the haptic
engine in advance of when we
want to use it.
Here, we call a helper method at
the point that the view has
loaded.
In the helper method, we began
by creating the instance of the
haptic engine and check for
possible errors.
The engine is assigned to our
member variable so we can keep
it around.
It is optional, but extremely
useful to assign a closure to
the engine's stoppedHandler
property.
This will be called if the
engine is stopped by some action
other than the application
itself asking it to.
Some possible reasons that this
might happen are an audio
session interruption or the
application being suspended.
We finish this method by
starting the haptic engine and
checking for possible errors.
The engine will continue to run
until the application, or a
possible outside action stops
it.
Note that the application tracks
whether or not the engine needs
to be restarted.
Typically, you might leave the
engine running for the entire
time that you have any view
visible on the screen which has
haptic interaction.
Here's the location in the
application where the simple
physics engine lets us know that
the ball has collided with the
wall.
In this example, we want to
generate our haptic and audio
pattern to interactively track
the velocity of the ball.
So the pattern player and its
pattern are created at the
moment they are needed.
This method is responsible for
creating the pattern to be
played in response to the ball
collision.
In here, we will create a
pattern with two events.
One haptic and one audio.
We create a haptic event of type
hapticTransient to produce that
impactful feel.
And we give it two event
parameters which configure the
event's sharpness and intensity,
which you've heard about
already, based upon the velocity
of the ball.
Then, we create the audio event
with type audioContinuous with a
set of event parameters for
volume and envelope decay also
calculated from the ball's
velocity.
The sustained parameter here
assures us that the intensity of
this event will die off to zero
instead of continuing on for the
length of the event.
We create a pattern containing
these two events synchronized in
time.
Finally, we create the pattern
player from this pattern and
return it to this layer, back in
the method that responds to the
collision.
The final step is to start the
pattern player at time
CHHapticTimeImmediate, which
indicates to play it back as
soon as possible with minimal
latency.
Notice that the app does not
hold on to the instance of this
player.
Its pattern is guaranteed to
continue playing until it is
finished.
So the application can simply
fire and forget it.
And that's the basic recipe for
playing your content using a
pattern that is created
programmatically within your
app's code.
Again, because this app is
continuously interactive we
don't stop the haptic engine
until the game screen is no
longer visible.
Now let's take a moment to talk
about one of the most powerful
capabilities of Core Haptics,
dynamic parameters.
Dynamic parameters let you
increase and decrease the value
of the existing event parameters
for all active and upcoming
events in a pattern as it plays.
Dynamic parameters take effect
at the timestamp you provide.
You can adjust multiple
different parameters at the same
time or with any arbitrary time
relationship.
You can include dynamic
parameters when you create your
pattern.
or send them to your player in
real time during playback.
This allows you to use a single
pattern to generate an infinite
number of haptic and audio
variations by adjusting the
pattern dynamically.
Let's take a look at an example.
In this diagram, on the bottom,
we have a haptic pattern that
was designed with all haptic
event intensities set to their
maximum value.
The first half are
HapticTransients.
The second half is the
HapticContinuous.
We'd like to reduce the
intensity of all the games
haptics temporarily.
For example, if a game -- if a
character was speaking in the
game.
I send a dynamic parameter for
intensity with a value of 0.3
that takes effect at time .5
seconds.
You can see that it reduced the
intensity of the event at that
time significantly to about a
third of what it was unmodified.
Finally, let's look at another
way to create patterns.
So what exactly is AHAP?
The Apple Haptic Audio Pattern
is a specification for
describing a Core Haptics
pattern in a text-based format.
It is built from nested key
value pairs which become quite
familiar for you, to you once
you start working with the
classes which make up the Core
Haptics API.
It is a schema for the widely
established JSON file format.
Which means you have already
quite a number of different
frameworks which can read,
write, and edit these, including
such things as the Swift Codable
framework.
AHAP makes it easy to share and
edit haptic patterns because it
is a format that all developers
can agree on.
Loading your haptic patterns
from external AHAP files allows
you to separate your content
from your application code.
Using the magic of a slide deck,
we're going to create a simple
AHAP file here.
We start with a version string.
Which indicates which version of
the system this pattern was
designed for.
Next, we add the key for our
pattern.
Which will be an array of
dictionaries.
We add our first event
dictionary to our pattern array.
This event has two required key
value pairs.
A time in seconds at which the
event should happen relative to
the start of the pattern and the
type of event.
This is a haptic transient event
starting as soon as the pattern
starts.
To this event, we add event
parameters which will affect
only this event.
These are stored in their own
array of dictionaries.
We add an event parameter to
control the intensity of the
event and another to control its
sharpness.
We can add a second event in the
same fashion.
This one starts at an offset of
.5 seconds from the first and is
of type HapticContinuous.
For the event parameters, we use
the same as we had for the first
event.
Events type HapticContinuous and
AudioContinuous require an event
duration in addition to the time
and event type.
This duration value is always
specified in seconds.
Here is a visual representation
of the pattern we just created.
You can see the two types of
events; the HapticTransient at
the very beginning, the
Continuous later with a relative
timing and duration and their
intensity and sharpness
parameter values.
That was a quick tour of AHAP.
This diagram shows a summary of
the AHAP file structure.
A single pattern consisting of
an array of event dictionaries,
optional dynamic parameters, and
optional use of parameter curves
which are an extension of
dynamic parameters.
Which you can read about more
on, within the information that
we have on the website.
You can find a full link to the
AHAP specification on our
sessions page.
Also on our sessions page,
you'll find a code example that
shows how to create, load, and
play the patterns described by
AHAP files.
This haptic sampler app includes
a range of patterns that
highlight the subtlety, dynamic
range, and audio haptic sync.
That's possible with the Core
Haptics API.
Thank you very much.
And now, I'd like to return the
stage to my colleague, Michael.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Doug.
So although we covered a lot of
ground today there is still much
more to discover with Core
Haptics.
Check out the online doc
reference for details.
Once you're up and running with
the basics of specifying
contents and playing that
content you'll probably be
wondering about the design
principles for these joints
haptic audio patterns.
You'll be wondering do the
rules, the guidelines for sound
design carry over to haptic
design?
What are some common pitfalls I
should be aware of?
The good news is that our Audio
and Haptic Design teams have
been doing this for years and
they've helped put together some
advice and guidance in an
updated human interface
guidelines or HIG for haptics.
As well as in the accompanying
talk in WWDC this year.
Check it out.
So let's recap.
Today, we talked about where
haptics can help you reach for
that next level of immersion and
make your app interactions more
effortless.
Having synchronized and
complimentary audio and haptics
together is a particularly
effective combination.
But there haven't been API's
that allowed you to actually do
this.
With iOS 13, we now have the
necessary ingredients to create
these rich multimodal
experiences.
We have the vocabulary to
describe haptics and audio
events and a file format, AHAP.
We've got a new performant API
Core Haptics which is designed
for low latency and real-time
modulation.
We've put together sample code,
sample patterns, design
guidelines, and support from
Apple.
And lastly, you've got an
incredible audience, incredible
hardware where you can feel your
haptics as you intended.
A huge installed base of taptic
engines that give you the most
powerful, expressive, and
precise haptics hardware
available.
So please come on down to the
labs on Thursday and Friday
where you can check out some of
these haptics samples that we
showed today and discuss your
own ideas for your apps.
You'll also find all of these
guidelines and references online
at our sessions page.
I know you're going to have a
lot of fun creating and using
these haptic patterns in your
apps.
We can't wait to hear and feel
what you come up with.
Thank you, and good night.
[ Applause ]