[upbeat music]
[Michael] Welcome to
"What's New in UIKit"
in iOS 15.
My name is Michael
and later I'll be joined
by my colleague Jamie.
iOS 15 is packed full of amazing
new technology and features.
We've updated UIKit in some
exciting ways to help you
adopt these new capabilities.
Together, Jamie and I will cover
productivity updates,
UI refinements,
API enhancements,
performance improvements,
as well as some
new security and privacy features.
Productivity is at the heart
of iPadOS,
and this year
is no exception,
with updates
to iPad Multitasking,
keyboard navigation,
keyboard shortcuts,
and iPad pointer,
just to name a few.
Let's start with a short
demo of how we've updated
Multitasking to take
iPad to the next level.
In Mail,
we are using the new
center scene Multitasking
feature to make it
easier than ever to focus
on a single message.
Just long press on
a message to open
the context menu and select
“Open in New Window."
This will open the message
in its own UIWindowScene
in the center of the screen.
This is a great way to focus
on the task at hand.
The new center scene
can also be moved to Split View
using drag and drop,
or by choosing the Split View
option in the new
Multitasking menu at
the top of the window scene.
Alternately, you can swipe down
on the Multitasking menu
and dock the scene
in the new window shelf.
Adding this functionality
to your app is as simple
as creating a new window
scene activation action.
This action takes a closure
that returns
an activation configuration,
created with an NSUserActivity
that can be handled by your app.
Add this action to a context
menu and you're all set.
With iPadOS 13.4 we
introduced the Magic Keyboard
and a pointer.
In iPadOS 15 we've
improved pointer support
by adding band selection.
In addition to providing
new API,
we've enabled band
selection by default
for UICollectionViews
that support multi-selection.
We've also added pointer
accessories that allow you
to communicate additional
context or hint at functionality
by combining secondary shapes
with any pointer style.
Multiple accessories
can be displayed at a time
and positioned
around the pointer.
They have the same fluid
nature as the pointer,
and the system seamlessly
animates
between different accessory
shapes and positions.
In iPadOS 15,
we've completely redesigned
the keyboard shortcut menu.
With categorized shortcuts
and built-in search,
finding the shortcut
you're looking for
has never been easier.
The new Keyboard Shortcut menu
also provides increased parity
between iPad and Mac Catalyst
versions of your app.
To take full advantage
of these new features,
you need to adopt UIMenuBuilder.
Implement
buildMenuWithBuilder
on your UIApplicationDelegate.
Assign commands to one of the
pre-defined categories
such as “View" or “File"
or even create your
own custom category.
To use categories, you will need
to audit your application
for uses of UIResponder's
keyCommands property.
Move any commands
assigned to this property
to the buildMenuWithBuilder
function.
To learn more about
Multitasking, iPad pointer,
and the new Keyboard Shortcut
menu, we have an amazing video
all about taking your iPad apps
to the next level.
We've also added rich
support for focus based
keyboard navigation
in iPadOS 15.
If you're already familiar
with the focus system on tvOS,
then you'll be happy to know
it's now available
in iPadOS as well.
In fact,
all focus navigation in tvOS,
CarPlay, iPadOS, and Mac Catalyst
are now built on UIFocusSystem.
With UIFocusSystem
on iPad and Mac Catalyst,
the arrow keys are used
to move between focus items
and the tab key
to move between focus groups.
In this example,
the Mail application is using
UISplitViewController
with a sidebar,
and when using
these standard UIKit components,
keyboard navigation
as demonstrated
will be enabled
by default in iPadOS 15.
Check out "Focus on
keyboard navigation"
to learn more about supporting
keyboard navigation
in your app.
Another essential
productivity feature of iOS
is multi-touch Drag and Drop.
Introduced in iOS 11,
Drag and Drop
has been an essential
productivity enhancement.
With one simple gesture, you can seamlessly
move data within
the application and on iPadOS
even between applications.
With iOS 15, UIKit has enabled
inter-app drag and drop
on iPhone as well,
unlocking many
exciting new interactions.
For example, It's now
easier than ever to quickly
share an idea for a new
watch band with a friend.
With one gesture,
you can simply drag a photo
from Safari right into
a Messages conversation.
The Drag and Drop APIs have
not changed to support
this expanded capability.
For a refresh of the technical
details,
we have four great videos from 2017
that go in-depth on how to take
advantage of Drag and Drop.
Next, I'll show you some
of the UI refinements
in iOS 15.
We refined the appearance
of UIToolbar and UITabBar.
This updated look removes
the background material
when scrolled to bottom,
giving more visual
clarity to your content.
In UITabBar, we've enhanced
support for SF Symbols,
giving great results when using
any of your favorite symbols.
While UIKit does its best
to make this new appearance
seamless in your app,
there are a few issues
you may encounter.
You should audit your
code for places where you
may be setting a bar's
translucent property to false
and check
for any UIViewControllers
that have non-standard
edgesForExtendedLayout.
Both of these conditions
will cause visual issues
with the new appearance.
If the new default behavior
is not appropriate for your app,
just create a custom
appearance and assign it
to the scrollEdgeAppearance
property on your bar.
This property
was previously only available
on UINavigationBar
but is now also available
on UIToolbar and UITabBar.
Setting a custom appearance will
avoid any of the visual issues
causes by the previously
mentioned incompatible APIs.
Additionally,
it is possible UIKit won't
be able to infer the proper
scroll view for observation
when performing the new scroll
edge appearance transitions.
To directly
specify the scrollView,
we've added a new function
on UIViewController —
setContentScrollView for edge.
Look at all your bars.
Make sure the appearance
is what you expect.
Be sure to check anywhere
you've done something
special —
it might need extra attention.
We have a new appearance
for headers in iOS 15.
For plain lists, section headers
now display seamlessly
in line with the content,
and only display a visible
background material
when becoming pinned
to the top as you scroll down.
In addition,
there's new padding inserted
above each section header
to visually separate
the sections
with this new design.
You should use this plain style
in conjunction with index bars
for fast scrubbing
when list content is long
as demonstrated
in the Contacts app.
UIKit also
offers a grouped style.
This is for use
in UI that doesn't contain
a lot of custom
or visually rich content.
This is a great choice
for configuration UI
or registration flows
similar to what you'd find
in the Settings app.
The prominent header style is
very similar to the existing
sidebar header style used
for sidebar lists on iPad.
Prominent headers
are a great choice to use
when adapting a .sidebar list
to an .insetGrouped list
in a compact size class.
The alarm tab in the Clock
app makes great use
of this new style.
And finally, we have a new extra
prominent grouped style
for use with content
that is visually rich
so that headers maintain
hierarchy
and avoid becoming lost.
Check out the Watch app's
Face Gallery
to see this style in action.
To access all of these
great header styles,
use the
UIListContentConfiguration API
introduced in iOS 14.
In iOS 14.5 we introduced
UIListSeparatorConfiguration
that allows full control over
separators in a list.
You can specify a configuration
for the entire list,
or you can override
the system-generated appearance
on a per-row basis, giving you
full control over separators.
Sheets in iOS 15 gain
the ability to only cover
half the screen, displayed
at what we call
the medium height detent.
With this new half
height functionality,
you can optionally disable
dimming behind this detent
to create a non-modal
experience
allowing interaction both within
and behind the sheet.
Watch "Customize and resize
sheets in UIKit"
to learn about all the ways
we've enhanced sheets in iOS 15.
Next up UIDatePicker.
And yes, In iOS 15,
we are reintroducing
the wheels of time.
But now,
you can simply tap the time
to use the keyboard for input.
And with Magic Keyboard on iPad,
you can even
edit the time right in-line.
Of course,
you can still tap the screen
to reveal those beautiful
wheels.
And with that, I'll hand it
off to my colleague Jamie.
[Jamie] Thanks, Mike!
I'm going to start out
looking at some more
enhancements to UIKit APIs
in iOS 15.
Our first API enhancements
is in many ways
also a UI refinement.
We've added new APIs
to UIButton, to allow you
to flexibly configure
your button's look and feel.
As well as the existing Plain
style, we've added Gray,
which has a gray background,
Tinted, which has a tinted
background,
and Filled,
which is entirely opaque.
In addition to the new styles,
buttons now better support
resizing in response to the
system "text size" setting
known as Dynamic Type,
and for the first time
formally support
multi-line text.
These changes, and the new
UIButton.Configuration API
that enables them,
don't just make buttons
more powerful,
they're also more customizable
and easy to update.
Together with the UIMenu
additions to buttons
released in iOS 14,
UIButtonConfiguration
allows you to make pop-up
and pull-down buttons natively
in UIKit for the first time.
And, of course,
if you're using UIKit on Mac,
and you've chosen in Xcode to
"Optimize Interface For Mac",
these buttons all look
and behave
just as
you'd expect them to.
Here's an example of how easy
the API is to use.
Just create a button
configuration.
This constructor
gives the Tinted style.
The configuration's properties
are used
to customize the button.
And then instantiate the button,
passing in the configuration.
It's not shown here,
but the only thing left
is to add an action,
and add the button to your view.
There's a lot more to
UIButtonConfiguration than I
can cover here, so there is
a full video covering it,
and other improvements
to UIButton, in detail.
Check out
"Meet the UIKit Button System"
to learn
all about the button APIs.
UIContextMenuInteraction
on iOS and iPadOS
now supports collapsible
submenus.
They appear when you tap
on any item with a chevron
like the "Sort By" item
in this menu.
There's no new API for this.
The UIMenu API already
supports submenus,
but prior to iOS 15,
they replaced the current menu
entirely when you tapped
on them.
This is also discussed
a little more in the
"Meet the UIKit Button System"
video.
In iOS 13,
we introduced SF Symbols —
hundreds of scalable
symbols that look great
next to our San Francisco fonts.
In iOS 15,
these get even better.
Not only are there additional
symbols, but we've added
the ability to use colors
in three new ways:
Hierarchical, Palette,
and Multicolor.
Monochrome symbols are
the single-color tintable images
you already know and love.
Hierarchical symbols
apply a single
runtime-specified tint color
to a hierarchy of layers.
Palette symbols
allow multiple colors
to be explicitly specified.
And Multicolor symbols,
previously available
only in AppKit and SwiftUI,
have a fixed
multicolor representation.
New APIs for using all
these colorful modes
are available in UIKit,
SwiftUI, and AppKit.
The APIs are really easy to use.
This code sets
up a UIImageSymbolConfiguration
to use the system orange color
as a basis for hierarchical tinting,
and then uses that to create
this image of a hierarchically tinted
orange sun symbol.
If you regularly use SFSymbols,
you know they come
in a few style variants.
For example, filled,
on circles or on rectangles.
In previous releases, these
are selected by specifying dotted strings.
In iOS 15, there is a new UIImage API
that makes working with these variants
super easy,
whether you want
to specify the type up-front,
or to generate
a variant of an existing image.
This is the symbol
represented by the "heart" string,
and two of its variants,
which can now be selected in code.
There are lots of videos about all aspects
of SF Symbols in the "Design and build
SF Symbols" collection,
and I encourage you to check them all out.
There's more on the UIKit API specifically
in "SF Symbols in UIKit and AppKit."
UIContentSizeCategory traits
represent the system text
size setting, also called
the dynamic type size, in code.
You can set your labels, textfields,
textviews, and image views —
perhaps containing SFSymbols —
to automatically adjust to the setting.
In iOS 15,
we've added a new way to restrict
how the traits
are applied to view hierarchies.
This enables you to easily set
a floor or ceiling for the size.
This can be a great help when
you're making sure
your app's text and images look great
at every text size setting.
Here, Clock is limiting how
small its large time labels get.
Please do not use this API
to unduly limit text size.
These settings serve
an extremely important function,
and it's paramount that your app's
functionality is all available,
and everything is legible, to people
using the highest text size setting.
So as another example,
you might use this to limit
the growth of a headline that's
already very large at the default size.
We've unified the system colors
across all of our platforms.
What does this mean for UIKit?
Well, there are some subtle
changes to some of the colors,
and some colors previously
only available in other frameworks
are now also available in UIKit
wherever your app is running.
So if you've
been itching to use systemMint
or systemBrown in your UIKit app,
now is the time.
Also new is UIColor.tintColor.
It's a color that's resolved at runtime,
based on the app
or trait hierarchy's current tint color.
It's perfect for using with the new
UIButton.Configuration,
and the new colorful SF Symbols APIs.
Along with UIColor,
there are also enhancements
to the UIColorPicker ViewController,
the standard interface
for mixing and picking colors.
In iOS 14.5, there's a new callback,
colorPickerViewController(didSelect:continuously:),
that allows app UI to be updated
as the color is mixed and changed,
as well as when the picking is complete.
TextKit 2 is the new,
next-generation text layout system
available in iOS,
iPadOS, tvOS, and macOS.
It's a powerful new system
that makes it easier
to express what you want to do
with text,
and it does it in a fast,
high performance way.
UIKit has adopted it behind the scenes
to power UITextField,
where it brings
better layout to text
in languages with complex scripts,
like Kannada
with no adoption required.
If you want to know more about TextKit 2,
what it can do,
and how to use it in your apps,
watch "Meet TextKit 2."
A UISceneSession represents
an instance of your application's UI,
and corresponds to an app window
represented in the app switcher.
Interface state is represented
by an NSUserActivity.
Your app provides this
NSUserActivity to the system
when a scene enters the background,
and should use it to restore
the interface state
when the scene is reinstantiated.
In iPadOS 15, there are a few new
APIs to make this easier.
There's a new way to get and set
the transient state
of our text input views.
There's a new UIScene
callback that provides
a more convenient place to restore
state after a storyboard loads.
And there's an opportunity
to extend the app launch process
and delay when your app's UI
becomes active
if you have asynchronous
model code that returns state.
All our engineering efforts
are focused on the UIScene-based APIs.
If you're still using the old
UIApplication-based lifecycle
from before UIScene was introduced
in iPadOS 13,
now is the time to switch to UIScene.
All UIKit apps can use it. Supporting
multiple windows is not required,
although, for iPad and Mac apps,
it is a great idea.
For a refresher on UIScene,
and more details on the enhanced
state restoration APIs, watch
"Take your iPad apps to the next level."
Speaking of scenes,
in UIKit in iOS 15,
there are new APIs
that allow apps to represent
the currently sharable content that's
being interacted with in each scene.
They're used by the new Siri "Share
This" feature on iOS and Mac,
and by the
NSSharingServicePickerToolbarItem
on Mac Catalyst.
There are a lot more details in the
"Design great actions for Shortcuts,
Siri, and Suggestions,"
and "Qualities of a great
Mac Catalyst app" videos.
For our last API enhancements,
we'll return to our dear friends,
UICollectionView and UITableView.
In iOS 14, we introduced new
APIs to allow you to configure
the look and feel of cells much more
easily and consistently than in the past.
In iOS 15, new
closure-based update handlers
make it easier than ever
to reconfigure your cells.
No longer do you need to create
a cell subclass and override
updateConfiguration using state.
You can now write
that code inline,
in the same place you create the cells.
Here, we're greying out our text
when the cell is disabled.
Similar closure-based functions
are available in
the new UIButtonConfiguration APIs too.
We've improved diffable data
source to make it easier to update
your collection and table views.
In iOS 15, when you apply a snapshot
without animating differences,
the UI updates based on those changes
without discarding all the existing cells.
And there's new API
to efficiently reconfigure items,
so you can update the content
displayed in existing cells
when the properties of items change
without their identity changing.
Every device that UIKit runs
on has multiple processor cores,
and powerful graphics hardware.
Things should happen fast. Animations
and scrolling should always be smooth.
In iOS 15, there are a few enhancements
and new APIs
that make buildings apps
with these characteristics even easier.
Let's talk about a few of the ones
that are available in UIKit.
First, we'll return
to UICollectionView and UITableView.
iOS 15 introduces
changes to cell prefetching.
These changes automatically
take effect when you build for iOS 15.
They can give apps up to twice
the amount of time —
almost two visual frame's worth —
to prepare cells
while keeping scrolling perfectly smooth.
Many cells show images.
In the past, you might have noticed
momentary interruptions in scrolling
when the main UI queue is tied up
decoding large images.
In iOS 15, app code can take
more control over this process.
There are new easy functions to prepare
images so they're completely ready
when your app needs to display them.
And these functions are easy to use
asynchronously,
so the UI queue can be free to process
events while the images are being decoded.
Many apps handle large images,
but display them at small sizes.
To help with this,
there are new UIImage APIs
that resize images more efficiently —
and save memory —
by using the system's knowledge
about the images and the display.
For more details of these collection view
and image improvements, information about
how you can take advantage them,
and some other great performance tips,
check out "Make blazing fast
lists and collection views."
Swift has introduced new features
that make writing asynchronous code
easier than ever.
Most UIKit APIs must be
called on the main UI queue,
and we've annotated those APIs
as Main Actor to ensure
that this is enforced,
for the first time, at compile time.
In other areas,
like the new UIImage preparation features,
we've tweaked our APIs to ensure
that UIKit is easy and safe to use
with the new asynchronous
Swift language features.
Check out "Meet async/await in Swift"
and "Meet AsyncSequence"
to get going with this new way
of developing asynchronous code.
Now, security and privacy.
We've built some new technology
into iOS 15 that allows the system
to verify what interface is
really being interacted with.
We've integrated
this into UIKit in a few places,
and here, I'm going to talk
about three that might affect your app.
First, the Location Button.
OS 15 introduces a new APIs allow apps
to embed buttons that grant case-by-case,
one-time access to the device's
current location.
They do this when, and only when,
they are tapped on
without lots of alerts or prompts.
The API is flexible, so it can match
every app's look,
but behind the scenes, it ensures buttons
are always clear and legible,
or they won't work.
There's a whole video discussing
how to embed this into any app,
"Meet the Location Button"
I'm sure you've
noticed this banner, introduced in iOS 14.
It's shown when
an app access data that's been copied
onto the pasteboard
in a different app.
In iOS 15, we're eliminating the banner
any time the system can confirm
that the data was accessed
after deliberate interaction
with a standard
system paste interface.
For example, a tap on the paste button
in the editing menu,
or a Cmd-V on a hardware keyboard.
We've also added API to provide
few new standard Paste menu items.
When these are used, the notification
banner is also not displayed.
We provide new ways to specify "Paste,"
"Paste and Go,"
"Paste and Search,"
and "Paste and Match Style."
For each of these, there are standard
UIResponder selectors —
for use with UIMenuController
and UICommand —
and new identifiers —
for use with UIAction.
Sometimes an app
wants more information
about what's on the pasteboard,
but doesn't need full access.
In iOS 14, we introduced an API that apps
can use to check if there is a number,
probable web URL, or probable
web search term on the pasteboard.
And we use these ourselves
in Calculator and Safari.
In iOS 15,
this API has been greatly expanded
to cover all
the standard Data Detectors types.
None of these will show the notice,
because they don't grant access
to the data itself.
There are also APIs to retrieve
the data values without having to parse
the text yourself, although if these APIs
used at any time other than after the use
of a standard paste interface,
the system will show the paste notice.
Our last privacy enhancement was new
in iOS 14.5, and built on an early version
of the technology that powers
the location and paste interfaces.
UIEventAttribution was developed
in conjunction with the WebKit team.
WebKit's Private Click Measurement feature
provides Web-to-Web Click Measurement.
UIEventAttribution brings PCM to UIKit,
and provides App-to-Web Click Measurement.
This means privacy-preserving
measurement of ad clicks and taps.
It's easy to use — just cover your ads
with UIEventAttributionViews,
and pass a UIEventAttribution object
along with any URLs you open
in response to ad taps.
To learn more about this, see the "Meet
privacy-preserving ad attribution" video.
There's also a great WebKit.org
blog post entitled
"Introducing Private Click Measurement."
Well, that was quite a whirlwind, and we
didn't even cover everything that's new.
What's next?
Please go and compile
your app using the iOS 15 SDK.
Test out new features like Drag and Drop
on iPhone and our enhanced system colors.
Adopt the new
iOS 15 look with new buttons,
bars, lists and symbols.
Adopt our new iPad features
for better multitasking,
keyboard, and trackpad support.
And use the new UIKit APIs
to respect user privacy,
and make even better,
even faster apps, even more easily.
Thank you.