[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[David] Hi.
Welcome to Meet Safari
Web Extensions on iOS.
I'm David Quesada,
an engineer on the Safari team.
And today, I'll be walking
through an exciting new feature
in iOS 15, Safari Web Extensions.
Web Extensions are a powerful type
of browser extension
that allows users to extend
and customize their browsing
in a huge number of ways.
They're built with the standard
web technologies:
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
And the WebExtension API
has been available
for all the major desktop browsers
for a while, which means you can write
a browser extension once and deploy it
across all those browsers,
reaching so many users.
But now, I'm thrilled
to tell you that Web Extensions
are coming to iOS 15, letting you build
a browser extension
for more users than ever.
I'd love to show you a demo now
of a Safari Web Extension
running on iOS.
I'll be showing off
an extension called Sea Creator.
This extension was originally written
for browsers on the Mac,
but I've been working
on bringing it to iOS.
This extension shows me fun facts
about sea creatures
and makes reading more about sea life fun
by replacing the names
of sea creatures with emoji.
Let's take a look at this on an iPad.
Now, I've just installed Sea Creator,
and I've opened up Safari,
where I'm reading an article about fish.
I'd really love to start
using Sea Creator here
so I can liven up this page
with some emoji.
So I'll open up the action menu
and drill into the new Extensions list,
which shows me all the extensions
that I have available,
including Sea Creator.
So I'll turn it on.
Now, another feature
of Sea Creator is that
I can put it front and center in Safari
with a custom Start Page
that I use every time I open a new tab.
I'll check that out in a bit.
And now that I've turned on Sea Creator,
it's right there in the Action menu
ready for me to use.
And when I do that,
Safari asks me if I'm OK
with giving Sea Creator
full access to this site.
We brought the same
Web Extensions permission model
from Safari on the Mac to iOS,
which means I, as the user,
have full control over how much
of my browsing extensions can access.
I'll talk in more detail about this later.
But right now,
I'll allow Sea Creator to run.
And just like that,
it swapped in all
these fish emoji on the page,
which is just how I like to read it.
It's also opened this popup
showing me a running total
of just how many words
I've replaced so far.
But it's not just this one page.
I gave Sea Creator permission to work
across this website as a whole.
So as I navigate to other pages,
Sea Creator is still working for me
and gives me emoji here as well.
I don't need to go out
of my way to open the extension again
once I've started using it.
Of course, Sea Creator
has one more feature
that I mentioned earlier.
When I open up a new tab
to do some more browsing,
I'm greeted by this bold New Tab page
from Sea Creator with a fact of the day
today about starfish--
and once again, that counter showing me
just how many emoji Sea Creator
has given me so far.
This is pretty cool.
So that was a quick look at Sea Creator
working great on iOS.
In this session, I want to show how
you too can create
a Safari Web Extension for iOS.
And I'll be using
Sea Creator as an example
of how I took an existing extension
and brought it to iOS
with just a few changes.
But don't worry if you've never
written a browser extension before.
I'll give you an overview
of how Web Extensions work
and how you can get
started creating a new one.
Along the way, I'll cover
some debugging techniques
and best practices
to help your extension
be the best it can be.
And I'll wrap it up with
some thoughts on user privacy
and how it relates
to the permissions model
of Safari Web Extensions.
So, our journey begins
with creating a web extension
that can run on iOS in the first place.
Let's look behind the scenes
to understand how this works.
It's important to understand
that for Safari,
Web Extensions are parts of apps.
So when you want
to install a web extension,
you install its app.
And like any other type of iOS app,
apps with Safari Web Extensions
can be found on the App Store.
And Xcode has everything you need
to build an app to ship your extension.
So when you think about building
a Safari Web Extension for iOS,
you may be starting
from one of three places.
Maybe you're looking at creating
a new extension from scratch,
or maybe you already
wrote one for another browser,
and you want to bring it to Safari,
or perhaps you already
have an extension for Safari
on the Mac, and you want
to make it available on iOS too.
I want to go over what you can do
in each of these cases.
So first, if you want to create
a brand-new Web Extension,
you can use Xcode's included templates,
which make it super easy to get started.
You can create a new Xcode project
and use the Safari Extension App template
to start building a web extension
as well as its containing app.
And when you use this template,
you get an extension that comes complete
with all the resources
a typical web extension might have.
You can use this as a starting point
by customizing what's already there
or adding or removing pieces
according to what your extension needs.
Now, if you've already built
a Web Extension
for another browser,
you can take advantage of a tool
called the Safari Web Extension Converter
to automatically create an Xcode project
from that existing extension.
You simply run the converter
on the command line,
provide it a path
to your extension's resources,
and it will create a new Xcode project
that packages your extension
in a native app.
And new in Xcode 13,
the Safari Web Extension
Converter creates a project
that supports Safari on both iOS
and macOS by default.
And the newly created project, by default,
references your existing
extension's resources
at the original path
rather than copying them.
Finally, if you've already
set up an Xcode project
in the past to build
a Safari Web Extension for macOS,
you can also use the converter
to upgrade that project
so it supports iOS too.
You can run the converter
and provide a --rebuild-project option
along with a path to your Xcode project.
Then the converter will add
an iOS-compatible version
of the extension and a containing app
to your project.
Now I want to show
the Safari Web Extension Converter
in action by retracing my steps
of bringing Sea Creator
to iOS for the very first time.
So here is my Sea Creator Xcode project,
which I used to develop Sea Creator
for Safari on the Mac.
But it only supports the Mac right now,
and I want to fix that.
So I'll open up a terminal
and type xcrun
safari-web-extension-converter,
and I'll use the --rebuild-project option,
and I'll provide a path
to my Xcode project
and run the converter.
And it confirms some details
about my existing project
and stops to ask me
if I'd like to overwrite it
with a cross-platform version.
Also, any time you run the converter,
it'll warn you about potential
compatibility issues with your extension.
In this case,
it's warning me about the use
of something called
a persistent background page,
which isn't supported on iOS.
I'll need to fix this later.
But for now, I'll let
the converter keep going.
And when it's done,
my project automatically opens.
Notice there are folders here
for both the iOS
and macOS versions
of my app and the extension.
Now, I want to take a look
at the Resources folder
within the Shared extension group.
Here is where I'll find the core pieces
of the Sea Creator Web Extension.
For those of you who are new
to the Web Extension API,
I want to explain
what some of these pieces are,
since I'll be referring to them later.
I'll start with the manifest.
This is a JSON file
that describes
the structure of the extension.
It includes important information
such as the extension's name,
which websites it wants to access,
and what features it supports,
such as a pop-up page or a New Tab page
like Sea Creator has.
Next, there's a JavaScript source
called the background script.
The browser can run this script
in the background
when your extension is enabled,
and it allows your extension
to listen for various events
coming from the browser
or other parts of your extension.
Sea Creator's background script
keeps track of that counter
of just how many emoji
it's added to web pages.
Next, there's another type of script
called the content script.
The browser automatically runs this script
on web pages that the user visits.
An extension can have
any number of content scripts,
and the manifest specifies
which content scripts
should run on which websites.
This script gives your extension
the power to extend
and customize pages
by directly manipulating them.
For example, Sea Creator's
content page is what actually does
the replacement
of animal names with emoji.
And after it does that,
it sends a message
to the background script
so it can update that central counter.
Of course,
the extension also has some HTML,
CSS, and other JavaScript files
for the New Tab page,
and that pop-up page as well.
And finally, there are
some other resources here
such as localized strings,
as well as the extension's icons
and other graphics.
So all of these pieces come together
to make the Sea Creator Web Extension.
And thanks to the Safari
Web Extension Converter,
I now have a project that packages all
of this up into a native app.
And I can run my project now,
so I can start using Sea Creator
in Safari right away.
I'll do that now by going to the toolbar
at the top of the screen,
selecting Sea Creator for iOS,
and choosing the destination
where I want to run the app.
I don't have any iOS devices connected,
so in this case,
I'll use an iPhone simulator.
I'll then click the Run button.
And Xcode will then build my app project,
load the simulator, and run my app.
So this is the Sea Creator app
generated by the Web Extension Converter,
and it contains
the Sea Creator Web Extension.
At the beginning of this session,
I showed that I can turn on extensions
directly within Safari,
but as the app suggests,
I can also use Settings
to manage my extensions.
And I want to show that off here,
so I'll switch to Settings.
I'll jump into Safari,
Extensions,
and then Sea Creator.
And here's the details page
for Sea Creator with some info
about the extension
and a switch to turn it on.
But that switch is grayed out,
and I can't turn on the extension yet.
This means there's a problem
with the extension
that keeps it from loading.
I definitely need to look into this next.
And this is where I want
to talk about debugging.
It's a great first step to just be able
to build your project
and install your extension,
but of course, it's essential to know how
to dig deeper to find out
why things go wrong if they do.
It's easy to identify errors
in web extensions and use tools
such as Web Inspector
to debug parts of your extension,
and that's what I'll show you now.
Looking back at Settings,
there's an error here
at the bottom telling me
that Extensions on iOS
must have a non-persistent
background page.
This sounds familiar.
It's the same issue the converter
warned me about earlier.
And now I want to actually go fix it.
So I'll go back to Xcode,
open up the manifest,
and add a "persistent": false key
in the background section.
I'll talk about this change
in more detail later,
but for now, this should
get me past the error.
Now that I've made this change,
I'll run the app again
to install the updated
extension on the simulator.
And here's the Sea Creator app once again.
It looked like I only
had that one error to fix,
so now I'll go straight to Safari
instead of going back to Settings.
I'll open up Safari,
open the Extensions list,
and there's Sea Creator,
and it looks like I can turn it on now.
Safari offers me the choice
to use Sea Creator's New Tab experience.
And I do want to check
out what that looks like
on iPhone since I haven't seen it before.
So I'll set that as my New Tab page,
close out the Extensions list,
and open up a new tab.
And just as I'd expect,
there's that New Tab page
from Sea Creator.
But the text is really small,
and the page just doesn't look good.
This is the first time I've ever run
this extension on iOS,
so it's not surprising
that the content hasn't yet
been adjusted to work well with iPhone.
I want to go fix this now, and to do that,
I'll use Web Inspector to take
a closer look at this page
and try out a few changes I have in mind.
So to get to Web Inspector,
I'll open up Safari on my Mac,
and then I'll double-check
in Safari's Advanced Preferences
to make sure I have
the Develop menu enabled.
And now that I have that Develop menu,
I can open it up,
select the iPhone Simulator
I've been using,
and choose a page to inspect.
Now, there are two options
here for Sea Creator.
I could select
the Extension Background Page
if I'd like to debug
the background script,
but in this case, I want
to inspect the New Tab page.
So I'll choose the other option.
And now I'm in Web Inspector.
The first thing I want to address here
is the overall size of the page.
By default, Safari on iPhone
renders the web page
as if it were the size
of a desktop browser,
and then it scales
that larger content down
so it all fits on screen.
But I don't want this behavior here
since it makes the text too small.
So I'll use a very common practice
when it comes to web design for iPhone.
I'll add a viewport meta-tag
to tell Safari
not to scale the content this way.
I'll select the Head element,
add a Child element,
and add the contents
of that viewport meta-tag.
I'll add the tag,
and the page updates live
in the simulator
in response to that change.
Now all the text is at a readable size,
but it doesn't all fit on screen,
which is my next problem.
I want to inspect the elements
on this page
to understand why it lays out like this.
I'll look at the body tag,
and I notice there's this div here
that contains all the content on the page.
If I focus it
and look in the stylesheet
sidebar to the right,
I notice that the element
has a fixed width of 850.
That would make sense on a desktop,
where windows can be really wide
and you'd want the text
to wrap at some point.
But that doesn't work on iPhone
because the phone just isn't that wide.
I think it would make more sense here
if that rule set a maximum width
for the content
rather than demanding an exact width.
And I can simply edit the rule here.
I'll click width
and change it to max-width,
and the page in the simulator updates
to reflect that change.
Now the content's width is much
more appropriate for iPhone,
and all of the text fits on screen.
This looks much better now,
but these changes that I've made
are only temporary
to this Inspector session.
I want to actually save these changes back
into my project so I don't lose them.
And it's really easy
to save an updated copy
of the stylesheet while I work
in the stylesheet Inspector.
I can simply type Command+S
to save my stylesheet
that has that updated rule.
And I'll overwrite the new_tab_page.css
in my project.
But for the viewport change,
I added that tag
to a live web page
rather than a static resource,
so I'll have to make the same
change to the original source.
I'll select that tag,
copy it,
go back to Xcode,
open up that source for the New Tab page,
and paste the contents there.
So the next time I run Sea Creator,
it'll use that updated
page source and stylesheet,
and it'll look just as good again.
And that's been a few examples
of using Web Inspector
to look under the hood of a web extension,
understand exactly what's happening,
and experiment with potential changes
while iterating on the extension.
For now, I'm only going
to look at the New Tab page,
but later on in development,
I should obviously go test
all the other parts
of the extension on iOS,
and I'd use the same tools
and techniques for that.
You can use Safari's
extension settings on iOS
to view any errors in the configuration
of your Web Extension.
Specifically,
Sea Creator had the fatal error
of using a persistent background page,
but there may also be
non-fatal warnings here
that you should check out.
These details will only appear in Settings
for debug builds of your app from Xcode
and not for copies from
the App Store or TestFlight.
As you make changes to your web extension,
you simply run your app again
to update the extension
on the device or simulator.
And of course, Web Inspector allows you
to investigate issues with
your extension's web content.
Remember that in order
to access Web Inspector,
I had to enable the Develop menu
in Safari's Advanced Preferences
on the Mac.
In my demo, I used the iOS
simulator for my extension,
but if you wanted
to use a physical iOS device,
you would also need
to enable Web Inspector support
on that device
in Safari's Advanced Settings.
To take a deeper dive into Web Inspector
and learn about some
of its newest features,
check out Discover Web Inspector
improvements.
Now that I've created
a Safari Web Extension for iOS
and I've debugged a few basic issues,
I'd like to walk through some
best practices to keep in mind,
including some things
you might need to watch out for
as you build an extension
for Safari on iOS.
I'll focus on five topics
that may be relevant to your extension,
starting with non-persistent
background pages.
The background page
is a web page that the browser loads
to run your extension's background script.
And this page allows
your extension to handle events
sent by the browser
or other parts of your extension.
But keeping this page loaded
has a performance cost.
It can use memory and power
as if you were keeping one more tab
open and running
for every enabled extension.
Keeping all these pages
loaded all the time
can be pretty wasteful.
But you can make
a background page non-persistent,
which means the browser will
only load it when your extension
actually needs to do work,
and the browser can later
unload that page
when it's been idle for some time.
That way, the performance cost
is only paid
while your extension
is doing something useful.
This is important because
background pages must be
non-persistent on iOS, where system memory
and battery life are especially
at a premium.
The web extension templates
in Xcode already come
with a non-persistent background page,
so they're ready to run on iOS.
But if you have an existing extension
that uses a persistent background page
like Sea Creator did,
you'll need to change it
to be non-persistent.
And you can do that by adding
that "persistent:" False key
in the background section
of your manifest.
To learn more about some best practices
and potential issues you may face
when updating an extension
to use a non-persistent background page,
check out
Explore Safari Web Extension Improvements.
Up next,
let's talk about responsive design.
As we learned with Sea Creator,
bringing an extension to iOS
means its web content may be rendered
in new environments
that you haven't considered before.
Just like I did
with Sea Creator's New Tab page,
be sure to test the layout
of your extension's web content
on iPhone and iPad
and use a responsive design
that can accommodate various screen sizes.
But the difference in screen size isn't
the only consideration when it comes
to making your web content
look great on iOS.
Let me tell you about a few things
you should be aware of.
If your extension has
full-page web content
that lays out important elements
near the bottom of the screen,
you may find it being covered
by Safari's Tab Bar
or the device's home indicator.
In CSS terminology,
this area near the edge
of the screen where
content may be partially hidden
is called the unsafe area,
while the usable area
of the viewport is called the safe area.
By using CSS environment variables,
you can calculate the safe area inset
to make sure important elements
are positioned
within the safe area.
On iPhone, this is also
worth considering in Landscape,
where devices may have safe area insets
on the left and right side
of the display as well.
By using similar CSS
and by specifying
the viewport-fit parameter
in your viewport,
you can give your web content
an edge-to-edge design
that still keeps important
content within the safe area.
Check out Design for Safari 15
to learn more about these APIs
that can make your web content
feel more at home on iOS.
On iPad and desktop browsers,
if your extension has a pop-up page,
you may be used to it
being shown as a popover
that's comfortably sized
to fit its content.
But on iPhone, however,
Safari will display
this web page as a sheet,
which may be a surprise to your content.
The sheet spans the full width
of the device,
and it may be laid out taller
than the content expects.
In this screenshot of
an early version of Sea Creator,
the content didn't have much padding
from the edge of the screen,
and we set a background color
on an individual element
in the page rather than on the body.
So the text looks a bit cramped
and the background doesn't fill
the whole page.
But we've since updated the alignment
and padding of the content
to give it a little more space to breathe,
and we now specify a background color
on the body so it covers the whole sheet.
If your extension has a pop-up page,
think about whether you should
make similar changes
for your extension.
And note that Safari will use
a similar presentation
in Landscape as well.
Be sure to test your extension's interface
in these configurations to make
sure its layout makes sense
when given this extra space.
And finally
among the design considerations,
I want to mention Dynamic Type.
Dynamic Type is a feature
that allows users
to adjust the size of text
and other visual elements.
You can make content smaller to fit more
or larger so it's more visible.
Be sure to test your extension's interface
under smaller or larger text sizes
to make sure it looks all right
with any size the user chooses.
To help your web content
make the most of Dynamic Type,
WebKit has a variety of system fonts
that respect
the user's text size preference
and resize to match.
You should adopt
these fonts in your extension
so that its text remains
comfortably readable to the user,
just like the rest of Safari's interface.
So the main takeaway here is
to design your extension's web content
with Safari's UI in mind.
Test any full page web content on iPhone
to make sure that it adapts well
to the screen size
and doesn't clash with Safari's UI
at the bottom of the screen.
You should test your pop-up
web page on iPhone to make sure
its layout makes sense
with the sheet-style presentation,
and you should test your interface
across a wide range of Dynamic Type sizes
to make sure it adjusts
for the user's preference.
For more tips on designing
web content to look great
in Safari's new interface,
check out Design for Safari 15.
Up next, pointer events.
If your extension currently depends
on handling mouse events
for arbitrary clicks and drags,
be aware that the same events
won't be sent when the user taps on iOS.
You should instead adopt
the Pointer Events API.
It's similar to the Mouse Events API,
and it works just the same
with mouse input,
but the Pointer Events API
also reports touches
and Apple Pencil input.
And now let's talk
about the Web Extension Windows API.
On desktop browsers,
users may have multiple windows open
and your Web Extension can use
the browser.windows API
to work with these windows.
And the same is true on iPad,
where you can also
open multiple windows of Safari.
Each Safari window might be full screen,
or it might be in split view,
side-by-side with another app,
maybe another Safari.
Under the hood though,
each of these windows is actually
called a scene on iOS.
If your extension uses the Windows API,
you should know that each scene
of Safari actually has two windows:
one for regular browsing
and one for Private browsing.
This is also true on iPhone,
even though there's
only one scene of Safari.
If I call the browser.windows.getAll API
to query what windows are open,
then the API returns
these two window objects.
In the first window,
the incognito property is false,
and focused is true.
This represents the window I'm looking at,
which is in regular browsing
and not Private Browsing.
The second window holds
the Private Browsing tabs
in the Safari scene.
And of course, its properties are
different from the first window.
Incognito is true, and focused is false.
Now when I switch Safari
to Private Browsing
and call windows.getAll again,
the API returns different window objects.
Now the focused property
has changed in both windows,
and the second window now has focus.
This works exactly the same on iPad
where one Safari scene
is represented by two windows.
But if I open a second scene
of Safari in split view,
the API would now report four windows.
And if my extension listens
for the windows.onCreated event,
it would observe that event fire twice
when opening split view,
once for each of the two new windows
in the new Safari scene.
So if you use this API,
keep this model in mind
as you encounter extra windows
you might not expect at first.
In addition to this model
of what a window actually is,
there are a few limitations
of the windows API
that may affect your extension.
The methods to create, remove,
and update the state of windows
aren't available.
On iOS, window placement
is fully controlled by the user,
not any app or extension.
The windows.onRemoved event won't be fired
as you'd maybe expect
when the user closes Safari
from the app switcher.
That doesn't truly close
or remove a window.
It just leaves it for the user to pick up
where they left off later.
And note that these restrictions
only apply
to the windows themselves
and not the tabs within those windows.
With the browser.tabs API,
Web Extensions still
have full control to add,
remove, and update
individual tabs as they'd like.
Now, last up in the best practices
is feature detection.
When bringing
an existing extension to iOS,
you may find some APIs are unavailable--
for example, the windows APIs
that I mentioned a moment ago.
But there are a few others,
like context menus
and WebRequest.
If non-essential parts
of your extension use such APIs,
be sure to use feature detection
to handle the case
that they're not available.
So, instead of unconditionally
calling these APIs,
conditionalize that code based
on the existence of those APIs,
so you can cleanly exclude parts
of your extension
and make it more flexible when it comes
to which browsers it supports.
You should also use this pattern
when adopting new APIs
that are added in the future,
as they might not immediately be available
across all browsers
or in previous versions
of browsers that some users
may still be using.
And that wraps up the best practices.
I've now covered many parts
of Safari Web Extensions,
but I've saved arguably
the most important topic for last,
and that's user privacy.
User privacy is a huge part
of everything we do,
so we believe users
deserve transparency and control
when it comes to how
their personal data is handled.
And of course that includes
everything they do in Safari.
Web Extensions can gain
a tremendous amount
of access to the user's browsing,
so the decision of whether
that should be allowed
and on which websites
should be up to the user.
Historically, other browsers
would give an extension
full access to every website it requests
right away when you turn it on,
which is potentially asking you
to sacrifice privacy up front
just to get a taste of the extension.
But Safari aims to do better
by providing transparency
and control to Web Extension users
with an opt-in model where
extensions are only given access
to websites when the user consents.
You caught a glimpse
of this earlier with Sea Creator.
It didn't immediately
start modifying my pages
when I turned it on,
but it was only able to do that
when I explicitly told Safari,
"Yes, I want to use this extension here,
and I'm okay with it having access."
And once I give an extension that access,
Safari tells me in the Tab Bar
that I have an extension running
on this page,
so I know that the extension
might be seeing my web browsing here.
But if I navigate to any website
that I haven't yet allowed
the extension to access,
that indicator disappears.
And I know that that extension
isn't running on this page
and can't see what I'm doing here.
Let's look at this permissions
model in more detail.
Again, users opt in to your extension
when they choose to use it
on specific websites.
Safari will ask the user for consent
by presenting a dialog
which makes it clear
which websites the extension
is trying to access.
This happens when the user
invokes your extension
by selecting it in the Action menu
or by using any of its keyboard shortcuts.
And this consent is required
for any privacy sensitive API to work.
Specifically,
any API that reveals the URL
or title of a tab
will only include this info
if your extension has
permission for that URL.
The Cookies API will
only let your extension
read and write cookies for websites
your extension has permission for.
And injecting JavaScript
and stylesheets will
only be allowed on websites where,
you guessed it,
your extension has permission.
If your extension's scripts
call any of these APIs
when your extension doesn't
have the required permissions
but hasn't asked the user yet,
Safari will wait to call
your completion handlers
and will show a non-disruptive banner
at the top of the screen.
This lets the user know
that your extension
wants some more access,
and they can then review the set
of websites your extension is asking for,
and they can make a decision to allow
or reject access for those websites.
You should avoid requesting
more permission this way
than your extension really needs.
For some types of extensions,
this way of thinking about permission
might be a bit more than you need.
For example, extensions that share or
annotate
individual web pages
don't need full access to the site
any time the user visits in any tab,
but rather they just want permission once
to do one thing at a time for the user.
And there's a great solution
for those extensions
called the activeTab permission.
When your extension requests
the activeTab permission,
Safari will automatically
grant your extension permission
on tabs where the user
explicitly uses your extension.
And this permission will be limited
to just the current website
in just the current tab.
So it'll be revoked
if the user navigates that tab
to a different website.
Safari won't display a prompt
when granting this permission,
since there's no long-term
commitment needed from the user.
To adopt this feature,
simply add activeTab
to the Permissions
section of your manifest.
So all of this is to say that in Safari,
users are always in control
of which websites
their extensions can work on.
So be aware that your extension
won't automatically be able
to go to work
on every page the user visits.
For many extensions,
the activeTab permission
is a great way
to get access to just the pages
where the user is using your extension
without bugging them
about any access beyond that.
All of these concepts are the same
across all our platforms that
support Safari Web Extensions.
To see this in action
on macOS and get a closer look
at updating an extension
to use activeTab, check out
Meet Safari Web Extensions from WWDC 2020.
And that's the privacy
preserving permissions model
of Safari Web Extensions.
Along with everything else
I've covered today,
I hope this gives you a more complete view
of Safari Web Extensions on iOS
and the tools available
to you for building them.
We're so excited to see
the Web Extension experiences
that will be brought to Safari on iOS 15,
including the many extensions
we already love on the Mac today
but also the great new extensions
that are yet to come.
So if you're new to extension development,
I encourage you to check out
the linked resources
associated with this session.
There, you'll find sample code
that you can download
and try out for yourself.
And you can read more
about the Web Extension APIs
available to you
in Apple's developer documentation
and the MDN Web Docs.
If you already develop a Web Extension
for another browser
or for Safari on the Mac,
I encourage you to try out
the Safari Web Extension Converter
in Xcode 13
to easily bring your extension to iOS.
If you have feedback
like bug reports, suggestions,
or compatibility issues,
I encourage you to send us that feedback
at feedbackassistant.apple.com.
You can also reach out to us
at the Apple Developer Forums
if you'd like to get in touch
or have questions.
And finally, I'd like to again recommend
two other sessions
you may be interested in.
Explore Safari Web Extension
Improvements will teach you
about some recent API additions
to Safari Web Extensions.
And Design for Safari 15 will show you
how to make your web content look great
with Safari's new design in iOS 15.
Thanks for watching,
and have a great WWDC.
[upbeat music]