[music]
[Cindy] Hello.
I'm Cindy Clarissa.
I'm a software engineer
with Core Location.
Today, I'll be talking about
some cool new things
for Core Location this year.
We are introducing
two new features
that may let you power
location-based functionality
in your apps
without confronting people
with the need to grant them
as much authorization.
Starting with the first feature,
we are bringing Region-based
user notifications to watchOS 8.
Now your Apple Watch app
can remind people
to start a workout
when they arrive at the gym
or feed the dog
when they get home.
For example,
here we have App in the Air
using this new feature
to notify people
about their flights
when they arrive at the airport.
With Region-based
user notifications,
the system can present
spatially relevant information
on behalf of your app
without it having
"always" authorization.
To learn more
about how you can adopt
Region-based user notifications
for watchOS,
check out the session
"What's New in watchOS."
Now let's talk about
the main topic of this session.
We're introducing
a new way to request location
that gives people more
control over their data
but, at the same time, gives more
functionalities to your app.
I'll begin by talking
about today's state
of location authorization
and the motivation
behind our new feature.
In iOS 14,
when an app requests
for location authorization,
an initial prompt shows up
and people have the ability
to choose from Allow Once,
While in Use,
or Don't Allow authorization.
And with last year's
new feature,
people have the ability
to control their precision
of the location
being sent to your app.
Some of you may have noticed
that people select Allow Once
on your app,
and it could be
that they don't think giving
when-in-use authorization
is necessary to your app.
For example,
a pet store app might request
location authorization
to determine
the closest pet store near them,
but it doesn't require
their location
when they are just browsing
for different cat food options.
In this case,
people using this app might be
more likely to select Allow Once
or Don't Allow authorization.
If people select Allow Once,
we would grant
location authorization
for the duration
that they are using your app.
But your app
will lose authorization
when it enters the background.
This could lead to multiple
location authorization requests,
which may negatively
impact the user experience.
In another case,
you might notice that someone
who is tired of the prompts
might select Don't Allow
to prevent the prompts
from being shown again.
This could result
in having to send people
to Settings to authorize
for locations later.
As privacy continues to be
an important priority for Apple,
we thought,
"How can we give more controls
without
hindering user-experience?”
Can we provide
an easy and friendly way
to authorize location
only at the moment
when its needed?
Starting in iOS 15,
we're introducing
CLLocationButton for UIKit
and LocationButton for SwiftUI
to tackle the pain points
I've mentioned.
Here, we have a Park Finder app
that finds
the closest park nearby.
At the bottom,
we have a blue
Location Button
with the title
"Current Location"
next to the arrow glyph.
When I press on the button,
Park Finder is able
to get my current location
and show a map view
of all the parks nearby.
A location arrow at
the top left
will turn blue
to call to the user's attention
to the authorization
they just have granted.
One thing to note
is that Location Button
is actually giving your app
Allow-Once authorization
without making people go
through the prompt each time.
Later, I will go over
about how this would affect
your existing
authorization status.
We'll be bringing
Location Button to watchOS, iOS,
macOS with Catalyst,
and iPad apps on Mac.
Now, let's dive into the API
and how you can add
CLLocationButton to your app.
CLLocationButton is part of
the CoreLocationUI framework.
Similar to the UIButton,
CLLocationButton
is derived from UIControls.
So, you're able to use UIControl
functionalities with the button.
In addition,
we have four properties
that are specific to our button.
We have CLLocationButtonIcon
to set the type of the arrow,
CLLocationLabel to set
the label of the button,
a cornerRadius to set
the roundness of the button,
and lastly, we have fontSize
to set the size of the label.
Now that I went through a brief
overview, you might wonder,
"How can I receive location
with CLLocationButton?"
Well, it's similar to requesting
location with a UIButton.
I think it's easier
to understand with an example.
Let me demonstrate
how you can replace
your UIButton
with CLLocationButton.
In this UIButton example,
I will create a simple button
that requests for location
by first requesting when-in-use
authorization upon button tap.
I'll begin by instantiating
a UIButton
and setting it's title
to "Current Location”.
I wanna add a target-action
that calls a function
and do the necessary action
we want
every time a button is tapped.
In this case, I wanna display
all the parks nearby.
So let's call this function
"showNearByParks”.
In this showNearByParks
function,
I will use locationManager
to call
requestWhenInUseAuthorization
and startUpdatingLocation.
Within this function,
I will also add additional logic
to render
the map view accordingly.
But, for simplicity,
let's omit that.
Let's begin
by replacing UIButton
by removing the first two lines
and replacing it
with an instantiation
of CLLocationButton
and then setting the label
to ".currentLocation”.
Lastly,
we can comment out the call
to
requestWhenInUseAuthorization,
and that's because
the Location Button
will grant
a one-time authorization
on your behalf every time
a button is successfully tapped.
So if you have
an existing UIButton,
replacing it will be
as simple as shown here.
But we wanna make it
even easier,
so you can see an example
of the Park Finder app
attached to this talk.
For those with SwiftUI apps,
the Location Button
is also in SwiftUI.
You can use LocationButton
as shown in the example here.
I'd like to point out
that I am using SwiftUI's
new "symbolVariant"
to set the arrow type,
and "tint"
to set the background color
of the button.
Let's go through some examples
on how you can customize
Location Button.
With our Location Button,
you are able to customize
the background color,
the text and glyph color,
the rounded corners,
and so forth.
Here are
just some example styles
that you can
create with our button.
Let's go through
step-by-step examples
of customizing Location Button.
Let's start
with our default button.
The default look has
"Current Location" title
in white
and a systemBlue
background color, as shown here.
We can set the button icon
to arrowFilled.
Next, we can change
the foreground color of the icon
by setting tintColor
from white to black...
and then setting
the backgroundColor to white.
And lastly,
I can set the corner radius
to have rounded corners
by setting it to 25.0.
And depending on how
you set the constraints
and the sizing for the button,
if the button's width
is equal to the height,
you can create a perfect circle
when the corner radius
is half of the width.
Now, we turned
our default location button
into a white circular button
with just simple adjustments.
We've just gone through
some stylistic changes
that you can add
to Location Button.
You can customize the button
to create the perfect look
that fits your app.
However, with great power
comes great responsibility.
When customizing
your Location Button,
there are some restrictions
that you might encounter
to ensure
that your Location Button
is clear and visible.
I wanna talk
about some examples
that you can expect
if your button does not
seem to be drawn correctly
or receive any location.
If that's the case,
while your target-action
will be called,
you won't get authorization.
But don't worry.
We'll give plenty of feedback
with log messages
to help you figure out
what restrictions
you're encountering.
For example,
these are just different
log messages
that refer to the insufficiency
of the button sizing,
alpha value, and color contrast
between tintColor
and backgroundColor.
Now
let's go through some examples
of what feedback you can expect
if you're using Interface
Builder in Xcode.
Continuing with the button
I have created earlier,
if I was to change
the existing button
to have a white tintColor,
people will not
be able to see this
because the button's background
color is already white.
So if you do this,
you will see this issue
shown in the navigation pane
under the Issue tab in Xcode.
Instead, let's revert
our original button
and try to change the opacity,
or alpha, of this button.
Maybe you can see this,
but to others,
it's a little too transparent,
and so it fails
our accessibility guidelines.
A similar issue statement
is produced in Xcode,
recommending you
to increase the alpha value.
Another issue
you might encounter
is insufficient button sizing.
This is when
the content of the button
is too small or too large
for the button size.
Depending on the user's
localization setting,
the button's text length
can change.
Now let's increase the text size
by changing the language.
Depending on whether
your implementation
is Auto-layout friendly,
if we change the language,
the size of the text
could outgrow the button.
Notice that the text does
not fit the button in German.
If this happens,
look at the log messages
for feedback.
Don't forget to test
your Location Button
with really small
or really large text sizes,
as well as testing it
in different languages
to ensure that your button
is working in all cases.
So, when customizing your button,
remember that it's imperative
that it's clear and visible.
If your button does not
seem to be drawn correctly
or receive location,
it could be that
it's no longer legible.
If that's the case,
we provide log messages
for guidance
to help you determine
what could be wrong.
Now that you know how
to implement Location Button,
you might wonder
how it will affect
your existing
authorization status.
As I mentioned before,
Location Button
is essentially giving you
Allow-Once authorization.
If your app does not have
any authorization status
of any kind,
it will have
"NotDetermined" authorization
with "When I Share" selected
in Privacy Settings.
If this is
your app's current state,
then the very first time
each user presses
a Location Button,
this prompt will ask them to
confirm that they're on board.
However, if your app is
already authorized for location,
such as "While Using
the App" state,
then using Location Button
will not change
your existing state
and will behave
like any other UIButton.
Where it works,
Location Button can feel
magical and also reassuring,
because you're letting
people decide
when and whether their location
will be used each time.
Since Location Button
is much more comfortable,
we think people will be more
likely to give your app location
via Location Button
than they were previously.
So we wanna give users
and your app
another chance
to get off on the right foot.
If someone, who has chosen
"Don't Allow" authorization
on your app in the past
taps our new Location Button,
they will see this button
introduction prompt
and have the opportunity
to move your app back
to NotDetermined
and use Location Button
going on forward.
So in this session,
I talked about bringing
more dynamic abilities
to your watchOS apps
with Region-based
user notifications.
If you're interested
in learning more,
don't forget to view
the resources with the session.
We've also covered
some cool new features
that can change the game
of how you can ask for location.
Giving people more control
over their data privacy
is important to Apple.
People are increasingly
more aware
of how their data
is being shared.
When designing your app
to provide the most amazing
user experience,
but also build trust
with your customers,
you might want to ask yourself:
"Does my app require
traditional authorization,
or would a one-time
location authorization
with Location Button
be more suitable?"
And the answer, in some cases,
might be that once is enough.
With Location Button,
you can gain trust with people
by giving more control
about when they want
to share their location.
Thank you.
[music]