[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Wil Addario-Turner:
Hi, welcome to
"Embrace Expected
Failures in XCTest."
My name is Wil,
and in this session,
I'm going to discuss ways
of improving the data you get
when you run
your project's tests.
To begin with,
let's consider why we test
our code in the first place.
Of course, at a high level,
it's how we ensure
the quality of the product.
But in more concrete terms,
I would say
it's to discover bugs
before we ship
and not afterwards.
Now, testing is an investment.
It takes resources to create,
run, and maintain tests.
As with any investment,
we want to maximize our returns
while minimizing our cost.
This session focuses on tools
for reducing
the maintenance cost.
By maintenance,
I'm primarily referring
to how you handle failures
when they occur
in your test suites.
When a test that's been passing
begins to fail,
that's a valuable piece
of new information.
This indicates
either a flaw in the product,
a problem in the test itself,
or some issue in
one of the dependencies --
that is, all of the frameworks
and subsystems
on top of which
the product sits.
Regardless of the type
of problem,
once that failure
has been registered,
subsequent reports
of the same failure
are significantly less valuable,
because they represent
information
that you already have.
Ideally, any new failure
is triaged and fixed quickly.
However, your team may not
be able to resolve a problem
right away, which means
that the failure quickly goes
from being a valuable piece
of new information
to a noisy distraction.
Given a known failure
in your tests
that cannot be
immediately resolved,
what tools are available
for managing the noise?
Two approaches
that might come to mind
are disabling and skipping.
Let's consider the tradeoffs
for these
and then we'll talk
about the best tool --
and the topic of this session --
XCTest's ExpectedFailures API.
Xcode lets you disable tests
in the test plan or scheme.
You can use this
for known test failures,
and one advantage is
that your test code
will continue to be compiled.
However, since the code
won't execute,
you won't see it
in the test report.
This reduced visibility
makes it harder to track
as an issue that
needs to be resolved.
Where this feature --
the ability to choose which
tests are enabled or disabled --
really shines is for curating
collections of tests
for specific purposes.
But it's rarely the best way
to handle a known failure.
XCTSkip is another way you might
manage a failing test.
With this approach,
not only does the code
continue to get built
with your tests,
it also executes up until the
point where XCTSkip is called.
This means that it's included
in the test report,
giving you much better
visibility of the issue.
However, it doesn't
execute all of your test,
which means you lose out on
potentially useful information
in the form of new issues and
changes to the existing issue.
XCTSkip is a great tool
for managing
configuration-based limitations
on your test,
such as requiring a specific
OS version or device type.
In the example here,
the test will be skipped
if it's not running on an iPad.
This brings us to
XCTExpectFailure,
a set of functions in XCTest
specifically designed
for managing known failures.
In Swift,
it has a number of overloads
for different use cases,
and Objective-C provides
the same capabilities
with several distinct functions.
With this API,
your test executes normally,
but the results are changed
as follows:
Failure in the test will be
reported as an expected failure.
Failure in the test suite
containing that test
will be reported as a pass,
unless of course
some other test in it fails.
This eliminates the noise
generated by the failure,
making it easier to see whether
there are any other issues
in your tests.
Of course,
suppressing the noise
doesn't solve
the underlying issue.
So to help you keep track of it,
the API takes a failure reason.
This string documents
the problem in your code
and you can even embed a URL
for your issue-tracking system.
Xcode's test report UI
shows expected failures
just as it does normal failures
or skipped tests.
When you hover, if the failure
reason contains a URL,
an issue-tracking button appears
that lets you jump out
to the link.
So let's see how this works!
I have here a simple project
with some unit tests
for my VendorAccount class.
I'm going to run the tests,
and when they finish,
we'll see that one is failing
while the other is passing.
You can see
three test result icons,
one for each test.
A red X for the failing test
and a green check
for the passing test,
and one for the test suite;
a red X because one of the tests
in the suite has failed,
so we consider the suite itself
to have failed.
Now I'm going to add a call
to XCTExpectFailure
at the beginning of
the failing test.
You can see the failure reason
begins with a URL
that references
the bug I've filed
to keep track of this failure.
Now I'll rerun the tests
and we'll see how this
affects the outcome.
OK, so the red X icon
for the failing test
has changed to a gray X,
which is the indicator
for an expected failure.
What's even more interesting
is that the test suite icon
has changed from a red X
to a green dash.
This icon indicates
that the test suite has passed
with a mixed state,
meaning that one or more
of its tests did not pass,
but was either a skip
or an expected failure.
So that's how easy it is to use
XCTExpectFailure
to handle a failing test.
Now let's take a closer look
at the API.
The first consideration
when using XCTExpectFailure
is which API variant to call.
There are two approaches:
a stateful approach where
you call XCTExpectFailure
and any subsequent failure in
the test is treated as expected;
alternatively, you can use
the scoped approach,
in which you wrap
the failing code in a closure
passed to XCTExpectFailure.
Let's look at some examples.
Here's a very simple test
that calls some function
in my project.
The test begins to fail
because the function
is no longer returning true.
Here's what it looks like
to use the stateful expected
failure approach,
just as we did in the demo.
Alternatively, we could use
the scoped approach
by wrapping the failing code
in a closure
trailing the call
to XCTExpectFailure.
This means any failure
in the code outside the closure
will be reported normally.
The API also supports nesting.
In other words, you can call the
API more than once in a test,
including inside the closure
from another call.
This is an important
consideration
when using the API
in test library code.
For example, if a common
utility function begins to fail,
many tests could be impacted,
some of which might already
be using XCTExpectFailure
for different issues.
When a failure occurs
in the context of nested calls
to XCTExpectFailure,
the issue is matched against
the nearest call site first,
and if rejected by the matcher,
will be passed on
to the next call and so on
with stack semantics for
the calls to XCTExpectFailure.
For this reason,
with shared code,
it's best to use
the closure-based API
to limit the effects
on test state.
The next thing to consider
is how precisely
to match the issue.
By default, any failure
in the affected scope is caught,
but you can be more selective
by specifying
an issue-matching filter.
In this example,
we construct an object
of type
XCTExpectedFailure.Options
and define its issueMatcher.
The matcher is passed
the XCTIssue object
with the failure details,
so you have full access
to that information
in determining
whether or not to match.
If the matcher
rejects the failure,
then it won't be handled
as an expected failure.
This can be useful in detecting
when new problems show up
in the code being tested.
The options object
also has a property
that can be used to disable
the expected failure
in certain configurations.
For example,
my test may be passing on macOS
but failing on iOS, so I only
want to expect failures on iOS.
To achieve that,
I disable the expected failure
via the options,
but only for platforms
where I don't need it.
So what happens when your
expected failures stop failing?
Usually this means
the underlying issue
has been resolved,
which is great.
But how does
XCTExpectFailure behave?
If you're still calling the API
and no failure is occurring,
it will generate
a new and distinct failure.
We call this an
"unmatched expected failure"
and it's part of the strict
behavior that is the default
for XCTExpectFailure.
This behavior helps you
maintain your code
by prompting you to remove
unnecessary calls to the API.
But what about tests
that only fail some of the time?
There are cases in which
a test might fail sometimes
but not other times.
These fall into two categories,
the first of which
is deterministic
and includes environmental
or other knowable conditions
such as the earlier example
of a test that only fails
on certain platforms.
On the other hand, some failures
are inherently nondeterministic.
These might be caused
by timing issues,
unreliable ordering
dependencies,
or concurrency bugs.
For nondeterministic failures,
the strict behavior
isn't helpful;
it just generates noise.
Once again, the options object
provides a way to control this.
The isStrict flag,
which defaults to true,
can be turned off.
Then, if XCTExpectFailure
does not catch a failure,
it will still allow the test to pass.
In Swift, you can also specify
the strict behavior
as a direct parameter
to XCTExpectFailure.
Disabling strict behavior
is great way to handle flaky
or nondeterministic tests
in your project.
As an aside,
when you need to investigate
a nondeterministic failure,
Xcode makes it easy
to run a test multiple times,
stopping when it fails
or some other condition is met.
This can be really helpful
in tracking down failures
in flaky tests.
For more about this,
watch the session
"Diagnose Unreliable Code
with Test Repetitions."
So that's XCTExpectFailure --
APIs in XCTest for improving
the signal-to-noise
in your test suite results.
This helps you identify
new issues more efficiently,
leading to higher-quality code.
Thanks for watching!
♪