[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Ben Cohen: Hi, I'm Ben
from the Swift team,
and in this video,
I'm going to walk through
porting an existing application
over to use Swift's
new concurrency features.
We'll see how
these new features
help you write
clearer asynchronous code,
and protect against
possible race conditions,
as well as look
at some techniques
for gradually moving your code
to this new way of operating.
I'm going to be using an app
called Coffee Tracker,
and it's based on a talk
from WWDC 2020
about creating and updating
watch complications.
This is a simple app
that lets you track
all the coffee
you've drunk today,
as well as a complication to
show your current caffeine level
on a watch face.
It's a nice example
to use for our purposes
because although
it's a small app,
it shows lots of different
things we want to think about,
including how concurrency works
with SwiftUI,
delegate callbacks
from the watch SDK, some I/O,
and interfacing
with asynchronous APIs
in Apple's SDK.
Now let's take a quick tour
of the app.
It's roughly broken up
into three layers.
First, there's the UI layer.
This is mostly SwiftUI views,
but in this we can
also consider things
like the complication data
source as part of the UI layer.
Next there's the model layer
that comprises a couple
of simple value types
to represent caffeine drinks,
as well as a model type
called "Coffee model."
Now, this is what you might call
the UI Model.
That is, the place where
you hold data for display
by the UI layer.
It's an observable object
that feeds our SwiftUI view,
and all of the updates on it
will need to be made
on the main thread.
I'm referring to it
as a UI model
because it might not be
the full model
of all of your
application's data.
It might just be a projection
of your data model
or a subset of it;
just what you need to display
on the UI at this moment.
Finally, we have what you can
think of as the back-end layer:
processing that happens --
probably in the background --
to populate your model or talk
to the world outside your app.
In our case, that's represented
by this HealthKitController type
that manages communication
to HealthKit
to save and load
the user's caffeine intake.
Now, before we start looking
at code,
let's talk about how concurrency
is managed in the app.
This architecture
looks fairly clean,
but when we layer on
how concurrency is handled,
we get a much messier picture.
This app is essentially broken
up into three concurrent queues
on which code can be executing.
Work in the UI and on the model
is done in the main queue.
The app also has
a dispatch queue
for doing work
in the background.
And finally, certain callbacks
into completion handlers --
like those returning results
from HealthKit --
are done on arbitrary queues.
This is a pretty common
situation.
What seems like a simple
application architecture
ignores a lot
of the hidden complexity
in how it handles concurrency.
Now, for a quick spoiler.
In adopting Swift concurrency,
we're going to go from this
ad hoc concurrency architecture
to something
that will look like this.
We're going to put our UI views
and model on what's called
the main actor.
We're going to create new actors
to operate in the background,
and these types will pass
thread-safe values
between each other using
the async/await feature.
When we're done,
the concurrency architecture
should be as clear
and easy to describe
as the type architecture.
Now we've used a few terms here
you might not be familiar with,
like "async/await" and "actors,"
and we'll explain them briefly
as we use them in code.
But for a more in-depth
explanation of these features,
there are several other talks
available
that go into much more detail.
So now we've seen
the overall architecture,
let's dive into the code.
Here we have
the different files.
First, of some Swift UI views.
And then we have our
watch complication controller's
extension delegate.
We have the simple model type
that represents a caffeine drink
and a CoffeeData UI model that
holds an array of these drinks.
And finally, we have
the HealthKitController.
And it's in this layer
I'm going to get started
introducing some of Swift's
new concurrency features
into our app.
The HealthKitController contains
a few different calls
into the HealthKit SDK
that take completion handlers.
Let's start by looking at this
controller's save operation.
So I just hit Control-6,
and that brings up the list
of functions in this file,
and we're going to go
to the save operation.
Now, before we even get into
the new concurrency features,
let's talk a little bit about
thread safety in Swift today.
This code accesses
some variables,
isAvailable and store.
Now, it looks like we're only
reading these variables
in this function.
Is that safe?
Well no, not if other code
could be writing to them
at the same time.
To know whether or not
this code is thread-safe,
I need more information than
just looking at this function.
There's no use of dispatch
queues or locks in it,
so whatever makes
this code thread-safe --
assuming it is --
must be elsewhere.
Maybe the caller
serializes all calls to save
through a queue.
Or maybe the app is constructed
in some way that means it's OK.
But I can't know this just
by looking at this function.
Being able to do that --
to look at this function
and know certain things
without having to go look
at other parts of my program --
is what we call
local reasoning,
and it's a really important goal
for Swift.
For example, Swift's emphasis
on value types
is about local reasoning.
Unlike a reference type,
you don't have to worry that
a value type you've been passed
is being mutated elsewhere
in your program.
A lot of the language features
being introduced for concurrency
in Swift 5.5
are about giving you
more opportunity
to reason locally
about your code.
Now, as it happens,
this function is entirely
thread-safe,
but I figured that out myself;
the compiler isn't helping me
spot these issues.
So down here, we have a call
to the HealthKit SDK
to save a caffeineSample
into the user's health data.
And this takes
a completion handler,
and that completion handler
takes two values:
success or error.
If the operation succeeds,
there's no error;
the error will be nil.
This means we need to remember
to check the status and then,
when appropriate, unwrap
the optional error down here.
Now, this isn't normally
how we handle errors in Swift.
This would be much better
as a method
that can throw on failure.
But that approach doesn't work
with completion handlers.
But now, with async methods,
we can have asynchronous
functions that can throw.
This HealthKit save method
now has an async equivalent
that does exactly that,
so let's switch over
to using it.
To do that, first we remove
the completion handler,
and we write "await"
in front of the method call.
This reminds us that
it's an async function call,
and the code will suspend
at this point
and allow other code to run.
We'll come back to why this
is important a little bit later.
So if we compile,
now that we've done this,
we see that the compiler is
telling us that we need a "try."
And this is a big benefit
of async functions;
they can throw.
There's no more having
to remember
to check an optional error.
So we can add a "try"
in front of this method call,
and we want to handle
the error right away.
So we wrap this call
in a do block...
[KEYSTROKES]
and then catch the error.
We can remove this guard.
And now that we're catching
the error,
it's no longer optional,
so we can remove the unwrap.
[KEYSTROKES]
This also means we can
rearrange our code
to keep the happy path
at the top
so we can move
the success logging line
up right underneath the save
and then just handle
the error logging in the cache.
Notice that save no longer
returns a value.
Returning success/failure
was really duplicative
with the error,
so our new function
only either throws
or it's succeeded.
Now that we've added
the try-catch,
we're getting one more error
from the compiler.
We're calling
an asynchronous function,
but we're calling it from within
a synchronous function.
This does not work.
Asynchronous functions
have a capability
that synchronous functions
don't have:
the ability to give up control
of the thread they're running on
while they await.
To do this,
they have a separate way
of handling their stack frame,
and this isn't compatible
with synchronous functions.
So one option is to make
this function async instead.
So we can just add
the async keyword
after the function definition.
And now, this file compiles.
But the whole project
doesn't compile yet.
Making this function async has
pushed the problem up a level
to where it's being called.
Here in my data model,
I'm now getting
that same compiler error
because this function
isn't async.
Now I could keep going
up the chain, but for now,
let's see another technique
to keep the changes localized.
To call my async function,
I'm going to spin off
a new asynchronous task
which will be allowed
to call async functions.
[KEYSTROKES]
This async task is very similar
to calling async
on the global dispatch queue.
You can't return a value back
from it to the outer function
because the block
executes concurrently.
So whatever you do
with the detached closure
needs to be self-contained.
In this case,
we're just calling save,
which doesn't return a value,
so that's fine.
You also need to be careful
that you're not touching
global state that might get
mutated simultaneously
from other threads.
And this is where
it was relevant
that save was
completely thread-safe,
otherwise we might
be accidentally introducing
new race conditions
by adding this new task.
Now that we've put it inside
an async task,
our awaited function compiles,
and we've finished our first use
of async/await in this app,
we could run it right now.
Let's do another one
of those refactors
and this time,
look at some other techniques
when migrating to async.
So let's have a look at the call
to request authorization
[KEYSTROKES]
of access to the user's
health data.
This similarly calls HealthKit
with a completion handler.
But unlike before,
this function takes, itself,
a completion handler.
What I'm going to do
is I'm going to create
a second version of the function
to become async
while keeping
the completion handler version.
That way other parts of our code
that call it
with a completion handler
can keep on working
while we refactor.
I can do this easily by using
the "Create Async Alternative"
refactoring action.
That's available
in the Code Action menu --
which I can bring up
with Command-Shift-A --
and choose the option
to add the async alternative.
[KEYSTROKES]
So this has added
a second async version
of the original call.
And it's replaced the original
completion handler code
with code that creates
a new async task...
...and then just awaits the
async version of the function.
Notice that
the async refactoring
has added a deprecation warning
to the original one.
These are going to help guide me
to parts of my code
that could next benefit
from refactoring
to call this new async version.
Let's undo and go back
for a moment
to that original
completion handler version.
Inside this requestAuthorization
callback,
this callback can happen
on an arbitrary thread.
So you need to know that the
code inside it is thread-safe.
But I don't think it is.
This assignment here
might happen simultaneously
with other code reading
this value on other threads.
And there's another example
of a lack of local reasoning
in this code.
After that assignment, this
completion handler is called,
and I have no idea
whether the code
inside that completion handler
is thread-safe.
I'd have to go and look
at all of the call sites
to this function
to look at how their completion
handlers are written
to know that this is OK.
Now, let's redo again
and see the refactored version.
Now remember,
an async task also runs
on an arbitrary thread
similar to a dispatch callback.
So this forwarding version
has similar problems
to the completion handler
version we had before.
We haven't made our code
any safer quite yet.
We'll fix this soon
by introducing actors
into our code.
But for now,
we should note
that just because we've
converted this function to async
does not mean we're free
from race conditions.
In fact, you should be aware
of the risk of introducing
new race conditions
into your code
if you only perform refactoring
to introduce async functions.
Now let's look
at this new async function.
The refactoring action
has already converted
the call with
a completion handler here
to call the new async version
of this SDK API.
But converting this function
to async
has highlighted
something interesting.
Here, when we were using the
completion handler technique,
we had a return without calling
the completion handler.
And this was probably a bug.
The caller would have been
left hanging.
But with async functions,
you must return a value,
so now we're getting
a compilation error,
which we can resolve just by
returning false for failure.
And just like before,
this new async version
of requestAuthorization
doesn't actually
return a value,
it either succeeds
or it throws.
So we just need to delete
this return value.
[KEYSTROKES]
And instead on this path,
we need to assume
that it succeeded...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and on the failure path,
we need to return false.
[KEYSTROKES]
If I try and compile now,
the project compiles
because the old code elsewhere
can still continue to call
the completion handler version
and we're now seeing
these deprecation warnings
when we're doing that,
which can lead us
to a next place that we might
want to refactor.
OK, let's do one more
async conversion.
Let's find the function
to load data from HealthKit.
[KEYSTROKES]
We'll start --
just like before --
by creating a stub
for the old code to call.
[KEYSTROKES]
Then moving
to the async version,
incidentally, this one takes
an optional completion handler
the async equivalent of this
would be to make this function
have a discardable result.
[KEYSTROKES]
So next, we start moving down,
replacing any use
of the completion handler
with returns.
So for example, we can delete
this completion handler
and just return false.
[KEYSTROKES]
But once we move
a little further,
we start to hit a snag,
and it has to do with how the
HealthKit query API is arranged.
Here, there's
a completion handler
but it's on this query object;
whereas really,
what I want to await
is the execution of the query
all the way down here
at the bottom of the function.
Incidentally, this hopping up
and down around the function
is another thing
that async/await
is great at helping resolve.
So what I want to do is create
a single async function
that both creates the query
and then executes it.
We're going to do that now
using a technique
called a continuation.
So I'm to go back up
to the top of this function
and I'm going to create
a helper function
[KEYSTROKES]
called "queryHealthKit."
I could do all of this work
inside the existing function
but it might get
a little bit messy,
so I like to keep it separate
in a helper function.
This function will be async,
so we can await it,
and it will throw because
the query operation can fail.
And this function is going
to return the useful values here
that are currently
being passed into
the completion handler
on the query.
So I'm going to take the logic
for performing the query,
cut it, and move it
into the helper function.
And I'm also going to take
the execution of the query
and move that too.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now, I need to somehow
invert this code
so that it can await
the completion handler
and return these values passed
into the completion handler
back from my new
asynchronous function.
And this is where I use
a continuation.
So in this function,
we're going to return
the results of trying to await
a call to a
withCheckedThrowingContinuation
function.
And this takes a block
that takes a continuation.
[KEYSTROKES]
And we're going to move
this code inside that block
and then within the block, we're
going to use the continuation
to pass data back out
of this function either
by using the continuation
to resume throwing
the error here...
[KEYSTROKES]
...or...
...to resume returning
the values that we received
into the completion handler.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now that we have
this awaitable function,
we can use it
in our original code.
[KEYSTROKES]
So we assign the results
from calling the function.
[KEYSTROKES]
And we need to handle the error
that can be thrown.
[KEYSTROKES]
In fact, actually,
I'm going to go up here
and take this bit of logging
and do that in the handler.
And then we just need to move
all of this success code
up into the happy path.
[KEYSTROKES]
Finally, we need to address
this closure.
Here, we're using dispatch async
back to the main thread.
But we've ditched
our completion handler,
so there's no way
of relaying this information
back to the main thread
using it.
We need a different way.
To resolve this, we're going
to make our first use of actors.
In Swift's concurrency model,
there is a global actor
called the main actor
that coordinates all of its
operations on the main thread.
We can replace our
dispatch main.async call
with a call to main actor's
run function.
[KEYSTROKES]
And this takes a block of code
to run on the main actor.
run is an async function,
so we need to await it.
[KEYSTROKES]
Awaiting it is necessary
because this function
may need to suspend
until the main thread is ready
to process this operation.
But because we await it,
we can just remove
our completion handler,
[KEYSTROKES]
and instead, return a value.
OK, finally, the compiler
is now giving me an error
about a captured variable.
This is a new error
that only occurs
inside asynchronous functions.
Because closures in Swift
capture variables by reference,
when you capture
a mutable variable --
in this case,
our newDrinks array --
you create the possibility
for shared mutable state,
and that can be the source
of race conditions.
So when doing this,
you need to ensure that you're
making a copy of this value.
One way to do this
is to add newDrinks
to the closure's capture list,
like this.
[KEYSTROKES]
But often it's better
to just avoid this problem
by not having mutable variables
in the first place.
Here, we can do this by changing
the code above instead.
It's written this way
because samples is optional.
But instead what we could do
is change newDrinks
to an immutable value
and either set the value here
in the if branch
[KEYSTROKES]
or an add an "else"
to set it to the empty array.
We could also have done this
with a nil coalescing operator
if we prefer.
Since this value is now declared
with let instead of var,
it's immutable
and that resolves the issue
without needing to make
an additional capture.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now let's keep talking
about the main actor
by taking a look
at this function
that needed to be called
on the main thread.
At the top of this function,
there's something
that's a really great idea:
there's an assert
that the function
is correctly running
on the main thread.
If you had ever made a mistake
and called this function
without wrapping it
in a dispatch async
to the main thread,
you'd get an error
in your debug builds,
and you should definitely
adopt this practice
in some of your existing code.
But this approach
does have some limitations.
You might forget
to put an assert
everywhere it's needed,
and you can't assert on access
to stored properties,
or at least not without
lots of boilerplate.
It's much better
if the compiler can enforce
some of these rules for you,
so you can't make mistakes
like this at all.
And that's how we use
the main actor.
I can annotate functions
with "@MainActor."
And that will require
that the caller switch
to the main actor
before this function is run.
Now that I've done this,
I can remove the assertion
because the compiler won't let
this function be called anywhere
other than on the main thread.
[KEYSTROKES]
We can prove
that this is working
by going back to the caller
and moving this call outside
of this MainActor.run block.
And you see
the compiler tells us, no,
we can't call that from here
because we're not
on the main actor.
Here's a way to think
about this feature:
it's a lot like optional values.
We used to have values
like pointers
and had to remember check
for nil,
but it was easy to forget,
and it's much better to let
the compiler make sure
this check always happens
along with some
language syntactic sugar
to make it easier.
Here, we're doing
a similar thing,
only instead
of enforcing nil checks,
it's enforcing what actor
you're running on.
Now that we've put this function
on the main actor,
we don't, strictly speaking,
need this MainActor.run anymore.
If you're outside of an actor,
you can always run functions
on that actor by awaiting them.
And in fact, that's what
the compiler is telling us here.
It's saying that we need
an await keyword
in order to make the switch
over to the main actor
to run this function.
So if we add it,
[KEYSTROKES]
then the code will compile
even without this call
being inside the run block.
Here, we're using await
on a synchronous function --
updateModel is synchronous --
but the await indicates
that the function we're in
may need to suspend to get
itself onto the main actor.
Think of this
as similar to making
a DispatchQueue.sync call,
except with await,
your function suspends
instead of blocking
and then resumes after the call
to the main thread is complete.
So, we don't need it here
anymore,
but this MainActor.run technique
is still important
for another reason.
At each await,
your function might suspend
and other code might run.
That's the point of awaiting:
to let other code run
instead of blocking.
In this case, we only had
one function to await,
so it doesn't really matter,
but sometimes you might want
to run multiple calls
on the main thread.
For example, if you're working
on UI updates,
such as updating entries
in a table view,
you might not want
the main run loop
to turn in between
the operations you perform.
In that case, you would want
to use MainActor.run
to group together multiple calls
to the main actor
to ensure that each ran
without any possible suspensions
in between.
So, we're now using
the main actor
to protect the code that needs
to run on the main thread.
But what about other code
in this class?
In particular, the code
that mutates local variables,
like the query anchor
that we saw assigned to here.
How can we guarantee those
are free from race conditions?
Or one way would be
to just put everything
in the HealthKitController
on the main actor.
If I go to the HealthKit
controller definition,
[KEYSTROKES]
and just write "@MainActor"
here on the class instead
of on individual methods,
that would protect every method
on this type,
and every stored property on it
would be coordinated
on the main thread.
And for a simple application
like this one,
that would probably be
an OK choice.
But that also seems
a little bit wrong.
This HealthKitController is
really the back end of our app;
it seems unnecessary
to be doing all of its work
on the main thread.
We want to leave that thread
free to do
UI-focused activities.
So instead,
we can change this class
to, itself, be an actor.
[KEYSTROKES]
Unlike the main actor,
which is a global actor,
this actor type can be
instantiated multiple times.
In my project, I'm still only
going to create one of them,
but there are many
other uses of actors
where you might instantiate
multiple copies
of the same actor.
For example, you might make
each room in a chat server
be its own actor.
So now that we've made
this class into an actor,
let's see what
the compiler says.
OK. So we're getting
some compilation errors.
Now let's take a pause here
and talk about compiler errors.
These errors are guiding you
towards the places in your code
you need to update
when you're migrating code
to the new concurrency model.
When you get these errors,
make sure you understand
what they're telling you.
Resist the temptation
to mash the fix-it button
when you're not sure
how or why it'll fix the issue.
One thing to be wary of
is getting into a cascade
of errors.
Sometimes you'll make
a change --
like converting a class
to be an actor
like we just did,
or making a method async --
and it'll generate
some compiler errors.
So you go to the site
of those errors,
and it's tempting to make more
changes to fix those errors,
like making that method async
or putting it on the main actor.
The trouble is that this
can lead to even more errors,
and quickly, you can feel
overwhelmed.
Instead, use techniques
like we're using here
in this walk-through,
and try and keep
the change isolated
and done one step at a time
with your project compiling
and running in between.
Add shims to allow your old code
to keep working,
even though you might end up
deleting them later.
That way, you can gradually
move out from a point,
tidying up the code as you go.
Incidentally, what I did here
is first convert
the HealthKitController's
methods to async
and then make it into an actor.
And I find it works out easiest
if you do it that way around,
rather than starting
with the actor conversion.
OK, so let's look at these
errors by jumping down to them.
They're down here
on the function
we put on the main actor.
And this makes sense,
because in this function,
we're touching a stored property
of our new
HealthKitController actor,
the model property.
The actor protects its state
and won't let functions,
not on the actor --
such as this function
that we've explicitly put
on the main actor --
touch its stored properties.
Now looking at this function,
it looks like the only state
on the actor that it touches
is the model object.
Everything else is passed in
as a function argument.
And to me,
this suggests that this function
belongs on the model;
that the model here
actually ought to be self.
So let's move it to the model.
So we can take this function,
cut it,
go over
to our CoffeeData UI model,
and paste it in.
It's going to be internal
rather than private,
so it can be called
from the HealthKitController.
And we just need to go through
and remove all references
to the model
because that's now self.
[KEYSTROKES]
Finally, we need to go
to where it was being called...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and replace self here
with a call to the model.
So now, this HealthKitController
file compiles,
and I get a new set
of errors from other files.
Let's look at those errors.
So here we're calling into
those completion handler shims
that we called earlier
to allow us to keep passing
in the completion handler
even though we've rewritten
this function to the async.
These functions are now
being protected by the actor
so I can't call them directly.
But they don't touch any
other part of the actor's state
if we look at them.
All they're doing
is spinning off a task
and then awaiting a call to the
async version of the function.
Since they don't touch any part
of the actor's internal state,
I can mark them
as what's called "nonisolated."
[KEYSTROKES]
Do the same down here.
Marking something as nonisolated
tells the compiler
that you're not going to touch
any of the isolated state,
and therefore, this function
can be called from anywhere.
The switch over to the actor is
actually happening automatically
when we await the call into the
async version of the function.
Note that the compiler
will check
that this nonisolated claim
is true.
If I were to try and access
some state of the actor --
such as, for example,
printing out
the authorization status --
the compiler will stop me.
So now, I've completed my work
converting
the HealthKitController
into an actor that protects
its internal state
from race conditions.
Next, let's follow
those deprecation breadcrumbs
to the next file to work on,
which is our CoffeeData
model type.
Now this class implements
ObservableObject,
and it has a Published property.
Any updates to properties that
are published to a SwiftUI View
must be done on the main thread,
so this class is probably
a good candidate
to put on the main actor.
But there's also
this background DispatchQueue
for doing some work
in the background.
Let's have a look
at how that's used.
And it's just in two functions:
load and save.
That makes sense;
you probably don't want
to do your loading and saving
on the main thread.
When you see
a pattern like this --
where a queue is being used
to coordinate
some specific activities,
but the rest of the class needs
to be on the main thread --
that's a sign that you want
to factor that background code
out into a separate actor.
So let's do that.
So let's go to the top
of the file and create
a new private actor...
[KEYSTROKES]
...which we'll call
"CoffeeDataStore."
[KEYSTROKES]
And let's open CoffeeData
in another window.
and start moving code across
into our new actor.
So we can give it
its own logger.
And let's tweak the category
so we can tell
when the actor is in use.
And next, instead of
this DispatchQueue,
we're going to instantiate
a copy of our new actor.
[KEYSTROKES]
Next, let's go
to the save operation,
and move that over.
So we can take this function...
...cut it from here,
and move it into the actor.
Let's start by compiling
and seeing what issues come up.
So first, there's
this currentDrinks property.
This was a property
of the model type
before we moved this method
out of the model into its actor.
So how can we access it now?
Well, the way actors
relay information
is they pass values
between each other.
So we should have this function
take currentDrinks
as an argument.
[KEYSTROKES]
This argument to save
receives the list
of currentDrinks to save
that's passed in
by the model type.
So that resolves that.
Next, savedDrinks.
This is a copy of the values
last saved
to avoid saving unnecessarily
when nothing has changed.
This value is mutated
by both the save
and the load function,
so it definitely needs
protecting by the actor.
So let's find it in our model...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and move it over.
OK, what's next?
All right,
this property dataURL,
that's actually being used just
by the load and save operation,
so we can just move it over
to be a private helper
on the actor.
OK, last issues to resolve.
Now, here we're getting errors,
and if we look,
it appears
that there's a closure
that's capturing some state
from the actor,
so we need to fix that.
So why is there a closure here?
Well, if you look down,
it's because
the same piece of code
is getting called in two places.
And it turns out
the compiler has flagged
something really
interesting for us.
What this code is doing is
checking if the watch extension
is running
in the background.
And the idea is, if it's running
in the background already,
then don't go into
the background queue;
just stay on the main thread
and perform the task
of saving synchronously.
But this doesn't seem right.
You should never block
the main thread
to perform an I/O operation
like saving,
even when your app is running
in the background.
Why does the app do this?
Well, we can trace it back
to where the save operation
is being called.
It's being called from a didSet
down here
on currentDrinks.
And that fires so that whenever
the property is assigned,
it saves the new values.
Now, didSets
are super convenient,
but they can be
a little too tempting.
Let's look at all of the callers
of the currentDrinks property.
If we drill in
all the way down here...
...we find
that the save operation
is ultimately synchronous
because of the way it's being
called from this function
which is the call
to handle background tasks
from the WatchKit extension.
Now this handle API
has a contract.
You're supposed to do
all of your work, and then,
when all your work is done,
call this
setTaskCompletedWithSnapshot
method.
And you must guarantee
all your work is done
when you call this
because your watch app
will be suspended.
You can't have
some I/O operation,
like our save operation,
still running when you say
that you're done.
This is a perfect example
of how asynchrony
forces global reasoning
throughout your code.
Let's visualize
what's happening here.
We start in
handle(backgroundTasks:)
which calls the load
from HealthKit function.
This takes a completion handler.
But then we switch
to updateModel(),
which is performed
synchronously,
and so synchronously
calls didSet,
which synchronously saves.
Once this is done,
the completion handler is called
and that notifies WatchKit
that it's all done.
It's the synchronous parts
that force us to perform
synchronous I/O
on the main thread.
How can we fix this?
To fix it
with completion handlers,
you'd have to update each
currently synchronous method
to now take
a completion handler.
But you can't do that
with a didSet;
it doesn't take arguments,
it just fires automatically
when you update the property.
But the good news is that
all our async refactoring
is going to pay off now,
because updating functions
from synchronous
to be async is way easier.
So first, let's go
to the published property,
currentDrinks,
[KEYSTROKES]
and let's change it
to a private(set)
so that we know all mutation is
happening only from this file.
[KEYSTROKES]
And then let's take
this didSet operation
and instead move that logic
into a new function...
[KEYSTROKES]
...called "drinksUpdated()."
We'll make it async,
because it's going to call
our save operation on our actor.
[KEYSTROKES]
And that needs to be an await...
...on the CoffeeData store,
into which we're going to pass
the new currentDrinks value.
[KEYSTROKES]
Then, we need to go to where
currentDrinks is updated
and ensure we call
drinksUpdated afterwards.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now in this function,
there's one thing to note.
It's important
that this operation --
that takes a copy
of currentDrinks,
mutates it,
and then writes it back --
all happens atomically.
And this is why
the await keyword is vital;
it indicates that at this point,
this operation might suspend,
and other functions --
functions that might also update
currentDrinks -- could run.
So we need to make sure
that our entire mutation
and writeback happens
before any awaits,
otherwise,
other functions coming
and mutating currentDrinks could
lead to an inconsistent state.
So this function needs
to be async.
[KEYSTROKES]
We can go to our save operation
and eliminate
this unnecessary background
and foreground branch
and just do the operation
on the actor every time.
[KEYSTROKES]
OK. Finally, let's look
at the load operation.
Now here, the logic is split
between code that needs to run
in the background
and code that needs to run
on the main thread.
So let's first take
the first half --
the background portion --
and move that into the actor.
Now doing this, we notice
another possible race condition.
savedValues here was being
mutated on the main queue,
but if you remember
the save operation,
it was both read and written
from the background queue.
Now, as it happens,
the way the app was constructed,
the load only ever happened
on startup, so this was fine.
But again, that's relying
on global reasoning,
and it's the kind of assumption
that can break in subtle ways
when you make future changes.
It's much better to let
the actor ensure the program
will always be correct.
So we're going to fix that now.
So first, let's remove
this queue management...
...reindent the function, remove
this other queue management.
[KEYSTROKES]
And just like with save,
we need a way to pass back
the loaded values,
which we do just
by returning a value
from this load function
on the actor.
[KEYSTROKES]
So now, let's hop back
to the original load.
And we've moved this logic,
so we can just delete it...
and replace it
with a call to await...
[KEYSTROKES]
...loading the drinks
from the actor.
Now, because we're awaiting
the actor,
that means this function
needs to be async.
[KEYSTROKES]
And while we're here,
we can clean up
these deprecation warnings.
[KEYSTROKES]
And finally,
because this load is now async,
we need to await it here.
[KEYSTROKES]
And because
we're awaiting it here,
we need to create a task.
[KEYSTROKES]
But at this point,
if we just used an async task,
we're potentially introducing
a new race condition.
Remember, outside of an actor,
this new task just runs
on an arbitrary thread.
We shouldn't mutate
shared state,
like currentDrinks,
from an arbitrary thread.
Now, one way to resolve this
would be to put the load
function on the main actor,
But it's much better to move
the entire of model type
to the main actor.
[KEYSTROKES]
So we go to
our CoffeeModel definition
and add "MainActor"
to our model type.
By putting the model
on the main actor,
we're now guaranteeing
that all access
to CoffeeData's properties
are going to be made
from the main thread.
And this is good because,
as we noted earlier,
it's an observable object
and it has a published property.
And properties
published to SwiftUI
must only be updated
on the main thread.
It also means any calls
to async from the actor
will also run on the actor.
so we can remove any other
"MainActor" annotations
such as the one
we added earlier.
[KEYSTROKES]
So now you might notice
that when we compile
we don't hit
any compilation errors,
unlike when we moved
other things
into an actor earlier.
And that's because the places
we're calling into our model
are things like SwiftUI views.
For example,
let's go to DrinkListView.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now, this type displays
a list of buttons on the screen.
And then it calls addDrink,
which is on our model type.
But this DrinkListView is itself
also on the main actor.
And so its methods...
...can call into the CoffeeData
model without an await.
What is it that determines
that this SwiftUI view
is on the main actor?
Well, it's inferred from its use
of EnvironmentObject here.
Any SwiftUI view
that accesses shared state --
such as environmental objects
or an observed object --
will always be
on the main actor.
Elsewhere...
...we're also accessing
our model
from this extension
delegate call.
Since this extension delegate
is guaranteed to be called
on the main thread,
it's been annotated by WatchKit
as running on the main actor,
and so it can also call
into our model type directly.
Finally, now that we're here,
let's refactor this method
and get rid of this deprecated
completion handler usage.
We can instead wrap this section
in a new asynchronous task.
Remember, this handler
is running on the main thread,
so when we create a task,
that task will also be running
on the main thread.
And inside this new task,
we can now await...
[KEYSTROKES]
...our call to load new data
from HealthKit.
[KEYSTROKES]
And a really nice thing about
getting rid of
completion handlers
is you can now compose
functions together.
So if you wanted,
you could just move this await
directly into
the if statement.
Once this function call returns,
we know that all our work
is complete because, inside it,
we will awaiting
the save operation.
And so, we can now
confidently call
background.Task.setTaskCompleted
knowing that we finished
all of our I/O operations.
We now have this nice,
structured, top-down approach
to waiting
for an asynchronous operation
before completing any more work.
Incidentally, this structured
approach to concurrency
is another really important part
of Swift's concurrency feature.
To learn more,
watch the associated talk,
which covers how you can
take advantage of this feature
to structure
more complex examples,
such as waiting on multiple
asynchronous operations
to complete before continuing.
If, while you watch this talk,
you wondered exactly how some
of these new features work,
check out
our under-the-hood talk
that explores some
of the technology in detail.
So let's recap.
We've taken some code
that had sound type architecture
but complex
concurrency architecture
that had some hidden
race conditions
that were really hard to spot.
And with the help
of the new concurrency features,
we've rearchitected it
so that the concurrency
and type architecture
are nicely aligned.
And the compiler helped us find
some hidden potential
race conditions along the way.
There's a lot more to Swift 5.5
we haven't covered,
like structured concurrency
with task groups,
async sequences,
and some great new
asynchronous APIs in the SDK.
There's also a few more
refactorings
we didn't do in this project
that you might want
to try yourself.
The best way to learn
these techniques
is to try them out
in your own apps,
so have fun and enjoy these
cleaner, safer ways to code.
♪