[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Patrick Angle: Hi! I’m Patrick,
an engineer on the WebKit
Developer Experience team,
and it is my pleasure
to show you
some of the many exciting
features and improvements
that are new
in Web Inspector this year.
Web Inspector is part
of Safari on macOS
and gives web developers
and designers
access to a rich set of tools
to inspect their web pages
and web applications.
It allows you to inspect
all the resources and activity
on a web page,
and works seamlessly across
macOS, iOS, iPadOS, and tvOS.
This year, I am thrilled
to show you
new features in Web Inspector
starting with a new overlay
for visualizing your CSS Grids,
enhancements to breakpoints,
and the ability
to author and edit audits
right in Web Inspector.
Before I talk about
these new features,
if you haven’t
used Web Inspector before,
you’ll have to enable it.
In the Advanced tab
of Safari’s Preferences,
enable
“Show Develop menu in menu bar”.
Web Inspector
can then be opened using
the Show Web Inspector item
in the Develop menu.
Now that Web Inspector
is enabled,
let’s look at our first new tool
this year: grid overlays.
Web page layout these days
can be quite complicated.
CSS Grid is a
two-dimensional layout system
that makes it easy
for designers to lay out content
in a way that is both
incredibly powerful
as well as instantly familiar
to anyone who has ever
worked in printed design.
A structure of rows and columns
is defined
where elements are then placed
or distributed in the grid
to achieve a flexible
yet predictable layout.
Grid is a highly capable way
to lay out your web page,
but it can bring a host
of new questions and confusion
as your layouts
become more complex.
Like, Why is my column
this size?
Or, Why is this blue box
down here?
Previously in Web Inspector,
the primary source of answers
to these pressing questions
was the Style sidebar
in the Elements tab,
which this year has moved
to its own independent sidebar,
allowing you to view
matching CSS rules
alongside other panels
like Computed styles.
If you look at
a grid’s authored style,
you can glean some information
about its layout.
But the grid’s authored style
only gets you
part of the way there.
Wouldn’t it be great
if there was a more visual way
to digest this information
with Web Inspector?
Well, now there is!
If you look at the elements
in the DOM tree,
you’ll see a new
clickable grid badge
next to each of the elements
that are a CSS Grid.
Here, we see the badge
for one of the two CSS Grids
on our page.
If we click this new badge
and return to our web page,
you can see
the new grid overlay
on top of your existing content,
allowing you to visualize
the layout of the grid inline
without the mental gymnastics
of reading your authored CSS
and hoping it does
what you think it will.
But what if this isn’t
the exact information
you want to see about your grid?
What about grid areas,
line names, and other options?
To answer that,
let’s return to Web Inspector.
Here, you can find
another new feature,
the Layout panel, which shows
all the options and controls
related to grid overlays.
First, let's take a look at
the list of grids on the page.
Here you have the option
to toggle all of the grid
overlays on or off all at once.
Or you can toggle a single
grid’s overlay off or on.
Each grid is listed with
its corresponding CSS selector
to help identify it in the list.
Next to each listed grid
is a color swatch
that allows you
to interactively change
the color of the grid overlay,
and the badges on each element
will use this color
when that grid overlay
is enabled.
Web Inspector will remember
your color for each element
the next time the same page
is loaded.
Now let’s take a look
at the options we have
to control how these overlays
are displayed,
starting with track sizes,
which show the authored sizes
of each track --
which is a row or column --
of your grid.
Like here, where a mix
of fractional units
and min-content are used.
Next, line numbers show you
the values that can be used
to place child elements
at specific rows or columns
in your grid.
We’ve placed
negative line numbers --
which represent line numbers
counting from
the last explicit grid line --
inside the label, alongside
the positive line numbers
to allow you to choose
how you want to place your item.
Line names provide another way
to refer to your lines
in your grid based on area names
as well as lines
that have been explicitly named.
Area names allow you to see
each of the named areas
in your grid,
which is helpful if you want
to place children in your grid
without addressing the lines
on each side
of your desired placement.
We’ve placed area names
in the center of each area
and outlined each area
in a thick stroke.
Lastly, turning on
extended gridlines
on this second grid container
allows you to see
the track lines extended
to the edge of the page,
allowing you to visually compare
the grid’s alignment
to other elements on your page.
We’ve built our overlays
with performance in mind,
and you can enable
as many as you need,
all while smoothly scrolling
through your page.
Dozens of grids
can be shown simultaneously,
all while providing you
buttery-smooth scrolling.
They work for all writing modes
like this vertically set text
originally from Wikipedia,
right-to-left text direction,
and combinations thereof.
And these overlays
are also available
on iOS 15 and iPadOS 15
when inspecting remotely
from a Mac with Safari 15
or the latest
Safari Technology Preview.
We believe that grid
is an incredibly important
layout tool on the web,
and that is why we have brought
these tools to Web Inspector,
enabling you to visualize
and debug grid
across all of our platforms
to continue to create
incredible layouts.
Now let’s take a look at
how grid overlays can help us
to better understand and solve
problems on our web pages.
Let’s take a look at a web page
I’ve been working on
that gives me a quick overview
of information I want to see
each morning.
I can see my commute, the
weather forecast for the day --
looks like I’ll want
a jacket tonight! --
and a list of things
to pick up at the store
after work today.
This page is laid out
with CSS Grid,
which made it easy to create
these varying sized tiles
and place them on my page.
But wait, it looks like I forgot
to place one of these fun emojis
I used to decorate my dashboard.
It belongs down here
with the rest of my emojis!
No problem.
I can use our new grid overlay
to help me place it
exactly where I’d like.
To begin inspecting my page,
I’ll right-click on
my problematic element
and select Inspect Element.
If you don’t see
Inspect Element,
make sure to enable
Web Inspector
like we discussed earlier.
I’ll then select the Layout
panel in the Details sidebar,
where I can see all
the grid contexts on my page.
I can’t quite remember
which of these grids
I want to work with,
but I can enable
all of the overlays at once
by checking the top checkbox
for all grid overlays.
I now see the grid context
I want to work with
is the pink one,
which holds all of my tiles.
I’ll just turn off
the other two overlays
by unchecking them
in this list of grid contexts.
And now I’m left with only the
grid overlay I’m interested in.
If you're like me,
you may only want to see
exactly the information you need
to perform the task at hand,
so I’m going to disable
Track Sizes labels
so I can focus
just on the line numbers
for placing my stray emoji.
And now the remaining
line number labels
let me see exactly
where I want to place my emoji:
at column track line 6
and row track line 4.
Because I explicitly
right-clicked
and inspected the tile
for my problematic emoji,
it's already selected for me,
and I can jump right to editing
its style to test my fix.
And with our new
three-panel layout,
I can keep the Layout panel
visible at the same time,
which is great for
when I want to switch
which labels or grid overlays
I’m showing
while testing different styles
on my page
without constantly
switching between panels.
In the Styles panel,
I'm going to click
in the Style Attribute section
and add a new property,
grid-area.
I can then type a colon
to jump to editing
my new property's value
where I will enter "4 / 6"
for row track line 4
and column track line 6.
Perfect, my emoji
is right where I want it now.
But now that I think
about it some more,
I really want to make sure this
emoji is always in this corner,
even if I add or remove rows
or columns from my grid later.
In the same labels
that gave me values
of row track line 4
and column track line 6,
I see a second line number,
-3, for each.
This negative line number
will actually keep my emoji
three track lines
from the end of the grid
I’ve explicitly defined,
and will be perfect
for my situation.
I’ll update my
grid-area property’s value
to these new values, "-3 / -3",
and see that my emoji
is still in the correct place,
and will continue to be
if I add another row
or remove another column
from my grid.
This new overlay
coming to Web Inspector
helped me quickly
adjust the layout of my page,
and is great for understanding
existing layouts
as well as
designing new layouts.
Now let’s talk about
improvements
in JavaScript debugging
with breakpoints.
For scripts,
we often start with console.log
as we try to figure out
why our script isn’t working
the way we think it should.
Alternatively, if you’ve
never tried breakpoints,
I highly recommend
checking them out.
They are powerful and,
as we’ll see in just a moment,
even more configurable
than before.
If you're new to breakpoints,
the easiest way to get started
is in the Sources tab
by clicking in the line gutter
of your JavaScript
on a line at which
you’d like to pause.
This creates a breakpoint
which, when reached,
will pause your script
at the beginning of that line,
waiting to execute the line;
allow you to step
through your code
one statement at a time;
or dive deeper into
a specific statement;
and view the state
of your variables
every step of the way.
But there's so much more
to breakpoints!
In fact, there are five
different types of breakpoints,
one for every occasion.
There are breakpoints
for debugger statements,
exceptions,
and assertions;
JavaScript breakpoints,
which you can set
on lines of JavaScript;
event breakpoints,
which pause
when an event like click,
timeouts, intervals,
or animation frames
are handled;
DOM breakpoints,
which pause when actions
related to a DOM node occur.
These can be added
in the Elements tab,
or from the context menu
for any node preview
in Web Inspector.
And URL breakpoints,
which pause
when a network request
is about to be made for a URL
via APIs such as XMLHttpRequest
or Fetch.
You can configure
your JavaScript breakpoints
by right-clicking
on a breakpoint
and selecting Edit Breakpoint.
Here, you can control numerous
aspects of the breakpoint.
Let’s take a look
at each of these options.
We can set a condition,
which must be true
for the breakpoint to be hit.
New this year, we now support
using Web Inspector’s
Console tab API
inside expressions
in breakpoint conditions
and actions,
like this one that refers to
the currently selected DOM node
in the Elements tab.
In some cases,
a breakpoint condition
may be better expressed
as a number of times
to ignore the breakpoint
before it is hit,
like while inside a loop
where we don’t want to stop
until some number of iterations
have been completed.
This can be used in addition to
or instead of a condition
to control when the breakpoint
will fire.
When used in addition
to a condition,
the count of ignored invocations
is incremented
only if the condition
was satisfied.
Next, you can define actions
that are taken
when your breakpoint is hit,
like evaluating JavaScript
in context
with access to variables,
as if the code was inline
in your JavaScript source;
log messages
to the console easily
with a template string literal;
play a system beep
so you audibly know
the breakpoint was hit;
and define a probe expression,
which is evaluated with its
result saved in the Probe panel
of the Details sidebar
of the Sources tab,
allowing you to see
the results of the expression
as it changes over the lifetime
of your web page.
New this year,
the action types
that support JavaScript
expressions
can be set to emulate
a user gesture,
which can be helpful when
interacting with JavaScript APIs
that normally require
a user to have initiated them,
like playing a video,
enabling you to quickly
test new behavior
before implementing the change
in the web page’s source.
You can mix and match
any number of these actions
to customize your breakpoints,
including multiple
of any action type.
Lastly, you can have
your breakpoint
automatically continue
after evaluating
and performing your actions
for situations
where you just wanted
to add some logging
or a quick patch to test
without modifying
the underlying web page.
These options
for configuring breakpoints
are incredibly versatile,
and this year
I’m pleased to tell you
that they are now available
for all breakpoint types,
not just JavaScript breakpoints.
This enables you to set
powerful breakpoint conditions,
like only pausing
on click events
for a specific type of element,
like button;
or playing a system beep
when a network request
is made for a specific URL.
These configuration options
being available
for all breakpoint types make
already great debugging tools
even better by helping you
cut through the noise --
or even make a little noise --
at just the right time.
Now, let’s return
to my dashboard web page
and take a look at an issue
that these new tools
will make a breeze to debug
and test a patch for.
I recently added a button
to my commute tile
that I want to use to share
my estimated commute time
with someone else.
You never know when you might
end up running late.
Unfortunately,
when I click my Share button,
nothing happens.
Even worse, it’s been a few days
since I’ve worked on this tile
and I don’t remember
where I handle click events
for this button.
Fortunately, I can use
an event breakpoint
to pause in my click event
handler to find my code.
I can create event breakpoints
here in the Sources tab.
Clicking the plus
in the top right
of the breakpoint section
of the Navigation Sidebar,
and selecting Event Breakpoint,
allows me to define
a new event breakpoint.
I’ll set the event to click,
and then press the Return key
to create my new breakpoint.
I now see my click breakpoint
listed in
the Navigation Sidebar.
This event breakpoint
should pause
when I click my button.
But first, I want to make sure
I’m sharing
the most up-to-date
time estimate for my commute,
so I’ll click my Refresh button
and -- Oops!
My event breakpoint
will actually pause
for all click events,
including my Refresh button,
even though
I really only want to pause
when I click on my Share button.
Let’s modify my breakpoint using
the new configuration options
that are available this year.
I can edit my breakpoint
by right-clicking on it
and choosing Edit Breakpoint.
Here, I get a popover
with the configuration options
for the event breakpoint.
I need to add a condition
to make sure I only pause
when I need to.
In this case, I can use
some Web Inspector console API
to get the current event
with "$event",
and check if the event’s target
is equal to my Share button.
Instead of hard-coding
my breakpoint
for this specific button,
I’ll use another piece
of console API
to check if the event’s target
is the currently selected
DOM node in the Elements tab
with "$0".
I can click out of
the configuration popover
and all my changes
are automatically applied.
I’m still paused
on my breakpoint
from clicking
on the Refresh button,
so I’ll click
the Continue button
to resume script execution
on my page.
Now, when I click
on my Refresh button,
my commute time updates
and my breakpoint isn’t hit.
But if I right-click
on my Share button,
and select Inspect Element
to make it the selected element,
I can now click
on my Share button and bingo!
The breakpoint paused
exactly where I wanted it to,
and now I see why
my Share button doesn’t work:
I forgot to write this function.
Breakpoints can save the day --
or at least this demo -- again,
and help me patch sharing in
right now to test my changes
before I go back to the source
to implement them.
I’ll add a breakpoint
in my share function
by clicking in the line gutter,
right-clicking
on the breakpoint indicator,
and choosing Edit Breakpoint.
I don’t need a condition
on this breakpoint,
but I want to add an action.
The default action type,
Evaluate JavaScript,
is exactly what I want here.
I’ll add my JavaScript
to the action,
which will call
"navigator.share"
with an object I’ve already
prepared with my data,
"this.shareData".
I don’t actually
need to pause my script
as part of testing this fix,
so I’ll also enable
Automatically continue
after evaluating.
Like before,
clicking outside the popover
saves my changes.
I'm done with my click event
breakpoint for now,
so let's click
on its indicator to disable it.
I'll also click
the Continue button
to resume script execution
on my page.
I can now click
on my Share button,
and am presented
with the Share menu.
I'll select Notes to confirm
my share data is correct.
This looks correct, so now
I can go back to my source code
and make this change.
Awesome!
These enhancements
to breakpoints
made it possible to identify
and test a solution
without having
to pepper my source
with console.log statements.
And now that
I have a working solution,
I can go add my fix
to my source.
Now let’s take a look at an
exciting new feature for audits:
the ability to create
and edit your tests
right in Web Inspector.
Each test in the Audit tab
is written in JavaScript
and is run against
the inspected web page.
These tests can check
for incorrect DOM structure,
help enforce
design system rules,
or help make sure you haven’t
missed accessibility attributes.
In addition to individual tests,
you can share
and run groups of tests.
By default, Web Inspector
has two test groups:
the Demo Audit, which provides
a tour of the way audits work
and the functionality
they support,
and a suite of accessibility
tests that check for a subset
of the DOM accessibility
best practices
in accordance
with the ARIA specification,
such as ensuring that
a title or alternate text
is set on all image elements.
You can run a test
by selecting it
and using the Start button
next to the audit name,
or run all of your tests
with the Start button
at the top of
the Navigation Sidebar.
After your tests have run,
you can see the results
of each test
as well as an overall summary
of passes and failures.
If there are any failures,
you can see information
about those failures
so you can get them patched up.
To share your tests,
or to edit them
in an external text editor,
you can export the test,
make your changes
to the resulting JSON file,
and then import the modified
test back into Web Inspector.
This process of exporting
and importing
is great for sharing your tests
across your team
or with the community.
And this year, we are making
creating and editing tests
even easier
with a new Edit mode.
When you click
on the Edit button
in the bottom
of the Navigation Sidebar,
the Audit tab transforms
into Editing mode,
where you now have
the ability to create new tests
as well as edit
your existing tests.
Note that the default Demo Audit
and Accessibility test groups
cannot be deleted or edited,
but can be duplicated
and then the duplicate
can be edited.
For now, let’s look
at creating a new test
by using the Create item
in the Navigation Sidebar.
You can create a new test case,
or a group of test cases.
For now, let’s look at creating
a new test case.
When we create a new test case,
you see that it is added
to the Navigation Sidebar,
and the default contents of the
test appear for you to edit.
Here you have several different
things available to configure.
The name, as well as
the description of the test,
and the minimum audit version
the test supports,
which makes sure
the audit is not run
in an older version
of Web Inspector
where some features
may not be supported.
The setup script is JavaScript
that will be executed
before every top-level test
or test group.
This allows you to perform
common setup functions
that all tests under
this top-level test rely on.
And last,
but certainly not least,
there is the test itself,
which is a JavaScript function
that can return true or false
or a result object
with more information
about the test’s run.
A special WebInspectorAudit
object is also available,
which exposes additional API
specifically for tests to use
in both the test itself as well
as the setup for the test.
You can learn more
about this API
in the Web Inspector Reference.
Your changes
are automatically saved,
and all of this can now be done
in Web Inspector
without exporting.
But to really get a feel for
the flexibility of these tests,
I’d like to show you them
in action.
Let’s return to my dashboard
one last time
and see how audits
can help me catch
some types
of accessibility problems
as well as design issues
in my web page.
The first thing I like to do
when I open the Audit tab
is to run the default
Accessibility test cases.
These will help me get
a good baseline reading
for how I’m doing on common
accessibility best practices.
I can quickly run these tests
by clicking on the Run button
next to the test group.
And not bad,
but I can do better.
I can look at the test failures
by clicking the Passed filter
button to hide those results,
leaving only my test failure
to view.
Let’s get this fixed.
This test provides a list
of DOM nodes that failed,
making it easy
to jump to that node
using the Reveal in Elements Tab
button that appears on hover.
In the Elements tab, I’ll test
adding a title to my image
by right-clicking
on the DOM node
choosing Add > Attribute,
and typing my new title.
I’ll return to the Audit tab
and run the same
test group again.
And this time,
I see that I pass all the tests.
Another great use for audits
is checking to make sure
my web page meets
my own design standards.
One of my rules while
working on this project
was to make sure
I was consistently using
a small set of font families
for all of my elements.
Let’s use the new
Audit Edit Mode,
added to Web Inspector this year,
to do just that.
I’ll begin editing by clicking
on the Edit button
at the bottom
of the Navigation Sidebar.
Now I’m in Edit Mode.
Here I can create
a new test case
using the Create button
at the top of the sidebar.
I’ll keep the default option
of Test Case,
and name my test case "Fonts."
I can now edit
the rest of my test case.
I’ll start by adding
a description
to help me remember
what this test case does.
Now let’s insert my actual
test code I’ve prepared.
My test will have
three main steps.
First, I’ll create an array
of expected font families.
Next, I’ll collect
all the elements on my page
with a font family
that isn’t listed
in my expected font families.
Lastly, I’ll return
my result object,
including any elements
that failed my test.
When I’m done writing my audit,
I just click Done at the bottom
of the Navigation Sidebar.
I can now run my audit
by clicking the Run button
next to its name.
It looks like I have an issue
with one of the nodes
on my page,
so let’s take a look
at what's wrong.
I can again use the
Reveal in Elements Tab button
to go to the element
and look at its style.
Well, this is embarrassing.
Comic Sans!
I really don't want
to use this font,
so let's change this to the
ui-rounded font family instead.
Now, I’ll return
to the Audit tab,
run my test again,
and perfect!
The last thing I want to do
is export my test
using the Export Audit button
so that I can share it
with my colleagues
to help them avoid the same
embarrassing mistake I made --
although maybe I’ll leave out
the Comic Sans
part of the story.
Not only were
the built-in accessibility tests
able to catch an issue I missed,
I was able to write a test
to enforce my own design system
rules for my web page,
making it even easier for teams
to make sure everyone
is on the same page
before ever checking in
their changes.
And with that, we’ve covered
these big new features
in Web Inspector!
A new overlay for CSS Grid
helps make sure your content
looks just right.
Breakpoint improvements
make it easier to find, debug,
and test fixes for issues
without leaving Web Inspector.
And with the new audit
creating and editing
right in Web Inspector,
you can quickly create tests
to make sure web pages
meet accessibility standards
as well as your own standards.
Along with these new features,
we’ve made tweaks
and enhancements
as well as fixed numerous bugs
to further improve
Web Inspector.
Before I go, there are
some helpful resources
I’d like to leave you with.
You may not have realized
that Web Inspector
is part of the open source
WebKit project,
which is the fast,
private, and secure
web browser engine used by
Safari, Mail, App Store,
and many other apps
on macOS and iOS.
You can learn more about the
WebKit project at webkit.org,
where you'll also find
blog posts
about new features in WebKit,
including this one about grid
overlays in Web Inspector.
In addition to blog posts about
new features in Web Inspector,
you can also find documentation
which covers
a wide range of Web Inspector’s
features and interface,
and goes deep on many of
the features we discussed today,
like audits and breakpoints.
There's so much more depth
to those features
than I was able to cover today,
and I highly recommend
checking out
the documentation
if you’d like to learn more.
We also would love
to hear from you!
If you come across a bug
or have a suggestion
on how we can improve
Web Inspector,
please file feedback for macOS
in Feedback Assistant,
and select WebKit as the area
for your feedback.
I’d also like to invite you
to download
Safari Technology Preview,
released approximately
every two weeks,
which is designed specifically
for developers
to get early access to new
WebKit and Web Inspector tools,
features, and fixes
before they appear
in the version of Safari
included on every Mac,
iPhone, and iPad.
Lastly, please check out
these other great sessions,
including
“Design for Safari 15,”
to learn how to adapt and design
beautiful content for Safari;
and “Develop advanced web
content,” to learn all about
new JavaScript
and WebAssembly features
you can use to further enhance
your web pages.
Also take a look
at our session,
“What’s new in Web Inspector,”
from WWDC 2020
to see even more improvements
we’ve made in Web Inspector.
You can find these
fabulous sessions,
and many more,
in your Developer app.
Thank you!
♪