[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
David Hayward:
Welcome, everyone.
My name is David Hayward.
I'm a senior engineer
on the Core Image team,
and I'll be giving
a short presentation today
that will show you
the latest best practices
when adding custom
Metal Core Image kernels
to your Xcode project.
In this presentation,
I will discuss
the general benefits of writing
custom CIKernels in Metal.
Next, I will introduce
two recommended ways
that Metal CIKernels
can be built.
And then I will demonstrate
step by step
how to add these
to your project.
First off,
let's review the benefits
of writing custom
CIKernels in Metal.
By writing CIKernels in Metal,
you will get access
to Core Image features
such as automatic tiling
and concatenation.
It will improve
your app's performance
by shifting some of the time
to compile kernels
from runtime
to when your app is built.
And doing so will give
your kernels access
to high-performance features
such as gather-reads,
group-writes,
and half-float math.
Last but not least, it will make
your life as a developer easier
by syntax highlighting
as you type
and inline error checking
when you build.
So with that for motivation,
I will now show you step by step
how to add Metal Core Image
kernels to your application.
There are now
two recommended ways
to add CIKernels
to your project,
and I will describe
both methods in detail.
I will refer to this
as the extern method
because it requires the kernel
functions to be specified
as extern "C" and built
using custom build flags.
The second method is new
in iOS 15 and macOS 12.
I will refer to this
as the stitchable method
because it requires
the kernel functions
to be in attributed
as stitchable.
Its implementation uses
Metal Dynamic Libraries.
In both methods, there are
four general steps to follow.
First, is to configure
your project appropriately.
Second, is to add Metal CIKernel
source files to your project.
Third, is to write
your Metal CIKernel code.
And fourth is to write
Swift or Objective-C code
to initialize and apply
your kernel
to create a new CIImage.
First, let's describe
these four steps
when using extern CIKernels,
starting with project
configuration.
Unlike conventional Metal
compute and graphics shaders,
this Core Image Metal code
needs to be compiled and linked
with special flags.
I recommend adding
two custom build rules
to your project targets
which will make using
these flags automatic.
First, you will go
to the project's target settings
and add a build rule for files
that end in .ci.metal.
For files with this extension,
this rule will run
a one-line script
that calls the Metal compiler
with the required
-fcikernel flag.
This build rule will produce
an output binary
that will end in .ci.air.
Next, you will add
a second build rule
for files that end in .ci.air.
For files with this extension,
this rule will run
a one-line script
that calls the Metal linker with
the required -cikernel flag.
This build rule
will produce an output
in your app's
Resources directory
that will end in .ci.metallib.
Now that you have added
the custom build rules,
all you need to do is add
.ci.metal sources
to your project.
To do that,
select from the File menu
that you want to add
a new Metal file
and then give that new file
a name ends in .ci.metal.
The next step is
to write your CIKernel
in the Metal source file.
First, at the top of the source,
you will include
the CoreImage.h header
so that you get access
to all the classes
that Core Image provides.
The kernel must be specified
as extern "C"
to be recognized by Core Image.
The content of your actual
kernel implementation
is up to your imagination.
For one example
of what you can do,
I recommend that you watch
our WWDC 2020 presentation
on "HDR editing and playback
using AVFoundation."
The final step is to add
Swift code to load your kernel
and apply it
to create a new image.
Kernels are typically used
in a CIFilter subclass
which will have properties
such as an inputImage
and other input parameters.
I recommend that your filter
instantiate its CIKernel object
into a static property.
This way, the work of loading
the metallib resource
is done only once
when it is first needed.
Because of the custom build rule
I described earlier,
you will need to specify
a resource URL
with the same name
as your source
and an extension
of .ci.metallib.
Lastly, a CIFilter subclass
must override
the outputImage property.
In the getter,
you will take the kernel
from a static property
and use its apply method
to create a new image
based on the input properties.
So that fully describes
the process
of building extern CIKernels.
Let's now describe
the new process
of building
stitchable CIKernels.
With the stitchable method,
only one setting
change is needed
to configure
your Xcode project.
This setting will tell
the Metal linker
to link against
the Core Image framework.
To do this, just go to
the project's target setting
and add a build setting
for Other Metal Linker Flags
with the value
"-framework CoreImage".
Because stitchable CIKernels
don't require
custom build rules,
you can simply add .metal
sources to your project
without any special suffix.
You can add kernels in either
one or several sources files.
By default,
Xcode will build all of them
into one .metallib resource.
The next step
is to write your CIKernel
in the Metal source file.
As before, you will include
the CoreImage.h header
to get access
to the Core Image classes.
But with this method,
the kernel must be attributed
as [[stitchable]]
to be recognized by Core Image.
Once again,
the final step is to add
Swift code to load your kernel,
and apply it
to create a new image.
The only change
with stitchable CIKernels
is that you can simply
load the resource
with the standard name
of default.metallib.
That concludes the process of
building stitchable CIKernels.
It is worth mentioning
some of the benefits
of using this method.
Stitchable kernels can link
against other Metal libraries.
And they now support
input parameters
that are integer and
unsigned integer vector types.
Another niche benefit
is that stitchable kernels
can be compiled
from source at runtime.
Most applications
should not use this feature
because it will incur
longer initial compile times.
That said, there are some
classes of applications
that may benefit
from this flexibility.
There is one last topic
to cover in this presentation.
The stitchable CIKernel
implementation
depends on two important
Metal features.
The first is the new Metal
Shading Language version 2.4.
Among other things,
this versions supports
the [[stitchable]] attribute
that causes the compiler
to associate additional metadata
with each function.
The second is the
Metal Dynamic Libraries feature
that is used
so that your kernels
can link against
the Core Image Metal classes.
For more details on these Metal
features, be sure to watch the
"Discover Compilation Workflows
in Metal" presentation.
Be aware, though,
that Metal Dynamic Libraries
are only supported
on some graphics devices,
specifically iPhone and iPad
with A11 and later,
all Macs with Apple silicon,
and Intel Macs
with AMD Navi and Vega GPUs.
Your application should check
the Metal device property
supportsDynamicLibraries
before using
stitchable CIKernels.
So that concludes
my step-by-step description
of how to use
the two recommended ways
to add Metal CIKernels
to your application.
For each method, I've covered
how to configure your project,
write the kernel source,
and initialize
the kernel objects.
I hope that this allows you
to add great visual effects
to your app's images and videos.
Thank you and enjoy
the rest of WWDC 2021!
♪