[upbeat music]
[Matt] Hello.
Welcome to Triaging TestFlight
crashes with Xcode Organizer.
My name is Matt,
and I'm an Xcode engineer.
Today I'm going to show you
some of the new tools we have
built into the Xcode Organizer
that will help you
triage crashes
across all of your
app's targets
and how to leverage feedback
from your TestFlight users
so you can get crash fixes
into your builds faster.
Then I'm going to show you
the new Terminations Organizer
and advancements
we've made in MetricKit.
If your app is utilizing
TestFlight
to test your beta versions,
you'll know that crash
feedback from your testers
can be really valuable.
When a tester
writes some feedback
after they
have hit a crash,
you can view that feedback
in App Store Connect
and download the crash log
to start analyzing
what happened.
Later on, I'm going to show you
the changes we made in Xcode
that will supercharge
this workflow.
First, I want to give
a quick overview
of the features available
before Xcode 13.
In the Crashes Organizer,
we support crashes
for both apps
on the App Store and TestFlight.
We show your app's crashes
across all of our platforms,
including crashes from your
App Clip and app extensions.
The Organizer
ranks your issues
to show you the highest
priority crashes
and shows
you how those crashes
are distributed across different
devices and OS versions.
And once you've decided to start
attacking that crash,
you can open it directly
in your Xcode project.
All of these great features
work out of the box
by simply signing into Xcode
with your developer account.
The journey of making
a great app
can be long and bumpy
at times,
because once you ship it,
customers always seem to
break it in ways that you didn't
even know were possible.
In Xcode 13,
we wanted to make the
Crashes Organizer even better
so you can continue
to get closer to the goal
of no crashes.
This set us on a mission
to make crash log delivery
almost instant,
provide richer data
about your crashes,
and give you more context
to help you fix those
hard-to-reproduce issues.
I am thrilled to show you
all of the incredible new
features we've added to Xcode 13
in the Crashes Organizer.
There are six major improvements
that I'm going to
share with you.
First, speedy delivery
of your TestFlight crashes.
Now when any of your testers
crash a TestFlight build,
we will deliver that crash
to you in the Organizer
just moments later.
This quick crash delivery
now allows you to view
all of your TestFlight crashes
from the last day,
and you will now have
an hourly graph
telling you when
the selected crash occurred.
In Xcode 13,
we're now making a year's worth
of crash history
available to you.
You can now filter crashes
by time period
to see all of the crashes
that have occurred
in the last year.
Because we can now show you
a year's worth of crashes,
you will see a time distribution
in the inspector's
graph area showing you
the prevalence of a crash
on a month-to-month basis.
We wanted to give you
more tools to better understand
the health across
all parts of your app.
So this year, we're adding more
filters to the Crashes Organizer
to allow you to focus
on specific parts of your app.
The Organizer can now also
filter the crashes list
by all versions and builds
or drill down to any
individual past release.
You can also filter
by any of the extensions
that ship with your app,
like your watch app,
App Clip or share extension.
You can even check in how
your iOS app is doing
running on those phenomenal
Apple silicon Macs.
Part of triaging
your app's issues
is getting the full picture
of who is affected
by a particular crash
and that crash is distributed
across different categories.
So this year,
we've added the ability
to see how a unique crash
is distributed
across your app’s versions
and across TestFlight
and the App Store.
You all have shipped some
amazing apps as solo artists,
in large teams,
and everything in between.
In Xcode 13,
we are introducing a new way
to collaborate with each
other by adding the ability
for you to share crash reports
directly from the Organizer.
Using the new Share
button in the toolbar,
you can share a crash directly
with members of your team
or just simply
add it to your to-do list.
And when you click
on one of these links,
the Organizer downloads
and focuses on this issue,
allowing you to zero in on this
crash and start investigating.
TestFlight is a valuable tool
for developers
to quickly
get new features and fixes
in the hands of their testers,
who help find
new crashes and bugs.
Beta testing an app
with TestFlight
helps instill confidence
in developers
that they are going to be
shipping
a sweet update
to the App Store.
I am super excited
to announce that in Xcode 13,
we are bringing TestFlight
Crash Feedback
directly into
the Crashes Organizer.
App Store Connect shows you
all of your TestFlight feedback,
including crash feedback.
You can continue to download
the raw feedback and crash log
directly from App Store Connect
or, new this year,
you can open
the associated crash
right in the Organizer with
the new Open in Xcode button.
Viewing your crash feedback
is now easier than ever.
There is a new inspector
in the Crashes Organizer
dedicated
to TestFlight crash feedback.
Opening this Inspector will show
you all of the feedback
that has been submitted
by testers
that have hit the crash
you have selected.
This allows you to see
one unified feedback list
alongside your crash report
that you can quickly
sift through
to find that extra bit
of information needed
to help you fix a crash.
We think this added context
is invaluable
when tracking down
hard-to-reproduce issues.
So a lot of cool new stuff.
Let's dive in and start
triaging some crashes
in the new Crashes Organizer.
I've been working on
my team's app, Fruta,
and we've have recently
shipped a new version
to the App Store but are
also continuously deploying
new versions to TestFlight
with Xcode Cloud.
Today I want to see if there
have been any recent crashes
in our App Clip,
so let's open up the Organizer
and see what's going on.
I can do this by selecting
the Window menu bar item
and selecting Organizer.
From the sidebar on the left,
I can tell that Xcode
has opened
to the Crashes Organizer
for my iOS app, Fruta.
In the toolbar at the top
of the window,
you'll notice all
of the new filter options
that are available this year.
Underneath the filter bar
is the crashes list,
which is showing us all of our
crashes for the last two weeks
across all versions,
builds, and products.
Quickly scanning this list,
I can see a number
of different kinds of issues.
Crashes in the list
display various badges
indicating whether
they came from our App Clip,
our watch app,
or an app extension.
This allows us to quickly
identify which area of our app
a crash is affecting.
To the right of the crashes
list, I see the log view.
This is showing me the friendly,
simplified view of the crash
I have selected
in the crashes list.
And finally,
to the right of the log view,
I see the inspector,
which shows me all kinds of
interesting information
about the selected crash.
Now that we're familiar
with the Organizer,
I want to take a look at all
of our recent issues
for our App Clip.
I can open up the products
filter in the toolbar
which lists all of the products
that ship with my app,
like our watch app,
App Clip, or app extensions.
I'll go ahead
and select App Clip here.
Selecting App Clip has filtered
the crashes list
to only display
our App Clip crashes
from the last two weeks.
The first crash in the list
here is our top crash.
Underneath the title,
the Organizer is letting us know
that this crash has been
affecting 21 devices
in the last two weeks
and 7 in the last day.
Now, before I start
digging into the code,
I like to ask myself some
questions that will help
guide my investigation and lead
me to some context clues.
First, how long has
this been an issue?
If we head over
to the inspector's graph area
on the right side of the window,
we can tell from
the graph legend
that this crash first
appeared in version 2.0
and is affecting our latest
TestFlight build, 2.0.1.
Next question, is this
affecting my production app
or just TestFlight?
I can change the filter
to Release to find out
that this is affecting both
TestFlight and App Store builds.
So this issue is pretty
important,
because our customers
are experiencing it,
and it looks like
it may have regressed
in our most recent
App Store release.
Now let's focus on
the log view.
The log view is conveniently
highlighting for me
the exact frame that crashed.
I also know that this happened
on a background thread
by looking at the thread number
above the back trace, thread number 6.
I can see this is crashing while
we're syncing favorites,
but isn't an area of code that
I work in too often,
and so I don't quite know
how to reproduce this.
I can't really think of more
questions to ask myself
that are going to give me more
insight into this crash,
so it would be really helpful
to get some more context.
Fortunately,
there's a feedback icon
next to this crash in the list,
so I know that
one of our testers
has experienced this crash
and submitted feedback.
This might just be the missing
piece of context I need
to start working on this crash.
I can see their feedback
by heading over
to the inspector area
and opening the new
Feedback Inspector.
I see that several testers
have hit this same crash,
including one who saw it
just a minute ago.
In the inspector,
I can see a preview
of each feedback report,
or if I click on one,
I can see more details
in a popover.
I'll click on this latest
feedback,
which opens up a popover
and shows me all of the rich
context for this tester's crash,
like the exact version
and build they had installed,
their device model,
battery level,
and available disk space.
These can all be helpful clues
when diagnosing a crash.
In this case, I can see
the tester was on cellular,
and their comment says,
"I was going through a tunnel
and I hit the favorite button.
A few seconds later,
it crashed."
Hmm. if they were going
through a tunnel,
they might have had a poor
network connection.
Now we can combine
all of our clues together
to know that pressing
the favorite button
will trigger some background
task that will eventually crash.
I think we have enough to start
diving into the code.
I'll use the Open in Project
button
to open this crash directly
in the Fruta Xcode project.
OK, so Xcode has opened
and is showing the backtrace
in the Debug Navigator
on the left,
and the editor
with our source file
and the exact line of crashing
code highlighted.
So why is this code crashing?
Well, it seems like
we're crashing on purpose
with a fatal error,
which is an interesting choice.
Let's take a quick pass through
our syncFavorites function
to understand
what it's trying to do.
First, we're jumping onto
a background thread.
Next, it appears like
we're saving this smoothie
as a favorite to disk.
Then we're updating our back end,
and we're using a dispatch group
to sync these operations
together.
We then wait on these operations
with a 10-second timeout,
and if it takes longer,
we crash.
This is pretty unfair.
Remembering
our tester's feedback,
it said they were
going through a tunnel
when they favorited a smoothie.
If they were going through
a tunnel,
then they probably had a poor
quality network connection,
which means that syncing
with our backend
could definitely take a lot
longer than 10 seconds.
This crash makes total
sense now.
Now that we know that
our timeout is too short
and we aren't handling it
properly, let's fix this.
I've been practicing
my Combine skills recently,
so I think I want to use
Combine to fix this.
Awesome.
So now we are merging
the results
of two publishers together,
and when we timeout,
which is now 30 seconds,
we call our completion
handler rather than crash.
Problem solved.
Let's head back to the Organizer
and mark this issue as resolved.
[chime]
Oh, it looks like my boss
just sent me a text.
Ooh, Craig
hit a crash in his demo.
Thankfully, my boss used the new
sharing feature in the Organizer
to send me the exact
crash that Craig hit,
so I don't have to
go digging for it.
When I click on this link,
the Organizer
creates this focused view
of the single crash that was
embedded in that link.
I've actually seen
this crash before.
I just fixed this the other day
and marked it as resolved.
I also gave the crash
a friendlier name
so that I could remember
the underlying issue.
I'll go ahead
and let my boss know
that I've already fixed this.
So we've just looked at how to
triage our App Clip crashes
using the new filters
in the Organizer,
how to use the new distribution
graphs in the inspector,
and how to make use
of our TestFlight feedback
to fix an issue
that would have been
otherwise hard to reproduce.
Now let's take a look at the
new Terminations Organizer
and improvements
we've made to MetricKit.
The new Terminations Organizer
shows trends of app terminations
that may be
affecting your customers.
The crashes you'll see
in the Crashes Organizer
are the result of programming
failures,
but there are other ways
that your app's process
can be terminated.
Terminations are categorized
by reasons like
"timing out on launch"
or "hitting
the system memory limit."
You can compare these categories
of termination events
for your app against previous
versions to find regressions.
Some of these terminations
happen in the background,
but in certain cases,
they can happen
while your app is onscreen.
The Terminations Organizer
can help you understand
the difference so you
can make a plan to fix them.
If you'd like to dive
into regressions,
check out
the Application performance
survival guide session
this year, and to learn
more about terminations,
I recommend
checking out the session
Why is my app getting killed?
from 2020.
If you're not familiar,
you can use the
Apple framework MetricKit
to collect
crash logs in your code.
All you need to do
is import MetricKit,
begin listening
to the MetricKit manager,
and use the crashDiagnostics
property
on MetricKit diagnostic payloads
when they are received.
New this year, crash diagnostics
are no longer aggregated
and delivered once daily
but are now delivered
on the next launch of your app
so you gain access
to crash logs faster.
I'm also happy to announce that
MetricKit now supports macOS.
To learn more about using
MetricKit,
I recommend the session
What's new
in MetricKit from 2020.
There are many other ways
to track down and view crashes.
You can access crashes
on your connected device
from the Devices window
or by sharing a log directly
from your device.
XCTest will collect
your crashes that occur
when running your tests,
and you can use the Console app
to view crashes from
your Mac and the simulator.
For more on these additional
tools, check out the session
Understanding crashes
and crash logs from 2018.
Today we saw
some great new features.
We hope that the new
speedy crash log delivery,
TestFlight feedback integration,
and distribution metrics
will dramatically improve
your experience fixes crashes
and ultimately improve
your app's health
and your users experiences.
Thank you for watching.
And remember,
the road to success
is always under construction.
[percussive music]