[upbeat music]
[Kieran] Hi, everyone.
My name is Kieran,
and I'm an Xcode engineer
working on source control
technologies.
Xcode 13 completely
reimagines code review mode
and introduces brand new
collaboration workflows
to help you improve
the quality of your app.
In this session,
I'll walk you through
a typical workflow
with our app Fruta.
We'll use the new code review
and pull request features
in Xcode 13
to find a bug, get feedback,
integrate those changes,
and provide feedback
to my colleagues.
Let's get started.
A big part of my work
is looking into issues
that our users reported.
In order to fix a bug,
I first have to understand
when and why
it started happening.
By stepping back in time
through my code changes,
I can often figure out the cause
using code review mode.
One of the App Store reviews
we had
mentioned that some UI changes
recently made to our app
don't look quite right.
I have a pretty good idea
what the issues are,
so I'll go ahead and start
making some changes.
As I start typing,
the changes appear
in the source editor's gutter.
I find it really useful to know
what the previous values were
so I can have a good idea
of everything that's changed.
For this, I can jump into
code review mode.
Simply click on the Code Review
button in the editor bar
to see the comparison
of local edits
against the most recent
revision.
As I'm working on my document,
code review mode
continuously highlights
the edits I'm making
so I always know what's changed
since my last commit.
When I've made multiple edits
to a file,
the stepper control
in the bottom bar
shows me how many changes
I've made.
Clicking the arrow icons will
jump between my code changes.
That way, I don't have to
scroll through the file
looking for the edits myself.
Sometimes it can be easier
to see what's changed
side-by-side,
but I prefer
to see my changes in-line.
Xcode can show me my changes
in either style,
and I can flip between the two
using the Editor menu
at the top right.
I want to ensure that
I've caught every issue
with the UI bug.
To really dig in and understand
where a bug came from,
I need to see what's changed
between releases of my app.
I can use the commit controls
in the bottom bar
to set up those comparisons.
Xcode 13 allows me to choose
commits across my branches,
tags,
and most recent locations
so I can easily see
the changes in my app
between
any two points in time.
I usually cut a release branch
every time I submit
to TestFlights or the App Store,
so I'll take a look at
two versions of my code
related to that release.
With my commit selected,
Xcode shows me a comparison
of the two historical versions
of my document.
The highlight colors change
to purple and orange,
corresponding with the commits
displayed in the bottom bar.
As before,
I can jump between changes
using the stepper control.
I can see the comparison either
in-line or side-by-side.
When I'm done
exploring this comparison,
I can quickly snap back
to my most recent changes
using the Reset button
in the bottom bar.
Usually, the changes
that I make to my apps
span across multiple files.
While it's really useful to
explore changes within one file,
I often want an overview
for all of the files that I've
changed across my whole project.
Thanks to the new Changes tab
in the Source Control Navigator,
I can see a list of
all the files I've changed
since my last commit.
Clicking on any of them
will automatically
enter code review mode
and show me all the changes
that I've made in that file.
I like to flip between the files
to quickly remind myself
of the other edits I've made.
Now that I know why
our app has this issue
when displaying ingredients,
I'll go ahead and create
a new branch
with my changes to fix it.
Creating and switching branches
is something I do a lot,
and Xcode 13 has a great
new way to do that.
Xcode's toolbar now
shows my current branch,
which is a helpful reminder
of what I was last working on.
By clicking on it,
I can quickly switch
between any of the branches
that I worked on recently.
In this case,
I'll use the secondary menu
to create a branch for my fix.
After exploring history
in code review mode,
I was able to come up
with a fix for the bug.
Now that I have
a proposed solution,
I want to get feedback
on my code change.
Since I'm not totally familiar
with this part of the code base,
I'd like my teammates to confirm
that my changes
won't introduce other issues.
To collaborate
with my peers on a code change,
I'll create a pull request.
I can do that right
from Xcode 13
using its new integrated
support for GitHub
and Bitbucket Server.
I can create my pull requests
right from
the source control popover.
Xcode will create
a draft pull request
to merge with my branch
into the default upstream
branch,
which in this case is main.
I can prepare my pull request
with information about the fix
before publishing it.
The changes that I've committed
and pushed to my branch
will show up
in the Pull Request section
in the Changes Navigator,
giving me a preview of the
changes that will be included
once published.
The Local Changes section
lets me see files
that won't be included
in my pull request
until I commit and push them.
When I'm happy with the contents
of my pull request,
I'll give it a title
and a description.
I'd like to ask a few
teammates in particular
to review this change,
so I'll click
the Participants button
and tag them as Reviewers.
As I wait for feedback
and switch to other branches,
Xcode figures out
which pull request to display.
Xcode will determine
the associated pull request
based on its source branch
and your current branch.
When you switch branches,
Xcode will automatically
discover existing pull requests.
I published my pull request
a little while ago,
and my team has since
left me some feedback.
Let's take a look at that now.
With the pull request selected
in the Changes Navigator,
I can see an overview
of my pull request
and everything that's happened
since I published it.
My team has left me
some feedback on my code.
I can reply to these
discussions if I like
or click "View Changes"
to jump straight into the file
in code review mode.
There are some great suggestions
in here from Matt,
and now we have the opportunity
to have this conversation
about my pull request in Xcode
and connect it
directly to source code.
I went ahead and updated
my pull request
in response to the feedback.
Now, looking at the comments
that my teammates have left here
it looks like they're on board
with my latest change.
I see that my colleague has
approved this pull request.
Now I just need to
check my status
of our continuous
integration workflow.
Since I'm using Xcode Cloud,
I can also see the status
of my continuous integration
workflows
within the pull
request's CI popover.
I'm able to quickly see
a summary of my test results,
and clicking on an entry
will jump me straight into
a detailed Xcode Cloud report.
For more information
about Xcode Cloud
and running your code in CI,
check out the session
"Meet Xcode Cloud."
OK, since my teammates
have all approved my changes
and all of my Xcode Cloud jobs
have succeeded,
I'm ready
to merge my pull request.
I'll use the Pull Request
actions and select "Merge."
Xcode allows me
to select a merge strategy
which determines
how changes are integrated
into the target branch.
I'll choose the default, which
will include a Merge Commit.
You can also enter an optional
commit message,
but I'll leave it as it is.
Everything looks good,
so I'll merge it now.
Now that I've merged
my pull request,
it's time to switch back
to other work.
Just like I find it helpful
to ask my peers
for their feedback,
they often ask me
to review their changes, too.
In addition to branches
I've worked on recently,
the source control popover
also shows me the pull requests
that are relevant to me.
I'll see the pull requests
that I've created,
but Xcode also shows me
any pull requests
that my teammates
have requested I review.
Looking in the source control
popover,
it looks like
one of my teammates
has asked me to do just that.
Let's check out
their branch and review it.
Just like with
my own pull requests,
I can see his overview,
review status,
and discussions
on my teammates' pull requests
since I've been tagged in.
Let's take a look
at their changes.
I'll step through the files
in the Changes Navigator
under the pull request node.
Clicking on any of these will
snap me into code review mode,
showing me the changes
that will be applied
if the pull request is merged.
I can leave a comment
for him inside the editor
by secondary clicking
and inserting a new comment
on the line.
I think I see a potential
improvement in his code,
so let's leave a note
for my teammate.
My feedback was pretty minor,
and this pull request
looks good to go.
I'll approve it using
the actions in the top right.
Xcode 13 offers great new ways
to review code
and collaborate with your peers.
Code review mode is a powerful
tool for investigating issues
and behavioral changes
in your app
by giving you insight
into how your app's source
code has changed over time.
Code review mode also
provides you with a new
in-line presentation mode
and expanded comparison options
to allow for more flexibility
for your workflow.
Pull requests allow you
to collaborate with your team
to improve your
app's code quality
by giving and receiving code
feedback on your team's changes
before merging them
into the main branch.
Discussions show up
right in your app's source code,
making teamwork truly part
of the development process.
Thank you, have a great WWDC,
and [foreign language].
[percussive music]