[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Juan Rodriguez Cuellar: Hello,
welcome to WWDC.
My name
is Juan Rodriguez Cuellar,
and I'm a GPU compiler engineer
at Apple.
In this session,
we’re going to talk about
the brand-new features
we’ve added this year
to enhance
our Metal ray tracing API.
But first, let’s do
a quick recap about ray tracing.
Ray-tracing applications
are based on tracing the paths
that rays take as they interact
with a scene.
Ray tracing is applied in
a lot of domains such as audio,
physics simulation, and AI;
but one of the main applications
is photorealistic rendering.
In rendering applications,
ray tracing is used to model
individual rays of light,
which allow us to simulate
effects such as reflections,
soft shadows,
and indirect lighting.
That is just a general
definition of ray tracing.
Let’s talk about
Metal’s approach to it.
We start with a compute kernel.
In our kernel, we generate rays,
which are emitted
into the scene.
We then test those rays
for intersections
against the geometry
in the scene
with an intersector
and an acceleration structure.
Each intersection point
represents light
bouncing off a surface;
how much light bounces
and in what direction
determines what the object
looks like.
We then compute a color
for each intersection
and update the image.
This process is called shading
and it can also generate
additional rays,
and those rays are also tested
for intersection.
We repeat the process
as many times as we’d like
to simulate light
bouncing around the scene.
This year, we focused
our new features
around three major areas.
First, I will talk about how
we’ve added ray-tracing support
to our render pipelines,
which allows us to mix
ray tracing with our rendering.
Then I will introduce you
to the new features
that focus on the usability
and portability.
These features will ease the use
of Metal ray tracing API.
Finally, I will cover the
production rendering features
we’ve added this year
that will help you create
more realistic content.
Let's start with ray tracing
from render pipelines.
Let’s consider the basic case
of a render
that has a single render pass.
With our new support for ray
tracing from render pipelines,
this makes it super easy to add
ray tracing into the render.
However, without this support,
to add ray tracing
to this render
with last year’s
Metal ray tracing API,
we need to add a compute pass.
Let’s just start by adding it
after rendering
to augment the rendered image.
Adding this extra compute pass
means writing more output
to memory
for the compute pass
to use for ray tracing.
Now, what if we wanted
to use ray tracing
in the middle of our render pass
to calculate a value
such as shadowing per pixel?
This means that we need
to split our rendering
and introduce a compute pass.
Thinking more about
what this means,
we need to write out
pixel positions and normals
to memory as inputs
to the ray tracing,
and then read
the intersection results back --
possibly several times.
But with the new support for
ray tracing from render stages,
we never need to leave
our render pass
and we just write our outputs
to memory.
Let's see how we use
our new API.
Preparing our render pipeline
for ray tracing
is similar
to a compute pipeline.
You start by building
your acceleration structure
and defining
custom intersection functions.
To support custom intersection,
we need
an intersection function table
and we need to fill it
with intersection functions.
This part has some differences
compared to last year’s API.
Let’s walk through
how we can do that.
Let’s consider some
simple intersection functions.
I have some functions here
that will allow us
to analytically intersect
objects such as a sphere,
a cone, or torus.
When we create our pipeline,
we add these functions
as linked functions
that we may call.
In this case, we are adding them
to the fragment stage
of the pipeline.
To use the functions,
we need to create
an intersection function table
from the pipeline state
and stage.
Once we have the table,
we can create function handles
from the pipeline state
and stage
and populate the table.
Specifying the functions
for the fragment stage
reuses the linkedFunctions
object
that we introduced last year.
Each stage has its own set
of linkedFunctions
on the render pipeline
descriptor.
Creating an intersection
function table
is much the same as when done
for the compute pipeline.
The only change is the addition
of the stage argument.
To populate the table,
we create the function handle.
Again, the handle
is specific to the stage,
so we need to specify the stage
when requesting the handle.
Once we have
the function handle,
we just insert it
in the function table.
And that’s all you need to do
to prepare your function tables
in render pipeline.
Now we just have to use
everything we have built so far
to intersect.
Actual use is straightforward.
The accelerationStructure and
the intersection function table
are both bound to buffer indices
on the render encoder.
The shaders can then use
these resources
to intersect rays
with an intersector
the same way you would
in a compute kernel.
More details about how
to prepare your pipeline
for ray tracing can be found
in last year’s presentation.
In that talk,
you will learn about
building acceleration
structures,
creating function tables,
and using the intersector
in the shading language.
With ray-tracing support
from render pipelines,
we are opening the door
for even more opportunities
like adding ray tracing
within a single render pass,
mixing ray tracing
with rasterization
in hybrid rendering,
and taking advantage
of optimizations
such as tile functions
on Apple Silicon.
In fact, we will be soon adding
ray tracing to our sample app
that we demoed during the
"Modern Rendering in Metal"
session at WWDC 2019.
With ray tracing
from render pipelines,
we can update the code
to use tile functions
to keep everything
in tile memory.
For more details about this,
see this year’s
"Explore hybrid rendering with
Metal ray tracing" presentation.
Next up, I want to introduce
the new features we've added
this year to improve
the usability and portability
of Metal ray tracing API.
These features not only provide
simpler use
of Metal ray tracing,
but they also provide
portability
from other ray tracing APIs.
One of these new features
is intersection query.
With intersection query,
we’re allowing you to have
more control
over the intersection process.
Intersection query is aimed
toward simple use cases
where intersector
can create overhead.
It is a new way of traversing
the acceleration structure
that gives you the option
of performing
in-line custom intersection
testing.
Let's take a look
at how we currently handle
custom intersection
using last year’s intersector.
Going back to the alpha test
example from last year’s
ray tracing with Metal
presentation,
we demonstrated
how alpha testing is used
to add a lot of geometric detail
to the scene,
as you see here
in the chains and leaves.
We also learned how easy it is
to implement alpha testing
by customizing an intersector
using the triangle intersection
function.
The logic inside this triangle
intersection function
is responsible for accepting
or rejecting intersections
as the ray traverses
the acceleration structure.
In this case, test logic will
reject the first intersection,
but it will accept
the second intersection
since an opaque surface
has been intersected.
Let’s see how
intersection functions are used.
When using Intersector,
when you call intersect(),
we start traversing
the acceleration structure
to find an intersection
and fill our
intersection_result.
Within the intersector,
intersection function
gets called
each time a potential
intersection is found.
And intersections are then
accepted or rejected
based on intersection function
logic.
This is a great programming
model using intersector
since it is both performant
and convenient,
but it does require creating
a new intersection function
and linking it to the pipeline.
There might be cases
where the logic inside
the intersection function
is only a few lines of code,
as it is the case
for alpha test logic.
This is
the intersection function
that contains the logic
to do alpha testing.
With intersection query,
we can place this logic in-line
without the need
of this intersection function.
Here is how.
With intersection query,
when you start
the intersection process,
your ray traverses
the acceleration structure,
and the query object contains
the state of the traversal
and the result.
Each time the ray intersects
a custom primitive
or a nonopaque triangle,
control is returned
to the shader
for you to evaluate
the intersection candidates.
If the current candidate passes
your custom intersection logic,
you commit it to update
the current
committed intersection
and then continue
the intersection process.
On the other hand, if candidate
fails custom intersection logic,
you can just ignore it
and continue.
Let me show you the code
to do alpha testing
using intersection query.
First, you start the traversal.
Note that we loop on next
to evaluate
all candidate intersections.
Second, you evaluate
each candidate
starting by checking
the candidate type.
For alpha test example,
you're interested
on intersections
of triangle type.
After checking the type,
you'll want to query
some intersection information
about the candidate.
We perform three queries
for information needed
in the alpha test logic
which is now in-lined.
Finally, if the candidate
intersection passes alpha test,
you will commit it
so that it becomes
the current committed
intersection.
Up to now, you have traversed
the whole acceleration structure
evaluating
candidate intersections
and commit the intersections
that passed
the alpha test logic.
Now, you need to query committed
intersection information
to do the shading.
First, you will query
the committed type.
If none
of the candidate intersections
met your conditions to become
a committed intersection,
committed type will be none,
which means
the current ray missed.
On the other hand,
if there is
a committed intersection,
you would want
to query information
about the intersection
applicable
to the intersection type
and then use it for shading.
That’s all the code you need
to perform alpha testing
using intersection query.
With the introduction
of intersection query
and the introduction of
intersector to render pipeline,
we are giving you
more opportunities
to start bringing
Metal ray tracing to your apps.
Here are some things to consider
when choosing between
intersector objects
and intersection queries.
Start by considering
if you have existing code,
such as using the intersector
in compute
and your plans
for porting that code.
If you have existing query code
from other APIs,
intersection query
can help to port that code.
Next, you have the complexity
of handling custom intersection.
Intersector requires
intersection functions
and tables, and it might be
easier to use intersection query
to handle custom
intersection yourself.
The last question
is performance.
In simpler cases,
intersection query
can avoid overhead
when building your pipeline
for ray tracing,
but custom intersection handling
requires returning to your code
during traversal,
which could have
a performance impact,
depending on the use case.
Also, use of multiple
query objects
will require more memory.
On the other hand,
intersector can support
those more complex cases
by encapsulating
all of the intersection work.
If you have the opportunity,
we would recommend
comparing the performance
of both solutions.
That’s all about
intersection query.
Now let’s move on
to some other new features.
The next two features
we’re going to talk about
are user instance IDs
and instance transforms.
These features will help
you add more information
to your acceleration structure
and access more of the data
that is already there.
Here is why we think these
are really useful features.
If we look back
to the sample code
from last year’s presentation,
we have multiple instances
of the kernel box.
Underneath this, we have an
instance acceleration structure
with a set of nodes that branch
until you reach the instances.
Looking at two
of these instances,
they are at the lowest level
of the instance acceleration
structure.
Currently, when you intersect
one of these instances,
you only get
the system’s instance ID
from the intersection results.
With this, you could maintain
your own table of data,
but there’s data
that we can expose
in the acceleration structure
to help you.
Let’s talk about user-defined
instance IDs first.
With this feature, you can
specify a custom 32-bit value
for each instance
and then you get this value
as part of the intersection
results.
This is really useful for you
to index into your own
data structures,
but it can also be used
to encode custom data.
For example, here we’re using
the user ID
to encode a custom color
for each instance.
You could use this
for a simpler reflection
with no need to look up any
additional material information.
This is just one example,
but the opportunities
are endless.
I can see how you would want
to encode things
like per-instance material ID
or per-instance flags.
We have created
an extended version
of instance descriptor type that
is used to specify these IDs.
Make sure you specify which type
of descriptor you’re using
on the instance acceleration
structure descriptor.
In the shading language,
the value of the current
user instance ID
is available as an input
to intersection functions
with the instancing tag.
To obtain the values
after intersection,
the user-defined instance ID
is available
from the intersection result
when using
an intersector object.
And when using
intersection query object,
there is a corresponding query
to access
the user-defined instance ID
for both candidate
and committed intersections.
Just like user instance ID,
we have added support
for accessing your instance
transformation matrices.
This data is already specified
in the instance descriptor,
and it is stored
in the acceleration structure.
This year, we’ve exposed
these matrices
from the shading language.
You can access
the instance transforms
in the intersection functions
when you apply
the instancing
and world_space_data tags.
Similarly, the instance
transforms are provided
in the intersection results
when using an intersector
with instancing
and world_space_data tags.
When using intersection query
with instancing tag,
there are corresponding queries
for accessing
the instance transforms
for both candidate
and committed intersections.
To summarize,
this year we are improving
the usability and portability
of Metal ray tracing API
by introducing
three new features.
Intersection query comes
as an alternative to intersector
that provides more control
over the intersection process.
And with the introduction
of user instance ID
and instance transforms
features,
we are providing you the ability
to access data
from the acceleration structure
instead of having to handle
some external mapping
in your code.
In addition,
these three features
offer portability
from other ray tracing APIs,
making cross-platform
development easier.
So far in the session,
we have talked about
our new support for ray tracing
in render pipeline
and the different usability
and portability features
we have added this year.
Now, let me show you
what features we are introducing
to enhance production rendering.
Since Metal ray tracing API
was introduced last year,
people have been using it
to render
some amazing
high-quality content.
This year, we’ve added
two new features
to make it possible to render
even better content.
Let's start
with extended limits.
Since we released
the Metal ray tracing API,
some users have started hitting
the internal limits
of our acceleration structures,
especially in production-scale
use cases.
So we are adding support
for an extended-limits mode
to support even larger scenes.
Last year, we chose these limits
to balance
acceleration structure size
in order to favor performance
with typical scene sizes.
There is a potential
performance trade-off
to turning on this feature,
so you’ll need to determine
which mode is best
for your application.
Extended-limits mode
increases the limit
on the number of primitives,
geometries, instances,
as well as the size of the mask
used for filtering out
instances.
To turn it on, you first specify
extended limits mode
when building
your acceleration structures.
Then specify
the extended_limits tag
on the intersector object
in the shading language.
That’s all you need to do
to turn on extended limits!
Next, let’s talk about motion.
In computer graphics,
we often assume that the camera
exposure is instantaneous.
However, in real life,
the camera exposure lasts
for a nonzero period of time.
If an object moves relative
to the camera during that time,
it will appear blurred
in the image.
In this extreme example,
the person in the center
has been standing still
during the whole exposure
while everyone else
has been moving,
causing them to be blurred.
This effect can go a long way
towards making
computer-generated images
look more realistic.
In this example,
the sphere is animated
across several frames,
but each frame is still
an instantaneous exposure,
resulting in a choppy animation.
Using the motion API,
we can simulate
camera exposure
lasting for a nonzero
amount of time.
This results in a smoother
and more realistic-looking
animation.
If we freeze the video,
you can see that the boundaries
of the sphere are blurred
in the direction of motion
just like a real camera.
Real-time applications
like games
often approximate this effect
in screen space.
But ray tracing
allows us to simulate
physically accurate motion blur,
which even extends
to indirect effects
like shadows and reflections.
Let’s take a look
at how the motion-blurred
version was rendered.
Motion blur is a straightforward
extension to ray tracing.
Most ray-tracing applications
already randomly sample
the physical dimensions such as
incoming light directions
for indirect lighting.
To add motion blur,
we can just choose a random time
for each ray as well.
Metal will intersect the scene
to match the point in time
associated with each ray.
For instance, this ray
will see the scene like this.
Another ray will see the scene
like this.
As we accumulate
more and more samples,
we’ll start to converge
on a motion-blurred image.
You could actually already
implement this today
using custom intersection
functions.
You could compute
the bounding boxes
of each primitive
throughout the entire exposure
and then use
these bounding boxes
to build
an acceleration structure.
However,
this would be inefficient;
the bounding boxes
could be so large
that some rays would need
to check for intersection
with primitives that they will
never actually intersect.
Instead, we can use Metal’s
built-in support for motion blur
which is designed to efficiently
handle cases like this.
The first thing we need to do
is associate a random time
with each ray in our
Metal shading language code.
We start by generating
a random time
within the exposure interval,
then we just pass it
to the intersector.
The next thing we need to do
is to provide our
animated geometry to Metal.
We do this using
a common method of animation
called keyframe animation.
The animation is created
by modeling the ball
at key points in time
called keyframes.
These keyframes
are uniformly distributed
between the start and end
of our animation.
As rays traverse
the acceleration structure,
they can fetch data
from any keyframe
based on their time value.
For instance Ray A
would see the scene
as it was modeled in Keyframe 11
because its time
happens to match Keyframe 11.
In contrast, Ray B’s time is
in between Keyframes 3 and 4.
Therefore, the geometry
of the two keyframes
is interpolated for Ray B.
Motion is supported
at both the instance
and primitive level.
Instance animation can be used
to rigidly transform
entire objects.
This is cheaper
than primitive animation
but doesn’t allow objects
to deform.
On the other hand,
primitive animation
is more expensive,
but can be used for things like
skinned-character animation.
Note that both instance
and primitive animation
are based on keyframe animation.
Let’s first talk about
instance motion.
In an instance acceleration
structure,
each instance is associated
with a transformation matrix.
This matrix describes
where to place the geometry
in the scene.
In this example,
we have two primitive
acceleration structures:
one for the sphere and another
for the static geometry.
Each primitive acceleration
structure has a single instance.
To animate the sphere,
we will provide
two transformation matrices,
representing the start
and end point of the animation.
Metal will then interpolate
these two matrices
based on the time parameter
for each ray.
Keep in mind that this is
a specific example
using two keyframes,
but Metal supports an arbitrary
number of key frames.
We provide these matrices
using acceleration structure
descriptors.
The standard
Metal instance descriptor
only has room for a single
transformation matrix.
So instead, we’ll use the new
motion instance descriptor.
With this descriptor,
the transformation matrices
are stored in a separate buffer.
The instance descriptor
then contains a start index
and count representing a range
of transformation matrices
in the transform buffer.
Each matrix represents
a single keyframe.
Let's see how to set up
an instance descriptor
with the new motion
instance descriptor type.
We start by creating the usual
instance acceleration structure
descriptor.
We then specify we’re using
the new motion instance
descriptor type.
Then, we specify
the instanceDescriptorBuffer
that contains
the motion instance descriptors.
Finally, we’ll need to bind
the transformsBuffer
containing the vertex buffer
for each keyframe.
The remaining properties
are the same
as any other
instance acceleration structure,
and we can build it
like any other
acceleration structure as well.
We only need to make one change
in the shading language,
which is to specify
the instance_motion tag.
This tells the intersector
to expect
an acceleration structure
with instance motion.
And that’s all we need to do
to set up instance motion.
Next, let’s talk about
primitive motion.
With primitive motion,
each primitive
can move separately,
meaning it can be used
for things
like skinned-character
animation.
Remember that we need
to provide a separate 3D model
for each keyframe,
and Metal will then interpolate
between them.
We’ll need to provide
vertex data for each keyframe.
Let’s see how to set this up.
We’ll start by collecting
each keyframe’s vertex buffer
into an array.
The MTLMotionKeyframeData
object
allows you to specify
a buffer and offset.
We’ll use it to specify
the vertex buffer
for each keyframe.
Next, we’ll create a motion
triangle geometry descriptor.
This is just like creating
any other geometry descriptor,
except we use
a slightly different type.
And instead of providing
a single vertex buffer,
we’ll provide our array
of vertexBuffers.
Finally, we’ll create the usual
primitive acceleration
structure descriptor.
Next, we provide
our geometryDescriptor.
Then we’ll specify
the number of keyframes.
Similar to instance motion,
we’ll need to make
a small change
in the shading language
to specify
the primitive_motion tag.
And that’s all we need to do
to set up primitive motion!
Keep in mind that you can
actually use
both types of animation
at the same time
for even more dynamic scenes.
Next, let’s take a look
at this all in action!
This is a path-traced rendering
created by
our Advanced Content team.
The video was rendered
on a Mac Pro
with an AMD Radeon
Pro Vega II GPU.
The ninja character was animated
using a skinned skeletal
animation technique
which allows each primitive
to move separately.
Each frame was rendered
by combining
256 randomly timed samples taken
using the primitive motion API.
We can slow it down to see
the difference more clearly.
The version on the left
doesn’t have motion blur,
while the version
on the right does.
And we can increase
the exposure time even further
to simulate a long exposure.
Motion blur can make
a big difference in realism
and it’s now easy to add
with the new motion API.
So that’s it for motion.
Thanks for watching this talk.
We have been putting
a lot of work
into our Metal ray tracing API
to provide the tools you need
to enhance your app.
We can’t wait to see
the amazing content
that you will create with it.
Thank you,
and have a great WWDC!
♪