[ethereal percussion music]
♪ ♪
[Ellie] Hi.
My name is Ellie Epskamp-Hunt.
I work as a Safari engineer.
Today, I'm giving an overview
of some new Web Extensions API
avilable in Safari.
Last year, Safari added support
for the Web Extensions API
on macOS.
It's been amazing to see all
of the new Safari extensions
that have shipped
over the past year
that use this new API support.
And with this release,
we're really excited
to bring web extensions
to iOS and iPadOS.
You can learn more
about extensions
on these new platforms
in its own dedicated session,
"Meet Safari Web Extensions
on iOS."
And if you wanna learn more
about Safari Web Extensions
in general,
you can check out
last year's session.
Today, we're covering
three new extension APIs.
First, we'll talk about
non-persistent background pages,
which are a way
to structure your extension
for better performance.
Then, I'll introduce
a content-blocking API
for web extensions called
declarative net request.
And at the end,
we'll look at how extensions
can customize new tabs
in Safari.
Before we learn more
about this new API,
let's talk about persistent
background pages.
Web extensions are made
using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS.
Some extensions have a script
that run in the background
of the browser
called a background page.
It doesn't have any visible UI,
but it can react to events
like a tab opening or a message
from another part
of the extension.
A persistent background
page never closes.
So, if I have two extensions
turned on in my browser,
there'll be two background
pages constantly running.
And if I use eight extensions,
that's eight extension processes
running in the background
at all times.
We can see there's
a problem here.
Persistent background pages
are like these invisible tabs
that a user can never close,
and they eat up memory
and increase CPU usage.
Users shouldn't have
to make a compromise
between using their extensions
and getting great performance
out of their browser.
So instead,
extensions can adopt
a non-persistent
background page.
These types of pages
can come and go as needed,
making your extension
more performant
and giving your users a better
browsing experience overall.
If you're developing for iOS,
your extension must have
a non-persistent background page
because of the resource
constraints on iOS devices.
So now that we have
an understanding of the reasons
to use a non-persistent
background page,
let's take a look
at how they work.
The lifetime of a non-persistent
background page
is structured around events.
A background page
registers event listeners
in order to react to things
that happen in the browser
like a tab closing
or a message from another part
of the extension.
And those events help
the browser to determine
if your background page
should be loaded or unloaded.
Let's take a look at an example.
When your extension
is turned on or updated,
your background page
will be loaded,
and it will register
event listeners.
For the sake of this example,
let's say that
this background page
has exactly one listener
for a message
from a content script.
If time passes
and our content script
doesn't send any messages,
the background page
will be unloaded by the browser
because of that inactivity.
But if our content script
sends a message,
the background page
will be woken up
so it can receive
and react to that message.
And after the event happens,
the background page
will stay loaded.
But if time passes again
and no more events fire,
the background page will unload.
So with that mental model
in mind,
we can talk about how
to actually implement
a non-persistent
background page.
First, you'll add
the "persistent" key
to the background section
of your manifest.
And then you might have to make
a couple more changes
to your background script.
Because your background page
can be unloaded,
you'll need to use
the storage API
to write information
to disk as needed.
Use browser.storage
to maintain information
across the lifetime
of your background page.
Next, you'll need to register
your event listeners
at the top level
of your script.
Do not register listeners
in the completion handler
of another event listener.
And you'll want to use
the browser.alarms API
instead of timers.
A timer won't be invoked
if the background page
has unloaded.
Now let's talk about
some code you want to avoid.
Remove calls to
browser.extension.
getBackgroundPage.
It won't wake up
the background page
if it's already been unloaded.
And finally,
you'll need to remove
any webRequest listeners.
webRequest is an API that
lets you analyze web traffic,
and the frequency
at which webRequest events fire
make this API incompatible
with non-persistent
background pages.
So to see how this
all works together,
let's try it out in Safari.
I'm using a modified version
of the sample code
from last year's session
about Safari extensions.
This extension can replace words
in web pages with emoji
and reports how many total
replacements have happened.
First, let's see
what this extension does
without making any changes.
Because we have left out
the "persistent" key
in the manifest, the background
page is persistent by default.
I'll build and run the app
containing the extension.
And then I'll turn it on
in Safari's preferences.
Now I'll use the extension
on a web page.
Let's go to this Wikipedia
article about fish,
and I'll use the popover
to interact with the extension.
When I click
the "replace words" button,
every instance
of the word "fish"
was replaced with a fish emoji.
If I click the popover again,
I can see my total number
of words that've been replaced.
The background page
for this extension is in charge
of keeping track
of that replacement count.
Let's head to Activity Monitor
to take a look
at our extension process.
Here we can see
the web process
where all our extension code
is running.
Because our extension uses
a persistent background page,
this process will always be
running when Safari is running,
even when I stop using
this extension hours later.
So let's make this
extension a little better
and make its background
page non-persistent.
The first thing I'll do
is add the "persistent" key
to the background section
of my manifest.
And let's stop here and see
if our extension still works.
I'll build the app
containing my extension.
I'll come back to Safari
and reload the page.
Then I'll replace some words.
After that, I'll briefly wait,
giving the background page
some time to go idle.
For the purpose of this demo,
I've modified Safari
to unload background pages
much faster than normal.
We can verify that
the background page has,
in fact, unloaded
in the develop menu,
under Web Extension
Background Pages.
This is also where you can
inspect your background page.
Note that if you choose
to inspect the page
when it's unloaded,
it will immediately load.
Now that the background page
is unloaded,
let's open the popover again.
Instead of our expected count
of 564,
we see zero words replaced.
So we've got a bug
in our extension.
We need to go back
and make some more changes
so that our extension
works correctly
with a non-persistent
background page.
Here we are in the code
for the background page
of the extension.
This background page
does two things.
It either adds one
to the word replacement count,
or it reports the current count.
The global variable is
what's causing our bug.
When the background page
is reloaded,
the count is reset to 0.
So instead
of maintaining that state
that 564 words were replaced,
we lose it.
So to get around this, let's
use the browser.storage API
to save and load
our word count as needed.
First, we'll add some code
to load that count from storage.
I'll parse the result
from the storage API
to get the value that I want.
And I'll save that value
back to storage
whenever it's updated.
And then I'll bring
that onMessage listener
into the body
of the storage callback.
But wait.
We've got a problem.
We know that event listeners
must be registered
at the top level of our script,
so this isn't going to work.
So let's restructure things here
and bring the storage call
into the body of the listener.
And because we are using
the storage API,
we need to add the storage
permission to the manifest.
Now I'll rebuild the app
and test my extension again.
I'll do the exact
same thing as before.
I'll view that Wikipedia page
about fish and reload the page.
Then I'll replace some words
and wait for a moment,
giving our background
some time to unload.
Great.
Our popover now reports
the correct number
of words replaced.
We took an extension with
a persistent background page
and successfully converted it
to use a non-persistent
background page.
And if we go back
to Activity Monitor,
the extension process
is no longer present
after the background page
has unloaded
because we did this work
to adopt a non-persistent
background page.
That was an overview
of non-persistent
background page support
in Safari.
Remember, if you are developing
an extension for iOS,
you'll have to adopt a
non-persistent background page.
Next, let's take a look
at declarative net request,
a new content-blocking API.
Safari has supported
Content Blocker Extensions,
built using WebKit Content
Rule List, since 2015.
There are a couple improvements
to them this year,
which you can check out
in Apple's
updated documentation.
However,
web extensions haven't had
that kind of fast,
privacy-preserving,
content-blocking capability
until now.
The declarative net request API,
which was recently
introduced by Chrome,
checks all of those boxes.
Let's go over the basics.
The content-blocking rules
are written in a JSON format.
Those JSON rules
are logically grouped
into files called rulesets,
and there's JavaScript API
that lets you individually
toggle these rulesets on or off.
And because Chrome
supports this API as well,
you can write one
content blocker that can run
in multiple browsers
across multiple platforms.
Let's go over how to write
content-blocking rules
using declarative net request.
The first step is
to specify a ruleset
in the extension's manifest.
Here, I've declared one ruleset.
You'll also need to add
the declarative net
request permission.
Here's an example of
a declarative net request rule
that would go inside the file
we specified in the ruleset.
It has four pieces.
There's a unique ID
along with a priority,
which determines the order
in which the rules are applied.
The action piece of the rule
allows you to block, allow,
or upgrade the scheme
of a resource.
And the condition is
where you tell Safari where
and under what conditions
to run this rule.
In the condition dictionary
of this rule,
there are two keys.
"regexFilter" is matched
against the resource URL,
and the "resourceTypes" array
specifies the types
of resources
that will be blocked.
Let's go into more detail
about what's supported
in this condition dictionary.
Here are all the resource
types you can target
using a declarative
net request rule.
The "excludedResourceTypes" key
lets you specify the types
that you don't
wanna match against.
The "domainType key" allows you
to block a resource
based on the relation
of the domain
of the resource being loaded
and the domain of the document.
A "first-party" load
is any load where the URL
has the same security
origin as the document.
Every other case
is "third-party."
And finally,
the "Case-Sensitive" key
allows you to control
whether the regexFilter
is case sensitive or not.
By default, it's true.
So now, let's build
a web extension
that blocks content using
the declarative net request API.
The first thing I'll do is add
a declarative net request
section to the manifest.
Inside that declarative
net request section,
I'll add a ruleset
by writing an ID,
a bool to indicate that it's on,
and a path to the JSON file
containing my rules.
And while we're in the manifest,
I'll also add the declarative
net request permission.
From here, let's go
into the ruleset JSON file.
I'll write a rule to block
images on all web pages.
I'll build the app containing
the extension and open Safari.
Notice how this extension
doesn't have the ability
to see any browsing history
or web page contents,
even though it will be able
to block content
across all web pages.
Before I turn on the extension,
I'm going to open a WebKit blog
post with some images in it.
We can see that there are
two images on this web page.
If I come back to preferences,
and turn on the extension,
and then reload the page,
the images will be blocked.
Now let's go
to another web page
like this Wikipedia page
about fish.
Images are also blocked here,
but I'd actually prefer
if I could see images
on this particular page.
So let's modify our extension
so that images are blocked
everywhere except here.
I'll come back to Xcode
and write a rule
to allow images on this page.
The action type of this rule
will be "allow,"
and it will be
a higher-priority rule
than our first blocking rule.
I'll rebuild my app,
and then I'll come back
to Safari.
I'll reload the page.
But this new rule didn't work
because I'm still
not seeing any images.
I'll look
in extension preferences
for any error messages.
Okay, it looks like
I used an empty array
for the resource types key
instead of an array
with the string "image."
I'll come back to Xcode
to fix my mistake.
I'll rebuild and come back
to Safari's preferences
to verify
that the error message is gone.
Then, I'll reload the page.
And great, images are
no longer being blocked
on this Wikipedia page.
So that was an overview
of how to build a web extension
that can block content
on the web.
You can consult
Apple's documentation
for more information on how
to use declarative net request.
Finally, let's take a look
at how extensions
can customize new tabs
in Safari.
We know that users love
to personalize their browser,
and extensions are
a great way to do that.
The new tab override API
allows extensions
to take over the new tab page
in Safari
and customize it completely.
This API is already
publicly available
in Safari 14.1.
New tab overrides are
declared in the manifest.
And when the user
turns on an extension
with a new tab override,
they make a choice
on whether or not
to let that extension
take over new tabs in Safari.
Here's how you'd point out
your new tab override page
in the manifest.
Let's build an extension
that uses this new API together.
I'm going to add
a new tab override
to the Sea Creator extension.
Our goal is to have
a fun web page appear
every time we open a new tab
in Safari.
I'll start by declaring
that my HTML page
is a new tab override
in the manifest.
I have some existing HTML
and CSS files
that I'd like to use.
They are in my extension's
resources folder.
I just need to add them
to the Xcode project.
If you've never added
a file to an Xcode project,
don't worry.
It's pretty easy.
I'll click File,
Add Files to Sea Creator,
and then select
the files I want to add,
making sure they're a part
of the extension target
and not the app target.
This HTML creates
a colorful page
with a fun fact.
So let's run the app,
and in Safari,
I'll turn on the extension.
I get this prompt, asking me
if I want this extension
to be able to take over
my new tabs and windows.
I'll allow it to do so.
If I wanted to make changes
to this later,
I can come
into General settings.
But now, when I create
new tabs in Safari,
my new tab page appears.
It looks pretty good!
But I wanna make
a couple of tweaks.
My new tab override page
doesn't have a very nice title.
So back in Xcode,
I'll add a title
so my pages look good
in Safari's tab bar.
I can also pick
a different theme color
if I want something distinct
from the one Safari inferred
from the page.
This meta tag I'm using isn't
specific to new tab overrides.
It will work on any web page.
If you wanna learn more
about the changes
to Safari's UI,
be sure to checkout
the session called
"Design for Safari 15."
Let's see how that looks now.
I'll build again.
And back in Safari,
I'll create a new tab.
Great.
We successfully added
a new tab override
to the Sea Creator extension.
And that was a look
at how extensions
can customize new tabs
in Safari.
Today, we discussed
three new Web Extension APIs
available in Safari
on macOS and iOS.
I encourage you to download
the sample projects associated
with this session and play
around with the new APIs.
I showed you how these
extensions work on macOS,
but they work on iOS as well.
We'd also love to know
what you think.
You can use Feedback Assistant
to file bugs,
or you can come chat with us
on the Safari Developer Forums.
And finally,
check out the other sessions
I mentioned today
if you haven't already.