[upbeat music]
[Katherine] Hello.
My name is Katherine Nepo.
I'm a program manager
with the App Store Trust
and Safety team.
In this video, my colleague
Jeremy Stober and I
will show you
how to safeguard your
accounts,
promotions, and content.
Today, we will discuss
the importance of designing
for trust and safety
and present a suite of tools
that you can use
to protect your apps
and your
customers from attackers.
Jeremy will walk you
through account risks
and promotion abuse.
I will close by talking
about content risks.
The Apple platform is designed
to help your business
grow and thrive with experiences
that are trusted, safe,
and fair
for you and your customers.
We're going to review
how Sign in with Apple
brings the simplicity
and security
of two-factor
authentication to your app.
We will then learn how you
can protect promotions
and offers and defend
the integrity of your
app with DeviceCheck
and App Attest.
Your features are exciting
to your customers
and may be
attractive to attackers.
If your app includes
the ability to create
and manage accounts,
supports user-generated content,
offers promotional pricing,
or includes premium content,
it may be a target
for fraud and abuse.
There are many types
of abuse that can happen
after you publish your app.
Let's take a closer
look at three of them.
In many app experiences,
accounts are used to protect
users' assets.
Attackers, eager to gain access,
seek new ways to take
over customer accounts
and steal their data.
If your app offers promotions,
you may be targeted by
attackers seeking to take
advantage of your discounts
or otherwise manipulate
your app or server.
These attackers can be
opportunistic individuals
or large-scale operations.
Attackers can scrape servers
for valuable content and steal
legitimate apps to modify,
repackage, and resell them
outside of the App Store,
which can impact your business.
I will now turn it over
to Jeremy to talk about your
account risks and how you
can protect your users.
[Jeremy] Thank you, Katherine.
I'll begin by talking
about account risks
that you should be aware
of as an app developer.
Many apps and services require
customers to create accounts.
However,
several problems can arise
from managing customer accounts.
For example,
there is an incentive
for others to compromise
the security of your
customers' valuable accounts.
Accounts can be taken over
through no fault of yours.
Your users might be
vulnerable to sophisticated
phishing attacks,
have their passwords leaked
from unaffiliated services,
or be the victim
of misplaced trust.
According to the Anti-phishing
Working Group,
an international consortium,
the number of reported phishing
attacks
observed by its members
doubled over the course of 2020.
Since user accounts are
valuable,
attackers may target them.
In addition to account
compromises, if you use customer
feedback in your app,
for example, to power a ratings
or recommendation system,
you may be creating a situation
where that feedback can be
used for illicit gain.
This might incentivize
the creation of high volumes
of fake accounts that are used
to manipulate these systems.
Fake account creations can
overload infrastructure,
disrupt user experience, and
impact the overall authenticity
of the app experience
you are working hard to craft.
There are other forms
of abuse that can arise
from inauthentic account
creation.
For example, if users
can communicate with each other,
then there may be an incentive
to send unsolicited advertising
over the platform you create
using fake accounts.
This can adversely impact
the customer experience
and your reputation.
Apple offers a few tools
that developers can use
to better
manage account risks.
One method to avoid a number
of issues with account
management is to adopt
Sign in with Apple.
Integrating with
Sign in with Apple will
allow you to benefit
from Apple's robust
and ongoing efforts to keep
customer accounts secure.
Sign in with Apple is
protected by Apple's
two-factor authentication.
Customers on Apple devices
can sign in
and re-authenticate with Face
ID or Touch ID any time.
The benefits to integrating
with Sign in with Apple
are not limited to security.
The credential return on first
authorization includes
a flag that indicates with
a high degree confidence
that a user is real
and not a bot.
This flag
can be checked on the client.
If a flag indicates
a user is likely real,
no additional challenge
is needed.
However,
if the platform is unsupported,
or the value returned
is unknown, a challenge
to the user is recommended
to prevent scripted traffic.
To provide this flag,
Apple uses a private, secure,
on-device machine learning model
in combination with
service side inferences
based on account activity.
With Sign in with Apple,
you can take advantage
of Apple's world-class security
and industry-leading
antifraud protections.
If you are not using
Sign in with Apple,
there are a number of tools
that you can use to improve
account security and prevent
inauthentic account creations.
There are several
videos describing ways
to encourage strong
and unique passwords
without
increasing user friction.
Watch "One tap account
security upgrades"
and "Autofill everywhere"
for more information.
For inauthentic account
creation, prevention means
making risk-based decisions
using the data
you are able to collect from
the account creation request
like email domain
and other account details
that may be part
of your sign-up flow.
As part of your strategy,
you may want to limit the number
of account creations that can
happen on a single Apple device.
Limiting account creation
on physical devices
will make it more difficult
to create large numbers
of fake accounts.
Apple offers an API
called DeviceCheck
that can help with this.
Using this API,
you can effectively
limit account creations
on authentic Apple devices.
You may be promoting
your business with free
or discounted items in your app.
Next, I'll talk about an example
of how this can be abused.
Suppose you want to offer
an in-app promotion
to grow your business.
Depending on the type of app,
this could be anything
from a free sandwich
to a discounted trial.
You may find, however, that
uptake of the special offer
comes at a cost, as some
people abuse the promotion
by re-downloading the app
multiple times.
Using the DeviceCheck API,
you can
limit the number of promotion
redemptions per device
while protecting user privacy.
The service allows you to set
two bits of information
on each device in a way
that's strongly tied
to device authenticity
and that can be read back
even after a complete
reset of the device.
At a high level, the use
of DeviceCheck will allow you
to verify that the device is
real and allow you to query
previously set values
of the two permitted bits.
You have the ability
to set and change the bits
as you please.
In the case of a free promotion,
you can use the value
of the return bits
to determine if the device
has been used to redeem
the promotion in the past.
You can also choose to set
the bits per device
on account creation instead,
which would offer
a robust new signal
tied to verified hardware
that you can use
in rate limiting account
creation in your app.
After a period of time, you can
choose to reset the bits.
This will facilitate
reuse of the promotion
on a time period that you
control and could help
manage situations
where devices change hands.
More details are available
in the videos
"Privacy and your apps"
as well as the video
“Mitigate fraud
with App Attest and DeviceCheck.”
Katherine will now talk about
ways to protect your content
and APIs from
inauthentic clients.
[Katherine] Thank you, Jeremy.
Let's walk
through some of the risks
potentially posed
to your content.
Your content is valuable
and may be an attractive
target for attackers.
An attacker
can develop and distribute
unauthorized software
that allows unpermitted access
to your app's premium content.
This illicit access may
negatively impact your earnings
and create opportunities
for cheating and deception.
Such abuses may undermine
the trust of your users
and ultimately harm
your business.
To help
you protect the integrity
of your app experiences,
we created App Attest,
which provides app protection
starting with iOS 14
and tvOS 15.
App Attest enables you to verify
that the apps connecting
to your servers
are the apps that you
published on the App Store,
unmodified and running
on genuine Apple devices.
Leveraging Apple's secure
enclave processor,
iOS and tvOS generate
a cryptographic attestation
of your app's identity which you
can send to your server
for verification before making
your critical assets available.
App Attest is easy to use.
With only a few exchanges
between your app and your server
you can verify the identity
of the app requesting
your content.
For more information
on App Attest,
including how your server
can perform verification,
please check out the
"Mitigate fraud with App Attest
and DeviceCheck"
technical video.
The tools we discussed
today will enable you
to guard your apps,
your users, and your content.
Implement Sign in with Apple
to secure your accounts from
attackers and prevent access
to your valuable data.
Use DeviceCheck to prevent abuse
of your promotional offerings.
And protect your content
with App Attest by validating
the authenticity of the apps
connecting to your server
before serving their requests.
Thank you for watching.
We look forward to seeing
your businesses grow
and thrive in a fair, safe,
and trusted environment.
[percussive music]