[upbeat music]
[Sonia]
Hi, I am Sonia,
a performance tools engineer.
Today,
my colleague Shreyas and I
will show you how to diagnose
power
and performance regressions
in your app.
Every year,
you work hard to release
the best apps possible.
You want to invite users
to an amazing experience
in your apps, which is why
optimizing for power
and performance is so important.
This talk will cover
key metrics that affect
your app's performance,
tools to help you
discover regressions,
insights to help you
reduce disk writes,
and APIs to automate
your performance workflows.
To help you
optimize performance,
there's a comprehensive
set of metrics and diagnostics
available to you
through the Xcode Organizer
and App Store Connect API,
without any changes to your app.
As you know, performance
is not easy to optimize.
With so many metrics
and diagnostics available,
it can be easy to get lost
in a sea of information.
You want to make each release
better than the last,
but need a quick way
to summarize
your performance priorities.
The Xcode Organizer
is a great tool
to understand performance.
It currently collects data
across seven metric categories,
including battery, launches,
hangs, memory,
disk writes, scroll hitches,
and terminations.
That's a lot
of information to process.
Let's dive
into the Xcode Organizer next
and diagnose
a performance regression.
I'll start by viewing
different metrics for my app.
I can choose
from seven metric categories
on the left navigation bar.
Some categories,
like battery and terminations,
can have multiple sections,
as well as subcategories
detailing different event types.
I can optionally
choose between dozens
of different device types,
as well as percentiles for top
and typical users of my app.
The center of the organizer
shows a chart with data
for the last 16 releases.
In this case,
I want to investigate
terminations in my app.
The onscreen chart
shows terminations
increased significantly
in the latest version,
indicating there may be an issue
with the release,
specifically due to more
illegal instruction exits
highlighted in blue.
There's such a rich
and interesting set of metrics
available for me to understand
performance in the field,
but with so many device options,
metric categories,
and subcategories,
it's not clear
where I should
start to optimize performance.
That's why
there's now an insights section
in the organizer to highlight
all of your
performance priorities
and streamline your workflow.
The Xcode Organizer
now processes metrics data
and identifies
interesting trends
such as performance regressions.
Before I dive in, let's talk
about what
a performance regression is
and how they're detected.
Regressions occur when an app
performs poorly
in a power or performance area
relative to recent releases.
For example,
when it takes longer
to launch after a release.
In this example,
the metric is analyzed
over recent releases
to determine
if the value is trending up.
The metric is then averaged
over the last few releases
and compared
to the latest value.
If the metric is trending up
and the latest value is higher
than the average
over the last few releases,
it's flagged as a regression
and summarized
in the insights section.
In this example,
the app took on average
1.1 seconds to launch,
then suddenly jumped
to 2.5 seconds
in the last release,
causing it to be flagged
as a regression.
Now that you know
how regressions are flagged,
let's go back to the organizer
and dive in to a few examples.
Here's a look
at the regressions tab.
It's a one-stop shop
where you can discover
your top performance priorities.
Is your app suddenly crashing
after a recent release?
Is that cool new camera feature
draining the device battery?
You'll find the answer
to these questions
and more
in the insights section.
All the data you need
will be highlighted
in this go-to section
to understand
performance in the field.
Here you can discover
regressions
for different metric categories
and subcategories
across devices for typical
and top percentiles
grouped together.
The left-hand side
will summarize
which metric regressed,
by how much,
and for which percentiles,
highlighting exactly
what you need to focus on
to create even better apps.
My app has several regressions
across terminations,
memory, and disk writes.
Next, I'll go through an example
of each
and how to interpret them.
I'll start
with termination regressions.
Before I go
through terminations,
check out the video on
"Why is my app getting killed?"
for more context.
Each regression will summarize
all the top issues
from my latest app release.
The top of the section
shows illegal instructions
are causing the crashes,
which can occur
when my app accesses
an invalid function pointer.
Further down, there's a chart
of illegal instruction exits
over the last four releases
of my app.
The top of the chart
shows which percentiles
and devices were affected.
In this case,
top percentile users
on all iPhones
are experiencing more crashes
in the latest release.
The average and latest number
of illegal instruction exits
are to the right of the chart.
In this case,
my app has started crashing
every ten days
in the latest version.
Onscreen terminations
are very disruptive
because users will have to go
back to the Home screen
and relaunch the app frequently.
I'll want to remove references
to the invalid function pointer
causing these crashes
and can dig in further
by taking a look
at my crash diagnostics.
Check out the "Triage TestFlight
crashes with Xcode" video
to learn more
about crash diagnostics.
Using regressions
and crash diagnostics,
I now know I need to reduce
onscreen terminations
in the next app release.
I don't want to stop
at onscreen terminations
and know there's more I can do.
I'll check my app's regressions
to discover
other areas for improvement.
Looks like there's a regression
in task timeouts as well.
Some metrics
can regress for multiple devices
and percentiles.
In this case,
task timeouts have increased
across all iPhones on both
typical and top percentiles.
I can scroll through
each regression on the right,
viewing data for recent releases
as well as the latest
and average value
for the metric.
When apps are switched
to the background,
they have 30 seconds
to execute tasks
before the system
terminates them.
This means that failing to end
background tasks appropriately
can cause your app to terminate
more frequently,
leading to a slow launch
the next time
a user switches back.
My app is now getting terminated
every three days
in the background.
While not as disruptive
as an onscreen termination,
background terminations
can be much more common.
It's essential to have
a seamless launch experience,
even when my app is terminated
in the background.
I can integrate UIKit's
state restoration features
to ensure a smooth recovery
from any background exits.
Lastly, coming back
to my app's regressions,
there's one more
performance area
I need to focus on.
Disk writes have increased
by 28% in the last release,
but it's not clear
what's caused the issue.
It's great I know there's
a performance problem,
but I'll need more insight
on where to start
before I optimize my app.
Next up,
Shreyas will tell you
how to discover top causes
for disk write regressions.
[Shreyas]
Thanks, Sonia.
Hi, I'm Shreyas.
I'm a storage software engineer
at Apple,
and I'll cover how to debug
disk write regressions
and stay on top
of the app's performance.
But before diving into this,
why are disk writes
so important?
Storage,
very much like CPU and memory,
is a limited resource.
Unchecked disk writes
can wear out
and damage
the underlying device.
They're also a common cause
for annoying onscreen hangs
and UI hitches.
If we are not careful,
they can eat up
the battery life quickly.
These make
optimizing disk writes
a key component in ensuring
a great user experience.
With that in mind,
let's learn about the resources
available to diagnose
high disk writes.
The disk writes report pane
in Xcode Organizer
is a great starting point.
These reports are collected
from devices
which have consented
to share app analytics,
and they contain information
about the stack trace
that led to the writes.
The stack trace from each report
is broken down
into multiple signatures,
and the writes are tracked
for a signature
across all reports.
In this report list,
the signatures are shown
sorted based
on the total writes.
For each of the signatures,
we can find detailed stack trace
showing us
the cause of the writes,
and we can also find statistics
about how many logs
were received,
what OS version
and hardware model
breakdown looks like, and so on.
To identify the problem areas,
pay close attention
to your top signatures.
In this case, the top signature
is responsible
for 67% of the writes.
We can infer from the callstacks
that this is due
to an SQLite function.
A lot of times, knowing this,
the source of the problem,
can go a long way
towards solving the issue.
But often, like in this case,
the fix may not be obvious.
The code here is critical
to my new feature,
I don't spot any obvious bugs,
and it's not apparent
what my next steps should be.
Turns out, the answer
is present in the stack trace
if you know where to look.
There are functions
often deep in the stack
sometimes in the libraries
that you are using
that can tell you what's wrong
and, with enough research,
how to fix it.
But that can be very tricky.
It often requires
specific domain knowledge
and can be
extremely time consuming.
To save you all this effort,
in Xcode 13,
organizer has
a new field called insights.
Behind the scenes,
a repository is maintained
with known antipatterns
that cause high disk writes.
As reports are received,
they're scanned for functions
that indicate
these antipatterns.
When there's a match,
the problem is highlighted here
along with
the optimization suggestion
to fix the issue.
This will make it easy
to reduce the app's writes
and improve performance
while saving
a ton of debugging effort.
For example,
for our top signature,
I see an optimization suggestion
to add an index.
There's also a link
to the documentation page
that will explain
the problem in detail
and give steps to debug
and fix the issue.
Great.
Now, let's follow the advice
and see if it helps.
And to do that, let me fire up
file activities instruments.
File activities instruments
is a fantastic resource
to debug
all storage-related issues.
It gives me
detailed breakdown
of all the reads and writes
that the app performs.
It's the perfect tool
to validate my fix.
Before, the instruments showed
around 180 megabytes
of writes to temporary files.
This also introduces
a 780 milliseconds of latency.
And now, after the index,
the writes due to the function
drops to zero.
This is because SQLite
is more efficient now.
This means we no longer have
780 millisecond latency
slowing us down.
SQLite index is one example.
There are a range of other
optimization suggestions
to improve
your app's performance,
and there is constant work
to expand this list,
so check out the insights
for your app today.
Let's come back
to the insights pane.
We had three regressions
for our app.
We scrutinized each one of them,
and we have discovered
the resources available
to resolve all of them.
That's great.
There are a ton of power
and performance analytics
in Xcode Organizer,
and the insights should be
a go-to pane to discover
your app's
performance priorities.
Make the most of it.
Plan to check for regressions
and insights periodically,
and definitely
after every release.
In addition
to the Xcode Organizer,
there's another way
for you access
all the analytics covered today,
and that is
App Store Connect APIs.
These are great
if you want to access
data programmatically
and build custom solutions.
Perhaps you already have
an analytics pipeline
that you have set up.
Then these APIs
are the perfect tool
for you to integrate
all these cool analytics.
Check out the video
"Identify trends with Power
and Performance API"
from WWDC 2020.
It covers the API end points
and responses in great detail.
Let me give a quick overview
of some of the API responses.
For metrics,
you can make a GET request
to the perfPowerMetrics
end point.
This returns a JSON response
that has app's metrics
and insights
for your recent versions.
Let's jump
into the insights section.
Within insights,
you'll find all the regressions
identified for your app.
For each regression,
you'll find metric category
and a summary
of the identified regression.
This is the onscreen termination
due to an illegal instruction
that we discovered earlier
in Xcode Organizer.
Next, you'll find
the populations section.
This provides
a detailed, structured list
of impacted percentiles
and devices.
You can use these
to take focused action
to improve
your app's performance.
Similarly,
for diagnostic reports,
you can make a GET request
to the diagnosticSignatures
end point.
The responses will have
a list of top signatures,
and each signature
will have a link
to the details associated
with it.
A GET request to this link
will provide you
with detailed diagnostic logs
and the insights
associated with the signature.
Use these APIs
in your analytics pipelines,
and when you see an insight,
take action immediately.
Now you know what
performance regressions are,
and how you can diagnose them,
and where you can find
actionable data to fix them.
Here's what you need to do next.
Go open Xcode Organizer now.
Check out the regressions pane.
See what your app's
top performance regressions are.
Find out how much
your app writes.
Are the top disk write
callstacks what you expect?
Or are there hidden bugs
slowing down your app?
Finally,
make a plan to stay on top
of your app's performance.
Check Xcode Organizer
periodically,
and use
the App Store Connect APIs
in any custom
analytics pipeline.
Thank you for your time.
Happy regression hunting.
[upbeat music]