[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Jake Petroules:
Hi, and welcome to
"Explore advanced project
configuration in Xcode".
I'm Jake, and together
with my colleague Prachi,
I'll discuss strategies
and techniques for making
the most of your Xcode project's
build configuration.
We're going to cover
three major topic areas.
First, Prachi will discuss
multiplatform projects
and Xcode 13's new support for
multiplatform framework targets.
Next, I'll cover best practices
for modeling
and configuring your project
through schemes,
target setup
and dependency management,
and build phases and rules.
And finally, Prachi will take
you on a deep dive
into build settings,
where we'll cover
their structure and behavior,
the project editor UI,
configuration settings files
and their syntax,
and a whole lot more!
Throughout this talk,
we'll be using
a multiplatform
app project called Fruta
to show how these techniques
apply to a real project.
And now I'm going
to hand it over to Prachi,
who's going to talk about
multiplatform frameworks.
Prachi Pai Asnodkar:
Thanks, Jake.
One of the new features
in Xcode 13
is support for
multiplatform frameworks.
Multiplatform frameworks
allow us to consolidate
multiple frameworks into one,
providing us simplified
target management,
one set of build phases
to manage,
and one set of
build settings to manage.
Let's take a look
at the Fruta app
and update our project to take
advantage of this feature.
This is the Fruta app.
It is a multiplatform app
that builds for macOS,
iOS, and watchOS.
It also has three
framework targets --
one for each platform that
contains a set of shared code
used by the apps.
Maintaining three
separate frameworks
can come with challenges,
such as keeping
build settings in sync,
and ensuring all of your source
files are properly added
to your compile
sources build phases.
To tackle these challenges,
we'll start by converting
one of our frameworks
to a multiplatform framework.
Here we have
the three frameworks --
one for each platform.
All of these targets
are identical
except that one has a file
which only builds on macOS.
First, let's navigate
to the Build Settings tab
in the project navigator for
the macOS framework target.
Next, we will configure
the framework
to build for all platforms
by going
to the Supported Platforms
build setting
and choosing Any Platform.
You can also see that
Allow Multiplatform Builds
has been set to "Yes"
automatically.
This informs the build system
to build this target
once for each
of its supported platforms,
as necessary.
Now that this
is a multiplatform target,
recall that the original
macOS framework
had one additional file
that should only build
when building for macOS.
In order to configure
our framework to do this,
we can add a platform filter
to specify that this file
should only build for macOS.
To do this, we will first
go to the Build Phases tab.
Next, expand the Compile Sources
build phase.
Finally, configure
Ingredient+macOS.swift
to build only for macOS
by clicking on the Filters item
and unchecking everything
but macOS.
Now that we have our new
multiplatform target configured,
we can delete the other two
variants of our framework,
as they are no longer needed.
Additionally, because we have
only one framework target,
we will have to configure
all of our apps
to link and embed
that new target.
The macOS app
is already configured
because we have set up
our multiplatform target
starting from the macOS one.
We can add the new framework
to the iOS and watchOS apps
by going to the General tab
for each of the app targets,
and adding the framework
to the Frameworks
and Libraries build phase.
To summarize: we took
our macOS framework target
and enabled it to build
for iOS and watchOS.
We customized that framework
with a platform filter
for our macOS-only source file.
And finally,
we configured our app targets
to link and embed the new single
multiplatform framework target.
And that's multiplatform targets
in Xcode.
Now back to Jake,
who's going to dive deeper
into project configuration.
Jake: Thanks, Prachi.
I'm going to discuss
best practices for modeling
and configuring
your Xcode project,
and show a few things you can do
to improve the performance
and correctness of your builds.
First, let's have a look
at build options for the scheme.
I'll click the scheme picker,
Edit Scheme,
then go to the Build section.
There's a few simple things
I can configure here.
For Build Order,
we recommend selecting
Dependency Order,
which will cause
targets in your project
to build in parallel according
to the dependency graph.
This can greatly improve
multicore build performance
and will also get you
faster results
from continuous integration.
In contrast, choosing
Manual Order is deprecated
and is not recommended.
Using this option
will slow down your build
and can cause cycle errors
when the target order
listed in the scheme
is inconsistent with
your project's dependencies.
Another important setting
in the scheme build options
is Find Implicit Dependencies.
Checking this option
allows Xcode
to automatically add
dependencies between targets
based on the information
in your project,
such as linker flags
in build settings
and the names of linked
libraries in build phases.
This can be especially useful
when the related targets
are in different projects
where you can't normally add
an explicit target dependency.
If you are using
manual dependency order
to build targets in a specific
order due to the inability
to add explicit target
dependencies
across different projects,
enabling Find Implicit
Dependencies
in conjunction with choosing
Dependency Order
is often a better solution.
Now I'm going to talk about
script phases and build rules.
I'll select
the SmoothieKit target
from the project's target list,
and then select
the Build Phases tab.
Here we have a Process Recipes
script phase
that contains some
custom build logic.
One of its responsibilities
is generating code
from a number of recipe files
with one output per input,
which we process in sequence.
Now, you may realize
that these computations
are completely independent
of each other.
This presents a performance
optimization opportunity
that we can take advantage
of by running them in parallel.
Build rules allow us
to do just that.
Let's take a look at how
we can extract this work
into a build rule.
I'll go to the Build Rules tab
in the project editor
for our framework
and click the plus button
to add a new build rule.
Then enter the file pattern
"*.recipe",
which corresponds
to the file extension
of the file type
I want this rule to process.
Next, I'll add dependencies
to this rule.
I don't need to add
any additional inputs
to the build rule,
because it will automatically
get each input file
it processes as an input.
However, I do need to tell
the build system
the path of the output file
that the rule will produce
for each file it processes.
I'll click the plus button
to add a new output file
and enter in
$(DERIVED_ FILE_ DIR)/$
(INPUT_ FILE _BASE)
.compiledrecipe.
It's best practice to write
generated files
under DERIVED_FILE_DIR
since this will point
to an appropriate location
managed by the build system.
You should avoid
generating output files
under the source root.
This can interfere
with source control
and lead to conflicts
when running multiple builds
simultaneously.
Now we, of course, have to copy
our script phase code
over to the rule.
I'll go back
to the script phase,
and copy out the code where
we processed each of the files.
Then I'll go back to the rule
and paste that in.
Remember that rules run once
for each input they process.
So I'll remove the for loop,
replace $RECIPE with
$SCRIPT_INPUT_FILE --
which corresponds
to the absolute file path
of the current input file
being processed --
and replace $DERIVED_FILE_DIR/
$RECIPE.compiledrecipe
with $SCRIPT_OUTPUT_FILE_0,
which refers to the output
file path I've entered
in the Output Files
section below.
Don't forget to quote variables
to make sure spaces
and other special characters
in file paths
are handled correctly.
Great.
Now there's one more thing
to configure in the rule.
I mentioned that rules run once
for each input they process.
By default, they also run
once for each architecture
that the target
is compiling for.
For example, a rule in
a Mac app target might run once
for arm64 and once for x86_64
times each of its inputs.
So if there are four inputs
times two architectures,
the rule would be invoked
eight times.
This is useful when
the output of the rule
is architecture-dependent,
such as object code.
However, in this case,
my rule produces output
which is independent of the
underlying CPU architecture,
so I'm going to uncheck
“Run once per architecture”.
Lastly, in order for the
build system to propagate
the input files
into the build rule,
I'll need to add
all of the .recipe files
into the Compile Sources build
phase of my framework target.
I'll go back to Build Phases,
expand Compile Sources,
and use the plus button
to add the recipe files.
Now let's go back
to the script phase.
The remaining
piece of work this does
is merge the contents
of multiple text files
into a single file
we can load at runtime
in our app more efficiently.
And in order to have better
source control experience,
I'm keeping scripts external
to the project file
and calling them from
the inline script editor here.
So let's follow the reference
to package.sh to see the code.
A build rule wouldn't be
appropriate in this case,
since we need to process
all the inputs at once
to combine them into one.
So there's no way to break it up
into isolated units
which can be run in parallel
and therefore it makes sense
to keep this work
in the script phase.
But this brings us to one of
the most important takeaways:
the script has no input and
output dependencies specified.
This might cause build tasks
to run in the wrong order
and slows down the build
because Xcode
has to be more conservative
with respect to running
other tasks in parallel,
as it doesn't know what files
the script phase may be using.
So it's important to add
input and output dependencies
to ensure the work performed
by script phases is done
in the correct order relative
to other tasks in the build.
For this particular script,
I have a large number of inputs.
Instead of entering these
in the project file one by one,
I can use an xcfilelist
to manage this list of inputs
via an external file.
I'll go ahead and add one
to the project now.
I'll go to File > New File,
and choose Build Phase File List
under the Other section.
I'll paste the list of input
files that will be processed
by this script phase,
one per line.
If you want,
you can even write comments
by beginning a line
with the pound sign,
which is great for adding
additional context.
Now I'll reference
this xcfilelist
from the script phase.
I'll go back to the script phase
and specify the path
to the xcfilelist
in the Input File Lists.
[KEYSTROKES]
Lastly, I'll specify
an output dependency
by providing the file path
at which the output contents
will be written,
just like I did
for the build rule.
[KEYSTROKES]
There's one more thing
to mention.
Similar to the build rule,
there are some crucial
environment variables
provided for you
by the script phase.
Let's navigate back
to package.sh
to have a closer look.
In the source, I reference
SCRIPT_INPUT_FILE_LIST_COUNT;
which refers to the total
number of input file lists
passed to our script phase,
SCRIPT_INPUT_FILE_LIST_n;
which refers to the resolved
absolute file path
of the input file list
at the nth index,
and SCRIPT_OUTPUT_FILE_0;
which refers to the resolved
absolute file path
of the first --
and in this case, only --
output file.
Here is an overview of some
of the key environment variables
provided to script phases.
The build settings of the target
are also made available
to the script phase environment.
Here is an overview of some
environment variables
specific to build rules,
as well as some
less common ones.
Like script phases,
the build settings of the target
are also made available
to the build rule environment.
OK. Now, if I try
to build the project,
I'll run into an issue.
Let's go to the build log
to take a closer look.
Because SmoothieKit
is a multiplatform target,
it's building twice: once for
iOS and once for watchOS,
and this means each of these
builds are trying to produce
the output of the script phase
at the same path.
This is not allowed
because the build system
requires that only one task
in the entire build
may produce the output
at a given path.
There are a couple different
ways I could solve this.
One simple solution would be
to change the output path
of the script phase
so that it's unique
each time the target is built.
In this case, I could consider
using a different build setting
like DERIVED_FILE_DIR,
which is platform-specific,
and would make the path
sufficiently unique
and solve the conflict.
However, if the actual work
that the script phase is doing
would be identical within
the context of each target,
that would simply cause
the same work to be done twice.
In that case,
it can be a better option
to move the script phase
to a new aggregate target
which the shared framework
target depends on.
That's what I'm going to do
for my project.
To get started,
I'll click the plus button
at the bottom
of the target list,
select the Other tab,
and choose Aggregate target.
I'll call it Resources.
Then I'll add
a new script phase,
and copy the name,
script source, inputs,
and outputs from
the framework target.
Finally, I'll delete
the original script phase
from the framework target
and then add a target dependency
on the new aggregate target.
This way, the work will
only be done once,
there will be
no output file conflict,
and both the iOS and watchOS
variants of the framework
will build in the correct order
relative to that script phase.
Build successful.
And now, back to Prachi,
who's going to tell you
all about build settings.
Prachi: Thank you, Jake!
So what is a build setting?
It is a property you can apply
to Xcode targets
to configure aspects
of how they are built.
Xcode provides
two main mechanisms
for configuring
build settings.
The first is through
the build settings editor.
The second is through
a configuration settings file
or an .xcconfig file.
Let's start by seeing how
the build settings editor
can be used to manage
the settings within our project.
In order to bring up
the build settings editor,
first you need
to select your project
in the Project navigator.
Next, make sure to select the
target you wish to configure.
And finally,
click the Build Settings tab
across the tab bar.
From here, you can add
new build settings
or modify existing ones.
You can also find out
additional information
for the selected build setting
by opening the
Quick Help inspector.
Build settings are defined
at multiple levels.
You can think of this
as a stack of definitions.
In fact, these levels
can be visualized
by clicking on
the Levels filter.
Each column represents
a different level
a build setting
can be defined in,
and they are evaluated
from the right to the left.
Starting from the lowest level
there is the default value,
which is defined by the
currently selected SDK,
the project level
configuration settings file,
the project level settings
from the Xcode project file,
target settings defined in
a configuration settings file,
the target level
settings defined
in your Xcode project file,
and finally, the resolved value
of the build setting.
Note that if you see
a bold setting
that denotes that the level
has an explicit value
for the build setting.
The other mechanism
Xcode provides
for managing build settings
are configuration setting files
or .xcconfig files.
Some of the benefits
of an xcconfig file include:
better source
control management,
sharing settings across
targets or configurations,
advanced composition
of build settings,
and the ability to include
additional xcconfig files
based on your development
or test environment.
Let's take a look at how
you can author build settings
in an xcconfig file.
At its most basic level,
a build setting is made up
of a name,
an assignment operator,
and a value.
You can narrow the value
of a build setting
using the conditional syntax.
Conditional settings are defined
using square brackets.
Some of the supported
conditions include
configuration, architecture,
and SDK.
As shown with the SDK condition,
wildcards can be used
for matching purposes.
Comments can be added as well
using the familiar
double-slash syntax.
A build setting
can be set to the value
of another build setting by
using the dollar-parens syntax.
In the example here,
MY_OTHER_BUILD_SETTING
has been set to YES.
The value of
MY_BUILD_SETTING_NAME
uses the dollar-parens
syntax to evaluate
MY_OTHER_BUILD_SETTING.
Multiple values
can be evaluated here as well,
like we see with MORE_SETTINGS.
And finally, existing values
for a build setting
can be used
with the $(inherited) value.
This allows you to append
additional values
to a build setting
while retaining
all of its existing values.
This is a convenience form
as you could also use
the build setting name,
APPEND_TO_EXISTING_SETTINGS.
Another use of the build setting
evaluation syntax
is to compose
build settings together
from a set
of other build settings.
First, we start with
a control setting:
IS_BUILD_SETTING_ENABLED.
We will use the value
of this setting as a suffix
for two additional
build settings,
MY_BUILD_SETTING_NO
and MY_BUILD_SETTING_YES.
Lastly, we define
MY_BUILD_SETTING
to have a value that is composed
of both MY_BUILD_SETTING
and IS_BUILD_SETTING_ENABLED.
Because build setting evaluation
happens inside-out,
the inner-most setting
is evaluated
and returns NO,
which is the value of
IS_BUILD_SETTING_ENABLED.
Finally, the composed
BUILD_SETTING_NO
is evaluated to a value
of -use_this_one.
When evaluating a build setting,
there are a set of operators
you can use to provide
some basic transformations
of your value.
The three classifications
of operators are:
string operators,
path operators,
and replacement operators.
The supported string operators
are quote,
which escapes the characters
within the string;
lower and upper, which convert
cases of characters;
and identifiers, which convert
strings to valid identifiers
in various formats.
We provide a set of path
operators to get the directory,
filename, base name, suffix,
and standardized path.
For each path operator, there is
a replacement counterpart
that allows you to replace
part of a value.
There's also a default operator
which provides
the replacement value
if the build setting is empty,
otherwise it uses the existing
value of the build setting.
The last item to look at
is the ability to include
xcconfig files within
other xcconfig files.
There are two mechanisms
available to you.
The first are required includes,
which requires the xcconfig file
to exist on disk.
A compiler error
will be produced
if the file cannot be found.
The second
are optional includes,
which allow for including an
xconfig file if present on disk.
This will not fail
if the file does not exist.
Note that the path is relative
from the location
of your Xcode project file.
So let's take a look
at how you might put
all of this information together
in a real-world scenario.
In this example,
we'll be taking a look at how
to solve the following problem.
On our development machines,
the compiler should aggressively
warn for expressions
that take too long
to type check.
However, the CI machines
are slower,
so the time for expression
checking should be increased.
For our solution,
there are three
configuration setting files:
debug, common, and ci.xcconfig.
The debug xcconfig file is used
for our debug builds,
and passes some additional
flags to the Swift compiler
via the OTHER_SWIFT_FLAGS
build setting.
The common xcconfig file
optionally includes
the ci.xcconfig file.
It also defines the
OTHER_SWIFT_FLAGS setting
to control the type
expression warning.
It makes use of $(inherited)
to ensure that any of the other
flag settings are included,
such as from
the debug.xcconfig file
and a build setting evaluation
for MAX _EXPRESSION_TIME
that has a default value of 200.
The ci xcconfig file
defines an override value
for MAX_EXPRESSION _TIME.
Finally, Xcode needs to be told
how to apply
these xcconfig files
to one of the supported
configuration levels.
This is done through
the project editor,
which is what we see here.
From the
Configuration section,
you can apply any
of the config files
from your project at either
the project or target levels,
for any defined build
configuration.
Here, you can see that
the debug.xcconfig file
is being applied
at the project level
for the debug configuration
of Fruta.
Also, common.xcconfig file
is set for each of the targets
within the project.
To recap the solution,
the default operator was used
to define a default value
for MAX_EXPRESSION_TIME.
The ci.xcconfig file was
optionally included
because it will only exist
on the CI system.
And an override
of the default value
for MAX_EXPRESSION_TIME was used
in the ci xcconfig file.
This wraps up
our practical example.
Now let's go back to Jake
to review everything
that we have covered.
Jake: Thanks, Prachi.
Let's recap.
You learned about
multiplatform frameworks
and how they provide
an easier way
to manage build settings
and build phases
in multiplatform projects.
You saw how you can improve
your project configuration
and build performance
by building targets in parallel
according to dependency order,
how to properly use build rules
and build phases,
and the importance
of specifying dependencies.
Finally, you took a deep dive
into build settings,
how you can use
configuration settings files
to manage them more easily,
and dived into their syntax
and all of the constructs
it provides.
We hope these lessons provide
you with a set of useful tools
to help you make the most
of your development experience.
Thank you for watching!
♪