[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
Nishant Nelogal: Hello,
and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Nishant,
and I’m an engineer
on the AVFoundation team.
Today, we will be looking
at HLS Variants.
First, we will look at how
you can inspect HLS variants,
using AVFoundation APIs,
and later on, we will see
how we can use the HLS variants
with downloads.
So let's start
with variant inspection.
You all must be familiar
with what a typical
master playlist looks like.
Here is an example.
In this particular playlist,
we have two variants.
One of the variants is an
SDR variant with stereo audio,
and the other one is
a Dolby Vision variant
with Dolby Atmos audio.
The asset representing
this particular playlist
may be presented
something like this in your app.
Looking closely,
you see that the asset has 4K,
Dolby Vision,
and Dolby Atmos badges.
Earlier, you had to get such
information out of the band.
Now in iOS 15,
you can directly inspect
the HLS playlist to infer them.
For that, you start
with an AVURLAsset
pointing to the location
of your master playlist.
Later on, you can obtain
the HLS playlist
via the variant's property.
This AVAssetVariant,
as we see here,
represents an HLS variant as is
from the master playlist.
So it has multiple properties
representing different
media attributes.
Some of the attributes,
such as the media bitrate,
can be accessed directly.
Other attributes,
such as those related
to video and audio renditions,
are grouped together
in their own subclasses.
They are called
as VideoAttributes
and AudioAttributes,
respectively.
As you see, each of them
has relevant properties,
which you can use
to understand your asset.
Now you know how to inspect
HLS variants in AVFoundation.
Let's see how we can use them
with downloads.
Downloading HLS content
for offline playback
has been supported since 2016.
If you're not familiar
with HLS download APIs,
I would suggest you check out
our earlier talk on the topic
from WWDC 2020.
In iOS 15, we are taking
our HLS download APIs
and making them
even more powerful.
Typically, you would like
to influence the HLS variants
selected for the download.
This may be due
to business requirements,
or you just want to provide
more choice to your users.
Before, you could provide
such input
via downloadTask options.
We had an option for HDR,
an option for lossless audio,
and a few other attributes.
In iOS 15, we are expanding
the variant selection
with the use of NSPredicates.
You may be already familiar with
using predicates from Core Data.
If not, don’t worry,
you will learn about them today.
So to get started,
let me introduce
the variant qualifier interface.
This interface allows you to
specify your variant preferences
to AVFoundation.
And, as I said,
they can be constructed
using NSPredicates.
Let’s understand
by looking at few examples.
Here, we have a NSPredicate
which expresses peak bitrate
to be less than five megabits.
You use this to construct
your variant qualifier,
which instructs AVFoundation
to prefer variants
under five megabits.
Simple enough, right?
Let’s take a look
at another example.
Here we create an NSPredicate
for HDR video range.
And similarly as before,
you can construct
a variant qualifier for it.
You can also combine
multiple predicates
to create a compound predicate
and use them to create
your variant qualifier.
Any property on variant
can be used
to create a predicate against.
For properties
such as audio channel count,
which cannot be easily expressed
using the predicate
format string,
we have custom constructors.
You can look them up
in our header doc
for variant qualifier.
Once you have
your variant qualifier,
you use it to create something
called as content configuration.
Each content configuration
represents a set of video,
audio, and subtitle renditions.
OK, let's understand
with an example.
Here is the variant qualifier
which combines the two
predicates we saw earlier.
Eh, this is compounding. Ha-ha.
It informs AVFoundation
to prefer HDR variants
under five megabits.
We also have a set
of media selections
representing English
and French audio,
and English subtitle renditions.
Both of these can be used
to create a content
configuration object.
You can create multiple
of these content configurations
and provide it
to the downloadTask.
These multiple content
configurations are tied together
by the download
configuration interface.
This is the root
which holds everything together.
It is created with an AVURLAsset
and needs an asset name,
and optionally, an image.
The asset name and image are
displayed in the Settings app.
This allows your users
to manage all of their downloads
in one place
in the Settings app.
And of course, the downloadTask
can be configured
with multiple content
configurations.
Looking closely,
one of the content
configurations
will be designated as primary
and the rest will be auxiliary.
The difference
between the two is
you typically want to download
a primary set of video, audio,
and subtitle renditions
and then complement them
with additional audio
or subtitle renditions.
By specifying
your additional renditions
as auxiliary content
configurations,
you instruct AVFoundation
to optimize
and avoid downloading
multiple video renditions.
It becomes more clear
as we go over an example.
Here is the complete example.
First, we start by creating
a download configuration
with AVURLAsset and a title.
The primary content
configuration
is the same one we saw earlier.
It is configured to download HDR
variants under five megabits,
with English and French audio
and English subtitle renditions.
In this particular example,
we would like to complement it
with an auxiliary
content configuration
to download English audio
in lossless format.
Now we have both
our content configurations,
which we want to download.
Make sure to set
optimizesAuxiliary
ContentConfigurations to true.
By the way, it is true
by default,
and it allows AVFoundation
to choose lossless variant,
such that the lossless
variant’s video rendition
is the same as the primary
content configuration.
Setting it to false
may cause lossless variant
to be evaluated independently,
which may cause duplicate video
renditions to be downloaded.
This may increase your download
size, which we don’t want.
OK, once you have
the download configuration,
you can use it
to create the downloadTask.
You resume the downloadTask
to start the download.
Starting in iOS 15,
you can also observe the
progress of the downloadTask
using NSProgress interface.
The NSProgress object
is KVO-observable,
and you can use it
to update your user interface.
Moving on.
We understand that some of you
may have business logic
for selecting variants,
which may be harder
to express via predicates.
For such cases,
you can also choose
to choose the variants
you want to download explicitly.
Here in this example,
we have already picked our
primary and auxiliary variant
and the media selections
to go with it.
We can instruct AVFoundation
to download them as is,
by creating a qualifier
with the variant directly.
Be careful to select variants
so that they are playable
on the device
where they are downloaded.
That's all we have today, folks.
To wrap up,
we looked at how you can
inspect HLS variants
and use them to configure
the downloadTask.
Along the way, we encountered
different interfaces
for downloadTask configuration.
The first one was
variant qualifier.
This is used to express
your variant preferences.
Then we saw content
configuration interface.
The content configuration
ties together
your variant preferences and
your media selection choices.
Finally, we saw
the download configuration.
The download configuration
is the root interface
which ties everything together.
Last, but not the least,
we also learned that
you can monitor your
downloadTask using NSProgress.
For more information,
check our header docs.
They're very well commented.
Thank you for watching
and bye-bye!
♪