[music]
[Arun] Hi, my name is Arun,
and I'm a system engineer
in the Wireless team.
Today, I'm gonna take you
on a journey
to explore UWB-based car keys.
Last year, we launched car keys
with the ability
to use your iPhone
or Apple Watch to unlock, lock,
and start your car,
share your keys
with family and friends,
and even manage them remotely.
And you can do all
of that knowing that the system
has been designed to be
secure and private.
This year, we are excited
to extend the capabilities
of car keys.
In this session,
we will look at the new features
and how to integrate them.
If you want to learn
the basics of the car keys,
including provisioning,
key management, and NFC,
check out last year's talk,
"Introducing car keys."
One of the key features
we are enabling this year
is passive entry.
Using UWB technology,
you can now lock, unlock,
and start your car
while leaving iPhone
in your bag or pocket,
or Apple Watch on your wrist.
RKE, or remote keyless
entry controls,
allow you to use your iPhone
or Watch to lock,
unlock,
and perform other actions
when you're in Bluetooth range
of your car.
And cars can now personalize
settings by identifying
which digital key is entering
the car through which door.
There are other features
that we will not be able
to cover in this session,
such as pairing your device
as Car Key
and Friend First Approach,
but experiences
for these features
have also been upgraded.
Now, let's take a look
at the technologies
that enable these features.
The U1 chip
with UWB technology allows cars
to determine the precise
location of nearby car key.
UWB is also the basis
of a secure-ranging protocol
for stronger protection against
replay and relay attacks.
The Secure Element is
a protected hardware unit
integrated into Apple devices.
In addition to storing car keys
and authenticating credentials,
we have expanded the use
of Secure Element
to derive session-specific
UWB ranging keys.
Bluetooth LE, or BLE,
is used as communication channel
between the car
and the Apple device,
to exchange data
during authentication
and to manage
secure-ranging sessions.
BLE's also used
as the anchor point
to initialize
a secure-ranging time grid.
And finally,
to ensure a common solution
with cross-platform support,
Apple,
along with other industry
partners,
has been leading efforts
to create
a standard specification at
the Car Connectivity Consortium.
At Apple, security and privacy
are part of our core values.
This UWB passive entry solution
was designed with both in mind.
Keys are unique to each session
and are derived
upon each connection.
Some of these session keys
are used to encrypt messages
at the link layer,
while others to ensure
that your devices can't be
tracked using UWB or BLE.
We use random identifiers,
derived from these session keys.
These identifiers are then
periodically rotated.
And most importantly,
we strengthened the security
of UWB-based localization
by building
a secure-ranging protocol.
This secure-ranging protocol
is a two-way ranging protocol
with a three-packet exchange.
Think of it as "ping-pong-ping"
where iPhone sends
a poll message,
and the car answers
with a respond message,
and iPhone sends another
poll message for added accuracy.
Each of these messages carry
a scrambled time stamp, or STS,
which is
a cryptographically-generated
and time-bounded packet,
meaning that even a verified
packet can only be accepted
for the time slot slot which was
used to generate this STS,
providing extra security against
replay and relay attacks.
So, how do we bring all
of this together?
Well, each car defines a series
of virtual zones.
These zones have associated
features that can be triggered
when a device
with a valid and active key
is localized entering
or exiting these zones.
The wider zone activates
welcome features,
such as turning on lights
or pre-warming the cabin
when you approach the car.
The zone
closest to the car typically
unlocks the door
when you approach.
And the lock zone secures
the cars when you walk away.
So, how does a car detect
you in these zones?
Well, to localize
the paired device
inside these virtual zones,
cars are equipped
with multiple UWB
and BLE transceivers
to ensure 360-degree coverage.
When the user first
approaches the car,
your iPhone or Apple Watch
is detected using BLE.
Upon proximity detection,
a communication channel
with the car is established.
Upon connection,
car authenticates the device,
and a shared ranging key
is derived on both sides.
This operation takes place
inside the Secure Element,
and generates a key
that is unique to each session.
The derived key is used to start
a secure-ranging session
with UWB transceivers,
which allows the car
to localize the device
and map its trajectory.
This is computed
by the localization algorithm
that runs inside the car.
We'll come back to it later.
The car continues
to map the trajectory
of the device
as the user approaches the car.
Based on the location
and trajectory of the device,
the car can decide
to trigger welcome features,
such as turning on lights
or adjusting seats.
And when the device is localized
inside the unlock zone,
the car can
initiate unlock operations
before the user
touches the door handle.
With precise knowledge
of whether the user's device is
inside or outside the car,
the engine only starts
when a device with a valid key
is detected inside the car.
And one of my favorite features,
now you get to enjoy
this UWB-based experience
even when your phone
is in power reserve mode.
So, after a long day of hiking
or backpacking, if you find
that your phone needs to be
charged, there may still be
enough power in the battery
to get you back on the road.
Now that you've seen how
passive entry works,
let's take a look at the remote
keyless entry controls.
Remote actions are useful
when you're farther
from the car.
You can use them by preheating
the cabin in the winter,
or find your car
by honking the horn.
And many actions can
be triggered directly
from within Wallet.
You can also use device to view
information about the car,
such as lock state,
its fuel level,
or battery-charging state.
Remote actions are sent
over Bluetooth LE.
Since they are independent
of UWB,
they work even outside
of UWB range.
And finally, remote actions
are standardized
at
the Car Connectivity Consortium,
so there's
a common implementation
for all the cars and devices.
For the best experience,
we recommend
that automakers implement all
the applicable remote actions,
and not just remote lock
and unlock.
Let's look at how does Remote
Keyless entry control works.
To trigger a remote command,
the device requests a challenge
for the associated action,
which is used as an input
to generate
the device signature.
The car verifies the device
signature against the challenge,
the associated action,
and other information.
If verification succeeds,
the car performs the action
and notifies the device.
With digital car keys,
cars can now automatically
personalize settings,
like cabin temperature,
seat position, seat heating,
and more, by observing
which digital key is
approaching the driver's door.
Today's car keys can
support personalization, too,
but they rely
on drivers always knowing
which key fob has
which user setting.
Now, with your car key
on iPhone or Apple Watch,
you don't have to worry
about that.
With precise trajectory
and the knowledge
that the personal devices
are strongly tied
to individual users,
cars can personalize
experiences
with greater confidence
than ever before.
And this works seamlessly,
even when multiple users
are approaching the car.
To sum it up, we are excited
about these new features
and look forward to automakers
launching UWB-based cars,
so our users can start
enjoying these features
on iPhones and Apple Watches
equipped with U1 chip.
Now, let's shift gears and talk
about how automakers
can get on-boarded
on the Apple platform,
and some of the areas
you will want to focus on
when designing
a car key solution.
As part of this discussion,
we'll cover system architecture,
time synchronization,
transceiver synchronization,
and about building a good
localization algorithm.
Let's start
with system architecture.
Since the passive entry
solution relies on reliable
and accurate localization,
it's essential that your system
has good performance
and low latency.
As we saw earlier,
each car is equipped
with multiple transceivers,
and one of your first decisions
will be to select
a suitable transceiver.
First, you need to ensure
that the transceivers
can provide
sufficient link budget.
Since the car key protocol
is bi-directional,
this means evaluating both
the Tx-radiated power
and Rx sensitivity for good
uplink and downlink performance.
By fine-tuning the antenna
directivity, you can ensure
that transceiver's antenna
supports the entire field
of view
for the required coverage.
Antenna diversity is critical
to achieve good operating range.
For example,
the use of two or more antennas
with different polarization
or separation can help
improve
received signal strength.
Finally,
you need to ensure that the 3D
time-of-flight measurements
are highly accurate.
Passive entry
and localization features rely
on time-of-flight
in their calculations.
Therefore, the accuracy must
be within defined bounds,
regardless
of the approach angle.
Since even well-designed
individual transceivers can
result in insufficient
coverage around the car,
or coverage in unwanted areas
if they are poorly installed,
you will need to identify
the best possible positions
to place transceivers
around the car
to provide
necessary coverage and,
at the same time, you will want
to limit the number
of transceivers to a minimum
to keep costs down.
Be sure to consider
height and orientation.
In general, the greater
the installation height,
the farther the fading point,
and better the range.
This obviously has to be done
within the design constraints
of the car.
Similarly, poor orientation can
result in gaps in coverage
or coverage in unwanted areas,
such as above the car.
Once you have
the suitable transceivers
and potential positions,
the next step is to verify
the system RF performance.
Examine the radiation pattern
of the transceivers
installed around the car
to ensure a symmetrical
coverage on all sides.
You also want to pay attention
to the maximum range
covered by the system.
This is important
for long distance features,
such as welcome lights
or preconditioning the cabin.
And most importantly,
you will want to ensure
that the system has
sufficient link margin buffer,
to ensure an unlock operation
can take place,
regardless of damping caused
by the human body,
channel shadowing, fading,
or other variables.
Another area you need
to consider is system latency.
When you approach the car,
a complex sequence
of events begins, starting with
the setup of a BLE connection,
authentication,
and key derivation,
followed by a secure-ranging
session setup,
where each
UWB transceiver starts scanning,
so the car can determine
the location of the device.
All these tasks must be
completed
before the user attempts
to open the door.
To keep the system latency
within the required bounds,
you will need a high-performance
crypto processor
for authentication
and key management.
The bus system that connects
your ECU
to each transceiver
must be of low latency;
a slow bus can really impact
system op performance.
Finally, you will need
a flexible software architecture
that allows you to support
optimization techniques,
be it multi-threaded
applications
or incorporation
of time synchronization.
Now, let's quickly talk
about time synchronization.
UWB transceivers needs
to be actively scanning
to detect ranging packets.
Without good time
synchronization,
long-scanning windows are needed
to reliably capture
incoming packets.
This consumes power
and processing time.
By implementing
a precise time synchronization
across your system,
each transceiver can know
when incoming packets are
expected
to an accuracy
of tens of microsecond.
By only scanning
during these time windows,
not only can you conserve power,
and improve performance
in multi-session
and congested environments,
but it also helps you
localize the device faster.
It does that by ensuring
successful ranging
from the very first
detected cycle
by keeping the transceivers
tightly synchronized.
Another important technique is
transceiver synchronization.
Sometimes,
some transceivers may fail
to connect or become out
of sync.
By implementing transceiver
synchronization,
transceivers that are
successfully synchronized
with the device can share
timing information
with other transceivers
in the car,
and help them quickly connect,
or even compute time-of-flight,
even when they have failed
to finish
the full-ranging cycle.
Last but not least,
localization algorithm.
One of the most important
task when designing
a passive-entry solution
is the development
of a localization algorithm
that can pinpoint the location
of approaching devices
relative to the car.
A localization algorithm
is a piece
of code
running on your car's ECU.
It collects device's distance
from each connected UWB
transceivers and process them
to locate the iPhone
or Apple Watch in space.
There are many ways to do this.
One simple example of this is
true-range multi-lateration.
The localization algorithm is
one of the most crucial pieces
of the solution
that you need to develop.
So, you will need to ensure
that your localization algorithm
is fast and accurate,
whether it wants to follow
the trajectory of the user
as they approach the car,
or determine whether the device
is inside or outside the cabin.
Speed, accuracy,
and precision are the key
to a good localization solution,
even when you are adding support
for a single
transceiver-based unlock system.
You may also need to adjust
your localization algorithm
for different cabin types
and physical characteristics
of the car.
Now, you've seen how
the car key feature works.
If you're interested
in development,
we recommend
the following workflow
for an organic progression
of software development
and qualification.
First, focus
on UWB interoperability
and ensure that it follows
the specification.
We have created a tool
that helps you test this.
It also lets you progressively
enable cryptographic operations,
so you can develop your system
in a step-by-step manner.
Next, integrate the BLE layer
for connection management
and owner pairing.
Then, focus on secure-ranging
management,
which is
crucial for passive entry.
Last but not least,
support remote actions
for control at a distance.
If you're interested
in learning more,
we encourage you to participate
in
the Car Connectivity Consortium,
and enroll in the MFi Program
for specific details
on working
with iPhone and Apple Watch.
The MFi Program is where you can
obtain additional documents
and tools to assist
in your development.
Thank you, and have a great day!
[music]