[upbeat music]
[Lauren] Hi, everyone.
I'm Lauren
from Privacy Engineering,
and welcome to "Apple's privacy
pillars in focus."
At Apple,
we believe that privacy
is a fundamental human right.
Our devices are an important
part of entertaining us
and connecting us
to one another,
especially when we have
had to stay connected
from a distance.
And what people share
from within these experiences
should be up to them.
When people understand what
happens with their data
and are in control,
they are more likely
to engage with your experiences
and let your app become
a trusted part of their life.
So, we have to work
together to make sure
that great features and great
privacy aren't a tradeoff.
This isn't always easy,
so in iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
we are continuing
to provide innovative tools
that make it easier
for you to protect people
while building features
that they will love.
In this video,
we will walk you through
Apple's approach to privacy
and introduce new technologies
that make
building new features
while respecting people's
choices as simple as ever.
Improving the privacy
protections of your app
can seem like a lofty goal,
or you may not even know
where to start,
so we've simplified
engineering privacy
into a series of principles
and related questions
that you can ask yourself that
guide how to design products.
So, what's
our approach to privacy?
At Apple, we have four
fundamental privacy pillars.
The first is data minimization,
which requesting and only using
data that you actually need.
The second is on-device
processing,
which is processing data
locally
without sending it to a server.
The third is transparency
and control,
which is providing people
with a clear understanding
and control over
how their data is used.
And finally, security
protections
help enforce the privacy
on our platform.
In practice, these guidelines
translate to a series
of questions that you can ask
yourself about your features.
For data minimization,
do I need this data
in order
to make my feature great?
For on-device processing,
why does the server
need visibility into this data?
For transparency and control,
what are we gonna use this
data for,
and how do we communicate
that to people?
And Finally,
for security protections,
how is this data protected
in transit and at rest?
Garrett and I will walk you
through the new features
that you can adopt
to only collect
the data that you need,
protect your user's data,
and a few technologies
that may inspire you
to think about new opportunities
for privacy in your app.
And then, Elliot will dive
into how Private Relay works
and how we applied the pillars
to shape its design.
Let's start with data
minimization in iOS 15.
The places that people go can
reveal a lot about their lives.
Your app
may have great experiences
that rely on location.
But people may be skeptical
of granting your app
location access right away.
In iOS 13, we provided
a new way for people
to try out location
features in your app
by selecting Allow Once.
But this experience can result
in repetitive prompts.
In iOS 15, there is a new way
to build location-based features
that more seamlessly blend in
with your app's experience,
while allowing people to choose
when they share location.
You can now add
a Share Current Location button
right into your
app's experience.
When people tap on it,
your app will receive
access to their location
for that session,
just like Allow Once.
For many apps, only a few
features may rely on location.
Adopting the location button
is a great way for you
to build trust with people
accessing location when they
interact with the features
that actually need it.
When people tap this button
for the first time,
they'll learn how it works
and select whether
the app will have precise
or approximate location.
The location arrow
on the top left
will then appear
to signal to people
that your app
has received their location.
Next time they tap a location
button in your app,
it will just work,
without any prompts.
The location permission
is session-based
and will last until
they leave the app.
This works just like
allow-once access
but is so seamless
that it's a great
replacement for while-in-use!
Compared to while-in-use,
location buttons let you
offer a lower-commitment
way for people
to try out your
location-based features.
The button can be customized
to fit in with the rest of
your app by setting properties
on the CLLocationButton.
Some aspects of the button
that you can customize
include background color,
text and location arrow color,
and rounded corners.
These location buttons are built
to ensure that people intend
to provide location to the app
when the button is pressed.
The consistent string
and iconography enables them
to be easily recognizable,
and limitations on contrast,
size, and shape ensures
that they are visible.
This means that iOS can
confirm that the button
was tapped directly.
Location buttons
are supported on watchOS,
iOS, iPadOS,
and macOS with Catalyst.
Often, people have to make
a big choice about
location access
right when they open your app.
The location button gives people
more precise control
over when their location
is used,
while ensuring a more
seamless user experience.
Using the same technology as
the location button,
secure paste confirms
that the paste button
was tapped directly.
Now, the OS can reliably
distinguish
user-triggered pastes
from programmatic pastes
that are initiated by the app.
In iOS 14,
the paste-transparency notice
let people know when apps
access the pasteboard.
This also helped you learn when
an SDK included in your app
may have accessed
the pasteboard unexpectedly.
The transparency notice
is no longer needed
when people paste through
the edit options.
The notice will only be shown
in the UI if the user
did not initiate the paste
themselves in the edit menu
or through their keyboard.
To improve your experience,
shift towards only
user-initiated pastes.
If you need
to access the pasteboard,
you can use the data
detectors to confirm
that the content
in the pasteboard is
relevant to your application
before you access it.
The next pillar
is on-device processing.
On-device processing is
a fundamental building block
to core features, like Face ID,
quick-type suggestions,
and measuring
blood-oxygen level.
The main benefit of on-device
processing is that you can
build amazing features
using sensitive data,
without sending it
to your server.
In iOS 15, we applied this
principle to Siri in a big way.
Siri is a great example of how
we deliver powerful features
with industry-leading
privacy built in.
From the beginning,
Siri has always been designed
to protect your privacy.
Audio recordings
are not stored by default.
Your requests are associated
with a random identifier,
not your Apple ID.
And we work to keep
your personal information
on your device.
However, running large
machine-learning models,
like those used by Siri,
typically requires racks of
servers.
But around the time we released
iOS 12,
we also added
the Apple Neural Engine
to our hardware.
The Apple Neural Engine
has enabled us to move
more components of Siri
on-device.
In iOS 13,
we introduced the ability
to generate the Siri Voice
entirely on-device.
This means that it became
possible for Siri's response
to your request
to not leave your device.
In iOS 14, we introduced
on-device keyboard dictation.
This was the first high-quality
speech-to-text model
that we ran on-device.
One concern that people
still have
with voice assistants is
unwanted voice recording.
To help address this concern,
we are moving all automatic
speech recognition models
for Siri
to run entirely on-device.
By bringing on-device
speech recognition to Siri,
this means that, by default,
the audio of your requests
will not leave
your iPhone or iPad.
This new innovation
is another step
in the right direction
for on-device processing.
Moving Siri automatic
speech recognition models
on-device is a great example
of how designing for privacy
enables great new features.
On-device processing means
that Siri is incredibly fast.
By no longer sending requests
to the server and processing
on-device, instead, Siri can
respond to your requests faster.
And now, you can even make
some requests while offline.
The Apple Neural Engine
has been a key part
of moving more Siri
processing on-device.
In iOS 15,
you can take advantage
of the Apple Neural Engine, too.
New in iOS 15,
you can use the CreateML
framework to train models
right on an iPhone or iPad.
Now, you can personalize
models to each person
who uses your app,
leaving sensitive data,
like photos,
all on their device.
Check out the Machine Learning
team's talk,
"Build dynamic iOS apps with
the Create ML framework,"
to learn more.
Next, Garrett will tell you
about transparency
and control on iOS 15
and macOS Monterey.
[Garrett] Thanks, Lauren!
Building clear transparency
and understandable controls
into your app can help you
build trust with people.
Knowing how you plan
to use their email,
photos, or health data,
or who you plan to share it with
gives people the comfort
to explore your app's features
and use your app more fully.
So, today, we're going
to talk through a number
of examples of transparency
and control on our platforms,
making sure you know
what steps to take for your app.
First, we'll talk about
email-related transparency
and control features.
You may have thought
twice before providing
your email address
to a service before.
People who use your app can have
the same apprehension.
They may be worried
that their information will
be shared with others
or used to link their purchases
or behavior
across apps and websites.
In iOS 13,
Sign in With Apple introduced
a new way to sign in
to apps and websites,
allowing people to hide their
names or email addresses.
In iOS 15, these benefits
are available everywhere,
using Hide My Email
with iCloud+.
From Safari,
where people can easily
generate a new email address
when filling in a form,
to right in Mail,
while composing a new message.
And these can come in
from other channels.
Anywhere you receive
email addresses
might have a Hide My Email
address.
When one of your customers
uses Hide My Email,
your email will land
right in their inbox.
Make sure to respect their
decision and only request
additional information,
like their name,
if needed for your experience.
In order to make email
rich and engaging,
emails often contain
remotely-hosted images.
When a mail program displays
one of those emails,
remote images are fetched,
revealing when, roughly where,
and on what kind of device
the mail was opened.
Many marketing emails now
include unique image URLs
for each user,
or even invisible pixels,
specifically to link
this information to people
when they read their messages.
This resulted in people choosing
between text-only emails
to preserve privacy,
or rendering emails
with full content,
but revealing mail activity.
In iOS 15, we're introducing
Mail Privacy Protection.
People can choose to have
iOS privately load
remote message content,
hiding their mail activity.
This is really cool!
And it's great news for you.
More people
will read your emails,
with all the images
and visuals you included.
If you've been using remote
images to measure the impact
of your campaigns, there are
a few changes to be aware of.
Since Mail content may be loaded
automatically after delivery,
the time of Mail viewing
will no longer be correct.
And since that content is loaded
without revealing people's
IP addresses and without
detailed headers,
the location and type of device
reading the Mail
aren't revealed.
And you'll see your
emails as being opened,
regardless of if the user
read it or not.
Next up in transparency
and control,
we'll take a quick tour through
focus and indicators.
New in iOS 15,
if you have a communication app,
you can assist people
in Do Not Disturb
or another Focus
by requesting access
to read their availability,
then sharing that status
within your app's experience.
To request access to status,
you'll need
a NSFocusStatusUsageDescription
key in your app's Info.plist,
and the User Notifications
Communication capability
enabled in Xcode.
For more information on Focus,
check out
"Send communication and Time
Sensitive notifications."
In macOS Monterey,
we've complemented the camera
indicator light
with a recording indicator.
Now, any time
the built in microphone,
or W1 or H1 audio device,
is listening,
people can see that with an
orange dot in the status bar.
Of course, part of building
trust is not abusing it.
Make sure your app runs
the microphone
only when it makes sense
to people.
As an example,
if your app has a mute button,
stop receiving audio from
the system when muted.
Make sure to test your app
on macOS Monterey
to make sure it behaves
the way people will expect.
Also, you can easily confirm
that no third-party
SDKs in your app
are listening unexpectedly.
Next, let's look at
tools that provide
transparency
for recent app behavior.
App Privacy Report will enable
people to understand
what's going on with their
everyday applications
and will be available
in an upcoming software update.
It will reveal to people
when your app accesses user data
and sensors, such as Location,
Photos, or Contacts
and show who your app
may be sharing data with
by listing all the domains
your app contacts,
as well as the domains
that websites accessed
within your app contact.
App Privacy Report
will be in Privacy Settings
and can be enabled
by people to better understand
the apps they have installed.
If people want to clear usage
history,
they can
just turn it back off again.
It's also important to note
that App Privacy Report
will not record ephemeral WebKit
sessions by web browsers,
such as Private Browsing Mode
in Safari.
In iOS 15, Record App Activity
provides export functionality
for you to better understand
your apps' behaviors.
So, you'll
want to grab the iOS 15 beta
and turn on Record App Activity
to get a head start
on what people
will see for your app
in the App Privacy Report
feature.
Then, when you select
Save App Activity,
iOS will produce a JSON file.
You should review
the content of this JSON file
to confirm your app
behaves as expected.
So, let's take a look.
The JSON will have a list
of stream dictionaries,
one for each time a binary
accessed user data and sensors,
like location or camera.
Here's an example
of a single access.
First, search for all
instances of the bundle IDs
of all your app's binaries.
From there,
the timestamps can help you
tie those accesses
to your software behavior.
To see all the domains
you've contacted,
look below
the section marker in JSON:
there's a final dictionary.
This uses bundle IDs for keys,
so there's one dictionary
for each
of your app's executables.
From there,
you can see all domain contacts,
when they were initiated, and if
they were app or user-initiated.
Now, let me show you
the difference between
a connection by an app
and a connection by a website.
Connections made by
SafariViewController
and ASWebAuthenticationSessions
are automatically tagged as
connections by websites.
You can also manually tag
connections
as being caused by a website
if a connection is made
on behalf of third-party content
and isn't core
to app functionality.
At standard layers,
we've added an attribution
enum to manually tag
a connection.
You'll need to specify "user."
If you don't specify,
connections will be
marked as app traffic.
This enum exists in
NSMutableURLRequests,
where you'll want to supply
the MainDocumentURL,
in NWConnection in the Network
framework,
and sockets.
You can also tag connections
via convenience methods in other
Apple frameworks,
such as LinkPresentation
and AVFoundation.
WKWebView has added new methods
to pass an NSURLRequest,
so you can tag your
connections appropriately.
For more info, see "Explore
WKWebView additions."
App Privacy Report exists
to provide transparency
on app behaviors.
And Record App Activity
is a great tool to help you
understand what people
will see when App Privacy Report
becomes available
in an upcoming software update.
Your app should access
only data the user would expect
and at the times
they would expect.
This is another opportunity
to really build trust
with your users,
as they can understand more of
what your application does.
Also, Record App Activity
is a good way
to better understand
the behavior of the SDKs
you've put in your apps
and confirm their practices
align with yours.
Integrate Record App Activity
into your QA passes,
and confirm that only
the data you expect to access
is present
in the App Activity JSON.
And for our final section
of transparency and control,
I'd like to walk through
a few existing areas
where we frequently see
questions from developers.
In late 2020,
Privacy Nutrition Labels
went live.
Labels are designed
to bring transparency
in a glanceable format.
Knowing what your app
will do with their data makes it
easier for people to trust you
and engage with your app.
We know how hard building
good privacy is
and that the best work
can be invisible.
Your label is a place you can
show off the hard work you do
to protect people.
Labels need to be inclusive
of all your practices,
all features, and all
OS versions per platform.
Labels must line up with your
App Tracking Transparency usage,
which brings me
to the next topic.
App Tracking Transparency
was announced at WWDC 2020
and was required beginning
in spring 2021 with iOS 14.5.
Now, people can chose
whether they want to be
tracked across apps
and websites.
This lets people more
easily trust new apps,
and existing ones, too.
To request permission,
you'll need to provide
a purpose string explaining
why you want to track.
You can further explain by
putting
additional information
ahead of that prompt.
If you choose to take this
approach,
there are a few details
to keep in mind.
For example, you shouldn't
pre-prompt with a yes or no.
For more information,
refer to our
Human Interface Guidelines.
Now, some things to keep
in mind.
Tracking is about linking user
data across apps and websites
for advertising purposes
or sharing with data brokers.
For the detailed definition,
see the User Privacy
and Data Use page.
App Tracking Transparency
is about
more than the IDFA, or
Identifier For Advertising.
The IDFA is one way to track,
but App Tracking Transparency
requires you to ask
permission for any tracking.
As part of your app's
functionality,
you might collect
names, email addresses,
or other identifiers.
Linking data using this
information
is also considered tracking.
Fingerprinting,
or the collection
of multiple bits of
information
to generate a stable
device identity,
is disallowed by the developer
program license agreement,
even if people give you
permission to track.
If tracking is denied,
all app functionality
must still be available.
Make sure that your
App Tracking Transparency usage
is reflected
in your Nutrition Label.
Many of you
embed third-party SDKs
to avoid reimplementing
functionality or to take
advantage of helpful
third-party services.
You need to be aware of what
those SDKs are doing.
You're responsible for the
behavior of your whole app.
If an SDK collects data,
you need to
put that behavior
on your Privacy Label.
If an SDK is going to track,
you need to get
people's permission
before calling those methods.
Many SDKs have documentation
related to the Privacy Nutrition
Label.
You can also reach out
to them to ask.
We know that advertising
is a key part of how our
developers thrive,
so we've been hard at work
building privacy-preserving
ad-attribution technologies.
If you run ads in your app,
pay for ads to grow
your customer base,
or work directly in the ad
ecosystem,
here are some
of the improvements.
We added conversion values
and the source apps
when possible,
hardened fraud resilience,
provided credit for
alternate advertising flows,
launched privacy-preserving
web attribution,
provided accounting
for lost conversions,
further hardened
our privacy protections,
and now,
with iOS 15, we've added
a specific pingback to you
so you can measure
ad campaign performance without
help from the ad network.
For more information on all
these changes, check out
"Meetprivacy-preserving ad
attribution."
And that wraps up
our tour
through the transparency
and control pillar
and all the actions you'll need
to take with your apps.
The final privacy pillar
is security.
Security is a vital part of
some of the most well-known
features on our platform,
such as ensuring only the person
that you are iMessaging
can read your messages.
As an example of how security
enables privacy,
the iMessaging
privacy assurance
is upheld
by end-to-end encryption.
If you use
CloudKit for your app,
we've got some new security
measures in store for you.
You have always been able
to have CKAssets
automatically encrypted
at rest with CloudKit.
In iOS 15,
we provide functionality
so you're able to have
other data types
similarly protected
with strong encryption
by just calling a function.
This means that where you were
previously handling encryption
of user data yourselves, now we
will provide the encryption
and key management for all
data types stored in iCloud.
We're now supporting strings,
numbers,
dates, CLLocation and Arrays.
And it's really easy!
You just set the key
value pair on the record
using the encryptedValues API,
and CKModifyRecordsOperation
to save.
And to retrieve
the encrypted value,
just call
CKFetchRecordsOperation
with the same encryptedValues
property.
And now,
I'll hand it off to Elliot
to talk about Private Relay,
and how the privacy pillars
helped shape
its design decisions.
[Elliot] Thanks, Garrett!
We use the internet throughout
our lives to express ourselves,
to connect us to work
and school, order food,
and to help us learn new
things at developer conferences.
Wi-Fi in a hotel,
cellular on the go,
and even the internet
in our homes--
wherever you go,
and whatever network you use,
privacy on the internet
has never been more important.
Let's walk through
my Sunday morning
after recently moving
to Cupertino.
After drinking a pot of coffee,
I sit down on my broken couch
and decide it's time
to get a new one.
I like the couches
at Apple Park,
so I open my Mac and browse
to Furniture Site in Safari
to find some similar styles.
As soon as I connect,
Furniture Site
has my IP address.
Which can be used to determine
which city I live in,
so Cupertino is also added
to my activity profile.
Behind the scenes,
Furniture Site,
like many other websites,
gathers information about me
to share with data brokers.
Furniture Site contributes
the data about my couch browsing
and my IP address is used
to combine all of the other
bits of data collected
about me from many other places.
When combined,
the bits and pieces form
a comprehensive profile
about what I do on the web.
Adding it all together,
the profile that is built
represents a very personal
and up-to-date snapshot about
who I am and what's going
on in my life right now.
My profile even includes
personal details,
like my email address,
and even my home address
that I shared to have
a table delivered.
I never provided
some of this information
intentionally or wanted it
to be shared.
This kind of browsing
history can't be cleared
or reset and isn't even
stored on my own devices.
Not only can this data
be used to serve ads
on other sites that I visit,
it can be used
to influence my behavior
without me knowing.
Later on Sunday,
I started researching
lawn mowers on Lawn Mower Site.
Using my IP address and other
profile information,
I was served an ad about
the couch that I looked at.
Two days later,
I received a couch catalog
in the mail
from Furniture Site.
Internet tracking doesn't always
stay on the internet.
With a detailed profile,
tracking can transition
to physical space.
Tracking reduces trust
and can lead people
to limit what they do
on your website.
Networks and equipment
makers are able to collect
this type of information,
too,
even discover behavior
patterns
from people who
use your website or app.
Technologies like TLS
and encrypted DNS
help protect behavior patterns
and your users' data
from being exposed
to network providers.
You should
adopt these technologies.
To learn more about how to use
built-in ways to protect
internet privacy in apps,
check the "Enable Encrypted DNS"
and "Boost performance and
security with modern networking"
videos from WWDC 2020.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
we are introducing
iCloud Private Relay,
a new internet privacy service.
Included in iCloud+,
Private Relay makes sure
every internet connection
you make is encrypted,
and your IP address
no longer identifies you
or gives away your location
to websites in Safari.
And the best part, with
Private Relay's unique design,
no one, including Apple,
can see both who you are
and which websites you visit.
Let's briefly explore
how Private Relay works
when I shop for my new home.
First, when making a connection
to Furniture Site,
two different Proxy operators
in the Private Relay Network
are randomly picked
so that no single operator
has control or can see
the whole picture.
The proxy that accepts
my connection from
the internet is called
the Ingress Proxy.
The Ingress Proxy prevents
other servers
from seeing my IP address
and encrypts my internet traffic
to prevent my network provider
from knowing what I'm up to.
The relay back
to the internet is provided
by the Egress Proxy,
which prevents the Ingress Proxy
from seeing what website
I'm contacting.
Private Relay manages
network access in a way
that doesn't require
identity or account information,
using RSA Blinded Signatures.
A cryptographic blinding
operation,
performed by my device,
lets me redeem it
for network access,
without giving away
any information about my account
or who's making the connection.
Using the public key
from the Token server,
a Private Relay Proxy
can quickly verify
network access permission.
Before making a connection,
the Private Relay Access Token
Server provides a bundle
of different tokens to my
device.
This gives me access to any
proxy operator I choose,
whenever I need it.
To enforce the separation
of information between
the proxies I picked,
the connection is built
using multiple
layers of encryption.
The proxies
remove layer-by-layer
when the connection passes
through.
Only my device
can decrypt every layer,
which is required to know that I
am accessing the Furniture Site.
When making the connection,
the Egress Proxy randomly
selects an IP address to use.
This helps to prevent linking
my couch search
to my lawn mower search,
or my recent table delivery.
Over time,
Private Relay connections
are automatically created
and reused
to provide IP
address tracking protection
and good performance.
The way Private Relay
hides my IP address
has one more privacy benefit.
Since my home IP address can be
geo-coded to my rough location,
the Ingress Proxy can share
that location with me.
This lets me inform
the Egress Proxy
which group of IP addresses
to choose between.
This is a great example of great
features and great privacy.
Websites can provide
local content in Safari,
while my precise location
stays hidden.
Remember, the Ingress Proxy
is the only one
that can see my IP address,
The Ingress Proxy
converts my IP address
to the same IP-based area
that lawnmower site
would have seen,
then returns
an approximated version back.
In this example,
the Ingress Proxy sends back
"Bay Area, California," which is
forwarded to the Egress Proxy
to help it pick from a group
of IP addresses
that are assigned
to that general area.
With a regional IP address,
sites that I contact
can still find nearby stores.
Let's visualize how this works.
When I connect,
both sites see connections
coming from an IP address
that maps to my general area.
The dots on the map
represent possible
Private Relay IP address
locations
that are shared by
everyone in the region.
When the "Use Country
and Time Zone" option
is selected in iCloud
Internet Privacy settings,
no hint is provided
to the Egress Proxy.
So, it picks a random
IP address from the group
that represents
the much larger region
that belongs
to the Ingress Proxy.
As a result,
websites will see connections
being made
from a broad regional area.
The same set of IP addresses are
used by everyone in the region.
With the more generalized
location setting,
the Lawn Mower Site can now
see a randomized location,
which, for me,
can be places like Los Angeles
instead of Cupertino.
Privacy on the internet
gets even better
when Private Relay and Hide
My Email are used together
to prevent websites from
using your IP and email address
to track your activity
across the web.
We've gone over how iCloud
Private Relay demonstrates
key concepts
from our privacy pillars.
The data minimization
concept is illustrated by
using unlinkable tokens
for network access.
Only devices are able
to process and decrypt
all of the encryption layers
in a Private Relay connection.
IP address protections
enhance control
over tracking on the internet.
Layered encryption and strong
security enforces control
over who can access
internet browsing content.
Our privacy pillars have helped
us every step of the way
when designing
iCloud Private Relay.
Back to Lauren.
[Lauren] Thanks, Elliot.
Great features and great
privacy becomes easier
when we all work together.
We hope that learning about
the new improvements in iOS 15
and how Apple builds
privacy into our products,
like Private Relay,
has inspired you to consider
opportunities for innovation
when building your app.
To better protect people's data,
encrypt new assets in CloudKit.
For seamless
location-based features,
adopt the Share Current Location
button.
Lastly, check your
Record App Activity log
to prepare for
the App Privacy Report
and ensure it aligns
with your nutrition label.
Apple builds tools
with privacy in mind
so that you
can build great apps
for anyone on the platform.
Having an ecosystem
where people are excited
to explore new apps
and try new features
while feeling in control
of how their data is being used
relies on all of us
doing our best work.
iOS 15 and macOS Monterey
provide more control and insight
than ever before, and we're so
excited to see what you build.
[upbeat music]