[percussive music]
[Luke] Hello.
My name is Luke Larson,
and I'm an Xcode engineer.
Later, I'll be joined by my
colleague, Youssef Elabd.
Interface Builder provides
a simple and intuitive way
to build app user
interfaces visually
without writing any code,
allowing developers to focus
on what's important in making
their app stand out.
Today we're going to show you
what's new in Interface Builder
in Xcode 13 that makes it easier
than ever to utilize
the latest platform features,
including new system provided
control styles, to make your app
stand out even more.
In this video, we're going
to cover improvements
to the Interface Builder
canvas and authoring support
for button styles,
table content styles,
hierarchical symbols,
and accessibility.
Let's start
with canvas improvements.
One of the first things you'll
notice with Interface Builder
in Xcode 13 is the completely
redesigned canvas bottom bar.
The controls to the left
of the bar provide all the same
functionality as before,
but in a more compact form,
reserving
more space for the canvas.
There's a popover to choose
a device
which contains a variety of
devices organized in groups.
Clicking a different
device group expands it
and causes the previous
group to collapse,
making it easier to find
the device you're looking for.
There are also buttons
to configure scene layout,
orientation, appearance,
and all-new accessibility
options
that we'll show
later in the video.
Other improvements
include refinements
to the canvas outline view.
And to show them, let's jump
into Interface Builder.
I'm working on a Booking Scene
in a hotel app,
and I noticed
that it isn't positioned
next to the Promotions Scene
in the outline view to the left.
Which is what I expect,
since the Booking Scene
segues to the Promotions Scene.
It's now possible to move
and rearrange one or more
selected scenes in the outline
view using drag and drop.
So I'll drag the Booking Scene
down to be positioned
just above
the Promotions Scene.
Great. Now the two scenes are
positioned next to each other
and are easier
to navigate between.
You can also copy
entire scenes
by holding the Option key
while dragging.
Another refinement
to the outline view
is that outline groups like
Constraints are now selectable,
allowing for keyboard
navigation and easy modification
or deletion of entire groups
of objects.
To show this,
I'll select a constraint group
in the outline view.
This is equivalent to selecting
all the constraints
in the group.
I'll press the Right Arrow key
to reveal
the four edge constraints
contained in the group.
Now I can easily modify
the constants
for all group constraints
in the inspector
Or delete
the entire constraint group
by selecting it
and pressing the Delete key.
Next, let's continue
to new button styles.
Interface Builder in Xcode 13
supports authoring buttons
with new preset styles,
including
the familiar Plain style,
and three new styles:
Gray, Tinted, and Filled.
These new styles make it
easy to create beautiful
and consistent looking buttons
directly in Interface Builder
that automatically provide
support for system features
like dynamic type, multiline
titles, and accessibility.
Additionally, button styles
support further customization
with options like preset button
sizes and corner styles.
I'll go into
more style customization
later in the video.
Check out the video "Meet
the UIKit button system"
for more information
on button styles.
Let's jump back into
Interface Builder to show
these new styles in action.
There's a Book Room button
at the bottom of the scene
that could use some attention.
I'll use pinch-to-zoom
to get a closer look.
I'd like this button
to have a fill color
and rounded corners to draw
more attention to it.
In Xcode 13, it's now possible
to create buttons like this
directly in Interface Builder
using button styles.
Let's focus on the inspector.
There's a new Style
property near the top
of the Button inspector.
When a non-default style is
selected,
a button will be opted
into the new button system,
automatically getting support
for dynamic type, multiline
titles, and accessibility.
I'll go ahead and open the Style
pop-up menu in the inspector
and select the Filled style
for my Book Room button.
The button now has a blue
fill color and rounded corners
that look just right.
And all I had to do was
make a single change.
Button styles are great
for quickly
getting the look you want.
After selecting a style,
new properties appear
in the Button inspector,
enabling further style
customization,
including Subtitle,
title alignment,
and color options,
image positioning,
Corner Style,
and more advanced background
configuration options.
As the name suggests, the Filled
style uses the app tint to set
a button's fill color,
giving it a prominent look
and making it appropriate
for important buttons
in a user interface.
And corner styles mean you
don't have to worry about
setting a specific
corner radius.
The default corner style
is called Dynamic,
which provides
a great-looking corner radius
that automatically scales
with dynamic type,
maintaining the appearance
of the button at any size.
Alternatively,
the Fixed corner style's radius
remains the same
as button sizes change.
For cases where
more control is needed,
both Dynamic
and Fixed corner styles
have customizable
corner radiuses.
Additionally,
a range of preset corner styles
are provided,
including Small, Medium, Large,
and Capsule, all supporting
dynamic corner scaling.
Buttons with styles
also gain access to
a new Button Size property
in the Size inspector
containing preset button sizes,
including Small, Medium,
and Large.
Let's go back
to the hotel app to look
for more opportunities
to adopt button styles.
The Check in and Check out
buttons are looking a bit plain.
To make them more visible, I'll
use the Tinted button style,
which has a transparent
tint-colored background
and is great for buttons that
are important but don't quite
need the prominent look that
the Filled style provides.
I'll select the Check
in and Check out buttons
in the outline view by holding
the Command key.
And choose Tinted
from the Button Style menu
in the inspector.
This is exactly what I was
looking for for these buttons.
Moving on, the Promotions Scene
in this app has a few buttons
that would also be perfect
for the new Tinted style.
Let's segue
on over and take a look.
Using the canvas Minimap,
I'll double click
on the Promotions Scene
to jump directly to it.
This scene displays a list of
active hotel promotions
guests can choose from
by tapping
the appropriate Get button.
Each Get button overlays
an image and will benefit
from the extra
contrast provided by
the transparent background
of the Tinted style.
I'll go ahead and select
the three Get buttons
in the outline view by
holding the Command key.
and choose Tinted from the Style
menu in the inspector
to change all the button
styles at the same time.
That looks great.
Tinted button title
and background colors
are based on the app's
tint color and provide
the appropriate level
of contrast.
I'd also like the Get buttons
to toggle and change
their appearance after being
tapped to indicate
which promotions
have been selected.
I'll configure them
to be toggle buttons
to achieve this behavior,
which are new in iOS 15.
In the inspector under Menu,
I'll toggle the "Selection
as Primary Option" property
to make the selected
buttons toggle buttons.
Before continuing,
I'd like to add a new button
to the Booking Scene to allow
customers to request help.
I'll go ahead and open
the object library...
which now has buttons
preconfigured to use
the new style system, including
buttons with the Plain style
and three new styles:
Gray, Tinted, and Filled.
The Gray style has a transparent
gray background
which provides
a bit more contrast,
so I'll drag out a new
Gray button to act
as a "Get Help" button
and position it
in the navigation bar.
I'll select the new
button in the outline view...
and use pinch-to-zoom
to get a closer look.
I'll set the button's Title
and Subtitle...
its Image
to a question mark symbol...
and to add a bit more space
between the image and titles,
I'll set the image Padding.
One of the advantages of using
Interface Builder
is being able
to try out changes
and quickly
check the result.
I'm not sure which
Corner Style to use here,
so I'll try the Capsule style
to see how it looks.
That looks good, but it's
not what I'm looking for.
Instead, I'll choose
the Large Corner Style
to get the desired look.
That was easy.
Everything needed to create
great-looking buttons is
now available directly
in the Button inspector.
For cases where more advanced
style customization is desired,
setting a custom
Background Configuration enables
more fine-grained control by
revealing additional properties,
including Corner Radius, Stroke,
and Background Image.
One of the steps before booking
a room should be selecting
the number of guests expected
to stay in the room.
I'd like this scene
to have the option
to choose between
1 and 4 guests.
iOS 15 now
supports Pop Up Buttons,
which are perfect
for this feature.
A pop-up button is
a button that when clicked
displays
a menu with a list of items.
A single item can then
be selected from that menu,
which becomes the new label
of the pop-up button.
I've already
created a Guests label,
so all I need to do now
is add a Pop Up Button.
I'll open the object
library and drag one out.
Pop Up Buttons also
support button styles,
so I'll choose the Tinted
style to match the Check in
and Check out buttons.
Then, I'll create two more
menu items using Option-drag
to copy the existing menu
items in the outline view.
Finally,
I'll configure the menu items
to have values from 1 to 4.
Note that when an app
is running on a Mac
with Mac Catalyst 15,
buttons with styles
automatically map
to native macOS variants,
making it easier to get your app
looking great on the Mac.
iOS pop-up buttons are also now
supported on Mac Catalyst 15,
as well as tooltips,
which provide more information
when the mouse cursor
hovers over a control.
I'm planning to have
a Mac Catalyst version
of this app, so I'll go
ahead and set a Tool Tip
for the new Pop Up Button
in the Control inspector.
And we're done.
Note that menu items
must be connected to actions
to display at runtime.
Now that I've adopted new button
styles across the app,
let's build and run.
Here's the app running
with the new Gray styled
Get Help button,
Tinted room options
and Filled "Book Room" buttons.
And finally the Tinted promotion
buttons, and they look great.
Next, I'll hand it off
to Youssef,
who will cover
table content styles,
hierarchical symbols,
and accessibility.
Youssef?
[Youssef] Thanks, Luke.
The next workflow we'll be
visiting is styling
your Table View Cells
using Table View Cell
contentconfiguration styles.
Most great hotels also
have a great restaurant.
This hotel is no different.
Recently, I've been working
on adding a few views to the app
to let guests
check out the restaurant's menu.
Let's pick up where I left off.
I'll two-finger doubletap
on his Table View controller
to focus in on it.
This static Table View
shows a list of the amenities
at the hotel,
and I've recently added
another Table View row
for the restaurant.
I want the title labels
in the cells here to stand out
above the subtitle labels
underneath them.
One of the new Table View Cell
content configuration styles
can give us
the appearance that I want.
Here are some of the cell
layouts you get
with the new
cell styles like grouped header,
value cell,
and grouped footer.
These new styles work great
with images
and also get some functionality
like dynamic type for free.
So let's head back
to Interface Builder
and restyle
the cells in this Table View.
I'll select all of the cells
in the document outline,
and I'll click on the Styles
drop down near the top
of the Attributes inspector,
showing me
all of the new content
configuration styles.
I'll select Subtitle Cell.
Since we're now using
one of the new styles,
we can change Image Padding
right from the inspector.
Let's do that here
to put some breathing room
between the cell's labels
and their images.
Our cells now have larger,
clearer title labels.
This is exactly what I wanted,
and a good visual improvement,
but I still think the cells
could do with some more color.
Next, let's go over how
hierarchical symbols
can help us out here.
New in iOS 15,
symbols can have multiple layers
that I can specify the color
for on a layer-by-layer basis.
This rendering can add more
color and depth to my symbols.
There are two new render modes
that take advantage of this.
The first is Hierarchical,
which lets you specify the color
for the symbol's primary layer
and derives the colors
for the symbol's other layers
as reduced alpha versions
of the primary layer color.
The other mode is Palette,
which lets you independently set
the colors
for the symbol's layers.
You can learn more about
the new symbol rendering modes
in the "What's new in SF
Symbols" video.
The symbols
in our Table View
are currently rendering
in Monochrome mode.
However, I want to emphasize
the symbol's primary elements.
The Hierarchical rendering
mode is perfect for this.
Here are our symbols rendered
using this new mode.
The varied opacities
between the symbol's layers
give it the emphasis
that I want,
so let's go ahead and adopt this
in Interface Builder.
Again, with all of the cells
selected,
I'll click on the Render Mode
drop down for cells' symbols.
I'll select Hierarchical
and choose Tint Color
to match my app's color scheme.
Great.
We've given this Amenities view
a fresh new look by using one
of the new
content configuration styles
for our cells
and the Hierarchical rendering
mode for our symbols.
Now that we've updated
our Amenities view,
let's go over accessibility.
Let's turn our attention
to the menu item detail view,
which shows us some
more information
on one of the restaurant's
menu items.
The Description Label here
is using the subhead text style,
which means
it supports dynamic type.
This label
is already pretty wide,
and I suspect
we might run into
some layout issues with some
of the larger type settings.
New in Interface Builder
in Xcode 13,
you can now preview
how your iOS scenes react
to Accessibility settings
right in Interface Builder
at design time.
As Luke mentioned before,
the canvas bottom bar
has all-new
accessibility options.
Clicking the Accessibility
button brings up
a popover showing me
the different settings
that I can adjust
in Interface Builder.
Some settings can change
text sizes,
frame values,
and colors in my scenes.
Now I can enable and preview
those settings in my canvas
to make sure my views react
as intended.
All right, let's get back
to our Description Label
and verify that it works well
in larger type sizes.
To do this, I'll open up
the Accessibility popover,
activate the settings,
and move
the Dynamic Type slider.
Notice that
the Description Label
is now out of the view's bounds.
I can fix this by opening
up the Constraint popover
and adding a trailing
constraint to my label.
I'll also need to change the
label's number of lines property
from the Attributes inspector
and set it to 0.
This makes the label wrap around
to as many lines as needed.
With those changes,
my label is no longer clipped
and grows to fit its text.
Dragging the Dynamic Type
slider again,
notice that
the Description Label
now fits great
across all type sizes.
Being able to preview
Accessibility settings
at design time
is really powerful
because it allows you
to iterate faster
and stay within Interface
Builder when adjusting
your views for the iOS
Accessibility settings.
Now that we've made
all of those changes,
let's check out our app
running in the simulator.
The cells
in our Amenities Table View
are using one of
the Table View Cell
content configuration styles
that gave us the new
layout that we wanted.
The cells have the symbols
we configured to use
the Hierarchical rendering mode,
making the symbol's primary
elements more prominent.
Clicking through to our
menu item detail view,
the Description Label
fits in great here.
To recap, we started off by
touring the more compact
device bar and improvements
to the outline view.
We took a look at how you
can customize your app's buttons
using the powerful new
button style system.
We went over how to adopt
pop-up buttons for both
iOS and Mac Catalyst,
as well as how to quickly give
your Table View Cells
a new layout
using content
configuration styles.
Your symbols can also
get a lot more color
and emphasis with the new
rendering modes.
Finally, we also went
over how previewing
Accessibility settings at design
time makes it much easier
to ensure that your app's views
work as intended
for the many iOS Accessibility
settings available.
We made all of these
changes without writing
a single line of code,
letting you spend more time
focusing on what
makes your app stand out.
We invite you to use all the
tools we talked about today
to refresh, stylize,
and modernize your app.
And be sure to sure to check out
the "Meet the UIKit
button system"
and "What's new
in SF Symbols" videos.
Thanks for watching,
and have a great WWDC21.
[percussive music]