[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Prashant] Hi, everyone!
I'm Prashant,
an AVFoundation Engineer.
Welcome to WWDC21.
In recent years, the popularity
of over-the-top
streaming services
have approached that
of linear television.
Depending on the market
that you're in,
your users might actually prefer
free ad-supported content
over ad-free content
that they need to pay for.
So if you're interested
in including ads
and other interstitials
in your HLS streams,
you've tuned in
to the right session.
Before we dive in,
let's quickly review
some of the existing mechanisms
for inserting ads
in HLS streams.
You could perform
server side ad insertion
using DISCONTINUITY tags.
This is a fairly static scheme
in that the ad segments
are stitched together
with the content segments,
and this stitching
has to be done
even before the playlist
is vended to the user.
As you might imagine,
this doesn't allow
for late binding
of your ad assets
where you'd like for an ad
to be decisioned
as the user is approaching
the ad marker
or even rebinding,
say, when a user navigates
to a portion of the video
that they've already watched,
they're going to see
the same ad all over again.
Since HLS operates
at a segment granularity,
transitions to and from ad pods
need to happen
at segment boundaries.
If your ad marker
happens to be present
in the middle a content segment,
you'd have to split up
that segment
in order to stitch in the ad.
Oftentimes, the number of
quality tiers would be different
between your primary
and interstitial assets.
In order to stitch
the ad together
with all the primary
quality tiers,
the ads would need
to be conditioned
to match the content encoding.
And you'd also want to make sure
that the ads use
the same codecs
as the primary content.
And in live streaming scenarios,
your packager might
have to do a lot
of back-end bookkeeping.
Your ads and interstitials
would mostly be
video-on-demand streams.
But the packager would have
to spool these out
on a per-segment basis
for the entirety
of the ad break.
You could also insert ads
on the client side.
Until now, we didn't have
an official recommendation
on how this can be done.
One of the more
popular approaches
is to use a two-player scheme
where one player would present
the primary content
while the other would
present the interstitials.
And transitions are achieved
by coordinating playback
between the two players
and by managing
player view hierarchies.
While this works well,
the issues here are
mostly on the performance side.
If buffering is not
properly coordinated
between the two players,
pre-fetching your ad
would impact
the adaptive
bit rate performance
of the primary content stream.
And features like
Picture in Picture and AirPlay
are really hard to do well
with these
custom player approaches.
This year, we've addressed
all these concerns
and in general attempted
to make ad insertion
a lot more simple.
We're introducing
HLS interstitials
where ads are treated
as separate assets
that can be scheduled
onto a program timeline.
Ads are no longer stitched in
with DISCONTINUITY tags.
Instead they remain
as self-contained assets
that can be referenced
via their master playlist.
As we'll soon see,
this scheme is dynamic,
allowing for late binding
and even rebinding
to your ad inventory.
You're no longer constrained
to segment boundaries.
You could arbitrarily
place ads anywhere
on the program timeline.
HLS interstitials
in conjunction with AVKit
offers built-in support
for navigation restrictions
on tvOS.
We also have built-in support
for AirPlay
and Picture in Picture.
All your scheduled ads
and interstitials will be
carried over
the AirPlay session.
We also coordinate buffering
and the use
of other system resources
between the primary
and interstitial players
so as to achieve
seamless transitions.
Now let's take a look
at a typical playback flow
when we present some
video-on-demand content
along with ads
using HLS interstitials.
The blue bar in this picture
represents your main content,
and the orange and green bars
are the ads that you'd like
to schedule during playback.
Now, the primary would play
up until the ad marker,
at which point it would pause,
and the first ad
would start playing.
Once the first ad plays out,
the second ad would
immediately follow.
After the second ad,
the primary would resume
from where it left off.
Now let's take a look
at the buffering sequence.
We start
by buffering the primary
up until the start time
of the first ad.
Now we'd pre-buffer
the first ad,
making it possible to achieve
a smooth transition.
After this has
completely buffered,
we'd pre-buffer the second ad.
And after the second ad
has completely buffered,
we'd start buffering
the primary again
so that we switch back
seamlessly.
The playback flow
for live scenarios is similar,
except that we'd rejoin
the primary
after jumping forward
by the ad duration.
This is so that we remain
in sync with the live edge.
And this also adopts
a similar buffering strategy
such that seamless transitions
are possible.
So how would you schedule ads
with HLS interstitials?
You can now do server side ad
insertion using DATERANGE tags.
For this, we're introducing
a new date range class
with attributes.
This playlist is carrying
timing information
through a PROGRAM-DATE-TIME tag.
These tags are now mandatory
since the ad schedule is now
specified using dates.
Here we see an ad lined up
using the DATERANGE tag,
with the class set
to com.apple.hls.interstitial.
The ID attribute
uniquely identifies the event.
START-DATE is where
you'd like for the ad
to start
in the primary timeline.
Here we see
that the ad is scheduled
at 5 seconds into playback.
The DURATION attribute specifies
the duration of the ad.
The X-ASSET-URI attribute
specifies the URI
of the ad's master playlist.
And the X-RESUME-OFFSET
attribute specifies the offset
from the START-DATE, where you'd
like primary playback to resume.
A resume offset of 0 would mean
that the primary would resume
from where it left off.
If the resume offset attribute
is absent,
we'd rejoin
the primary at an offset
which equals the ad duration.
This is probably what you'd
want to do for live scenarios.
Sometimes you might wish
to skip over in-stream ads
as shown here.
For that, you'd simply specify
the resume offset
to be the duration
of the in-stream ad.
You can schedule multiple ads
using DATERANGE tags.
Here we see
the first ad scheduled
at 5 seconds into the primary
and the second one
at 10 seconds.
You can schedule
back-to-back ads
simply by specifying the same
start time for each of them.
Here we see
that the first ad starts
at 5 seconds into playback,
and so does the second.
The ads would be
displayed in the order
that they appear
in the playlist.
These approaches where you use
the X-ASSET-URI attribute
to reference your ad
would require you
to define your ad pod
when you're adding
the DATERANGE tag
to the playlist.
But you could defer
that decision
using the X-ASSET-LIST
attribute.
The X-ASSET-LIST points
to a JSON object
that contains
the event schedule.
The object has
an ASSETS array that specifies
the list of interstitials,
with each entry specifying
the URI of the master playlist
and the duration.
Note that this JSON object
would be fetched
only at buffering time,
allowing for late binding
to your ad inventory.
Usually, ads would play out
fully to the end.
However,
you can specify an end time
for your ad using
the X-PLAYOUT-LIMIT attribute.
You can use
this attribute to implement
early return scenarios
in live broadcasts.
An early return is where
you'd like to interrupt
your ad break in order
to return to the live feed.
This could be due
to a breaking news scenario,
or maybe there was some sudden
excitement on the sports field
that you don't want your viewers
to miss out on.
So how would you use this
to implement early return?
Here we have a live playlist
that contains six segments.
The live edge
is at the end of segment six.
Now the playhead
would usually be
three target durations
behind the live edge.
In this case, it's at the end
of segment three.
At this point,
a 15-second ad spot
is decisioned
to follow segment six.
So the playlist update actually
contains all six segments
along with a DATERANGE tag
carrying the ad schedule.
In the next update,
the playhead would've moved
to the end of segment four,
and the ad is still scheduled
to follow segment six.
The shaded segment seven here
simply represents the ad break.
In the following update,
the playhead has moved
to the end of segment five,
and in the next update,
we're at the beginning
of the ad break.
If you don't do anything, the ad
would play out for 15 seconds.
But if you want to schedule
an early return,
say, after 12 seconds,
you'd simply specify
the play-out limit to be that.
Now your ad would play
for 12 seconds
before returning to the program.
Oftentimes
for contractual reasons,
you'd want to prevent your user
from jumping over
or skipping through the ads.
You can specify
navigation restrictions
using the X-RESTRICT attribute.
X-RESTRICT with a value jump
would prevent a user to seek
from a time before the ad
to a time after the ad.
An X-RESTRICT with a value skip
would prevent one
from playing the ad at a rate
different from what is desired.
Note that these restrictions
are enforced by the UI.
On tvOS,
they're enforced by AVKit.
And they should be
available to you if you use
the AVPlayerViewController
for your video presentation.
When you're on other platforms
or if you're not using AVKit,
it's up to your application
to enforce these restrictions.
Now that we've seen
how you could schedule
server side ads
using DATERANGE tags,
let's see how you can monitor
their progress at the client.
For this, we're introducing
two new AVFoundation objects:
the
AVPlayerInterstitialEventMonitor
that notifies the client
when an interstitial
is scheduled or playing
and the
AVPlayerInterstitialEvent object
which contains
all the information necessary
to place ads
on a player item's timeline.
The
AVPlayerInterstitialEventMonitor
has the following properties:
a primary player that is playing
your primary asset,
a handle
to the interstitial player
that you can use
to monitor playback of the ads,
an events array
which is an array
of AVPlayerInterstitialEvent
objects that represent
the different interstitials
set on the player.
We'll get to the description
of the AVPlayerInterstitialEvent
object shortly.
A handle to the currentEvent.
So this would be valid
when an interstitial
is playing and null otherwise.
And then we have
the eventsDidChangeNotification
which would fire when
the event schedule changes,
and finally the currentEvent-
DidChangeNotification
which would fire
when we transition
to and from interstitials.
The AVPlayerInterstitialEvent
object that describes
an interstitial event has
properties that are basically
analogues of the DATERANGE
attributes that we saw earlier.
The primaryItem represents
your primary asset
on whose timeline you'd like
to schedule the interstitials.
The identifier is similar
to the ID attribute
and this uniquely identifies
the event.
The time and date fields
specify the start time
of the interstitial in media
time and date respectively.
This would be like
the START-DATE attribute.
We'd use a copy
of the template items to create
the interstitial player items
that'd represent your ad pod.
So this is similar
to the ASSET-LIST attribute
that we saw earlier.
The restrictions property
would specify
the navigation restrictions
for your interstitials.
Then we have
the resumptionOffset
and playoutLimit
properties that are similar
to their DATERANGE counterparts.
And finally we have a dictionary
of userDefinedAttributes.
So you can specify
custom attributes
in the DATERANGE tag,
and these would be surfaced
to your client application
through the
userDefinedAttributes property.
For instance, you might include
a beacon URL
and other custom attributes
for reporting
ad playback metrics.
Here's some example code
that shows how you might use
these APIs to update your UI
when an interstitial is playing.
You create an AVPlayer
to play your primary content.
So this content has
interstitials scheduled
using the DATERANGE tags.
And then create an
AVPlayerInterstitialEventMonitor
and set it on the player.
You then subscribe
to the currentEvent-
DidChangeNotification
to inform your application
when the player transitions
in and out of interstitials.
And when
that notification fires,
you simply update your UI.
Sometimes you might want
to schedule ads
on the client side.
For that, we're introducing
the AVPlayer-
InterstitialEventController
that lets you programmatically
set events on an AVPlayer.
This object inherits from the
AVPlayerInterstitialEventMonitor
and so has a lot
of properties in common.
One thing to note is that while
the events property
is read-only at the monitor,
it is a read-write property
at the controller,
thus letting you
programatically schedule events.
And this also has
the cancelCurrentEvent API
that lets you cancel
the currently playing
interstitial.
In this sample,
we see how one might schedule
an ad pod containing two ads
on an AVPlayer.
You create an AVPlayer
to play your primary asset.
You then create an AVPlayer-
InterstitialEventController
and set it on the AVPlayer.
You create
an array of AVPlayer items
that represent your ad pod.
Then create
an AVPlayerInterstitialEvent
object where you specify
the primaryItem to be
the player's current item,
as this represents
your movie asset,
the start time in this example,
some 10 seconds into playback,
and the templateItems
to be the ad pod
that we created earlier.
And after the object is created,
you simply set it
on the events property
of the controller.
You might notice
that just before we set
the player
on the AVPlayerViewController,
we set the
currentItem.translates-
PlayerInterstitialEvents
property to true.
When this is set, AVKit
would place navigation markers
on the timeline and also enforce
navigation restrictions on tvOS.
Now let's cut to a demo
where we go over
AVKit integration
with HLS interstitials on tvOS.
Here we have an ad
scheduled to start
at some 40 seconds
into playback.
And this ad has no
navigation restrictions set.
You can see that the ad marker
is visible on the timeline.
As the ad is playing,
a countdown timer appears
over the playhead.
And since this ad has
no restrictions set,
as I glide my hand
over to the edge
of the Apple TV remote,
I'd get an option to skip.
And doing so would cause us
to skip out of the ad
and go back to the primary.
Now for this one,
we have the same setup,
but the ad has
the skip restriction set.
So now when the ad plays,
you will not see an option
to skip out of the ad.
You will have to wait
for it to play out completely
before returning to the primary.
[announcer]
Tom Hanks in "Greyhound."
Rated PG-13.
Exclusively on Apple TV+.
[person] Thank you, Josh.
[Prashant] Here we have two ads
as we see on this timeline.
The first with no
navigation restrictions
and the second
with a jump restriction.
So when we attempt
to jump past both the ads...
We see that the playhead snaps
to the restricted ad marker
while the ad plays.
[Tom] We'll bring hell down
from on high.
[announcer] Tom Hanks
in "Greyhound."
Rated PG-13.
Exclusively on Apple TV+.
[Prashant] And after the ad
plays out,
we'd resume
from the seek location.
To wrap up, you can now schedule
server side ads
using DATERANGE tags.
You'd want to specify
the resume offset to be 0
for video-on-demand streams
such that you'd rejoin
the program
from where you left off.
And you could skip
this attribute for live streams
so that we rejoin
at the live edge.
You can use the X-ASSET-LIST
attribute for late binding
of your ad assets,
schedule early return
in live broadcasts
using the X-PLAYOUT-LIMIT
attribute,
and specify
navigation restrictions
with the X-RESTRICT attribute.
To monitor ad playback
on the client side,
you'd use the AVPlayer-
InterstitialEventMonitor.
And you can
programatically set ads
using the AVPlayer-
InterstitialEventController.
Thank you for watching
and enjoy the rest of WWDC21.