[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Linda] Hi.
My name is Linda Dong.
I'm a Design Evangelist,
and I'm going to be
joined shortly by Sam Iglesias,
a Prototyper
on the Apple Design Team.
We're gonna talk about
best practices when it comes
to designing inclusively.
But before we get into that,
I wanted to touch
on why we make apps and games.
As a developer,
the things you create
bring people joy,
enrichment, and convenience.
They help us accomplish tasks
and reach personal goals.
They connect us with other
people from around the world.
They entertain us
through fun gameplay
or make us thoughtful
through touching narratives.
At the end of the day,
they add emotional
and practical value
to our lives.
And I'm sure one of the goals
you have
for your app or game is enabling
as many people as possible
to enjoy these benefits.
Over the years,
the App Store has grown
into a huge marketplace
that serves 500 million visitors
per week.
People from over 175
regions around the world
and 40 different languages
can potentially see
what you've built.
If you want to reach even
a fraction of that audience,
you owe it to yourself to design
with inclusivity in mind,
so that your app or game
is great for everyone.
This means that people can
interact with your design
through different languages
and accessibility features.
That it's easy to learn,
feels natural,
and is a pleasure to use.
But great usability isn't
the only important goal.
What also matters is
that your app or game is
welcoming and respectful
of folks
from diverse backgrounds
and perspectives.
Our perspectives are shaped
by a number of factors,
such as our individual
experiences.
This could be where
we grew up in the world
and where we live now,
the cultures
we're familiar with,
and the languages we speak
or hear around us.
They're also shaped
by our human characteristics,
like our gender, our age,
and the physical and mental
abilities and disabilities
we might have.
You can think of each
of these factors
as its own diversity axis,
and the intersection of where
someone lands on all these axes
makes up their unique identity.
It's a good reminder
to think critically about
how people with completely
different identities
and perspectives will all be
able to enjoy what you've built.
When someone approaches
your app or game,
they should feel like
you designed with them in mind.
Not only will people feel taken
care of, you'll build trust
that extends to other areas
of your app, game, and brand.
One of the great things
about being
in your position is
that you're in charge
of how accommodating
your designs will be for people.
It does take
work and consideration,
and you're not always
gonna get it right,
but any intentional steps
you take
will be appreciated
by so many people.
To help, we're gonna talk about
how to approach designing
inclusively, especially
in the area of content.
At Apple, we define
"content" as the words,
images, audio,
and video that live
inside your designs,
as well as your marketing.
Content is the language you use
to speak to your audience.
And it's also how you let
folks identify themselves.
This can be through the names,
profile details,
avatars, or characters
that people can customize
within your app or game.
The way you address people
through your content
and how you let folks
represent themselves
are great moments where you can
make more people feel welcome.
So with that,
I'll hand it over to Sam
to get us started.
[Sam] Thanks, Linda.
In this video, we'll go through
six specific practices
you can use to make
your app or game more inclusive.
Tell diverse stories.
Avoid stereotypes.
Adopt accessibility.
Localize for culture.
Use color mindfully.
And finally,
encourage self-expression.
The first practice is
tell diverse stories.
As Linda mentioned,
people who might use
your app or game will come
from a rich and diverse set
of individual backgrounds
and experiences.
You have an opportunity
to make them feel included,
even before
they've downloaded it.
This could be through something
like a web page
or your app's page
on the App Store.
The way you describe
your app or game, its name,
video trailer, and even
the screenshots you select
tell a story
about whom it was built for
and how they might use it.
If you don't approach
this step with creativity
and empathy,
you might unintentionally make
some potential customers
of yours feel unwelcome.
Let's focus on app screenshots.
You might start with names
that are familiar
from your immediate circle
of family and friends.
Or depict
hobbies and discussions
that personally interest
or excite you.
Or draw on familiar stories
for your app's
example scenarios.
For example, your app might be
social in nature,
and you're gonna be
making choices
about what kinds
of content shows up
in the example feed,
who's posting that content,
and even the tenor
of interaction
among people who use your app.
Or it might be something
like a to-do list,
and you're gonna be making
choices about a day in the life
of somebody using your app:
the activity or celebration
they might be planning,
their reading list,
their aspirations.
Or it might be
a food-tracking app,
and you're showing examples
of the kinds of foods someone
could be interested in logging,
or the kinds of food choices
they'll be making
throughout their day.
These are excellent
opportunities
to tell interesting
and diverse stories.
In my social app,
I might wanna depict
a group of people having
fun on a kayaking trip.
While this definitely
looks like a lot of fun,
this group might not necessarily
reflect the diversity
of people who might be
interested in my app,
or a lifestyle that everyone can
relate to.
There are a number of ways
this might be improved.
Here's an example of a set
of changes we could make.
Now, we have a photo
that depicts a slightly
more diverse group
of people performing
an act of community service.
In our example to-do app,
we might depict
a fairly pedestrian day
for some Americans,
where we're returning a call
to our best friend,
then shopping
for a birthday party,
reading a book, and then
practicing an instrument.
But the problem is these are,
at least to some audiences,
kind of overly familiar
cliches, right?
Here's how this example
might be improved.
Instead of returning
John's call,
now I'm returning Abhi's call.
Instead of shopping for dinner,
I'm planning Diwali,
a holiday that's observed
by over a billion people.
For a book, maybe a lesser-known
voice, like Chinua Achebe's?
As for an activity to practice,
how about sign language,
which can promote inclusion
of the deaf community?
While still telling
the story of someone
who needs an app to keep
track of various tasks,
we've made some of the content
more relatable and inclusive
to more people along
different diversity axes.
How about something like
a food-logging app?
It's probably really tempting,
when putting
screenshots together,
to reach for what's familiar.
So if you're American,
examples like these--pancakes,
pizza, hamburgers--might
make you feel right at home.
But let's remember that not
everyone around the world,
or even in the United States,
imagines a screen like this
when they're thinking
about food.
Adding some foods that might
speak to other cultures
could be an excellent way
to tell
a slightly different story,
not just about how someone
might use your app,
but whom your app is for.
So when you're setting up
your App Store page,
tell diverse stories.
Fill your screenshots
not with the names and scenarios
that come to mind the quickest,
but try to dig a little deeper,
to find a story
that's told less often.
Not only will this make new
groups of people feel welcomed
by your app or game, it'll help
it stand out even more.
[Linda] The second practice
for designing inclusively
is to avoid stereotypes.
Stereotypes are
oversimplified beliefs
about communities of people.
They make you overlook
differences between individuals
and perpetuate incorrect ideas
of how people behave.
The truth is all of us hold
these types of beliefs,
and, usually, we're not
even aware we have them.
But if you aren't careful of how
stereotypes influence the design
of your app or game,
you may be unconsciously
excluding people,
by not recognizing them
in your content
and functionality.
For example,
in your language and visuals,
it's sometimes easy to fall
into the stereotype that people
are divided into just
two genders, men and women.
This binary is deeply embedded
in some languages and cultures,
and if you're part
of those communities,
you can unknowingly overlook
millions of people
who don't identify with either.
Throughout history,
people have recognized
a spectrum of human gender,
and you can
honor this diversity by avoiding
unnecessary references
to a gender binary
in your content.
For example, when you don't know
someone's gender,
instead of using
the binary pronouns "he"
or "she" in your copy,
you can replace this language
with the gender-neutral pronoun
"they" instead.
You can also avoid overlooking
parts of your audience
by referring to people
as a single gender.
Like saying "Hey, guys!"
in video content,
when you can include
more people by saying
"Hey, everyone!"
Removing unnecessary
gender references
also applies to visuals.
Take, for example, a placeholder
icon for someone's new profile
that uses a stereotypical
masculine avatar.
This icon tells a story
about who you think
your app is for
and maintains a message
that a generic person
means a masculine person.
Let's make this better,
by using a non-gendered
human icon that doesn't
make any assumptions
about who a person is.
SFSymbols provides a number
of these gender-neutral glyphs
you can use throughout
your apps and games.
Just as you don't want your app
or game to disregard
people through gender,
you also don't want
to exclude people
by unintentionally using
ableist language.
If you're not familiar
with the term "ableism,"
it's a stereotype that having
a certain set of physical
or mental abilities
makes you "normal"
and having disabilities
makes you "abnormal."
But we all know that there's
no such thing as normal.
Everyone has
a unique set of abilities,
some people have disabilities,
and everyone's capabilities
are equally valuable.
Like gender, ableist language
can be deeply embedded
in the way that we talk
and can slip into your copy.
Like using words that reference
disabilities, such as "insane"
or "crazy," to describe
something that's undesirable.
Even if you're trying to use
that word
to describe something
positively,
like "Achieve
insanely fast speeds,"
it's still labeling
a condition as an outlier,
which can stigmatize
mental health.
In cases like this,
you can rethink
how you can convey
the same meaning
without casting disabilities in
a negative or alienating light.
Here, instead of saying
"Achieve insanely fast speeds,"
you could say "Achieve
ridiculously fast speeds."
Now, all of this isn't to say
that you should completely
avoid acknowledging
disability in your content,
but rather to avoid
referring to disability
in language when suggesting
something is less than.
In fact,
it's a great idea to recognize
and reinforce representation
of disabilities.
Showing people with disabilities
in your emoji,
photography,
and game characters can help
debunk stereotypes of who uses
and plays apps and games.
Outside of content,
avoid letting stereotypes
limit your interface's
functionality.
Let's say I'm designing
an app that lets families
manage who has access
to a shared movie library.
If I have a stereotypical view
of what a family looks like,
perhaps a married man
and woman and young children,
I might end up designing
an interface like this.
Which buckets
family members into a father,
a mother, and child roles.
In this case,
my app's understanding
of what a family is doesn't
consider that families can look
like single parents,
same-sex parents,
multi-generational households,
adult children,
and legal guardians.
Whether I planned it or not,
my app's design
and functionality excludes all
those families who are different
from the stereotype from being
able to this interface.
So how could I improve
this feature?
Well, instead of assuming
there are fixed family roles,
I can label each profile
something neutral,
like "family member."
And instead of assuming how many
people make up a family,
I can start with just the person
setting up the account,
and let them add as many people
to their family as they need.
For you,
not making assumptions about
who is using your app
can enable you to build
functionality that supports
everyone.
The best way to develop
your awareness
of your own stereotypes
is to talk to people from beyond
your immediate community.
Look for people with a diversity
of lived experiences that can
help you recognize where
your knowledge falls short.
And remember that language is
constantly evolving,
and that this guidance
will change over time,
so be open to updating your
knowledge as definitions shift.
[Sam] In our third practice,
we'll discuss why it's important
to try to adopt accessibility
in your app or game.
Imagine someone who is
blind has just downloaded
your app,
is extremely excited to try it,
and is greeted with this
from VoiceOver.
[text to speech]
Button, gear shape two.
[Sam] Or someone who is deaf
has made it
through an exciting level
in your game
to a cutscene,
and captions aren't offered.
Linda told you earlier
about ableism,
which stems from the idea
that somebody who is disabled is
"abnormal" and should not
receive the same attention
of those who are "normal."
If your app or game's content
isn't as accessible as possible,
it is not inclusive.
Do not start with the assumption
that someone who is
disabled wouldn't want
to use your app or game.
Let's look at some ways you can
make it benefit more people.
The world is a rich tapestry
of experiences and abilities.
From those who are blind
or have low vision,
are deaf or hard-of-hearing,
have sensitivity to motion,
or physical
or motor disabilities,
hundreds of millions of people
use at least one
accessibility setting.
And even if you or anybody
you know doesn't use one,
it's possible that at some point
in your life, you might find
Accessibility helpful,
even if temporarily.
This can be something temporary
like having your pupils dilated
at the optometrist and needing
larger text, or needing
to reduce exposure to loud
sounds after a concussion,
or it might be some other
health circumstance.
So what are some things
you can do to ensure
that your app is accessible?
Let's have a look
at a few things you can do,
starting with text and type.
Visual perception varies a lot.
That's why it's important
to make sure
that your app functions
properly across the range
of Dynamic Type settings.
iOS supports a wide range
of text size preferences,
but by using the right
layout APIs in SwiftUI
or UIKit,
your app's layout should
be able to adapt flexibly
and automatically.
Here's an example of how
a To-Do app using
SwiftUI's font system
adapts automatically.
Try to take care
that your app is intelligible
across the type size gamut.
Look for truncated
and clipped text,
and maybe rethink
some of your layouts
if they have trouble
with the larger sizes.
Additionally, you wanna
make sure that your app
consistently honors some
of the settings that UIKit's
or SwiftUI's text system doesn't
handle for you automatically.
For example,
if the person using your app has
Bold Text turned on,
make sure that elements
that are not text,
but which still might pose
legibility challenges,
are thickened.
These circles, for example.
Here's what the app looks like
with bold text turned on,
but we aren't done yet.
We need to go further and have
some of our other interface
elements respond to this new,
bolder preference.
That's better.
Now, let's talk about VoiceOver.
VoiceOver is a screen reader
that lets people use
an interface without
looking at the screen.
For someone who is blind,
VoiceOver is
absolutely critical,
but VoiceOver also benefits
people who have other reasons
not to look at a screen,
such as someone who's riding
a bus, who might be motion sick
if they look at their device.
By default, VoiceOver attempts
to step over interface elements
in a logical order
and will glean information
embedded
in system-standard controls.
However, there will be cases
in which VoiceOver
needs more help.
The first case is where
a button is simply
represented by a glyph.
If you use a glyph from
SFSymbols, VoiceOver will use
the symbol's name, but even
a description of the glyph might
not be enough to convey
the button's functionality.
[text to speech]
Gear shape two, button.
[Sam] Whether you're using
SwiftUI or UIKit,
take care to add a descriptor
that makes more sense
in your app's context.
You want VoiceOver to read
this button out to say
something like this.
[text to speech]
Account settings, button.
[Sam] Or this, where the button
is also reflecting some state.
[text to speech]
Remove favorite, button.
[Sam] The second important note
is to pay attention
to VoiceOver's ordering.
This app features a prominent
"post" button at the bottom
of the screen, placed there
so it can be easily accessed.
But VoiceOver
will probably start
reading out interface
elements on the top left.
Fortunately,
SwiftUI and UIKit make it easy
to specify that the "post"
button should be read out first.
[text to speech]
Make new post, button.
[Sam] And the top left
will be read second.
[text to speech]
Profile picture.
Hi there, Enrique!
Venice, CA, 68 degrees.
[Sam] You've probably gathered
by now that testing is critical.
While it's never possible
to have complete access
to someone's lived experience,
try your app or game
with some of these Accessibility
settings turned on.
You can add a number
of accessibility settings,
like VoiceOver, Increase
Contrast, Reduce Transparency,
Reduce Motion,
and the Grayscale Color Filter
into your Accessibility Shortcut
menu
and access it
from Control Center.
Another really handy feature
is the Text Size toggle,
which can also be added
to Control Center.
Try experiencing your app
or game in grayscale
to get a sense for how
reliant you are on color
and how strong your app's
color contrast is.
Try experiencing your app
or game with no sound,
to get a sense for how reliant
your app is on audio alone.
Taking a different perspective
on how your app or game
might be used
can actually lead
to some insights and innovations
that can make the experience
better for everyone.
One of my favorite examples
is the QuickPath Swipe Keyboard,
which was originally invented
to help those who lack
the manual dexterity
to thumbtype type as quickly
as everyone else.
As it happens, many people
love typing in this way.
A solution to a challenge
for one group of people
ended up helping
many, many more.
We didn't touch on all
the ways you can make
your interface more accessible,
but be very conscious about
who can use your app or game,
and try really hard to widen
the circle so that even more
people can enjoy your work.
[Linda] Our fourth practice
for designing inclusively
is localizing for culture.
A big step in growing
your app or game's reach
is translating it
into different languages
so more people can enjoy it.
Even if you're not
looking to expand
into other countries just yet,
remember that the people
who live in your country speak
different and, sometimes,
multiple languages.
In fact, it's estimated
that roughly half
the people in the world
speak more than one language.
Translation is all about
prepping your interface
so that it can handle
different word lengths
and writing systems.
It also involves
carefully dubbing any audio
and translating
closed captioning in video.
As well as paying attention
to how you format units,
such as time, phone numbers,
and currency.
But localization isn't
just about translating words
and numbers from one
language to another.
It's also about
making your content
more relevant
to different cultures.
And again, this matters
even if you're only focused
on the country you're based in
because those folks
around you still come from
different cultural backgrounds.
One of the first things
you can do to make people
from other cultures feel welcome
is to double-check whether
you're using phrases that only
make sense to certain people.
Take this phrase:
"Nine cows and one hair."
If you're not familiar
with Chinese expressions,
you're probably wondering,
"What the heck does this mean?"
This expression is an idiom,
which is a phrase that has
a different meaning
than its literal words.
If I were to convert this
into an English idiom,
you might recognize it
as "a drop in the bucket,"
which, in turn, means
"a tiny amount."
Language like idioms,
and slang, and humor,
can be tricky to make inclusive.
Not only do they take
a lot of steps
in your head to understand,
people need to share
the same cultural background
in order to get them.
And sometimes, they don't have
a direct translation.
Imagine if your app's copy
said something like
"Plan your vacation
from A to Z."
How would you translate
"A to Z," to make sense
in, say, Korean?
Always try to speak with plain,
direct language,
avoiding metaphors
and complex terms.
It will make your copy
easier to understand,
easier to translate,
and more culturally inclusive.
In this case, I would rephrase
"Plan your vacation from A to Z"
plainly as "Plan your vacation
from beginning to end."
To dive deeper into clear
language that's understandable
to everyone, check out the new
section on "Writing Inclusively"
in the Apple Style Guide
website.
Beyond words, it's good
to consider whether your content
is respectful of different
cultural norms and customs.
Say I've just launched a cooking
app in the United States,
which compiles recipes
for popular meals
like homemade pizza,
roast chicken, and hot dogs.
My app is doing really well,
and I'd like to expand
into international markets,
starting with India.
I might work closely
with a translator
to get my screens written
into the language Hindi,
which would look like this.
If I stopped there and just
launched my app in India as-is,
it would probably flop
in that market.
Why?
Because even though
people in India would
be able to read
all of the text in my app,
my recipe content
is still very catered
towards a U.S. audience.
In India, a large portion
of the population are vegetarian
and follow Hinduism,
where cows are revered,
and it's very uncommon,
sometimes banned, to eat them.
Surfacing suggestions
like beef and sausages
can come off as insensitive
to local cultures.
Instead,
I could tailor my app's content
to fit with local
dietary customs,
researching dishes
that would be more relevant
and ingredients that are
more widely available in India.
I could also use
this opportunity
to recognize cultural moments,
like surfacing recipes
typically eaten
during local festivals.
Together with translation,
acknowledging cultural
differences gives my app
a better chance
of being well-received
in a new country.
In games,
respecting others cultures can
come into play if you have
characters and environments
that are inspired by real-life
people and places.
An inclusive game is able
to avoid
creating caricatures
of different cultures.
Ask yourself,
"Am I associating an enemy
as someone from an already
marginalized race?"
or "Am I basing 'exotic' alien
or fantastical characters
"off of the physical traits
and languages
of real ethnicities?"
Even though you're crafting
fictional scenarios,
they can still have real impact
and hurt players' perceptions
of real people and cultures.
So take care with how
you depict others,
and engage in conversations
with people from other cultures
to learn how you can adapt
your content
to better serve
and respect them.
[Sam] The fifth practice
is to use color mindfully.
Linda mentioned earlier
that different cultures
and languages have idioms
that we should be mindful of
when we're localizing.
The same can apply to color.
Colors elicit emotion,
and some of those emotions
can change
from culture to culture.
For example,
in many Western countries,
green can symbolize
environmentalism
and going green,
or can, in Western countries,
come to symbolize luck,
money, or fortune.
But in a lot of Asian cultures,
red is used to connote fortune,
happiness, and well-being.
This is why it's considered
good luck to wear red
during the Lunar New Year.
In many parts of the world,
red can be associated
with love and red roses.
Or red can be associated
with danger, negativity,
and even violence.
These associations are why,
for instance,
in most localizations,
Stocks shows green for gains
and red for losses,
but why, if you set
your region to Mainland China,
gains are shown in red.
As mentioned earlier,
in a lot of Asian cultures,
red connotes fortune
more strongly than green does.
There are probably opportunities
to customize your colors
by region to be
more understandable
to a specific culture.
As with localizing for culture,
the best way to fully understand
whether your color choices are
eliciting the intended emotions
is to ask people
who come from those backgrounds.
Let's also briefly touch
back on accessibility
as it relates
to color blindness.
You might not know that color
blindness affects almost 5%
of the world's population,
so make sure your interface
elements don't solely rely
on color to get
their points across.
Here, we have two kinds of dots
to indicate "unread"
and "flagged."
But someone who is colorblind
might not be able
to easily distinguish these two
kinds of dots from color alone.
In such a case,
we might need to instead
opt to change one
of the dots to a glyph.
As a result,
you might even end up
with something that is easier
to understand at a glance.
Also pay attention
to contrast ratios
between text and backgrounds,
particularly when "Increase
Contrast" is activated.
Not only are
some people sensitive
to low-contrast interfaces,
there are also
environmental factors,
like bright sunlight
and use of sunglasses,
that can also benefit
from higher contrast.
The default iOS palette actually
contains an additional set
of colors to support
high-contrast mode,
so if your app uses
system colors,
you can automatically benefit
from system support.
If your app has
its own color palette,
you're gonna need to calculate
the luminosity ratio
between backgrounds and text,
using tools
that are available on the web
or in the App Store.
When "Increase Contrast"
mode is turned on,
aspire to a minimum of 4.5:1
in your interfaces.
Plugging these colors in,
we find that our contrast
doesn't meet the bar of 4.5.
What if we try black instead?
Now, we can see that we're
comfortably over 4.5.
In fact, we should probably
keep this text color,
regardless of whether
high-contrast mode is turned on.
This is just a rough guide.
There will be cases in which
this ratio is misleading,
and you'll need to use
your own judgment.
For instance, this color
combination also exceeds the bar
of 4.5, but it's still
hard to read in context.
Correctly assessing
your app or game's contrast
is as much of an art
as it is a science.
Culture is about more
than words and symbols;
it's about things
like color, too.
And not everybody perceives
the same color palette,
so be sure to use color
with care
so that your app or game
can delight everyone.
[Linda] The last practice
we wanted to share with you
is encourage self-expression.
Your app or game can acknowledge
and celebrate
people's individuality,
and the best way
to make that happen is by not
limiting or enforcing how people
can identify themselves.
Take names, for example.
When you meet someone new,
"What's your name?"
is one of the first things
you ask them.
It can also be the first thing
your app asks for
when someone launches
your experience.
And your interface should
accept the diversity
of names people can have.
Very often, names don't pass
form validations
because they have
hyphens or accents,
or are shorter or longer
than an allowed character count.
You might have even
experienced this yourself,
or can at least understand
how annoying it would be
to have this happen
to you all the time.
So to provide a good experience,
be flexible in supporting
special characters
and not enforcing
specific name lengths.
Also recognize that concepts
like having a first name
and a last name
are very region-specific.
If you're from Latin America,
chances are you have
two family names,
one from each parent.
If you're from China,
your family name is
written first
and your personal name last.
And in some countries,
like Malaysia and Afghanistan,
you might not have
a family name,
and go by just
your personal name.
If you were any of those people,
how would you approach
these first and last name
input fields?
Depending on what you're
using their name for,
a more culturally-inclusive
solution can be to provide
a single text field for someone
to enter their full name.
Better yet,
you can always ask people
what their preferred name is,
which can differ from
what they go by legally.
Providing this type
of flexibility makes sure
that all people's names
are welcome
and creates a more personal
connection if you ever
address someone by name
in your app or game later.
Similar to names,
gender is also an opportunity
to acknowledge
someone's identity.
As I mentioned earlier,
human gender is a spectrum
and presenting someone
with limited options
to represent their gender,
such as Male, Female, and Other,
doesn't fully represent
how broad that spectrum is.
The dating app Bumble
is a great example
of presenting gender choices.
At registration,
you have the choice to identify
from a wide range of gender
options and can submit your own.
You can also choose
to make your gender
public or private
and can change it at any time.
An interface like this,
that acknowledges diversity,
makes more people feel welcome.
In games with human
character creation screens,
how you let people
customize themselves
is a great way
to acknowledge identity.
A lot of times,
people craft characters
to look like themselves,
so they can feel
more immersed in a role
or a story.
You can think back
to the diversity axes
to consider all the ways people
might want to physically
represent themselves
with different appearances.
And if your narrative
has a romantic element,
you can give people agency
to choose relationships
based on different
sexual orientations.
A great example of giving
people customization options
is a game called "Say No! More."
Its gameplay is about
setting boundaries
at work by saying the word "No!"
as a super power.
When you create your character,
there's a wide variety
of ages,
skin colors, body types,
hairstyles,
and clothing to choose from.
You also can choose
how you say "No!"
based on a number
of languages and vocal tones.
Better yet, none of your choices
are bucketed by what gender
your character is.
In fact, the game never asks
for your gender
because it doesn't need to.
Clothing and hair styles don't
belong to a certain gender,
and neither does how
someone's voice sounds.
In this case,
not asking for you to identify
makes this game's interface
more inclusive.
Always prioritize
asking people how they'd like
to represent themselves
through your app or game,
and design flexible interfaces
that respect those identities.
[Sam] So we've covered
a lot in this video.
The importance of thinking
carefully about how
you craft the stories
around your app.
Tell diverse stories.
Avoiding stereotypes
in your language and content.
Making sure
that you are taking advantage
of the accessibility features
offered on our platforms
and testing accordingly.
That your app is thoughtfully
localized and sensitive
to how culture can affect
how content is carried over.
That your app mindfully uses
color, both to respect culture
and those who perceive
color differently.
And lastly, that your app
doesn't unduly restrict
someone's ability
to identify how they want to.
These practices stem
from our duty to each other
to design inclusively
and to help each person
live their best life.
Inclusive design is
welcoming and respectful,
and inclusive design
is great for everyone.
These practices take, well,
practice to get right.
And while this might seem
like a lot to do, it's worth it.
Because when we craft
something with respect,
consideration, and love,
that care can be felt.
For more resources
on how you can
design inclusively,
check out our new section
on "Inclusion" in the Human
Interface Guidelines.
And on how you can instill
inclusive principles
deep into your process,
watch the talk,
"The process
of inclusive design."
Thanks.