[upbeat music]
[Shefali] Hi, everyone.
My name is Shefali Saboo,
and I'm a performance tools
engineer here at Apple.
I'll be your guide
as we navigate
application performance
together.
Today's journey will be
a thrilling tour
through the world
of performance.
Your apps play
a significant role
in the overall software
experience on our devices.
Continuing to optimize your apps
and improve performance
means your users will use
your app more often,
stay more engaged,
and will use your app
for a longer period of time.
Optimizing for performance
can seem like a daunting task
with many metrics to track
and tools to use.
But fear not.
This survival guide
will get you up to speed
on tooling, metrics,
and paradigms
that can help take your
development to the next level
and ensure the best possible
customer experience.
I'm so excited to be your guide
as we walk through
our performance tools
and the great things
that you can do with them.
There will be five major tools
that we'll be covering today:
the Xcode Organizer, MetricKit,
Instruments, XCTest,
and the App Store Connect API.
We'll start with a quick
introduction of the key metrics.
Then step through
some common problems
in each domain area
and ways to resolve
and prevent them.
And finally,
we'll end with some next steps.
Performance optimization is like
a long river with many stops.
There are a few different tools
needed for navigation,
and at each of the stops,
there's something new to learn.
Let's take a trip
down the river.
First, a quick introduction.
Let's take a look at the
different performance metrics
we'll cover today.
There are currently
eight key things to track
for application performance:
Battery Usage, Launch Time,
Hang Rate, Memory,
Disk Writes, Scrolling,
Terminations, and MXSignposts.
All of these can be tracked
through our toolset.
I'm a developer for an app
called MealPlanner
that allows users to track
their meals for the week
and save cool recipes.
Here's an example of a poor
user experience within my app,
specifically in the form
of scroll hitches.
Notice the slow, skipping,
and jittery scroll?
On the flip side,
here's the same application
with a seamless user
experience and no hitches.
We can already see that
there's quite a difference
between the two experiences,
and this smooth scroll is what
we want to help you achieve
through performance
optimizations.
Each performance metric
has its own unique set
of paradigms and common tooling.
Let's jump right
into some common problems
in each domain area
and ways to resolve
and prevent them.
Our first stop along
the river is battery usage.
If your app is draining
a lot of battery,
here's what a user
will see on their end.
This is the Battery UI.
It shows users how much
of their overall battery drain
an app on their device
contributed towards,
as well as its foreground
and background activity.
Why should you care
about improving battery life?
Easy.
Users prioritize using apps
that allow them
to use their devices
throughout the day
without needing to recharge.
By optimizing for battery life,
users can use their devices
and your app
for a longer period of time.
That, in and of itself, is a win.
There are many
different subsystems
to pay attention to
when it comes
to optimizing battery life.
The top three to make note of
are CPU, Networking,
and Location.
I can track and triage
the battery life of my app
using a few different tools
during development
or after a version
has already released.
While I'm developing and testing
a new feature at my desk,
I'll build and run my code
through Xcode,
and click
on the Debug navigator,
which looks like
a little spray bottle,
to see the various gauges
Xcode has to offer.
The one I'll pay close attention
to is the Energy Gauge.
The Energy Gauge allows me
to track my CPU usage
as I'm testing my app
and shows me regions
of high CPU utilization
and CPU Wake Overhead.
High CPU utilization is
when CPU use
is greater than 20%,
and CPU Wake Overhead is regions
where the CPU wakes
from an idle state,
and there's
an incurred energy cost.
It's common to see
a spike in CPU
when my app is drawing
the user interface,
processing data
from the network,
or performing calculations,
but once those tasks are
complete and my app is waiting
for the user to perform
their next action,
I should see the CPU usage
be at, or near, zero.
From here, I can
also click Time Profile
to profile my app in Instruments
and see the thermal state,
CPU usage,
and active call stacks
for the profiled duration.
I can also use
the Location Energy Model
to measure the impact
of Core Location
and make sure my app
isn't using the location
when it shouldn't be.
Occasionally,
there might be a bug in a beta
or released version of my app
that's tough to reproduce
at my desk
or may need more logging
and context to debug.
MetricKit,
which operates on-device
as an all-in-one performance
telemetry framework,
can help me narrow down
the root cause
and provide me valuable insights
into problems my customers
are facing.
To use MetricKit,
all I need to do is add
and implement a custom class
called AppMetrics in my app
and conform this new class
to the MXMetricManagerSubscriber
protocol.
I can then add a reference
to my custom class
to the manager.
And remove a reference
to my custom class on deinit,
which is a recommended
best practice.
I can process this data
in the corresponding
didReceive methods.
If done strategically,
I can augment much
of the same data
I'll find in the Organizer,
such as the energy logs
and CPU metrics,
with contextual data
from MetricKit
about what may have been going
wrong when the problem occurred.
A simple version of this data
is available to you,
with no extra effort,
thanks to our
on-device analytics pipeline.
As users use your app,
we collect performance data
from consented devices.
This data is then aggregated
on our servers
and sent back to you
through one of our many tools,
like the Xcode Organizer.
Accessing the Xcode Organizer
to see performance data
for a version of my app
that's already in the app store
is as easy as navigating
to the menu bar
while Xcode is open,
going to window,
and clicking Organizer
to launch.
Once I'm here, I can click
on the battery usage metric
to view aggregated data
for my app
across the last 16 app versions,
as well as a detailed breakdown
by major subcomponent
to the right of the chart.
If the newest version of my app
has a major regression,
I'll know about it
right after a version shows up
in the Organizer,
if I navigate
to the Regression pane,
which is new in Xcode 13.
This new regressions pane
isolates all the metrics
that have increased
significantly
in the most recent version
of my app
so I can see all the things
I need to focus on in one place.
To determine what areas
of my app caused the issues,
I can also use
Energy Organizer under Reports
to view regions of high CPU use
and logs that were collected
from consented user devices.
This provides
a more detailed look
into what was happening
in my app.
I can get all of this data
by querying the App Store
Connect API as well
and running my own analysis
on the JSON payload
that is returned
with my requested data.
All of these tools will make it
easy for me to catch and resolve
a lot of the battery usage
regressions in my app.
To learn more about
battery life optimizations,
check out the "Improving Battery
Life and Performance" talk
from 2019, and to learn more
about using Instruments,
check out
the "Analyze HTTP Traffic
in Instruments" talk this year.
Our next stop is
Hang Rate and Scrolling,
two metrics that convey
that my app wasn't responsive.
A hang is when
the app is unresponsive
to user input or actions
for at least 250 milliseconds.
Hangs in the app
can lead customers
to force quit the application
from the app switcher
and are a major impediment
to the user's experience
in your app
and should be prioritized.
Stuttering scrolls occur
when new content isn't ready
for the next screen refresh.
These will lead to an
unenjoyable user experience
and overall frustration,
resulting in users spending
less time in your app.
As an app developer,
the goal is to maximize
the amount of user engagement,
so this is a great place
to start optimizing.
Remember that smooth scroll
we showed you earlier?
Aiming for this is in
the best interest of your users.
I can track hangs
and my scrolling metrics
in the Xcode Organizer
by navigating
to their respective views.
A sign that I need
to pay close attention
to what my app is doing
is if I notice
either of the charts
trending upwards
or, in the case of scrolling,
if I notice that the graph is
showing more yellow and red bars
instead of green ones,
like in this graph here.
According to the key
to the right of the chart,
the red bar is indicative
of the poor scroll experience
we saw in the video earlier
and should be fixed immediately.
This data is now also available
through the App Store
Connect API.
I can use Instruments
to detect the cause of my hangs
by using the Thread State
or System Call Traces.
The Thread State Trace
instrument shows a timeline
of the thread's state
and when the OS
has scheduled the thread to run.
I can see how long
a thread was blocked for
in the details section.
The System Call Trace
shows a narrative
that details
the system calls entered
and how long they took.
To verify that I'm not
releasing app versions
with bugs that will affect
my users' scroll experience,
I can write a performance test
with XCTest
that launches and scrolls
through my app.
In this test,
I'm specifying that I want
to measure the
scrollDeceleration submetric,
and in the body
of the measure block,
I'm swiping up
with the scroll velocity
I expect in my app.
Since this measure block
runs five times by default,
I'll reset the application state
between runs
by using the XCTMeasureOptions.
I can pass this
into my measure block,
stop measuring,
and then reset
my application state.
Sometimes, reproducing
responsiveness issues
in forced test cases
may not be easy.
Luckily, MetricKit,
when deployed in my
production application,
can allow me
to collect telemetry
and diagnostics for these issues
at the time they occur.
In the case of hangs, in iOS 14,
MetricKit would deliver
these diagnostics to me
at a 24-hour cadence.
New in iOS 15 and macOS 12,
I will now receive all
diagnostics, including hangs,
in my app immediately
after an issue occurs.
Using these instant diagnostics
in conjunction
with my own telemetry,
I can quickly root cause
and resolve the most pressing
responsiveness problems.
In the case of scroll hitches,
iOS 15 introduces a new API
within MetricKit
to tag custom animations
using MXSignpost.
MXSignpost is a wrapper API
shipped with MetricKit
that allows me to mark
critical code sections
for telemetry.
Using the MXSignpostAnimation-
IntervalBegin API,
I'll be able
to strategically mark
the beginning
of custom animations.
Using the MXSignpost end API,
I can mark the end
of the animation
and collect hitch-rate telemetry
during that interval.
These two functions
will not only capture
granular performance data
for this interval,
but will also capture
any hitches that occur.
To learn more about how
to understand
and eliminate hangs,
I recommend checking out
the "Understand and Eliminate
Hangs from your App" talk
this year.
For in-depth details
on how to identify
scroll hitch issues,
I recommend checking out
the "Eliminate Hitches
Using XCTest" talk
and the "Explore UI Animation
Hitches and the Render Loop"
tech talks from 2020.
We're approaching
the halfway mark now
as we now move on
to discussing Disk Writes.
Writing to disk can wear out
my users' NAND,
which will lead
to poor device health.
Writes also take a lot of time
and can lead
to poor user experience
and slow performance
if done frequently,
so it's important
to batch these writes.
Before releasing my app version,
I can profile my app
using the File Activity template
in Instruments.
This records file system use
in the form of system calls,
so I can easily identify
places in my app's code
where I'm accessing
the file system.
There are many ways
to be good citizens
of the system
and limit writing to disk.
Some common ones are
batching your write operations,
using Core Data
for frequently-changing data,
and avoiding rapid file
creation and deletion.
In addition to profiling my app,
I can also write
performance tests with XCTest
to measure the disk usage
of my app
to prevent code
with excessive Disk Writes
from running on user devices.
This is as simple
as passing an instance
of XCTStorageMetric
to the measureWithMetric API
and then invoking the code
that writes to disk.
The test measures
the amount of data
written to disk
by the code in the block
and shows me the result
within Xcode itself.
I can set a baseline
of the amount of data
I expect to be written to disk
so that the test fails if the
code in the block exceeds that.
This will help me ensure
that I'm not putting out
any buggy code.
If I've already released
a version of my app
with high Disk Writes,
I can use the Organizer
to track its performance
on user devices.
The Disk Writes metric
shows me the trend
of how many writes the current
version of my app is doing
compared to the previously
released versions.
Spikes in the graph can
indicate that my app has bugs
that are causing
a high amount of writes.
I should identify
the top sources of these writes,
understand them,
and look for ways reduce them.
I can look for the sources
of these writes
by taking a look
at the Disk Writes Reports.
These are a collection
of exception reports
that are generated when my app
writes more than 1 GB
in a 24-hour period.
The stack trace shows me
where in my code
I was doing excessive writes,
and, new in Xcode 13,
I can also get additional
details called Insights,
which point me
to some easy optimizations
I can make to be
a good citizen of the system
and reduce some
of the writes in my app.
All of this data
is now also available to me
through the App Store
Connect API.
I can also obtain
these reports in MetricKit
at the time they occur
in my application.
If I'm using MetricKit
to monitor my app's disk usage,
I can book-end
critical Disk Write paths
with MXSignpost intervals
to collect
more granular telemetry,
which can help me discover
opportunities for optimization.
To learn more about how
to seamlessly identify
and resolve Disk Write issues,
be sure to tune in
to the "Diagnose Power
and Performance Regressions
in your App" talk this year.
As we approach the next stop,
we'll be discussing
launch time and terminations.
Launch time
is the amount of time
between when the user
taps your app icon
and when the first frame
gets rendered in your app.
If your user spends a long time
waiting for your app to launch,
that can lead to unintentional
frustration for the user,
and extended launch times
can lead to the system
terminating your app.
When the system
terminates your app,
your user will experience
the entire launch flow
from the beginning,
which takes much longer
than resuming
from a background running state.
Process exits can happen
for many different reasons,
like hitting and exceeding
the system memory limit
or timing out on launch.
Every time your app terminates
for one of these reasons,
it goes through
the full launch flow
the next time your user
taps your app icon,
and that not only
takes a long time,
but is also
a frustrating experience,
especially if it's
happening frequently.
If you're not restoring state,
this can also add
to the frustration of a user
having to find their place again
or recreate lost work.
I just released
a new version of my app
with a feature
that allows my users
to add pictures and detailed
recipes for their meals.
Let's see what the launch time
for my app looks like
with this new feature
and what it looked like before.
This is what the user will see
when they try to launch
my app now that it has
the new feature in it.
Notice how much time
was spent attempting
to render the first frame?
My app was suspended
before we even had
a chance to use it.
In comparison, here's what
the launch looked like
before that feature was added.
It's almost like my app
anticipated a launch
and had the first frame
ready to display.
From these two examples,
I already know that the first
incredibly slow launch
is not what I want
my users to remember
when they think of my app.
So I'll need to fix this
as soon as possible.
Since the launch issue
is already in a version
of my app that users are using,
I can start by going
to the Organizer
and taking a look
at the Launch Time
and new Terminations panes.
Looking at launch times
will give me an idea
of what the average "time
to first frame" of my app is
over the last 16 versions,
so I can see how fast it was
before my new feature was added.
I can also go
to the Terminations pane
to see how frequently
my app is being terminated
by the system because of
how long it's taking to launch.
After looking at the Organizer,
it actually looks like this is
a pretty bad bug that was
introduced with my new feature,
and it's hitting
a lot of my users.
Let's take a look at how
I can go about fixing this.
I can test this issue at my desk
by using the App Launch template
in Instruments
to profile my app's launch time.
This template runs my app
for five seconds,
during which it gathers
a time profile
and Thread State Trace
of what was going on
while the app was launching,
so I can figure out
why the threads were blocked
and fix that.
I can also measure launch times
in a performance XCTest
by using
the XCTApplicationsLaunchMetric
in a measure block similar
to what we saw earlier.
If I want to do
my own analytics,
with MetricKit implemented
in my app,
I'll receive
termination telemetry
as part of the daily
metric payload by default.
For more information
on state restoration
to avoid data loss
when your app is terminated,
check out the "Why is my App
Getting Killed?" talk
from 2020.
Yay, we've done it.
We're at our final stop
before we wrap up our journey.
Our final stop is Memory.
Memory is a shared resource
between apps, the OS,
and kernel.
If your app exceeds
the memory limit,
it will be terminated
by the system,
and the next time
the user goes to launch it,
it'll launch from the beginning,
which takes much longer
than resuming from
a background running state.
The new feature in my app
allows developers
to add pictures and descriptions
to their meals,
which means that
there's a chance
that the memory use
gets a little high.
If this happens,
there's a chance
that my app can get terminated
for exceeding the memory limit,
so I should keep an eye
on the Memory
and Terminations metrics
in the Organizer
to make sure
that isn't the case.
It looks like
it's not being terminated,
but there's a large spike
in memory use
in this new version of my app,
according to the peak memory
and memory at suspension
charts in the Organizer.
I can profile
the memory use of my app
by using the Leaks, Allocations,
and VM Tracker templates
in Instruments.
Leaks will examine
my process's heap
and check for leaked memory.
Allocations will analyze
the memory life cycle of my app.
And VM Tracker will show
the virtual memory space
of my app over time.
I can also use MetricKit
to get the same information
and run my own analysis on it.
In addition to using
my daily metric payloads
that contain termination
and memory telemetry,
I can also
instrument MXSignposts
around critical code sections
to capture more granular
telemetry about memory usage.
To learn more about detecting
and understanding
how to resolve
memory regressions
before they make it into
your application, check out
the "Detect and Diagnose
Memory Issues" talk this year.
Before I send you on your way,
let's wrap up
what we've seen here today
and go over some next steps.
We understand
how challenging it can be
to identify
performance optimizations.
Over the last few years,
developers have used
these same tools
that we provide to you
to make significant
performance optimizations.
A great example is Snapchat,
an app that millions
of people use every day.
Snapchat has
a long-standing dedication
to improving the launch
experience of their app
and driving down terminations.
In the last year,
we've seen a 99% reduction
in undesirable terminations
for Snapchat.
We think that's incredible,
and using the performance tools
and data we've
discussed here today,
you can accomplish this too.
If you're new
to performance tools,
I recommend taking
a moment to check out
the "Diagnose Performance Issues
with the Xcode Organizer"
and "What's New in MetricKit"
talks from 2020,
as well as the "Identify Trends
with the Power
and Performance API" talk
from 2020
and the "Getting Started
with Instruments" talk
from 2019.
After digging into all
of these metrics and tools,
we're hoping that
you're well equipped
with the resources you'll need
to ship the most performant apps
in the App Store.
Your users will
thank you for this
as they enjoy
a seamless user experience.
There was a lot
of material covered here,
so as a fun exercise,
I recommend
you use the Xcode Organizer
to see trending data
on your app's performance.
Explore and play
with the different templates
offered in Instruments.
Challenge yourself
to write XCTests
to catch issues
before they're released.
And broaden the scope of your
analytics with MetricKit.
There's so much
our tools have to offer
when it comes to optimizing
for performance,
so don't hesitate
to get your hands dirty
and explore all
that comes with them.
Thank you for joining me
on today's journey,
and I hope you have a wonderful
time at this year's conference.
[upbeat music]