[music]
[Egor] Hi! My name is Egor,
and today, I’d like to tell you
about all the improvements
and new features
in Metal Debugger.
This year,
we are bringing support
for more Metal features,
such as ray tracing
and function pointers.
We have added brand-new
profiling workflows,
like the GPU timeline
and consistent
GPU performance state,
to help you get the most out
of GPUs across Apple platforms.
We’ve made improvements
to other debugging workflows
you know and love,
including broader support
for shader validation,
and precise capture controls.
We are also introducing
advances in texture compression,
which my colleague
Amanda will talk about later.
First,
let’s talk about ray tracing.
Last year, we introduced
a new Metal ray tracing API,
and now, in Xcode 13,
we support it in Metal Debugger,
along with function pointers
and function tables,
which bring flexibility
to your shaders.
And dynamic libraries,
which give you a way to build
well-abstracted and reusable
shader library code.
Also, for ray tracing, we are
introducing
a brand-new tool,
the Acceleration
Structure Viewer.
Take a look at ray tracing
in the Metal Debugger.
I’ve opened a GPU trace
of the ModernRenderer
sample app.
It was modified
to use the Metal ray tracing
to achieve effects such as
shadows and ambient occlusion.
This encoder creates a beautiful
ray traced shadow map.
I’ve selected a dispatch call
so that you can see
the acceleration structure
in bound resources.
From here,
I will open the acceleration
structure
to go to our new
acceleration structure viewer.
Here, you can see the geometry
of the familiar bistro scene
on the right,
and its outline on the left.
Clicking on an instance
in the scene
will select it in the viewer
and also in the scene outline.
You can see the transformation
matrix
and other instance properties
by expanding it.
You can also select
an individual geometry
by holding the Option key
while clicking
in the scene viewer.
This will also select it
in the scene outline,
and vice versa.
You can also see the relevant
intersection functions
used with
the acceleration structure
right here in the viewer.
But the Acceleration
Structure Viewer
can do much more
than simply display geometry.
Here on the bottom-right,
you will also find
a number of highlighting modes
that will help you visualize
some of the properties
of your scene.
For example,
the bounding volume
traversals mode
can help you visualize
the complexity of your geometry.
A deeper blue color shows areas
where the bounding
volume hierarchy
is more computationally
expensive to traverse
relative to other parts of it.
For all of the modes,
we have this small view
that shows
the relevant information
when you hover over
different parts of your scene.
Here, it displays the number
of bounding box traversals
and primitive intersections.
To give you more flexibility,
we also included
traversal settings.
With them, you can configure
the acceleration
structure viewer,
using same properties
you can find
on an intersector object
inside your shaders.
There’s so much more
to talk about
when it comes to ray tracing.
If you’d like to learn more,
check this year’s session
“Explore hybrid rendering
with Metal ray tracing.”
And if you want to know more
about the API in general,
check out last year’s talk,
“Discover ray tracing
with Metal.”
Next,
let’s talk about profiling.
Profiling your app
is an important step,
and we already have a lot
of great tools at your disposal.
For example,
using the Metal system
trace in instruments,
you can explore a timeline view
that shows CPU and GPU durations
for different rendering stages,
GPU counters,
and shader timelines.
And in the Metal Debugger,
GPU counters show a rich set of
measurements
directly from the GPU,
either per encoder or per draw.
Both are excellent tools,
which provide complementary
views of your app’s performance.
But aligning those views
may take additional effort.
So, that’s why
I’m excited to show you
a new GPU profiling tool
that combines Metal system trace
and GPU counters
in a unified experience.
Introducing GPU Timeline
in Metal Debugger,
a new tool designed
specifically for Apple GPUs.
It gives you
a different perspective
on the performance data,
and it can help you find
potential points of optimization
in your app.
Let’s walk through
this latest addition
to our suite of profiling tools.
The GPU Timeline is available
under the Performance panel.
You can find it
in the debug navigator
after you’ve captured
a frame from your app.
When you open
the Performance panel,
you’ll be greeted
by a set of different tracks
laid out in parallel.
Before we continue,
I want to explain
why encoder tracks
are in parallel.
On Apple GPUs,
vertex and fragment stages
of different render passes,
and also compute dispatches,
can run simultaneously.
This is enabled
by Apple GPU architecture
and use of rendering technique
called “tile-based
deferred rendering.”
We thought it is important
for you to be able to see this
parallel nature of Apple GPUs
in the context of your app.
And that’s where GPU Timeline
comes in handy.
At the top, you can see
the Vertex, Fragment,
and Compute encoder timelines,
with each encoder
showing the resources it uses
at a quick glance.
Below the encoders,
you will find Occupancy,
Bandwidth, and limiter counters.
Let’s take a closer look
at the encoder timeline.
You can expand
each encoder track
to see an aggregated
shader timeline.
Expanding the timeline
even further
will show you
each individual shader
in a waterfall-like fashion.
It’s easy to navigate
the encoders.
Select an encoder track
to see a list of all
the encoders on the right.
There, you can sort them
by their average duration.
Clicking on an individual
encoder in the timeline
will show you more information
about it in the sidebar.
For example, here you can see
the attachments
for this render command encoder.
You may have noticed
that when you select an encoder,
time ranges where it’s active
become highlighted
across all the tracks.
With this,
you can easily examine
how different stages overlap,
and also correlate
counter values for the encoder.
Moving away
from the timeline view,
you can access the GPU counters
by switching
to the Counters tab,
or you can just open encoder’s
context menu
and reveal it
in Counters from there.
And this is just a sneak
peek at the GPU Timeline.
To learn more
about using Metal Debugger
to understand
your app’s performance,
check out this year’s session
“Optimize high-end games
for Apple GPUs.”
Now that I’ve showed you
a new way to profile your app,
it’s important to understand
that its performance
depends on several factors.
When we are talking about Metal,
the GPU performance state
is a very important factor.
It’s managed
by the operating system,
which will lower
or raise the state
depending on device thermals,
system settings,
GPU utilization,
and other parameters.
These state changes can affect
profiling results
you are seeing.
This year,
we are introducing new ways
for you to profile your app
with more consistent results.
We have added ways
for you to see and change
the GPU performance state
across our whole suite
of Metal tools,
starting with Instruments
and Metal system trace
for live performance recordings,
continuing with Metal Debugger,
for profiling GPU traces,
and finally,
Device conditions in Xcode,
for general use cases.
First,
let’s talk about Instruments.
This year, we’ve added a track
for GPU performance state
to the Metal system trace.
Use it in conjunction
with the other tracks
to correlate
your app’s performance
with the device’s
performance state.
Keep in mind, though,
that being able to see
the performance state
is just part of the equation.
In order to get
profiling results
that are consistent
and reproducible,
you also need a way to set
a GPU performance state
on a device.
New this year is the ability
to induce a specific GPU
performance state
when you are recording
a trace in Instruments.
Simply go to Recording Options,
and choose a performance state
before the recording starts.
After that, you can record
the performance trace as usual.
Instruments will induce
the state you chose
for the duration of the trace,
if the device can sustain it.
Sometimes,
you might need to check
if an existing Instruments trace
had a GPU performance state
induced during recording.
You can find this information
in the “Recording Settings”
section
in the information popover.
And now, you know how to view
and induce the GPU performance
state from Instruments.
The second way to leverage
a consistent
GPU performance state
is by using Metal Debugger.
By default, when you capture
a GPU trace of your app,
Xcode will profile
the trace for you.
And it will do so using
the same performance state
the device was in
at the time of the capture.
That state may have fluctuated,
depending on the factors
we mentioned previously.
If, instead,
you would like to select
a certain performance state
yourself,
use the Stopwatch button
in the debug bar.
After you make a selection,
Metal Debugger will profile
your GPU trace again.
After it’s done,
the button is highlighted
to reflect that the consistent
performance state was achieved.
Also, “Performance”
section on the summary page
now shows new
performance data at a glance,
as well as the selected
performance state.
These two approaches are tied
to the suite of Metal tools.
But sometimes,
you might want to induce
a consistent performance state
outside of profiling workflows.
The third way to set
a GPU performance state
is through Device conditions.
If you want to test
how your app performs
under different
GPU performance states,
this is the option for you.
In Xcode 13, we have added
the GPU performance state
device condition.
It forces the operating system
to use the specified state on a
device,
as long as it can sustain it
and it stays connected
to the Xcode.
You can add this condition
from Xcode,
if you go to Window,
Devices and Simulators,
choose your device there,
then scroll to
the “Device Conditions” section,
and add
a “GPU Performance State”
condition
with the desired level.
Press Start
when you want to apply
the GPU performance state change
on the device.
Then, when you are done,
press Stop.
These new ways to see
and change GPU performance state
right from our tools
should help you with profiling
and testing your apps.
And I think
you are going to love
our latest additions
and improvements
to profiling workflows,
and I hope they will help you
make your apps even better.
Now, let’s talk about
some other improvements
we are bringing
to Metal Debugger this year.
First, I’ll tell you about
improvements
to shader validation.
Then, I’ll show you
precise capture controls.
And after that,
I’ll give you a look
at the new
pipeline state workflows.
Finally, I want to introduce
two new features
related to shader debugging
and profiling,
separate debug information
and selective shader debugging.
Last year, in Xcode 12,
we introduced shader validation,
which helps you diagnose
runtime errors on the GPU,
like out of bounds access,
and others.
Remember that if shader
validation is enabled,
and an encoder raises
a validation error,
you will get a runtime issue
in the issue navigator,
showing both
the CPU and GPU backtraces
for the call that faulted.
We already have a session that
covers this in a greater detail,
so to learn more about using
shader validation,
check out
last year’s talk, called
“Debugging GPU-side
errors in Metal.”
This year, we are extending
shader validation
to support more use cases,
making it available
when you are using
indirect command buffers,
dynamic libraries,
and function pointers
and tables.
This should allow you
to use shader validation
more extensively
throughout your app
during its development.
Next, I wanna show you
our new precise
capture controls.
But first, take a look
at the Capture button,
which now
looks like the Metal logo.
It’s located on the debug bar,
at the bottom
of the Xcode window.
When you click it,
a new menu appears.
This menu lets you choose
a scope for your capture.
The default
is to capture one frame,
but you can specify
how many you want to capture,
up to five.
You can also choose to capture
a number of command buffers
that have
the same parent device,
or a command queue,
as well as those that present
a certain Metal layer,
and even custom scopes
that you can define
in your app’s code
using MTLCaptureScope API.
These new controls
give you incredible power
out-of-the-box in deciding
how and when
your Metal calls are captured.
Next, let’s talk about Metal
libraries and pipeline states.
These are the essential building
blocks of your Metal app.
And in Xcode 13,
we’ve made it easier than ever
to examine all the
pipeline states and libraries
your app is using.
Now, let’s see
how it looks in practice.
Here, I’ve captured a GPU trace
from a ModernRenderer
sample app.
I wanted to see how the
GBuffer pipeline state works,
so I selected this draw call.
If I look in bound resources,
I can now see the pipeline state
which was used.
Opening it takes me to
the Pipeline State Viewer.
From here,
I can examine the functions
and see other properties the
pipeline state was created with.
Further, from the viewer,
I can either check out
the performance data
associated with the state,
or I can go to Memory Viewer
and reveal the state there.
In Xcode 13,
Memory Viewer now shows
how much memory
the pipeline states
are taking up in your app.
These are just
some of the additions
that make it easier to inspect
pipeline states
across the Metal Debugger
when you’re looking
at GPU traces of your app.
Next, let’s talk about
shader debugging and profiling
in Metal Debugger.
Right now,
if you wanna use these features,
you have two choices.
First option
is compiling your libraries
from source code
when the app is running.
A second, better option
is building Metallib files
with sources embedded offline,
and then loading those
at runtime.
But then, App Store rules
don’t allow you
to publish your apps
with these debug Metallibs.
All of that means
that if you compile
your libraries offline
and you want to be able
to debug your shaders,
you have to compile them twice:
once with sources embedded,
for use during development,
and once without sources,
for distribution.
This year, we are changing that.
You can now generate
a separate file with sources
and other debugging information
while compiling a Metallib.
These files
have a Metallibsym extension,
and they allow you to debug
and profile shaders
without embedding
additional information
in the libraries themselves.
The most important benefit
of having them separately,
is that now you don’t need
to have two versions
of the same Metallib.
Another benefit is that
with these Metallibsym files,
you will now be able
to debug shaders
even in release versions
of your app,
without having to compromise
your shader sources.
I’ll show you an example
of how to compile
a shader source file
into a Metallib with
Metallibsym file alongside it.
I’ll start with xcrun terminal
command
that compiles a Metallib
as normal.
To generate a Metallibsym file,
I simply need to add the flag
“record-sources”
with the “flat” option,
and then run the compiler.
Now, when I try
to debug a shader
that was compiled
with a separate debug
information file,
I’ll be prompted to import it.
Clicking on Import Sources
opens up a dialog
that lists all the libraries
and whether they have
their source files imported.
From here, I can import
any Metallibsym files,
and once imported,
the libraries and their sources
will be matched automatically.
When I’m done importing,
I can close the dialog,
and now I can see the sources
for the shader and debug it.
There is one last debugging
improvement I wanna show you.
It’s called
“selective shader debugging.”
If your app uses large shaders,
you might have noticed
that the shader debugging
may take a while to start.
To help in such cases,
this year, we are bringing
selective shader debugging.
It helps you narrow down
the debugging scopes,
so you can debug
your shaders quicker.
Let’s see it in action
with one of such large shaders.
I would like to debug
this GPU ASTCDecoder.
I know that if I tried
to debug this whole kernel,
Shader Debugger
would take a long time to start.
I wouldn’t want
to wait that long,
so instead,
I can narrow down
the debugging scope
to just this function,
decodeIntegerSequence.
To do so, I can right-click it
and select Debug Functions.
This opens
“functions to debug” menu,
with the function scope
already selected.
Now, the debugger
will start almost instantly.
Selective shader debugging
is a great way to pinpoint bugs
in huge shaders quickly.
These are all the Metal tools
improvements
I wanted to show you today.
And now, Amanda will tell you
about advances we’ve made
in texture compression.
Amanda?
[Amanda] Thanks, Egor.
I’m going to walk you through
the updates we’ve made this year
to texture compression tools.
Before I dive into the tools,
I’m going to briefly discuss
the basics of texture
compression on Apple platforms.
Texture compression,
in this case,
is fixed-rate, lossy compression
of texture data.
This is primarily intended
for offline compression
of static texture data,
such as decals or normal maps.
While you can compress
dynamic texture data at runtime,
that’s not something
I’m covering today.
Most texture compression
works by splitting a texture
into blocks
and compressing each block
as a pair of colors.
This pair defines
a localized palette,
including other colors
interpolated
from these endpoints,
and a per-pixel index
that selects from this palette.
Each format
has different strengths
that suit different kinds
of texture data.
Apple GPUs also support
lossless frame-buffer
compression
starting in our A12 devices,
and is great
for optimizing bandwidth.
Check out last year’s session
“Optimize Metal apps and games
with GPU counters”
to learn more about measuring
the memory bandwidth
the GPU is using for your app.
Another option is to perform
lossless compression
of texture files
on top of the GPU texture
compression
I’m covering
in this presentation.
This can give you additional
reductions
in the size
of your app download.
Now that I’ve defined
texture compression
for this talk,
I’ll talk about the benefits
texture compression
can bring to your app.
Texture compression
is an important step
in the development of your apps.
In general,
most of the memory footprint of
games
consists of textures.
Using texture compression
allows you to load more textures
into memory,
and use more detailed textures
to create more
visually compelling games.
Compression may also allow you
to reduce the size and memory
footprint of your app.
Now that I’ve covered
the basics,
I’ll discuss the current state
of texture compression tools
on Apple platforms.
The existing TextureTool
in the iOS SDK
has a relatively
simple pipeline.
TextureTool
reads the input image,
generates mipmaps if desired,
compresses the texture,
block by block,
then writes the results
to a new output file.
But as graphics algorithms
increase in complexity,
textures need more
advanced processing.
The core of these processes
is performing operations
in the correct color space,
while minimizing rounding from
transformations
between numeric precisions.
Understanding this,
we’ve designed a new compression
tool
called TextureConverter
to handle the necessary increase
in texture processing
sophistication,
and give you access
to a host of new options.
Let’s take a closer look
at how we’ve revamped
the texture processing pipeline
on Apple platforms.
The texture processing pipeline
has been rebuilt
from the ground up to give you
access
to a fully-featured
texture processing pipeline
with TextureConverter.
TextureConverter leverages
a set of industry-recognized
compressors
to support a wide range of
compression formats,
and give you the option to
tradeoff
between compression speed
and image quality.
You can specify
which compressor to use,
or allow TextureConverter
to select
based on the compression format,
quality level,
and other options.
Each stage is now
fully configurable by you,
and texture processing
is gamma-aware.
To support integration
into all your content pipelines,
TextureConverter is available
for both macOS and Windows,
and is optimized for use
with Apple Silicon.
Let’s step through each stage of
the expanded pipeline,
starting with gamma.
Gamma correction
is a nonlinear operation
to encode and decode
luminance in images.
Textures can be encoded
in many gamma spaces.
The best choice is dependent
on the type of data
that the texture represents.
Most visual data,
such as decals or light maps,
do best when encoded
in a non-linear space,
like sRGB.
Non-visual data,
like normal maps,
should be encoded
in linear space.
This choice gives you
more accuracy
in the dark areas
where it’s needed.
Non-visual data,
like normal maps,
should be encoded
in linear space.
Compression should be performed
in your target color space,
specified with the “gamma_in”
and “gamma_out” options.
You can either
input a float value
for linear gamma space,
or use the string “sRGB”
to specify that color space.
You also have the flexibility
to use these options
to convert to a different
target space.
Other operations,
such as mipmap generation,
should be performed
in linear space.
I’ll walk through the linear
space processing stages now.
Now that the input has been
converted to linear gamma space,
the linear space operations are
performed
before the input texture
is converted
to the specified target
gamma space.
The three stages
are physical transforms,
mipmap generation,
and alpha handling,
and some of these
have substages.
I’ll start
with physical transforms.
By defining
the maximum size in any axis,
you can downscale your image
as you need
for your top-level mipmap.
In this stage,
you also have control
over the resize filter
and resize rounding mode.
The resize filter options use
different algorithms
to help you reduce blurriness
of your mipmaps
as they go down
in dimension size.
Resize round mode
is used in conjunction
with max_extent
when resizing your image.
If max_extent is exceeded,
the source image is resized
by maintaining
the original image’s aspect.
The specified round mode
will be used when finding the
target dimensions.
If you’re unsure which resize
filter or rounding mode to use,
we’ve picked defaults
that work well in most cases.
And the flip options
in this stage
give you control over
linear transformations
on the X, Y, and Z axes.
After transforms
is mipmap generation,
used in the majority of common
texture processing situations.
Mipmaps are a precalculated
sequences of images
that reduce in resolution
over the sequence,
used to increase rendering speed
and reduce aliasing.
The height and width
of each level
is a power of two smaller
than the previous level.
When customizing
mipmap generation,
specify the maximum number
you want,
and which mip filter to use.
TextureConverter
defaults to Kaiser filtering,
with options for “box”
and “triangle” filtering.
The last stage in linear space
processing is alpha handling.
If alpha to coverage is enabled,
this is applied first,
using the specified
alpha reference value.
Alpha to coverage
replaces alpha blending
with a coverage mask.
When antialiasing
or semitransparent textures
are used
this gives you order-independent
transparency,
and is
a particularly useful tool
for rendering dense greenery
in your game.
Afterwards,
the option to discard,
preserve, or premultiply
the alpha channel is presented.
In premultiplied alpha,
partly transparent pixels
of your image
will be premultiplied
with a matting color.
At the end of the linear
space processing stages,
we’re ready to move back
to the target gamma space
and compress
the processed mip levels.
The last step in texture
processing is the compression.
The compression stage
can be divided
into two substages,
channel mapping and encoding.
Channel mapping is a technique
to optimize general purpose
texture compression algorithms
for particular data types.
Specifying a channel mapping
in TextureConverter is optional.
If you do want to use it,
TextureConverter
currently supports
two modes of channel mapping,
RGBM encoding
and normal map encoding.
I’m going to cover both of these
formats in more depth,
starting with RGBM encoding.
RGBM encoding is a technique
to compress HDR data
in LDR formats
by storing a multiplier
in the alpha channel
and scaling the RGB channels
by this multiplier.
Here’s an example
HDR image of a classroom.
And here’s the same classroom
image again
with the multiplier stored
in the alpha channel
visible in grayscale.
I’ll show you how to calculate
the multiplier
to encode to RGBM
with a code example.
EncodeRGBM is a simplified
pseudocode function
that I’ll walk you through
to help you understand
the mechanics
of encoding to RGBM.
This snippet includes
use of RGBM_Range,
the brand-new parameter
for setting the range
of RGBM and defaults to 6.0.
In order to calculate
the RGBM alpha value,
the multiplier,
first, I’ll determine
the maximum
of the input texture’s
red, green, and blue channels.
This is done
with Metal’s max3 function.
Then this maximum
is divided by RGBM_Range.
In order to calculate
the encoded RGBM’s
red, green, and blue channel
values,
first, the previously calculated
multiplier
is multiplied back
by RGBM_Range,
which was used
to scale the value
for storage
in the alpha channel.
Then, the input texture
is divided
by the final multiplier value.
To decode RGBM in your shader,
you multiply the sample’s RGB
by alpha and the fixed factor,
as I showed you
in the encoding function.
I’ll walk through the DecodeRGBM
code snippet
to show you how to do this.
The scaling factor
is recalculated
by multiplying
the RGBM alpha channel,
where the multiplier is stored,
by RGBM_Range.
The original texture’s RGB
is calculated by multiplying
the RGBM sample
by the calculated multiplier.
Now that I’ve introduced you
to RGBM encoding,
I’ll move on
to normal map encoding.
In most cases,
when referring to normal maps,
we’re specifically referring
to object-space normal maps.
When encoding our normals
in object-space,
we know that each normal
is a unit vector,
which has the benefit
that it can be represented
in two axes with the third axis
trivially derivable at runtime.
This allows us to remap
these two channels
to best take advantage
of texture compression
algorithms,
and achieve superior
compression quality
compared to compressing
XYZ as RGB.
How you remap channels varies
depending
on the compression format.
I’ll walk through an example
of encoding a normal with ASTC,
using this chart as a guide.
When encoding with ASTC,
the red, green,
and blue channels
are set to the X component,
and the alpha channel
is set to the Y component.
The colors correspond
to which channel
the X and Y components
will be reassigned back to
when sampling
the encoded normal.
TextureConverter takes care
of encoding remapping for you
by automatically remapping
to your chosen format
if you pass
the normal map parameter.
When sampling normal maps
in your shader,
it’s important to know
the channel mapping.
While the X component is read
from the red or alpha channel,
the Y component comes from
the alpha or green channel
depending on the compression
format.
Coming back to the ASTC example,
to sample a texture, the X
component
is sampled from the red channel,
and the Y component is sampled
from the alpha channel,
the reverse of how
the normal was encoded.
If you’re encoding
to multiple formats
to achieve the best possible
quality on any device,
then this mapping is something
that you’ll need to handle
at runtime.
I’ll walk through an example
of runtime normal sampling
using Metal texture swizzles.
Encoding to multiple formats
could lead to needing
multiple shader variants
if the different formats used
different channel mappings.
To avoid this,
Metal allows you to apply
custom swizzles to your texture.
Swizzles allow you
to remap X and Y components
to red and green channels
so your shaders can be
compression format neutral.
Here’s an example
of remapping channels
to red and green
for a normal map
compressed with ASTC,
as we saw
in the diagram previously.
After the texture descriptor
is initialized,
the red channel is set
to MTLTextureSwizzleRed,
and the green channel is set
to MTLTextureSwizzleAlpha.
Since this is a normal map,
only two channels
are needed for sampling.
Since the red and green channels
are now assigned
to the X and Y components
originally encoded
to the red and alpha channels,
the blue and alpha channels
are set to zero.
Once that’s done,
the last line is to assemble
the final swizzle
with the remapped channels
using
MTLTextureSwizzleChannelsMake.
Once the X and Y channels
are sampled in your shader,
you can reconstruct
the Z component.
I’ll walk you through
the ReconstructNormal function
to show you how.
First, the code rebiases
the X and Y components
into the correct range,
which is negative one to one
for a normal.
The next step is to subtract
the dot product
of the X and Y components
from one,
to ensure the result of the
dot product has the right sign.
The saturate function
is then used to clamp this
result
within the range of zero to one.
The last step to calculate
the Z component
is to take the square root
of the output
of the saturate function.
Now that I’ve explained
RGBM and normal map
encoding options
available for channel mapping,
I’ll finish the discussion
of the texture compression
pipeline
with the final
compression substate,
encoding.
All TextureConverter
command lines
require specification
of the target compression format
with the compression_format
argument.
You can also specify
which compressor to use
or let TextureConverter make the
selection
based on the compression format
and other options
you’ve selected.
You may also select
the compression quality
from these four options.
Note that there’s a tradeoff
between compression speed
and image quality,
and you may wish to select
a lower compression quality
while iterating on your game,
but use the highest quality
for released builds.
Now, I’ll cover the texture
compression formats
available for you to select.
Here’s an overview
of the texture compression
format families
supported on Apple platforms.
iOS and Apple Silicon platforms
support ASTC and PVRTC families,
and all macOS platforms
support BCn families.
I’ll go over each of these
format families in more detail,
and give you some guidelines to
help you choose
the best ones for your needs.
I’ll start with BCn formats.
BCn is a set of seven formats
that all operate using
four-by-four blocks of pixels,
and either use four
or eight bits per pixel.
Each compression format is ideal
for a different data format.
BC1 and BC3 are commonly used
for RGB and RGBA compression,
BC6 is ideal for HDR images,
and BC5, with its dual
independent channels,
is ideal for normal
map encoding.
Next is ASTC,
a family of RGBA formats in LDR,
sRGB, and HDR color spaces.
The ASTC family of formats
allows for the highest quality
at all sizes,
and is therefore more generally
recommended over PVRTC.
There’s a range
of bits per pixel
versus quality for each format.
With ASTC,
the byte size of each block
is the same
regardless of the format,
while the number
of texels it represents varies.
This gives you a continuum
between the highest quality
compression
but lowest compression rate
at the four-by-four block size
versus the lowest compression
quality
but highest compression rate
at the 12-by-12 block size.
The LDR, sRGB, and HDR variants
describe the color range
for compressed ASTC textures.
LDR and sRGB are both
in the zero-to-one range,
in either linear or sRGB space,
while the HDR variant
is for data outside
of the zero-to-one range.
Lastly,
PVRTC formats are available
in RGB and RGBA
in 2-bit or 4-bit mode.
A data block in this format
always occupies eight bytes,
so in 2-bit mode
there’ll be one block
for every eight-by-four pixels,
and in 4-bit mode,
there’s one block
for each four-by-four pixel.
Now that I’ve introduced
the supported format families,
I’m going to give some
recommendations
for choosing formats
for your app.
On iOS devices,
you should always be using
ASTC compression by default,
with the addition
of PVRTC compression
and per-device thinning
only if you’re supporting
A7 GPUs and earlier.
If you have any HDR textures,
you can take advantage of
ASTC HDR on A13 and later GPUs.
For macOS, BCn is available
across the board.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
you also have the option
of using ASTC,
and you should consider this
option
if you’re also targeting
iOS devices.
While PVRTC is available
on Apple Silicon,
we don’t recommend this option,
and it’s intended
only for iOS legacy support.
Since there are a lot
of different formats
within each compression
format family to choose between,
the guideline for selecting
the most effective
texture compression
formats for your app
is to select per-texture
and per-target when possible.
Unless all of your textures
are RGB or RGBA data,
you should select
the compression format
based on the type of data
you’re compressing,
like choosing a format
that allows compression
as two independent
channels for normal data.
When compressing
to an ASTC format,
you may want to select
a subset of the formats.
Consider bucketing textures
by those that require the
highest quality
versus those that are acceptable
at higher compression rates.
Now, let’s review
what we’ve covered.
We’ve completely remade
the texture processing pipeline
from TextureTool
to give you complete control
over every stage of the pipeline
with our new
TextureConverter tool.
I’ve walked through each
stage of this new pipeline
and explored all of the options
available for you to use
at each stage,
and introduced you
to the channel mapping
and texture compression format
families
supported on Apple platforms.
We want to make it
as easy as possible
to update your workflows
from using TextureTool
to TextureConverter,
so we’ve added a compatibility
mode
to help you switch over
your command lines.
Whether using TextureTool
compatibility mode
or calling TextureConverter
with native options,
invoke with xcrun
TextureConverter.
Here’s an example command line
of TextureConverter
being called
with TextureTool options.
TextureConverter
will translate the options
to native
TextureConverter options,
do the compression,
and then tell you
what the new native options are,
so that you can update
your build scripts easily.
That was an introduction
to TextureConverter.
Here’s how to get it.
TextureConverter ships
as a part of Xcode 13
and is available to use
in seed 1.
On Windows,
TextureConverter ships
as a part of the Metal Developer
Tools for Windows 2.0 package,
available from
developer.apple.com.
Seed 1 is available now.
Be aware that in Windows,
there’s no support for
compressing to PVRTC formats,
as PVRTC is available in macOS
for supporting
legacy iOS platforms.
Another important part
of the Metal Developer Tools for
Windows
is the Metal Compiler
for Windows.
The Metal Compiler for Windows
was introduced last year,
with support for Metal Shading
Language version 2.3.
Updates throughout the year
mirrored the updates
to the Metal compiler
shipped in Xcode.
The latest
release version is 1.2,
which includes support
for Metal Shading Language
on Apple Silicon Macs.
Seed 1 of version 2.0
is now available
with support for all
of the great new features
in Metal Shading Language 2.4.
Here’s a summary of everything
we’ve covered today:
Egor discussed support
for more Metal features,
like ray tracing
and function pointers.
He introduced brand-new
profiling workflows,
like GPU Timeline and consistent
GPU performance state,
to help you get the most
out of the GPUs
across all Apple platforms.
And he demonstrated improvements
to debugging workflows
you’re already familiar with
to give you more support
for shader validation
and precise capture controls.
And I introduced you
to TextureConverter,
a new tool to help you take
full advantage
of the texture
processing pipeline
and all of the supported texture
compression formats
available on Apple platforms.
Thanks, and have a great
rest of WWDC 2021.
[music]