[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Ali de Jong:
Welcome to WWDC 2021.
My name is Ali de Jong,
and I'm a GPU software engineer
at Apple.
And today, along with
my colleague David Núñez Rubio,
we'll explore
hybrid rendering
with Metal ray tracing.
We'll start by showing you
some improvements
that ray tracing
can bring to your visuals;
then discuss how to incorporate
a ray tracing pass
into rasterization,
using a technique called
"hybrid rendering;"
then David will walk us through
the new tools
to help you implement
ray tracing.
Let's start by taking a look
at some great use cases
for ray tracing.
Games and movies
are in the constant pursuit
of ever-increasing realism,
and for many years,
the approach to graphics has
been by means of rasterization.
Rasterization is great
at producing beautiful images
at real-time rates.
However, there are limitations
to what we can achieve.
Ray tracing is a mechanism
that allows us to query
the world from shaders,
opening the door
to new, exciting techniques.
And by combining it
with rasterization,
we can greatly improve
our visuals.
Let's take a look
at a few examples.
One area that's always been
problematic for rasterization
is reflections.
This is because when we're
shading a rasterized pixel,
we have no context
of the rest of the scene
for accurate reflections
and we have to do extra work
to generate that information.
Ray tracing allows us
to trace array
from the pixel being shaded
and discover what's out there
in the world.
Even better, we can apply
this process recursively
to apply correct shadows
and even reflections
in reflections.
Another area where ray tracing
excels is shadows.
Notice with rasterization,
the shadows' general blurriness
and the aliasing caused
by a shadow map resolution
on the curved surfaces
of the moped.
Ray-traced shadows are sharper
and address aliasing issues
without the need
of artificial parameters
such as a shadow bias.
Soft shadows can also be
approximated more accurately.
We can naturally produce shadows
that are harder or softer,
depending on the proximity
of the occluding object
to the shaded point.
With rasterization,
we would need to rely
on filtering the shadow map
at sampling time.
But with ray tracing,
we can simply trace rays
in a cone to get this result.
Lastly, another area
where ray tracing can elevate
our visuals is transparency.
This is traditionally very hard
to handle accurately
for rasterization techniques.
In this image,
note how the sunlight
is coming through the window,
yet the opaque letters
on the glass produce no shadow.
Traditional shadow-mapping
techniques
often have problems
with transparent objects.
With ray tracing,
we can create a custom
intersection function
for transparent materials.
With this, we can define
which rays are able
to pass through the material
and which ones don't,
naturally producing
projected shadows
like the letters
on the head of the bust.
And of course, all the shadows
look sharper overall.
So why is it that ray tracing
is able to improve our visuals
so dramatically?
To understand this,
let's take a look
at how the traditional
rasterization process works.
In the rasterization process,
meshes are sent down to Metal
to be rendered.
They are placed in the world
and in front of the camera
by a vertex shader,
and those primitives
are placed onto pixels --
or fragments --
by the rasterizer.
These pixels are then shaded
by a fragment shader,
and the result is blended
onto the output image.
As you know, each pixel
can be shaded independently,
operating in parallel,
which is what makes GPUs so good
at the rasterization process.
The tradeoff, however,
is at the time
we're applying our shading,
we've completely lost
the context
of the rest of our scene
and we don't know what objects
might be surrounding
the point associated
with this pixel.
Advanced game engines
make up for this situation
by adding extra render passes
that generate
intermediate information.
The fragment shader can then
leverage that data
to approximate the details
of the geometric context
the point is in.
Let's take a look at how
this works in a bit more detail.
For this technique,
you rasterize geometric
information about the scene
to intermediate textures instead
of directly to the screen.
This can be things like albedo,
depth, or normals.
This is commonly referred to
as a Geometry Buffer pass
or G-Buffer pass for short.
The intermediate textures
are used as input
for light approximation passes
that use smart tricks
to approximate how the light
would interact with the objects
in the scene.
Some examples are
screen-space ambient occlusion
and screen-space reflection.
In the last step,
our intermediate attachments
are often denoised
or blurred slightly
to make for a smoother image,
and everything
is combined together
to produce the final image.
While these sometimes
elaborate techniques
can help improve the image,
they're still
just approximations.
On the other hand,
ray tracing takes
a completely different approach
that enables
more accurate visuals
and simplified
visual techniques.
Instead of processing meshes
one at a time,
in ray tracing, we build
an acceleration structure
that encompasses
the whole scene.
Once we have that,
we can have the GPU
trace rays from a point
toward a given direction
and find intersections.
This gives us access
to all the contextual
scene information.
Since ray tracing
models ray interactions,
it has applications
beyond rendering, too.
It can be used for audio
and physics simulation,
collision detection,
or AI and pathfinding.
Since ray tracing
is such a powerful technique,
we'd like to bring together
ray tracing and rasterization
to get the unique benefits
of each,
and we can do so
through a technique
called "hybrid rendering."
Now let's look at how to create
a hybrid rendered frame
and some use cases
for this technique.
If we start from
our rasterized frame diagram,
we can use ray tracing
to replace some or all
of our light approximation
passes.
We still rasterize
our G-Buffer --
it plays the role
of our primary rays --
and then we use ray tracing
to more realistically simulate
the properties of light
by querying
into the rest of the scene.
We still denoise and do
a light composition pass,
but our results are much more
accurate to the scene data.
This frame architecture
provides a good foundation
to explore a number
of hybrid rendering techniques.
Let's take a look at how we can
encode a frame like this
using Metal.
We start with filling out
our G-Buffer.
To do so,
we create a render pass
and fill out a G-Buffer
and set its textures
as the attachments for our pass.
We make sure our images
are stored to memory
so the rendered contents are
available to subsequent passes.
We start our pass,
encode our rendering,
and end the render pass.
Next, we'll add a ray-tracing
compute dispatch to this.
So after we create
the intermediate textures,
let's encode
our ray-tracing pass.
We create the compute pass
from the same command buffer
and make sure to set
the G-Buffer textures as inputs.
By default, Metal will track
write-read dependencies for you,
so you're free to focus
on your algorithm
without being too concerned
by synchronization.
Since this is compute,
we set our output textures
to write the results
of our ray-tracing work.
We set the PipelineState object
for our ray-tracing technique.
Each thread
in the compute shader
will calculate the ray-tracing
result for a pixel or region.
Finally, we dispatch our 2D grid
and end this pass.
After this pass is encoded,
we can now continue to encode
more work
such as
the light accumulation pass,
or we can submit
the command buffer now
so the GPU starts working on it
while we encode
the rest of the frame.
Since we encoded our work
in two passes,
this requires saving our
intermediate render attachments
to system memory for the passes
to communicate with each other.
This works, but on Apple Silicon
and iOS devices
there's an opportunity
to make this even better.
On Apple GPUs, the hardware
utilizes tile memory
to hold our pixel data
as we work on it.
At the end of the pass,
this tile memory is fleshed out
to system memory
and must be reloaded at
the beginning of the next pass.
Ideally, though, we would have
the compute passes
work directly on tile memory,
avoiding the round trips
to system memory.
I'm excited to share
this year we've added
the ability to do that
by dispatching ray-tracing work
from render pipelines.
This allows mixing render
and compute via tile shaders
in a single pass to leverage
on-tile memory for ray tracing.
This will reduce bandwidth use,
memory consumption,
and help your users' devices
run cooler.
Please make sure to review
our 2019 "Modern rendering
with Metal" session
to learn how to efficiently mix
render and compute,
so you can apply that
for ray tracing from render;
as well as this year's
"Enhance your app
with Metal ray-tracing" session
to learn about
other improvements
coming to Metal ray tracing
this year.
Now that we know how to encode
a hybrid rendering workload,
let's review some techniques
that can be improved
with ray tracing.
We'll focus on shadows,
ambient occlusion,
and reflections.
Let's start with shadows.
Shadows help convey
the proximity of objects
to each other within the scene.
This is a challenge
for rasterization, though,
because we lose the context
of the scene
at the time of shading.
Shadow mapping
can help supplement
this lack of information
but requires extra rendering
from each light's point of view.
This rasterization technique
starts by rendering the scene
from every light's perspective.
This produces a series
of depth maps
that need to be stored
alongside each light's
transformation matrix.
Then we render from
the main camera's perspective.
To shade each pixel,
we need to convert the point
to the light's coordinates.
We sample the depth coming
from the depth map
and ultimately compare
these depth values
to determine if we're in light
or shadow
for each light source.
There's a couple of drawbacks
with this technique.
First, we'll have
to render the scene
from the light's perspective
for each light.
This means processing the scene
multiple times.
Second, the shadow maps
have a predetermined resolution,
which means our shadows
will be subject to aliasing;
and worse,
we won't have information
for pixels that didn't fit
in the image.
Let's compare this
to ray-traced shadows.
To compute shadows
with ray tracing,
we can simply trace a ray
from a point
toward the direction
of the light source
and determine if any object
is blocking its path.
If we don't find anything,
that means the point
should take this light source
into consideration for shading.
In the case an object
is blocking the path,
we just exclude that
light source's contribution
in the lighting equation.
Notice how this produces
a natural shadow
corresponding to the silhouette
of the occluding object.
Even better, we're no longer
limited to the information
stored in a depth map.
We can determine shadows
for points outside the light's
frustum or camera's view.
Let's see how our shadow
technique is simplified
with ray tracing.
We start by rendering
from the main camera.
Next, we take
the acceleration structure
and the depth map rendered
from the camera's position
and feed it into
our ray-tracing kernel.
Calculate the pixel position,
and then we simply trace a ray
in the light's direction
From this, we determine if
the point is lit or in shadow,
depending on whether
an intersection was found
with an occluding object.
This process produces
a shadow texture
that we can then combine
with our render pass results
to get the final image.
Let's look at how to code
a Metal shader to do this.
In our shader code,
we start by calculating
the position
each thread will process from
the depth and the thread_id.
We create our shadow ray
from the calculated position
and set it up to trace
in the light's direction.
For most light types,
like point lights,
spotlights, and area lights,
we set the min and max to trace
all the way from the point
to the light source.
For directional shadows,
we may want to set
the max to infinity.
Additionally, if we decide
to implement cone ray tracing
for softer shadows,
this is a great place to add
jitter to our shadowRay.
We then create
an intersector object.
If we find any one intersection,
that means we're in shadow,
so we configure the intersector
to accept any intersection.
Finally, we intersect against
the acceleration structure.
Based on that
intersection result,
we write whether
the point is lit or not,
which creates a shadow texture
that's more accurate
to the scene.
When that shadow texture
is applied,
you can see we get
much more realistic shadows
and get rid of the aliasing.
With ray tracing,
determining shadows becomes
a very natural technique.
We just trace a ray
to find if something
occludes the light source
for that point or not.
There is no longer a need
to have intermediate depth maps,
and we can avoid having
multiple extra render passes
for each light.
This technique is easy
to implement into a deferred
or forward renderer,
as it only depends on depth.
And finally, it allows for
custom intersection functions
for translucent materials.
Next, let's take a look
at ambient occlusion.
Conceptually, a point surrounded
by geometry is less likely
to receive a large amount
of ambient light.
Ambient occlusion consists
in muting the ambient light
received at a point based
on how busy its neighborhood is,
which naturally
darkens crevices,
giving the final image
more depth.
Rasterization techniques
to achieve this
depend on sampling the depth
and normals
in the neighborhood
of the point,
to determine if there are
objects surrounding
and potentially occluding it.
Based on how many
nearby objects are found,
we calculate
an attenuation factor
to mute the ambient light
and create a texture
to apply to our image.
Relying on screen-space
information like depth buffer
and surface normals, however,
is missing information
for nonvisible occluders
and objects outside
the border of the image.
With ray tracing,
instead of relying
on screen-space information,
we can rely on actual
geometric data of our scene.
The idea is
for every pixel to shade,
we generate random rays
in a hemisphere
and search for intersections
against objects.
If any intersections are found,
we take it into consideration
for our ambient occlusion
factor.
We start again
with the acceleration structure.
For this technique, we require
normal data as well as depth,
so we collect those
in our G-Buffer pass.
The depth and normals are used
to generate the random rays
in the hemisphere.
Next, we trace rays
and calculate
the attenuation factor.
This produces an image where
crevices are naturally darkened,
creating the effect.
Let's take a look
at a Metal shader
for ambient occlusion.
First, we generate
the random rays.
In this case, we take
a cosineWeightedRay
along the normal in each thread.
We set the max_distance
to a small number,
as we're only interested
in a small neighborhood.
Next, we create our intersector
and intersect
the acceleration structure.
Depending on the result,
we accumulate
into our attenuation factor.
Here's a side-by-side
comparison.
And we can immediately see
how much better
the ray-traced approach looks.
I want to highlight a few places
that really show the limitations
of a screen-space effect.
Here is an example
where the neighborhood
is misrepresented due to limited
screen-space information.
This is because
the actual geometry
is almost perpendicular
to the camera and, therefore,
not in the depth buffer
at this angle.
The same problem occurs
across the image,
in particular,
under the moped.
From this angle,
the bottom of the moped
is missing
from the depth buffer.
So the screen-space technique
completely misses
the attenuation.
The ray-traced version,
on the other hand,
correctly discovers
the intersections
against the bottom of the moped
for the floor pixels.
And here's a great example
of the limitations around
the screen border.
The occluding geometry
is offscreen,
so its contribution is lost
in the screen-space technique,
but accounted for
in ray tracing.
As we can see,
hybrid rendering provides
a significant quality
improvement
by using the actual geometry
of the scene,
freeing the technique
from limitations
in screen-space information.
And finally, let's take a look
at reflections.
Reflections
have traditionally been
very difficult
for rasterization.
Reflection probes
is a technique that works well
but is limited in resolution,
requires filtering,
and struggles
with dynamic geometry.
Screen-space
reflection techniques
are limited by
screen-space information.
Reflection probes
are a solution that requires
strategically placing cameras
along the entire scene
to capture surrounding
color information.
To use reflection probes,
cube maps are captured
from different locations
in the scene.
This is essentially a rendering
of the scene in six directions
from the same point.
When a pixel is shaded,
you calculate the relation
to the probes
and sample the cube maps
to produce
the reflected shading.
For realistic results,
usually many probes need to be
scattered across the scene.
And as dynamic objects
move across the scene,
shaders need to sample
from more than one cube map
and manually interpolate
reflected colors.
The cube maps also need
to be prefiltered
to accurately
represent irradiance
and are limited in resolution.
Another rasterization technique,
screen-space reflection,
avoids some of these problems
by basing its reflections
on pixels already
on the framebuffer.
The fragment shader
uses the normals
to incrementally march outwards
and check the depth map
for potential nearby objects.
If we find something,
we sample the color
directly from the frame buffer
and shade it onto
the output image.
It does suffer, however, from
the screen-space limitations
we discussed earlier.
Notice in this moped example
how only part of the surface
can get an accurate reflection,
corresponding to the floor tiles
present in the framebuffer.
The rest of the scene
is missing.
Worse, the lower portion behind
the fender, marked in yellow,
is missing information;
we have no way of knowing
what the surface facing away
from the camera would look like.
The ray marching can also get
computationally expensive.
Ray-traced reflections, however,
helps us overcome
both sets of problems,
as we can rely on
the true scene information
in the acceleration structure.
Let's take a look at how
a perfect mirror would work.
First, we take the incident ray
from the camera's position
to the point.
Then, we reflect this point
on the normal
associated with the point.
This provides us
with a direction
we can trace a ray towards,
and find any
reflected objects.
For this, we provide our
reflection ray-tracing kernel
with the normals and depth
of the G-Buffer.
This ray-tracing kernel
calculates the view vector,
from the camera to each point,
reflects this vector,
and traces a ray in
that direction from the point.
Finally,
for accurate reflections,
we can shade the intersection
found directly
in the ray-tracing kernel.
Let's take a look at coding
this shader.
Once again, we start
from the point's depth,
and reconstruct its position.
This time, we want the position
to be in world space.
So in our calculatePosition
function,
we'll need to multiply
the inverse of the view matrix.
Then, we calculate our reflected
incident vector over the normal
and create a ray
in that direction.
Next, we create our intersector
and trace our reflectedRay.
If we hit an object,
we now shade that point
to produce the reflection.
If the intersection
missed all objects,
we can just sample a skybox
and return its color
to simulate a reflection
that's showing the sky.
Note that the shading
is performed
directly in the compute kernel
for this technique.
Let's compare reflection probes
to ray-traced reflections.
The image on the right
used hybrid rendering,
and we can see the details
of the floor tiles
much more clearly.
The buildings are present,
and we can even see shadows
reflected on the front panel
of the moped.
Reflections are a natural fit
for ray tracing.
It nicely handles
mirror-like reflections
and rough reflections.
Those can be achieved
by tracing multiple rays
along a cone
and filtering the results.
Because they rely
on perfect information
coming from
the acceleration structure,
ray-traced reflections are free
from screen-space artifacts
and can handle both static
and dynamic geometry
in the scene.
Now, one important detail:
we mentioned
that for reflections,
we need to shade the point
directly in the compute kernel.
Some techniques like this one
or global illumination
require accessing vertex data
and Metal resources
from the compute kernel
directly.
For these cases
we need to make sure
the GPU has access to the data
that it needs
to apply our shading equations.
This is achieved
with a bindless binding model
which in Metal is represented
as argument buffers.
Please make sure to check out
this year's
"Bindless rendering in Metal"
talk for more detail.
We just saw how hybrid rendering
can be put into practice
with several
different techniques.
This leads
to more natural algorithms
that also have the advantage of
producing more accurate results.
In some cases,
when we compare
to the traditional
rasterization techniques,
we see that we can
remove render passes
and save memory and bandwidth
in some cases.
With the addition
of ray tracing from render,
we can even keep
our entire work on chip.
Ray-tracing adoption
is a big task,
and we have
excellent new tooling
to assist you in the process
of bringing these techniques
to your engine.
This year,
we're introducing tools
that enable you to capture
ray-tracing work,
inspect acceleration structures,
and inspect visible
and intersection functions.
Now David will give us a tour
of these new tools.
David Núñez Rubio: Thanks, Ali.
My name is David Núñez Rubio,
and I am a GPU
software engineer.
Last year, we introduced
ray-tracing support in Metal.
However, developing complex
application can be challenging.
Fortunately, Metal Debugger
is here to help you.
This year, we introduced
ray-tracing support
in Metal Debugger.
Thanks to the adoption
of hybrid rendering,
our demo is looking
better than ever.
Ray-traced soft shadows,
reflections, ambient occlusion;
the results are amazing.
During development of the demo,
we hit some issues.
This is how tools can help you
resolving these problems.
In this early version
of the demo,
ray-traced shadows have
already been implemented.
But if you look carefully,
you'll notice missing shadows
from the tree leaves
on the ground.
It is more obvious if we compare
with the reference version.
See reference versus ray traced.
Let's jump into Xcode
and take a capture
to see how the tools can help us
debugging this issue.
We need to press
the Metal button
and click on Capture.
Since this is a static problem,
we just need a single frame.
In the debugger, API calls
are organized in the left side
on the debug navigator.
Let's unfold
the offscreen command buffer
to look for our shadow encoding.
I have labeled
my compute command encoder
as "Raytrace Shadows."
It is a good practice to label
your Metal objects
so you can easily find them
in the Metal Debugger.
The thumbnail
also gives us a hint that,
indeed, this is the encoder
we are looking for.
We can now click on the dispatch
Threadgroups API call
to show band resources.
This is a list
of all the objects
associated with
our current kernel dispatch.
And here, we can see
an acceleration of structure,
which we have
conveniently labeled as well.
Our kernel uses
an acceleration structure
to cast rays.
This is commonly implemented
as a bounding volume hierarchy
or BVH, which is a tree-like
data structure
representing the 3D world
that rays will intersect.
Now, double-click to open the
acceleration structure viewer.
This is a great new tool
built into the Metal Debugger.
Let me give you an overview
of how it is organized.
On the right side,
we have the 3D view
where we have a ray traced
visualization of our 3D scene,
including any custom geometry
or intersection functions.
This works great with custom
geometry such as hair
or when using alpha testing.
You can use familiar controls
to move the camera
and look around.
And here's a tip:
press Option key while scrolling
to zoom in and out.
We have built some
great visualization tools
to better understand our scene.
Let's click on
the highlighted menu
to see the different modes
available.
For instance, we can visualize
bounding volume traversals.
This is a heat map showing
how many nodes a single ray
will need to traverse
before hitting a surface.
Darker colors mean more nodes
need to be traversed
and a slower intersection test.
We can also color-code our scene
based on
acceleration structures...
geometries...
instances...
or intersection functions.
Now that we are a bit
more familiar with the tool,
we can go back
to our original problem.
Thanks to the 3D view,
we have confirmed
that our geometry is there.
So there must be something else.
On the left side,
there is the navigator area.
Here we can see
our top- and bottom-level
acceleration structures.
We can unfold
any acceleration structures
to see the list of geometries
it is built from.
We can unfold again
to see their properties
such as opacity
or primitive count.
We can also see
the list of instances
of this acceleration structure.
Let's click on the tree leaves
to reveal their instance
on the navigator
and inspect its properties.
The matrix looks correct,
and there are no flags set,
but it seems that the mask
is missing something.
In this demo, we are using
intersection masks.
We use the lowest bit
of the mask
to flag objects casting shadows.
Our intersector then
will test this mask
using a bitwise and operation
and reject the intersection
if it fails.
We can visualize this behavior
directly in the 3D view.
We need to open
the intersector hints menu.
Here we can configure
ray traversal options
for visualization.
We can change
culling operations,
disable custom intersections,
or change
the intersector’s mask.
By default,
it will intersect everything.
Let's change it to the value
that we are using for shadows.
This will show us an exact
visualization of our scene
when using our shadow mask.
And indeed, we have confirmed
that our tree leaves
are now missing.
Once we have identified
the problem,
we need to go back to our source
and make sure we are setting
the right mask value.
This is how shadows
looked before.
And this is how they look
after fixing the mask value.
This is an example
of the workflows
that can help you debug
your ray-tracing applications.
If you want to learn more
about tools,
make sure you check out
this year's
"Discover Metal debugging,
profiling,
and asset creation tools"
WWDC session.
In this session,
we have reviewed
how ray tracing
can elevate your visuals.
Hybrid rendering
is the combination
of rasterization
and ray tracing.
This allows replacing
light approximation techniques
with more accurate ones
that also happen to be simpler.
We also saw the new tools
to aid you in the process
of adopting ray tracing
in your engine.
We have only scratched
the surface
on what new possibilities
are available to you
by combining rasterization
and ray tracing.
We can't wait to see
how you put these technologies
in practice
to develop the new
innovative graphics techniques
of the future.
Thank you
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
♪