[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[person] Six, five, four,
three, two, one, zero.
All engines running.
[rocket blasting]
[soft music]
♪ ♪
[Tiera] I had the passion
of designing, building.
I really, really loved math.
So at the age of 11, I decided
to become an aerospace engineer,
and ever since that moment,
I've been stuck on that dream.
My name is Tiera Fletcher.
I'm a rocket scientist working
on NASA's Space Launch System,
and I'm working
to get us to Mars.
I was born and raised
in a small town
outside of Atlanta
called Mableton, Georgia.
Fortunately, I grew up
with both of my parents
and two older siblings.
My father, he was a construction
worker, and he would show me
how to take measurements or how
to build small-scale houses.
And he didn't realize it,
but he was
introducing me to engineering.
And my mom, when we would go
to the grocery store,
she would challenge me
to calculate the total
of the groceries,
including tax,
minus the coupons,
without a calculator.
So she did those exercises
because she understood
that I had a passion
for mathematics.
So at the age of 11, I decided
to become an aerospace engineer.
I joined a program that
taught students about robotics.
So being able to design
and build was already a passion
that I had acquired prior
to the program, but being able
to program that structure
that I create and make it move,
that just brought it
all to life for me, literally.
Being able to see
something go from paper
to product to movement
put it all together for me.
To continue towards my dream,
I decided to attend
the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology.
While at MIT,
I had the opportunity
to define antigravity
rotations for astronauts.
And I also had the opportunity
to define
the outer protective layer for
the space suit of the future.
Since our very first breath,
humankind has just had
this passion to explore
and discover the unknown,
to determine the new frontiers.
And really that hunger
to produce
all of this innovation
and technological breakthroughs
has caused us
to create fantastic innovations
from personal computers
to global positioning systems
or, as you know it,
GPS, and even the Internet.
But even before
all of those innovations,
we've had the passion
to go to Mars.
Sending 24 humans into space,
completing 13 launches,
weighing over 6 million pounds
and standing taller
than the Statue of Liberty
was the Saturn V,
the largest rocket
ever created in history.
Some may even argue
that the Saturn V was created
to take humanity to Mars.
So from 1969 to 1973,
the Saturn V served
as the launcher
for the Apollo program.
So it was literally facilitating
human footprints to the Moon.
This rocket did not merely just
launch into the air and break
through the atmosphere.
It was controlled
by groundbreaking avionics
of the time and notably
the Launch Vehicle
Digital Computer.
With increased computer use
on board, it caused an increase
of computer use
off board as well.
So thankfully,
software-enabled processes
caused our manual processes
to then become
completely automated.
We are voyagers collecting
data beyond our solar system.
Space probes Voyager 1
and Voyager 2 have been
traveling through space
since the '70s.
At more than 14 billion miles
away from Earth's surface,
these spacecraft are literally
in the interstellar medium,
breaking barriers
of our solar system.
Programmed spacecraft
are traveling throughout space
collecting asteroid samples
to bring back to Earth.
OSIRIS-REx literally collected
a sample
of a near-Earth asteroid
called Bennu
and is bringing it back to Earth
so that we can do
more research in our labs.
Knowledge expands
billions of miles away,
as we are on a mission
to explore new horizons.
Known as the fastest human-made
object
launched from Earth,
New Horizons has been able
to tell us more about
our former planet, known as Pluto,
and also traveling
through the Kuiper belt
to tell us more about
the formation
of our solar system.
Trips to
the International Space Station
are now second nature.
Crew-1 just returned from their
mission and Crew-2 went off
to the International
Space Station
back in April.
so yeah, one mission down,
one mission underway,
four more missions to go
as part of the commercial
Crew program.
Our Perseverance has
led us to see and hear Mars
more clearly than ever before.
The Perseverance Mars Rover
has been able to send back data
detailing the visuals
and the audio of Mars
and also deploy the Ingenuity
helicopter so that we can
have that first powered flight
on the Martian surface.
Humans are now returning
to the Moon in preparation
to pursue deep space missions,
including Mars.
And we have a vehicle
to propel us there:
NASA Space Launch System.
I began working
on the Space Launch System
program at the age of 22
as a structural design
and analysis engineer,
and what that means is that
I would design
different parts of the rocket
and verify the structural
integrity of those same parts.
And then I wanted to see
the rocket, so I decided to go
to the Michoud Assembly Facility
in New Orleans,
Louisiana, and I worked
as an engine section task lead.
So those same parts that I just
designed, I had to spearhead
the installation of those parts
and work with the technicians
to verify that all
of the assemblies were correct.
Moving on from there,
I became a structural engineer,
and what that means is that
my role was very multifaceted.
So I did manufacturing
engineering work,
structural design
anything and everything
to make sure
that the rocket was complete.
And then I became fully
a structural design engineer,
where I had to create
drawings and verify
all of the different intricacies
of the designs for the vehicle.
And now I'm
a configuration management
and product
integration engineer,
or you can say
a product life cycle engineer.
What that means is
that I have to verify
that all of the engineering
designs for the parts align
with the installations
of the parts.
[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
Being able to not only design
components
with multiple types of software
on the computer screen
but also see those components
in my face
and touch them,
it's--it's mind-blowing.
I literally would get
to the point of tears
just thinking about
all of the different days
and hours that I worked
designing different components
of the rocket, seeing them in 3D
modeling for computer-aided
design software and then
seeing it up front in person
actually manufactured
and fabricated
and assembled on the rocket.
Towering 322 feet tall,
the Space Launch System consists
of a few major components.
Four RS25 engines.
And then you have
the core stage,
the upper stage,
or also known as the interim
cryogenic propulsion stage,
and then you have solid
rocket boosters on either side,
and of course you have
a crew capsule called Orion
that sits at the top
of this massive rocket.
The Space Launch System
is the most powerful rocket
ever created in history.
Producing over 8 million pounds
of thrust,
that's actually 15%
more thrust than the Saturn V.
Most recently,
the Space Launch System
core stage underwent
green run testing.
What green run testing
means is that the engines are
all fired up at the same time
as a whole structure,
and let's just say
that anyone who is near
the Stennis Space Center can
feel the rumbling and the growl
of the propulsive system
of the Space Launch System.
This was a significant test
because we had a chance to have
multiple and multiple test cases
play a role all within
8 to 9 minutes, so it was
a very short time frame
but super monumental
for our process to get
the Space Launch System
on the launch stand
at the Kennedy Space Center.
The interesting part is
that we had to move this
massive structure all the way
from New Orleans, Louisiana,
to the Kennedy Space Center.
And that's where the historical
Pegasus barge
had to come into play.
We were able to load
the core stage
and carefully bring it over
to the Kennedy Space Center.
Although it can undergo
millions of pounds of force,
we want to make sure that
the structural integrity is
maintained throughout the whole
transportation process.
And now we are
stacking up multiple components
of the rocket in the vertical
assembly building so that we can
then shift it over
to the launch stand
so that we can launch
at the end of this year.
♪ ♪
So now let's talk about
the missions of how we get
back to the Moon and on to Mars.
This is through
the Artemis program,
and it consists
of three different missions.
The first mission
takes place this year in 2021.
The Artemis 1
Space Launch System will pair
along with the Orion crew
capsule for an uncrewed flight.
And the significance
of this flight is that it is
the initial flight
for the Space Launch System,
so it is a mission that will be
proving ground for the structure
before we allow astronauts
to come on.
And the Orion will travel
40,000 miles away from the Moon,
which is about 280,000 miles
away from the Earth's surface.
In total,
Orion will undergo about
1.4 million miles of travel
from Earth and all the way back.
This journey is going to prove
very significant because
we are going to be able
to collect data that will fuel
the next Artemis mission,
but also it will fuel
the whole future
of space travel.
Orion is going to undergo
an entry at about
24,500 miles per hour.
And that's going to cause
the capsule to reach
about 5,000 degrees Fahrenheit.
All of the data that we will
collect from this mission
will definitely teach us
what to do before we allow
astronauts on board.
In 2022, the Artemis 2
Space Launch System
in conjunction with the Orion
will carry four astronauts
back to the lunar environment
for the first time
in over 50 years.
This is extremely significant
for the future
of human space travel.
The astronauts will undergo
a ten-day mission
where the capsule will make
two orbits
around the Earth
and then head over to the Moon.
The Orion will begin by reaching
an initial insertion orbit.
After the first orbit,
the interim cryogenic propulsion
stage will then propel Orion
to high-Earth orbit.
The Orion will then be
separated from the interim
cryogenic propulsion stage
so that the astronauts can
verify valuable performance
and operational capabilities
so that that data can
carry forward
for the next Artemis mission.
In 2024,
Artemis 3 Space Launch System
and Orion will carry astronauts
back into the space environment.
But this time, the first woman
and the first person of color
will step foot on the Moon.
♪ ♪
I knew that I needed
a role model to serve
as my guiding light
throughout my journey,
and in that search, I discovered
Mae Jemison, the first
Black female astronaut.
Being able to see
someone who looks like me
allowed me to see myself
becoming an aerospace engineer.
Representation is
such a vital component
of being able to bring
your dreams into reality.
I had many moments where I felt
that I couldn't speak up
in meetings or that I couldn't
contribute because of the way
that I look
or just because I was
the youngest on the team
or the only female on the team
or the only
African American on the team.
But I had to overcome
those barriers and set myself
on the challenge
of not only contributing
but giving 150% at all times,
because I understood
that I did not have
only the responsibility
of contributing as an engineer
but also the responsibility
of widening the pipeline
in order to encourage the youth,
the upcoming generations,
to pursue this field as well,
even though there aren't many
of us or a large representation
of minorities at this time.
So in order to do that,
I created an organization
alongside my husband,
who’s also a rocket scientist,
called Rocket
with the Fletchers.
So through Rocket
with the Fletchers,
we do many different
outreach opportunities
for students to motivate them
to follow their dreams.
So we teach about
aerospace engineering…
we mentor…
and that's not only the fact
of talking about how cool
aerospace engineering is -
it’s about the importance
of diversity and inclusion
when it comes
to innovation for humanity.
Diversity of mind
is at the center,
at the forefront, at the root
of successful innovation
for the space industry.
By actually playing
an active role in getting
the first woman and the first
person of color on the Moon,
I feel very proud, very proud
of the work that I do.
But truly in order for us
to continue to power innovation
within the space industry,
we have to look
at the critical components
of innovation: passion,
data, and diversity of mind.
And you know what?
Maybe I'll see you
on Mars someday.
[person] Three, two, one.
♪ ♪