[percussive music]
[Graham]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Graham, and I'm here
with my colleague, Nadia,
and we're from the Device
Management team here at Apple.
This past year has seen
unprecedented changes
in the way we work, live,
and learn.
From the office
to the kitchen table
to the living room sofa,
Apple hardware, software,
and services
have been there
to give people the power
and flexibility to do
whatever needs doing.
Apple platforms provide
a huge opportunity
for system administrators
and mobile device
management developers
to deliver
incredible apps,
rich content,
and powerful services
to customers, employees,
students, and teachers.
At Apple,
we believe that the balance
between privacy, user agency,
and administrative control
is what makes for a great
device management solution.
And in iOS 15 and macOS
Monterey,
we're introducing
a number of great new features
across all of our platforms.
With so many exciting
new features to share,
we've created deep dive
sessions for many of them.
I'd like to briefly touch
on a few topics
before we get
into today's content,
starting with changes
to user enrollment.
User enrollment is designed
for Bring Your Own Device
deployments,
where the user and not the
organization owns the device.
This MDM enrollment type
protects the privacy
of personal data
while still securing
corporate data on the device.
This year, we have some
exciting improvements
to data separation
and user onboarding.
Check out the "Discover
account-driven user enrollment"
session to learn more.
Next, I'm very excited to share
with you that Apple Configurator
for iPhone is coming
to the App Store,
and we have a new feature
for macOS
automated device enrollment.
You are not going to want
to miss
the "Manage devices with Apple
configurator" session.
We're enhancing the device
management protocol
to be more
robust and performant.
For a look into the future
of MDM,
check out the "Meet declarative
device management" session.
This year,
we have a number of exciting
software update changes for iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS.
See what's new in the
"Manage software updates
in your organization" session,
where we'll discuss testing,
deploying,
and enforcing OS updates.
Now I'd like to turn
it over to my colleague, Nadia,
to tell you about
some very exciting new features
coming to iOS
and iPadOS 15 this year.
[Nadia] Hi, I'm excited to tell
you about all the new
iOS and iPadOS features
for device management.
This year,
we've made a significant change
to the way users view their
managed account,
the profiles
installed on the device,
and how VPN is configured
in Settings.
VPN & Device Management
have been combined together,
providing
one comprehensive place
to display the device state.
There, you can get
a complete understanding
of how your device
is being managed.
Another key component
of MDM is installing apps.
Many MDM vendors have an agent
app that they require
as part of configuring devices,
or perhaps an organization
has a critical app
all their employees need.
On supervised devices,
this isn't a problem
because apps install
without prompting the user.
However, unsupervised devices
prompt for permission
to install apps, which
the user could then decline.
Wouldn't it be great if you
had more control over this?
Well, now you do.
Introducing Required App.
You can now specify one app that
you would like to be installed
on unsupervised devices.
We ensure user privacy
is protected,
since the user
is consenting to the app install
during MDM enrollment,
and only this app
will install
without additional
user approval.
Simply add the iTunes Store ID
of the App Store application
to the MDM profile.
Then ensure your app has
a device or user license
and send the InstallApplication
command.
Also make sure to add
a managed app attribute
to ensure the user
cannot remove your app.
Securing the flow of data
between apps
is also a really
important consideration.
Managed open-in allows you
to control whether data
is allowed to enter or leave
the management sphere.
At its most basic, it controls
independently whether data can
can be sent
from an unmanaged app
to a managed app
and vice versa.
And now we're making
it better than ever
with managed pasteboard.
A new restriction called
requireManagedPasteboard
controls whether copy/paste is
affected by managed open-in.
System apps that will
honor the restriction
include Calendar,
Notes, Mail, and Files.
All other apps require
no additional changes
to adopt this feature.
Like usual,
apps installed via MDM
will automatically be
treated as managed,
and apps installed by the user
will be treated as unmanaged.
With managed pasteboard,
you'll always be allowed
to see the paste button.
If you're not allowed
to paste content somewhere
due to the restriction,
you'll get
a "Paste Not Allowed"
notification.
As a side note,
the organization name
that appears in the notification
can be modified using
the OrganizationInfo Settings
command.
Last year, we brought Shared
iPad to Business,
which allows employees to have
a personal experience
on a shared device.
Shared iPad has traditionally
required
the use of a Managed Apple ID,
but with Temporary Session,
anyone can use a shared iPad.
When logging out, all data,
such as Safari browsing history,
modified user settings,
and files added
will be deleted from the device,
leaving it
ready for the next user.
In iOS 14.5, we have introduced
three new features
in the SharedDeviceConfiguration
Settings command.
TemporarySessionOnly is
to limit the ability to log in
with a Managed Apple ID.
TemporarySessionTimeout
and UserSessionTimeout
will automatically log the user
out after a set amount of time,
ensuring that your data
is secure
after a period of inactivity.
Make sure to not set
the timer to a value too short,
and also pressing the power
or Home button
will cause
the timer to reset.
Now let's talk about
some changes
we've added for Apple TV.
The TV Remote payload
is useful for connecting
specific Apple TVs
with the Remote widget
in Control Center on iOS
and iPadOS devices.
In tvOS 15, there is a new
security enhancement
where Apple TV
will no longer broadcast
Mac addresses over Bonjour.
Due to this change,
we can no longer prevent
PIN prompts
from appearing on the TV.
To ensure minimal impact
to your deployments,
we've added a new key
to the TV Remote payload.
Use the new TVDeviceName key
in addition to the TVDeviceID key
to filter Apple TV device
names in the Remote widget.
This will prevent any
unwanted pairing attempts
from managed devices.
A few other changes
you will want to be aware of:
all payload types
within a single profile
require unique
payload identifiers.
Additionally
for unsupervised devices,
the Take Management
prompt for apps
can be declined
up to three times.
After that, the device will
not prompt for 24 hours.
Also, we've updated a number
of payload keys
to use more inclusive language.
Be sure to check out
the updated Device Management
documentation
for more information.
Thanks for exploring
all the incredible features
with iOS and iPadOS 15.
Now I'm going to hand
it back to Graham to talk
about all the great new
features coming to the Mac.
[Graham] Thank you, Nadia.
I think you'll agree that 2020
was a very exciting year for the Mac,
from the amazing new look and feel
of Big Sur to the introduction
of Apple silicon.
This new generation of Mac
is enabling our users
to do all
kinds of amazing new things.
And we have some great
new device management features
in macOS Monterey.
Let's get started by
talking about System Extensions.
System Extensions
allow for software
like network extensions
and endpoint security solutions
to extend the functionality
of macOS
without requiring
kernel-level access.
We've made a few changes
to the System Extension payload
to enhance
the management experience.
In macOS 11.3, installing
the System Extension payload
changes the state
of a system extension.
For example,
if a system extension
is pending user approval,
installing the payload
will activate the extension.
Conversely,
removing the payload will now
deactivate
the system extension.
In macOS Monterey,
there is a new feature
called RemovableSystemExtension.
This will allow an app
to deactivate
its own system extension,
for example,
when the app uninstalls itself.
With this feature, there will be
no admin password required
to remove the system extension.
This may
be useful in deployments
where the Mac has no admin user.
In macOS Big Sur,
it became a requirement
to reboot a Mac to modify
kernel extensions.
We've added
a few features to make
managing kernel
extensions easier.
First, we added an option
to the RestartDevice command
that tells the Mac to rebuild
its kernel extension cache
on reboot.
This is required anytime
a kernel extension
is added or removed.
Use the optional KextPaths
key to specify kernel extensions
that haven't been discovered
by the operating system.
This allows
MDM to install an app
and load the kernel
extension without requiring
the user to launch
the app before rebooting.
The new NotifyUser
option will allow MDM
to display a reboot
notification to the user.
When clicked,
the user can perform
a graceful restart of the Mac.
The NotifyUser feature
can be used outside
of the context of kernel
extensions,
but it's especially helpful
when they're combined.
The AllowNonAdminUserApprovals
key
in the System Policy
Kernel Extensions payload
allows a standard user
to complete the installation
of kernel extensions.
Note the user must
perform the restart from within
System Preferences
or use the notification
from MDM to trigger
the kernel cache rebuild.
Depending on the hardware,
you may need a bootstrap token
to complete this step.
You can find out
if this is required
in the SecurityInfo query.
Next, let's talk about apps.
One of the coolest new features
of Mac computers
with Apple silicon
is the ability to run iPhone
and iPad apps.
With the initial launch
of macOS Big Sur,
we added a new DeviceInformation
query key
that reports if a Mac
supports iPhone
and iPad app installs,
and in macOS 11.3 on Apple
silicon, this now returns true.
Once you're ready to install
an App Store app
or your own
in-house enterprise app,
you'll need to include
a new flag
in the InstallApplication
command
to indicate that it's an iPhone
or iPad app.
And in the case
of in-house enterprise apps,
ensure the URL in the manifest
points directly to an .ipa file
and not a. pkg.
We now support the ability
to manage
iOS-style
provisioning profiles.
This feature allows
for independent management
of in-house enterprise apps
and provisioning profiles.
Now, let's talk about
some new features
exclusive to Apple silicon.
We are enhancing
the DeviceLock command
on Mac computers
with Apple silicon.
With this change, administrators
will now be able to send
a six-digit PIN, message,
and phone number to the device.
This will cause the Mac
to reboot and present the user
with the information provided,
bringing feature parity
across all Mac models.
With remote lock in place,
the user is unable to use
a Mac until the PIN
has been provided.
Once the PIN is entered,
the Mac will reboot
with all data intact
ready for login.
While this is a great start,
rebooting to recovery could
allow for unintended data access
or changing critical
security settings.
So we're adding a new feature
to set a recovery password.
The new SetRecoveryLock
and VerifyRecoveryLock
MDM commands
allow you to set
and verify a password
that must be entered
before the Mac
can reboot into recovery.
There are some important details
that you will want to know
about using these new commands.
The password can only
be set and removed by MDM.
Therefore,
if a user un-enrolls from MDM,
the recovery password
will be removed.
The MDM server needs
to know the existing password
to set a new password.
And finally,
both the DeviceLock PIN
and the Recovery Password
will be removed
when the Mac is erased.
Therefore, we recommend using
these features
in conjunction
with Activation Lock
to provide the best
security for your fleet.
Now, we know you're pretty
excited about these features,
but we do have one last thing.
Erase All Content and Settings
for the Mac.
New in macOS Monterey is
the ability to Erase All Content
and Settings
for a quick return to service.
And we're very excited
that this functionality
will be available
via MDM as well.
Sending the EraseDevice
command will now erase
all user data and reboot
back to Setup Assistant,
ready for the next user.
A couple of notes
on this feature
you'll want to be aware of:
This feature is supported on Mac
computers with Apple silicon
and the Apple T2 security chip.
If the Mac
has multiple partitions,
it will reboot back to setup
on the current system volume,
and all other volumes
will be erased.
On devices with Apple silicon,
this will also reset
any security settings that have
been modified in recovery.
We also know that you might not
want users to erase their Mac,
so we're bringing
the allowEraseContentAndSettings
restriction to the Mac.
We've covered
a ton of new features today,
and we're so excited for you
to get your hands on them.
To keep up to date with the
latest changes in each seed,
please review the Device
Management documentation
at developer.apple.com.
Also remember,
AppleSeed for IT
helps you access and test
all of these new features.
Any nonstudent Managed Apple ID
from Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager
can participate in the program.
Along with access to pre-release
Apple software for testing
in your environment,
it includes detailed test plans
and a way for you
to provide feedback.
I'd also like to remind
you to check out
all the great
deep-dive sessions.
These sessions will
give you even more details
on all the new device
management features.
From the updates
to user enrollment
to Shared iPad
and all of the exciting
new features for the Mac,
we look forward
to seeing you take
the device management experience
to the next level.
Thank you,
and enjoy the rest of your WWDC.
[percussive music]