[upbeat music]
[Saharsh] Hi.
I'm Saharsh Oza.
I'm with the GPU Software
Engineering team at Apple.
Today my colleague,
Yuliya Pylypiv, and I
will talk about what's new in
Metal Performance Shaders Graph.
Let us begin.
MPS is a library of metal-based,
high-performance,
GPU-accelerated primitives
for varied fields
like image processing,
linear algebra,
ray tracing,
and machine learning.
MPS team optimizes Metal kernels
to give the best performance
on each hardware
across Apple's various
platforms.
Last year, we introduced
the MPSGraph framework,
a general purpose compute
graph for the GPU.
It is supported on macOS, iOS,
iPadOS and tvOS,
same as the MPS framework.
Please watch our last year's
session
to get more introductory details
on the MPSGraph.
Let's take a look at the agenda.
We have a lot to cover.
We will discuss ML inference
and training acceleration
through MPSGraph.
We will introduce some exciting
new MPSGraph operations.
We will introduce new ways
for you to control compilation
in MPSGraph.
And finally, we will look
at the all new control-flow
capabilities of MPSGraph.
I'd like to introduce
my colleague, Yuliya,
who will share
some exciting updates
for inference
and training acceleration.
[Yuliya] Thanks, Saharsh.
Hi.
I'm Yuliya Pylypiv.
I am a part
of GPU Software team at Apple.
Today, I want to share
the improvements we've made
to boost training and
inference performance on GPU.
Let's get right into it.
The MPSGraph framework
has been adopted
by higher level machine learning
frameworks like Core ML
and TensorFlow for GPU
acceleration.
This year, we have optimized
MPSGraph even further
with a combination of kernel
improvements
and stitching adoption.
This has translated
to large performance gains
to the machine learning
frameworks that use MPS.
Let's take a closer look
at the new Metal Plugin
for TensorFlow.
TensorFlow is a popular machine
learning training platform,
and GPUs are the
predominant accelerator device.
This year, we have
developed a new Metal Plugin
using TensorFlow PluggableDevice
Interface
released in TensorFlow 2.5.
This brings the power
of Metal to TensorFlow
using MPS and MPSGraph.
This allows us to train
any machine learning model
on Mac platform GPUs
without modifications.
Now, let's see one of these in
action.
For this demo, I am going to
use a Jupyter environment.
On my M1 system,
I have the latest available
TensorFlow installed.
When we list physical devices,
you can see there is only
a CPU device registered.
Here I am defining a popular
machine learning model,
ResNet50, which is widely used
for image classification,
transfer learning, and more.
Current model uses
a standard ImageNet dataset
with 224 by 224 image sizes.
As you can see, the current
ETA for the first epoch
running on CPU is
around 20 minutes.
Let me install the TensorFlow
Metal Plugin
which we introduced earlier
and see if we can add some
speedup to the current network.
To do so,
I'm gonna use
pip install tensorflow-metal...
going back to the same
ResNet50 model we used before.
Only this time,
you can see
there is a new GPU device
registered.
This is the GPU device we
introduced
as a part of the TensorFlow
platform using Metal Plugin.
All callbacks and network
definition
remain unchanged.
Kicking off the network again
so we can compare ETAs.
You can see that the GPU version
of the same network
is training around
four times faster
using TensorFlow Metal Plugin.
Now let's take a closer look
at the other networks.
Here we show the performance
on key machine learning training
benchmarks relative to the CPU.
As you can see, we have a good
speedup across all benchmarks,
going up to eight times faster
on the M1 MacBook Pro.
Installing the new Metal Plugin
for TensorFlow is easy.
After installing the base
TensorFlow
using pip install
tensorflow-macos,
you can install Metal Plugin
using pip install
tensorflow-metal.
The Metal Plugin
will be available
on the official Python package
repo, pypi.org.
For details on environment setup
and installation,
please refer to Metal Developer
Resource.
That's it for TensorFlow.
Next, let's talk about Inference
acceleration in Core ML.
Core ML is Apple's machine
learning inference framework.
We also saw significant
performance improvements
on Core ML with MPSGraph.
We show here inference speedup
of key classes
of machine learning networks
on M1.
We get a 2x speedup on BERT,
which is a canonical
transformer network
used for NLP applications.
ResNet50, which is central
to computer vision applications,
has been tuned for texture
paths in previous releases.
This is an additional
performance improvement of 16%
with our new buffer backend
through MPSGraph.
These performance improvements
in Core ML and TensorFlow
are due to performance
improvements
in MPS primitives like
Convolution2D.
Here, we show the speedup of
Convolution2D
on NHWC and NCHW data layouts
which are used for training
and inference respectively.
That's it for the improvements
in inference and training.
Next, let's go back to Saharsh
to learn more
about the new operations
in MPSGraph.
[Saharsh] Thanks, Yuliya.
Now we will take a look
at the new set
of operations supported
by MPSGraph.
We support a plethora
of operations on the MPSGraph,
from multiple variants
of convolutions and reductions
to all the basic math ops you
may need in your compute graphs.
This year,
we added special operations
to enable you to do even more
with MPSGraph.
We will introduce three new
primitives:
control dependency,
stencil operator,
and gather operator.
First, we'll look at control
dependency.
Control dependency is needed
to explicitly order operations
in the graph.
To understand this,
let's formally define a graph
operation.
Operations in the graph connect
with each other
via three kinds of edges:
input tensors,
which represent which tensors
act as data inputs to the op,
output tensors, which are
created by the op itself,
and finally,
a special kind of edge
called control dependency.
They must execute
before the current operation,
even if the current operation
itself does not depend on it.
This API also offers
a convenient way to prevent
operations
from being optimized away by
MPSGraph.
This is needed to implement
machine learning layers
like batch normalization.
Let's see this in practice.
Batch normalization is a
standard layer
used in ML training
to make the network
more stable and converge faster.
Here we see the computational
graph for batch normalization
that is used for training.
The first step is to compute
the mean and variance.
These are, in turn,
used to update the running mean
and running variance
which are needed for inference.
However,
the training graph result
does not require these
variables,
so the MPSGraph might
optimize them away.
We can solve this
by explicitly ordering them
before the final normalization
operator
using control dependencies.
Let's look at a simple example
with some code
that shows how you can
use this API.
This graph shows an exponent
and assign operator.
The assign operator is not used
by anything else in the graph.
So it may be optimized away.
One way to solve this is
to explicitly set the assign
as a targetOperation.
However,
this requires the developer
to track dependencies globally
across the graph.
Instead, with the new
control dependency API,
you can make the exponent
operation
depend on the assignment.
This removes the need
to have a targetOperation
and also ensures that the graph
does not optimize it away.
Next,
we will see this in code.
We first define the operator
that the exponent is
dependent on.
Next, we create a dependentBlock
which defines the exponent
operator.
Finally, we call the run API
on this graph.
Note that no targetOperations
need to be tracked globally.
That's it for control
dependency.
Now let's talk about stencil
operators.
A stencil operation
is a generalization
of sliding window operators
like image convolution.
These operators are essential
in finite element methods,
machine learning,
and image processing
applications.
Here,
we see a five-point 2D stencil
commonly used to
implement Laplacian operations.
The stencil operator shown here
can be applied
to higher dimensions too,
as shown with this seven-point
3D stencil diagram.
Let's take a closer look at the
operator.
For each output value,
it computes a weighted reduction
over the stencil window
on the input tensor, as shown.
The operator supports
various reduction modes
including argmin/argmax,
and various padding modes,
including reflection
and clampToZero.
MPSGraph enables stitching
across MPS kernels
for optimal performance.
With stitching support,
the stencil operator allows you
to express complex mathematical
operations
in a single kernel launch.
Let us see one such example
in action.
Local response normalization
is a pytorch op
used for normalizing
in the channel dimension.
It's very straightforward
to implement this
with the new stencil operation.
Here, we see the graph for
this normalization technique.
We see that it's just element
wise ops
around the stencil operation.
Without the new operation,
multiple dispatches
will be needed.
Now, since the stencil op
supports stitching,
this entire graph can be
launched in a single dispatch.
So that's it for the stencil
operator.
Next, let's take a look at
improvements
in gather operations.
This year,
new gather operations
have been added to MPSGraph.
These allow for efficient
copying
of arbitrary sized slices
in noncontiguous memory
locations.
Conceptually,
we are gathering the values
from locations marked in blue
from a chunk of memory.
These gather layers allow
for efficient implementation
of embedding lookup
and dynamic matrix copy.
GatherND is a powerful extension
of the gather operation.
While the normal gather
supports linear indexing,
the gatherND operation enables
N-dimensional indexing.
This allows for seamless
copying of data
from anywhere in an
N-dimensional input.
The input to this operation
is a vector of coordinates,
and each coordinate can be up
to the rank of the input tensor.
Any dimensions not specified
in the coordinates
result in slice copies.
We can step through an example
of a gather of row slices
from a 3D tensor.
In this example, the indices
specify two coordinates
corresponding to the matrix
and row coordinates.
With no third coordinate
to column index,
this gatherND will copy
entire rows.
The result tensor is a 2D matrix
of the rows gathered
from the input matrix.
GatherND can represent nearly
any form of gather operation
and give great performance.
For example,
let's see how we can implement
embedding lookup using gather
operations.
Embedding lookup
is a common operation
used to find embedding vectors
for a provided set of input
objects.
Commonly, this layer is used
in language processing networks,
where an embedding matrix
is generated
associating each word
in the vocabulary
to an embedding vector.
The ID of the words
in the vocabulary
can be used as the indices
to a gather operation,
and the embedding matrix
is our input tensor.
We would like to
get the corresponding rows
for each word ID,
which we can do easily
using a gather layer.
We only specify one coordinate,
so the entire row will be copied
for each input word.
The resulting tensor
is a 2D matrix
of each input word's embedding
vector along the rows.
That's it for the new MPSGraph
operations
we have introduced this year.
Now let's talk about the
compilation APIs.
This year, we are introducing
the new MPSGraphExecutable API.
This compilation API
improves performance
in two ways.
First,
it gives the developer control
on when to compile the graph.
Second, it allows you to reduce
the number of compilation calls
through deferred type inference.
Now let's take a closer look at
each.
Last year, we provided
a really convenient API
to define and execute an
MPSGraph.
Under the hood, the first time
an evaluation was requested,
MPSGraph invoked compilation
for the input types
and internally created
an executable.
For any subsequent executions,
MPSGraph seamlessly cached
this executable
to ensure compilation cost
is not paid again.
Users now have the ability
to invoke
compilation ahead of time
so you can choose
the timeline for compilation.
With the compiled executable,
you can call run directly
on the MPSGraphExecutable.
This gives the user control
on when the graph is compiled
and also the ability
to cache the compiled executable
so you can gain even more
performance.
Let's see this in code.
Here, we have a simple graph
to add two tensors.
Now to compile, we provide
the types for the feeds
and target tensors
along with the operations.
What we get is a compiled graph
and an executable.
And the evaluation method
is just as simple.
We provide a Metal command queue
and our input tensor data.
So those are the basics
of compiling an MPS graph.
Next, let's talk about how we
reduce
the number of compilation calls
through deferred type inference.
Type inference
is a compilation pass
where MPSGraph must determine
tensor shapes
where they are not specified
by the user.
In this graph,
we are performing
a matrix multiplication
of two 2D tensors.
The shapes of the input tensors
are shown.
However, the output tensor
is of an unknown shape.
Once the type inference pass
is complete,
the output tensor shape
is determined
based on the inputs
and operation type.
In standard neural networks,
the inputs to the network
are not always the same size.
For natural language processing,
the sentences or sequences
can be of different lengths.
For CNNs,
we see different-sized images
coming in to be evaluated.
Before the compilation upgrades
of this year,
for every new sized image,
a compilation would be invoked
to do type inference
for the whole graph.
Now with control over
compilation, you, the developer,
can invoke compilation
with type inference pass
turned off.
This can save tens or hundreds
of many seconds
of compilation time
on each iteration
and get the best performance.
MPSGraph runtime
will infer types
just in time during encoding
and seamlessly make things work.
It is a tradeoff between
saving compilation time
versus getting the most
optimal graph.
Let's see how this can be used
in the code example
shared before.
Disabling the type inference
pass can be achieved
by setting the compilation
descriptor as shown.
That's it for compilation APIs.
Finally, let's talk about the
new
control flow APIs of MPSGraph.
These APIs let you
dynamically dispatch operations
based on tensors previously
evaluated by the graph.
This is common in applications
like batch normalization
and recurrent neural networks.
Let's take a look at how a
“while loop” can be implemented
with MPSGraph today without
the new API.
First, we create a graph
that computes the predicate.
Next, the predicate is evaluated
on the CPU
through an explicit
memory synchronization.
If the predicate is true,
the previously created graph
is re-executed with the new
inputs.
Otherwise,
if the predicate is false,
the loop ends
and a second MPSGraph is created
and executed to consume
the result.
With the new control flow API,
all these steps can be launched
as part of a single
MPSGraph execution.
This is more convenient
to implement
because you don't have to
introduce
explicit memory
synchronization primitives.
Now let's take a look
at how this can be
potentially more efficient.
Here we see the control flow
timeline
without the new API.
We encode
the first kernel on the CPU.
Once the kernel is complete,
we have to synchronize memory
to read the result.
This is potentially inefficient,
as the CPU has to wait
for the GPU to finish executing.
Similarly,
the GPU also has to wait
for the CPU synchronization
and subsequent encoding
to complete.
This happens in each iteration.
Now let's see the benefits
of using the new MPSGraph API.
We have to perform
only one CPU encode call.
Since the predicate is evaluated
on the GPU timeline,
no synchronization overhead
is incurred,
and the kernels can be launched
without any bubbles.
Now let's see what the new APIs
are.
We added three new
control flow APIs:
if/else, for loops,
and while loops.
Let's start with the if/else
primitive.
We are all familiar with this.
Based on a predicate,
different code paths
are executed.
We are provided a Boolean
predicate
along with a code block for
the “if” and “else” conditions.
If this predicate is true,
we execute the then
block of code.
Otherwise, if it's false,
the else branch is executed.
Having the if/else operation
is very useful in neural
networks.
One canonical usage is
in batchNormalization operation,
which has different behavior
in training and inference.
With the isTraining Boolean,
we can have a single graph
to represent both variants
of the normalizer.
Let's look at how to set up
an if/else branch in code.
Let's take a very simple example
of two input scalar tensors.
If the first tensor is smaller
than the second,
we return the sum of the
operations.
Else, we return the difference.
First, we compute the predicate
and pass that to the API.
Next,
when the predicate is true,
we compute the then block
and add the tensors.
Finally,
when the predicate is false,
we compute the else block
and subtract the tensors.
Next, let's see how to implement
a for loop.
The for loop primitive loops
over a set of operations
a fixed number of times.
This is common
in recurrent neural networks
where we have to loop over
sequences
of different lengths
during training.
We need to provide the
numberOfIterations
of the for loop.
The index is initialized to 0
and compared against
the numberOfIterations
each loop iteration.
If it's less than the
numberOfIterations,
we execute the body
of the for loop
and increment the index by 1.
When the index is equal to
or greater than the
numberOfIterations,
we end the loop.
Let's see how to implement this
in code.
Let's say we wanted to implement
a really simple example.
We'll initialize the result
variable to some input value.
Then we loop four times,
multiplying the result
by another input value
each time.
First, we create two graph
tensors.
The output tensor
will be initialized to input0.
In each iteration,
this tensor will be multiplied
by input1.
Next, we set
the numberOfIterations to 4
so that we can execute
the loop four times,
from index 0 to index 3.
Next, we create the body
of the for loop.
This is done by creating
a closure
which represents a single
iteration.
Each iteration is passed the
index of the current iteration,
as well as the output
of the previous iteration.
Then, we'll update the result
and return it,
to be passed to the next
iteration.
Finally,
we pass all these arguments
to the for loop API in
the graph.
Note that the iterationArguments
of the body
are initialized to input0
tensor.
That's it for the for loop.
Now let's look at the while loop
API.
This primitive executes
a set of operations
while a condition is met.
We need to provide two blocks
of code
to use this API.
In the first block,
the condition
is checked with a predicate.
When the predicate is true,
the body of the while loop
in the after block is executed.
This recomputes the predicate.
MPSGraph then uses this
predicate
in the next iteration of
the before block.
If the condition evaluated
is false,
it exits the loop.
The API also allows for
implementing the do-while loop
by swapping the body
and condition evaluation
code blocks.
Let's say we wanted to implement
a really simple example.
We'll initialize the result
variable to some input value.
Then we'll multiply the result
by a multiplier each time
in a loop till we exceed
a threshold.
First, we define a block of code
that will evaluate the predicate
using the result
of the previous iteration.
It also stores the results
of the previous iteration
in a returnTensors NSArray.
This array will be used
as the input
to the next iteration
when the predicate is true
and used as the final result
if the predicate is false.
Next, we define the body
of the while loop
where the tensors are
multiplied.
The product is returned
for the condition block to read.
Finally, we'll pass all these
arguments
to the while loop API as shown.
Note the initialInputs argument
is used in the first iteration
of the before block.
That's it for while loops.
Next, we'll see how this can be
used in a real application.
Image composition is a
common image editing utility.
Here, an object is implanted
into a target image.
We start with a source image
and a background image,
as shown.
Next, we create a mask
on the source image.
Let's place this mask of the
source image
directly against the background.
That does not look great,
as we can clearly see the edges
of the source image.
Through image composition,
we want to smoothen these edges.
Pairing a Laplacian edge filter
with an iterative linear solver
is a common way to achieve this.
Now let's look at the details.
Here, we see the pipeline needed
to perform image composition
with MPSGraph.
We start with our input tensors,
the background image,
source image,
and a mask of the object.
Next we use an iterative
linear solver
coupled with a Laplacian
edge detector.
The output of this set of
operations is
a composite image
with smooth edges.
Let's take a look
at the Laplacian edge filter.
Implementing the Laplacian
edge filter
involves a windowed reduction
over the source image
with a set of weights.
The stencil operator is used
to implement this as shown.
Using this operator,
we are able
to see the edges of the
source object.
The edges computed here
will be used
as the input to the linear
solver.
Next, let's take a look
at the linear solver.
We start with the background
image
and feed it into the linear
solver.
The solver updates this image,
and the result is
subsequently read back in.
As we can see,
this is an iterative process.
As the iterations progress,
the solution image improves
till we arrive
at the perfect blend
at the edges.
The loop terminates
when the error
is below a user defined
tolerance.
This requires a while loop.
You can now use
the MPSGraph Control Flow API
to implement this.
Now, let's look at the demo.
We have implemented
an image composition utility
using the MPSGraph
as an iPad Pro application.
We start with a source image
on the top
and a target image below.
We will be cloning objects
from the source to the target.
The first thing we need to do
is to draw a mask
around the cow
that we want to move.
Let's see how this looks
with a naive clone.
That does not look very good,
as we can see the rough edges.
Now let's try the image
composition technique
we just described.
We will start by setting
the initial solution
to the background image.
Let's run this for about 50
iterations.
Clearly, the solution image
has not yet converged.
Let's run it for about 50 more
iterations.
This looks way more natural
as the edges smoothen out.
The ease of programming with
MPSGraph
makes experimenting with
different techniques
straightforward.
Initializing the solver
with the cloned image
instead of the background image
can result in faster
convergence.
We can enable this
initialization mode
by toggling this switch.
Let's see this in action by
setting the iteration count
to 50 again and
resetting to the naive clone.
Now let's rerun the solver.
We can see the solution image
after 50 iterations
looks pretty good.
Since we already start
with the source object,
we also observe less bleeding
at the edges.
This is great.
But what we really want is
to automate convergence
based on an error tolerance.
This will require a while loop
which we will enable by
using this switch.
We have implemented this
with the new MPSGraph API.
The error tolerance can be
controlled with this slider.
We have set it to 0.1, as shown.
Let's reset this back to the
naive clone.
Now we start the solver.
With this while loop, we
converge to the solution image
in about 80 iterations
without me having
to specify any iteration count.
Now let's have some fun
by cloning other animals
onto this background.
Let's try this cute puppy.
All right, done tracing.
I think it would look great
at the bottom right
of this image.
Maybe we can try a bird next.
This would look good on the
top right of the background.
The new background with all
these images looks pretty neat.
That's it for the demo.
In summary,
we showed how adopting MPSGraph
led to amazing performance
improvements
for CoreML and TensorFlow.
Inference
is now up to twice as fast.
We introduced
useful new compute primitives,
including the stencil operator
that is going to enable
a wide range of applications.
We showed new compilation
flexibility
that MPSGraph offers.
This is going to shave off
latency from inference networks.
And finally, we showed all new
control flow capabilities of
MPSGraph.
This API is key to expressing
several linear algebra
applications
in addition to machine
learning networks.
We are excited to see how you
will take advantage of
these features.
Thank you,
and have a great WWDC 2021.
[upbeat music]