[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Matt Ricketson: Hi, I'm Matt,
and later on
I'll be joined by Luca and Raj.
Today, we're going
to demystify SwiftUI.
Now, we've heard it
many times before
that SwiftUI is
a declarative UI framework.
That means that you describe
what you want
for your app at a high level,
and SwiftUI decides
exactly how to make it happen.
Now, most of the time,
this works great!
And that's when SwiftUI
feels magical.
But there will always
be those moments
when SwiftUI does something
that you might not expect.
And in those moments,
it helps to understand
a bit more about what SwiftUI
is doing behind the scenes
to build a better intuition
for how to get the results
you're looking for.
So today's question is,
When SwiftUI looks at your code,
what does it see?
The answer is three things:
identity, lifetime,
and dependencies.
Identity is how SwiftUI
recognizes elements
as the same or distinct across
multiple updates of your app.
Lifetime is how SwiftUI tracks
the existence of views
and data over time.
And dependencies
are how SwiftUI understands
when your interface
needs to be updated and why.
Together, these three concepts
inform how SwiftUI decides
what needs to change,
how, and when,
resulting in the dynamic
user interface you see onscreen.
Today, we'll talk about each of
these three concepts in more depth.
Let's start with identity,
and I have a few friends
here to help me.
These Ruby Spaniels
are adorable,
but they're also the subject of
a deep philosophical question.
Are these two different dogs?
Or are these, in fact,
two pictures of the same dog?
The truth is,
it's impossible to say!
We just don't have
enough information.
But this question of whether
things are the same or different
is at the heart of what we call
"identity."
Identity isn't just important
for dogs though.
It's also a critical aspect
of how SwiftUI
understands your app.
Let's look at an example.
This is an app I made called
"Good Dog, Bad Dog,"
which helps me keep track
of whether my furry friend
has been on her best behavior.
It's pretty simple.
I can just tap
anywhere on the screen
to flip between
the good and bad states.
So what does identity
have to do with my app?
Well, it's actually very similar
to that philosophical question
we just asked about the dogs.
Looking at those icons, do those
seem like two different views,
completely distinct
from each other?
Or could they be the same view,
just in a different place
and with a different color?
That distinction
actually matters a great deal
because it changes
how our interface
transitions from one state
to another.
Let's say those icons are,
in fact, different views.
That means the icons
should transition independently,
such as fading in and out.
But what if they're,
in fact, the same view?
That would instead imply
that the view
should slide across the screen
during the transition
because it's the same view
moving from one location
to the other.
So connecting views across
different states is important,
because that's
how SwiftUI understands
how to transition
between them.
This is the key concept
behind view identity.
Views that share
the same identity
represent different states of
the same conceptual UI element.
In contrast, views that
represent distinct UI elements
will always have
different identities.
Later in the talk,
Luca and Raj will talk about
the practical impacts
of view identity
on your app's data
and update cycle.
For now, let's look
at how identity
is represented in your code,
focusing on
the two different types
of identity used by SwiftUI.
First, explicit identity:
using custom
or data-driven identifiers.
And second, structural identity:
distinguishing views
by their type and position
in the view hierarchy.
Now, to help understand
these concepts,
let me introduce you
to some more of my friends.
OK, remember that it can
be difficult to tell dogs apart,
especially when
they look the same.
So what kind
of extra information
would help us identify our dogs?
One way would be
to simply ask for their names.
If two dogs look the same
and also share the same name,
then I'd say it's pretty likely
that they're,
in fact, the same dog.
But if they have
different names,
then we can guarantee
that they are,
in fact, different dogs.
Assigning names
or identifiers like this
is a form of explicit identity.
Explicit identity is powerful
and flexible,
but does require that
someone, somewhere
keeps track of all those names.
One form of explicit identity
you may already be used to
is pointer identity,
which is used throughout
UIKit and AppKit.
Now, SwiftUI doesn't use
pointer identity,
but learning about it
will help you better understand
how and why SwiftUI
works differently.
Let's take a quick look.
Consider a UIKit or AppKit
view hierarchy, like this one.
Since UIViews
and NSViews are classes,
they each have a unique pointer
to their memory allocation.
The pointer is a natural source
of explicit identity.
We can refer to individual views
just using their pointer,
and if two views
share the same pointer,
we can guarantee that
they are really the same view.
But SwiftUI
doesn't use pointers
because SwiftUI views
are value types,
commonly represented
as structs instead of classes.
In the "SwiftUI essentials" talk
from 2019,
we discussed why SwiftUI
uses value types
instead of classes
for its views,
so I recommend watching
that talk to learn more.
For now, the important
thing to know is that
value types do not have
a canonical reference that
SwiftUI can use as a persistent
identity for its views.
Instead, SwiftUI relies on other
forms of explicit identity.
For example, consider this list
of rescue dogs.
The id parameter used here
is a form of explicit identity.
The dog tag ID of each
rescue dog is used
to explicitly identify its
corresponding view in the list.
If the collection
of rescue dogs changes,
SwiftUI can use those IDs to
understand what exactly changed
and generate the correct
animations within the list.
In this case, SwiftUI was even
able to correctly animate views
moving between
different sections.
Let's look at a more advanced
example.
Here, we're using
a ScrollViewReader
to jump to the top of the view
using a button at the bottom.
The id(_:) modifier provides a way
to explicitly identify a view
using a custom identifier --
in this case, our header view
at the top of the page.
Then we can pass that identifier
to the scroll view proxy's
scrollTo(_:) method
to tell SwiftUI
to go to that specific view.
What's great about this is that
we don't have to explicitly
identify every view,
just the ones we need to refer
to elsewhere in the code,
like our header text.
By comparison,
the ScrollViewReader,
ScrollView, backstory Text,
and Bbutton
do not need explicit
identifiers.
But just because their identity
isn't explicit,
that doesn't mean these views
have no identity at all
because every view
has an identity,
even if it's not explicit.
This is where
structural identity comes in.
SwiftUI uses the structure
of your view hierarchy
to generate implicit
identities for your views
so you don't have to.
Now, let me bring in
some more of my friends
to help explain
what I mean by that.
Let's say we have
two similar dogs
but we don't know their names,
but we still need
to identify each one.
Well, suppose these
are very good dogs
and they're capable
of sitting very still.
If we can guarantee
they don't move,
we could identify them just
based on where they're sitting,
like "The dog on the left"
or "The dog on the right".
We're using the relative
arrangement of our subjects
to distinguish them
from each other --
that's structural identity.
SwiftUI leverages structural
identity throughout its API,
and a classic example
is when you use if statements
and other conditional logic
within your View code.
The structure of
the conditional statement
gives us a clear way
to identify each view.
The first view only shows
when the condition is true,
while the second view only shows
when the condition is false.
That means we can always
tell which view is which,
even if they happen
to look similarly.
However, this only works if
SwiftUI can statically guarantee
that these views stay where
they are and never swap places.
SwiftUI accomplishes this
by looking at the type structure
of your view hierarchy.
When SwiftUI
looks at your views,
it sees their generic types --
in this case, our if statement
translated into
a _ConditionalContent view,
which is generic over
its true and false content.
This translation is powered
by a ViewBuilder,
which is a type
of result builder in Swift.
The View protocol implicitly
wraps its body property
in a ViewBuilder, which
constructs a single generic view
from the logic statements
in our property.
The some View return type
of our body property
is a placeholder that represents
this static composite type,
hiding it away so it doesn't
clutter up our code.
Using this generic type,
SwiftUI can guarantee
that the true view will always
be the AdoptionDirectory,
while the False view
will always be the DogList,
allowing them to be assigned
an implicit, stable identity
behind the scenes.
In fact, this is the key
to understanding
the Good Dog, Bad Dog app
from earlier.
With the code on the top,
we have an if statement
that defines different views
for each conditional branch.
This will cause the views
to transition in and out
because SwiftUI understands that
each branch of the if statement
represents a different view
with a distinct identity.
Alternatively, we could just
have a single PawView
that changes
its layout and color.
When it transitions
to a different state,
the view will smoothly slide
to its next position.
That's because we're
modifying a single view
with a consistent identity.
Both of these strategies
can work,
but SwiftUI generally recommends
the second approach.
By default,
try to preserve identity
and provide
more fluid transitions.
This also helps preserve
your view's lifetime and state,
which Luca will talk about
in more detail later on.
Now that we understand
structural identity,
we need to talk about
its evil nemesis, AnyView.
To understand the impact
of using AnyView,
let's look at the effect
that it has
on the structure of your views.
Earlier we wrote
this if statement
to switch between
the AdoptionDirectory
and the DogList.
When SwiftUI looks at this code,
it sees the generic
type structure on the right.
Now let's look
at a different example,
one that uses AnyView
extensively.
This is a helper function
I've written
to get a view that represents
a dog's breed.
Each conditional branch
in the function
returns a different
kind of view,
so I've wrapped them all
in AnyViews
because Swift requires
a single return type
for the whole function.
Unfortunately, this also means
that SwiftUI can't see
the conditional structure
of my code.
Instead, it just sees an AnyView
as a return type
of the function.
This is because AnyView
is what's called
a "type-erasing wrapper type" --
it hides the type of the view
it is wrapping
from its generic signature.
But perhaps more importantly,
this code is also
just really hard to read
for us mere humans.
Let's see if we can
simplify this code
and also make more of its
structure visible to SwiftUI.
First, it looks like this branch
is conditionally adding
a SheepView alongside
our BorderCollieView
if there are sheep nearby.
We can simplify this by
conditionally adding the view
inside the HStack
rather than
conditionally adding
the HStack around our views.
With that change,
it's now easy to see
that we're just returning
a single view from each branch,
so our local dogView variable
isn't necessary.
Instead, we can replace it
with return statements
inside of each branch.
As we saw earlier,
normal SwiftUI View code
can use if statements that
return different types of views.
But if we just try deleting
the return statements
and AnyViews from our code,
we see some errors
and warnings appear.
This is because SwiftUI
requires a single return type
from our helper function.
So how can we avoid
these errors?
Recall that the body property
of a view is special,
because the View protocol
implicitly wraps it
in a ViewBuilder.
This translates
the logic in the property
into a single, generic
view structure.
Now, Swift does not infer
helper functions
to be view builders by default,
but we can opt into that
by manually applying the
ViewBuilder attribute ourselves.
And that allows us to remove
the return statements
and the AnyView wrappers
without any warnings or errors.
OK, our code is looking
pretty good now!
We've gotten rid
of all of the AnyViews,
making it easier to read
than before.
And if we look at the type
signature of the result,
it now exactly replicates
the conditional logic
of our function with
a tree of conditional content,
providing SwiftUI
with a much richer perspective
of the view and the identities
of its components.
But there's one more small
improvement we can make.
The top level of our function
is just matching
against different cases
of the dog's breed.
This seems like an excellent
use case for a switch statement,
which are also supported
by view builders.
Now it's even easier
to quickly understand
all the different cases
of our view.
And because switch statements
are really just syntactic sugar
for conditional statements,
our resulting view's
type signature on the right
remains exactly the same.
Stepping back,
we just showed you
how AnyViews erase type
information from your code,
and walked through how to
get rid of unnecessary AnyViews
by leveraging view builders.
In general, we recommend
avoiding AnyViews
whenever possible.
Having too many AnyViews
will often make code
harder to read and understand.
Traditional control flow
statements
like if/else and switch
make it much easier
to see the different possible
states of a view.
And because AnyView
hides static type information
from the compiler,
it can sometimes prevent helpful
diagnostic errors and warnings
from being surfaced
in your code.
Finally, keep in mind that using
AnyView when you don't need to
can result in worse performance.
When possible, use generics to
preserve static type information
rather than passing AnyViews
around your code.
And with that, we've finished
introducing the basic types
of view identity in SwiftUI.
With explicit identity,
we can tie the identity
of our views to our data,
or provide custom identifiers
to refer to specific views.
And with structural identity,
we've learned how SwiftUI
can identify our views
just based on their type
and position
within the view hierarchy.
And now I'll hand things
over to Luca
to discuss
how the identity of your views
is related to their lifetime
and state.
Luca Bernardi: Thanks, Matt.
Now that we understand how
SwiftUI identifies your views,
let's explore how identity
ties into the lifetime
of your views and data.
This will help you better
understand how SwiftUI works.
To help illustrate this,
I'm also going
to bring in a friend.
This is Theseus.
Isn't he adorable, too?
Someone will say more adorable,
but I digress.
It is very intuitive
for us to think that
once we name our favorite pet,
he'll always be
the same adorable cat,
even when he is
in different states
and he moves
throughout the day.
When we look at him one moment,
he might be sleepy
and a moment later,
being a proper cat,
he's annoyed by my presence --
but he'll always be Theseus.
This is the essence of
connecting identity to lifetime.
Identity allows us
to define a stable element
for different values over time.
In other words, it allows us to
introduce continuity over time.
You might be wondering,
how does this apply to SwiftUI?
So let's bring back
a cat-friendly version
of the app
Matt was working on.
Just like Theseus
can be in different states
at different moments in time,
our views are also
in different states
throughout their lifetime.
Every single state is
a different value for our view.
Identity connects
these different values
as a single entity --
a view -- over time.
Let's look at some code
to clarify this.
Here we have a simple view
that displays
the intensity of purring.
Spoiler: Theseus is pretty loud.
Through the evaluation of body,
SwiftUI will create a new value
for this view;
in this case, with an intensity
value of 25.
Theseus is getting hungry
and wants more attention.
body is invoked again
with a higher intensity,
and the new value for the view
is created.
These are two distinct values
created from the same
view definition.
SwiftUI will keep around
a copy of the value
to perform a comparison and
know if the view has changed.
But after that,
the value is destroyed.
What it is important
to understand here is that
the view value is different
from the view identity.
View values are ephemeral
and you should not
rely on their lifetime.
But what you can control
is their identity.
When a view is first created
and it appears,
SwiftUI assigns it an identity
using a combination
of the techniques
discussed before.
Over time, driven by updates,
new values for the view
are created.
But from SwiftUI's perspective,
these represent the same view.
Once the identity
of the view changes
or the view is removed,
its lifetime ends.
Whenever we talk about
the lifetime of a view,
we are referring to
the duration of the identity
associated with that view.
Being able to connect
the identity of a view
with its lifetime
is fundamental to understand
how SwiftUI persists your state.
So let's bring State and
StateObject into the picture.
When SwiftUI
is looking at your view
and sees a State
or a StateObject,
it knows that it needs
to persist that piece of data
throughout the view's lifetime.
In other words,
State and StateObject
are the persistent storage
associated with your
view's identity.
At the beginning
of a view's identity,
when it's created
for the first time,
SwiftUI is going to allocate
storage in memory
for State and StateObject
using their initial values.
Here we are focusing on
the title state.
Throughout the lifetime
of the view,
SwiftUI will persist this
storage as it gets mutated
and the view's body
is re-evaluated.
Let's look at a concrete example
of how changes in identity
affect the persistence of state.
This is an interesting example
because we have the same view
but in two separate branches.
If you remember from before,
because of structural identity,
the two views are considered
to have different identities.
Matt has discussed
how this affects animations,
but this also has
a profound impact
on the persistence
of your state.
Let's see this in practice.
When we first evaluate body
and we enter the true branch,
SwiftUI will allocate
persistent storage for the state
with its initial value.
Throughout the lifetime
of this view,
SwiftUI persists the state
as it gets mutated
by various actions.
But what happens if
the value of dayTime changes
and we enter the false branch?
SwiftUI knows this is
a different view
with a distinct identity.
It creates new storage
for the false view,
starting with
the state's initial value,
and the storage for the true
view is deallocated right after.
But what if we go back
to the true branch?
Well, that's a new view again,
so SwiftUI creates new storage,
starting again from
the state's initial value.
The takeaway here is that
whenever the identity changes,
the state is replaced.
Let me pause here for a moment
and make sure
that you understand
this important point:
the persistence of your state
is tied to the lifetime
of your views.
This is a very powerful concept
because we can clearly separate
what is the essence of a view --
its state --
and tie that to its identity.
Everything else
can be derived from it.
And your data is so important
that SwiftUI has a set
of data-driven constructs that
use the identity of your data
as a form of explicit identity
for your views.
The canonical example
of this is ForEach.
Let's now take a look
at all of the different ways
you can initialize a ForEach.
This will help us build a better
intuition around this type.
The simplest form of ForEach is
one that takes a constant range.
This is a very convenient
initializer,
especially when
you are getting started
prototyping some new UI.
SwiftUI is going to use
the offset in this range
to identify the views produced
by the view builder.
By requiring a constant range,
we guarantee that
the identities are stable
for the lifetime of the view.
In fact, it is an error
to use this initializer
with a dynamic range.
And new this year,
you will see a warning
when providing
a non-constant range.
Let's make things
more interesting
and bring in a dynamic
collection of data.
This initializer takes
a collection
and a keypath to a property
serving as an identifier.
This property must be hashable
because SwiftUI
is going to use its value
to assign an identity
to all the views generated from
the elements of the collection.
Later, Raj is going
to show you some examples
of how choosing
a stable identity affects
the performance and
correctness of your app.
This idea of providing
a stable identity for your data
is so important that
the standard library
defines the Identifiable
protocol
to describe this capability.
And SwiftUI takes full
advantage of this protocol,
allowing you to omit
the key path
and use the identifier provided
by the protocol requirement
to define the identity
associated with your data
and your views.
Something that I really love
about Swift is that
we can take advantage
of its type system
to precisely describe
the constraints of the problem
that we are solving.
So indulge with me
in taking a look
at the definition of the
initializer we are using here.
There are a lot of interesting
things in this short definition,
so let's try to unpack them.
ForEach needs two main pieces:
a collection --
here indicated by
the generic argument Data --
and a way to generate a view
from each element
of the collection.
The shape of this initializer
should give you the intuition
that ForEach defines
a relationship
between a collection of data
and a collection of views.
But actually, the most
interesting part here
is that we constrain
the elements of the collection
to be Identifiable.
Again, the purpose
of the Identifiable protocol
is to allow for your type
to provide
a stable notion of identity
so that SwiftUI
can keep track of your data
throughout its lifetime.
In fact, this is very similar
to the concepts
of identity and lifetime
that we discussed earlier.
SwiftUI views that takes
an Identifiable type
and a view builder
are data-driven components.
These views use
the identity of the data
that you provide
to scope the lifetime
of the views
associated to it.
Choosing a good identifier
is your opportunity
to control the lifetime
of your views and data.
So let's recap what we have
discussed in this section.
Views values are ephemeral
and you should not
rely on their lifetime.
But their identity is not,
and is what gives them
continuity over time.
You are in control
of the identity of your views,
and you can use identity
to clearly scope
the lifetime of state.
And finally, SwiftUI
takes full advantage
of the Identifiable protocol
for data-driven components,
so it's important to choose a
stable identifier for your data.
And now continuing
the tradition,
I'm going to hand it over
to Raj. Raj?
Raj Ramamurthy: Thanks, Luca!
So far, we've explained
what identity is
and how it ties into
a view's lifetime.
Next, I'm going to dive into
how SwiftUI updates the UI.
The goal is to give you
a better mental model
for how to structure
SwiftUI code.
I'm also going to show
a few examples
outlining everything at the end.
To kick this discussion
of dependencies off,
let's look at a view.
Here's a simple view.
It shows a button that
rewards a dog with a treat.
Sorry, Luca,
but I'm more of a dog person.
Let's focus on
the structure of the view.
First, let's look at the top.
There are two properties:
one for a dog
and another for a treat.
These properties are
dependencies of the view.
A dependency is just
an input to the view.
When a dependency changes,
the view is required
to produce a new body.
The body is where you build
the hierarchy for the view.
Diving into this view's
hierarchy,
we have a button
with an action.
Actions are what trigger changes
to a view's dependencies.
Let's swap the code out
for an equivalent diagram.
Here's a diagram of our DogView.
When we tap on the button,
it dispatches an action
to reward the dog.
Our dog gulps down the treat
in a flash.
And that results in
a change to the dog --
maybe he wants another.
Because the dependency changed,
DogView produces a new body.
To learn more about
the general concepts
of data flow in SwiftUI,
check out
"Data essentials in SwiftUI"
from WWDC 2020.
Next, let's simplify
this diagram a bit.
Focusing in on
the view hierarchy,
notice how our views
form a tree-like structure.
And if we add the dog and treat
dependencies back at the top,
it still looks like a tree.
However, the DogView is not the
only view with dependencies.
In SwiftUI, each view can have
its own set of dependencies.
So far, this still
looks like a tree.
But note, there can be
multiple views
dependent on the same state
or other data.
For example,
one of the descendants
might depend on the dog, too.
And this could happen for
one of our other dependencies.
So we started with a tree,
but this structure
only loosely resembles
a tree now.
In fact, if we rearrange it
to avoid overlapping lines,
we end up with this structure,
which reveals that this is
actually a graph, not a tree.
In fact, we call this structure
the "dependency graph".
This structure is important
because it allows SwiftUI
to efficiently update
only those views
that require a new body.
Take, for example,
the dependency at the bottom.
If we examine this dependency,
it has two dependent views.
The secret of the graph is that
if the dependency changes,
only those views
will be invalidated.
SwiftUI will call
each view's body,
producing a new body value
for each view.
SwiftUI will instantiate
the values
of each invalidated view's body.
That may result in more
dependencies changing,
but not always!
Because views are value types,
SwiftUI can efficiently
compare them
to only update
the right subset of views.
This is another way to look at
what Luca discussed earlier.
A view's value is short-lived.
The struct value is just used
for comparison,
but the view itself
has a longer lifetime.
And that's how we can avoid
generating a new body
for the view in the center.
An identity is the backbone
of the dependency graph.
As Matt said,
every view has identity,
whether specified explicitly
or structurally.
That identity is how SwiftUI
routes changes
to the right views
and efficiently updates the UI.
There are many kinds
of dependencies.
We saw a few examples
earlier with the treat property
and the dog binding,
but you can also form
dependencies by using
the environment, state,
or any of the observable object
property wrappers.
Next, I'd like to talk about
how to improve
the use of identity
in your views.
This will help SwiftUI
better understand your code.
As Luca said,
the lifetime of a view
is the duration of its identity,
and that means the stability
of an identifier is crucial.
An identifier that isn't stable
can result in
a shorter view lifetime.
And having a stable identifier
also helps performance,
since SwiftUI doesn't
need to continually
create storage for the view
and churn through
updating the graph.
As you saw earlier,
SwiftUI uses lifetime
to manage persisted storage,
so stable identifiers
are also important
for avoiding loss of state.
Let's turn to a code example
to explain the importance
of identifier stability.
In this example, I have a list
of my favorite pets.
We've got an identifier
on our pet struct.
But there's actually a bug;
every time I get a new pet,
everything on screen flashes!
Let's stop for a second
and look at this code.
Can you spot
where the bug is?
The bug is here, in our
Identifiable conformance.
If you didn't pass the test,
don't worry;
there are no treats
in this section.
The problem is that
this identifier isn't stable,
so anytime the data changes,
we get a new identifier.
What if instead, we used
the indices of our pets array?
Unfortunately, this has
a similar problem.
By using the indices,
views are now identified by
the position of their respective
pet in the collection.
If I decide I have
a new first favorite pet,
all the other pets
will change their identity,
which could cause a bad bug.
In this example, the button
inserts a new element
at index zero, but because
the last index is the new one,
we get an insertion at the end
instead of the start.
This is because, like
computed random identifiers,
indices are not
a stable form of identity.
In this example, we need
to use a stable identifier,
like one from a database
or derived from
stable properties of the pet.
Any persistent identifier
is a great choice.
Now our animation looks great!
But stability isn't
the only property we need
for good identifiers.
Another property of good
identifiers is uniqueness.
Each identifier should map
to a single view.
This ensures that
animations look great,
performance is smooth,
and the dependencies
of your hierarchy
are reflected in
the most efficient form.
Let's look at another example.
In this example,
I'm working on a view
with all of my pet's
favorite treats.
Each treat has a name, an emoji,
and an expiration date.
I've chosen to identify
each treat by its name.
At this point --
I'm sure you can guess --
we have a bug here, too.
What happens when we have
more than one
of the same kind of treat?
I don't know about you,
but I like to buy dog biscuits
in bulk.
When I add them to the jar,
they might not show up!
The problem is that
the name of a treat
is not a unique identifier
for it.
Instead, we can use
a serial number
or other unique ID per treat.
And this ensures all the right
data is shown in our jar.
It will also ensure
better animations
and better performance.
When SwiftUI needs an
identifier, it needs your help!
Please be careful when using
random identifiers,
especially in computed
properties.
In general, you want all of
your identifiers to be stable.
An identifier shouldn't
change over time;
a new identifier represents
a new item with a new lifetime.
And lastly, identifiers
need to be unique.
Multiple views
can't share an identifier.
SwiftUI relies on
these properties
to make your app
run smoothly and bug-free.
Now that we've talked
about explicit identity,
I'd like to move on
to structural identity.
In this example, I'm working
on the treat jar from earlier.
As a responsible pet lover,
I only feed my pets
the finest, unexpired foods.
To help me tell when treats
have gone bad,
I've added a new modifier that
optionally dims a treat cell
when the treat is expired.
I've highlighted the cell
that's dimmed.
Let's dive into the modifier.
You can see that
in the modifier, I have a date
and compare it
to the current date
to know when to dim the view.
This seems fine at first blush,
but there's a subtle
problem here.
If the condition changes
and our treat becomes expired,
we end up with a new identity
because there is a branch here.
As Matt discussed, branches are
a form of structural identity.
This means we have
two copies of the content
instead of a single,
optionally modified copy.
Note that the branch here
is in a modifier.
For clarity, I've put
the modifier and its use site
on the same slide,
but in your project,
you might have branches
like this across files
without even being aware of it!
Of course, everything
we've discussed here
applies to views
and view modifiers.
So how can we avoid this?
Well, one way is to fold
the branches together
and move the condition inside
the opacity modifier, like so.
By removing this branch,
we've correctly
described this view
as having a single identity.
Furthermore,
moving the condition
inside the opacity modifier
can help performance,
because we've tightly scoped
the dependent code.
Now when the condition changes,
only the opacity
needs to change.
The trick to this is that
when the condition is true,
we have an opacity of 1,
which looks like this.
An opacity of 1 has no effect.
We call modifiers like this
"inert modifiers,"
because they don't
affect the rendered result.
SwiftUI modifiers are cheap,
so there is little inherent cost
with this pattern.
Because there is
no resulting visual effect,
the framework can efficiently
prune away the modifier,
further reducing its cost.
Branches are great,
and they exist in SwiftUI
for a reason.
But when used unnecessarily,
they can cause poor performance,
surprising animations,
and, as Luca showed,
even loss of state.
When you introduce a branch,
pause for a second
and consider whether
you're representing
multiple views or two states
of the same view.
As we saw, it often works better
to use an inert modifier
instead of a branch
to identify a single view.
Here are just a few examples
of inert modifiers.
I especially love
transformEnvironment
for conditionally writing
to the environment.
Putting everything together,
we've shown you today
that identity
is one of the secrets
to amazing performance.
We've discussed explicit
and structural identity,
and how you can
take advantage of each
to improve your app.
From identity, we can derive
a view's lifetime,
which controls its associated
storage, transitions, and more.
And we've also explained
that SwiftUI
uses identity and lifetime
to form dependencies,
which are represented
by a graph
that can efficiently
update the UI.
Along with demystifying SwiftUI,
we've given you
some tips and tricks
to avoid bugs and improve
performance in your apps.
And now that you've learned
these tricks,
take a tour through your code
to see if they can help you.
Thank you, and keep building
great apps!
♪