[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Jacob] Hey, I'm Jacob.
Welcome to "SF Symbols in SwiftUI."
We're going to look at a few topics
during this session.
First, some of the fundamentals
of using SF Symbols from SwiftUI.
Then, how to use variants of your symbols.
And finally,
working with the new Rendering Modes.
One note on the availability
of these APIs:
everything we'll see in this session
is available on all Apple platforms,
and look for the new badge to know
when something's new
in this year's releases.
Let's get into the fundamentals.
If you've already used Symbols
from SwiftUI,
this part should be a breeze.
To start, let's just show a Symbol.
The most simple way is to use one
of the system-provided symbols,
like "heart," in an Image.
A Label view is the other
main way to show symbols.
A Label is a combination
of a title with an icon,
which is most often a symbol.
The great thing about a label is
that it's a general description
of this pairing
and will adapt its behavior
to the context where it's shown.
For example, in many components,
the label will be shown with the symbol,
and then the title.
Sometimes, they'll be shown
in a different layout,
or sometimes, a component will show
only the symbol or only the title.
SwiftUI automatically makes these changes
for you in built-in views,
and you can use label styles
in your own views to do it, too.
You can show custom symbols
in both Image and Label
by just changing the initializer you use.
This is what each of these
configurations looks like,
but their visual representation
isn't the only one that matters.
This is how each of these views
will appear to VoiceOver by default.
You can see that using Label
automatically gives us
great Accessibility support,
since the title gives
a textual description
of the content.
Let's look closer at the image-only cases.
When possible,
SwiftUI will provide a label
based on a system symbol's content.
This might be all you need,
like if you were using a heart
for a "love" button.
However, some symbols
don't have a standard meaning,
and in those cases,
the default Accessibility description
won't be as useful.
You also might be able to add
more specific information
about how your app is using the symbol.
You can always use an accessibilityLabel
to provide that information.
Our custom symbol is another case
where we're not getting
an ideal accessibility description.
A great way to improve that
is to provide a localization
for the image's name
in a Localizable.strings file.
SwiftUI will automatically
use this localizable string
for the accessibility label
of this image anywhere it's used.
One last way to use symbols
is as part of Text.
You can embed a symbol
inside a run of text
by using string interpolation.
This is a good technique to use
when you want a symbol to reflow
along with your text, like this chevron.
Okay, let's go back
to our Label with the heart
and look at some
of the modifiers we can apply
to symbols to customize them.
Let's start by changing our symbols' color
with the foregroundStyle modifier.
Text and symbols default to black or white
in light mode or dark mode.
You can set the foregroundStyle
to a specific color, like red,
or to more semantic values,
like the current tint or secondary style.
We'll come back
to foregroundStyle again later
to see some more advanced effects
we can do with it.
You can use a font modifier
to change both the text size,
as well as the size of your symbols.
If you use a text style,
like body or caption,
then the text and symbol will scale
with dynamic type,
and if you choose a fixed size,
then they stay constant.
The other axis where you can change
the size of symbols is their scale,
using the imageScale modifier.
This doesn't change
the font size that's used,
but how large a symbol appears
relative to text.
Next, let's take a look at variants.
You may have noticed that iOS tab bars
should use filled symbol variants.
In the past, this was something
that you had to do yourself
by carefully choosing the right symbol
from the Symbols app,
and knowing when a symbol
didn't have a fill variant,
like "sparkles" here.
New this year, tab bars and other views
now automatically opt
into specific variants,
like fill, to be applied
to any symbols they contain.
This means you can just use
the base version of the symbol
and get the right variant
without any extra work.
And by not over-specifying
the exact configuration you want,
you also get code that's more reusable.
For example,
if we run this same code on macOS,
we get the correct variant
for that platform: outlines.
We can use this variant support
in our own components, as well.
Here, I have a simple list of labels,
shown with the default outline variant.
To use filled variants here,
I can use the new symbolVariant modifier.
This modifier sets the specified variant
in the environment,
so it's great to use
on a whole view hierarchy,
like we're doing here.
There's a large set of variants available:
fill, slash,
and a set of shape encapsulations.
And these can be combined
with each other, as well,
the same way they're combined in the names
of the symbols themselves,
like .circle.fill.
This same set of variants works
on your custom symbols, as well.
All you have to do is follow
the same naming patterns
used by system symbols.
Next, let's look at rendering modes.
Symbols support four different
rendering modes to allow you
to customize the way
your symbols are colored.
Here are some examples
of each rendering mode.
We'll go over them one by one.
And if you want to learn more
about the design
of the different rendering modes,
I highly recommend
"What's new in SF Symbols."
Okay, let's go back to our list of cards,
this time on macOS.
Right now, our symbols are showing
the default rendering mode,
which is monochrome.
This works well
for showing consistent colors
for a set of symbols.
However, in this case,
I'd like to show these symbols
using the colors associated
with each card.
The multicolor rendering mode
is a great way to show colors
for what each symbol represents.
And we can change to it
by adding a symbolRenderingMode
modifier on multicolor.
If a symbol doesn't have
a multicolor representation,
it will fall back
to the monochrome rendering mode.
You can use the SF Symbols app
to look up which symbols
have multicolor definitions
and to add multicolor support
to your custom symbols.
Check out the "SF Symbols App Overview"
to learn more.
In another part of this app,
we have some buttons
to shuffle cards to different parts
of the deck.
I'd like to emphasize
the key parts of these symbols
with different levels of opacity.
Do you remember
which rendering mode does that?
That's right!
Hierarchical!
We can use the same
symbolRenderingMode modifier
with hierarchical.
This uses the current foreground style
to apply a single color to the symbol,
like monochrome,
but also adds multiple levels of opacity,
to emphasize
the key elements of the symbol.
There's one last rendering mode,
and there's a button
in my app that it could help with.
I'm not very good at card games,
so I need this button to undo my mistakes.
Here, I'm showing
a symbol in a button
with a .circle.fill variant
to get this circular background.
But the coloring isn't exactly
what I want.
I'd like something that better matches
the color of our cards.
Remember that we can use
the foregroundStyle modifier
to set a color on a symbol.
But we can go further.
New this year, we can set multiple colors
to be used to draw our symbol.
This uses the palette rendering mode,
which allows maximum control
over the coloring of the layers
of a symbol.
You can specify up to three styles
to control each level of the symbol.
This symbol has primary
and tertiary content,
so the first and third colors
will be used.
If we used a symbol that just has
primary and secondary content,
like the outline version of this symbol,
then only those colors would be used.
Because most individual symbols
only use two layers,
like both of these,
you can specify two styles
instead of three,
and the last style is used
for everything from secondary onwards.
In many cases, this is all you need.
We've been using colors so far,
but this is a foreground
style modifier,
and it works with any ShapeStyle.
We can use a secondary style
to get a vibrant effect in front of blurs,
or even use a material
to blur the background
behind a symbol.
If you want to learn more
about foreground styles and materials,
check out "Add rich graphics
to your SwiftUI app."
Let's look back at the full
set of rendering modes again.
The best way to see and choose
which rendering modes to use
is the SF Symbols app and its inspector.
And these APIs to express
these configurations in SwiftUI
work the same way,
so it's easy to go back and forth
between the Symbols app and your code.
You also get the best behavior
with minimal configuration.
If you have only one foreground style,
and don't specify a rendering mode,
you'll automatically get monochrome.
And if you specify more
than one foreground style,
but don't specify a rendering mode,
you'll automatically get palette.
The Symbols app has a large set
of colors available to use
with these different rendering modes.
And that full set of colors
is available in SwiftUI, as well,
including several colors and styles
that are new this year.
These colors are optimized
for all the different configurations
they appear in:
light and dark mode,
special rendering over blurs,
even the specific platform
they're shown on.
We just saw how to create symbols,
a set of modifiers
to change their appearance,
how to change which variant
of a symbol is shown,
choosing different rendering modes,
and how to use foreground styles
to customize your symbol's coloring.
SF Symbols make it easy
to add beautiful graphics to your app
and to customize them as little
or as much as you want.
See where you can adopt them
to make your apps look even better.
Thanks for watching
and have a great WWDC.
[upbeat music]