[MAC ST ARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Simon Goldrei: Hello.
This session is all about
how to transition media
gaplessly with HLS.
I'm Simon and I'm a member
of the Streaming Media team
here at Apple!
Do you utilize AVQueuePlayer,
or would like to offer
your customers
a seamless, Up Next-style
playback of HLS items
in your application?
Do you want to present
your media with the continuity
that the producer intended?
Can we support our customers
by providing an experience
to enjoy our media for longer?
If yes, then you've tuned in
to the best session
to learn how you can now
transition HLS items gaplessly.
Here's our agenda.
We'll survey some of
the engaging media experiences
you can deliver
with this new feature,
I'll detail the media
authoring requirements,
I'll step through some
playlist examples
highlighting best practices,
and we'll end with a demo.
The benefits of transitioning
between HLS-backed AVPlayerItems
in an AVQueuePlayer
are straightforward.
Until now,
the point of transition
could be a little jarring;
anything from an audible glitch
to a momentary visual hiccup
or even an indication
of indeterminate buffering.
Gapless item transitions
maintain a bond
that your application provides
between the customer
and the content.
Perhaps you recall the phrase
"don't touch that dial."
You can build
an episodic treatment
that seamlessly transitions
from the end of one episode
into the start of another.
Gapless transitions permit
the ability to replicate
the seamless track-to-track
album experiences
that we've long enjoyed.
When doing this,
we're delivering
a more correct reproduction
of what may have been live
or intentionally authored.
We can deliver an experience
that is unbroken
and uninterrupted.
We can replicate
linear programming.
But we can also provide
a dynamic and perhaps even
interactive experience
that takes the viewer
from one task or scene
and directly segues
into the next.
Consider a transition
between a set of workouts
or other instructional media.
With gapless transitions
we can now, programmatically,
stitch scenes
of an audiovisual sequence
while maintaining
accurate continuity.
You can add reps...
...or add a cooldown,
to the workout.
We can achieve all of this
while still delivering media
with all the benefits
of adaptive bitrate media
streaming over HTTP.
Of course, we use this, too!
New features of Apple Music
deliver content via HLS
and achieve a gapless
transition between each song.
We're very excited to bring this
to our customers,
and we'd like to offer this
to your customers, too.
Let's now take detailed look
at the authoring requirements
you need to incorporate to
affect the same item transitions
in your HLS content.
By providing --
in your HLS manifests --
variants that offer
audio-format continuity
between sequential items,
you're enabling
a gapless transition.
Your content should provide
variants that match
the following
audio media traits:
the use of FairPlay Streaming,
the audio codec --
specified by the codecs
attribute of the Stream tag --
and the channel count,
as specified by the Channels
attribute of the Media tag.
Note that if you decide
to offer audio renditions,
at different sample
rates and bit depth,
you may inhibit
the gapless transition.
The same advice
to provide a match
and maintain continuity
applies to these traits, too.
Which is to say,
to achieve a gapless transition,
be sure to offer equivalent
audio media in each variant
for consecutively
enqueued items.
Finally,
when authoring your media,
please adhere to CMAF
authoring guidance.
CMAF stands for "common media
application format."
In this MPEG specification,
there is a specific
recommendation
to use an edit list to signal
the presence of priming
and remainder frames.
Let's now look
at a simple example
by inspecting
the master variant playlists
of two candidate items.
In this HLS manifest
I've offered four
audiovisual variants:
a pair of 720p variants
and a pair of 1080p variants.
Within each pair,
I offer a variant encoded
with the High-Efficiency
Advanced Audio Codec, HE_AAC,
and another with AAC
Low Complexity, or AAC_LC.
In this example, consider that
playback conditions support
the selection of the 720p video
paired with HE_AAC.
As playback nears the end,
the AVQueuePlayer will,
at least initially, select
the similarly encoded variant
offered in the subsequent item.
This is true even
if network conditions
now support
a higher-quality tier.
Servicing the gapless transition
is a higher priority
than choosing a high quality
when transitioning gaplessly.
As playback proceeds,
the adaptive bitrate heuristics
are evaluated and,
if the conditions persist,
the player will seamlessly
switch to that higher quality.
Fantastic!
Now suppose we didn't
offer HE_AAC in item two.
In that case, the AVQueuePlayer
is unable to maintain
audio continuity
and the gapless transition
but is free to select
the most appropriate
initial variant
for the playback conditions.
Let's say that we have
authored our content
to support a gapless transition.
In that case,
we should remind ourselves
how to use an AVQueuePlayer.
Here we have a short
code snippet.
We create two AVPlayerItems
and enqueue them, in order,
ahead of playback.
Note that our items
source from two different URLs.
After creating
our AVQueuePlayer,
we can use
the "insert after" method
to inform the queue player
of the intended sequence.
All that's left
is to message "play".
An advanced technique
I'd like to share with you
permits the use
of a single asset.
From this asset,
you can instantiate
multiple AVPlayerItems.
We can define different
in and out points
on each distinct AVPlayerItem,
prior to enqueuing
in our AVQueuePlayer.
Using the AVPlayerItem
seekToTime method,
we can define our in point.
Then we can define our out point
with forwardPlaybackEndTime.
Here's an illustration
of this concept.
Item one, two, and three are all
sourced from the same AVAsset,
consisting of the same
three scenes.
They are distinct in that
I have cued each
with different in points,
using seekToTime,
and defined distinct out points,
using forwardPlaybackEndTime.
Now I can enqueue these
three otherwise identical items
into my AVQueuePlayer,
and what I achieve
is a customized,
dynamic sequence.
Now let's see and hear
gapless transitions in action
with a demo.
In this demo, we will
interactively stitch together
three workout video streams.
I've left the AVKit controls
visible in each
so that you can really see these
are distinct stream resources.
I'll start by showing
a seamless playback of all three
and then we'll edit
the sequence interactively.
In your software, you can
imagine offering the same --
or perhaps perform the
reordering -- programmatically.
>> [WHOOSHING]
Right! Let's do a warm-up.
♪ Energetic electronic music ♪
♪
Ready or not?
Let's do a hills run.
♪ Lively hip-hop music ♪
♪
That's it! We're done.
It's time for a cooldown.
[WHISTLE TRILLS]
♪ Calm electronic music ♪
♪ <
I can break a sweat
just watching that.
I'm tempted to skip straight
to the "That's it, we're done,"
and skip the hills run.
There's a lot of that
here in San Francisco.
To do this, let's edit the order
of our exercise sets.
I'll move the hills exercise
to the top.
This allows me
to just do the warm-up
then immediately and gaplessly
segue into the cooldown.
Then I'll start by selecting
the warm-up,
now in the second position,
as my first workout.
>> [WHOOSHING]
Right! Let's do a warm-up.
♪ Energetic electronic music ♪
♪
That's it! We're done.
It's time for a cooldown.
[WHISTLE TRILLS]
♪ Calm electronic music ♪
♪ <
Let's summarize the key points
that we've learned
in this session.
We've learned that to achieve
gapless transitions using HLS,
we must provide variants
in each item
that have matching
audio formats.
Then we saw how easy it is
to instruct an AVQueuePlayer
to perform
the gapless transition
just by enqueuing items
in sequence.
We have one related session,
where we introduce new APIs
for variant discovery.
You may find that session useful
if your software or service
cannot guarantee the items
of matching audio format.
I hope you've enjoyed
this session
and enjoy the rest
of this WWDC 2021.
Thank you.
♪