[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Chris Donegan: Hi, I'm Chris,
an engineer on UIKit.
I'll be joined later by my
colleagues Anant and Mohammed.
iPad is the primary device
for many people
due to its power
and capabilities.
In this video, you'll learn
about some exciting new features
you should use to take
your iPad app to the next level.
First, I'll show you
the latest advancements
in multitasking and scenes.
Then, Anant
will walk you through
the powerful changes
to keyboard shortcuts.
Finally, Mohammed will show you
the latest enhancements
to the system pointer.
Let's get right into
multitasking.
iPadOS 13 introduced the ability
to run multiple instances
of your app's UI.
In iPadOS 15,
we're improving this experience
with new APIs
for scene presentation
as well as
enhanced state restoration.
These enhancements build upon
the existing UIScene
infrastructure.
If you haven't adopted
UIScene,
check out "Introducing
Multiple Windows on iPad."
Let's briefly go over
the key concepts.
A scene represents a single
instance of your app's UI.
The structure
of a scene's components
is defined by
a scene configuration.
At a minimum, it defines the
scene's role and delegate class.
You can also provide a name,
storyboard, and scene subclass.
Scene configurations can either
be declared in your Info.plist,
or created at runtime
using the
UISceneConfiguration object.
The content of a scene
is represented by
an NSUserActivity.
These activities are used
for requesting scenes
as well as
for state restoration.
A scene is managed
by a scene delegate.
The delegate is responsible
for setting up the UI,
responding to lifecycle events,
as well as saving
and restoring state.
Finally, a scene is tracked
by a scene session.
The scene itself can be
disconnected and reconnected
by the system
when it's in the background.
The scene session
tracks the scene
regardless
of its connection state
and persists between launches.
The session can be thought of
as the representation
in the system app switcher.
Each item in the switcher
corresponds to a scene session.
When requesting a scene
from the system,
you can provide
an options object
for customizing the request.
iPadOS 15 has
a new options subclass
specifically
for window scenes.
Using this subclass
allows you to specify
a presentation style.
Window scene
presentation styles
influence how
the scene is presented
relative to other scenes
in the workspace.
There are three possible values:
prominent, standard,
and automatic.
This is a scene using the
prominent presentation style.
It's presented modally
in the current workspace
with the scenes behind it
dimmed.
Because it's modal,
it should provide
Cancel, Close, or Done buttons.
This new style
can be thought of
as a staging ground
for new scenes.
It can be repositioned
like any other scene
using the new multitasking
controls,
and it can also be moved
into the app shelf for later.
When considering if this style
is appropriate for a scene,
there are some guidelines
to keep in mind.
First, prominent scenes
should be useful on their own.
They should not be used
for providing options or tools
for another scene.
They should provide
a Done or Close button,
and they should be dedicated
to specific content
within your app
like a document or file.
This dedicated content scope
must be defined
in the scene's
activation conditions.
For more information
on activation conditions,
check out "Targeting Content
with Multiple Windows."
This example shows how Safari
is opening a new scene
using the standard style.
They are presented side by side,
allowing interaction with each,
and both provide the full
functionality of the main scene.
You can also specify
automatic as the style.
This value tells the system
that it should choose
the best style
based on how it was requested.
iPadOS 15
not only provides
a way to customize presentation
using styles,
it also makes it easier
for people to open their content
in new scenes.
On the Mac, it's common to find
an Open in New Window item
in context menus.
You should bring this
familiar experience
to your iPad app by using
UIWindowScene.ActivationAction.
It's a new UIAction subclass
for requesting scenes
that can be used in menus,
buttons, and bar button items.
To add this functionality
to your app,
start by initializing a
UIWindowScene.ActivationAction.
It's initialized with a closure
that is executed
when the item is selected.
The closure should return
an activation configuration
with a user activity
for the new scene's content.
Finally, put the action in
a menu and you're good to go.
On iPad and Mac Catalyst,
the menu shows
an Open in New Window item
that, when selected,
will present a new scene.
On iPhone, the item
is automatically hidden
because multiple scenes
are not supported.
If you would rather show
another item in its place,
you can provide
an alternate action.
Let's update the previous
example to offer one.
To do this, start by creating
the alternate action.
The new action's title and image
are shown
when multiple windows
are not available.
Then, update the initializer
of the scene activation action
by passing the new action
as the alternate.
With an alternate
action provided,
the menus on iPad
and Mac Catalyst
still show
the Open in New Window item
but on iPhone, the Show Details
item is visible;
all done without
a single condition in your code.
Adding these menu items
is a clear and familiar way
for people to open their content
in new scenes.
But it's not the only way.
iPad is a touch-first device
and it's easy to open scenes
with a single gesture.
In the Notes app,
pinching out on a cell
opens the note in a new scene.
The scene interactively animates
from the cell
to its final position.
There are two ways
of offering this functionality
in your app.
If you're using
a collection view,
there's a new delegate method.
For other views,
use UIWindowScene
ActivationInteraction.
Both of these are only
for presenting scenes
with a prominent style.
To support this gesture
in your collection view,
implement the new delegate
method named
sceneActivationConfiguration
ForItemAt indexPath.
It's very similar to the context
menu example from earlier.
Create the user activity
for the new scene's content,
then return
an activation configuration
with that activity.
You may not want every cell
to support opening a new scene.
To prevent the gesture
from beginning,
just return nil.
To support this gesture
on other views,
create a UIWindowScene
.ActivationInteraction.
It's created with a closure
that accepts two arguments:
the interaction itself
and the point of the interaction
in the view's coordinate space.
These can be used to create
specific user activities
for different regions
of the view.
The closure should return
an activation configuration
with the user activity.
The interaction also
takes an error handler.
While the interaction
is disabled on platforms
that don't support
multiple scenes,
errors can still occur
due to configuration issues
or a lack of system resources.
You've probably noticed
that all of these ways
of presenting window scenes
use the same
activation configuration object.
Its only requirement
is a user activity,
but it also contains
scene request options
and a targeted preview.
If these are not provided,
the system will do its best
to create them for you.
However, you can explicitly
provide them
to refine the experience.
As an example,
these collection view cells
have a thumbnail,
title, and caption.
When the cell is pinched out,
a scene is presented
which mainly displays
the larger version
of the thumbnail's content.
Notice that the new scene
is transitioning
from the cell as a whole.
It would look better
if it transitioned
from just the thumbnail.
To achieve this effect,
the activation configuration
is created as before.
Then, check if the cell
is a thumbnail cell.
If so, use the cell's
thumbnail view
to create a targeted preview
and set it on the configuration.
By providing a custom preview
on the activation configuration,
the transition
is much more polished.
Let's take a closer look.
Now, rather than transitioning
from the cell itself,
it transitions
from the thumbnail,
leaving the rest of the cell
in place.
Activation configurations
allow you to request
any of your app's scenes.
However, you may simply
want to display a file
without having to build
a scene yourself.
iPadOS 15 makes this very easy.
There's a special subclass
of UIWindowScene
.ActivationConfiguration
called "QLPreviewScene
ActivationConfiguration".
Returning a preview scene
configuration
requests a system-managed
preview scene.
There's no scene delegate
and no callbacks to worry about,
but your app
must declare support
for multiple windows
in the Info.plist.
Providing polished
and convenient ways
for people to open content
in new scenes is important.
But it's equally as important
to save and restore
the scene's state
so returning to them later on
is a seamless experience.
When a scene
moves to the background,
the system will ask
the scene's delegate
for an NSUserActivity
to represent its state.
This activity could be the
root view controller's activity
if it supports Handoff,
or one created on the spot.
Here, a user activity is created
saving the contents
of a text field
in the activity's
user info dictionary.
To give the best experience,
the scene state should go
beyond just the content.
You should also save
the visual and interaction state
like scroll position,
cursor position,
and first responder status.
Rather than saving
each of these independently,
UITextField and UITextView
now have
an interactionState property.
This property
provides a single object
containing all
of the interaction state.
The object doesn't contain
the content itself,
it's additional information
for you to save
in the user activity.
I've updated
the previous example
by saving the interaction state
of the text field.
Now, by saving both the content
and the interaction state,
the user activity
contains enough information
to be accurately restored.
On iPadOS 14, restoring state
can be a little tricky.
If you tried to restore state
when the scene was connecting,
you'd notice that the storyboard
and views weren't fully loaded.
If you restored later,
when the scene was transitioning
to the foreground,
you had to track whether or not
it was for the first time.
iPadOS 15 solves this problem
with a new delegate method
explicitly for restoring state.
It's called after
the scene is connected
and the storyboard
has been loaded,
but before the first transition
to foreground.
Regardless of whether your app
uses storyboards,
you should use this new callback
for restoring state.
Restoring state
from the activity
saved in the previous example
starts with the system calling
sceneRestoreInteractionState.
Then, restoring the content
of the text field.
Finally, restoring
its interaction state.
It's critical that
the content be restored
before the interaction state.
Lastly, synchronously
restoring state can be complex.
You may need to access
a database or load a file
and don't want empty UI
during that time.
To account for this,
iPadOS 15 allows your app to
request a short-term extension.
During this extension,
the launch image
will remain visible
while still allowing
the main RunLoop to execute.
Once your content is loaded,
the app should signal
to complete the restoration.
This extension is short
and not intended to be used
for potentially long-running
tasks like network access.
If your app
fails to signal completion,
or takes too long,
it will be closed by the system.
To use extended state
restoration,
start by requesting an extension
from the scene.
Then, kick off your
asynchronous work.
Once the content is loaded,
restore it and tell the scene
to complete restoration.
The scene will then display
your freshly restored UI.
Supporting multitasking
in your app makes it shine,
but to be a true
next-level iPad app,
there's more to do.
And now, over to Anant.
Anant Jain: Thank you, Chris!
My name is Anant
and I'm a UIKit engineer.
People love that iPad is light
enough to hold in their hands
while still being able to attach
to a physical keyboard
at a moment's notice.
They expect your app
to keep up with them
by having
great keyboard support.
iPadOS 15 introduces
several new features
to bring your app's keyboard
shortcuts to the next level.
iPadOS 15 features
a totally new interface
for discovering
keyboard shortcuts.
It structures each command
into familiar categories,
bringing increased parity
between the iPad
and Mac Catalyst versions
of your app.
The menu offers
a convenient search feature
that can be brought up
from anywhere across the system.
You can even tap
on a shortcut to trigger it.
If you need a refresher on how
to support keyboard shortcuts
with UIKeyCommand,
including how commands
are dispatched
to the responder chain,
check out "Support hardware
keyboards in your app."
On Mac Catalyst,
apps each have a global menu
called the main menu,
which is displayed
in the menu bar
at the top of the screen.
The main menu consists
of several category submenus,
like File and Edit,
and these category menus
in turn contain further submenus
with all the app's commands.
On iPadOS 15,
we've brought
the main menu system
to iPad apps.
The new shortcut interface,
which appears by holding down
the Command key,
displays this menu.
Now, the main menu system
is represented a bit differently
on the iPad
compared to the Mac.
The Mac displays
the full submenu hierarchy
within each category,
whereas the iPad
flattens those hierarchies.
Disabled and non-performable
commands
appear grayed out
on the Mac,
whereas they are hidden
on the iPad.
Furthermore,
the iPad shortcut menu
is designed to help discover
keyboard shortcuts in an app.
It won't display
keyless commands
like the Mac menu bar does.
By default,
the main menu contains
all the system category menus
like File and Edit.
These include
all the system commands,
like Undo and Redo,
Paste and Match Style,
and so on.
iPadOS 15
adds the Print command
to this list of system commands,
which apps can get by adding
the UIApplication
SupportsPrintCommand key
to their Info.plist.
Now that iPad apps on iPadOS 15
support the main menu system,
they can use
the UIMenuBuilder API
to customize it,
just like Mac Catalyst apps.
In fact, if you already have
a Mac Catalyst version
of your app,
you've already done
most of the work.
Apps should use the builder
to add all supported key
commands to their main menus.
This is a change
from how apps would previously
declare keyboard shortcuts:
by overriding the keyCommands
property on UIResponder,
or by calling addKeyCommand(_:)
on a view controller.
Commands defined this way
do still work,
but they'll appear
in a separate
uncategorized section
of the new interface.
Apps should remove key
command declarations like this
and instead add them
to the main menu.
To customize the main menu,
override buildMenu(withbuilder:)
in your AppDelegate.
UIKit calls this method
at app launch
and passes in
a UIMenuBuilder object.
Apps should check if the builder
is modifying
the main menu system.
If so, they can use the builder
to make customizations.
Suppose an app wants some
key commands in the File menu
for working with tabs.
The app simply creates a submenu
using the UIMenu API
and adds the desired
key commands
as that menu's children.
Then the app calls
the insertChild method
on the builder object
to insert the submenu
into the File menu.
To reference an existing element
in the main menu system --
like the File menu,
in this case --
apps should specify
the element's identifier.
The built-in
system menu identifiers
are defined as constants
under UIMenu.Identifier.
Apps can easily create
their own menu categories, too.
Here, the app creates
a Bookmarks menu --
once again,
using the UIMenu API.
Then, the app uses the builder
to insert that menu
into the root menu --
in this case,
after the system View menu.
That's all it takes!
Now, the builder can be used
to make further insertions
into the Bookmarks menu,
just as it would
with the File menu.
Just pass in
the new menu's identifier,
which UIKit automatically
generates.
Now, I keep mentioning
identifiers.
UIMenuBuilder will enforce
that each element
in the main menu system
has a unique identifier,
including individual commands.
Suppose an app
inserts key commands
to display content
either as a list or as a grid.
Both commands
share the same action:
changeViewMode(_:).
In the main menu system,
commands are implicitly
identified by their actions,
so both of these commands
share the same identifier.
UIMenuBuilder won't allow
both commands to be inserted
unless they have
different identifiers.
One way to distinguish
these commands
is to give them different
propertyList values.
But a better way is to simply
give each command
a unique action describing
what it specifically does.
The builder also enforces that
keyboard shortcut combinations
in the main menu are unique.
Suppose an app inserts
a Get Info key command
on Command-I.
Because the system Italic
shortcut in the text style menu
shares the same shortcut,
this insertion will also fail.
Once again,
there are two solutions.
The app can change the Get Info
shortcut to something
that doesn't collide
with an existing shortcut,
such as Control-Command-I.
Alternatively,
the app can tell the builder
to remove the text style
commands if they're not needed.
If an insertion
includes a duplicate,
then UIMenuBuilder
fails that insertion
and logs an error in the console
showing either
the duplicated key commands
or the shared identifiers.
If you're finding your
insertions aren't appearing,
chances are there's
a duplicate somewhere,
so look for logs like this
in the console.
After the call to
buildMenu(with builder:)
finishes, the app's
main menu appears
in the Mac menu bar
and the iPad shortcut overlay.
There is one problem,
though.
The app added a submenu
with commands
to sort bookmarks
either by name or by date.
But because
the iPad shortcut overlay
doesn't display
the submenu hierarchy,
it's not clear what
these shortcuts do on iPadOS.
For situations like this,
set a more descriptive
discoverability title
on the key commands.
iPadOS prefers
the discoverability title
over the regular title
if both are provided.
Now, I mentioned earlier
that individual responders
should avoid declaring
keyboard shortcuts
and instead declare them
in the main menu system.
However, responders should
still implement action methods
for main menu commands.
When key commands
are triggered,
UIKit automatically dispatches
the action to a responder.
UIKit does this by traversing
the app's responder chain.
As soon as it finds a responder
that can perform the action,
it calls that responder's
action method.
If nothing in the chain
can perform the action,
then the key command
isn't performable.
If you're new to UIResponder
concepts,
"Support hardware
keyboards in your app"
has a fantastic introduction
to how it works.
"Qualities of
a great Mac Catalyst app"
also dives into
a bit more detail.
When UIKit performs a responder
search along the chain,
it calls two useful
UIResponder methods.
Apps can override these
methods in their responders
to improve their key commands.
The first is canPerformAction
(_:withSender:),
which UIKit uses to check
if a responder
can perform an action.
By default, this returns true
if the responder implements
that action method;
otherwise, it returns false.
Responders can override this
to add custom logic.
For example,
a web browser can tell UIKit
that the closeTab command
isn't performable
if there are no open tabs.
Since UIKit can't find a target
responder for that action,
the command will be
non-performable
and it won't be shown
in the shortcut interface.
Note that overrides
for this method
must call super
for unhandled cases.
The other useful method
is validate(_ command:).
When UIKit finds a target
responder for a key command,
it calls this method
on that responder
and passes in
a copy of the command.
Responders can override
validate(_ command:)
to update the appearance
of the command
for the current state
of the app.
Here, the app updates the title
of the toggleBookmark(_:)
command
based on whether or not
the current page is bookmarked.
The title set in this method
will reflect in the shortcut
interface when it appears.
In iPadOS 15,
UIKit is introducing
a major change
to the responder chain.
When apps
adopt keyboard navigation
with the focus system,
then responder traversal
will begin at the focused item
rather than the first responder.
This change plays incredibly
well with key commands.
Photos, for example,
allows users
to work with their photo library
using just the keyboard.
When users focus
a cell in the grid,
they can hit the Space bar
to view that photo.
They can even hit
Command-C to copy that photo
for pasting into another app.
Each cell implements
various key command actions,
and since responder traversal
starts at the focused item,
then the key commands
target the cell.
In short, the focus system
levels up key commands
and the responder chain.
Take advantage of it to support
powerful contextual shortcuts
in your app.
To learn more, check out
"Focus on iPad
keyboard navigation."
Finally, iPadOS 15
and macOS 12
introduce keyboard shortcut
localization.
When you build your app
with these SDKs,
the system automatically
localizes shortcut modifiers
and inputs for each
keyboard layout.
Take the Command-backslash
shortcut, for example.
While the shortcut
works on a US keyboard,
it's impossible to perform
on a Japanese keyboard,
since that layout
has no backslash key.
So the system will remap the
shortcut for Japanese keyboards.
This means apps should not
localize shortcut modifiers
or inputs,
and instead let the system
do the work.
Apps can also opt out
of automatic localization,
either at the app-wide level
or on a per-shortcut basis.
When the system
localizes shortcuts,
it also mirrors them
for right-to-left layouts.
For example, a shortcut
to navigate backwards
with Command-left bracket
is flipped
to Command-right bracket.
If a shortcut
shouldn't be mirrored,
set the command's
allowsAutomaticMirroring
property to false
to disable mirroring
without disabling
automatic localization entirely.
iPadOS 15 is a huge release
for keyboard shortcuts.
There's a ton
of other enhancements
on top of everything
we've covered today.
So you've adopted all
the new Multitasking features,
and you've built
great keyboard support.
Now, Mohammed will give you
a few pointers
to take your iPad app
to the highest level.
Mohammed Jisrawi: Thanks, Anant!
Hi, I'm Mohammed.
Let's talk about
the improvements
iPadOS 15 brings
to the system pointer.
iPadOS 13.4 introduced
an adaptive system pointer
that bridges between
the touch-based UI of the iPad
and the precision
of a mouse or trackpad.
If you're new
to pointer interactions,
take a moment to familiarize
yourself with them
and check out
these previous videos.
"Build for the iPadOS pointer"
breaks down
the pointer interaction APIs.
"Design for the iPadOS Pointer"
dives into the design philosophy
behind them
and discusses best practices
when adopting them in your app.
iPadOS 15 brings over some
familiar Mac user interactions
in a way that's consistent
with the iPad's design language.
It also introduces
some new concepts
that enhance usability
and clarity.
The first of these additions
is band selection,
a new pointer-specific
multiselection experience
that should be familiar
to anyone who's used a Mac.
In iPadOS 15, when you click
and drag in a collection view,
the pointer stretches
into a rectangle,
and the collection view
selects the items
that the rectangle encompasses.
Of course this
translates naturally
to the familiar Mac UI
on Mac Catalyst apps.
This interaction is built into
non-list UICollectionViews.
Any UICollectionView
that supports the existing
one- and two-finger
multiselection gestures
via the shouldBeginMultiple
SelectionInteraction API
gets this behavior automatically
in iPadOS 15.
For anything other than
a UICollectionView,
the new
UIBandSelectionInteraction API
allows you to easily adopt
this experience in your app.
Since the selection logic
is completely up to you,
you're able to support
custom selection behaviors
and have your UI react
to the changing selection
in any way you choose.
To get started,
instantiate the interaction
with a selection handler to be
called as the pointer moves
and the interaction's
state changes.
Once it's created,
add the interaction to your view
as you would
any other UIInteraction.
In the handler,
you can implement
your custom selection logic
by responding to changes
in the interaction's state
and selectionRect.
Here we have
a simple implementation
that sets the selection
to the items
within the interaction's
selectionRect
while the pointer is moving.
It then finalizes
the selection session
when the primary mouse button
is released
and the interaction ends.
In addition to basic selection,
UICollectionView's
built-in band selection
supports some common
keyboard shortcuts
out of the box.
Holding Shift at the start
of the drag, for example,
causes items to be added
to an existing selection
rather than replacing
the currently selected items.
Holding Command toggles
the selection state of items
in the selection rect.
This can be implemented
in custom UI
using the interaction's
initialModifierFlags property,
which provides the keys
held at the start of the drag.
Since it's a set of all
the pressed modifiers,
you can respond
to arbitrary key combinations
to support custom
or more advanced behavior
that's specific to your app.
The second addition
to the system pointer
is the ability
to attach accessories.
Accessories communicate
additional information
and provide contextual hints
by combining secondary shapes
with the primary pointer.
For instance,
in the example on the left,
the two arrows indicate
that this view
can be dragged horizontally.
In the example on the right,
the plus provides
some additional context
for this Add to Cart button.
There are a few key distinctions
between accessories
and using a custom
pointer shape.
Accessories
are visually separate
and secondary
to the main pointer.
This is emphasized by the fact
that they may be rendered
with a different appearance
and animate separately
from the main pointer.
They are independent units
which can be combined
and positioned
around the pointer
to communicate different ideas.
Since they are independent,
they can be combined
with any pointer style.
Here's a demonstration of how
the same set of accessories --
two arrows indicating
draggability --
can be combined
with different pointer styles.
On the left, they're combined
with a lift effect
where the pointer merges
with the view and lifts it up.
In the middle, they're
alongside a highlight effect,
where the pointer
turns into a rounded rectangle
and goes under the view.
On the right, they appear
with the default system pointer
using the new
UIPointerStyle.system() API.
So we're able to provide
this additional context
while still using the ideal
effect for the situation,
without sacrificing the
liveliness of the pointer,
and while still maintaining
its deep relationship
with the app's UI.
Just like it animates
between pointer styles,
the system will automatically
animate the appearance
and disappearance
of accessories.
It'll also seamlessly animate
between accessory
shapes and position.
The act of transitioning
accessories
while a given effect is active
can be meaningful.
Such a transition can be
used to communicate
a change in state or
behavior in the underlying UI.
In the example on the left,
the transition
from a plus to a no sign
may indicate that an operation
that was previously possible
is no longer permitted.
Pointer accessories are
composed of a UIPointerShape
and a
UIPointerAccessory.Position,
which describes
the desired position
as an offset from
the pointer's midpoint
and an angle from the top.
For convenience, UIKit
provides some predefined values
for positions
around the pointer.
If the predefined positions
don't quite fit your needs,
you can use them
as a starting point
and customize individual
properties.
This example starts
with the topRight position
and customizes the offset.
You can also define
entirely custom positions,
as in this example,
which creates a position
with a custom offset and angle.
To set up the example we saw at
the beginning of this segment,
we'll create a UITargetedPreview
with our view
and use that to create
a UIPointerStyle
with a lift effect.
Then we'll set the style's
new accessories property
to an array that contains
our two arrow accessories.
UIKit provides a premade
arrow accessory,
so we can just create
two of those
positioned on the left and right
sides of the effect.
So now when the pointer
hovers over this view,
the two arrows animate out
as the view lifts,
hinting that it can be dragged.
If you've ever tried
to implement
this sort of interaction
where a view with
a pointer effect is draggable,
you've probably noticed
something like this.
When the pointer reaches
the edge of the pointer region,
it disengages from the lifted
view and the effect ends.
This is usually desirable,
since it prevents the pointer
from sticking to views
as it moves around.
However, in scenarios like this,
the ideal experience
would be for the pointer effect
to remain stable
and latch to the view and follow
it along as it's dragged.
To better enable
these sorts of interactions,
iPadOS 15 introduces
the concept of latchingAxes
on UIPointerRegion.
When a region latches
along a given axis,
its pointer effect follows
the pointer along the axis
when the primary
mouse button is pressed.
A horizontally latching region
lets you drag freely
along the x-axis while still
rubberbanding along the y-axis.
A vertically latching one
lets you drag freely
along the y-axis.
And one that latches along both
lets you drag freely
along both axes.
These new tools
can be used to build
some really powerful
new experiences.
Here they are combined
in a document editing app
like Pages or Keynote.
This image can be selected
using band selection.
Selecting the image causes
dragging indicators to appear,
and when the pointer
hovers over an indicator,
accessories appear
to hint at
how the image will be resized
if it's dragged.
And finally, latching allows the
pointer effect and accessories
to follow the axis-locked
resize gesture.
These are just some
of the enhancements
iPadOS 15 brings to the iPad.
Take advantage of them
where applicable
to really maximize
the utility of your app.
Adopt prominent scenes
to give people a focused,
uninterrupted view
of your app's content.
Empower them to achieve
complex tasks quickly
with the new
keyboard shortcuts menu,
and boost their productivity
with the new pointer features.
Thanks for watching!
♪