[music]
[Jiabao] Hello! I'm Jiabao Li,
a designer
on the Prototyping team.
I'll be joined later
by my colleague,
Mylène Dreyer.
We are so excited to talk about
how to design user interfaces
that are discoverable.
Your app has amazing features,
but people might not know the
features exist
if they are not self-evident.
So, today,
we are going to talk about
how people learn about
what your app can do.
If your interface
is discoverable,
it means that people should
be able to look at a screen
and, before they touch anything,
know what they can do, and how.
Let's use an example
to explore different ways
to make your app
more discoverable.
For several years now,
our team has worked
on a boutique app
for finding the best toast.
This year, our app
is expanding into making toast.
Introducing Toasty!
The premier
smart toast recipe generator.
You can choose recipes from
curated selections of toast.
You can see fancy toast
your friends made.
You can even generate a recipe
by taking a picture of toast
that's right in front of you.
How will people learn
about all the features?
Hmm, let's line them up
one by one
in our onboarding tutorial.
Let's tell people
how to browse toast,
and about generating recipes
from a picture.
Oh, but also
all the instructions about
how to take a picture in Toasty,
specifically to make
for the best results.
OK, except,
let me be honest.
I always skip through
these onboarding screens.
I don't even read them,
so why would people
want to read onboarding screens
I made?
When I open up this Toasty app,
these screens are
just another thing between me
and fancy delicious toast.
Even if people had the patience
to read each screen,
why would they remember
everything later?
You need an interface
that stands on its own,
without heavy-handed tutorials,
because learning by doing
is a lot more fun and effective
than reading
a list of instructions.
So, here are five fundamentals
to make your app
more discoverable.
First, rank your features
so you can make
the most important ones visible.
Second, use words and symbols
people are familiar with
to provide visual cues.
Third, use gestures
for fluid navigation,
but hint at gestures.
Fourth, group content
to fit people's behavior.
And fifth,
convey a sense of control
over personalized content.
These concepts may seem basic.
In a way, they are.
They are so fundamental,
we take them for granted.
But there are nuances here
that might not be obvious
and are worth unpacking
because your app
doesn't get a second chance
at a first impression.
So, first,
prioritize important features.
Not all pixels
are created equal.
Which is great because
neither are all of our features.
The essential parts of your app
should be immediately visible
to people.
It's okay for the non-essential
parts
to require some
navigation to reach.
When we were designing Toasty,
we wrote down a list
of all the important features
of our app.
These are a lot of features,
and there's no way
they're all going to fit
into one screen.
We really need to prioritize
which features are important
so that we're not trying to cram
all of them onto one screen.
So, we ordered
a list of features
by their level of importance.
Browsing toast recipes
and viewing my recipes
are very important for people to
see.
"Settings" and "About Us" are
less critical,
especially the "About Us" page.
A person using your app
might want to know
the developer of the app
to report a problem
or make a suggestion,
but it's not
one of the top three things
they'll want to do.
When designing your app,
try to understand
what is important
from your user's perspective.
Great!
So, we have our ten
main features,
and we know people
love clean interfaces.
So, we'll just throw
all the non-essential features
into a menu.
Clean and easy, right?
You may have seen
this icon before.
It's called a hamburger menu.
When we tested our interface
in the hands of people
and found out that,
when the hamburger menu
is closed,
people don't know what's inside.
The three lines
don't convey anything
about the features inside.
So, instead,
we decided to go with
a tab bar navigation system,
which appears
at the bottom of an app
and lets people quickly switch
between different sections.
It's better because
you can immediately see
the most important
features of the app.
The most minimal user interfaces
might not be usable or simple
because people
won't know what to do.
Because when we hide things
to make the app look minimal,
we increase the risk
that people won't find features.
They might even forget that
your favorite feature exists.
On the other extreme,
what if all the features
are equally important,
and I have to cram them all
into one space
with six tab buttons?
But too many tabs reduces
the tappable area of each tab
and increases the complexity
of your app,
which can make it harder
for people
to locate information.
Look, I understand that
you have been in
these situations.
Some people think
everything is important
to show first,
and some people want to hide
everything
for a cleaner look.
It's hard to serve both of them,
and you have to make hard
decisions
in terms of what to prioritize.
It's a balancing act.
What are the reasons
features might be worth
showing front and center
in your app?
The features
are the main points of the app,
or people
use the features frequently.
The main unique points of Toasty
is browse toast recipes,
view my recipe,
and take a picture
to generate a recipe.
And people browse through
pieces of toast
and collect a set of recipes
most frequently.
We divided these features
into two screens.
We named the screens "For You"
and "Recipes."
We placed these screens
in the most visible
and reachable place,
the tab bar.
And as an added bonus,
it aligns the ergonomics of the
screen
with the expected frequency
of actions.
Taking a picture is to generate
a new recipe in my Recipes page.
It's an important feature.
So, we put
a prominent button at the top,
before other recipes.
The Search Bar
is placed on the top,
for very visible access.
We are fine with it
being further
to reach for my thumb
because we imagine it
as an action
people use less frequently,
relative to our tab bar actions.
The rest of the features
from our list
relate to my personal
preferences,
so we put them into
the Profile icon on the top.
My preferences
do not change frequently,
so it's OK if it takes
an additional tap to get there.
To summarize this section,
prioritize important features,
make the essential features
immediately visible.
To make other actions
and navigation discoverable,
use visual cues
to direct attention.
Visual cues are elements
that guide people
toward a particular
piece of content or action.
How we think about visual cues
begins with knowing
your audience.
Knowing your audience is key
because it helps you understand
what needs to be spelled out
and what can
be inferred by people.
First, think about,
who is your product for?
In the case of Toasty,
our product is for toast lovers,
who might not be
professional chefs,
but still want to make
tasty toast on their own
with the help of a recipe.
Toasty is an app
for a general audience,
not a professional tool.
So, there is not much tolerance
for spending time and effort
to learn this app.
As in,
people are unlikely to want
or think it's necessary
to have extensive
how-to instructions,
like a multi-step
onboarding tutorial.
We want to provide
as many visual cues
that clue them
into how to use the app
while they're using it, instead.
So, we ask,
what do people know already?
We assume people
can infer this icon
relates to toast because,
as toast lovers,
they've naturally come across
bread that resembles that shape.
Our icon is tied
to the physical world.
But, hey!
It's not just people's physical,
lived experiences
we can count on.
We can expect some familiarity
with common digital patterns
because most people using Toasty
aren't new to having a phone.
For example, people using iOS
associate the action
of going to a previous screen
with tapping a chevron
on the top left
of the navigation view.
Because people are familiar
with this interaction,
we don't need to add
extra visual cues.
If you are building unique
designs or interactions
that people may not
be familiar with,
you should include words
or on-screen elements
that help people understand
what to do.
Even recognizable icons
can be vague.
Is that a book?
A favorite newspaper?
By adding labels,
we clarify the meaning
of each icon:
to browse
suggested kinds of toast,
to view saved recipes.
Even the camera icon
that we are familiar
with could have
many possible uses,
such as taking a picture,
scanning a document
or a QR code.
When we add text
labeling the button "New,"
we clarify this button
is for capturing toast
to add a new recipe.
Beyond the visual cues
that make it clear
what the action will be,
you can also provide visual cues
that help people understand
how to make use of that action.
Take the search bar,
for example.
People are familiar enough
with the search icon and action,
but draw a blank
on what to write,
because we haven't clued them in
on how to search in the app.
We call this
the blank page problem.
When you create things,
presenting people with a giant,
blank white screen
can lead to indecision
because people don't know
what they want to make
when there's nothing
in front of them.
It's something
you can get around
by guiding people
with various options.
So, we decided
to provide examples
of possible types of input,
such as searching by
ingredients, places, or friends.
In this way,
people can quickly discover
different methods
for how to search.
Besides guiding people
with words and visuals,
you could also use
animation and interactivity
to teach gradually
and in context.
In Toasty, for example,
we have the ability
to scan real toast,
using the camera
to generate a recipe
and set a cover photo
for that recipe.
[pop]
It's a unique feature,
so we'll have to guide people
through how to do this.
[ringing]
The toast outline hints at
keeping the toast in the center
and a certain distance away.
Before you have toast in view,
the shutter button
is deactivated,
and we let you know
it's because the camera
is looking for toast.
When a camera
is at the right angle,
the outline visually changes.
[ringing]
And then,
there's haptic feedback
to indicate
the recommended moment
to take a picture of your toast.
[camera shutter clicks]
These animations and visual cues
help ensure people
get our instructions,
when the info is relevant,
instead of early on
in the onboarding.
So, design your app
by considering what knowledge
people are already equipped with
and when they need
an extra helping hand.
Number three, hint at gestures.
Making use of gestures
in your app
will make your app feel
more fluid and responsive
than navigating through
with only discrete taps.
Gestures are great as shortcuts
to certain actions
or navigation,
but are invisible,
and so might not be
as immediately discoverable.
First, as a general rule,
use the accepted gesture for the
platform.
If you're inventing
a new gesture,
try to mimic
real-life interactions.
People can have a hard time
learning new gestures
that do familiar interactions.
In games
and other immersive apps,
custom gestures can be
a fun part of the experience.
In other apps, it's best
to use standard gestures,
so extra effort isn't needed
to discover or remember them.
Some standard gestures
are Tap, Swipe, Long Press,
Pan, Pinch, and Rotate.
People generally expect
these standard gestures
to work the same across
the system and in every app.
Some experiences
don't have standard gestures.
If they are new,
make sure to align interactions
with real-world behaviors.
For example,
in Scribble with Apple Pencil,
we can scratch out the text
that you want to delete.
The gesture works the same
way in the real world
to create
a familiar interaction.
In my recipes, we use pinch
to show more recipes,
similar to the Photos app that
uses the same gesture
to pinch to show more photos.
People should be familiar
with this standard gesture.
But even some gestures
that people are familiar with
can be confusing.
For example,
people who heavily use
social media apps
might be familiar
with Double Tap to Like.
But people who use
a lot of Photos and Maps
might expect
Double Tap to zoom in.
In designing Toasty,
we show a clear "Like" icon
for Tap to Like,
but also include the Double Tap
gesture as a shortcut.
This leads to the second point.
Use gestures as a shortcut,
not a replacement.
Because gestures,
no matter how intuitive
they might be,
are still invisible.
If there's no way
to look at interface
and know how to use a gesture,
then treat a gesture
as an accelerator.
You should still have
a primary way
to perform the same action
that is clearly legible.
And third,
make gestures more discoverable
through your animated
transitions.
In my recipes,
we could tap a toast
to see its recipe.
To get back to all the recipes,
we use swipe down as a shortcut.
Similar to the Photos app,
where you can swipe down
to go back to all photos
from viewing one photo.
Even though
it's a common gesture,
we kept an explicit
button to go back
because we can't assume
everybody knows this gesture.
And gestures have directions.
Tapping the back chevron
still triggers
a sliding down animation,
which hints that you can
also swipe down to go back.
So, ensure your transitions are
consistent
with the motion
of the associated gesture.
We want to let people
navigate between recipes
by swiping left or right.
But just by looking at a screen,
people wouldn't know
they can do that.
So, let's give a visual cue,
by adding the smaller toast
images on either side.
To summarize this section,
use standard iOS gestures,
or gestures that are similar
to real-life interactions.
Provide a primary, legible way
to perform the same action.
And use animation
to hint at gestures.
These are three methods
to improve discoverability,
by ensuring people can
easily move through your app,
can understand
what actions are available,
and can learn how to do so
in the moment.
As general principles,
when people use your app,
they should be able to know
what to do immediately,
without having
to touch the screen.
Try to understand
how people know things.
Do they know this
from the real world?
Do they know this from iOS?
Do they know this because
they've used our app before?
Next, my colleague, Mylène,
will speak to discoverability
for content.
[Mylène] Thank you, Jiabao!
Making the functionality
of your application
easy to understand
will be pointless
if people cannot find
the content
they are looking for.
The best apps have features
you know how to use
and content
you know how to navigate.
The core content of Toasty,
is toast recipes.
A lot of them. Hundreds!
And people will keep
adding recipes, so, eventually,
we'll have thousands.
With that much content,
how are we going to ensure
people can discover
the kinds of toast they want?
To answer that question,
here's our fourth principle:
organize by behavior.
Organize the content of your app
into categories
that fits people's motivation
and natural behavior.
Let's start by choosing
what these categories are.
We think people
get very excited about
what kind of topping or
unique ingredient combinations
they would like to find
on a toast.
So, naturally, when choosing
categories for our app,
we decided
to organize by ingredients.
People can
have grouped selections
of avocado or blueberry toast.
But that doesn't
scale well because
there are just too many
possible ingredients.
It is a legitimate choice
to categorize by ingredient.
There are tons of different ways
to organize content,
and we know how difficult
it can be to make choices.
But this isn't helping
make a decision
about the pieces of toast
people want to try next.
The amount of ingredients
categories is overwhelming.
With Toasty,
we want to help people
explore and discover
new toast recipes.
So, we put ourself
in the position
of the people using our app.
How would people
discover toast in real life?
In what context?
What is people's behavior
regarding toast?
Well, they find new toast
when they try new restaurants
or when friends recommend them.
This led us to organize
recommendations
based on whether
they are from restaurants
or shared by friends.
These two categories
apply to other motivations
than just making
a piece of toast.
It's about getting to know
restaurants in your area better
and connecting with friends.
It is more
interesting and engaging
to discover content this way.
But we felt
we were still missing
one strong category
that would connect with
the individual's personal taste
and the flavors they favor.
That leads us
to our second point,
which is to use personalization.
Organize content
into a dedicated section
that will surface suggestions
from a machine-learning-powered
recommendation engine.
Because food taste
is something personal,
it makes sense
to personalize content.
As I said earlier, we can't have
a category for each ingredient,
but we can have
a recommendation engine
that will target people's
favorite toast recipes
based on ingredients they like.
So, adding
to our existing categories,
we've created a new one
we're calling "Tasty Picks."
Tasty Picks
shows the best toast recipes
generated by our own
recommendation engine.
For certain
types of application,
personalized content
can improve the app's experience
if it's implemented well.
Especially when dealing
with a lot of content,
it's possible people
could find something
they might like faster.
And when people don't
have to type in a search bar,
it is usually a sign that
your content is discoverable.
Once we have organized
the content into categories
that match people's behavior,
we need to visually
perceive these divisions.
Which brings us to the final
point about organizing content:
visualize the content
organization
by making the categories
clear at a glance.
When designing
the user interface of Toasty,
we started by just putting
every item on screen.
When we do this
with our toast recipes,
you can already see
this is overwhelming.
There are too many items
that are equally important.
It becomes difficult to discover
the one you really want.
Moreover,
without clear division,
people have no sense
of existing categories.
The content is just one giant,
unsorted box of toast recipes.
By grouping the categories
into different logical sections,
separated by a header title,
it feels immediately
more understandable.
People can easily ignore
one category
and explore deeper
in one specific section.
Organize content into
categories that translates
people's behavior
and real-life context.
Use personalization
so people can more easily
find what they like.
Finally, visually reinforce
these categories
by having clear divisions.
Now, let's move to our last
and fifth principle:
convey a sense of control,
so people know
how to easily influence
a machine-learning system
and edit irrelevant
personalized content.
First, let people provide
explicit feedback
about the item on their screen.
Explicit feedback comes
from people's intentional input.
When an option exists
to tell a system
about content
you want to see more or hide,
this is explicit feedback.
If you clearly invite people
to provide feedback,
they are more likely
to give feedback.
This will feed
the recommendation engine's
useful data that
will reinforce relevant items
and discoverability
of the content.
So, be mindful about
how you communicate
and make these feedback
actions discoverable.
After browsing
hundreds of toast,
people eventually land
on a yummy toast page.
As Jiabao mentioned earlier,
visual cues are elements
that guide people
toward a particular piece
of content or action.
Because we want people to
tell us if they like this toast,
we decided to use
a heart button.
We showed our design
to friends and colleagues
to find out
what is or isn't working.
We quickly realized
most people thought
this action meant
"add to favorites" rather than
"I would like to be recommended
more toast like this."
The heart icon alone
doesn't help to discover
what this feature does.
It is open to interpretation
and not clearly indicating that
tapping on it
will have any consequences
on the system.
Moreover, in iOS,
the standard is that
you can only unloved
once you have loved.
So if we can't use
the unlove icon,
what would be
a good input to say
"show me less
this type of toast"?
The iOS guidelines for
recommendation feedback icons
is to pair thumbs up
and thumbs down.
So, we went with that.
We showed this updated design
to our friends,
and they were still confused.
It could be that,
this thumbs up meant
other people would see
that they have liked this toast.
They just weren't understanding
that it's going to change a
recommendation engine
within their own iPhone.
So, we tried even harder
to be clear and upfront
about the consequences.
Using the label
"Suggest toast like this"
has clear consequences
because "Suggest" is a term
that is much more
closely associated
with recommendation engines.
Now, by just looking
at the screen,
you know what will happen
after tapping the button "less."
Future recommendations
will be adapted
to show less banana toast.
Communicating
how your system works,
where you can interact with it,
and what will result
from a person's actions
is crucial if you want
people to easily discover
how to give useful feedback.
So, now that we know how to
design feedback and actions,
the next step is to be mindful
about the outputs
of these actions.
So, in order to do this,
disclose implicit feedback.
Implicit feedback
is information that arises
as people interact
with your app's features.
"Implicit" means that it happens
without people
consciously asking for it.
For example,
when viewing a recipe
or sharing toast with a friend.
By disclosing
the implicit inputs,
we inform people of the system
recommendation input source
and, therefore, increase the
discoverability of the content
and the understanding
of the system.
In the "For You" tab of Toasty,
we have the section
"Tasty Picks."
Without an explanation,
it's difficult to understand
where this content
is coming from.
Why am I seeing
these particular toast recipes?
Is this curated content
from the developer themself
or machine learning?
So, after considering
these questions ourself,
we added a description,
"Because you added
avocado toast."
Adding a text label
is a simple but efficient method
to clarify anything on screen.
In this case,
it helps people know
they'll get more
personalized recommendations
as they add recipes
to their collection.
Now, what if people don't want
their added toast recipes
to be used as an input
to get recommendation?
How do they edit
personalized content
if the results are no longer
valuable,
or simply not as good
as expected?
These questions brings us
to the last point
of our talk today,
which is to give control
over recommendations.
Allow people to act on
the recommendations
they receive,
in case they are not happy
with the results.
Let me tell you a little story
to illustrate that.
I'm used to eating
an avocado toast every morning,
and I get most of my recipes
from Toasty.
Now, let's say I move
to a new country.
Everything is exciting and new,
but I realized one terrible
thing there:
I just can't find or purchase
avocados anywhere!
How terrible would it be
to still get
delicious avocado toast
suggestion,
when I can't get
that ingredient anymore?
Yes, indeed,
that would be very frustrating.
The app needs to stop showing
me what I can't have.
For this reason,
you should allow recommendations
to be edited
so people feel in control.
Allow them to act on something
that is frustrating
and that they want to correct.
But most importantly,
make that action easy to find
and quick to perform.
In the "Tasty Picks" section,
next to the description
"Because you added
avocado toast,"
we've put
a "More Options" button.
By doing so, people know
they can act directly
on the recommendation.
But from the perspective
of discoverability,
you should already sense
something wrong here.
We've hidden everything
behind a "More Options" menu,
where people might not find it.
Maybe we should try to be
even more descriptive?
So, for our last design,
we simply added a green text
button,
right at the end
of the descriptions, that says
"edit suggestion."
After tapping on that button,
different options
are presented to people.
"Suggest Less Avocado Toast"
and
"Stop Suggesting Avocado Toast."
By just reading
the button label,
people should
easily understand what to do
and perceive what would result
from both actions.
By using a thumbs-down icon,
the same way as we do
for the explicit feedback,
we show people
that these buttons
have the same outcomes
as ones elsewhere in our app,
which is to show more
or less of certain content.
So, use descriptive labels
and use icons to help clarify
or emphasize the description.
Some people might want
to provide even more
specific feedback than just
"suggest less avocado toast"
and "stop suggesting
avocado toast."
I mean,
there are many situations where
"suggest less"
or "stop suggesting"
aren't exactly how I want
to change my recommendations.
Maybe people are just not
in the mood
for avocado
on this particular day.
They might want to see
different recommendations today,
but still be suggested
avocado toast in the future.
Or maybe they just
don't like one specific item
in "Tasty Picks"
and would like to remove it.
For the sake of discoverability,
it's fair to debate exactly
what kind of feedback to provide
to a recommendation engine
and how to label those actions.
Even Jiabao and I
have different opinions
on which controls
would be best here.
So, to be confident
when making such difficult
design decisions,
make a prototype of your app,
show it to people,
and learn from their feedback.
Repeat the process until
you are happy with the result.
Here is what we discussed
for the fifth and final
principle.
People should feel and have
control
over your app
personalized content.
They should be able
to quickly understand
what explicit feedback
to provide
and how to edit
or remove content
they don't value anymore.
Let's recap the five principles
to make your app
more discoverable.
Prioritize important features.
Have the essential features
of your app immediately visible.
Provide visual cues.
Use words to disambiguate.
Teach in context with animations
and interactivity.
Hint at gestures:
make gestures discoverable
by using animations.
Use standard gestures
as much as possible.
If using custom gestures,
provide a legible way
to perform the same action.
Organize by behavior.
When dealing
with a lot of content,
categorize by people's behavior.
Visually organize
these categories
and use personalization
in order for people
to quickly find what they want.
And finally,
convey a sense of control.
Make sure people are in control.
Allow them to make corrections
and edit personalized content.
You can have
the most innovative app,
with the most polished
custom icons.
But when using your app,
if people get lost
or don't understand
what those beautiful icons mean,
they might get confused.
You have worked very hard
to build your app's features and
content,
so you really want
people to find them.
As general principle,
when people use your app,
they should be able to know
what to do immediately.
Even without having
to touch the screen.
Think about your audience,
and what they might know.
Do they know this icon from iOS,
or do they understand this
symbol from the real world?
Great design requires
trial and error.
So, make things,
show them to people,
and learn from their feedback.
If you are interested to know
more about design principles
and how to make apps
that feel fluid to use,
here are some videos
we recommend.
Thank you for watching!
[music]