[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Ron Santos: Hey, everyone.
I'm Ron Santos.
I'm a software engineer
working on Keyboards.
And I'm here to show you
how to make the most
of a new feature
that lets you input text,
not by typing or by dictation,
but by using the camera.
So we've been working
really hard on this new release
and now that WWDC
is finally here,
I am so ready for a vacation.
As soon as it's safe,
I'd love to take some time off
and travel.
One thing about traveling
that bugs me though,
is dealing with all of that
nondigital text.
You know what I mean?
Invoices, activity flyers,
and that giant binder they leave
for you in hotel rooms?
Luckily, iOS 15 has
a new feature that allows you
to capture text
from the world around you.
Let me show you what I mean.
Check it out!
I'm building
this travel journal app.
I'll use it to document
trips I've taken
and places I've stayed,
like my last trip to Hawaii.
At the top here,
I can add an image header;
maybe a nice landscape photo
from my Camera Roll.
Then I have fields
for hotel information
like name, phone number,
and address.
I actually have all of that
information on a document
right in front of me.
I don't want to have
to type it all out,
and now I don't have to.
For example, if I tap twice
on the Phone Number field,
I see a new option
in the editing menu
to use Text from Camera.
Once it launches,
the camera instantly recognizes
this group of text
on the document.
I can freeze it and select
just the phone number.
Then I tap Insert and I'm done.
I think that's pretty awesome.
Reminds me of that saying
how a picture is worth
a thousand words.
But with this feature,
we can literally take
a thousand words from a picture.
Anyways, like I said earlier,
I'd love to show you how to get
the most out of this feature.
Let's get started by talking
about filtering content.
If you remember,
I had to drag-select
the phone number
from the large block of text.
Well, I shouldn't
have to do that
if the app knows I'm looking
for a phone number.
It should ignore everything else
and just grab the number.
So first, I'll show you
how simple it is
to filter for the content
you want.
Filtering is done by using
the TextContentType
and KeyboardType properties
which are available
on text fields
and text views.
In fact, you're probably already
using these properties
to support things like AutoFill.
If so, terrific.
You'll get the extra benefit
for camera input.
And if you haven't used them,
here are some videos
from previous years
that show you how.
OK, back to TextContentType.
The TextContentType can be
any one of these various values.
But the camera won't filter
for all of these types.
It'll filter
on just these seven.
Let's look at some examples.
These first four --
telephone number,
full street address,
URL, and email --
they all preexist in iOS today.
New in iOS 15, we've added
three additional types:
flight number,
shipment tracking number,
and the combination of dates,
times, and durations.
You can imagine how
flight number might be useful
to travel apps,
or how tracking numbers
would be cool
for package-tracking apps.
Anyways, here's how you would
use these content types.
It's super simple.
If you're in Interface Builder,
look for Content Type
and Keyboard Type
in the Attributes inspector.
If you're doing this in code,
just assign the values you want.
Here in my travel journal app,
the Phone Number field
is using the phone pad keyboard,
and the Address field
has textContentType
of fullStreetAddress.
And notice that
for the phone number,
I set the autocorrectionType
to no.
Because if there
are no autocorrection
or predictive text candidates,
iOS gives you a button
for quick access to the camera.
OK, let's go back to my app,
and we can try capturing
the hotel phone number again,
but this time, with our changes.
Now, when I bring up the camera,
it smartly ignores
all the other text
except for the phone number.
Let's try that again
with the Address field.
That's so much faster.
A lot less tapping and swiping.
So that's how
you filter content.
Let's move on
to a different challenge.
How do we make
this functionality
more discoverable
to really encourage its use?
As app developers,
we love having
a streamlined user interface.
Which means we sometimes
have additional functionality
hidden behind menus and gestures
the user doesn't know about.
For example, if I use
the Notes field in my app,
it's not obvious that I can use
the camera for input here.
The editing menu
only appears on a second tap.
And the candidate bar
has predictive text
instead of the button
I showed you earlier.
So if you want a button onscreen
hinting at camera input,
you'll want to add your own
dedicated launcher button.
To do that, first we need
to create a UIAction
using the captureTextFromCamera
factory method, new in iOS 15.
The action knows
how to launch the camera,
but also provides
an image and a label
when it's used together
with buttons and menus.
Let's add a menu to my app
with an item to insert text
from the camera.
So here's my app again.
When editing the notes field,
I have this toolbar shown
above the keyboard.
When the second item
with a camera icon is tapped,
I want a menu to appear for a
bunch of camera-related actions,
like our new feature,
Text from Camera.
Here we create the action.
And notice, other than
the optional identifier,
the factory method just requires
a responder to accept the text.
Then, I create actions
for the other menu items.
Finally, I assemble the menu
and populate it
with each one of the actions
I just created,
including the textFromCamera
action.
Remember, I don't have
to specify the title
or which image to use.
That's all provided
by the action.
The title will even
be localized for me.
OK, let's try it out.
We're back in the app.
Here's the Notes field and the
toolbar with our camera menu.
Let me insert some text
from an activity flyer
in front of me.
And done!
A user-discoverable launcher
with just a few lines of code.
There is, however,
one thing to keep in mind.
Before you add
any camera launchers,
you'll first want to check
the result of
canPerformAction withSender.
That's because our UIAction
works by invoking a new method
on UIResponder objects
called captureTextFromCamera,
which works similar
to standard edit actions
like cut, copy, and paste.
And those actions
aren't always available,
depending on the context.
For example,
you can't cut text
if you have nothing selected.
Same thing goes here;
the captureTextFromCamera
action has some prerequisites.
That one method will make sure
all the requirements are met.
But let's go
through each of them.
That way, you have a better idea
of why that method
may return false.
First, there are some
hardware requirements;
not all devices running iOS 15
support the feature.
The device should be an iPhone.
And not just any iPhone,
one with the machine learning
super powers
of the Neural Engine.
Aside from hardware,
your responder has to handle
text insertion.
We'll talk more
about that later.
Next, and this might be obvious,
but if your responder
is a text view or text field,
it has to be editable.
And finally,
users must have at least one
of these seven
supported languages
in their list
of preferred languages.
You're now well-equipped
to handle camera input.
But before we wrap up,
let me show you something fun
I added to my app.
Remember the header photo?
It's nice, but I think
it'd be kind of cool
to add a caption over it.
Maybe a caption taken
from the camera.
So I added
a launcher button here
just like what we did
with the menu item.
[PAPER RUSTLING]
And now, I can capture text
and place it over the image.
But how'd I do that, though?
I mean, it's an image view
and not a text control.
Let's step back and figure out
how the text controls work.
And then we'll talk
about image views later.
Text controls adopt
a protocol called UIKeyInput.
It defines a basic set
of methods
for responders to accept
keyboard input.
The protocol has three methods,
one of which
is the insertText method.
And that method
is exactly what's used
to transport text
from the camera to your app.
So for a responder
to support camera input,
it needs to adopt this protocol.
I know I just said text controls
adopt UIKeyInput.
But in reality,
they adopt a protocol
called UITextInput,
which is an extension
of UIKeyInput.
If you adopt UITextInput,
you'll get an extra feature
when using the camera:
a preview of the text
to be inserted.
And that's done with the
setMarkedText method shown here.
Having a preview is optional,
though.
If you opt not to have it,
you only need
to adopt UIKeyInput.
There's one last protocol
to mention,
and you might have caught it
already a few minutes ago.
UIKeyInput itself
extends UITextInputTraits.
That protocol consists
only of optional properties
like KeyboardType
and TextContentType,
which you know from earlier
are used to filter camera input
for specific content.
So for camera input,
you'll want to adopt UIKeyInput
and, optionally,
depending on the level
of functionality you're after,
adopt UITextInputTraits
or UITextInput.
OK. Now, let's bring it back
to our ImageView.
I'm going to create a new class
called HeadlineImageView
which subclasses UIImageView
and adopts UIKeyInput.
Here's it is in code.
It's a simple subclass
of UIImageView,
and it has a UILabel subview
that we'll use
to display the caption.
Remember, to adopt UIKeyInput
we need three methods:
hasText, deleteBackward,
and insertText.
Typically, responders
adopt UIKeyInput
to summon the keyboard.
But because I only want
camera input
and not keyboard input,
we only have to implement
insertText.
hasText can just return false
and deleteBackward
doesn't need to do anything.
As for insertText,
its implementation
is really simple.
It just takes the text
from the camera
and gives it to our label.
That's all there is to it!
Now we have an image view with
a way of displaying a caption
captured from the camera.
Thanks for taking
this trip with me!
Here's what I hope
you come away with.
Take advantage
of text content types.
They help in more ways than one,
including filtering text
from the camera.
Create your own launchers
when you really want
to promote camera input.
We provide labels and images
for a consistent look
that users can associate
with camera input across apps.
But make sure
you first check to see
if the functionality
is available.
Finally, remember you can
use camera input
for your own custom responders
that aren't text controls.
You just need to adopt
the UIKeyInput protocol.
Safe travels and enjoy
the rest of WWDC 2021!
♪