[upbeat music]
[Victoria] Hi, I'm Victoria.
I'm an engineer on
the Documentation Tools team
here at Apple,
and together
with my colleague Ethan,
we're going
to give you an introduction
to the new documentation
features in Xcode 13.
There are new ways to read
and write documentation
that both fit
right into your workflow
and unlock new possibilities
for your development.
Xcode 13 has new features
to build, write,
and browse documentation
for Swift frameworks
and packages.
This unlocks a powerful mode
of documentation-driven
development
where you can read all about
your Swift dependencies
while you write your code.
This documentation lives right
alongside the platform libraries
in the Developer Documentation
window right in Xcode.
In this session,
we'll give an overview
of the documentation
features in Xcode 13,
walk you through
building documentation
for the Swift frameworks
and packages
you're writing and using,
show you how you can use
Xcode 13
to write great documentation,
and finish up by
showing off the ways
you can share documentation
with Xcode 13.
Let's get started
with why I'm personally excited
about the new documentation
features.
I'm sure we've all been there.
There's some new framework
or package that we want to use,
but when it comes time
to integrate it into our code,
we need to figure out
what all comes in it.
This is where Xcode 13 steps in.
Now Xcode comes with a compiler
for your documentation
as well as your code,
and you can build
and view documentation
for Swift frameworks
and packages all inside Xcode.
We call it DocC,
and we've integrated it
all throughout Xcode
to enhance the way you read
and write documentation.
Now, DocC is more than just
a documentation compiler
run after the fact.
It's a fully integrated
documentation environment
that complements Xcode,
offering a rich,
live environment with your docs
appearing in Quick Help,
rich code completion
to allow you
to tie your docs together
into a cohesive whole,
full documentation available
in the integrated Developer
Documentation window,
and an easy option to share
pre-built documentation
to view in Xcode and on the web,
just to name a few.
Stay tuned for our other
DocC sessions at WWDC 2021,
which will go over all these
in detail and much more.
DocC empowers you to write
excellent reference
documentation,
leveraging
the power of Xcode and Swift
to give users a bird's-eye view
of the public APIs
in your framework or package,
complete with the ability to
describe how APIs work together,
not just in isolation.
DocC enables you to write
much more than great reference
documentation, though.
There are two additional
ways to write documentation
with DocC that we're excited
to show off this year.
Articles allow you to walk users
through the big picture
behind your framework,
giving you an opportunity
to tie individual items
in your framework together
with a cohesive story.
And tutorials are a powerful
step-by-step walk-through
of writing a project
that uses your framework.
They allow you to go
much deeper
than reference
documentation or articles
by giving your users
a guided introduction
to your framework
from the ground up.
All of these authoring
experiences leverage and extend
the power and simplicity
of Markdown
to make authoring
your documentation
as fluid
as writing your code.
If you want to know more
about assembling
a documentation catalog
with articles and tutorials
outside your source code,
check out these sessions
at WWDC this year.
And finally, we're releasing
DocC as Open Source
later this year,
alongside a web app
that allows you to host
your built documentation
archives on the web
so you can take advantage
of these new
documentation workflows
even outside of Xcode.
Now that you have a taste
of the new documentation
features in Xcode 13,
let's dive in and talk about
building your documentation
with DocC in Xcode.
Let's take a quick peek
under the hood first
to see how it works.
To build your documentation,
Xcode builds your framework
or package
and asks the compiler
to save information
about its public APIs alongside
your compiled artifacts.
That public API information
is then handed to DocC,
which then combines it with
your documentation catalog
containing articles
and tutorials
written outside your source code
to create the final archive
containing
the compiled documentation.
To learn more about
documentation catalogs
and organizing your docs,
check out the “Elevate
your DocC Documentation
in Xcode” session.
And thanks to DocC's integration
with Xcode's build system,
this process repeats
for every Swift framework
and package that your
target depends on.
This way,
you have all your relevant
documentation all in one place.
But what does this mean for your
day-to-day documentation needs?
There are three ways
to build documentation
for Swift frameworks
and packages in Xcode 13.
To build
documentation on demand,
there's a new
Build Documentation menu item
to compile
and load up your docs.
And if you're working on
a Swift framework
and always want to
preview your documentation
as you go, there's also
a new build setting
to build docs
every time you compile.
And for your
command-line and CI needs,
xcodebuild has a new command
to build documentation too.
This runs the same build
as selecting Build Documentation
in Xcode but using xcodebuild
on the command line.
My colleague David
has much more information
about automating documentation
workflows in the “Host
and Automate your DocC
Documentation” session.
Let's see this in action.
My teammates have been
working on this package
called SlothCreator,
which is all about
cataloging and customizing
cute little sloths.
I want to try it out, so let's
see how that looks in Xcode 13.
I've set up this app I've called
Slothy so I can use SlothCreator
to customize my sloths
and preview them as I go.
I've set up SlothCreator as
a dependency of my app already,
but I want to see more
about what APIs it offers,
so let's
open up the Product menu...
And select Build Documentation
to take a look.
And just like that,
the Developer Documentation
window opens,
and over in the Navigator,
I can expand my Slothy project
and the SlothCreator package
I'm working with to see
an overview in the Navigator.
I'll load the SlothCreator
overview in the main view,
and if I scroll down,
there's a list of types
and protocols available.
Here I can see
this type called Habitat.
Let's click on it
to load its page.
There's some
good information here,
but I wonder if anything
else has mentioned it.
Let's select the Search field
up top and look for "habitat".
It looks like a few different
things mention this.
Let's click
on this sleep method
to bring up
its documentation page.
This page is specific
to the sleep method,
but I'm curious what
type this is part of.
Up in the jump bar
at the top of the window,
I can see this is
part of the Sloth type.
If I click this Sloth,
a pull-down menu appears,
and if I click it again,
I can open that type's
documentation page.
Now I'm getting a picture of how
all these APIs fit together.
So now we've had a chance
to walk through the
documentation of SlothCreator.
Let's rewind and take a look
to see how it got to that point.
My colleague Ethan
will start off by showing
some of the new features
in Xcode 13
to write great documentation.
Take it away.
[Ethan] Thank you, Victoria.
Now that we've gone over
Xcode 13's great support
for building
and browsing documentation,
I'd like to show you
a few tricks
to write even better
documentation with DocC.
DocC is designed around
the benefits
of in-source documentation.
You write your documentation
right alongside your code,
making it convenient
and easy to integrate
with your existing
development workflow.
To add documentation
to a declaration,
you just write a special kind
of comment directly above it.
This makes it easy to keep
your documentation in sync
with any code changes
you might make in the future.
And, of course,
it will fit right in
with your existing text-based
tooling, like Git diffs.
You're likely already
annotating your source code
with comments
to provide extra context
to future maintainers
of your codebase.
In Swift and many other
languages, you write a comment
by starting your line
with two forward slashes.
By writing these comments,
you've gone a long way
in helping future maintainers
to understand
and be productive
within your codebase.
But what
if you want to help
today's adopters
of your framework?
This is what documentation
comments are for.
By writing a comment
that begins with
three forward slashes,
you're telling the Swift
documentation compiler
to associate the comment
with the declaration
immediately below it.
The comment will be
included in the symbol's
compiled documentation page
and accessible to anyone
who imports your framework.
And if you prefer to use
block-style comments,
you can create a documentation
comment in that style
by just including
an extra asterisk
in the opening delimiter.
Let's see how this all
works in practice.
As Victoria mentioned,
over the last few months,
we've been working
on the SlothCreator framework.
SlothCreator is a Swift
package that provides
functionality for cataloging
and customizing cute sloths.
As a developer of SlothCreator,
I want to be sure
that there's an easy way for
any adopters of the framework
to get started,
so I've been working on
adding documentation comments
to the parts
of the codebase I worked on.
In particular,
I want to be sure that every
public API in SlothCreator
is well documented,
because it's these API
that are accessible
to anyone
importing my framework.
For the same reason,
DocC only generates
documentation pages
for the public
and open symbols
in your framework.
There's just a couple
of symbols in SlothCreator
that still need documenting.
Let's start
with this Food struct.
I'll begin by adding
three forward slashes
above the type's declaration
to create
a documentation comment.
And then I'll write that this is
"Food that a sloth can consume."
The first line of my
documentation comment
will turn into
the symbol's summary,
but I'd like to add
some extra information
with a discussion section.
I'll add one now
by adding a line break
after my summary and then
adding some additional detail
about the kinds
of foods sloths love.
And because DocC has full
support for Markdown,
I can add a code example
using Markdown's
fenced code block syntax.
Great.
I think this adds some really
helpful additional context
around the Food struct.
Let's see how my documentation
is looking now
by rebuilding documentation.
I can do that by moving
my mouse up to the Product menu
and then selecting
Build Documentation.
Xcode will now rebuild
SlothCreator's documentation
alongside
the framework itself.
And because I used
the Build Documentation
button for this build,
when it's complete,
the documentation viewer
will open with
my updated documentation.
But I'm actually interested
in going straight to the page
for the Food struct to review
the comment we just added.
Fortunately, Xcode has
a feature called Quick Help
that will let me do just that.
Quick Help offers
a short summarized version
of a symbol's documentation
right in the source editor.
I can try it out now
by holding down the Option key
and then clicking
on Food's declaration.
But an adopter of SlothCreator
could open the same view
by option-clicking on any
reference to the Food struct
in their code.
So the comment we wrote
is right here
in the Summary
and Discussion sections.
But if I'm looking for more
than the summarized view,
new in Xcode 13 is the Open
in Developer Documentation link.
If I move my mouse
to the bottom right-hand corner
of the Quick Help view
and click on Open
in Developer Documentation,
the documentation window
will launch
right to that symbol's page.
Awesome.
There's one other symbol
that's still missing
documentation in SlothCreator.
I'll open the Sloth file
by moving my mouse
over to Xcode's Navigator
and clicking on the Sloth item.
And if I scroll down,
I'm noticing that the Eat method
still needs
a documentation comment.
So let's take a quick look
at the best way
of documenting methods.
We start the same way,
by adding a triple-slash
comment
above the method's
declaration and adding text
that will make up
its documentation summary.
But we should also
document specifically
what we're expecting to be
passed as a parameter.
We do this via
a Parameters section.
You add a Parameters section
to your documentation
by writing
a Markdown list item
starting with
the word Parameter
followed by the name
of your method's parameter,
a colon,
and then its documentation.
You can add a Returns section
in a very similar way,
this time by writing a Returns
delimiter followed by a colon
and a description of what
your method returns.
But what if your method
has multiple parameters?
In this case, the best
thing to do is to go from
a singular Parameter delimiter
to a plural Parameters one.
This works much the same
as the others
except your parameter names
are written
as children of the parent
Parameters delimiter.
So now that
we've gone over the basics,
let's document
the sloth Eat method.
Now, I could begin
the same way we did
when documenting
the Food struct
by manually writing
a documentation comment
beginning
with three forward slashes.
But since I'm documenting
a more complicated symbol,
I'm going to take
advantage of Xcode's great
Add Documentation feature
which will insert a template
best-suited for documenting
the current declaration.
I can do this by holding
down the Command key
and then clicking on
the method's declaration
to open the Action menu.
Next, I can click
on Add Documentation
in the Action menu
and, just like that,
I have a great template to get
started documenting my method.
I'll begin by filling out
the method's summary,
and then I'll describe the
food and quantity parameters
as well as
what this method returns.
And then I'll finish off
the documentation by adding
a Discussion section
along with a code example.
Just like last time,
I can rebuild documentation
by moving my mouse
to the Product menu
and selecting
the Build Documentation item.
And once again, Xcode
is building my documentation
alongside
the framework itself.
This time, I'll navigate
to the Sloth struct
via the window's Navigator,
where I'll find Sloth
in the Sloths topic group.
If I scroll
down on the Sloth page,
I'll find my method in the
Instance Methods section...
Along with my updated
documentation.
I'm already really happy
with it.
The inputs and outputs
of the method
are really well defined,
and there's a helpful
code example here as well.
I think this is nearly
ready to go,
but we're still
missing something here.
If I'm just reading this
page of documentation,
I don't have a great
context of the other
relevant symbols I should
be considering here.
And as a maintainer
of SlothCreator,
I'd really like to call out
some other symbols
that my reader should consider
learning about next.
Well, new to Xcode 13
is the ability to link to
symbols in your documentation.
This is a really great way
to connect
different parts
of your framework
and guide your reader to
relevant pieces of information.
You write these links via
a new double backtick syntax.
Let's look at an example.
Here's the method we
previously documented, sleep.
But it doesn't exist
in a vacuum.
There's actually another
property in the Sloth struct.
There's a value representing
the current energy level
of the sloth,
and I think
it's important here
for my reader to understand
that one
of the side effects
of calling sleep is a change
to the sloth's energy level.
So I'll add to my methods
Discussion section here
with a reference
to the energyLevel property.
Before Xcode 13,
the natural way to do this
would be to just write
the property's name
in a monospace code font by
surrounding it in backticks.
But now I can transform
to double backtick syntax
and create a link.
Now, linking to energyLevel
was pretty simple because
that property is a sibling
of the method I'm documenting,
and just like when referencing
a local variable in Swift,
I don't need to further qualify
my link with the parent type.
I can just write the name
of the property, energyLevel.
But if I want to reference
a child of a different type,
I need to be
a little more specific.
So here I write
Habitat/comfortLevel
to link to a child
of the Habitat struct.
Great.
Let's see how this works
in practice by adding some links
to the documentation
for the eat method.
I'll begin here
by writing that
"When they eat food,
a sloth's..."
and now I'm going to
write a symbol link
to the energyLevel property.
So I'll type two backticks,
and then I'll begin
writing energyLevel.
Xcode's code completion
will help me out
to make sure I'm
getting the correct link.
I'll go ahead and select
that item.
And so I'll say that
the energy level
"increases by the food's"--
and now I'm going to
reference a child
of the Food struct.
I'll begin
with two backticks again.
And then I'll write Food,
a forward slash,
and then energy.
I've now created two
symbol links which I think
are going to really help
my reader understand
the context around
this method better.
And these links are even
accessible in Quick Help.
So I'll hold down the Option key
and click on
my method's declaration
to open the Quick Help popover.
Here's the Discussion
section we added
and, of course, in the
discussion, our two links.
And if I click on one,
I'm brought straight to
the referenced symbol's page
in the documentation window.
Now that I've written
a good documentation comment
for every public API
in SlothCreator,
I'm really excited to share
it with my colleagues
and maybe even make it
available on the web.
I can do this via
the documentation archive
that Xcode outputs as part
of every documentation build.
Contained in the documentation
archive is a single-page web app
that you can use to share your
documentation on the web.
My colleague David will be going
in depth on just how to do that
in his “Host and automate
your DocC documentation” session.
I highly recommend
you check that one out.
But Xcode also supports
exporting and importing
your documentation directly from
the documentation window.
Let's take a look at that now.
I'll export SlothCreator
from the documentation window
by first moving my mouse over
to the window's Navigator.
When I hover over
the SlothCreator framework item,
a contextual menu icon
will appear.
I'll click on it, and now
I have the option to Export.
I'll just save it to my desktop.
Great.
Now I'm ready to send it
off to my colleagues,
and if they just
double-click on the archive,
it will open in Xcode's
documentation window.
But since I already know
about SlothCreator,
I'd like to open up a different
documentation archive.
I've recently been discussing
with the team
that it would be great
to add a command line
interface to SlothCreator,
and one of my colleagues
mentioned that ArgumentParser
They sent me the latest
documentation archive
for ArgumentParser,
so let's open it up now.
I can just double-click
on the documentation archive
and, just like that,
get started learning right away.
Documentation is key
to developing a successful
and long-lasting framework.
We think that you'll find
writing documentation
directly in source is really
convenient and powerful.
And new in Xcode 13
with DocC integration,
all your hard work writing
great documentation
is going to pay off
in new and powerful ways.
We have several other
sessions at WWDC
that really help you take your
documentation to the next level.
“Elevate your DocC documentation
in Xcode”
picks up where
this session leaves off,
showing you how to better
organize your documentation
by adding
a documentation catalog.
“Host and automate
your DocC documentation,”
which I mentioned earlier,
explains how to integrate
documentation builds
into your existing continuous
integration setup
as well as how to host
your documentation online.
Finally, if you have
a more complicated
part of your framework
that could benefit from
step-by-step instruction,
I recommend you check out
“Build interactive tutorials
in DocC”
which will show
you how to do just that.
Thank you for watching.
[percussive music]