[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Olivia Hillman: Hi,
I'm Olivia Hillman,
and I'm a security engineer
working on Apple's
Notary service.
I'm going to talk to you
about some exciting
work we've been doing
to make notarizing Mac apps
faster and simpler.
I'll start with a brief overview
of what the Notary service is.
Then I'll dive into our new tool
and I'll share how you
can get started using it.
So, let's begin!
Notarization is
for Mac developers
that distribute their software
outside of the App Store,
and this talk specifically
is for those of you
that use the existing
command-line tool, altool
to interact with Notary.
If you're notarizing
with Xcode only,
your workflow isn't changing.
Mac developers submit
their software to be notarized
before it's distributed,
so it can run on a user's Mac.
This notarization process
gives users confidence
that software running
on their machines
has been checked by Apple
for malicious components.
Notarization has been helping
to protect customers
since macOS 10.14.
And now, we've made it
faster and simpler to use.
For more background
about Notary,
check out our in-depth 2019 talk
"All about Notarization".
Let's take a look
at the Notary workflow.
Developers build their software
and send it to us
for notarization.
The Notary service
runs automated analysis
that scans the software
for malicious content
and checks for code signing
issues.
If there are no issues,
Notary publishes a ticket
to be retrieved by users’ Macs
when they launch the software.
And then we return the result
to your developer team.
We're committed to completing
this process within 15 minutes
for 98 percent
of Notary submissions,
and most complete in under five.
You can then provide your app
for users to download,
and macOS checks the software
before it can run
on a user's machine.
We care about protecting
customers from malware
and making it easier for
developers to submit to Notary
and even faster for users
to get access to new software.
And with that mission in mind,
I'm thrilled to share with you
the new way to notarize.
Introducing notarytool.
notarytool provides
a one-line command
for submitting your software
and waiting for your result.
We've introduced
targeted enhancements
focused specifically on
the needs of Mac developers
that are notarizing software
independently
without the need for altool's
App Store support.
These improvements make
notarization faster and easier,
all while we continue to protect
customers from malware.
Developers depend on
the Notary service,
so we want it to be
as reliable as possible
and available whenever
developers need it.
In addition to the changes
to the client software,
we've also streamlined
the service.
In fact, we've built
a new dedicated service backend
that's focused on reliability
just for Notary.
The new service is designed
to bring you improvements
in end-to-end processing speed,
and we're excited
for you to try it out.
We know you may be waiting
as your submission uploads,
so we've worked hard
to make upload speed
up to four times faster
for most developers.
To take advantage of these
incredible performance
and reliability gains,
be sure to transition
from altool to notarytool.
notarytool is easy to use
and carefully designed
with your notarization
workflow in mind.
We've heard your feedback
and we wanted to improve
the developer interaction
with a simpler client
and a single line
to get things done.
So let's say I'm a developer
and I've just finished building
the latest bug fix to my app.
I want to get this published
as soon as possible.
The quickest way
for me to accomplish this
with altool on the command line
is with a polling loop,
like this.
I first submit my application,
and when that's done,
I start to continuously
poll for status
until processing is complete.
Now, with notarytool,
we've added a wait flag
to the client
that allows you to submit
and wait for
your notarization result
all in one command.
As soon as your job completes,
the program will display
the results of your submission.
Once you receive
your submission result,
you're only one command away
from viewing your Notary log
using the new client.
You'll be able to view details
about your result
directly from notarytool,
including any reasons
why your application
may not be notarized.
We've also added
a brand-new feature
that's accessible to you
when you submit to Notary:
webhook notifications.
This feature allows you
to specify a URL
for a server callback
as soon as we finish
processing your software.
By specifying a webhook URL
when you submit,
you can seamlessly add
notarization
into your continuous
integration workflows
by automatically retrieving
your result and your Notary log
when you receive a notification.
We can't wait for you to start
using this powerful new tool,
and we look forward to receiving
your feedback about notarytool
and this new
developer experience.
notarytool is the new client
for interacting
with the Notary service
and is distributed with Xcode.
altool isn't going away,
but is now deprecated
for use with Notary.
notarytool makes your workflow
faster and simpler
with a client that's dedicated
to the Notary service.
You'll be able
to find more details
about the latest features
and performance improvements
in the documentation linked to
this talk in the coming weeks.
Access to the tool is available
with the latest Xcode build,
with information
to help you get started
in the tool's man pages.
So make the switch today
to start distributing software
more quickly and seamlessly
than ever before.
Thank you.
♪