[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Dan]
My name is Dan Harris.
I'm a longtime --that's my way
of saying I'm old--
longtime correspondent
and anchorman
with "ABC News."
I've worked at "ABC News"
for 21 years.
And then about seven years ago,
I wrote a book
called "Ten Percent Happier,"
which was about how
a skeptical journalist
came to embrace meditation.
For me, the whole thing
started with a panic attack,
a very public panic attack
on "Good Morning America."
Even more embarrassing
than having a panic attack
on national television was what
caused the panic attack.
I think at the root
of that meltdown
was something that everybody
who is part of this conference
has, which is ambition.
I arrived at "ABC News"
at the big leagues,
the network, at the tender age
of 28 years old,
and I was really anxious
about being so young
and being so inexperienced,
and I just threw myself
into my work in a really, really
sort of workaholic-style way.
And shortly after
I arrived at "ABC News,"
there was a huge event
in the news, and that was 9/11.
And I kind of raised my hand
after 9/11 to volunteer
to go overseas to cover
whatever was gonna happen next,
and I spent many years
in war zones
like Afghanistan and Israel,
the West Bank,
Gaza, a lot of time in Iraq…
six or seven long stays in Iraq.
And I came home
in the middle of this period,
and I got depressed,
although I didn't actually know
I was depressed,
and I did something
extremely stupid at this point,
which is I started
to self-medicate
with recreational drugs.
And even though my drug use,
primarily cocaine,
was pretty limited
and I was never high on the air,
after I went to--
after the panic attack,
I went to go see a doctor,
and he asked me
a bunch of questions.
And one of the questions
was, "Do you do drugs?"
And I kind of sheepishly
said, "Yeah, I do."
And he gave me a look
that indicated, "OK, moron.
Mystery solved."
And he pointed out
that even though the drug use
was somewhat unspectacular,
it was enough
to change my brain chemistry
and make it more likely
for me to freak out.
So this was
a huge ‘Aha!’ moment for me,
and I decided to quit
doing drugs
and to go see this shrink once
or twice a week indefinitely.
I started to poke around
and realized that there was
a lot of evidence that suggested
that meditation
was really good for you,
that it could lower
your blood pressure,
boost your immune system,
literally rewire
key parts of your brain.
And there was at this time
a not very well-publicized
body of research
that strongly suggested
that meditation
was really good for you,
so I started to try it,
and I started with, like,
five or ten minutes a day.
And I found that there
were really three main benefits.
The first benefit
is that it made me calmer.
Now, I want to be careful
about this word, "calm."
Because some people sit
and meditate, and they expect
to feel calm immediately
and that if they don't,
they feel like
they're a failed meditator.
That's not quite how it works.
Just because
you sit to meditate,
you are not necessarily
going to get calm lickety-split.
But the cumulative effect
of taking myself
out of the traffic
for five minutes every day
just injected my overall life
with a little bit
more calm and sanity.
The second benefit
is that it helped me with focus.
As you'll see in a minute,
meditation,
the practice of meditation
is generally where you just try
to pick one thing
to pay attention to,
usually the feeling of
your breath coming in
or going out,
and then every time
you get distracted,
you start again
and again and again.
And every time you do that,
it's like a bicep curl
for your brain.
And this has been shown
on brain scans
to change the area of the brain
associated
with attention regulation,
and I really found
that in my hectic life
where I actually have
other people's voices
piped directly into my head
as a news anchor,
it really helped me…
meditation…
it really helped me
to stay on task.
The third benefit
is the most important one,
and it's a word
that is thrown around
a lot these days.
It's become
somewhat of a buzz phrase,
and it's mindfulness.
Mindfulness is,
just to put it very simply,
it's the skill
that allows you to notice
what's happening in your head
at any given moment without
getting carried away by it.
I'm just going to--I'm just
going to say that again
because this is really
the most important point.
Mindfulness is the ability,
the kind of self-awareness
that allows you to notice
what's happening
in your body
and in your mind
without necessarily
taking the bait
and acting on it.
So, for example,
I would notice that I would be
in a conversation
with my wife,
maybe things weren't going well.
I would notice, "Oh, yeah,
I'm starting to get angry,"
but I don't have
to say something
that's gonna ruin
the next 48 hours of my life.
Or maybe I'm bored or lonely
and I see a zombie arm
reaching into the cabinet
and aiming to scarf
a sleeve of Oreos,
but I would notice the urge
and, instead of acting on it
reflexively, I would be able
to respond wisely.
And that was really--
it doesn't work all the time,
which is why I call my book
"Ten Percent Happier,"
but when it does work,
it's a game changer,
and it is a skill that you
can improve over time.
So as advertised
at the beginning
of this talk,
I want to bring in somebody
who's a genuine
meditation expert
to talk a little bit more
about how we can apply
these skills now
and how we can boot up a habit
because habit change
is often very, very tricky.
My friend's name is Jeff Warren.
He's a meditation teacher
based in Toronto.
He and I wrote a book together
a few years ago
called "Meditation
for Fidgety Skeptics,”
and as part of that book,
we traveled
all across the United States
of America in a bus.
So let me just show you
a little clip of that
and then I'll bring in Jeff
on the backside.
♪ ♪
Good times.
Jeffrey, are you there?
Can you hear me?
[Jeff] I'm here, Dan.
It's good to see you.
Always good for me to hear
your story
of public humiliation.
[laughter]
[Dan] Yes, Jeff has meditated
for many years to develop
a highly valuable skill
called schadenfreude,
which I recommend to everybody.
[Jeff] Apparently compassion
is supposed to emerge
spontaneously at some point.
I'm still waiting for it.
[Dan] Jeff, it's really great
to see you.
Let me just ask you.
I'm assuming--
you know, we wrote a book
called "Meditation
for Fidgety Skeptics."
I'm assuming
there are some fidgety skeptics
in this audience,
so, yes, I just said everything
about all that meditation
has done for me,
but let me just hear from you.
If somebody's watching this
and thinking,
"Why should I do this?
What's in it for me?"
How do you answer that question?
[Jeff]
How about emancipation?
I would say that's probably--
for me, it's been sanity,
and it's been a sense
of more control in my life.
More control over my--
how I respond
to the world
and not being a victim
to every impulse
and whim and emotion
and mood that picks me up
and takes me around,
which they do a lot.
So it's been--it's kind of,
like, given me my life back.
So--not all at once.
It's kind of
a progressive thing,
but there's no question
that's been the big effect,
and then the roll-on effect
from that
is when you're
more centered in your life,
you're more available
for everyone else.
So my relationships,
yeah, they've gotten better —
my friendships,
my family relationships —
I mean, the roll-on effects
are quite significant.
So how's that for a start?
[Dan] You and I
are meditation nerds.
I mean, unreconstructed
meditation nerds,
and I think appropriately
based on scientific evidence
and the evidence
of our own minds,
we are focused on getting people
thinking about meditation.
And I do, though, want to say
that I kind of put meditation
in what I call a pantheon
of no-brainers when it comes
to taking care of yourself
so that you can be
maximally effective,
and I think there are
probably at least five
other things I would
put in this pantheon.
So start with meditation,
but I would also add sleep,
which is incredibly important.
Exercise,
healthy eating--
without getting
too obsessive about it,
so I think it's important
to eat healthy
but not to the point
where you're obsessing
about what you're eating
all the time.
The fourth thing I would
say is nature, access to nature.
There's a ton of data
that strongly indicate
that if you are getting
consistent access to nature
that it's going to have
all sorts of physiological
and psychological benefits.
And then finally,
and I mentioned this
a little bit earlier,
but I think it bears repeating.
The quality
of your relationships--
now I'm stealing a quote
from somebody else,
so I'll own that
in the middle of this quote.
"The quality
of your relationships
will dictate
the quality of your life."
That's a quote
from Esther Perel
who's a legendary
couples counselor and podcaster.
And, you know, it's so true
as to be a truism in some ways,
this notion
that relationships matter.
We are a social species.
The reason why,
for better or worse,
humans took over the planet
is not because
we were the strongest.
It was because
we could work together
to take down the mastodon
or whatever it was,
so this need
for social connection is,
you know, just baked
into the motherboard for us,
and that was my attempt
to use some sort
of vaguely
technological language.
I don't even know
if that was appropriate,
but, anyway,
it's baked into our DNA
and so--
but it's easily overlooked
at a time--
especially in the West
when there's such an emphasis
on individual achievement
and we tend to live
away from our families —
and the number of people who say
they have close confidants
has declined over time —
and many of us have our nose
in screens all the time —
that there's a way in which
we can deemphasize the value
of relationships —
and we have just run
a global unregulated experiment
in what happens
when you deny social connection,
and the results
are really clear…
massive spikes
in anxiety, depression,
addiction, and suicide.
[Jeff]
Oh, my God, absolutely.
[Dan] I think something
that a lot of people
are struggling with now
after this long period
of lockdown,
which, for many of us,
is not over —
in some parts of the world,
we're emerging from lockdown —
we're really still in it —
but social anxiety
is a real issue.
It was a real issue
going into the pandemic
and I would imagine
even more so now.
Do you have any thoughts
about how to manage that?
[Jeff]
I would say a couple things.
The first is a seated practice
of five or ten minutes
of just getting relaxed
will center you
and make you--and, you know,
help you manage
that anxiety a little bit more.
I mean, that's just a kind of
a no-brainer
from my perspective.
Another thing is to get clear
about what is
actually making you anxious
and share that
with the people that you need
to hang out with.
So this is, again,
where the mindfulness thing
can be useful.
You know, we may
have a specific anxiety
'cause, you know,
you have some friends that want
to suddenly abandon the masks
and start hugging way sooner
than you're ready to do it,
or you're worried about the--
you have specific anxieties
about travel or you're--
whatever it is,
like, you
have a specific anxiety,
but until you actually
look and notice what it is,
that thing will own you
in a kind of a vague,
generalized way.
You'll just know
you don't really want
to go outside around people.
You won't really have
a good excuse for what it is,
or you can't really--you know,
you're just--because you
haven't brought clarity
to what's actually going
on in your experience.
So taking the time
to really identify,
what is
it that I'm worried about?
Can I--what
is the specific thing?
And then, based on that,
having conversations
with the people in your life
around--if there's any protocols
you might be able
to collectively agree on.
I mean, that's--it may sound
so common-sense,
but I think this is, again,
the great move of practice,
the great move of mindfulness
is to begin to actually
clarify what's really going on
in your experience,
and we may hear that
and think, "Oh, yeah,
that makes sense."
But we don't realize
that we're subject
to this kind of
unconscious thing all the time,
that we're
not actually doing that.
We don't have a lot of clarity
about what would
actually help us.
[Dan] People may be wondering,
"OK, how do I do this?
How do I start meditating?"
And often,
the question people have is,
"What's the least amount
I can do
and get all of
the advertised benefits?"
What's your recommendation
for folks
who are trying to boot up
a habit?
- Five minutes, ten minutes?
I mean, what you want is to give
your nervous system a taste.
So I would say just start
with five minutes a day.
And just--and then, you know,
let the practice inform you.
If you do five minutes
and, you know,
you can play around with--
I mean, the basic strategy
is just to sit
and notice your breath,
but you can play around
with other objects,
something else
that's just whatever,
for whatever reason,
is interesting to you.
But take five minutes
and see if you can
completely commit yourself
in that way,
and then notice--do you feel
a little bit more settled after?
If you do, then that's
a good place to begin.
And then, you know, I--
there's value
to moving it up from there,
but sometimes
five minutes a day is all I get,
but I'm gonna actually
throw it back to you,
Dan, 'cause
I know you're, like,
the expert at getting
regular folks to meditate.
So what's
your advice around this?
[Dan] I'll lower
the bar even further.
Try to meditate
for at least one minute
on 25 out of 31 days.
And this is actually
backed by science.
What we know
about habit formation
is that it is
infernally difficult
and that the best way
to approach it
is with a sense of humor,
a sense of exploration,
and a sense of humility,
that it's hard for everybody,
including you,
and so if you set the bar low,
you're more likely to succeed,
and so we have
these two little slogans
that kind of govern
our approach,
and actually I came up
with these slogans
while working with you, Jeff,
on our book,
"Meditation
for Fidgety Skeptics."
One slogan is
"One minute counts."
Yes, I would love
to see you
do five to ten minutes,
even more,
but let's be honest, again,
given what I said,
what we all know
about habit formation
being difficult, one minute--
in one minute
you can get a sense
of how wild the mind is,
and therefore you have
a little bit of a leg up
in dealing with
all of the terrible ideas
that the voice in your head
is offering up
to you on the regular.
And then the other
little slogan is "daily-ish."
Again, I would love
to see you do this every day.
I try to do it every day,
but if you tell yourself,
"I am gonna do this every day,"
and then you miss a day,
there is some
reasonable likelihood
that the voice in your head
will swoop in
and tell you, "Well,
you're a failed meditator now.
Deuces, I'm out."
And so "daily-ish" provides
what the psychologists call
psychological flexibility.
It's a kind of elasticity
that allows you
to start over,
and that resiliency,
the capacity
to start over, is so key
in a meditation practice
while you're
actually meditating,
and it is so key when it comes
to starting any habit
that you have to--
because it's so hard
to do this, you have to be able
to pick yourself up
after three weeks
of not meditating
or three weeks of not exercising
and say,
"OK, nothing's been lost.
I can just start again."
So I know
I lowered the bar there, Jeff,
from what you said.
Does that give you--
does that give you hives?
[Jeff]
No, not at all.
I mean, I use the same thing,
so I think it's exactly--
I mean, do what works.
Do whatever you can
to start to kind of get into it,
get a bit of a taste of it,
and I think one minute is--
if that can give you
a taste of it, perfect.
[Dan] So since we keep talking
about meditation, Jeff,
it may make sense to me--
if you're up for it,
to--let's just do
just a few minutes
of it 'cause I think
once people have a sense
of how simple this is
and how doable it is--
are you game for that?
[Jeff]
Oh, yes, I am.
In fact,
I was thinking--
I'm gonna guide a dead-simple,
five minute meditation,
but I'm gonna do it
with our audience in mind,
knowing that we have
a group of creatives
and developers and programmers.
I'm gonna use this metaphor
that I'll thread into it
that will hopefully speak
to that audience
and help actually dramatize
what it is we're doing.
So that's the five-minute
meditation intro.
So go ahead and close your eyes.
Get yourself into,
you know, whatever position
just feels comfortable.
Actually, you can even
have them open if you like,
looking at the ground
in front of you.
It's sort of user's choice.
Now if you're closing
your eyes or open,
you start
with a few deep breaths…
stretching out the spine
on the inhale…
and then the exhale
is kind of like
your "ahhhhh…”
Super relaxing.
Sending a wave of relaxation
down through the body,
meaning deliberately
softening your forehead...
and your shoulders...
and your belly.
With each exhale,
you can imagine
you're, you know,
settling a little more,
landing a little more
in your chair
or wherever you're sitting.
And the first thing
I like to do
at the very start
of the meditation
is--it's sort of tuning in
with this internal adjustment,
the equanimity adjustment,
which just means
the "letting everything be here"
adjustment.
So you're not gonna get uptight
about sounds being imperfect
in your environment or the fact
that you might have lots
of thoughts
or very few thoughts
or your body's uncomfortable.
It's all--the idea
is that you're just gonna
let all this be there.
We're kind of embracing
the imperfection of life,
and that actually is palpable
as an adjustment.
It's sort of, like, this--
the other way of being is
a kind of uptightness.
[growls]
Instead, just kind of
melting everything.
So sounds just pass through you.
Body sensations and thoughts
rise and fall.
It's all good.
And then we settle
into this creaturely pose.
Maybe feeling the breath.
And what's happening here is--
it's like our experience
has all these different layers.
And there's sort of
an "into it" quality
in meditation.
Sort of one of the secrets
is you choose.
You decide.
Not only are you choosing
which layer to pay attention to.
You're kind of choosing
to maybe a little bit
enjoy this opportunity
to take a break.
Seeing if you can kind of
get into the feeling
of breathing
like you're kind of into it.
You know,
if we make it enjoyable,
you're just gonna want
to meditate more,
as opposed to making it
some grim endurance test.
The mind wanders.
Totally natural.
You notice 'cause you've got
this awareness thing going on.
You notice that layer
that got activated
that superimposed itself
over top of the breath
and kind of drifted away,
and then you come back
to the breath layer.
And you let the thought
just play out on its own.
Now you're not feeding it.
It doesn't have to go away.
You're not trying
to get rid of thinking.
That thinking process
will just keep unspooling.
So just for fun here -
we're working with our layers -
we just select
this item in the menu,
in the drop-down menu,
one of the tools —
the good-naturedness tool.
Make sure that's selected.
It's kind of like you're kind of
putting a warm glow
over everything,
so you're just kind of--
you're enjoying your experience.
I'm going to risk
a 20-second silence here
before we wrap it up,
then I'll come in at the end,
but just seeing how fully
you can commit yourself to this.
Some sensation in the body.
The more we feel
what's here in the body,
things start to settle.
Sensations get subtler.
As we get more still,
our experience
often gets more still —
and then a thought
comes and takes us away.
That layer gets activated.
We notice.
We come back.
And that's the--
that's the movement of practice.
The movement is committing,
getting distracted,
recommitting,
and then suffusing
the proceedings with a kind of
equanimous good-naturedness.
So I'll just let us have
a few more seconds here.
And then as we prepare
to move out
of this
extremely short meditation,
just notice…
Do you feel more settled?
… More present?
And that's
the litmus test ultimately.
How is it--how do you
bring the practice back?
Now when you're ready,
open your eyes.
[Dan]
Thank you, Jeff.
There were two things
you emphasized, at least,
in that meditation
that I want
to kind of just reemphasize.
One is the immense benefit
of getting out
of your head and into your body.
It's--this is sadly a bit
of a cliché, you know,
the body knows,
et cetera, et cetera,
but there's a reason
why clichés become clichés,
and that's because they're true.
And I love this word you used
where you get us to kind of
get in touch
with the creaturely feeling
of having a body.
Most of us, you know, we're like
Macy's Day parade balloons.
We're just all head
floating through the world
with a tiny little body
just dragged beneath it,
but actually there's
enormous potential
to getting out
of the spinning stories,
which are
mostly past and future,
and into your body.
It can be really calming.
The other thing you talked about
is the fact that we are
gonna be distracted
in meditation.
All sorts of crazy things
are gonna go through your mind.
What's for lunch?
Do we need a haircut?
Blah, blah, blah…
And a lot of people feel or fear
that when they get distracted
in this way,
when they sit and meditate
and notice
that working with the mind
is a little bit like holding
a live fish in your hand,
a lot of people
tell themselves a story
that,
"Oh, I'm a failed meditator.
I can never do this."
And that's because there's this
really pernicious misconception
that correct meditation
involves clearing your mind.
As I like to joke,
clearing your mind
isn't possible
unless you're enlightened
or you've died.
The whole game in meditation
is to notice
when you've become distracted…
again and again and again…
and just start over,
and this is the bicep curl
for your brain,
and this is what shows up
on the brain scans
of meditators.
So I just want to--
and by the way,
it has this really important--
I shouldn't--
this isn't a "by the way."
This is a
"Here's the sales point."
The value
of seeing the cacophony
and chaos of your own mind
is that when you're ambushed
by anger or random urges
or random distracting thoughts
off the cushion
in your actual life,
you're less likely
to be owned by it.
That's what we're doing here
in meditation is getting
more familiar with the workings
of our own mind
so that it's not yanking us
around all the time,
so that we can learn
how to respond wisely
to the things in our life
instead of reacting blindly.
So anyway, Jeff,
I just said a bunch of stuff.
Does any of that
make sense to you?
[Jeff]
It doesn't just make sense.
It's familiar to the benefits
of how meditation
have showed up
in my life personally.
Everything you just said there,
I've found to be true for me.
[Dan]
Beautiful.
Let me ask you
one last question, Jeff,
before we let everybody go.
Especially for this crowd,
I think
an interesting question is,
"How do we manage what,
for many of us,
is a fraught relationship
to technology?"
What do you do to make sure
that you're using technology
as a tool and not having it
the other way around
where the technology
is owning you?
[Jeff] Well, I mean,
it's super hard
because so many
of our connections
happen virtually now.
I mean, that's how I
stay connected to my parents,
you know, and my friends
all over the place.
All my work happens.
I would say
it's being smart about
getting balance
in the nervous system
by not being so fixated
on a single thing,
and you get that feedback
by beginning to pay attention
to what's going on,
you know?
So you take a--you know,
you take a pause
in your work and you go,
"OK, let me check in.
How am I doing over here?"
I mean, that's the--
the mind is very, very powerful.
It's like a superpower,
but it will completely take over
with its obsessiveness.
So I think that that's
how I manage my technology use.
I'm constantly stopping,
stretching,
going for a walk, come back.
And I also make sure
that I'm only, you know,
doing X amount
of screen time a day,
and that amount of time
is a lot lower now
than it used to be.
[Dan] I just want
to wrap up here
with one final appeal.
I think happiness is
such a commonly-
misunderstood concept.
What the science
around meditation
is showing us, the neuroscience,
the looking into people's brains
and looking at what happens
when they meditate -
what this is showing us
is that happiness is a skill -
that the mind is trainable -
that all the things we want
can really be boiled down
to mind states.
We may think we want
professional success,
romantic success,
to get that new car,
to go on that big vacation,
all of which are fine
to have as goals,
but what we really want
are the mental states
that accompany those goals.
And as it turns out,
all of these
mental states--
calm, happiness, connection,
compassion, love--
these are trainable skills,
and meditation is one modality
through which you can do it,
so I really do encourage you
to give it a shot.
Before I close,
I just want to say,
Jeff, thank you.
I love you.
It's great to see you.
Thanks for doing this with me.
[Jeff] No, problem.
I love you too, buddy.
[Dan] I know we are living
through really difficult times,
and I just want
to wish you the best
and hope that you
can hang in there
and also to thank you
for watching this talk.
♪ ♪