[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Nathan Tannar: Hello,
and welcome to WWDC!
My name is Nathan,
and I'm an engineer
on the Accessibility team.
Today we'll be going
beyond the basics to learn
how to deliver exceptional
and accessible SwiftUI apps.
This year marks
a huge leap forward
for accessibility in SwiftUI.
At Apple, accessibility
is one of our core values.
Our assistive technologies
across all our platforms
make sure that anyone
can use your app
regardless of any physical,
visual, audible,
or motor impairment.
My team and I work to make sure
most of your app is accessible
by default,
but there is always more you can
do to enrich the experience.
Today I'll show you the new
tools and APIs for SwiftUI
that make enriching
this experience easy.
Let's begin with the tooling
improvements in Xcode.
SwiftUI Previews have changed
how many of us develop apps.
It dramatically improves
your ability to iterate
upon your views
across multiple environments,
all without the need
of running your app.
To make the most important
accessibility modifiers
just a click away,
we've added a curated list
of accessibility editors.
I hope this encourages everyone
to always make
their views accessible.
But there's more.
Since accessibility modifiers
don't have visual changes
in the previews,
a new tool was developed
that allows you
to inspect the accessibility of
your view without leaving Xcode.
Let's switch
from the editor's panel
to the new accessibility panel.
Shipping in Xcode 13,
SwiftUI Previews
will now also feature
an Accessibility Preview.
With it, you can inspect
the accessibility elements
for a preview in real time.
And this is a game changer.
Accessibility Preview will help
you make accessible apps
even if you don't have
a deep understanding
of each assistive technology.
Let's take a closer look to see
how changes are reflected
in the Accessibility Preview.
This is a simplified version
of the view we just saw.
After running the preview,
I can select the VStack
and the Accessibility Preview
will update
to display the elements
in their sorted order.
Notice that each element
will always display
its basic properties --
such as a label and traits.
For example, the Text view will
create an accessibility element
with the string as its label.
It also gains
the .isStaticText trait.
The preview will update for any
accessibility changes we make,
such as adding
the .isHeader trait.
You will also be able to see
some of the automatic
accessibility that takes place
behind the scenes, such as
automatic SF Symbol labels.
For example, the
checkmark.seal.fill symbol
is labeled "Verified"
by default.
If you're relying on a symbol's
default label, it's important
to check that it accurately
describes your interface.
We'll continue to use
the Accessibility Preview
as we step through
five importance areas
that'll help you deliver
an exceptional experience
to all of your app's users.
We'll start by examining
the best way
to make custom
controls accessible.
Next, we'll discuss how to make
a view accessible with children.
I'll highlight
how to audit your app
for common navigation problems
and how the Accessibility
Preview can assist with this.
Then I'll show you
how to supercharge
your app's navigation
with VoiceOver rotors.
And finally, we'll look at focus
and how it relates
to assistive technologies.
I've been working to prototype
a new finance app
I call Wallet Pal.
It's still in the early stages,
but so far, I'm pretty happy
with the initial design.
I was pleased to hear that early
beta testers are also loving it.
Now that I've polished the UI,
I should spend some time
to polish
the accessibility interface.
The accessibility interface
compliments
the visual experience
to make sure that it’s usable
by everyone.
I've asked some VoiceOver
users to help test Wallet Pal
and I've heard that the app
is hard to navigate
and not fully accessible.
If parts are not accessible
to VoiceOver,
then they are also
not accessible
to other assistive technologies.
It's important that anyone
be able to use Wallet Pal,
so let's investigate
to see where we can improve
the experience.
We'll begin with reports
of users
not being able to edit
their budgets,
a critical feature
in Wallet Pal.
This is the Budget Planner view
which allows users to edit
their food, entertainment,
and savings budgets.
To fit the design of Wallet Pal,
I ended up needing
to create custom sliders.
I accomplished this
by creating a budget slider
out of shapes and used
a drag gesture for interaction.
Shapes in SwiftUI make it easy
to create stunning
and unique views,
but they are not accessible
by default,
and so neither
is my budget slider.
This must be why some users are
not able to edit their budgets.
We can confirm
it's not accessible
by running a SwiftUI preview
and selecting the SliderShape.
The Accessibility Preview shows
that there are no elements,
so this control
is not accessible.
Ideally,
we should have a single
labeled accessibility element
with a value
that can be changed.
In contrast, standard controls
are accessible by default,
meaning little to no
extra effort is required
to provide a great experience.
SwiftUI uses the view type and
its initialization parameters
to automatically derive the
accessibility element's label,
value, traits, and actions.
So what's the best way to make
our custom budget slider
accessible?
Since the standard slider
is accessible by default,
my team and I thought
it would be great to have an API
that allows the accessibility
of one view
to be represented by another.
This is what led us
to us to create
accessibilityRepresentation(representation:).
It's an API that allows
the accessibility of one view
to be defined by another.
Since I want this
to be perceived
by assistive technologies
as a slider,
that's what I'll use for the
accessibility representation.
With
accessibilityRepresentation(representation:),
we're now well on the way
to making this
budget slider accessible.
The only change needed
to improve the experience
of the slider is to describe
the value in dollars.
And great, just like that,
now our budget slider
is perfectly accessible.
On macOS,
the type of control will also
be spoken to VoiceOver users.
So by using the slider view
in our budget slider's
representation,
it will be announced
as a slider.
It's recommended to use
accessibilityRepresentation(representation:)
when possible, to make
custom controls accessible.
This is just one way to use
accessibilityRepresentation(representation:).
Its flexibility allows
for many more creative uses.
Let's see if we can use it
to fix other accessibility bugs
in our app.
While we have now fixed
the functional ability
to edit budgets,
some users reported
that they couldn't discover
how to navigate
to the Budget Planner view.
When designing Wallet Pal,
we decided to use SF Symbols
for all of our buttons.
While SF Symbols may have great
default accessibility labels,
they may not always fit
the intended use case.
Let's investigate if the problem
is a poorly labeled button.
The NavigationBarView contains
the Edit Budgets button.
Since we rely on SF Symbols
for so many of our buttons,
I created a custom buttonStyle
called SymbolButtonStyle.
But it appears that despite
initializing the button
with the label "Edit Budgets",
the label for the button
is slider.vertical.3.
So the accessibility label
is being derived
from the SF Symbol.
Let's take a closer look
at the SymbolButtonStyle.
The SymbolButtonStyle's
makeBody(configuration:) method
returns an Image view.
The Edit Budgets string
we initialize the button with
would create a Text view
as the configuration's label.
But this style
completely ignores
the configuration's label.
This is why the button is
not labeled "Edit Budgets".
While we want an SF Symbol
to appear visually,
we want the accessibility
of the button
to be represented
by the configuration's label.
And so this seems
like a great use case
for accessibilityRepresentation(representation:).
Using
accessibilityRepresentation(representation:),
I can substitute the
accessibility of the Image view
with another view, in this case,
the configuration's label.
This way,
we can preserve the label
we used to create the button.
accessibilityRepresentation(representation:)
is not just the ideal
and recommended way to make
custom controls accessible,
it also opens up
new creative possibilities
to make views accessible.
Next, let's discuss
the relationship
between children
and accessibility containers.
As you may recall, accessibility
elements can be wrapped together
in a group as children
of an accessibility container.
This is done with the
accessibilityElement(children:) modifier
and the contain child behavior.
In case you're unfamiliar,
the contain child behavior
can be used to create
an accessibility container,
which wraps existing
accessibility elements
as children.
But what if instead you have
an accessibility element
and you want to set
its children?
I'm running into this case
when trying to make the
Budget History graph accessible.
Users reported the graph
is completely inaccessible.
And so this means
when assistive technologies
are focused on
the Budget History header
and try to navigate
to the next element,
they end up
at the Alerts header.
VoiceOver users would not even
know that this graph exists.
I built the graph
using the new Canvas view.
Canvas makes it easier
to draw a collection of shapes.
For more on Canvas, please
check out Jacob's presentation
on how it can be used to add
rich graphics to your app.
The most important takeaway
for accessibility
is that Canvas draws
a collection of shapes.
And just like we saw
with BudgetSlider,
shapes are not accessible
by default.
All users need to be able
to view their budget history,
so let's make this
accessible for everyone.
Starting with the basics,
let's give our Canvas a label.
This will automatically create
a new accessibility element
for the Canvas
and assign its label.
Now, I'd like each bar
in the graph
to be represented by their own
accessibility element.
This is a use case where we have
an accessibility element
and want to provide
its children.
To do this, I'll use the new
accessibilityChildren(children:) modifier.
This will transform
the accessibility element
into an accessibility container,
preserving other accessibility
properties, such as the label.
The modifier takes
a ViewBuilder,
which allows us
to set new views
as children
of the accessibility container.
Recall that our
Budget History graph
is drawing a horizontal bar
graph, so we'll use an HStack
and return a view
for each budget.
I'll use a Rectangle
for each accessibility element
so that the frame will fill
all available vertical space.
This will make each
accessibility element's frame
bigger than what's displayed
visually, and that's OK.
Having a large but consistent
frame will make it easier
to navigate on iOS
when VoiceOver users drag
their finger across the screen
to scan
for accessibility elements.
If I select the HStack
from within the
accessibilityChildren(children:) modifier,
the Accessibility Preview
confirms
that an element has been created
for each bar in the graph.
These will all be accessible
as children
of the Canvas
accessibility container.
With these changes,
the Budget History graph
is now completely accessible,
and assistive technologies
can navigate
through each bar in the graph.
Notice that the frame
for each element is the same,
which is ideal.
For more complex charts,
we have other ways
of making them accessible.
For that, please check out
Preston's presentation
on bringing accessibility
to charts.
But with accessibility children,
the accessibility elements
of a view can differ
from what's presented visually,
allowing you to tailor
a great experience.
But accessibility children
can also be used to compose
the accessibility with the help
of the combine behavior.
As a quick refresh,
the combine child behavior
will merge properties from
multiple accessibility elements
into a new or existing
accessibility element.
But with the addition of
the accessibility children API,
it can now also be used
to compose accessibility
in a generic way.
With
accessibility representation,
the original accessibility
is completely replaced.
This means no composition
can take place;
whereas accessibility children
is additive.
This means you could later
combine the children
to merge their properties
into the original element.
This is a more advanced use case
of the accessibilityChildren(children:) modifier,
but it's a functionality
I wanted to highlight.
Examples are featured
in this presentation's
Accessibility Catalog
Sample Project.
I hope to see many of you
explore what's possible
with this kind of composition.
accessibilityChildren(children:)
gives you control
over the children
of a container.
And with that, complex graphs
drawn with Canvas
can be made accessible
with modifiers and views
you're already familiar with.
And with the combine
child behavior,
the accessibility of a single
view can be composed of many.
Now that we've learned how to
make individual components
of our app accessible, we can
start putting things together
to refine the navigation
experience.
I've heard that navigating
Wallet Pal with VoiceOver
is confusing and difficult.
So we have some more work to do
if we want to deliver
a great accessible app.
Let's take a closer look at the
Friends carousel at the top.
While I don't have
this feature built yet,
I plan to add some kind
of gamification to Wallet Pal.
So I've added a challenge button
at the top left
of each friend view.
We already fixed
the SymbolButtonStyle,
so the challenge button
will be properly labeled now.
But since users are reporting
that navigation is confusing,
are there other issues?
To answer that,
we must first understand
how assistive technologies
will navigate Wallet Pal.
By default, accessibility
elements are sorted
based off their
geometric position
in relation to other elements,
from top left to bottom right.
This means that without
accessibility containers
to differentiate the content,
VoiceOver would navigate
through each
of the challenge buttons,
then the Image
and Add Friend button,
and finally, the text
with the user's name.
A great feature
of the Accessibility Preview
is that it shows accessibility
elements in their sorted order.
This makes it easy to visualize
how assistive technologies
will navigate right
from within Xcode.
As expected, the sorted order
matches what we previously saw.
And this order would certainly
be confusing to navigate.
Now there are multiple ways
we could fix the sort order
of the accessibility elements.
One thing we could do
is to introduce
accessibility containers.
I'll add the
accessibilityElement(children:) modifier
with the contain behavior.
This will wrap the accessibility
elements of each FriendCellView
in an accessibility container.
This fixes the navigation order,
because children
of an accessibility container
are navigated before moving to
the next accessibility element.
With this change, VoiceOver will
navigate through the children
of the accessibility container
before moving to the next
accessibility element.
And so we achieve a much more
desirable navigation order.
But could we do better
to improve this experience?
One problem is that
the challenge button
is navigated to before
knowing who the user is.
A VoiceOver user would want
to know the name of the user
before sending a challenge,
so this button should
really be sorted last.
We can use the
accessibilitySortPriority(_:) modifier
to fix this.
accessibilitySortPriority(_:)
can be used to change the order
of elements within
an accessibility container.
An element with a higher
priority will be sorted first,
whereas a lower priority
will be sorted last.
Elements with equal priorities
are then sorted
based off
their geometric positioning.
I'll add the
accessibilitySortPriority(_:) modifier
to the challenge button
to improve the navigation order.
I'll use a priority of -1
since the default is 0,
to force the sort order of the
challenge button to be last.
Now the challenge button
will be navigated to last.
This is a good improvement,
since there is less chance
a VoiceOver user
would be confused
as to who they are sending
a challenge to,
but it's still not great.
Rather than wrapping
each FriendCellView
in an accessibility container,
we could combine the children
into a single element.
Recall that combine merges
properties from children
into an existing
or new accessibility element.
The combine behavior
also curates
which properties are merged
for the best default result.
For example, the challenge
button has become an action
named "Send Challenge".
This too fixes the navigation
order and reduces the number
of accessibility elements.
Now there's a single
element for each user,
and each element
has a Send Challenge action.
It is often ideal to combine
the accessibility elements
of views that are represented
in a ForEach.
As you may have
picked up on by now,
combine is a super
useful child behavior.
Instead of children being
individually navigable,
it merges their properties into
a single, navigable element.
For when you need
a single element
but do not want it to inherit
properties from the children,
use the ignore behavior.
And lastly, the contain child
behavior wraps the children
in an accessibility container
and should be used
to express a groups
of views that are related.
This not only improves
the default sort order
but has other advantages
to assistive technologies.
With the new
Accessibility Preview,
discovering these
navigation problems is easy.
And with a few small changes,
you can dramatically
improve the experience.
But to deliver
a truly exceptional
navigation experience
to VoiceOver users,
you'll will want
to consider rotors.
Now if you are new
to accessibility,
you might be thinking,
"What are rotors?"
In short, rotors are
a powerful navigation tool.
They can be thought
of as bookmarks
that allow users to quickly
navigate between them.
System rotors,
such as the headings
and containers rotor,
provide the foundation
for this supercharged
form of navigation.
For example, users can quickly
navigate through sections
using the headings rotor.
This is because the Section view
automatically adds the isHeader
trait to the header view
If you are not using
the Section view,
you can add the isHeader trait
to your view
with accessibilityAddTraits(_:).
Similarly, accessibility
containers are added
to the container's rotor,
which as we saw earlier,
are created with the
accessibilityElement(children:) modifier.
As you can see,
supporting the headings rotor
is incredibly easy,
and the container's rotor
further adds to the benefit
of grouping
your accessibility elements
with the contain
child behavior.
Now that the basic navigation
experience of Wallet Pal
has been refined,
let's take it a step
further with rotors.
In Wallet Pal, alerts help keep
users' spending habits in check
by providing motivation
messages and warnings
when budgets near
or exceed their limit.
We've incorporated SF Symbols
for the different types
of alerts.
These allow visual users
to quickly scan
through the list.
But this iconography will
not help VoiceOver users.
They would instead have
to navigate through every alert
just to know
if they have any warnings.
To replicate
a similar experience
that sighted users have,
VoiceOver users need
to be able to exclusively
navigate warnings,
that way, in an instant,
they can navigate
to the next warning alert.
To do this, we can use rotors.
For more examples
of custom rotors
and why they're so important
to efficiency,
please check out our "VoiceOver
Efficiency for Custom Rotors"
presentation from 2020.
To add a warnings rotor
to my AlertsView,
the first thing I'll do is
to make sure I'm adding my rotor
to an accessibility container.
Some views in SwiftUI
are accessibility containers
by default --
such as List or LazyVStack --
but VStacks
and HStacks are not,
so I'll add the
accessibilityElement(children:) modifier
with the contain
child behavior.
Next, I'll create my rotor with
the accessibilityRotor(_:entries:) modifier,
giving it the name "Warnings".
And lastly, I'll declare
which of my alerts
I want included
in the warnings rotor,
in this case all
of the warning alerts.
And that's it!
It's this easy to supercharge
your app's navigation.
Part of what makes rotors so
easy for these simple use cases
is that SwiftUI can
automatically match
the rotor entry
to the accessibility element
based off the ID.
This is because the ID
of our rotor entry will match
the ID given to the
AlertCellView by a ForEach.
The identity of a view is
important to understand
for accessibility rotors.
So if view identity is unclear
or you'd like a refresher,
I strongly encourage
you to check out
the "Demystifying SwiftUI"
presentation to learn more.
Now you might be thinking,
"Hold on,
my view isn't this simple.
What about views
that are not within a ForEach?"
Don't worry,
the accessibility rotor API
can scale from simple
to complex views.
This simple case works elegantly
because there is a single
accessibility element --
due to the combine --
for the AlertCellView.
And the AlertCellView
is identified by the ID
of the alert.
What if for every alert
there was also an Actions view?
In this case, the VStack is now
the root view of our ForEach,
and it's the VStack
which will be given the identity
of the alert.
So to include the AlertCellView
in our warnings rotor,
we will need to explicitly
mark it as a rotor entry.
We can do that
with the accessibilityRotorEntry
modifier.
This modifier requires
a namespace and an ID,
which could be anything
as long as they match the ID
and namespace used to create
the AccessibilityRotorEntry.
And lastly, we'll need
to include this namespace
for each rotor entry.
The ability to refer
to an explicit namespace
is what enables the
accessibility rotor API
to scale from simple
to complex use cases,
allowing accessibility elements
that span across multiple views
to be included
in the same rotor.
Accessibility rotors can also be
added to enrich text navigation.
To do that,
use a different variant of the
accessibilityRotor modifier,
which allows you provide
an array of text ranges.
This modifier is great
for giving VoiceOver users
quick and easy access
to specific strings
within a TextEditor, such as
emails, links, or phone numbers.
Accessibility rotors makes
complex navigation
easy for VoiceOver users.
And with the new SwiftUI rotors
API, it's never been easier
to deliver this exceptional
navigation experience.
The last topic
for today is focus.
The concept
of element of focus
is something you may
already be familiar with,
but what you may not know
is that many
of our assistive technologies
have their own focus state.
This is what we call
"accessibility focus".
It's the focused view you
have been seeing change
when I refer to assistive
technologies navigating.
The position of an assistive
technology's cursor
is critical
to the user experience.
When focus is changed
in VoiceOver,
the cursor moves to match
the focused element's path
in addition to speaking
a description of the element.
So when does focus change?
Focus can but may not
always change
when one of three events occur.
The first and most
common use case
is when a user drives
a focus change
when navigating to a different
accessibility element.
The second case is
when the UI changes,
and the previously focused view
is no longer on screen
or is covered by a modal view.
When this happens,
focus is often reset
to the first sorted
accessibility element.
This covers many use cases
automatically,
such as moving to the first
accessibility element
of a newly presented view.
But that may not be
the best behavior in your app,
which is why focus
can also be changed
upon programmatic request.
However, this should be
handled with caution,
because moving
a VoiceOver user's focus
can be very disruptive.
On that note, let's focus --
no pun intended --
on the last case.
This year we have a new API
that will allow you
to both request an assistive
technology to move its focus,
in addition to reading
where an assistive technology
is currently focused.
Here we have a simple view
which tracks a notification,
and if it exists, overlays
a custom NotificationBanner.
We want to use
this view in Wallet Pal
to show alerts
for push notifications
received while the app
is in the foreground.
When the NotificationBanner
is added,
assistive technologies will
not automatically focus on it.
But we can request they do so
with the new
AccessibilityFocusState.
AccessibilityFocusState is a
property wrapper that provides
both a way of reading where an
assistive technology is focused
and requesting
a programmatic focus change.
I'll add one to my view and bind
it to the NotificationBanner
with the accessibilityFocused(_:)
modifier.
Next, I'll use
the onChange(of:perform:) modifier
to track when a new notification
is received.
Only when a high-priority
notification is received
do we request accessibility
focus to change.
It's especially
important to note
that moving focus
programmatically
can be very disruptive
if no user interaction occurred.
It takes the user out
of whatever context
they are currently focused on,
so it must be handled with care.
So for lower priority
notifications,
I'll post an accessibility
notification
for VoiceOver to announce.
This way,
VoiceOver users still know
a new notification has appeared
and can navigate
to it if desired.
Now let's step inside
the NotificationBanner view.
When the notification appears,
a timer is started.
Upon it completing,
the notification is set to nil.
Recall from before that
when the notification is nil,
the NotificationBanner
will be hidden.
This means if a VoiceOver user
was focused
on the notification banner
and the timer expired,
their focus would be reset,
since the view is removed;
and this isn't
a great user experience.
To fix this, let's read
if our NotificationBanner
is focused by
an assistive technology,
and if it is, delay
the notification dismissal.
This is the ideal solution.
A VoiceOver user's focus
will no longer be reset,
since the view is no longer
removed while focused.
Additionally, we have given
assistive technology users
an unlimited number of time
to digest the content
and interact if desired;
two things that may take
assistive technology users
much longer to do so.
AccessibilityFocusState
is the last piece you need
to deliver exceptional
and accessible SwiftUI apps
this year and beyond.
With it, you can read
and direct the focus
of assistive technologies
to create smooth transitions
between views.
Wow, we've covered a lot today
for SwiftUI accessibility.
We were introduced to the new
Accessibility Preview,
which enhances the way
you can develop
and debug SwiftUI accessibility;
we covered how to make
custom controls
and complex graphs accessible;
and we took the time to learn
how the navigation experience
can be improved with grouping,
rotors, and focus.
Put everything together,
and it truly has been
a huge leap for accessibility
this year.
For some great simple
and complex examples
of our Accessibility APIs,
please checkout
the Accessibility Catalog
Sample Project.
It features more examples
that we couldn't cover today
and some of our recommended
best practices.
Thank you so much
for joining me.
We look forward to seeing
how you make your app accessible
to everyone.
♪