[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[David]
Hi.
I’m David Duncan,
and with my colleague,
Eric Dudiak,
we’re going to be discussing
all the ways that UIKit
makes buttons better in iOS 15.
The humble button,
a staple of apps
large and small.
Buttons are perhaps
the most common way
to solicit user input.
Buttons come in many forms:
large and small;
with images, text, or both;
with and without backgrounds;
and every color of the rainbow.
Let’s start by focusing
on a few specific styles.
In iOS 15, UIKit now provides
these four basic styles.
Adding to the plain style
you already know and love
are the new gray,
tinted, and filled styles.
But UIKit doesn’t just
make buttons more stylish
in iOS 15.
It also makes them
more powerful.
Dynamic type
is now supported by default,
and multiline text support
is built into button system.
Accessibility has been enhanced
with better support
for all accessibility features
as well as generating buttons
that are more accessible
by default.
And with all these new features,
buttons are more customizable
than ever, so you can get
exactly the style you want.
So with that primer,
let’s meet
UIButtonConfiguration,
the entry point
to the new button system.
Welcome to Button Emporium,
the premier supplier
of buttons
of all shapes and sizes.
Button Emporium always wants
to have the best buttons,
so let’s update the app to adopt
UIButtonConfiguration...
starting with the all-important
Sign In button.
Currently the app generates
a Sign In button with this code,
generating a plain system button
with the title “Sign In”.
But this is
a super important button,
so let’s make it stand out more
using the new filled style.
And we’re done!
It’s easy to get started
with UIButtonConfiguration,
as UIButton automatically
integrates titles and images
set with the existing API
on configurations you provide,
making it easy
to update your button’s style
without updating
all your code at once.
But when you’re ready to update
your code, there is plenty more
to UIButtonConfiguration
than just styles.
Let’s take a look at that next.
This is our current
“Add to Cart” button.
It’s a pretty basic button
right now,
but we’re going
to take advantage
of new features
offered by UIButtonConfiguration
to turbo charge
the button-buying experience.
To start,
we’ll use the tinted style
as it complements
our other buttons.
We start by creating
a tinted button configuration,
set its title,
matching how we previously
configured our button.
Next we create the button
with our filled out
configuration.
This is already
quite an improvement,
but let’s take it over the top.
The next improvement we’ll make
is to add an image
to the button,
making it simple to determine
what it does at a glance.
Our designer
really wants the image
in the trailing position,
so alongside setting
the image property,
we also set
the imagePlacement property,
putting the image
exactly where we want it.
But there are two more features
we want to add
to our new “Add to Cart” button.
The first
is to preview what happens
when you order multiple items,
which will use
the subtitle feature
of UIButtonConfiguration.
The second is to switch
from the outlined image
to its filled version
when the button is pressed.
For that, we need to update
the image property
at the appropriate time.
In order to update
the button correctly
when either
of these changes occur,
we’ll add
a configurationUpdateHandler.
The configurationUpdateHandler
is called when the button
needs an update, allowing you
to make centralized changes.
Usually you’ll change
the button’s configuration,
so it typically begins
by obtaining
a starting configuration
and ends with setting
the changed configuration.
Here we start with the button’s
existing configuration,
but you can just as easily
create a new one and fill out
all of its parameters instead.
First let’s set
the correct image
for the button.
When the button is pressed,
isHighlighted returns true,
and we set the filled version
of our cart symbol.
Otherwise,
we use the outlined version.
Since isHighlighted is a state
of UIButton,
it automatically arranges
for the
configurationUpdateHandler
to be called
when that value changes.
Next, we update the subtitle
when itemQuantityDescription
changes.
But itemQuantityDescription
isn’t a property of UIButton.
How do we arrange for
the configurationUpdateHandler
to be called
when the value changes?
When the customer
changes the number of buttons
to be purchased, the app
updates itemQuantityDescription.
To ensure
that the Add to Cart button
also updates,
our didSet handler calls
setNeedsUpdateConfiguration,
which in turn
arranges for
the configurationUpdateHandler
to be called and triggers
an update of the button.
At Button Emporium,
we’ve never met
a button we didn’t like,
and with UIButtonConfiguration,
there is plenty to like.
Before we update
our next button,
let’s quickly cover
some other features.
Buttons can now show
an activity indicator,
making it easy to provide
feedback that your app is busy.
Just set
showsActivityIndicator to true
in your button configuration,
and we’ll show the indicator,
replacing the image
if necessary.
Adjusting aspects
of the button’s layout
is straightforward,
giving you more control
over how content
is positioned in the button.
Here you can see
how contentInsets
reserve space
on the edges of the button,
and imagePadding
and titlePadding allow us
to increase the space
between those elements.
And while UIKit will layout
these components automatically,
you have control over
how titles align
with each other as well
as how the button’s content
aligns
inside the content region.
Semantic stylings make it simple
to create buttons
with cohesive styles
without having to dig
into details.
Starting with
a simple filled button,
we configure
the baseBackgroundColor,
baseForegroundColor,
cornerStyle, and buttonSize
to generate a customized button,
and you automatically get
thematic states,
such as pressed and disabled
without any extra effort.
But even
with lots of automation,
it’s still easy to make
detailed customizations
for those times when you simply
must have exactly what you need,
like with our
all-important “Check Out” button.
To ensure
that Button Emporium customers
can get their buttons
with a minimum of fuss,
the check out button
is big and easy to find.
To build it, we’ll start
with the filled style,
set its size to large,
and fill out
its image and title.
When the button is tapped,
we start processing
the cart and want to show
an activity indicator.
To enable this, we add
a configurationUpdateHandler
to manage the
showsActivityIndicator property
of the configuration.
Just as before, changes
to the isCartBusy property
will call
setNeedsUpdateConfiguration
on the check out button
to ensure the activity indicator
is turned on and off
as necessary.
And while blue is nice,
we want to make sure
to leave an impression.
So to ensure
our precise color
is used for the background,
let’s set the backgroundColor
of UIButtonConfiguration’s
UIBackgroundConfiguration.
That’s way better.
Now that we’ve discussed
how UIButtonConfiguration
can make your buttons
look better than ever,
I’ll hand it over
to Eric to talk
about other new things
that buttons can do.
[Eric]
Thanks, David.
Now that we’ve checked out
how buttons can have
their appearance customized,
let’s inspect how buttons
can have
their functionality customized.
Most buttons are just
simple push buttons,
but sometimes a button
needs a bit of extra behavior.
The first ones we’re going
to examine is the toggle button.
These buttons
preserve the selected state
from UIControl.
They automatically
toggle it on and off
each time the button is pressed.
It also can be
programmatically changed
as necessary.
In addition to built-in styles
for the on and off states,
we can take advantage
of the UIButtonConfiguration
to customize the presentation
of these on and off states.
The concept of toggle buttons
on iOS is not new.
You may have noticed
some buttons
like the lyrics button
in the Music app.
It toggles the lyrics on and off
in the player like this.
Functionally,
this works just like UISwitch,
but it saves some space
in the UI
and it fits the design
of the app much better.
Toggle buttons
also work off UIBarButtonItems
like this one in Calendar.
In the top bar, the day details
can be enabled and disabled.
Pushing it toggles the display
of the details.
In this case,
there is a new selected property
on UIBarButtonItem
that can be read or set
for the selected state.
Now let’s update Button Emporium
to adopt toggle buttons.
Our app lets us browse
for the kinds of buttons
we want to buy.
But while browsing,
I only want to peruse
what’s currently in stock.
Here, we’ve added
a toggle button
to toggle between showing
absolutely everything
and just what’s in stock
and ready to ship.
This is a great use
of the toggle button.
One advantage
is that, since it’s a button,
the label is part of it,
making it very clear
what is being toggled here.
So let’s check out
how we made that.
Here, we have the basics
of setting up a button.
To make it a toggle button,
we just set
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
to true.
Now it’s a toggle button.
That’s it.
We can also
set the selected state
to match our internal model.
Now, we might want something
a little more complicated
that just two states
of on and off.
For buttons that can have
more options to switch between,
we can use pop-up buttons.
Pop-up buttons
are a close relative
to pull-down buttons,
which already exist in iOS.
These present
a menu when pressed.
Pop-up buttons
take that a step further
and ensure that one and only one
of the menu elements
is ever selected.
They also show
that current selection
as their title and image.
Building a pop-up button
is actually an extension
of building
a pull-down button.
For those, a menu
is assigned to the button.
To make the menu
the default action,
the showsMenuAsPrimaryAction
property is set to true.
Pop-up buttons
take that one step further
by just turning on the
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
property.
That’s all it takes.
They work
like UISegmentedControl
but can be useful
when there are more choices
than might fit
on the segmented control.
They can also be useful
for cases where the choices
have an inherent hierarchy.
Some examples of this style
of button exist today.
For example, the Phone app
uses a pop-up button
to switch between
SIMs for outgoing calls.
And here
the button presents a menu.
Selecting secondary
switches the line.
As a result,
the button is updated
to the new outgoing line.
The label
and image have been updated
to display the new selection.
Similarly, we have some use
for this in Button Emporium.
When we’re browsing buttons,
we have some that come
in a variety of colors.
The number of colors
is a fixed set
to choose from,
but probably too big
for a segmented control,
but it’s also small enough
that we really want
to change it in-line.
This is a great use
of a pop-up button
because we want the selection
to be the title of the button.
We can then present
all the color choices.
And on a new selection,
our app
can just update
for the color choice.
Let’s investigate
the code for that.
Here we actually have
the code to make
a simple pull-down menu
that we can just update.
Just like the toggle button,
we switch
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
to true.
And now it’s a pop-up button.
If we want to have
a particular color
be the default selection
instead of just the first color
in the list,
we can preassign that one
to “on” when we set the menu.
That will make it
the default selection.
We can check the selection
by asking the button’s menu
for the current selectedElements,
which will always have
exactly a single element.
And if we need to set a new one
in code, we can just change
the state on the element
from the button’s menu property.
Pop-up buttons can also
be created in Interface Builder,
but in this case we’re going
to want to retrieve
the colors dynamically
from the server
instead of using a fixed list,
so we’re gonna do it in code.
To learn more about
using the new button system
and button types
with Interface Builder,
check out the “Build
interfaces with style” video.
One of the best parts
of these new button types
is that they automatically
work on Mac Catalyst.
Mac users expect buttons to look
and behave a certain way,
including pull-downs,
pop-ups, and toggle buttons.
With these iOS buttons,
they automatically
get updated
to their Mac versions.
So here we have a selection
of buttons from an iPad app,
like we’ve been using
throughout the presentation,
which include
the default borderless buttons
and some
using the new configurations
as well as pop-up
and pull-down buttons.
And here they are
with no manual changes
on Mac Catalyst.
Just the way a seasoned Mac user
would expect.
We get the standard
bezeled buttons,
including the Mac indicators for
pull-down and pop-up buttons.
In some cases, however,
the extra customization
of the iPad buttons
may be more appropriate
even for a Mac app.
For that, button support
changing the behavior style
from the default
of automatic to iPad.
This is useful
for very prominent,
custom buttons in an app,
like the check out button
we made earlier.
For more information
about building
and customizing
Mac Catalyst apps,
check out the “What’s
new in Mac Catalyst” video.
As you may have noticed
in the pop-up button examples,
much of the functionality
is built on top
of new
and existing features of UIMenu.
UIMenu pairs
really well with UIButton
and UIBarButtonItem
for lots of great interactions.
We’ve explored how you can
adjust the behavior of buttons
to create both pop-up buttons
and pull-down buttons.
On iOS and iPadOS,
these behaviors are independent
of the visual customizations,
so you can
easily combine them
with UIButtonConfiguration
to create
lots of different button styles.
These buttons also benefit
from improvements
in menus like the ability
for menu items
to have subtitles
for greater clarity.
On top of that,
submenu navigation
on iOS and iPadOS
has also been improved,
allowing the creation
of hierarchies within a menu.
And in some cases,
you might want the submenu
of a pull-down button to behave
as a single-selection
menu itself.
This can be useful
if you have a “sort-by” menu
within an action menu,
for example.
Some of
the new menu improvements
make this much easier to create.
Here’s a custom
pull-down bar button item
using a submenu in our code.
It has a couple of actions
and then a submenu
for sorting results.
Instead of manually turning
on and off the menu items
within that submenu,
we’re just gonna indicate
that this submenu
is for single selection
when we create it.
Now it gets the same
automatic selection behavior
that pop-up buttons get
but just within the submenu.
Only one selected element
will be allowed,
and the element selected will be
updated when the user taps it.
It can be updated or accessed
in code in the exact same way
as we did earlier
with the pop-up menu.
And single-selection behavior
works if the menu
has its own submenu.
Only one element
in the entire subtree
then can be selected at a time.
And the selectedElements
property
includes selection in submenus,
making the access
just as easy
as if we didn’t have a submenu.
So that’s how to make
better buttons in your app.
Add configurations to buttons
to get more control
over the styling
to unlock much richer styling
while still staying consistent
with the platform.
Also explore ways to replace
existing picker interfaces
or controls
with pop-up or toggle buttons
to get more
streamlined interactions.
With these changes,
you will likely find
UIButton subclasses that can
be removed or simplified.
And because the system
can better understand
your buttons,
you’ll get much better
Mac Catalyst
conversion automatically.
Thank you
for joining us,
and I hope you’ve enjoyed
this deep dive
into the world of buttons.
[upbeat music]