Buckle up!
Your day two recap starts now.
♪ "Better Days (Instrumental)"
by DARKMINDS ♪
We learned how to analyze
and classify sounds
while sharing a cup of tea
with Jon.
- The demo app is using
my Mac's built-in microphone
to listen to sounds
in the environment.
- And discovered
how to recognize custom audio
with ShazamKit.
- What if you could play a video
on your Apple TV
and have a companion app
that displays questions
at exactly the right time?
- At lunchtime, aerospace
engineer Tiera Fletcher
took us to space.
- We are voyagers collecting
data beyond our solar system.
- Then we explored
Screen Time API with Nolan...
- Homework encourages
good habits
by restricting a child's access
to certain apps.
- ...designed inclusive apps
with Cynthia,
and learned how to quickly
implement in-app subscriptions
with StoreKit 2.
We found out how you can use
Nearby Interaction
with third-party accessories...
- For example, you can create
a nearby peer configuration
when you want to start
a session between two iPhones
that are running your app.
- ...and discovered how to build
a simplified sign-on process
for tvOS.
No. Password. Needed.
What a packed day!
I think I need to go visit
the Health & Fitness pavilion
and check out
today's Mindful Cooldown.
[INHALING DEEPLY]
And here's a quick preview
of what's coming tomorrow.
♪
Pretty cool stuff, eh?
See you along the way.
♪