[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Max Stepanov: Hello!
My name is Max,
and I'm a software engineer
on the tvOS team.
Today, I'm excited
to share with you
a great all-new look
of the media playback UI
on Apple TV
and what you can do
to get the most
out of this new functionality
available to you as a developer.
In this session, we will
overview the enhancements
to the standard playback UI
in tvOS 15;
we will introduce new APIs;
and finally,
we'll discuss best practices
that will help you create
a great playback experience
in your application.
Let's get started.
AVPlayerViewController provides
the standard media playback
for users on Apple TV.
It supports a wide variety
of remotes,
including the new
Click Wheel remote,
as well as skipping, scanning,
scrubbing functionality,
Siri command,
interstitial support, and more.
We encourage you to start
using AVPlayerViewController
in your application
to allow users
to have a similar experience
as with first-party applications
on Apple TV.
If you haven't yet used
AVPlayerViewController --
or would benefit
from a refresher --
I recommend you to watch
"Delivering intuitive media
playback with AVKit"
from WWDC 2019,
which goes into greater detail
on how to incorporate
AVPlayerViewController
into your application.
Now, let's overview
the enhancements
we are bringing this year.
In tvOS 15,
we entirely redesigned
the standard playback UI
to help viewers
stay in the moment
through a more consistent,
interactive experience.
By adding relevant controls and
options to the transport bar,
we improved the discoverability
of common playback tasks,
such as turning on subtitles
or changing audio language.
The transport bar controls
are both universal in nature
as well as can be
application-specific.
And with new content tabs,
users can now easily access
supporting information --
like Info or Chapters --
making inline navigation
accessible and discoverable.
Content tabs can also be used
to show related content.
Here in this example,
I'm viewing a session
from last year's WWDC
and can browse content
recommendations for the session
without leaving the player.
Lastly, we added contextual
actions available to users
during playback.
Those actions have
perfect functionality,
like Skip Intro or Recap.
To take advantage
of the new playback UI
on Apple TV,
your application must be linked
with tvOS 15 SDK.
We took this approach
to maintain compatibility
with any existing applications
available to users
in the App Store.
Those applications will get
default tvOS 14 playback UI
and functionality.
By now, you're probably
excited to learn
how to adopt some
of this new functionality
in your media application.
So let's dive into the new APIs
in tvOS 15...
...starting with Title View.
The new Title View displayed
just above the transport bar
will help users to instantly
know what they're watching.
To present the Title View,
we'll use values
for commonIdentifierTitle
and iTunesMetadataTrackSubtitle
from the metadata
of the current AVPlayerItem.
If a media asset does not
contain embedded metadata,
or you need to augment it,
use the externalMetadata
property of AVPlayerItem.
When playing
live streaming content,
the Title View will
also display a badge
to indicate the content state
to the viewer.
Lastly,
if your application would prefer
not to display Title View,
suppress it by setting
the value of new property
transportBarIncludesTitleView
to false.
Next, let's take a look
at the transport bar controls.
Transport bar controls
is a collection of UI elements
sitting right on top
of the transport bar scrubber.
Those controls will help users
quickly and intuitively
find all the playback options
your application
may provide.
Some standard controls --
such as subtitles,
audio languages,
and Picture in Picture --
are provided by the system.
As a developer,
you can extend the list
of transport bar controls,
using the new property
of AVPlayerViewController,
transportBarCustomMenuItems.
It supports instances
of UIAction and UIMenu classes.
Let's take a look at an example
of using transport bar controls.
Here, I'm using UIAction
to let users add the current
media item to their Favorites.
You could also create more
advanced arrangements of actions
and present them in a menu,
using UIMenu class.
UIMenus presented
by AVPlayerViewController
support up to one level
of nesting,
using the displayInline option.
For greater detail on using
UIMenu and UIAction classes,
I recommend you to watch
"Modernizing your UI for iOS 13"
from WWDC 2019.
Now, let's talk
about content tabs.
Content tabs will allow
your application
to display
complementary information
or recommendations
for more content.
AVPlayerViewController
will display the Info tab
when a media asset
contains embedded metadata
or when you supplement external
metadata with AVPlayerItem.
Also, when you supply
navigationMarkerGroups
with AVPlayerItem,
AVPlayerViewController
will show the Chapters tab.
Your application can present
additional content tabs
using the new property
of AVPlayerViewController,
customInfoViewControllers.
And in tvOS 15,
we are deprecating
the customInfoViewController
property
in favor of the new property
that allows
for multiple view controllers.
To size your content tabs
appropriately,
please specify the height
using
preferredContentSize property
or define appropriate
autolayout constraints.
When calculating the required
height to display content tabs,
the system will size
all view controllers
to the height
of the tallest content tab.
When working with
multiple content tabs,
size your custom view
controllers consistently
or verify that the layout
is expected at runtime.
And don't forget
to set title property
on your custom view controller.
We will use it for the title
of the content tab.
To help you create
great-looking content tabs,
this year, we are introducing
new content configurations
in TVUIKit framework:
TVMediaItemContent
Configuration
and TVMonogramContent
Configuration.
Let's take a look
at a couple examples
of how these configurations
can be used in your code.
For instance,
to present a list of media items
at 16:9 aspect ratio,
you can use the wide cell
from TVMediaItem
ContentConfiguration.
Set its properties, like image,
title, or secondary text.
You could also configure it
to show a badge
and playback progress.
When you're done,
assign the contentConfiguration
to your collection view cell.
It's that easy.
If you would like to display
people or characters
associated with the current
media content,
use
TVMonogramContentConfiguration.
For more information
on using content configurations,
I recommend you to watch
"Modern cell configuration"
from WWDC 2020.
Finally, contextual actions.
Contextual actions
allow your application
to display relevant controls
during the playback.
To display contextual actions,
use new contextualActions
property
of AVPlayerViewController
and provide one
or more UIActions.
Typically,
your application would want
to present contextual actions
during a relevant section
of the content.
To achieve this,
observe the AVPlayer timing
by adding periodic
or boundary time observers.
To hide contextual actions,
reset the property
to an empty array.
Some of you may have already
implemented solutions
for the skip functionality
within your applications.
With this new API,
the user interaction
with contextual controls is
consistent with focus behavior,
and when used,
it will also maintain
the Now Playing status
for your application.
Now, let's talk about
some best practices
with AVPlayerViewController
on tvOS.
First --
and most important --
avoid adding extra gestures
to the player.
This will interfere
with standard playback UI
and most certainly
might not work in the future.
Second, supplement
missing metadata.
Sometimes we have media that
doesn't have all the metadata
baked in with the asset.
In those cases, provide
all essential metadata --
like title, artwork,
or description --
using the externalMetadata
property of AVPlayerItem.
And when you do so,
we will do the rest to populate
Title View and Info tab
with all relevant information.
Lastly, consider enabling
Picture in Picture
in your tvOS application.
It will give your users
multitasking flexibility,
allowing for simultaneous
video playback
and the ability to swap
between full-screen content
and Picture in Picture.
To get started
with Picture in Picture,
I recommend you to watch
"Master Picture in Picture
on tvOS" from WWDC 2020.
So to recap.
tvOS 15 makes it
easier than ever
to build great media experiences
using standard playback UI.
The powerful new APIs make
AVPlayerViewController
more configurable
and customizable than ever.
There's never been a better time
to adopt it
into your applications.
And it's easy to get started.
For more information,
see additional resources
for this session
in the Developer app.
Thanks for watching
and enjoy the conference.
♪