[Susan] Welcome to the WWDC2021
platform state of the union.
WWDC is a time
when we come together
as a developer community to look
at what the near future holds
for our platforms.
I also want to reflect a bit
on how the work you did
helped all of us to get
through this past year.
Your apps and your creativity
have enabled people
to find new ways
to keep things moving
under extraordinary
circumstances.
There are so many great examples
of developers making
a difference,
and we know there's much more
we can do
to help you make the world
better faster.
So this year we're delivering
tools, technologies, and APIs
designed to help you
accomplish more.
And we'll be talking today
about three big areas
where we're making that happen.
First, we'll talk
about the things
that help you build great apps:
Xcode and Xcode Cloud, Swift,
and our UI frameworks.
Then we'll look at how Apple
technologies can help you
build apps that make it possible
with augmented reality
and our graphics technologies
for users to see the world
in new ways.
Finally, with new features like
Focus, the Screen Time API,
Widgets, and Share Play,
we'll see ways in which the apps
you build can help users
better connect with each other
and prioritize what's most
important to them.
Let's start
with developing apps.
To tell you more, here are
Alison, Rhonda, and Andrew.
[Alison] Developing an app today
is a pretty
sophisticated process
and you rely on your tools
to keep you focused
and effective.
The most essential part
of the process is coding,
but building a quality app today
involves a number
of specialized steps and tools.
You need to test your code
across various configurations.
Your team reviews your code,
and you integrate changes
into a shared repository.
You deliver to beta testers.
And based on their feedback,
you constantly refine your app.
All of these steps are important
and it’s important to get
all of them right.
You often have to jump
between different apps,
websites, and services
to get everything done.
All of this context switching
disrupts your focus
and pulls you
away from your code.
It’s time to do something
about that,
to remove the friction
and bring everything together,
so you and your team can focus
on creating great experiences.
That’s why we created
Xcode Cloud:
a new continuous integration
and delivery service
built right into Xcode
and hosted in the cloud.
It helps you manage every stage
of your development process,
and makes it easy to get
the important things right.
Xcode Cloud was designed
and built from the ground up
to support development
for all Apple platforms.
It’s deeply integrated
into Xcode,
saving you time by keeping you
focused in one place.
It leverages Apple’s
cloud infrastructure to offload
your builds, tests, and even
code signing for distribution.
It integrates with Apple
services like Test Flight
and App Store Connect,
as well as every major
git-based
source control provider.
It even has
REST APIs to help connect
to other aspects
of your development process.
And it’s built
with advanced security
to protect you
and your projects.
This is the biggest
investment we’ve made
in our developer tools since
the original release of Xcode,
and all of it is inside
the experience you already know.
You create and manage
Xcode Cloud workflows
in Xcode 13,
letting you stay in your code
while test suites, code signing,
and TestFlight distribution
are handled for you.
And when
Xcode Cloud finishes a build,
your results
are right inside Xcode.
This is going to change
the way you work.
It’s already changing
the way we work.
Many teams at Apple
have incorporated Xcode Cloud
into their development process,
including the team
behind Xcode itself.
[Rhonda] It's incredibly easy
to get started with Xcode Cloud.
It only takes four steps:
selecting the product,
confirming your workflow,
granting access
to your source code,
and linking
with App Store Connect.
Let's walk through the process
with Fruta,
a SwiftUI sample app.
Xcode Cloud
automatically detects
the products and platform
for my project,
so I'll click next.
Then I'll review
the suggested workflow,
which tells Xcode Cloud
what to do and when to do it.
The default actions build
every change I make,
which is exactly what I want.
Now, Xcode Cloud will
securely connect
to the hosted account
for my source code.
I've already granted access
using my credentials,
so I can just move on.
Finally, Xcode Cloud recognizes
that Fruta already exists
on the App Store
and asks me to confirm
the information.
If your app isn't
registered yet,
Xcode Cloud will do it for you.
I'll click Complete and start
my first build in the Cloud.
When the build is finished,
I'll be able to view the results
in the report navigator.
And just like that, I set up
continuous integration
and delivery for my app
in one minute
all from within Xcode.
Let's take a closer look
at how results are presented.
Under the Cloud tab
in the report navigator,
builds that have been run
for each workflow
will be grouped by branch
or Pull Request.
Selecting an individual build
brings up its overview
with information like how
and when it was started,
which Xcode and macOS versions
were used,
and the status
of all the actions.
You can even check out
the source
or initiate a rebuild.
While the default workflow is
great for getting started,
Xcode Cloud gives you
even more power
to accomplish goals
like analyzing an app
or deploying new releases
to Test Flight or the App Store.
My team wants to run our iOS
tests on every new Pull Request,
so let's set
that workflow up now.
I'll go back to the Xcode Cloud
product menu,
selecting Manage Workflows
this time,
and I'll click Plus
to add a new one.
I'll name the workflow
Pull Requests,
then edit its start conditions
to run on every Pull Request
that targets the main branch.
I want our tests to run
on the public beta versions
of Xcode and macOS,
so I'll set that here.
Next, I'll look
at the workflow's actions,
where I'll add a test action,
then select
an existing iOS test plan
from the project.
To get broad testing coverage
for my app,
Xcode Cloud recommends
simulators for me to use.
With just two clicks, I get
a curated set of iPhones
and iPads for my workflow.
Now that's pretty neat.
Our team also needs
to be notified
when a build succeeds or fails.
So I'll add a Notify post action
and add our team's
Slack channel.
By clicking Save, our workflow
has been added to our product
on Xcode Cloud.
Now, my team will have
added confidence
in the changes we're making.
[Alison] There's so much more
you can do with workflows,
including running
custom build scripts,
and using Xcode Cloud’s web
hooks and APIs to integrate
with other systems you
and your team depend on.
And the workflow management
and build reports you just saw
in Xcode are also available
in App Store Connect on the web.
This makes it easy
for you or other members
of your team to use
Xcode Cloud from anywhere.
Now that you’ve seen
the basics of working
with Xcode Cloud,
let’s see how it helps you
in each specific area
of your development cycle.
Writing good tests
and running them repeatedly
is critical to creating
a quality application.
With Xcode Cloud,
you’ll be testing your code
more thoroughly,
more consistently,
and more efficiently.
You can configure
your Xcode Cloud workflows
to run multiple test plans
across multiple platforms,
device simulators,
and OS versions all in parallel.
You can also run
your tests in Xcode Cloud
on beta OS releases
before you even download
the betas to your own machine.
So Xcode Cloud will help you
test more
and Xcode 13 will help you
test better.
[Andrew] Our app Fruta supports
the Light and Dark appearance,
portrait and landscape
orientations,
and localizes to two languages.
I've been working on a suite
of user experience tests
that exercise Fruta's
most popular features.
Here in my test code, I'll adopt
this simple XC test API
to make these tests go
even further
by automatically running
each test in each variation.
Let's look at that test coverage
in Xcode Cloud
by selecting
the most recent build
and the workflow test action
I have configured.
Results are displayed
in the familiar Xcode
test report.
These tests ran across a set
of recommended iPad simulators
running iOS 15,
once per configuration,
capturing screenshots
all along the way.
Xcode 13 has a brilliant new way
to review those results.
From the editor options menu,
I'll enable
the new gallery view.
The screenshots from my tests
are displayed
in every variation
and images from each test
presented together.
I can zoom out even further
to see all images,
and when I find one
I'm really interested in,
I can see it at full resolution
using quick look.
The gallery view
makes it effortless
to confirm our app is
looking fantastic
across all conditions,
languages, and layouts.
Over in my unit tests,
I have a test failure
that I'm sure
you will relate to.
Sometimes the test passes
and sometimes it fails.
We've all been here before.
And Xcode 13 is here to help.
I navigate to the test source,
click on the test gem,
and choose Run Test Repeatedly.
Let's get a better sense
of reliability
by running it 100 times.
If I wanted to do this before,
I'd have to run the test
many, many times myself.
Now, I can sit back as the tools
do all of the work.
As I suspected, Xcode is showing
this test is very unreliable.
There must be a problem
in my code.
But until I can fix it, I'll
adopt the new Expected Fail API
and include a message
about reliability
for the rest of my team to see.
To make sure things are
just as I expect,
I'll make use
of the Test Again feature,
available from the product menu.
Xcode remembers what it did
last time
so it's really easy.
My test is still
raising assertions,
but it's not failing anymore.
And I have a gentle reminder
to fix it down the road.
That is exactly what I need.
[Alison] As you can see,
Xcode 13 and Xcode Cloud
help you find and address
issues in your app,
or your tests, faster than ever.
Tests are one form
of insight on your code.
Another is input from your peers
through code reviews
and Pull Requests.
To keep you focused
on your code,
Xcode 13 brings
these discussions
with your team
directly into the editor.
[Andrew]
I've created a Pull Request
from the feature branch
I've been working on.
My feature allows users
to favorite
the most delicious smoothies.
In the navigator on the left,
you can see the new
source control changes tab.
It shows all the files
I've modified locally,
my Pull Request,
and the changes
that are included.
When I select the Pull Request,
I get a full overview
of all the activity
and the conversation going on.
And as I scroll,
I see my description
and the interesting events
and time,
as well as any code feedback
from my team
and new commits that I make.
But we're using Xcode Cloud,
and our Pull Request workflow
is building and testing
every commit that I make.
At the top, I get a live status
from all of my workflows.
Rhonda has a few suggestions
to make my code even better.
When I navigate
to the source code,
I see comments from Rhonda
in my editor.
This code requires
the user to be logged in.
So it needs to be reworked
to allow signing in
before favoriting a recipe.
I'll reply to let Rhonda know
that I'm working on a change
and also give her a heads-up:
This might crash in the build
if she doesn't sign in first.
Beyond Pull Requests,
Xcode 13 makes reviewing
local changes really easy too.
As I navigate
to a file that I'm working on,
Xcode automatically displays the
diff of my changes
against the latest revision
in this beautiful new
in-line presentation.
I can use
the updated revision selectors
to compare my local changes
against any branch or tag
in history.
Best of all, I can use
code review in any editor,
even when I'm using
multiple editor splits
across different files
in my window.
And now with two options--
in-line comparison
and side by side--
I get to pick
the perfect presentation
for what I'm working on.
With one last code change
and comment,
it could not be easier
to review and respond
to insight from my team.
[Alison] Part of delivering
a great experience
is getting your app
into the hands
of your team and beta testers.
Xcode Cloud
makes that process effortless.
Xcode 13 now uses the cloud
to securely obtain and manage
everything you need
to code sign your apps.
This means you no longer
need to worry
about keeping your certificates
and profiles up to date
on your Mac.
The archive action
in your Xcode Cloud workflow
uses the same system to sign
your app for distribution.
And by adding a postaction
to your Xcode Cloud workflow,
you get automatic delivery
of betas
through Test Flight
to all Apple platforms,
including macOS
with the new Test Flight
for Mac.
Once you've delivered
your latest build,
you'll get even more insight
from your beta testers.
Xcode 13 includes
major improvements
to better connect you
with the same diagnostics
and feedback
found in App Store Connect.
Crash logs from Test Flight apps
are now delivered directly
to the Organizer
within minutes.
And the Organizer now shows
the written feedback
a user attaches
to a crash report.
This gives you valuable context
when analyzing the crash
and a broader view
into your app's usage.
[Rhonda]
After Andrew's test passed,
Xcode Cloud submitted the build
directly to Test Flight.
I just received
a notification on my phone
for a new iOS build of Fruta,
and there's the Mac version
from Test Flight for Mac.
Since Fruta
is a multiplatform project,
I'm getting this new build
in both places at the same time.
I'm really excited
to install this build
and see
how the new feature feels.
So I'll do that now.
I suspect
there are still
a few rough edges.
Maybe the app will crash if
I try to favorite this smoothie.
And sure enough, it does.
I can use Test Flight's
crash feedback UI
to let Andrew know.
I'll explain what I was doing
when the app crashed,
and he'll be able
to fix the issue
and add a test to ensure this
is caught earlier next time.
[Andrew] I've been looking
at our most recent app releases
in the Organizer
When I filter to the last day,
here's a crash
Rhonda experienced
just a moment ago,
fully symbolicated
and ready for investigation.
The new Test Flight feedback
inspector includes her comments,
information on the app build,
version, and her device.
And I can even contact her to
learn more about her experience.
What's even better:
Xcode knows where in my code
this crash came from.
So with one click,
I can open it in my project.
The debug navigator
has the full back trace.
My source editor
highlights the assertion
and my Pull Request conversation
displays too.
It's incredibly exciting
to have what I need
to fix this problem
right here in Xcode.
[Alison] We've brought
everything you need
into the tools you use
every day--
test results,
comments from peers,
and user feedback--
all to give you greater insight
and help you deliver
the next great version
of your app.
Xcode Cloud was built
with your privacy
and security in mind.
Your data--
including your source,
access tokens,
sign-in keys,
and build artifacts--
are handled securely.
And we use the least amount
of data possible
to run the service.
This is a huge year
for our developer tools.
With Xcode 13 and Xcode Cloud,
you'll be building
and delivering quality apps
across all of Apple's platforms
in less time
and with less effort than ever.
Xcode Cloud will initially
be available
as a free, limited beta.
Developer Program account
holders can sign up right now
at developer.apple.com.
We will gradually add more teams
as we work towards
making this available
to all developers next year.
We'll provide more details
on pricing and availability
this fall.
You can check
your registration status
from inside Xcode 13
or the Xcode Cloud tab
in App Store Connect.
In addition
to everything you've seen here,
we have a huge list
of improvements and features
in our developer tools
that you can learn about
in this year's sessions,
including
some terrific enhancements
to Swift support in Xcode.
That's just the start
of an exciting story
for Swift this year.
To tell you more,
here are Josh, Holly, and Matt.
[Josh] Swift has become
a critical language
for developers
across Apple's platforms
and beyond.
It's enabled
our most modern technologies,
serving as the foundation
for a new generation
of frameworks
like SwiftUI, CreateML,
and the new StoreKit 2.
It provides a modern,
type-safe language
to craft your most complex apps
with powerful tools
like Xcode Previews
and Swift Package Manager
to accelerate your development.
And it's friendly
and approachable for newcomers,
with engaging content
and lessons
available in Swift Playgrounds
to learn how to code.
Now, a key part of ensuring that
a technology is great for you
is adopting it ourselves.
High-profile apps like Music
have been written in Swift
for years now,
and system-wide features
like Widgets have been designed
from the ground up with SwiftUI.
Learning Swift and SwiftUI
gives you a common,
powerful set of tools and APIs
to build fully native apps
for all of our platforms.
And because Swift itself
is open source,
we've been able to work together
with many of you
to deliver tons of new features
and capabilities
over the last few years.
Now, one of those capabilities,
which is crucial
to building any app,
is support for concurrency.
And here's Holly
to tell you all about it.
[Holly] Whether you think
about it or not,
you are writing
concurrent code today.
Concurrency enables your apps
to perform multiple tasks
at the same time,
which helps your apps
stay responsive to user input
while doing work
in the background,
like a weather app
fetching forecast data
while the user selects a city.
And it's essential
to taking advantage
of multicore processors
to achieve high performance
for heavy computation,
like rendering complex
visual effects in a video app.
But without language support,
writing concurrent code
is really hard to get right.
So we're bringing first-class
support for concurrency
to Swift.
Our approach
to building concurrency
into the language
follows the same core principles
of Swift itself,
making it easier to write
modern, safe, and fast code
that eliminates entire classes
of programming mistakes.
First, let's talk about how
we've taken a modern approach
to building concurrency
into Swift.
Today, we think of modern code
as structured
and easy to express
what you want to do.
Unfortunately,
most of today's
asynchronous code
uses completion handlers
that are unstructured
and hard to express.
To make expressing asynchronous
functions easier,
we've built the modern
async/await pattern into Swift.
Now you can mark
an asynchronous function
with the async keyword.
When the function is called,
you use the await keyword
to indicate that other work can
be done while the caller waits
for the result
of the async function.
To understand the improvements
async/await brings
over completion handlers,
let's walk through an example.
When I'm not working
on the Swift compiler,
I like to dance.
To prepare for a show,
a dance company
must first warm up,
the crew will fetch the scenery
and props from storage,
and then the stage is set.
Once all of that is done,
the dancers can move
into their opening positions.
Here is an asynchronous
implementation
of "prepareForShow"
that uses completion handlers.
What this code
is trying to accomplish
is really simple,
but the code is convoluted.
It uses nested completion
handlers
that make the flow
of execution unnatural,
so the code
is really hard to read.
Adopting async/await
in this example
leaves us with code
that's now in a straight line.
This code is so much easier
to understand.
The control flow goes
from top to bottom,
like any other function.
You handle errors
and return values
in the same way
as you're used to in Swift.
You can use all of the normal
control flow constructs, too.
So it's easy to add
conditional logic,
so the function behaves
differently during a rehearsal.
Async/await makes writing
asynchronous code easier
by leveraging the tools
you already know.
It's also easier to introduce
concurrency where you need it
using Structured Concurrency.
Structured Concurrency
is a way of organizing
concurrent tasks to make them
easier to reason about.
Let's introduce concurrency
into prepareForShow.
Right now, the function waits
until the dancers
finish their warm-up
before starting
to fetch the scenery,
but these tasks could be done
in parallel.
With Structured Concurrency,
you can easily create
concurrent child tasks
using async/await
with local variables, like this.
Now, the code uses
'async let' variables
to create child tasks that
execute concurrently
with the parent.
So, the company warm up
and fetching the scenery
will run concurrently
with the rest of prepareForShow.
When we need the results
of those child tasks,
we await the results.
Because fetchStageScenery
executes concurrently,
it's possible that
the result isn't ready yet
when prepareForShow
needs to use it,
so accessing the result must be
done asynchronously.
Swift's concurrency model is
also designed to be safe.
Just like Swift eliminates null
pointer mistakes with optionals,
the compiler will now
help eliminate
common concurrency issues
by ensuring
that access to shared state
is safely coordinated
between concurrent tasks.
A core part of this safe
concurrency model
is built around actors.
Actors are
an industry-proven model
for safe concurrent programming,
and a powerful synchronization
primitive.
Conceptually, an actor is
an object that protects
its own state by only providing
mutually exclusive access.
This completely eliminates
concurrent access
and the low-level data
races that come with it.
This concept might sound
familiar, because it's similar
to a pattern that you might
already use
for classes
with a dispatch queue,
which was itself
inspired by actors.
In this pattern,
the instance properties
in a class are carefully
accessed using
a serial dispatch queue
to maintain mutual exclusion.
But this pattern is
prone to mistakes.
There's a lot of boilerplate,
and it's too easy
to forget to manually
use the queue just once
and introduce a race condition
into your code.
To solve these issues, we went
back to the core idea of actors,
and built it into Swift as
a first-class construct.
Now, you can declare
an actor type in Swift
with a simple keyword.
It has the same structure as
the constructs you already know,
and there's no need
for manual synchronization.
With actors built
into the Swift language,
synchronizing access
to actor state
can be managed
for you automatically.
An actor can access its own
properties directly,
and interacting with an actor
externally uses async/await
to guarantee mutual exclusion.
The actor concept is so powerful
that it also solves
another common source
of concurrency problems,
which is proper use
of the main thread
for things like UI operations.
Today, you have to manually
dispatch to the main queue
each time you call an API that
must be run on the main thread.
Now, we're introducing
a way to state that an API
is always run on the main thread
using the main actor.
Making sure that an API
always runs on the main actor
is as easy as annotating
the declaration
with the MainActor attribute.
Just like with other actors,
calling a function
that runs on the main actor
is just an await away.
Altogether,
this means it's easier write
safe concurrent code that you
don't have to manage yourself.
As we build support
for concurrency
directly into the language,
it gives us the opportunity
to better optimize
the performance
of your concurrent code.
With async/await,
the compiler understands
the concurrency of your code,
which allows for more
effective optimizations.
This includes reducing
reference counts and inlining
as well as addressing
concurrency-specific
performance issues like
excessive context switches.
And of course,
your concurrent code will get
even faster as the compiler gets
smarter in the years ahead.
There are
tons of asynchronous APIs
in the SDK that you
already use in your apps.
We've refined the SDK
to enable async/await
with these asynchronous APIs,
so you can immediately
adopt async/await
in your existing code.
And we didn't stop there.
We've added new purposely
crafted APIs
that take advantage
of async/await
for when you work with URLs,
when you're
doing asynchronous I/O,
and we even added support
for asynchronously iterating
line-by-line through a file.
Async/await makes it natural
to express asynchronous code,
structured concurrency
makes concurrent code
easier to reason about,
and actors help you safely model
shared state
in a concurrent program.
The Swift concurrency
model brings together
these fundamental pieces
to make you more efficient,
give you more power,
and allow you to have
more fun
building concurrent apps.
Of course, the language
is just one piece of the puzzle.
The frameworks built with Swift
are just as important.
Now, back to Josh.
[Josh] Swift is the foundation
for the next generation of APIs.
With new features
like Concurrency,
we're evolving the language
and frameworks together,
so you'll see immediate
benefits across the SDK,
including with key
technologies like SwiftUI.
Two years ago, we began
to reinvent UI development
on our platforms.
We started small,
with a core API
that allowed you to adopt
SwiftUI incrementally
in your existing applications.
Last year, we added API to
describe your app's life cycle,
enabling you to develop apps
entirely in SwiftUI
from your first line of code.
And this year, SwiftUI is taking
another huge step forward,
helping you deliver
great experiences
to all your users
across all Apple platforms.
We focused on APIs that we know
are critical to your apps,
because we also needed them
to build ours.
And your feedback helped us
enhance the most important APIs,
while also refining
the development experience.
This year, we've started
using SwiftUI in apps like Maps,
Photos, and Shortcuts.
And we've rebuilt iOS apps
like Weather,
system interfaces like
the Apple Pay payment sheet,
and brand new watchOS apps
like Find My,
entirely with SwiftUI.
To see just a few
of the enhancements
that make this possible,
let's take a look at some ways
that we can improve Fruta.
We'll start with List,
the most ubiquitous component
across all our platforms.
We can now easily add
a swipe action
to mark a smoothie
as a favorite.
Adding pull-to-refresh
is just one more line.
And Swift now makes it
easy to limit a modifier
to a single platform--
in this case, iOS.
Adding a Search field
is just one more line.
Now, we could stop there,
but let's add some
search suggestions as well,
which will be shown
while we're typing.
And let's test it right here
in Xcode.
We have a swipe action now,
pull-to-refresh,
and full search support
including suggestions,
all in just a few lines of code.
Next, let's refine Fruta's
accessibility support.
First, a new modifier which adds
accessibility rotors
can make our app faster
to navigate with VoiceOver.
And second we'll improve
the accessibility
of this custom stepper control.
Custom controls are often
a source of poor accessibility,
but we can now simply inherit
the full accessibility
implementation from
the standard Stepper.
Most SwiftUI APIs are
available across all platforms,
but we're moving platforms
forward individually
where appropriate as well.
Let's add a multi-column
table to our macOS app.
I already added a new file
for this,
so we'll just add the new
Table component here.
And then within it, we'll just
add three columns of data.
Now let's run the macOS
version of our app.
We'll find a search field
placed right where you expect it
in the toolbar,
and suggestions appear
just below it while we type.
We can switch to our new
multi-column table
that we added,
and we'll see it's displaying
the search results as well.
And of course, we can clear
the search to get them all back.
Now let's switch to recipes
and turn on VoiceOver.
With VoiceOver, we can
easily access the rotor
that we added to quickly choose
a smoothie from the list.
And VoiceOver interaction
with our custom stepper
now behaves exactly like
a standard stepper,
making it easy to use
for all of our users.
We're building our apps using
these new capabilities,
so we know that you'll find them
helpful in yours as well.
And we've just scratched
the surface of what's new.
For example,
you're going to love
SwiftUI's new material support.
In the Fruta app, views like
this are made more interesting
by adding a background image,
and they're kept legible
by applying
one of the new material styles
behind the content.
Content responds dynamically
to this background,
so instead of the gray
normally used
for secondary content
in an opaque context,
SwiftUI will automatically apply
vibrant rendering to text,
symbols, and even standard UI
like separators.
So with just one line of code,
you can get great-looking
results like this,
automatically.
And there's so much more.
With all of these improvements,
SwiftUI is the best way to build
great experiences for all your
users across all our platforms.
And this year, we're
bringing app development
with SwiftUI to iPad
in Swift Playgrounds.
It's so much fun, and Matt will
show you all about how it works.
[Matt] You know Swift
Playgrounds provides
a great way to learn how
to code,
and it's been used
by millions of people
to expand
their knowledge of Swift.
And beyond being a great way
to learn,
we know a lot of you already
use Swift Playgrounds
to experiment,
sketching out new ideas
and playing with the latest
features in the iPadOS SDK.
This year, Swift Playgrounds 4
is taking a huge step forward
by allowing you to build apps,
and even submit them
to the App Store
right from your iPad.
With the ability to create apps
on iPad,
you can be more productive
in Swift Playgrounds
than ever before, allowing you
to work on your ideas
wherever you go,
on whichever device you prefer.
And with a new
package-based project format,
you can seamlessly
bring your work between
Swift Playgrounds and Xcode.
Let's dive in and take a look.
This is Swift Playgrounds 4.
It's got all of the great
Learn to Code content
that's helped inspire
new developers around the world,
and now, you can create projects
that let you build SwiftUI apps.
Let's make a new one now
and see what we can build.
I'll open the new project
I created.
In an app project
in Swift Playgrounds,
my code is on the left,
and the result of my work
is on the right,
just like I'm used to.
What's new is deeply integrated
support for SwiftUI,
with live interactive previews
powered by the same technology
used in Xcode.
My new project template comes
with a Hello World placeholder,
which I can easily replace
with a text view of my own.
I'll start typing Text and right
away, I get helpful suggestions
from code completion,
which, new in this release,
appears right below
my insertion point.
I'll accept the completion
and write my own hello message.
While I'm typing,
my app updates live
to show my changes
with each keystroke.
Now, let's have a little fun.
I'm going to replace this
static text with a button.
I'll select my text view,
and then add a button
from the library.
Here in the library,
I can browse and search
through assets in my project,
as well as the SwiftUI views,
modifiers,
colors, and SF Symbols
provided by iPadOS.
For now,
I'll just add my button.
I'm going to fill the action in
with a simple print statement.
For the body, I'll use
a Label with a system image.
The text will be "Say Hello."
And the image will be
the SF Symbol for Swift.
I've now got an interactive
button in my app.
When I tap it,
the print message I wrote
appears as a message bubble
at the bottom of my screen.
If I open the console, I can see
a history of print statements
that have been executed
since I opened this project,
and it updates in real-time
as I interact with my app.
Now, this button is
purple because that's
my app's accent color,
which Swift Playgrounds
chose for me
when I created my project.
If I open the document sidebar,
I can access all of my app's
top-level settings,
like its name, accent color,
and icon.
As much as I do love purple,
I think this smiley face
will look big and bright
in orange,
so I'll change my accent
color here,
and both my app's icon
and the tint color
of the button I just made will
update to reflect the change.
This has been really fun,
but Swift Playgrounds
isn't just for experimentation.
I've got another app that I've
been working on for a while.
I use this app to track
the amount of time I spend
on my favorite hobbies,
and I think
others might find it useful
as well.
I can get a feel for what the
installed app would look like
by taking it full-screen.
Now I can explore my app
in its full-width two-,
or three-column layout.
I can jump out of full screen
and return
to my code whenever I like.
This feels great,
and I think my hard work is
ready to share with my friends
and family with TestFlight.
Anyone with a Developer Account
can upload their apps
from the App Settings area
once they're ready
for App Store Connect.
When I tap the upload button,
Swift Playgrounds builds,
packages, and uploads my app.
I can then hop over to the App
Store Connect website,
and make my app available
via TestFlight,
and when it's ready,
submit it to the App Store,
and share it with the world.
And that's a quick look
at Swift Playgrounds 4,
with the ability to create
apps using SwiftUI
right on your iPad.
Swift Playgrounds 4 will be
available later this year.
We know you're going to love
having the freedom to develop
your app ideas wherever you go,
on whichever device you prefer.
And now,
I'll hand it back to Susan.
[Susan] So much of the way
we experience the world is
through visual communication,
and that's a big part
of using Apple devices.
Our technologies
for graphics, displays,
and augmented reality are front
and center,
whether you're glancing
at the Always on Display
on Apple Watch,
enjoying ProMotion as you work
with video tools on iPad Pro,
playing a game on your iPhone,
or creating immersive 3D content
on your Mac.
And now Myra and Eric are gonna
take you through what's new
this year starting
with augmented reality.
[Myra]
AR is a powerful technology
and thousands of you are already
using it in your apps
to transform how we all work,
play, and express ourselves.
With over a billion AR
enabled iPhones and iPads
around the world today,
there's never been
a better time to start adding
AR experiences to your apps
or building entirely new ones.
Historically, building great AR
apps has required
deep knowledge of 3D modeling
and a mastery
of sophisticated
rendering engines.
However,
we want all of you to be able
to create amazing AR
experiences.
This is why we've released
a suite of technologies
to make it easy for you
to get started with AR.
One of these is RealityKit,
our 3D rendering, audio,
animation, and physics engine
built from the ground up for AR.
RealityKit makes
rendering immersive
AR experiences simple,
featuring
photorealistic rendering,
and camera effects
like noise and motion blur.
RealityKit also takes
advantage of our latest hardware
like the LiDAR Scanner,
which enables virtual objects
to behave just like
they were really there
with people
and object occlusion.
And it's all written in Swift.
Today, we're announcing
RealityKit 2,
a huge update that gives
you more visual, audio,
and animation control
and tackles the most difficult
part of making great AR apps--
creating 3D models.
If you've ever
created one before,
you know a single model
can take hours
and thousands of dollars
to make.
Now, with Object Capture,
you'll be able to make 3D models
in minutes using your iPhone
to capture
2D images of an object
and the Object Capture API
on Mac to turn these images
into lifelike 3D models,
optimized for AR.
This process is so simple.
You start by taking a series
of pictures with your
iPhone or iPad to capture
all angles of the object,
including the bottom,
because we support
flipping the object
and automatic foreground
segmentation.
You can use apps like Qlone,
which provide excellent guides
to help streamline
your workflow.
Then, using
the Object Capture API,
it only takes a few lines of
code to generate your 3D model.
You start a new photogrammetry
session in RealityKit
that points to the folder
of your captured images.
Then, call the process
function to generate
the model
at the desired level of detail.
It's that easy!
Object Capture enables you
to generate USDZ files
optimized for AR Quick Look,
so users can view them
in Messages, Mail, Safari,
and other apps.
You can also generate USD
or OBJ asset bundles
from the Object Capture API
that can be used for ray-tracing
and other
post-production workflows.
Turning real world objects into
3D models has never been easier.
You can get started using
Object Capture today
with our sample code,
and we're working with
some of the leading 3D content
creation tools
to bring this workflow into many
of the pro apps you already use
like Unity Mars,
Cinema 4D, and Qlone,
available later this year.
It's easy to bring
Object Capture models into Xcode
and use the new RealityKit
APIs to add effects.
My team and I tested
Object Capture by scanning
our favorite food,
and we built an AR App Clip
to share our recipes,
which include the AR preview
of the dish.
The chocolate croissant we
captured using Qlone
is actually a virtual
replica of a croissant
someone on my team baked,
and I want to add it as another
recipe to our App Clip.
I'll start by dragging
the 3D model of my croissant
into my ARApp project.
Next, I'll anchor it
to my App Clip Code
using ARKit and initialize
a ModelEntity for the asset.
I can always fully examine
the 3D model directly
in Xcode Quicklook at any time
while building my project,
before deploying my app clip.
We've used the new
RealityKit APIs in our App Clip
to add effects to each AR dish
to make it more realistic.
Because RealityKit is
a native rendering engine,
we can fit multiple AR scenes
or recipes into the App Clip.
Let's check it out.
When I scan the App Clip Code,
it launches the App Clip
and then anchors the chocolate
croissant right on top.
To make the croissant
more realistic,
we used the new RealityKit
custom surface shader
to add emissive light and pull
back on the ambient occlusion.
Let's take a look at
a few more dishes from the team,
like seared steak.
Here we added
onto the custom surface shader
by creating a steam effect
with the new
Procedural Geometry API
to layer in a flip-book shader.
Because the steam is procedural,
we can use the same effect
on lots of recipes,
like this pizza.
Notice how the steam
effect procedurally expanded
with size of the pizza.
For this barbecue chicken dish,
we've added a full screen
post processing fire effect
to indicate this dish is spicy.
And finally, we dropped
the flames and instead used
a new compute shader
and geometry modifier
to add some celebratory confetti
around the birthday cake.
As you can see, we've opened up
RealityKit rendering
to more customizations,
and we can't wait to see
your creativity in how
you use these new APIs.
These are just some
of the exciting new improvements
we have for AR that enable
all developers
to create 3D models
to build more immersive
and lifelike AR experiences.
One of the foundational
aspects of what we do
in ARKit and RealityKit
is our graphics technologies.
And Eric will give us
an update on what's new.
[Eric] A core idea of how
we build products at Apple
is that we bring together
the most amazing
hardware and software,
and our approach to graphics
reflects that ideal.
For years,
we've delivered powerful
Apple-designed GPUs
for iPhone and iPad,
paired with our Metal graphics
and compute APIs
to help you get
the most out of our products.
And now, with the M1 chip,
not only are we are delivering
an unprecedented level
of graphics performance
and power efficiency
in our latest Macs and iPad Pro,
but we have created a unified
Apple graphics platform
with a common architecture based
on Metal, the Apple GPU,
and unified memory, that spans
from iPhone, to iPad, to Mac.
And this platform enables
a fundamental shift.
Graphics workloads that
previously required
high-end workstations or
discrete GPU gaming computers,
are now possible across
our most popular products.
For instance, the console-level
performance of this unified
platform has enabled developers
like Larian to bring their
AAA game,
Divinity Original Sin 2,
to Mac and now to iPad.
And Deep Silver is using M1
and Metal's modern
shader pipeline
to enable the high performance,
immersive graphics
in their survival game
Metro Exodus for Mac.
But this graphics platform
is not just for games.
Metal compute APIs are now
accelerating the next generation
of professional GPU renderers,
like the all-new Octane X
from OTOY
and Maxon's Redshift
renderer in Cinema 4D,
now running Metal-accelerated
on the Mac
for the very first time.
So to help you bring your
graphics apps and games across
all of Apple's powerful devices,
we focused on two big areas
this year:
advanced graphics
and gaming features,
and powerful
graphics developer tools.
First, we focused on three
key features essential to modern
high end games
and GPU rendering algorithms
In order to accelerate
complex mathematical operations,
model the behavior of light,
and represent realistic
surfaces, modern GPU renderers
need to interleave Metal
graphics and compute commands
in the same pipeline,
which is why Metal can now call
dynamic libraries,
and Ray Query primitives,
directly from
your graphics shaders.
And you can create even more
photo-realistic rendering
with the new Stochastic
Motion Blur function
in the Metal Ray Tracing API.
For games to achieve higher
frame rates
with lower latency
and less judder,
developers need more control
over the display.
To accomplish this
and take advantage of
the awesome graphics performance
of the latest iPad Pro,
your game can use the Metal
presentation time API
and the ProMotion display
to dynamically adapt
your app's frame rate based
on your desired latency
between rendering and input.
And macOS Monterey adds support
for Adaptive Sync Displays.
This means you can now
take advantage of these
ultra low-latency and variable
refresh rate displays
for your Mac games as well.
Now, high-end games
with advanced graphics
are often designed around using
game controllers as input.
And adding game controller
support is a powerful
and easy way to use a common
input model
to bring your games to our
unified graphics platform.
Our Game Controller
framework now supports
the most popular controllers,
Including support for the latest
Xbox Series X
Wireless Controller
and the PlayStation 5
DualSense Controller,
complete with haptics support.
To make it even easier
for you to bring your
controller-based games
to iPhone, and iPad,
we've added a new API so that
you can enable an on-screen
virtual Game Controller,
with just a few lines of code.
and game controller support is
more valuable than ever,
because in macOS Monterey
and iPadOS 15,
players can find the games
their friends are playing,
directly navigate
to the app library
to launch a game,
and then hit the "Share" button
to record their favorite
game highlights,
all without the controller
ever leaving their hands.
Now, along with these new
advanced APIs and features,
Xcode 13 adds powerful
new graphics developer tools
for you to optimize
and debug your GPU code,
each designed to bring your
modern high-end games
and graphics applications
to the next level.
First, when building advanced
GPU renderers and games,
GPU shaders can get really big.
Debugging 10,000 lines
of shader code
across thousands of workgroups
all running in parallel
can take a really long time.
To help you streamline this
process, Xcode 13 adds
Selective Shader Debugging.
Here, we're using
Selective Shader Debugging
to choose exactly which
functions to debug,
within a much larger GPU shader.
This can dramatically
reduce the time it takes you
to iterate and debug
your largest shaders,
which lets you develop faster,
and focus on adding features
and performance
to your GPU code.
Next, high end AAA games
also require the latest
in modern texture
compression support,
which is why we've updated
our powerful
Metal Texture Converter Tool
to give you direct control
over the Texture Converter
compression pipeline,
added all-new gamma-aware
pixel transforms,
and vastly expanded support
for the latest ASTC
and BC texture compression
formats used by Mac, PC,
and iOS games.
This makes it even easier
to optimize
your game's texture assets
for each of Apple's devices.
Finally, to help you achieve
peak performance with your
most advanced rendering,
Xcode 13 adds an all-new
GPU Timeline view
in the Metal Debugger.
This powerful new view allows
you to combine the best
of visually debugging
your Metal commands,
resources, and buffers,
on the timeline of events,
in addition to powerful
performance counters
and bottleneck
analysis information.
With Apple CPUs, GPUs,
and Metal, we have created
a unified graphics platform
with over a billion devices,
with the latest features
and developers tools
to enable you to unleash
all-new levels of capability
and performance for your
graphics, pro apps, and games.
And now back to you, Susan.
[Susan] Your apps can help
connect people
with ideas, services, tools,
and most importantly,
other people.
Finding balance is just as
important as connecting,
so this year we're enabling you
to help users
focus on your app
at the right moments,
to manage devices of loved ones
while respecting their privacy,
and to make your app's content
the center of new, shared,
intimate experiences
built across Apple platforms.
We created a powerful new set
of APIs
that'll help your app create
those kinds of relationships.
Let's start with Heena and Matt
to tell us about Focus.
[Heena] iOS 15 introduces
a powerful new set of tools
to help people focus.
These tools
help reduce distractions,
so that people can be
in the moment.
And it starts with an entirely
new approach to notifications.
Here are some notifications
that have piled up
on my Lock screen.
Their levels of urgency
are clearly different.
But they all behaved
identically.
They had the same look,
the same haptic,
the same apparent
level of importance.
Now, with the new
Interruption Level API,
there are more nuanced
ways for apps to convey
different levels of urgency.
Notifications can be assigned
one of four interruption levels.
Passive interruptions are silent
and don't wake the device.
People will see them the next
time they pick up their phones.
You might want to use
these for notifications
that aren't time-sensitive.
Active interruptions
will play a sound or haptic
just like notifications today.
Time Sensitive interruptions are
designed to visually stand out
and hang out on the Lock screen
a little longer
if the user hasn't tapped on it.
They'll also be announced
by Siri if someone
is wearing AirPods.
And you'll want to use
this for notifications
that require
immediate attention.
Critical alerts are
the most urgent category.
They'll play a sound even if
the device is muted.
These are reserved
for only very serious health
and safety concerns, and require
an approved entitlement.
[Matt] There's another
category of notifications
that deserves special attention:
communications from people.
If you have a communication app,
it's important that you tell
the system about your message
and call notifications.
The system will then
use this information
to tune your notifications'
appearance and behaviors,
which will help people
better interpret them.
Once implemented,
your notifications
will go from the standard
appearance to looking like this,
featuring a prominent avatar
with your app icon superimposed,
and the same avatars will be
used elsewhere in the system,
like in the Share Sheet.
[Heena] I'm so excited
to see those avatars!
All right, so notifications are
a really effective way
to get people's attention.
But they can also be
kind of ephemeral.
If they're not well-timed,
people can easily miss them.
To help users engage on
notifications on their own time,
we're introducing
the Notification Summary,
which delivers notifications
as a helpful bundle
at times the user chooses,
so they can quickly catch up
when it's best for them.
The summary bundles
Passive and Active
notifications from
user selected apps
and presents them
in a beautiful layout.
It then sticks around
on the Lock screen
for a while until it's seen.
The summary is also
personalized for each user.
As you can see, there are two
marquee slots at the top.
What's featured there
is based on a few factors:
First, to provide variety,
those two apps
are sampled from
inside the summary.
From there,
we do some additional weighting.
A notification
with a large thumbnail
will always be chosen
over one without.
And the notification with
the highest relevance score--
which is something
that you determine--
will be chosen over others
from the same app.
Okay, so you might be wondering,
"How does my app end up
in the summary at all?”
Well, first,
it's completely up to the user
if they want to use
the notification summary.
And if they do,
apps that send the most
notifications will be suggested.
Users can then customize
which apps go in the summary
along with the times
they'll receive them.
If your app is placed
in the scheduled summary,
there's still a way for you
to reach the user in real time.
That's where Time Sensitive
notifications come in.
Notifications that use
this interruption level
will be delivered immediately.
Remember, you should only
mark notifications
as Time Sensitive if they
require the immediate attention
and are relevant in the moment.
[Matt] No feature
eliminates distractions
more than Do Not Disturb.
But Do Not Disturb
silences all notifications
and we wanted to give
users more flexibility.
With Focus,
users can choose the apps
and people that they need
to receive notifications from
based on what
they're currently doing.
They can carve out their day
for work or create a Focus
for an activity like gaming,
reading, or fitness.
While in a Focus,
users can share
their status with others,
so they know not to interrupt.
But if it's truly urgent,
a message can break through
and notify anyway.
Your communication
app can also request access
to the user's Focus status.
If granted,
the system will inform your app
when it changes,
so your app can keep its status
in sync
with the rest of the system.
Your app can even provide
users the ability
to break through
for urgent communications.
We're providing users with more
control and flexibility
than ever to manage
their notifications.
And to help make sure these
tools are working for them,
the system will periodically
check in to see if
a specific adjustment to their
settings might be helpful.
It's based off of how
users interact with your app
and your notifications.
So if a user is typically using
an app while in a Focus,
then the system might
suggest allowing that app's
notifications during that Focus.
Or if a user is
interacting with an app's
Time Sensitive notifications,
then the system might suggest
reverting them back
to active notifications.
The same goes for when an app
sends one notification
after another
and the user isn't engaging.
The system might suggest muting
all notifications
from that app or maybe just
a single conversation
for a limited amount of time.
So to make the most
of these new features,
there are a few key things
that you need to do.
You can help make sure
the right content
is featured in the marquee slots
at the top of the summary
by setting a relevance score
on your notifications
and attaching
the appropriate thumbnails.
You should think carefully about
which interruption levels
make sense
for your notifications.
If you have a communication app,
you should adopt
the new User Notifications API
to tell the system
about your message
and call notifications.
You should also reflect
the user's Focus in your app
by using the new
Focus Status API.
We think these tools,
with your help,
will go a long way in helping
users reduce distractions.
Next, Martin is gonna tell us
about the new Screen Time API.
[Martin] Thanks, Matt.
Okay, let's switch gears
to talk about Screen Time
and parental controls.
We recognize that parents
need modern,
innovative solutions
to help their children
build healthy digital lives,
and they also deeply value
their family's privacy.
And we've seen an appetite
from many of you to deliver
on these user needs.
So today, we are releasing
Screen Time API,
a set of tailor made
parental control frameworks
that build upon our deep
commitment to privacy.
We had three key goals in mind
with the Screen Time API.
To offer you modern solutions
for developing
parental control apps.
To empower you to build
dynamic experiences
and innovate beyond what even
Screen Time offers today.
And to protect user privacy.
To that end, we've added
three new Swift frameworks
to the iOS SDK
that enable you to innovate
in the world
of parental controls:
Managed Settings,
Family Controls,
and Device Activity.
First, let's talk about
Managed Settings.
Fundamentally,
your parental control app
needs a way to restrict
what a child can do
across their devices,
and ensure that
those restrictions
remain in place
until the parent says otherwise.
With Managed Settings, your app
can set a number of restrictions
like locking accounts in place,
preventing a password change,
filtering web traffic,
and limiting access
to applications,
much like Screen Time.
customized with your app's
branding and functionality.
By leveraging this framework,
your app will be able
to manage
all of these restrictions.
Beyond restrictions
you'll be able to limit access
to apps and websites
when appropriate
and provide a set of actions
unique to your use cases.
And finally,
we lock the app in place
so it can only be removed with
the parent's explicit approval.
Now, the Family Controls
framework is at the heart
of our privacy model
and it serves two key
user-facing experiences.
First, it allows parents
to authorize your app
for management
with their iCloud credentials,
ensuring that the device is
for a child in that family.
And it provides a personalized
experience via
a system App & Website picker,
which allows parents
to choose which apps and sites
should be restricted, all while
protecting user privacy.
We wanted to allow parents
to manage and restrict
the apps and websites
that their children use,
but do so in a way
that doesn't divulge
their private application
and web browsing details.
So, rather than returning
a selection of raw bundle IDs
and URLs, the picker will return
opaque tokens instead.
These tokens allow
your app to keep track
of which apps and websites
a parent wants to manage,
all while ensuring that
parents are the only people
who can access this highly
sensitive information.
And these tokens enable
functionality across
all of these frameworks.
Use a token to limit access
to a specific app or website
with Managed Settings,
or gain insight into app
and website activity,
something that wasn't possible
on iOS until today,
with the Device Activity
framework.
With the tokens provided
by the Activity Picker
in Family Controls,
you're ready to leverage
the power of Device Activity.
You can register
unique time windows
for different apps
and activities,
each emitting a warning like,
"Five more minutes left,"
and a completion event.
Once your app receives these
events, it can react accordingly
by changing restrictions,
limiting access to relevant apps
and websites
or...
encouraging children
to do their homework.
Whatever experience
you are trying to deliver
for your users.
This concept of seeing
device activity,
not just browser activity,
but across all apps
on the device
is totally new
and is a unique opportunity
for you to innovate in the world
of parental controls.
With the Screen Time API,
you could enable
family-wide downtime,
or even create incentives
to do something fun
after something educational,
like unlocking some gaming
after doing some homework.
We're super excited to see
how you will build on these APIs
to help parents and families
manage the way
that they use our devices.
And now over to Vi to tell us
what's new with Widgets.
[Vi] Last year, we introduced
Widgets on the Home screen.
and people loved them.
Widgets provide
deep personalization
with delightful and timely views
of the most relevant content
from your app.
They're all about glanceability.
People love how widgets present
the most useful information
from your app,
in a single glance,
at exactly the right time.
A tap can deep link just
to the right part of your app.
Over the past year,
you've created some
amazing widget experiences
that have truly inspired us.
The best widgets are
focused, dynamic,
and provide unique views
of the app throughout the day.
Like this one, from Day One.
That's me and my kids
on a trip to Santa Cruz.
Surfacing just the right
piece of content
in the right context
helps your users discover
the magic of your apps.
And we've seen that
widgets encourage people
to use your app even more.
This year,
we are taking the next step
in making your apps more useful
and more discoverable
with widgets.
And it starts with letting
people place widgets
among your apps
on the iPad Home screen.
To take advantage
of the large screen,
we're introducing a new
extra-large size for widgets.
This means a whole new set
of opportunities
for entirely new types of
widgets that work best on iPad.
To make getting into widgets
even easier,
we're adding new default
Home screen layouts
with widgets on iPhone and iPad.
These include widgets
from apps people use the most,
arranged in Smart Stacks.
Stacks let you save space
by placing multiple widgets
on top of each other.
Smart Stacks use on-device
intelligence to show the widget
that's most relevant right now.
Building on the foundation
of last year's
TimelineRelevance API,
we are going beyond
simply rotating the stack
with on-device intelligence.
Now we can give your widget
more exposure by suggesting it
even if it was not
already in the stack.
And how do we do this?
Enter widget suggestions.
How people interact
with your app, as well as
what you can tell us, helps us
suggest your widget in a stack.
Let us see how this works
with our Fruta example app.
If the user orders
a green juice every morning,
on-device intelligence
will learn to suggest it.
To opt in, you'll need to adopt
the intents framework
and donate an Interaction.
That's it!
Now your widget can be
automatically suggested
based on how people
use your app.
When you want to provide
new information to users,
you can also donate
using the Intents API.
For instance,
the Fruta app can adopt this
to offer
a free birthday smoothie.
Both past usage behavior,
as well as
new relevant intent donations
can then help us suggest
your widget in a stack
at the right time.
And if a user finds
your widget useful,
they can easily add it
permanently with a long press.
So that's our big update
to widgets this year.
More useful,
and more discoverable than ever.
Next up is some news
on SharePlay.
Over to Ryan and Juan.
[Ryan] This year,
we've all had to improvise
to find new ways of connecting.
And it has been striking
to see many of you innovate,
and build awesome new ways
for people to feel
a sense of togetherness
while at a distance.
And with people relying
on FaceTime and iMessage
more than ever
to stay connected,
it was only natural for us
to build on those experiences,
to help people feel more
together when they're apart.
Some of the most meaningful
moments people have together
are about more than just
sharing a conversation
they're about
sharing experiences.
So to foster
that sense of closeness,
we needed to build
something completely new.
And we had an ambitious goal.
We wanted FaceTime
to feel like a portal
which transported people
into the same space
as some of their closest
friends and family.
So we built SharePlay.
And we've given you the tools
you need
to create magical
SharePlay experiences
with the new
GroupActivities framework.
We bring the group,
you bring the activities.
And it all comes down
to this concept of activities.
When someone in a FaceTime
call starts an activity,
SharePlay will bring the group
directly into your app,
allowing for rich
interactive experiences
where users can communicate,
just like they're used to.
There are a lot of possibilities
to explore
with the Group Activities
framework.
And what better activity to do
in your virtual living room
than watching
your favorite shows
with some of
your closest friends.
Hey, Juan, since your team
just finished integrating
SharePlay into the TV app,
why don't you show us around?
[Juan] Sure thing!
What do you want to watch?
[Ryan]
How about a little "Ted Lasso"?
[Juan]
Sounds good.
I press play,
and the system asks me
if I want to start
shared playback,
or play locally instead.
This is where you come in.
We're offering new APIs
to start playback
that are designed to fit
right into your app's
existing video experience.
Now because I chose
shared playback,
the system is coordinating
the video on my device
and Ryan's at exactly
the same time with Core Media
and Group Activities
doing the heavy lifting.
[Ryan]
That means when I hit pause,
Juan's video pauses
on the exact same moment.
I can even jump
to a favorite scene
and everyone comes with me,
as if we were all
in the same room.
[Ted] All right?
I mean, hey,
Higgins and I are having
lunch today.
[Juan]
I love this scene!
The magic behind this
playback coordination
means your media isn't
retransmitted in any way.
Everyone will get your
full-fidelity video
because it's playing
in your app and streaming
from your servers
as it always does.
Now, let's see how easy it is
to adopt Group Activities
in a simple media app
and take full advantage
of the framework.
There are just a few steps
to get your app ready
for shared playback.
First, we need to define
our Group Activity.
We'll create a new type
that conforms
to the Group Activity protocol,
and supply a URL for everyone
in the group to load.
If your app already
supports deep-links to content,
you can use those here.
We'll also provide
some basic metadata
to the system
to customize system UI
like confirmation dialogs
and notices.
Next, we need to hook up
our play buttons.
In our play() function,
we'll create a new activity,
and call
.prepareForActivation() on it.
This is when the system presents
that confirmation dialogue
you saw earlier.
You can call this without any
extra conditionals.
It'll return immediately if the
user is not on a FaceTime call.
Now let's turn our attention
to handling incoming activities.
The initiator joins the session
just like other participants,
so the code looks the same
for everyone.
Here, I'm using
Swift concurrency
to create a new model
with each session
that's delivered.
We'll then join the new
session once the player appears.
You can observe the session
for other state changes
to update our UI accordingly.
Finally, let's make sure
we synchronize our players.
Step 1: Grab your AVPlayer,
and call
.playbackCoordinator.coordinate
WithSession
passing in your session.
Step 2: There's no step 2.
That's it!
That's all you need to do to get
frame-accurate AV sync
with Group Activities
and AVPlayer.
The system handles the rest.
[Ryan] Now we've talked a lot
about shared media experiences.
But we wanted Group Activities
to provide a foundation
that could power even the most
ambitious experiences
that you could dream up.
So we started building
on top of the fabric
that powers
Group FaceTime today,
providing your app with a fast
and reliable data channel.
By taking on the job
as group leader,
our servers orchestrate
a centralized state
for the entire group.
These servers don't see
your users' data,
because it's all
end-to-end encrypted
so that it stays private.
And using this fast
and secure data channel,
you can create
immersive experiences,
from turning the page
on a shared book,
to seeing the strokes
that someone has drawn
on a shared whiteboard live.
We want to really inspire you
to take full advantage
of our APIs
and bring your users together
like never before.
But before we show you a demo,
we're gonna need to call in a
little extra help with this one.
Hey, everyone.
Thanks for joining.
We're gonna need your help
with this one last demo
to really demonstrate the power
of Group Activities.
All right, we have a whiteboard
demo app to show you
what can be done
with Group Activities.
Now, by opening a shared canvas,
I'm starting a new activity
with the group to draw together.
Now we're all looking
at the same canvas,
and we can interact with
each other in a whole new way.
If I draw
somewhere on the canvas,
everyone can see
what I'm drawing live.
Now this app is using the same
APIs that you saw previously,
but instead
of synchronizing media,
it's using GroupSessionMessenger
to send my strokes
to everyone's device.
[Juan]
And this isn't screen sharing.
Because the app is running
natively on everyone's iPad,
I can draw on the canvas, too.
Let's all give it a try.
So we can gather
around a shared canvas
no matter how far apart we are.
[Ryan] And it's bringing us
together like never before.
Thanks for the help, everyone.
[Juan] The best part is,
everything you just saw--
SharePlay activities,
playback synchronization,
and the fast,
secure data channel--
you get all of these benefits
just by integrating your app
with GroupActivities framework.
SharePlay is a great new way
to elevate your app's content
and help you create
a more immersive experience
for your users.
We're eager to see
the new shared experiences
that you'll come up with
using Group Activities.
Now, over to Susan
to wrap things up.
[Susan] We believe the advances
you've see today
will help you
continue to build apps
that make a difference.
We're building tools that
streamline your workflow
and make it easier
to build great apps faster.
We've made it easier
to build immersive content,
games, and tools
for professional creators.
We've shown you how your apps
can help users connect
while still focusing
on the things that matter most.
What you've seen today
is just the start.
There's so much more
to check out this week
that we haven't even
had a chance to touch on.
We know you're gonna build
something awesome,
and we can't wait to see it.