[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Jonathan Hogg: Hello,
and welcome to this session
on the Accelerate
and associated frameworks.
I'm Jonathan from Apple's
Vector & Numerics team,
and today I'm going
to talk to you briefly
about the Accelerate framework
before telling you what's new
in our machine learning library,
BNNS.
I'll then cover improvements
to simd.h,
and introduce Apple Archive,
and our new Apple Encrypted
Archive containers.
So let's get started
with a brief overview
of the Accelerate framework.
Accelerate provides
high-performance
numerical computation
across all Apple platforms:
MacOS, iOS, iPadOS,
watchOS and tvOS.
Accelerate also provides access
to the machine learning
accelerators
in Apple Silicon Macs and
recent iPhone and iPad devices.
The only way to leverage
this hardware
is by calling Accelerate
either directly
or through higher-level
frameworks such as Core ML.
Accelerate is composed
of several parts.
vDSP provides primitives
for signal processing
such as DFT and FFT routines.
vImage provides routines
for image processing
such as format conversion
and convolution.
vForce provides
vectorized versions
of transcendental functions
such as sine and cosine.
BLAS and LAPACK provide
high-performance implantations
of the standard dense matrix
algebra routines,
while Sparse BLAS
and our Sparse Solvers
provide similar functionality
for sparse matrices.
Finally, BNNS provides support
for machine learning.
I'm also going
to talk to you today
about some related frameworks.
simd.h provides computational
small vectors and matrices,
such as those covered
in graphics programming,
whilst Compression
and Apple Archive
provide support
for lossless data compression.
In order to use
these frameworks,
simply add the relevant include
or import statement to your code
and add the framework
to your Xcode project.
Now, let me tell you
about BNNS in more detail.
BNNS stands for
Basic Neural Network Subroutines
and provides performance
primitives for machine learning
on the CPU.
For those of you unfamiliar
with Apple's machine
learning ecosystem,
this diagram shows
the lay of the land.
There are three main
hardware blocks:
the CPU, which includes the
machine learning accelerators
I mentioned previously;
the GPU;
and the separate neural engine.
BNNS provides performance
primitives on the CPU
in the same way as MPS
provides performance primitives
on the GPU.
Above this layer, there are
a number of frameworks
that run on one
or more of these backends.
These include Apple's high-level
machine learning frameworks --
Core ML and Create ML --
as well as
the specialist frameworks
like Vision
and Natural Language.
BNNS provides support for both
training and inference
across a wide range
of layer types,
as well as support for the
optimizers shown at the bottom.
In this release,
we have added support
for several new layer types:
embedding, random fill,
and quantization;
as well as support
for AdamW optimizer.
We've also improved
existing layers,
adding two new
activation functions:
SiLU and HardSwish,
as well as support for new
arithmetic functions:
ternary select, multiply add,
as well as element-wise
minimum and maximum.
Layer fusions
provide the ability
to consume the output
of one layer immediately
as the input
to a subsequent layer,
avoiding the need
to write it out to memory
and read it back in again.
We've added layer fusions
of convolution
and fully connected layers
with the new quantization layer,
as well as a fusion
between the arithmetic
and normalization layers.
Other improvements
include improved support
for gradient clipping
in the optimizer,
which can also be used
as standalone functions,
as well as AMSGrad support
for our Adam-based optimizers.
Together, these improvements
have expanded the range
and network architectures
we can accelerate even further.
Now, let me tell you about
some improvements to simd.h.
simd.h provides computational
primitives on small vectors
and matrices that fit
into the CPU's registers,
including support for functions
such as sine and cosine
as well as useful
geometric operations,
including support
for quaternions.
The thing I really like about
simd.h is it lets us jump in
and get 90 percent
of the benefit of vectorization
with 10 percent of the effort.
Here, let me show you.
Here's a neural network
activation function
I just invented.
As you can see, it has
three different branches.
If the input is less than
minus pi,
I just return zero.
If it's between
minus pi and pi,
I return two times
the exponent of x,
multiplied by x plus pi
over two.
Otherwise,
if it's greater than pi,
I return two times
the exponent.
That's great, but if I have
a large amount of data,
I may want to run it faster
than a scalar loop allows.
So let me show you how
to implement that in simd.
I already have some
boilerplate in place,
an extension which allows me
to easily write vectors
to a buffer,
and a simple loop that iterates
over our output array
in increments of one length
eight vector at a time.
The interesting part is how
to translate our scalar function
into a simd equivalent.
Let's start by looking again
at our scalar code.
I see it has several branches.
These don't work well
for vectorization.
Instead, let's construct this
out of parts we can merge
based on a mask.
Looking more closely,
if x is less than minus pi,
I just return zero.
If it's greater,
I return an expression involving
two times exponent of x.
Let's pull that out.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now, we want to construct
a vector from that y,
replacing with zero everywhere
that x is element-wise
less than minus pi.
Next, we can look
at a greater than case.
Here, we are either multiplying
by one in the high region,
or by x plus pi over two
in the middle region.
So let's write that
in the same way.
We take our x plus pi
over two expression
[KEYSTROKES]
and this time we're replacing
with one everywhere
that x is element-wise
greater than or equal to pi.
Now all that remains
is to multiply
these two quantities together.
[KEYSTROKES]
Obviously, if a zero element,
multiplying by either value of b
still returns zero.
So let's run that
and see how it looks.
Now, I can see --
looking down the console --
that my new simd version
is almost three times faster
than the previous scalar code.
So how is simd improved
in this release?
We've improved usability for C++
programmers using templates.
We have added types
and traits structures
to allow you to move between
the underlying scalar type
and vector length
and the concrete simd type
without complicated
code structures
or needing to implement
similar types yourself.
To simplify their use, we have
also added convenient aliases
to reduce the need
for C++ boilerplate.
Here's an example
of what they look like in use.
The vector and matrix types
allow us to go
from an underlying type --
such as float or int --
and a vector length
to a concrete type
and also have members providing
access to related types,
such as the unaligned version
and the mask type
resulting from comparisons.
The Vector_t
and Matrix_t aliases
provide simplified syntax
to access the same definitions
as we had before.
The get_traits struct allows us
to go in the other direction,
moving from the concrete
simd type to the generic one.
And again, there are aliases
to simplify the syntax
for common use cases.
We've also added
templated versions
of the make
and convert functions
to allow their use
in templated code.
These work the same
as the existing functions,
but their destination type
is now a template parameter
rather than part
of the function name.
In addition
to our C++ improvements,
we have added
several new functions
supported across
all our languages.
These are classification
functions --
like isfinite and isinf --
that provide vector versions
of the scalar functions in libm,
as well as new functions for
calculating the gamma function,
as well as the trace
of simd matrices.
Now, introducing Apple Archive
and our new Apple Encrypted
Archive formats.
Apple Archive has been powering
our system updates
for the better part of a decade.
In the macOS 11 release,
we gave you access
to the compressed container
and archive format.
New in macOS 12,
we have added APIs
for encryption to this support.
The archive format itself
provides a modern,
modular approach,
allowing you to select
exactly which file attributes
and metadata you want to store.
It is streamable, which means
you don't have to worry about
fitting the entire data
in memory at once.
It also supports
separate manifest files
for indexing into large archives
like file system images.
The new Apple Encrypted Archive
builds on this,
combining compression,
authenticated encryption,
and a digital signature
into a single secure package.
It gives you state-of-the-art cryptography
that's been designed and audited
by our Security team,
as well as outside experts.
Data confidentiality means
that your data stays secret.
Data authenticity means
that you can be sure
it hasn't been corrupted
in transit.
Sender authentication means
you can be sure who sent it.
Signature privacy means
that in a public key context,
only you and the sender
know who has signed it.
We also obfuscate metadata --
such as the file lengths --
and include resigning
attack protection.
Together, this means
you can be confident
that your data remains
private and secure.
In order to facilitate
correct deployment,
we offer a number
of different profiles
for different use cases.
The basic profile
is to have a digital signature
without encryption.
This can be used for things
like software updates
where the contents
are not secret,
but you want to be sure the data
hasn't been tampered with.
Next, we have
symmetric encryption,
with or without a signature,
using a securely shared
binary key.
This is similar
to the next option
which uses a password
rather than a binary key.
Finally, we have full-blown
public key encryption,
again with or without
signature.
In all profiles,
compression is optional
and data
is always authenticated.
To work with these formats,
we provide a number
of command-line tools.
For working with the compressed
archive portion of the format,
there is compression_tool,
and for the encrypted archive,
there is aea.
The aa tool handles
the entire container.
There is of course also an API
provided by the Apple Archive
framework in both Swift and C.
It is stream-based,
allowing for both sequential
and random access.
Its implementation
is multithreaded
for blazingly fast performance.
So, let's see
this API in action.
Here, we have a simple demo
app we have put together.
The top portion of the window
acts as a drag-and-drop target
for things we want to encrypt,
whilst the bottom part
is a simple status pane.
Let's say I want to encrypt
this TopSecret directory.
I just drag and drop
this into the app.
And, oh no!
We get an error.
We haven't implemented
this function yet!
Let's do that now.
So, what do we need to do to
encrypt this with Apple Archive?
First, we need
an encryption context
that describes the algorithm
and profile to use,
along with our encryption
secret.
We also need a file stream we're
going to write the archive to.
We combine these
to create an encryption stream.
The encryption stream
will encrypt a stream of bytes,
so we need an adaptor that
will translate the directory
we want to encrypt into such.
This is the encoder stream.
The data, of course,
flows in the opposite direction
to the object creation.
We feed archive entries
into the encoder stream,
which transform them into bytes
for the encryption stream,
which then outputs the encrypted
data to the file stream.
Let's see how that looks
in code.
Here, we specify that we're
using a symmetric profile.
And the "none" tells us
that we're going to use
no digital signature.
The initial portion
of the enum
just specifies the particular
algorithm we want to use.
Here, we're going to use "lzfse"
to compress our data.
With the context created,
we just need to specify
our symmetric encryption key.
Next, we create
those three streams.
[KEYSTROKES]
First, we create
the file stream,
then we combine it
with a context
to create the encryptionStream.
Finally, we derive
the encoderStream.
Now, it's important
that we remember
to close these streams
in the correct order.
In particular,
closing the encryptionStream
does a lot of work
behind the scenes,
as it signs and seals
the archive.
Finally, all that remains
is for us to feed our files
into the encoderStream.
I specify the file attributes
I want to encode
and then call the
writeDirectoryContents method.
All that remains is print
a status message to the console
with the encryption key.
Let's see if that worked.
If I drop our TopSecret
directory into the app,
it succeeds, encrypts it, and
prints out our encryption key.
Now, if I drag and drop our
encrypted archive into the app,
it tries to decrypt it
and asks for the encryption key.
So let's copy and paste
that encryption key
and let's see what's inside.
Mmm, delicious!
That's everything I have for you
on Apple Encrypted Archive,
so let's wrap up.
Today, I talked to you
about improvements
to the Accelerate framework,
including support
for new layer types in BNNS,
as well as expanded C++ support
and other functionality
in simd.h.
I then gave you an introduction
to the Apple Archive
and new Apple Encrypted Archive
formats
and their support
in the frameworks.
Thank you
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
♪