[upbeat music]
[Camille] Hi.
I'm Camille Moussette,
designer
on the Apple Design team.
In this session,
I will walk you through
the practical steps
and design considerations
for adding audio and haptic
feedback to an app.
Historically, it's been quite
challenging both from a design
and engineering perspective
to deliver rich app experiences
that include animation,
sound, and haptics.
With Core Haptics on iPhone,
it's now easier to create
magical moments that look,
sound, and feel real.
To explain
and practice those skills,
I'll use an iOS app
derived from a previous
code sample project
called HapticBounce.
A few additions were
made to make it like
a mini game and to offer
a canvas to design visual,
sound, and haptics
working well together.
The new demo
is called HapticRicochet.
HapticRicochet is the story
of a ball that comes to life
in the iPhone
and moves around based on
the iPhone's orientations.
The ball rolls around
and bounces off the walls
of the phone with audio
and haptic feedback,
just like you expect
in the physical world.
If you tap the ball...
it grows into a larger ball.
If you tap once more,
a shield gets added to the ball.
That shield gets damaged
and depleted with each collision
with the walls, and ultimately
the ball implodes and dies.
We also added a texture
to the background that you
enable or disable by tapping
anywhere on the background.
[bass bloop]
[bass thrumming]
For this session, I will
focus on only two mechanics:
adding the shield and enabling
the rolling texture.
Before I proceed further,
let's review the agenda.
I'll first review the key audio
and haptic design principles
we often use within Apple.
I will follow up with a brief
introduction to Core Haptics,
the framework that enables
rich multimodal feedback.
The core of the session
will examine
the HapticRicochet
project in Xcode
and see how one adds,
designs, and refines
feedback for the shield
and rolling texture moments.
Designing multimodal
experiences can be challenging,
but when done well, it truly
elevates the user experience.
It feels magical,
delightful, and just right.
One example
is the Flashlight button in iOS.
It combines visual animation,
sound, and haptic feedback
in a unified experience that is
clear, precise, and succinct.
It's an iterative
and creative process
that involves design
and engineering effort.
Normally you would feel the
haptics rather than hear them,
but for demonstration
purposes,
we've converted
these haptics to sound
so you can hear it
in this video.
To help achieve magic and
delight in your app experience,
here are three principles
to guide the work.
They have been useful
to us internally,
and I hope they can help you
as well.
They are causality,
harmony, and utility.
For feedback to be useful, it
must be obvious what caused it.
It's about making
the source or the cause
of the feedback
clear and obvious.
The simplest form
is getting feedback
as the ball hits the wall
and the boundary of the phone.
It's a collision with associated
sound and haptics.
Similarly, the haptics rolling
texture is only presented
when the background visual
is shown.
You understand that the grid is
what created that sensation.
Our second principle, harmony,
highlights that our senses
work best
when they are coherent,
consistent,
and working together
to create a given experience.
It should feel the way it
looks, and the way it sounds.
A small ball should feel
small and sound small.
A large ball ought
to sound and feel heavier,
like it has real extra mass.
Our third principle, utility,
is about providing
clear value
to your app experience.
Don't add feedback
just because you can.
It can quickly become
overwhelming and unpleasant.
Reserve haptics and audio
for significant moments
in your app,
like the growth of the ball.
Next,
let's review Core Haptics.
Core Haptics is the technology
on iPhone and iOS
that lets you design
custom haptics
and audio feedback for your app.
It's a powerful API
centered around
four fundamental elements:
engine, player,
pattern, and event.
Let's review them briefly.
The highest level element
is the engine.
That's our link to the physical
actuator on the phone.
Next we have a player.
It is used for playback control,
like start, stop, and pause.
Then we
have patterns and events.
Patterns are a collection
of events over time.
Events are the building blocks
used to specify the experience.
There are many types of events.
The most common ones
are transient and continuous.
Practically,
here's a concrete example
of a pattern made of events.
I'm using
the QuickLook Visualizer
available in MacOS 12
to see the haptic pattern
specified in an .ahap file.
AHAP stands
for Apple Haptic Audio Pattern.
Let's look at it again.
Select an .ahap file in Finder,
then press
Space bar on your keyboard.
Now let's look in detail at
the items in the pattern.
The first event in blue
is a transient event.
The second event in orange
is a continuous event.
The pattern is using
JSON syntax.
The transient event is
created from this code.
This sums up
our overview of Core Haptics.
For more in-depth information,
check out
the documentation online.
For the practice
in this session,
we'll focus on loading,
changing, and playing patterns.
It's time for Xcode
and the HapticRicochet.
Open the project from
HapticRicochet-Start folder.
Make sure you can compile and
run the project on your iPhone.
The simulator
doesn't work for haptics.
You need a physical iPhone 8
or newer to feel the haptics.
Verify that the phone
is not silenced
and that the volume level
is high.
The plan is to work
with ViewController files
and the .ahap, .wav
and .png asset files.
Make sure you familiarize
yourself
with the game and all
its interactions.
Remember, you can tap the ball,
tap the background,
and tilt the phone around.
[bass blooping]
[bass thrumming]
Once you're ready, let's dive
into the shield transformation.
I'll use the harmony
principle to dissect
the shield moment and look
at the design details.
For visual,
we have an animation
that is 500 milliseconds
in duration
and that looks like this
in the upper right.
For haptic,
we'll want to highlight
the transformation
to a new state.
For audio,
we want to convey a gain
in energy and an end state
that is robust and protected.
For this practice, we've
created two different assets
that convey
different qualities.
We'll look at them
and see what works best
for the shield experience.
But first,
let's look at how we load
and play feedback for shield.
Functionally, the code
is divided in two parts.
We first initialize our
building blocks and, second,
a function to play and render
that shield transformation.
In the initializeShieldHaptics
function,
I first create a pattern
from a ShieldTransient file.
Then create a shieldPlayer
with that pattern.
The feedback is ready to play
at this point.
The function shield is called
when the transformation
is ready to be rendered.
The haptic and audio
feedback are played via
calling startPlayer
on our shieldPlayer.
It's a convenience function we
reuse frequently in the project.
The visual animation
is then played.
Now let's look at our
ShieldTransient asset.
It defines the experience
we have
for haptic and audio feedback.
The haptic should feel
like this:
[staccato beats]
And the audio should sound like this:
[bass upswing]
I like the sound.
It feels
like a gain of robustness
and protection for the ball.
Let's hear it again.
[bass upswing]
The problem is
the haptic and the sound
don't really match.
The haptic is made
of three transients...
[staccato beats]
While the audio is
continuous and progressive.
[bass upswing]
There's no harmony
between the two senses.
[staccato beats]
[bass upswing]
Let's look
at the alternate asset
which is called
ShieldContinuous.
It has a continuous
haptic progression...
[tone]
And a wobbly audio that decays.
[off notes]
Again, I can feel and hear
that the haptic and audio
don't really match.
But I like the haptic.
It feels like
a good transformation
for gaining a shield.
Let's hear the haptic again.
[tone]
My plan is to use that
continuous haptic pattern
but use the sound
from the first asset.
I'll use the two assets and take
the audio I like
from the first pattern
and use it in the second
continuous haptic pattern.
Let's see
how I do that in practice.
First I open the
ShieldContinuous.ahap file
in a text editor and scroll
to the end of the file.
You'll see this event where
we specify the audio file
to play with the haptics.
It's using
the EventType AudioCustom
with a filename
for the audio file.
You can specify and adjust
the volume
using a ParameterValue.
To use the preferred audio,
I change
the file reference from
ShieldB.wav to ShieldA.wav.
The revised and final asset
looks like this.
The haptic...
[tone]
and audio are coherent.
They support and reinforce
each other.
Let's listen to the combined
audio and haptics together.
[tone upswings]
The last change needed is to use
that final asset I just created.
I go back to
InitializeShieldHaptics function
and instead
of using ShieldTransient,
I specify and load
the ShieldContinuous file.
Voilà!
Here we have it.
I now compile and run on device.
[tone, notes upswing]
I end up with a harmonious
shield transformation
that feels just right.
The haptic, audio, and visual
are working well together
to convey the addition of shield
protection to the ball.
Next, I'll review how to add
the rolling texture to the app.
HapticRicochet starts
with no rolling texture,
just collision with the walls.
If I tap on the background,
the polka dot texture shows up,
and I get additional
haptic feedback
as the ball rolls around.
We'll encounter and resolve
two issues moving forward,
one of a technical nature.
The other one relates to
the design of the experience.
In the initializeTextureHaptics
function,
I first create a pattern
from the texture ahap file.
I then create a ShieldPlayer
with that pattern.
The function
updateTexturePlayer
is called on every frame
the texture is active.
We use it to update
the intensity of the haptic
based on
the speed of the ball.
Let's look at the results.
The issue I'm noticing
is the texture goes away
after a few seconds.
[bass thrumming, blooping]
I know why it's happening
like this.
There's an easy way
to fix that behavior.
The issue we have
is that the texture
of the .ahap files has only
2 seconds of haptic content.
There's a way to change
that behavior
and make it play endlessly.
The advanced variant
of the pattern player
offers additional
functionalities
like pause, resume,
and other callbacks.
In HapticRicochet,
I will use the advanced
pattern player only for
its looping capabilities.
Let's walk through this change.
I first modify
the declaration of texturePlayer
to be of
CHHapticAdvancedPatternPlayer
type.
Then I'll use the same
texture file,
but this time,
creating an AdvancedPlayer.
I can now enable the looping
behavior on that AdvancedPlayer.
The nice thing is that the rest
of the code stays all the same.
Let's look at the results.
[blooping sounds,
bass thrumming in background]
The rolling texture plays
in a loop this time
with no apparent pause or seam.
[blooping, thrumming]
The second issue I want
to address is related to
the look and feel
of the texture.
We see that our haptic pattern
asset is quite dense,
with nearly 100 entries
over 2 seconds.
Our visual background
texture is very coarse,
with just a few dots across.
I think the experience
would be improved and more
realistic if the dot pattern
would be more dense.
I'll change
the resource file we used
for the backgroundImage to use
the Fine version of this file.
If I run the app, the new denser
texture will be used.
Let's take a look.
[blooping, continuous thrumming]
If you run into issues
or problems,
we've included
the final version of the project
in the HapticRicochet-Final
folder.
It has all the changes
we've made during this session,
ready to compile
and feel on your iPhone.
There is still room
for you to explore
and design your own
haptic experiences.
I invite you to look at
the other transformation
in the game and try
to design your own
new haptic and sound feedback
for them.
To recap,
I introduced audio and haptic
design principles that can
guide you to design
great multimodal experiences
in your app.
I reviewed the fundamentals
of Core Haptics,
the API to add custom
feedback in iOS.
I've put them in practice using
the HapticRicochet project,
focusing on the shield
and rolling texture mechanics.
For additional information
and resources, please refer
to the Human Interface Guideline,
and the Developer documentation.
Lastly, you can revisit
the WWDC 2019 session
covering
the launch of Core Haptics.
Thank you
for watching.
[percussive music]