[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Boris] Welcome to the session
"Discover and curate Swift Packages
using collections."
In Xcode 11, we introduced
support for Swift packages,
offering a straightforward approach
to distributing libraries as source code.
As more and more packages
are being published,
we want to make the discovery of packages
that fit particular use cases
more accessible.
When adding packages to their project,
developers would also like to see
more information, such as their license.
To do that, we want a standardized way
of accessing metadata.
This is why, in Xcode 13,
we are introducing Package collections,
curated lists of packages
that can be shared with others
and which drive a whole new
and improved experience
for adding packages to your projects.
Educators and community influencers
can publish package collections
to go along with course materials
or blog posts,
removing the barriers
when using packages for the first time,
and the burden of deciding
which packages are useful
for a particular task.
Enterprises can use collections
to narrow down the decision space
for their internal engineering teams,
focusing them on a trusted set
of vetted packages.
First, a quick overview of the talk.
We start with a demo,
then see how to use collections
in more detail.
We'll dive into creating
our own collections,
and finish off with another demo.
I found a blog post on Swift Numerics,
and I'm eager to try it out in Xcode.
I'm just going to copy
the first example from the post
and switch over to Xcode
to paste in the code.
We're getting a build failure
because the Numerics module
isn't present in my project.
Previously, I would have needed
to go back to the post
to figure out how to add
the Numerics package to my project,
but in Xcode 13, because we
are providing a default collection
of open-source packages,
get a fix-it right here in the editor.
Now, if I click “Search,"
I will be taken to the new
"Add Package" workflow,
with Numerics preselected.
We have a lot of information
about the package
right here in Xcode,
such as the latest version,
authors,
the license, as well as the README.
We can also switch
to the Release History tab
to see release notes
of all available versions.
For adding the dependency,
we can pick the version requirements
and the project to add to.
I'll accept the defaults for both
and click "Add Package."
Now, the package will be checked out,
and Xcode offers a selection of products
from the given version.
I will pick the Numerics product
and add it to my one target.
To finish, I'll click
"Add Package" once again.
If we take a look
at the project navigator,
we'll see the new dependency there.
And if we perform a build,
we see that the project
builds successfully now.
Let's take a quick look
at the exact changes
the "Add Package" workflow
made to the project.
For that, we'll open up
the project editor,
select the project,
and open the Swift Packages tab.
Here, we can see our dependency
and the version rule.
Now, if we open the target editor
to take a look
at the Frameworks, Libraries,
and Embedded Content phase,
we can see the Numerics product
being linked here.
This is the new
"Add Package" workflow in Xcode.
Now, how did Xcode know
about the Numerics package?
Xcode ships with a pre-configured
default collection,
which contains a set
of open-source packages
published by Apple,
such as Swift Argument Parser
and Swift NIO.
This makes the use of these projects
in Xcode much more seamless
by offering auto completion
of module names
and fix-its for adding packages
using the information from the collection.
This default collection
is being updated regularly,
so the exact list of packages can change.
Now, I'll let my colleague, Francesco,
tell you more about using collections.
[Francesco] Thank you, Boris.
Importing that package directly through
an import statement was effortless.
Let's take a closer look
at what a collection is.
Collections are a JSON file,
typically fetched via HTTPS.
A collection contains
a list of package URLs
and their metadata,
including a summary,
versions, and vended products.
This allows for rich information
to be displayed in Xcode.
This is a snippet
of the JSON of a collection.
You usually won't look at this in detail,
but let's take a look
at a few important fields.
We can see a package's URL,
the URL of its README,
a summary,
as well as more detailed information
about the versions of a package.
The Swift Package Manager,
which we often abbreviate today
as "SwiftPM,"
manages a database
for caching collections
on your Mac.
This means that you can access
your configured collections
from any tool that uses libSwiftPM,
not just Xcode,
including SwiftPM on the command line.
SwiftPM is part of the larger
Swift open source project.
The swift.org website is a great place,
where you can learn about the community
and the process to contribute.
SwiftPM offers
its functionality as a library,
including the support for collections.
We call the library libSwiftPM,
and it powers packages in Xcode, as well.
Boris and I are putting together
a blog post for our website.
We're going to create
a collection with the packages
we are using in the post,
so that our readers can follow along.
[Boris] Thanks, Francesco.
We like to use Alamofire
to make network requests,
so we add it to the collection.
Additionally, we also
want to keep the formatting
of our project consistent,
so we will also use swift-format.
Now that we know which packages
we want to have in the collection,
let's continue and create it.
For creating a collection,
we have published a tool on GitHub.
You can clone and build this locally
if you want to publish
your own collections.
The generator simplifies the process
of creating collections
by collecting information automatically
and always producing output
according to the latest version
of the format.
The tool takes an input JSON file,
which is a list of package URLs
with optional metadata,
and produces an output file
which will be shared with others.
There is also a separate tool
for signing collections
that is part of the same GitHub project.
Signing your collection is optional,
but allows verifying the author
and protects the integrity
of the collection.
This is how the input
JSON format looks like.
There's a bit of metadata
for the collection as a whole,
such as an overview, keywords,
and author information.
This will be displayed
when adding a collection in Xcode.
And most importantly,
a list of package URLs.
The tool will fetch information
about each package automatically,
but it is also possible to provide
additional metadata per package
when authoring the collection.
This includes metadata
that can improve search results,
such as a custom summary or keywords,
restricting the versions
that the collection will represent,
excluded products, which can be useful
to guide users to the most relevant
product a package vends,
and specifying a README URL.
Distributing a collection based
on the input JSON file
is a three-step process.
First, we use the generator
to create an output JSON file.
Then, we take the output
and a signing key plus certificate
to create a signed collection
with the sign tool.
And finally, we can distribute
the signed collection,
either by sharing it directly
or by putting it on a web server.
You can sign collections
with any valid, non-expired,
non-revoked code signing certificate.
For more information
about the requirements,
check out the SwiftPM documentation.
If you do not want to sign
your collection,
then proceed to distribution
after using the generate tool.
But for this collection that Francesco
and I are working on,
we're going to go ahead and sign it.
I have already prepared
the files for signing,
as well as the input JSON
that we saw on the slides earlier.
I also downloaded and built
the generator and signing tool.
We start by running
`package-collection-generate`
with the input JSON,
as well as an output path.
We are passing `--verbose`
to get more informational output,
and we are passing a GitHub auth-token
to query the GitHub API for more metadata.
We see that the command
checks out different versions
of the packages to collect information.
This should take a few seconds.
And then, it is done
and has generated an output file.
Next, we'd like to sign the collection.
We run the
`package-collection-sign` command,
pass in the JSON file
that we just generated,
specify the output path.
We also pass in the key and certificate
we exported earlier.
I've already uploaded
the generated collection to a server.
Let's see how to interact with it
using the command line.
SwiftPM brings a subcommand
called `package-collection` to do so.
To start, we add the collection
to our list of configured collections,
which will also make
it available in Xcode.
This fetches the collection and adds it.
Of course, you can also
do this in Xcode's UI,
which Francesco will show you later.
Next, let's take a look at the contents,
using `swift package-collection describe`.
First, there is the metadata
that we specified earlier.
We get the list of packages
in the collection,
and finally,
information about the signature.
This shows who has signed the collection,
as well as that the signature
has been verified by SwiftPM.
This can be used to determine
whether the given collection
was created by who you expect
and also protects the integrity
of the collection
from modification.
Next, let's take a look
at an individual package,
like swift-format.
For this, we use
the describe command again,
this time with a package URL.
In the output of this command
we see the information
about the entire package,
such as available versions,
authors, stars, and the README URL,
and also details about the latest version,
including the Swift tools
version being used,
as well as the modules and products.
Now that we verified
that our new collection looks good,
I'm going to send it
to my colleague, Francesco,
who will show you a bit more
of the Xcode experience
by putting together our demo app.
[Francesco] Thank you, Boris.
I just created a new project
for our demo app.
I can add our new collection to Xcode
by navigating to File > Add Packages
and clicking the + button
to add the collection.
Now, I can paste
the URL of the collection,
and after clicking "Load,"
Xcode tells me
how many packages it contains
and when it was last updated.
After adding the collection,
we can see its packages:
Alamofire and swift-format.
I want to use
a networking API from Alamofire,
so I'll add the package to my project.
I'll select the Alamofire product
and add it to my only target
by clicking "Add Package."
We see that Xcode added the dependency,
so we can now go back into our source file
and start writing some code.
Now that I've downloaded
the README using Alamofire,
I wanna parse the Markdown
using the swift-cmark package.
Let's go back to the "Add Packages" panel.
New in Xcode 13,
we added quick access to package options
through a context menu
on the project navigator.
From here, I can re-open the panel
by selecting "Add Packages."
I don't have swift-cmark
in any of my collections,
and I can still add it by pasting its URL
directly into the search bar.
I'm going to select the main branch
of swift-cmark
and add the package to my project.
Now that I've added swift-cmark,
we can finish our app for our blog post.
It's now this easy to use packages
from all over the internet
and focus on what matters most
to us: writing our apps.
Swift Package collections in Xcode 13
help with the discovery of new packages.
Creating your own collection
allows sharing curated lists of packages,
which streamlines
adding them to your projects.
To learn more about packages in general,
I would recommend the WWDC19 sessions,
"Adopting Swift Packages in Xcode"
and "Creating Swift Packages."
Thank you for watching.
[upbeat music]