[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Yagil] Hi, my name is Yagil Burowski,
and I'm an engineer on the Location
Technologies team at Apple.
In this talk, I'll cover
the latest advancements,
as well as the new features
that are coming
to the Nearby Interaction framework
this year.
The Nearby Interaction framework
makes it easy
to take advantage of the unique
capabilities of U1,
Apple's chip
for Ultra-Wideband technology,
and enables creating precise
and spatially-aware interactions
between nearby devices.
It's the same technology that powers
"Precision Finding" with AirTag
and the fluid handoff gestures
between iPhone and HomePod mini.
This is what we'll cover in this session.
We'll start with updates
to the user permission flow.
After that, we'll introduce new APIs
for running Nearby Interaction
with compatible third-party hardware.
And we'll finish with talking
about resources for app developers,
as well as accessory manufacturers,
for getting started with adopting
these new APIs
in apps and third-party accessories.
Before we dive in, for those of you
who are new to Nearby Interaction,
or just need a refresher,
let's quickly recap
how you use the framework
in your app.
You start with creating
a session instance.
That's the main object
through which you'll configure
and run your spatial interactions
with nearby devices.
Next, you'll need to designate
a part of your app
to conform
to the NISessionDelegate protocol.
The delegate will receive updates
from the framework.
The next thing you need to do is
create a configuration object,
which will be a subclass
of NIConfiguration.
For example, you can create
a NearbyPeerConfiguration
when you want start a session
between two iPhones
that are running your app.
Once you call run on the session
with the configuration you had created,
Nearby Interaction
will start providing your app
a stream of NearbyObject updates,
each containing distance
and, optionally, direction,
to nearby devices
that are actively participating
in the session.
If you're interested in a deeper dive
into the framework's APIs,
please watch last year's WWDC talk,
"Meet Nearby Interaction."
To access data such as distance
or direction to a nearby device,
your app needs to get
the user's permission.
So, let's talk about the improvements
to the user-permission flow
we've made this year.
This is the Nearby Interaction
permission flow in iOS 14.
The prompt will appear the first time
your app runs a session
in a new app lifetime.
The options on the alert,
"Don't Allow" or "Allow Once,"
provide a very clear choice,
but since this permission is one-time,
it can also lead to additional prompts
in certain situations.
So, this year, there's a new way
to grant apps permission
to use Nearby Interaction.
This is the new "Nearby Interaction"
permission prompt in iOS 15.
It looks kind of similar,
but it's different
in a couple of important ways.
The system will automatically show
the permission prompt
on the first time
your app runs an NISession.
So, it's really important
for you to make sure
that the timing
of when you run your NISession
coincides with a clear user intent,
so it's easy for your users to understand
why a particular feature in your app
requires access to Nearby Interaction.
Let's take a closer look
at the new options on the prompt.
The new "OK" option
grants your app permission
while the app is in use.
Whether the user accepts or denies
your app's request
to use Nearby Interaction,
the permission prompt will not show again.
Starting in iOS 15,
apps that use Nearby Interaction
will appear in Settings.
So, if users ever change their minds,
they can head over to the Settings app
and change your app's
"Nearby Interaction" access.
Make sure to test for this scenario
when developing your app.
Let's summarize the new
Nearby Interaction user permission model.
The new permission prompt,
when accepted,
gives your app persistent permission
to use Nearby Interaction
while the app is in use.
The alert will present
a usage description string,
provided by you
in your app's Info.plist.
In this purpose string,
be clear and concise,
and explain what are
the awesome features in your app
that need access to Nearby Interaction.
After the prompt shows
for the first and final time,
your app's name and icon
will appear in the Settings app,
which means that users can change
your app's permission state at any time.
When your app does not have sufficient
permission to use Nearby Interaction,
your NISessions will be invalidated
with a permission-related error code.
So, if a key functionality
in your app relies on access
to Nearby Interaction,
be sure to explain this clearly
to your users and guide them
to the Settings app when appropriate.
That was the new permission prompt
in iOS 15.
And now, we're excited
to introduce some new APIs
that make it possible
to use Nearby Interaction
with compatible third-party hardware.
We wanted this API to work
with a wide range of accessories
you may consider building.
So, we based Nearby Interaction's
third-party hardware support
on standards we've been working
on with industry groups.
And to help you get started
on prototyping, experimenting,
and building your accessories,
we've worked
with the chipset manufacturers,
who are making available development kits
containing hardware and firmware
that is able to interoperate
with U1 in iPhone.
So, alongside development kits,
we're also making available
sample app code
that works out-of-the-box
with the hardware in the development kits.
So, together, they can serve
as an excellent starting point
for your project.
And if you're an accessory manufacturer,
please check out the Nearby Interaction,
Accessory Protocol Specification document
that will be available
to you in "Developer Preview"
on the Apple developer website.
Whether you just want to tinker
with this exciting new technology,
or you're ready
to integrate Ultra Wideband
into your very own accessory,
let's look at a simple example
that illustrates how you use
the Nearby Interaction API
with a third-party accessory.
Enabling different functionality
based on the user's precise distance
to an accessory
can be a powerful way
to streamline interactions
with that device.
So, let's say that
you're building an accessory,
and you want to integrate
Ultra Wideband into it,
to enable a set of features
that will really make it stand out.
And since Ultra Wideband
can give you precise distance,
you're planning to utilize it
to keep track
of a couple of precise zones
or regions around the accessory.
So, let's say that you define a region
around the accessory
that has a 1.5-meter radius,
and another, larger one
with a 3-meter radius.
And let's say that you care
about these specific distances
because, when the user enters
the larger region around the accessory,
you want to enable some functionality A.
And when the user enters
the smaller region,
you want to enable functionality B.
So, how do you actually
achieve this in your app
using the Nearby Interaction framework?
First of all,
Nearby Interaction expects your app
and your accessory to have some sort
of capability to exchange data
between them.
As for the particular technology
to use to exchange data,
that is entirely up to you
and what your accessory does
and does not need to do.
Suppose your accessory
already supports Bluetooth.
This will put you in a great spot
because you'll be able to utilize your
existing Bluetooth capability
for your data exchange requirement.
If your accessory is connected
to the local network
or is securely connected to the internet,
you're in great shape, too.
That capability to send data
back and forth between the app
and the accessory will serve you
for what you'll need to do next.
Recall that when we wanted
to start a session
between two iPhones running your app,
we created a NearbyPeerConfiguration.
To start a session with an accessory,
we'll create
a NearbyAccessoryConfiguration.
This is a new NIConfiguration type
in iOS 15.
To instantiate an Accessory Configuration,
we need to provide it
some configuration data,
describing the accessory
that the framework expects to receive
in a particular format
called Accessory Configuration Data.
But how do we get this configuration data,
and what is this particular format?
U1-compatible Ultra-Wideband hardware,
like the types you'll be able to get
from certified technology providers,
will know how to generate
this configuration data
upon request.
This means that code you're running
on the accessory itself
will need to generate this data
and then send it over to your app
on your data channel.
Let's look at a code example
for instantiating
a NearbyAccessoryConfiguration
with data received from an accessory.
Let's assume that setupAccessory
is a helper method I wrote in my app.
Whenever I get
the Accessory Configuration Data
from an accessory,
there's logic in my app
that routes it to this function,
along with the accessory's name.
At this point, I can create
an NINearbyAccessoryConfiguration
using the data I received
from the accessory.
You'll notice
that I create my configuration
inside a do/catch statement.
I do this because if the data
I received from the accessory
is invalid in some way,
the NIConfiguration init method
will throw an exception.
But if the configuration object
is created successfully,
it means that the data I
received from the accessory is
in the right format and can now be used.
The ultimate reason
for creating a configuration
is for using it to run a session.
But before I do that,
there's a good opportunity for me
to cache some useful data for later use.
The new NearbyAccessoryConfiguration type
has a DiscoveryToken property
for the accessory
that the framework
automatically populates.
In addition,
in the setupAccessory function I defined,
I also have the accessory's name.
So, it could be really useful
to save the discovery token
alongside the accessory's name
at this stage
because, later on, when I start receiving
NearbyObject updates about this accessory,
I would be able to use the token
and the name
to correlate the updates back to this
accessory,
and then display more relevant
and rich UI.
Okay.
So, we have valid configuration data
from the accessory,
and we used it to create
an accessory configuration object.
Now, we can get ready
to interact with this accessory.
To manage the interaction,
we'll need an NISession instance,
and we'll need to set
the session's delegate.
To start the session, we simply call
the "run" function on the session,
using the accessory
configuration object we created.
Just like Nearby Interaction
needed configuration data
from the accessory,
the accessory also needs
configuration data from Nearby Interaction
in order to know how to configure itself.
This data needs to be in a format
called "Shareable Configuration Data."
When you run a session
with an accessory configuration,
Nearby Interaction will provide
the Shareable Configuration Data
to your app through a delegate callback.
And just like we used the data channel
to receive the accessory's
configuration data,
here, we'll use it again
to send the shareable configuration data
back to the accessory.
To make things more concrete,
let's look at a code example.
Shareable Configuration Data
is provided to your app
through the didGenerate delegate callback,
which is a new delegate callback
in iOS 15.
Here is a possible implementation
of this callback in an app.
The framework provides
the Shareable Configuration Data,
and also indicates
which accessory it should go to,
which is really useful
in case you're interacting
with multiple accessories.
You should plan to send the data
to the accessory
as soon as possible
over your data channel.
On a general note,
managing data connections
to different accessories can
take on many different forms,
all depending on your use case.
For simplicity,
let's say that in my app's architecture,
I chose to keep
an independent data connection
for each accessory I'm interacting with.
And to keep my code nicely organized,
I defined a helper function
that gives me back a connection
based on the NearbyObject I give it.
Once I get a reference to the connection,
I'll use it to send
the Shareable Configuration Data
to the accessory right away.
It's important to optimize your app
for sending the shareable
configuration data
to the accessory
with as little delay as possible.
If the ShareableConfigurationData
is not sent quickly enough,
your session may timeout.
A timeout in a session with an accessory
will be communicated to your app
through the didRemove delegate callback.
Let's look at how you might
handle this scenario.
When Nearby Interaction
gives me the didRemove callback,
shown on the screen,
I'll first check the "reason" parameter.
If the reason is .timeout,
and I have high confidence
that the accessory may still be nearby,
I can attempt to retry
to interact with it.
To decide whether or not I should go
into a "retry flow" with this accessory,
I defined a helper function
that contains specialized logic
that helps me make this decision.
You can imagine that conditions like
"How many times have I retried
without being successful?"
or "Has the accessory notified
me it has stopped?"
or other similar questions can be
a part of decisions like this.
If I do decide to retry,
all I have to do is run the session again
with the same configuration.
Keep in mind,
that the cached configuration
will only remain valid
as long as the session
on the accessory was not terminated.
If the session was terminated,
I'll have to go through the same flow
I used to create and run
the session the first time.
Keep in mind that sessions
on the accessory
is something the code running
on the accessory has to manage,
and can be done in many different ways,
all depending on your use case.
Okay.
You sent the Shareable Configuration Data
to your accessory,
and you even have logic
to handle retries if needed.
What's next?
Just like with the Accessory Configuration Data
U1-compatible hardware
in the accessory
will automatically know what to do
with the Shareable Configuration Data
once your accessory code
provides it to it.
So, once the code running on the accessory
receives the data,
it needs to provide it as-is,
and as quickly as possible,
to the Ultra-Wideband hardware on board.
You might be wondering--
how will the Ultra-Wideband hardware
in the accessory
know to generate
or consume the configuration data?
Both the Accessory Configuration Data
and the Shareable Configuration Data
are defined in a specification document
we published earlier this spring.
The document is intended
for chipset and module manufactures,
and it contains the necessary details
for creating Ultra-Wideband solutions
that use industry standards
to interoperate with U1 in iPhone.
On top
of the interoperability specification
for chipset manufacturers,
we are also releasing a specification
targeted at accessory manufacturers.
So, if you're hoping to build an accessory
that contains Ultra-Wideband hardware,
and you want to interact with it
using the Nearby Interaction framework
in your app,
this document is for you.
You'll find it on the developer website,
alongside additional resources
for getting started.
This is where we left off.
We had just sent
the Shareable Configuration Data
to the accessory over the data channel.
Now, let's see what happens
once the code
on the accessory receives it,
and provides it
to the Ultra-Wideband hardware.
After receiving
the shareable configuration data,
the Ultra-Wideband hardware
on the accessory
will immediately start running
in the appropriate configuration
for interacting with the NISession
in your app.
And if both the accessory
and the iPhone running your app
are nearby one another,
the session will start providing your app
a stream of NearbyObject updates,
containing distance and, optionally,
direction to the accessory.
You can even interact
with several accessories simultaneously,
by creating and running
a session for each one.
Depending on the hardware features
on the accessory,
you may also be able
to get equivalent proximity updates
in the code running on the accessory.
Once you get NearbyObject updates
from the framework,
what do you do with them?
As a reminder,
we wanted to build an experience
in which the app and the accessory
when the user enters the larger region,
and enable functionality B
when the user enters the smaller region
around the accessory.
Let's look at a code example
that shows how you could do this
using NearbyObject updates
in your iOS app.
When the session between the app
and the accessory is running,
updates about the accessory
are delivered to the session's delegate
through the didUpdate delegate callback.
First, I'll grab a reference
to the nearby object
for which the framework
is giving me an update.
Next, I'll create a local variable
with the distance to this object,
which the framework
is providing in meters.
The next thing I'll do
is provide this data
to a helper function I have in my app
I called getSmoothedDistance.
I defined this function in my app
to help me guard against rapid changes
in the distance.
For example, in cases where the user
makes sudden movements,
or they happen to be standing
on the boundary between the zones.
Lastly, I can check to see
if the user's distance from the accessory
crossed my predefined thresholds.
Here, I can choose to
enableFunctionalityA
or FunctionalityB based
on the current distance.
If you're interested in learning more
about designing experiences
based on distance and direction
between devices,
check out the "Design for Spatial
Interaction"
WWDC talk from this year.
So, let's summarize
what we discussed in this session.
We talked about how the new
permission model allows your app
to access Nearby Interaction
while the app is in use.
We took a deep dive into the brand-new
world
of Nearby Interaction-enabled
third-party accessories,
and what APIs you can use
to build spatial interactions
with your very own accessory.
We also discussed
third-party development kits,
available from supported
technology providers,
and iOS app code
that you can use to get started
with your project right away.
So, go on ahead, give it a try,
and start experimenting
and prototyping your use cases.
And when you're ready to adopt
Ultra Wideband in your accessory,
read the relevant specification documents,
available on the Apple developer website.
That's it for this year's
Nearby Interaction updates.
Thanks for tuning in.
We hope this session was helpful
and contained all the information you need
to get started with building some
amazing apps and accessories.
[upbeat music]