[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Alex Telek: Hi, I'm Alex.
I'm an engineer
on the Shazam team.
Thanks for joining this session.
Today, I'm going to show you
how to create
custom audio experiences
for your app with ShazamKit
using custom catalog
recognition.
On this session,
I'm going to use
some of the existing
ShazamKit concepts,
such as catalogs, signatures,
and media items.
If you're not already familiar
with those,
make sure to check out
the "Explore ShazamKit" talk.
Let's take a look at
what we will be covering today.
We will talk about
how to build catalogs
with custom audio and metadata.
We will learn how you can match
audio to your own custom catalog
when using the microphone
and the AVFAudio framework
to record audio.
Then we are going
to customize our app
to synchronize content
to the custom audio.
Finally, we will cover
some of the best practices
that you can use when working
with custom catalogs.
This is a code-along.
There is a project available
on the developer portal
that we will be using
throughout this session.
I recommend that you download
the project before we begin.
As learning becomes
increasingly more digital,
we need to come up with ways
to keep children engaged.
What if you could play a video
on your Apple TV
and have a companion app
that displays questions
at exactly the right time?
Today, I'm going to show you
how to build a remote app
that synchronizes and reacts
to an educational video
using custom catalog
recognition.
First, what are custom catalogs
exactly,
and how do we build one?
Custom catalog is a collection
of signatures that you generate
from any audio.
You can also add associated
metadata for each signature.
To add signatures
to your custom catalog,
you can use
the SignatureGenerator object.
It will convert audio buffers
into a signature.
First, create
a signature generator,
then using
the installTap function
on the audioEngine's inputNode,
append the buffer
and the audioTime
to the generator.
The buffer parameter
is a buffer of audio
captured from the output
of the inputNode.
audioTime is the time
when the buffer was captured.
When you specify the audioFormat
make sure that the format is PCM
in one of the supported
sample rates.
Calling the signature function
on the generator
will convert the audio buffers
into a signature.
We call this
the reference signature,
which we can then add
to a custom catalog.
You can also add signatures
to a catalog
by using a shazamsignature file.
This is an opaque file that
can be shared across devices.
To make it easier adopting
custom catalogs with ShazamKit,
for this session we included
this file for you to use.
Before we begin, let's open
the downloaded project
and see what we have in there.
Let's take a close look
at the Question object.
A Question represents
a custom content in the app.
First, there's a title
and an offset.
A title is a string describing
a section in the video.
Offset is the time
when this section appears.
For example, at 45 seconds,
the teacher starts talking
about a math equation.
You would create
a Question with that title
and 45 as the offset.
Equation represents
a teaching moment,
showing mathematical equations.
You can use this
as incremental building blocks.
For instance,
you might want to show
the left- and the right-hand
side of an equation
at different offsets.
Finally, answerRange
and requiresAnswer
are used to indicate when
an interactive UI would show,
so children can practice
answering the questions.
Let's take a look at
what this would look like
for our educational video.
The first question
starts at 14 seconds.
I have one red apple
at 21 seconds
and adding three green apples
at 25 seconds.
Finally, at 31 seconds,
the student will have a chance
to answer the question.
Note, that videos
are usually formatted in hours,
minutes and seconds,
so to create offsets
like I did here,
you should convert the time
into seconds first.
For example,
you could ask Siri for help,
like, "What's three minutes
and 14 seconds in seconds?"
Now, let's dive into the code
and see how we can get started
with custom catalogs!
First, I'm going to build
a catalog by adding a signature
with some metadata
associated to it.
Here, I have CatalogProvider
with a function
that creates the catalog.
The reference signature that you
are going to add to the catalog
is called
FoodMath.shazamsignature.
Let's load that file in
and create a signature object
from it.
Once you have that,
you define the metadata
using media items.
I'm going to set
some of the predefined
media item property keys,
such as title and subtitle.
This is going to describe
the educational video.
I also created an extension
on SHMediaItemProperty
with two custom keys:
teacher and episode.
Setting the episode number
and the name of the teacher
will further customize
the content of the catalog.
All you have to do now
is to create
a customCatalog object.
Then call
addReferenceSignature on it
and pass in the signature
and the mediaItem object.
This will associate the metadata
you just created
with the reference signature
you loaded from disk.
Perfect!
Now that I have that in place,
I can start matching audio
to the catalog
and see the result in action.
So let's open the Matcher.
We are going to match the input
audio from the microphone
to the content of the custom
catalog we just created.
To capture audio
from the microphone,
you can use
AVAudioEngine from AVFAudio.
In this project,
I already added a description
for the microphone usage
in the Info.plist file.
Also in the Matcher,
I included code
to request microphone permission
and set up the audio session.
First, to receive updates
on matches,
you create a session object
and set the delegate.
The match function takes
the custom catalog
we created before,
so you can just pass that
to the session.
Now, you're ready
to match the audio
using the installTap function
on the audioEngine's inputNode.
The function returns
an audioBuffer --
which is the converted audio
from the microphone --
and an audioTime --
which is the time
when the buffer was captured.
Then, you call
matchStreamingBuffer
on the session and pass in
the audio buffer
and the audio time.
We recommend that you include
the time when available
as this is going to be validated
by the session
to ensure that the provided
audio is contiguous.
Since you set the session
delegate at the beginning,
to handle updates,
you can implement
the session: didFind match:
function
from the session delegate.
For this, I created an object
called MatchResult.
It contains
a MatchedMediaItem,
returned by the session:
didFind match: function,
this is the metadata
that's associated
with the reference signature
in the catalog.
It will include details
we created earlier,
like the episode number
and the teacher's name.
It can be only generated
from a match,
and it contains extra
information related to that.
Also in the MatchResult,
we have the Question object
I showed you earlier.
This is representing
a section in the video
with a math equation.
We will use this to find
the relevant content
for a match.
So inside the delegate,
we set MatchResult
to take the first
MatchedMediaItem object,
and for now we, will set
nothing for the Question.
Now let's build and run
and see the match in action.
This is our FoodMath app,
it has a list of episodes that
are available for the students.
I can play the video and
together with my colleague Neil,
we can learn to solve
some math problems.
Neil, what do you have
for us today?
>> Neil: So the format is
I'll ask you a question,
you'll have some time
to think about it,
and then we'll see
if you got it right!
You can play along too
if you have our app. <<
[CLICK]
As I started the video,
the app recognized that we are
listening to episode three,
"Count on Me."
This is great!
Next, I want to figure out
what sections to show
for a particular offset
in the audio,
using our Question object.
We use MatchedMediaItem
to know what video
we are watching,
but it also contains
extra information about a match,
such as the
predictedCurrentMatchOffset.
This is an auto-updating
position
in the reference signature
represented as a time interval
in seconds.
You can use this to figure out
where you are in the video
and find the relevant
Question object.
Going back to the code,
in the delegate callback,
instead of setting nil,
I want to find the last Question
that comes right after
the
predicatedCurrentMatchOffset.
I can use the question's offset
to compare the values.
session:didFindMatch
can be called multiple times
with the same match.
So let's implement a filter
that will only update the result
when you get
a new Question object.
Once you have that,
you can update the result
with the value.
Now let's see how that looks;
build and run.
This time,
I want to learn about addition.
I'm going
to play the video again
and see if the content
of the question will show up
synced with the video.
>> Neil: Question one.
Let's get started.
I went to the shops today
and I fancied some apples,
so I bought one red apple;
and I bought one, two,
three green apples.
How many apples did I buy
in total?
Your timer starts... now. <<
Alex: Now it's question time.
What's one plus three?
Could it be five?
Oh. No, I got that one wrong.
Let's try again.
I'm going to rewind the video,
and this time
I'll pay more attention!
>> Neil: Question one.
Let's get started.
I went to the shops today
and I fancied some apples,
so I bought one red apple;
and I bought one, two,
three green apples.
How many apples did I buy
in total?
Your timer starts... now. <<
Alex: Now that I heard it again,
I know that the answer is four.
What if you find this question
too easy?
Let me skip forward and see
if Neil has something
a bit more complicated
to teach us.
>> Neil: Question four.
The last question.
So today,
I'm feeling pretty hungry.
So I've decided
I'm going to buy 14 apples.
One... two...
three... four -- <<
[CLICK]
Alex: That's a lot of apples.
Let me go ahead a bit more.
Skip ahead 20 seconds.
>> Neil: So I decided to buy
another 28 apples.
[SIGHS DEEPLY]
[THUD]
One... two... three...
four... five... six...
26... 27...
28 apples.
[THUDDING]
How many apples did I buy
in total?
[CLATTERING]
Your timer starts now. <<
Alex: Now,
that is a great question.
Did you follow?
I'm going to go
with my favorite number!
That is correct!
The answer
to the ultimate question is 42!
It's simple: no matter where
the student is in the video,
your remote app will keep up
and update the content.
Let's cover
some of the best practices
when using custom catalogs.
Custom catalogs can be shared
between devices seamlessly
using the shazamcatalog
file extension.
You can load from
and save to disk using a fileURL
as well as deliver them
over the network.
When using a remote web service,
you may want to download
the catalog first
and then use the add function
on the custom catalog object.
Make sure to provide
a local catalog
when there's no available one
over the network.
Catalogs can store custom keys
to return data
specific to your use case.
Make sure that the data you add
in your catalog
is one of the valid
property list values.
When using matchStreamingBuffer,
ShazamKit will match
the audio stream
and balance the performance
as well as the intensity
of the search,
doing all the work of generating
and auto-updating
the signature for you.
So now you built a full app
that's synchronized
to an educational video,
updating the content to where
the student currently is
using only a signature
and a custom catalog.
This is just one
of the many examples
that is possible,
and we are really excited
to see what you will build
using ShazamKit.
Thank you
and have a great WWDC.
♪