[upbeat music]
[Baek] Hello.
My name is Baek San Chang,
and I work on Core Audio.
Today I will discuss a new way
to create audio drivers
with DriverKit.
But first let's review
how audio drivers work today.
Prior to macOS Big Sur,
an audio server plug-in
would need
to communicate
with a hardware device
through a user client
to a kernel extension.
In macOS Big Sur,
the CoreAudio HAL
provided support
to create
an audio server plug-in built
on top of a DriverKit Extension.
The layer between the plug-in
and the dext was the same
as with a kext,
but security was improved
by moving out of the kernel
and into user space.
For more information
on DriverKit,
please check out the previous
WWDC DriverKit videos.
While the current solution
allows audio driver development
to move out of the kernel,
two separate components
are still needed
to implement a functional
hardware audio driver:
An audio server plug-in
and a driver extension.
This complicates development,
increases resources,
and can increase overhead
and latency.
Starting in macOS Monterey,
you only need a dext,
no more plug-in.
AudioDriverKit is a new
DriverKit framework used
to write audio driver extensions
alongside USBDriverKit
or PCIDriverKit.
This new framework handles all
the inter process communication
to the CoreAudio HAL.
Since you only have a dext,
now you don't need
to communicate between your dext
and an audio server plug-in.
You can stay
focused within DriverKit.
Since AudioDriverKit extensions
are bundled inside a Mac app,
a separate installer is
no longer necessary.
And now your driver
is loaded immediately,
no reboot required.
Now that you know the benefits
of AudioDriverKit,
let's dive into making
a new audio driver.
I will start
with a brief overview
of the components involved
in an audio driver,
then cover some things you'll
need before writing your dext.
Once we're ready
to start writing code,
I will walk
through how to configure
and initialize your dext,
create devices, streams,
and other audio objects,
and deal with the IO path
and timestamps.
Lastly, I will discuss how
to handle configuration changes
and show you a demo of the dext
at the end.
So let's
start with architecture.
The diagram shows
how the HAL communicates
with Driver Extensions using
the AudioDriverKit framework.
The AudioDriverKit framework
will create
a private user client
that will be used
for all the communication
between CoreAudio
and your audio dext.
This user client is not
intended to be used directly
and not exposed to your dext.
Notice that there is no plug-in
or custom user client required
to communicate
between your app and dext.
Optionally, your app can
open a custom user client
to communicate with
your dext directly if needed.
Now let's talk about
the entitlements you will need.
All DriverKit driver extensions
must have
the DriverKit entitlement.
AudioDriverKit dexts
must also have the entitlement
to allow any user client access.
This is available
to all developers
who have been approved
for any DriverKit entitlements.
Additionally, any transport
family entitlements should be
added as necessary.
If you have not yet
requested a USB
or PCI transport entitlement,
visit Apple's developer site
to submit a request.
Keep in mind that the sample
code presented is purely
for demonstration purposes and
creates a virtual audio driver
that is not associated
with a hardware device,
and so entitlements will not
be granted
for that kind of use case.
If a virtual audio driver
or device is all that is needed,
the audio server plug-in driver
model should continue
to be used.
Now let's look
at your dext's info.plist.
These settings need to be added
to the IOKitPersonalities
of the dext.
AudioDriverKit will
handle creation
of IOUserAudioDriverUserClient
required by the HAL.
The HAL has
the required entitlements
to connect to the user
client connection.
Here's an example
of a custom user client
for SimpleAudioDriverUserClient.
See the AudioDriverKitTypes.h
header file
for more information.
Next, let's talk
about configuration
and initialization.
The first step to configuring
an audio dext is
to subclass IOUserAudioDriver
and override
the virtual methods.
IOUserAudioDriver
is a subclass of IOService.
Subclass any IOUserAudio objects
that are needed
to implement custom behavior.
Then configure and add them
to IOUserAudioDriver.
The diagram shows an overview
of IOUserAudio objects
you will be creating.
SimpleAudioDriver is a subclass
of IOUserAudioDriver
and the entry
point into the dext.
SimpleAudioDriver will
create a SimpleAudioDevice,
which is a subclass
of IOUserAudioDevice.
The audio device handles all
start-stop IO-related messages,
timestamps,
and configuration changes.
SimpleAudioDevice will create
various IOUserAudioObjects.
The device object will also
create OSTimerDispatchSources,
OSActions,
and implement a tone generator
to simulate hardware interrupts
and IO.
IOUserAudioStream is a stream
owned by the device.
The stream will use
an IOMemoryDescriptor
for audio IO,
which will be mapped to the HAL.
IOUserAudioVolumeLevelControl
is a control object
that takes scalar or dB values.
The control value will
be used to apply gain
to the input audio buffer.
All IOUserAudioObjects can have
IOUserAudioCustomProperties.
SimpleAudioDevice will create
an example of a custom property
and a string as its qualifier
and data value.
Let's take a look at the code.
SimpleAudioDriver is a subclass
of IOUserAudioDriver.
Start, Stop, and NewUserClient
are virtual methods
from the IOService class that
the driver needs to override.
StartDevice and StopDevice
are IO-related virtual methods
from IOUserAudioDriver.
These will be called
when the HAL starts or stops IO
for an audio device.
I will discuss the IO
path after going over devices,
streams,
and other audio objects.
The example shows
how to override NewUserClient
to create
user client connections.
NewUserClient will be called
when a client process wants
to connect to the dext.
The AudioDriverKit framework
will handle creation
of the user client required
by the HAL
by calling NewUserClient
on the IOUserAudioDriver
base class.
This will create
the IOUserAudioDriverUserClient
that is needed by CoreAudio HAL.
A custom user client
can be created as well
by calling IOService Create,
which will
create the user client object
from the driver extensions
info.plist entry added earlier.
Let's take a look
at how to override Start
and create a custom
IOUserAudioDevice object.
First, call Start
on the super class.
Then allocate
the SimpleAudioDevice
and initialize it
with a few required parameters.
The initialized device
needs to then be added
to the audio driver
by calling AddObject.
Finally, register the service,
and the driver is ready to go.
Now that your driver
is initialized,
let's create a device, stream,
and a few other audio objects.
Subclass IOUserAudioDevice
to get custom behavior.
Let's create an input stream,
volume control,
and a custom property object.
The init method
for SimpleAudioDevice shows
how to configure the device and
create various audio objects.
The sample rate related
information of the device
is configured by calling
SetAvailableSampleRates
and SetSampleRate on the device.
Create
an IOBufferMemoryDescriptor
that will be passed
to the IOUserAudioStream.
The memory will be mapped
to CoreAudio HAL
and used for audio IO.
The memory should ideally
be the same IO memory used
for DMA to hardware.
IOUserAudioStream is
created by specifying it
with input stream direction
and passing in
the IO memory descriptor
that was created above.
A few additional things
need to be configured
on the stream
before it is functional.
The stream formats are defined
by creating a format list
of IOUserAudio
StreamBasicDescriptions.
Specify the sample rate,
format ID,
and the other required
format properties.
Set the available
formats by passing
in the stream format list
declared above.
And then set the current format
of the stream.
Finally,
add the configured stream
to the device
by calling AddStream.
Now let's go over creating
a volume level control.
To create
a volume control object,
call the
IOUserAudioLevelControl::Create
method.
The control is a settable
volume control
with initial level set to -6dB
and with a range of 96dB.
The element, scope,
and class of the control
also needs to be specified.
Finally, add the control object
to the device.
The volume control gain value
will be used in the IO path
by applying the gain
to the input stream's IO buffer.
Now let's go over creating
a custom property object
for the device.
A property address
needs to be provided
for every
custom property object.
Define a custom selector type
with a global scope
and main element.
Next, create
the custom property object
by providing the property
address defined above.
The custom property is settable,
and the qualifier and data value
types are both strings.
Now create an OSString for
the qualifier and data value.
Then set it
on the custom property.
Finally, add the custom property
to the device.
Now that you have created audio
objects, let's talk about IO.
The GetIOMemoryDescriptor
method will return
the IOMemoryDescriptor
used by the IOUserAudioStream.
The IOMemoryDescriptor
is passed into the init method
when creating a stream,
and the stream can be updated
with a new memory descriptor
as well.
The memory will be mapped
to the HAL
and used for audio IO.
The same memory descriptor
used by the stream should
ideally be the same one used
for DMA to the hardware device.
IOUserAudioClockDevice
is the base class
of IOUserAudioDevice.
UpdateCurrentZeroTimestamp and
GetCurrentZeroTimestamp should
be used to handle timestamps
from the hardware device.
The timestamps will be handled
atomically,
and the HAL will use
the sample time-host time pair
to run and synchronize IO.
It is vital to track
the hardware clock's timestamps
as close as possible.
Let's take a look
at the SimpleAudioDevice class
and focus
on the IO-related methods.
StartIO and StopIO will
be called from the driver
when the HAL is attempting
to run IO.
The private methods are shown
that use
IOTimerDispatchSource
and OSAction
to simulate hardware interrupts,
which will be used
to generate zero timestamps
and audio data
on the input IO buffer.
Since this example is
not running
against a hardware device,
timers and actions are used
in place of hardware interrupts
and DMA.
StartIO will be called
on the device object
when the HAL is attempting
to start IO on the device.
Any calls necessary to start IO
on the hardware should be done
here.
Afterwards, StartIO should
be called on the base class.
Next, get the input stream's
IOMemoryDescriptor
so an IOMemoryMap can be created
by calling CreateMapping.
The buffer address,
length, and offset
will be used
in the action occurred handler
to generate a tone
on the IO buffer.
StartTimers is called
to configure
and enable the time sources
and actions
to generate timestamps and fill
out the input audio buffer.
UpdateCurrentZeroTimestamp
is called
to atomically update
the sample time-host time pair
for the IOUserAudioDevice.
The timer source is enabled
and set with a wake-up time
based on mach_absolute_time
and host ticks configured
from the device.
The ZtsTimerOccurred action will
be called based on the wake time
so that a new timestamp
can be updated on the device.
Not shown here,
but the sample code also updates
the tone generation timer
and action in a similar way.
When the zero
timestamp action fires,
the last zero timestamp value
is obtained from the device
by calling
GetCurrentZeroTimestamp.
If this is the first timestamp,
use the mach_absolute_time
passed into the timer
as the anchor time.
Otherwise,
the timestamps are updated
by the zero timestamp period
and host ticks per buffer.
Calling
UpdateCurrentZeroTimestamp
will update
the device's timestamps
so that the HAL can
use the new values.
Set the ZTS timer
to wake up in the future
for the next zero timestamp.
To simulate DMA,
audio data will be written
to the input IO buffer
when the timer action runs.
First,
check if the input memory map
that was assigned when
start IO was called is valid.
Use the memory map buffer length
and stream format
to get the length in samples
for the IO buffer.
Since the stream only supports
signed 16 bit pcm sample format,
get the buffer address
and offset,
and assign it
as a int16_t buffer pointer.
Now the input IO buffer
can be filled out
by generating a sine tone.
First, get the input volume
control gain as a scalar value.
Then loop for the number
of samples needed
and generate a sine tone,
applying
the volume control gain.
Next, loop through the buffer
and fill in the sine tone sample
to the IO buffer based
on the channel count,
also accounting for wraparound.
Now that the audio dext
is configured and can run IO,
the next step is
to handle configuration changes
to update the device
and its IO-related state.
The device methods shown
can be used to request
and perform
configuration changes.
For changes
to an audio device's state
that will affect
IO or its structure,
the driver needs
to request a config change
by calling
RequestDeviceConfigurationChange
The HAL will
stop any running IO, and
PerformDeviceConfigurationChange
will be called on the driver.
Only then can the audio device
update its IO-related state.
A common scenario of this
would be
updating the audio device's
current sample rate
or changing
the current stream format
to correspond with changes
to the hardware device.
The diagram shows the sequence
of events
for device configuration
changes.
The driver should first
request a configuration change.
The HAL will
notify any listeners
that the config change
will begin for the device.
IO will be stopped on the device
if it is currently running.
The current state
of the device will be captured.
PerformDeviceConfigurationChange
will be called on the driver.
This is
when the driver is allowed
to change any state
on the device and hardware.
Once the config change is
performed,
the new state
of the device will be captured,
and all IO-related state,
such as IO buffers
or sample rate,
will be updated.
Any changes
to the device's state
will then be notified
to any client listeners.
If IO was previously running
prior to the config change,
IO will be restarted
on the device.
Finally, the HAL will
notify any listeners
that the config change has
now ended.
To simulate a hardware
bottom up config change request,
a custom user client command
is used
to trigger a sample rate change
on the dext.
RequestDeviceConfigurationChange
will notify the HAL
of a config change request
on the audio device.
Notice that the change info
can be any kind of OSObject.
This example provides
a custom config change action
and the change info
as an OSString.
To handle performing
the configuration change,
the SimpleAudioDevice class
needs
to override the method
PerformDeviceConfigurationChange
In
handle the config change action
in the switch statement.
Log the same OSString object
that was supplied
as the change info when
the config change was requested.
Next,
get the current sample rate,
and set a new rate
on the device.
Make sure the audio stream
updates
its current stream format
to handle the sample rate change
by calling
DeviceSampleRateChanged
on the stream object.
Other config change actions
the device does not
handle directly can
be passed off to the base class.
Let's take a look
at this on the Mac.
So SimpleAudio is
the sample code application
that bundles
the driver extension.
To install
the audio driver extension,
simply press Install Driver,
and that should bring
up the security preferences.
So if we press Allow,
that should dynamically
load the audio driver extension.
Previously,
this was not possible
with the kext because
a reboot would be required.
So SimpleAudioDevice has
the sample rate formats
available and
the tone selection data source.
And the volume control
we added in the sample code.
Now we can open QuickTime
and do audio recording
on the audio device.
[tone]
[different tone]
And to test
the bottom-up config changes,
we can directly communicate
with the dext
to toggle the tone frequency
or the sample rate,
and the changes should also
be reflected
in Audio MIDI setup.
To get rid
of the driver extension,
simply delete the application.
And you can see it is no longer
available in Audio MIDI setup.
To wrap things up,
I did a recap of the state
of audio server plug-ins
and DriverKit extensions.
This will continue
to be supported
and the AudioServerPlugIn driver
interface is not deprecated.
I introduced
the new AudioDriverKit framework
and discussed the benefits
of the new driver model.
I went over an in-depth example
of how to adopt
the AudioDriverKit framework
and showed sample code
to create an IOUserService based
audio dext,
all running in user space.
Download the latest
Xcode and DriverKit SDK.
Adopt AudioDriverKit
for audio devices
that have DriverKit supported
hardware device families.
And please
provide any feedback
about AudioDriverKit through
Apple's Feedback Assistant.
Thanks.
[upbeat music]