[music]
[John]
Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name’s John,
and I work on Core ML,
Apple’s machine learning
framework.
Together
with my colleague Brian,
we're excited to show you
how to tune up your models
as you bring the magic
of machine learning
to your apps.
To start things off,
I’m going to show you
some enhancements
to our machine learning APIs.
After that, we’ll dive
into file format improvements
that open up a range
of new possibilities.
Later on,
Brian will show us ML Programs
and take us under
the hood and walk us
through typed execution
and how you can use it
to fine-tune the accuracy
and performance of your models.
You can use these improvements
to streamline your workflow
and push your ML-powered
experiences even further.
Let’s start
with the API improvements.
Core ML provides you
with a simple API
to work with models
on your user’s device.
These models can be designed
to work with a variety
of inputs and outputs, such
as strings or primitive values
or more complex inputs
like images and MultiArrays.
Let’s talk more about
this last type, MultiArray.
Core ML makes it easy to work
with multidimensional
data using MLMultiArray.
While it’s a simple API,
the code you have to write
to manipulate data with it
doesn't always feel natural
in Swift.
For example, to initialize
a MultiArray with a bunch
of integers, you have to pass
in the type at runtime.
Plus you have to use NSNumber
instead of regular integers,
and that’s not type-safe
and doesn’t really look
like elegant Swift.
Core ML is introducing
MLShapedArray to make it easier
for you to work
with multidimensional data.
MLShapedArray is a pure
Swift type that’s similar
to a normal array but supports
multiple dimensions.
Like array, it’s a value type,
with copy-on-write semantics
and a rich slicing syntax
that works easily
with your existing
MLMultiArray code.
To initialize a two-dimensional
MLMultiArray,
you typically use two
nested “for” loops.
With an MLShapedArray,
you can initialize
the same 2D array
with a single line.
MLShapedArray fits naturally
in Swift and makes writing
and reviewing your code
that much easier.
Here’s another example.
To access the second row
as a slice,
you can just index
into it like this.
To access multiple rows
and columns as a slice,
you can use a range
for each dimension.
MLShapedArray and MLMultiArray
are fully compatible
with each other.
You can easily convert one type
into the other by using
the initializer that takes
an instance of the other type.
You can also convert data types
by using
the converting initializer.
For example,
this code converts a MultiArray
of doubles to a ShapedArray
of Floats.
Shaped arrays come in handy
anytime you need to work
with multidimensional data.
For example, the YOLO object
detection model finds objects
in an image, and then it
outputs a 2-dimensional array.
The table shows the data
from one prediction.
Each row
represents a bounding box,
and the values in each column
range between 0 and 1.
Each value represents
how confident the model is
that the bounding box
contains a person,
bicycle, or car, et cetera.
I want to write some code
to pick the most likely label
for each bounding box.
Here’s an example of how
to do that.
The code starts with the
output’s confidence property,
which is
a 2-dimensional MultiArray.
This function loops
through each row to find
the highest confidence score
in that row.
Notice it has to frequently cast
integers to NSNumber.
This code uses MLShapedArray
instead and does the same job
in fewer lines
that are easier to read.
Notice the model’s prediction
result gives us
a ShapedArray property that
contains the confidence values.
This code is simpler because
MLShapedArray and its scalars
conform to the standard
Swift collection protocols.
This provides a nice
strongly typed experience
that’s more readable
and a joy to work with in Swift.
Next up,
let’s talk about Core ML models
and how they’re represented
in the file system.
Core ML makes it easy
to build rich
machine learning-powered
experiences for your user.
An ML model is the engine
that brings these experiences
to life.
The .mlmodel file format encodes
and abstracts
the model’s functionality
so you don’t need to worry
about it.
The format stores all
the implementation details
and complexities of a model.
As a developer,
you don’t need to care
about whether it’s a tree
ensemble or a neural network
with millions of parameters.
An ML Model is just a single
file that you simply add
to an Xcode project
and write code that works
with it,
just like any other API.
Each Core ML model file consists
of several components.
The metadata stores information
such as the author, license,
version,
and a short description.
The interface defines
the model’s inputs and outputs.
The architecture defines
the model’s internal structure.
For example,
with a neural network,
the architecture section
describes the model's layers
and all the connections
between them.
Finally, the last section
stores the massive array
of values that the model learned
during the training phase.
An ML Model file encodes
all these sections
into a protobuf binary format,
which file systems
and source control software see
as a single binary file.
Source control software can’t
tell that the binary model file
is actually a combination
of several distinct components.
To solve that, Core ML is
adding a new model format
that breaks these components
into separate files,
using macOS’ built-in
package functionality.
Which brings us to the new
Core ML Model Package.
It’s a container that stores
each of a model’s components
in its own file,
separating out its architecture,
weights, and metadata.
By separating these components,
model packages allow
you to easily edit metadata
and track changes
with source control.
They also compile
more efficiently
and provide more flexibility
for tools
which read and write models.
Core ML and Xcode still
fully support
the original ML model format.
But you can move
to a more extensible format
and compile more efficiently
by updating to a model package.
Let’s try this out in Xcode.
Here’s a simple app that uses
an object detection model
to identify animals in an image.
Notice that some of the metadata
fields are empty.
It’s fairly common
to come across models
where the metadata isn’t
filled in.
In the past, you couldn’t
edit these fields in Xcode.
But now that Xcode supports
model packages, you can.
Right now the model’s
file type is ML Model,
but when I click on the Edit
button, Xcode prompts me
to update the ML Model file
to an ML Package.
Xcode tells me
that it’s about to update any
of my workspace’s references
to the original model file
to point at the new.mlpackage.
I’ll go ahead and click Update
and Edit.
Xcode’s UI
now indicates the model is
in the ML Package format.
Now I can fill in the missing
values directly in Xcode.
I’ll go ahead
and update the description
with the word “animals.”
Since this model came
from my coworker, Joseph,
I’ll put his name
in the Author field.
I’ll say MIT License
and version 2.0.
I can also add, modify,
and remove additional
metadata fields as well.
I’ll add a new metadata item
that indicates
which year we used
this model at WWDC.
So we’ll say 2021.
Now, in addition
to the UI support,
all of this information is
also accessible using
Core ML’s MLModelDescription API
at runtime.
I can also modify
the description
of the model's Inputs and
Outputs in the Predictions tab.
Here I’ll change the description
of this Input.
We'll add "of an animal."
And down here, I’ll fix a typo
by adding a missing hyphen.
Now, a model with good
metadata is a lot like code
with good comments.
It helps you and your team
understand the model's intent,
and so it’s particularly
important
to make sure
you write good descriptions
for your model’s inputs
and outputs.
I’ll click Done
to save the changes.
Now if I click on Source Control
and then Commit,
Xcode shows
the changes in a diff view.
The metadata is now
in its own.json file,
which makes it easy
to verify my changes.
Similarly,
the Feature Descriptions
have their own
separate.json file.
If we had changed a few bytes
of a 62-megabyte binary
ML Model file,
we’d have
a 62-megabyte binary diff.
Model packages, however,
are much more efficient and easy
to work with, especially
for small text changes.
Xcode supports
both model packages
and model files equally.
For example,
I can use the Preview tab
to test out my model package.
If I bring in an image
of two bears, we’ll see
that we get two bounding boxes,
one for each bear.
Similarly, I can go
to the Utilities tab,
where I can generate
an encryption key
or an ML archive
for a model package the same
as I would for an ML model file.
So that’s model packages
in Xcode.
Packages can do everything
a model file can and more,
such as editing model metadata.
The last thing I want
to show is the code
that Xcode
automatically generates
for each model you add
to a project.
I’m going to click on this icon
to see the generated code.
Earlier,
we took a look at MLMultiArray
and its new Swift counterpart,
MLShapedArray.
Xcode now adds a new
shaped array property
for each MultiArray output
in the wrapper class.
For example,
the generated class now has
a confidenceShapedArray property
for the model’s output.
You can still use the original
confidence MLMultiArray property
if you like.
Note that your project’s
deployment target must be one
of these OS versions,
for example, macOS 12 or iOS 15,
to take advantage of the new
shaped array property.
Now that we’ve seen
all this in action,
let’s take a look at ML Model
and ML Package side by side.
ML Packages support all the same
types that ML Model files
support, including trees, SVMs,
neural networks, and so on.
In addition to these types,
ML Packages also support
a powerful new model type
called ML Program.
ML Program is a model type
that represents neural networks
in a more code-oriented format.
To tell you more
about ML Programs
and the new features
they enable,
I’ll hand it over to Brian.
[Brian]
Thanks, John.
My name is Brian Keene,
and I’m excited to talk
about ML Programs and how typed
execution gives you more control
over accuracy
and better model performance.
There are various ways
a machine learning model
may have been presented to you.
If you’re taking
a machine learning course
or reading a paper, you may
encounter a model described
with respect to its mathematical
or statistical formulation.
However, these mathematical
expressions are often abstracted
and alternatively presented
to you in the form
of a computation graph
or network.
This graphical representation
as depicted
in the middle two figures,
describes how data flows
through a series of layers,
each of which applies
their own specific transform.
In a machine learning
software library,
the model is instead expressed
as operations in code.
Machine learning engineers
are increasingly leveraging
this more generic program
structure
composed of blocks,
functions, and control flow.
The new ML Program model type
in Core ML aligns itself
with this last representation.
This is
a representative ML Program.
It’s in a human readable
text format, although
the intention is that you don’t
have to write it yourself.
The ML Program will be
generated automatically
by Core ML’s converter.
An ML program consists
of a main function.
This main function
consists of a sequence
of operations, or ops.
Each op produces a variable,
and this variable is
strongly typed.
For operations that have
weights, such as the linear
or convolution ops,
the weights are typically
serialized
into a separate binary file.
This is a brief summary
of how ML Programs
compare to Neural Networks.
Neural networks have layers,
while ML Programs have ops.
Weights in neural network
models are embedded
in their layer descriptions,
while ML Programs serialize
the weights separately.
And neural networks don’t
specify
the intermediate tensor types.
Instead,
the compute unit determines
these types at runtime.
ML Programs, on the other hand,
have strongly typed tensors.
Today I’ll focus on ML Program’s
strongly typed syntax
and the implications that typed
intermediate tensors have
for on-device machine
learning with ML Programs.
But first,
how do you get an ML Program?
Core ML previously introduced
a unified converter API.
This unified converter API
provides a convenient means
to get your model
from Tensorflow
or PyTorch to the Core ML
neural network model
with a single function call.
You can now use the same API
to convert
to an ML Program
by selecting iOS 15
as the minimum
deployment target.
Under the hood,
the Core ML converter
selects
an on-disk representation
for the model
at conversion time.
For ML Programs, the on-disk
intermediate representation is
provided
by Model Intermediate Language,
a feature
introduced at WWDC 2020.
The unified converter
API is where you can opt-in
to deploy your model
as an ML Program.
Moving forward,
ML Program will be
the favored format
over neural network.
And ML Program is available
beginning
with iOS15 and macOS Monterey.
Core ML supports both ML Model
and ML Package formats
for neural networks models,
but ML Program must be
an ML Package to store
its weights separately
from the architecture.
Core ML
is investing in ML Program
as a foundation for the future.
There will be continued support
for neural networks,
but ML Program will be
central to new features.
So if ML Program is the future,
what are the benefits
of adopting ML Program today?
This brings us
to typed execution.
To highlight the benefits
of typed execution
with ML Programs,
let’s first discuss what happens
with neural networks.
Shown here is an example input
and output
to a Core ML Neural Network
model that specifies Float32
for the input
and output tensors.
Inputs and outputs can also be
double or 32-bit integer types.
So the neural network model
strongly types
these input and output tensors.
What about the types
of the intermediate tensors?
A neural network doesn’t
strongly
type its intermediate tensors.
There is no information
about the types
of these tensors
in the on-disk model.
Instead, the compute unit
that runs the model
infers the tensor’s types
after Core ML loads the model.
When the Core ML runtime
loads a neural network,
it automatically and dynamically
partitions the network graph
into sections:
Apple Neural Engine friendly,
GPU friendly, and CPU.
Each compute unit
executes its section
of the network using
its native type to maximize
its performance and the model’s
overall performance.
The GPU and the Neural Engine
both use Float16,
and CPU uses Float32.
As the developer,
you have some control
over this execution scheme
by selecting .all, .cpuAndGPU,
or .cpuOnly with the model’s
computeUnits property.
This property defaults to .all,
which instructs Core ML
to partition the model
across the neural engine,
GPU, and CPU at runtime
to give your app
the best performance possible.
And if you set it to cpuOnly,
Core ML will not use either
the Neural Engine or the GPU,
which ensures your model is only
executing the Float32 precision
on the CPU.
To summarize, neural networks
have intermediate tensors,
which are automatically typed
at runtime
by the compute unit responsible
for producing them.
You do have some control
of their precision
by configuring the set
of allowed compute units,
but doing so is a global setting
for the model
and may leave some
performance on the table.
What about ML Program?
In the ML Program depicted here,
the input and output
tensors are strongly typed,
and so is every intermediate
tensor of the program.
You can even mix
and match precision support
within a single compute unit,
say, the CPU or GPU,
and these types are well defined
at the time of model conversion.
That’s long before you would use
Core ML to load
and run the model
in a deployment scenario.
ML Programs use the same
automatic partioning scheme
that distributes work
to the Neural Engine,
GPU, and CPU.
However,
it adds a type constraint.
Core ML retains the ability
to promote a tensor
to a higher precision,
but the Core ML runtime
never casts intermediate tensors
to a lower precision
than that specified
in the ML Program.
This new support
for typed execution
has been made possible
via expanded op support
on both GPU and CPU,
particularly for Float32 ops
on GPU
and selected ops in Float16
on CPU.
With this expanded support,
you can still
see the performance
benefits of the GPU
when your ML Program
specifies Float32 precision.
Let’s try out
the unified converter API
to produce ML Programs
with different precisions.
OK,
I’m now in a Jupyter notebook,
which is a convenient tool
for executing Python code
in an interactive way.
I’ll go over the process
of converting a model
to the new ML Program format.
The model I’m going to use today
is a style transfer model.
I’ve already downloaded
a pretrained Tensorflow model
from Open Source.
This model takes in an image
and produces a stylized image.
The first thing needed is
a few import statements.
I’ll import coremltools,
the Python image library,
as well
as a couple helper libraries
and simple helper functions
that I’ve written
to keep the code
I use here succinct.
Now I’ll specify the path
of the style transfer model
and the path to the image
I’m going to stylize.
I’m going to also set up
the input types
for the conversion.
In this case, it’ll be an image
input type which specifies
the dimensions of the image
on which the model was trained.
Finally,
there’s some additional setup
to prepare the input
dictionary that I can use
to run the Core ML model
post conversion.
So the input has been loaded,
and the source model is
available.
At this point, all of the
external resources are ready
for conversion to an ML Program.
For conversion, I’ll use
the Unified Converter API.
The first argument is
the source model path.
Next, pass the array
of input types.
Here, there’s just the one.
Finally, the minimum
deployment target argument
will determine if Core ML Tools
produces a neural network
or an ML Program.
It defaults to iOS 13
and produces a neural network.
Right now I want
to get an ML Program,
so I’ll set the deployment
target to iOS 15.
I want to eventually
deploy this model on an iOS app.
I could have alternatively
specified a deployment target
of macOS 12,
if my target device was a Mac.
I’ll press Shift-Enter
to convert the model.
And conversion has completed.
There is a graph transform
that happens automatically
for ML Programs
during conversion.
It’s called
the FP16ComputePrecision pass.
This graph pass
casts every Float32 tensor
in the original Tensorflow graph
to a Float16 tensor
in the ML program.
OK, now since the conversion
is done, the next step is
to check the correctness
of the ML program.
I can compare
the output numerics
with the original Tensorflow
model by calling prediction
with the same image
with both the models.
It’s worth noting
for ML Programs,
I’m using exactly
the same Core ML Tools APIs
as in previous
years for prediction,
model saving,
and other utilities.
To do the comparison,
I have already written
a utility method called
_get_coreml_tensorflow_output.
It will print out multiple
error metrics to evaluate
the output from Tensorflow
and the output from Core ML.
So since this is an image,
the most appropriate
error metric may be
the signal to noise ratio,
or SNR.
In practice,
an SNR above 20 or 30 is
usually indicative
of good results.
Here I have an SNR of 71,
and that’s pretty great.
There’s a couple other metrics:
max absolute error,
average absolute error.
I’m curious, though,
what’s the accuracy cost
of using Float16?
What have I lost?
To find out,
I can disable the Float16
transform and convert again.
I’ll use the same convert
command, but this time
I’ll specify a compute_precision
argument and set it to Float32.
This will tell the converter
to not inject
those Float16 casts,
and so the Core ML Tools
converter will produce
a Float32 ML Program.
OK, now I’ll compare
this Float32 ML Program
to the original Tensorflow one.
And the SNR has increased
to over 100,
and the maximum absolute error
has decreased
from about 1 down to 0.02.
I still haven’t answered whether
the error I got earlier
with the Float16 model
had any discernible impact.
This is a style transfer model,
so the verdict could be made
based on a simple plot
of the output image.
I’ll plot the source image
and the stylized versions
from all three models that
I have: the Float16 ML Program,
the Float32 ML program,
and the Tensorflow model.
And I really don’t see
any difference
between the three model outputs.
Of course, this evaluation
of a single image,
once with a couple of metrics
and a visual inspection
is really just a smoke test.
Things look OK.
In practice, I’d evaluate
with more error metrics
across a large dataset,
evaluate failure cases
within the pipeline used
by the machine learning model,
and triage those.
I have a small dataset handy,
and to go one step further
with this example,
I can compare
the two ML Programs
with the Tensorflow model for
each image within the dataset.
The SNR of the Float32 ML
program versus Tensorflow
is depicted as a red line
with Xs,
and the Float16 ML Program
is a blue line with circles.
The Float32 ML Program seems
to average an SNR around 100,
and the Float16 ML Program stays
around 70.
The Float16 precision does
affect the numerics
a little bit,
but it doesn't seem significant
for this use case.
Although, even in this small
dataset of 131 images,
there are a few outliers.
Overall,
the model is doing pretty well
what it’s expected to do.
And this is the case
for a majority
of deep learning models.
They typically tend
to work just fine,
even with Float16 precision.
That’s why we have turned
the Float16 transform on
by default
in the Core ML converter.
A Float16 typed ML program
will be available to execute
on the neural engine,
which can present a substantial
performance boost and reduction
in power consumption.
Since the runtime treats
the types of the tensors
as a minimum precision during
execution, a Float32 ML Program
will execute on a combination
of only the GPU and the CPU.
This demo demonstrated
how easy it is now
to control the minimum precision
in which the ML Program
will execute right
at conversion time.
And unlike neural network
Core ML models, if your model
needs higher precision, you do
not have to change the setting
of the compute unit to cpuOnly
in the app code to achieve that.
And as a final note,
this demo notebook will be
available as an example
on the Core ML Tools
documentation site.
To recap, to get an ML program,
use the convert function
and pass an additional argument
to specify
the deployment target,
and set it
to at least iOS 15 or macOS 12.
By default,
the Core ML converter
will produce
an optimized Float16 model
that is eligible for execution
on the neural engine.
If, as it might happen
in some cases,
the model is sensitive
to Float16 precision,
it’s simple to set the precision
to Float32 instead.
There are, in fact,
more advanced options available
in the Core ML Tools API,
using which you can select
specific ops to execute
in Float32 while keeping
the rest in Float16 to produce
a mixed type ML Program.
Please check
out our documentation
for these examples.
In summary, Core ML has
several new enhancements
that make it easier to tune
and work with your models.
The new MLShapedArray type
makes it easy to work
with multidimensional data.
The ML Package format allows you
to edit metadata directly
in Xcode.
An ML Package with the new
ML Program model type
supports typed execution
with Float32 support on GPU,
giving you more options
to play with
as you tune your model’s
performance and accuracy.
We encourage you
to upgrade your model
to ML Packages
and use ML Programs.
Thanks for watching our session,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[music]