[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Brian]
Hello and welcome.
I’m Brian Goldberg, an engineer
on the App Clips team.
I can’t wait to show you
some great tips
and techniques to build
light and fast App Clips.
Let’s get started.
App Clips are a great
way for your customers
to quickly access and experience
what your app has to offer.
An App Clip is a small
part of your app
that’s discoverable
and downloaded
at the moment it’s needed.
App Clips are deeply integrated
into the OS.
They can be invoked in Safari
and Messages
as well as out in the real world
by scanning an App Clip Code,
a QR code,
or by tapping an NFC tag.
App Clips are also surfaced
in Maps and Siri suggestions.
This session is loaded
with best practices
and troubleshooting tips
that will help you build
and deliver great experiences
for your customers.
I’ll show you a plan for getting
your clip under the size limit.
Maybe your App Clip isn’t being
surfaced on your web page
or the App Clip card does
not appear when you scan a code.
Perhaps you’re looking
for some tips on maintaining
quality in your code base,
while taking on
the added complexity that comes
with adopting new features.
And maybe you’re curious to know
what functionality
you can leverage that’s specific
and unique to App Clips.
Whether you’re
building from scratch
or adding a clip target
to an existing app,
I’ll walk you through real-world
issues developers face
on a daily basis,
and I’ll give you
actionable next steps
for building better clips
and apps.
Even when your users
are in areas
with good mobile
network coverage,
their download speeds can vary.
To ensure that App Clips
can be provided on demand
at a moment’s notice,
the maximum size
of an App Clip is limited.
Therefore, as a developer,
it’s important to optimize
your content for size.
It’s good to know early on
and often during development
if your clip is compact enough
to be delivered on-demand.
Many of you are familiar
with the iterative process
of profiling and optimization
in software development.
I’d like to show you a process
where you
can use Xcode
to generate a size report
and export an IPA
for each device variant.
Then I'll walk you
through a set
of basic
and advanced optimizations
you can perform to reduce
the size of your App Clip.
The goal is to avoid
being surprised
at app submission time
if your clip
is over the limit.
I put together
a fun example for us to look at.
It’s a version
of the Fruta sample
that has a number of gotchas
that put it over the size limit.
The gotchas are simple
to illustrate some key points.
Your apps are undoubtedly
more complicated
and have tons more features,
so please use my example
as a starting point
for further exploration.
Let’s start by launching
into Xcode
to go through the steps
to generate the size report
and export the IPA files,
and we’ll uncover these gotchas
and learn
how to fix them together.
First select
the full app scheme.
Then go to the Product menu
and choose Archive.
This builds the project
using the configuration
specified in the scheme editor.
When the organizer opens,
click Distribute App.
Choose Development.
Now select your App Clip.
In the App Thinning dropdown,
choose
all compatible device variants.
Make sure that rebuild
from bitcode is checked.
When the archive
is done preparing, click Export.
Then select a location
on the file system to export to.
Now open
the Export folder in Finder...
And then open the App Thinning
Size Report.txt.
There’s a section
for each device variant.
The second to the last line
in each section
will tell us
the uncompressed size
for that variant.
That’s what we’re interested in.
Looking at the size,
this tells me two things.
One, I’m over the size limit.
Two, I’m not seeing the effects
of app thinning
because all the device variants
are around the same size.
Let’s close the size report
and dig a bit deeper
to see why that is.
Open the Apps subfolder.
Rename one of the variant
IPAs extension to .zip,
and confirm.
Double-click to uncompress.
Open the Payload folder
and Control-click to show
the package contents.
Let’s look closely.
Looks like my images
are individual bundle resources.
Perhaps I’ll save some space
if I put these
in an asset catalog.
I see a documentation zip
and a README file
that don’t belong here
in the installable product.
There’s a framework
being used by my clip.
I bet that’s taking up
some space too.
I see some
localization folders present,
and I know that sometimes
these files
can grow if left unchecked.
The compiled executable
is relatively small...
but maybe there’s a way
to get it even smaller.
Every little bit helps.
Let’s continue on and see
what can be done
to fix some of these issues.
That process
of generating a size report
and looking through the IPA
was very helpful
because it identified
a number of steps
I can take
to reduce the App Clip size.
Let’s start
with some basic steps first,
and then we’ll move on
to more advanced techniques.
We’ll double-check
the build settings,
we’ll go over the benefits
of using asset catalogs,
we’ll exclude any files
from making their way
to the final product
that don’t belong,
and we’ll go through our code
and settings and refactor
for size reduction.
Keep in mind the optimizations
we’ll cover apply
to both your app and App Clip,
so feel free to apply
these tips
to both types of products.
Now let’s explore each
topic in more detail.
The compiled code portion
of the App Clip package
certainly wasn’t the largest
contributor to the clip’s size.
It was definitely the assets,
which we’ll get to in a moment.
But every little bit helps.
By default, Xcode will build
using the smallest,
fastest optimization setting,
but let’s double-check
to make sure that’s what’s
set in my project.
Make sure the full app
is set as the active scheme
and Option-click to display
the scheme settings.
Our archive build
should be set to release,
but it looks like I changed it
at some point
and forgot to change it back.
I was also experimenting a bit
in build settings
and moved
the release optimization level
off of the default.
Let’s change it back
so that we’re using
the best combination
of small binary size
and fast runtime execution.
Most of the time, as in my case,
assets like images,
audio, and video
take up the most space.
The most important step
you can take
to reduce the impact
these assets
have on your App Clip size
is to use asset catalogs,
and this is for two reasons.
One, the media you add
to asset catalogs
is automatically optimized
as part
of the Xcode build process.
And two, when customers
download your app or clip,
the product they download
will be made small enough
to only contain assets
suitable for their device.
This is also
known as app thinning,
and we should certainly
take advantage of it.
In my project,
I really should have put
those images
in an asset catalog.
We can actually do even better.
I’ll create
a second asset catalog,
and I’ll move all the images
that are shared
between my app
and App Clip into this catalog.
Let’s bring both catalogs
side by side.
We’ll move the icons and colors
into the shared catalog.
Then we’ll put the ingredient
and smoothie images
into the shared catalog.
Since the recipe images
are only needed by the full app,
I’ll put those
in the unshared catalog
so they don’t count
against the size of my App Clip.
I’ll make sure to remove
those images that I copied
over to the asset library.
And last, I’ll use
the target membership editor
to exclude
the unshared asset catalog
from my App Clip.
For a deep dive
on the asset catalog,
check out the sessions on
optimizing storage in your app
and optimizing app assets.
Earlier, we inspected
the IPA on the file system,
and we saw a few things
that didn’t belong
like a README file
and a zip
containing documentation.
Let’s go ahead and use
the target membership editor
in Xcode to exclude these files
from all of our build products.
Ensure you’re
only including code
in your App Clip target
that’s necessary
for the task being performed.
I find it helpful to look
in the build phases
to get an overview
of every source file
that is contributing
to my App Clip.
If I see something
that looks unnecessary,
I remove it from the list
of sources and rebuild.
The recipe and rewards
functionality of Fruta
are necessary
for the full app
but not the App Clip,
so let’s remove those files.
You can even
let the compiler assist.
If there are build errors,
either the file
was necessary,
there’s more to remove,
or perhaps there’s code
that needs
to be conditionally compiled
out of the App Clip target.
Over time,
localized strings files
can become inflated
with duplicates
and unused strings.
Inspect the strings files
and delete anything
that’s not needed.
Similar to what we did
for asset catalogs,
you can create
a dedicated strings file
so that you aren’t including
your full app’s
localized strings
with your App Clip.
I’ve covered
some basic optimizations
you can implement today
to get your App Clip
ready for submission.
Now suppose, as part
of this iterative process,
you measure again,
you look at the size report,
and you still aren’t
where you need to be.
That’s OK.
I have several
advanced optimization strategies
for you to consider.
First, evaluate
your external dependencies
and take their size
into consideration.
Remember, App Clips
are bite-sized versions
of your app, so make sure
you are only linking
what's needed
for your clip’s functionality.
Remember that
SmoothieAccountLogin framework
that was adding
to my App Clip’s size?
Most of the time,
there’s an Apple framework
already integrated
into the OS
that will help you
accomplish your goal.
Using one of these
built-in frameworks is free,
and it’ll make your app
and App Clip lighter and faster,
which means it’ll
download faster, launch faster,
and allow your customers
to complete the task
at hand faster.
Use Sign in with Apple
to make it easy for users
to sign in to your service
with just their Apple ID.
For payments, Apple Pay
is fast and easy both for you,
the developer,
and for your customers.
For communication
over the network,
use NSURLSession.
For 3D graphics,
leverage RealityKit and Metal.
For more in-depth
authentication flows,
check out
ASWebAuthenticationSession.
It’s almost always the assets
and not the code
that pushes the size
of an App Clip over the limit.
More often than not,
those assets are images.
In the basic steps, I moved
all my images to asset catalogs
to take advantage
of built-in optimization
and app thinning.
Sometimes that’s not enough
and you need to take
further action to reduce
the size of your images.
The format and options you use
when saving the source image
can often have a profound effect
both on size and quality.
So how do you
make the best choice?
Generally speaking,
a PNG image will consume
more space than a JPEG image,
so use PNG
if you need a specific feature
that format provides
like transparency...
Or when JPEG's lossy compression
would result
in an unacceptable loss
of quality.
These examples contain
high-frequency features,
crisp edges,
and defined highlights.
The lossless compression
of PNG
will preserve these features
much better than JPEG.
And while we’re
on the subject of PNG,
consider PNG8
for non-photographic material.
The image on the right
was saved out as PNG8
for a huge
reduction in file size.
When you export your images,
do a side-by-side comparison
to make sure
your optimizations hold up.
A reduction in color depth
can save a lot of space
but is only appropriate
for certain imagery
that won’t suffer
from quantization artifacts.
For photographic material,
when you need to save space,
use JPEG and lean a bit
on lossy compression.
You don’t have to accept
your content creation
tool’s defaults
when saving your images.
In my case, I reduced
the file size significantly
without
a perceptible loss in quality.
Let me show you a little trick
that you might be able to use
in your project
to make sure your image quality
holds up
under various optimizations.
I temporarily replaced
the pineapple with a mango
that was saved out
as a higher compression ratio.
This lets me do
a quick A/B comparison
in the actual app to verify
my changes didn’t result
in a loss of quality.
For video, encode using
the latest standards like HEVC.
As a general rule,
compress audio using AAC
or MP3 codecs, and experiment
with a reduced bit rate.
Quite often,
super-high bit rates
aren’t necessary,
and a lower bit rate clip
won’t result in
a perceptible drop in quality.
For certain kinds of images
like interface controls,
logos, and icons,
representing them
in SVG format can lead
to significant space savings,
and because
it’s a vector format,
it will look great
rendered at any size.
Speaking of the SVG format,
we love it so much
we chose it to back SF Symbols,
which I highly recommend.
There are over 2,000
configurable symbols
to choose from.
They come in a wide range
of weights and scales
that automatically align
with text labels,
and dynamic type
is supported out of the box.
Here’s some code
to get you started
using SF symbols
in your project.
This code snippet shows
how a similar text style
can be applied to both
a label and a symbol image.
A baseline constraint
keeps the label and symbol
image aligned perfectly.
Instead of including
several variations of an image
in your asset catalog,
include one base image
and build the variations
needed at runtime.
Check out the Fruta sample
for a fantastic example
of how
this is put into practice.
Instead of using
a separate image
for each presentation
of the orange ingredient--
one for this collection view,
another for the full image view
with vertical text and controls,
and a third
for the ingredient card back...
This one single image
serves as the backing asset
for three distinct uses.
The result
is a significant space savings
achieved by constructing
the variations at runtime.
Finally, if you’ve completed
all the other steps
and still have assets
that put your clip
over the size limit,
consider lazily loading
those assets
from a content delivery network.
For example,
ship good quality
but lower resolution
placeholder assets
with your App Clip
and use the new Async image API
to replace these assets
progressively after launch.
Check out the What’s new
in SwiftUI session for more.
And a tip:
use the network link conditioner
to test your App Clip
under a variety
of different bandwidth scenarios
to make sure
you aren’t introducing
any delays for your customers
in completing the task at hand.
With these
advanced optimizations,
we’ve reached the end
of the first topic.
You can explore further
and discover more techniques
in the developer documentation
for reducing your app’s size.
Say you’ve released
your App Clip to production
and you don’t see it offered
as expected when you view
your website in Safari.
Or maybe you scanned a QR code
and were directed
to Safari instead of seeing
the App Clip card.
Generally, these issues fall
into a couple
of different buckets:
registration of the experience
and associated
domain configuration.
Let’s do
a quick terminology refresher,
and then I’ll go over some steps
you can take to fix the issues.
In App Store Connect,
you have the ability
to add two types of experiences.
All App Clips must have
a default experience.
For the default experience,
you specify metadata
that populates
the App Clip card
when invoked from your web page
in Safari or when someone sends
a link to your web page
in Messages.
In order to take advantage
of physical invocation
like QR scanning, NFC,
and App Clip Codes,
you need to be sure to add
an advanced experience.
Keep in mind,
registration takes time
to propagate to devices,
so changes
made in App Store Connect
won’t be instantly available.
For an in-depth look
at registering experiences,
please see the sessions
for What’s new
in App Store Connect
and Configure
and link Your App Clips.
Prior to displaying UI
that surfaces your App Clip,
the OS checks to make sure
that the invocation domain
is verifiably associated
with your App Clip.
In other words, that means
the URL viewed in Safari
or encoded in a QR code
must have a secure association
via entitlements
and an AASA file
with your app and App Clip.
If this is not
configured properly,
your clip will not be surfaced.
For more information
on establishing
this secure association,
please see
the What’s new
in Universal Links session
and the Configure and link
your App Clips session.
Let’s say
you’ve configured everything
and you check Safari
and you expect
to see your App Clip card
presented inline like this.
But unfortunately
you just see your web page
and nothing else appears.
So what might be the problem,
and what troubleshooting steps
can you take?
First, verify the syntax
of your meta tag
and make sure it looks similar
to this template.
Replace the yellow placeholders
with your full app’s
App Store ID
and your App Clip’s bundleID
respectively.
I’ll show you a technique I use
to make sure
the meta tag
is constructed correctly.
Navigate to your web page
in Safari
and open the web inspector.
Expand the head element
and look closely at the source.
Then check the node attributes
to ensure
your meta tag
is parsed correctly
and that your App Clip bundleID
is exactly the same
as what is shown in Xcode
and App Store Connect.
Is forwarding or redirection
interfering
with domain validation?
Example.com is not considered
equal to www.example.com
as far as the domain validation
machinery is concerned.
The important thing
to remember here
is that the domain
serving the content,
the domain that’s at the end
of the redirection chain,
should be the domain
that serves the AASA file
and is included in your
associated domain’s entitlement.
Also remember that Safari won’t
display the full App Clip card
or the Smart App banner
if private browsing is enabled.
If you’re still stuck,
verify the AASA
passes validation
in the ASC portal.
You can use the SWCutil
command line tool
to retrieve an AASA file
from your web site
at the expected location.
This is very similar
to the operation performed
by App Store Connect.
You can use this to ensure
there are no errors
preventing App Store Connect
from retrieving the file.
Check the JSON output
for common mistakes
such as bundleID specified
instead of applicationID.
For more information,
please check out
the What’s
new in App Store Connect session
as well as the What’s new
in Universal Links session.
Now for physical invocation
like App Clip Codes,
QR codes, and NFC tags,
here is the expected experience.
If not fully configured,
your web page
will be offered in Safari
instead of your customers
seeing the App Clip card
in Camera.
Many times the reason
this occurs is because
an advanced experience
has not been created
for the URL encoded
in your physical codes.
Even if your QR code URL
is the same as your website URL
and your experience
displays perfectly in Safari,
it’s still necessary
to create an advanced experience
in App Store Connect
to power your physical codes.
Remember this slide from when
we were troubleshooting
Safari invocation?
For web traffic,
all redirects are followed
prior to domain validation.
I’d like to make you aware
of a subtle
yet important difference
in the way domain validation
is handled for physical codes.
Say you’ve been using
a unique domain
in your QR code URLs
and have been forwarding that
to your website
to provide consistency
across platforms.
You’re already serving
an AASA file from that domain
for customers that enter
directly through the web.
Now, here
comes the subtle difference.
For code scanning,
it’s necessary to add
the exact domain
to your App Clip’s entitlements
and serve an AASA file
as well from this domain.
The reason behind this
is to give quick feedback
to the user that is scanning
a physical code.
And we avoid performing
network requests
that would typically result in
following a redirection chain.
Changes to
advanced experiences
or site association take time
to propagate to devices.
If you’ve made sure
the URL you’ve been scanning
has been added
as an advanced experience
and you still don’t see
the App Clip card,
try clearing
the experience cache
in Developer settings.
On to the next topic.
You’ve undertaken
some additional complexity
in your project,
and the upside is that you now
have a more modern,
platform-following experience.
I’d like to show you some steps
you can take to embrace
the extra functionality
while maintaining the level
of quality you’ve worked so hard
to achieve up to this point.
Let’s take a look
at a diagram that shows
functionality
for a basic restaurant app.
In this example,
customers start by browsing
the restaurant’s menu.
Next, they can customize
a burger
or a cocktail and then checkout.
After that,
they see their order status
and options for order pickup.
Now let’s say the restaurant
would like to enhance
the experience by adding
two features: pay at the table
with a QR code and send
the burger you customized
to a friend as a link
so they can order one too.
This will require
some significant redesign
because both of these features
rely on launching
directly to the checkout step.
The requested features
are really great opportunities
for an App Clip,
but shoehorning it
into the current design
will create
a lot of additional complexity.
What steps can be taken
to make the app more flexible?
First, I’d like encourage
you to create flattened,
modular functionality
where each component of your app
is independent and can be
directly launched into.
This approach is much
more suited to deep linking,
which is fundamental
to how App Clips
are invoked and provided state.
Design the checkout module to be
directly invoked by providing,
say, a list of menu items,
which you can encode in a URL.
By representing
the order as a URL
embedded in a visual code,
you give your customers
the ability to pay
for their check at the table.
Once a food item
is encodable in a URL,
you can use this paradigm
to encourage your customers
to share what they’ve ordered
with their friends
so they can buy
the same thing too.
With very
little overhead remaining,
you’re able to adopt App Clips
and increase your reach
by providing
this functionality on demand
to customers that haven’t yet
downloaded your app.
I just showed some ways
to think a bit differently
about the design
of your application,
to unlock extra functionality
while keeping
the overhead to a minimum.
Now let’s look
at how to minimize
some of the boilerplate code
that’s involved
in offering an App Clip.
In your app’s code,
you are likely responding
to life cycle events,
typically with these methods
that are called
when your app is launched
or resumed from background.
Adopting App Clips
adds another set of these
same exact life cycle methods.
You might be tempted
to place code in your App Clip’s
life cycle methods
that extracts the URL
from the UserActivity
and uses that extracted URL
to derive some state
and show some UI.
The concept is sound,
but before doing that,
I suggest refactoring
so that the code that handles
both your app
and App Clip launch is shared.
This eliminates a whole class
of bugs and headaches
of trying to maintain
similar functionality
in separate launch paths
between your App Clip
and full app.
Consider creating a method
like respondTo that takes
the user activity
as a parameter.
Use this method
as the main entry point
of your app
and clip by directly calling it
from all of
the relevant life cycle methods.
Now you’re executing code
that’s common
to both your app and clip,
which greatly reduces
the overhead.
Perhaps you respond
to that user activity
by extracting
restaurant menu items
from the URL to facilitate
the customer paying
the check at the table.
Since this is all code
that’s shared,
you can make changes once
and get the benefits
in both your app and App Clip.
Any discussion
on adopting modern features
in your project
while maintaining quality
would not be complete
without mentioning testing.
There are two techniques
specific to App Clips
that I’d
like to remind you about.
For iterative development,
when building and running
in Xcode, set the _XCAppClipURL
environment variable
to an invocation URL
of your choice.
When you run your clip,
the URL you set here
will be passed
through to your clip
just as it would be
on a customer’s device.
To see your in-development clip
surfaced by the OS
similar to production devices,
navigate to Developer settings
and create
a local experience.
You really need to try this out
before submitting
your clip to get a better feel
for how your customers
will use your App Clip
on their devices.
Otherwise, you’re missing out
on some great opportunities
to test many of the ways
your clip can be invoked,
like scanning a code in Camera.
It’s also a great way to try out
new features in seed builds
before they’re
available in production
like the new App Clip card
experience in Safari.
I’ve just
skimmed the surface
on how awesome local experiences
are for testing App Clips.
For more, please see this year’s
What’s new in App Clips session
and, for a detailed description
on testing App Clips,
please see
the developer documentation
titled Testing Your App Clip’s
Launch Experience.
Last, there’s some functionality
that’s specific to App Clips
that all developers
should take advantage of.
When App Clips were introduced,
two streamlined
permissions items
were made available
just for App Clips.
These items are called
ephemeral notifications
and location confirmation.
You’re able to provide
pre-authorization
for your customers
to take advantage of
right on the App Clip card.
Ephemeral notifications
lets you send notifications
for 24 hours since your App Clip
was last launched,
and location confirmation
helps you confirm
the customer is within an area
you expect without asking for
or needing to know
their precise location.
This helps prevent
an accidental payment
at the wrong gas station
or ordering a smoothie
from a Fruta shop
in the wrong town.
As a developer,
you opt in to this functionality
in your Info.plist.
Now your App Clips
have access
to these unique permissions
without interrupting
the launch of your experience
with alerts that ask for more
than you actually need.
Location confirmation
is only available
for physical invocations
like an NFC tag,
an App Clip Code, or a QR code.
Customers can opt out
of location confirmation
for the current session
or for all requests.
Please be sure to handle
these states appropriately
by checking the error
from confirmAcquired
and offer the customer
helpful guidance
on what occurred
and perhaps options to resume
their transaction
under more favorable conditions.
A quick note about profiles
and signing in Xcode.
Most of you have enabled
automatically manage signing
in the Signing
and Capabilities section
of your project settings,
which is fantastic.
If you’re manually
managing signing,
make sure you obtain
a recent profile.
One immediate benefit
is when your customers
upgrade from
your App Clip to your full app,
their data
will be migrated faster.
This is one of the many benefits
to you that we’re
constantly working on.
Having a recent profile
ensures that your app
and clip have the capabilities
necessary to take advantage
of these improvements.
You’ve now learned
some great techniques
to build
light and fast App Clips.
It’s time to wrap it all up.
I’ve covered basic and advanced
techniques to get your clip
small enough to be delivered
lightning-quick on demand.
I showed you how to ensure
your App Clip is being
invoked
where and how you expect.
I showed some best practices
for getting your project
ready for deep linking, to adopt
App Clips and universal links.
And I covered functionality
that’s unique and streamlined
for App Clips.
I hope you can
launch Xcode today
and use some of these tips
to make your App Clip
lighter and faster.
Please be sure to check out
my colleague Yongjun’s session
on What’s new
in App Clips this year.
Thank you,
and have a wonderful WWDC.
[upbeat music]