[music]
[Yann] Hi.
My name is Yann,
and I'd like to tell you about
a new way to connect
your Bluetooth devices
to Apple Watch.
First,
I'll review how Core Bluetooth
works on watchOS 7.
Then I'll talk about an exciting
new feature in watchOS 8.
And I'll discuss the best ways
to design your accessories
and your app
to work with Apple Watch.
Let's start with
how Core Bluetooth works today.
You can only connect
to Bluetooth devices
while your app
is in the foreground
or during a background session.
This is great when a person
wants to focus on your app
to get information
from their accessory.
But what if you wanted
to have a complication
with information
from your accessory?
Currently,
the complication
could not be updated
unless a person opened your app.
Now in watchOS 8,
you can connect
your Bluetooth accessory
during Background App Refresh.
This enables you to update
your complications
with information
from your accessory
or send local notification
if its battery is running low.
With my example
temperature sensor,
now I can update the temperature
in a complication,
so I can see it
whenever I glance at my watch.
We are using
a temperature sensor
in our example,
but it could be any accessory
that someone would want to see
at-a-glance information about.
To start using Bluetooth
during Background App Refresh,
simply add bluetooth-central
to UIBackgroundModes
in your Info.plist.
This may also appear
as "Required background modes"
and "App communicates
using CoreBluetooth."
Here's a table showing
differences between platforms.
These are the current
supported configurations
for Bluetooth Low Energy.
Let's dive into how
your accessory communicates
with Apple Watch.
Let's say a user has already
paired with your accessory
and they open your Watch app.
Your app tries to connect
to your accessory,
and as soon as
an advertisement is seen,
a Bluetooth LE connection
is established.
When a user exits
your watchOS app,
the Bluetooth
connection will terminate.
The Bluetooth connection
won't be available
until the next time your watchOS
app has runtime available.
Let's analyze what happens
during your next
background app refresh
on watchOS 8.
Your app initiate a connection
to a known peripheral,
and the next time
an advertisement is received,
Apple Watch will connect
to your accessory.
As soon as you're finished
retrieving data,
you can terminate
the Bluetooth connection
and process the data.
Background App Refresh
can happen at any time,
so your accessory should
advertise as often as possible
when it has an important update
to display on Apple Watch.
Now,
let's say your accessory
advertises very rarely
to conserve power.
It is possible
that no advertisement
will be received
during
the Background App Refresh
and no connection will occur.
Background App Refresh is
not guaranteed to happen
at a specific time,
so your accessory must advertise
frequently
whenever
it has important updates.
One possible strategy
is to buffer sensor data
on your accessory.
When it's close
to the buffer limit,
increase its advertisement rates
to increase the chances
of reconnection to Apple Watch.
As a guide,
you should advertise
at least every two seconds
in ideal RF conditions.
If you expect your device
to work
in a more challenging
RF condition,
your accessory should advertise
more frequently
to increase the chances
of reconnection.
Let's look at how
your app will interact
with Core Bluetooth
and how watchOS will interact
with your Bluetooth accessory.
This is a time diagram flow.
Time advances
from top to the bottom.
Let's start with what happens
when your app
is in the foreground.
Your accessory is advertising.
You can scan for a new device
to detect
your Bluetooth accessory.
Once your device has been
discovered,
you can initiate
a connection to it.
As soon as Apple Watch
receives an advertisement,
it will connect.
Once you're done
with the Bluetooth connection,
you can call
cancelPeripheralConnection,
which will disconnect
your Bluetooth device.
Then, at a later point,
when the Apple Watch screen
goes off,
your watchOS app
will be suspended.
Now, let's take a look
at what happens
in the next
Background App Refresh.
Note that the time elapsed
is not to scale.
If your app needs to reconnect
to your Bluetooth accessory,
it can initiate a connection.
Here the connection
gets established.
As mentioned before,
we highly recommend to only
connect to your accessory
for only the amount of time
you need.
You should retrieve
the data you need
and then request a disconnection
during Background App Refresh.
In this case,
data transfer completes
and the app cancel
the peripheral connection.
Let's look at another
potential user flow.
In this one,
the Bluetooth Accessory
is not near the Apple Watch
or not advertising during
the Background App Refresh.
Here's how
you should manage this
during
Background App Refresh period.
First, you will connect
to a peripheral,
but there are no advertisements.
When the expiration handler
is called,
you should
ask to cancel the connection.
This way,
you will have a clean slate
and can ask to reconnect
at the beginning of the next
Background App Refresh.
It is also a good practice
to cancel the connection
before the expiration handler
is called
in order to save battery.
If you need to reconnect at
the next Background App Refresh,
you can issue
a connectPeripheral again.
As soon as Apple Watch
sees the advertisement,
it will connect
to your accessory.
At this point,
you can fetch and download
all the data you need.
Then, you can disconnect
as soon as you are done
with the connection.
Let's look at the final flow,
where we see what happens
if you don't disconnect
during Background App Refresh.
Initiate a connection.
As soon as Apple Watch sees
advertisement,
it will establish a connection.
Here,
let's say your app didn't have
time to retrieve all the data
before Background App Refresh
expires.
In this case,
Core Bluetooth would
automatically terminate
the connection at the end of
the next Background App Refresh.
At the next
Background App Refresh,
your app will get the event
didDisconnectPeripheral.
At this point,
if your app needs to,
it can initiate
a Bluetooth connection
or it can wait till the next
Background App Refresh.
We highly recommend to only
connect to your accessory
for only
the amount of time it needs.
Your app should request
a disconnection
during
the Background App Refresh.
Let's take a closer look
at the code to implement this.
When someone launches
your app in the foreground,
it can discover peripheral
and connect to them.
The didDiscoverPeripheral
delegate method
is called when
an advertisement is detected.
If you have used CoreBluetooth
in the past, this is familiar.
Now let's look at what happens
during Background App Refresh.
The handleBackgroundTasks
delegate method is called.
You can start any
of your background work,
and in our case,
we want to connect
to our Bluetooth peripheral.
During
the Background App Refresh,
just before termination,
you also get a notification
that the Background App Refresh
is about to finish.
This is a new API in watchOS 8.
You can use this to cancel
any existing work
and prepare your application
to go into suspended mode.
Then set the task as completed.
Also, when getting
background runtime,
you need to determine
what will be the behavior
when your Bluetooth
device disconnects.
Remember that the callback
didDisconnectPeripheral
can happen
while in the foreground
or in Background App Refresh
and happens on all platforms.
Here, when we have
the didDisconnectPeripheral,
we call a function called
didCompleteDisconnection
that resides in your WatchKit
Extension delegate.
This way,
the behavior of this function
is specific to watchOS.
What the function
didCompleteDisconnection does
is verify that
we are in a Background App Refresh
and if so,
indicates that
the task is complete.
This will terminate
the Background App Refresh.
Let's talk about best practices
for using Core Bluetooth
on Apple Watch.
For first-time device setup,
your app must be running
in the foreground,
meaning the user is
actively using your Watch app.
Scan for new peripherals
at this time.
Once your app discovers
a peripheral,
it can set up the initial
Bluetooth connection.
It can also pair to your device
if needed.
Once your app exits
the foreground,
it cannot scan
for new peripheral.
Instead,
it should request a connection
to a previously discovered
peripheral.
Once connected,
retrieve the data needed.
Once finished retrieving
the data,
your app should disconnect
from the peripheral
to preserve battery.
If your app doesn't disconnect
before
Background App Refresh ends,
Core Bluetooth will
automatically disconnect
from your accessory.
You can only reconnect
when your app has runtime.
I encourage you
to join our lab this week
if you have any questions
about Core Bluetooth.
Thanks.
[music]