[upbeat music]
[Mahesh] Hi.
My name is
Mahesh Molakalapalli.
I'm an engineering manager
from the App Store team.
In this session,
I am excited to introduce you
to the newly redesigned
App Analytics
and highlight
a number of updates.
Our goal with App Analytics is
to maximize your opportunity
on the App Store by
providing unique insights.
We do this by sharing metrics
about your app
across the entire
App Store ecosystem
without requiring you
to add any code.
Today, I will tell you four
new ways that App Analytics
gives you the data you need
to grow your business.
I will talk about the new
metrics that allow you
to monitor transactions
better than before.
Then I will show you how
you can measure macOS usage,
including for iPhone
and iPad apps on Mac.
After that,
I will talk about how you can
use data to analyze
your App Clips performance.
I will end with how you can
enhance your presence
on the App Store
with Custom Product Pages,
In-App Events,
and Product Page Optimization.
Let's start with monitoring
store transactions.
Later this year,
we will be adding
a lot of new metrics
to App Analytics,
helping you better understand
transactions
from pre-orders
to total downloads.
To help bring this data
to life, I will be using
my favorite test app,
Mountain Climber.
This app helps customers view
livestreams of hikes
at famous mountains
so that people
can enjoy the outdoors
while staying at home.
Let's pretend you are the
developer of Mountain Climber,
and you are about to launch
your app
for the very first time.
Your app will be live-streaming
a climb up Half Dome
as your inaugural event,
and you want to get
as many people onto the app
as you can
in anticipation of the climb.
In order to generate
that excitement,
you set up a pre-order
to drive people
to your product page,
as you want to make sure
your customers have the app
on day one.
Later this year,
App Analytics will let you
monitor how your
pre-order campaign
is driving interest
in your app
with a brand-new
pre-order dashboard.
This dedicated dashboard
will let you see how many
Impressions, Product Page Views,
and Pre-Orders you have.
And you will be able
to view your pre-orders
by device and by source type.
You can also view by territory.
This will help you to see
where your pre-orders
are coming from
and focus your marketing
efforts on those areas.
And on the Metrics tab,
you will be able to see
how your pre-orders
are rolling in over time.
It is common to see a large
spike in the beginning
when the pre-order
is first launched.
This is a good indication
that some of your
future customers
are very excited
about your app.
When your pre-order
is complete
and your app
becomes ready for sale,
the dashboard will open up
and show all of the metrics
for your app.
Once Mountain Climber goes live,
it's time to see how many
purchases you are getting.
You are selling access
to the Half Dome stream.
And in this case,
it costs $0.99
to have unlimited access
to the climb.
The proceeds
from this transaction
will be available
in App Analytics.
To view your proceeds,
click on the drop-down
and select Proceeds.
This will pull up the Proceeds
chart so you can track it
over time and see if your
overall revenue is increasing.
Now, let's say you have just
released a new update
to Mountain Climber,
which you call version 1.1.
And you want to see
how many customers
have updated
to this latest version.
Later this year,
you will be able to go into
App Analytics and see your
app updates over time.
The total number of updates
tell you
how many customers have
your new app version,
allowing them
to take advantage
of the new features
you just rolled out.
Next up, re-downloads.
We know that customers might
remove apps from their devices
for different reasons,
and it's important for you
to understand when and how your
app gets those customers back.
So later this year,
we're excited to introduce
re-downloads to App Analytics.
You will be able to view
re-downloads by territory,
device, and more,
so you can pinpoint
where your re-downloads
are coming from
and adjust your
re-engagement strategy
to maximize your customer base.
But it doesn't end there.
We are going even further
by providing
total downloads as well.
Total downloads represent
first-time downloads
plus re-downloads
and will give you
the most complete picture
of how many customers
are downloading
your app from the store.
Now that you know about
all the ways you will be able
to monitor your
store transactions,
let's talk about how you
can use macOS to reach
even more customers
with your app.
With the introduction
of Mac with Apple Silicon,
iPhone and iPad apps
are now automatically
available on the Mac
with no additional code,
which lets you reach more
customers with your app.
Now you can see
how many customers
are using your app
on the Mac in App Analytics.
By selecting the dimension
drop-down at the top
and clicking on Device,
you can view data by device
and see how many of your
sessions are coming from MacOS,
which falls under
the Desktop category.
Here we can see that
there have been
over 6 million sessions on Mac
in the last 30 days.
Clicking on the metrics
drop-down allows you
to see a number of other
new metrics for the Mac,
including Installations,
Active Devices,
active in the last 30 days,
Crashes, and Deletions.
Let's take a look at crashes.
Looking at the data,
it looks like Mountain Climber
has very few crashes
on the desktop.
Considering how many sessions
the app has,
this is a good sign
that the app is stable
and working as expected on Mac.
Now you know how to measure
your macOS usage
even if your app wasn't
originally built for the Mac.
Next, let's talk about how you
can analyze your App Clips.
App Clips are a great way
for customers to quickly
access and experience
what your app has to offer.
Whether your customers
are ordering take-out
from a restaurant,
renting a scooter,
or setting up a new connected
appliance for the first time,
they will be able to start
and finish an experience
from your app in seconds,
with App Clips.
And now in App Analytics,
you can learn all about
how your customers
are discovering
and using your app clip.
Let's take a look.
On the Overview page,
we have a dedicated ribbon
to help you get a high-level
understanding of
how your app clips
are performing
by viewing Installations,
Sessions,
and Crashes
for your clip.
If you click on View Details,
you will be taken
to a more detailed Overview
page for App Clips.
Here, you can see how many
Card Views your clip has.
Cards are what pop up
on the customer's phone
to confirm that they
want to open a clip.
We also show how many Sessions
your clip has attracted
as well as
how many Crashes you have.
Below that, we show you
how many Installations
your clip has and where those
installations came from.
The last part of the Overview
page highlights
the Top Territories where your
app clip was found,
which can be viewed
by Card Views,
Installations, and Sessions.
As you can see, there are
a ton of great ways
to analyze your App Clips and
see how your customers use them.
Lastly, let's talk about
how you can enhance
your presence on the App Store.
We have three new App Store
features coming up in the fall
that we are very excited about -
Product Page Optimization,
Custom Product Pages,
and In-App Events.
Each of these features
is designed to help you
acquire more customers
through the App Store.
Let's talk about how you
can use App Analytics
alongside
each of these features.
First, let's talk about
Product Page Optimization.
With this feature,
you can set up and test
different variants
of your default page
to determine which one
best works with
your App Store visitors.
As part of this,
App Analytics will be
releasing a brand-new dashboard.
The new dashboard
helps you determine
which variant results
in the best conversion rate.
We will also perform statistical
analysis on the results
using a Bayesian methodology
allowing you to monitor
the test over time.
And you will also be able
to stop the test at any time.
With this feature,
you can be sure that
you are using your best icons,
screenshots, and preview videos.
Next, let's talk about
Custom Product Pages.
With this feature,
you will be able to customize
the content of your product
pages and drive audience
to the page you think
will be the most relevant.
Then in App Analytics,
you will be able to view
the results of each product page
across multiple metrics,
including product page views,
downloads,
conversion rate, proceeds,
retention, and more.
You can learn about both
Product Page Optimization
and Custom Product Pages
in the session called
"Get ready to optimize
your App Store product page."
One more existing feature
that we announced
is In-App Events.
This lets you promote
app experiences
happening within your apps
on a particular date and time,
such as a game competition,
a live-streaming experience,
and more.
In App Analytics, you will
be able to see how your event
is performing on the store,
including how many impressions
your event had on the store,
how many people asked to be
notified when the event begins,
how many customers downloaded
the app from your event page,
and how many app opens
came from the event page
on the store.
All of this will help you
understand
which events are catching
your customers' attention
and making them excited
about your app.
You can learn more about
In-App Events by viewing
the session "Meet In-App Events
on the App Store."
With that, I want to thank you
for watching this presentation.
To recap,
the goal of App Analytics
is to help you maximize your
opportunity on the App Store
by providing insights
that only Apple can offer.
Whether you're using
In-App Events,
Custom Product Pages,
Product Page Optimization,
App Clips, and more,
App Analytics has you covered.
Thank you.
[upbeat music]