[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Paul Sim: Hi there! I'm Paul,
and I work
on the SF Symbols app.
Today, we're going to go through
some of the awesome new features
we've added to the app
this year and talk about
how the SF Symbols app can
help you create your own apps,
whether you're a designer,
a developer,
or a little bit of both.
First, we'll go over how to find
symbols to use in your projects
and preview how they'll look.
Then we'll talk about
how the app can help manage
custom symbols that you create.
And finally, we'll show you how
you can copy and export symbols
for use throughout
all stages of the design
and development process.
Now, I've got an idea
for a card game app.
I want my family to be able
to play games together,
even if we can't be
in the same room.
So let's dive
into the SF Symbols app
and find some symbols
I can use in my UI.
First off, I'll start
by making a collection
using the plus button
here in the corner,
so I can keep symbols
for my card game together
and find them quickly later on.
Now, let's start
finding some symbols.
It won't be much
of a family game night
if I'm the only one playing,
so let's look for a symbol I can
use for inviting other players.
You can browse the SF Symbols
catalog by category
here in the sidebar.
The Human category
has some symbols
that could be perfect
for adding a player.
I'll drag and drop this symbol
with a person and a plus
onto my Card Game collection so
I can find it quickly later on.
Well, once we've invited some
players, we'll need some cards.
I'll need symbols for spades,
hearts, clubs, and diamonds --
the four suits of cards.
So I'll search for the word
"suit" up here in the toolbar,
which filters
the system-provided catalog
of symbols.
And SF Symbols
has me covered here, too.
I will add the filled versions
of these suits
to my Card Game collection.
Some symbols for moving cards
around in the deck
could come in handy.
Let's search
for the word "stack"
and find a few more
symbols to use.
And finally, I want to make sure
new players can get
their bearings
when facing off against some of
the card experts in my family,
so we should have
a rule book, too.
One more search for "book"
and one more symbol
to add to my collection.
Great, now I've got an
easy-to-get-to shortlist
of all the symbols
I've found for my project.
So what's next?
Well, the SF Symbols library
is constantly growing,
so it's important to make sure
I can use these symbols
on all of the platforms
I want my app to run on.
Let's take a look
at my Add Player symbol.
I know that some
of my family members
are still running older OS's,
so I want to make sure
that my app runs on iOS 13.
I can see here
in the information inspector
that the name
person.fill.badge.plus
has been available in monochrome
since SF Symbols version 2.0,
which corresponds to iOS 14;
that's too new for me.
However, there's another name
down here
with a warning
symbol next to it.
That is a deprecated name,
which will work if I need
to target older platforms.
person.badge.plus.fill
is available in monochrome
going all the way back
to SF Symbols 1.0,
which corresponds to iOS 13.
So I can use that name if
I want to maintain compatibility
with iOS 13
and other older platforms.
But remember that deprecated
names are, well, deprecated.
So, you should move to the newer
names as soon as you can.
Once I know my family
has updated their devices
and I'm ready to drop support
for older OS's,
I should switch to using
the more modern name
for this symbol.
What else should I check
before I'm ready to use
these symbols in my app?
Well, lots of my family members
use languages
other than American English
on their devices,
and I want to make sure
that my card game app
looks great for them, too.
The information inspector also
shows how a symbol's appearance
will change
in different localizations.
The symbol I grabbed
for my rule book earlier
automatically appears
with a character
in the user's native script.
It even adjusts the direction
that the book opens
to account for differences
between left-to-right
and right-to-left languages.
So that means,
with zero extra work from me,
every member of my family
is going to see a book
with a character
from their preferred language,
which is pretty awesome.
Now, it is possible to specify
a particular localization
in Xcode using suffixes
like .ar or .zh, but in general,
you'll want to use the symbol
name with no localization suffix
and let the system choose
the proper representation
for your user's
preferred language.
Now, let's get an idea of what
these symbols will look like
in our app.
Using the rendering inspector,
I can control
how the symbols are rendered
here in the app
and see how they'll look
next to each other.
Let's take a quick tour through
the different rendering modes.
In Monochrome mode,
I can choose a single color
to use when rendering symbols,
like the built-in
system purple.
Or I can choose a custom color.
If I switch to Multicolor mode,
the symbols take on colors
intrinsic to their meaning.
The heart and diamond suits
turn red,
and the spade
and club turn black.
In fact, the spade and club
will even adjust their color
to account for Dark Mode,
which I can test using
the Background picker here.
And I can pick a color
to use for the parts of symbols
that don't have
an intrinsic color.
This year, we introduced
the Hierarchical rendering mode
which takes a single color
and uses opacity to add depth
and interest to symbols.
I can pick a single color
and see how different parts
of the symbol use different
levels of opacity to stand out.
And finally, the new Palette
rendering mode
provides finer-grained control.
I can specify two or three
different colors to use
during rendering and see how
that affects the symbols.
For a deeper dive into
the different rendering modes
and when you might want
to use them,
along with some insight into the
latest additions to SF Symbols,
check out Thalia's session,
"What's new in SF Symbols."
All right, now I've got a bunch
of SF Symbols picked out
that are going to speed up
the design and development
of my app --
not to mention make it
look amazing.
There are now
over 3000 SF Symbols
built into Apple platforms.
But what if we need something
for our app that isn't covered?
That's where custom
symbols come in.
Since the queen of hearts
plays such an important role
in so many card games,
I want to make sure that she has
a special symbol in my app.
There isn't a symbol
in the system set for this,
so it's time to make
my own custom symbol.
Now, I like the built-in crown
SF Symbol,
and I think that's a great place
to start for my custom design.
So I'll select crown.fill,
and choose File >
Duplicate as Custom Symbol.
And that's it, I've just created
a custom symbol.
From here, I can give it
a more descriptive name
like queen.heart.fill,
and start making changes
to the design.
To change the shape
of a custom symbol,
I'll export a template SVG file,
open it with a vector editor
like Sketch,
and make my modifications
to the design.
Once I'm done, I can just drag
and drop the edited template
back onto my custom symbol
in the SF Symbols app,
and my symbol
will update instantly.
Now, like I said earlier,
I want to make sure
our queen has a symbol
that really pops,
so I want my new custom symbol
to use the new rendering modes
that were introduced this year.
When I switch to a rendering
mode like Multicolor,
in the sidebar
with my custom symbol selected,
I can see a new set
of controls that allow me
to annotate my symbol and opt
into the new rendering modes.
I can also use
the new Gallery view
to get a big representation
of my symbol to edit.
For Multicolor mode, let's make
the heart part of the crown red
and the lower part
of the crown yellow.
I'll select the heart
and drag it to a new layer.
Then I can set
the new layer's color to red
and set the older layer
with the lower parts
of the crown's color to yellow.
In Hierarchical mode,
we'll put the heart
on a primary layer
and the rest of the crown
on a secondary layer.
Well, the default layer
is already set to Primary,
so let's grab the two lower
parts of the crown
and drag them to a new layer.
Since I've already
got a primary layer,
the new layer that's created is
automatically set to Secondary,
so I'm done.
OK, now that I'm done
annotating,
let's add my symbol
to my Card Game collection
to keep it with all
my other symbols.
Once it's part of my collection,
I can see how it looks alongside
other system symbols
using all the new
rendering modes.
If you'd like to do a deep dive
into how to make
your own custom symbol
and learn about some
of the awesome new things
that were added to custom
symbol templates this year,
you can find all of that
in the "Create Custom
Symbols" session with Mike.
All right, I've got
my collection of symbols
ready to go.
Now it's time to get them into
my designs and into my code.
Let's start with a simple case
for a design comp.
Remember the book symbol
I grabbed for my rule book?
I want to mock up a button with
that symbol and the word "Rules"
so users know they can tap
for more information
on how to play the game.
So I'm using
a system-provided SF Symbol,
I'm placing it alongside text,
and I'm planning on using
the Monochrome rendering mode.
In this case, the absolute
best way to get this symbol
into a design app
is to use the SF fonts
that were installed
alongside the SF Symbols app.
To do this, I'll choose
Edit > Copy Symbol --
or press Command-C --
and paste into my design app.
This will paste
the symbol as text.
I can add the word
"Rules" to it --
right alongside it --
in the same text box.
Using the SF fonts means
that the pasted symbol
will be aligned
and weight-matched
with text around it,
with no additional work
required from me.
And the kind of design
that requires
no additional work from me
is my favorite kind of design.
For more information
on using the SF fonts,
check out the "SF Symbols 2"
session from WWDC20.
So that's the story for system
symbols in monochrome.
But what about our special
queen of hearts symbol?
Since it's a custom symbol,
rather than a built-in
system symbol,
we can't use the SF fonts.
And what about system symbols
using rendering modes
like Multicolor or Hierarchical?
Well, I'm super excited to
announce that the SF Symbols app
now supports copying
images of symbols
to place in your design comps.
Just select a symbol, pick the
correct weight in the toolbar,
and set up
the rendering inspector.
Then, choose
Edit > Copy Image --
or press Option-Command-C --
and paste into your design.
You can also choose
Edit > Copy Image As...
to control the format
of the copied image.
Symbols can be copied
in either PNG or SVG format,
and you can specify
a point size and pixel scale.
The SF Symbols app will
keep using these settings
for copying images until you
come back and reconfigure them.
Note that copied images
of symbols
may have some extra vertical
padding added to them.
This is done
so that the vertical center
of the symbol images will align,
so it's easy to work
with several symbols
in a horizontal row.
Now, unlike using the SF fonts,
these images aren't guaranteed
to be weight-matched
or automatically aligned
with text near them,
but we're really excited
about the flexibility
that this new feature brings
to designing with symbols.
Remember that Copy Image
is intended to be used
when you're making design comps.
It's the best way to get
your custom symbols
into your designs,
and it will be a big help
when you're designing with
symbols that use rendering modes
like Multicolor, Hierarchical,
or Palette.
I won't go into much detail
about using SF Symbols
in code here, but I want to
mention a common sticking point.
When copying an SF Symbol
for use in code,
make sure you're copying
the name of the symbol,
rather than the symbol itself.
And though it may be tempting
to use the new Copy Image
feature to bring a symbol
into an asset catalog,
you should instead
use the Export Symbol option
to make sure you get
all the features
that a full custom symbol
provides.
For more information
on using SF Symbols in code,
check out
Tom and Jacob's sessions
on using SF Symbols in SwiftUI,
UIKit, and AppKit.
So the SF Symbols app
is here to help you
throughout your entire design
and development process.
You can keep the symbols
you're using close at hand
with collections and preview
what the symbols will look like
in your app
using different rendering modes.
You can create
your own custom symbols
and adopt the new rendering
modes to give your app
its own special personality,
while making sure it looks right
at home on Apple platforms.
And of course, you can copy
or export symbols
to use in your design comps
and Xcode projects
to make an app that looks
and feels great.
And that's what's new in
the SF Symbols app this year.
We hope that it will help you
design and develop accessible,
inclusive, and great-looking
apps in record time.
And hey, once you're done
doing that,
you're always welcome to join
my family for a game of cards.
♪