[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Megan Gardner: Hello!
My name is Megan Gardner,
an engineer on the WebKit team,
and today we're going to explore
WKWebView additions together.
Before we start our journey,
let's make sure we know
what we're exploring.
Let me tell you
what WKWebView is
and why you might want to use it
in your app.
When a user clicks a URL,
they are expecting a web page
to load and be able
to interact with that content.
Loading the URL,
rendering the content,
and running any JavaScript
on that content
is a very complicated task!
So we have encapsulated
most of that work for you
inside of WKWebView.
And not just for you!
WKWebView is the view that
is used to show all web content
on iOS and much of MacOS.
This includes Safari.
So if you need to show
a web page in your app,
then you might assume you need
to add a WKWebView.
But wait!
What are you doing
with that content?
If you need a way
to view a web page,
but you don't need
much customized interaction
with that content,
you probably just need
an SFSafariViewController.
This is like a tiny Safari
inside your app.
Using one of these views
is incredibly simple,
but there is a trade-off.
There is little you can do
to interact
with the web content.
But this year, we have made it
easier to do just a bit more
with Safari view controller.
Your users have always been able
to run app extensions
through the share sheet on your
Safari view controller's content,
but for special functions
built only for your app,
that has been
a little cumbersome
and hard for users to discover.
So in iOS 15,
we have added a new API
to bring one
of your app extensions
to a customized button
on Safari view controller.
You can map this button to one
of your app's share extensions,
and you can even set an image
for that button
that will best represent
the extension that will run,
allowing users
to run your app extensions
directly from the toolbar,
including running JavaScript
on the page.
But this is still a very limited
amount of interaction.
And that's where WKWebView
comes in.
WKWebView allows you to do
many things
with the content
that it is showing.
We have many APIs for loading,
manipulating,
and interacting
with the content.
So, if you need
to show web content,
and you need to have
complex interactions with it,
then WKWebView is for you.
And since WKWebView is about
interacting with web content,
we are always striving to make
that easier for you to do.
We take on more of the workload
by making easy APIs
for you to adopt that will
help you access and manipulate
the content of your web view.
This year we have been
hard at work,
adding new and helpful features
to WKWebView,
and today, I'd love to tell you
about some of them.
First, we'll cover
several APIs
that will allow you
to interact with
and manipulate your web content
without using having
to inject JavaScript.
Then we will cover several APIs
that will give you access
to functionality
that previously has only been
available in Safari,
allowing for a deeper
browser-like experience
in your app.
Before we go over these APIs
that will allow you to opt-out
of using JavaScript,
let's review why you might want
to avoid JavaScript.
We love JavaScript!
It is the language of the web!
But injecting JavaScript
is complicated.
The interface
between native and web
that you need to cross
via injection
can be difficult and cumbersome
to navigate.
It can also easily have
unintended side effects
or be difficult to manage
when dealing with content
from multiple web sources.
It's best to avoid that headache
if you can.
There are also some features
that are just incompatible
with injected JavaScript.
Last year, we introduced
a new feature
called app-bound domains.
This allows you to specify
which domains
you would like to allow
deep interaction with
in your app.
App-bound domains helps increase
the security and privacy
of your app for your users.
But to get this benefit,
you cannot inject JavaScript
into your web view.
Doing so disables the feature.
There are also
other high-value features,
like Apple Pay,
that you do not have access to
in your web view
if you choose to inject
JavaScript.
Therefore, we've added
several new APIs
to allow you to easily interact
with the content in your web view
without having to deal
with injecting JavaScript.
These new APIs
fall into three categories.
First, we have simple ways
for you to access
the pages' theme color
and related colors
for a website.
Next, a way to disable
text interaction,
as well as being able to control
media playback in your web view.
First, let's explore
theme color.
You might remember last year
we told you about
one of our mission-critical
internal apps, Browser Pets,
which was written
by Brady Eidson
to combine the feeds
from our WebKittens
and Pups on Safari websites.
Well, with all the new APIs
available,
Brady and I decided we should
update this important tool,
to get the most out of our many
morale-raising cats and dogs.
One of the engineers
on the WebKittens website
has decided to add
a dynamic theme color
that changes with the season,
adding a little flair
to our important pet photos.
I wanted this to be reflected
in the app as well,
but I did not want
to duplicate the code.
Fortunately, we have a new API
that makes this very easy.
As you can see here,
I can set the color
of the header view
to the theme color
of the website
using this new API,
thus leveraging the work
that my fellow engineer put into
the WebKittens website.
The website engineer can even
add new themes in the future,
and they will be reflected
in the app
without any additional work
on my part.
If themeColor isn't set,
in a future seed
we have an alternate calculated
background color exposed
as underPageBackgroundColor,
which you can use similarly.
You might have noticed
how Safari is using this
to create a look that blends
the app with the web page.
You can even write to this value
to customize the color
that is used
to fill the background
when scrolling past
the end of web content.
Next, let's talk about
text interaction.
We have recently added videos
to the WebKittens
and Pups on Safari websites,
and Browser Pets users
have been complaining
about accidentally activating
the text selection controls
when trying to play
those videos.
Well, we don't want that!
Fortunately, there is a new API
to quickly and easily disable
text interaction on a web view.
It's simple!
When setting up your web view,
just make sure to set
textInteractionEnabled to false
in the preferences used
to create the web view.
This will turn off all text
interactions in that web view.
Now text selection controls
won't get in the way
of the media controls,
and we can play
those kitty videos unhindered.
Speaking of media controls,
we have some great updates
for media playback controls!
Previously, if you wanted
to pause or suspend media
that was playing
in your web view,
you'd need to inject JavaScript.
You'd also need to find
the specific element
in the DOM to be able
to control it.
But now, we have a simple API
that makes it easy to control
the state of media
in your web view.
You can now easily pause
all media,
close all media windows,
get the state of the media
on the page,
or set media suspended,
which will pause media
and disable user controls
until
setAllMediaPlaybackSuspended
is set to false.
To help you get more familiar
with these new APIs
and how easy they are use,
I'm going to turn it over
to Brady who will show you
how we utilized these
new media control APIs
in Browser Pets!
Brady Eidson: Thanks, Megan.
Hello, I'm Brady Eidson,
an engineer on the WebKit team.
As Megan alluded,
both the WebKittens
and Pups on Safari websites
recently added the ability
to post videos
instead of just still images,
which means our Browser Pets app
has videos now, too.
Here's how the app looks
right now.
These buttons are
native UI buttons
for various features I'm adding.
That banner at the top
of the page is web content,
and the website has set
a theme color,
which I have adopted using
the web view themeColor property
Megan mentioned.
Once videos were added,
some folks expressed
their preferences
to not have videos autoplaying.
This Pause button
is to accommodate them.
Let's see what it does.
Just the kittens video paused,
not the dogs.
And pressing Play,
nothing happens.
Let's take a look at the code.
This JavaScript
was my only option
to try to pause
these videos before,
and it's been problematic.
I have to understand
the structure of web pages
from two different websites,
and that structure
is constantly changing.
For example, this JavaScript
from the Pups website
used to work
but doesn't anymore.
Fortunately now
there's a better way.
First, I adopted calling
pauseAllMediaPlayback
on the web view.
That's equivalent to calling
the JavaScript function pause
on every media element
on a page.
And it works nicely.
But notice what happens
when I refresh the page.
The videos play again.
New page load.
These videos
have never been paused.
If I want something more sticky,
I'd use
setAllMediaPlaybackSuspended.
Let's try that now.
Notice how it pauses the videos,
and they remain paused,
even after refreshing the page.
That's because this setting
is a property
of the web view itself
and not of any content
inside of it.
It also allows me to resume.
Thanks to these new APIs,
you now have the flexibility
to add a better media experience
to your app.
Back to you, Megan.
Megan: Thanks, Brady!
Those pets look great,
and even better
with the new media controls.
So those are our new APIs
for WKWebView
that let you avoid
using JavaScript.
We hope they make
writing your apps
and interacting
with your web content
even easier than before.
Next, we'll review several
browser-level APIs
that will give you access
to functionality
that previously has only been
available in Safari.
We have three areas of API
to cover.
First is a simple
HTTPS override flag.
Next is media capture or --
as it known on the web --
getUserMedia,
which is fully available
in your web view now.
And finally, a new API
to manage downloads
which will work in connection
with WKWebView
to allow and manage
downloads in your app.
So let's start with HTTPS.
Security and privacy
on the web
has always been important,
and we are always searching
for new ways
to make security and privacy
easier for you and your users.
There has been a broad industry
push to move traffic to HTTPS,
as this is a safer
and more secure way
to browse the web.
Many top sites support HTTPS,
and some even automatically
upgrade connections
from HTTP to HTTPS.
Beginning in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
we are taking HTTP requests
to sites that we know
support HTTPS
and upgrading them for you.
In order to get
this added security,
you don't need to do
anything at all!
But, if you do need
to turn it off
for some local debugging,
there's an easy flag
to set on configuration.
Hopefully you will
not need this,
but it's here if you do,
and it probably shouldn't
be done in production code.
Next, let's review what's been
happening with media capture.
Staring in iOS 14.3,
we enabled getUserMedia
for WKWebView,
which allowed WebRTC functions
to work inside your app.
Now, we've made it even better!
When you load your web content
from a custom scheme handler,
the user request prompt
will show your app
as the origin of the request,
rather than show a request
from the website URL.
This should make the experience
more intuitive and seamless
for your users.
If you want the prompt to remain
as a request from the URL,
just load without
the custom scheme handler,
and the prompt will be shown
as it is today.
We also have a new API
to allow you to decide
when and how to prompt the user
for camera and microphone
permissions
when working with web content.
Once you have obtained
user permissions
for the camera and microphone
via normal entitlements
and prompts,
you can decide if the permission
prompts should be shown.
You can use this to implement
your own prompt
or remember
the users' previous response
for web content
you control and trust.
By creating and setting
the UI delegate
on your WKWebView,
you can now decide
when the user should be prompted
for permission to use
their camera or microphone.
If you do not implement
this delegate,
users will continue to get
the prompt as they do today.
But if you want to skip
the prompt
because you have saved
the user preferences
from previous interactions
with a website,
this delegate will allow you
to do that.
How did we leverage these
new APIs for Browser Pets?
Well, due to circumstances
beyond our control,
the team had to cancel
our monthly
Pups in the Park meetup.
To fulfill that need to share
our dear doggies
with each other,
Brady and I decided
to add a virtual dog park
to Browser Pets,
so we could still get our
social doggy goodness going on.
This involves using getUserMedia
to set up WebRTC functionality
so we could see and chat
with each other
and our doggie friends
real time!
When setting up the UI delegate,
we know that requests
from our server
are ones that our users
would give permission to
if they already gave permission
to the app
to use the camera
and microphone.
So I can skip that prompt
by setting this delegate
on my WKWebView.
But that's not all I can do!
Instead of having
to execute JavaScript
to start and stop
this user media,
we can get and set the state,
similar to how we can interact
with media controls
without JavaScript.
This work for camera
as well as for microphone.
To help you get even more
familiar with these new APIs
and how easy they are use,
I'm going to turn it back over
to Brady who will show you
how we added that virtual
dog park to Browser Pets!
Brady: Thanks, Megan.
As Megan mentioned,
we had to get a virtual dog park
up and running
because of the times
we're living in.
Let's take another look
at the Browser Pets app.
Some of you may have noticed
a Call button.
Let's tap that now.
We're instantly connected
to our virtual dog park
hosted at our friend's house.
Let's join the fun
by tapping Connect.
Now, because this is
the first time
we've ever used the camera
in this app,
we get the system-wide prompt
about Browser Pets.
Let's definitely choose Allow.
And the second prompt --
specific to the website
we are currently viewing --
is the default behavior today
in the system.
Let's allow that also.
And there we are.
getUserMedia in action.
But let's see if we can make
a change to our WKUIDelegate,
like Megan mentioned,
to make the experience
even better.
In our delegate,
we'll just check for the host
providing our virtual dog park
content
and allow media capture access.
Let's see how that changes
Browser Pets.
Great.
No prompt.
And the way we used
the delegate,
we also keep our users
safe and private
if future content comes
from any other host
and tries to access the camera.
Now that we're in a video chat,
let's try the Mute button.
As you can see,
my camera feed dropped.
You'll also notice that
the recording indicator
in the status bar
has disappeared
and unmuting,
I can bring back my camera feed
and the recording indicator
returns.
This was easy;
no JavaScript necessary.
All I had to do was hook it up
to webView.setCameraCaptureState
as Megan had mentioned.
This was just a taste of how
these APIs enable you
to easily customize
the media capture experience
in your WKWebView app.
Back to you, Megan.
Megan: Thanks, Brady!
I'm so glad we could
continue to meet
with all our fabulous pets.
Lastly, let's talk about
downloads.
Browser Pets users have been
telling me they want to be able
to share these cute
animal pictures
with their friends and family,
but only Apple employees
have been allowed to use
the Browser Pets app.
Fortunately, we've added an API
that lets you allow and manage
downloads from your web view,
making sharing files
easier than ever!
There are three ways to initiate
a download from the web.
The web content can initiate
a download,
the server can initiate
and the app can initiate
a download.
Web content initiates a download
with JavaScript similar to this.
When this JavaScript
is executed,
it initiates a download
navigation action,
which calls
the navigation delegate
with shouldPerformDownload
set to true.
You should use this value
to determine --
along with other logic --
if the download
should be allowed.
The server can initiate
a download in HTTP like this
after calling loadRequest
on your web view.
When that happens,
your WKNavigationResponse
will have a Content-Disposition
header field
with a value containing
"attachment",
and when it does,
you should return
WKNavigationActionPolicyDownload
from your decision handler
to start the download.
Finally, your app can decide
it wants to download something
in the context
of the current page
using an NSURLRequest
like this.
Whatever method you use,
when you get
the WKDownload object,
you need to set the delegate
property on that object
to be able to tell it where
to write the bytes to disk.
If you do not, the download
will automatically be cancelled.
If a download fails,
the data to resume the download
will be handed to you
if you implement the method
on the delegate.
You can then use that data
to restart the download
off of a web view.
With this new API,
I can now offer an easy way
to download the kitties
to Files,
and not to save them to Photos.
So those are our
browser-level APIs.
We think they will offer you
and your users
many more options for having
a rich web experience
in your app.
Wow, what a journey!
Today we have explored
so many things together.
We've talked about several APIs
that you can use
instead of injecting JavaScript,
and we've covered some more
powerful browser-level features.
It's so much easier to use
our new theme color,
text interaction,
and media playback APIs.
And we've made it easier
and safer
to have a richer experience
in your app
with automatic
HTTPS connections,
easy and safe control
of getUserMedia prompts,
and the addition of WKDownload,
so you can easily manage
downloads in your app.
You can learn more about
some of the new web APIs
we are supporting this year,
in the "Develop advanced
web content" session.
You can also discover new ways
to debug and improve
your web content in "Discover
Web Inspector improvements";
two great sessions that will
help you with making
great web content for your app
or for the web.
The web is still growing,
and as it does, so will we.
Many of the APIs
we implemented this year
were based
on developer feedback.
So if you have an API
you are wanting to see,
we want to hear from you!
In addition to feedback
with Apple,
webkit.org has multiple ways
to reach out,
from our Slack workspaces
to our mailing lists.
WebKit is open source,
so this is also where you can
learn to check out
and build WebKit yourself,
as well as file bugs.
Thank you joining me
on this exploration
of our new APIs!
I hope you have
a great rest of WWDC21!
♪