[music]
[Hayden]
G'day.
Welcome to the session,
"Coordinate media experiences
with Group Activities."
My name is Hayden,
and I'm an engineer
on the Group Activities
team here at Apple.
Today, we will talk about how to
create synchronized media apps
that give users the ability
to watch
and listen to content
together across devices.
The goal is
for your users to feel
as if they were physically
together, wherever they may be.
The GroupActivities API
is a Swift framework
for creating shared experiences.
It takes care of coordinating
media for you, via APIs
for playback coordination
and group session management.
And it is supported across
a wide range of Apple platforms,
such as iOS, iPadOS,
macOS, and tvOS.
Let's start off with a demo
of the GroupActivities API,
by calling my colleague,
Moritz, and sharing a video
from the sample app
attached to this talk.
Let's see
if Moritz is available.
[ringing]
Hi, Moritz!
[Moritz]
Hey, Hayden!
[Hayden] I'm gonna home out
and open the sample app.
You can see it's a list of drone
footage from Apple Park.
I'm gonna show
the theater footage to Moritz.
How does that look, Moritz?
Do you wanna watch it?
[Moritz] That looks great.
I really love that one.
But did you see
the new one I uploaded
last week from the rings?
[Hayden]
Oh, it looks great!
I'm gonna start playback,
and our videos will be in sync
across our devices.
You can see if I pause,
it'll also pause for Moritz.
And if he moves ahead,
it'll also move ahead for me.
Looks awesome.
OK, thanks, Moritz!
[Moritz] Yeah, that was great.
Bye, Hayden.
[Hayden] There are
three main pieces that you need
to think about when creating a
coordinated media playback app.
First is implementing
the new GroupActivities API.
Second is how you can take
advantage of picture-in-picture
to make sharing your experiences
as seamless as possible.
And third, my colleague,
Moritz, will do a deep dive
into how playback
coordination works
and the features of the new
playback coordination object.
Let's familiarize ourselves
with the GroupActivities API
by looking at the life cycle
of a GroupActivities app.
Here, we have two iPhones
in a FaceTime call,
just like in the first demo.
My device is on the left,
and my colleague,
Moritz's is on the right.
On my device,
I open the shared app.
In the app, I then
share an activity to the group.
The GroupActivities framework
creates a session object
for the activity,
and then delivers it to my app.
Meanwhile, the session object
is shared to Moritz, where
the framework handles opening
the same app on his device.
Finally, the framework passes
Moritz's app the GroupSession.
Now, we have two apps
able to communicate
over the same GroupSession.
Now, let's look
at the steps you need
to take in order to adopt
the GroupActivities framework.
The first step is creating
a GroupActivity
along with its metadata.
So, let's talk
about what a GroupActivity is
and how you define it.
GroupActivity is a Swift
protocol that represents
the item that your users
are experiencing together.
This will be
a single piece of content,
like a movie or a song.
You should include
any properties on this type
that you need
to set up your experience.
For example, you may want to
include the URL to a video here,
so you can load a video
in preparation for the session.
In order for the framework
to send the data
over the network,
it conforms to Codable.
This means your properties
must also conform to Codable.
You'll notice there
are two required properties.
ActivityIdentifier
is a unique type identifier
so the system knows how
to reference this activity.
GroupActivityMetadata
contains information to show
this activity in system UI
on the remote device.
You'll notice this is an example
of the new async effectful
read-only properties
feature that is being introduced
with Swift Concurrency
this year.
For more information
see the session,
"Meet async/await in Swift"
at WWDC this year.
So, you've defined
a GroupActivity.
Now, you wanna
share it to the call
by calling the activate method
on your GroupActivity.
When you activate
a GroupActivity,
the framework creates
a GroupSession object,
which is delivered to both
the local and remote devices.
The system is in charge
of launching the app,
and system UI will
show the activity metadata.
But first, there's something
we glossed over.
How does your app know
that you're in a FaceTime call?
And what if,
when a user selects a piece
of content, they don't mean
to share it to the group,
and instead
just wanna view it locally?
The PrepareForActivation
function solves these problems
for you, by letting the system
work out the user intent.
Here's an example
of the prepareForActivation API.
In the switch statement,
there are three cases
we need to handle.
The first, activationDisabled,
will be taken when the user
is not in a FaceTime call,
or the system has decided
that they wish
to consume it locally.
The second, activationPreferred,
will be taken
when the user is
in a FaceTime call,
and they wish
to share it to the group.
Canceled is taken when the user
cancels the share action.
This is already enough knowledge
to create a GroupActivities app
that shares an activity.
So, let's jump over to Xcode,
and I'll show you it
in practice.
Before we add
GroupActivities support,
I'll give a quick run through
of the project.
It's a simple movie-watching app
that lets you select a movie
and watch it.
It consists of a list
of movies to watch,
along with a movie detail page
to show you the video player.
Right now,
the app only lets you watch
movies alone,
so let's change that.
You'll notice we have the Group
Activity entitlement set.
And then, we'll add
a GroupActivity to Movie.swift.
First thing to do is
import GroupActivities.
And then,
we'll add the GroupActivity,
MovieWatchingActivity.
You'll notice
it has a movie property,
and it uses that property
to fill in the metadata.
Let's share this activity now.
We'll go
to the CoordinationManager
and find
the prepareToPlay function.
Currently,
this function starts playback
immediately
by enqueueing the movie.
Instead, we'll replace this
with our prepareForActivation
function
that we showed in the slides.
You can see we immediately
enqueue the movie
in the activationDisabled case.
And activate() is called
when the user wants to share it
to their FaceTime call.
Later in the talk, we'll enqueue
the movie to start playback,
but for now, let's see what
happens if we run the app as-is.
I've grabbed Moritz's device,
and I've started a FaceTime call
between the two iPhones.
I'll home out and then launch
the sample app on my phone.
I'll share the rings video
we watched earlier
and launch the app
on Moritz's device.
You can see that it
received the GroupActivity.
However, it didn't
load the correct video,
and there's no
playback synchronization.
So, let's learn how
to add that into the app now.
The main thing to learn
about receiving a Group Activity
is the GroupSession object
and the way
you receive a GroupSession,
the GroupSessions
async sequence.
Here's a high-level diagram
showing the typical
GroupSession life cycle.
Both the local and remote
devices receive a group session.
The app should then set up
in preparation for playback.
And finally, when ready,
join the group session.
The GroupSession
is the object that represents
the realtime session between
devices of a group activity.
It provides state
about the session, such
as the latest group activity,
the connection state, and
the set of active participants
connected to the session.
As we'll see in a moment,
it's also used
for synchronizing playback.
The GroupSession AsyncSequence
delivers GroupSessions
to your app.
Your app never instantiates
a GroupSession object directly,
so this is the only way
to receive GroupSessions.
It's important to note
that you should
get the latest GroupSession
from this sequence,
on both the local
and remote devices.
AsyncSequence is covered
in the Swift Concurrency talk
mentioned earlier.
Here's what awaiting
on the GroupSessions
AsyncSequence
looks like in code.
When a GroupActivity
is activated,
the system
will return a GroupSession
from the AsyncSequence
into your await loop.
Now that we've received
a GroupSession, let's learn
how to use it to set up
playback synchronization.
This latest release
of AVFoundation
introduces a new type
called AVPlaybackCoordinator.
Moritz will give more
information on this object
later in the talk,
but for now, I'll show you how
to attach a GroupSession
to the playback coordinator,
which will enable
synchronized playback.
The way to access
the playback coordinator is
by the playbackCoordinator
property on AVPlayer.
Then, to attach the groupSession
to the coordinator,
we call coordinateWithSession
and pass in the GroupSession.
And that's it.
Under the hood, the framework
handles all the intricacies
of playback coordination
and realtime networking for you.
There's one final step
to session management,
and that's finally
joining the session.
Initially,
a GroupSession is not connected
and is instead
in a "waiting" state.
Calling "join()" connects
the GroupSession to the group
and begins the realtime
connection, allowing messages
to be sent and received
from other devices in the group.
Once the GroupSession
has successfully joined,
playback synchronization
will begin.
Let's add this session
management code
to our sample app.
In CoordinationManager,
let's add the session's async
sequence in an await loop.
Remember, this gives your app
GroupSessions when they've been
activated from either the local
or remote devices.
Let's store this groupSession
on the CoordinatorManager,
which will propagate the change
over to our
MoviePlayerViewController.
Once set, we'll attach the
session object to our AVPlayer
via playbackCoordinator
.coordinateWithSession.
Then, back in our await loop,
we'll get the movie
from the session object.
Since the activity can change
throughout the session,
we use a Combine publisher
to get the activity.
Then, we enqueue
a movie to start playback.
And finally,
we join the session.
Now that we've set up
the code to receive
a GroupSession
and sync playback,
let's run the app on our devices
and see what happens.
Again, the two devices
are in a FaceTime call,
and on the first device,
I'll open the sample app
and share the rings video.
You can see
Moritz's device received
the Group Activity,
so we'll launch the app.
And this time, both devices
show the right video.
Then, if I press "play,"
we can see that playback
synchronization works.
And if I pause on one,
it'll pause on the other.
Or I can move ahead,
and it'll move ahead on both.
And playback is in perfect sync.
One final thing to note
about GroupSession is
how the session is finished.
There are two ways
to finish a GroupSession.
The first is leave().
This disconnects
the local user from the session,
but leaves the session active
for the remaining participants
in the call.
The second is end().
This ends the session,
not just
for the local participant,
but for the entire call.
For extra details on creating
advanced GroupActivities apps,
see the following WWDC session,
"Build custom experiences
with Group Activities."
It covers how to change
the activity of a GroupSession,
observe state of a GroupSession,
and how to use advanced
features, such as
the GroupSessionMessenger,
which lets you send arbitrary
messages between the group.
I highly recommend it.
Let's switch gears and look
at how you can take advantage
of picture-in-picture to make
sharing a video GroupActivity
as seamless as possible.
Why is picture-in-picture worth
thinking about
for GroupActivities apps?
Well, supporting
picture-in-picture allows
content to start playing
instantly after being shared.
Since it doesn't take a user out
of their current context, there
is no need for an explicit user
interaction to start playback.
This saves your users
an extra step and results
in a frictionless experience
to share content.
For more information on setting
up picture-in-picture,
see the 2019 WWDC session
on "Delivering Intuitive
Media Playback with AVKit."
However, there are some nuances
in how picture-in-picture works
with GroupActivitities,
so let's go over them now.
The GroupActivities framework
will deliver sessions
to your media app
while in background,
to give your app a chance
to set up picture-in-picture.
If the GroupSession
indicates playback can start
in the background,
you should set up
picture-in-picture,
and then go through
the regular
GroupActivities flow.
The system
will start playing the content
in picture-in-picture without
launching the app in fullscreen,
so users get
that seamless experience
and aren't taken
out of their current context.
But in some cases,
you won't be able
to set up picture-in-picture
because you may need the user
to sign in to your app,
or the content might not
be available without some
additional steps from the user.
For these cases, GroupSession
provides APIs
for your app to request
to be foregrounded.
Another handy thing we've built
into picture-in-picture
is that it handles leaving and
ending a GroupSession for you,
via a system dialog, so there's
no need to worry about leaving
or ending a session when
picture-in-picture is active.
And now, I'll pass it
over to my colleague,
Moritz, to do a deep dive
on the playback
coordinator object.
[Moritz] Hello,
my name is Moritz Wittenhagen,
and I am an engineer
on the AVFoundation team.
Hayden has introduced
you to AVPlaybackCoordinator
as an object that automatically
keeps playback on multiple
devices in sync, and we've seen
it working in the demo.
In this part of the talk,
I am going to demystify
what the coordinator
actually does under the hood
and how it interacts
with your code.
For the most part, I will focus
on how the coordinator interacts
with AVPlayer,
how you should select
your assets for coordinated
playback, how individual
participants can suspend
coordination temporarily,
and I will also give
you a brief insight into how
to implement coordination
when not using AVPlayer.
AVPlaybackCoordinator is
an object
that shares playback state
across devices,
and it coordinates playback
start across those devices,
with the goal of no one
missing any content.
There are two subclasses
of the coordinator.
An instance
of AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
is always tied
to a particular AVPlayer,
and it handles all
remote state management for you.
This makes it the easiest way
to jump into coordinated
playback, and I highly
recommend you start here.
We are not going
to talk much
about
AVDelegatingPlaybackCoordinator,
but this subclass gives
you the flexibility to control
any other playback objects
that aren't an AVPlayer.
Let's look
at our device setup again.
For the rest of the talk,
we are going to represent
the GroupActivities objects
through the GroupSession.
We also assume that your UI
presents an AVPlayer playing
some AVPlayerItem,
and this is where the new
AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
comes in.
When you call coordinator
coordinateWithSession,
as Hayden showed earlier,
we have effectively connected
the two AVPlayers, and
they start to affect each other.
The basic rule
is the coordinator
will intercept any
transport control API,
so any API that changes rate
or current time.
It takes those commands, figures
out if it needs to coordinate
them with someone else, and
then, at the appropriate time,
lets them take effect
on the AVPlayer.
Let's look at an example.
Here, Hayden and I are
in a GroupSession together,
and because the GroupActivity
told us which URL to load,
have enqueued
the same AVPlayerItem.
Now, if my device changes
the AVPlayer's rate property,
the playback coordinator
will intercept that command
and not immediately allow
the player to start playback.
Instead, it will ask the player
to enter a timeControlStatus
of WaitingToPlayAtSpecifiedRate.
UIs will typically
represent this timeControlStatus
with a waiting spinner.
The coordinator will
then send the command
over to Hayden's iPad.
The AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
there receives the command
and similarly
asks Hayden's AVPlayer
to change rate
and enter a waiting state.
The coordinators give
everyone some time to prepare
for playback with the goal
of everyone starting playback
at the same time
without missing any content.
When everyone is good to go, all
devices begin playback together.
All coordinators
in the session are equal,
meaning that Hayden
can also initiate a command.
Let's have him seek this time.
Again, the seek API is
intercepted,
and the coordinator forces
the AVPlayer to wait
while it shares the command
with connected coordinators.
Everyone is given some time
to complete the seek,
and when all devices
are ready to go again,
playback resumes
for everyone together.
You may ask yourself,
what happens when the AVPlayers
are playing different items?
And the answer
is that the coordinator
only applies state
to the other player
when both players are
playing identical content.
I will elaborate on the concept
of identity later.
For now,
think that content is identical
when you create the items
from the same URL.
What this means is that any
command you send for item A will
only be applied if the receiver
is also playing item A.
And changing the item to B will
ignore all state from item A.
We do this because
distinguishing commands
per-item allows for safe joining
of participants
and transitions between items.
Let me show you what I mean.
Here's our example again,
but this time,
we start
with Hayden already playing.
As I join and connect
my playback coordinator
to the same session,
nothing happens to my AVPlayer,
because I am not playing
the same current item as Hayden.
Even creating that same item
has no impact
because the item is not current
in my player.
This means that I can
even seek the item
without consequences
for anyone else.
Only when
the item becomes current
in the AVPlayer will
the coordinator start
doing its work and try
to apply the right state.
The rule is that
the coordinator always starts
with the group state,
if there is one.
And since Hayden was already
playing in the GroupSession,
the coordinator
prefers his state
over my own configuration
from before enqeueuing the item.
This means that my coordinator
will override any configuration
in the AVPlayer and AVPlayerItem
to match Hayden's device.
And with that,
we are both in the same state
and can play together.
Let's repeat this
with an item transition.
As we both
approach the end of item A,
my AVQueuePlayer is getting
ready to play the next item.
Usually, we would expect
Hayden to get ready, as well,
but for this example,
let's assume Hayden's iPad
is in a bad network and
cannot load the next item yet.
So, now that I'm at the end
of item A,
I already have item B enqueued,
and it is ready to play.
But because
the item is not current,
the coordinator
is not doing anything yet.
Only when my player transitions
to the new item,
will the coordinator
do its job again.
And this time, it does
not find an existing state
for item B,
so it just continues
with the state
my player is proposing.
Even though
the coordinator shares
this new state with Hayden,
he is not affected
because he is still
displaying item A.
But when he eventually
transitions to match my item,
his coordinator will
again apply the existing state
to his player.
And with that, everyone
is playing in sync again.
After all this,
here is my first call-to-action.
Be careful about the order
of your item changes
and transport control commands.
Let's say we have
a function beginPlayback
that enqueues an item and
automatically starts playing.
This code would be
called whenever the user
has selected something to play
or when our GroupSession
informs us of a new activity.
It is important that we seek
to our start time first,
and similarly,
we should change player rate
before the item is enqueued
so that our initial
configuration
cannot affect anyone else.
If we do it in this order,
the playback coordinator can
decide if we are first
and our state should be shared
with everyone else,
or if another state already
exists, and that should
override our state instead.
Also, audit your transport
control commands and consider
if they should affect everyone
in the group.
Usually,
an API call should affect
the group if it
originates from playback UI.
So if the user pauses,
everyone else should pause, too.
In that case, just call
the AVPlayer API as usual.
So, what should we do
with the other API calls
not coming from playback UI?
Usually,
these are automated pauses
because your app has
encountered some system event.
Automatic pauses
like this should
not usually affect
the other participants.
In such a situation, where
your users are playing together
with others, you should first
consider not pausing at all.
Since everyone else continues
to play, users will often prefer
to stick with the group, even
if it has some kind of drawback,
like not being able
to see the content temporarily.
If you have no other choice but
to pause, you have two options:
remove the item first,
or begin a coordinated playback
suspension, which I will
cover later in this talk.
Now that you have an idea of how
the playback coordinator works,
let's talk about content
for coordinated playback.
As I stated previously,
we consider two player items
on different devices
to be the same
when their assets were created
from the same URL.
While this default can
work well, there are situations
where you want
to change this behavior.
For example,
your app may offer the user
a choice to download
and cache the content on device.
So, if I have downloaded
the asset to my local cache,
and Hayden is still streaming
the content from the cloud,
we are no longer using the same
URL, meaning the playback
coordinator will not keep
our playback states in sync.
Similarly, some of you
may have exciting use cases
for coordinating the state
of AVMutableMovies or
AVCompositions, which don't have
a URL representation at all.
Again, the playback coordinator
does not know what to do here.
To solve this problem,
you can provide a custom string
as an identifier
for an AVPlayerItem.
If this string is present,
the coordinator will use it
to decide if two items
represent the same content,
and it will ignore the URL.
You do this by implementing the
AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
Delegate protocol
and its playbackCoordinator
identifierFor playerItem
function.
The coordinator will ask
its delegate for an identifier
whenever you enqueue
an item in the player.
Whenever the playback
coordinator considers
two items equal,
it is important that a time
on one device matches
the same time on the others.
This means
that you need to be careful
with content
that is automatically injected
into the playback stream
by a server.
So, if Hayden
and I request the same URL,
but the server decides to inject
an ad into only my stream,
the devices are now out of sync,
as I play into the ad,
and Hayden continues
with the main content.
The right way to approach
this problem is to move ads
and other interstitials
into a separate player.
That leaves
the main asset unaffected.
Now, as I play into the ad,
my phone switches
to a different player
for the duration of the ad.
And when the ad is over,
the coordinator can easily
rejoin everyone else's timing,
and we are back in sync.
If you are playing HLS content,
AVPlayer will be able to help
you with this through the new
AVPlayerInterstitialEvent API.
Check out the dynamic pre-roll
and mid-rolls
in HLS talk to learn more.
In summary,
use custom identifiers to match
content if the URL does
not cover the right information.
Make sure times are
the same for everyone.
And if you want to play
personalized interstitials,
play them
through a different player,
so that your main content
is not affected.
And finally,
use date tags when coordinating
live content
so that the coordinator
can share the correct timing
with everyone else.
So far, we have only dealt
with the perfect playback cases,
where everyone can stay
in sync the whole time.
Unfortunately,
that is not always possible.
Let's say Hayden
and I are playing together,
but an alarm goes off telling me
to feed my cat, Zorro.
By the rules of AVAudioSession,
my app must now pause,
and those rules still apply,
even when playing in a group.
Yet, we do not want my pause
to affect everyone else.
Forwarding everyone's
little pauses to the whole group
would just cause
too many annoyances.
So, instead, we want Hayden's
iPad to continue playing.
And when I dismiss my alarm,
playback should catch up,
and everyone should play
in sync again.
So, how can we
implement behavior like this?
You use a new object
called an
AVCoordinatedPlaybackSuspension.
Such a suspension
represents a separation
between one
participant's coordinator
and the other
participants' coordinators.
The participant
is separate from the group,
and player rate changes or seeks
no longer affect anyone else.
Similarly,
any rate change coming
from the group will not change
the AVPlayer's rate or time.
In the example,
this means that it
is not possible
for Hayden to start
my player while
the alarm is still playing.
There are two different kinds
of suspensions:
automatic suspensions and
suspensions you add yourself.
Automatic suspensions are added
by AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
when the player
pauses automatically.
We already saw
the example of the audio
session interruption,
but this also applies
to network stalls
or playing an interstitial
through the new
AVPlayer interstitial API.
Suspensions added
by the playback coordinator
end when the player
resumes playback, and it causes
the player to match timing
to the current group state.
For our example,
this means that I will
automatically rejoin the group
when my player rate changes back
to one after my app
handled the end-interruption
notification
from dismissing the alarm.
Let me show you two examples
of how the system uses
coordinated
playback suspensions.
Here is our sample app playing
drone footage of the rings.
Let's look at the interruption
example we discussed before.
I have set a timer
to go off in a few seconds,
so let's wait for that.
[timer ringing]
Ah, here we go.
This has paused the iPad
on my left, but as you can see,
the other device
is still happily playing.
And as I dismiss the timer,
playback on the device
on the left jumps forward
to rejoin
the other device
and is perfectly in sync.
This is not the only way
the system makes use
of suspensions.
AVKit uses them
to keep random video frames
from flashing in front
of everybody during scrubbing.
You may have noticed
already that scrubbing will
show intermediate frames only
on the device
that I'm interacting with.
So, as I touch the scrubber,
the device
on the right continues playing,
while the left device
shows the scrubbing frames.
Only when
I let go of the scrubber
will the new time be shared
with the other device,
and playback resumes
for everyone.
These are examples of how
the system uses suspensions.
Now, let's look at how
you would adopt one yourself.
So, let's jump into Xcode
and actually do that.
Let's say you wanted
to implement a feature
that allows one participant
to rewatch something
they just missed.
Maybe there was
a particularly exciting moment
in the drone footage
we are watching.
With all the coordinator
behaviors we discussed so far,
seeking back and playing
again will affect everyone.
And I want to emphasize
that this may very well be
the right thing to do.
Try to keep your users together
as much as possible.
But let's say seeking back
for everyone is not an option.
So, what we will build instead
is a way to seek back
by a few seconds and play
the content at twice the speed
until we join back up
with everyone.
I have already added a button
in my UI that a user
can use to indicate
that they missed something.
It is hooked up
with this function
in our
MoviePlayerViewController.
Let's fill that in.
Here is just the player logic.
We figure out
what time to seek to,
seek back,
and set the player rate to 2.
When we have caught up, we just
resume playback at rate 1.
So far, this would all happen
to everyone because
the playback coordinator
will intercept those API calls.
This is where
the suspensions come in.
Right before we seek back,
I want to separate our player
from everyone else.
And we do
that with the coordinator's
beginSuspension function.
It requires a reason,
and to provide that reason,
we just extend the Reason struct
with a new string constant.
In this case, what-happened.
Now, we can use that
in our beginSuspension call.
Since the coordinator is now
suspended, we can safely seek
and set the rate,
just for our player.
Once we are ready
to meet up with everyone else,
we need to signal
to the coordinator to listen
to the group again, so we call
suspension.end().
Note that we don't actually need
the player rate change anymore.
Since ending
the suspension will always
rejoin everyone else,
our player rate change would
also change back to whatever
the current group rate is.
Now, let's try this out.
Everyone plays together.
I miss an exciting event,
like the approach to the ring,
and I tap our new
what-happened button.
So, you can see,
the device I'm interacting with
jumps back
to repeat the content.
It plays faster to catch up,
while the other
device is not affected.
And now, we are
already perfectly in sync again.
So, when you begin a suspension
on an AVPlaybackCoordinator,
you separate its player
from the group,
and it is now safe
to issue any rate change
or seek
without affecting anyone else.
Ending the suspension will
rejoin the group's
current time and rate.
And, new on this slide,
you can optionally propose
a new time to the group
when ending the suspension.
This is how you can implement
a scrubbing suspension
that changes time
for everyone only
when letting go
of the playback control.
Here is a summary of when
AVPlayer transport control
commands are actually
shared with other participants.
First, you have to connect
the AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
to other participants
through a group session,
as Hayden showed you
at the beginning of the talk.
Second, the AVPlayer's current
AVPlayerItem must have
the same URL as the other
participants' player items.
Or if you're providing
your own identifiers,
they must have
the same custom identifier.
Once an item is enqueued,
all seeks and rate changes
affect everyone in the group,
except when you begin a
coordinated playback suspension.
And to close out the discussion
of AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator,
here's a quick tour of other API
related to coordinated playback.
If you want other participants
to wait
during one user's suspension,
you can configure this
using the coordinator's
suspensionReasons
ThatTriggerWaiting property.
This is how you could request
that no one misses any content
if participants have
different length ads.
To learn more about the state
of other participants,
take a look at the coordinator's
otherParticipants property
and its corresponding
notification.
The
AVCoordinatedPlaybackParticipant
most notably gives you the list
of suspensionReasons,
which may be useful
to inform UI,
especially if you use suspension
ReasonsThatTriggerWaiting above.
Whenever the coordinator
requests its AVPlayer to wait,
that is reflected in the players
reasonForWaitingToPlay,
with the new waiting
ForCoordinatedPlayback reason.
To override waiting
and immediately start playback,
regardless of the other
participants' states,
use the player's
playImmediately atRate function.
Note that this can cause other
participants to miss content,
so be aware
of that when using this API.
AVPlayer also has
a new rateDidChangeNotification,
which provides more information
about the rate change,
including when another
participant caused it.
And similarly,
AVPlayerItem's
TimeJumpedNotification
will also tell you
if a time jump originates
from another participant.
There is some
AVPlayer API you cannot use
with
AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator.
The default time pitch algorithm
on iOS used to be
low quality zero latency.
This value is now
deprecated in iOS 15.
LowQualityZeroLatency
is not supported
for coordinated playback,
and you should watch out
for code resetting
to this now-deprecated value.
Use one of the other
algorithms instead.
Also, do not use
AVPlayer's
setRate(time:atHostTime:)
function with an
AVPlayerPlaybackCoordinator
because it is vital
that the playback coordinater
is in charge of player timing,
which is incompatible
with external startup sync.
After all this talk
about AVPlayer,
let's quickly dip
into the second subclass
of AVPlaybackCoordinator,
AVDelegatingPlaybackCoordinator.
A lot of the concepts
that we discussed still apply
for delegating playback
coordinator, but instead
of observing the player for you,
the delegating coordinator
requires you to provide
information about playback state
and apply state to your
playback objects yourself.
A custom playback object setup
will look something like this.
Your UI controls the player,
which uses one of the other
system-rendering APIs
underneath.
The delegating
playback coordinator fits
in between your UI
and your player implementation.
As the name suggests,
AVDelegatingPlaybackCoordinator
requires you to implement
a delegate protocol
that receives playback commands
for playing,
pausing, seeking, and buffering.
Instead of sending a play
command to your player directly,
your UI would tell
the coordinator first.
The coordinator will
then decide if it needs
to first negotiate
with other connected players,
before changing your playback
object's time or rate.
You also have to tell
the coordinator whenever
your player transitions
to a new current item,
so that the coordinator knows
which commands to send to you.
As before, items are identified
by arbitrary strings.
When the coordinator
sends a command, it should
affect the originating UI,
as well as the receiver UI.
And when it is time to play,
it should affect all players
in the same way.
It is your responsibility
to make your playback object
follow along
and to update your UI
for commands appropriately.
I want to specially call out
that the delegating coordinator
will often tell you
to begin buffering,
even if your device
is already ready to go.
This means the coordinator
is still waiting for other
connected participants,
and your UI should reflect that,
even if there is nothing
to do on your end.
Final words of warning.
Be careful with events
like route changes
that briefly pause
and resume your player.
It is your responsibility
to stick to the requested timing
and reapply the group timing
as needed.
If you cannot keep up
for whatever reason,
you should communicate that
to the coordinator
using a suspension.
The delegating
playback coordinator
also does not add
any automatic suspensions.
This means you should begin
and end suspensions
for relevant system events
yourself.
Use the reasons provided
by AVFoundation
where appropriate.
And it is possible
to connect a delegating playback
coordinator on one device
to a player playback coordinator
on another, but you must
use custom identifiers
on the player
playback coordinator end.
Let's wrap up.
To build a coordinated
media playback app,
use a GroupActivity
to define the content you are
playing and to propose it
to the group.
Start to keep track
of GroupSessions as soon
as your app launches
to learn when your users
are in a FaceTime call
and want to play together.
And finally,
connect the playback coordinator
to your GroupSession
to keep your content
in sync for everyone.
Thank you,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[music]