[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Michael Patrick Johnson: Hi!
My name is
Michael Patrick Johnson,
and I am an engineer
on the Object Capture team.
Today, my colleague
Dave McKinnon and I
will be showing you
how to turn real-world objects
into 3D models using our new
photogrammetry API on macOS.
You may already be familiar with
creating augmented reality apps
using our ARKit
and RealityKit frameworks.
You may have also used
Reality Composer
and Reality Converter
to produce 3D models for AR.
And now,
with the Object Capture API,
you can easily turn images
of real-world objects
into detailed 3D models.
Let's say you have some freshly
baked pizza in front of you
on the kitchen table.
Looks delicious, right?
Suppose we want to capture
the pizza in the foreground
as a 3D model.
Normally, you'd need to hire
a professional artist
for many hours to model
the shape and texture.
But, wait, it took you
only minutes to bake
in your own oven!
With Object Capture, you start
by taking photos of your object
from every angle.
Next, you copy the images
to a Mac
which supports the new
Object Capture API.
Using a computer vision
technique
called "photogrammetry",
the stack of 2D images
is turned into a 3D model
in just minutes.
The output model includes
both a geometric mesh
as well as various
material maps,
and is ready to be dropped
right into your app
or viewed in AR Quick Look.
Now let's look at each of these
steps in slightly more detail.
First, you capture photos
of your object from all sides.
Images can be taken
on your iPhone or iPad,
DSLR, or even a drone.
You just need to make sure
you get clear photos
from all angles
around the object.
We will provide
best practices for capture
later in the session.
If you capture
on iPhone or iPad,
we can use stereo depth data
from supported devices
to allow the recovery
of the actual object size,
as well as the gravity vector
so your model is automatically
created right-side up.
Once you have captured
a folder of images,
you need to copy them
to your Mac
where you can use
the Object Capture API
to turn them into a 3D model
in just minutes.
The API is supported
on recent Intel-based Macs,
but will run fastest on all
the newest Apple silicon Macs
since we can utilize
the Apple Neural Engine
to speed up our
computer vision algorithms.
We also provide
HelloPhotogrammetry,
a sample command-line app
to help you get started.
You can also use it directly
on your folder of images
to try building a model
for yourself
before writing any code.
Finally, you can preview
the USDZ output models
right on your Mac.
We can provide models
at four detail levels
optimized for your
different use cases,
which we discuss
in more detail later.
Reduced, Medium, and Full
details are ready to use
right out of the box,
like the pizza shown here.
Raw is intended
for custom workflows.
By selecting USDZ output
at the Medium detail level,
you can view the new model
in AR Quick Look
right on your iPhone or iPad.
And that's all there is
to getting lifelike objects
that are optimized for AR!
Oh wait, remember the pizzas
from before?
We have to come clean.
This image wasn't
really a photo,
but was actually created
using Object Capture
on several pizzas.
These models were then combined
into this scene
in a post-production tool
and rendered using a ray tracer
with the advanced material maps.
So you see,
Object Capture can support
a variety of target use cases,
from AR apps
on an iPhone or iPad
to film-ready production assets.
In the remainder
of this session,
we'll show you
how to get started
using the Object Capture API
and then offer
our best practices
to achieve
the highest-quality results.
In the getting started section,
we'll go into more details
about the Object Capture API
and introduce
the essential code concepts
for creating an app.
Next we will discuss best
practices for image capture,
object selection,
and detail-level selection.
Let's begin by working through
the essential steps
in using the API on macOS.
In this section, you will learn
the basic components
of the Object Capture API
and how to put them together.
Let's say we have
this cool new sneaker
we want to turn into
a 3D model to view in AR.
Here we see a graphical diagram
of the basic workflow
we will explore in this section.
There are two main steps
in the process:
Setup, where we point to our set
of images of an object;
and then Process,
where we request generation
of the models we want
to be constructed.
First, we will focus
on the Setup block,
which consists of two substeps:
creating a session
and then connecting up
its associated output stream.
Once we have a valid session,
we can use it
to generate our models.
The first thing we need to do
is to create
a PhotogrammetrySession.
To create a session,
we will assume you already have
a folder of images of an object.
We have provided some
sample image capture folders
in the API documentation
for you to get started quickly.
A PhotogrammetrySession
is the primary top-level class
in the API and is the main
point of control.
A session can be thought of
as a container
for a fixed set of images to
which photogrammetry algorithms
will be applied to produce
the resulting 3D model.
Here we have 123 HEIC images
of the sneaker
taken using
an iPhone 12 Pro Max.
Currently there are several ways
to specify the set of images
to use.
The simplest is just a file URL
to a directory of images.
The session will ingest these
one by one
and report on any problems
encountered.
If there is embedded depth data
in HEIC images,
it will automatically be used
to recover the actual scale
of the object.
Although we expect most people
will prefer folder inputs,
we also offer an interface
for advanced workflows
to provide a sequence
of custom samples.
A PhotogrammetrySample
includes the image
plus other optional data
such as a depth map,
gravity vector,
or custom segmentation mask.
Once you have created a session
from an input source,
you will make requests on it
for model reconstruction.
The session will output
the resulting models
as well as status messages
on its output message stream.
Now that we've seen
what a session is,
let's see how to create one
using the API.
Here we see the code to perform
the initial setup of a session
from a folder of images.
The PhotogrammetrySession
lives within
the RealityKit framework.
First, we specify the input
folder as a file URL.
Here, we assume that we already
have a folder on the local disk
containing the images
of our sneaker.
Finally, we create the session
by passing the URL
as our input source.
The initializer
will throw an error
if the path doesn't exist
or can't be read.
You can optionally provide
advanced configuration
parameters,
but here we'll just use
the defaults.
That's all it takes
to create a session!
Now that we've successfully
created a session object,
we need to connect
the session's output stream
so that we can handle messages
as they arrive.
After the message stream
is connected,
we will see
how to request models
that will then arrive
on that stream.
We use an AsyncSequence --
a new Swift feature this year --
to provide the stream
of outputs.
Output messages include
the results of requests,
as well as status messages
such as progress updates.
Once we make
the first process call,
messages will begin to flow
on the output message stream.
The output message sequence
will not end
while the session is alive.
It will keep producing messages
until either the session
is deinitialized
or in the case of a fatal error.
Now, let's take a closer look
at the types of messages
we will receive.
After a request is made,
we expect to receive periodic
requestProgress messages
with the fraction completed
estimate for each request.
If you're building an app that
calls the Object Capture API,
you can use these to drive
a progress bar for each request
to indicate status.
Once the request
is done processing,
we receive
a requestComplete message
containing the resulting
payload,
such as a model
or a bounding box.
If something went wrong
during processing,
a requestError will be output
for that request instead.
For convenience,
a processingComplete message
is output when all queued
requests
have finished processing.
Now that we've been introduced
to the concept
of the session output stream
and seen the primary
output messages,
let's take a look
at some example code
that processes
the message stream.
Once we have this, we'll see
how to request a model.
Here is some code
that creates an async task
that handles messages
as they arrive.
It may seem like a lot of code,
but most of it is simply message
dispatching as we will see.
We use a "for try await" loop
to asynchronously iterate
over the messages in
session.outputs as they arrive.
The bulk of the code
is a message dispatcher
which switches on
the output message.
Output is an enum with different
message types and payloads.
Each case statement
will handle a different message.
Let's walk through them.
First, if we get
a progress message,
we'll just print out the value.
Notice that we get progress
messages for each request.
For our example,
when the request is complete,
we expect the result payload
to be a modelFile
with the URL to where
the model was saved.
We will see how to make
such a request momentarily.
If the request failed
due to a photogrammetry error,
we will instead get
an error message for it.
After the entire set of requests
from a process call
has finished,
a processingComplete message
is generated.
For a command-line app,
you might exit the app here.
Finally there are other status
messages that you can read about
in the documentation,
such as warnings
about images in a folder
that couldn't be loaded.
And that's it
for the message handling!
This message-handling task
will keep iterating
and handling messages
asynchronously
for as long as
the session is alive.
OK, let's see where we are
in our workflow.
We've fully completed
the Setup phase
and have a session ready to go.
We're now ready to make requests
to process the models.
Before we jump into the code,
let's take a closer look
at the various types of requests
we can make.
There are three different
data types you can receive
from a session:
a ModelFile, a ModelEntity,
and a BoundingBox.
These types have an associated
case in the Request enum:
modelFile, modelEntity,
and bounds;
each with different parameters.
The modelFile request
is the most common
and the one we will use
in our basic workflow.
You simply create
a modelFile request
specifying a file URL
with a USDZ extension,
as well as a detail level.
There is an optional
geometry parameter for use
in the interactive workflow,
but we won't use that here.
For more involved
postprocessing pipelines
where you may need USDA
or OBJ output formats,
you can provide an output
directory URL instead,
along with a detail level.
The session will then write USDA
and OBJ files into that folder,
along with all
the referenced assets
such as textures and materials.
A GUI app is also able
to request a RealityKit
ModelEntity and BoundingBox
for interactive preview
and refinement.
A modelEntity request
also takes a detail level
and optional geometry.
A bounds request will return
an estimated capture volume
BoundingBox for the object.
This box can be
adjusted in a UI
and then passed in the geometry
argument of a subsequent request
to adjust
the reconstruction volume.
We'll see how this works
a bit later in the session.
Most requests also take
a detail level.
The preview level is intended
only for interactive workflows.
It is very low visual quality
but is created the fastest.
The primary detail levels
in order of increasing
quality and size
are Reduced, Medium, and Full.
These levels are all
ready to use out of the box.
Additionally, the Raw level
is provided for professional use
and will need a post-production
workflow to be used properly.
We will discuss these
in more detail
in the best practices section.
OK, now that we've seen what
kinds of requests we can make,
let's see how to do this
in code.
We will now see how to generate
two models simultaneously
in one call,
each with a different output
filename and detail level.
Here we see the first call
to process on the session.
Notice that it takes
an array of requests.
This is how we can request
two models at once.
We will request one model
at Reduced detail level
and one at Medium, each saving
to a different USDZ file.
Requesting all desired
detail levels
for an object capture
simultaneously in one call
allows the engine
to share computation
and will produce
all the models faster
than requesting
them sequentially.
You can even ask
for all details levels at once.
Process may immediately throw an
error if a request is invalid,
such as if the output location
can't be written.
This call returns immediately
and soon messages will begin
to appear on the output stream.
And that's the end
of the basic workflow!
You create the session
with your images,
connect the output stream,
and then request models.
The processing time
for each of your models
will depend on the number
of images and quality level.
Once the processing is complete,
you will receive
the output message
that the model is available.
You can open the resulting USDZ
file of the sneaker you created
right on your Mac
and inspect the results in 3D
from any angle,
including the bottom.
Later in this session,
we'll show you
how to achieve coverage
for all sides of your object
in one capture session,
avoiding the need to combine
multiple captures together.
It's looking great!
Now that you've seen
the basic workflow,
we will give
a high-level overview
of a more advanced
interactive workflow
that the Object Capture API
also supports.
The interactive workflow
is designed to allow
several adjustments to be made
on a preview model
before the final reconstruction,
which can eliminate the need
for post-production model edits
and optimize the use of memory.
First, note that the Setup step
and the Process step
on both ends of this workflow
are the same as before.
You will still create a session
and connect the output stream.
You will also request
final models as before.
However, notice that we've added
a block in the middle
where a 3D UI is presented
for interactive editing
of a preview model.
This process is iterated until
you are happy with the preview.
You can then continue to make
the final model requests
as before.
You first request
a preview model
by specifying a model request
with detail level of preview.
A preview model
is of low visual quality
and is generated
as quickly as possible.
You can ask for a model file
and load it yourself
or directly request a RealityKit
ModelEntity to display.
Typically, a bounds request
is also made at the same time
to preview and edit
the capture volume as well.
You can adjust
the capture volume
to remove any unwanted
geometry in the capture,
such as a pedestal needed
to hold the object upright
during capture.
You can also adjust
the root transform to scale,
translate, and rotate the model.
The geometry property of
the request we saw earlier
allows a capture volume
and relative root transform
to be provided before the model
is generated.
This outputs a 3D model
that's ready to use.
Let's look at this process
in action.
Here we see an example
interactive Object Capture app
we created using the API
to demonstrate
this interactive workflow.
First, we select
the Images folder
containing images
of a decorative rock,
as well as an output folder
where the final USDZ
will be written.
Then we hit Preview
to request the preview model
and estimated capture volume.
After some time has passed,
the preview model of our rock
and its capture volume appear.
But let's say that we only want
the top part of the rock
in the output
as if the bottom
were underground.
We can adjust the bounding box
to avoid reconstructing
the bottom of the model.
Once we are happy,
we hit Refine Model
to produce a new preview
restricted to this
modified capture volume.
This also optimizes the output
model for just this portion.
Once the refined model is ready,
the new preview appears.
You can see the new model's
geometry has been clipped
to stay inside the box.
This is useful for removing
unwanted items in a capture
such as a pedestal
holding up an object.
Once we are happy
with the cropped preview,
we can select
a Full detail final render
which starts
the creation process.
After some time, the Full detail
model is complete
and replaces the preview model.
Now we can see the Full detail
of the actual model,
which looks great.
The model is saved
in the output directory
and ready to use
without the need
for any additional
post-processing.
And that's all there is
to getting started
with the new Object Capture API.
We saw how to create a session
from an input source
such as a folder of images.
We saw how to connect
the async output stream
to dispatch messages.
We then saw how to request
two different level of detail
models simultaneously.
Finally, we described
the interactive workflow
with an example RealityKit
GUI app for ObjectCapture.
Now I will hand it off
to my colleague Dave McKinnon,
who will discuss best practices
with Object Capture.
Dave McKinnon: Thanks, Michael.
Hi, I'm Dave McKinnon,
and I am an engineer
working on the Object Capture
team.
In the next section we’ll
be covering best practices
to help you achieve
the highest-quality results.
First, we'll look into
tips and tricks
for selecting an object that has
the right characteristics.
Followed by a discussion
of how to control
the environmental conditions
and camera
to get the best results.
Next, we'll walk through how
to use the CaptureSample App.
This app allows you
to capture images
in addition to depth data
and gravity information
to recover true scale
and orientation of your object.
We illustrate the use of
this app for both in-hand
as well as turntable capture.
Finally, we will discuss
how to select
the right output detail level
for your use case
as well as providing some links
for further reading.
The first thing to consider
when doing a scan
is picking an object that has
the right characteristics.
For the best results,
pick an object that has
adequate texture detail.
If the object
contains textureless
or transparent regions,
the resulting scan
may lack detail.
Additionally, try to avoid
objects that contain
highly reflective regions.
If the object is reflective,
you will get the best results
by diffusing the lighting
when you scan.
If you plan to flip the object
throughout the capture,
make sure it is rigid
so that it doesn't change shape.
Lastly, if you want
to scan an object
that contains
fine surface detail,
you'll need to use
a high-resolution camera
in addition to having
many close-up photos
of the surface
to recover the detail.
We will now demonstrate
the typical scanning process.
Firstly, for best results,
place your object
on an uncluttered background
so the object
clearly stands out.
The basic process involves
moving slowly around the object
being sure to capture it
uniformly from all sides.
If you would like to reconstruct
the bottom of the object,
flip it and continue
to capture images.
When taking the images,
try to maximize the portion
of the field of view
capturing the object.
This helps the API to recover
as much detail as possible.
One way to do this is to use
portrait or landscape mode
depending on the object's
dimensions and orientation.
Also, try to maintain
a high degree of overlap
between the images.
Depending on the object,
20 to 200 close-up images
should be enough
to get good results.
To help you get started
capturing high-quality photos
with depth and gravity on iOS,
we provide
the CaptureSample App.
This can be used as a starting
point for your own apps.
It is written in SwiftUI
and is part of
the developer documentation.
This app demonstrates
how to take high-quality photos
for Object Capture.
It has a manual
and timed shutter mode.
You could also modify the app
to sync with your turntable.
It demonstrates how to use
the iPhone and iPads
with dual camera to capture
depth data and embed it
right into the output
HEIC files.
The app also shows you
how to save gravity data.
You can view your gallery
to quickly verify
that you have all good-quality
photos with depth and gravity
and delete bad shots.
Capture folders are saved
in the app's Documents folder
where it is easy to copy to your
Mac using iCloud or AirDrop.
There are also help screens
that summarize some of
the best practice guidelines
to get a good capture
that we discuss in this section.
You can also find
this information
in developer documentation.
We recommend turntable capture
to get the best
results possible.
In order to get started,
you'll need a setup
like we have here.
This contains
an iOS device for capture,
but you can also use
a digital SLR;
mechanical turntable
to rotate the object;
some lighting panels
in addition to a light tent.
The goal is to have
uniform lighting
and avoid any hard shadows.
A light tent is a good way
to achieve this.
In this case,
the CaptureSample App
captures images using
the timed shutter mode
synced with the motion
of the turntable.
We can also flip the object
and do multiple turntable passes
to capture the object
from all sides.
Here is the resulting USDZ file
from the turntable capture
shown in Preview on macOS.
Now that we've covered tips
and tricks for capturing images,
let's move to our last section
on how to select
the right output.
There's a variety of different
output detail settings
available for a scan.
Let's take a look.
Here is the table showing
the detail levels.
The supported levels are shown
along the leftd side.
Reduced and Medium
are optimized for use
in web-based
and mobile experiences,
such as viewing 3D content
in AR Quick Look.
They have fewer triangles
and material channels
and consequently
consume less memory.
The Full and Raw are intended
for high-end interactive use
such as computer games
or post-production workflows.
They contain the highest
geometric detail
and give you the flexibility
to choose between baked
and unbaked materials.
Reduced and Medium detail levels
are best for content
that you wish to display on
the internet or mobile device.
In this instance,
Object Capture will compress
the geometric and material
information from the Raw result
down to a level that will be
appropriate for display
in AR apps
or through AR Quick Look.
Both detail levels,
Reduced and Medium,
contain the diffuse, normal,
and ambient occlusion PBR
material channels.
If you would like to display
a single scan in high detail,
Medium will maximize the quality
against the file size
to give you both more geometric
and material detail.
However, if you would like
to display multiple scans
in the same scene,
you should use
the Reduced detail setting.
If you want to learn more about
how to use Object Capture
to create mobile
or web AR experiences,
please see the "AR Quick Look,
meet Object Capture" session.
Exporting with Full output level
is a great choice
for pro workflows.
In this instance, you are
getting the maximum detail
available for your scan.
Full will optimize
the geometry of the scan
and bake the detail
into a PBR material
containing Diffuse, Normal,
Ambient Occlusion, Roughness,
and Displacement information.
We think that this output level will
give you everything you need
for the most challenging
renders.
Lastly, if you don't need
material baking
or you have your own
pipeline for this,
the Raw level will return
the maximum poly count
along with the maximum
diffuse texture detail
for further processing.
If you want to learn more about
how to use Object Capture
for pro workflows on macOS,
please see the "Create 3D
Workflows with USD" session.
Finally, and most importantly,
if you plan to use your scan
on both iOS, as well as macOS,
you can select multiple
detail levels to make sure
you have all the right outputs
for current and future
use cases.
And that's a wrap.
Let's recap
what have we have learned.
First, we covered, through
example, the main concepts
behind the Object Capture API.
We showed you how to create
an Object Capture session
and to use this session
to process your collection of
images to produce a 3D model.
We showed you an example
of how the API can support
an interactive
preview application
to let you adjust the capture
volume and model transform.
Next, we covered best practices
for scanning.
We discussed
what type of objects to use
as well the environment,
lighting, and camera settings
that give best results.
Lastly, we discussed
how to choose
the right output detail settings
for your application.
If you want to learn
how to bring Object Capture
to your own app,
check out both the iOS capture
and macOS CLI processing apps
to get started.
Along with these apps comes
a variety of sample data
that embodies best practice
and can help when planning on
how to capture your own scans.
Additionally, please check out
the detailed documentation
on best practice online
at developer.apple.com,
as well these related
WWDC sessions.
The only thing that remains
is for you to go out
and use Object Capture
for your own scans.
We are excited to see what
objects you will scan and share.
♪