Phew!
[EXHALES]
What a ride we’ve had
at Dub Dub.
Here’s your recap!
[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ "Better Days (Instrumental)"
by DARKMINDS ♪
We learned how to create apps
for research and care...
- We can provide educational
text from the clinicians.
- This cutting-edge research
is going to help so many people.
-...And discovered how to design
for Safari 15’s tab bar
and incorporate
visual intelligence.
- Well that's what we've done
in Safari 15.
- Beautiful!
We also explored how to build
Mac apps with SwiftUI...
- These APIs and concepts
apply to all platforms.
- ...and said hello
to CloudKit Console.
- The next time
I launch the console,
it will bring me straight
to the last container I visited.
- Wow! How is it Friday already?
There was just so much:
async/await, Xcode Cloud,
SharePlay, Metal,
Mindful Cooldowns for coding,
watchOS,
Tiera Fletcher’s amazing talk,
Xcode, gaming, accessibility...
[EXHALES]
We hope you had a great week
and cannot wait to see
what you make this fall.
Ciao!
♪