[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Will] Hello, and welcome
to "Meet In-App Events
on the App Store."
My name is Will Averill,
and I'm an engineering manager
on the App Store Connect team.
The App Store
is more than a store.
It's a daily destination
designed to help users discover
all the rich experiences
that apps have to offer.
So they can find
their next favorite app
or get the most out of the ones
they already have.
This fall, we're taking this
even further with In-App Events.
In-App Events are timely events
within your apps and games,
such as a game competition,
a fitness challenge,
a movie premiere, and more.
In fact,
some of you may already be
running events inside your apps.
For those of you who aren't,
now is a great time
to consider doing so.
That's because this fall,
In-App Events will be
discoverable
right on the App Store.
This a whole new way
to showcase your app's events
and expand their reach.
In this session, I'll show you
how In-App Events work
on the App Store
and how to create them
in App Store Connect.
In-App Events
appear on the App Store
in the new event card.
The design is focused
on letting your content come
front and center and supports
either an image or a video.
The event card also
displays your event name,
a short description,
and a time indicator,
which automatically updates
as the event approaches
and once it starts.
Users who have your app
installed will be able
to jump right into the event
by tapping Open.
This event card is discoverable
across the App Store,
beginning with
your product page.
Here, on your app's
product page,
events are listed in order
of their start and priority.
Their location
on the product page varies,
with events appearing
above screenshots
for users who have
downloaded your app,
and below screenshots
for those who haven't.
Tapping the event card brings up
the event details page.
The event details page,
with its longer description
and larger media asset,
gives users
additional context
around your event.
You can also link directly
to your event details page
by appending the unique event ID
to your app's App Store URL.
In order to build anticipation
for events,
you'll be able to promote them
up to two weeks
before they start.
And users will be able
to easily request
a notification
for when your event begins.
These notifications come
from the App Store
and will launch users directly
into the event inside your app.
If the user doesn't have
your app installed,
they will be directed
to the event details page.
In-App Events are also
discoverable through search.
Users who search for your app
will see the event card
along with the app
if they've downloaded it before.
For those users who haven't
downloaded your app,
they will instead see
screenshots alongside your app.
When users search directly
for your In-App Event,
the event card always appears
next to your app.
On the Games and Apps tabs,
users will see personalized
event recommendations
that can help them stay informed
about the apps and games
they already have,
find something new,
or rediscover an old favorite.
And lastly,
our editorial team will be
curating the most
exciting and innovative events
on the Today, Games,
and Apps tabs.
In-App Events will be
available on iOS and iPadOS.
Now that you've seen
what In-App Events look like
on the App Store,
let me show you
how to create an event
in App Store Connect.
Start by logging in
and navigating
to the app you wanna create
an event for.
Then click the new
In-App Events option
under Features on the left.
This takes you to a high-level
overview of your app's events.
Since you're creating
your first event,
there's not much here
at the moment.
So click
the "Create In-App Event"
to begin the process.
You're then asked
to provide a Reference Name
for your new event.
Your event's reference name
is only visible
within App Store Connect.
Pick a reference name
up to 64 characters long
and click Create.
With your event now created,
you land on the event page.
Here, you'll provide
all the information necessary
to publish your In-App Event
to the App Store.
You'll start by filling in some
of the most fundamental metadata
about your event under
the Event Information section.
All fields under
Event Information are localized.
Click the current language
for a drop-down
of all available localizations.
You should consider broadening
your event's audience
by localizing for as many
languages as possible.
Once you've selected
your intended language,
you'll need to pick
an event name.
This name has a limit
of 30 characters
and will appear
throughout the App Store.
I'll also point out
that as you fill in
the fields on the left,
those values are rendered
in the preview window
on the right.
The preview window shows
both the event card
and event details page as they
will appear on the App Store.
From looking
at the preview window,
you can see that the event name
is shown on both.
The short description is used
on the event card and is used
to briefly summarize your event
with up to 50 characters.
As the name suggests,
the event card media
is the image or video
that appears on your event card.
While the long description
is used
on the event details page.
This has a 120-character limit,
so you can include
additional details,
like potential rewards,
for example.
Next, you'll add
either an image or video
for the event details page.
Videos you use on both
the card and details page
will loop and are limited
to 30 seconds.
Lastly, pick
from the badge options
to define the type of event
you're running.
This badge is
displayed on the card
and details views
on the App Store.
With your Event Information
now finished,
let's continue down the page.
Just like Apps
and In-App Purchases,
you'll need
to define availability
for your In-App Event
on a per Country
or Region basis.
Click the Edit button to open
the Country and Region selector,
something that should be
familiar to most of you.
The only difference here
is that your In-App Event
can only be made available
in Countries where
your parent app is available.
After deciding availability,
you need to schedule your event,
which means defining its start,
end, and publish date and times.
Event start represents
when your event begins
inside your app.
You'll also need to define when
the event ends inside your app.
Together,
the start and end represent
the total duration
of your In-App Event.
Your event can run
as long as 31 days
or as short as 15 minutes.
The next thing you'll need
to consider is when you want
your event to first appear
on the App Store.
This is controlled
by your event's publish date,
which can be up to 14 days
from your event's start.
When your event is published
to the App Store, it will be
discoverable through all of
the ways we discussed earlier,
like on your product page
and in search.
Once your event reaches its end,
it is no longer discoverable
on the App Store
by browsing or searching.
However, users will still
be able to see
your event details page
via the App Store URL
for another 30 days,
after which point,
it is then archived.
This ensures links you've shared
through marketing channels
will still work for a while
after the event ends.
This 30-day period
happens automatically
and is not configurable.
If you want to archive
your In-App Event sooner,
you're able to do so
by editing its availability
in App Store Connect.
Now that you've set up
your event's default scheduling,
you're given the ability
to set custom scheduling
per Country or Region.
This is completely optional,
but to do so,
click the "Customize Dates
and Times" link.
First, select the Countries
or Regions you want to add
custom scheduling for,
and then click Next.
Now, choose one or more
new scheduling dates
to apply to these
specific Countries.
The custom dates need to be
within 48 hours
of your default selections.
In this example, I've bumped
my start and end date
in Europe to account
for the time difference.
Lock in your custom scheduling
by clicking Done.
And with that,
you've just finished configuring
your event's availability
and scheduling.
There's only a few more
pieces of metadata to provide.
This is done
in the final section
of the page,
Additional Information.
First, you can edit
the Reference Name
that you chose earlier.
Next, you need to provide
an Event Deep Link.
This link makes it possible
for users
with your app installed
to quickly jump
from the App Store
into your In-App Event.
Your event deep link can
either be a universal link
or a custom URL
that opens directly
to a particular place
in your app.
In order for your link
to function correctly,
avoid using URL shorteners
or other services
that add unnecessary redirects.
With the Event Purpose field,
you can indicate
whether your event is meant
to attract new users,
keep your active users informed,
or bring lapsed users
back to your app.
Many events are equally
suited for all these purposes,
so that's the default selection.
Your selection here
is one of the factors
that the App Store uses to offer
personalized recommendations.
To help your event reach
the people it's intended for,
the App Store incorporates
app-usage information.
That data is processed
on the device
to minimize data collection
and enhance user privacy.
Note that regardless
of which purpose you select,
your event will be discoverable
by all App Store users.
Here you can indicate
your event's priority level,
which affects how it's ordered
on your app's product page.
High-priority events are shown
in front of normal ones,
and events are sorted
by their start time
within these respective groups.
Next, you'll indicate
whether your event requires
an In-App Purchase
or a Subscription.
This information is displayed
on your event card
and event details page.
Make sure your selection here
is accurate to set
proper expectation with users
and to ensure
a seamless review process.
And finally, you can update
your event's Primary Language.
By default, this is set
to your app's primary language.
With that, you've now fully
configured your In-App Event.
Make sure you click
the Save button
to persist everything
you just filled out.
After saving,
you'll notice your In-App Event
is listed in the "draft" state.
Draft events are simply
any event that you've started,
but haven't yet added
for review.
To publish your event
to the App Store,
it must first be reviewed.
To add your event for review,
navigate back to the event page
and click the button
in the top right.
You'll be able to add
an event for review anytime
after you've filled in
all the required metadata.
There's no need to create
a new version of your app
or upload a new binary.
As you just saw,
events begin in the draft state
and can be reviewed
once fully configured.
After they pass through review,
events enter the approved state.
Once approved,
events automatically publish
to the App Store
according to their scheduling.
Approved events
with a future publish date
are labeled "Set to Publish,"
while those
with past publish dates
are marked "Published."
After an event's end date
is reached,
the event moves
to the "Past" state.
While no longer published
to the App Store,
remember that your event
details page is still
link accessible on the App Store
for an additional 30 days.
And finally, after 30 days
in the "Past" state,
your In-App event moves
to its final state, Archived,
and is no longer
accessible via link.
Now that you understand
the event state life cycle,
let's discuss
two important limits.
First, your app can have
ten events
in the approved state.
And second,
your app can have five events
published to the App Store
at a time.
You won't be able to add
an event for review
if its scheduling would cause
either limit to be exceeded.
After your events have been
published to the App Store,
it's important to measure
how they're performing.
So there's a robust
new set of capabilities
to do this in App Analytics.
Your event page
in App Store Connect
will link directly
to your event in App Analytics.
From there, you'll find
many important metrics
allowing you to measure
your event's effectiveness.
First, you'll be able to track
your impressions,
which shows how many people
saw your event on the App Store.
You'll also be able
to drill down further,
to figure out where users
saw your event,
like on your product page,
in search, or other locations.
Next, you'll see metrics
around how many users
opened your app or opened
the event details page.
In addition, you'll see
how many users downloaded
or redownloaded your app
as a result of your event.
And lastly,
you'll see how many users
enabled notifications
for your In-App Event.
There's additional insights
available in App Analytics
that I didn't cover,
so if you're interested
in learning more,
be sure to check out
the What's new
in App Analytics session.
And finally, we know
how important it is
for you as developers
to automate
as much of your app workflow
process as possible.
That's why
I'm pleased to announce,
all the In-App Event
functionality I just discussed
will be supported
by the App Store Connect API.
The full spec will be
provided later this year.
I've covered a lot of
new information in this session.
First, I showed you
how users will discover
In-App Events on the App Store.
Next, I walked you through
how to set up
your In-App Events
in App Store Connect.
And finally,
we covered how you'll be able
to measure their performance
in App Analytics.
I can't wait to see
all of the exciting events
within your apps, now
discoverable on the App Store.
And I hope you start thinking
about how you can bring
In-App Events to your own apps
if you haven't already.
In-App Events launch
later this fall.
Thanks for watching
this session,
and please enjoy
the rest of your conference!
[upbeat music]