[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Peter Tsoi: Hello and welcome
to "Design for
spatial interaction."
My name is Peter,
and I'm a designer
on the Apple Design team.
Together with my colleagues
Arian, Taylor, Linus, and Pedro,
we're excited to share
some of the considerations
that guide how we approach
designing spatial interactions.
We'll share lessons learned
while creating interactions
for AirTag, HomePod mini,
and iPhone,
and also give you tips
and tricks that will help you
apply those principles
while designing interactions
of your own.
Let's get started.
As our devices have evolved,
so too has the way
that we interact with them.
Early computers were operated
only using a keyboard
and interfaces
were entirely text based.
Users memorized
abstract commands
and relied on arrow keys
to move around the screen
and express their intent.
Nowadays, most people
use their keyboards together
with graphical user interfaces
and a mouse.
These innovations
removed a layer of abstraction
and allowed people
to use the mouse
to point, click, and drag
to more directly
express their intent.
Later, Multi-Touch
brought the digital world
to people's fingertips,
removing yet another
layer of abstraction
and allowing people
to touch their music,
their photos,
and the mobile web.
Today we want to talk about
a class of interactions
that go beyond the bounds
of a single device
and ways to use the capabilities
of the latest Apple devices
to help users interact
more directly
with their physical
surroundings.
Some of these interactions
may already feel familiar,
like how you can
pay for a coffee
by holding your phone or watch
close to a payment terminal.
Or how you can quickly check the
battery level on your AirPods
just by flipping open the case
when it's near your phone.
These human-scale
interactions --
the ones that happen
between devices nearby --
have the ability to remove
layers of abstraction
and allow users
to interact more directly
with their surroundings.
And with the enhanced
spatial awareness
enabled by the U1 chip
in the latest Apple products,
we've been able to deliver
more capable and responsive
experiences for AirTag,
HomePod mini, and iPhone.
And now, thanks to new APIs
and the ability to interact
with third-party hardware
that you build in iOS 15,
you can now bring
these kinds of experiences
to your own products.
In designing these interactions,
we learned that
it's important to consider
distance and ability,
provide continuous feedback,
and embrace the physical action.
Let's dive right in.
In iOS 13, we made it
even easier to share content
by bringing spatial awareness
to the share sheet.
Using information about
who you are facing
or physically close to, combined
with on-device knowledge
about the frequency and recency
of your communications,
allows your device
to intelligently predict
who you are trying
to share with.
This is a great example of how
existing features in your apps
can be made more intelligent
with spatial awareness.
You don't have to build
an entirely new experience
to take advantage
of these new capabilities.
When incorporating
spatial awareness
into existing features,
be mindful
that these capabilities
are not available on all devices
and your design
should accommodate
varying levels of capabilities.
With the share sheet,
all devices are able
to look for others
using Bluetooth and Wi-Fi.
However, iPhones with
the U1 spatial awareness chip
take this a step further
by prioritizing others
that you are facing
or are very close to.
Of course, spatial awareness
can be used
to not just enhance
existing experiences;
it can help build
entirely new ones.
Next, Arian will share
how these same concepts
apply to AirTag.
Arian Behzadi: With AirTag,
we will show you
how your design can adapt
to accommodate different
distances and abilities.
In this example, imagine I've
misplaced an item I care about.
I retrace my steps and realize
I'm not sure where it is.
I use my iPhone
and feel relieved
that I can see
where it is on a map.
Previously, I'd only be able
to get to the general vicinity
of this item,
but now my iPhone can guide me
at a scale
that is much more helpful.
In fact, the same button
that gave me directions
when I was far away
has now become a button
that will help me find it
as I'm closer.
Augmenting elements
of the design
when at the appropriate scale
is a great way for people
to discover and use
these new abilities.
As iPhone is locating my AirTag,
I'm invited to move around
and search my surroundings.
Once connected,
an arrow forms
and points directly to where
I need to go. [LOW CHIME]
As I align with the direction
of my AirTag,
the design lights up
to reinforce this.
We emphasize
this facing direction
and provide guidance
when not facing this direction.
In a subtle way,
this distinction also scales
based on distance.
When further away,
we found that it is really hard
to remain facing
a specific direction.
To remedy this, we are actually
more generous
with the angle that iPhone
considers facing.
As you get closer, this
forgiveness becomes more narrow
to become
more and more specific.
This happens
without you noticing [CHIME]
as you're gently guided
to your AirTag.
When you're finally within
arm's reach of your AirTag,
the arrow defers
to a form of feedback
that we find much more effective
at this small scale. [CHIME]
The design transforms
to highlight haptic feedback
as you pass your iPhone over
where your AirTag
might be hiding.
With this example,
we've shown you
how your design can transform
based on distance,
whether you're very far away
or within millimeters.
Think about how
your design can best
accommodate varying abilities
we all share as humans.
Be forgiving with angles
at a distance,
and consider changing
the dominant form of feedback
to one that works best
at smaller scale.
Next, I'd like to hand it
over to Taylor
to show you just how critical
this continuous feedback is
when designing these kinds
of interactions.
Taylor Carrigan: Thanks, Arian.
We've gone to great lengths
to make onscreen interactions
fluidly and dynamically respond
to touch input,
but this continuous feedback
is even more critical
when interacting in the physical
world where your device
becomes a more literal
extension of your body.
The right type of feedback
applied and choreographed
at the right time
throughout these interactions
can help make the feature
you're designing discoverable,
provides instruction,
and can communicate
success or failure.
It also acknowledges
that our movements
can start, stop,
and be interrupted at any time.
We're going to talk about
how you can use feedback
you can see, [CHIME] hear,
and feel
to help connect your interaction
to the physical world.
Though dependent
on the capabilities
of the devices used,
there are multiple
types of feedback
worth considering
and using together.
These can include
visual feedback --
such as user interface changes,
lights and hardware
interactions,
and visual feedback coordinated
across both devices --
audio feedback [CHIME],
and haptic feedback.
We'll also talk about
natural interruption
and cancellation and
the importance these play
in creating a successful
interaction between two devices.
Let's look first at how
different types of feedback
help make the transfer of music
to HomePod mini
intuitive and satisfying.
[MUSIC PLAYING QUIETLY]
With HomePod mini,
we use multiple types
of feedback to establish
a physical relationship
with your iPhone,
provide direction,
and ultimately confirm
that your music has been
successfully transferred.
We achieved this by creating
two discrete boundaries
around the HomePod,
and respond to your movement
across and between them.
Feedback is provided when your
iPhone reaches the first zone,
between the first and second
to instruct you to move closer
or allow you to cancel
the interaction,
and finally when your iPhone
reaches the second zone,
to confirm and transfer music.
Feedback is continuously
provided
from the moment iPhone reaches
the first distance threshold.
On screen, the banner position,
scale, and modality
created by the background blur
increase fluidly
and in direct response
to your distance
from the HomePod.
When designing
visual feedback,
look for opportunities for the
onscreen elements to animate
in a way that feels related
to your physical movements --
like how the movement
of this banner
is related to the linear
movement of your hand
towards or away
from the HomePod.
Haptic feedback complements this
with a physical acknowledgement
that the two devices
are aware of each other,
and increases in strength
to encourage you
to continue moving closer.
In addition to the feedback
on iPhone,
HomePod mini acknowledges
the proximity of iPhone
through the animations
on the top of the speaker.
Great spatial interactions
use natural body movements
to not only confirm
but also to cancel actions.
[MUSIC PLAYING QUIETLY]
When moving an iPhone
near a HomePod mini,
clear and continuous feedback
that tracks your distance
from the HomePod
makes it clear that
you can simply pull away
to cancel or interrupt
the gesture.
This allowed us to create
an interaction that can be done
entirely without
looking at the display
or requiring additional
onscreen buttons
to cancel or confirm
user intent.
All of these aspects
are driven by and respond to
the movement of your body
as it brings iPhone
closer to or farther away
from the HomePod.
The directness
of the relationship
between someone's movements
in the physical world
and what they're seeing,
hearing, and feeling
on one or both devices
are critical
when designing
a spatial interaction.
Next, Linus will talk about
the unique constraints
of providing feedback
while finding an AirTag.
Linus Persson: HomePod mini
is a good example
of how to choreograph
feedback across two devices,
both capable of expressing
rich feedback.
For designs where
this is not a possibility,
you might have to rely
more heavily on a single device.
Since AirTag helps you
find an item when it's lost,
the experience is designed
for scenarios
when it's hidden from view.
Let's revisit the finding
experience we saw before,
this time with an eye on how
we provide continuous feedback
across the senses using iPhone's
rich haptic, visual,
and acoustic capabilities.
A spatial interaction
feels great when it's responsive
and follows your motion.
That means responding
to movements that are big
as well as ones
that are subtle.
Even as iPhone
is connecting to the AirTag,
the interface gently rotates
and responds as I turn,
implying the nature
of the interaction
that is about to follow.
These dots also
provide the building blocks
for a continuously
adapting experience.
Once connected, the distance
between me and my AirTag
also appears.
This distance responds
incredibly precisely
as I walk in any direction.
It instantly updates
and tells me
if I'm walking toward, or away,
from where I want to go.
As I walk around, the same dots
smoothly form an arrow
pointing me
in the right direction.
This moment is reinforced
further using a delicate haptic
and sound to mark
its importance.
[LOW TONES]
It feels as though the arrow
floats in space as my iPhone
moves around it.
As you saw earlier,
the interface reinforces moments
when I am on the right path.
[LOW TONES] When facing
the direction of my lost AirTag,
the screen boldly lights up
and I also feel and hear
the arrow snap into place.
By responding to every step
and subtle turn,
the design feels tightly coupled
with me and the space I'm in.
When designing
your spatial interaction,
consider how people
will connect their own movement
with what they experience
on the device.
Try to make a clear link
between action and feedback
in a way that is mindful
of the particular motion.
Just ahead of the arrow,
there's a dot that starts
to pulse in my hand.
The pace of this pulse
picks up as I get closer,
and the haptics become
tighter and crisper
[CHIME]
along with it.
If I break away
from this direction,
the pulse stops and
the interface guides me back.
If I walk far enough away
from my AirTag,
the arrow disassembles
to mark the loss of signal.
Nuance in moments like these
also provide important
and very helpful guidance.
Be mindful of how feedback
can complement human motions
that are varied
and unpredictable,
and build a design
that is resilient
and can adaptively change
to accommodate the way we move.
When within arm's reach,
we visually zoom in on this dot,
and the pulse changes
to continuous haptic feedback
that shifts with my movement.
This haptic response changes
in character as I move closer
and further away.
I can move my iPhone over
where AirTag might be
and sense through my hand more
precisely where it's hiding.
Note that we do not use sound
for this part of the experience,
as haptic feedback does
a much more effective job.
As with any continuous
feedback,
your design should be mindful
of how haptics, sound,
and visuals work together
in concert across the senses.
Similarly to the way
we perceive what we see,
hear and feel in the world
as one holistic experience.
When designing your interaction,
it is important to consider
the different strengths
of each form of feedback
and how they can
be used together.
Seek to provide a visual layer
of continuous feedback
tied to physical motion
and use additional feedback
to emphasize important moments
in your interaction.
Use haptics and sound
judiciously
and at the right levels,
with a repeatable
cause and effect
so it is clear what is being
communicated.
In addition to working
with feedback in this way,
keep in mind that your design
will complement
a physical action.
And to speak about this
is my colleague Pedro.
Pedro Mari: In the case
of HomePods,
we use spatial awareness
to make the task
of selecting a speaker
more natural.
Oftentimes, I'll be listening
to some music,
and I'll want to move it
from my iPhone
to a better speaker near me.
Previously, if I wanted
to play this song
on a different speaker, I'd have
to go into the AirPlay list.
In this list, all of the other
devices in my space
are presented equally,
whether they are near me or not.
What I am really
interested in, though,
is this particular HomePod.
With this new human-scale
interaction,
I can finally transfer a song
to this HomePod
without navigating
an onscreen UI,
or having to interact with the
screen at all, for that matter.
We provide visual feedback
on the HomePod itself
to show that the music
is about to be transferred.
[MUSIC PLAYING QUIETLY]
The light modulates precisely
with my movement, growing in
intensity as I approach,
and shrinking as I move away.
[MUSIC PLAYS ON IPHONE]
[MUSIC PLAYS ON HOMEPOD]
[MUSIC STOPS]
And of course,
the ultimate confirmation
of the transfer
is the music playing
from the speaker itself.
By embracing
the physical action,
a previously intangible
experience
now feels completely tangible,
visceral, and instinctive.
Think of ways
that your own interfaces
can support
a natural physical motion,
rather than an abstracted
list of options.
Try to make your experiences
and designs
defer to the physical task
at hand.
Also, consider how the concepts
of "this" and "that"
can be finally used to create
a more natural experience
that aligns with how we think.
Make sure to provide
instant and continuous feedback
on both devices.
Specifically, be very clear
on the target device
that an action is happening,
as this is where your attention
will be naturally drawn to.
Similarly,
when finding a lost item,
my attention is meant to be
directed at the world around me
and where it might be hiding.
Playing sound from the AirTag
gives me an immediate sense
of its place in space,
drawing my attention
to my surroundings.
[CHIMES, BEEPING]
When it comes to the visual
feedback on iPhone itself,
make sure it can be read
when performing a task
that extends beyond the bounds
of the display.
We often design our interfaces
to work in this manner
when we anticipate it will
be viewed in the periphery.
For instance, when using
turn-by-turn navigation,
the typography of when and where
I need to take my next turn
is bigger and bolder
than other notifications
that might occupy
the same space.
The buttons and active area
of TV Remote are extra large
and are designed for your eyes
to be directed to the TV itself,
rather than the control for it.
The digits and operation buttons
in Calculator
are large and bold,
as we anticipate
you might be referencing numbers
on a restaurant bill
to calculate a tip,
for instance.
As in the previous examples,
the type size we use
for the distance
when finding an AirTag
is set much larger
than in other parts
of the system,
and the entire UI
revolves around
the central element
of a giant arrow.
[LOW TONE]
Bold color changes
can be read in my periphery.
Sound reinforces
key moments and states --
I can actually feel the distance
getting smaller as I walk
without ever having
to look at the screen.
This ultimately supports
a more natural pose as I use it.
[LOW TONES]
[CHIME]
When in arm's reach,
haptic feedback
can guide me closer
even if the screen
is not in my periphery.
[CHIME]
These large and bold UI choices
enable those
with varying abilities
to access the experience
as well.
Make sure your design uses
more than one mode of feedback,
and that each one is salient
enough to be clearly understood.
Your design shouldn't
demand too much attention
to communicate its information
or compete with
the primary task.
Lastly, try to reinforce
good states
and celebrate positive progress
along the way to completing
a spatial interaction.
Always consider
the physical action
your experience
is complementing.
And now, back to Peter!
Peter: We've covered
a lot today.
We've seen how new
and existing experiences
become more intelligent
and relevant
when they consider the device's
context and surroundings.
You learned how responsive
and continuous feedback
can help users discover
and use these new experiences.
And finally, we took a look
at techniques
that allow your design
to be effectively experienced
peripherally
while keeping attention
on the physical surroundings.
We hope that you are
just as excited as we are
about how spatial awareness
can simplify
and bring more directness to
interactions between our devices
and our users'
physical surroundings.
For more information, be sure
to visit developer.apple.com
where you'll find
the Human Interface Guidelines
for spatial interactions,
as well as technical information
about how to implement
these types of interactions.
We can't wait to see
what you'll build next.
♪