[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Brady White: Hi, I’m Brady.
I’m an engineer
on the Fitness team.
Thanks for joining me.
There are lots of great workout
apps already available
in the App Store.
Apple Watch is an amazing device
capable of tracking all sorts
of fitness activity.
It can track distance
and elevation
on those challenging bike rides.
You can monitor your heart rate
and energy burned
during intense workouts.
For swimming, it can even detect
stroke type and count laps.
All of this and more
is available for you
to build a great workout app.
Let’s take a look at
what we will be covering today.
This session is a Code-Along.
We'll go over what that means
and how you can participate.
We'll build our workout views
in SwiftUI.
Then, we'll integrate HealthKit
to our views.
We'll also show you how
to support the Always On state.
I'm excited,
let's get started.
This session is a code-along.
We will build a workout app
together from scratch.
While you get your Xcode ready,
let's cover
a couple of concepts.
What is a workout app?
A workout app tracks
fitness activity
during a workout.
A workout can be started
with a single tap.
While the workout is in session,
live metrics are displayed,
such as elapsed time,
energy burned, heart rate,
and distance.
When the workout ends,
a summary shows the metrics
recorded for the workout.
This is what
we will build today.
Let’s get started building
our workout views.
Let’s open Xcode
and start a new project.
Click
Create a new Xcode project,
watchOS, Watch App,
click Next.
Give your workout app a name,
such as "MyWorkouts".
Ensure Interface is SwiftUI,
and language is Swift
and click Next.
Find a location for your project
and click Create.
Let’s hide the inspector
and resize our canvas.
Let’s click Resume to see
what our app looks like,
using Xcode previews.
Great, our SwiftUI app is ready.
Let’s provide a way for someone
to start their workout
with a StartView.
A workout can be started
with just a single tap.
The list view
with carousel-style layout
will provide a list of workouts
that scrolls vertically
with a great depth effect.
Our list of workouts will
include bike, run, and walk.
Let’s create our StartView.
Let’s rename "ContentView"
to "StartView".
Command-click on ContentView,
click Rename,
Enter "StartView"
as the new name.
Notice that in
MyWorkoutsApp.swift
StartView is now
NavigationView’s root view.
Click Rename.
Let’s define an array
of workout types
to display
in our StartView’s list.
First, let’s import HealthKit
to get access to
HKWorkoutActivityType.
Next, let’s add our array
of workout types.
Our workout list will have
HKWorkoutActivityTypes
of cycling, running,
and walking.
Let’s make
HKWorkoutActivityType
accessible to our list
by extending the
HKWorkoutActivityType enum
to conform to
the identifiable protocol
and add a name variable.
The ID-computed variable will
return the rawValue of the enum.
The name variable will switch
through the cases
to return a name
like “Run”, “Bike”, or “Walk”.
Let’s add a List view
to our StartView’s body
to display the list of workouts.
The list uses the workoutTypes
variable as its model.
A NavigationLink is displayed
for each workoutType.
A NavigationLink defines
a destination
for a navigation-based
interface.
For now, the destination
will be a text view.
We'll set these navigation
links up later
to make sure they are tracking
the right workout.
Padding makes
the navigation links taller
to give them a larger tap area
to easily start a workout.
The list uses
a carousel listStyle
to provide a depth effect
when scrolling.
The navigationBarTitle
will display “Workouts”.
Let’s click Resume to see
a preview of our StartView.
Click Live Preview
to be able to scroll.
Scroll up to see the
carousel ListStyle depth effect.
Looks great.
The workout session will be
presented as a modal experience.
During a workout,
people typically need
only session-specific
functionality.
They don't need to review
the list of workouts
or access other parts
of your app.
Offering the most important
items in a modal experience
can help people
manage their session
while minimizing distraction.
People who use workout apps
on Apple Watch
expect the views
to be in this order.
On the left,
our controls view has buttons
that control
the in-progress session
such as End, Pause, and Resume.
In the center, metrics appear
on a dedicated screen
that people can read
at a glance.
On the right,
media playback controls
allow media to be controlled
during a workout.
A TabView on watchOS switches
between multiple child views
when someone
swipes left or right.
A TabView also provides
a page indicator
at the bottom of the view.
A TabView will work great
to display our in-session views.
Let’s create a SessionPagingView
with a TabView
for our three workout
session views.
Click File > New > File...
SwiftUI View, click Next,
name this "SessionPagingView"
and click Create.
Let’s create a Tab enum to model
each view that can be selected
in our TabView.
The Tab enum has three cases:
controls, metrics,
and nowPlaying.
We’ve also added a @State
variable named "selection"
to provide the binding
for the TabView’s selection.
Selection’s default value
will be metrics,
so that when the workout starts,
the metrics view is displayed.
Let’s add the TabView.
The TabView’s selection
parameter uses a binding
to our selection state variable.
Text views are placeholders
for each view
until they are created.
Each of the views have a tag
so they can be selected.
Let’s click Resume
and see what our
SessionPagingView looks like.
Click Live Preview to be able
to swipe between the views.
Notice the Metrics text view
is displayed first,
because SessionPagingView's
selection variable's
default value is metrics.
Swiping to the left
shows the Controls text view.
Swiping all the way to the right
shows the Now Playing
text view.
Great!
While the workout is running,
live metrics are displayed.
When a session requires
movement, like running,
your app should use large font
sizes and arrange text
so that the most important
information is easy to read.
Our MetricsView will display
elapsed time, active energy,
current heart rate,
and distance.
HealthKit has many more
HKQuantityTypes
available for you to use.
Let’s create the MetricsView.
Click File > New > File
SwiftUI View, click Next,
name this "MetricsView"
and click Create.
A VStack will contain
our four metric Text views.
The Text views have
default values for now
until we connect
these Text views to our model.
Let’s make elapsed time
the focal point by giving it
a yellow foregroundColor
and semibold fontWeight.
The active energy text view
creates a measurement
using a default value
in energy unit kilocalories.
The Measurement uses
a new formatted function
which abbreviates the unit,
usage is workout
for workout energy burned,
and numberFormat
has zero fractionLength
to trim fractions.
The heart rate text view
uses a default value
formatted with fractionLength
zero.
It appends “bpm” --
for beats per minute --
to the formatted string.
The distance text view
uses a default value
with UnitLength.meters.
The measurement is formatted
with abbreviated units.
usage is road, which displays
naturally progressing
imperial or metric units
based on locale.
We’ll use a system font
of title with rounded design,
monospacedDigits,
and lowercaseSmallCaps.
We want our metrics to
be aligned to the leading edge,
so we’ve given the VStack
a frame view modifier
with maxWidth infinity,
and leading alignment.
We want to allow content
of this VStack
to extend all the way
to the bottom of the screen.
To allow this, we ignore
the bottom safe area.
We want our metrics
to be aligned
to the navigation bar title,
so we've used
scenePadding() to do this.
We want our elapsed time
Text view
to format the elapsed time
properly
and hide or show subseconds
based on the Always On state.
To do this, let’s create
an ElapsedTimeView
and create a custom
ElapsedTimeFormatter.
Click File > New > File,
SwiftUI View, click Next,
name it "ElapsedTimeView",
and click Create.
Our ElapsedTimeView
has elapsedTime,
which is a TimeInterval,
defaulted to zero.
showSubseconds is a Boolean
argument defaulted to true.
timeFormatter is
an ElapsedTimeFormatter
state variable
that we define below.
The View’s body contains
a Text view
that casts the elapsedTime
to an NSNumber
so that the timeFormatter
can use it.
Text view has
a semibold fontWeight.
When showSubseconds
changes, the timeFormatter’s
showSubseconds variable
also changes.
The ElapsedTimeFormatter
is a custom formatter
that uses a
DateComponentsFormatter.
We want elapsed time
to show minutes and seconds
and pad zeros.
The showSubseconds variable
dictates if subseconds
are shown.
We override the string
for value function,
which returns
an optional String.
The first guard ensures
the value is a TimeInterval.
The second guard ensures
the componentsFormatter
returned a string.
If showSubseconds is true,
calculate the subseconds
by getting
the truncatedRemainder
by dividingBy 1,
then multiplying by 100.
Use a localized
decimalSeparator,
then return a formattedString,
appending the subseconds.
If showSubseconds is false,
then just return
the formattedString
without subseconds.
Click resume to see a preview
of our ElapsedTimeView.
Looks good.
Minutes has zeros padded
on the left side of the colon.
Seconds has zeros padded
on the right side of the colon.
Subseconds are displayed
after the decimal.
Let’s add the ElapsedTimeView
to MetricsView.
Click MetricsView.
Replace the elapsed time
Text view
with the ElapsedTimeView.
Let’s preview our MetricsView.
Looks great!
The ControlsView has buttons
that control
the in-progress session,
such as End, Pause, and Resume.
When the End button is tapped,
the workout summary
will be displayed.
When the Pause button is tapped,
the workout will pause
and the MetricsView
will be displayed.
Let’s create the ControlsView.
Click File > New > File,
SwiftUI View,
name this "ControlsView"
and click Create.
Let’s add the End
and Pause buttons.
An HStack contains two VStacks
where each VStack contains
a button and a text view.
The End button’s label is an
Image with systemName “xmark”.
The button has a red tint
and uses title2 font
to increase the size
of the symbol.
The text view below
has an “End” string.
The pause button uses an image
with systemName “pause”.
It has a yellow tint.
The text view below
has a “Pause” string.
Click Resume to preview
the ControlsView.
Looks great.
The NowPlayingView
provides media playback controls
while the workout is in session.
This includes controls
for third-party apps
that are currently
playing media.
Let’s add the NowPlayingView.
Select SessionPagingView.
The NowPlayingView
is provided by WatchKit.
Let’s import WatchKit.
Let’s replace our text views
with ControlsView, MetricsView,
and the NowPlayingView.
The NowPlayingView is a SwiftUI
view provided by WatchKit.
It’s that simple.
Click Resume to see a preview
of SessionPagingView.
In Preview, we can see
our MetricsView.
Swipe to the left
to see the ControlsView.
Swipe all the way
to the right...
...to see the NowPlayingView.
Let’s go back to our StartView
and change the destination
of the NavigationLink
to SessionPagingView.
Select StartView.
Update the destination
to SessionPagingView.
A Summary screen confirms
that a workout is finished
and displays
the recorded information.
We will enhance the summary
by including Activity Rings
so that people can easily check
their current progress.
Let’s create the Summary view.
Click File > New > File,
SwiftUI View, click Next,
name this "SummaryView"
and click Create.
Let’s create a custom
SummaryMetricView
that describes the metric
and its value.
SummaryMetricView takes a title
that describes the metric
and a value string
of the metric.
Body contains the two text views
and a divider.
The text view showing
the metric value
uses a title system font
with rounded design
and lowercaseSmallCaps.
It uses the accentColor
as its foregroundColor.
Let’s create the workout
duration formatter
for the SummaryView.
durationFormatter
is a DateComponentsFormatter
that displays hours, minutes,
and seconds separated by colons
and pads zeros.
Let’s add the SummaryMetricViews
and the Done button
to our SummaryView.
A ScrollView and VStack contain
our four SummaryMetricViews
and Done button.
Total Time text view uses
the durationFormatter
to display hours,
minutes, and seconds,
separated by colons.
Total Distance SummaryMetricView
uses Measurement
with a default value
that is formatted
using an abbreviated unit.
usage is road, which displays
naturally progressing
imperial or metric units
based on locale.
Total Energy SummaryMetricView
uses Measurement
with a default value
and energy unit of kilocalories.
It is formatted
using an abbreviated unit.
usage is workout
for workout energy,
and numberFormat has a precision
with fractionLength zero.
Average Heart Rate
SummaryMetricView
uses a default value
formatted with number precision,
fractionLength of zero,
and appends "bpm"
for beats per minute.
We’ll provide actual
workout values later
for the SummaryMetricViews.
We want the text views
and dividers
to align to the navigation
bar title
so we've used .scenePadding()
on the VStack.
The navigationTitle
will be "Summary"
and will display inline
in the navigation bar.
Next let’s add Activity Rings
to the workout summary.
Click File > New > File,
Swift File, click Next,
name this "ActivityRingsView"
and click Create.
Import HealthKit to get access
to the HKHealthStore.
Import SwiftUI to get access to
WKInterfaceObjectRepresentable.
The ActivityRingsView
struct conforms to
WKInterfaceObjectRepresentable.
The healthStore constant
is assigned at initialization.
Two functions are required
to conform to the protocol:
makeWKInterfaceObject
and updateWKInterfaceObject.
Inside makeWKInterfaceObject,
we declare the
activityRingsObject
which is a
WKInterfaceActivityRing.
Next we create the predicate
for the HKActivitySummaryQuery
and use date components
for today.
Then we create the query
and handle the result,
which sets the activity summary
on the activityRingsObject
on the main queue.
Then execute the query
on the HKHealthStore.
Finally, return
the activityRingsObject.
Let’s add the ActivityRingsView
to the SummaryView.
Click SummaryView.
Let's import HealthKit
to get access to HKHealthStore.
Next, let's add a Text view
and an ActivityRingsView
above the Done button.
We’ve added a Text view
and an ActivityRingsViews
with a frame width
and height of 50.
We’ll create
an HKHealthStore for now.
Later, we’ll reuse one.
Let’s preview our SummaryView.
Click Resume.
Click Live Preview
to be able to scroll.
See each of our
SummaryMetricViews,
Activity Rings,
and Done button.
Let’s talk about
HealthKit integration.
HealthKit provides
built-in functionality
to track fitness activity
during the workout
and save that workout
to HealthKit.
This saves you time
as a developer,
and your customers will have
all their workouts
saved to one location.
HK workout session prepares
the device’s sensors
for data collection so that
you can accurately collect data
that’s relevant to the workout,
like calories and heart rate.
It also allows your application
to run in the background
when the workout is active.
HKLiveWorkoutBuilder will create
and save an HKWorkout object.
It automatically
collects samples
and events for you.
To learn more, check out
the “New ways to work
with workouts” session.
Let’s see what the data flow
will be for our app.
WorkoutManager will
be responsible
for interfacing with HealthKit.
It interfaces with
an HKWorkoutSession
to start, pause,
and end the workout.
It interfaces with an
HKLiveWorkoutBuilder
to listen for workout samples
and provide that data
to our views.
WorkoutManager will be
an environment object.
An environment object
invalidates the current view
whenever the observable
object changes.
We will assignMyWorkoutsApp’s
NavigationView
the WorkoutManager
environmentObject,
which will propagate
WorkoutManager to views
in the NavigationView’s
view hierarchy.
Views will then declare
an @EnvironmentObject
to gain access to WorkoutManager
in the environment.
Let’s create the WorkoutManager.
Click File > New > File,
Swift File, click Next,
name this "WorkoutManager"
and click Create.
Import HealthKit
so that WorkoutManager has
access to HealthKit’s APIs.
Then define the WorkoutManager
class which is an NSObject
that conforms to
the ObservableObject protocol.
We want to give all of our views
access to WorkoutManager.
We do this by assigning
WorkoutManager
as an environment object
on MyWorkoutsApp’s
NavigationView.
Select MyWorkoutsApp.
Add workoutManager
as a StateObject.
Add the environmentObject
view modifier
to the NavigationView.
When a NavigationView is
assigned an environmentObject,
it automatically passes
the environmentObject
to views in its view hierarchy.
Let’s set up
our navigation model.
Select WorkoutManager.
WorkoutManager will manage
the selected workout,
which is an optional
HKWorkoutActivityType.
We’ve added
the selectedWorkout variable
to track the selected workout.
Now our StartView’s
NavigationLink
needs to bind its selection
to WorkoutManager’s
selectedWorkout.
Select StartView.
Add workoutManager
EnvironmentObject to StartView.
Let’s update NavigationLink
with tag and selection.
tag is the workoutType.
selection is a binding
to selectedWorkout
on workoutManager.
Now, whenever
a workout is tapped,
selectedWorkout on
workoutManager will update.
Now let’s start
an HKWorkoutSession
and HKLiveWorkoutBuilder
when a workout is selected.
Select WorkoutManager.
Add the HKHealthStore,
HKWorkoutSession,
and HKLiveWorkoutBuilder.
Now, let’s create a startWorkout
function to start the workout.
The startWorkout function
takes a workoutType parameter.
A HKWorkoutConfiguration is
created using the workoutType.
For our app, all of our workouts
will be outdoor.
Note that location type
determines how
the HKWorkoutSession and
HKLiveWorkoutBuilder behaves.
For example,
an outdoor cycling activity
generates accurate
location data,
while an indoor cycling
activity does not.
Create the HKWorkoutSession
using the healthStore
and configuration.
Assign builder to the session’s
associatedWorkoutBuilder.
This is done in a do-catch block
to handle any errors thrown.
Assign the builder’s dataSource
to an HKLiveWorkoutDataSource
using the healthStore
and workoutConfiguration.
An HKLiveWorkoutDataSource
automatically provides live data
from an active workout session.
Create a startDate,
call startActivity
on the session,
and beginCollection
on the builder.
Whenever
selectedWorkout changes,
let’s call startWorkout.
selectedWorkout
can be nil.
Use a guard statement
to only call startWorkout
when selectedWorkout is not nil.
Before our app can create
a workout session,
we need to set up HealthKit
and request authorization
to read and share any health
data our app intends to use.
Let's add a function
to request authorization.
For workout sessions,
we must request permission
to share workout types.
We also want to read any data
types automatically recorded
by Apple Watch
as part of the session.
[CLICKING]
We also want permission to read
the Activity Rings summary.
Then call requestAuthorization
on the healthStore.
Let’s have the StartView
request authorization
from HealthKit
when the view appears.
Click StartView.
On appear, workoutManager’s
requestAuthorization function
will be called.
Let’s enable HealthKit
for our extension.
Select MyWorkouts's
project file...
...MyWorkouts WatchKit
Extension,
Signing & Capabilities.
Select Add Capability,
scroll down, select HealthKit.
Apps with an active
workout session
can run in the background,
so you need to add
the background modes capability
to your WatchKit Extension.
Workout sessions require
the Workout processing
background mode.
Select Add Capability,
Background Modes.
Select Workout processing.
We need to add
usage descriptions
to our WatchKit Extension’s
Info.plist file.
Select Info.plist.
Select the last row,
then press Return.
Use the NSHealth
ShareUsageDescription key.
Describe why your app needs
to read the requested data.
Press Return.
Use the NSHealth
UpdateUsageDescription key.
Describe the data
your app intends to write.
Let’s build and run our app
to see our app request
permission from HealthKit.
Click Run.
Our app has requested
HealthKit authorization.
Scroll down
and click Review.
Select All Requested Data Below.
See that our app has requested
to share Workouts.
See our provided explanation.
Tap Next.
Our app has requested
read access.
Select All Requested
Data Below.
See the data types that our app
has requested read access to.
See our provided explanation.
Tap Done.
Now that the workout session
can start,
we need to control
the HKWorkoutSession.
Select WorkoutManager.
Let's add our session state
control logic.
A @Published variable
named "running"
tracks if the session
is running.
The pause and resume functions
pause and resume the session.
The togglePause function
will either pause
or resume the session based
on if the session is running.
The endWorkout function
will end the session.
Let’s extend WorkoutManager
to be an
HKWorkoutSessionDelegate
to listen for changes
to the session state.
The workoutSession
didChangeTo toState fromState
with Date function is called
whenever the session
state changes.
Our running variable will update
based on if the toState
is running and is dispatched
to the main queue
for UI updates.
When the session
transitions to ended,
call endCollection
on the builder
with the end date provided to
stop collecting workout samples.
Once endCollection finishes,
call finishWorkout
to save the HKWorkout
to the Health database.
Make sure to assign
WorkoutManager
as the HKWorkoutSession
delegate.
Now let’s have the ControlsView
pause, resume,
and end the session.
Select ControlsView.
Add workoutManager
as an EnvironmentObject
so that our view
can control the session.
Have the End button’s action
call endWorkout
on workoutManager.
The Pause/Resume button needs
to pause or resume the session
and update its image and text
based on the session state.
The button’s action
calls workoutManager’s
togglePause function
to pause or resume the session.
The button’s Image’s systemName
is either "pause" or "play",
based on workoutManager’s
running variable.
The text below the button shows
either “Pause” or “Resume”,
also based on workoutManager’s
running variable.
Let’s update
our SessionPagingView
to display the workout name
in the navigation bar.
Select SessionPagingView.
The SessionPagingView
needs access
to the WorkoutManager
environment variable,
so let’s add that.
[CLICKING]
Now let’s configure
our navigation bar.
The navigation title
is the WorkoutManager’s
selectedWorkout’s name.
The navigation bar’s
back button is hidden,
because we don’t want someone
to go back to the StartView
while they are in a workout.
When the NowPlayingView
is shown,
we want to hide
the navigation bar.
When someone pauses
or resumes their workout,
they shouldn’t need to swipe
to the MetricsView.
We can do this for them
by adding an onChange
view modifier.
When WorkoutManager’s running
published variable changes,
the displayMetricsView
function is called.
displayMetricsView sets
the selection state variable
to metrics withAnimation.
Now that the workout can end,
let’s add the ability to show
and dismiss the SummaryView.
Click WorkoutManager.
Add a published variable
named "showingSummaryView"
which is a Boolean
defaulted to false.
This variable will provide
a binding to a sheet’s selection
on our app’s navigation view.
In endWorkout,
set showingSummaryView to true.
Let’s add the SummaryView
as a Sheet
to MyWorkoutsApp’s
NavigationView.
Click MyWorkoutsApp.
Add a sheet view modifier
to NavigationView.
The isPresented parameter
is a binding
to workoutManager’s
showingSummaryView.
The sheet’s content
is a SummaryView.
In SummaryView,
let’s add the ability
to dismiss the sheet.
Click SummaryView.
Add the dismiss
Dnvironment variable.
In the Done button’s action,
call dismiss().
Let’s run our application
to start and end the session
and see the SummaryView
displayed.
Click Stop to stop
the previous run.
Click Run.
Tap the Run workout.
Default metric values will
still be displayed in-session
and in the summary.
We'll set that up later.
Swipe to the left.
Tap Pause.
Notice the MetricsView
is displayed.
Swipe to the left.
Notice the button
now shows "Resume".
Tap End.
Our workout summary
displays as a sheet.
Scroll down.
[CLICKING]
Tap Done.
The sheet is dismissed
and the StartView is displayed.
Let’s get our MetricsView
and SummaryView
to show actual workout metrics.
WorkoutManager will expose
published workout metrics
that MetricsView
and SummaryView can observe.
Select WorkoutManager.
Let’s add the Published metric
variables to WorkoutManager.
averageHeartRate will be used
by SummaryView.
heartRate, activeEnergy,
and distance will be observed
by MetricsView.
WorkoutManager needs
to observe workout samples
added to the builder by being an
HKLiveWorkoutBuilderDelegate.
Let’s do this now.
First, let’s assign
the builder’s delegate
as WorkoutManager.
Now let’s make WorkoutManager
conform to the HKLiveWorkout
BuilderDelegate protocol.
We’ve extended WorkoutManager
to conform to the HKLiveWorkout
BuilderDelegate protocol.
workoutBuilderDidCollectEvent
is called
whenever the builder
collects an event.
We will leave this function
empty for our app.
workoutBuilder didCollectDataOf
collectedTypes
is called whenever the builder
collects new samples.
We will iterate over each type
in collectedTypes.
The guard ensures the collected
type is an HKQuantityType.
Statistics are read from the
builder for that quantity type.
updateForStatistics --
a function we will
create shortly --
will be called, which updates
the published metric values.
Let’s create the
updateForStatistics function.
updateForStatistics takes
an optional HKStatistics object.
A guard early returns
if statistics is nil.
Dispatch the metric updates
asynchronously
to the main queue.
Switch through
each quantity type.
For heartRate,
we want beats per minute,
so we use a count HKUnit
divided by a minute HKUnit.
Assign heartRate as
the mostRrecentQuantity’s
doubleValue for
beats per minute.
Assign averageHeartRate
as statistics.averageQuantity’s
doubleValue for
beats per minute.
For the activeEnergyBurned
quantityType,
use the kilocalorie energyUnit.
Assign activeEnergy as
the sumQuantity’s doubleValue
for the energyUnit.
For walking, running,
and cycling distance
get the sumQuantity’s
doubleValue for meterUnit.
Now let’s have MetricsView
use metric values
from the WorkoutManager.
Select MetricsView.
Add workoutManager
as an Environment variable.
Let's update our views
to use metric values
from WorkoutManager.
The ElapsedTimeView
uses the workoutManager’s
builder’s elapsedTime.
The activeEnergy
Text view’s Measurement
uses workoutManager’s
activeEnergy.
The heartRate Text view uses
workoutManager’s heartRate.
The distance text view’s
Measurement
uses workoutManager’s distance.
The builder’s elapsed
time variable isn’t published,
so our view currently
will not update
when builder’s
elapsedTime updates.
What we can do is wrap
the VStack in a TimelineView.
TimelineView is new this year.
A TimelineView updates over time
in line with its schedule.
watchOS apps now support
Always On state.
TimelineViews make
our view aware of changes
to the Always On context.
To learn more, check out
the “What’s new in watchOS 8”
and "What's new in SwiftUI"
sessions.
Apps can be in either
active state or Always On state.
Apps with active workout
sessions can update, at most,
once every second
in Always On state.
This means the MetricsView
needs to hide subseconds
in Always On state.
Other design considerations
should be made
for Always On state,
such as hiding the page
indicator controls
to simplify the view.
Our TimelineView needs
a custom TimelineSchedule
that changes its interval based
on the TimelineScheduleMode
dictated by
the Always On context.
Let’s create our custom
TimelineSchedule.
MetricsTimelineSchedule
has a startDate
for when the schedule
should start.
Its initializer
takes a startDate.
MetricsTimelineSchedule
implements the entries function
to produce
PeriodicTimelineSchedule
entries.
The function creates
a PeriodicTimelineSchedule
using the startDate.
The interval is determined
by the TimelineScheduleMode.
When the TimelineScheduleMode
is lowFrequency,
the TimelineSchedule
interval is one second.
When the TimelineScheduleMode
is normal,
the interval is 30 times
per second.
Let’s wrap our VStack
in a TimelineView.
The TimelineView uses
our MetricsTimelineSchedule,
using the builder’s startDate.
ElapsedTimeView’s
showSubseconds is determined
by the TimelineView’s
context.cadence.
When cadence is live,
subseconds are shown.
Otherwise subseconds are hidden
in Always On state.
Let’s run our application
to see the metrics
updating during the workout.
Click Stop to stop
the current run.
Click Run.
Tap the Run workout.
Notice that elapsed time
is incrementing.
The watchOS simulator
automatically
simulates collecting live
workout samples for you.
Calories are accruing.
Heart rate is updating.
Distance is accumulating.
Let’s try the Always On state
by clicking the Lock button
on the simulator.
Notice subseconds are hidden
and metrics update
only once per second.
Click the Unlock button
to return to active state.
[CLICKING]
Swipe left and end the workout.
The SummaryView still needs
the actual HKWorkout values.
Let’s do this now.
First, let’s add the HKWorkout
to the WorkoutManager
to be used in the SummaryView.
Select WorkoutManager.
[CLICKING]
Add a HKWorkout
Published variable.
When the builder has finished
saving the workout,
assign the workout
to WorkoutManager
when builder’s finishWorkout
function completes.
We do this assignment on
the main queue for UI updates.
When the SummaryView dismisses,
we need to reset our model.
Let’s create a resetWorkout
function that does this.
The resetWorkout function resets
all of our model variables
back to an initial state.
Let’s call resetWorkout
when the summary dismisses.
This is done in the didSet
of showingSummaryView.
Let’s display a progress view
when the workout ends,
while the workout is saving,
before displaying
the SummaryView.
Let’s go to our SummaryView.
Click SummaryView.
First, add the workoutManager
EnvironmentObject
to SummaryView.
We want to display
the ProgressView
until workoutManager has
the HKWorkout assigned
when the builder finishes
saving the workout.
If workoutManager’s
workout is nil,
then display the ProgressView
with the text showing
“Saving workout”,
and hide the navigation bar.
We've also updated
ActivityRingsView
to use workoutManager’s
HKHealthStore.
You only need a single
HKHealthStore per app.
Let’s update
our SummaryMetricViews
to use the HKWorkout values.
The Total Time metric view
uses the workout duration.
The totalDistance metric view
uses the workout’s
total distance.
The Total Energy metric view
uses the workout’s
totalEnergyBurned.
The Average Heart Rate
metric view
uses the workoutManager’s
averageHeartRate.
If you want to save
average heart rate for later,
you can add it as metadata
to the builder
before saving the workout.
Let’s update
our SessionPagingView
to react to Always On state.
Select SessionPagingView.
Add the isLuminanceReduced
Environment variable.
During Always On state,
we want to hide the TabView’s
page indicator
and ensure the MetricsView
is displayed.
We’ve set the tabViewStyle's
indexDisplayMode
to either never or automatic,
based on isLuminanceReduced.
When isLuminanceReduced
changes,
call the displayMetricsView
function
to display the MetricsView.
Let’s run our app
in the simulator and try it out.
Click Stop to stop the last run.
Click Run.
Select the Run workout.
Notice metrics are updating live
from the builder.
Swipe left.
Tap Pause.
Notice metrics have
stopped updating,
because the workout is paused.
Swipe left.
Tap Resume.
Metrics resume updating.
Swipe right,
see the NowPlayingView.
Swipe left.
Click Lock to trigger
the Always On state.
Notice subseconds are hidden
and page control indicators
are hidden.
Click Unlock to resume
active state.
Swipe left, tap End.
The workout saves.
The summary is displayed.
Scroll down to view
each of the metrics.
[CLICKING]
Activity Rings will populate
based on the amount of energy,
exercise minutes,
and stand hours.
Tap Done.
[CLICKING]
We are taken back
to the start view,
ready for our next workout.
You saw how easy it is
to use SwiftUI
to implement a fully functioning
workout app
integrated with HealthKit that
supports the Always On state.
We can’t wait to see what great
workout apps you’ll build next!
♪