[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Nathan] Hi, and welcome
to "Classify Hand Poses
and Actions with Create ML."
I'm Nathan Wertman.
And today, I'll be joined
by my colleagues,
Brittany Weinert
and Geppy Parziale.
Today, we're going to be talking
about classifying
hand positions.
But before we dig into that,
let's talk
about the hand itself.
With over two dozen bones,
joints, and muscles,
the hand is
an engineering marvel.
In spite of this complexity,
the hand is one
of the first tools
infants use to interact
with the world around them.
Babies learn the basics
of communication
using simple hand movements
before they are able to speak.
Once we learn to speak,
our hands continue
to play a role in communication.
They shift to adding
emphasis and expression.
In the past year,
our hands have become
more important than ever
to bring people closer.
In 2020,
the Vision Framework introduced
Hand Pose Detection,
which allows developers
to identify hands in the frame,
as well as each
of the 21 identifiable joints
present in the hand.
This is a great tool
if you are trying to identify
if a hand exists or where
a hand is in the frame,
but it can be a challenge
if you're trying to classify
what the hand is doing.
While the expressive
capabilities of the hand
are limitless,
for the rest of this session,
I'd like to focus on short,
single-handed poses,
like stop, and quiet, and peace,
and short,
single-handed actions,
like back up, go away,
and come here.
I just referred
to hand poses and actions.
How about some more
concrete definitions?
Well, on the one hand,
we have poses,
which are meaningful
as a still image.
Even though
these two videos are paused,
the intent of the subject
is clearly expressed.
Think of a pose like an image.
And on the other hand,
we have an action,
which requires movement
to fully express meaning.
The meaning of these
two actions is unclear.
Looking at a single frame
simply isn't sufficient.
But with a series
of frames over time,
like a video or a live photo,
the meaning of the action
is obvious.
A friendly "hello"
and "come here."
With that cleared up,
I'm excited to introduce
two new Create ML
templates this year,
Hand Pose Classification
and Hand Action Classification.
These new templates allow you
to train Hand Pose
and Action models
using either the Create ML app
or the Create ML framework.
These models are compatible
with macOS Big Sur and later,
as well as iOS and iPadOS 14
and later.
And new for this year,
we've added the ability
to train models on iOS devices
using the Create ML framework.
You can learn more about this
in the "Build Dynamic iOS Apps
with the Create ML Framework"
session.
First, I'd like to talk
about Hand Pose Classification,
which allows you to easily train
machine learning models
to classify hand positions
detected by
the Vision Framework.
Since you are in charge
of training the model,
you define which poses
your app should classify
to best suit its needs.
Let me give you a brief demo
of a trained model in action.
Starting from
a simple prototype app,
I was able to easily integrate
a Hand Pose Classifier model.
My app can now classify
hand poses
and show the corresponding emoji
and confidence
of the classified pose.
It classifies the hand poses One
as well as Two.
But you'll notice
that all positions
which it does not recognize
are classified as part
of the background.
This includes
the Open Palm pose,
which I'd like
to add support for.
I'm going to hand this model
off to my colleague Brittany
in a moment,
to show you how to integrate
a Hand Pose Classifier
model into your app.
Before I do, I wanna add support
for the Open Palm pose.
It'll be really easy,
but we should talk
about how a model
is trained first.
Just like all other
Create ML projects,
it's very simple to integrate
a Hand Pose Classifier
into your app.
The process has three steps.
Collect and categorize
training data,
train the model,
integrate the model
into your application.
Let's start by talking
about collecting training data.
For Hand Pose Classifier,
you will need images.
Remember, poses are
fully expressive as images.
These images should be
categorized into folders
whose name matches the pose
present in the image.
Here we have two poses
which we would like to identify:
One, Two, as well
as a Background class.
The Background class is
a catch-all category for poses
which your app doesn't care
about correctly identifying.
In my demo, this includes
many hand positions
which are not One or Two.
A well-defined Background
class helps your app know
when your user is not
making an important pose.
There are two types of images
which make up
a Background class.
First, we have a random
assortment of hand poses
which are not
the important poses
you'd like your app to classify.
These poses should include
a diverse set of skin tones,
ages, genders,
and lighting conditions.
Second, we have
a set of positions
which are very similar
to the expressions
you'd like your app to classify.
These transitional poses
frequently occur
as the user is moving their hand
towards one of the expressions
your app cares about.
When I raise my hand to give
an Open Palm pose,
notice I transition
through several positions
which are similar to
but not quite
what I want my app to consider
an Open Palm.
These positions occur as I
lower my arm afterward as well.
This isn't unique
to the Open Palm.
The same type
of transitional poses occur
as I raise my arm
to give a Two pose,
as well as when I lower it.
All of these transitional poses
should be added
into the Background class,
along with the random poses.
This combination
allows the model
to properly differentiate
the poses your app cares about
and all other background poses.
With the training data
collected and categorized,
it's now time to train our model
using the Create ML app.
So let's get our hands dirty.
I'm gonna start with
the existing Create ML project
I used to train the model
in my previous demo.
The training results
looked good,
so I'm expecting this model
to perform fairly well.
Fortunately,
the Create ML app allows you
to preview your model before
integrating it into your app.
On the Preview tab,
you'll find that,
for Hand Pose Classifiers,
we've added Live Preview
capability this release.
Live Preview takes advantage
of the FaceTime camera
to show you predictions
in real-time.
Using Live Preview,
we can verify that this model
correctly classifies
the poses One and Two.
And I would like it
to correctly classify
the Open Palm as well,
but it currently
classifies that pose
as part of the Background class.
In the Data Source
that I used to train this model,
notice that it does not include
an Open Palm class,
only classes for One, Two,
and Background.
Let's train a new model
which supports Open Palm now.
First, I'm gonna create
a new model source for this.
I have a data set which
includes an Open Palm class
that I'd like to use
for this training.
I will select this data set.
Jumping into
this new data source,
we find that it now includes
an entry for the Open Palm
as well as the classes
from the previous data set.
Back on the model source,
I'd like to add
a few augmentations
to extend the training data
and make my model more robust.
That's it.
It's time to hit Train.
Before the training can begin,
Create ML needs to do some
preliminary image processing,
as well as feature extraction.
We told Create ML to train
for 80 iterations.
This is a good starting point,
but you may need
to tweak that number
based on your data set.
This process will take
some time.
Fortunately,
I've already trained a model.
Let me grab that now.
Live Preview shows
that our newly-trained model
now correctly identifies
the Open Palm pose.
And just to be sure,
I'm gonna verify
that it continues to identify
the One and the Two pose.
Wasn't that easy?
I'm gonna send this model
to my colleague, Brittany,
and she will talk about
integrating it into her app.
[Brittany]
Thanks, Nathan, for the model.
Hello. I'm Brittany Weinert.
And I'm a member
of the Vision Framework team.
When I first learned
about Hand Pose Classification,
I immediately thought,
I can use this to create
special effects with my hands.
I know that using CoreML
to classify hand poses
and Vision to detect
and track the hands
will be the perfect technologies
to use together.
Let's see if we can
give ourselves superpowers.
I've already created
a first draft of the pipeline
for a demo that can do
just that.
Let's review it.
First, we're going
to have a camera
providing a stream of frames,
and we're going to use
each frame
for a Vision request to detect
the location and key points
of the hands in the frame.
DetectHumanHandPoseRequest
will be the request we're using.
It will return
a HumanHandPoseObservation
for each hand it finds
in the frame.
The data we will send
to the CoreML Hand Pose
Classification model
is an MLMultiArray
and a property on the
HumanHandPoseObservation
called the keypointsMultiArray.
Our Hand Pose Classifier
will then return back to us
the top estimated
hand action label
with its confidence score,
which we can then use
to determine action
within the app.
Now that we've gone over
the high-level
details of the app,
let's look at the code.
Let's start out by looking
at how to use Vision
to detect hands in a frame.
For what we want to do,
we only need one instance
of the
VNDetectHumanHandPoseRequest,
and we only need
to detect one hand,
so we set
the maximumHandCount to one.
If you set the maximumHandCount,
and there's more hands
than specified in the frame,
the algorithm will detect
the most prominent and central
hands in the frame instead.
The default value
for maximumHandCount is two.
We recommend to set
the revision here,
so you're not surprised
by updates to the request later.
But if you always want to opt in
for the latest algorithm
supported by the SDK
you're linked against,
you don't have to set it.
Also, as a note,
we will be doing the detection
on every frame retrieved
by the ARSession via ARKit,
but this is only one way to grab
frames from a camera feed.
You may use
whichever method you like.
AVCaptureOutput would also be
a useful alternative.
For every frame received,
we need to create
a VNImageRequestHandler,
which handles all the requests
on a given image.
The results property
on the hand pose request
will be populated with
VNHumanHandPoseObservations,
up to a max hand number of one,
as we specified
on the request earlier.
If the request detects
no hand poses,
we might want
to clear out any effects
currently being displayed.
Otherwise, we will have
a single hand observation.
Next, we want to predict
what our hand pose is
using our CoreML model.
We don't want to do
a prediction every single frame,
as we don't want the rendering
of the effect to be jittery.
Doing a prediction at intervals
creates a smoother
user experience.
When we want
to make a prediction,
we start by passing
the MLMultiArray
to the Hand Pose CoreML model,
and we retrieve the top label
and confidence
from the single
prediction returned.
I want to trigger changes
to the effects being displayed
only when a label is predicted
with a high level of confidence.
This also is key to protecting
against behavior
where the effect may switch
on and off too quickly
and become jittery.
Here, Background classification
is helping us
by allowing us to keep
the confidence threshold very high.
If One is predicted
with great confidence,
we can set the effectNode
to render.
If One isn't predicted
with great confidence,
I want to stop the effect
on the screen
to match what my hand is doing.
Let's test out what we have.
If I make my hand
into the One pose,
it should trigger
a single energy beam effect.
Very cool!
The model could tell
that I made the pose One
and triggered the effect.
Although it would be even cooler
if it followed my finger.
Even better if it rendered
at a specific point
on my finger.
Let's go back
to the code and change it.
What we need to do is feed
the key point location
of the hand
to the graphic asset,
which means using
the view to translate
the normalized key points
into the camera view space.
You may also want to consider
pruning which key points
you save
by looking
at the confidence scores.
Here, I only care
about the index fingertip.
We need to translate
the key point
to the coordinate space,
as Vision uses
normalized coordinates.
Also, Vision's origin point
is in the lower left corner
of an image,
so keep that in mind when
you're doing the conversion.
Finally,
let's save the index location,
and if no key point was found,
we default to nil.
Let's look
at the code responsible
for rendering the effect
and how I can adjust it
to follow my finger.
We want to find the spot
where the location
of the graphical object
is being set.
setLocationForEffects
is being asynchronously called
every frame.
As a default,
we set the effect to appear
at the center of the view.
Switching it out for the
indexFingerTipLocation CGPoint
from earlier, we can
get the intended effect.
Awesome!
This is starting to look cool.
Let's take it one more step.
To create a more interesting
graphical story
surrounding superpowers,
it would be good
to utilize a few more
of the Hand Pose Classifications
in our application.
In this case, we'll pick
the classification
Two and Open Palm.
I've already extended
my application
to take action when both
of these poses are detected.
Here, I'm centering
the energy beam
to appear at the tip of my index
finger,
as shown before,
for the pose One.
Two energy beams at the tip
of my middle and index finger
for the pose Two.
And the last energy beam
is triggered
by the Hand Pose Open Palm
and is anchored
between a key point
at the bottom
of my middle finger
and the wrist key point.
All right.
Everything Nathan and I
have introduced
covers the steps
of fully integrating
your own Hand Pose
Classification model.
There is one more
new feature in Vision
that you may find helpful,
so let me introduce to you
an API that might help
with triggering and controlling
this app's functionality.
Vision is introducing
a new property
that allows users
to differentiate
between the left hands
and right hands
on the HumanHand-
PoseObservation: chirality.
This is an Enum
that indicates which hand
the HumanHandPoseObservation
most likely is
and can be one of three values:
left hand, right hand,
and unknown.
You can probably guess
the meaning
behind the first two values,
but the unknown value
would only appear
if an older version
of the HumanHandPoseObservation
were deserialized,
and the property
had never been set.
As Nathan mentioned earlier,
you can get more information
on Vision hand pose detection
by referring back
to the WWDC 2020 session,
"Detect Body and Hand Pose
with Vision."
As a side note, for each hand
detected in a frame,
the underlying algorithm
will try to predict
the chirality
of each hand separately.
This means that the prediction
of one hand does not affect
the prediction
of other hands in the frame.
Let me show you an example
of what code
using chirality can look like.
We've already covered the setup
to creating and running
a VNDetectHumanHandPoseRequest.
After performing the request,
the observations will have
the Enum property chirality,
and you can use it
to take action on
or sort through Vision hand
poses observations like so.
Everything thus far
has been about how to use
Hand Pose Classification.
But as Nathan mentioned earlier,
Hand Action Classification
is another new technology
this year.
Here's Geppy to talk
to you about it.
[Geppy] Thanks, Brittany.
Hello, my name is
Geppy Parziale,
and I'm a machine learning
engineer
from the Create ML team.
In addition
to Hand Pose Classification,
this year, Create ML introduces
a new template to perform
Hand Action Classification,
and I'm going to show you
how to use it in your apps.
For this reason, I will extend
Brittany's superpowers demo
with some hand actions
and highlight some
important distinctions
between hand poses
and hand actions.
Please refer to the session
"Build an Action Classifier
with Create ML"
from the WWDC 2020
for additional information
and comparison
since Hand Action
and Body Action
are two very similar tasks.
But now, let me explain
what Hand Action is.
Hand action consists
of a sequence of hand poses
that the ML model needs
to analyze
during the motion of the hand.
The number of poses
within a sequence
should be large enough
to capture
the entire hand action
from start to end.
You use video
to capture hand actions.
Training
a Hand Action Classifier
is identical to training
a Hand Pose Classifier,
as Nathan showed us earlier,
with some minor differences.
While a static image
represents a hand pose,
videos are used to capture
and represent hand actions.
So to train
a Hand Action Classifier,
you use short videos,
where each video
represents hand action.
These videos can be
organized into folders,
where each folder name
represents an action class.
And remember to include
a Background class
containing videos
with action dissimilar
than the action you want
the classifier to recognize.
As alternative representation,
you can add all your
example video files
in a single folder.
Then, you add
an annotation file,
using either a CSV
or JSON format.
Each entry in the annotation
file represents the name
of the video file,
the associated class,
the starting and ending times
of the hand action.
Also, in this case, remember
to include a Background class.
Remember,
you train the model with videos
of the same length,
more or less.
Indeed, you provide
the action duration
as a training parameter and then
Create ML randomly samples
a consecutive number of frames
according to the value
you provide.
You can also provide
video frame rate
and training iterations.
In addition to that,
the app offers different types
of data augmentation
that will help the model
to generalize better
and increase its accuracy.
In particular,
Time Interpolate and Frame Drop
are the two augmentations added
to Hand Action Classification
to provide video variation
closer to real use cases.
So I already trained
a Hand Action Classifier
for my demo--
let's see it in action.
Well, since I'm a superhero,
I need some source of energy.
Here is mine.
Here, I use hand pose
to visualize my source
of energy.
But now, let me use my
superpower to activate it.
In this case,
I'm using hand action.
This is cool.
And now, Hand Pose
and Hand Action Classifier
are executing concurrently.
I'm taking advantage
of the new chirality feature
from Vision
and use my left hand
for hand poses
and my right hand
for hand action.
This is super cool.
So this is possible because
of the optimization
that Create ML applies,
a training time
to every model
to unleash all the power
of the Apple Neural Engine.
And now, let me go back
to my real world
and explain you how to integrate
the Create ML Hand Action
Classifier into my demo.
Let's look at the input
of the model first.
When you integrate
a Hand Action Classifier
into your app,
you need to make sure
to provide the model
with the correct number
of expected hand poses.
My model is expecting
a MultiArray
of size 45 by 3 by 21,
as I can inspect
in the XCode Preview.
Here, 45 is the number of poses
the classifier needs to analyze
to recognize the action.
21 is the number
of joints provided
by the Vision Framework
for each hand.
Finally, 3 are
the x and y coordinates
and the confidence value
for each joint.
Where does the 45 come from?
That's the prediction
window size
and depends on the video length
and the frame rate
of the videos used
at the training time.
In my case,
I decided to train my model
with videos recorded at 30 fps
and 1.5 seconds long.
This means the model was trained
with 45 video frames
per hand action,
so during inference,
the model is expecting
the same number of hand poses.
An additional consideration
needs to be taken into account
with respect to the frequency
of the arriving hand poses
at inference time.
It's very important
that the rate of the hand poses
presented to the model
during the inference
matches the rate of the poses
used to train the model.
In my demo, I used ARKit.
So I had to halve the number
of the arriving poses
per each second,
since ARKit provides
frames at 60 fps,
and my classifier was trained
with videos at 30 fps.
If done otherwise,
the classifier
could provide wrong predictions.
Let's jump now into
the source code
to show you how
to implement this.
First, I use a counter
to reduce the rate of the poses
arriving from Vision
from 60 fps to 30 fps,
matching so the frame rate
my model is expecting
to work properly.
Then, I get the array
containing joints
and chirality
for each hand in the scene.
Next, I discard the key points
from my left hand
since, in my demo,
I use my right hand
to activate some of the effects
with the hand action.
Okay, now I need to accumulate
hand poses for the classifier.
To do so, I use a FIFO queue
and accumulate 45 hand poses
and make sure
the queue always contains
the last 45 poses.
The queue is initially empty.
When a new hand pose arrives,
I add it to the queue,
and I repeat this step
until the queue is full.
Once the queue is full,
I can start to read
its entire content.
I could read the queue
every time I receive
a new hand pose from Vision.
But remember, now I'm processing
30 frames per second.
And depending on the use case,
this could be
a waste of resources.
So I use another counter
to read the queue
after I define
number of frames.
You should choose
the queue sampling rate
as a trade-off
between the responsiveness
of the application
and the number of predictions
per second you want to obtain.
At this point,
I read the entire sequence
of 45 hand poses,
organized in MLMultiArray,
and input it to a classifier
to predict the hand action.
Then, I extract
the prediction label
and the confidence value.
Finally, if the confidence value
is larger than
our defined threshold,
I add the particle effects
to the scene.
So remember, when you integrate
the Create ML Hand Action
Classifier in your app,
make sure to input
the sequence of hand poses
at the frame rate
the model is expecting.
Match the same frame rate
of the video used
to train the classifier.
Use a first-in-first-out queue
to collect hand poses
to the model prediction.
Read the queue
at the right frame rate.
I'm looking forward to seeing
all the cool applications
you will build
with the hand action models
trained with Create ML.
And now, back to Nathan
for final consideration
and recap.
[Nathan] Thanks, Geppy.
You and Brittany did
a great job on your app.
I'm excited to try it out.
But before things
get out of hand,
here are a few things
you should keep in mind
to ensure a high-quality
experience for your users.
Be mindful of how far away
the hand is from the camera.
The distance should be
kept under 11 feet,
or 3 1/2 meters,
for best results.
It's also best to avoid
extreme lighting conditions,
either too dark or too light.
Bulky, loose, or colorful gloves
can make it difficult
to accurately detect
the hand pose,
which may affect
classification quality.
Like all machine learning tasks,
the quality and quantity
of your training data is key.
For the Hand Pose Classifier
shown in this session,
we used 500 images per class.
The Hand Action Classifier,
we used 100 videos per class,
but the data requirements
for your use case may differ.
What is most important
is that you collect
enough training data to capture
the expected variation
your model will see in your app.
Now feels like
a good time for a recap.
So what have we learned?
Well, starting in 2021,
you can build apps
which interpret expressions
of the human hand.
We discussed the differences
between the two categories
of hand expressions,
poses and actions.
We talked about
how to prepare training data,
including a Background class,
for use in the Create ML app
to train a model.
We talked about how to integrate
a trained model into an app.
And finally,
we talked about incorporating
multiple models
into a single app
and using chirality
to differentiate the hands.
Obviously, today's demo
only scratches the surface.
The Vision Framework
is a powerful technology
for detecting hand presence,
pose, position, and chirality.
Create ML is a fun
and easy way to train
and classify hand poses
and hand actions.
When used together,
they provide deep insights
into one of humankind's most
powerful and expressive tools,
and we can't wait to see
what you do with them.
Bye.
[upbeat music]