[music]
[Ian] Welcome to “Design
for Group Activities.”
I’m Ian Baird, manager
of the FaceTime team at Apple.
In this session,
we are going to talk about
designing a great experience
using Group Activities,
but before we get started, let’s
recap what Group Activities are
and how it relates to SharePlay.
Group Activities is
the framework
which plugs your app
into SharePlay.
It also provides the capability
for messaging
and synchronizing
media playback.
But before we get started,
I’d like to share the promise
of Group Activities with you.
Imagine you had access
to a framework backed
by a world-class low-latency
networking infrastructure,
allowing you to privately
and securely reach anyone
in the world
using an Apple device.
That’s the powerful system
behind FaceTime,
which is now open
to you with Group Activities.
With the power
of Group Activities,
you can watch a movie
with a distant relative,
shoot
the perfect three-pointer,
share photos
of your amazing vacation
with friends and family,
or learn a new language,
like Swift using Swift
Playgrounds and screen sharing.
My friend just found
a new house in Nashville
and wants me to take a look.
Using the power
of screen sharing,
I’m transported directly
to the experience,
and I can tell her exactly
what I think of the house
she's interested in while we’re
on a FaceTime call.
The key here
is that these activities
are all things people love
to do together.
Before SharePlay,
you’ve probably designed
and built your app
around a single person.
All these examples are things
people love to do together.
You should look for activities
in your app
to bring people together,
encourage conversation,
collaboration,
or just enjoyment.
As we noted, first you’ll want
to discover the activities
in your app best suited
to sharing on a FaceTime call.
Once you identify
these experiences,
next you want to enhance them
for sharing,
add context to make
the experience meaningful
to the participants in the call,
and automate the experience
by adopting
Group Activities API.
This will make it easy
for people
to get into your experiences.
Let’s talk about how
to enhance your app for sharing.
There are three tools
in Group Activity you can use
to bring people together.
First is screen sharing,
second is shared media playback,
and finally, we’ll talk about
some custom UI techniques
which can make your experience
fit well in Group Activities.
While on a FaceTime call,
people can share their screen,
and they can share
your app automatically.
This is a great way for people
to discover what to do together.
When your app UI is shared,
it’s important to consider
which parts of your app
are relevant for sharing.
By default, everything is shared
except for secure entry fields.
You can use UIKit API to further
restrict the visibility
of this information on iOS
during screen sharing sessions.
Your audio is also
shared automatically
with those on the call,
but protected content like music
and movies will not be
shared over screen sharing.
This is where you need
to implement Group Activities
to support
coordinated media playback.
This starts media on everyone’s
device at the same time
and keeps them in sync
with rate changes and seeks.
To be clear, this does not
stream media from device
to device but synchronizes
playback on multiple devices.
You get smart volume control
and the synchronization
for free, but it is up
to you to decide what to do
with seeking, rate changing,
playback controls, et cetera.
For more information, check out
the related session below.
IOS 15 supports
seamless upgrades
from screen sharing
to media playback.
Beginning SharePlay
automatically upgrades
the experience
to rich media content.
What if your app doesn’t fall
into a media bucket?
No, problem.
The Messenger protocol
allows you to broadcast data
to all the other apps
on the call in near real time.
It’s private
and end-to-end encrypted
just like the FaceTime call.
This makes it great
for driving apps with Custom UI.
Custom UI is a great way to get
people together in your app.
You can us this
to draw custom views,
like the one that Adam has
drawn “Hello World” into.
For more information on this,
check out
the related session below.
Now that you have evaluated
your app, its activities,
and thought about ways it can be
enhanced for sharing,
you might come up with new ideas
on activities
which didn’t make sense
with a single person in mind.
We are especially excited
about the opportunities here
where Group Activities inspires
a whole new kind of app
that brings people together.
Here are some examples of how
SharePlay is used by Apple.
The TV app can be used
with screen sharing for people
to discover their next favorite
TV show to binge watch together.
The Music app has been enhanced
to share your favorite new songs
and artists with your friends
on a FaceTime call.
Now that we have defined
our activities and looked
at some of the cool new shared
experiences Apple has defined,
we can come up
with great experiences
to bring people together.
The next concept I want
to talk about is how
to make Group Activities
contextual.
Relating your app
and its content
to the conversation is
a super helpful way
to make sure your app
is SharePlay ready.
When someone first launches
your app
while on a FaceTime call,
they’re shown
if it supports SharePlay right
within the context of your app.
And if your app
contains video content,
then you have an opportunity
to communicate to them
that they can share that content
with the people
who are on the FaceTime call.
Once they find the content
they want to watch,
they will simply tap
the SharePlay button,
and everyone’s show will start.
Once an app or content is
shared,
activity preview tells
everyone else
about what you’re suggesting
they watch.
Activity previews
are an opportunity
to give everyone context about
what they are about to watch,
so it’s important that you use
this as best as possible.
Use it like a rich link,
with a title, subtitle,
and thumbnail
to describe the experience
everyone is enjoying
on the FaceTime call.
Imagine receiving a message like
this with very little context.
It’s important to make sure
that these titles
and subtitles correspond
to the action in the call.
As you can see in this example,
it’s important
to make these titles
and subtitles meaningful.
This is a great example of how
to make
a meaningful activity preview.
Remember that whenever someone
is interacting
with their phone
during SharePlay,
they are
essentially multitasking,
so we need to make sure
the interaction is as easy
as possible.
So automate as much as you can
and minimize unneeded
upfront interaction
before getting
into the activity.
One way you can make
SharePlay super easy
is to have your app auto launch
from the background
on everyone’s device
automatically.
The way you do this is
by supporting Picture in Picture
within your app.
For more information on this,
check out
related sessions below.
Sometimes your app might
need some interaction,
like to sign up or subscribe
for more content.
If that’s the case, simply call
the Group Activities API
and tell us that your app needs
foreground presentation.
The user will tap the banner,
and your app will be brought
to the foreground,
allowing the user to interact
before joining the experience.
However, it’s important
to use this feature with care.
If someone doesn’t have
your app installed,
when the activity begins
or they join the call,
they’ll be taken
to the App Store
to install it
when they tap the notice.
As you can see,
we’ve made it easy for people
to get into your app.
You should streamline the path
into the activity.
It’s important to remember
that any user interaction
is happening on a FaceTime call,
so things
like account sign up,
purchases, et cetera,
all need to be done while also
chatting to your friends.
Your friends
are going to be waiting
for you
to complete this interaction.
The last thing your want to do
is make all of your friends wait
while you fill out
a lengthy form.
So question every interaction
and see if it’s really necessary
to get to the content and,
if possible,
delay
or automate those interactions.
Group Activities are a great way
for people
to experience your app.
We are really excited
to see the types of activities
you will enhance for SharePlay.
And make sure
you’re adopting all the APIs
to make the experience
effortless and seamless.
For more information on this,
check out
the related sessions below.
And thanks for watching.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC21.
[music]