[music]
[Jake] Hello and welcome
to “What’s new in watchOS 8.”
My name is Jake Behrens, and
I’m Apple’s Watch Evangelist.
watchOS 7 opened up
many new opportunities,
with features like Family Setup,
allowing family members to stay
connected without an iPhone;
multiple complications,
allowing you to create richer
experiences for the watch face;
and watch face sharing,
which allows you to create
a watch face that’s all
your own with complications
that you love that you can share
with someone or post online.
In watchOS 8,
we’ve focused on some
of your top requests
to help you create
even more incredible
Watch app experiences.
There’s a lot to talk about,
so let’s dive in.
First is the Always-On Display.
Apple Watch Series 5
and watchOS 6 brought
the Always-On Display
to the watch face,
and now in watchOS 8,
we’re bringing
the Always-On Display
to your apps.
I’m also going to talk
about how you can take advantage
of background delivery
of HealthKit data
and Bluetooth scanning
to keep health-related
complications up to date.
Apple Watch has become
more independent over time.
With watchOS 8,
we’re bringing region-based
user notifications to the wrist.
I’m going to talk
about how these can bring
relevant information
to someone at the right time
in the right places.
Finally,
I’ll talk about some new system
and API enhancements
coming to watchOS 8
that make developing and using
Watch apps even better.
Let’s start
with the Always-On Display.
The Always-On Display
allows you to see content
on your watch without having
to raise your wrist.
When you raise your wrist,
the display is active again.
The Always-On Display
is supported
on Apple Watch Series 5 and 6.
In watchOS 7,
the always-on state
showed your app’s UI
blurred with the time overlaid.
When you rebuild your app
with the watchOS 8 SDK,
your app’s UI will now be
shown in a dimmed state instead
and is immediately interactive
if someone taps the UI.
In the always-on state,
the system automatically
reduces the overall brightness
of the display
while keeping it bright enough
for someone to see.
To help you adapt your app’s UI
to this reduced brightness,
we’re introducing
a SwiftUI environment property
called isLuminanceReduced.
You can respond to this state
by highlighting information
that’s especially important
and hiding information
that should stay private.
To help you iterate quickly,
we’ve included support
for this environment property
in Xcode previews
as well as in the simulator.
In the simulator,
you click a button
in the window
to simulate a wrist-down event.
This will be really helpful
when you want to see
how your app’s UI responds
to the always-on state.
Now let’s talk
about some guiding principles
for your app’s UI
in the always-on state.
The transition from active state
to the always-on state
should feel seamless.
Don’t drastically alter the UI
or reorganize information.
Otherwise the transition
from the always-on state
to being active will be jarring.
Maintaining the context
of the active UI is key.
In this example,
Fitbod keeps the UI grounded
and consistent between states
while further dimming some
of the brighter elements
and secondary text.
Next,
you should dim non-essential
information and elements.
If you have secondary text,
images, or fills,
you can further dim them
yourself
to give more prominence
to the piece of information
you want to stay highlighted
and visible.
AnyList, which helps you create
and share grocery shopping lists
and organize recipes, removes
the background of list items
and further dims
the secondary information,
like which flavor of Greek
yogurt or how much milk.
This allows
the main list item title
to be even more glanceable,
as you might be pushing
a shopping cart
or carrying a shopping basket.
If your UI has large elements
that are filled
with color or imagery, you may
want to reduce those elements
to be represented with a stroke
or dimmed color,
again maintaining
the UI’s grounding
but allowing your highlighted
information to still be visible.
In this example,
Pandora dims secondary controls
along the bottom
and removes the album artwork
and uses a similar
but dimmed color.
This works really well
to highlight the song name
and artist name
at a quick glance.
When luminance is reduced,
you may also want
to redact or remove
sensitive information.
Information like account
numbers, balances,
shown in this example,
and some personal health data
may be good candidates
to obscure
from prying eyes
while someone’s wrist is down.
To learn more
about redaction using SwiftUI,
see the “Principles
of great widgets” video
in the Developer app,
since widgets share
a similar redaction model.
Finally, if you have
animations happening,
you should reset them
to the first frame
of their loop or resolve them
to a rested state.
It’s best to not leave them
mid-animation.
Now that you know how
to make your UI look its best
in the always-on state,
let’s talk
about the technical side
of how you update your app's UI
while the wrist is down.
For apps with an ongoing,
active session
like a workout session
or audio session
that gives you
continuous runtime,
you can update your UI
up to once per second.
This allows you
to keep counters,
metrics,
and other data up to date,
though will require you
to remove
sub-second incrementing,
like tenths of seconds.
For apps
without an active session,
you may update
up to once per minute.
While the default timeout
before the system returns
to the clock face
is two minutes,
you should plan for your app
being visible longer than this,
as your customers may
change this setting.
So how do you tell us
that your inactive app needs
to update its UI?
For that, we’ve created
a TimelineView in SwiftUI.
TimelineView takes a schedule
and constructs a view dependent
on a date.
When it comes
to scheduling updates,
we’ve provided a handful
of TimelineSchedules
to help you do whatever
is right for your app.
There is Every minute,
which updates every minute.
This also aligns to the system
clock, meaning that each update
will occur at the top
of the minute on the device.
There’s Periodic, which allows
you to set an interval,
such as every two minutes
or whatever is appropriate
for your app.
If you use a periodic schedule
for one-minute intervals,
they are not aligned
to the system clock.
This can be really useful
if you need to time an update
in relation to a specific event,
like when a workout was started.
There’s Explicit,
if you have changes that occur
at specific times, such as
needing an update at 1.5 minutes
followed by an update
2.5 minutes later, and so on.
There’s also Custom.
This can work really well
if you have something
like a timer that updates
every minute but you’d like it
to update once per second
for the last 60 seconds.
If your app is not in an active
session and you tell us
that you need faster updates
for a short period,
as in the last 60
seconds of this timer,
the system will
attempt to do so,
but those updates
are not guaranteed.
Finally,
there’s an Animation schedule.
To learn more
about TimelineView, schedules,
animations, and more, watch
the “What’s new in SwiftUI"
and the “Add rich graphics
to your SwiftUI app” videos
in the Developer app.
We love the impact that health
and fitness apps have
made on Apple Watch.
In watchOS 8, we’ve brought
background delivery
of HealthKit data to Watch apps.
This opens up passive
health monitoring for apps
and can make a big impact
for standalone Watch apps
used
in Family Setup configurations.
Setting up background
delivery of HealthKit data
works similarly to iOS.
On watchOS, when the predicate
matches due to new health data
being collected and
your background observer query
gets handled, your app is woken
to receive results.
This can be up to once per hour
for a Watch app.
If someone has added
your app’s complications
to their active watch face,
you can receive results
up to four times per hour.
All of these opportunities
will count against your app’s
background app refresh budget,
so they will only add up
to a maximum of four results
being received per hour and
could impact background app
refresh wakes for other reasons.
Let’s talk
about update frequencies.
When we deliver results
to your app,
we will do it immediately
for various critical data types,
including fall events,
low blood oxygen saturation,
heart rate events, and more.
Look at the developer
documentation
on the Apple Developer website
for the full list
of affected data types.
All other data types
will be delivered hourly
or at longer intervals.
We’ve also added new information
in the HealthKit authorization
sheet
to let customers know
that your app has increased
awareness of their health data
on Apple Watch.
We think background delivery
of HealthKit data will
bring new possibilities
to health
and fitness related
complications on the watch face.
In watchOS 4, we enabled
Bluetooth devices to connect
directly to Apple Watch
and make use of Core Bluetooth.
We’ve seen some really
incredible uses of this.
In watchOS 8,
we’re taking another step
forward and allowing devices
to connect
during background app refresh
opportunities that your app’s
complications get when they’re
on the active watch face.
For instance, this is Qardio,
which allows people to monitor
their heart conditions
with Qardio’s medical grade ECG.
And this is Sonra Watch,
which allows soccer coaches,
or football, for those
of you outside of the U.S.,
to monitor up to 28 real-time
metrics of their players’
performance during training
using their GPS tracker.
With Bluetooth connections
during background app refresh,
this means that your app’s
complications can stay
up to date
with your Bluetooth device
and display updated
information throughout the day.
Background app refresh
gives your app’s complications
that are on the active watch
face up to four opportunities
per hour to connect and update.
Remember that these
opportunities will count
against your app’s overall
background app refresh budget.
Make sure to set up
your initial device connection
when the app is
in the foreground.
This can’t be done
from the background.
Once a connection
to the device is established,
background app refresh
gives your app the opportunity
to connect and get new data.
It’s also important to connect
and process your data
within a very short period
of time.
To help you with this,
we’ve added
a new expiration handler
on WKRefreshBackgroundTask
so you can be told when
you’re about to run out of time
and need to finish up
what you’re doing.
This allows your app to clean up
and degrade gracefully
if needed.
For more information, watch
“Connect Bluetooth devices
to Apple Watch”
in the Developer app.
Apple Watch is the device
that’s always on you.
With independent Watch apps
becoming more prevalent and
customers increasingly running
out for coffee or to the store
with only their watch,
location is a key part
of staying on top
of what’s important.
In watchOS 8,
we’re bringing region-based user
notifications to Apple Watch.
This means you can get notified
of important things
based on geofences.
For example,
you can be reminded to start
your skiing workout when you’re
at the lift, using Slopes.
Or you can receive
your flight information
when you get to the airport
using App in the Air.
Region-based user notifications
on watchOS
work similarly to iOS.
To preserve
your customers’ privacy,
they will first receive
a static notification where
they can tap a button to see
the full dynamic notification.
This allows you to deliver
pre-created local notifications
based on someone entering
or exiting a region you’ve set
for a notification trigger
based on location.
Keep in mind that the “When
in use” permission is required
for you to take advantage
of this.
You should also limit the number
of regions to only include
important points of interest
near someone
or locations they’ve
shown explicit intent for,
like setting
a favorite store location.
Regions are most power-effective
when they're
about a couple hundred meters
in radius.
Alongside region-based
user notifications, watchOS 8
supports the new location
button in Core Location.
This button gives a one-time
location authorization without
going through authorization
prompts each time it’s tapped.
Behind the scenes,
it acts like an "Allow once”
traditional authorization.
The location button
is an easy way to gain trust
from people by giving them
more control
of when they want
to share their location.
For more information
on Core Location updates
in watchOS 8 and iOS 15,
watch “Meet the location button"
available in the Developer app.
We’re also introducing
a new always-on altimeter API
in Core Motion.
This gives you access
to real-time elevation updates
with minimal impact to all-day
battery life and without
requiring someone to share
their location with the app.
Aside from new features
and APIs coming to watchOS 8,
we’ve made a lot of enhancements
to make developing
and using your Watch apps
easier than ever.
With watchOS 8,
Apple Watch can now
measure respiratory rate
while you sleep.
This allows apps
like Sleep Details to display
your respiratory rate data
and visualize changes
when you wake up in the morning.
We’re happy
to bring AssistiveTouch
to Apple Watch for those
with limb differences.
This is really exciting because
we can recognize a person’s hand
gestures to help them
perform actions and navigate UI.
We’re also bringing
a large accessibility text size
to watchOS 8.
To learn more on making
your Watch app more accessible,
watch “Create accessible
experiences for watchOS”
in the Developer app.
Unit testing and UI testing
for Watch apps
was introduced in Xcode 12.5.
But making your apps accessible
is what allows them
to be testable, so with new
accessibility features
on watchOS, the time
has never been better
to make your apps
more accessible.
watchOS 8 also adds large titles
at the top of scrolling views,
like you see in iOS,
allowing for a more consistent
feel across devices.
Text input has been revamped
in watchOS 8,
remembering if someone
prefers Scribble
or Dictation per app,
and giving quick access
to changing between input types
while entering text.
This allows much more text
to be easily entered,
and you get this functionality
free with SwiftUI text fields.
The new searchable API allows
you to easily add search fields
to your apps
with customized suggestions.
Customers will see
a button in the search field
indicating suggestions
are available.
When they tap on that, they’ll
see your customized suggestions.
You can also provide
customized UI for results.
You can learn more by watching
the “Craft search experiences
in SwiftUI” video
in the Developer app.
Lists now support swipe actions,
so in addition to removing
items, you can now perform
custom actions like favoriting.
Button roles let the system
know how to present and handle
specific button types,
like destructive ones,
but they also include
a controlProminence modifier,
which will give those buttons
an additional haptic
when tapped.
And the SwiftUI Canvas API
is also available on watchOS 8,
which means you can
do rich programmatic drawing
that uses the incredible GPU
found in Apple Watch.
There are many reasons
to be excited
about new possibilities
on Apple Watch with watchOS 8.
TimelineView can help you update
your UI when a person’s wrist
is down and they need
to get info at a quick glance.
This is something
all apps should adopt,
so check it out first.
Your app’s complications
have gained new ways
to get updated information
to them with background delivery
of HealthKit data
and Bluetooth connections.
This further supports
that complications
are a main way
some people use Watch apps.
If you can deliver more
at a glance,
you absolutely should.
Region-based
user notifications have
enhanced what location means
to Watch apps.
Adopting these where they make
sense can add that surprise
and delight moment that keeps
customers engaged in your app.
And finally, making
use of next-level capabilities
like AssistiveTouch and
the SwiftUI Canvas API can make
your Watch apps more useable
and more immersive than ever.
I’ll be watching
to see what you create.
Thank you.
[music]