[percussive music]
[Joel]
Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Joel,
and I would like to tell you
about how you can add music
to your apps with MusicKit.
MusicKit is a new framework
for Apple platforms
which offers expressive APIs
for your apps to access
music items in Swift.
It leverages the new
Swift concurrency syntax
and is designed from
the ground up to be
used in conjunction
with SwiftUI.
MusicKit accelerates
the way your apps integrate
with Apple Music API,
which are our set
of server-side APIs
for accessing the wide array
of catalog content
from Apple Music,
thus making it much easier
for you to build compelling apps
that tie into Apple Music.
First, we'll talk about
how to request music content
with MusicKit.
Next, we'll talk about
other topics that are
important for the way your
apps integrate with Apple Music,
such as requesting consent from
the user for your app to access
Apple Music-related data,
managing tokens required
for accessing Apple Music API,
accessing subscription
information
and related capabilities,
playing music from
the Apple Music catalog,
and finally, how to show
subscription offers
for Apple Music, in case your
user isn't already a subscriber.
MusicKit offers
a new model layer
for accessing music items,
with structured requests that
allow you to fetch content
from Apple Music API.
You can either search
for content
in the Apple Music catalog,
or fetch resources
based on a specific filter.
These requests produce
responses with items
grouped in collections,
which have built-in
support for pagination,
allowing you to get
the next batch of items
from an initial response.
So, what do these
music items look like?
Let's take a look at a specific
example with an album.
"Album" is a value type
with properties grouped
in three different categories.
The first category contains
simple attributes,
such as a string property
like "title,"
a boolean property
like "isCompilation,"
or more structured properties
like "artwork,"
which gives you access to URLs
for the artwork
alongside relevant sizing
information and related colors.
Album also offers several
relationships,
such as related
artists or genres,
or the list
of tracks in a given album.
For example, the result
of the "tracks" relationship
is a collection of values
of type "Track,"
which is
another type of music item.
Finally, in addition to these
strong model-level
relationships,
"Album" offers several
weaker associations
of related content.
Associations are very similar
to relationships,
but they are
typically more ephemeral,
or more editorially driven.
For example, the "appearsOn"
association on an album
returns a collection of
playlists,
but, unlike collections
for relationships,
this one also has a title.
Loading and accessing
relationships
with MusicKit is very simple.
Given an album, you can easily
fetch another representation
of this same album that includes
relationships like "artists"
and "tracks,"
as well as associations
like "related albums,"
in a single operation.
The "with" method needs to be
called
with the special
Swift keyword "await,"
which indicates that this
will perform
an asynchronous operation
behind the scenes.
This will indeed fetch a more
complete representation
of this album from Apple Music
API over the network.
You can then
get the list of tracks
from this detailed album,
and iterate over those tracks as
you would with a regular array.
And here's the console
output for this code.
Accessing associations such as
"related albums"
works the same way,
with the only difference being
that they typically
also include a title, accessible
directly on the collection.
You can then iterate over the
collection in that same manner
to print a few
of those related albums.
And here's the console
output for this code.
Now, let's take a look at
a demo of requesting
music content with MusicKit.
I've been working
on an app which allows me
to find and enjoy
albums from Apple Music.
I can search for albums
using this search field,
which is already connected
some code to load
matching search results
using the music catalog
search request.
This app also keeps track
of the list of albums
I recently viewed.
We can find more information
about this album titled
"Catch A Vibe - EP"
by selecting it,
and you may have noticed
the list of tracks for
this album being animated in
after this detail view appeared.
This is done by loading
the "tracks" relationship
of this album as we just saw,
and updating the state variable
for our SwiftUI view,
which is then used
to populate this list.
We can begin playing music from
this album with the play button
underneath the artwork,
or by selecting
a specific track.
This will simply use the
playback API in MusicKit
to set the queue
with this list of tracks,
and call the play
method on the player.
Let's try it out!
So, if I select the track
titled "Catch a Vibe"
by Karun & MONBRU...
[music playing]
This song begins playing.
[singer]
♪ Ooh, oh, no ♪
[Joel] Our app even
works automatically
in media controls
in the Lock screen,
which allows me to scrub
to a halfway point in this song.
[music playing]
But I was hoping to use this app
to help me rediscover
old music from my CD library,
like this album from Phoenix.
So, I'd like to add a feature
that would allow me
to point the camera of my iPhone
to the barcode of an old CD
and have this app surface this
same album in digital format.
I've already added
some experimental code
for this feature.
When I enable it,
I can see a barcode button
at the bottom,
which brings up a camera view.
If I point it to the barcode
of this CD,
it automatically recognizes the
barcode value and displays it.
All I'm missing is some
code that uses MusicKit
to find the corresponding
album.
Let's go ahead
and add that to our app.
So let me make
an albumsRequest
using the
MusicCatalogResourceRequest.
I am looking specifically
for albums.
And here, we want to make sure
we find albums
where the UPC property,
which stands
for Universal Product Code,
that's the technical term
for bar code,
is equalTo: detectedBarcode.
I can perform this
request asynchronously.
albumsRequest.response.
And then from the response,
I can look for the first album
in the results.
Then I can then pass this
first album
to the
handleDetectedAlbum
helper method down below.
(firstAlbum).
This method dismisses the
barcode scanning view,
and then pushes the album detail
view for the detected album.
And it's decorated here
with MainActor
to make sure it will be
executed on the main thread.
So when we call it,
we need to make sure
that we add the await keyword.
So let's build and run
our app again and try it out.
Tap the barcode button.
Take my album.
It worked!
Now, it's going to be
much easier to enjoy
my old music in digital
format on Apple Music.
MusicKit also offers a general
purpose data request,
which is different from
structured requests
in that it allows you
to load content
from an arbitrary Apple Music
API endpoint using its URL.
What you'll get back from
this request is the raw data
for the JSON response
from Apple Music API.
You need to decode this raw data
with JSONDecoder,
but doing that
doesn't have to be hard
because you can leverage
existing music item types,
since they conform
to the Codable protocol.
Let's take a look
at an example.
If you wanted to load the list
of top level genres
from Apple Music,
you could do it
by loading content
from this
specific URL,
and here's the corresponding
JSON response.
If you take a closer
look at this result,
you can see in the middle what
looks like a genre resource.
So, how would you
represent this in Swift?
Sure enough,
MusicKit has a Genre type.
Zooming back,
how would you represent
the entire response in Swift?
You can create a struct,
with a data member,
which is
a simple array of genres.
Then, make sure to mark
this struct as Decodable.
And this doesn't even require
writing
any additional decoding logic,
because "Genre" itself also
conforms to Decodable.
So, to load this data in your
app,
you would put this struct
at the top of your file,
then you would construct
the URL using the specific
country code for your user.
Create a music data
request using this URL,
and get the response from that,
following the same
pattern we've already seen.
Once you have that response,
you can decode its data
using JSONDecoder,
by passing
in the type MyGenresResponse
to the decode method.
And that's it!
You can now access
individual genres
in your strongly-typed
genres response.
And, as you can see, you get
the same kind of music item
you can otherwise fetch
from other requests in MusicKit.
So, that's how you would
load content
from any arbitrary URL
for Apple Music API.
And now that we know how to load
music content,
let's discuss
some important preliminary steps
for integrating your
apps with Apple Music,
starting with privacy.
We want users to remain
in control over which apps
have access to their data.
So, before you can request any
data from Apple Music API,
which can include the user's
listening history
or their music library,
you need to get the user's
informed consent
for your app
to access Apple Music.
Asking for this user
content needs to be done
on a per-device
and per-app basis.
And here's what the user consent
dialog looks like
in the context
of an app named Zova,
which is a great fitness app
that allows you to
work out with their playlists
on Apple Music
or your own playlist.
When you go to start
a workout for the first time,
Zova asks for permission
to access Apple Music.
This dialog needs to convey
to the user why your app
needs access to Apple Music.
To that end, your app's usage
description for Apple Music,
which you need to define
in your Info.plist,
is included
as the subtitle of this dialog.
Here's an example of how
you might request user consent
for MusicKit.
Say you have a feature
in your app
that requires MusicKit,
and that you're gating
access to this feature
using the
isAuthorizedForMusicKit
state variable.
At the appropriate point
in your app,
before you try to use MusicKit,
you can request authorization
to access Apple Music with this
asynchronous request method.
This will only prompt
the user if your app
hasn't been authorized yet.
The request method returns
a status value,
and you can set
your isAuthorizedForMusicKit
variable to "true" if that
status is equal to "authorized."
Now, let's talk briefly about
tokens required
for loading data
from Apple Music API.
Apple Music API requires
a developer token,
which essentially authenticates
your app with the API.
Previously,
to get this developer token,
you would have had to create
a MusicKit private key
in the developer portal,
put it on a server
under your control,
to ensure the key
is kept private,
and have your app request a new
developer token
from your server.
But now,
with MusicKit for Swift,
you no longer need to worry
about any of this,
as the developer token
is automatically generated
for your app.
You just need to opt in
to this new automatic behavior
by enrolling in
the developer portal.
Specifically, in the page where
you register your App ID,
select the App Services
tab at the bottom,
and enable the MusicKit
checkbox.
And you're done!
Additionally,
Apple Music API requires
a user token for any
personalized endpoint.
And just like the developer
token, new this year,
the user token is automatically
generated on your behalf.
One more thing you may need
to use MusicKit in your app
is a way to figure out
if your user has
an active
Apple Music subscription.
Subscription information
in MusicKit is exposed
as three distinct capabilities,
which tell you if the user
can play content
from the Apple Music catalog,
if they have iCloud
Music Library enabled,
or if they
can become subscribers,
in case they don't already
have an active subscription.
Make sure to check the relevant
capability for the specific
Apple Music-related
functionality in your app.
For example,
if you have a play button
hooked up to play some music,
you may want to keep it disabled
if your user
cannot play catalog content
from Apple Music.
You can define a state
variable in your view
to keep track of the music
subscription.
Then, you can apply the disabled
modifier to your button
to make sure it stays disabled
if the music
subscription property
"canPlayCatalogContent"
is set to "false."
And finally, inside of an
asynchronous block
passed to
the new task modifier,
you can use the new
subscription updates stream
to be notified of changes
in the music subscription.
Now, let's talk about
playback with MusicKit.
MusicKit offers
two distinct players,
which we call SystemMusicPlayer
and ApplicationMusicPlayer.
Let's get into the differences
between those players,
starting with an example.
Whereas a social media
app may want to use
the SystemMusicPlayer to change
what's playing
out of
the system music app,
a fitness app might prefer
to use
the ApplicationMusicPlayer
to keep their playback state
completely independent
from the system music app.
Both of these players
automatically report
the now playing information
and handle remote commands.
This is what gave us
deep integration
with system media
controls in the lock screen,
earlier in our demo.
However, the now-playing app
is reported differently.
If you use
the SystemMusicPlayer,
the Music app will be reported
as the now-playing app,
whereas if you use
the ApplicationMusicPlayer,
your app will be the one
reported as the now-playing app.
Ownership of the playback
queue is also different.
With SystemMusicPlayer, your app
is merely remote-controlling
the system Music app, whereas
with ApplicationMusicPlayer,
your app owns a completely
separate playback queue.
Both of these players
allow you to set the queue
with one
or more items,
add an item to play next,
or to play later.
But only
the ApplicationMusicPlayer
gives you additional control
over the playback queue,
allowing you to insert
items in the middle,
or removing items that had
been added previously.
Finally,
if your user isn't already
an Apple Music subscriber,
you may want to allow them
to start a free trial
for Apple Music
from within your app,
so they'll be able to enjoy
all the functionality
you've worked on to improve
the user experience
of your app with music.
The subscription offer
can be configured by tailoring
the main message shown
to the user to better correspond
to the functionality in your
app, like “play music”.
It can also be contextual,
highlighting a specific song,
album, or a playlist.
And by using the subscription
offer sheet in your app,
you can
get rewarded for bringing in
new Apple Music subscribers,
through our affiliate program,
which we call
the Apple Services
Performance Partners Program.
To show a contextual
music subscription offer
in your app,
you'll need to keep track
of the music subscription
as we saw earlier.
You'll also need another state
variable
to keep track of whether
the offer is being shown.
Pass in the ID of, say,
an album,
as the itemID property of your
subscription offer options.
Keep the offer button disabled
whenever “canBecomeSubscriber”
is set to "false"
on the music subscription.
Then, use the musicSubscriptionOffer
modifier
with a binding
to the isShowingOffer property,
and also including your options.
Finally, set the isShowingOffer
variable to "true."
Let's go back
to our app and see what
the contextual offer
for Apple Music looks like.
In our earlier demo,
we were already signed in
with an active
Apple Music subscription.
So, to simulate the scenario
where it might be appropriate
to show a subscription
offer for Apple Music,
you can just go Settings,
and sign out of your account.
Then, if I go back to my app,
you can see that the play button
was disabled and moved
to the left to make room
for another button that invites
the user to join Apple Music.
If I tap this button,
a subscription offer
is presented,
highlighting the specific album
we were just
looking at in our app.
And that's how you can allow
users to start a free trial
for Apple Music
from within your app.
In conclusion,
there are many types of apps
that can be enhanced by adding
a little bit of music
as part of their experience.
For example, you can make your
games a lot more immersive
by playing background music that
matches the mood of your game.
Or you can play upbeat music
to keep your users
motivated in a fitness app.
And in a social media app,
you can keep your users
even more engaged with content
that highlights music.
To go even further,
make sure to check out
some related sessions,
so you can learn about
harnessing the power of Shazam
signatures with ShazamKit,
and dive deeper into
concurrency with SwiftUI.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy WWDC 2021!
[percussive music]