[music]
[Yongjun]
Hi!
Welcome to WWDC.
My name's Yongjun.
I'm an engineer
from App Clips team.
I'm joined today
by my colleague, Luming,
to talk about what's new
in App Clips.
An App Clip is a small part
of an app that can be launched
at the moment when it's needed.
It provides fast and focused
experience on a specific task.
User can easily upgrade
to your app
after they complete the task.
Since it's launched, we have
seen many great App Clips
from developers
all over the world.
They are well designed,
easily discoverable,
with great ways to engage users.
Let me share some examples
with you.
Firi Games has an App Clip
for their popular
Phoenix 2 game.
I can go to their web site
in Safari, tap the banner.
It will show the App Clip Card
for this game.
From there,
I can launch the game.
In a couple seconds,
the game's ready to play.
After I play the first level,
I can download the full game
right from the App Clip.
TikTok has an App Clip
to make sharing video
really fun and easy.
When I receive a video
from my friend,
iMessage will show
the TikTok App Clip preview.
Tap of the preview
shows the card.
There I can
open TikTok App Clip.
I can enjoy the video
right away.
Panera bread
is a U.S.-based food service
with thousands of stores.
If I look up one of the stores
in Maps,
the place card will show
"order food" action button.
I can open their App Clip
right from there.
Within seconds,
the App Clip launches
and shows the menu
for this particular store.
I can make order
and pay with Apple Pay.
In iOS 15, if I search
a business in Spotlight,
like Panera, the App Clip will
show up in search results, too.
With on-device intelligence,
if I'm nearby Panera store,
my phone can suggest
the App Clip
to me in Siri suggestion widget.
Tap the suggestion, I can open
it and order food right away.
Honk created an App Clip
for touchless payment
for parking.
All I need to do is
scan their QR code
attached at the parking lot.
With one tap,
I can open the App Clip
and pay with Apple Pay.
Primer AR Home Design has
an App Clip for you to try
paint, tile, and wallpaper
in an AR environment.
I can scan
or tap the App Clip code
on a tile to open the App Clip.
There, I can experience
how this beautiful tile
would look like
in my living room.
These are some great
example App Clips.
There are many, many more.
You can discovered them
in Safari, Messages,
or in the real world by a QR
code, NFC tag, or App Clip code.
I encourage you to try them out
and see what App Clips can do.
In this session,
we will cover three topics.
First, App Clip Card in Safari
and SafariViewController.
Then, we will talk about testing
App Clip with local experiences.
Last, we will cover
App Clip code.
Let's look at a new way
to explore App Clips.
Your website can use
apple-itunes-app meta tag
to display the smart app banner
in Safari
or Safari View Controller.
In iOS 15, you can configure
the meta tag to show
a full-sized App Clip Card,
right in the middle of web page.
User can
open your App Clip from there.
If they choose "View in Safari,"
Safari will remember the choice
and not show the card next time
the page is loaded again.
And it will fall back
to the original banner.
To opt-in card mode,
you just need to add
"app-clip-display" key
to the meta tag
and set it to "card."
The card mode works great
if you like to promote
your App Clip in the web page.
For apps
using SafariViewController
to render web content,
like Twitter,
it can show the card
as a part of the app's UI.
Now, user
can launch the App Clip
directly from the app.
This is the App Clip Card
in Safari
and SafariViewController.
Let's talk about test
with local experiences.
For users,
their App Clip experience
starts with the App Clip Card.
The card shows your App Clip's
title, subtitle,
what action can take,
and a header image
to show your brand and style.
You can create an App Clip Card
in App Store Connect.
Follow the step-by-step guide
to configure all the elements.
You can also specify locations
associated with your App Clip.
This could make the App Clip
show up in Maps place card,
Siri suggestion widget,
or Spotlight search.
To know about how to customize
App Clip Card, please refer
to WWDC20 sessions, "What's
new in App Store Connect"
and "Configure
and link your App Clips."
Now, when you develop
your App Clip, you might
not have registered
any App Clip experiences yet.
Sometimes, you do want
to test the end-to-end flow
and role-play
the whole experience.
You can do
that with local experiences.
A local experience is
an experience you enter
in your own testing device.
You can launch it with most
of regular
App Clip invocation methods.
To create a local experience,
go to Developer Settings
and select Local Experiences.
Specify your App Clip's name,
title, URL prefix,
bundleID, and select an image
in your photo library
as the header image.
You can then scan
a QR code or NFC tag
to launch the experience.
Local experiences support QR,
NFC, App Clip Code,
Safari, and Messages.
They don't show up in Maps,
location suggestions,
and Spotlight search.
These require
registered experiences.
Also, you can only
specify local experiences
for Xcode-installed App Clips
or App Clips in Beta testing.
This is how you can test
with local experiences.
With that, I would like
to hand over
to Luming to show you a demo.
[Luming]
Thanks, Yongjun!
As Yongjun mentioned
in the talk,
you can now configure
the meta tag
to show a full-sized App Clip
Card right in the middle
of the web page in both Safari
and SafariViewController.
I'm in the FoodGrid app,
a third-party app
my friend has built,
which helps you
discover nearby restaurants
and beverage shops.
As you can see,
my smoothie stand, Fruta,
is featured
in this FoodGrid app.
Tapping on my smoothie stand,
Fruta, in my friend's app opens
a SafariViewController showing
my smoothie stand website.
Because my smoothie stand
website has already adopted
Smart App Banner meta tag
for iOS 14 and iPadOS 14,
my customers can open
the Fruta App Clip
from the Smart App Banner,
but opening the App Clip this
way requires the customer
discovering the banner,
tapping open, then confirming it
in the App Clip Card,
which is a multi step process.
So, adopting the new full-sized
App Clip Card for iOS 15
and iPadOS 15 is a great way
to promote and elevate discovery
of our Fruta smoothie stand
App Clip
within the web page
or within third-party apps
that embed our website
through SafariViewController.
Let's see how to do just that.
Here, I am on the Fruta web
server that hosts our website.
Within the apple-itunes-app
meta tag, I just need
to add "app-clip-display,"
and set its value to "card."
Now, if I tap to open
the restaurant website again
in the FoodGrid app,
you will notice
the App Clip Card shows up
immediately
within the web page as a part
of the FoodGrid app's UI.
The user can then launch
the Fruta App Clip
directly
from this third-party app.
Back to you, Yongjun.
[Yongjun]
Thank you, Luming.
Now, I know
how to launch my App Clip
from the app with the help
of SFSafariViewController.
Now, let's talk
about App Clip code.
App Clip code is a new,
Apple-designed visual code.
It is the best way
to discover App Clip experiences
in the real world.
It is available from iOS 14.3.
So, there are
almost 1 billion devices ready
for your App Clip code.
An App Clip code always leads
to an App Clip.
When the user sees such a code,
they know there's an App Clip
to explore.
Each code encodes a unique URL
for specific experience.
iOS decodes the URL
before sending to the App Clip.
This means your App Clip
doesn't need
to do anything special
to handle these codes.
Your existing URL handling
will just work.
There are two types
of App Clip code:
NFC integrated or Scan only.
User can interact
with NFC-integrated code
by tap it or scanning it
with the camera.
Use this type when customer
can easily access the code.
For example,
on a vending machine,
or on a restaurant table,
or on storefront window.
Use scan only if the code
may be placed out of reach
for the customer,
or when NFC is not appropriate.
For example,
when it is displayed digitally
in a marketing email.
You can customize
the style of App Clip code
to fit specific use cases.
You can pick you own foreground
or background color.
You can also
hide the App Clip logo.
We suggest to show the logo
when there is enough space.
This gives new customer
a clear message
that it is for App Clips.
If you have an ARKit App Clip,
you can use App Clip code
as an anchor,
tracking its position
in the physical world.
This could
bring amazing experiences.
For example,
a user can scan an App Clip code
on a package,
exploring what is inside,
like this guitar,
without opening the package.
To know more
about App Clip code and ARKit,
please check out WWDC21 session,
"Explore ARKit 5."
There are two ways
to create an App Clip code.
You can use
the App Clip Code Generator tool,
available
from developer.apple.com,
or you can download the code
directly from App Store Connect.
We recommend
to use the command-line tool
when you're testing
or developing an App Clip,
or you need
to automate code generation.
Use App Store Connect to create
codes for registered URLs.
For the best scanning
experience,
here are some guidelines
to keep in mind.
First, keep the code
on a flat surface.
The code should be placed
at upright position.
Make sure you don't rotate
the code or the central logo.
Small codes are harder
for customers to see and scan,
so make sure your code is large
enough, at least 1 inch wide.
Ensure good visibility.
Make sure your code is
not blocked, damaged,
or placed too close
to other codes.
You can add a text next
to the code to inform people
how they can use it
to launch your App Clip.
Make sure the message is concise
and with a clear call to action.
For more information,
please check
the Human Interface Guidelines
and This is App Clip Code.
I would like to hand
over to Luming, again,
to show you how to quickly
generate App Clip Codes.
[Luming]
Thanks, Yongjun!
As Yongjun mentioned,
the easiest way
to generate an App Clip Code is
to download it
from App Store Connect.
For cases where you
need more customization,
or need to script App Clip Code
generation in bulk,
generating them locally using
the App Clip Code Generator
command-line
tool is a great option.
I've already downloaded
and installed
App Clip Code Generator
from the Apple Developer website
onto my Mac,
so I can open Terminal
and interact with the tool.
It's really easy to use.
As Yongjun mentioned,
there are a variety
of templates available
to choose.
And I can enter
"App Clip Code Generator templates"
to view a list
of all available templates.
But how do these templates look,
exactly?
Well, you can
find a preview of all
of these template
at the following location:
/Library/Developer/AppClipCode
Generator/SampleTemplates.
Let's look
at these using Quick Look.
Number 4 looks really great,
so I'm going
to generate an App Clip Code
using this template
for our Fruta App Clip.
I'll enter
"AppClipCodeGenerator generate."
We'll generate
an NFC App Clip Code
since I'll place an NFC tag
behind the printed
App Clip Code.
I'll pass in a URL
that I have registered
as an advanced App Clip
experience
on App Store Connect,
which is fruta.example.
I'll choose template 4,
which we figure looks great
from the Quick Look preview
in Finder.
Finally, I'll pass in
the desired output
SVG file name fruta.svg.
SVG graphics are vector based,
so they scale beautifully
when you print them
from a piece
of U.S.-letter-sized paper,
all the way
to a 24-by-36 poster.
Let's open a generated SVG
in Safari to preview it.
I have already printed
this App Clip Code
on a poster,
so let's try scanning it
from the Code Scanner module
in Control Center.
And here we are.
We are now
in the Fruta App Clip.
And that is
a quick demonstration
of how to generate App Clip Code
using
the App Clip Code Generator
command-line tool.
Back to you, Yongjun.
[Yongjun]
Thanks, Luming.
Now, I know how to generate my
own codes with different styles.
To wrap up, in this session,
we looked
at some great App Clips.
Then, we talked
about App Clip card in Safari
and SafariViewController.
We also discussed how to test
with local experiences.
Last, we covered App Clip Code,
an Apple-designed visual code
for App Clips.
Thank you,
and I'm looking forward
to trying more great App Clips
from you.
Have a great WWDC.
[music]