[percussive music]
[Harrison] Hi, I'm Harrison
from the Game Center team.
Thanks for joining me
to learn about using
recurring leaderboards
in your games.
Game Center provides a convenient
identity players can use
to access their data across
many of their games.
As a developer,
Game Center allows you to easily
add features like achievements,
multiplayer, and leaderboards,
which is what I'm here
to talk about today.
As this is a code-along,
you'll need to do
some initial setup
in order to participate.
Then, I'll give a quick recap
of Game Center's
leaderboard types
and walk through
the provided sample game.
Finally, I'll add a recurring
leaderboard in App Store Connect,
and show a couple different ways
to use it in the sample game.
Let's start with some setup.
We've provided a project
compatible with Xcode 13
in the developer portal
to get you started.
I encourage you to pause
the video and download that now.
After it's downloaded,
resume, and I'll walk you
through some initial setup.
In the folder you downloaded,
you'll find an Xcode
project called The Coast.
Go ahead and open that now.
Since you're going
to modify this app
to use Game Center features,
it needs to be registered
with your team.
Follow along, pausing as needed.
First, select TheCoast project
file from the project navigator.
Then, select TheCoast
from the list of Targets.
In the Signing
& Capabilities pane,
choose your
team from the Team menu.
If your Apple ID or team isn't
in the menu,
first choose
Add an Account
and enter
your Apple ID information.
Next, set the bundle
ID to a unique identifier.
You must change the bundle ID
to proceed.
If prompted,
click Register Device
to create a provisioning
profile.
Once you've successfully
registered,
there won't be any warnings
listed under the status.
Now that your chosen
bundle ID is registered,
you can add an app record
to App Store Connect.
In the top right corner
of App Store Connect,
select the team you used
when registering your bundle ID.
Then, navigate to the My Apps
section.
Click the plus button in the top
left corner,
and select New App.
You'll be
working on an iOS-only app,
so select iOS as the platform.
Pick an appropriate name,
primary language, and SKU.
For bundle ID, make sure you
choose the bundle ID
you registered in Xcode.
After all the required
fields are filled out,
select Create to add
your app record.
You'll be coming back to
App Store Connect a little later.
But now, I'm going to give
a quick recap of leaderboards.
All of our leaderboards let
players see how well they rank
against friends
and players around the world.
Our leaderboard types
primarily differ
by how long
the leaderboard is active.
Classic leaderboards are
always active, with no ending.
They maintain an all-time
ranking,
as well as rolling weekly
and daily rankings.
They're particularly useful
for cumulative scores,
like total experience points
earned
or current number of coins.
Recurring leaderboards,
on the other hand,
are short-lived leaderboards
that repeat
on a developer-defined schedule,
like every 5 minutes
or every 30 days.
You can retrieve
a currently active
leaderboard occurrence,
and you can also retrieve
the most recently finished
occurrence that a player
has submitted to, for up to 30
days after its end time.
Recurring leaderboards
are useful for periodic,
timed events,
like a 1-hour challenge
every Sunday at noon,
or a new leaderboard every week.
I'm going to highlight
a specific use case
for recurring leaderboards
during the session.
But first,
let's go back to the project
you opened in Xcode.
Build and run it on an iOS
device or a simulator.
This is the title
screen of The Coast.
For now, this screen just has
a button to start the game.
Go ahead
and tap on "PLAY."
Gameplay
is pretty straightforward:
when you see a ship,
tap on it to get a point.
Each session lasts 60 seconds.
At the end,
you'll have the option to retry
or return to the title screen.
If you select the menu button
in the top right corner,
you can finish early.
So, how is this implemented?
I'm going to highlight a couple
of the main classes to start.
TitleScreenViewController
is responsible
for the title screen.
In a bit, it will be used
to authenticate with Game Center.
For now, it's mainly
responsible for presenting
GameViewController when
the PLAY button is tapped.
GameViewController
is pretty simple.
It brings up a SpriteKit scene,
called GameScene,
when the view is loaded,
and has a delegate method
called endGame for going back
to the title screen.
Let's look at GameScene, which
manages all the gameplay logic.
When it's presented, it sets up
a couple of SpriteKit nodes.
One is a node created
with a background image.
This is scaled based on your
device's screen size,
and all of the other nodes
are added to it as children.
Another is scoreLabel,
an SKLabelNode
positioned
in the top left of the screen
displaying the current score.
The last is a CountdownNode,
which shows players how much
time they have left and notifies
the GameScene when time is up.
With those nodes added,
the setupBoatNodeWithActions()
method is called.
This kicks off a sequence
of SpriteKit actions
to fade in and fade out
boat sprites
over the course
of the session.
The touchesEnded method is
overridden to remove
those boat sprites when tapped
and increment the score.
At the end of the countdown,
in the timeIsUp method,
all nodes are removed
from the background
and a menu with the final
score is displayed.
There are lots of ways recurring
leaderboards can be leveraged
to improve the experience
of The Coast for players,
but today,
I'm going to focus on three.
First, I'll show you how
to establish a daily competition
by creating a 24-hour recurring
leaderboard,
and show how to link to
Game Center's
default leaderboard UI.
This is probably the easiest way
to add a recurring leaderboard,
and it's a great way
to let players find out
how they stack up against
others.
The daily cadence ensures
that everyone will have
fresh opportunities
to earn a top spot.
Next, we're going to display
live rankings during gameplay.
This adds
a lot of excitement to the game,
as players get to see
in real time
how well they're doing and how
close they are to the top spot.
Finally, we'll use ranks
from the current
and previous occurrences
to show how a player
is changing over time.
This is a really simple
way to give players
a sense of progress in the game.
Let's get started.
I mentioned earlier
that I'll be using
a daily
recurring leaderboard.
Before you can use
a leaderboard in your game,
you need to configure
it in App Store Connect.
Pull that up in Safari
now and open your app.
Navigate to the Features tab,
and make sure that Game Center
is selected.
Then, click the plus button
next to leaderboards,
and choose the recurring
leaderboard option.
Both classic and recurring
leaderboards
have these six fields
to configure.
The leaderboard reference
name is used internally
in App Store Connect.
Pick something descriptive,
like "DailyHighScore."
The leaderboard ID
is used to reference
your leaderboard within the app.
For simplicity,
I'm just going to use the same
descriptive value I used
for the reference name.
Score format type determines
how scores are formatted
in the Game Center UI.
The Coast's scores
are just integers,
but other games might
use time or money.
If a player submits
multiple scores
to the same
leaderboard occurrence,
the score submission
type determines
which one gets ranked:
either the best score
or the most recent.
Use best for The Coast,
since you want to record
a player's highest score
for the day.
Sort order determines
how players' scores
are ranked against each other.
For The Coast, high scores are
better,
so choose High to Low.
You can optionally define
a range for valid scores.
Any score outside of that
range will be rejected.
This is useful as a mitigation
against cheating.
I'm going to set a minimum of 0
and maximum of 200,
since I don't reasonably
expect players
to score outside of that range.
Recurring
leaderboards have these
additional required fields.
Start Date and Time
is the date and time
of the first occurrence
of the leaderboard, in UTC.
You can't choose a start
in the past,
so choose a date and time
in the immediate future,
like in one minute,
so that you can begin
using the leaderboard
right away.
Duration is the length
of time that scores
can be posted for a leaderboard.
This is, of course, one day
for the daily leaderboard.
Restarts Every
specifies the frequency
that new occurrences
of the leaderboard are created.
The frequency is required
to be greater than or equal to
the duration, so that
occurrences will not overlap.
The Coast doesn't need any
gap between occurrences,
so set this
equal to the duration.
Here's a diagram showing
how these fields interact
to produce occurrences.
At the start date you select,
say June 11 at 9:00 a.m.,
an occurrence is created.
You can submit to this
occurrence for one day
because of the configured
duration.
Immediately after that
occurrence expires,
June 12 at 9:00 a.m.,
a new occurrence is created,
because the restart
is configured
to match the duration.
This process
continues indefinitely.
The last thing to configure
is the localization information.
Leaderboards need this
in order to display properly
in Game Center UI.
At least one language
must be configured.
I'm going
to configure for English.
Pick an appropriate
display name,
like "Daily High Score"
for a daily leaderboard.
You also
need to pick a score format.
For an integer type,
you can use periods
or commas
as the thousands separator.
Select one that makes
sense for your language.
The score format suffix
is a way to specify
the unit of your score,
like points or hits.
I'm just going to leave this
blank for The Coast.
Leaderboard image is optional,
but it's recommended
because it
gives a customized look
for your game
in the Game Center UI.
There's an image provided
in the Assets directory
of the project for you to use
here, named leaderboardImage.
Upload that.
Once you've
saved the leaderboard,
you can authenticate
with Game Center
and use it in your game.
So, let's start by enabling
Game Center authentication.
In the
TitleScreenViewController,
there's a method called
authenticateLocalPlayer(),
with the body commented out.
Go ahead and uncomment it.
This code
sets the authentication handler
on the local player,
which will trigger
a Game Center log-in flow
on start.
If you need more information,
follow the provided
link to documentation.
Now, we can submit scores.
Earlier, I showed you the method
in GameScene that updates
the score when a touch ends,
called touchesEnded.
Navigate to that.
There are
two submitScore methods.
One is a class method,
and one is an instance method.
When you submit to the class
method,
the submission will go to
whatever occurrence
is currently active.
It will only fail if there isn't
an active occurrence.
To use the instance method,
you first load a GKLeaderboard
representing
the current occurrence.
Then, when you submit a score
in the completion handler,
it will only succeed if
that occurrence is still active.
Consider a game that offers
a unique challenge every hour,
using an hourly recurring
leaderboard.
You wouldn't want any scores
from one challenge to leak into
the next challenge's occurrence,
say due to network delays
between a player's
device and the server.
The instance submit score method
ensures that won't happen.
The Coast's daily
leaderboard isn't tied
to a particular game session,
so it doesn't matter
what occurrence receives
the score.
Let's just use the class method.
Now, the score will be submitted
to the currently active
leaderboard occurrence.
Note that
I'm setting the context to 0.
The context can be used
to encode
some game-specific
information
and store it with the score.
For The Coast, scores don't need
any additional context.
Now that you're submitting
to the daily leaderboard,
let's add a button to show
the leaderboard in Game Center UI
from the title screen.
First, head to the
TitleScreenViewController.
You'll need to create
a new IBAction method.
Call it showLeaderboardVC.
Instantiate
a GKGameCenterViewController.
Pass in a leaderboardID,
a playerScope--
I'm using global--
and a timeScope.
For recurring leaderboards,
timeScope must be allTime.
Set the gameCenterDelegate
to "self."
Then, present it.
You also
need to create a UIButton.
I'm just calling mine
leaderboardButton.
Then, wire everything
up in the main storyboard.
We've provided a leaderboard
glyph for you to use
in the assets directory.
Add a button with that image,
and remove the text.
I'm going to set an aspect ratio
constraint
to ensure the glyph
doesn't get stretched out.
Then, position it next
to the PLAY button.
Set the Touch Up Inside
event to your new method.
And set a New Referencing
Outlet to your new button.
Now, build and run the app
to try out your new leaderboard.
You might be prompted
to log in to Game Center.
Do that now, since an
authenticated account
is required for leaderboards
to work.
Tapping the leaderboard
glyph takes you directly
to the leaderboard
in Game Center UI.
If you haven't played yet,
the leaderboard will be empty.
Play briefly, and check back
in on the leaderboard
to see your new score.
Now that you have a leaderboard
and are submitting scores,
let's add in live scores
during gameplay.
Take a look
at the LeaderboardNode class.
This is a SpriteKit
node that takes a list
of leaderboard entries
consisting of names and scores,
then displays them according
to rank.
It can be initialized
with entries and updated
when the entries need to change.
Add an optional leaderboardNode
as a member of GameScene.
We initialize the leaderboard
position
in setupInitialGameplay.
Initialize
the node right under that.
I'm configuring it
with five rows,
and leaving
the initial entries blank.
Add it to the backgroundNode
to display it in your scene.
Now, we need to load entries
and update the leaderboard.
I'm going to create
an updateLeaderboardNode
function for this.
First, load
the DailyHighScore leaderboard.
In the completion handler,
use the leaderboard
to load the top five entries
from the global leaderboard.
Since this
is a recurring leaderboard,
the timeScope will
always be allTime.
Once these have loaded,
you'll need to convert
the GameKit entries into
the LeaderboardEntry struct
that LeaderboardNode uses
if the entries aren't nil.
[typing]
Then, call the LeaderboardNode’s
updateEntries method.
The last step is to update
the LeaderboardNode
throughout gameplay.
In this game, the player's score
is frequently changing,
and you should keep
the LeaderboardNode in sync.
To do that,
call updateLeaderboardNode()
in the completion
handler for submitScore.
To properly
display the leaderboard
before a player has scored,
also call immediately after
the node has been created.
Now, I'm
going to build and run again.
I have a couple friends playing
the game along with me.
You can see the leaderboard
continuously update
as our scores increase.
The last change I'm making
is to show how a player's
current daily rank differs
from their previous daily rank.
I'm going to put this
in the GameMenuNode
when the time is up.
I could use a series
of nested completion handlers
to implement this,
but using GameKit's
new async methods will make
this code more readable.
Create a new async method.
Let's call
it addRankToGameMenu().
Since GameKit's async
methods can throw,
you'll want to catch any errors.
I'm just going to log them.
Load the daily leaderboard
and confirm
that it
was successfully returned.
With that leaderboard instance,
do two things.
First, asynchronously
load entries
with async let.
I'm leaving
the for parameter empty,
since I only care about
the local player's score.
Second, asynchronously
load the previous occurrence
of the leaderboard and use
that to load entries.
I'll need to write a method
on the gameMenuNode
to display this information.
Let's call it addRankNode.
Pass in the current
and previous ranks.
You'll need to use try await
to wait for them to be ready.
Go ahead and call the new
async method
in a detach block from timeIsUp.
Then, head to GameMenuNode
to implement addRankNode.
addRankNode is going to generate
some simple text
using the difference between
the previous and current rank.
If both ranks are nil,
you can just return.
Display
your text in a label node.
I'm using a helper
function to create that.
Position it appropriately.
I'm going to add it
centered horizontally
and slightly below center
vertically.
Then, add it to the background.
Now, let's see the result.
I played yesterday, so I have
a previous rank available.
As you can see, my rank is
down a little bit today,
a good reason to keep playing.
In this session,
I've shown you how to get
a recurring leaderboard set up
in App Store Connect,
and then how to use it in your
game, by submitting scores,
linking to Game Center's
own leaderboard UI,
and using the leaderboard APIs
to display live global ranks,
and ranks from
a previous occurrence.
For even more information
on recurring leaderboards,
see "Tap into Game Center:
Leaderboards, achievements,
and multiplayer"
from last year's WWDC.
And be sure to check out
"What's New in Game Center"
at this year's WWDC.
[percussive music]