[music]
[Rusty] Hi, I'm Rusty.
I'm an engineer
on the CloudKit team,
and I'm excited to introduce
a new CloudKit developer tool,
as well as a brand-new
CloudKit schema language.
In this session,
I'll talk about
why integration testing
can be challenging
for an application
that integrates with the cloud.
Then, I'll demonstrate cktool,
our new command line
developer tool for CloudKit.
You'll find out how
cktool can be used
inside of Xcode
to automate test setup.
You'll learn about CloudKit's
new declarative schema language.
And then, I'll wrap things up
with next steps.
Let's get started.
When you write applications
that depend on cloud services,
there are explicit contracts
between your application
and the services you depend on.
Integration tests
can help you validate
how you interact with these
services,
but properly automating setup
of these integration tests
can be challenging
for a few reasons.
First, it's not always easy
to keep the server
up to date
with the data model
your app is using.
As you iterate on your schema
during development of your app,
it's important
that the schema on the server
exactly matches the schema
your app is using
when your tests run.
Also, it can be difficult
to ensure that your tests
are running
against a consistent set
of sample data in the cloud
each time the tests run,
particularly if your tests
modify that data
as part of the test.
The CloudKit team has just
made all of this easier for you.
With the new CloudKit schema
language we've just introduced,
you can declare
your CloudKit schema
in a file right alongside
your application code,
and then check it
into version control
so that you can track changes
along with all other changes
in your project,
and always ensure
that your app's data model
is consistent
with your CloudKit schema.
And with the new cktool
command line developer tool,
you can easily automate
the process of sending
this schema declaration
to the CloudKit server,
while also creating
a consistent set of sample data
on the server
right before you run your tests.
Let me jump right in
and start using cktool.
First, cktool
is installed with Xcode 13.
Once you install Xcode 13,
you can start using cktool
from the Terminal right away.
cktool is invoked with xcrun.
It offers several commands.
For example,
it can create records
on the CloudKit server,
query records that
already exist on the server,
import and export
the new schema language files,
manage authorization
for the tool itself, and more.
Before using cktool,
there are a few things
to understand
about authorization
with CloudKit.
Since cktool
communicates directly
with the CloudKit server,
it's necessary to first
get the tool authorized.
You can choose
to only authorize cktool
to perform container-management
functions like schema import,
or you can additionally
authorize the tool
to access data
in your container.
CloudKit has introduced
two new concepts
for this purpose.
The first is called
a "management token,"
which is used by cktool
to manage
your CloudKit container.
The management token is tied
to a single developer account
and can be used
across developer teams
if that developer is
a member of multiple teams.
A management token
is intended
for configuration use
cases only,
like schema import and export.
This token doesn't provide
any access
to data in the container.
So, we've also introduced
a user token,
which can be used to authorize
the tool to write data
into the user's private database
of an app's container
or to the public database
of an app's container.
I can get a management token
and also a user token
from the CloudKit Console.
For more information
on the CloudKit Console,
you can check out
"Meet CloudKit Console,"
another WWDC21 session.
Now that I've obtained
both a management token
for my developer account
and also a user token,
I can add them to the tool,
which will store them securely
in my macOS Keychain,
and I'm ready to proceed.
I can now start doing
some interesting things.
For example, I'll ask for a list
of my Apple developer
team memberships.
And I get back
a list of teams
that I'm a member of. Great.
Now let's say
that I have a database schema
defined in my container,
and I want to commit it
to my source code repository
prior to making changes.
With cktool, that's easy to do.
Using this
export-schema command,
I can pull down
my development schema
to a file called “schema.ckdb.”
This file is formatted
in the new
CloudKit schema language
I mentioned earlier,
and we'll explore this file
in detail in just a minute.
With cktool, I can add data
to my container, too.
Here, if I have sample values
expressed as JSON,
like for this
sample Book record here,
I can use that JSON
as input to the tool,
just like this,
to create a record
in my public database.
Okay, so now that you have a
basic sense
of how the tool operates,
I'll make
a simple three-step script
to delete all the data from the
development environment
of my app's CloudKit container,
then send my schema
declaration to the server,
and finally,
load some test data.
That way, I can run this script
as part of a test pre-action in
Xcode
and ensure
that my CloudKit container
is always in a consistent state,
with the exact schema my
application is using
before each time
that I run my tests.
So, here in Xcode,
I'll edit the scheme
for my project's application
and choose Pre-actions
in the Test phase.
Now, I can add
a New Run Script Action.
I'll provide build settings
for my app target,
so that the script
has a path to the schema file
in my project.
Right here,
I'll paste a cktool command
to reset my container,
and then, one to import schema
from the file
in my application project,
and finally, one to create an
example record
in my container's
public database.
Note that since these
commands are synchronous,
they will execute
one after another,
and any failure
will stop execution,
just in case something
doesn't go as expected.
In that case,
I can take care to resolve
any pre-test issues
before actually
running my tests.
That's it.
Now, when I run my Xcode tests,
cktool will prepare my CloudKit
container
right before they run.
Perfect.
So, what if I need to change
the data model
for my application?
Let's talk more about
CloudKit schema language.
In fact, let's examine
that schema.ckdb file
that I downloaded earlier.
Inside the file
is the new CloudKit
schema language,
which is a powerful way
to describe
the record types in my schema.
It's easy to read and write,
and to include right here in my
project
with my application code.
Here inside the schema section,
there are record types.
These exactly mirror
the record types
as shown for my container
in the CloudKit Console.
Each record type
has multiple fields,
and each field
has a name and data type.
The triple-underscore
field names are system fields,
which are created by CloudKit
for every record type.
Below these system fields
are my custom fields,
which represent
my custom application data
for this record type
in CloudKit.
I can create
an index for a field,
like a Queryable,
Searchable, or Sortable index,
just like I can do
in the CloudKit Console.
I do this in CloudKit
schema language
by declaring the index
right after the data type
for the field,
like for this
"title" custom field
in my Book record type here.
Below the field definitions
are the security role settings
for the record type.
This is where
permissions can be granted
to each named security role,
like for each
of these three built-in
system security roles here.
“_creator" includes only the user
that created the record,
“_world" includes all users,
and “_icloud" includes
any authenticated user.
Note that in CloudKit
schema language,
you can include both
single and multi-line comments
to make the schema files
even more readable
for you and your team.
Comments will be ignored
by the CloudKit server
when the file is processed,
so feel free to put comments
wherever you'd like.
Now that CloudKit
schema language
provides developers
a fast, flexible way
to declare and modify schemas,
it's important to remember
a few core concepts
around CloudKit
schema evolution.
First, you have full control
over record types
in the development environment
of your container.
You can add and remove
record types in development,
and also add and remove
custom fields
inside those record types,
with no limitations.
Of course, new record types
can always be promoted
to production,
and new fields can be added
to existing record types
in production, as well.
But once record types
have been promoted
to the production environment
of your container,
they can't be deleted or
renamed,
and custom fields inside record
types
that have been
promoted to production
cannot be deleted
or renamed, either.
The reason for this
is to ensure that
the CloudKit server
always understands
record types and fields,
which older versions of your app
might still be using.
This means that while you can
make destructive changes
to your schema declaration
in the development environment
of your container,
you will not be able to promote
these destructive changes
to production.
Note that it is possible
to add and remove
indexes in production,
and security role settings can
be modified, too.
All of these
schema promotion concepts
are not new to CloudKit,
but the flexibility you get
from this new file-based
schema declaration
means that it's important
to review and understand them.
Now that you've gotten a sense
of what cktool can do
and how CloudKit
schema language works,
I encourage you to try out both
in your own projects.
Authorize cktool
with a management token
and user token
from the CloudKit Console,
and explore its commands.
Export your existing
CloudKit schema
into a CloudKit
schema language file,
and add it to your project,
making sure to check it
into version control
with the rest of your project.
Compose some setup steps
for your integration tests
using cktool,
and add the script
as a test pre-action
to your Xcode scheme.
The ability to administer
certain elements
of your CloudKit container
from the command line
can be really powerful.
Maintaining a declaration
of your CloudKit schema
in a file, right alongside all
of your other application code,
can help you keep it
consistent with your data model
throughout your development
life cycle,
and tying all of this together
to automate cloud setup
of your integration tests
is even better.
We're excited to find out
what you do
with these new tools.
Thanks for taking the time
to learn more about CloudKit,
and for your interest in WWDC21.
[music]