[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
David Stites: Hi,
and welcome to "Showcase
app data in Spotlight".
My name is David Stites,
and I am an engineer
on the Core Data team.
In this session,
I am excited to show you
how to add Spotlight indexing
in your app
using
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate.
The agenda for this session
is to learn about the
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate
object
and why you should use it,
setup a simple implementation,
learn how to customize
that implementation,
and lastly, validate the code
by adding full-text search.
First, let's look at
Core Data and Spotlight.
People are going
to create and store
a lot of great and important
content in your app.
As their use of your app
and the size of their
data set increases,
they're going to want to be able
to quickly find that data
both inside the app using
standard search methods
and outside the app,
for example,
in Spotlight search.
Wouldn't it be great
to have data inside your app
show up in Spotlight?
Well, this is where Core Data
can help you.
The NSCoreDataCore
SpotlightDelegate object
does all the heavy lifting
and provides a set of APIs
that quickly and efficiently
indexes content
provided by your app.
You just have to turn it on!
Once indexed,
search results will also appear
in the Spotlight search user
interface outside your app.
The Spotlight delegate
automatically processes changes
to your graph's managed objects
and then updates
the Spotlight index accordingly.
In addition, it provides robust
index management capabilities
to interact with the private,
on-device-only index
and allows you to tailor the
index results to your liking.
In fact, any content
that is in your persistent store
is eligible to be indexed.
The reasons to use the Spotlight
delegate are threefold:
(1) the Spotlight delegate
maintains feature parity
with Core Spotlight APIs,
(2) it removes a lot of
necessary implementation code,
and (3) it provides a great
additional feature set
that we'll be discussing
later in this session.
To illustrate my previous point,
this is a very simple
implementation
using the Core Spotlight APIs
that only adds items
to a search index
and reduces it to... this!
Two lines!
Simple, easy to read
and maintain.
I mean, come on, who doesn't
prefer less code?
Let's take a look at how to get
setup and running right away.
This simple example will cover
deciding what to index
and creating the delegate.
Throughout this session,
I will be referring
to an app called Tags
that I wrote for myself,
which is a simple
photo tagging application.
This sample app will incorporate
many of the APIs
I am discussing today.
Prior to adding
Spotlight support,
you can see that all the tag
and photo data is trapped
inside Tags as there are no
Spotlight search query results
for "Natural Bridges
State Park".
Let's change that!
The first step
in any implementation
using the
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate
is to decide what you're going
to index in Spotlight.
What gets indexed in Spotlight
is completely up to you.
In Tags, I've decided to index
the userSpecifiedName
attribute on the entity Photo
and the name attribute
on the entity Tag.
To prepare the model
for indexing,
I've opened the project's
Core Data model in Xcode,
selected each attribute
I want to index,
and have ticked the
Index in Spotlight checkbox
in the attributes inspector.
Our work continues
in the Core Data model editor,
as it's required to set
the Core Data Spotlight
display name.
The Core Data Spotlight display
name is an NSExpression.
At indexing time,
this expression is evaluated
with each managed object
that has properties
indexed by Spotlight
and the result is saved.
Later, when the Spotlight search
user interface is shown,
these stored results are used
as the “display name”
for the search result.
What is an NSExpression?
Well, an expression can be as
simple as evaluating a key path,
in this case Tag.name.
This object has quite a few
more tricks it can do
besides evaluating key paths,
however.
In this example,
it is doing some math for you.
The expression can be
even more complex,
such as calculating
the standard deviation
of a set of numbers.
In Tags,
the Spotlight display name
is set to userSpecifiedName
on the entity Photo,
and name on the entity Tag.
Now that the model
is prepared for indexing,
let's create
the Spotlight delegate.
Beginning in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
the initializer
forStoreWith: model:
is now deprecated.
The new way initialize
a Spotlight delegate
is using forStoreWith:
coordinator:.
By adopting the new
designated initializer,
it is no longer required
to add an instance
of the Spotlight delegate
to the store options
prior to adding the store
to the coordinator.
However, you must call
startSpotlightIndexing
for the Spotlight delegate
to start its work.
I want to call out
a couple requirements
to using the
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate.
The store type of the store
to be indexed must be SQLite
and must have persistent
history tracking enabled.
And with that,
you're done!
That's it!
You don't need to do
anything else
and your data will be
indexed in Spotlight.
I just demonstrated how easy
it is to add Spotlight indexing
to my Tags app.
Now that I've described
the basics,
let's customize
that implementation a bit.
The first way to customize
the implementation
is by defining a domain
and index name.
To start off,
I'll define a class,
TagsSpotlightDelegate,
which is a subclass of
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate.
Now, I'll override domainName
and indexName
with an implementation.
Overriding these selectors
tells Spotlight where to store
the indexed data and allows you
to better identify it later,
especially if you have
multiple indices.
If you do not override
domainIdentifier,
the default domain identifier
is the store identifier.
If you do not override
indexName,
the default index name is nil.
The next step in customizing
the Spotlight delegate
is defining an attribute set.
In the setup portion
of this session,
the NSCoreDataCore
SpotlightDelegate object
defined the attribute set
returned to Spotlight for us,
simply by ticking the check box
Index in Spotlight.
Now, I am going to demonstrate
exactly how to specify
the attributes that will be used
for indexing.
Specifying which attributes
that should be indexed
allows more explicit control
over what's indexed
and how it's searched for.
To do that, use
CSSearchableItemAttributeSet.
An attribute set contains a
number of predefined properties
allowing you to specify
the metadata to display
about the specified
managed object
when it appears
as a search result.
The attributes you choose depend
completely on your domain.
You can use
predefined properties
available in
CSSearchableItemAttributeSet
or you can define
your own properties.
The Tags app uses
the predefined properties
keywords, displayName,
and thumbnailData.
It's important to note
that you should only modify
an attribute set
on one thread at a time
as concurrent access to the
properties in an attribute set
has undefined behavior.
Back in the
TagsSpotlightDelegate class,
let's see how this works
by overriding
attributeSet (for object:).
In the override implementation,
begin by determining
if the object is
a Photo type object.
Next, initialize an attributeSet
with the content type .image.
Then, set
the properties identifier,
displayName, and thumbnailData
on the attribute set
using the appropriate attributes
from the Photo object.
Now, append tags
from the Photo object tag set
to the keywords array
on the attribute set.
It is worth mentioning
at this point
that if your model indexes
a relationship,
attributeSet (for object:)
must be overridden
so that it defines
what about that relationship
in particular is indexed.
Lastly,
return the attribute set.
Since the model is also
indexing Tag objects,
the code needs to handle
the case of a Tag.
For that, create an attribute
set with the contentType .text,
set the display name
to the name of the tag,
and then return
the attribute set.
As a last step, remove the
Core Data Spotlight display name
that was set in the model editor
in a previous step.
Let's go further
and define an event loop
for starting and stopping
indexing.
Earlier, when we setup
the Spotlight delegate,
startSpotlightIndexing
was called immediately after
creating the Spotlight delegate.
To give you precise
control over when the
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate
is performing indexing work,
stopSpotlightIndexing
has also been added
to the framework.
Using these two selectors
in concert gives you the ability
to start and stop indexing work
as necessary,
say, in the case where your app
is performing intense CPU
or disk activity operations.
Now, let's add some support
for being notified
when index updates complete.
When a change occurs
to an entity or entities
that is indexed in Spotlight,
that index is updated
asynchronously.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
the Core Data framework
has added index update
notifications.
To be informed when the index
update is complete, subscribe to
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate
.indexDidUpdateNotification,
which is posted
by the Spotlight delegate.
These notifications will
be posted after processing
a call to save:
on NSManagedObjectContext
or after the completion
of batch operations.
Let's see this in action.
First, check to see
if indexing is enabled.
If it is, then register for the
indexDidUpdateNotification.
Then, in the handler,
inspect the notification,
which will have
a userInfo dictionary
that contains
two key-value pairs,
similar to a remote change
notification:
an NSString UUID of the store
that for which
the Spotlight delegate
updated its index,
and the persistent history token
of the store for which
the Spotlight delegate
updated its index.
You can use both of these keys
to determine
if the store you're
interested in has been indexed
up to the latest persistent
history token.
If indexing is not enabled,
you can remove yourself
as an observer
from the notifications.
Prior to this year,
the only way to delete data
indexed by your app
was to either implement
the Core Spotlight APIs
to remove the index entries
or delete the entire
client graph in Core Data.
Crucially, new in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
Core Data has given the
developer a new way to manage
the Spotlight index without
deleting the client graph,
which is a great win
for user privacy!
First, the code
will stop indexing.
Then, call deleteSpotlightIndex.
Lastly, handle any resulting
error in the completion handler.
Note that calling this method
may return errors
from lower-layer dependencies,
such as Core Data
and Core Spotlight,
and you should be prepared
to handle those.
Now that I've shown you how
to customize an implementation
of the Spotlight delegate,
let's validate our setup
by adding full-text search
to the Tags app using
the Core Spotlight APIs.
The results will be
what was previously indexed.
Start by defining an extension
for PhotosViewController
that adopts the
UISearchResultsUpdating protocol
and a function
updateSearchResults
(for controller).
The Tags user interface
has a UISearchController.
We'll get the user input
from that search controller's
search bar.
If the user input is empty,
fetch all the images
from our data provider
and then reload
the collection view
as there is no search query.
Now let's handle the case
where there is a search query.
To start, sanitize
the user input string
by escaping it.
Next, define a query string
using the user's
sanitized input string.
Query strings operate
on the values associated
with a property in a
CSSearchableItemAttributeSet
object.
In this case, the code will be
operating on the
Keywords attribute
that was set in a previous step.
In the search query,
the modifiers c, d, and w
are being used.
c is for case insensitive.
d is for diacritic insensitive.
And w is for
a word-based search.
Now, create a CSSearchQuery
object by specifying
the formatted query string
that was just created
and an array of attribute names
that correspond
to properties defined by
CSSearchableItemAttributeSet.
This search query object
manages the criteria
to apply when searching
app content
that you have previously indexed
using the Spotlight delegate
APIs.
Following that,
set the foundItemsHandler.
This handler will be called
repetitively with items
that match the search query
previously defined.
In the completionHandler
for the query,
which will be called once,
check for an error
and potentially perform
some error handling.
Absent an error,
dispatch a block
onto the main queue
to use our data provider
to perform a fetch for the items
Spotlight found
and load them
in the user interface.
Lastly, and most importantly,
don't forget to start the query.
Now that the Tags app
has a Spotlight delegate
indexing its content,
the data has been freed
from within the app!
When I go to Spotlight,
and I search for a tag
I have previously added,
it returns two results:
the tag name itself and
the specific photo that I tagged
with the keyword
"Natural Bridges State Park".
Wrapping up,
we've learned about the
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate
and how it can help your users
find their content
inside your app
and outside your app
in Spotlight search,
setup the Spotlight
delegate quickly and easily
to start indexing
without a huge code burden,
and customized
our Spotlight delegate
using some of the new APIs
available to you this release.
I hope you've found
this information useful
and that you'll consider
adopting
NSCoreDataCoreSpotlightDelegate
in your project
to help users
find their content.
Have a great WWDC!
♪