[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Nikhil Palekar: Hi, I’m Nikhil,
and I’m an engineer
on the CloudKit team.
Today, I’m excited to introduce
you to CloudKit Console.
iCloud is an incredibly
powerful service
for expanding the capability
of your users’ devices
to the cloud.
Millions of people use iCloud
to store their photos,
files, and data securely.
CloudKit, the database
behind iCloud,
can efficiently and seamlessly
synchronize content
across devices
for a magical experience.
And being cloud-based,
CloudKit services
are managed online
through developer.apple.com.
Today, I’m excited to show you
CloudKit Console,
a redesigned set
of dashboard tools
that help you manage
how your applications
interact with CloudKit services.
In the Console, you can access
and manage CloudKit database
and view telemetry and logs
in a fresh new interface
that makes it easier than ever
to get things done.
Throughout the Console,
the content follows the same
familiar structure
that you're used to
with other Apple applications:
context and account information
on the top,
navigation and properties
on the left,
and details in the middle.
From this new layout,
you can easily select a feature,
then dive deeper
into the details.
Let’s start by looking
at a few features
in the new Database app.
In case you're new
to CloudKit database,
the short story
is that CloudKit databases
exist within a container
defined for your use case,
and developers use
two database environments:
development and production.
Database schemas are promoted
from development to production
once the app developer
is comfortable with the changes
they made during development.
As you’re getting started,
you can iterate quickly
on development databases
using just-in-time
schema creation
or by defining your
data model in the Console.
When you're ready, you can
deploy the schema to production
and CloudKit will verify
the integrity of the updates
to avoid breaking older clients
of your database.
As I launch the Database app,
I can see a list of containers
owned by my developer team.
The next time
I launch the Console,
it will bring me straight
to the last container I visited.
I’ve selected the Development
environment in the dropdown,
and now let’s look
at the Schema section
to explore how
record types are defined.
Record types are used
to define data structures
in CloudKit database.
I can quickly view the list
of existing record types,
and then click to see details
on the fields and indexes.
Adding a field is simple.
I just provide a name
for my new field,
and choose
its corresponding type.
Managing indexes in the Console
is also straightforward.
From this page, I can easily
view the existing indexes,
or click to create a new index
by selecting a field
and choosing one of the three
index types.
Here, I’m adding
a sortable index
to alphabetically
sort the author field.
And while I’m managing
the schema,
let's take a quick look at
how security roles are managed
for the public database.
If you've used CloudKit before,
you may already
be using security roles
to manage access to records
in your public database.
And now there's a new UI
that makes them easier than ever
to define and manage.
Now that I have a schema
defined for my app,
let’s use the Console
to explore some data
that I’ve stored
during development.
From this view, I can either
create or view records.
The new UI presents
a left-to-right flow
for selecting context
of how I want to retrieve
records for display,
starting with the database,
then the zone,
and finally the record type.
Once I set the context, I can
see records in the list view
and see their details
in the detail view.
If I need to refine the request,
I can use the new query builder
to apply filters
so I can get to
the exact records I want.
So let’s say that I’m building
a feature for my app
that writes a new record type
into CloudKit,
and I want to verify
what CloudKit actually receives
in the development environment.
With the new UI,
I can simply set up
the query once, save it...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and then come back
to it again
as my development
moves forward.
The URLs used
throughout the Console
are also structured to point
directly to specific features.
So for example,
if I want to have
fast access to the record view,
I can just add that direct link
to my Safari bookmarks.
With the new Console,
managing your data and schema
is quick and intuitive,
with a familiar user experience
across each feature.
Now that I’ve created a schema
and confirmed
that I have the right data
stored in development,
I’m ready to deploy the schema
to the production environment.
Earlier, I mentioned
the difference
between development
and production,
so let me show you how
the Console makes it easier
and safer to deploy
a schema to production.
Clicking "Deploy Schema Changes"
brings me to a clean,
actionable view of the changes
that will be applied
to my production deployment.
Here, I can see everything
that’s changed
between my previous production
schema and the changes
that would be applied from
the development environment.
Since production changes
cannot be reversed,
this diff view gives me
a quick way to confirm
that only my intended changes
end up in the production
environment.
That’s it for the features
in the new Database app,
so now let’s take a look
at Telemetry.
After setting up the database
and promoting my schema
to production,
I’m moving to the next part
of the developer lifecycle
where I can observe
and investigate
how my app is
interacting with CloudKit.
The Telemetry app
within the Console
gives me a number of charts
that show key metrics
about how my app is interacting
with the database.
Request rate, server latency,
error count,
and average request size
are all shown
in filterable charts that
help me find the data I need.
These charts
can help me identify
when my app behavior
changes over time
and give me a signal about
whether a new version of my app
is behaving in unexpected ways.
Now let’s take a look
at the Logs app.
The Logs app within the Console
lets me dive even deeper.
It shows detailed logging output
from CloudKit Database
so I can see how my app requests
have actually been processed.
This app is a great tool for
debugging and investigations,
both during development
and in production.
We think you’re going to love
using CloudKit Console
as you’re developing
and shipping your apps.
I hope you’ll spend some time
trying the new schema management
and querying capabilities
in the Database app
and review
the new instrumentation
in the Logs and Telemetry apps
that give you
actionable information
about how you’re using CloudKit.
We’re also excited to have
brand-new documentation
at developer.apple.com
as well as helpful
sample projects on GitHub.
Finally, if you’re interested
in learning
about new CloudKit features,
please review the
"Explore CloudKit" collection.
Thanks for your time today.
I hope you enjoyed
meeting CloudKit Console.
♪