[upbeat music]
[Michael]
Hi, I'm Michael Ochs.
I'm a framework engineer
on the UIKit team.
Welcome to Focus
on iPad keyboard navigation.
People love using hardware
keyboards with their iPads.
Mac Catalyst and iPadOS
15 introduce powerful API
to support keyboard navigation
in your app.
Navigating any app
with a keyboard on iPadOS
will feel very familiar.
The tab key navigates between
significant areas in an app.
The arrow keys navigate
within an area,
and an item can be
selected with the return key
on iPadOS or the space bar
on Mac Catalyst.
If your app already
uses these key commands,
your custom commands
will no longer work.
I'll show you how to resolve
these conflicts later.
First, let me show you
keyboard navigation in action.
In Photos, I can press the tab
key to move the focus
from the Library cell
in the sidebar
to the photos grid on the right.
Now I can navigate
between the photos
in the grid
using the arrow keys.
Once I found
the photo I'm looking for,
I can select it
by pressing return.
Once you compile
with the iOS 15 SDK,
this behavior will be
enabled automatically
for text fields,
text views, and sidebars.
You should also
opt in other collection,
table, and custom views
for a great experience.
I'll show you how
to do this in a minute.
I know this
is an exciting feature,
but don't make every element
in your app keyboard navigable.
Keyboard navigation
is intended
to give users access
to key features of your app,
so focus on text input, lists,
and collection views.
Leave controls such as buttons,
segmented controls,
and switches aside.
Full Keyboard access already
allows these controls
to be keyboard navigable.
To learn more
about full Keyboard access,
check out "Support Full Keyboard
Access in your iOS app."
Keyboard navigation on iPadOS
uses the same focus system
as tvOS
If you have
written tvOS apps before,
many of the APIs
will feel familiar.
However,
there are some new APIs
and behavioral differences
that you should be aware of.
If you wanna learn more about
the focus system in general,
check out
"Focus Interaction in tvOS."
In this video,
I'm going to show you how
to make more content in your app
focusable and how
to customize the appearance
of these focusable items.
I'll show you some special
behavior in sidebars
that you should be aware of,
and we are going to talk
about focus groups, a new way
to define structure in your app.
At the end, I'm going to show
you some important changes
in the responder chain that
you should be familiar with.
But now,
let's take a look at how
to make more elements
in your UI focusable.
canBecomeFocused
is the single source of truth.
It is a read-only
property of UIFocusItem.
Override it and return
true to make an item focusable.
Now, you might be wondering,
what is a focus item?
The backbone of the focus
system are the two protocols:
UIFocusItem
and UIFocusEnvironment.
FocusItems are simply that,
items that can be focused.
FocusEnvironments
define the hierarchy
of focusable items.
UIView conforms to both
of these protocols,
since any view
can be focused itself,
but it can also contain subviews
that can be focused.
UIViewController,
on the other hand,
only conforms
to UIFocusEnvironment,
since it doesn't provide
any visuals itself.
You can also implement both
protocols on your own objects.
This allows you to adopt focus
in content that is rendered
with other technologies,
like Metal.
The most likely candidates
for keyboard navigation
are cells in a table
or collection view.
UIKit offers
some convenience APIs,
so you don't have to subclass.
Set allowsFocus to true
on a table or collection view
to make all
of its cells focusable.
Note that in sidebars,
allowsFocus is true by default.
For more fine-grained control,
you can use canFocusItemAt
indexPath in your delegate
to control focusability
for each cell individually.
Both of these methods
will only have an effect
on cells that don't
override canBecomeFocused.
If a focus item is not
behaving as you would expect,
there are some
debugging tools available.
In lldb you can call
UIFocusDebugger.
CheckFocusability(for item:)
and pass in the item
you want to debug.
For example, a view that you
are trying to make focusable.
It will give you an explanation
of why the focus system
does not consider this
item to be focusable.
So, we talked about how
to make your UI focusable.
Let's take a closer
look at the appearance
of focused items.
There are two styles
you will commonly see
throughout the system.
First, there is the Halo Effect,
similar to the focus ring
on macOS.
In fact, this is the default
effect on Mac Catalyst.
On iPadOS,
you can use this effect
by assigning a UIFocusHaloEffect
to the focusEffect property.
If initialized with no
arguments,
the system will infer
the shape of the halo.
You can also customize the shape
to better match the content.
For example,
if an image has rounded corners,
the halo should match
its appearance
by also having rounded corners.
UIFocusHaloEffect has
a number of initializers
for different shapes,
including one for rounded rects.
Use these initializers
to make sure the halo's shape
creates an outline
around your view's content.
The Halo Effect also gives you
control over its position
in the view hierarchy.
Here the halo is rendering
above the badge on the image,
but it would look better
if the halo was
between the image and the badge.
By specifying the image view
as the referenceView,
UIKit will render the halo
on top of the image
and below the badge.
The reference view
defines the relative order
of the halo
in the view hierarchy.
You can also
specify a container view,
which defines the superview
of the halo effect.
This is useful
if the direct superview
of the focused item
is clipping its content.
Both of these are optional,
and you should only provide them
if the inferred appearance
isn't what you expect.
Cells in collection
and table views should
show a halo around
them only when they have
fully-opaque content,
like an image.
In all other cases,
when a cell becomes focused,
it should look highlighted.
This means the background
should turn into the tint color
of your app,
and the foreground color
for text and icons should
be adjusted for good contrast.
This highlight appearance is not
available as a UIFocusEffect.
Instead,
you will get this appearance
automatically
when using the background
and content configurations
introduced in iOS 14.
To learn more about these,
take a look
at "Modern cell configuration."
If you're not using background
and content configurations,
the sample app shows you
how to get the correct color
in all cases.
Make sure to check that out.
Now, if you want
to apply a custom appearance,
first set
the focusEffect property to nil.
This turns off
any system styling.
Next override
didUpdateFocus (in: context
withAnimationCoordinator :)
on your focus item.
If the next focused item
is self,
apply styling to indicate focus.
If the previously-focused
item is self,
restore
the nonfocused appearance.
You should only make changes
in didUpdateFocus(in: context)
when the next
or previously focused item
is relevant
to this environment.
This is because
all ancestor environments
of the previously focused item,
as well
as the next focused item,
receive a call
to didUpdateFocus(in: context).
So every superview and view
controller will get this call.
This allows for very
flexible implementations,
where a parent can react
to focus changes of a child.
Now let's take a closer look
at a feature specific
to sidebars
and similar context-changing UI.
Selection and focus
are two different concepts.
However, in a sidebar,
when I move focus,
the selection follows.
Likewise, if I select
a new cell by tapping on it,
focus also moves
to this newly-selected cell.
This is called
"selection follows focus."
Set this property
on any table or collection view
to the behavior you want
for most of the cells.
If you want to change the
behavior for individual cells,
implement selectionFollowsFocus
ForItemAtIndexPath
in your delegate.
Turning off
selectionFollowsFocus
is useful when selecting a cell
causes a disruptive action
to occur, such
as pushing a new view controller
in the same column
or presenting an alert.
For example, in Photos,
selecting "new album"
shows an alert asking
for the album's name.
When using the delegate,
the value of the property
still matters.
Set selectionFollowsFocus
to the overall intent
of the collection view
and then use the delegate
to express special behavior
for individual cells.
The system will take
both values into account
when choosing
the right behavior.
Now, let's take
a look at focus groups,
a new feature
for keyboard navigation
to express structure
in your app.
UIKit automatically infers
focus groups from the hierarchy,
but you can also declare
them explicitly to customize
how the tab key moves
focus through your app.
tvOS only
uses directional focus.
You can reach every
single element simply by swiping
on the Siri Remote or using
the arrow keys on a keyboard.
iPadOS and Mac Catalyst,
on the other hand,
have two different methods
of navigating with the keyboard:
The arrow keys
and the tab key.
Unlike tvOS,
the arrow keys only move focus
within a defined area
of your app.
These areas
are called focus groups.
For example,
I can navigate the list
of reminders using the up
and down arrow keys.
To navigate the lists,
I can press the tab key
to focus on the search field
and then press tab again
to move to the lists.
If I press tab one more time,
focus loops
back to the reminders.
The reminders, the search field,
and the lists
are each a focus group,
and the tab key
moves focus between them.
When focus moves to a group,
it chooses an item inside
of that group to focus on.
That item is called
the group's primary item.
A group's
primary item can change.
For example, here I focus
on the second reminder.
The focus system remembers this
when I switch away
from this group,
and when I come
back to the reminders,
focus moves to the second item
again
as this item is now
the group's primary item.
The tab key connects
the primary items of each group
and moves focus between them.
This is called the tab loop.
Some environments define
their own focus groups
by default.
These include scroll views
like collection and table view,
as well as text input classes,
like text fields and text views.
If an environment does
not define its own group,
it inherits the group
of the parent environment,
commonly its superview
or view controller.
For example, by default,
every cell automatically belongs
to the group
of its collection view.
By being in the same group,
you can navigate between
cells with the arrow keys.
To define
a focus group yourself,
assign a focus group identifier
to any view or view controller.
When two environments
share the same identifier,
either explicitly
or by inheritance,
they are part of the same group.
To customize the primary item
of a group,
assign a focus group priority
to that item.
This defines how important
an item is within the group.
The visible item
with the highest priority
is the group's primary item.
By default,
the system assigns one
of the predefined priorities:
Ignored, the default priority;
previously focused;
prioritized,
indicating an item is more
important than others,
like a selected cell;
and currently focused,
which is the highest
priority possible.
It's important to understand
that you can never lower
the priority
of an item below
its system-provided priority.
Instead,
you should raise the priority
of a different item.
For example,
if you assign a priority higher
than .previouslyFocused
to a cell,
that cell will
become more important
than the last-focused
item of that group.
So even if this customized cell
and the previously focused cell
are both visible,
the customized cell would become
the primary item because
it has a higher priority.
So, now you know how
to group your items together.
Next, let's focus
on how these groups are sorted.
Here, we see Reminders again.
As mentioned before,
each table and collection view,
as well as each text field,
define its own group.
As seen before, when pressing
the tab key continuously,
focus goes from the search field
to the lists in the sidebar,
and then
to the reminders on the right.
This is what
UIKit does by default.
However, if you built this
kind of container view yourself,
focus would move from the search
field straight to the reminders
because all the groups
are sorted in reading order,
leading to trailing,
top to bottom.
The focus system does
not know that the sidebar
is a distinct column.
To ensure the search field
and lists are sorted
in one continuous block,
you can put them
in a common parent group.
This is done by defining
a focus group identifier
on the sidebar's container view.
Even though this new group does
not contain any focusable items
directly, the tab loop will
move from the search field group
to the lists group before
moving on to the reminders list.
Many standard UIKit
presentations already
provide these
intermediate groups.
For custom container views,
declare your own
focusGroupIdentifier
on common ancestors.
Focus groups are an easy way
to define the visual
structure of your app.
You don't have to define
a fixed order for your tab loop.
Instead,
the system uses focus groups
to derive a tab loop order
that takes into account
reading direction, layout,
and visibility
to provide
a consistent experience.
When customizing focus groups
in your app,
UIFocusDebugger is your friend.
If you call checkFocusGroupTree
(for environment:)
it'll print
the focus group structure,
starting
at the passed-in environment.
You can even
pass in the focus system itself
to see all current groups.
Now, this textual structure
is helpful,
but there's
one more debugging tool.
Remember the screenshot
I showed you
with the focus groups
and Reminders?
You can actually get this live
in your app.
When enabled,
the focus loop debugger
visualizes the tab loop order
in your app when you press
and hold the option key.
And when pressing option
and control,
you get a visualization
of the focus groups.
In this mode,
the primary item of a group
is indicated by a dotted line.
To enable it,
go to your scheme settings
in Xcode, select "run,"
and then "arguments."
Then add the launch argument
-UIFocusLoopDebuggerEnabled YES,
and don't forget to put
the dash in front of it.
Now, whenever you run
your app from Xcode,
this debug overlay
is available right in your app.
This covers the basics of focus
on iPadOS and Mac Catalyst.
There's one more topic to cover
for keyboard navigation,
and that's the responder chain.
Since both the responder chain
and the focus system are dealing
with keyboard input,
UIKit synchronizes these systems
as much as possible to make
sure the focused item is always
inside the first responder or
is the first responder itself.
Let's look at a simplified view
hierarchy with a text field
and a collection view cell.
Currently,
the text field is focused,
indicated by the solid ring,
and it is also
the first responder,
indicated by the dashed ring.
When focus moves to
this collection view cell,
UIKit also tries to move
the first responder
to this cell.
If this cell returns false
from canBecomeFirstResponder,
the system iterates
up the responder chain
to find a responder
that returns true.
In this case, that responder
is the cell's view controller.
Note that the inverse
is also true.
When the first responder
changes,
the focus system will try
to find a new focusable item
inside of that responder.
With this relationship
between the first responder
and the focused item, key events
will always be delivered
to the focused item and move up
the responder chain from there.
This allows for some
interesting new behavior.
For example,
if a cell responds to a key
command and becomes focused,
the key command
is delivered to that cell.
For ways to use this,
take a look at our sample app.
When updating
your app for iPadOS 15,
be conscious about where
you call becomeFirstResponder.
Since the responder chain
and focus are synchronized,
changing the first responder
will force focus to update.
This might be
very disruptive to your users.
It is typically best to avoid
calling becomeFirstResponder,
especially in response
to a focus update.
The focus system provides
a consistent experience
across all apps.
To do this, it needs priority
for certain key commands.
If your app is using
a key command like tab
or arrow down,
that key command will
no longer work when
compiling with the iOS 15 SDK.
If this key command is used
to build your own
custom keyboard navigation,
you can leave it untouched.
It'll work on previous versions,
and on iPadOS 15,
the focus system will take over.
Otherwise,
remap this key command.
If you really want to continue
using this key command,
make sure it doesn't break
keyboard navigation,
and then set
wantsPriorityOverSystemBehavior
to true.
If you want to learn more
about improvements
to keyboard shortcuts,
check out "Take your iPad apps
to the next level."
If you handle presses manually
by implementing pressesBegan,
pressesChanged,
pressesEnded,
and pressesCancelled,
make sure to implement all
of these methods
and call super consistently
for presses
that you don't handle.
Keyboard navigation
in iPadOS 15 and Mac Catalyst
is a powerful
tool for your users.
Make collection
and table views focusable
to provide
a great user experience.
Update your key commands
so they don't collide
with keyboard navigation.
Also, check out the sample app,
which illustrates
a couple more features,
such as building
a great search experience,
custom selections, focus guides,
and much more.
I can't wait to see
what you're building
with keyboard navigation
on iPadOS 15.
Thank you for watching.
[percussive music]