[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Rui Paulo: Hello, everyone,
I'm Rui.
Today, my colleague Eric
and I are going to talk about
how you can speed up
your app's networking
with HTTP/3 and QUIC --
two new protocols available
in iOS 15 and macOS Monterey.
We'll begin by exploring
the evolution of HTTP
and how HTTP/3
improves performance.
We'll also talk about QUIC,
the new transport protocol
behind HTTP/3.
After that, we'll explain how
you can use HTTP/3 in URLSession
and how you should
configure your HTTP server
to support HTTP/3.
Finally, we'll take a deep dive
into the API for using QUIC
and how you can implement
your custom networking protocols
on top of QUIC.
Let's then begin
with the evolution of HTTP.
Let's say we need
to fetch a resource.
We set up a connection,
send the request,
wait for the server
to process it,
and receive a response.
Now, if we want to fetch
another resource
before the first one finishes,
we have go through
the same process again:
setting up a connection,
sending the request,
waiting for processing,
and receiving the response,
this time indicated
in dark green.
Here's another example
for a third resource, in orange.
As outlined by the diagram,
a lot of time is spent
on connection setup.
What if we reuse a single
HTTP/1 connection?
We saved the connection
set up time,
but a request can only be sent
after the previous
response has ended.
This is known
as head-of-line blocking.
In the past,
HTTP implementations
used many parallel connections
to overcome this problem.
The number of parallel
HTTP connections
was even configurable
by the app.
However, this led to inefficient
networking behaviors
for both client and server.
HTTP/2 solves
head-of-line blocking
by multiplexing multiple streams
on a single connection.
Requests are sent earlier,
and data from different streams
can be interleaved.
This allows more efficient use
of a single TCP connection,
as idle waiting time
is drastically reduced.
With HTTP/3, connection
set up is much faster,
so requests can go out sooner.
However, that's not
the only benefit of HTTP/3.
HTTP/3 streams are independent,
which is different from HTTP/2,
where all streams share
a single TCP connection.
On most networks,
packets are lost.
This is a normal event
on wireless networks
and a natural part of detecting
the capacity of a network.
In HTTP/2, packet loss
may affect many streams
since all of the HTTP/2 streams
share a single TCP connection.
In HTTP/3,
only the corresponding
HTTP stream is affected.
Data that belongs
to other streams
can be delivered earlier.
We've just shown how HTTP/3 can
establish a connection sooner
and how it can better cope
with packet loss.
These improvements are enabled
by the underlying
transport protocol: QUIC.
QUIC is a new reliable
transport protocol
that has been standardized
by the
Internet Engineering Task Force.
It's based on
the same concepts of TCP
but provides
end-to-end encryption,
multiplexed streams,
and authentication.
QUIC's security builds on top of
the well-known TLS 1.3 protocol.
The major benefit of QUIC
is improved performance.
Let's explore how QUIC
achieves just that.
QUIC relies on TLS 1.3
to perform a secure handshake
and does not require
the familiar TCP
three-way handshake,
reducing the handshake time
to a single round trip.
Multiplexed streams
are a key concept of QUIC,
so it doesn't suffer
from head-of-line blocking.
A QUIC endpoint
is able to communicate
more complex information
about packets it has received
to the other endpoint and is not
encumbered by TCP's limits,
so QUIC connections experience
improved loss recovery.
The protocol also supports
connection migration
which allows connections
to move seamlessly
across different
network interfaces
without reestablishing
a session,
for example, between
cellular networks and Wi-Fi.
If you would like to learn more
about networking delays,
please watch the "Reduce network
delays for your app" session.
Let's talk about how
you can use HTTP/3 in your app.
If you're using URLSession,
you don't need to change
your app since iOS 15
and macOS Monterey ship
with HTTP/3 enabled by default.
Once you enable HTTP/3
on your server,
you're good to go.
Both the upcoming
HTTP/3 RFC version
and the earlier HTTP/3
Draft version 29 are supported.
So how can you make sure
your app is using HTTP/3?
Let's use Instruments
to find out!
In Xcode 13, we're introducing
a new instrument
within the networking
profiling template
to inspect HTTP Traffic.
It taps into URLSession
directly,
so there's no setup required.
We can use Instruments
to find out
if our app is using HTTP/3
or an earlier HTTP version.
We're going to launch
an iOS app that, upon starting,
fetches a set of dog pictures.
We'll then inspect
HTTP headers to find out
how the server
is advertising HTTP/3.
Let's go ahead and select
the Network profiling template.
Let's click Record
on the top left.
A prompt will be displayed
indicating
the privacy implications
of recording HTTP Traffic.
After we agree,
Instruments will begin recording
HTTP transactions.
Next, Instruments
will show a plot
with all HTTP transactions
per app and per domain.
We have now captured
all the data that we need.
We can click the Pause button
located on the top left.
Let's select the domain
that we're using.
We can do that
by Option-clicking
on the HTTP transactions
and then selecting the domain.
We need to configure
Instruments
to show the details
of the HTTP Transactions.
To accomplish that, make sure
the menu on the left side shows
HTTP Transactions.
Let's select the first request.
By scrolling right, we can find
the HTTP Version column
which identifies the version of
HTTP that this transaction used.
Hm, we're still using HTTP/2,
but why is that?
On the right-hand side,
we can find
the extended detail view that
contains the response headers.
This give us the answer:
the server used
HTTP Alternative Services
to advertise support for HTTP/3.
URLSession won't use HTTP/3
unless it was advertised.
In this example,
HTTP/3 was advertised
through the Alt-Svc HTTP header.
It's common for HTTP servers
to advertise support for HTTP/3,
using this header.
This information is remembered
for future connections,
and we call this
"service discovery."
Now let's record the app again.
Once Instruments
relaunches the app,
the same set of HTTP
transactions take place.
Again, we can now
pause Instruments.
Let's zoom in again and inspect
the first transaction.
Since we've remembered that
the server supported HTTP/3,
we're now using HTTP/3.
HTTP/3 service discovery
is transparent to your app.
Discovery of HTTP/3 server
support happens in two ways.
The recommended approach
is to configure your DNS server
to advertise support for HTTP/3
through the HTTPS
resource record.
Simply configure
the application layer protocol
to advertise HTTP/3
using the h3 string.
You should also configure
your server
to add a new header
that advertises HTTP/3
using Alternative Services.
Your server should send
a Alt-Svc header
that advertises HTTP/3.
This includes the port number
and the max-age of the service,
in seconds.
The advantage
of the DNS record is that
since the information is in DNS,
an HTTP/3 connection
can be established
the very first time your app
tries to contact to your server.
When you know that
your server supports HTTP/3,
and you would like to speed up
the discovery process,
you can use the
assumesHTTP3Capable property.
This allows the HTTP stack
to assume that you have
an HTTP/3 server
but does not guarantee
that HTTP/3 will be used.
Networks may still block
HTTP/3,
or your server may not
actually support HTTP/3.
In that case,
we'll fall back to HTTP/2.
HTTP allows clients to specify
priorities for each resource.
Since resources
are often related,
priorities allow the server
to send some resources
earlier than others,
based on the needs
of the client.
For example, user experience
for web browsing can be improved
by prioritizing resources
that affect web page rendering
the most.
A priority scheme
was introduced in HTTP/2
but it was not often respected
due to its complexity.
For that reason,
the old priority model
was removed from HTTP/3.
A new, simpler model,
which relies on HTTP headers,
is used by the HTTP/3 stack.
In this model,
priority is specified
with an urgency parameter --
zero to seven --
and an optional incremental
delivery parameter.
When using URLSession,
the API to support priorities
remains the same.
You still specify
the HTTP priority,
using the priority property,
which is communicated
to the server using urgency.
You can enable
incremental delivery with
the prefersIncrementalDelivery
property.
The default priority is 3.
URLSession infers
incremental delivery
depending on whether
a convenience API --
like the async data method --
is used.
When your app is downloading
content that cannot be processed
until the entire resource
is downloaded,
you should set this property
to false.
Dynamically changing
the priority of a resource
after the request was sent
is also supported.
For example, you can prefetch
photos at a lower priority
and then raise that priority
as the user navigates
to that section of your app.
Next, my colleague Eric
is going to explain
how you can change
your custom networking protocols
to adopt QUIC.
Thank you.
Eric Kinnear: Thanks, Rui!
As we discussed earlier,
HTTP/3 is built on top of QUIC,
which provides
multiplexed streams,
similar to those found
in HTTP/2,
but without the problems
introduced
by sharing a single
TCP connection
as the underlying transport.
A QUIC transport connection --
or QUIC tunnel --
multiplexes data
for multiple unidirectional
or bidirectional QUIC streams.
Streams can be created
by either endpoint,
can concurrently send data
interleaved with other streams,
and have states similar
to the traditional streams
provided by TCP.
Best of all, QUIC has
TLS 1.3 security built right in
and can better respond
to changing network conditions.
These capabilities are useful
for more than just HTTP.
If your application
is exchanging
non-request/response based data,
could benefit from having
multiplexed streams
that share an underlying
transport context,
or is implementing
any other custom protocol --
such as peer-to-peer
communication or RPC calls --
consider using QUIC transport
for your app.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
NWProtocolQUIC joins
the other built-in protocols
provided by Network.framework.
Creating a connection
that uses QUIC is very familiar.
Simply provide your endpoint
and the newly available
QUIC parameters.
These parameters specify
the ALPN string,
the application layer protocol
to negotiate with the server.
Set a state update handler --
just like usual --
to be able to respond
as the connection makes progress
and becomes ready.
And, finally, start your
connection on a dispatch queue
that you'd like to use
for those state updates
and other callbacks.
Now that you've got
a QUIC stream established,
you can send and receive data
just like any other
NWConnection.
Use the send function to provide
the data you'd like to send
to the remote endpoint,
and schedule subsequent sends
when complete.
Use receive to handle
incoming data,
and schedule subsequent
receives when it completes.
Last year, we introduced
the Connection Group object
in Network.framework
to make it easier
to handle situations
where multiple connections
are related or grouped.
QUIC streams
that are multiplexed
on an underlying
transport context --
or tunnel --
are logically grouped
based on that relationship
and can be used
with a new group type:
NWMultiplexGroup.
A Connection Group
follows a lifecycle
similar to that of the other
Network.framework objects
and allows you to reason
about the state
of the underlying QUIC tunnel
shared by your QUIC streams.
It also allows you to create
new outgoing streams
from a specific QUIC tunnel
as well as receive
new incoming streams initiated
by the remote endpoint.
To create a connection group
for a multiplexing protocol,
use a multiplex
group descriptor.
In this case,
we'll create a group descriptor
to example.com on port 443.
Next, we create
a NWConnectionGroup
with that descriptor
and QUIC parameters,
providing our ALPN string
when we create them.
Just like with an NWConnection,
we set a state update handler,
but this time,
it's tracking the state
of the underlying QUIC tunnel,
rather than the state
of an individual stream.
Finally, we start
the connection group,
providing our callback queue.
New outgoing streams can be
created by initializing
a NWConnection from the group
or by calling the extract
function on the group.
Incoming streams initiated
by the remote endpoint
can be handled by setting
the new connection handler
on the group.
These connections can be set up
as usual with a state handler --
this time tracking
the stream state --
and started with the queue
to use for callbacks.
Just like with other protocols,
you can use QUIC.Options
for configuration
when creating
your parameter's object.
For QUIC, you can configure
the transport parameters
listed in the QUIC
specification,
and you can also customize
properties of individual streams
when creating them
from a connection group;
for example, if you want create
a new, unidirectional stream.
If you're using NWListener
to run a server in your app,
it has also been enhanced
to allow you to receive
new incoming QUIC tunnels
via the
newConnectionGroupHandler.
Your newConnectionGroupHandler
will be called
every time someone establishes
a new QUIC tunnel
to your server.
Inside that handler, you can
set up the group as usual
to receive state updates.
This is also a good place to set
the new connection handler
we were just discussing.
If you'd like to receive
subsequent streams
opened on this tunnel,
start the group with the queue
to use for callbacks,
and you're all set!
Finally, you can use
NWProtocolMetadata
to access information
about streams.
For example, you might want
to check the stream ID
of a newly created stream.
And when you're done
with a stream,
if your custom protocol has
defined applicationError codes,
you can use the metadata
to communicate any errors
to the remote endpoint
before you cancel the stream.
So we've just explored
how we can use
the new NWMultiplexGroup type
to create and manage
QUIC tunnels,
and from that group,
create individual NWConnections
for each QUIC stream.
We can use a NWListener
to listen for incoming tunnels,
and use the resulting
connection groups
to receive new incoming streams.
On those streams,
we can send and receive data
just like on
any other connection,
and we can use
QUIC protocol options
to specify transport parameters
and configure streams,
while using
QUIC protocol metadata
to inspect the streams
and communicate
QUIC-specific information
to the remote endpoint.
Now that we've improved
the networking in our app
by adopting QUIC,
how do we tell if it's working?
We can launch our app
while debugging,
with a new environment variable
that outputs qlog files.
qlog is a new standardized
logging format
proposed in the IETF,
which allows you to export
even richer information
about how your QUIC connections
are behaving
than would be present
in a traditional packet capture.
After your test run, you can use
the Devices window in Xcode
to download your app's container
with the qlog files
for analysis.
And there are a number
of different open-source
visualizations
that make it much easier
to introspect the behavior
of your QUIC connections.
Today, we've examined
the improvements
that HTTP/3 provides
for your HTTP traffic.
On the client,
it's already on by default
for users of the modern
networking APIs,
so enable HTTP/3 on your server
to take advantage
of its increased performance
and resilience
to changing network conditions.
If you're using a custom,
non-HTTP networking protocol,
use the new multiplexing
protocol support
built into Network.framework
to create QUIC connections
with NWConnectionGroup.
And whichever protocol
you're using,
you can use new debugging tools
to visualize
the awesome benefits
of the next generation
of networking protocols.
Thanks for watching.
♪