[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Daniel Li: Welcome to "Add
intelligence to your widgets."
My name’s Daniel,
and I’m an engineer on
the Proactive Intelligence team
at Apple.
In this session,
I’ll show you
how your widgets can
work with the system
to provide intelligent
experiences for your users
so your widgets can show up
right when they need them.
Widgets live in many places.
From the Home screen on iOS
to Notification Center on macOS,
widgets provide users
with information
that they can quickly view
with just a glance.
With iPadOS 15, widgets come
to the iPad Home screen as well.
There are now
more places than ever
for your widgets to call home.
I’ll first talk about
what it means
for widgets to be intelligent
in the system,
and then I’ll show you
how you can enable intelligence
for your widgets by donating
relevant information
with the available APIs.
Let’s first go over
widget intelligence.
On iPhone and iPad,
widgets can be placed together
in a Smart Stack,
where they can be
scrolled through
to provide different kinds
of information in one place.
When a user edits a stack,
in addition to being able
to add, remove,
or reorder widgets,
they can also view
and manage
the stack’s
intelligent behaviors.
iOS 14 introduced Smart Rotate.
Smart Rotate allows the system,
at the right time,
to automatically
scroll to a widget
that is already in a stack.
To know when to rotate
to a widget,
the system uses
relevance signals
that the widget provides
alongside its timeline entries.
It can also rotate to a widget
by learning patterns
in the user’s behavior.
It does so by receiving
donations from the app
whenever the user
views information
corresponding to the widget.
With Smart Rotate,
if I have a Weather widget,
a Reminders widget, and
a Calendar widget in a stack,
the Weather widget
might tell the system
to suggest itself in the morning
when I wake up
to give me
an overview of the day.
At 9:30, the Calendar widget
may tell the system
that I have a meeting
coming up at 10,
so my stack might rotate
to Calendar.
In the afternoon,
one of my reminders
has a due date of 3:00 p.m.,
so the widget
might tell the stack
to rotate to Reminders.
And in the evening,
the Weather widget
might tell the system
to show me the weather again
because it just started raining,
so I know to take an umbrella
if I go out for dinner.
iOS 15 introduces a new feature
called Widget Suggestions,
a brand-new way for users
to discover your widget
and receive proactive
and relevant information.
For Smart Stacks with
Widget Suggestions enabled,
the system can insert
a new widget into a stack
that doesn’t already contain it.
The system can do this given an
explicit donation from your app.
And like with Smart Rotate,
the system can also
make a Widget Suggestion
by learning the user’s
behavioral patterns in your app.
With Widget Suggestions,
if I only had a Weather widget
and a Reminders widget
in my stack,
I would still see
Smart Rotations to these widgets
throughout the day.
But since I have
that meeting at 10:00,
and I don’t have
the Calendar widget in my stack,
the Calendar app
may tell the system
to proactively insert the widget
into my stack at 9:30
so I don’t forget.
After the widget
is no longer relevant,
the system will remove it
from my stack.
When I finish
my evening workout,
the system might show me
the Fitness widget
so I can get a quick summary
of my day’s progress
in closing my rings.
And afterward,
the stack will again return
to its original state.
Since apps tell the system
to temporarily insert widgets
when they’re useful,
they can help users
discover widgets
that they may not
even know existed.
Now let’s see how you can adopt
both Smart Rotate
and Widget Suggestions
using the available APIs
to donate relevant signals
to the system.
When donating,
you should consider
all the possible information
your widget can show
and determine which types are
more suitable for a suggestion
than others.
The end goal when choosing
how to make donations
to the system
is to provide
timely, glanceable information
with obvious value to the user,
so you should consider
highlighting situations
that users may find
more interesting than others.
A weather widget,
for example,
could consider imminent rainfall
to be a situation
suitable for suggestion
as opposed to,
say, a point in time where
only the temperature has changed
by an unremarkable amount.
You can adopt Smart Rotate
and Widget Suggestions
for your widgets
in three separate ways.
First, your app can donate
an INRelevantShortcut
to tell the system
when it should create
a Widget Suggestion
for one of your widgets.
Second, your widget can
provide relevance scores
through
TimelineEntryRelevance
to enable Smart Rotations
when the widget is in a stack.
And third, if your widget
is configurable,
when your app donates
the configuration intent
using INInteraction,
the system can learn
the user’s behavioral patterns
to promote your widget
through both Smart Rotations
and Widget Suggestions.
Each of these APIs
enhances your widget’s presence
in powerful ways
but they all work
a bit differently,
so let’s break it down.
Let’s start with donating
INRelevantShortcuts
for Widget Suggestions.
Whether you use an intent
to configure your widget or not,
when your app becomes aware
of a highly relevant situation
to show your widget to the user,
donating an INRelevantShortcut
allows the system to proactively
insert your widget
into one of the user’s stacks
if they don’t already
have your widget
on their Home screen.
A relevant shortcut can either
specify a period of time
that it’s relevant
or have the system determine
when to insert the widget
based on the user’s
behavioral patterns.
INRelevantShortcut
supports both static
and intent-configured widgets
but the donation
will look a little different
for each configuration type,
so let’s take a look at
how to adopt for both types.
If your widget supports
StaticConfiguration,
simply create a new
INRelevantShortcut
without an intent
and set the widgetKind property
to the widget’s kind string.
This tells the system which of
your app’s widgets to suggest.
Then, optionally set the
relevanceProviders property
to an array of
INRelevanceProviders.
This tells the system
when to suggest your widget.
I’ll explain this
in more detail in a bit.
If your widget supports
IntentConfiguration,
create an instance of the intent
used for configuration
with the necessary parameters.
Then create
the INRelevantShortcut
by passing in the intent
as an INShortcut.
And of course,
set the widgetKind and
relevanceProviders properties
just as you would
for a static widget.
To donate a relevant shortcut,
include it in an array
of relevant shortcuts
to set in the default
INRelevantShortcutStore.
To update the donated shortcuts,
you can replace the array of
relevant shortcuts in the store
to a new array.
This means that
you can invalidate
a previously donated
relevant shortcut
by omitting it in the new array.
And donating a relevant shortcut
that contains an intent
can also surface the intent
on the Siri watch face.
To tell the system
when it can insert your widget,
set an array
of INRelevanceProviders
on your relevant shortcut.
There are two options here.
First, you can use
INDateRelevanceProvider
to supply start and end dates
for a fixed, known time period
of relevance,
such as an upcoming event
or breaking news.
You can even use
multiple providers
to specify more than one
relevant time period.
Second, you can also
choose to supply
an empty array of relevance
providers to tell the system
that your widget
has something new to show,
and the system will choose
a time to suggest the widget
based on when the user
typically uses your app.
All other relevance providers
support INRelevantShortcuts
for Siri watch face
and are not supported
by Widget Suggestions.
Now I’ll walk you through
what an adoption might look like
using an example app.
We built an app called Cards
that lets you view
the transactions and balances
on all of your credit cards
and includes a widget
that shows recent purchases.
Let’s see how we can
enable Widget Suggestions
for the Recent Purchases widget
by donating INRelevantShortcuts
in our app.
We want to suggest the widget
after a recent purchase
has just been made
on one of our cards.
Since the widget is configured
with an intent,
in order to allow
Widget Suggestions,
we’re first going to make sure
that our intent
supports donations
in our intent definition file.
Here’s our intent editor for our
ViewRecentPurchases intent,
which tells our widget
which credit card to show
and which merchant category
to filter the purchases by.
We want to make sure that
"Intent is eligible for Siri
Suggestions" is checked.
This enables suggestions for
our widget on the Home screen
as well as suggestions
in other places around iOS
if we choose to donate them,
but we’ll get to that later
with INInteractions.
Then we need to create
a parameter combination
that includes the necessary
parameters to form the intent.
Since we need both
the credit card
and the merchant category
to configure our widget,
we’ll create
a supported combination
with both card
and category parameters.
Now we can create
the intent in our code.
In this code, our app was
just notified that the user
has just made a purchase.
To make a donation,
we start by creating an empty
array of INRelevantShortcuts,
in case we want
to donate multiple shortcuts.
We initialize the intent
that we used to configure
the Recent Purchases widget,
and set any parameters
that we might need.
Here, we want to set
the card parameter on the intent
to a card object
referring to the card
that the recent purchase
was made on,
and set the category to all
to have the widget show
all purchases on that card.
Then we create an INShortcut
with the intent
and create an INRelevantShortcut
with it.
We set the shortcut role to be
the information shortcut role,
since the user views information
in the widget,
and set the widgetKind.
We provide
an INDateRelevanceProvider
starting now and ending in
30 minutes, or 1800 seconds,
so that the system can remove it
30 minutes right after
the purchase was made.
Then we add the shortcut to
our array of relevantShortcuts.
Finally, we donate the shortcut
by setting our
relevantShortcuts array
in the default
INRelevantShortcutStore
and handle any errors
in the completion handler.
Now whenever a recent
purchase is made,
the system can make
a Widget Suggestion
with the widget by proactively
inserting it into a Smart Stack.
Now let’s talk about
TimelineEntryRelevance.
When your widget provides
timelines to WidgetKit,
you can specify
the relevance of your widget
by providing
TimelineEntryRelevance
in each timeline entry.
Annotating an entry
with relevance indicates
how worthy the widget is
of a Smart Rotation
at the time of the entry.
This worthiness of rotation
is relative to all other entries
in the timelines
that the widget provides,
so you should determine
which entries
may be more relevant
to the user than others.
TimelineEntryRelevance
is an optional struct property
on TimelineEntry, along with
the date of the entry.
The relevance struct
contains a score and duration.
The struct’s float score
represents
how relevant this entry is
compared to others.
The higher the score,
the more likely the system is
to rotate to the widget.
When determining
what scores to return,
know that positive scores
indicate timeline entries
that are eligible
for Smart Rotate.
A score of zero tells the system
that the widget
should not be rotated to,
such as when the widget
doesn’t have
any information to show
and rotating to the widget
would not be a positive
experience for the user.
Remember that the significance
of any provided score
is relative to others
in the widget’s timelines.
Whatever scaling you decide to
use for your relevance scores,
just make sure
that it’s consistent
across the timelines you return.
We’ll go over an example
in a just a bit.
The duration
in the relevance struct
specifies how long
the relevance score is valid.
The system uses this,
along with the entry’s date,
to determine
the valid timeframe
in which to rotate the stack
to the widget.
After the duration passes,
the system will treat the score
as zero
until relevance is provided
again in a future entry.
You can specify a duration
of zero to keep the score valid
until the next entry
that provides relevance.
Let’s take a look
at what this looks like in code.
Here we have our
CardRecentPurchasesEntry struct,
which conforms
to the TimelineEntry protocol.
Since the protocol requires
an optional relevance property,
we can declare the relevance
property in our struct.
Now when we create
the timeline entry,
we can attach a
TimelineEntryRelevance instance
to our entries
when we create our timeline.
Now let’s work through
what a timeline might look like
for the Recent Purchases widget
and see some examples
for scores we can provide
for our timeline relevance.
Here’s an example timeline
that the Recent Purchases widget
might return throughout a day.
We might think, perhaps,
that a user cares
more about purchases
that involve higher spending.
We can then make our
scores for our purchases
scale linearly
with the amount spent.
Let’s leave the relevance
durations as 0 for now.
At 8:15, we would return
a score of 0,
since there’s no purchases
to show.
At 9:41, our
52 dollar and 60 cent purchase
means that our score
would be 52.6, and so on.
Plotting it on a graph,
we see that our shopping spree
has a relatively high score
compared to other scores,
so the system will prioritize
rotating to our widget
more with this entry
than with other entries.
The other entries
still have positive scores,
so the system could still rotate
to the widget at those times,
though with a lower priority.
And since we set
our durations to 0,
the relevance scores stay valid
until the next timeline entry
with a relevance update.
We could just as well
have chosen
another scoring mechanism.
Let’s say we return
a score of 50
if the purchase
is above 50 dollars,
and 1 for purchases below.
Once again, we return 0
if there’s no purchases at all.
For our grocery
and shopping purchases
we returned 50,
and for our spending
at the Soup Diner
and the movie theater,
we return 1.
With the score graph,
we can see that the score
rises to 50 at 9:41
and stays there until 6:52.
Since 50 is the highest possible
score in our timeline,
the system is most likely
to show our widget at this time.
Since our widget
shows recent purchases,
we don’t want the system
to rotate to our widget
with purchases
made a long time ago.
So let’s only allow the system
to rotate to our widget
within the 30 minutes
after the purchase was made.
To achieve this, we can use
the duration property
on the relevance struct.
We set a relevance duration
of 30 minutes,
or 1800 seconds,
for each entry.
By setting the duration
of relevance to be half an hour,
we’re telling the system
to mark the entries
as eligible for rotation
for half an hour,
and then mark them as ineligible
for rotation afterward.
In these examples,
we’re basing our score
off of the purchase amount,
but really,
timeline relevance scores
can be whatever you like.
We could have also used
which credit card it is,
where the purchase was made,
when the purchase was made,
or something else entirely.
There’s no one right way
to do it.
Now onto donating
INInteractions.
In your app, you can create
and donate an intent
used to configure your widget
to enable both Smart Rotations
and Widget Suggestions
through INInteractions.
An app donates an INInteraction
every time the user
views information in the app
corresponding to information
that the widget shows.
Each donation is a data point
for the system’s
behavioral model
that learns when the user
tends to view
information in the app.
Whenever the model
predicts that the user
may want to perform
the interaction again,
the system creates
a suggestion for the intent.
And as long as
the donated intent
is the same one
used to configure your widget,
the system will automatically
produce both Smart Rotations
and Widget Suggestions
from the prediction,
along with other suggestions
around the system.
To get going
with donating INInteraction
in the Cards project,
just as with donating
INRelevantShortcuts,
we want to make sure
that our intent
is eligible for suggestions,
and create
a supported combination
with the parameters necessary
to configure our widget.
Here, also make sure
to eventually design
the suggestion UI for
when your donation shows up
in other locations
in the system.
In the Cards app,
whenever our user
views all of the recent
purchases for a card,
we can donate our widget’s
intent to let the system know
that the user is currently
interested in the information
that our widget shows.
First, we initialize our intent.
We set the card parameter
to the card
that the user
is currently viewing,
and set the category to be all,
since the user
is currently viewing
all transactions for this card.
Then we’ll wrap our intent
with an INInteraction
and call the donate method.
Now the system
will know that the user
has just looked at the
recent purchases for this card
in our app.
After a while,
the system can learn
when the user tends to do this,
and suggest the matching widget
at the most opportune times.
Not only do the INInteraction
donations you make
enable Smart Rotations
and Widget Suggestions,
but they also allow the system
to show your intent
as a Siri Suggestion
on the Lock Screen,
in Spotlight, and in the Siri
Shortcut Suggestions widget.
This is true even if your widget
doesn’t adopt intents.
To learn more about
what donating INInteractions
can do for your app
and getting even more out of
the on-device intelligence,
be sure to check out the talk,
“Donate intents and expand
your app’s presence.”
So, INRelevantShortcut,
TimelineEntryRelevance,
and INInteraction are the three
ways in which you can support
Smart Rotate and Widget
Suggestions for your widgets.
Due to other donations
in the system,
along with performance
considerations,
a donation is not a guarantee
that your widget
will be surfaced.
But by adopting these APIs
in a cohesive manner,
you can work with the system
to give your widget
the best shot possible
at being shown.
While developing,
it may also be helpful to bypass
the system’s limitations
for surfacing widgets
by turning on WidgetKit
Developer Mode,
found in Developer Settings
in the Settings app.
So to wrap up,
Widget Suggestions
are a brand-new way
for your widgets
to proactively show up
right when your users need them,
who may not even
know they existed.
And for your widgets
already added to a stack,
Smart Rotate
lets them be a reliable
and dependable
part of your user’s day.
By working with the system
and leveraging
on-device intelligence,
these features allow your widget
to be more discoverable
and more proactive,
and contribute to an intelligent
Home screen experience.
We’re incredibly excited to see
how you add intelligence
to your widgets.
Thank you
and have a wonderful WWDC.
[HARMONICA SCALE]
♪