[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Balraj] Hi, my name is Balraj,
and I am an engineer
on the Xcode team.
Today, I would like to tell you
all about app distribution
in Xcode 13.
There are a variety of different
ways to distribute apps,
and today, I'll be discussing
how to upload apps
to App Store Connect,
distribution options
outside of App Store Connect,
and how to automate
distribution.
I will also be going over
new features we have added
in the distribution workflow
in Xcode 13,
so you will find the content
in this session valuable,
whether this is your first time
distributing an app
or hundredth.
Lately, I've been baking
quite a lot, so I felt inspired
to create an app to get
others started called Baker.
Baker will help people
make a variety
of different types of bread
and baked goods.
I recently completed the first
build of the Baker iOS app,
tested it extensively,
and want to distribute the app
to beta testers for feedback.
For beta testing,
I want my app to be available
on TestFlight,
which is a service
for distributing beta builds
of apps and getting feedback.
In order to make a build of
Baker available on TestFlight,
I will need to first upload
the build to App Store Connect.
App Store Connect is where
I can manage the builds
of Baker on TestFlight,
as well as configure
settings for my developer team.
App Store Connect is also
where I will manage
builds of Baker
for the App Store.
So whether I am intending
to make Baker available
on TestFlight or the App Store,
I will need to first upload
a build of Baker
to App Store Connect.
I will upload my beta build
of Baker to App Store Connect
right in Xcode,
so the distribution
process starts
right where I have been
developing my app.
Xcode 13 has some exciting
new changes in distribution
that allows me to upload Baker
without performing
any setup on App Store Connect
or my local machine.
The first new addition
in Xcode 13 is that you can
create an app record directly
in Xcode prior to uploading.
Next, Xcode can manage
your app's build number for you
during the distribution process.
And finally, with cloud signing,
certificates and private keys
will be stored in the cloud,
meaning you will no longer need
to manually set them up locally
when using automatic signing.
Let's take a look
at how this all works
by uploading the Baker app
to App Store Connect from Xcode.
I have the Baker project open,
ready to be uploaded.
The first thing I need
is a build of the Baker app
that can be processed
for distribution.
To perform this type of build,
I will first select
the Any iOS Device
run destination in the toolbar,
as I need to ensure Baker can be
ran on any supported iOS device.
I then will select Product
in the menu bar,
and click Archive.
An archive is
a developer-signed release build
of an application,
which contains metadata
about your app and team that
will be used when distributing.
After the archiving
operation is complete,
the Xcode organizer will
automatically appear.
The built archive
is automatically selected,
which is what I want to use
for distribution.
In the inspector on the right,
I can also see information
about the archive,
such as version, bundle ID,
team name,
as well as a big blue button
in the top right corner
for distribution.
In addition to storing archives,
the organizer is also where
I will be able to view
different app analytics
for all of my apps
such as crashes,
energy, insights, and metrics.
As Baker is being beta tested,
I will definitely be checking
back here to get insight
on how the app is running.
To get started
with distribution,
I'll use
the currently selected archive
and click
the Distribute App button.
The first step
of distribution is selecting
how I want to distribute Baker.
App Store Connect
is the default method,
and I'll leave that selected,
as this is where
I want to upload to.
There are a variety
of additional ways
to distribute your app
displayed in this window,
such as Ad Hoc and Enterprise,
and I'll go over these
in more detail later.
To continue uploading
to App Store Connect,
I will click Next
in the bottom right hand corner
of the distribution assistant.
I am then brought
to a step asking
whether I want to upload
or export.
Upload will take my archive,
sign and generate an IPA,
which is the format
of an app packaged for upload,
and send it
to App Store Connect,
while Export will
also build an IPA
and sign the content
in the exact same way.
The only difference
is that Xcode will not upload
the IPA to App Store Connect,
but rather move it
to a designated directory
on your machine.
This IPA can later be
submitted to the App Store
using Transporter.
As I wish to upload Baker
to App Store Connect right now,
I will leave Upload selected
and click Next to continue.
Xcode will now check
App Store Connect status
and perform a variety
of distribution setup steps.
New in Xcode 13, I am shown
a prompt to create an app record
on App Store Connect,
which is required
before we can upload
the actual build of Baker.
The app record creation step
provides default values
for properties like app name,
bundle ID, and primary language,
which are derived from the Baker
archive and system settings.
I am happy
with the default options,
so I will click Next.
Xcode now creates the required
app record on App Store Connect.
An app record
is where I can view
all the uploaded builds of Baker
and is where I can set up
TestFlight, in-app purchases,
pricing information,
and so much more.
The Baker app record is now
available on App Store Connect
and is visible
in my list of apps.
The newly created
Baker app record will be
where all the builds
of Baker will be managed,
so I won't have to create
a new app record again
when performing
subsequent uploads.
After Xcode has created
the Baker app record
and validated
our App Store Connect settings,
I will be provided with a list
of options that is determined
by the content of my archive
and how I am distributing
an app.
I would like
to build for bitcode,
I would like to include symbols
so crash reports of my app
are detailed and descriptive,
and I would like to ensure
the build number
of Baker is consistent
across every framework,
so I will keep
the default values selected
and click Next to continue.
I am now brought to a page
asking how I want to sign Baker.
Signing is used to validate
that Baker is coming
from a trusted developer
and to ensure
that software is secure to run.
The two options provided
to me are automatic
and manual signing.
Automatic signing lets Xcode
handle signing for me,
while manual is
for when I want full control
over the signing process.
I want Xcode to handle
signing for me, so I will keep
automatic signing checked
and click Next to continue.
Xcode will now transform
the Baker archive
into an IPA
and sign it for distribution.
Automatic signing
in the distribution workflow
has underwent
some exciting changes
that makes signing work
with no local machine setup.
The signing process
requires a certificate
and private key to validate
that I am a trusted developer.
When locally signing,
I would need to ensure
that I had a distribution
certificate and private key
installed on my machine,
which would often require
manual setup before entering
the distribution workflow.
In Xcode 13,
when using automatic signing,
no certificate setup
is required.
Certificates and private keys
can now be securely stored
in the cloud, where the signing
operation now takes place.
This means that when using
automatic signing,
I don't have to set up
certificates at all.
This new style of signing
is supported
by every distribution method
in Xcode,
such as App Store uploads,
Developer ID,
and Enterprise distribution.
Cloud signing works completely
behind the scenes by managing
all of your signing assets
and signing your app.
Let's go over how this works
in more detail.
Xcode will take
the developer-signed Baker app
in your archive and generate
a partial signature for it.
This partial signature
contains hashes
of the content within your app.
A copy of those hashes are then
sent to our servers,
who, using a private key
and certificate,
signs your app in the cloud.
We then return the remaining
part of the signature
and insert that
into the partial signature
to complete the signing process.
Now, by using automatic
and cloud signing,
we have a fully
distribution signed Baker app
that can be uploaded
to App Store Connect.
Anyone with an Admin
or Account Holder role
on App Store Connect can
cloud sign for App Store Connect
distribution by default.
If I want someone with
a Developer role to upload Baker
using cloud signing,
I can grant them permission
on App Store Connect
by checking
the Access to Cloud Managed
Distribution Certificate
checkbox.
Xcode has now completed
packaging and cloud signing
the Baker app
and shows me a summary page
before I perform the upload
to App Store Connect.
I can see information
such as the type
of certificate used,
the version number,
and the entitlements
the Baker app was signed with.
I am happy with what I see,
so I will go ahead
and click Upload.
Now, Xcode will upload
the first build of Baker
to App Store Connect.
Now, when I get
onto App Store Connect,
I can see the first build
of Baker in the app record
Xcode created earlier.
From here,
I will be able to set up Baker
for TestFlight
and start beta testing.
For information on how to set up
your app on App Store Connect
for TestFlight,
and also the App Store,
please see our guide
in the description.
After getting Baker
on TestFlight and beta testing,
I have addressed
many bugs and feedback.
I now want to upload
another build of my app
with the needed updates.
The process looks
mostly the same
as what we just went through.
I will archive my app
with the desired changes
and distribute through
the Xcode Organizer.
There will be two differences.
First, I won't need to create
an app record again,
and second,
I will need to make sure
the build number of Baker
is different,
as App Store Connect keeps
each build
and uses version and build
number to differentiate them.
I can do this by modifying
the build number
in my project file
before archiving.
But if I don't want
to manage my build number,
the distribution workflow
can now do this for me.
New in Xcode 13, if Xcode
detects I am distributing
with a build number
that has already been used
on App Store Connect,
or that is not incrementing,
it will offer to increment
the build number in the archive
to one that is valid.
Take a look
at the Manage Version
and Build Number option to see
the build number Xcode selects.
As I let the distribution
workflow manage my build number,
I followed
the exact same process
as the first upload of Baker,
and I now have a second build
of Baker on App Store Connect.
This cycle
of releasing beta builds
and addressing feedback
will continue
until I have a build that meets
the desired quality
needed for an App Store release.
To get Baker on the App Store,
I can promote
one of the TestFlight builds
on App Store Connect,
or upload another build in the
organizer to App Store Connect
in the exact same way
we did before.
Once Baker is on the App Store,
I can then continue working
on adding new features,
bug fixes,
and enhancements
to the Baker app.
When I am ready for the next
upload for either TestFlight
or the App Store, I can follow
the same process in Xcode again.
With the new additions
we have made
to the distribution workflow
in Xcode 13,
such as cloud signing,
app record creation,
and build number management,
it is now possible
to distribute apps
with no prior machine setup
or setup on App Store Connect.
This makes
distributing your apps
more streamlined than ever.
Xcode provides a multitude
of different
distribution options.
Let's take a look
at some of the other options
for distributing apps,
starting with Mac apps.
Most iOS apps,
including Baker, are available
on Apple silicon Macs
by default.
To configure this setting,
I can go to the Privacy
and Availability section
of the Baker app record.
I want Baker to be available
on Intel Macs as well, though,
so I can create
a Mac Catalyst version
or native Mac version of Baker,
and then I will have two options
for how to distribute
my app to the world.
I can distribute the build
of my Mac Baker app
to the Mac App Store
by cloud signing
and distributing in the exact
same way we did for iOS.
If using the same bundle ID
as the iOS app,
my Mac app will use the same
app record as the iOS version.
This will also mean
that certain features,
such as in-app purchases,
will be shared across
the two platforms.
I will also be able to make my
Mac app available in TestFlight,
as it is newly available
in MacOS Monterey.
This means I will be able
to use TestFlight
for beta testing Baker
across all Apple platforms.
If I want people
to download Baker
outside of the Mac App Store,
I can choose to distribute
my app using Developer ID.
Developer ID distribution cloud
signs Baker
with a Developer ID certificate
and uploads the app
to be checked for malware
in a process
known as notarization.
Once Baker has been
signed and notarized,
macOS will trust the app
to run on any Mac.
For more information
on distributing
using Developer ID
and notarization,
please view the "All about
notarization" session.
Developer ID
and the Mac App Store
are the two main methods
of distribution for macOS,
and both are great options for
getting your app to the world.
Now that we have gone over
the different ways
to distribute on Mac,
let's take a look
at a couple more ways
to distribute your apps on iOS.
Sometimes, I want
to directly send my teammates
a distribution signed build
of Baker.
This can be done
for testing a bug fix,
testing an experimental
new feature,
or a variety of other reasons.
For this use case, I will want
to use ad hoc distribution.
Ad hoc distribution allows me
to sign Baker to run
on up to 100 devices registered
to my team per device type.
Using Xcode, I can choose
the ad hoc distribution option,
export my app,
and then send Baker
to one of my teammates
with a registered device.
Finally, my team has an app
called Campus Explorer
that we'd like to distribute
internally within our company.
Xcode provides two options
to distribute in this way:
custom apps
and enterprise distribution.
To use custom apps,
I can distribute
to App Store Connect
and set up my custom app there.
Second, if I want
to distribute privately
through the enterprise program,
I can select
the enterprise distribution
method in the organizer.
For more detailed information
on custom app distribution,
please view
the "Custom app distribution
with Apple Business Manager"
session.
We have now distributed Baker
in a variety of different ways
and for many different builds.
Over time,
I will continually select
the same options and methods
when distributing,
so I'll want to start automating
the distribution process.
Automating distribution
is especially great
when using a continuous
integration service,
as I can build, test,
and distribute my app
in one continuous workflow.
The new Xcode Cloud CI service
is great for this.
Once you have built
and tested your application,
Xcode Cloud supports
automated distribution
of your app
to App Store Connect.
To learn how to set up
and distribute your app
in Xcode Cloud,
please take a look
at the "Explore Xcode
Cloud workflows" session.
If you want
to automate distribution
using a different CI service
or automate it locally
on your machine,
you can use the Xcode
command line tool, xcodebuild.
The `xcodebuild
-exportArchive` command is used
to automate distribution,
and it takes in an archive,
export options plist,
and credentials.
I can create
the archive in Xcode,
like I did during
the first upload of Baker,
or I can build it using
xcodebuild's archive command.
To refer to the built archive,
I will use
the `-archivePath` argument
and pass the path
to my built archive.
Next is the export
options plist,
which is like a recipe
for distributing apps.
This is where all of the options
I selected manually
in Xcode's distribution workflow
are specified.
If you export an IPA,
an export options plist is saved
to your exported directory with
all the options you selected.
When we uploaded Baker
to App Store Connect,
an export options plist
was created,
keeping track of options
such as selecting upload,
enabling bitcode,
and selecting automatic signing.
When xcodebuild uses this plist,
it will distribute by selecting
the exact same options
as we did in Xcode.
For a list of options
that are available
in an export options plist,
you can run `xcodebuild -help`
on the command line.
To specify
the export options plist,
I need to pass the `-exportOptionsPlist` argument,
with a path to my plist file.
Finally, I'll need to ensure
xcodebuild has access
to valid credentials
in order to successfully
cloud sign
and upload to the App Store.
There are two ways to do this.
The first way
is to sign in to Xcode
prior to running xcodebuild,
and the session will persist
on my machine
for a period of time.
If I sign in with Xcode,
the only required flag
will be `-allowProvisioningUpdates`,
which gives permission
for xcodebuild
to communicate with
the Apple Developer website.
New in Xcode 13, you can
use App Store Connect keys
to sign in to xcodebuild
without ever signing into Xcode.
The keys can be fetched
from App Store Connect
and passed to xcodebuild.
The three things you'll need
is the Issuer ID,
which is passed to xcodebuild
using `-authenticationKeyIssuerID`;
the Key ID,
which is passed using
`-authenticationKeyID`;
and finally, you'll need
to download the API Key
using the Download API Key
button.
The path to the downloaded file
can be passed to xcodebuild
using `-authenticationKeyPath`.
xcodebuild still requires
allow provisioning updates,
as it still needs to communicate
with the developer website.
Once you have that and all
the App Store Connect keys,
you will have
the credentials needed
for xcodebuild
to distribute your app.
Now that I have an archive,
export options plist,
and credentials,
I have everything needed
to construct the full
xcodebuild command.
Here are all the elements
put together for the command
to automate distribution
for Baker.
I want to continue
to provide updates
to my beta testers once a week,
so I will set up my CI
to do this using
this command for distribution.
And that is all the ways
to distribute apps
using Xcode 13.
From distributing
to App Store Connect
for TestFlight
and the App Store,
to distribution methods
such as Developer ID,
ad hoc, and enterprise.
Then, finally, to automate
the distribution process,
you can use xcodebuild
or the Xcode Cloud CI service.
For more information
on how to distribute
your app using Xcode Cloud,
please view the "Explore Xcode
Cloud workflows" session,
and for more information
about other distribution methods
in detail,
the "App Distribution — From
Ad Hoc to Enterprise" session
has some great information.
Thank you so much for listening,
and have a great WWDC!
[upbeat music]