[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Erik Hornberger: Welcome back
to the research and care app
code-along!
This is part two
of our three-part series
where you and I will build out
a physical therapy app
for our friend Jamie.
If you'd like to follow along,
you can find our project
in the session resources.
I'll just go ahead
and get logged in here.
If you joined us
for session one,
you'll recall that we just
finished onboarding and consent.
In this session --
Oh, hang on.
[LAUGHS] It looks like
we've got a message from Jamie.
"Got some new ideas
for the app."
"Did you see my last text?"
Additional app requirements.
Jamie has invited you to
collaborate on a Notes document.
OK, well, let's just see
what we're going
to be doing this time!
Displaying forms,
persisting some data,
dynamic schedules,
range of motion. OK.
So it looks like Jamie wants us
to set up a daily
check-in survey
where we ask the participants
about how much sleep they got
and how much pain
they're experiencing.
We'll show you how to use
ResearchKit's form items
to put multiple questions
on a single page.
Then, we'll need
to parse the results
from the ResearchKit survey
and persist them into CareKit.
That'll cause
our completion rings to fill up
and our task card UI to update.
We'll also go into detail
on how to create
more advanced schedules
with CareKit,
and then we'll use
one of those schedules --
along with ResearchKit --
to prompt participants
to measure the range of motion
in their knees.
We've got a lot to cover here,
so let's jump in!
We'll get started with
the daily check-in survey.
Just like we did
for our onboarding task,
we'll begin by defining
a schedule and a CareKit task.
It's supposed to be
a daily check-in,
so let's just schedule it
to happen each morning
at, say, 8:00 am.
We'll create the check-in task
with a unique identifier
and the schedule
we just defined.
And of course, we'll need
to persist it here in our store.
This is all exactly the same
as what we did
for the onboarding task.
Hopefully it's starting
to feel familiar to you!
And just like
the onboarding task,
our next step will be to jump
over to CareFeedViewController
and tell CareKit
how to display this task.
This time around,
let's make our solution
a bit more generic.
We'll fetch all the tasks
for the current date.
Then for each task,
we'll create a view controller,
and append that view controller
into our list.
This should scale a bit more
nicely as we add more tasks.
Now, we haven't actually
defined this fetchTasks method
or this viewController method.
We'll need to drop down
a bit further in our file
and write them out.
So here's our fetchTasks method.
We start by creating a
task query for a specific date,
and we specify that
we want to exclude tasks
that don't have
any scheduled events.
This comes into play
when we have tasks
that don't happen every day.
Let's say, for example,
you've been given
a prescription to take
a medication every Monday.
On Tuesdays and Wednesdays,
that prescription
is still assigned to you,
there just aren't
any pills to take.
This property ensures
that such tasks
are not returned from the query.
Once the query comes back,
we'll pass the tasks we fetched
to our completion handler.
We'll also need to fill out
a method that takes a task
and returns a view controller.
We'll inspect
the id of the task,
and if it's the checkIn task,
we'll use the new
SurveyTaskViewController
we introduced in part one.
Just like before,
we'll supply a task,
an eventQuery,
and a reference
to the storeManager.
We'll also need to pass in
a ResearchKit survey
and a function for converting
the ResearchKit result
into an array of CareKit
outcome values.
We'll write these two methods
in just a moment,
but first let's take a look
at how our app,
ResearchKit, and CareKit
are going to work together.
Our app will create
a ResearchKit survey.
ResearchKit will take over
and guide the participant
through the survey flow.
It will produce
an ORKTaskResult,
which it will hand back
to our app.
Then our app will convert
the ResearchKit result
into CareKit outcome values to
be persisted in CareKit's store.
Saving a new outcome will cause
our completion rings to fill up
and our task cards' UIs
to update.
All right, so let's tackle
these two methods.
We'll define them
over in Surveys.swift.
I've prepared
a couple of identifiers
that we'll be using down below.
We need one method for
creating a ResearchKit survey
and one for
converting the result
into CareKit outcome values.
We want to discover
if there is a link
between the amount of sleep
a participant gets
and how much pain
they experience,
so we'll create a form
with two questions.
The formStep requires
a unique identifier,
a title, and some text.
We'll also mark it nonoptional,
since we don't want
the form to be skippable.
Next, let's create our two items.
The first will inquire
about pain,
and we'll make it
a nonoptional question.
What that means is that the form
itself cannot be skipped,
nor can we submit the form
without an answer
to this particular question.
You can see that we also need
to provide an answer format.
The answer format
tells ResearchKit
what kind of answer to expect
and how to prompt the user
to enter it.
Are they entering a weight,
are they selecting an image,
or are they recording
their voice?
In this case,
we'll opt to use
the ORKScaleAnswerFormat,
which creates a UISlider.
Sliders are a familiar interface
to iOS users;
they're intuitive, and they
provide a much nicer experience
than filling in circles
on a paper survey.
We'll specify a maximum
pain score of 10,
a minimum value of 1,
set the step size to 1 so that
only round numbers are allowed,
and provide descriptions
of the min and the max values.
All right, let's drop down
a little further
and create one more item:
a sleepItem.
This is almost exactly the same
as the painItem,
and we'll use a nearly identical
answer format as well.
The only difference
is the identifier,
and that we've changed
the min to 0 hours of sleep
and the max
to 12 hours of sleep.
Now we just need to pass these
two items into our form item,
then create an ORKOrderedTask
with a single formStep.
The second function
is supposed to take
a ResearchKit task result
and create an array
of CareKit values to persist.
But before we write this code,
let's take a look
at the structure of
a ResearchKit task result
so that we have a better idea
of how to parse it.
It's important to understand
that ORKTaskResults
are nested types.
We want to start at the root
result for the check-in survey
and then drill down
to the checkin.form.
The checkin.form
has two children itself,
and we'll need to dig down
to each of them.
First, we want to find
the answers given
for the pain item identifier
and then for
the sleep item identifier.
We know those are both
scale question results,
and we can get
the scale answers off of them.
In this example, 4 and 11.
So that's what
it looks like visually,
and this is what the same
process looks like in code.
Starting at the root result,
we find the first child
that is marked
with the form identifier.
That result will have
its own children,
and we can extract
all of the children
with the type
ORKScaleQuestionResult,
of which we know
there will be two.
The pain answer is the first one
marked with the pain identifier,
and the sleep answer
is the first one
marked with
the sleep identifier.
Both will have scaleAnswer
properties.
Once we have
the answers in hand,
we need to convert them
into a CareKit outcome value --
one for sleep
and one for pain.
The kind property here
is optional.
You don't need to set it,
but it can be helpful if you
want to look up a value later.
We'll see why this is useful
in part three!
The last thing
that we need to do
is return our two values
from this function.
With all that in place,
our daily check-in
should be good to go!
Let's run the app
and see how we're doing.
Note that we have
already completed onboarding
in part one,
so we don't need to go through
the consent flow again.
This is the true content
of our app,
and the CareKit check-in task
we've just created
is right where
we expect it to be.
Tapping on the card takes us
into the ResearchKit survey.
We'll just go ahead
and give some answers here.
Let's go with,
like, say, a 4 for pain
and we'll go with
8 hours of sleep.
When we get back
to our Care Feed,
we can see that the completion
ring at the top fills up,
indicating that the answers
from ResearchKit
were successfully
parsed into CareKit.
This is looking really good.
So we've finished
our check-in survey
with its multiquestion form,
and we've verified that data
is persisted into CareKit
the way that we want it to be.
That means we're about
halfway there!
It's time to move on to
advanced schedules in CareKit,
which we'll later apply
to our range of motion task.
Like the check-in task and
the onboarding task before it,
the first step
is to define a schedule.
But we're going to do something
a bit more involved
for this one.
Jamie has asked that we reduce
how often we ask participants
to measure their range of motion
as time goes on.
Specifically, we want
to set up a schedule
that prompts the participant to
measure their range of motion
every day for the first week,
but then, only once a week
until the end of the month,
and then never again after that.
So once a day
for the first week,
then once a week
for the rest of the month.
Let's begin by defining
a few key dates:
thisMorning, nextWeek,
and nextMonth.
Now, if you want to create
more nuanced schedules
in CareKit,
OCKScheduleElement
is the tool for the job.
Schedule elements
have a start date, an end date,
and repeat at some interval
during that period.
The dailyElement here
starts this morning,
ends next week,
and repeats every day.
The second element
is the weeklyElement.
It starts next week,
ends next month,
and repeats every week.
Now that we have
our two elements,
we can compose them together
to create a compound schedule,
and then we can create
a new range of motion task
using that schedule.
Of course, we'll need to add it
into our store as well.
Just like our other tasks,
the next step is to hop back
into our CareFeed
and specify how we want CareKit
to display this task.
Once again, we'll use
the SurveyTaskViewController,
and we'll need to supply
a survey, as well as functions,
to extract the answers.
Let's jump back into
Surveys.swift and stub those out
to provide a bit of structure
before we get started.
OK, so the range of motion task
is actually pretty simple.
As a matter of fact,
it's built into ResearchKit
as a predefined task.
We just need to give it
an identifier
and specify which knee
is to be measured.
Now the predefined task has
a completion step built into it,
and the message it shows
is a reasonable default,
but we'd really like to show
a custom message
tailored to our use case.
So we're going
to tell ResearchKit
to omit the standard
completion step.
Then, we'll define our own
and give it
an encouraging message
specifically related
to physical therapy.
So that's the first function.
The second one
is where we'll convert
from a ResearchKit result
to CareKit outcome values.
Hopefully this is starting
to feel familiar now.
There are a lot of ways
we can go about this,
but today we're going
to dig down
until we get to the first
range of motion result.
And we know
there will only be one.
Range of motion results
actually have a bunch
of useful properties on them,
but the one we're most
interested in for our use case
is range, which measures how far
the participant was able
to bend their knee in degrees.
We can use the kind field
along with key paths
to make it easy to look up
this value later.
That's foreshadowing
for part three, by the way.
All right, and that wraps up
our function
for extracting
the outcome values.
Nice!
I think we're all set up.
Let's run our app and
I'll show you how it all works.
The first thing that we want
to check is that our schedule
is working the way
that we intend it to.
The Range Of Motion task
should show up
every day during the first week.
As I page through the 8th,
and the 9th, and the 10th,
the range of motion task
shows up every day.
But when I get out to next week,
it stops showing up
except on Monday here,
which is the one day of the week
that we still want it to appear.
Here it's still showing up
only once per week.
But if we go out even further
into the future,
all the way to next month,
it doesn't show up
at all anymore.
CareKit schedules
are a great way
to preprogram
regimens like this.
Let's jump back to today
and try this out.
When I tap Begin,
our instructions step helps me
understand what to do.
When I start, Siri will give me
audio guidance,
so I'm just going to follow
her instructions.
Siri: Place your device
on your left knee.
Tap the screen
and extend your left knee
as far as you can.
Touch anywhere to continue.
[BEEP] When you are done,
return your left knee
to the start position,
then tap anywhere.
[BEEP]
Erik: Nice.
That's pretty neat, right?
Usually you'd have to make
a visit to the doctor's office
and a therapist would help you
take measurements like this,
but ResearchKit
can help participants
take measurements
in their own homes.
I think Jamie will be
really impressed
with the progress we've made.
I'll FaceTime him
right after this
and send him the latest version
of our app on TestFlight.
While I'm bringing Jamie
up to speed on our progress,
you can find more info
about our frameworks
on researchandcare.org,
or read through
the source code on GitHub.
In session one,
we set up onboarding.
In this session,
we scheduled a pair of tasks.
Join us again
for our third and final session
to see how ResearchKit
and CareKit
can help us finish up our app.
See you soon!
♪