[upbeat music]
[Jason] Welcome to
What's new in Mac Catalyst.
My name is Jason Beaver,
and I'll be joined later
by my colleague
Nick Teissler.
Mac Catalyst is the technology
that lets you bring your
existing iOS applications
to macOS,
allowing them
to take full advantage
of the Mac's larger display,
integrated keyboard,
and mouse or trackpad.
Thousands of developers
have used Mac Catalyst
to bring their iOS
applications to macOS,
and the results have been
incredible.
Let me tell you about
a few of the recent
Apple Award-winning
Mac Catalyst apps.
Shapr3D is an
industrial-strength CAD tool,
supported on both Mac and iPad.
While the iPad version was
designed as a multi-touch
and Pencil experience,
the new Mac version,
built with Mac Catalyst,
takes advantage of mouse
and keyboard support, just as
desktop users would expect.
Instapaper is a very popular app
for reading articles offline,
and because of Mac Catalyst,
it's made its debut on the Mac.
Notability is an outstanding
note-taking app.
Replacing the existing
Mac version,
the new version of the app gives
users all the cool features
of iPad,
but optimized to take advantage
of Mac's screen size,
keyboard, and faster speed.
It even supports Sidecar
with Apple Pencil.
We're going to start
with an overview of new APIs,
and then cover APIs that we've
enhanced in macOS Monterey.
Finally, we'll show these
new APIs in action
when Nick adopts
them in our demo app.
Let's start with an overview
of the new APIs
in macOS Monterey.
Previously, in macOS Big Sur,
we added support
for attaching a menu
to a button with
the showsMenuAsPrimaryAction
property.
This allowed you to create
a pull-down menu.
Now, in macOS Monterey,
we've added support
for pop-up buttons,
with a new property called
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction,
that causes the title
of the button to track
the selection in the menu.
With these two properties,
there are now four ways
that we can configure
our button.
With both properties set
to false,
we get a standard push button.
Note that this can still
display a menu if one
is set when you click
and hold on the button.
The code to create
that button is shown below.
If only
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
is set to true,
you get a toggle button that can
clicked to turn on and off.
This can be used to indicate
state in your application.
If only showsMenuAsPrimaryAction
is set to true,
you get a pull-down menu.
And if both properties
are set to true,
you get the new pop-up button.
Now, for buttons configured
to show a menu
as the primary action,
the buttons will
show the menus immediately
with the primary interaction,
which is a left click in macOS.
However, for buttons that are
not configured to show a menu
as the primary action,
the behavior depends
on the app's idiom.
In the iPad idiom,
menus are triggered
with the secondary interaction,
which is a right click in macOS.
But if the application
adopts the Mac idiom,
the menu is triggered by
a long press on the button.
You can find out more about
what's new with buttons
in the "Meet the UIKit
button system" video.
We've now made ToolTips
available to Mac Catalyst apps.
A ToolTip is a small,
floating window that will appear
when the cursor hovers
over a view in your application.
And it can
be used to provide context
or additional detail
about your content.
To add a ToolTip to any UIView,
use UIToolTipInteraction.
All you need to do is create
a UIToolTipInteraction
with a text string, and then add
that interaction to your view.
One common use of ToolTips,
however,
is to clarify the behavior
of controls in your UI.
This is a common enough pattern
that we've added a convenience
property to UIControl
to let you
quickly set a ToolTip.
Labels are used throughout
iOS apps
to display non-editable strings.
When the contents of a label
are too long to fit,
the label has to truncate
the text.
Now, in macOS Monterey,
we've added support
for expansion ToolTips
so that the full contents
of the label are available.
In this sample UI,
the title label's contents
are too long to fit.
By enabling expansion ToolTips,
when we hover the mouse
over the label,
it shows the full title.
You can enable this
with a new property
on UILabel called
showsExpansionTextWhenTruncated.
We've introduced a new
info.plist key
called UIApplicationSupports
PrintCommand
that you can add
to your info.plist.
If set to true, we will
automatically add "Print,"
and "Export as PDF"
menu items
to your Mac Catalyst
application at launch.
This plist key can also be added
to your iOS applications
and will result in just
the "Print" option on the iPadOS
shortcuts overlay and will also
show the "Print"
and "Export as PDF" menu items
when your iOS application
is run on M1 Macs.
While this plist key
tells the operating system
that you want the "Print,"
and "Export as PDF" menu items,
it is only half of the story.
You still need to explicitly
implement
print support in your code.
To do that, there
is a new UIResponder action
called printContent.
You can implement this on any
UIResponder,
and the responder
chain search is used
to find
the appropriate print target.
When your implementation
of printContent is invoked,
simply set up and use
a UIPrintInteractionController
as you normally would.
We now have support for adding
a subtitle to your window.
This could be used
to provide auxiliary information
about the state
of your application.
This can be set with a new
property on UIScene
called subtitle.
In macOS Monterey,
the Shortcuts application
is now available on the Mac.
If your application adopts
custom intents on iOS,
they will
now be available with Siri
and Shortcuts on the Mac.
Both in-app intent handling
and Intents extensions
are available.
So, if you've previously
disabled
building your Intents extension
in your Mac Catalyst app,
you can now re-enable it.
You can find out more
in the "Meet Shortcuts
for macOS" video.
That wraps up
the overview of our APIs
that are new in macOS Monterey.
Let's move on to an overview
of the APIs that we've
enhanced in macOS Monterey.
If you have custom buttons
or sliders that you've written
to fit the theme of your app,
you can keep those
in Mac Catalyst
when you adopt the Mac idiom
by opting out
of the native controls,
but you'll need to take care
of your own scaling down to 77%.
Now, we don't recommend doing
this app-wide,
but only for certain controls
that are key
to your app's experience.
The new button system can also
be used to create buttons
that fit with your app's theme
in a more cross-platform way.
And you can find out more
about this
in the "Meet the UIKit
button system" video.
UIBehavioralStyle is the new
enum that makes this possible.
UIButton and UISlider have
two new properties each:
preferredBehavioralStyle
is readwrite,
and behavioralStyle
is the readonly
resolved value
for this property.
On iOS, the resolved value for
behavioralStyle won't change,
so it's easy to set
this line of code to .pad
or ,mac explicitly to handle
the Mac Catalyst case
without affecting your iOS app.
For document-based apps,
there's a new plist property
called UIApplicationSupports
TabbedSceneCollection
to opt out of window tabbing.
When set to false,
window tabbing will be disabled,
and the default tab-related menu
items will not be added.
We now support
UIPointerLockState
for hiding the cursor
and locking it
so that it doesn't move
outside the Mac window.
This is really useful for games,
so that the user doesn't
inadvertently click
outside the game
and bring another
application to the front.
It temporarily unlocks
the window when you switch apps
or windows, and relocks it
when you click the window.
We also support UIPointerShape,
which can be used
to get iBeam cursors in either
the horizontal or vertical axes.
When you use this API on macOS,
you'll get one of
the canonical NSCursor shapes.
Finally, we support a pointer
style of hidden to allow you
to hide the cursor
when necessary in your app.
We've gone over a number of new
and enhanced UIKit APIs.
Now, I'll hand it over to Nick
to take us through
how we'll use these new
and enhanced APIs
to make our Mac Catalyst app
feel even
more at home on the Mac.
[Nick] Thanks, Jason!
Those new features
are very intriguing.
I've already had the chance
to try them out.
I'm going to walk you
through a demo of an app
that the Catalyst team
has developed.
It turns out the Catalyst team
moonlights as travel writers.
And so,
we developed Trip Planner
for the iPhone and iPad.
Here is Trip Planner
running on a 13-inch
MacBook Pro with M1.
We opted our app in to running
on M1 Macs so we could have
the app available to as
many users as possible.
Let me give you a tour
of the app's features.
Trip Planner is an app
that lists some great places
to visit across the globe
and allows you to redeem
reward points for various
frequent-traveler programs.
Its UI is
based around a three-column
split-view controller.
Using the sidebar,
I can navigate between lodgings,
restaurants, and sites
in my favorite countries,
or select a rewards program
to review and spend my points.
When I select
something in the sidebar,
if it's a category,
Trip Planner shows its content
in the supplementary column
of the split-view controller.
The supplementary-view
controller
populates with sights,
restaurants,
and lodgings in Japan,
Spain, Brazil, and Tanzania.
If I instead select a leaf item
in the sidebar
or an item in the
supplementary-view controller,
the secondary-view controller
shows details for that item.
I'll select one of my favorite
cafes in Japan, Extreme Matcha.
The detail-view controller
includes
some text about the cafe,
buttons to help me plan my trip,
and a map view showing
where Extreme Matcha is located.
In the case of Trip Planner,
everything just worked out
of the box on M1 Macs.
However, being an iOS app,
there was only so much
we could do to make it
feel at home on the Mac.
To go further,
we needed to check that checkbox
and make it a Mac Catalyst app.
This checkbox, to be specific.
Can we zoom?
And enhance your app
by checking the check box.
Here is Trip Planner
optimized for Mac Catalyst.
We've added
Mac-specific functionality,
like double-tap gesture
recognizers to open new windows,
custom title bar appearances,
and we've gone all-in
by optimizing for the Mac
giving us
native controls and sharp text.
Watch the "Qualities of a great
Mac Catalyst app"
and the "Optimize the interface
of your Mac Catalyst app"
for the full
story on that process.
In the final
version of Trip Planner,
I've adopted the new APIs Jason
just told you about.
I'll cover
the adoption of each one.
I highly recommend you
download the sample project.
All of the snippets
I'll show here are taken
directly from that code.
Here's the app completely
updated for macOS Monterey.
I have Extreme Matcha
selected again.
You may notice some color
in the UI
in the form of macOS-style
buttons with a background color.
But I'll come back to those.
I'd like to talk about
scene subtitles first.
I'm using the new UIScene
subtitle property
to do two things.
First, I'm using the subtitle
to show the detail-view
controller's title
in a way that feels more
at home on the Mac.
A window subtitle
is more Mac-like
than a navigation item's
title is.
Second,
I'm changing the subtitle
to provide some helpful context
as a user navigates the app.
In Trip Planner,
I'll select Japan and Tanzania.
So, the window's subtitle
reads "Countries."
If I select this little
camping spot,
here in the supplementary-view
controller,
the subtitle changes
to let me know
I've selected Glamp Kilimanjaro.
And if I select the whole
Rewards Programs section...
The subtitle changes again
to Countries & Rewards Programs,
adding context for the user.
Think about how subtitles
might help to add context
to your Catalyst apps, too.
Also note that the subtitle
is displayed differently
for each
UITitlebar toolbarStyle.
Experiment with this to find
the best look for your app.
To set the subtitle,
start with a string value,
get a reference to the scene,
and then
set the subtitle property.
You can either set this
at scene connection time,
or later by accessing
the scene of a view's window.
Next, I'll show you
how I adopted ToolTips
in Trip Planner.
A very common interaction
pattern on macOS
is momentarily hovering
the mouse over something
to get more detail
about that something.
This technique
is a long-established way
of educating the user without
cluttering your app's UI.
ToolTips also can also show
a truncated label's full text.
Here, I've selected
Iguaçu Falls in Brazil.
Hovering the mouse over the
image for a moment
reveals a ToolTip!
"A lush, deep green forest
surrounds the roaring Iguaçu
Falls on an overcast day."
What a nice description.
We've used the new
UIToolTipInteraction API
to add this functionality
to all of our images,
and it really makes the app feel
more at home on the Mac.
I've also used the UILabel API
to allow expansion of these
labels that get truncated
due to the internationalized
currency formatting, making them
a bit longer than expected.
As Jason went over earlier,
there are
various forms of ToolTip API.
In the hero image case,
using
the UIToolTipInteraction API
without
a UITooltipInteractionDelegate
fit my need because I wanted
to attach constant text
as the ToolTip
to an arbitrary view.
For the currency text,
I used the
showsExpansionTextWhenTruncated
property on UILabel.
And if I
want to attach a ToolTip
to an arbitrary control,
the ToolTip property
on UIControl
is the right API to use.
I'll move on to the wide
variety of new buttons
available in Catalyst
on macOS Monterey.
I recommend you check out
the "Meet the UIKit
button system" video
for an introduction
to the new iOS 15
UIButtonConfiguration APIs.
Many of those new
UIButtonConfiguration properties
have their own manifestations
in Catalyst apps
optimized for Mac.
And even better,
just like on iOS,
the properties defined
on UIButton can be mixed
and matched with those
on UIButtonConfiguration.
I'm going to show you a bunch
of buttons, and then after,
I'll show how each one
was configured in code.
I'll pick a new destination
to show off the new
button background color.
How about Copacabana?
The buttons here are using
the filled configuration,
and so they pick up the tint
color of their environment,
automatically getting
a color that matches
the image
and background blur well.
Now, I'll navigate to a rewards
detail-view controller.
I'll bring up my programs
from the sidebar...
And select the Diamond Dubloons
Rewards Program.
The purpose of this view
is to allow me
to redeem points
I've earned from traveling
and choose what to redeem
them on.
I can use the slider to choose
how many points I'm spending.
I can use this toggle
button to activate
the points multiplier,
and even choose my multiplier
with the attached menu.
I feel like choosing
the biggest number
as my points multiplier
only makes sense.
So, I'll choose six.
I wonder what the catch is.
I can toggle these larger
buttons
to select
the categories to redeem.
I can choose between redeeming,
cashing out,
or donating my points.
And when I'm finally ready
to submit,
I can click the submit
button in the bottom right,
or click this reset button
to start over.
There are a quite a few
new buttons here.
I'll show you how to configure
each one.
I'll first cover the one
we're all familiar with:
the push button.
In the detail-view controller,
this was the submit button.
This is just a UIButton
of the system type,
introduced in Big Sur,
with its role set to primary.
Up next, I have the points
multiplier menu button.
This button toggles
its state on primary click
and shows a menu on long press.
I know I'll want a custom
background color eventually,
so I'll use the filled
configuration
and set the title
to "Points Multiplier."
To get the toggle behavior,
I'll use the new boolean
property Jason told us about,
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction.
Set that to true.
Now, our button's
background color will
toggle between the app's
tint color
and the standard colorless
appearance.
I'll attach a menu, as well,
configured with our multiplier
values and some UIActions.
And finally,
in our menu's action handlers,
if the user selects
the biggest points multiplier,
we will conditionally change
the toggle's background color
to a system red.
Now to configure
the Reset button.
I can use the plain
configuration
to get the borderless
appearance.
This configuration
looks very similar
to the iPadOS appearance.
I'll set the button's
role to destructive,
which tells the system
to do some event handling
that prevents accidentally
triggering its action.
And set its
tintColor to a systemRed.
That's it for that button.
For the pop-up button
in the bottom left of the view
that lets me select between
Redeem, Cash Out, and Donate,
there's no need to use
the button configuration API.
I'll just create
a system button
and set
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
to true.
Semantically, that's what
a pop-up button does.
Next, I want to set
showsMenuAsPrimaryAction
to true because that is
also semantically
what a pop-up button does.
But what gives?
The button hasn't changed.
Actually, it has.
We've achieved another
toggle button.
But the default state is,
of course, off.
We are missing a non-null menu
property.
That is critical to getting
the pop-up appearance
new in Mac Catalyst.
Now that we've set
the menu to something,
our pop-up button
is fully functional.
Finally, focus on these big,
panel-like toggle buttons.
This layout takes advantage
of how iPad-style buttons
stretch to fill the space
they are laid out in.
Buttons using the Mac style
don't behave this way.
I was able to keep the iPad
behavior,
even while Trip Planner
was set to Optimize for Mac,
and here's how.
I started with yet another
filled-button configuration.
I then used the configuration
to set an image,
with no need to specify a button
state for the image.
By specifying the
.pad behavioral style,
I get the layout behavior
I would on iPad.
Namely, the button's background
stretches to fill its frame.
The symbol
needed to be a bit bigger,
so I set a preferred
symbol configuration
on the button with a larger
point size.
As before, I set
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
to true and provided
a colorUpdateHandler
to specify a selected
and unselected color,
based off the button's
isSelected property.
I know you're as excited as I am
for all of these new options.
The long-standing members
of UIButton's API and shiny,
brand-new properties
can be mixed and matched
in many, many ways to create
a plethora of buttons
that are all
right at home on the Mac.
The last feature
of Trip Planner
I'd like to show you
is printing.
Printing is easier than
it's ever been on Catalyst
with the new built-in
key command support.
I was able to enhance
the printing experience
in Trip Planner by using
the responder chain
to select
the most appropriate object
to handle printing.
Let me demonstrate
what I mean by that.
Back in the newest
version of Trip Planner,
I've selected one of my most
beloved restaurants in Spain,
Charcuterie Bored.
I'll interact with the map view
by clicking
on the Catalyst-specific zoom
controls.
Now, application focus
and first responder status
have moved into this
detail-view controller.
When I select File Print
from the menu,
a Print dialog comes up...
Offering
to print just this one item.
Now, I'll also select Parque
Guell and Hotel Barcelona
to complete
my planning for the day.
I'll use the built-in
shortcut command+P to print.
The Print dialog that comes
up now offers to print
all three of my selected
items...
Not just the current
detail-view controller.
Lastly, if I Shift+Tab focus
over to countries in the sidebar
and have nothing selected
in the supplementary
or detail-view controllers...
And then try to print,
Trip Planner knows what to do
and prints every item
I've selected in the sidebar.
So, how do I achieve this?
First and foremost, the new
info.plist key Jason introduced
must be set to let
the system know Trip Planner
supports printing and would like
the menu item added.
In the detail-view controller,
I've overridden two
methods from UIResponder.
Print content
does the actual printing,
and UIKit looks for objects
that can perform this action
in the responder chain.
In some cases, dictated by
application business logic,
the detail-view controller
may not want to print.
So, I've used the method
canPerformAction
to inform the responder chain
whether or not the detail-view
controller can print.
This method is called
before printContent,
and if it returns false,
the detail-view controller
will be skipped over,
as UIKit
climbs the responder chain
looking for an object
that can perform that action.
In
the BrowserSplitViewController,
which is the application's
root-view controller,
and therefore almost always near
the top of the responder chain,
I've implemented another
UIResponder method,
targetForAction:withSender.
This lets
the split-view controller
choose which object
should handle the printing.
This is useful when the user's
selection and business logic
dictate we should
be printing some set of pages,
but the object that implements
that specific printing
isn't part of
the responder chain.
This is much preferred
over forcing that object
into the responder chain
by sending
becomeFirstResponder
to that object,
which would be an anti-pattern
if used in this scenario.
And that's it for printing.
Looks like I'm ready
to travel off the grid.
In this video,
Jason introduced us
to new Mac Catalyst APIs
and enhanced
Mac Catalyst APIs
that help
bring your app to the Mac
better than ever before.
Then, I showed how to adopt
them in Trip Planner.
In most cases,
they are just new properties,
a single line to set,
that bring quintessential
Mac features
to your Catalyst app.
Go try these out for yourself.
Make some minor code changes,
and watch how your
Mac Catalyst app
gets some major improvements.
Thanks for watching.
[percussive music]