[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Kritarth Jain: Hi there
and welcome to
"Send communication and
Time Sensitive notifications."
I am Kritarth, an engineer
on the Notifications team,
and later I will be joined
by my colleague, Kevin.
Notifications are
a key component
of the application experience
and we will cover new ways
to enhance them,
along with elevating certain
categories of notifications.
We will start out by covering
some visual updates
to notifications
and how to augment them
with new API.
Then we will do an overview
of new management controls
and how these are relevant
to communication
and Time Sensitive
notifications.
Then we will focus on
notification interruptions
and cover new APIs
to control them.
After which,
we will hone in
on the two types
of notifications --
Time Sensitive
and communication --
and cover ways in which
these can be configured.
Let's begin by going over
some visual updates
to notifications.
Now, notifications have
a new look
with greater focus on the
content and the associated media
along with the application icon.
The rich notification
presentation
and accompanying actions
have been updated
to match the system style.
You can now associate
notification actions with icons.
Iconography conveys
what the action will do
and provides visual context
next to the action.
Here there are
two notification actions --
like and comment --
and these are set on the
custom notification category.
To add icons to these actions,
create objects of type
UNNotificationActionIcon
with the image name,
either for a system image
or a template image.
Then provide these icons
to the respective constructors
for UNNotificationAction.
When a notification associated
with this category is expanded,
the actions are presented
along with the icons
that were provided for them.
Because notifications display
the app icon at a larger size,
provide a high-resolution icon
with the application bundle.
Ensure content extensions
continue to work with
the new presentation and layout
of the rich notifications,
and adopt icons for notification
actions to add more context.
Next, let's go over new
notification management options.
There are new system controls
which affect the delivery
and interruption of
notifications from applications.
These are notification summary
and Focus.
Let's discuss
notification summary first.
Notifications can now
be delivered
at scheduled times in the day
as a summary.
This reduces the number
of active interruptions
from incoming notifications
and presents them collectively
at preset times.
All notifications delivered
to the summary on a schedule
are present in the notification
list on the Lock screen.
Include media attachments
with the notification content
so there is a better chance
for that notification
to be featured at the top
of the notification summary.
Adopt the new API
to provide a relevance score
for the notification content
so the right notifications from
the application get featured
in the notification
summary as well.
The other management tool
relevant to notifications
is Focus.
The device can be set
in a particular Focus
based on the activity
or time of day
such as Reading, Sleep, or Work.
When in such a configuration,
the device will filter
the presentation
and interruption
of notifications.
Focus configuration
allows selecting people
and applications
that can send interruptive
notifications.
For example,
during the Work Focus,
Mail and Messages are
allowed to send notifications,
along with direct communication
from coworkers.
So notification summary
and Focus
control which applications can
send interruptive notifications
and when.
This allows better management
of interruptions
throughout the day.
There is opportunity for
notifications to break through
these management controls,
but only if allowed to do so.
It is also possible
for communication
and Time Sensitive notifications
to break through.
Next let's discuss
how applications
can control interruptions
tied to notifications.
There is a new API
for interruption levels
as part of the UserNotifications
framework.
There are four distinct
interruption levels
that are supported.
These are Passive, Active,
Time Sensitive, and Critical.
Notifications with
Passive interruption level
do not alert
or light up the screen,
and do not break through
system controls.
These notifications
are delivered
to the notification list
silently
and are available the next time
the list is viewed.
Passive interruption
should be used for notifications
that do not require
immediate attention to interrupt
but should be seen eventually.
Some examples are
dining recommendations
and new episode availability.
Active interruption resembles
the behavior that exists today,
where notifications
will play sound and vibrations
and light up the screen.
These notifications
will not break through
system management
of notifications.
This is the default
interruption level.
Active interruption should be
used for notifications
that do not warrant interrupting
if the system is configured
not to be interrupted currently.
Some examples
are sports updates
and live stream
video notifications.
Time Sensitive notifications
alert
just like active notifications.
These are special because
they can break through
system controls
such as notification summary
and Focus,
if it has been allowed.
These notifications
should only be used
when it is relevant
to actively interrupt,
requiring immediate attention.
Some instances
are account security
and package delivery alerts.
Lastly, Critical interruption
level is equivalent
to the Critical notification
support that exists in iOS 14.
Notifications with
this interruption level
actively alert, break through
system controls,
and also bypass
the ringer switch on the device.
Because of this disruptive
behavior,
critical interruption
will continue
to require an approved
entitlement.
Some use cases
for critical notifications
are severe weather
and local safety alerts.
To support the new API in
the UserNotifications framework,
there is a new enum for
UNNotificationInterruptionLevel
with the different
levels defined.
Set this interruption level
while configuring
the content object
for the notification request.
Passive is set in this example.
If no interruption level
is provided,
then the default level is used.
For a push notification payload,
provide a new key-value pair,
with the key interruption level.
Here again, set the
interruption level as passive.
When this notification
is delivered to the device,
it will be visible
on the Lock screen
without any interruptions, since
it was configured as passive.
Another form of interruption
tied to notifications
is Announce.
Siri can announce notifications
if there are
compatible devices --
such as AirPods Pro
and AirPods Max -- connected.
To get this announce
behavior in iOS 14,
notifications had to be
tied to a category
that requests the
AllowAnnouncement option.
In iOS 15, the requirement
for this category option
is deprecated.
Now announce is supported
for any notification
while connected
to a supported audio device.
Communication and
Time Sensitive notifications
will be announced by default.
While connected to CarPlay,
communication notifications
can be configured
to announce automatically,
making the experience
more seamless.
Next let's focus on
Time Sensitive notifications
and how to configure them.
are those that require
immediate attention.
Because of their importance,
these can breakthrough
system controls
such as notification summary
and Focus if allowed to do so.
An example of
a Time Sensitive notification
is one from Reminders
about taking medication.
This notification is posted
immediately and prominently,
breaking through the Work Focus.
It is important
to maintain trust
when sending
Time Sensitive notifications.
Do not overuse
their interruptive nature
and only use them
when it is relevant to do so.
Know that there is an option to
turn off Time Sensitive alerts
or even all notifications
from an application.
To configure Time Sensitive
notifications,
enable the associated capability
via Xcode
for your application.
Set the Time Sensitive
interruption level
on the notification request
being posted.
For a local notification,
the Time Sensitive
interruption level
is set on the content object.
For a push payload,
set the interruption-level key
with value as time-sensitive.
When delivered,
this notification
is posted prominently,
highlighting the urgency.
Let's discuss
communication notifications.
And to tell you all about them,
let me hand over to Kevin.
Kevin?
Kevin Harrington:
Thanks, Kritarth.
I'm Kevin, an engineer
on the Notifications team.
There's an importance
for urgent notifications
breaking through Focus
and notification summaries.
Communications from people
also warrant
elevated notification delivery.
These communications
can come in many forms,
including calls and messages.
I will highlight a new API
that allows your applications
to signal what notifications
are communications,
and the people associated with
those communications.
The importance of
communication notifications
is determined by user decisions.
Siri Suggestions helps
inform these decisions,
suggesting important people that
should be allowed to interrupt.
As your user interacts
with the device --
taking calls, joining FaceTimes,
sending messages --
Siri learns who is a candidate
to break through Focus
and Notification Summaries.
In iOS 15, communication
notifications
get a richer user experience.
Most visible are
the prominent avatars.
The title and subtitle
are standardized.
It always includes the sender
in the title,
and in the case
of group communications,
recipients in the subtitle.
The title and subtitle text
are localized and formatted
for all devices,
across platforms.
For example, watch prefers
to show just first names
for recipients of
a group communication.
Siri will now announce
the contents of communication
notifications
on supported devices including
HomePod, AirPods, and CarPlay.
And Siri will provide
suggestions
to help prioritize these
communication notifications.
People in your apps
will get associated
with people in Contacts.
These associations
are shown as suggestions
on notifications.
Once a user
confirms a suggestion,
Siri Shortcuts are available
for tasks
with those people in your app.
Siri will suggest relevant
people to break through
in the Focus configuration --
including those people
associated with communications
in your app.
To make these decisions on what
is and isn't a communication,
this new API lets you add
SiriKit call and message intents
to Notifications.
Intents are driven
by common tasks.
Your app donates these
intents when events happen,
like placing a call
or receiving a message.
From there, Siri provides
shortcuts and suggestions
based on these intents,
like people in your apps
to message from share sheet
or to start a call
from your app via Siri.
This new API associates these
same intents with notifications
to further integrate your apps
into the Siri ecosystem.
Using SiriKit intents for
communication notifications
will increase engagement
in your apps
while maintaining consistency
throughout your app, Siri,
and system UI.
The intents that represent
relevant communications
are the StartCall
and SendMessage intents.
The NotificationContentProviding
protocol is the mechanism
to associate intents
with notifications.
On a NotificationContent
object,
call updating with
a ContentProviding intent
for communication treatment.
StartCall and SendMessage
intents conforms to providing.
Communication notifications
are delivered
through Apple Push Notification
service.
You need to update
a NotificationContent object
with a SiriKit intent
in your app's
NotificationServiceExtension.
SiriKit intents
are local to the device,
and thus must
be serviced locally.
The service extension
is for exactly these cases.
It is the place to customize the
content of a remote notification
before it is delivered.
You can also do this
in your main app process
for local notifications.
In your didReceive function,
update the content of
a push payload with an intent.
For messaging notifications,
create a SendMessageIntent.
And for call-related
notifications,
use a StartCallIntent.
Create an interaction
to tell Siri intelligence
what is happening.
In a notification extension,
the interaction direction
is always incoming.
This is an event
that is happening to the user;
they are receiving
the incoming call.
Next, you need to donate
the interaction.
Donations also help the system
make better suggestions
in the future.
Update the content of your
notification with the intent.
And finally,
call the contentHandler
with the returned intent.
Donations are required
so Siri can learn from events
that happen in your apps.
The interaction direction
is always incoming
for notifications.
For other SiriKit uses,
the direction can be outgoing
for actions initiated
on the device,
like sending an outgoing message
or placing a call.
Only system objects
that conform
to content providing
are supported.
Do not conform your objects
to content providing.
To send communication
notifications,
enable the communication
capability via Xcode
for your application.
Support communication intents
by adding intent types to
your user activity types array
in Info.plist
or by implementing
an intents extension.
Donate communication intents
when the user
takes actions
in your app foreground,
like when the users hits send
after composing a message.
Siri then uses outgoing intents
to better aide
in who should be suggested
to break through Focus
and Summaries.
Same for Contacts suggestions.
For this feature,
Siri only learns from
outgoing intent donations,
so Contacts are not cluttered
by people not engaged with --
like spam callers.
The proper usage
of communication intents
is fundamental to an intelligent
notification experience,
and there are
a few gotchas to cover.
Intent persons are
the building blocks
of SendMessage
and StartCall intents.
Each and every parameter
you populate
provides a richer and more
intelligent user experience.
Same goes with creating intents
with intent persons;
each and every parameter
you populate
provides a richer and more
intelligent user experience.
Start using intents
if you don't already.
Intents will provide
more visibility to your app
in notifications, share sheet,
Contacts, and Spotlight.
And you can use SiriKit
to offer Siri Shortcuts
like sending a message
or starting a call.
Get in the habit
of donating intents
for both incoming and outgoing
interactions.
You might already be donating
outgoing intents.
Start donating incoming
StartCall
and SendMessage intents
in your service extension.
This is fundamental
to the communication
notification experience.
If your app doesn't already use
a notification service
extension,
you'll want to add one.
Finally, put the pieces together
by using
the content providing protocol
to decorate each notification
you want delivered
as a communication.
We've covered a lot
in this session,
from visual updates to
communication notifications.
Here are a few takeaways.
Account for the new visual
updates and management options
and ensure that notifications
work seamlessly with them.
Adopt interruption levels
to have better control
over how
a notification interrupts
in synergy with system controls.
Use Time Sensitive
notifications when relevant
to prominently interrupt
and get automatic behaviors
such as breakthrough
and announce.
Implement and donate
call and messaging intents
to get the upgraded
communication experience
tied to notifications,
along with breakthrough
and announce behavior.
We can't wait to see all
the new and amazing experiences
you build around notifications.
We hope you all
have a great WWDC!
♪