[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Simon Goldrei: Hello!
In this session,
we'll explore how to immerse
your app in spatial audio.
I'm Simon and I'm part
of the streaming media team
here at Apple.
Do you want
to offer your customers,
and differentiate
your service,
with the experience
of a movie theater?
Would you like to offer
immersive audio
with rendering
of multipoint audio sources
that provides that sense
of being there?
Can we do all this
from the convenience
of the mobile device
in our customer's pocket?
In this session, we're going
to explore spatial audio
and how to deliver it with the
Core AVFoundation playback APIs
and WebKit.
We've got a full agenda.
Together we'll cover
what is spatial audio
by contrasting it to existing
technology we're familiar with.
Then we'll enumerate
the technologies and treatments
that the feature offers.
In the second half,
I'll introduce API
and highlight different
treatments that are applied.
Next up, we'll review
the levels of support
for spatial audio
in prior releases
so that you can target features
appropriately.
I'll also reveal
what's new this year
in our fall 2021 OS releases.
Then to top it all off,
we'll end with a demo.
I'm excited to share that
with you.
You're in for a treat!
To understand
what is spatial audio,
let's start by considering
classic stereo.
Be it headphones
or stereo speaker arrangements
of yesteryear,
the soundstage we perceive
is rather limited.
We don't hear sounds
from behind us,
directly in front,
or above us.
It's missing lifelike,
positional reproduction.
And in the case
of headphones,
the sound emanates from tiny
speakers in, or on, our heads;
we call this
an in-head experience.
As we naturally move our heads
while watching a movie,
those tiny speakers
move with us.
This is not
a theater-like experience,
but this is where
spatial audio can help.
Spatial audio offers
a theater-like experience.
It's a psychoacoustic technology
that has the effect
of producing a compelling
virtual soundstage.
It works best with
multichannel content
but it also offers
a compelling experience
for stereo content as well.
Finally, spatial audio support
is offered for audiovisual
and audio-only media sources.
Best of all, it works with
a variety of Apple products
your customers already have.
We made it simple to bring
the spatial audio experience
to your customers.
As I just alluded to, the best
way to enjoy spatial audio
in your applications is to
provide multichannel audio.
That experience is most adaptive
to the customer's environment
when providing HLS variants
that reference multichannel
audio alternates.
In fact, you may already have
in your content library
multichannel audio source media.
Simply publishing this
will enable, by default,
spatial audio
in your application.
There's absolutely no
software change needed.
Multichannel audio tracks
in regular media files --
and WebKit's MSE
in the fall 2021 releases --
also benefit from limited
support that I'll detail later.
Let me tell you
about media experiences
you can now expect to create.
There's so many experiences
you can now recreate
with spatial audio.
You can deliver music
that surrounds us,
that feels like
being at the concert.
You can build
full-motion video games
with interactive scenes
that take gamers
on their own
immersive adventures.
But how does
this technology work?
When spatial audio is used, the
virtual soundstage is static.
The soundstage doesn't move
with casual head movement,
unlike we saw earlier
with stereo.
What we get is the same
audible effect and feeling
we expect from the theater.
This effect is possible
both from the built-in speakers
in many of our products
and now is also available
in select headphone products.
When spatial-capable
headphones are used,
measurements from
inertial measurement units
in the playback device
are compared with
similar measurements
in the headphones
to determine the customer's
head pose.
This is used to dynamically
alter the audio rendering
to maintain that static
soundstage effect.
The result is a feeling
like the audio is emanating
from the original placement
around the camera,
or listener,
for an out-of-head experience.
It even works on a turning bus
or a banking airplane.
We also offer a technique
to up-mix stereo sources
to reproduce
a 5.1 channel experience.
We provide this feature
to offer spatial audio
along with your existing library
of stereo content.
For supported headphones,
it is the default
stereo treatment
in our fall 2021 releases.
We also use this treatment
implicitly to make spatial audio
even more compelling
for you to adopt and offer,
because right about now,
you're probably thinking
that distributing
multichannel audio
might impede the visual quality
of your media.
After all, multichannel audio
is much higher bitrate
than the stereo AAC renditions
you offer today.
How can you possibly
fit both in a constrained
network bandwidth
environment?
This a real problem.
We solved this by making
the spatial audio experience
adaptive to your customer's
bandwidth.
When bandwidth
is insufficient to deliver
a high-quality audiovisual
experience,
the audio seamlessly degrades
to a stereo, up-mixed --
but a still spatial --
treatment.
Head-tracking, if offered
before the transition,
is maintained.
Soon after, when bandwidth
reliably recovers,
the full multichannel
spatial treatment is restored.
With this adaptive
spatial audio experience,
it is ever more important
to both normalize
the volume levels between stereo
and multichannel renditions.
In addition,
please provide DRC --
Dynamic Range Control --
and dialnorm metadata
in your media encodings
as is appropriate.
This is described in more detail
in the HLS Authoring
Specification
available at
developer.apple.com.
Let's take a look now
at the interfaces you can use
to tailor the spatial audio
experience.
To customize the default
spatial audio experience
in your application --
be it via AVPlayerItem or now,
AVSampleBufferAudioRenderer --
you specify one of four
AVAudioSpatializationFormats.
These are to permit
the spatialization
of mono and stereo,
multichannel,
and the combination
of the last two --
that is mono, stereo,
and multichannel
source audio formats.
You can also specify zero
to inhibit audio spatialization.
Do note that our platforms
provide system-level controls
for customers to tailor
the experience further,
depending on the type
of audio route,
through Control Center
and Bluetooth settings.
We take one of these four values
and set it on the
allowedAudioSpatialization
Formats property
on an AVPlayerItem and now,
new in our fall 2021 releases,
an AVSampleBufferAudioRenderer.
Now, you may be wondering,
how do you use AVFoundation APIs
to discover if an audio route
supports spatial audio?
How do you know if you should
deliver multichannel audio to
your AVSampleBufferAudioRenderer
instance?
Well, in the fall 2021 releases,
we're introducing a property
that indicates this
on an
AVAudioSessionPortDescription.
In addition, on AVAudioSession,
we're introducing a mechanism
for you to advertise
to the system
that your application is able
to offer multichannel audio.
This indication is shown
if the customers
haven't enabled
the spatial audio treatment
in Control Center
or Bluetooth preferences.
Note that if your application
uses AVPlayer,
these indications
are managed for you.
The isSpatialAudioEnabled
property indicates that the port
is capable of both
rendering spatial audio
and that the customer
permits it.
You are encouraged to observe
route change notifications
and to check
isSpatialAudioEnabled
at each event.
Similarly, AVAudioSession
will emit
a spatialPlaybackCapabilities
ChangedNotification
when the customer
alters the spatial preferences
in Control Center
and Bluetooth settings.
As a convenience, this
notification carries information
about the state of spatial audio
enablement.
Use the AVAudioSession
SpatialAudioEnabledKey
to retrieve the state as it
pertains to this notification.
Finally, to indicate
to the system that your software
or service can provide
multichannel content,
you call the function
setSupportsMultichannelContent
with your intent.
This is used
to relay to the customer
that a spatial experience
is available
if network conditions permit
and if the treatment is enabled.
Let's now survey
the feature support
across the last three
release years.
In macOS Catalina,
iOS and iPad OS 13,
spatial audio is offered
via built-in speakers
with AVPlayerItem
and the WebKit video tag
by specifying any URL
with an http scheme.
It is available to customers
with 2018 and later year model
MacBook, iPhone,
and iPad Pro product lines.
The default is to offer
spatialization by selecting
multichannel audio renditions
where available.
In macOS Big Sur,
iOS and iPad OS 14,
we introduced support for
the AirPods Pro and AirPods Max
head-track-capable headphones.
Spatialization capabilities
via these accessories
is offered to 2016 and later
iPhone- and iPad-paired devices.
The default remains
to offer spatialization
by selecting multichannel audio
renditions where available.
That brings us to the all-new
support in macOS Monterey,
iOS, iPadOS,
and now, tvOS 15.
Here we offer support
via AVPlayerItem,
AVSampleBufferAudioRenderer,
and limited WebKit support
for W3C Media Source Extensions,
MSE.
The MSE path offers no interface
to tailor the spatialization
experience.
However, there does exist
an interface to detect
the availability
of spatial audio support
via the AudioConfiguration
dictionary
within the Media Capabilities
API set.
The default in these releases
is to offer audio spatialization
by default
for all of mono, stereo,
and multichannel sources
where available
and conditions permit.
For audio-only presentations,
including all AVSampleBuffer
AudioRenderer uses,
only multichannel
audio renditions
are offered the treatment
by default.
Now that we know
what spatial audio is
and how to use it, we've got
something really special
lined up for you today.
We're going to show you
how you can use spatial audio
in your software and services
to help tell stories
in new, creative ways.
Let's have a listen!
>> ♪ Upbeat music playing ♪
[BEEP]
[SLOW WHIRRING] <<
Uh-oh.
Let's try that again.
Um... Uh...
[EMBARRASSED LAUGHTER]
Cupertino?
We have a problem.
Offscreen voice:
What is it this time?
Simon: [SIGHS] I know.
I know. Anything?
Offscreen whisper: Sorry, Simon.
Simon: No?
Offscreen whisper: It's not
going to work.
Simon: Really?
Offscreen whisper: I know...
Simon: [SOFTLY] Bugger it.
All right. All right. All right.
So we made
this really great demo
to demonstrate all
the cool things you can do
with spatial audio but...
you know...
it seems like
this isn't happening today.
[SIGHS]
Look.
We're going to try something.
I can't show you this video
but what if I could, um...
...describe it?
OK. So I don't know
where you are right now,
but I want you
to close your eyes
and let's imagine
we're in a WWDC hall.
You know what that
sounds like, right?
What that feels like?
Picture it in your mind.
Picture the stage
and the big screen.
We're just about
to dim the lights
and start playing this video.
Oi! You!
Dim the lights.
[DISTANTLY] We're high in
the sky above San Francisco.
Whooshing from the bay,
down through the tall buildings.
[VOCAL PANS RIGHT] The wind
is rushing all around us,
and then we're zooming
out of the city
and down the peninsula,
all the way to Apple Park.
[VOCALS PAN FORWARD]
We soar into the park
and you see somebody
with amazing hair
duck as we fly past.
He shouts, "Slow down!"
which has this really cool
left-to-right Doppler effect.
[ELONGATED] Slow down!
[LAUGHTER]
And we're flying through
the Apple orchard now.
Feel the whoosh of the trees.
We find ourselves at the pond
for a moment of peace
and tranquility.
Whispered voice: I'm honestly
not sold on spatial audio.
Simon: And then,
we're on the move again,
whooshing over the birds
until we reach
the big glass doors
of Caffè Macs
sliding across
the smooth terrazzo floor
until we find this woman.
She's eating a pizza with her
iPad propped up on the table,
totally absorbed in this movie
that's really, really tense.
It's this teeming jungle
at the earliest hours of dusk.
[IMITATES BIRD CAWING]
The audio is literally --
no really!
It's -- It's pulling us
into the scene.
Whispered voice: He's doing a
great job describing this demo.
I almost feel like I'm there.
It's so vivid.
[BIRD CALLS]
Simon: ...and distant monkey
calls. [QUIETLY IMITATES MONKEY]
But suddenly it gets eerie...
[MOSQUITO PANS LEFT TO RIGHT]
...and all the creatures
go quiet.
All we can hear
is the rustling of leaves.
Then a c-c-c-crash
[RUSTLING CRASH]
as a tree falls.
Something is coming!
Something big!
[THUMPING FOOTFALLS]
Thump. Thump. Thump.
We can hear our heart beating,
right in the chest.
[THUMPING CONTINUES]
And then... silence.
[RUSTLING]
We're about to relax when...
[IMITATES ROAR]
[THUMPING INTENSIFIES]
a dinosaur bursts through
the trees right across from us!
[THUMPING IN RIGHT SPEAKER]
And we look up,
straight into its gaping maw!
[ROAR]
[SIMON SCREAMS]
[BELL RINGS]
Voice over PA:
That's a wrap on 42...
Simon: We pull back to reveal
we're on a film set.
Man: I'm not sure
I love that lighting...
Simon: The dinosaur
has stopped moving
and a crew of people have
appeared to clear the set.
[BUSTLING SOUNDS]
Woman: Go for Kelly.
Voice over radio:
You got a 20 on actors?
[AUDIO PANS RIGHT TO LEFT]
Woman: Yeah. They're in makeup
watching the launch.
Going off comms.
[RAPID FOOTFALLS]
Woman: Are you coming?
Simon: We follow two of them
into a trailer
to watch today's space launch --
streaming, of course,
in surround audio.
The audience
is holding their breath
but we move through them
and into the TV.
Woman: Go for launch.
Man: Good across the board.
Simon: And now we're inside
the capsule.
[COUNTDOWN OVER RADIO]
Woman: Let's put the pedal
to the floor.
[RUMBLING]
Simon: The rocket ignites!
Woman: [VOICE VIBRATING]
Here we go!
Express service to the moon!
Next stop, Tranquility.
Man: All still good.
[RUMBLING CONTINUES]
Booster separation
in three, two, one...
Clean and smooth.
[RUMBLING FADES]
Simon: The second stage
of the rocket has dropped away,
and we drop with it...
...and follow the stage
as it falls back to Earth,
getting faster and faster.
[AIR WHOOSHING]
We're dropping through
the atmosphere now,
back towards the ground.
Towards something.
[WHOOSHING INTENSIFIES]
A big jet plane.
Getting bigger,
and bigger, and --
[MECHANICAL WHIRRING]
[THUMP]
[AIRPLANE HUMMING]
[CHIMING TONES]
Woman on PA:
Good morning, folks.
This is your captain speaking
from the flight deck.
[INDISTINCT VOICES
FROM LEFT]
...our descent towards
our final destination today.
Shouldn't be more...
[BABY CRIES]
[CRYING AND ANNOUNCEMENT
CONTINUE]
[PERSON SIGHS]
[CRYING AND ANNOUNCEMENT FADE]
[RUSTLING]
[AIR HISSES]
[SEAGULLS CRYING]
[WAVES CRASHING]
Simon: [SIGHS]
It's beautiful!
[GASPS]
[CLAPS] Well, so, uh...
that was fun.
Let's summarize
what we saw and heard.
We discovered how easy it is
to offer our customers
a spatial audio experience.
In fact, you may not need to do
anything to your application
to take advantage
of spatial audio.
Just by offering
multichannel audio
in your HLS variant playlists
is often sufficient.
Remember, it is important
to normalize volume levels
between stereo and multichannel
renditions,
and to include DRC metadata.
Finally, we've seen how you can
offer spatial audio
to a wide customer base
across the last three years
of OS releases.
In our related sessions,
you can learn how to discover
if your HLS resources
have multichannel audio.
Learn all about that
as you explore HLS variants
in AVFoundation.
I hope you've enjoyed
this session
as much as the team here
and I have.
We hope you'll immerse yourself,
and your app,
in spatial audio and enjoy
the rest of WWDC 2021.
Thank you.
♪