[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Caleb] Hi. My name is Caleb.
I'm a software engineer
on the tvOS team.
Today, I'm excited to share
some great improvements
we've made to sign-ins
in tvOS 15.
We want everyone using Apple TV
to be able to get
to their content quickly,
and with as little friction
as possible.
That means the process
of signing in to your apps
should be fluid and painless.
One of the most common ways
to sign in
is by using a password.
Users are encouraged to have
strong or unique passwords,
but these can be
frustrating to type.
In tvOS 15,
we have a great new feature
that makes it easier
than ever to perform
password-based sign-ins
in your apps.
It starts with the new
system sign-in view.
This view does a few
really important things.
First, it provides a consistent
sign-in experience across tvOS.
Second, it tells users
they can use their iPhone
or iPad to complete the sign-in.
Third, it gives users options
for other sign-in types
your app may support.
I'll talk more about that later.
For now, I wanna focus on using
your iPhone or iPad to sign in.
If a user begins
a sign-in in your app,
then wakes their iPhone,
they'll see a notification
like this from the Apple TV.
When they tap the notification,
iPhone will guide them
through the process
of signing in.
It will suggest a credential
from iCloud Keychain.
And they can use Face ID
to confirm the sign-in.
The credential is then
sent back to the Apple TV.
Now, the app can
finish the sign-in
and take the user
right to their content.
I want to take
a moment to point out
that this is not
a text-entry experience.
It's a first-class
sign-in experience,
where both the Apple TV
and the iPhone or iPad
cooperate to guide the user
through the sign-in process.
Adopting this new sign-in
experience is really easy.
There's a high-level API
on all Apple platforms
that's designed to help people
sign in to your apps.
It's especially powerful
in tvOS 15.
With just a little bit of code,
you can take full advantage
of the great sign-in experience
I just showed you.
I'd love
to walk you through it now.
Let's start with configuring
your app's associated domains.
Associated domains
establish a secure link
between your app and domain.
This allows the Apple TV
and the iPhone or iPad
to work together
to safely suggest
credentials to use
for signing in.
First, make sure the Apple
app site association file
hosted by your domain
lists your tvOS app's
application identifier
inside the web credentials key.
Next, add
the Associated Domain capability
to your tvOS app in Xcode.
And finally, add your domain
to the Associated Domains
capability
with the web credentials prefix.
To learn more about configuring
web credentials domains
in your apps,
see the "Introducing Password
AutoFill for Apps" video
from WWDC 2017.
Next, I'd like to show you
how to request
a credential using
AuthenticationServices.
Let's take a look at some code.
Here we have
the basic ingredients
needed to request a credential.
If you're already using
the AuthenticationServices API
in your iOS or macOS apps,
this code should look
very familiar.
I'll start by creating
an instance
of ASAuthorizationController
with a password request.
Something really powerful
about this API
is that it lets you specify
multiple different kinds
of requests.
If your app also supports
Sign in with Apple,
you may include
an Apple ID request
in the authorization
requests array.
When you specify
multiple requests,
iPhone and iPad will let
the user decide
which type of credential
they would like to use
to sign in.
Next, I'll set myself
as the delegate
of the authorization controller
and call performRequests
to start the sign-in.
Now, I need to implement
a few methods
from ASAuthorization-
ControllerDelegate.
When the user has
selected a credential
they want to use
on their iPhone or iPad,
the system will call
didCompleteWithAuthorization.
Now, I can use the user
and password properties
on the credential
to finish the sign-in.
If the sign-in fails, the system
will call didCompleteWithError.
If the user canceled
the sign-in,
I'll return from this method
so the app can go back
to the main sign-in UI.
Otherwise,
I should let the user know
something went wrong
and that they should try again.
Next, I'd like to show you
how you can customize
the system sign-in view.
The custom authorization
methods API allows you to show
buttons for other sign-in types
your apps may support.
The ".other" value provides
a great deal of flexibility.
You may use this option
to navigate directly
to a manual sign-in flow,
like asking for a username
and password.
Or you may use it to navigate
to your own UI
that allows the user to select
a different type of sign-in
to perform.
If your app allows users
to sign in
using their TV provider account,
you should use
the .videoSubscriberAccount
value.
And finally,
the .restorePurchase value
allows users to sign in
by restoring an in-app purchase.
When the user selects
one of these
custom authorization methods,
it is up to your app
to begin
the requested sign-in flow.
Let's take a look
at how this works.
First, I'll go back to the
ASAuthorizationController code
I showed you earlier.
In order to show
custom sign-in options,
I'll set
the customAuthorizationMethods
property on my
authorization controller.
In this example,
I'm using the .other
and .restorePurchase values
to display "Sign in Manually"
and "Restore Purchase" buttons
in the system sign-in view.
You should choose the values
that are appropriate
for your app.
When the user selects
a custom authorization method,
the system will call
didCompleteWithCustomMethod
on my authorizationController
delegate.
In this method, I can check
the value that was passed in
and perform the type of sign-in
that the user requested.
Finally, I want to take a moment
to talk about
some best practices.
The best sign-in experience
on tvOS
starts with
a single "Sign In" button.
It guides the user
through the sign-in process,
offering a limited number
of clear choices.
By replacing your existing
sign-in experience
with the new
system sign-in view,
users will always have
the option to sign in
with their iPhone or iPad.
And the custom authorization
methods API is a great way
for you to offer your users
additional sign-in options.
tvOS 15 makes it
easier than ever
to build
great sign-in experiences.
The system sign-in view
allows users
to sign-in
with their iPhone or iPad.
And the powerful new
API in AuthenticationServices
makes it easy
for you to get started.
For a more in-depth look
at some of the examples I shared
in this presentation,
see the sample code project
for this session
in the developer app.
To learn more about
how the AuthenticationServices
framework can help you build
great sign-in experiences
across all Apple platforms,
see the "What's new
in Authentication" video
from WWDC 2019.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the conference!
[upbeat music]