[percussive music]
[Suzy] Hello
and welcome to WWDC 2021.
I'm Suzy,
and I work on XCTest in Xcode.
In this session,
we're gonna learn about how
to diagnose unreliable code
with test repetitions,
a tool to repeat your tests.
In the process of running
tests that exercise your app,
your tests may occasionally fail
when running unreliable code.
You may run into this type
of inconsistency
when dealing
with race conditions,
environment assumptions,
global state, or communication
with external services.
These are hard bugs
to track down
because they're
challenging to reproduce.
One way to diagnose these
types of failures
is to run your tests repeatedly.
Test repetition,
added in Xcode 13,
allows you to repeat
a test up to a specified number
of iterations
with a stopping condition.
Xcode supports three
test repetition modes.
The first
mode is Fixed iterations.
Fixed iterations will
repeat your tests
a fixed number of times
regardless of the status.
Fixed iterations is
great for understanding
the reliability of your test
suite and helping
keep it reliable as new tests
are introduced over time.
The second is Until failure.
Until failure will continue
to repeat a test until it fails.
I love using this tool
to reproduce a nondeterministic
test failure to catch
it in the debugger.
Lastly is Retry on failure.
Retry on failure will
retry your test
until it succeeds
up to a specified maximum.
This is useful to identify
unreliable tests
which fail initially but
eventually succeed on reattempt.
If a test in CI is exhibiting
this behavior,
you could enable
Retry on failure
in your test plan temporarily
and gather additional
data to fix the issue.
It's important to remember
retrying failures
can hide problems
in the actual product.
Some functionality fails
initially
before eventually succeeding,
so it's best to use
this mode temporarily
to diagnose the failures.
Let's get a better understanding
of how this works in practice.
I created an app called
IceCreamTruckCountdown
that tells me how long until
the ice cream truck
drives by my home.
I love when the truck
has cookies and cream,
and so I wrote a test
called testFlavors
to ensure that the truck
has all the flavors.
testFlavors has a truck that
I get from the truckDepot.
I call prepareFlavors
and, lastly,
assert that the truck
has all 33 flavors.
Recently,
I've noticed testFlavors
sometimes fails on the main
branch in Xcode Cloud.
To gather more information,
I temporarily configured
my test plan,
enabling Test Repetition Mode
to Retry on failure.
Let's take a look at
the report navigator
and check our cloud reports.
My tests are inconsistently
failing,
so let's check this last
one for more information.
If I expand
the first device open,
there is an iteration label here
letting us know
it was the first
iteration of this test.
Huh. And when I expand all
the other rows,
the assertion
failures are all the same,
and this last test passed.
I expected all the tests
to pass consistently,
not just on one device.
I'm gonna try to reproduce
this failure locally.
Let's go to our file
that has testFlavors.
I'll Control-click on the test
diamond for our test.
In the menu, I'll select Run
"testFlavors()" Repeatedly…
to bring up
the test repetition dialog.
Here you can select
the stopping condition
of your repetitions,
set Maximum Repetitions,
and other options
like Pause on Failure.
I want to try to reproduce
the issue that happened
in our cloud report, so I'm
setting my stopping condition
to go through maximum
repetitions and keep it at 100.
Now I'll run my test.
Oh, yay!
The test failed locally.
When I click on the failure
annotation,
it displays the same error
that happened in Xcode Cloud,
and it failed
4 out of 100 times.
Great!
I can now debug this issue.
I'll Control-click again
on the test diamond
for testFlavors,
selecting
Run "testFlavors()" Repeatedly…
but this time,
I'm gonna use stop on failure
so I can debug the issue
when it happens.
Thankfully, Xcode automatically
selects Pause on Failure for me,
so I can catch the error
in the debugger.
All right,
we have caught the issue.
And I know we're looking
at inconsistencies
with the flavors on the truck,
so I'll take a look
at our truck object
in the debugger.
It seems strange that flavors
is 0 when it should be 33
because we already
called prepareFlavors.
I wonder if we've made it
inside this completionHandler.
I'll add a breakpoint
and click Continue.
Hmm, that seems wrong.
Oh, the fulfill is called
in the outer completionHandler
and not the inner prepareFlavors
completionHandler.
This is a fairly simple bug
caused by asynchronous events
with multiple completionHandlers
and the expectation
not being fulfilled
in the correct place.
XCTest's support for Swift
5.5's async/await
lets me simplify this test so
it won't happen again.
To transform this test
to use async/await,
I'll add “async throws”
to the method header.
I'll use the “await”
version of getting
the iceCreamTruck
from the truckDepot.
I'll use the "await"
version of prepareFlavors.
I'll keep the same assert, but
the truck is no longer optional.
Let's run this test
one more time
to make sure that it is fixed.
I'll Control-click and select
Run "testFlavors()" Repeatedly…
and once again
select Maximum Repetitions
as the stop condition.
Yay!
The test passed 100 times.
I'm now confident that this is
fixed,
and I'm ready to remove
Retry on failure
from the test plan
and commit my change.
So we just got
a better understanding
of how to use this at desk
and one way to run your test
repeatedly in CI
by configuring it
in your test plan.
Let's talk about another way
to run your tests
with repetition, like in
the demo, using the CLI.
When running xcodebuild
directly,
you can add xcodebuild flags
which override
any test plan setting.
Pass -test-iterations
with a number
to run a test
a fixed number of times
or combine it
with -retry-tests-on-failure
or -run-tests-until-failure
to use it with one of the other
stopping conditions.
To run your test the same as
in the demo with xcodebuild,
you start with the base
xcodebuild command
used to run your tests
and add the flags
-test-iterations set to 100
and -run-tests-until-failure.
In summary,
use test repetitions as a tool
to help diagnose
unreliable code.
For more information about
handling inconsistent tests,
watch "Embrace expected
failures in XCTest."
To learn more about Swift async,
check out
"Meet async/await in Swift."
Thanks for watching.
[percussive music]