[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Garrett Davidson: Hi,
I’m Garrett,
an engineer on the
Authentication Experience team,
and I'm very excited
to give you a peek
into what we’ve been working on:
the first step Apple is taking
to support the industry-wide
transition away from passwords.
Every time you sign in
to an app or website today,
you’re probably entering
a password.
The iconic User name
and Password field pair
is instantly recognizable
and really easy to use,
and most people immediately
know what to do
when they encounter it.
But developers, users,
and the industry as whole
have collectively learned
that this great convenience
of being able
to quickly authenticate
to sign in to an account
comes at a cost
to account security.
As authentication technologies
have evolved over the years,
there are a few
fundamental lessons
that the industry has learned.
First off,
protecting secrets is hard,
especially when those secrets
are shared.
Most authentication today
relies on the user
and server sharing a secret --
like a password --
when the account is created,
and resharing that secret
during every authentication.
Each time that secret is shared,
there’s a risk
that someone other than
the intended recipient
learns that secret.
Phishing -- such as fake emails
and phone calls
or misleading websites --
is the most common way
for the wrong party
to learn a secret.
And if a secret like a password
does get out,
using weak passwords
or reusing the same password
across multiple accounts can
quickly compound the problem.
In fact, according to
the 2020 Verizon Data Breach
Investigation Report,
more than 80 percent
of hacking-related data breaches
involved the brute force
of credentials
or using lost
or stolen credentials.
It doesn’t have to be this way.
Authentication technology
has continued to evolve
to try to mitigate
some of these risks.
At first, passwords were
mostly stored in people’s heads.
But it turns out that people
generally aren’t good
at coming up with
and remembering
strong and unique passwords
for every account.
Password managers
can create strong,
unique passwords per account,
and can provide hints about
some forms of possible phishing.
iCloud Keychain’s
password manager
is built in
to your Apple devices,
and we’ve made APIs available
for third parties
to integrate their own password
managers into the system.
Service owners can also add
additional steps
to the login flow,
such as requiring a password
plus an additional factor
like an OTP;
for instance, an SMS
or a generated
one-time verification code.
macOS Monterey and iOS 15
even have a code generator
built in to the iCloud Keychain
password manager,
which you can
learn more about
in the “Secure login with iCloud
Keychain verification codes”
video from my teammate Eryn.
Some apps and websites
alternatively choose
to outsource authentication
entirely to a third party
through federated
authentication,
such as Sign in with Apple.
Federated authentication
lets people keep their trust
confined to a small number
of highly protected accounts.
But for this video,
I’m going to be focusing
on nonfederated
authentication options.
Let’s talk about
how these compare.
They’re all pretty easy to use,
they all work on most devices,
and they’re more or less
always with you.
But the security level
could be better.
Passwords that can be remembered
probably aren’t strong
and unique for every account.
A password manager can be used
to create strong
and unique passwords,
but it is only as strong
as the password --
and potentially
additional factors --
that you use to protect it.
And single-use codes
can also help
but are still subject
to many of the same problems
as passwords,
since they’re still typeable,
phishable, shared secrets.
Also, if passwords
are in your head,
you can forget them.
This means apps and websites
need a separate recovery flow,
which today is usually a link
in an email.
This can reduce the entire
account’s security level
to the level of security
of the email provider,
which is generally not something
you control.
Some password managers
and second-factor solutions
can help with recovery but tend
to face similar problems.
Remembered passwords
also don’t offer
any kind of phishing resistance.
Password managers can provide
hints about phishing --
such as not offering to fill
a password on a phishing site
that looks otherwise
legitimate --
but they still can’t prevent
someone
from manually entering
the password themselves
and getting phished.
One-time codes have
similar problems,
though there are some
modern mitigations
you can put in place.
And finally,
all of these methods
rely on a shared secret
between the user and a server,
making them fundamentally
no stronger
than the weakest protection
of that shared secret.
With that chart in mind,
let’s talk about the properties
of an actual solution
to the password problem.
First off, a replacement
for passwords
needs to be secure by design.
Passwords can be
reasonably secure,
if all of the best practices
are followed.
However, experience has shown us
that that’s pretty hard
for everyone to do
all of the time.
A replacement for passwords
should build that security in
from the beginning.
But we don’t want to go
backwards in usability either.
Passwords have been with us
for so long
because they’re so easy to use.
We don’t want to lose that.
Being easy includes
always being available
and being usable everywhere.
Today, as long as I know
or can look up my password,
I can pretty much assume that
the device I want to sign into
supports it.
Any additional friction
to authenticating on new devices
is going to hurt adoption
from people who just want
to quickly get signed in.
And finally, recovery should be
a first-class feature
not something that gets added
as an afterthought.
People make mistakes,
bad things happen,
and a solution to passwords
should be fault tolerant enough
to handle humans being human
without compromising
the overall security.
One of the strongest security
options out there today
is security keys,
the hardware dongles or fobs
that are generally used
as a second factor in especially
high security contexts.
They are based
on the web authentication --
or WebAuthn -- standard,
which is open to everyone.
And most of them
are pretty easy to use
after the initial
learning curve.
And they’re way more secure
than just a password.
Most of this strength
comes from WebAuthn,
which I’ll talk about more
in a bit.
Modern web browsers
also support security keys
on most modern devices.
Safari on macOS and iOS
has supported USB,
NFC, and Lightning security keys
for a while.
Most security keys also support
more than one connection method,
so a single hardware key can be
used on many different devices.
Let’s compare WebAuthn
and passwords.
One of the biggest advantages
of WebAuthn
is it uses public/private
key pairs
instead of shared secrets.
If we examine how passwords
work today,
first you enter your password.
Then, it’s usually obfuscated
through something
like hashing plus salting,
and the resulting salted hash
is sent to the server.
Now, both you and the server
have a copy of the secret,
even though the server’s copy
is obfuscated,
and you’re both
equally responsible
for protecting that secret.
This is what
we’re getting rid of.
With public/private key pairs,
instead of a password,
your device creates
a pair of keys.
One of these keys is public;
just as public as your username.
It can be shared with anyone
and everyone,
and is not a secret.
The other key is private.
This private key is a secret
and is protected by your device.
Your device never shares
this key with anyone else,
not even the server.
When you create an account,
your device generates
these two associated keys.
It then shares the public key
with the server.
Now, the server has a copy
of the public key,
which does not have the same
protection requirements
as a password
because it’s public information.
The private key
stays on your device,
and only that device is
responsible for protecting it.
Later, when you want to sign in,
you don’t send the server
anything secret.
Instead you prove
that it’s your account
by proving that your device
knows the private key
associated with your account’s
public key.
That exchange works like this.
First, I go to sign in
to my account.
Then, the website asks my device
to prove that
it’s actually my account.
It does this by performing
what’s called a "challenge"
for me to prove that my device
has the private key
associated with my account’s
public key
without actually saying
what my private key is.
To do so, the server sends back
a single-use challenge.
My device has the private key,
so it takes that challenge
and does something called
“signing” of the challenge,
using my private key.
Only my private key can produce
a valid signature
for my account.
This signature then gets
sent back to the server.
The server already
has my public key,
so it can check this signature
against that public key.
Anyone who has my public key
can easily check
if a signature matches that key.
However, only I can create
a valid signature
for the challenge because
only I have the private key.
Therefore, anyone can
easily verify my identity
without ever learning
what my secret is.
And finally,
assuming the signature does
actually match my public key,
the server tells me
I’m signed in!
Notice that my private key
never left my device.
The server was able to verify
that this is my account
without ever learning
what my secret --
my private key --
actually is.
Because public/private key pairs
mean credentials are created
and managed by the device --
and private keys are
never shared with a server --
these keys are never going to be
guessable, reused, weak,
or vulnerable to your server
being breached.
WebAuthn also roots its trust
in the browser
and operating system,
not the human.
The software strictly enforces
that credentials
are only ever usable
on the websites and apps
that they were created for,
preventing someone from even
attempting to authenticate
on the incorrect website.
And because all credentials
in WebAuthn
are public/private key pairs,
the server is no longer
responsible
for maintaining
authentication secrets.
This means less work
on the server side
to keep secrets safe,
and servers are less valuable
targets for attackers
because there are
no authentication secrets
for an attacker to steal.
Let’s compare security keys
to the other items
in that chart.
They’re fairly easy to use after
the initial learning curve.
They work on
all of your Apple devices
and many modern
non-Apple devices.
But they’re not necessarily
always with you.
You need to purchase
and carry around
additional hardware
at all times.
This can be a barrier
to entry for adoption,
and is a step back in usability
compared to passwords.
The security level
is very good, though.
Credentials on a security key
are guaranteed
to never be easily guessable
or reused
across multiple accounts,
and have phishing protection
built in at the OS level.
That security
comes at a price, though.
If credentials are tied
to single security key
and that security key
is ever lost, stolen,
or damaged,
so are all of those credentials.
Adopters must have
a backup system in place,
such as purchasing
an additional security key,
storing it somewhere safe,
and hoping they never lose both
at the same time.
Thanks to WebAuthn, though,
they do provide
very strong phishing resistance
and remove the need
for server-stored secrets.
In iOS 14.5, we extended
security key support
to work in all browsers on iOS.
New in macOS Monterey
and iOS 15,
we’re also making
security key API
available for the first time
for all apps on macOS and iOS.
This API is being added to
the ASAuthorization API family
in the AuthenticationServices
framework,
as a native equivalent
to the WebAuthn API on the web.
ASAuthorization
is your one-stop shop
for getting signed in
with whatever mechanisms
the system supports,
including passwords,
Sign in with Apple,
and now security keys.
Carrying around
additional hardware,
like a security key,
isn’t necessarily for everyone,
though.
We believe this API
will be useful for apps
in especially
high-security contexts,
where the usability tradeoffs
for your users
are outweighed
by special security needs,
and we’re excited
for you to try it out
if you fall in that category.
Now, passwordless authentication
using key pairs
is the next big thing
in authentication technology.
The standard has been
a collaborative effort
across the industry
from both platform vendors
and service owners
with the goal of pushing
account security forward.
Support for WebAuthn is growing
across operating systems,
app platforms, web browsers,
and websites.
What I’m going to be
talking about
for the rest of this video,
and what I’m really excited
to introduce here,
is a preview
of Apple’s contribution
to a postpassword world;
a new feature that builds
the security of WebAuthn
into every iPhone, iPad,
and Mac,
so it can be used everywhere
as a replacement for passwords.
It’s called "passkeys
in iCloud Keychain".
This new feature stores
a new type of credential,
called a "passkey",
in your iCloud Keychain.
Passkeys are WebAuthn
credentials
with the amazing security
that the standard provides
combined with the usability
of being backed up, synced,
and working
on all of your devices.
We’re storing them
in iCloud Keychain.
Just like everything else
in your iCloud Keychain,
they’re end-to-end encrypted,
so not even Apple can read them.
Your secrets are your secrets.
And they’re very easy to use.
In most cases,
it just takes a single tap
or click to sign in.
And they’re stronger than most
password-plus-second-factor
solutions out there today,
thanks to the combined security
of WebAuthn and iCloud Keychain.
And because it’s just
a single tap to sign in,
it’s simultaneously easier,
faster, and more secure
than almost all common forms
of authentication today.
Let’s add it to that chart.
As I just said,
it’s super easy to use;
usually just one tap, or click,
to sign in.
What we’re releasing as part
of macOS Monterey and iOS 15
works on all
of your Apple devices.
Of course, to replace passwords
for everyone,
this technology needs
to work on all of your devices,
including those that
don’t support iCloud Keychain.
That functionality
is not present
in macOS Monterey and iOS 15.
Because it’s built in
to all of your Apple devices,
it’s available any time
you have your iPhone,
iPad, or Mac nearby.
No additional hardware required.
It builds on all
of the advanced protections
that are part of both
the WebAuthn standard
and iCloud Keychain.
And since it’s backed
by iCloud Keychain,
you can still get
your credentials back,
even if you lose
all of your Apple devices.
It has the same
strong platform-provided
phishing resistance
as security keys.
And because it uses
public/private key pairs,
it also means servers
can get out of the business
of storing
authentication secrets,
making them less valuable
targets for attackers.
So here’s how it works.
This is Shiny, our favorite
authentication demo app,
whose source code you can find
in the related links
for this video.
First, I need
to create my account.
I’m going to type in my username
and tap
the Create Account button.
Then, a trusted system sheet
comes up with some information
about the credential and where
I can expect to use it.
I’m going to tap Continue,
Face ID, and I’m done.
I didn’t really have
to think about it,
but I now have a very strong
public/private key credential
for this account,
which is safely stored
in my iCloud Keychain.
When I come back to this app
and want to sign in,
it’s just as easy.
When the sheet comes up,
I get asked
a very clear question,
including the name of the app
I’m signing into
and my account.
That’s what I want,
so I’m going to tap Continue,
Face ID, and I’m done.
That’s it!
This is all it takes for people
to create and use
these new credentials.
And because they’re
system-managed
public/private key pairs,
they won’t be reused
or guessable,
they’re not vulnerable to
breaches of the app or website,
and very strong
phishing protections
are built in to the operating
system and browser.
Speaking of browsers,
these credentials also work
on the web.
Here I am in Safari
on the Shiny website’s
home page,
which has adopted WebAuthn.
When I tap the Sign In button,
I get options here
to use the credential
that I just created
or a security key
if I want to use that.
I can tap Continue here,
Face ID,
and I’m signed in,
just like in the app.
This also works in all
web browser apps on iOS.
And it works on Mac, too!
These credentials are stored
in iCloud Keychain,
so they sync across
all of your devices,
and they work
in all kinds of Mac apps,
as well as on the web in Safari.
Now let’s take a peek
at the implementation.
First off, for that strong,
platform-provided
phishing protection
to work for your apps,
the device needs
a strong association
between your app and website.
This is done through
associated domains,
using the “webcredentials”
association type.
I won’t go into
too much detail here,
but you can learn more
by watching
the “Introducing Password
AutoFill for Apps” video
from a few years ago.
Next, let’s talk about
creating an account.
The code here is actually
pretty straightforward.
Let’s break it down.
Our createAccount function
needs three inputs:
a single-use challenge
fetched from your server,
the username for the account,
and the userID,
which is generally
the identifier
for the account on your backend.
First, you need
a request provider
to create request objects.
The relyingPartyIdentifier
depends on your WebAuthn setup,
but it’s usually
your domain name.
Use that provider to create
a registrationRequest
and pass the request
to an authorization controller.
Finally, set the delegate
and presentationContextProvider
on the authorization controller
and start your request.
This will cause that sheet
from earlier to pop up
and ask you to create
a credential.
When the transaction
is finished,
you’ll receive
a delegate callback
with the details
of the new credential.
Now, signing in is very similar.
Just a few things
need to change.
Instead of creating
a registrationRequest,
you now create
an assertionRequest,
which is the WebAuthn
terminology used
when signing in.
The assertionRequest
only needs a challenge.
And that’s all you need
to change.
I want to take a second
to highlight
that this parameter
to the authorization controller
is an array.
You can pass in a list here
of requests
for all of the different
authentication mechanisms
that your app supports,
including passwords
and Sign in with Apple.
That sheet from earlier
will be populated
with whatever credentials
are currently available.
The only caveat is that
public key registration requests
can’t be mixed
with nonregistration options.
OK, so finally,
let’s talk about the callback
to your delegate object
when the authorization
completes.
The credential is a property
of the provided
authorization object.
If the user registered
a new platform credential,
you’ll receive a platform
credential registration.
If they signed in with
an existing platform credential,
you’ll receive a platform
credential assertion.
Or if they signed in
with something else
that you support,
you can handle that here, too.
In any case, you should read
the properties that you need
from the credential object
just like you would on the web,
send those values
off to your server,
verify them,
and finish the operation.
And that’s how it works.
Now, I just want to mention
a few more details.
A transition away from passwords
is going to take time,
and it’s important
to get the details right.
In macOS Monterey and iOS 15,
passkeys in iCloud Keychain
is being released
as a technology preview
and is off by default.
On iOS, there’s a new switch
in the Developer settings
section of the Settings app.
Turning this on will allow you
to use these synced keys
in both apps and on the web.
And on macOS, the switch lives
in Safari’s Develop menu.
First, you’ll need to turn on
the Develop menu,
in Safari’s Advanced settings.
You’ll find the setting for this
at the bottom
of the Advanced pane
in Safari’s preferences.
Then, you can find the option
to turn on the Syncing Platform
Authenticator
in the Develop menu.
Make sure to turn the feature on
when testing.
In macOS Monterey and iOS 15,
these passkeys
are only meant for testing,
not for production accounts.
The emphasis of this preview
is the authentication
technology,
an iCloud Keychain-backed
WebAuthn implementation.
An industry-wide transition
away from passwords
will need thoughtful
and consistently applied
design patterns,
which are not part
of this preview.
And finally,
since this is a preview,
we've made sure it behaves
gracefully when turned off.
Platform registration requests
will return an error,
and platform assertion requests
will be silently ignored
when the switch is off,
even when mixed with other
credential request types.
So here’s what you can do next.
Public key-based,
phishing-resistant credentials
are the next frontier
in account authentication.
Go check out
our developer documentation
and the sample code
linked from this video
to help you get started.
And if you don’t
already have one,
bring up a WebAuthn
implementation on your server,
so that you can start trying out
WebAuthn-based credentials.
Now, my favorite part:
try out this technology preview
of passkeys in iCloud Keychain
to see how it fits into
your existing workflows
in your websites and apps.
As you’re trying it out,
please let us know
what you think
in the developer forums
and Feedback Assistant.
We really want to hear from you.
As I mentioned earlier,
this is the first step
of a multiyear effort
in replacing passwords,
and we’re very interested
in what you all have to say.
Thank you for watching!
♪