[upbeat music]
Nihar: Hello, and welcome to
"What's new in CloudKit."
My name is Nihar Sharma
and I'm an engineer
on the CloudKit team,
and I'll be joined
by my colleague Qian.
We're going to start by
highlighting some changes
to the CloudKit API that take
advantage of Swift concurrency.
Then, Qian will walk
us through
the use
of encrypted fields on records.
Finally, we'll dig deeper
into a new feature
that allows you
to easily share record zones.
First up, we have CloudKit
and Swift concurrency.
As a bit of background,
CloudKit is a framework
that gives your application
access to a database on iCloud.
This is exposed in the API
as a CKContainer
through which you can access
multiple CKDatabases.
Each container has one
public database
where all users can potentially
read and write records.
If the device has
a logged-in iCloud account,
then your app also has
access to a private database,
which contains that user's data.
And if your app
supports sharing,
then data which is shared
to the current iCloud user
will be available to your app
in the shared CKDatabase.
When writing code against
CloudKit,
there are
two general areas of API.
First, the functions,
which are available
on CKContainer and CKDatabase.
This API is useful for new
adopters of CloudKit,
and is meant to provide
a low barrier to entry.
Instead of providing you
with all of the available
configurations,
the framework chooses
a default behavior,
which is most appropriate
for a UI application
that the user
is interacting with.
Next is the Operation API,
which is exposed as
a set of NSOperation subclasses.
This API provides
a number of features
not available as CKContainer
or CKDatabase functions.
This includes sending
and receiving batches of items
in a single
round-trip to the server,
paging through large result sets
by incrementally fetching
them from the server,
requesting database and record
zone changes from the server
since some point in the past,
and lastly, grouping different
operations together.
This allows them to be
logged as a unit
and lets you inform the system
about the size of your
operation-spanning workload.
Many developers eventually
use this API
when writing
production-quality code.
Taking advantage of the new
Swift concurrency functionality,
CloudKit has made
several improvements.
First, I'll cover how you
can use
the new Swift async/await
feature alongside CloudKit APIs.
Then, I'll talk about new
API that helps to clarify
the difference between
a per-item
and a per-operation callback,
and how CloudKit takes advantage
of the Swift.Result type
to clarify the role of
parameters to those callbacks.
And finally, I'll go over
enhancements we've made
to our container and database
functions
which help bring over
some of the features
and configurability
previously available
only via the operation APIs.
CloudKit API
is introducing async variants
for functions
on container and database.
You can use async functions
to improve your code
that deals with concurrency.
It helps with making error
handling more natural,
and simplifies the visual
control flow in your code.
For more detail
on async functions,
please refer to the "Meet
async/await in Swift" session.
Let's check out an example.
This snippet is taken from
the PrivateDatabase code sample.
This is one of several
CloudKit-specific code samples
that Apple recently posted
to GitHub,
and they are available to you.
This specific function
wants to delete a record
from the server and inform
the caller when it's done.
Note that there are many
optionals
and conditional unwrappings
sprinkled around.
And when you first try
to understand this function,
the control flow
isn't immediately obvious.
Now, let's compare this
to code
updated to use CloudKit's
async functions.
Here, the optionals
and unwrappings
have been eliminated,
and the control flow is linear
and easier to follow.
I'm happy to say
that each of our code samples
on the GitHub repository
have updates
which demonstrate
how the code can be
similarly refactored
to use Swift concurrency.
Let's talk about per-item
callbacks.
As an example,
here's a CKFetchRecordsOperation
sending four
CKRecord.IDs to the server,
to ideally get back
four CKRecord payloads.
This operation can go
one of three different ways.
In the first case,
the operation succeeds.
There are no errors,
your records are successfully
fetched from the server.
The second possibility
is that you hit
an operation-wide error.
This is an error that causes
the entire operation to fail.
As an example, maybe the device
lacks a network connection.
In that case,
the entire operation would fail
with a networkUnavailable
error code.
Here's the third option.
In this scenario,
your operation
has successfully
round-tripped to the server.
The server has
successfully returned
three of the requested
CKRecords,
alongside an error
indicating
that the fourth requested
record does not exist.
In this example,
the per-item error
is unknownItem,
and it gets bundled
into a per-operation
error called partialFailure.
So, how is this handled in code?
On top, CKFetchRecordsOperation
declares
its perRecordCompletionBlock
and per-operation
completion block,
alongside
a sample implementation
of each
of these on the bottom.
Note the overlap between
these two callbacks.
From the missing record
example from before,
the code expects
a per-item error twice--
once as a top-level unknownItem
error in the per-item callback
and again bundled inside
a partialFailure error
in the per-operation callback.
Similarly, it also expects
per-item successes
in two places for the records
which are fetched successfully--
first, as a top-level parameter
to a per-item callback,
and once again, wrapped in
the recordsByRecordID dictionary
of successful results
in the per-operation callback.
By leveraging Swift.Result type,
CloudKit has replaced
both of these callbacks
to make the API clearer.
Notice the top-level of
separation of block parameters
in the new
result-based callbacks.
perRecordResultBlock has an ID,
identifying the item
that CloudKit is calling
back about.
And it has its per-item result.
The result
is now strongly typed,
so you know you're getting
either a successfully
fetched CKRecord payload,
or a per-item error.
Similarly, the operation-scoped
completion block
has also been updated to an
operation-scoped result block
which no longer duplicates
any success or failure
already reported by
the per-item result block.
So, CloudKit has now formally
separated their concerns.
One block is used exclusively
for per-item reporting,
and another exclusively
for per-operation reporting.
Going back to our
missing record example,
the expectation is three
invocations of the per-item
result block with successfully
fetched CKRecord payloads,
one invocation of the per-item
result block
with an unknownItem error,
and one invocation of the
per-operation result block
with no error,
as the operation succeeded
overall.
One of CloudKit's new
improvements is to surface
separate per-item and
per-operation callbacks
everywhere.
Previously,
only the highlighted operations
have had per-item callbacks
that surface per-item errors.
I'm happy to announce
that all CKOperations
now expose per-item
callbacks that pass back
per-item errors
when appropriate.
Now, let's take a look
at some enhancements
and expansions we've made to our
container and database APIs.
The enhancements take
the form of new functions
on CKContainer and CKDatabase.
Together, these new functions
make a large chunk
of CKOperation APIs
available as functions
on CKContainer and CKDatabase.
Importantly, this isn't
a one-to-one mapping
of the operation API.
Instead, we've leveraged
default parameters
and the Swift.Result type
to craft an API
that is approachable,
powerful,
and works with async/await.
That is, each new function
is exposed twice--
once taking a completionHandler,
and again as an async function.
With this enhanced API,
functions on the container
and database now support
some of the features
from the Operation API,
like batching multiple items,
paging through large data sets,
and fetching changes.
You can also group
function invocations together
for logging,
and informing the system
about combined workload size.
Function invocations
can now also be configured,
such as by setting timeouts.
So, how does this work?
Here, once again,
is the GitHub PrivateDatabase
code sample we saw earlier,
using async functions
to delete a record.
Let's see how this code
can be updated
to take advantage
of item batching.
I'm going to change
the behavior of this function
to delete two records
atomically
by taking advantage of the
enhanced function API
on database.
Notice the separation
of concerns.
The highlighted areas operate
at the function scope.
They kick off the function
and catch
any function-scoped errors
that are thrown.
And if the function successfully
completes,
this highlighted area
will inspect
the per-item successes
or failures.
We have similar examples
covering each of these features
in the code sample repositories
on GitHub,
and the notes for this session
will include links
to those repositories.
We hope you'll find them useful.
And with that,
I'd like to turn it over
to Qian to walk us through
encrypted fields.
[Qian] Thanks, Nihar.
I'm Qian,
and I will be talking about
a new feature in CloudKit
that will make it super easy
to protect your
users' data privacy.
To do this, I will first
give an overview of how CloudKit
protects your users' data,
then I'll introduce the new
data encryption feature,
and finally,
some prerequisites
on the user’s
account for encryption.
At Apple, privacy is one
of our core values
that we build
into all of our products.
As the framework that powers
many Apple apps and services,
CloudKit has been innovating
privacy technologies constantly
to offer protection for any data
stored and synced with CloudKit.
Firstly,
let me review how CloudKit
protects your users' data.
CloudKit's approach includes two
primary data protection methods,
account-based protection
and cryptographic protection.
Any data stored with CloudKit
is by default protected
by account-based authentication.
This includes your
CloudKit-backed apps
and all the Apple
CloudKit-backed apps.
Upon storage and retrieval,
CloudKit uses secure tokens
to enforce that only authorized
users can access their data
and not Apple
nor any third party.
As a reminder,
only data in private
and shared databases are covered
by account-based protection.
In those databases,
data either belongs to
or is shared to a specific
iCloud account,
and access to the shared
data needs authentication.
However, in public databases,
data can be accessed by all
users, and therefore,
account-based data protection is
not applicable by default.
Now, moving on to the other data
protection technology--
cryptographic protection.
CloudKit provides cryptographic
protection for sensitive data
stored in Apple-owned apps
and services
as well as all of your
users' data
stored in the form of
CKAsset.
These data are preprocessed
and encrypted locally
before it's sent to the CloudKit
server for storage,
and is decrypted locally
upon retrieval.
This encryption functionality
uses key material that is
stored in the iCloud
Keychain belonging
to the iCloud account
signed in on the device.
It's also compatible with
CloudKit's sharing
functionality,
ensuring that only the users
on the CKShare
can decrypt
the relevant encrypted fields.
Cryptographic protection
adds another layer
on top of account-based
protection.
Because even if an unauthorized
party somehow bypasses
the authorization, they cannot
decrypt the data retrieved.
Cryptographic protection
should be used for data
that is sensitive
or private to your users.
Many CloudKit-backed apps
within Apple
take advantage
of this functionality
with Photos and Notes
as two examples.
Until now, CloudKit's protection
for your users' non-asset data
provides account-based
protection by default.
CloudKit is now offering
the cryptographic protection
in addition to save you from all
the key derivation, management,
and the encryption/decryption
processes,
and this will help you
build CloudKit-backed apps
with stronger than ever
privacy promises.
Let's check out the new API
to help you do that.
You can add any key value
pair in the new property
encryptedValues on CKRecords
for encryption,
and the same
exact property to get back
the decrypted original value.
I'm going to go over
how the encryptedValues API
enables you to sync encrypted
data over the CloudKit server.
Here, you have two devices
and one CloudKit server.
If you set the encryptedValues
key value pair,
CloudKit will automatically
encrypt the record
values locally
in CKModifyRecordsOperation
to the server.
On another device,
after retrieving the records
from the server,
you can call the same API
and CloudKit will automatically
unwrap the key value pair.
You only need minimum code
changed to achieve this process.
On the first device,
using the encryptedValues API,
you can set the key value
pair on the record.
In this case, the key
is "encryptedStringField"
and the value
is a string object.
After that, you can then call
CKModifyRecordsOperation
to save the new records
to the server.
On the second device, you
can call CKFetchRecordsOperation
to retrieve the encrypted
record,
and by using the same
encryptedValues property,
you get the string back.
That's it.
One simple property will
handle all of the encryption
and decryption processes
for you.
And you can encrypt almost
all of the CKRecord value types
except for CKReference
because they need to be
visible to the server.
Note that because CKAsset
field, as mentioned previously,
already employs
encryption by default,
they cannot be set
as an encryptedValue.
You can visualize
the encrypted fields
by going to the CloudKit
database schema,
just like
for the regular fields.
There is a CloudKit Console
session,
"Meet CloudKit Console,"
that shows you other changes
made to the Console,
and feel free to check it out.
In the Console,
all encrypted fields will
be shown in the drop-down
for record value data types.
They will have the prefix
"encrypted" such as
"Encrypted Double,"
"Encrypted Timestamp,"
to help you differentiate them
from the unencrypted ones.
You can also manage
encrypted fields through
the CloudKit Console directly,
without any code change.
For example, you can add
a new encrypted field
to a new record type in your
development database schema.
Moving on to the prerequisite
on accounts for operations
involving encryption.
As any other operations
in private and shared databases,
they require a valid
logged-in account.
You need
to check the status of your
current account in your
initialization logic by calling
CKContainer accountStatus(completionHandler:).
As a reminder,
the status will need
to be "available" for operations
in private and shared databases.
Any other states
will result in error:
"CKErrorNotAuthenticated,"
including the new state,
temporarilyUnavailable,
introduced this year to indicate
that an account is logged in
but not ready,
and you may direct users to
verify their credentials
in the Settings app.
If your user's account is
not in "available" state,
you should listen to
CKAccountChanged notification,
which posts whenever the account
changes,
to be notified
when the state may be ready.
That's all
you need to know about
encrypting data with CloudKit.
It will protect your users' data
and will save you all the time
and energy from implementing
your own custom solution.
Now, back to my amazing
colleague Nihar
to talk about zone sharing.
[Nihar] Thanks, Qian! Let's
talk about CloudKit sharing.
CloudKit is your secure,
privacy-conscious iCloud
database in the sky
that helps you store
and sync user data
across
all of your users' devices.
iOS 10 and macOS Sierra
introduced CloudKit sharing,
a way to securely share data
with other iCloud users.
Before diving into what's
new in sharing,
let's take a closer look at how
CloudKit sharing works today.
As a reminder, CloudKit sharing
is initiated via the creation
of a CKShare object
which separates the data
being shared
from sharing-related details,
like who the data
is being shared with,
what permissions those share
participants have, et cetera.
Behind the scenes,
CloudKit establishes
cryptographic access
to the shared data
for participants,
on top of requiring
account-based authentication
for all requests.
Now, there are two
main ways that you can
add sharing support
in your apps.
You can either get
started quickly by using
the system-provided UI
for share management,
vended via
UICloudSharingController on iOS,
and NSSharingService
on macOS.
Or, you can also build
your own custom UI
for letting users
interact with the share setup
by using these
framework operations.
Like I mentioned earlier,
CKShares separate
what's being shared
from who it's shared with.
Today, we're going to be
focusing on the first half
of that equation,
and more specifically,
take a look at a couple
of different ways
you can model your data,
and how that affects
the way that you leverage
the CloudKit sharing APIs.
Let's start with an example
that takes advantage
of existing CloudKit
sharing functionality.
iCloud Drive folder sharing
is built on top of CloudKit.
Let's see how you could go
about building something
similar in your own apps.
So, the data model here
represents a filesystem
hierarchy,
and so you would start off
with records of type "file"
and "folder,"
and you want to give users
the ability to easily share
any folder record
along with all of the records,
file or folder,
that are contained within it.
The way to represent this
hierarchical relationship
in CloudKit and leverage
it for sharing is to use
CKRecord.parent references
from child to parent records.
This makes
it so that CloudKit will
treat the resulting hierarchy
as a single shareable unit,
and so you'll want to go ahead
and add those references here.
This is very important
and what makes parent
references special in CloudKit.
Note that if you don't
plan to support sharing,
you don't need to use
parent references,
and any plain CKReference field
in your own schema will suffice.
With that set up,
folder sharing can now
be supported simply by
initializing a CKShare,
with the folder record as
a CKShare's root record.
Using the folder as
the root record means
that CloudKit will
automatically share
all records that are part
of the parent-reference based
hierarchy ultimately pointing
at that folder record.
This also
means that records added
or removed from this
hierarchy at a later point
are automatically shared
or unshared respectively.
So how is this simple folder
sharing model set up in code?
Continuing our example,
here are the two file records
along with the folder
record to be shared
in a custom zone
in the private database.
First, the parent
references are set on both
file records pointing
to the folder record,
and the file records
are then saved.
Note that it
is good practice to save
the parent references
as early as possible
in order to minimize
the number of records
that need to be modified
when the folder is being shared.
Then, all three records are
shared by initializing a CKShare
with our folder as the root
record,
and saving the CKShare
along with the folder record
in the private database.
Note that since the parent
references were previously
saved to the server,
only the root folder record
needs to be modified along
with the share at share-time.
And that's it, your app
is now sharing folder records
along with the records
underneath them.
CloudKit can support multiple
CKShares within the same zone,
as long as their record
hierarchies don't overlap.
Now, let's say instead
of a hierarchical folder
sharing model, you have records
representing a few distinct
types in your zone, and no
logical hierarchy between them.
In other words,
the zone is being treated as
a bucket of records,
and you want to quickly
get started with sharing
all of the records in it.
Ideally, you'd just be able
to mark an entire record zone as
"shared" without manipulating
any records within it.
Now, with zone sharing,
you can do just that.
So, let's set this up in code.
All you need to do is
to use the new initializer
for CKShare
that takes a record zone ID
for an existing zone
in the private database.
Once this new zone-wide
share record is saved,
all records that exist
in this zone on the server
are automatically shared,
and sharing new records
or unsharing records going
forward works by simply
adding or removing those
records from the zone.
The entire record zone can
be unshared at any point
by deleting
the zone-wide share record.
Let's dive a little
deeper into these new
zone-wide share records.
For convenience,
the zone-wide share record
always has
a well-known record name,
CKRecordNameZoneWideShare,
which can be used along
with the zone ID
to create
the full share record ID.
Zones using zone sharing
do not require any parent
references to be set up
between records in that zone.
Note that since zone sharing
only allows a single
share record per zone,
this flavor of sharing
cannot coexist
with hierarchical shares
within the same zone.
So, you can either have one
or more hierarchical shares
in a zone, or a single
zone-wide share record.
You can save zone-wide
shares in any non-default
record zone,
and these are also marked
with a new zone capability,
CKRecordZoneCapability
ZoneWideSharing.
All existing CloudKit sharing
mechanics past the creation
of the CKShare record remain
the same and are fully supported
for zone-wide shares,
with one exception.
Since there are no
longer any root-records
when using zone sharing,
related properties
on CKShareMetadata,
like hierarchicalRootRecordID
and rootRecord, will be nil
when accepting zone shares.
Similarly, when using
CKFetchShareMetadataOperation
to bootstrap a custom
share acceptance flow,
properties
"shouldFetchRootRecord"
and "rootRecordDesiredKeys"
will be ignored by the system
when fetching share metadata
for zone-wide shares.
So, there are now two
flavors of CloudKit sharing
available depending
upon your data model.
If your app's schema
logically forms hierarchies
and hierarchical trees make
sense as shareable units,
then continue to use CKRecord
parent references to represent
those hierarchies, and then
share their root records.
At Apple, we do this for Notes,
Reminders,
and iCloud Drive folder sharing
in a similar fashion
to that explored today.
And for all other cases,
you can now efficiently share
an entire record zone
simply by creating
a single zone-wide
share record
and take full advantage
of CloudKit sharing.
At Apple,
we already leverage zone sharing
for several features, like
HomeKit secure video sharing
and HomePod multiuser.
So today we explored how you
can start writing CloudKit code
in a new way using async/await
in Swift,
including enhancements
to the per-item progress
and error reporting APIs.
We talked about how you
can leverage encrypted fields
on your records
for sensitive user data,
taking advantage of Apple's
commitment to user privacy,
without rolling
your own cryptography.
And we learned about
a faster way to get started
with CloudKit sharing
when your data model
isn't hierarchical
with zone sharing.
There's some great new
documentation on these
features
and more available for you
on developer.apple.com,
so please
take a look.
There are many
related sessions
in the "Explore CloudKit"
collection
for you to check out
as well,
including one from Core Data,
introducing sharing
functionality
built on top of
CloudKit.
Thank you, and hope you have
a great WWDC.
[upbeat music]