[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Jer Noble: Hello, I'm Jer!
And I work on media playback
in WebKit and Safari
here at Apple.
People love watching
their favorite shows and movies
and listening
to their music together,
whether it’s with people
in the same room, next door,
or on the other side
of the world.
And now with GroupActivities,
it’s easier than ever to provide
a SharePlay experience
to your users,
wherever they are.
In this session,
we'll cover four topics.
An introduction to coordinated
playback in Safari;
how to prepare your iOS app to
work with SharePlay in Safari;
how to adopt the Media Session
API in your app's web page;
and a new web API
for coordinating playback
across multiple devices.
So let’s start by talking
a little bit about SharePlay
and Safari.
In the previous session,
you learned how to create
an amazing SharePlay experience
in your iPhone
and iPad applications
with GroupActivities.
And on macOS Monterey,
you can bring
that same experience --
along with your great iPhone
and iPad apps --
to Mac using Catalyst.
And if your application
has a companion website,
you can bring that same amazing
SharePlay experience
to your Mac Safari 15 users,
without requiring those users
to download your app
from the App Store.
And that’s what I’m going
to show you how to do
in this session.
I’ve been working
on an iPhone application
that lets you watch
movie trailers.
I’ve already added support
for GroupActivities to my app,
and that lets friends watch
movie trailers together
over FaceTime.
But my movie trailers app
also has a website.
And here’s how it should look
once I add support
for GroupActivities
in that web page as well.
I’m on a FaceTime call
with my friend Sam.
Sam loves
watching movie trailers,
so I’ve asked them
to help me test this new
Movie Trailers app.
When they start playing
a new trailer in that app
during our call,
I’ll be invited to watch that
trailer through a notification.
It will give me the option
to join the session in Safari.
When I click that notification,
Safari will be launched with
a URL for the shared content,
and when Sam starts
playing the trailer,
it will play here in Safari
at the same time.
I can pause, play, and even seek
the video here in Safari,
and everyone else in the session
will see those same commands
reflected in their local video
at the same time.
It's going to be really great!
So, what will it take to add
GroupActivities support
to the movie trailers website?
Before we take a look
under the hood of Safari --
at the new Web APIs
available in Safari 15 --
let's talk about how to get
your app ready to work
with Safari
through GroupActivities.
In order to join
a GroupActivities session
with Safari, a user
with your iPhone or iPad app
will need to create
a GroupSessionActivity
with a fallbackURL
that points to your website.
The fallbackURL must identify
not just your website,
but the specific content
to be played.
When a Watch Together invitation
is issued by an iPhone user
to a user on a Mac,
Safari will be launched
and asked to load the URL
that you provide
in GroupSessionActivity.
Once the fallbackURL
is loaded in Safari,
your site will need to implement
a few simple
but important Web APIs.
The first is Media Session.
Media Session is
a standard Web API
which allows your site
to tell the browser -- Safari --
more about the current state
of media playback
within your page.
Your site can tell the browser
the current play state,
the duration of your content.
It can provide artwork
for the current playback item.
It can even tell the browser
that the current content
is an advertisement
that can be skipped.
Once the Browser has all
this metadata available,
it can provide that metadata to
the rest of the operating system
and present it to your users
outside of the browser
window itself.
One place the operating system
displays that data
is within something
called "Now Playing."
Now Playing is a great way
for users to quickly see
and control the media
that they’re enjoying right now.
In iOS, users can access
Now Playing
from the Control Center
as well as from the Lock screen.
And now in macOS Monterey,
users can access Now Playing
directly from the menu bar.
And Safari will use
the information
provided through Media Session
to populate Now Playing
with your content’s title,
duration, play state, artwork,
and more.
Now Playing also allows users
to control playback
of what they’re listening to,
by showing the user a simple set
of playback controls.
Your site can register
with the Media Session
for specific actions to perform
when a user interacts
with Now Playing,
so that for example,
when a user taps
the Play button in Now Playing,
Safari can run
your site’s own action handler
to begin playback.
Media Session gives your site
complete control
over what metadata
to expose to the browser,
as well as control over how to
implement playback commands.
Need to do some set up
or preflighting
before beginning playback?
No problem.
With mediaSession’s
play action handler,
now you can.
If your site has previously
adopted Media Session,
you’re halfway done already.
But the movie trailers site
hasn’t adopted Media Session
yet, so let’s add support
for that now.
This site will want to add
actions for play,
pause, and seekto.
To do so, we’ll use
the mediaSession property
of navigator.
Let’s first add
an action handler for play.
We’ll call mediaSession.
setActionHandler(),
passing in the string play
and an inline function
that just calls play()
on our video element.
Then, we’ll do the same
for pause and seekto.
And to make sure
that we’re accurately
representing playback state
to the browser,
we’ll add event listeners
to our video element
and update mediaSession
when that state changes.
First, let’s add a function
called
updateMediaSessionState().
It will query the video element
to find out
if it’s playing or paused.
Then it will set mediaSession’s
playbackState property
to either the string
playing or paused,
depending on the video element’s
playback state.
Next, it will query
the video element’s duration,
playback rate,
and current time.
Then, using those values,
it will call mediaSession’s
setPositionState() function,
passing in those values
in the dictionary parameter.
Then, let’s add
an event listener
to detect when
those values change,
and call
updateMediaSessionState()
to update mediaSession
with those new values.
We’ll need an event listener
for playing,
pause, duration change,
rate change, and time change.
And last, because
the movie trailers website
has both a title string
and a URL for the title artwork,
we can set the Media Session’s
metadata property
to a new MediaMetadata object
containing those values.
So let’s try it out!
I’ll reload my page in Safari,
begin playing,
then click on the Now Playing
icon in the system menu.
And I see the title and artwork
in the Now Playing panel.
And when I tap the Pause button,
our pause action handler
is called and playback pauses.
Media Session provides
the building blocks
for a Watch Together experience
in a web page,
by providing a mechanism
for the browser to tell the page
it should start
or stop playback.
Now we’re ready move
onto the second part
of creating a cowatching
experience in our web page:
coordinating playback across
every device in the session.
To do so, we’ve extended
Media Session
by adding a new property
on it called "Coordinator."
Your page will use
Media Session's Coordinator
to inform every other user in
the session of the page’s intent
to begin or pause playback,
to seek to a specific point
in the media’s timeline,
or to move to the next item
in a playlist.
The Coordinator will
communicate those intents
with all the other devices
in the session
and listen for changes to every
other device's play state,
resolve conflicts,
and wait for everyone
to be ready to begin playback.
And when everyone is ready,
the Coordinator will use the
Media Session action handlers
we added earlier
to start playback
along all the other users
in the session.
And if another user pauses
playback for whatever reason,
the Coordinator will call
your Media Session’s
pause action handler.
That said, I’d like to point out
a few caveats.
The Coordinator interface
is an experimental web API;
it has yet to go
through standardization,
and while that process
will likely improve this API,
some aspects
of the API may change.
To find out more,
please watch the W3C’s
Media Session GitHub page.
This API is currently
only implemented in Safari,
though the GroupActivities
framework,
which Safari uses
to implement the Coordinator,
can -- and we hope will -- be
adopted by other Mac browsers.
And the final caveat is
that while your users can join
an existing session in Safari,
a GroupSession currently
must be initiated
from an iPhone, iPad,
or macOS application.
So let’s add support
for the Coordinator now.
The first thing I’d like to do
is join the session
once it becomes available.
So I’m going to add a
coordinatorchange event listener
to mediaSession.
In the handler, if there’s
a non-null coordinator property
on mediaSession,
I’ll call its join() function.
I’d also like to add an icon
to my controls
to show that we’re playing back
in a session.
So in the handler, I’ll either
show or hide the icon,
based on whether
there’s a coordinator property
on mediaSession.
I’m also going to hook up a
click event listener to the icon
to call leave()
on the coordinator.
Next, I’m going to modify
the event handlers
for my custom controls
to check for the presence of a
coordinator, and if we have one,
call the appropriate
coordinator function instead.
I’ll add one for my Play button,
and then for my Pause button,
and also for timeline slider.
And let’s see it in action!
I’ve got an invite here
from my friend Sam,
and I’m going to accept it.
My page loads
to the same content
that Sam is watching
on their iPhone.
And when I click the Play
button, both Sam's iPhone
and my web page begin playing
simultaneously.
>> Allie Fox: The way
we get there is an adventure.
[SUSPENSEFUL MUSIC]
Dina: I'm scared.
Allie: If it didn't feel
that way,
it wouldn't be an adventure.
♪ <<
That was great.
Now that the trailer's ended,
Sam uses the iPhone
to scrub back to the beginning.
We think that users are going
to love watching or listening
to their favorite content
together in your applications,
whether it’s on their iPhone,
iPad, Apple TV,
or in Safari running
on their Mac.
And we hope you can now bring
that experience
to all of your users,
wherever they are.
For more information
about GroupActivities APIs,
start with the sessions
"Coordinate media playback
with Group Activities"
and "Design
for Group Activities."
If you’re interested in
the other new web APIs
that will be available
in Safari 15,
make sure to check out
the session,
"Develop advanced web content."
Thanks for coming and enjoy
the rest of your WWDC21.
♪