[upbeat music]
[Tom] Hi, I'm Tom,
and I'd like to welcome you
to "SF Symbols in UIKit
and AppKit."
Today I'm going to take you on
a tour of how to implement
the new features
of SF Symbols in your app.
First, we're gonna go over
the different color modes
and how to use them.
Then, we'll talk about
how to combine configurations
to get the effects
that you want.
And finally,
we're going to explore using
these colored symbols
in attributed strings.
You will see examples that apply
both to AppKit and UIKit.
The new APIs are identical
for both frameworks,
so what applies to one,
also applies to the other,
with the exception of some
framework-specific nuances.
The new features center around
adding colors to SF Symbols.
While AppKit added multicolor
symbols in macOS 11,
UIKit is adding them
in iOS 15.
For this year's releases,
additional
color rendering modes
for SF Symbols are being added.
And to be clear, these rendering
modes work on all platforms.
In order to support the new
rendering modes,
symbols
now have different layers,
each having a different color.
These layers
are defined in a hierarchy,
meaning that one layer
is more prominent than another.
This means we've got
three layers: primary,
secondary, and tertiary.
On iOS, symbols
require template mode
for the new rendering modes
to take effect.
On macOS,
applying the new configurations
will automatically set
the correct template mode.
And if you're new to SF Symbols,
check out
"Introducing SF Symbols"
from WWDC19.
The first rendering mode
we're going to look at
are monochrome symbols.
Here's a Voicemail app.
In this UI,
a couple symbols are being used.
There's one monochrome symbol,
and a few other symbols
using a different color mode.
But let's focus on
the monochrome symbol first,
and we'll come back
to the others later.
As the name implies,
a monochrome symbol
only has one color:
usually the tint
or accent color of the view.
And in order to accomplish this
result,
we create a new symbol
image,
assign it to the image view,
and set a tint
or accent color to configure
the color of the symbol.
And nothing has changed here:
we don't need
any extra configuration
to render a monochrome symbol,
as it is the default behavior.
So, monochrome was
the only rendering mode
before iOS 15 and macOS 11.
To specify a color, all we
have to do is set the tint
or accent color on the image
view, and that's it.
Now that we have
the previously-existing
monochrome mode out of the way,
we can talk about a new mode:
hierarchical color symbols.
A good example of hierarchical
symbols on a Mac
are the icons used
in Control Center.
There are a few places
where symbols are being used
in Control Center, but let's
zoom in on the Display section.
There are a few symbols
being used here:
the row of toggle buttons
in the center,
and the icons in the list
of devices.
The device symbols
are tinted differently
than the toggle buttons
above them,
and these are
hierarchically-colored symbols.
The hierarchical color mode
uses the layer hierarchy of a
symbol to color each layer,
and the provided color is
used as the primary layer color.
The secondary and tertiary
layers
get variations
of the primary color
with progressively
reduced opacity.
You specify the color mode
through a new type
of symbol configuration,
which works exactly like
the existing types
of symbol configurations.
And by setting the symbol
configuration of an imageView
to this type of configuration,
the symbol will be displayed as
a hierarchical color symbol.
The color scheme
of a hierarchical color symbol
is based on one color,
with the other colors
derived from that one color
by reducing opacity.
The layer hierarchy
is important here.
If one layer is missing,
the associated derived
color will not be used.
There's also a third color
rendering mode: palette.
As we will discover,
it's much like hierarchical
color rendering mode,
but also different.
Let's go back to our
Voicemail example.
The three buttons on the right
each have multiple colors,
and each have different colors.
We're going to build these
buttons one step at a time.
First, we're gonna initialize
our buttons
with the desired images.
We're using a new button
configuration for this.
But these plain images
isn't what we want at all.
The images should have
a circle shape and be filled in.
We used to be able
to do this by appending
the desired modifiers
to the symbol name,
but now there's a better way:
image variants.
As the name implies,
when using image variants,
you can request a different
variant of an image
without manually changing
the name.
First, let's turn our
images into circles.
Then, we'll add a nice fill
to those circles.
Since we
are specifying the variants
on the button container view,
those variants are
applied to all the images
in all the buttons.
If an image
doesn't have that variant,
the originally-specified
image will be used.
The variant specification
will propagate down
the view hierarchy,
and the image view
in that hierarchy will pick them
up to do their magic.
Now that we have the shape out
of the way,
how do we specify the colors
for each of these symbols?
Well, we can create a new type
of symbol configuration,
one that specifies
a palette of colors.
These colors are applied
to the layer hierarchy
similar to the hierarchical
color configuration.
But we're using colors
here that are specified
explicitly versus
using derived colors.
And we're also using
a new type of color
in the list of palette
colors: tint color.
This means that the view
will automatically
apply its tint color
to the appropriate layer.
And for the next button,
we do exactly as before.
Load the base image, build the
right color configuration,
and apply them
to the button configuration.
And in this case, it looks
exactly the same as before,
but there's a catch here,
and I'll explain that later.
And the same scenario also works
for the last button,
but just with different colors.
And like before,
you might wonder why
we explicitly have
to specify white here.
Couldn't we just use
a monochrome symbol
and tint them correctly?
The answer is no, we can't,
and this is the catch
I mentioned before.
Our designer specified
that the inner parts
of these symbols
should always be white.
And up until now,
we would've gotten
the correct result
by accident,
even when using
monochrome symbols.
Why?
We were in light mode.
But when we switch to dark mode,
monochrome symbols do not
give us the desired results.
This is because the monochrome
versions
use knockouts
for the inner parts,
and so the background
bleeds through the gaps.
Now, by using
a palette rendering mode,
we make sure
these buttons appear correctly
for different
user interface styles.
I mentioned a new color
before: tintColor.
This is a new dynamic
color in UIKit that will
resolve to the tint color
of the view it is used in.
This is especially handy when
specifying symbol layer colors,
but you can also use
this color
everywhere where you
can use any other color.
However,
keep in mind that the rules
around dynamic colors
still apply.
See "Implementing dark
mode on iOS" session
of WWDC19 to learn more about
how dynamic colors work.
Some symbols
only have two layers.
For instance,
there's a bunch of symbols
that are missing
a secondary layer.
How do we handle palette
mode for these kinds of symbols?
A good example of these
are the device symbols,
which only have a primary
layer and a tertiary layer.
How do we color this iPad symbol
with two layer colors?
Since symbols can have
up to three layers,
you can just specify three
colors, one for each layer.
In this case,
the secondary color is not used
because the layer isn't there.
However,
there's another way to do this
for symbols
with only two layers.
For those symbols,
we can specify just two colors
in your configuration,
and the colors will be
applied to the available
layers in sequence.
The former method
allows for consistency on how
to specify palette colors
for related symbols
with a mixed number of layers,
because the colors directly
map to the correct layer.
The latter method is
a convenience for when
you know for sure
that the symbol only has
two layers.
The palette configuration
specifies an explicit
set of colors that are
applied to the layer
hierarchy of the symbol.
Unlike the hierarchical
rendering mode,
the palette rendering mode
doesn't create derived colors.
And similar
to hierarchical rendering mode,
the hierarchy level of each
symbol layer is important.
There's
also a convenient solution
for symbols
with less than three layers.
This brings us to the last color
rendering mode: multicolor.
Like I mentioned before,
this color mode
was added to AppKit
and SwiftUI last year
but is introduced
to UIKit this year.
Some of these categories have
images with multiple colors.
These are multicolor symbols.
Let's see
how we would implement this.
First of all, we need to load
the images for each cell.
For now,
these are regular symbols,
and we get
the monochrome mode by default.
Then we need to indicate
that we want multicolor symbols.
We do this
by creating a configuration
requesting the multicolor
variant of a symbol
and assigning that configuration
to the image view.
But one icon didn't change:
its symbol does not
support multicolor.
So, how do you figure out
which symbols support
multicolor or not?
An easy way to find out is
to use the SF Symbols app.
Search for the symbol,
then use the inspector to see
which color rendering modes
the symbol supports.
For instance, our flame
symbol only supports monochrome.
But the lung symbol supports
all four color rendering modes.
Additionally, you can also play
with the color mapping
for each layer here,
in order to get a better feel
of how the symbol would appear
without having
to write one line of code.
Let's go back to our example.
So, since not all of these
symbols support multicolor,
we need to manually set
the tintColor to the right value
in order for the symbol
to display correctly.
Some multicolor symbols
have a tint layer,
and they will be
affected by the tint
or accent color of the view.
Symbols without such layer
won't be affected.
In our example, none of them do,
so everything remains as is.
As you might have guessed from
the name of the configuration,
the multicolor configuration
indicates
a preference for a multicolor
rendering of a symbol.
As I mentioned before,
not all symbols
have a multicolor variant.
You can combine
a multicolor configuration
with one of the other
color configurations,
but more on that later.
And the result is
a configuration that supports
two color modes: multicolor
when it is available,
and the other color mode
otherwise.
Note that combining hierarchical
mode and palette mode
will result
in the last-specified mode,
as they are mutually exclusive.
If, in turn, that color mode
is not supported,
the system uses monochrome mode.
So, multicolor symbols
have a fixed set of colors
which aren't modifiable in code.
Additionally,
some symbols have a layer
that will be rendered using
the tint or accent color.
And you don't have anything
to do in order for this to work.
The symbol picks up
the right tint or accent color
from its imageview
when it is displayed.
Now, we've covered
all four modes
and how to use them
in your code.
But can we do the same
in Interface Builder?
Fortunately, the answer is yes.
Xcode has added similar
functionality to configure
color rendering modes
right from the IDE.
Here we have Xcode Open
displaying
a storyboard
for the Planets app.
The ImageView UI
has been expanded
to enable specifying
a color rendering mode.
And the resulting color
configuration is also combinable
with the previously-existing
configurations.
If you want to learn more
about all these new features
in Interface Builder,
check out this year's
"Build interfaces with style."
Now that we have talked about
all these different color modes,
how can we combine them
with other configurations
to get more complex effects?
Luckily, it's not that hard.
Let's check out another example,
this time
from the Shortcuts app.
The icons of each
of the actions are quite large,
but they also appear to have
a hierarchical color
rendering mode.
So, we need two configurations:
one for specifying a point size,
and one for specifying
a color configuration.
But we can only apply one.
How do we combine them?
Turns out there's
an easy way to do this.
There's a method to combine
two configurations,
resulting in a configuration
that has the elements
of both configurations.
In the example here,
we create two configurations:
one
for specifying a point size,
and another one for specifying
a hierarchical color.
We then combine them
using the applying methods
to create a final configuration.
And that configuration is
applied on the image view
displaying the image,
giving us the desired result.
Note that this mechanism
is not limited to color
configurations only.
You can also use this
with the other types
of configurations.
For instance, combining text,
style, and weight.
Now we know how to combine
different configurations.
We've got one topic left:
using color symbols
in attributed strings.
Take this last example.
This is an imaginary app
that lists various hotels
and information
about their available rooms.
There's
a few places where symbols
are combined with text.
But let's focus on
the room amenities
and how we would
implement this text.
It's fairly simple,
but a bit elaborate.
We have to build an attributed
string with an image attachment.
First, we load the image, using
the correct color configuration.
In this case,
we're using a hierarchical
color configuration.
We use this image to create
a text attachment,
and then we use
that attachment
to complete
our attributed string.
And this is then repeated
for all the available amenities.
On the label
displaying the text,
we also
specify the correct font
and the same text color
as we used
for the hierarchical
color configurations.
Monochrome symbols pick up
the text color automatically,
but for symbols with a color
configuration,
we have to specify
the colors explicitly.
And color symbols do
pick up the font sizes
specified in the string,
just like monochrome symbols.
After these steps,
we have the result that we want:
a label with the right content,
color, and size,
thanks to the integration of
symbols in attributed strings.
We introduced three new color
modes for SF Symbols
in addition to the existing one,
and we explained
how to use them in your app.
Symbols are a great way to add
high-quality images to your app.
Colored symbols expand on that,
allowing
for even more possibilities.
If you enjoyed this session,
be sure to check out
a few related sessions.
Watch "What's new in
SF Symbols"
for a primer on the
new capabilities.
Or take a look at
"SF Symbols in SwiftUI"
to see how you can use
the new symbols in SwiftUI.
Thanks for watching,
and now go build
amazing apps!
[upbeat music]