Ready for your day three recap?
[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
Here we go.
♪ "Better Days (Instrumental)"
by DARKMINDS ♪
We discovered how to bring
real-world objects
into augmented reality.
Ari showed us how to design
incredible actions
and shortcuts for our apps.
- You open your app up
to a world of Shortcuts
possibilities.
- While Yusef helped us
add some style
to our user interfaces.
- This makes the label
wrap around
to as many lines as needed.
- Check out
the new buttons system.
Pop-ups, accessible design,
and so much more!
And hey, speaking of,
did you catch Apple engineers
and designers as they shared
how we built Apple Watch
with accessibility in mind?
- I mean, we're talking about
real sci-fi kind of things
right now.
- Amazing!
Meanwhile, we explored how
to turn people into superheroes
with Vision.
- This is cool.
- Can't wait to try that.
We discovered how to move
beyond passwords
with iCloud Keychain
and Passkeys.
- This is the first step
of a multiyear effort
in replacing passwords.
- Phew.
I'm gonna feel so secure.
And we learned how you can
create interactive,
memorable experiences
to onboard people into your app.
And there's so much more
amazing stuff on the way.
♪
[LAUGHTER]
Wow, that was a trip!
♪