[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Tommy Pauly: Hi,
I'm Tommy Pauly,
and along with my colleague,
Delziel,
I'll be giving you
an introduction
to an exciting new feature
in internet privacy.
iCloud Private Relay
is a new service
that prevents
networks and servers
from monitoring user activity
across the internet.
And it's available as part of
every iCloud+ subscription.
Private Relay
not only protects users
when they're browsing the web,
but also adds protection
to the traffic
generated by your app
to make sure
you're not unintentionally
leaking user information
or exposing users
to security attacks.
Today, you'll learn
what iCloud Private Relay is
and how it affects your app;
how to ensure that your app
works great with Private Relay;
how to prepare
your websites and servers;
and, lastly,
how to manage a network
and monitor your traffic
when Private Relay is enabled.
Let's get started.
Private Relay is
built into iOS and macOS,
so you don't need to do anything
to adopt it from your app.
It's also important
to understand
that it won't always
be affecting your app.
It will only apply when a user
is an iCloud+ subscriber
and has Private Relay enabled.
You're probably wondering,
What does it actually do?
Here's how things currently work
without Private Relay.
When someone
accesses the internet,
anyone on their local network
can see the names
of all of the websites
they access
based on inspecting DNS queries.
This information can be used
to fingerprint a user
and build a history of
their activity over time.
No one should be able
to silently collect
all of this information,
whether it's
a public Wi-Fi operator,
another user on the network,
or an internet service provider.
When connections reach
the servers that run websites,
those servers can see
the user's IP address.
This allows the servers
to determine user location
without explicit permission.
Even worse, the servers are able
to fingerprint user identity
and recognize users
across different websites,
even when tools like Intelligent
Tracking Prevention in Safari
are preventing correlation
via cookies.
These are big problems
for user privacy,
and in order to fix them,
we need a new approach
that has privacy built in
by design.
iCloud Private Relay
adds multiple secure proxies
to help route user traffic
and keep it private.
The proxies are run
by separate entities.
One is Apple,
and one is a content provider.
Now, when someone
accesses the internet,
only the client IP address
is visible
to both the network provider
and to the first proxy.
The second proxy only sees
the name the user is requesting
and uses that to build
the connection to the server.
It is critical to note
that no one in this chain --
not even Apple --
can see both
the client IP address
and what the user is accessing.
The opportunities
for fingerprinting
have been removed.
This is privacy by design.
Private Relay uses
the latest transport protocols
and privacy-preserving
authentication
to ensure that every transaction
is both secure and fast.
You can learn more
about this technology
in the “Apple's privacy pillars
in focus” session.
Private Relay is
focused on securing
the most sensitive traffic
on the system
without impacting
user experience.
In iOS 15 and macOS 12,
Private Relay will apply
to all web browsing in Safari,
all DNS name resolution queries,
and a small subset of traffic
from apps.
Specifically, this will include
all insecure HTTP traffic,
such as TCP port 80.
If your app provides
a content filter
or a parental controls filter,
it will still see traffic before
it goes through Private Relay,
so you can apply your filters
just as before.
You can learn more about this
in the "Meet the Screen Time
API" session.
Not all networking
done by your app
occurs over the public internet,
so there are several categories
of traffic
that are not affected
by Private Relay.
Any connections your app makes
over the local network
or to private domain names
will be unaffected.
Similarly, if your app provides
a network extension
to add VPN
or app-proxying capabilities,
your extension
won't use Private Relay
and neither will app traffic
that uses your extension.
Traffic that uses a proxy
is also exempt.
Next, let's cover
what you need to do
to make sure your app is ready
to work well with Private Relay.
The great news is that
for almost every app,
you don't need to do
anything new!
Private Relay will just work.
However, there are some best
practices you should know about.
Private Relay works
no matter what networking API
you're using.
For several years, we've
recommended that your apps use
modern APIs such as
URLSession and NWConnection.
Now, you have one more reason
to adopt them
throughout your apps.
These APIs provide you
the best tools
to understand how Private Relay
is applying to your traffic.
If you use URLSession,
you can use
the Network Xcode Instrument
to inspect your tasks,
even when they are going through
Private Relay.
You can learn more
about how to do this
in the "Analyze HTTP traffic
in Instruments" session.
And you can use metrics APIs
in both
URLSession and Network.framework
to understand when your
connections use Private Relay.
In TaskTransactionMetrics,
you can check to see
if your task used a proxy.
In NWConnection's
EstablishmentReport,
you can also inspect the timings
of DNS name resolution
and each stage of the proxied
connection establishment.
Private Relay takes a big step
towards making unencrypted
and insecure HTTP connections
a thing of the past.
You can join in this effort too!
If you're still using
insecure HTTP --
that's connections
on TCP port 80 --
now is the time to change.
When Private Relay is enabled,
these insecure connections
will be proxied,
which protects them from
attackers on a local network
between the client
and the proxy.
However, it’s still best
to have your connections
be secure end to end
for all users.
To do this, make sure
your server supports TLS
and change your URLs
from http:// to https://.
Your app may have exceptions
for App Transport Security
to allow insecure traffic.
You can look at this list
to audit what insecure traffic
your app uses
and remove these exceptions.
If your app provides
functionality based on location,
this is also a great time
to make sure you're using
APIs from Core Location
instead of relying on servers
inferring location
from IP addresses.
IP address geolocation is often
unreliable and inaccurate.
Core Location allows you
to specify
the precision of the location
you need
and is based on
explicit user permission.
You can learn more about
the latest enhancements
to location access
in the “Apple's privacy pillars
in focus” session.
Once you've made sure your app
is ready for Private Relay,
try it out!
Sign into an iPhone,
iPad, or Mac
with an iCloud+ subscription,
and make sure Private Relay
is enabled
in the iCloud section
of the Settings app
or in System Preferences.
You can provide feedback
with the tag
"iCloud Private Relay"
in the feedback app.
Now I'll hand it off
to my colleague, Delziel.
Delziel Fernandes:
Thanks, Tommy.
Hi, I'm Delziel Fernandes,
and I'll be talking about
how to prepare your server
and manage your network
with Private Relay.
If you have servers
that your app relies on,
or that user access in Safari,
there are a few things you can
do to prepare for Private Relay.
Your servers can identify
connections that come in
using Private Relay
by recognizing
the proxy IP addresses.
These proxy IP addresses
may be shared by many users
within a region.
Each address is mapped
to a specific city or region.
So if you apply the correct
geo IP mapping databases,
your servers will still have
the relevant information.
Private Relay guarantees
that users can't use the system
to pretend to be
from a different region,
so you can continue to enforce
region-based
access restrictions.
Details about
the proxy IP addresses
will be available as an article
associated with this session.
Now let's take a look
at network connections
from devices using
Private Relay.
When a device tries
to access a server,
it first sets up a network
connection to the ingress proxy.
This connection is set up
using an IP address
assigned by
the network provider.
The device then uses
the ingress proxy
to forward network requests
to the egress proxy
using the ingress proxy
IP address.
The egress proxy
then forwards these requests
to the destination servers
by choosing an IP address
that maps to the device's
city or region.
In general,
your servers and websites
should stop solely relying
on client IP address
to determine user location
or identity.
If you need location access,
consider requesting
the user's location explicitly,
and only at the granularity
you need.
If you need to identify users,
request a login or some other
form of explicit identification
rather than assuming that the IP
address is tied to the identity.
Last, let's cover some tips
for managing your network
when Private Relay is in use.
If you're running a packet trace
on your local network
when Private Relay is in use,
you'll see
some new traffic patterns.
You'll now see a lot more
traffic running on UDP port 443.
This is QUIC --
or HTTP/3 --
traffic that's being used
to communicate
with the Private Relay proxy.
You can make sure
your traffic works well
by allowing UDP port 443
on your network
and by making sure your routers
or Network Address Translators
are tuned to handle it well.
You'll also see fewer cleartext
UDP DNS queries on your network.
Let's go over a typical
network connection request
from a device when
Private Relay is not in use.
When a device tries
to access a server,
it first sends a DNS query
for the hostname of the server.
Once the hostname is resolved
to an IP address,
the device then connects
to the IP address of the server
using a transport protocol
like TCP.
The device then performs
a TCP three-way handshake
with the server
followed by a TLS exchange
to set up a secure connection
with the server.
But as you can see,
without Private Relay,
the hostname of the server
and the IP address of the device
connecting to the server
are visible by simply observing
packets on the network.
With Private Relay,
the device first sets up a
connection to the ingress Proxy
using QUIC, or HTTP/3.
In packet captures,
you will notice UDP packets
sent to port 443
of the ingress proxy.
Once the network connection
is established
to the ingress proxy,
access to a server is secured
within the connection
to the ingress proxy.
On the server end,
there is no change in protocol.
The TCP/TLS exchange
is similar to traffic
without Private Relay.
The only difference
is that the server sees
the incoming connection
from a proxy IP address
instead of a device's
IP address.
Most networks don't need
to audit or monitor
all user traffic.
However, if you run
an enterprise or school network,
your network may have policies
that require intercepting
all traffic.
To support this use case,
you can block the hostname
of the iCloud Private Relay
proxy server.
Then, when a device connects
to your network,
the user will receive a prompt
indicating that Private Relay
is blocked
on the current network.
They can then choose to either
disable Private Relay
for that network
or switch networks.
Information about the proxy
hostname will be available
as an article
associated with this session.
For parental controls,
the best solution is to use
content filter APIs
provided by
NetworkExtension framework.
This allows traffic
to be audited on device
even when Private Relay
is enabled.
For more information
on content Filter APIs,
watch "Meet the Screen Time API"
and "Network extension
for the modern Mac" sessions.
To wrap things up,
use modern secure networking
APIs like URLSession
in your apps;
test your apps
with Private Relay;
and make sure your servers
and websites work well
when they receive connections
routed through Private Relay.
Thanks for watching, everyone!
♪