[music]
[Anubhav]
Hi, my name is Anubhav,
and I'm an engineer
on the OS Performance Team.
Today, I'm excited to share how
you can understand
and eliminate hangs
from your application.
We'll break this talk into four sections,
starting with understanding,
"what is a hang?"
We'll then talk about
the common causes for hangs
and what to look out for when developing.
After that, we'll discuss tools
you can use to monitor and diagnose hangs.
Finally, we will learn common
strategies to eliminate hangs,
and how to choose which ones
work best for your app.
Let's jump right in.
Let's take a look at my new recipe app,
Desserted,
an application
that shows you how to make
my favorite drinks and desserts.
This Mango Tango smoothie looks great.
I'll tap on it to see how it's made.
Hmm.
Looks like nothing is happening.
Wow. That took a lot longer than expected.
The app was just stuck
and would not accept any of my touches
for a few seconds.
This experience can be described as
"laggy," "slow," or "stuck."
These are
not words that me, or anyone else,
wants used to describe their app.
At Apple, we call this
period of unresponsiveness, a "hang."
To understand a hang,
and what was happening in Desserted,
we must first understand
what an app's main runloop is.
The main runloop is a loop
your application's main thread enters
to run event handlers
in response to incoming events,
primarily user interactions.
When a user interacts with an app,
the runloop receives the event,
processes it,
and then updates the UI, if required.
This all happens in one turn
of the runloop, and on the main thread.
This process repeats for each user input.
This is how the main thread would
look like with one turn of the runloop.
If processing the event takes a long time,
there'll be a delay
between the user input and any UI update.
To make matters worse,
events are buffered
and cannot be handled by
the main thread during a hang.
If I interact with an app during a hang,
that event is not handled
until the current hang first terminates…
…compounding hangs, one on top of another.
In general, a delay of over
one second will always look like a hang,
though a shorter
delay can be perceived as one.
For example, a half-second delay
while scrolling is jarring,
but the same delay is far less
noticeable when entering a view.
By eliminating hangs, your apps
will be snappy, quick, and responsive.
Now that we know a hang is,
let's look into what commonly causes them.
A hang occurs when there's too
much work being done on the main thread.
To determine exactly what that work is,
we have to look at what the main thread
is doing while processing the event.
This time can be split into two cases.
Either the main thread
itself is busy doing work--
this can be a single long
task or many short ones--
or the main thread is blocked
by another thread or system resource.
Let's start by looking at common causes
for the main thread being busy.
Proactively doing work is doing
more than whats necessary to update UI,
keeping the main thread busy for longer.
In Desserted,
the Recipe View only displays image tiles
for four out of
the many ingredient images.
If the main thread were to load
all ingredient images at once,
it would spend time reading, preparing,
and compositing each and every image.
Most of the work that's happening
won't even affect what a user sees.
The view only shows four images,
and only those four need
to be immediately generated.
Another cause for hangs is performing
irrelevant work on the main thread.
Note that the main thread services blocks
from the main dispatch queue,
but it can also service blocks
from other queues via dispatch sync.
Anytime a queue dispatch
syncs onto another queue,
all pending blocks on the other queue have
to execute before the newly enqueued one.
Consider an app with a low
priority serial dispatch queue,
perhaps a maintenance queue.
If the main thread dispatch
synced a block onto the maintenanceQueue,
it would have
to wait for all pending blocks
on that queue to execute
before the enqueued block runs.
Only a fraction of time was spent
doing work meant for the main thread.
Similarly, if a block is dispatched
onto the main queue from another queue,
that block has
to execute on the main thread.
This holds even if the block is
enqueued via a dispatch async.
One more cause for hangs
is using suboptimal API.
There are many ways to accomplish a task.
Be sure to read API docs so you can
use the best one for the task at hand.
Desserted adds rounded corners
to all images in the recipe view,
though doing so also adds
latency when entering this view.
To add rounded corners,
Desserted uses a bitmap-based
graphics context
to convert an image to a bitmap,
apply a UIBezier path on that bitmap,
then convert that bitmap back to an image.
This set of operations is CPU intensive,
uses lots of memory,
and can take a long time.
This is because the wrong hardware
is being used for the job.
Instead of using the CPU,
I should leverage the GPU.
By using CoreAnimation methods on a layer,
adding rounded corners
is easy and instant.
This is just one example of using
the wrong API for the job at hand.
Now that we've looked into some
common reasons the main thread
of an app can be busy,
let's investigate why it can be blocked.
Synchronous APIs block execution from
the time they're called to the time they return.
These should not be used on the main
thread if the API does a lot of work
or has the potential to block
for a long period of time.
Apart from delays, these also
add an additional point of failure.
One such case is if
the main thread of an app
makes synchronous requests to the network.
For those with 5G,
there may not be any delay.
For those with slower network speeds,
this may take longer.
And for those with very bad signal,
this may hang indefinitely.
There's no guarantee
on how long this can take,
which is why such synchronous operations
should be avoided on the main thread.
Another way to block the main
thread is on a system resource,
as these are often constrained.
File I/O is one of the most commonly used,
and contended, system resources.
Latencies are dependent on hardware,
and other reads and writes happening
at the same time, things that can
be beyond the app's control.
So, apps need to do what
they can to defend against hangs
by avoiding I/O on the main thread.
Data stores, which do not support
concurrency, are especially problematic.
If the main thread attempts to read from
one while writes are already occurring,
that read would be pushed out until all
writers complete, which may be unbounded.
Another cause
for hangs is synchronization.
By definition, synchronization primitives
can block execution,
so it is important to limit,
and be cautious of,
synchronizing from the main thread.
The thread it synchronizes with
can take a long time
to release an implicit or explicit lock.
These are some common primitives to look
out for,
including the @synchronized directive,
dispatch sync,
os unfair lock, and posix locks.
Specifically, be aware of semaphore use,
as they do not propagate priority
and can lengthen a hang due to preemption.
A common anti-pattern is when
trying to make asynchronous API
act synchronous
by waiting on a semaphore.
This should always be
avoided on the main thread.
One more way to block the main thread
is by doing work, IPC,
or using system resources
to fetch the value of something
which doesn't change often.
In Desserted,
there's an icon for a social feature,
which is only shown if I have
added a contact as a friend.
Querying all contacts on every
tap into this view is one way to check,
though it adds unnecessary overhead
and delays,
since the main thread
blocks on frameworks,
which are performing
expensive operations under the hood.
Furthermore, the value I'm fetching
does not change often,
so querying this frequently is unnecessary
and adds burden on system resources.
The state of system resources,
such as CPU, memory, and storage
play a large part in when hangs occur.
Different hardware and device conditions
in the field mean real world scenarios
will be significantly different than those
encountered while testing on desk.
It is important you do what
you can to defend against these cases
by having robust tests
and using the oldest-supported hardware
as a benchmark.
The high-level cause for hangs
is too much work being done on,
or on behalf of, the main thread.
To ensure performance,
it's important the main thread
of your application focuses
on what's necessary to update UI.
Now that you know common causes for hangs,
let's talk about some helpful tools
you can use to monitor
and triage hangs in your app,
both during development and production.
In order to triage a hang, you would want
to know what your app is doing
during that time.
The time profiler instrument
lets you do that
by showing your application’s
callstacks over time,
indicating exactly what's executing.
The system trace instrument adds
more context with data on system calls,
VM faults, I/O, as well as inter
and intra-process interactions.
For more information, check out the
"System Trace in Depth" talk from 2016.
Now, I'll use the time profiler
and system trace instruments
to find what's causing Desserted to hang.
After taking a trace of the hang, here's
how it looks like opened in Instruments.
In the system trace output,
the red line indicates system calls,
the purple graph
indicates virtual memory faults,
and the horizontal blue bar indicates
the main thread is busy doing work.
The next step is to see what this work is.
The time profiler
allows you to do just that.
It presents a call tree
by aggregating main-thread callstacks
for the duration of the 4.7 second hang.
The highlighted portion of the tree
illustrates that 4.6 seconds of this hang
was due to a loadAllMessages
method in the Recipe View.
This pattern looks familiar.
Desserted might be loading
in more images than needed.
Once your application has shipped,
you can use MetricKit
to collect call trees for hangs
hit in the field.
This enables you to prioritize fixes
based on which issues customers
are most commonly hitting.
To learn how to use MetricKit for hangs,
check out the "What's new
in MetricKit" talk from 2020.
I've shipped Desserted and have
some hang reports from MetricKit.
Let's look at one of them to see if
it's similar to the hang we just triaged.
MetricKit returns a call tree
by aggregating callstacks
taken during a hang.
This tree format is similar
to what the time profiler presents.
The highlighted portion indicates
this hang is different
from the one we just
investigated with Instruments.
This one is due
to a new social feature I added,
which blocks on a dispatch
queue querying contacts.
Without MetricKit,
I may not have found this issue,
and it would still persist in the field.
When fixing hangs,
it is important to baseline
and quantify the performance of your app.
The Xcode organizer does this
by showing performance metrics,
including a chart displaying
hang rate per app version.
This is especially helpful
when triaging regressions.
Check out these two talks for more
information on the Xcode Organizer.
Now, let's go over some common strategies
you can use to fix hangs in your app.
Each of these strategies can
address multiple causes for hangs.
In order to know
which fix is best for your app,
you will need to look at
their side affects and tradeoffs.
To eliminate and defend against hangs,
reduce the amount
of work done on the main thread.
This can be done in two ways.
The first is to optimize
the work already being done
on the main thread
to reduce execution time.
The second is to move work off the main
thread in a non-blocking manner
to keep it responsive.
Let's start by looking at ways
to reduce main thread execution,
starting with caching.
Caches are a great way to quickly
access frequently used assets
or previously queried values.
They're often an in-memory store,
but can be persisted to disk,
if needed across multiple app invocations.
Formatted assets that can be needed later,
like ingredient image tiles in Desserted,
are great candidates for caching,
since it's expensive to create
these assets every time they're needed.
By caching these in an NSCache,
the overhead of generating assets
is replaced by a quick memory read.
This would eliminate the hang
we looked at in Instruments.
It is important to have an accurate cache
invalidation mechanism to strike a balance
between having stale data
and constantly updating a cache.
This work should happen asynchronously
on a secondary dispatch queue
to keep the main thread responsive
to events.
Notification observers are another way
to reduce work on the main thread.
They allow your app to react
to changes in a value or state,
without having to do expensive,
on-demand computation.
Any class can post notifications,
even your own.
To find notifications from a specific
class, check its API documentation.
To find all observable
system notifications,
check out the Apple developer
documentation page
for NSNotification.Name.
A great candidate for this is
the social feature in Desserted.
By registering an observer for the
abDatabaseChangedExternally notification,
the main thread no longer has to wait
on querying contacts.
Once a notification comes in,
the observer is invoked.
In this case,
it'll be updating a cached value.
To keep the main thread responsive,
these updates should be asynchronous,
which is achieved by dispatch_asyncing
the handler to another queue.
Now, I provide the same feature as before,
but without the hang we saw
in the MetricKit log.
Another way to eliminate hangs
is by moving work off the main thread.
First, we need to determine
what this work should be.
In general, important tasks providing
critical information for the UI
should remain on the main thread.
Furthermore,
all views and view controllers
have to be created, modified,
and destroyed on the main thread.
However, the computation needed
to update a UI element can be
offloaded to another thread,
with a completion handler
to perform the actual update
on the main thread.
This pattern is useful when
computation is known to take a long time.
Other less important, maintenance,
or non-time-critical tasks
should be performed asynchronously
on another thread.
These would then run at a lower
scheduling priority and can take longer
to complete than
work that's on the main thread.
This is intentional and reflects
the idea that the main thread
should only perform critical work.
The most straightforward way to perform
asynchronous operations
from the main thread is to use
asynchronous counterparts
of synchronous APIs.
Let's take networking as an example.
By using async NSURL counterparts
to synchronous networking APIs,
apps will be responsive.
Asynchronous APIs are often
indicated by the word "asynchronously"
or the presence of a completion
handler in the method name.
Grand Central Dispatch is a powerful
multi-threading mechanism,
which you can leverage in cases
where there aren't async API variants,
or the code you want to move
off the main thread is your own.
Grand Central Dispatch provides
simple mechanisms to move
any block of work to another thread,
both synchronously or asynchronously.
This makes GCD incredibly effective at
eliminating most general causes for hangs.
To perform a block of work
asynchronously on another thread,
dispatch async that block
to another dispatch queue.
A completion handler can be
added within the asynced block
by dispatching back to the main queue.
Grand Central Dispatch also
enables you to pre-warm computation.
By dispatch asyncing a task onto a queue,
perhaps a prefetchQueue,
the task will start executing while the
main thread stays free to do other work.
When these results are needed by
the main thread,
it can dispatch sync
onto the prefetchQueue
to wait for the task to complete.
We've just touched
the surface of what GCD can do.
To learn more, check out the "Modernizing
Grand Central Dispatch" talk from 2017.
Let's understand some tradeoffs
with the solutions we just talked about.
Caches use memory,
so you should be cognizant
of their size
to avoid large memory growth.
It is also important to ensure there's an
accurate invalidation mechanism
so values are not stale.
Notifications can be chatty.
When observing one,
it is important to consider
the frequency at which
that notification fires.
Adding a filter before handling or
coalescing multiple notifications
will reduce CPU churn.
When using asynchronous APIs,
it is important to know whether
the operation
in question should be asynced,
particularly by first checking
whether it is crucial for a UI update,
as the operating system
deprioritizes asynced work.
When using Grand Central Dispatch
to perform tasks asynchronously,
you are changing the order at
which tasks in your code execute.
It is important to keep in mind
what tasks have to be ordered on others
to ensure your app does not break.
Using dispatch_sync
with serial queues
is a great way to synchronize operations
when needed.
Compared to the severe impact
hangs pose to user experience,
these tradeoffs are always worth it.
Some thoughts to keep in mind
while eliminating hangs
are use Apple Frameworks and APIs.
These are already compatible
with a wide set of devices,
are performant, and are constantly updated
to be more efficient and effective.
Perform improvements iteratively
in your code.
This way,
you'll make targeted fixes,
and be able to see
the affects of individual changes.
Be a good neighbor
when using system resources.
Using more resources than needed not only
reduces the performance of your own app,
but can also cause other
slowdowns in the system.
Together, we experienced
how jarring hangs can be,
and just how important it is
to defend against hangs in your app.
Going forward, set performance baselines
of your app via the Xcode organizer.
During development and code reviews,
watch out for anti-patterns
that can cause hangs.
We discussed
seven of the most common ones.
Diagnose issues that come up with the time
profiler and system trace instruments,
using MetricKit to prioritize issues
customers are most frequently hitting.
Eliminate any hangs you find by
using caches, observing notifications,
looking for asynchronous alternatives, or taking
advantage of Grand Central Dispatch.
By following these steps, your apps
will have even better performance
to provide
the best possible user experience.
Thanks for hanging around.
[music]