[upbeat music]
[Ayaka] Hi, everyone!
My name is Ayaka,
and I'm so happy to be
here to introduce you
to Shortcuts for Mac.
I wanna first start
with a quick overview
of Shortcuts for Mac,
and also some of the other
exciting new updates we're
bringing this year to Shortcuts.
Shortcuts lets people
automate repetitive tasks
and connect together
functionality
from different apps
to solve problems.
It lets you be creative with how
you use your technology.
And Shortcuts for Mac
is gonna make automation
more fun and accessible
than ever before.
When you open the app
for the first time,
you'll see all of your shortcuts
already synced from your iPhone.
The app also includes
a Shortcuts Gallery,
where you can discover new
shortcuts that are ready to use,
including brand-new
Mac-specific ones.
And if you want to create your own
shortcuts,
you can also use
the Shortcuts Editor,
which is re-designed from
the ground up
to feel at home on the Mac.
By the way,
we wrote almost the entire
Mac app in SwiftUI,
which allows us to maintain
a unified codebase between
our iOS and Mac apps
while letting us tailor
the details to each platform.
Like on iOS,
any app on the Mac
can provide actions
to Shortcuts.
In this session, we're gonna
cover how supporting Shortcuts
in your apps can enable
powerful workflows on macOS,
whether you're developing
an iOS app, a native Mac app,
or an app
built with Mac Catalyst.
We'll also cover how Shortcuts
fits into the bigger picture
of Mac automation,
including existing tools
that we know and love
like AppleScript and Automator.
This year, we also added
two new automation types
for Focus and Sound Recognition,
along with a whole new suite
of actions
that let you manage
your windows and files,
plus many more,
which we'll highlight later.
We'll cover how your app, too,
can provide custom actions
for people to create
powerful shortcuts.
By the way, if your app
integrates with file providers,
these new Files actions
will automatically work with
the files that your app
provides.
And, if you have an app
that adopts the existing
SiriKit messages intent,
we'll now automatically
expose this capability
via a custom Send Message
action from your app.
We also have some exciting
new updates to Sharing,
and we know developers love
to build and share shortcuts.
This year,
we're making Shortcuts
much easier to distribute.
We also have a new file format
that lets you distribute
Shortcuts as files.
And we've enabled private
sharing,
which is useful for sharing
Shortcuts with your peers.
Let's take a look.
Now, anyone can download
Shortcuts,
without having to turn
on any special settings.
This means that you
can distribute your
own Shortcuts on your
website or in your app.
For example, let's say,
you wanna give people
an awesome Shortcut that uses
actions from your app.
Now, if you build that Shortcut
and share it to iCloud,
Apple will notarize the Shortcut
and turn it into a link,
which you can feature
in your app or website
and make it easy
for people to download.
We're also keeping people
in control of their data
by presenting more
specific permission prompts
when they download a Shortcut
that passes data into your app
like a photo from their library.
And there's more.
Shortcuts can now also be shared
as files, which is useful
if you need to distribute
Shortcuts outside of iCloud.
And just like iCloud links,
Shortcuts files are notarized by
Apple to make sure they're safe.
Last but not least,
there's a new mode for sharing
Shortcuts privately,
without uploading to iCloud,
that you can use
for sharing with contacts
or for saving personal backups.
Shortcuts files are
signed with the identity
of the person who sent them.
If you need to re-sign
a Shortcut,
you can use the new
Shortcuts command-line tool.
So those are all the exciting
new updates
for Shortcuts this year.
Now let's take a look
at how Shortcuts fits in
with our existing
Mac automation technologies.
The Mac has a long history
of deep support for Automation,
including AppleScript,
Shell Scripting, and Automator.
We're excited to share
that Shortcuts has full support
for AppleScripts
and Shell Scripting.
We have new actions,
built right into Shortcuts,
that let you
write and run scripts
directly inside
the Shortcuts editor.
Next, let's take a look
at Automator.
Automator is an existing
automation tool on the Mac
that lets you create workflows
to automate repetitive tasks.
Shortcuts is the future
of Mac automation.
But we still care
deeply about Automator
and everyone who relies on it.
In order to make the transition
from Automator to Shortcuts
as smooth as possible,
we've built a migration tool
that can convert most Automator
workflows into Shortcuts.
For example,
if you have a great workflow
that makes images from PDF
documents selected in Finder,
Shortcuts can import that
and turn each Automator action
into one or more
Shortcuts actions.
All you have to do,
is open the workflow file
in the Shortcuts app
by dragging it into the app
or by using the right-click
menu, and that's it!
Your workflow is turned into
a Shortcut.
In order to enable the migrator,
we added all of the most popular
Automator actions to Shortcuts,
actions that run Shell Scripts
and AppleScripts,
manage your files, and more.
And, of course,
all of these actions
are supported by our migrator.
Now, let's talk about how your
app fits in to Shortcuts
and the value it can
create for customers.
The main way your app can
integrate with Shortcuts is
by exposing its capabilities via
"actions."
By exposing actions
to Shortcuts,
people can use
your app's functionality faster,
create powerful workflows
using your apps,
and last but not least,
use your app
in conjunction with other apps.
Let's take a deeper look
at these.
There are so many places
in macOS where people
can run their shortcuts.
If you expose an action from
your app, all of a sudden,
people will be able to use it
from the Shortcuts app itself,
the Shortcuts menu bar,
by typing a Keyboard shortcut,
by searching in Spotlight,
and much more.
So you're opening people up
to use your features
faster and in more places
than ever before.
And on top of that,
your app's actions can be
used as a part of powerful,
multi-step Shortcuts.
Let's say you make a to-do app
that lets people
manage their tasks.
If you expose the app's
capabilities as actions,
all of a sudden,
people can use those actions
to make powerful workflows.
For example, I can create
a Shortcut
that finds all of my to-do’s
that are due tomorrow,
sets the priority to high,
and shows them to me in a list,
all in one click.
Because of all
the different ways
you can hook actions together,
by exposing just a few actions,
you can enable
thousands of new use cases
for your app's functionality.
By exposing actions from your
app, you can also enable people
to use your app's functionality
in conjunction with other apps.
For example,
if you make an image editing app
and expose an action to apply
your app's custom image filters,
all of a sudden,
people can use that action
to make workflows
like this one
that lets me select a photo,
applies an image filter,
and posts it to social media,
all in one click.
So, those are just a few
examples of how exposing actions
can supercharge what people
can do with your apps.
Be sure to check out the session
covering designing great actions
to learn more about what
kinds of actions
you can provide to empower
people with your apps.
I'm gonna hand it off
to Ian now
who will show you how to
actually build these actions.
[Ian] Hi, I'm Ian,
and today
I'm going to show you
how to build Shortcuts
actions for your Mac apps.
Later, I'll cover some
special considerations
you should keep in mind
for your integration.
Let's get started
with building actions.
Just like on iOS,
actions for Shortcuts are built
using the Intents framework,
which is also known as SiriKit.
For this session,
I'm gonna pretend that
I'm developing a collaborative
task management app
which lets people keep
track of a list of tasks
that they need to do,
each with their own due date,
and share
those tasks with others.
It's really important
for people to be able use
my app's functionality
from anywhere on the Mac.
By integrating with Shortcuts,
I can allow my users to build
multi-step Shortcuts
involving tasks in my app.
Looking at the app,
the primary type of content
the user interacts with
is a task.
Each task has a couple
of important attributes.
First, there's the title,
which is some text
that describes
what needs to be done.
Tasks also have a due date
and a link to share
the task with others.
There's a bunch of operations
you can perform related to tasks
in the app, as well, which we
can think of as the verbs.
You can add new tasks,
edit or delete existing tasks,
get tasks that match a certain
criteria, and, of course,
the app can display
a specific task to you.
So, for each of those verbs,
I'm going to create actions.
These will form the primitive
operations
that users can invoke,
and these actions are
designed so that people
can use them together.
For example,
you could get a task,
and then delete it,
by pairing those two together.
With just Create Task,
someone could create
an automated workflow
that takes selected text
from Notes,
capitalizes
the text if necessary,
and asks the user
to enter a due date.
Then, the shortcut can
pass that text and due date
into the Create Task action,
which will deliver an intent
to create the task to my app.
Once the task has been created
in my app,
my intent will return the task,
including the sharing URL,
and the Shortcut
can send that link
to someone in a message.
Now, that's just one example.
Because there are so many
different
actions in Shortcuts,
people can utilize
the Create Task action
in nearly infinite ways.
Now that I know which
actions the app will expose,
I'm going to get started
implementing them.
The first step of implementing
is creating an intent definition
file for your app.
Add this file to your Xcode
project,
and it will compile
alongside your source code.
For this presentation,
I have a fairly basic
SwiftUI app for Mac.
However, regardless of the UI
framework that you use,
the process of adding intents
will be very similar.
First, I'll create
an intent definition file.
In the template pane,
I'll search for
intent definition.
The default name is fine.
Make sure to add it to the app
target so it compiles.
Here's the new,
empty intent definition file.
Inside the file,
I'll need to define each intent
that the app implements,
as well as
other types that are used,
like task, in this case.
This app will have a number
of intents,
each which reference
this task type,
so I'll start by
defining our task type.
To do that, click the + button
in the bottom left
and select "New Type."
Each type
will automatically have
identifier
and displayString properties.
The displayString property will
work for the title of the task,
but we'll need to add
more properties
to the type for the
due date and sharing link.
First, I'll add the due date
property,
which specifies when the task
has to be completed by.
I'm going to choose
the Date Components type
since this will represent
a date and time.
I'll also add the URL,
which is a link to the task
that can be shared
with others.
Now that the first task is
complete, no pun intended,
I'll move on
and define an intent.
This will be the intent
that lets you create a task.
I'll give it a name,
"Create Task,"
and change the category
to Create.
I'll also
write a short description,
describing what the intent does.
Users will see this
when they're looking through
the list of actions
that the app implements.
Next, I will define
the parameters for the intent.
Think of the intent like
a function,
and parameters as the arguments
that must be passed in
for the function
to do its work.
In order to create a new task,
my app will need to know
the title and the due date,
so I will make a parameter
for each of those.
The sharing link will not need
to be collected up front,
since the app will generate
one when the task is made.
Let's start by adding
a parameter for the title.
We'll select String as the type.
Each type of parameter
has some configuration options
associated with it.
You can specify a default value,
if that makes sense.
But for this case, I'll just
leave it as an empty string.
Next, I'll add the due date
parameter,
with a Date Components type.
And I'll add a prompt here,
so if the user doesn't enter
a date ahead of time, the app
can ask them for one at runtime.
Now that both parameters have
been defined, we're almost done.
Finally, I need to scroll down
to the Shortcuts app section
and fill in a few more things.
First, I'll specify
an input parameter.
Since often users will
be taking text from
somewhere else and passing it
into our action,
I will pick the title
parameter to be the input.
This will improve the experience
when building the shortcut,
so if the user already
has text from a previous action
in their shortcut,
it'll be filled in automatically
for them when they add
our action.
The last thing I need to do
is define a summary.
This string is displayed
to the user
when they look at
this action in a shortcut.
I will call it
"Create task with due date."
Both of our parameters are
required to create a task,
so I'm putting both
of those in the summary,
so they are always visible
when you look at the action.
If you have more parameters
that you don't wanna
put in the summary,
feel free to leave them out.
If you do this,
the user will be able
to expand the action
and edit those.
Once you've defined intents,
Xcode will generate classes
and protocols for you to use
in your implementation.
Now,
I'm going to build the app.
This will make sure
there's no problems
with the intent definition
before we continue.
In the build log, I now see
some new code getting built.
These source files are
generated by Xcode based on
what was put into
the intent definition.
Xcode generated source
code for the Task type,
as well as the CreateTaskIntent.
These new types can now be
used in our app's codebase.
Additionally, now that
the intent has been defined,
I can launch the Shortcuts app
and create a new shortcut
and search for
the new Create Task action.
It won't work yet, since I
haven't written any code.
Next, the app will need
to dispatch
and handle incoming intents.
This code will run when
someone runs the action
through Shortcuts or Siri.
Apps need to decide
which process will
handle their intents,
and there's two options.
First, handling them in-app,
or second,
building a separate
intents extension.
In-app intent handling
allows an app to manipulate
its state in response
to incoming intents
which get delivered
to the app delegate.
Most apps should start
with this and move
to an intents extension,
if necessary.
An intents extension is
a lightweight,
standalone process
that can handle intents
on behalf of an app.
Since every time
an intent is run
a process needs to be launched,
building an intents extension
can help be
as efficient as possible,
since the app itself
won't have to launch.
Apps and intents extensions
will be asked to instantiate
and return an intent handler
object for each incoming intent.
Let's look at the APIs
you should implement to do this.
For in-app intent handling,
there are AppDelegate methods
that let you
return your intent handler.
In macOS Monterey,
this API is now available
for NSApplicationDelegate,
as well.
For intents extensions,
subclasses of INExtension
can override
the handlerForIntent method.
For more information
about the differences
between in-app intent handling
and intents extensions,
watch the "Empower your intents"
session from WWDC 2020.
Now, I'll go into
the app and implement
in-app intent handling.
The first thing I need to do
is add the CreateTaskIntent
as a supported intent
for the app.
This lets the system
know that this intent
should be delivered
into the app delegate.
Next, go to the main
app source code.
First, I'll create an app
delegate for the app.
Since this is using
the SwiftUI app life cycle,
I'll also need to create
a delegate adaptor
to hook
the object up to SwiftUI.
To receive intents,
import the intents framework
and implement
the handlerForIntent method.
Now that there's
a dispatch method,
the next step is to implement
a handler for the intent.
For this example,
I'll create a new class
to handle the intent,
and this can be
any object in your app.
The intent handler
must conform
to the generated protocol
for this intent
which ends with the word
"Handling."
For the Create Task intent,
it's named
CreateTaskIntentHandling.
Then, I'll update
the handlerForIntent
method to return a new
IntentHandler object
when the intent
is a CreateTaskIntent.
Xcode should let you know which
methods you need to implement.
Intent handling protocols
can contain
four different types
of methods:
resolve, provide options,
confirm, and handle.
A resolve method will be
generated
for each of your parameters.
This will be your chance to
check if the parameter is valid
and tell the system
what to do if it's not.
For this intent,
there are two resolve methods,
one for the title,
and another for the due date.
For the title parameter,
the app needs to make sure
the value is not nil
and isn't empty.
If the title's empty,
it returns needsValue,
which tells the system to prompt
the user to enter a value.
For the due date parameter,
something similar
is implemented
where the due date
is validated to make sure
it's not nil.
Looking at the app's
requirements for due dates,
the resolve method also needs
to ensure that all due dates
are in the future
and show an error to the user
if the date is in the past.
To do this, I'll go back
to our intent definition file
and add
a custom validation error.
I'll give it a code,
invalidDate,
and an error message
saying that the due date
must be in the future.
Now, the app can return
the unsupported result
with the custom validation error
that I just added,
which will display
the error message
about the date being invalid.
Another type of method
is provide options.
You'll see this for
any parameter
with the Dynamic Options
setting enabled.
If any of your parameters
only has a finite set
of possible values,
and you don't want users
to be able to enter their
own arbitrary values,
you can enable dynamic
options for that parameter.
This will create a method called
provide options that lets you
specify what those possible
values are as the intent runs,
and Shortcuts will ask the user
to pick from one of the values.
After the parameters
are resolved individually,
you can optionally also
implement the confirm method,
which is where you should
make sure everything looks good,
and you should be able
to handle the intent
and throw an error
if there's a problem.
If, for example, a network
connection is required,
here is where you should check
to make sure
you can actually
reach the network.
Finally,
the handle method is where
you actually do what the intent
is telling you to do.
The handle method
will create the task in the app
and return success.
After the action creates
the task,
it should provide
the task as output
so later actions
can use attributes
such as the sharing URL.
Back in the intent editor,
I'll go to the response
section for the intent.
In here, I'll add a property
for the task that was created.
I'll select the task type
that I made before.
I'll select that property as
the output of the intent,
to make it available
to Shortcuts.
And now, back in the code,
the response will have
a task property where I
can assign the task object.
Once this is done,
your intent should appear as
an action in the Shortcuts app.
So, be sure to spend
some time testing it
and trying all the ways
people could use it.
To begin testing, I'll open
the Shortcuts app again
and look at
the Create Task action.
I'll fill in a name
for the task and a date--
"Tomorrow at 3:00 p.m."
When I hit the run button,
the task
gets created successfully.
However, if I change the date
to "Yesterday at 3:00 p.m."...
It'll show the error message,
just as we expected.
So that's it for building
an action in Shortcuts.
Finally, today I'll go over
some considerations
that you should keep in mind
when developing
for Shortcuts on the Mac.
I'm going to cover four
different types of apps
including apps that are
built with Mac Catalyst,
that work with files,
that deploy to both iOS and Mac,
and apps and tools
that need to run Shortcuts.
First, if you're using
Mac Catalyst to bring your
iOS app to the Mac, here's a few
things you need to know.
In macOS Monterey,
your apps can now use
the same Intents APIs
if it's built with Mac Catalyst.
If you're building a new app,
everything should work
the same as it does on iOS.
However, if your app
is already available on Mac,
and you integrated with
the Intents framework on iOS,
it's likely
that you have compiled out
your Intents integration
in the process of coming to Mac.
So, make sure to audit your code
to re-enable this functionality
when running on macOS Monterey.
Another type of app
I'd like to highlight
is a document-based app.
In the demo before,
our task management app
operates on tasks which exist
entirely within the app.
However, many other apps
operate on documents
that exist as files on disk.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
file parameters for intents
allow users to select
specific files and pass them
into your app's actions.
If your app deals primarily
with file-based documents
rather than a database,
consider building
a suite of actions
that operate on files.
For example, a spreadsheet app
can create an action
to open a document
or to add data to a row
of a specific file.
Another really cool example
of how third-party Shortcuts
can work with files
is shown in this session
from Sound Analysis.
If you are developing an app
that exists on both iOS and Mac,
in order for your actions
to work on both platforms,
you should deploy
the same intents
in both copies of your app.
This will allow people
to build a shortcut
on one platform and have it work
the same way on the other.
To do this,
you should compile the same
exact intent definition
to both apps,
and make sure the intents share
the same name and parameters.
Sometimes,
your apps may have different
bundle identifiers
across platforms,
and this is okay.
Shortcuts will handle this
for you,
but please keep in mind
that the intents with the same
name will only be shared
among apps deployed via the same
Apple Developer team.
Also, if you ever need
to upgrade users
from one version of your app
to another, on iOS 15,
as long as the two apps
are from the same developer
and use the same intent name,
your app's Shortcuts
will automatically transfer
from one to the other.
Finally, if you'd like to run
Shortcuts from your app
or command-line tool, there
are two methods to consider.
First, Shortcuts exposes
a scripting interface
which lets Mac apps
and AppleScripts
list and run Shortcuts.
Additionally, there's a
Shortcuts command-line tool
which lets you list and run
Shortcuts in your Shell Scripts
or command-line tools,
as well.
If you develop an app
or a script that would
benefit from the ability
to run Shortcuts,
you should use
the Scripting interface.
By communicating with
the "Shortcuts Events" process,
your app can get
a list of shortcuts
that the user has set up,
as well as start running one.
In AppleScript, you can
accomplish this by telling
the "Shortcuts Events" process
to run a shortcut by name.
Using the Scripting Bridge
framework,
you can ask the Shortcuts Events
process to run a shortcut
directly from your Swift
or Objective-C apps.
For sandbox apps, you'll need to
add an entitlement called
"com.apple.security.scripting
targets."
In order to access
the list of shortcuts
and run them,
you'll need to add
the "com.apple.shortcuts.run"
target.
Finally, macOS Monterey also
includes a command-line tool
that can list shortcuts
and run them by name.
If you have command-line
tools or scripts, they can
integrate with Shortcuts
via this interface.
So, to wrap up, Shortcuts is now
available on the Mac,
and no matter what
type of app you have,
you should participate
in the Shortcuts ecosystem.
By adding actions for your app,
you can multiply what
people can do with it.
Shortcuts lets people be
creative with your apps.
You might be delighted
to find out
what sorts of Shortcuts people
build with your actions.
[percussive music]