[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Ari] Hi, I'm Ari, and today,
along with Cameron,
I'm excited to introduce you
to the world of Shortcuts
and talk about how you can design actions
that power great experiences
in Shortcuts, Siri, and Suggestions.
When we think about designing apps,
we usually focus on the details of the UI
and what the user can see and feel
when they're inside of your app.
But in this talk, we're going to do
something a little different.
We're going to focus on experiences
that people can have
with your app
when your app isn't even open.
We think that there's
a world of opportunity
that we can open up by thinking this way.
It all starts with a concept
we call "actions."
An action is a way of representing a task
that people can complete with your app.
By creating actions, you can let people
perform those tasks
in new and exciting ways.
Let's say you make the Calendar app.
What are some of the most
common things people do
when they're inside of the Calendar app?
Well, people probably add new events,
look up existing events,
and make changes to events.
Those are all great ideas for actions.
So, the Calendar app can define an action
for each one of those activities.
This is where the magic begins.
Once the Calendar app
creates these actions,
people can use them
as building blocks to form shortcuts.
For example,
this Add New Event action is great
for quickly adding events to my calendar.
People can customize actions,
like by setting this one
to create events called "Yoga"
from 6:00 p.m. to 7:00 p.m.
The action can then become a shortcut,
which people can use to perform the action
whenever they want, in a single tap.
People can also mix
and match different actions together
to form a shortcut that does
something even more powerful,
like finding all your Calendar events
for today
and adding a personal
meeting room URL to each one.
That can form
another super valuable shortcut.
And people can use actions
from different apps together
to get even more done
in a single shortcut,
like this one that gets
my next Calendar event
and sends a message to the attendees
saying I'll be running late.
And these examples are just scratching
the surface of what people can do.
By creating only just a few actions,
the Calendar app has opened itself up
to thousands of new use cases
that can be used with Shortcuts
across Apple devices.
With the updated Shortcut editor,
anyone can build Shortcuts
by dragging and dropping actions together.
Creating actions can help people
who use your app,
even if they don't set up any shortcuts.
If you donate actions to the system,
Siri will automatically learn
how people use your app
and will suggest your actions
at the right time,
in the Suggestions widget,
in Search, and on the Lock screen.
And people can use any shortcut
just by saying its name to Siri.
"Hey Siri,
Order Starbucks."
Just like that,
Siri will kick off the action
and can ask follow-up questions
to get the information
your app needs to take an action.
So, by creating actions,
you're automatically making
your app's functionality voice-enabled,
so people can use it from anywhere.
That extends beyond Siri, too.
Shortcuts can be run from
across iOS and macOS,
like with a single tap from
the Shortcuts widget on the Home screen
or from the menu bar on the Mac.
By exposing actions from your app,
you open your app up to a world
of Shortcuts possibilities.
Exposing a great action can delight users
by saving them time and enabling them
to build new things.
So, in this session,
we're going to try to answer the question,
"What makes an action great?"
And to walk through that, we've broken it
down into a few principles.
Great actions are useful, modular,
multi-modal, clear, and discoverable.
So let's dive in.
It sounds obvious
that great actions are useful,
but what does it really mean
to design something that's useful?
In the context of Shortcuts,
a useful action is one
that performs a task that people
would normally do inside of your app.
Your action should perform
the task completely,
and you should avoid opening your app
into the foreground,
unless it's necessary for your use case.
Where possible,
you should ask follow-up questions
instead of opening the app.
Let's look at the Reminders app.
One of the primary features
in the Reminders app
is the ability to add a new reminder.
When you edit a reminder,
you can configure
a variety of its attributes.
Adding a reminder is something you
can do inside of the Reminders app,
but it would also be useful to be
able to do it outside of the app,
so this will make
a great Shortcuts action.
Here's what the action
would look like in Shortcuts.
Note that the options you can choose
when setting up a reminder
are configurable as parameters here.
When I use a shortcut
to add a new reminder,
it should add immediately,
without opening the Reminders app.
But let's say I'm designing
a different action,
one that shows a particular list
inside the Reminders app.
In this case, opening the app is necessary
to fulfill the goal of the action,
so it's okay to make an action for this.
But the action for adding new reminders
is a bit more valuable than this one
because people can use it without being
pulled away from their current context.
One more thing to consider
is what to do
if your action needs more information
from the user to complete,
like if someone uses
an Add New Reminder action
that doesn't have a title specified.
In this case, when the shortcut is run,
the action can ask a follow-up question,
like, "What do you wanna be
reminded about?"
When possible, you should handle ambiguity
by asking a follow-up question,
instead of by opening your app,
which should be a last resort.
A related topic to consider
when deciding which actions
will be useful is immersion.
Your action should perform a task
without immersing people
in a complex experience.
Let's say I'm designing actions
for the Apple Watch app.
A great feature of this app is the ability
to create and customize Watch faces.
This is a very complicated
and visual task
with tons of custom UI controls
and live visual previews.
Ultimately,
it's a very immersive experience,
and so it's probably not going
to make a great Shortcuts action.
On the other hand, a simple task,
like switching between Watch faces
that are already set up,
is not too immersive,
and it's something that can be used
without your full attention.
So this functionality
will be really useful
as a Shortcuts action.
With this action, I can make a shortcut
that lets me change my Watch face
in one tap,
or I could make an Automation
that changes it automatically
throughout the day.
Lastly, the most useful actions
are usually the ones
that are the most repeatable.
When you're deciding
which actions to build,
prioritize those that are useful
on a recurring basis
and that can be used
quickly and frequently.
For example, the Apple Music app
has the ability to follow friends.
It would be cool to expose this
as a Shortcuts action.
People could use it
in a multi-step shortcut,
for example,
to follow many friends at once.
But if you compare following friends
to other features of the Music app,
like actually playing music,
it's clear that following friends
is something that people do
much less often.
If time permits,
it's always better to build more actions,
so you could consider making both,
but you should always prioritize
building actions for the features
that people will use the most.
So a useful action is one
that performs a task,
ideally without launching your app,
is not too immersive,
and is repeatable, in that people
will use it quickly and frequently.
To tell you a whole lot more
about designing great actions,
I'm going to turn it over to Cameron.
[Cameron] Thanks, Ari!
My name is Cameron, and I'm a designer
on the Siri and Shortcuts teams.
Today, I'm really excited
to take you through
the finer points
of designing great actions.
First, let's start by talking
about how to design actions
that are modular.
For the sake of example,
imagine there are
two separate To Do apps
that are both thinking
about creating actions for shortcuts.
They're called "Dog Do's" and "Shortcats."
They both have the same goal:
to create a shortcut
that enables people
to clean up their old tasks.
Dog Do's has the idea to create
an action called "Clean up old tasks,"
which seems reasonable.
After all, it does everything, all in one.
But really, the Cat app
has the right idea.
They've created a suite of actions
that each individually do one thing
and together can do so much more.
Let's take a look at how that works
for our cleanup shortcut.
Here we can see Dog Do's and Shortcats
can both fulfill the goal
of "Cleaning up old tasks."
But they do so in a very different way.
Dog Do's has a single action,
whereas the Cat app combines
the Get Task action with an Archive
action to accomplish the goal.
The first action,
"Get tasks created before a week ago,"
finds old tasks,
and the second one archives them.
On the other hand,
looking at the Dog Do's' action,
it's unclear what exactly
this action will do
because the summary isn't specific.
So what will happen
when someone runs the Cats' shortcut?
For example, with Siri,
Siri will ask the user to confirm
whether or not they want
to archive the tasks,
along with showing a preview
of which tasks will be archived.
This example is using the Get
and Archive actions working together.
But because the actions are modular,
they can also be useful
in other combinations, or even standalone.
Here, you can see that Archive action
is quite useful by itself.
When it's used without a Get action,
it should ask which task
they want to archive.
The Get action is also useful on its own,
like in this case,
where it's used to show all
of the tasks I created
before one week ago.
Already, you can see
that the Shortcats' actions
are much more extensible
than the Dog Do's action,
which can't be reused for other purposes.
In the context of Siri suggestions,
the Dog Do's action is vague;
it's difficult to tell what it would do
if it was tapped on.
On the other hand, Shortcats has
donated the Get Tasks action,
which includes a parameter:
the period of time to get tasks for.
This makes it super clear what will happen
if someone taps on the suggestion.
Including parameters makes
for a more approachable
and better user experience.
In the context of the shortcut editor,
again,
we can see the Dog Do's action
is vague and inflexible,
whereas the Shortcats actions' parameters
can easily be customized
to change the window of task retrieval
from one to two weeks.
But the story isn't just
about your app's actions;
it's also about actions
that are built in to Shortcuts
and actions from other apps.
By combining all of these types
of actions together,
people can create entirely new Shortcuts
and use cases with your app.
You might be wondering
how actions work together.
You can see how it works
in the Shortcut editor.
Each action has an output,
which can be passed
into the parameter of another action
using a variable.
Here, the Archive Task action
is using a variable
called "Cat Tasks" to archive the tasks
that meet the criteria specified
in the first action.
But the Cat app has gone further
and exposed additional properties
as output from the Get Tasks action,
like Reminder, Attachment,
Parent task, Deadline, Notes,
and the list the Task is in.
When people attach other actions,
they can employ these output properties
to create new functionality.
For example, the built-in
Show Result action can be used
with the Get Tasks action
to show all of the notes
from all of my old tasks.
Or the same action can be combined
with a Save File action
to save all of the attachments
from my old tasks to iCloud.
When you separate your output
into pieces and label them,
they show up when you're editing
a variable in the Shortcut editor.
This gives Shortcuts authors
a powerful tool they can use
to create new use cases that go beyond
what's possible, even in your app.
When creating actions
for concepts specific to your app,
like tasks in the Shortcats app,
or files in the Files app,
here are some common actions
that you should consider designing.
Create actions.
They add a new thing,
given some parameters, like a new task.
The new thing is passed as output.
This action should also include
a custom interface
and dialogue summarizing what was added.
Edit actions.
They change a thing in your app.
The new item should be passed as output.
Delete actions cause the specified thing
to be deleted in your app.
Get actions.
They find things in your app
that match certain criteria.
Everything that is found
is passed as output.
Get actions should also include
a custom interface
and dialogue that summarizes
what was found.
Thing actions.
They let someone pick a specific thing
from your app, for example,
a task in the Shortcats app.
This action should both include
a custom interface showing the thing
and pass the thing as output,
for use with other actions.
Lastly, open actions.
They cause your app to be opened
in the foreground,
with a specific thing in view.
Now, you know how and why to design
your actions to be modular.
Remember, it's about
making things composable,
while still making them
useful stand-alone,
making things customizable
with parameters,
and offering outputs for all your actions.
Multimodality is about making
one piece of functionality,
your action, work in multiple ways
and across contexts and devices.
When you're designing Shortcuts actions,
keep in mind that they can be used
in these three ways:
by running a shortcut in the UI,
either from a tap or a click;
by running a shortcut with your voice,
with Siri;
and when configuring your action
in the Shortcut Editor.
Let's say you're adding a deadline
to one of your Cat tasks with a shortcut.
When you run the shortcut
by tapping on it,
a UI will be shown to resolve the date,
using a calendar picker.
When this same shortcut
is run on the HomePod,
Siri will ask someone a question
with a prompt,
like, "When is the deadline?"
And they might say something like
"Tomorrow" or "Next Tuesday."
Note how the same prompt
is used in the compact UI
when someone tapped to run a shortcut,
and on the HomePod
when they asked Siri to run it.
This works great because the prompt
is phrased as a question
and is appropriate in both contexts.
The Dog Do's app, by contrast,
chose the dialogue "Deadline:,"
which looks fine
in the compact UI on the iPhone,
but doesn't make any sense
when spoken by Siri.
You should always make sure
to phrase your prompts as questions
to avoid this problem.
There's a whole lot more to designing
great dialogue for Siri to speak,
and I'd encourage you to check out
these talks from my colleagues
in years past on the topic.
Finally, your action
also has an interface
in the Shortcut editor,
where people can use it
as a building block.
In the Shortcut editor,
the same parameters that Siri asks about
are displayed as blue rectangles
that the author can edit
when setting up the shortcut.
For this date parameter,
a floating tip shows the date
that is recognized from the entered text.
You should always aim to make
all parameters useable,
both when running a shortcut
and configuring it in the editor.
When choosing your action's parameters,
you'll need to pick a type for each one.
The system includes many parameter types,
which will work well across modalities.
That said, if your action needs to deal
with a unique entity from your app
that isn't well represented
by a system type,
you can define a custom one.
Let's take a look at an example.
The Set Playback Destination action,
built in to Shortcuts,
sets the audio route of your device,
like to your AirPods
or your Bluetooth speaker.
To help people understand
the devices they can choose from,
the Shortcut editor shows visuals
of those devices
when someone clicks the parameter.
Because there isn't a built-in parameter
for representing devices,
the action defines a custom parameter
and a UI to go along with it.
We call these UIs "Dynamic Enumerations,"
and you can create them, too.
There are two different times when people
can pick values for parameters:
configuration and resolution.
Configuration is when someone is setting
up your action in the Shortcut editor.
Resolution happens
when your action is run.
For example, on the left,
is a dynamic enumeration shown
when someone taps on the "Cat Task" field
of the Archive Task action.
On the right is the visual list
that is shown
when Siri asks someone
what task they want to archive.
Both of these UIs are filling
the same parameter in the Archive action,
the left one during configuration,
and the right one during resolution.
And both should be populated
in similar ways,
since they're both filling
the same parameter.
Now that you've learned how people
can fill in your action's parameters,
let's take a quick look
at the custom interfaces
that you can show to people
when they run your action.
We call these "snippets."
For example, when we run
the Starbucks Order Coffee action,
a snippet is shown to preview
the order that will be placed.
For actions that are permanent,
like deletion or ordering,
you should strongly consider
showing a different snippet
before the action is completed as compared
to the one that is shown
after it's completed.
The snippet you show beforehand
should aid people
in understanding what the action will do.
This is useful to help them understand
the stakes of going through with it.
There's a lot
to designing multimodal actions,
but by phrasing your prompts as questions,
choosing appropriate parameters,
creating visuals for filling parameters,
and by designing great snippets,
you'll be well on your way.
Despite all this talk of actions,
we haven't actually discussed
how actions are represented in the editor.
This section is all about that.
In iOS 13,
we introduced the concept
of a parameter summary,
a new visual format
that describes a task
using natural language.
This year, we've redesigned
the appearance of actions
in the Shortcut editor to focus
on the parameter summary.
Notably, app names have been
removed from the action,
and app icons
have been integrated in-line,
along with the Show More control.
We made these changes to make actions
look even better in multi-step shortcuts
and to save space so even more actions
can fit on-screen at a time.
It's important when designing actions to
consider the experience people will have
with your actions in the editor itself
because Shortcuts exists
to give people the ability
to create new functionality
and share it with others.
Remember that all Shortcuts
are open source,
and anyone can look inside them
to see how they work.
Before we go into the details
of actions themselves,
remember that your parameter summary
is different to your action title.
Your action titles are used
in the Shortcuts action list
to briefly identify your action.
It's important for your action title
to begin with the same verb
as your parameter summary,
and share as many words as possible,
like here,
with the Send Message action.
Let's take a look at another example.
Here's a new app for helping me
with my morning breathing exercises
called Awebreath.
The app has a simple and focused UI
that lets you choose the length
you want to breathe for
and optionally play music.
When designing your action,
start with the parameter summary.
The summary succinctly describes
the action that will be performed,
including the most important parameters.
The summary should also begin with a verb
and should be written like a sentence,
but without the period.
Even though the Awebreath action
includes a parameter
for music to play while you breathe,
it's not required,
so it doesn't belong in your summary.
Punctuation, like semicolons,
commas, and periods,
should also never be
in your parameter summary.
People can still use this parameter,
the music to play,
from your Options UI,
which can be expanded
by tapping on the chevron.
If a required parameter is left empty,
when it's resolved,
your action should ask for a value.
If you have a strong inclination
about the best experience for your action,
consider providing
a default value for a parameter.
If you do this, your action may be able
to skip asking a question when it runs.
In this example,
the Awebreath app provides
a default breathing time of 15 minutes.
Regardless of whether or not
a parameter is required
or has a default value,
people can always choose to make
any parameter into a question
by using the special variable,
"Ask Each Time."
When this is used, a shortcut will prompt
for the parameter value when it's run.
For this reason,
you should always include a prompt
and/or visual list, if applicable,
for all of your action's parameters.
When designing your parameter summary,
make sure to summarize, starting with a verb,
consider providing default values,
remember that any parameter can be prompted for
if someone uses Ask Each Time, and place all your optional parameters
in the
options UI.
Last but not least, it's important to understand
how you can make your actions discoverable
and get them in front of people.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterrey, we've
introduced new sharing methods
for Shortcuts
that make it easy to share multi-step Shortcuts
that include your actions. The updated download UI
also displays where Shortcuts can be run,
so people know what to expect. As the creator of an app,
you can place links to multi-step Shortcuts that use your actions
on your website, social media channels, or in the help sections
of your app to give people ideas on how to asked
use your actions together. Also new,
when someone taps "Add to Siri,"
the shortcut is added instantly, using
your suggested invocation phrase. This new UI emphasizes
your suggested invocation phrase, so people know what to
say to Siri to run your shortcut. It also
encourages them to audition your shortcut
right after adding it. If you don't
provide a suggested invocation phrase, the shortcut won't be added
immediately after someone taps on "Add to Siri."  Instead, they will be
asked to provide their own shortcut name,
which isn't as seamless of an experience and
decreases the chances someone will successfully add and use your shortcut.
That's a wrap on changes
to sharing Shortcuts
and getting your actions
in front of people.
And with that,
we've discussed how to design actions for
Shortcuts, Siri, and Suggestions.
Great actions are useful, modular, multimodal,
clear, and discoverable.
Good luck designing actions.
We can't wait to see what you build and
how it contributes to the world of Shortcuts. Have a great WWDC.
[upbeat music]