[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Prabha Bashyam:
Hello, my name is Prabha,
and I'm on the Apple Media
Products Engineering team.
In this session,
I'm going to tell you about
some exciting new features
to optimize your App Store
product page on iPhone and iPad.
Today the product page
is the home for your app.
It's where users learn
all about your app,
before they decide
to download it.
You use the app icon,
name, and subtitle
to make a great
first impression.
And you share even more
details with app preview videos,
screenshots, promotional text,
and the description.
Later this year, you'll be able
to use custom product pages
and product page optimization
to make your product page
even more relevant and effective
for your audience.
For each of these
new capabilities,
I'll provide details
on how the feature works
and share more about what you
can do to get ready for them.
With custom product pages,
the product page
becomes even more flexible.
Custom product pages let you
showcase different features
and content for different users.
Each one can have a different
set of app preview videos,
screenshots,
and promotional text.
Each page is fully localizable,
and each is shareable
using its own unique URL.
You'll also be able to view
metrics for each page,
including impressions,
downloads, and conversion rate
in App Analytics.
This information lets you know
how effective each page is
at driving users
to download your app.
You will also be able to monitor
what happens after the download.
App Analytics will provide
retention data
and average proceeds
per paying user
for each custom product page,
so you can see how certain pages
are converting users.
You can create up to 35
different custom product pages
for your app.
So to prepare for this feature,
think carefully about
how you want to use them.
Consider the rich content
and engaging features
your app has to offer
and how you can highlight them.
For an app
like Mountain Climber,
we could choose to showcase
the live streaming functionality
to appeal to people
interested in following climbers
in real time
or streaming their own journeys
up to the summit.
And we could create
another custom product page
highlighting
the GPS tracking feature
to appeal to people
interested in planning a climb
with a group of friends.
If you develop a game,
you may want to create one
to highlight your most
engaging characters
or popular gameplay modes.
If your app features
video content,
you can consider creating
custom product pages
for specific shows or channels.
No matter how you want to use
custom product pages,
here's how you can get ready
for this feature.
First, plan your goals.
Have a clear objective in mind
before you set up your page.
Remember you can create
up to 35 custom product pages,
so carefully plan
how you want to use them.
Next, consider the features
and content in your app
and the ones you want
to highlight on these pages.
Lastly, begin preparing
your metadata.
Remember each page
can have
a different set of app preview
videos, screenshots,
and promotional text,
so you can get started now
on creating new visual assets
and text for your pages.
Then, when the feature launches
later this year,
you'll be ready
to create your pages
and submit the metadata
in App Store Connect.
And you'll be able to do this
without having to submit
a new version of your app.
Once approved, you'll be able to
share your custom product pages,
using their own unique URL.
Of course, the users who arrive
on your default product page
through searching
or browsing the App Store
are also incredibly important.
That's why we're introducing
product page optimization.
With this feature, you can set
up and test different treatments
of your default page
to determine which one best
resonates with your users.
For example, given the original
page with the blue icon
and the treatment page
with the red icon,
by splitting the traffic
going to each page
and measuring download
conversion on each,
you may learn that the treatment
page actually performs better,
suggesting you may want to apply
the treatment metadata
to your default product page
to improve overall conversion.
For your treatment page,
you have the flexibility
to try a different app icon,
or you can try different app
preview videos or screenshots.
And each test can have
up to three treatments,
like in this example
with three icon color styles.
You can choose the percentage
of your audience
that will see
one of the treatments.
For example, if you choose 30%,
then each of the three
treatments would get 10%
of the total traffic.
When running a test
that involves the app icon,
we've made sure that all users
who download your app
will have
a consistent experience.
After all, your app icon
is an important way
to appeal to App Store users
and stand out
on their home screens.
So for anyone
that sees your test icon
on the product page,
they'll see that same icon
when they download
your app on their device.
To allow for this, you'll
include the variant icon assets
in your app binary
for the version of your app
that you want to test,
including all sizes
for the applicable devices
and the 1024x1024 version
for the App Store.
You'll also have
the ability to run tests
in only specific localizations.
For example,
if your product page
is currently localized in
English, Japanese, and Korean,
you can choose to run your tests
in Japanese only.
This means that
any users that see
the English or Korean localized
versions of your product page
will not be included
in the test.
This gives you the flexibility
to focus your test
if your treatment
is only relevant
for a subset
of your localizations.
As the test runs, you'll be able
to monitor the results,
including metrics
for impressions,
downloads, conversion,
and the improvement
that each treatment gets
against the baseline.
For more details on what's
coming in App Analytics,
check out
"What's New in App Analytics".
After reviewing the results,
you'll be able to apply
one of the treatments
to your app's default page
to let all users see
the most effective version
of your page.
Note that if the treatment
you want to apply
features a different app icon,
you'll apply that icon
by updating the default icon
in the binary
of the next version of your app.
With that overview,
let's recap what you need to get ready to
enhance your App Store product page.
Before running a test, make
sure to form a strong hypothesis. For example, you may predict
that changing your app icon to a different
style will drive better conversion
in certain locales. Make sure to have
all the necessary videos and screenshots ready to go
when setting up your test.
They will be reviewed by App Review before your test can
begin, but you can submit them without creating
a new app version.
And remember, to test
a variation
of your app icon, you'll need to
include the icon assets in the binary of your
app version that is currently live, so make sure to prepare
your
app releases accordingly.
So these are the new ways you can optimize
your
App Store product page.
Custom product pages gives you the flexibility to highlight specific content and
features in your app. Product page optimization helps
you determine the visual assets that your users
find most appealing.
Lastly, all the functionality
we just discussed for both features will be supported
by the App Store Connect API. A full API spec will be
published
later this year. We look forward
to launching these features later this year and seeing how you use them
to optimize
your product pages.  Thank you for watching
and have a great WWDC!
♪