[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
♪
Melissa Nierle:
I'm Melissa Nierle,
a software engineer
on the Enterprise and Education
Technologies team.
At Apple, we're always working
to create the best
device management features
and functionality to equip
our enterprise partners
and education organizations
with the tools they need
to connect their team members
and students.
The backbone of all
of these management features
is the MDM protocol itself.
The protocol is
a well-established,
heavily used solution
provided directly within iOS,
macOS, and tvOS
and has become a standard
across mobile device management.
And while we add features
to it each year,
we also continually evaluate
the protocol
against our device
management goals
and evolve it to meet
the dynamic needs
of MDM solution developers,
admins, and users.
Today, our MDM protocol
can be described
as an imperative
and reactive protocol.
Each management workflow takes
time and multiple round trips
between the device and server.
Then any performance challenge
is compounded
when you manage
a large number of devices
across an organization.
This is an example
of where we want to ensure
our protocol is as performant
and scalable as possible.
And to achieve optimal
performance and scalability,
we've reenvisioned
the MDM protocol itself.
The future of device management
is declarative management;
a transformative update
to the protocol
which brings policy management
to the device.
Declarative management allows
the device to be autonomous
and proactive,
freeing up the server
to be lightweight, reactive,
and subscribe to updates
without constant polling.
An autonomous device reacts
to its own state changes
and then applies
management logic to itself
without prompting
from the server.
A proactive device
has a status channel
asynchronously reporting
to the server
when important
state changes occur,
avoiding the need for servers
to poll devices.
Enabling devices to be both
autonomous and proactive
is the foundation
of declarative management
and allows for increased
performance and scalability.
And the best part is,
while it's a new paradigm,
it's not a new protocol.
We've built this new
declarative functionality
right into our existing
MDM protocol,
starting with iOS devices.
We'll take a deep dive
into the data model
that powers the new
declarative paradigm.
Then later, we'll talk
about integration with MDM.
We'll go through
a specific example
and learn how to get
yourself started.
Let's begin with
the declarative data model.
There are three pillars
to the declarative data model.
Declarations, which are payloads
that the server defines
and sends to devices;
the status channel, which is
a new channel of communication
where the device proactively
updates the server
with new information
about itself;
and extensibility, so that,
as Apple introduces new features
to declarative management,
your devices and servers
handle it seamlessly.
Understanding these three
pillars will prepare you
to incorporate
declarative management
into your MDM solution.
Let's start with declarations.
Declarations represent
the policy
an organization wants
to enforce on devices --
for example, accounts,
settings, and restrictions.
Declarations can be created
for policy
that is common to all users,
as well as policy
that is specific
to a single user or device.
Let's examine
the makeup of declarations.
The data representation
for declarations
is similar to profiles, where a
declaration is also a dictionary
with a set of keys
and standard types for values.
Declarations, however,
are serialized as JSON objects
when sent over the network,
instead of plists.
All declarations have
three required properties:
Type, Identifier
and ServerToken.
Type defines which policy
a configuration represents.
The Identifier key has a value
that uniquely identifies
the declaration within the set
of all declarations
sent to the device.
Typically, this will be a UUID
represented as a string.
The device uses this value
when synchronizing declarations
with the server.
The ServerToken key
represents a unique revision
of the declaration
based on the Identifier key.
This key is also used when
synchronizing declarations
with the server.
The value is a string that must
be different for each revision.
It could be a simple counter
or a UUID string,
as shown in the example.
The payload is a data-specific
piece of the declaration,
containing the keys and values
pertinent
to the declaration type.
Just like with profile payloads,
some keys may be required,
and others may be optional.
Values can be strings, numbers,
booleans, arrays,
or dictionaries and may be
constrained in range --
like numbers one through ten --
or to a specific set of values
like a string enumeration.
There are four types of
declarations: configurations,
assets, activations,
and management.
The first type of declaration
is a configuration.
Configurations represent
the policies
to be applied to the device --
for example, accounts,
settings, and restrictions.
Configurations are similar to
MDM's existing profile payloads.
Here is an example of
a configuration declaration
that applies restrictions
to the device passcode.
The standard keys --
Type, Identifier,
and ServerToken --
are present, as required
for all declarations.
The value of the Type
identifies this
as a passcode configuration
type of declaration.
The Payload key contains
the passcode policy data
for the configuration.
The next type of declaration
is an asset.
Assets represent
references to ancillary data
needed by configurations.
This can be a shared item
of large data
or a personalized one.
For large data items, the asset
declaration contains a URL
that the device uses to fetch
the actual asset data
from a server.
This server could be
your MDM server,
or it could be a separate
content delivery network server.
Serving assets from a separate
content delivery network
shifts the burden of supporting
large network bandwidth
to a service
better suited for it.
Assets can also be used
to represent data
specific to a user,
such as their name,
email address, passwords
for accounts, and certificates.
This takes the per-user
customized data
out of configurations
and moves it into smaller,
dedicated asset-type
declarations.
Assets have
a one-to-many relationship
with configurations.
For example, one credential
asset can be referenced
by several
account configurations,
avoiding the need to replicate
the same user information
in each account configuration.
Then, if the user credential
needs to be updated,
only that asset
needs to be updated.
All the configurations
referencing that asset
remain unchanged,
and the device updates
the policy accordingly.
The ability to do incremental
updates like this,
for many configurations
at a time,
will improve the overall
responsiveness
of the device management system.
Let's examine the makeup
of an asset declaration.
Here is an example
of an asset declaration
that defines a user identity --
essentially the contact
information for a user.
The three required standard keys
are present,
and the value of Type
defines this
as a user identity
asset declaration.
The Payload key contains
the user identity properties
of this asset.
The next type of declaration
is an activation.
Activations represent sets
of configurations
that the device will
atomically apply.
This means all configurations
in the set,
along with any
referenced assets,
must be valid in order
for all of them to be applied.
If any are invalid,
the activation will fail
to apply the associated policy.
Here is an example
of a simple activation
that contains
two configurations.
The three required
declaration keys are present,
and the payload contains
the set of configurations
to be atomically applied
by the activation.
Configurations are referenced
by their identifier key.
There is a many-to-many
relationship
between activations
and configurations.
Activations can refer
to multiple configurations,
and a configuration can have
multiple activations
reference it.
This many-to-many relationship
allows for complex
business logic
to be handled autonomously
by the device.
Activations can include
a predicate
that determines when
the activation state is active
or inactive on a device.
The device will only process
the configurations referenced
by an activation if
the predicate evaluates to true.
As an example,
a predicate can declare
that the particular activation
is only active
on a specific device type,
such as an iPad.
Another example is wanting
a set of policies
to apply only to a particular
version of the OS.
This allows the server
to send all the declarations
for any device states
and lets the device itself
determine which ones to apply,
making the device
even more autonomous.
As the device state changes,
the activation predicates
are reevaluated without
intervention from the server.
Policy associated with the new
device state will be applied
and any outdated policy removed.
The device here becomes
increasingly proactive.
In the absence of a predicate,
the device will always process
the configurations referenced
by the activation.
Here we have the activation
example from before,
but now there's a predicate
present,
indicating that this activation
should only have
its policy applied
when the device
is an iPad.
The last type of declaration
is a management declaration.
Management declarations are used
to convey overall management
state to the device.
This includes a declaration
describing details
about the organization
as well as a declaration
that describes
the capabilities of the server.
These declarations are helpful
for conveying static information
to the device.
And those are the four types
of declarations
for applying organization policy
to your devices.
The second pillar
of the new declarative
management data model
is the status channel.
Given the way
that declarations work,
the declared state of the device
may not match
the actual state of the device
at any point in time.
For instance, any declaration
that requires user interaction
will not apply
until that action is taken.
A good example of this
is a passcode policy,
where the user
has to take action
to create a new policy-compliant
passcode for the device.
To add visibility into
this device state transition,
we've created
the status channel.
Updates of the device state
are sent in a status report
to the server.
The server can subscribe
to specific status items,
so it only receives updates
for the changes it cares about.
Status items are identified
by key-paths,
which consist of
period-separated string tokens.
Status items can be used
as expressions
in activation predicates,
as shown in the earlier
activation predicate example.
The server subscribes
to specific status items
using status subscription
configurations.
Upon receiving
this configuration,
the device will send
an initial status report
for the subscribed status items,
and then send a report
if a subscribed item changes.
The status reports
are incremental,
so only the changed items
are reported.
The status of declarations --
whether they are applied
or not --
is always reported
to the server when changed,
without the need
for the server to subscribe.
Let's inspect a configuration
that subscribes to specific
status item updates.
This configuration subscribes
to three status items
representing the device's
operating system version,
type, and model.
When this configuration
is activated on the device,
it will send
the initial status report
for each of the newly
subscribed status items.
Status items are represented
as a JSON object,
nested by the hierarchical
components
of that corresponding key-path.
In this case, the device
reports it is on iOS 14.5.
When the user updates
the software
to the latest iOS version,
the device will report
the status change for the
operating-system version item.
The server now detects
that the device has been
upgraded to iOS 15.
The third pillar
of the declarative data model
is extensibility.
Given the long life cycle of
Apple products, it is essential
to maintain compatibility
between different versions
of your MDM solution
with Apple devices,
especially as software updates
and new hardware models
are released.
With declarative management,
both the device and server
now advertise supported
capabilities to each other.
Each knows when it can start
taking advantage of new features
without having
to hardcode software version
or hardware dependencies.
The capabilities that the server
and client both advertise
includes a list
of supported features
representing both minor
and major protocol updates.
The client also advertises
supported payloads,
which lists the full set of
declarations and status items
supported by the client.
The server's capabilities
are sent to the device
via a management declaration.
When the server is upgraded,
it synchronizes all new
capabilities to the device
just as it would
any other type of declaration.
The device is immediately
able to take advantage
of the server's new features.
The client's capabilities
are sent to the server
as a specific status item
any time capabilities change.
This way,
the server can immediately
start taking advantage
of the device's new features
and payloads.
Building extensibility
into the declarative data model
ensures that
declarative management
is built for the present
and the future.
Now that you understand
the data model,
let's dig into how
declarative management
is seamlessly integrated
within the MDM protocol.
Existing MDM vendors can use
declarative management features
starting today.
Declarative management is
integrated into the MDM protocol
and utilizes it
for managing the enrollment
and unenrollment process and
for handling the HTTP transport
and device and user
authentication.
Existing and mature MDM products
can smoothly transition
to declarative management
without a disruptive change
to adopt a new protocol
or server infrastructure.
Declarations
and the status channel coexist
with your already in-use
MDM commands and profiles
in an extensible way.
This allows you to gradually
adopt the different features
of declarative management
without having to update all of
your MDM workflows at once.
For example,
a server could choose
to only implement
status subscriptions,
effectively adding a status
channel to the MDM protocol
without having to adopt
all of declarative management.
When the device
is unenrolled from MDM,
all declarations are removed,
and the device state
is adjusted accordingly.
Importantly,
declarative management
does not impact existing
MDM behavior at all.
Actually, declarative management
leverages existing MDM behaviors
using an MDM command
for activation
and an MDM CheckIn request
for synchronization
and status reports.
Let's zoom in
on each of these next.
A DeclarativeManagement
command has been added to MDM.
This command serves
two purposes.
First, it activates the
declarative management features
on the device.
Please note, once turned on,
declarative management
cannot be turned off.
However, the server
can remove all declarations
to effectively disable
declarative management.
Second, the command
can include a payload
containing
synchronization tokens
that will initiate a
synchronization flow if needed.
There is also a new DeclarativeManagement
CheckIn request type
used by the device
when synchronizing declarations
and to send status reports
to the server.
Here is an example
of the new CheckIn request type.
The MessageType key is set
to the new
DeclarativeManagement value.
The endpoint key
is set to a value
indicating that the client
is making a request
to retrieve the declaration
manifest data from the server.
Some requests --
such as this status report --
can also include
Base64-encoded data.
When using the CheckIn request
to synchronize declarations,
there will be a response
from the server.
There are two types
of responses: a manifest,
which lists the identifier
and server token properties
of all declarations
that the server defines;
and single declarations
for the device to apply.
Now that you've learned how to
activate declarative management
and synchronize declarations
with a CheckIn request,
let's talk about how you can
migrate your policies gradually
from profiles to declarations.
There's a declaration type
specifically for sending
and installing profiles
as configurations.
This enables you to utilize
the full suite of MDM profiles
to immediately take advantage
of declarative management
by shifting profile-based
policy logic to the device.
Here is an example
of a profile configuration.
The profile is referenced
via URL.
When this configuration
is activated,
the profile is fetched from the
URL and installed on the device.
We've taken these steps to make
declarative management
easy to adopt today
with the iOS 15 beta.
Now let's go through an example
of how declarative management
interacts with the server.
First, we activate
declarative management.
This starts with the device
already enrolled in MDM.
The server sends a push
notification to the device.
The device responds
to the push in the usual way,
by sending a ServerURL
endpoint request
with its status set to Idle.
The server then responds
with the DeclarativeManagement
command.
Upon receipt,
the device activates
declarative management.
After processing the
DeclarativeManagement command,
the device sends an Acknowledged
status back to the server.
Then if the server
has no more commands,
it will return
an empty response.
The device then starts
its declarative management
synchronization process;
let's go through that next.
The device first sends
a CheckIn request
with the endpoint key
set to declaration-items.
The server responds
with a manifest
containing declaration metadata.
The device then compares
the items in the manifest
to the set of declarations
it previously received
from the server.
Through this comparison,
the device can tell
which declarations are new,
which have changed,
and which have
been removed.
For each new
or changed declaration,
the device sends
a CheckIn request.
This request's EndPoint key
is set to a path
uniquely identifying
the declaration resource.
The server then responds
with the JSON object
representing that declaration.
Once all declarations have been
fetched from the server,
the device starts applying
the policy changes
represented by this updated
state of declarations.
Once the policy changes
have been applied,
the device will send
a status report to the server,
with the corresponding
updated status items.
To help get you started,
let's go through
what we are shipping in iOS 15.
The declarative management
feature is supported on devices
with iOS 15 and iPadOS 15.
It's also only available
when the MDM enrollment type
is a user enrollment --
either the new onboarding flow
introduced with iOS 15,
or the flow from iOS 13.
For configurations,
we have account
and passcode configurations
that cover the equivalent set
of MDM account
and passcode profile payloads.
We also support profile
configurations
enabling you to start installing
the full suite
of MDM-supported profiles
to your devices declaratively.
Status subscription
configurations
are also available today
and are used for the server
to declare the specific status
item updates
it wants to receive.
There is one type
of activation available today.
This simple activation
defines a list of configurations
that must be applied atomically
and may include
an optional predicate.
For asset declarations,
there are two types available:
user identity assets,
which represent a user's
contact information;
and user credential assets,
which contain user IDs and
passwords for user accounts.
For management declarations,
we are supporting two types:
organization details
and server capabilities.
Next, here are the status items
available today.
Each declaration
has its own status item
that is automatically sent
to the server from the device.
Also available
are a set of status items
that cover basic properties
of the device,
like details about a device's
hardware model
and its operating system.
For more detail on these
declarations and status items,
check out Apple's
Device Management
developer documentation.
Today we covered
the new paradigm
of declarative management
and its functionality,
discovering how declarative
management empowers you
to make devices more autonomous
and proactive.
We learned how to integrate
declarative management
into your MDM solution.
We went through an example
showing how declarative
management works
and reviewed how declarative
management is ready for you
to start using today.
We can't wait to find out how
you'll reinvent MDM solutions
with declarative management.
Thanks for joining me
and have a great WWDC.
♪