[music]
[Marl]
Hi, and welcome.
My name is Marl, and I'm
on the Shazam Product team.
I hope you're enjoying WWDC21,
and I'm here to introduce you
to ShazamKit,
the framework
that gives you the ability
to integrate audio
recognition into your apps.
Today I'll take you
through what ShazamKit is
and a few use cases
for applying it.
Then, I'll turn it over
to my colleague James,
who will show you how Shazam
catalog recognition works
and offer tips
for getting started.
Let's start
with what ShazamKit is.
You might already be familiar
with Shazam,
the audio recognition app
that debuted in 2008
as one of the first apps
in the App Store.
13 years later,
the app's grown quite a bit,
and Shazam is even used
as a verb.
Its technology powers
Siri's What Song is This
and is integrated in Shortcuts
and Control Center.
That core technology is
audio recognition--
precise and almost instantaneous
audio matching--
even with noise
in the background.
Recognition is achieved
by listening
for the distinct acoustic
signature of the audio
and searching for an exact match
either within Shazam's own
catalog of content
or within custom audio catalogs
that you will
now be able to create.
Unlike SoundAnalysis, however,
Shazam isn't
an audio classifer detecting
and analyzing classes of speech,
singing, or humming.
In fact, Shazam doesn't
identify specific sounds,
like laughter or applause,
in audio at all.
James will take you through
Shazam's recognition process
in a few minutes,
and if you'd like to learn
about detecting
and classifying sounds,
check out the SoundAnalysis
session as well.
In the meantime, let's talk
more about ShazamKit,
the framework that brings
the recognition functionality
to your apps.
ShazamKit is divided
into three components.
There's Shazam
catalog recognition,
custom catalog recognition,
and library management.
Shazam catalog recognition
gives you the ability
to add song identification
to your apps.
With custom catalog recognition,
you can take this a step further
and perform on-device matching
against arbitrary audio.
This session will focus
primarily
on Shazam catalogue recognition
and library management,
but be sure to code
along with our colleague Alex,
who will show you how to
"Create custom audio experiences
for your apps."
Next, I'll take you through some
of the amazing opportunities
we see for you to leverage
ShazamKit across your apps.
Let's start with finding
the perfect selfie.
They can be fun to take
and even more fun
when creating a specific mood
or ambiance.
Shazam catalog
recognition can help
by recognizing the song
playing in the environment
and fetching song metadata
like song title and artist.
However, you can also create
a slightly different experience,
or vibe, so your selfie goes
beyond listening
and taping from your couch.
The ShazamKit API also
returns metadata like genre,
which you can use
to simulate enjoying that song
at a club downtown instead.
ShazamKit also
recognizes more than music,
which can be useful useful in
the context of virtual learning.
Remote schooling can
create different challenges
for teachers and students,
including keeping up
with on-screen lessons
and navigating between apps.
Custom catalog recognition
presents an opportunity
to make your education app
experience even more seamless
for them.
By using
the lesson content's audio
as a kind of remote control,
the framework
can trigger synced activities
in student apps as content
streams over video conference.
Teachers can rest easier knowing
students' apps follow along,
even after pausing or repeating
portions of the lesson.
If you enjoy home improvement
television as much as I do,
you'll appreciate the challenge
of trying to search
for furniture as quickly as
the pieces flash by on screen.
Use ShazamKit to make
your show or video shoppable
with an interactive
second screen AR experience.
Whether watching in real time
or on demand,
viewers at home can
synchronously browse,
simulate, and purchase styles
as they watch.
Now let's try this out
in real life.
You ever watch videos
of moments
that you and your friends
have shared
and wish you knew the songs
playing in the background?
Here's one, for example,
that my friend sent me
to compare our Friday nights.
[music] Don't know anyone
who makes me catch a vibe,
Feel the frequency,
catch a vibe, only you and me.
[Marl] Using ShazamKit, my app
kicked off the recognition
and found the audio
match in Shazam's catalog.
Now that I know
which song was playing,
I can save it to a library
or use it to start
the perfect weekend playlist.
Now here's James
to show you how Shazam
catalog recognition works.
[James]
Thanks, Marl, and hi, everyone.
I'm James, an engineering
manager on the Shazam team.
Today I'm going to take you
through how ShazamKit was used
to recognize the music
in Marl's video.
So what happened
when Marl pressed
the Identify Song button?
ShazamKit sent a representation
of the audio
in the video to Shazam's server.
A match was found
in Shazam's music catalog,
and information about the song
was returned,
which we displayed in our app.
Let's take a closer look
at how Shazam matches audio.
It is important to note
that Shazam does not match
against the audio itself.
Rather, it creates
a lossy representation of it,
which we call a signature,
and matches against that.
There are two benefits
to this approach.
Firstly, a signature is at least
an order of magnitude smaller
than the audio
from which it was derived.
This greatly reduces the amount
of data
that needs to be sent
over the network.
Secondly,
signatures are not invertible,
which means
that the original audio
cannot be reconstructed
from a given signature.
This is very important
for protecting the privacy
of our customers.
So what does a signature
sound like?
Let me play one and see
if you can identify the song.
[bleeps and bloops]
That's right.
It's "My Future"
by Billie Eilish.
You can even try Shazaming it
for yourself.
Now let's talk about catalogs.
Catalogs are collections
of signatures.
Of course, signatures
in a catalog are not very useful
without some associated metadata
describing the audio
from which they were generated.
We will refer to these
as reference signatures,
as the metadata is a reference
back to the original audio.
The Shazam catalog
is a collection
of reference signatures
comprising much
of the world's music.
It lives in the cloud
and is hosted
and maintained by Apple.
It is regularly updated
with the latest tracks.
Every signature
in the Shazam catalog
has been generated from
the full audio of a song
and has
a corresponding reference
to that song's metadata.
Now, what if you wanted
to match against your own audio?
In this case,
you could use a custom catalog.
These are collections
of signatures which have been
generated from arbitrary audio,
not just music,
and you can add your own
custom metadata to them.
As opposed to the Shazam catalog
which lives in the cloud,
matching custom catalogs
takes place within your app.
Watch the code-along
"Creating custom audio
experiences with ShazamKit"
to learn more.
When you want
to search a catalog,
you need a query signature,
which is a representation
of a small part of the audio
that you want to match.
In this app,
it's the part of the audio
that includes the song.
In this visualization,
a query signature has
been compared
against a reference signature,
which represents
the complete audio of a song,
and a match has been found.
This same process occurs
for every song
in Shazam's catalog
to identify matching candidates.
So going back to that first
diagram, we now know
that we sent a query signature
over the network to be matched
against the Shazam catalog,
which is a collection
of reference signatures
and song information.
When Marl
pressed the Identify button,
a match was found and
the song information returned.
Now, the great thing about
ShazamKit is that it handles all
of this for you
through the session object.
A session can take as input
either audio or signatures.
Results are communicated
via its delegate.
Before you can match
against the Shazam catalog,
you will need to enable
the ShazamKit App Service
for your app identifier
in the Developer portal.
This step is not necessary
for matching
against custom catalogs.
OK, let's see what
this looks like in code.
First,
I create a session object.
Its default initializer
will match
against the Shazam catalog.
Next, I set its delegate
so that I can be notified
of any matches
that might be found.
If you were matching against
continuous stream of audio,
for example, from a microphone,
we recommend you use
the matchStreamingBuffer
method on the session
as it is optimized
for that scenario.
However, in our case,
I already have access
to the complete audio
in the video,
so I'm going
to create a signature generator
and pass the audio to it.
When I'm ready
to perform a match,
I will call the signature
method on the generator
to convert the audio
I've passed into a signature.
Then I hand
the generated signature
to the match method
of the session object.
Back to our app.
After generating a signature
from the audio
and using a session
to find a matching song
in Shazam's catalog,
the next step is
to display the song information.
Earlier,
I described how catalogs
are made up
of signatures and metadata.
In the case
of the Shazam catalog,
this metadata
is song information,
such as the title
and artist of the track,
and other properties
like its album art.
In ShazamKit, the object
that represents this information
is called a media item.
For signatures
that have just been matched,
you are also returned
extra information,
such as whereabouts in the audio
the match occurred
and any difference in frequency
between the matched
and original audio.
This is called
a matched media item
and is a subclass of media item.
In the previous code example,
I set the session delegate.
When performing a match,
we can rely on it to inform us
of success, no match,
or an error.
It is possible for a signature
to match multiple tracks.
These are represented as
an array of matched media items.
In our app code,
we will take the first one.
Now we can start setting some
of the properties returned.
The album art was fetched
using the artworkURL property.
The name of the song and
the performer were populated
from the title
and artist properties.
As the song matched is available
in the Apple Music catalog,
and its details are
being displayed,
attribution needs to be given
as set out
in the Apple Music
Identity Guidelines.
In the app, we've added
a button that launches
the Apple Music URL
returned by the media item.
A customer that has
recognized a song in your app
may wish to save this
in their Shazam library.
The Shazam library is accessible
from the Shazam app
if installed,
or by long-pressing
on the Music Recognition
Control Center module,
and it is synced across devices.
Let's try this out.
First, I'm going to long press
on the Music Recognition
Control Center module.
It shows that I've already
got a few songs in there.
Next, I'll tap the plus button
in the app
to add the matched song
to that list.
Now I'll reopen my library
and check it's been added.
Great, it's in there,
and the name of my app shows up
as the source of the match.
And here's
what the code looks like.
SHMediaLibrary
offers a default instance
that corresponds
to a customer's Shazam library.
This is stored end-to-end
encrypted and is only available
on devices that have enabled
two-factor authentication.
The library only accepts items
that correspond
to a song in the Shazam catalog.
There is no special permission
required to write
to the Shazam library,
but we strongly recommend
you avoid storing content in it
without making customers aware.
All songs saved in
the library will be attributed
to the app that added them.
There are many
more properties exposed
on the MediaItem
that we've made available
for you to explore,
such as matchOffset,
which shows whereabouts
in the song a match was made.
In addition,
the new MusicKit framework
provides strongly typed objects
describing a song
and its relationships.
We've made this available
to you in Swift
as the Songs property.
For more details,
you can check out
the "Meet MusicKit for Swift"
session.
So now we have
the complete picture.
We sent an audio signature
to match
against the Shazam catalog
using a session
to manage that process.
The session then
returned song information
in the form of a matched
media item via its delegate.
We also offered a customer
of our app the option
to add it
to their Shazam library.
Now I'll hand back to Marl,
who'll take you
through some best practices.
Over to you, Marl.
[Marl]
Thank you, James.
Now that you know what
ShazamKit is, how it works,
and how to apply it,
you're ready to start building.
As you get started
implementing with ShazamKit,
consider these best practices.
First, if you're matching
against real-time audio,
say, from a microphone,
then use matchStreamingBuffer.
It's simpler and handles lots
of the underlying logic
for generating
well-scoped signatures.
Next, if your use case
requires the microphone,
stop recording as soon
as you have the result you need.
That way, you'll avoid consuming
unnecessary resources
or launching the microphone for
longer than customers intend.
Finally, before writing
to a customer's library,
we strongly recommend providing
the option for the customer
to opt in and clarifying this
behavior right from the start.
I hope you enjoyed
getting to know ShazamKit.
We can't wait to see
the magical experiences
and features you create.
All of the information
we discussed and links
to documentation
are attached to this session,
so you're ready to get going.
And don't forget
to try the code-along
with custom catalog recognition.
Thanks for joining.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC21.
[music]