[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Graham Seyffert: Hello
and welcome to WWDC 2021.
My name is Graham Seyffert,
and I’m a MusicKit engineer.
Over the past few years,
we’ve enhanced the ability
of developers
to fetch new, enriched data
from the Apple Music catalog.
Today we’re excited
to introduce
some of those
improvements to you.
In this presentation,
we’ll be going over enhancements
to the search functionality
in the API,
as well as new ways
to request data
by relating resources,
extending attributes,
and requesting
relationship views
for resources in your responses.
Finally, we’ll go over some new
enhancements to the Charts API.
Before going over some
of the search enhancements,
I’d like to quickly recap the
current /search/hints endpoint.
You might already use
this endpoint today
to fetch a list
of suggested search terms.
As an example, here’s some
results you might get back
for the search term “taylor”.
Today, we’re introducing the
/search/suggestions endpoint
which replaces
the /search/hints endpoint.
This endpoint provides access
to the same terms
as the /search/hints endpoint,
and you can continue to fetch
these by specifying kinds=terms
on your request.
However, you can see that
the response from this endpoint
is a bit different.
suggested results
now indicate their kind,
which will match one of the
kinds specified on the request.
It also differentiates the term
that should be used
for the search query
from the term that should be
displayed to the user.
More importantly, this endpoint
now also allows access
to the top suggested
search results --
ideal for powering
typeahead results.
These may be requested
by specifying kinds=topResults
on the request,
as well as some resource types
that you’re interested in
fetching results for.
Resources for topResults kinds
can be found
under the content key.
It’s worth noting
that the results
you’ll get from this endpoint
might be noticeably different
from the results you’d get
from a regular search,
as this response prioritizes
speed over breadth.
As such, this is not intended
to be a replacement
for the regular
/search endpoint,
but rather a complement to it.
Before going into
how to modify resources,
I’d like to reintroduce
what a resource is
for those
that may not be familiar.
All resources have what we call
a “resource identifier,”
which is the minimal amount
of information you’d need
in order to look a resource up
in the API.
Resource identifiers will
include a resource’s ID,
its type, and its href.
The complete representation
of a resource
will also include
that resource’s attributes,
such as its name,
and potentially relationships
if they’ve been requested
using the include parameter.
Relationships are collections
of related resources,
such as a song’s genres
or a playlist’s tracks.
With that,
I’d like to now introduce the
concept of relating resources.
Relationships requested
with relate
are different from relationships
requested with include
in that they only return
the aforementioned
Resource Identifiers
for the resources
in that relationship.
This means that relating
a relationship
results in a faster response
if all you need access to
is a resource's reference.
You can relate a relationship by
using the relate query parameter
and classifying it with the
resource type you’re targeting,
followed by a list
of relationship names
you’re interested
in getting back.
For example, on the
/search /suggestions endpoint,
you may decide that when a user
selects a song result
that you want to pop out
to the album page for that song.
In this case, all you need is
the href for that song’s album
in order to navigate there,
so we can specify
relate[songs]=albums
in order to get that data.
After doing that, we can see
that song results
in our response now
include the resource identifiers
for their respective albums.
So relate is great to use when
we want to quickly reference
additional related content,
but what if we want to learn
more about the resources
we’re already getting back
in our responses?
As mentioned previously,
every resource today has
a default set of attributes --
things like its name,
its artwork, et cetera.
But resources may also
have extended attributes.
Extended attributes are either
more expensive to calculate
or are less frequently needed,
such that including them
by default
might either slow down
responses noticeably
or bloat the object model.
Similar to what we just saw
with the relate query param,
you can request extended
attributes on resources
by using the extend query param,
classifying it
with a resource type,
and following it
with a list of attribute names
that you’re interested in.
Building on our /suggestions
request,
we might decide that,
for song results,
we also want to allow users
the ability
to link out to that artist’s
page on Apple Music.
In order to do this,
you could simply append
extend[songs]=artistUrl
to your request.
Indeed, after doing this,
we can see the songs resources
in our responses
now include
the artistUrl attribute.
Now I’d like to introduce the
concept of relationship views.
Compared to relationships,
views are more loosely coupled
to their resource.
They don’t necessarily represent
some ground truth
about a resource
like relationships do.
This makes views ideally suited
for driving product page
experiences,
such as an album page.
Compare this to relationships
which may be useful to use on,
for instance,
search result pages.
Additionally, views may have
attributes -- like a title --
as well as data.
Views are also only requestable
on direct resource fetches.
This means that there
are two different ways
you can fetch them.
You can either use
the views query parameter
and specify a list,
or a single one
via /view/
right after the resource’s ID
in the request path.
In this response,
we have an example
of what it might look like
to include the Top Songs view
on an artist resource.
Other examples include
Top Music Videos
or an artist’s singles.
The full list of supported views
for a given resource type
can of course be found
in the official Apple Music API
documentation.
Finally, let’s take a look at
the updates to the Charts API.
Today, Apple Music supports
chart playlists for the world,
storefronts, and more recently,
specific cities.
Users can add these chart
playlists to their libraries,
which will update automatically.
You can now fetch these directly
from the /charts endpoint
by specifying types=playlists
and using the "with"
query parameter
to indicate
which sets you’d like --
either dailyGlobalTopCharts
or cityCharts, or both.
And here we have an example
of how a chart’s response
with those query parameters
might look.
So in summary,
today we went over enhancements
to the search
and charts endpoints,
and looked at new ways
to fetch data for resources
in our responses.
If you’d like to learn more
about the Apple Music API,
I’d highly suggest
this year’s session
on how to Cross reference
content on the Apple Music API,
or 2017’s Introducing MusicKit
presentation,
which goes over some
of the API’s core concepts
in even greater detail.
Thanks so much for watching,
and we hope you enjoy
this year’s WWDC.
♪