[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Tanu Singhal: Hello, everyone.
My name is Tanu,
and I'm a SwiftUI engineer
on the Apple TV team.
Today, we'll talk about
some new ways
of working with focus
in SwiftUI.
One of the great things
about SwiftUI
is how much functionality
you get for free,
right out of the box.
Built-in components
base their default behavior
on SwiftUI's knowledge
of platform conventions,
resulting in
an overall experience
that is sensible and familiar
in various contexts.
We see this intelligence
at work when we look at focus.
Focus is the system
that lets your app
take input from keyboards,
remotes, game controllers,
accessible switch controls,
and other sources that --
unlike touch inputs --
are not tied to specific
screen coordinates.
Often, the focus view is drawn
with special embellishments,
making it easy
for people to predict
where their input
will be directed.
For the most part, SwiftUI
manages focus on your behalf.
When someone clicks
in a text field
or presses the Tab key
or when someone taps
an adjustable watch complication
or swipes on the Siri Remote,
SwiftUI decides
how focus is affected
and how its next placement
is indicated.
This is great for simple cases
where the right behavior
can be decided by convention.
There are, however,
some cases where you may want
a more accelerated experience
around focus.
In this example
from the Notes app,
when we select
the new note button,
we want focus to automatically
move to the newly created note.
This type of behavior certainly
requires custom implementation.
Over here, we have a scenario
in which we want to move focus
from a button
on the bottom-left side
to content near
the top of the screen
when a user swipes right
on the remote.
Since the Music button
and the App tiles
are not adjacent to each other,
SwiftUI cannot automatically
guess where to move focus.
It needs more information
before distant focus targets
can be linked.
And in this example from iOS,
we simply want the keyboard
to go away
when a user selects an event.
Thanks to new APIs
we're introducing this year,
you can now do all of this
in SwiftUI.
In this talk, we will focus on
two kinds of use cases.
We'll see how we can move focus
to a particular view
without any direct input,
and we'll make large navigation
targets out of small views
so that nothing is
out of the user's reach.
Let's first look an example
where we may want to move focus
to help direct
the user's attention.
We're so ready
to go on a vacation,
and we've started working on
a vacation planner app.
This app works across
all Apple platforms,
and it allows you
to browse destinations
as well as book trips.
When you launch this app,
we present an email field,
a password field,
and a Sign in with Apple button
so you can log
into your account.
On this login screen, if we
discover that the email entered
was not in the correct format,
we want to programmatically move
focus back to the email field.
To accomplish this behavior,
we'll use the FocusState APIs.
The existing code
for our login view
contains a VStack that has
a TextField and a SecureField.
Now, we'll add a FocusState
property wrapper to this view.
FocusState is a new API that
we have introduced this year!
This is a special type of state
that changes
depending on the current
location of focus.
We'll use FocusState
to hold an identifier
for the field that is focused.
The focusedField variable is of
an enum type that we created
for this example.
You can use strings, integers,
or any other hashable value type
for FocusState.
Note that the FocusState
value is optional.
In general,
types used for FocusState
must be both hashable
and optional,
with nil used for cases
where focus
is in an unrelated
part of the screen.
Next we'll add
a focused modifier
to the TextField
and the SecureField.
Also new this year,
this modifier creates a link
between the placement of focus
and the value of
the focusedField property.
This simple link
is a powerful tool,
because it means you can use
the current placement of focus
for making other decisions
in your app.
We can watch that play out
in our login form.
When the screen first appears,
nothing has focus,
so the value of focusedField
is nil.
But if someone then taps
on the email text field,
that field gains focus
and the keyboard appears.
Since the focused text field is
bound to a FocusState value,
the value of focusedField
will automatically be updated
to hold the identifier
for the email text field.
The link between focus placement
and FocusState works both ways.
This means
that we are not limited
to reacting to focus changes;
we can move focus
programmatically
just by updating
our FocusState property.
So for example, if we
programmatically set the value
of focusedField to .password,
SwiftUI will know
that our SecureField
is associated with
the new value we're setting
and focus will automatically
move to the password field.
Now that our focus bindings
are in place,
we can put them to work.
In the Vacation Planner app,
when a user submits their data,
we want to validate it.
If the email is not
in the expected format,
we set the focusedField
to email.
This will send focus back
to the email text field,
if it's not there already.
Further, we'd like to highlight
the email field with a border
if the email was invalid.
We want this border to appear
only while focus
is on the email field.
To do that, we can easily read
the value of focusedField
when we create the border.
Let's see how
this all comes together.
Note the email field doesn't
have a valid address.
Focus is currently
on the password field.
When we hit Go, the onSubmit
callback is triggered
where the focusedField is set.
This causes the cursor to
move back to the email field.
While the email
field is focused,
we see the red border around it.
However, once we move focus
away from the email field,
our focusedField is no longer
equal to the email identifier,
and so the red border
disappears.
In the scenario where
all the form data is valid,
we want to simply
dismiss the keyboard.
To dismiss the keyboard,
we will set our
FocusState variable to nil.
Since the focusedField
is an optional,
we use nil to indicate
that focus has left this view.
In the video, notice that the
email address has been updated.
This time when we submit,
the keyboard gets dismissed
since we have set
the FocusState variable to nil.
We've seen how it can be helpful
to programmatically
control focus
when our app has text fields.
However, FocusStates
are not just for text fields.
They can be used to
programmatically control focus
for any focusable view on iOS,
tvOS, watchOS, or macOS!
In the next section,
we'll discuss the role
of focus-based navigation
in our apps.
Let's take a look
at the tvOS version
of our Vacation Planner app.
We have leveraged
the extra space on TV
by adding photos
from some destinations
that you may want to visit.
You can view more photos
by clicking the
Browse Photos button
even before you've logged in.
Notice that focus is initially
on the Email field.
If we swipe right
on the Siri Remote,
we'd expect focus to move
to the Browse Photos button.
However, that doesn't work
by default.
This is because
directional focus navigation
is based on
adjacency relationships.
When swiping to move focus,
focus will only move if there is
something adjacent and focusable
in the given direction.
Take a look at the focusable
views in this app.
Since there's no focusable view
adjacent to the login fields
on the left,
the button on the bottom
is unreachable.
To make this screen navigable,
we will extend the Browse
button's focusable area,
so it becomes adjacent
to the login fields.
This is done using
the new FocusSections API.
Let's see how easy that is.
Here we have
a simplified version
of the Vacation Planner code
for TV.
It contains an HStack
with two VStacks;
one for the login fields,
and another VStack
for the image and the button.
We want to create a larger
logical focus target
around the button
so focus can behave
as if the button was adjacent
to the login fields.
This can be done by simply
adding a focusSection() modifier
to the VStack
that contains the button.
When focusSection() modifier
is added to any view,
the frame of that view becomes
capable of accepting focus
if it contains
any focusable subviews.
Since we also want to move focus
back to the login fields
when swiping left
on the button,
we'll add another focusSection()
modifier to the first VStack.
Now when we run this app,
users can move focus
between the input fields
and the Browse button
by swiping left and right
on the remote.
As we wrap things up,
I'd encourage you
to think about focus,
which can often look different
on different platforms.
SwiftUI has great
default behaviors
built in for most cases.
The new focus states
and FocusSections APIs
can help you
take advantage of focus
to create even more
streamlined experiences.
As you work on your apps,
take a moment to observe
the many ways
in which focus impacts
user behavior.
We hope this session
has equipped you with the tools
that'll help users focus
on what's most important.
Thanks for watching,
and have an awesome WWDC!
♪