[upbeat music]
Donna: Hi.
I'm Donna Tom,
and I'm a TextKit engineer.
My colleague Chris Willmore will
join me later in this video.
We're introducing TextKit 2,
Apple's next-generation
text engine.
To understand
what TextKit 2 is all about,
let's briefly review
the original TextKit,
which we'll call TextKit 1.
TextKit 1 is a text engine
that drives text layout
and display
across all of Apple's platforms.
Text controls in UIKit
and AppKit use TextKit 1
to manage the storage
and control the layout
of text content.
TextKit 1 first appeared
on the system in OpenStep
over 20 years ago.
It's grown and evolved with us
over the years
from macOS 10.0
to iOS 7
to macOS 11 and iOS 14.
It's pretty amazing
that TextKit 1 still powers
so much essential functionality
across all Apple devices.
Technology design and
engineering principles
have changed a lot
over the decades.
Since TextKit 1 is tied
to its original principles,
it's become more challenging
over the years
to provide APIs
that integrate well
with our newer technologies
while still delivering
a high standard of performance.
That's why
we've built TextKit 2.
TextKit 2 is Apple's
next-generation text engine,
built on a set
of forward-looking
design principles.
And guess what?
You're already
using TextKit 2 on your Mac.
In Big Sur,
we updated many of the text
components across the OS
to use TextKit 2
behind the scenes.
Big surprise:
you've been using TextKit 2
since macOS 11.
Now, let's briefly review
the architecture
that let us do this.
TextKit 2 coexists
with TextKit 1.
Just like its predecessor,
TextKit 2
is built on top of Foundation,
Quartz, and Core Text.
Text controls in UIKit
and AppKit
are built on top of TextKit 2.
TextKit 2 also loosely
retains the MVC design
of its predecessor.
The view portion remains
in the view objects
of the UIKit
and AppKit frameworks,
while there are new versions
of our old friends,
NSTextStorage
and NSLayoutManager.
In addition
to these new versions,
there are many more
new classes and protocols
joining the model
and controller layers.
There are a quite a few of them,
but don't be alarmed.
These new components are simple,
focused,
and powerful in combination.
They make it easier
for you to express
what you want
to do with your text
and worry less about
how the system accomplishes
what you want.
Now that we've gotten
an architectural view
of the system,
let's dive into the details.
First, we're going to discuss
the core design principles
of TextKit 2
and how these principles
will change the way you think
about customizing the storage,
layout, and display
of text in your apps.
After that,
Chris will walk you through
a TextKit 2 sample app
we've created
to collaborate
on a book of recipes.
This app uses
the new TextKit 2 classes
to lay out and display text
in CALayers.
Here, you'll get to learn
how the design principles work
in practice.
Finally,
we'll cover some
important technical details
for modernizing your apps
for TextKit 2.
So let's get started
with the design principles.
The core high-level
design principles of TextKit 2
are correctness,
safety, and performance.
We've taken a balanced approach.
All three principles
are important,
so there is no priority
to the order
in which we discuss them.
Each of these
high-level design principles
informs a specific design change
in the system.
For correctness, TextKit 2
abstracts away glyph handling.
For safety,
TextKit 2 places a heavier focus
on value semantics.
And for performance,
TextKit 2 uses
viewport-based layout
and rendering.
We'll begin with correctness.
In this area, we've abstracted
away glyph handling
to provide
a consistent experience
for international text.
Apple devices are used
everywhere around the world,
so it's really important
to provide correct layout,
rendering,
and interaction for text
in all languages and scripts.
We want everyone to be able
to read and interact
with text on their devices.
And the design
of some of the TextKit 1 APIs
makes it difficult
to work with international text
in a way
that's universally correct.
To understand why,
we first need to understand
what a glyph is.
A glyph
is a visual representation
of a variable number
of characters.
In many Western languages,
one glyph usually represents
one character,
but this is not always true.
You can have multiple glyphs
representing a single character,
or it could be
the other way around.
A single glyph could represent
multiple characters.
This single glyph
used to represent
multiple characters
is called a ligature.
There aren't too many ligatures
in Western languages,
and they don't usually affect
the legibility of the text.
You can still read it
just fine without ligatures.
But that's not true
for all languages.
Scripts like Arabic
and Devanagari
use lots of ligatures,
and they do affect
the legibility.
Check out this word
in Arabic script.
It's an Urdu word
that means "moment."
Now take a moment
to compare these two renderings.
The full word,
drawn with ligatures
on the right,
appears very different
from the individual characters
on the left.
Native readers of the language
would consider the version
on the left to be illegible.
Many of the APIs in TextKit 1
require working with
a glyph index or range.
For example,
to get the bounding rectangle
of some text,
you need to know the glyph range
of the text you want.
If the text is
in a Western language,
figuring out the right
glyph range isn't too bad.
In this English example,
it's pretty easy to find
the glyph range
for the first four characters
of the text.
Now consider Kannada,
a script and language
spoken by millions
of people in India.
Not only does it use
lots of ligatures,
the glyphs can be reordered
and combined
in all sorts
of interesting ways.
This Kannada word
meaning "October"
features a split vowel
at character index four,
so that gets split up
into two glyphs.
Then the one on the left
gets reordered
between the glyphs representing
characters one and two
before the ligature
for two is applied.
The glyph representing
the character at index three
also gets substituted
to a conjoining form.
In the final word,
it's drawn below
one of the glyphs
in the split vowel.
Now,
if you didn't understand
any of what I just said,
that is totally OK.
These are details
that the framework
should be handling for you
so that you can focus
on building your app.
The point is,
it's not possible
to find the glyph range
for the first four characters
of text like this.
There is no single glyph range
that will represent
those four characters.
And since many TextKit 1 APIs
require a glyph range,
using those APIs
can potentially break
layout and rendering
for complex scripts like this.
And that's why TextKit 2
abstracts away glyph handling.
TextKit 2 renders
all text with Core Text--
so you'll automatically
get correct rendering
for complex scripts.
You won't have to manage glyphs
at all with TextKit 2.
Instead,
you use higher-level objects
to control text layout
and interactions.
Meet NSTextSelection,
one of these
higher-level objects.
It contains
all the necessary context
to represent a text selection,
such as its granularity,
its affinity,
and the possibly disjoint
ranges of text
that make up the selection.
These properties
on NSTextSelection
are read only,
so you won't modify instances
of the selection object
to change them.
Instead,
you use an instance
of NSTextSelectionNavigation
to perform actions
on text selections,
receiving new instances
of NSTextSelection
that represent
the resulting selection.
You can ask
the navigation object
to give you selections
resulting from tap
or mouse-down events
at a point on the screen
or get a new selection resulting
from navigating forward
or backward.
This makes it easier
to do things,
like extend
the selection forward
by one word
and get the correct result,
accounting
for bidirectional text
in right-to-left languages.
Now I wanna call your attention
to something interesting
about these new selection APIs.
This method takes
a NSTextLocation.
This is another new object
in TextKit 2.
Meet NSTextLocation
and NSTextRange.
These are very similar
to the UITextPosition
and UITextRange classes
from UIKit,
except you're not required
to subclass them.
Most of the time,
you'll use the default location
and range objects
with TextKit 2.
Using objects
instead of integers
allows for more
expressive document models
because the ranges are defined
in terms of locations
relative to each other.
The HTML document object model
is a good example of this.
Since it has nested elements,
a location needs to represent
both the absolute position
in the document
and also the position
in the visible text.
This can't be expressed
with a single numerical index.
And that's it for correctness.
Next up is safety.
In this area,
we've designed TextKit 2
with a greater emphasis
on value semantics
to better align
with the goals of technologies
like Swift and SwiftUI.
And when I say
"value semantics,"
I'm not talking
about value types.
We did not make
NSLayoutManager into a struct.
Value types keep
a unique copy of their data,
which prevents
mutation of that data.
This makes your code safer
and more stable
by removing unintended sharing
and associated side effects.
But value types
are not the only way
to get this benefit.
Immutable classes
have properties
that cannot be changed
after initialization,
which also prevents
mutation of their data.
These classes
behave like value types,
so we refer to them
as having value semantics.
If you want to change the data
in one of these objects,
you have to make
a brand-new instance
to replace the original one.
And many of the classes
in TextKit 2
are designed in this way.
To illustrate the benefits
of this design change,
let's refresh our memory
on the design of TextKit 1.
The flow of text
from the storage to the screen
used to work like this.
Updates to the text storage
notified the layout manager,
which would then
generate glyphs,
position them, and draw them
directly into the view.
With this approach of drawing
glyphs directly into the view,
it's difficult to figure out
where to separate the text
to create spaces
for custom drawing.
To understand
what I mean by that,
check out
this sneak-peek screenshot
from the sample app,
where I've left
some comments on a recipe.
Notice how the comment appears
right underneath
the recipe it's referring to
and it's drawn with
this distinct, bubble-shaped,
indigo background
and white text.
What approach should we take
to insert comments
in the correct place
and make them look different
from the rest of the text?
You might expect to do this
by dividing the recipe text
into meaningful units,
or elements,
putting each comment
in its own element,
and positioning each comment
after the recipe
it's related to,
while providing instructions
for how to draw the comments.
With TextKit 1,
the reality is quite different.
You have to worry about
a lot of details,
like finding the glyph index,
making sure that the glyph
is not in the middle
of a grapheme cluster,
adjusting that glyph index
if it is,
changing the line spacing,
and possibly customizing
the line-fragment geometry.
And these details are not
relevant
to what you're trying to do.
So with TextKit 2,
we're aiming to make
the expectation into reality.
We've changed the flow
of text through the system
to make approaches
like this possible.
Here's how that flow works
in TextKit 2.
Updates to the text storage
go through a new object
called the content manager.
The content manager divides
the text up into elements
and keeps track of them.
When it's time for layout,
the text layout manager
asks the content manager
for the elements.
Then the text layout manager
lays out the elements
into the text container
and generates layout fragments
that contain the layout
and positioning information.
When it's time for display,
the layout fragments
are handed off
to the ViewportLayoutController,
which coordinates
the positioning
and layout of those fragments
in your rendering surface
of choice,
whether it's a view or a layer.
As you can tell,
there are a lot of new objects
involved in this process.
And this is where the emphasis
on value semantics comes in.
You control the layout
and display of your text
by hooking into the system
at the right point
and obtaining the information
you need
from objects
that use value semantics.
To make changes,
you create new instances
of the value objects
with the changes you want
and give them back
to the system.
The system uses the values
from your replacement objects
for layout and display.
So now,
let's meet these new objects
and identify
the different points
of the system
where you can receive
or replace them.
We'll start
with the storage objects.
Meet NSTextElement.
Elements are the building blocks
of your document.
Each element represents
a portion of the content
and contains a range
that describes
where it is in the document.
And elements
have value semantics.
Their properties,
including the range,
are immutable
and cannot be changed
after creating the element.
Modeling the document
as a series of elements
rather than
a series of characters
gives us a lot more power.
We gain the ability
to easily distinguish
what kind of content
a given element represents,
whether
it's a paragraph of text,
an attachment,
or some other custom type.
And we can make decisions
on how to lay out elements
based on their type.
Now let's meet
NSTextContentManager.
The content manager knows
how to generate elements
from the text content
and keeps track of the ranges
of those elements
within the overall document.
It also knows how to work
with the backing store
and how to generate new elements
with updated ranges
when the content
in the backing store changes.
Think of the content manager
as a wrapper
for the backing store.
The content manager provides
an interface
for translating
the raw data into elements.
NSTextContentManager
and NSTextElement
are both abstract types,
so you could subclass them
if you need to use
a custom document model
or a custom backing store.
The headers and documentation
provide guidance
on how to do this.
But most of the time,
you can use the default ones
that TextKit 2 provides.
Meet NSTextContentStorage
and NSTextParagraph.
These are the default content
manager and element types.
NSTextContentStorage
is a content manager
that uses an NSTextStorage
as the backing store.
It knows how to divide
the contents of the text storage
into paragraph elements,
which are instances
of NSTextParagraph.
NSTextContentStorage also knows
how to generate updated
paragraph elements
when the text
in the text storage changes.
This brings me
to an important point.
When making changes
to the underlying text storage,
you should wrap your updates
in this
performEditingTransaction
method.
This ensures
that the other parts
of the TextKit 2 system
are notified of your changes.
You can do some cool stuff
with
the content storage delegates
without having to implement
a full NSTextContentManager
subclass.
Later in this video,
Chris will cover how
to use content delegates
to change
the comment font and color
without modifying
the text storage
and how to hide comments
altogether.
So stay tuned for more details.
OK.
Now we understand how
TextKit 2 creates elements
from your text content.
That takes care
of the first two steps
from our new approach.
The content storage
automatically
divides the text
into paragraph elements,
and it knows
how to create new paragraphs
for the new comments.
Next,
let's figure out
how we can accomplish
the last two steps:
the positioning
and display of comments.
Returning to our flow diagram,
we need
to get layout information
for our comment elements.
There are new layout objects
to help us with these tasks.
Let's meet them now.
Meet NSTextLayoutManager.
The text layout manager controls
the text layout process.
NSTextLayoutManager is similar
to the old NSLayoutManager
from TextKit 1
with one major difference:
NSTextLayoutManager
does not deal with glyphs.
Instead,
NSTextLayoutManager
takes text elements,
lays them out
into the text container,
and generates layout fragments
for those elements.
You work with layout fragments
to get layout information
for text elements.
So now let's learn
about layout fragments.
Meet NSTextLayoutFragment.
A layout fragment
contains layout information
for one or more text elements.
Just like elements,
they use value semantics
and their properties
are immutable.
So the text layout manager
will create layout fragments for
each of our comment elements,
and then we can
use the information
from the layout fragments
to position and display them.
Layout fragments
communicate layout information
through three properties:
an array of textLineFragments,
the layoutFragmentFrame,
and the renderingSurfaceBounds.
If you want to customize
or change the layout,
it's essential to understand
the information you get
with each of these properties.
So we'll go over that next.
For the first property,
we'll meet NSTextLineFragment.
Line fragments contain
measurement information
for each line of text
in the layout fragment.
These are useful
for obtaining
geometric information
for specific lines
or for counting the number
of lines in a layout fragment.
The second property,
the layout fragment frame,
describes how the text
in the layout fragment
is laid out
inside the text container area.
In TextKit 2,
text layout is basically
stacking up
the layout fragment frames
within the container.
Think of these frames
like tiles.
The system is dividing up
the text container area
into tiles,
where each layout fragment
is a single tile.
Empty lines have
their own layout fragment frame,
as shown in the diagram.
In general,
layout fragment frames
are useful for positioning
other views in your UI
near the fragment contents
or for calculating the total
height of the text content.
Now, this frame
does not accurately represent
the space needed
to draw the text itself.
That information comes
from the third property.
The rendering surface bounds
describes the area required
to draw the text.
This is the rectangle
you want to use
to get the size of the text
in the view's coordinate space.
And this is different
from the layout fragment frame
because the text can overshoot
the edges of the fragment frame.
This happens with diacritics
or, as shown here,
with long descenders
in italic fonts.
Notice how the bottom-left
edge of the J
sticks out just a little bit
from the layout fragment frame.
It doesn't stick out that much,
so here's
a more extreme example.
Some fonts, like Zapfino,
have glyphs that extend very far
outside the typographic bounds.
The rendering surface bounds
will be much larger
than the layout fragment frame
in this case.
Now that we understand
the layout information
that layout fragments provide,
let's back up a bit
and talk about how to use
this information
to customize
the layout of text elements.
Since layout fragments
are immutable,
you can't directly change
the layout information
on a fragment.
Going back to our flow diagram,
we need to hook into
the layout process
and create new instances
of NSTextLayoutFragment
with the information
we want to change.
And you hook into
the layout process
using this delegate method
on NSTextLayoutManager.
This method gets called
during the layout process
when the text layout manager
is generating
the layout fragments
from the elements.
Here you have an opportunity
to create
your own layout fragment
for an element.
That takes care
of the last two steps
in our approach
to the comment problem.
We'll handle the positioning
and custom drawing
of our comment layout fragment
by using a subclass
of NSTextLayoutFragment
and providing instances
of our custom fragment
in the text layout
manager delegate.
Later in this video,
Chris will demonstrate how
this is done in our sample app.
And that's safety.
Now let's move on
to performance.
Performance is one
of the greatest challenges
for any text engine.
TextKit 2 is extremely fast
for an incredibly
wide range of scenarios,
from quickly rendering labels
that are only a few lines each
to laying out documents
that are hundreds of megabytes
being scrolled through
at interactive rates.
And for these scenarios,
when you're scrolling through
these really large documents
at variable rates,
noncontiguous text layout
is absolutely essential
for great performance.
Let's review the difference
between contiguous
and noncontiguous layout.
This diagram shows a document
where the yellow rectangle
represents
the visible content area
on the screen.
Contiguous layout starts
at the very beginning
of the document
and goes in order
from the beginning
to the end of the text.
So if you scroll to some point
in the middle of the document,
contiguous layout
performs layout
for all of the text
that came before that point.
This includes all the text
that's been scrolled
off the screen,
all the way back
to the beginning.
And if there's a lot of text,
the performance can be slow
and you can get animation
hiccups when scrolling.
In the worst case, it can hang.
In contrast,
noncontiguous layout means
we can lay out
a piece of the text
anywhere within the document
without laying out the pieces
that come before it.
Now when you scroll
to the middle of the document,
layout happens for that visible
area right away.
This improves performance
by performing layout
only for the portions of text
that are visible on the screen,
plus an additional
over-scroll region,
resulting in a smoother
scrolling experience.
And layout in TextKit 2
is always noncontiguous.
In contrast,
noncontiguous layout
is optional in TextKit 1.
It's enabled
using a boolean property
on NSLayoutManager.
This API is simple,
but because it is simple,
it can't express information
about the state of the layout
at the time
you request layout information.
Noncontiguous layout
relies on estimates
that may change later
once other portions
of the document
have been laid out.
With TextKit 1,
you can only turn
noncontiguous layout on or off.
There is no ability to control
which parts of the document
get laid out
and no way to know
when layout finishes
and the layout estimates
are updated to the real values.
The TextKit 2 API is richer
and more expressive.
TextKit 2 gives you
consistent layout information
for elements
in the visible content area
and notifies you
when the layout updates
for that visible area.
This area is called
the viewport.
You manage the viewport
by adjusting or relocating it,
and you receive callbacks
before, during,
and after viewport layout.
For optimum performance,
your code should focus
on working
with layout information
inside the viewport area.
Avoid requesting
layout information
for elements outside
the viewport when possible.
The layout information
for elements outside
the viewport
might not be accurate
unless you explicitly ask
to ensure layout
for the text ranges
corresponding to those elements.
This call can be expensive,
especially for large documents.
Revisiting
our flow diagram from earlier,
there's another
new controller class
to help us manage the viewport.
Meet
NSTextViewportLayoutController.
This is the source of truth
for viewport layout information.
It talks
to the text layout manager
to get layout fragments
for elements
within the viewport area.
You can access
the viewport layout controller
through the property
on the text layout manager.
Now that we've met
the viewport layout controller,
let's talk about how
to participate
in the viewport layout process.
The viewport layout controller
calls three important methods
on its delegate
during the viewport layout
process:
TextViewportLayoutController
WillLayout,
textViewportController
configureRenderingSurface
FortextLayoutFragment,
and textViewportLayoutController
DidLayout.
First,
the viewport layout controller
calls the willLayout method
before laying out elements
in the viewport.
Here is where you do
any setup work
to prepare for layout,
such as clearing out
the contents
of the view or layer.
Next,
the viewport layout controller
calls configureRenderingSurface
for every layout fragment
that's visible in the viewport.
Here is where you update
the geometry
of each fragment view or layer.
Finally,
the viewport layout controller
calls the didLayout method
after it's finished laying out
all of the layout fragments
visible in the viewport.
And here's where you perform
any needed updates
after viewport layout
is finished,
like if you wanted
to adjust the viewport
to make the last element
fully visible on the screen.
And that sums it up
for performance.
Now I'll hand it off to Chris
to show you how to use
TextKit 2 in practice.
[Chris] Thank you, Donna.
We wrote a sample app
that demonstrates
some of the different ways
you can use TextKit 2
to lay out and interact
with text in your app.
You can download the sample code
used in this video.
Let's open it up and try it out.
We're using
this collaboration app
to review a book of recipes
so we can figure out
what we want to make for lunch.
Scrolling through the recipes
works as expected,
but something special
is happening behind the scenes:
Only the paragraphs
that are visible in the viewport
are being drawn.
And instead of every paragraph
being rendered
on the same big surface,
each paragraph is being
rendered into its own layer.
If I click
the Show Bounds button
in the toolbar here,
these colored rectangles appear.
The orange rectangle
shows the bounds of each layer.
Drawing text
into separate layers
lets us implement a fun feature:
I can leave comments
on the recipes.
Now, I think an egg sandwich
sounds pretty good,
so I'm going to double-click
on this paragraph
and type,
"hey this sounds pretty good,"
and hit Enter
to insert the comment.
I've just inserted
a new paragraph
into the document.
The bubble background
is being drawn
by a custom subclass
of NSTextLayoutFragment
called BubbleLayoutFragment.
More on that later.
What's special is,
as I insert comments
into the document,
all of the paragraphs
below the comment
move to make room for it.
If you didn't catch it
the first time,
I'm going to click
this turtle button
in the toolbar
to enable Slow Mode.
Let's add another comment.
"Yeah let's make it
for lunch today."
After I hit Enter,
the comment is added
to the document below it,
and all paragraphs below it
animate slowly.
If you want
to hide all the comments,
you can click
the Toggle Comments button
in the toolbar.
This is not actually editing
the underlying document.
It's instead asking
the text content manager
to skip comments
when enumerating text elements
for layout.
TextKit 2 works just as well
on iOS as it does on macOS.
This means the TextKit 2 parts
of the macOS app
can be reused on iOS.
Let's run it on iPad.
We've used those parts
to write an iOS version
of our collaboration app
with all the same functionality.
I'm long-pressing on a paragraph
to leave a comment,
then typing,
"hey that sounds good"...
and hitting Enter.
Just like the app on macOS,
I can tap
the comment Show/Hide button
to hide all comments.
I've just gone through an app
that uses TextKit 2
to lay out, draw,
and interact with text.
Now let's go over some
of the code in the sample app
and how TextKit 2
makes it possible.
The app demonstrates
a lot of the functionality
that TextKit 2 provides,
but I want to focus on
two areas for now:
how it lays out the text
in the viewport
using NSViewportLayoutController
and how it implements
the custom hiding behavior
and rendering of the comments.
When the text layout manager is
about to lay out the document
either because it changed,
the container size was changed,
or a previously unseen
portion of the document
has moved into the viewport,
it calls textViewportLayout
ControllerWillLayout
on its viewport layout delegate.
We're using it here
to clear out
all the text sublayers
and open
an animation transaction.
For each text element
that the text layout manager
lays out,
it calls
textViewportLayoutController,
configureRenderingSurfaceFor
textLayoutFragment.
Here we're getting a layer
to display
the text layout fragment in,
updating its geometry,
animating it
to its new position,
if possible,
and adding it
as sublayer of the view.
When the layout manager
is done laying out,
it will call textViewportLayout
ControllerDidLayout.
We commit
the animation transaction,
update the selection highlights,
and update the content size
so the scroll thumb
is placed correctly.
Now let's talk about
the comments.
TextKit 2 provides several hooks
that you can use
to customize layout element
and layout fragment generation.
I'm gonna show you
how we take comments
in the document,
set custom attributes
like font and color for display,
and draw the bubble behind them.
For each paragraph
in the document,
the text content storage gives
its delegate a chance
to customize the attributes
on that paragraph.
In our implementation,
we're setting a custom font
and color on comments
without having to alter
the font or color
of the underlying text storage.
The text content manager
also gives its delegate
the chance to decide which text
elements will be shown
to the text layout manager
during layout.
Returning false
for a text element
prevents it
from being displayed.
Here we're hiding comments
by choosing
not to enumerate them
without having
to actually delete them
from the underlying
text storage.
The text layout manager
has a delegate too.
By implementing
textLayoutManager,
textLayoutFragmentFor location
in textElement,
the delegate can generate
a custom text layout fragment
instead of the default
NSTextLayoutFragment instance
for a given NSTextElement.
In this case,
when it encounters
an NSTextElement
that represents a comment,
it creates
a BubbleLayoutFragment,
which is a custom subclass
of NSTextLayoutFragment.
BubbleLayoutFragment
overrides the draw method
of NSTextLayoutFragment
to draw the background bubble
before calling
the base class implementation
to draw the text on top.
Note that the text
is being rendered
with the custom font
and text color
that we set earlier.
I've gone over how
the sample app uses TextKit 2
to perform viewport-based
animated layout of text
and how it renders comments
in those colorful bubbles,
going all the way
from custom attributes
in the text storage
to custom drawing.
But there's a lot more
in the sample code
that takes advantage of new API
provided by TextKit 2,
including interpreting
mouse events
to determine the text selection,
rendering
the text selection highlight,
placing the comment popover
at a particular paragraph
in the document,
and estimating
the document height.
You can find further discussion
of all of these topics
in the sample code.
Let's go back to Donna
to talk about preparing
your apps for TextKit 2.
[Donna] Thanks, Chris.
That's a fantastic example of
how TextKit 2 works in practice.
Now that we've gone over
what TextKit 2 can do,
let's discuss some approaches
for app modernization.
Everything
we've talked about so far
applies to creating
your own TextKit 2 stack
to use
with a generic view or layer.
All of the new classes
are available
in UIKit with iOS 15
and in AppKit with macOS 12.
So if you wanna go this route,
you can start writing
new code with TextKit 2 today.
On the other hand,
many apps use the built-in
text controls, like text view,
to take advantage of all the
great, free functionality,
like accessibility support
and selection
and editing services.
Some of these controls
have already been updated
to use TextKit 2.
If your app uses
the built-in controls,
there are
a few additional details
to be aware of.
Maintaining compatibility
is as important to us
as it is to you.
Since TextKit 1
is such an integral part
of the built-in text controls,
we're going to great lengths
to maintain compatibility
for apps that are using them.
This is why only some controls
use TextKit 2 automatically
in iOS 15 and macOS 12.
Additionally,
some controls require taking
extra steps to use TextKit 2
in these OS versions.
For AppKit developers,
NSTextView does not
use TextKit 2 automatically.
If you want to use TextKit 2
with a NSTextView,
you need to opt in
programmatically
at creation time.
This is how to do it.
First,
create a text layout manager.
Next, create a text container.
Then associate
the text container
with the text layout manager
using the textContainer property
on NSTextLayoutManager.
Finally,
create your NSTextView
using the designated initializer
with the text container.
Now you'll have a text view
that uses TextKit 2.
You can access
the text layout manager
and text content storage
with new properties
on NSTextView.
There's just one thing
to be careful of.
Recall that NSTextView
has a layoutManager property
that allows getting
and setting its NSLayoutManager.
NSLayoutManager
is a TextKit 1 object
and it's not compatible
with the TextKit 2 stack.
A text view can't have
both a layout manager
and a text layout manager
at the same time.
So here's the deal.
We added
a special compatibility mode
for NSTextView
that switches it to TextKit 1
when needed.
The text view
can automatically detect
whether it needs
to use this mode
and replace
its NSTextLayoutManager
with NSLayoutManager.
For optimum performance,
the text view will remain
in compatibility mode
from that point forward.
Even if you opted in
to TextKit 2,
your text view will
automatically switch
to TextKit 1
if you explicitly call
the layoutManager property
on your text view
or text container.
The text view will also switch
if it encounters text content
that is not yet supported
or detects other conditions
that require TextKit 1.
And this can happen
for field editors as well.
Field editors for NSTextField
use TextKit 2 by default.
But if your text field subclass
is requesting layout information
from the field editor's
layout manager,
the field editor will switch
to TextKit 1
for all text fields
in that window.
The system will
issue notifications
before and after a text view
switches to TextKit 1.
You can observe
these notifications
to receive this information.
The notification objects
contain a reference
to the exact text view
that changed modes.
For complete details
on the TextKit 1 compatibility
mode for AppKit,
please refer
to the documentation
on the Apple Developer portal.
For UIKit developers,
UITextField uses TextKit 2
automatically in iOS 15.
UITextView with TextKit 2
is not available in iOS 15.
We're working to ensure
maximum compatibility
for all applications
that use UITextView,
and there are
quite a lot of them.
In the meantime,
you can review
your existing code
for uses of UITextView's
layoutManager property
and think about how to express
your intent with TextKit 2.
That way,
you'll be ready to transition
once it's available.
And that's a wrap.
Now you've met TextKit 2,
Apple's new text engine
to take us into the future.
We look forward to seeing
what you'll build
with TextKit 2.
Thanks for watching.
[upbeat music]