[percussive music]
[Ernest]
Hello, and welcome to
"Discover rolling clips
with ReplayKit."
My name is Ernest,
and I'm a software engineer
on the ReplayKit team.
Today, I'm really excited
to show you a new way
to capture
your application highlights.
Let me start by giving you
an overview of ReplayKit.
ReplayKit is a framework
that enables you to record
your application's screen
and audio.
When people want to make
an instructional video,
or simply just wanna
show off their gameplay,
in-app screen recording
creates a video
that they can save and share
with their friends.
And what if you wanted
more control over
the video content people create?
You may want to add additional
filters, or overlays.
You can do this
with in-app screen capture.
In-app screen capture will
give the audio and video samples
directly to your application
process,
so you'll have complete control
over the content
that is being created.
And we all know the next
best thing to playing a game
is watching gameplay live.
In-app broadcast makes it easy
for people
to stream your application to
third-party broadcast services,
to be viewed all around
the world.
While our current recording
features cover a wide variety
of use cases, there is one
that we currently don't.
So, imagine your players
just fought all the enemies
and unlocked the key
to a level in your game,
and now they wanna share that
moment with their friends.
But because it's their first
time playing this level,
they didn't know something
exciting was gonna happen,
and they weren't able
to capture that moment.
Currently, players will
need to record
their entire gameplay
in order to save
all their memorable highlights.
This results in a large
recording that will
not only take up a lot of space,
but will require time to trim
into shorter clips.
Wouldn't it be awesome
if you could record
all the highlights
right when they happen?
Or even better, what if
ReplayKit does this for you,
and gives you the video
clip of each moment?
This year,
I'm excited to show you
a new feature
we've been working on,
clips recording.
Clips recording will
keep a rolling buffer
of audio and video samples.
When clip export is called, the
samples up to 15 seconds prior
can be exported
into a short video clip.
So now, instead of needing
to know when to Start Recording,
you just need to know
when you want to export.
There are several ways
to export a video clip.
You can add UI buttons
or a game controller support
to your application,
so people can have
manual control
on when to capture clips.
With the tap of a button,
they can
get the clip exactly
when they want it.
You can also add triggers
in your application
that will automatically
capture clips.
With this,
you will always capture
those exciting moments when they
get a perfect combo,
defeat the final boss,
or beat their best speed run.
And with all of these clips,
you can create
personalized user experiences.
You could add a custom
overlay that opens
to a collection of recordings,
or you could present
a highlight reel
with all the clips captured
at the end of a level
for your players
to see and share.
Clips recording will be
available for iOS and macOS,
and is a powerful feature
that will sit alongside
our existing recording,
capture, and broadcast APIs.
Similar to our other features,
clips recording will provide
the same HD quality,
low-performance impact,
and built-in privacy safeguards.
How does clips recording
work under the hood?
Let's take a look.
Clips recording includes three
APIs: start, stop, and export.
To start clip buffering,
your application should
call into RPScreenRecorder
to get the sharedRecorder
singleton instance.
With the shared instance,
you can
call the startClipBuffering API.
At which point,
ReplayKit will store screen
and audio samples from your
application in a rolling buffer.
Every time ReplayKit
receives new samples,
any samples older than 15
seconds will be discarded.
After the rolling buffer starts,
ReplayKit
waits for your application
to tell it to export.
When the application calls
the export clip API,
ReplayKit takes care
of the rest and returns you
the video clip of that moment.
When you no longer need
the rolling buffer,
or when you want to use
another ReplayKit feature,
such as in-app broadcast,
you can call the stop API,
and ReplayKit will
tear down the session.
With this information in mind,
let me show you
a sample project
that implements
the new clips APIs.
You may already be familiar
with this sample project
from our session last year.
The updated sample project
now includes code for clips.
Let's take a look at this code.
Just like the other
recording sessions,
here's the IBAction associated
with the "start clips" button
in the main storyboard.
This button is used to start
clip buffering
if you aren't already active,
and stop clip
buffering if you are active.
Now, let's go ahead
and take a look at
what happens when you start
clip buffering.
Here is the code
to start clip buffering.
You're going to get
the shared recorder instance
from RPScreenRecorder
and call startClipBuffering
with your
completion handler.
Here, within
the completion handler,
you will need to handle any
error that occurred
while attempting to start,
including updating the UI.
If there's no error, then you
should also update the UI
to show that the recording
is currently active.
Similar to start,
there's a stop clip
buffering method
in the sample project.
This is where you're going
to get the shared instance,
but this time, you'll call
the stopClipBuffering API.
In the completion handler,
you will need to handle
any error that occurred
while attempting to stop,
and should update the UI to show
that you're no longer recording.
Now that I went through
the code for start
and stop clip buffering,
let's look at the code
needed to export a clip.
This is
the code for the IBAction
associated
with the "export clip" button.
The action is triggered
when a person decides
they want to generate a clip.
Just a reminder that
you're not limited
by this approach and may
export clips automatically
based on your own
application triggers.
Here, if you're actively
recording and the button
is enabled from the previous
startClipBuffering method,
the exportClip function
will be called.
To call the exportClip API,
you will need to specify
a URL and a clip duration.
Similar to the start
and stop APIs,
you will then handle any
errors in the completionHandler.
If there's no error,
then you should have
the clip at the specified URL.
With access to the clips,
you can then build and organize
your own user experiences.
In my sample code here, the clip
is simply saved to Photos.
And that's it!
With these three APIs,
you can now add clips recording
in your application.
You will have direct access to
the clips in the specified URL,
so you can build
your own in-app experiences.
As previously mentioned,
another way to get clips
is by adding game
controller support.
The game controller
framework will now have
built-in clips recording.
Keep in mind, clips exported
from the game controller
will save directly
to Photos or the Desktop.
So, to make your own
in-app experiences
with the generated clips,
you will need to implement
the ReplayKit clips API.
When integrating
both ReplayKit
and the game
controller framework,
it is good idea to make sure
you're using key value
observing for both available
and recording properties
on RPScreenRecorder.
Also be sure to follow
the protocol
RPScreenRecorderDelegate
so that you can update
your application's state
as needed.
And it's that simple
to integrate clips recording
in your applications.
With clips recording,
your application will be ready
to capture all of the exciting
moments when they happen.
I look forward to seeing
all of the clips
and the new user experiences
you will create.
Thank you so much
for watching our session.
I hope you
have a wonderful WWDC.
[percussive music]