[MACBOOK STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Sommer Panage: Hi,
my name is Sommer Panage.
I'm excited to talk to you today
about Full Keyboard Access
on iOS.
Full Keyboard Access
is a feature
for our customers
with motor impairments.
So to begin today,
I'll be giving you
a quick overview
of motor accessibility
in general on iOS.
After that,
we'll take a closer look
at Full Keyboard Access
and all the power
it brings users,
particularly on iPad.
And finally, we'll dive
into key APIs and principles
that you as a developer
should be sure to keep in mind
as you build your applications
to be certain that they support
keyboard users.
Now, let's get started with
a review of motor accessibility.
When we discuss developing
accessible apps for iOS,
we want to keep all users
in mind.
We often talk about
accessibility
in terms of VoiceOver,
a technology for those
who are blind or low vision.
However, it's important
to also make sure
our software works for anyone
with motor impairments as well.
Motor impairment
is a wide-ranging term
and can impact how someone uses
their iOS device in many ways.
Some people may have
a limited range of motion.
Others may have
finer motor impairments
such as tremors
or other difficulties
touching the screen.
And depending on the severity
of the motor impairment,
many people find it easier
or even necessary
to interact with their devices
via external hardware
such as keyboards,
joysticks, or buttons.
iOS provides numerous
assistive technologies
to help those
with motor impairments
have a seamless experience
with their devices.
For example,
we offer AssistiveTouch
for people who might have
some difficulty
with hardware interactions
or Multi-Touch gestures.
AssistiveTouch uses
an onscreen menu
to simplify these interactions
down to simple single taps.
Switch Control allows those with
more limited motor abilities
to interact
with their iOS devices
using one or more
external switches or buttons.
And of course,
there's also Voice Control,
which allows people to interact
with their iOS devices
using only their voice.
And that brings us to one of our
newest motor technologies,
Full Keyboard Access.
While iOS has offered support
for keyboards since iOS 9,
it's been a supplementary mode
of input.
With Full Keyboard Access,
released in iOS 13.4.1,
customers can now interact
with their device
100 percent via the keyboard.
It's a middle ground
between AssistiveTouch
and Switch Control
for those who may not have
enough dexterity
to touch their screens
but who also do not
necessarily need or want
to use external switches.
It also offers an alternative
to Voice Control
for those who may be nonverbal,
have a speech impairment,
or who simply might be in
an environment
where using Voice Control
doesn't make sense.
Full Keyboard Access
is also great
for those who depend on custom
or accessible keyboard layouts
such as a one-handed keyboard
or this ergonomic split keyboard
here.
In order for
Full Keyboard Access
to offer people
a true iOS experience
without the touchscreen,
it provides numerous additions
to basic keyboard input.
Full Keyboard Access
also has navigation commands
so that users can get to
every single element onscreen,
interaction commands,
and a Gesture mode
for things like drag and drop.
And all of these commands
use Tab as the modifier key.
However, they're also
fully customizable
for people who may prefer
different key combos.
So let's take a look at how
a user might navigate
on their iPad using
Full Keyboard Access.
So first, I can use
the arrow keys
to move to the Notes app
and Space bar to activate.
From there, I can Tab over
to create a new note
and then I can
immediately edit.
I think I'm going to take
some notes about version two
from one of my apps
called Shape Shuffle.
[KEYSTROKES]
Let's make it great for iPad.
When I'm done editing,
I can use Control-Tab
to get out of editing mode.
Now if I want to delete
an old note,
I can use Tab-Z
to bring up a list of actions.
Then I can use arrow and Space
to delete the note.
Now, let's say I want to make
one more new note.
Well, I could Tab over
to the Create Note button again,
or I could use the Find feature
by using Tab-F.
Then I just type in "new",
and there we go.
So now that you know
all about Full Keyboard Access
and how it's used,
it's time to look into how you,
as an app developer,
can make sure
that keyboard users
have the best possible
experience.
In 2020, I talked with you
about Switch Control,
and we worked
on this fun game for kids
to learn their shapes,
colors, and numbers.
Together, we made this app
accessible.
This year, I decided to rev
Shape Shuffle for iPad
so that we can make sure
that it works great
with Full Keyboard Access.
If you haven't seen
Shape Shuffle yet, no worries.
Here's a quick tour.
In each level,
the player gets a prompt
like the one we see here:
Two Yellow Squares.
Then they have to tap through
the cards below
to try to find
the three required cards;
in this case,
a card with two objects,
a square card,
and a yellow card.
Once they've double-tapped
each correct card,
they can move on
to the next level.
And as the levels go up,
the prompts get harder.
It looks like I just found two,
so I can double-tap
to add it to my board
and continue searching
for yellow and square.
Now, if I'm not sure if the card
is the right one or not,
I can put a pin in it
by long-pressing it
so I know to come back later.
I'll put a pin in these two
in the bottom left.
Then, when I return,
I can make my final pick
and beat the level.
Hm...
I got it!
Now let's start
with our gameplay view
to see how things work
when I play another round
but this time via my keyboard.
So as I hit Tab and Space bar,
things seem to be working well.
I can move between cards
with Tab
and flip them with Space.
Now let's try to add or pin
our triangle card.
I'll hit Tab-Z to bring up
my Actions menu,
but I'm not seeing
any actions available.
Now, there are actually two ways
we can address helping users
to quickly get to common actions
in our game, like add and pin.
The first way we can solve this
is via a custom action.
Custom actions are great
because they translate across
many assistive technologies.
When you add custom actions
to something,
it will show up in VoiceOver,
Switch Control,
and Full Keyboard Access.
Custom actions are what show up
when you hit Tab-Z.
As you can see here,
all I need to do is create
a UIAccessibilityCustomAction
for the actions I want to add,
then go ahead and set those
to my accessibilityCustomActions
array on my cardView.
Also, it's always great
to add an image.
While these images won't show up
for Full Keyboard Access,
they will show up
for Switch Control.
Here's what my UI looks like
with custom actions added.
When I press Tab-Z,
I see this nice popover letting
me add the card or pin it.
Custom actions are great
for anyone using
our accessibility features;
however, there's another
really cool approach
that you can take here.
You can add
a custom keyboard shortcut.
The nice thing
with a custom keyboard shortcut
is that it will work for both
your Full Keyboard Access users
as well as for those
who are just using a keyboard
with their device,
but they don't have
Full Keyboard Access turned on.
It's great for accessibility
and power users alike.
To see a list
of keyboard shortcuts,
you just need to hold down
the Command key.
You can learn all about
keyboard shortcuts
and much more for iPad
in our talk this year,
"Take your iPad apps
to the next level."
Today, I'll show you
a short example
of how you can harness this API
which was new in Mac Catalyst 13
and now brought to iOS
and iPadOS 15.
By overriding buildMenu
in your AppDelegate,
you can set your key commands
Here I create
two UIKeyCommands;
one for my add action
and one for my pin action.
I make sure to add
a discoverability title
as that's what will show up
in my KeyCommand HUD
when I hold down Command.
Next, I create a new UI menu,
which I name "gameplay",
and I pass the new commands
as "children".
Finally, I insert the menu
into my menu builder,
and I'm done!
Now, since I only want these
items to be active in the HUD
when I actually have
a selected card,
I also override canPerformAction
on my GameViewController
so that I only show these items
when a card
is actually selected.
Here's what our game looks like
when I hold down
the Command key,
and I have a card selected.
And here, I want to highlight
a key principle
of developing
for Full Keyboard Access.
You should try to add
custom actions
and keyboard shortcuts
to all of your common actions
to improve efficiency
for your users.
Not only are they both
easily discoverable,
but they improve
the experience for anyone
interacting with your app
via a keyboard.
Let's come back to our game.
I've added the triangle
with my new actions.
Now I'll use Shift-Tab
to go back
toward the home button.
However, as I'm doing that,
I see another issue.
That triangle is selectable
even though when I tap on it
with Space bar nothing happens.
So first of all, why is our
cursor going to this element
if we can't interact with it?
Well, I've already done some
VoiceOver support work
on this app,
and here's what that looks like.
You'll see that I'm setting
isAccessibilityElement to true
on my items as well as giving it
an accessibilityLabel.
This is great because VoiceOver
needs to read each item
to our user.
However, if someone is a
Full Keyboard Access user only,
then their cursor will also
go to many items
marked with
isAccessibilityElement.
In order to tell Full Keyboard
Access to skip this element,
we need to add one more line.
Here, you can see that we set
accessibilityResponds
ToUserInteraction to false.
This tells our system
that while this is
an accessibility element,
it's not one that the user
can interact with.
So the cursor
for motor technologies
such as Full Keyboard Access or
Switch Control should skip it.
Note that accessibility
RespondsToUserInteraction
is only meaningful
if isAccessibilityElement
is already true.
By default, the system tries
to correctly set elements
with isAccessibilityElement true
to interactive or not.
In most cases
you'll only need to set
accessibilityResponds
ToUserInteraction to false
when you have an object
that you want to be accessible
to VoiceOver but not
to Full Keyboard Access
or other motor technologies.
This brings us
to a second key principle
of developing for
Full Keyboard Access.
As you're testing your app,
you'll want to be sure
that the cursor only goes
to items that the user
can interact with.
Now, as you're building your app
and making sure focus only goes
to the right places,
it might be tempting to override
canBecomeFocused
instead of the API
that we just discussed.
However, this overrides
focus behavior
for the whole focus engine
and will impact people
using Tab to navigate
when Full Keyboard Access
isn't even on.
So it's best to steer clear
of this when only wanting
to modify behavior for
Full Keyboard Access users.
In fact, this brings up
an important area.
The focus system that's used
to drive Full Keyboard Access
is the same one
that drives Tab navigation
across all of our OSs
like iPadOS.
While you likely
won't need to touch it
in order to work with
Full Keyboard Access,
if you'd like to learn more,
I recommend these three talks.
This year we have
two other talks called
"Focus on iPad
keyboard navigation"
and "Direct and reflect focus
in SwiftUI."
And back in 2017,
there's a fantastic talk
all about how the focus engine
drives tvOS.
Now, coming back
to our home screen,
I want to be sure that I can use
Full Keyboard Access's
awesome Find feature.
So let's give it a try.
OK, the number levels
work great out of the box.
Searching for levels eight
and twelve is easy.
And because I've already added
some VoiceOver support,
I'm getting the Settings button,
too, with Find.
But what happens if I don't know
that the button
is called Settings?
Maybe I type in "preferences"
or "prefs."
Hm. No luck.
To solve this, we can set
an array of strings
to our
accessibilityUserInputLabels.
Here, I'm setting the localized
words for prefs,
preferences, gear,
and settings to this label
to be sure that people
can reach it
no matter what they might type.
By adding these strings,
you'll also be doing a favor
to your Voice Control users,
as they can now speak
any of these names
to tap your Settings button
as well.
Of course, this won't interfere
with your VoiceOver label.
So now when you type in
"prefs" it works great!
And this brings me to our
third and final principle today.
Make sure that you always
provide as many labels
as you can for
your image-based controls
so your users can always
get to them quickly with Find.
Now, before we finish up,
I want to do
a little fun polish.
So let's take one more look
at my home screen.
Since all these items
are UI buttons,
Tab is moving to them naturally.
And that's great.
But notice how my cursor
is always a rectangle?
To make things more playful,
let's make it match
the shapes of the buttons.
To show nice cursor shapes
around our buttons,
we can just use
accessibilityPath --
the same accessibilityPath,
in fact,
that you'd use for VoiceOver.
For static views, you can set
the accessibilityPath
to that of the shape
itself with a UIBezierPath.
Notice that I'm setting
the accessibilityPath
in screen coordinates.
If you're in a scroll view,
you'll want to override
accessibilityPath
so it's always correct
relative to screen coordinates,
even when you're scrolling.
Let's take a look at how fun
this bit of polish looks.
Now as I Tab through,
we can see circles,
[KEYSTROKES]
triangles, and squares.
And it'll be the same
with VoiceOver as well.
With that, let's review some
of the key ideas to keep in mind
when you're developing your app
for keyboards,
but particularly,
for Full Keyboard Access.
First, use custom actions
and keyboard shortcuts
to really go that extra mile,
adding efficient means
to navigate your apps.
Next, make sure the cursor
doesn't land on items
that the user cannot
actually interact with.
And finally, be sure that
you add user input labels,
especially on
image-based controls,
so that people can take
full advantage
of Full Keyboard Access's
Find feature.
And that's everything!
I hope that today you now
understand the importance
of motor accessibility
in all of Apple's products.
While there are numerous ways
of interacting with our devices,
the keyboard has become
a powerful tool for our users.
With the information
from this talk,
you should now be able
to be certain your apps provide
an excellent experience
to Full Keyboard Access users
and to everyone.
Thank you and have
an amazing WWDC 2021.
♪