[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Owen Monsma: Hello,
and welcome to
"Qualities of a great
Mac Catalyst app."
My name is Owen Monsma,
and I'm a Cocoa engineer.
And I'll be joined later
by my colleague
Dave Rahardja
from UIKit.
Today we're going to go over
three important considerations
for making an amazing
Catalyst app.
First, we'll cover some
high-level changes
that happen when you migrate
to a Mac Catalyst app.
Next, we'll dive into some
specific code modifications
you can make to improve
your app experience on Mac.
And we'll end with information
about app distribution.
So let's begin with migrating
your app to Mac Catalyst.
The first step toward
a great Catalyst app
is having a great iPad app,
and your app already runs
with no additional changes
on Macs with M1.
If you have an M1 Mac,
you can try this right away
with the Designed for iPad
run destination in Xcode.
By adopting these features
on iPad,
your Mac app will have
a great head start.
If your app supports
multitasking on iPad,
you can automatically get
multiple window support on Mac.
And if you use UIMenuBuilder,
your menus
are automatically picked up
in your app's menu bar,
and by contextual menus
with a secondary click
on your views.
We also automatically
bridge system behaviors
like copy/paste
and drag and drop.
To learn more about how your
iPad app runs as-is on M1 Macs,
check out our video,
"Qualities of great iPad and
iPhone apps on Macs with M1."
But you're here because
you want to take things further.
By checking the Mac checkbox,
you gain the ability
to distribute to all Macs,
and get access to additional
APIs to further refine your app.
So let's do it with our app,
Trip Planner!
In our Xcode project settings,
we check the Mac option
under Deployment Info.
Notice to the right,
an additional pop-up appears,
letting us choose between
a scaled iPad interface
and a Mac optimized interface.
We will examine this choice more
in a little bit.
For now, let's click build
and run in the Xcode toolbar.
And our app builds and runs!
Now, if your app
failed to build,
there are a few things
to investigate.
Certain deprecated frameworks
and classes
are unavailable
for Mac Catalyst,
so now is the time
to modernize.
Not only will this get your app
running on Mac,
but it will improve
your iOS app, too.
Moving from OpenGLES
to Apple's own Metal framework
unlocks the full power
of the GPU.
The Contacts framework replaced
the deprecated AddressBook
and is a forward-looking,
thread-safe way
to handle contacts.
And UIWebView is deprecated
and has been superseded
by WKWebView.
Also, make sure to check
your third-party dependencies.
If those frameworks
are distributed
as an XCFramework bundle,
make sure that they provide
a Mac binary to link against.
As you begin work
on your Mac app,
watch for compiler warnings
when building your project,
and monitor the console log
for runtime messages.
These warnings tell you
how to fix your code
so it runs well
as a Mac Catalyst process.
And remember
to only use supported API
so your app continues to run
on future macOS releases.
It's also important to be aware
of the lifecycle events
that your app will receive
when running on a Mac.
If your app currently
relies on lifecycle events
called on your app delegate,
you should instead
monitor scene lifecycles
so your app can
respond to events
specific to the content
of each window on the desktop.
Remember, a Mac Catalyst app
will not receive the
sceneDidEnterBackground event
as often as an iPad app.
Scenes enter
the background state
when a desktop window
is minimized or closed.
If your app uses
sceneDidEnterBackground
to perform some routine work
like autosaving a document,
using a timer instead
will ensure this action
is taken regularly.
Finally, remember that
your Catalyst app
may have zero scenes
but continue
to run in the foreground.
This state happens when all your
app's windows have been closed,
but your app's name remains
visible in the menu bar.
Now let's decide whether to
optimize our interface for Mac.
This is one of the most
important decisions to make
when you first begin
bringing your app over.
Using Mac idiom is recommended
to make your app
feel the most at home on Mac,
but it does require
some additional work.
In the Mac idiom, your app
will run at 100 percent scale,
giving you pixel-perfect
text and images,
and native AppKit controls.
If you want, you can add
new Mac-specific assets
in your asset catalog
to take advantage
of this additional detail.
It's good practice to provide
both 1x and 2x assets
to support all monitor
resolutions.
Be aware, the size metrics
of many of your controls
will change, so it is important
to adjust your app's layout
to accommodate.
For custom controls in your app,
you have an additional choice.
Automatically, you get
the Mac style of control.
But now you can opt out
your buttons and sliders
from this conversion
to use customization APIs
that are unavailable
on Mac controls.
If you use any custom assets --
like setting the thumb
on a UISlider --
they will appear larger
than expected by default,
so you may need to scale them
or provide new assets.
Also keep in mind that Mac users
expect AppKit-style controls,
so custom controls
should be used sparingly.
For more detail
on the Mac idiom,
check out our video,
"Optimize the interface
of your Mac Catalyst app."
Because a Catalyst app
in the Mac idiom
takes on AppKit control styles,
both the appearance
and behavior of some
of your controls will change.
In our video,
"What's new in Mac Catalyst,"
we introduced
the new pop-up button style
which rounds out
our suite of Mac button types.
Let's dive into what makes
these controls different
and how the system
picks which one to use.
Understanding these controls
and where they are
commonly found
will help you
make informed choices
about their use in your app.
The default UIButton type
is UIButton type .system.
With this button type,
the button automatically
takes on the expected appearance
for its context.
In the Mac idiom,
this means it becomes
a bordered push button.
Pull-down buttons
are a Mac-native control
used to provide
a list of possible actions,
and are drawn with
a single-arrow indicator.
A good example is the PDF
pull-down in the print dialog,
which presents actions such as
Save as PDF or Send in Mail.
To get a pull-down button,
make sure that you have assigned
a UI menu to your button
via its menu property,
and additionally set
showsMenuAsPrimaryAction
to true.
Your button will take on
the pull-down look
and present the menu on a click.
And new to Catalyst
with macOS Monterey
are pop-up buttons.
Pop-up buttons look similar
to pull-down buttons
but have a double-arrow
indicator,
and they do something
slightly different.
Where the pull-down
triggers an action,
a pop-up button
is used to select
one of a set of mutually
exclusive options.
For example,
selecting the day of the week.
The title in the button
then updates
to reflect the selection.
This is a good,
Mac-friendly choice
to replace a UIPickerView
in your app.
Getting this control is similar
to a pull-down button,
but the property
changesSelectionAsPrimaryAction
must also be true.
Finally, checkboxes
are used to represent
a non-exclusive binary toggle,
and are a more mouse-friendly
alternative to a switch.
And as it turns out,
you get the checkbox
with no additional work!
Just make sure that
the switch has a title set,
and keep in mind
the title property
is only supported
in the Mac idiom.
By default, the switch
has a preferredStyle
of automatic,
and you can verify at runtime
whether it is
a switch or a checkbox
using the read-only
style property.
Now, to dive into
some specific code changes,
let's hand things off
to my colleague, Dave.
Dave Rahardja: Hi everyone,
my name is Dave,
and I'm an engineer
on the UIKit team.
Let's talk about some specific
things you can do
to make your Mac Catalyst app
feel more at home.
A Mac Catalyst app
may have access
to a lot more
screen real estate.
Your app's windows can be
resized much larger on a Mac
than on an iPad,
and can be shown full screen.
Take a moment
to resize your app's windows
and pay attention to its layout.
Make sure you're using
the additional space
to show more content
and controls
to make your apps easier to use.
Live resizing will put
your app's layout performance
to the test.
Your app should do the least
amount of work possible
during layout to keep
your app's windows responsive
during resizing.
Take special note of
interactions in your app
that rely on modal presentations
and popovers.
With a larger display area,
you can make these interactions
always available
by showing them
as child views.
Now, let's talk about
pointer input devices.
Remember that not all Macs
have a trackpad,
and some Macs are connected
to input devices
that don't support scrolling.
If your views rely on a pinch
or rotate gesture to work,
make sure that all of its
capabilities are accessible
using a mouse
without scroll input.
Add additional buttons
or other controls
to your Mac Catalyst app's view
to make sure all of its
functionality is accessible.
Additionally,
detecting keyboard modifiers
on tap or pan
gesture recognizers
can sometimes provide
faster access
to your view's functionality.
For example,
allowing Shift-pan to zoom.
Let's talk about keyboard
shortcuts and the main menu.
The main menu of a Mac app
is a great place
to discover all the actions
available in your app,
as well as their associated
keyboard shortcuts.
If your app already supports
keyboard shortcuts
by returning key commands
from its responders,
add these commands
to the main menu
using the menu builder API
instead.
Moving all your keyboard
shortcuts to the main menu
makes them discoverable
even when they are not
currently enabled.
What's more,
using the MenuBuilder API
to organize your shortcuts
on Mac Catalyst
also organizes them
on the iPad shortcuts overlay.
As you build out
your main menu,
be sure to add
all the actions needed
to interact with your app.
Actions performed
with gestures on an iPad
should also be accessible
by selecting items
from the main menu.
Adding keyboard shortcuts
to your menu items
will provide even quicker
access to these actions.
Because menu bar
and key command actions
are routed starting
from the first responder,
make sure that the views
that would be
the target of those actions
can become first responder
and can accept focus.
You can do this by having
your views return true
for the canBecomeFirstResponder
and canBecomeFocused properties.
Since a Mac app must rely less
on direct manipulation of views,
and more on the user
selecting a view
and then selecting an action
from the main menu,
the ability for more
of your app's views
to become first responder
and focused
becomes more important
on Mac Catalyst.
For more information about
focus and first responders,
check out the video, "Focus on
iPad keyboard navigation."
While we're on the subject
of responders,
be sure to leave the responder
chain unmodified in your app.
In other words,
don't override nextResponder.
Leaving the responder chain
unmodified
ensures that Mac Catalyst
can route your actions
to the appropriate targets.
If your app has to handle
certain actions
using objects that are not
in its responder chain,
use the target(for Action:,
withSender:) function
to delegate these actions
to the appropriate object
instead.
Let's go over the code.
In this example,
our view delegates
the setAsFavorite action
to a model object,
while allowing other actions
to continue to propagate
up the responder chain.
Now let's talk about scenes
and how they work
in a Mac Catalyst app.
A Mac app may have
many desktop windows
open at the same time.
In a Mac Catalyst app,
each of these windows
is paired with a UIWindowScene.
Your app may offer windows
that have different functions.
For example, it may have
a document window,
a detail viewer window,
a message composer window,
and so on.
The best way to organize
these different scene functions
is by defining
a scene configuration
for each type of window.
To define scene configurations,
add them to your Info.plist
under the Application Scene
Manifest entry.
Under the Application
Session Role array,
create one configuration
for each type of scene
your app supports.
Give each of these
configurations a name
and choose the scene class,
delegate class,
and storyboard
that will be instantiated
when the scene is created.
Now that we've defined
our scene configurations,
let's discuss
how we can use them
to create a new scene
of a particular configuration.
In this example, we want to
create a new detail viewer scene
when a view is double-clicked.
The first thing we do is define
a new user activity type
for requesting
a detail viewer scene.
We'll call it
viewDetailActivityType.
When we create
that new user activity,
we want to pass along
an identifier
for the item that we want
to show in detail.
To do that,
we define an itemIDKey
that will hold that information
in the user info dictionary.
Then, in our double-click
event handler,
we create a new NSUserActivity
object of the appropriate type,
and set its userInfo property
to a dictionary
holding the itemID
that we want to show.
Finally, we call
the UIApplication
requestSceneSessionActivation
function,
passing in the user activity
we just created.
This will cause the system
to create our new scene.
So now we know
how to request a new scene
for a particular
user activity type.
Now let's talk about
how to use that information
to load the appropriate
scene configuration.
We respond to scene creation
requests by implementing
the application
configurationForConnecting
function in the application
delegate.
In our implementation,
we examine
if the incoming scene request
contains any user activities.
The request can contain
multiple user activities,
but for this code example,
we'll just examine
the first one.
If there is an activity
we need to handle,
we then check its activityType.
Here, we test if it's equal
to the viewDetailActivityType.
If so, we return the scene
configuration named
DetailViewer.
This will cause the system
to check in our Info.plist
for a configuration
of that name,
and load the appropriate scene
and scene delegate classes,
and display
the specified storyboard
in a new desktop window.
If no specific scene
configuration should be loaded,
we fall back to returning
the default configuration.
There is one more thing to do.
Remember that
we saved the itemID
for the item to be shown?
We still need to set that value
on the view controller
of the scene
that we just created.
We do that in our
SceneDelegate class.
The scene willConnectTo session
function is called
just before the scene is about
to be shown on the desktop.
The user activity
that was passed
into our application delegate is
also passed into this function
in the scene delegate.
We can now extract the itemID
from its userInfo dictionary
and set it on our new
view controller.
Using NSUserActivity
to configure new scenes also
makes it easier for your app
to support state restoration.
If your scene delegate
responds to
the stateRestorationActivity
(for Scene:) callback,
the returned user activity
will be saved by the system
when your app exits.
If state restoration is enabled
in System Preferences,
the next time your app
is launched,
the system will recreate
your scenes
and pass each scene's
user activity object
to your app delegate's
application
configurationForConnecting
SceneSession function.
This is the same function
that is called when your app
creates new scenes,
as covered earlier.
By using a consistent set
of activity types,
you can use the same code
to select
the appropriate scene
configuration when your app
creates new desktop windows
and during state restoration.
There is one thing you need
to add to your scene delegate
so your app can handle
both new scene requests
and state restoration
with the same code,
and that is to modify your scene
willConnect session function
in your scene delegate
so that it falls back
to the stateRestorationActivity
if the activity in the scene
connection options is nil.
Now your app is ready
to handle new scene requests
and state restoration.
For more information
on state restoration,
check out the "Introducing
Multiple Windows on iPad" video.
Next, let's talk about
your app's toolbar.
A great Mac app
uses its windows' toolbars
to present frequently used
actions
and other navigation options
for quick access.
Unlike toolbars on iOS,
the toolbar on a Mac Catalyst
app's desktop window
does not change as view
controllers appear and disappear
in the Split View controller
or a navigation controller.
Because toolbars are
strongly associated with scenes,
the best place
to configure your toolbar
is in your scene delegate
subclass.
One important item
usually found on the toolbar
is the sharing button.
Adding an NSSharingServicePicker
ToolbarItem to your toolbar
allows your app to share the
main content shown in your scene
using the Mac's
standard sharing menu.
In macOS Monterey, we have
added the ability for the button
to automatically use the
activity items configuration
shared by your scene.
Notice that this is
the same configuration
that the new Share This function
of Siri uses on iOS.
A good way to provide
a sharing configuration
for your scene
is to return an object
from your RootViewController's
activityItemsConfiguration
property.
On Mac Catalyst,
an NSSharingServicePicker
ToolbarItem
in your app's toolbar
automatically uses
this property.
On iOS, Siri uses the same
property to share data
using Share This.
Of course, the toolbar
is not the only place
your app can offer items
to share.
Often, you'd want to allow
sharing of images
or other items
through a context menu.
To do this, return an
activityItemsConfiguration
object from your view
then add a
contextMenuInteraction.
Here are the results,
on both Mac Catalyst and iPad.
On Mac Catalyst, note that
a Copy action and a Share menu
are automatically added.
And when your app
runs on iPad,
a Copy and Share action
are added.
Tapping the Share action
automatically presents
the share sheet.
Using the Activity Items
Configuration API
allows your app to declare
what its views can share
so the system can display the
appropriate UI on each platform.
Now that we've talked about
how your app can share its data,
let's talk about how your app
can import images
from an iPhone or iPad
using Continuity Camera.
If your app uses a UITextView
to display rich text,
Continuity Camera support
is automatically enabled
in macOS Monterey.
A right-click on a text view
will show a context menu
with an option to take a photo
on your iPhone or iPad
and automatically add it
as an attachment.
To add support for
Continuity Camera to any view,
simply return
a UIPasteConfiguration object
that accepts images
from your view's
pasteConfiguration property,
then add a UI
contextMenuInteraction.
Then implement the
paste(itemProviders:) function
to load and paste
the incoming objects --
in this case, images.
As a bonus, returning
a paste configuration
from your view not only
enables Continuity Camera
when the configuration
accepts images,
it also automatically
enables a Paste action
in the context menu
and allows your view
to accept incoming drags,
both on Mac Catalyst and iPad.
So those are some
specific things you can do
to help make your app
a great Mac Catalyst app.
Now let's go back to Owen
to talk about distribution.
Owen: Thanks, Dave.
When it comes
to releasing your app,
the big thing to remember
is that Mac Catalyst apps
are Mac apps,
and can be distributed
through all the same means
as any other Mac app.
You can publish your app
on the Mac App Store,
with the option
for Universal Purchase
so your existing iOS customers
automatically get your Mac app.
You have access to TestFlight
for beta releases of your app
and to get early feedback
on new builds.
You can also use
App Notarization
and distribute it yourself.
And if you develop a framework,
use XCFrameworks
to distribute cross-platform,
bundling together binaries
for all platforms.
Today, we've covered the process
of building your iOS app for Mac
with Mac Catalyst,
and highlighted
some important decisions
and changes to make
along the way.
Now it's time to consider
your own projects.
It's easy to get your app
running on Mac,
and with just a little bit
of work,
you can make your app
feel right at home
and make it available to a whole
new set of excited customers.
Thank you!
♪