[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Justin] Hi. My name is Justin.
I'm a Photos engineer.
Together with my colleague,
Adam, we will talk about
ways to improve access
to Photos in your app.
First, I will talk about
the improvements we made
to the system Photos picker.
Then, Adam will show
the new cloud identifier APIs
and how you can use them
to identify the same asset
across different devices.
Lastly, he will
also discuss changes
to the limited
library access mode.
Let's start
with the Photos picker.
In iOS 14,
we introduced PHPicker,
the modern replacement
for UIImagePickerController.
The PHPicker API ensures privacy
while providing your app
the features you need,
like multiple image selection
and search.
If you haven't heard
of PHPicker,
you can watch our WWDC 2020
"Meet the new Photos picker"
session to learn more about it.
In iOS 15,
the system Photos picker
has four major improvements.
First, privacy.
We believe it's important to let
people know what information
your app can access,
which increases trust.
In iOS 14,
some people may assume
that your app has access
to their entire photo library,
even if it only presents
the out-of-process Photos picker
and only has access
to photos they selected.
To help people
understand the difference,
we added a new section
to Settings > Privacy > Photos.
The new section contains apps
that only use the system
Photos picker,
explaining that those apps
only have access
to photos people selected.
We really encourage you
to replace your custom picker
with the system one
if you haven't done so already.
Next, let's talk about
ordered selection.
Sometimes,
people may want to control
the order of photos
when selecting them.
In iOS 15, your app can
configure the picker
to show the selection order,
as shown here.
By default, we will still show
the selection checkmark.
To opt in to the new
ordered selection behavior,
you only need to enable
multiple selection
and set "selection"
to "ordered."
The PHPicker API works great
when all someone needs to do
is to select new photos.
But what if people
also want to deselect photos
using the picker?
In iOS 15, a new preselection
API is available for you to use.
But before we talk about
the new API, let's revisit
how the PHPicker API
is used currently.
You just need to create
a PHPickerConfiguration object
and use it
to initialize the picker.
When the picker session
is completed,
selected photos will
be returned to your app.
Suppose the configuration
is initialized
with a PHPhotoLibrary object,
picker results will contain
both item providers
and asset identifiers.
Your app can use
the item provider
to load and display
selected photos.
In iOS 15,
you can also present the picker
with some photos
initially selected.
It allows people
to select more photos
or deselect those photos
preselected by your app.
To do it, you need to create
a new configuration object.
You can give the configuration
an array of asset identifiers
you retrieved previously,
ID: 1 and ID: 2 in this case.
When a new
PHPickerViewController
is presented, photos with ID: 1
and ID: 2 will be
selected by default.
People can deselect them
or select additional photos.
You still want to keep
the old picker results for now
because you will
need to use them later.
Let's say the photo
with ID: 2 is deselected,
but a new photo with ID: 3
is added to the selection.
When the picker
session is completed,
selected photos
will be returned.
But the first result only has
the asset identifier
without the actual asset data.
Why?
Because it was selected
by your app.
All results
not selected by people
using your app have
empty item providers.
Old picker results
have actual asset data,
so you can use the old
ID: 1 result to replace
the one
with the empty item provider.
Because ID: 2
is no longer selected,
you can discard
the old ID: 2 result.
OK.
Now we can continue handling
selected photos like before.
To summarize: if a picker
session is completed,
all selected assets,
including preselected assets
that haven't been deselected,
will be returned.
And keep in mind,
returned item providers
for preselected assets
will be empty.
In the case
a picker session is canceled,
only preselected assets
will be returned.
All item providers
will be empty.
All right,
let's take a look at the code.
To set preselected assets,
you only need to initialize
the configuration
with a photoLibrary object
and enable multiple selection.
You can set preselected assets
using the new
preselectedAssetIdentifiers API.
In the delegate callback,
you need to retrieve
the existingSelection from
the previous picker session.
Then, you can iterate
through all
of the newly returned
picker results.
You should replace new results
with the old results
if they are part
of the existing selection.
Finally, you can save
the updated selection.
Last but not least, let's talk
about progress reporting.
It can take some time
to download a large asset
if it's not available
locally on the device,
which can happen
if iCloud Photos
and Optimize Storage
are turned on.
Previously, you can only
show a spinner while loading,
which is not always
the ideal user experience.
I'm happy to announce
that in iOS 15, your app can
retrieve the actual loading
progress from the picker.
The loading progress
is available
via the existing
NSItemProvider API.
You can use
the returned progress
to show
a loading UI accordingly.
That's all
for the Photos picker update.
Now I will hand over
to my colleague, Adam,
to talk more about the new
cloudIdentifier APIs.
[Adam] Thanks, Justin.
With the new features
and APIs we've added,
Photos picker is the best way
for most developers
to use Photos in their apps.
But we know there are special
categories of applications
that require a deeper level
of access and integration
for managing or editing photos,
custom cameras,
or apps that give people a way
to browse their photo library
in a unique way.
For those apps,
PhotoKit provides a rich set
of APIs for accessing
and updating photos,
videos, and albums
stored in the photo library.
Assets and albums
are given unique identifiers
by PhotoKit that can be
saved in your app
and then later used to retrieve
the same records
from the photo library.
Every photo library
and its identifiers are specific
to the device
they are running on,
even when
those devices are syncing
libraries with iCloud Photos.
So let's turn our attention
back to your app.
People love the way
they can use apps on an iPhone
when they're out and about
and then, back at their desk,
use a laptop or iPad to take
advantage of the larger format.
Your customers want
a seamless experience
when switching
from one device to another.
For example,
let's say I've built
a photo journaling app
for people
to document experiences
with pictures and comments.
It's perfect as an iPhone app
for capturing content on the go.
They should be able to pick up
working on that journal
right where they left off
when they open my app
on an iPad or Mac,
with all the photos
and content they added
on their phone.
So how does that work?
How do you find the same
assets when each device has
its own photo library
and distinct identifiers?
It works by using the new
cloud identifier APIs.
They give you a way
to find the same assets
and albums between devices.
You use cloud identifiers
to look up the local identifiers
that are unique
to each photo library.
And these new APIs
are available on every platform
that supports PhotoKit: iOS,
iPadOS, macOS, and tvOS.
The goal is to give you
a simple way to map assets
between devices without
having to worry about the cloud.
It's designed to work best
when running on an account
signed in to iCloud Photos,
but cloud identifiers will work
even if the account is
signed out or running
on a system that has
never been signed in to iCloud.
It's all based on identifier
mapping, so let's be clear.
There are two kinds
of identifiers.
Local identifiers are what
I talked about earlier,
the identifiers
you use on the device
that are specific
to that library.
If you've used PhotoKit before,
you've seen them called
localIdentifiers in the API.
Cloud identifiers are
the new API, which are used
to look up local identifiers
on one device or another.
They are represented
by a newly available class
called PHCloudIdentifier.
Let's dig in to how to use them.
We'll start on the source
device, where your app has
gathered a list of local
identifiers for some assets.
From that array
of local identifiers,
we want to get the corresponding
cloud identifiers.
Here's an example of how to use
the API to get them.
This call to the photo library
returns a dictionary
with cloudIdentifierMapping
objects
for each localIdentifier.
We'll iterate through
that dictionary and get
a cloudIdentifier
from the cloudMapping object.
I'll talk about error handling
in a bit.
For now, we should have
our cloud identifiers
and we're ready to use them.
And the biggest benefit
of cloud identifiers
is using them everywhere,
so we need to share them
to other
cloud-connected devices.
You want to make them
available to your app
when it runs on any device
connected to this
iCloud account.
You can archive
cloud identifiers to a string
and share that data
using CloudKit
or another network data service.
How you package up this data
is really up to you
and your app's needs.
Think about how you'll use
the information
on a second device.
How do you reconstruct
the application state to include
the content referenced
by those cloud identifiers?
Now, on a second device, once
you've downloaded and unarchived
the cloud identifiers,
we want to use them to look up
the library-specific
local identifiers.
Working in the other direction,
this call to the photo library
returns a dictionary with
localIdentifierMapping objects
for each cloudIdentifier.
Again, we'll iterate through
the dictionary and this time get
a localIdentifier
from the localMapping object.
Once I have
all the localIdentifiers,
I can use them
to fetch and display
the assets I had
on the source device.
You can see how the API makes it
easy to look up identifiers
in both directions,
but the reality of different
device configurations,
account settings,
network states,
and countless other variables
can mean things aren't
always that simple.
To handle that complexity,
the API uses a pair
of helper objects
to hold a valid identifier
or an error indicating
why the mapping failed.
There are two kinds of errors
you should handle
when looking up
identifier mappings.
If the photo library isn't able
to resolve an identifier mapping
because the underlying record
isn't present or the app
doesn't have access to it,
the mapping object returned
by the API will contain
the Identifier Not Found error.
Here you can see
how we're getting the error code
from the
localIdentifierMapping object
if the identifier isn't set.
For an Identifier Not Found
error, it makes sense
to keep track of the unresolved
cloudIdentifier so we can put
a placeholder in the UI
to indicate the photo
couldn't be found
on this device.
The other type of error happens
if we can't resolve
an identifier mapping uniquely.
In other words,
there are multiple assets
that match
the provided cloud identifier.
This can happen
if the cloud state isn't
totally in sync on this device
and the library has to rely
on the image content
to find a match.
In this case,
the mapping object will have
a Multiple Identifiers Found
error, and the error
user info will contain
the matching identifiers.
With the Multiple Identifiers
Found error code,
we can get the matching
local identifiers
from the error user info using
the LocalIdentifiersErrorKey.
In this example,
we've stashed them
in a dictionary
so we can later fetch
and show the matching assets
and let the customer decide.
That's an overview of cloud
identifiers and how to use them.
Keep in mind
that looking up the mappings
between local and cloud
identifiers can be expensive,
so use local identifiers
in your app interactions
with the photo library,
perform the mapping work
at load and save points,
and then store and share
the cloud identifiers to make
them available on other devices.
Next up, limited library.
Before we dive into
the updates to limited library,
let's quickly review
how photo library access works.
When someone launches
an app and requests access
to photos data using PhotoKit,
the system requires
their permission
before granting the app access.
And the first time this happens,
they'll see an alert
like this one.
This is really important
to our customers.
It gives them the control
over how much access
to give this application:
to allow access to a limited
selection of photos,
full access
to their entire library,
or to deny access completely.
If they choose
the Select Photos option,
then the app is granted
limited library access.
You can refer
to our WWDC '20 session
"Handle the Limited Photos
Library in your app"
for a more complete description
of limited library mode
and how to design your app
to work best with it.
For now, it's enough to know
that limited library access
is designed to be transparent
to the app developer.
In general,
PhotoKit APIs should work
like normal,
behaving like the library
only contains the photos
that were selected.
It works conveniently
with common workflows.
For example,
when an app adds a photo
to the library,
that photo is automatically
included in the app's
limited library selection.
There is another workflow
we see in apps
using a custom album
to keep track
of the assets they've added.
But in iOS 14,
limited library mode
did not allow creation
or access to custom albums.
I'm happy to tell you
that in iOS 15, we've added
support for applications
to create, fetch,
and update their own albums when
running in limited library mode.
Now let's turn our attention
to a different workflow,
and for this,
I'm going to refer back
to my example
photo journaling app.
Since I want to give
my customers a great experience
when they've chosen limited
library access for my app,
I've customized the interface
to present
limited library picker
as part of creating
a new journal.
This provides a natural step
during journal creation
for them to choose more photos.
But once the selection
is updated,
it would be great to know
what photos were added,
since they're the ones
my customer wants
to use in this journal.
With a new
presentLimitedLibraryPicker
API in iOS 15, I can pass in
a completion handler
that gives me the identifiers
of the photos they just selected
in the picker.
This lets me know when
the selection update is done
and which assets they added.
That covers our updates
for limited library,
support for apps to create
and work with their own albums,
and a new API to give apps
a way to track
what was added to the limited
library selection.
That's most of what we had
to talk about today,
but before we go, I'd like
to leave you with the following.
For those who haven't
updated your code in a while,
it's time to move away
from Assets Library.
It's been deprecated
since iOS 9,
and we're planning to remove it
in a future SDK.
This is the time to move
to the new Photos picker
or PhotoKit for a deeper
integration with photos.
And one more reason to make
the move to PhotoKit:
we know we've had long-standing
gaps in error handling,
and I'm so happy to tell you
that we've finally
addressed those with
new error codes to identify
the underlying issue during
change request processing,
resource requests,
and library access calls.
We can't wait for you to check
out all the great new features
we've added to Photos picker
and PhotoKit in iOS 15.
Thank you.