[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Nicole] Hi!
I'm Nicole, and welcome
to "What's new in Swift."
Swift 5.5 is
our best release yet!
The Swift language continues
to evolve at a rapid pace,
with many new features,
including Swift Concurrency,
a new model for asynchronous
and concurrent programming
designed to make
concurrent programming in Swift
convenient, efficient, and safe.
In addition,
we've made it easier than ever
to develop in Swift,
thanks to advances
in the package experience,
new standard library packages,
and features enhancing
the developer experience.
As important
as these advances are,
the heart of the Swift project
is not code,
but a community of people
working towards the goals
of the Swift project.
This is why
it is important that we invest
in our community,
as well as our software.
I'd like to start things off
by talking about
an important Swift
community initiative.
Diversity is a core value
of the Swift community.
Research shows that diverse
open source projects
are more productive
and make better decisions.
Including people
from all backgrounds
and with diverse perspectives
helps a community thrive.
We, and other members
of the Swift community,
saw the opportunity
to encourage active engagement
in the Swift ecosystem
and community from a wider range
of developers with our
Diversity in Swift initiative.
The mission of Diversity
in Swift is to foster
an inclusive Swift community
by elevating
a wide variety of voices
and making it easier
for developers to start learning
or contributing to Swift,
regardless of their background.
As part of this initiative,
we have expanded
the swift.org blog
to include posts that recognize
and highlight the contributions
from a wide range of developers
within our community.
We have also created
community groups
in the Swift forums
for developers to connect
with others who may have had
similar experiences
or faced similar barriers.
To get involved
with Diversity in Swift,
or find out more,
please visit
swift.org/diversity.
We also want to help developers
already in the community
grow and reach their goals
with Swift.
To make contributing
to Swift open source projects
more approachable,
we recently announced
the Swift mentorship program
to help newcomers get
direct support and guidance
from regular contributors.
This program isn't limited
to Apple's projects.
It also encompasses
the entire ecosystem
of Swift packages
and open source tools.
Next, I'd like to talk
about packages.
Packages are
a fundamental building block
for building software,
allowing you
to conveniently take advantage
of an ever-growing array
of open source code.
Members of the Swift community
have come up
with some great solutions
to help developers
find packages,
like the Swift Package Index.
The Swift Package Index
is a page
created by the community
that helps you find
packages which support
the Swift Package Manager.
Now, in Swift 5.5 and Xcode 13,
we are providing
additional ways for you to find
and access packages,
by providing integrated
Xcode tooling support
to make it even faster
and easier to use packages
in your project as part
of your development workflow.
This year, we are introducing
Swift Package Collections,
curated lists of Swift packages
you can use
both from the command line
and from Xcode 13.
With package collections,
you no longer need to search
for packages on the Internet,
or copy and paste URLs
to add them.
You can now simply browse
a collection and add packages
from a new package
search screen in Xcode.
Package collections
are simple JSON files
you can publish anywhere.
Package collections are meant
to allow anyone to build
curated lists of packages
for different use cases.
For example, an instructor
for a computer science class
can put together
a set of packages
that helps teach
the concepts of that class,
or someone can put together
a collection of packages
that are good
for a particular domain or task,
or that are used
by their organization.
We're excited to see
all the different ways
in which people will
use collections.
We have a great presentation
on package collections
that I recommend
you check out to learn more.
Package collections include
some powerful tooling support
in Xcode.
You are now just an import away
from using your favorite APIs.
When you try to import
a module that cannot be found,
Xcode will check
if any of the packages
in the package collections
that you have configured
provide that module
and provide you the opportunity
to automatically start using
that package.
Once you choose to use
a package,
all configuration
is handled for you
based on the information
in the package collection.
Package collections
are also searchable,
making it easy to find packages
to meet your use case.
If you are interested in trying
out package collections today,
there are some
already available,
including a package collection
of the Swift Packages
that Apple publishes on GitHub.
Xcode comes pre-wired
to use the Apple collection.
If you are interested
in learning more
about package collections,
including collections
already available
from the community,
check out the new swift.org
blog post
on package collections.
Speaking of your favorite APIs,
Apple publishes
a growing family
of open source Swift packages.
In addition
to some big enhancements
to your favorite packages,
this year,
we launched
four more new packages.
First, I'd like to tell you
about Swift Collections.
Swift Collections is a new
open source package
of data structures
that complements those available
in the Swift Standard Library.
The initial version
of Swift Collections
comes with implementations
for three
of the most frequently requested
data structures:
Deque, OrderedSet,
and OrderedDictionary.
Deque is like an Array,
except that it supports
efficient insertion
and removal at both ends.
OrderedSet is a powerful hybrid
of an Array and a Set.
Like Array, OrderedSet
maintains its elements in order
and supports random access.
Like a Set,
OrderedSet ensures each element
appears only once and provides
efficient membership testing.
And last is OrderedDictionary,
which is a useful alternative
to Dictionary
when order is important,
or we need
random access to elements.
Next, let's talk
about Swift Algorithms.
Swift Algorithms is
a new open source package
of Sequence
and Collection algorithms.
We've already added over 40
algorithms to Swift Algorithms
for things like generating all
the combinations or permutations
of a collection of elements,
or iterating the elements
of a sequence by two
or three or in groups
determined by a predicate,
or selecting the five smallest
elements in a collection,
the five largest,
or just any five at random.
It takes a little investment
to learn the vocabulary,
but once you do,
it can be striking to discover
just how many algorithms
are hiding in plain sight.
If you want to learn more,
we have a session
which describes
how the new Swift Algorithms
and Collections packages
can help you make your code
clearer, faster,
and more correct.
Now, let's talk
about Swift System.
Last fall,
we open-sourced Swift System,
a library providing idiomatic,
low-level interfaces
to system calls.
System is available
on Apple platforms,
Linux, and even Windows.
We recently added
powerful new APIs
to System's FilePath type
for performing common path
manipulation operations.
These include the ability
to query or set extensions,
add and remove components,
and perform path normalization.
A path can be decomposed
into its root
and its relative components.
FilePath's ComponentView
is a collection
of structured path components,
meaning it comes with support
for many of Swift's generic
algorithms right out of the box.
And when targeting Windows,
Windows paths,
with their complex
root components,
are fully supported
by all the new FilePath APIs.
Next, let's talk
about Swift Numerics.
Swift Numerics received a number
of big additions this year.
We brought Float16 to iOS,
tvOS, and watchOS last year.
This year, we added Float16
support to Apple Silicon Macs
and the ability to make
Float16-based complex numbers.
Another addition this year
is complex number support
for all
the elementary functions,
like log, sine, and cosine.
Because these implementations
are written in Swift,
they are frequently
more efficient
than a traditional C library
and allow for optimizations
that would otherwise
not be possible.
Finally, let's talk
about Swift ArgumentParser.
We've continued to refine
Swift ArgumentParser this year,
with enhancements like
the ability to generate
code-completion scripts
for the Fish shell,
joined short options,
and improved error messages.
We also passed
an important milestone
this spring when
ArgumentParser was adopted
by the Swift Package Manager
in Xcode 12.5.
That's right!
If you've used
the Swift Package Manager
command-line tool recently,
you've used
Swift ArgumentParser.
Next, I'd like to talk
about some work we've done
to support Swift
on server development.
Last year, we added support
for a number of platforms,
including Amazon Linux.
This year, we've followed up
on that work by investing
in performance and functionality
for Swift server applications.
We started by enabling
static linking on Linux,
which improves
application startup time,
as well as simplifies
the deployment
of server applications,
which can now be deployed
as a single file.
Also, in Swift 5.5,
the JSON encoding and decoding
used on Linux were
reimplemented from scratch,
resulting in performance gains
for most common use cases.
Finally, we've enhanced
and optimized the performance
of the AWS Lambda
runtime library itself.
All this work made Swift
programs running on AWS Lambda
start 33% faster,
as well as 40% faster
invocation time
for a lambda routed
via AWS API Gateway.
In addition to optimizing
the AWS runtime
library performance,
we refactored it to use
our new async/await model
instead of closures.
Improving the Swift
developer experience
is another key focus
in Swift 5.5.
I'd like to start by talking
about documentation.
Providing great documentation
is key for creating a smooth
and enjoyable experience
for users of a framework.
This year,
we are introducing DocC,
a documentation compiler
that's deeply integrated
inside Xcode 13,
to help you teach developers
how to use your Swift framework
or package.
It's now easier than ever
to write and share
great documentation.
DocC is built
from the ground up,
using tools and technologies
that you already know and love,
such as markdown comments
in your Swift source code,
so that you can easily write
and diff your documentation.
We have four fantastic sessions
to show you
every aspect of DocC
documentation in Xcode.
I highly recommend
you check them out.
And now,
I'm thrilled to announce
that Swift DocC will be
open-sourced later this year.
Open-sourcing Swift DocC
will allow developers
to more easily generate
great documentation
on all of Swift's
supported platforms.
In Swift 5.5,
we invested in quality
and performance improvements
in the type checker.
One result of this is
you will see fewer
"expression too complex" errors
when compiling your code.
We also sped up the performance
for type checking
of array literals.
In this release, we're also
enhancing developer productivity
with three major improvements
to speed up incremental builds.
First of all, we now support
incremental imports,
meaning we now no longer rebuild
every source file
that imports a module
when that module changes.
In addition, we now compute
the module dependency graph
up front
so that we can quickly start
incremental builds
of only what has changed.
Finally, we've extended
selective recompilation
to work with extensions,
meaning fewer recompilations
when you change the body
of an extension.
Using the SwiftDriver open
source project as an example,
on the average,
with incremental imports
in Swift 5.5, we now recompile
less than a tenth as many files
when imported modules change,
and the build time
is decreased by about a third.
The performance improvements
from incremental imports
means that you can now
modularize your project
and change an imported module
without a large penalty
in build performance.
And by the way, some of these
performance improvements
were made possible
by an important milestone
for the Swift project,
the first part of the compiler
to be written in Swift.
This is the Swift Driver,
the program that coordinates
the compilation
of Swift source code.
This project began in late 2019
and, as of Xcode 13,
is now the default
for Swift compilation.
Finally, let's talk about
improvements we've made
to make memory management
in Swift more efficient,
so Swift programs reclaim
memory more quickly.
Swift class instances use
Automatic Reference Counting,
ARC,
to track how many
references there are
to a particular object
at any given time.
In most cases, this means
that memory management
just works in Swift,
and you don't need
to think about
memory management yourself.
ARC automatically frees up
the memory used
by class instances
when those instances
are no longer needed.
To do this, the Swift compiler
inserts a retain operation
any time a new reference
is created
and a release operation
whenever a new reference
stops being used.
This year,
we introduced a new way
to track references
inside the compiler
that allows the compiler
to significantly reduce
the number of retain
and release operations.
We've seen measurable
performance and code size
improvements from this change.
We've added an Xcode setting,
Optimize Object Lifetimes,
that will allow you to see
the effect of this new,
more aggressive ARC
optimization on your code.
For more information on ARC,
please check out
the "ARC in Swift" session.
These are just some
of the improvements
brought to you by Swift 5.5.
Next, Tim will talk to you
about Swift Concurrency
and other evolutions
in the Swift language.
[Tim] Thanks, Nicole.
We're all very excited
about Swift Concurrency,
but before I get to that,
I want to discuss a number
of other changes
we've made to Swift
to simplify and improve
everyday programming.
Here's a list
of the ergonomic improvements
we've made this year.
The SE numbers identify
Swift Evolution proposals.
Each of these proposals
was written by a member
of the community, discussed
on the Swift Evolution forum,
and approved
by the Swift Core Team
before being accepted
into the language.
All SE proposals,
whether accepted, rejected,
or still in discussion,
can be found
in the Swift Evolution
repository on GitHub.
Let's look
at a few of these changes.
First, Result Builders.
When SwiftUI
was first announced,
it introduced a new syntax
that could be used
to quickly and easily describe
complex object hierarchies.
This past year, that syntax
was standardized and refined
through the Swift Evolution
process so that it could be
more easily used
in a wide variety of contexts.
If you'd like to take advantage
of this powerful technology,
we have a session
specifically devoted
to using Result Builders.
The Codable protocol
is a convenient way
to serialize your data,
but it's long suffered
from a notable omission.
Consider this two-case Enum.
In order to make it conform
to Codable, you used to have
to manually implement
all of this boilerplate.
Now, you just need to declare
the Codable conformance,
and the compiler will do
all of that work for you.
We also made
some key improvements
to Swift's type checker.
As you know,
type inference in Swift
means you can omit
redundant type information.
Here, it lets you shorten
Coffee.regular
down to just .regular.
But Enum-like structures are
also represented in other ways.
For example, you might have
a collection of types
that conform to a protocol
and want to use instances
of those types in your API.
You can now refer to instances
of those types
using the same dot-notation
that you use for Enums,
by declaring a few static
properties on your protocol.
This is enabled by improvements
to Swift's type checker
that allows it to reason
more generally
about static properties
in generic contexts,
including chained
property references
such as the .large here.
This allows library authors
to build sophisticated generic
data models with natural
and easy-to-use Enum-like APIs.
Property wrappers were
also improved this year.
Property wrappers
are a convenient tool
for applying common
semantics to properties.
Many of you have implemented
your own property wrappers
using the @propertyWrapper
annotation on a struct.
Here's an example
that adds the requirement
that the property not be empty.
With the implementation
of SE-0293,
those same property wrappers
can now be used
on function
and closure parameters.
Cumulatively,
these and other changes
to the language can simplify
a lot of common coding problems.
Let's look at them together
in the context
of a simple SwiftUI code sample.
Here's a SwiftUI View
that has a single property,
holding an array of settings,
and a body that presents
a list of those settings,
with a toggle next to each one.
Let's review this code
and see how
the new Swift 5.5 features
can simplify it.
First, that Toggle() initializer
is obviously duplicated.
This duplication
used to be necessary,
but we've relaxed the use
of #if to allow it to surround
postfix expressions,
such as the toggleStyle
modifiers here, which allows us
to factor out that redundancy.
SwiftUI has also been updated
to take advantage of the new
type checker improvements
I mentioned earlier.
So you can use
natural dot-notation
in many more places.
It's--it's a little awkward
to specify indexes
for the settings array
and then index the array
within the closure.
We'd rather just step
through the values.
Now you can pass
the projected binding
directly into
the List constructor,
which can then iterate
over the array values.
The new support
for property wrapper arguments
lets us write the closure
argument with a dollar sign,
which will give us
a bound setting in our closure.
That, in turn,
allows us to access
both the wrapped value
and the binding.
And finally, the Swift compiler
now transparently converts
between CGFloat and Double,
which allows you to eliminate
many redundant numeric
conversions when working
with Apple platform APIs.
As you see,
our continuing effort
to refine the core language
is making the code you write
every day simpler than ever
and creating more opportunities
for library authors to build
rich and easy-to-use APIs.
For more information
about some of the many ways
that SwiftUI programming
has been improved this year,
please watch the "What's new
in SwiftUI" session.
Of course,
the highlight of Swift 5.5
is a set
of interlocking features
to support asynchronous
and concurrent programming.
I'll introduce these
in a moment, but first,
let me briefly explain
what I mean by "asynchronous"
and "concurrent."
Software projects are composed
out of blocks of code
that execute in some order.
In the simplest case,
those blocks execute,
one after the other
in a simple sequence.
But other structures
are common as well.
For example, networking APIs
are often designed
in an asynchronous style.
In these APIs,
after you've sent a request
to the remote server,
there may be a long delay
until you receive a response
and need to do more work.
Ideally, your code
would be suspended
during this delay
so it does not use any resources
until you are able
to act on the response.
In contrast,
concurrent code is when
you have two or more
blocks of code
that you would like to have
running at the same time.
These are often independent
but related operations.
Processing several frames
of a video, for instance,
or running the next iteration
of an ML classifier
at the same time
that you're updating the UI
with the previous set
of results.
With those ideas in mind,
let's look at a simple
asynchronous programming example
without using
Swift's new features.
If you've done much
iOS or macOS programming,
you may have written code
similar to this many times.
This uses Foundation's
URLSession class
to make a network call.
The dataTask method
is an asynchronous operation.
You call it
with a closure argument.
When the result
becomes available,
your closure will be called
with the results to process.
Using closures in this way
to express asynchronous code
results in a somewhat awkward
order of operations, though,
as you can see
by walking through this code.
First, there's
some initial setup,
and the dataTask method
gives us back a task handle.
Then we resume the task handle
to start
the background operation.
The fetchImage function
actually returns at this point.
Whoever called us must be
ready to continue,
even though we haven't
actually done the work
we were asked to do.
Later, after the network
operation finishes,
this closure will have a chance
to deal with the results.
Hopefully, everything goes well,
and we can
call our completion handler
with the final result.
Besides the somewhat awkward
order of execution,
using completion handlers
also prevents us
from using
try/catch error handling.
Notice how dataTask provides
an extra error parameter
to its completion handler
and how we have to invoke
our completion handler
with every possible error.
To see how
Swift 5.5 improves this,
let's take a look
at this one line of code.
Notice how this call
returns a task,
an abstract handle
that represents
the background operation.
That's not really what we want.
We just want to get the data.
So let's push that idea a bit
and see where we end up.
Since we're dealing with HTTP,
we also need to capture
some response metadata.
So the function is really
going to return a pair,
with the actual data
as the first item
and additional information
as the second.
By structuring this
as a function call
that returns the data,
we can now use
try/catch error handling
to eliminate
a lot of the boilerplate
from the previous example.
We just need a bit of syntax
to tell the compiler
that our function
can be suspended
as soon
as the data method begins
and that we won't be able
to finish the assignment
until that operation
has completed.
Which is exactly what
the new await keyword does.
Let's look at that in context.
Here's what our fetchImage
function looks like now.
As you see, this code is
now much easier to follow.
Control flows
from top to bottom,
we no longer need
nested closures,
and we can use
try/catch error handling.
The await keyword
indicates a point
where this fetchImage function
can be suspended,
set aside to not run
until some event happens
that allows it to continue.
In this case,
as soon as URLSession
initiates the request,
our function will be
suspended by the Swift runtime
while the operation is
carried out elsewhere.
When the final result is ready,
whether that's a successful
response or a thrown error,
only then will our function
be resumed.
If it's a successful response,
we'll complete
the initialization of the data
and response variables.
If it's a thrown error,
we'll pass that back
to whoever called us.
An asynchronous function
does not use
any resources
while it's suspended.
In particular,
it's not blocking a thread.
This allows the Swift runtime
to reuse the thread
this function was running on
for other work.
This allows a very few threads
to be shared
among many
asynchronous processes.
Syntactically,
the async and await keywords
are used similarly
to throws and try.
async decorates the function
declaration to indicate
that this function must be
compiled to support suspension.
Use the await keyword
to mark any call
to an async function,
method, or closure.
Of course, the full mechanism
is a lot more interesting
than what I've shown here.
You can watch
the "Meet async/await in Swift"
and "Swift concurrency:
Behind the scenes" sessions
to learn more
about how all of this works.
Next, let's take a look at
Swift's new concurrency support,
which builds on the async/await
concepts I just described.
Here's a function that renders
three different images
and then combines them.
As written here,
these operations are sequential.
The background, foreground,
and title images will be
rendered one after the other,
with each one starting
only after the previous one
has completed.
We'd like for the rendering
operations to occur in parallel.
But just running them
in different threads
isn't enough:
we also need the merge operation
to be held,
until we have all three results.
This is similar,
in some respects,
to the asynchronous coding
I was just talking about.
So we mark this function "async"
so that it will be able
to suspend if it needs to wait
for results that are being
computed in other threads.
Next, we use
the async let syntax
to run the first two operations
in parallel.
async let looks a lot
like a variable initialization,
and that's basically what it is.
But this initialization
will run in parallel
with other code until you try
to use the results.
Because the background
and foreground variables
are being initialized
with async let,
Swift's runtime will,
if necessary,
suspend the merge operation
until those values are ready.
We mark the merge function
with the await keyword
to indicate this.
The most important point
about this code
is that the background tasks
cannot outlive this function.
Put another way,
this function cannot
and will not return if either
of the two background tasks
is still running.
If an error is
thrown from anywhere
inside this function,
the Swift runtime will
still wait for the background
tasks to complete.
Here, I've highlighted
a try marker that indicates
the computation
of the title image may throw,
but the same applies
to all thrown errors,
even if they occur
in a separate thread.
In order
to keep things responsive,
when there is a thrown error,
the Swift runtime will signal
unfinished tasks to give them
a chance to complete early.
Our session
on structured concurrency
provides more details,
including a full discussion
of this cancellation mechanism
and more flexible alternatives
to the async let syntax
I've discussed here.
In the previous section,
I showed how Swift 5.5
makes it easy to run operations
on multiple threads
in a disciplined,
structured fashion.
Of course,
that's not quite enough.
Whenever two separate threads
share data,
you run the risk that the data
will be inconsistent,
or even corrupted.
Swift's new actor construct
helps protect your data
against such problems.
Again, let's start
with an example of code
you may have written yourself.
Here's a class
that collects statistics.
It contains a counter,
and various other code
will call the increment method
to update that counter
whenever something
interesting happens.
Unfortunately,
this code doesn't work well
in a multi-threaded system.
If two or more threads
call the increment method
at the same time, you can end up
with a badly-corrupted count.
Changing this class
into a Swift actor
protects against
such corruption.
Actors work by suspending
any operation that might cause
data corruption until it's safe
to make that particular change.
This means you generally
need to use await
when you call an actor method
from outside of the actor.
Actors also work seamlessly
with async/await.
Marking this publish method
as async allows it
to be suspended while waiting
on network operations.
While it's suspended,
other methods can run
on this actor without waiting
for the network operation
to complete and without risk
of data corruption.
Actors are reference types,
like classes,
but they obey a number
of rules designed to ensure
that actors are safe to use
in a multi-threaded environment.
By packaging your data
into actors,
you are clearly stating
that you expect this data
to be accessed concurrently
and that you want
the Swift compiler and runtime
to coordinate access so that
no corruption is possible.
And, of course,
we have a full session
devoted specifically to Swift's
new actor construct.
There, you can find out
how to take advantage
of the full range
of capabilities this brings.
Before we wrap up,
let's talk a little bit
about the future of Swift.
We believe
the three key concepts
we've introduced in Swift 5.5--
asynchronous functions,
structured concurrency,
and actors--
are a good basis
for creating safe
and high-performance code.
For Swift 6,
we're already researching ways
for the compiler to catch more
kinds of concurrency mistakes
earlier in
the development process
and give you
more detailed errors
and guidance
in fixing those issues.
Our goal, quite simply,
is to entirely eliminate
the most common kinds
of concurrency bugs,
in order to make asynchronous
and concurrent programming
no more complex than
any other kind of programming.
And, of course,
as we continue to improve
the compiler's understanding
of these concepts,
we also expect code
using these new constructs
to become even more efficient
than it is today.
Swift is an open, collaborative
effort that welcomes your input.
To help make Swift 6
even better,
tell us about your experiences
with Swift 5.5.
How well are these new features
working for you
in real-world app development?
Try one
of the compiler snapshots
that you can find on swift.org.
We provide these snapshots so
you can install them into Xcode
and try out new features
as we're developing them.
By using these snapshots,
you can help guide
the next version of Swift.
The Swift forums
are the lifeblood
of the project.
Each of the features
I've discussed started life
by being pitched
on the Swift Evolution forum,
where a diverse group of people
helped to refine it
into a working proposal.
We also have forums devoted
to many other aspects of Swift,
including a help area
for new users and a place
to exchange news of interest
to the Swift community.
There are many other ways
you can make Swift better,
and we are eager
to engage even more people,
such as through
the new Mentorship Program
that Nicole mentioned at
the beginning of this session.
The only requirement
is a sincere desire
to help improve Swift
for everyone in our community.
I look forward
to hearing from you,
and I hope you enjoy
the conference.
[upbeat music]