[upbeat music]
[Bharath] Hello,
my name is Bharath,
and I am from Apple's
Core Audio team.
And today,
and I would like to talk to you
about geometry-aware audio
with PHASE.
We will talk about why
you would want to use
the new PHASE framework.
We will introduce you to
some of the features
the framework offers.
Then, I will hand it over to
my colleague, David Thall,
to take you through concepts
in some depth
and sample use cases
with this API.
Let's begin.
Audio is a critical aspect of
any gaming experience.
Spatial audio on headphones
takes the overall
gameplay to the next level
and makes you
feel more involved.
In games today,
various subsystems of the
engine like physics,
animation, visual effects,
et cetera,
all communicate
with each other and move
the game flow or storyline
forward
based on the player's actions.
However, the audio
subsystem is generally managed
and driven separately
from the rest.
They sometimes are also
authored through middleware
that isn't always aware
of the simulation.
Audio assets
are post-produced, pre-baked,
hand-tuned
to tell an audio story
that matches the game visuals.
As visuals evolve,
audio system, sound design,
and associated assets
needs to be regenerated
to keep audio experience
cohesive
on a wide range of
platforms.
This iterative
development process needs to be
accounted for during the game
development.
This typically leads
to audio experiences
lagging the visual side
of the gameplay.
To provide a better
game audio experience,
we want to bring
the audio system
closer to other subsystems.
We also
want to make it easier for you
to write applications
that can provide
a consistent spatial
audio experience
on all these
supported devices.
Let us now take you through
the new audio framework
PHASE and its features.
PHASE is a new framework
that will enable you to provide
geometry information
to the audio engine,
help you build a sound-design
friendly,
event-driven audio playback
system,
enable you to write applications
that can automatically provide
a consistent spatial audio
experience
across all supported devices
and can be integrated
with existing authoring
solutions and pipelines.
Before we jump into
learning more about PHASE,
let us review a commonly used
game audio workflow.
Here's an example
outdoor scene
with a listener, a sound source,
a creek flowing and an occluder,
a barn.
Occluders are objects
in the scene
that could dampen the sound
between a source
and the listener.
Typically, you would place
multiple point sources
along an area.
As the listener moves,
you have to use various
techniques
such as ray tracing
to determine the proper
filtering and mix ratio
between the point sources
and manually blend between them
to provide a good
audio experience.
During the natural course
of the game development,
if visual scenes change,
for example,
the barn in the
example scene,
you have to update and
hand-tune the audio experience
to match the visual scene
change.
Imagine you can build
applications
where audio sources are
not points
you need to manage and mix
based on the scene
but rather as sound
emanating over an area
or volume that the audio system
can automatically manage
for you.
PHASE does exactly that.
Introducing volumetric sources.
The new framework provides API
that allows you to pass sound
sources as geometric shapes
to the underlying audio engine.
In addition
to volumetric sound sources,
you can also pass occluders
in the scene as geometric
shapes.
You can also choose
acoustic material properties
from a set of presets and attach
them to occluders.
PHASE framework also allows
you to set medium propagation
and source directivity for
point sources
as required by your application.
We are looking at
an outdoor scene
as an example here.
However, if your
application has indoor scenes,
you can choose early reflections
and late reverberation
properties from
a library of presets.
Once you tell the framework
where various sound sources,
occluders, and the listener are,
PHASE will help
with the heavy lifting and model
the occlusion and spreading
effects of various sound sources
in the scene for you.
Now that your application's
audio system is geometry aware,
it can adapt to visual scene
changes
much quicker
as the game development evolves.
In addition to geometry
awareness,
PHASE also provides
an event-based
interactive playback system.
Sound events are basic units for
describing audio playback events
in PHASE.
They encapsulate the selection,
blending,
and playback of audio assets.
Sound events can range
from simple events
like one-shot playback, looping,
to complex sequences
organized as a tree
that can blend or switch
between subtrees
of playback events.
Let us take a simple example of
playing footsteps.
Here we have a random node
that will automatically
choose between three different
sounds of a footstep on gravel.
We can have another sound event
for cloth rustle.
Both event trees can be grafted
onto another tree,
"near" in this example,
to play back a mix of cloth
rustle and footsteps sounds.
We can have another tree,
"far" in this example,
to play a different set of
sounds
when the character is at a
distance.
The mix of near
and far trees
can be now controlled by
distance based on the gameplay.
You can add more event trees
like footstep on snow or grass,
for example,
and build a complex sequence
of playback events
that can be triggered by user
interaction or by subsystems
like physics and animation.
With PHASE, sounds can be
played either to a simple
channel configuration or in a 3D
space
with orientation and position,
or as ambient beds
where the sounds have
orientation but no position.
The underlying engine
is built upon
our spatial
audio rendering capabilities
already available on supported
iOS, macOS devices,
and also Air Pods family
of headphones.
This enables you to build
applications
that provide a consistent
spatial audio experience
on all the supported devices
automatically.
Next, I would like to invite
David Thall
to dive deeper
into PHASE and talk more about
the concepts and the API
for some example use cases.
[David] Hi, everyone,
my name is David Thall,
and I'm System Architect and
Development Lead on PHASE.
Today I'm going to
walk you through the PHASE API.
In this section, I'll introduce
you to the general concepts.
Following this, I'll run through
some sample use cases
to get you started.
The PHASE API can be separated
into three main concepts.
The engine manages assets.
Nodes control playback.
And mixers control
spatialization.
The PHASE engine
can be broken down into
three main sections.
The asset registry, scene graph,
and rendering state.
Throughout the engine life cycle
you'll register and unregister
assets with the engine.
Today, PHASE supports
registering sound assets
and sound event assets.
Sound assets can be loaded
directly from an audio file
or packed and embedded
as raw audio data
in your own assets and loaded
directly into the engine.
Sound event assets
are a collection of one or more
hierarchical nodes that control
sound playback
and downstream mixers that
control spatialization.
The scene graph is a hierarchy
of objects that take part
in the simulation.
This includes listeners,
sources, and occluders.
A listener is an object that
represents the location in space
from which
you hear the simulation.
A source is an object
that represents
where sound originates.
As Bharath mentioned earlier,
PHASE supports both
point sources
and volumetric sources.
An occluder is an object that
represents the geometry
in the simulation that affects
sound transmission
as it moves
through the environment.
Occluders are also assigned
materials that affect
how they absorb and transmit
sound.
PHASE comes with a library
of material presets that
can be assigned to occluders
to simulate everything
from cardboard boxes
to glass windows
to brick walls.
As you add objects to your
scene, you'll organize them into
a hierarchy and attach them
to the engine's root object,
either directly or indirectly.
This will ensure
they take part in the simulation
from frame to frame.
The rendering state manages
playing sound events
and audio IO.
When you first create the
engine, audio IO is disabled.
This allows you
to register your assets,
build your scene graph,
construct sound events,
and perform other engine
operations,
all without having to run
audio IO.
Once you're ready
to play back sound events,
you can start the engine,
which will internally start
the audio IO.
Likewise, when you're finished
playing back sound events,
you can stop the engine.
This will stop the audio IO
and stop any playing
sound events.
Nodes in PHASE control playback
of audio content.
Nodes are a hierarchical
collection of objects
that either generate
or control audio playback.
Generator nodes
produce audio.
They are always leaf nodes
in a node hierarchy.
Control nodes set the logic
for how generators are selected,
mixed and parameterized
before spatialization.
Control nodes are
always parent nodes
and can be organized into
hierarchies
for complex sound design
scenarios.
A sampler node is a type
of generator node.
Samplers play back
registered sound assets.
Once constructed, you can
set some basic properties
on the sampler node to get it
to play back correctly.
The playback mode determines how
the audio file will be played.
If you set
the playback mode to OneShot,
the audio file will play once
and automatically stop itself.
This can be used
in "fire-and-forget" scenarios,
such as triggering sound
effects.
If you set the playback mode to
looping,
the audio file will
play indefinitely,
until you explicitly stop the
sampler.
The cull option
tells PHASE what to do
when the sound becomes
inaudible.
If you set the cull
option to terminate,
the sound will automatically
stop itself
when it becomes inaudible.
If you
set the cull option to sleep,
the sound will stop rendering
when it becomes inaudible
and start rendering again when
it becomes audible.
This makes
it so you don't have to
manually start and stop sounds
when they are culled
by the engine.
The calibration level sets the
real-world level of the sound
in decibels SPL.
PHASE also supports
four types of control nodes.
These include random, switch,
blend and container nodes.
The random node
selects one of its children
according
to a weighted random choice.
For example, in this case,
the left sampler has 4:1 odds
over the right sampler of being
selected the next time the sound
event is triggered.
The switch node
switches between its children
based on a parameter name.
For example, you could change
the terrain switch
from "creaky wood"
to "soft gravel."
The next time
the sound event is triggered,
it'll select the sampler that
matches the parameter name.
The blend node blends between
its children
based on a parameter value.
For example, you could assign
a wetness parameter
to a blend node,
which could blend between
a loud footstep
and quiet splash on the dry end
and a quiet footstep and
loud splash on the wet end.
The container node plays
all its children at once.
For example, you could
have one sampler
that plays back a footstep
and another sampler that plays
back the sound of clothing,
like the sound of a ruffling
Gor-Tex jacket.
Every time
the container is triggered,
both samplers will play back
at the same time.
Mixers in PHASE control
spatialization of audio content.
PHASE currently supports
channel,
ambient, and spatial mixers.
Channel mixers render
audio without spatialization
and environmental effects.
Use channel mixers for regular
stem-based content that
needs to be rendered directly
to the output device, such as
stereo music or center channel
narrative dialogue.
Ambient mixers render audio
with externalization
but without distance modeling
or environmental effects.
As the listener rotates
their head,
the sound will continue
to come from
the same relative location
in space.
Use ambient mixers
for multichannel content
that isn't being simulated
in the environment but should
still sound like it's coming
from somewhere out in space,
for example, a
background of crickets chirping
in a large forest.
Spatial mixers perform
full spatialization.
As the sound source moves
relative to the listener,
you'll hear changes
in perceived location,
level, and frequency
response based on panning,
distance modeling, and
directivity modeling algorithms.
In addition to this,
geometry-aware environmental
effects
are applied to the path between
the source and listener.
If you're wearing headphones,
you'll also get externalization
through the application
of binaural filters.
Use spatial mixers for sounds
that should take part in the
full environmental simulation.
Spatial mixers support
two unique
distance modeling algorithms.
You can set up standard
geometric spreading loss
for natural attenuation
over distance.
You can also increase or
decrease the effect
to your liking.
For example, lowering the value
could be useful
if you wanted to boom mic
a conversation at a distance.
On the other end of
the spectrum,
you can add full piecewise
curved
segments
of attenuation over distance.
For example, you could
construct a set of segments
with natural distance
attenuation
at the start and end of the
range,
but decrease the
attenuation in the middle
to keep important dialogue
audible at increased distances.
For point sources,
spatial mixers support
two different directivity
modeling algorithms.
You can add cardioid directivity
modeling
to your spatial mix.
Using some simple modifications,
you could model a human
speaker
with a cardioid directivity
pattern
or the sound of an acoustic
stringed instrument
with a hyper-cardioid pattern.
You can also add cone
directivity modeling.
This classic mode allows you
to limit directivity filtering
to within a specific
range of rotation.
Spatial mixers also support
geometry-aware environmental
effects
based on a spatial pipeline.
The spatial pipeline
selects environmental effects
to enable or disable,
as well as the send levels
to each.
PHASE currently supports
direct path transmission,
early reflections,
and late reverb.
Direct path transmission
renders the direct and occluded
paths between the source and
listener.
Note that with occluded sound,
some energy is absorbed by
materials,
while other energy is
transmitted
to the other side of the object.
Early reflections
provide both intensity
modification and coloration
to the direct path.
These are usually built
from the specular reflections
off the walls and floor.
In larger spaces, they also
add noticeable echoes
to the experience.
Late reverb provides
the sound of the environment.
It's a dense build-up
of the diffuse scattered energy
that coalesces into the final
audible representation
of the space.
In addition to providing cues
for room size and shape,
it's also responsible for giving
you a sense of envelopment.
Now
that I've reviewed the concepts
behind the PHASE engine,
nodes and mixers, it's time
to bring these concepts together
with some sample use cases.
In this section, I'll walk you
through playing an audio file,
building a spatial audio
experience,
and building a behavioral sound
event.
These three key areas
will give you a wide overview
of the capabilities of PHASE,
with a gentle introduction at
the beginning and a deep dive
into the more interesting
capabilities
toward the middle and end.
To kick things off,
I'll show you how to play
an audio file.
First, let's create a PHASE
engine instance.
Next, I'll retrieve the URL
to an audio file
and register the sound
asset with PHASE.
I'll give it the name "drums"
so I can refer to it later.
Here I'll create an engine
and register a sound asset
in code.
First, I'll create a PHASE
engine instance
in automatic update mode.
This is the preferred mode
to get things up and running,
so I'm using it here for
demoing simple playback.
Note that when a game requires
more precise synchronization
with the frame update,
manual mode is the way to go.
Check out the documentation
for more details.
Next, I'll retrieve the URL to
an audio file
stored in the application
bundle.
This is a mono 24bit,
48kHz WAV file
with a prepared drum
loop sample.
When registering the sound asset
with the engine, I'll provide
some additional arguments.
I'll give the sound asset
a unique name
so I can refer to it later.
I'll specify that the audio data
within the sound asset
should be pre-loaded into
resident memory,
as opposed to streaming it into
memory in real time.
This should be fine since the
drum loop is fairly short,
and I might want to play it back
several times
in short succession.
I'm also choosing to normalize
the sound asset
for calibrated loudness
on the output device.
In general, it's advised
to normalize the input.
This'll make it
easier to mix the content
once we assign it to a sampler
and set its
target output level.
Now that I've registered
a sound asset with the engine,
I'll construct a sound event
asset.
First I'll create a channel
mixer from a channel layout.
Then I'll create a sampler node.
The
sampler node takes the name
of the registered sound asset
and a reference to the
downstream channel mixer.
Next I'll set some basic
properties on the sampler node
to get it to play back
correctly.
The playback mode
will set whether or not
the sampler will loop
the audio file,
and the calibration level
will set
the perceived loudness of the
sampler within the mix.
Now that I've hooked the output
of the sampler node
to the input of the channel
mixer
and set some basic parameters,
it's time to register the sound
event asset with the engine.
In this case, I'll register
the sound event asset
with the name drumEvent,
which I'll use to refer to it
later.
Here I'll register a sound event
asset in code.
I'll create a channelLayout
from a mono ChannelLayoutTag.
Then I'll initialize the channel
mixer with the mono
channelLayout.
Next I'll create the sampler
node and pass in the name drums,
which refers to the mono
drum asset
I previously registered with the
engine.
The sampler node will be routed
to the downstream channel mixer.
I'll set
the playbackMode to looping.
This will ensure
the sound continues to play back
until I explicitly stop it from
code.
I'll set the
CalibrationMode to relativeSpl,
and the level to 0 decibels.
This will ensure a comfortable
listening level
for the experience.
Finally I'll register
the soundEventAsset
with the engine,
passing in the name drumEvent
so I can refer to it later
when I start creating
sound events for playback.
Once a sound event asset is
registered,
I can create an
instance and start playback.
The first thing I'll do is
create a sound event
from the registered sound
event asset named drumEvent.
Now that
I have a sound event, I'll go
ahead and start the engine.
This will start the audio IO
so I can listen to the audio
feeding the output device.
Finally I'll
start the sound event.
At this point,
the loaded sound asset
will be
played through the sampler,
routed to the channel mixer,
remapped to the current output
format,
and played back through
the output device.
Here I'll start a soundEvent
in code.
The sound event asset
is constructed from the name
of the registered sound asset.
Here,
I'm passing in drumEvent.
I'll go ahead
and start the engine,
which will start the audio IO
and start the sound event.
Once I'm finished
playing back the sound event,
I can clean up the engine.
First I'll
stop the sound event.
Then I'll stop the engine.
This will stop the audio IO and
stop any playing sound events.
Next I'll unregister the sound
event asset named drumEvent
and unregister the sound asset
named drums.
Finally I'll destroy the engine.
Here I'll do
the cleanup in code.
First I'll stop the sound event
once I'm finished
listening to the drum loop.
then I'll stop the engine,
which will internally stop
the audio IO.
Next I'll unregister the sound
event asset named drumEvent
and unregister the sound asset
named drums.
Finally I'll destroy the engine.
Now that I've covered the
basics,
I'll show you how to
build a simple
spatial audio experience in
PHASE.
We'll cover topics
including spatial mixers,
volumetric sound sources,
and occluders.
This first thing I'll do
is register a sound event asset
with the engine.
For this example,
I'll start with an engine that
already has the drums sound
event registered.
From here,
I'll upgrade the mix to go
from simple channel-based
playback to full spatialization.
The first thing I'll do is
construct a spatial pipeline
to selectively apply different
environmental effects
to my sound source.
Then I'll create a spatial
mixer from the spatial pipeline.
Once constructed,
I'll set some basic properties
on the spatial mixer to get
it to play back correctly.
In this example,
I'll set the distance model
to control level attenuation
over distance.
I'll also set the directivity
model
to control level attenuation
based on the angle between
the source relative to the
listener.
Then
I'll create a sampler node.
The sampler node takes the name
of the registered sound asset
and a reference to the
downstream spatial mixer.
Next I'll set some basic
properties on the sampler node
to get it to play back
correctly.
In addition to the
playback mode
and calibration level, I'll also
set the cull option here.
This will tell PHASE what to do
when
the sampler becomes inaudible.
Now that I've hooked the output
of our sampler node
to the input of the spatial
mixer
and set some basic parameters,
it's time to register the sound
event asset with the engine.
I'll use
the same name as before.
Here I'll create a sound event
asset in code.
First I'll create
a spatialPipeline
to render
.directPathTransmission
and .lateReverb.
I'll also go ahead and set
the .lateReverb .sendLevel
to control the
direct-to-reverberant ratio
and choose
a .mediumRoom preset
for the late reverb
simulation.
Then I'll create a spatial
mixer with the spatialPipeline.
Next
I'll create a natural-sounding
GeometricSpreadingDistanceModel
and assign it to the spatial
mixer.
I'll set the cullDistance
to 10 meters.
If the source were to go beyond
this distance,
I'd want to automatically
cull it from the mix.
And I'll adjust
the rolloffFactor a little
to de-emphasize
the distance attenuation effect.
Then
I'll create a sampler node
and pass it the name "drums,"
which refers to the mono drum
sound asset I previously
registered with the engine.
I'll set the playbackMode to
.looping.
I'll set the calibration
mode to .relativeSpl,
and the level to +12 decibels
to increase the output level
of the sampler.
And I'll set the
cullOption to sleep.
Finally, I'll register
the soundEventAsset
with the engine, passing
in the name drumEvent so I can
refer to it later when I start
creating sound events.
Now that I have a sound event
asset registered with the engine
I need to create
a scene for the simulation.
This involves creating
a listener, source,
and occluder.
In this example,
I'll place the occluder
between
the source and listener.
First I'll create a listener.
Then I'll set its transform.
Once I'm ready to make
the listener active
within the scene graph,
I'll attach it to the engine's
root object or one of its
children.
Here I'll set up the
listener in code.
First I'll create a listener.
Then I'll set its transform.
In this example,
I'll set the listener to the
origin with no rotation.
Finally I'll attach the listener
to the engine's root object.
Now let's set up a volumetric
source.
First I'll create a source shape
from a mesh.
Then I'll create a source from
the shape.
This inherently constructs
a volumetric source.
Next I'll set its transform.
And once I'm ready to make the
source active
within the scene graph,
I'll attach it to the engine's
root object
or one of its children.
Here I'll set up a volumetric
source in code.
First I'll create an Icosahedron
mesh and scale it
to about the size
of a HomePod Mini.
Then I'll create a shape
from the mesh.
This shape can be reused
to construct multiple instances
of a volumetric source.
For example, I could place
multiple HomePod Minis
in the simulation that share
the same mesh.
Next I'll create a volumetric
source from the shape.
Note that I could also create
a simple point source by using
a version of the initializer
that doesn't
take a shape as input.
Then I'll set its transform.
I'll translate the source
2 meters in front
of the listener and rotate
it back toward the listener
so they are
facing each other.
Finally I'll attach the source
to the engine's root object.
Now
let's set up an occluder.
First I'll create
a shape from a mesh.
Then I'll create
a cardboard material
and assign it to the shape.
Now the shape has a geometry
and an associated material.
Next I'll create an occluder
from the shape.
Then I'll set its transform.
And once I'm ready to make the
occluder active
within the scene graph,
I'll attach it to the engine's
root object
or one of its children.
Here I'll set up
the occluder in code.
First I'll create a boxMesh
and scale its
dimensions accordingly.
Then I'll create a shape
from the mesh.
This shape
can be reused to construct
multiple instances
of an occluder.
For example, I can place
multiple boxes in the simulation
that share the same mesh.
Next, I'll create a material
from a cardboard box preset
and assign the material
to the shape.
Next I'll create an occluder
from the shape.
Then I'll set its transform.
I'll translate the occluder
1 meter in front of the listener
and rotate it back toward
the listener
so they are facing each
other.
This puts the occluder
halfway between the source
and listener.
Finally I'll attach the occluder
to the engine's root object.
At this point, I have
a scene with an occluder halfway
between a source and listener.
Next I'll create a sound
event from our registered
sound event asset
and associate it
with the source
and listener in the scene graph.
When I start the sound event,
I'll hear an occluded drum loop
playing from a small volumetric
source
on the opposite side of a
cardboard box.
Here I'll start the sound event
in code.
First I'll associate the source
and listener
with the spatial mixer
in the sound event.
Then I'll create a soundEvent
from the registered soundEvent asset
named drumEvent.
The rest is the same
as before.
Make sure the engine is running,
then start the sound event.
Now that
I've covered spatial audio,
I'll show you how to build
a complex sound event.
Sound events can be organized
into
behavioral hierarchies
for interactive sound design.
In this section, I'll walk you
through consecutive examples
that build upon each type of
sound event node
to create the final sound event.
Here we'll model an actor
wearing a noisy Gore-Tex jacket
walking on different types
of terrain
with variable surface
wetness.
First I'll create a sampler node
that plays back a footstep
on creaky wood.
In code,
I'll create a sampler node
with a registered sound asset
named "footstep_wood_clip_1."
For this example,
this node and all others
will play back
on a single pre-constructed
channel mixer.
Now I'll add some randomness.
I'll create a random node
with two child sampler nodes
that play slightly different
footstep on creaky wood samples.
In code,
I'll create two sampler nodes.
The first
uses a registered sound asset
named "footstep_wood_clip_1
and the second
uses a registered sound asset
named
"footstep_wood_clip_2."
Then , I'll create a random node
and add the sampler nodes
as children.
Note that a weighting factor is
applied to each child node
to control
the likelihood of that child
being chosen over
successive iterations.
In this case, the first child
has twice the chance of being
selected over the second child.
Next I'll add a terrain
switch.
I'll create a switch node and
two random nodes as children.
In this case, the second
random node plays back random
footsteps on gravel as opposed
to random footsteps on wood.
I'll use a terrain parameter
to control the switch.
In code,
I'll create two sampler nodes.
The first
uses a registered sound asset
named "footstep_gravel_clip_1"
and the second
uses a registered sound asset
named
"footstep_gravel_clip_2."
Then I'll create
a random node
and add the sampler nodes as
children.
Next I'll create a terrain
parameter.
The default value will
be "creaky_wood."
Then I'll create a switch node
that's controlled by the terrain
parameter.
I'll add two children,
the wood random node
and gravel random node.
If I set the
parameter to "creaky_wood,"
it'll select the wood random
node.
Likewise, if I set the
parameter to "soft_gravel,"
it'll select the gravel random
node.
Next
I'll add a wetness blend.
I'll create a blend node
with a terrain switch node
and random splash node as
children.
The new random splash node
plays random splash noises
as the actor takes steps,
while the terrain switch
determines
if the actor's feet
are walking on creaky wood
or soft gravel.
The blend between the dry
footstep sounds
and the splashes is dependent on
the wetness parameter,
from completely dry--loud
footsteps and no splashes--
to completely wet--quiet
footsteps
and loud splashes.
In code,
I'll create two sampler nodes.
The first uses
a registered sound asset named
"splash_clip_1" and the second
uses a registered sound asset
named "splash_clip_2."
Then I'll create a random node
and add the sampler nodes
as children.
Next I'll create
a wetness parameter.
The range will be 0 to 1,
and the default value will
be 0.5.
Note that I can set the
parameter
to any value and range supported
by my game.
Then I'll create a blend node
that's controlled by the wetness
parameter.
I'll add two children,
the terrain switch node
and random splash node.
If I set the parameter to 0,
I'll only hear dry footsteps
on creaky wood or gravel,
depending on the terrain.
As I increase
the wetness from 0 to 1,
I'll increase the loudness of
splash noises
that accompany each footstep,
simulating wet terrain.
Finally I'll create a container
node with the wetness
blend node and a random noisy
clothing node as children.
The new noisy clothing node
plays back
the ruffling noises
of a Gore-Tex jacket
whenever the actor takes a step
on changing terrain with
variable wetness.
With this final node hierarchy
in place,
I have a complete representation
of the actor walking in a scene.
Every
time the actor takes a step,
I'll hear the ruffling of the
jacket,
plus footsteps
on creaky wood or soft gravel,
depending on the terrain
parameter.
In addition to this,
I'll hear more or less
of the splashes with each
footstep,
depending on the wetness
parameter.
In code, I'll create two sampler
nodes.
The first uses a
registered sound asset named
"gortex_clip_1" and the second
uses a registered sound asset
named "gortex_clip_2."
Then I'll create a random
node and add the sampler nodes
as children.
Finally I'll create
an actor_container node.
I'll add two children,
the wetness_blend node
and noisy_clothing_random
node.
Together, they represent
the complete sound
of the actor.
In review, we learned how
to play an audio file.
Following this, we expanded
our knowledge by diving
headfirst into constructing
a simple yet effective
spatial audio experience.
Here we learned about listeners,
volumetric sources,
and occluders.
Finally, we learned about
building behavioral sound events
for interactive sound design.
Here we learned about grafting
random,
switch, blend, and
container nodes together
to form hierarchical,
interactive sound events.
Taken together,
you should now have a broad
understanding of the inner
workings of PHASE
and be able to take a deeper
dive into the underlying system
components when you're ready
to settle in and build your
next geometry-aware game audio
experience.
Thank you.
Have a great WWDC21.
[upbeat music]