Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome.
My name's Yongjun,
and I'm an engineer on the App Clips team.
I'm joined today by my colleague, Luming,
to talk about how to streamline
your app clip experience.
As you know, the app clip
is a small piece of your app.
They're lightweight, delivered on demand
at the moment you need it.
They are invoked by URLs that you
have registered as app clip experiences.
Users can also easily
get your app during this experience.
Today, I will talk about three topics.
First, best practices for designing
and building your app clip.
Then, I will show an example of how to
streamline transactions in your app clip.
Finally, I will share some techniques
to help transition users
from app clip to your app.
Let's talk best practices.
App clips are designed for speed.
Interactions with App Clip
needs to be quick and focused.
Your app clip should
focus on essential tasks
and the named features to what is needed
for the task at hand.
For the vast or complex features,
reserve them for your app.
When your app clip launches,
it should be usable right away.
Include all required assets
for a fast initial experience.
Do not include splash screens
or make users wait for download
before they can start a task.
Creating an account is a complex task
and takes time and effort.
Wait to ask people to sign up
until after they have finished the task.
When asking user data, request permission
at the moment you need.
And clearly state why you need them.
When users upgrade to your app,
it replaces the app clip.
Your app should provide
the same streamlined experiences
that the app clip offers.
And make sure that your app clip
has the same name and icon as your app,
so the user can have
a consistent experience.
For more information
about app clip's design,
please check,
"Design Great App Clips" session.
To build an app clip,
you'll need to add a new target
in your app's Xcode project.
Your app already has assets and classes.
Some will be shared with your app clip.
Identify all resources
that are required for the experience.
Include them
in your app clip Apple bundle.
Keep in mind, the smaller your app clip
is, the faster it gets to your users.
So only add what you need.
For assets that are used
in both your app and app clip,
pull them in a shared asset catalog.
Organize your classes
and localization strings files
such that you can share them
for both your app and app clip.
"Sign in with Apple"
is the best way to get a user's account.
If your service supports
a federated log-in system
that isn't Sign in with Apple,
ASWebAuthenticationSession
is a great lightweight solution
to authenticate with third-party services.
It keeps the user in your app clip,
and it doesn't require
switching to an app.
For users who already have
an account with your app,
you should also offer
username-password log in.
App Clip supports Password AutoFill,
which makes logging in really easy.
If a user used passwords
to log into the app clip,
consider offering Sign in with Apple
upgrade when users get the app.
To learn about the best way to support
username and password sign-in in your app,
check out, "What's New in Authentication."
And to learn about
how to offer Sign in with Apple
and strong password upgrades,
see, "Securing Accounts with Upgrades
to Sign in with Apple
and a Strong Password" session.
App clips are ephemeral.
Your users should try them out
with great confidence
that their privacy is very protected.
Some sensitive user data
are not available to app clips.
They are not essential to a lightweight
experience an app clip offers.
And you can always encourage users
to get your app for these functionalities.
App clips can request permission
for camera, microphone, and Bluetooth.
To preserve the fast
and streamlined experience,
we also transfer this data
when the user gets your app,
so you don't need to request them again.
To know more
about app clips and app privacy,
please check out, "Build Trust
Through Better Privacy" session.
We use many iOS apps for transactions
in our daily life.
A typical transaction
involves multiple steps.
Let me walk you through with an example.
Let's say I wanted to order a smoothie.
I walk into a smoothie store, tap NFC tag
and a food app clip launches.
The app clip asks my permission
to get my location
to find out which smoothie store I'm at.
Next, the app clip
shows the menu for ordering.
I select my favorite smoothie and pay.
Then, the app clip asks my permission
to send a notification
to tell me when my smoothie's ready.
Last, this app clip offers to sign up
or sign in to get a discount later.
There are quite a few steps here.
Let's see how we can improve this...
to this.
First, location.
Your app clip can be triggered
by physical codes like NFC tags.
In our smoothie example,
the URL in the NFC tag
tells which smoothie store it is for.
With that,
you can get the location of the store,
show the right menu
and accept the payment.
However, what if the tag
is placed at the wrong store?
Or what if someone intentionally placed
a different tag in this store?
This could cause confusion
or even lead to fraud.
To prevent that, you need to know
if the user's actually at the store
when they scanned the tag.
To do that,
you need to get the user's location.
Then use that
to match the store's location.
Location confirmation reveals just
enough information to accomplish this.
You do not need the full location access.
The user has the control
to allow that in the app clip card.
When your app clip receives the payload
from a physical code,
you can ask the system if the payload
is acquired at a specific location,
and you will get a binary
yes or no answer.
No prompt needed.
To enable location confirmation,
add NSAppClipRequestLocation-
Confirmation Key to the Info.plist.
When your app clip launches,
get the payload from NSUserActivity...
then prepare the region
where the code should be acquired
with the coordinates and the radius.
You can set the radius up to 500 meters.
Last,
code confirmedAcquired(in: region) API.
The closure will tell you the result.
This is location confirmation.
Next, payment.
Just like in apps, your app clip
can use any payment method.
Apple Pay allows people
to make purchases fast and secure.
No need to enter credit card numbers.
It is a great way
to speed up the payment experience.
You can use notifications to connect
to users after they use your app clip.
To send the notifications today,
you need to request permission first.
With app clip notification,
you get permission
for up to eight hours after each launch.
User can grant the permission
in the app clip card.
After it launches,
you can send the notifications,
no prompt needed.
At any time when App Clip is running,
you can always ask for regular permission.
To enable app clip notification,
add NSAppClipRequestEphemeral-
UserNotification key to the Info.plist.
To tell if the user has granted permission
in the app clip card,
check authorizationStatus
in notifications settings.
Last, sign in.
Sign in with Apple is a private and
convenient way to create an account
or sign in with an existing one.
If a user already has
a password best account with you,
you can also use
AuthenticationServices API
to streamline the sign in
without even showing the log in screen.
Now, when you put
all these improvements together...
this transaction experience
is much smoother.
My user has the app clip.
They can easily get your app at any time.
iOS provides plenty of opportunities
for them to do it.
After your app clip's activated,
the App Banner will show your app's name,
icon and App Store link for a moment.
Tapping the banner takes the users
to the App Store
where they can install your app.
Users can also get your app
from App Clips Settings panel.
Your app clip can embed
StoreKit SKOverlay in a view.
We think it works best
if you display the overlay
after the user finishes the task.
For example, you can put it
next to the payment confirmation page.
To add SKOverlay to your app clip,
use appStoreOverlay modifier
and make a config
with AppClipConfiguration.
To know more about SKOverlay,
please refer to
"What's New with In-App Purchase" video.
Your app clip may want to pass user data
to your app
like Shopping List or Order History.
You can do this with a secure app group.
This secure app group is only accessible
between your app clip and your app.
When a user installs your app,
the app group will be transferred
to your app
after the app clip is deleted.
If the user has already signed in
to the app clip with the app group,
they can automatically sign into the app.
Here's how to do it.
In your app clip,
when users log in with Sign in with Apple,
save the user ID in the shared app group
as a file or in a database.
After the user upgrades to your app,
read the saved user ID
from the App group...
then use iOS authorization app ID provider
to verify the user ID.
If the user has already signed in
to your app clip,
you can seamlessly
sign them into your app.
With that, I would like
to hand over to Luming to show you a demo.
Luming.
Thanks, Yongjun, for your great talk about
streamlining your app clip experience.
I'm Luming,
an engineer from the App Clips team,
and today, I'll be demoing how to
streamline your App clip experience.
Without a streamlined experience,
if you launch an app clip,
your users may see something like this.
They'll have to decide on the spot
about giving location access
as well as notification access.
Not exactly a frictionless experience.
So let's see how we can streamline
these permission requests.
Let's look at notifications first.
App clips can request for
eight hours of ephemeral notification
without throwing up an alert.
I have the Fruta Xcode project open,
and let's first look
at the app clip's Info.plist.
I've expanded the NSAppClipDictionary,
and I'll set the Boolean value
of NSAppClipRequestEphemeral-
UserNotification to "Yes."
Now, I can come back to FrutaClip.swift,
and before we request
for notification authorization,
we can check
if our app clip has already been granted
ephemeral notification status.
[typing, mouse click]
This is a new value
introduced in iOS 14 for App Clips.
If we have already acquired
ephemeral notification status,
there's no need
to prompt the user for an alert.
Let's build and install the clip
on the device.
While there is still a location prompt,
there is no more
notification permission prompts.
Let's verify this.
If I go to Settings and look
at the notification setting for Fruta,
you can see that there is
"Will turn off in 8 hours."
This indicates
the Fruta App Clip has been given
an eight-hour ephemeral notification,
tied to physical invocations.
What a coincidence.
Looks like my smoothie's ready,
and ephemeral notifications
are also confirmed working.
Next up, since app clips can request
for a one-time location confirmation,
when launched through physical invocation
methods, such as NFC or QR code,
let's take a look at setting it up.
Just like setting up
ephemeral notifications
under the NSAppClipDictionary
in Info.plist,
what we need to do for location
confirmation is also very similar.
This time,
I'll instead set the Boolean value
of NSAppClipRequest-
LocationConfirmation to "Yes."
Then, we can go back to FrutaClip.swift.
I can remove our existing code
to explicitly request for location updates
using Core Location APIs.
Since I have already linked against
AppClip.framework
in our project settings,
I'll import the framework here.
Next, in handleUserActivity,
I'll get the app clip activation payload
and the location latitude and longitude
to verify from the URL.
After this, I'll instantiate a region
I would like to confirm.
Then, I'll call confirmAcquired-
(in: region) on the payload.
After this, I'll only allow Apple Pay
if the user is within that region.
I'll Build and Run the app clip again.
At Fruta headquarters,
the QR code shipment team
has mixed up QR code printouts
for Fruta Cupertino with QR code printouts
from Fruta San Francisco.
Without location confirmation,
unsuspecting customers
may end up paying
for someone else's smoothie by mistake.
The good thing here
is location confirmation has us covered.
Let's see how location confirmation
protects you and your customers in action.
I am at Fruta Cupertino right now,
and I'll scan this QR code
that belongs to Fruta San Francisco.
[beeps]
Now, if I launched the app clip
then try to place an order,
you will see
that location confirmation is working,
and I am no longer allowed
to pay for smoothies
since I am not at San Francisco
where the Fruta shop is located at.
Now, let's go back to Xcode
and use Xcode to simulate our device
as if it's in the center of San Francisco.
We really are traveling
at the speed of light
and teleportation technologies
have come a long way.
Let's scan the same QR code again.
[beeps]
This time, if I open the app clip,
I can proceed through the payment
as usual.
[phone dings]
Finally,
let's look at migrating credentials
from the app clip to the full app.
As my colleague, Yongjun,
has explained in the talk,
I have already set up
a secure group container,
shared between the app and the app clip.
I'll open OrderPlacedView.swift.
And if Sign in with Apple has succeeded,
we write the authorization credential
into the group container.
For users to be easily able
to upgrade to the full app,
this is also the perfect opportunity
to configure a StoreKit overlay.
[typing]
And also show it right after
Sign in with Apple has succeeded,
and your user has completed a transaction.
Then, when we first launch the full app,
we can add some code to migrate
the credential over in FrutaModel.swift.
And I'll migrate
the account information over
only if we're building,
not for the app clip,
but for the main app.
We'll read the saved user ID
from the group container,
instantiate
a new ASAuthorizationAppleIDProvider
and get its credential state.
Let's run the clip again.
This time, I'll place an order...
[dings]
...and when the order is ready,
I'll Sign in with Apple.
For your users, this is
a great opportunity to get your full app
and have their log in information
automatically migrated over.
So as we have added this UI SKOverlay,
as Yongjun has explained earlier,
we've got just that.
Since we have just made changes to our app
to handle account migration,
which hasn't been submitted
to the App Store yet,
let's build and run the app
to simulate the full app upgrade.
In the target scheme selection,
I'll choose the full app
and build and run it on my device.
As you can see,
we're automatically logged in,
and all my rewards are right there
waiting for me.
So you've seen how to set up
ephemeral notification
and one-time location confirmation,
as well as migrating user data
from the app clip to the full app.
That's my demo of
"Streamlining Your App Clip Experience."
Back to you, Yongjun.
Thank you, Luming.
It's great!
I learned how to use location confirmation
and app clip notification.
To recap, in this video,
we talked about best practices
for designing and building app clips.
Then we covered how to
streamline transactions in your app clip.
Last, we learned some ideas to help users
transition to your app.
Thanks, and I hope you have a great WWDC.