Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Brent
from the Swift Compiler team.
I'm gonna talk to you today about
how to make your Objective-C frameworks
work really nicely in Swift.
We first introduced Swift
six years ago this month.
Since then,
something amazing has happened.
Most of you
have turned into Swift developers.
But Apple's platforms spent a very long
time as Objective-C-only platforms,
and a lot of you couldn't adopt Swift
right away.
So, many of you still have
a lot of Objective-C code today
that's increasingly being used
by Swift clients.
We understand that
because Apple is in the same boat.
We probably have more Objective-C
frameworks than anyone in the world.
So, we designed Swift to not only import
our Objective-C frameworks,
but also to automatically translate them
into more idiomatic Swift APIs.
We designed in ways
to customize the translation
by adding macros and keywords
to your header files.
And we built in the ability
to extend Objective-C frameworks
with custom Swift code
to wrap existing APIs or add new ones
that can't be expressed in Objective-C.
Best of all, we designed all of this
to work not just for us, but for you.
That's my topic for today.
I'm going to teach you the techniques
that Apple's Objective-C frameworks use
to improve how they're imported
into Swift.
And to do that, I'll be using
a little framework I call SpaceKit.
Let's take a look at it.
SpaceKit is an Objective-C framework
which has a few model APIs
for describing
NASA's early, crude space program.
So it can describe, you know, astronauts,
missions, rockets and so on.
If I look at the headers,
it's clear that this is
an Objective-C framework
full of #import directives,
@interface blocks,
methods with selectors.
But if I import it into Swift,
the compiler will automatically
translate it into a Swift API,
and I can see what that API will look like
right in Xcode
by looking at the header's
generated interface.
All I need to do
is open the Related Items menu
in the top left of the editor...
go down
to the Generated Interface submenu...
and then ask for the Swift 5 interface,
since 5.3 is the Swift version
in Xcode 12.
And what I end up with is basically
what a Swift header file would look like
if Swift had header files.
You can see that it has this class,
there's some initializers,
some properties, some methods.
But I don't see the bodies of these
declarations, just the interfaces.
This is a really valuable tool
to understand what Swift will see
when it imports this framework.
I'm going to be showing you
a lot of SpaceKit's generated interfaces,
these sort of pseudo headers,
throughout this talk.
If you poke around a little in them,
you'll see that Swift
is already doing some great stuff for you.
For instance, these parameters
were all NSString
and NSDate objects in Objective-C,
but the compiler has bridged them
into the structs you would use in Swift.
It's imported init methods
as initializers,
rewritten method names
into a style closer to Swift
and turned methods that follow
the Objective-C error handling convention
into throwing members.
But there's also some room
to improve this framework.
The API is peppered
with these implicitly unwrapped optionals.
The "Any" in "AnyHashable" types
in these collections are really vague.
This throwing method
will sometimes throw when it shouldn't.
And this method's name
may not quite be perfect.
Looking elsewhere, these two initializers
seem oddly redundant.
And this NSError information
will be difficult to use with try-catch.
And if you move away from objects
and take a look
at a more C-style part of SpaceKit,
you'll see more work
that needs to be done.
This type used NS_ENUM, so it comes in
as a very nice Swift enum.
But these collections of string constants
could use the same treatment.
And one of these constants
has straight-up vanished.
These free-floating utility functions
aren't ideal for Swift,
and this UInt result
will be a pain to work with.
I'm going to walk you through
how to improve all of that.
I'll show you how to specify the types
in your APIs more precisely
to help your Swift clients
use your framework correctly.
I'll talk about two very important
Objective-C conventions
that Swift assumes your APIs will follow.
I'll teach you how to correct situations
where Swift might not import things
that Objective-C can access.
And I'll help you put
the finishing touches on your framework
and make it feel
like a good Swift citizen.
So, let's get started...
with those implicitly unwrapped optionals
that appeared virtually everywhere
in the API.
They leave really important aspects
of your framework's behavior undeclared.
So, where did they come from,
and how do we get rid of them?
Objective-C pointer types,
including id-types and blocks,
can have a valid value
or they can have zero value,
which we call "null" or "nil."
This is a lot like Swift's optional type,
which can either have value or be nil,
except that in Objective-C,
every pointer type is effectively optional
and every nonpointer type
is effectively nonoptional.
But, of course, a lot of the time,
a property or method
won't actually handle a nil input
or won't ever return a nil result.
So, when Swift imports
an Objective-C pointer type,
by default, it marks it
as an implicitly unwrapped optional
to tell you that this value could be nil,
but Swift isn't sure if it ever really is.
Fortunately, Objective-C provides
two nullability annotations,
nonnull and nullable,
which let you say
whether nil is a sensible value
for a particular property,
method parameter or method result.
Objective-C doesn't enforce
these annotations.
They just document your intent.
But Swift picks up this information
and uses it to decide
whether to make a type optional or not.
You apply these annotations
by editing your Objective-C header files.
In a property, the annotation goes
in a list of the property's attributes.
In a method parameter or result type,
it goes right before the type's name.
So, let's say you're starting
with this name property.
You decide that instances of this class
may not always have a name,
so you add the nullable annotation
and the type in the generated interface
changes to optional.
Great. But then you hit "build"
and you start seeing new warnings appear.
Don't panic. You didn't break anything.
What happened is Xcode noticed
that you started using
nullability annotations in this header,
so it starts telling you
about all the places
that you still need to fill them in.
So that gives you a nice workflow.
Add the first annotation
somewhere in the header,
then work through it one warning at a time
filling in either "nullable" or "nonnull"
until all the warnings are gone.
Once you've done that, there's one more
clean-up step you should do--
add the NS_ASSUME_NONNULL_BEGIN macro
at the top of the file
and the matching end macro at the bottom,
then delete all the nonnulls between them.
This just cleans up the file a little
so that whenever you see
one of these keywords,
it always indicates
you'll get an optional in Swift.
When you're adding these,
occasionally you'll come across a case
where these annotations don't work,
like this constant.
If you try to put
the nonnull annotation in front of it,
you'll get a compiler error
and the generated interface
probably won't display at all.
The annotations I showed you
work with methods and properties,
but anywhere else, like constants
or global functions or blocks,
you'll have to use the qualifier versions
of these annotations instead.
These start with an underscore
and a capital letter,
and they work on any pointer type
anywhere in Objective-C.
You'll also need these
for pointer-to-pointer types.
In that case, you'll specify one keyword
for each level of the pointer,
so you can say that the inner pointer
can be nil, but the outer one can't be,
and Swift will nest the optional and
unsafe mutable pointer types correctly.
So, going back to our global,
we apply the underscore qualifier,
and it becomes nonoptional in Swift
just like we wanted.
When you're doing this, you need to be
careful that your annotations are correct.
For instance,
maybe you glance over this header
and you decide, "Of course every mission
is going to have a capsule.
Let's make the capsule property nonnull."
But it turns out later
that there was a mission
where they didn't launch a capsule,
and you do model that
by setting the capsule to nil.
In other words,
the nonnull annotation was wrong.
So, what's gonna happen
when Objective-C returns "nil"
for a value Swift thinks
can't be optional?
Well, if it's an NSString or NSArray
on the Objective-C side,
there's a special case.
You get an empty Swift string or array.
That could be a problem here
because SpaceKit expects the string
to equal one of its SKCapsule constants,
and none of those equal empty string,
so you'll end up with a value
that you might not handle correctly.
For other types, it can get a lot weirder.
You can end up with an invalid object,
something you usually can only get
from unsafe operations.
If it's an Objective-C object,
you might not even notice
because Objective-C method calls
ignore nils.
But in some cases, you'll crash
with a null pointer dereference
or get other unexpected behavior,
and the compiler doesn't promise anything
about what happens,
so switching to release mode
or changing Xcode versions
could change the symptoms
of this kind of bug.
The important point is when you write
in the header that something can't be nil,
Swift doesn't force-unwrap it,
so you won't see a crash
at the place where it returned nil.
Swift doesn't second-guess
your Objective-C headers.
It believes what they tell it.
The good news is the Objective-C compiler
and the Clang Static Analyzer
also look at nullability annotations
and can point out many violations
in your Objective-C code.
So, if you say something can't be nil,
but you have Objective-C code
that makes it nil,
these tools might tell you
that something's amiss.
Once you finish adding
nullability annotations,
it's a good idea to look for new warnings
or static analyzer results
in both the framework's
implementation files
and any Objective-C clients
you have access to.
Those results could indicate
that you have mis-annotated,
or they could be telling you about subtle
bugs that you never knew were there.
But suppose you see some warnings
or analyzer results
and can't quite decide
if they can actually happen.
Or you just had
some really complicated old code
and you can't figure out if there's
an edge case where it will return nil.
What should you do then?
Well, earlier I mentioned the nonnull
and nullable annotations.
There's actually a third option
called null unspecified
which makes Swift import the value
as an implicitly unwrapped optional.
You should use this in all the places
you'd use an implicitly unwrapped
optional in Swift,
like values that are only nil
very early in an object's life cycle.
But you can also use it
when you think an API can't return nil
but you're not sure,
that way Swift clients can still use
the result without unwrapping it.
But if the framework
does end up returning nil,
you'll reliably get a crash
at the use site
instead of maybe getting
some impossible-seeming misbehavior
sometime later.
We've gone through our project and we've
added all of the nullability annotations.
Great. Next we'd like to deal
with this array of "Any"
and other collections
that aren't bridging very well.
It turns out Objective-C
supports a generic syntax
that's a lot like Swift's,
so if you make it an NSArray
of SKAstronauts in Objective-C,
you'll get a Swift array of SKAstronauts
in Swift.
This also works with NSSet
and NSDictionary,
so it can really improve a lot of APIs.
Next, let's go take a look
at a different area of the project.
Here we have a function
called SKRocketStageCount,
and, like you'd expect from the name,
it returns a count.
Since a count can't be negative,
it returns it as an NSUInteger,
which means that in Swift,
it returns a UInt,
and that means this function
breaks a Swift convention.
In both Objective-C and Swift,
it's conventional to use unsigned types
when an integer represents
a collection of bits
and you want to perform bitwise operations
on those bits,
or do some other computation where
signed arithmetic might get in the way.
Usually,
when you're working at this level,
you care about the exact number of bits
in the value.
NSUInteger's size varies by architecture,
so people rarely use it in this way.
Rather, the main reason people use
NSUInteger in Objective-C
is to indicate that a number's value
is never negative.
Objective-C enables this style
with automatic conversions
and carefully designed overflow behaviors,
but these exact features
can cause serious security bugs,
so Swift doesn't include them.
Instead, Swift requires you to explicitly
convert unsigned types to signed
if you wanted signed arithmetic,
and stops execution if unsigned arithmetic
would produce a negative result.
This makes it more difficult
to mix Int and UInt in Swift
the way you might mix NSInteger
and NSUInteger in Objective-C.
So, the conventional Swift style
is to just not do that.
Instead, idiomatic Swift APIs use Int,
even for values that are never negative.
For Apple's frameworks,
we applied a blanket rule
that all NSUIntegers turn into Ints
when Swift imports them.
For your frameworks, it's your choice
whether to update your headers
to use NSInteger or not,
but we recommend that you do.
It makes very little difference
in Objective-C,
but it has a huge impact in Swift.
If we look at the broader context, there's
a bigger problem with this function,
and it's that clients can misuse it
very easily.
The SKRocketStageCount function
is supposed to be used
with these SKRocket constants.
That's what the matching names
are supposed to indicate.
But Swift doesn't know that
because what Swift sees
is this function takes a string.
These constants are all strings,
but there are a heck
of a lot more strings out there too.
And if you pass one of those
to SKRocketStageCount,
it probably won't do anything good.
In a pure Swift framework,
you could prevent this.
You'd just turn these constants
into an enum or a struct
with a raw value of type String,
and then change the function
to take only that type.
You could do that to SpaceKit
by wrapping these APIs by hand,
but there's a much easier way.
First, you introduce a new typedef
to group the constants together
and change all the places
involving the constants to use that.
By itself, this does practically nothing.
A typedef gets imported as a type-alias
in Swift,
and in both languages, that's just
an exact synonym for the original type.
But that's just a preparatory step.
Next you add the NS_STRING_ENUM macro
after the typedef.
This dramatically reshapes
the typedef in Swift.
It now imports as a struct
with the constants nested inside it,
making something that looks and feels
just like an enum with a raw string value.
And most importantly,
it means that the StageCount function
no longer takes arbitrary strings.
It only takes instances of SKRocket.
Mission accomplished.
You can use this feature
to define your own custom string enums,
but Apple's frameworks
define a lot of them too.
I've listed a few common ones
from Foundation here,
but there are least 50
in the iOS SDK alone.
It'd be a good idea to look
for NSString parameters
or constants in your APIs,
which really ought to be one of these,
and update them to match.
Next, let's talk about some ways
that you could get into trouble
by not following Objective-C conventions
correctly
when Swift assumes that you will.
When you look at the generated interface
for SKAstronaut,
you see something kind of funny.
This class has two initializers.
Both of them are passed a person's name,
but in two slightly different forms.
One takes a PersonNameComponents,
a Foundation type that has properties
for things like given name and surname.
The other take a string labeled "name."
It stands to reason that one of these
initializers probably calls the other.
And yet if you subclass SKAstronaut,
Swift will make you override both of them.
That seems a little unnecessary.
But there's actually a second issue
with this class's initializers,
one that isn't visible
in the generated interface.
If you look in SKAstronaut's
code completion,
you'll see a third initializer
with no parameters.
This init isn't in the generated interface
and it's not in
the original header either.
It seems like it came from outer space.
But in fact it came from here,
from the super class.
SKAstronaut inherited it from NSObject,
and even though your clients can call it,
it may not actually work properly.
These two problems
have the same root cause.
In Objective-C,
there's a convention for initializers
which makes sure
the clients know how to write a subclass
that will always
get initialized correctly.
The convention divides initializers
into two categories--
designated and convenience.
You need to override
all of the designated initializers
to make it safe to inherit
the convenience initializers.
Now, if you're thinking,
"Gosh, this sounds really familiar..."
that's because it is.
Swift classes use the same basic model
for their initializers.
There are some differences in the details.
For example, you mark
the designated inits in one language
and the convenience inits in the other.
But Swift classes have these
same two categories of initializers,
and they work in basically the same way.
But unfortunately, the biggest difference
between the languages here
is that in Objective-C, designated
initializers are not a language rule.
They're a convention
that each class must choose to follow
by marking at least one initializer
as designated.
And many Objective-C classes don't opt in.
This means that clients don't know
how to subclass your class.
That's not great for any class,
but it's especially bad for frameworks
because then clients have to read
your source code
or reverse engineer your behavior
or just guess,
and those are all good ways
to end up with buggy subclasses.
That's bad enough, but it also means
that you, the frameworks maintainer,
don't get warnings if you forget
to override something you want to.
If a client uses an initializer
that you forgot to override,
that means your class gets skipped over
during initialization.
So, ivars you thought would always refer
to an object will be nil instead.
And even if you did override
everything you needed to,
mistakes are so common
that clients can't really be sure of that.
So, the first step in fixing this problem
will be to opt in to this convention
by marking your designated initializers
in your headers.
If you're not sure which initializers
should be designated,
take a look at the implementation.
Typically, designated initializers
will call an init with "super,"
convenience initializers
will call one with "self."
So, by looking at their bodies,
you can determine
that an init With Name Components
should be designated,
and init With Names should be convenience.
With that in mind,
you can go back to the header file
and mark the designated initializers
with NS_DESIGNATED_INITIALIZER
while leaving
the convenience initializers unchanged.
In SpaceKit, you'll mark
init With Name Components as designated,
while leaving init With Name alone.
Once we're done, Swift will recognize that
init Name is a convenience initializer
and mark it with a convenience keyword.
At this point,
you may start seeing warnings
in your Objective-C implementation files
about superclass designated initializers
that you need to override.
These were latent bugs.
If someone had used one of them,
your object
wouldn't have been initialized correctly.
If you want your class to support
any of these initializers,
just go ahead and implement them normally.
But if you don't,
implement an override
that calls does Not Recognize Selector.
Then go back to the header file
and declare it
with the NS_UNAVAILABLE attribute.
Then do the same thing for any superclass
convenience initializers
since they might call
the one you disabled.
Marking these initializers as unavailable
is the equivalent to not inheriting them,
which is what Swift would do automatically
if you didn't override
a designated initializer.
With these changes,
your Swift and your Objective-C clients
will now know which initializers will work
and which ones they need to override
in their subclasses.
That's a win all around.
Next, let's talk about
the Objective-C error handling convention.
Earlier, I said this method might throw
when it shouldn't.
This doc comment,
or rather the behavior it describes,
is the reason.
A lot of Objective-C developers
misunderstand
the error handling convention.
They think that if a method
wants to signal failure,
it has to return "false"
and set the error to a nonnil value.
A "false" return alone, they think,
isn't a failure.
It's just false or nil or whatever.
But that isn't actually the convention.
The convention is, if a method returns
a false value, that's a failure
even if the error value is "nil."
We really don't recommend
leaving the error "nil"
because then your caller
has no idea what happened.
But if you do,
a "false" return is still a failure.
When Swift generates a call
to an Objective-C method it has imported
with throws,
it assumes that the method
will follow this rule correctly,
so it always throws
if the method returns "false."
Swift doesn't allow you to throw "nil,"
so if there is no error,
Swift throws
a nonpublic Foundation error type.
Because the type is not public,
you can't write a catch statement for it.
But if you see this type and case in logs,
the debugger or error messages,
it means that some Objective-C code
either returned "false"
even though it didn't fail,
or it failed but didn't tell you why.
So let's think about how that applies
to this SpaceKit method.
Its documentation says
that it can return "false"
in a situation where it has skipped work,
but hasn't actually failed.
But Swift assumes
that a false return value
means it should throw an error,
and since the method didn't set an error,
it'll be one of those internal Foundation
"nil errors" I mentioned.
What can you do about that?
Well, you have a few options.
The easiest is to simply remove
the special case
so that false always means failure
and the method follows
the convention properly.
But that's probably not workable
if clients actually need
to detect this case.
An alternative is to use NS_SWIFT_NOTHROW
to tell Swift that you're not following
the error convention.
Swift will then import the method
the normal way
and you can write
error handling code manually.
This still leaves the method
kind of broken,
but it might be a good solution
if you're also planning
to deprecate the method
and write a better replacement.
Whether or not you kept
the original around in deprecated form,
that better replacement would need
to change the method's signature
so that it can follow
the error handling convention
while returning the extra information
another way.
For instance, you could add
a Boolean out parameter
to say whether the file
was actually saved.
Then the return value can be used
the way the error convention specifies.
That's not perfect,
but it's about the best you can do
from just Objective-C.
But if you want to go a little further
and write a bit of Swift code,
you can get perfect Swift import
from this method.
Let me show you how.
So, let's take a look at the header
for SKMission.
You can see I've been updating it
as we go along
and now it has the old deprecated method
plus the new method
with the extra parameter
so it follows the convention.
Great.
Now, let's write the better Swift version.
To start, I need to add
a Swift file to my project
so I can put my Swift method in it.
I'll do that the same way
I'd add an Objective-C file,
but choosing the Swift template instead.
I don't need to import
SpaceKit in this file
because it's already
part of the framework.
But it doesn't automatically see
every bit of Objective-C in SpaceKit.
What happens is that Swift
automatically imports everything
in SpaceKit's umbrella header.
The umbrella header is the header
with the same name as the framework,
so for this framework it's SpaceKit.h.
Since the umbrella header
imports all of the public headers
in this framework,
my Swift file will see everything
declared in all of those headers.
It's always a good practice to have
an umbrella header in a framework,
but it's especially important
in a framework that'll be used from Swift.
App and test targets
don't have umbrella headers,
so Xcode offers to add
a special bridging header to those targets
that serves this function.
Quick aside here,
there's one public header
that I shouldn't import
in the umbrella header.
And that's the generated header.
The SpaceKit-Swift header
which declares anything I mark
with @objc in Swift.
The problem is that this forms
a circular dependency.
Swift can't make the generated header
without first importing everything
in my umbrella header.
So, if the umbrella header
imports the generated header,
then Swift will try to read this file
that it hasn't generated yet.
And that will just ruin your whole day.
So, don't import the generated header
in your other headers,
only in your implementation files.
Even though it's not
in the umbrella header,
Objective-C clients
who have modules enabled
will automatically import it anyway,
so it should all just work out.
Anyway, back to the task at hand.
I'll extend SKMission...
to add a new method called save to,
which both throws and returns a Bool.
I couldn't return the Bool in Objective-C
because the Objective-C error convention
takes over the return value.
But that's an Objective-C convention.
In a Swift method,
the return value is totally separate
from whether or not
the method threw an error,
so there's no problem with this.
Now, let's implement this.
First, I'll need a Bool variable
to receive the wasDirty value.
Next, I'll call the Objective-C method
and finally, I'll return
the wasDirty value.
Hit "Build" and...
Oops, I have a type error.
What happened?
Well, on some of our platforms,
Swift's Bool and Objective-C's Bool
actually have a slightly different
memory representation.
Normally, Swift inserts
a little conversion to smooth this over.
But here, you're trying to take
a pointer to a Swift Bool
and pass it off to Objective-C
so that Objective-C
can directly read and write it.
There's no way for Swift
to insert a conversion there,
so instead it uses a type called ObjCBool,
which matches the Objective-C
Bool representation.
So, to make this work...
I need to change
the variable's type to ObjCBool.
And then, in the return statement...
use its bool Value property
to return a Swift Bool.
Build and...
Great. This works.
But I can make it a little better.
You see, even though I have
this great new method for our Swift users,
the Objective-C one
is still available to them.
Swift clients might get confused
and wonder which one they should use,
so it'd be better to hide it from them.
But I don't want to stop
Objective-C clients from using it
and I don't want
to totally block Swift either
because this method I just wrote
still needs to use it.
So, what I can do is...
I go over to the SKMission header...
and I annotate the method
with NS_REFINED_FOR_SWIFT.
What NS_REFINED_FOR_SWIFT does
is very simple.
It adds two underscores
to the beginning
of the method's Swift name.
When Xcode sees something
with a leading underscore,
it usually hides it from editor features
like code completion
and generated interfaces.
So, if I build the project now,
I'll get an error in my Swift code.
Let's take a look at it.
Swift complains that save to
doesn't have a wasDirty parameter.
This means the NS_REFINED_FOR_SWIFT
macro is working.
Swift doesn't think the method
I'm trying to call is named save to.
It now thinks it's
underscore underscore save to.
And if I use code completion,
there's no sign of the wasDirty version
of the method there either.
But even though I can't see the method
in the code completions,
if I add two underscores
before the name and build again...
it works.
Now, our Swift clients will use
this really nice wrapper
that still calls the Objective-C method,
but gives it an interface
we couldn't have achieved
from Objective-C alone.
You can use this technique
whenever an API could be expressed
more nicely in Swift.
Next, let's look at a problem
you might see in your framework.
Swift goes to great lengths to import
everything it can from your headers,
but when it can't figure out
how to import something,
it'll skip over it and move on.
This usually happens when there's
no good or natural way
to automatically translate
an Objective-C feature into Swift.
For example, Swift will skip over
functions or methods
which use C's variadic parameters
and struct members which declare
a C array of unknown size.
If a forward declaration,
like an @class
or @protocol with a semicolon,
appears in a header file,
but the class or protocol
is never fully declared,
Swift won't have enough information
about that type to import it
and it may end up dropping
methods, properties
or even entire categories
that try to use one of these types.
If Swift sees two inconsistent
declarations for the same thing,
it will often skip over both of them
rather than guess which one it should use.
In Xcode 12, Clang is now better
at detecting these conflicts.
So if you see types or methods
suddenly disappear when you upgrade,
that might be something to investigate.
And finally, Swift imports
some macros, but not all.
And this is where SpaceKit
runs into trouble.
Earlier, we turned a group
of string constants into a type
using NS_STRING_ENUM.
SpaceKit actually has
two sets of constants like this
and we'd like to give the other set
the same treatment.
But these are defined with macros
and there's a problem.
One of them has been jettisoned.
What happened?
Well, Swift can't import
every macro you might write.
A macro is basically
just a snippet of text
that can be used anywhere
in your Objective-C source code.
The same macro could mean different things
when it's used in different places
and there's no way for Swift to figure out
how a macro was meant to be used.
But Swift does recognize macros
which match certain patterns
that are often used to declare constants.
When it sees one of these,
it imports it as a Swift constant.
The first three SKCapsule macros
fit one of the patterns Swift recognizes,
a single string literal,
so Swift imports them as constants.
But the fourth macro
substitutes in another macro,
then concatenates
the string literal to it.
Swift doesn't fully understand
how macro substitution
could interact
with other Objective-C features,
so it allows you to name another macro
or have other things in the macro,
but not both.
Since Swift doesn't recognize
the pattern of code,
it skips this macro and moves on.
There are a bunch of ways
you could fix this unimportable macro.
The simplest would be
to just form the string literal
in the same way as the others.
But if you want to turn these
into string enum cases,
it'd be better to convert them
into real constants.
Then, you can string enum them,
just like the SKRocket constants
and be on your way.
Okay. So, at this point,
you've strengthened your types,
you fixed up some incorrect code
and you've made sure everything
that should be visible is.
Now comes the fun part.
Polishing and improving the framework
so it feels as nice as possible
to Swift clients.
I'll start with some naming.
Swift's method naming conventions
are a little different from Objective-C's.
Both languages use relatively long names
where every argument is labeled,
but Swift's names
tend to be a little shorter
and omit information
that's obvious from the types.
There's also a technical difference
between the two languages.
In Swift, each method has a base name
and by default every argument
also has a label.
Objective-C selectors essentially
just have argument labels
without a separate base name.
So the information that would be
in the base name
is included in the first argument label.
To help you with these differences,
Swift automatically renames
your Objective-C methods
when it imports them.
It strips off prefixes and suffixes
that match type names
and it uses a table
of English grammar and vocabulary
to figure out how to split
the first portion of the selector
into a base name and argument label.
The results are usually pretty good,
but this is basically a computer program
making aesthetic judgments,
so it'll sometimes make decisions
you disagree with.
For instance, many developers
would say this method selector
hasn't been split correctly.
The word "flown" should be part
of the argument label, not the base name,
because the method fetches
a list of previous missions
and they are the missions
flown by a particular astronaut.
Not every developer will agree,
but it's a judgment call.
To fix it, you'd put
the NS_SWIFT_NAME macro after the method,
passing it the base name
and argument labels
the way you would write them in Swift
if you were trying to refer
to the method without calling it.
Swift will then import the method
with the name you specified
instead of the one
it would generate itself.
But NS_SWIFT_NAME is not just for methods.
It can be applied to nearly anything.
For instance, take this enum.
Swift has already done
a pretty good job with it.
Because the author used NS_ENUM,
it imports as a Swift enum.
But if we want to tweak the name a bit,
NS_SWIFT_NAME can do that.
Now, you could use NS_SWIFT_NAME
to remove the SK prefix from the name,
but we don't actually recommend
you do that.
A lot of Objective-C type names
combine the framework's prefix
with a word like "query" or "record"
that would be too vague on its own.
You would need to add
something else to the name
to make up for the precision lost
by deleting the prefix.
What it's best used for
with types, though, is nesting them.
For instance,
if there was an SKFuel class
that this SKFuelKind enum went with,
you could change it to be SKFuel.Kind,
which is probably what you would call
this type in Swift.
Another good use is with libraries
whose type names
look totally different from Swift types.
Like the lowercase type names
you sometimes see in C libraries.
NS_SWIFT_NAME can also be used
with global constants,
variables and functions.
For example, we can apply NS_SWIFT_NAME
to the SKFuelKind To String function
to not only remove
the extra information from its name,
but also add an argument label,
something Objective-C
doesn't support on functions.
But now we've actually entered
some really interesting territory
because, when applied
to global constants and variables,
and especially global functions,
NS_SWIFT_NAME gains
some astonishing superpowers
that can dramatically reshape
how clients use your framework.
To start with, you can turn
a global function into a static method
by specifying the type's Objective-C name,
followed by a dot
and then the static method's name.
Then, you can turn it
into an instance method instead
by changing
one of the argument labels to "self"
so Swift knows where to pass
the instance you called it on.
And then you can turn
that method into a property
by putting "getter" in front of it.
You can do the same thing with a setter
to create a mutable property.
Apply these techniques across
an entire framework full of functions
and you can dramatically reshape
its whole API surface.
If you've used Core Graphics
in both Objective-C and Swift,
you probably know what I mean.
We applied this renaming capability
to hundreds of global functions
to convert them into methods,
properties and initializers
which are much easier to use.
Now, at this point, you must be wondering
if there's anything
NS_SWIFT_NAME can't do.
Well, there is.
Even though you renamed
this global function
into an instance property
named "description,"
you can't use NS_SWIFT_NAME
to conform the type
to the CustomStringConvertible protocol,
which would make Swift use that property
to convert SKFuel.Kinds into strings.
But you can add that conformance
using one line of custom Swift code.
So, let's do that.
The one line of code
I need to add is this.
I write an extension to SKFuel.Kind...
and conform it
to the CustomStringConvertible protocol.
And since my Objective-C header
already provided a description property
using NS_SWIFT_NAME...
That's it. There is no step three.
I've only demonstrated very simple uses
of custom Swift code,
but you can write any Swift-only APIs
you want in these Swift files.
For instance, you could import SwiftUI
and write SwiftUI views that use AppKit
or UIKit views from your framework.
Or you could take an API that uses
something like a completion handler
and write a wrapper that returns
a Combine Future instead.
We can and have given entire sessions
about using these technologies
with Swift classes and types,
and nothing really changes when you
use them in a mixed-language framework.
So, rather than try to give you
a crash course,
I'll point you to some relevant sessions
on SwiftUI and Combine
and leave the rest to you.
Finally, let's talk
about error code enums.
Like many frameworks,
SpaceKit needs some custom error codes
it can use with NSError.
To keep them from colliding
with other frameworks' errors,
it declares a string constant
with an error domain
and then an NS_ENUM
with the specific error codes.
Now, looking at this generated interface,
you might be thinking,
"What's the problem here?'
You declared a string constant
and it came in as a string constant.
You declared an NS_ENUM
and it came in as a Swift enum
with all the cases and codes intact
and even the names correctly shortened.
And really, there's no problem
with the interface itself.
The problem becomes more clear
when you think about
how you would actually use it.
For instance,
let's say you launch a mission
and if the launch is aborted,
you want to make sure the rescue squad
goes and gets the astronauts.
That's gonna look roughly like this.
You call mission.launch,
then you want to catch the error
if it's a launch Aborted error.
But what does that catch clause
actually look like?
Well, we're going to need to extract
the domain and code from the error,
so first we have to catch it
as an NSError.
Next, we need to make sure
the error is in the SKErrorDomain,
not some other domain
that might use the same error code
for something different.
Then we'll need to convert the error code
from an int to an SKErrorCode.
And finally, we can check
if it's the case we wanted.
Looking at all these checks together,
this is, um...
not something I'd want to make
my users write.
It shouldn't take this much effort
just to match an error.
If you had written SpaceKit in Swift
and this had been a Swift error enum,
you could do the same thing
in less than a line.
Just name the error type and the case
and Swift matches them
against the thrown error.
That's way better.
But, of course, you don't have
a Swift error enum.
You have an Objective-C enum
and an error domain constant.
Can you turn those into something
similar to a Swift error enum?
You can, and really it couldn't be easier.
All you need to do is replace
NS_ENUM with NS_ERROR_ENUM.
Then replace the raw type
with the error domain constant.
This has an enormous effect
on the error code enum.
SKErrorCode gets nested inside SKError,
a new type Swift invents from whole cloth.
In the Xcode generated interface,
you'll see that the enum has
all of the error codes as its cases
and they're also repeated
as static constants on the struct,
and there's a static constant
for the domain, too.
But SKError also conforms to Error,
so you can throw and catch it
just like a native Swift error.
It has initializers and properties
for the error code
and user info dictionary.
And the error code enum
has a tilde-equal operator.
This is the matching operator
used by case and catch clauses.
Here, it says that if you're
switching or catching an error,
you can match it against an SKErrorCode.
The match succeeds
only if the error domain
and error code are both correct.
Since SKError has those
static code constants on it,
you can write
catch SKError.launch Aborted
and Swift will use this operator
to match the error
against that error code.
These parts of SKError aren't visible
in the generated interface
because the Swift compiler
synthesizes them.
But they're there for you to use
and they make Objective-C error codes
work pretty nicely in Swift.
And the only thing you have to do
to get all this is change two identifiers.
Not bad for a one-line diff.
But I want to go back to where we started
with these error codes
and think about a bigger lesson.
There is no obvious sign of a problem
in the generated interface.
It's only when you saw
how SKErrorCode would be used
that you realized
there was room for improvement.
All through this talk,
I've been showing you generated interfaces
because they're a good way to see
how Swift is importing your headers.
But generated interfaces
are just a tool for understanding
what's in the framework.
What really matters is the calls
your clients will write
when they try to use it.
So, when you're working on a framework,
you should look
at the generated interface,
but you should think about the use sites.
Imagine them in your mind's eye.
Scribble them on a whiteboard.
Tinker with them in a playground.
Codify them in a test.
Your clients will love
or hate your framework
based on the code they write with it,
not the interface they see
when they Command-click.
So, to sum up.
If you have an Objective-C framework,
you can make it work really nicely
for Swift clients
with just header annotations
and sometimes a little bit of Swift code.
When you're doing this,
look for opportunities
to present stronger,
more specific types to Swift clients.
And make sure you're following
Objective-C conventions
so that Swift will use
your framework correctly.
And even though Xcode shows you
the generated interface,
look beyond that and think
about how your APIs will be used.
That's what should drive your design.
If you want more information,
the Swift documentation has a section
called "Language Interoperability"
which digs into all of these features
and more in greater detail.
If you want to get a more concrete feel
for what makes a Swift API idiomatic,
the "API Design Guidelines"
describe some of the principles and rules
recommended by the Swift
core team and community.
And the session "Behind the Scenes
of the Xcode Build Process"
digs deep into how Swift
imports Objective-C headers
and how Xcode builds mixed frameworks.
It's particularly relevant
if Swift seems to be missing
some of your Objective-C
framework's headers
or just won't import it at all.
So, thank you for your time
and I hope this helps you launch
something stellar.