Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. I'm Brandon Walkin,
a designer on the Apple Design Team.
I'll be joined later
by other designers on the team:
Marcos Alonso, CC Wan, and Dylan Edwards.
We're going to talk about how to design
for the new pointer in iPadOS.
Today, we're going to talk about
the design principles
behind the new pointer,
go behind the scenes
and take a look at how it works
and the different effects you can use.
Then we'll talk about
the appearance of the pointer,
how to make a custom pointer shape,
using pointer interactions,
and how to make your app work great
with gestures on the trackpad.
Let's start off with some of the thinking
behind the new pointer.
The iPad works great with touch,
so why would we want to add pointing?
Well, one of the reasons is ergonomics.
Adding trackpad capability
allows people to have
a more comfortable experience
where they can leave their hands
on the same plane as the keyboard,
instead of having to frequently reach up
to touch the screen.
We also wanted to make
editing text easier.
Editing text
requires a lot of fine manipulation,
and since the finger
is a coarse-grained input,
it's more difficult to position
the text cursor and make a selection
compared to using a trackpad or a mouse.
What's the best way to let people
control the interface using the trackpad?
iPad is unique in that its interface
was fundamentally designed for touch.
Hit areas are generous so they can support
being easily tapped with the finger,
and buttons are spaced further apart
to avoid accidental mis-taps.
We looked at just bringing the traditional
arrow pointer over from the Mac,
but that didn't feel quite right on iPadOS
where the entire operating system
and every app
is designed to be used
by an input the size of a fingertip.
You'd be using a high-precision tool
to interact with low-precision controls.
This got us thinking more deeply
about the concept of precision.
The traditional arrow pointer can move
very precisely over the whole screen.
This is great for certain tasks.
Say you're making a marquee selection
to edit a particular section of an image,
or maybe you're trying to select some text
from the middle of a paragraph.
In these cases,
it's helpful to have very precise control
over where the pointer is onscreen
so you can place it
just where you want it.
But this high level of precision
also has some downsides.
Most of us are experts at using mice
and trackpads
and aren't conscious of this,
but the traditional pointer
actually requires
a lot of physical dexterity to use.
Say you're trying to click a button
and you quickly move the pointer there
but end up clicking just a few pixels
above the button and nothing happens.
Or maybe you end up clicking
between two buttons,
and neither is activated.
Or say you intend
to click the pause button
and end up
rewinding to the beginning of the track.
Let's take a close look
at what's happening here.
There are two independent layers
that are interacting with each other:
the interface layer
and the pointing layer.
The traditional pointer
moves at pixel-level precision.
You can place it
on any pixel of the interface.
But the underlying interface
is built out of three button regions.
It only cares which of the three
playback buttons you click,
not the precise pixel coordinate
you click on a button.
There's an inconsistency
between the precision of the pointer
and the precision required by the app.
So, while people
generally think about the pointer
in terms of giving you increased precision
compared to touch,
in this case, it's helpful to actually
reduce the precision of the pointer
to match the user interface.
This concept of dynamically adjusting
the precision of the pointer
to match the precision of the interface
is called adaptive precision.
Let's look at
how adaptive precision works.
The pointer starts off as a circle.
This is its default state
when the pointing system isn't aware
of any particular level of precision
of the interface around it.
It's sized to match a fingertip,
since everything you're interacting with
on iPad must be usable with touch.
When you move the pointer
to a group of buttons,
the pointer will adjust itself
to match the precision of the buttons.
As I move the pointer
into the group of buttons,
it snaps itself to the button
while morphing its shape
to the shape of the button.
The change in shape indicates
its new reduced level of precision.
As I move between them, the pointer
will always snap itself to a button,
making it clear
exactly which one I'm interacting with.
This feedback you get from the pointer
reduces the likelihood
that you'll mis-click.
You'll also notice
that the pointer highlights the element
rather than obscuring it.
A traditional pointer is drawn
over the entire interface,
often obscuring the control
you're interacting with.
We thought it was important to have
the controls you're interacting with
completely unobstructed.
In fact,
when the pointer snaps to a control,
the pointer actually moves
along the Z-axis
from being in front of the app to being
behind the button's icon or label.
This lets people see
the true color of the icon.
The icon on the left
with the pointer behind it
has the brightness level
that the designer intended.
Now, let's look at how
the pointer interacts with text.
You may have run into this issue before,
where you try to select some text
and you end up selecting the line
just above or below
the one you're aiming for.
Here I'm trying to select
the word "environment"
but I've started my click
just slightly too high
and selected the line above.
Why does this happen?
Well, the traditional I-beam pointer
moves up and down
at pixel-level precision,
letting you click on individual pixels.
However, the text view behind it
only cares about line-level precision:
which specific line of text
you're clicking on.
Let's zoom in a little closer.
There's an invisible boundary
just above the line of text
where if I move my pointer
just a single pixel over the boundary,
the text view will think
I'm interacting with the line above.
This inconsistency
between the input precision
and the interface precision
is what leads people to mis-click
and select the wrong text.
Now let's unify
the precision of the pointer
and the text view together
with adaptive precision.
As the pointer moves over the text view,
it morphs from the circle pointer
to a beam shape
that matches the line height of the text,
its new level of vertical precision.
As you move the pointer up and down,
it snaps to each line of text,
making it clear
which line you're interacting with.
In fact, the pointing system
makes it impossible
to place the pointer in
an ambiguous position between two lines.
You can give the pointer
a different amount of precision
for each axis.
So, when you move horizontally,
we give you pixel-level precision
so you can place the insertion point
just where you want it
and make your selection.
So, we showed how the pointer
snaps to buttons and lines of text.
You get both of these behaviors for free
if you use our standard UIKit controls.
But let's look at an example of when
you'd want to use adaptive precision
in a view that's custom for your app.
Here, we have a scheduling app that
lets you manage events over a day view.
You make new events
by clicking and dragging on the day view.
It's common for these types of interfaces
to round the start times of the events
to 15-minute intervals.
So, instead of your click and drag
starting a meeting at 9:41, for example,
which is an odd time to start a meeting,
it'll round it to a more common start time
of 9:45.
While this is a helpful behavior,
it often results in errors
where you're trying to make an event
that starts at a certain time.
Say you're trying to make an event
that starts at 2:30,
but the interface ends up interpreting
that click as 2:15,
resulting in a frustrating experience.
It turns out what's happening here
is exactly the same issue
as with the text view.
Just like with the text view,
the vertical precision of the pointer
is different than the vertical precision
of the interface.
The pointer is letting you start a drag
at any pixel onscreen,
but the interface only accepts drags
starting within 15-minute blocks.
And the boundaries of these blocks
aren't exposed to you,
so it's not clear what'll happen on click.
And from a design perspective,
it may be distracting
to visualize these regions
using divider lines or hover states.
Let's use adaptive precision
to customize the precision of the pointer
to match the day view.
Now as you move up and down,
the pointer is always snapped
to a 15-minute interval,
making it clear
what time the event will begin.
When you move quickly, you can
just barely tell that it's snapping.
But when you slow down,
you really feel it snap
to those time blocks.
Here, adaptive precision makes it easy to
start an event at just the time you want,
and reduces potential errors
you'd see with a traditional pointer.
So that's adaptive precision.
Now let's take a look at how
the pointer works behind the scenes.
When you move the pointer around onscreen,
you're actually moving two pointers:
the one you see onscreen,
and an invisible one that tracks
the true position of the pointer.
We call this the model pointer.
The model pointer is used to decide
which item the pointer is hovering over,
and it takes advantage
of the generous padding
that buttons have on iPadOS
to make them easier to tap
with the finger.
Let’s see this in action.
Once the true pointer position
reaches the edge of the button’s hit area,
it begins to move
and resize to highlight the button.
This effect of animating the pointer
towards the button is called "snapping."
Now, the pointer doesn’t actually move
to the center of the button at this point,
though it may appear that way.
The true position of the pointer
still remains on the edge of the button,
and this is indicated
with a parallax effect.
We do this so the amount
the true pointer position moves onscreen
is always based on how much movement
you apply to the trackpad,
making it feel more predictable.
As you move the pointer
along a set of buttons,
the visible pointer
will animate to the next button
once the true pointer position
reaches the edge of the button’s hit area.
Once you lift your finger,
the pointer centers itself on the control.
This is called "re-centering."
Re-centering makes it easier
to click the button
when you put your finger
back down on the trackpad.
If you place a traditional pointer
near the edge of a button,
release your finger, and click,
it’s possible the finger
may roll slightly,
moving the pointer off of the button.
The pointer then auto-hides
after a short delay.
We found that
if the pointer persisted onscreen,
it would remind people to perform
their next interaction using the trackpad,
rather than with touch or the Pencil.
We want people to feel like they can
fluidly move between different inputs
without thinking about it.
In fact, there are many places on iPadOS
where you can use touch
and the pointer simultaneously.
For example, with one hand, you can use
the pointer to pick up an app icon,
and with the other,
you can swipe on the touchscreen
to move it to another page.
This is a huge advantage
to having both input methods available.
For your app, think about how users
will switch between different inputs,
and even try to use multiple
at the same time.
Now let’s look at how the pointer
moves around the screen.
The macOS pointer moves at a speed
that you can customize
to what feels right for you.
But it gets a little extra speed boost
with something called
an acceleration curve.
The acceleration curve
moves the pointer a longer distance
the faster you move your finger
on the trackpad.
Here, I’m swiping slowly
and swiping quickly
over the same physical distance
on the trackpad.
We’ve carefully tuned
the acceleration curve on the Mac
to work just right
and we’re using that same curve on iPadOS.
But sometimes, the boost you get
from the acceleration curve
just isn’t enough to quickly move
the pointer to where you want it.
For instance, with a traditional pointer,
to move it all the way
over to the Settings icon,
I need to perform
two separate swipes on the trackpad.
I wish I could get there
in just one swipe,
but if we made
the acceleration curve stronger,
or increased the speed of the pointer,
it could make it hard to control.
On iPadOS,
we solve this by adding inertia.
Inertia makes it easy
to move long distances
with a small amount of physical input.
Similar to how you can flick to scroll
a long distance on the touchscreen.
Now with just one flick on the trackpad,
I can reach the button.
When we were building the pointer,
we liked being able
to flick to target controls,
but we found that
based on the speed of your swipe,
sometimes the pointer would overshoot
or undershoot the control.
Wouldn’t it be great
if the pointer could just figure out
which control you were aiming for
and move there automatically?
Well, the new pointer has something
called magnetism that does just that.
Magnetism scans the interface
to find the control
you most likely want to target.
Let’s go back in time to see how it works.
At this point, I’m mid-swipe
and my finger
is still touching the trackpad.
The moment I lift my finger
from the trackpad,
the pointing system immediately calculates
where the pointer would have landed
if it continued moving with inertia.
We know that there isn’t a target there,
so we start scanning around that position
in circles up to a fixed radius.
We’ll find the nearest target
in the direction of your swipe
and automatically move the pointer there.
Since the Settings icon
is the closest snappable element
to the projected position that is also
in the direction of the pointer,
we move the pointer there automatically
the moment you lift your finger
from the trackpad.
We put a lot of work
into tuning this to feel just right.
Ideally, people aren’t even aware
that this is happening.
The pointer just
magically reads their mind
and does the right thing.
And what’s great is,
any control in your app
that supports pointer snapping
gets magnetism for free.
We just learned about
why we added a pointer to iPadOS,
the power of adaptive precision,
and went behind the scenes
to look at how the pointer works
with snapping, re-centering,
inertia, and magnetism.
Now I’m going to pass it off to Marcos,
who’s going to talk about how you can
use pointer effects in your app.
Thanks, Brandon. Hi, everyone.
In this section,
we're going to have a look
at the different pointer effects
you can use
when adding trackpad support to your apps.
When the iPadOS pointer
hovers over an interactive element,
both the appearance
and the behavior of the pointer
and the interactive element become one,
bringing focus to the item
that is being targeted.
We refer to this integration
of pointer and content
as a pointer effect,
and it changes
based on context and content type.
iPadOS provides three pointer effects
you can use
to bring focus
to the interactive elements in your app.
So, when adding pointer support
to your apps,
you can use one of the provided effects,
you can modify them to suit your app,
or design a completely new one
if you desire so.
The first effect we provide
is called highlight effect.
This effect is used for small controls
that don’t have a background,
and it’s the default effect
for bar buttons and tab bars,
for instance.
When the pointer hovers over a control,
it becomes the control's background
by moving behind it
while adopting a lighter color.
When the control gets selected,
its contents scale up
and move with the pointer
with a gentle parallax effect.
A light effect
connected to the pointer movement
is added on top to highlight the object.
And on click, the three layers scale down
and move to the object center.
The next effect we provide
is the lift effect.
You might want to use it
for medium-sized elements
that already have a background.
The pointer transforms into the element,
highlighting it
without obscuring its contents.
Examples of this effect in iPadOS
are the app icons
or the Control Center modules.
When the pointer approaches a control,
it disappears behind it.
The object appears lifted
by scaling up and adding a shadow,
and the color of the item bleeds around it
and illuminates the background behind it.
Let’s look at how the effect works
when an object gets selected.
These are the different layers
that are added on top
and below the selected element.
A soft, specular highlight is added
on top of the element to illuminate it.
The element itself is scaled up
and its colors bleed around it,
covering its surroundings.
This light effect is called radiosity.
And lastly, a shadow is projected
under the element
to give the illusion
the element is floating above the screen.
The specular light is used
to highlight the selected object,
but it has a second purpose.
The position of the light
shows the actual position of the pointer
under the hood,
as you can see
with the dashed circle here.
The specular light
shows you where the pointer is
and connects your gestures
with the movement on the screen.
The strength of the light
is based on the object size too.
It gets bigger and brighter
for bigger elements
where the position of the pointer
is harder to see,
and gets smaller
or it’s not visible at all
for smaller objects that don’t require it.
This is automatically done by the system
so you don’t have to worry about it.
The last effect we provide
is called hover.
It is generally used for larger objects
that would behave poorly if the pointer
were to morph into their shape.
When the pointer hovers over an object
that uses this effect,
the object changes its appearance
to show it's being focused,
and the cursor retains its default shape
and remains visible on top of the object.
This effect is highly customizable
and it can be just a scale of the object,
and a shadow to lift it,
a color tint added to the object,
or any combination of the three.
So, how do you use the different effects?
Let’s have a look at how to pick
the best effect for your app
and how to use it.
The main rule
when picking a pointer effect
is to try the automatic effect first.
When using the automatic effect,
the system uses a combination of rules
like the object type and location,
and the object size and shape
to decide the best effect for it.
These rules can change in the future,
so using the automatic effect
ensures your app will always look good.
Using the automatic effect is very easy.
Just pick "automatic"
when assigning a UIPointerEffect
for your interactive element.
For more technical
and implementation details,
check out the talk
"Build for the iPadOS Pointer"
from this year’s WWDC.
But the automatic effect
is not always the right solution.
Like in this example from the Books app.
The bookmark icon on the right
has its own background
and it seems like the lift effect
should be the appropriate one for it.
But because it’s in a toolbar
next to other buttons
that use the highlight effect,
it feels out of place
and we shouldn’t use it.
The right thing to do in this case
is to use the highlight effect.
The highlight effect
will make the button look consistent
with the other buttons around it.
You should try to be consistent
when designing
the size of your objects too.
Like in this example,
we have three buttons side-by-side,
but their highlight background size
is not consistent.
This discrepancy will look bad
when the pointer moves over them.
So make sure the objects in the same group
have a consistent size between them.
For toolbar-sized buttons,
like in this example,
we recommend using a height of 37 points.
Effect consistency
is not always the right choice, though.
For instance, when we were designing
the pointer behavior
for segmented controls,
we arrived to the conclusion
that mixing effects was
the right thing to do in this situation.
So, even though "Day" and "Month"
use the highlight effect
and get a rounded rectangle around them,
when focused, using the highlight effect
for the selected option
looks out of place.
In general, you should try to avoid
the highlight effect
around rectangular objects.
The right thing to do in this case
is to use the lift effect
so the selected option appears lifted
above the control around it.
The hit region of your objects
will determine the area
your pointer effect is active,
and you should make sure
it’s the right size.
If the hit region is too small,
it can make people feel
that they have to be extra precise
when interacting with the element.
On the other hand,
when an element’s hit region is too large,
people can feel
that it takes a lot of effort
to pull the pointer away from the element.
So try to define a region
that feels comfortable.
In general, it works well
to add about 12 points of padding
around elements that include a bezel,
and about 24 points
around elements without a bezel.
An extended hit region
will also make your apps more comfortable
when using the touchscreen.
A common issue
when defining your hit region
is leaving a gap between objects.
This will make the pointer morph back
into the circular shape between them,
creating an unnecessary animation.
So make sure your hit region
extends between your objects,
leaving no gap between them.
That way, the pointer
will flow nicely between them.
This change will make your apps
work much better with touch too.
A common problem
when adopting the lift effect
is the extended shadow around it.
Because the app was not designed
for the extended size of the object,
the shadow might get clipped
by other UI elements around it.
So make sure that the objects
that adopt the lift effect
are on top of their surrounding layers
to ensure the shadow
is rendered correctly.
Next, we're going to have a look
at how to customize and combine
the pointer effects in your app.
When using the highlight and lift effects,
you can specify the size
and corner radius of your object.
If your object has a circular shape
or the corner radius is not 8 points,
it is very important that you provide
the correct corner radius,
otherwise it will not render correctly.
When using the hover effect,
your object can scale up
or have a shadow when it is highlighted,
like we see in this example.
Both the scale effect and the shadow
can be turned on and off
so you can pick the right combination
that matches your app design.
But in general,
we don't recommend using the shadow
if you are not scaling your object.
Another effect you can combine with hover
is tinting.
You can use it to highlight objects
you don't want to scale,
as you can see here for Notifications.
When tinting is turned on,
it will add a special material on top
or below the object and change its color.
This material can be dark or light
depending on your Dark Mode settings.
When using the hover effect,
you can provide a custom shape
for your pointer too.
The pointer will morph
from the default circle
into the provided shape
when it hovers over your object,
like the I-beam pointer we use
for text on iPadOS.
Custom pointers can show you
extra information
about a specific region on the screen,
or a change in the pointer behavior.
We're going to learn a lot more
about custom pointers in the next section.
If we visualize the actual position
of the pointer,
we can see how the I-beam tries to stay
in the center of the text field.
This effect is called snapping,
and creates a magnetic attraction
that pulls the pointer
to the center of the object.
It increases the precision of the pointer
and creates a more comfortable experience
when interacting with your app controls.
You can use this effect in your apps too.
Adding snapping to controls
helps you be more precise
and simplifies common tasks
like grabbing small handlers,
as you can see in this example.
Just remember,
you should never enable snapping
if you are not providing a custom pointer.
So we just had a look
at the three pointer effects
provided by iPadOS:
highlight, lift, and hover.
Remember, you should try to use
the automatic effect whenever possible.
Be consistent picking the pointer effects
and designing your object's shape.
Extend your object's hit region
to make it more comfortable to use.
Remember, when using the lift effect,
you have to provide the correct size
and corner radius.
And if you use the hover effect,
you can enable a scale, a shadow
or a tint color for your object.
I hope this section gave you
a good overview
of the different pointer effects
provided by iPadOS,
and how to successfully use them
to create a great pointer experience
for your apps.
That's all from me.
I'm going to pass it over to CC
who is going to show you how to design
a great pointer for your app.
Thank you.
Thank you, Marcos. Hi, everyone.
I'm going to talk about
the pointer appearance
and how to design a custom pointer.
First, let's look at the pointer material.
The pointer in iPadOS has a material
that constantly adapts
to the background color smoothly.
It provides optimal contrast at all times
without being distracting.
When the background color changes,
so will the pointer's color.
This material maintains contrast
without obscuring the background.
That is because when people
are using the iPad with the trackpad,
we want the pointer to be there
to show the location of interaction,
but it shouldn't draw
too much attention to itself
and take away from the content.
However, the pointer should
indicate intention when it's needed.
In this case, when the pointer
is transformed into a button shape,
not only does it change its shape,
but the color of it also becomes lighter
to provide good legibility to the label.
On top of that, when people click,
the circle scales down and becomes darker
to provide a satisfying feedback
for the click action.
These are examples
of the pointer's material
adapting to its function.
And all of these color adaptations
are provided by the system automatically.
Next, we are going to look
at the pointer shape.
As Brandon mentioned earlier,
the pointer shape is a circle
that represents touch.
The size of it relates well
with the touch-based UI elements.
The circle shape
provides a perfect foundation
for it to transform into any shape.
In the previous example,
the pointer transformed from a circle
to a rounded rectangle
to highlight the button.
This is our first type
of pointer shape transformation:
from a circle to a rounded rectangle.
And it's not just for buttons.
The circle can transform
to a vertical bar for an I-beam,
a horizontal pill
to highlight the top status region,
or to highlight a grabber.
These are all considered
the rectangle type
of pointer transformation.
The second type of transformation
is when the circle morphs
into any arbitrary shape.
This can be used to inform people
when there is a change of functionality
or precision.
For example,
the pointer can turn into a cross shape
to indicate an area
with a higher level of precision.
It can also transform
into a pair of triangles
to inform people
the direction of a drag movement,
or when the Command key is held down
and the function
of the pointer is modified.
Both of these transformations
are available
with their corresponding APIs.
If the pointer is going to morph
from a circle to a rectangle shape,
apply the top API.
If it is changing to a more complex shape,
use the bottom one.
And check out the talk
“Build for the iPadOS Pointer”
for more details on how to use these APIs.
Now let's talk about how to design
a great custom pointer.
As we just learned,
the pointer in iPadOS has many ways
to morph its color and shape.
These behaviors provide the pointer
with the flexibility
to fully adapt to its context
at any given moment.
When we design a new custom shape for it,
we should keep in mind
this characteristic
of a constant state of transformation.
So how do we design
a great custom shape for the pointer?
First, make sure your custom shape
is simple and easy to understand.
The shape of the pointer informs people
the action they can take
in the current context.
For example, in Keynote,
the pointer transforms
into a pair of arrows
that show the directions in which
people can drag a selection handle.
If people cannot instantly understand
your custom pointer,
they're likely to waste time
trying to figure it out.
Second, use solid shapes
as much as possible.
Remember, the pointer color
is constantly changing.
A solid shape will maintain legibility
and make it easy to read.
A shape with strokes
will be difficult to read.
But if it happens
that you cannot use a solid fill shape,
use heavy strokes
and make sure the stroke weight
is thick enough to maintain visual weight.
It will be difficult to see the pointer
if the stroke is too thin.
And don't forget to use a size
that is similar to the default pointer.
The size of the custom shape
should visually balance
with the default pointer,
which is a 19-point circle.
In other words,
if you have a shape that is narrow,
you may want to make it bigger
to maintain a similar visual weight.
In this example,
the cross mark is 24 points
compared to the 19-point circle.
Keep in mind that the pointer will morph
from its default state
to the custom state.
If the custom pointer is too small,
it may get lost.
And if there is a big size difference
between the two states,
the transformation can become jarring
and distracting.
Now, when you design your custom pointer,
make sure the shape
communicates its intention
as directly as possible.
Here is an example.
Say if you are designing an app
to read and highlight text,
instead of using a marker pen glyph
as the custom highlight pointer,
a better solution
is to show the marker tip shape.
In this case,
the shape not only informs people
the height of the text selection,
but also resembles the I-beam,
which implies all the system behaviors
of adaptive precision and snapping.
The shape of the marker tip
has the same anchor point as the circle,
resulting in a nice transition
between the two shapes.
Speaking of anchor points,
when designing a custom pointer,
we should also make sure
the anchor point matches well.
If your custom shape is a circle,
a simple geometric shape,
or a symmetrical shape,
it's natural to see
the point of interaction
as the center of these shapes.
If the shape is directional,
or with a specific focus area,
we will need the anchor point set
to match the intent.
However, it also means the transformation
will appear to be off-centered.
It would be nice to think of other ways
to indicate these functions,
and maintain the center anchor point
as much as possible
for a nice experience.
In this example, instead of using
an eyedropper glyph as our custom pointer,
we can use a target shape
for precise color sampling.
Lastly, a couple of things to keep in mind
when designing a custom pointer.
Make sure you apply
standard pointer behaviors
on your custom pointer.
For example,
if buttons in a custom navigation bar
don't use the standard highlight effect,
people might think they are broken.
Apply similar functions
to similar pointers.
For example,
if your app helps people draw,
every drawing area in it
should have a similar pointer experience
so that people can apply the knowledge
they gain in one area to the others.
Last but not least, try not to create
unnecessary custom pointers.
People notice when the appearance
of the pointer changes,
and they expect the change to be useful.
Creating a purely decorative
pointer effect
can distract and even irritate people
without providing any practical value.
All right, we just learned about
the pointer material, pointer shape,
and how to design a great custom pointer.
I'm sure you can create a pointer
that makes your app
feel native and intuitive
when people experience it with a trackpad.
Now I'm going to pass it
to my colleague Dylan.
He is going to talk about
pointer interactions.
Thanks, CC.
Let's talk about
all the new interactive behaviors
your app can gain with the pointer.
Let's start by talking about
increasing precision in your app.
The presence of a pointer means
that people can now interact with your app
with much greater precision
than previously possible with the finger.
So how do we let them
take advantage of this
without redesigning our apps entirely?
We can use the pointer
to do finer-grained selection,
as well as adding quicker interactivity
to smaller elements of your interface.
A great example of finer-grained selection
is the text-editing experience on iOS.
As shown here, you can use
the low-precision input of your finger
to perform text selection
on a word boundary,
and then use the drag handles
to carefully adjust your selection.
But with the high-precision input
of the pointer,
this interaction is a bit different.
As Brandon described,
the narrow beam pointer
makes it easy to see
exactly where you're selecting,
while we also snap it to the current line
and grow its height
to match the line height,
reducing the ambiguity of its position.
Because of this high precision
and low ambiguity afforded by the pointer,
we can begin selecting with
character-level precision immediately.
Consider places in your app where
you might need a more precise pointer,
or where you can use snapping
to aid people in navigating your UI,
and strive to always use a pointer
that matches the precision necessary
for the current task,
defaulting to the circle when necessary.
You can find another case of this type
of precise input here in Numbers.
Using our finger,
we can tap to select a column header
and then drag a finger
on the exposed drag handle
to resize a column.
But with the precision of pointer input,
we can actually expose a control
that isn't available with the finger.
Rather than selecting a column
to expose a resize handle,
we can move the pointer directly
to the small divider between columns
and begin dragging,
again avoiding the need
to first make an imprecise selection
to achieve our goal.
It's important to note
that neither of these examples
adds new functionality for the pointer,
but rather they use the added precision
to make this functionality
easier to use with the pointer.
You should avoid
updating your app's layout,
increasing density,
or introducing features
that only work with the pointer,
but instead use the pointer's precision
to make using your app quicker
and more intuitive.
The pointer clearly enables
new possibilities with precise input,
but that's only half the story.
The pointer system really shines
when you make great use
of adaptive precision.
Let's take a look at how you can make
your larger, low-precision interfaces
work wonderfully with the pointer too.
Adopting pointer effects in places
where high precision isn't necessary
still can vastly improve the experience
of your app.
A great example is the interface
in Reminders for creating a new list.
These are approximately
finger-sized targets,
a UI that already works great
with the finger,
but adding the lift effect to these
creates a fun and easy-to-use picker
that gives exactly
the amount of precision required.
Consider places in your app that
adjacent controls can use pointer effects
to gain great visual feedback
and snapping behaviors.
As Marcos described previously,
in cases of even larger UI
that may behave poorly
with a morphing pointer,
you can still adopt a hover effect.
This isn't just for show.
It can provide a lot of information
about precision.
The Calendar app often has events
much larger than a finger.
While you might think such a coarse UI
doesn't need to adapt to the pointer,
this is actually an excellent place to add
a hover effect to indicate interactivity
and disambiguate
in cases of overlapping events.
Now I'd like to share how the unique
characteristics of pointer input
can accelerate
some of the interactions in your app.
The pointer's presence on the screen
serves as a great indicator of intent.
We can use this new information
to speed up interactions
that previously would have required a tap.
Now that we know
the position of the pointer,
we know that hovering over a region
means a person is likely
to interact with it,
and our app can respond proactively.
For instance, the Books app makes use
of the hover position of the pointer
to control the visibility of its toolbars.
We can hide the bar interface
while reading to reduce distraction,
but immediately reveal it
when the pointer moves over it,
removing the need
for a click to hide and show.
The pointer's movement, or lack thereof,
can also be a helpful hint
to update our UI.
In a full-screen experience
or media playback,
you might wish to automatically hide UI
after a period of inactivity.
In these cases,
pointer movement is a clear indication
that someone wants to interact
with your interface,
and can be used to reveal your controls.
Because pointing devices can scroll
with a dedicated gesture or scroll wheel,
your app can instantaneously respond
to a click and drag
to implement things
like instantaneous drag-and-drop,
or drag-select, as we see here in Pages.
Previously,
these interactions required you
to press and hold and wait
with your finger
to disambiguate between
scrolling with a single finger
and dragging on the content.
Now let's take a step beyond the way
the pointer interacts with your app,
and think about how the people
using your app
interact with the trackpad itself
through gestures.
While one-finger interaction is largely
reserved for pointing and clicking,
and three-finger gestures
are reserved by the system
for actions like multitasking,
your app can make use
of two-finger gestures on the trackpad.
We'll automatically enable
two-finger scrolling for scroll views,
but you may wish to provide
more custom interactions.
Be sure to design your trackpad gestures
with a relationship
to your touchscreen gestures
to create a consistent experience
across input modes.
When adding gestures to the trackpad,
we should always treat them as happening
relative to the pointer in your app.
This means that gestures should be
performed on the view under your pointer.
In this example, the pointer is moved
between the left and right scroll views,
and the scroll gesture is always
performed on the appropriate view.
Taking this a bit further,
let's take a look
at how two-finger gestures behave in Maps.
As expected,
the map scrolls with two fingers
when the pointer is above it,
and the card scrolls
when the pointer is above it.
But Maps also allows using two fingers
to zoom and rotate.
This brings us to another detail
about gestures behaving
relative to the pointer.
As we zoom and rotate,
the view remains anchored to the pointer.
This keeps the pointer in a fixed position
relative to the map below,
no different
than if I had performed this gesture
with my fingers on the touchscreen
centered on the pointer.
Because the two-finger gestures
are intended to act
relative to the pointer,
it follows that you should be able
to use these gestures directly
on a focused element.
Think about places in your app
that allow dragging with a finger today
that could be adapted
to a two-finger trackpad drag.
Another capability of trackpads and mice
is the ability to offer a secondary click.
This can be exposed
via a two-finger click on a trackpad,
a secondary button on a mouse,
or even holding the control key
and clicking,
but the important fact
that these all have in common
is that they're all fast
and just about as easy as a regular click.
This means
we can instantaneously perform an action
that would have otherwise required
a long press or a special mode
to distinguish it
from a regular tap with the finger.
By default, we use this
to immediately show context menus.
This is an accelerator for an action
that would have otherwise required
a long press.
You'll get this for free in your app,
but in your custom interfaces,
you may want to consider the places
that an accelerated or alternate action
is appropriate for a secondary click.
So we've learned a lot today.
We've learned about adaptive precision,
how to customize the pointer
and its effects,
and how to make use
of pointer interactions
and gestures in your app.
These are all small pieces
when viewed individually,
adopting pointer effects to provide
the right amount of precision
and improve ergonomics,
integrating hover
to let your app respond to intent,
responding fluidly to two-finger gestures,
accelerating interactions
with secondary click,
and applying custom pointer shapes
that allow precision
while using snapping to improve accuracy.
But these small pieces combine to form
a whole, powerful, functional system
that allows you to build
highly responsive,
understandable interfaces,
combining unprecedented precision
with ease of use.
We hope you take what you've learned today
to elevate your already excellent
touchscreen apps
and make them even more powerful
with the pointer.
Thank you.