Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name's Quinton,
and I'm an engineer on the ARKit team.
Today, both Praveen and I get to show you
some of the new features in ARKit
with iOS 14.
So let's jump right in
and explore ARKit 4.
This release
adds many advancements to ARKit,
which already powers
the world's largest AR platform--
iOS.
ARKit gives you the tools
to create AR experiences
that change the way your users
see the world.
Some of these tools include
device motion tracking,
camera scene capture
and advanced scene processing,
which all help to simplify the task
of building a realistic
and immersive AR experience.
Let's see what's next with ARKit.
So first, we're gonna take a look
at the Location Anchor API.
Location anchors bring your AR experience
onto the global scale
by allowing you to position
virtual content in relation to the globe.
Then we'll see what
the new LiDAR sensor brings to ARKit
with Scene Geometry.
Scene Geometry provides apps
with a mesh of the surrounding environment
that can be used
for everything from occlusion to lighting.
Next, we'll look at the technology
that enables Scene Geometry--
the Depth API.
We're opening up this API to give apps
access to a dense depth map
to enable new possibilities
using the LiDAR sensor.
And additionally, the LiDAR sensor
improves object placement.
We'll go over some best practices
to make sure your apps take full advantage
of the newest object placement techniques.
And we'll wrap up with some improvements
to Face Tracking.
Let's start with location anchors.
Before we get too far,
let's look at how we got to this point.
ARKit started on iOS
with the best tracking.
No QR codes,
no external equipment needed--
just start an AR experience
by placing content around you.
Then we added multi-user experiences.
Your AR content
could then be shared with a friend
using a separate device
to make experiences social.
And last year,
we brought people into ARKit.
AR experiences are now aware
of the people in the scene.
Motion Capture is possible
with just a single iOS device,
and People Occlusion
makes AR content even more immersive,
as people can walk
right in front of a virtual object.
All these features combine to make
some amazing experiences, but what's next?
So now we're bringing AR into the outdoors
with location anchors.
Location anchors enable you to place
AR content in relation to the globe.
This means you can
now place virtual objects
and create AR experiences by specifying
a latitude, longitude and altitude.
ARKit will take
your geographic coordinates,
as well as high-resolution map data
from Apple Maps,
to place your AR experiences
at the specific world location.
This whole process is called
visual localization,
and it will precisely locate your device
in relation to the surrounding environment
more accurately than
could be done before with just GPS.
All this is possible due to
advanced machine-learning techniques
running right on your device.
There's no processing in the cloud
and no images sent back to Apple.
ARKit also takes care
of merging the local coordinate system
to the geographic coordinate system
so you can work in one unified system
regardless of how you want
to create your AR experiences.
To access these features,
we've added a new configuration,
ARGeoTrackingConfiguration,
and ARGeoAnchors
are what you'll use to place in content
the same way as other ARKit anchors.
Let's see some location anchors in action.
We've got a video here in front
of the Ferry Building in San Francisco.
You can see a large virtual sculpture
that's actually the Companion sculpture
created by KAWS
and viewed in the Acute Art app.
Since it was placed with location anchors,
everyone who uses the app
at the Ferry Building
can enjoy the virtual art
in the same place and the same way.
Let's see what's under the hood
in ARKit to make this all work.
So when using geo-tracking,
we download all the detailed map data
from Apple Maps
around your current location.
Part of this data is a localization map
that contains feature points
of the surrounding area
that can be seen from the street.
Then, with the localization map,
your current location
and images from your device,
we can use advanced machine learning
to visually localize
and determine your device's position.
All this is happening
under the hood in ARKit
to give you a precise, globally aware pose
without worrying
about any of this complexity.
The Location Anchor API
can be broken down into three main parts.
ARGeoTrackingConfiguration
is the configuration that you'll use
to take advantage
of all the new location anchor features.
This configuration contains a subset
of the world-tracking features
that are compatible with geo-tracking.
Then, once you've started an AR session
with a geo-tracking configuration,
you'll be able to create ARGeoAnchors
just like any other ARKit anchor.
And also, while using geo-tracking,
there's a new tracking status
that's important to monitor.
This is contained
in ARGeoTrackingStatus
and provides valuable feedback
to improve the geo-tracking experience.
So building an app with location anchors
can be broken down into a few steps.
The first is checking availability
of geo-tracking.
ARGeoTrackingConfiguration
has a few methods
that let us check the preconditions to
using the rest of the Location Anchor API.
Then, location anchors can be added once
we know there's full geo-tracking support,
and after anchors are added,
we can use a rendering engine
to place virtual content.
We'll then need to take care
of geo-tracking transitions.
Once started, geo-tracking
will move through a few states
that may need some user intervention to
ensure the best geo-tracking experience.
Let's build a simple point-of-interest app
to see what these steps look like
in practice.
In our app, we're gonna start
with helping our users find
the iconic Ferry Building
in San Francisco, California.
As you can see, we've placed a sign
to make the building easy to spot.
To begin the app, let's first start
with checking availability.
As with many ARKit features,
we need to make sure
the current device is supported
before attempting to start an experience.
Location anchors are available on devices
with an A12 Bionic chip and newer
as well as GPS.
ARGeoTrackingConfiguration's
isSupported class method
should be used to check for this support.
For geo-tracking, we also need to check
if the current location is supported.
We need to be in a location that has
all the required Maps data to localize.
The geo-tracking configuration
has a method
to check your current location's support
as well as an arbitrary latitude
and longitude.
Additionally,
once a geo-tracking session is started,
ARKit will ask the user for permission
for both camera and location.
ARKit has always asked
for camera permission,
but location permission is new
to geo-tracking.
Let's see what this looks like in code.
ARGeoTrackingConfiguration
has all the class methods
that we need to check
before starting our AR session.
We'll first check if the current device
is supported with isSupported.
Then we'll check if our current location
is available for geo-tracking
with checkAvailability.
If this check fails, we'll get an error
with more info to display to the user--
for example, if the user
hasn't given the app location permissions.
Then once we know our current device
and location are supported,
we can go ahead and start the session.
Since we're using RealityKit,
we'll need our ARView
and then update the configuration.
By default, ARView uses
a world-tracking configuration,
and so we need pass in
a geo-tracking configuration
when running the session.
The next step is adding a location anchor.
To do this, we'll use
the new ARAnchor subclass, ARGeoAnchor.
Geo anchors are similar
to existing ARKit anchors in many ways.
However, because geo anchors
operate on global coordinates,
we can't create them with just transforms.
We need to specify
their geographic coordinates
with latitude, longitude and altitude.
The most common way to create geo anchors
will be though specifying
just latitude and longitude,
which this allows ARKit
to fill in the altitude
based on Maps data
of the correct ground level.
Let's now add a location anchor
to our point-of-interest app.
So for our app, we need to start
by finding the Ferry Building's location.
One way we can get the latitude
and longitude is through the Maps app.
When we place a marker in the Maps app,
we now get up to six digits of precision
after the decimal.
It's important to use six or more digits
so that we get a precise location
to place our content.
Once we have a latitude and longitude,
we can make a geo anchor.
We don't need to specify an altitude
because we'll let ARKit use Maps data
to determine
the elevation of the ground level.
Then, we'll add the geo anchor
to our session,
and since we're using RealityKit
to render our virtual content
and we've already created our geo anchor,
we can go ahead and attach the anchor
to an entity to mark the Ferry Building.
Let's run our app
and see what it looks like.
We'll start near the Ferry Building
in San Francisco
looking towards Market Street.
And as we pan around,
we can see some of the palm trees
that line the city.
And soon,
the Ferry Building will come into view.
Our sign looks to be on the ground,
which is expected,
but the text is rotated.
Since we'd like to find the Ferry Building
easily from a distance,
we'd really like to have the sign floating
a few meters in the air
and facing towards the city.
So, how do we do this?
To position this content,
we need to first look
at the coordinate system of a geo anchor.
Geo anchors are fixed
to the cardinal directions.
Their axes are set
when you create the anchor,
and this orientation will remain unchanged
for the rest of the session.
A geo anchor's x-axis
is always pointed east,
and the z-axis is always pointed south
for any geographic coordinate.
Since we're using
a right-handed coordinate system,
this leaves positive Y pointing up,
away from the ground.
Geo anchors, like all other ARKit anchors,
are immutable.
This means we'll need to use
our rendering engine
to rotate or translate our virtual objects
from the geo anchor's origin.
Let's clean up our sign that we placed
in front of the Ferry Building.
Here's some RealityKit code
to start updating our sign.
After getting the signEntity
and adding it to the geoAnchorEntity,
we want to rotate the sign
towards the city.
To do this, we'll rotate it by
a little less than 90 degrees clockwise,
and we'll elevate the sign's position
by 35 meters.
Both of these operations
are in relation to the geoAnchorEntity
that we had previously created.
Let's see what this looks like in the app.
Now when we pan around
and we get to our Ferry Building,
our sign is high in the air
and we can see it from a distance.
The text is much easier to read
in this orientation.
This looks great,
but we're missing some crucial information
here about the geo-tracking state
that we can use to guide the user
to the best geo-tracking experience.
When using a geo-tracking configuration,
there's a new geo-tracking status object
that's available on ARFrame
and ARSessionObserver.
ARGeoTrackingStatus
encapsulates all the current state
information of geo-tracking,
similar to the world-tracking information
that's available on ARCamera.
Within GeoTrackingStatus is a state.
This state indicates how far along
geo-tracking is during localization.
There's also a property
that provides more information
about the current localization state
called GeoTrackingStateReason.
And there's an accuracy provided
once geo-tracking localizes.
Let's take a closer look
at the GeoTrackingState.
When an AR session begins,
GeoTrackingState starts at Initializing.
At this point, geo-tracking is waiting
for world tracking to initialize.
From Initializing, the tracking state
can immediately go to Not Available
if geo-tracking isn't supported
in the current location.
If you're using
the checkAvailability class method
on GeoTrackingConfiguration,
you should rarely get into this state.
Once geo-tracking moves to Localizing,
ARKit is receiving images
as well as Maps data
and is trying to compute pose.
However, during both the Initializing
and Localizing states,
there could be issues detected
that prevent localization.
These issues are communicated through
GeoTrackingStateReason.
This reason should be used
to inform the user
how to help geo-tracking localize.
Some possible reasons include
the device is pointed too low,
which we'd then inform the user
to raise the device,
or geoDataNotLoaded,
and we'd inform the user
that a network connection is required.
For all possible reasons,
have a look at ARGeoTrackingTypes.h.
In general, we want to encourage users
to point their devices at buildings
and other stationary structures
that are visible from the street.
Parking lots, open fields,
and other environments
that dynamically change
have a lower chance of localizing.
After addressing
any GeoTrackingStateReasons,
geo-tracking should become Localized.
It's at this point
that should you start your AR experience.
If you place objects before localization,
the objects could jump
to unintended locations.
Additionally, once localized,
ARGeoTrackingAccuracy is provided
to help you gate
what experiences should be enabled.
It's also important to always monitor
GeoTrackingState,
as it's possible for geo-tracking
to move back to Localizing
or even Initializing,
such as when tracking's lost
or map data isn't available.
Let's take a look at how we can add this
tracking state to improve our sample app.
Now we can see this whole time
we were actually localizing
when looking at Market Street
and the surrounding buildings.
As we pan around, we can see
from the tracking state that we localize
and then the accuracy increases to high.
I think we've got our app
just about ready,
at least for the Ferry Building.
We've added a more expansive
location anchor sample project
on developer.apple.com
that I encourage you to check out
after this talk.
For more information
on the RealityKit features used,
check out last year's talk, "Introducing
RealityKit and Reality Composer."
In our sample app,
we saw how to create location anchors
by directly specifying coordinates.
We already knew the geographic coordinates
for the Ferry Building.
However, these coordinates
could have come from any source,
such as our App Bundle,
our web back end or, really, any database.
Another way to create a location anchor
is via user interaction.
We could expand on our app in the future
by allowing users to tap the screen
to save their own point of interest.
GetGeoLocation(ForPoint on ARSession
allows us to get geographic coordinates
from any world point
in ARKit coordinate space.
For example, this could have come
from a raycast or a location on a plane.
Location anchors are available
for you today with iOS 14,
and we're starting with support
in the San Francisco Bay Area,
New York, Los Angeles, Chicago and Miami,
with more cities coming through
this summer.
All iPhones and iPads
with an A12 Bionic chip and newer,
as well as GPS, are supported.
Also, for any apps
that require location anchors exclusively,
you can use device capability keys
to limit your app in the App Store
to only compatible hardware.
In addition to the GPS key,
you'll need to use a new key
for devices with an A12 Bionic chip
or newer that's available on iOS 14.
With location anchors, you can now bring
your AR experiences onto the global scale.
We went over how
ARGeoTrackingConfiguration
is the entry point
to adding location anchors to your app.
We saw how to add ARGeoAnchors
to your AR scene
and how to position content
in relation to those anchors.
We also saw how ARGeoTrackingStatus
can be used to help guide the user
to the best geo-tracking experience.
And now here's Praveen
to tell you more about Scene Geometry.
Hi, everyone. I am Praveen Gowda.
I am an engineer on the ARKit team.
Today, I am going to take you through
some of the APIs available in iOS 14
that help bring the power
of the LiDAR Scanner to your applications.
In ARKit 3.5,
we introduced the Scene Geometry API
powered by the LiDAR Scanner
on the new iPad Pro.
Before we go into Scene Geometry,
let's take a look
at how the LiDAR Scanner works.
The LiDAR shoots light
onto the surroundings
and then collects the light
reflected off the surfaces in the scene.
The depth is estimated
by measuring the time it took
for the light to go from the LiDAR
to the environment
and reflect back to the scanner.
And this entire process runs
millions of times every second.
The LiDAR Scanner is used
by the Scene Geometry API
to provide a topological map
of the environment.
This can be optionally fused
with semantic classification,
which enables apps to recognize
and classify physical objects.
This provides an opportunity
for creating richer AR experiences
where apps can now occlude
virtual objects with the real world
or use physics
to enable realistic interactions
between virtual and physical objects...
or to use virtual lighting
on real-world surfaces,
and in many other use cases
that we've yet to imagine.
Let's take a quick look
at Scene Geometry in action.
Here's a living room,
and once the Scene Geometry API
is turned on,
the entire visible room is meshed.
Triangles vary in size to show
the optimum detail for each surface.
The color mesh appears
when semantic classification is enabled.
Each color represents
a different classification,
such as blue for the seats
and green for the floor.
As we saw, the Scene Geometry feature
is built by leveraging the depth data
gathered from the LiDAR Scanner.
In iOS 14, we have a new ARKit Depth API
that provides access
to the same depth data.
The API provides a dense depth image
where a pixel in the image corresponds
to depth in meters from the camera.
What we see here
is a debug visualization of this depth
where there is a gradient from blue to red
where blue represents regions
closer to the camera
and red represents those away.
The depth data would be available at 60 Hz
associated with each ARFrame.
The Scene Geometry feature
is built on top of this API
where depth data across multiple frames
are aggregated and processed
to construct a 3D mesh.
This API is powered by the LiDAR Scanner
and hence will be available
on devices which have LiDAR.
Here is an illustration
of how the depth map is generated.
The colored RGB image
from the wide-angle camera
and the depth readings
from the LiDAR Scanner
are fused together
using advanced machine-learning algorithms
to create a dense depth map
that is exposed through the API.
This operation runs at 60 times per second
with the depth map
available on every ARFrame.
To access the depth data,
each ARFrame will have a new property
called sceneDepth.
This provides an object
of type ARDepthData.
ARDepthData
is a container for two buffers--
one is a depth map,
and the other is a confidence map.
The depth map is a CVPixelBuffer
where each pixel
represents depth and is in meters.
And this depth corresponds to the distance
from the plane of the camera
to a point in the world.
One thing to note is that the depth map
is smaller in resolution
compared to the capturedImage on ARFrame
but still preserves the same aspect ratio.
The other buffer
on the ARDepthData object
is the confidence map.
Since the measurement of depth using LiDAR
is based on the light
which reflects from objects,
the accuracy of the depth map
can be impacted by the nature
of the surrounding environment.
Challenging surfaces,
such as those which are highly reflective
or those with high absorption,
can lower the accuracy of the depth.
This accuracy is expressed
through a value we call "confidence."
For each depth pixel,
there is a corresponding confidence value
of type ARConfidenceLevel,
and this value
can either be low, medium or high
and will help to filter depth based
on the requirements of your application.
Let's see how we can use the Depth API.
I begin with creating an AR session
and a world-tracking configuration.
There is a new frame semantic
called sceneDepth
which allows you to turn on the Depth API.
As always, I check if the frame semantic
is supported on the device
using the supportsFrameSemantic method
on the configuration class.
Then, we can set the frame semantic
to sceneDepth and run the configuration.
After this, I can access the depth data
from the sceneDepth property on ARFrame
using
the didUpdateFrame delegate method.
Additionally, if you have an AR app
that uses People Occlusion feature
and hence sets
the personSegmentationWithDepth
frame semantic,
then you will
automatically get scene depth
on devices that support
the sceneDepth frame semantic
with no additional power cost
to your application.
Here is a demo of an app
that we built using the Depth API.
The depth from the depth map is
un-projected to 3D to form a point cloud.
The point cloud is colored
using the capturedImage on the ARFrame.
By accumulating depth data
across multiple ARFrames,
we get a dense 3D point cloud
like the one we see here.
I can also filter the point clouds
based on the confidence level.
This is the point cloud
formed by all the depth pixels,
including those with low confidence.
And here is the point cloud
by filtering depth
whose confidence is medium or high.
And this is the point cloud we get
by using only the depth
which has high confidence.
This gives us a clear picture
of how the physical properties of surfaces
impact the confidence level of its depth.
Your application and its tolerance
to inaccuracies in depth
will determine
how you will filter the depth
based on its confidence level.
Let's take a closer look
at how we built this app.
For each ARFrame,
we access the sceneDepth property
with the ARDepthData object,
providing us with the depth
and the confidence map.
The key part of the app is
a Metal vertex shader called "unproject."
As the name suggests,
it un-projects the depth data
from the depth map to the 3D space
using parameters on the ARCamera
such as the camera's transform,
its intrinsics and the projection matrix.
The shader also uses capturedImage
to sample color for each depth pixel.
What we get as an output of this
is a 3D point cloud
which is then rendered using Metal.
To summarize,
we have a new Depth API in ARKit 4
which gives a highly accurate
representation of the world.
There is a frame semantic
called sceneDepth
which allows you to enable the feature.
Once enabled, the depth data will be
available at 60 Hz on each ARFrame.
The depth data will have
a depth map and a confidence map.
And the API is supported
on devices with a LiDAR Scanner.
One of the fundamental tasks
in many AR apps is placing objects.
And in ARKit 3,
we introduced the raycasting API
to make object placement easier.
In ARKit 4, the LiDAR Scanner brings
some great improvement to raycasting.
Raycasting is highly optimized
for object placement
and makes it easy to precisely place
virtual objects in your AR app.
Placing objects in ARKit 4
is more precise and quicker
thanks to the LiDAR Scanner.
Your apps that already use raycasting
will automatically benefit
on a LiDAR-enabled device.
Raycasting also leverages Scene Depth
or Scene Geometry when available
to instantly place objects in AR.
This works great,
even on featureless surfaces
such as white walls.
In iOS 14,
the raycast API is recommended
over hit-testing for object placement.
Before you can start raycasting,
you will need to create a raycast query.
A raycast query describes
the direction and the behavior
of the ray used for raycasting.
It is composed of a raycast target
which describes the type of surface
that a ray can intersect with.
Existing planes correspond
to planes detected by ARKit
while considering
the shape and size of the plane.
Infinite planes are the same planes,
but with their shape and size ignored.
And estimated planes
are planes of arbitrary orientation
formed from the feature points
around a surface.
The raycast target alignment specifies
the alignment of surfaces
that a ray can intersect with.
This can be horizontal, vertical or any.
There are two types of raycasts.
There are single-shot raycasts
which return a one-time result,
and then there are tracked raycasts
which continuously update the results
as ARKit's
understanding of the world evolves.
In order to get the latest features
for object placement,
we're recommending migrating
to the raycasting API
as we deprecate hit-testing.
The code we see on the top
is extracted from a sample app
which uses hit-testing to place objects.
It performs a hit-test with three
different kinds of hit-test options,
and it is usually followed
by some custom heuristics
to filter those results
and figure out where to place the object.
All of that can be replaced
with a few lines of raycasting code,
like the one we see below,
and ARKit will do the heavy lifting
under the hood
to make sure that your virtual objects
always stay at the right place.
Raycasting makes it easier
than ever before
to precisely place virtual objects
in your ARKit applications.
Let's move over to Face Tracking.
Face Tracking allows you to detect faces
in your front-camera AR experience,
overlay virtual content on them
and animate facial expressions
in real time.
This is supported on all devices
with a TrueDepth camera.
Now, with ARKit 4,
Face Tracking support is extended
to devices without a TrueDepth camera
as long as they have
an Apple A12 Bionic processor or later.
This includes devices
without the TrueDepth camera,
such as the new iPhone SE.
Elements of Face Tracking,
such as face anchors,
face geometry and blend shapes,
will be available
on all supported devices.
But captured depth data will be limited
to devices with a TrueDepth camera.
And that's ARKit 4.
With location anchors,
you can now bring your AR experiences
onto the global scale.
And we looked at how you can use the LiDAR
to build rich AR apps
using the Scene Geometry
and the Depth API.
There are exciting improvements
in raycasting
to make object placement in AR
easier than ever before.
And finally,
Face Tracking is now supported
on a wider range of devices.
Thank you,
and we can't wait to check out
all the great apps
that you will build using ARKit 4.