Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hey. My name is Sofiane,
and I work on Proactive Intelligence
here at Apple.
Today, I want to talk to you about
how your app
can make friends with the system.
As Radhika showed in the previous video,
system intelligence can help people
at every step of their journey
in using their apps and the devices
that those apps are installed on.
The better job you, as a developer,
do to integrate with the system,
and the more people use your apps,
the more we can help them over time.
But how do you do a good job
of integrating with the system?
I'll explain by talking about
a few key concepts
shared across
all of our intelligence technologies.
Then I'll have my colleagues,
Mert and Chad,
talk about how their teams
use these foundational concepts
in slightly different ways,
all to achieve the same goal:
making everyday things easier.
And then Mark will come back
to recap exactly what we hope you do next.
So, let's talk about
what makes the intelligent system work.
We all live busy lives,
and for many of us,
our iOS devices have become
an important part
of how we get things done.
People rely on apps
dozens of times every day,
for tasks ranging from communication,
ordering food,
or even tracking water intake.
And again, our goal is to make
these everyday interactions
as smooth and frictionless as possible
so you can get time back
to focus on your life.
And for this to happen,
the system and your app
need to work together.
And by working together,
what I really mean is that
we need to speak the same language.
For that common language,
we built the Intents framework.
There are three key concepts
you should know about,
and these are define, learn and execute.
Understanding them will help you
accelerate your users
along your apps' critical paths,
and adapt to their preferences over time.
Let's first talk about
what we mean by "Define."
Ultimately, you,
as developers and designers,
just need to ask yourself,
what are the important actions
that people want to perform with your app?
The goal is simply to determine
what are the key and repeatable things
that people want to accomplish.
You can define these actions
using what we call "intents."
Intents represent the "what."
What do people do in your app?
Ask yourself, "What are those tasks?
And what are
all of the relevant attributes
necessary to carry them out?"
What, for example,
does it mean to track your water intake?
Or what's involved in checking the news?
Or what does it mean to order coffee?
Let's actually take a closer look
at that example.
So, to order coffee, you know you'll need
an intent that represents that action.
And, of course,
people like their coffee made differently.
There are obviously
different types of coffee.
Maybe the size of the drink matters too.
Details like this
are the attributes of the action,
also known as the parameters
of the intent.
The Intents framework
gives you the flexibility
to define your intent and its parameters,
making it easy for you
to package all of the information
about the action someone is performing
inside your app.
Here we're creating
an "order coffee" intent
and defining two of its parameters,
representing the type of coffee item
and its size.
With those parameters defined,
we can set these values
to represent
what the user is actually ordering,
and here, it's a large iced latte.
So, to summarize, the intents you define
are a key building block
that enable your app and the system
to speak the same language.
Now, a key piece
of that intelligent system experience
is learning how people do things
in order to predict
how they might do so again in the future.
But how do we learn?
All it takes is someone using your app,
and as long as you, as a developer,
do something called a "donation"
as people use your app and perform
the tasks that are important to them,
these donations provide signals
that the system can use to learn from.
This happens using on-device intelligence,
and eventually, we'll detect patterns
that help us make predictions,
like the Siri Suggestions
we surface on the lock screen.
And when someone uses
a lock screen suggestion,
not only do they save time,
but we can tell that we did a good job,
and that positive signal helps us make
even better predictions in the future.
So, let's dive deeper
into this concept of donations.
Donations help us answer questions
like when do I order coffee?
Or where does that typically happen?
But time and location
are only a few of the signals that we use
to understand something more important,
which is context.
As JP said earlier, we want you
to feel like you have superpowers.
We pull that off when we match
the task you want to accomplish
with just the right moment.
Now, a donation is simply a record,
a snapshot in time,
of an intent
that's actually been executed.
Maybe today,
your app donates your large latte order
because that's just what you crave
as you start the day.
And a bit later in the day,
you order something more refreshing,
like a lemonade.
But the next day,
you start your morning off again
with another large latte.
And as people continue to use your app,
these signals accumulate over time.
And while there might be changeups,
patterns emerge
and the system can learn them.
Once we learn these patterns,
we make predictions.
We try to match the right task
to your context,
and we get better the more we learn.
And again here,
privacy is at the very core of what we do.
The information you donate
never leaves the device.
The system uses your donations locally
to offer an amazing,
personalized intelligent experience.
What happens on your device
stays on your device.
So, we keep returning to this point
that an intelligent system
should save you time,
but it can only do that
if we drastically reduce
the amount of friction
required to get something done.
A key way we do that
is by accelerating people
to the things they want to accomplish.
So, as a developer, it's important for you
to be prepared to perform an action
even when your app is not running.
When we make a prediction,
we may reconstruct an intent
from the information
gleaned from your app donations.
When our prediction is right
and someone engages with it,
we pass the underlying intent
back over to you
so you can execute it in your app.
Now, your goal is to execute that action,
and there are two ways
you might go about this.
Whenever possible, you should
execute the action in the background.
If you support background execution,
the action is performed
right then and there
and the user doesn't have to switch
between apps.
You even have the ability to display
your beautiful app UI right in this flow.
Here, we're showing a dialogue
to let the user confirm their order
before placing it.
Alternatively, we can launch your app.
Here, you should execute the action
and take the user
right to the relevant part of your app.
In that case,
it's our order confirmation screen.
These were some of the important concepts
you should know about
so your app can take full advantage
of our intelligent system experience.
Now to share more about how teams at Apple
use intents and donations
in greater detail,
I'm going to hand it off
to my colleague Mert
to talk about Shortcuts. Mert?
Thanks, Sofiane.
To illustrate how we use
intents and donations,
I'm going to use an example some of you
might be familiar with called Soup Chef.
We've used this as an example app
for Shortcuts since we launched,
and it's a great way for me
to use the real plural of "soup,"
which is, in fact, "soups."
This app is pretty basic.
You can launch it,
take a look at today's soups
and place an order for one of them.
But let's step back for a second.
What can you do using the Soup Chef app?
You can order one of the available soups,
check the remaining delivery time
for a soup order,
or get your order history.
But how does the app actually get
these features in front of people?
All of these things, this functionality,
is contained in the app itself.
So, to build on
what Sofiane was talking about,
that means I have to stop
whatever it is I'm doing at that moment
to unlock my device, find the app icon,
and maneuver through
some layers of that app's UI,
all just to get soup.
I mean, let's say I'm driving
and I really, really want soup.
This has been known to happen.
I should not reach out to my phone,
launch an app,
and dig around some nested table views.
And, yes, I won't drink my soup
until I'm stationary at some later time.
For that, we have Siri.
We have CarPlay for the car,
HomePod in the home,
or even AirPods when you're on the go.
There's always some device
that can respond to "Hey Siri."
So, stepping back
into the role of the app user,
this is why we often talk about how
Shortcuts can accelerate everyday tasks.
Using my voice to ask Siri to order soup
is mostly convenient
because it makes this thing
I already do easier.
And for someone who's looking for ways
to make their everyday routines easier,
setting up a shortcut
and getting into the habit
of using your voice is very much worth it.
So, whatever that thing is for your app,
that killer feature,
which may even differ
between different people,
that's the thing
you should expose as a shortcut.
And it doesn't need to be limited
to a single shortcut either.
After placing an order
for a delicious soup,
I might want to use Siri
to check the delivery time
until my delicious soup arrives.
So, how can you make this a reality?
As Sofiane described: intents.
For general categories of actions
like sending a message,
we have system-defined intents
that you can adopt.
For describing any other action
unique to your app, like ordering soup,
you can define
entirely custom intents in Xcode.
When you say, "Hey, Siri, order soup,"
Siri runs your "order soup" intent.
And when you say,
"Hey, Siri, check delivery,"
Siri runs your
"check delivery time" intent.
For more on understanding intents,
make sure to check out
the Human Interface guidelines.
It's a great resource for engineers
and designers alike.
For your users, adding custom intents
to Siri in the form of a shortcut
is as easy as tapping on
an "Add to Siri" button.
And the parameters that Sofiane
was talking about earlier,
which describe the important aspects
of the thing that's being done
even appear right here
in the Add to Siri flow.
That's because you can actually change
how this shortcut works
right when you're setting it up.
Let's say I don't actually want
tomato soup every time.
I could change it to clam chowder.
Or, if I'm feeling really wild...
I can leave it empty.
And Siri will ask me what soup I want
every time I order with my voice.
So, once my shortcut
has been added to Siri,
now this flow can happen
without the app needing to be open.
Just ask Siri.
Soup time.
[Siri] I found two restaurants near you.
Which one do you want to order from?
Because voice is a powerful way
to make specific features
of your app quickly accessible,
it's important to provide this
Add to Siri setup flow
in the flows that people already use.
A lot of you developers
already do a great job of providing
Add to Siri flows in your Settings views,
but we all know the best real estate
to getting someone's attention
is while they're focused on your app
to do something.
Setting up a shortcut should never
interrupt that flow, of course.
We're not asking you to sign up
for an email newsletter in a pop-up,
but providing it somewhere
like an order confirmation view
can help people get the most
out of your app.
There is also, of course,
the Shortcuts app,
which is built right into iOS, iPadOS,
and now watchOS.
This is another popular place
for people to set up shortcuts
for your intents,
as well as stringing them together
with other intents from other apps
to do some pretty powerful things,
even automatically.
In the Shortcuts app,
intents can actually take in information
from other apps,
and likewise provide information
back to other apps.
And the people that use your app
can set these kinds of multistep shortcuts
by just dragging and dropping
in the Shortcuts app.
And with that, you can do multiple things
across multiple apps with a single tap.
This may be a somewhat ridiculous example,
but it's going to illustrate
my point well,
so let's go for it.
Here, I have my "order history" intent
from Soup Chef in a shortcut.
This intent returns a list
of the orders I've placed per week
in the past seven weeks.
Below it, I have a great example
of a full-featured intent
from the App Store,
the "new chart series" intent
from the graphing app Charty.
This action consumes the output
of the Soup Chef action,
the weekly number of soups I ordered,
and passes them onto Charty
to make a graph.
Now, when I tap "Run,"
I'll get a chart
of my soup-drinking habits.
Look at that beautiful graph.
Wow. That's a lot of soups.
Again, this example
may not apply to you exactly,
but intents and the shortcuts they power
are incredibly flexible.
Instead of creating a data visualization
of your soup drinking,
and, yes, you drink soup,
you can ask Ari about that,
he manages the Shortcuts team,
you could just as easily hook up an app
that logs your water intake
and visualize it using Charty,
or almost anything else you can imagine.
Also, as Sofiane discussed,
we, the system, can learn and predict
future behavior, too, using donations.
Soup Chef donates its intents
as you use the app.
After a while,
if iOS notices that you order soup
when leaving work on Thursdays,
we can show its prediction
directly in Search.
Or even as an automation suggestion
in Shortcuts
to automatically order soup
when going home.
That's intents in Siri and Shortcuts.
Now we hand it off to Chad
to talk about how system intelligence
works with the brand-new widgets
in iOS 14. Chad?
Thanks, Mert.
Hi, I'm Chad, and I work
on the Proactive Intelligence team.
Today, I'll be talking about
the new widgets in iOS 14,
and how the intelligence of the system
enhances the user experience.
This might sound obvious,
but part of what makes apps so great
is that they provide people
with timely information.
For instance, when I want to check
the weather for my family in New York,
it's as simple as tapping on an app icon,
although I might need to scroll
through a list to find the city.
Or I can open Music to find some tunes.
Let's see. I'll... How about some jazz?
Yeah, that sounds good.
Or if I wanna look at my list
of very important tasks,
I can open the Reminders app
and drill into the list.
Just as in these examples,
there are some pieces of information
that are so important,
you revisit them time and time again.
And that's the problem we wanted to solve
with the new and improved widgets.
Widgets make it super easy
to see the information
that's deep in an app's UI
right on your Home Screen.
It's glanceable, and the best widgets
are also timely and relevant.
As you would expect, tapping on the widget
brings you right to that exact spot
in the app.
Widgets are now backed by intents.
Intents allow people to configure
the exact kind of data
they want shown in their widget.
It allows for more personalization.
The intent is the kind of widget.
In the case of weather,
the "show weather" intent
allows you to pick a specific location
because the location is defined
as a parameter in the intent.
Now let's talk about
another new feature: Stacks.
As you can see,
it's very easy to drag and drop
multiple widgets on top of each other
to create a stack.
But we wanted to make sure
the topmost widget was timely and relevant
using a combination
of intents and donations.
And what's really cool
is that we use donations
to actually rotate the widget
that's on top of the stack.
So, let's say I check the weather
in New York the same time every day,
the system will learn that and...
automagically it flips for me.
As Sofiane mentioned,
donations help us learn
how people use your apps.
And as Mert mentioned,
that can drive things
like Shortcut Suggestions
on the lock screen or in Search.
Similarly,
the way people use your main app
is what drives
this automagical experience.
So, not only are we making it easier
to see relevant information,
if it's something you look for every day,
we eliminate swiping around your phone
to make it even more glanceable.
It's classic "surprise and delight."
If we do our job right,
the user may not even know
that we're doing
all this intelligent calculation
under the hood.
They'll just see that the information
they want is right there
and move on with their day.
The less effort required,
the more successful we've been.
That's all for the new widgets and Stacks.
Now back to Sofiane to talk
about Siri Event Suggestions.
Thank you, Chad.
There are many other technology areas
that build on the same concepts.
With Siri Event Suggestions,
our goal is to make
integrating your reservations
with the system really easy,
and enable people to get
a ton of great benefits along the way.
This feature is also powered
by the Intents framework.
When a user views a reservation,
your app should donate the details
of that reservation to the system.
And we know you interact with customers
through many channels,
like your website or even emails.
So in iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
we're introducing new ways to integrate
with Mail and Safari by using web markup.
These were just a few of the technologies
which leverage these three concepts:
define, learn and execute.
By making friends with the system,
you can meet users where they are,
and make it easier than ever
for people to get things done.
Now I'll hand it back to Mark
to talk about next steps.
Thanks, Sofiane.
We've hammered home a few key ideas.
The intelligent experience we strive for
should make the everyday
easier for people.
It should help you get more value
out of your devices and your apps.
It's about spending your time well,
not spending your time
going through the motions,
even if that motion is a swipe up to Home,
or a tap on an app icon,
or a drill into a detail view.
We want you to experience
your life as it is,
fully in control,
not overly tethered to a device.
Our apps and our devices
feel magical not when they
force you to engage with them,
but when they enhance the things
you do out there in the real world.
But we can't do it on our own.
It's only an intelligent system
if each of its constituent parts works
in harmony, speaks the same language
and helps people solve problems
they didn't even know they had.
As JP put it so well,
we want people to feel
like they have superpowers.
And as developers and designers,
you have the opportunity
to give that to the people
using your apps.
So why don't you?
You'll find links with resources
to other videos,
including how to implement
the technologies you've seen here.
No matter which you choose,
just remember to define
your key features as intents,
donate to the system to power suggestions,
design a great voice experience
for people to use,
but above all,
focus on how you can add value
and make sure that people's time
is well spent.
Thanks for watching,
and I hope
you have a great rest of your WWDC.