Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi there, and welcome to my session,
"Get Your Test Results Faster."
My name is Sean, and I'm an engineer
in the Developer Technologies group
at Apple,
working on the XCTest framework
and its Xcode integrations.
This session is grounded in a concept
called "The Testing Feedback Loop,"
and in case this concept is new to you,
I wanted to briefly take you through it.
After this, we'll be going over
some techniques and features within Xcode
that you can use to speed up
getting results from your tests.
If you've ever written
an automated test before,
there's a good chance
that you have an intuition
of what the testing feedback loop is,
and this is because writing a test
is the beginning of the loop.
The loop then continues
into you running those tests,
usually alongside some other tests.
And then ends up
with you interpreting the results,
and making some decisions
based on what's in your test report.
Depending on your report,
you may decide to write more tests
because there are cases or features
you're interested in covering.
Or you may decide
that you've written enough tests
and the results give you confidence
your code behaves as you expect.
This confidence
lets you move on to other tasks.
Having short feedback loops is important
because that means
you get results from your tests faster.
If your tests are faster, then you can get
confidence in your code faster,
which then means you can
ship features to your users faster.
Now, having gone over
the test feedback loop,
I wanted to let you know
what we'll be going over today.
We're first going to discuss
some features in Xcode 12
that will ensure your tests
always complete.
We'll also talk about how to use
some diagnostics these features surface
to figure out
what may be breaking your feedback loops.
Then we're going to talk about
how you can get
even faster results from your tests
by using the test parallelization options
available to you in Xcode 12.
Now, let's ground this discussion
in a real-world example.
Imagine you're at work,
looking at the results
from a CI job that you kicked off
on Friday before leaving the office.
With a hot beverage in hand,
you realize that your
long-running test suite never finished.
You'd probably feel like
how this person looks--
frustrated and a little upset
that you need to start the week
understanding why
your tests aren't working.
If we don't investigate this problem,
our tests will continue to take longer
and will intermittently not finish,
which is gonna ruin our confidence
in our tests and application code,
and that's gonna hurt
our ability to quickly deliver
new features to our users.
This is a very unfortunate
situation to be in,
but lucky for us, there are some features
in Xcode 12 to help us out.
So, let's look into it.
We're gonna start
with fixing the hang in our test suite,
so we can always
get feedback from our tests.
Right now, the feedback loop is broken.
Because our tests hung and never finished
running, we never got our results,
so we can't interpret them.
We're left to cancel the tests
and forfeit getting a complete
understanding of our code base's quality.
This image is from a result bundle
from that CI job which never finished.
It has an error message
that says testing was canceled
because we had to cancel the CI job,
which isn't exactly actionable.
I'm left wondering what exactly
went wrong in the first place.
Without much in terms of diagnostics
to understand why our tests are hung,
we can try thinking
of a few causes offhand.
A classic example is a deadlock,
where two sections of code are waiting
for the other to make forward progress,
and therefore neither does.
Even if our tests aren't stalled,
their rate of progress may be so low
that they're effectively stuck.
Alternatively, this could just be due
to poorly chosen time-out values
in some application code,
or it could be due
to large amounts of CPU work
that we're doing on the main thread
of our app or framework we're testing.
Available in Xcode 12, though,
is a solution to our problem
of hung tests.
It's a new test-plan option
called "executionTimeAllowance."
executionTimeAllowance
is a customizable feature
that you can opt into
when running your tests.
When enabled, Xcode enforces a limit
on the amount of time
each individual test can take.
When a test exceeds this limit,
Xcode will first capture a spindump,
then kill the tests that hung...
then restart the test runner
so that the rest of the suite can execute.
We know it's not a great experience
to try to guess
at what could be causing
our tests to hang.
After all,
our code base could be large and complex,
and that doesn't lend itself
to being easily reasoned about.
Instead, we'd benefit from having
some better diagnostics given to us
so we can understand
the cause a bit better.
A spindump can help us out here a lot,
and this is why executionTimeAllowance
attaches them to your test report.
A spindump shows you which functions
each thread is spending the most time in.
If our tests are stalled,
a spindump would help us see
what functions the issue may lie in.
It's also possible
to manually capture a spindump
from Terminal using the spindump command,
or from within Activity Monitor
if you prefer a GUI.
By default,
each and every test will get ten minutes.
If a test successfully finishes
before that ten minutes elapses,
the timer will get reset
for the next test.
If you need more time for all tests,
you can customize the default allowance
in your test plan's configuration.
And if you need more time
for a specific test or test class,
you can use
the executionTimeAllowance API
to special-case a particular test
or subclass.
executionTimeAllowance is represented
as a time-interval property
on XCTestCase.
It's important to note
that time-allowance values
will be rounded to the nearest minute.
For values under 60 seconds,
they'll be rounded up to 60 seconds,
and for a value like 100 seconds,
it would be rounded up to 120 seconds,
since that's the nearest whole minute.
Having gone over the new
executionTimeAllowance feature,
let's go through a quick demo
of turning it on
and using the spindump it attaches
to fix our hung test.
I have here in Xcode 12
the test that was hanging in CI.
It's a test called
testUpdatingSmoothiesFromServer.
And it's a test of a method
called fetchSynchronouslyFromServer.
I'm gonna try to reproduce
the issue at my desk here
and I'm gonna do that
by pressing the play button
in the source editor gutter.
Now when I do this, I see the activity
indicator in the Test Navigator spinning.
If this test was working and not hung,
it would execute immediately.
I'm gonna stop the test
because there's no use
in waiting for it to stall.
Now, I wanna turn on
the executionTimeAllowance feature
to get a spindump, so let's do that.
I can do that
by opening the test plan... menu,
clicking the "Edit Test Plan" item,
selecting configurations,
turning test timeouts "on"...
and then rerunning my test
by pressing the play button again
in the Test Navigator.
This will generate
a new report for me that I can use,
and I can view that report
in the navigator.
If I go ahead and I open up
the report that I just generated,
I'm gonna see the same test as failing,
but its failure reasoning is different.
It's gonna say that it exceeded
the test executionTimeAllowance
of ten minutes, which is the default.
And it's also going to attach a spindump.
You can open that spindump
by double-clicking it
and it will open inside of an editor tab.
Spindumps are generally
broken up into two sections--
a preamble, which contains metadata,
and then a series of stack traces
for each thread within the process
that was sampled.
Since we're sampling
our test-runner process,
I know that my test names
should be somewhere in that spindump.
If I do a quick find, I can rapidly find
my test within the stack trace,
and see that it's calling
the method under test
as well as a private helper method.
After that,
I can see that it's acquiring a lock,
and then it's waiting.
This suggests to me that the issue
is in that helper method that we have.
I'm gonna look at the code,
and I'm gonna navigate to the code
by opening up the Smoothie.swift file.
Upon looking at this code,
I can see that in this second method
it's acquiring the same lock
as our method under test,
fetchSynchronouslyFromServer.
It seems questionable to me
that this helper method,
which is just for
performing a Get request,
is acquiring a lock.
And so I'm gonna try deleting
this lock acquisition code from here
to see if that fixes our deadlock.
I'm going to reopen the Test Navigator
by selecting the Test Navigator icon,
and clicking
the play button for our tests.
We see that the test immediately executes,
indicating that we fixed the hang.
Having demoed turning on
time allowances for our project,
let's talk about some ways
you can customize them.
There are two ways you can customize
the default time allowance.
The first, is using the test-plan setting,
which is available in Xcode 12.
And the second,
is using the xcodebuild option.
Once you've enabled time allowances,
there's a precedence order
the configurations follow.
This is so that you can set
coarse-grained defaults
and finer-grained values
for special cases,
such as CI jobs
or long-running test suites.
The TimeAllowance API
has the highest precedence,
while xcodebuild's TimeAllowance option
has the second highest precedence.
A Test plan setting
has the third highest precedence,
and the system default of ten minutes
has the lowest precedence,
and will be overridden
by any of the other three options.
With all of these ways to set
a time allowance, a question emerges,
which is, what happens
if a test requests unlimited time?
There's a way
to prevent this from happening,
and that's by enforcing
a maximum allowance.
Your test is guaranteed
not to exceed this value,
regardless of the configuration you set
in test plans or through API calls.
You can enforce a maximum allowance
either via a setting in the test plan
or through an xcodebuild option.
Having gone over how to use
the new time-allowance features,
we wanted to offer
a couple of recommendations
for how to get the most out of them.
For starters, use time allowances
specifically to guard against test hangs
and ensure you get diagnostics
when they do.
If you're concerned about
keeping your tests fast,
we recommend using
XCTest's performance APIs
to automate testing for regressions
in the performance of your code.
And if you need to identify
what parts of your code are slow,
we recommend using Instruments
to profile and understand
your app's performance.
Instruments provides a rich set of tools
that will give you a lot of info
that can help you figure out
where to begin
adding perf tests to your app code.
If you're interested
in learning how to use Instruments,
check out this talk from WWDC 2019
entitled "Getting Started
with Instruments."
Now, having adopted time allowances,
our feedback loop
has gone from being broken
during the "running tests" phase,
to being complete.
And what's more,
is that we will now always get results
if our tests unexpectedly hang or stall.
We now have the ability
to turn our attention
to the fact that our tests
take a lot of time,
so let's dig into
how we can speed up Fruta's test suite.
Xcode 12 can help us
shorten the loop even more
by letting us run tests
on multiple devices.
This is a test report from Fruta.
We see the results of about a dozen tests
that took between a few hundred
milliseconds to several minutes to run.
Overall, our tests took
just about 13 minutes to run,
with many of these tests taking time on
the order of minutes to complete running.
This is a clue that we would
benefit from parallel testing.
Right now,
Fruta is using non-distributed testing.
That means each
and every test case defined
is executed serially on a run destination,
and that will always take
the most amount of time.
You've likely experienced this
if you have ever pressed Cmd+U in Xcode
with parallelization disabled.
A solution to speed this up is to use
a feature we call
parallel distributed testing.
In the case of
parallel distributed testing,
xcodebuild will distribute tests
to each run destination by class.
Each device will then run
a single test class at a time.
Once a run destination
has finished running a class,
xcodebuild continues to give it a new one
until there aren't any left.
It's very important to note
that the allocation of test classes
to run destinations is nondeterministic.
If you're testing logic
that is device- or OS-specific,
this can lead to unexpected failures
or skipped tests.
When we first added support for
parallel distributed testing to Xcode 10,
the supported configuration matrix
looked like
unit tests on macOS, and unit and UI tests
on iOS and tvOS simulators.
Starting with Xcode 12,
the matrix now looks like this.
You have the ability
to run tests in parallel
on physical iOS and tvOS devices
via xcodebuild.
To enable parallel distributed testing,
set the parallel-testing-enabled flag
to "YES,"
then set the parallelize-tests-
among-destinations flag.
This makes xcodebuild divide your tests
over the destinations you specify.
With just two devices, XCTest's own
tests suites achieved a speed-up of 30%.
Just imagine what this
would do for the Fruta app,
or your app with more devices.
By adopting distributed testing,
we've been able to take our long
feedback loops on XCTest
and shorten them, enabling us to write,
run and analyze our tests faster.
Now, we wanted to offer you
a few recommendations
for how you can leverage
distributed testing in your own tests.
Since test allocation is nondeterministic,
it's ideal to use a device pool
of identical devices and OS versions.
This is so you can avoid
difficult-to-reproduce test failures
that may have been driven out
due to the particular destination
allocation xcodebuild made.
If you are using a device pool
of different devices and OS versions,
then we recommend you prefer distributing
tests that are agnostic to the devices
and OS's they would be running on.
For example, tests for a framework
of pure business logic
are less likely to encounter issues
since they wouldn't be running code
that depended on
destination-specific details.
Lastly, if you're interested in testing
your code against more OS's and devices,
for example, to prove that your
app works with both iOS 13 and 14,
then we recommend you use
Parallel Destination testing.
Destination testing runs the entirety
of a test suite on a given destination,
and does not distribute
the individual tests across destinations.
If you're interested in learning more
about destination testing,
and how tests are allocated, check out
"What's New in Testing" from WWDC 2018.
Now, as a result of focusing on
our test report and using Xcode 12,
our tests will no longer hang or stall,
they'll give us more diagnostics
should a test take an unexpected
amount of time, and they're faster!
In conclusion, we recommend
you use Execution Time Allowances
to ensure your tests always complete
in the event they hang.
Use spindumps for diagnosing
application stalls and hangs,
both for when your tests and app stall.
Use parallel distributed testing
to speed up your tests
by running portions of your suite
on different run destinations.
And use parallel destination testing
to simultaneously run your tests
on more OS versions and devices.
Do this to get faster feedback
on whether your code
is behaving as expected
between different OS's and devices.
Thank you all so very much
for joining me during this session.
We hope your test suites are fast,
that their feedback is actionable,
and that you enjoy the rest of WWDC 2020.