Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I am Yuxin,
an engineer on the Create ML team.
Today, my colleague, Alex, and I
are very excited
to introduce a new template:
Action Classification in Create ML.
Last year,
we introduced Activity Classification,
which allows you to create a classifier
using motion data.
But what if you wanted it to classify
actions from videos?
Cameras are ubiquitous today,
and it's become so easy to record
our own videos with our phones.
Whether we are in a gym or at home,
a self-guided workout
could easily brighten our days.
Other activities, such as gymnastics,
reveal the complexity
of human body movements.
Automatic understanding of these actions
could be helpful
for athletes' training and competition.
This year, we built Action Classification
to learn from human body poses.
Look at the sequence
of this amazing dance.
It would be interesting
to recognize these moves
and even build
an entertainment app around it.
So, what is Action Classification?
First, it's a standard classification task
that has the goal
to assign a label of action
from a list of your predefined classes.
This year, the model is powered by
Vision's human body pose estimation.
And therefore,
it works best with human body actions
but not with actions
from animals or objects.
To recognize an action over time,
a single image won't be enough.
Instead,
the prediction happens to a time window
that consists of a sequence of frames.
For a camera or video stream,
predictions could be made,
window by window, continuously.
For more details about poses from Vision,
please check our session
"Body and Hand Pose Estimation."
Now, with Create ML,
let's see how it works.
Assume we'd like to create
a fitness classifier
to recognize a person's workout routines,
such as jumping jacks, lunges, squats,
and a few others.
First, I need to prepare some video clips
for each class,
then launch Create ML for training.
And finally,
save the Fitness Classifier model
and build our fitness training app.
Now, let's dive in to each step.
My colleague, Alex,
will first talk about data and training
for Action Classification.
Thanks, Yuxin.
Since I can't get to my gym class
right now,
an exercise app which can respond
to how I do workouts
seems like a good way to keep fit.
My name is Alex,
and I'm an engineer on the Create ML team.
Today I'm going to show you
how to capture action videos
and train a new Action Classifier model
using the Create ML app.
Let's start by capturing the actions
on video.
We want our model to be able to tell
when we're exercising
and which workout we're doing.
We need to collect videos
of each of the five workouts:
jumping jacks, squats, and three others.
Each video should contain
just one of the action types
and should have just one human subject.
After taking your video,
if there's extra movement
at the start or end of your video,
you might want to trim these off
in your photo app.
We identify actions using the whole body,
so make sure the camera can see
the arms and legs
throughout the range of motion.
You might need to step back a bit.
Now,
make a folder to hold each action type.
The folder name is the label the model
will predict for actions like this.
If you collected some examples of resting,
stretching, and sitting down,
you could put all these together
in a single folder called "other."
We're now ready for training.
But I want to take a moment
to consider what to do
if we have a different sort of data.
Perhaps someone else
prepared the video for us,
or we downloaded it from the Internet.
In that case, we have a montage.
With a montage, a single video contains
multiple different actions we need,
as well as titles, establishing shots,
and maybe people just resting.
Looking at this video in sequence,
we see periods of no action
mixed with specific actions
we want to train for.
We have two options here.
We can use video editing software to trim
or split videos into the actions we need,
and then put them into folders
like before, or...
we can find the times in the video
where the actions start and stop
and record those in an annotation file
in CSV or JSON format.
Here's an example.
You can find out more
in the Create ML Documentation
on developer.apple.com.
Let's set that aside, though,
and keep going with the exercise videos
we already prepared.
On my Mac, I'm going to start up
the Create ML application.
If you are using Mac OS Big Sur,
it has a new template:
Action Classification.
Let's create an Action Classification
project for our exercise model.
We give it a suitable name.
And I'm going to add a description
so I can recognize it later on.
Our new Action Classification project
opens on the Model Source Settings page.
This is where we prepare for training,
by adding the data we captured
and making some decisions
about the training process.
We're going to need to drag the folder
of videos we already prepared
into the training data source.
Let's take a look at that now.
I've collected all the videos
in a "train" folder,
which has sub-folders named
for each of the actions we want to train.
Let's have a look in the "jacks" folder.
It contains all of the videos
of jumping jacks.
Let's drag that "train" folder
into the training data well.
The Create ML app
checks the data's in the right format
and tells us a little about it.
It says we've recorded seven classes.
That's the five exercises
plus two negative classes:
"other" and "none."
It also says we recorded 362 items.
Videos.
We can dive into this
using the data source view.
Here we can see that each action
has around 50 videos.
That's what you should aim for
when building your project.
Below the data inputs
are some parameters we can set.
There's two I want to talk about here:
Action Duration and Augmentations.
Action Duration
is a really important parameter.
It represents the length of the action
we're trying to recognize.
If we're working with a complex action,
like a dance move,
this needs to be long enough
to capture the whole motion,
which might be ten seconds.
But for short, repeating actions,
like our exercise reps,
we should set the window
to around two seconds.
The length of the action,
also known as prediction window,
is actually measured in frames,
so Create ML automatically calculates
the number of frames, 60,
based upon the frame rate
and action duration.
Augmentations are a way
to boost your training data,
without going out
and recording more videos,
by transforming the ones you already have
in ways which represent
real-world scenarios.
If all of our videos were taken
with a person facing to the left,
then "horizontal flip" generates
a mirror-image video
that make the model work better
in both orientations.
Let's turn it on.
You'll have noticed two other boxes
you can add data to.
These are Validation and Testing.
If you have extra data set aside
to test your model,
you can add that now
to the testing data well.
Create ML will automatically
perform tests on it
when the model is done training.
Machine learning veterans might like
to choose their own validation data,
but, by default,
Create ML will automatically use
some of your training data for this.
Let's hit the "train" button
to begin making our model.
When your Mac is training
an Action Classifier from videos,
it does this in two parts.
First, it does feature extraction,
which takes the videos
and works out the human poses.
Once that's complete,
it can train the model.
Feature extraction is a big task
and can take a while,
so let's dig a little deeper.
Using the power of the Vision API,
we look at every frame of our video
and encode the position of 18 landmarks
on the body,
including hands, legs, hips, eyes,
etcetera.
For each landmark,
it records x and y coordinates,
plus a confidence,
and these form the feature
that we use for training.
Let's go back and find out
how it's getting on.
The feature extraction is going to take
about half an hour,
and we don't want to wait,
so I'm going to stop this training process
and open a project
with a model that we made earlier.
[clicking]
This model's already finished training
on the same data that we used before.
I also added some validation data.
You can see the final report
in the training and evaluation tabs.
We can see how the model performance
improved over time.
It looks like 80 iterations
was a reasonable choice.
The line going up and to the right
and then flattening out
means that training has reached
a stable state.
I can review the performance per class
using the evaluation tab.
This lets me check that the model
will perform equally well
across each kind of action
we want to recognize.
If we added validation or test data,
you could see the results here.
But what I really want
is to see the model in action.
Let's go to the preview tab,
where we can try the model out on
new videos we haven't used for training.
Here's one I recorded
in my garden yesterday.
The video is processed to find the poses,
and then the model classifies these
into actions.
Right now,
it's classifying the whole video up front,
but when you make your own app,
you can choose to stream it
if you're working with live videos
or want a responsive experience.
Let's press "play"
to see what it's detected.
Look out for the label on the video.
You can see the classification change
as the action in the video unfolds.
Let's see it one more time.
You can see that pose skeleton
superimposed over the video.
We can turn that off.
Or we can just watch the pose skeleton
exercising in the dark.
Below the video, we can see the timeline,
which has divided the video
into two-second windows.
Remember when we chose that?
And it shows the best prediction
for each window underneath,
as well as other predictions
with lower probability.
I think we're ready to make a great app
using this model.
For this, I need to export the model
from the project.
And we can do this on the output tab.
On the output tab, we can also see
some facts about the model,
including the size,
which is an important consideration
for assets in mobile apps,
and you can find out what operating system
versions this model is supported on.
Let's save the model
by dragging the icon into the finder.
FitnessClassifier.MLmodel.
And now we can share it with Yuxin,
who's going to show us how to build
an awesome iOS fitness app.
Now we've got a classifier from Alex
to drive our fitness training app.
Let's first check out
how to use the model to make a prediction.
For example,
we'd like to recognize jumping jacks
either from a camera or a video file.
The model, however, takes poses,
rather than a video, as the input.
To extract poses, we use Vision's API:
VNDetectHumanBodyPoseRequest.
If we are working with a video URL,
VNVideoProcessor could handle
the pose request for an entire video,
and pose results for every frame
can be obtained in a completion handler.
Alternatively,
when working with a camera stream,
we could use VNImageRequestHandler
to perform the same pose request
for each captured image.
Regardless of how we get poses
from each frame,
we need to aggregate them
into a prediction window
in a three-dimensional array
as the model input.
This looks complicated,
but if we use the convenient
keypointsMultiArray API from Vision,
we don't have to deal with the details.
Since our fitness model's window size
is 60,
we could simply concatenate poses
from 60 frames
to make one prediction window.
With such a window prepared,
it can be passed to our model
as the input.
And finally,
the model output result includes
a top predicted action name
and a confidence score.
Now let's take a tour of these steps
in Xcode.
This is our fitness training app.
Let's open it.
And this is the Fitness Classifier
we've just trained.
This Metadata page shows us
relevant user and model information,
such as the author, description,
class label names,
and even layer distributions.
The Predictions page shows us detailed
model input and output information,
such as the required input
multi-array dimensions,
as well as the names and types
for the output.
Now let's skip the other app logic
and jump right to the model prediction.
In my predictor,
I first initialize
the Fitness Classifier model,
as well as the Vision body pose request.
It's better to do this only once.
Since the model takes a prediction window
as the input,
I also maintain a window buffer
to save the last 60 poses
from the past two seconds.
Sixty is the model's prediction
window size we have used for training.
When a frame is received from the camera,
we need to extract the poses.
This involves calling Vision APIs
and performing pose requests
that we have already seen on the slides.
Before we add the extracted poses
to our window...
remember that Action Classifier
takes only a single person,
so we need to implement some
person-selection logic
if Vision detects multiple people.
Here in this app,
I simply choose the most prominent person
based on their size,
and you may choose to do it in other ways.
Now, let's add the pose to the window.
And once the window is full,
we can start making predictions.
This app makes a prediction
every half a second,
but you can decide a different interval
or trigger based on your own use cases.
Now let's move on
to make a model prediction.
To prepare the model input,
I need to convert each pose
from the window into a multi-array
using Vision's convenient API,
keypointsMultiArray.
And if no person is detected,
simply pad zeros.
Then we concatenate 60
of these multi-arrays into a single array,
and that's our model input.
Finally, it's just the one line of code
to make a prediction.
The output includes
a top-predicted label name
and the confidences in a dictionary
for all the classes.
In the end,
don't forget to reset the pose window
so that once it is filled again,
we're ready to make another prediction.
And that's everything about making
predictions with an Action Classifier.
Now let's try out this app
and see how it works in action.
I feel some extra energy today
and would like to challenge myself
to a little workout.
Let's open the app...
and hit the "start" button
to begin a workout.
Now my poses are extracted
from every incoming frame,
and predictions are made continuously,
as displayed at the bottom of the app.
That's our Debugging View:
confidence and the labels.
Now, let me get started.
Wow. I finished a five-second challenge.
As you may have seen,
as soon as the model recognized my action,
the timer starts,
and as soon as I stopped,
the model recognized my action
as "other action" class now
and starts to wait for next challenge,
lunges.
I'm ready.
[sighs] I finished lunges,
but I am not in a hurry yet
and would like to take a rest
and drink some water.
Everything happens interactively...
and I don't have to get back
and operate a device,
which is very convenient
for home exercises.
Lastly, let's try squats.
Now all three challenges are finished,
and here is the summary
of my time spent for each.
Wow. That's a lot of exercise for today.
Now we have covered how to train an
Action Classifier in making predictions.
Let's invite Alex back and wrap up
this session with some best practices.
Thanks, Yuxin.
I love the way this application
waits for me to start my workout.
I often need time to remember
how an exercise is done
and maybe which arm or leg is moved first.
Building great features like that
needs great data,
so let's make sure
we get the best performance
out of the athletes, gamers and kids
who bring our videos to life.
Your model will train best
if it's exposed to repetition and variety.
Earlier,
I made sure I had around 50 videos
for each exercise I wanted to classify,
and you should, too, in your apps.
Make sure you train
with a variety of different people.
They'll bring different styles,
abilities and speeds,
which your model needs to recognize.
If you think your users
will move around a lot,
consider capturing the action from
the sides and back as well as the front.
The model does need
to understand exercises,
but it also needs to understand
when we're not exercising,
or not moving at all.
You could create two extra folders:
one for walking around and stretching,
and one for sitting
or doing nothing quietly.
Let's consider how to capture
great videos for the Action Classifier.
Any motion from the camera person
might be interpreted
as the subject moving around,
so let's keep the camera stable using
a tripod or resting it somewhere solid.
The pose detector needs to clearly see
the parts of the body,
so if your outfit blends into
the background, it won't work as well,
and flowing clothing might conceal
the movement you're trying to detect.
Now you know how to take the best videos
for your Action Classifier.
Yuxin, can you tell us how to get the most
out of training in Create ML?
Sure, Alex.
Once you have the data, take a moment
to configure your training parameters.
One key parameter is action duration,
in seconds,
or prediction window size, which is
number of frames in your time window.
The length should match the action length
in your videos,
and try to make all actions roughly
at the same duration.
Frame rate in your video
affects the effective length
of the prediction window...
so it's important to keep
the average frame rate consistent
between your training and testing videos
to get accurate results.
When it comes to using the model
in your applications,
make sure to only select a single person.
Your app may remind users
to keep only one person in view
when multiple people are detected,
or you can implement your own
selection logic to choose a person
based on their size
or location within the frame,
and this can be achieved by using
the coordinates from pose landmarks.
If you'd like to count the repetitions
of your actions,
you may need to prepare
each training video
to be just one repetition
of a single action.
And when you make predictions in your app,
you should find a reliable trigger
to start a prediction at the right time
or implement some smoothing logic
to properly update the counter.
Finally, you can use an Action Classifier
to score or judge
the quality of an action.
For example, your app could use
a prediction's confidence value
to score the quality of an action
compared to the example actions
in your training videos.
So, that's Action Classification
in Create ML.
We can't wait to see the amazing apps
you are going to create using it.
Thanks for joining us today,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.