Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Karoy Lorentey,
and I'm an engineer
on the Swift Standard Library team
here at Apple.
Today, I'm going to talk about
unsafe APIs in Swift.
The standard library provides
many different constructs:
types, protocols, functions, properties,
and so on.
A small amount of these
are explicitly labeled as "unsafe."
What does this mean?
What makes these special?
The distinction between
safe and unsafe constructs
is not apparent
in the interface they provide,
rather it arises from the way
their implementations
deal with invalid input.
Most operations in the standard library
fully validate their input
before executing.
So we can safely assume
that any serious coding errors we may make
will be reliably caught and reported.
One example for such an operation
is the familiar force unwrapping operator
on Swift's Optional type.
It does require that the value
must not be nil,
but if we get this wrong,
we are guaranteed to get
a nice, clean fatal runtime error.
Here, we asked Optional to do something
that is nonsensical,
so stopping execution
is the only responsible thing it can do.
Of course,
trying to force unwrap a nil value
is still a serious programming error,
but its consequences are well-defined.
We say that the force unwrap operator
is safe
because we can fully describe its behavior
for all possible inputs,
including input
that doesn't satisfy its requirements.
So by extension,
unsafe operations must exhibit
undefined behavior
on at least some input that violates
their documented expectations.
For example, Optional also provides
an unsafe force unwrapping operation
through its unsafelyUnwrapped property.
Just like the regular
force unwrap operator,
this also requires the underlying value
to be non-nil.
However, when compiled
with optimizations enabled,
this property doesn't verify
this requirement.
It trusts you
that you only call it on a non-nil value
and directly reads it out.
So what happens
when you accidentally call it on nil?
Well, it reads a value that isn't there,
and it's difficult to say
what exactly this means.
Depending on arbitrary circumstances,
it could trigger an immediate crash
or it may return some garbage value.
Perhaps it will do something else.
It could do the same thing every time,
or its result may change
on every execution.
The point is that by using this property,
you assume full responsibility
to fulfill its requirements.
If you accidentally violate them,
the effects can be unpredictable,
and debugging the problem
may be extraordinarily difficult.
This is the quintessential property
of all unsafe types and operations
in the standard library.
They all have assumptions that they
are unable or unwilling to fully verify.
The "unsafe" prefix is a naming convention
that works a bit like a hazard symbol.
It warns you and anyone reading your code
of the danger inherent in their use.
Interfaces marked "unsafe"
can still be used
to build code that works reliably.
Indeed, some tasks
can only be done using them.
However, you need to be extra careful
when you reach for these,
and you must fully understand
the conditions of their use.
In exchange, though, we get to achieve
something that will be difficult
or impossible to do otherwise.
The use cases of unsafe APIs
typically fall into one of two categories.
Either they provide interoperability
with C or Objective-C,
or they provide fine-grain control
over runtime performance
or some other aspect
of the execution of your program.
Optional's unsafelyUnwrapped property
falls squarely in the second category.
It enables us to eliminate
a superfluous check for a nil value.
This is best reserved
for the most critical parts
of our code base,
where performance measurements indicate
that the tiny, tiny costs
of a potentially unnecessary check
still has a detrimental impact.
To help us sketch potential mistakes,
this property only elides the nil check
in optimized builds.
In unoptimized debug builds,
it still fully validates its input value.
If you ever implement your own
performance-oriented unsafe interfaces,
it is a good idea
to replicate this behavior
because it makes it so much easier
to detect problems during development.
It is important to note
that the goal of safe APIs
is not to prevent crashes.
In fact, it's kind of the opposite.
When they are given input outside
of their documented constraints,
safe APIs guarantee to stop execution
by raising a fatal runtime error.
These situations indicate
serious programming errors.
Our code broke a critical contract,
and we need to go and fix it.
Proceeding with execution
would be irresponsible.
The crash report generated by the error
lets us know the circumstances
of how the problem occurred,
so that we can debug the problem
and correct it.
When we say that Swift
is a safe programming language,
we mean that, by default,
its language and library-level features
fully validate their input.
Any construct that does not
or cannot do this
is explicitly marked as "unsafe."
For instance,
the Swift Standard Library
provides powerful unsafe pointer types
that are roughly on the same level
of abstraction
as pointers in the C programming language.
In order to understand how pointers work,
we have to talk a little bit about memory.
Swift has a flat memory model.
It treats memory as a linear address space
of individually addressable 8-bit bytes.
Each of these bytes
has its own unique address,
usually printed as
a hexadecimal integer value.
Now, at runtime, the address space
is sparsely populated with data
that reflects our app's execution state
at any given moment.
It includes our app's executable binary,
all the libraries and frameworks
that we have imported,
the stack, providing storage
for local and temporary variables
as well as some function arguments,
dynamic memory regions,
including class instance storage
and any memory
we manually allocate ourselves,
and some regions may even get mapped to
read-only resources such as image files.
Each individual item is assigned
a contiguous memory region
storing some sort of data in the same
shared linear address space.
As your app executes,
the states of its memory keeps evolving.
New objects get allocated,
the stack keeps changing,
old items get destroyed.
Luckily, the Swift language
and the runtime
take care of keeping track
of where things are for us.
We generally don't need
to manually manage memory in Swift.
When we do need to do so though,
unsafe pointers give us
all the low-level operations we need
to effectively manage memory ourselves.
Of course,
the flip side of all this control
is the responsibility that comes with it.
These pointers simply represent
the address of a location
somewhere in memory.
They provide powerful operations,
but they have to trust you
that you will use them correctly,
and this makes them fundamentally unsafe.
If you aren't careful,
your pointer operations
may scribble all over the address space,
ruining the carefully-maintained state
of your application.
For example,
dynamically allocating storage
for an integer value
creates a storage location for you
and gives you a direct pointer to it.
The pointer gives you full control
over the underlying memory,
but it does not manage it for you.
Neither is it able to keep track of
what happens to the memory location later.
It merely executes the operations
you tell it to do.
The pointer gets invalidated
as the underlying memory
is deinitialized and deallocated.
However, an invalid pointer
looks just like a regular valid one.
The pointer itself doesn't know
that it has become invalid.
Any attempt to dereference
such a dangling pointer
is a serious programming error.
If we are lucky,
the memory location was rendered
completely inaccessible
by the deallocation,
and trying to access it will result
in an immediate crash.
However, this isn't guaranteed.
Subsequent allocations may have reused
the same address
to store some other value.
In this case,
dereferencing the dangling pointer
may lead to even more serious problems.
Attempting to write through it
may silently corrupt the state
of some unrelated part of our application.
This is bad
because this may have arbitrary effects.
For example,
it can lead to silent corruption,
or even loss of user data.
Such bugs are especially sinister
when the values we access
contain object references,
or when the memory now contains
a Swift value of an incompatible type.
Xcode provides a runtime debugging tool
called the Address Sanitizer
to help you catch such memory problems.
For more information on this
and similar Xcode tools,
see the "Finding Bugs Using
Xcode Runtime Tools" session
from our previous conference.
For a more detail discussion on how
to avoid issues with pointer type safety,
check out my colleague Andy's talk
on this topic this week.
So, if pointers are so dangerous,
why would you ever want to use them?
Well, a big reason is interoperability
with unsafe languages
like C or Objective-C.
In these languages,
functions often take pointer arguments.
So to be able to call them from Swift,
you need to know how to generate pointers
to Swift values.
In fact, there is a direct mapping
between C pointer types
and their corresponding
Swift unsafe pointer counterparts.
C APIs that we import to Swift
get translated using this mapping.
For example,
consider the simple C function
that processes a buffer
of integer values in some way.
When it gets imported to Swift,
the const int pointer parameter
gets translated into an implicitly
unwrapped optional UnsafePointer type.
One way to get such a pointer
is to use the static allocate method
on UnsafeMutablePointer
to create a dynamic buffer
suitable for holding integer values.
Then we can use pointer arithmetic
and dedicated initialization methods
to set up the buffer's elements
to particular values.
And once that's all arranged,
we can at last call the C function,
passing it the pointer
to the initialized buffer.
When the function returns,
we can deinitialize
and deallocate the buffer,
allowing Swift to reuse
its memory location
for something else later.
We have full control
over every operation along the way,
but every step is fundamentally unsafe.
The lifetime of the allocated buffer
is not managed by the return pointer.
We have to remember
to manually deallocate it
at the appropriate time
or it will stick around forever,
causing a memory leak.
Initialization cannot automatically verify
that the address location
is within the buffer we allocated.
If we get it wrong,
we get undefined behavior.
To correctly call the function,
we have to be aware
if it is going to take ownership
of the underlying buffer.
In this case, we are assuming
that it merely accesses it
for the duration of the function call,
and it doesn't hold on to the pointer
or attempt to deallocate it.
This is not enforced by the language,
we have to look it up
in the function's documentation.
Deinitialization only makes sense
if the underlying memory
has been previously initialized
with values of the correct type.
Finally, we must only deallocate memory
that was previously allocated
and which is in a deinitialized state.
At every step,
there are unchecked assumptions.
Getting any one of them wrong
will lead to undefined behavior.
Now, this code works fine,
but it has some questionable choices.
One of these is that the buffer is
represented solely by its start address.
Its length is a separate value
that is duplicated all over.
We could improve the clarity of this code
by modeling the buffer
as a pair of start address
and length values.
This way, the boundaries of the buffer
are always easily available,
so, for example, it becomes possible to
easily check against out-of-bounds access
at any point.
This is why the standard library provides
these four unsafe buffer pointer types.
These come handy whenever we need to work
with regions of memory
rather than pointers to individual values.
By including the size of the region,
as well as location in a nice package,
they encourage best practices
and let you manage memory more carefully.
In unoptimized debug builds,
these buffer pointers check against
out-of-bounds access
through their subscript operation,
contributing a little bit of safety.
However, this validation is incomplete
by necessity.
It is limited to bounds checking.
Like pointers, they cannot verify
that the underlying memory
is in the expected state.
Still, partial checking
is far more helpful
than no verification at all,
and the mere act of considering the length
and the address together as a single unit
already helps preventing
some simple mistakes.
Swift's standard contiguous collections
use these buffer pointers
to provide temporary direct access
to their underlying storage buffer
through these handy unsafe methods.
It is also possible to get a temporary
pointer to an individual Swift value,
which we can then pass
to C functions expecting such.
We can use these methods
to simplify our code,
isolating unsafe operations
to the smallest possible code section.
To get rid of the need
for manual memory management,
we can store our input data
in an array value.
Then we can use
the withUnsafeBufferPointer method
to temporarily get direct access
to the array's underlying storage.
Within the closure
we pass to this function,
we can extract the start address
and count values
and pass them directly
to the C function we want to call.
In fact, the need to pass pointers
to C functions is so frequent
that Swift provides special syntax for it.
We can simply pass an array value
to a function expecting an unsafe pointer,
and the compiler
will automatically generate
the equivalent
withUnsafeBufferPointer call for us.
Remember, though,
that this does not change the fact
that the pointer is only valid
for the duration of the function call.
If the function escapes the pointer
and tries to access
the underlying memory later,
then that will result
in undefined behavior
no matter what syntax
we used to get the pointer.
Here's a list of such implicit
value-to-pointer conversions
supported by Swift.
As we have just seen, to pass the contents
of a Swift array to a C function,
we can simply pass in
the array value itself.
If the function
wants to mutate the elements,
we can pass in an inout reference
to the array to get a mutable pointer.
Functions that take C strings
can be called by directly passing in
a Swift stringValue.
The string will produce
a temporary C string,
including the all-important
terminating null character.
If the C function simply expects a pointer
to an individual value,
we can use an inout reference
to the corresponding Swift value
to get a suitable temporary pointer to it.
Careful use of this feature lets us call
even the most complicated C interfaces.
For instance, here is a C function
provided by the Darwin module
that you can use to query or update
low-level information
about the running system.
It comes with six parameters specifying
the location and size of an integer buffer
serving as the identifier
for the value we want to access,
the location and size of another buffer
where we want the functions
to store the current value,
and an optional, read-only third buffer
containing a new value we may want to set
for the specified entry.
This all looks rather intimidating.
However, calling this function from Swift
isn't necessarily more complicated
as it is in C.
We can use implicit pointer conversions
to great effect here,
resulting in code that is roughly similar
in apparent complexity
as it would be in its native language.
For example, here,
we want to create a function
that retrieves the size of a cache line
for the processor architecture
we are running on.
The documentation of sysctl tells us
that this information is available
under the identifier "CACHELINE"
in the hardware section.
To pass this ID to sysctl,
we can use
an implicit array-to-pointer conversion,
and an explicit integer conversion
for its count.
The information we want to retrieve
is a C integer value,
so we create a local integer variable,
and generate a temporary pointer to it
for the third argument
with another inout-to-pointer conversion.
The function will copy the size
of the cache lines into the buffer,
starting at this pointer,
overwriting our original zero value
with another integer.
The fourth argument is a pointer
to the size of this buffer,
which we can get from the memory layout
of the corresponding integer type.
On return,
the function will set this value
to the number of bytes
it copied into the result.
Because we only want to retrieve
the current value, not set it,
we supply a nil value
for the "new value" buffer,
and set its size to zero.
Sysctl is documented to return
a zero value on success.
We assume that this call cannot fail,
but we do verify this assumption
in case we have made a mistake
in the arguments we supplied.
Similarly, we expect the call to set
as many bytes as there are
in a C integer value.
Finally, we can convert the C integer
to a Swift Int, and return the result.
As it happens, the cache line
is 64 bytes wide on most platforms.
Notice how the unsafe parts
are neatly isolated
into the single function call.
Of course, we could also choose
to expand this code
into explicit, closure-based calls.
It would look something like this.
This code is functionally equivalent
to our original version.
Choosing between the two styles
is mostly a matter of taste.
To be honest, though,
in this particular case,
I think I prefer to go with
the shorter variant.
Whichever version we choose, though,
we need to always be aware
that the generated pointer values
are temporary,
and they get invalidated
when the function returns.
While inout-to-pointer conversions
can be convenient,
they are really only intended
to help calling C functions.
In pure Swift code, we need to pass around
pointers far less often,
so it makes sense to highlight the cases
when we do such things
by preferring to use closure-based APIs.
They might be more verbose,
but I find that their explicitness
makes it easier to understand
what exactly is happening.
In particular, their closure-based design
makes the actual lifetime
of the resulting pointer
far more explicit,
helping you avoid lifetime issues,
like this invalid pointer conversion.
Here, passing a temporary pointer
to a mutable pointer initializer
escapes its value
out of the initializer call.
Accessing the resulting
dangling pointer value
is undefined behavior.
The underlying memory location
may not exist anymore,
or it may have been reused
for some other value.
To help catch these sort of bugs,
the Swift 5.3 compiler now produces
a helpful warning
when it can detect such cases.
Another recent improvement
is that the Swift Standard Library
now provides new initializers
that allow us to create an array
or a stringValue
by directly copying data into
their underlying uninitialized storage.
This gets rid of the need to allocate
temporary buffers
only to prepare such data.
For example,
string's new initializer can be used
to call the same sysctl function
to retrieve a stringValue.
Here, we want to find out
the kernel version
of the operating system we are running on,
which is identified by the version entry
in the kernel section.
Unlike the cache line example,
we don't know the size
of the version string in advance,
so in order to figure it out,
we'll need to call sysctl twice.
First, we call the function
with a nil output buffer.
On return, the length variable
will get set to the number of bytes
required to store the string.
Like before, we need to remember
to check for any reported errors.
With the size of the result on hand,
we can now ask string
to prepare uninitialized storage for us
so that we can get the actual data.
The initializer gives us a buffer pointer
that we can pass to the sysctl function.
The function will copy the version string
directly into this buffer.
On return,
we verify that the call was successful,
we double-check that the function
did actually copy some bytes
to the buffer,
and that the last byte is zero,
corresponding to the null character
terminating a C string.
This null character
is not part of the version string,
so we discard it by returning one less
than the amount of bytes copied.
This signals to the string exactly
how many bytes of UTF-8 data
we have copied into its storage.
By using this new string initializer,
we get rid of the need
for manual memory management here.
We get direct access to a buffer
that will eventually become storage
for a regular Swift string instance.
We don't need to manually allocate
or deallocate memory.
When we call this function,
we get the expected version string.
So, as we have seen, we can use
the standard library's unsafe APIs
to elegantly solve even the most tricky
interoperability puzzles.
In summary,
to effectively use unsafe APIs,
you need to be aware of their expectations
and be careful to always fulfill them,
otherwise your code
will have undefined behavior.
It is easier to do this if you keep
unsafe API usage to the minimum.
It is always a good idea
to choose safer alternatives
whenever they are available.
When working with a region of memory
containing more than one element,
it is best to keep track of its boundaries
by using UnsafeBufferPointers
rather than just a pointer value.
Xcode provides a set of great tools
to help debug issues
with how we use unsafe APIs,
including the Address Sanitizer.
Use these to identify bugs in your code
before putting it in production,
and to debug problems
that may have been uncovered.
And with that, thank you,
and have a great WWDC.