Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome
to the ReplayKit for macOS session.
My name is Johnny Trenh,
and I'm a software engineer
on the ReplayKit team.
Today, I'm really excited to talk to you
about ReplayKit on the Mac platform,
as well as some new, exciting features
for all platforms.
I've got a lot to cover,
so let's get started.
ReplayKit is a framework
that gives you the ability
to record or capture your application's
screen, audio and microphone content
to a video that people can edit,
save and share.
ReplayKit also gives you the ability
to broadcast your application's screen,
audio and microphone
to other third-party broadcast services
to be viewed all over the world.
ReplayKit originally launched for iOS
in 2015,
and in 2016,
ReplayKit for tvOS was introduced.
This year, I'm pleased to announce
ReplayKit is coming to the Mac.
All the great features that are available
to your iOS and tvOS applications
will now be made available
for your Mac applications.
You can now record, capture
and broadcast your Mac application
to everyone in the world.
The main goal in bringing ReplayKit
to the Mac
was to ensure that you have access
to all the great features
that were already shipping
with iOS and tvOS,
along with the same HD quality,
low performance impact
and built-in privacy safeguards.
Now, as you can imagine,
applications work quite differently
on the Mac when compared to iOS or tvOS,
so let's take a look at
the major ReplayKit features in the Mac.
And I'll start with screen recording.
Screen recording gives you the ability
to record your application's screen,
audio and microphone
into a video that people can then edit,
save or share.
How does screen recording work
under the hood?
Well, let's take a look.
Your application
will call into RPScreenRecorder
to get the shared recorder instance.
With the shared instance,
you call startRecording,
at which point,
ReplayKit will start to capture
the screen, audio and microphone samples
from your application,
and start writing those samples
into a movie file.
When your application calls stopRecording,
ReplayKit saves the recording,
calls the preview and share extension,
and passes that information back up
through RPPreviewViewController.
You then present
the previewViewController,
which allows people to edit,
save or share that movie file.
Why don't we jump in
and see how we can start
in-app recording in a project?
So here, I wanna talk a little bit
about our project first.
I'm here on our main storyboard.
So, the main storyboard,
we have three buttons
that are gonna indicate
the different functionalities
that we're going to express
and build out throughout this demo.
We're only gonna focus on
a Start Recording button right now
that you see right here on our storyboard.
So this button is already hooked up
to our code
via IBOutlets and through the storyboard.
What we're gonna look at now
is the IBAction
for what happens
when someone presses this button.
So here in our code, the IBAction
is right here for recordButtonTapped.
We're gonna do two different types
of things with this button.
We're actually gonna have the button
pull double duty for us.
If we're actively recording,
this button's gonna stop recording.
But if we're not actively recording,
this button's gonna start recording
for us.
So let's go ahead and take a look
at what happens when we start recording.
So here is our IBAction,
and we're gonna look at the method
startRecording.
This is very easy.
The first thing you wanna do
is you wanna go ahead
and call RPScreenRecorder
and get the shared recorder instance.
From there, we're gonna go ahead
and call startRecording.
After that, this entire block
is going to be executed right here.
So, the first thing you wanna do,
'cause we're gonna give back an error,
is you wanna see if we have an error.
If we don't have an error,
then we're properly recording,
and everything has started up fine.
So here, we say if there's no error,
all we're simply gonna do
is we're gonna go ahead
and update our recording state.
What do we do when we update
our recording state?
Actually, what we do when we update
our recording state
is we simply set the button
to reflect that.
Are we recording or not recording?
"Start" or "stop," and that's it,
and we update our state.
After that, we are now up and recording.
ReplayKit is now actually
capturing everything
and recording a video for you.
So what happens when your user
taps the button again?
Well, here, we're gonna go ahead
and call stopRecording.
And let's take a look at how that works.
Going down to the stopRecording method
right here,
once again, we're gonna go ahead
and get the shared recorder instance,
and then we're gonna go ahead
and call stopRecording.
When we do that,
the completionHandler block
is then executed.
Now this looks a little bit complicated,
but I'll walk you through it
'cause it's actually really simple.
The first thing I'm gonna do
is check to see if we have an error.
If we don't have an error,
let's check to see if we have
a previewViewController.
Now, this is where it gets
really interesting.
What we wanna do with
the previewViewController is,
like we spoke about,
you wanna display it so people can edit,
save or share their video.
So, we get the previewViewController,
we go ahead
and save a reference to that here,
and then this is the important part,
you want to make sure that you are
a delegate of the previewViewController.
And I'll talk to you about
why that's important in just a little bit.
Then you wanna go ahead
and share the sheet.
In this case,
I'm using mainWindow and beginSheet.
You can share the sheet or show the sheet
however which way you choose using UIKit,
but in this example,
we're gonna go ahead and use beginSheet.
And that's it.
We're gonna go ahead and show the sheet.
We do some error-checking here,
and if there's errors, we print them.
If not, then after that,
we go ahead and set the recording state
because we're no longer recording.
So, let's take a look at what happens
after the user interacts
with the previewViewController.
That's why we wanna be part
of the delegate.
So, I'm gonna go ahead
and scroll down here,
and here is our delegate,
previewViewControllerDidFinish.
This is gonna be called when the user
is done using the previewViewController.
They're gonna go ahead
and click Save or exit out of it,
and that's when you get notified.
So the reason why this is important
is because we wanna keep a reference
to that previewViewController
so that we can dismiss it.
And that's it.
Just like that,
you're up and running with ReplayKit
and recording your application to a video.
Now that you've seen
what it looks like in code,
I wanna take a moment to highlight
some of the differences
with RPPreviewViewController.
People will be able to edit
and trim the recording
by tapping on the Edit button
in the previewViewController.
Saving the video will be
a very familiar experience for people
as it follows the standard
macOS file-save flow.
With just two simple API calls,
you're now up and running
and recording with ReplayKit.
With in-app screen recording,
you and your application
don't have access to the movie file.
ReplayKit handles
the creation of the movie,
and people drive the sharing
and saving of the recorded session.
However, in the past,
I've received a lot of requests
from other developers
about having access to the recorded movie.
I think we finally have an answer
for those requests.
This is how screen recording
currently works.
As you can see, the movie file is created
and saved within ReplayKit,
and your application has no access
to the recorded movie itself.
It is only provided with
a previewViewController
for people to edit and save the video.
But what if instead of ReplayKit
handling the video file,
we give your application
direct access to the video?
You can now do that with our new stop API.
The new stopRecording(with URL
will allow you to provide
a destination URL,
and ReplayKit will write and save
the recorded movie to that URL.
You now have direct access
to the recorded movie,
and you can incorporate them
into your application.
With it, you can create and manage
ReplayKit videos in your application.
You can even create a custom video editor
and have it integrated
right into your own app experience.
These are just some of the new
and exciting experiences you can create
using the new stopRecording API.
But you might be thinking,
"What if I don't want ReplayKit
to make the movie recording for me?
What if I want more control
of my application's video
and audio content?"
And for that,
you can use in-app screen capture,
the next major feature
we've brought to the Mac for ReplayKit.
With in-app screen capture,
ReplayKit will send
the audio and video samples
straight to your application's process,
where you'll have complete control
in how to use them.
Let's go ahead and take a quick look
at how that works.
You've already seen how
in-app screen recording is done
by interacting with
the shared screen recorder instance,
but instead of calling startRecording,
when startCapture is called
on the shared recorder,
ReplayKit will start to capture
your audio, visual and microphone samples
from your application.
However, instead of ReplayKit
creating and managing a movie for you
as we do in recording,
we send all audio and visual samples
back to your application process.
Let's jump back
into our sample code project
and see how we can get started
with in-app capture for the Mac.
Okay, so we're back into our project here,
and once again,
we're taking a look at the storyboard.
Remember, like we said before,
we're building out this demo
so that we can cover all three
of the major functionalities in ReplayKit.
We've already covered
the Start Recording button.
Now we're gonna go ahead
and focus on the Start Capture button,
and let's take a look
at how that looks like inside the code.
So here we have an IBAction
that's tied to the button
from our storyboard.
Just like with recording,
our button's gonna pull double duty.
If we're actively not recording
or broadcasting or capturing,
tapping this button's gonna start capture.
Now, if we are actively capturing,
tapping this button's gonna stop capture.
So let's go ahead and take a look
at what happens
when we hit Start Capture.
Here's our code for startCapture.
Now, it looks a little bit crazy,
but I'll talk to you step-by-step.
Here, we're gonna go ahead
and call ScreenRecorder
and get the shared recorder instance.
From there,
you're gonna call startCapture.
StartCapture is gonna take in
two different handlers.
The first handler is going to be
your sample handler, which we see here.
This block of code is executed
every time ReplayKit gives you a sample,
whether it be audio, video or microphone.
So this block of code is run continuously.
Now, the second handler
is going to be the completionHandler,
which we have here.
Now, the completionHandler
is called only once
when you start capture.
This is much like
the recording completionHandler
where it signifies to you
that capture has started,
and will give you an error
if there's something that happened
in the process.
So, let's take a look
at the completionHandler first,
and then we'll take a look
at what we do when the samples come in.
Here in the completionHandler,
just like with recording,
we're gonna check to see
if we have any errors.
If we don't have any errors,
we're gonna set the captureState
much like we did with the recording.
And what did we do
in the recording captureState?
Well, we set the button title,
our active state internally,
and we disabled the other buttons.
And we set up the cameraView.
Now, we saw this back in
the recording as well.
The cameraView's gonna allow you
to use the camera PIP
to add to your application.
So, what happens when we do have an error?
We're gonna go ahead
and print the error and move forward.
Now let's go ahead
and look at the sample block,
because this is actually
the most interesting bit
because this gets called every time
ReplayKit gives you a sample.
So what you wanna do is,
you wanna go ahead and take a look
at all the different samples
and all the different types
that we give back.
Then you wanna go ahead
and decide what you wanna do with it.
So, in this completion block,
we give you back a sample.
We give you back the sample type
and an error.
And in this block right here,
the first thing we do is we take a look
to see if we have any errors.
If we do, we go ahead and print them.
If not, we're gonna run
a switch statement on the type.
Now, I'm sure in your application,
you're gonna be doing
a lot of really, really awesome things,
but in this application,
we'll keep it simple.
We're gonna go ahead
and go through each one of these types,
and we'll process them separately.
So for if it's a video type,
we'll go ahead
and say processAppVideoSample.
We'll do the same for audio and mike,
and that's it.
These samples are given to you
from ReplayKit,
and then you can do
whatever you need to do with them.
Let's take a look at what we do
in this example, which is pretty simple.
For all of our process methods,
all we do is print.
Now, again, I'm sure you can do something
far more interesting,
and I'm excited to see
what you do with it,
but for this example, we just print,
and that's it.
We're getting all of these samples,
and we print if we get an audio,
we print if we get a video,
and then we print if we get a mike.
And just like that,
you're up and running with capture.
With in-app screen capture,
your application now has access
to all the video and audio samples
through ReplayKit.
You can build dynamic in-app experiences
that include screenshots.
Now that you have access to the samples,
you can add custom gaming overlays
to the videos.
With this raw data, you can even implement
a custom heads-up display like this
for your application.
The possibilities really are endless.
Okay, so now we can record
and we can capture.
But what happens when you're ready
to take things global?
That's what live broadcast is for,
the final major feature we've brought over
to macOS for ReplayKit.
With live broadcast,
you give people the ability to stream
their experience in your application
to a third-party streaming service,
allowing viewers from all over the world
to watch live.
Let's take a quick look
at how live broadcast works,
before we jump into another example
of how to set up a live broadcast.
With in-app broadcast,
you will call into
RPBroadcastActivityController
to display a picker for the available
third-party streaming services.
When people select
a third-party streaming service,
ReplayKit will set up the broadcast
connection to the streaming service
and give back a RPBroadcastController
to your application.
The broadcastController is what you'll use
to control the actual broadcast.
Here is a quick overview
of the three-part process
that will allow you to start
live-broadcasting your application.
People will initiate a broadcast,
and you'll present the broadcast picker.
People will select a broadcast service,
and you'll get back a broadcastController.
Then you'll start to broadcast
using that controller.
Now that we have an idea
of how that works,
let's go ahead and take a look
at how we can do that in a project.
Okay, so we're back in here
in our storyboard.
We've already covered the Start Recording
and Start Capture.
Now we're going to go ahead and focus
on the Start Broadcast button.
This is where things
get really, really cool.
All right, let's jump back
into our Swift code here.
And here we go. We're right here
on the IBAction for the button tap.
Once again, our broadcast button
is gonna pull double duty for us.
If we're active, the broadcast button
is gonna stop broadcast,
and if we're not active,
it's going to start a broadcast.
Let's look at the more interesting bit,
which is starting a broadcast.
And you'll see how easy it is
to actually get your app global
and broadcasting to the world.
All right. Here's our button.
And we're gonna go ahead
and do the presentBroadcastPicker.
Like we covered in the slides,
this is what happens
when your application presents a picker
for the available third-party broadcast
so that people can choose.
Let's go ahead
and jump into that code right here.
And here it is.
Well, first thing we're gonna do
is we're gonna decide
on a picker origin point.
This is the origin point
that is the bottom left-hand corner
of the broadcast picker.
Next, we're gonna go ahead and go
on to the RPBroadcastActivityController
and we're gonna call showBroadcastPicker
at our origin point
from the shared window of our application,
and we're gonna pass in a nil
for preferredExtension
because for now, I just want to show
all the available
third-party streaming services.
All right. When we call that, this block
right here is gonna get executed.
And the first thing we want to do
is check for errors.
If we don't have an error,
this is what we're gonna do.
We're gonna go ahead
and set the activityController
that we give back from this call,
and we're gonna keep a reference to it.
You'll see why this is important later.
And then you're gonna get
an activity controller delegate.
Now, the delegate part
is a really, really important part.
You're going to need to set yourself
as the delegate
or your application as the delegate.
I will explain that in just a little bit.
If we have an error,
go ahead and print it.
So now you're gonna go ahead
and present this picker.
People are gonna go ahead and choose
a broadcast that they want to do,
and then you're gonna want to be notified
when they're done.
This is where the delegate comes in
and why it's very, very important.
Let's go ahead and take a look
at the delegate call.
Here is the broadcastActivityController
delegate...
didFinishWith broadcastController.
So we definitely want to go ahead
and be a delegate here.
And the reason why is when the user
is done picking a third-party broadcast,
ReplayKit will connect your application
to the broadcast extension,
and we're gonna give you back
a broadcastController.
You need the broadcastController here...
because that broadcastController
is what you're gonna use
to actually control the broadcast.
So, in this call, we're gonna go ahead
and check to see if we have an error.
If we don't have an error,
we're gonna go ahead
and save the broadcastController
because the broadcastController, again,
controls your broadcast.
You can pause, you can stop, start.
All of those things are tied in
with the broadcastController.
Then we immediately use
the broadcastController
to call startBroadcast.
Then another block is executed.
This is just like your startRecording.
You call this,
and we give you back an error.
If there's an error,
that means something went wrong,
but if there isn't,
you are now broadcasting
to the third-party streaming service
people have selected.
What we do is update our broadcast state,
like we did with the other ones,
which is going to update our button,
title, our internal state,
and disable the other two
ReplayKit functional buttons.
And that's it. You're now broadcasting.
You are now sending audio and video
to the user's selected
third-party broadcast service.
Now, what happens
when we want to call stopBroadcast?
This is interesting because
when we call stopBroadcast,
right here, this is why we want
to save the broadcastController,
because here we simply call
our reference broadcastController,
and we call finishBroadcast,
at which point,
this entire block will be executed.
Just like with stopRecording
and stopCapture,
it will give you an error
if something has happened.
First thing you want to do
is check the error.
If you don't have an error,
set your broadcast state to false
because we're no longer broadcasting,
tear down your camera
and anything else that you need to do.
And that's it.
You've just started and stopped
a live broadcast with your application,
and you're ready
to take your application global.
I want to take a minute
to go into a little bit more depth
with the differences for in-app
live broadcast that were made for macOS.
If you're coming from iOS,
you'll notice that we no longer interact
with the RPBroadcastActivity-
ViewController class.
Instead, for macOS,
that class has been replaced
with RPBroadcastActivityController.
Due to macOS supporting
multiple screens and windows,
instead of calling
loadBroadcastActivityViewController
like we do in iOS,
for macOS we call showBroadcastPicker
with a CGPoint and a window reference.
We also take in
a preferredExtensionIdentifier
if your application
wants to stream directly
to a specific broadcast service.
The CGPoint passed in
is a reference to the origin point
of the passed-in window
and represents the bottom left-hand corner
for your broadcast picker.
You're now global with your application
using ReplayKit live broadcast.
When you start to implement ReplayKit
in your macOS applications,
you're gonna notice something new
that's been added to your menu bar.
With ReplayKit on macOS,
in keeping with the goal of user privacy,
you'll see a new menu-bar item
shown on the menu bar
every time you start an active recording,
capture or broadcast session.
The menu-bar icon indicates
that there is an active ReplayKit session.
It also serves as a way for people
to stop the active ReplayKit session.
You'll need to make sure that you adhere
to RPScreenRecordingDelegate
method call didStopRecording-
WithPreviewViewController,
as this will be called
when people click on the menu-bar icon
to stop a session.
For in-app capture
and live-broadcast sessions,
the RPPreviewViewController passed in
will be nil.
With that, you're now ready
to add ReplayKit
to record, capture
and broadcast your applications
and share them with the rest of the world.
But we have one last thing
we want to talk about, and that is...
game controllers.
I'm happy to announce
that there is now ReplayKit support
for the Game Controller framework
in iOS, tvOS and macOS.
Game Controller framework will now have
built-in ReplayKit functionality.
Double-tapping the Share button
on the PS4 controller
or the Select button
on the Xbox controller
will start an in-app recording.
Double-tapping again will automatically
stop the in-app recording
and save it to your photos for iOS
and your desktop for macOS.
For applications already using ReplayKit,
game controllers can start
and stop recordings
outside of your application's control.
So, it's a good idea to make sure
you're using key-value observing
for both availability and recording
properties on RPScreenRecorder,
so that you can update your state
as needed.
Also be sure to follow the protocol method
didStopRecordingWith-
PreviewViewController
on the RPScreenRecorderDelegate
so that you can update
your application state as needed.
I'm super excited to be announcing
ReplayKit support for game controllers.
I hope to see it in your games very soon.
Wow. We covered a lot today.
Let's go ahead and take a quick recap
of what we talked about.
I covered in-app screen recording,
where ReplayKit will record
your application's audio and video
into a movie that people can edit,
share and save.
I covered in-app screen capture,
where ReplayKit gives your application's
audio and video samples
right back to you
in your application's process.
I covered in-app screen broadcast,
where ReplayKit sends
your application audio and video
to a third-party livestreaming service.
And finally, I covered
the new built-in functionality
found in Game Controllers framework.
The sample code project,
as well as the documentation
regarding ReplayKit framework,
or to revisit this session,
please visit us at developer.apple.com.
We look forward to seeing you add
ReplayKit to your iOS, tvOS
and now macOS applications.
Thank you so much for watching our session
on ReplayKit for macOS,
and I hope you have a wonderful WWDC.