Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Greetings, racing fans, and welcome to
"Accelerate Your App with CarPlay."
I'm Jonathan Hersh
from iOS Car Experience.
Today, we're going to add an amazing
car experience to your apps with CarPlay.
Buckle up, and away we go.
If you've driven with CarPlay,
you're probably familiar with some
incredible third-party navigation apps,
like Waze and Google Maps.
These navigation apps built their CarPlay
experience with the CarPlay framework,
a set of APIs first introduced in iOS 12.
The CarPlay framework provides
several types of template objects,
which your app can configure
to build an amazing CarPlay experience.
But until now, CarPlay templates have only
been available to navigation apps.
Today, we are thrilled to announce
a brand-new set of CarPlay templates,
plus some amazing improvements
to existing templates,
that together make CarPlay available
to a whole new set of apps
for the first time in iOS 14.
iOS 14 introduces several new templates
for audio apps.
Apple Books has created an amazing
new CarPlay experience for your audiobooks
in iOS 14 with these new audio templates.
If you've built
a CarPlay audio app before,
you're probably familiar
with the playable content API.
In iOS 14,
playable content will be deprecated.
Audio templates open up a whole new world
of possibilities for your audio apps.
We're introducing new templates
for communication apps,
like messaging and calling apps.
We have new templates to drive
your EV charging and parking apps.
And we have new templates that support
quick-service restaurants in CarPlay.
We're going to take a scenic drive
through all of these new templates
in just a few minutes.
But first,
let's review some design principles
that you should keep in mind
while building your app in CarPlay.
CarPlay is designed for the driver,
not for passengers.
Think about optimizing your app
for tasks that make sense in the car.
CarPlay apps are purposeful.
Start with the most common scenarios
in your app
and distill them down to glanceable,
streamlined interactions,
each interaction being a task the driver
can complete in just a few seconds.
Whenever possible,
reuse configuration from your app
to minimize or eliminate any setup
your user has to do in CarPlay.
Your app's first-run experience
should already be completed on-device
before the user starts driving.
And remember, your app may be launched
first in CarPlay, and only in CarPlay.
When the user taps your app
on the CarPlay home screen,
your app will connect to a car scene,
not an iPhone scene.
So it's very important that you eliminate
any logic in your app
that depends on being launched on iPhone.
This is easy to do with UIScene,
and in fact, your app must adopt UIScene
to use the CarPlay framework,
so you'll want to transition away
from the legacy UIWindow
and UIApplicationDelegate APIs.
And with those design principles in mind,
let's take a drive through
new CarPlay templates for audio apps.
And even if you're not developing
an audio app, stay tuned,
because your app
can use some of these new templates too.
I mentioned a minute ago that until now,
if you were building an audio app
for CarPlay,
you would implement
the playable content API.
Playable content is a metadata-based API.
You describe your app's data,
like albums and songs,
and the system assembles
a tree-style UI on your behalf.
Keep in mind that if you want to deploy
your app to iOS 13 and earlier,
playable content and audio templates
can coexist in your app.
On iOS 13 and earlier, the system will
launch your app with playable content.
And in iOS 14,
the system will launch with your CarPlay
templates if you've provided them.
So let's take a look at converting
your playable content app's life cycle
to CarPlay templates.
Now, I mentioned earlier
that you'll need to adopt UIScene
to use CarPlay templates,
and here you can see
just how easy that is.
A key part of adopting UIScene is
declaring a Scene Manifest for your app.
You can add this manifest to your app's
Info.plist as a new top-level key.
This is a sample scene configuration for
the CarPlay template application scene.
You'll want to specify a scene
configuration for your CarPlay scene,
like this example, in addition to a scene
configuration for your app on iPhone.
If you're building a navigation app,
you can also provide a scene configuration
for the CarPlay dashboard.
We're also specifying the name of a class
that serves as the scene delegate
in your app for the CarPlay scene.
Here, we're implementing the class that
we specified in our scene configuration.
This is the connect method from
the CPTemplateApplicationSceneDelegate
protocol in the CarPlay framework.
The CarPlay framework
calls this connect method
when your app has been launched
on the CarPlay screen.
First, you'll probably want to hold onto
this CPInterfaceController object,
because you'll need it later.
And here, I'm setting a CPListTemplate
as my app's root template,
and it's just that easy.
We now have a template on the car screen.
And here, in the disconnect method,
we can release the interface controller
that we were holding.
Let's look at the list template
in a little bit more detail.
We'll start by creating a list item.
Each list item represents a single row
in our list template.
Here, I'm starting with just a title
and subtitle
in a list template with a single section.
When the user selects your list item,
the list item handler will be called.
The handler receives two arguments.
The first is the list item
that was selected,
and the second is a completion block.
When a list item is selected,
your app probably has some work to do.
For example, you might initiate playback
of the item that the user selected,
or you might configure and present
a new template.
After you finish any work,
you must call the completion block.
But if you don't immediately call
the completion block, that's okay.
CarPlay will display a spinner to
let the user know that your app is busy.
When you call the completion block,
that signals to CarPlay that you've
finished processing the user's selection,
and CarPlay will remove the spinner
from your list item.
Also new in iOS 14, we've added
support for dynamic list item updates.
Many properties on CPListItem that were
previously read-only are now writable.
In this example,
it might take my app some time
to fetch an album artwork image
over the network.
Updating my list item to show that image
is as easy as assigning a value
to the newly writable image property
in the list item,
and CarPlay will automatically reload
only the affected rows
in your list template.
It's like magic.
For example,
Apple Podcasts uses these dynamic updates
to keep the progress indicator updated
with your listening progress.
Let's now turn to another new template
in iOS 14,
the tab bar template.
This is a new type of container template.
It can display several of your app's
templates in a tab-bar-style interface
that's instantly familiar
to CarPlay users.
So, let's make a tab bar template.
We'll start by creating two tabs
for the tab bar:
one of them a list template
and the other a grid template.
Here's a list template
to show some of my favorite albums.
In iOS 14, every CarPlay template
inherits some new properties
to let you customize
how that template appears in the tab bar.
You can set the tab's title,
pick a system tab image,
or provide your own custom tab image,
and indicate whether the tab
should show a badge.
We can create a tab bar template
by providing an array of templates,
and each template in the array
becomes a tab on the tab bar.
We can also dynamically update
the tab bar template.
We can add new tabs, remove tabs,
rearrange tabs,
or in this example, we can show and hide
the badge on one or more tabs.
Let's turn now to some new additions
in the list template for audio apps.
Here, Apple Podcasts
is using the new tab bar template
plus some new list item customizations.
You'll find a host of new properties
available in CPListItem for audio apps,
like the playback progress indicator
and the Now Playing bouncing bars.
And here, in iOS 14, Apple Books is using
the new CPListImageRowItem,
which brings this stunning artwork grid
to your audiobooks in CarPlay.
The list image row item
is available for your apps too.
It's as easy as adding the list image
row item to your list template.
So let's try out those new list items.
Here, I'm creating an imageRowItem
to show some recently played audiobooks
in a grid of artwork.
And just like the other list items,
the image row item has
a listItemHandler.
It's called when the user selects
the title in the image row item.
So, in this example,
I might push a new list template
to show even more
of the user's recent audiobooks.
And just like in the other list items,
make sure to call the completion handler
after your app finishes
any asynchronous work.
Each artwork in the grid
is individually selectable,
so in addition to that title handler,
we'll also specify
a listImageRowHandler.
In the image row handler,
we can take some action
in response to the specific audiobooks
that the user selected.
For example,
we might start playback of that book.
Let's turn now to the cornerstone
of your audio app in CarPlay...
the nowPlayingTemplate.
The Now Playing screen
is instantly familiar to CarPlay users,
and with templates, you have even more
control over its appearance and behavior.
Your app can optionally enable
the "Playing Next" button
and the "Album Artist" button.
You may also optionally provide
custom Now Playing buttons
across the bottom
of the Now Playing screen.
Your Now Playing buttons
can use your own custom images,
or you can choose
from several system-provided images
that cover many common playback actions.
The nowPlayingTemplate
is unique among templates,
and it has several special behaviors
that you should keep in mind.
First, the nowPlayingTemplate
is a shared instance.
There's only one instance
of this template in your app.
You should configure the properties
of that shared instance,
and, if you enable the optional
"Playing Next" and "Artist" buttons,
you should add at least one observer
for those button actions.
You should perform that initial Now
Playing configuration as soon as possible,
immediately after your app launches
in CarPlay.
Why?
Because the system may display
the nowPlayingTemplate on your behalf.
For example, when the user taps the Now
Playing button on the CarPlay home screen,
the system will launch your app
and immediately present
the shared nowPlayingTemplate.
When your app becomes the Now Playing app,
the system will also add
the Now Playing bar button
to your app's navigation bar or tab bar.
If the user taps that button,
the system will present
the same shared nowPlayingTemplate.
If a different app
becomes the Now Playing app,
the system will automatically remove
the Now Playing bar button
from your navigation bar or tab bar
in CarPlay.
Lastly,
only the list template may be pushed
on top of the nowPlayingTemplate
in the template stack.
For example, if your app enables
the "Playing Next" button
in the nowPlayingTemplate,
then pushing a new list template
is a great way to show your user
the upcoming playback queue.
So, let's revisit our template life cycle
example from earlier.
When your app is launched in CarPlay,
you'll always want to configure
the shared nowPlayingTemplate instance
immediately,
because the system may be launching
your app just to show Now Playing,
and when your app connects
to the CarPlay scene,
that's a great time to set up
the shared nowPlayingTemplate.
In this example,
I'm configuring a playback rate button
that will call a handler
when the user selects it.
This would also be an ideal place
to enable the "Playing Next" button
and add observers
for the nowPlayingTemplate buttons.
With that initial configuration done,
your app is ready for the system
to present Now Playing on your behalf,
and you can always update
the shared nowPlayingTemplate later.
That was a quick look
at some new CarPlay templates.
We saw the new tab bar template,
a foundational interface
for all kinds of apps in CarPlay,
plus the nowPlayingTemplate and other
list-item updates for audio apps.
Next up, my colleague, Allen,
will take us on a drive
through the other
new CarPlay app categories.
Thanks, Jonathan.
I'm Allen Langmaier
from iOS Car Experience.
Now that we've seen how improvements
to existing templates
will make current apps that much better,
I'd like to introduce a whole new set
of app categories for CarPlay.
Starting in iOS 14,
communication apps can take advantage
of the CarPlay framework
to provide an experience
right on the car's display.
And for the first time,
EV charging, parking,
and quick food ordering
are brand new categories of apps
that can now be brought to CarPlay.
Communication apps are what were
previously known in CarPlay
as Messaging and VoIP calling apps
that traditionally worked
by leveraging SiriKit and CallKit.
Communication apps must continue
to use SiriKit and CallKit
to provide voice and telephony features.
But starting in iOS 14,
they can also take advantage
of the CarPlay framework
to show contacts, organize message lists
and display message status.
Here's an example of a communication app
that makes use of these new features
of the CarPlay framework.
This app uses the new tab bar template,
as we saw earlier,
to intuitively allow the user
to choose contacts and listen to messages.
A common feature of communication apps
is the ability to show
a list of message threads.
Starting in iOS 14,
we are introducing a new list item
subclass called CPMessageListItem
that includes
a number of useful properties
to help create a rich user experience.
For this type of list template item,
handlers are not called
when tapped by the user.
Instead,
Siri will be automatically invoked
using the parameters you specify
in the message list item,
and the user will continue
a message compose, read,
or reply flow through Siri.
On the leading side, you can choose
to display an unread indicator,
a pin, a star, or icon.
Use some or all of these options
to match the capabilities of your app.
And the trailing end can be configured
with a mute indicator, text
and an optional image.
And like other items,
CPMessageListItem
supports dynamic list updates,
allowing you to easily change elements
of a message
just by updating its properties.
Another important feature
for communication apps
is the ability
to show contact information.
The contact template
is a brand new template in iOS 14
that will bring your address book
to the foreground.
In this example, the app has set up
the contact template with an image,
descriptive text, a set of action buttons,
and navigation bar buttons.
Note the template supports up to
three lines of text and up to four buttons
that can individually be configured
with custom images and text.
With all these new features available
to communication apps,
we can't wait to see the experiences
you'll bring to the CarPlay screen.
Now let's look at new app categories
appearing for the first time in iOS 14:
EV charging, parking,
and quick food ordering.
These type of apps
have many things in common.
They're all intimately involved
with the driving experience,
as they help find destinations on a map.
Additionally, these apps make it possible
to check availability,
reserve chargers or parking,
and place orders.
We're excited to introduce
a set of new templates in iOS 14
that enable your apps
to provide these features in CarPlay.
Let's start by looking at an example
of a quick food ordering app.
The app has four tabs across the top
for nearby store locations,
previous purchases, favorites,
and order information.
Notice that the app is streamlined,
and everything is immediately actionable.
There is no detailed food menu,
account management, or other settings.
Focus your CarPlay experience
on providing easy, one-step access
to the most common tasks.
Whether you are looking for
a nearby drive-through,
a charging station
for your electric vehicle,
or a nearby parking garage,
your first task is to identify a location.
iOS 14 includes the brand new
point of interest template.
The point of interest template combines
an interactive map
provided by the MapKit framework
accompanied by an information panel.
Use it to show nearby locations
and let users pick one.
Your app supplies a list of locations
and optional images to show on the map.
The template provides
pan and zoom capabilities
and will notify you
of changing map regions.
To create a point of interest template,
start by constructing a list of up to 12
CPPointOfInterest instances.
Each of these includes a title,
an optional subtitle,
and an informative text that will
be shown on the information panel.
Remember to show only the most relevant
information to drivers in CarPlay.
On iPhone, your app might show
all possible locations,
but in CarPlay, you should limit the list
to those that are most relevant or nearby.
If multiple locations appear
close to each other on the map,
CarPlay will automatically group them.
The point of interest template supports
dynamic property updates
like other CarPlay templates.
Here, to indicate selection,
we have updated the pin image property
of a location to use a different color.
When a location is selected from a list,
you may choose to show a secondary card
for that point,
revealing additional information
and up to two buttons.
These buttons could be used
for a variety of tasks.
For instance, they may signal you
to switch to a navigation app
for driving directions
or push to another template to display
additional information for that location.
Let's take a look
at how to update the template
in response to either
user pan and zoom actions, or movement.
All three of these events will result
in the visible map region changing,
and your app should update the template
with a new list of locations
that correspond to that region.
Start by assigning the template
an object conforming to
CPPointOfInterestTemplateDelegate
so it can be notified each time
the map region changes.
Here we see the delegate method
being defined...
and new locations being computed...
and then passed to the template.
At this time, CarPlay will update
your locations list and map
with the new values.
Next,
let's take a closer look at how your app
may go about managing
all your relevant points of interest.
In the previous slide, we saw the need
to compute new locations for a region.
You may choose to query
your own locations database
or leverage MapKit's
to determine nearby destinations.
Then you'll need to construct a list
of CPPointOfInterest models,
initializing each with the data
from your lookup.
This is where you bring coordinate values,
titles,
and other available data from your app
and make them available to the template.
In this example, the app attempts
to reuse models whenever possible
as an optimization
and to reduce work for the template.
And it's just that easy.
By responding to map region changes
and keeping the template current,
you'll enable your users
to find nearby destinations.
And lastly, let's add one more bit
of functionality to your app.
Having just enabled location browsing,
your users will likely need
to pick one to proceed.
Making use of the optional button
properties of CPPointOfInterest
is a convenient approach
in making locations selectable.
Here we assign
a CPPointOfInterest instance
a primary button that will appear
on the information panel.
As you can see, a "Select" button
is now available for the location.
As noted earlier, the information panel
supports up to two buttons
and several lines of descriptive text
for each point.
The next step
is to assign the button a handler.
The button's handler
will be called when tapped,
and here we're maintaining
both selection state,
in addition to updating annotation images
to make it more clear
which location is selected on the map.
Again, any changes to template properties
will immediately translate
to car screen updates.
In this case, assigning
the selectedIndex of the location
will have the template show the new state.
And that completes our quick tour
of the point of interest template,
taking us from handling map region changes
to making locations selectable.
Now, once the user has chosen a location
or performed a task,
you may need to show a summary
or otherwise finalize the interaction.
The information template is new in iOS 14.
It brings everything together
in a one-stop shop
for displaying text
and receiving user responses.
The information template is created
with a list of labels
that may be configured
in either one or two columns
and a set of footer buttons.
The template can serve many purposes
where full-screen interaction is needed.
For quick food ordering apps,
the information template may be used
as an order summary,
as seen here, or even a confirmation page.
And for EV charging apps,
the information template
can be used to show important information
about a charging station.
That takes us to the end
of this quick overview
of some of the new templates in iOS 14.
The contact template takes
the address book
in your communication apps
to the foreground...
and the point of interest template is
making it possible to build EV charging,
parking,
and apps for quick-service restaurants...
while the information template
ties everything together
by providing the ability to display text
and receive user responses
on the car screen.
We're excited to see all the great apps
you'll come up with making use of them.
And now back to Jonathan
to wrap things up for us today.
Thanks, Allen.
Today, we took a scenic drive
through some new additions
to the CarPlay framework.
If you're working on a navigation app,
then you can use many of the new templates
and improvements we discussed today.
Your audio and communication apps
can now take advantage of new templates,
like the tab bar template,
plus some improvements
to existing templates,
like the list template.
We also introduced
brand new app categories
that are supported in CarPlay
for the first time.
We saw new templates
for EV charging and parking apps,
like the new point of interest template.
Apps whose primary function
is EV charging or parking
can now provide a great experience
in CarPlay.
And if your app serves
quick-service restaurants,
you can add CarPlay to your app
to allow users to easily choose
recent or favorite items
and order them for pickup
or drive-through.
Now, keep in mind
that the car is a special place.
If you have an app in one
of the categories we've discussed today,
then you'll need to apply
for an entitlement
to enable CarPlay for your app.
CarPlay apps must be single-category.
You will need to choose the category
that you are supporting with your app
and use a single entitlement.
The entitlement you choose
will determine which CarPlay templates
are available to your app.
And remember,
if you're building an audio app,
and you want to deploy to iOS 13
or earlier,
that playable content and audio templates
may coexist in your app.
For much more
about CarPlay templates,
check out the updated
CarPlay App Programming Guide
on developer.apple.com/carplay.
This is also where you can go
to request entitlements for your app.
There's also much more detail here
about which entitlements
may use which CarPlay templates.
If you're deploying an audio app
to iOS 13 or earlier,
you may want to revisit
the playable content documentation.
And if you're building
a communication app,
your app must implement SiriKit.
There's a wealth of documentation
and resources available
on the CarPlay developer site.
If you're working
on a navigation template app,
check out our session from WWDC 2018.
Thank you so much for joining us today.
We are so excited to accelerate your apps
onto the car screen
and to see what you build
with CarPlay templates.