Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Roger Pantos.
And today we are gonna talk about
some updates to Low-Latency HLS.
The first thing I'd like to announce
is that Low-Latency HLS
is coming out of beta!
That means it will be available
to everyone
in iOS 14, tvOS 14, and this year's macOS.
That includes support
for bit-rate switching,
FairPlay Streaming, fMP4 CMAF,
and all your other favorite HLS features.
It's available to any native application,
and this year
there's no entitlement necessary.
Also, given that we're finalizing
the Low-Latency protocol,
the time has come to add them
to the HLS spec itself.
So, the second revision draft
of the HLS RFC on ietf.org
now includes all of the rules
for Low-Latency.
And in addition to those rules,
it also includes a couple new appendices
for the Low-Latency Server
Configuration Profile
and describing the CDN tune-in algorithm.
Also, the page that was hosting
the provisional Low-Latency spec
while it was in beta is now being turned
into an informative article
with some more descriptions and examples.
You can find information
about Apple device support
in the HLS authoring spec
on developer.apple.com.
Now, in the year that Low-Latency HLS has
been in beta, we got some great feedback,
and, as a result, we made
some significant changes to the protocol.
One of the areas that we focused on
since the beginning
of the original Low-Latency design
was reducing segment delay.
That's the time between
when a new segment is produced
and when the client begins to receive it.
The approach that we took initially
was to have that segment
ride along with the Playlist update
using HTTP/2 Push.
But one of the biggest areas
of feedback we received
is that the Push approach
doesn't really work
for how a lot of people
deliver their content,
and, in particular, it's not compatible
with how a lot of ad-supported content
gets delivered.
And so we replaced H2 Push
with a new approach
that we call "Blocking Preload Hints."
The basic idea is that,
similar to Blocking Playlist Reload,
the client will ask for the next part
before it's ready
and then the server will hold on
to the request until it can send it.
If you'd like to know more
about Blocking Preload Hints,
we've got an entire talk
where we go into it in more detail.
One of the things
that we're really pleased about
is that Blocking Preload Hints
actually perform better than H2 Push
when you're using a CDN.
And that's because driving the request
from the client
also triggers CDN cache fill
without requiring an extra round trip
between the edge and the origin.
And so that's great for CDNs.
And it's also good that we're no longer
asking them to support Push,
although they do
still need to support HTTP/2.
In addition to moving away from Push,
we made some other improvements as well.
One of the bits of feedback
that we received from the CDN folks
was that allowing a client
to ask for specific rendition reports
could lead to a combinatorial explosion
of different request URLs
that all reference
the same playlist update,
and that reduced caching efficiency.
So we changed the spec to eliminate
the report delivery directive,
and, instead, we now put all Rendition
Reports into every playlist update.
We also heard from providers
who are using lots of date-range tags
with long DVR windows.
So we added a way for them
to incorporate date-range tags
into Playlist Delta Updates,
so the update only carries
the most recent one.
And we go into more detail about that
in our separate video
about Playlist Delta Updates.
Finally, we added gap signaling
to Rendition Reports and Partial Segments
in the form of new attributes
on the Part and Rendition Report tags.
This allows clients to deal better with
encoded outages in Low-Latency streams.
Beyond improving the spec,
we also updated
our server reference implementation.
Now if you remember that from last year,
we have a set of Low-Latency tools
that allow you to generate
your own Low-Latency stream.
Late last year, we added an option to that
to package media as fragmented MPEG-4
so it's compatible with CMAF.
The web server is also
much easier to set up.
Rather than having to configure
your own web server
and then mating a PHP script to it,
you can now just run a Go script
and that will implement
the delivery directives
and an HTTP/2 web server
in a single package.
Finally, we've incorporated
the Low-Latency tools
into the regular HLS tools package.
So now, once again,
there's a single download for everything.
You can find out more about that
in Eryk's talk
about improving stream authoring
using the HLS tools.
So to summarize what's new
in Low-Latency HLS,
we've made several important improvements,
including using Preload Hinting
instead of Push,
improving
the Delivery Directive interface,
and providing CMAF support
in the server reference implementation.
The Low-Latency extensions are now
part of the core HLS spec on ietf.org.
And with all of this in place,
Low-Latency HLS will be available to users
later this year.
So if your users have been asking you
for a lower-latency live stream,
now is the time to act,
and we will look forward to seeing them.
Thank you very much.