Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I’m Eric and along with
my colleague Pınar,
we manage the Retail Store Apps
Mobile Engineering team,
and we're here to discuss
building enterprise applications
that are robust, flexible
and maintainable.
At Apple, we have over 500 stores
where we work to constantly redefine
the retail experience.
Our amazing retail employees are
the heart of our retail operations
and we build the apps that support them...
from our system
that manages store reservations
to our product catalog
and managing store layout.
They all work together
to build a fluid system
that makes our stores run smoothly.
Now you know a bit about
why we do what we do.
The rest of this session
covers how we do it,
and how you can take advantage
of the same practices
in your own enterprise apps.
Our agenda includes
architecting for sharing across apps,
which covers some of the basic principles
you should consider
when either building new apps
or rearchitecting existing apps.
We'll also cover testing your apps
after they've been built.
And finally, Pınar will discuss
some aspects of managing your app
once it's been pushed to production.
When building your apps,
there are many features of iOS that
make multiple apps work together nicely.
I’ll go over a few of them.
Enabling app groups,
benefits of Swift packages
and finding good package candidates.
App groups are one of the first
iOS features that we took advantage of
when developing our suite of apps.
Once enabled, it gave us the ability
to share multiple types of data
via UserDefaults and shared files.
All of the setup can be done
via the Signing and Capabilities section
in your project file within Xcode.
Let’s see how it works.
First, click on the + Capability button
and then select App Groups.
This will add a new App Group panel.
Selecting the plus button in that panel
will add a new App Group
and add it to your developer portal
as well,
so other apps in the same portal
have access to it.
Once you have your app group set up
in Xcode, sharing data is easy.
This example shows how
to share data using UserDefaults.
First, we’ve created
an instance of UserDefaults,
passing it to our app group
to initialize it.
After this initial setup, setting values
is as easy as calling the set method.
Reading values is also just as easy
using one of the named type methods,
such as string, integer,
Boolean, et cetera.
Next, let’s talk about Swift packages.
There are many reasons
we used Swift packages
when looking at our existing apps,
as well as when we build new ones.
The most obvious is that
it reduces code duplication.
This decreases our development time
and the risk of human error,
thus increasing the reliability
of our apps.
It also provides more flexibility
in our organization,
allowing people to move from team to team
easier with less onboarding overhead
since much of the codebase
will already be known.
We’ve also built a team that solely works
on developing these packages,
allowing them to focus more in-depth
on the problems the packages are solving.
After building our iOS apps,
our team identified many areas
that were great candidates.
Just like many of you,
Apple uses standard authentication methods
across our applications.
Because of this,
authentication was a perfect choice.
We’ve built ours on top of URLSession,
and in doing so, it removes the burden
of thinking about auth from the engineer,
allowing them to interact with the server
as if the authentication doesn’t exist.
Another network-related package
is for image caching and fetching.
This allows us to queue images
and cache them to disk as necessary,
again, freeing our engineers
from worrying about
the network connection
or where the image is coming from.
Everything we build is based on UIKit.
We use custom table view cells
and product detail views,
which we package to ensure consistency
where the same UI is used
across multiple apps.
Many of our applications
have similar objects,
such as customers,
reservations and products.
These model objects are prime candidates
for extracting into a Swift package
and sharing across each of our apps,
allowing for standardized definitions
of our model.
The final package I want to talk to you
today about is our scanning package.
We built it on top of
Vision and AVFoundation.
This gives a common look and feel
for our bar code, QR and text recognition
across each of our apps.
Let me show you what that looks like.
Using the Vision framework, our package
is capable of scanning many symbologies,
such as PDF417, DataMatrix and QR codes.
In addition, it also allows us to do
real-time OCR to capture text-based data.
On top of the Vision framework,
we've built a layer that can show
a supplementary UI view
to help the user target the camera,
customize accessibility support,
control the flash,
and simplify configuration
into a clean, common API.
Let’s look at what
a couple of those look like.
Our code uses the same patterns
whether you’re scanning a barcode or text.
The setup is simple.
Initialize the appropriate
view controller,
passing in a struct containing
configuration options
and assign a delegate.
It’s that simple for the engineer.
The delegate handles the messaging
for successes and failures
of the scanning process.
I’ll show you a bit more how that works.
Here, we create an instance
of scan options,
which is a struct that holds
the configuration in our scanning package.
We then initialize
a new barcodeScannerViewController
with that same configuration.
This configuration/initializer pattern
allows us to easily save and reuse them
across each of our apps.
Our next example is very similar
to the first.
Rather than scanning a barcode,
this controller allows us to scan
and recognize text within the view area.
We’ve kept the same
configuration/initializer pattern
as the barcode example,
making it quick and easy
to use either package.
With both of these,
our API provides a default UI
that can be replaced or fully customized
to the needs of each application.
This makes it easy to keep the UI
in all of our apps consistent.
We talked about app groups
and Swift packages.
Now let’s talk about testing.
After our apps were built,
we, of course, needed to test them
to make sure that they did
what we expected them to.
We could have an army of people do this,
but there are more efficient ways
to go about it.
Let's go over a few of
the most common cases.
Three of those are unit testing,
UI testing and performance testing.
Unit testing is the first step
in our testing strategy
and begins with the engineering team.
As they write the classes and functions
that power the apps,
it's important to create unit tests
to make sure that they return the values
that are expected for each code path.
Xcode provides fantastic support
for unit tests with the XCTest framework,
which enables you to quickly write
and run your tests.
For more in-depth information,
there are many sessions available.
I would recommend starting with
"Testing in Xcode"
and "Testing Tips and Tricks."
We use UI testing as much as possible,
as this is where you see
real efficiency gains.
UI testing takes the manual test cases
your QE team has created
and encodes them in Swift.
Xcode comes with XCUITest that provides
a structure for building and running them.
Once we created these tests,
we broke them down by importance.
Tests can take time to run,
so breaking them down by priority
allows us to run the most important tests
more frequently than others.
The more frequent they're run,
the quicker we can catch any failures.
We do this on a check-in, daily
and weekly basis.
The WWDC session "UI Testing in Xcode 7"
is a great place to start for more info.
When we look at performance testing
on iOS devices,
what we’re really looking at
is two things:
rendering performance
and battery performance.
The CPU and GPU in modern iOS devices
are very powerful,
but we still need to focus on
the performance
of every interaction in our app.
There’s nothing more frustrating
for a user
than a view that doesn’t scroll smoothly
or a drag operation
that takes a split second too long.
Battery performance is also
very important for us.
Our devices are on the store floor
all day long.
When an employee has
to step out of the front of house
to take their device
to a charging station,
that’s lost productivity,
not to mention the extra devices
that we have to have on hand.
Engineers have an excellent tool
at their disposal
that makes accomplishing these tasks easy
and straightforward: Instruments.
Instruments is a tool
also built in to Xcode
that has helped us analyze
areas of our apps
that are taking a long time to execute,
have higher than expected memory
or battery usage and much more.
For more information on Instruments,
please check out the sessions "Practical
Approaches to Great App Performance"
and "Improving Battery Life
and Performance."
Now, I’ll hand this off to Pınar
to dive into managing apps
once they’re deployed to production.
Thank you, Eric.
With all the wonderful info
Eric just shared with you all,
you might be wondering how we manage our
apps in production with configurations.
First, I will discuss why we develop
with app configurations in mind.
Then I will discuss points
on backwards compatibility
and requiring users to force update.
There are two configurations
our applications
currently support simultaneously:
Client based configuration file
and a Server based one,
which is essentially Boolean values
downloaded from our server.
Let’s talk about client based
configuration first.
Having a configuration file
that is baked in our client
but hosted on the server,
allows us to have more flexibility
and adaptability
around the user experience
in our application.
These elements can then be manipulated
at the geo, market,
and, in our case,
at the Apple retail store level.
Changing these attributes in production
does not depend on any code changes.
Therefore, no new client builds
would be necessary.
This makes the application
highly adaptable
to our ever-changing business needs.
Our applications also have
server configurations in place
which can also drive the app behavior.
We rely on data from our server
to show certain elements.
This provides a great flexibility
where some features may not be used
for certain geos, markets and,
in our case, certain Apple retail stores.
Our server can simply turn on or off
features based on the global market level.
Just like having a robust client config,
changing values on the server
does not require any code change.
Once config values are deployed
on the server,
changes will automatically be reflected
in our application’s behavior.
Server configurations can also be exposed
to business and operations teams,
where they can take sole control
of the values being set.
They can then turn on or off features
according to the business needs.
This partnership frees up developers' time
to maintain these configs
and allows them to focus on
the engineering instead.
Here’s a high-level illustration
of how these configurations
might work for your application.
With client configuration,
you can create a PLIST file
with all the attributes
you want to include.
Your server can then host this file
in a JSON format.
During your startup sequence,
your application can download
all the attributes that are set.
If, for any reason, during production
you want to change a value
for an attribute,
you can just change it in the PLIST file
and upload a new version
of the config to the server.
When your application launches again,
the new changes will take place.
I will show you how that can be done
in just few minutes with an example.
With server based configurations,
your business or operations teams can
take full control of setting the values.
This way they can turn on or off features
at a global level
and change values to adapt
to business and market needs.
Your iOS application can then
fetch a service API
where these attributes are set,
and these flags will ultimately drive
your application’s behavior.
Let’s dive in to a client-based
configuration as an example.
Here we have all the fields
we want to define for a customer form.
We have First Name, Last Name,
Email, and Phone Number,
and maybe other info that
we'd like to collect from our customers.
These attributes are carefully mapped
in our client code
and remain as generic as possible
in our function definitions.
That way, we can manipulate them
in our PLIST files.
Here's what the form looks like
in our application’s UI in production.
Now, let’s say our stakeholders
do not need to collect
customers’ email addresses any longer
and want to remove that field
from the UI right away.
We can simply delete the Email field
in our configuration PLIST file
and upload a new version
of the config to our server.
When the application is launched again,
the email field is no longer seen.
No code changes, no new client builds,
it just works.
Now let’s say our stakeholders
do not need to collect
customers’ phone numbers either
and needs this change done right now.
We can repeat the same process
and upload the new version
of the config to our server.
And again, when we pull the new config,
Phone Number field is no longer shown.
As you can see,
having a config-driven user experience
allows us to manage
our application in production
with greater flexibility and adaptability.
With server and client hand in hand
and work in such close orchestration,
backwards compatibility is something
we always have to keep in mind
as new changes in the server
may not be supported in our old client
and vice versa.
In our experience,
having config versioning in place
has helped us a great deal
in navigating these waters.
Our application checks which version
of the server and client configuration
that is being downloaded at startup.
We can then determine which
user experience to show, or not show,
to our users.
There are, of course, cases
where we do need our users
to force update to the version of the app,
otherwise they will not be able
to see the new features we developed.
When a new value for an attribute
is added in the client
but server does not have mapping for it,
neither server nor client
can support each other.
In such cases, requiring users
to force update is necessary.
And to wrap up, we covered app groups,
shared frameworks and testing,
we went over utilizing config-driven
user experience,
and, finally, discussed points
in why backwards compatibility
and requiring users
to force updates are necessary.
Thank you for watching.
We look forward to seeing
the apps you develop with iOS 14.
Hope you have an enjoyable WWDC this year.
Stay safe and healthy out there.