Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Nils,
and I'm an engineer
on the iOS System Experience team.
Today I'm going to show you
how to build SwiftUI views for widgets.
First, we'll talk about
how widgets are enabled by SwiftUI.
Then, in the main part of this session,
we're going to build
a widgets view together.
And we'll finish by going over
some of the new APIs
that make building widgets
with SwiftUI awesome.
Let's jump right in.
With SwiftUI and WidgetKit,
you can provide a timeline of views
to be displayed by the Home Screen
at the appropriate time.
Thanks to SwiftUI's adaptability,
you can write a widget
and deploy it to both iOS and macOS.
Because they're
self-contained experiences,
new in iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
widgets are an amazing opportunity
to learn and use SwiftUI,
even if you need to deploy your app
to older versions of our OSes
where SwiftUI may not be available.
I don't know about you, but I've been
drinking a lot of coffee lately.
Some days, a bit too much.
So I created an app to log and track
the caffeinated beverages I drink
and to give me an estimate
of how much caffeine is in my body.
I called it Wired.
I think a widget would be a great addition
to the app,
to be able to know at a glance
at all times how caffeinated I am.
This is what
I want my widget to look like.
First you can see that it's using
my app's visual identity and color scheme.
At the top, we are showing the amount
of caffeine currently in my body,
and at the bottom, the last drink I had
and how long ago that was.
Note that the shape of the background
for the caffeine amount
is concentric with the widget's shape.
Also, I want the duration
at the bottom of the widget
to be updating live to always be correct.
Let's jump to the demo
to see how SwiftUI makes all of this easy.
I've already set up the widget
configuration to read on a timeline
so that we can focus
on creating the views for our widget here.
I'm going to be using SwiftUI
to build this widgets view.
And that means everything I write here
can be used in your app too.
Here is my view.
And here is the preview for it.
I'm using a WidgetPreviewContext
to specify which widget family
I want my preview to display.
In this case, systemSmall.
First, let's define a struct for the data
that is going to drive our UI.
I called it CaffeineWidgetData,
and it has three properties,
for the caffeine amount,
the drink name and the drink date.
I also have a steady constant
for some preview values
that I'm going to use
to make my previews look real.
Let's add the property to our view
to hold this data.
Next, let's update our preview
to use the preview data.
We're ready to start building our view.
Let's start by adding some content.
I'm using a VStack
to stack views vertically.
At the top, I have the word "caffeine"
styled with the body font "bold"
and using a custom color that
I've defined here in my asset catalog.
Below that, I have the amount.
That gets a bigger font
but a similar look.
Because this font is pretty big,
I want to allow it to shrink a bit
if our layout requires it.
That's why I have set
a minimumScaleFactor here.
Next, let's give our widget
some personality
by putting a background color behind it
using a ZStack.
A ZStack allows you to overlay views
on top of each other.
You'll notice that our widget
automatically gets its shape,
size and corner radius from the system.
Now, let's continue building our widget
by adding the name of the last drink I had
and how long ago that was.
For the time elapsed since my last drink,
you can see that I'm using
a new initializer on text
that takes a date and a style
to format it for you.
When using this initializer,
the content will count up or down
from the specified date automatically
as time passes.
This is a great way to make your widgets
feel alive on the Home Screen.
Let's see what it looks like by clicking
the "live preview" button in the canvas.
You can see
that the duration is counting up.
I can even use string interpolation
to add more content to the string.
So I can add the word "ago"
just like this.
And because this is using
string interpolation,
the framework will generate
a localized key for you
so that the format can be adapted
for other locales and languages.
We really have two groups of content here,
as shown by the text color:
this brown text at the top
and this white text below it.
So let's split them into two VStacks
and add a spacer between them.
I'm going to come and click
on this text here
and select "Embed in VStack."
Gonna move this text inside the VStack.
Next, I'm gonna do the same thing
with this text here.
Come and click "Embed in VStack."
And move the second text inside.
And add a spacer between them.
I'm going to make both of my VStacks
leading-aligned.
To do that using the canvas,
I can click the leading button
in the vertical stack section
of the Attributes Inspector.
Here...
and here.
This is starting to get a bit complicated,
so I'm going to extract
the top and bottom parts
into their own subviews.
Because this is SwiftUI, views are cheap,
and I can do this with almost no cost.
I come and click on the VStack here
and select "Extract Subview."
Let's call it "CaffeineAmountView."
Let's add a property to it
to hold some data.
Then I'm gonna do the same thing
to the bottom VStack.
Come and click "Extract Subview."
Let's call it "DrinkView."
And let's also add
the same property to it.
Finally, let's pass in some data.
Things look the same, but we have
better code structure to build upon.
I want my content to be leading-aligned
instead of centered.
I'm going to wrap the content
of the CaffeineAmountView in an HStack
and add a spacer at the end.
Come and click "Embed in HStack."
An HStack, or horizontal stack, allows you
to place views next to each other.
By putting a spacer at the end,
I'm telling the layout system
to push my content to the opposite edge,
the leading edge.
Because I don't need any minimum spacing,
I'm going to specify a min length of zero
so that my content can take as much space
as is available.
Let's add some padding to our content
to make it look better.
Because this is SwiftUI,
I can do this using the canvas
by placing my cursor on the main VStack...
and then clicking
the four checkboxes here
in the padding section
of the Attributes Inspector.
Easy.
You can see that I'm not specifying
a value for that padding.
SwiftUI will use
an appropriate default value
for the device and configuration
it's running on.
I want to emphasize
the CaffeineAmountView,
so I'm going to give it a background.
I'm using the color named "latte"
from my asset catalog.
Let's add some padding again
by clicking the four checkboxes
in the Attributes Inspector.
That's a bit too much.
Let's make it eight.
Okay.
You can see that the corners
of this shape are not rounded.
As described in the
Human Interface Guidelines for widgets,
rounded rectangles are an important part
of widgets' visual design language.
So I'm going to round the corners
of this shape.
I could use a cornerRadius modifier,
like this...
and then try to find a value
that looks good.
But then different devices may use
a different radius for their widgets,
so it can become a bit cumbersome.
We have a much better way to do this
in iOS 14
using the new ContainerRelativeShape.
ContainerRelativeShape
is a new shape type
that will take on the path
of the nearest container shape
specified by a parent
with an appropriate corner radius
based on the position of the shape.
In this instance, the system is defining
the container shape for our widget,
and we get the corner radius
concentric with it super easy.
If I change the value for the padding
of our main VStack,
the corner radius
of the CaffeineAmountView changes
so that the border around it
keeps a constant thickness
around the corner's curve.
Finally,
let's give our most important content
some room to breathe using a spacer.
There. We've implemented the design
that we were going for.
I personally think it looks gorgeous,
and I can't wait to add it
to my Home Screen.
Let's see what my widget looks like
in Dark Mode.
To do this, let me duplicate my preview
and add a modifier to set it to Dark Mode.
Because all of my colors
come from an asset catalog
where I've already defined
dark appearance variants for them,
my widget automatically adapts
for Dark Mode.
My mom drinks a lot of coffee too,
so I'm sure she will be super excited
about Wired.
But this small text at the bottom
may be difficult for her to read.
So let's update our widget
to support dynamic type
so that she and all our users
who prefer larger text can use it too.
First, let's add a new preview
to check what my widget looks like
at a larger size category.
Here, I set the size category
to extraExtraExtraLarge.
It looks great.
Thanks to SwiftUI's adaptive nature,
I didn't have to change anything
to support dynamic type.
And I built a widget that's more inclusive
with no additional work.
Isn't that amazing?
Next, I want to talk about placeholders.
For a great widget experience,
you should provide a placeholder
that the system can use while it's
requesting a view from your extension
or when the device is locked.
Your placeholder should look
just like your widget
but without any specific content.
Let's see how we can modify our view
to also use it as a placeholder.
First, I'm going to create another preview
by copying an existing one.
And I'm going to add
the isPlaceholder(true) modifier to it
to make it a placeholder.
You can see that SwiftUI knows
to automatically replace the content
of all my text with rounded rectangles
and to style them in a way that
matches the content they're replacing.
And if I want to preserve some text
in my placeholder,
I can add
the isPlaceholder(false) modifier to it.
Let's add it to the word "caffeine."
Just like that, I updated my view to
use it as the placeholder for my widget.
Simple, right?
The isPlaceholder modifier
that I just showed you
will be available in a later seed.
You probably know that widgets
come in three different families:
system small, medium and large.
Let's look at how easy it is
to update my widget
for another widget family.
Let's start by adding another preview
for systemMedium.
This looks okay,
but it's a bit of a waste of space.
In my app, I let the user take a photo
of their drink when they log it.
So let's make better use
of screen real estate
by including these photos in our widget.
First, I'm going to add the property
to my data struct
to hold the name of that photo.
And then add a sample photo
from my preview asset catalog.
Let's add the photo to our view.
We only want the drinks photo to appear
on systemMedium.
To be able to create
this conditional layout,
let's add an Environment variable
for the widget family.
I want my photo to appear
next to the existing content,
so I'm going to wrap all our content
in an HStack.
Then, if we are in a systemMedium widget,
and if we have a photo to display,
let's add our image.
And make it resizable.
Awesome.
Finally, let's look at our placeholder
for this size
by adding another preview.
I'm pretty sure
you're starting to get the hang of this.
I'm copying the existing one
and adding a modifier to it
to make it a placeholder.
You can see that SwiftUI knows
to automatically replace the content
of my image with a fill color,
so I didn't have to do any additional work
to create my systemMedium placeholder.
Awesome, right?
And that's how easy it is
to build your widgets views with SwiftUI.
Let me go over two new APIs
that I just showed you in the demo.
First, let's look at how to make corner
radii look beautiful in your widget.
When nesting rounded rects,
most of the time you don't want them
to use the same corner radius.
Instead, you want them to be concentric.
In iOS 14, this is effortless.
Set the new ContainerRelativeShape
as the background for your view,
and SwiftUI will take it from there.
That's almost too easy.
In iOS 14,
we added a new initializer on text
to format a date according to a style.
This allows you to create countdowns,
timers,
and other styles
of absolute and relative dates.
Because this will automatically update
as time passes,
it's a great way to make your widgets
feel alive on the Home Screen.
Let's wrap it up.
SwiftUI enables you to build compelling
widget experiences for your users.
Widgets leverage SwiftUI's
existing support for adaptive layouts.
We've added new APIs
to make it easier to do some things
that we found common in widgets.
Note that these APIs work everywhere,
not just in widgets,
so use them in your apps too.
Be sure to check out
the "Meet WidgetKit" session
to learn more about widget timelines
and also the "Widgets Code-along"
by my colleague Izzy,
to watch him use WidgetKit
to build a widget from scratch.
I hope you had a great WWDC.
Thank you, and see you next year.