Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Holly,
and I'm an engineer
on the Swift compiler team.
Welcome to "Embrace Swift Type Inference."
Swift uses type inference extensively
to achieve concise syntax
without compromising safety in your code.
Today, we'll talk about
when you can leverage type inference,
we'll learn about
how type inference works in the compiler,
and finally,
we'll see how to work with Swift and Xcode
to understand and fix
compiler errors in your code.
Before we dive in,
let's review what type inference is.
Type inference allows you to omit
explicit type annotations
and other verbose details
in your source code
when the compiler
can figure out those details
from the surrounding context.
In this case, there is no type for x
written in the source code,
but the compiler infers
the type of x to be a string
based on the value provided
in the assignment,
which is a string literal.
The type of x
could have been specified explicitly
with a type annotation
using a colon after x
or by coercing the right-hand side
to String using the "as" keyword.
This is a very small example,
but things get much more interesting
when the code leans heavily
on type inference,
like in a SwiftUI project.
Many SwiftUI apps create
large, complex interfaces
by composing small, reusable views,
and this kind of code
relies heavily on type inference
at the call-sites
of those reusable components.
We're going to take an in-depth look
at code in a SwiftUI app
that leverages type inference
at these call-sites.
Then we'll learn how the compiler
solves the type inference puzzle,
and finally, we'll see how to work
with the Swift compiler and Xcode
to understand and fix
compiler errors in the code.
We'll be looking at an app
that I've been working on with my team,
called Fruta, for ordering smoothies.
Currently,
the app shows a list of smoothies,
which you can see on the right
in the Preview.
I want to add a feature
to allow the user to search for smoothies.
Let's take a look at how
the current smoothie list is implemented.
The SmoothieList body
creates a SwiftUI List
from an array of smoothies,
mapping each smoothie
to a SmoothieRowView.
To add a search functionality,
I need to filter the smoothies based on
a string that the user searched for,
so SmoothieList needs a State property
to store this string.
I built a new reusable view
called FilteredList
that is similar to List,
but allows me to pass two additional
arguments to the initializer
that specify how to filter the smoothies.
The first is a KeyPath
to the property on smoothies
that I want to filter by,
and the second is a function
to compute whether the smoothie
should be included in the list
based on that property.
In this case, the smoothies will be
filtered by their title,
and a smoothie will be included
if the title has the searchPhrase
as a substring.
The hasSubstring method does the work
of checking for the searchPhrase
within the title,
and it will also return true
if the searchPhrase is an empty string.
It's not obvious
from looking at the call-site,
but this call
to the FilteredList initializer
leans heavily on type inference.
Let's talk about what causes this code
to rely on type inference,
and how the call-site
leverages type inference for cleaner code.
To understand the incidental details
that are omitted from this call-site,
we need to look at the declaration
of FilteredList and its initializer.
Since FilteredList
is a general-purpose view,
it should work with
any type of data and content
that the client
needs to show in their list.
This flexibility is achieved
using generics.
I introduced three type parameters,
which are placeholders
that will be replaced with actual types
at the call-site.
These actual types,
which are formally called concrete types,
are either specified at the call-site
or inferred by the compiler.
In this case, Element is a placeholder
for the type of element in the data array,
FilterKey is a placeholder
for the type of the specific property
on Element
that the data will be filtered by,
and RowContent is a placeholder
for the type of view to be displayed
in each row of the list.
Now that I have
these three type parameters,
I can use them
in the initializer's parameter list.
Each place that a type parameter appears
in the initializer's parameter list
is an opportunity to leverage
type inference at the call-site
by providing an argument
that gives the compiler a clue
about what the type parameter
should be replaced with.
We'll see how this works later,
but right now,
let's focus on the type of each parameter
as we build up the list.
First, FilteredList will be initialized
with the data to map,
which is an array of Elements.
The next parameter is a specific property
of Element to filter by,
which is a KeyPath
with an Element base type
and a value type of FilterKey.
The next parameter
is the isIncluded closure,
which is a function type
taking FilterKey as input
and returning Bool.
The closure is marked as "escaping"
because FilteredList will need
to store this closure in a property.
The last parameter is a closure
to map a data element to a view,
which is a function type
taking Element as input
and returning RowContent.
The closure is also marked as "escaping"
because it needs to be stored.
Note that this parameter
is marked as a ViewBuilder
to enable the SwiftUI DSL syntax
in the closure argument at the call-site.
The SwiftUI DSL enables you
to declare several child views
by listing them out
in the body of the closure,
and the ViewBuilder
will collect the child views into a tuple
for the parent view to work with.
And this is the full initializer
of FilteredList.
When a FilteredList is initialized,
its type parameters
will be replaced with concrete types.
Let's take a look at this initializer
side by side with the call-site
in SmoothieList
to see how the call-site
leans on type inference.
Notice how clean the call-site is.
There are no explicit type annotations
written at the call-site,
but it still gives the compiler
all of the information it needs
to infer concrete types
for each type parameter of FilteredList.
Let's see what this call-site
would look like
if all of the argument types
were explicitly specified in the code.
We'll use placeholders for type parameters
to see exactly where type inference
needs to fill in a concrete type.
First, the three type parameters
of FilteredList
could have been
explicitly specified at the call-site
in angle brackets after FilteredList.
The type of the first parameter,
which is an array of Elements,
could have been specified
using the "as" keyword
after the "smoothies" argument.
In the second parameter,
Element is the KeyPath base type.
This could have been specified
by writing an explicit base type
in the KeyPath literal
between the backslash and the dot.
The KeyPath type as a whole
could have been specified
using the "as" keyword
after the KeyPath literal.
Next, the type of the isIncluded closure
could have been specified
using a type annotation
in the closure body.
And finally,
the type of the RowContent closure
could have also been specified
using a type annotation
in the closure body.
Now, the initial source code that I wrote
is riddled with a lot of
verbose type annotations,
including a bunch of placeholders
for types that need to be filled in
by type inference.
Instead of figuring out
what these placeholders
need to be filled in with manually,
I am relying on type inference
to figure out exactly
what those types should be.
In other words, type inference
helps you write source code faster
because you don't need to know
exactly how to spell
all of these types in your code.
Let's talk about
how the compiler figures out
what these placeholders
need to be replaced with.
You can think of type inference
like a puzzle.
The type inference algorithm
solves the puzzle
by filling in the missing pieces
using clues from the source code.
Filling in one piece of the puzzle
can also uncover more clues
about the remaining pieces.
Let's see if we can
solve this puzzle together,
using clues from the source code
just like the compiler does for us
with type inference.
First, the "smoothies" argument
could tell us what to fill in for Element,
and we know that "smoothies"
is a property which already has a type.
Using QuickHelp,
we can see that the property
is an array of "Smoothie" elements,
so Element can be filled in
with "Smoothie."
Now that we have filled in
one of the Element placeholders,
we can replace
all of the other Element placeholders
with that same "Smoothie" type.
Now, filling in
the other Element placeholders
uncovered a clue
for the concrete type of FilterKey
because now we know
that the KeyPath literal
is referring to Smoothie.title.
Using QuickHelp again, we can see
that Smoothie.title is a string,
so FilterKey can be
filled in with "String."
And now that we know what FilterKey is,
the other FilterKey placeholders
can also be replaced with "String."
The last piece of the puzzle
is RowContent,
which is the return type
of the trailing ViewBuilder closure.
Since this closure
only has one view in the body,
the ViewBuilder will return
the single child view,
which has type SmoothieRowView.
And once again,
now that we know what RowContent is,
the last placeholder can also be replaced
with SmoothieRowView.
And with that,
we've solved the last piece of the puzzle.
This is the strategy that the compiler
uses to infer types throughout your code.
The code that you write
provides clues for the compiler to use.
And each step of the algorithm
uncovers more information
for subsequent steps to use.
However, it's possible
for one of the clues in the source code
to cause the compiler
to fill in one of the placeholders
with a concrete type that doesn't fit
with the rest of the puzzle.
If one of the pieces doesn't fit
and the puzzle can't be solved,
it means that there's an error
in the source code.
Let's talk about how the compiler modifies
its type inference strategy
to solve the puzzle
in the presence of source code errors.
Then, we'll take a look
at how you can utilize your tools
to understand and fix those errors.
Let's rewind back to where the compiler
inferred the concrete type for FilterKey.
Remember that, in the previous step,
the compiler inferred Smoothie
as the key-path base type,
and it used this information to figure out
the concrete type for FilterKey
by looking up the type of Smoothie.title.
If I had made the mistake
of using the wrong property
in the key-path literal,
the compiler would have tried
to infer the type of FilterKey
to be the type of that incorrect property,
which in this case is Bool.
Then, it would continue to fill in
the other FilterKey placeholders
with that same incorrect type.
Now, if we look
at how this Bool type is used
in the isIncluded closure,
it's clear that this piece doesn't fit
because Bool doesn't have any method
called hasSubstring.
So, the compiler needs to report
what went wrong.
Making mistakes
in the code that we write is inevitable,
and programming languages
and their tools must be designed
to account for our limitations as humans.
The Swift compiler is designed
to catch these mistakes
by integrating error tracking
into the type inference algorithm
to use later on in error messages.
During type inference,
the compiler will record information
about any errors it encounters.
Then, the compiler uses heuristics
to fix errors
in order to continue type inference.
Once type inference is done,
the compiler will report
all of the errors it collected,
often with actionable fix-its
to automatically fix the error
in the source code
or with notes
about concrete types the compiler inferred
that might have led to the error.
Integrated error tracking was introduced
for many error messages
in Swift 5.2 in Xcode 11.4,
and in Swift 5.3 and Xcode 12,
the compiler uses this new strategy
for all error messages in expressions.
Now, we have all had frustrating moments
when trying to fix compiler errors
in our code.
But error messages are designed
to be like a pair programmer
that is built into the compiler
to catch your mistakes
and help you fix them,
rather than allowing you to continue on
with that error in your code.
Let's jump over to Xcode
to see how to work with these tools
to fix errors while writing Swift code.
Before writing any code,
I'm going to open up the Xcode menu
under behaviors,
and click on Edit Behaviors.
I'm going to add a behavior
for when the build fails
to automatically show me
the issue navigator.
Now, I will see all of the errors
across my project
each time my project fails to build.
Here, were looking at
the current implementation of SmoothieList
and its preview.
I've already added FilteredList
to my project
which you can see
in the project navigator.
But before I replace List
with FilteredList,
I need to add a search field
above the list.
I've already added the State property
to store the user's search phrase.
So now, I'm going to add a TextField
above the list in the VStack.
I want the title of the text field
to be "Search"
and I'll pass in the search phrase.
And now I'm going to build using Command+B
to make sure I haven't made any mistakes.
Notice that there is now a compiler error
on the line of code that I just added.
I can expand the error by clicking on it.
And it looks like I used
an argument whose type,
which is "String," isn't compatible
with the expected parameter type
of this TextField initializer,
which is binding.
I made the mistake
of passing the search field value
rather than its binding
and the Swift compiler
was able to figure out
that the binding does
have a compatible type,
providing me with a fix-it
to refer to the binding instead,
using dollar sign.
Next, I want replace this List
with my new FilteredList.
And I'm going to build again
to make sure I haven't made any mistakes.
But it looks like there's another error.
If I expand the error,
I can see it's about
Smoothie not conforming
to the identifiable requirement
of FilteredList.
And this might be a little confusing
because "Identifiable" isn't written
anywhere in this part of the code.
Notice that on the left,
in the issue navigator,
there is a compiler note attached
to this error.
With the new integrated error tracking,
the compiler records information about
what was happening during type inference
when this error was encountered,
which allows the compiler
to leave breadcrumbs
that direct you to look
at other parts of your code
through compiler notes.
These notes can help you connect the dots
between the error that you see
in your source editor
and essential information
from other files in your project.
And you'll be seeing a lot more notes
in Swift 5.3 and Xcode 12.
I want to view this note
side by side with the error,
so I'm going to close the canvas,
which I can do
using the shortcut cmd+enter.
Now, I'm going to hold down
Option and Shift
while clicking on the note
to show the destination chooser.
And now I can arrow over to the right
and hit Enter
to open the file in a new editor.
Now, we are looking
at the FilteredList declaration.
And if I expand the note, it points out
that the compiler inferred
the concrete type of Element
to be Smoothie.
At this declaration,
I can see that Element or Smoothie
is required to conform to "Identifiable."
I must have forgotten
to add this conformance to Smoothie
before trying to use it in FilteredList.
In the editor on the left,
I'm going to cmd+click on Smoothie,
and use Jump to Definition.
And here I can add
the required conformance to Identifiable.
Smoothie already has
a property called "id."
So the requirements of the identifiable
protocol are already implemented.
But just to double-check,
I'm going to build one more time
to make sure that this does fix the error.
And it looks like we're error free again.
Now, let's close the editor on the right,
and hit the Back button
to go back to SmoothieList.
Now, if I use QuickHelp
on one of the arguments
to the FilteredList initializer,
I will be able to see the concrete type
that was inferred by the compiler.
Let's try using QuickHelp on
the key-path literal using option+click.
Just like we saw
when solving the type inference puzzle,
the compiler inferred the type of title
to be a string
based on the inferred key-path base type.
And remember that the compiler inferred
the base type to be Smoothie
based on the Smoothie's argument
on the line above.
Before we finish up, I wanna make sure
the filtering works using the canvas.
I can turn the canvas back on using
the key binding cmd+option+enter.
And I'm going to add a another preview
in the preview provider
that has some text in the search bar.
Now, the preview provider is iterating
over all of the search phrases
that I want to test,
which in this case
are empty string and the string "Berry."
And if I refresh the preview,
using cmd+option+P,
I can see that it works.
I can see the second preview
with "Berry" typed into the search bar
and only the Smoothies with Berry
in their title are showing in the list.
When I made typos
and other mistakes in my code,
error messages from the compiler
were actionable and informative.
Furthermore, the new integrated
error tracking in the compiler
allows the compiler to gather
a lot more information about failures,
which the compiler presents through notes.
These are just a few of the improvements
that you'll find using Swift 5.3
in Xcode 12.
During this session, we learned
that SwiftUI code relies heavily
on type inference
when interfaces are composed
of reusable views.
Next, we saw how type inference fills in
incidental details that are omitted,
by figuring out those details
using clues in the source code.
Finally, we learned about
how the compiler integrates error tracking
into the type inference algorithm
to record more information
and leave breadcrumbs for error messages
which help you understand
and fix mistakes.
To learn more,
you can read the Swift blog post
about the compiler's
new integrated error tracking
called the new diagnostics architecture.
To learn more
about building SwiftUI views,
I recommend following a SwiftUI tutorial
on developer.apple.com.
Finally, check out Swift Generics
from WWDC 2018
for an in-depth look at generics in Swift.
Thank you for watching.