Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to
"Write Tests to Fail."
My name is Kelly Keenan
and in this session,
I'll be sharing
some of the lessons I've learned
over the years of writing user interface
and integration tests for Xcode.
While I'll focus on UI tests,
many of these lessons are applicable
to unit tests as well.
Regardless of whether I wrote my tests
before or after I wrote my code,
my main motivation has always been
to get our tests to green,
because seeing this icon tells me
that my tests are passing,
which means I can ship my product.
However, my new mantra for this year
is write tests to fail,
because great tests catch bugs,
so we should plan for failure.
Tests are written once,
but are triaged many times.
When my tests find a product bug,
it fails,
which is exactly
what they're designed to do.
In my case, my tests all run
in a continuous integration system,
so the tool I have
for triaging the failure
is the test result bundle.
In this session,
we'll explore ways I've found
to make my tests easier to triage
with just the result bundle
as well as ways to make
my tests more robust
so that I'm spending time
triaging the product failures
instead of debugging my tests.
The test templates follow
the testing pattern
of set up, test, and tear down.
Within the test section,
we can break this down into
actions and assertions.
We'll use this
as the agenda for this session.
So, let's start
with the set up for our tests.
This is where I explicitly state
the assumptions I require
and set the state of my app
and environment before I run my tests.
In Xcode 11.4, we introduced
a new setUp function
called setUpWithError which now throws,
allowing me to catch or pass on any
errors that are thrown during my setup.
I found it useful to modernize
my existing setUp methods
to take advantage of the error management.
I use the setUpWithErrors method
to set the initial state
required for my tests before they run
because previous tests
may have changed the state of my app
or modified data that my tests use.
In this example,
I set continueAfterFailure to false
so that my test fails immediately
when an issue is found.
This helps me to find
the first error faster
instead of wading through multiple errors.
I also use this as an opportunity
to launch the app
for each test in this class.
One technique that I've incorporated
is to leverage launchArguments
and environment variables
to set up state within my app quickly.
This should not be used to set all state,
but there may be cases where it's needed,
like bypassing two-factor authentication
during testing.
In this case, I'm using it as a way
to bypass the Menu tab,
and instead, start from the Recipes tab.
Small changes like this
can improve the speed of running my tests
by avoiding unnecessary work,
but more importantly,
it avoids me having to triage failures
that might be happening in the Menu tab
while I'm expecting to see results
for testing my Recipes tab.
To recap, I'm using setUpWithError throws
to improve error handling.
I perform common setup tasks
for every test in the class
like launching the app.
I'm using launchArguments
to communicate with the app to set state.
And I adopt product changes
to quickly setup state and focus testing.
The next step is to run our tests.
Tests should be focused on doing an action
and then asserting
that the action completed.
Let's start with how I can
make my actions easier to triage.
The first thing I consider
is that each test should have
a specific goal in mind.
That goal should be reflected
in the title of the test.
In this case, I'm testing
the ingredients list for accuracy.
The only action my test needs to perform
is to select the Berry Blue Recipe.
Minimizing the actions
makes it easier to triage failures later.
Tapping this row brings up the recipe
and I can verify the ingredient list
as a result of my action.
As such, in my result bundle,
I can easily see
what the test is validating
thanks to the name of my test.
Speaking of naming, over the years,
I've found that the labels
of UI elements change often,
so as a preventative measure,
I use enums for all string values.
That way, when the UI changes,
I can easily update my tests
to react to those changes.
This not only saves me time
to update my tests to UI changes,
it has also minimized the number of times
I've dealt with one test failing
due to a spelling mistake
that was hard to recognize.
Just like collecting all the strings
into enums,
another way that I've minimized mistakes
is by factoring common code
into helper functions,
so that multiple tests
can use the same code path.
In this case, multiple tests need to
access the Smoothie List in the app,
and to select a recipe.
Pulling out this common testing path
means that rather than duplicating code,
I can spend my efforts hardening
these paths to reduce test errors.
Another technique I've employed
is to model the domain of my app
and design a test language
around that domain.
Then my test reflects
the language of my app.
In this example, I can ask my Fruta app
for it's Smoothie List,
and I can do an action on my Smoothie List
like select a recipe,
which returns the Recipe UI element.
These are based on
the FrutaUIElement class I've created
to keep track of the app
and the element at a lower level.
In this way, I've made
my shared code object-oriented-ish.
While testing is treated
as very functional
and based on elements and queries,
I can simulate an object-oriented
environment for readability.
Doing so, gives me the ability
to make calls from my test
that map to how I think of my app,
as a series of subviews.
The result of doing this modeling
is that I'm working with
a reduced hierarchy with each element
and can focus my queries
on just the subelements of that element.
Over the years, our shared testing code
has become quite large.
So, to deal with that,
we treat it like our product code
and have created a shared framework
for our tests.
You may also consider
using a Swift package
to share your testing code,
especially if you're sharing code
between multiple applications.
To recap this section,
I design tests for a specific goal
to focus what I'm testing.
I'm using enums and factoring
common code into helper functions
to simplify resolving UI changes.
I'm modeling objects in my tests
to reflect the UI hierarchy of my app.
And I'm using a framework,
or you can use a Swift package,
to share code between projects.
Now, let's look at my favorite section:
test assertions.
Because this is where we are actually
doing the heart of our testing.
Here are some of the lessons I've learned
with test assertions and error handling
for making test failures
easily triage-able.
One small thing
that has helped me immensely
is to use the optional message
in XCTAssert functions.
Leaving out the message is fine
when I'm triaging tests at my desk,
but when all I have is the result bundle,
there's a lot of context missing.
In this case,
I know that three is not equal to two,
but two what?
If I add a message, I can add context.
Humans are reading
my assertion messages most of the time,
and it's often me,
so I like to leave myself a clue
as to why this expression failed.
However, sometimes, my assertion failures
are read by automation systems,
in which case, I want my messages
to be specific, but not too specific.
So, I leave out things like
date/time stamps or unique file paths
so that assertion messages
can be used to recognize multiple tests
that are failing for the same reason.
I also try to make sure
that I am using the correct assertion
for what I'm trying to accomplish.
Doing so ensures that
the automatic message
that I see when it fails is more relevant.
In Xcode 12, we added XCTIssue
which is a new low-level way
of reporting failures.
For more information,
watch the related video,
"Triage Test Failures with XCTIssue."
One of the pitfalls of asserting that I've
come across is asynchronous events.
I've sometimes had difficulty
triaging asynchronous events.
In this case, I tap the recipe button,
but it may take a while to load
depending on what my code is doing.
If I immediately return
the recipe element,
it may not exist yet.
In the past, I've used sleep
to give my test a little built-in time.
However, I wouldn't sleep on the job,
so why let my tests do it?
And it delays getting my results faster.
XCTest has built-in retries,
but depending on my app code,
it might not be enough.
So, I prefer to use
waitForExistence with a timeout.
This provides polling
so that if the expectation is true
earlier than the timeout,
then I've saved that much time waiting.
It also allows my test
to pass or fail deterministically
in an environment I've designed.
In the result bundle, I'm able to see
that my test waited five seconds
to find the Ingredients View.
Another recommendation
is to unwrap optionals.
In this example, I want to return
the count of the favorites
in a string array that is passed in,
however, I didn't take the time
to unwrap my optional.
When I'm running the code locally,
this results
in a crash and halts my tests,
which is really unfortunate
if I set them to run
while I went to get lunch
and they didn't finish when I returned.
When this happens
in a continuous integration environment,
I get a result bundle
with a failing test that reads,
"Test crashed with signal ill."
I can easily avoid this situation
by making sure that I unwrap my optionals.
I can use the Swift-provided methods
of unwrapping optionals
such as "if let", where I can then use
the unwrapped value in the if-block.
If I want to use
the unwrapped variable later,
I can use "guard let".
This allows me to throw an error
that I provide in the guard-block
if I encounter nil.
The third option is using
the nil-coalescing operator,
which allows me to provide
a default value if I encounter nil,
in this case, an empty array.
The fourth option, is to use XCTUnwrap,
which is provided by the XCTest framework.
It's a simplification of "guard let"
where it throws an error
if my test encounters nil.
Using XCTUnwrap
shows my comment from the call
in addition to the auto-generated message
in my result bundle.
The best part about unwrapping optionals
is that by failing gracefully
instead of crashing,
my tearDown method will be called.
Speaking of failing gracefully,
let's talk about throwing errors.
In my tests, the rule is that I always
throw instead of assert from shared code.
The reason is because the shared code
is being run from many tests,
and in some of those tests, I may
purposely be testing negative test cases
to ensure something hidden isn't shown
or to force an error dialog
to appear for testing purposes.
So, in a case like this, where I have
a shared method to verify the ingredients,
I may be testing a bug where I had
extra ingredients showing previously,
and I'm testing that those extra
ingredients aren't showing up anymore.
So, I throw an error.
In my errors, I often pass in values that
I want to appear in my error descriptions,
which are a requirement
of the CustomStringConvertible protocol.
Using the description function means that
I see a more contextually relevant error
in the result bundle for those times
I'm not triaging my results locally.
If I am triaging locally,
then new in Xcode 12 is the ability
to see the backtrace for errors
directly in my code,
so I don't have to wonder anymore
where the error is actually hiding
in my shared code.
I can also find a backtrace
in the Runtime Issues Navigator
as well as the result bundle.
To learn more about
how to leverage the testing backtraces,
see the related video,
"Triage Test Failures with XCTIssue."
Also in this result bundle,
is a user-readable disclosure group
that my code added to provide more context
of what action I was taking at the time.
I can easily see here that I was looking
for Grape in my Berry Blue smoothie,
which is definitely wrong.
To provide myself
little breadcrumbs like this,
I use XCTContext.runActivity
and provide a name.
This is what appears in the result bundle
along with any actions
performed in its block.
This is a great way to add
some organization and context
to my result bundle
and make it easy to read
according to the actions
my test is taking.
Another thing I can do
with the runActivity
is to add attachments with XCTAttachment.
I can add attachments
like files, images, and data
to my XCTContext or the test case
and it will show up in a result bundle.
It's a great way to gather
extra logging for a failed test
especially when it's coming
from a CI system.
Earlier I said not to add file paths
into assert comments
because instead,
I can add both the file path
and the file itself as an attachment.
This makes it easier
to triage the failures later.
I believe that tests should be responsible
for gathering all the data needed
to triage the product failures
because that data
may not be available later.
Now sometimes, a test shouldn't run at all
and for that I use XCTSkip,
XCTSkipUnless, and XCTSkipIf
for documenting tests that aren't running
by adding the optional message.
The main use is to skip tests
that aren't relevant
to the platform my tests are running on.
Some alternatives
that I've used in practice
are for stubbing out tests
I want to write for a new feature,
which allows me to see
which tests are unimplemented
versus what tests regressed.
The third is that there are sometimes
tests that just can't be fixed for now,
for various reasons,
and I don't want to continue
triaging the failures,
but I also don't want to lose track
of the test by disabling it.
Using XCTSkip allows me to continue to
see the skipped test in the result bundle
so that I don't forget
that I need to write the test
or fix it when the issue is resolved.
To recap this section,
I like to add assertion messages
and use the relevant XCTAssert functions
to add context to the failures
in my result bundle.
I definitely unwrap my optionals
to ensure that my tests don't crash
while I went to lunch,
but also so that my tearDown methods
are called.
I use the waitForExistence method
for asynchronous events
and timing issues instead of sleep.
I throw errors from shared code
instead of asserting
so that other tests using that code
can catch the errors for negative testing.
I use XCTContext.runActivity
and attachments
for adding more context
and content to my result bundles.
And I use XCTSkip for tests
that just aren't expected to be running
in the current scenario.
Lastly, let's look at tear down.
Since most of my work is already done,
there are only three recommendations
I have for tear down.
The first is that I've modernized my tests
to use tearDownWithError that throws
to take advantage
of the new error management.
I use the tearDown method
as a time to collect additional logging,
including some analysis of the failures.
And this is when I reset the environment
from the changes I made during setup.
To recap this video,
we looked at set up,
where I change the environment
and confirm my assumptions
needed for my test.
Test actions are where I perform
the necessary actions I want to test
through shared code modeled after my app.
I then verify
that the actions completed properly
by using helper methods,
errors, and test assertions.
Then, I finished with the tearDown method
to gather data and clean up after my test.
I hope that these techniques
and recommendations
help you to make your tests more robust
and to easily and quickly
triage your product issues
so that your tests turn green
and you can ship a quality product.
Thank you.