Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Izzy.
I'm an engineer
on the iOS System Experience team.
Thanks for joining me.
Let's take a look at today's agenda.
We'll talk about widget families
and what they are.
If you built a watchOS complication
before, this will sound familiar.
We'll cover timelines
and how to update them.
We'll go over how to make a widget
user configurable.
We'll talk about how a widget can link
to content in its app.
And we'll update our widget
to do all of this.
It sounds like a lot,
but the power of SwiftUI
combined with WidgetKit
really makes each step
simple and straightforward.
There are three families
provided by WidgetKit,
systemSmall, systemMedium,
and systemLarge.
If you've built a complication before,
these are the same in concept
as complication families.
As we saw in Part 1,
the timeline provider
is the engine of the widget.
We returned one entry from our provider...
but we could have returned many.
The big question
is what happens at the end?
How do we provide more entries?
The answer is that we pick
a TimelineReloadPolicy.
The first one, atEnd,
tells WidgetKit that when the last entry
of a timeline is displayed,
to start scheduling an update.
When that update happens,
our timeline method will be called again,
allowing us to return more entries.
Similarly, "after" tells WidgetKit
to start scheduling an update
at the date provided.
Let's say we passed in
an after date of 10:00 PM.
Then, WidgetKit will schedule an update
for 10:00 PM,
regardless of how far in the future
or past other entries in the timeline are.
Our last option is "never."
"Never" means that the system
will not independently update a widget.
It is up to us
to explicitly tell the widget
when to reload via the widget center API.
Note that there may be many timelines
active in the system at a time,
each with its own reload policy.
In order to provide
the best user experience,
and provide widgets updates
as close to when the user
will see them as possible,
the system intelligently
schedules updates.
This means "atEnd" and "after"
represent the earliest times
a widget can be refreshed.
Widgets can be configurable
right on the Home Screen.
WidgetKit configuration
is driven by SiriKit,
which means that
just by having configuration,
our widget is eligible
for intelligent system behaviors.
The core technology for configuration
is INIntents,
specifically custom intents.
For a deep dive into these subjects,
see the configuration
and intelligence presentation
from this year's WWDC.
Widgets do not have animation
or custom interactions,
but we can deep link from our widget
into our app.
SystemSmall widgets
are one large tap area,
while systemMedium and systemLarge
can use the new SwiftUI link API
to create tappable zones
within the widget.
This session is a code-along.
We're picking up from where we left off
on the first widgets code-along session,
so if you've been following along so far,
you're in the right spot.
If not, don't worry,
you can pick up from the Part 2 target
in the sample project.
Since we're covering a lot of subjects
in this session, I've made a checklist.
We're starting in Part 2,
so let's jump in.
[clicks mouse]
In our previous session, we limited
our widget to just systemSmall.
I have an idea for how to update it
to work in the medium size as well,
so let's do that.
First, we need to update
our supported families.
So we need to support systemSmall,
and systemMedium.
Now, we need to know which family
our view is being drawn in.
WidgetKit provides a widgetFamily
environment value that we can use.
Now, we can just switch over that family
and decide which view we want to return.
We can move our AvatarView.
So for systemSmall,
we're returning our same AvatarView,
and in our other case,
we'll return something new.
I used a snippet here,
but this is just the same AvatarView
we were using before
in an HStack with some text next to it,
and that text is our character's bio.
In order to add a little bit
of visual interest,
I've added a background color as well.
So let's go ahead and do that
for our systemSmall.
I like using this trick
where I embed in an HStack,
but I don't actually want an HStack.
I want a ZStack.
So we can just use
the embed in HStack shortcut
and change that to a ZStack
and add a background color the same way.
And now that we have a background color,
we need a foreground color as well.
So let's take a look
at what that looks like in our preview.
So notice in our preview,
we're returning our AvatarView.
But our entry actually returns two
different views based on widgetFamily.
So let's just return
our entry view directly instead.
We'll want to update both our placeholder
and our primary at the same time.
You'll notice that our PlaceholderView...
is always returning an AvatarView
like our preview was.
Instead, we want it to return
our EntryView the same way.
So let's look at that in our preview.
Great. Now we have a medium-size view,
and our preview was automatically updated
to reflect the new content.
Let's Build and Run this,
and see it in action.
[clicks]
Here's our Emoji Rangers app that we love.
And now, when I go to the widget gallery,
I can add a small or a medium widget
to my Home Screen.
So that's families.
Let's talk about timelines for a second.
Like we talked about earlier,
WidgetKit is trying to schedule
all the widgets on the system
at the same time.
And we're sitting here asking to reload
when we don't even need to.
We know our character's healing over time.
We even know exactly
when they will be fully healed.
There's a timer right there.
What we can do is generate a full timeline
out until the character's healed,
and we can fill that timeline
with more entries
than would have been fetched otherwise.
That sounds ideal, so let's do that.
I use a snippet,
and I hope you're following along,
so I'll cover each line while you type.
First, we have our selectedCharacter,
and we have the endDate we know
when our character will be fully healed.
We're going to provide updates
on one-minute intervals,
and we're going to start
at the currentDate.
We start with an empty array of entries.
And while our currentDate
hasn't yet reached our endDate,
we create a new entry
with the currentDate,
step the currentDate forward
by one minute,
and add that entry.
So now, we have a full timeline
and WidgetKit won't attempt to reload us
until that timeline is exhausted.
We talked about intelligent
system behavior before.
One thing that means
is if our widget is in a stack,
the system can intelligently rotate to it.
We can give the system hints about times
we think it should prioritize our widget
using "relevance."
You may have noticed relevance
as an optional property
on timeline entry already.
Let's go ahead and add it.
Note, the range of relevance values
is set by us.
Since our character, being fully healed,
is the most important state,
we can just use the health level directly
as our relevance.
So we can pass our relevance
to our sample entry here.
And now, we have a full timeline
with relevance.
And that's timelines.
Now, our widget is only showing
Power Panda.
But there are two other heroes.
That's unfair because both of them
saved the day as well.
Let's make which hero the widget displays
a configuration option.
I've already added an intent definition
to this project.
But here's how you would do it fresh.
You go to File, New File,
Search for Intent.
And add a SiriKit Intent Definition file.
I've already added it,
so I'm not going to do that here.
But one thing we want to double-check
is that our target membership
includes both the widget and the app.
So the Intent Definition file
has a few fields we need to fill out.
Because widgets display information,
our category is information view.
We have a custom title and description.
And we need to make sure
that we check this box
to let our intent be eligible for widgets.
Our intent has one parameter named "hero."
And that parameter is an enum.
And we can set what values
our enum provides in the enum editor.
Here I've already added Panda and Egghead,
but we also need to add Spouty.
[typing]
So now my intent definition is complete.
How do we make our widget
use our intent definition?
Back in our widget...
we need to change our widget type...
from being a static configuration
to an intent configuration.
This requires one extra argument.
And I'm going to let Xcode tell me
exactly what it is by building...
[clicking]
...and applying this fix-it.
And we can use
our CharacterSelectionIntent.
And an intent configuration
needs a matching intent timeline provider.
So up at the top,
we can change our timeline provider
to be an intent timeline provider.
And an intent timeline provider
passes one extra argument
to its snapshot and timeline methods.
And that's the configuration.
We added it to snapshot,
and we also need to add it to timeline.
Now we just need a map
from the configuration to a character.
Note that these enum values look the same,
but one is from the intent definition,
and one is our character
detail definition.
Now we just need to set
the selected character
for the character of our intent.
Now let's Build and Run it
and see it in action.
Now when I add Emoji Rangers widget
from the gallery,
it defaults to Power Panda.
But when I long press on it,
I have this new "Edit Widget" option.
When I tap that, my widget flips around,
and I can select between Power Panda,
Egghead and Spouty.
And I want Spouty on my Home Screen.
So that's configuration.
So this is super cool,
but I'm kind of expecting to jump directly
into the characters' detail screen,
now that I can pick
exactly which character is showing,
and doing that is super easy.
We just add a widgetURL modifier
onto our view.
And we do that for both our systemSmall
and our systemMedium views.
Now, when I Build and run...
when I add my Emoji Ranger widget...
when I tap on it,
now I go directly into Power Panda.
And if I switch my favorite Ranger...
I'll go directly
into their information as well.
Fantastic.
So now,
we've built a fully-featured widget
that supports multiple families,
has a full timeline,
supports user configuration,
and deep links into its host app.
There's one more section
of this Code-Along
that I would love for you to join me on.
For insight on how to approach
widget design,
see the "Designing Great Widgets" talk.
And my teammate, Nils,
is giving a talk about how to make
the most of SwiftUI and widgets
to really nail those designs.
Thank you and have a great WWDC.