Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Tobias Conradi,
and I'm an engineer on the Photos team.
Together with my colleague, Justin,
I will introduce you
to the new Photos picker.
First of all, let's answer this question:
"What is PHPicker?"
PHPicker is a system-provided picker
which allows you to get access
to photos and videos
from the user's Photo Library.
It has now built-in support for search
just like the Photos app.
It supports fluid zooming in the grid
and a very often requested feature,
multi-select for third-party apps,
where you can even review
your selection in one app.
In short, PHPicker is the best way
for an app to access
photo and video data from Photos.
It comes in an all-new design
you just saw,
has a new, easy-to-use API,
supports multi-selection,
and apps can specify the selectable types.
Another very important feature
is the privacy aspect of it.
It has privacy built in by default.
The app doesn't need direct access
to the Photos Library to show the picker,
and the picker won't prompt for access
on behalf of your app.
It provides the user-selected photos
and videos only,
which is a clear user intent
of sharing the assets with your app.
You might wonder,
"How do we achieve that?"
Well, PHPicker runs out of process
of the app.
Even though it looks like
PHPicker runs inside the app,
it is really running in a separate process
from the host app rendered on top of it,
but the app can't access
the picker directly
and not even take screenshots
of the picker content.
Only what the user actually selects
is passed back to the host app.
Now let's have a look
at the different components of this API.
First, there is PHPickerConfiguration,
which is used to specify
the multi-select limit,
or with an optional PHPickerFilter
to reduce the selectable types.
The configuration is passed
to a PHPickerController
during its initialization.
Set a delegate implemented in your app
to get a response back.
Once your user confirms their selection,
the picker creates
an array of PHPickerResult objects
which is then passed back to the delegate.
Let's have a look how it works in code.
As I already mentioned,
you can use the configuration
to specify the selection limit
and filter down the visible item types.
First, we initialize the configuration.
You can specify
a selection limit for the picker,
the default limit is one,
and to allow unlimited selection,
set the selection limit to zero.
You can then specify a filter
to restrict the types of selected items.
For example,
if you only want to show images,
including live photos,
use the "images" filter.
You can even combine filters.
In this example,
the picker will only show videos
and live photos but no images.
The PHPickerViewController
is initialized with the configuration.
First, let's create a configuration
and then pass the configuration
to the PickerViewController
during initialization.
Assign a delegate to the picker
and present the picker.
Please note that your app
is responsible for presentation
and dismissal of the picker.
The picker doesn't manage
presentation itself.
Once the user confirms their selection,
the delegate method will be called.
So first, let's dismiss the picker.
Then you can ask result objects
for an NSItemProvider.
The item provider vends multiple different
representations of the selected item.
First ask the provider
if it can load the type you want to load,
and then actually load it.
Then your app can do something
with the image.
Remember that the item provider API
is async,
and you should handle
any errors occurring here.
Let me now hand over to my colleague,
Justin, to show it to you in Xcode.
Thanks, Tobias.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Justin.
I'm an engineer on the Photos team.
I'm here to show you how you can integrate
PHPicker into your iOS application.
We will build a simple photo preview app
that can display
user-selected photos on screen.
Before we start, let's build and run
to see what we have currently.
We have a UIImageView
displaying a placeholder image.
There's also a "plus" button,
but tapping it
doesn't do anything right now.
So what does it take to complete this app?
We're going to do it in two steps.
First,
we'll support previewing a single image.
We want to present the picker
when "plus" is tapped
and display the selected image
on the image view.
Then we will add multi-image support.
In addition to what we have
with single-selection,
if more than one image is selected,
a user can display the next selected image
by simply tapping on the screen.
Okay.
Now that we understand
what features we want to add,
let's start building.
The first thing I need to do
is to present the picker.
I already set up the UI
so presentPicker method will be called
when "plus" is tapped.
We just need to implement this method.
To actually present the picker,
we will create
the picker configuration object first.
Since we are only interested in images,
we want to specify the images filter.
We don't need to set a selection limit
because the default selection limit
is one.
We will add multi-selection support later.
Then we can initialize
PHPickerViewController
using the configuration object
I just created.
We want the presenting view controller
to receive user selections,
so we need to set delegate to "self."
We are seeing this compiler error
because our view controller didn't conform
to the delegate protocol yet.
Let's add the conformance
to fix the error.
We only need to implement a single method:
pickerDidFinishPicking.
It will give us an array
of PHPickerResult objects.
If a user cancels the picker,
that array will be empty.
We should always dismiss the picker first.
Then we can check
if we receive any result.
And if the item provider can load images,
we will retrieve the image
and display it on screen.
In your real app,
you should also handle the error
when the image can't be retrieved.
All right.
That's all we need
to implement single-selection.
Let's build and run
to see what we have so far.
Now, if I tap the "plus" button,
the picker will be presented.
And then if I select the image...
it will be displayed on screen.
It worked.
It's that easy to use
the new PHPicker API.
Great.
Let's complete the app
by adding multiple selection support.
The first thing I need to do
is to set selection limit to zero
to enable unlimited selection.
The great thing
about the new async image-loading API
is we don't need
to load all images up front.
We just need to keep a reference
to all returned item providers
and load images when necessary.
So let's do that.
Now we have an array to store
all picker-returned item providers.
We also created an iterator
so we can know which selected image
is currently displayed.
We can create a method
to display the next image.
You may notice that this is very similar
to our previous
single-selection implementation.
The only difference is we use the iterator
to get the current item provider.
Like I mentioned earlier,
whenever the screen is tapped,
we want to display the next image.
So we just need to override touchesEnded
and call displayNextImage.
And lastly,
we can update our delegate method.
So we can delete single-selection first.
We just need to save all item providers,
create an iterator,
and call displayNextImage
to display the first image.
That's all we need to implement
multi-image preview.
Let's run the app to see what we built.
I can tap the "plus" button.
You may notice that the picker
now has that slightly different UI.
That's because the picker knows
we're in multi-selection mode.
We'll also show the staging area
and also the "add" button
on the top right corner.
I can select a couple images...
and tap "add."
The first image
is correctly displayed on-screen.
It is as fast as single-selection mode
because we don't need
to load other images at all.
And if I tap the screen,
the next image will be displayed.
Tap it again and again and again
until I reach the end.
That's it for the demo.
Now, back to slides.
As seen in the demo,
you don't need to prompt
for Photos Library access
to use PHPicker.
Actually, for most apps
that only want photo and video data,
you don't need to use PhotoKit at all.
But at the same time,
we know that some PhotoKit-based apps
want to get user-selected PHAssets
from the picker.
So let's talk about how you can do that.
Before we dive into the API,
let's reconsider what types of apps
can benefit from using PhotoKit.
For example,
if your app supports
non-destructive image editing
or has Photos Library
organization features...
you need to use PhotoKit.
But please make sure you only request
Photos Library access when necessary
and handle the case
where Photos Library access
is denied by the user.
Let's look at some code now.
Using PHPicker with PhotoKit
is very simple.
You just need to initialize
PHPickerConfiguration
with a PHPhotoLibrary object.
Then you can get asset identifiers
in your delegate callback,
and you can fetch PHAssets
using asset identifiers
you received
through standard PhotoKit API.
In iOS 14,
we also introduced a new feature
called Limited Photos Library.
If your app doesn't use PhotoKit,
you don't need to worry about that.
For apps asking for Photos Library access,
we will show a third "Select Photos"
option in the user prompt
in addition to the existing "Allow Access"
and "No Access" options.
The new option will only allow your app
to access a portion of PHAssets
in a user's Photos Library.
We believe it can enable users
to better control their privacy.
If a user places your app
under Limited Photos Library,
there's a couple things
you need to keep in mind.
First, the picker will still show
the entire Photos Library,
and all photos and videos
can be selected by the user.
Second,
no matter what users select in the picker,
PHAssets you can access will not change.
If you want to request access
to additional PHAssets,
there's a separate API for you to do that.
For more information, please refer to
"Handle the Limited Photos Library
in Your App" session.
Now, back to Tobias
to wrap up this session.
Thank you, Justin.
Let's talk about some best practices
and summarize what you've just learned.
First,
let's start with a deprecation reminder.
AssetsLibrary has been deprecated
years ago, and is still deprecated.
If your app needs access
to the Photos Library,
please switch over to PhotoKit.
AssetsLibrary will eventually go away.
The other deprecation announcement today
is about the Photos Library portion
of UIImagePickerController.
It is being deprecated,
and we encourage you to adopt
PHPickerViewController instead.
If your app needs access
to images or videos,
we really encourage you to adopt
the new PHPicker
instead of writing
your own custom picker UI.
It supports multi-select, search,
and has a consistent UI
with the main Photos app,
so your users already know
how to get to their images and videos.
Also, please don't prompt
for Photos Library access
before showing the picker,
and don't require the user to grant you
access before showing the picker.
There is no need to do any of this,
and it doesn't help with your user's trust
into your app.
If your app leverages PhotoKit
to access the Photos Library,
please reconsider if it really needs
to have access to the library
or if you can use PHPicker instead.
We really hope you like
the new picker and API.
We're looking forward
to you adopting it in your apps.
Thank you.