Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name's Roberto,
and I'm a software battery life engineer
here at Apple,
and I'm going to demystify
background execution for you today.
You may have asked yourself this question:
"My app adopted a background mode,
but it's not running as much
as I would like it to.
Why?"
At Apple, we understand
that background execution allows apps
to take their user experience
to the next level,
and we provide a wide variety of APIs
that grant background execution
for different use cases,
each with different parameters.
In this video,
we will address some of these APIs
and answer this most common question.
Today we'll start by talking about general
factors affecting background runtime.
Then we will dive into four specific APIs:
background app refresh tasks,
background pushes,
URLSession background downloads
and uploads,
and background processing tasks.
Now, before you proceed,
if your app does not
currently use these APIs,
or you want to learn how to adopt them,
then we recommend viewing
existing sessions and documentation first.
A great start would be the "Advances
in App Background Execution" session
from WWDC 2019.
And before we dive into
the general factors affecting runtime,
let's highlight the goals we balance
when determining what factors play a role
in system scheduling
of background execution.
On the right, we have your app's goals:
having the latest content,
being fresh when the user
brings the app to the foreground,
and being able to achieve
both of these reliably.
And we balance these with the goals
on the left.
First, there's battery life.
We want to make sure
that any background execution can occur
while maintaining all-day battery life.
Next is performance.
We set strategic limits to ensure
that opportunistic background execution
does not interfere with active usage.
Third is privacy.
We want to make sure
that users are not surprised
by an app running in the background.
That is,
based on their particular usage patterns,
they would reasonably expect that this app
should get some background execution.
Finally, we have user intent.
This is really important to us.
If a user takes a certain action,
we want to make sure the system
responds to and tailors the experience
to those unique actions.
In balancing all these goals,
we arrive at many different factors that
affect background launches and runtime.
And here you can see some
of these factors.
Today, we'll cover the top seven factors
that are likely to affect you.
These are critically low battery,
Low Power Mode,
app usage, the App switcher,
the Background App Refresh switch,
system budgets, and rate-limiting.
Let's start with critically low battery.
Sometimes people find themselves
in critically low battery conditions
where they may not have
much battery charge left,
but they still expect
their phone can last long enough
to get them to a place to charge.
An app running in the background
may be invisible to the user,
so it doesn't make sense to use power
and risk the user not being able to reach
that charging destination.
That's why in these situations,
the system will attempt to pause
discretionary and opportunistic work,
which may not bring direct utility
in real time,
and instead focus on essential work
that is directly user-requested.
Next, we have Low Power Mode.
Low Power Mode is different
from critically low battery
because it is a user-determined setting.
The user has explicitly told the system
that preserving battery
is critically important to them,
potentially even at levels
higher than 20 percent.
Therefore, given it is such a strong
and direct signal,
the system will take this as a cue
to limit certain activity.
As a developer,
remember you can always check
if a user is in Low Power Mode.
And further, you can register
for state change notifications.
These can both be a trigger
to pause activity in your app.
For example, maybe your app can turn off
autoplaying videos in Low Power Mode
to limit energy consumption
due to networking and rendering.
Now, let's talk about other user-driven
factors affecting background runtime.
One of these is app usage.
There is a finite amount of resources
on the system,
and sometimes the system must prioritize
running certain apps over others,
as running everything at once
would be detrimental
to performance and battery life.
Therefore, whenever reasonable,
the system will prioritize apps
that are most important to the user.
Typically, these are simply
the apps they use the most.
There is an on-device predictive engine
that learns which apps people will use
and when,
and this information is used
to prioritize background activity.
But it's not just the apps
the user uses the most.
We sometimes have indirect cues from
the user on which apps they want to run.
For example,
they may jump into the App Switcher
and decide to swipe up
to remove a few apps,
perhaps to declutter
or explicitly terminate an app.
For the modes we will discuss today,
when the system determines
which apps to run,
it constrains to the set of apps that
are still visible in the App Switcher.
Similarly, there are more direct cues
on which apps to run,
like specific user settings.
There are settings
for many different background modes:
for example, Location and Bluetooth.
For discretionary
and opportunistic background execution,
we have the Background App Refresh switch.
It may be obvious that this maps
to Background App Refresh tasks,
but it may not be as apparent that
this setting applies to other modes too.
In fact, it applies to every mode
we will discuss today.
This switch defaults to "on."
No special permission prompt required.
And just like Low Power Mode,
you can query the state of the switch
as well as listen for notifications
when the state is changed.
Now, because this switch defaults to "on,"
the system needs a way to mitigate against
all apps running all day
and overwhelming a user's battery
or data plan.
This is where system budgets
come into play.
To ensure that opportunistic activities
do not deplete batteries or data plans,
we have an energy and data budget,
and every time an app runs,
it deducts from these budgets.
The budgets are slowly made available
throughout the day
so that updates can be distributed
and apps remain fresh throughout.
As long as you limit the amount of energy
and cellular data that you use per launch,
this will prevent the system
from limiting you.
Also, to help apps with budget management,
the system performs some rate-limiting
on your app's behalf.
This means the system
reasonably spaces out launches
just enough to maintain freshness
while mitigating against frequent energy
and data usage.
This is all done for you, so don't worry
about implementing complex logic
to do rate-limiting on your own.
Just request what you need,
and the system will space out launches
depending on what's appropriate
for each background mode.
So those are the top seven factors
the system considers
and that you should keep in mind when
examining your app's background execution.
And now, here's my colleague Andy
to explain how the seven factors apply
to specific background modes.
Thanks, Roberto.
I'm Andy from iOS System Experience.
Let's see how the seven factors apply
to each of the specific background modes.
First, let's start
with Background App Refresh tasks.
Background App Refresh tasks
are a way to ask the system
to run your app periodically
in the background
so that your app can be fresh
just before the user foregrounds it.
It's great for things like
refreshing a social media feed,
fetching emails,
and retrieving the latest stock price.
Let's take a look at how
your Background App Refresh tasks
might run over the course of the day.
On this timeline,
I have plotted the background launches
for App Refresh tasks.
You might expect that they would be evenly
distributed over the course of the day.
But in reality,
you may observe something like this.
Why could this be?
This is where
the seven factors come into play.
Over time,
the system learned usage patterns
and understood that the user typically
launches your app in the morning,
around lunchtime, and in the evening.
Therefore, the launches were scheduled
just before typical launch times.
But wait. Maybe you also notice
a large gap in launches.
Why could this be?
This is where
the other factors come into play.
Maybe the user was in Low Power Mode,
as they realized they would be out
until late in the evening
and wanted to preserve battery life.
Or maybe the user forgot to charge
their phone the previous night,
and the battery was critically low.
Any of the seven factors
could have played a role.
There's one factor, though, where you
have the most influence as a developer,
and this is the system budgets.
As a developer, you can focus
on efficient usage of these budgets
to maximize the opportunities
for your app to run.
So, first, minimize power consumption.
Avoid bringing up unnecessary hardware
like the GPS or accelerometer
unless you absolutely need to.
Along those lines, try to finish your work
as quickly as possible.
This can mean
parallelizing network activity
and limiting computation
to the bare minimum.
And don't let these optimizations
go to waste.
Tell the system when you are done.
This allows the system
to immediately suspend your app
and enter a lower power state.
For Background App Refresh tasks,
this means calling setTaskCompleted.
For other APIs,
it means calling a completion handler.
The other budget to optimize for
is the cellular data budget.
Try to limit your downloads
to what's necessary for a fresh UI.
For example, download thumbnails
instead of full-size images.
And enqueue the rest of your downloads
as a URLSession discretionary
background transfer
for completion at a better time.
Try to keep your cellular data usage
under a hundred kilobytes
each time your app refreshes.
This is a good target to use
for Background App Refresh tasks
as well as for background pushes.
Now let's talk about background pushes.
Background pushes
are pushes that wake up your app
without a visible notification
to the user.
They are great
for when you have new content,
but it's not immediately important
to the user.
For example,
a message to a muted conversation
or an email to an unimportant in-box
or even as a trigger
to initiate a discretionary download
for a new episode of a TV show.
The seven factors come into play
for background pushes as well
except for one: app usage.
The system does not gate
background pushes based on app usage.
One common question we hear is,
"How does rate-limiting apply
to background pushes?"
Let's take a look at that.
Here's the timeline again,
and let's hone in
on an early part of the day.
Say in a given window,
you send 14 pushes
with a few denser clusters.
You may expect a launch upon every push.
But running this frequently could cause
significant battery-life issues,
and on top of that,
it could lead to exhausting the energy
and data budgets early in the day.
Just imagine if that one chatty Messages
conversation you muted
caused your app to run
every time you received a message.
Instead of running upon every push,
the system does this.
The system delays the delivery
of some pushes
to limit the amount of execution while
maintaining a frequent launch cadence.
So the 14 pushes we had
result in seven launches.
And while you might be thinking,
"Oh, no.
Only half our pushes are being delivered."
Well, the time interval between runs
was just 15 minutes,
meaning we had many times per hour,
and the app will be up-to-date
before the user launches it.
So focus on the launch interval
when evaluating your background push
deliveries instead of the delivery rate.
Now that we've talked about
background push,
let's talk about Background URLSessions.
Background URLSessions
are downloads and uploads
that are off-loaded
from your app to the system.
This is great because it allows transfers
to continue after the app exits,
meaning they are unconstrained
by runtime limits.
Background URLSessions are perfect
for things like file downloads,
photo uploads,
and full-size social media content
kicked off
as a result of a background push.
There are many different parameters
you can configure for your download.
One important one
is you can prevent the transfer
from going over cellular
and other expensive links.
Another important parameter is
sessionSendsLaunchEvents.
Setting this to "Yes" requests
that the system launch your app
after the background transfer is complete.
There are two main types
of background URLSessions:
discretionary and nondiscretionary.
You signal this
by setting the isDiscretionary property.
Discretionary background transfers
are transfers you are okay with deferring.
The system will perform discretionary
transfers when conditions are optimal,
perhaps when the phone is plugged in
and on Wi-Fi.
Nondiscretionary transfers are transfers
you want to occur as soon as possible,
perhaps because the user
hit a download button in your app.
If you enqueue a transfer
while the app is in the background,
the system will ignore the isDiscretionary
property and treat it as true.
From the foreground,
you can optionally request discretionary.
For discretionary transfers,
most of the seven factors apply,
but there aren't app usage requirements,
nor does the system impose rate limits
on the transfers you enqueue.
If you requested
sessionSendsLaunchEvents,
it will attempt to launch you
if conditions permit.
Distinct from the transfers,
we have some basic rate-limiting
for the launches.
If the app was brought foreground
recently,
rate-limiting won't apply.
For nondiscretionary transfers
that you've enqueued in the foreground,
the transfer continues
after you dismiss the app.
For these,
only two of the seven factors apply.
Users can stop transfers by swiping
to kill the app in the App Switcher.
And there are indeed some system budgets,
but they are greatly relaxed and unlikely
to get in your way.
And again, if you requested
sessionSendsLaunchEvents,
the launches will follow five
of the seven factors.
Since these sessions were enqueued
while the app was foreground,
rate-limiting due to app usage
won't happen.
Last, there is one more specific run mode
we want to cover:
background processing tasks.
Background processing tasks give your app
several minutes' worth of runtime
at system-friendly times
to do maintenance work,
like indexing a database.
You can also do intensive work
like on-device Core ML training.
Given these are long-running tasks,
the system will wait to run you until
the user is not actively using the device,
such as when it's charging at night.
So how do the seven factors apply
to background processing tasks?
Since you're going to be running
while plugged in,
you won't have to worry
about critically low battery,
Low Power Mode,
or the system energy budget.
With regard to app usage, the user
doesn't need to use your app every day
for your processing tasks to run.
As long as they've brought the app
foreground in the past couple of weeks,
you should be fine.
The App Switcher and Background App
Refresh switches are still gating factors,
so as to prevent the app from
running unexpectedly, against user intent.
And with regard to rate limits,
as long as the user plugs in every day,
your background processing tasks
should be able to run daily.
Now that you've learned the seven factors
and how they apply
to specific background modes,
think about how they apply to your app.
Remember,
you can check the state of user switches,
such as Low Power Mode
and Background App Refresh,
in order to respond gracefully
to user intent.
And now that you understand
the differences between these modes,
reevaluate whether you are choosing
the right mode for a specific job.
This could even mean using multiple modes.
Finally, the power is in your hands.
If you reduce energy and data usage,
then you can maximize
your app's freshness,
maintain great battery life,
preserve data plans,
and overall deliver
a mystically delightful experience.
Thanks for watching.