Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Roger Pantos,
and today we will be looking
at Playlist Delta Updates.
We introduced Playlist Delta Updates to
optimize one particular use case of HLS.
As you probably know,
when a client is playing a livestream,
it is constantly reloading the media
playlist to discover new segments.
Now,
that's fine when the playlist is small,
but if you want to present
a large DVR window or a long event,
the playlist can actually become
pretty large, even using gzip.
Reloading a big playlist over and over
takes time,
and the bandwidth it requires can even
make the player switch down
to a lower quality tier
if it's on a bad network.
So Playlist Delta Updates are a new way
to reload an HLS playlist,
where the server sends only
the most recent changes to the client.
The client then combines that update,
with the version it already has,
to reconstruct the current version
that's on the server.
Let's walk through the entire process.
First,
Playlist Delta Updates are optional.
The server advertises
that it supports them
using the Can-Skip-Until attribute
of the server control tag.
The value of Can-Skip-Until
is the skip limit,
which is how old something
in the playlist has to be in seconds
to be skipped by a delta update.
It is always
at least six target durations.
The client downloads
the first full playlist at least once.
If the server has advertised
Playlist Delta Updates,
then the next time it asks for one,
it can use
the HLS skip Delivery Directive.
It will then use the delta
that is produced
to update the previous version
of the playlist to what's current.
Let's take a closer look
to see how a delta update is structured.
First,
the playlist version is nine or higher,
and that indicates to clients
that they have to understand
Playlist Delta Updates to parse it.
A delta update
is not a stand-alone playlist,
so it's not backward-compatible.
Clients will look
at the media sequence tag
to find out which segments
have been removed since the last update.
And then, the most important part of
a Playlist Delta Update, is the skip tag.
The skip tag replaces
all the segment URL lines
which were added to the playlist
before the skip limit,
as well as any media segment tags
applied to one of those lines,
such as discontinuity tags
or Program-Date-Time tags.
For a long playlist,
this one skip tag could replace
thousands of lines of playlists
that the client already has.
It has a skipped segments attribute that
says how many segments were skipped.
After the skip tag
is the rest of the playlist.
And that will include
any segments and tags
that were added since the last skip limit.
Let's take a look at an example.
On the left here,
we have a regular live HLS playlist.
I've omitted some stuff in the middle
to save space,
but you can see that
it starts with segment 0,
and the last segment is segment 20.
It has that Can-Skip-Until attribute,
so the client knows
that as long as it got this playlist
comfortably within the last 36 seconds,
it can ask for a delta update.
And so it does that
by adding an HLS skip Delivery Directive
to its playlist request.
That will produce
the delta update on the right.
It has a version number of nine,
and the media sequence is one,
which tells us that that first segment
has been rolled out of the playlist.
Then we have the skip tag,
and that acts as a stand-in
for all the segments in the middle.
It's followed by
all the recently added segments,
including a new one, segment 21.
And so the client will take
what's new on the right
and combine it
with the previous version on the left
to produce a complete playlist that is
up to date with what is now on the server.
Now, Playlist Delta Updates were
actually a feature of last year's OS,
and one of the bits of feedback we got
was that, while they were great,
they didn't go quite far enough
for providers who had large playlists
that also included lots
of playlist metadata in DATERANGE tags.
And so this year, we are adding
an extension to Playlist Delta Updates
that supports skipping DATERANGE tags
as well.
Servers say they support it by advertising
a Can-Skip-Dateranges attribute
in their server control tag.
Clients, in turn,
will ask for a date range-skipping update
with a new form
of skip delivery directive, skip=v2.
The way v2 updates work
is they skip any date range that was added
to the playlist before the skip limit.
Also, they indicate which, if any,
DATERANGE tags
have been removed since the skip limit,
using the Recently-Removed-Dateranges
attribute.
Now again,
this is an incompatible version,
so that is signaled
with a playlist version of 10.
Next, let's take a look at an example
of date range skipping.
So on the left,
we have a live HLS playlist,
this time with DATERANGE tags
and a Can-Skip-Dateranges attribute,
saying that the server supports
skipping date ranges.
Now, DATERANGE tags
can go anywhere in a playlist.
In this case, the author decided
to put them all at the bottom.
The client asks for a delta update
using the HLS skip=v2 delivery directive.
And that will produce this delta
on the right.
It's version 10,
because it skips date ranges.
As before,
the media sequence tag indicates
that segment 0 has rolled off.
The skip tag also contains
a Recently-Removed-Dateranges attribute
that says that DATERANGE ID 1
was recently removed from the playlist.
At then at the end of the update,
we see our new segment 21 as before.
DATERANGE ID 1 is missing
because it was removed by the author.
DATERANGE 2 is not in the update
because it was in the playlist previously,
early enough ago that it was skipped.
DATERANGE P, on the other hand, is there
because it was added to the playlist
more recently.
And finally, at the end,
there's a new DATERANGE, DATERANGE Q.
And so, when the client combines the delta
with the previous playlist,
it will get this:
an updated playlist
with all the DATERANGE tags
still in the playlist present.
We've got 2, we've got P, we've got Q.
And without the DATERANGE ID 1
that was previously removed.
So Playlist Delta Updates
are a powerful tool
for optimizing livestreams
with large playlists.
In this year's OS,
they can also do a great job on playlists
with lots of DATERANGE tags.
They can dramatically improve
playlist reload performance,
which at the end of the day
will improve playback reliability,
and ultimately, your users' experience.
And so we hope
that you can take advantage of them.
Thank you very much.