Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Paresh Sawant
and I'm going to talk about the new
Local Push Connectivity API in iOS 14.
Push notifications are great
for keeping your app users informed
with timely and relevant content.
However,
delivery of push notification relies
on Apple's push notification service,
which is only available
when devices have an Internet connection.
We received feedback from some of you
that the ability to receive messages
from your application server
is a critical part
of your app's functionality
and must continue to work
even when there is no Internet connection.
To meet this requirement for your apps,
we have added a new API in iOS 14
that allows you to create
your own push connectivity service
that works on Wi-Fi networks.
I will start out
with a recap of Apple push notifications,
then I will talk about how to build
a custom push notification service
using the new API.
Later, I will demo this new feature
using the sample app,
and then I will head over to the details
of using the new API.
So, let's get started.
I'm sure many of you
are familiar with push notifications.
Many apps use push notifications
for news alerts, sports updates,
instant messaging,
receiving VoIP calls and many more.
Let's review how it works.
Your provider server
sends a push notification request
to the Apple Push Notification service,
also known as APNs.
APNs conveys corresponding notification
payloads to each targeted device.
On receipt of a notification,
the system delivers the payload
to the appropriate app on the device.
Depending on the notification type,
your app uses either PushKit
or the UserNotifications framework
to receive the payload.
APNs is the centerpiece
of the push notification feature.
Push notifications
is the right solution for your apps
when used on networks that have
APNs connectivity or the Internet.
It's very optimal
since it implements a single connection
between the device and the APNs
to deliver the notifications to all apps
on the device.
Push notification offers
the desired user experience in your apps,
and most importantly,
it is very energy efficient.
So, developers should prefer
either PushKit
or the UserNotifications framework
to handle notifications originated
from their servers.
However,
if your app is used in network
environments where APNs cannot be reached,
the app cannot receive
these notifications.
For example,
places like cruise ships,
airlines, camping sites or hospitals
may have limited or no APNs connectivity.
The push notifications feature of your app
can get impaired in such conditions.
Push notifications play
a very important role
in providing users with timely information
and give them the ability
to take appropriate actions in response.
So, it's very important
to keep push notifications functional
even in constrained network environments
when it matters most to the users.
Local Push Connectivity is a solution
that is designed to solve this problem.
And we have added
the Local Push Connectivity API in iOS 14.
This is new member
in the NetworkExtension family of APIs.
Let's see how it works.
With the help of this new API,
you can build an app extension
that can directly communicate with your
provider server on a local Wi-Fi network.
Since there is no APNs,
you need to define your own protocol
between the provider server and the app
extension to deliver the notifications.
Your app must specify the Wi-Fi networks
where you wish to enable Local
Push Connectivity for your app users.
The system starts the app extension
when the device joins
the specified Wi-Fi networks.
The app extension is responsible
for maintaining a network connection
with the provider server
and receiving the notifications.
The app extension continues to run
in the background
as long as the device is associated
to the specified Wi-Fi networks.
The system stops the app extension
when the device loses connection
to the specified Wi-Fi networks.
Now, since we know about
the new Local Push Connectivity API,
and also we reviewed
the standard push notifications,
I would like to talk about
general guidelines on selecting
the right API for your apps.
You should prefer either PushKit
or the UserNotifications framework
for your general
push notifications requirements.
The Local Push Connectivity API
is designed
for a small set
of very specific use cases.
The use cases are mainly defined
by limitations in network environments
and users' requirements
in those environments.
Local Push Connectivity
can be the right solution
in scenarios
where notifications are essential
and network environments have constraints.
To implement the specific use cases
using the Local Push Connectivity API,
you will need to request
the new entitlement.
Let's now see how these two mechanisms
look in comparison with each other.
New Local Push Connectivity is all about
direct communication
between your provider server
and your app extension
using your protocol
on your specified Wi-Fi networks.
It's completely in your control.
Now let's understand how the app extension
handles different types of notifications.
On receiving user-facing notifications,
your app extension uses local
notifications to get the user's attention.
App extension code
uses the UserNotifications framework
to create and schedule
local notifications.
It can display an alert,
play a sound or badge your app's icon.
For example, on receiving
the notification for a text message,
the user can be notified using a banner
rolling from the top of the screen
as shown here.
The app extension should always use
user local notifications
for user-facing notifications.
Now let's see how the app extension
can handle a VoIP notification.
This notification conveys information
about an incoming VoIP call
for your app user.
On receiving a VoIP notification,
the app extension uses
the NEAppPushProvider class
to report the incoming call to the system.
In response to that, system wakes
your containing app if it's not running
and delivers the call info to it.
The containing app uses CallKit framework
to display the incoming call UI
as shown here.
I will talk about how to handle VoIP
notifications in your app in detail later.
Now let's see this working in a demo app.
Cruise ships have
limited or no Internet connectivity,
or sometimes they offer paid data plans.
The cruise ship company in the demo
has developed an app named SimplePush
which is using
the new Local Push Connectivity API
to provide text messaging
and VoIP services.
They want friends and families on board
to stay in touch using this app.
Jane and John are users of this app.
In the demo, they communicate
with each other using the SimplePush app
while their devices don't have
an Internet connection.
This is Jane's device,
and this is John's device.
Let's take a look at the settings
in the SimplePush app on Jane's device.
The settings consist
of provider server's host name
and the SSID of the Wi-Fi network
where Local Push Connectivity is enabled.
As you can see here,
Jane's device is connected
to Cruise Ship Wi-Fi.
These are Jane's contacts.
I will have Jane
send a text message to John
that will show a notification
on John's device.
So let's go ahead
and select John from the contacts
and tap the Text button.
I will type in, "Hello, John"...
-and tap the Send button.
-[phone chimes]
And the notification appeared
on John's device.
John taps the notification to open
the text message in the SimplePush app.
Now Jane makes a voice call to John...
and that shows the incoming call UI
on John's device.
John answers the call...
and you can see here
the call is in progress.
Now John hangs up the call.
So that was a brief demo
of the SimplePush app
that uses the new
Local Push Connectivity API in iOS 14.
The new Local Push Connectivity API
comprises two classes--
NEAppPushManager and NEAppPushProvider.
NEAppPushManager class
is used by the containing app,
and app extension code implements
a subclass of NEAppPushProvider class.
Your app extension and the containing app
both need to have the NEAppPushProvider
entitlement to use this API.
The containing app uses an instance
of the NEAppPushManager class
to create a configuration
which mainly consists of Wi-Fi networks
where Local Push Connectivity
is expected to work.
You can load, save and remove
a configuration using this class.
If you are implementing a VoIP app,
the NEAppPushManager class is also used
to set a delegate
to handle the incoming VoIP calls.
Your app extension implements
a subclass of the NEAppPushProvider class.
This class defines
life-cycle management methods
that you need to override
in your subclass.
The methods are called by the system when
the app extension is started and stopped.
The app extension is started when the
device joins the specified Wi-Fi networks.
The system stops the app extension
when the device loses the connection
with the specified Wi-Fi networks.
The app extension establishes
a network connection
with its provider server on start
and tears down the connection on stop.
On receiving a VoIP notification,
the app extension uses this class
to report the incoming call to the system.
In response to that,
the system wakes the containing app
and delivers the call info to it.
Now let's take a look at how your app uses
the NEAppPushManager class
to create a configuration.
You need to import
the NetworkExtension module
to use the Local Push Connectivity API.
Creating a configuration
for your app push provider is very simple.
You need to create an instance
of the NEAppPushManager class
and use that to set these properties.
matchSSIDs specifies an area of SSIDs
of the Wi-Fi networks
where you wish to enable
Local Push Connectivity.
providerBundleIdentifier is the
bundle identifier of your app extension.
This setting allows the system to run
the appropriate app extension when needed.
providerConfiguration is a dictionary
that specifies configuration data
for your app extension.
And finally, you need to set isEnabled
to "true"
in order to enable Local Push Connectivity
using this configuration.
After you have
all the settings configured,
call saveToPreferences method
to process the configuration.
If the configuration is saved successfully
and it is enabled,
the system enables Local Push Connectivity
using this configuration.
The app extension implements
a subclass of the NEAppPushProvider class
and overrides the required methods.
The system calls
startwithcompletionHandler
to start the app extension.
The app extension establishes a network
connection with its server in this method.
The system calls stopwithreason
when the app extension is stopped.
The app extension tears down
the server connection in this method.
Upon receiving a VoIP notification,
the app extension calls
reportIncomingCall
to report the incoming VoIP call
to the system.
In response to that, the system wakes
the containing app if it's not running
and delivers the call info to it.
As we saw in the last slide,
the app extension is responsible
for reporting incoming VoIP calls
to the system,
and in response,
the system launches the app.
The containing app must implement
an app delegate object
conforming to
UIApplicationDelegate protocol
in order to know
when an app process is launched.
On app launch,
you must call loadAllFromPreferences
to load all the saved configurations
and set the NEAppPushDelegate object
for each NEAppPushManager instance
as shown here.
The system delivers the user info
dictionary to the containing app
by calling the
didReceiveIncomingCallWithUserInfo
delegate method
for the appropriate NEAppPushManager
instance on the app's main queue.
On receiving the user info,
the app must report
the incoming call to CallKit
using the appropriate CallKit API
and let it display the call UI.
Please see the CallKit API documentation
for the details
on reporting incoming calls,
and also refer to the SimplePush
sample app code for more details.
Please note,
in order to receive incoming call info,
your containing app must have
the Voice over IP background mode enabled
in the Xcode project capabilities pane
as shown here.
Now you know the details
of the new Local Push Connectivity API
introduced in iOS 14,
let's talk about the next steps you should
take to use notifications in your app.
You should prefer either PushKit
or the UserNotifications framework
for most general push notifications
requirements in your app.
You should use Local Push Connectivity
only in network conditions
where APNs connectivity is not available
and notifications are essential
for your app users.
If you determine Local Push Connectivity
is the right solution for your app users,
remember that you must request
the NEAppPushProvider entitlement
in order to use
the Local Push Connectivity API.
Thanks for watching.