Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, and welcome
to Data Essentials in SwiftUI.
I'm Curt Clifton,
an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Later I'll be joined by my friends
and colleagues, Luca Bernardi
and Raj Ramamurthy.
We're going to cover three main areas
in this talk.
I'll talk about getting started
on the data flow in your SwiftUI app,
and cover topics like State and Binding.
Then Luca will discuss how you can build
on those ideas and more
to design the data model for your app.
Finally, Raj will share techniques
for integrating your data model
into your app.
Along the way, we'll discuss
the life cycle of a SwiftUI view
and share several cool, new features
that make it even easier
to model your data.
We'll also help you develop
a deeper understanding
of how value and reference types in Swift
interact with data flow in SwiftUI.
I'll be walking through some basic
data flow features in SwiftUI,
and we'll cover some questions
you should ask yourself
whenever you create a new SwiftUI view.
Luca is really into book clubs.
He's so into them that he decided
he needed an app
to keep track of
what each of his clubs is reading
and take some notes
for their next meeting.
I enjoy reading too,
and thought it would be fun
to work on an app together.
To get started,
I want to prototype the view
that represents a book I'm reading.
When I start on a new view in SwiftUI,
there are three key questions
I like to think about.
What data does this view need
to do its job?
In this example, the view needs
a thumbnail of the book cover,
the title, the author's name,
and the percentage of the book
that I've read.
How will the view manipulate that data?
This view just needs to display the data.
It doesn't change it.
Where will the data come from?
This is the "Source of Truth".
In the examples throughout this talk,
Luca, Raj and I will use this badge
to label the source of truth.
Ultimate, as we'll see,
this question of the source of truth
is the most important one
in the design of your data model.
Let's build out this view and see
what its source of truth should be.
So what data does this view need
to do its job?
The book value provides the name
of the cover image,
the author and the title.
The progress value provides
the percent complete.
And how will the view
manipulate this data?
It just displays the data,
it doesn't change it,
so these can be "let" properties.
And where will the data come from?
It will be passed in from the superview
when the BookCard is instantiated.
The source of truth is somewhere
farther up the view hierarchy.
The superview passes the true data in
when it instantiates a BookCard.
A new BookCard is instantiated every time
the superview's body executes.
The instance lives just long enough
for SwiftUI to render it, then it's gone.
We can visualize the internal structure
using a diagram.
The boxes on the left represent
the SwiftUI views
that are composed to build this BookCard.
The capsules on the right represent
the data that's used
to render the views.
We'll return to diagrams like this
throughout the talk.
Next, I'd like to look
at a slightly more interesting view.
When I tap on a book,
the app takes me to this screen
where I can review my progress.
I want to add a way to update my progress,
and add notes when I tap
on the "Update Progress" button.
Something like this.
Let's look at how the parent view
and this sheet work together.
We'll focus on how the sheet is presented.
When the user taps
the "Update Progress" button,
we'll call the presentEditor method.
It will mutate some state
to cause the sheet to appear.
What data does this view need
to control the presentation of the sheet?
We need a Boolean to keep track
of whether the sheet is presented,
and we need a String
to keep track of the note,
and a Double to track the progress.
Whenever I have multiple
related properties like this,
I like to pull them out
into their own struct.
Besides making BookView more readable,
there are two other great things
about this approach.
We get all the benefits of encapsulation.
EditorConfig can maintain invariants
on its properties
and be tested independently.
And because EditorConfig is a value type,
any change to a property of EditorConfig,
like its progress,
is visible as a change
to EditorConfig itself.
Our next question is,
how will the view manipulate this data?
When the "Update" button is tapped,
we'll need to set
isEditorPresented to "True"
and update progress
to match the current progress.
Because we extracted the state
into the EditorConfig struct,
we can make it responsible
for those updates,
and just have the BookView
ask the EditorConfig to do the work.
Then, we'll add a mutating method
to EditorConfig, like so.
And where will the data come from?
Well, the editor configuration is local
to this view.
There isn't some parent view
that can pass it in,
so we need to establish
a local source of truth.
The simplest source of truth
in SwiftUI is State.
When we mark this property as State,
SwiftUI takes over managing its storage.
Let's look at that as a diagram.
Again, we have the views represented
by these boxes on the left,
and the data by a capsule on the right.
Notice that the capsule
has a thick border.
I'm using this border to indicate data
that's managed by SwiftUI for us.
Why is that important?
Well, remember that our views
only exist transiently.
After SwiftUI completes a rendering pass,
the structs themselves go away.
But because we marked this property
as State,
SwiftUI maintains it for us.
The next time the framework needs
to render this view,
it reinstantiates the structs,
and reconnects it to the existing storage.
Let's look at the ProgressEditor next.
What data does the ProgressEditor need
to do its job?
Well, all the data from an EditorConfig.
And how will the view
manipulate that data?
It needs to change it, so we'll use a var.
And where will the data come from?
That's an interesting question
in this case.
Back to the diagrams.
Let's focus on the BookView
and the ProgressEditor.
Suppose we just pass the EditorConfig
down to the ProgressEditor
as a regular property.
Because EditorConfig is a value type,
Swift would make a new copy of the value.
Any changes the ProgressEditor made
to the note, or the progress,
would only change this new copy,
not the original value that SwiftUI
is managing for us.
So this doesn't allow ProgressEditor
to communicate with BookView.
What next?
Ah! What if we gave ProgressEditor
its own State property?
That seems like it might be what we want.
It tells SwiftUI to manage
a new piece of data for us.
Sadly, this is also wrong. [sighs]
Remember,
State creates a new source of truth.
Any changes made by the ProgressEditor
would be made to its own state,
not the one shared with BookView.
We want a single source of truth.
We need a way to share write-access
to the source of truth from BookView
with ProgressEditor.
In SwiftUI,
the tool for sharing write-access
to any source of truth is Binding.
BookView creates a Binding
to EditorConfig.
A read-write reference
to the existing data
and shares that reference
with ProgressEditor.
By updating the EditorConfig
through this Binding,
the ProgressEditor is mutating
the same state that BookView is using.
SwiftUI notices changes
to the EditorConfig.
It knows that both BookView
and ProgressEditor
have a dependency on that value,
and so it knows to re-render those views
when the value changes.
The ProgressEditor needs to pass data
back to the BookView.
We've just seen that Bindings
are the right tool for this task.
The dollar sign in the call
creates a Binding from the State
because the projected value of
the State property wrapper is a Binding.
The Binding property wrapper
creates a data dependency
between the ProgressEditor
and the EditorConfig state in BookView.
Many built in SwiftUI controls
also take Bindings.
For example, the new TextEditor control
used for our notes
takes a Binding to a String value.
Using the dollar sign
projected value accessor,
we can get a new Binding to the note
within the EditorConfig.
SwiftUI lets us build a new Binding
from an existing Binding.
Remember, Bindings aren't just for State.
That's a bit on getting started
with data flow in SwiftUI.
Remember to ask yourself
the three questions
when adding a SwiftUI view.
What data does this view need?
How will it use that data?
And where does the data come from?
You can use properties for data
that doesn't change.
Use State for transient data
owned by the view.
Use Binding for mutating data
owned by another view.
Now I'd like to turn things over to Luca
to dive into designing your data model
because State is not the whole story.
Thank you, Curt.
Ciao, everyone. My name is Luca.
My colleague, Curt, has just described
how to use State and Binding
to drive changes in your UI,
and how these tools are a great way
to quickly iterate on your view code.
But State is designed
for transient UI state
that is local to a view.
In this section, I want to move
your attention to designing your model
and explain all the tools
that SwiftUI provides to you.
Typically, in your app,
you store and process data
by using a data model
that is separate from its UI.
This is when you reach a critical point
where you need to manage the life cycle
of your data,
including persisting and syncing it,
handle side-effects, and, more generally,
integrate it with existing components.
This is when you should use
ObservableObject.
First, let's take a look
at how ObservableObject is defined.
It's a class constrained protocol
which means it can only be adopted
by reference type.
It has a single requirement,
an objectWillChange property.
ObjectWillChange is a Publisher,
and as the name suggests,
the semantic requirement
of the ObservableObject protocol
is that the publisher has to emit before
any mutation is applied to the object.
By default, you get a publisher
that works great out of the box.
But if you need to,
you can provide a custom publisher.
For example,
you can use a publisher for a timer,
or use a KVO publisher
that observes your existing model.
Now that we've seen the protocol,
let's take a look at a mental model
for understanding ObservableObject.
When your type conforms
to ObservableObject,
you are creating a new source of truth
and teaching SwiftUI
how to react to changes.
In other words, you are defining the data
that a view needs to render its UI
and perform its logic.
SwiftUI will establish a dependency
between your data and your view,
here represented with blue boxes.
SwiftUI uses this dependency
to automatically keep your view consistent
and show the correct representation
of your data.
We like to think of ObservableObject
as your data dependency surface.
This is the part of your model
that exposes data to your view,
but it's not necessarily the full model.
If you think of ObservableObject this way,
it doesn't need to be
exactly your data model.
You can separate your data
from its storage and life cycle.
You can model your data using value type
and manage its life cycle and side effects
with a reference type.
For example,
you can have a single ObservableObject
that centralizes your entire data model
and is shared by all your views,
like in the diagram here.
This gives you a single place
for all your logic,
making it easy to reason
about all the possible states
and mutations in your app.
Or you can focus on part of your app
by having multiple ObservableObject
that offer a specific projection
onto your data model
are are designed to expose just the data
that is needed.
This works better when you have
a complex data model
and you want to provide a more tightly
scoped invalidation to part of your app.
Let's go back to the app we were building,
and let's see how we can apply
what we have just discussed.
Let's bring back the view
that Curt was working on before.
This is the view that allows me
to update my progress in the book
and add some notes of things I found
interesting during my reading session.
Curt focused on the data
for the progress sheet.
Let's look at the rest of the data
we need for this view
and how to use ObservableObject
to add rich features,
such as storing data on disk
or syncing it with iCloud.
We can create a new class
called CurrentlyReading
that conforms to ObservableObject that
stashes a book and its reading progress.
This is the part of our model
that we will expose to our view
to present data and respond to changes.
The specific book will never change,
so we can just make this property a let.
We want to be able to update the progress
and have our UI react to it.
We can do this just by annotating
the progress property
with the @Published property wrapper.
Let's take a look at how @Published works.
@Published is a property wrapper
which makes a property observable
by exposing a Publisher.
For most models, you can just conform
to ObservableObject,
add @Published to the properties
that might change, and you're done.
It's that simple to never have to worry
about keeping your data
in sync with your view.
When you use @Published
with the default
ObservableObject publisher,
the system will automatically
perform invalidation
by publishing right before
the value changes.
For advanced use cases,
the projected value of @Published
is a Publisher that you can use
to build reactive streams.
Let's revisit the three questions
that you should be asking
when designing your data model.
With ObservableObject,
answering the second question
is pretty straightforward:
we always assume mutability.
Let's now take a look at how
to answer these other two questions
when it comes to ObservableObject.
We have seen how to define our model,
but now we need to use it in our view.
SwiftUI offers three property wrappers
that you can use in a view
to create a dependency
to an ObservableObject.
These tools are ObservedObject,
StateObject, which is new this year,
and EnvironmentObject.
Let's start by taking a look
at ObservedObject.
ObservedObject is a property wrapper
that you can use to annotate properties
of your view
that holds a type conforming
to ObservableObject.
Using it informs SwiftUI
to start tracking the property
as a dependency for the view.
You are defining the data
that this view will need to do its job.
This is the most simple
and flexible of the tools.
ObservedObject does not get ownership
of the instance you're providing to it,
and it's your responsibility
to manage its life cycle.
Let's see how to use it in our app.
Here I have my BookView.
It's the view that displays the book
and all the progress I've logged so far.
From this screen, I can also
update my progress for this book.
We can add a property
of the type currentlyReading,
the type we have just created,
and annotate it with
the @ObservedObject property wrapper.
The instance that is assigned
to this property
is going to be the source of truth
for this view.
Now, we can read the model
in the view body.
SwiftUI will guarantee that the view
is always up to date.
There is no code that you have to write,
and there is no event to manage
to keep your view in sync.
You can just declaratively describe
how to write the view from the data,
and SwiftUI will take care
of all the rest.
My colleague, Raj,
will go into more detail
about the SwiftUI update life cycle,
but I want to take you behind the scene
and show you
what SwiftUI is doing for you.
Whenever you use ObservedObject,
SwiftUI will subscribe
to the objectWillChange
of that specific ObservableObject.
Now, whenever the ObservableObject
will change,
all the view that depends on it
will be updated.
One of the questions that we often get
is "why 'will' change?
Why not 'did' change?"
And the reason
is that SwiftUI needs to know
when something is about to change
so it can coalesce every change
into a single update.
But how do we produce mutation?
Many of the UI components vended
by SwiftUI
take a Binding to a piece of data
and, earlier in the talk,
you have seen an example of how
to design your component to do the same.
This is one of the fundamental
design principles of SwiftUI.
Accepting a Binding allows a component
read and write access to a piece of data
while preserving a single source of truth.
Curt has shown you how to derive
a Binding from State.
Doing the same with ObservableObject
is just as easy.
You can get a Binding from any property
that is of value type
on an ObservableObject
just by adding the dollar sign prefix
in front of your variable
and accessing the property.
Let's see a concrete example
in our book club app.
One of the great satisfactions
when reading a book
is finishing that last chapter,
and I want a grand gesture
to mark this event.
I can't think of anything better
than tapping on a Toggle
to say, "I'm done with this book."
The first thing I need to change
is my model.
We can just add a new property,
"isFinished"
and annotate it with @Published
so that whenever its value changes,
our UI will reflect the change.
Let's see how we can change BookView
to add this feature.
I can add a Toggle with a nice label
to allow me to mark this book as done.
The Toggle expects a Binding
so that it can show the current state
and when the user taps on it,
it can mutate the value.
We can provide a Binding to "isFinished"
just by adding the dollar sign prefix
to currentlyReading
and accessing the "isFinished" property.
Now, whenever the user interacts
with the Toggle,
currentlyReading will be updated
and SwiftUI will update all the views
that depend on it.
For example, in this view, we will disable
the button to update the progress
when we are done reading the book.
Throughout our app, we are shown
these beautiful book covers,
and we want to load them asynchronously
from the network,
just before they are displayed on screen.
They're expensive resources,
so we want to keep them alive
only while the view is visible.
More generally, we noticed that often
you do want to tie the life cycle
of your ObservableObject to your view,
like with State.
If you recall,
ObservedObject does not own
the life cycle of its ObservableObject,
and so we wanted to provide
a more ergonomic tool.
[clicks tongue] This tool is StateObject,
which is new this year.
When you annotate a property
with StateObject,
you provide an initial value,
and SwiftUI will instantiate that value
just before running body
for the first time.
SwiftUI will keep the object alive
for the whole life cycle of the view.
This is a great addition to SwiftUI
and let's see how we can use it
in practice.
Let's create a CoverImageLoader class
to load a specific image by name.
Here I'm just showing
the skeleton of this class,
but not how I made it an ObservableObject
and annotated the property
that holds the image with @Published.
Once we have our image, SwiftUI
will automatically update the view.
And now in our view,
we can use CoverImageLoader
and just annotate the property
with StateObject.
CoverImageLoader will not be
instantiated when the view is created.
Instead, it will be instantiated
just before body runs
and kept alive
for the whole view life cycle.
When the view is not needed anymore,
SwiftUI will release
the CoverImageLoader as expected.
You don't need to fiddle
with onDisappear anymore.
Instead, you can use the ObservableObject
lifetime to manage your resources.
In SwiftUI, views are very cheap.
We really encourage you to make them
your primary encapsulation mechanism
and create small views that are simple
to understand and reuse.
This means that you might end up
with a deep and wide view hierarchy,
like in the diagram here.
If we look at this
through the perspective of data flow,
you might need to create
an ObservableObject
high up in the view hierarchy
and pass the same instance to many views.
Sometimes, you need to you use
your ObservableObject in a distant subview
and passing it down through views
that don't need the data
can be cumbersome
and involve a lot of boilerplate.
Luckily, we have a solution
for this problem with EnvironmentObject.
EnvironmentObject is both a view modifier
and a property wrapper.
You use the view modifier in a parent view
where you want to inject
an ObservableObject.
And you use the property wrapper
in all the views
where you want to read an instance
of that specific ObservableObject.
The framework will take care of passing
that value everywhere it's needed
and track it as a dependency
only where it's read.
In this part of the talk we have seen
how to design your model
using ObservableObject
and how SwiftUI provides
all the fundamental primitives
that you can use to build
the best architecture for your needs.
We have seen how to create a dependency
between a view and a piece of data,
how with the new StateObject
property wrapper
you can tie the life cycle
of an ObservableObject to a view,
and finally, how EnvironmentObject
gives you the convenience
to flow ObservableObject
in your view hierarchy.
Now I'm going to hand it over to Raj.
He's going to dive deep
into SwiftUI's life cycle
and how it relates to performance,
how to handle side effects
and some exciting new tools.
Thank you, everyone,
and have a great WWDC. Raj?
Thanks, Luca.
You've learned how to get started
with data in SwiftUI
and how to design a great model.
Now, I'd like to tell you how to design
for the best performance,
as well as some further considerations
in choosing a source of truth.
To begin with, let's talk about views
and their role in the SwiftUI system.
A view is simply a definition
of a piece of UI.
SwiftUI uses this definition
to create the appropriate rendering.
SwiftUI manages the identity
and the lifetime of your views.
And because a view defines a piece of UI,
they should be lightweight
and inexpensive.
In the book club app, like in every app,
everything on screen is a view.
Note that the lifetime of a view
is separate from the lifetime
of a struct that defines it.
The struct you create that conforms
to the View protocol
actually has a very short lifetime.
SwiftUI uses it to create a rendering,
and then it's gone.
Let's use a diagram to illustrate the
importance of making views lightweight.
This diagram shows
the SwiftUI update life cycle.
Starting at the top, we have your UI.
Moving counterclockwise, an event comes in
which causes some closure
or action to run.
That then results in a mutation
of a source of truth.
Then once we've mutated
the source of truth,
we'll get a new copy of the view,
which we'll use to produce a rendering.
That rendering is your UI.
That's just the basics.
We'll revisit the diagram in a bit.
For now, let's simplify it.
And a little bit more.
Ah. Much better.
As the name implies,
this life cycle is a cycle.
It keeps repeating many times
while your app is running.
This cycle is also really important
for performance...
and ideally,
the cycle carries on smoothly, like this.
But if there's expensive blocking work
at any of these points,
the performance of your app will suffer.
We call this a slow update.
It means you might drop frames
or your app might hang.
So how do you avoid slow updates?
Well, the first thing you can do
to avoid slow updates
is to ensure that
your view initialization is cheap.
A view's body should be a pure function,
free of side effects.
That means you should simply create
your view description and return.
No dispatching, no other work.
Just create some views and move on.
Avoid making assumptions
about when and how often body is called.
Remember,
SwiftUI can be pretty smart sometimes,
which means it might not call body
in line with your assumptions.
To illustrate the importance
of body being cheap,
let's look at an example.
Here's a simplified example of what our
Currently Reading list might look like.
In the ReadingListViewer,
we'll define body as a NavigationView
with the ReadingList within.
Then, in ReadingList, we'll use
an ObservedObject to generate the data.
This seems pretty reasonable,
but there's actually a bug lurking here.
Can you see it?
It turns out whenever the body
of ReadingListViewer is created,
you're going to incur a repeated
heap allocation of ReadingListStore,
and this can cause a slow update.
Remember from earlier that your view
structs do not have a defined lifetime,
so when you write this,
you're actually going to create
a new copy of the object every time.
And a repeated heap allocation like this
can be expensive and slow.
It also causes data loss
because the object is reset every time.
Okay, so we've identified a problem,
but how do we fix it?
Well, in the past you had to create
the model somewhere else and pass it in.
But wouldn't it be great
if you could just do this inline?
I'm happy to tell you that this year
we have a tool to solve this problem,
called StateObject,
and as Luca explained earlier,
StateObject lets SwiftUI instantiate
your ObservableObjects at the right time,
so you don't incur unnecessary heap
allocations, and you don't lose data.
This means you can get great performance
and correctness.
One thing to note:
We are declaring
a new source of truth here,
so let's slap the badge on it.
All right,
let's bring back the diagram again.
And enhance.
Great.
One thing to note is there are multiple
sources of the events at the top left.
Your app might react to an event
generated by user interaction,
such as tapping a button,
or it might react to a publisher firing,
like a timer or a notification.
Regardless of what triggers the event,
the cycle is still the same.
We'll mutate a source of truth,
update the view
and then produce a new rendering.
These triggers are called event sources.
They are the drivers of change
in your views.
As I mentioned, a good example of this
is user interaction
or a publisher, such as a timer.
And new this year, we have new ways
to react to events,
such as changes
to the environment and bindings,
and new ways to handle URLs
and user activities.
Each of these modifiers takes a parameter,
such as a publisher or a value to compare,
and it also takes a closure.
SwiftUI will run the closure
at the right time
to help you avoid slow updates
and keep body cheap.
However, note that SwiftUI will run
these closures on the main thread,
so if you need to do expensive work,
consider dispatching
to a background queue.
We're not going to go into detail
on these today,
but I encourage you to check out
the documentation to learn more.
So that's a bit on
how to avoid slow updates
and how to design for great performance.
Next, let's bring back
those three questions.
So we've largely covered
how to solve the first two questions,
but the third one isn't as easy.
When you answer this question,
you're making a decision about the
source of truth that you're going to use.
And this is a hard question.
There's no one right answer here,
so to help, I'd like to walk through
some considerations.
An important question to ask is,
who owns the data?
Is it the view that uses the data,
or maybe an ancestor of that view?
Perhaps it's even another subsystem
of your app.
A few guidelines here:
As mentioned earlier,
share data with a common ancestor.
Also, prefer StateObject as a view-owned
source of truth
for your ObservableObjects.
Lastly, consider placing global data
in the app.
We'll cover this next.
Now let's talk about data lifetime.
We'll cover tying data lifetimes
to Views, Scenes and Apps.
For more on SwiftUI Scenes and Apps,
please refer to
the "App Essentials in SwiftUI" session.
First, let's start with Views.
As we've shown you throughout this talk,
Views are a great tool
to tie your data lifetime to,
and all of the property wrappers
we've discussed today work with views.
You can make use of the State
and StateObject property wrappers
to tie data lifetime to view lifetime.
Next, let's talk about scenes.
Because SwiftUI's scenes each have
a unique view tree,
you can hang important pieces of data
off the root of the tree.
For example, you can put a source of truth
on the view inside of a window group.
In doing so, each instance of the scene
that the window group creates
can have
its own, independent source of truth
that serves as a lens
onto the underlying data model.
This works great with multiple windows.
As you can see here,
the two scenes have independent UI states
that represent the same underlying data.
So now, Luca can go to
two online book clubs at the same time.
Next, let's talk about Apps.
Apps are a powerful new tool
this year in SwiftUI
allowing you to write your entire app
in just SwiftUI.
But what's great about Apps
is that you can use State
and other sources of truth in an app,
just like you do in a view.
Let me show you an example.
Here, we'll create a global book model
for our entire app
by using the StateObject property wrapper.
Whenever the model changes,
all of our app's scenes,
and consequently,
all of their views, will update,
and by writing this, we've created
an app-wide source of truth.
When considering
where to put your source of truth,
you might want to put it in the app
if it represents truly global data.
Your data's lifetime is important,
but that lifetime is tied to the lifetime
of its source of truth,
and in all of the previous examples,
we've used tools like State,
StateObject, and Constants.
But these have a limitation,
which is that they're tied
to the process lifetime,
which means if your app gets killed
or the device restarts,
State won't come back.
To help solve this problem, new this year,
we're introducing Storage.
These have an extended lifetime
and are saved and restored automatically.
Note, these are not your model.
Rather, they are lightweight stores that
you use in conjunction with your model.
Let's start by taking a look
at SceneStorage.
SceneStorage is
a per-scene scoped property wrapper
that reads and writes data
completely managed by SwiftUI.
It is only accessible from within Views,
which makes it a great candidate
for storing lightweight information
about the current state of your app.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here's the book club app from earlier
with two scenes side-by-side.
The first thing to think about
when using SceneStorage is,
what do you really need to restore?
In this case, all we need to save
and restore is the selection.
The names of the book, progress
and the notes are all stored in the model,
so we don't need to save
and restore those.
Let's jump to code.
Here you can see how we use SceneStorage
to save and restore our selected state.
We'll pass a key, which must be unique
to the type of data we're storing.
Then, we can use it just like State.
SwiftUI will automatically save
and restore the value on our behalf.
And since this behaves like State,
we've actually declared
a new source of truth here,
and this time,
it's a scene-wide source of truth.
Now, if the device restarts,
or the system needs to reclaim resources
backing a scene,
the data will be available
at the next launch,
allowing Luca to pick up his book club
activities right from where he left off.
Now that you've seen SceneStorage
in action,
I'd like to discuss AppStorage.
This is app-scoped global storage,
which is persisted using UserDefaults.
It's usable from anywhere,
so you can access it from within your app
or from within your view.
AppStorage, like UserDefaults,
is super useful
for storing small bits of data,
such as settings.
In our book club app, we've also decided
to introduce some settings.
Let's take a look at how to use
AppStorage to accomplish this.
In our Settings view,
all we need to do is add the AppStorage
property wrapper and give it a key.
By default,
this uses the standard user defaults,
but you can customize it if you need to.
For more information,
please refer to the documentation.
In this case, we'll set up an AppStorage
for each of our two settings here.
We'll give them each a unique key because
they are independent pieces of data.
When using SceneStorage and AppStorage,
it's important that unique
pieces of data have unique keys.
And just like the other property wrappers,
this is also a source of truth,
which means we can get bindings to it,
such as for use in a toggle.
And now, whenever the data changes,
it will automatically be saved
and restored to and from user defaults.
We've seen a variety of tools today for
Process Lifetime and Extended Lifetime,
and you use each of the tools here
to store UI-level state.
For the storage types, please be careful
not to store everything with them
because persistence isn't free.
I'd also like to call out one more tool,
and that's ObservableObject.
We've designed ObservableObject
to be very flexible,
so you can use it to achieve
super custom behaviors,
such as backing the data by a server
or by another service.
And together, these tools form a family
that gives you a high degree of freedom
to choose what best suits your needs.
We've seen a lot of tools
and uses of them today,
but the main takeaway is that
there isn't a one-size-fits-all tool.
Each has its own set of traits, so
a typical app will use a variety of tools.
We've done just that in our book club app.
We've used State for buttons
and our progress view,
StateObject for
our currentlyReading model,
SceneStorage for our selection,
and AppStorage for our settings.
It's important to think about
what the properties of your data are
and what the right source
of truth to use is,
and you should also try to limit
the number of sources of truth
to cut down on complexity.
And finally, take advantage of bindings
as a way to build reusable components.
Remember, bindings are completely agnostic
to their source of truth,
which makes them a powerful tool
for building clean abstractions.
Now that you've learned the essentials,
it's time to build a great model.
Thank you.
And have a great WWDC.