Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Sam Colbran
from the GPU Software team at Apple,
and today we're gonna be talking
about Metal tools
and how they can help you gain insights
into your apps in the world of Apple GPUs.
These days, the rendering pipeline
is increasing in complexity,
with potentially hundreds
of render passes.
And that probably sounds a bit daunting,
especially if you're new
to the Apple platform.
But don't worry.
We've got a bunch of great Metal tools
that can guide you and help to reduce
some of that complexity.
We're gonna be going through them today,
and once you use them,
I hope that you'll be able to deliver
amazingly optimized,
beautiful apps and games
to people all over the world.
In this session, we're gonna dig around
in the Metal toolbox
and discover what's available in
the Metal Debugger and Metal System Trace.
At the end, we're gonna have a sneak peek
at an upcoming game from Larian Studios,
and then I'll show you how you might
investigate it with the tools.
First up is the Metal Debugger,
which you'd typically use
when you're GPU-bound.
The Metal Debugger in Xcode
is a powerful toolset
for capturing and debugging
a single frame of your app.
It lets you deep dive
into your render pipeline
and helps to diagnose issues
at an API level.
Let's take a closer look
at each of the tools.
It all begins with a frame capture.
In Xcode, make sure
to first enable GPU Frame Capture
under the scheme options,
and then run your Metal app.
Once you're at a frame
that you wanna debug,
simply click on the camera icon
in the debug bar.
To help you better understand your frame,
this year we've created a new summary view
with the information about a frame
in one convenient location,
giving you quick access
to an overview of encoders,
performance numbers and memory usage.
From here, you can jump into tools
that are specific to the areas
you're interested in exploring.
The summary also shows Insights,
which suggest changes
that you can make to your app
in order to improve memory usage,
bandwidth, performance or Metal API usage.
It's okay if this is your first journey
into the world of Apple GPUs.
The tools will give you the guidance
you need to face the challenges.
Each insight is accompanied
by a description of the problem,
a hint on how to fix it,
along with links to related documentation.
Let's move on to the dependency viewer,
which you can get to by clicking
on the Show Dependencies button
in the summary view
or by clicking on any command buffer
or encoder in the navigator.
As apps and render pipelines
become more complicated,
it's often useful to see all the
dependencies between different encoders
to understand how your frame is rendered.
The dependency viewer provides
a bird's-eye overview
of all of the GPU passes
encoded by your app
and is a great place
to start debugging load/store actions
and bandwidth in general.
If you're interested in learning more,
check out the "Delivering Optimized
Metal Apps and Games" talk
from last year's WWDC.
We'll also come back
to the dependency viewer a bit later,
so let's move on for now.
Apple GPUs are packed with enormous power,
and we want you to take
full advantage of it.
Clicking on Counters in the navigator
brings you
to the GPU Performance counters,
which give you great detail
into how long the GPU is spending
on the various parts of your frame.
If you're interested in learning more,
we have another session this year
that goes into much more detail
about performance counters
and how to use them to fine-tune your app.
So go check it out.
Shaders are also becoming
more powerful each year.
But not to worry.
Simply switch the navigator
to "View Frame by Pipeline State"
and then select a render pipeline.
On Apple GPU's, you can get
per-line performance breakdowns
directly in your shader source code
with the shader profiler.
You can even make edits
directly in the shader profiler
and see how the performance would change.
The "Metal Shader Debugging
and Profiling" talk from 2018
goes into much more detail,
so I encourage you to check it out.
But why stop at performance?
You can also debug your shaders
with the shader debugger.
There are a couple of ways
to get to this tool,
but the easiest is to click
on the debug button in the debug bar.
You can then select a pixel
to debug the fragment shader,
geometry to debug the vertex shader
or threads to debug a compute shader.
Once you're ready,
click on the debug button.
The shader debugger provides you access
to variable state over multiple threads,
so you can easily see
exactly what is happening
during the entire execution
of your shader.
For anyone who's used
a traditional CPU debugger,
you've probably been in a situation
where you've accidentally stepped too far
and can't go back.
In the shader debugger
that's not a problem.
There's also no need
to step over and into instructions,
because you get access
to all of the variable values
for the entire execution of your shader.
For example, if you wanna look
at iteration 28 of a loop,
it's right there.
That's pretty cool.
Like the shader profiler,
the shader debugger also lets you
directly edit the source code
and see your changes live.
These tools combined let you
write huge performance shaders
without worrying about
seeing a black screen
and trying to figure out
where you went wrong.
Once again, if you want to learn more,
the "Metal Shader Debugging and Profiling"
talk also covers the shader debugger.
Finally, that brings us
to the Memory Viewer,
which is the go-to place to learn more
about your app's memory usage.
You can get here
by clicking on Memory in the navigator.
In modern rendering pipelines,
you have so much more explicit control
over the memory usage.
The Memory Viewer provides a breakdown
of all of the resources in your app
and their various properties.
You can also filter by categories,
including volatility, resource type,
access and whether they're used or not.
The "Delivering Optimized Metal Apps
and Games" talk from last year
also includes the Memory Viewer
and goes into much more detail.
So these are just some
of the amazing tools in the Metal Debugger
that can help you to understand
and take further advantage
of Metal and Apple GPUs in your app.
I encourage you to go through
each of the related talks from past WWDC's
for each tool
to learn more about them.
Of course, there are also
a few extra tools in Xcode,
such as the new shader validation,
that we didn't cover.
You can learn more about it
in this related talk.
Now, let's move on to Metal System Trace.
Metal System Trace
is a template in Instruments
that lets you capture
traits of your app over time,
as opposed to a single frame
in the Metal Debugger.
This is perfect
if you're trying to find issues
like stutters, dropped frames
or memory leaks.
We also provide the Game template,
which is a great set of tracks
if you're trying to investigate a game.
Let's start with the Encoder Timeline.
You can disclose the GPU track
to see a timeline
of all the command buffers
running in your app,
color-coded by frame.
This is perfect
to see the overlap between encoders
and to make sure there are
no bubbles where the GPU is idle.
It's also great for correlation
because you have access
to the state of system in other tracks,
like the current thermal state.
For example,
if your encoder is taking longer
because the device is in a critical state,
maybe you need to do less work
to let it cool down.
I encourage you to check out
the "Delivering Optimized
Metal Apps and Games" talk to learn more.
Next up is the new Shader Timeline.
If you want more detail
about encoders on Apple GPUs,
you can enable the Shader Timeline under
the Metal Application recording options.
The Shader Timeline shows you
which shaders are running at sampled times
during the execution
of your command encoder,
and this fine-grain detail
makes it really easy to see
why a given encoder is taking
a certain amount of time.
You can even see the number of times
that shaders were sampled
and an approximate GPU time
for how long they were running
in the table at the bottom.
In addition to the Shader Timeline,
we also have
the Performance Limiter tracks.
Once again, you can enable these
in the Metal Application recording options
under GPU Counter Set.
These tracks show you
the values of the limiters over time.
I really encourage you to check out
the "Optimize Metal Apps
and Games with GPU Counters" talk
if you're interested in
learning more about counters,
as it basically explains
every single limiter,
what they mean
and what to do if you see a high value.
This year, GPU Counters are also available
for non-Apple GPUs.
Lastly, the memory allocations track
shows you when resources,
such as buffers or textures,
are allocated or deallocated,
which can help you to find memory leaks
or just overall reduce
your memory footprint.
And that's a quick summary
of the tools we provide in Instruments
to help you debug your frame over time.
These, plus all of tools
from the Metal Debugger,
work together to help you understand
and take further advantage
of Metal and Apple GPUs in your app.
But that's a lot of tools,
and it might seem a little daunting,
so let's see them in practice.
Coming to iPad soon,
we have one of the world's greatest RPGs,
with over 100 hours of role-play
and over a million words of voice over.
Divinity: Original Sin 2.
[title screen music plays]
Larian Studios has given us
their first iPad game to play with,
and it's just beautiful.
It really goes to show the quality of
graphics that can run on modern Apple GPUs
and, of course, the amazing talent
and commitment at Larian.
Now I wanna show you how to use the tools
to debug something like this.
It's obviously a pretty advanced
rendering pipeline,
but let's see if the tools will guide us
and help to make any improvements.
I've got the game running on my iPad Pro,
so let's quickly look
at the GPU gauges in Xcode.
So we're now in the Metal Debugger
and looking at the summary of our frame.
In the overview we can see
that this app has four command buffers,
53 render command encoders
and almost 1000 draw calls.
Under Performance we can see that this
frame took about 26 milliseconds to render
and has almost
four-and-a-half-million vertices.
We can also see how much memory
the app is using for various resources.
And that brings us to the most interesting
section of the summary page: Insights.
If you remember from earlier,
Insights suggest changes
that you can make to your app
in order to improve memory usage,
bandwidth, performance or Metal API usage.
Each insight is accompanied
by a description of the problem,
a hint on how to fix it,
along with links to related documentation.
Let's look at some bandwidth insights.
So if you've watched the
"Harnessing Apple GPUs with Metal" talk,
you know that load/store actions
are pretty important.
And here, it seems like
we have a few unused resources.
If we look at the description,
it seems like this encoder
is storing a resource
that's never again used in this frame.
The insight gives us a hint
that we should consider
changing the store action to "Don't Care."
So I'm going to click
on the Show In Dependencies button
to jump right into
the Dependency Viewer to investigate.
The Dependency Viewer shows us
all of the GPU passes encoded by an app.
In essence, we can see when a resource is
stored in one encoder and used in others.
Focusing back in on this encoder,
we can see that the depth and
stencil textures are both set to "Store,"
but there's no line coming out of them,
so they're not actually being used
by any other
render command encoder in this frame.
The Metal Debugger knows this,
so it's put an insight right here
which suggests that we change
the store action to "Don't Care."
Now, if we do that, we'll save
almost 11 megabytes of memory bandwidth.
Let's go back to the summary page
and look at some other insights.
This time I'm gonna look
in the Performance category.
So it looks like
this render command encoder
might be an unnecessary depth pass.
So, Apple GPUs with a Tile Based
Deferred Rendering architecture
automatically perform
hidden surface removal
to avoid invoking
the fragment shader unnecessarily.
Once again, let's jump back
into the dependency viewer to investigate
by clicking on the
Show in Dependencies button.
So it looks like this encoder
takes 1.71 milliseconds of GPU time
and has roughly a million vertices.
From the thumbnail, it looks like
it's drawing the entire scene
into the depth and stencil textures.
So what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna disclose it in the navigator
and use the new thumbnail popover
to scroll through the draw calls.
And we can see
that our suspicions are confirmed.
It's then storing this result,
which is being used by this encoder...
which looks like it's drawing
the entire scene once again.
Now, this looks very much
like a traditional depth pre-pass
that you might use
to cull invisible meshes.
While on non-Apple GPUs this is a pretty
common technique to reduce overdraw,
it's not actually needed here
thanks to Apple GPUs
and their hidden surface removal.
So this encoder
could be eliminated entirely,
and we'd save
1.71 milliseconds of GPU time.
So in a matter of mere minutes,
we've captured Divinity: Original Sin 2
in the Metal Debugger
and used Insights to find
both a bandwidth issue
and an advanced performance issue,
along with a detailed description
about how to fix them.
What I'm trying to stress here
is that you don't need to be an expert
in the world of Apple GPUs
to start taking better advantage of them.
The tools are here to help you,
so capture your game
and let them guide you.
You have incredible hardware,
software and tools at your disposal,
so use them to create
your beautiful apps and games.
There are a ton of talks
that you can watch
to learn more about the tools
and how to take better advantage of Metal,
so I really encourage you
to go and check them out.
I hope you enjoyed today's session,
and have a great WWDC 2020.