Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, my name is Paul Borokhov,
and I'm a software localization engineer
at Apple.
Today, I will discuss how to build
localization-friendly layouts using Xcode.
We will go over some common patterns to
accomplish this goal and things to avoid
and discuss the tools that are
at your disposal to make your job easier.
First, let's take a look
at some common design patterns
that you want to follow in your apps
to make them localization friendly.
Crucially, these patterns are applicable
no matter what platform you develop on
or whether you employ manual layout,
auto layout or SwiftUI
to implement your designs.
First and foremost, you want to avoid
using fixed widths or frames
on any controls containing text.
In a practical sense,
this means remembering to call sizeToFit
with manual layouts,
avoiding fixed width constraints
with auto layout
and not setting explicit frames
in SwiftUI.
As an example,
consider this button on macOS.
While in English it looks good,
when we translate it into Greek,
which tends to use longer strings
for the same words,
you can see that we clip the word
midway through a character,
and the ellipsis is missing completely.
In most cases,
you can simply remove the fixed width
or change it to a greater-than
or equal-to constraint
to allow the text to show fully.
Next,
you want to avoid having fixed spacing
when it is between two distant objects.
Consider the example below.
There is a bunch of free space
between the Publish and Cancel buttons.
While this looks good in English,
when we translate to Greek,
you can see that the entire window grows
because the translations
for Publish and Cancel are longer.
But a more pleasant design
would allow the wider buttons
to simply eat into the space between them,
keeping the window width the same.
We can accomplish this with stacks
or greater-than or equal-to constraints.
On all platforms,
you will want to make sure
that text is allowed to wrap to multiple
lines when it makes sense to do so.
Consider the following example on iOS,
where UILabel is restricted
to one line of text by default.
This looks fine in English
on an iPhone 11 Pro.
To get a sense of how it might look
in other languages that are longer,
we can use double strings mode.
This feature, which can be enabled
both in the preview and at runtime,
simply doubles the text
inside every control and label.
Testing out this UI in double strings mode
shows that the text no longer fits
on one line and truncates as a result.
Setting the number of lines to 0
will allow this text to wrap properly.
Finally, try to avoid placing
too many controls in a fixed space
with no affordance
for an alternate layout.
Consider this example,
where I have four buttons side by side.
As you can see, in double strings mode,
they no longer fit on a single line
and end up truncating.
This can be
particularly problematic in bars,
where you cannot easily provide
an alternate layout.
We will see in the demo one of the ways
we can work around this problem.
Now let's jump into Xcode
to see these patterns in action
and how we can apply them
in a typical app.
Here I have a simple iOS app
that prompts the user
to pick their favorite food.
We have a title label, a regular label
and a bunch of buttons to make the choice.
I'm going to go ahead
and open the document preview.
I will then click English
at the bottom right
and choose Double-Length Pseudolanguage
to see what my UI might look like
when I go to localize my app.
Immediately, I see that my labels should
have their number of lines set to 0
so that they are allowed to wrap.
Once I fix that in the attributes
inspector, the labels look good,
but the buttons are still truncating.
Before I go and address that,
let me add a comment to my translator
explaining the context
for the title label.
I will select the title,
switch over to the identity inspector
and provide a helpful comment
in the Localizer Hint field.
Now, to address the truncated buttons,
I have a couple of options.
Perhaps instead of using strings
in these buttons,
I could use pictures of the food
so that they're all the same size.
The approach we will cover today
will be to change the layout
of the buttons from horizontal to vertical
when there is not sufficient space
to display them all side by side.
You can do this by placing the buttons
in a horizontal stack view
and then querying its layout fitting size
to determine whether it has sufficient
space to display all of its content.
If it doesn't, we will change
its orientation to vertical.
Conveniently, I already have
a custom class written to do just that,
so I will simply set it
in the storyboard...
and make a connection to the leading
constraint of the stack view.
If you want to see the details of how
this dynamic behavior is implemented,
go ahead and download the companion
sample project below this video.
Since this is a code change, I will not
be able to see its effects in the preview,
and I will need to build and run the app.
First,
let's just try running it in English.
As you can see, the layout hasn't changed
from what I have defined
in Interface Builder.
Now let's try running it again
in double strings mode.
I will go into the scheme editor,
go into the Options tab...
and select Double-Length Pseudolanguage
from the app language pop-up.
Since I haven't changed the app,
I will run it with Command-Control-R
to relaunch the already-built version.
You can see that the labels
have wrapped as we expect
and our stack view has also changed
its orientation to vertical
to accommodate the longer buttons.
Now, I have also set up
a first-generation iPhone SE here
with the largest non-accessibility
dynamic typeset.
You can see that even in English,
the layout gracefully adjusts to
accommodate the narrower screen width.
I can open the Accessibility Inspector
from Xcode
to change the dynamic type settings
to the default.
And as you can see, the layout reverts
back to the horizontal layout as expected.
I can also use Xcode's
Environment Overrides feature...
to do the same thing.
We just saw a lot of the design
best practices applied in the demo,
as well as some tools
that Xcode provides for you
to make it easy
to test your app in other languages
and validate that the layout works well.
Let's recap some of the tools
that we used in the demo
to achieve a localization-friendly layout
and see additional ones
that are at your disposal.
As we saw in the demo,
the document preview allows you
to preview your UI adjustments immediately
without having to build and run your app.
It supports the pseudolanguages,
as well as any localizations
that you have in your application,
as we will see shortly.
Scheme options allow you to runtime test
your app in specific languages,
including the numerous pseudolanguages.
To quickly change dynamic type settings
and verify that your app
adapts to them accordingly,
you can add the dynamic type widget
to Control Center on iOS,
as well as use the Accessibility Inspector
and Xcode's Environment Overrides feature
with devices
that are attached to your Mac.
There are additional tools
that Xcode provides
to make your job even easier
when implementing your layouts.
Just like in your source code,
Interface Builder provides fix-its
with quick solutions to common problems
like suboptimal or missing constraints
when using auto layout.
The "Embed in" feature
in Interface Builder
allows you to adopt modern container views
for multiple controls
that automatically provide
the correct constraints
for a wider variety of scenarios,
including stack views and grid views.
Now let's jump into Xcode
to see auto layout fix-its
and the "Embed in" functionality
in action.
Here I have a xib for a Mac app
in which I have not added
any auto layout constraints yet.
You can immediately see that there is
a warning icon in the document sidebar
for the top-level window.
If I click it,
I will see multiple localization issues
being reported about missing constraints.
If we open up the document preview
and choose
the Double-Length Pseudolanguage,
we can see that none of the controls
grow to accommodate the longer text.
If we build and run the app,
we can also see
that the UI does not flip in Arabic.
Going back to the list of issues,
perhaps seeing so many at once
is a bit overwhelming,
and I want a quick way
to resolve them all.
If I click
the "Resolve Auto Layout Options" button
in the bottom right of the canvas,
there is an option to Add Missing
Constraints for all views in the window,
so let me try that.
Now all the controls have constraints,
but I still have
a bunch of localization warnings.
Let's look at the one
about the Publish button.
We don't really need
this fixed width at all,
and it was added because the button
happened to be a little larger
than its intrinsic content size,
the natural size of the view
that takes only its contents into account.
I can go ahead
and click the yellow triangle
and choose the Remove Constraint fix-it
to resolve this issue.
Next, I have the OK button
with a width of 70.
In some languages, the word for OK
could be much longer,
so we do not want
to restrict the width here.
However, for languages like English
with very short translations,
we don't want a tiny button either.
Conveniently, the fix-it pop-over provides
an option to do just what we want--
choose the Set Constraint Greater Than
or Equal to Minimum Width
to get appropriate behavior
for all languages.
Next, let's make sure that the Cancel and
Publish buttons can't overrun each other.
This is highlighted by the
"Trailing constraint is missing" warning
for the Publish button.
We can choose the Fixed Leading and
Resizing Trailing Constraint option here,
as we want the space to the right
of the button to be flexible in this case.
Finally, we can resolve
all of the misplaced views
by clicking the windows content view
and clicking the Update Frames button
in the lower right of the canvas.
Now I'm down
to just three localization warnings.
I could go ahead and resolve them here,
but I will take the opportunity
to illustrate the "Embed in" functionality
in Xcode instead.
The entire top part of this dialogue
looks a lot like a spreadsheet,
so let's try embedding it in a grid view,
which is specifically tailored
for these kinds of layouts.
Before we start, I will fix the width
and height of the icon
because I do not want it to change size.
Let's also add a height constraint
to the description input field
since we always want it
to be two lines tall.
We will do this by control-click
and dragging over the text field...
and choosing Height from the pop-up menu.
Finally, the vertical constraint
between the image and the Publish button
is no longer needed, so we can delete it.
Now let's select all the text fields
and the checkbox,
click "Embed in" at the bottom right
and choose Grid View.
The layout of the controls
is now managed entirely by the grid view,
so they don't need
any explicit constraints.
Of course, I must still constrain
the grid view to its siblings,
so let me do that by adding standard
space constraints on the top,
leading and trailing edges...
and set the bottom space to 27.
Using standard space gives me spacing
recommended
by the Human Interface Guidelines,
which automatically changes
based on the context,
avoiding the need for hard-coded values.
The bottom space of 27
was given to me by my designer,
so that's what I will use.
Our OK button used to be trailing
aligned with the text field above it,
and that went away
when we put it in the grid view,
so let's add it back
by control-click and dragging
from the OK button in the canvas
to the grid view
in the document sidebar...
and choosing Trailing
from the menu that appears.
Next, I need to merge the cells
in the first row
so that the title can span both columns
and move the Ignore Alerts checkbox
from the first column to the second.
First, let me select the top two cells
in the document sidebar
by holding down the Command key
as I click them,
then choose Merge Cells
from the row options menu in the canvas.
To move the checkbox, I will simply drag
and drop it from one cell into the other.
The basic structure is now done,
but the layout doesn't quite match
what I want.
First, let's adjust the grid view
attributes to match our expectations.
I will select the grid view
and then show the attributes inspector.
Since we have text in our grid view,
we should set our row alignment attribute
to First Baseline.
We also want to set
the X placement to "Fill"
so that all the available space
is taken up by the content inside.
The spacing should match standard spacing,
implying row spacing of 12
and column spacing of 8.
And we still have an unnecessary
width constraint on the Name label,
so let's go ahead and remove that.
We also don't want the first column
to be any wider than it needs to be,
so let's set
the horizontal hugging priority
of the Name and Description labels to 749,
causing the grid view's column
to hug them tightly.
We choose 749
because it is lower than the labels'
default compression priority of 750,
but higher than the window's
holding priority of 500.
Finally, set the vertical content
hugging priority of the grid view to 600
so that our window
cannot be resized vertically.
Looks like we have misplaced views again,
but we can quickly resolve that
by clicking the window's content view
and then clicking the Update Frames button
in the lower right of the canvas.
Now let's open up the document preview
and see how our app looks
in different languages.
Greek...
Chinese...
and Double-Length Pseudolanguage.
All look great.
Now let's do a quick runtime test
in Arabic as well.
No issues. Looks perfect.
Before we wrap up, I wanted to call out
the importance of user testing
for delivering
a high-quality localized app.
Of course, no amount of automation
and scrupulous testing
can replace human-driven testing
by native language speakers.
These testers
will be able to immediately spot
glaring issues in your application,
such as inconsistencies
with OS terminology,
truncated and clipped text which might
not be obvious to a non-native speaker,
as well as out-of-context translations,
which no automation or fix-its
can determine.
This testing is particularly critical
if you're adding new localizations
or making big UI changes to your app.
Customers will be very excited
to see their app
is finally localized
into their native language.
And making a good first impression
will do wonders
for building a good relationship
and reputation
for your brand in a new market.
In summary, as international customers
are the majority of your customers,
it is important that you are aware
of the impact localization will have
on the design and layout of your app.
By following the localization-friendly
design patterns
that we have discussed and demonstrated,
you can make nondisruptive adjustments
to your app to make it truly world ready.
Finally, UI testing by native speakers
of the localizations
can make a significant impact
in the quality of your localized apps
and the impression they leave on users.
Thanks for watching.