Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name is Dina,
and I'm an iOS engineer here at Apple.
And today,
I'm gonna introduce you to HealthKit
and get you started building
your first health application.
Our own health data
makes up some of
the most personal parts of who we are.
Whether it's tracking menstrual cycles
and fertility to get pregnant,
or my lab test result
from my doctor's appointment,
and even the workout I completed
this morning on my Apple Watch.
Ready access to our own health data
is one of the most empowering
developments of modern technology.
Today, there are over 18,000 applications
on the App Store
that all focus on improving
our health and fitness.
That's mind-blowing!
Like, seriously, it's mind-blowing.
There are applications today
that help us reach our fitness goals
at home by providing at-home workouts,
help us track
our menstrual cycles and fertility,
and even log the food that we eat
to help us reach our goal weight.
There is a whole diversity
of different applications available today
that help us take control
over our health.
All of these applications are built
on the foundation of HealthKit.
HealthKit is a framework that creates
a central repository
of all the users' health data,
allowing applications to read data
from it, and also contribute data to it
to help create
the most seamless user experience.
We can interact with our health data
on multiple devices,
including our iPhone,
Apple Watch, even iCloud.
HealthKit securely stores and synchronizes
all of our health data
across these devices,
so you as a developer
don't have to worry about handling that.
HealthKit also guards users' privacy
by giving us explicit control
over what data
applications have access to.
HealthKit is a framework that helps create
a more seamless health application,
while also protecting our health data.
So, today, we're gonna join
this healthy community of ours
by building an application
of our own with HealthKit
called SmoothWalker.
And just like its name,
the goal of this application
is to allow us to record
the walks that we've been on,
and visually see the daily steps
we've taken over the past week.
To build SmoothWalker, we'll need
to accomplish three different tasks.
The first one being setting up HealthKit
in our Xcode project.
Once we do,
we'll be able to start saving data,
specifically, the distances we've walked.
And finally, we can read data
to display our daily step count
over the past week in our application.
To set up HealthKit,
we'll need to accomplish
several different tasks.
The first one being we'll need to enable
the HealthKit capability
in our Xcode project.
Once we do,
we'll need to check whether or not
the platform we're running on
supports HealthKit.
And finally,
we'll create an HKHealthStore,
the entry point to the HealthKit API.
To enable the HealthKit capability
in your application,
you'll select the target that you want
to integrate users' health data into,
you'll tap "Signing and Capabilities,"
and hit that "Add Capability" button.
You'll type in HealthKit,
and right then and there,
you'll add the HealthKit framework
into your application,
which will allow you to retrieve and store
users' health information.
We'll now need to check whether or not
the platform we're running on
supports HealthKit.
It's really common for developers
to have one application
and have it run on multiple platforms
or operating systems.
So we'll need to check whether
the platform we're running on right now
supports HealthKit.
You'll need to import HealthKit,
and then, using HKHealthStore,
you'll check whether or not
health data is available.
If it is,
you'll continue being able to integrate
users' health data into your application.
If not, then make sure
that your application
is still able to operate
without having users' health data.
Finally, we'll create an HKHealthStore.
An HKHealthStore is
what I like to think of
as the gateway or portal
to the world of health data.
It's what you'll use when you wanna
request access to users' health data,
it's how you'll save data,
and even read data using queries.
You only need to create one instance
and reuse it across the life cycle
of your application.
There's no need
to create multiple instances.
Here we have our healthStore object,
the one that we'll be using
across the entirety of our application.
And if health data is available,
we'll instantiate our healthStore object.
And setting up HealthKit is that easy.
Enabling the HealthKit capability,
checking whether or not
our platform supports HealthKit,
and creating an HKHealthStore.
That's all you need to do.
Now that we've finished
setting up HealthKit,
let's move on to saving data,
specifically, the distances we've walked.
But before we do,
we'll need to take a deeper look
about how HealthKit organizes
and structures our data.
I have this little ritual of mine,
where right before
any presentation or talk,
I like to do a little bit of a workout.
It helps boost up my energy
but also calm my nerves.
There's nothing a couple of push-ups
or a couple of sprints can't fix.
So that's what I did
right before this presentation,
I did a quick workout.
So let's see all of the health data
that was recorded during my workout.
For my workout, I went for a walk
from 2:35 to 3:00 p.m. today.
I walked outside
because the weather was gorgeous,
partially cloudy, low humidity,
great for a good hair day.
I walked 628 meters,
and I was blasting Lizzo and Rico Nasty
a little bit too loudly on Apple Music,
and should probably turn down
the volume moving forward
to preserve my hearing health.
Five minutes into my walk,
I also started noticing
some mild abdominal cramping
due to the fact
that my period's gonna start any day now.
All of these different types
of health data
are stored as health samples.
Health samples are all structured
in a very similar pattern.
They all have the associated type of data
that they represent,
the value of that type of data,
the time these health events occurred,
and metadata, which represents
any additional information
we wanna store about these samples.
Like whether or not my workout
was outdoors or indoors,
the weather outside,
the device that recorded it,
and even the application
that wrote it.
As all of these different types of data
are stored as samples,
there are some nuanced differences
between all of them.
Right now, I'm gonna focus on one
type of sample, called quantity samples.
Quantity samples store a numerical value
and unit associated with our health data.
Perfect for storing the distance we walk,
and our headphone audio-level exposure.
Regardless of type, we always want
to remain in control of our data.
And to do so,
HealthKit has its authorization system,
which will allow you
to request authorization
for users' health data
by specific data type.
And to give users the most control over
what data applications have access to,
read permissions and write permissions
are handled separately.
So, your user may or may not
grant you permission to the data
that you requested for
depending on the sensitivity of it
and what they feel comfortable sharing.
Any time you request authorization,
this screen on the right
might appear to the user.
This is HealthKit's authorization sheet.
It allows the user
to grant or deny permission
to the data
that you're requesting access for,
so it's important to request authorization
in context
so the user has an understanding
of what this screen is
and why this application needs
access to their health data.
You'll be required to define two keys
in your application's info.plist,
Health Update Usage Description
and Health Share Usage Description.
This will give you an opportunity
to briefly explain
what your application does
and how it interacts
with the user's health data.
Another important part of context
is requesting authorization
when there's good timing.
Request authorization any time you intend
to interact with the user's health data,
whether that's saving
or reading their health data.
Onboarding is also another great place
to request authorization
because that's usually where
the user has an understanding
of what your application does
and how it'll use their health data
in the experience.
As requesting authorization in context
is really important,
make sure to request authorization
for only the data that you need
to create the best experience
for the user.
If, for instance,
you requested authorization
for all HealthKit data types,
that's well over 100, by the way,
then the user might be
a little bit confused
as to why an application that's
helping them perform a swimming workout
is also asking them for all the times
they brushed their teeth.
I mean, you could be hitting
that really niche group of athletes
who swim while also brushing their teeth,
but I'd be a little bit skeptical.
Finally, request authorization
every time you intend
to interact with the user's health data.
HealthKit is the source of truth
when it comes to user permissions,
and user permissions can change
at any time outside of your application.
So, make sure to request authorization
so your application stays up to date.
To save the distance
I walked during my workout today,
the first thing we'll need to do
is request write access
to our walking-distance data type
using HealthKit's authorization system.
Once we do, we'll need to create
our walking-distance sample
and save that sample
using our health store.
To request write access,
what we'll need to do
is to find the type of data
that we want write access to.
In this case, it's just our
distanceWalkingRunning quantity type.
Then we'll call
the requestAuthorization method
on our healthStore,
passing in the data
that we want to write to and read from.
In SmoothWalker, we're only writing
the distances we've walked,
we're not reading any of that data,
so we're only gonna request write access.
Finally, we'll know if we successfully
requested authorization
in our completion handler.
Success in this case does not mean
that the user has granted permission
to these data types,
it just means that you successfully
requested authorization.
And if it failed,
you can always try again.
User privacy is so important when it comes
to our sensitive health data,
so make sure
when requesting authorization
to only ask for what you need,
when you need it, every time.
We finished requesting write access,
so let's move on to our final two tasks
of creating our sample that represents
the distance I walked during my workout,
and saving that sample
using our health store.
We'll need to define
the type of data that we wanna save,
which is our quantity type,
distanceWalkingRunning,
the same quantity type
we requested write access for.
Then we'll need to instantiate
the start and end time
of when I walked that distance,
in this case
it was 2:35 and 3:00 p.m. today.
All quantity samples in HealthKit
are stored with an associated HKQuantity.
HKQuantities represent the value and unit
associated with this sample.
So, for my walk today,
I walked a distance of 628 meters.
A really powerful part of HealthKit
is that it can convert between
different units for you.
So, for instance, if I wanted to see
all the distances I've walked
in meters in one application,
but in yards in another application,
then HealthKit can do all that conversion
for you on the same data set,
so you don't have to do
any of that manual math.
We have all the pieces needed
to construct our sample.
We'll pass in the type of data
we wanna create,
which is our distanceWalkingRunning
quantity type,
our quantity of 628 meters,
and our start and end date,
2:35 and 3:00 p.m. today.
Finally, we'll call our save method
on our healthStore,
and pass in our sample.
And we'll know if we successfully
saved the sample into the database
through our completion handler.
And just with that, we saved the distance
I walked during my workout.
We just took a deeper look
into how quantity samples
are structured and stored in HealthKit.
But not all of our data is necessarily
best represented in quantity samples,
like my workout
or my abdominal cramps today.
So, let's take a deeper look
into how HealthKit
organizes our data in a more general way.
To reiterate, we have quantity samples
that store a numerical value and unit
associated with our health data,
perfect for storing the distance I walked,
and my headphone audio-level exposure.
However, not all of my health data
is necessarily quantitative,
some of it is more qualitative.
And those are stored
as category samples in HealthKit,
where the value that you can record
comes from a predefined list
and it doesn't carry a unit.
So, for instance, when I logged
my mild abdominal cramping today,
I had the option to log
whether it was mild,
moderate, or severe,
and thankfully, it was just mild.
Both of these types of samples
represent singular values,
but not all of our health data
is necessarily represented
in that way in HealthKit,
like my workout,
which summarizes multiple values
and can carry multiple units
depending on the values
that it's summarizing.
My workout today summarized
the 628 meters I walked,
the three flights I climbed,
and even the 105 calories that I burned.
All of these different types of data
are samples in HealthKit.
Samples all have
an associated start and end time
of when these health events happened.
As we looked at quantity samples,
category samples, and workouts,
there are many more
different types of samples available
that I encourage you to look into.
Not all of our health data, though,
changes over time like samples do.
Some of our health data
remains more static over our life,
like my birthday or my blood type.
These are stored
as characteristics in HealthKit.
All of these different types of objects
are unified under HKObject,
where it has
the associated unique identifier for data
so you can easily reference it,
the device that recorded it,
and even the application that wrote it.
This hierarchy represents
the objects that are stored in HealthKit.
There is also a parallel hierarchy
of all the types in HealthKit.
For instance, the distance I walked today
was stored as a quantity sample
of the quantity type
"distanceWalkingRunning".
My mild abdominal cramps
were stored in a category sample
of the category type "abdominal cramps".
We just took a look into how HealthKit
organizes and structures our data.
So let's move on to
our final and third task
of reading data.
When it comes to reading health data,
you'll want to use queries.
HealthKit has a wide range of queries
to help you accomplish the task
that you have at hand.
Here are some of the many.
Today,
we're gonna look into three of them.
HKStatisticsQuery,
HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
and HKSampleQuery.
When it comes to using queries,
the first thing you'll need to do
is construct a query object.
You'll need to define the type of data
that you wanna read,
as well as specify a filter
that will restrict the results
returned from your query.
This is done by defining a predicate.
A predicate can vastly improve
the efficiency and performance
of your query by filtering out
the results that it returns.
Finally, you'll execute your query
on our health store
and get our results from our handler.
The first query we're gonna look in to
is HKStatisticsQuery,
and it is exactly what it sounds like.
It's a query that performs statistics
on samples,
specifically, quantity samples.
Let's take a look
at what type of statistics
can be computed with
an HKStatisticsQuery.
For instance, I might wanna know
the total amount of steps
I took during my workout,
or the total amount of calories I burned.
And if I'm feeling particularly brave,
I might wanna know the total amount
of caffeine I consumed today,
which might unveil
a matcha latte addiction.
I think I'll hold off on that one.
We can compute the sum
of these different data types,
but it doesn't make sense
to sum up all of our health data.
For instance, I might wanna know
my average UV exposure for today,
so I know that my SPF 50
and my shades had me fully protected.
Or to know that my HIIT workouts
were really impacting
my minimum resting heart rate.
And even know
my maximum body temperature
from when I was sick
a couple of weeks ago.
We can also compute the average minimum
and maximum on our health data.
It doesn't make sense to sum up
all of our body temperatures,
or compute the average calories
I burned during my workout.
So, the type of statistics we can compute
depends on what makes the most sense
and what reveals the most insightful
information about our health.
This is known as the aggregation style
of samples in HealthKit,
where the total steps I took
and my calories burned
are all cumulative,
while my UV exposure
and my heart rate are discrete.
Today, I wanna know the total amount
of steps I took this past week,
from June 15th to today.
Here are all my steps for the past week.
What I'll do is construct
an HKStatisticsQuery
specifying the type of statistics
I wanna compute, which is cumulative sum.
I'll execute it on our health store,
and we'll get back an HKStatistics object,
which has the start date and end date
of all the samples
that make up our statistic,
as well as our sum of 6,902 steps.
It's not that much. I probably should
really up my activity moving forward.
All of those samples were recorded
on my Apple Watch,
but sometimes when I go for a walk,
I like to bring my iPhone with me
in case I need to make
a couple of phone calls.
Both my Apple Watch and my iPhone
are both recording steps.
If we were to sum up all of my steps
over all of my devices,
then we would naively be double counting
a lot of those steps.
HKStatisticsQuery can help with
the deduplication of data.
For instance, on June 15th,
HKStatisticsQuery
will ignore those 900 steps
recorded on my iPhone
since that would be duplicated data,
but it would also add in
those additional 1,100 steps
that were recorded on my iPhone
when I forgot my Apple Watch at home.
So, we'll construct
our HKStatisticsQuery,
execute it on our health store
and get our updated HKStatistics object
with our new sum of 8,002 steps.
So I did better, but not by that much.
I'm more interested in the patterns
of my daily step count.
I wanna know the steps that I take
every day for the past week.
What we could do
is construct HKStatisticsQueries
for every day of the week.
That would be seven of them.
That might be fine for now,
but if I wanted to know
my daily step count over the past year,
then that would be well over
300 HKStatisticsQueries to manage
and that just becomes too much.
HealthKit has a solution.
It's called HKStatisticsCollectionQuery.
And it's a query that performs statistics
on fixed time intervals that you specify.
In this case,
we'll specify a daily cadence
of when I want the sum of my steps
to be computed.
I'll also need to specify an anchor date,
which represents
when our statistic starts being computed
and how our samples get bucketed.
When I construct
my HKStatisticsCollectionQuery,
I'll specify my anchor
of June 15th at midnight,
my time interval of a daily cadence,
and the statistics I wanna compute,
which is the sum.
I'll execute this on my health store,
and we'll get back
an HKStatisticsCollection object.
An HKStatisticsCollection object
is exactly what it sounds like.
It's a collection of HKStatistics.
So, for every day of the week,
we'll get an HKStatistics object
with the sum of our steps.
So, for Monday, June 15th,
I'll get a sum of 2,222 steps.
Tuesday, I'm not gonna lie,
I was super lazy,
didn't even get out of bed,
so I didn't take any steps.
Wednesday, I have a sum of steps of 1,100,
so I'll get an HKStatistics object
with a sum of 1,100.
And the rest will follow suit.
Here are some of the many charts in health
that are all powered
by HKStatisticsCollectionQueries.
It's incredible to see how one query
can unveil so much useful
and insightful information
about our health.
HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
is really powerful.
I wanna touch on
one of its other superpowers.
It can listen for updates
to the user's health data.
To do so,
we'll need to set its update handler
before executing the query.
That way, our query will be running
in the background
listening to any new statistics
or new data
coming into the health database.
Now, our query will be running
in the background indefinitely,
so we'll wanna make sure to call "stop"
when we're done collecting
all the data that we need.
So, let's go ahead
and use HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
in SmoothWalker
to display our daily step count
over the past week.
The first thing we'll need to do
is construct
our HKStatisticsCollectionQuery.
Once we do,
we'll execute it on our health store
and update our UI with
the HKStatisticsCollection object
we get back.
Let's move on to our demo.
All of the code you're about to see
is available online
through a sample Xcode project
for you to download
and to play around with.
Here, we have SmoothWalker
running in our simulator
in the left-hand portion of my screen.
The view is empty right now
because we haven't implemented the pieces
to display our daily step count.
In the upper right-hand corner,
we also have an "Add Data" button,
which will allow us
to add any new steps for today.
So, let's go ahead
and move over into our Xcode project
and implement all the pieces
we need to display our daily steps.
Here I am in
DailyStepCountTableViewController.
This is the ViewController that's powering
our view in the simulator right now.
We have an array
that's hooked up to our table view,
so all we need to do
is read our daily steps
and populate our array with that.
The first thing we'll need to do, though,
is request read and write access
to our step-count data.
We'll need to request authorization
where there's appropriate context.
A great place to do that
is in our method viewWillAppear.
That way, when our application loads
or we hit that "step count" tab,
our authorization sheet will appear.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Here, we define the type of data
that we want read and write access to,
which is our step-count data type.
Then using our healthStore,
we will request authorization,
passing in the data that we want
to write to and read from.
If we successfully request authorization,
we'll call the method
calculateDailyStepCountForPastWeek.
This is the method
where all the magic happens.
It's where we'll read our daily steps
and update our UI.
So, let's go down into this method.
Here I am in
calculateDailyStepCountForPastWeek.
We'll need to construct
an HKStatisticsCollectionQuery,
execute our query on our healthStore
and update our UI with our results.
The first thing we'll need to do
is define all the pieces
needed to construct our query,
like the type of data we wanna read,
which in this case is our step-count data.
We'll need our anchor,
which is Monday at 3:00 a.m...
our time interval,
which is a daily cadence.
There can be a lot of steps data
in HealthKit,
but we're only interested
in computing statistics
over the past week's worth.
So, we'll define a predicate
that we were only computing statistics
over the past week's worth
of step samples.
Here, I define my date
from one week ago,
and I'll construct my predicate
using HKQuery's predicateForSamples.
We have all the components needed
to construct our query,
so let's go ahead and do that.
Here I have my HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
passing in the type of data
I want to read,
which is our step count data,
our predicate of one week ago,
the statistics we want to compute,
which is our sum,
our anchor of Monday,
and our time interval of a daily cadence.
Now that we've constructed our query,
we'll need to update our UI
with the results we get back.
Here we have our initialResultsHandler.
When our query is done executing,
we'll get back our statistics collection,
and an error if there was any issue
reading our health data.
Here is where we'll update our UI.
If there are any statistics
to show in our table view,
we'll call our method
updateUIFromStatistics.
This is where we'll pass in
our statistics collection
and update our array
that's backing our table view.
So, let's go down into this method
and implement it.
Here I am in updateUIFromStatistics.
It takes a statisticsCollection object,
so we'll enumerate
over all of our statistics
and append it into our array
that's backing our table view.
Since we'll be updating our UI,
we wanna make sure
to dispatch back to the main thread.
Here we have our dataValues array,
which is the array
backing our table view and our UI.
It is an array of HKStatistics.
What we'll need to do
is enumerate over our statistics
for the past week
in our statisticsCollection object.
We'll define our start date
of one week ago,
and we'll enumerate until today.
Then we'll call our enumerateStatistics
method on our statisticsCollection,
and as we enumerate,
we'll append our statistics
into our array backing our table view.
Finally, when we're done enumerating,
we'll call reloadData.
This will refresh our table view
and update our UI.
The final thing we need to do, though,
is execute our query.
So, we'll go back up into our calculate
DailyStepCountForPastWeek method
and execute our query after setting
our initialResultsHandler.
And with that, I'll hit "run"
and let's see what happens.
Ah!
Our authorization sheet
just popped up on our device.
This will allow us
to deny or grant permission
to our step-count data for SmoothWalker.
Since I'm not particularly sensitive
about steps data,
I'll enable both
read and write access for it.
I'll hit "Turn All Categories On"
and hit that "Allow" button.
And our table view just updated with
all of our daily steps for the past week.
Let's go ahead
and try and add some data for today.
I'll add 800 steps.
I'll hit that "Add" button,
and as you can see,
our table view didn't update,
and that's because we haven't set
our updateHandler on our query.
So, let's go back into Xcode
and set up our updateHandler.
That way, our query will be
running in the background,
listening for any new health data
or any new steps coming in.
We'll set up our updateHandler
in our method
calculateDailyStepCountForPastWeek.
We'll need to set up our updateHandler
before we execute our query,
so that's where we'll do it.
Here, I have my statisticsUpdateHandler.
This'll get called
when there's any new data
that's coming into the database,
or if there's any new statistics.
We'll get back any new statistics,
a statisticsCollection object,
and an error
if there's any issue reading our data.
Here, we'll update our UI
calling the same method
we did in our initialResultsHandler.
Now our query is going to be
running in the background indefinitely,
listening to any new steps
that'll be added into the database.
So, we'll wanna make sure to call "stop"
when we're done collecting all the data
that we need.
A great place to do that
is in our method viewWillDisappear.
That way, our query will stop
when our view is no longer visible
on our device.
So, let's go ahead and implement that.
Here, we're in viewWillDisappear.
We'll stop our query in this method.
And with that, let's hit run again
and see what happens
when we add some new steps for today.
So, I'm gonna add some data,
I'll add 235 steps.
And our table view just updated
with that new step count.
And with that, we just finished displaying
our daily steps in our application.
Let's just take a look
at what we just did.
We constructed our
HKStatisticsCollectionQuery,
executed it on our healthStore,
and updated our UI
with our statisticsCollection object.
We just took a look at HKStatisticsQuery
and HKStatisticsCollectionQuery.
They are super powerful.
However, you may not always want
to compute statistics on health data,
and not all of
our health data is quantitative.
You can use HKSampleQuery
to retrieve the raw health samples
stored in the database.
Let's go take a look
at how we would do that.
Here, we'll define the type of data
I wanna read, which is my workouts.
Then I'll define a sort,
which will sort all of the objects
returned back from my query.
In this case, I want them sorted from
the most recent date that they finished.
Finally, we'll construct our sample query,
passing in the type of data we wanna read,
our predicate, which is nil,
our limit of one,
since we're only interested in
the most recent one workout, and our sort.
Finally, we'll execute our query
using our healthStore.
There are many other types of queries
available on HealthKit
to help you accomplish the task
that you have at hand.
We have HKAnchoredObjectQuery,
which will allow you to detect changes
in the user's database.
There's also HKActivitySummaryQuery,
which will allow you to display
the rich activity ring data
from our Apple Watch.
There's also HKWorkoutRouteQuery,
which will display all of the locations
we've been on during our outdoor workouts.
And with that, we finished integrating
HealthKit into SmoothWalker.
We discussed a lot today.
I wanna go over
some of the bigger takeaways.
HealthKit is a framework
that helps create and manage
essential repository
of the user's health data,
providing a rich ecosystem
for your health application.
However, our health data makes up some
of the most sensitive data on our device,
so make sure to request authorization
for only the data that you need,
when you need it, every time.
HealthKit has a rich type system
to help organize and structure
our health data.
We looked at quantity types,
category types, and even workouts,
but there are many more
that I encourage you to look into
to see what works best
for your health application.
HealthKit has a wide range of queries
to help you efficiently
and performantly read data.
We looked at SampleQuery
and StatisticsQueries today,
but there are many more to help you create
the next great health application.
We're so excited for you to join
our healthy community here at Apple,
and to see the incredible
health applications you'll build
that will revolutionize the way users
take control over their health.
I hope you have a wonderful rest
of your WWDC, and let's go get healthy.