Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone,
and welcome to "What's New in HealthKit."
My name is Netra,
and I'm a software developer
on the HealthKit team.
We have some exciting new developments
in HealthKit to share with you,
and we can't wait to see
what you do with them.
The first thing I want to share with you
is the ability to track symptoms
in HealthKit.
Tracking symptoms is an important aspect
of monitoring health data.
Our users might want to track
a wide range of symptoms.
This could be shortness of breath,
sleep or appetite changes,
or simply a running nose.
Symptoms offer valuable insights
into your health.
They can also help you or your doctor
make informed decisions
about diagnoses or treatment.
This year, we are proud to introduce
30 symptom data types to HealthKit.
We have attempted to cover
a wide range of symptoms.
Developers can now read and write
symptom samples in order to build
virtual health experiences in their apps.
We can't wait to see the amazing apps
you create using these symptom data types.
We recently introduced the ECG App
on Apple Watch.
An ECG, or electrocardiogram, is a test
that records the electrical pulses
that make up a heartbeat.
By looking at an ECG,
a doctor can gain critical insights
about your heart rhythm,
and also look for irregularities in it.
The ECG App on Apple Watch
can recall heartbeat and heart rhythm
using the electrical sensors
on the Digital Crown.
These waveforms can be viewed
in the Health app,
and they can also be exported as PDFs
to a doctor.
This year, we're putting the power of ECG
in the hands of all you developers.
In the latest version of iOS and watchOS,
ECG samples will be available for reading.
An ECG sample can be read
as an HKElectrocardiogram.
An HKElectrocardiogram represents
a waveform as a series of voltage values.
Now, this sample has some
important properties associated with it.
When you take an ECG on Apple Watch,
the recording is checked
for atrial fibrillation.
Atrial fibrillation is a form
of irregular rhythm.
It signifies that
the upper and lower chambers of your heart
are out of rhythm.
After a successful recording,
Apple Watch will give you the result
of the recording.
The result is in the form
of a classification.
The classification can be a sinus rhythm,
which means that the heart is beating
in a uniform pattern.
Or it can be atrial fibrillation.
Atrial fibrillation implies
an irregular heart rhythm.
It is an indication that the user
should probably go see their doctor.
If Apple Watch is unable
to determine the ECG result,
either due to a low or a high heart rate,
or due to any other reason,
the result is considered inconclusive.
There are some more important properties
that make up
an HKElectrocardiogram sample.
The next one is the symptomsStatus.
It tells us if the user associated
a symptom with this ECG.
We already saw the new symptom data types
introduced this year.
When a user takes an ECG,
quite often it's because they have
a symptom they are experiencing.
This could be heartburn
or tightness in their chest.
The symptom experienced
can be recorded along with the ECG.
As mentioned earlier,
the HKElectrocardiogram sample
is a collection of voltage measurements.
The sample is backed by more properties
that describe the measurements.
These include the average heart rate,
the sampling frequency
500 Internal Server Error
QTL_Cache/1.2.14
The number of voltage measurements refers
to the individual voltage measurements
that make up an ECG sample.
To retrieve the individual measurements,
you can run the HKElectrocardiogramQuery.
You can fetch the ECG samples
via any of the HealthKit queries
and then initialize
the HKElectrocardiogramQuery
with the fetched sample.
When this query is executed
on the health store,
you get the individual
voltage measurements backing the ECG
in the data handler.
Electrocardiograms are an important
diagnostic tool for heart health.
Another important metric
of the user's health is their mobility.
These are metrics that gauge
a user's functional exercise capacity,
or their ability to do aerobic work.
Mobility is strongly tied
to respiratory diseases and heart health.
Mobility is especially important
for patients recovering from an injury,
or aging individuals.
Mobility metrics are usually measured
across a period
where the user is walking without stopping
on a flat surface.
Your iPhone or Apple Watch
can also record some of this data
during bouts of walking.
HealthKit is proud to introduce
a new set of mobility types this year.
The first is the walking speed
and step length.
Walking takes strength, fitness, balance,
and coordination.
Changes in any of these areas could affect
your walking speed and step length.
This may also decline with age, injury,
pain, or illness.
Balance and coordination are captured
by the walking asymmetry
and double support percentage.
The next one is the stair ascent
and descent speed.
They are an indication
of your cardiovascular health,
balance and coordination.
Finally, the six-minute walk test distance
is a frequent clinical test for mobility.
The more mobile and fit you are,
the higher this number will be.
These data types are available for reading
and writing on the latest iOS and watchOS.
We have introduced some major features
in HealthKit this year.
These include symptoms,
the HKElectrocardiogram sample
and the HKElectrocardiogramQuery,
and the mobility data types.
We are so excited to see how you
take advantage of all these new types,
and we look forward to seeing
all the amazing apps that you create.
Go build great health apps, and as always,
let us know
if you have any feedback for us.
Thank you for watching.
Have a great a WWDC.