Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm JP Lacerda, and I work
on the Proactive Intelligence team.
An intelligent system experience
is a collaboration
between the operating system
and your apps.
It is a platform convention
and a quality of great design.
It's also powered in large part
by extensibility.
Let's talk about the huge opportunity
that you have with intelligence.
We'll start by defining
how we think about intelligence.
Then we'll walk through
the many intelligence entry points
on the system.
We'll conclude by talking about
how you can measure
the impact of intelligence on your app.
So let's define intelligence.
The goal of intelligence
is to make your Apple products
feel like they know you.
Like they understand you,
your goals, your intentions,
your habits, your preferences,
your interests,
and even your relationships.
And they can use this understanding
to help you achieve more
by accelerating you to a goal
that you already have in mind.
And discover more by enriching your life
with meaningful content, people, places
and apps,
delivered to you at just the right time.
Intelligence helps you accomplish all this
with less tedium
by saving you clicks or taps
to get to what you want,
and also fewer distractions
by helping you focus on what matters most.
Ultimately, intelligence allows
your Apple products
to give you superpowers.
As a developer, you play a crucial role
in the creation of these superpowers.
Your app can participate in intelligence
by integrating with the system,
which allows the system to see your app
as much more than a monolithic container.
The capabilities of your app
extend to the system.
And you get many more entry points
into your app beyond the home screen
when we make suggestions on your behalf.
Let's walk through some examples of this,
starting with Shortcuts.
Shortcuts lets you get things done
with your apps with just a tap
or by asking Siri.
The Shortcuts app is built right into iOS,
and allows you to set up simple or complex
multi-step shortcuts and automations.
You can run Shortcuts with your voice,
and get relevant suggestions
throughout the system,
like in the new Siri Suggestions widget,
in Search, and on the lock screen.
New in iOS 14, if your app vends a widget,
a Smart Stack will position your widget
at the top of the stack
at just the right time,
like the Weather widget in this example.
Let's look at other
intelligence entry points, like Sharing.
Our devices allow users to create
beautiful content like photos and videos.
Sharing Suggestions make it really easy
to get content to the people in groups
that matter the most to you.
Intelligence also makes it easier
to get information on your app
to other parts of the system.
Like with Siri Event Suggestions,
you can get reservations
from your app into Calendar.
All you have to do is book a reservation,
like a restaurant reservation,
and it'll automatically appear
in Calendar, just like this.
On the lock screen, Siri can notify you
when it's time to leave
for your restaurant reservation
based on current traffic conditions.
When you open Maps,
you get Siri Suggestions,
which makes it super convenient
to get directions to the airport,
for example, with just one tap.
Siri can proactively suggest
turning on Do Not Disturb,
so you can stay focused
on what matters most,
like the movie you're about to watch.
And we may even provide a suggestion
to check in for a flight,
right on your lock screen.
But how can we measure
the impact of intelligence?
Privacy is a fundamental human right,
and at Apple, it's one of our core values.
If you choose to opt in,
we use analytics from your device
to help us improve our products.
The collected information
does not identify you personally,
and can be sent to Apple
only with your explicit consent.
Participating in intelligence
is a great way
to improve the traffic, utility
and visibility of your app.
For example, when a user engages
on their first Sharing Suggestion
for your app,
they will, on average,
share twice as much as they did before
through your app.
We saw this trend across many apps
that opted into Sharing Suggestions.
Participating in intelligence
can also be a great way
to make your app more useful
to your users.
Some airlines shared with us
that they saw
82% of notification check-ins
come from their Siri Event Suggestion
check-in action.
Intelligence can also be a great way
to increase the visibility of your app.
Some third-party apps are seen,
on average,
five times every day on the lock screen,
in Sharing, in Search,
and other entry points
throughout the system.
So, play your part in intelligence.
You'll get more entry points into your app
and help your users build superpowers.
Here are some concrete ways
you can do that.
Think about which entry points
would be best suited to your app's actions
and adopt those that make sense.
You should also consider
how you will measure
the impact of intelligence on your app.
And finally, while this section covered
your opportunity with intelligence
as a developer,
you can build
an even more holistic view of intelligence
by looking at it
from your users' perspective
and how they may string together
these various experiences.
To help you do this,
in the "Meet People Where They Are"
section,
Radhika is going to take you through
a day in the life of a user
who benefits
from intelligent system experiences.
I hope you've enjoyed this session,
and enjoy the rest of your WWDC.