[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Ada, an engineer on App Clips.
I'll be joined
by my colleague Luming today
to show you all you need to know
about linking to your app clips.
App Clips provides an entry point
for your users
to experience your app
with minimum friction.
When your users need your app's
functionality to perform a task,
your app clip is presented to the user
seamlessly with a deep-link navigation.
This session covers what you have to do
to handle linking into your app clip
and configure the linking experience.
First, let's take a look at an example
of how one can perform a task
with an app clip.
Imagine you come across a smoothie stand.
You really want a nice, cold smoothie.
You find an NFC tag with a sign that says,
"Tap here to order."
You tap the tag and a card pops up
at the bottom of the screen
which has a brief description
of the smoothie-ordering app clip.
When you tap on the "Open" button,
the app clip is launched on your device,
taking you directly
to the smoothie-ordering page.
You complete the purchase with Apple Pay,
and now you have a smoothie in your hand.
The linking magic happens in these steps.
The NFC tag actually encodes a URL that's
registered with an app clip experience,
which I'll explain later in this session.
Once you tap "Open,"
the app clip gets launched with a URL
that is passed via an NSUserActivity,
and the app clip takes you directly
to the ordering page.
Besides NFC, app clip links
can also appear in other places.
These are URLs that could be encoded
in physical tags or visual codes,
or associated
with a physical location on the map.
Let's go through
each of these linking methods.
As I mentioned in my example earlier,
an NFC tag can encode an app clip URL
that users can tap their phones on
to open an app clip.
An app clip URL can also be encoded
in a QR code,
which people can scan to open an app clip.
App clip links can show up
on the Maps place card
for registered businesses,
and also in the Siri nearby suggestions.
You can also open an app clip from Safari.
If your web page is configured
with a Smart App Banner for app clip,
people can tap the "Open" button
in that banner to open the app clip.
And when they send an iMessage
with that web page's URL,
it's presented as
a special app clip link bubble,
which gives the user a choice to open
the link in the app clip, or in Safari.
And to give you an even better experience,
later this year,
Apple will be releasing
the new app clip codes,
which is the best way for your users
to discover your app clip.
It's visually beautiful and distinct,
so when they see one, they know
there's an app clip waiting for them.
Each app clip code encodes a URL.
Apple will be releasing tools
later this year
that can create
these beautiful visual codes.
Now that we've looked
at the different ways
people can follow links
into your app clip,
let's go through the steps
an app clip developer needs to do
to set up this linking experience.
First, you have to make changes
to your web server
and your app clip project
so these links
can be handled by the app clip.
Next, you have to configure
the app clip card,
which is the card that introduces the user
to the app clip
and is part of the app clip experience.
You can set up the default
and advanced app clip experiences
on App Store Connect.
Lastly, let's configure
the Smart App Banner
to show your app clip on your web page.
If the contents of your web page
can be delivered
as a better and more streamlined
app clip experience,
consider adding this banner
to provide a way for your users
to get to the app clip from that web page.
First, let's start with configuring
your web server and your app clip
for link handling.
The association between your website
and your app clip must be validated
for the app clip to be able
to present contents
in place of the website's URL.
To securely associate your app clip
with the server,
you will need
the apple-app-site-association file
on your web server,
along with the appropriate
associated domains entitlement
on your app clip.
Then you have to update the code
in your app clip
to handle links from incoming
NSUserActivities.
First, let's update
the apple-app-site-association file
on the web server.
This file is located in
a .well-known subdirectory
in your server's root folder.
If you have set up universal links
for your app before,
you probably have this file
already set up on your server,
and the root dictionary
has other entries already,
such as web credentials and app links.
To declare the new app clips association
in this file,
add another entry in the root dictionary
with the key "appclips"
and the value containing a dictionary
containing a single "apps" key
that is set to an array containing
your app clips app identifier.
Next, let's update the app clip project
to add the associated domains entitlement.
In Xcode,
navigate to your project settings
and add the associated domains capability.
Under domains, add a new string
"appclips:your-website-domain."
Now that both your website
and your app clip
have been set up with associated domains,
let's add code to handle NSUserActivity,
which contains the URL
passed into your app clip.
If your app clip has adopted
the new SwiftUI app life cycle,
this is how you would add a handler
for the web-browsing userActivity.
In that method, you can get the web page
URL property from the NSUserActivity.
Then you can parse that URL
and direct the user to the linked content.
Keep in mind that once the user upgrades
from the app clip to the app,
navigating to that app clip link
will actually open your app,
rather than the app clip.
So make sure your app
also has similar code
for handling the URLs
for universal links as well.
If your app clip uses
the UIKit's SceneDelegate life cycle,
here's some similar code
for handling incoming user activities
in the UISceneDelegate.
To learn about
how to set up associated domains,
and handling NSUserActivities,
please refer to the "What's New
in Universal Links" sessions.
To test the URL handling code
in your app clip in Xcode,
you can specify a test URL
to be passed to your app clip.
Open up the scheme editor in Xcode.
Select the "arguments" tab.
Under "environment variables,"
specify the _XCAppClipURL variable.
Now when you run your app clip from Xcode,
it'll be launched with this URL.
Now that we're done configuring
the web server and the app clip,
let's configure the app clip experiences.
Each app clip experience starts
with the app clip card
that the user sees
when they tap on an app clip link.
It shows the information about
the app clip,
and asks for the user's consent
to open it.
When coming up with the metadata to use
to configure the app clip card,
please follow these requirements
on the length of the title and subtitle
for the optimal layout of the card.
There are also requirements for
the image's size, aspect ratio and format
for the best user experience
across all devices.
The image you choose
should match the experience
this app clip action delivers.
Now let's set up the app clip card
on App Store Connect.
After you've delivered a build
containing both your app and your app clip
to App Store Connect,
the app clip should be visible
on App Store Connect
with a new app clip configuration section.
This is where you can start setting up
the default and advanced
app clip experiences.
The metadata for
the default app clip experience
includes the app clip card's image,
subtitle and the verb for the action.
There's a list of predefined actions
you can choose from.
This metadata will be used
in a Smart App Banner in Safari,
and in the app clip link bubble
in Messages.
And also in the app clip card
when it's presented.
If you want your app clip to be accessible
from more than just Safari and Messages,
you must set up
an advanced app clip experience
by clicking the "Get Started" link here.
Each advanced app clip experience is tied
to a URL
which can be encoded in a physical tag,
such as the NFC tag, or a QR code,
so your app clip can be launched
from these physical invocation methods.
After clicking through
some introduction screens,
you will arrive on this page
where you can specify the URL
for the advanced app clip experience.
For the same app clip, you can set up
multiple advanced app clip experiences,
each with a different URL.
I'll give you some examples
of multiple app clip experiences in a bit.
On the next page,
you can set up the image, title, subtitle,
and choose an action verb
for the app clip card for this experience.
You can also choose to associate
this app clip experience
with a physical location.
Now let's take a look at some use cases
of advanced app clip experiences,
and the best practices for
registering URLs for these experiences.
A single app clip could handle
different types of tasks,
and therefore
different app clip experiences
can be customized for the same app clip.
For example, this restaurant app clip
provides two types of experiences
for their customers:
the food-ordering experience,
where users can view the menu
and place their order,
and the reservation experience,
where customers can reserve tables.
In this case, two advanced
app clip experiences can be set up.
One for melamela.example/order
where the image could be
a picture of their menu,
and the subtitle "View menu and order."
And another one
for melamela.example/reservation
where the image could be a picture
of the restaurant setting,
and the subtitle "Reserve a table."
One thing to remember about the way
the URL is mapped to the app clip
is that it's based on
the most specific prefix match
against registered
app clip experience URLs.
That means you don't need to register
every single possible app clip URL
for the business.
Do keep in mind, though, that even if
your registered experience URL
is used only as a prefix,
your app clip must be able
to handle being launched
with the exact registered URL.
This can happen when your app clip is
invoked through Siri nearby suggestions,
and from Maps.
Here's an example of how you can register
one app clip experience URL
to work with multiple invocation URLs.
A bike shop
has an online bike rental system.
It has hundreds of bikes for rent,
which are identified by an ID number.
The URLs for reserving these bikes
will specify that ID
in the query string argument.
Fortunately,
this bike shop does not need to register
an advanced app clip experience
for every one of these URLs
because URLs are matched
based on prefix match.
Only one app clip experience URL
needs to be registered:
https://bikesrental.example/rent.
That is enough to deliver
an app clip experience
for all these bike URLs with that prefix
and different query string arguments.
Here's another example
to explain a strategy
for picking the URLs to register
for advanced app clip experiences.
The café in this example
is a big chain with multiple locations,
where each location basically offers
similar experiences to their customers.
Because of the common URL format
for all the locations,
which all start with
https://brighteggcafe.example/store/,
we can just register
an app clip experience
for that URL prefix.
When their customers follow a link
to any of their stores,
they'll get the same app clip card.
But let's say the coffee shop
wants to provide
a more special app clip experience
for its flagship store in Cupertino.
To handle this, you can also register
the Cupertino store URL
for a different app clip experience
with a different image and subtitle text.
The main takeaway here is you can register
a shorter, more general URL prefix
that covers most cases,
and register a more specific URL
only when you need to provide
a different app clip experience.
For more information on setting up
the default and advanced
app clip experiences
on App Store Connect,
please refer to the "What's New
in App Store Connect" session.
And for best practices
on the app clip card design,
please refer to
the "Design Great App Clips" session.
Now to the last step for handling
linking into your app clip,
setting up the Smart App Banner
to open your app clip.
This is how people can open app clips
from a web page in Safari,
or in Messages when a web page URL
that has this banner configured is sent.
If you have set up Smart App Banners
for your app before,
you must be familiar with
the Apple iTunes App Meta Tag
that you add to your web page's HTML
to specify your app's unique identifier.
To configure this banner
for your app clip,
set the app-clip-bundle-id
content attribute
to the app clip's bundle identifier.
You should continue to set
the app ID attribute as well,
so it will fall back to
the full app-linking behavior
for users with systems older than iOS 14.
Safari will verify the domain association
between the website and the app clip
before showing the banner.
By default, when the user taps on
a Smart App Banner's "Open" button,
they will see the default app clip card
configured for this app clip.
But if you register this URL
with an advanced app clip experience,
you can customize the metadata
for the experience
such that the user could see
a more descriptive title in the banner
and get an app clip card that's tailored
for the task this app clip performs.
To demonstrate what we have talked about
on handling linking for your app clip,
I'll ask my colleague Luming
to give us a demo.
Luming.
Thanks, Ada,
for your wonderful introduction
on linking to your app clips.
I'm Luming, an engineer
from the App Clips team,
and today, I'll be showing you
how to link to your app clip.
To link your users to your app clip
through physical or digital invocation
you need to set up
associated domains first.
As my colleague, Ada,
mentioned earlier in this talk,
we need to both configure our web server
and our app clip project
for link handling.
So let's start with the web server first.
Here, I have the source code
of my web server.
It's a pretty straightforward
static website.
Under the root directory of my web server,
I have already created
a .well-known folder, and within it,
there's
an apple-app-site-association file.
My AASA file has already been configured
for universal links, Handoff,
and web credentials
with Password AutoFill.
Now all we need to do here is to update
the AASA file to link to our app clip.
And there we go.
Now that we have already configured
our web server,
let's come back
to the Fruta Xcode project.
To link your app clip, you need
to register to handle userActivity
of type NSUserActivityTypeBrowsingWeb.
In our app clip's WindowGroup declaration,
I'll add a new
onContinueUserActivity handler
of TypeBrowsingWeb.
Inside it, I'll parse the incoming URL
and get the queryItems in the URL.
After that, I'll get the first queryItem
that has the name "smoothie,"
and if there is one,
set the selectedSmoothieID
on the data store to that URL parameter,
which is our smoothie identifier.
Back in the Fruta Xcode project,
I'll go to
the "Signings and Capabilities" tab.
In it, I'll add a new capability.
I'll choose to add "associated domains."
I'll expand this capability
and click on the plus button
to add a new associated domain.
Here I will enter
"appclips:Fruta.example."
Now that we have set up
our associated domain,
let's configure a launch URL
to debug our app clip with.
To do this,
I'll click on the "Target Popup" button
and click "Edit Scheme."
You'll see the environment variables
section has already been prepopulated
with the value "example.com."
All we need to do here
is to tick the checkbox
before the environment variable
of name _XCAppClipURL.
In it, I'll enter a URL
that our app clip is able to parse,
and our app clip will pick up
the smoothie=BerryBlue parameter
as we have set up earlier.
I'll close the editor
and build and run the clip on the device.
Voilà.
Our app has automatically parsed
the app launch URL
and navigated us
to the Berry Blue smoothie.
I'll order, pay with Apple Pay...
and wait for my order to be ready.
Looks like my smoothie is ready.
I would love to enjoy the smoothie myself,
but there's more to demo.
Since I've already submitted my Fruta app
to App Store Connect,
and have configured
an app clip card experience
on App Store Connect
using the flow Ada has discussed earlier
in this talk,
so now, if I tap my phone on this NFC tag,
an app clip card shows up
and I can launch the clip right here
through physical invocation.
Another way, as my colleague, Ada,
has discussed earlier in this talk,
is through the Smart App Banner in Safari.
So now I'm back at my website sources,
and in the index.html file,
all we need to do is to add a new meta tag
for our app clip.
I've specified a name
of "apple-iTunes-app"
and "app-clip-bundle-id" as its content.
Notice I'm keeping the app-ID parameter
so that my users running an iOS release
before iOS 14
can still see a Smart App Banner,
referring them to download the app
from the App Store.
All right.
After pushing my changes up to the server,
I'm back onto my phone and have navigated
to Fruta.example in Safari.
As you have guessed,
while Fruta.example is
a .example domain, and it's not for sale,
we have a lot of production budget
this year.
You all are really worth the exhilarating
14-hour domain auction marathon.
So, of course,
you can still browse through the menu
on the web page as you would before,
but on top of the page,
there's a new Smart App Banner.
When I tap on "Open,"
I'll see the same app clip card
as we saw earlier
with physical invocation via NFC.
And after tapping "Open,"
we're brought to the app clip again.
And that is a quick demo
on linking to your app clip.
Thank you, and back to you, Ada.
Thanks, Luming, for showing us
how to set up linking in app clips.
That Berry Blue smoothie
sure looks refreshing.
There's one more thing
that I want to briefly talk about,
which is beta testing for app clips.
So, after you've delivered your build that
includes both your app and your app clip
to App Store Connect,
you should find a new app clip section
in TestFlight
that lets you add test invocation points
for your app clip
so your beta testers
can test opening the URLs
for the different app clip experiences.
Click on "Add App Clip Invocation"...
and set up the title and URL
of an app clip experience
you'd like your beta testers to try out.
For more information about testing
and submitting app clips
in App Store Connect,
please refer to the "What's New
in App Store Connect" session.
To summarize,
in this session, we have shown you how
you can handle links into your app clip
by setting up the associated domains
for the new app clip service type,
and handling the web-browsing
NSUserActivity in your app clip...
how you can configure default
and advanced app clip experiences
on App Store Connect,
including best practices
on what URLs to use
when registering app clip experiences...
how to set up the Smart App Banner
to open your app clip on your web page,
and finally, what's new in TestFlight
for testing app clips.
Thanks for watching this session,
and I can't wait to see
the cool app clips you will create.
[chimes]