Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is Takayuki Mizuno.
I am a CoreMedia engineer at Apple.
This session is about a new feature
of AVFoundation
for writing fragmented MP4 files for HLS.
Here is a diagram
that shows a typical workflow for HLS.
There is a source material.
This may be a video on demand material
or live material.
There is a part that encodes media data.
There the video samples are encoded to,
for example, HEVC,
and the audio samples are encoded to,
for example, AAC.
Then there is a segmenter here...
which segments media data
in a specific format.
The segmenter also creates a playlist
that lists those segments
at the same time.
Finally, there is a web server
that hosts the content.
AVFoundation provides new features
that is useful
mainly for what the segmenter does.
AVFoundation has AVAssetWriter
to allow media authoring applications
to write media data to a new file
of a specified container type such as MP4.
We enhanced it to output the media data
in fragmented MP4 format for HLS.
Apple HLS supports other formats
such as MPEG-2 transport stream,
ADTS and MPEG audio.
But this new feature is specific
to fragmented MP4.
Here is an example of a use case.
My example is that the source is
video on demand material.
AVFoundation has AVAssetReader,
which is an object to read sample data
from a media file.
You read sample data from a source movie,
push the samples to AVAssetWriter
and write the fragmented
MP4 segment files.
Another example
is that the source is live material.
AVFoundation has AVCaptureVideoDataOutput
and AVCaptureAudioDataOutput,
which are objects to provide you
with captured sample data
from a connected device.
You receive sample data from a device,
push the samples to AVAssetWriter and
write the fragmented MP4 segment files.
Fragmented MP4 is a streaming media format
based on ISO base media file format.
Apple HTTP Live Streaming has supported
fragmented MP4 since 2016.
Here's a basic diagram
of a regular MP4 file.
It starts with a file type box
that indicates which of the file formats
this file conforms to.
There is a movie box
that is organizing the information
about all that sample data,
then there is a media data box
that contains all that sample data.
The movie box contains the information
relevant to the entire sample
such as audio and video codecs.
It also contains references
to the sample data
such as location of the sample data.
The order of most of those boxes
is arbitrary.
The file type box has to come first,
but the other boxes
can come in pretty much any order.
If you have used AVAssetWriter,
you may know that AVAssetWriter has
a movieFragmentInterval property.
This specifies the frequency
at which movie fragments will be written.
The resulting movie
is what is called a fragmented movie.
Here is a basic diagram
of a fragmented movie file.
There are movie fragment boxes
in this movie
which referenced all the sample data
held in the media data box followed by it.
This format structure is useful,
for example, for live capture
since even if writing
is unexpectedly interrupted
by a crash or something,
data that is partially written
is still accessible and playable.
Please note
that this fragmented movie case,
if writing finishes successfully,
AVAssetWriter defragments the file
as the last step.
So, this ends up making
a regular movie file.
Here is a basic diagram
of a fragmented MP4 file.
The file type box comes first,
and the movie box comes
after the file type box.
Then there is a movie fragment box
which is followed by a media data box.
And after that,
a pair of movie fragment boxes
and the media data box continues.
The order of those boxes
should be like this.
The major difference between
fragmented movie and the fragmented MP4
is that the movie box
of the fragmented MP4
does not contain references
to the sample data.
It only contains the information relevant
to the entire samples,
and the order of the movie fragment box
and the media data box is reversed.
Now I'll talk
about how to use AVAssetWriter.
This shows how to create
an instance of AVAssetWriter.
You do not provide output URL,
since AVAssetWriter
does not write a file but outputs data.
You just have to specify
output content type.
Fragmented MP4 conforms to the MP4 family,
so you should always specify UTType
with AVFileType.MP4.
You create AVAssetWriterInput.
In this example, compressionSettings,
which is a dictionary,
is provided to encode the media samples.
Alternatively,
you can set nil to the outputSettings,
which is called passthrough mode.
In passthrough mode, AVAssetWriter
just writes the samples as it is given
and then adds the input
to the AVAssetWriter.
Here is how to configure AVAssetWriter.
You have to specify outputFileTypeProfile.
You should specify Apple HLS
or CMAF compliant profile
to output the media data
in fragmented MP4 format.
You specify
preferredOutputSegmentInterval.
AVAssetWriter outputs the media data
at that interval.
This interval time can be a rational time,
but target segment duration for HLS
must be an integer in seconds,
so we are not using greater precision here
because this is the right choice for HLS.
You also specify
initialSegmentStartTime...
which is the starting point
of the interval.
Then you specify a delegate object
that implements a designated protocol.
I will talk about the protocol later.
After this, the same process
as normal file writing continues.
You start writing, then append the samples
using AVAssetWriterInput.
I'm not actually going to talk
about this anymore in this session,
but if you watch the WWDC session
"Working with Media in AV Foundation"
in 2011, you will see
how you perform those processes.
You can find the session video
on Apple's Developer site.
Here is the protocol
for the delegate methods.
There are two methods.
Both delegate methods deliver NSData
of a fragmented media data.
They also deliver AVAssetSegmentType...
that indicates a type
of the fragmented media data.
You should implement one of them.
The difference is that the second one
delivers an AVAssetSegmentReport object.
That object contains the information
about the fragmented media data.
If you do not need such information,
you should implement the first one.
AVAssetSegmentType has two types...
initialization and separable.
Fragmented media data
with type of initialization
contains the file type box
and the movie box.
Fragmented media data
with type of separable contains
one movie fragment box
and one media data box.
You will receive data
with a type of separable successfully.
You package the media data you received
into what is called a segment
and write the segment to files.
A pair of file type boxes
and the movie box...
should be an initialization segment.
And the pair of movie fragment boxes
and the media data box...
can be one segment.
For HLS, a single file that contains
all of those segments
can be used for streaming.
Or each segment can be divided
into multiple segment files.
Moreover,
multiple pairs of movie fragment boxes
and the media data boxes
can be one segment
and stored in one segment file.
HLS uses Playlist.
Playlist is the centerpiece of how
the client finds out about the segments.
Here is an example of Playlist.
There are several tags
that indicate information about segments,
such as URL and the duration.
AVAssetWriter does not write the playlist.
You should write the playlist.
That is why one of the delegate methods
delivers AVAssetSegmentReport.
You can create the playlist
and the I-frame playlist
based on the information
AVAssetSegmentReport provides.
If you look at our sample code
called fmp4Writer,
you will see how to create the playlist.
Also, the document about Playlist
can be found here
at the Developer streaming page.
In passthrough mode, which is a mode
where a sample is not encoded,
AVAssetWriter outputs media data
that includes all the samples
just prior to the next sync sample
after the preferred output segment
interval has been reached or exceeded.
The sync sample here is a sample
that does not depend on another sample.
This is because CMAF requires that
every segment starts with a sync sample,
and Apple HLS also prefers this.
This rule applies not only to video,
but also to audio that has
sample dependencies, such as USAC audio.
Therefore, for passthrough,
only one AVAssetWriterInput can be added.
If sync samples are not laid out
near to the interval,
the media data may be output
in a considerably longer duration
than what is specified.
As a result,
it will be unsuitable for HLS.
One of the solutions is
to encode video samples at the same time.
As I mentioned earlier, if you specify
output settings for compression
in AVAssetWriterInput,
samples will be encoded.
In encoding mode,
a video sample that just reaches
or exceeds
the preferred output segment interval
will be forced to be encoded
as a sync sample.
In other words,
sync samples are automatically generated
so that the fragmented media data
will be output at or very close to
the specified interval.
If you encode both audio and video,
one AVAssetWriterInput for each media
can be added.
Earlier, I said that for passthrough,
only one AVAssetWriterInput
can be added.
But you can deliver video and audio as
separate streams using a master playlist.
You can deliver not just one pair
of audio and video streams,
but also streams at various bit rates
or in different languages.
You need to create multiple instances
of AVAssetWriter
to create multiple streams.
Again, the documents about master playlist
and recommendations
for encoding video and audio for HLS
can be found here
at the Developer streaming page.
This is an advanced use case,
but if you require different segmentation
than preferredOutputSegmentInterval does,
you can do it on your own.
For example,
you may want to output media data
not at a sync sample
after an interval has been reached,
but before the interval has been reached.
Here is the code I showed you earlier
that set properties of AVAssetWriter.
To signal custom segmentation,
set preferredOutputSegmentInterval
to CMTime indefinite.
It is not necessary
to set initialSegmentStartTime
since there is not an interval.
Other settings are the same
as the settings that are used
for preferredOutputSegmentInterval.
This is only for passthrough.
You cannot encode
with custom segmentation.
So when you create AVAssetWriterInput...
you have to set nil
to the output settings.
You call the flushSegment method
to output media data.
FlushSegment outputs a media data
that includes all samples appended
since the previous call.
You must call flushSegment
prior to a sync sample
so that the next fragmented media data
can start with the sync sample.
Otherwise, an error that indicates
that a fragmented media data started
with nonsync sample occurs.
In this mode, you can mux audio and video.
But if both audio and video
have sample dependencies,
it would make it difficult
to align both media evenly.
In that case,
you should consider to package
video and audio as separate streams.
AVAssetTrack now has a new property
that indicates whether the audio track
has sample dependencies.
You can check if a track
has sample dependencies in advance
using this property.
I mentioned earlier
that you should specify
Apple HLS or CMAF compliant profile
to output media data
in fragmented MP4 format.
CMAF is a set of constraints for how
you construct fragmented MP4 segments.
It is a standard
for using fragmented MP4 for streaming.
It is supported by multiple players,
including Apple HLS.
Some of the constraints are not required
if you target just Apple HLS.
But if you wanted a broader audience
for your media library,
then you could consider CMAF.
Now I will talk
about how HLS deals with audio priming.
This diagram represents
audio waveform of AAC audio.
AAC audio codecs require data
beyond the source PCM audio samples
to correctly encode
and decode audio samples
due to the nature
of the encoding algorithm.
For this reason, the encoders add silence
before the first true audio sample.
This is called priming.
The most common priming for AAC
is 2,112 audio samples,
which is just about 48 milliseconds,
presuming that that sample rate is 44,100.
When audio and video are written
in separate files as separate streams,
the media data are laid out like this...
presuming that both media start
at time zero.
As you may have noticed, if audio
and video start at the same time...
the audio will be delayed by the priming
so that the audio and the video
will be slightly off.
CMAF adopts edit list box in audio track
to compensate for this issue.
The priming is edited out...
so that start time of audio
and video match.
Historically,
Apple HLS hasn't used edit list,
so if you specify Apple HLS profile,
the edit list box is not used
for compatibility with older players.
Instead,
baseMediaDecodeTime of audio media
is shifted the amount of priming backward.
However, the baseMediaDecodeTime
cannot be earlier than zero
since it is defined
as an unsigned integer.
One solution is to shift both audio
and video forward by same time offset.
This way,
the baseMediaDecodeTime of audio media
can be shifted
the amount of priming backward.
Even if start time is not zero,
in HLS, playback starts at the earliest
presentation time of video sample...
so playback starts immediately
without waiting for the time offset.
This is important,
not only for exact video and audio sync,
but also for exact match of time stamps
between audio variants
with different priming duration.
So we recommend you to shift media time
by adding a certain amount of time
to all samples
if you specify Apple HLS profile.
Initial segment start time
should be shifted
same time offset as well.
As I said earlier, the most common
priming is less than one second,
so a couple of seconds
is enough for the time offset.
But Media File Segmenter,
which is Apple's segmenter tool,
has a ten-second offset,
so you could choose the same ten seconds.
Our sample code shows how to add
a time offset to all samples.
In this demo, I will use
our sample command line application
to create fragmented MP4
segment files and the playlist.
Then I'll play the resulting content
using Safari.
This demo scene is set up
as a local server
in advance to host the content.
I entered the command line application
in the terminal application.
This command line application
reads media data
from a premade source movie
and encodes the video and the audio.
This is the source movie.
The length is just 30 seconds.
This command line application
uses six seconds
as the preferred output segment interval.
The segment files and the playlist
will be created in this directory.
Let's get started.
The video frame rate of the source movie
is 30 frames per second.
You see five segment files
and a playlist was created.
I open the playlist.
Each segment's duration is six seconds.
I enter the local host as URL
to play it using Safari.
Let's play it.
[soft music playing]
HLS has several requirements.
It also has several recommendations
to improve the experience for users.
We recommend you to validate
segment files and playlist that you write
using AVAssetWriter
to make sure that those files
meet the requirements and recommendations.
WWDC session
"Validating HTTP Live Streams" in 2016
is a great source for this purpose.
You can find the session video
in Apple's Developer site.
AVAssetWriter now outputs media data
in fragmented MP4 format for HLS.
Thank you for joining the session.
[speaking Japanese]