Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Roman,
and I'm a Shortcuts engineer at Apple.
Today, I'm going to share some tips
on how to efficiently debug your Siri
and Shortcuts support.
Let's start by taking a look
at how you can automate Siri queries
using the scheme editor in Xcode.
You can provide the Siri intent query
from the get-go,
so you don't actually have to trigger Siri
and speak to it
when you debug your extension.
When you're attaching
to your Intents extension,
you have an option to choose between Siri
and the Shortcuts app as the host process.
Sometimes you might wonder
why you don't hit breakpoints
in your Intents UI extension
while you're being attached
to an Intents extension in Xcode.
This is because both of these extensions
are separate processes.
You can use the Xcode debug menu
to attach to multiple processes
at the same time.
So, you implemented SiriKit support
in your app
but you're getting,
"Sorry there was a problem with the app"
when you execute your intent in Siri.
Now what can you do about this?
First, make sure that
you call your completion handlers
of your intent handling protocol methods
before the 10-second time-out.
You also need to make sure that you
call the completion handlers only once,
otherwise an exception will be thrown
in your process.
You should also
verify that your process is not crashing
in the middle of the request.
Open Devices and Simulators in Xcode
and click the "View Device Logs" button
and scan it for crashes in your processes.
Using os_log statements
and the Console.app
can help you understand
how multiple processes work together.
When composing your os_log statements
you can prefix them with an emoji
or some other unique keyword
and then use the Console.app
to filter by your unique keyword
to get an accurate timeline of events
in all processes involved.
Thanks for watching.