Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name's Jared McGann.
I'm an engineering manager in watchOS.
Today, we'd like to talk about
Apple Watch face sharing,
a new feature in watchOS 7 and iOS 14.
Face sharing is exactly what you'd expect:
the ability to share a watch face
with anyone,
configured just the way you like.
Watch faces can be shared
directly from the watch
by long-pressing on your face
and tapping the new "share" button.
Select a recipient, compose a message,
and that's it.
In Messages, you'll see an inline preview
on your watch,
and so will the recipient.
They just tap the preview,
and they'll be prompted
to add the face to their watch.
You can also share watch faces
from your iPhone.
Just open the iOS Watch app
and select a face.
Then tap the familiar "share" icon
in the upper right-hand corner.
You'll be presented with a share sheet,
where you can pick
how you'd like to share your watch face.
So how can you as a developer
take advantage of face sharing?
Well, watch faces can be shared
directly from your apps
and hosted on Web sites.
With just a couple taps,
the watch face you've configured
can be on a customer's Apple Watch.
And if you include your complication
in the watch face,
the customer will be prompted to
install your app when they add the face.
If your app's not available
in the recipient's region,
your complication won't be available
on the watch face.
It's also worth mentioning
that some newer faces
are not available on older watches.
And Nike and Hermès watch faces
can only be generated and added
on respective hardware.
Watch face files
contain all the face's configurations,
including color, styles,
photos and complications,
anything you can configure on a watch.
If the watch face has your complication,
the file will include a sample entry
so it can be previewed
on the recipient's device
even if your app's not installed.
We have exciting new complication API
in ClockKit this year.
Watch faces now support
multiple complications from the same app.
And if your complication takes advantage
of user info dictionaries
or user activities,
those preferences can be included
in a shared watch face.
For example, if a shared face
included Dawn Patrol's complication,
the user info dictionary could be used
to specify
which city's surf conditions
are displayed.
To learn more, please check out the talk
"Create Complications for Apple Watch."
So this year,
we've added new API to ClockKit
that allows you to prompt a customer
to add a watch face from within your app.
Call addWatchFace with the local URL
to your preconfigured watch face file,
and the customer will be prompted
to add the face to their Apple Watch.
This API is available in ClockKit
on both watchOS and iOS.
After a face with your complication
is added to a watch,
your app will run and respond
to a timeline request from ClockKit.
At this point, your app can reference the
user info dictionary I mentioned earlier.
Now I'd like to hand it over to Joe,
who's gonna walk us through the process
of adding this functionality
to an existing app.
Thanks, Jared.
Hi. My name is Joe Dion,
and I'm a software engineer in watchOS.
Today, I would like to show you
how to easily adopt
the new Watch Face Sharing API
in your iOS and watchOS apps.
I have an app called "Coffee Tracker."
This app allows you to track
your daily caffeine intake.
Here is the main view of my app,
where I can view my caffeine intake
for the day.
If I tap the coffee cup button
at the bottom,
it opens the drink list view.
In the drink list view,
I can see a list of caffeinated drinks.
If I tap one of these drinks,
it will be added
to my caffeine intake for the day.
My app also has a watch app
with complications
that display your current caffeine intake.
I think my app's complications
are super helpful,
and I'd like to share these with
my customers within the context of my app.
I think implementing watch face sharing
in my iOS app
is a great way to accomplish this.
Let's take a look how to implement this.
Here's a rundown of how I will implement
face sharing in this app.
First, I need to generate a watch face
with my app's complication.
Next, I will need to import the watch face
and face preview into my app's bundle.
Then I will create the UI
for displaying and adding the watch face.
And finally,
I will add support for older watches.
So let's see how to do this.
Here I am on my phone.
To get started, I need to create a face
to share, so I'll open the Watch app.
I'll open the Face Gallery.
Now, let's look for a watch face
that complements our app.
I like the classic analog look
of the Modular Compact face,
so I'll select that.
My watch app has a fantastic
graphic rectangular complication
that would look great
at the bottom of this face...
so I'll select
the Coffee Tracker complication.
This looks great,
but I'd like to make this face my own,
so I'm gonna pick a color for it.
Something to make this face
more coffee-ish.
Walnut looks just like a cup of coffee.
Now I'll select
a good middle complication too.
I think the Breathe complication
will help our caffeine-addicted users
calm down a little bit.
That looks great.
I'm happy with our coffee-tracking
watch face now and I'm ready to share it.
Before we share, it though,
keep in mind that your app needs to have
already been published to the App Store
before you can share this watch face
in your app.
With that out of the way,
I'm ready to share my face.
I just need to tap the "share" button
in the upper right-hand corner.
Here in the share view,
you can see the "options" button,
where you can exclude
any of the complications or their data
from the shared face.
My complication is configured to always
record a shot of espresso when tapped
using the user info dictionary
that Jared mentioned earlier.
But I don't want that to be the default
for my customers
when I share that face with them,
so I'll select "Include without data"
for my complication.
Everything else looks good,
so I'll leave it as is.
When you share a face via e-mail,
you will get the face file,
along with a preview image of the face.
The preview image
will be very helpful later on.
I've already e-mailed
the watch face to myself
and extracted the contents
to my downloads, so let's take a look.
Here on my Mac,
I've opened my "Downloads" folder.
You can see I have the watch face file
and its associated preview
from the e-mail.
I'm gonna add this face file
to my Xcode project.
Another important aspect
of sharing a watch face in your app
is displaying a preview of the face.
Here in the folder,
you can see there's a preview image.
I'm going to use this preview image
when creating the UI,
so I'll take this image
and drag it into my Xcode assets folder.
Now that we have the image,
we're finally ready to get coding.
I'll start by opening up
the DeviceModel class.
I've created this class in order to detect
if a watch is paired to the phone.
I'll use this in my view
to only display my watch face
to users that have a watch.
I've imported
the WatchConnectivity framework as well,
which allows me to implement
the WCSessionDelegate protocol
in this class.
By implementing this protocol,
I can use WCSession to determine
if a customer has a paired watch.
I'm going to create an isPaired
computed variable in this class
using WCSession to indicate
if a watch is paired.
Now that I have the isPaired variable,
let's go to the DrinkListView.
At the bottom of this drink list,
I'd like a navigation link
to a view where someone can add the face.
However, I'd only like to show
this navigation link
to someone with a paired Apple Watch,
so I'll use my DeviceModel class
to create a constant equal to
the DeviceModel's isPaired variable.
Now I'll use my newly created constant
to determine if this view should display
a navigation link to the "add face" view.
I'm gonna add the check
and the UI for this now.
And here is our newly created
navigation link.
But right now the AddFaceView
doesn't have any content in it,
so let's go over
and take a look at the AddFaceView.
Here in the AddFaceView, I need to
display a preview of the watch face
and a button for adding the face.
I'm going to add the UI for this.
This displays a preview of the watch face
that I imported
and creates a button for adding the face.
It also displays an activity indicator
while the button is executing
its action block.
I created this button using an asset
from the Apple Design Resources Web site.
Right now, the button doesn't do anything,
though,
so I'll fix that by using
the new addWatchFace function.
First, I will import ClockKit.
Now I'll create a wrapper function
for calling addWatchFace.
Let's walk through this code to see
how to use the new addFace function.
First, I create a URL that points to
the watch face file in my app's bundle.
Next, I use the new addFace function.
I use it by creating an instance
of CLKWatchFaceLibrary.
Then I call the addWatchFace function
using my unwrapped watchFaceURL.
In the completion block,
we need to account for any errors
that might occur when adding the face.
For now, I'll just print the error out.
Now let's call this method
in the button's action block.
Here you can see that I'm calling addFace
using the face that I just created
and imported to the project.
Now let's see the Add Watch Face API
in action and run this app.
I'll open the drink view...
and here we can see
my navigation link button at the bottom.
I'll tap it to open the "add face" view.
And here we can see the "add face" view
with a preview of our watch face.
This face looks super helpful,
so I'm going to tap
the "Add Watch Face" button.
And here we are in the Watch app.
I'll tap "Add to My Faces"...
and now the face is added to my watch.
This is great.
I think customers are going to find
this face to be super helpful.
However, this Modular Compact face
is not compatible with Series 3 watches.
To support older devices,
we can provide a fallback face
in case the customer has an older device.
Let's go back to Xcode
to see how we can do this.
Right now, the addWatchFaceWrapper
isn't handling errors it might encounter.
Let's change that
by trying to add a fallback face
when the first face is not compatible.
Now let's call
my addWatchFaceWrapper function
with a Series 3-compatible fallback face.
I'm using the Modular face as my fallback.
I picked this face
based off of a list of faces
that are compatible with Series 3 watches
outlined in
the Human Interface Guidelines.
I've also already put this file
into my Xcode project,
so now anyone with an Apple Watch
can utilize our app's watch face.
Before we move on, let's review
some best practices from the demo.
First, when you share your watch face,
remember that user data can be included.
This can be valuable for specifying what
content is displayed in your complication,
but be careful not to unintentionally
include private data.
It's also important to make sure that
your complications include sample data
so the watch face preview is not blank.
It's also helpful if you use
the WatchConnectivity API
to detect if a customer has a paired watch
before offering a watch face
from an iOS app.
Also remember that the best way to obtain
a preview image of your watch face
is to e-mail it.
Remember that if your watch face
is not compatible with Series 3 watches,
you should provide a face
for those customers as well.
Most importantly,
don't forget that your app
must be published
before you can include it
in a shared watch face.
This is because the App Store Connect ID
needs to be included
in the watch face file.
Now let's go back to Jared.
Thanks, Joe.
Watch faces
can also be shared on Web sites.
When a customer downloads a face in iOS,
Safari will prompt the customer
to add the face to their Apple Watch.
Safari is most likely
to recognize your file as a watch face
if you serve the file
using the watch face MIME type shown here.
Here we see an example
of what a watch face might look like
shared on a Web site.
A preview of the watch face
should be displayed above the official
"Add Apple Watch Face" button.
The preview image can be obtained
by sharing a watch face via e-mail
in the iOS Watch app,
as we just saw Joe do.
The button can be found
on the Apple Design Resources Web site,
along with a compact version
that can be used in watchOS.
If you prefer to display your preview
within photographic hardware,
as seen here, those images
can also be found in the design resources.
If the shared watch face
is incompatible with Apple Watch Series 3,
it's important to provide
an alternate watch face.
When you share two watch faces,
separate previews and buttons
should be included on your Web page.
More details,
including watch face compatibility,
can be found
in the watchOS Human Interface Guidelines.
QR codes and NFC tags provide additional
opportunities to share watch faces.
Just embed a Web link
that hosts a watch face file
to easily get your complications and app
onto a customer's Apple Watch.
We hope you'll go configure
your own watch faces
and adopt the face-sharing API
in your app,
or host watch faces on your Web site.
It's a great way to get your apps
and complications
onto customers' Apple Watches.
Thanks for joining us.