Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Andy Aude,
and I'm an iOS System Experience engineer.
Today, I'm going to shed light
on the many reasons
applications can be terminated
in the background
and what you can do about it.
Just as you wouldn't want an app
to crash while it's in the foreground,
it can be equally as disruptive
to have it crash in the background.
For example, I have this to-do-list app
that launches to a main screen
with several lists.
I'll drill into the grocery list
and I'll start making a reminder
to buy a pineapple.
Now, say I have to leave
the app for a moment.
At some point, I'll come back to it.
Oh, no. Why did the app
launch from scratch?
And where's my reminder
to buy the pineapple?
This is because the app
was terminated in the background.
There are many reasons apps
get terminated in the background.
Here are the most common,
which we'll cover today.
Prior to iOS 14,
you only had a signal
for if two of these were happening.
But now, in iOS 14,
we have new API for you to find out
how often these terminations happen
broken out by the specific reason.
MXBackgroundExitData provides
the counts of each termination type.
And we're even going to
give you counts for normal exits
where the user explicitly terminated
your app in the app switcher.
It should no longer be a mystery
why your app was killed.
Crashes are the most straightforward
type of termination.
Crashes are typically
due to segmentation faults,
illegal instructions and asserts.
These events all generate crash logs,
which are surfaced in the Xcode Organizer
for you automatically.
If you want to learn more about crashes
and how to fix them,
check out "Understanding Crashes
and Crash Logs" from WWDC 2018.
In addition to the Xcode Organizer,
new in MetricKit, we've added the ability
to get crash info programmatically
directly from the device.
The MXCrashDiagnostic object
contains everything you need
to track down crashes
and other terminations.
Check out "What's New in Metric Kit"
to learn how to obtain these
and other diagnostic reports.
Another common termination
is a watchdog event.
This is a long hang
during key app transitions,
such as launch, going background
and becoming foreground again.
These transitions have a time limit
on the order of 20 seconds.
Note that these terminations do not happen
while the Debugger is attached.
Watchdogs usually indicate
something seriously wrong,
like a deadlock, infinite loop
or some other unending
synchronous work on the main thread.
When these happen,
you can get a diagnostic report
via MXCrashDiagnostic.
Inside, the call graph is there,
and it will show you the offending symbols
where your app is getting stuck.
Next, if your app relies
on background execution,
know there are strict CPU usage limits.
After a sustained high CPU load
in the background,
the system will generate
an energy exception report.
If the sustained work goes on long enough,
the system terminates the app.
CPU resource exception logs
are available in the Xcode Organizer,
as well as via MXCPUExceptionDiagnostic.
These reports contain call stacks
to identify what exactly
your app was doing
at the time of the termination.
Perhaps there's a bug in your code
causing excess CPU activity
that you can simply fix.
But if you need to do
truly intensive work in the background,
consider moving the work
into a background processing task.
The background processing task
gives you several minutes of runtime
while the device charges overnight,
without CPU resource limits.
Similar to avoiding excessive CPU usage,
it's important to keep memory usage
under control as well.
If your app's memory,
represented by this green square,
grows way too large,
the system will terminate it
right as it crosses the footprint limit.
The footprint limit is the same
in the foreground and the background.
Instruments and Xcode's Memory Debugger
help to track down the source
of excess memory use in your app.
Note that the limit does vary
from device to device.
Older devices generally have lower limits.
If your app targets devices
before iPhone 6s,
you'll want to aim to stay
under 200 megabytes at all times.
This will give you
more than enough safety margin.
Now, unlike
the footprint exceeded terminations,
we have another type
of memory-related termination:
the pressure exit, also known as jetsam.
This is the most common
background termination.
If these are happening, you're not
necessarily doing anything wrong,
it's just that the system
needs to free up memory
for the foreground application
and other running applications
like music and navigation apps.
If the foreground app grows too much,
your app, the green block,
will be terminated.
You can directly reduce
the rate of terminations
by shrinking your memory footprint
to be as small as possible
when you go background.
When going into the background,
aim for less than 50 megabytes.
The smaller, the better.
Consider dropping caches and any resources
you can just read back from disk.
You can always set things back
to the way they were
when going foreground again.
But remember, you can cause
other apps to jetsam,
so try to be a good steward
and minimize your foreground usage too.
And even if you manage to get
under 50 megabytes,
you can't eliminate the risk
of jetsam entirely.
Jetsam is inevitable.
When it happens is very unpredictable too.
It can happen in the mere seconds
after backgrounding your app
if the very next user action
requires an extreme amount of memory.
For example, launching camera
and taking dozens of photos in a burst.
So, what should you do about this?
You should absolutely save your state
upon going background.
Such that when your app is launched next,
it goes back to the same place
the user left off.
If they had been editing a text field,
users expect that text
to be there when they come back.
If media playback is involved,
be sure to restore the playback position.
You can do this with UIKit's
built-in State Restoration APIs
which do a lot
of the heavy lifting for you.
If you implement State Restoration
throughout your app,
many users won't even realize
the app had been killed in the background
and had to relaunch.
After jetsam, the second
most common termination reason
is a background task timeout.
When moving from the foreground
to the background,
you can get some extra runtime
to finish up critical work
by calling
UIApplication.beginBackgroundTask.
When you finish that work,
you call endBackgroundTask.
What you may not realize
is that if you don't explicitly call
endBackgroundTask,
the system will terminate the app
when the time runs out.
And that termination happens
only 30 seconds after suspending your app,
which can be massively frustrating
if your app doesn't implement
State Restoration.
Think of each task as a stick
of dynamite with a 30-second fuse.
Once your app enters the background,
the fuse is lit.
As long as you end all tasks
within 30 seconds,
your app will suspend gracefully
instead of terminating.
Now, we don't surface crash logs
when these terminations happen,
but we do surface the statistics
around their frequency
via MXBackgroundExitData.
The good news is that
these are preventable
with very careful handling
of your background tasks.
To prevent these terminations,
the first thing you should do
is switch to the named variant
of the UIKit API.
The named variant is helpful
because it lets you isolate
which of the potentially
many background tasks in your app
are not being ended.
Note that these terminations
don't reproduce in the Debugger.
So, to make things easier,
starting in iOS 13.4,
there's a new console message that prints
when a task has been held
for way too long.
These prints happen
even if your app is in the foreground.
So if you see these prints
while debugging your application,
you should do an audit of your calls
to beginBackgroundTask,
ensuring there's a matching call
to endBackgroundTask.
Another thing that can help
is the expiration handler.
It's good practice for all calls
to beginBackgroundTask
to provide an expiration handler.
Note that it's safe to call
endBackgroundTask inside the handler.
Be careful to not kick off
any additional expensive work
in this expiration handler
as you only have a few seconds.
Think of the expiration handler
as a safety net against terminations.
They shouldn't be the only place
you call endBackgroundTask.
You should call endBackgroundTask
when the work actually ends,
which allows the device
to go to sleep sooner
and preserve battery life.
If you are seeing your app
is encountering these terminations
via MXBackgroundExitData,
and you are not able to reproduce
the issue in the Debugger,
it can be useful to add telemetry
to see which expiration handlers
are being called.
To do this, first make a log handle.
Then, drop an event signpost
to say you've entered
the expiration handler.
Then, do the necessary cleanup work
to make it safe to suspend your app.
And lastly, drop a signpost
as you exit the handler.
To check how often
the signposts are being emitted,
you inspect the signpost counts
inside your MXMetricsPayload.
It can also indicate if your app
is not making it
through the expiration handler.
In this example, I have an imbalance.
Our entered signpost count
is greater than the exited signpost count.
This means the DatabaseExpirationHandler
is either hanging or crashing.
You should be extra careful
in starting tasks
while the application
is already in the background,
since the expiration handler
won't be called
if you start a task
with fewer than five seconds remaining.
To guard against this,
you can estimate how long
the work will take to complete
using five as a lower bound.
And then compare this
to how much background time remains.
If enough background time remains,
it's safe to call beginBackgroundTask.
If not enough time remains,
you could enqueue the work
as a background processing task
to happen later, such as
when the device is charging.
The next thing to be careful with
is how you store
your UIBackgroundTaskIdentifiers.
If you're storing them
in an instance variable, like so,
it's easy to run into trouble.
In this example, I begin a background task
when the user taps
the beginDataExport button in my app.
After several seconds,
the data finishes exporting
and I get a completion handler.
If I tap the beginDataExport button
a few times,
I can end up with multiple
outstanding background tasks.
Remember, our instance variable
can only hold a single task at a time,
and so we'll leak all the identifiers
except the most recent one.
Fortunately, it's easy
to avoid this kind of bug.
The easiest fix is to use a local variable
instead of an instance variable
to hold your UIBackgroundTaskIdentifier.
In Swift, this local variable
is captured by closures,
so you can access it
in the completion block
and even the expiration handler.
With this strategy,
each invocation of beginDataExport
will track the task identifier
in a separate underlying
memory location, preventing a leak.
If you carefully audit all uses
of beginBackgroundTask
and endBackgroundTask in your application,
you should be able to eliminate
background task timeout terminations.
Now you know how to investigate crashes,
watchdogs, resource exceptions
and background task timeouts.
If you fix these,
your app will appear to launch much faster
since it'll resume
instead of launch from scratch.
As for the most common termination,
you can reduce the chance of jetsam
by using less than 50 megabytes
of memory when in the background.
The smaller, the better.
But jetsam is inevitable.
It's going to happen.
Make sure your app can recover
with State Restoration
and launch smoothly,
returning to where the user left off.
Doing these three things
will ensure a truly seamless
multitasking experience.
Thanks for watching
and happy termination hunting.