Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Danny Mandel,
and I'm here to talk about
how we make sure
your SiriKit Media apps have the
highest-quality Siri experience possible.
Why do we care about quality?
I think we all want to build things
people will enjoy using,
and nobody enjoys using
bad voice implementations.
Additionally, the trust barrier
for voice assistants
is even higher
than with a traditional user interface.
So the reliability needs to be even better
to maintain usage.
If you're going to take the time
to build SiriKit Media support,
take the time to make it good.
This might sound kind of silly,
but the single most important thing
you can do
is play something
when someone asks to play.
And think about it.
If the first time someone is excited
to use your app with voice
and nothing plays,
they probably won't ask again.
So having a robust playback stack
is the first place
you're going to want to invest
your Siri engineering resources.
And the next thing we want to do is
make sure that we start playback quickly.
Over the past year, we've learned that
one of the single biggest failure cases
in SiriKit Media apps are timeouts.
Particularly in environments like CarPlay,
starting playback quickly
is really important.
In cases like CarPlay,
when you're hands-free on the road,
we can be more aggressive with timeouts,
and your app will get killed off
if it doesn't start playback quickly.
To help, we added a couple new options
for performance enhancements this year,
so make sure to check out
"Expand your SiriKit Media Intents
to More Platforms" for more details.
Another way to make
a high-quality experience
is to let Siri understand
your listeners' preferences.
The way you do this is by adopting
the Siri user vocabulary API.
Similarly, you can help Siri
to understand your app's catalog
by adopting Siri's global vocabulary API.
We'll do a deep dive on both of these
topics a little later in this talk.
When you're choosing
the perfect thing to play,
you're going to want to allow people
to ask in different ways.
The more utterances
you can support in your app,
the more likely people are going to
want to use it in their everyday lives.
After all, the promise of Siri
is that it's an intelligent assistant.
And it's only truly intelligent
if we support a wide variety
of natural-language utterances.
So let's take a look at some of the most
common natural-language patterns
we see across all SiriKit Media apps.
What do we mean by perfect-ish?
Ultimately, perfect-ish is the best guess
when you don't know what someone wants.
And we see greater than half
of all SiriKit Media requests
follow this kind of pattern.
Requests as simple as "play your app"
or "play music on your app."
And that makes this generic case,
when someone doesn't tell you specifically
what they actually want,
the single most important use case
to get right.
By making sure you handle this scenario,
you can service a huge amount
of listeners off the bat.
It's up to you to decide
what perfect-ish means for your app.
But make sure it does something
that will give people
that classic surprise and delight.
The way you'll know someone asked
for these very generic cases
is you'll either get a nil media search
or a media search containing
a media type of music.
Our next important use case
is the "play something" use case,
where people specify the title
of what it is they want to play.
They won't say what the media type is,
so it could be a song, album,
artist, podcast, you won't know.
It's important
that when you implement this case,
you accommodate for different media types
and execute a very broad search.
The way you'll recognize
this kind of request
is that there will only be
a media name populated
in the media-search object.
We see about 30% of queries like this.
Moving down the list,
we start to see more precise queries,
with a combination of artist
and some other search field.
So make sure you support
these compound searches with artists.
In this case,
you'll get a populated media name
with the title of what someone asked for,
and then also an artist's name
with the artist they're looking for.
As we start to get more specific
in the query types,
we do see the usage start to go down
and see usage of this pattern
at around five percent of requests.
A final category where we see
a lot of usage is playlists.
So make sure you support
playlist searching.
Again, this is
one of the more specific queries,
and we do see its usage
at around five percent of the time.
When someone includes a playlist query
in their utterance,
we'll get the media-name property
populated with the playlist query
and the media-type property
will be set to "playlist."
The list does continue,
as there's a number of other search fields
in INMediaSearch.
But you can see
with just these four use cases,
we've captured more than 90%
of the current SiriKit Media traffic.
Please do implement as many other fields
as makes sense for your app.
But it does make sense to prioritize
your engineering and QA
around the popular use cases,
as these are what people
are most likely to use.
And one final note on this.
We've also seen that
the better your Siri support is,
the more likely it is that people
will make more complicated Siri requests.
So as you make it better,
expect the usage patterns to change.
That's a good thing.
That means they like
using your app with Siri.
We just looked
at the high-traffic utterances
and saw how we can capture
the vast majority of usage
with just a few intents.
So let's look at those intents
in the debugger,
and see what the media search looks like
in each case.
All right,
we're gonna put a breakpoint here,
so we can see
what the media search looks like.
The first utterance we'll look at
is the empty play case.
"Play ControlAudio."
All right. Looking at our breakpoint,
we can see that in this case,
there is no media search.
This makes sense because
we didn't specify any search criteria.
Now let's look at
"play music in ControlAudio".
In this case, we can see that
we have the music media type set,
and all the other fields are empty.
Now a sample case of "play
Special Disaster Team in ControlAudio".
And as we expected,
we see "Special Disaster Team"
in our media name.
Now let's try a more advanced case
and include both a title and an artist.
All right, here we can see that we have
a media name of "Maybe Sometime."
And similarly,
"Special Disaster Team" in artist name.
And the rest of the fields
aren't populated.
The last one to check was playlists.
So we're going to try
"play my WWDC playlist in ControlAudio".
Since we included the word "playlist"
in the utterance,
we can see we have the playlist media type
as a parameter
and then we also have a media name
of WWDC.
With just those few intents,
we can capture the vast majority
of Siri traffic in our intent handler.
Now let's do a deep dive
on SiriKit Media vocabulary features.
Siri's natural-language-processing system
is a machine-learned system.
And what that means
is there's a probabilistic model
that will try and predict someone's intent
when they ask Siri
to perform a particular action.
What it also means
is that the model has been trained
to recognize particular features.
For example, you don't need to teach Siri
about music genres,
media types, sorts, or release dates,
because the Siri model
has already been trained
to recognize these features
when people ask.
And generally speaking, this is good from
an engineering and a usage perspective.
For engineering, it means that we don't
need to do additional model training
every time a new app adopts
SiriKit Media Intents.
And from a usage perspective,
it's also nice,
because if someone knows
how to use one SiriKit Media app,
they know how to use them all.
However, like with all systems,
sometimes this can cause problems.
For example, in ControlAudio,
say we have a playlist called
"70s punk classics."
By default, the Siri model
is probably going to parse this
as a media release date
corresponding to the 1970s
and a media name of punk classics.
So ControlAudio is going to get an intent
that doesn't exactly map
to the name of that playlist.
The way we solve this
is to sync additional vocabulary to Siri,
so that Siri knows
that "70s punk classics"
is the name of a playlist in ControlAudio.
Now let's look at two different ways
to accomplish this.
The first way we can teach Siri
about our catalog
is by using
Siri's user vocabulary feature.
You're going to want to use
the user vocabulary feature
for things that apply
only to a particular person,
as opposed to all people
that use your app.
You share the vocabulary with Siri
using the INVocabulary API.
So let's take a quick look at that.
You just get a reference
to the shared instance of INVocabulary.
Create an ordered set
with the values you want to store.
One note here.
Make sure the important ones
are at the beginning of the set,
as Siri does pay attention to the order.
Then call setVocabularyStrings
on the type you want to store,
which, in this case,
is mediaPlaylistTitle.
When you're working with INVocabulary,
you'll generally want to focus
on user-created content
like someone's playlists.
However, you could also use it to bias
speech-and-natural-language recognition
towards the taste profile around
music artists or subscribed podcasts.
Global vocabulary, on the other hand,
is appropriate for things
that are available for all people
that use your app.
And unlike user vocabulary,
since global vocabulary is static,
you package it up in a .plist
that you distribute as part of your app.
Note that you only need to include things
that are particular to your app.
So you don't need to include
popular music or podcast entities,
as those are generally already recognized
by Siri as part of its NL model.
So here's an example
of a global vocabulary .plist.
The first thing to note is that
this example is syncing data
to the INPlayMediaIntent.playlistTitle
field.
The next thing to note is that
the identifier for the vocabulary item
is "70s punk anthems".
The identifier is the value
that you'll receive from Siri,
in the INMediaSearch mediaName field.
This identifier is going to be the key
to let Siri know
that the string "70s punk anthems"
matches up to a playlist
in your app catalog.
As you can see here, we have a number
of different types of vocabulary
that you'll want to use depending on
the media types your application supports.
You'll note that the data type
for user vocabulary
and the key in global vocabulary
have different naming,
but they ultimately sync to Siri
in the same place.
For music apps, we have playlistTitle's
and musicArtistName's.
For audiobook apps,
we have audiobookTitle's
and audiobookAuthorName's.
And radio and podcasting apps
can use the showTitle type.
Let's take a look
at how using the Siri vocabulary features
can influence the intent
Siri delivers to your app.
We'll use the example,
"Put on some '70s punk classics"
as an intent that Siri could deliver
that might not match up
with what your app expects.
So let's take a look at that
in the debugger.
All right.
So now we're gonna go set the scheme
and test with that utterance.
And we'll run it.
Okay. So the intent we got
isn't quite matching up
with the playlist title
that we were hoping for.
We have a genre name of "punk,"
we have a decade of the '70s.
So let's go fix that. All right.
So we're going to add the vocabulary
into our app delegate.
One important thing to note
about this code
is that the vocabulary is an ordered set.
And the reason for this
is that Siri is going to prioritize
the items at the beginning of the list.
So make sure that the most important items
are at the beginning,
as there are a limit to the number
of items that Siri will recognize.
Now that it's set up,
let's run the ControlAudio app
and make sure it has a chance to sync up
to the Siri server.
A note about this. In a real-world
scenario, it may take a bit of time
before the vocabulary is synced up
to the Siri server
as it's subject to network
and power conditions.
All right. It synced up,
so let's run the intent handler again
with the same phrase
and look at the intent we get.
Okay. The first thing to note
is that we got the media type of playlist
set in the media search.
Siri recognized
it got a user vocabulary hit,
and it set the media type for us.
And the media name is as we hoped,
and it has the full string
"'70s punk classics" in it.
That's user vocabulary. Let's take
a similar look at global vocabulary.
As a reminder, global vocabulary .plist
is available to everyone using your app
as opposed to user vocabulary,
which is on a per-user basis.
So the first thing we're gonna do
is we're gonna add our vocabulary .plist
to ControlAudio.
And let's take a look at it.
All right. Let's focus
on the parameter vocabularies key.
The first thing we'll do
is look at the parameter names.
In this case, we're defining vocabulary
for playlist titles,
so we see the value is
INPlayMediaIntent.playlistTitle.
Now we can see
that the parameter vocabulary
has a value
for Vocabulary Item Identifier.
The identifier is the value you'll receive
in the Intents Media Search.
And in this case,
we tweaked it from the previous example
and called it "'70s punk anthems."
So now that we have
the global vocabulary file added,
let's give it a whirl and see what we get
in the intent handler.
Okay. Looking at the intent again,
we can see
that we got the playlist media type...
and we see our expected playlist title
of '70s punk anthems.
And that's how you can use
Siri global vocabulary
to make sure that Siri knows
about the entities
that are important
to everyone using your app.
One of the bigger Siri use cases we see
with media apps are Now Playing controls,
so you're going to want to make sure
to test these out.
iOS's Now Playing support is implemented
using the MPRemoteCommandCenter class.
The way this works
is you register a command handler
for a particular Now Playing command.
Some examples of Now Playing commands
are "play," "pause," "next track"
or "previous track."
The basic idea is that if there's
a button in control center
or on the CarPlay Now Playing screen,
then there's a corresponding
Now Playing command class.
And there's a really great existing
sample code project
that dives into the details
of the Now Playing API called
Becoming a Now Playable App.
And I'd encourage you
to take a look at that
if you're interested in more details
about how this all works.
Siri acts as a simple voice interface
on top of particular Now Playing commands.
This behavior isn't new. In fact,
it's been around for many years now.
So, what happens when you issue
a Now Playing command to Siri?
Like most Siri commands,
the first thing that happens
is Siri recognizes what someone says.
In this case,
the utterance is "next track."
Once Siri does that, it sends a command
to the MPRemoteCommandCenter.
In this case,
because the person said, "Next track,"
it's going to send the next-track command.
Finally, your app's registered handler
for next-track command is invoked
and you have the opportunity
to handle the next-track command.
Note that since this implementation
is the same thing
that's handling button presses,
your Siri handling
and Now Playing button presses
will have identical implementations.
In most cases, this is probably okay.
It's just something you'll want to keep
in mind as you're implementing them.
Let's walk through a few of the commands
and how you invoke them via Siri.
Note that the utterance examples
we're using here
are just one of the many
natural-language utterances Siri supports
to accomplish these actions.
When you're implementing
your Now Playing support,
Siri takes care of that for you
so you don't need to worry about it.
You just need to make sure
that your MPRemoteCommandCenter
implementation works correctly with Siri.
First up is the pause command.
You invoke it with Siri
by saying something like "pause,"
and it routes to MPRemoteCommandCenter's
pause command.
Next we have play, and you can use this
to resume music when it's paused.
You invoke it with Siri
by saying something like "resume,"
and it routes to
MPRemoteCommandCenter's playCommand.
Next we have previous track.
You invoke it with Siri
by saying something like "previous track,"
and it routes
to the previousTrackCommand.
Next we have next track.
You invoke it with Siri
when you say something like "next track,"
and it routes to the nextTrackCommand.
Moving on, we have skip forward.
When you say something
like "skip forward,"
it goes to the skipForwardCommand.
Something interesting about skip forward
is that someone can tell Siri
how far they want to skip forward.
Siri will package this up
in the command's interval property.
Next we have skip back.
When someone says something
like "skip back,"
it routes to the skipBackwardCommand.
Like skip forward, people can say
how far they want you to go back,
and you'll receive this
in the command's interval property.
There are a few more commands
that don't show up on the lock screen
that you want to be aware of.
changeRepeatMode and changeShuffleMode
take an argument
as to whether the mode
should be enabled or disabled.
Also, note that these are only used
to turn the repeat and shuffle settings
on or off.
If you want to start playback shuffled
or on repeat,
use INPlayMediaIntent for that.
changePlaybackRate
also takes an argument
as you can say what speed
you want to play something at.
For example, "Play it slower,"
or "Play at half speed."
Similar to the way we can control
Now Playing interactions
by implementing the Now Playing commands,
we can help Siri answer questions
people ask about what's playing
by setting properties
in MPNowPlayingInfoCenter.
A few of the supported properties
are MPMediaItemPropertyTitle,
which you can use by saying,
"What song is this?"
MPMediaItemPropertyArtist,
which you could get with,
"What band is this?"
And MPMediaItemPropertyAlbumTitle,
which you'd similarly get by asking,
"What album is this?"
And when it comes to errors, there's
three ways you can let someone know
that you don't support the command.
You might want to do it
a couple different ways
depending on what's appropriate
for your app.
The easiest way is to just
not implement the command.
If you don't install a handler
in MPRemoteCommandCenter,
Siri will still gracefully give
an error dialogue.
You can also temporarily disable
the command.
And this might be useful in a context
where you normally support something,
but don't in certain circumstances.
For instance, maybe you disable
the next-track command
if you're playing an advertisement
on an ad-supported music stream.
Finally, you can fail the command
which will generate
a generic error dialogue.
Typically, you'll only do this
in exceptional cases,
but Siri will still handle this.
One last thing.
A quality SiriKit Media experience
is one that people know about.
This is a challenge
with any voice integration.
Sometimes people are unaware
of the hard work
that you've put into making
an awesome voice experience
because, you know,
out of sight, out of mind.
But we also see that people are
more likely to use Siri
when they know about the functionality.
How much more likely?
We've seen Siri engagement increase
up to ten times
when there's some education
about the feature in the app.
Of course,
you'll want to present this in your style
and match your app's
overall look and feel.
But if you want people to use your app
more easily by just asking Siri,
you're definitely going to want
to tell them about it.
Thanks for watching.
We really want people to have
a great experience using your app
and a great experience using Siri.
So don't forget.
A high-quality Siri experience
is one people will actually use.
And I hope you really enjoyed WWDC20.