Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Kevin, and I'll be
joined later by my colleague, Madhu.
Today we'll be going over
what's new in DriverKit.
First I will give a brief recap
of system extensions with DriverKit.
Then I will talk about the new
PCIDriverKit framework.
Then I'll hand it over to Madhu,
who will be going in-depth
on writing a SCSI controller driver
using PCIDriverKit in the new
SCSIControllerDriverKit framework.
Then she'll be showing us a demo
of these new frameworks in action.
Finally I will wrap things up
with a summary
of everything that we went over today.
Last year, we introduced DriverKit,
a replacement for IOKit device drivers.
DriverKit brought a new way
to extend the operating system
that is more reliable, more secure,
and easier to develop.
Driver extensions allow developers to make
powerful and innovative apps
without the pitfalls of writing code
that runs in the kernel.
For an in-depth look at DriverKit
and how it works,
please check out last year's video titled
"System Extensions and DriverKit"
on the Apple Developer website.
DriverKit system extensions
run in user space,
not kernel space.
Like other apps,
they have to follow the rules
of the system-security policy.
Unlike other apps,
system extensions are granted
special privileges to do special jobs.
For example, they have direct control
of specific hardware devices,
or special APIs to interface
directly with the kernel.
Because DriverKit drivers
are in user space,
their access is limited
and their resources are separate
from the rest of the system's resources.
When a driver extension crashes,
the kernel and the rest of the system
can keep running.
The development cycle is much faster,
where you can build, test and debug
on one machine,
whereas kernel extensions
bring along security implications.
A bug in a kext can compromise
the entire kernel.
A kext has access
to all of the computer's resources,
not just a specific piece of hardware
or resource.
When a kernel extension crashes,
the kernel panics
and takes down the entire machine.
Debugging and development can be slow.
We need multiple machines,
and we'll need to reboot on every crash.
Another great benefit to driver extensions
is installation is much easier.
Your driver extension
stays in your app bundle.
You should not copy your driver extension
directly to any system folders.
To install your app, you'll use
SystemExtensions framework
and create an activation request
to request the extension
to be made available to the system.
A system administrator would need
to approve this request.
Most apps should create
an activation request during app launch
so the extension is made available
right away.
However, you may wish
to activate your system extension
at different points
in your app's life cycle,
such as after the user has agreed
to a license agreement,
or made an in-app purchase if
that's required for your system extension.
You can get started writing
DriverKit drivers right away,
before they're ready
to go into the App Store,
without a provisioning profile.
To do this, you'll need to disable
system integrity protection,
sign your dext to run locally,
and be sure to include all
the entitlements needed for your driver.
Last year, when DriverKit first launched,
there was support for USB,
serial, network interface controllers,
and human interface devices.
Then later, PCI support was introduced,
and now SCSI controller support
has been added as well.
Because DriverKit brings so many
great improvements over kernel extensions,
we recommend migrating to DriverKit
immediately for available frameworks.
Catalina was the last release
to fully support kexts
without any compromises.
We've begun deprecating kernel extensions
that can perform the same function
as a system extension,
including the device families
supported by DriverKit.
In macOS Big Sur,
kexts that were deprecated in
macOS Catalina will not load by default.
We will continue to add
more types of system extensions,
and more device families to DriverKit.
In turn, kernel extensions of these kinds
will also be deprecated.
This year, we've added support
for PCI and SCSI controller drivers.
This means kext support is now deprecated
for PCI and SCSI controller
device families
for kernel extensions that can perform
the same function as a system extension.
This also means
PCI and SCSI controller kexts
will not load by default
in a future macOS release.
Now we'll talk about one of the exciting
new additions to DriverKit,
PCIDriverKit.
I'll show you some of the key differences
in driver models
between PCI driver extensions
and kernel extensions.
Then I'll be showing some code examples
almost every PCIDriverKit driver
will need.
PCIe is used to expand
the capabilities of a machine
as though they were built into the system.
PCIe brings a lot of advantages,
as it can handle the most demanding,
high-performance jobs.
Some common PCIe devices include
serial, Ethernet and SCSI controllers.
Users can add PCIe devices
through Thunderbolt or through PCIe slots,
such as in the latest Mac Pro.
As with all driver extensions,
PCIDriverKit requires entitlements
to grant access to your PCI devices.
This is to ensure another app
or malicious software
cannot access your PCI device.
The new entitlement uses the same
IOPCIFamily driver-matching criteria
as the Info.plist.
However, you can make
the entitlements more generic
if you need to support multiple devices.
In this example, I have an entitlement
that will allow you to access any device
with a provided vendor ID.
In this case, we're going to use ABCD.
The PCI entitlement takes a list
of PCI matching dictionaries.
You can be as specific
or generic as you want
by using the IOPCIFamily
matching categories.
In this case, we're doing a primary match,
which means we'll be comparing
the primary vendor ID
and device ID of the device
to the entry that we have
in our dictionary.
By using the ampersand, we can have a mask
that allows the matching dictionary
to be more generic.
This effectively removes the device ID
from the matching dictionary,
allowing the driver extension
to be entitled
for all devices of this vendor ID.
With PCIDriverKit,
you will likely need to interact with one
of the many other DriverKit frameworks.
This is an example
of what your entitlements will be
if you wanted to write
a custom Ethernet NIC driver.
In this case, you'll add
the networking family entitlement.
With this family entitlement,
you can now use
the networking DriverKit framework
to interact
with a networking stack as well.
With PCIDriverKit,
the only class in the framework
is the IOPCIDevice.
This class is not intended
to be subclassed.
You'll use this class as the PCI provider
to access all of your PCI resources.
Here's what your driver extension
may look like,
using our network interface controller
example.
The user-space IOPCIDevice
will do the PCI-related communication
needed with the kernel.
Your driver will use the IOPCIDevice
for any PCI-resource access.
Your driver can then use
the PCI device resources
to talk to the networking family
and other user clients.
The layering structure
for the driver extension
is mostly the same
as the kernel extension.
However, almost everything
is in user space.
While encouraged in kernel extensions,
PCIDriverKit mandates that,
prior to accessing the PCI device,
you must successfully call Open
on the device.
Once Open returns successfully,
your driver has exclusive access
to the PCI device.
If your device has resources that are
intended to be shared by multiple clients,
you will need to design
your driver extension
in a way that has a single
PCI resource manager
that distributes its resources
amongst all of its clients.
This is to enforce good design
and allows the system to handle
driver-extension crashes more gracefully.
When done using the device,
such as during the driver stop routine,
you will need to call Close on the device.
You should not expect
the state of the device to remain
after calling Close.
For instance,
the PCI stack will disable
bus mastering and memory space
once Close has successfully completed.
Another driver may open the device
and change its state
if it's entitled to do so.
Another difference
between PCI kernel extensions
and PCIDriverKit
is that PCIDriverKit framework takes care
of all the device mappings for you.
There are new APIs
that all memory accesses will use.
This allows developers to take advantage
of any future optimizations
Apple may explore.
It removes the need
for any device-memory management
and will also allow more observability
and debuggability.
With a single point of access,
you can now use programs such as DTrace
to observe all device-memory accesses.
This can be especially helpful
when debugging PCI issues
in a multi-threaded environment.
The APIs work by passing the memory index
of the memory space
that you wish to access
along with the offset.
I will go over what the difference
between a memory index is
versus a base address register index now.
This is a diagram of the PCI device's
base address registers,
or BARs.
For 32-bit BARs,
the memory index and the BAR index
are the exact same.
For example,
with 32-bit addresses,
if you want to access BAR2,
you'd use two as the memory index
because it's the same index
into the device's BAR space.
64-bit BARs
are where the memory index and BAR index
can differ.
The memory index
is the index for each memory entry.
All memory indexes are base zero.
So for example, if BAR0 AND BAR1 combined
are one 64-bit address,
your memory index would be zero
because it's the first memory entry.
Then if BAR2 and BAR3
are another 64-bit address,
they would memory index one
because it's the second memory entry
in the device's BAR table.
Accessing configuration space
of your device
is mostly a one-to-one mapping,
and still works the same
with just a new name.
The major difference between PCIDriverKit
and kernel extensions
for configuration space
is that you will first need to have
an open session
to read or write
any configuration-space registers.
Next I'll be going over some examples
of common code you'll likely need.
First is how you enable
bus mastering in memory space.
These will be needed in order to access
memory on your device
along with enabling your device
to issue I/O.
Previously, there were
explicit kernel APIs
for each of these operations.
Now, in order to achieve the same result,
you'll first read the command register
and write back to it with the bus-master
and memory-space bits set.
This example is what
most PCI drivers will look like.
In their start routine, they will first
start a session with the PCI provider.
Then they will read the PCI device's
command register.
Set the bus-master and memory-enable bits.
Then write the values
back to the PCI device.
This will need to be done before issuing
any memory reads or writes.
All these offsets and definitions
can be found
in the PCIDriverKit framework headers.
To disable bus mastering,
the processes are the same,
but instead of setting the bits,
the driver will mask them out.
In this example,
Close is also called in the stop routine.
This means that we are done
talking to the PCI device
and can close our session.
Now we'll be going over
how to set up an interrupt handler.
First we'll need to declare
an Interrupt-Occurred method
in our iig header file.
In the definition of our interrupt handler
we'll be using
an implementation definition.
In this example when we begin interrupt,
the handler will clear the interrupt
by writing a register in MMIO space
to one of the device's memory indexes.
Now we need to do the setup
to make it so
our Interrupt-Occurred method gets called
when an interrupt fires.
First thing we'll need to do
is find out which interrupt index
we want to use.
To do this, we'll iterate
through all the interrupt indexes
associated with the PCI device.
Then we'll check its interrupt type.
In this example, we want to handle
the device's MSI interrupts.
So that means
we want to break out of the loop
once we've found the interrupt index
that supports MSIs.
Then we'll need to choose
which dispatch queue
the interrupt will be handled in.
For this example, we're going to keep
everything single-threaded
and use the default dispatch queue.
If you want to create a new dispatch queue
just for interrupt handling,
that's supported as well.
Next we will create the dispatch source
by specifying the interrupters
for the PCI device
at the interrupt index we found earlier
in our default dispatch queue.
Then we'll need to create
an interrupt action
for our newly created source
to use to handle the interrupts.
Once the source is enabled,
our interrupt handler will get called
when our device triggers an interrupt.
Lastly we'll go over
how to set up a DMA transfer
for your PCI device.
First we'll create
a buffer-memory descriptor.
We'll need to set the length of the buffer
prior to writing to the buffer.
And then here's an example of how you can
take the virtual address of our segment
and write some data to it.
Next, in order to give the PCI device
access to our buffer,
we'll need to create an I/O DMA command.
First we'll set up the DMA specification
that describes our hardware's
DMA capabilities.
Then we'll create the I/O DMA command,
specifying this is for our PCI device.
This is to ensure
the correct memory mapper
is used for all of your transfers.
Next we're going to take the DMA command
and prepare our buffer-memory descriptor
so we get a physical address
to give to our PCI device.
Then we can use the result
of the physical address segment
to get the buffer's physical address
to write it to our PCI device.
Once our transfer has finished, we'll need
to call Complete on our DMA command
so that the physical memory can be used
by another process or device.
That was a brief introduction
to the new PCIDriverKit framework.
Now I'd like to hand it over to Madhu,
who will be going into detail on how
to write a SCSI driver using DriverKit.
Hi, I'm Madhu,
and I'm going to be talking about
the SCSIControllerDriverKit framework.
It's a brand-new framework in DriverKit
to build driver extensions
for SCSI controllers.
Let's start with an overview.
SCSIControllerDriverKit framework
is available today in macOS Big Sur.
It supports all IOKit-based
device-driver features
that SCSI kexts
have supported in the past.
This framework is going to serve
as a replacement
for IO-SCSI-Parallel-Interface-Controller
implementation,
which was being used until now
for kext development.
The framework has been built
keeping performance as a top priority.
It is highly optimized
to minimize interactions
between the user space and the kernel
in the I/O performance path.
It can support a variety
of SCSI-based devices,
like fiber-channel controllers,
RAID controllers,
serial-attached SCSI, and more.
Since these will be
PCIe-based controllers,
we've make sure our framework
is fully compatible
with the PCIDriverKit framework.
IO-User-SCSI-Parallel-Interface-Controller
is a new class
defined in the iig interface file.
SCSI dexts are required to subclass this
and implement its functions.
Now, we have tried to maintain
similar API structure here
compared to the kernel class
with the prefix "User"
added to API names.
For example, User-Process-Parallel-Task
is the new API dexts need to implement
to submit I/O requests to the hardware.
It is quite simple to determine
which framework functions to override
in the dext.
Just override all the functions
that are marked "pure virtual."
These functions are calls
made by the framework into the dext,
to get controller-specific information
or to perform specific tasks.
For example,
the framework calls
User-Does-HBA-Perform-Auto-Sense
to check if the HBA supports AutoSense.
It calls User-Initialize-Controller
to initialize the controller
and dext data structures.
All non-pure virtual functions
get invoked by the dext
to perform specific tasks like
creating a SCSI target with a unique ID,
or setting target properties
for a specific target.
The implementations of these functions
will be present in the kernel.
Like we already know,
entitlements are required to be added
before we build and load
driver extensions.
Other than the generic
DriverKit entitlement
and the transport-specific entitlement,
we have added a new family entitlement
for SCSI controllers.
A SCSI dext needs to add this entitlement
to run and have full access
to the framework.
With that, let's create
an example SCSI dext.
I have divided this
into four important phases.
In each phase, I will show
how to override some important functions,
discuss some guidelines,
and share some performance tips.
Let's begin with start and initialization.
The kernel is going to control the start
and initialization phase of the dext
by making a whole bunch of calls.
Other than making calls
to initialize the controller,
it is also going to be making
a number of calls
to gather controller-specific information,
like maximum task count supported,
highest supported device ID, et cetera.
And sets up all the kernel data structures
accordingly.
Let's see what happens when
a SCSI controller device is plugged in.
IOKit Matching kicks off,
and an IOService object of that type,
IO-User-SCSI-Parallel-Interface-Controller
starts up in the kernel.
IOKit's IOService implementation
will now start creating resources required
to start the dext in the user space.
It initializes the IO-User-Server IPC
layer,
and creates a process hosting the dext
with its DriverKit classes initialized.
DriverKit SCSI device is loaded,
and
IO-User-SCSI-Parallel-Interface-Controller
will first call its start implementation.
It will then call
a whole bunch of other functions,
like User-Initialize-Controller...
and User-Start-Controller to finish
the start and initialization phase.
Let's start implementing.
I'm only going to be discussing
some important framework functions
that the dext needs to implement,
the first one being
User-Initialize-Controller.
We're first going to be opening
a new session
with PCIDriverKit,
like Kevin discussed before.
The DriverKit framework already creates
a default dispatch queue for us.
We are going to be creating and setting up
two additional dispatch queues here.
We are also going to create
an Interrupt-Dispatch-Source,
and register a handler
to process interrupts.
This brings us to the queuing model
we would like you to follow
while building your dext.
We suggest having
three dispatch queues in total.
The default queue,
which is created for you
by the DriverKit environment.
Additionally, an interrupt queue
and an auxiliary queue.
Default queue will run all the calls
that originate from the kernel.
For example, User-Initialize-Controller...
User-Process-Parallel-Task, and so on.
It helps to have a separate queue
to service interrupts.
Since DriverKit dispatch queues
are serial,
interrupts and I/Os
won't be competing with each other to run.
This will give
a huge performance boost as well.
This queue can also be used to service
dext I/O time-out handlers.
A separate auxiliary queue
needs to be set up to create SCSI targets.
As part of creating targets,
the kernel makes
a number of calls to the dext
to help initialize the target.
Since these calls will run
on the default queue,
the dext needs to create the SCSI target
from a separate auxiliary queue.
The kernel is going to be maintaining
a list of I/O DMA commands,
SCSI-Parallel-Task in this case,
based on the total outstanding commands
the controller can support at a time.
Every time it creates
a new SCSI-Parallel-Task object,
it calls User-Map-HBA-Data implementation
of the dext.
The dext can use this opportunity
to create
its controller-specific task
data structure.
And maintain a list of them.
Here are some implementation details
of my example SCSI dext.
I have created
an IO-Buffer-Memory-Descriptor object
for my controller-specific
task data structure.
I have also mapped
the buffer-memory descriptor
in my dext address space.
It is important to do any kind
of preprocessing like this here
before we start serving I/Os.
Doing this in the I/O path
can negatively impact performance.
I add this task data to my task data list.
I also assign a unique task ID
to this task
so that the kernel can correlate this
with its corresponding
SCSI-Parallel-Task object.
Next, in my
User-Start-Controller implementation,
I enable interrupts on the hardware.
I then enable
the interrupt dispatch source.
Returning success from
User-Start-Controller
indicates to the kernel the dext is up
and ready to serve I/Os.
That brings us to
the most interesting part
of any storage driver: the I/O path.
Let's first refresh our memory a little,
and review how this works
in the kernel today.
Before, the kext would override
the function Process-Parallel-Task
and would have access
to SCSI-Parallel-Task object.
SCSI-Parallel-Task is a subclass
of I/O DMA command.
The kext was responsible
to prepare the I/O DMA command
and generate physical segments
for DMA to happen.
It would call Complete-Parallel-Task
once it receives the interrupt completion
for the I/O.
We have changed a whole lot
of this behavior with the dext.
The kernel will now call the dext
User-Process-Parallel-Task implementation
to submit an I/O.
As part of this call,
it'll send a copy
of SCSI-User-Parallel-Task object
to the dext.
This object will contain
all the information
the dext will need to perform this I/O.
And the dext will not have to make
any more calls to the kernel.
Like I mentioned at the beginning,
this framework has been built
keeping I/O performance as a top priority.
Note that the dext does not have access
to SCSI-Parallel-Task object.
The kernel will do
all of the heavy lifting
of preparing the I/O DMA command
and generating physical segments
for the dext.
This way of letting the kernel handle
all of the operations required
to prepare an I/O for DMA
has obvious performance benefits.
Preparing an I/O DMA command
in the user space
will result in additional IPC calls
being made to the kernel,
and we would want to avoid that
at any cost in the performance path.
After the I/O is submitted,
dext interrupt handler gets invoked
whenever the hardware
sends an interrupt completion.
It will then have to call
Parallel-Task-Completion,
which is an OSAction callback,
to complete this I/O.
Here are the two main functions
we need to care about.
The dext needs to implement
User-Process-Parallel-Task functions
for I/O submission,
and needs to call Parallel-Task-Completion
to indicate I/O completion.
We already discussed about
SCSI-User-Parallel-Task a little.
As we can see, it contains
a lot of information about an I/O,
like the CDB, data transfer count,
data transfer direction, et cetera.
An important field in this structure
is f-Buffer-IOVMA-ddr.
Like I mentioned before,
the kernel generates
DMA physical segments for us.
F-Buffer-IOVMA-ddr is going to be
the start physical address
of this segment.
It is guaranteed
that the kernel is going to generate
one long contiguous segment
that can fit all of the buffer data.
The dext needs to send its response object
as part of
Parallel-Task-Completion callback.
It needs to have
all the relevant information
for the specific I/O completion,
like completion status,
number of bytes transferred, et cetera,
and sense data, if any.
Let's look at our example implementation.
I first fetched the specific task data
for the task ID from my list.
I set all the metadata for this I/O
in my task data.
The kernel is going to generate
one long physical segment
with f-Buffer-IOVMA-ddr
as the start address.
Feel free to prepare
your own Scatter-Gather-List
if your hardware specification
requires you to chop this up
into multiple segments.
I retain and stash away
the completion callback object for later.
I post the request to the hardware,
and send an appropriate response
back to the kernel.
Once I receive an interrupt completion,
I process the interrupt response,
and fill out
the SCSI-User-Parallel-Response structure.
I then invoke the completion callback.
We now have I/O submission
and completion logic
implemented in our example dext.
Let's move on to the next phase
of our driver development:
power management.
Supporting power state transitions
in DriverKit
is as simple as
overriding Set-Power-State function
and implementing
your hardware-specific functionalities
for every power state supported.
DriverKit framework today
supports three power states,
an off state, an on state,
and a low-power state.
For PCIe-based devices,
we need to mainly care about
the off and the on states.
Off state for when
the device is entering sleep state,
like during system sleep,
or even during a PCI pause operation.
An on state for when
the device is fully powered on,
or during a system break.
Delayed acknowledgement
of power state transition
is also possible in DriverKit.
Let's look at an example.
Here, I have overridden Set-Power-State,
and to keep it brief, I have only shown
Power-State-On transition.
For my hardware,
I'm going to be issuing a hard reset
to change the power state to on.
I then return the callback to the kernel.
Since I issued a hard reset,
my driver starts a complete
SCSI Target-Rescan on the hardware.
I make sure all my targets are up,
and then acknowledge
the power state transition
by issuing a SUPERDISPATCH
Set-Power-State call.
I now have power management support
implemented in my example dext.
Let's finish by discussing termination.
DriverKit termination
is quite straightforward.
Just override Stop method,
and tear everything down in there.
We have made it simpler for you.
The dext is not responsible for completing
any outstanding I/O requests.
The kernel handles all of that for you.
Let's look at an example.
In my Stop implementation,
I first close my outstanding PCI session.
I then cancel
all of my dispatch queues and sources.
I release them in a finalize code block,
which gets called by the framework
once the cancel call completes.
That's it.
We now have all the major features
of our example SCSI dext implemented.
Now, I know what you all must be thinking.
Here we have a system
where every single I/O that is coming down
from the file system in the kernel
gets sent to the dext running
in the user space via an IPC call.
The interrupt handler is getting invoked
via an IPC call from the kernel.
And the dext I/O completion is sent from
the user space back to the kernel
via an IPC call.
This sounds like a lot of overhead.
Will this affect my dext's performance?
Will my dext be able to achieve
the same throughput as my kext?
Can I still run pro workloads
on these devices like I used to?
These are all great questions.
We had the same concerns
when we started developing this framework.
Like I have mentioned
a couple of times already,
we designed and implemented this framework
keeping performance as a top priority.
I am happy to report
that SCSIControllerDriverKit
can handle the same workloads as kexts.
Let's run a realistic workload
on our example SCSI dext
and see how it performs.
My device setup includes
a four gigabits per second
fiber-channel host bus adapter
connected to a RAID disk array.
I have connected this setup
to a MacBook Pro here via Thunderbolt 3.
To build and install my example SCSI dext,
I made sure I added
all the required entitlements,
and packaged it inside
a system extension app.
I also made sure my system extension app
created an activation request
during app launch
so that my dext is available right away.
I then built my system extension app
and code-signed it appropriately.
I have already installed
my system extension app on this system.
Let's peek into the I/O registry
and see if our dext has matched.
There it is.
Our example SCSI dext
has started successfully and is running.
Our fiber-channel controller in this case
is actually a multifunction PCI device.
So we see two separate instances
of example SCSI dexts running.
Let's open Disk Utility to see
if our dext is providing any disks.
Looks like we have one external disk here
with a fiber-channel interface.
The disk is formatted
to have one APFS volume.
The volume is already mounted
as we can see here on the desktop.
We thought it would be a great idea
to demonstrate performance
by running an actual pro workload.
I have a Final Cut Pro library
on this external SCSI disk.
Let's open that.
Video processing and playback
can be CPU and disk-intensive.
While serving I/Os,
if our dext CPU utilization
increases for any reason,
it is going to show.
Our dext process can steal CPU time
from the actual video playback,
which would result in frame drops.
Our goal here is to make sure our dext
is able to stream this video
without any frame drops.
Just to be sure we'll see if this happens,
I'll enable this option here,
so that we get warned about frame drops
because of disk performance.
Let's start playing the video.
[music playing]
I'm also going to open
Activity Monitor on the side
so we can see disk usage.
I have already selected
the Final Cut Pro process here.
We have this beautiful video playing
in Apple ProRes format.
This video has a maximum disk throughput
of around 350 megabytes per second,
which is quite close
to the maximum throughput
that our four gigabits per second
fiber-channel controller can support.
Our dext is doing great so far.
[music ends]
This entire video was streamed
from our example SCSI dext
running in user space.
How cool is that?
And we did not get alerted
of any frame drops,
which means our dext was able
to handle this pro workload like a pro.
There we have it.
All the advantages of DriverKit,
like security, ease of development,
and debugging
without compromising on performance.
So that was a brief overview
of SCSIControllerDriverKit framework,
a brand-new framework
to build driver extensions
for SCSI controllers.
Back to you, Kevin.
Thanks, Madhu.
Today, we briefly went over
DriverKit system extensions,
and saw how you can adopt
the new PCIDriverKit
and SCSIControllerDriverKit frameworks,
for your devices.
We went over an in-depth example
of writing a SCSI controller driver
over PCI.
And got to see a real-world demo
of how you can use these frameworks.
With the new SCSI controller
and PCIDriverKit frameworks,
SCSI controller and PCI kernel drivers
are now deprecated
when a system extension
can perform the same function.
For an in-depth look at DriverKit,
please check out last year's
"System Extensions and DriverKit" session
on the Developer website.
I encourage developers
to start adopting DriverKit immediately
for the device families
that are available.
Please go and download
the latest DriverKit SDK,
and let us know any feedback you have
through Feedback Assistant.
We'd love to hear from you,
and are excited to see what you'll create.