Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Richard Cooper,
and this session is all about
how you can make your applications
more secure,
protecting the data and resources
users entrust to you.
Here at Apple,
we're passionate about ensuring
applications handle data correctly,
respecting users' privacy,
and that software is designed
to be robust against attack
to ensure that
that effort isn't undermined.
My team works with software
and hardware teams within Apple
to help them improve the security
of what we're building
and find issues in things
we've already built.
We'd like to share with you
some of the techniques we found useful.
In this talk,
we're going to cover some ideas
about how you can think about security
in the context of your application.
To do this, we're going to talk about
threat modeling,
how to identify untrusted data,
and go over some common mistakes
we see people making.
To help visualize the problem,
we're going to use a simple hypothetical
application called Loose Leaf.
We've got high hopes for Loose Leaf
and expect it to become
the leading social platform
for hot, cold and bubble tea drinkers.
Perhaps even coffee too.
To make this happen,
we're gonna support these great features:
We want social networking so you can
share your activity with the world,
the ability to use the camera
to take photos to post
but also to create
live-action pouring videos.
We also want to support private tea clubs,
allowing you to talk
with just your friends.
Finally, we're going to have the ability
to support longer form reviews,
pairings, etcetera.
Whilst it's quite a simple example,
it has many features
in common with popular applications.
The first thing you want to do
when looking at your app
is to stand back
and think about the threat model.
Threat modeling is the process
of thinking about what can go wrong
in the context of security,
and it is important, as it allows you
to consider what risks you face
and what you can do to mitigate them.
We're not going to describe
a specific formal process,
as for many developers,
learning and following one
simply wouldn't be practical.
Instead, we're going to describe some
strategies you can use for threat modeling
and which will help you think about
security and risk.
So, how do we do this?
One of the key things
your application has are assets.
These aren't the assets you would find
in an Xcode asset catalog,
but the things the user might consider
valuable, sensitive, or private.
Camera and microphone, location data,
contact information, and photos and files
are all really good examples of assets,
and why we've been working hard
over the last few years
to provide platform-level protection
of many of these things.
As a general rule,
if the user was required to grant access,
it's an asset.
In doing so,
they are delegating control of it to you,
so you need to concern yourself
with how to protect it.
But there are other things
which also represent assets.
Opinions and views which users
enter into your application
are a hugely important asset.
Whilst platform protection can help,
it's a class of asset
where you need to be particularly careful
and ensure to adopt those protections.
Now, no threat model would be complete
without attackers.
These can be the obvious ones:
criminals who want to steal
from your users
or competitors
who want to undermine your platform,
but we should also consider
other classes of attacker
who might have different levels of access.
Romantic partners and family members
are good examples of these.
So you should ask yourself, "How do I
protect against these attackers?"
This is important,
as they often have vastly different levels
of access to a device,
both physically
and through shared accounts.
Whilst you might not think Loose Leaf
is interesting to these attackers,
if we have access to useful assets
and are as successful as we intend to be,
we can become a target.
Attackers regularly attack social media,
banking, productivity,
dating apps, and even games,
so nobody is immune.
In general, who the attacker is
is actually less important
than what capability they have
and how that can be used to affect us.
To help us visualize
what data the attacker can control
and where it goes in our application,
we recommend doing a data flow diagram.
To start, draw out
where the data stores in your system are.
In our case, we've got some information
hosted on our website.
We're going to use that for public posts,
account information, etcetera.
Some information
is also stored in CloudKit,
allowing us to have
decentralized tea clubs...
and a cache, which is going to store
local versions of posts and images.
Ultimately, these are gonna be the places
where user sensitive information
is persisted.
Next, we should add in system resources
we leverage.
We should also think about other ways
data might be able to make its way
into our application.
In our case, we have a URL handler,
which allows links to be passed to us.
Finally, we need to decide
where the security boundaries
should be in our system.
Placement of these is really important,
as it provides the basis
for all the decisions we're gonna make
about what we do and don't trust.
The key question to ask yourself here is,
where can attackers influence
my application,
what data is attacker-controlled,
and how can they use that
to gain access to our assets?
In our case,
we're going to place a boundary here,
between the system resources and our app.
Whilst we trust the system,
the content is uncontrolled.
For example, a file selected by the user
might have come from an untrusted source,
so if we process its content,
we need to be careful.
Custom document formats being
a great example of where this can happen.
Other local applications
are also untrusted to us,
so we'll place a security boundary
at the URL handler,
as the data provided may be malicious.
We're also going to place another boundary
between our app
and all of its remote assets.
Even though it's our code which should've
written the data into these remote stores,
that might not be the case.
An attacker may have written software
to craft a malicious post.
With this understanding of
where attackers can influence our system,
we should think about architectural ways
to secure it.
This is particularly relevant here,
on the connection between our app
and our website.
We at Apple have provided
a generic mechanism
for strengthening these connections
called App Transport Security.
ATS ensures that all connections
your application makes via the URL system
offer sufficient protection to user data
as it transfers over the Internet.
ATS is on by default,
but to make use of it,
you need to ensure
you use the higher level APIs
like NSURLSession and friends.
As such,
you should make development policies
to ensure their use over lower-level APIs.
You also want to make sure you don't ship
with any ATS features disabled
in your Info.plist.
Equally, you want to think about
the format you use to store data,
both on the server and locally.
In general, you want to choose a format
which is simple to parse
and easy to validate.
plist and JSON are both good choices,
balancing flexibility against security.
Formats where you can perform
schema validation, though, are ideal,
as these provide strong checking
and centralized logic.
We also want to think about
how to protect user data in these stores.
Is CloudKit protection sufficient
for a tea club,
or should we also be manually encrypting
the data ourselves?
When we laid out our security boundaries,
we didn't place one
between the local cache and the app.
Our reasoning here is that we shall
validate the data on the way into the app,
and any locally-stored copy
can be trusted.
On iOS,
this is a strongly enforced guarantee,
as other apps can't change
our local files.
But on macOS, that's not true.
So we may need to reconsider
how we protect this data
if we plan to support macOS.
We should also think about
third-party dependencies.
What libraries are we using,
is their approach to security
consistent with ours,
and is testing sufficient to allow
quick updating of these dependencies?
Now that we've found ways to mitigate risk
architecturally,
let's have a look inside our application
at the implementation.
In our app,
there are three main classes of object:
those responsible for retrieving data
from external sources,
those responsible for parsing that data
and converting it into a model,
and those responsible
for displaying the data to the user.
What we want to do
is identify which is which,
and where the highest risk areas are,
as these are the parts
which will most directly work
with attacker-controlled data,
and thus,
where we need to be most careful.
Data stored on remote servers
is one of our highest risks.
The information stored on our website
can be created by any attacker,
so we need to take a lot of care
when handling it.
Data in our tea club, though,
can only be modified by its members.
CloudKit ensures that.
Here,
the set of attackers is more restricted,
and so the level of risk
depends on which attackers we consider
part of our threat model.
We can now follow this data flow
through our system
and get a corresponding risk profile.
Components responsible
for transferring the data have some risk.
And this is particularly true
where you have an interactive connection
with an untrusted entity.
But those which process the data
and are responsible for its validation
are the highest risk.
Note we've excluded the servers here,
as they're out of scope
for this discussion.
We can do this process for our whole app
and get a view of where risk lives,
where we need to be most paranoid,
and where we're most likely
to make mistakes
which will result in security issues.
So to recap:
Identify what assets your system has
and think about how you can design
to protect them,
particularly how to protect your data
in transit and at rest.
Identify where attackers
can influence your application,
tracing that data through the system
so you can understand
where the high-risk components are
and can plan to mitigate issues
that might occur during implementation.
Now, over to Ryan
to talk a bit more about untrusted data.
Thanks, Coops.
So, before we even begin
to secure our applications,
we have to be able to identify
how untrusted data is getting in.
Well, what is untrusted data? It's simple.
We're gonna always assume
that external data is untrusted
unless you're in control of it.
And when you're not sure if
you're in control of it, assume the worst.
Let's see some simple examples now
of how untrusted data
can get into our apps.
You may not realize it,
but if your app uses custom URL handling,
the URL is completely untrusted
and can come from anywhere,
even from someone you don't expect
sending it to a user over iMessage.
Similarly,
if you have a custom document format,
there may be vulnerabilities in parsing it
that could compromise your application.
The first action we want to take is to
figure out all the data entry points
so we can begin to see how the untrusted
data is being handled by our application.
Now that we've already done
our data flow diagram,
we should have this information available.
This is just an example and is by no means
an exhaustive list of every entry point
that iOS and macOS
exposes to your application.
Most commonly, our application probably
deals with some amount of networking.
This represents the highest relative risk
for handling untrusted data,
as an attacker can target a user
without needing to be in
physical proximity to the user's device.
This can be in the form of
talking to your server over HTTPS,
peer-to-peer communication,
such as real-time video calling,
or even Bluetooth communication.
In our example,
Loose Leaf has a few features
which process untrusted data
from over the network.
And because we care about
the privacy and security of tea fanatics,
we've implemented end-to-end encryption
for all of our device-to-device messaging.
Now, we won't get into exactly how
to implement encrypted messaging,
but it's critical that we understand
an intrinsic property
of these types of security technologies
when we're developing secure applications.
Encryption does not imply
the message is trusted and valid.
To put that simply,
I can know with cryptographic guarantees
that the message is from my friend,
but that doesn't mean my friend
isn't trying to hack me.
The contents of an encrypted message
are still untrusted data.
Okay, so we know our application
gets some messages over the network.
And then typically
we'll do some message processing here.
That could be some decryption or verifying
a cryptographic signature, for example.
Then it will get to the point
where our application will want to read
the contents of that message.
And now our job
is to look at these messages
and figure out what's trusted,
what's untrusted,
and then we'll be able to see
how we're using the untrusted data.
So we might take a look at our protocol
and find that this sender e-mail address
is a verified sender address.
In our example,
this is cryptographically verified,
so it can't be spoofed and can't be
something that we don't expect.
So we can trust this.
Then we look at the message identifier
and find that it's partially controllable.
When we say
something is partially controllable,
we typically mean that it's bound to some
range of values or some specific type.
For example, this has to be a UUID,
but someone could still send us
any valid UUID.
Then we look at the message payload
and find that
it's completely sender-controlled.
This means that they can send us
any arbitrary message payload,
and it might not even be in the format
that our application expects.
So with anything that's sender-controlled,
we have to make sure that we validate
and sanitize this untrusted data
before using it.
Okay. So far, we've seen how to identify
and classify untrusted data.
Now, let's look at some common ways
for how untrusted data can be mishandled,
so you can learn how to find
bugs like these in your own applications.
We're gonna look
at a path traversal bug here,
which is a very common type
of security bug
that you may find in your own application.
Now, in Loose Leaf, we have the ability
to send photos of your tea latte art
to your friends,
and it looks like
this is the code that handles that.
In this example,
we're taking the downloaded photo,
and the goal here is to move that
into a temporary directory
so we can use it before the system
deletes the downloaded file.
The first thing we want to do is look at
what comes in to the method here.
Our goal is to figure out what's trusted,
what's untrusted,
and see how we're handling
the untrusted data.
So we take a look at our method here
and find that this incoming resource URL
is a random file name.
It's generated locally on the device
when the file is downloaded
from the Internet.
It can't be influenced by the sender,
so we can trust that.
Then we look at the fromID here.
That's the verified sender address.
In our example,
this is cryptographically verified,
and so it can't be spoofed
and it can't be something we don't expect.
So we can trust that.
Then we take a look at the name here,
and this is completely sender-controlled.
This is what they're telling us
the name of the file is,
but they can send us
any arbitrary string here.
So let's see how we're using it.
We take the name
and pass it into appendingPathComponent
to try and build this destination path
in our temporary directory.
What happens if they send us this string
with any number of these backtracking
components at the beginning of it?
Now they've managed to traverse
outside of our temporary directory,
and when we copy the file,
we'll be copying it into
whatever arbitrary location
the sender has given us.
So, obviously, this is pretty bad,
as it can overwrite
potentially sensitive files
accessible in our application's container.
So you might take a look and go,
"Okay, I'll just take
the lastPathComponent here."
And in this example, that would work.
It would give you the safe file name.
But it will also return this if the last
components are the backtracking ones.
So we can still potentially overwrite
sensitive files for our application.
Another mistake we can make
using lastPathComponent
is if you build the URL manually
using URLWithString,
because lastPathComponent
will still return this
if the slashes have been encoded
with percent encoding.
And when we go to use the URL,
it will decode the percent encoding,
so they've still managed
to make us traverse
outside of our intended directory.
So, what's the correct way to do this?
We'll take lastPathComponent
on the file name
and then make sure that there's
actually still a file name there.
We'll make sure it's not equal
to these special path components.
Otherwise we bail out
and refuse to process the file.
And we also have to make sure
to use fileURLWithPath,
which will add additional percent escapes
so we're not vulnerable to
these kinds of percent encoding attacks.
So, what have we learned from this?
Don't use remotely controllable parameters
in file paths.
It's so easy to get this wrong.
If you have to, use lastPathComponent
along with additional validation
and sanitization, as shown in our example.
And always make sure to use
fileURLWithPath,
which will add additional percent escapes
to your file paths
so you're not vulnerable
to these same percent encoding attacks.
But generally, just try and avoid
this pattern if you can.
Just use a temporary file path with
a locally-generated and random file name.
Some actions you can take right now
are to check for all uses
of untrusted strings
being passed into the following methods.
Another example
of mishandling untrusted data
is uncontrolled format strings.
So, we might have some method
like this in our application,
where we get a request message
from a device
and then generate a response from it
and send the response back to them.
We're going to do the same exercise here.
We want to look at our method
and figure out what's trusted
and what's not trusted,
and then figure out how we're using
the untrusted data.
So we look into it
and find out that this name
is the local user name on the device.
It's generated locally and can't be
influenced at all by the sender,
so we can trust this.
But then this request they're sending us
is again the sender-controlled payload.
They can send us
any arbitrary request message,
so we can't trust that.
So let's see how we're using
that parameter.
Well, we're taking the request,
and then we're grabbing this localized
format string off the request
and passing it to NSLocalizedString.
So the goal here is to generate
the correct response
in the user's local language
on the device.
But again,
this is just an arbitrary string,
so they can send us anything here,
even if we can't localize it.
Now when we pass it to string with format,
there won't be enough arguments here
to correctly format the string.
So what ends up happening is,
we'll actually be leaking the contents
of the stack
and sending that back to the person.
This can potentially reveal
sensitive information
from your application's memory,
or in some cases,
it can even allow an attacker
to take control over the execution
of your application.
So we definitely want to avoid this.
So what have we learned from this?
Never use or generate a format
string specifier from untrusted data.
There's actually no correct way
to do this, so just avoid this if you can.
Don't try and validate or filter
the format specifier either.
You'll probably get it wrong.
Make sure that you don't have the
format-security compiler flag disabled.
It is on by default,
but make sure you're not disabling it
for a section of code.
But we have to be aware
there are some cases this will not catch.
For example, the one we just looked at
won't actually give you a compiler warning
because in some cases,
the compiler can't do anything
to reason about the format string
if it's not a string literal.
You also have to be extra careful
with format strings in Swift,
because Swift doesn't have the level
of compiler validation for format strings
as C or Objective-C has.
So in Swift, you want to use
string interpolation wherever possible.
Sometimes you have to use format strings,
such as when you're building
these localized strings.
We just have to be extra vigilant
not to introduce bugs like this.
Some actions you can take right now
are to check for all uses
of untrusted strings
being passed into the following methods
as format specifiers.
So we've looked at
two common security issues so far
that are generally easy to find
when you know what you're searching for.
But it's not always straightforward.
A lot of the time you'll find logic issues
that untrusted data can take advantage of
to make your code flow
in unexpected directions.
The first one of these we'll look at
is state corruption issues.
In Loose Leaf, we've added the ability
to enter a live stream brewing session
with your tea club members.
To do this, we follow an invite-based
session state machine here,
where I can invite someone
to a brewing session,
and if they accept,
we'll end up in this connected state,
where I might share a live stream
from my device's camera.
Let's dive in a little deeper here
and look at what will transition us
between these states.
So I can send someone an invite,
and I'll end up in this inviting state
and they'll end up in the invited state.
If they accept the invite,
we'll both end up in this connected state
and might now share this connected
socket between our devices.
But what happens
if I send someone an invite
but also send them
an inviteAccept message?
Can I force them into this connected state
without them actually having
accepted our invitation?
Well, let's take a look
at the code here for this.
Now that we understand the difference
between trusted and untrusted data,
we should be able
to go through here quickly and see that
this is the verified sender address,
and I can trust this.
And this is the sender-controlled message,
so I can't trust that.
So what's happening here is
we're taking the type out of the message
and dispatching it to some other handler
based on the type of message.
But again, this comes
from the sender-controlled payload,
so they can still send us
any message type here.
Now, in this case, we want to look
at the inviteAccept message,
so let's jump into the handle there.
It looks like we're checking
that the session exists
based on the session identifier
that the sender gave us,
and then we're setting the state
to "connected."
It looks like in this case,
the sender can actually force us
into this connected state.
We're probably missing a check here.
We probably want to check
that we're actually in the inviting state
and are expecting to receive an "invite
accept" message before transitioning.
So, is this enough? Well, probably not.
There's probably some other checks
that we want to do,
some state invariant that has to be true
before proceeding.
So in this case,
we want to ensure that the inviteAccept
message that will transition us
is coming from someone
we actually invited.
So what have we learned here?
We want to define clear state invariants
that must be true before proceeding.
But as we saw, this can be really subtle
and easy to get wrong.
In our example, it wasn't just as simple
as checking
that we're in the correct state,
and there were other properties
we needed to validate before proceeding.
And we want to bail out early on
and refuse to proceed
if any of these checks fail,
as we don't want our code
to go in unexpected directions
that could potentially modify the state.
Another common logic bug you might find
is piggybacking on untrusted data.
So in our application,
we might do a lot of message processing,
where we take some JSON data
the sender gave us from over the network
and create a dictionary from it
that has this remote entry on it.
Then after we're done processing,
we tack on this other entry
to the dictionary.
And now you pass that dictionary
to another part of your application,
perhaps to modify the UI or the database.
And when it gets to that part of
your application and it's time to use it,
now we have to figure out
what's trusted on it before we use it.
So you might take a look
at the dictionary and go,
"This is the remote entry. And I know
this is the sender-controlled entry
because I know
it's sent over the Internet.
But this other entry, can I trust that?"
Well, you might think you can,
because you know it's generated locally
by your application,
so it can't be sender-controlled.
But it turns out,
of course we can't trust it
because it comes
from the sender-controlled message.
And they can give us this entry as well.
And if they can force our application
to go down some unexpected path
where it doesn't also tack on
this other entry,
then when it gets time
to use this message,
we have no idea
whether it came from the remote sender
or if it was generated locally.
So we have to assume
that we can't trust it.
Let's take a look at an example of this.
We've added the ability to react
to someone's live tea-brewing session,
and you can even attach
an image of your reaction
to show them what you think.
So it looks like we created
this Reaction object from the JSON data.
And if there was some image data attached,
we write it to a local file URL
during the message processing
and then set that as the imageURL
on the reaction object.
We then pass it to our ViewController
to display it.
So let's take a look
at what happens there.
If the imageURL is non-nil,
we'll display it...
then remove the image we wrote to disk
once it's finished displaying.
But because we're taking the imageURL
off of the same object
that's created with the untrusted data,
we've given an attacker
the ability to delete arbitrary files
that are accessible
from our application's container.
Because what will happen
if someone sends us this message
with the imageURL already set in it
is we'll skip over this block of code
because the image data wasn't set
and go straight to displaying it here.
But because the imageURL was set,
we'll try and show
whatever is at the file path,
but actually we'll end up deleting
whatever file was specified in the JSON.
So what have we learned from that?
You want to separate trusted
and untrusted data
into completely different objects.
Don't try and combine them
into a single object,
because what you'll be doing
is introducing ambiguity
between trusted and untrusted parameters.
We always want it to be very clear
what's untrusted
so that we can audit our use
of the untrusted data
and make sure it's always validated
and sanitized before we use it.
Now I'll hand it back over to Coops
to talk about NSCoding.
Thanks, Ryan.
NSCoding, and its more modern
NSSecureCoding companion,
have been around for a long time
and provide the valuable capability
to serialize and deserialize
complex graphs of objects.
It's the kind of thing we might use for
storing parsed data into our local cache,
or for a custom document format.
We're going to cover
some of the mistakes which we see
and which are particularly dangerous
if the archive comes from untrusted data.
To start, please stop using NSUnarchiver.
It's been deprecated for ages
and isn't suitable for data
coming from an untrusted source.
What you want to be using
is NSKeyedUnarchiver.
Much like NSUnarchiver, it allows you
to pack and unpack graphs of objects,
but it has the ability
to be used securely.
NSKeyedUnarchiver
has also been around for a while,
so there are deprecated ways of using it.
Many of you may be using it in these ways,
unaware that you're leaving your software
and your users exposed to attack.
The top set of methods here
are the ones you should be using.
The bottom ones are all legacy,
and if you're still using,
you should migrate away from
as soon as possible.
The naming of the two sets is very close,
but all the deprecated ones
are named "with" rather than "from."
The reason we deprecated these methods
is that they're incompatible
with secure coding.
You might not fully understand
what secure coding is,
so let's look at the problem it solves.
Without secure coding,
when you take an archive
and call unarchiveObjectWithData,
it unpacks an object graph for you.
In this example, we're expecting
to get back an array of strings.
The problem here
is that the types of objects created
are specified inside the archive.
If that comes from an untrusted source
or can be modified by an attacker,
any NSCoding-compliant object
can be returned.
What this means is an attacker
might modify the archive
and cause us to unpack
a completely unexpected class,
like WKWebView.
Although this object might not conform
to the interface we expect,
and you may even perform a type check,
a security issue still remains,
as any bugs reachable by an attacker
during the un-archiving of the class
will have triggered already.
Secure coding resolves these issues
by restricting the compatible classes
to those which implement
the secure coding protocol
and requires that you specify the classes
you expect at each call site.
This information is used
inside the KeyedUnarchiver
to perform validation
before the decoding is even attempted.
Doing this drastically reduces
the number of classes
which can be leveraged by an attacker
and thus reduces the attack surface.
But even with this, there are a number
of common mistakes we see.
Let's take a look at some.
In this simple example,
we're using secure coding
to retrieve an array of objects.
The issue here is that we've specified
NSObject in the allowedClasses set.
Secure coding will decode objects
which conform to its protocol
and are either in the allowedClasses set
or a subclass of one specified.
As all objects derive from NSObject,
this allows any secure coded object
to be decoded,
undermining the attack surface reduction
which secure coding gave us.
This is a simple example
which is easy to spot,
but we also see this happening
in more complex cases,
where class lists get passed
through multiple layers of framework
and end up being supplied
to a KeyedUnarchiver method.
Another similar pattern is this.
A string is decoded from the archive.
That string is then used to look up
a class via NSClassFromString,
the resulting class
used as the allowedClass
for the extraction of an object.
Hopefully
the issue here is obvious to people.
Both the className
and thus the resulting allowedClass
are under attacker control.
As such, they can easily pass the name
of a specific class
or even NSObject
and bypass the benefits of secure coding.
So how do we solve these problems?
If possible, simply use a restricted,
static set of classes,
making sure to avoid classes
which are the base for large hierarchies
to reduce the number of classes
available to an attacker.
What about the case where you do
want to support dynamic classes?
One of the most common places we see this
is where support for plug-ins is required.
In this case, we recommend creating
the allowedClass list dynamically,
but from trusted data.
The easiest way to do this
is where your plug-in supports a protocol.
Thus you can simply enumerate all
the classes that the runtime knows about
and create a set of those
which conform to the protocol.
This can then be safely used
with secure decoding,
as the class list is outside
the attacker's control.
To summarize, migrate your code away from
all the deprecated methods and classes,
avoid using NSObject
or overly generic base classes,
and use a static allowedClass list
wherever possible.
And when you can't,
generate it from trusted data.
Another good alternative
is to avoid it completely
and use things like Swift Codable
or a less flexible encoding format
like plist, JSON or protobuf.
You can act on this information right away
by searching your codebase
for use of these items
in areas which deal with untrusted data.
Another problem which plagues
high-risk code is memory corruption.
Whenever using Objective-C
or Swift's UnsafePointer,
it's possible to introduce
memory safety issues.
These are particularly prevalent
when parsing untrusted data,
be it from a buffer, a string,
or out of a structured archive.
Let's take a look at some examples.
As we've talked about already,
security issues arise
when untrusted data
is mistaken for trusted data.
In this example,
we're unpacking the CloudKit record
for a private tea club.
The first thing we do is copy the bytes
of the UUID into an iVar.
If we take a look at each element,
we can see that the CKRecord is trusted,
as it's generated by CloudKit.
But the data fields retrieved from it
are under attacker control.
So we can't trust that they contain
a fixed amount of data.
The problem here is that the length
of the data is under attackers' control,
but the size of the UUID iVar is fixed.
As such, if the supplied NSData
contains more than the UUID can hold,
attacker-controlled data
will be written out of bounds.
To see why this can be a problem,
we need to look at what will happen.
In the object which contains the UUID,
we can see that the next iVar
is the path to the local cache.
Now, this field isn't set
from the CloudKit record.
Thus,
overflowing the UUID allows an attacker
to gain control of a field
they shouldn't have the ability to.
The memcpy will cause
attacker-controlled data
to be written into UUID as intended,
but as the size is too great,
it will overflow into localCachePath.
With this, they can reconfigure
the cache for the group,
causing files to be downloaded
and overwriting
the users' local preferences.
Using various techniques,
attackers can use these kind of bugs
to get code execution
inside your application,
which gives them access
to all your users' data
and access to all the resources
that were granted to you.
The obvious fix for this
would be to use sizeof(_uuid),
but this exposes a different problem,
as, if the attacker supplies
less data than expected,
the memcpy will read
off the end of "data,"
causing other user secrets in memory
to be disclosed into the UUID field.
When the app syncs that information
back to the server,
it will encode that user data
and return it to the attacker.
The correct fix is to validate that
the object we retrieved is an NSData
and check its length is an exact match.
This prevents both
the overwrite of the destination
and the overread of the source.
Whilst this is a simple example,
extra care should always be taken
when parsing untrusted data,
particularly where the format
is complex or nested.
Always validate lengths,
as even casting a C structure
onto a buffer
will disclose user information
if there is insufficient data.
Another case where we need to be careful
is when dealing with integers,
as these have a habit of overflowing.
In this example,
further down the same method,
we extract an NSData
with UNICHAR characters
and a count from a separate field.
As before,
we should look at which data is trusted.
In this case,
both name and count are untrusted,
as they've come
from attacker-controlled data.
Now, the developer has foreseen the danger
of blindly trusting the count,
and so validates it
against the length of the data.
But there's a problem.
The attacker actually controls
both sides of this comparison,
and there exists a set of values
where the assumptions the developer made
are no longer correct.
In this case, if an attacker passes
a zero-length string for "name"
and 80 million hex for nameCount,
the integer will overflow
and the "if" statement will fail.
This will result in a very large read
off the end of "name,"
potentially disclosing user data.
The fix is to add
a comprehensive validation check,
checking the type and the length.
But most importantly,
use of the os_overflow method
to perform the arithmetic.
In this case, we've used os_mul_overflow.
For those which don't know about them,
os_overflow
is a really useful set of functions
which allow safe handling of numbers
and robust detection
of under- and overflow conditions.
Use is simple.
Just replace your arithmetic operation
with the relevant os_overflow method.
We've provided ones for add,
subtract and multiplication,
using both two and three parameters.
On overflow, they return non-zero.
Using these makes it easy to ensure
that calculations
using attacker-controlled values
can be performed safely.
So to summarize,
always validate length
and consider all cases.
Too big, too small,
it should be just right.
When working with numbers,
be wary of arithmetic,
as if you're not using
os_overflow functions,
there's a high risk you'll make a mistake.
Finally, seriously consider using Swift
for these high-risk code paths,
though remember to avoid the use
of UnsafePointer
and other raw memory
manipulation features.
In closing,
hopefully this talk has given you
some ideas of how to think about security
and some examples of common pitfalls
to try and avoid.
Security is a huge topic, and it's hard,
because as we've seen,
the smallest error can be enough
to compromise your entire application.
But by understanding where the risk is,
designing to mitigate it
and taking care
when handling untrusted data,
we can massively reduce the chances
of things going wrong.
Thanks for coming.