Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, and thanks for joining us.
My name is Roman,
and I'm a shortcuts engineer at Apple.
Today I'm going to be sharing with you
some techniques and some strategies
for efficiently implementing Siri
and Shortcuts support
in your applications.
First, we are going to take a tour
of the new APIs in SiriKit.
Then, we are going to learn all about
how you can fine-tune custom intents
in your app.
So let's start with a brief overview.
SiriKit encompasses the Intents
and Intents UI frameworks,
which you use to integrate your services
with Siri, Shortcuts, and Maps.
And in iOS 14,
you can use Intents to add configuration
and intelligence to widgets.
An Intents UI app extension
displays custom UI in the Siri,
Shortcuts, or Maps interface
after your Intents app extension
fulfills a user request.
An Intents app extension
receives user requests from SiriKit
and turns them into app-specific actions,
such as sending a message,
playing some music,
getting current weather conditions,
or ordering a soup.
SiriKit defines a large number
of system intents
that represent common tasks people take.
For system intents,
Siri defines the conversational flow
while your app provides the data
to complete the interaction.
If your app lets people perform
an everyday task
that doesn't fit into any
of the SiriKit domains,
you can create a custom intent
to represent it.
The job of your Intents extension
is to provide SiriKit
with the handler objects
that you use to handle specific intents.
You provide these objects
from the handlerForIntent: method
of your extension.
Let's take a look at the life cycle
of handling an intent.
Every time the user
interacts with an intent,
whether at the resolve,
confirm, or handle phases,
your intent handler has ten seconds
to complete the request.
The ten-second timeout starts
as soon as the user request
initiates a connection to your extension.
When this happens,
if your extension is not yet running,
it will be launched by the system.
The amount of time it takes
to launch your extension
depends on how long it takes to load
all of the frameworks your process links,
and how much time it takes
to run the +loads
and static initializers
included in your process
or any frameworks it links.
Your extension also needs some time
to perform your business logic.
So it's important to optimize
for launch time
by making sure that your extension only
links the frameworks that it really needs,
because the time spent loading
all of the link frameworks
counts towards the ten-second timeout.
The amount of time it takes
to handle a request
also affects how people perceive
interactions with your app.
Siri interactions are intended to be quick
and lightweight,
so you should avoid making the user wait
while your intent handler is working.
Ten seconds seems like a lot.
Since in most of the cases
your Intents extension
doesn't really need to link all
of the frameworks that your app links,
you have the opportunity to minimize
the number of symbols that you import.
Another noteworthy characteristic
of Intents extensions
is that they are modular,
independently run processes
with a lower memory footprint than an app.
However, sometimes it's not always
possible or convenient to use extensions.
In iOS 14,
we are introducing in-app intent handling.
Now, you have an option
to add an intent handler to your app
where you can handle SiriKit requests
such as Resolve, Confirm, Handle.
Let's talk about a few good use cases
that should help you decide
when to handle your intents
in your app versus your extension.
Starting or controlling media playback,
or starting a workout,
previously required you to perform
resolve and confirm
in your Intents extension,
and then handle in your app.
It is more efficient to do this entirely
in your app process now.
In another scenario,
if handling your intent affects
your app's user interface live on-screen,
it's also a good candidate
for in-app intent handling.
In-app intent handling also opens up
an opportunity for new use cases
that weren't possible before
due to memory constraints of extensions,
such as photo and video processing.
And, well, let's be honest,
in some cases your app's structure
doesn't currently allow you
to factor out code
into an intents extension
or a shared framework.
But, of course, be mindful
about the launch time of your app
because it will eat
into the ten-second timeout
we talked about earlier in this session.
When you're designing
your intent handlers,
you should evaluate which intents need
to be handled in your intents extension,
and which can be moved to your app.
Let's see how you can implement support
for in-app intent handling in your app.
The first thing you need to do
is to make sure that your app
supports multiple windows
and has adopted the UIScene life cycle.
When your app is launched
in a response to a SiriKit request,
it will be launched without any
UIScene objects connected to your app.
Then, you need to list all of the intents
that you would like to handle
inside of your application
in the Supported Intents section
of your app's target.
And finally, you need to implement
the handlerForIntent: method
in your app's delegate.
This method acts as a dispatcher
mapping incoming intents
to the object capable of handling them.
In your implementation,
check the type of the intent parameter
and return an object capable
of handling that type of intent.
The object you return must adopt
the protocol used to handle that intent.
For example, when handling
a ProcessPhotoIntent object,
return an object that adopts
the ProcessPhotoIntentHandling protocol.
If handling an intent updates
your application's user interface,
and requires your users to be looking
at something in the app
before using the intent,
your intent handler may need to make sure
that the relevant UI is on-screen
in the handle phase.
You can do this by checking to make sure
the app is not in the background.
And if it is, asking the system to open it
by responding with continueInApp
response code.
Let's see how to add
in-app intent handling
to an app in Xcode.
I got into cooking at home recently,
so I've been working on this app
called Recipe Assistant
that allows me
to browse my favorite recipes.
When I tap on a recipe,
I can see all of the ingredients
needed to make this recipe.
I can tap on the "Directions" button
to view step-by-step directions.
When I tap on the "Next Step" button
I can advance to the next step.
However, sometimes
it's not always convenient
to tap buttons on-screen
while you're preparing the meal.
So I would like users of my app
to be able to advance to the next step
by using a shortcut that they invoke
with their voice using Siri.
I'm going to implement
in-app intent handling in my app
since my users will be interacting
with the content on-screen.
Here in Xcode,
I have my intent-definition file
where I define my custom intent
called "ShowDirections."
I also added the "Add to Siri" button
to my recipe directions view
so users can easily set up
a shortcut here.
This is what it looks like in the app.
Now, back to Xcode.
I have already adopted
multiple-window support in my app.
Now, I need to add ShowDirectionsIntent
to the list of intents eligible
for in-app intent handling.
To do that, I'm going to click
on the "Plus" button and add my intent.
Now, what I want to do is to make
every view controller in my app
to be able to respond
to the "Next Step" command.
To do that, I'm going to define
a common intent handler
that accepts an object conforming
to the NextStepProviding protocol.
A view controller that adopts
the NextStepProviding protocol
will need to return an instance
of the IntentHandler class.
It would also need to implement
the nextStep function
that will take the user to the next step
in the app.
Let's conform our intent handler
to the showDirectionsIntentHandling
protocol
that was code-generated for us,
and implement the resolve method.
In the resolve method
for the recipe parameter,
we are going to check if we have a recipe.
If we don't have a recipe,
we will ask for disambiguation.
Otherwise, we will return success.
In the handle method,
we are going to tell
the next-step provider
to go to the next step.
We need to make sure that our app
is in the foreground.
And if it's not,
that we are going to launch the app
using the continueInApp response code.
We will need to handle launching
with a user activity in our SceneDelegate,
and I will come back to this in a moment.
Now, I will create a new singleton class
that will hold a weak reference
to the current intent handler.
We are going to assign
the current intent handler
in viewDidAppear
of each view controller in our app.
In my app delegate,
I need to implement
the new handlerForIntent: method,
and return the current
IntentHandler instance.
In my SceneDelegate object,
I need to implement
both willConnectToSession
and continueUserActivity methods
to continue user activity when we respond
with continueInApp response code
in our handle method.
willConnectToSession will be invoked
when the app does not have
a UIScene object connected to it.
Now, we need to conform
each view controller
to the NextStepProviding protocol.
And finally, we need to make sure
to assign the current intent handler
in viewDidAppear.
Let's give it a try.
First, I need to add my shortcut to Siri.
Now, let's see what the experience
looks like.
Hey Siri, next step.
[Siri chimes]
[Siri] Which recipe would you like to see?
Spicy tomato sauce, chickpea curry,
or cinnamon apple cake? [chimes]
The first one.
[Siri chimes] Okay. Viewing.
Here are the ingredients
for spicy tomato sauce.
Hey Siri, next step.
[Siri chimes] Okay. Viewing.
Step one, in a large pot,
heat olive oil on medium heat.
Hey Siri, next step.
[Siri chimes] Okay. Viewing.
Step two, add minced garlic
and sauté for a few seconds
until fragrant.
Pretty cool, isn't it?
When deciding between handling an intent
in an extension versus an app,
you should ask yourself first,
can this task be accomplished
in an extension?
Because if so, it's better to do that.
Intents extensions can be more lightweight
and faster to launch
depending on the number of frameworks
and symbols that you link.
This is your opportunity
to optimize for launch time
since you decide which frameworks
your extension is linking.
To summarize what we learned
about in-app intent handling today,
consider implementing
an Intents extension first.
Always be mindful
of how many frameworks you link
in both your app and your extensions.
In-app intent handling is only supported
for multi-window apps,
so make sure to check out
"Introducing Multiple Windows on iPad"
and "Architecting Your App
for Multiple Windows"
from WWDC 2019.
We are very excited to see
all the great new SiriKit integrations
that you will build
using in-app intent handling.
Now, let's take a look
at another API enhancement
that we made this year.
We call it "rich disambiguation."
In iOS 13, we introduced
parameters for Shortcuts
which allow your users to provide
intent parameter values at runtime.
When resolving parameter values
of your intent,
you can return disambiguation
resolution result,
and the user will be prompted
to pick from a list of values.
This year, we are introducing the ability
for your app to include subtitles
and images in those lists.
The API is pretty simple.
You just need to provide
the subtitle as a string,
and the image as INImage,
for your custom types at runtime.
What's really cool is that
you can also provide dynamic options
with images and subtitles
that your users will see
when they configure your intent
in the Shortcuts app.
Another addition to disambiguation lists
is pagination in Siri.
As a developer, now you can provide
the number of items
that Siri should speak
to the user at once,
and also provide subsequent introductions
spoken by Siri.
The disambiguation pagination
will be only used
when the user invokes Siri
by saying, "Hey Siri."
Here's how to support rich disambiguation
with Xcode.
Open your intent-definition file
where you define your custom intents
and expand the Siri Dialog section
for the parameter that needs
customized disambiguation pagination.
Here, you can simply specify
the maximum number of items
that can be spoken to the user at once,
as well as the subsequent
introduction stream.
You can also override the disambiguation
introduction dialog
provided by Siri in the voice-only mode
by specifying your own dialog
in the intent editor.
Another addition to the SiriKit APIs
this year
is dynamic search for dynamic options.
Last year, we introduced
a dynamic-options API
that allows you to provide a set of values
for eligible parameters dynamically
when the user is configuring your intent
in the Shortcuts app.
This year, we are expanding this API
to include the search term
provided by the user.
There is a new checkbox
to provide search results as you type.
If you check the checkbox,
it will code-generate a new method
that includes searchTerm.
This method will be called repeatedly
while the user is typing.
If the search term is empty,
you can provide the user
with a list of default values.
Dynamic search should only be adopted
for searching large catalogs,
not for filtering small static collections
because the Shortcuts app
supports filtering by default.
The provide options collections method
completion handler
accepts a new INObjectCollection object.
Using this new object,
you can now group your dynamic options
into sections with titles,
and optionally use indexed collation.
In iOS 13, we introduced configurable
parameters for Shortcuts.
Each parameter that you specified
as user-facing
had to be resolved at runtime.
Now, in iOS 14,
you can mark each parameter
as configurable and resolvable separately.
Siri and the Shortcuts app
will not resolve parameters
which are marked as unresolvable.
You don't need to provide Siri dialog
for unresolvable parameters.
Today, you learned all about
in-app intent handling,
and how you can add support for it
in your apps.
You can enhance your disambiguation lists
and dynamic options
with rich disambiguation in iOS 14.
Dynamic search gives you
a new, flexible way
of providing dynamic options
for your intent parameters.
When you're designing your intents,
decide which parameters
should be configurable
and resolvable at runtime.
Now, let's take a look at some useful tips
and tricks
that could help you take
your custom intents to the next level.
If one of your custom intents
is no longer needed
because you discontinued
the corresponding feature in your app,
or you're replacing the intent
with another intent,
it is now possible to deprecate
custom intents in iOS 14 using Xcode 12.
In the intent editor,
select the intent
that you would like to deprecate,
and reveal the inspectors
by clicking on the "Expand Inspectors"
button in the toolbar.
Now, all you need to do
is just check the deprecated checkbox.
In the Shortcuts app,
your existing users will see
that this intent action
might be no longer available
in future versions of your app.
Additionally, this intent action will
be hidden from the Shortcuts action list.
Now, let's talk about how you can specify
your custom-intent class names.
When you define a custom intent,
a custom type,
or a custom enum in the intent editor,
you define a type name,
not the actual class.
The actual class will be code-generated
for you based on the type name.
So if your app uses a class prefix,
this is not the right place to specify
for your custom intents, types, and enums.
Instead, provide your desired class name
in the Custom Class inspector
of your intent.
Alternatively, you can specify
a common class prefix
used for all custom intents,
types, and enums
in the Project Document inspector
of your target
where the code generation needs to happen.
This allows you to have
different class prefixes
in different targets if you need.
Some custom intents that you define
in your intent-definition file
may require an Intents UI view
for the confirm and handle phases,
while others don't.
Let's see how you can
efficiently manage that.
When add your intent-definition file
to an Intents UI extension target,
Xcode automatically lists
all of the intents
from that intent-definition file
as supported by this Intents UI extension.
However, for some of your custom intents,
you might not want to display
any UI at all.
You can easily achieve this by creating
a separate intent-definition file
for your non-UI intents.
Then, in the target membership inspector
of your intent-definition file,
simply don't include it
in your Intents UI extension target.
Sometimes you might want to explicitly
choose the code-generation language
for your custom intents.
And you can easily do this
in your project's build settings.
By default,
Xcode will automatically decide
the intent code-generation language
for each of the targets eligible
for code generation
based on the existing search files
included in this target.
But here, you have an option
to customize this behavior.
So we've gone over a lot today.
We've gone over some
of the major enhancements
in the SiriKit APIs this year.
We've also gone over
some of the best practices
that you can keep in mind
when you're designing your custom intents.
Thank you so much for watching,
and we can't wait to see what you build.