Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name is Tanuja Mohan,
and I'm a software engineer on
the Power and Performance team at Apple.
Animations are an important part
in our application's customer experience.
Animations can be subtle,
such as when we tap on the back button
to navigate from one screen to another,
or they can be
the main focus of a gesture,
such as when we scroll up or down
on an application.
We want these gestures
to produce smooth responses
since it's noticeable when a navigation
takes too long
or a scroll appears to jitter.
We call these user perceptible jitters
"hitches."
A hitch is any time that a frame appears
on the screen later than expected.
This is distracting to your users
and is detrimental to
the perceived quality of your application.
Let's zoom in on the individual frames
of our application
to see what is really going on.
The first three frames are displayed
as expected.
We have a gradual movement of the list,
perfectly matching
the movement of our finger.
But then frame three remains
on the screen.
The application no longer appears
to track the movement of your finger.
Then, when frame four
is displayed to screen,
the list makes a sudden large jump
back to your finger.
This is not what we expect
and what we want to avoid.
To understand what is happening here,
we first need to understand
how frames are displayed to the screen.
Frames on iPhones and iPads are
usually expected to update at 60 hertz,
giving a cadence of 16.67 milliseconds
for each frame.
On iPad Pro,
we can expect 120 hertz updates,
or a cadence of 8.33 milliseconds.
This cadence is represented by VSYNCs,
which are when the screen determines
whether to swap a frame
onto the display or not.
We see a hitch
when a frame misses its expected VSYNC.
The severity of a hitch is measured by
how late the frame is to appear on-screen.
In this example,
frame four is 16.67 milliseconds late.
There are two ways
we can quantify hitches.
Hitch time is the time in milliseconds
that a frame is late to display on-screen.
We prefer to express hitch ratio,
milliseconds per second,
which is the total hitch time
in milliseconds
over some other duration
of time in seconds.
For example, over the duration of a test.
This sounds complicated.
Why don't we just say dropped frames
and measure frames per second?
Frames per second is an absolute target
that is easily skewed.
If your test contains any resting time
during the execution of an animation,
then fps is useless since we did not
expect any frames to be swapped
during the resting period.
And we often intentionally
do not target the maximum fps.
Maybe a game only wants to run at 30 fps,
or a video at 24 fps.
For power and performance reasons,
the hands on the Clock app icon
only run at ten fps.
Hitch time's target is always zero and is
reliable even with these considerations.
But hitch time is not always comparable.
Total hitch time for a one-second test
cannot be compared
to that over a ten-second test.
By normalizing hitch ratio as milliseconds
of hitches per second of test duration,
we get a metric that is both comparable
across different tests
and can be used as an approximation
for the end user impact.
For end user impact, these are the target
hitch ratios we recommend
and use in our tools.
A hitch ratio of less than
five milliseconds per second
is good user experience.
In the five-to-ten millisecond
per second range,
users will start to notice hitches,
and these hitches should be investigated.
At ten milliseconds per second or more,
hitches are quite distracting to the user,
and we should take immediate action
to resolve them.
In iOS 14, you can track hitches in both
your development and production workflows
using our suite of tools.
The XCTest framework allows you to collect
hitch and animation data
directly in unit and UI tests,
while MetricKit and Xcode Organizer
give you access
to performance metrics
from your customers.
In this portion of the talk, we're going
to focus on the development workflow
of catching hitches
using Performance XCTests.
If you wanna learn how you can view
hitches in your production workflow,
check out the separate talks we have
for MetricKit and Xcode Organizer
this year at WWDC 2020 as well.
In Xcode 11, we introduced XCTMetrics.
These metrics specify
what part of the system
you want to measure in your test.
The XCTMetrics we have available today
allow you to test around clock time,
CPU utilization, memory use,
os_signposts, storage,
and with Xcode 12,
we have a separate metric
to measure application launch times.
We also have a template for you
to write your own custom metrics.
In this talk, we will focus
on the XCTOSSignpostMetric,
which is the XCTMetric
used to do animation performance testing.
Starting with Xcode 11,
you can use the XCTOSSignpostMetric
to measure the duration
of the os_signpost interval.
Now, with Xcode 12, when using
an animation os_signpost interval,
you will receive not just duration,
but also three hitch related metrics,
frame rate, and frame count.
You may already be familiar
with frame rate and frame count.
These two values measure the frequency
and number of frames
displayed to the screen respectively.
And now you are also familiar
with hitches.
You can now track how many hitches
occur in the tested code block,
what the total duration is
we spent hitching in our test,
and the ratio of this total time hitching
over the duration
of the measured code block.
To collect these metrics,
you first need to instrument your code
to emit an os_signpost interval.
There are three ways you can do this,
and we will refer to them
as non-animation intervals--
intervals that only return back duration,
and animation intervals--
intervals that return back
the additional animation metrics.
With Xcode 11, you could only instrument
a non-animation os_signpost interval
using the "begin" and "end" interfaces.
This would just return back duration.
Now, in Xcode 12, to specify
an animation os_signpost interval,
all you need to do is use
the animationBegin interface instead.
With just this one change, you can convert
any of your existing instrumentation
to emit animation intervals instead
and receive back the animation metrics
mentioned earlier.
Aside from using a custom interval,
you can use one of the predefined
UIKit instrumented intervals
for testing around navigation transitions
and scrolling.
These are sub-metrics provided on
the XCTOSSignpostMetric class.
Let's take a look at an example of writing
a test using one of these sub-metrics.
Here I have a performance XCTest
that is going to launch my application,
tap on the "Meal Planner" cell,
and swipe up on the foodCollection view
to scroll down.
In this test,
I'm specifying that I want to measure
the scrollDeceleration sub-metric.
In the body of the measure block,
I'm swiping up,
and now with Xcode 12, you can customize
the velocity of the scroll.
This test looks good so far,
but there is an improvement we can make.
Remember by default
a measure block is run five times
to collect performance measurements.
Meaning that
in the current implementation,
we are going to swipe up five times
back-to-back
and will most likely be swiping
over different content in each iteration.
To avoid this, we want to reset
the application state between runs.
We can do this
by using the XCTMeasureOptions
to let our measure block know
that we are going to manually stop
our measurement collection.
Then, pass this into our measure block,
call stopMeasuring,
and then reset our application state.
Now that we have our test written,
we wanna run it.
But before we do so, we first wanna modify
some settings on our test scheme
to eliminate their impact
on our performance measurements.
We first wanna make sure we use a separate
test scheme for our Performance XCTests.
Then, we wanna select the release build
configuration and disable the debugger.
We also wanna disable
automatic screenshot collection
and turn off code coverage.
And finally, we wanna turn off
all diagnostic options.
These are the options listed under
Runtime Sanitization,
Runtime API Checking,
and Memory Management.
Now we can run our Performance XCTest
and view our results in the report UI.
In the drop-down,
we can see our new animation metrics.
Let's select the Hitch Time Ratio metric.
We see that we collected measurements
for five iterations...
and we got an average of 1.2 milliseconds
per second for our hitch time ratio.
As a next step,
we could set this average value
of 1.2 milliseconds per second
as our baseline,
so that any future runs of this test
would be compared to this baseline value.
Let's take a look at an example of how you
might encounter a hitch in your code base
and how you can use a Performance XCTest
to prevent it from shipping
to your customers.
Let's say I'm an app developer
at a meal planner company
that wants to support online orders
and deliveries.
So far, I've implemented a view that lists
the different menu items available.
As a next step,
I wanna make my food appealing
by including images of what
the different dishes look like.
Before I dive into writing
this new feature,
I wanna measure
my current animation performance,
so I can use it as a baseline
to compare for after I add the feature.
I've set up a separate test scheme
for my performance test
and have configured the settings
to what we talked about earlier.
I can now write my test.
As we saw before,
I'm going to launch my application,
tap on the "Meal Planner" cell,
and measure
my scrolling animation performance.
I've already pre-ran this test,
so let's take a look at our measurements.
It looks like we have zero hitches
and our animations are performing
as expected.
Let's go ahead and add in our new feature.
First, I'm gonna set my image view
to contain the images
I've already pre-included in my project.
Second, I'm gonna scale these images
so that they fit well in my application.
Now we can go ahead
and rerun our performance test.
Note that when using
the XCTOSSignpostMetric,
the measure block will listen for when
your instrumented os_signpost interval
is emitted within the code block
and collect metrics only for the code
executed within this interval.
Another thing to note
is that a measure block supports listening
for multiple distinct
os_signpost intervals.
For example, you could listen
for both the scrollDeceleration
and scrollDragging os_signpost intervals
within the same block of code
that calls swipe up.
Let's skip ahead
to the completion of this test.
It looks like we have an increase
in the number of hitches
and we should immediately investigate.
It looks like our issue is here
in our scaleAspectFit call.
We are redrawing the image
on the main thread
which is responsible for rendering
the rest of the UI.
We are using the CPU, which creates
new pixels and allocates memory.
We can reduce this impact
by using Core Animation's setContentMode
which will hand off redrawing these images
to the GPU.
This allows us to use
the existing image pixels,
reducing the amount of work we do
on the main thread.
We can rerun our Performance XCTest again
to see if this resolves the issue.
We can confirm that our animation metrics
now report back zero hitches
and our performance is back
to what we expect.
Using our Performance XCTest,
we were able to see
that our new feature caused a regression,
giving us a chance to fix it,
and that now our feature
is ready to reach our customers.
Let's recap what we've talked about.
We learned that a hitch occurs
any time a frame appears on the screen
later than expected.
And we can quantify these hitches
using the recommended good,
warning and critical categories.
We then learned that we can catch hitches
in our development workflow
using Performance XCTest.
We can do this by using a UIKit or custom
animation os_signpost interval.
We also talked about best practices,
which include resetting our
application content between iterations
and configuring our scheme settings
to prevent inaccuracies.
With this knowledge, you are now ready
to prevent hitches in your code base
and provide smooth animation experiences
to your customers.
Thank you for listening,
and we hope you have a great
rest of your conference.