Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. Today we're gonna talk about
creating great enterprise applications
with Apple technology,
and with me is Aaron Levie,
the founder and CEO of Box.
Welcome, Aaron.
Hey, Mike. Great to be here.
Thanks a lot for having me.
Right now,
it's a very, very interesting time
with remote working in COVID
and some of the things it's requiring.
Aaron, what are you hearing
from your customers
in terms of this new world
that we're entering?
Obviously, this has been
just a complete transformation
in how people work in organizations
of all sizes all around the world,
obviously, brought on by
an incredibly tragic and difficult event
with massive health care
and economic impact,
but what it really did was cause companies
to have to accelerate
their digital transformation strategies,
in some cases,
by multiple years or a decade.
So, one example is, we have a project
going on right now at Box
which is to improve
the performance of our application.
So, we want every single part of our app
to be able to work in less than a second,
whether you're on the Web or on mobile,
wherever you are.
And normally, that would be five, ten,
15 people working on that project
in different meetings,
on whiteboards at the office,
and that was what we thought of
as productivity.
That's what we thought of
as creativity and collaboration.
Now, when we're in a virtual environment,
we have 100 people in a Slack channel
that are all contributing ideas
of how we can get to sub-second latency
across our application.
And so we can now include
people from all different departments,
all different teams,
people that normally wouldn't have
thought of themselves
as performance engineers,
can now contribute ideas
to this way of actually driving updates
and pretty important upgrades
to our software.
And so, a lot of opportunity, I think,
for digital transformation today,
and really excited
to have that conversation with you.
And, obviously, with Apple
being so important in this space,
it's great to be here.
I'm also, frankly, personally, curious
what you guys are doing as well
in this environment.
Yeah, we'll talk a bit more about that.
One of the things that we're seeing,
especially in
this remote work environment right now,
is companies like IBM, and Oracle,
and others that are Mac,
that use a lot of Macs,
really want zero-touch deployment
using Apple Business Manager,
so they can ship that device to that
new employee or the existing employee,
and it's all set up for them.
And so, I think there's a general trend
that we're seeing of,
how do we actually enable
that remote worker to be more effective
across the board, across all our devices,
across all of our products.
And so, in this new world that we're in,
which is probably
not going to go back to the old way,
what is Box doing to kind of advance
on the product side to realize this?
So, we think that the future
is a hybrid one,
where offices are going to be playing
an important role.
At the same time, we think
that there's going to be more flexibility,
more agility
introduced to the ways that we work
that give people more choice and allow
them to be more productive from anywhere.
And so, the center of that, that ability
to create a hybrid environment
where we can work from the office
or work from anywhere,
the cloud is at the center of that,
and delivering a modern digital workplace
is at the center of those two worlds.
And so, we think a digital workplace
is going to bridge the physical
and the virtual in the future.
At the center of that digital workplace,
we need modern technologies
to be able to do our work.
We need to be able to have modern devices
like MacBooks and iPhones and iPads.
We need to be able to be
on modern and secure networks.
We need to be able to protect our identity
from the cloud,
so we can work from anywhere.
We need to be able
to collaborate in real time,
to be able to hop on a video call,
whether that's WebEx or Zoom
or Google Hangouts.
We need to be able to chat and communicate
on products like Slack and other tools.
And our job at Box is, we want to be
the best way to manage content securely
in that remote
and distributed way of working.
And so, anytime you want to
be able to access files,
anytime you want to be able to
share files securely with your partners
and your colleagues and people in
and outside of your business,
we want to be the best way
to do that in the cloud.
Fortunately, we work with
nearly 100,000 customers globally.
We're in about 70% of the Fortune 500,
and we have amazing organizations
that are trying to enable
this new digital way of working,
where on a moment's notice, you can hop on
a new MacBook or jump on an iPad
and be able to get to
all of the data in your enterprise
that you have access to
in a very secure way,
and be able to securely collaborate
and share with the people
that matter most in your business.
So we've really pivoted our road map
and pivoted our strategy
to help our customers
with these remote work use cases
to really be able to help customers
drive a new level of
digital transformation in their business.
There's sort of two big pillars
that we think about.
The first is the pillar of,
how do you enable collaboration
and modern work to get done
in this new distributed environment
where you might go into the office or you
might work from anywhere instantaneously?
And that's technology
and products and services
like the ability
to collaborate in real time.
We are really excited. We're working with
an all-new version of our iPad app
that will have Apple Pencil support.
So you'll be able to annotate
in real time on a document
and be able to make sure
that those annotations are seen on the Web
or on the desktop from other people that
need to be able to collaborate with you.
We're working on all-new ways to be able
to securely share content
on mobile devices in a very seamless way.
So, we're really, really excited about
the innovation that's coming
for helping remote workers
and being able to work in this modern way.
At the same time,
we're also really excited
about the number of business processes
that we're seeing that are now going
to be digitized for the future of work,
and that's in a range of industries.
From banking to health care to education
to life sciences and more.
So that's how
we've sort of pivoted our strategy
to make sure that we can
help support customers right now.
And in that strategy,
could you elaborate a little bit more
around Apple technology and how you
think about that in your business
as well as
what you're hearing from your customers?
Fundamentally, we think
that there's a bridging
of the consumer-grade technology
that we're used to in our personal lives,
whether it's a device like a MacBook
or an iPhone,
as well as the cloud services
and the security
that we need from an enterprise context.
And that's really where, obviously,
products like Box comes in.
So, we are building across
all the core platforms.
Across Apple products, our vision is that
we want to deliver the most seamless way
of getting work done.
Whether you're leveraging a MacBook
or whether you want to be able to
collaborate securely on an iOS device,
we make sure
that we have an iOS-first strategy
in terms of
how we design our applications,
making sure that we're leveraging
the best user experiences.
And again, fundamentally thinking about
this as a consumer-grade experience.
How do we bring consumer-grade experiences
into the enterprise,
so people,
no matter where they're working from,
they don't have to worry about
all the complexity the support
and all the challenges that you might
have to have in a normal IT environment.
And that's really going to require
consumer-grade solutions
to being able to enable
this new way of working.
Mm-hmm. And I think
that's one of the reasons
why our companies work so well together,
because we are
obviously very consumer-focused.
We obviously have this focus
on the enterprise as well that's emerging.
We want to bring that consumer DNA
and that kind of consumer thinking
in the products to enterprise products.
So, if I think about even the things
that we're working on right now,
it's expanding
on zero-touch Mac deployments,
it's expanding on auto-advance to
allow an organization to order computers,
so once they arrive,
they can just plug them right in
and instantly, that employee is actually
basically working and functioning.
And then also been realizing that
there are requirements in the enterprise
that are really unique.
Like updates,
being able to control updates,
when they happen, when they don't,
and being able to recognize the fact that,
unlike the consumer space,
that enterprises have a different tempo
or different kind of speed
that they're actually iterating on.
So, just a personal example.
So, when we first went to
a remote work environment even at Box--
We have only 2,000 employees,
so it was easier for us
and a little bit smoother.
I remember when I needed to set up
my new iMac
to make sure that I had all the right
video setup and the right environment,
it took me, literally, maybe five minutes
from booting up a brand-new machine
to having access to every single
critical application in our business
and being able to work securely
with all the people that I needed.
And so, that ability to be able to work
seamlessly in the cloud on any device,
being able to work in any environment
and instantly boot up
the technology that you need
from a fresh start of a computer,
that's the power of what
consumerization of technology
is going to look like in the future.
So that's something
that we're really excited about.
And again,
as a personal user of these products,
I can see it firsthand of being able to go
from zero to your entire IT stack
in five minutes on a new device:
That's what the future of work is.
Mm-hmm. What can you be-- If you want to
give guidance, let's say, to an enterprise
that's out in the audience listening,
what kind of guidance can you give
on how they can better deal with
this rapidly-changing landscape?
Yeah, I think,
regardless of industry, again,
we're seeing this across
every single sector.
I think this is a catalyst
for digital transformation
that is going to accelerate projects
that maybe were
two or three or five, ten years out,
and that's going to start to happen.
Those projects are gonna be executed
in the coming months and quarters.
So, I personally think
this is one of the best times ever
to be in either information technology or
developer working on enterprise software,
because of the fact
that every single business
is going to have to rewrite
their underlying processes
and their experiences
for both employees and their customers.
And so if you think about
working backwards from--
Instead of looking at our business process
that got developed over the 20th century
and saying, "What could that look like
in the digital world?"
we have an opportunity now, from scratch,
to say in the 21st century,
"What should that experience look like?"
When you can really kind of work backwards
from what's the right way
to deliver education in the future,
what's the right way
to deliver health care in the future,
the right way
to be able to serve customers
if you're a bank and you want to
automate their onboarding process
and make sure
that they never have to send you paper
or do signatures in the future?
So, I think developers
are going to be at the center
of being able to transform
both the future of work,
and the future
of a lot of these enterprise experiences.
So, I think a couple things
that come to mind.
First is, think like a consumer.
When you're developing software
for the enterprise, think consumer first.
We are all consumers
in our personal lives,
and yet, somehow,
when we go to the office,
we sort of give up on thinking
that we have to deliver
consumer-grade experiences.
We sort of have this feeling that,
"Okay. Well, enterprise software
can be slow and complicated
because, oh, it's enterprise software."
Well, that makes no sense
in the 21st century.
We should have every single experience
in the enterprise
be able to match and keep up
with experiences that we have
in our personal lives.
That's the first thing.
The second thing is,
I think we have to be thinking about
a mobile-first and digital-first world.
When you think about
the kinds of products that you deploy,
when you think about the kind
of user experiences that get created,
we know that
these are going to be the ways
that people want to be able to work.
They want to be able
to load up their iPhone quickly,
be able to make sure
that they can use these applications
in a very, very seamless way.
I'm spending more time on my iPhone
in my work-from-home environment
than I am even on my computer
and it's because, in some of these cases,
it's just easier to be able to communicate
and chat and collaborate and get on video
and open up a document
when you're on an iPad or an iPhone.
And so we want to be able to make sure
that we're delivering amazing experiences.
I think the third thing is, really,
to be thinking about security, by design,
built into the products
that you're creating.
We know that the world is dealing
with a tremendous amount of challenge
around data security and cyber security
and data privacy,
so really making sure
that the software that we build
has security built into the core,
data privacy built into the core,
this is what's going to differentiate
all of our applications
that we create for enterprises,
and it's the only way
that we can realistically go
and serve at hospitals
and government agencies,
life sciences organizations,
banks, universities,
K-12 education and so much more.
So, think like a consumer
when you're building software,
make sure that security
is built in by design.
And again, I think we have
an opportunity to rebuild
much of the software
and the experiences for the 21st century.
And what have you found
as you focus on security and privacy,
how you leverage with
the Apple technology stack, let's say,
to enable that for your customers?
Yeah, I mean, first and foremost,
the underlying capabilities
that Apple devices are providing
our users and our developers
is obviously fundamental.
So, whether it's the encryption
that we have on an iOS device,
whether it's the security and safety
that's offered on a Mac device,
this is why we recommend these platforms
to our customers.
We're leveraging a lot of the native APIs
and core experiences
from a security standpoint,
and we're really excited about, again,
whether it's MDM technology
and so much more,
to be able to plug in to more and more
of these experiences over time.
What are the some of the challenges
that you're running into as you--
I mean, this vision that you paint,
I totally agree with,
in the enterprise,
of where the trends are going,
but what are the technical challenges
you said that you see on the horizon
that you would
challenge the audience to focus on,
or even ourselves here at Apple?
Well, I think we've got a lot of--
certainly a lot of legacy technology
that most enterprises are dealing with,
and any large business,
whether it's 5,000 employees
or 100,000 employees and more,
they're dealing with this duality of
there's so much innovation,
so many modern experiences
they want to go create,
and at the same time,
they've a lot of legacy infrastructure.
They've a lot of legacy processes.
So, our general view is starting with
some of the highest leverage parts
of the business.
The things that touch the end user,
the employee, the customer,
really start there,
and make sure that we're focusing
on those types of user experiences.
I think we have to build toward
a cloud-first architecture,
a digital-first experience,
oftentimes a mobile-first architecture
in terms of the software
that we're building,
and I would just challenge
every enterprise software developer,
every IT organization to think in terms
of those ways of delivering technology.
I think obviously, Apple has been
an incredible partner in this ecosystem.
Apple probably single-handedly
has done more
to modernize people's thinking
about enterprise software,
especially because of iOS devices
that caused the industry to say,
"Wait a second.
Why do we have to have bad technology
in our business environment?
Why can't we use MacBooks,
why can't we use iPhones,
why can't we use iPads?"
And that's caused
a different level of thinking
about the software that
we go out and build for our customers,
and I think it's been a huge boon.
There's a lot of things
I think we all need to be doing
around deeper interoperability,
better seamlessness of experiences
as more data moves to the cloud.
It behooves
all enterprise software developers
to create a level of interoperability
so customers can have choice,
so they can have integrated experiences.
I think there's going to be
some exciting, new--
On the forefront of security
that we're going to see,
especially what Apple is delivering,
but I think we have to make sure
that security is baked into
all of the technology that we use.
It used to be that
if you were a software developer,
you thought it was somebody else's job
to handle data security.
It was the device
or it was the network provider
or it was just
a security technology vendor.
That's not the case in the 21st century.
If you're developing software
for the enterprise,
security has to be baked
into every single thing that you do
and every single way that you handle data.
So I think there's going to be
a lot of change.
I think we're going to see more change
in the next couple of years
in the software ecosystem than
we have in the past couple of decades,
and that's because we know
that we're at the start
of another wave of digital change
happening in these industries.
In this mobile-first approach
that you're suggesting,
how do microservices
and continuous integration development
play into that
from a culture and a process perspective?
Fundamentally, I think you have to be
oriented toward microservices
because of the fact
that there's too many capabilities
that you need to be delivering
to your customers,
and so we have to be able to deliver
individual innovations
that get updated for our customers
on a continuous basis
because of how quickly
the world is changing.
And so, when we think about releases,
we don't think about releases
in quarters or years,
as you maybe would have
five or ten or 20 years ago
in traditional enterprise software.
We think about releases on a daily basis.
And we think about releases not only
when we're going to ship native code
that people are going to update
on their iOS devices,
but what cloud services
are we now implementing in the background
that's going to make our software
better, faster, simpler, easier,
more secure for our customers?
The only way to really do that
is if you have a modern architecture,
if you can run on top of microservices,
if you can separate out
the core components of your application,
if you can make sure you're doing
continuous development and integration.
All of those things are fundamental
to a modern way
of developing enterprise software.
Now, realizing there's a lot of sessions
at WWDC
around new frameworks
or updates to existing frameworks.
This conversation's a little different
'cause we're talking about the cloud
and the endpoints.
What are the other considerations
that developers need to have
for how to design those cloud services
that the devices are connecting into?
Yeah, I think
we're definitely in a new era
of the client server architecture, right?
What logic do you put in the cloud,
what logic do you have on the device,
how do you leverage and take advantage
of the native characteristics
of these devices,
so where is the moment where something
like Core ML starts to make sense,
to be able to have
device-level machine learning
and leverage the processing power
and the security and privacy power
of the device?
What things do you run in the cloud?
And we're always having
that sort of debate internally.
What belongs at the end user level,
whether that's a security reason
or performance reason
and what things do we want to make sure
that we're leveraging the cloud for?
We have a lot of services
where we'll even have in the browser
on a MacBook or any device,
we'll have the browser be doing processing
that maybe a couple of years ago
we would have done
as server-side processing,
but because we've seen such improvements
in HTML5 and modern technology,
we can go improve that.
Same thing on the iOS device, right?
So, what things can we do
local to that device
so we can improve the user experience,
make something snappier, make it faster,
cache it in a more efficient way?
And I think, again,
it behooves all software developers
to get clear on that architecture,
because it's not a given that the way
you would've done something ten years ago
when the devices were slower,
maybe they didn't have
as much compute capacity,
maybe we didn't have Core ML.
You don't want to be designing things
in the same way you would have
maybe ten years ago
today, when there's all-new services
that you can be leveraging.
I think taking a step back,
taking inventory
of what's possible now in 2020,
and how we should be building software
is a really big opportunity
for, I think, all developers.
And then bringing that full circle
to the trend towards working from home,
being forced,
and then probably having a world where
we have this hybrid, as you point out.
What are the areas that you feel like
are not being met?
So, I think there's a huge opportunity
for developers right now to say
what is work going to look like
in the future
when, on a moment's notice,
you might want to pull up any device,
you might be in any location,
you might be on any network,
and you want to be able
to collaborate in real time
with anybody in your business?
I think there's going to be
a wave of innovation
that reimagines the combination
of synchronous work and asynchronous work
the way that--
How do you start to approximate
some of the ways
that we used to maybe work in an office,
but do that virtually?
How do you start to hop on a video call
within, literally, a couple seconds
without having to schedule
the full meeting?
How do you collaborate in real time
on documents
and be able to leverage new ways
of sharing information
across just a plethora
of devices and networks?
So I think this is going to be
an amazing opportunity right now
for software developers
both in large enterprises
as well as start-ups
to start to think about
the new characteristics of work,
the ways that we can deliver
a modern digital workplace,
to be able to get people on the same page,
whether that's on video
or whether that's in documents
or whether that's in chat
or whether that's in other ways
of sharing knowledge,
and there's going to be all-new companies
that we look back on five years from now
that will be the next era
of Slacks and Zooms of the world
that get created
because of this new way of working
and it's going to be incredibly exciting
to see what emerges
in the coming quarters and years.
Yeah, I know.
It's a really remarkable time,
this convergence of home and work.
Truly. It's blended now.
And there's gonna be a whole new set
of experience and applications
and services that emerge from that.
We definitely share a similar vision.
Well, Aaron, thank you so much
for your time today
and hopefully
you all enjoyed this discussion
around creating great enterprise
applications with Apple technology.
-Thanks, Mike.
-Thanks.