Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hey there. My name is Rachel,
I'm a designer from Apple Maps,
and I want to talk to you
about location privacy.
Today people share precise location data,
like this,
with many of the apps that they use.
In iOS 14, Core Location gives people
new control over their data
by allowing them to share
their approximate location instead.
This is a massive change.
And it blew our minds.
After all, our team designed Apple Maps
entirely around precise location.
It's the focal point of the map,
it's used throughout the app
to find the most relevant search results
and calculate arrival times and distances,
and our navigation features depend on it.
Location data is used everywhere,
and apps of all kinds will be impacted
by this change.
Just here at Apple,
Weather uses location data
to provide live, nearby forecasts.
Wallet uses location data
to match transactions to places.
And Photos uses location data
to tag photos and create Memories.
When our design team first heard
about approximate location,
it was really hard for us to imagine
how Apple Maps could work
without precise location data.
For those of you who are feeling similarly
about your app right now,
we want to share how we adapted Apple Maps
to support approximate location,
and in doing so improved on our approach
to respecting people's data and privacy.
We hope that our experience
might inform your work,
no matter what kind of app you design.
If this is the first you're hearing
about approximate location,
consider checking out these two talks,
"Building Trust Through Better Privacy,"
and "What's New in Location,"
before continuing on.
Three principles guided our team
as we designed Apple Maps
for location privacy.
First, when designing for location
privacy, prioritize user control.
Give everyone control
over the location data that they share
and respect their preferences.
Our design team made several changes
in Apple Maps
to ensure that the app works well
for people
no matter what kind
of location data they share.
The biggest change, and challenge,
was annotating approximate location
on the map.
A pulsing blue dot
represents precise location today.
It is a very strong visual in our app
and acts as a primary
organizational element.
We needed a different annotation
to represent approximate data accurately,
and to do so
without impeding map functionality.
So we designed a shaded, circular area
to indicate approximate location.
This new element both shares
in the visual language of the blue dot,
and adapts in styling to interaction,
so as people zoom in, the overlay fades,
to maintain cartographic legibility.
The design team also audited the app
to identify where else we use
precise location data,
such as to calculate arrival times
and distances,
like here in Favorites.
Calculating this data is not feasible
with approximate location,
and removing it from the user experience
does not drastically impact functionality.
We made small adjustments like this
to Search and place details as well.
So, to prioritize user control
in your app,
don't require precise data
to use your product.
Allow people to do as much as possible
while sharing approximate location.
And for those people
sharing approximate location,
remove nonessential UI
that requires precise data.
Second, when designing
for location privacy,
build trust through transparency.
We all want to use data responsibly
and to create great user experiences.
Communicate clearly with people
about what data your app uses
and how that data is used.
In Maps, we invest in writing.
Clear language,
especially at important decision points,
like here on first app launch,
explains what data our app asks for
and what value it provides.
Clarity and accuracy will ensure
that people have the right knowledge
to make decisions
about their location data.
Next, communicate to people
the result of their choices.
For people who choose to share
approximate location with Apple Maps,
we added a status bar and control
at the top of the map.
When people first launch Maps,
that status appears larger
and stronger in visual treatment.
This reminds them of past decisions
and gives them direct access
to control of the setting.
Once people show interest
and interact elsewhere in the app,
the visual treatment
reduces in prominence.
This way, people still get the benefit
of persistent transparency and control,
without distracting
from other functionality.
So, to build trust through transparency
in your app,
use clear writing to explain data usage
and its value proposition.
Remind people
of what data they are sharing.
They may be sharing location data
with multiple apps.
And make your app flexible
so that people can change their experience
as their needs change.
Finally, when designing
for location privacy,
offer proportional value
in exchange for the data shared.
Some features will absolutely require
precise location data,
and that's okay.
Limit requests for precise data
to specific features that require it
and connect your request
to value in the user experience.
In Apple Maps, turn-by-turn directions
require precise location.
So when people indicate
they want directions,
we ask for one-time access
to precise location.
And we try to ask people as close
to giving them directions as possible.
For Apple Maps, this means that
people sharing approximate location
will still see
all the same directions buttons,
like this one in place details.
When someone taps Directions
they will be able to manually input
their places of origin and destination.
Since Maps needs precise location
to auto-populate the place of origin,
we add in a new option,
called My Location,
to the suggested places.
This gives people the option to create
a route from their precise location.
When someone chooses My Location,
then we ask for their precise data.
This request is connected
to people taking action,
in this case, asking for directions,
and is positioned close to when
they will receive those directions,
making clear the use and value of sharing
precise location in this scenario.
So in order to offer
proportional value in your app,
only request precise location
when the functionality requires it.
Make your request in response
to related action people take in your app,
and position this request
close to the functionality it powers.
Our team found that designing
for location privacy is very important
and very possible.
Just remember to prioritize user control,
build trust through transparency,
and offer proportional value.
With this guidance,
we were able to support
approximate location in Apple Maps
in a way that respected everyone's choices
about data sharing
and maintained an elegant experience.
We hope these principles
might come in handy
as you develop support
for approximate location in your apps.
Thanks for your time, and enjoy WWDC.