Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to "Add Configuration
and Intelligence to Your Widgets."
My name is Ian,
and I'm here with my colleague Kelvin.
In this talk, we'll show you
how to make widgets configurable,
and show you how a configurable widget
can help the system work
in more intelligent ways.
New in iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
we have a whole new widget experience.
Widgets allow your app
to surface new information to people
in exciting new ways.
Widgets can live in more places than ever.
They can live on pages of the Home Screen,
as part of Stacks,
on the Today View,
and in macOS Notification Center.
Powering those widgets is WidgetKit.
WidgetKit allows you
to create multiple widgets,
each to solve its own unique problem.
Each widget can support
different sizes and layouts.
Let's take a look at an example.
We've built an example app
that lets you view all of the transactions
on your credit cards.
It lets you view information
about your spending
and track balances
on all of your accounts.
The two most common things
that I do in the app
are check balances
and look at recent transactions.
It would be really great to see
this information right at a glance
on the Home Screen,
so we built two widgets for our app.
The first one
is called "Recent Purchases,"
which shows a list of purchases
on one of your cards.
The other one is called "Due Date,"
which shows your next payment's due date
and how much you owe.
Because I often want to see information
about one card at a time,
we added configuration
to pick which card to show.
I can change which card is shown
by tapping on "Edit Widget"
and then selecting a card.
Because we made our widget configurable,
now people can create multiple
different instances of the Due Date widget
and show a different card in each.
Now let's look at
what we're going to cover today.
First, we'll talk about the basics of how
to add configuration to your widget.
Next, we'll talk about
the types of information
that you can ask the user to enter,
and show how to populate the interface
with data from your app.
After that, we'll talk about how
you can customize the title, description
and colors of the backside of your widget.
And finally, we'll cover how
adding configuration to your widget
allows the system to better predict times
to display your widget in a stack.
Let's start with the basics.
The first piece of the system is
the widget extension.
Widget extensions contain SwiftUI code
that renders the visual appearance
of the widget.
They also contain some metadata
about the widget itself.
Before you get started,
make sure that you have set up
a widget extension already
using WidgetKit and SwiftUI.
If you haven't done that yet,
make sure to go watch
the "Meet WidgetKit" talk.
When your widget is configurable,
you can specify which options to ask
the user on the backside of the widget,
and the system will display them for you.
These questions are called parameters.
Here's our Recent Purchases widget.
It has a "Card" parameter
and a "Category" parameter.
The Card parameter allows people
to choose a card to display,
and the Category parameter
lets people filter the list
to only include transactions
for a specific category,
like groceries, if they'd like.
To define which parameters are shown,
we use intents,
which is the same system that you can use
to add support
for Siri and Shortcuts to your app.
An intent contains
an ordered list of parameters.
Each parameter that you put on the intent
will show up as a row
in the widget's configuration UI.
You declare your intents in Xcode
using an Intent Definition File.
This file contains all of your intents,
their parameters,
and indicates which parts
of the system they support.
By compiling this file into your app,
the system will be able
to read information about your intents.
Once you define an intent,
Xcode will also generate
an intent class for you,
containing a property for each parameter.
For this widget, we have
a ViewRecentPurchasesIntent class,
with Card and Category properties.
An instance of this intent class
will be passed into the widget extension
at runtime,
allowing your widget to know
what the user has configured
and what to display.
Next, let's talk about
the types of parameters
that you can add to your intent.
As I mentioned before,
we build the widget configuration UI
for you,
based on the intent's definition.
We support a wide variety of input types,
which I'll walk you through now.
When you specify "String"
as the type of your parameter,
the configuration UI shows a text field,
and it will show a switch
for the "Boolean" parameter.
The configuration UI also supports numbers
with a few different input mechanisms.
For integers,
it supports number fields and steppers,
and for decimals,
it supports number fields and sliders.
The configuration UI also has support
for contact and location pickers.
The "Person" type will show
as a contact picker,
and the "Location" type will show
as a location picker.
The configuration UI
also supports enumerations.
You can make these enumerations static,
or dynamically populate them
with content from your app.
We'll talk about dynamic options
in more detail later.
The configuration UI supports
a number of other types as well,
each with their own UI.
Parameters can also support
multiple values.
For example, if your widget shows
a list of events from your calendars,
you can configure the intent
to support selecting multiple calendars.
New in iOS 14,
Intents now supports fixed-size arrays.
This is useful if your widget
supports showing a fixed number of items,
and lets you prevent the user from adding
more than a defined number of items
into the array.
You can specify the number of items
based on the widget size
in the intent editor.
Now I'm going to walk you through
how to add rich configuration
to your widget.
The first step is identifying
what you want to make configurable.
Let's use the Recent Purchases widget here
as an example.
In the Recent Purchases widget,
each widget can only show one card,
but people may have multiple cards
in the app,
so it would make sense
to make that configurable.
This allows people
to have multiple Recent Purchases widgets
on their Home Screen,
each showing different cards.
It also would be useful
to be able to filter by category.
That way, people could have one widget
to show transportation expenses
and another widget to show food expenses.
So, in addition to making
the card configurable,
we are also going to allow people
to configure the category.
Now I'm going to walk you through
how we can make
the Recent Purchases widget configurable.
This is our project,
where we already have our widget set up.
You can see that the widget currently has
a StaticConfiguration.
In order to make the widget configurable,
we need to switch
from a StaticConfiguration
to an IntentConfiguration.
The first step in switching to
an IntentConfiguration
is defining an intent that
you'll use to configure the widget.
You can define a custom intent
inside of an Intent Definition File.
I already have one here in this project.
You'll note that it is checked in
to both the app
and the widget extension targets.
Now let's create an intent using
the plus button in the bottom left.
I'll be calling it ViewRecentPurchases.
Next we're going to check the
"Intent is eligible for widgets" option.
This will allow the intent to work
as a configuration for a widget.
If you want this intent
to also support the Shortcuts app,
check the "Intent is user-configurable in
the Shortcuts app and Add to Siri" option.
We'll uncheck this option for this demo
and just focus on widgets.
We're also going to leave the
"Intent is eligible for Siri Suggestions"
checkbox unchecked for now,
and my colleague Kelvin
will walk you through
how to add intelligence to your widget
later in this talk.
We'll also set the category
of this intent to "View"
because the purpose is
to view your transactions.
Now, using the plus button
in the parameters list,
I am going to add a parameter
for the card.
The first step here
is naming the parameter.
This label will be displayed
in the widget configuration UI.
I'm going to name this "Card."
Next, I need to pick a type.
Because a credit card represents
an object inside of my app,
I'm going to create a custom type
to represent it.
You'll see that I already created
a "Card" type,
which has a name and identifier,
so I'll use that here for my type.
The list of cards
will need to be provided by the app,
and will change depending on
who is signed in,
so I will check
the "Options are provided dynamically"
checkbox.
We'll go into detail later
on how to populate this dynamic list.
Since this intent
won't support running in Siri,
we can uncheck the
"Siri can ask for value when run" option
Next, because we want to allow people
to choose the category,
we'll add a "Category" parameter
to the intent.
We can use an enum
for the type of this parameter
because there are
a fixed set of categories.
I already have an enum defined,
so I will choose that.
We'll set the default value
for the category to "All"
so that people will see
all of the transactions by default.
And we'll also uncheck the
"Siri can ask for value when run" option
for the category.
Now let's talk about dynamic options
and search.
In many cases,
the data that you want to display
in the widget configuration
can vary by person,
and can't be specified up front
in the Intent Definition File.
For example, the list of cards
in our example app varies by person.
You can accomplish this
by implementing dynamic options.
You can enable dynamic options
for any parameter on an intent
by checking the "Dynamic Options" checkbox
in Xcode.
Enabling dynamic options
will indicate to the system
that it should consult your app
to retrieve the possible values
that a person can choose from,
instead of allowing them
to enter any value that they want.
Once you enable dynamic options,
two things will happen.
First, the visual appearance
of your parameter will change
on the backside of the widget
into a button
that opens a modal list of options.
Second, two methods will be generated
for you to implement in your app,
one to provide a list of possible options,
and a default value.
These methods are part
of the intent handler protocol,
which Xcode generates for you.
You will need to make a class
that conforms to this protocol,
either in your app
or in an Intents extension.
This class will be asked by the system
to provide possible options
while the person is configuring
your widget.
In the example app, the two methods
that we need to implement
are provideCardOptionsCollection
and defaultCard.
For provideCardOptionsCollection,
we will load the list of cards
that the user has set up
and then call the completion handler.
For defaultCard,
we return the primary card
that the user has set up.
The provideCardOptionsCollection method
lets you either provide
a flat list of cards
or a list of sections containing cards.
For example, we can display a section
for each type of card,
like credit or debit.
If you use sections,
your UI will look like this.
Now all of my credit cards
show under the "Credit" section,
and I can see more sections
containing other types of cards.
By default, the search bar at the top
will filter the options that you provide.
In some cases,
your app might have more data
than you can easily provide
up-front in a list.
If that's the case, you can provide
search results as the person types.
These results can include options
outside of the standard options
that you provide dynamically.
To do this, make sure to check
the "Intent handler provides
search results as the user types" checkbox
and also provide a prompt.
If you check the checkbox,
the provideCardOptionsCollection method
will get a search term parameter.
When a person first looks at the list,
this method will get called
with a nil search term,
and then as they start typing,
the method will get called again
with the updated search term.
Now let's do a quick demo
of how you can implement dynamic options.
Continuing from our last demo,
let's go ahead and implement returning
the list of cards to the user dynamically.
The first step is setting up
the intent handler
for the ViewRecentPurchases intent.
We're going to put our intent handler
inside of an Intents extension.
I already have an Intents extension set up
for our other widget,
so I can add my code there.
The next step is making
our intent handler conform
to the ViewRecentPurchases
intent handling protocol.
You can see that this protocol has
a single required method,
which is the
provideCardOptionsCollection method.
We need to implement this such that it
returns a list of cards inside of the app.
First, I create custom Card objects
from the objects inside of my app.
Then I put them into
the INObjectCollection,
which allows me to add sections if I want.
I don't have any sections in mind here,
so I will just create the collection
from a list of items,
and then call the completion handler
with the created collection.
There's also an optional method
to provide a default card.
The default is used
when a widget is dragged
onto the Home Screen for the first time,
so it's really important
to provide a good default.
Now that we've created our intent
and implemented our intent handler,
we can adopt the IntentConfiguration
in our widget.
It's very similar to
the StaticConfiguration
that we had before,
but it takes an intent type
as an argument.
You'll also need to switch
your TimelineProvider
to be an IntentTimelineProvider.
It's very similar to
the default TimelineProvider,
but the methods have
an additional intent argument
that you use to determine what to show.
Here, we’ll need to take the card
from the intent
and use that to determine
which purchases to show.
Previously, it was just showing
the purchases from the default card.
Let's run the code
and try to configure the widget.
Notice that when I drag out the widget,
it shows me transactions
from the default card.
This is because I implemented
the default card method.
Now if I go and flip it around
and tap on the "Card" button,
it shows me a list of cards.
Tapping on the "Category" option
also shows a list of categories.
Voilà.
Now let's talk about a few ways
that you can further customize
the appearance
of your widget configuration UI.
You can customize the title
and the description
by using the SwiftUI modifiers called
"configurationDisplayName"
and "description"
in your widget extension.
Next is colors.
You can style the background
and the accent color
of the widget configuration UI
to match your app's color scheme.
To do this,
you'll need to add named colors
to your widget extension's asset catalog.
Here we're adding one for the accent color
and another one for the background color.
And then you'll need to add
the names of your colors
to your widget extension's build settings
for "Global Accent Color Name"
and "Widget Background Color Name."
Another thing you might want to do
is hide and show specific parameters
based on another parameter.
For example, in the Calendar widget,
if you turn off
the "Mirror Calendar App" switch,
the "Calendar" parameter appears,
and you can manually choose
which calendar to show.
Let's take a look at
the Intent Definition File
to see how to specify the relationship
between Mirror Calendar App and Calendar.
To specify that we only want
the "Calendar" parameter to show up
when the "Mirror Calendar App" option
is off,
make the "Mirror Calendar App" parameter
a parent of the "Calendar" parameter.
To do that,
we'll select the "Calendar" parameter,
then select "Mirror Calendar App"
as its parent.
Then we'll set it up to show only if
the parent has the exact value of "false".
Now the "Calendar" parameter
will only show up
if the "Mirror Calendar App"
is turned off.
That's it from me.
Now over to Kelvin to talk about
system intelligence and widgets.
Hi, I'm Kelvin, and I work on
the Proactive team here at Apple.
Next, we're going to talk about
system intelligence.
Widgets are one of the most exciting
new opportunities
across iOS, iPadOS and macOS.
On iOS 14, not only can you add widgets
to the Home Screen,
you can stack multiple widgets together
and provide access to a variety of widgets
in one place by easily swiping through.
Everyone will find a different way
to take advantage of this,
but it's easy to imagine that
you could group multiple widgets together
that would be useful
as you progress through your day.
Now, what's exciting about Stacks
is that the system can automatically
rotate widgets to the top of the stack
to provide useful and timely information.
Let me walk you through
the underlying design principles
that drive stack intelligence,
and how you should implement some new APIs
to ensure your app is part of
this new Home Screen experience.
Let's dig a little deeper into what makes
for a good Smart Stack.
Stacks should provide timely
and glanceable information
with obvious value to the user.
You want your widget to be surfaced
when you have timely information
relevant to the people using your app,
like when you know
there is a thunderstorm coming,
but not when you're just updating
the temperature regularly.
Broadly speaking, the system will try
to surface widgets based on two reasons.
The first is user behavior-based.
We want to surface widgets
that provide information
the user typically looks for
at a particular time.
For example,
if someone frequently launches
your weather app to check on the weather,
the system can instead surface your widget
with that information
to provide quicker access
to what they're looking for.
The second is based on
relevant information from your app.
So, for example,
if a thunderstorm is happening,
your widget can inform the system
that it has a highly relevant update,
and the system will consider surfacing
your widget to the top of the stack.
Now let's talk about the APIs you can use
to provide the information
the system needs to surface your widget.
Let's start with user behavior.
So the system wants to surface your widget
when someone is typically looking
in your app for information,
and in iOS 12, we introduced the concept
of Shortcuts and custom intent donations,
which provides a way for the system
to understand what people do in your app.
And using this information,
the system provides predictions
in Spotlight
on what actions they want to perform.
Now, new in iOS 14,
these same donations
will also inform the system
about when would be a good time
to surface your widget.
So now, let's continue
from our previous example
with the Recent Purchases widget.
Here we have already set up an intent
for widget configuration.
It allows a user to specify
the credit card
and the category they want to view.
Now, to enable system intelligence
to rotate to our widget,
we have to set this same intent
for donation by our host app.
The idea here
is we want to inform the system
when a user is checking
a particular credit card in our app,
and we will do so by donating this intent.
We'll describe what happens
under the hood in just a bit.
So for now, let's dive into some details
about how to set it up.
First, we need to mark this intent
as eligible for Siri Suggestions,
and that opens up the bottom section
here labeled "Suggestions."
And for our example,
we want the system to predict
when someone will check
a particular credit card,
and we want it to match any widget
with that same card configured.
In order to convey that,
we need to add a "Supported Combinations"
with just the Card parameter.
And so now that we have set up
our custom ViewRecentPurchases intent,
we need to have our host app donate it
whenever the user views recent purchases
in our host app.
And to do that,
we create an INInteraction object
and call the donate function,
passing in our intent.
And since we've specified
a "Supported Combinations"
as just the Card parameter,
even if we provided the Category parameter
in our donation,
the system will only consider
the Card parameter.
And that's all you have to do.
The system will do the rest.
Now let's take a closer look
at what the system does
with your donations under the hood.
So let's say someone views
grocery purchases
for our AcmeCard regularly at noon,
and checks their SoupPay card
for restaurant purchases in the evenings.
Now, our host app
would donate intents like this.
And based on these donations,
the system would recognize that the user
typically checks their AcmeCard at noon.
And then on Friday at noon,
the system would predict the intent
for viewing AcmeCard
and would surface our widget,
as long as they have configured it
to show their AcmeCard
regardless of the category.
But what if instead we added both Card
and Category as a supported combination?
Let's look at what would happen.
Now, since Category is part
of the supported combination,
you are telling the system
that it is an important parameter.
Then on Friday at noon,
the system would predict the intent
for viewing AcmeCard
in the "Groceries" category,
which would only surface widgets
where the user has explicitly configured
both parameters
to show the AcmeCard
for the "Groceries" category.
So, in short, "Supported Combinations"
is the way to communicate to the system
which configurable parameter
truly represents
the information people are looking for.
We walked through a lot of steps there,
so to quickly summarize,
first, set up a configuration
for your widget with an intent.
Second, mark it as eligible
for Siri Suggestions
to allow the system to predict it.
Next, configure "Supported Combinations"
for only the parameters
that you want the system to predict.
And finally, donate the intent
when the user views that information
in your host app.
Now let's talk about the second scenario,
where you want the system
to surface your widget
when you have important,
relevant information.
So, a quick recap.
Using WidgetKit,
you provide timeline entries
that will determine what your widget
will look like at various points in time.
It works great whether your widget
can schedule your entries ahead of time,
like this weather example
where you can provide forecasts
for future views.
It also works if your widget needs
to react to new information in real time,
like our Recent Purchases example,
where you can only provide
each entry as they occur.
So now, let's say we know that people
using our app want to be alerted
if they got a charge for over $50.
How can you inform the system
that your widget has relevant information
for the Acme Books purchase?
You can convey that information
by supplying
a TimelineEntryRelevance object
with your TimelineEntry.
A TimelineEntry has effectively
three components:
a date time stamp that determines
when this entry should be rendered,
the view that should be rendered,
and the relevance of this entry.
The relevance is
a TimelineEntryRelevance object,
which has two fields:
a score and a duration.
And here's what it looks like in Swift.
Let's start with the score.
The score is a value indicating
how relevant an entry is
compared to all entries
provided in the past.
The range and scale
is largely up to you to define,
as the system only considers the score
in relation to other entries.
The only exception being a score of zero
or lower will indicate to the system
that your widget currently has
no relevant information
and should not be surfaced.
Now, coming back to our example,
we want to convey to the system
that we have important information
when there is a purchase of more than $50.
We can simply provide a score of one
when that happens
to emphasize the importance,
and a score of 0.1
for all other purchases.
That way, there will be a slight chance
the system might surface our widget
for the minor purchases,
but will try to prioritize
for the big purchase.
When there is no important information,
like when we have
no recent purchases at 8:04 a.m.,
we set a score of zero.
And keep in mind, it doesn't matter
what scores other widgets provide.
Scores are only compared
within the scores you provide.
Now, on the other hand,
let's say we think the amount spent
is a good indicator of relevance.
We can set the amount spent
to be the score,
and the system will likewise prioritize
surfacing the expensive purchases.
Next, let's talk about duration.
The duration is a field for situations
where you have
a well-defined period of time
where the relevance score will be fixed.
Otherwise,
feel free to leave duration as zero,
which will mean
the relevance score will last
until the next TimelineEntryRelevance
is received.
Here's an example
to highlight how duration can be used.
We want to build a basketball widget
that shows the progress of a game
as it occurs.
So, at the beginning of the game,
we can create an entry with a score of one
and a fixed duration
for the length of the game.
During the game, we can continue
to make TimelineEntry updates
without affecting the relevance
by just leaving
the TimelineEntryRelevance field as nil.
Setting the entry as nil
is how you can tell the system
to ignore this update
for relevance purposes.
So to wrap up, with Smart Stacks,
we have an opportunity to surface
your widget on top of a stack.
You can make this work
for your widgets in two ways.
First, by donating intents from your app
that match configuration of your widget,
and secondly,
by providing TimelineEntryRelevance
when your widget has
important information.
Thanks for watching.
We can't wait to see what kind
of configurable, intelligent widgets
you will build.