Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. I'm Udayan Kale.
I'm on the Game Center engineering team.
In this session, we will be talking about
all the new features
in Game Center Leaderboards, Achievements,
and Multiplayer.
So let's talk about
Game Center Leaderboards.
I will do a quick recap
of Game Center Leaderboards
and then show you
everything that's new this year.
Leaderboards have always been
an integral part of Game Center.
A leaderboard is driven by scores
and ranks players based on these scores.
Players can view
their friend and global ranks
and challenge other players
to beat their scores.
You can share leaderboards
across versions of your games
on iOS, tvOS and macOS.
Game Center provides a lot of choices
when it comes to configuring leaderboards
and setting the score formats,
scoring types and sort orders.
Game Center leaderboards have always been
the traditional non-expiring type.
They maintain
player scores and rankings forever.
We now refer to these leaderboards
as classic leaderboards.
Here are a few examples.
A game wants to keep track
of the overall total number
of experience points earned by players,
or the most coins that were collected,
or the shortest time taken
to complete a game level.
These are all good use cases
for classic leaderboards.
So what's new this year?
We now have a new type of leaderboard
called recurring leaderboards.
We have also completely redesigned
the in-game UI,
and we have a new set of APIs to access
leaderboard data and submit scores.
I will cover the new UI and APIs later.
For now,
let's look at recurring leaderboards.
Recurring leaderboards
are short-lived leaderboards
that repeat on a periodic basis.
These leaderboards will be great
if your game wants to support
periodic timed events.
Here are some good use cases.
You want your game to run
a 15-minute competition every hour,
or you want to host
a one-hour challenge every Sunday at noon,
or you just want to run
a new leaderboard each week.
Recurring leaderboards will give
your players a fresh start every time
to compete for top spots.
Here is a deeper look at how
Game Center recurring leaderboards work.
A recurring leaderboard is a sequence
of individual timed leaderboards
that start and end on a periodic basis.
We call each of these
individual leaderboards an occurrence.
These occurrences are short-lived
and do not overlap.
Each new occurrence begins
only after the current one ends.
You configure a recurring leaderboard
using a set of parameters
in App Store Connect.
Initial start date defines
when your leaderboard
will start creating occurrences.
Frequency specifies
the rate at which occurrences repeat,
and Duration specifies
the time during which
scores can be submitted
to an active occurrence.
You can introduce a time delay
between occurrences
using different values
for Frequency and Duration.
Each occurrence also maintains information
about the start date
of the next occurrence,
so you know exactly
when the next one begins.
You can access each occurrence through
an instance of the GKLeaderboard class.
So let me show you how to configure
the examples I mentioned earlier.
In the first example, you have
a 15-minute competition every hour
at the top of the hour.
You configure this leaderboard
with a desired initial start date,
a 60-minute frequency,
and a 15-minute duration.
The second example describes
a one-hour contest every Sunday at noon.
You set the start date,
a frequency of seven days,
and a duration of 60 minutes.
The third example shows
a recurring leaderboard that runs daily
with no gaps between occurrences.
And to ensure
that occurrences do not overlap,
the duration must not be greater
than the frequency.
Now that you know
how recurring leaderboards are configured,
let's talk about
incorporating leaderboards in your game.
The whole purpose
of adding leaderboards to your game
is to capture scores earned by players
and display these scores
so players can see their rankings.
I will now show you
how to submit scores to leaderboards.
Submitting scores
to a classic leaderboard is easy
because a classic leaderboard never ends.
You just call the submitScore method,
passing in a score, a context, player,
and one or more leaderboard IDs.
Context is an optional value
that you can associate with the score.
The leaderboard will retain either
the best score or the most recent score.
For recurring leaderboards,
scores can only be submitted
to the currently active occurrence.
You have two ways to submit scores
to a recurring leaderboard.
The first is to use the same method
we used for classic leaderboards.
The score will be posted
to the currently active occurrence
if one exists at the time of submission.
The second option is to use
a method on the GKLeaderboard instance
that corresponds to an occurrence.
As long as that occurrence is active,
score submissions will succeed.
You can query the startDate
and duration properties of GKLeaderboard
to determine if the occurrence is active.
Game Center defers forwarding scores
to the server if the device is off-line.
The server validates a score
based on the time it's received,
not when it was earned by the player.
So it is possible that an active
leaderboard occurrence may have expired
when the score reaches the server.
Next, let's talk about
displaying leaderboards in your game.
You have two options when it comes to
showing leaderboards within your game:
using GameKit's new in-game UI
or displaying your own custom UI.
We strongly recommend
using GameKit's in-game UI,
as it's very easy to adopt and does
most of the heavy lifting for you.
For this, you will use
the GKGameCenterViewController class
that you may already be familiar with.
In the previous session, I showed you
how to invoke the Game Center Dashboard.
I'll now show you how to directly display
a list of leaderboards within your game.
You can see here I initialized
the GKGameCenterViewController
specifying the "leaderboards" state.
This gives you a list of leaderboards
that you see here on the right.
At this point, the user can navigate
to a particular leaderboard
that they are interested in and select it.
That will display the scores
for that leaderboard.
On the scores view, players can see
how they rank against friends,
recently played, and global players.
They can use the filter in the header area
to change the time scope
for classic leaderboards
or the occurrence
for recurring leaderboards.
They can scroll to the top of the list
by tapping on the name in the header.
You can even deep-link to a specific
leaderboard to directly display scores.
So here I have initialized GKGameCenter
ViewController with a leaderboard ID,
a player scope, and a time scope,
and you get the scores view
that you see on the right.
So you see, adopting Game Center's
in-game UI is that easy.
But if you want to draw your own UI,
you have to load the leaderboards
and scores programmatically.
We have introduced new APIs
to work with leaderboards and scores,
and you can read about them
in the developer docs.
Recurring leaderboards need special
handling when dealing with occurrences.
When you load a recurring leaderboard,
only the current occurrence is loaded.
You can use this current occurrence
to load a previous one
by calling the method
loadPreviousOccurrence, as shown here.
Here are some considerations to keep
in mind when loading previous occurrences.
Game Center keeps
expired occurrences around
for up to 30 days from their expiry.
However,
a signed-in player can view scores
only on the current occurrence
and one previous occurrence.
The previous occurrence is usually
the most recent expired occurrence
in which the player submitted a score.
In the example shown here,
Player 1 can view their scores
on the current occurrence, 53,
and the previous occurrence, 50.
If a player never submitted a score
to an occurrence,
or if that occurrence was purged,
then the immediate previous occurrence
is accessible.
So in the case of Player 2,
they can view occurrences 53 and 52.
If no occurrence is currently active,
the most recent occurrence is still
considered current for accessing scores.
Next, let's talk about setting up
the leaderboards in App Store Connect.
This screen shows the leaderboards
for a typical game in App Store Connect.
Most of the setup involving leaderboards,
sets, and groups is the same as before
and is common to both classic
and recurring leaderboards.
I will now show you
the additional configuration
you will need for recurring leaderboards.
To add a new leaderboard, just click
the "plus" icon next to the section title.
On the pop-up that shows, choose the type
of leaderboard you wish to create.
Your game can have
just classic leaderboards
or just recurring leaderboards
or a combination of both.
Once you select the type of leaderboard,
you'll need to configure it.
For classic and recurring leaderboards,
you must populate the section at the top.
This is the same as you do today.
The section at the bottom is
only available for recurring leaderboards.
The Start Date and Time specifies
when your leaderboard
will start creating occurrences.
The Duration is the time interval
during which
scores can be submitted to an occurrence.
And Restart specifies how frequently
new occurrences will be created.
The Duration and Restart period are
both specified in minutes, hours or days.
The restart period must be equal to
or larger than the duration
so occurrences do not overlap.
Once you have configured a leaderboard,
you must localize it.
Both classic and recurring leaderboards
have the same options
when adding languages.
We strongly recommend that you upload
an image for your leaderboard
that reflects some aspect of your game.
This image is prominently displayed
in the in-game UI.
So that's it
for Game Center Leaderboards this year.
We cannot wait to see games adopting these
new features in various creative ways.
Next up is Achievements,
and for that, let me welcome Dersu.
Thank you.
Thank you, Udayan.
Let's talk about Achievements
in Game Center.
So, what is an achievement?
An achievement is a collectible item
indicating the player has successfully
reached a particular goal in your game.
Achievements have been a fundamental part
of Game Center since its inception,
as they provide players an additional way
of engaging with the game,
tracking gameplay progress,
and sharing that progress with friends.
Players will notice a fresh, new
and consistent look to achievement badges.
As the developer,
you define the achievements available
for players to work towards.
An achievement will appear to players
in one of four forms:
locked, in-progress, completed, or hidden.
Before the player has made any progress
toward an achievement,
it will appear locked.
Some players will often scan
the achievements list
and browse locked achievements
as a guide for what they should do
in your game.
In this sense, your achievements list
gives you an opportunity to tell users
what to think about
while playing your game.
After you start reporting progress
for a user toward some achievement,
it will display as in-progress.
Once you report 100% progress
for that achievement,
it is considered complete.
At this point, the user will see
the image tied to the achievement,
and it will show up
in their list of completed achievements.
Last, you can explicitly mark
an achievement as hidden
until the player has completed it.
You might do this if you feel
the achievement description itself
prematurely reveals
aspects of the game's story or plot.
Alternatively, consider
using hidden achievements to surprise,
delight or humor the player.
For example,
you might include a hidden achievement
that rewards the player
for failing spectacularly.
This year, we're bringing Achievements
to more places,
including the Game Center Dashboard
on iOS, macOS, and tvOS.
The Dashboard is a brand-new area
for players to view
Game Center-related information
for your game.
It's accessible straight from your game,
and it showcases your game's achievements,
personalized
according to the player's progress.
This means
it's as important as ever to make sure
your achievements are engaging,
accessible, and interesting for players.
For some useful tips and best practices
for building achievements,
we recommend you check out this year's
session "Design for Game Center."
Before finalizing
your achievements design,
it's important to keep in mind
that there are limits
to how many you can include in your game.
Your game can have a maximum
of 100 achievements,
each of which can award up to 100 points.
And overall,
your game can award up to 1,000 points.
You'll want to make sure
you make the most of this budget,
creating a set of achievements
that require
a range of skills and dedication
to complete.
Finally,
you should keep these limits in mind
when shipping
the initial version of your game,
as you may want to create
new achievements for future updates.
After you've designed some achievements,
you're probably ready
to start integrating them into your game.
And there are three simple steps
needed to do this.
First, you'll need to authenticate
the local player.
Without first authenticating,
any API calls you make to GameKit
will result in an error.
For more on using the local player,
refer to session "Tap into Game Center:
Dashboard, Access Point, and Profile."
Next, you need to report
the player's progress to GameKit.
As long as GameKit maintains
a progress of zero for an achievement,
it's going to appear to the player
as locked.
But the most interesting part
of achievements happens
when the player makes progress
in your game.
You'll notice in-progress achievements
have been completely redesigned.
Game Center will present players
with this brand-new styling,
which features a progress circle,
enticing them to get back into your game.
Unsurprisingly,
reporting achievement progress
is done through the GKAchievement class.
Every achievement has a unique identifier,
which you use
to initialize the GKAchievement.
Anytime the player makes progress
towards that achievement,
it's important to update
that percentComplete property.
Finally, you can call the report method
to register that change
and handle any potential errors.
Now the player will see
their achievement progress update
anywhere they see this achievement,
and they will unlock its imagery
if it's completed.
Finally, let's talk about how
we can show the player their achievements.
Achievements have a brand-new home
in the Game Center In-Game Dashboard.
If you integrate the new Access Point,
this dashboard is just one tap away
for the player in your game.
The Achievements tab is front and center,
giving players a one-stop shop
for viewing all things achievements.
Inside this tab,
the summaries give the player
a high-level view
of how they're doing in your game.
But players can dive deeper,
scanning through the achievements
they've already collected
as well as previewing
the ones they're working on
and some others
you've got in store for them.
While the player can reach
this page from the Dashboard,
you can also present it directly with API.
Doing so is done using
the GKGameCenterViewController.
You can initialize it
with an "achievements" state
and optionally assign the gameCenter
Delegate property on the view controller.
With just these few lines of code,
you'll guide players into the all-new
achievements page for your game.
This UI provides a clean and consistent
window into your game's achievements,
so it will be the preferred experience
for the vast majority of games.
For those that need to customize their
achievements' display in their own UI,
this can be done using
the GKAchievementDescription class.
Like GKAchievement, which is what
you use to update the player's progress,
this class has an identifier.
But it also has the "achievements" title,
as well as separate descriptions
for when the achievement
is unachieved and achieved.
It's important to note that the title and
descriptions associated with this class
are localized according to
the player's localization preferences.
As the game developer, you will make sure
that all the relevant
translations are included
when you set up an achievement
in App Store Connect.
But when interacting
with the achievement descriptions,
GameKit will give you strings
that are ready to display to the player.
And finally, there are also APIs
for accessing achievement images
for the achieved and non-achieved cases.
So we've talked a bit about how to design
achievements that work well for your game.
We've also shown how to work with GameKit
to view and update players' progress.
But before you can submit
an achievements-ready build of your game
to the App Store,
you'll need to configure the achievements
in App Store Connect.
To do so, go to the Features tab
of your game's page on App Store Connect.
Then,
after selecting the Game Center section,
you'll see an Achievements section.
To add an achievement for your game,
you can click the "plus" button.
This will bring up
the Add Achievement screen.
The achievement ID must be unique
to this achievement,
and,
as you saw in the previous code sample,
is used to initialize
your GKAchievement object.
You'll also have to configure
a few attributes,
such as point value,
whether it's hidden until achieved,
and whether the player
can earn the achievement multiple times.
These values will be reflected
in the GKAchievement class
we discussed earlier in the session.
We can finish adding this achievement,
and after we're done,
our build is ready to deliver to users.
Now I'm going to hand it over to Christy
to talk about multiplayer gaming.
Thank you, Dersu.
I am back to talk about
multiplayer gaming using Game Center.
First, I will give a quick overview
of Multiplayer.
Then I will show our new streamlined UI.
Next, I will give a quick review
of our basic API flows
and introduce some new options
for the Matchmaking UI.
Finally, I will talk about some changes
to privacy and restrictions.
We support several types
of multiplayer games:
real-time, turn-based and server-hosted.
The basic idea of our APIs
is that we take care of as much
of the multiplayer as we can for you.
For real-time,
we take care of finding players,
connecting to them, and sending data.
For turn-based, we take care of
turn management and storing the data.
For server-hosted,
we deliver you a list of players
that you can share with your server.
We have various ways
to find people to play with.
Firstly,
we have a really robust auto-match system
where we can find players
and get you into the game fast.
All you have to do is hit "Start Game."
You can also invite other players.
We have made it super easy to interact
with people you have made friends with.
We also make it fast
to find someone you just played with
so you can play with them again,
even in a different game.
We want you to play
with whomever you want,
so you can invite from your contacts.
This is great for developers
to bring new players into the game.
And finally, we work cross-platform,
so your players can play multiplayer
on whatever platform they like.
As you've just seen,
there's a new streamlined UI.
This is designed to help your users
find other players quickly
and get into the game faster.
We did this by simplifying the flow
and providing improved player suggestions.
But why talk about it
when we can show you?
Here we tap on the multiplayer button
and it brings up our matchmaking UI.
Now we tap "Add Player"...
and we'll invite our friend JonB.
Next...
we'll click on the "plus" button
to bring up contacts and invite Vance.
Now we tap "Invite and Start Game"...
and the last player will be auto-match.
So that's how you set up
a multiplayer game using our new flow.
What does matchmaking look like
from a coding perspective?
Let's take a look at the elements
of a real-time multiplayer match.
Starting from MyGameController,
first I authenticate the player,
create a match request,
and this is where I set
the number of players in a match,
and I can define people to invite.
it could be a friend,
another person I recently played with,
or someone discovered nearby.
And if appropriate,
I can use player groups and attributes
to filter the match request
to a specific game mode or other criteria.
Now I have a choice: either to
use this request for auto-matching
or to present a UI for the player
to select other people to invite.
So, let's say I'm doing auto-matching.
Then I'd simply use
the shared GKMatchmaker
and provide it with my match request.
Game Center will find other players.
It's time to play,
and you'll use the returned match object
to send data from player to player.
Or, as I said, I could choose to present
a GKMatchmakerViewController,
given the match request parameters,
and let the player select
their own people to invite.
Once they've accepted, the game can begin.
One more piece, very important,
which typically should be done
right at app launch,
is to adopt
the GKInviteEventListener protocol...
register it with the local player
in order to listen for invites
coming from other people,
and now
everything is ready to get started.
Turn-based matchmaking
follows virtually the same flow.
Like in this case,
you adopt a GKTurnBasedEventListener
with a couple more methods to implement it
and, like before,
register it with the local player.
Then you set up a match request
and call findMatchForRequest
on the GKTurnBasedMatch
for programmatic matchmaking.
Or you present a
GKTurnBasedMatchmakerViewController.
Either way,
an important difference with turn-based
is that you do not wait
for other players to match,
but instead start playing immediately
because it'll always be your turn.
For iOS 14, we have new options
to configure the matchmaking UI.
You can set "auto-match only"
if you want players to match up
with random other players
and get quickly into the game.
You can choose "nearby only"
for games like ARKit games,
where you wish to have players
that are in the same room with you.
There is a new restriction this year
that when enabled restricts both
the custom message in multiplayer invites
as well as voice chat.
Here is a new flag,
personalizedCommunicationRestricted,
that lets the app know this so they can,
for example, turn off their voice chat UI.
So if your app shows
a little microphone for voice chat,
and if this flag comes back true, then
disable the icon for this functionality.
In closing, I've talked about
the different types of multiplayer,
ways to find players,
and gave you a glimpse of the new UI.
Then I did a quick API review
and introduced you to new UI options
for our matchmaker view controller.
And finally,
I discussed a new privacy restriction.
So that's our session on Game Center.
Here we've covered leaderboards,
achievements, and multiplayer.
Here are some resources
to check out for more depth.
You can also see our design talk
for more information.
So thank you, and have a great WWDC.