Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Ted. And welcome to
"What's New in Swift."
Today, the ecosystem around Swift
is blossoming in many directions.
The introduction of API stability
in Swift 5
brought binary frameworks to Swift.
This led to the advent
of powerful new APIs, such as SwiftUI,
that are front and center
to the Apple developer experience.
Over the last year,
many investments have been made in Swift,
both on the surface and under the hood,
that will amplify Swift impact
on Apple's APIs,
the core of its operating systems
and the Apple developer ecosystem.
There's also a growing set
of powerful open-source APIs
that take full advantage of Swift,
which are conveniently accessible
to app developers in Xcode
using the Swift Package Manager.
Finally, Swift's reach
as a cross-platform language
for tackling problems in many domains
continues to grow
with support for more platforms
than ever before.
Across both releases,
there has been a continuum of investments
in performance, language refinements,
and the developer experience.
Let us start things off
by looking at some significant advances
in Swift's runtime performance.
The first piece to look at is code size.
Code size is the part of the app
that represents
the machine code representation
of the app's logic.
This has been a focus of optimization
for several releases now.
To track progress,
we have been using a Swift rewrite
of one of the apps that ships with iOS.
We've been tracking the code size
of the Swift version of the app
versus the Objective-C version
since Swift 4.
We started out with the Swift version
at about 2.3 times the code size
of the Objective-C version.
Swift 4.1 took a big chunk out
with the optimize for code size
optimization setting.
At each subsequent release,
we narrowed the difference.
With Swift 5.3, we're down to
below one-and-a-half times
the code size of the Objective-C version.
Note that some amount of difference
is inevitable
because Swift comes with safety features
that take some amount of code size
to implement in an app.
Different styles of applications, however,
produce different binary sizes.
This application was a UIKit app.
But what about a SwiftUI app?
In Swift 5.3,
there are significant improvements
to the code size of SwiftUI apps.
Here's MovieSwiftUI,
which is an excellent open-source app
by Thomas Ricouard.
We see that its application logic
code size is reduced by over 40%.
Now, binary size is essential
for things like download times,
but when you're running the app,
it's part of what we call clean memory.
That's memory that can be purged
because it can be reloaded when needed.
So it's less critical than dirty memory,
the memory the application allocates
and manipulates at runtime.
Let's next look at how dirty memory usage
has significantly improved.
Swift's use of value types
has some fundamental advantages
over reference type based languages.
To understand why, here's an example
in Objective-C of a simple model type
with a UUID, a string, and a number.
Let's look at how this model is held
in memory when we store it in an array.
In Objective-C,
object variables are just pointers.
So the array holds pointers
to the model objects.
Those objects, in turn,
hold pointers to their properties.
Every object you allocate has some
overhead and performance and memory use.
This is so important that Objective-C
has a special small string representation
for tiny ASCII strings that allow them
to be stored within the pointer,
which saves on allocating
the extra object.
Now, we'll look at the same model
in Swift.
Swift's use of value types
avoids the need for many of these values
to be accessed via a pointer.
Thus the UUIDs can be held
within the Mountain objects.
And Swift's small string could hold
many more characters,
up to 15 code units,
including non-ASCII characters.
Finally, all the Mountain objects
can be allocated
directly within the array storage.
So, with the exception of a few strings,
everything is held
within a contiguous block of memory.
Swift programs can get
a significant memory benefit
from using value types like this.
So if we examine the heap memory used
by an array of 400 of these model objects,
we can see
the Swift model data is more compact.
About
20 kilobytes instead of 35 kilobytes.
Note these measurements
are from Swift 5.1.
Despite this advantage,
some Swift programs previously still used
more heap memory
because of runtime overhead.
Previously, Swift created
a number of caches and memory on start-up.
These caches stored things
like protocol conformances
and other type information,
as well as data used to bridge types
over to Objective-C.
All language runtimes have some overhead,
but in Swift's case, it was too large.
This was a big focus for us to optimize.
I'm happy to say that in Swift 5.3,
we've cut that overhead way down
to the point where the Swift version
of the app now uses
less than a third of the heap memory
it did in last year's release.
To get full advantage
of these improvements,
an app's minimum deployment target
needs to be set to iOS 14.
But many of these improvements
will benefit apps
that back deploy to earlier OS releases.
In most applications,
these differences
are not often noticeable,
but optimizing Swift's memory like this
was critical to allow us to push Swift
further throughout Apple system
to be able to use it in daemons
and low-level frameworks
where every byte of memory used counts.
To that end,
we've also made another important change.
We have moved Swift's Standard Library
so that it sits
below Foundation in the stack.
That means it can actually be used
to implement frameworks
that float below the level of Objective-C,
where previously C had to be used.
Next, let's turn our attention
to how we continue to refine
the developer experience.
Starting with looking at how diagnostics,
errors and warnings from the compiler,
have vastly improved
in this release cycle.
The Swift compiler
has a new diagnostic strategy
that results in more precise errors
that point to the exact location
in source code where the problem occurs.
There are new heuristics
for diagnosing the cause of issues
that lead to actionable errors
with guidance on how to fix issues.
Here's an example
of an incomprehensible diagnostic
the Swift 5.1 compiler would have produced
on SwiftUI code a year ago.
Fast forward today,
the diagnostic is significantly better
with an error that tells you
exactly what is the problem.
When diagnosing issues,
the compiler internally also records
more information about problems.
So it now produces additional notes.
These notes can help the developer
in a variety of circumstances
to better understand and resolve an issue.
In this case, applying the fix-it
naturally guides the developer
to provide the missing pieces
to an incomplete initialization
of a Text-Field.
If you're interested in finding out more
about the new diagnostic architecture
in the compiler,
you can navigate over to Swift.org
and find a great write-up in a blog post.
Code completion for Swift has also
dramatically improved in this release.
All the way
from the code completion inference
provided by the compiler and SourceKit,
and through the experience
in the Xcode code editor.
Let's turn our attention
to how completion results
have fundamentally gotten much better.
First, the inference
of candidate completions
has significantly improved.
Here the compiler is inferring the value
in a ternary expression
when used within
an incomplete dictionary literal.
This simply would not have worked before.
Code completion also provides
the values you would expect
for some of the more dynamic features
of the language,
such as using KeyPath as functions.
Besides the quality of completion results,
code completion performance
has drastically improved.
In some cases, up to 15 times
speed improvement compared to Xcode 11.5.
This is particularly beneficial
for editing SwiftUI code.
These bar charts show the performance
for common uses of code completion
in SwiftUI code measured in seconds.
In Xcode 11.5, these actions would take
around half a second to complete,
which is quite noticeable.
Now, these are under a tenth of a second.
Code indentation in Xcode,
also powered
by the open-source SourceKit engine,
has significantly improved.
You will see improved handling
of chained method calls
and property accesses,
a major component of Swift UI code.
You'll also find improvements
for alignment of call arguments,
tuple elements, collection elements
that span multiple lines,
and multi-line control flow.
Here you can see
one of the improvements at work
in SwiftUI code taken from
the open-source MovieSwiftUI project.
Before, you would get sometimes
a natural indentation
for some of the chained accesses.
But now,
they are cleanly visually aligned.
These, and the other improvements
I mentioned,
will have a noticeable effect
on your editing experience.
Next, let's talk about improvements
to the core experience
of debugging Swift code.
When debug information is available,
the debugger will now display
the reason for common Swift
runtime failure traps
instead of just showing
an opaque "invalid instruction" crash.
Further, Swift debugging support
is now more robust in general.
To understand why, let's look at a key way
Swift interoperates with Objective-C
at compile time.
Swift imports APIs from Objective-C
using Clang modules.
To resolve information
about types and variables,
LLDB needs to import
all Swift and Clang modules
that are visible
in the current debugging context.
While these module files
have a wealth of information about types,
since LLDB has a global view
of the entire program
and all of its dynamic libraries,
importing Clang modules can sometimes fail
in ways they would not at compile time.
One common failure scenario
is when the search pass
from different dynamic libraries
are in conflict.
As a fallback, when this occurs,
LLDB can now also import
C and Objective-C types
for Swift debugging purposes
from DWARF debug information.
This vastly increases
the reliability of features
such as the Xcode variable view
and expression evaluator.
Swift is an excellent
general-purpose language.
Swift is great for building apps
on Apple's platforms,
but also great for many other tasks.
For this reason, we think cross-platform
support in Swift is so important.
Swift's official support
for more platforms continues to grow.
This year, Swift updated its support
for Ubuntu,
as well as picked up official support
for more variants of Linux
with CentOS and Amazon Linux 2.
And coming for Swift 5.3
will be the initial support for Windows.
Follow along on Swift.org
to find out more as it becomes available.
With these ports comes increased
opportunity to use Swift in more places.
One of those places is AWS Lambda.
Serverless functions are an easy way
for client application developers
to extend their applications
into the cloud.
It is now easy to do this in Swift
using the open-source Swift AWS runtime.
The runtime is 100% open-source
and available on GitHub,
and is the result of a group effort
that included engineers
across the Swift community.
It includes instructions, how to build
and deploy to AWS Lambda
and programming to AWS Lambda.
As this example shows in Xcode,
the amount of code needed
is as simple as writing "Hello, world".
Those are just
some of the exciting updates
in the Swift ecosystem.
Next, Kyle will talk about changes
to the Swift language and libraries.
Thanks, Ted. Hi, I'm Kyle,
a member
of the Swift Standard Library Team.
It's been a big year for the Swift
language and the Swift Library ecosystem.
Let's start by talking about the language.
In addition to the improvements
Ted just discussed,
we've added over a dozen
new language features
across Swift 5.2 and Swift 5.3.
Because we don't have time
to cover all of them today,
I want to draw your attention
to these SE numbers.
As many of you know,
the Swift language goes through
an open evolution process.
Each one of these numbers
corresponds to a feature document
that you can look up
on the Swift Evolution website.
This website
is also a great jumping-off point
if you're curious about how you can help
shape the future of Swift.
All right, let's dive in.
Some of the most exciting additions
this year
are the powerful new tools
available to API designers,
which is all of you,
whether you maintain
a popular open-source package,
work on a team with other developers,
or just use Swift
for your own personal projects.
If you code, you design APIs.
Let's begin
with multiple trailing closure syntax.
Since its inception, Swift has supported
something called trailing closure syntax,
a bit of syntactic sugar that lets you pop
the final argument to a method
out of the parenthesis
when it's a closure.
Trailing closure syntax
has proven to be very popular.
And it's not hard to guess why.
It can be more concise
and less nested without loss of clarity,
making the call site much easier to read.
However, the restriction
of trailing closure syntax
to only the final closure
has limited its applicability.
In this case, the trailing closure
makes the code harder to read
because its role is unclear.
Worse, it changes meaning
from the completion block at one call site
to the animation block at another.
Concerns about call site confusion
have led Swift style guides
to prohibit
the use of trailing closure syntax
when a method call, like this one,
has multiple closure arguments.
As a result, if we ever need to append
an additional closure argument,
many of us find ourselves
having to rejigger our code
more than may seem necessary.
New to Swift 5.3
is multiple trailing closure syntax.
This extends the benefits
of trailing closure syntax
to calls with multiple closure arguments,
and there's no rejiggering required
to append an additional one.
Multiple trailing closure syntax
is also a great fit for DSLs.
SwiftUI's new Gauge View
is used to indicate the level of a value
relative to some overall capacity.
Here I have a circular watchOS gauge
for tracking the acidity level
of my garden soil.
But tomatoes are finicky enough to where
I'd really like to see
the exact value at a glance.
Fortunately,
I can add a currentValueLabel
and minimum and maximumValueLabels.
By taking advantage
of multiple trailing closure syntax,
Gauge is able to elegantly, progressively
disclose its customization points.
Let's take a moment
to explore the implications
of trailing closure syntax
on Swift API design.
Imagine you encounter this line of code
in, say, a messaging app
you're working on,
where summary is used to show a snippet
of the last message in each chat.
What's the value of summary?
What's the call to the take method doing?
The closure is probably determining
which characters to take,
but how's it being applied?
Pause and think about it for a second.
Is it taking characters
that match the predicate
and dropping those that don't?
Is it taking characters
while they match the predicate
and dropping everything that follows?
In this case, the call site is only clear
if we use the longhand spelling
that includes the argument label.
We can do better.
Because folks can drop the argument label,
it's best to name methods
assuming that they will.
A better name for "take"
might be something like "prefix,"
which suggests the result is anchored
to the start of the collection.
In fact, prefix(while is the name
that was ultimately chosen for this method
when it was added to the Standard Library
way back in Swift 3.1.
The same guidance applies
to more complex APIs,
including those
with multiple trailing closures.
It's important the base name of the method
clarify the role
of the first trailing closure.
Because its label will be dropped
even if it isn't the first argument
to the method.
Next, let's discuss KeyPath expressions
as functions.
Back in Swift 4.1,
we introduced smart KeyPaths,
types that represent
uninvoked references to properties
which can be used to get
and set their underlying values.
When you're designing an API,
KeyPaths are a tempting alternative
to function parameters
if you expect the call site
to be a simple property access,
because they're more concise
and less nested.
For this example,
I've borrowed an algorithm from Ruby.
Chunked. It's an adapter over a collection
that groups adjacent elements
while their keys are equal.
I happen to keep a list handy
of my friends' and family's shoe sizes.
A new pair of shoes
always makes a good present.
I can get a quick overview by sorting,
and then chunking my contacts
by shoe size.
Hmm. If I ever need to re-gift a pair,
it looks like I should try Charles.
Of course, every once in a while,
you're going to encounter a use case
that isn't a simple property access.
Say you're shopping for sandals
which don't come in half sizes.
To support both of these call sites,
you'd have to duplicate the declaration.
New to Swift 5.2, you can use
a KeyPath expression as a function.
This means you can pass a KeyPath argument
to any function parameter
with a matching signature.
And you can delete
any duplicate declarations
you may have added in the past,
in order to accept KeyPaths.
Next, I'll introduce you to @main,
a tool for type-based
program entry points.
Every program
needs to start execution somehow.
Here, I'm using
the new ArgumentParser package
to declare a simple tool
that prints "hello"
to a name drawn from the command line.
But the boilerplate
required to start execution
is as long as the program itself,
and it seriously kills
the declarative vibe.
Since Swift 1.0, you've been able to use
the UIApplicationMain attribute
on your AppDelegate
to tell the compiler to generate
an implicit main.swift that runs your app.
In Swift 5.3, we've generalized
and democratized this feature.
If you're a Library author,
just declare a static main method
on the protocol or superclass
you expect your users
to derive their entry point from.
For ArgumentParser,
that's ParsableCommand.
This will enable your users
to tag that type with @main
and the compiler to generate
an implicit main.swift on their behalf.
This standardized way to delegate
a program's entry point
should make it easier
to get up and running,
whether you're working
on a command line tool,
an existing application,
a new one, or something else entirely.
We can't wait to see how you put these
powerful new API design tools to use.
Next, I want to highlight
some language enhancements
that eliminate boilerplate
and increase expressivity.
Let's start
with the increased availability
of implicit self in closures.
In order to draw attention
to potential retain cycles,
Swift requires the explicit use of "self"
in escaping closures which capture it.
But when you're required to include
many self.s in a row,
it can start to feel a bit redundant.
New to Swift 5.3,
if you include "self" in the capture list,
you can omit it
from the body of the closure.
You're still required to be explicit
about your intention to capture self,
but now the cost of that explicitness
is only a single declaration.
Sometimes, however, even a single use
of self. can feel unnecessary.
Like in SwiftUI,
where self tends to be a value type,
making reference cycles much less likely.
Well, with Swift 5.3,
I'm pleased to tell you
that if self is a struct or enum,
you can omit it entirely from the closure.
We think these refinements
will increase the signal-to-noise ratio
of compiler errors related to
the implicit use of self in closures,
mitigating the temptation to slap on self.
without due consideration.
Next, let's talk about
multi-pattern catch clauses.
Historically, do-catch statements
have not been as expressive
as switch statements,
leading folks to resort
to nesting switches
inside of catch clauses.
Well, in Swift 5.3, we've extended
the grammar of catch clauses
to have the full power of switch cases.
This allows you to flatten
this kind of multi-clause pattern matching
directly into the do-catch statement,
making it much easier to read.
Next, let's look at a couple enhancements
we've made to enum types.
Since Swift 4.1,
the compiler has been able to synthesize
equatable and hashable conformance
for a wide variety of types.
Sometimes, though, you run into situations
where it'd be awfully convenient
to have a comparison operator.
I'm pleased to tell you that in Swift 5.3,
the compiler has learned
how to synthesize comparable conformance
for qualifying enum types.
Next, let's discuss enum cases
as protocol witnesses.
Consider these two call sites.
Is fileCorrupted a static var
or an enum case?
Is keyNotFound a static func
Static var and static func:
enum cases.
The call sites for the two declarations
are identical.
In recognition of this, in Swift 5.3,
we've enhanced enum cases
so they can now be used to fulfill
static var and static func
protocol requirements.
Last year, Swift added support
for embedded DSLs
to power SwiftUI's declarative syntax.
This included builder closures
to collective view's children,
and basic control flow statements
like if-else.
I'm excited to tell you that in Swift 5.3,
we've extended embedded DSLs
to support pattern matching
control flow statements
like if-let and switch.
Here, I'm able to compose a photo gallery
of my favorite animals
by using a switch statement
to alternate between
the different image layouts
within this scrollable vertical stack.
Next, I'll introduce you
to builder inference.
Here, I've written an app
for keeping track of the books
I'm currently reading in my book club.
I've got a main window
for my primary user interface
and a Preferences window
for my app settings.
Previously, to use DSL syntax
at the top level of body like this
required tagging it
with the specific builder attribute.
With Swift 5.3, I'm excited to tell you
that builder attribute
will no longer be required
because we're teaching the compiler
how to infer it
from the protocol requirement.
SwiftUI added a ton
of exciting new features this year.
If you want to know more,
I recommend you watch
the "What's New in SwiftUI" session.
Now I want to change gears and talk about
some of the powerful,
new Swift APIs available to you,
beginning with those in the SDK.
Let's start with Float16.
Float16 is an IEEE 754
standard floating-point format
that's new to Swift 5.3.
As the name suggests,
a Float16 takes just two bytes of memory,
as opposed to a single-precision float
which takes four.
Since it's half the size,
you can fit twice as many of them
in a SIMD register or page of memory
which, on supported hardware,
generally results
in a doubling of performance.
Beware, though. As a smaller data type,
it also has
a more limited precision and range,
so be careful translating code
that was originally implemented
for double or float to work with Float16.
For more on Float16, I recommend you watch
the session we've prepared
on "Numerical Computing in Swift."
Next, let's talk about Apple Archive,
a new modular archive format
based on the battle-tested technology
Apple uses to deliver OS updates.
It's optimized
for fast, multithreaded compression
and comes with Finder integration,
a command-line tool,
and a host of other powerful features,
including an idiomatic Swift API.
This is how simple it is
to efficiently compress and archive
a source directory using Apple Archive.
I want to draw your attention
to the FileStream constructor
which leverages another new library
we're introducing this year: Swift System.
Swift System provides
modern idiomatic interfaces
to system calls and currency types
for low-level system APIs
like Apple Archive.
The raw weakly-typed interfaces
imported through the Darwin overlay
can be finicky and error-prone.
Swift System wraps these APIs
using techniques such as
strongly-typed RawRepresentable structs,
error handling, defaulted arguments,
namespaces, and function overloading,
laying the groundwork
for a more idiomatically Swift
system layer of the SDK.
Last, let's look at some enhancements
to OSLog.
OSLog is a unified logging API
that's been optimized
to have minimal overhead
and crafted to prevent
inadvertent logging of sensitive data.
In Swift 5.3, we've leveraged
sophisticated compiler optimizations
to make OSLog dramatically faster
and more expressive,
adding support for string interpolations
and formatting options.
If you're still using print
as your logging solution,
now is the perfect time to reconsider.
If you want to learn more about these APIs
and how to leverage logging
to track down hard-to-reproduce bugs,
I suggest you watch the session
on "Logging in Swift."
Last, let's turn our attention
to the growing number of APIs
available to you outside the SDK
via the Swift Package Manager.
Let's begin with Swift Numerics,
a new open-source package
for numerical computing.
Swift Numerics defines
all the basic math functions
like sine and logarithm
in a way that's much more useful
for generic contexts,
as well as support for complex numbers
and arithmetic.
Swift Numerics complex numbers
are layout compatible
with their C counterparts,
but faster and more accurate.
There are many other exciting projects
being actively discussed right now
on the Swift Numerics GitHub page,
including
approximate equality comparisons,
arbitrary-precision integers
and decimal floating-point numbers.
The Swift Numerics package
is discussed in-depth
in the session we've prepared
on "Numerical Computing."
Next, let's look at Swift Argument Parser,
a new open-source Swift package
for command-line argument parsing.
Earlier, we saw how to use Argument Parser
to print "hello" to a name drawn
from the command line.
Let's extend this
by adding an integer option,
count, with a default of one,
and a loop to print the greeting
"count" number of times.
Now our tool can be
that much more enthusiastic.
It's also smart
about what values it accepts,
guides users towards correct usage,
and includes
a richly-documented help screen.
All this and more from a program
that comfortably fits on a slide.
Last, I'll introduce you
to the Swift StandardLibraryPreview
Package.
The Preview Package provides access
to functionality
that's been accepted
through the Swift Evolution process,
but hasn't yet shipped
as a part of an official Swift release.
By getting new features
into your hands sooner,
we think we can make Swift even better.
As part of this effort,
we've also made it easier
for Swift Evolution proposals
to proceed to review.
In the past, that would have meant
building the entire compiler stack.
Now, you can provide the implementation
for a StandardLibrary feature proposal
as a stand-alone Swift PM package.
We've seeded the preview package
with the functionality from SE-0270,
which includes operations
on sub-ranges of collections
and the supporting range set type.
I encourage you to try it out.
The future of the Swift Library ecosystem
is being molded right now
as we push onto new platforms
and into new domains,
and it's being done in plain sight
as we increasingly leverage
open-source packages.
We're deliberately
releasing these packages early
while they're still malleable
and developing them
as community efforts on GitHub.
So try them out. File an issue.
Open a pull request.
It's never been a better time,
and it's never been easier
to get involved and make an impact.
I hope you're as excited
about these new Swift releases as we are.
We can't wait to see what you build.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC.
Thank you for watching.