Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to "App Essentials in SwiftUI."
My name is Matt Ricketson,
and I work on SwiftUI.
Later on,
I'll be joined by my colleague Jeff.
Last year we introduced SwiftUI,
a powerful new way
to build great user interfaces
on all of Apple's platforms.
We build user interfaces using views,
and SwiftUI provides a suite of APIs
for modifying views
and composing them together.
This year, we're extending the framework
with new APIs for declaring
scenes and apps,
a big expansion to what you can build
using SwiftUI.
The bottom line
is that you can now build an entire app
with just SwiftUI.
In this session,
we're going to introduce these new APIs
and explain how views,
scenes and apps work together.
Next, we'll go in-depth
on SwiftUI's scene architecture
and show how you can customize
the scenes in your app.
And finally, we'll give a quick overview
of the different APIs available
for customizing your apps
and where you can go to learn more.
For now,
let's start by talking about views,
which you will already be familiar with
if you've used SwiftUI before.
Views are important
because each view
defines a piece of your UI.
When you look at an app,
everything you see is a view.
Individual images
and pieces of text are views.
The containers holding them
are also views.
In fact, every pixel you see on screen
is in some way defined by a view.
But not all views belong to the same app,
since apps do not have complete control
over the entire screen.
Instead, the platform controls
how apps are presented,
showing pieces of apps
in distinct regions.
In SwiftUI, we refer to these
distinct regions as "scenes."
A window is the most common way
that a scene's content is shown on screen.
Some platforms, like iPadOS,
can show multiple windows side-by-side.
Other platforms,
such as iOS, watchOS and tvOS,
prefer to show only a single
full-screen window for each app.
macOS is another great example
of how scene content
can appear in different ways.
In this case, we see a collection
of related windows,
where each window is a manifestation
of a different scene's content.
macOS also allows you
to gather up related windows
into a single, tabbed window.
In this case, our scenes are represented
as individual tabs instead.
This shared window
is also represented by its own scene,
serving as a container for
the child scenes associated with each tab.
These collections of scenes
make up the entire content of an app.
Together, apps, scenes and views
form a unified hierarchy of ownership.
As we mentioned earlier,
views serve as the basic building blocks,
rendering everything you see on screen,
and can be composed together
to form more complex user interfaces.
Views form the content of scenes,
allowing them to be independently
displayed by the platform.
Like views, those scenes
can also be composed together
to form more complex scenes,
like in our tabbed-window example
that we saw earlier.
And finally, all these scenes
form the content of your app.
Now that we understand how apps,
scenes and views work together,
let's look at how this plays out
in your SwiftUI code.
Here we see a basic app I wrote in SwiftUI
to help me keep track of the books
I'm reading in my book club.
As you can see, apps in SwiftUI
have a concise declaration,
meaning basic apps like this
can fit into only a handful
of lines of code.
Without that extra boilerplate,
you can focus immediately
on the code that's unique to your app.
In this case, we've defined
the actual interface of our app
using a view called ReadingListViewer.
ReadingListViewer
is a custom view I built separately
that allows me to browse my reading list.
Our ReadingListViewer is contained
within a scene called WindowGroup.
The WindowGroup scene manages the window
that our ReadingListViewer
will render into.
It can also create additional windows,
or new tabs within the same window,
on platforms that support those features.
Jeff will explain how WindowGroup works
in much more detail later in the talk.
Our WindowGroup scene
is contained within an app,
represented by a custom struct
conforming to the App protocol.
You'll notice
that the structure of the code
matches the hierarchy of ownership
we saw earlier--
the app contains the scenes,
and the scenes contain views.
You might also notice
that our app declaration
looks similar
to a custom-view declaration.
For example, both views and apps
are able to declare data dependencies.
Here, our ReadingListViewer
observes a ReadingListStore object.
Our app also depends
on a ReadingListStore object,
but declares itself
as the owner of that object
using the StateObject property wrapper,
which is a new feature
in SwiftUI this year.
Both views and apps
also declare a "body" property,
defining their user-interface content.
We talked earlier about how views
are composed of other views,
which is why a view's body returns a view.
An app, however, is built using scenes,
and so its body property
returns a scene instead.
Finally, you probably noticed
the @main attribute decorating our app.
This is a new attribute in Swift 5.3
that allows a type
to serve as the entry point
of our program's execution.
Normally, a Swift program would require
a main.swift file to execute.
With the @main attribute,
we can delegate that responsibility
to our app struct instead,
which automatically performs
all the necessary setup on launch
to get our app to appear on screen.
Now that we've reviewed the code,
let's take a step back.
What we see here is a complete declaration
for a basic app in SwiftUI,
fitting into only a handful
of lines of code.
But don't let this deceive you.
There is a ton of automatic,
intelligent behavior
packed into this simple declaration.
To really understand how this app works,
we need to talk more
about that WindowGroup scene,
which manages our user interface.
And for that,
I'm going to hand things over to Jeff.
Thanks, Matt. Hi, everyone.
First, I'd like to show you
some of the concepts
that Matt outlined in practice,
with a short demo,
and then I'll discuss
some of the finer points of WindowGroup.
I'm a pretty avid reader,
so I've been working on a little app
to track my progress in all of the books
I'm currently reading.
As you can see, my app launches
with an initial window on iPadOS
using the view I've specified as content.
Looks like I'm in the middle
of quite a few books,
so let's open some new windows
so I can check my progress.
If I open App Exposé,
I can easily create a new one here
and navigate to a different book.
WindowGroup provides
this functionality for my app
automatically on iPadOS.
You'll notice that each of my windows
is reflecting a different state
in the interface.
The selected book
is different in each one,
and changing it in one
does not affect the others.
This is a key aspect to scenes in SwiftUI.
An app can provide a shared model
for each scene to use,
but the state of the views in those scenes
will be independent.
I'd also like to point out something
in the App Switcher.
Each of my windows
is showing the name of my app,
as well as the name of the selected book.
This is done via a new view modifier
that we've introduced this year,
"navigation title,"
which on iOS can be used to populate
the title in the navigation bar
and the App Switcher.
This is one example of a view modifier
which can affect the state
of its parent scene.
On the Mac, it's very common for apps
to support multiple windows.
By using WindowGroup in your app,
SwiftUI will provide a menu item
in the file menu,
which supports creating
new scene instances.
This item can also be invoked
via the standard
Command-N keyboard shortcut.
You'll notice how navigation title
applies here on macOS.
The book title is being displayed
in the window's title-bar area.
It also will be used in the windows menu.
Providing a good title here
is important for the users
since, in addition to giving them more
context for what they're interacting with,
it also helps them select
their desired window
from the list of open ones.
Besides supporting multiple windows,
macOS also supports
grouping its windows together.
Via the window menu,
I can merge my open windows
into a single, tabbed interface...
with each tab being represented
by a separate scene.
Again, I didn't have to write any code
for this functionality.
SwiftUI provides this automatically.
Now that you've seen
some of the practical implications
of using the WindowGroup scene
in your app,
let's go over a few more details.
To recap what I showed you just now,
WindowGroup is a scene
which lets you express
the primary interface of your app.
The view that you provide to it
will be used
as the definition of that interface.
And this works on all of our platforms
in the expected way.
For example, on iOS and watchOS,
your view will be presented
in a window which occupies
the entire screen of the device.
While on macOS,
this window will be sized
according to your view's definition.
The life cycle of scenes
are managed by the platform
they are running on.
Using macOS as an example,
when the platform needs to create
a window for your app,
WindowGroup will instantiate
a new child scene
which by default will display its content
within a window.
On platforms which support
multiple windows,
such as macOS and iPadOS,
WindowGroup can instantiate
multiple children.
This can happen
in response to user actions
such as clicking a menu item
or invoking a multitasking gesture.
While each scene shares
the definition of its user interface,
the views which make up this definition
all have their own independent state.
And this means that changing
the view state in one window
does not affect the state of the others.
This functionality
lets you provide a template
to be used for your interface,
while letting your users
customize this interface
through the state you provide.
Since the platform is in charge
of the life cycle of scenes,
we've introduced
a new property wrapper this year
to help you manage restoration
of your view state.
The SceneStorage property wrapper
can be used to persist your view state.
It takes a unique key
which identifies the state to be stored.
This state will then be
automatically saved and restored
at the appropriate times by SwiftUI.
Now that I've shown you
more about how scenes
and specifically WindowGroup work,
I'd like to hand things back to Matt
who will give you some more info about
how you can customize your apps further.
Thanks, Jeff.
Before we finish up, I'd like to show you
just a few other new app-related features
available this year.
The BookClub app we saw earlier
was a data-driven app
backed by a shared data model.
But there are other kinds of apps as well,
such as document-based apps,
like we see here with the ShapeEdit app.
New this year
is the DocumentGroup scene type,
which automatically manages
opening, editing
and saving document-based scenes.
To learn more, you should check out
this year's "Build Document-Based Apps
in SwiftUI" talk.
Now, going back to our BookClub example,
a common feature of macOS apps
is a preferences window.
This year we're exposing
the new "settings" scene type,
available on macOS,
which automatically sets up
the standard preferences window.
The settings scene will automatically
set up the preferences command
in the app menu
and also give the window
the correct style treatment.
Speaking of menu commands,
SwiftUI is also providing an API
for you to add custom commands
to your scenes
using the new "commands" modifier.
BookCommands is a custom type
that I've defined.
Let's take a quick look.
The commands API is powerful and flexible,
using the same declarative,
state-driven programming model
we use in views, scenes and apps.
You can encapsulate commands
in custom types,
target actions based on user focus,
similar to the responder chain
in AppKit or UIKit,
and use normal views
to build the commands themselves.
Check out our reference documentation
for more information
about working with commands.
That was just a peek
at the new app-related APIs
available in SwiftUI this year.
I'd recommend also checking out
these other SwiftUI talks,
which will help you with building
the content of your apps.
"Data Essentials in SwiftUI"
will build your knowledge
of how to properly pass data
between your apps, scenes and views.
And "What's New in Swift" will show you
the latest improvements in the language
that can improve all of your SwiftUI code.
We really look forward to seeing
all the great SwiftUI apps you build,
and we hope you share
your creations with us on the forums.
We love all your feedback
and can't wait to see what you build next.
Thanks and have a great WWDC.