Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I am Dhruv.
I am a GPU software engineer at Apple,
and I am here to talk about implementing
customized machine learning operations
using the new
Metal Performance Shaders Graph.
Let us begin.
MPS is a library of Metal based
high performance
GPU accelerated primitives
for varied fields like image processing,
linear algebra,
ray tracing and machine learning.
MPS team optimizes Metal kernels
to give the best performance
on each hardware
across Apple's various platforms.
We have an exciting set of new features
to discuss today.
We'll talk about performance improvements
made across MPS,
discuss how to leverage
the full 32-bit floating point support
in machine learning...
reveal the new MPSNDArray primitive,
and finally, we will introduce
the new Metal Performance Shaders Graph.
Allow me to go over
some of the amazing improvements
we added to image processing in MPS.
We tuned and improved
our distance transform filter.
It made for 15 times faster features
in Final Cut Pro.
MPS also has
a new edge detection primitive
using the EDLines algorithm.
It improved the Measure app
and made it ten times faster,
which enables it to do
even better line segment detection
in higher resolution.
We have also expanded support
for our CNN primitives.
We now have full FP32 support
for convolution
and fully connected primitives,
so developers do not need to recalculate
their hyper-parameters
or refactor their code
to get the same accuracy.
To enable this, implement
the kernelWeightsDataType method
on your data source provider
and set it to float32.
Please refer to our previous years' talks
for more details on how to implement
a convolution data source provider.
There is a new MPS primitive
called MPSNDArray.
MPSNDArray and corresponding operations
can support up to 16 dimensions,
which is more than enough
for machine learning
and various other scientific domains.
Also, there are virtually no restrictions
on the dimension sizes
in this new primitive
as long as you can fit them in memory.
To create an MPSNDArray,
first use an MPSNDArrayDescriptor
to specify a shape
and a data type for the elements.
Then pass it to the initializer,
along with the Metal device
on which you wish to allocate
the MPSNDArray.
MPSNDArray provides converters
to and from our already existing
MTLTexture based MPSImageBatch types.
And it can even import and export data
using your Metal buffers.
Now let's get to the meat
of what we would be talking about:
the new Metal Performance Shaders
Graph framework.
MPSGraph sits on top
of the MPS framework in the stack.
We use it to extend
Metal's compute functionality
to multidimensional tensors.
The new MPSGraph framework
will be supported on macOS,
iOS, iPadOS and tvOS,
same as the MPS framework.
You can include the new framework
in your project
from the "Build Phases" tab in Xcode.
It is right next to
the Metal Performance Shaders framework.
We have a lot to cover.
We will introduce the new MPSGraph,
walk through the different APIs available
to write custom compute functions,
and finally, look at writing and executing
machine learning training graphs.
Let's start looking at the basics
of the MPSGraph.
MPSGraph represents
a DAG of operations and tensors.
The operations are nodes of the graph
representing a unit of computation.
Here we have an example
of three basic math operations:
multiply, add, subtract.
Along with operations,
tensors are the edges of the graph
defining the dataflow in the graph.
We can see in our example
the tensors are flowing through
our basic math operations.
This symbolic representation allows us
to abstract away numerous data primitives
and provide a unified interface
to get the best performance on the GPU.
The MPSGraph object maintains ownership
for all the tensors and operations
created using methods on the graph.
MPSGraphTensors represent
a symbolic abstraction of data.
It consists of a shape, data type,
and a reference to the operation
responsible for creating the tensor.
Here we can see
how to create a constantTensor
simply by calling the constant method
on the graph.
Operations in the graph connect with
each other via three kinds of edges...
input tensors, which represent tensors
that act as data inputs
to the operation...
output tensors, which are created
by the operation itself...
and finally, a special kind of edge
called control dependency.
These are a set of operations
the graph would execute
before the current operation
even if the operation itself does not
depend on these set of operations.
Just like the constant operation,
operations can be created by calling
simple intuitive methods on the graph.
Here we see how to add two tensors
in the graph.
MPSGraph provides
a numerous set of operations
to manipulate tensors in the graph.
For example,
you could reshape a one-dimension tensor
into a two-dimension tensor.
You can slice apart that tensor
and take a small piece of it.
You can concatenate that piece
back into the original tensor
to create an even bigger one.
You can transpose tensors
in any dimension.
And finally,
you can even create a zero-length slice.
Zero-sized tensors
are supported in MPSGraph.
This enables some dynamic use cases
like recurrent neural network operations
on variable length sequences.
We support a plethora of operations
on the MPSGraph,
from multiple variants of convolutions
and reductions
to all the basic math operations
you may need in your compute graphs.
Let's start putting
some of these operations together
to create and execute
a custom compute function
with our very first MPSGraph.
In recent years,
machine learning research
has found novel ways
to handle natural language processing.
One such innovation was a new
kind of activation function used in BERT.
This activation
is called Gaussian Error Linear Unit,
commonly known as GeLU.
For our example, we will try to implement
a custom GeLU function
on the GPU using MPSGraph.
This is a simple three-step process.
We define the inputs to the graph,
write a set of operations to perform,
and finally,
execute the graph on provided data.
Let's start
by defining the inputs to the graph.
Our GeLU activation function
consists of a single input.
Input tensors are created
using placeholder operations in the graph,
which, as the name suggests,
act as placeholders during run time.
They are replaced
by caller provided input data.
We show here the API call
to create an example placeholder
of the type float32
with three columns and two rows.
Users might have varying sizes of inputs
going into the graph
known only at run time.
For example,
in the machine learning domain,
users frequently pass in
variable length sequences
or differing batch sizes of input images.
For these scenarios, MPSGraph supports
dynamic sizes in placeholders.
Simply specify
the size of the dimension as -1,
and the graph will evaluate shapes from
the corresponding fed inputs at run time.
If even the number of dimensions
of the incoming input is unknown,
simply pass a nil
to the placeholder shape.
MPSGraph fully supports type inference
and will propagate the shapes at run time
all through the graph.
Now that we have defined the inputs
to the graph, we can go to step two
and write out our custom compute function
in the graph.
Usually,
we expect to use the GeLU activation
at various points in our neural network.
So, for modularity, we will define
a helper function on our graph
which takes a tensor as an input.
Let's add the necessary operations
to apply the activation
on the given input tensor.
First, let's define some of the constants
used in our GeLU neuron.
We simply call the constant method
on the graph
with a scalar passed in
and set it to float32 dataType.
Next up, we have a unary math operation:
namely squareRoot.
MPSGraph provides
basic unary math operations.
We just call the squareRoot method
on the graph
with the half constant tensor
as the input.
Now that we have
our constants and inputs prepped,
we start doing some compute
with a couple of multiplies.
These operations
implicitly support broadcasting,
so the result tensor shape
would be automatically inferred
to be the same shape
as the input to the neuron.
We pass the two input tensors
into the multiplication method
on the graph to do just that.
This little unary method
forms the heart of the GeLU neuron,
known as error function.
Once more, we simply pass in
the input to the unary operation
and get back the output tensor
on the left-hand side,
ready for further computation.
Finally, we finish off the activation
with an add and a multiply.
Just as before,
we create the binary math operations,
and the output of the multiplication
is returned from our GeLU function.
We have successfully and quite easily
constructed a graph of operations
representing our GeLU neuron.
We can finish off
with the third and final step,
which is seeing how we execute this graph.
Running the graph is very easy.
Firstly, we pass the dictionary of feeds
which map to
the placeholders in the graph.
Next,
we specify the list of target tensors
we want the graph to evaluate
and return the results for.
These results are returned in a dictionary
on the left-hand side.
Finally, the users can optionally pass
a list of target operations
which the graph guarantees to execute.
As we saw, at execution time,
developers can feed placeholders
by passing MPSGraphTensorData objects,
which in turn returns a set of outputs
using the same
MPSGraphTensorData object.
MPSGraphTensorData helps abstract
over the numerous data primitives
available in the Metal ecosystem.
You can initialize it with a Metal buffer.
You can create a four-dimensional
tensor data using an MPSImageBatch.
We abstract over MPSVectors
and MPSMatrices as well.
And finally,
the new MPSNDArray primitive
can also be used to initialize
the MPSGraphTensorData.
So, we put it all together.
We start by creating an MPSGraph.
We define the inputs to the graph
with placeholders.
We call our GeLU helper function
to write out
the necessary operations in the graph.
Finally, we execute the graph
by passing the input data as feeds
requesting the GeLU tensor as a target.
And that's all that is needed
to execute a custom compute function
on any multidimensional tensor
on the GPU.
We just witnessed how you can use
basic math operations in the MPSGraph
to create a custom compute function.
Usually, for every operation,
output would be written out to memory.
The next operation would read
from this same global memory,
and this would end up causing unneeded
memory traffic and performance issues,
especially on the GPU.
However, MPSGraph compiler
applies a special optimization
to automatically fuse such operations
for the users.
We call this stitching.
The MPSGraph compiler
recognizes all adjacent operations
and passes it to the Metal compiler.
The Metal compiler
fuses the operations together
to create a single optimized Metal shader.
This leads to no memory overhead
and improves performance.
MPSGraph compiler
goes even one step further.
For any math operations
around hand tuned MPS kernels,
like convolution, matrix multiplication,
or reduction,
MPSGraph recognizes adjacent stitchable
operations to create a region...
and once more passes the region
of operations to the Metal compiler
for them to be fused
directly into the hand tuned MPS kernel,
giving the best of hand tuned
MPS optimizations for each hardware
and the memory savings
from automatic fusion of operations
by the Metal compiler.
Using the stitching optimization makes
GeLU go almost ten to 50 times faster.
We even gain significant memory savings.
All this is done
always and automatically for you
without a single line of code needed.
One such custom compute function
is machine learning inference.
Inference is the process
of applying a network on an input
and producing an output.
The network is made up
of a collection of operations,
such as convolution
and neuron activation layers,
which, as we showed, can be expressed
with operations in MPSGraph.
These layers, in turn,
depend upon a set of trained parameters.
During inference,
these parameters are fixed.
Their values are determined
during the training phase.
Therefore, for inference,
we can use constants to represent
these parameters in our MPSGraph.
With support for these
wide variety of operations in MPSGraph,
we now support recurrent neural networks
in the graph as well.
I'd like to introduce my colleague, Chris.
He will show us an exciting demo
of a text generation inference network
in action.
Thanks, Dhruv.
I'm Chris. I'm a GPU software engineer,
and I am here to make your iPad Pro
write a Shakespearean play.
We do this using the Long Short Term
Memory based Text Generator model.
The generator loop works
on a single character input,
in this case the letter O,
which is the last letter
in our initialization string "Romeo."
We feed the character index
into the embedding layer,
which is a gather operation in MPSGraph.
This produces a single vector,
and we feed this rank-one tensor
to the LSTM layer,
which has a constant set
of trained parameters.
The result of the LSTM layer
is fed to the un-embedding layer,
which can be implemented with a matrix
multiplication operation in MPSGraph...
and the state of the LSTM layer
is updated for the next iteration.
Then the results are multiplied
by the inverse temperature.
MPSGraph automatically broadcasts
this scalar value to the vector length.
The result is then fed
into the softmax layer,
which gives us a probability distribution
for the next possible character.
We sample the distribution of predicted
characters from the softmax layer.
This gives us the index
of the next character,
which we can look up
in our index-to-character table.
Finally,
we move the newly generated result
as the input to the next iteration
to produce the next character.
Now let's see this network created
with MPSGraph in action.
We have implemented
an LSTM-based text generator network
with the new MPSGraph
that is running here in an app
on the iPad Pro.
MPSGraph allows our users
to implement these models,
and thanks to the flexibility
of the new graph interface,
it's easy to make tweaks to the models
to run experiments
and still enjoy
the benefits of optimized kernels.
The network has been trained
on a large text file
containing writings of Shakespeare
that we can see by clicking
the "Show Training DataSet" link
at the top.
Here we can see
a short excerpt of the text.
Now let's see if we can use the network
to generate Shakespearean-looking text.
We have set by default
the initial text to be "Romeo."
So let's see what happens
when we hit "Generate."
As we can see, the model is producing text
that looks like Shakespeare's texts,
at least to my untrained eye.
We can choose another initial word,
so let's type here "Juliet."
And hit "Generate" again.
Now the produced text
starts with the word "Juliet."
The length of the generated text can be
controlled by the slider at the bottom.
This will generate a longer piece of text.
We can also change
the temperature variable with a slider.
The reciprocal of this value
is used to multiply the input values
going into the softmax layer,
which creates a more smooth and flat
distribution for high-temperature values
and a more sharp distribution
for low-temperature values.
This has the effect
of making the sampling process
become more random with high temperatures
and less random with low temperatures.
Let's move the temperature slider
to about two
to see if it generates
more surprising text.
It does look more random to me. I'm unsure
if this is even proper English anymore.
Let's try setting it to three
and hit "Generate" again.
Okay, yeah. Now it's starting to look
like pure random letter soup.
I want to get back
to more conventional Shakespeare,
so let's move the temperature slider
back to 0.1 and see what happens.
Okay, that's better.
Now the model seems to be generating text
that resembles
the training data set more closely.
The MPSGraph not only enables us
to run these models in the graph,
it also enables the user to make a wide
variety of customizations to the models
while still enjoying the benefits
of tuned kernels
thanks to the stitching capabilities.
This allows support for a wide array
of models, enables rapid prototyping,
and reduces the amount of workarounds
and hacks needed to support a model.
That's all I have. Back to you, Dhruv.
Thanks, Chris.
We saw how easy and intuitive it was
to write custom compute functions
with MPSGraph.
Now let's look at features in MPSGraph
you can leverage to easily and optimally
train your neural networks.
The training process involves
repeatedly attempting
to execute the network on known data.
Each attempt updates
the set of parameters,
improving the ability of the network
to work correctly.
When the network works well,
the training process is stopped.
Now we can look at how to use
the new MPSGraph
to implement some of these ideas.
For the purposes of our talk,
we will implement
a simple digit classification network.
As we saw before,
for doing computations with the MPSGraph,
there are three major steps.
Here is our road map
to training our neural network.
The first and the last step
remain the same.
We will dive deeper into step two
and take a look
at what operations we must create
to train the parameters
of our neural network.
As before,
first we define our set of inputs.
We define placeholders for our inputs
and target labels.
We use -1 to specify a variable length
batchSize for our network.
Next, we must specify the trainable
parameters we spoke of before.
With MPSGraph, these parameters
are part of the graph itself.
As a simple example,
we will be looking at training
a single layered
convolution neural network.
This network has a set of weights
corresponding to the convolution
and biases to be added
to the result of the convolution.
These are the parameters
we would be updating
as part of the training process.
To specify these parameters,
we will utilize variable support
in the MPSGraph.
Variables retain values across graph runs,
so you do not need to pass these
as inputs to the graph for each iteration.
To create a variable,
we call the variable method on the graph,
providing initial values, shape,
and an element dataType.
Now that we have our parameters to train,
let's specify our forward pass,
which also happens to be
the inference network for our model.
First up, we look at how to create
a convolution layer.
Convolution layer is the workhorse
of the neural network,
where most of the computation occurs,
and the MPSGraphConvolution layer
supports numerous variants.
To create a convolution layer,
we first create a convolution descriptor.
Next, we pass this descriptor
to the convolution method on the graph.
We support numerous padding styles
on our convolution.
Developers can explicitly set padding
in height and width
or use convenience padding modes
SAME and VALID,
which apply padding
exactly like TensorFlow.
Sometimes tensor dimensions
have a semantic meaning
attached to them for convenience.
This is where MPSGraph
TensorNamedDataLayout helps.
It conveys which dimension
corresponds to what name,
like batch, channel, height or width.
MPSGraph supports NCHW and NHWC formats,
which are commonly used for image data
in TensorFlow and PyTorch.
Weights can also be specified
in multiple formats
like the OIHW format,
which has been used in MPS,
or the HWIO format used by
third-party frameworks like TensorFlow.
When it comes to passing the values of
our weight variables to the convolution,
we would utilize
the readVariable operation.
It returns a tensor
representing the value of the variable
at this point
during the execution of the graph.
In our training network,
we read the weights variable
and pass the returned tensor
to the convolution.
The convolution layer will use
the shape of the weights tensor passed in
to infer kernel sizes
and number of output feature channels.
MPSGraph provides the convenience
of not needing to explicitly call
the readVariable operation.
If the variable tensor
is directly passed to any operation,
the graph will implicitly add
readVariable operations
for your convenience.
For the bias after the convolution,
we will call the add node,
which implicitly supports broadcasting.
For nonlinearity, we apply
the rectified Linear Unit function,
which is a commonly used activation.
We reshape
the four-dimensional reLU output
to a two-dimensional tensor,
which happens to be the same shape
as our labels.
Its dimensions represent
an unknown batch size
and the number of classes to classify to,
which, in our case, are the ten digits.
Finally, we add a softMax layer
to estimate probabilities of each class.
We set the axis to be -1,
which helps us indicate
the fastest moving axis.
We have successfully defined
the forward pass for our neural network.
Now we define the loss function,
which we will try to minimize
to train our neural network.
We will use the commonly used
Softmax Cross Entropy loss function.
We define the loss
by passing in the labels
and the evaluated reshapeTensor.
We utilize reductionSum to accumulate
the losses across the batch
into a single scalar loss value.
Now that we have defined
our loss value to minimize,
we need to calculate the gradients
for the computed loss
with respect to the trainable parameters.
To do that, we must backpropagate
the gradients using the chain rule.
To begin our chain rule,
the first step is to calculate
the gradient of the loss with itself,
which happens to be 1.
After that,
we need to utilize gradient operations
and the other operations
available in the graph.
We use them to apply chain rule
by multiplying partial derivatives
of each layer all the way
till we get the gradients of the loss
with respect to each trainable parameter.
However,
MPSGraph provides a convenience method
which gives the gradients of a tensor
with respect to a list of tensors.
We call this automatic differentiation.
It automatically writes out
the backward pass of the graph
and returns a dictionary of tensors
and the corresponding gradients.
You can use the gradient method
to write out the gradient function
for even any basic math function.
We take a simple logarithm operation here
for our example.
The gradient method correctly creates
a reciprocal operation
as a partial derivative
and multiplies it
with the starting gradient
which, as we discussed, is always 1.
However, we end up
with a set of unused operations.
Once more,
the graph compiler helps us out here.
The graph is pruned to eliminate
any dead code whose results are unused,
and any constants like 1
are folded and eliminated.
So in the case of our neural network,
we would take the gradient
of the loss tensor
with respect to the weights
and the biases.
Once we have a gradient of loss
with respect to trainable parameters,
we can update the variables.
To calculate updates to the tensors,
we use the stochastic gradient
descent optimizer.
It takes in a learningRate,
the original weight value,
and the gradient for the weights
which we get by using
the gradients dictionary.
Finally, we use the assign variable
operation in the graph
to assign the new update tensor value
to the variable.
Final step is the same as before.
We wrote out our training graph,
and now we need to execute it.
Our training loop
is quite straightforward.
For each iteration,
we get a sample of training input images
and corresponding labels.
We pass these into the graph as feeds.
Then we request the lossTensor
be targeted and returned.
Every iteration, the weights
and bias variables would get updated,
since we also target
the assignment operations in the graph.
The graph compiles once
for each unique type of inputs and outputs
on the very first invocation,
and the executables are automatically
cached for any further iterations
to get the best performance.
MPSGraph also offers
asynchronous run methods.
This execution call is non-blocking
and will immediately return
without waiting for the GPU
to finish computing.
The optional executionDescriptor
can be utilized
to synchronize between the CPU
and the GPU.
We use one such synchronization method
on the descriptor.
Users can register
their completion handlers,
which will be called once the GPU
is finished executing the graph.
In the past years,
we have showcased the virtue
of overlapping CPU encoding
and the GPU execution.
The training iterations we execute
can use the same principles.
We create a semaphore with a value of 2.
We signal the semaphore
from the completion handler
of our execution descriptor.
Inside the loop, we wait on the semaphore,
and once through,
we asynchronously execute our graph
so it immediately returns.
For users who wish to integrate MPSGraph
into their existing Metal work flow,
MPSGraph offers
low-level execution methods
in which you can pass
your own existing MTLCommandQueues.
MPSGraph even provides MPS style ability
to encode the graph
on your MPSCommandBuffers.
Users can specify
their own results dictionary,
giving them fine-grained control
over their output allocations.
Now we go back to Chris.
He will show our digit classifier
training network in action.
Now that Dhruv has shown us
the new MPSGraph for training,
let's see how we can use it to implement
digit classification on an iPhone 11.
We have implemented
a simple convolutional neural network
using the new MPSGraph framework,
and we can use this to classify digits
drawn by a user.
Upon opening the app, we start off
with a completely untrained graph.
On the inference tab, we can see that
currently the network is doing a lousy job
trying to label these numbers.
It can't predict this 1.
Nor can it predict this zero.
But if I go back to the training tab,
I can press the "play" button
to kick off a small batch of training.
We use the auto differentiation feature
of MPSGraph to get weight gradients
and target operations
to update our weight variables
to easily implement training.
The loss for each iteration
is plotted at the top,
and we can see it going down
as the network is trained.
We train for only a few hundred iterations
with a small batch size,
and we already have almost 95% accuracy
on the test set.
Going back to the inference tab...
we can test our newly trained graph.
We can see it has already learned
to classify our inputs with good accuracy.
The new MPSGraph makes it easy to build
custom machine learning models,
and use them for both training
and inference.
This example of how you can use MPSGraph
to build, train,
and execute a digit classifier
will be available as sample code online.
Now back to Dhruv for more on training.
Thanks, Chris, for showing us the power
of the MPSGraph training on an iPhone.
MPSGraph adds the capability to support
even more sophisticated
neural network architectures.
Let's look at one such example.
This time, we want to create new sets
of real looking handwritten digits.
However, there is an issue.
There is no way for the machine
to determine
what constitutes
a real-looking handwritten digit.
The answer to our problem is competition.
Humans have for many years
used competition to better each other
and achieve heights of excellence
which they can't by themselves.
We do the same here,
training two neural networks
by making them compete against each other.
One tries to create handwritten digits
and the other tries
to evaluate its quality.
The first of our networks
is the generator, the artist.
Its purpose is to take
a random set of values as seed
and generate
a real-looking handwritten digit.
The generator network is quite simple.
We take our random set of values
and pass them through three stages
to progressively increase the image size
to create our handwritten digit.
Let's quickly go through
some of the new layers here.
Firstly,
we see some convolution transposes.
Convolution transpose is a unique layer
which derives from the gradient
of a convolution operation.
So for a stride two,
the output size would be twice as big
rather than half the size of the input.
To describe a convolution transpose,
we pass the descriptor
for the corresponding convolution
and the output shape we expect.
Another new-looking layer here
is batch normalization.
Normalization layers are
a very important part of neural networks.
They help us ensure our trained values
and their corresponding gradients
don't vanish or explode.
To normalize a tensor, we need to use
the statistics for the tensor.
MPSGraph has methods
to get mean and variance
of the tensor on selected axes.
The axes we choose
give us an opportunity to select
if we want batch normalization,
instance normalization,
or any other variant.
For batch normalization, we would choose
batch, height, and width dimensions.
Then we call the normalization layer
with trainable gamma and beta parameters.
The second layer is the discriminator,
our detective.
Its purpose is to take a handwritten digit
and classify it as real or fake.
We already saw how to write
classifier networks.
This network is very similar.
Only difference is that
instead of ten digits,
now we have one class to predict.
That is the realness
of the incoming image.
The discriminator has another new layer:
namely, dropout.
The dropout layer
randomly drops values of the input
by making them zero at a given rate.
At the same time, it boosts the rest
of the values by the inverse of the rate
to retain the energy
of the propagated features.
Now that we have looked
at the forward pass for both networks,
we'll look into training
for the two networks.
Let's start
with our discriminator network.
We control if we pass real or fake images
into the discriminator.
The discriminator's objective
is to predict the realness
of the incoming image,
so for real images, it should predict 1
for the probability of being real,
and for fake images,
it should predict a probability of zero.
For the generated images,
we subtract the discriminator result
from 1
to instead get the fakeness
of the input images.
We use the commonly used
cross entropy loss
to quantify how far our discriminator was
from the correct real or fake prediction.
Finally, we want to provide
the discriminator equal opportunity
to learn to classify real and fake images
without introducing bias.
So for each iteration, we pass
the same number of real and fake images
and add their losses together.
With the loss in hand,
we use the automatic differentiation
feature of the MPSGraph.
Notice how we ask for the gradients for
the list of discriminator variables only.
This is because we only wish to train
the discriminator in this pass.
We have the makings of a good detective.
Now let's look at training our artist
to generate realistic digits.
As we described before,
we use the discriminator to quantify
how realistic our generated image is.
The generator will try to learn
to fool the discriminator
into predicting
that the generated image is real.
And once more,
we use the cross entropy loss
to quantify how far
the probability of being real was.
We use this generator loss
to get the gradients.
Notice again, we only get the gradients
for the generator variables.
This is because
we don't want the discriminator
to learn to predict fake images as real.
MPSGraph will automatically differentiate
through both networks
and return gradients
for the generator variables only.
With the gradients for both networks,
we can update the variables just as before
by applying optimizers.
And now we see how to execute
the training for the two networks.
MPSGraph makes it really easy to execute.
We simply pass both losses as targets
and request both the generator
and discriminator update operations
in a single run call.
The MPSGraph will compile and optimize
across both networks
and execute them together.
We just saw how easy it was to write out
two networks within a single MPSGraph
and execute them together
with a single execution call.
Let's ask Chris
to generate some digits for us.
Hello again.
Now that we know how these networks work,
let's see them in action on our iPad Pro.
I'll hit the "play" button
on the "train" tab to begin training.
On the top, we
see the loss for the generator network
and the bottom shows the loss
for the discriminator network.
In the center, we can see images
generated by the generator network,
and as the networks train,
we will see these generated numbers
start to resemble digits.
Just like we saw
in the digit classifier demo,
we use the auto differentiation feature
of MPSGraph to update the trainable layers
in both the generator
and discriminator networks.
Both networks are trained
using a single MPSGraph.
We can see these networks
are already battling each other,
but it'll take time before the generator
is able to produce believable digits.
We can pause this training...
and jump to the "inference" tab
to test the networks
after they have trained
for a few hundred epochs.
Here we see a 5, 9.
I don't know what that is.
7, 9.
They look like digits to me.
All of this is running on an iPad Pro
using MPSGraph.
Okay, back to Dhruv.
Thanks again, Chris.
In summary,
we introduced the new MPSGraph framework.
We learned how to write and execute
custom compute functions using MPSGraph.
We saw how the MPSGraph compiler
stitches and optimizes operations
across your entire graph
to give the best performance.
And finally, we saw how easy it is
to train neural networks using MPSGraph
with support for features like variables
and automatic differentiation.
Thank you for listening.
Please check out
our sample code and documentation,
and have a great WWDC.