Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello everyone. My name is Michael Kent,
and I'm a ClockKit engineer.
In this session, we'll be talking about
complications on Apple Watch
and how you can add them to your app.
Complications are a great way to
get your content in front of your users.
They're easily glanceable
right on the clock face.
With watchOS 7,
we've made it even easier than ever
to create a great complication experience,
and that's why
complications are as important
as the app experience on the watch.
They're the easiest way
to get your content in front of the user.
How can you add them to your app?
We'll be talking about timelines,
which are
the backing structure of complications,
all the bits and pieces
you need to get going,
how you can get your data
into complications,
how you can utilize
a new watchOS 7 feature
to provide more than one complication
from your app,
and we'll run through an example.
We'll start out talking about timelines.
Timelines play a central role
in complications.
They're a representation
of your complication's data over time.
Since a timeline provides
all of your complication's data,
ClockKit can ask your app once
for all the information needed
to drive your complication
automatically through a date you specify.
Of course, if you get new data in your app
and need to give us more entries,
you can ask ClockKit
to extend your timeline
or completely invalidate it.
I've been working with some teammates
to develop an app
to track whale sightings around Hawaii.
In the app,
you can see recent whale sightings
at several viewing stations around Maui.
Let's look at an example of a timeline
that might come from this app.
Here I've got a schedule
of whale-watching tours,
three throughout the day
at different locations.
Now here's how it might look
as a timeline presented to ClockKit.
There are a few differences you'll notice.
First, each tour is associated
with only one time rather than a range.
This is because
your complication will show an entry
until the date of the next one.
Second, you'll see that the times
associated with each tour
are earlier than their actual start time.
This is so that a user has
a bit of a heads-up
in order to catch the boat for the tour
on time if they're interested.
Not all types of data
would behave like this.
A temperature forecast, for example,
would want to have entries
right at each forecasted time.
Up top is the data I'd like to show
in this complication at the current time.
And as that progresses throughout the day,
you can see the information updates
as the time changes
until there are no more tours for today.
Now, let's get into
how you actually specify
what you want your complications
to display.
Families of complications are how we break
them up into different visual groups.
The graphic families
were introduced in watchOS 5,
with the exception
of the Graphic Extra Large,
which is new in watchOS 7.
These families allow for more
visually oriented presentations of data.
Different watch faces
use different complication families.
Here are some examples.
The Infograph face uses Graphic Corner
and Graphic Bezel
as well as Graphic Circular,
which is also
on the Infograph Modular face,
along with Graphic Rectangular.
This is Graphic Extra Large, which is
now supported on the Extra Large face.
Modular Small and Modular Large
on the Modular face,
Utilitarian Small Flat on the Motion face,
Utilitarian Small and Large
on the Utility face,
and lastly, Extra Large,
which is used on the Extra Large face
if your complication doesn't support
the Graphic Extra Large family.
This family is always used on
the Extra Large face for Series 3 watches.
Ideally, you will want to support
as many complication families as you can
for your complications.
This way, all of your users
will be able to use your complications
on whichever face they prefer.
Complication templates represent
different visual layouts within families.
Here's an example
of just some of the complication templates
available in a few different families.
Despite being associated
with a specific family,
each template inherits
from a common base class,
CLKComplicationTemplate.
There are a lot of options to choose from
to best represent the data
that you want to show.
You can find out more about
what's available
in the documentation
on the Developer website.
Now let's look at a brief example of what
the code looks like to supply a timeline.
The first type I want to talk about
is CLKComplicationTimelineEntry.
You populate your complication's timeline
by giving us a list of these.
Each represents
what your complication should look like
at a certain point in time.
It only has two properties:
date, which is the date
that this entry should be visible at,
and complicationTemplate,
which is the template containing the data
you want to display for this entry.
Going back to our timeline example
from before,
at 6:00 a.m., we'll have a timeline entry
populated with the date, 6:00 a.m.,
and a complicationTemplate representing
the Ma'alaea Harbor Tour.
At 9:00 a.m.,
the date and template change,
as well as throughout the rest of the day.
Your main interaction with ClockKit
is through an object you create
that conforms to
CLKComplicationDataSource.
There's only one required method
in this protocol:
getCurrentTimelineEntry
for complication withHandler.
You can implement this
by simply calling the handler
with the current timeline entry
for the given complication.
We'll talk more about
what this complication is later.
For some complications,
a current entry is enough,
like the current score in a baseball game
or the current Apple stock price.
But if your complication can provide
a timeline with entries in the future,
you'll need to implement
these two methods as well:
getTimelineEndDate
for complication withHandler,
which specifies how far in the future
you can provide entries,
and getTimelineEntries for complication
after date limit withHandler.
That's a bit of a mouthful,
but all you need to do
is provide as many entries
as is appropriate for the data you have
up to the limit after the given date.
The date represents the last
timeline entry that we already have,
and the limit is so that we only get
as many entries as we need at one time.
If you provide more, we'll drop
all of the entries over the limit.
What if your app gets new data,
and you need to reload your timeline?
We've got two options.
First, if your data changes completely,
and all of the entries you provided
are invalid,
you can call
reloadTimeline for complication
on the shared instance
of CLKComplicationServer.
For example, if an unexpected storm
came through Maui,
all our whale-watching tours
would be canceled,
and we'd want to invalidate
our whole timeline to reflect that.
But if your previously provided entries
are still valid,
and you just want to let us know
you can provide more,
call extendTimeline for complication.
ClockKit only keeps track of timelines
for complications that are currently
on the user's watch face.
We let you know about these
via the activeComplications property.
You don't ever create
CLKComplication objects directly.
You always get them from here
or passed into a data source method
you implement.
Now let's talk about what really goes into
creating these complication templates.
Complications have several limitations:
Watch screens are small,
complications are smaller.
You may want to display the same string
in different templates
or families of complications,
all with very different
layout constraints.
To give the best possible experience,
we have a concept called data providers.
These allow you to consistently
express the same information
in many different locations and contexts,
formatted for you by ClockKit.
Since we take care
of the specific layout details
of complications on your behalf,
we need enough information
to do so flexibly.
Let me show you what I mean.
We'll start with some text.
Watches are all about time,
so showing a date is something
you may want to do often.
Here's a nice way
to write out a long date.
But in most complication contexts,
you'd end up with something like this.
That's not very clear what it's saying.
So how can we do better?
You would use a data provider
called CLKDateTextProvider.
You declare what you would like,
in this case, "Wednesday, September 23,"
and we'll do the best we can to show it.
But if space is constrained, we'll start
falling back to shorter versions...
eventually dropping
less-useful information like the weekday,
and if needed,
all the way down to the day of the month.
Here's what that would look like in code.
You create a CLKDateTextProvider
by giving it a date
and the calendar units you'd prefer
in the longest case.
What about if you wanted
to answer questions like,
"How far is my date
from the current time?"
Or "How far is my date
from some other date?"
You could use
a CLKRelativeDateTextProvider.
In the case of the first question,
a relative date text provider
will auto-update its text
for whatever the current time is.
This can be accurate down to the second
with no extra work on your part.
You can use it for different formats,
displaying strings like this,
the time from now until sunset,
or this: how much longer is left for
the dough you're making to finish rising.
In the latter case, you'd create it
by providing an end date,
specifying the "timer" style
and giving the units you'd like displayed.
Here are some other text providers,
like the time text provider,
which acts very similarly
to the date text provider
but shows a time rather than a day,
time interval text provider,
which can be used to show
a range of time, like 7:30 to 9:00 a.m.,
and lastly, simple text provider,
which displays any string you'd like.
You can also give it a shorter version
of that string to fall back on
in contexts where space is constrained.
Image providers
are a lot like text providers
in that the data they contain can be used
across several different contexts.
The big difference is that these contexts
are more focused
on the color of the watch face.
Many watch faces allow users
to customize this attribute,
and complications
need to match consistently.
Some watch faces apply a single color
to the whole image of the complication,
and others allow a more multicolor image,
composed of a background and foreground.
You can see some here on the bottom:
timer, sunrise and stopwatch.
CLKImageProvider is the object
that makes this possible.
The graphic complication families
allow displaying full-color images,
so their templates ask for
CLKFullColorImageProviders.
However, these graphic complications
are tinted in some contexts.
If you only provide a full-color image,
we'll desaturate it for you
to apply this tint color.
If instead
you want to override this behavior,
CLKFullColorImageProvider
allows you to set
a CLKImageProvider to fall back on.
You can see here
that by providing the same image
with a CLKImageProvider,
the complication appears brighter,
with the same white color as
the other complications on the top left.
For more about adapting
to complication tinting,
check out this great talk from 2019.
Gauge providers are a way
to encapsulate the data necessary
to show a graphical gauge or progress.
These adapt
to different complication layouts,
like those seen here,
in both the corners and the center.
You can customize the color
or gradient of the gauge,
as well as the fill fraction,
all with minimal work on your part.
If you want a gauge that updates
its fill fraction in real time,
you can use
a CLKTimeIntervalGaugeProvider,
which lets you specify
a start and end date,
and it'll be updated automatically
to show the progress at the current time.
New in watchOS 7,
you can use SwiftUI in complications.
All of the complication templates
that use CLKFullColorImageProviders
have SwiftUI view alternatives.
You can easily reuse components
from other parts of your app,
and it's even easier than ever
to stand out
and create unique complications
to engage your users.
If you want to learn more
about using SwiftUI in complications,
we've got a wonderful session
that covers this in depth.
What if your app is full of useful,
relevant information to your users,
and you want to provide them
quick, easy access to all of it?
Also new in watchOS 7,
you can now provide multiple complications
from a single app.
This is a great way to get your data
in front of your users
at a quick glance down to their wrist.
You can even fill a watch face
with your own complications and share it.
Multiple complication support
is declared in your implementation
of CLKComplicationDataSource.
There are two relevant methods:
getComplicationDescriptors withHandler,
which specifies the current list
of complications that your app supports...
and handleShared
ComplicationDescriptors,
which will be called when a watch face
containing some of your complications
was shared with this watch
in order to give you a heads-up
that ClockKit will start asking
for timeline entries for them.
A CLKComplicationDescriptor
is how you define a complication.
It consists of an identifier
unique within your app...
a displayName, which will be shown
during watch face editing,
a list of complication families
that this complication supports,
and two optional
and mutually exclusive properties
that allow you to include custom data
for your use later:
a userInfo dictionary or a userActivity.
Our Whale Watch app has support for
a few different kinds of complications:
some for the number of whale sightings
at each location,
a complication
to quickly log a new sighting,
and a complication to show
the overall season data.
Let's look at how this works.
In the getComplicationDescriptors
withHandler method,
you'll create an array
of ComplicationDescriptors
and use it to call the handler.
Here, we iterate through each station
in our data model,
creating a ComplicationDescriptor
for each.
These will be used to show
sighting information at each location.
Next, we add a descriptor
for a complication
to log a new whale sighting
and one to view overall season data.
You'll notice that this last complication
only supports
the graphicRectangular family,
while the others supported all families.
Since the season data complication
will display a lot of information,
the large canvas
of the graphicRectangular family
is the only one that made sense
for this complication.
If you ever need to invalidate this list,
you can call
reloadComplicationDescriptors
on CLKComplicationServer,
and we'll call this method again.
In our Whale Watch example,
maybe we only show complications
for the user's favorite viewing stations.
If they update those, we'll want to
update the complications as well.
If you ever update this list
to remove support for a complication
that a user
currently has on their watch face,
we'll continue to ask you for
timeline entries for that complication.
Do your best to ensure
that you can continue to provide
useful information in this case.
Note that this method is different
from CLKComplicationServer's
reloadTimelineForComplication method.
This reloads the list of complications
your app offers,
where the other reloads
a specific complication's timeline.
Just like always,
when a user taps your complication,
we'll launch your app.
If the tapped complication's descriptor
was created with a userActivity,
then it will be used when launching it.
In either case, we pass some entries
in the userInfo dictionary:
the date of the complication's
currently visible timeline entry
as well as the complication's identifier.
And of course, this dictionary contains
developer-specified entries
defined in the complicationDescriptor
as well.
We've talked about how to describe
your supported complications,
but how do you know what complication
ClockKit is asking for
timeline entries for?
Here are a couple methods
that we saw earlier:
getCurrentTimelineEntry
and getTimelineEndDate.
Each takes a complication parameter
of type CLKComplication.
This looks a lot
like a complicationDescriptor.
However, where a complicationDescriptor
defines what a complication supports,
this object represents a specific,
concrete instance
of a complication on a user's watch face.
So instead of a list
of supported families,
it has a property containing the family
of the real complication instance.
And of course, the information
you provided in the descriptor
with a userInfo dictionary
or a userActivity
is contained here as well.
We have something called
the default complication identifier.
Is this something you should be using
to identify one of your complications?
Sure, you could,
but that's not its main purpose.
If you had a complication
before watchOS 7,
and a user has it on their watch face,
or if a user shares a watch face
with your complication
but chooses to remove the associated data,
then you'll get asked about
a complication with the identifier
CLKDefaultComplicationIdentifier
even if you don't explicitly support it
in your list of complication descriptors.
This is very important.
You should support this complication.
If not, your users will be wondering
why they're seeing a broken complication
on their watch face
that says it's from your app.
So how can you do that?
You could display the same information
as your complication did before watchOS 7,
or maybe you could choose to show
the most popular or relevant information
from your app,
or you could just show your app icon,
so at the very least,
the user knows what the complication is
and has an idea of what would happen
if they tapped on it.
Now let's look at more of the specifics
of our whale-watching app.
We saw this method before.
It creates the current entry
for the given complication.
Here's another method
that we haven't looked at yet:
getLocalizableSampleTemplate
for complication withHandler
is also a part of
the CLKComplicationDataSource protocol.
The template it's asking for
will be used while selecting complications
in face editing
as well as in the Apple Watch app
on the paired iPhone.
This template should contain sample data,
as we only ask for it once
per complication and cache the result.
We've seen this createTimelineEntry
method used a few times now.
It's pretty simple. It creates a template
and then a timeline entry with
that template and the date passed into it.
Let's take a closer look
at the createTemplate method.
We first grab some data that we'll need
to reuse while creating templates.
We pull the station information
from the complication.
Remember,
we created the descriptors with it.
And we create a FullColorImageProvider
to use in a few different cases.
And we create a SimpleTextProvider
for logging a sighting.
Lastly, we create a closure that returns
a default template for a given family
that we can fall back on
if something unexpected happens,
like being asked for a template
for the default complication identifier.
To determine which template to create,
we switch on both the family
and the identifier.
For the SeasonData complication
in Graphic Rectangular,
we create
a GraphicRectangularFullView template,
which has a SwiftUI view displaying
a nice visual chart of the data.
For the "log a sighting" complication
in graphicCircular,
we create
a GraphicCircularStackImage template
with our ImageProvider
and TextProvider that we created earlier.
For any other kind
of graphicCircular complication,
we want to show another SwiftUI view
that displays information
about the sightings at that location.
GraphicCorner and GraphicExtraLarge
are also very similar,
each returning a complication template
containing corresponding text
and imageProviders from the station data.
There are a lot of other cases here
to correctly provide a template
for each complication supported,
but since they're all similar,
I won't go into all the details here.
But of course, if we are getting asked
about a complication
we don't think we can do anything about,
like the default complication identifier,
we'll just return a default template.
Here's how some of those complications
look in action.
We have two different kinds
of Graphic Rectangular complications,
two kinds of Graphic Circular,
we used SwiftUI
to draw these beautiful charts,
and the complications look great
in both full-color and tinted contexts.
In watchOS 7,
there are so many opportunities
to get your data in front of your users
right on their watch face.
So make some complications,
provide your data in a timeline
to keep your complication up to date,
create great, customized
complication content with SwiftUI,
and make sure you support
the default complication identifier
for when you get asked about them.
If you're looking for more information
on building great complications,
here are some other sessions
you can check out.
Thanks for joining me.