Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. My name is James Kelly,
and I'm a member of the Game Technologies
engineering team at Apple.
In this video, we'll be talking
about new game controller features
and changes coming
to our platforms this year,
and we'll give some advice on how
you can best adopt these new changes.
As a reminder,
the Game Controller framework
has a goal
to make it easy to add support for MFi
and select third-party game controllers
to your games on iOS, tvOS and macOS.
By abstracting controller hardware
through a common API,
the Game Controller framework
lets you write your code once
without you having to worry
about how that controller data is mapped.
This year, we're making sure
you can take advantage of and customize
the great features of game controllers
like haptics and rumble, motion, lights,
as well as unique inputs
like touch pads and paddles.
We'll also show how users
can remap their controllers globally
or tune it to their game
to get just the configuration they want.
Before we start,
we're excited to announce some additions
to our supported lineup
of great controllers.
First up, we've added support for the Xbox
Elite Wireless Controller Series 2.
It's got a really great feel, and it's
been highly requested by our users.
We're also really excited to announce
support for the Xbox Adaptive Controller.
This unique, extensible controller helps
to make gaming more accessible for all.
Developers are creating some great games
with controller support.
Oceanhorn 2, Sonic Racing, Spyder
and LEGO Brawls
are some excellent examples
on Apple Arcade
and just a few of the games on
the App Store that support controllers.
By using the Game Controller framework,
these games automatically support
newly added controllers
like the Xbox Adaptive Controller
or the Xbox Elite Wireless Controller
Series 2.
Let's talk about changes coming to
the Game Controller framework this year
in support of these new controllers.
Let's start by talking
about how you can access the buttons
of these new controllers.
There's a new way
to access controller input this year,
GCPhysicalInputProfile,
which represents the collection of all
physical inputs available on a controller,
meaning its buttons, triggers, Dpads,
thumbsticks and so on.
We're calling this
the new extensible input API
as it allows your game
to dynamically query and support
all of a controller's inputs at runtime,
even nonstandard inputs,
like the DUALSHOCK 4's touch pad
or the Xbox Elite controller's
paddle buttons.
Every controller
now has a physical input profile.
So, GCExtendedGamepad
and GCMicroGamepad
have both been made subclasses
of this GCPhysicalInputProfile.
You're encouraged to still check
for the presence of profiles
like GCExtendedGamepad
to filter out controllers
that don't have the buttons you need.
You can then use
the physical input profile
to access the controller's unique buttons,
like the DUALSHOCK 4's touch pad.
Let's take a look at a coding sample
to get a sense of these changes.
Let's say we want to add
some special shortcuts
for controllers with extra buttons.
First, we'll add an action that can
instantly trigger an attack combo
which would normally require
a combination of button presses.
We'll also track the buttons
on the controller
that we have
and have not mapped to actions.
Now let's look
at setupConnectedController
that is called when a controller connects.
We grab a reference to the physical
input profile on the controller.
Remember that every controller
will have this profile.
We have a helper function,
setupBasicControls,
that will set up all the standard controls
for the face buttons,
the left and right thumbsticks,
the Dpad, etcetera,
and it will also update mapped buttons.
Using that physical input profile,
we can then easily grab a reference
to a paddle button, if one exists,
and update our mappedButtons set.
Finally, we can look at all of the buttons
available on the physical input profile
and filter out any buttons
that have already been mapped.
We can use this to populate an in-game
mapping UI with a list of unused buttons.
So, for ease of use, we've added two new
subclasses to the GCExtendedGamepad,
GCDualShockGamepad,
and GCXboxGamepad.
The DualShockGamepad exposes the touch
pad surface with two-finger tracking
as well as the touch pad's button.
The XboxGamepad
exposes the four paddle buttons
of the Xbox Elite Wireless Controller.
Use extra buttons to augment your games
with additional convenience controls,
but avoid requiring these buttons
as other controllers don't have them.
One quick note about the paddle buttons
on the Xbox Elite
Wireless Controller Series 2.
The controller supports
hardware button remapping
which can be configured and then stored
in one of three profiles.
The selected profile is indicated by the
three LEDs on the front of the controller.
And due to how the controller sends data,
the paddle buttons will only work
when the controller does not have
a button mapping profile selected,
meaning that the three LEDs are unlit.
[vibrating]
Up next,
let's talk about haptics and rumble,
one of the most exciting additions
to the API this year.
Games coordinate visuals, sounds
and haptics from the controller
to more deeply immerse the player.
Great haptics can help give a sense
that your car is driving over gravel,
that your character
is walking through sand,
that you feel a recoil
in your trigger finger,
or even that a nearby explosion
is shaking your room.
Many of our supported controllers
can provide haptic feedback,
including the DUALSHOCK 4,
the Xbox Wireless Controller
and the Xbox Elite Wireless Controller,
and that feedback is programmable,
meaning that you have fine-grained control
over the low-level haptic feeling
that is played.
These controllers all use
different hardware for generating haptics.
So, let's talk about how you can
easily add haptic feedback to your game
without having to worry about
the physical details of each controller.
This year we're happy to add
Game Controller support to Core Haptics
on top of the existing
phone haptic support.
Core Haptics is a powerful API that allows
you to compose and play haptic patterns
to customize your app's haptic feedback.
In Core Haptics,
you can craft custom haptic patterns
from basic building blocks
called haptic events.
These patterns
can be created programmatically
or stored in Apple Haptic
and Audio Pattern-- or AHAP files.
After designing your haptic patterns,
you simply create pattern players
from a haptic engine
to play your haptic content.
Core Haptics and AHAP allows you to design
your haptic content once
and then play it everywhere,
be it a phone, a DUALSHOCK 4
or any one of our other supported devices.
For more information on the details
of the Core Haptics framework,
including some excellent examples
on how to design AHAP content,
please watch "Introducing Core Haptics"
from WWDC 2019.
Let's look at a simple practical example.
Haptic feedback is a great way
to immerse players in a game
and let them really feel the impact
of their gameplay.
Let's say we have a player and an enemy
in an action game.
When the enemy attacks the player,
they're dealt damage
and the controller rumbles.
How do we achieve this in our game
using the Game Controller
and Core Haptics frameworks?
First, we need to design
our haptic content.
Here we've programmatically created
a haptic pattern called "enemy strike"
that will play when an enemy attacks.
We can then feed this data
into a CHHapticPattern.
Once we have our haptic content designed
and loaded into a pattern,
we can get ready to play it.
But how do we play it on a controller?
First, we need a GCController instance,
here representing the Xbox
Elite Controller shown on the right.
Next, we can create a CHHapticEngine
that targets the locations on a controller
that we'd like to play haptics on.
A haptic engine is just an object
that manages your apps' requests
to play haptic patterns.
Finally, we can create
a CHHapticPatternPlayer
from our engine and our pattern.
Once we call start on this pattern player,
our AHAP content
will play on our controller.
In this case, just the handles.
You can even layer these pattern players.
The system
will automatically combine the haptics
from all active patterns for you
at runtime
allowing you to create
some really dynamic effects.
So, how do you create a haptic engine?
Simply call createEngineWithLocality
on a controller instance
then pass in a GCHapticLocality.
This locality defines
the physical locations on the controller
that the haptic engine will target.
The default haptic locality
is geared towards providing
a haptic experience
that your users would expect.
For example, on game controllers,
the default locality
typically targets the handles.
You can get more specific if you'd like.
Here we're targeting
just the left impulse trigger.
So, how do we put all this together?
Let's look at a code example.
We begin by creating an instance
of a CHHapticEngine,
one that targets the handles
of the active controller.
The engine is assigned to our member
variable so we can keep it around.
After creating the haptic engine,
we'll need to start it
and check for possible errors.
The engine will continue to run
until the application
or possible outside action stops it.
So, let's play some haptics.
Here's the function that executes when
the player is dealt damage by an enemy.
In this example,
you want to generate a haptic pattern
that scales with the amount of damage
that was dealt.
So, we have to create the pattern player
and its pattern
at the moment they're needed
to account for this damage.
Once the pattern player is created,
we start it
at time CHHapticTimeImmediate,
which indicates that we want to play it
with minimal latency.
If you had two separate haptic players
that you wanted to synchronize,
you would need to specify
an actual time here.
Notice that the app does not hold on
to the instance of the player.
Its pattern is guaranteed
to continue playing until it's finished,
so we can simply fire and forget it.
Let's look at creating a pattern player.
This method is responsible
for creating the custom haptic content
that will play when we take damage.
We'll create a continuous haptic event
that applies over a specified duration.
We'll give it a sharpness and intensity.
This will provide a nice baseline
of haptic feedback
regardless of how much damage
was done to the player.
Next, we create a transient haptic event.
These are brief impulses
that occur at a specific point in time,
such as the click you would feel
from toggling a switch.
Note that the transient events
don't have a specified duration.
They're just the shortest haptic event
that you can produce,
so the actual time a transient takes
will vary from controller to controller.
Again, we set the sharpness and intensity.
This time, we scale the intensity
by the amount of damage
that was dealt to the player.
Next, we create the pattern
containing these two events.
Finally, we create the pattern player
from this pattern and return it.
Okay. So, now that you saw how easy it was
to generate haptic content
in Core Haptics,
let's talk about how you can transition
your existing rumble code
from other platforms.
In many existing games, haptics are tied
directly to the update loop.
This typically means that, every update,
the engine will set the intensity
of each physical actuator
on a game controller directly.
With this approach, the engine combines
different haptic effects each frame.
Let's talk
about how you can migrate a game
that uses this architecture
to Core Haptics.
Our goal is to update the intensities
of the controller's motors each frame.
To achieve this,
we'll need to create a pattern player
so we can send changes to it.
And then we'll create
a long-running pattern
with an initial haptic intensity
set to one.
In our update loop, we'll just change
the intensity of the motors.
To do this, we create a dynamic parameter
with a haptic intensity
we calculated for a given motor,
and then we send it to the pattern player.
We can do this each frame.
And as long as our updates
are fast enough,
the user will feel a continuous change
in the haptic intensity.
Let's take a quick look
at how we can achieve this in code.
Here, we're setting up
all the pieces you need
to be able to update your controller's
motors in your update loop.
We're setting up our pattern player,
which will later send new intensities
to each update.
In this function, we'll create
a long-running, continuous haptic event
with a haptic intensity
set to the max value of one.
We'll use the continuous event
to create a haptic pattern.
And finally, we'll create our pattern
player and start it immediately.
You'll need to hold onto this
as you'll be using it later.
Now, in our update loop,
we're also going to update our haptics.
This is where we update
the intensity of our motors.
We create a dynamic parameter
targeting haptic intensity.
These are similar to the parameters
used to generate events,
except these could be applied dynamically
to an already running pattern,
and they apply to the entire pattern,
not just the single event.
Here, hapticEngineMotorIntensity
represents the intensity of the motor
from zero to one
as calculated by the engine
for this frame.
This will act as a multiplier
on the pattern player's intensity.
We finish up by sending
our dynamic intensity parameter
to our pattern player.
Please note that this example only covers
one CHHapticEngine.
You will need to repeat
this approach for each motor
if you would like to control them
independently from one another.
Next up, let's talk about
some other features that we've added
to the Game Controller framework this year
that will help you fully utilize
the extended capabilities
of newly supported controllers.
Let’s start by looking at a situation
that single player games
frequently need to handle.
Your game launches, and you see
multiple controllers connected.
Particularly with the Apple TV,
it’s common to see the Siri Remote
and a game controller,
but which one should you take input from?
How do you know which controller
is currently being used by the player?
You could register your controller
connection and disconnection handlers
and manage the life cycles
of the controllers.
But you still need to track
when a controller becomes active
to update the UI and controls
as the user switches
between input devices.
This is why we are introducing
some new API to handle this for you.
We've added the current property
to GCController,
which always returns
the most recently used controller
or nil if no controller is connected.
We've also added
two new notifications that you can observe
to properly respond
to the current controller changing,
GCControllerDidBecomeCurrent
and GCControllerDidStopBeingCurrent.
Single player games should adapt
to the currently active game controller
by using this property.
By listening to the notifications,
you can easily adapt your UI
to reflect the currently used controller.
Next, let's talk about the motion sensors
on the DualShock 4.
The DualShock 4 has a gyroscope,
meaning that it knows
its rotation rate and 3D space,
allowing for some great
game play possibilities.
One common technique
is to use the gyroscope
for fine-tuned camera aiming,
with the thumbsticks used
for more coarse aiming.
The DualShock 4 also has an accelerometer.
There are many ways
to use the accelerometer.
For example, you can detect
whether the controller is tilted
to the left or the right
for driving controls in a racing game
or you can interpret high, rapid shifts
in acceleration as a shake gesture
to make your player character attack.
We've introduced support
for the DualShock 4's motion sensors
via GCMotion, a property on GCController.
For those of you familiar with supporting
the Siri Remote on tvOS,
we're using the same API here,
but with a few tweaks.
When supporting the DualShock 4,
you need to manually
turn the motion sensors on and off
to preserve battery.
You can query whether you need
to manage the sensors yourself
or leave it up to the system,
like with the Siri Remote.
Set motion.sensorsActive
to toggle motion sensors on and off.
Additionally, some controllers,
like the DualShock 4,
do not separate gravity
from user acceleration
and only report
the total acceleration of the controller.
Query whether the connected controller
has the ability to separate
gravity from user acceleration
and if it doesn't,
use the total acceleration instead.
The next feature I wanna tell you about
is the DualShock 4's light bar.
It's usually used as a player indicator,
but you can also use it for game effects.
For example, it could flash
a different color
when the player walks into lava
or shine green, then yellow, then red
as the player loses health.
We've surfaced support
for the DualShock 4's light bar
via GCDeviceLight,
a property on GCController.
It's easy to change the color
of a DualShock 4 light bar,
just set the GCDeviceLight color value.
Here, we are setting the color to red.
Nowadays, many controllers are wireless
and may need charging.
We're making battery state
available to you
so that you can show it in your UI,
particularly in low-battery situations.
This is provided via GCDeviceBattery,
a property on GCController.
You can check the level of the battery,
as well as its charging state,
whether it's charging,
discharging or fully charged.
You can then use
Key-Value Observing, or KVO,
to monitor any changes to the battery.
Now, I'd like to introduce
my colleague, Hannah Gillis,
who will give some tips
on how to take advantage
of our new input remapping feature.
Thanks, James.
Let's talk about how you can indicate
that your app supports game controllers
and the benefits that come along
when you do so.
There are a few reasons
to indicate controller support.
First, it surfaces information
on the App Store
and on Apple TV to communicate to users
when a controller is required
for an application.
A game controller badge
will be listed on the apps product page
to visually declare this info.
Second, indicating controller support
provides the ability
for input remapping in your application,
which I'll discuss shortly.
For these reasons, we highly recommend
you update your apps
for the best user experience.
To indicate controller support,
you should enable
the Game Controllers capability in Xcode.
This informs the system that your app
uses Game Controller features.
Once enabled, you can take advantage
of many associated benefits.
As mentioned, one of these benefits
is game controller input remapping.
And I'm excited to tell you
about this feature in both iOS and tvOS.
Have you ever played a game and wished
the buttons were configured differently?
For example, maybe you are
in an open world,
you have a controller in your hand
and want your character to look up.
What direction do you push the joystick?
Well, depending on your preference,
you might actually want
to invert the Y axis
if it better matches your intuition.
This is called input remapping
and it's incredibly powerful
for allowing users to customize
their gaming experience.
Additionally, it empowers
our accessibility community
to enjoy gaming the way they want.
In iOS 14 and tvOS 14,
we have created a method
to support input remapping
even if it's not built
directly into your app.
There are two ways you can
take advantage of input remapping.
The first is globally,
meaning any button customizations
will apply to all
game controller apps on your device.
The second is per-application.
It allows you to specify
different remapping
for an individual app.
Both of these options are available
if you've indicated
game controller support in Xcode.
Let's take a look at how a user
will experience input remapping.
In iOS 14, start by connecting
one of our supported game controllers
via Bluetooth.
Go to Settings and tap General,
where you will now see Game Controller.
Tap Game Controller to see
your currently connected device.
Then tap Customizations
to choose the button
you want to customize.
I want to remap the R1 button,
so I'll select that.
Let's remap this to the L1 button.
Now, if you go back,
you can see the R1 button
is remapped to the L1 button.
Remember our joystick example?
You can invert
the joystick axis here as well.
Simply click Left Stick
and then toggle Invert Vertically.
Now, let's say you want to add
custom remapping
for just one specific app.
You can do this by selecting Add App
and choosing one of your
game controller supported apps
to remap as needed.
These customizations will only apply
to the app you have selected
rather than all game controller apps
you might have.
We have input remapping available
in tvOS 14 as well.
It can be found under Settings,
Remotes and Devices, Bluetooth.
Then simply select
your connected controller
for customization.
So now that you know how global
and per-app input remapping
work for the user,
how can you adopt this in your game?
To support global remapping,
you simply need to use
the Game Controller framework
we reviewed earlier.
This ensures the benefit
of input remapping
across all apps on the device.
For per-application remapping,
you should additionally check the box
called Extended Gamepad
in the Game Controller section of Xcode.
This allows users to apply
unique customizations
to your app specifically.
If a user has applied input remapping,
you can make sure your in-game UI
and tutorials reflect this,
along with other controller scenarios
your player might encounter.
To enable this, we have added
game controller input glyphs
to SF Symbols in iOS 14.
You no longer need to generate
art assets on your own.
And Apple keeps this library
of glyphs accurate
for all controllers that are supported
today and in the future.
Like all SF Symbols,
you can choose different weights
for your game controller glyphs.
And to match the look
and feel of your game,
you can chose light and dark mode glyphs,
as well as tinted colors
to go with your design.
To learn more, check out
"Introducing SF Symbols"
from WWDC 2019.
To find the correct glyph
that matches the player's input,
you can look
at the SF Symbols name property
of the GCController element.
This works for the button, axis,
joystick, trigger or shoulder button.
Here, if I want to display
the corresponding glyph
for the classic Y button,
it'll return the Y in a circle glyph
if the input device is an MFi
or Xbox controller,
or the triangle in a circle glyph,
if the input device is a DualShock 4.
And, of course, we made sure
that the UI accurately reflects
any global or per-application
button remapping
your player has chosen to do.
For example, say the player
remaps the Y button to the X button,
when you reference
the Y button in your game,
it will display
the X in a circle glyph in the UI.
Your game and your UI
are easily responsive
to input remapping decisions like these.
And that wraps our section
on input remapping and UI glyphs.
Now, I'll pass it back to James.
Thanks, Hannah.
Okay, so let's summarize
what we've discussed in this video.
We talked about
how the extensible input API
can keep your controller support flexible
to any new controllers that may be added.
We went over Game Controller
and Core Haptics integration
that'll allow you to create
rich haptic and rumble experiences
on supported controllers.
We dove into how you can support
some of the more unique features
of controllers
like motion, light bar and battery.
We also went over the new input remapping
available on iOS and tvOS
and what that means for your game.
We talked about
new controller button glyphs
that have been added to SF symbols
and how you can use them to create
a polished and adaptive UI.
And finally, we showed how updating
your app's capabilities in Xcode
to indicate extended gamepad support
will badge your game in the App Store,
allow per-app input remapping,
and future-proof your game
for any new features
that rely on this capability.
For more information
about this year's Game Controller update,
please visit the developer site
for the Game Controller framework.
If you are interested
in learning about adding
keyboard and mouse support to your game,
watch this year's talk
on "Bring Keyboard
and Mouse Gaming to iPadOS."
That's it for this year's
Game Controllers update.
Thank you for watching.
We hope you found this information helpful
and that you use it to create
some awesome games
with Game Controller support.