Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome. My name is Steve Breen,
and I'm an engineer on the UIKit team.
In this video, we're going to chat a bit
about advances in UICollectionView
for iOS 14.
Before we dive into our content,
I'm gonna highlight a portion of the
companion sample project for this video,
entitled Emoji Explorer.
This sample has a lot of interesting
components baked in to its design.
In this first section, there's
a horizontally scrolling grid of emoji.
This is a pretty common design element
in today's applications.
Now, this middle section of Emoji Explorer
is especially novel.
It's an expandable-collapsible outline,
which is new in iOS 14.
And finally, in this last section,
there's a design that looks suspiciously
like a UITableView right here,
camped out in the middle
of our UICollectionView.
Okay, so that's Emoji Explorer.
And we'll be referring back to this
throughout the video.
The APIs that comprise UICollectionView
can be slotted
into three distinct categories--
Data, Layout and Presentation.
One of the novel concepts
UICollectionView was built on
was the separation of concerns
between the data, or the "what,"
from the layout,
the "where" content is being rendered.
This distinction is at the core of
what makes UICollectionView so flexible.
When UICollectionView
was first released back in iOS 6,
data was managed
via an indexPath-based protocol,
UICollectionViewDataSource.
For layout we had an abstract class,
UICollectionViewLayout,
and we shipped a concrete subclass,
UICollectionViewFlowLayout.
And on the presentation side,
we published two view types--
UICollectionViewCell
and UICollectionReusableView.
Back in iOS 13,
we introduced two new components
for Data and Layout respectively
with Diffable Data Source
and Compositional Layout.
These are APIs to use for building apps
with UICollectionViews today.
For iOS 14, we built on these modern APIs
and introduced new features
across all three of these API categories
with enhancements
to Diffable Data Sources,
Compositional Layout and cells.
First up, let's chat about enhancements
to Diffable Data Source.
Diffable Data Source,
introduced in iOS 13,
greatly simplifies the management
of UI State
through the addition
of the new snapshot data type.
Snapshots encapsulate the entire UI State
via the use of unique section
and item identifiers.
When updating a UICollectionView,
we first create a new snapshot,
populate it with the current UI State
and then apply it to the data source.
Diffable Data Source
computes the differences
and generates animations automatically
without requiring any additional work
from you.
So we covered this API
in detail in the WWDC 2019 video
"Advances in UI Data Sources."
And I encourage you
to check out that video to learn more.
For iOS 14, we're adding a new
snapshot type we call section snapshots.
And as the name implies,
section snapshots encapsulates the data
for a single section
in a UICollectionView.
There are two reasons
for this enhancement--
first, to allow data sources
to be more composable
into section-sized chunks of data...
and second,
to allow modeling of hierarchical data,
which is needed
to support rendering outline-style UIs,
a common visual design
found all throughout iOS 14.
So let's go back to Emoji Explorer
and see how section snapshots
are used to build out this sample app.
First,
in our horizontally scrolling section,
we see we're using
a single section snapshot
to completely model the content
found here.
And next in our second section,
where we see this
expandable-collapsible outline style,
a second section snapshot is used
to model this hierarchical data.
And finally in our list section,
we again model this section's content
with a third section snapshot.
So for Emoji Explorer,
we have composed our Diffable Data Source
into three distinct section snapshots,
each representing
a single section's content.
That's a brief overview
of the new section snapshots
we've added to UICollectionView's
Diffable Data Source for iOS 14.
But there's more.
We've also added new reordering APIs.
To take a deeper dive into these new APIs,
please check out the video
"Advances in Diffable Data Sources."
Next up, let's talk about some advances
in Compositional Layout for iOS 14.
Compositional Layout was introduced
back in iOS 13,
and it allows us to build rich,
complex layouts
by composing smaller,
easy-to-reason bits of layout together.
Compositional Layout is fast
because you describe
what you want the layout to look like
instead of how the layout ought to work.
Compositional Layout
also includes the ability
to have section-specific layouts
to help you build more sophisticated UIs.
And there's even support
for orthogonal scrolling sections.
To learn more about Compositional Layout,
check out the WWDC 2019 video
"Advances in Collection View Layout."
Okay, so for iOS 14,
we've built on the foundation
of Compositional Layout
with a new feature we call Lists.
Lists allow you to include
UITableView-like sections
right in to any UICollectionView.
And these lists are rich with features
you've come to expect from UITableView,
like swipe actions
and many common cell layouts.
Creating a list-style layout is simple.
Since Lists is built
on top of Compositional Layout,
we can easily mix and match Lists
with other kinds of layout
on a per-section basis.
Let's check out a code snippet
to see just how easy it is
to create a list-styled layout
with Compositional Layout.
As you can see, it's quite simple--
just two lines of code.
In this example,
we're creating a UICollectionView layout
where every section
in our CollectionView is a list
with an insetGrouped appearance.
And here's what that layout
would look like.
So that's just a brief tour
of Compositional Layout lists.
But there's a lot more to Lists.
There's a new concrete
UICollectionViewListCell,
header and footer support,
and also a new Sidebar appearance
we see in many iPadOS system apps.
For a deeper dive, please check out
the video "Lists in UICollectionView."
Finally, let's chat a little bit
about UICollectionView and modern cells.
For iOS 14, we have a brand-new way
to configure cells
with a new API we call cell registrations.
Cell registrations are a simple,
reusable way
to set up a cell from a view model.
Cell registrations eliminate
the extra step
of registering a cell class or nib
to associate it with a reuse identifier.
We instead use a generic registration type
which incorporates a configuration closure
for setting up a new cell
from a view model.
Let's take a look at this API in action.
First, we create our cell registration,
which is generic over the cell class--
in this case MyCell--
and our ViewModel class.
Notice the registration takes a closure,
which is called
whenever a new cell is constructed.
This is where we configure
the cell's content from our ViewModel.
With cell registrations, we no longer
need the extra step of calling register.
We simply use the cell registration from
our Diffable Data Source cell provider
with the new API
dequeueConfiguredReusableCell
using registration.
So that's cell registrations.
Next up, cell content configurations.
Cell content configurations provide
standardized layouts for cells
similar to what is seen
in UITableView standard cell types.
These configurations can be used
with any cell, or even a generic UIView.
They're very flexible.
Let's check out a few visual examples
to get a taste of how these work.
Here we can see a simple case
of an image and some text
in a very standard-looking cell layout.
And here's the valueCell variant,
where the second text
is on the trailing side of the cell.
And finally we have the subtitleCell,
which has the secondary text
underneath the main text.
Note here-- these content
configuration types are very lightweight
and simply describe
what the content should look like.
The framework takes care
of all the layout considerations
and automatically optimizes
for performance.
And finally, background configurations.
These are quite similar
to content configurations
but apply to any cell's background
with the ability to adjust properties
such as color, border styles and more.
So we've barely scratched the surface
with modern cell configuration.
For a deeper dive, please check out
the video "Modern Cell Configuration."
That wraps up this overview
of advances in CollectionView for iOS 14.
Go download the sample app
to see these APIs in action.
And use our code as a basis
for adding these features to your apps.
And to learn more,
go check out the related videos.
And thanks for watching.