Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hey. My name is Sofiane.
I work on Proactive Intelligence
here at Apple,
and today, I'll be joined
by my colleagues Romain and Magnus
to tell you about how we make
integrating your reservations
with the system really easy,
and all of the great benefits
that come with it.
We first introduced
the Siri Event Suggestions API
last year in iOS 13,
and over the past year,
we've seen some great adoption
of the API in your apps.
But we've also listened to your feedback
and made a ton of improvements.
So let's dive right in.
So, what is Siri Event Suggestions?
At its core,
the feature makes it super easy to get
reservations from your app into Calendar.
All someone has to do
is make a reservation in an app,
like they normally would,
and it'll magically appear in Calendar,
just like that.
The system then uses
on-device intelligence
to streamline everyday interactions
with your reservations.
So, for example, on the lock screen,
Siri can notify you when it's time
to leave for a restaurant reservation,
based on local traffic conditions.
And when you open Maps,
you get a Siri Suggestion,
so getting directions
to the airport to catch a flight
is as easy as just one tap.
Siri can also proactively suggest
turning on Do Not Disturb,
so you can stay focused on what matters,
like the movie you're about to watch.
And Siri can even provide a suggestion
to check-in for your flight
right on your lock screen.
Today, we're gonna talk about
some of the enhancements we've made
to make your life as a developer easier,
as well as some of the improvements
we've brought to the user experience.
We're gonna break the talk down
into four broad segments.
We're gonna go over some exciting updates
on reservation categories
and how we've expanded to more platforms.
Next, my colleague Romain will introduce
a brand-new way to use web markup
to integrate with Siri Event Suggestions
on your website and emails.
We've also gotten great feedback from you
over the past year,
so Magnus will speak
to some donation best practices
we know you'll be interested in.
Finally, we have a short segment
where we'll share some tips and tricks
to make debugging easier.
All right. We've got a ton
of great content, so let's get started.
We already support
a wide range of categories,
from restaurants, to flights,
to event reservations,
and this year,
we're expanding transit support
to include bus and boat reservations.
As with train reservations,
these are not meant to represent
things like an all-day bus ticket,
but instead, trips that are booked
for a specific time.
In addition to supporting
more reservation categories,
we're also expanding to new platforms.
This year, we're delighted to bring
Siri Event Suggestions to macOS Big Sur.
You can use the Intents framework
to donate your reservations in your app,
including apps built with Mac Catalyst.
And just as with iOS, all you need to do
is donate your reservations to the system.
And just like that,
people will get all of the same
on-device intelligence they do today,
like getting a reservation in Calendar,
Siri Suggestions, and more.
And if you have an iOS and a macOS app,
you should still donate
your reservation on all platforms.
As long as the data
you're donating is consistent,
the system will make
the cross-platform experience seamless
by automatically syncing reservations
across all devices
using end-to-end encryption.
By popular demand, we're also making
development easier than ever
by enabling you to use Simulator.
Just select the simulator as a target,
and build and run your app
as you normally would.
The Siri Event Suggestions API
is offered as part
of the Intents framework,
which is available for apps on iOS,
and now on the Mac as well.
You can check out last year's session
"Integrating with Siri Event Suggestions,"
which covers this topic in-depth,
and is a great way
to get started with the API.
We really want everyone to benefit
from the same on-device intelligence,
regardless of how they're making
or accessing
their reservation information.
And we know you interact with customers
through many channels.
Someone might start by making
a reservation on your website,
then later modify it using your app,
maybe check it from a confirmation email.
And that's why we're thrilled to announce
that we're introducing new ways
to integrate with Mail and Safari.
All you need to do is embed web markup
within the HTML of your website or emails,
and it just works.
And now I'd like to invite
my colleague Romain
to tell you about how to use markup
to integrate with Siri Event Suggestions
on your website and emails.
Romain?
Hello, everyone.
My name is Romain,
and I'm going to walk you through
how to add markup
to your website and emails
for Siri Event Suggestions.
This is new in iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur.
Now, when you view
a reservation in Safari,
the system will look
for markup you've added
and automatically
add the reservation to Calendar.
In Mail, reservations are intelligently
added to Calendar in the background,
without even having to open the Mail app.
We even display a useful banner at the top
to make it easy
to see the most important information
at a glance.
We're leveraging a web standard
called schema.org.
Schema.org is a standardized
markup vocabulary
which makes it easy to annotate
reservation information
on your website and emails.
And because it's a standard,
it can be used by any email client
or web browser,
even on other platforms.
Adding markup is easy,
and we support both JSON-LD and Microdata.
We created documentation
about the specific categories
and properties we support,
as well as some examples
to get you started on developer.apple.com.
Let's have a look on how to add markup
to your emails and web pages.
Here's an example of a confirmation email
for a restaurant reservation.
This email has lots of useful information.
For example,
we have the name of the restaurant,
the date and time of the reservation,
but also the phone number
and address of the restaurant.
And so, this is what the complete
JSON-LD markup looks like.
So, the more details
you provide in the markup,
the better user experience we can provide.
For instance,
knowing the address of the reservations
means we can notify the user
when it's time to leave.
And here's the same markup,
but using Microdata.
When a user changes
or cancels a reservation,
it's important to keep
the markup up to date.
For a modification,
the markup should represent
the updated reservation information.
As long as you keep
the same reservationId,
Siri will automatically update
the Calendar event.
In our example, the user
modified the time of the reservation
from 7:30 to 6:30 p.m.
So we're reflecting that
in the startDate property,
while keeping the same reservationId.
If a user cancels a reservation,
set the reservationStatus
to ReservationCancelled
and Siri will automatically
cancel the Calendar event.
Now, you have all the tools you need
to add markup to your website and emails.
Great!
Next, let me tell you
about our requirements.
First, you must register your domain
with Apple.
For that, we've created a simple form
on developer.apple.com
where you can submit your domain
and samples of your markup.
We also require that your website
uses HTTPS,
and that your emails
have a valid DKIM signature.
With that taken care of,
Safari and Mail will donate
your reservation to the system.
We also added two settings
that disable this requirement
to make testing your markup in development
super easy.
First, to enable your domain for testing,
open the Developer Settings
and enable Allow Any Domain on iOS,
or use the command below on the Mac.
Likewise, for local development,
you can enable Unverified Sources
in the Developer Settings on iOS,
or by using this other command on the Mac.
Now, let me show you
how all of this comes together.
As I mentioned before,
to test the schema.org markup
in my development environment,
I'll need to do some prep work.
First, I'll set the
SuggestionsAllowAnyDomainForMarkup default
which will allow for unregistered domains.
Great.
Next, since my local environment
doesn't use HTTPS,
I'll set
SuggestionsAllowUnverifiedSourceForMarkup,
enabling
unverified source verification check.
And done.
In this example,
I'll be using a website
that handles restaurant reservations,
which already has
schema.org markup embedded.
Let's find a restaurant.
This one looks good to me.
Let's make a reservation
for this Friday for 7:30PM.
For two.
I'm going to make the reservation.
The website allows me to review
that all the information is correct,
and because the reservation
isn't confirmed at this point,
it won't be added to Calendar.
This looks all good to me,
so let me go ahead
and confirm the reservation.
Since my markup now contains
a confirmed reservation,
Safari is donating the reservation
to the system,
and I'll get this handy
Calendar notification.
Let's have a look at the Calendar event
Siri just created.
By clicking on the notification,
I can see all the information I need.
Let's add it to Calendar.
If your markup contains a URL,
the system can provide it
as a link in Calendar,
so I can quickly get back to my website
to access and manage the reservation.
When I click on it,
it goes right back to that specific page.
Let's have a look
at the markup on this page,
using the Safari Web Inspector
to view the source code.
Here you can see the JSON-LD tag.
It contains all the information
about the reservation.
You can see
that the reservation is confirmed,
the reservationId,
and also the URL we use
for the "Show in Safari" link we just saw.
There's also the start time
of the reservation,
which uses the ISO 8601 format,
including the time zone
of where the reservation is happening.
Now, let's say the user changes their mind
and wants to cancel their reservation.
It's really important here
that the markup reflects this change.
The reservationStatus is updated
to ReservationCancelled.
And just like that, the Calendar event
is automatically cancelled in Calendar.
This feature also works great in Mail.
We've included the same schema.org markup
in the automatic confirmation emails
sent from our demo website.
Let's have a look at this on iOS.
I just received the email confirmation
about my reservation being cancelled.
I'm opening it.
And you can see at the top,
Siri detected the event,
but knows it's cancelled.
With just one tap,
I can delete the Calendar event
directly from the banner.
And it's gone.
The key takeaway here
is to keep the same reservationId
for confirmation, updates,
and cancellation.
And that's how easy it is to integrate
with Siri Event Suggestions
using markup on macOS and iOS.
Now that you know
how Siri Event Suggestions markup works,
I wanted to highlight a few key points.
It's important to respect
the format and type of each property
as defined in the developer documentation.
And here's a few examples.
First, use the appropriate
reservationStatus.
For example,
use the ReservationConfirmed status
only when the reservation is confirmed.
In some cases, that might mean making sure
payment has been processed.
For date times,
we all know this can be tricky,
so here, it's important to use
ISO 8601 format,
including the time zone
of where the reservation is happening.
And make sure all markup for a reservation
use the same reservationId.
This will allow Siri to update
the user's Calendar event,
if the reservation
is modified or cancelled.
Now that you are ready to integrate
with Siri Event Suggestions,
let's talk next steps.
Again, make sure to add markup
that accurately reflects
your reservation details,
including the correct status.
Use Developer Settings
to test your markup locally.
And finally, once you've verified
your markup is working
register your domain with Apple,
so people can start enjoying
an even richer experience,
interacting with your reservations.
And now, I'll hand it off
to my colleague Magnus
to talk about donations best practices.
Thank you, Romain.
Since releasing the API last year,
we've seen some great adoption.
We also heard
some helpful feedback from you
about what features you'd like us to add,
and what some of the challenges were
when adopting the API.
In this section, I'd like to talk
about some of the best practices
for providing a great user experience.
Let's start with a quick refresh
on how the API works.
Integrating with Siri Event Suggestions
starts with the reservation details
in the app.
As an example, I'll be using
this made-up restaurant booking app
to walk through a typical donation flow.
To donate to Siri,
the app first maps its reservation details
into INReservation objects.
The INReservation object
is shown in green here,
and contains the details
about the reservation shown in the app.
To keep it simple, we're only showing
the itemReference in this example.
The INReservation objects
are added to an intent response
that together with the intent
forms the interaction
that the app donates to Siri.
Once donated, Siri may create
one or more Calendar events
and notify the user
that the reservations were added
to their Siri Event Suggestions Calendar.
Now the user has access
to some of the most important details
right in Calendar.
To get more details,
or to manage the reservation,
we want people
to easily get back into your app,
so we put a "Show in App" button
right in Calendar to make this easy.
When the "Show in App" button is pressed,
the system will construct
an INGetReservationDetailsIntent
containing information about
the reservation the user wants to view.
The intent uses
the container and item reference
from the donation
that was used to create the event.
The app is then launched to the foreground
with the user activity and interaction
with that intent.
The app uses this information
to display the right reservation
to the user.
As we've seen,
the container and item references
are used to launch your app.
Let's take a look at some more details
on how the two are different
from a similar INReservation property,
the reservation number.
The reservation number is used by Siri
to identify changes to a reservation
across sources.
For instance, if you support both
the Siri Event Suggestions API
in your app,
and the Siri Event Suggestions markup
in your emails or on your website,
make sure the reservation number
is the same in all places.
Similarly, if a reservation is updated
with new information, or is cancelled,
Siri uses the reservation number
to identify which Calendar event
to update.
Like we talked about earlier,
the container and item references
are used for launching your app.
The container reference uniquely
identifies a reservation within your app.
That reservation may consist
of one or more parts.
For example, in a flight reservation
with multiple legs,
each leg is one part of the reservation
and must be represented
as an individual INReservation object
with a unique item reference.
The reason the item reference
must be unique
is that the system may launch your app
to display a single part of a reservation,
like one of the two legs
from that flight reservation.
Now that we have an understanding of what
the container and item references are for,
let's take a look
at some concrete examples of reservations
and how we can choose good values
for them.
I'll use the app we saw
in the previous section as an example.
In this app,
users make restaurant reservations
like the one on the screen.
For this reservation,
the reservation number
identifies all parts of the reservation,
which in this case is only one.
So, I'll use that
as the containerReference.
When there's only a single part
in the reservation,
I can make the itemReference
the same as the containerReference.
I'll also set a descriptive spokenPhrase
for the reference,
in this case "Table at ACME Eatery."
This'll be used
if the reference needs to be displayed,
like if the user makes a shortcut
to launch this reservation.
Again, I use the same value
for both references.
Next up is an app
for booking transit reservations,
like this round-trip train reservation
shown here.
This reservation has two parts,
one part for each leg of the trip.
Like in the previous example,
the reservation number identifies all--
in this case two--
parts of the reservation,
so I'll use that as the containerReference
and make sure I set a spokenPhrase
that also describes
all parts of the reservation.
For the two legs of the trip,
I'll create two TrainReservation objects.
Since there are two parts
but only a single reservation number,
I can't use that as the itemReference
like I did in the first example.
Instead, I'll have to pick an identifier
that's unique
to each part of the reservation.
In this case, I'm using the ticket number
associated with each
of the two legs of the trip.
That way my app can easily determine
which leg to show
if it's being launched
to show just one of them.
I also set a spokenPhrase
that describes each of the legs.
Finally, some apps allow users
to book reservations
with multiple different categories,
like a travel-agency app offering bundles
of transportation, lodging, and so on.
In this example,
the reservation has three parts:
two flight legs and one hotel stay.
In addition to having three parts,
the reservation also has
three reservation numbers.
One is for the two flight parts,
one is for the hotel part,
and one is for the whole trip.
The containerReference should identify
all parts of the reservation.
So, in this case, I'll use
the reservation number for the trip.
For the flight, I'll create
one flight reservation for each leg.
Like in the previous example,
the two legs share
the same reservation number,
so I can't use that for the itemReference.
In this case, I'll create a new identifier
combining the reservation number
and the flight number
and use that for the itemReference.
You can choose any identifier
you'd like here, as long as it's unique
and it enables you
to find a specific part of the reservation
to show when being launched.
For the hotel part of this reservation,
I'll create a LodgingReservation object.
The reservation number for the hotel
is only used
for that one part of the reservation.
Since it's unique,
I'll use that for the itemReference.
Now we've seen a few examples of how
to set the container and item reference
so your app can provide
a great user experience
and show the right part of the reservation
when being launched.
Next, let's take a look
at how this experience changes,
if the calendar event is being displayed
on a device
where your app is not installed.
This year, we added a new URL property
to the INReservation class.
If a Calendar event that was created
from one of your app's donations
is being displayed on a device
where your app is not installed,
and the reservation you donated
included a URL,
we'll display a "Show in Safari" button
in Calendar.
Instead of launching your app,
pressing this will open the URL
you set in Safari,
so the user can view
their reservation details on your website.
Make sure you adopt this new URL property,
since calendar events will be synced
to all the users' devices,
some of which
may not have your app installed.
That way you can still provide
a great user experience.
Providing a great user experience
also means donating
at the right time and place in your app.
That will give your users
the necessary context
if a notification is shown,
and it makes sure the system
has up-to-date reservation details.
This year, we made some changes
to how notifications are shown,
so your app can donate multiple
interactions containing reservations.
Now, the system
will intelligently group notifications
when multiple donations are made
within a short amount of time.
The ideal place to do this
is when your app is displaying
a list of upcoming reservations.
We also recommend you donate
when viewing a single reservation
and when viewing
a specific part of a reservation,
such as one of the two tickets
for this movie.
The system will only show a notification
for a reservation
the first time it's donated.
Another great time to donate
is in reaction to the reservation
changing outside your app.
Doing this means your users' data
is as up to date as possible,
both in your app and in the system,
by donating to Siri.
There are two complementary ways
of achieving this,
and Apple offers great APIs for both.
Your app can use
the Background App Refresh APIs
to periodically check for updates
and donate to Siri in the background.
Your app should also adopt
silent push notifications
so it can react to changes as they happen.
When a silent push notification
is received,
your app can refresh
its reservation details
and donate to Siri.
For more information about these APIs
and other information
related to background execution,
please refer to the "Advances
in App Background Execution" session
from last year.
So that's donation best practices.
Next, I'd like to talk
about how to debug issues
when donating reservation details to Siri.
When your app donates reservation details,
they may be processed asynchronously
by different parts of the system,
so it's not always possible to let
your app know if something went wrong.
To help you debug issues
during development,
we added extra logging for some
of the most common issues we've seen
and heard about from you.
You can view these logs in the Console app
in Mac OS.
To only show logs
related to your donations,
set the search filter to the category
"siri-event-suggestions."
Let me show you a quick demo
of how this works.
So, here I am in the sample app.
I want to try out the new
bus reservation type we added this year,
so I've added
a createBusReservation method.
So far, I made some helper methods
to create the two bus trips
I'm making the reservation for.
And here, I'm creating
the reservation objects.
Finally, I'm adding them
to the list of reservations in the app.
Let's run the app and see it in action.
New in iOS 14, we added support
for using the Siri Event Suggestions API
in the iOS Simulator, so I'll use that.
To run the app in a simulator,
I simply select an iOS simulator
from the list of devices
next to the target.
And press "run."
Looks like my bus reservation
is visible in the app.
Great.
I'll press the reservation
to show more details.
That will also donate the reservation
to Siri,
so I should see a notification
telling me Siri has created an event.
I'm not seeing a notification,
so something must have gone wrong,
but I'm not sure what or why.
Starting with iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
we added extra logging
to help debug donations like this.
To see what's going on,
I'll first open Console.
In the Console app, I can choose
which device to see logs from,
and how to filter those logs.
I want to see logs from my simulator,
so I'll select it
from the list of devices.
There's a lot of logging going on
in the system,
so we created a logging category
for Siri Event Suggestions.
By setting this as a filter in Console,
I'll only see the messages
related to my donations.
To use this, I go to the search bar
and enter "siri-event-suggestions."
I also change the type of search
from "any" to "category."
Finally, I press "Start streaming."
Let's go back to the app and try again.
In Console, I now see a log message.
Let's click it for more details.
It says that two or more reservations
use the same itemReference.
As we talked about in the section
on donation best practices,
all parts of my reservation
must have a unique itemReference
so my app can show the right thing
when it's being launched.
When I wrote this code, I copy-pasted
the part to create the second reservation.
I forgot to change the itemReference.
They're both "ABC-001."
To fix this, I'll change the itemReference
of the second object to "ABC-002."
Keep in mind that in the production app,
you would likely get these values
from a database or a server.
But for the sake of this example,
I'm using some simple hard-coded values.
Let's run the app again.
I'm still not seeing a notification,
but it looks like there's a new log entry
in Console.
Let's look at the details.
It tells me I haven't acknowledged
the What's New in Calendar screen.
Siri won't add events to the calendar
until the user has done this,
and I haven't used Calendar
on this simulator before.
So let's open Calendar and do that.
That should do it.
I'll go back to the app and try again.
And there we go!
I now see a notification
telling me Siri has added
the reservations to my calendar,
and if I press the notification,
I can see that both parts
of the reservations
are in my Calendar inbox.
That's great.
Debugging issues in the Console app
isn't just useful
for the Siri Event Suggestions API.
It can also be used
for the new markup support
that Romain talked about earlier.
Let's take a look at a quick example.
I'll open Safari.
Here's the reservation site
from earlier in this session.
I'm gonna make a reservation for two
at this restaurant and confirm it.
Since this page contains markup
with a confirmed reservation,
I'm expecting to see a notification
telling me Siri has added the reservation
to my Calendar.
But like before, I'm not seeing one,
and I'm not sure why.
To debug this issue,
I'll bring up the Console app again.
This time,
I need to set the device to my Mac.
When I change the device,
I also have to set up my filter
in the search field again.
And press "start."
I'll go back to the web page
and reload it.
That way, Siri will read the markup again.
I'll then switch back to Console
to see if there's anything in there
to help me understand what's going on.
I now see some log entries.
I'll press the most recent one.
It tells me the end time
of the reservation has already passed.
Siri won't add events to the calendar
if the reservation has already ended.
I'll go back to the website,
and, sure enough,
it looks like I tried
to make this reservation for yesterday.
I'll update it to tomorrow...
and confirm.
And there we go.
I now see a notification
telling me Siri has added the reservation
to my Calendar.
That's how you can debug
Siri Event Suggestions
to catch some of the most common issues,
whether you're using the API in your app,
or markup in your emails
or on your website.
Now I'll hand it back to Sofiane
to wrap up. Thank you.
Thanks, Magnus.
We talked about a ton
of great updates today, so let's wrap up.
We added support
for bus and boat reservations,
and we've made it possible
to donate your reservations on macOS
for a great cross-platform experience.
We've introduced a new way to add markup
to your website and emails,
which will enable the same intelligent
user experience people love,
no matter how they're accessing
their reservation information.
And finally, we've enhanced
the experience for you as a developer
by making it easier to debug using Console
and test your adoption using Simulator.
We talked about how to best donate
your interactions,
and how the new URL property
can provide a great experience
even if your app is not installed.
We can't wait to see how you take
advantage of all of these improvements.
Thank you!