Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone.
I hope you're having a great conference.
Now, if you're looking to improve
the data efficiency,
and at the same time,
the fidelity of your HLS audio streams,
you've found the right session.
I'm Simon, and I'm a media streaming
engineer here at Apple.
Together, in this session,
we're going to discover how to deliver
a better HLS audio experience.
Before we begin, I want to say
that I'm going to provide to you
some additional guidance that supplements
the existing HLS authoring specification
for Apple devices,
a document that is available
at developer.apple.com.
I encourage you to become familiar
with the contents of that document
before we get into this session.
So, if you need to,
by all means, pause me.
I'm a video on demand.
Go check that out, get familiar
with the recommendations there,
and come right back in here.
Without further ado, let's get into it.
Today we're going to cover two topics.
The first topic,
I'm going to introduce to you
three new audio codecs that are new to HLS
in the 2020 OS releases,
and then I'm going to have
a conversation with you
about using two of these audio codecs
in a multichannel setting.
Let's discover the new audio codecs
for the 2020 OS releases.
The first one is xHE-AAC.
That stands for Extended High-Efficiency
Advanced Audio Codec.
And all of those adjectives
are there to remind you
that this audio codec is a very efficient
audio codec at low to medium bit rates.
Bit rates below, say,
200 kilobits per second.
The other two audio codecs
that are new to the 2020 OS releases
are Lossless Audio Codecs.
They are FLAC, which stands for
the Free Lossless Audio Codec,
and Apple Lossless.
xHE-AAC is new to HLS
in the 2020 releases,
but it was available for file-based
playback in the 2019-based releases.
That's iOS 13 and macOS Catalina.
FLAC and Apple Lossless
have been available
for file-based playback
for quite some time.
Let's chat about the first one, xHE-AAC.
xHE-AAC also has another name
in the MPEG-D standard,
and that's USAC, and that stands for
Unified Speech and Audio Coding.
That name is there to remind you
that this is also a codec
that is specifically tuned
to speech reproduction.
It's also very good
as a general-purpose audio codec.
Specifically, like I said before,
those low to medium data rates.
Let's have a look now
at how xHE-AAC compares
with the AAC family at large.
It's a little bit different.
The AAC family starts with a codec that
you're all familiar with, which is AAC-LC.
That stands for AAC Low Complexity.
We recommended the use of this codec
to data rates as low
as 96 kilobits per second.
We identify this codec using
the ISO syntax for the codec attribute,
which is mp4a.40.2.
This codec evolved into another codec,
which is HE-AAC.
That's the High-Efficiency
Advanced Audio Codec.
It does so with the addition
of an additional coding tool called SBR.
That stands for Spectral Band Replication,
where high frequencies are reconstructed
from lower frequencies
that are present
in the core AAC media encoding.
We recommended the use of HE-AAC
to data rates as low
as 48 kilobits per second.
You identify HE-AAC
with the codec string mp4a.40.5.
But it doesn't stop there.
This evolved into a version two,
HE-AAC v2,
with another coding tool
called Parametric Stereo.
Parametric Stereo
reconstructs a second audio channel
from a single audio channel--
a mono audio channel--
with some additional parametric data.
And we recommended the use of HE-AAC v2
to data rates as low
as 32 kilobits per second.
Now, that's where
the interoperability ends.
All three of these audio codecs
have a level of interoperability.
You can decode a HE-AAC v2
with a HE-AAC decoder.
There is a caveat to this, of course,
which is that
you'll only get one channel of audio,
because the earlier codecs don't know
how to deal with Parametric Stereo.
So let's take a look at what xHE-AAC does.
The backwards compatibility
isn't there in xHE-AAC.
The coding tools remain,
or are quite similar,
but they're even more advanced.
They've been refined.
They're more efficient.
It's very important, therefore,
to identify xHE-AAC correctly
in your master playlists,
with the ISO syntax for
the codec attribute being mp4a.40.42.
This is such an advanced codec,
and so efficient,
that we recommend
it's used down to 24 kilobits per second.
Another way that xHE-AAC differs
from the rest of the AAC family
is how the standardization bodies
have approached it.
Now, we've always recommended
in the HLS authoring guideline
to include loudness and DRC,
or Dynamic Range Control, metadata.
What is Dynamic Range Control?
Well, it's extra metadata
that allows the media system
to continuously adjust
the audio signal levels
to reduce the level difference
between loud and soft passages.
We've recommended you include
this metadata,
or to ensure that your program content
and any interstitials within it
are all normalized
to the same volume level.
Our recommendations are consistent with
the new standard from ANSI/CTA-2075,
which also has some informative text
recommending the inclusion
of this metadata.
Another standard that differs from this
and, in fact, goes a little bit further,
is CMAF.
CMAF stands for
the Common Media Application Format.
It's a format that seeks to unify
media encodings between MPEG-DASH and HLS.
It goes a step further in this regard
in that it mandates the inclusion
of this metadata in your media encodings.
For the rest of the AAC family,
CMAF merely recommends
that you include this metadata.
So the takeaway is that DRC is becoming
more relevant throughout our industry,
and your inclusion of this metadata
is the way forward.
Let's take a look now at how HLS intends
to support xHE-AAC on Apple devices.
So, as I mentioned before,
it's really important for xHE-AAC
that we advertise its use
through the codecs attribute,
again, with the syntax mp4a.40.42.
AVPlayer, from the AVFoundation framework,
supports mono and stereo
channel configurations.
There is no multichannel support
at this time.
Carriage is restricted
to the fragmented MP4 container type,
and the only encryption mechanism
supported is common encryption.
So, how can you leverage xHE-AAC
in your software and services?
Well, first of all, let me reiterate,
it is a well-suited codec for use
for data rates as low
as 24 kilobits per second,
all the way up to the maximum
that we have recommended, AAC,
at 160 kilobits per second for stereo.
And the simplest way to leverage xHE-AAC
in your software and services
is to add additional low bit rate
audio variants to your master playlist.
The motivations for doing this
are twofold.
One, you want to reach customers
on low data rate networks.
Data rate networks, and in scenarios
where they would otherwise stall.
The second motivation
is to reach customers
on data rate constricted devices--
devices that have multiple different paths
of network connectivity.
An example of such a device
is Apple Watch.
And we have another session entitled
"What's New in Streaming Audio
on Apple Watch,"
and I encourage you to check it out.
But I've got an example right here.
Suppose you've got
an existing master playlist
in your content library
that advertises two audio variants.
The first audio variant
is leveraging HE-AAC
and uses 48 kilobits per second.
The second audio variant in this playlist
uses AAC-LC
and is at 64 kilobits per second.
To reach customers
on low data rate networks
and prevent them
from stalling during playback,
and to reach customers
on data rate constricted devices,
you need only introduce a new variant
leveraging xHE-AAC
advertising its codec string correctly.
And now you've got a variant
at 24 kilobits per second.
There are some additional ways
that you can leverage xHE-AAC
in your software and services.
The first way is you can parallel
some or all of your AAC codecs
or your AAC variants with xHE-AAC.
And your motivation here
is to provide high-fidelity variants
for the same given bit budget.
Another way
that you can leverage this codec
is you could see it as an opportunity to
introduce DRC support to your playlists,
migrating your library to a future
where DRC is becoming
increasingly relevant.
So, you may be wondering,
how can you coerce an AVPlayer
into choosing
this high-fidelity audio variant
over your existing set of audio variants?
Well, the answer is, we've introduced
a new attribute to the string tag.
It's called the SCORE attribute.
We detail the SCORE attribute
with more detail in the session entitled
"Improved Stream Authoring
with HLS Tools."
I encourage you to check it out.
However, I've got an example right here.
In this example,
I've got two audio variants.
The first audio variant
is advertised as xHE-AAC.
Its bit rate is advertised
at 94 kilobits per second.
I've got a second audio variant at AAC-LC
at 96 kilobits per second.
And I've scored the xHE-AAC higher
than the AAC-LC variant.
And you might also note that the bandwidth
of the xHE-AAC variant
is lower than the AAC-LC variant.
Using the SCORE attribute,
the AVPlayer will prefer
the xHE-AAC variant where support exists.
Let's switch gears now
and talk about lossless audio.
The new audio codecs,
as I've already mentioned,
are FLAC and Apple Lossless.
Both of these are open source,
but they've got an advantage
over the other.
FLAC is in wider general use
throughout the industry,
whereas Apple Lossless has
more established carriage in MPEG-4.
How does HLS intend
to support lossless audio
in the 2020 OS releases on Apple devices?
Well,
we have to advertise its use correctly.
Again, it's very important
that we advertise its use
using the codec strings "fLaC"
where the "L" and the "C" are capitalized,
no matter how strange that looks.
And for Apple Lossless, it's "alac."
AVPlayer in the AVFoundation framework
supports all the channel configurations
from these two audio codecs,
up to eight channels.
More about that in just a minute.
Carriage is restricted
to the fragmented MP4 container type.
And the only encryption mechanism
supported is common encryption.
So, how can you leverage lossless audio
in your software and services?
Well, the first one is you can add
additional high bit rate audio variants
to your playlists.
And you would only do this
if you know that your customers
have plentiful bandwidth.
You would only also consider this
when your customers expect
exceptionally high audio fidelity.
Let's now move to our second topic
for this session
and have a look at how we're going to use
these lossless audio channels
in a multichannel usage.
So, as I alluded to earlier,
FLAC and Apple Lossless
support up to eight channels.
That's in channel configurations
of 5.1 and 7.1.
Now one thing to note is that
the channel layouts of the two audio
codecs are slightly different.
And you must follow these if you want
the audio to come out the right speakers.
Apple Lossless requires
the center channel first,
then left and right.
Whereas FLAC requires
left and right channel first,
and then the center channel.
By now you'll hopefully understand
that lossless audio requires
a much higher data rate
than we're used to with lossy audio codecs
such as AAC.
But how much more?
If I'm going to show you
how much more FLAC requires
when compared to AAC-LC,
I'm going to need to make
a lot more space in my graph.
I'm going to have to change the y-axis.
Hang on a second.
I'm going to do that right here.
And there we go. Okay.
AAC-LC at 48 kilohertz
is still 160 kilobits per second.
But now that I've changed my graph around
a little bit, it's really, really small.
That gives me lots of space
to introduce lossless audio.
The lossless audio
is nearly four times more.
At 16 bits per sample, 48 kilohertz,
we're nearly one megabit.
On the high end,
where we've got 24 bits per sample
and 96 kilohertz sampling rate,
we're pushing nearly three megabits.
But it doesn't stop there.
You see, lossless audio codecs like AAC,
you're able to configure the encoder
to deliver a specific target bit rate.
You can't do that
with lossless audio codecs.
They will consume
as much data as they need
in order to deliver the audio fidelity
that you have requested.
So these are average data rates.
The full picture is when I add
the peak data rates.
Now, at the closest audio fidelity
to our AAC--
that's 16 bits per sample,
48 kilohertz sampling rate--
we are over one megabit.
A similar story
is present in multichannel.
Note that the y-axis now changed,
and AAC-LC is 400 kilobits per second.
The next closest in lossless
is in excess of two megabits per second,
and on the high end,
it's eight megabits per second
for 24 bits per sample,
96 kilohertz sampling rate,
and six channels of audio.
So it's very important that we consider
how to scale up adaptively
to these very high bit rates.
And the way that we recommend you do that
is include multichannel AAC
in your master playlists.
Apple's software package compressor
can encode it.
But one thing to note
about multichannel AAC
is it doesn't enjoy uniform support
across Apple devices.
It can't be decoded
to its full channel complement.
On devices where it can't be decoded
to its full channel complement,
you'll get two channels, or stereo.
But do note, this does not preclude us
from the requirement
of including stereo AAC
for backwards compatibility.
Let me demonstrate with an example.
Here we've got a playlist
with the media tags up top.
They declare the number of channels.
Let's move that out of the way
because it's not really relevant
to our discussion here.
The highlighted variants are the variants
that are eligible for playback
on a device that is able to decode
multichannel AAC
to its full channel complement.
Assuming we're on such a device,
and the device has an audio route
that can render multichannel audio,
we can scale adaptively
from HE-AAC multichannel
up to AAC-LC multichannel,
all the way up to two megabits per second,
lossless multichannel.
The same story is true of stereo.
We can scale adaptively from an AAC stereo
in a low bit rate
to a high stereo AAC bit rate,
and then scale adaptively
up to a full megabit for stereo lossless.
Now, suppose we omit the multichannel AAC
from our playlist.
I don't recommend this,
so don't try this at home.
Here's the same playlist
with the multichannel AAC omitted.
Again, I've got my media tags at the top,
and I'm just going to remove them.
Now, if we're on a device
that supports a multichannel output--
its current audio route
supports multichannel rendering--
there's a single audio variant
that is eligible for playback.
It's the lossless audio variant,
and it requires two megabits per second.
If your customer cannot sustain
two megabits per second,
your playback or their playback
will stall.
Now, because we mandate the inclusion
of stereo AAC in all playlists,
the playback of the stereo
will still adaptively scale
from a low bit rate AAC
to a high bit rate AAC,
all the way up to lossless stereo.
So we've learned a lot here.
Let's summarize everything
that we've learned.
I've introduced three new audio codecs.
And we've talked about the need
for including DRC metadata
in your media encodings.
And it's important in the industry
going forward.
We've also talked about the considerations
for using multichannel lossless
and utilizing multichannel AAC
as a means to scale up
to those very high data rates.
So, what should you do when you get home?
Well, maybe you are already home.
Well, consider how to employ xHE-AAC
to target customers
on low throughput networks.
And then, how you can use this codec to
better utilize their existing throughput
to deliver better audio fidelity.
And do consider
how to use lossless audio codecs
if it's applicable
to your software or service.
I hope you've learnt lots
and have a great rest of conference.
And as always,
we wish you safe travels home,
even if that's to the adjacent room.