[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Matthew Koonce
and I'm a watchOS SwiftUI engineer.
I'll be joined later by my colleague,
August.
Today we get to dive into
all the awesome things you can build
with SwiftUI complications.
Complications are how you display timely
and relevant information about your app
on the watch face.
Some of the most powerful
and useful complications
are able to distill complex information
into something that
can be quickly understood at a glance.
For example, the UVI complication features
vertical gauges with a color gradient
which quickly tells me that
sunscreen would be a good choice today.
Building complications like the UVI chart
can be challenging.
But with SwiftUI complications,
you can bring your knowledge about SwiftUI
right to the watch face.
And of course,
we can't have SwiftUI complications
without Xcode previews.
Now you can view your complications
on different faces at the same time.
So today
we're going to take a look at how you can
build your own complication in SwiftUI.
To do that,
we'll look at the new API in ClockKit
and SwiftUI that make this all possible.
We'll see how our SwiftUI views work
with watch face tinting
and some best practices.
Let's get started with the API.
In order to use SwiftUI views
in complications,
we turn to our trusty
complication templates.
ClockKit has dozens
of predefined templates
that provide easy-to-use layouts
for your complications.
New in watchOS 7,
we've added templates
that take a SwiftUI view
right alongside other ClockKit providers.
These templates
are for the Graphic Corner,
Circular, Rectangular...
and Extra Large families.
But where SwiftUI really shines
are the templates that take
just a single SwiftUI view.
These templates provide
a full canvas for drawing in each family.
And
the GraphicRectangularFullView template
is a brand-new template that gives you
an even larger canvas for drawing.
And with that canvas, you can use SwiftUI
to do just about anything.
SwiftUI's powerful drawing library
is at your full disposal,
allowing you to easily create
novel designs for complications
like this awesome tide chart
from Dawn Patrol.
So that's how you can get your
SwiftUI views into ClockKit templates.
We've also made changes in SwiftUI
that bring more power and flexibility
to complications.
First, let's talk about text.
We've updated text to be aware of
the complication family it will appear on.
The default font size
will change for each family.
For example, this same text shown here
in the GraphicRectangular complication
will be much larger
on the Extra Large face.
The default font has also changed
to SF Rounded
to look right at home on the face.
Additionally,
text features new date formatters
that work great on the watch face.
In particular,
the relative, offset and timer styles
will be automatically kept up-to-date
by the watch face.
For example,
using the relative style for this date
will make sure it's always accurate
relative to now.
Same for the timer style.
I can place the date
right inside an interpolated string
and it will automatically show
the time remaining on my Sourdough Timer.
So that's the improvements
we've made to text.
Next, let's look at two popular controls
from complications
that we've brought right into SwiftUI.
Those are Progress View and Gauge.
Both Progress View and Gauge
are super useful,
and each have a specific purpose.
Progress View is great for information
that progresses in a linear fashion,
like music.
And the Gauge is great for information
that varies over time, like temperature.
Let's start with Progress View.
In its most simple setup,
Progress View just has a single value
and can be set with a style.
In this case,
we're using the Circular style.
We can also add a label to the
Progress View which describes its purpose.
In our case,
we're using the music note SF symbol.
Finally, Progress Views can be tinted,
completing the look
of our musical Progress View.
Progress View
also comes in a linear style.
And all the same API works
just like you'd expect.
Next, let's look at Gauge.
Gauge is a superpowerful control
with a ton of configuration options.
Let's take a look.
Here we have a simple Gauge that shows
the soil acidity level of our garden.
It's using the CircularGaugeStyle.
We can also add a current value label
that will appear
in the center of the Gauge
to provide some context at a glance.
For some Gauges, it might be useful
to label the start and end values.
In our case,
our Gauge is from three to ten.
So let's add those labels
with the minimum and maximum value labels.
Like Progress View,
Gauge can also be tinted with a color.
Here we add a green color.
But where Gauges really come
into their own is with a gradient tint.
By using SwiftUI's gradient,
I can easily specify the color stops
for my acidity Gauge.
Gauge also comes in a linear style
which is great for
Rectangular complications
like on the Modular Compact face.
So that's the Gauge API.
But one thing to remember
is that both Gauge and Progress Views
are available in SwiftUI as a new control
that you can build as needed.
For example, we can use a Circular Gauge
in a Rectangular complication...
or use Gauges right in the app.
So that's the new API we've added
to SwiftUI and ClockKit.
Next, let's talk about one of
my favorite features of watch faces,
watch face tinting.
Watch faces support
a full range of tinted colors,
allowing for even more personalization.
Complications take on this face color,
giving each face a unique style.
Some faces, like the Solar Dial face,
take this a step further
and alters the tint color and the color of
each complication as the day progresses.
So understanding how your complication
will behave on a tinted watch face
is intrinsic to
the design of your complication.
So let's dive into
how watch face tinting works.
I have a full color view here
of a yellow apple over a blue circle.
When the watch face
becomes tinted by a color,
one of two possible tinting effects
will be applied.
The first is a desaturated tint.
And the second is a color opacity tint.
Let's start by talking about
desaturated tinting.
Desaturated tinting is the default
tinting mode for complications.
When the watch face is tinted, it
creates a grayscale version of your view.
Some faces, like the Extra Large face,
may apply a single color
over this desaturated view.
Let's see how we can build
a SwiftUI complication
that becomes desaturated
on the watch face.
Here I have the code for my view which is
a ZStack of a circle and an apple image.
On the watch face that looks pretty good.
When the watch face color
is changed to red...
you can see that
the default desaturation mode kicks in,
and the view becomes desaturated
automatically on the watch face.
And on the Extra Large face,
a single color is applied
over the desaturated view.
So that's pretty easy.
With no changes to our SwiftUI view,
we get a good tinted complication.
With that said, be mindful about the
colors you choose for your complication.
If I had instead
chosen colors with a similar brightness,
the apple will just disappear
when the view is desaturated.
So it's important to consider
how your view will look desaturated
when building a complication.
So that's desaturated tinting.
Next, let's look at color opacity tinting.
While desaturated tinting
is the default tinting behavior,
color opacity is an alternative
tinting style that we can opt into.
This tinting style works by
creating layers within our complication.
And then the watch face
applies a color to each layer.
Starting with our fullColor view,
we first want to identify
the layers of our complication.
Watch faces support two distinct layers.
In this case, we've chosen the circle
to be separated from the apple.
These will now be our two layers.
Next, as the name implies,
the watch face only considers
the opacity of each view.
Since each of these views are at
full opacity, they both become white.
Then the watch face applies a color
to the appropriate layer.
Each watch face determines
the color applied to each layer.
In this case, the watch face determined
that the circle's layer should become red
and the apple's layer should remain white.
Then the layers are brought back together.
It's up to the watch face to define how
the chosen color is applied to each layer.
On the Extra Large face, for example,
our apple is white on a red background...
but will be red on a white background
on the Meridian face.
And other faces, like the Solar Dial face,
may apply a different color
to both layers.
So let's return to our example,
this time using the Extra Large face
and see how we can make
our complication use a color opacity tint.
I want my circle and my apple
to each be in their own distinct layer.
By default, all view content is
considered to be in the background layer.
By applying
the complicationForeground modifier,
I've determined that the apple image
should be promoted
to the foreground layer.
And the circle
will remain in the background layer.
Now that I have distinct layers,
color opacity tinting kicks in.
When the watch face color
is changed to red...
the apple now becomes white
and the circle becomes red.
If I change the color of the face again,
you'll see that the background
changes right along with it.
On the Extra Large face,
the background layer
was given the watch face color.
Let's look at a different face.
On the Meridian face, you'll notice
that the opposite layers are colored.
So that's color opacity tinting,
where we create distinct opacity layers
within our view hierarchy.
Then the watch face applies a color
to these layers for a striking result.
In some cases,
you may want to make additional changes
to your view for tinting.
For example,
you may want to change
the background color to use a gradient.
Or you may want
to remove the background entirely.
We can do that
with the new ComplicationRenderingMode.
The rendering mode has two values,
fullColor for when this view
is being rendered for a full color face,
and tinted for when this view
will be shown on a tinted face.
We can get the current value
out of the environment.
Let's return to our example
and see how we can use
the ComplicationRenderingMode.
First, I can use the environment
to get the current rendering mode.
Next, let's use the rendering mode
by changing the fill of our circle
and the complication
is for color or tinted.
We'll add a switch statement
to check for
the current value of rendering mode.
In the fullColor case,
we keep our circle exactly the same
using a blue fill color...
but in the tinted case,
we're gonna change the fill entirely.
Instead of a single color,
we're gonna use a linear gradient.
In particular,
a gradient that only changes
the opacity of this view.
Recall from earlier,
this is a color opacity complication.
Therefore the opacity of the view
is the only thing being considered
when it's shown onscreen.
Since the opacity is the only thing
we can change,
this gradient goes from an opacity of one
to an opacity of zero.
So now we have a tinted complication
with an opacity gradient fill
in tinted mode
and a blue fill in fullColor mode.
That was a lot of information,
so let's go over some key takeaways.
First, by default, a SwiftUI view
will be desaturated on the watch face.
If you want a color opacity complication,
use the complicationForeground modifier
to group pieces of a view together
for tinting.
And finally, the ComplicationRenderingMode
allows for advanced customization
of a view
for fullColor and tinted complications.
So now we've learned about all the new API
that you can use
to build amazing SwiftUI complications.
But to see it all happen in action,
I'd like to hand it over to August.
Thank you, Matthew.
I'm August Joki, a watch face engineer,
and I'm gonna show you how to use
what we've learned in Xcode.
Not long ago, we released new sample code
for creating and updating complications.
It's called Coffee Tracker.
Here's what the app looks like.
It already includes complications.
This'll make a great place to show off
the new SwiftUI complication features.
Matthew and I have been working on
incorporating a new SwiftUI view
to show the user
their historical caffeine consumption.
They can see the equivalent number of
cups of coffee consumed in the past week,
and the chart incorporates
the colors of the app.
The view's turning out really nice,
and we think it'd make
a great Graphic Rectangular complication.
Let's go to Xcode
to see how to incorporate SwiftUI
and complication templates
and how to support
the two options for tinting.
While previously working on
the History View of the app,
we set up a preview to quickly see
changes we make to our view.
Simple views may not need any changes
for inclusion in a complication
or only need a new property or two
to key off of
for rendering in a complication.
But because our chart is fairly complex,
we decided we will create a new view
to use in our complication.
The separate view allows us
to encapsulate any changes
that are specific to the complication.
We add the new view to our preview
because we want to see
the Apps version of the HistoryView
alongside our new ComplicationHistoryView
to ensure
we are not accidentally modifying it.
Let's take the HistoryChart part
of the HistoryView
to use in our complication.
To preview our complication,
we start by creating
a FullViewGraphicRectangularTemplate
using the new SwiftUI view.
But the template
is not a SwiftUI view itself
so it can't be previewed on its own.
To address this,
we've added a new function
to CLKComplicationTemplate:
previewContext.
It is defined when both ClockKit
and SwiftUI are imported together.
The function wraps the template
in a SwiftUI view
that Previews knows how to transform
into a clock face
with a complication template set on it.
Every complication template previewed
is set on a face
that is best suited for its family.
Thanks to the power of SwiftUI,
our complication looks almost done
right out of the gate.
But the default Graphic
Rectangular font size is a bit large
for the kind of content we are displaying.
Let's start by fixing that.
We add a font modifier to the chart
to set a size more suitable
for displaying in our complication.
We also wanna take up
all the available space
for the GraphicRectangular
FullView template.
Matthew will explain complication
safe areas in more detail later.
That font size looks great.
And since we can see our chart is next to
other complications on the watch face,
we should provide some context
for our complications data.
Adding a title is a great way
to provide that context.
Since this is all SwiftUI,
we can add "Weekly Coffee" as a text
and wrap it up together
with the History Chart in a VStack.
And now that is looking really polished.
But what does our complication look like
when the face is tinted?
To find out, let's set
the preview's face color to blue.
Nothing is blending together,
but we lost all of our color.
Let's use complicationForeground
to make the title adopt the tint color.
Now our title's automatically tinted
to match the color of the face.
Since we are focusing on
supporting tinting,
let's focus our previews on tinting too.
Now we can see what a multicolor face
looks like right next to a tinted face.
And I've just noticed
that using complicationForeground
also made the gradient
and the Gauges disappear.
That's because,
as soon as we adopt tinting support,
our complication
is no longer getting desaturated.
Instead, only the opacity
of our view hierarchy is used.
That means everything in the hierarchy
is reduced to their opacity values,
the parts marked
with complicationForeground
are grouped together
and have the same
color wash applied to them.
As we learned earlier,
we have another way to work with tinting:
the ComplicationRenderingMode
environment value.
Let's use it to change
how we render the chart when tinted.
But first, let's paint our previews
so that we can watch in real time
the complication update as we are
making changes to a different file.
Here we have the view
that creates a column for a given day.
We add an environment property
for ComplicationRenderingMode
and pass the new property
to our custom HistoryGaugeStyle
to hide the background when tinted.
We can see that the chart
now renders differently
from the fullColor case.
With ComplicationRenderingMode,
we are able to change
pieces of our view hierarchy
while keeping the code pads
from drastically diverging
between fullColor and tinted rendering.
Let's go back to ComplicationHistoryView.
We've seen what our new complication
looks like with a blue face color,
but what about
the other sample preview colors?
We can take advantage of the power
of using ClockKit and SwiftUI together
to enumerate the PreviewFaceColors
to see them all at the same time.
We can now make sure
our complication looks good
with a sampling of different options
a user could set for their face color.
I've shown you how easy it is to use
SwiftUI and complication templates,
how to quickly support tinting
with complicationForeground
and how to make use
of complicationRenderingMode
for finer-grained tinting control.
And now I'll hand it back to Matthew
to talk about best practices. Thank you.
Thanks, August.
That was some pretty cool stuff.
SwiftUI makes it really seamless
to create compelling charts
like our weekly summary view.
It has never been easier
to turn that into a complication.
Next, let's talk about
some best practices to consider
when building
your own SwiftUI complication.
First, it's important to know
that tapping anywhere on a complication
will always launch your app.
Buttons, gestures
and other interactive elements
are not supported in complications.
Stick to text, images
and drawing primitives
when building your complication.
We've added a new runtime warning
to Xcode,
in case you try to use a view
that is not compatible with complications.
And finally, remember that a complication
is a timeline composed of static views.
Therefore, SwiftUI animations
are not supported.
We want you to also consider
the performance characteristics
of your view.
In order to keep the watch face
performing at a high level,
every SwiftUI view's performance
is measured before it's shown on screen.
Consult the Human Interface Guidelines
and our documentation to ensure you use
appropriately sized images
for each complication...
and be mindful about the runtime costs
of certain drawing attributes,
such as blurs and formatted text,
and only use what is absolutely necessary.
Note that poorly performing views
may penalize your complication's runtime.
Watch out for runtime warnings
like this one
regarding the size or complexity
of your view.
If your complication is giving
a runtime warning like this,
treat it like a build error
and make sure you fix it
before shipping your complication
for the best experience
for your customers.
Finally, some layout best practices.
Use the default font size
for each complication
as a guide for the kinds of views
that you should build.
For example, the Extra Large complication
may have a large canvas for drawing,
but its purpose is to provide
large and easy-to-see information.
Note that the Circular
and Rectangular complication families
will mask your content
to their respective shapes.
And the Rectangular Full View complication
features a safe area for layout
to help prevent your content
from being clipped on the watch face.
This new larger drawing area
could be clipped by
the corners of the Apple Watch display
on certain watch faces.
By default, the safe area
provides you with space that's safe
for all complication placements.
If you'd like to use
the full area of the complication,
like we did
for the Weekly Coffee complication,
you can use
the edgesIgnoringSafeArea modifier.
This will give you
that little bit of extra space.
Be mindful, though,
about the layout of your content
to prevent it being clipped.
So that was a look
at some of the awesome things
that you can now do
with SwiftUI complications.
We saw how, for the first time,
you can bring your knowledge about SwiftUI
right to the watch face.
We saw some great new APIs for Text,
Progress View and Gauge
and how our complications are tinted
on the watch face.
And how you can use Xcode previews
to work on multiple complications
at the same time
and on different watch face colors.
If you've never built
a complication before,
or you wanna freshen up your knowledge
about complication templates
and descriptors,
check out the "Create Complications
for Apple Watch" talk.
And to make sure your complications
are always showing
the right information at the right time,
I highly recommend watching
"Keep Your Complications Up to Date."
Thank you.
[chimes]