Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Lucas, and I'm an engineer
on the Caffè Macs team at Apple.
In this session, I'll talk about how
we've considered location
at a micro and macro level
to provide a great Caffè Macs
app experience to our employees.
I'll talk primarily about the employee
experience before social distancing
and share a few places where
we're already working on new features
around safety considerations.
Whether you're working on
your own Caffè app,
an app for your corporate facility,
or an enterprise app
used by employees around the world,
these considerations should help you
deliver a great app experience.
First, I'll give you a quick inside view
of Caffè Macs Apple Park.
By understanding
the Caffè Macs experience,
you'll see why location was so important
for the app we built.
Second,
we'll discuss how user preferences let
our users control their app experience,
even before calling location services.
Next, we'll talk about delivering
on-site, in-app experiences
using location services.
And finally, we'll briefly dive
into the world of internationalization.
Let's begin with an overview of Caffè Macs
and the employee experience
we wanna provide.
Caffè Macs is Apple Park's
unofficial town square.
It's a gathering place
where everyone in the company
comes to meet, chat and share a meal.
Whether you're looking for a lunch,
a snack or a coffee,
Caffè Macs is the perfect place
for some healthy, delicious food.
Our mission is to provide great food
and service to our employees.
To do so, we offer employees
an in-house enterprise app,
where you can browse the menu,
order meals and pay using Apple Pay.
We also have a kiosk app on iPad,
which allows guests to place orders.
That order is then sent
to our third application,
the Kitchen Display System,
which is used in the kitchen, on an iPad.
Once the order is received,
the chefs will begin preparing your food.
And when it's ready,
they'll use the Kitchen Display System
to notify the user
that their food is ready to be picked up.
Preferences and location services
in the Caffè Macs app are critical
in order to deliver a great made-to-order
food experience for our employees.
Okay, so that's a brief overview
of the cafeteria experience.
Now let's look into
our location-based app experience.
In the Caffè Macs app,
we've allowed employees
to select their default location.
We use this preference in order to
quickly show the menu for a Caffè.
Notice my current Default Location
preference is set to "Closest to Me."
The selection will use my location
in order to show
the appropriate Caffè menu.
When I select a specific Caffè,
the app defaults
to showing the menu for that location.
This allows the user to control
their location-based experience,
where they wanna preempt or deny
permission for location services.
During app launch,
we check the user's Caffè preference.
We allow users to select
either "Closest to Me,"
which will use location services
to determine which Caffè to show the user
when they launch the app,
or a specific Caffè,
which will show the user
the Caffè of their choice.
These options give users control
over which menu they see.
This is great for one of the recent
updates we've made to the Caffè Macs app,
which allows users to quickly choose
a pickup window at their selected Caffè,
ensuring proper social distancing.
You can then store the preference
and use it to determine
the app's default state at start-up.
A simple approach is to store the user's
selection using Foundation's UserDefaults,
where you store key-value pairs
persistently across launches of your app.
UserDefaults is a great place to store
these types of small preference values
for your app use.
As we just saw,
allowing users to select their
default location is a great first step.
Next, let's take things one step further
and talk about how we deliver on-site
experiences using location services.
One of the challenges we have
with the Caffè Macs app
is to show the correct menu,
based on where the user is standing.
There's one main Caffè on campus
and a coffee station nearby,
and at any given time,
a person can be near both locations.
You may experience the same challenge
when building an app for your facilities,
where multiple points of interest
are close together.
For our app, we wanna ensure
our users are placing orders
at the location they are expecting.
To achieve this, we can use Core Location
and the iBeacon protocol.
In order to use Core Location in your app,
you'll have to request authorization
for these services from your user.
At Apple, we care deeply about privacy.
Employees choose whether or not
to grant permission
to enterprise apps
that use location services.
It's important to only request access
to the data that your app needs
and explain to the user why you need it.
To go deeper on ensuring privacy
when using location,
please watch this year's related session.
There are two types of authorization
your app can request:
"When in Use" and "Always."
With the "When in Use" authorization,
your app will receive location events
while in the foreground,
and by enabling
the background location usage indicator,
the app may continue to access location
in the background.
The "Always" authorization would allow us
to access the user location
in the background,
without starting in the foreground
and without the indicator.
But this is unnecessary
for the Caffè Macs app.
The Caffè Macs app requests "When in Use"
preference for location services,
which is all we need
for our location experience.
For more about requesting authorization,
including the new
approximate authorization request,
please watch this Core Location session.
Keep in mind that asking for authorization
doesn't guarantee
your app will receive it.
Your app should gracefully handle the case
where authorization is denied,
where the user chooses to grant your app less access
than you requested,
or where the user grants your app
temporary access
with the "Allow Once" option.
To prepare our app for calling
"Request When in Use" authorization,
we add the NSLocationWhenInUseUsageDescription
key,
with purpose string,
to our app's Info.plist file.
The system displays our purpose string
and the authorization request dialogue.
Before requesting authorization,
add the required keys
to your Info.plist file.
If a required key isn't present,
authorization requests fail immediately.
Additionally, request authorization only
when your user needs location services
to perform a task in your app.
If it's not clear to your user why
your app is requesting location services,
the user may deny your request.
When you request authorization, or when
your app's authorization status changes,
you use the locationManager,
didChangeAuthorization method
of your delegate object
to process the changes.
The availability of location services
may change at any time.
The user can disable location services
in the system settings,
either for your app specifically,
or for all apps.
If your app is running, either
in the foreground or in the background,
when the availability status changes,
the system calls locationManager,
didChangeAuthorization method
to notify you of the changes.
Location services require hardware
that may not be present on every device.
Before relying on
a specific location service,
check if the device supports the service
by calling the methods
of the CLLocationManager object.
If location services are not available
on the device,
you can fall back on the default
user preference that we discussed earlier.
Once your app has received authorization
and you've determined
the device supports it,
your app is ready to use location.
We can use Core Location
in order to arrange for beacon signals.
A beacon is a device that emits a signal
which can be detected by the system
and passed to your app.
Those signals can identify
that the user is within a Caffè.
And once we detect
a specific beacon signal,
we can then show the menu for that Caffè.
Only the previously mentioned
location authorization is required
in order to use iBeacon protocol.
When deploying your beacon hardware,
you must program each beacon
with an appropriate proximity UUID,
major value and minor value.
The values identify
each of your beacons uniquely
and make it possible for your app
to differentiate between them later.
This also helps you establish hierarchy,
where applicable in your use case,
for example, so that you can match
the Caffè level,
or a specific food station.
Beacons make location-based products
and services available to users
by broadcasting these unique values
to your device.
Adding beacon support to your app involves
detecting beacons in two different stages.
One: Use region monitoring
to detect the presence of a beacon.
And two: Use beacon ranging to determine
the proximity to a detected beacon.
You can find out more about this
by watching the 2019
"What's New in Core Location" session.
Here's how you can use region monitoring
to alert your app when a beacon is nearby.
To monitor for beacons, create
a CLBeaconIdentityConstraint object
with your proximity UUID.
Next, instantiate
a CLBeaconRegion object
and register it
with the startMonitoring for method
of your CLLocationManager object.
The beaconRegion contains
the proximity UUID,
major value and minor value,
of the beacons that you wanna detect.
Only beacons with matching values
trigger a call to your delegate object.
Prior to calling this method,
you must have created
a CLLocationManager object
and assigned a delegate to it.
When a matching beacon is detected,
the CLLocationManager object
notifies its delegate
by calling the LocationManager,
didEnterRegion method.
Similarly, when a detected beacon
moves out of range,
the locationManager calls the
LocationManager, didExitRegion method.
Next, you can check if ranging is
available on the hardware running your app
by calling isRangingAvailable
type method on CLLocationManager.
Start ranging
only if the device supports the service.
Also, you can optionally store the beacon
so that the ranging
can be stopped on demand.
You can use the major
and minor values here
in order to distinguish amongst
your unique beacons.
If multiple beacons use the same UUID,
major and minor values,
the array of beacons delivered
to the LocationManager,
didRangeBeacons in method
might be differentiated only by
the proximity and accuracy values.
We've seen how ranging for beacon signals
is a great resource
for creating tailored,
on-site experiences,
and these location services make our apps
more contextual to the user's environment.
Let's talk about how to adapt
your app's behavior
to location on a global scale.
At Apple, we have employees
around the world.
We want our apps
to provide a great experience,
no matter where they're used.
There are a number of internationalization
topics you should consider
for your global enterprise apps.
For user-visible representation
of dates and times,
DateFormatter provides
a variety of localized presets
and configuration options.
Instances of DateFormatter create
string representations of date objects
and convert textual representation
of dates and times
into date objects.
For instance, users in different regions
might expect to see dates and times
formatted in a specific way.
In the new pickup window feature
we've added for social distancing,
we'll need to have the correct
localized time presented to the user
for them to select from,
no matter where they are.
This is how you can create
a DateFormatter instance.
The Foundation framework also provides
a NumberFormatter class.
Instances of NumberFormatter
can configure the textual representation
of NSNumber objects
and convert textual representation
of numeric values
into NSNumber objects.
Note that NumberFormatter only formats,
it doesn't provide currency conversions.
You can format currency amounts
using the predefined
currency number format style,
which is used by the NumberFormatter's
numberStyle property.
By observing both the device's locale
and the ISO 4217 currency code,
you can format the amounts
using a NumberFormatter instance.
Here in the kiosk application,
we use a NumberFormatter
on an order summary screen,
which is a fantastic resource for
formatting the total in the user's locale.
But notice how the image is displaying
the total in Uruguayan pesos.
Just behind the modal, you'll notice
that the Caffè is Parmer Lane 5,
which is in Texas.
In order to format
the amount appropriately,
we'll need to set the currency code
to American dollars.
After setting the format style
to the predefined currency style,
you'll also want to set
your NumberFormatter's locale
and currency code.
A currency code is a three-letter code
that is, in most cases, composed of
a country's two-character Internet code
plus an extra character
to denote the currency unit.
For example, the currency code
for the Canadian dollar is CAD.
The NumberFormatter locale
instance property
determines the default values
for many formatter attributes,
such as the currency code
and the decimal separator.
By setting the currency code and locale,
we can display prices according to
the user and business preferences.
You can find out more about this
by watching this year's session
on formatters.
In order to provide
a great user experience,
our enterprise app should be localized to
your user's preferred reading language.
For user interface files, Xcode generates
a file with a .strings extension
that contains placeholders for the text
that localizers translate later.
Learn more about how to best localize
your app by watching these sessions.
By looking at the Caffè Macs app,
we reviewed how user preferences
can be used
to deliver a default location experience.
Location services take it one step further
by delivering location-based
products and services.
Internationalization ensures your app
offers a great experience
all around the world.
Incorporating location, both at a micro
and macro level, in the Caffè Macs app
has allowed us to deliver
a great experience for employees at Apple.
We're looking forward to seeing how you
apply these learnings to your own apps,
and we can't wait to see what you build.
Thanks.