Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Suresh Koppisetty,
and I'm an engineer
in Streaming Media Team.
Today I'm going to give you
some updates on
"What's New in Streaming Audio
on Apple Watch."
Last year in watchOS 6
we introduced the ability
to stream audio content directly
on Apple Watch.
As a developer,
you could use Apple's very own AVPlayer
or your own custom audio protocols
for streaming audio content
on Apple Watch.
This year with watchOS 7,
we are bringing the support
for new audio codec in AVPlayer.
Extended High-Efficiency
Advanced Audio Coding,
xHE-AAC,
gives us the ability to deliver
equivalent quality at a lower bitrate,
or you can choose to deliver
higher quality at equivalent bitrate
as compared to other codecs in AAC family.
Now, given that Watch has highly variable
network conditions,
we should aim to deliver
high-quality audio content
with as low bitrate as possible.
Hence, we recommend using xHE-AAC
for encoding all your audio assets.
Having said that,
for interoperability reasons
we also want you to include AAC-LC, HE-AAC
or HE-AACv2 variants in the manifest
and let the AVPlayer decide
what's the best variant to play.
That's all about new codecs on watchOS.
In case you want to learn more,
we have an amazing talk
"Deliver a better HLS Audio Experience"
by my colleague Simon.
Okay, great.
Now you got streaming audio
on Apple Watch working,
and you also have this
new highly efficient codec
to help you improve user experience,
but there is still one thing missing.
That's access to protected content.
Developers have this vast,
evergrowing catalog
of protected content that they would love
to be able to deliver on Apple Watch.
To support this, we are happy
to bring FairPlay Streaming to watchOS 7.
FairPlay Streaming was first introduced
on iOS in 2015.
It's a specification which describes
the set of steps an app needs to follow
in order to securely deliver
content decryption keys
so the platform could decrypt
and play back encrypted media.
While delivering FairPlay Streaming keys,
your app works as a liaison
between the platform and your key server.
AVContentKeySession is an
AVFoundation class designed specifically
for handling decryption keys.
When the application receives
an on-demand key loading request
from AVFoundation,
It handles the various steps
in key loading process
and responds back to AVFoundation
with an encrypted key response.
With this, AVFoundation can start
decryption and playback.
Now, in watchOS 7 we are bringing support
for AVContentKeySession
for all your key handling needs.
AVContentKeySession is not tied
to lifecycle of an Asset.
This decouples key loading
from media loading and playback.
Hence, applications can have
better control on the lifecycle of keys.
AVContentKeySession allows applications
to initiate key loading on their own
at any point in time.
This gives applications the ability
to optimize key delivery
and improve different aspects
of playback experience.
To know more about AVContentKeySession,
please refer to
"AVContentKeySession Best Practices" talk.
That's all about the new things
in watchOS 7.
Next, I would like to highlight
some of the best practices
specific to streaming on Apple Watch
for improving the user experience
even further.
Streaming on watchOS is not the same
as streaming on iOS.
Watch is a low-power wearable device,
and due to its increased user mobility,
the network conditions
on Watch are highly variable.
This presents us with some
interesting challenges
for building streaming applications.
With that in mind, we recommend avoiding
unnecessary network round trips,
including HTTP redirects on any
of the resources needed for playback.
Any additional HTTP redirects
would directly contribute to startup time.
Pre-fetch resources like keys
and certificates.
This will reduce the number
of network requests
during critical path of playback start.
You could use the newly introduced
AVContentKeySession
for prefetching content keys.
It also helps
if you cache the certificate.
You could use the expiry tag from HTTP
responses to decide how long to cache.
Since Watch is only dealing
with audio-only content,
we recommend using a higher
target duration of around 20 seconds
to be more resilient to network mobility
and battery performance
without having a drastic impact
on playback startup time.
To summarize,
we have introduced a new audio codec
that helps you deliver audio content
more efficiently.
We have added the ability
to stream protected content
on Watch with FairPlay Streaming.
We have also talked about
some of the best practices
specific to streaming on Apple Watch
for improving streaming performance.
I hope you use
these new additions and tips
to build amazing audio apps on Watch
and bring novel audio content
to our customers.
If you need more information
on best practices
for building audio streaming apps
on watchOS,
please refer to
these other sessions as well.
Thank you and enjoy the rest of WWDC.