Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. I’m Kevin Matsumura,
and I’ll be explaining the simple steps
you need to follow
to preserve High Dynamic Range
in your exported videos.
In this session,
we’ll review some basic points
on what High Dynamic Range video is,
what HDR formats we support in export,
how simple it is to export HDR video
content with AV-Asset-Export-Session,
the additional flexibility
that AV-Asset-Writer provides
when exporting HDR,
and finally touch on which Apple platforms
support HDR export.
All right, let’s get started.
High Dynamic Range extends
the dynamic range of the video
above and beyond what is capable
by Standard Dynamic Range video.
It does so via a significantly
increased range of luminance values.
SDR video is limited to up to
100 candelas per square meter,
also commonly referred to as nits.
HDR video, on the other hand,
can go all the way up to 10,000 nits.
That’s two orders of magnitude greater.
This results in videos that can display
brighter whites and deeper blacks.
HDR also offers better contrast,
resulting in more details in shadows
and striking highlights.
While this is technically
all that High Dynamic Range means,
HDR is often implicitly paired
with Wide Color gamut.
The color gamut, in combination
with the dynamic range,
defines the color volume,
or the total number of colors
that can be described.
To accommodate the larger luminance
and color ranges,
HDR is also typically associated
with higher bit depths,
with 10-bit common for distribution media.
HDR is all about the transfer function.
Transfer functions describe
how scene linear light is mapped
to non-linear code values
and then back to display light.
The goal throughout this overall process
is to preserve the artistic intent
of the original scene
all the way to the end user’s display.
Opto-Electronic Transfer Functions,
or OETFs,
are on the encode or capture-side
and map from scene light to code values.
Electro-Optical Transfer Functions,
or EOTFs,
are on the decode or display-side
and map from code values
back to display light.
Note that the EOTF is not necessarily
an exact inverse of the OETF.
HDR introduced two new transfer functions.
The Hybrid Log-Gamma,
or HLG, transfer function
was designed to be backwards compatible
with SDR.
This means that HLG content
will display on SDR displays
but any pixels exceeding 100 nits
would be clipped.
HLG is a scene-referred system,
which means the encoded code values are
relative to the normalized scene light.
The Perceptual Quantizer,
or PQ, transfer function
was designed based on how
the human visual system works,
specifically with regard
to contrast sensitivity.
Some common PQ HDR formats
that you are likely familiar with
are Dolby Vision and HDR10.
While an HDR transfer function is
sufficient to categorize a video as HDR,
there are HDR formats that insert
additional information
into the output bitstream.
This additional information,
let’s call it HDR metadata,
allows better mapping of the encoded code
values back to display light
and is used by the EOTF in the decoder
to account for differences
between the mastering display environment
and the current display environment.
The contents of HDR metadata
can generally be categorized
as stream, scene, or frame statistics.
An example of an HDR format
with no metadata is HLG.
Some formats add a bit of static metadata
that is constant over the entire movie.
An example of this is HDR10.
And then there are formats that add
dynamic metadata that varies per scene,
or even on every video frame.
This is what Dolby Vision does.
Note that dynamic metadata
can also be paired with static metadata.
I mentioned earlier that HDR
is often associated with Wide color gamut.
This diagram illustrates the differences
in the color gamuts.
This first triangle represents
both the BT.709 and sRGB color spaces,
which were originally developed
for the standard definition
broadcast television industry.
This next larger triangle represents
the P3 color space,
originated by Digital Cinema Initiatives
for the film industry.
P3 can represent more nuanced colors
over BT.709.
This last and largest triangle
represents BT.2020,
which offers even more colors.
BT.2020 was developed as a standard
for ultra-high definition television.
Wide Color gamut, in combination with
HDR transfer functions and 10-bit formats,
result in videos that are more vibrant
and representative of the original scene.
Now that we have
a basic understanding of HDR,
let’s go over which HDR formats
are supported by export.
AVFoundation supports HDR
via the HLG and HDR10 formats,
which are both industry standards
and widely supported by consumer displays.
This is important, because we want your
user to be able to capitalize
on all the benefits of HDR
all the way to their display.
So regardless of
if your user is viewing your content
on an Apple device
that natively supports HDR,
like an iPhone, or iPad, or MacBook, or iMac,
or if they are displaying
to an external HDR monitor or TV,
your exported videos will render in HDR
for your user.
Note that Apple already brought support
for HDR export
to our Pro users back in 2017,
specifically via Final Cut Pro X
and Compressor.
This year we are bringing HDR export
to you, the developers.
While HDR video content
has typically been limited
to high-end video cameras to date,
we anticipate that HDR content
will become more common in the future
and want to position you with the tools
to take full advantage of it.
Now let’s talk about
the main export interface
that most of you will be dealing with,
AV-Asset-Export-Session.
AV-Asset-Export-Session is
the most common interface of export.
It assumes a file transcoding workflow.
You can use it to simply export
a single asset in a sharing use case,
or you can do some editing
by temporally combining multiple
track segments via AV-Composition,
or performing spatial compositions using
AV-Video-Composition prior to exporting.
AV-Asset-Export-Session is designed
to make exporting simple.
AV-Asset-Export-Session is preset-based.
The presets define what
the output encoding parameters are,
and AV-Asset-Export-Session
takes care of the rest for you.
If needed,
it will perform color space conversion,
downscaling,
frame rate conversion, and so on.
AV-Asset-Export-Session offer presets
for H.264,
HEVC and Apple ProRes codecs.
There are presets that conform
to specific maximum video resolutions,
and there are also
a limited number of presets
that allow for selecting
different video quality levels.
Here’s a code snippet that illustrates
the simplicity of AV-Asset-Export-Session.
You first create the export session
with a source asset and a preset.
In this case, I’ve chosen
the HEVC-Highest-Quality preset.
You then specify the output file name
as a URL and the outputFileType.
That’s it.
In the minimal case, this is
all you need to kick-off the export.
So what do you need to change
in order to export HDR videos
with AV-Asset-Export-Session?
I think you’ll like the answer to this.
Nothing, if you are using HEVC
or Apple ProRes presets.
We have upgraded the existing HEVC presets
to preserve the source’s HDR format.
For example, HDR10 source assets
will export as HDR10,
HLG exports to HLG,
and SDR source assets, of course,
will continue to export as SDR.
The Apple ProRes presets will also
preserve the HDR format of the source.
In order to convert from HDR to SDR,
we recommend that you use
the H.264 presets
which will also maximize
backwards compatibility.
Compositions,
whether they are temporal or spatial,
need additional handling
when mixing dynamic range formats.
Let’s consider the case where
we have a mix of HDR and SDR content.
AV-Asset-Export-Session will inspect
all source assets presented to it,
searching for HDR content.
Upon finding the HDR content,
the exported file will be HDR,
and any SDR assets in the composition
will be converted to HDR.
If there's a mix of differing HDR formats,
export’s default policies are
to first prefer HLG over PQ formats.
Note that AV-Asset-Export-Session
knows how to convert properly
between PQ and HLG formats.
If further refinement is needed,
then export prefers HDR formats
with metadata over those with no metadata.
Graphically, the export composition
policies I just described
are shown in this table.
The first row and column show
the preference of HDR over SDR.
The second row and column show
the preference of HLG over PQ.
And the logic reflected in this table is
extensible to any number of source assets.
While we expect AVAssetExportSession to
be sufficient for many developers' needs,
we know it doesn’t work for everyone.
That brings us to AVAssetWriter.
Here are two common workflows
for AVAssetWriter:
The first workflow employs reading samples
from AVAssetReader
that were optionally edited via
AVComposition and/or AVVideoComposition
and then exporting with AVAssetWriter.
The next workflow represents an app
that uses AVAssetWriter
to export camera-captured frames.
AVAssetWriter puts you
in complete control of the export process.
You can explicitly specify
the video codec,
what bit rate you want to use,
the frame rate of the exported video,
the exact dimensions of the video frames,
the color space and the dynamic range.
On Macs with multiple video encoders,
you can even specify which video encoder
to use for the export.
Note this is not an exhaustive list
by any means,
but it gives you an idea of some common
parameters that you may want to configure.
Since AVAssetWriter offers
many controls,
I’ll now discuss two methods that
can simplify the configuration process.
This code snippet shows the simplest
invocation of AVAssetWriter.
First you create the AssetWriter with
an output URL and file type.
Then you need to provide
an outputSettings dictionary,
which controls all facets of the export.
However, here we are using
the AVAssetWriterInput interface
which accepts a sourceFormatHint
in the form
of the videoFormatDescription
of the source.
In this case, the only required key
in the outputSettings dictionary
is the video codec type.
AVAssetWriter will construct reasonable
defaults for the remaining parameters
based on
the source videoFormatDescription
provided in the hint.
This next code snippet shows how
to configure AVAssetWriter
with AVOutputSettingsAssistant.
AVOutputSettingsAssistant offers
presets to choose from
similar to AVAssetExport-Session.
The presets provide a template dictionary
that you can either use directly
or as a starting point for configuring
AVAssetWriter-Input.
Here I’ve selected the hevc1920x1080
dimensional preset.
We also strongly recommend
that you provide
the sourceVideoFormatDescription
to the settings assistant
prior to retrieving the video-Settings.
By providing the sourceVideoFormat,
AVOutputSettingsAssistant can combine
the source characteristics
with the preset settings,
and return settings very similar
to what AVAssetExportSession
would configure for an analogous export.
It is quite possible that these settings
are sufficient for you,
in which case you can pass them unmodified
to AVAssetWriter-Input.
But you also have the opportunity to alter
the settings at this point,
possibly changing
the output video dimensions,
or the video bit rate, as examples.
Now let’s talk about the various keys
within the AVAssetWriter-Input
output-Settings dictionary
that are relevant to HDR.
There are three such keys that you need
to take care in configuring
when dealing with HDR:
the video codec, color properties
and compression properties keys.
Let’s go into more detail
on each of these.
The AVVideoCodecKey.
AVFoundation supports HDR via two codecs:
HEVC and Apple ProRes.
HEVC is a very common distribution format
for HDR.
HEVC provides good compression efficiency,
so the exported file sizes
will be manageable.
Apple ProRes is a mezzanine format
used in professional video workflows.
The AVVideoColorPropertiesKey is
a dictionary with three keys:
transfer function, color primaries
and YCbCr-Matrix.
Transfer function we’ve already gone over.
HLG and PQ are the two supported
HDR transfer functions.
The Color-Primaries-Key is typically set
to a Wide Color gamut format.
BT.2020 is common for HDR content.
The YCbCr-Matrix-Key represents
how to convert
between YUV and RGB color representations.
BT.2020 non-constant luminance system
is typical for HDR.
The AVVideoCompressionPropertiesKey
is a dictionary
that contains most of the keys that you
may want to vary in the output settings.
However, the only relevant HDR key in this
is the VideoProfileLevelKey
which must be set to HEVC_Main10_AutoLevel
when exporting HDR using the HEVC codec.
Note that 8-bit HEVC HDR is not supported,
and this key is not applicable
to ProRes exports.
All right, let’s take the time now
to summarize how you would configure
the keys I just discussed when outputting
to two common HDR formats:
HLG and HDR10.
This table shows what the relevant HDR
settings are for exporting an HLG file.
You must select either HEVC
or Apple ProRes for the codec.
You can specify any value
for color primaries and YCbCr-Matrix,
but they are both typically
set to ITU_R_2020.
The transfer function must obviously be
set to HLG, since we desire an HLG file.
And if you’ve selected the HEVC codec,
you’ll also need to specify the
Profile-Level as HEVC_Main10_AutoLevel.
Now let’s tackle HDR10,
which is a bit more complicated.
As before, select either HEVC
or Apple ProRes as the codec type.
While HDR10 is conventionally HEVC-based,
we also use HDR10 to define a ProRes asset
that has MasteringDisplayColorVolume
and ContentLightLevelInfo specified.
More on that in a bit.
As in the HLG case,
the Color-Primaries and Matrix
are typically set to ITU_R_2020,
and the transfer function
must be set to PQ.
Again, set the Profile-Level
to HEVC_Main10_AutoLevel
for HEVC HDR10 exports.
Finally for HDR10, there are two optional
keys that we recommend you also specify.
Let’s discuss these in more detail.
Mastering Display Color Volume, or MDCV,
describes the display on which
the content was mastered.
Content Light Level Information, or CLLI,
provides information about
the overall light levels of the movie.
Ideally both the values
should be specified.
This will allow more accurate
HDR rendering by the EOTF of the decoder.
If absent, the EOTF of the decoder will be
forced to assume a default for them,
which may not match what you intended.
MDCV and CLLI SEI message formats
are defined in this referenced
ISO specification.
At this point, I’d like to briefly touch
on which Apple platforms
can support HDR export.
iOS supports HEVC hardware encoding
on devices with Apple A10 Fusion chips
or newer.
Fortunately A10 devices have been around
for a while,
dating back to the iPhone 7,
iPads released in 2018,
and the 2019 iPod touch.
In regards to Macs,
both HEVC and Apple ProRes software
encoders are available on all Macs.
HEVC hardware encoding
is generally available
on 2017 and newer Macs
running the new macOS.
Hardware encoding will make
the export significantly faster.
All right, time to wrap this up.
We’ve briefly reviewed what HDR is
and how it is designed to preserve
the artistic intent of the original scene
all the way to the end user’s display.
With increased dynamic range,
HDR can create videos with brighter whites
and deeper blacks,
as well as increased details
in shadows and highlights.
Due to all the benefits
that HDR video provides,
you need to ensure that your apps preserve
this vibrant HDR content in your exports.
The steps are simple.
Like with any export,
you can use AVAssetExportSession
or AVAssetWriter to do this.
Select either an HEVC
or Apple ProRes codec or preset.
With AVAssetWriter, remember to set
the transfer function to HLG or PQ.
Explicitly set the video profile level
to HEVC_Main10_AutoLevel
for HEVC HDR exports,
and finally, use a Wide Color gamut,
preferably ITU_R_2020.
Here are some additional references
on HDR.
Note there is a companion session
to this one,
addressing HDR editing
and playback using AVFoundation.
Thank you for watching my presentation.
I hope you enjoy the rest of WWDC 2020.