Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to our WWDC talk on iOS Pickers,
Menus, and Actions.
My name is Cas Lemmens,
and I'm a part of the Apple Design Team.
I'm very excited to talk about
three new components we've added to iOS 14
that you can use
in your iPhone and iPad apps.
We'll talk about menus,
the date and time pickers,
and the brand-new color picker.
So let's start with menus.
iOS 14 now allows you
to show a menu from any button,
and they look like this.
And you might recognize them
from the actions you can add
to context menus in iOS 13.
So why did we add these new menus?
In iOS 13, menus were presented
using an action sheet on iPhone
or a popover on iPad.
These components have been with us
since the very first versions of iOS,
and they've served us
a great amount of functionality.
But with iPhone screens becoming larger
and iPad apps becoming richer and denser,
the action sheets and popovers
started to show some disadvantages.
Upon appearing,
they dimmed the background,
which causes a heavy transition,
especially on larger screens like an iPad.
The actions in the list are quite large
even though the labels
are often quite short.
The actions are also quite limited.
For example,
I cannot use them to make a selection.
And especially on the iPhone,
I often have to move my finger all the way
to the other side of the screen
just to choose an action or cancel out.
The new menus on iOS 14
resolve a lot of these issues.
To start, the menu appears
right next to where you tapped,
and that requires far less movement
of your finger to select an action.
The transition is very fast and light,
it's shorter but it still feels smooth,
and it's less drastic,
as it doesn't dim the background.
The items in the menu are smaller
and more concise,
but still easily tappable,
and they support multiple lines
for longer strings.
And where menus in iOS 13
could only be used for actions,
these menus can also be used
for selection and navigation,
and we'll see more of that in a second.
The content that can appear in a menu
is very similar to what's already possible
for the actions in a context menu.
Each action has a label on the left
and an optional icon on the right.
This can be an SF Symbol
or a custom image.
A title can be added
to help you understand
what selection you need to make.
And separators can be added
to create hierarchy.
A menu can present itself from any button.
For example,
the "Sort" button here in Music.
To select an option,
I can tap and hold the button,
move my finger down to the option
I'd like to select, and release.
Alternatively, I can simply tap the button
and tap the action I'd like to select.
At any given time,
I can tap outside the menu to dismiss it.
This will hide the menu
and take me back with no changes applied.
It is therefore not needed
to add an additional option
to your menu to cancel.
Simply tapping outside the menu
has the same effect.
Instead, the menu can focus
only on the actions to move forwards,
which is, in this case,
choosing a sort option.
The menus adhere
to the Accessibility settings
available in iOS and iPad OS,
for example, VoiceOver, Increase Contrast,
Reduced Motion, and Larger Text,
as you can see here.
Menus can be used in various ways.
We'll talk about
the most common use cases in iOS 14:
disambiguation,
navigation,
selection,
and showing secondary options.
Let's start with disambiguation.
Menus can help you disambiguate
your choice at the right moment.
In the examples we'll see,
we start from a very clear action
with a clear intent,
and once you select this action,
a menu is shown to disambiguate.
It will ask a more specific question.
For example, in Photos,
there's a clear "add" button
in the top left corner.
Tapping this will show a menu
to ask you what exactly you'd like to add.
In Notes, there's a clear action
to add an image to a note.
Upon tapping, it will ask you
what kind of image you'd like to add.
And again in Photos,
when I'm editing a video,
there's a clear "Done" button
to save my edited video.
Tapping it will ask me
how I want to save it.
All of these are great examples
on how to use menus for disambiguation.
Menus can also be used for navigation.
For example, here in Safari,
I can tap and hold the "back" button
to show a list of sites
I've previously visited in this session.
Similarly,
the "back" button in any navigation stack
brings up a similar menu.
Menus can also be used for selection.
For example,
here in Podcasts with the "Sort" button.
Menus used for selection
receive check marks
next to the items that are selected.
And lastly, menus can be used to collect
a range of secondary actions.
A simple "more" button in a view
is a great way to show a menu of actions.
These actions are often
not important enough
to be prominently displayed,
but they still should have easy access.
And they can really clean up
your design a lot
and help you focus on what really matters.
For example, here in Files,
the view focuses entirely on your content.
In comparison, Files in iOS 13 had
many actions scattered across the view,
and that takes attention away
from your content.
So by simply collecting
and organizing them in a menu,
the app becomes a lot easier to use.
Similar menus appear throughout iOS 14,
for example, here in Messages.
Now, considering menus like this
can clean up your view,
you might ask yourself, why stop there?
Why not collapse all the actions
in the navigation bar into a "more" button
and when you tap it,
you get a nice list of all these options?
Hiding all actions in a menu
is definitely not an approach
we encourage.
It hides primary actions
behind an additional tap,
and it doesn't give you
a good understanding
of what this view can do for you.
So finding the right balance
between your primary and secondary actions
can help you decide
which actions can go in a menu, if any,
versus which ones should stay prominent.
For Messages,
we kept the ability to compose a message,
as it's a very important and frequent
action you might want to take.
Additional options don't always
have to be hidden behind a "more" button.
They can also appear
on a different gesture.
For example, in Safari,
tapping the top right action
allows me to manage my tabs,
but by tap and holding the same action,
I get a range of actions
related to those tabs.
One last thing to mention
regarding secondary actions
are destructive actions.
For example, here in Reminders,
to delete a list.
As mentioned before,
these new menus remove the need
to move your finger
to the bottom of the screen
to select an action,
but sometimes,
that gesture can come in handy.
Since destructive actions often cause you
to lose information you've entered,
we want to make sure
there's enough friction,
and throughout our different OSes,
we've always done this
by asking for confirmation.
To avoid accidentally deleting something,
the confirmation action
needs to be in a different place
than the delete action.
Hence here,
when I'm tapping the delete action,
an action sheet appears
at the bottom of the view
asking for confirmation.
I will have to move my finger down
to either confirm or cancel out,
and the time and effort it takes to do so
serves as enough friction to avoid
accidentally deleting this list.
Even for destructive actions
outside of a menu,
we still recommend
to keep using action sheets on iPhone
and popovers on iPad.
In Mail,
there's friction when you cancel a draft.
It will ask you whether you want to save
or delete the draft.
We wouldn't want to use menus for this,
since it makes it far too easy
to accidentally delete a draft.
Instead, action sheets and popovers
require more movement of your finger
and help prevent
accidentally deleting a draft.
So just when you thought you could get rid
of all your action sheets,
we've still managed to keep them around.
All the work we put into menus
was heavily based on
how they worked on a Mac for years.
And you'll see now that you're able to use
these menus in various similar situations,
for example,
disambiguation and navigation.
And so that summarizes
the menus in iOS 14.
It replaces the action sheets on iPhone
and the popovers on iPad.
You can use them for disambiguation
by asking for a more specific question
via a clear action.
Navigation,
by giving a list of pages to navigate to.
Selection,
by giving a list to select an item from.
Or showing secondary actions
via a "more" button
or tap and holding an action.
Destructive actions
always need a confirmation,
and for those,
we keep using action sheets and popovers.
And the new menus will make it easier to
translate your app between iPad and Mac.
So that's it for menus.
Let's move on
to the new date and time picker.
Previously, the date and time pickers
looked like this.
They consisted of multiple wheels
you had to turn individually
to select a date or a time.
Throughout iOS 14,
you'll notice these have been replaced
with the following new design.
This is the new date picker,
the new time picker,
and a new date and time picker,
which combines both.
Let's look at how they work.
Reminders is a great example
on how to use
the new date and time picker.
For example, here I'm adding a date
on which I would like to be reminded,
and you can see
the new date picker being presented.
Notice you have
a much better representation
of the days, weeks, and months.
It's easy to jump between months
by simply sliding left and right,
and you can make a further jump ahead
or back in time
by tapping the month
and selecting a different month and year.
Reminders also allows you
to choose a specific time
on which you would like to be reminded,
and here as well you can see
the new time picker being presented.
Instead of having to use the wheels,
I can now simply type
the time of my choosing.
And so the new design
makes it easier to select a date or a time
with any kind of input:
touch, pencil, keyboards, or cursor.
Now, these new date and time pickers
work really well
if you can show them inline in your view,
for example, as Reminders does here.
But that's not always possible.
Specifically for those moments
where it's difficult,
iOS 14 has a brand-new way
to show these pickers,
which we call compact.
When you ask UIKit
for a date picker in compact mode,
you get a button like this.
It shows a date in the key color
on top of a light platter.
Tapping the button shows
the new date picker,
but it's presented inside a modal
on top of the view.
The same can happen for a time picker...
and for a date and time picker.
Let's look at an example.
As mentioned before,
the compact pickers are great when
it's difficult to show a picker inline.
These buttons can appear, for example,
in rows,
as you can see here in Contacts
when I'm adding a birthday to a contact.
Tapping the button shows
the new date picker on top of the view,
and I can change the date
as many times as I like,
and once I've found the date,
I can simply tap outside to confirm.
As with all of our new components,
they of course adhere
to all Accessibility settings,
for example, larger font sizes,
as you can see here.
And the new design also creates
better parity between iPad and Mac,
since the same information
is shown on both.
So just as with menus,
this will help you scale your app
between iPad and Mac.
And so that wraps up
the new date and time picker.
It's an improved way
to select a date or a time
by giving you
a much better representation.
You can use them inline in your view
or use the new compact date
and time picker
when showing inline is difficult
or not possible.
And it will make it easier to translate
your app between iPad and Mac,
since the same information
is shown on both.
So that's the new date and time picker.
Let's move on to the color picker.
iOS 14 introduces
a new color picker for you to use.
You can pick a color
in four different ways.
You can pick it from a grid,
a spectrum,
by filling in an RGB value...
or by selecting a color from screen.
You do this by tapping the pipet
in the top left corner,
after which a magnifier appears.
You can drag it around
to the color you prefer,
and once you release,
the color will be selected.
The color you select
will always appear in the bottom left.
You can also save a color to a palette,
which is accessible from any app.
So the new color picker
is a great way to let you choose
any color you'd like to use.
For example, here,
when I'm using the pencil on iPad.
And just as with menus
and date and time pickers,
the new design brings parity
between iPad and Mac
And so that's, in short,
the new color picker.
It's a brand-new component in iOS 14.
You can select colors
in four different ways:
via a grid, a spectrum, an RGB value,
or picking a color from screen.
It holds a palette of colors
that is shared across apps,
and the new picker will help align
your app between iPad and Mac.
So that wraps up
these three new components in iOS 14.
We added these components
to make your apps faster,
more lightweight, and more responsive,
and they provide much needed functionality
with support for accessibility
and localization.
So by using these new components,
your app will feel more native
to the iPhone and iPad,
and it will save you a lot of time
in making sure your app is inclusive
for all people all over the world.
So we're very excited
for you to use them in our apps,
and we're looking forward
to seeing them appear in yours.
That's it for pickers, menus, and actions.
Thank you for watching,
and until next time.