Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Karan Miśra,
and today I'd like to talk about
how we can format data in our apps
to be friendly and understandable.
Every day, we use many apps which shows us
all different kinds of data.
Some apps, like Weather,
are full of different measurements.
Others, like Health,
show us some key statistics with trends.
And yet others, like Notes, may only
show us a simple date or time stamp.
No matter how prominently
the data is shown,
it's important to get it right
all the way from what units are used
to what formats are used.
And this is crucially important
regardless of whether the app
is available in just one language
or whether it's available
in dozens of different languages.
We also update the underlying algorithms
and data sets that power our formatters,
and one of our focus areas
has been expanding our support
for combinations of languages and regions.
Why? Because we're living
in an increasingly globalized world
and we find that people all over the world
are using their devices in languages
that may not be traditionally associated
with that region.
For example, someone living in Abu Dhabi
might be using their iPhone in French.
Before, this meant that
we would get number formats
that were intended for France
with the decimal separator as a comma,
as shown here in the Home App.
Now with iOS 14, and the latest versions
of Mac OS, watchOS and tvOS,
we will get formats that are better suited
for the region, which is UAE in this case.
And it goes without saying
that this change is not limited
to a single language or region
but is a general algorithm
that will improve the formats
across hundreds of combinations
of languages and regions.
I want to show you the power of using
the formatter APIs in your app,
how much time and effort
these APIs can save you,
and how you can use these APIs
to build versatile UIs.
I'm going to walk through
several sections,
and as I walk through each of them,
I will focus on real-world examples
from Apple's own apps,
going down in order
from most specific to most generic.
My goal is to show that we have
an extensive set of APIs at our disposal,
that simple things are easy
and complex things are possible.
Let's get started with dates and times.
Let's start with a simple example.
In the Notes app,
at the top of every note,
you will see the last modification
date and time.
Let's see how we can do this.
Here we want to show a full date with day,
month and year and also the time.
This is something that can be accomplished
with the predefined styles
in dateFormatter,
with the medium style for the date
and the short style for the time.
Note that the word "at"
is automatically added here
as a consequence of this being
a medium-length format.
So, as I said, simple things are easy.
Now let me show you that
more complex things are possible too.
Here, we have the Screen Time UI
in Settings
and we want to show the day of the week
followed by the day and month
but not the year.
This is not something that any
of the predefined styles can offer you,
but it is possible by specifying
a template.
As one more example from Screen Time,
which you will see in many other UIs too,
if you just want the abbreviations
for the days of the week,
you can request that
with a custom template.
As we can see,
the template mechanism is really powerful.
So let's dive a little deeper
into templates.
Unicode publishes various
technical reports,
including this one on dates,
one of a seven-part series, in fact,
for which I'm proud to say that Apple,
as a Unicode member,
has been one of the key contributors.
This is an excellent reference
for templates,
and there are lots of explanations
and examples.
So when I was looking for day of the week
earlier, I scrolled down,
and found this section.
Here you can see that
I can choose between an uppercase "E,"
a lowercase "e" and a lowercase "c."
So which one should I use?
Now, as you may recall, I was showing
these days of the week labels in a graph,
so these are stand-alone
and not part of a longer format.
This helps me choose the lowercase "c"
for my template.
Now that we've chosen a template,
let's see how it works.
Here, you're seeing the output
of different lengths of lowercase "c."
Notice that here the template with five
C's is the one that's appropriate,
because we want the most abbreviated form.
Also, note the way
that these lengths are interpreted
across different languages will vary.
Here, we see that in English each of the
five lengths produces a different output
but not so in Arabic or Japanese.
So it's important to choose
the right template
and consider all the locales
that we're supporting,
since some distinctions may only manifest
for certain languages or locales.
This is also why it was very important
that we chose the stand-alone style.
It may not make a difference in English,
but it may make a difference
for other languages.
Another important thing to note
about templates
is that the order of the fields
does not matter.
This template is the same as this template
which is the same as this template.
The template takes the pieces of data
that we're interested in
and it is the formatter's job
to assemble them into something
that makes sense for the locale.
So for American English,
you'll see that it adds a comma.
For British English, you'll see that it
makes sure that the month follows the day
and not the other way around.
And as one last example,
you'll see that for Japanese it adds
the characters for month and day
which are needed to produce
a sensible-looking date in Japanese.
Lastly, I should point out
that dateFormatter
has a property called dateFormat,
and we should never set the template
directly onto that property,
since it will cause it to be
interpreted literally
and almost certainly produce
the wrong result.
Instead, we should always create
our date formats from a template first.
There are a few more APIs
for formatting dates and times.
DateComponentsFormatter
helps you format components,
such as those used in durations.
You can also format ranges of time,
like this example from the Health app
by using DateIntervalFormatter.
It even takes care of avoiding
repeating elements
that are both in the start and end date.
Lastly, the RelativeDateTimeFormatter
is a powerful tool
for dates in the past or future which
you want to present in a natural manner.
Next up, let's take a look
at measurements.
If your app uses any kind of measurements,
MeasurementFormatter is your friend.
Let me show you a few examples
that we use in the Weather app.
Let's start with temperature.
Note that in all these examples, I am
setting the measurements in metric units,
but the display you see on the right
has everything localized for the US,
which uses imperial units.
So the temperature of 16 degrees Celsius
will come out as 61 degrees Fahrenheit.
The same goes for speed.
Here the value is converted
to miles per hour for the US.
And similarly for pressure.
I'm showing these examples
because your data source for measurements
may use metric or other units
and MeasurementFormatter
does all the heavy lifting for you,
not only across units
but also across languages and locales.
Now, while I just showed you examples
of three different kinds of measurements,
MeasurementFormatter supports
many, many more.
And, in case it doesn't support
a unit that you'd like to use,
it can even support custom units.
For all this and more,
do check out the excellent WWDC 2016 talk
on "Measurements and Units."
Next, let's talk about names.
Names are one of the most personal bits
of data that we display in our apps,
and we all have a very strong response
when we see our names on screen.
So getting name formatting right
is absolutely crucial to making
a good impression.
Luckily, PersonNameComponentsFormatter,
which I like to call "Name Formatter"
for short,
makes it easy to do the right thing.
All we need to do is to populate
the components object
and ask for the formatted strings.
By default, Name Formatter
will choose the medium style
which includes all the primary components
like family name and given name.
We can also request a short style,
which, depending on user preferences,
may use the nickname
or a shortened version of the name.
The abbreviated style is intended
for specific use cases like monograms,
as shown here.
Over the past few years, more and more
apps have been using monograms.
So let's dive a little deeper into them.
Monograms are a great alternative
in the absence of an avatar or photo
while still making the UI
feel friendly and inviting.
And the Name Formatter was designed
with monograms in mind.
However, it is important to note
that monograms cannot be generated
for all names
and some abbreviated names
may be too long to fit in a given UI.
With Swift, it's easy to restrict
monograms based on a length check.
Because Swift's count
is based on user-visible characters
and not Unicode code points,
this works well across languages.
Of course,
a character count cannot determine
how tall or wide the string would be
when rendered.
So we still need to make sure
that the string fits appropriately.
When the character count is too long
or the string is too large to fit,
a fallback option needs to be used,
such as a generic icon
that can be used in place of a monogram.
Lastly, it's worth mentioning
that the Name Formatter
has a lot of intelligence built in
and uses several pieces of information
when formatting names,
such as the user's language settings,
their contact settings, such as
name order, as well as the name itself.
For example, here a Japanese name
is shown on an iPhone running in English.
I've intentionally chosen this example
to show you
that the Name Formatter will render
the name appropriately in all cases,
even in cases
where the language of the name
is different from the iPhone language.
For names written in Chinese,
Japanese and Korean,
this means that they will always use
the family name followed by given name,
which is the only appropriate way
to write these names.
Next up, let's see
how we can make well-formatted lists.
Anytime we're showing a list of items
that's formatted as human readable text,
we can use ListFormatter.
Let me show you
how it can not only save us time
but also make our app look polished
by getting the nuances right.
The API couldn't be easier.
We simply specify an array of strings
or other objects
that we want to combine into a list,
and we get back a concatenated list.
Let's see the subtle benefits we get
by doing this.
This is the keyboard settings UI,
and here we're formatting
a very simple list with two elements:
the language names "English"
and "Spanish."
In English, all this takes
is inserting the word "and" in the middle.
And if the order of the languages
is changed, it's still the same.
But if we take a look at the same UI
now localized to Spanish,
we'll see that the word for "and"
is in Spanish,
but did you know that the Spanish word
for "and" can vary based on context?
Notice that when the order of the elements
is changed,
so is the Spanish word for "and."
In fact, in iOS 14, as well as the latest
versions of macOS, tvOS and watchOS,
ListFormatter has been updated to adhere
to the grammatical rules
of several languages, including Spanish.
This is one of the many reasons
that we should use formatter APIs
wherever possible.
Not only do they abstract away
a ton of complexity
and provide localization for free,
as the underlying implementation
is updated and improved,
our app gets improved behavior
without modifying a single line of code.
Now let's talk
about two generic data types.
Let's start with numbers.
Here is a quick quiz.
What's the number you're seeing onscreen?
It's a little bit of a trick question.
Depending on what language we use
and what region we're in,
we may interpret this as 32,768
or as 32.768.
In this case, the decimal separator button
on the calculator gives it away
and tells us that this is actually 32.768.
And this is how we can format it
super easy.
Now what happens
if the app is instead launched
with the language set to Arabic
and the region to Egypt?
As we see here, NumberFormatter
does all the heavy lifting
to ensure that everything is localized
appropriately.
It's also worth noting
that if we need to access certain symbols
that change
according to the language or locale,
there are convenience methods
to fetch the percentSymbol
and the decimalSeparator.
In fact, there are also convenience APIs
for many more symbols
that aren't shown here.
NumberFormatter supports
several different styles,
including a percent style.
And, as we would expect,
it handles nuances
across languages and regions here too.
For example, we can see
that it correctly formats the number
with the percent sign
going in front of the number for Turkish.
I'm not going to go into more detail
on NumberFormatter here
because it is chock-full
of useful functionality,
but please do check out the documentation,
or try using it in an Xcode Playground.
Lastly, let's talk about strings.
While the various formatter APIs
will cover a wide range of data types
that are commonly formatted
across all apps,
your app may have its own kinds of data
that don't have a standard formatter.
For example, there's no standard formatter
that will format the number of photos.
Let's see an example
of how this would work.
Doing this is extremely simple.
Using the text element in SwiftUI,
we specify the text as we normally do.
As far as code goes,
that's all we need to write.
Then all we need to do is to make sure
that we have a stringsdict file
that contains the corresponding string.
To learn more about stringsdict, or even
more about localization in general,
do take a look at the documentation
at the URL mentioned here.
Let's say our translators have translated
the text into English and Arabic.
Let's see what the result looks like.
When a single photo is selected, note that
while the English uses the numeral "1,"
in Arabic, it spells out the words,
as that is more natural.
When two photos are selected,
the English, again, uses a number,
but "photo" becomes "photos,"
following English's grammar.
On the other hand, in Arabic,
the dual form is used
following Arabic grammar.
For three photos,
both English and Arabic look similar,
using the number followed
by the plural form of the word "photo."
And this goes on for numbers up to ten.
For 11 photos or more,
Arabic grammar dictates
that a different plural form be used.
Now, maybe you're interested in learning
the grammar rules of a hundred languages.
I know I am. However,
what I want you to take away from this
is that if you correctly localize strings
using stringsdict,
and if you use the formatters
wherever you can in your app,
your app will shine regardless
of whether you support
only one language or a hundred.
Also, all of this is code
that you need to write only once,
no matter how many languages
you support in your app,
either now or in the future.
Lastly, to show you even more features
of all the formatters I talked about
and let you explore, we have a sample app
that you can download and play with.
So happy formatting.