[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Luming,
an engineer from the App Clips team.
In this video, I'll discuss creating
app clip experiences for other businesses.
We'll start by introducing the concept
of creating advanced app clip experiences
on behalf of other businesses.
Then we'll walk through
how to get started.
After that, I'll show you
how to set up an app clip card
for every advanced app clip experience,
so the brand of every business you power
shines through.
Finally, I'll cover
different types of icons,
where they appear
and how to customize them.
So when should you consider
creating an advanced app clip experience
for other businesses?
Let's look at a few sample apps.
If your existing app
aggregates many businesses
into a customer-facing app
and lets users discover them
from a catalog,
then it's natural to create
app clip experience for all of them.
This way, the customers
of the businesses you represent
can experience rich functionalities
you provide
without having to download your app.
This sample app, Food Grid,
has a vast catalog
of popular restaurants across the nation,
making it a great candidate
to get started.
Without an app clip, most of the discovery
only happens within your app.
By creating app clip experiences,
more users can discover these businesses
through system-wide features
such as
location-based app clip suggestions.
Potential users
no longer have to install your app
just to discover nearby restaurants.
Many smaller businesses
don't have their own apps.
After all, their primary focus
is to deliver great products or services,
not to build apps themselves.
In these cases,
creating app clip experiences are great
because it lets expert developers like you
create app-like experiences
on those businesses' behalf.
An example of this kind of app is Reward+,
which lets customers get reward points
by entering a promotional code
they have already obtained
from another business off-line.
With app clips, you can work
with businesses to create NFC tag,
app clip code or print QR code
to offer additional value to customers
that they have already obtained off-line.
Finally, if your business
focuses on building white-labeled apps
across a particular industry,
and all of these apps are really similar,
and you're thinking of consolidating
all of these templated apps
into one single app,
but you're not sure if combining
all of these into one single app
can quite capture the individuality
and the brand identity of every business,
creating app clips are a fantastic option,
because now, by combining them
and building app clip experiences,
each client can still have
its unique brand
across the app clip experience,
but now, you only need to build
and maintain a single app.
Now that we've covered
when to consider creating
multiple advanced app clip experiences
for other businesses,
let's talk about why.
You can build app clips
with familiar technologies
you already use to build your app,
so technologies that you already know,
such as SwiftUI, still applies.
Since app clips
are considered as a part of your app,
most of the code in your app clip
are just code from your app.
All you need to do is to re-use them
and include them in a new build target
for your app clip.
Your users can discover app clips
through both digital
and physical invocation methods,
such as Messages, the Smart App Banner,
location-based Suggestions
as well as NFC and QR.
Because app clips are launched on demand,
there's no need
for users to download your app.
They just use them.
This provides a frictionless,
fast and focused experience.
And finally,
app clips let the brand identity
of the business you power shine through.
Every business gets its own app clip card
with a beautiful
and distinctive header image,
as well as custom title and captions
just for them.
If you have watched
some of our other talks,
like "Configure and Link Your App Clips,"
you may realize that there are
a few different types of app clip
experiences you can create.
There are a lot of similarities
and overlap
between creating
multiple app clip experiences
for your own business
versus for other businesses.
The important distinction
and the greatest benefit
of creating app clip experiences
for other businesses
is that by building
one single app clip binary
and creating multiple experiences,
you can represent and promote
as many distinctive brand identities
and app clip cards as you would like.
This is especially suitable
if you have a full app
that aggregates multiple businesses.
Getting started with creating
advanced app clip experiences
for other businesses takes a few steps.
First, let's take a high-level overview.
Make sure you build an existing app
and make it ready!
Then build an app clip by selectively
including parts of your app.
After that, submit your app, along with
your app clip in App Store Connect.
And finally, create an app clip experience
for each business
you're promoting or representing
through the advanced section
in App Store Connect.
Let's go over each of these
in more detail,
starting with getting your app ready.
First, make sure your app handles
each business you represent or promote.
If you have built
multiple white-labeled template apps,
one for each client,
it may be a great opportunity
to consolidate them into a single app.
Then consider providing
a custom experience
to fit each category of business.
For example, you should consider
representing restaurants
differently than retail stores in your app
from both a visual
and functional standpoint.
To make sure your full app
provides the greatest functionality
and usability to your users,
provide a way to browse through,
search from
or otherwise explore
your catalog of businesses.
Finally, you should handle
universal links in your full app.
Universal links let you deep link users
from a URL into a part of your app,
and it is a great technology to adopt
even independent of app clips.
While links are handled slightly different
as NSUserActivities in an app clip,
handling universal links well in your app
sets you up for success
for a great linking experience
in your app clip.
To learn more about universal links,
please refer to
"What's New in Universal Links."
After getting your existing app ready,
it's time to build an app clip
based on your app.
To do this, create a new app clip target
in Xcode to embed in your full app.
Then selectively include code,
assets and framework dependencies
in your app clip.
To learn more about
bringing up an app clip target,
please refer to "Explore App Clips."
After this, you need to make sure
your users can be linked to your app clip.
To do this,
you need to set up associated domains,
handle NSUserActivity
and configure app clip cards
via the advanced section
of the App Store Connect.
This lets your users access your app clip
through physical invocation methods
such as by scanning an NFC tag,
QR code or app clip code.
To learn more, please refer to
"Configure and Link Your App Clips."
Finally, to provide
an even better user experience,
you should consider
streamlining transactions in your app clip
with app clip-specific technologies,
such as ephemeral notification,
location confirmation
and seamless data migration
between your app clip to your full app
using a secure shared group container.
To learn more about this, please refer to
"Streamline Your App Clip."
You will learn
all you need to build an app clip
based on your app from these sessions.
Along the way,
you may also see a very familiar demoer.
If you have watched the talks,
you're mostly ready to go.
When creating app clip experiences
for other businesses
instead of just your own,
there are a few important considerations
to keep in mind:
launching from notifications
and directly launching
an app clip experience.
Let's look at
launching from notifications first.
The Food Grid app clip powers
a few app clip experiences on my device:
Metatop+, Mandy and Jason, and Fantastico.
Since notifications are delivered
to your app bundle
instead of
a particular app clip experience,
iOS needs additional information to route
the notification to the correct app clip.
To do so, you should fill out
the targetContentIdentifier field
in the notification payload
with a URL describing
what your notification is about.
iOS then performs
the longest prefix match,
and since the targetContentIdentifier
has the prefix
foodgrid.example/fantastico,
it is routed to
the Fantastico app clip experience.
For more information, please refer
to the developer documentation,
"Enabling Notifications in App Clips,"
available at the following URL.
Each app clip invocation comes with
an NSUserActivity of type browsing web.
Naturally, you may be tempted
to always push your users to a new session
with the URL from the user activity.
However, it is important to make sure
you don't push or pop away
if the URL corresponds
to the same session.
Why is this?
Well, consider the following case.
Your user has tapped on the Fantastico
app clip from the App Library.
Food Grid gets a user activity,
parses the URL in the user activity
and navigates to Fantastico.
I'm really hungry,
so let's look at the menu.
Now I've added some pancakes
and appetizers to my shopping cart.
Imagine I'm interrupted
by an important message,
switched to the Messages app
and went back to the Home Screen.
Now, I've launched
the Fantastico app clip again
from the App Library.
Food Grid resumes from the background,
and a new user activity
with the Fantastico URL
is delivered to Food Grid,
so Food Grid pushed a new screen
up the navigation stack.
Without checking for current state,
Food Grid started a new session
from the URL in the user activity.
This means I have lost my order
during the previous session,
even though the URL of both sessions
are the same.
So, instead of doing this,
you should check if the URL
in a new user activity corresponds
to the current, in-flight session
before pushing or popping the user away.
Finally, while app clips represent
and promote multiple businesses,
they don't support multiple windows.
Therefore, if you get a new user activity
with a URL that corresponds
to a different business,
you should consider
saving state or user data
before moving to the new,
different session.
This way, if your user later comes back
to an app clip experience
that has a saved state,
you can seamlessly restore
back to this state to your user.
The expectation that each business
you represent has its own app clip is met,
and from the user's perspective,
they are just using multiple app clips,
even though they are backed
by a single binary.
When archiving your full app,
Xcode will automatically
embed the app clip
within your full app's archive.
To submit it for review,
upload the full app
with the embedded app clip
as a single submission
using Xcode or Transporter.
To learn more about
submitting app clips to the App Store,
please refer to
"What's New in App Store Connect."
After you have submitted your app
and app clip to App Store Connect,
it's time to create an app clip experience
for each business you promote
in App Store Connect.
To do so, create a new
advanced app clip experience
in App Store Connect,
specify an app clip experience URL,
choose to promote a different business
and send it to Apple for review.
You'll learn more about creating
advanced app clip experiences this fall,
but today, I'll quickly walk you toward
how to set things up.
On the App Store Connect page
for your app clip,
if you scroll down, there's
an Advanced App Clip Experiences section.
In it, there is a Get Started button.
Click on it, and you'll be taken
to an advanced app clip experience.
When creating a new app clip experience,
specify an app clip experience URL
and click Next.
When asked about what is presented
in the app clip experience,
you can choose to promote
a different business, service
or brand powered by your app.
Choose the right radio button
and send your app clip experience
for review.
That's it!
Of course, the app clip card
is how your users discover
the app clips you have created.
It is also where
the business you're promoting
or representing should really shine.
So it's not only really important
to make a great first impression,
but it's also the perfect opportunity
to establish a strong brand identity
of the business with your app clip.
Let's take a look
at setting up the app clip card.
You can individually set up app clip cards
per business in App Store Connect,
and you get to customize
the header image, display title, subtitle,
location association
and action per business.
For more details, please refer to
the "Design Great App Clips" video.
Next, I'll briefly walk over
setting up the app clip card.
When creating a new advanced
app clip experience in App Store Connect,
you'll be given the option
to customize your app clip card.
So first, header image.
The header image should be representative
of the business your app clip promotes.
It should use rich image and graphics
that represents the business you're
promoting in the best light possible.
So you should not show text or ads
in the header image.
The header image is shown
in both the app clip card
and the loading screen
with a vibrant background effect.
There are some additional
format requirements to keep in mind.
The header image is displayed
in 3:2 under aspect fill mode.
You should strive to upload
the highest quality image available,
and the recommended image size
is 3,000 pixels by 2,000 pixels.
Apple will automatically take care
of downscaling the image
when showing the app clip card
so that it loads quickly
in a variety of network conditions.
To make sure the image
remains crisp and clear
after it has been
automatically downscaled,
it is, again, important for you
to upload the highest quality original.
The image should be in PNG or JPG format,
and since transparency is not supported,
the image should be fully opaque.
Let's drag Fantastico.png
into App Store Connect
to update the header image.
Next, let's look at the title
and the subtitle.
Because attribution to your app
is already shown
at the bottom of your app clip card,
the title and subtitle here
should always represent the business
your app clip is promoting,
not your app itself.
If the business you're promoting has
presence in multiple regions or locales,
you should consider localizing
both the display title and the subtitle,
so that information on the app clip card
can be read and understood
by global users.
Now, let's give our app clip card
a default display title and subtitle.
Finally, for the action, you can choose
from a pre-defined list of actions
such as Open, View and Play.
Additional actions are available
in the context of the Maps app
if your app clip
is tied to a physical place.
These actions
are also automatically localized.
We look forward to hearing your feedback
for additional actions you would
like to display in the app clip card.
Let's configure an action.
I'll choose "Open (Order Food)" here,
and the app clip card preview
has updated accordingly.
And that is setting up the app clip card.
Another core part of your app clip
branding and identity are icons.
There are a few different types of icons
in the context of app clips.
First, app icon. This has existed
before iOS 14 and app clips.
It is newly shown in the app clip card
because the app clip experience is
powered by technologies in your full app.
It is shown in the App Banner
within your app clip,
because the App Banner refers users
to download your full app.
What's new here is the app clip icon
and the app clip experience icon.
Let's go over both of these
in more detail.
The app clip icon is shown when iOS
is generally referring to your app clip,
but it is not referring
to a specific business
you're representing
or promoting with your app clip.
In other words, it represents an app clip,
but does not represent
a specific app clip experience.
It is shown across the iOS system UI
just like your app icon,
such as in the multitasking switcher,
Notifications and in Settings.
iOS automatically applies
a beautiful treatment to your app icon.
Therefore, you should continue
to create square, opaque icons.
Your icon is scaled down,
and a distinctive border treatment
indicates to users this is an app clip.
The most distinctive type of icon
is the app clip experience icon,
which is sometimes also referred to
as the business icon.
The icon always represents
a particular app clip experience,
and even if your app clip powers
multiple app clip experiences,
each experience gets its own icon
to stand out in system UI.
From a technical perspective,
the app clip experience icon
is always associated with a URL,
and tapping on
the app clip experience icon
always launches the app clip
with the experience URL.
The app clip experience icon is visible
across the system UI experience,
and you'll see it in Recently Added folder
in the App Library, in Spotlight Search,
location and usage-based
Proactive suggestions,
as well as built-in apps
like Messages, Maps and Safari.
I know what you're all wondering:
"Where do these
app clip experience icons come from?"
Well, app clip experience icons
match the Maps Point of Interest icons
for businesses with a physical presence.
So it's customizable.
Businesses can upload an icon
to Maps Connect
for their app clip experience.
If the business or app clip experience
has no icon,
iOS will then automatically fall back
to the generic category icon,
such as theater, shopping,
food and parking.
To wrap things up,
if your app represents
or promotes multiple businesses,
you should consider creating advanced
app clip experiences for all of them.
To create an app clip,
you can use the same technologies
you use to build an app.
App clips are easy to build.
Just selectively include parts of your app
in your app clip build target as needed,
be it code, assets
or framework dependencies.
You should consider using
app clip-specific technologies,
such as one-time location confirmation
or ephemeral notifications,
to further streamline the experience.
Store data and credentials
in a secure shared group container
so that when your users
upgrade from the app clip to the full app,
user data can be automatically migrated.
Finally, you should upload
unique metadata and icon
of each app clip experience you create,
so that the brand identity
of every business you promote
shines through the app clip card
and across system UI.
That's "Create App Clips
for Other Businesses."
Thank you for watching this video,
and have a great WWDC!
[chimes]