Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. My name's Zeheng Chen,
and I'm a keyboard engineer.
Today I'm going to talk about AutoFill.
I'm going to share some tips
about how you can help your users
complete some everyday tasks in your app.
I'm going to talk about
AutoFilling recent addresses,
contact information,
as well as passwords and security codes.
If your app requires a log in
or a new account setup,
I will also talk about some best practices
for that.
Now let me start with an example
of how AutoFill can use recent addresses.
If you are building a navigation app,
there maybe a text field
expecting an address.
As soon as the user taps that text field,
iOS will intelligently suggest
an appropriate location.
For example,
you just checked out a restaurant
and now the keyboard will suggest
a restaurant address
right in the in QuickType bar.
So, your user is only one tap away
from inputting the address.
If you are interested
in promoting locations
from your app to the system,
you can watch the WWDC 2016 session
"Increase Usage
of Your App with Proactive Suggestions."
Another example:
You have a Calendar event coming up
and now the keyboard will suggest
event location.
Or maybe you want to go home,
and the keyboard
will suggest your home address.
Now you may be wondering:
How do I do this in my app?
Well, the good news is it's easy.
Let me show you.
You can adopt this in code.
You just need to annotate
your text field
with the UITextContentType API,
which provides the semantic meaning
of these text fields to iOS.
Here we are setting the Content Type
to fullStreetAddress,
which is all you need
to get recent address AutoFill
from the previous example.
It's that simple.
You can also set the Content Type
for a UITextView or a UITextField
directly
in the Xcode Attributes inspector.
One thing to pay attention to
is the expected semantic meaning
for each text field should be identified
as precisely as possible.
You can't combine multiple values
for one Text Content Type property.
So think about your specific use case
and find the appropriate one.
For example:
for a navigation app,
a full street address
might be the right granularity,
but for a weather app,
a city address is likely enough.
I want to pause here
and take a moment to talk about privacy.
At Apple, it's one of our core values.
Our devices are essential
to so many parts of our lives.
What we share and who we share with
should be entirely up to us.
We design our products
to protect our users' privacy
and give them control
over their information.
It's not always easy.
Sometimes building a great experience
might need some level of access
to personal information.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here I'm building a payment app
that allows users to send money
to their friends.
How can I help my users
find their intended recipient quickly?
Should I bring up a Contact Picker
and let them choose,
or should I suggest Contacts as they type?
Either way,
I probably need to request access
to their Contacts, right?
But is asking for Contact access
a good idea?
If I ask for their Contacts,
users will be prompted to allow access.
This is not only going to
interrupt their flow,
they might not even feel comfortable
sharing their Contacts.
Besides, even if they do choose
to share their Contacts with my app,
my app now has a greater risk
for potential privacy exposure
because I have access
to their personal information.
A better approach is
to use the Contact Picker API.
By using this API,
the app does not need access to Contacts
and users will not be prompted
to grant permission.
There's no prompt
because the app only has access
to the specific information that the user
chooses to share with the app.
In iOS 14,
we are now suggesting Contact information
in the QuickType keyboard
while the user types.
Just like the previous example,
the app has no access to Contacts
and so
there will be no prompt here either.
Nothing is shared with the app
until the user taps the QuickType bar
and inserts the text.
So, how do we accomplish this?
The adoption of this new Contact AutoFill
feature may look familiar to you.
Similar to recent address AutoFill,
you just set the Content Type to email
or telephone number
to get Contact AutoFill in your app.
To reiterate, if your app requires access
to users' Contacts,
try to use these two solutions first.
This way
you don't have the potential liability
of holding users' data,
you don't have to prompt users,
and you don't have to maintain custom UI
for Contact selection and suggestions.
Now let's talk about Password AutoFill.
Even if your app
has adopted Sign in with Apple,
which is the best way to get users
signed in with an account quickly,
Password AutoFill may be important
to your app
if your app has a way
to log in with usernames and passwords.
And, fortunately, it's easy to make
Password AutoFill work great in your apps.
For Password AutoFill,
you just need to tag the username
and password fields with the corresponding
content type, username: password.
The keyboard will automatically suggest
the corresponding username
and password saved in iCloud Keychain
or another password manager.
For security codes,
the Content Type you want to use
is One Time Code.
Automatic Strong Passwords can hugely
simplify the onboarding flow in your app.
By suggesting unique strong passwords
and automatically saving them
to iCloud Keychain,
this is not only quick and easy
for the user,
it also helps
increase your app's security.
An adoption couldn't be easier
as shown in the example here,
where we are using the newPassword
Content Type.
The last step is
to associate your app with a domain.
To learn how to do this,
check out "Automatic Strong Passwords and Security Code AutoFill"
from WWDC 2018.
Let's talk about the Mac.
New to macOS Big Sur,
Catalyst apps
now have security code AutoFill.
If security code AutoFill works
in your iPad apps,
it will work great on macOS.
And also new to macOS Big Sur,
AppKit based apps have full support
for password and security code AutoFill.
AppKit now has a NSTextContentType,
which is similar to UITextContentType
in UIKit.
Currently the supported values
are .username, .password and .oneTimeCode.
And one more thing that's cool
is that macOS Big Sur also supports
password manager apps as a data source
for AutoFill.
Last, but not least,
if you get one thing out of this talk,
it should be:
Tag every text field in your app.
Tag address fields, tag email fields.
Tag all text fields.
Thanks for your time. Happy AutoFilling.