Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. Welcome to "Expanding Automation
with the App Store Connect API."
My name is Geoff Coffey.
I'm an engineer on App Store Connect.
Today, we're gonna look at
some new capabilities
coming to the App Store Connect API
later this year.
We introduced this API
two years ago at WWDC
and since then, the response
from our users has been really great.
We love seeing and hearing about
how you use the API
to streamline your app development
and TestFlight programs.
For the first release,
we focused on things
you do repeatedly in App Store Connect.
Things like
managing the users on your team,
creating provisioning profiles,
adding and removing beta testers
and downloading your sales
and financial reports.
Since you do these things
over and over again,
we gave you the tools to automate them
so you have more time
to focus on your apps.
Here's where we started two years ago.
But there are important parts
of your app development workflow
that aren't covered by the API.
I'm excited to announce
two powerful new extensions
coming to the App Store Connect API
later this year.
First, we're adding
a comprehensive App Metadata API
so you can manage your presence
on the App Store,
and the new Power and Performance
Metrics and Diagnostics API
lets you programmatically access
the same aggregate data
that drives the Power and Performance
analysis tools in Xcode.
This is a huge update
to the App Store Connect API.
We've added over 200 new endpoints,
more than doubling the size
of the API in all.
You can manage app information
like your app categories,
global availability,
primary locale and license agreements.
You can make new versions
or add new platforms,
upload app previews and screenshots
and add and update localized information
like your app name, description
and keywords,
and so much more.
The API has complete coverage
of app version metadata
so you can do everything
from creating a new version
through to submitting for App Review.
I do want to note that you'll still need
to use the App Store Connect website
to manually release your app
and to configure in-app purchases
and Game Center.
With so much new to discover
and code against,
we want to make the process
of using the API as easy as possible.
So, we're also making
a full OpenAPI specification file
available to you to download.
If you're not familiar with OpenAPI,
it's the open standard version 3
of the popular Swagger format.
You can view it in the Swagger-UI
for a quick API reference,
or better yet,
feed it into a code generator
to make bootstrapping your API integration
in almost any language faster and easier.
We've also improved the documentation.
Of course,
all the new endpoints are documented,
now with clearer complete request
and response examples.
We've added
several new explanatory articles
on topics like rate limiting
and file uploads.
And we're providing
downloadable sample code
that demonstrates important API concepts
like creating and signing
authentication tokens,
interacting with API responses
and using the new asset upload APIs.
So, let's take a look at what you can do
with the new App Metadata API.
This is my app, Forest Explorer.
I've been hard at work on a new version,
and I'm ready to submit this version
to the App Store.
Let me show you
how I would do this using the new API.
We're going to focus on five areas.
We'll create a new version, set pricing,
update the app metadata,
associate a build with that version
and then submit that new version
for App Review.
Let's start by creating
a new version of our app.
In App Store Connect,
you do this on the App page
using these links here in the sidebar.
I can make a new version of my iOS app,
or I can add a macOS or tvOS version.
The API supports the same operations.
In the API,
we have a resource called Apps.
You have one of these
for each of your apps.
And each app has a relationship
to App Store Versions.
They have a platform, iOS, tvOS or macOS,
and they have a version string,
which is the version number
that you want to show in the App Store.
So all we need to do is create
a new App Store Version.
When we do that,
we'll link it to our app by ID.
So really, the first thing we need to do
is look up our app identifier.
We can do this with the API.
I'm going to do a GET on v1/apps,
and I'm going to filter by bundleID
since that's a good way to find
exactly the app I'm looking for.
If I send that request,
I get a successful 200 response.
The response contains the app resource,
and here we see the app identifier.
In the App Store Connect documentation,
you sometimes see this ID
called the Apple ID of your app.
We'll take note of this ID
and we're ready to make a new version.
We do a POST to v1/appStoreVersions,
we supply the platform
and our new versionString
and we include a relationship link
to the app.
And here's where we use that App ID
we just looked up.
I send this request,
and I get a 201 CREATED response.
This tells us App Store Connect
has created this new version.
If we were to log in
to App Store Connect right now,
we'd see this version in the sidebar.
And here in the response,
we see the identifier
App Store Connect has assigned
to this version.
Now we want to set pricing
and availability for our app.
On the App page in App Store Connect,
you start by clicking
Pricing and Availability
here in the sidebar which takes us to
the Pricing and Availability page.
And in particular, today we're going to
look at the Price Schedule.
Now, I'm not going to show it today,
but you can also use the API
to manage your app preorders
and your app's global availability.
So, how does pricing
fit into the API resource model?
Once again,
we start with the Apps Resource.
It has another relationship
to a resource called App Prices.
Each App Price has a startDate.
For the current price, this will be null.
But this is a Price Schedule,
so we may have multiple
planned future price changes.
In that case,
our app will have multiple prices,
and each additional price
will have a startDate,
which is the date that price takes effect
around the world.
Each App Price also has a Price Tier.
These are exactly the same tiers
you're familiar with
from App Store Connect.
The free tier, Tier 1, which is 99 cents
in US dollars, and so on.
To select a tier in App Store Connect,
you would normally refer to
All Prices and Currencies page.
Let me show you.
Back on the Pricing and Availability,
we click All Prices and Currencies here,
and we see a list of prices like this.
It has tiers down the side
and App Store territories across the top,
and for each tier and territory,
we see individual price points.
Each price point has two values:
the price the customer pays for the app
in the currency
relevant to that territory,
and the proceeds you will earn
for each sale.
Back on the resource model,
the price tier here
is actually a relationship
to another set of resources.
These gray resources
are read-only reference data,
the exact same data you just saw
on the All Prices and Currencies page.
Each price tier contains
a collection of price points,
one point for each app store territory.
And these price points tell you
the customer price and the proceeds.
Okay, with all of that in mind,
let's use the API to look at
the current Price Schedule for our app.
We do a GET on v1/apps
and then the ID of our app,
and then the prices relationship,
and I'm also going to include
the related priceTier
so we can see that in the response.
I execute this request
and I get back a list of prices.
In this case, we have just one price.
The startDate is null,
meaning it's currently in effect,
and here's the priceTier relationship
where I can see it's linked to Tier 1.
Let's compare this JSON data
to what we see in App Store Connect.
If we look closer at the Price Schedule,
we can see the same basic information.
We have one price,
it's currently in effect, at Tier 1.
Now, suppose we want to run
a special pricing promotion for our app.
Starting on June 29th, for one week,
let's give our app away for free.
In other words, we want
the Price Schedule to look like this.
Now we have three prices.
Tier 1 is in effect until June 29th.
Starting on June 29th,
we'll switch to the free tier.
And then a week later, on July 6th,
we want it to change back to Tier 1.
Let's make this Price Schedule change
using the API.
Although we're adding three prices,
I want to make a single atomic change
to the overall Price Schedule.
So, we're going to make a PATCH request
against the app itself.
We're not changing any app attributes,
so we leave the attribute section off,
but we are changing
the prices relationship.
Now, if you're familiar
with App Store Connect,
you know that we would normally
add the IDs of the resources
we want to associate with the app
right here.
But in this case, the app price resources
don't actually exist yet.
We need to create them
and attach them to the app,
all in a single request.
Since the prices don't exist,
they don't have IDs,
so let's assign them temporary IDs
for now.
We have three prices,
so we need three temporary IDs.
I'll use new-price-1, new-price-2
and new-price-3.
You can use any values you want
for these temporary IDs.
The important things is
I'm using this syntax
with a dollar sign
and braces around the ID.
That serves as a signal to the API
that this is a temporary ID
for a resource that doesn't exist yet,
one that we will be defining
in this same request.
Now we need to define
those new app price resources.
Here's the first one.
We give it the first temporary ID
of new-price-1,
again with that dollar sign syntax.
It has a startDate of null, meaning this
is the price we want right now.
You can also just leave the startDate off
in this scenario.
It would do the same thing.
And finally, we link it with Tier 1.
Next, we define the second price.
It looks like this.
It has an ID of new-price-2,
a startDate of June 29th,
and we link it to Tier 0, the free tier.
And finally, we define new-price-3
with a date of July 6,
and we'll switch back to priceTier 1.
Now bear in mind,
we haven't sent any requests
for this Price Schedule change.
We're still building the JSON payload
for that single atomic request
I talked about before.
Here's the request we were working on.
And now we need to add the prices
we just defined into this request.
We add an "included" section
to our request entity,
and then we take those three new prices
and insert them into this included array.
The final payload looks like this,
or at least as much of it
as I can fit on the screen.
Now, the order of the resources
in the included array doesn't matter.
The important thing is
that these temporary IDs up here
match one-to-one
with the temporary IDs down here.
When we send this request,
App Store Connect
will create these three prices,
assign them real IDs
and link them to our app,
all in one atomic operation.
Let's send it.
We get back a 200 response,
and our new Price Schedule is now applied.
Now, it's important to note
that price changes
and available territory changes
go to the App Store right away.
If your app is already released,
the changes will take effect immediately.
They will not wait for your next version
to go through App Review
and then be released.
So when experimenting with the API,
be sure not to test on live apps.
Now let's talk about
editing your app metadata.
This is a really big area in the API
with lots of endpoints,
so let me show you around first.
Back on our Version page,
I can click App Information,
and that takes me to a page
where we see app-level information
including the localized app name,
subtitle and privacy policy
and the App Store categorization.
And if we click here on our version,
we see version-level information.
This is metadata that changes
on a platform-by-platform basis
like screenshots, promotional text
and keywords.
The API resource model
works in much the same way.
Here's what we've seen so far.
The app also has a relationship
to a resource called App Info.
This is where you'll find
app-level information
like your App Store categorization.
And some of that app information
is localized,
so each App Info has a relationship
to multiple App Info Localizations,
one for each locale.
Here you'll find attributes like app name,
subtitle and privacy policy.
And, of course, there's localized data
at the version level too.
We call this resource
the App Store Version Localization.
The version has one of these
for each locale as well.
Let's flip back to App Store Connect
and look a little closer
at our version page.
I'm looking at
the US English localization here,
and if we look closer at screenshots
and app previews,
we see we have multiple display types
like the 6.5-inch iPhone,
the 5.5-inch iPhone
or the 12.9-inch iPad Pro.
Within each display type,
we can upload up to three previews
and up to ten screenshots.
All of this is modeled in the API
through resources
and relationships as well.
The version localization
has a relationship
to multiple app screenshot sets,
one for each display type.
The localization also has
multiple app preview sets.
And finally, each screenshot set has
a relationship to multiple screenshots,
and each preview set to multiple previews.
There's a lot more
to app version metadata,
but these are the major resources
we'll talk about today.
So let's say we want to upload
a 6.5-inch iPhone app preview
in the US English localization
to promote my new version.
In other words,
let's find the US English localization,
get the app preview set
and add a new preview to it.
Every version has
at least one localization:
the one in your app's primary locale.
We can fetch that localization
for our versions like this.
We issue a GET request to
the appStoreVersionLocalizations URL
for our version ID.
The response includes
all of our localizations
including this one for US English.
And down here we see the related URL
for the appPreviewSets.
Let's GET this URL,
and we get back an empty data array.
This tells us we don't have any
app preview sets for this localization.
So, let's add one.
As you probably would guess,
we POST to v1/appPreviewSets.
We'll use a previewType of IPHONE_65,
that's the 6.5-inch iPhone,
and we link it to the localization
we were just looking at by ID.
We send this request,
and the preview set has been created.
Now we're ready to add an app preview.
We send this request,
and the preview set has been created.
But a preview is more than
just some attributes and relationships.
You have a video file that you need
to upload to App Store Connect.
This is a type of API interaction
you've never seen before
in the App Store Connect API,
so let's step back a minute
and look at how this works.
App previews are just one type of file
you can upload using the API.
You could also upload screenshots,
App Review attachments
and GeoJSON routing app coverage files.
But whatever you're uploading,
the fundamental problem is the same:
you have this file on your disk,
we call it an asset,
and you want to get it up
to App Store Connect.
But the Internet is standing in the way.
Our asset upload process
is a multi-step process
designed to ensure that you can get
even large video files
into App Store Connect
as quickly as possible,
and get them there reliably
even if the Internet connection
isn't always perfectly reliable.
It works like this.
First, you create a reservation.
Then you upload the actual assets,
possibly in multiple parts.
Then you commit the asset.
And finally, you check for errors.
Let's try it out.
You create an app preview reservation
by doing a POST to v1/appPreviews.
And you tell App Store Connect
the name of the file you'll be uploading
and the file size in bytes.
You link it to the preview set
we just created,
and App Store Connect reserves a place
for this preview.
It uses the file size
to create a set of upload operations.
For small assets, this is simple:
just an HTTP PUT operation
to upload the data to our servers.
But for large assets,
we will send you back multiple operations.
Each operation
includes the same properties:
an HTTP method, a URL, a length in bytes,
an offset in bytes
and a set of request headers.
You then take these operations
and use the information in them
to split your asset into multiple parts:
one part for each operation.
You'll use the length and offset values
in each operation
to determine the range of bytes
in the file associated with each part.
Note that you should always be prepared
to receive multiple operations.
We may use various factors to decide
how many operations are needed.
So, an asset that you upload
in just one part today
might require multiple parts tomorrow.
So your code should always expect the
possibility of multiple upload operations.
Okay. With our asset split into parts,
we're ready for step number two.
Using the method, URL and request headers
in each upload operation,
you upload the associated part.
You can do this one at a time
or you can upload multiple parts at once.
You can upload these parts in any order.
It doesn't matter at all.
Of course, sometimes the upload will fail.
That's okay. Just try the part again.
If one part fails, there's no need
to re-upload the other parts.
Just keep trying
until all of the parts are up.
Once they are,
you're ready for step number three,
which is to commit the asset.
To do this, you PATCH the preview URL
and mark the preview uploaded
by setting its uploaded attribute to true.
You also need to provide an MD5 checksum
of the original source file.
App Store Connect will use this checksum
to make sure the multiple parts
were divided and uploaded correctly.
We send this request.
App Store Connect
then reassembles the asset,
validates the checksum,
checks the file integrity,
like, is this actually a video file,
and checks various metrics
like video length,
dimensions and audio track.
If everything looks good,
the asset is marked complete,
and your app preview
is ready to submit for review.
Bear in mind that asset processing
is asynchronous.
For large assets, it may take some time.
You can use the API to re-fetch an asset
at any time to check on its status.
If we fetch the app preview,
we can check its state attribute
right here.
Once validation is successful,
the asset state will switch to COMPLETE.
If anything goes wrong,
the state will instead change to FAILED
and the errors array will tell you
what went wrong
so you can delete the asset,
fix the problem and re-upload.
We looked closely at app previews
and a few other
app metadata-related resources today,
but we only scratched the surface.
There's lots more metadata
you can manage and edit with the API.
Be sure to check out the new
App Metadata section in the documentation.
It has a complete list of API endpoints
related to app and version metadata.
Now let's look at adding a build
to our new version.
In App Store Connect,
you do this on the version page
in the Build section right here.
Where does that fit
into our resource model?
Right here. The App Store version has
a relationship to its associated build.
Of course, you don't actually
create builds with the API.
You create your builds with Xcode
and you upload them using Xcode
or using Transporter.
So presumably, the build is already
in App Store Connect.
We just need to look up its ID
and associate it with the version.
This is probably starting
to look familiar to you now.
We GET v1/builds.
I'm gonna filter by the app ID,
the pre-release version number
and the build version number.
And from the response,
I'll grab the build ID.
Now we can PATCH the build relationship
on our new version with that build ID.
We send it in and we get back
this 204 NO CONTENT response.
Since this was a relationship update,
there's no resource data to return.
So, this is a successful response message
telling us the build
and version IDs were valid,
and they're now correctly associated
with each other.
With metadata complete and a build added,
we're ready to submit for Review.
In App Store Connect,
this is a three-step process.
First, we provide the contact info,
demo account
and any notes that App Review may need.
Then, if necessary,
we can upload attachments.
And finally, we click submit for review.
In the API, we once again start
with the App Store version.
It has a relationship
to App Store Review Details,
where you can add information
for App Review.
This in turn has
multiple App Review attachments.
These work just like app previews,
allowing you to upload files
to App Store Connect.
To add App Review details
to a new version,
just POST to v1/appReviewDetails,
provide the necessary information
and associate it with the version.
And we're good. App Review details
are now attached to our version.
If you've already added
App Review details,
you can edit them using a PATCH instead.
You can edit this information
as often as you want
up to the point
where you actually submit for review.
Now let's see how we do that.
How do we actually click
that Submit for Review button
using the API?
Once again, we have another resource.
It's called
the App Store Version Submission.
To submit a version to the App Store,
we just create one of these.
We POST
to v1/appStoreVersionSubmissions,
link it to our version
and send the request.
And that's it.
Our version is on its way to App Review.
If we made a mistake
and want to pull this app back
before it gets reviewed,
we can just delete this
App Store Version Submission resource.
Of course, if our version isn't ready yet,
say we forgot to add screenshots,
then creating a submission will fail
with a 400 response
and that response
will contain error messages
explaining what we need to fix.
And remember,
if your version requires in-app purchases
or Game Center configurations,
you'll need to set those up
in the App Store Connect website
before you submit for review.
That's the App Metadata API.
Hopefully this gives you a sense of
how these API resources all fit together.
Using them, we were able
to successfully create a version,
provide all the necessary
App Store information
and send it in to App Review.
If we have auto-release enabled,
our app will go to the App Store
as soon as review is complete.
You can also release manually
in App Store Connect on the web
or on iOS if you prefer.
Now let's turn
to the new Power and Performance
Metrics and Diagnostics API.
This is the Power and Performance view
in Xcode.
It helps you monitor
app performance indicators
like memory usage, launch time, hang rate,
disk writes and battery consumption
using data collected
from real customer sessions.
You can access this same information
using the API.
I'm going to give you a high level view
of how to access this data
and how it fits into
the larger API resource model.
But we actually have a whole session
devoted to this feature
where you'll learn more
about this new API,
including how to interpret
the response data
and find insights
into your app's behavior.
So be sure to check out
the "Power and Performance
App Store Connect API"
session video as well.
You can get performance metrics
for recent versions of your app
by requesting the perfPowerMetrics
relationship off the app URL.
The metrics data uses a custom media type,
so you need
an appropriate Accept header as well.
That will get you metrics
for recent versions of your app,
but you can also fetch metrics
for a particular build
using the perfPowerMetrics relationship
off the build URL instead.
Either way, once we send this request,
we get back a successful response
with a structured set of metrics data.
In this, I can see that the first set
of metrics are HANG metrics
and the first data set is the hang rate
expressed in seconds per hour.
Check out that other session
to see the rest of this response
and learn how to interpret this data.
But there are two more endpoints
I want to show you.
For Disk Writes in particular,
once you've identified a problem spot,
you can view diagnostic information,
including call stacks,
to help pinpoint the source
of potential problems.
In Xcode, we show you a list
of diagnostic signatures.
These are just places in your app
where you do disk writes.
These signatures are sorted by percentage
contribution to total disk writes,
so the biggest contributors
are up at the top.
And for each diagnostic signature,
you can view the actual call stack
and additional diagnostic details.
You can get this same information
using the API.
Once again, we start with the build URL
and we fetch its new
diagnosticSignatures relationship.
Let's get it.
And the API responds
with a list of diagnostic signatures.
These are standard App Store Connect
API resources.
They have a signature attribute.
This identifies where in your run time
the disk write takes place
and a weight which tells you how much this
signature contributes to total writes.
Each signature also has
a relationship to its log data.
If we take this link and once again use
that custom media type,
we get back diagnostic data.
In addition to app information
and total disk writes,
you'll find detailed call stack
information in this response.
And that's the App Metadata
and Power and Performance
Metrics and Diagnostic APIs.
Together these represent a big update
to the App Store Connect API.
We look forward to seeing
how you take advantage of them. Thank you.