Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello everyone.
My name is Rich Forster,
and I'm a GPU software engineer at Apple.
In this session, I'm going to talk to you
about the new function pointers API
that we've added to Metal this year.
Let's start
with the humble function pointer.
Function pointers give us the power
to refer to code that we can call.
They make our code extensible
by allowing us to write our code
so that it can later call code
that we have never seen before.
The classic example is the callback,
where execution jumps to code
identified with a function pointer.
This lets us provide functions
for plug-ins,
specializations or notifications.
But we can do so much more.
Today I am going to talk about how we
expose function pointer support in Metal
and how we use visible functions
to achieve our goals.
I will cover the different
compilation models we support,
what they mean, and when to use them.
I will then discuss
tables of visible functions
and finish with a discussion
of performance.
So let's start
with function pointers in Metal.
When we added function pointers to Metal,
we knew there would be
a range of opportunities to use them.
The obvious case is ray tracing,
where we use function pointers
to specify
our custom intersection functions.
And I would encourage you
to watch the ray tracing talk
which accompanies this session.
Ray tracing is also a great place
to talk about other uses
of function pointers,
and that's where I'd like to start today.
When we apply ray tracing
to the classic Cornell Box,
we fire our rays into the scene,
and when they hit surfaces,
we need to shade the intersections.
Typically, we have the material
for the surface that we intersect,
and then we will continue tracing
until we hit a light,
at which point we will evaluate
the contribution of the light.
Let's revisit the process flow
for ray tracing.
First, we generate rays
which start from the camera
and are emitted into the scene.
We then test those rays for intersection
with the geometry in the scene.
Next, we compute a color
at each intersection point
and update the image.
This process is called shading.
The shading process
can also generate additional rays.
So we test those rays
for intersection with the scene
and repeat this process
as many times as we'd like
to simulate light
bouncing around the scene.
Today, we're going to simplify things
for this presentation
and start by considering a path tracer
that performs a single intersection
and then shades the result
of that intersection.
This will be in a single computer kernel
that creates a compute pipeline
that includes the code
for each of these three stages.
However,
the stage I want to focus on is shading.
This is the last step
before we output our image
and provides a range of opportunities
to use function pointers.
Within our ray tracing kernel,
shading happens near the end.
Once we have an intersection,
we find the matching material
and perform our shading for that material.
In this example,
all of our material and lighting code
lives in the shade function
which exists elsewhere in our file.
Let's dig deeper into the shade function.
Our shade function has several steps.
This is a simple path tracer,
so it immediately calculates the lighting
from the light
at the intersection point on the surface.
And then we use the material to apply
that lighting at the intersection point.
In terms of flow, we can consider lighting
and material as separate stages.
But there's more than one type of light
and more than one type of material.
We can break lighting
into separate types of light,
which will require different code
for each light type.
And the code for materials can be
even more varied than the code for lights.
We are going to use
the new visible function type in Metal
to help us work with our lighting
and material functions.
Visible is a new function qualification
attribute like vertex, fragment or kernel.
We can use the visible attributes
on function definitions,
and when we use the visible attribute,
we are declaring
that we want to manipulate
the function from the Metal API.
We check if we can use the API to perform
this manipulation with the device query.
With visible functions,
we can consider our code
as a flexible object that we can refer to.
In this case, let's consider the code
for our area lights.
That code is an object
that can exist outside of the kernel
that represents our pipeline.
The code can exist in another Metal file
or another Metal library.
To declare our lighting function
as visible,
we add the visible attribute
before the definition of the function.
This will allow us to create
a Metal function object
to represent the code in this function.
Our next step is to connect
our Metal shader code to our pipeline
so that we can call it.
First, we wrap our area light code
in a Metal function object.
Then the new Metal function object
can be added to the pipeline.
With the visible attribute
on our area light function,
we can wrap it in a Metal function object
on the CPU.
We create a Metal function object by name
for our visible function
using the standard methods.
We then add the function object
to the compute pipeline descriptor
as part of the linkedFunctions
to allow the pipeline creation process
to add it to the pipeline so that we can
refer to it later with a function pointer.
Now that we're talking about adding
visible functions to our pipelines,
we need to discuss the compilation
model choices that we have available.
Once we have Metal function objects
for each of our lighting
and material functions,
we can add them to our pipeline.
When we build our pipeline, we can take
a copy of each of those visible functions.
We call this "single compilation,"
since we then have a single object
that represents our pipeline
and all of the visible functions
that it uses.
We use the same linkedFunctions object
that we saw earlier
to list the functions that we may call
from our pipeline.
Then we create our ComputePipelineState
using the standard pipeline creation API.
The creation of our pipeline
results in an object
that contains both a specialized version
of our kernel code
and specialized copies
of all of our functions.
This specialization is similar
to link-time optimization,
where the kernel code
and the visible functions
can be optimized based on their usage.
However, this optimization can increase
the time taken to create our pipeline
and results in a larger pipeline object
due to the copies of the function objects
that we add into the pipeline.
But what we may want to do is have our
function objects outside of our pipeline
as separate objects that our pipeline
can call but does not have to copy.
This is the foundation
of a separately compiled pipeline.
When we create each Metal function object,
we can compile each function
to a stand-alone GPU binary form
so that we can keep
the function code separate
and reuse it across multiple pipelines.
To compile our functions to binary,
we will use a function descriptor.
This allows us to add options to
the creation of a Metal function object.
In the case of creating our function,
this snippet of code creates
the same resulting Metal function
as the same method with a name parameter.
However, the functionDescriptor lets us
specify more configuration options.
We request binary precompilation
by using the "options" property
of the descriptor.
The function creation will now precompile
our function to binary.
We then provide our new function
in the binary function's array
of the linkedFunctions object.
This indicates that we are referring
to the binary version of the function
rather than requesting
copying and specialization of the function
for the compute pipeline.
As you can see, we can mix and match
precompiled functions
with those we want specialized.
And then we use the standard call
to create the pipeline, as before.
Now that we have covered both single
and separate compilation,
this is a good point
to compare the advantages of each.
For single compilation, we create visible
functions using our standard methods.
For separate compilation,
we will precompile to binary
to allow us to share the compile binary
and avoid the binary compilation
of our function during pipeline creation.
When we configure our pipeline descriptor,
we use the functions array
to indicate that we want them specialized
and the binaryFunctions array to indicate
that we want to use the binary versions.
The result of specialization
is a larger pipeline
in the single-compilation case.
Separate compilation
will result in a pipeline
that adds calls to binary functions,
and the binary functions will be shared.
Specialization of functions also requires
a longer pipeline creation time
than adding calls to binary functions.
As I mentioned earlier, this is similar
to link-time optimization,
where the compiler can take advantage
of knowing the whole pipeline
but requires extra build time
to apply the specializations.
All of that function specialization
means that single compilation
has the best runtime performance.
The flexibility
of the separately compiled pipeline
means that there is some runtime overhead
to calling our binary functions.
As we saw earlier,
you can mix sets of precompiled functions
and functions for specialization,
but a fully specialized,
single-compilation pipeline
will offer the best performance.
It should always be possible
to create a new single-compilation
pipeline in the background
to replace any separately compiled
functions in an existing pipeline.
Going back
to our separate compilation pipeline,
we have our array of functions available
to call from the pipeline.
However, whenever you think
you have a fixed set of functions,
another function always appears.
In this case, we have a new wood material
that we want to add to our pipeline.
Incremental compilation is intended
for adding new functions
to an existing pipeline.
The appearance of new functions
is typically quite common
in dynamic environments,
especially games where streaming
may load new assets with new shaders.
Putting this into code,
first we need to make the choice
to support incremental compilation
when we create
our initial compute pipeline.
The default is to not support
incremental compilation
because enabling the later addition
of binary functions
means that pipeline creation has to expect
possible calls to binary functions
even if none are specified
at pipeline creation time.
We then use a function descriptor
to create the Metal function object
for our wood shader
as a precompiled binary function.
Finally, we use a newly added method
on ComputePipelineState
to create a compute pipeline
with any additional binary functions.
Next, I want to talk
about visible function tables.
Visible function tables
are how we pass function pointers
to our visible functions to the GPU.
Going back to the set
of the lighting and material functions
that we considered for our shading,
we need to provide these
to the kernel running on the GPU.
To allow us to group
our related functions together
and pass them to the GPU,
we create visible function tables
using the Metal API.
Visible function tables are then an object
that we can pass to our Metal shader code.
Before we start,
let's add some using declarations
to define our function pointer types to
avoid making our code examples too wordy.
Visible function tables can be specified
as kernel parameters,
and they use buffer binding points.
We can also pass them in argument buffers.
Then, in our shaders,
we access our functions by index.
We can take a pointer to the function
or call it directly from the table.
On the CPU,
we allocate the visible function tables
from the ComputePipelineState
based on the number of function entries
we want in the table.
We then populate the table
with handles to the functions
that we specified
when creating the pipeline state.
Finally, when we come to use the table,
we set it on our computeCommandEncoder
or argumentEncoder as required.
Don't forget to call useResource
if using an argumentEncoder.
To ensure that using
incrementally compiled pipelines
is as low-cost as possible,
we ensure that you can reuse
the visible function tables
from the ancestor pipelines.
The handles that are already in the table
are still valid,
and you just need to add
the new function handles to the table.
You do not need to create and build
an entirely new table.
And finally, you just need to make sure
that you do not access the newly added
function handles from older pipelines.
Last but not least today,
I want to discuss
the performance considerations
of using function pointers
in your application.
There's three main areas
we will cover in performance.
Let's start with function groups
for optimization.
Going back to our earlier diagram,
we could already see that we had groups
of functions for specific purposes.
However, pipeline creation is unaware
of these relationships.
We can group the functions
based upon their use in the shader.
We know which functions
we will be using for lighting
and which we will use for materials.
To express the grouping of functions
in our shading function,
we've updated it to include
function groups for the calls we make.
In Metal,
function groups let us tell the compiler
where the functions will be used.
In our shader code,
we apply function groups attributes
to the lines where we invoke our functions
to give names
to the group of possible functions
that are callable from that location.
Then, when configuring
our compute pipeline descriptor,
we specify the groups in a dictionary
with the setter functions
that may be called for each group.
This gives the compiler
the maximum amount of information possible
and can help with the optimization
when generating the pipeline.
On top of the specialization
that the compiler performs
for functions in our functions array,
the compiler is able to take advantage
of any commonalities
between the setter functions in each group
and then apply that to the call site
marked with the function groups attribute.
All this new flexibility also means that
you can now implement recursive functions.
If we go back to where we started
with the ray tracing process flow,
this model of ray tracing,
where we consider multiple bounces,
can be implemented in either an iterative
or recursive manner.
If we focus on the relationship
between intersection and shading,
we can follow this call graph.
With our recursive path tracer,
after an intersection,
we shade the intersection point.
In this case,
we hit our new wood material function.
This wood material includes
a reflection component,
and so it intersects another ray with
the scene and shades the intersection.
Again, we intersect a surface
covered in the wood material.
This then reflects
and intersects the scene again.
We hit the wood material one more time.
We could continue, but typically you would
limit the depth in a recursive ray tracer
for both performance
and to avoid overflowing the stack,
so we will stop here.
To support the varying stack usage
for compute kernels
that call chains of visible functions,
we expose the maxCallStackDepth property
on the compute pipeline descriptor
so that we can specify how deep we expect
to call functions from our kernel.
The default is 1
so that the typical use cases of visible
functions and intersection functions
work out of the box.
This value is expected to be used
for any chains of visible function calls,
but in the case of ray tracing,
this code could have been written
in an iterative manner
to reduce stack usage.
The last performance consideration
I want to discuss today
was the impact of divergence
when we use function pointers.
Before diving into function pointers,
though,
I should highlight that last year's
"Ray Tracing with Metal" presentation
covered high-level methods to handle
the divergence inherent in ray tracing
when subsequent bounces
become less coherent.
This included ray coherency
with block linear layout,
ray compaction for active rays
and interleaved tiling
for load balancing across GPUs.
I recommend reviewing that presentation
for a great review of ideas
of ray tracing optimizations.
For function pointers, however,
we need to consider divergence
at the thread level.
When we dispatch our threadgroups,
we know that they execute
in smaller groups of threads,
defined as a SIMD group.
In this example,
we have eight SIMD groups.
The threads in the SIMD group perform best
when they execute the same instruction
at the same time.
Divergence occurs
when the next instruction to execute
is different
for the threads of the SIMD group,
typically, when they reach a branch
in our shader code.
This is normally handled
by letting a subset of the threads
execute their instruction
while the other threads are left unused.
We have the best performance
when all threads are actively executing
useful instructions.
Function pointers are another case
that can lead to divergence.
When we invoke a function
via a function pointer,
we need to consider how divergent
the setter function pointers will be.
In the worst case, within a SIMD group,
each thread
could be calling a different function,
and the execution time
will be the time to execute
each of the required functions
one after the other.
But if we consider the entire threadgroup,
we may have enough work
to create full SIMD groups.
To handle our divergence,
we are going to reorder the function calls
to introduce coherence to our SIMD groups.
This means that the function call
for one thread
will likely be executed
by another thread in the threadgroup.
In terms of code, we will start
by writing all the function parameters
and the index of the thread
and the function to call
to threadgroup memory.
We will then use our favorite sort
to sort a function indices.
Next, we invoke the functions
in their sorted order.
The results of the functions
go back to threadgroup memory,
and then each thread
can read its result from there.
We can also implement a similar version
using device memory
for our parameters and results.
In the case of calling complex functions,
this should reduce the overhead
of divergence.
There's a lot of great things you can do
with function pointers in Metal.
Today we've covered the creation and use
of visible functions
and how we add them
to visible function tables
to provide functions
that we can call from our compute kernels.
We've discussed
the different compilation models
that allow you to choose
how you balance pipeline size
and creation time
against runtime performance
and needing to be able
to dynamically add functions.
And we finished
on some performance considerations
for using function pointers
in your application.
I've really enjoyed
working on function pointers this year,
and I'm really glad
to be able to share it with you.
I hope you've had a great WWDC.