Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Danny Mandel,
and welcome to "Expand Your SiriKit
Media Intents to More Platforms."
We've got an exciting mix
of SiriKit Media new features
and experiences for you this year.
We've got a lot to talk about.
We're putting a particular emphasis
on SiriKit Media Intents
in the home this year.
As part of that,
we'll be opening up to new platforms.
Additionally,
we have some new features to discuss.
Finally,
we'll finish up with some new ways
to make your SiriKit Media experience
even faster.
So let's dive right in
to the new SiriKit Media platforms.
Last year, we made a great experience
for you on the go,
and this year we're bringing
that same great experience
to one of the places
you listen to music the most--
in the home.
On HomePod,
we're using the same media intents
and a new cloud playback API
to take advantage
of the unique characteristics
of the HomePod in the Apple Home.
You'll want to check out
the full developer program details
at developer.apple.com/siri.
We're happy to announce
that SiriKit Media Intents
also now work on Apple TV.
In addition to your iOS apps,
we know many of you
have custom Apple TV experiences,
and we wanted to open up SiriKit Media
to those apps as well.
Now I'll hand it over
to my colleague Ryan Klems
to give us a demo of the new
Apple TV functionality in action.
Last year, in iOS 13 and watchOS 6,
we introduced SiriKit Media Intent
handling for your media applications.
This year, we're happy to announce
that we've brought that same functionality
to tvOS 14.
Now you can add Siri support
to your applications on the big screen.
SiriKit Media Intents
allow you to add a wide variety
of natural language queries
to your application.
You can do simple searches:
Play music on ControlAudio.
You can ask to play a band:
Play the band Khruangbin on ControlAudio.
You can ask to play a song by an artist:
Play the song "Be Kind"
by Marshmello and Halsey on ControlAudio...
and many more.
So how do you do that?
Adding SiriKit Media Intent handling
to your tvOS application
is done the same way
you would add the support to iOS.
Please see the 2019 WWDC session,
"Introducing SiriKit Media Intents,"
for more information on the steps to add
the extension target to your application.
Now, let's do a quick recap of how
we handle natural language requests
in SiriKit Media apps.
The intent handler is the key class
in handling SiriKit Media requests,
and the key method to implement
is resolveMediaItems.
resolveMediaItems is where you
evaluate the INPlayMediaIntent object
that is received by your application
and perform a search to turn it
into the concrete media item
that you want your app to play.
After you resolve the media item,
your handler will be called,
and this will cause your application
to be launched so you can begin playback.
One difference with tvOS
is that the customer is
generally only interacting
with one application at a time,
and as a result, a foreground app launch
is likely the more preferred interaction.
Unlike on iOS where a background launch
is more likely the preferred interaction.
You control this by returning
continueInApp
from your handle method
instead of handleInApp.
So, with the same few short steps
that we showed you last year,
you can add the ability
for your application
to play audio content through Siri
on tvOS.
We were very excited
to see all the great adoptions
of SiriKit Media Intents last year
on iOS and watchOS
and are looking forward to seeing
what you do on tvOS this year.
Thanks for that awesome demo, Ryan.
Now I want to switch from platforms
to new features
that make the experience of asking Siri
to listen to music even easier.
As we work through these examples,
we'll be using our example app,
ControlAudio,
which was introduced at WWDC19.
So let's talk about
the new Siri alternatives UI.
So, let's take a look at the current
SiriKit Media experience
in the new compact Siri UI.
We ask to play a song
from the album New Me, Same Us.
ControlAudio chose a single song to play,
and playback begins.
There isn't a way
to present more information than this,
so we're only able to play that one song.
We all know that sometimes
we want something slightly different
than what starts playing.
So we've made it easier
to make tweaks on the fly,
without having to open the app and disrupt
whatever you're doing while on the go.
We do so with the new
alternatives UI in SiriKit Media.
We can see that someone asked
to play that same song,
and Siri started playing it for them.
However, we can now also see this new menu
that says "Maybe You Wanted,"
and if we tap on it,
we are taken to the following UI.
And as you can see here,
there are a number of different songs
from the same album
that someone might have wanted instead
of the one that ControlAudio chose.
Now we can tap on any one of those options
to start playing that
instead of the first choice.
And that is the new
SiriKit Media Alternatives UI.
So how do we make this work?
It ends up being quite simple.
In your current
resolveMediaItems method,
you're probably calling the success
with resolvedMediaItem method
on INMediaItemResolutionResult.
Now, that method is going to return
a single media item resolution result.
In order to return multiple items,
all you need to do is switch over
to the new plural version,
successes with resolvedMediaItems,
and anything
after the first item in the list
will show up as an alternative.
So the next question you may ask
is how do you handle the taps
when someone chooses
one of the alternatives?
All that happens when someone taps
on one of the alternatives
is that the media item they've tapped on
is set as the media item
in the INPlayMediaIntent
that is passed to handle.
What this means
is that you can handle this
just as you handle
any other INPlayMediaIntent today.
Let's see the code change we need to make
in order to get SiriKit Media
alternatives working.
The first thing we're gonna do
is open our intent handler
in our sample project, ControlAudio.
And we'll navigate
to our resolveMediaItems method.
[typing continues]
Currently, we're calling
the singular version of the method
success with:
So let's run the app and see what it does.
Play a song from New Me, Same Us
on ControlAudio.
[Siri] Here's "Where You Belong"
by Little Dragon on ControlAudio.
All right, we can see
that it started playback,
but there are no alternatives.
So let's go back to Xcode,
kill the process,
and update the method
to return multiple media items
instead of just a single one.
[typing]
So now we're calling
the plural version of the method
successes with:
Let's run the app
and see what it does this time.
Play a song from <New Me, Same Us
on ControlAudio.
[Siri] "Where You Belong" by Little Dragon
now playing on ControlAudio.
All right now we have alternatives.
Let's go play one.
And I'll play "New Fiction."
And we can see that it started playing.
It's just that easy
to get the new alternative support
hooked up in SiriKit Media.
Now let's talk about
some performance improvements
that are new to SiriKit Media this year.
Last year, when we launched
SiriKit Media Intents,
we required the use
of an intents extension
to adopt your SiriKit Media functionality.
This year, there's a new way
to handle SiriKit Media Intents--
in-app intent handling.
In-app intent handling moves all
the intent handling stages into your app
rather than in an extension.
An advantage here
is that it avoids a process launch,
as you don't need to launch
your intents extension and your app
to start a background audio session.
You only need to launch your app.
However,
because it's launching your full app,
this could potentially mean
a slower Siri response time
during the resolve phase.
Intents extensions are small, lightweight
processes optimized for quick launching,
so you will definitely need
to tune your full app launch experience
to get the same quick response out of it.
One other benefit you could see
is that you can start the player
warming phase much earlier in your app,
since you'll be implementing
resolve there.
So, if you know you need to kick off
network requests to fetch credentials,
you can start that
at the beginning of resolve
and ensure that the player
is 100% initialized
by the time you get to handle the intent.
I refer you to the presentation,
"Integrate Intents with Your App,"
to get the full details
on in-app intent handling.
For those of you with existing
extension-based implementations,
we also have a performance boost
this year via app pre-warming.
Looking at your existing
SiriKit Media implementation,
we go through the standard resolve,
confirm and handle phases,
and then once all those are complete,
we issue a background app launch
for your app to begin playback.
This does provide
for a nice separation of concerns
in that the extension can contain
all the intent handling logic,
and the app can handle the playback logic.
However,
it can delay important app concerns
such as playback engine setup
or credential fetching
until much later than they need to be.
With app pre-warming,
SiriKit will get your app fired up earlier
and have playback ready to go
once your extension is complete.
It's important to note that app pre-warming
does require some additional work
in your app,
so you'll want to work with us
to make sure you get it working properly.
And last, there are benefits and drawbacks
to both in-app intent handling
and app pre-warming,
so you're going to need
to evaluate the pros and cons
for your particular implementation
to see what works best for you.
We wanted to let everyone
in the developer community know
that, as the saying goes,
we're eating our own dog food.
We're thrilled to have a common
framework for our bug fixes,
new features, and performance improvements
that both you and the Siri team at Apple
can benefit from.
Thank you, and we hope you enjoy
giving people great, new
SiriKit Media experiences this year.