Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Mike Boylan
and I'm a senior consulting engineer
supporting enterprise and education.
I'm excited to be here with you today
alongside my colleague Sudhakar
to discuss enterprise identity
and authentication.
Apple's focus on security extends beyond
just our software, hardware and services.
For organizations
that deploy Apple devices at any scale,
identity has become the centerpiece
of how users authenticate to devices,
Web sites, apps and services.
And it's a critical part
of ensuring security across our platform.
It's no surprise
that identity and authentication
have been getting
more and more complicated.
All enterprise apps or Web sites
need to authenticate a user
in order to function.
These apps connect to systems of record
either in the cloud, on premise, or both.
So how do organizations
deal with these challenges?
To help with what's out there,
Apple has built a number of tools
and technologies
that streamline how organizations
can leverage identity
across devices, Web sites,
apps and services.
We view identity as something
that needs to be tightly integrated
into our operating systems
in order to provide
a seamless, nearly invisible experience
for our users.
This empowers users to work from anywhere
while giving IT
the visibility and control that they need
to feel comfortable enabling that.
This session will focus
on three different technologies
and how they can be used together
in practice,
along with what's new this year.
We'll cover device authentication
and macOS account types,
single sign-on extensions,
and Managed Apple IDs
and federated authentication.
Let's start by talking about
device authentication.
Identity on our devices often starts
at the lock or log-in screen.
Here's an example of a Shared iPad
and a shared Mac
where users can select their account,
enter their credentials,
and see this personalized experience.
On iPadOS,
this is enabled by Managed Apple ID,
and on macOS, accounts can be local,
or come from the network.
On this Mac,
we can see identity playing a role
even during the initial deployment process
when a device is getting assigned
to one specific user.
Last year, we added a new feature
called enrollment customization
which allows a web page,
like you see here, to load during setup,
and can allow for a user to authenticate
using modern authentication methods.
User information
from the authentication process
can then be used to pre-populate
the local account name
and short name for the user
in the macOS setup assistant,
optionally locking them into place.
So that assumes
the user is using a local account.
On the Mac,
there are two primary types of accounts:
local accounts
and network, or mobile, accounts.
Mobile accounts
are a specific type of network account.
Depending on different
deployment scenarios over the years,
organizations have used
either type of these accounts,
or sometimes both depending on use case.
Mobile accounts and network accounts
are where organizational identity
first started on the Mac,
years before mobile devices
like iPhone and iPad were around
or as prevalent as they are today.
They existed primarily
to help with shared devices
in settings like computer labs,
but they make much less sense
to be used today,
especially in 1:1 deployment scenarios.
Using local accounts on macOS
is our recommendation
whenever possible for 1:1 deployments.
The user record
is stored locally on the Mac,
and the source of truth
for the authentication
is the local macOS directory services.
This helps ensure that
there are no unnecessary log-in delays,
and password management
happens locally on the Mac.
Now, we get a lot of questions about
when to bind a Mac to a directory service
and when not to do so,
especially for 1:1 deployments.
So for organizations
who have traditionally bound their Macs
to Active Directory or another
directory service for 1:1 deployments,
they should consider
not binding the machines.
Instead, consider using
the built-in Kerberos extension,
other SSO extensions,
or additional third-party value-adds
often provided by MDM vendors
to provide directory connectivity.
We'll discuss
the built-in Kerberos extension
and SSO extensions more
later in this session.
Using the built-in Kerberos extension with
on-premise Active Directory environments
allows the user to obtain
a Kerberos ticket-granting ticket,
otherwise known as TGT,
and access directory resources
like file servers and printers.
The extension can also help
keep the user's password in sync
with what is in the directory,
and can help ensure
when changing their password,
that the new password meets the
organizational complexity requirements.
Note that to traverse
Active Directory DFS,
or Distributed File System,
or to be able to acquire
an Active Directory machine certificate
using the AD Certificate payload
delivered via MDM,
the Mac itself does need to be bound
to Active Directory.
However, just because the Mac itself
is bound and has an AD machine record
does not mean that the user needs to use
a domain account to log in to the Mac.
Ideally, a local account, as was
just described, would be used instead.
Local accounts offer the best,
most reliable experience on macOS,
and we recommend that
they be used whenever possible.
Another type of account
is a network account.
With these accounts, the source of truth
for authentication is a directory server.
Home folders
are optionally on a network volume,
and when logged in to macOS,
the contents of the home folder
can be accessed directly over the network.
Modern apps, file sizes and file types
including the fact that many applications
now use databases for storing content,
and the inherent concept of mobility
present immense challenges
for network accounts
and network home folders.
We really view accounts of this type
as legacy and do not recommend their use.
However, they're not deprecated
and can be used if absolutely necessary.
We recommend using local accounts
whenever possible,
and if absolutely needed,
at least consider mobile accounts,
which we'll discuss next.
Mobile accounts
are a type of network account
and are far more commonly used
than true network accounts.
The source of truth for authentication
is still a directory server,
but the credentials
are also cached locally.
A home folder
is also created locally on the Mac.
The locally cached credentials
and the local home folder
helps ensure a user can use their Mac
even if the directory server
is unavailable.
However, because the source of truth
for the user's authentication
is the directory server,
there can be log-in delays that exist
as a result
of trying to access the directory server.
This can happen for a variety of reasons,
but most often,
it's a result of a DNS misconfiguration
or unexpected redirect--
for example, on a public Wi-Fi network.
Additional complexities also exist
in synchronizing the password,
as the password can be changed externally
and then needs to be updated on the Mac.
This is especially true
when using FileVault.
Mobile accounts are supported in macOS
for 1:1 deployments,
but are not recommended.
For shared lab environments, however,
mobile accounts
are often appropriate to use,
and they can even be configured to expire
after a certain period of time if desired.
So that's a recap
of device authentication,
and how we manage different types
of accounts and authentication
between shared and individual devices,
both during and after deployment.
Now let's talk about
single sign-on extensions.
As a quick recap,
SSO extensions were introduced last year
in iPadOS, iOS 13 and macOS Catalina.
They enable native apps and WebKit
to provide
a more seamless single sign-on experience.
We use an SSO extension internally
for our own single sign-on
against our own
identity management system,
and we've seen large identity providers
like Microsoft and Okta
bring offerings to market as well.
SSO extensions allow organizations
to leverage existing credentials.
They're configured
via Mobile Device Management,
or MDM, for short,
and can provide a native UI, Web UI,
or a totally transparent
authentication experience to the user.
Here's a graphic depicting
how both Safari and WebKit
as well as native apps can call
into a single sign-on extension
to authenticate against
an organization's identity provider.
This year, we're introducing
a number of new features and enhancements
to SSO extensions.
First is the ability to configure
SSO extensions on the user channel
on both macOS and iPadOS with Shared iPad.
We've improved the way that SSO extensions
interact with per-app VPN configurations.
We've added the ability for
SSO extension apps to include wild cards
in the list of matching URLs
that are embedded inside of the app.
We now provide additional information
to the extension
about the calling app
that's requesting authentication.
And when the MDM profile
that configures an extension is removed,
there is now an operation that is called
to allow for any cleanup tasks
needed by the extension.
And finally,
we've made some great enhancements
to our first-party
built-in Kerberos extension.
Let's take a deeper look
at all of these changes,
starting with
user-channel profile delivery.
This year, we're introducing
the ability to configure SSO extensions
on the user channel on both macOS
and iPadOS with Shared iPad.
This will allow MDM developers
to more easily integrate configurations
of SSO extensions into their products.
This feature is enabled
for all SSO extensions.
Settings configured on the user channel
take priority over any settings
configured at the system level.
This improvement will also allow for
easier per-user settings for SSO,
such as setting the user name.
We've also significantly improved
how an SSO extensions work
with per-app VPN.
New this year, associated domains
now work with per-app VPN.
As a result, SSO redirect extensions
can now redirect traffic for
identity providers that are on-premise.
The on-premise IdPs
have the same certificate restrictions
as Internet-based IdPs,
meaning that the certificate
needs to be issued
by a pre-installed, system-trusted CA.
To use this feature, you will need to add
the associated domains
to your per-app VPN payload
and enable
the new direct downloads feature
for the domains
via the Managed App attribute on iOS
or the Managed Associated Domains payload
on macOS.
We'll recap associated domains
and discuss some changes to them shortly.
Let's look at how the extension
can use per-app VPN
for on-premise identity providers.
When the app is installed, the OS
will request the site association file
through the per-app VPN
when the associated domains are present.
A native app can send an operation
to an extension, such as "Login".
That request then goes through
the per-app VPN to the on-premise network
to the on-premise identity provider.
The response
then goes back to the extension,
still through the per-app VPN.
And then the response and tokens
are sent back to the native app
SSO Extensions inherit the per-app
VPN settings of their host app.
If the host app is assigned a per-app VPN,
then all of the host and extension traffic
will use the per-app VPN.
This can impact performance
of the extension
because all of the traffic
has to be routed through the VPN,
even though some resources
may be in the cloud.
New this year, you can use
the "per-app VPN Excluded Domains list"
to allow your cloud IdP traffic
go do direct from the device to the IdP
to take advantage of load balancing
and regional instances.
This is useful when an app needs
simultaneous access
to both trusted cloud
and on-premise resources.
The exclusion list
is global for the device.
Previously,
to connect to a cloud resource,
an SSO Extension or app
had to send the traffic
through the per-app VPN
to the on-premise network.
Then it would be routed to the Internet
from there.
This can be inefficient
and can reduce the advantage
of global CDN or regional load balancing
for Internet resources.
Now you can connect directly
to trusted Internet resources
using excluded domains.
So here, you can see the SSO extension
sending some traffic
through the per-app VPN
to the on-premise network.
But now, using the excluded domains list,
the extension can also send traffic
directly to trusted cloud resources
for the domains you specify.
Also new this year, we'll also trigger
per-app VPN for auth-only requests
such as a log-in event
or a password change.
It no longer requires a separate http
or similar request to trigger the VPN.
And this applies to all platforms.
For a quick recap of associated domains,
we introduced these last year
to go alongside SSO extensions.
On iOS, these are configured
via the Managed App configuration
alongside the app
providing the SSO extension,
and on macOS, they're installed
via the separate managed associated
domains configuration payload from MDM.
When used with SSO extensions,
these allow identity providers
that have different host names per tenant
to specify the hosts for a customer
via MDM
rather than trying to add every customer
into the app's embedded set of URLs
before submitting the app
to the App Store.
To have an app be able to be used
together with associated domains,
it requires an entitlement.
The entitlement allows MDM
to supplement the associated domains
that are included with the app.
New this year is that
com.apple.developer.associated-domains.mdm
-managed entitlement
is now public
and no longer requires approval
from Developer Technical Support.
Associated domains
included in inside of an application
must be paired
with an Apple App Site Association file
on the related Web site.
This file contains app IDs and app keys
specifying the application identifiers
for the apps
that are available for use on the Web site
and with the given service type.
New this year is that
the Apple App Site Association file
is no longer directly accessed
by the device itself by default.
Instead, the file is accessed by
an Apple-operated content delivery network
that's dedicated to associated domains.
This reduces load on servers
and routes devices to a known-good,
known-fast connection.
For managed devices where an app may have
an associated domain
that's not available on the public
Internet for Apple's CDN to access,
an additional parameter can be added
to the domain inside of the app
to specify that it is a domain
for a managed app on a managed device.
For more information, see this related
session from this year's WWDC.
This year,
we're providing more information
about the app
that is trying to use an SSO extension.
Specifically, we added
the Calling App Name, which is localized,
the Calling App Team Identifier,
and an Is-Caller-Managed flag.
SSO extensions can use this information
to both improve the user experience
by providing a more user-friendly name
of the app to the user,
and they can also use the Team Identifier
and the "is managed" flag
to make more informed security decisions
about the calling app.
Now, to operations.
We included some standard operations
last year
for typical uses of the extensions,
including log-in, refresh, and log-out.
Developers should have already
adopted these in their extensions.
This year we added
a new configuration-Removed operation.
This operation will be called
when the profile configuring an SSO
extension is removed from the device.
This will give extension developers
a short window of time
to log out, clean up files
or Keychain entries, revoke tokens,
or perform other cleanup actions
as necessary.
Using this feature
requires the SSO extension
be built with the iOS 14
or macOS Big Sur SDK.
We've added the ability
for SSO extension developers
to include embedded wild cards
in the list of matching URLs
for which their extension is used.
This allows for a much easier setup
for large identity providers
that use a common URL scheme
with slightly different URLs
to identify specific customers or tenants.
So, for example,
if an identities provider log-in URL is
auth.pretendco.com/CUSTOMER NAME/login,
they could include
auth.pretendco.com/*/login
in their embedded list of URLs.
This is different
from an associated domain
where the entire domain may be different.
These embedded wild card URLs
work together with associated domains
and aren't meant to replace them.
This improvement is focused
on extension developers
being able to more easily match
a large number of customers
when the URLs are similar and often
the host names themselves are the same.
Also new this year
is a number of improvements
to our built-in Kerberos extension.
First, the menu extra on macOS
now more accurately represents
the state of the extension.
The extension requires a credential,
an active network connection,
functioning DNS, and an unexpired
Kerberos ticket to work correctly.
The menu extra will show solid
if all of these are in place,
or now, when something is missing, it will
indicate to the user what the problem is.
We realize not all organizations
use the same names for their identities.
Some call it the Associate ID,
some call it their AD Account,
or even the PretendCo ID, where
PretendCo is the name of the organization.
This year, we're adding the ability
to customize the label
that is shown in the Kerberos extension
so that it can match the name
of your identity in your organization.
You can also now add help text
to let your users know
where they can get help
if they have trouble logging in.
This text is shown
at the bottom of the sign-in window.
So, here's an example
of the identity name being customized
alongside the custom help text.
Here are a few examples of the menu extra
showing different states to the user.
For example, on the left,
the user is not signed in,
and there is no network available.
In the middle, they are signed in,
but now the network is not available.
And on the right, the user is signed in,
and both the network and credential
are available,
and notice that the key icon is solid
in the menu bar.
The extension will now trigger per-app VPN
for an authentication-only requests
on iOS, iPadOS and macOS.
This will enable you to log in without
having a separate network request
or manually triggering the VPN.
The Kerberos extension
also now fully supports
app-to-per-app VPN on macOS.
You'll need to add the App-SSO-Agent
and the Kerberos-Menu-Extra
to the app-to-per-app VPN payload.
We discussed user channel profile delivery
being supported earlier
for all SSO extensions,
and this includes
the built-in Kerberos extension.
A large driver for the development
of this feature was the request
to be able to more easily reference
user-level certificate identities
delivered via MDM
and to use them
for certificate-based Kerberos or PKINIT.
It's important to mention that referencing
a user-level certificate identity
in a system-level scoped profile
has always been supported
in the context of configuring
the Kerberos extension,
but this improvement will make it
significantly easier for MDM vendors
to bundle the configurations
and the certificates together.
We're also providing more control
for administrators
regarding when a user is prompted
to log in to the extension
for the first time on macOS.
For example, previously, the app SSO agent
would listen for network state changes
and prompt for credentials.
Using this new option
will delay the first log-in prompt
until an administrator runs a command
to enable it
or the first authentication challenge
is received.
We've also added an optional
Managed App Access Control on iOS.
If set, if the source app trying to access
the credential is unmanaged,
then it won't be able to do so.
So that's a recap
of single-sign-on extensions
and the built-in Kerberos extension.
Now I'd like to turn it over to Sudhakar
to talk about Managed Apple IDs.
Thanks, Mike.
Hi. I am Sudhakar Mambakkam.
I'm a senior engineering manager
in Apple's Identity Management team.
Today,
I'll be talking about Managed Apple IDs
and federated authentication.
The features I cover today are applicable
to both Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager.
To keep it simple, I may refer
only to Apple Business Manager at times.
If there are actual feature differences,
I will call those out specifically.
Let's start with
what Managed Apple IDs are.
They are Apple user accounts
owned and managed by an organization.
Account management tasks such as creation,
deletion and password management
are done by IT administrators
or automated systems for these accounts.
Managed Apple IDs are used
to personalize a device
and to access Apple applications
and services.
Certain applications
can be tailored for their use,
and other applications
are available only for Managed Apple IDs.
IT teams use them
to sign into Apple Business Manager
for carrying out tasks
such as device management
and app purchase for their organization.
Features such as User Enrollment
and Shared iPad
are available for use
only with Managed Apple IDs.
Managed Apple IDs for education
support features such as Schoolwork
and come with 200 GB free iCloud storage.
Most importantly,
Managed Apple IDs have the capability
for federated authentication.
Let's see what that is
and why it's important
for enterprise identity.
Federated authentication
is a simple and secure
identity management architecture
that spans organization boundaries.
It allows organizations
in Apple Business Manager
to connect
to their existing identity systems
based on Microsoft Azure Active Directory.
This automatically sets up users
with access to Apple Services.
No new sign-in credential is created,
and Apple Services can be accessed
using the same credentials
a user would use normally
within the organization
for other applications.
This is the core objective
of the federation feature,
where organizations can determine
the authentication policy for their users.
When a user signs in
to an Apple device for the first time
using federated authentication,
the Managed Apple ID
needed to access the Apple service
is created automatically.
Federated authentication
reduces account-related overheads
for both IT teams and end users.
It ensures that identity policies
are consistently enforced
across all applications and services
used within the organization.
Now, let us see
how federated authentication works.
First, federation needs to be set up
between Azure Active Directory and Apple.
This is done using Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager.
Once federation is set up,
organization users can access
all Apple applications
using their organization
sign-in credentials.
Federation is configured
for each domain individually.
In this example, the domain acme.com
has been set up for federation.
After this,
when a user in the acme.com domain
attempts to access an Apple service,
Apple will recognize the user as federated
and redirect their device
to Azure AD for authentication.
After the user authenticates in Azure AD,
the device will be redirected back
to Apple with an authentication token.
The federation protocol used here is SAML,
and the authentication token
is the SAML response signed by Azure AD.
Apple will verify the token signature
using information exchanged
during the setup process
and will allow the user
to access the service.
Federated authentication works
even if the identity system
is not natively on Azure AD
but is behind it on another system
such as on-premise ADFS
or another identity provider.
Azure AD's integration
with the other identity provider
is transparent to the Apple service
which still receives
the authentication token via Azure AD.
Let's go over the details
of the setup process.
Setting up federation requires the user
to have administration capability,
both within Apple Business Manager
and in Azure Active Directory.
Let's assume you are an administrator
in both these systems
for your organization
and walk through the process step by step.
As federation is set up by domain,
if your organization has multiple domains,
you need to decide
which of these domains to federate.
You get the most benefit
when you federate all domains
that have users
who will be accessing Apple Services.
Domain verification is a new feature
introduced this year
in Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager.
Domains that are used
to create Managed Apple IDs
need to undergo ownership verification.
Let's start with that process.
Enter the domain you want to federate
and select "continue."
The domain will be saved
in an unverified state,
and you can start
the verification process now.
The domain verification feature
uses a standard DNS TXT record-based
verification method.
Use the "verify" button
to generate a verification code.
Then, create a TXT record in your domain
using this code.
The code is valid for 14 days
from the time of generation,
and you need to complete the process
within this period.
After updating the DNS record,
you can trigger a DNS check manually
or let the scheduled process
do it automatically.
Either way,
keep in mind that DNS record propagation
may take a few hours after you update it.
Once the TXT record is visible
to Apple Business Manager,
it will be checked against the code
originally generated for the domain.
If it matches,
the domain is marked as verified
and it's available for federation now.
Start the federation process
using the "connect" button
under "federated authentication."
Sign into Azure AD as an administrator.
This can be a user
with one of the following roles:
a global administrator,
an application administrator
or a cloud application administrator.
Approve the integration between Azure AD
and Apple Business Manager.
This allows your users to sign in
to Apple Services
with their Azure AD credentials.
It also allows Azure AD
to share user information,
such as an employee's e-mail address
and name, with Apple.
This step is needed only once
for an organization.
Read the agreement and accept it.
Once you have granted permission,
sign in as a user belonging to the domain
you are federating.
This is a test sign-in that validates
that the permission grant was successful
and confirms that users
can now use their Azure AD credentials
to sign in to Apple Services.
If you federate a second domain later on,
you will directly go to this step,
as the permission for integration
has already been granted.
Next, Apple will scan its database
for username conflicts.
These are existing accounts
with usernames from your domain.
You will not be able to create
new Managed Apple IDs
with usernames that already exist
in Apple ID database.
So there is a resolution process
to remove these conflicts.
Apple will notify users to select
a new username in a different domain.
After 60 days, any remaining usernames
will be automatically updated
to a temporary domain by Apple.
Once that is done,
you can create Managed Apple IDs
with any username
in the domain you are federating.
Even if there are conflicts,
you do not have to wait 60 days
to enable federation.
Once the scan is complete
and you have the conflict results,
you can go ahead
and enable federation anytime.
Users without username conflicts
can then use Apple Services
with their organization credentials
right away.
Let's do a quick recap on the steps needed
to enable federation.
First, verify your domain.
Then sign in as an administrator
and provide consent.
Then sign in as a user in the domain.
Review username conflicts
and initiate resolution steps if required.
Then turn federation on.
Federated authentication removes
many of the account management challenges,
particularly the hardest one
of credential management.
But there are still a few important ones
that need to be addressed.
What happens when a user
leaves the organization?
Their access must be revoked
in a timely manner
to meet security and regulatory needs.
Of course, with federation, the user will
not be able to sign in after they leave,
but what about the devices and
applications they are already signed into?
How can we ensure
that those sessions are terminated?
Over the life of an account,
information such as
the department a user works in
or even their name, can change.
What is the best way to ensure
that the user's profile information
is consistent across all services?
Creating the Managed Apple ID
automatically at the time of sign-in
works for most users.
But what if there are certain
service-specific permissions
required for a user?
How do we avoid the manual work needed
to pre-create the account
so that permissions
can be granted up-front?
SCIM is a standard solution
that addresses all these problems.
We are very happy to share
that we are introducing SCIM integration
with Azure Active Directory
later this year.
This integration will be available
in both Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager.
Let's see what SCIM is
and how it will help.
SCIM is an automated process
for exchanging information
between an identity provider
and a service provider.
It allows the synchronization of
account data between Azure AD and Apple.
It's a standards-based data exchange
covering the full life cycle
of the account.
So account creations, modifications
and deletions, all can be synchronized.
It will be available
for all federated organizations
in Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager.
Education organizations
that already have a process
for importing account information
into Apple School Manager
via the SIS or SFTP process
will now have SCIM as another option.
Let's look at an overview
of the SCIM process.
Once a SCIM connection is set up
for your organization,
Azure AD monitors your user directory
for changes
and automatically publishes these changes
to Apple Business Manager.
Over a period of time, users may be added.
Some users' profiles may be updated,
and some other users may be deleted.
Azure AD monitors for these changes
and, using the SCIM interface,
identifies the changes to be sent
to Apple Business Manager.
Apple Business Manager consumes this data
and applies it to its database,
synchronizing it with Azure AD.
By keeping the two repositories in sync,
SCIM enhances the security and usability
of the federated architecture.
Now let's go over the SCIM setup process.
Similar to federated authentication,
SCIM configuration also requires you
to be an administrator
in both Apple Business Manager
and Azure AD.
Apple Business Manager will now have a new
data source option to configure SCIM.
Apple School Manager already supports
data source configuration
for SIS and SFTP.
It will now offer SCIM
as an alternative option.
Select "connect"
to start the configuration process.
This will generate a SCIM token
that you need to upload
to Azure Active Directory.
Copy this token for later use.
Once generated, the SCIM token
must be used within four days,
after which it will expire.
After you generate the token,
a tenant URL will also be displayed
in the user interface.
Note the tenant URL, too,
as both the token and the URL are needed
for Azure AD configuration.
Sign into Azure AD as an administrator.
Navigate to
Enterprise Applications section
and find the Apple Business Manager
application.
Go to the Provisioning section
for this application
and enter the information you obtained
from Apple Business Manager.
You can also choose to synchronize data
for all users in your directory,
or you can choose to synchronize data
for just the subset of users you assign
to Apple Business Manager.
Make your selection and click "save."
Azure AD
will automatically test the connection
and start data synchronization.
You can verify the SCIM status
in Apple Business Manager
using the Activity sidebar.
You can see the connection status and
the count of accounts imported via SCIM.
You can also see SCIM as a data source
on the label on accounts that have been
synchronized via the SCIM interface.
From now on, account information
will be automatically synchronized
between Azure AD
and Apple Business Manager.
Together, federation and SCIM will greatly
simplify your account management processes
and we are very excited to make
SCIM integration available to you.
Managed Apple IDs
allow you to use Apple Services
in a way that is tailored to your needs.
Federated authentication and SCIM
automate and simplify
identity management processes,
provide a seamless experience
to your users,
and help you get the most value
out of Apple Services.
I'll now hand it back to Mike.
Thanks, Sudhakar.
I'd like to briefly focus in a bit more
on federation and SSO.
These are complementary technologies
within our ecosystem.
Identity providers support SSO extensions.
As I mentioned
in the beginning of the session,
we've seen several large providers
like Microsoft and Okta
bring SSO extensions to market already.
SSO extensions allow non-Apple
applications and Web sites to use them
to directly integrate
with the identity provider
for the SSO experience.
On the other hand, Apple apps and services
work only with Managed Apple IDs,
meaning they do not use SSO extensions
to integrate
with your identity provider directly.
Instead, they integrate with Apple
for authentication,
which can then use federation
with Microsoft Azure Active Directory.
Whether Microsoft Azure Active Directory
is the actual backing identity provider
is up to you.
As Sudhakar described earlier,
Azure Active Directory also supports
federating with other identity providers.
So while Apple Business Manager
needs to talk to Azure Active Directory,
the backing source for the identities
could be another identity provider.
I'd like to wrap up by summarizing
what we discussed today
and provide some calls to action.
Use local accounts on macOS
whenever possible for 1:1 deployments
and enable directory connectivity
via the built-in Kerberos extension,
other SSO extensions,
or additional third-party value adds
often provided by MDM vendors.
Mobile accounts are supported in macOS
but are not recommended
for 1:1 deployments.
For shared lab environments,
mobile accounts
are often appropriate to use,
and they can even be configured to expire
after a certain period of time if desired.
This year we've brought a number
of new improvements to SSO extensions
and the built-in system
Kerberos extension.
We encourage you take advantage
of these improvements
to allow for an even better
single-sign-on experience for your users.
Use Managed Apple IDs in your institution,
as they're purpose-built
for enterprise and education.
They are created and managed
by your organization,
built for data privacy,
and provide access to Apple Services.
Verify domains in Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager
to enable the use of federation
for easy account creation
backed by an existing Microsoft Azure
Active Directory credential.
SCIM support is new and will be launching
in Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager
later this year.
It provides a data feed
directly from Microsoft Azure
Active Directory back to Apple
to help with account creation,
modifications and deletions.
Please be sure to explore all the other
WWDC 2020 Enterprise sessions
which are dedicated to IT professionals.
And also, look in this session's resources
for last year's tech talk
providing a deep dive on extensible SSO.
Thank you, and we hope you enjoy
all of the great content
that WWDC 2020 has to offer.