Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Anders,
and today I'll be talking about
Swift package resources and localization.
First we'll see how to add resources
to a Swift package.
Next, we'll talk about what happens
when the package is built,
and how code in a package
can use resources at runtime.
Finally, we'll take a look at how to
localize the resources in a package.
Let's start by adding resources
to a package.
Xcode 11 introduced support
for Swift packages,
letting you create packages
as well as use existing packages
in your Xcode projects.
You can implement a package in Swift
or in any of the C-based languages.
And in Xcode 12, you can add resources,
such as images, storyboards,
and other files to a package.
You can also localize those resources
so that internationalized apps
can take advantage of the functionality
your package provides.
And adding resources to a package
works with existing APIs,
so it does not affect the OS version
requirements of your package.
Let's take a look at how this works.
Here I have a package
that implements a SwiftUI view.
It shows the side of a die
and has a button
that lets you roll the die.
And one of the things
that's new in Xcode 12
is that it can show previews
for SwiftUI views in packages
without having to have a client app
in the same workspace.
But as we can see,
there's something missing.
This package view is showing a black box
instead of the dots on the die.
When I click the button to roll the die,
it picks a new number of dots,
but it doesn't display it.
Let's fix that.
I'm going to create an asset catalog
right next to the source code
in the DiceUI target.
Because of its filename suffix,
Xcode will know that it's an asset catalog
and will know how to process it.
The asset catalog starts out empty,
but I'm going to add some images
that show dice
with various numbers of dots
at three different resolutions.
Now I go into the implementation
of the view,
and I replace the Rectangle view
with an Image.
I've chosen the names of my images
so they match the names of the dot count,
so I can just pass the name
to the initializer.
I'm going to specify a bundle parameter
to indicate that the images should come
from the resource bundle for the module
into which my code is built.
Package resources use existing
Foundation APIs of the bundle type
to access resources,
so you can then pass that to any API
that takes a bundle parameter.
We'll take a closer look at how this works
in a moment.
And then I see
that the image of the dice shows up.
And if I click the "roll" button,
I can see that
it picks the different numbers.
Now, I can actually delete
the bundle part here,
because with Swift type inference,
I can just have .module.
So here we've seen how you can easily
add resources to a Swift package,
and to show the preview
while working on the package in Xcode.
Files in a package
are processed according to their type,
as indicated by the filename suffix.
Some kinds of files,
such as asset catalogs,
storyboards and Core Data models,
have a clear purpose.
These kinds of files
can just be added to the package,
and Xcode knows what to do with them.
Other kinds of files could have
a variety of purposes.
A plain text file might be needed
at runtime,
or it might only be used
during development.
The same is true for images,
shell scripts,
and other common types of files.
For those kinds of files,
you need to declare the intent
in the package manifest.
Let's look at an example.
Here is the file system structure
of an example package called MyGame
with a single target called GameLogic.
All the target's source files are located
underneath the Sources directory,
in a subdirectory
with the same name as the target.
If we look at the contents
of the package manifest file,
we see the corresponding product
and target definitions
for the GameLogic target.
This is where we're going to declare
what to do
with any target files
whose purpose is ambiguous.
To learn more about the syntax
of the package manifest
and how it relates
to the file system structure,
see the video for the "Adopting Swift
Packages in Xcode" session from WWDC 19.
So let's focus in on the target directory,
under which all the target's sources
and resources are located.
There's already a Swift source file there,
and the intent is pretty clear:
It should be compiled
when the package is built.
We don't need anything extra
in the manifest.
Now let's add an asset catalog.
An asset catalog is a directory
with a well-defined filename suffix
and a structure.
It'll be processed at build time
and included in the client of the package.
We don't need anything special
in the manifest.
The same thing is true
if we add a storyboard.
It has a clear purpose, too,
and will be compiled the same way
as if it were in an Xcode project.
Next, let's add a plain text file.
Now things get a bit more interesting.
Text files could be used
for all kinds of things,
so it isn't obvious
what Xcode should do with it.
Maybe it's a resource for use at runtime,
or maybe it's just some
internal development notes.
In this example, we don't want Xcode
to treat it as a resource.
We add it to the list of excluded files
in the manifest,
which will cause it to be ignored
when the package is built.
We can also add a directory
full of files and folders,
such as the sketches and design documents
for creating the artwork in the game.
Just as for a file, we can add the name
or sub-path of a directory
to the exclusion list in the manifest.
This will cause that directory
and everything under it
to be skipped when the package is built.
Now let's add a stand-alone image file.
In this case, we will need it at runtime,
so we add it to the manifest
as a resource,
and we specify the process action for it.
Most resources should use
the process action
so that they are transformed
as appropriate at build time.
The exact type of processing
that will happen
depends on the platform
for which the package is built.
Now let's add a directory full of files
that our sample game will need at runtime.
In this case, there is a whole hierarchy
of files and folders underneath it.
We want all of it to be available
at runtime,
including the directory structure.
So we declare it as a resource,
but this time,
we specify the "copy" action.
This will cause it to be copied
exactly as it is,
preserving its directory structure.
So now we've seen how to add
several different kinds of files
to a package target,
and we've seen how to declare the intent
for any cases where it isn't clear
from the file type.
As we saw,
any resource can be either processed
or copied byte for byte.
The "process" action is usually
the recommended choice,
because it will apply the appropriate
built-in rules for the platform.
This might include converting
a storyboard or asset catalog
into a form suitable for use at runtime,
or it might include compressing an image,
etcetera.
If the file type is unknown,
or no special processing is needed
for the platform,
the file will be copied.
The processing rules
are applied recursively
to every file under a directory,
and each resulting output file is included
in the product as a separate resource.
The "copy" action is appropriate
when you want to make an exact copy
of the resource, regardless of its type.
Copying doesn't do
any transformation at all,
so it can be used, for example,
to copy a source file that would
normally have been compiled
if you want to use it
as a template at runtime.
Copying can also be used
if you want to include a whole directory
and preserve its hierarchical structure.
So what happens to the files in a target
when it's built?
For example, here we have a package,
and an app that uses the package.
The package contains source files
as well as resource files.
Each target's sources get compiled
into a code module
and linked into the client app.
Each target's resources are processed
into a resource bundle for that module,
which then gets embedded into the app.
On Apple platforms,
applications
and app extensions are bundles,
so nothing more needs to be done.
The resource bundles
for each package module
are a part of the app bundle,
and will therefore be available
at runtime.
When building an unbundled product,
such as a command line tool,
the resource bundles would need to be
installed alongside the tool.
There's one more thing to note
about the package manifest,
and that is the minimum tools version.
The Swift Package Manager
is part of the Swift toolchain.
Support for package resources is new
in Swift 5.3,
so the package manifest
needs to declare 5.3
as its required tools version.
But how does this relate
to the Xcode version?
Every Xcode release
includes a version of the Swift toolchain.
Xcode 11 was the first version
to support Swift packages,
and its Swift toolchain version was 5.1.
In Xcode 12, the included version
of the Swift toolchain is 5.3.
The tool version should be set
to the lowest version
that supports the features needed
by the package.
This is because any package or project
that uses it
will also need to have
that tool version or later
in order to build the package.
Now that we have added the resources
to the package,
let's talk about how to access them
from code.
As we saw,
you use Foundation's Bundle API
to access package resources at runtime.
Foundation is available on all platforms
that support Swift packages,
so this provides a consistent
and platform-neutral way
to access resources,
regardless of what kind of artifacts
the build system creates
for a particular platform.
When Xcode builds a package target
that contains resources,
it synthesizes an accessor
for the resource bundle
and includes it in the code module
that it creates for the target.
The module can then access
its resource bundle
regardless of whether it's implemented
in Swift or Objective-C.
The bundle object that's returned
is specific to each code module,
but the way you access it
is always the same in the source code.
Here's an example of using Bundle APIs
to access the files in the resource bundle
from both Swift and Objective-C.
In both languages, the accessor returns
a Foundation Bundle object
that can be used to look up resources
by name.
But the resource bundle can also be passed
to any system API
that takes a bundle as a parameter.
In the example shown here,
it's being passed to a UIImage method
that can look up images
from the package resource bundle.
When adding a resource to a package,
you should add it to the target
for the code module that uses it.
The resource bundle accessor
is only visible to the code
that's in the same module
as the resources.
If you need to provide resources
to other modules,
it's best to do so
by adding specific typed accessors
that vend the individual resources.
It's generally not recommended
to vend the whole resource bundle
to other modules,
because that would create
an external dependency
on the specific names of resources.
Xcode 12 also lets you add
localized resources to your packages.
Let's take a look at localizing the text
in the sample package we saw earlier.
First thing I'm going to do
is to add a defaultLocalization parameter
to my package manifest.
This declares the language
I'm using during development
and will be used as
the fallback localization at runtime
if no better match is available.
This is needed for any package
that contains resources.
Next, I'm going to create
a localization directory
for my default localization, English...
and name it "en.lproj."
And inside, I create a file
called "Localizable.strings."
I add one entry to the strings file
that just maps the localizable string key
I used in the code
to the English word "roll."
Now I'm going to do the same thing,
but for French.
I create a directory called "fr.lproj,"
and I create
a "Localizable.strings" file in it.
In this file, I'm going to add a mapping
from the English string key...
to the French translation of the word.
Now I'm going to do the same thing
with the Text view
as I did with the Image view,
which is to pass in the resource bundle
for the module that contains my code.
This uses Foundation support
for localization
to find the right localized content
based on the user's chosen language.
The preview is still showing in English,
and that's because
my system language is English.
But with SwiftUI,
we can customize our preview.
For example,
we can add an environment override
to see the French localization
in the preview.
And we can see that it's using
the localized strings
from the generated resource bundle.
As we saw in the demo,
a localization directory
has a .lproj filename suffix.
Localization directories can be included
in package targets
without mentioning them in the manifest
because the .lproj suffix
makes their purpose clear.
A localization directory
usually contains string files
and string dictionary files
for translating text,
but it can also contain
customized versions
of individual resources in the package.
It's also possible to localize
the contents of an asset catalog.
This lets you provide different artwork
for specific localizations
where that's appropriate.
You can learn more about how to do this
in the "Creating Great
Localized Experiences" session
from WWDC 19.
When you add localized resources
to a package,
you need to declare the default
localization in the package manifest.
This uses the same kind of language ID
that is used for all localization
on Apple platforms
and specifies the language
that will be used as a last resort
if no preferred language is available.
You can find more information
about this topic
in the "Language and Locale IDs" document
on developer.apple.com.
In this video,
we've seen how to add resources
to a Swift package,
and how Xcode builds resource bundles
that let you access those resources
at runtime.
We also saw how to localize the resources
in your package.
Xcode lets you create Swift packages
and also take advantage
of a great and growing ecosystem
of existing packages.
Xcode 12 makes it easier to develop
packages containing SwiftUI views
by letting you interact with your views
even in the absence of a client app.
And the support
for localized package resources
lets you create packages
whose functionality is available
to people all over the world.
Thank you, and enjoy the rest of WWDC 20.