Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to "iPad and iPhone Apps
on Apple Silicon Macs."
My name is Jason Beaver,
and I'll be joined later by my colleagues
James Snee and Patrick Heynen.
As you may have seen in the Keynote
or State of the Union talks,
Big Sur on Apple Silicon
allows you to run iOS apps natively
on the Mac without recompilation.
The Mac is a robust platform
for development
that enables all kinds of apps.
There's everything
from powerful desktop apps
to web-based experiences
and graphic-intensive games.
These experiences are all powered
by our dedicated UI frameworks.
In macOS Catalina,
we added the ability to build
your iOS apps for the Mac
with Mac Catalyst.
Mac Catalyst makes UIKit
a native peer to these other
UI frameworks on the Mac
and enables you to bring your iOS apps
over to the Mac
as first-class experiences.
You can refer to last year's
"Introducing iPad Apps for Mac" session
to hear all about how we did this.
Mac Catalyst requires building your app
with the macOS SDK
and gives you the ability to customize
and optimize your application
to take full advantage of the Mac.
In macOS Big Sur,
we are leveraging
this Mac Catalyst infrastructure
to enable running
your existing iOS apps as-is
on Apple Silicon-based Macs.
Here, "as-is" really means "as-is."
We enable the user on the Mac to purchase
or download, through the Mac App Store,
the application you've already
made available on the iOS App Store.
It is the exact same binary.
Because these apps use
the same underlying infrastructure
that is used for Mac Catalyst apps,
the same unified frameworks
and the same iOS frameworks
brought over and integrated with the Mac,
your iPad and iPhone apps
get a tremendous amount
of behavior automatically,
making them feel right at home on the Mac.
However, they don't have access
to all that a Mac app would like to offer.
If you want to take your iOS applications
further on the Mac,
create a Mac Catalyst version
by checking that switch in Xcode.
This will give you
the ability to customize
your app's behavior on the Mac,
as well as allow you to distribute
your application on all Macs,
not just those running Apple Silicon.
For your app to be available
in the Mac App Store,
it must be compatible with the Mac.
Your app can't be dependent
on an unavailable symbol or framework,
it can't be dependent on missing
functionality in existing frameworks,
and it can't be dependent
on hardware capabilities
that don't exist on the Mac.
Compatible iOS apps
are automatically available
in the Mac App Store,
but you can manage the availability
of your app in App Store Connect.
You might choose not to make your
iOS app available in the Mac App Store
if you already have a Mac app
or are planning on shipping one
or if your app
doesn't make sense on the Mac.
Patrick will discuss this further
later in the session.
Most existing iPad and iPhone apps
run great on macOS,
but the environment has some differences
that you should be aware of.
These fall into three categories:
hardware differences, UI differences
and system software differences.
Let's start with hardware differences.
iOS is built around a direct,
multi-touch interaction model,
but macOS is built around an indirect,
cursor-based interaction model.
The infrastructure automatically maps
many multi-touch gestures,
but if your application uses
custom touch handling,
you should test whether your application
is compatible with the Mac.
If your application supports
keyboard entry
as an alternative
to your custom touch handling,
that will also help your app
be more compatible with the Mac,
as well as a better experience on iOS.
iOS devices have a range of sensors
that aren't available on Macs,
such as accelerometers, gyroscopes,
magnetometers,
depth-sensing cameras and GPS.
By dynamically confirming in your code
that the appropriate sensor is present,
you can ensure that your app is compatible
with the entire range of iOS devices,
as well as compatible with the Mac.
Note that not all APIs
that are dependent on these sensors
fail to work on the Mac.
For example, even though Macs
do not contain GPS receivers,
they do support Core Location
and can provide position information
to your app,
though it will be less precise
than it would be with GPS.
iOS devices typically just have
front- and rear-facing cameras.
Macs, on the other hand,
may have built-in front-facing cameras,
like in our laptops and some desktops,
but may also include cameras
built into external displays
or cameras plugged in via USB.
iOS apps may not be prepared
to deal with all of these configurations,
but using
the AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession
instead of enumerating
all of the AV capture devices
will allow us to ensure
that your app has access
to the most appropriate camera
for your needs.
Now, let's talk about some UI differences.
As we discussed before,
iOS apps automatically get a great deal
of system behavior from macOS.
This will necessarily look and behave
differently than on iOS devices.
For example, alerts and pop-ups
may show up in different locations
on the Mac
and Open and Save panels
will show in separate windows.
This means that it's important
that your app
does not hard-code any assumptions
about the UI,
like the location of system UI,
since those assumptions might be wrong
when running on the Mac.
On macOS, windows are typically
resizable by the user.
If your iPad app already supports
multitasking on iOS,
it will be fully resizable on macOS.
This means that it can run
at a wide range of sizes,
not just the small number of fixed sizes
supported by iOS multitasking.
Using Auto Layout will help you ensure
that your app can run correctly
at any size.
Window resize is also live on macOS.
Optimizing the performance
of your application layout
will improve the resize experience
on the Mac
and make your app even more responsive
when multitasking on iOS.
If your iPad app
does not support multitasking,
or if you have an iPhone app,
it will run in a fixed-size window
and will not be resizable.
Now let's look at some
of the system software differences.
On iOS, apps live in a standard location,
but on macOS, the user can move the app
wherever they would like.
Your app's data containers are also
in a different location on the Mac.
If you're using the Foundation APIs
to locate items in the file system,
all of this will be transparent to you,
and your app will behave correctly
when running on the Mac.
Some system APIs will reveal
that your application is running on a Mac.
For example, if you've hard-coded
parts of your system,
whether on the device or on your servers,
to expect only the devices
iPhone, iPod Touch or iPad,
you will likely encounter problems
when running your iOS application
on the Mac.
It is better to ensure your software
robustly handles unexpected values
and falls back to some default behavior.
Other device properties,
such as screen size,
can vary dramatically across Macs,
and your application
should not make the assumption
that it will match one of
the screen resolutions in our iOS devices.
Now I'd like to hand it over
to my colleague James,
who will talk about testing and debugging
your iOS apps on the Mac.
Thanks, Jason.
Being able to run iPhone and iPad apps
natively on the Apple Silicon Mac
allows you to reach
a whole new set of users.
And with macOS Big Sur,
Apple has done all the hard work
to make that possible
with minimal to zero effort on your part.
So I'm sure you want to see how your app
looks running on the Apple Silicon Mac.
As Jason mentioned,
your apps may be making some assumptions
about the devices they're running on
that are no longer true on the Mac.
The goal here is to ensure
that your apps function correctly
and that there aren't any major
UI glitches or unexpected behavior.
The good news is that
Xcode has great support
for debugging, testing and profiling
iPhone and iPad apps
natively on the Mac,
just as if it were running in a simulator
or on an iOS device.
Let me show you how that works.
Here I've got an iOS app project
open in Xcode.
Some of you may recognize it
from a previous session.
In order to run an iOS app
on the Apple Silicon Mac,
all you need to do is select
the new run destination,
My Mac, Designed for iPad.
So let's go ahead
and build and run this app.
I want to call out that this app
is building against the iOS SDK,
so barring the edge cases Jason mentioned,
you don't have to make any source changes
in order for this to run.
So, here we have this iOS app
running natively on the Apple Silicon Mac.
It's built against the iOS SDK
and isn't running in a simulator.
As I click around the various views,
I can verify that it behaves the same
as it does on an iPhone.
As well as running iPhone and iPad apps,
we've also brought all of Xcode's
great debugging and profiling capabilities
along for the ride.
While an app is running, you can get
a high-level view of its performance
by checking out Xcode's debug gauges.
You can see how much CPU time
and memory it's consuming,
as well as any network
and disk I/O it might be performing.
If you want to take a more targeted look
at what your app is doing,
you can pause it or set a break point
and use one of Xcode's
great debugging features,
just like you would on an iPhone or iPad.
For example, a common use of the debugger
is to investigate the state of an app
in response to a user action.
Let me show you how this works with
this iOS app running natively on the Mac.
I'm going to set a break point
here in this IBAction method.
And I'm going to trigger it by clicking
on this useful button in the app.
You'll see, in response
to triggering this break point,
Xcode presents its debugging interface.
Once in the debugger, you can make use
of all the features you'd expect,
such as inspecting variables
and evaluating expressions.
To investigate more specific issues,
you can check out the Memory
and View debuggers.
And for understanding or tracking
the performance of your app,
you can use Instruments.
And finally,
I'm sure you're wondering about testing.
Tests are a great way to verify
that your software
is behaving as you expect.
Let me show you.
With Xcode, you can run
your iOS app XCTest unit tests
natively on your Apple Silicon Mac.
I'm going to execute these tests
by clicking Run here
in the Test Navigator.
Like running the app, these tests
are being built against the iOS SDK
and are running natively.
Great. The tests pass.
Xcode provides a great set of tools
to help you debug, test and profile
iPhone and iPad apps
natively on the Apple Silicon Mac.
And with that,
I'll hand it over to Patrick
to talk about distributing
iPhone and iPad apps for the Mac.
So, now that we understand
how iPad and iPhone apps work,
let's talk about how these apps
get on the Macs
your users and team members
will be running.
The good news is that distribution
for your iOS app on the Mac
works exactly like it does
on iPad or iPhone today.
All of the workflows
you are familiar with today
have been seamlessly extended
by adding the Mac to the family
of devices supported by your app.
All you really have to do
to make your apps available on the Mac
is sign the new Developer Agreement,
and your compatible apps
will be made available
on the Mac App Store later this year.
For new submissions,
distribution for the Mac
will fit seamlessly
into your existing development workflows.
From the Xcode organizer, you can
prepare your app for running on the Mac
by exporting through App Store Connect
or use any of the local
distribution options,
such as ad hoc, enterprise or development
to distribute versions
of your iPad or iPhone app
directly to members of your team.
If your app takes advantage
of App Store features,
they will all be supported when running
your iPad or iPhone app on a Mac.
Users will have full access to any
in-app purchases and subscriptions
associated with your iPad or iPhone app
when running on Mac
and can make new purchases
using the StoreKit framework.
If your app uses on-demand resources
to dynamically manage
the content downloaded for your app,
the experience will be identical
when running on a Mac.
In fact, all App Store features
work just like they do on iPad and iPhone.
App thinning has also been extended
to work with deploying
to Apple Silicon Macs.
App content is automatically selected
for best fit for running on a Mac,
and inapplicable resources
best suited for other iPad
or iPhone devices are left out
for a streamlined install experience.
In fact, for app thinning,
a new Mac looks just like
any other very capable iPad.
To support this workflow,
Xcode has added a new virtual
thinning destination for Mac
in the Organizer export workflow.
Use the Mac device to produce
an install variant
optimized for running or testing
on any Apple Silicon Mac.
Note that because Mac users
are accustomed to moving apps
seamlessly between machines
and removable storage,
only a single app variant
and thinning target is needed.
If your app relies on developer
or ad hoc distribution,
that will work just like it does
on iPhone and iPad.
The good news is that you can get
your iPhone or iPad app onto Macs
by exporting just like you would
for other iOS devices.
If you take advantage
of Over-the-Air installation,
distributing to the Mac
requires no changes.
The Mac will automatically select
an appropriate variant
from your OTA manifest to download
and run on your suitably provisioned Macs.
For scenarios involving managed devices,
iPad and iPhone apps
can be pushed to enrolled Macs
just like any other device.
Although distribution to the Mac
is incredibly straightforward,
the Mac is a distinct platform,
and there are some key points to consider
when deploying to Mac.
TestFlight is not available for Mac,
so any prerelease distributions
ahead of your final submission
will need to use ad hoc
or development distribution
as an alternative to test your app.
In addition, as Jason noted earlier,
there are limits to iPad and iPhone app
run-time compatibility on Mac.
Xcode will tell you if your app
has hard dependencies
on symbols or frameworks
unavailable on Mac,
but it is always a good idea
to test your app
on Apple Silicon Mac hardware
when available
in order to evaluate the user experience
of your app on a Mac.
We have made it incredibly easy
to get your apps onto the Mac App Store.
To ensure that your customers
will have the best experience
with your iOS apps on the Mac,
App Store Connect will be providing tools
to help you test and validate
that experience later this summer.
Of course, you will still have the choice
of whether your apps are available
on the Mac App Store.
Let's look at how you'll control that now.
After you sign the Developer Agreement,
all your compatible apps will
automatically be made available on Mac.
Use App Store Connect to review
the status of all of your apps.
In App Store Connect,
the Pricing and Availability page
is where you make your choice
about whether to distribute your app
on the Mac App Store.
If you don't want this app
available on the Mac,
simply uncheck this box,
and it will no longer be offered for sale
on the Mac App Store.
Note that once your app
is made unavailable,
Mac users will no longer
be able to re-download
existing versions of your app
until the app is made available
on Mac again.
So, now you know.
Your apps can now run natively
on Apple Silicon Macs without change.
Users will love the ability
to run your apps on their desktops.
Most functionality just works,
and the apps run adapted
to the familiar Mac user experience.
Building and debugging is just the tools
that you already know and use.
So all you need to do is test your apps
on Apple Silicon Macs
to confirm your apps come across well.
Then you'll have a whole new set of users
enjoying your apps
from the Mac App Store soon.
Thank you for watching.