[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name is Conrad
and welcome to my crib.
I'm very excited to tell you today about
the new Shortcuts experience in watchOS 7.
First, I'm going to introduce you to the
all-new Shortcuts app on Apple Watch.
Then my colleague Alex will walk you
through what you can do as a developer
to craft a delightful
Shortcuts experience on watchOS.
Last year, in watchOS 6, we brought some
exciting new updates to Shortcuts in Siri.
We added the ability for shortcuts
to have parameters
which means that Siri
can ask follow-up questions.
You can see here that Siri is asking
which items to add to my Walmart cart.
You can also run shortcuts
right from the Siri watch face.
Shortcuts are suggested on the face
when they become relevant,
and you can run them with a tap
at just the right moment.
This year, I am really excited
to share with you all
the new Shortcuts app on watchOS 7.
The Shortcuts app on watchOS
naturally complements its iOS counterpart
and you can run shortcuts
with a single tap right from your wrist.
The Shortcuts that you know and love
on iOS
work just as well in Shortcuts on watchOS.
For example, here is a great shortcut
from the Shortcuts Gallery
that automatically texts someone an ETA
of how long it will take to get home,
running right on the watch.
In the new Shortcuts app, you can organize
and edit your Apple Watch collection
to determine which shortcuts should sync
via iCloud to your watch.
If a shortcut asks a question,
you can answer those questions
inline inside of the Shortcuts app.
For example, here, I am prompted to choose
which event I want to get directions to
in my Directions to Event shortcut.
We're also very excited
to support complications
for the new Shortcuts app on watchOS.
You can see here
that I can launch the Shortcuts app
in just a single tap,
straight from the watch face.
But that's not all.
You can also set up complications
that launch a specific shortcut directly.
You can see here that I can send my ETA
right from my watch face.
I just tap on the complication, tap run,
and there is my message.
That message looks good,
so I'll go ahead and send it.
By supporting Shortcuts
inside of your app,
your app's shortcuts could also
be available right from the watch face.
Now, I am going to hand it over to my
colleague Alex, who will explain
how you can build an awesome experience
for Shortcuts on watchOS.
Alex.
Thanks, Conrad. Hi, everyone.
Let's start with a quick recap
about how you can offer shortcuts in your
apps, so that you can take full advantage
of this great new Shortcuts
experience on watchOS.
Just like in iOS,
your apps can support Shortcuts
by using the APIs from the SiriKit suite
of frameworks and the NSUserActivity API.
If you are new to Shortcuts or SiriKit,
you should start with watching
these great sessions
from the previous years' conferences.
Now, let's talk about
how running shortcuts on the watch
is different from running them
on iOS devices.
As you may know,
Shortcuts are seamlessly synced
across all of your devices via iCloud.
This means that people can configure
shortcuts on an iOS device,
put some shortcuts
into the Apple Watch collection,
and will expect to run those shortcuts
on their Apple Watch.
So what happens when someone
runs a shortcut on their watch?
The flow will be different depending on
how the shortcut is implemented.
For shortcuts that you offer
via the NSUserActivity API,
we need to open the app
to handle the activity.
But we cannot open the app
if it's not installed on the watch,
and in that case, attempting to run
such a shortcut would result in an error.
Let's now take a look
at intent-based shortcuts.
Now, intents are handled
by Intents extensions.
If an Intents extension
is installed on the watch,
and it supports this intent,
we just hand the intent over to that.
If not, we will try to run this intent
remotely, on the paired phone.
We call this remote execution.
Note how this is in contrast
to NSUserActivity-based shortcuts,
which can only be run
directly on the watch.
But if the Intents extension on the phone
tells us that it needs to
continue in the app,
then, just like for
user activity-based shortcuts,
we won't be able to open the app
remotely on the phone,
and an error will be shown.
Otherwise, the shortcut is executed
remotely on the phone.
And here's what
the overall decision process
for running shortcuts
on the watch looks like.
You should design your shortcuts
to avoid these "error" nodes,
to ensure that people using your apps
have a great experience on the watch,
and we'll go over how you can do that
further in this session.
And now, let's take a closer look
at remote execution
and see what it means for you
and the people who use your shortcuts.
If an Intent is supported natively
on the watch,
we'll launch the associated
watchOS Intents extension
and let it handle the intent.
Similarly, user activity-based shortcuts
will be opened
in their corresponding watchOS app
if it is installed.
If, on the other hand, we have to send
the intent over to the paired phone,
we introduce an additional hop
for sending the data to the phone,
which inevitably increases the overall
time it takes to perform the task.
As you can see,
even if you don't have a watch app yet,
or you are not supporting all of the
intents in your watchOS Intents extension,
we will still run the shortcuts
based on your intent,
but it will be slower
than running locally.
Best experience is achieved
when the intent
can be handled directly on the watch.
Now that we've seen how running shortcuts
on watchOS is different from iOS,
let's take a look at what your options are
when supporting shortcuts on the watch.
The best approach by far
is to have a watchOS app
and have that app support
the same user activities or intents
that you support in your iOS app.
This will ensure the best
Shortcuts experience on the watch.
And if you don't offer a watch app yet,
consider building one.
If for some reason a watchOS app
is not an option for you,
you can instead ensure that your shortcuts
work well with remote execution.
Now, while remote execution
is great for running shortcuts
for those of you
who don't offer a watch app yet,
your shortcuts need to satisfy
a few requirements
in order to work well with it.
First, remote execution is only supported
for intent-based shortcuts,
not NSUserActivity-based ones.
This is because
user activity-based shortcuts
require the app to be open
in order to run,
and opening an app on another device
would be a very jarring experience.
And second, only those intents that can
perform the task entirely in background,
without opening the app,
can be executed remotely.
This means that you need to not return
".continueInApp"
in your intent handling code.
Additionally, you would need to check the
"supports background execution" checkbox
in the Suggestions section
of the Xcode intent editor
for all parameter combinations that you
are using in your interaction donations.
Let's now go over some of the best
practices for implementing shortcuts.
As I mentioned earlier, there are two ways
to support shortcuts in your app.
The first is through
the NSUserActivity API.
And the second is
using the Intents framework.
And for all new shortcuts adopters,
we recommend to implement
shortcuts using Intents,
because it provides richer
and much more flexible APIs
and allows you to offer shortcuts
that support parameters
and can run in background.
Another very important part is to make
sure to compile your Intents extension
not only for iOS but also for watchOS.
This usually means creating
a separate Intents extension target
in your Xcode project and bundling
that extension with your watchOS app.
As we've talked about previously,
the best experience is achieved
when shortcuts can run locally
on the watch
and don't need to rely
on remote execution.
And for that, you really
want to strive to support
as many intents in your watchOS
Intents extension as you can.
Ideally, on watchOS,
you should support all of the intents
that you support on iOS.
As you may know,
the great thing about shortcuts
is that any shortcut
that you see in the Shortcuts app
can also be run in Siri with your voice.
And on Watch, it is especially important
to provide carefully constructed dialogs
in your intents
because Intents UI extensions
are not supported on watchOS.
Here's an example of a Siri confirmation
UI for an intent-based ordering shortcut
that is using
the default confirmation prompt.
This is what you would see
if you return a default intent response
with code "ready"
from your "confirm()" method.
But it doesn't provide
a lot of information
beyond the fact
that you're about to order a soup.
In contrast to the previous example,
here we use a custom confirm response
and provide the person ordering the soup
with the order total
before they make the purchase.
But custom responses are very flexible
and you can provide
any additional information in your dialogs
that you think can be relevant or helpful
to people using your shortcut in Siri.
For information on how to
make your shortcuts work great in Siri,
please refer
to these past years' sessions.
Another great spot to showcase your app
on the watch is the Siri watch face.
You should see whether the shortcuts
that your app supports
can be relevant in various circumstances
and offer them on the Siri watch face.
And to do that, you can use the relevant
shortcut APIs from the Intents framework.
To learn more,
watch the "Siri Shortcuts on the Siri
Watch Face" session from WWDC 2018.
Let's recap what we've covered today.
First, to make your shortcuts work
on watchOS,
you should either build a watch app
or develop your shortcuts
to work with remote execution.
Second, if you're just starting
to adopt shortcuts in your apps,
prefer to implement them
using the richer Intents API.
Next, don't forget to compile
your Intents extension for watchOS
and to bundle it with your watch app.
You should also
construct your dialogs carefully
to ensure a great voice experience
for your shortcuts
when people run them in Siri.
And finally, consider offering
your shortcuts on the Siri watch face.
Thank you all for your time,
and we can't wait to see
what great shortcuts you will build.
[chimes]