Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome.
My name is Michael Ochs.
I'm a frameworks engineer
on the UIKit team,
and in this video we're going to talk
about lists in UICollectionView.
What you can see here is the architecture
that we consider part of
a modern Collection View setup,
and this diagram is covered in detail
in "Advances in Collection View."
There are individual videos
for the different parts of this diagram,
and in this video we're covering
list configuration and list cell.
But let's first talk about what
lists in collection views actually are.
Lists in iOS 14 give you UITableView-like
appearances in Collection View.
We built it on top of Compositional Layout
which we introduced in iOS 13.
That makes it very flexible
and highly customizable.
We also greatly improved the self-sizing
support specifically for lists
and are making self-sizing
the new default behavior
when using lists in UICollectionView.
What that means is,
you no longer need to worry
about manually calculating
the height of your cells,
but instead, you can simply
build your cells using auto layout,
and Collection View
will take care of the rest for you.
If you do require manual sizing, though,
you can still do this
by overriding
preferredLayoutAttributesFittingAttributes
on your cell sub-classes.
But let's circle back
to the customization aspect
and take a look at what I mean
when I say "highly customizable."
Here you can see an example of an app
that shows all my recently used emojis
in the top row, scrolling orthogonally.
Below that, you see an outline
that sorts all the emojis by group
and has this hierarchy built into it.
And then at the bottom,
we have something that looks
a lot more like a UITableView,
and in addition
you can also swipe each of the cells
to mark your favorite emojis.
What you see here
is a single collection view
using a combination of lists
and Compositional Layout.
Before we dig deeper into how this works,
let's look at the components of a list.
In iOS 14, we're offering a new type
called
UICollectionLayoutListConfiguration.
This is the only new type
that is required on the layout side
to build lists in Collection View.
UICollectionLayoutListConfiguration
is built on top of
NSCollectionLayoutSection
as well as
UICollectionViewCompositionalLayout,
which are both parts of the existing
Compositional Layout system
we introduced in iOS 13.
We're not going to cover Compositional
Layout in detail in this talk,
so if you're not familiar with it,
I highly recommend you to check out
"Advances in Collection View Layout"
from WWDC 2019.
But now,
let's take a look at list configuration.
List configuration gives you
the same appearances
that you already know
from Table View as styles:
plain, grouped and inset-grouped.
But we're also introducing two new styles
exclusive to lists in UICollectionView
which we call "sidebar"
and "sidebar plain."
And you can use these new styles
to build amazing multi-column apps
on iPadOS 14.
In addition to the general appearance,
list configuration also gives you
the option to show or hide separators
as well as to configure
the headers and footers of your list.
All this terminology on list configuration
should sound familiar to you
if you have used UITableView before.
But we did add a couple
of new bells and whistles
that we're going to talk about
in a minute.
But first,
let's take a look at how to create a list.
The easiest way to create a list
is to create
a UICollectionLayoutListConfiguration,
give it an appearance,
and then create
a UICollectionViewCompositionalLayout
using this configuration.
In this example,
we're using the inset-grouped style,
which will make this look exactly like
an inset-grouped UITableView,
with every section in this layout
looking the same.
So it's very similar to UITableView,
and I recommend you
to use this approach when possible.
However, there is a much more
powerful way to create a list,
and we call this the per-section setup.
In the per-section setup,
you use the exact same configuration,
but instead of creating
a compositional layout with it,
you create an NSCollectionLayoutSection
using this configuration.
This code can then be used inside
the existing section-provider initializer
on Compositional Layout,
which will then be called
for every section in your collection view,
allowing you to return
an individual layout definition
specific to the particular section.
What you see here will result
in the exact same design
as the simple setup I showed you earlier.
However, now that we have this set up,
we can start customizing our layout
on a per-section basis.
For example, here, for the first section,
I'm returning a custom grid layout
that I built using the existing
Compositional Layout APIs.
This is very powerful
and can be used for layouts
like the one you saw earlier in the video,
where I showed you
the orthogonally scrolling section
of my recently used emojis.
Now that you've seen how to create lists
in UICollectionView,
let's talk about how to configure your
headers and footers in a list section.
Headers and footers in lists
in collection views
work a bit different than
what you are used to from UITableView.
Headers and footers
in lists in UICollectionView
have to be explicitly enabled,
and there are two ways to do this.
The first way is to register your headers
and footers as supplementary views.
In this example,
we're going to configure a header,
but the same code also works for footers.
Simply set either the header
or the footer mode on the configuration
to "supplementary."
Next, when configured that way,
Collection View will ask you to provide
a supplementary view
when it's time to render
your header or footer on-screen.
The easiest way to provide this view
is through a supplementary-view provider
on your diffable data source,
but you can also implement
the equivalent method
on your UICollectionView delegate.
Inside of this callback,
you can then check the element kind
for either elementKindSectionHeader
or elementKindSectionFooter
and configure and return
the appropriate view.
It's important to keep in mind
that when using this approach,
you have to provide a supplementary view
when Collection View asks you to.
If you return nil
in the supplementary-view callback,
Collection View will assert.
So if some sections in your layout
require a header while others don't,
simply use the per-section configuration
that I showed you earlier
and set the mode
to either "supplementary" or "none,"
depending on whether this particular
section should show a header or not.
I mentioned there are two options.
The second option
is only available for headers,
and is enabled by setting the header mode
to firstItemInSection.
This tells the collection view
to configure the first cell
in this particular section
to look like a header.
This is the mode we're recommending
when using hierarchical data structures
and the new section-snapshot APIs.
You can learn all about how this works
in "Advances in Diffable Data Source."
However,
keep in mind that when using this mode,
your data source needs to be
aware of this,
because the first item in your data source
no longer represents
the actual content of your section
but rather the header,
probably just a title, of the section.
Now that we have covered
the layout of lists in Collection View,
let's talk about the presentation side.
In iOS 14, we are introducing
a new UICollectionView cell subclass
called UICollectionViewListCell.
It's worth mentioning that,
staying true to the compositional nature
of collection views,
you can use a list cell anywhere a regular
collection-view cell is expected,
and also you can just use any
UICollectionView cell with list sections.
So you can just pick the bits and pieces
of the API that you need
in order to achieve the design
that you are aiming for.
Let's take a look at what the pieces are
that list cell can help you with.
List cell has more fine-grained support
to configure the insets of separators
as well as the indentation
of your cell's content.
In contrast to UITableView,
swipe actions are now
also a feature of the cell.
Furthermore, we have
a greatly improved accessories API,
and of course you have access
to the default system content
and background configurations
that you can learn all about
in the video "Modern Cell Configuration."
So let's talk about separators.
Here you can see an example of a cell
that is rendering an image and a label
and a separator beneath it.
It's a pretty common layout.
However, as you might have noticed,
the layout you can see here
is actually not correct.
The separator is supposed to line up
with the primary content of your cell,
which in this example
is not the image view
but rather the label of the cell.
So on the leading side,
the separator is supposed to be inset
to match the edge of this label.
Like this.
On UITableView,
this is done by providing
a point-based value
called a separator inset.
This was pretty easy
when this API was introduced,
because you probably already had a method
that manually calculated
the x-offset of your label,
so you could use the same method
to also configure the separator inset
with the same value.
However, in the modern auto-layout world,
where you have safe-area insets,
layout margins,
dynamic font sizes and SF symbols,
it's not that easy anymore.
Today we have a highly dynamic environment
where all these values
could change at any time.
With dynamic fonts and SF symbols,
even the size of your image could change
depending on the preferred font size
of your users,
and then alter the position of the label.
So it's pretty hard to know up front
where the label is going to end up.
In list cell,
we're introducing a new concept
we're calling the separator layout guide.
This layout guide works a bit different
than the existing layout guides in UIKit.
Instead of constraining your content
to this layout guide,
you constrain this layout guide
to your content,
so it's the opposite of what you're
used to when working with layout guides.
The easiest way to set up
the separator layout guide
is to configure you cell's layout first,
and once your cell looks the way
you intend it to,
simply add a single additional constraint.
Constrain the separatorLayoutGuide's
leading anchor
to your label's leading anchor
or to whatever the primary content is
in your cell.
List cell, together with list section,
will then make sure to automatically keep
the separator aligned
with the primary content of your cell.
Note that if you're using the
system-provided content configurations,
it will do this automatically for you,
and you don't have to worry about this.
But if you have custom cell layouts,
this is an easy way to make sure
the separator is positioned correctly.
Now let's talk about swipe actions.
In contrast to UITableView, swipe actions
are now a feature of list cell.
You configure them together
with the content of your cell.
So wherever you configure the image view
or the labels of your cell,
you can now also set the leading
or trailing swipe-actions configuration.
This requires communication
between the cell and the layout,
so swipe actions are only supported
if your cell is rendered
inside of a section
that was configured
using a list configuration.
If you require the dynamic nature of the
swipe-action API we had on UITableView,
where you only create
the swipe configuration
when the swipe is about to start,
you can override the leading or trailing
swipe-actions configuration getter
and then create
the configuration in there.
We will make sure to only call the getter
when the user actually attempts
to swipe this cell.
A word of caution.
In the action handler
of your swipe actions,
make sure to never capture the index path
of the cell you are configuring.
The index path is not a stable identifier.
The index path of this cell changes
whenever you're inserting
or deleting content above it,
which doesn't necessarily reload
this particular cell.
So if you use a stored index path
to fetch the data model of the cell
when the user triggers a swipe action,
you might actually operate
on the data of another cell.
This is particularly dangerous
for the delete action,
as you might delete the wrong data.
Instead,
either capture the data model directly
or a stable identifier that you can use
to identify the content of this cell.
Diffable data source
and its stable item identifiers,
as well as the new
cell-registration type in iOS 14,
are a perfect fit for this.
Next, let's talk about accessories,
On UITableView,
the accessories API was fairly limited.
You had access to an accessory type
and an accessory view,
which were mutually exclusive
and were only relevant
for the trailing side of your cell.
List cell offers many new accessory types
and also allows you
to configure accessories
for both the trailing
and the leading side of the cell,
and you can even configure multiple
accessories on the same side.
Furthermore, where in UITableView cell
accessories were more like
decoration views,
in list cell
they can enable functionality.
For example, if you configure a cell
with the reorder accessory,
we will automatically put
the collection view in reordering mode
when the user taps this accessory,
assuming you also implement
the necessary reorder callbacks.
Another example is the delete accessory,
which was previously known
as the delete edit control.
If the user taps this accessory,
list cell will automatically reveal
any configured trailing swipe actions
of your cell.
And we also have a brand-new accessory:
the outline-disclosure accessory.
When the user taps this accessory,
the cell will automatically communicate
with the data source
and expand or collapse
the children of this cell.
This requires the use
of the new section-snapshot APIs,
and you can learn all about that
in "Advances in Diffable Data Source."
Now let's take a look
at how the API works.
In order to configure
the accessories of your cell,
all you have to do is to set
a single accessories property on list cell
to an area of UI cell accessories.
For this example,
I'm going to configure the cell
with a disclosure indicator
and a delete accessory.
The system knows
that the disclosure indicator
is supposed to always be
on the trailing side of your cell,
whereas the delete accessory always shows
on the leading side of your cell.
So UIKit will automatically sort
the accessories in the correct order
and show them on the appropriate side.
Furthermore, the system also knows that,
while the disclosure indicator
is supposed to be visible all the time,
the delete accessory
should only be visible
when the collection view
is in editing mode.
So UIKit will automatically animate
the delete accessory in or out
when entering or exiting edit mode.
We provide a lot of these system defaults,
but we allow you to customize
almost all of them.
For example,
if you want the disclosure indicator
to only be visible
when not in editing mode,
simply set the displayed parameter
to whenNotEditing.
This is a super-declarative API,
where UIKit takes care
of all the states for you.
As you've seen,
lists are a highly customizable layout
that is very modular and flexible.
It is super easy to adopt,
so go check out the sample code
and play around with it.
There is a lot more to discover in there.
And once you've familiarized yourself
with the new APIs,
think about where you could enhance
the layouts in your app.
Think about where you could replace
an existing table view
and make use
of the flexibility to mix lists
with any custom compositional layout.
And of course, also check out all the
other videos we have on UICollectionView.
There are a lot more amazing features
in collection views in iOS 14.
Thank you so much for watching.