Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, WWDC. This is Swan's Quest.
I'm Rob,
your host as we take an inside look
at an exciting Swift Playgrounds challenge
our crack team has built for you.
Are you ready?
In this episode, we're going to build upon
our knowledge of Timer and ToneOutput.
In this third episode,
you again start back in the lizard's hut
to uncover the mystery
of another scroll from the Swan.
I don't want to spoil it for you,
but I can tell you, to pass this challenge
you need to understand tempo
and how to play notes of different length.
We're going to start with a crash course
on music theory.
You're going to learn about the difference
between quarter notes and half notes.
The second challenge
only used a single note length,
so we'll revisit our timer, and talk about
how to create variable durations.
And finally, we're going to wrap up
with another exciting side quest.
Let's talk about rhythm.
We've already discussed in prior episodes
how to play notes of different pitch.
But as you can see in the Swan's scroll,
we need to learn how to play notes
of different length.
Since everyone can't read music,
let's discuss three different lengths
of notes as an example.
Here we see the quarter note,
the half note, and the dotted half note.
Most tempos are defined by the quarter
note, so we'll use that as our baseline.
A half note is twice as long,
and a dotted half note
is three times as long as a quarter note.
The tempo for the song the Swan wants
to hear is 120 beats per minute.
That means there are 120 quarter notes
in a minute.
From there, we calculate the interval
for our timer
so we can play each length of note
in the scroll.
In Music.swift, we've included protocols
for you to implement.
The first is Pitches, to capture
the frequency for the ToneOutput.
An example could look like this.
You'll want to add additional cases
for each pitch in the Swan's scroll.
Next, we need to represent a note
as a tone of a certain length.
The length should be provided
as a multiple of a quarter note.
For example, a half note would return 2.0
and an eighth note would return 0.5.
An example could look like this.
Again, you'll need to add cases
to the enum
for each length of note in the scroll.
Next we need to update our timer code.
So let's check in with Stephen.
As Rob mentioned,
we need to update our timer code
to allow for variable-length notes.
Before we get into our approach,
let's update our code
to use the types that Rob just showed you.
First, let's update our sample to use
the pitch and note types we just defined.
Unfortunately,
this isn't going to work out of the box
because the TimeInterval for the timer
does not respect our note length.
Remember that the ToneOutput
emits a continuous tone
until it is told to stop.
Our approach to updating the timer
can take advantage of this.
First, we need to set the timer's interval
to the duration
of the shortest note's length.
To do that, we'll update our NoteProtocol
to add a property,
shortestSupportedNoteLength.
Then we update our note implementation.
Since the quarter note is
the shortest note in the Swan's scroll,
we'll choose the quarter note
to keep things simple.
Finally, we update our timer's interval
to the shortest note length
multiplied by our tempo.
This example assumes 120 beats per minute,
which means the length of a quarter note
is 500 milliseconds.
Next, we need to subdivide
our larger notes
into a flattened array of pitches.
We need to send the ToneOutput
a set of pitch instructions
for each timer interval.
Since our smallest supported note
is the quarter note,
we only send one instruction.
Likewise,
half notes send two instructions.
Dotted half notes
would send three instructions, and so on.
To subdivide your notes,
you'll need to implement another method
in your NoteProtocol implementation.
"Subdivide" returns an array of pitches
that can be collected
and sent to the ToneOutput.
Now, in our timer loop, we first create
the subdivided array of pitches.
Then we update our timer loop
to iterate over the pitches,
instead of the notes array.
This completed example
demonstrates all of the API you need
to complete the challenge.
Rob, do you have another side quest
for our audience?
I sure do, Stephen. But before we get
to that, I need to warn you.
This side quest will contain spoilers
for this chapter's challenge.
If you want to complete the challenge
first, hit pause on this video
and come back
after you've completed the challenge.
Good luck!
Okay, are you ready?
The Swan's challenge
was to play "Ode to Joy,"
and the scroll provided
all of the notes for you.
Let's see if you can upgrade that code
to play bass chords underneath it.
I just have one hint for you.
You can layer tones on top of one another
by using multiple timers.
During this episode we gave you tips
for completing the third challenge
in Swan's Quest.
We talked about rhythm
and how tempo is defined.
Then we discussed how to use
a single, fixed-duration timer
with subdivided pitches
to play notes of different length.
Good luck, have fun,
and join us in the forums to share
your solutions for the side quests.
We'd love to hear how you did.