Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Michael Harris,
and I'm a GPU software engineer at Apple.
Today I'd like to talk about
the improvements we've made
to Metal's debugging tools,
specifically for errors
in GPU-side Metal shader code.
So what are a few examples of errors
that we can make in Metal shader code?
You could have an out of bounds access
in global or shared memory.
You could attempt to access
a null texture resource.
Or you might have forgotten to call
useResource when using argument buffers,
resulting in invalid resource residency.
You may have a timeout, which can be
caused by long-running or infinite loops.
This isn't an exhaustive list,
but it's some of the more common errors
we Metal developers experience.
These errors can often cause one another.
An infinite loop may be caused
by an out of bounds access
of the loop iteration count.
The result of a GPU-side error
is a message like this one.
In comparison, here's what we get
from an API usage error on the CPU.
Let's compare and contrast
these two errors
because there's a pretty large gap
in useful information.
For a GPU error, all we get is a message
that says something went wrong,
but not much about what or where.
But when there's an API usage error,
Metal provides
a lot of useful information.
It shows the API entry point
the error occurred on.
It shows what type of error it was.
In this case, we set an offset
larger than the buffer's length.
There's also a call stack
of exactly where the error occurred,
including line and file information
from your codebase.
Wouldn't it be nice if the GPU errors
looked a bit more like the API errors?
Today, we'll show you some new tools
to help improve the debugging experience
of GPU errors.
To help illustrate
where our new tools fit in,
we'll use a debugging workflow of detect,
locate, classify and fix.
Metal has always had API validation
to help you catch issues early.
Finding them early means
that they're caught
before they can cause problems
further down the line.
Using it,
you can detect when there's API misuse,
locate the function causing the issue,
and classify the error message.
We'll leave fixing the error up to you.
But what about errors in your Metal
shading language usage on the GPU?
You've seen how these errors appeared
on iOS 13 and macOS Catalina.
Metal provides a basic error message.
It's enough to tell you something happened
in the execution of that command buffer,
but not much else.
So today, Metal is introducing
two new diagnostic tools
that will help improve the debug workflow:
enhanced command buffer errors
and the shader validation layer.
First, let's talk about
enhanced command buffer errors.
What is it? Well, it enhances
your command buffer's errors.
To be more specific,
it improves the existing
command buffer error mechanism
by helping you detect and locate
execution errors at the encoder level.
Here's that GPU error again.
There isn't a lot
of actionable information here.
When you're debugging a command buffer
that might have hundreds of encoders,
making progress is a lot of work.
Here's that same error,
but this time we've turned on
enhanced command buffer errors.
It's an obvious improvement
over what we had before.
You have information about each encoder
within this command buffer,
and that helps you
narrow down the failure.
Most of our encoders completed their work.
But there are a few suspect encoders
that have been marked
as affected or faulted.
That narrows
our search down significantly.
Enabling enhanced command buffer errors
is simple.
All you have to do
is create your command buffer
with the new descriptor-based API
and set the errorOptions
to encoderExecutionStatus.
That's it.
If an error occurs
while the feature is enabled,
you can get encoder-level information
about that error.
Here in our code example,
we're using the encoder info error key
to access the user info data
of this error.
This is where we'll find the array of
our encoder info objects to iterate over.
As you can see here,
each encoder info object
has the label and debugSignposts
that you're already using
to uniquely identify each command encoder.
If you're not already using
labels and signposts,
now's a great time to start.
The error state tells you the status
of the command encoder
at the time of the fault.
Or, alternatively,
if you don't want to format it yourself,
you could just log the whole error.
That will print all the information
related to the error.
The ErrorState property
has a few possible values:
completed, pending, faulted,
affected and unknown.
Faulted is the most important error state
because it means that this encoder
was directly responsible
for the command buffer fault.
Affected could still indicate
the faulting encoder,
but unlike the faulted state,
we're not a hundred percent sure.
A fault on one encoder
could have affected multiple encoders
that are running in parallel, including
encoders from different processes.
In the rare event where we can't tell
the state of an encoder,
we'll report the unknown state.
There's synergy
with the existing GPU tools as well.
Since the encoder info objects
are in recorded order
and use your labels and debug signposts,
you can easily associate them
with the same encoder in Metal Debugger,
Metal System Trace,
and other tools built into Xcode.
For example, with this information,
you can jump right to the relevant encoder
in Metal Debugger.
So, when should you turn it on?
First off, you should enable it
on every command buffer
during development and QA.
That will enhance
all your internal error reports
and give you quick feedback on any errors.
Since enhanced command buffer errors
are built right into Metal,
it doesn't require any auxiliary layers.
It's designed so that the API
can leverage hardware functionality
in its implementation.
That makes it into a low-overhead feature.
Because it is so low-overhead,
you can even ship your application
with the feature enabled.
Since it's command buffer-specific,
you can target what command buffers
to enable it on.
As you get telemetry and bug reports,
you can tune the set of command buffers
to hone in on the problem.
That said, test your performance
before enabling on user devices.
The performance impact varies
across devices and workloads,
so you'll want to check
whether the overhead is acceptable to you.
The challenge with debugging
Metal shader code
is that the codebase can be large
and can contain
a lot of places for errors to occur.
The first step is knowing where to look,
and enhanced command buffer errors
helps with that.
It can get us to the encoder level,
but to go deeper,
Metal provides another tool.
That's where shader validation comes in:
to detect, locate and classify
the error at the draw call level
to help you debug and fix it.
So let's talk about the shader validation
layer and what it can do for you.
It's a layer similar to the API
validation layer, but running on the GPU.
It instruments your Metal shaders
to detect logical issues
as well as locate and classify them.
When it detects that an operation
would've caused undefined behavior,
that operation is prevented
and a log is created
that can be used to locate the draw call,
Metal function,
possibly even the line in the shader
causing the error.
This tool can help you debug issues
that cause command buffer errors,
and it can help you
detect ones that don't.
This is important
because there's many types of errors
that don't actually cause
a command buffer to fail
but are still undefined behavior.
Let's walk through one of those cases now.
We'll start by allocating two buffers,
A and B.
We want to read from buffer A
but have a logic issue
such that it causes us
to read out of bounds.
What happens next is undefined
and depends on
Metal's allocation behavior.
You could get lucky,
and there's unallocated memory
in between the two buffers.
If you go out of bounds in this case,
you can get a command buffer fault.
Since there's a fault,
it's obvious feedback
that something bad has happened,
and enhanced command buffer errors
will narrow it down to the encoder.
But if you're unlucky,
out of bounds access
won't cause a command buffer fault.
Metal may place the buffers
one after another in virtual memory
with no unallocated space between.
Here, our logic error
won't cause a command buffer fault.
We still go out of bounds
but end up landing in another allocation
and either read the wrong data
or corrupt another buffer.
Such issues can be hard to detect
and frustrating to debug,
as they may appear intermittent.
The most important thing to take
from that example
is that you should always test
with API validation
and shader validation before shipping.
Just because you're not seeing
a command buffer fault
does not rule out that you don't have
any undefined behavior.
Undefined behavior isn't always obvious,
and it can appear intermittent.
But the good news is
that shader validation
is meant to detect these cases,
including the ones that aren't obvious.
Let's go over what shader validation
can and cannot detect.
It can detect out of bounds device
and constant memory access,
out of bounds threadgroup memory access,
and attempting to use texturing functions
on a null texture object.
This doesn't cover
all of the common issues mentioned,
but for everything else,
enhanced command buffer errors can help.
You won't get draw information,
but it will narrow down to the encoder.
The most powerful way
to use this feature when debugging
is from within Xcode,
and enabling it is easy.
First, bring up the scheme settings
in your project.
In the Diagnostics tab,
we have a new section
for diagnostics specific to Metal.
Checking the box next to Shader Validation
will enable the layer
and enhanced command buffer errors
for all command buffers.
Once the layer is enabled,
you still need to enable
the Metal diagnostics breakpoint.
The Metal diagnostics breakpoint
tells Xcode to stop
the execution of the program
when a shader validation error occurs
and to show the recorded
GPU and CPU backtrace for that error.
Clicking the arrow
to the right of shader validation
will add the breakpoint.
Once the breakpoint has been added,
you can find it in the Debug Navigator
on the Breakpoints tab.
You can view
the settings of this breakpoint
by clicking on the blue arrow.
That will bring up this interface,
where you can customize the breakpoint.
To configure the breakpoint
for shader validation,
first make sure
the breakpoint is enabled.
Then set the Type
to System Frameworks
and enter "Metal Diagnostics"
into the Category field.
At this point, you're ready
to use the feature within Xcode.
Now let's jump into a demo
showing it in action.
We're using the Metal Performance Shader
Ray Tracing sample code.
We've introduced an easy-to-make GPU error
into the sample for this demo.
During the demo,
we'll go through using shader validation
to detect and debug this issue.
First, I'll start by launching the app
without shader validation.
That doesn't look quite right.
There's missing shadows
and a bunch of lines on the screen.
Why this isn't rendering isn't obvious,
though.
We're not getting
any command buffer errors,
so we don't know which encoder
or Metal function has the bug.
Before we start trying to debug this
line by line,
I'll use Metal's new debugging workflow
by enabling shader validation.
First, I'll bring up
the scheme settings in my project.
And then I'll go into the Diagnostics tab
and then down at the bottom,
there'll be options
for API validation and shader validation.
The API validation has been moved
from a different tab to this one.
Now I'll enable API validation
and shader validation.
Since I want to have Xcode break
on the first validation error,
I'll click this arrow to add
the Metal diagnostics breakpoint.
Now I'm set up to use shader validation,
and I'll relaunch the application.
So we have some logs being printed
in the console from shader validation
indicating that it detected an error.
Since I have the breakpoint enabled,
Xcode has stopped my application
and brought up the Metal shader
where the error occurred.
Xcode is also showing a shader annotation
on the line that shader validation found
had an error.
I can click the shader annotation,
and it'll show some more details
about this error.
Based on the annotation,
I'm hitting an out of bounds memory read.
Looking at this expression,
there's only one memory access going on.
We're reading the maxDistance field
from the shadowRay argument,
which is a pointer in device memory.
There are two possibilities here:
either shadowRay is null
or shadowRay points to invalid memory.
Since we enabled API validation,
that would've caught a null buffer
binding, so we can rule that one out.
Just looking at the function here,
it's not clear how the address
of shadowRay is being calculated.
So we'll use the GPU backtrace view
in the bottom left-hand side of Xcode.
This view shows
the GPU backtrace of the error,
which has the recorded
call stack of the error
at the time the error occurred.
We can traverse this call stack just like
you would any other recorded call stack.
I'll click on the stack
below our function,
which will jump me to the call site
of the function shadowRayIntersection.
It looks like the variable shadowRay
is what's being passed in,
which is computed by taking
the shadowRay's argument
and indexing it using
the rayIndex variable.
Since we suspect an invalid offset,
we need to investigate rayIndex.
Looking at the comment
above the computation of rayIndex,
its code intends to convert
a 2D grid coordinate
into a 1D array coordinate.
That's typically accomplished by
multiplying the grid Y with the grid width
and then adding the grid X.
However,
looking closely at this expression,
we see that instead of multiplying
the grid Y and the width,
we're multiplying the X and the width.
That's definitely a typo, so let's
correct that and rerun the application.
Now our app is fixed.
With the help of shader validation
and API validation,
we were able to quickly locate
and classify this issue.
We realize you're not always able
to run everything under Xcode,
so with some additional setup, you can
use shader validation without Xcode.
That lets you use shader validation
for use cases like automated testing.
Similar to API validation,
shader validation can be enabled
using two new environment variables
we've added to the new macOS and iOS 14.
These variables must be set
before any Metal device
is created for that process.
Once a device is created,
we latch their values,
so any changes to them after that point
will not have an effect.
To enable API validation,
set MTL_DEBUG_LAYER to any non-zero value.
And to enable shader validation,
set MTL_SHADER_VALIDATION
to any non-zero value.
Both of these can be set at once
or used independently.
The command buffer
now has a new logs property
which allows you to retrieve the details
for any validation errors that occurred.
The first thing to note
is that the log's property
is only valid
after a command buffer finishes.
For that reason, we're doing all
of our work inside the completion handler.
We'll walk through this code sample,
showing how to use the new API
and what information it provides.
Each command buffer can have
multiple shader validation errors.
So we're gonna iterate
through all of them.
Every log object contains information
about the shader validation error.
Like the label of the encoder
that had an error,
that will give you the label,
but there can be more information.
If your Metal library
was compiled from source
or was compiled with debug samples,
each log may also have
a debugLocation property.
This property is the GPU stack frame
containing the error,
and it will hold the file URL
and line of the faulting expression.
Alternatively, you could just use
the description property.
This contains all the same information
formatted in an easy-to-read string.
You'll also be able to find
this information in the system log.
You can access this log by running
this highlighted command in your Terminal.
When a validation error occurs,
it'll show up like this.
The first thing in the log
is the process name
the error is occurring from.
The next will be the type of error
and then the error details.
Finally, the name of the Metal file
and the line information.
We have some tips to help you
get the most out of shader validation.
You can expect pipelines
to take a bit longer to compile.
Because of that,
you should really be using
the asynchronous compilation methods.
That will parallelize compilation
across multiple threads,
which will help mitigate the increased
load times during development.
You should also enable debug symbols
when compiling your Metal libraries.
That should automatically happen
if you're using a debug scheme in Xcode.
But if you are invoking
the Metal front-end manually,
symbols can be enabled
by adding the "-g" flag.
If any of your libraries
are compiled from source online,
debug symbols
will automatically be enabled.
If you are compiling libraries online,
we recommend using
the line preprocessor directive.
The backtrace we report
uses the file name to identify a shader.
Off-line compiled metalib files
include this information automatically,
but it's missing when compiling
from source at runtime.
You can manually add
the file name information
by using the line directive to tell
the compiler what file it was sourced from
or to provide a useful identifier.
Due to the nature of its instrumentation,
there are a few things to be aware of
when enabling shader validation.
Shader validation is a process-wide switch
that when enabled
causes all Metal commands,
including UI rendering,
to go through the shader validation layer.
Unlike enhanced command buffer errors,
using shader validation does have
a high performance and memory impact.
We recommend enabling this feature
in development and during QA
but not for users because of this impact.
Enabling the feature may also change
some queries to return different values.
In particular, you should always check
the maxTotalThreadsPerThreadgroup
and the threadExecutionWidth properties
of a compute pipeline state,
as these two may change
when shader validation is enabled.
We support some level of customization
on how this feature behaves,
such as disabling specific checks.
For example, if you're already doing
null texture checks,
you can safely disable
texture usage instrumentation
by setting the environment variable
MTL_SHADER_VALIDATION_TEXTURE_USAGE
to zero.
While disabling some instrumentation
can improve runtime
and compile time performance,
it's at the cost of no longer detecting
some possible issues.
More information
about what flags are supported
can be found
at the new MetalValidation man page.
Some features are not supported
when using shader validation.
Binary function pointers
and dynamic linking are not supported.
There's an additional limitation
for MTLGPUFamilyMac1,
as well as MTLGPUFamilyApple5
and older devices,
which is that global memory access
of pointers
coming from an argument buffer
are not checked.
Thank you very much
for coming to our session
about the two new Metal debugging tools
we've added this year.
First, we covered
enhanced command buffer errors,
which is a low-overhead in-framework tool
that helps you detect and locate
your faulting encoders
in multiple environments,
like during development and QA,
or even after you've shipped.
And we just covered shader validation,
which helps you detect,
locate and classify
both subtle and obvious shader errors
during development and QA.
Now go out and try the features.
Test your apps with enhanced command
buffer errors and shader validation.
Thanks, and have a great WWDC.