Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Roger Pantos,
and today I'd like to talk to you
about Blocking Preload Hints in HLS.
So first, what are Blocking Preload Hints,
and what are they good for?
To understand preload hinting,
it helps to understand a similar feature
of Low-Latency HLS,
which is Blocking Playlist Reload.
We actually have an entire other talk
about Blocking Playlist Reload.
But the basic idea is that the client
can ask the server
for the next version of the playlist
in advance.
The server will then
hold onto that request
and unblock its response
when that playlist updates.
That allows the client
to receive the update immediately.
Preload hinting is similar,
except it's for loading
the partial segments themselves.
The idea is to make the request in advance
to lower the eventual response time.
The benefit of preload hinting
is that it gets the media flowing
to the client from the server
as soon as it's available.
And that eliminates that round-trip bubble
between seeing a new segment
appear in the playlist update
and then having to go back
and ask the server for it.
It's also effective
for driving HTTP cache fill,
because it eliminates another round trip,
this time between the cache
and the origin.
That is a significant win for global CDNs,
because the round trip there
between the edge and the origin
can easily exceed 100 milliseconds.
So let's take a look at how it works
in Low-Latency HLS.
In Low-Latency HLS, every playlist
must carry a Preload Hint tag
that has the URL
of the next Partial Segment
that the packager expects to appear.
When the client gets that playlist,
it will turn around
and ask for that hinted URL.
The server then holds onto that request
until that Partial Segment is available
and then sends it to the client.
Now, normally the client also has
a Blocking Playlist Reload pending request
at the same time,
which will unblock at about the same time
as the hint request.
So the client will generally
see them both arrive at the same time.
Preload hints are also used
to signal upcoming MAP tags
so that the client can get a jump
on content transitions,
such as at AD boundaries.
So to recap,
here is the request flow for hinting.
Here we have an HLS client on the left
and a server on the right.
First, the client issues a Blocking
Playlist Reload request for the next part.
That blocks on the server,
and the client issues a request
for the hinted partial segment,
which also blocks because
that partial segment isn't there yet.
Eventually the server will finish encoding
and packaging the partial segment,
and it will unblock the response
for the hint request.
At the same time, it will add
the new Partial Segment to the playlist
and unblock the playlist update as well.
So that's the request flow.
Let's take a look at how it looks
in the playlist syntax.
Here we have a Low-Latency playlist
with one-second parts.
That last part at the bottom in green
is called "part1.1.m4s."
Beneath that, there is a Preload Hint tag
saying that the next part the client
can try to load is "part1.2."
And so that's the mechanism
for the client issuing a preload hint.
Now, in this case,
every Partial Segment has its own URL.
But a Partial Segment can alternately be
a byte-range of a larger resource.
And so how does preload hinting
work for those?
The Preload Hint tag can optionally
include the start of the byte-range
and the length of the Partial Segment.
The length is omitted if we don't know
it when the hint is published.
So one way that can look is like this,
where we're hinting the range
from zero to 4,044 of segment 23.
But you can alternately hint the client
to load more than one Partial Segment
in a single request.
You can do that with an open-ended
preload hint like this one.
And this is actually a good excuse
to talk about CMAF Chunks.
Chunks are essentially what CMAF calls
fMP4 Fragments
that can be transferred individually.
Where byte-ranges come into play is that
one way to deliver Partial Segments
is to progressively append them
to their parent segments
and have the client make one request
for the parent segment URL
to get every Partial Segment
as it becomes available.
Doing it this way does require you
to use Chunk Transfer Encoding
between the server and the client.
And the caveat here is that many CDNs
don't actually support Chunk Transfer
Encoding for live content delivery.
But if you have a CDN that does,
then the benefit you get
is that you can use the same media
that you're serving to
your Low-Latency HLS clients
to serve the Latency Dash as well.
Let's see how that works.
First,
every resource URL is a Parent Segment.
The Parent Segment is going to be made up
of multiple CMAF Chunks.
Then, for Low-Latency HLS, each Chunk
would be mapped to a Partial Segment.
They get specified with
a Parent Segment URL and a byte-range.
Here's how a Partial Segment
might be declared in a Playlist
as a Part tag with a URL and a byte-range.
So that's how CMAF Chunks show up
as Partial Segments in a playlist.
Now, how does preload hinting work?
The Preload Hint tag in this case
will just contain the URL
of the parent segment.
And that Preload Hint tag will get updated
every time the server moves
to a new parent segment.
Every time it finishes appending
a new CMAF Chunk,
it will update the byte-range
start attribute of the Preload Hint tag
to point to the end of the new Chunk.
Because remember,
this tag's hinting the next
Partial Segment here, not the current one.
And we leave off the byte-range length
because at this point
we don't actually have it.
At that point,
every time the client sees a new
Preload Hint URL appear in the playlist,
it will issue a GET request for it.
And every time a new Chunk
finishes being appended,
the server will send that byte-range
to the client via Chunk Transfer Encoding
and the client will harvest every Partial
Segment out of that single HTTP request.
Let's look at an example.
Here we have a playlist
with one-second parts.
You can see that the Partial Segments
above segment zero
are actually expressed in byte-ranges
of segment zero
and that the Preload Hint tag
at the bottom
tells the client to start loading
segment 1 at offset zero.
One second later,
the playlist gets updated,
and now there's a new Partial Segment.
And sure enough, it's declared
as the first 3,000 bytes of segment 1.
In addition, the Preload Hint tag
has been updated to say
that the next Partial Segment
will start at offset 3,000.
So one second after that,
the playlist updates again.
And now there is a second part, specified
as a new byte-rate range of segment 1,
and the Hint says that the next part
will start at offset 8,000.
And so we repeat this pattern.
We hint a part and then we add it.
So that's how preload hinting works.
But before we finish talking about it,
there are a few more things to know.
First, it is legal
for a server to change its plan
after it publishes a Preload Hint tag,
and the most common reason for this
is when an operator decides that they
actually want to return early from an ad,
so they change their mind halfway through.
In that case,
the next time the playlist updates,
the client will notice
that the previously hinted URL
no longer appears in the playlist,
and so it will cancel
its pending hint request
and switch to loading
whatever it finds in the playlist now.
The other thing to know is that
hint requests for prerecorded content,
such as ads, can be served right away
without blocking.
So that's in contrast to live content,
where you have to wait
for the entire thing to be encoded
before you can put it on the server.
We've got a separate session
that goes into more detail
around serving ads for Low-Latency HLS.
But for right now, let's wrap up
our discussion of preload hinting.
So in summary,
preload hinting is where clients ask
for the next Partial Segment in advance,
and that gets the part
flowing to the client as soon as possible.
A server can either hint
an entire resource
or individual byte-ranges,
and that enables Chunk Transfer delivery
of CMAF segments and interoperability
with Low-Latency DASH.
Preload hinting is an important part of
optimizing the entire delivery pipeline,
which is why they are required
by Low-Latency HLS.
I hope this gives you a good idea of
what preload hinting is and how it works,
and that it helps you to deploy
Low-Latency HLS.
Thank you very much.