Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, I'm Alex Walczak,
and today I'll be showing you
how adding Custom Rotors to VoiceOver
can make your apps more accessible
for all users.
VoiceOver is Apple's screen reader that
lets you interact with any Apple device
even if you can't see the screen.
You use VoiceOver by touching the screen
to hear what's under your finger
and then perform simple gestures
to navigate the user interface.
People who aren't looking at the screen
rely on the rotor for many tasks,
a couple of which I will show you today.
By twisting two fingers on the screen,
as if rotating a dial,
the power of the rotor becomes enabled
at your fingertips.
A swipe down now moves you
to the next rotor item on the screen
and a swipe up moves you
to the previous item.
By adding custom rotors to your app
that respond to simple flick gestures,
you can transform
how a user experiences your app.
Navigating complex interfaces
becomes so much easier
and finding related elements in your app
is as simple as a flick up or down.
So to show you that,
we'll look at a couple examples,
beginning with how custom rotors make
navigating a complex interface easier.
But first, I'd like to show you
the VoiceOver experience in my app
without any custom rotors.
I'm developing an app that shows
your location on the map
and Apple Stores and parks around you.
I'll turn on VoiceOver so we can see
how it traverses the views of the app,
from top to bottom,
following the layout direction
of the user interface.
[VoiceOver] Apple, Bay Street.
San Francisco Bay.
Bay Bridge. Alcatraz Island.
This grid represents how people
might experience my app through VoiceOver
without any custom rotors.
Just as in the demo,
let's see how VoiceOver cursor moves
not only between Apple Stores and parks,
but also between bridges
and other points of interest.
Notice how someone using VoiceOver
has to move sequentially through
the items from all categories
while someone looking at the screen
will use an icon and its color
to focus on items from a single category.
How could we enable VoiceOver users
to experience my app
the same as anybody else?
What we could start by doing is
figuring out which items in the interface
draw our attention visually.
So in the case of my app, that would be
the markers for Apple Stores and parks.
Next, we can group these items
by category,
and then create custom rotors to explore
items just within their categories.
So let's do that.
We'll implement a rotor for Apple Stores
and another rotor for parks.
When we do that, we can sort the items
of each rotor by distance from the user.
and include the distance in the
accessibility information of each item.
This way, somebody using the rotor
to interact with the UI
can quickly scan
the closest Apple Stores...
and scan the closest parks...
just as how somebody looking at the screen
might focus on the locations
closest to their position.
Let's see how these two rotors operate
once they're implemented.
First, we look at
the finished Apple Stores rotor.
[VoiceOver] Apple Stores.
Apple, Chestnut Street, 0.9 miles.
Apple, Union Square, 1.8 miles.
Apple, Stonestown, 4.6 miles.
[Alex] And now, we see the Parks rotor.
[VoiceOver] Parks.
Alamo Square, 0.8 miles.
Corona Heights Park, 1.5 miles.
Hippie Hill, 1.5 miles.
In both examples,
as the user moves through
the sorted locations in each custom rotor,
they can quickly determine
which locations,
either Apple Stores or parks,
they are closest to.
This shows that
custom rotors make it possible
to deliver a similar experience
for all users
especially in navigating
complex interfaces like this map.
How can we add these rotors to the app?
Well, when VoiceOver lands
on the 'map view',
it looks for any custom rotors
in the view's
accessibilityCustomRotors property.
My app needs two rotors,
one for Apple Stores and one for parks,
so we'll be setting this property equal to
two custom rotors.
And since each rotor filters
the same map annotations,
we only need to implement one method
to make both rotors.
Let's start building this method
which returns
a new UIAccessibilityCustomRotor
for one type of point of interest.
A custom rotor is implemented
with minimal extra work by the developer,
thanks to a block syntax.
After initializing a UIAccessibilityCustomRotor with a localized name,
we'll perform some basic logic
in the closure,
and return a UIAccessibilityCustomRotor
Item Result
representing the next point of interest
VoiceOver will land on.
You can extract the current rotor item
from the block argument
and prepare a list of possible items
the user can move to.
The property 'searchDirection'
tells you whether the user flipped up
to go to the previous item
or down to go to the next item.
This information can be used to decrement
or increment the index
in the list of possible items.
Return nil to tell the user
they're at the first or last item
and VoiceOver will remain focused
on that point of interest.
Otherwise, finish by returning a new
UIAccessibilityCustomRotorItemResult
with the previous or next item
as the target element.
I've described a number of steps here,
but as a developer,
remember that all you need to do
to take advantage of
the custom rotor API in your app
is implement this closure
and add your new custom rotor
to your view's list of
accessibility Custom Rotors.
Custom rotors can have a huge impact
on how somebody will interact with
groups of elements in your app.
But they aren't the only way to improve
the accessibility of complex interfaces.
To learn another way,
check out this talk on how
custom actions can enhance interactions
with individual elements in your app.
We've already seen that custom rotors
can be used to find related elements
like stores and parks on a map.
Now let's learn how a custom rotor can be
used on a different kind of content: text.
My app pulls up a brochure
when you tap on a location,
and since I'm planning a picnic
at Golden Gate Park,
I've pulled up its brochure.
Wow, so many things to do.
Let's use the built-in Lines rotor
which automatically appears for text,
to navigate this brochure line by line.
[VoiceOver] Lines.
Golden Gate Park. Plan your visit.
Dutch Windmill. Visit in March
to see the tulips in full bloom.
This towering landmark
stands on the park's eastern edge.
East Meadow.
Picnic area closed for maintenance.
A great place for families with pets
to have a picnic.
Great. We were able to hear
some of the content
but look how long it took us
to get to that first alert.
We had to hear all the preceding content
just to find out
that I should definitely not be choosing
East Meadow as my picnic spot.
Not to mention, there are
a couple more alerts we haven't gotten to,
so we won't know
if we've listened to all the alerts
if we don't carefully listen
to every line in this brochure, right?
Wait, actually,
we can implement a custom rotor
to take us through just the alerts
so we can hear this critical information
as fast as anyone looking at the screen
will notice the alert icons.
So let's see
what a rotor for 'alerts' will look like.
[VoiceOver] Alerts.
East Meadow.
Picnic area closed for maintenance.
Oak Woodlands Trail.
Muddy trail conditions.
Ocean Beach.
Expect dense fog and high winds.
Great. As expected, the 'alerts' rotor
only moves among the alerts
so we can plan our trip to the park
so much more efficiently.
Our text view only has one custom rotor,
for alerts.
So in our implementation,
this time the textView's
accessibilityCustomRotors property
will just contain a single rotor.
As before, we'll implement a method
that also returns a new rotor,
but instead of passing in a location type,
such as a store or park,
we'll pass in the type of text attribute
we wish to put in the rotor.
In this case,
that's the 'alerts' attribute.
As we expect, this method
has a similar syntax to the maps example.
So again, we initialize a UIAccessibilityCustomRotor with a localized name
and implement the closure that returns
the item VoiceOver will move to.
We can find all the alerts
in the textView's attributed Text
because they are all marked
with a custom 'alerts' attribute.
Given the range of the current rotor item
in our text,
our goal then is to find the range
of the previous or next alert
depending on the direction
the user wants to go in.
And here, we are doing just that:
determining the range of the text we'll be
searching for our custom alert attribute
and the direction that we will search it
based on the user's gesture.
When a match for an alert is found,
we know we can stop,
at which point we return a new
UIAccessibilityCustomRotorItemResult,
passing in the new targetRange
of our attribute.
Otherwise, we pass in a nil targetRange
to indicate that we are
either at the first or last rotor item.
But we must be careful here to ensure
that targetRange is a UITextRange,
and that targetElement conforms
to the UITextInput protocol.
This is quite a bit of information
to absorb but when we take a step back,
we can see that
implementing a custom rotor in our app
comes down to returning the previous
or next CustomRotorItemResult
from the block used
to initialize the rotor.
Accessibility custom rotors allow us
to filter information from your app
and focus only on particular categories.
Earlier we saw how custom rotors improve
a complex map-based app,
and now we have just seen
how custom rotors can enhance
how a user interacts
with text-based content as well.
To go deeper on learning how to further
improve the accessibility of text content,
view this session on
creating an accessible reading experience.
And now that you've learned
quite a bit about VoiceOver,
including two ways
you can make custom rotors,
I encourage you to use your knowledge
and audit your apps for accessibility.
And for more details on that,
have a look at the past session
on app testing with VoiceOver.
To conclude,
here's what I hope you will do to improve
VoiceOver efficiency in your app.
First, identify the most
visually complex areas of your interface.
Turn on VoiceOver and determine
if you could reach that content
as easily as when VoiceOver is off.
If not, this is as good of an experience
as somebody
who is not looking at the screen will get.
So consider adding custom rotors
where they can help.
After all, you put in a lot of time
designing your app for people,
so make sure
that it works well for everyone.
Thanks, and have a great WWDC 2020.