Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi everyone, I’m Ben.
I’m in the Languages and Runtimes team,
and I’m going to talk to you
about changes we’ve made this year
in the Objective-C runtime
in iOS and mac OS
that significantly improve memory use.
This talk
is a little bit different to most.
You shouldn’t need to change
any of your code.
I’m not going to talk about
any new APIs to learn this year
or deprecation warnings to squash.
With any luck,
you won’t need to do anything
and your apps will just get faster.
Why are we telling you
about these improvements?
Well, partly because we think
they’re cool and interesting,
but also because
these kind of improvements in the runtime
are only possible because our internal
data structures are hidden behind APIs.
When apps access these data structures
directly, things get a little crashy.
In this talk you’ll learn
a few things to watch out for
that might happen when someone else
working on your codebase,
not you obviously,
access things that they shouldn’t.
We’re gonna cover three changes
in this session.
First, there’s a change
in the data structures
that the Objective-C runtime uses
to track classes.
Then we’ll take a look at changes
to Objective-C method lists.
Finally, we’ll look at a change
in how tagged pointers are represented.
So, let’s start off with changes
to the runtime data for classes.
On disk, in your application binary,
classes look like this.
First, there’s the class object itself,
which contains the information
that's most frequently accessed:
pointers to the metaclass,
superclass, and the method cache.
It also has a pointer to more data
where additional information is stored,
called the class_ro_t.
"Ro" stands for read only.
And this includes things
like the class's name
and information about methods,
protocols, and instance variables.
Swift classes and Objective-C classes
share this infrastructure,
so each Swift class
has these data structures as well.
When classes are first loaded
from disk into memory,
they start off like this too,
but they change once they're used.
Now, to understand what happens then,
it’s useful to know about the difference
between clean memory and dirty memory.
Clean memory is memory
that isn’t changed once it’s loaded.
The class_ro_t is clean
because it’s read only.
Dirty memory is memory that’s changed
while the process is running.
The class structure is dirtied
once the class gets used
because the runtime
writes new data into it.
For example, it creates a fresh method
cache and points to it from the class.
Dirty memory is much more expensive
than clean memory.
It has to be kept around
for as long as the process is running.
Clean memory, on the other hand, can be
evicted to make room for other things
because you if you need it, the system
can always just reload it from disk.
macOS has the option
to swap out dirty memory,
but dirty memory is especially costly
in iOS because it doesn’t use swap.
Dirty memory is the reason why
this class data is split into two pieces.
The more data that can be kept clean,
the better.
By separating out data that never changes,
that allows for most of the class data
to be kept as clean memory.
This data is enough to get us started,
but the runtime needs to track
more information about each class.
So, when a class first gets used,
the runtime allocates
additional storage for it.
This runtime allocated storage is
the class_rw_t, for read/write data.
In this data structure, we store
new information only generated at runtime.
For example, all classes
get linked into a tree structure
using these First Subclass
and Next Sibling Class pointers,
and this allows the runtime to traverse
all the classes currently in use,
which is useful
for invalidating method caches.
But why do we have methods
and properties here
when they're in the read only data too?
Well, because they can be changed
at runtime.
When a category is loaded,
it can add new methods to the class,
and the programmer can add them
dynamically using runtime APIs.
Since the class_ro_t is read only,
we need to track these things
in the class_rw_t.
Now, it turns out that this takes up
quite a bit of memory.
There are a lot of classes in use
in any given device.
We measured about 30 megabytes
of these class_rw_t structures
across the system on an iPhone.
So, how could we shrink these down?
Remember we need these things
in the read/write part
because they can be changed at runtime.
But examining usage on real devices,
we found that only around 10% of classes
ever actually have their methods changed.
And this demangled name field
is only used by Swift classes,
and isn't even needed for Swift classes
unless something asks
for their Objective-C name.
So, we can split off the parts
that aren't usually used,
and this cuts the size
of the class_rw_t in half.
For the classes that do need
the additional information,
we can allocate one of these
extended records
and slide it in for the class to use.
Approximately 90% of classes
never need this extended data,
saving around 14 megabytes system wide.
This is memory that’s now available
for more productive uses,
like storing your app’s data.
So, you can actually see the impact
of this change yourself on your Mac
by running some simple commands
in the terminal.
Let’s take a look at that now.
I'm gonna go into the terminal
on my MacBook here,
and I'm gonna run a command
that's available on any Mac, called heap.
And it lets you inspect the heap memory
in use by a running process.
So, I'm gonna run it against
the Mail app on my Mac.
Now, if I just ran this,
it would output thousands of lines
showing every heap allocation
made by Mail.
So, instead I'm just gonna grep it
for the types
we've been talking about today.
The class_rw_t types.
And I'm also gonna search for the header.
And from the results that come back,
we can see that we're using about 9000
of these class_rw_t types in the Mail app,
but only about a tenth of them,
a little over 900,
actually needed this extended information.
So, we can easily calculate the savings
we've made by this change.
This is the type that's halved in size.
So, if we subtract from this number
the amount of memory we've had to allocate
to the extended types,
we can see that we've saved
about a quarter of a meg of data
just for the Mail app.
If we extend that system wide,
that's a real savings
in terms of dirty memory.
Now, a lot of code
that fetches data out of the class
now has to deal with classes that both do
and don't have this extended data.
Of course,
the runtime handles all of that for you,
and from the outside, everything
just keeps working like it always did,
just using less memory.
This works because the code
that reads these structures
is all within the runtime,
and it's updated at the same time.
Sticking to these APIs is really important
because any code that tried to access
these data structures directly
is going to stop working
in this year's OS release
since things have moved around, and that
code won't know about the new layout.
We saw some real code that broke
due to these changes,
and, in addition to your own code,
watch out for external dependencies
you might be bringing into your app
that might be digging into these
data structures without you realizing.
All of the information in these structures
is available through official APIs.
There are functions like class_getName
and class_getSuperclass.
When you use these APIs
to access this information,
you know they'll keep working no matter
what we change behind the scenes.
All of these APIs can be found
in the Objective-C runtime documentation
on developer.apple.com.
Next, let's dive a little deeper
into these class data structures
and take a look at another change,
relative method lists.
Every class has a list of methods
attached to it.
When you write a new method on a class,
it gets added to the list.
The runtime uses these lists
to resolve message sends.
Each method contains
three pieces of information.
First is the method's name or selector.
Selectors are strings,
but they're unique so they can be
compared using pointer equality.
Next is the method's type encoding.
This is a string that represents
the parameter and return types,
and it isn't used for sending messages,
but it's needed for things like runtime
introspection and message forwarding.
Finally, there's a pointer
to the method's implementation.
The actual code for the method.
When you write a method,
it gets compiled into a C function
with your implementation in it,
and then the entry in the method list
points to that function.
Let's look at a single method.
I've chosen the init method.
It contains entries for the method name,
types, and implementation.
Each piece of data in the method list
is a pointer.
On our 64-bit systems,
that means that each method table entry
occupies 24 bytes.
Now this is clean memory,
but clean memory isn't free.
It still has to be loaded from disk
and occupies memory when it's in use.
Now here's a zoomed out view
of the memory within a process.
Note that it's not to scale.
There's this big address space
that requires 64 bits to address.
Within that address space,
various pieces are carved out
for the stack, the heap,
and the executables and libraries
or binary images
loaded into the process,
shown here in blue.
Let's zoom in
and look at one of these binary images.
Here, we show
the three method table entries
pointing into locations in their binary.
This shows us another cost.
A binary image can be loaded
anywhere in memory
depending on where the dynamic linker
decides to place it.
That means that the linker needs to
resolve the pointers into the image
and fix them up to point to their
actual location in memory at load time,
and that also has a cost.
Now note
that a class method entry from a binary
only ever points to method implementations
within that binary.
There's no way to make a method
that has its metadata in one binary
and the code implementing it in another.
That means that method list entries
don't actually need to be able to refer
to the entire 64-bit address space.
They only ever need to be able to refer
to functions within their own binary,
and those will always be nearby.
So, instead of an absolute 64-bit address,
they can use a 32-bit relative offset
within the binary.
And that's a change
that we've made this year.
This has several advantages.
Firstly, the offsets are always the same
no matter where the image
is loaded into memory,
so they don't have to be fixed up
after they're loaded from disk.
And because they don't need
to be fixed up,
they can be held in true read only memory,
which is more secure.
And, of course, 32-bit offsets
mean that we've halved the amount
of memory needed on 64-bit platforms.
We've measured about 80MB of these methods
system wide on a typical iPhone.
Since they're half the size,
we save 40 megabytes.
That's more memory your app can use
to delight your users.
But what about swizzling?
The method lists in a binary
can't now refer to the full address space,
but if you swizzle a method,
that can be implemented anywhere.
And besides, we just said that we want
to keep these method lists read only.
To handle this,
we also have a global table
mapping methods
to their swizzled implementations.
Swizzling is rare.
The vast majority of methods
never actually get swizzled,
so this table doesn't end up
getting very big.
Even better, the table is compact.
Memory is dirtied a page at a time.
With the old style of method lists,
swizzling a method
would dirty the entire page it was on,
resulting in many kilobytes
of dirty memory for a single swizzle.
With the table, we just pay the cost
for an extra table entry.
As always,
these changes are invisible to you,
and everything keeps working
just like it always has.
These relative method lists
are supported on the new OS versions
coming out later this year.
When you build with the corresponding
minimum deployment target,
the tools will automatically generate
relative method lists in your binaries.
If you need to target
older OS versions still, not to worry.
Xcode will generate
the old style method list format as well,
which is still fully supported.
You still get the benefit
from the OS itself
being built with the new
relative method lists,
and the system has no problem
with both formats in use
in the same app at the same time.
If you can target
this year's OS releases though,
you'll get smaller binaries
and less memory usage.
This is a generally good tip
in Objective-C or Swift.
Minimum deployment targets
aren't just about which SDK APIs
are available to you.
When Xcode knows that it doesn't need
to support older OS versions,
it can often emit
better optimized code or data.
We understand that many of you
need to support older OS versions,
but this is a reason why it's a good idea
to increase your deployment target
whenever you can.
Now, one thing to watch out for
is building with a deployment target
that's newer
than the one you intend it to target
Xcode usually prevents this,
but it can slip through,
especially if you're building
your own libraries or frameworks elsewhere
and then bringing them in.
When running on an older OS,
that older runtime
will see these relative methods,
but it doesn't know anything about them,
so it will try to interpret them
like the old style pointer-based methods.
That means it will try to read
a pair of 32-bit fields
as a 64-bit pointer.
The result is two integers
being glued together as a pointer,
which is a nonsense value that is certain
to crash if it's actually used.
You can recognize when this happens
by a crash in the runtime
reading method information,
where the bad pointer looks like
two 32-bit values smooshed together
as in this example.
And if you're running code
that digs through these structures
to read out the values,
that code will have the same problem
as these older runtimes,
and the app would crash
when users upgraded their devices.
So again, don't do that. Use the APIs.
Those APIs keep working regardless
of how things change underneath.
For example, there are functions that,
given a method pointer,
return the values for its fields.
Let's explore one more change
coming this year.
A change to the tagged pointer format
on arm64.
First, we need to know
what tagged pointers are.
We're gonna get really low-level here,
but don't worry.
Like everything else we've talked about,
you don't need to know this.
It's just interesting,
and maybe helps you understand
your memory usage a little better.
Let's start by looking at the structure
of a normal object pointer.
Typically when we see these,
they're printed
as these big hexadecimal numbers.
We saw some of these earlier.
Let's break it out
into the binary representation.
We have 64 bits, however,
we don't really use all of these bits.
only these bits here in the middle
are ever set in a real object pointer.
The low bits are always zero
because of alignment requirements.
objects must always be located
at an address
that's a multiple of the pointer size.
The high bits are always zero
because the address space is limited.
we don't actually go
all the way up to two to the 64.
These high and low bits are always zero.
So, let's pick one of these bits
that's always zero and make it a one.
That can immediately tell us
that this is not a real object pointer,
and then we can assign some other meaning
to all of the other bits.
We call this a tagged pointer.
For example, we might stuff
a numeric value into the other bits.
As long as we were to teach NSNumber
how to read those bits,
and teach the runtime to handle
the tagged pointers appropriately,
the rest of the system can treat
these things like object pointers
and never know the difference.
And this saves us the overhead
of allocating a tiny number object
for every case like this,
which can be a significant win.
Just a quick aside,
these values are actually obfuscated
by combining them
with a randomized value
that's initialized at process startup.
This is a security measure that makes it
difficult to forge a tagged pointer.
We'll ignore this
for the rest of the discussion,
since it's just an extra layer on top.
Just be aware that if you actually
try and look at these values in memory,
they'll be scrambled.
So, this is the full format
of a tagged pointer on Intel
The low bit is set to one
to indicate that this is a tagged pointer.
As we discussed, this bit
must always be zero for a real pointer,
so this allows us to tell them apart.
The next three bits are the tag number.
This indicates the type
of the tagged pointer.
For example,
a three means it's an NSNumber,
a six, that it's an NSDate.
Since we have three tag bits,
there are eight possible tag types.
The rest of the bits are the payload.
This is data that the particular type
can use however it likes.
For a tagged NSNumber,
this is the actual number.
Now, there's a special case for tag seven.
This indicates an extended tag.
An extended tag uses the next eight bits
to encode the type,
allowing for 256 more tag types
at the cost of a smaller payload.
This allows us to use tagged pointers
for more types,
as long as they can fit their data
into a smaller space.
This gets used for things like
tagged UI colors or NSIndexSets.
Now, if this seems really handy to you,
you might be disappointed to hear
that only the runtime maintainer,
that is Apple,
can add tagged pointer types.
But if you're a Swift programmer,
you'll be happy to know that you can
create your own kinds of tagged pointers.
If you've ever used an enum
with an associated value that's a class,
that's like a tagged pointer.
The Swift runtime stores
the enum discriminator
in the spare bits
of the associated value payload.
What's more, Swift's use of value types
actually makes tagged pointers
less important,
because values no longer
need to be exactly pointer sized.
For example, a Swift UUID type
can be two words and held inline
instead of allocating a separate object
because it doesn't fit inside a pointer.
Now that's tagged pointers on Intel.
Let's have a look at ARM.
On arm64, we've flipped things around.
Instead of the bottom bit,
the top bit is set to one
to indicate a tagged pointer.
Then the tag number comes
in the next three bits,
and then the payload uses
the remaining bits.
Why do we use the top bit
to indicate a tagged pointer on ARM,
instead of the bottom bit
like we do on Intel?
Well, it's actually a tiny optimization
for objc_msgSend.
We want the most common path in msgSend
to be as fast as possible,
and the most common path
is for a normal pointer.
We have two less common cases:
tagged pointers and nil.
It turns out that when we use the top bit,
we can check for both of those
with a single comparison,
and this saves a conditional branch
for the common case in msgSend
compared to checking for nil
and tagged pointers separately.
Just like in Intel,
we have a special case for tag seven,
where the next eight bits are used
as an extended tag,
and then the remaining bits
are used for the payload.
Or that was actually the old format
used in iOS 13.
In this year's release,
we're moving things around a bit.
The tag bit stays at the top,
because that msgSend optimization
is still really useful.
The tag number now moves
to the bottom three bits.
The extended tag, if in use, occupies
the high eight bits following the tag bit.
Why did we do this?
Well, let's consider
a normal pointer again.
Our existing tools,
like the dynamic linker,
ignore the top eight bits of a pointer due
to an ARM feature called Top Byte Ignore,
and we'll put the extended tag
in the Top Byte Ignore bits.
For an aligned pointer,
the bottom three bits are always zero,
but we can fiddle with that just by
adding a small number to the pointer.
We'll add seven
to set the low bits to one.
Remember, seven is the indication
that this is an extended tag.
And that means
we can actually fit this pointer above
into an extended tag pointer payload.
The result is a tagged pointer
with a normal pointer in its payload.
Why is that useful?
Well, it opens up the ability
for a tagged pointer
to refer to constant data in your binary
such as strings or other data structures
that would otherwise
have to occupy dirty memory.
Now, of course, these changes mean that
code, which accesses these bits directly,
will no longer work
when iOS 14 is released later this year.
A bitwise check like this
would've worked in the past,
but it'll give you the wrong answer
on future OSs,
and your app will start
mysteriously corrupting user data.
So, don't use code that relies
on anything we've just talked about.
Instead, you can probably guess
what I'm gonna say,
which is use the APIs.
Type checks like isKindOfClass
worked on the old tagged pointer format,
and they'll continue to work
on the new tagged pointer format.
All NSString or NSNumber methods
just keep on working.
All of the information
in these tagged pointers
can be retrieved
through the standard APIs.
It's worth noting
this also applies to CF types as well.
We don't want to hide anything
and we definitely don't want
to break anybody's apps.
When these details aren't exposed,
it's just because we need to maintain
the flexibility to make changes like this,
and your apps will keep working just fine,
as long as they don't rely
on these internal details.
So, let's wrap up.
In this talk, we've seen a few
of the behind-the-scenes improvements
that have shrunk
the overhead of our runtime,
leaving more memory
available to you and your users.
You get these improvements
without having to do anything
except, maybe,
consider raising your deployment target.
To help us
make these improvements each year,
just follow a simple rule.
Don't read internal bits directly.
Use the APIs.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy your faster devices.