Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome to the session
"Meet Nearby Interaction."
My name is Yagil, and I'm an engineer
from the Location team here at Apple.
Today we will talk about how to build
a completely new class
of user interactions
that are based on spatial awareness
in iOS.
Spatial awareness, in essence,
means understanding
the physical world around you.
Such understanding in a device
you're holding in your hand
can translate into fluid interactions
with the environment.
This is AirDrop in iOS 13.
The top selection
that I'm highlighting here
uses spatial sensing technologies
available for the first time
in the iPhone 11.
The user can orient their device
toward someone else's device
to give a strong hint to the share sheet
for presenting
the most relevant sharing selection.
This sort of high-fidelity interactivity
is only possible
thanks to the Apple-designed U1 chip.
We wanted to empower you to use
such capabilities in your application.
So today, we are introducing
the Nearby Interaction framework,
a powerful yet easy-to-use interface
to spatial awareness in iOS.
Let's start by talking about
user control and transparency.
Say your app wants to run
a Nearby Interaction session
with another user's device.
The first thing the system will do
is present a permission prompt
to both users.
The user can choose between
not allowing your app
to interact with a nearby device,
or granting it a one-time permission
that remains in effect
until your app is exited.
If users on both sides
choose to grant permission,
their devices can start to understand
how far apart they are
and in which relative direction.
This kind of rich spatial information
enables you to create user experiences
that are more natural and more intuitive
in your application.
Nearby Interaction
will be available to your apps
on U1-equipped devices running iOS 14.
Here's what we'll cover today.
I will talk about spatial awareness in iOS
with Nearby Interaction.
Then I will take you through what it takes
to start streaming
relative position updates.
And I'll close with some best practices
for you to adopt in your application.
So let's jump right in.
Nearby Interaction provides your app
two main types of output:
a measurement of distance between devices,
and a measurement of relative direction
from one to the other.
So when your app is running
a Nearby Interaction session,
it is able to get
a continuous stream of updates
containing distance
and direction information.
As this slide shows,
these updates are bi-directional,
and both sides of the session
are learning about each other's
relative position simultaneously.
Your app is not limited
to interacting with just one device.
Each device can run several sessions
at the same time,
each session with one other peer.
In this graphic, I'm showing four devices
interacting with one another
by each running three sessions
in parallel.
Let's talk about the interface
for making this happen.
You start with creating
a Nearby Interaction session object.
All Nearby Interactions
are encapsulated in sessions.
Similar to patterns in other
Apple frameworks such as ARKit,
you provide your session object
a configuration
you would like it to run with.
So let's say that there are
two or more users running your app,
and they want to interact with one another
in some spatial manner.
Before this can happen,
your app needs to let the system know,
on both sides,
how to identify the other device
when it is nearby.
Peer discovery is a key concept.
Devices can discover each other
in a privacy-preserving manner
by using something
we call a discovery token.
A discovery token is a randomly generated
identifier for a given device
in a particular
Nearby Interaction session.
The discovery token has a limited
time period for which it can be used,
and that time period is exactly as long
as the session itself,
meaning that if you invalidate the session
or if the user exits your app,
any session and its associated token
get invalidated.
The token is generated by the system,
and you receive it in your application
through the session object.
Each session you create has its own
unique associated discovery token.
Finally, your app needs to copy
the discovery token
from the session object
and then share it between users
that want to interact.
Let's go into a little bit more detail
about what that means.
Let's say that your app is running
on both of these devices,
and that your app
has some networking layer
over which the devices
can talk to one another.
Use your networking layer
to send a discovery token
from one device to the other,
and do exactly the same on the other side.
How do you do this?
The discovery token type
conforms to the NSSecureCoding protocol,
which means you can easily encode it
and then shuttle it over
using whatever transport technology
is available to your app.
For example, you can use
Apple's MultipeerConnectivity framework,
or, if applicable to your app,
via the cloud.
Coming back to the block diagram.
The discovery token your app exchanged
goes into the session configuration,
and the configuration is provided
to the session via the "run" method.
Let's jump into the code.
This short code snippet here
shows you all you need to do
to get a session going in your app.
First, create a session object.
Behind the scenes, this call allocates
all the needed resources
for running a session,
including a discovery token.
Next, to be able to receive callbacks
from the system,
set the session's delegate.
The next step is exchanging
the session-specific discovery token.
This needs to be done
over your app's networking layer.
When the token exchange step is complete,
proceed to create a session configuration.
And finally,
run the session with the configuration.
Let's keep building this down
to match the code.
The session takes a delegate
to provide updates to,
and after calling "run,"
your delegate starts getting updates
about nearby objects.
That's the basic structure
of a Nearby Interaction session.
Time for a demo.
Let's see a fun little app
that makes use of distance and direction:
Monkey Time.
I have an app here
that is also running on the phone
behind me on the table over there,
and I already started the session.
Let's see what's on the screen.
We see a measurement distance at the top,
and you see it's updating.
And we also have our little friend,
the monkey here,
and he's covering his eyes.
So I'm going to head over
towards the other phone
and see what's gonna happen.
All right. I went through
a lot of new stuff, so let's recap.
To run a session, first create
a session object for each peer
and exchange tokens with that peer.
Once discovery tokens are exchanged,
create a session configuration.
And to start streaming updates,
run the session with the configuration.
You can also pause a session
and resume it later
by calling the "run" method again.
I mentioned that after calling "run,"
you will start getting updates
from the session.
With that in mind,
let's go into a little more detail
about the delegate callbacks
you can implement in your app.
This is the session delegate protocol.
Your app receives updates
about nearby devices
by implementing the didUpdate callback.
There are a few more
interesting methods here.
The system will notify your app
whenever it is no longer interacting
with a nearby object.
This notification comes
with a reason associated with it.
The two reasons you can expect
are "timeout" or "peerEnded."
They are different in some important ways.
Timeout means that
there wasn't any activity in the session
for over some time period.
This may happen, for example,
if the devices are too far apart.
PeerEnded, on the other hand,
means that the session was
explicitly invalidated on the other end.
A word of caution here.
This notification is delivered
on a best-effort basis
and may not always be received.
Those were the nearby object
removal reasons.
The final three delegate callbacks
have to do with the session life cycle.
Whenever there are conditions
preventing your session from running,
your delegate will get
a suspension notification.
The session will be suspended,
for example,
when your app is no longer
in the foreground.
You need to wait for a notification
that the suspension ended
before being able to use it again.
When you finally get a callback
that the suspension ended,
your session
will not resume automatically.
This is to allow you to decide what to do
with the session at this point.
If you want to resume the session,
you can call "run" on both sides,
just like you did
when you first started the session,
but this time, there's no need
to exchange discovery tokens.
Last but not least
is the sessionDidInvalidate callback,
which notifies your app
about session invalidation.
The session will be invalidated
with an associated error code
upon certain error conditions
or resource constraints.
Sessions that are invalidated
cannot be run again,
and their associated tokens
cannot be used anymore.
To restart interaction,
you'll need to create a new session
and re-exchange discovery tokens.
These were the different
delegate callbacks
your app might get from the system.
Back to the full diagram.
This is illustrating a single session.
I mentioned that your app
can run several simultaneous sessions.
This is what it would look like
with multiple sessions.
You create a session for each peer,
and you can re-use other parts of your app
whenever it makes sense.
For example, here, I'm using
the same delegate for all sessions.
Maintaining the principle
of "one session for one peer"
makes managing multiple sessions
straightforward.
You can interact
with multiple nearby devices
by creating an interaction session
for each one.
You can think about it
like a conversation with that device.
We recommend storing sessions
in a data structure like a dictionary
in order to map your app's notion
of peer users
to their respective
Nearby Interaction sessions.
All right. You've constructed and run
a session or two,
and you start getting updates
about nearby objects.
Now I'll dive into
what nearby objects contain
and how you can use them
in your application.
Each nearby object
comes with three properties.
A discovery token that you provided
to the session in the configuration.
This property is here to allow you
to tie back these updates
to the user from which
you received the token in the first place.
The next property is distance.
It contains a distance measurement
in meters,
indicating how far apart
the two devices are.
And the final property is direction.
It contains
a three-dimensional unit vector
pointing at the other device,
relative to the local device itself.
This is what it looks like in code.
A discovery token
identifying this nearby object,
a distance measurement in meters
between you and the object,
and a vector expressing
the relative direction to the object.
I'd like to call your attention
to the fact that the distance
and direction properties are nullable.
This is an excellent segue
to some best practices
we'd like you to keep in mind.
First, always verify hardware support.
Choose a strategic place in your app
to check whether Nearby Interaction
is supported.
Make sure to fall back to a different
user experience when necessary.
Next, become familiar with the concept
of the directional field of view.
Similar to other hardware sensors,
like the camera, for example,
the hardware used in Nearby Interaction
is also subject to a field of view.
The field of view, notionally,
is a cone that looks just like this
coming out of the back of the phone.
It roughly corresponds with the Ultra Wide
camera's field of view on the iPhone 11.
When devices you're interacting with
are inside this field of view,
both distance and direction updates
are expected to be produced
with high confidence.
But if a device is outside
that directional field of view,
your app may get distance updates about it
but not direction updates.
Remember this when developing your apps
and designing your user experiences.
Next, understand the impact
of physical device orientation.
For optimal performance,
devices should be held
in the portrait orientation.
One device in portrait
and the other in landscape
would lead to limited
measurement availability.
This is something
you absolutely want to avoid,
so make sure that your app
does not lead users to this situation.
Moving on, be mindful of occlusions.
Devices that are in clear line of sight
of each other
will achieve optimal performance.
You can think about it in terms
of the devices looking at one another.
Brick walls, people,
or any body or object in between devices
may reduce measurement availability.
Like I mentioned,
the distance and direction properties
of a nearby object are nullable.
So whenever either one cannot be produced
due to the scenarios I just talked about,
these fields are expected to be nil.
Be prepared for this
and handle nullability accordingly
in your application.
As for best practices
around your development process,
take advantage of the natively integrated
Simulator support in Xcode.
The same application code
that runs on actual devices
will get triggered
with distance and direction updates
between two or more Simulator windows.
We're happy
to be able to ship this to you,
and we hope that this functionality
will simplify and accelerate
your development process.
This makes our final
best-practice recommendation.
Leverage the native Xcode support
for simulating Nearby Interactions.
Today we introduced Nearby Interaction.
It enables you to add spatial awareness
to your application
and create new kinds of user interactions
that are based on knowledge
of relative device position.
Thank you for joining the session today,
and we truly can't wait to see
what you'll build with this.