[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name is Aseem,
and I'm from the Core ML team.
In this session, I want to share with you
a few exciting new developments
in Core ML converters.
We have been working hard
on improving the experience
of converting models to Core ML
and have significantly updated
our conversion tools.
Let's first start by looking, though,
at why Core ML is such a great solution
for integrating machine learning
into your apps.
Since Core ML was launched in 2017,
our mission has always been
about making it as easy as possible
to deploy machine learning models
into your application
to create a wide range
of compelling experiences.
With Core ML, the same model
can be conveniently deployed
to all types of Apple devices,
and the best compatibility and performance
across OS and device generations
is guaranteed.
Core ML models seamlessly leverage
all the hardware acceleration
available on the device,
be it the CPU, the GPU
or the Apple Neural Engine,
which is specifically designed
for accelerating neural networks.
In addition, with each new release,
you get the best of Apple's ecosystem.
For instance, this year we are introducing
Core ML model deployment
to make it really easy
to update your models.
Furthermore,
Core ML models can now be encrypted.
For more details,
please check out our session
on "Model Deployment and Security
with Core ML."
So really, the starting point
to unlock all this awesomeness
is the Core ML model.
And how it can be created
is the topic of this session.
A variety of machine learning models,
ranging from deep learning to tree based,
can be expressed in Core ML.
Of course, one of the best sources
is the Create ML app,
but you can also easily create an ML model
starting from your favorite framework
using the Core ML Tools Python package.
Over time, as the ML ecosystem grows,
the Core ML converters continue
to extend support to more frameworks.
This year,
we have some exciting announcements
regarding our support
for neural network libraries.
So far we have supported
the conversion of neural network models
from one of these frameworks.
This year, we have focused
on the two most commonly used libraries
by the deep learning community,
which are PyTorch and TensorFlow.
Lets look at TensorFlow first.
So far, if you wanted to convert
a TensorFlow model to Core ML,
you would have to
additionally install tfcoreml
and use its API,
which internally depended
on the Core ML Tools package.
Well, this has changed,
and now all you need is Core ML Tools.
We have now fully integrated
TensorFlow conversion
within Core ML Tools.
We are also very excited to announce
a much expanded support for TensorFlow 2.
TensorFlow 1 has been supported
for a while now through tfcoreml,
and we had added support for TF 2
convolutional models last year.
This year, we significantly expanded
to include dynamic models
such as LSTMs, transformers, et cetera.
The new converter supports
all the different formats
in which a TensorFlow model
can be exported.
Let's look at conversion from PyTorch now.
So far, the way to do this
is to use the PyTorch export tool
to produce an ONNX model
and then use ONNX Core ML
to get to ML model.
However, many times
the first export step may fail
since ONNX is an open standard
that evolves independently,
so it may lack
a newly added feature to PyTorch,
or the torch exporter hasn't been updated,
or maybe it has a bug.
Well, now this extra dependency
has been removed
since we have implemented
a new PyTorch converter.
It's now a one-step process
starting from a torch_script_model.
You may have noticed that the API
to invoke the PyTorch converter
is exactly the same
as was used with TensorFlow.
That's because we have redesigned the API
to keep a single call
to invoke all converters.
It works,
irrespective of which source framework
the model needs to be converted from.
With these changes,
Core ML Tools is now the one-stop shop
for converting models
from TensorFlow and PyTorch.
And it's not just the API
that has changed.
We haven't simply added
two new converter paths.
Instead, we have undertaken a major effort
to redesign the converter architecture
to significantly improve
the experience and code quality.
So, we have moved from having
separate converter pipelines,
that were built when different converters
were added at different points of time,
to a single converter stack
with maximum code reuse.
And to achieve this consolidation,
we have introduced
a new in-memory representation
called Model Intermediate Language,
or MIL for short.
MIL has been designed
to streamline the conversion process
and make it easy to add support
for new frameworks.
It unifies the stack
by providing a common interface
to capture information
from different frameworks.
It has a set of operations,
optimization passes
and a model builder API.
As an end user,
you generally don't interact with MIL,
but it can be really useful
in certain scenarios.
We will revisit MIL
a bit later in this talk.
Let's first see a few examples
of using the new converters.
Let's start with
a simple image classifier example
to get familiar with the new unified API.
Let me switch
to the Jupyter notebook for that.
Here I am in a Jupyter notebook,
and I've already imported Core ML Tools.
Let's convert from TensorFlow 2 first,
which I've imported as well.
I'll grab a model
from the TensorFlow 2 model zoo.
I'm using a MobileNet model,
which is a popular convolutional model
for image classification.
Let's load it.
And let's convert it.
To do that I simply type ct.convert...
and provide to it
the TensorFlow model object
and hit enter.
The converter automatically detects
the type of the model,
its input shapes, outputs, et cetera,
and continues to convert it through MIL.
Okay, it's done. That was easy!
Why don't we try it again?
This time let's use a model from PyTorch.
For that, let me go ahead
and import torch and torchvision.
And I'll grab a model this time
from torchvision,
the mobilenet v2 model.
Now, we need a TorchScript model
to convert to Core ML,
which can be obtained
by either scripting or tracing.
I'm gonna use tracing here.
Tracing can be done
by using functions provided by PyTorch.
Let's see how.
We first get the model in inference mode
by using eval.
And then invoke the jit.trace method,
which needs an example input to work.
Let's hit enter.
So, we have the traced model,
and now we can use Core ML Tools
to convert it.
So, I'll again type ct.convert.
And this time,
I provided the traced model.
Now, one more thing.
Generally,
the information about input shape
is not present in the TorchScript model,
but that's required for conversion.
So let's give it to the converter.
And this can be done
using the inputs argument
to which I will provide
the type and shape of the input.
And I can do that
by using the TensorType class,
which takes a shaping.
That's it. Let's hit enter.
We see the familiar steps
of conversion to MIL,
a few optimization passes
and finally conversion to ML model.
And that's done.
Let's check out the model interface
by printing the ML model object.
Let's see.
So, we see
that there is an input called input.1,
and it's of type multiArray
since we provided a TensorType here.
And there is an output called 1648.
Hmm. That is a bit odd.
What really happened there
is that that's the name
of the output tensor in the torch model,
and the converter just automatically
picked it up from there.
Well, it's easy to rename it
to something more meaningful.
Let's see how.
So I use the rename feature utility
from Core ML Tools
to rename my inputs and outputs
to whatever I want.
In this case, I use a placeholder name.
So let's hit enter
and then again print the ML model object.
Nice.
So we see that the name of inputs
and outputs has been updated
to the names that I provided.
Let me do one last conversion now,
this time from TensorFlow 1.
For that,
let me move to a different notebook,
where I already set up
my TensorFlow 1 environment.
I also pre-downloaded
the mobilenet TensorFlow 1 model,
which is in this protobuf pb format.
Along with this model came
the labels.txt file,
which contains the names of the classes
that this model was trained on.
So let's convert this model.
We'll invoke our familiar convert API,
and now we can provide
the protobuf pb file to it.
Now, this will work.
But let's make a nice Core ML model
this time
by doing a couple of extra things.
So, earlier we had used the TensorType,
but since this model really works
on an image, you know,
it would be nice
to let the converter know about it.
And I can do that
by using the ct.ImageType class,
to which I'll provide
a couple of pre-processing parameters.
Bias...
for each channel in an RGB image
and scale.
This will normalize the image
as expected by the mobilenet model.
Another thing that I'll change is that
since this model performs classification,
you know, probably it's a good idea
to generate a classifier Core ML model.
And this can be done
by using the ClassifierConfig class,
which takes the labels.txt file as is.
Isn't this great?
Let's hit enter.
And we are done. Let's go ahead
and save this model to disk.
Before that though,
I'll add some useful metadata
regarding license and author.
And then I'll go ahead and save the model
by typing mlmodel.save.
I'll name my model as mobilenet.mlmodel.
And now I can see that it's on disk.
Let's check out this model in Finder.
So we see the model is here.
Let me click to open it.
It automatically opens in Xcode.
This year, we have updated our Xcode UI.
For classifiers now,
the class labels are visible right here.
As we can see,
this model has about 1,000 classes.
There is also a new tab called Preview
which is really convenient.
And I really like it.
We can simply drag and drop
a few images in here,
and it will automatically run our model
on these images
and display the predictions.
As we can see here, our model seems
to be doing quite well on these images.
So that wraps up the conversion API demo.
Let's recap.
We invoked the conversion function
with different model types,
and it just worked.
Now let's try converting
a slightly more complex model.
For that, I'd like to invite
my colleague Gitesh,
who will convert a model
that's used in translating audio to text.
Thanks, Aseem.
Hi, I am Gitesh,
an engineer in the Core ML team.
In this demo,
I will illustrate the automatic handling
of flexible shapes
and related capabilities
of the new Core ML Tools conversion API.
And I will demonstrate these using
an Automatic Speech Recognition task.
In this task,
the input is a speech audio file,
and the output
is the text transcription of it.
There are many approaches
to Automatic Speech Recognition.
The system that I use in my example
consists of three stages.
There are pre- and post-processing stages
and a neural network model in the middle
to do the heavy lifting.
Pre-processing involves extracting
the mel spectrum,
also called MFCCs,
from the raw audio file.
These MFCCs are fed
to the neural network model,
which returns
a character level time series
of probability distributions.
Those are then post-processed
by a CTC decoder
to produce the final transcription.
Pre- and post-processing stages
employ standard techniques
which can be easily implemented.
Therefore, my focus will be
on converting this model in the center.
I use a pre-trained TensorFlow model
called DeepSpeech.
At a high level, this model uses an LSTM
and a few dense layers stacked
on top of each other.
And such an architecture is quite common
for seq2seq models.
Now, let's jump right
into the Jupyter notebook
to convert this model to Core ML
and try it out on a few audio samples.
We start with importing some packages.
I found the pre-trained weights
for DeepSpeech model
on this GitHub repository from Mozilla
and have already downloaded
those weights and a script
to export the TensorFlow 1 model
from that repository.
Let's run the script.
We now have a frozen TensorFlow graph
in the protobuf format.
Let's look into the outputs of this graph.
And for that, I have already written
some inspection utilities.
So, this model has four outputs,
and this first one, called "mfccs,"
represents the output
of the pre-processing stage.
Which means the exported TensorFlow graph
contains not just the DeepSpeech model,
but also the pre-processing sub-graph.
Let's strip off
this pre-processing component
by providing
the remaining three output names
to the unified converter function.
And with this information,
let's call the Core ML converter.
Nice! The conversion is successful.
Now let's run this converted model
on an audio sample.
First, we load and play an audio file.
Once upon a time,
there was an exploding chicken.
He met up with a golden tiger,
and together, they walked
through the green forest.
The end.
Next, we pre-process it.
For the full pipeline
to work in this notebook,
I have already constructed
these pre- and post-processing functions
using code in the DeepSpeech repository.
So, this pre-processing
has transformed the audio file
into a tensor object of this shape,
and the shape can be viewed
as one audio file,
pre-processed into 636 sequences,
each of width 19
and containing 26 coefficients.
The number of these sequences
change with the length of the audio.
For this 12 seconds audio file,
we have 636 sequences.
Let's now inspect the input shapes
that the model expects.
So, we see that
the first input of this model
has almost the correct shape.
The only difference is that it can process
16 sequences at a time.
Therefore, I will write a loop
to break the input features into chunks
and feed each segment to the model
one by one.
I've written that bit of code already.
Let me paste it here.
You don't need to follow all this code.
Basically,
we break the pre-processed feature
into slices of size 16
and run prediction on each slice,
with some state management, inside a loop.
Let's run it.
Nice.
The transcription looks pretty accurate.
Now, everything looks good,
but wouldn't it be great
if we could run the prediction
on the entire pre-processed feature
in just one go?
Well, it's possible,
and we would need a dynamic
TensorFlow model for that.
Let's rerun the same script
from the DeepSpeech repository
to obtain a dynamic graph.
This time, we provide
an additional flag called "n_steps."
This flag corresponds to sequence length
and had a default value of 16.
But now we set it to -1,
which means that the sequence length
can take any positive value.
We have a new TensorFlow model.
Let's convert it.
Great. Conversion is done.
Let's inspect how this model
is different from the previous one.
Well, one difference I see
is that this Core ML model
can work on inputs
of arbitrary sequence length.
And the difference lies
not just in the shapes.
Under the hood, this dynamic Core ML model
is much more complicated
than the previous static one.
It has lots of dynamic operations
such as get shape,
dynamic reshape, et cetera.
However, our experience of converting it
was exactly the same.
The converter handled it with just
the same amount of ease as before.
Let's now validate the model
on the same audio file.
This time, we don't need the loop
and can directly feed
the entire input features to the model.
Let's run it.
Great. Transcription looks perfect again.
Let's recap what we saw in this demo.
So, we worked with two variants
of the DeepSpeech model.
On a static TensorFlow graph,
the converter produced a Core ML model
with inputs of fixed shape.
And with the dynamic variant,
we obtained a Core ML model
which could accept inputs
of any sequence length.
Converter handled both cases
transparently...
and without making any change
to the conversion call.
One thing I did not get the chance
to show in the demo--
we can start
with a dynamic TensorFlow graph
and get a static Core ML model.
Let's see how we can do it.
First,
we define a Type description object...
with name of the input...
and its shape.
Then we feed this object
to the conversion API.
That's all.
Under the hood,
the type and value inference
propagates this shape information
to remove all the unnecessary
dynamic operations.
Therefore, static models
are likely to be more performant
while the dynamic ones
are definitely more flexible.
Which one to use depends
on the requirements of your application.
At this point, we have seen few examples
of successful conversion to Core ML.
However, in some cases,
we might encounter
an unsupported op error.
In fact, I recently hit this issue.
Let me show that to you.
So, I was exploring this library
for natural language models
called "transformers."
And a recent model called T5
had caught my attention.
Let's convert it.
First, we load the pre-trained model
from the library.
Since the returned object
is an instance of tf.keras model...
we can pass it directly
into the Core ML converter.
Let's do that.
And here we see this unsupported op error
for the operation "Einsum."
I will now hand it back to Aseem,
who will go through a few approaches
to handle this issue,
and then we will come back
to convert this model.
We recognize that hitting this error
is a challenge
in an ever-evolving machine learning space
as new ops are regularly added
to TensorFlow or PyTorch,
or you may be using
a custom-built op yourself.
What to do in this case?
Well, one option
is to use a Core ML custom layer,
which allows you to accompany the ML model
with your own swift implementation
of the op.
This is great, but in many cases,
it may be possible
to take another easier approach.
You can use
what we call the "composite op,"
which does not require
writing additional Swift code
since it can keep everything bundled
in the ML model file.
A composite op is built
from existing MIL ops.
Let's dig a little bit into what MIL is
and how we can construct
a composite op using it.
We developed
the model intermediate language
to unify the converter stack.
If we expand to look at the internals,
this stack consists of three sections--
the frontends,
the intermediate MIL portion
and the backend.
For each source framework,
there is a separate frontend,
which captures
a framework specific representation.
After that, an MIL program is built,
at which point the representation
becomes source agnostic.
A lot of common optimization passes
such as operator fusions,
dead code elimination,
constant propagation, et cetera,
happen here,
after which the graph is serialized
to the protobuf ML Model format.
Another way to look at the same picture
is that each source framework
has its own dialect
which is converted to MIL,
as a consolidation point, to ML model.
This is one way of going to the MIL format
which is what the converter does.
But there is another way
to directly write out an MIL program
using the builder API.
MIL is a stand-alone language
that can be used to directly express
a neural network model.
And it is quite similar in its API
to the ones many of you
are already quite familiar with,
whether you are a TensorFlow 2
or a PyTorch user.
Let's check out this builder API.
Here is how we can start writing
an MIL program in Python.
We import the builder and define the input
by specifying its shape,
which is 1, 100, 100, 3 in this case.
We can print a description of the program
by simply calling print.
In the description below,
we see that the type of the input
was inferred to be Float32,
which is the default type.
Now let's add the first op.
So, we added a ReLu op
with this simple syntax.
Let's add another op,
a transpose op this time.
A great thing about the MIL builder
is that it instantly performs
type and shape inference.
We can see here that the shape
of the output of the transpose
has been updated correctly
in the description below.
Let's add a reduction operation
on the last two axes.
And we see, as expected,
the shape of the tensor
is 1, 3 now.
Let's add one last op.
Finally, the program returns
the output of the log op.
So, we see that the API
to define a network in MIL
is quite straightforward.
Let's now see how it can be used
to implement a composite op
and bypass the unsupported op error.
Let me hand it back over to Gitesh
to illustrate this.
So, we were converting the T5 model
and had come across
an unsupported op error for Einsum.
I read the TensorFlow documentation on it
and found that it refers
to Einstein summation notation.
Lots of operations like reduce_sum,
transpose, trace, et cetera,
can be expressed in this notation
using a string.
For this particular conversion,
let's focus on the notation
that this model uses.
Looking at the error trace,
we see that this model uses Einsum
with this notation,
which translates to
following mathematical expression.
This might look complicated,
but, effectively,
it is just a batched matrix multiplication
with a transpose on the second input.
And that's great since MIL supports
this operation directly.
Let's now write a composite op.
First, we import MIL Builder
and a decorator.
Then we define a function
with the same name
as TensorFlow operation,
which is Einsum in this case.
Next, we decorate this function
to register it with the converter.
This would ensure that the right function
would be invoked
whenever Einsum operation
is encountered during the conversion.
And finally, we grab the inputs
and define a MatMul operation
using MIL Builder.
That's all.
Let's call the Core ML converter again.
Conversion is completed.
To verify if it is successful,
let's print the ML model.
Perfect!
To recap, while converting T5 model,
we had hit an unsupported op error
for Einsum.
In general,
Einsum is a complicated operation
and can represent
a variety of tensor operations,
but we did not have to worry
about all the possible cases.
We just handled the particular
parameterization needed for this model,
and that was easily implemented
using composite ops.
To summarize, we have packed Core ML Tools
with many new features
such as powerful type inference,
user-friendly APIs, et cetera,
which make Core ML converters
easier to use and more extensible.
To read more about these features,
visit our new documentation
that contains several examples
including the demos for this session.
To wrap up, we have announced
the new PyTorch converter
and enhanced support for TensorFlow 2.
These are available
through the new unified API
and made possible via MIL.
We would like to invite all of you
to try them out
and help us make Core ML Tools
even better with your feedback.
Thank you.
[chimes]