Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. Welcome to our session
on natural language processing.
The goal of this session
is to help you make your apps smarter
by using the power of NLP
in the Natural Language framework.
I'm Vivek, and I'll be jointly presenting
this session
with my colleague Doug Davidson.
So let's get started.
Let's begin
with the central notion of language.
Language is a core system
that helps us humans
solve difficult problems
through communication,
and it also provides us with
a very unique type of social interaction.
If you think of how we communicate
using language,
language is an intermediate representation
that helps us translate
concepts into symbols,
which can then be expressed
in the form of words,
phrases or sentences
with some grammatical structure.
The medium of expression
can be through speech,
perhaps through writing
on a keyboard or Apple Pencil.
It can even be an image or a video
that you capture using your camera.
Now, language also has
this remarkable property
that not only helps us
translate concepts into symbols,
but it also helps us
assimilate content into concepts.
In the last few years,
as we have moved from human intelligence
into machine intelligence,
this central notion of language
has been replaced by NLP.
NLP has now become
the intermediate representation
that helps machines
translate concepts into symbols,
and also assimilate content into concepts.
Now, what does on-device NLP
at Apple look like?
Until 2017, the primary modality
where NLP was exposed at Apple
was through the NSLinguisticTagger class
in Foundation.
Now, this provides
fundamental text processing
such as language identification,
tokenization, and so on.
In 2018, we introduced
the Natural Language framework.
The Natural Language framework
provides everything
that NSLinguisticTagger can,
and on top of it, we started focusing on
state-of-the-art machine-learning
and modern NLP techniques
such as text embeddings and custom models.
Not only that, we also started
tightly integrating
Natural Language framework
with the rest of
the machine-learning ecosystem at Apple
through tight integration
with Create ML and Core ML.
Now, before we jump into
the rest of the session,
we'd like to tell you
that NSLinguisticTagger
has been marked for deprecation.
We strongly encourage you
to move towards Natural Language
for all your language-processing needs.
Now, if you look
at the kinds of functionalities
provided in
the Natural Language framework,
they can be broadly broken down
into three different categories.
The first is in the area
of fundamental text processing.
The second
is in the realm of text embeddings.
And the third is in the area
of custom models.
So, let's begin with
fundamental text processing.
Natural Language framework
provides several
basic fundamental building blocks,
such as language identification,
tokenization,
part of speech tagging, lemmatization,
and named entity recognition.
And we provide these APIs
across a wide variety of languages.
For more information about these APIs,
you can refer to
our 2018 and 2019 WWDC sessions.
But at the high level, all of these APIs
operate on a piece of text,
and what they give as an output
is a hypothesis or a prediction.
However, they did not tell us
a notion of confidence
associated with this prediction.
And this year, we have a brand-new API
called confidence scores.
So, this builds on top
of the existing functionality,
and in addition to the hypothesis
or the predicted labels,
you can also get the confidence scores
using the APIs.
Let's see how we can use this.
We start off by creating
an instance of NLTagger
and specify the tagScheme to be .nameType.
This is something
that you've been used to so far.
Now we have a brand-new API
called tagHypotheses.
So, when you use tagHypotheses,
in addition to getting the predictions
either at the sentence level
or the token level,
you also get a confidence score
associated with that prediction.
Let's look at how to use
these confidence scores
through the lens
of a hypothetical app called Buzz.
Buzz is a news reader app.
As part of this application,
you can browse articles,
you can bookmark them,
and you can organize them
so that you can read them later.
And what we would like to do
is add a new feature to this application
wherein we extract recent entities
from the articles that you've read.
So, we want to populate these entities
on the right-side pane,
and when you click on an entity,
you can be taken back to the article
that you've already read.
So, how do we do this?
So, we want to use
our named entity recognition API
to automatically analyze this text
and extract these named entities,
so that we get these named entities
such as Cartagena, and so on and so forth.
Now, if you take a close look
at the entities on the right side,
you'll see there is a spurious entry.
We have something called,
"Do Not Disturb While Driving."
So, while the named entity recognition API
gives us person names,
organization names,
as well as location names,
this seems like a false positive
from this machine-learning API.
So, how do we fix this?
Suppose we had an input sentence such as,
"He was driving with
Do Not Disturb While Driving turned on."
When we pass this sentence
through the named entity recognition API,
what it does is
it analyzes the sequence of tokens
and produces a span of tokens
as an organization name.
Now, this hypothesis is incorrect
in this machine-learning model.
Now, armed with the power
of confidence scores,
you can also get the confidence scores
for each of these labels.
As you can see,
the confidence score is pretty low.
By setting a threshold of,
for instance, 0.8 for organization names,
you can easily filter out
this false positive.
With this, if you now go back to the app
and incorporate this in your application,
you can easily filter out
the false positive,
and you have a much better
and enhanced user experience.
We do have a few recommendations
in terms of best practices.
First, we'd like to recommend
that you avoid heuristic hard coding
of these threshold values
and calibrate it on representative data
that is pertinent to your app
and domain of operation.
We'd also recommend that you consider
creating thresholds on a per-class basis.
Rather than setting a global threshold
for all the classes
in a particular application,
you can set it on a per-class basis
so that you get finer control
of false positives versus false negatives
in your app.
Now let's move on and shift our attention
to text embeddings.
Text embeddings are really important.
In fact, they have been the cornerstone
of recent advances in modern NLP.
To really understand text embeddings,
let's begin with the notion
of a text corpus.
What is a text corpus?
A text corpus is a collection of documents
which are comprised of paragraphs,
sentences, phrases, and words,
and in conventional NLP,
when we start with the text corpus,
the first thing that we do
is to tokenize this corpus.
When we tokenize a text corpus,
what we get is an inventory
of words in this corpus.
And this inventory of words
can be thought of
as a bag-of-words representation
where each word is independent.
Now, if you were to look at this
from a machine representation standpoint,
it is also called as one-hot encoding.
So, in this example,
we have a bunch of words:
food, burger, pizza,
automobile, bus, and car.
And we've gone over the corpus
and extracted these words.
Now, each word here
is represented by a bit vector
which has one bit on
and the rest of the bits off.
And the length of this vector
is the same as
the number of unique words in your corpus.
Now, as humans, we can see that food,
burger, and pizza are related concepts,
and similarly, automobile, car, and bus
are also related concepts.
However, if you just look
at this bit vector representation,
it doesn't provide any information about
the similarity or dissimilarity of words.
So, wouldn't it be great
if we had a representation
that also incorporated the information
about similarities of words?
And this is really where
word embeddings come in.
When you use word embeddings,
again, you start with a text corpus,
and what you get as an output
is a vector representation of words,
wherein words that are similar
are clustered together,
and words that are dissimilar
are clustered away.
So, in this example,
you can see that burger, pizza, and food
are clustered together,
and away from the concepts
of automobile, car, and bus.
Now, to obtain these word embeddings,
you can use different sorts
of machine-learning algorithms
which could be linear models
or nonlinear models,
but at a high level,
they capture this vector representation
by analyzing global co-occurrences
of words in the text corpus.
If you consider this and look at it
from a machine representation standpoint,
now the representation is different
from one-hot encoding.
Each word gets a real-valued vector
of D dimensions,
or you can think of it as D columns.
And now, if you look at the vector
for food, burger, and pizza,
they're close to each other
in the vector space.
Similarly, the vectors for automobile,
car and bus are also close to each other,
but far away from the food concepts.
Now that we've understood word embeddings,
let's look at
the different types of word embeddings.
The first is called
static word embeddings.
Let's understand this concept.
Suppose we had an input sentence,
"I want a burger from a fast food joint."
And we want to extract the word embedding
for the word "food".
For the case of static embeddings,
what we do is,
for all the words in the vocabulary,
we pre-compute the embeddings
and store it as a lookup table.
Now, this lookup table is pre-computed
and stored on-device
in an efficient manner.
So, when we need to look up
the word embedding
for a particular word such as "food",
we simply go into this lookup table,
pick the corresponding vector,
and give it as the output.
Now, static word embeddings
are really useful.
They are very useful
to get the nearest neighbors of words
in the vector space,
and they're also very useful
as inputs to neural network algorithms.
But they do have some shortcomings.
Suppose we had an input sentence
such as, "It is food for thought,"
where the word "food"
is represented in a different connotation
based on the context.
What happens in static word embeddings is
you will still pass this
through the lookup table
and extract the same vector
for the word "food",
even though we know
that the connotation is different
and the context is different.
So, even though the semantic connotation
of the word "food" is different
because of the context in which it's used,
we still get
the same vector representation.
So, can we do better?
And this is where dynamic word embeddings
come into the picture.
So, in dynamic word embeddings,
what we do is
we pass every sentence
through a neural network,
and what we get is a dynamic embedding
for every word in that sequence
which is completely contextual.
So, if we pass these two sentences
through dynamic word embeddings,
which can be a neural network
such as a transformer network
or an ELMo-style model,
what we get as an output
is one vector for each word
that is different based on the context.
So, the word "food"
now gets completely different
vector representations
because the context of food
in these two sentences is different.
Now, on the OS,
we support static embeddings
in a variety of languages,
also across different Apple platforms.
For more information
about static word embeddings,
you can refer to our 2019 WWDC session.
In addition to static word embeddings,
we also support
what we call custom word embeddings,
wherein you can train your own embeddings
using a third-party toolkit
such as fasttext, word2vec, GloVe,
or perhaps even a custom neural network
in TensorFlow or PyTorch.
Once you do this, you can bring
these embeddings onto Apple platforms,
compress them, and store them,
and use them in an efficient way.
Once you convert them
to a representation on-device,
you can use them just the same way
as static word embeddings.
Now, in order to use word embeddings,
let's look at how you use it.
So, you create an instance
of NLEmbedding.wordEmbedding,
and you specify the language,
and once you have this,
you can perform
three different operations.
The first is, given a word,
you can get the vector representation
of the word.
The second is, given two words,
you can get the distance between
these two words in the vector space.
And the third is, given a word,
you can find the nearest neighbors
of the word in the vector space.
Let's look at the use of word embeddings
through a hypothetical app called Nosh.
Nosh is a food delivery app,
and as part of this application,
we have an FAQ section.
Now, the user experience in this app,
especially in the FAQ section,
is not great.
So, if I were to find some information,
I have to scroll through
all these questions
and look for the question
that I'm interested in,
and then for the corresponding answer.
So we want to improve this user experience
in the Nosh app
by adding an automatic search feature,
so that you can type,
or you can speak the query,
and we can pick the corresponding question
and show you the relevant answer.
How do we build this
using word embeddings?
So, one way to build this
is using static word embeddings.
Let's say you have an input query,
"Do you deliver to Cupertino?"
When you pass it
through the word embeddings API,
you can enumerate every word
and get one-vector representation
for each word in the sequence.
Once you do that, a heuristic way
of getting a sentence representation
is to simply take the average
of the vectors of every word.
And what you'd get as an output
is one vector of the same dimension.
Now, you can also pre-compute
the word embeddings
for every single FAQ question
in your database.
So you would take every question,
run it through word embeddings,
get the vectors, average them,
and pre-compute the embeddings.
So at runtime, given a query,
you find the question
that is closest to the input query vector,
and you pick the question,
and show the corresponding answer
in the UI.
Now, this seems like
a reasonable way of solving this problem,
but it does have several shortcomings.
The first is the issue with word coverage.
Since static word embeddings
work with a finite vocabulary,
if you have an input query that does not
have a word in the lookup table,
you will lose information.
The second is using this averaging process
is very noisy.
It's akin to a bag-of-words representation
that loses compositional knowledge.
For instance, if we had a query such as,
"Do you deliver from Cupertino
to San Jose?"
by simply taking the average,
we are jumbling up the words,
and we lose the compositional information
contained in words
such as "from" and "to".
So, the big question is: can we do better?
And yes, we certainly can.
And we are delighted to tell you
that we have a brand-new technology
called sentence embedding
that solves this problem.
Now, by using sentence embedding API,
when you pass an input query,
or a sentence such as,
"Do you deliver to Cupertino?"
it analyzes this entire sentence
and encodes this information
into a finite-dimensional vector.
In the current API, the dimension
of this vector is 512 dimensions.
So, how does this work?
Intuitively, you can think of it
as starting from a text corpus,
and in the text corpus,
if you were to tokenize the text
at the sentence level,
when you pass it
through the sentence embedding,
instead of working with words,
now you have sentence representations.
Each of these sentences are represented
in this vector space in such a way
that sentences
that are conceptually similar
are clustered together,
and sentences that are dissimilar
are clustered away from each other.
Now, the technology under this
is fairly complex
and utilizes
several machine-learning techniques,
one of which is pre-trained models
in conjunction with custom layers
such as bidirectional LSTM,
as well as fully-connected layers.
And we train this network
in a multitask training setup
on different tasks
such as natural language inference,
binary text similarity,
as well as next sentence prediction.
But to use it, you don't have to
worry about these details,
you simply have to ask for it.
So, you start
by importing NaturalLanguage,
and you create an instance
of NLEmbedding.sentenceEmbedding
and specify the language as English.
Once you have this, you can
ask for the vector of an input sentence.
When you do this, the sentence is run
through the neural network,
and what you get as an output
is a finite 512-dimensional vector
that encodes the meaning of this sentence.
Given two sentences, you can also find
the distance between these two sentences
in the vector space.
You simply run these two sentences
underneath this API
through the neural network,
get the vector representation,
and then compute the distance.
Now, there are a wide variety
of other potential applications
for this technology.
But since we don't have
a finite list of sentences right now,
and you cannot pre-compute the embedding
for all the sentences a priori,
there is no nearest neighbors API
available for this technology.
But later in the session,
Doug will tell you
how you can use sentence embeddings
and do nearest neighbors
by leveraging custom embedding technology.
Now, if we were to go back
to the Nosh application,
when you have a query such as,
"Do you deliver to Cupertino?"
you simply pass it
through the sentence embedding API,
and you get one vector
that encodes all of the meaning.
Similarly, for all of the FAQ questions
in your index,
you can pre-compute
the sentence embeddings.
And at runtime, given an input,
you simply find the closest question.
And once you do this,
you show the relevant answer
in the application at the UI level.
To see the sentence embeddings in action,
I'm going to hand it over to Doug,
who's going to show us a demo
of this working in the Nosh application.
Over to you, Doug.
Thanks, Vivek.
So, let's see some of this in action.
In our Nosh application,
what we're going to do is
to let the user type in a query string,
and then we're going to return
an appropriate answer
from our frequently asked questions
using sentence embeddings.
So, let's look at some code.
So, the first thing we're going to do
in this method
is to just get a sentenceEmbedding,
in this case, for English. Very simple.
And then we'll ask that embedding
for the vector
for the user's query string.
When we first constructed
this application,
we took each of our answers
and constructed for it
two or three example queries,
and pre-calculated
the sentence embedding vectors
for each one and put them in a table.
So what we're going to do
is just iterate through that table.
We'll go through... For each key,
we have two or three vectors
representing these example queries.
We'll find the distance between
each of those and our query vector,
and the smallest distance
is our nearest neighbor,
which represents the answer
that we're going to show,
and we return that answer.
So, let's try it out.
So, if the user types, for example,
"How do I use it?"
then we can search,
and go through and find a nearest neighbor
and point them to
the "How does it work?" section
of our frequently asked questions.
Or maybe they ask, uh,
"Where do you deliver?"
And then we'll search
and find a nearest neighbor,
and point them
to the "Delivery area" section
of our frequently asked questions.
Or maybe the user wants to know,
"Where is my order?"
In which case, we search,
and we can point them
directly to the "Order status" section
of our frequently asked questions.
Now, there are
many other possible uses for this.
Let's consider another hypothetical
sample application called Verse,
and Verse is an application
for showing poetry.
So, Verse has
many, many different poems in it.
And one obvious UI for this
is that we could just have
a long list of the poems
where the user picks one,
and then the user sees that poem,
and that's fine.
But wouldn't it be nice
to have some additional ways
of looking for these poems?
For example, suppose that I type in,
"You're beautiful."
Well, then we can find out
that Shakespeare said it better,
and we can do this
using sentence embeddings.
So, what we can do
is take each line of each poem
and calculate the sentence embedding
vector for that line
and then put them in a table,
and then iterate through them
just as we did in the Nosh application.
But there's one twist here,
and that is that we have hundreds of poems
and thousands of lines.
So it may be
that the simple linear search and table
that we used in the Nosh app
isn't efficient enough,
and we have a solution to that.
And the solution
is to make use of custom embeddings.
What do we need in order to create
a custom embedding?
We need a dictionary.
The keys in the dictionary are arbitrary.
So I've chosen them here to be,
for example,
poem_1_line_1, poem_1_line_2,
to be strings from which
we can readily determine
which poem we were looking at,
and which line.
And then the values are just these vectors
that we got for each line.
And from that,
we can produce a custom embedding,
and the custom embedding
has two important properties.
First, it gives a very space-efficient
representation of that dictionary,
and second, it has geometric information
that we can use
to do efficient nearest-neighbor search
without having to go through
the entire thing.
And now to create one of these
custom embeddings, it's very simple.
You can do this in Create ML,
and then all you do
is to take that dictionary
and pass it into Create ML.
And what comes out is a Core ML model
that represents that custom embedding.
So, let's take a look at this in action.
Let's take a look at some code
in our Verse application.
And here is the corresponding method
in Verse
that takes the user's query string
and returns the answer key.
So, just as before,
we get the sentence embedding for English,
and we get the query vector
for that embedding.
But now the rest is even simpler.
We just take our custom embedding
and pass it in that query vector
and it will directly return to us
the nearest neighbor,
and it will return the key
that we put into that dictionary
from which we created
the custom embedding.
And as I mentioned,
we can easily determine
which is the right poem
to return from that key.
So, let's try it out.
If the user types in something like,
let's say, "I love you,"
we can get a poetic expression for that
and find a poem
that represents that sentiment.
Or maybe they type in something like...
"Don't... forget me,"
and we can find a poem
that expresses that sentiment.
Just about anything we want,
we can find a suitable expression.
Maybe it's, uh...
"Love... isn't... everything."
And here's a poem for that, too, as well.
Now, I don't want to give the impression
that the only thing you can do
with sentence embeddings
is this sort of text retrieval,
because sentence embeddings are useful
for all sorts of different applications.
For example, consider a hypothetical app
called FindMyShot,
which stores images,
and happens to have captions
for each of those images.
Now, since the image
is associated with captions,
I can use sentence embeddings
to find an image
based on similarity between
the user's query text and the caption.
And there are many other
possible usages for these.
You can use them
for detecting paraphrases,
you can use them for input
for training more complicated models,
and you can use them for clustering.
So let me spend a moment
to talk about clustering.
If you don't have any prearranged text,
if all the text comes in from the user,
then you can still make use
of sentence embeddings.
For example, if you had messages,
or maybe reviews,
or maybe problem reports from your users,
you can take sentence embeddings
and calculate a vector
for each one of these.
And then you can use
standard clustering algorithms
to group these into
as many groups as you want.
And what sentence embedding means is that
these groups are going to be sentences
that are close together in meaning.
The availability
of the sentence embeddings
is for a number of different languages,
English, Spanish, French, German, Italian,
Portuguese, and Simplified Chinese,
and on macOS, iOS and iPadOS.
Now, these sentence embeddings
are intended for use
on natural language text,
um, especially text
that's come in from the user.
You don't have to do
a lot of preprocessing on this text.
You don't have to remove stop words,
for example,
because the sentence embeddings
have seen all this in their training.
And they're intended
for being applied to text
that is similar in length
to a single sentence,
maybe a couple of sentences
or a short paragraph.
Um, if you have text
that's longer than that,
then you can divide it up into sentences
and apply the sentence embeddings
to each one,
just as we did with our poems.
And, uh...
Also, you can make use
of the custom embeddings
in case you have large numbers
of the usage you want to store
and look through.
So, next, I'd like to turn
to the topic of custom models.
The idea in custom models is that
you bring in
your custom training data,
and we train a model for you
for some particular NLP task.
Now, there are two broad kinds
of NLP tasks that we support
that cover a wide range of functionality.
And the first is a text classifier,
which the object is
to take a piece of text
and supply a label to it.
And the other is a word tagger,
in which the object is to take
a sequence of words in a sentence
and supply a label for each one.
The custom model training is exposed
through Create ML.
You pass in your training data,
Create ML passes it to Natural Language.
Natural Language produces a model,
and what you get out is a Core ML model,
either a tagger or a text classifier.
And our focus for the last couple of years
has been on applying the power
of transfer learning to these models.
With transfer learning,
the idea is that you can incorporate
pre-existing knowledge of the language
so that you don't have to supply
quite so much training data
in order to produce a good model.
And this pre-existing knowledge comes in
by means of word embeddings,
because the word embeddings
have been trained
on large amounts of natural language text.
Now, we introduced this last year
for text classifiers,
and that provides
a very powerful solution for many apps.
For example, we can consider
a hypothetical app called Merch,
which is intended for transactions
between buyers and sellers,
and they communicate with each other
about these transactions.
But one complaint the users have, perhaps,
is that they get sometimes spam messages
and they don't want to
have to look at all these.
Well, one possible solution is that
you can train a text classifier
by bringing in large amounts
of example sentences
labeled as spam or not spam,
and then train a text classifier.
And a transfer-learning model is actually
very effective for this sort of task.
And then the model in your app
will tell you
whether a particular message
is likely to be spam,
and then you can show it, appropriately,
or not, to the user.
But what I really want to talk about today
is the application of transfer learning
to word tagging, which is new this year.
Now let's go back
and talk about the task of word tagging.
As I said, the object is to take
a sequence of words in a sentence
and supply a label for each one.
And probably
the prototypical task for this
is part of speech tagging,
but it can be used for many other things.
For example,
you can potentially use word tagging
to divide a sentence up into phrases,
or, and this is what
we're going to be talking about here,
you can take a sentence and extract
important pieces of information from it,
even though it's unstructured text.
For example, in a travel application,
I might want to know
where the user's coming from
and where they're going to.
Can we make use of this
in our Nosh application?
Well, let's take a look.
So, we saw that
with the sentence embedding vectors,
we could return general answers
to the users' queries.
But there are other things that I might
want to look at in a user sentence.
For example, I might want to know
what kind of food they're looking for,
or where they want to get it from.
And I could potentially label
these parts of the sentence
as food,
or a city where the food is coming from.
Now, the most obvious and simple way
to handle this sort of problem
would be to just list all
the potential foods and potential cities,
and then just search through the text
for each of those.
And, of course,
we support that sort of thing.
We have our NLGazetteer class,
which provides an efficient representation
for any number of tables of items
that you might want to look for in text.
But the problem with this approach
is that, in general,
you're not going to be able to list
all the potential values
that you might want to look for.
So, as soon as you encounter
some piece of text
that you hadn't thought of before,
then this simple search
is not going to help you.
And the other problem with this approach
is that it doesn't take into account
anything about the meaning
of words in context,
and a word tagger can solve
both of these problems.
In addition, it's possible to combine
a word tagger and an NLGazetteer
for even greater accuracy.
So, suppose I've decided that
I actually want to use a word tagger
for my Nosh application.
Where do I start?
The first thing to do is to decide
what pieces of information
I want to get out
and assign labels to those.
Then I collect
sufficiently many example sentences
that the user might enter,
and I decide how I'm going to label them.
And then I actually label those sentences
and continue to repeat this process
until I have enough data
to train a good model.
And I might have to continue repeating it
if my model ever runs across a situation
that it doesn't handle adequately.
Usually, the solution is to add some more
training data and retrain the model.
So, what does our training data look like?
Um...
So, in our Nosh application,
we're going to add some labels
to sentences like this.
So we'll use a neutral label,
"O" here, in this case, for "OTHER,"
for the pieces of text
that we're not particularly interested in,
and we'll use labels like FOOD,
FROM_CITY, RESTAURANT,
for the pieces of text
that we are specifically interested in.
Now, why did I say "FROM_CITY"
rather than just "CITY"?
Because I noticed that
in these example sentences,
there are two kinds of ways
where a city can come in.
The first is where it's the city
where the restaurant is located,
where the food
is supposed to be coming from,
and the second is where
it's the city the user's located,
where the food is being delivered to.
So I'm going to label those differently
as "FROM_CITY" and "TO_CITY."
And because the word tagger
can take advantage
of the meaning of words in context,
it can distinguish between these two,
provided I give it
sufficient training data.
And here is what the training data
looks like in JSON format,
which is very convenient
for use with Create ML.
So when I want to go and train a model
on Create ML, it's very simple.
If I'm doing it in code,
I just import Create ML.
And then I ask Create ML
to provide me a model.
Now, we've supported this
for a couple of years
using an algorithm known as CRF,
conditional random fields,
and it works well.
But what's new this year is that
we are applying the power
of transfer learning to word tagging.
And as I said before,
what transfer learning does
is to allow us to apply
pre-existing knowledge of the language
so that you don't have to supply
quite so much training data
in order to train a good model.
And the way in which
this knowledge comes in
is via dynamic word embeddings.
As we said before,
the dynamic word embeddings
understand something about
the meaning of words in context,
which is just what the word tagger wants.
So we use the dynamic word embedding
as an input layer,
and on top of it,
we take the data that you provide
and we train a multi-layer neural network,
and that is the thing
that actually produces the output labels.
Now, this sounds complex,
but if you want it,
all you have to do is ask for it.
So, instead of asking
for the CRF algorithm,
you just ask
for a transfer learning algorithm
with dynamic word embeddings,
and then it will train a model for you.
So let's take a look at that in action.
So here's the Nosh application,
and here is some of the training data
that I have added for it.
And I produced, oh, somewhat over
1,000 sentences of this format,
and you'll notice
these are in JSON format.
So each example is a parallel sequence
of tokens and labels,
one label for each token.
And you'll notice that cities are labeled
"FROM_CITY" or "TO_CITY,"
and you'll notice that foods are labeled
and restaurants are labeled.
And this is the data that I'm going to use
to train my model.
And so it's possible to train it in code,
but I'm going to train this model
using the Create ML application
which makes it very simple.
So here's the Create ML application.
All I have to do
is point it to my training data,
tell it which are the labels and tokens,
and tell it which algorithm I want to use.
In this case, we're going to use
the transfer learning algorithm,
and this is going to be for English.
And that's really
about all there is to it.
I just started off and set it to train.
And the first thing that it does
is to load all the data,
extract features from it,
and then it's going to start training
using transfer learning,
and it will train a neural network.
So, this takes a number of iterations.
With each iteration,
it gets more and more accurate.
Now, this particular training process
takes two or three minutes,
so I'm not going to make you
sit through all of it.
I actually have a pre-trained model,
so let's go back...
to... the application
and take a look at some code.
So here is an example method
in the Nosh application
that's going to make use
of our trained model.
So we're going to be passed in
the user's string that they've typed...
First thing we'll do is load our model,
our word tagger model as an NL model,
and then what we're going to do here
is use it with an NLTagger.
And that's convenient because the NLTagger
will take care of all of the tokenization
and application,
and just give us the results.
So we've created a custom tagScheme.
That's just a string constant
that refers to this set of tags.
And we'll tell our tagger
that that's what we want to use,
and then we tell our tagger
to use our custom model
for this custom tag scheme.
We attach the user's string to the tagger,
and that's really all there is to it.
We can then use the tagger
to go through the words,
and it will tell us, for each one,
what it thinks the label should be,
whether it's RESTAURANT, or FOOD,
or FROM_CITY, or TO_CITY, or nothing.
And then we take note
of those particular pieces
of what the user has entered.
And then we can use that
according to the needs of the application
to generate any sort of custom response
that we might want to provide.
So I've taken the liberty
of adding a few custom responses
to the Nosh application.
Let's try it out.
So, the user might type
something like, uh,
"Do you... deliver to...
Cupertino?"
So what is our model going to tell us?
It's going to look at all these words,
and it will notice
that Cupertino is a city,
and it's a city they want delivery to,
so we can generate a custom response
that is specific to Cupertino.
Or they might ask,
"Do you deliver... pizza?"
And then our model will notice
that pizza is a food name,
so we can generate a custom response
based on pizza.
Or maybe they ask
if we deliver from a specific restaurant,
say, Pizza City,
and the one in Cupertino.
And in that case, the model will tell us
that Pizza City is a restaurant name
and that Cupertino is a city
where the food is coming from,
and we can use either or both of those
to generate a custom response
that mentions those.
So that shows the power of word tagging
to extract pieces of information
from unstructured text.
So let's go back to the slides
and let me turn it back over to Vivek.
Thank you, Doug, for showing us a demo
of transfer learning with word tagging.
Now, transfer learning for word tagging
is supported for the same languages
as static embeddings
and sentence embeddings
across Apple platforms.
To get the best use
out of transfer learning
for word tagging technology,
we have a few recommendations.
We recommend that you first start off
with the conditional random field,
especially for languages such as English.
The conditional random field, or CRF,
pays particular attention
to syntactic features,
which are quite useful
in many applications.
However, if you do not know
the kind of distribution
that you will be encountering at runtime,
it is better to use transfer learning
because it provides better generalization.
We also recommend you to use more data
for transfer learning for word tagging.
Since the prediction
is at a per-token level
in contrast with text classification,
it requires an order
of more magnitude data.
As I mentioned, NSLinguisticTagger
has now been marked for deprecation.
We strongly encourage you to move towards
Natural Language framework.
We also told you how to use
confidence scores
along with existing APIs.
And this can be used to prune out
false positives in your application.
And then we provided an overview
of sentence embedding technology
and demonstrated how you can use this
in several hypothetical apps.
And we concluded with a new technology
for transfer learning for word tagging.
With that,
we'd like to conclude by saying,
make your apps smarter by using
the Natural Language framework.
Thank you for your attention.