Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome, everyone.
My name is David Hayward,
and I'll be giving
a short presentation today
that will show you some powerful
Core Image debugging techniques.
This debugging feature
will give you new insights
on how Core Image works
in your application.
The debugging feature I will describe
in detail is called CI_PRINT_TREE.
In this presentation,
I will tell you what CI_PRINT_TREE is,
how to enable and control it
in your application,
and then I will demonstrate how to get
and interpret the files it produces.
So, let's get started with,
what is CI_PRINT_TREE?
It is based on the same infrastructure
that gives Core Image Quick Look support
in Xcode.
This gives developers immediate
visualization of Core Image graphs...
and it is beautifully integrated
into the Xcode debugger.
Let me show you how this works.
Imagine you were debugging some code
that creates a filter,
sets its input properties, and then gets
its output image property.
If while debugging,
you hover over a CI image variable,
a small popover will appear
that shows the object's address.
Then if you click on the small eye symbol,
a new window will appear
that shows a visual representation
of the recipe that makes the image.
But Quick Look of images
is just the beginning.
CI_PRINT_TREE
is a flexible environment variable
with several modes and operations...
which allows you to see how Core Image
optimizes and renders images.
The first thing you'll need to know
is how to enable CI_PRINT_TREE.
There are two ways to enable
the CI_PRINT_TREE environment variable.
The most common
is to edit your Xcode target scheme.
Go to the arguments pane and add it
to the Environment Variable list.
You can also enable CI_PRINT_TREE
environment variable in Terminal.app
by setting it before launching
your application's executable.
The next thing you will need to know
is how to control CI_PRINT_TREE.
The value of CI_PRINT_TREE
is a string of this form:
A , an  and .
I will describe what each part does
in the following slides.
Graph types represent the three stages
of a Core Image render.
Specify type one if you want to see
the initial state of each image render.
This is useful for seeing, among
other things, what color spaces are used.
Specify type two if you want to see
how Core Image optimizes a render.
This is useful for seeing how Core Image
reorders, combines,
and prunes the stages of each render.
And specify type four if you want to see
how Core Image concatenates the stages
into GPU programs.
This is useful for seeing how many
intermediate buffers each render requires.
Lastly, the above values can be combined.
So, for example, specifying seven
will print graphs one, two and four.
Output type can be either PDF or PNG.
If you specify "either,"
then for every render,
Core Image will save the tree
as a document.
On macOS, the documents will be saved
to the temporary items directory.
On iOS, they will be saved
to the documents directory,
and if that's not possible,
the temporary directory.
If output type is not specified,
then Core Image will output the tree
in a compact text only format
to standard out.
You can also have the text go
to Console.app
by setting CI_LOG_FILE="oslog".
This can be more convenient
when developing for iOS.
Lastly, you can also specify
a variety of additional options.
Using "context==name"
will limit the output
so only the output
for a specific named CI context is logged.
Similarly, frame-number
will limit the output
so that only the nth render
of each context is logged.
There are also options that request
that the inputs, intermediates
and output images
be included in the documents.
These options can provide
very useful debugging information,
but they should be used with caution
because they increase the time and memory
to produce the documents.
The next thing you will need to know
is how to get the CI_PRINT_TREE files.
On macOS, this is very easy.
You just need to go
to the temporary directory,
and there you will find
the documents made by Core Image.
Note that sandboxed applications
will have a unique temporary directory.
To make getting the files just as easy
when debugging your iOS application,
there is one important setting
you should use.
Go to your app's
Custom iOS Target Properties.
Once there, you should make sure
the application supports iTunes
file sharing key as the value "yes."
With this setting, all you need to do
is connect your iOS device,
select the finders sidebar
and go to the files pane.
Once there,
you can see your application's documents
and then drag them to your Mac's drive.
The next thing you'll need to know
is how to interpret
the CI_PRINT_TREE files.
Here are some tips for how to read
the CI_PRINT_TREE documents.
Firstly, inputs are at the bottom,
and output is at the top.
Green nodes represent warp kernels,
and red nodes represent color kernels.
It is easy to look for colormatch nodes
in the graph in the initial tree.
Here you can see the name
of the colorspace.
In this case, the input image
is colormatched from the HLG colorspace
to the Core Image linear working space.
Every node also displays its ROI,
which stands for "region of interest."
This shows the area of each node
that was needed for this render.
If you use 4 and dump-intermediates,
then the concatenated graph document
will show the intermediate buffers
for every pass but the output pass.
This can be very helpful
to track down where in the render
an error was introduced.
If you don't see an intermediate image
in the tree,
then Core Image did not need to render it
because it was cached
from an earlier render.
And if you look closely, the document can
show you the execution time of each pass
as well as the pixel count
and pixel format of each intermediate.
This can be useful to help you understand
which passes are using the most time
and memory.
So that concludes
my step-by-step description
of how to use CI_PRINT_TREE
as a Core Image debugging technique.
I hope that this allows you
to further understand and improve
the visual effects
in your applications, images and videos.
Thank you very much,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC 2020.