Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi there, my name is Jay Mulani,
and I'm gonna talk to you
about one-tap account security upgrades.
I'm so excited to talk to you today
about what we've added in iOS this year
to help improve
your users' account security.
We've got some great new features
that raise user awareness
about account security risks,
and with your buy-in,
make addressing those risks
faster and easier than ever.
We'll get started with a brief discussion
on account security,
and then walk through
security recommendations
new in iOS this year.
I'll show you how to adopt
our new extension point
to offer your users
fast, easy security upgrades
on the operating system.
And then how to add those flows
within your app.
We'll close with some best practices
on adopting the extension.
Let's start by talking about
account security.
Accounts are staples of our identities.
We use them to manage
our most personal, private data,
and to access services
that power our lives.
Accounts manage our finances, health,
emails, social media profiles, and more.
Accounts are so important.
Their ever-growing integral role
in our lives
means that
we have a lot of them to keep track of
and that they need to be
carefully protected.
Most accounts are unlocked with passwords,
and so account management is
heavily dependent on password management.
Many of you are already using
iOS and macOS features
to make password management
easy for your users.
Password AutoFill provides users
with a super-fast
and convenient login experience.
AuthenticationServices
takes this a step further
and removes a keyboard
from the sign-in process.
Security Code AutoFill
streamlines the login process
for accounts that have
SMS two-factor authentication enabled.
And Sign in with Apple
completely removes the password component
of account management.
It's the fastest way for users
to get a new account and sign in.
Accounts should be convenient to use
and secure.
These features I just mentioned,
integrated into your apps,
make signing in super easy.
In this year's iOS, we've added
new account management features and APIs
to help you keep
your users' accounts secure.
My goal today is to show you
how beneficial it is, and how easy it is,
for you to use these new features
to continue our joint mission
of keeping users' accounts secure.
To motivate that, let's talk about
the new Security Recommendations feature.
Every iPhone and iPad
has the built-in
iCloud Keychain password manager.
It's deeply integrated
with the operating system
and securely synchronizes passwords
across all of a user's devices.
It provides easy password lookup
and powers Password AutoFill,
and now
it's home to Security Recommendations.
This new section of the password manager
will show all of the warnings
the system has found
with passwords saved in Keychain.
Security Recommendations educates users
about why certain passwords are flagged
and motivates them to take action.
High-priority recommendations
will be highlighted based on the severity
of the warning and the type of account.
The system will flag passwords
that are reused across sites,
easily guessed,
and, new this year,
iOS will flag passwords
that are seen in public data breaches.
In fact, iCloud Keychain
will show users notifications
when one of their passwords
has been seen in a data breach.
Tapping on one of those notifications
will bring them
into Security Recommendations
to view the warning for the password.
Having a password be publicly breached
puts all accounts
using that password at risk.
We'll show this notification
for any account using a password
that has been breached,
even if the breach
came from another service.
Each of the warnings
in Security Recommendations
will include actions the user can take
to fix the corresponding account.
One option users will have
to fix their accounts
is the "Change Password
on Website" button.
This will take the user to the web
to the credential's
Well-Known-Change-Password-URL,
if the service has adopted that standard.
This is great for motivated users,
but navigating through a website
to change your password is a hassle.
Most users avoid changing passwords
because doing so feels like so much work.
Ideally, users should be able to visit
Security Recommendations
and quickly make progress
on addressing their warnings.
New in iOS this year,
it will be possible
with just the tap of a button
in the password manager
for users to upgrade
at-risk password-based accounts
to an automatically-generated
strong password...
or even to use Sign in with Apple.
These upgrades are powered
by the new account authentication
modification extension.
These extensions
change user perception on fixing accounts.
They provide fast, easy
account security upgrades.
The extension point
offers two upgrade options:
upgrading to Sign in with Apple,
and upgrading to a strong password.
If necessary,
extensions allow the opportunity
for additional user authentication
before completing an upgrade.
For example, you may want a user to enter
an SMS two-factor authentication code
before they switch their account
to use Sign in with Apple.
With just one extension implementation,
these upgrades can be accessed
from three places:
in the password manager,
when looking at a password detail view...
directly off of
a high-priority recommendation item
in Security Recommendations,
or, third, via automatic system prompts
when users sign in to your apps.
The system will prompt users
with security recommendations
when they sign in to your app
with a weak or breached password.
Once you've implemented an extension,
you can also add these upgrade flows
within your app
using new
AuthenticationServices framework API.
This is an awesome way that you can offer
system-integrated
account security upgrades
with the user experience
you want your users to have in your app.
We'll walk through
how to do this towards the end.
Now that I've introduced
the new account authentication
modification extension point,
let's walk through
how to implement an extension.
Throughout the presentation,
I'll be adding upgrades
to my test app, Shiny.
We're going to walk through
four different aspects
of implementing the extension.
Depending on which upgrades
you choose to support,
some of these steps may not apply to you.
Regardless, they'll all help you
better understand
what's involved in this process.
We'll start by discussing how to associate
your app with your domain.
For your app to be able
to upgrade users' accounts
saved in the password manager,
you'll need to securely associate
your app and domain.
If you haven't already done this
for your app to support Password AutoFill,
it's really easy.
You'll serve a JSON file
on your domain's server
that identifies that the domain
is affiliated with your app.
For the purpose of tying your app
and domain together for authentication,
use the "webcredentials" service.
Then you'll add a matching
associated domain entitlement to your app.
You can do that in Xcode
by adding the associated domain capability
and specifying the domain for your app.
Once you've associated your app
with the webcredentials service,
your app will be eligible to offer
an upgrade
for a password saved
in the user's iCloud Keychain.
For more information
about associating apps and domains,
check out the WWDC session,
"Introducing Password AutoFill for Apps."
And that was associating your app
with your domain.
Now, it's time to implement
a strong password upgrade.
A strong password upgrade helps users
by giving them a strong, unique password
for your service.
The very first step will be
to create a new target in your project
using the new account authentication
modification extension template in Xcode.
Next, you'll need to declare support
for strong password upgrades
in your extension's Info.plist.
Setting the
ASAccountAuthenticationModification-
SupportsStrongPasswordChange key
to "yes"
will tell the system to offer
the strong password
extension upgrade option
for credentials for your app.
The template will declare support
for both upgrades by default.
If you don't want to support this upgrade,
you can just set the key to "no."
You'll implement your extension
in a special subclass,
which will be the brain of the operation
and contains the business logic
for the upgrade,
including communicating
with your back-end server
to commit account changes.
It's exposed out of
the AuthenticationServices framework,
and you'll notice
that it's a ViewController.
The reason it's a ViewController
is because you'll have the flexibility
to show security step-up UI
to have the user fully authorize
before performing an upgrade,
if necessary.
We'll talk about that later,
and for right now,
we'll cover upgrade flows
without security step-up UI.
When users tap an extension upgrade button
within the password manager,
or just after signing into your app,
the system will launch your extension
and start an upgrade request
with a system-generated strong password
and an existing credential.
The system will call
changePasswordWithoutUserInteraction
on the ViewController
to begin the request,
passing in a serviceIdentifier
which provides the domain or URL
for the passed-in credential.
The serviceIdentifier is useful
if your extension offers upgrades
for several different services.
You'll also be passed a new, unique,
strong password generated by the system,
and userInfo, which we will revisit
when we talk about in-app upgrades.
This argument will always be nil
for system-initiated upgrades.
Upon receiving this initial request,
your extension needs to authorize
the upgrade before proceeding,
communicating with your back-end server
to do so.
The result of the authorization
will decide what your ViewController
should do next.
Your extension should check
with your back-end server
to see if it is authorized to perform
the upgrade for the passed-in credential.
You can also leverage
any existing login cookies or tokens
stored in a data container
shared between your app and extension.
If the upgrade is authorized,
you can continue with the upgrade.
If not, you'll need to cancel the upgrade.
When your extension is informed
that the authorization failed,
it should cancel the request.
In your extension implementation,
you should do this
by canceling the request
with the failed error code.
If you'd like to provide
a failure message to be shown to the user,
you can specify one in the userInfo
using the ASExtensionLocalized-
FailureReasonErrorKey.
If not, the system will provide
a default error message
and encourage the user to try again later.
If upgrade authorization succeeds,
you can commit the change on your end
and complete the request.
In this successful case,
your extension should commit the change
on your back-end server.
If the change commits successfully,
you can complete the upgrade
by calling
completeChangePasswordRequest
using an ASPasswordCredential
with the username and updated password.
Note that you can change the new password
passed in from the system if you need to.
If you end up doing so,
you should be sure to pass
the correct password
to the completion method.
That's the password
that will be saved to Keychain.
This is an example password
that iCloud Keychain could generate.
It's a strong password
designed to be easily typeable
for those times that AutoFill can't help
the user with using the password.
It's also designed
with a length and character set
to be compatible with most services.
That said,
if the iCloud Keychain-generated passwords
aren't compatible with your service,
you can specify your own password rules
to ensure iCloud Keychain
generates a compatible password.
You can specify
password requirements for your app
with a technology called Password Rules.
At the Password Rules website,
you'll find a validation tool
that you can use to make
your passwordrules string.
You can then add it
to your extension's Info.plist using the
ASAccountAuthenticationModification-
PasswordGenerationRequirements key.
Once again,
you should only need to do this
if you find the default passwords
generated by the system
are not compatible
with your password rules.
And that's how you support
strong password upgrades.
Next, let's look at supporting
upgrades to Sign in with Apple.
Before adding Sign in with Apple upgrades,
you'll need to support Sign in with Apple.
Check out these talks for more information
on adding Sign in with Apple support
to your apps.
Just as we saw
with strong password upgrades,
you'll need to declare that your extension
supports Sign in with Apple upgrades
in your extension's Info.plist.
You'll do this by setting the
ASAccountAuthenticationModification-
SupportsUpgradeToSignInWithApple
key to "yes."
By default, the template will declare
support for both upgrades.
If you don't want to support this upgrade,
you can just set it to "no."
Sign in with Apple upgrades
start just like strong password upgrades.
The system will launch your extension
and make the upgrade request
with an existing credential.
The system will call
convertAccountToSignInWithApple-
WithoutUserInteraction
on the ViewController
to begin the request...
passing in a serviceIdentifier
and an existing password credential.
And finally, userInfo, which we'll ignore
until we talk about in-app upgrades.
UserInfo will always be nil
for system-initiated upgrades.
Once again, your extension
will need to authorize the upgrade.
Your extension should check
with your back-end server
to see if it is authorized
to perform the upgrade
for the passed-in credential.
You can also leverage
any existing login cookies or tokens
stored in a data container
shared between your app and extension.
If the upgrade is authorized,
you can continue with the upgrade.
If not, you'll need to cancel the upgrade.
When your extension is informed
that the authorization failed,
it should cancel the request.
In your extension implementation,
you should do this
by canceling the request
with the failure error code.
You can use the ASExtension-
LocalizedFailureReasonErrorKey
to communicate the reason for the failure
to the user, if you'd like.
When upgrade authorization succeeds,
your extension should request
a Sign in with Apple credential
for the upgrade.
In code, your extension will request
the credential from the system
by calling getSignInWithAppleUpgrade-
Authorization on the extension context.
This method takes
state and nonce arguments
that you can use to securely verify
the Apple ID credential for the upgrade.
To learn more about this,
you should check out
the Sign in with Apple talks
referenced earlier.
It's possible
that when you call this method,
the system won't be able
to return a credential
and your extension
will need to fail the request.
The system may fail to return
a credential here for various reasons,
such as the user tapping the cancel button
on the system Sign in with Apple sheet,
or if there's a bad network connection.
In this case, your extension will cancel
the request with the failure error code.
If the system returns a Sign in with Apple
credential successfully,
you should do the necessary bookkeeping
to process the upgrade on your end,
and then successfully
complete the request.
In code, once your extension
has successfully committed the upgrade
on your back-end server,
it can complete the request
by simply calling
completeUpgradeToSignInWithApple
on the extensionContext.
One of the promises of Sign in with Apple
is having one fewer password
to manage and keep track of.
Once the upgrade is completed,
the system will delete the Keychain
password credential used for the upgrade.
These flows cover the ideal scenarios
for upgrades,
with minimal user interaction.
However, in some cases,
your extension may require
some additional user authentication
to complete an upgrade.
Your extension will have the capability to
show security step-up UI in upgrade flows.
As an example, you may want the user
to enter a two-factor authentication code
to complete an upgrade.
Let's pick back up on the flow
when your extension is verifying
the credential passed in for the upgrade.
When your extension is checking
with your back-end server
to authorize the upgrade,
we saw that if the upgrade is authorized,
you can continue with the upgrade,
or if not,
you'll need to cancel the upgrade.
But now,
we'll consider a third possibility
in which further authorization is required
to complete the upgrade.
When further authorization is required,
your extension can cancel
the initial request
and specify that it needs to show
security step-up UI.
Your extension can do this
by canceling the initial request
with the userInteractionRequired
error code.
In response,
the system will create a new request
configured to allow user interaction.
The system will call
prepareInterfaceToChangePassword
on your ViewController subclass
for strong password upgrades.
For Sign in with Apple upgrades,
the system will call prepareInterface-
ToConvertAccountToSignInWithApple.
In each of these methods,
your extension should quickly do
any work necessary
to prepare the interface to be presented.
Once this method finishes,
the system will present your interface.
Your interface will be presented
with a system-provided navigation bar
with the name of the containing app
for the extension as the title,
and a cancel button.
Once your interface is presented,
there are three possible scenarios.
If the additional
user authentication fails
or something else goes wrong,
you can fail the request
by canceling with the failure error code.
The second scenario is that all goes well,
and you can continue with the upgrade.
For a strong password upgrade,
the next step will be
to commit the password change.
For a Sign in with Apple upgrade,
your extension's next step
will be to request
the Sign in with Apple credential.
The system will take this as a sign
that the work in your security step-up UI
is complete,
and will dismiss it to show
the system Sign in with Apple sheet.
From here, the upgrade will continue
the same exact way we saw earlier.
The third possibility,
regardless of the upgrade type,
is that the user taps
the system-provided cancel button.
In this case, your extension
will need to cancel the request.
The system will call cancelRequest
on your ViewController subclass.
The superclass implementation
of this method
simply cancels the request
with the userCanceled error code.
If you want the ability to clean up state
before the request is canceled,
you should override this method,
and be sure to still cancel the request
at the end.
We've completed the core implementation
for the extension
and the hard work is done.
Now, if you want to use the upgrades
from within your app,
all you have to do
is invoke the extension.
Let's talk about in-app upgrades.
In-app upgrades begin when your app
creates and performs an upgrade request.
Performing the request
will launch your extension.
The request will have a username
and will not have a password.
There's no password in this flow
because your app should not be able
to provide plaintext passwords,
and because, unlike the system,
you won't have a handle
to a Keychain credential
to perform the upgrade with.
However, you may pass
any information you'd like
to your extension for the upgrade
with the userInfo property
of the request object.
We ignored this earlier
because it's always nil
for system-initiated upgrades.
Your extension can use this information
to authorize the upgrade.
The upgrade authorization process
works as outlined before,
where your extension will need to talk
to your back-end server
to ensure the account is authorized
to perform the upgrade,
with the same three possible outcomes
of successful authorization,
failed authorization,
or finding that
further authorization is required.
Ideally, you shouldn't need
any further authorization in this flow
as the user
is already logged into the app.
Let's add in-app upgrades
to the account settings section
of the Shiny app.
Let's start with
in-app strong password upgrades.
The upgrade will be added here
in the handler
for the changeToStrongPassword button
in the account settings section.
The first step
is to specify the serviceIdentifier
for the credential to be upgraded
by creating an ASCredential-
ServiceIdentifier for the Shiny app.
The next step is to get the username
for the upgrade.
Remember that for in-app upgrades,
your extension
will not receive a password.
You can authorize the upgrade
by passing authorization information
in on the request's userInfo.
In this example,
I'm passing in the auth token
for the current user
logged into the Shiny app
for the Shiny extension to use
to authorize the upgrade.
These three pieces of information
are used to create
a strong password upgrade request.
Next, we need to create an ASAccount-
AuthenticationModificationController
to perform the request.
In order to be informed
of the results of the upgrade,
the ViewController needs to be set
as the upgrade controller's delegate.
Lastly, a presentationContextProvider
must always be provided
to tell the system
the window to show UI in.
Once this is all done,
the request can be performed.
Now, let's quickly see how to add
in-app Sign in with Apple upgrades.
They're very, very similar to the strong
password upgrades we just saw.
The only difference
for the in-app Sign in with Apple upgrades
will be to create and use
a Sign in with Apple request object.
For in-app upgrades, you are in control
for communicating upgrade results
to the user with your user interface.
The ASAccountAuthentication-
ModificationController delegate protocol
has two methods to handle upgrade results.
There's a method that will be called
for successful upgrades
where you should inform the user
that the upgrade succeeded.
After a successful upgrade,
the system will look
for a Keychain credential for your service
with the username used in the upgrade.
If a Keychain credential is found,
it will either be updated or removed,
depending on the type of upgrade.
There's also a method to indicate
an upgrade has failed
where you should inform the user
that it failed
and provide the reason why, if possible.
Here's a successful Sign in with Apple
upgrade in the Shiny app.
People love Sign in with Apple.
Providing this upgrade flow in your app
allows your users
to convert existing accounts
to Sign in with Apple
without having to create a new account.
We just looked at adding upgrades
in an account settings view.
Another great opportunity
to offer upgrades
is when a user transitions
into using your app
after using your App Clip.
Let's quickly review some best practices
for adopting the account authentication
modification extension point.
Keep upgrades as quick
and as effortless as possible.
Only request to show your extension's UI
when absolutely necessary.
Your extension can authorize upgrades by
communicating with your back-end server,
but you can also leverage
any existing login cookies or tokens
that you have saved in a data container
shared between your app and extension.
Once an account upgrades
to use Sign in with Apple,
do not allow the account to log in
using a password anymore.
If you override
the system cancel button method,
cancel the request as soon as possible.
Consider offering
account security upgrade options
when a user signs into your service
with an App Clip
and is later upgraded to the full app.
Those are some best practices
to keep in mind
when implementing your extension.
Let's wrap up by reviewing the experience
you can provide for your users
by adopting the account authentication
modification extension point.
The new Security Recommendations feature
warns users about
at-risk password-based accounts.
It educates users about
why certain passwords have been flagged
and motivates them to take action.
Users will even get notifications
about breached passwords
that will take them
to the password manager
to secure their accounts.
If you choose to adopt
the new account authentication
modification extension,
they'll have access to upgrades
to secure their accounts
with the tap of a button
and use Sign in with Apple,
or change to a new, strong password.
When the system alerts your users
about a security warning
for an account with your service,
they'll be able to address it
instantly and seamlessly.
Lastly, we saw that
once you've implemented an extension,
you can easily add the upgrade flows
within your application
using new
AuthenticationServices framework API.
This buys you system-integrated
account security upgrades
with the experience
you want your users to have in your app.
I hope you'll choose to adopt
the account authentication
modification extension
to provide your users
with a first-class experience
when they need to secure their accounts.
Thank you so much for watching.
I hope you enjoy WWDC 2020.