Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, WWDC. This is Swan's Quest.
I'm Rob, your host,
as we take an inside look
at an exciting Swift Playgrounds challenge
our crack team has built for you.
This was built to remind you
that writing code should be fun.
Swift Playgrounds is an environment.
It's jam-packed with frameworks and APIs
that make it simple to experiment
with complicated technologies
while writing less code.
This allows you to focus
on what you want to build
instead of spending your time
figuring out how to build it.
In this episode...
we're gonna introduce you to Swan's Quest,
which is divided into four chapters.
Each chapter has a specific
programming challenge for you
that will build on the prior chapters.
This first challenge
requires you to navigate
through a dark and mysterious cave.
You're gonna be armed only with VoiceOver
and our easy-to-use APIs
for providing descriptive context
to on-screen elements.
We'll discuss how to turn on VoiceOver
for your device,
then give you a primer
on the Accessibility APIs
that we use to make our education content
the most accessible
programming environment in the world.
Finally, we'll give you some clues
on how to use these APIs
to navigate the cave and meet our Swan.
Are you ready to get started?
Swan's Quest is a four-part challenge,
where you're gonna use
your programming skill
to guide our brave Turtle
on their epic quest.
Our Turtle's journey sends them
into a dark, dark cave
in search of a royal Swan.
The Swan can grant the Turtle safe passage
through their kingdom,
but only if the Turtle
can win their favor first.
To win favor,
the Turtle must complete a series
of musical challenges from the Swan.
That's where the Turtle needs your help...
and the help of a local Lizard,
who helps decode the Swan's clues.
The Lizard gives you hints
about which APIs to use along the way.
Swan's Quest consists
of four programming exercises,
which were built using the same frameworks
that we used to deliver education content
with Swift Playgrounds.
We use this framework
to teach beginning programmers
how to write code in Swift.
But did you know you can remix our content
and use the same frameworks
for your projects?
The best way to get started with our SDK
is our starting points,
like the three that you see here.
These are templated playground books
that allow you to create new pages
and new Swift modules
without leaving Swift Playgrounds.
For each of these templates,
we include the same modules
built to create
their guided learning companions.
We make it easy to experiment
with our audio APIs in Sonic Create,
take advantage of different iPad sensors
in Sensor Create,
and create your own augmented reality
experiences with AR Create,
using custom art from Sarah Rothberg.
For Swan's Quest, we created a new,
more powerful template
that combines API
from several of our starting points.
You can download this template,
along with Swan's Quest,
directly from the Developer app.
And like all of our provided content,
these books are open-source.
That means that you can unpack them
on your Mac,
and you can see how we use the APIs
to build each challenge.
During our four sessions,
I'm gonna describe some of the APIs
you'll need to complete each challenge.
For today's challenge, you're going to use
our Accessibility APIs and VoiceOver.
And you're gonna need it.
You'll need both of them
to get out of this dark cave
between you and our Swan.
Lucky for you, my first guest, Jordyn,
is an ace on our assistive technologies.
She's here to give you
a crash course on VoiceOver.
Pay attention, because VoiceOver is the
best tool to solve the riddle of our Cave.
Thanks, Rob. Hey, everybody.
My name's Jordyn, and I'm an
accessibility engineer here at Apple.
I not only help build Apple's
assistive technology,
but I use it every day to keep in touch
with my family and friends,
order food for my adorable cats,
learn to play piano and, of course,
write code.
Speaking of coding, let's dive right in.
To complete the first challenge,
you're going to use VoiceOver.
VoiceOver is Apple's screen reader,
and it's built into all of our products.
It provides information about text,
controls, and other elements
as you move through an app's interface
using text-to-speech, braille,
or a combination of the two.
You'll need VoiceOver to navigate
through a dark, spooky cave
and write code to help light your path.
You heard me right.
You're gonna write code using VoiceOver.
But don't worry.
It's not that hard once you get
the hang of it. Take it from me.
Before we begin,
let's set up your Accessibility Shortcut.
This will allow you to turn on or off
Accessibility Settings quickly
by pressing the Home
or Sleep/Wake button three times.
Go to Settings, Accessibility,
and all the way at the bottom,
you'll see Accessibility Shortcut.
Let's select "VoiceOver" here.
Next, let's turn on VoiceOver.
If you're on an iPad,
you can go into Settings, Accessibility,
and VoiceOver.
And you'll notice
a Toggle switch at the top.
To enable it, turn on VoiceOver here
or use the Accessibility Shortcut
we just set up.
You can also ask Siri,
"Turn on VoiceOver."
First, you'll hear the prompt,
"VoiceOver on."
You may need to double-tap the OK button,
confirming that
the gestures will be different
once VoiceOver is enabled.
The black rectangle around the selected
control is called your VoiceOver cursor,
and it confirms visually
which item has VoiceOver's focus.
Flick left or right with one finger
to move the cursor over
different elements on the screen.
[VoiceOver] Accessibility features
Help, Vision, Heading, VoiceOver on,
zoom off, VoiceOver on. Button.
Alternatively, you can drag
your finger around the screen
to move the cursor
over elements more quickly.
Audio, VoiceOver--
Take a minute now to adjust
VoiceOver's speaking rate to your liking
by swiping up or down
on the Speaking Rate slider
with one finger.
Speaking Rate, 45%, 55, 65%, 75%.
85%, 95%, 100%, 95%, 80%, 70%.
Many experienced VoiceOver users like
to turn the speaking rate all the way up
to take in information quickly
and navigate efficiently.
That's about 720 words per minute.
That sounds a little something like this.
Speaking rate--
If you're wondering, yes,
I can understand VoiceOver that fast.
To exit Settings, you'll need to either
press the Home button on your iPad,
or if your device doesn't have
a Home button, slide one finger up
from the bottom edge of the screen
until you hear the first sound.
If you pause there, VoiceOver will say,
"Lift for Home."
Lift for Home.
Once you're on the Home Screen,
navigate to the Swift Playgrounds icon
and double-tap to open it.
Playgrounds.
Double--
If you're on the Mac,
you can use Command plus F5
or triple-click the Touch ID button
to activate VoiceOver.
Once activated, you can move
the VoiceOver cursor through the screen
by pressing Control plus Option
plus either the left or right arrow keys.
Likewise, you can navigate up and down
by using Control plus Option
plus the Up or Down arrow keys.
To enter a group of controls or elements,
such as the source code editor
in Playgrounds,
press Control plus Option
plus Shift plus the Down arrow
to do what we like to call "interacting."
And to stop interacting,
to get out of a group of controls,
press Control plus Option
plus Shift plus the Up arrow key.
Use Control plus Option
plus the space bar to activate a control.
Now that you're familiar with VoiceOver,
how to turn it on,
and a little bit of the basic gestures
and commands, I want to discuss
a tragic experience that turns away
many blind people
from using the amazing apps
that you develop.
At Apple, we pride ourselves
on best-in-class interface designs
for our products.
And that same quality
is given to accessibility.
Accessibility is one of Apple's
core values.
So, when you turned on VoiceOver,
you were greeted with a wealth of context
as you moved around Settings
and the Home Screen.
Sadly, not all developers
pay this much attention to accessibility.
And it shows.
When you first download an app,
you hear it immediately.
Instead of rich detail, I'm greeted
with a ton of unlabeled buttons.
So, when I swipe around the screen,
all I hear is
"button, button, button."
And maybe some image file names
thrown in there for good measure.
And in this case,
when I swipe around the screen, I hear...
Seen. Twenty-- Torch two, graphic.
Torch three, graphic.
Torch six, graphic.
I'm left wondering,
"What do these torches look like?"
"What am I supposed to do with these?"
And in the case of the apps,
I'm left guessing,
"What do these buttons do?"
"And how am I supposed to use this?"
To be honest,
I delete an app with unlabeled buttons
within the first minute of opening it.
But you have the power to change
this experience.
You can make a better app interface
for everyone,
starting by adding labels
to your buttons and controls.
Seen. Torch three. Tor-- Torch.
A 12-inch rock blazing with a ball
of mystical blue flame.
Ah. That makes a lot more sense.
That sounds great.
When people use Swift Playgrounds,
they expect a great user experience.
Our content must be designed
for everyone to learn how to code.
No exceptions.
That's why my fellow engineers
built a simple-to-use API
for building fully accessible
Swift Playgrounds content.
To tell you more about these APIs,
I'd like to introduce my colleague
from the Swift Playgrounds team, Stephen.
Thanks, Jordyn.
Hello. I'm Stephen, an education engineer
on the Swift Playgrounds team.
We don't want anyone
to have the experience
Jordyn described with our content.
At Apple,
we believe that everyone can code,
and that's why we've built a simple-to-use
accessibility interface
into our Swift Playgrounds content SDK.
There are four onscreen elements that
form the foundation of our content SDK:
Graphic, Button, Sprite, and Label.
All of them inherit from BaseGraphic,
which contains properties
for accessibility support.
Here, we see the optional
accessibilityHints property.
Setting that property is how you indicate
that this screen element
should be read by VoiceOver
and makes it visible
to other assistive services.
To support VoiceOver,
these are the values you need to supply.
makeAccessibilityElement tells VoiceOver
it should stop the cursor on this item.
accessibilityLabel is what VoiceOver reads
as it stops on the item.
Let's walk through an example.
First, you create an instance
of accessibilityHints.
We want VoiceOver
to stop on this graphic and read,
"Activate button to start the party."
We then create our graphic
and set its accessibilityHints
to the hints variable
we created in the first step.
I hope this example makes sense,
because you're gonna need it
to complete our first challenge.
Thanks, Stephen.
As you probably guessed,
our first challenge, "Voices in the Dark,"
is all about making onscreen controls
more accessible.
When you enter our cave,
none of the torches are lit.
In fact,
you won't be able to see anything.
And your character, they're not gonna move
until you light enough torches.
To light the torches, you need to set
an accessibility label on them.
With VoiceOver, you'll be able
to navigate to each of them.
And when you land on one,
you'll hear a property name like
"Torch one" or "Torch three."
Once you've added
an accessibility label to each torch,
your character can pass through the cave
and meet our Swan.
In the Playgrounds source editor,
you need to replace that unhelpful label
with something more descriptive.
Use your ears and change the label.
Like you see here, once you do,
you'll be off to meet the Swan
and get a clue for our next challenge.
During this episode,
we introduced you to Swan's Quest,
an exciting four-part challenge
for WWDC attendees.
We introduced you to VoiceOver
and how to use Swift Playgrounds
to write accessible software.
And finally, we gave you some tips
on how to navigate the cave
on your way to meet our Swan.
We'll be back tomorrow
to talk about Chapter 2.
Until then, good luck, have fun,
and drop into the forums to let us know
what you thought of our first challenge.