Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Sommer, and I'm here to talk about
app accessibility for Switch Control.
Today I'm really excited to be discussing
a very important technology
that supports our users
with motor impairments:
Switch Control.
We often talk about our APIs
in terms of visual accessibility,
but less frequently in terms of motor.
When it comes to our Switch Control users,
we may need to take a few additional steps
to truly empower these customers.
Today we'll cover what Switch Control is
and who uses this feature.
Then,
we'll dive into the APIs that you can use
to specifically support
users of Switch Control.
And we'll finish off by going over
some general best practices
to support better accessibility
for anyone with motor impairments.
So let's get started
and learn a bit more about Switch Control.
Switch Control is a technology
built into Apple devices
that allows users
with limited motor abilities
to interact with those iOS devices
using one or more
external switches or buttons.
They use these switches
to navigate a cursor around their screen.
Activating these switches can then
bring up menus that allow users to tap,
gesture, scroll, control the volume,
and much more.
Because those who use switch systems
often have limited use of their limbs,
it's common for these switches or buttons
to be mounted on wheelchairs
and operated by head taps, tongue clicks,
or breathing in or out into a straw.
Since these devices
are mounted to a chair,
they're often powered as well,
allowing the screen to remain on.
Of course,
the best way to understand Switch Control
is to see one of our customers using it.
Here, we meet Ian McKay
as he's navigating the woods
and taking a picture
using his mouth-operated switch.
[birds chirping]
[wheelchair motor whirring]
[mechanical clicking]
[shutter clicks]
Notice how he can use
different mouth gestures
to move an on-screen cursor, tap,
and more.
While we saw Ian using multiple switches
via his mouth in the last video,
it's also very common
for our Switch Control users
to utilize an automatic cursor
that advances through items
until they interact with it.
Here we can see a close-up
of that autoscanning behavior.
I'm using a switch to add a new clock
to my world clock
for one of my favorite cities, Amsterdam.
Notice that the cursor advances
automatically.
I don't have to do anything.
When I do tap the switch, the cursor
navigates into the group that it's on,
or, if it's on a leaf item,
Switch Control shows the menu.
This is a very common way for our users
to interact with their devices
when using Switch Control.
When building apps that work well
for users of Switch Control,
there's some extra information
to consider.
Because when using the autoscanner,
they often have to wait for
the correct item or group to be selected,
tap-timing is very important.
A mistap can result in numerous more steps
to perform a simple action.
Additionally, the efficiency and grouping
of these navigation items
is key for Switch Control users,
as poor grouping can lead to
large wait times
to arrive at the item of interest.
Finally, some switch users may have
tremors or other involuntary movements.
This can lead to a higher rate of mistaps
than we often see with
other assistive technologies.
If there's an option to delete all data
or log out,
one accidental tap
could have quite destructive consequences
for a Switch Control user,
so error tolerance is very important.
Now that we've gotten a better understanding
of who uses Switch Control
and important considerations
for this user group,
let's take a look at how we can build
our apps with these users in mind.
But before we dive into code,
I want to call out one important point.
Very often, you don't have to do
anything extra for Switch Control.
By making an app that's 100% accessible
to VoiceOver,
it will likely already be great
for Switch Control.
Sometimes, however,
we'll want to add a bit more polish
to our Switch Control experience,
especially where we may need
specialized behaviors
that don't apply to VoiceOver.
Also, by understanding
these Switch-Control-specific APIs,
we can even design and build apps
specifically targeted at customers
who use Switch Control.
Now let's dive into some code and see how.
Lately, a lot of my friends
have been having kids.
And as those kids are getting older,
they're starting to learn their numbers
and shapes and colors.
Now,
I've always been a fan of handmade gifts,
so I thought it would be fun
to make an app for them.
This is a game called Shape Shuffle.
In it,
children can travel down a learning path
by completing
more and more challenging quests
to build groups of objects
of different counts and shapes and colors.
Let's watch this video of how it works.
In the home screen, we can select a level
on our winding road of shapes.
I'll select level three.
When we enter the level,
we get a prompt like we see here:
Two Blue Squares.
Now we can flip cards by tapping on them
to try to find a set of three cards
that will complete the prompt.
Ah. I just found the blue card.
I can double-tap the blue card
to commit it to my answer.
So I double-tap, and there it is.
Now I'll keep on tapping cards,
searching for either two or square.
[clicks tongue] Hmm. Not yet.
Ah, I found two.
Now I can double-tap that one
and continue looking for that square.
Now,
if I'm not sure if something is a square,
I can put a pin in it with a long press
to remind me where it was,
and that will help me remember
to come back to it.
Then, I can keep looking.
So now I can decide between a few shapes
until I'm sure I've found my square.
[clicks tongue] Hmm.
I think the bottom one is it.
So I double-tap, and there we go.
I've solved my first level.
Two Blue Squares.
While this game is simple and fun
for our touch users,
it poses some challenges
for our Switch Control users.
First of all, on the home screen,
there's no clear element grouping.
Normally, the Switch Control cursor
will travel top to bottom, left to right.
This will cause it to travel through
our levels in the wrong order
because of the curvy path.
Also,
because we don't group levels at all,
a user looking for level 30
would have a long time to wait
for the switch cursor
to get all the way there.
Secondly, we're relying
on tapping cards to see them.
In order to see a card,
a manual Switch Control user
might need to interact
with their switch multiple times.
This might get exhausting,
as the number of cards
increases in higher levels.
Finally,
double-tap and long-press gestures
have to be performed frequently.
While these are possible
for someone using Switch Control,
they require navigating
into the gestures submenu,
and that could slow down
game play even more.
So let's see how we can
address that first issue,
where we have too many elements
for Switch Control on our levels screen
and they are navigated out of order.
There are two steps.
First, we need to tell Switch Control
to group items in a single levels section
by setting accessibility-Navigation-Style
to combined.
Luckily this is easy because
I already built my view hierarchy
using container views
for every three levels.
Next, we need to control
the ordering of elements
so the top-to-bottom,
left-to-right ordering doesn't prevail.
We do this by explicitly setting
the Accessibility Elements array
to return the precise ordering
that we want.
This will cause Switch Control
to jump first to level four before five
and then to six.
The next issue we had
was that touching to reveal cards
requires multiple interactions
from our Switch Control users.
While those using autoscanning
may not mind this,
those manually scanning
may find card navigation taxing.
For these users,
we've added an extra setting
to auto-flip cards
when their cursor gets to them.
To implement this,
whenever a card gets focus,
accessibility-Element-Did-Become-Focused
will be called.
When this happens,
we just flip our card and show the front.
Whenever a card loses focus,
we will get a call for
accessibility-Element-Did-Lose-Focus,
and we'll flip the card back over.
Now, let's see how this looks.
Notice how the flips
are happening automatically.
There's no menu interaction required.
Before we solve our last issue
of our game requiring multiple gestures,
I want to quickly introduce the concept
of Accessibility Custom Actions.
Custom Actions give assistive technologies
like VoiceOver and Switch Control
quick access
to common behaviors in your app
that might be hard to reach
by cursor navigation.
For example, in reminders,
the swipe actions such as Delete and Flag
are presented as Custom Actions.
By making these items Custom Actions
rather than views
the user has to navigate their cursor to,
we greatly reduce clutter.
Also, we make navigation much faster
for common behaviors
and thus more convenient.
Now, let's loop back to our app.
Our game has frequent double-taps
and long presses
which would cause a Switch Control user
to have to return
to that gestures menu repeatedly.
So, we should turn those into actions
that our users can easily get to
on that top-level menu.
We can use Accessibility Custom Actions
API to do just this.
For each action we'd like to show up
in that top-level menu of Switch Control,
we simply create
a UI-Accessibility-Custom-Action.
Once we've created an item
for each action,
we just assign those items as an array
to Accessibility-Custom-Actions.
Now they will show up in the top level
of the Switch Control menu
when the user activates their switch
on that view.
But before we leave this slide,
I want to call out one more thing.
We've introduced a new API in iOS 14
to allow you to set an image
for your custom action.
As you can see here, I've used SF Symbols
to make a pin for my pin action
and a plus sign for my add action.
And if you don't use an image,
you'll see our old default behavior.
The menu item will display
the first letter of the action's name.
Now, let's take a look at our game running
with Switch Control.
In order to show the auto-flipping,
I've turned off autoscanning,
so you'll see me using two switches.
I'm using the right red switch
to move my cursor to the next item
and the left yellow switch
to enter a group
or activate my menu on an item.
Since I'm doing manual scanning,
you'll notice that I have auto-flipping
behavior turned on for my cards.
As I search for my six blue triangles,
I'll use my new pin action
in my top level menu
to pin the card on the top right.
Then, with a little more card flipping,
I'll find and add that blue card
with another action.
Before we move away from API,
I wanted to call out a couple more
useful methods and properties
that we have for Switch Control.
First, if you ever need to detect
when Switch Control is running,
you can call is-Switch-Control-Running
or use the associated notification.
Secondly, there are sometimes cases
when you have UI
that would otherwise be static,
like a UI-Label,
that updates when the user taps.
In this case,
we want to let Switch Control know
that it should navigate to this item,
even though it looks like static text,
so we can set accessibility-Responds-
To-User-Interaction to true.
And that's it for API.
Hopefully you've learned a few useful tips
to hone and polish your app
for Switch Control.
Or perhaps, now you have a vision
for an app built entirely
for your Switch Control customers.
To wrap up, I'd like to share with you
some general best practices
when it comes to making sure
that your app is accessible to users
with motor impairments.
However, these suggestions
are not only for Switch Control.
They'll bring a better experience
to all of your users.
First, make sure you confirm
any destructive behaviors
or high-consequence behaviors
in your applications.
This is especially important
for Switch Control users
who may be more likely to mistap an item.
It should never be too easy
for a user to delete all their data
or delete their account.
Next, we recommend against
having any timeouts in your apps,
at least when Switch Control is running.
Screens for entering pairing codes
and authentication codes
will often have short timeouts
for security purposes.
However, as Switch Control users
often enter information more slowly,
due to waiting on the cursor,
and take longer to correct input errors,
these timeouts may become frustrating.
Third, be sure that your view hierarchy
makes it easy to group items on screen.
All users benefit from clear
and easy-to-follow item groupings.
Once Switch Control is running,
those groups become even more important
for the efficiency and speed
of cursor navigation.
And finally,
remember that Switch Control users
can use devices mounted on wheelchairs,
and this means that it might be harder
for them to keep their screens private.
Avoid putting private information like
account numbers or medical information
on screen for longer than it needs be.
And with that,
we're at the end of our session.
I hope you've been able to better
understand who uses Switch Control
and some of the key considerations
to keep in mind for this user group
as you build your apps.
With just a few additional lines of code,
we were able to customize our game
to provide a smooth and easy
Switch control experience.
And finally,
we learned how some best practices
have a disproportionately large impact
for our Switch Control users.
We hope this helps you build apps
that are truly accessible to everyone.
Thank you so much for your time,
and have a great WWDC 2020.