Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hey, everyone. My name is Josh,
and I'm an engineer
on Apple's Education and Enterprise Team.
Today I'm excited to share with you
what Apple's been up to the past year
in the assessment space.
Education is deep in Apple's DNA.
Whether Apple's striving
to put Apple II's in every classroom,
or iPad and Apple Books
is transforming textbooks,
Apple products have been hailed
as revolutionary educational tools.
Our introduction to assessment was in 2013
with autonomous single app mode
on the iPad.
This system piggybacked off MDM
to restrict devices during exams,
but was soon replaced
with an entitlement-based system
known as
Automatic Assessment Configuration,
or AAC for short.
This next step made deployment
of assessment apps easier
and expanded their use
to non-supervised devices.
We work closely with developers
to make iPad a modern assessment platform.
It helps prevent unfair advantages like
switching apps, using auto-text-complete,
and looking up words in the dictionary.
And as a result, assessment mode on iPad
has been adopted by a majority
of standardized digital test vendors.
And now we're going
to push things forward again
by bringing standardized testing
to the Mac with a new framework
called Automatic Assessment Configuration.
I'd love to give you a tour
of what this new framework has to offer.
Assessment mode on the Mac
is not identical to iPad
because it runs on, well, not an iPad.
The goal is to preserve the same
testing environment on each platform.
Typically with a new feature,
I'd explain what new things a user can do,
but with assessment mode,
the magic's in
what a user is prevented from doing.
During assessment mode,
only your app is visible,
and things like the Dock,
Mission Control and Notification Center
are all unavailable.
You can't record or capture your screen.
While other apps can be opened,
their windows are hidden,
and for all other processes,
network access is prevented.
Playing media gets paused,
and your pasteboard is cleared
when the session begins and ends.
This list is a subset.
You can always look to the developer docs
to answer any specific questions
about what system services
are affected during this mode.
An important thing to note
is that this new feature
is guarded by an entitlement.
Information about
how to apply this entitlement
and how to integrate it into your app
are also available in the developer docs.
Now that we've learned about
what the new AAC framework does,
let's take a closer look at how it works.
But before we hop into any code,
I wanna talk about the assessment mode
life cycle and how it relates to your app.
When your app begins running,
assessment mode will be inactive.
It's up to you to decide
when the appropriate time
to restrict the device is.
When that time comes,
your app will request
for assessment mode to begin,
at which point
the AAC framework will start modifying
and restricting system services
to create the safe testing environment.
This can take some time,
so it's a good idea for your app
to present some kind of transition UI,
maybe a spinner.
Once all services are in the right state,
your app will be informed,
and you can begin your exam.
After the exam is complete,
your app should request
for assessment mode to end.
Just like before,
this might take some time,
so presenting transition UI
will make for a better user experience.
Once the OS is restored
to its previous state,
your app will be notified,
and you will have completed
the assessment mode life cycle.
This is the happy path through AAC,
but in the real world,
there's always the possibility
for errors to pop up,
and it's important that your app knows
how to deal with them.
The first place an error might bubble up
is right after requesting
to begin the mode.
It's possible the service
couldn't be restricted,
or maybe you just forgot
to entitle your app to use this feature.
Either way, your app will be informed
and assessment mode
will return to the inactive state.
The next place an error could occur
is while the exam is running.
Although very unlikely,
it's possible that a service stops
respecting assessment mode,
and we can no longer
make the same safety guarantees as before.
If this happens,
we do not tear down assessment mode.
Instead, we inform your app
that something has gone wrong
and that you should stop your exam.
Your app should hide
all sensitive content immediately,
and then release the remaining
system services by ending the mode.
Now let's take a look
at how this cycle actually looks in code.
To get started, I'm gonna walk you through
implementing your own AAC client.
First, let's create a new class
called the AssessmentManager.
This class's job is to bridge your app's
UI and the assessment mode life cycle.
We'll give it two functions:
beginAssessmentMode
and endAssessmentMode.
To actually begin and end the mode,
our manager needs
an AEAssessmentSession
provided by the framework.
The assessment session reports all
of its life cycle events via delegation,
so we need to implement the AEAssessment
SessionDelegate protocol in our manager.
Now let's focus on
what happens in the begin function.
First, you construct
an AEAssessmentConfiguration.
This object defines
your customized assessment experience
and by default, is the most restrictive.
You'll use that to construct
your AEAssessmentSession.
After construction,
you'll wanna set its delegate
in order to receive life cycle events.
It's also important
you hold on to the session
to ensure it doesn't deallocate
prematurely, ending assessment mode.
I mentioned earlier that entering
assessment mode might take some time,
so you'll present some transition UI
so your users understand
something's going on.
Finally, you'll call "begin"
on the session
and wait for the OS
to enter assessment mode.
The session will delegate
back to the manager,
either through the DidBegin
or failedToBegin delegate functions.
In DidBegin,
you'll have completely entered
assessment mode.
You can tear down the transition UI...
and present your testing material
to the student.
The other possibility
is the failedToBegin function is called.
In failedToBegin,
you will start by tearing down your
transition UI just like in DidBegin...
and since something went wrong,
you'll probably present
some kind of error to your users,
and then finally, since you weren't able
to get into the mode,
your session is now invalid,
and its reference can be discarded.
Now, assuming everything went okay
and you received the DidBegin delegate
call, the student can begin their exam.
Once the student signals they're all done,
you'll end up calling endAssessmentMode
on your assessment manager.
Now, first, your stored assessment session
is an optional,
so you'll have to unwrap it.
Just like entering assessment mode,
exiting may take some time,
so you'll also present
some kind of transition UI to your users.
Finally, you can ask
your unwrapped session to end
and take the OS out of assessment mode.
Once the OS is restored
to its original state,
the assessment session
will inform the manager
through the DidEnd delegate function.
In our DidEnd function,
we can tear down the transition UI,
and we can present our post-test content,
maybe something like
a result page or a success page,
and you can finish by discarding
your reference to the assessment session.
The last part of this protocol
is the wasInterrupted function.
This will be called when something goes
wrong during an active assessment session.
In this function,
you should immediately hide
all sensitive content.
You could also use it as an opportunity
to perform necessary cleanup
or save test progress.
After that, you can present
an error message to your users.
Next, you'll present
your exit transition UI
and bring the OS out of assessment mode
by asking the session to end.
You'll know this has been completed
once you receive
the DidEnd delegate function.
And that's it.
You have your own AAC client
that's nicely integrated
with your assessment application.
Now that we've covered
the assessment mode life cycle
and how it looks in code,
it's important we go over some strategies
for adopting this new framework
in your projects.
But first, let's talk about vegetables.
When I was much younger, I always hated
when my vegetables got mixed up.
I did not like
when my peas touched my carrots.
I would always divide them up on my plate
with clear boundaries.
Today as a developer,
this really hasn't changed.
But now instead of peas and carrots,
I'm drawing clear boundaries
between my logic and effects.
When I say logic and effects,
I'm drawing the line
between the parts of my code
that decide to do things,
and the parts that actually do things.
Examples of this idea are things like
deciding to write a string to a plist
versus actually writing it,
or deciding to make a network request
versus actually making that request.
Or in your case,
deciding to enter assessment mode
versus actually entering the mode.
In all these cases,
an important pattern emerges.
What if we look at all of these pieces
in terms of who owns them?
Your app owns all the logic.
Your app's the star of the show.
It's the thing that creates
the cool new experience,
and everything on the right side
of the fence is just a detail.
Now, you might be thinking,
"Neat. What does this have to do
with assessment mode?"
Well, like other side effects,
AAC can make writing tests difficult,
and in your case,
even make debugging in Xcode difficult.
So what do you do?
You should establish a good boundary
between your logic and effects
provided by AAC.
One way to do that is with protocols,
often referred to
as protocol-oriented programming.
With protocols, you can define a contract
detailing what work you need to be done
without having to worry about
who does that work.
Why is this valuable?
Let's take a look at some sample code
just to see why.
Let's pretend you've defined a protocol
that encapsulates
the entirety of assessment mode.
It's got begin, end,
and everything in between.
We'll call it AssessmentManaging.
One implementation of this protocol
will depend on
a real AEAssessmentSession.
This implementation will do the work
in a production setting.
In a test setting, however, you don't want
your machine to get locked down.
For this case, you can replace
the real one with an implementation
that just logs
when asking to enter assessment mode.
Or even better, you could write
an implementation specifically for testing
that's loaded up with test expectations.
That way you can be sure you're invoking
your dependency correctly as well.
Depending on a protocol makes it easier
to exercise all the logic
surrounding assessment mode.
If this seems a bit high-level
or confusing,
you can always look to
the presentation companion sample app
to see functioning examples
of all of these ideas.
This has been
a more lightweight explanation
of protocol-oriented programming,
so I recommend checking out
these previous sessions
that dive deeper into the topic.
It's a valuable tool
that will make writing tests
for your assessment apps much easier,
and as a result,
make the apps themselves better.
Since assessment developers
are distributing tests for students,
I think it only makes sense
that their apps are tested as well.
Besides the testing context,
establishing boundaries
will be particularly helpful
when debugging your assessment app
in Xcode.
Assessment mode on the Mac restricts
which apps can receive user input events.
If you're debugging your app in Xcode
and you hit a breakpoint,
you will have no way to proceed.
The app will hang,
waiting for the breakpoint,
and you will be stuck,
unable to interact with Xcode.
Fortunately, there's a solution.
If you restart your Mac,
assessment mode will stop running.
In fact, all system services
are guaranteed to be restored on reboot.
This is both a feature
and a great way to give students
some agency over their own Mac.
If you manage to deadlock Xcode
and your assessment app,
make sure to remember
rebooting is your friend.
Now let's talk about what we've done
this year on iOS and iPadOS.
Along with the Mac, the AAC framework
is also available on iOS and iPadOS.
This will make for
a unified developer experience
when building on any platform.
On iOS and iPadOS,
the AAC framework actually improves upon
the previous assessment experience.
Let me show you how.
This is the original API from UIKit
that developers have been using
to enter assessment mode on iPad.
I brushed past this a little earlier,
but during the sample code segment,
I'm sure some assessment veterans
noticed something a bit different
about the AEAssessmentSession.
It's the config.
The assessment session is designed
to be configurable.
We've heard loud and clear
that developers want ways to make
more customizable assessment experiences,
so we've made it possible
with this new framework.
In iOS 14,
you'll notice AEAssessmentConfiguration
includes options
for enabling system services
like dictation,
predictive keyboard and spell check.
These capabilities are critical
for a great user experience,
especially when you consider
the many different kinds of exams,
the different countries
students might be taking them,
and different needs students might have.
For example, allowing spell check
might make more sense on a math test
where spelling isn't really being tested.
Or continuous path keyboard
might be beneficial for tests in languages
where it makes inputting answers easier.
This list of capabilities we're releasing
is pretty cool,
but actually, the idea of the list
is cooler than the list.
What I mean to say
is that assessment mode configurability
is now a first-class citizen.
The AEAssessmentConfiguration
is an expandable value
designed to evolve
with the landscape of the operating system
and more importantly,
with the needs of developers.
I think it's pretty cool.
These new points of customization
will only be available
in the new AAC framework,
so you'll want to migrate away from
the existing assessment mode API in UIKit.
I have one more exciting piece
of AAC news to give you.
Now that we have
a new assessment framework
for iOS, iPadOS and macOS,
and we expose the exact same API
across all of them,
it's only natural that we make
this functionality available
for Catalyst apps.
Beginning in iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
your iOS apps will have
complete assessment mode support
when running on the Mac.
No matter the platform,
your app will initiate
the contextually correct assessment mode.
In summary,
we brought assessment mode to the Mac
with a new dedicated framework.
We made that framework available
on iOS and iPadOS
and expanded upon the experience,
making it more customizable.
And finally, we shipped
a friendly, cross-platform API
that makes bringing your iOS
and iPadOS apps to the Mac even easier.
Thank you for listening
to what Apple's been working on
in the assessment space.
Have fun building amazing apps
with these powerful new tools.