Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Tommy Pauly, and I'll be sharing
some important privacy updates
about how your apps
interact with local networks.
A network isn't just a way
to connect to the internet.
Your iPhone is often interacting directly
with other devices on its local network.
You may be controlling the lights
at your house,
printing a document at work,
watching a video on an airplane,
or playing a game with a friend nearby.
If your app provides an experience
like this, it uses the local network.
On Apple devices, the best way
to use the local network is with Bonjour.
Bonjour lets your app discover nearby
services, and advertise its own services.
Bonjour is the foundation
for streaming video and audio,
playing peer-to-peer games,
and communicating with printers,
cameras and home devices.
Some apps also interact
with the local network at a lower level.
Your app may configure a Wi-Fi router,
or use a custom multicast
or broadcast protocol
to communicate with legacy hardware.
For your app, accessing the local network
is a powerful tool.
And with this great power
comes an equally great responsibility.
Respecting user privacy.
Users should know
when your app accesses the local network.
And you as a developer
should also be aware when the frameworks
used by your app do the same.
Let's explore how privacy intersects
with network access.
Location is one of the most
privacy-sensitive pieces of information
that your app can access.
Starting in iOS 13,
your app needs Location permission
to read a network's name and BSSID.
But simply accessing the local network
can also provide a location hint.
For example,
when someone is on their home network,
the set of devices
and services around them is unique.
No two home networks
look exactly the same.
And this information
about devices on a network
can be used by apps
to create a location fingerprint.
Your app also needs permission
to control devices around you.
Communicating over Bluetooth allows
your app to access sensitive information.
But accessing the local network
can reveal a lot of similar information.
For example, many devices can be set up
and managed by an app over local Wi-Fi.
However, any other app can also
try to communicate with that device.
If your app manages a camera,
it should have access to sync photos,
but other apps probably shouldn't.
And that's why, in iOS 14, users can now
control which apps are allowed to access
and interact with the local network.
This is a great opportunity to provide
more transparency to your users,
and review the ways in which the code
running in your app accesses the network.
If your app just accesses resources
on the wide internet,
you don't need to do anything different.
You also don't need to update
if you only interact
with the local network
using a system service,
like AirPrint, AirPlay, AirDrop,
or HomeKit.
These system services
handle device discovery
without exposing the full list
of devices to apps.
On the other hand,
if your app accesses the local network
directly within your app,
either with unicast
or multicast protocols,
your app will require permission.
You'll also need to make a few
simple updates to your app for iOS 14.
To get into the details,
let's look at how your app gets permission
to access the local network,
how you update your app for iOS 14,
and how to ensure a great experience
when people use your app's features.
Let's start by looking at permissions.
Apps now trigger a prompt
the first time they try to interact
with the local network.
Until permission is granted,
all local network communication
is blocked.
The prompt includes a usage description
that you specify in your app's Info.plist.
Apps that haven't updated to iOS 14
will show default reason text.
If you notice a prompt
that you don't expect for your app,
you might be using a third-party framework
that accesses the local network.
Remember, any permission
that is granted to your app
also applies to the frameworks you use.
The permission for your app
can be checked and modified at any time
in the Privacy panel of Settings
under Local Network.
Every app that has requested access
to the local network shows up here.
The toggle will also show up
in the settings for your specific app.
Once your app updates to iOS 14,
there are a few modifications
you need to make to ensure it works
with the privacy permissions.
There are two new keys you can provide
in your app's Info.plist.
First, if your app ever accesses
the local network,
you should provide a usage description.
This explains which features
in your app require the local network.
And second, if your app uses Bonjour
to browse or advertise,
you must provide
a list of the service types that you use.
Each service type is a unique string
registered with IANA,
that identifies your application protocol.
Here, the service type is tictactoe.tcp.
There are several different APIs
that allow your app to use Bonjour.
If you use any of these APIs,
be sure to update your Info.plist
to list out your Bonjour service types.
There's a small set of apps that perform
their local multicast discovery
without Bonjour,
or that need to enumerate all
of the Bonjour service types on a network.
These operations
require an entitlement in iOS 14.
You can request this entitlement
through the developer portal.
Now let's walk through the process
of updating your app.
So here's an app
that I originally built for iOS 13,
that lets me play tic-tac-toe
with others around me.
All I'm going to do is rerun the app
against the iOS 14 SDK
and see what happens.
All right. So I don't see anyone nearby.
And that's kind of unexpected to me.
It's not working as I really wanted.
And if I look at the debug output,
you can notice that there is an error
that we're getting from our browser object
of "NoAuth."
This error means
that the app is being blocked
without any local network access prompt.
If you see this NoAuth error, it means
that you need to add your Bonjour services
and usage description to your Info.plist.
Let's go do that now.
So what we do is, we go to
the project settings, and we look at Info.
Here, we're gonna need to add
two new fields.
First is the privacy field
for the local network access
usage description.
Great.
So here let's put something like,
"TicTacToe uses the local network
to discover players around you."
That makes sense.
And the other thing we need to do
is add the Bonjour service types.
So this can be added as Bonjour services.
And automatically this knows
that it's an array of strings.
This app only uses one type,
and that type is tictactoe.tcp.
Great. Let's recompile the app now
and see what happens.
All right.
So we see that immediately
we get a prompt in the app
that TicTacToe would like to find and
connect to devices on my local network.
And we also see that custom usage string
that we set in the Info.plist.
Now, if I click "Ok,"
the app is actually browsing on Bonjour.
That's great.
However, you might have noticed that this
happened right when I launched the app,
and that can be a bit of
a jarring experience for the user.
Instead, I have also created
another version of the app
that only prompts,
and only tries to browse,
when the user actually does an action.
So let's go over to the phone
and look at that now.
So here is this other version of the app.
And you notice that once I started
running it, there wasn't a prompt.
Instead, only when I start clicking on
"Search for games"
to initiate the discovery
of other players,
do I get the prompt.
This experience is much better,
and let's allow that.
As you just saw,
gating local network access
with a privacy permission
might change the experience
of using your app.
I want to highlight
a couple of best practices to consider
when updating your app.
First, make sure that people aren't
confused when your app triggers a prompt.
Rather than trying to browse the network
when your app launches,
wait for an action that requires browsing.
This is your app's opportunity
to be granted access to the local network.
Choosing the right moment
makes it more likely
that someone will allow access.
When your app does trigger a prompt,
make sure you've provided
a clear usage description
that indicates exactly
what feature is being enabled.
Your app may also encounter errors
and API behaviors
that it hadn't handled previously.
Bonjour APIs deliver results
asynchronously.
Whenever your app
is waiting for permission,
it will simply look like
there are no devices nearby.
Local connections that use NWConnection
will stay in the waiting state
until your app gets permission.
Similarly, if your URLSession tasks
use the local network,
make sure to set
the waitsForConnectivity property,
so your task will complete
once permission is granted.
And if you're still using
sockets directly,
you will need to handle system call errors
when your app doesn't have permission.
Lastly, your app should prefer
using system-provided experiences
for local networking whenever possible.
If you use AirPrint, AirPlay,
AirDrop, or HomeKit,
your app doesn’t
need to handle anything special,
while still providing
strong privacy guarantees.
Let’s recap what you need to do
in your app.
First, rebuild your app
with the iOS 14 SDK
and test out the ways that your app
uses the local network.
Second, make sure to provide a clear
usage description in your Info.plist
if your app does use the local network.
And last, if your app uses Bonjour,
declare your service types
in your Info.plist.
Thanks for watching.