[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, my name's Nick Gillett.
I'm an engineer here at Apple
on the Core Data team,
and today we're gonna talk about
what it's like to build applications
with NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
that sync Core Data stores
with the public CloudKit database.
To do this,
we'll be introducing some new API,
and we'll talk a lot about things
that you need to think about
when building applications
for the public database.
Finally, we'll take a detailed look
at how importing works
with NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
in the public database.
Now before we get started,
I'd like to do a quick review
of where we are so far.
In 2019 in our session
"Using Core Data with CloudKit,"
we introduced
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
as a way of easily syncing
your Core Data stores
with a private CloudKit database.
As well,
we introduced a new sample application
that demonstrates how this works,
and we wrote a ton of documentation about
how NSPersistentCloudKitContainer works
and how you can integrate it
with your applications.
So if at any point during this session
you feel like you're lacking some context
or some of the concepts
we're discussing feel foreign,
I highly recommend that you review our
documentation and our previous session.
I also want to review some terms.
You see, Core Data and CloudKit
are very similar frameworks,
and they express themselves through
a similar set of ideas and APIs.
We think of each framework in terms
of objects, models and stores.
In Core Data, we know these
as instances of NSManagedObject,
and these are the objects that you work
with directly in your application.
Likewise in CloudKit,
we know them as CKRecord.
We model these objects, or describe them,
using an instance of NSManagedObjectModel,
and in CloudKit this is called the schema.
Finally, objects are persisted,
to use the Core Data vernacular,
in an instance of NSPersistentStore,
or, in CloudKit, in a CKRecordZone,
which is part of a CKRecordDatabase.
Now that we've got that out of the way,
I want to show you what it's like
to actually build an application,
or in this case, customize one that
works with the public CloudKit database.
To do that, I'm just gonna open
our sample application,
and I'm looking for a specific file
called the Core Data stack.
You see, the Core Data stack is where this
application keeps all of the code it needs
to set up its instance
of NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
You can see here at the top
that it's already using
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer,
which means it's ready to sync
with the private database.
Now, to make it work with
the public database,
we just want to add one new line of code.
I'm simply gonna change
the existing StoreDescription
to set its CloudKitContainerOptions
and use the new databaseScope property
to set it to public.
Now, imagine that you want
to use multiple persistent stores
with your application instead of just one,
as many of our clients do
with NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
To do that, all we have to do
is add a new store description
instead of customizing the existing one.
You can see I've just pasted in
a lot of code,
so let's take a detailed look at
what's actually going on here.
In this code, we create a new instance
of NSPersistentStoreDescription
and customize it with
the normal CloudKitContainerOptions,
things like HistoryTracking
and RemoteChangeNotifications.
Then we create a new instance of
NSPersistentCloudKitContainerOptions.
This is what tells
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
that we want to use this StoreDescription
with CloudKit.
We set its databaseScope property
to "public,"
and that tells it that
we wanna use it with the public database.
Next, we assign
the CloudKitContainerOptions
to the StoreDescription
and append the StoreDescription
to the array of stores
that we want
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer to load.
Finally, we load our stores
as you normally would.
Now, I would like to say that
that's all you have to do at all,
but we have to configure
our CloudKitContainer
to work correctly
with NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
You see, it fetches data differently
in the public database.
And so, I want to use
the CloudKit Dashboard now
to change the configuration of our schema.
To do that, I'm just gonna open Safari.
And you can see that I already have
the page I need open in Safari.
So let's orient ourselves to where we are.
At the top, you can see that I've selected
the iCloud container
for our sample application,
and we're in the development environment
looking specifically at the schema.
We're looking at the indexes section
of the schema
because we need to add some indexes
to all five of the record types
that you see listed on the screen here
on the left-hand side.
We need to add two new indexes
to each record type,
and to do that, I'm just gonna use
this "Add Index" button down here.
I'll click it once and add one
for the record name,
and then another one
for the modified at date.
And finally, I'll save my changes.
These are the indexes that
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer needs
to run its queries against the public
database to fetch records of this type.
Of course, for your application,
you would have to repeat these steps
for all of your record types,
so we would do this four more times
for our sample application.
So that's all we have to do
to build an application
that works with
the public CloudKit database.
We simply adopt
NSPersistentCloudKitContainerOptions'
new databaseScope property
and add a couple of indexes
to all of our record types.
Now if you don't see all of your indexes
in the CloudKit Dashboard,
you may need to go through a process
that we call "schema initialization."
And schema initialization is detailed
in our documentation
and in the session from 2019.
Once you finish that,
you will have a complete local mirror
of all of the data in CloudKit
on the device your application
is running on.
Now you might be wondering
why we create a complete local mirror,
and the reason is, you asked us to.
You see, since our talk in 2019,
we've received a slew of feature requests
for support with the public database,
and they had some common themes.
The first being that all of the requests
wanted to create a dataset
that everyone could use,
that is, all users of your application
could access.
Now sometimes this was data that you,
the developer, would create,
such as an application template
or an initial dataset
so that your user has a rich experience
with your application from day one.
In other cases,
it was data created by users.
Now, I'm gonna be candid here.
The most common request
that we got for this
was for a high scores table
in a video game.
And this is actually a great example
of what we want
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer to support.
You need all the data locally,
so that you can quickly fetch it,
sort it and order it,
and it's something that
your users will want to contribute to.
We also know that you want to mix data
from the private database as needed
in these applications.
And this makes a lot of sense.
Your user may want to upload
their high score,
but they may not want to upload
their saved game state
or their character configuration
to the public database,
and instead, to sync that,
you would use the private database.
And that's actually a great segue
to our next section,
which is special considerations,
or things that you need to think about
as you're building applications
that work with the public database.
To dig into this a little bit,
we're gonna compare and contrast
the behavior
of NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
when working with the private database
and the public database.
The first thing that we'll look at is
the notion of accounts and ownership,
and how that changes between the two.
You see, in the private database,
accounts are required,
and all the data's owned by a single user,
so the behavior is fairly straightforward.
But the public database
doesn't work that way.
Accounts are optional.
You can read data from the public database
without an iCloud account,
and that data could be owned by
any user of your application.
We'll also talk about import
and how that changes
between the public and private database.
You see, the private database
supports push notifications,
and the public database does not,
so we have to query for records
that we want to import
using a process called polling.
Now, I wanted to call out export here
because we won't be talking about it.
It works identically between
the private and public databases,
and we talked about it in detail
in our session in 2019.
When we think about
accounts and ownership,
what we're really talking about is the set
of actions that your application can take
when you're signed in or signed out
of an iCloud account.
Now as I said, in the private database,
this is super straightforward.
If you're signed out,
you can't do anything.
If you're signed in,
you can do everything.
The world is your oyster
and all the data is yours to work with.
In the public database, though,
this gets a lot more complicated.
You can read data
if you're signed out or signed in,
but you can only create data, new records
if you're signed in to an iCloud account.
What about modifications?
Well, it's tricky.
And this poses a problem for applications
that have UIs like our sample application.
Maybe you have some editing controls,
such as this Edit button in the top left,
or this plus button in the top right
that allows us to create new records.
Likewise, our sample application
has a DetailViewController
that allows us to edit individual objects,
and that also has
an editing control in it.
Our application may need to know
whether or not
it can use one or any of these controls
based on where that object is stored
and where the database that
that object lives in.
And it turns out that you can use
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer's
existing APIs to figure this out.
You simply ask CloudKit
for the current account.
Then you ask NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
for the record that backs
an object you're working with,
and if you compare the creator user ID,
then you'll know whether or not
that object is mutable.
But this is a ridiculous amount of code
just to turn this question mark
into a yes or no,
and it's an insane amount of code
to execute for every user interface
element in your application.
So we can do better.
And we have.
This is NSPersistentCloudKitContainer's
new canUpdateRecord
forManagedObjectWith ID method,
which tells us exactly
what we need to know
about whether or not
this object is mutable
with respect to the current configuration
of the device,
the persistent store the object is kept in
and whether or not that store
is backed by CloudKit.
It even handles all the edge cases
you might expect,
like that object being stored in a store
that's not backed by CloudKit at all,
or the account changing on the device
while you're using your application.
And we cache this state
so that it's efficient enough
to use in your user interface.
Now, if you have a more coarse-grained
view of the world
such as this table view
in our application,
you can use
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer's
canModifyObjects in store
to tell whether or not any of the objects
in a given persistent store
would be mutable with respect
to the configuration on the device,
and whether or not that store
is backed by CloudKit.
Now, I'd like to switch gears a bit
and talk in detail about how import works
in the public database with
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
To do that, I wanna review some content
from our session in 2019.
You may remember this graphic
where we talked about how,
when we get a push notification
from CloudKit,
we schedule an import operation
that brings all of the changed records
down to the local store...
and makes them available
to your application.
And this works really well, even if you
have a large set of changed records
or a very complicated object graph.
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
can efficiently import
complicated graphs and large change sets
whether you're using the public database
or the private database.
To understand how they're different,
we want to take a look at
exactly what happens
between the cloud
and the local persistent store.
When I say that we create
an import operation,
what I really mean
is that we create an instance
of CKFetchRecordZoneChangesOperation.
And this creates a single request
against the CloudKit server,
which brings down
all of the changed records
from the private database.
But CKFetchRecordZoneChangesOperation
relies on some technologies
that are specific to the private database,
and so, in the public database,
we have to use CKQueryOperation instead.
Now, if you've ever used CKQueryOperation,
you know that queries affect
a specific record type,
which means that we have to make
one request for the post
and another request for their tags,
and another request for the attachments,
and another request for the images,
and another request for
the many-to-many relationships.
And so on. It continues until we fetch
all the record types in our application.
And this means that stores backed by the
public database are doing a lot more work.
And that's how we import data
into the public database.
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer has
to use CKQueryOperation
instead of
CKFetchRecordZoneChangesOperation,
and we have to poll for changes
instead of using push notifications
to know exactly when to make our requests.
Now this means that we need to be careful
about how we load up the CloudKit server
because of the way
we want your applications
to scale with the public database.
So we're only going to poll for changes
on application launch
or after about every 30 minutes
of application use.
This is to ensure that we align
the load of these requests
with the actual usage
of your applications.
Of course, this does mean
that the quality of freshness
that you can expect from a public database
will be noticeably different
from the private database.
I also want to mention that this means
that simpler ManageObjectModels--
that is ManageObjectModels
that have fewer entities in them--
will make fewer requests
through the public database.
Now that's not to say
that you shouldn't have complicated
object graphs in your application,
or that the public database
doesn't support them.
In fact, you absolutely should.
You should build the ManageObjectModels
you need for the public database,
but it does mean that
you should restrict that model
to only the entities
that are used in the public database
so that NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
isn't making unnecessary requests.
Now we do this using a configuration
in the ManageObjectModel,
and we talk about those in detail
in our documentation
about how you set up a ManagedObjectModel
for use with
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
You want to restrict the entities
that are used in the public database
to a specific configuration
for that store.
Now, why does any of this matter?
Well, because queries affect how deletes
propagate throughout the public database,
consider the following set of objects.
If we import those objects
onto two devices,
both devices will come to an identical
picture of what's in the cloud,
as we would expect, right?
In the private database,
if we delete an object from one device
and then export that delete to the cloud,
that will leave behind a shell
called a tombstone,
which contains the record type
and the record ID
of the object that was deleted.
Now this allows us to fetch that tombstone
via CKFetchRecordZoneChangesOperation
when we import changes
from the private database
and delete that record
on the other device.
So both devices, again, come to
the same picture of what's in the cloud.
However, as I said,
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer can't use
CKFetchRecordZoneChangesOperation
with the public database.
It has to use CKQueryOperation.
So when we delete our record
from one device
and export that delete
to the public database,
the record is deleted immediately.
And this means that when we execute
our CKQueryOperation,
we ask the public database what's changed,
and it says, "Nothing."
There's no tombstone left behind
for us to fetch.
This means that we can't propagate
the delete to the other device,
and they will have different pictures
of what's in the cloud.
And this poses a potential problem
for our applications,
especially if they have user interfaces
like this one
where we have swipe to delete,
for example, in our table view.
In swiping to delete this object,
that delete won't propagate
in the public database
to all the devices
that have downloaded this object.
And it turns out that you can
totally detect that this will occur
using an API on CKRecordZone
called Capabilities.
If a zone doesn't support
the fetchChanges capability,
we can't use
CKFetchRecordZoneChangesOperation
to import data from it.
We have to use queries instead,
but that takes so much code
to integrate into your application
that I didn't even bother
to put it on slides.
Instead, we can detect this
in one line of code
using NSPersistentCloudKitContainer's
new canDeleteRecord
forManagedObjectWith ID method.
If it returns false,
that means that this record is stored
in the public database,
and NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
can't import the delete
in the same way that it would
from the private database.
Now, that doesn't mean
that you can't delete.
In fact, you definitely should delete data
when you need to.
But there's a difference
between deleting data
for the sake of removing it
from the public database
and removing it from the user interface
in your application.
In this code, we use canDeleteRecord
forManagedObjectWith ID
to tell whether or not
we should be updating a record
to remove it from our user interface
instead of deleting it.
To do that, we set the isTrashed property
on this tag to "true"
when we can't delete something
from the public database.
And in our application,
we use a fetchRequest
with a predicate that filters out
all the trashed records
to remove them from the user interface.
In this way, we're using an update,
or a modification, in place of a delete
to achieve the desired effect
in our user interface.
Now, we can carry
this paradigm even further,
say, for example, by milling out
all the fields on the record
that we no longer need once it's trashed.
This reclaims space
in the public database,
as well as on disc on your users' devices.
And you could go even further
by eventually purging these trashed
records from the public database
once you're confident that all of
the users who downloaded these records
have processed this update.
And so what you really need to decide
in your application is,
do you want to delete something
from the public database
so that no one ever downloads it again,
or do you want to pull something
out of the UI?
In this session, we learned a lot about
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer,
including its new databaseScope API
that allows you to configure
whether you want to use a store
with the public or private database.
And we took a detailed look at what the
public database means to your application.
Finally, we learned about some other
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer APIs
and how they can help make
some of these considerations
easier for you to deal with.
So that's all about
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
and the public database.
It's been my pleasure
to bring you this session,
and from all of us here at Apple,
have an amazing WWDC.
[chimes]