Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Kevin,
and I work on Xcode Previews.
Xcode Previews
helps you write SwiftUI code,
edit your views
in multiple configurations at once,
and quickly test all of your changes.
But previews benefit your app as a whole.
By structuring your app
to make it more previewable,
you make your app more understandable,
more testable and more maintainable.
In this video,
I want to show you four ways
you can structure your app
to get the most out of Previews.
First, we'll look at how
to preview multiple files at once,
so that you can edit views
in the larger context.
Secondly, we'll look at the relationship
between previews
and the SwiftUI app life cycle,
so that you can get both
great performance for your previews
while also defining
explicit data dependencies.
Third, speaking of data, we'll look at
where to define sample data,
so that you can have a comprehensive set
of examples during development
without affecting
the size of your deployed app.
And finally,
we'll look at a handful of techniques
for making your views themselves
more previewable.
We have a lot to cover in this video,
so let's dive in.
I'll be using the same app
for all the demos in this video.
It's an app for creating collages
of the photos I've taken.
You can create a collage, pick a layout,
pick some photos, add your friends,
and, like every great photo app,
even add some effects.
So first, let's look at how to preview
multiple files at once.
We'll start in the view for the thumbnail
for picking a layout for our collage.
I have this gray rectangle here, and it
looks great on this white background.
But how does it look in context?
For that, I'll switch over to the selector
for picking the layout.
Now I have two previews here.
One is showing the selector
on a white background,
and the second is showing it
on top of an image.
This is meant to show what it looks like
when the user pinches-to-zoom the collage
and content slides underneath
that selector.
As you can see,
that thumbnail kind of disappears
when there's content behind it.
So I want to make that color
stick out a bit more.
But as I edit that color, I don't want to
lose the context of where I'm using it.
I can accomplish this
by pinning the preview
by clicking this button in the bottom bar.
Now, when I switch back
to my Layout Thumbnail view,
Xcode is showing me both the previews
for the view that I just pinned
and the previews
from the file you're working in.
And Xcode adds dividers to show
where each set of previews comes from.
And now I can edit this color.
So let's change this to 70%.
It looks a little better,
but 80% looks even better.
But how does this look in Dark Mode?
I'll duplicate the preview
by clicking the "plus" button.
I'll select the preview,
open the inspector,
pick a dark appearance...
And now when I see this preview,
that gray looks a little out of place.
I'd like to customize this gray
for Dark Mode.
The recommended way to do this
is to use an asset in the Asset catalog.
So I'm gonna select my color.
And I've already set up a color,
so I'm gonna open the library,
go to my colors,
and pick our grid placeholder.
Now, nothing's changed because I haven't
customized this color yet for Dark Mode.
So let's go do that.
But when I do that,
I want to be able to edit that color,
again, in the context of
where I'm using it in this thumbnail.
So I'm gonna unpin the previews
from our layout selector
and re-pin the previews
for our layout thumbnail.
Let's go into the Asset catalog
to edit this color.
Here you can see that gray.
I'll select it, and using the inspector,
add a customization for Dark Mode.
You can select that customization.
I'm gonna change this to 20%.
Now I'll save the Asset catalog.
Resume the preview.
Xcode will rebuild the app
and show me what this new color looks like
in context.
And that looks great.
I want to show you
one other use-case for pinning,
which is by bringing in
additional previews
that you might not need
during the entire time you're developing.
Using the navigator,
I'm gonna navigate over
to another set of previews
in this extra previews file.
This is showing me several different
previews for our accessibility layouts.
They all look the same right now
because I actually haven't
customized my view yet
to react to
the different accessibility sizes.
So let's unpin the preview
and pin these different
accessibility previews.
Then I can switch back to my thumbnail.
And now I can scale the size
and the spacing of this thumbnail
based on the size category.
I've passed the size category in
through the environment,
and I've added an extension
to the content size category
to provide a scale
that's appropriate for my app.
I can use that scale
by selecting each place I need to use it
and multiplying
by the size category scale.
And now it looks great across
all these different size categories.
And just like you would expect,
I can continue to edit my preview
and see what these changes look like
across all those different sizes.
So that's three ways that we can
leverage previewing pinning,
whether it's making edits
within a larger context,
being able to edit non-Swift files,
or being able to pull in
additional previews
that you need for a particular task.
Next, we'll look at the relationship
between previews
and the SwiftUI app life cycle,
which was introduced
in iOS 14 and iPadOS 14.
All of our apps do
some kind of initialization at startup.
This might be
loading a document from disk,
connecting with CloudKit,
or communicating with various devices.
Whatever it is, the point is
that often this work is expensive.
What's great about previews
is that we can edit small and leaf views
in our project
and jump right to them
right in the canvas.
For these previews, we want to avoid
doing that expensive initialization work.
Now, it's important to think about this
in terms of defining
explicit dependencies for our data.
It's not so much about doing work
for previews or not for previews.
It's about defining
when you want that work to happen.
SwiftUI app life cycle gives us
just the tool to define this dependency.
Let's take a look at how it works.
Here's the definition of my app type.
And here as a property,
I've defined my network model.
So every time my app gets created,
it'll create my model.
Let's take a look at what my app is doing
when I'm running under previews.
And to do this, I'm gonna attach
a debugger to our preview.
I can do that by pressing
and holding the "play" button
and picking Debug Preview.
I can attach a debugger
to any of my previews,
and it's really great
'cause I can do two things:
One, if I have any breakpoints set,
I can hit those breakpoints
and debug why my preview
isn't showing what I expect.
Or, in the case of this demo,
I'm gonna give you an example
of how using the debug gauges
will help you see what your app is doing.
When I open the debug gauges,
I can see that my app
is doing a lot of work on startup,
both on the CPU, and the network
is pulling down a lot of data.
This is because I'm initializing
that data model.
For the preview that I'm looking at,
I don't need to do that work.
So I'm gonna take advantage of
SwiftUI's StateObject property wrapper.
Let's pause our preview.
And let's add @StateObject
to our property.
This will tell SwiftUI
to only initialize our data model
when the app is first created,
and it allows SwiftUI to react
to any changes in our data model.
Also, for previews,
models that are created
using StateObject are not initialized.
And this give us a great opportunity
to do work
only when we need to run our app.
So now, let's resume our preview.
Let's start debugging again.
And let's take a look
at where our CPU is now.
That looks much better.
We're doing no unnecessary work
on the CPU or on the network.
So that's an example of using StateObject
to only initialize our data
when we actually need it.
To learn more about StateObject,
check out the video
"App Essentials in SwiftUI."
If we're not initializing our data models
as part of our StateObjects,
how do we get data into our previews?
We'll look at this in two parts.
First, let's look at where to define
sample data for our previews.
Our collage editor is a photo app.
So during development,
I want to have a lot of examples
to make sure that my effects
and my layouts are working properly.
So I've defined an Asset catalog
and added a bunch of images to it
that I can reference in my previews.
But I don't want to ship
all of these images in my final app.
So I can take advantage of Xcode's
development assets for my target.
So let's switch over
to our project editor,
scroll to the bottom, and you'll see
a section here called Development Assets.
A development asset is a path
to a file or folder,
and Xcode will only include those paths
in the development version of your app.
If you're creating a SwiftUI app
form an Xcode template,
the app comes pre-configured
with a development asset path for you.
That's this one right here.
But you can also easily add your own,
like I've done here,
and you can also add them
to additional targets.
So I'll switch over
to my Mosaic Kit framework,
click the "plus" button,
type in "preview content,"
and find that additional preview content
to only include
for the development version of my app.
What's great about Development Assets
is they apply not only to files
like Asset catalogs, but also to code.
Let's look at what's inside that preview
content folder that we just added.
By using the navigator, we can
look inside and see two Swift files.
These Swift files contain code
that I only need for development
and debugging and testing my app,
and I don't want to include these
when my app is actually deployed.
So that demo was mainly about defining
where to define our preview assets
and resources and code.
But how about actually
feeding that data into our previews?
Well, for this, we're gonna make
our views themselves previewable.
And this is really
where we're gonna see the payoff
in structuring our app
to make it more previewable.
I want to start with a big idea.
What makes our apps unique
is the user experience.
But behind our unique user experience
is a unique data model.
I call this a rich data type.
It could be something from Core Data
or from CloudKit
or something custom that we've built.
But at the end of the day,
our users are gonna interact
with our apps using simple data types.
This might a be a string in a text field
or a Boolean in a Toggle.
And in between is all of our views.
And those translate the rich data type
into the simple data type.
The question is, where in our view
hierarchy should we do this translation?
Now, as a general rule of thumb,
the sooner that we do this translation
from our rich type
into our simpler data types,
the more reusable, testable,
and previewable our app is gonna be.
The big incentive here is that we want to
make it easy for us to add previews
so that we can test our app in all of
the configurations so they all look great.
We'll look at four examples
of how to structure our views
to make them more previewable.
First, we'll look at at an example
of passing immutable, simple data types
into a view
that doesn't need to change the values.
Secondly, we'll look at an example
of using SwiftUI bindings
to pass simple data types into a view,
an inspector,
that does need to change those values.
Third, we'll use generics
so that we can pass an abstraction
of our data into a view
so that we can pass that on
to other views.
And finally, we'll look at an example
a little different from the others
and use the environment
to pass inputs into our view.
So first,
let's look at an example of passing
immutable, simple data types into our cell
for adding a collaborator for our collage.
We'll start by looking at the data model
behind our collaborator.
It has some simple types, like this color
and last contribution date,
but most of the model
is backed by the CKUserIdentity.
So now, let's go look at the cell.
Our cell takes a collaborator
as an input as an observed object.
So, let's create a preview.
I'll create the cell,
and then need to create a collaborator.
When I get to the point
of filling in the CKUserIdentity,
I know that I need to create
a fetch operation on our CK database.
But our data model for CloudKit
was exactly what we turned off
in one of the previous demos.
For this view,
I don't actually need the full model.
So let's look at another way to do this.
This brings up a really important idea,
which is to look at the UI that
you're building, and look at your model,
and identify the minimum amount of data
that you need to pass through your model
into the view.
So let's look at another example
of our CollaboratorCell.
In this cell, we're passing the name,
the image, and the connection status
as individual simple inputs.
So now, creating a preview for this
is really easy.
So, we'll create a CollaboratorCell...
And this is gonna take that name--
we'll say Jane Doe--
an image-- for now
we'll just pass an empty image--
and the status.
And we'll start with Jane on-line.
And just like that,
I have a preview for that cell.
What's great is it's really easy to create
multiple configurations of this cell.
So I'm gonna duplicate this preview
a few times.
And one of these, I'll make Jane off-line.
And we'll give her an image.
So, open up our Asset Catalog
and pick an image.
And we'll also make sure the text is gonna
properly resize as it gets larger.
So we'll give her
a really long middle name.
And that's just how easy it is to create
multiple configurations
with these simple data types as inputs.
But sometimes we can make
our data types too simple.
This can happen when we want the system
to format a value
based on the locale
that your user is using in the app.
For example, with a date, or in this case,
with a name.
So instead of passing a string in
for our name,
we're gonna pass in PersonNameComponents.
And now we can tell SwiftUI
to format the text for this name
at exactly the right time.
This is as easy as defining a formatter...
and then passing that formatter
into our text.
Finally, let's update our previews to
create name components instead of strings.
So I'll select each instance
of my static string...
and replace it with a call
to create the PersonNameComponents.
Now, I can refresh my preview,
and you can see how easy it is
to create one of these
PersonNameComponents
and still give me
all the configuration that I need.
Now we can also add in that example
with the middle name.
So we'll say "Really Long Middle."
And just like that,
all my previews look great,
and I can see
all these different configurations.
So when you can,
you wanna make the inputs to your views
simple, immutable data types.
But sometimes our viewers
need to actually change values.
So, second, let's look at an example
of using SwiftUI bindings
to pass in a simple data type
that our viewer can change.
So in this inspector,
I'm passing in the slot data
for an image as an observed object.
A slot just represents
one of the photos on our collage.
Let's take a look
at that ImageSlot data type.
Now, this has some simple types,
but really,
the core of this
is a backing ClockKit record.
As we saw from our previous examples,
in order for me to create a record,
I'm gonna need to have that
full ClockKit data model all pulled in.
I wanna make it really easy
to create previews,
so I'm gonna apply that same idea
that I did in the previous demo.
I'm gonna look at the UI
and pick out just the pieces
that my UI actually needs to edit.
So let's switch
to a different version of our inspector.
And in this case, we're passing
a binding in for our SlotEffects.
This is a really simple type
that just has some floating-point values
for each of our different filters.
It's really easy to create previews.
So I'm gonna create an inspector
and pass in some effects.
And you can see here
I'm using a constant binding,
which just means that in this view,
the binding can't be changed.
But that's actually what we want to test.
So let's add an example where we can
actually change the value of this binding.
To do that for previews,
I'm gonna introduce an intermediate view
that will store some state
that I can pass as a binding into my view.
So let's define my view...
and let's define a new preview
that creates that new view
and passes in some effects.
Those effects are stored as state,
and our inspector passes them in
as a binding.
And now, when we resume our preview,
we can take this preview live...
and we can interact with it
right here in the canvas.
There's one more piece of UI
I want to add here,
which is a button that allows me
to replace the photo.
I could pass in the whole image slot
data type into this view
and do all the replacement logic here,
but really,
I want clients to decide how to do that.
So instead, I'm gonna pass in a closure
that will get called
when the button is pressed.
So I'm gonna add a closure as an input,
and let's add that button.
This is just a simple button that calls
that replacePhotoHandler.
And now let's go update our previews
to provide a value for this callback.
For the first one,
I'll just pass an empty closure.
But for the second one, I wanna make sure
that button is actually working.
So for that, I'm actually gonna have
my callback just change our effects,
so I can see that it's working.
And now, when we resume the preview...
As we click our button,
you can see that saturation is going down.
But what's great about previews
is that I can interact with it
not only right here on the canvas,
but I can interact with it in multiple
places by using on-device previews.
So I have an iPhone XR here in Dark Mode,
and I want to put that same preview
on that device as well.
I'll click the "device" button,
click my iPhone XR...
and Xcode will now mirror this preview
onto a device.
And just like before,
I can fully interact with it
right here on the device.
Now, in Xcode 12 and iOS 14 and iPadOS 14,
there's a new experience
for on-device previews.
As you make changes,
they're seamlessly reflected
on to your devices.
You'll notice that the first time
you use on-device previews with Xcode 12
that an icon appears on your Home Screen
called Xcode Previews.
By tapping this icon,
you can get back to the last preview
you were looking at
even if your phone is disconnected
from Xcode.
This makes it great
for being able to make some changes,
put them in a preview,
and go show your colleagues.
So that's a quick look at using bindings.
So we can keep using
simple data types for our inputs
while also allowing our views
to mutate them.
But there are cases
when we need to pass richer data types
from one view to another.
So third,
let's look at an example of using generics
to pass data
into the main editor for our collage.
So let me switch over first to show
what the model for our collage looks like.
Like the other types that we have,
it's backed
by this CloudKit CKShare record.
Now, as with the other examples
that we've seen,
I'm gonna need that full data model
in order to create
one of these collage model objects
and pass it into a preview.
We could use the approach
we used in our previous demo,
and use bindings to pass in the data.
Let's try that.
so I'll switch over
to the Editor for our collage.
And here you can see it's taking
a binding in for the name and the layout,
which are simple types,
and for the slot data.
So let's create a preview.
I'm gonna provide a name
using a constant binding for now,
and the layout using a constant binding.
But when I get to the slot data,
I noticed that the slot data
is still using that rich data type
that we used in a previous demo.
This is gonna make it difficult for me to
pass in data for each one of my previews.
So even though I'm using bindings,
I still can't pass in the data
that I actually need.
Let's step back and use that same approach
we've been using for our other demos,
to think about the UI that we're building
and the minimum amount of data
that we need from our model
to create that UI.
And in this example,
we're gonna define a protocol
to create an abstraction
of exactly what we need.
So let's look at this abstraction,
which is called a CollageProtocol.
This defines everything
that a collage needs to have
in order to be editable by our UI.
I have a name, a layout,
and some slot data,
but that slot data is also an abstraction.
Each slot in our collage
must have an imagePublisher.
It's a publisher because that data could
be asynchronously provided from the cloud,
already on disk or in an error state.
And it's also providing those effects.
Now that we have this collage protocol,
we can define a Design Time version
of our model that's really easy to create.
So I've done that
over here in the preview content
for our framework.
You can see that this Design Time collage
has a name and a layout and some slots,
and that's using this DesignTimeSlot.
The DesignTimeSlot
has a publisher and some effects.
So now let's go look
at a version of our editor
that allows passing in
this Design Time version of our model.
So I'll switch over to the editor here.
And this collage editor is generic
over two things.
First, it's generic over the collage type,
which conforms to that collage protocol
that we just saw.
It's also generic over an ImagePickerType.
This allows me to define
a simpler UI for Design Time
to allow picking a photo for that collage
instead of having to go to the full photo
library every time I want to test it.
So now you'll see how easy it is
to create previews for our collage editor.
So just call our collage editor.
That's gonna take two inputs.
First, our collage.
Do a Design Time collage.
And this, as we saw,
takes a couple inputs.
It takes a name,
which we'll just call "My Collage."
Takes a layout. We'll start with twoByTwo.
And it takes some slot data.
For now,
we'll just pass in some empty data.
It also takes a closure
for making this photo picker.
I've created a Design Time version
of this photo picker
that just draws on images
from that previews asset catalog
that we saw earlier.
And just like that,
I have a preview for my collage editor,
and it's completely functional.
But it's using
that Design Time simpler data model.
And, because it's a view,
I can also add view-specific modifiers.
So let's give it a bit of padding.
And now I can test this collage editor
right here in the canvas.
By clicking the "play" button...
I can double-tap on a slot
and pick a photo
or maybe pick a different layout.
Also, I can pass in examples
of our Design Time slot data.
So I can pick an address--
The address is--
Think of it like a row in a column.
And then I can pass in an example
of our DesignTimeImageSlot.
This is just taking one of the images
from our asset catalog
and passing in some empty effects.
And I can see what it looks like
if it's in the second column
or in the second row
or maybe a different image,
or I can even pass in some effects.
So I want to see
what the saturation looks like at 50%.
This looks great on iPhone,
but how does it look on iPad?
Like the last example, we're also
gonna put this preview on-device.
I can select the On Device button
and select "My iPad."
And this'll let me see
what this collage editor looks like
on an iPad in landscape.
Just like the version in my canvas,
this is fully interactive.
I double-tap, pick a photo,
and I can even open the inspector
and add some effects.
I was able to test all the functionality
for this collage editor
without ever creating
my CloudKit-backed data model
and just using
the Design Time version of my data model.
Fourth, let's look at an example
that's a little different from the others.
When you can,
you should define explicit
data dependencies between your views
by defining inputs on them.
But sometimes it's convenient
to pass data through the environment.
Let's look at the relationship
between previews and the environment
by adding some previews for the view
that shows the status
of syncing with our cloud.
So let's switch over to our CloudSyncView.
Our CloudSyncStatusView takes
the CloudSyncStatus as an input
as an EnvironmentObject.
In SwiftUI,
when you have an EnvironmentObject,
you need to provide a value
for that object higher in the hierarchy.
When you're creating previews
for these views that take
EnvironmentObjects as inputs,
you also need to provide a value
for each preview.
Let's see how that works.
So I'll create a CloudSyncStatusView...
and then attach
the EnvironmentObject modifier.
I'll create a CloudSyncStatus,
and there's a preview of what my view
looks like when our cloud is on-line.
But just like with our other examples,
it's so easy to add
multiple configurations
when you're using environment.
So I'll duplicate my preview...
and this time, I'm gonna pass in
what happens when our cloud is off-line.
So there's my icon
for the cloud being off-line.
Let's duplicate it again,
and let's make sure we can correctly show
the time of when it last synced.
So we do lastSync,
and let's try "a few hours ago."
Finally, to make sure
that we're covering all of our bases,
let's look at when the cloud is on-line
and having just recently synced.
So there's an example
of using the environment
to pass inputs to our views,
and just like with other explicit inputs,
it's really easy to create
multiple configurations of our previews
when we're using these simpler types.
For our last example,
I want to bring together all the things
we've been seeing in this video.
So let's switch over
to the root view of our app.
This root view, like our collage editor,
is generic over two things:
first, the CollageType,
which is that CollageProtocol,
and the ImagePickerType.
I've defined an intermediate view
that has some state
which is storing our collages
which are the Design Time collages
that we made earlier.
Then it's creating one of those root views
and passing the collages in as a binding.
There's also an action callback
when the "plus" button is pressed
that allows me to create
one of these Design Time collages,
and because it's so easy to create
one of the Design Time collages,
this closure is simple to fill in.
And finally, it's passing in
the DesignTimePhotoPicker.
When I actually use my preview,
then I'm attaching an EnvironmentObject
with our CloudSyncStatus.
And now, I have a fully functional version
of my application
right here in the canvas.
I click the "play" button.
I can click the "plus" button
to add a new collage,
go in, pick a different layout,
maybe pick a photo.
I can go back,
and I can delete it by swiping to delete.
And I can also make changes live
to this view.
So let's pin the preview,
and I'd like to make the thumbnail
a little bit bigger here.
So to do that,
I'm gonna switch over to our Collage List
to the collage label
that shows the thumbnail
for our collage and the title.
Now I can go into this value
and change it to something a bit bigger.
Okay, maybe that was a little too big.
Let's go back to 30. That looks great.
Now finally, this looks great in iPhone,
but how does it look in an iPhone
in dark appearance or on the iPad?
So we can see
multiple on-device previews at once.
I'm gonna click
my on-device preview button
and select both devices,
my iPhone and my iPad.
And now Xcode is putting
fully functional versions of my app
on all of these devices.
In the canvas, I could, you know, again,
add and swipe to delete.
On my iPhone,
I could go into the portraits here
and maybe pick a different layout.
Oh, that looks a lot better. Go back.
On my iPad, I can select a collage,
pick a photo,
and open up the effects...
and test all of that functionality
without ever running my app.
And what's great is when I make edits,
it reflects on all these devices
at the same time.
So I'll select that 30.
I'll change it to a 90.
And now I can really make sure
that I see that thumbnail.
I hope you can see
just how powerful previews can be
when you're defining abstractions
for your data
and using multiple previews
and multiple contexts
to test all of your configurations
without ever running your app.
So there's four examples
of how to structure your views
to make them more previewable.
Now, we've seen a lot in this video.
First, we looked at how to preview
multiple files at once
so that you could edit a view
in the larger context.
Secondly, we looked at
the relationship between previews
and the SwiftUI app life cycle
and using StateObject
to only initialize data when you need it.
Third,
we looked at where to define sample data
and how to keep it out
of our release product
by using development assets.
And finally, we looked at four ways
that you can make your views themselves
more previewable.
I want to leave you with one big idea.
The investments to make your app more
previewable benefit your app as a whole.
I hope you saw from this video that
a previewable app is more understandable,
more testable,
and a more maintainable app.
So let's go build some great apps.
Thank you.