Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, I'm Mike Lamb. I'm a software
engineer on the Apple Watch team.
I'm here today to talk about the best ways
to keep your complications up to date.
We have a lot to cover,
so let's get started.
Complications are intrinsic
to the user experience on the Apple Watch.
With Face Sharing, SwiftUI complications
and multiple complication APIs
being released in watchOS 7,
complications are an even bigger focus
for Watch apps this year.
Complications are a great way to provide
timely and relevant information
on the Watch face at a quick glance.
Keeping complications up to date
is imperative
to making a great experience
for customers.
watchOS provides complication apps'
special capabilities
to enable a great experience.
Complication apps are kept around
even when other apps may be stopped
and removed from memory.
If the system does need
to stop a complication app,
it will be restarted later
to update its complications.
Since complications are always visible,
complication apps
are considered in use for privacy.
Our goal today
is to go over the techniques apps can use
to keep dynamic complications up to date.
We'll start by discussing
an example app I'm building
to illustrate these techniques.
An excellent time
to update our complications
is when the app is being actively used.
We'll go over how to do this.
Even when the app isn't in the foreground,
watchOS provides mechanisms to allow it
to keep its complications up to date.
Background updates
make complications feel like magic.
The first background update mechanism
is Background App Refresh.
Background App Refresh
allows apps to schedule background runtime
to access APIs and data on the Watch.
Apps can also schedule
background URLSessions
to pull data from servers
while the app isn't active.
And data can be sent directly to the app
on the Watch using complication pushes.
We'll end today's talk
with an example of how to do this.
To reiterate, for each of the three
background mechanisms,
the app doesn't need to be active
all the time.
It will be launched as necessary
to update its complications.
All these mechanisms
can be used separately or in combination
depending on your app's needs.
To illustrate
how to keep complications up to date,
I've been working
on an example kite flying app.
Our goal is to provide a compelling
experience without requiring a phone,
so we're building
an independent Watch app.
We're gonna make use of the new APIs
available in watchOS 7
to support multiple active complications.
To be clear, today we're showing
how to keep complications up to date.
We're not showing
how to design or build them.
See our other sessions
for information on how to do that.
We want the app to encourage people to
be more active, so our first complication
will pull information
about the day's activity from HealthKit.
We'll use Background App Refresh
to pull that data.
It's important to track the weather
when you're thinking about flying a kite,
so we'll need weather data,
especially wind.
We'll use background URLSessions
to grab weather data
for the latest cached location
periodically.
Flying kites with friends is great fun,
so we'll want to provide a complication
that displays encouragement
from our friends.
We'll use complication pushes
to provide updates for this complication.
Let's talk about updating
in the foreground first.
Any time our app is launched by the user
is a great time
to update our complications.
Once we have updates we want to display,
we use the ClockKit APIs
to reload our complication's timeline.
A complication consists
of a timeline of entries.
When an app wants to update
a complication,
it calls reloadTimeline
on the complication's server
for that complication.
Here we've written
an updateActiveComplications method
which we'll use throughout our app.
This method iterates
over the array of active complications
and asks the complication's server
to reload each one.
In this example, we're updating
all complications each time.
Typically, you should be more selective
and only update those complications
that need to be updated.
We will call updateActiveComplications
any time we want to update
our complications.
After reloadTimeline is called
by updateActiveComplications,
or at other times as needed,
the complication server will call
the app's CLKComplicationDataSource
to get the current timeline entry.
In response, our app then builds an entry
using a template and providers.
When the app is finished building
the entry,
our app passes it
to the complication server
using the provided completion handler.
Here's the code.
After reloadTimeline is called
by updateActiveComplications,
our CLKComplicationDataSource is invoked.
It is asked for the current timeline entry
for the complication to update.
A handler is provided
to pass back the entry after it's built.
We use a template that's appropriate
for the type of complication.
We fill the template with providers
to build a timeline entry.
Once the entry has been created,
you pass it back
using the handler that was provided.
As you can see, updating complications
while in the foreground
is straightforward.
We ask the complication server
to reload our complications
and then provide the current entry
for each one.
We'll do this whenever the user
changes selections in the app
or our app receives new data
while it's in the foreground.
Often though,
our app isn't in the foreground,
and in that case we can use mechanisms
like Background App Refresh
to get the data needed
to refresh our complications.
Going back to our example app,
we want to pull data from HealthKit
for our activity complication.
Background App Refresh allows us
to schedule periodic updates
to keep that complication up to date
even when the app isn't in use.
Our app can use Background App Refresh
to refresh complications
up to four times per hour.
This number doesn't change regardless
of how many of our app's complications
might be configured
on the active Watch face.
The actual number of updates an app
receives is dependent on conditions
such as how many other processes
are running and battery usage.
To schedule Background App Refresh,
call scheduleBackgroundRefresh
on WKExtension.
It's possible your app will be launched
in the background,
so consider scheduling your first request
in applicationDidFinishLaunching.
We've written a method
to schedule Background App Refresh.
First we choose the schedule date.
This is our first request.
We make that request sooner as shown.
The system will choose
the right time to launch your app.
This will always be after the time
you've requested.
Typically, it is within a minute or two,
but that depends on system conditions.
Use the userInfo dictionary
to supply your own data.
In this case,
just to illustrate how this is done,
we're passing the time
the request was made.
Once we have the schedule date
and the optional userInfo,
we call scheduleBackgroundRefresh
on WKExtension.
WKExtension will call our completion
handler asynchronously on the main thread
when the request has been scheduled.
Process any errors
that might have occurred.
When the task is ready,
our app will be made active,
and the extension delegate will be called
to handle the background task.
After doing some processing,
we'll request a complication update
and schedule our next
Background App Refresh.
Then we'll set the task completed.
Let's look at our extension delegate.
When Xcode generates
our extension delegate,
it also generates a method
to handle background tasks.
The system might have
more than one task to complete.
Our extension delegate loops
through all tasks and hails each one.
Generated code provides default handlers
for all types of background tasks
the app can receive.
We're handling it
WKApplicationRefreshBackgroundTask
and replacing the default handler
with our own code.
In this code, purely as an example,
we retrieve the userInfo we added
when we scheduled the request.
We use a date that we stored within it
to calculate the time
since the request was made.
Then we call
our updateActiveComplications method
and ask the complication server
to reload our active complications.
We then schedule
the next background refresh.
After we've updated our complications
and scheduled another request,
then we complete the current task.
We pass "false" to indicate
that no snapshot is needed.
Each complication update
results in a snapshot request,
so we don't have to request one
separately.
The app may be suspended as soon
as it completes the background task,
so we must do all our work
before setting the task completed.
If we want to do something more complex,
like access HealthKit,
we'll need to revise our strategy.
To avoid putting too much code
in our extension delegate,
I've added a data provider
that uses HealthKit
and adds a method
that takes its own completion handler.
HealthKit queries can be asynchronous,
so we'll need to wait
until the refresh is completed
before updating our complications,
scheduling our next request
and setting the task complete.
Doing this is pretty straightforward
because the HealthKit work is done
by our new HealthDataProvider.
We call the HealthDataProvider
to refresh this data.
It does that asynchronously.
When it's finished refreshing its data,
it calls the completion handler,
telling us whether or not
to update the complications.
Within the completion handler,
we actually update our complications,
schedule our next refresh
and set the task completed.
To review, Background App Refresh is great
for scheduling periodic background tasks.
Your app can be resumed or launched
to handle these tasks
up to four times per hour.
Here are some guidelines to keep in mind.
Only one request is outstanding at a time.
If you need periodic updates,
do what I've shown
and schedule the next one
before marking the current one complete.
No networking activity is allowed.
You use most of the APIs
available on the Watch,
but URLSession is an exception.
If you do try to use URLSession,
it will fail with an error.
Your app is limited to a maximum
of four seconds of active CPU time.
That may not sound like much,
but four seconds of constant processing
is actually quite a lot.
If you need to do
more processing than that,
consider breaking it into smaller chunks.
The app has a maximum of 15 seconds
of total time to complete the task.
A common reason for going over 15 seconds
is neglecting to mark the task completed.
Background App Refresh is great,
but if you need to access data
over a network while in the background,
use a background URLSession.
Background URLSessions allow your app
to schedule and receive data
even when the app isn't running.
Background URLSession can be used
in addition to Background App Refresh.
You can even change the request on the fly
and insert authentication challenges.
It's pretty cool.
We'll use it
to retrieve weather information
for the localized wind complication
we're planning to add to our app.
Under most conditions, your app can make
and receive up to four requests per hour.
The actual number depends
on a number of factors,
including the availability of Wi-Fi,
cellular reception and battery life.
Your app can have multiple
outstanding background download tasks.
Always make sure to attach to your session
when your app is launched
so you can receive
the URLSession delegate callbacks.
First, let's go over how to schedule
background URLSessions.
In our app,
we want to get weather data periodically,
and we'll use the URLSession framework
for this purpose.
We've created a WeatherDataProvider
to be our URLSession delegate.
Our data provider creates a background
URLSession configuration.
We set sessionSendsLaunchEvents
on the background configuration
to wake the app in the background.
We use the configuration to create
a URLSession in a download task.
We set the task's earliest begin date.
That will be the date
the task is scheduled for.
Then we resume the task to start it.
Here's the first part
of our WeatherDataProvider.
It's a URLSessionDownloadDelegate.
To create our URLSession,
we get a background configuration,
we mark the configuration
as nondiscretionary
and make sure sessionSendsLaunchEvents
is set to "true"
so the app is launched in the background.
Then we use a configuration
to create the URLSession.
So, if we set the delegateQueue to "nil,"
URLSession's responses will be sent
on a background serial queue.
Continuing with our WeatherDataProvider,
we've added a schedule method
to create and schedule a download task.
We have multiple outstanding requests,
but in this case, you only need one,
so we'll schedule a new background task
as long as one isn't already outstanding.
We build the URL we need using the latest
cached location from Core Location
and create our download task
for the background session.
We set the earliest begin date
for this task.
As we did earlier,
we make our first request right away
and schedule follow-on requests
for every 15 minutes.
We set the number of bytes
we expect to send and receive.
Finally,
we resume the task that is ready to run.
After it's scheduled, the download task
will run independently of our app.
When it's completed,
our app will be resumed in the background
or launched as necessary
to handle the request.
When the download is complete,
the WKExtension delivers
a WKURLSessionRefreshBackgroundTask
to our extension delegate.
We use our WeatherDataProvider
to handle the request.
Until we mark the task completed,
URLSession delegate methods
will be delivered.
Don't mark the task as completed
before handling those calls.
If the task completed successfully,
our delegate receives
a didFinishDownloadingTo delegate call.
Regardless of whether the download
completed successfully or not,
our delegate will receive
didCompleteWithOptionalError.
When that call is completed,
the WeatherDataProvider calls
the completion handler it was given,
which allows us to update
our complications,
schedule a new request
and then set the task completed.
The download task we scheduled earlier
is complete,
and now it's time to handle the results.
Our session delegate is asked to handle
WKURLSessionRefreshBackgroundTask.
The session delegate asks
the WeatherDataProvider to refresh
and passes a closure to be called
when done.
When the refresh is done,
the WeatherDataProvider calls the closure.
Within that closure,
we schedule our next retrieval,
update complications as necessary
and then mark the task completed.
Within our WeatherDateProvider,
our refresh method
stores the completion handler it is passed
so it can call it once the expected
delegate methods have been delivered.
Our WeatherDataProvider,
since the task is completed,
receives the URLSession delegate method
downloadTask didFinishDownloadingTo.
The data we asked for has been downloaded
to a file, we check for that,
and then process the json weather data
we received.
After the download task is complete
and we've processed the data,
our app receives
didCompleteWithOptionalError.
We want to call a completion handler
on the main queue,
so we dispatch to the main queue
and call the completion handler.
If there's no error,
we tell it to update the complications.
We then set the completion handler to
"nil" so it isn't called more than once.
Depending on the request,
our app may get intermediate requests
that allow our app to update the URL,
cancel the download task
or answer authentication challenges
before the download completes.
Let's look at those briefly.
As in other cases we've looked at
so far involving URLSession tasks,
these will come to our app
as WKURLSessionRefreshBackgroundTask.
As before, our extension delegate
will be asked to handle these tasks.
We'll use our WeatherDataProvider
to handle these requests.
While the task is active,
the WeatherDataProvider
will receive delegate calls
from the URLSession subsystem.
WillBeginDelayRequest allows our app
to update or cancel our URL request.
For example, if it's been a long time
since we initiated our request,
we might substitute the latest
cached location from Core Location
for the one we specified
when we first made the request.
DidReceiveChallenge allows our app to
respond to any authentication challenges
that may occur.
Our delegate will receive
SessionDidFinishEvents
when all events have been delivered,
so this is when we'll call
our completion handler.
You might be tempted
to schedule a new task at this point,
but don't, as the current task
hasn't been fully completed.
Instead, just mark this task as completed.
The guidelines are the same
as for Background App Refresh.
Your app should avoid
expensive processing,
and make sure to set the task completed
within 15 seconds of when it was received.
Background URLSessions are great
for retrieving data from remote servers.
They can be scheduled, revised
or canceled as needed.
The last mechanism we'll look at today
are complication pushes.
Depending on the use case,
pushes can be more efficient
than pulling servers for data.
This is especially true
for event-driven data.
We'll use complication pushes
to provide data for our last complication,
which keeps track of encouragement
from fellow kite flyers.
Servers can send up to 50 complication
pushes per day to each individual Watch.
Complication pushes
don't need to be regularly spaced.
If the data are bursty,
requests can be sent more rapidly
than with the other mechanisms
we discussed.
Throttling may be necessary
to prevent exceeding the daily cap.
The server sending the pushes to the Watch
needs to have a proper certificate,
so let's take a quick look
at how to set that up.
First we need an identifier
that includes your app's bundle ID
and ends in .watchkitapp.complication.
This is crucial.
If the app identifier
isn't in the correct format,
your push may be rejected by Apple servers
or may not be received on the Watch.
Once the .complication app identifier
has been created,
use that to create an Apple
Push Notification service SSL Certificate.
Your server will use that certificate
to authenticate
to Apple's push notification servers.
Your app also needs
the remote notification background mode
and the push notifications capabilities
in its WatchKit extension.
With our Watch app,
we'll use our PushNotificationProvider
to register it with PushKit.
When the registration succeeds,
the app receives credentials.
Upload these credentials to your server
so your server can communicate
with the Watch.
Here's our PushNotificationProvider.
It is a PKPushRegistryDelegate.
It creates a PKPushRegistry instance
and provides the main queue for callbacks.
It sets itself as a delegate.
It also sets the desiredPushType
to .complication,
which matches the .complication identifier
and certificate we created
and installed on our server.
When registration is complete,
registry returns credentials
and the didUpdate pushCredentials call.
We send these credentials to our server
so they can communicate
with this instance of the app.
Once the Watch uploads its credentials
to the server,
the server uses those credentials to send
pushes for that Watch to Apple servers,
which will then deliver them to the Watch.
As we said earlier, 50 of these
are allowed per Watch per day.
When sending a complication push,
format as you would any background push
providing the content-available entry
in the aps dictionary.
After the push is received
by PushKit on the Watch...
it is passed to our app with
didReceiveIncomingPushWithPayload.
A completion handler is provided
for after call
when it has finished processing the push.
Back to the implementation
of our PushNotificationProvider.
When a push is available, our app will be
resumed or launched, if it's not active.
At that time, the
didReceiveIncomingPush payload for type
will be called on our delegate.
The queue we specify
when registering with PushKit
is used to make this call.
In our case, that's the main queue.
The completion handler is provided.
It must be called
when the payload has been processed.
Process the payload
and call our extension delegate
to update our complications.
Here we're updating all complications.
If this were a shipping app,
we'd want to update
only the complications that need it.
That's it for complication pushes.
To wrap up, each instance of an app
can receive up to 50 per day.
That number doesn't change when an app
has multiple active complications.
The guidelines are the same as they are
for other types of background updates.
To summarize the techniques
we discussed today,
use foreground opportunities, when active,
to update your complications.
Do this especially when the app's state
changes in response to input
or if your app pulls data from a server
while it's in the foreground.
Apps can use a ProcessInfo activity
to complete work when your app moves
from the foreground to the background.
Background App Refresh
is great to schedule runtime
for accessing your own data or using
the watchOS APIs such as HealthKit.
Apps can use background refresh
to update its complications
up to four times per hour.
Background URLSession tasks
can be scheduled to pull data from servers
up to four times per hour.
Remember to always reattach your delegate
when your app is activated
so that it can receive updates
that might be pending.
Push notifications can be sent
from your servers to each Watch
up to 50 times per day.
Space them at regular intervals
or send them more frequently
if the data are bursty.
The 51st and later notifications
will be ignored,
so apply throttling on the server
as needed.
Use these mechanisms individually
or combine them as needed.
You can see how important it is
to keep your complications up to date.
There are multiple mechanisms
at your disposal
to allow you
to keep your complications up to date
even when the app isn't active.
Mix and match
the techniques we've discussed
to deliver the best possible experience.
All the mechanisms we discussed today
can be used with independent Watch apps
to give your app
the greatest possible flexibility.
The "Meet Watch Face Sharing" video
from earlier this week
discusses the new multiple
complication APIs in greater detail.
"Build Complications in SwiftUI"
describes how to build
beautiful complications using SwiftUI.
Lastly, there's a great video on "Creating
Independent Watch Apps" from last year.
Check all of these out.
Thank you, and I can't wait to see
the magical complications you build
using these techniques.
Have a great WWDC.