Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Tori, and I'll also be presenting
with my colleague, Ross,
who you'll hear from later today.
I'm so excited to share with you what
we have new for you with in-app purchases.
And we have a lot to cover today.
This session will be divided
into two sections.
I'll focus on covering
what's new on the server side,
and later I'll hand it off to Ross
to cover StoreKit updates.
So let's get started
with our server updates.
On the server side,
first, we'll cover refunds
and how you can handle transactions
that are refunded.
Next, we'll cover some new ways
to help you manage the subscription status
for your customers
and how you can use
App Store Server Notifications
to get notified and respond
to various subscription billing events.
We'll also cover the different scenarios
where you may still need to use
verifyReceipt to get the latest status.
And finally,
we'll dive into Family Sharing.
We have a lot to cover,
so let's get dive right in with arguably
what brought us all here today:
an in-app purchase.
So this is an in-app purchase
in one of my apps.
I'm so excited to use this,
but what happens if I change my mind?
If I have an issue with the content
and call Apple to request a refund,
what should you, as a developer, do?
That's why handling refunds
is so important,
but keep in mind
that while it's important,
it only affects
a small percentage of transactions.
However, proper refund management
could drive that percentage down.
So let's dive into that now by walking
through a typical refund scenario.
First a customer purchases some content
in an app, like 100 gems.
However, the purchase was an accident,
so they call Apple for support.
After considering their case,
we issue a refund.
Later, the customer contacts you
for support
as they notice they still have
the gems that were refunded.
If you don't know that Apple
has refunded the content,
it's difficult to determine
how to respond.
It would be so much better
if you could easily determine
if we had already refunded that purchase
so you could take action appropriately,
such as acknowledging the refund
but letting the customer keep their gems,
or deducting their balance.
That's why we're working
to bring you new ways
to manage refunds for your content.
Having the ability to manage your refunded
purchases is important for many reasons.
Most importantly it gives you control
to take action as you see fit,
such as messaging the customer,
or even taking back the content if needed.
It also lets you handle
any potential abuse of your content,
such as customers trying
to keep their content
after receiving a refund from Apple,
and you can resolve customer issues
like the previous one swiftly.
This will also allow you to manage
your in-game economy,
making gameplay more fair for all players
as there will be repercussions
for refunds.
So for all of these reasons,
and because we want you
to be able to manage refunds
for purchases in your app,
we're bringing you
a brand-new App Store Server Notification
and our first ever notification
for content types
other than auto-renewable subscriptions,
the refund notification.
So why did we decide on
an App Store Server Notification for this?
Well, the primary reason is that
you don't have to ask us for information.
We'll just tell you.
You're notified immediately with
a JSON POST upon a status change,
and we even retry up to three times
if we don't get an HTTP OK back from you.
If you're already receiving
App Store Server Notifications
for auto-renewing subscriptions,
then you'll get the new refund
notification for your other content types
with little additional work on your end.
We'll also send you
an updated unified receipt
with your canceled transactions included
so you can update your records.
And this solution is also scalable
as you grow your business on our platform.
So our goal for all content types is
to allow you to obtain information
about refunded purchases
through App Store Server Notifications.
For consumables, non-consumables
and non-renewing subscriptions,
you'll receive
the brand-new refund notification.
For subscriptions, you'll continue
to receive the cancel notification.
Enabling App Store Server Notifications
is straightforward
if you've never done it before
and can be done in a few steps.
First, set up your desired endpoint for
your notifications in App Store Connect.
Next, make sure your endpoint
meets App Transport Security requirements
as outlined
in the developer documentation.
Then you're all set
to start receiving notifications.
So in App Store Connect,
just navigate to your app's page
and find the URL for
App Store Server Notifications section.
Enter your desired endpoint here so
we know where to send your notifications.
Know that if your endpoint already
meets security requirements,
you'll immediately
start receiving notifications.
Now let's take a deeper look
at the refund notification.
We'll send you this notification
when any consumable, non-consumable
or non-renewing subscription
is refunded for your app
after we issue a refund to the customer
for that purchase.
Getting notified in this way
makes it easy for you
to take immediate action
on your refunded content.
This notification has also been
implemented in a privacy-friendly way,
as we're not giving you any information
about the customer,
only information you'd already have
about the purchase.
The refund notification is live today,
so if you're already receiving
App Store Server Notifications,
make sure you're looking for it.
With that in mind,
when you receive this notification,
there are a few things I want you
to look out for in the payload.
You should look for
the original_transaction_id
to tell you which transaction
we've refunded,
the cancellation_date
to know when we refunded it,
and the cancellation_reason.
The reason can have values of 0 or 1,
and a value of 1 can indicate
the customer requested a refund
due to an issue within the app,
which you could then investigate.
Also look for the bid and the product_id
to verify the app and product
you've received a notification for.
All these fields can be found
in the unified_receipt object
in the App Store Server Notification
payload
in the latest_receipt_info section,
except for the bid, which is found
at the top level of the payload.
So what does the App Store
Server Notification look like?
Well, it looks something like this.
Not all the fields are listed here,
but we have explanations for all possible
fields in the developer documentation.
Right now let's take a look at the ones
we just discussed, plus a few others.
In addition to
those transaction identifying fields,
look for the password in the payload.
This is a shared secret for your app,
which you can find in App Store Connect,
and it allows you to verify the payload is
from Apple and is trustworthy.
At the same level as the password,
you'll find the bundle identifier.
You can verify this field to know
which app you've received a refund for.
Next, look in the unified_receipt object,
specifically in
the latest_receipt_info array,
for information about
your refunded transactions.
This array contains
the 100 latest transactions for your app
and the four fields
we told you to look for:
the cancellation_date,
the cancellation_reason,
the original_transaction_id
and the product_id.
So let's revisit our refund scenario
from earlier
and look at how the refund notification
can now help you
in a slightly different situation.
In this situation,
the customer still buys 100 gems,
but then consumes the gems and still asks
Apple for support with their purchase.
Once again, we make a decision to honor
or deny the refund.
Because we don't know
if the customer has consumed the gems,
we may still honor the refund,
and if we do,
we'll send you a refund notification.
Then, if the customer reaches out to you
asking for further support,
such as in-game compensation,
but now you'll know
the purchase has been refunded
and you can choose
to take proactive action,
such as providing an in-app message
in your app.
A message such as this is great
as it notifies the customer
that you've observed a refund
for their purchase,
the action you've taken,
and what they can do
to regain access to the content.
In-app messaging is just
one of many actions
you can take upon observing a refund.
Let's take a quick look at those now.
So there are many actions you can take
depending on the content type,
ranging from moderate to severe.
For all content types, you can use this
for refund monitoring,
for in-app messaging
and restricting access
to the refunded purchase.
Because we're sending you
a server-to-server notification,
this gives you the ability to restrict
access cross-platform if needed.
In the case of consumables,
there are additional actions you can take,
like deducting
the in-app currency balance.
You, as a developer, are responsible for
making decisions on what measures to take
and how to implement them.
So think carefully about
which action you decide to take
in order to promote a healthy community
within your app.
So now we've covered a lot about refunds
and how to handle them appropriately.
So now let's switch gears
and jump into how we are making it easier
for you to manage subscriptions,
first taking a look at some of the key
events in the subscription life cycle.
These include acquiring a subscriber
for the first time,
any auto-renew,
successful or unsuccessful,
disabling or enabling auto-renew,
upgrades or downgrades and cancellations.
So what do all these events look like
for a customer and for you?
So when the customer first subscribes,
we establish the subscription period
and a fixed auto-renew period
to repeat renewal after renewal.
Within the first subscription period,
your customer decides
to turn off auto-renew,
thinking that they just aren't using
the subscription enough,
but later turns it back on after a little
more time with their subscription.
After that, we approach
our first scheduled auto-renew,
but there's an auto-renew failure
due to a billing issue.
At this point, we'll try to auto-renew
for the duration
of the billing retry period,
also establishing a grace period.
Luckily the subscription is recovered
during our grace period,
so the renewal cycle remains the same.
Shortly thereafter, your customer decides
they're enjoying the subscription so much
that they want to upgrade.
For an upgrade, we start the customer
at the higher tier immediately,
shifting our upcoming renewals.
Later, after not using the higher tier
as much as expected,
your customer decides to downgrade
back to a more basic tier.
Downgrades take place at the end
of the subscription period,
so your customer will have access
to the higher tier of service
until their next scheduled auto-renew.
So how can you keep track of all of these
important events for your subscriptions?
What we recommend is using App Store
Server Notifications for status updates.
This is a push approach,
meaning you don't ask us for information,
we'll just tell you
when something happens,
and we do.
We notify you when the status
of one of your subscriptions changes,
providing you with a new receipt
for your records at that time,
but only when you need it.
This solution is also more scalable
as you acquire more subscribers.
So let's dive into
our App Store Server Notifications now
to see what we offer
and to learn a little more about them.
When you start receiving App Store Server
Notifications, or if you are already are,
this is the payload you can expect to see.
Note that this a subset of possible fields
and not all of these may be present
all the time.
There's a lot of information here,
so I want to focus on some of
the key components.
When you receive this payload,
first look for the auto_renew_product_id
to see exactly which product
the notification applies to
and the product we plan
to auto-renew next.
Then check the notification_type.
This will tell you the type of event
you are receiving.
You should also verify the value in the
password field matches your shared secret,
so you know the content comes directly
from Apple and is trustworthy.
You should also look
for the bundle identifier.
This will tell you which of your apps
you've received a notification for.
Then you want to look for
the unified_receipt.
This object mimics the response
from verifyReceipt,
so if you're already using verifyReceipt,
this should be familiar.
The latest_receipt
in the unified_receipt object
gives you an updated app receipt
for this customer for your app.
The latest_receipt_info array contains
the 100 latest transactions for your app.
You can search here
by the original_transaction id
to know which subscriptions are active
for this customer.
Finally look at
the pending_renewal_info array
to find the upcoming renewal info
for each subscription
the customer uses in your app.
Now let's quickly revisit
the notification_type field.
We'll send you notifications
for several events,
and the notification_type field can have
the following possible values:
INITIAL_BUY,
when a customer first subscribes,
INTERACTIVE_RENEWAL, when a customer
upgrades or renews their subscription
in your app
or through Manage Subscriptions...
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS, when
a customer changes their renewal status,
such as toggling auto-renew on or off,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_PREF,
when a customer makes a change
that takes place at the end
of the subscription period,
such as a downgrade,
CANCEL,
when a customer calls Apple Support,
and we issue a refund to them
for their subscription
or for an upgrade as we cancel
the previous lower-tier subscription,
DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW,
when we fail to auto-renew as scheduled
due to a billing issue,
and DID_RECOVER, when we recover billing
of the subscription
in the billing retry period
or grace period.
For more information
on these notifications
and when you can expect to observe them,
see our WWDC 2019 session,
"In-App Purchases
and Using Server-to-Server Notifications."
To learn more about which notifications
are available to you in SandBox,
check out this year's session
"Introducing StoreKit Testing in Xcode."
So if we go back to our timeline
from earlier,
we have notifications to cover
almost all of these events.
INITIAL_BUY, for the purchase
of the subscription,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS
for disabling and enabling auto-renew,
DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW for the renewal failure,
DID_RECOVER for the billing recovery,
INTERACTIVE_RENEWAL for the upgrade,
plus a CANCEL
for the previous lower-tier subscription,
and DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_PREF
for the downgrade.
So with App Store Server Notifications,
you can easily monitor
your subscription events.
But we decided we could make this
just a little bit better,
which is why this year we're bringing you
an App Store Server Notification
for every successful auto-renew.
This is a new notification type,
which we're calling "DID_RENEW."
Coming later this year,
we'll send you this notification
after every single successful auto-renew,
every time.
Like all the other notifications,
it contains the unified receipt,
which gives you
all the information you need
to identify the subscription
that was renewed.
This includes the original_transaction_id,
which is a unique identifier
for the subscription,
the transaction_id, a unique identifier
for the new subscription period,
the expiration date of the new period,
and the auto_renew_product_id
to tell you exactly
which product was auto-renewed.
So jumping back to our timeline,
notice that the addition of the DID_RENEW
notification completes our events,
bringing you everything you need
to monitor your subscriptions
in App Store Server Notifications.
However, in addition
to this new notification,
we thought there was
a little more information you might need
concerning your subscriptions.
We think you should know
if one of your customers
has decided to apply a subscription offer
before we renew the subscription
with that offer.
That's why we've added
the promotional_offer_id
to the pending_renewal_info section.
This will be available
through verifyReceipt
and in the App Store Server Notification
in the pending renewal info array,
so you'll know if there are
any pending offers for that subscription.
This feature is live
in the pending_renewal_info section today,
so be sure you're looking for it.
For more information
on using subscription offers,
see our WWDC 2019 session,
"Subscription Offers Best Practices."
So now that we have
a DID_RENEW notification
and the promotional_offer_id
in the pending_renewal_info,
what should you do with
this new information?
Most importantly this allows you
to rely on App Store Server Notifications
for updates,
eliminating the need
to poll verifyReceipt.
However, you should still use
verifyReceipt for a few key use cases.
If you experience
an outage on your server,
the next time one of
your customers comes online
you can call verifyReceipt
to check their status,
making up for any missed updates.
In this way,
verifyReceipt offers a recovery mode.
Second, you can use verifyReceipt
to immediately determine entitlements
for a customer.
To learn more about
determining entitlements,
tune into this year's
"Architecting for Subscriptions" session.
Finally, you can use verifyReceipt
to verify a successful auto-renew.
So what do we mean by using verifyReceipt
to verify a successful auto-renew?
Because auto-renew is so critical,
you want to ensure
that you get the update.
For this reason, approach marking
an auto-renew through a double check.
First, subscribe to
our App Store Server Notifications
so you receive the DID_RENEW notification
in addition
to our other notification types.
Second, schedule a call to verifyReceipt
for your subscription
shortly after its scheduled
expiration date.
When you receive
the DID_RENEW notification as expected,
you can cancel this job,
but if there is a delay,
you can fallback to verifyReceipt
to verify a successful auto-renew.
So we just covered a lot about App Store
Server Notifications and subscriptions.
Now I'd like to discuss a new feature
for App Store subscriptions.
One of the things customers love most
about subscriptions
like News+ or Apple Arcade
is that they can be shared
with their family members.
Well, we're very excited to announce
that this year
the App Store will support Family Sharing
for in-app purchases,
which will allow up to
five additional family members
to share a single purchase.
Family Sharing works for both
auto-renewable subscriptions
and non-consumable in-app purchases
like those that are used to offer
a full-feature unlock.
Customers will choose
which in-app purchases
they'd like to share with their family.
We're so excited about
what this means for developers
and your ability to engage millions
of family members that are already set up.
Because the use of family
is so widely adopted,
Family Sharing for in-app purchases
can help increase customer engagement
and improve retention for your app.
To begin, you can visit App Store Connect
to turn on Family Sharing
for a specific product.
You can navigate to your app's page,
and select "Turn On"
in the Family Sharing section.
Note that once you turn on Family Sharing
for a product, you cannot turn it off.
Let's review how customers will manage
their shared purchases.
When new customers subscribe,
the subscription will be shared
by default.
Subscribers can turn off sharing later
for their family
on the Manage Subscriptions page.
For existing purchasers,
they'll be notified if one of
their subscriptions becomes shareable.
Then, they can manage
their sharing preference
from the same Manage Subscriptions page.
For non-consumables, all purchases
will be shared with the family
if the customer has turned on
"Share Purchases with Family" in Settings.
So what do you need to do in your app
so family members can enjoy access
to the shared purchase?
With this feature,
not only are we creating
a transaction for the purchaser,
we're also creating a transaction
for each family member.
So when a family member opens the app,
they will have a transaction available
in the transaction queue,
for each of their devices.
And there will be a unique receipt
for each family member
that will contain shared transactions
in the latest receipt info array.
You should keep track of the original_
transaction_id for each family member
as you already would
for your subscriptions.
Note that this only applies
to new purchases
made after sharing is enabled.
For non-consumable purchases
made before sharing was enabled,
you'll still have to restore purchases
for these to be available
to all family members.
So let's get an idea of
what this looks like for new purchasers.
After you've enabled Family Sharing
in App Store Connect,
when a family member makes
a shareable purchase,
not only do we put a transaction in
the transaction queue for their devices,
we also put a transaction
in the transaction queue
for every member of their family
for all of their devices.
So when their family members
open up your app later,
you can unlock access to the subscription
or non-consumable instantly.
It's like magic,
and it makes it so easy for you
to reach more developers than ever before.
Before moving on,
let's quickly review what this looks like
for both new and existing subscribers
for both subscriptions
and non-consumables.
So, for new purchasers,
any shareable subscription they purchase
is shared with their family by default.
Any sharable non-consumable
they purchase is shared with their family,
if they have purchase sharing enabled
in iCloud
if the family is sharing payment,
and if the app is not hidden
from their purchase history.
For existing purchasers,
for a sharable subscription
to be shared with their family,
they must opt-in
from the managed subscriptions page.
For existing non-consumables to be shared,
the same three conditions must be met,
and you have to restore purchases
to unlock the content
for the family member.
To manage access for all family members,
you'll need to use the receipt.
You can get an updated receipt
from verifyReceipt
or from App Store Server Notifications.
Additionally, whenever the customer opens
the app,
you can refresh the receipt on device
to verify access for each customer.
But I'm getting ahead of myself here.
So with that, I'll hand off
to my colleague Ross
who will talk to you more
about Family Sharing within StoreKit.
Thanks, Tori.
So let's take a look at how Family Sharing
and App Purchases works within your app.
First off, how can your app tell
if a product supports Family Sharing?
Well, we've added a handy new property
on SKProduct called isFamilyShareable.
It's as easy to use
as requesting a product information
from the app store,
and then checking the isFamilyShareable
Boolean.
You can use this
to programmatically display to customers
that one of your products
is Family Sharable,
and not have to hard code any logic.
So now one of your customers has seen
this Family Sharable product,
and taps to purchase it.
What happens next?
Well, when a customer purchases
a Family Sharable in-app purchase,
everything begins as normal.
Your app uses StoreKit
to send the purchase to the app store,
and then you get a transaction back
in the purchase state.
The next time their family members
open your app...
each of the family members
will get a transaction
that looks just like a restored purchase.
So your existing app logic should be able
to handle it with no additional coding.
Now, Tori mentioned that customers
can also enable and disable sharing
for specific products.
When a customer enables Family Sharing
for a product,
something similar to a purchase happens.
Their family's devices
will all get a transaction
that looks just like a restored purchase.
So again, your app should be able
to handle it with no additional coding.
But what about the opposite case?
What about when a customer disables
Family Sharing?
Well, normally non-consumables
are permanent,
and auto-renewable subscriptions
only end when they expire.
But when a customer
disables Family Sharing,
they expect access
to be halted immediately.
So for this case, we've added a new API.
It's a new method on
the SKPaymentTransactionReserver protocol
called paymentQueue didRevoke
EntitlementsForProductIdentifiers.
When a customer disables Family Sharing,
StoreKit will automatically update
your receipt, and then call this method.
Inside the method, you should be prepared
to verify the receipt, whether locally,
or by uploading it to your server
and using the verifyReceipt endpoint.
Products that have been revoked
will no longer be present in the receipt.
Now, you should make sure that you're not
simply looking at the product identifiers
in the array and revoking access
based on that.
Depending on the set up of your products,
and other products the customer
may have purchased,
they may still be entitled to some access
that overlapped the revoked purchase.
So we added this API to handle
a couple of new situations
that occur due to Family Sharing.
As I mentioned,
it will be called when a purchaser
disables Family Sharing for a product.
It will also be called
if a customer leaves a family group
that was sharing a purchase.
And we've also taken this opportunity
to add support for refunds.
If a customer receives a refund
for a non-consumable,
or an auto-renewable subscription,
StoreKit will call this method,
and you may revoke access immediately.
And that wraps up Family Sharing,
which we think users will love,
and will give you new opportunities
to increase value to your customers,
and improve engagement and retention.
Now, I'm going to give you a tour
of some of the other improvements
and features we've added to StoreKit,
and what to look forward to
in the latest releases.
First, I'll start with a couple things
we already shipped since WWDC last year.
We have in-app purchase on Apple Watch,
and improvements
to our subscription price increase flow.
Then, I'll move on to what's new,
including SKOverlay,
and improvements to SKAdNetwork.
So this first one is especially for
all you Apple Watch developers out there.
As of watchOS 6.2 earlier this year,
we've added StoreKit and in-app purchases
to watchOS.
This means that for apps
your customers use mostly on the watch,
you can offer in-app purchases directly
in the watchOS interface,
your customers are already using.
Using StoreKit on watchOS
is almost exactly the same as using it
on any other platform.
You can observe the payment queue,
request products,
and add them to the payment queue
the same as you do in other platforms.
When it comes to verifying the receipt,
you can, of course, continue to use
server-to-server validation.
However, if you prefer
to do local validation,
there's just one difference
you should be aware of.
When you're retrieving
the deviceIdentifier,
instead of UIDevice, you need to use
the WKInterfaceDevice API.
Here's an example of some code
that runs on both iOS and watchOS.
Once you've retrieved
the deviceIdentifier,
everything else is the same.
Use that deviceIdentifier along
with the opaque value in the receipt,
to create a hash.
Then make sure that hash
matches the one in the receipt.
And that's all you need to know to add
in-app purchases to your watchOS app.
Another feature we rolled out in iOS 13.3
is an improvement to handling
subscription price increases.
A subscription price increase occurs when
you have an existing subscription product
you want to charge more for.
Setting up a price increase is easy.
You just go into app store connect
and change the price.
But you can't just bump up the price
of an auto-renewable subscription
without telling your customers.
That's why the app store requires
each customer to agree to the new price.
You should note that if you decrease
the price of a subscription,
customers don't have to take any action,
and they'll get
the new price automatically.
Now, unfortunately, this process
of informing the customer,
and asking them to agree to the new price
can result in churn.
Churn is when customers
stop using your product,
and are no longer paying for it.
And I know you're thinking,
"Well, of course,
customers don't want to pay more."
But actually we've found,
in a lot of cases, that's not the issue.
Customers can sometimes miss the e-mails
that the app store sends...
or perhaps they don't want to engage
in the price increase flow at that time.
And sometimes they put it off until later
and simply forget.
Additionally, customers might not
be informed
of additional value that you're providing.
For example, if you run a video service,
and you've added new content.
So for users experiencing a price increase
who are using your app,
we've implemented an automatic in-app
price increase consent sheet.
After you initiate a price increase
in app store connect,
any affected customers will see
this app store UI when opening your app.
This way, customers are informed,
and can agree
to continue their subscription
at the time they're using the app,
which presumably means
they're finding value in your products.
Once they agree, or dismiss the sheet,
your app's UI's underneath it
and continues as normal.
Now, we realize that not all apps
will want to display the sheet
immediately upon opening.
So we've added some tools
to allow you to control the flow.
First, you'll want to implement
this new SKPaymentQueue delegate method.
StoreKit will always call this method
before presenting the price consent sheet.
Inside the method,
it's up to you to determine
if you want to show a sheet now,
and then return "True" if you do,
and "False" if you don't.
Now, if you return "False" here,
you're going to want a way
to show the sheet later
at a time that's more opportune,
perhaps after you've educated the customer
about additional value you're providing.
To do that, simply call this other
new StoreKit API.
SKPaymentQueue
.showPriceConsentIfNeeded.
Now, you should only call this
if you previously returned "False"
to the method above.
However, if you do call it, and there's
no pending price increase, don't worry.
StoreKit will always check to make sure
there is a pending price increase
for the customer before showing the sheet.
And it won't show it at all
if there isn't.
Next, I'm happy to introduce
an entirely new API
in the latest iOS release.
It's called SKOverlay,
and it's a sleek new UI element
for displaying and promoting apps.
Take a look.
SKOverlay presents a floating view
at the bottom of your UI
that displays information about an app.
It's similar to
the SKStoreProductViewController class
that exists in StoreKit today,
except SKOverlay was designed
to work seamlessly with your app's UI.
Additionally,
unlike SKStoreProductViewController,
SKOverlay is only used to display apps.
SKOverlay was also designed
to work seamlessly with your app clips
in order to help you transition users
from your app clip to your full app.
But that's not all it's used for.
You're entirely able to use it
within your full apps as well.
Simply enter the app ID
of the app you want to display,
and customers can install it directly
from the overlay.
If you're interested in learning more
about our new app clips feature,
I highly recommend checking out
the "Exploring App Clips" session
as well as the "Streamline Your App Clips"
session,
both in this year's WWDC.
So now, let's dive into the SKOverlay APIs
and see how you can best integrate
SKOverlay into your app.
Creating and presenting an SKOverlay
is fairly straightforward.
First, you initialize it
using an SKOverlay configuration object.
We'll get back
into that configuration object later,
but it essentially allows you
to set up the details of the overlay.
Then, you call the present method,
passing in the WindowScene
where you want the overlay to appear.
That's all you need to do
to create and present an SKOverlay.
Of course, we've also added lots
of other tools
to allow you to customize
the overlay flow.
First, there's a dismiss function
that allows you to manually dismiss
the overlay.
You'll notice that this dismiss function
is a class function,
and it doesn't take an overlay
as an argument,
but rather another UIWindowScene.
That's because only one overlay
can be displayed in a scene at a time.
And doing it this way,
allows you to remove any overlays
that may be on a scene
even if your current code context
doesn't have access
to the specific overlay object.
SKOverlay also has a delegate.
As you'd expect,
this delegate allows you to react
to changes in the overlay's status.
We'll see the details of that later.
And finally,
SKOverlay has a configuration object.
This allows you to see the configuration
that was used to set it up.
Now that we've come back around
to the configuration,
let's take a look at those two objects.
SKOverlay's actually comprised
of two classes.
The first
is called AppClipConfiguration.
This configuration is used
to transition users
from your app clip to your full app.
The app clip configuration
can only display the full app
for the current app clip the overlay
is displayed in.
The next class is the AppConfiguration.
And this configuration can be used
to display any app that--
Much of these two classes is the same,
so let's start there.
Both classes have a campaign token
and a provider token
so that you can use SKOverlay
with the app analytics.
They also have functions that allow you
to set and get arbitrary key values.
Now, most developers won't need
to use these,
but they're there so that you can
integrate SKOverlay
with other StoreKit APIs,
such as SKAdNetwork.
Both classes also have
the position property.
While SKOverlay always appears
at the bottom of your screen,
apps that use tab bars will want
to choose the bottomRaised property,
so that the overlay appears
just above the tab bar,
rather than on top of it.
In addition to these properties
and functions,
the app configuration also offers
two additional properties on top of these.
The first is the appIdentifier.
You can use this to enter
the iTunes identifier
of the app you wish to display.
The app clip configuration
doesn't have this property
because, as I mentioned before,
that configuration is only used
for displaying the full app
of the current app clip the overlay is in.
And the app configuration also has
a userDismissable Boolean.
This is set to "True" by default,
which means that the user will be able
to swipe down in the overlay
to dismiss it from the screen.
If you set this to "False",
the user will not be able
to swipe down on it,
and the overlay will only go away when
you call the dismiss function manually.
That's it for the configuration.
So let's move on to the delegate.
The first delegate method is simply
an error handler.
If you try to present an overlay
and an unexpected error occurs,
it will call this delegate method,
passing in the overlay,
and a specific error as an argument.
The rest of the delegate methods
are all revolving around animating
of the overlay.
You can see there's a method
for the start and end of the presentation,
as well as the start and end
of the dismissal.
You can also see
that each of these methods
includes an SKOverlay.TransitionContext
object.
That's because these methods are used
to help you coordinate
your UI animations alongside the overlay.
Let's walk through how you might present
an overlay,
and use these APIs
to coordinate animations.
Here, we're creating and presenting
an SKOverlay inside our app clip.
First, we grab the current WindowScene.
And then,
we create an app clip configuration
using the bottom position.
We'll then initialize an overlay
using that configuration object.
And we'll set it to delegate.
Finally, we present the overlay
in that scene.
And this is all you need to do
to use SKOverlay in your app or app clip.
If we want to animate our own UI
alongside the overlay,
we can do so using the delegate methods.
First, we can set up any initial state
for our UI elements
directly inside the delegate method.
And these delegate methods are always
called in the main queue,
so you can manipulate UI
right inside them.
Then, we add any animations we want
inside an animation block
on the transition context.
Again, simply declare any changes
in animatable properties here.
There's no need to use a UIView
animate block
since any code inside this block
will be animated for you by the overlay.
Whether you're optimizing your app clip
or promoting other apps
inside your own app,
SKOverlay's a great option for
a seamless integration and a beautiful UI.
Finally, I'd like to share with you
some updates about our SKAdNetwork API.
Introduced in iOS 11.3,
SKAdNetwork allows ad networks
to measure the effectiveness of their ads
while still respecting customer privacy.
In the latest iOS release,
we've made it even more powerful,
while still not compromising
the customer privacy.
Let's start with an overview
of SKAdNetwork.
SKAdNetwork involves three stakeholders,
ad networks, source apps,
and advertising apps.
Each stakeholder has a role
in making the feature work.
Ad Networks places ads within apps,
and receive postbacks when the ads
results in conversions.
Source Apps display the ads
that are sent to them by the ad networks.
And advertising apps are the ones
that appear in the ads,
and then submit the postback
to SKAdNetwork once they're opened.
Let's take a closer look at this flow
from start to finish.
First, the ad network
places the SKAdNetwork data
inside an ad for the advertising app,
which we'll call app B.
Then, it displays this ad
in the source app,
which we can call app A.
Once the user taps the ad,
installs app B, and then opens it,
app B should call another SKAdNetwork API
in order to initialize the postback.
Calling this API will set a timer...
and once that timer expires,
the user's device will send a postback
back to the ad network's URL.
Ad networks should use Apple's public key
to verify the data in the postback
and make sure it's legitimate.
So that first bundle of data
that the ad network sends up
when displaying an ad looks like this.
It contains the ad network ID,
which has been registered with Apple,
and a campaign ID from 1 to 100,
which ad networks can use
to measure their campaign effectiveness.
It contains the ID of the advertising app,
the one that's displayed in the ad.
And has a timestamp.
This timestamp should be generated
at the time the ad is displayed,
because timestamps that are too old
will cause the ad data to be rejected.
The nonce is just a random view ID,
used to ensure that each ad impression
is unique, and to prevent double counting.
And finally, the signature is generated
using all of the other pieces of data
in this bundle
to ensure that only your ad network
can start ads using your ad network ID.
In the latest iOS release,
we're requiring two new pieces of data.
The first is the version,
which is now 2.0.
And the second is the Source App ID.
This is the ID of the app
that's displaying the ad.
Next, the postback API should be called
by the advertising app,
app B, upon the first launch of their app.
This method generates a postback,
which is the cryptographically signed data
validating that a user installed
and launched this app
after seeing the ad.
The first call to this API
starts the postback process
if the device has attribution data
for the app.
And subsequent calls have no effect.
Starting in the latest iOS,
advertising apps will be able to call
the updateConversionValue API
if they choose.
This allows the app to add
an additional six-bit value
that represents some action
that took place in the app.
For example, let's say you wanted to know
whether a user purchased an item
in your app
before you count the conversion.
In this case,
you can call updateConversionValue
and include a value that you mapped
purchasing an item.
Since the conversion value
is chosen at runtime,
we can't sign it on the app store server,
so it's the only piece of the postback
that isn't protected with cryptography.
The value itself is an integer
between zero and 63,
which may represent actions such as
making a purchase,
signing up for a free trial,
or completing a level.
Apps can call this API multiple times
to update the conversion value.
However, only values that are higher
than the previous value
will be accepted.
Values that are lower than
the currently stored value
will simply be ignored.
This means you don't have to worry about
accidentally overwriting
your conversion value with a lower value.
Now, let's see the details of the postback
that StoreKit sends to the ad network
once the process is complete.
We'll send up the ad network ID
and the campaign ID
that were used in the ad,
as well as the ID of the advertising app,
app B.
A transaction ID
is another unique identifier
you can use to make sure
you aren't double counting conversions.
And you can use Apple's public key
to verify the signature
to know that it's all legitimate.
In the latest iOS,
we've added new information
to the postback too.
First, we've added the version.
We've also added a key
called "redownload,"
which will indicate whether
this was the first time
the customer purchased the app,
or if they previously purchased it
and are installing it again.
Prior to this, SKAdNetwork only worked
for the first purchase of an app.
So adding redownloads will give you
a lot more insight
into the effectiveness of your ads.
Furthermore, in the latest iOS,
we've added two new optional items
in the postback.
The first is the ID of the source app,
so that you can know which app displayed
the ad that resulted in the conversion.
And the second is the conversion value
that was chosen by the advertising app.
It's important to note
that these last two pieces of data
won't always show up in the postback.
In order to preserve customer privacy,
the app store servers do calculations
to make sure that sharing these values
won't allow the postback to be linked
to the customer that generated it.
So we'll share them when we can,
but your server should be ready
to handle the postbacks
both with and without them.
So how do you get started?
If you're interested in using SKAdNetwork
as an ad network,
you'll need to sign up with Apple
so we can register your information.
You should enroll in the developer program
as an organization,
and then fill out the form
to request access to SKAdNetwork.
We'll then send you instructions on how
to generate a public-private key pair,
and you'll send us the URL
you want postbacks to be sent to
along with your public key.
Remember, never send your private key.
Always keep that secure.
Then, you're registered and ready
to begin using SKAdNetwork.
If you're a source app,
and you want to work with an ad network,
ask them for their ad network ID,
and put it into your Info.plist file.
This will make sure StoreKit knows
to accept the ad data
when you display an ad in your app.
And finally, if you're an advertising app,
and you want to measure
the conversion of your ads,
make sure to configure your app
so that it initializes the postback
when it first launches.
Today we've covered lots of information
on best practices and new features,
in both server-to-server
and customer device environments.
You can now take advantage
of new server-to-server notifications
for refunded purchases.
And we saw how you can use
subscription notifications
to get the latest information
without needing to poll
the verifyReceipt endpoint.
We introduced our brand-new way
to share in-app purchases
among family members,
giving you a new tool to increase value
and engagement with your customers.
On the client side,
you can now offer in-app purchases
directly inside your watchOS apps.
And subscription developers will benefit
from our new, improved
subscription price increase flow.
We got into the details
of our new SKOverlay API
for promoting apps,
including using inside app clips.
And finally, we explained
how our SKAdNetwork API
can help advertisers gather
and use conversion data
without compromising on customer privacy.
We think these tools will help you
continue to grow your business
with in-app purchases.
For more information,
please join us on the forums
and in the labs.
Thank you.