Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, my name is Ashish,
and I'm a performance tools engineer
at Apple.
Yeounoh will join me later,
and we are very excited to talk to you
about the new App Store Connect API
for obtaining power and performance data.
The amazing work done by developers
in building great applications
is an essential part of our users'
overall software experience.
And two of the most important aspects
of ensuring a great user experience
are optimizing the power
and performance impact
of your applications.
At Apple, we are deeply committed
towards providing you actionable tools
to help you easily
identify the areas to focus on.
Last year at WWDC 2019,
we first introduced
a new feature within Xcode 11
for out-of-the-box
power and performance analytics.
The Xcode Organizer allows you to view
aggregated power,
performance and I/O metrics
to help identify areas
for improvements in your applications.
Since that release,
we have received many requests
to be able to access the same
Xcode data programmatically.
One of the common requests we heard
was the ability to consume this data
in your own analytics
and monitoring pipelines.
So, we are very excited to announce
the new Power and Performance API
which is part of the App Store Connect API
being released later this year.
We highly recommend you to check out
the "Expanding Automation
with the App Store Connect API" video
to learn more about App Store Connect.
The new API enables you
to programmatically access
the Xcode metrics and diagnostics data,
allowing you to consume
this data yourself.
We've also provided
a new built-in smart insights feature
to identify your application's
power and performance hotspots
without any additional effort.
As people use your application,
we collect the power and performance data
from consented devices.
This data is then aggregated
on our servers
and made available to you
through the App Store Connect API.
You can use data from this new API
for building highly customized
analytics pipelines,
as well as automated monitoring
of your app's performance
through dashboards.
During the rest of this talk,
we'll first go through
a brief overview of this new API
and the data types vended by it.
Next, we'll walk through a few examples
of accessing the same aggregated data
that drives the power
and performance analytics in Xcode,
as well as the new smart insights.
Finally, we'll present a live demo
to extract aggregated metrics,
insights and diagnostics
for a sample application
and wrap up with a brief summary.
Now, let's walk through
an overview of this API.
There are four new REST API resources
available this year.
Let's take a look at each resource.
The first API resource
uses your application's ID
to provide aggregated metrics and insights
for your app's most recent versions.
The smart insights help identify
your application's hotspots.
We'll go into more details
of this data in the next section.
The second API resource
allows you to download metrics
for a specific app version.
To get this data,
you'll need to provide the build ID
provided by App Store Connect API
for a specific application version.
Next, you can access
top diagnostic signatures
for a specific app version.
These signatures are used
to group common problems.
We also recommend you check out
this year's talk on Xcode Organizer,
which goes into details about accessing
the same diagnostics data through Xcode.
Finally, you can download logs
corresponding to diagnostic signatures
for your root cause analysis.
This requires the diagnostic signature ID
as part of the GET request.
To summarize the new API,
you can incorporate these four endpoints
into your analytics workflows
to automatically track
your application's footprint
using aggregated metrics,
smart insights and diagnostics data.
Now, let's walk through a few examples
to get data and insights
through these API endpoints,
starting with aggregated metrics data.
The power and performance
metrics data for an application
is aggregated by each unique metric
and device type.
These metrics are the same as those
available in Xcode Organizer today,
such as battery drain,
launch and disk writes.
The new API currently supports
vending this data
for all iPhone and iPad device groups.
As discussed earlier,
you need to make the following GET request
with your application ID
to receive both aggregated metrics
and insights for your recent app versions.
This returns a structured JSON string
with two major sections:
aggregated metrics, which is represented
as productData, and insights.
Let's take a look
at the sample metrics JSON.
For each metric, such as hangRate,
the JSON structure contains
some metadata, such as unit.
And for each unique device
and metric combination,
the JSON contains the 50th
and 90th percentile values.
Finally, the metric summary is generated
for up to eight most recent versions
of the application.
As this example JSON indicates,
you can use this data
to build highly customized
power and performance analytics
across different metrics,
devices and percentiles.
But we didn't stop here.
Our team went one step further
to also help you quickly identify
your application's power
and performance hotspots
without the need for custom analytics.
We are very excited to bring you
the new smart insights feature.
These smart insights
use the earlier metrics data
to automatically flag
major hotspots in your application.
This is especially helpful
if you want to track
top application regressions in the field
without any additional effort.
Currently, these insights flag regressions
and uptick in metric values.
The insights JSON response
contains three sections:
the versions analyzed for the insight,
a summary of the regression,
and a list of impacted devices
and percentiles.
Let's walk through the details
of a sample insight.
The highlighted section
indicates the metric type
and summary of the identified regression.
You can use these summary strings
to track top regressions
for your application.
As shown here, the application's
launch time is regressed
only for the 90th percentile iPhone users.
Such insights can help you
take more focused actions
to improve your app's performance.
The population section
contains a detailed structure list
of impacted percentiles and devices.
And the third part contains the metadata,
such as the latest application version,
and the list of previous
application versions used for comparison.
In the final part of this section,
let's take a look at diagnostics data
for root cause analysis.
Over to Yeounoh now
to continue the rest of the talk.
Thank you, Ashish.
Hi, I'm Yeounoh,
a performance tools engineer at Apple.
In addition to metrics and smart insights,
we also provide diagnostics data
to help you deep-dive into regressions.
There are two parts
to power and performance diagnostics.
First, we use diagnostic signatures
to group similar problems together.
For instance,
similar disk writes exceptions
are aggregated to generate
disk writes signatures.
Using diagnostic signatures,
we can do root cause analysis
by problem group.
The API returns most prevalent
top signatures for your app version,
and given a top signature and its ID,
you can get related diagnostic logs
with more details.
To receive top signatures
for your app version,
you need to make following
GET request with build ID
from App Store Connect API.
This year, you can access
disk writes diagnosticSignatures
from both Xcode and the API.
The response contains
a list of top signatures in data,
and each signature contains
a unique signature ID and attributes.
From these attributes,
you can tell that this is an example
of a disk writes signature,
and the signature string
is the call frame that represents
the call stack in Xcode UI.
And weight is the normalized
signature weight
which indicates the relative importance
of this signature.
And it also comes with a URL
to get diagnostic logs.
As you can see, this URL
already contains the signature ID.
The second part of power
and performance diagnostics
is diagnostic log.
It contains anonymized diagnostic details
from individual devices.
And this includes metadata information,
such as platform,
OS version and device type.
And also, the log contains
function call stack trees,
which can be extremely helpful
to understand what is causing
the power and performance hotspots.
The diagnostic call stack JSON structure
is also shared with MetricKit.
So check out this year's MetricKit talk
to learn more about on-device
power and performance diagnostics.
Getting diagnostic logs requires
the following GET request
with a signature ID.
This is the same kind of URL
that we have seen
from the diagnosticSignature response.
The response contains
a list of diagnosticLogs,
and each log contains diagnosticMetadata
with information like deviceType,
osVersion and buildVersion.
In this example, the log is generated
for a disk writes exception event.
The log also comes with callStacks.
Each callStack frame contains rawFrame
and parsed frame information,
and a list of subFrames.
Following the subFrames
from the root frame,
you can traverse
the entire call stack tree structure.
Now, let's jump into a demo.
In this demo, you will see
how to access the API yourself,
as well as using a sample script
that will be released with the API
later this year.
For the purpose of this demo,
let's assume that I'm a developer
for an app called MealPlanner.
This app helps me plan meals
and save recipes.
In the latest release,
we introduced a new feature
to save delicious photos with entries.
And now, I can use
Power and Performance API
to make sure that app users
don't experience any regression.
To access the API, we first need
to generate an API access token.
I will run a script to generate the token
using an App Store Connect API key.
With the token, I can access
perfPowerMetrics resource
with MealPlanner app ID.
As you can see in this response,
we get insights, as well as productData,
in the same format
that we have seen during the talk.
And productData contains
a lot of aggregated metrics information.
So, let's go look at smart insights
to see if we have any regression.
Taking insights regression
and its summary string,
we see that there is
a disk writes regression
for the latest app version
for 50th percentile users on all iPhones.
To further investigate this,
let's get diagnostics logs
and look at exception call stacks.
First, I will request
top diagnosticSignatures
using the latest app version build ID.
By taking the top disk writes signature
and its related URL...
I will request diagnosticLogs
for the signature.
The diagnosticLog response
contains callStack information...
and this call stack structure
is efficient for machine processing.
And for us to look at
the original call stack,
I've written a sample code
to parse and pretty-print
this stack information.
The sample script programmatically access
the same diagnostic API resources.
Hit Enter, we get
the original call stack from the log.
Looking at the call function frames
from the bottom...
I see that the new feature
to add photos with the entries
is causing heavy disk writes I/O.
By following the stack trace,
I can go to the exact location
in the source code
to debug and optimize the implementation.
The sample codes to generate a token,
as well as to get diagnostics data
will be released with the API
later this year.
So, please check out the sample codes
for a quick reference to API access.
To summarize this demo,
you can view and monitor
aggregated metrics using the API,
and use smart insights to identify
power and performance regression.
And finally, use diagnostics data
to do root cause analysis of the problem.
Let's recap what we have discussed today.
We introduced our new
App Store Connect API
for power and performance.
With this new API,
you can programmatically access
the same metrics and diagnostics data
as Xcode Organizer,
and build customized data analytics
and monitoring systems
around power and performance metrics.
We also introduced smart insights
that can help you identify
key trends and regression in metrics.
We are very excited about this new API
for you to continue building amazing apps.
So, we kindly ask you to try it out
and give us your feedback. Thank you.