Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone. My name is Shefali
and I'm a performance tools engineer
here at Apple.
Today, I'm excited to talk to you
about the Xcode Organizer.
Your apps are the backbone
of our software experience.
Now more than ever, it's important
that we continue working together
to improve battery life and performance
so users can get the most
out of their devices.
Year after year, you will strive to build
the most performant apps for your users,
asking us what more you can do
and what areas you should prioritize.
To help you ensure that your apps
are performing well on customer devices,
we're dedicated to providing you
with actionable tools and data
so you can quickly determine
what areas of your app to focus on.
The Xcode Organizer Window
allows you to track aggregated battery,
performance, and IO metrics
for your applications.
Today, I'm very excited to introduce
some of the new features
we've added this year.
First, I'll go through a brief overview
of the Xcode Organizer,
and show you
what it looks like in Xcode 11.
Then we'll jump into
the new features we've added this year,
which includes a new category of metrics
and diagnostics reports,
as well as a new UI.
Finally, we'll tie all of these
new features together in a demo
where I'll show you
how you can use this powerful tool
to track the battery life
and performance impact of your app
from release to release,
and we'll wrap it up with some next steps.
Let's begin
with a brief overview of the Organizer.
What is the Xcode Organizer,
and how do I get to it
to see my app's data?
As the name suggests,
the Xcode Organizer Window
is built directly into Xcode,
which means all you have to do
is navigate to the menu bar,
go to "Window,"
and click "Organizer" to launch.
What's great about using the Organizer
is that it requires absolutely no changes
to be made to your app.
As users use your app,
we collect battery life
and performance data
from consented devices.
This data is then aggregated
on our servers
and sent back to you
through the Organizer.
To learn more about the Xcode Organizer,
I recommend you check out
the "What's New in Energy Debugging" talk
from 2018,
and the "Improving Battery Life
and Performance" talk from 2019.
Last year, through the Organizer,
we provided data
for various app-usage metrics.
Since then, we've loved seeing you use
the metrics and diagnostics reports
to monitor your app's performance
and drive some really great bug fixes.
Now let's take a look at the new data
we've added in the Organizer this year.
This year, we're providing more data
across both metrics and diagnostics.
We've added
a new category of metrics for scrolling.
We're calling these "hitches."
Before we go into the details,
let's take a look at the Meal Planner app
I've been working on with some colleagues,
and what a user perceives as a hitch.
Notice the slow, skipping,
and jittery scroll.
And here's the same application,
but without any hitches.
As we can see, there's quite a difference
between the two experiences,
and this smooth scroll here
is what we wanna help you achieve
using the scroll hitch metric.
But what is a scroll hitch?
A scroll hitch is when a rendered frame
does not end up on-screen
at its expected time
while a user is scrolling within your app.
This usually causes frames to be dropped,
which can be perceived
as a jittery scroll.
For the scrolling section
of the Organizer,
we take the hitch time,
which is the total amount of extra time
frames take to show up on-screen,
and we divide that by the scroll duration,
which is the total amount of time
a user spends scrolling within your app.
The result is the hitch rate,
which is an important metric you can use
to measure app performance
because it provides an estimate
of the severity of hitches
as perceived by the user.
There are three buckets
for how you should interpret hitch rate.
This first is when the hitch rate
is less than five milliseconds per second.
Here, there's quite a large window of time
between dropped frames,
and users are likely to perceive
the smooth scroll
that we saw in the Meal Planner app
just a little earlier.
Between five and ten milliseconds
per second,
frames are dropped
every couple of seconds.
And when the hitch rate is greater
than 10 milliseconds per second,
users will be perceiving
frame drops very frequently,
leading to a poor scroll experience.
To learn more about hitches,
I recommend you check out
the "Eliminate Animation Hitches
with XCTests" talk
we've prepared for you this year.
The second piece of new data
we've added this year
is disk write diagnostics reports.
Last year,
we gave you metrics for this category,
and this year,
we're providing you with even more context
to help you pinpoint and really narrow in
on any issues your app encounters.
Disk write diagnostics logs
are aggregated when disk writes exceed
one gigabyte in a 24-hour period.
By reducing the amount
of writes your app is doing,
you can ensure better performance,
longer battery life,
and overall good device health.
Let's take a look at an example
of what these reports look like.
In the left pane of the Organizer,
when we navigate to the "Reports" section
and click on "Disk Writes",
here's what we'll see for our app.
We'll go into more detail about this
during the demo.
So far, we've seen some great new data,
and to go along with it, in Xcode 12,
we've completely redone the interface.
We're thrilled for you to finally see it.
The new interactive UI allows you
to compare and contrast metrics
for different versions of your app
with a single click.
Let's go to the Organizer
and take a better look
at all of these new features.
Let's say I'm a developer
for an app called Meal Planner
which allows users
to plan meals for the week
by saving pictures and recipes
so that they're all in one place.
In XCode 12, when I open up the Organizer,
I can do a side-by-side comparison
of two of my releases
thanks to the new interactive UI.
I can now click on
any of the older versions of my app...
and on the right side,
we can see the UI update
to reflect the differences
between the latest and selected versions.
There's also a more detailed breakdown
of the subcategories accounting
for the battery usage of my app.
We can see here
that in the latest version,
there's an increase
in Camera and Bluetooth usage
that I now know to go investigate.
I can also go back and select
any of the older versions whenever I want.
This is really useful
because it opens up
a lot of new possibilities
for version comparison,
and it gives me control
over the data I'm looking at.
As developers, we love seeing data
about the usage of our app,
but what if it takes days or even weeks
before we can see it in the Organizer?
It's important to note that last year,
we set a threshold
where we expected each app version
to have a certain amount of usage
from user devices
before we could show histograms for them
in the Xcode Organizer.
This year, we're thrilled
to show this data even sooner,
giving you an early glimpse
of your app's performance.
In Xcode 12,
we've lowered the required usage threshold
by a factor of five.
This means that if you're currently able
to see data for your app,
you'll now see this data even sooner.
If your app's usage
was below the old threshold
but is above the new one,
you'll start seeing data
for the first time.
We're incredibly happy that
a much larger audience of app developers
can now use the Organizer
to monitor their apps' battery life
and performance impact.
Looking at this battery-usage graph,
we can see an icon
in the X-axis by version 1.0.1.
This icon indicates that a version
of our app had limited usage.
Associated with this icon
is additional information
regarding the margin of error
for that version.
We can see this on the right side here.
This is important
because we're analyzing fewer data points
for these versions with limited usage.
The data from the smaller working set
will stabilize as more people
update their app and use the new version.
As the usage increases,
the error margin will decrease
until the version gets enough usage
where the error margin is low enough
that's it's omitted from the UI.
Now let's take a look at how we can use
the new reports as part of our workflow.
Clicking on the disk write metrics
on the left,
we can see that there was
a sudden increase in disk writes
in version 2.2.
Let's walk through how we at Meal Planner
would triage this regression.
After identifying the spike
in disk writes here,
we'll navigate
to the "Reports" section on the left...
and click on "Disk Writes".
It looks like
there were a couple of different issues
contributing to the increase we saw.
The top one looks like
it's actually related to a new feature
we added in version 2.2,
where users can now add
their own custom pictures
and recipes to their meals.
Since the stack trace tells us exactly
what the signature of the issue is,
we can jump to that part of the code
and begin investigating.
Under the signature,
we can also see
what percentage of our disk writes
a given signature accounted for.
For a particular signature,
the "Reports" section on the right
shows us a breakdown
by device type and operating system,
and the bar graph below the pie chart
gives us a trend of how many reports
were received for our app
over the last 14 days.
Similar to the energy reports,
we also provide
sample stack traces per signature
and additional information
regarding the stack trace
in the "Details" section on the right.
I can use all of this information
to make the fix so that our app
isn't doing as much writing.
I'll go ahead
and mark the signature as resolved
so my colleagues can address
some of the other regressions
the Organizer caught.
Once our users are using
the version with this fix,
we'll come back to the metrics
to confirm that our data returns back
to what it previously was.
We're incredibly excited to show you
more data in a new interactive Organizer,
and we're excited to see how you use
all of these new features
to drive some great optimizations
within your app.
If you're a developer using the Organizer,
I encourage you to go compare metrics
for two of your app versions
with the new interactive UI,
check out what scrolling performance
looks like for your app
with the hitches metric,
and take a deep dive
into the disk writes for your app
by using the disk write reports
along with the disk write metrics.
We're very excited for you
to continue using the Xcode Organizer
to optimize your apps
for battery life and performance.
Thank you for taking the time
to listen to this presentation,
and I hope you enjoy
the rest of this conference.