Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to what's new in Mac Catalyst.
My name is Jason Beaver,
and I'll be joined later
by my colleague Brycen Wershing.
As you all know,
Mac Catalyst is the infrastructure
that allows us to bring iOS applications
to macOS.
We introduced Mac Catalyst
in macOS Catalina as public API,
and the developer community
has used this technology
to bring some amazing iPad apps
to the Mac.
The apps can take advantage
of the much larger display,
and many have added custom toolbars
and menus.
They get a great deal
of the macOS look and feel automatically,
making them feel right at home on the Mac.
In macOS Big Sur,
I'm excited to announce a number
of improvements to Mac Catalyst
that will make it easier for you
to bring your iOS application to macOS
and help you make your app
an even better experience on the Mac.
One of the biggest challenges
developers have faced
when trying to bring
their iOS applications to the Mac
is that many iOS frameworks
weren't available to Mac Catalyst apps.
We've worked hard over the past year
to bring dozens of additional
iOS frameworks to Mac Catalyst,
or to bring over missing functionality
so that your applications are even
more compatible with macOS.
We've even brought over frameworks
that aren't available on macOS
to make it easier for you
to bring your application to Mac Catalyst
without having to conditionally
exclude code when compiling for the Mac.
For example, if your application
is dependent on ARKit,
previously, you would need to remove
the framework from your macOS target
and conditionalize your code
so that you didn't reference ARKit symbols
when building for macOS.
Now, if you're targeting macOS Big Sur
or later,
your iOS code can work
exactly the same way it would
on an iOS device that doesn't support AR.
You can link ARKit and use runtime checks
to determine whether your AR features
should be enabled.
This, of course,
goes for dozens of other frameworks
that are now available in the macOS SDK
for Mac Catalyst apps.
Now let's focus on some of the new APIs
we've added in the past year.
We recently added support for handling
physical keyboard events in iOS,
and these are available
to Mac Catalyst applications
in the latest macOS Catalina update.
These can be added to your application
by implementing the methods
pressesBegan, and pressesEnded
on one of the responders
in your responder chain.
Games can especially benefit from this
as an alternative to multi-touch.
See the "support hardware keyboards
in your apps" session
where this will be covered in-depth.
In addition,
the focus engine APIs from tvOS
are now available to apps in Mac Catalyst.
This allows you to set
focus group identifiers on your views
to control which views are related,
and receive callbacks
when the focus is changed
to allow you to update your UI.
See the technical documentation
for details on how to customize
what can be focused in your application.
UICollectionView and UITableView
allows the selection
to follow the keyboard focus.
For example, users can use the arrow keys
to navigate between the cells
in a sidebar.
If you're navigating a table
or collection view
in a detail view though,
keyboard navigation
acts more as a highlight.
In this case, hitting enter or space
would trigger the selection
of the focused cell.
You can override this default behavior
by changing selectionFollowsFocus.
UISceneActivationRequestOptions.
CollectionJoinBehavior
allows you to specify
the window creation behavior.
By specifying the collection join behavior
when activating a scene,
you can control whether it appears
as a new tab in an existing window,
or it appears as a new top-level window.
In an update to Catalina,
we exposed the AppKit class
NSCursor to Mac Catalyst app.
This allows you to hide the cursor
in your app,
for example,
when starting to play a full-screen video.
NSCursor also allows you
to change the cursor's image.
Here are some of the cursor images
that are available to you.
These cursor images can be used
over certain regions of your application
to help your users understand
how to interact with it.
UIKit now includes a color well
and a color-picker view controller.
In Mac Catalyst apps,
this automatically brings up
the standard system color-picker
that is provided by AppKit.
UIDatePicker now uses the AppKit-provided
inline date-picker
to make Mac Catalyst apps
feel even more at home on the Mac.
UIButtons now support bringing up
pull-down menus.
And on macOS Big Sur,
they are regular Mac pull-down menus.
You can find more about all
of these controls
at the "UIKit Menus, Pickers,
and Controls" session.
Sheets are now presented
in their own separate NSWindow.
These windows are resizable
but default to the preferred content size
of the modal view controller.
Using Autolayout will ensure
that your content resizes well.
Popover presentations are now presented
in NSPopovers,
which have their own separate windows
that extend outside
of the presenting
view controller's window.
And finally, UISplitViewController
now supports three columns,
and the leading column can be a sidebar.
Of course, sidebars were supported
by Mac Catalyst apps in Catalina,
but with Big Sur,
we have made them even more Mac-like.
In macOS Big Sur,
UIKit and AppKit fully support SF Symbols,
and they are heavily utilized
in the system applications.
SF Symbols integrate seamlessly
with the San Francisco system font,
so the symbols automatically ensure
optical vertical alignment
with text for all weights and sizes.
Adopting SF Symbols will make your app
work and feel even better
on iOS and macOS.
Podcasts uses SF Symbols in the sidebar
so that it can adapt well
to different sizes
without having to include image assets
for each supported size.
Now I'd like to hand it over
to my colleague, Brycen,
to take you through
some additional changes to Mac Catalyst.
Thanks, Jason.
Hello. I'm Brycen Wershing
from Core Darwin,
and I'm going to take you through
a few more
of the new features
in Mac Catalyst this year.
First, a short peek at the new ways
that you can optimize UI.
"Optimized for Mac"
is a new Mac Catalyst mode
that you can choose for your apps
that lets you take that extra step
towards a truly refined Mac experience.
It changes the default scaling
from the 77% we have today, to 100%,
which will yield more crisp text
and graphics
at the cost of potentially disturbing
your application's layout.
This change is particularly noticeable
for text,
such as the word "tarte"
in our sample app.
By increasing the default scaling,
"tarte" will look more clear and crisp.
Optimized for Mac also allows
various controls
to change your app's metrics and behaviors
to match the Mac.
There's also some additional API
for access to things like checkboxes,
which have not previously been available
to Catalyst apps.
This is the largest new addition
to Mac Catalyst this year.
And you can check out
the "Optimizing Catalyst UI
for the Mac Idiom" session
to learn all about it, and how to adopt
“Optimized for Mac” in your apps.
Next up, let's take a look at SwiftUI.
If your app is written in SwiftUI,
you don't need Catalyst.
But if you're using SwiftUI
alongside UIKit in an iPad app,
the same code will also work
in the context of Mac Catalyst.
This year,
SwiftUI has a number of new features
that will work wonderfully with Catalyst.
Looking at some examples,
commands in SwiftUI work delightfully
for Mac Catalyst apps.
This integrates seamlessly
with Mac features, such as the main menu.
The new toolbar support in SwiftUI
will work just as expected
in Mac Catalyst.
With the use of semantic placement,
toolbar items can be automatically placed
in the Mac toolbar
with no extra adoption needed.
SwiftUI works exceedingly well
when apps are optimized for Mac,
which is expanded on in the "Optimizing
Catalyst UI for the Mac Idiom" session.
Generally, the parts of a UIKit iPad app
that use SwiftUI
will continue to work in Mac Catalyst.
For more information about SwiftUI,
check out "What's New in SwiftUI."
Now let's take a look
at something different:
Application Lifecycle.
Application Lifecycle in UIKit
revolves around a few states
that your application can be in
depending on where the user's focus is.
There are some big changes to this
in macOS Big Sur.
As a quick refresher,
on both iPad and Mac,
an app, when in front of the user,
is in the foreground active state.
When the app moves to the background,
such as when you switch
to another app on the iPad,
it will transition through
the foreground inactive state
to the background state.
On Mac, when the user quits the app,
the app will terminate.
When transitioning between app states,
the delegate calls
and notifications on Mac,
and the sequences thereof,
are the same as on an iPad.
If you want to learn more about
what happens during a state change,
take a look at "Taking iPad Apps
for the Mac to the Next Level"
from WWDC 2019.
Although what happens
during a state change
is the same on iPad and Mac,
there's not a direct parallel
for when state changes occur.
That being said, there are some
approximations that can be made.
This year, we've added more scenarios
where a scene may transition
to the background state,
even while the app is perceived
to be running.
It's worth mentioning
that the overall app state
in a multi-window app
depends on the activation state
of the individual scenes.
Considering this, you will likely want
to handle state changes per scene.
A scene will enter the background states
when the user no longer perceives
the window that contains that scene
to be part of an active space.
For example,
when a window becomes minimized,
or the space with the window
moves out of view,
or the app is hidden,
the scene will transition
to the background.
In addition,
the app as a whole will be foreground
whenever at least one window
is foreground,
or if the app has control
over the menu bar.
Let me be clear, your app will not
transition to the background
when it gains or loses the menu bar
while in an active space,
or when a window becomes occluded.
In summary, we've made Mac Catalyst
Application Lifecycle more iOS-like,
so that your apps can more easily get
the behavior that your users expect.
Looking at an example,
say your app is a game.
Depending on how that game interacts
with the user,
you may or may not wish
to have that game pause
when it moves to the background.
Typically, you'll want the same behavior
as on iPad.
But consider carefully the best behavior
for your app on a Mac.
Be aware that while Mac Catalyst apps
do get all the benefits of AppNap,
they do not get the benefit
of being suspended,
even when in the background.
Now let's take a look at what's new
for Mac Catalyst Extensions.
Photo editing extensions
are now available.
You can bring your great
photo-editing extensions to the Mac.
Mac Catalyst extensions now have
a more iOS-like lifecycle.
One example of this
is that when not in use,
rather than being terminated,
extensions will be suspended,
and they will be unsuspended immediately
when needed.
We've also brought iOS-style memory limits
and memory pressure controls to the Mac,
making sure that your extensions behave
as expected
when the system is under memory pressure.
When you put all this together,
it means that more of your iOS extensions
will work as expected
right out of the box on macOS.
There's nothing you need to do
to get this behavior,
it will apply automatically
to all Catalyst extensions.
Great WidgetKit iPad widgets
can also make great Mac widgets.
Simply opt in to Mac Catalyst
and your widgets will work
just as expected on Mac.
Check out "Getting Started with WidgetKit"
to learn all about how to create
WidgetKit widgets
for iOS and Mac Catalyst.
Now let's take a look at a new feature
this year, Universal Purchase.
Now, when you bring your iPad app
over to the Mac via Catalyst,
your existing users on iOS no longer
have to purchase your app a second time.
In addition, the capabilities
and App Store metadata of your app
can be managed consistently in one place.
In other words, any purchase
of a Universal Purchase app
will result in the user having access
to the app across all platforms.
All new Mac Catalyst apps are opted in
to Universal Purchase,
and may opt out if they choose.
To opt out, simply uncheck
the "Use iOS Bundle Identifier" checkbox
in your project settings.
If you have a non-Catalyst Mac app,
or if you have an existing Catalyst app
created in Catalina,
and you want to adopt Universal Purchase
with an iOS app,
see the documentation
on "Offering Universal Purchase"
for instructions on how to enable this
for your app.
Next up, let's look at Mac Catalyst
in the context of the New Look of macOS.
Many of the new Mac UIs
that have been introduced
are also available
to help make Catalyst apps.
In fact, most of this will work
automatically for your apps.
Let's walk through a few examples
of how your app can take advantage
of this new UI.
One new feature this year
is toolbar styles.
You can experiment with this
and make sure that you get a toolbar look
that's right for your app.
All these looks are now available
to Catalyst applications
via UITitlebarToolbarStyle.
In addition, you can set the toolbar style
per window
on the UITitlebarForWindows.
For more information
on all the new toolbar styles on Mac,
check out the "Adopting the New Look
of macOS" session.
Next, let's take a look
at separator items,
a tool to help position toolbar items
in Mac Catalyst.
When you're crafting the look
of your toolbar items,
you may want your items to appear
in different areas of your app.
UIKit provides separator identifiers
to help you with this.
When you add these separator identifiers
to a toolbar,
we will automatically create zones
in the app
bounded by the position of the divider.
For example, in the Messages toolbar,
from left to right,
the compose icon is in the sidebar,
then a sidebar separator item indicates
a jump out of the sidebar.
After that, the "To" field is displayed
left-justified,
then, a flexible space sidebar item
indicates a change in justification.
And finally, the Info icon,
which ends up on the far right of the app.
The code that describes
the Messages toolbar layout
is simple and easy to understand.
Separator Identifiers are simply added
to toolbarDefaultItemIdentifiers method.
That's all that needs to be done
to get this behavior automatic.
Now let's look at accent colors.
This year, you have the ability
to specify a brand color
that is used for things like selection.
This color will work just as well
on both iPad and on the Mac.
You simply create a symbolic color
in the Assets catalog,
and then set it as the accent color.
UIKit will use this color
for highlights in your user interface.
Use this accent color
as an application-wide color.
Essentially, it becomes the default
tint color of your app.
Of course, you can override it locally
in specific parts of the UI.
Now let's look at the sidebar.
There is now more flexibility
for sidebars in your app
available automatically.
One example is automatic drag reordering
for collection views.
If you're using collection views
in your app,
your users will be able to drag
and reorder the contained items.
There's no work that you need to do
to get this behavior.
In general, we're encouraging you
to use collection views wherever possible,
and with List Layout,
adoption should be effortless.
Now, with new frameworks
and APIs supported,
more iOS code will work
right out of the box on macOS.
If you choose to use SwiftUI,
it will work wonderfully
in your Catalyst app,
giving you more options
on how to write your app.
With improvements to application
and extension lifecycle,
at runtime, your Catalyst apps
will run just like on iPad.
Now that we have Universal Purchase,
app discovery and enablement
will be even easier for your users.
And your Catalyst apps will automatically
get all the UI improvements
that have been introduced
in macOS Big Sur.
We're really excited about
all the improvements we've made
to Mac Catalyst, and the impact
it's going to have on your apps.
Thanks for watching, and enjoy WWDC 20.