Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Mike Imbrogno
from GPU software.
And welcome to "Optimize Metal Performance
for Apple Silicon Macs."
As you know by now, Apple GPUs
are coming to the Mac for the first time,
and we're really excited
for you to see what they can do.
Apple GPUs are faster
and more power-efficient.
Your apps are gonna perform great
out of the box.
They support all the features
of Intel-based Macs.
And support all the Metal features
unique to Apple GPUs.
This talk will show you how to optimize
for the Apple GPU architecture.
If you previously developed for iOS,
then some of the advice here today
may already be familiar to you.
But if you're new to Apple GPUs,
and want your app to stand out
on Apple Silicon Macs,
then this is the session for you.
Before we get started, let's take a look
at where this session fits
in your transition to Apple Silicon Macs.
On Intel-based Macs,
your app runs natively.
On Apple Silicon Macs,
your app will run out of the box
under Rosetta's highly optimized
translation layer.
Under translation,
your app will also be automatically opted
into several Metal consistency features
to ensure that they look great too.
But translation and consistency features
will cost you some performance.
So your next step will be
to recompile your app
with the new macOS SDK.
To learn more about Metal consistency
and translation behavior differences,
please see the earlier session
from my colleagues Gokhan and Sam.
Once consistency issues are fixed,
you're ready to focus
on performance optimizations
and the focus of this talk.
Let's look at today's agenda.
In the first section, I'll describe
how to fix the top performance issues
we've observed in your apps
that come from not taking into account
Apple's tile-based
deferred rendering architecture.
You'll learn how
to schedule work efficiently,
optimize pass management
and minimize overdraw.
In the next section,
my colleague Dom will explain how to use
Metal's explicit TBDR features
to take your optimizations
to the next level.
You'll learn how to manage Tile Memory
and use Tile Shaders
to optimize the rendering techniques
that you already use.
And finally, in the last section,
Dom will also show you how to optimize
for the Apple GPU Shader Core.
Let's jump in.
This section requires a good understanding
of the Apple GPU architecture.
So let's start with a recap
from our earlier talks.
Apple-designed GPUs have a tile-based
deferred rendering architecture
designed for both
high performance and low power.
It uses a high-bandwidth,
low-latency Tile Memory
to eliminate overdraw
and reduce System Memory traffic.
The Apple GPU first processes all geometry
of a render pass in the vertex stage.
It transforms and bends your geometry
into screen-aligned Tile Vertex Buffers
that are then passed
to the fragment stage.
Each Tile Vertex Buffer is then processed
entirely on-chip
as part of the fragment stage.
The GPU rasterizes
all primitives in a tile
before shading any pixels
using fast, on-chip Tile Memory.
Metal is designed to directly
take advantage of this architecture.
For example,
load and store actions make explicit
how render pass attachments
move in and out of this Tile Memory.
Keep this in mind as we dive
into our top performance best practices.
I have three optimization categories
to share with you today.
The first category is workload scheduling.
Apple GPUs execute different workloads
concurrently
to maximize utilization
and minimize latency.
But unnecessary dependencies across
render passes can create serialization.
So in this section, I'll teach you how to
identify and eliminate those dependencies.
The next category
is minimizing system bandwidth.
Apple GPUs achieve maximum performance
when System Memory bandwidth is minimized.
So in this section, I'm also going to show
you how to structure your render passes
to reduce load and store traffic.
And finally,
I'll teach you how to minimize overdraw
by maximizing the hidden surface
removal capabilities of Apple GPUs.
Let's start with workload scheduling.
Apple GPUs process vertex, fragment
and even compute workloads
in parallel
using independent hardware channels.
Overlapping these workloads
maximizes GPU utilization
and minimizes execution time.
So your goal is to overlap
wherever possible.
Metal automatically overlaps
your workloads
whenever there are no data dependencies
between them.
But data dependencies are a natural result
of producing and consuming
Metal resources between passes.
So what we're focusing on here
are the unnecessary dependencies
that don't need to be there.
Let's take a closer look.
Apple GPUs process all vertices
of render pass before any fragments.
So stages from the same pass
must execute serially.
But vertex processing of the next pass
should overlap with fragment processing
of the current pass.
This even occurs across frame boundaries,
so oftentimes the vertex cost
is almost entirely hidden
by fragment processing.
Let's take a look at what happens
when you make vertex work dependent
on fragment work of a previous pass.
In this example,
the fragment stage of each pass
is producing data
into a Metal buffer or texture
that is read by the next vertex stage.
This will reduce your overlap
and extend execution time
by creating a bubble of inactivity
in the vertex stage.
If you see this pattern in your app,
then you really wanna fix it.
But sometimes the pattern
won't be so simple or obvious.
Unnecessary dependencies often involve
multiple chains of vertex,
fragments and compute.
In this example,
the vertex stage of Render Pass 1
depends on Compute Pass 1.
And Compute Pass 1 in turn depends on
the fragment stage of Render Pass 0.
All these holes in your GPU activity
will again hurt your performance.
So now that you know what to look out for,
let's talk about how false dependencies
come up in practice.
False dependencies are caused
by sharing the same Metal resources
between adjacent passes,
but not the data inside those resources.
In this example,
Render Pass 0 produces data
for some later passes
into the same resource
that Render Pass 1 consumes,
but the data is unrelated.
Metal only tracks dependencies
at the resource level
and not the data itself.
So one way to fix this
is to use separate resources.
In this example,
I've separated the resources into two,
so now Metal understands
that there's no dependency
and will schedule your work optimally.
But if separating your data
into different resources isn't an option,
then you can also ask Metal
to not track the resource at all.
In this example,
we're back to only one resource,
but it's now marked as untracked
so that Metal will schedule it optimally.
Untracked resources let you control
if and when synchronization is required.
You'll be responsible for inserting
any necessary synchronization
using Metal fences or events.
Metal fences and events
are powerful synchronization primitives
that give you fine control
over the scheduling of your work.
To learn more about them, please see
the previous Metal WWDC talks listed here.
Now, the last tip
for optimal workload scheduling
is pass reordering.
You should always encode independent work
as early as possible.
Let's consider this example again.
If Compute Pass 2 is not dependent
on Compute Pass 1,
then encode it ahead of Compute Pass 1
to fill in the execution gap.
Likewise, if Render Pass 2 is independent
of Render Pass 1,
then it should also be encoded
ahead of Render Pass 1.
You might not always observe
a performance improvement
after reordering your passes
because Metal will also reorder
independent passes when it can,
but Metal's visibility is limited,
so it's always better
to reorder explicitly.
Okay, so now you know what patterns
to look out for and how to fix them.
But how do you actually
find these bubbles?
The answer is to use Metal System Trace.
Metal System Trace will clearly highlight
missed overlap opportunities in your apps.
In this example, you can see that
the vertex, fragment and compute stages
do not overlap at all.
This is because there are
unnecessary dependencies
inserted between each stage.
Here is the exact same frame
at the exact same scale,
but with all
the unnecessary dependencies removed.
Notice that there is now significantly
better overlap between stages,
particularly between
the vertex and compute stages.
Be sure to use Metal System Trace
while tuning your workloads
to verify that you're taking advantage
of overlap between stages.
So that's it for workload scheduling.
Now let's explore how
to minimize System Memory bandwidth.
Apple GPUs process render pass
attachments in tile storage,
and those attachments are moved
in and out of Tile Memory
using load and store actions.
These actions consume the majority
of your app's system bandwidth.
Apple GPUs achieve peak performance
when they are not
System Memory bandwidth bound,
so it's important
to minimize load and store traffic.
Load and store actions are executed
for each render pass,
so you can minimize load and store traffic
by reducing the number
of render passes used.
We sometimes see apps with more
render passes than necessary.
Let me show you some of those
common cases and how to fix them.
Some apps split updates
to the exact same set of attachments
into separate yet adjacent passes.
In this example,
we have three render passes drawing
to the same attachments incrementally,
so that each attachment
is loaded and stored multiple times.
That uses a lot
of System Memory bandwidth.
This often happens when you parallelize
encoding using multiple command buffers.
Metal lets you encode different passes
to different command buffers in parallel
to minimize CPU latency,
so it's not surprising that you might
be using it in this way.
You might even think it's the only way
to achieve encoding parallelism
in Metal based on experience
with other graphics APIs.
In this example,
the app is encoding, on the CPU timeline,
the three parts of the G-buffer
into three separate command buffers.
But the G-buffer is logically
a single render pass,
so it should be encoded that way
to avoid the execution overhead
of repeatedly loading and storing
the same attachments.
To fix this, we should instead use Metal's
parallel render command encoder.
With parallel render command encoders,
you still achieve your goal
of multi-threaded encoding
but without the execution cost.
In this example,
I've replaced the separate command buffers
with parallel sub-encoders.
Metal will combine those sub-encoders
into a single render pass
before execution,
saving most of the System Memory
bandwidth along the way.
Let's take a quick look
at how the API is used.
You start by creating
a parallel render command encoder.
The descriptor is set up
exactly how you would
for a regular render pass encoder.
All sub-encoders will share
the exact same render pass configuration.
You then create your sub-encoders.
In this case,
I'm creating two sub-encoders.
The order in which sub-encoder commands
execute is implied by the creation order.
So it's important to create those up front
to match your intended order.
You then hand off the sub-encoders
to your worker threads for async encoding.
In this case, I'm dispatching
asynchronously to the global queue.
And once encoding is complete,
you need to finalize the parallel encoder.
In this example,
I first wait for completion
using my dispatch group before finalizing.
Now let's look at another common case
where render passes are split
unnecessarily.
In this example,
we have a forward renderer
drawing opaque geometry in the first pass
and translucent objects in the second.
The set of attachments are the same,
but the load and store actions
are different.
In the first pass,
color and depth are written,
and in the second pass,
color is accumulated
but depth is only loaded.
We often see this pattern in apps
that choose to abstract
their graphics API usage,
and that abstraction decides
when to start a new pass
based on the attachments used
and the actions needed.
Now, you don't have to change
your abstraction layer to fix this.
You only need to update your app logic
to avoid splitting passes
when only the actions change.
Here, I've merged the two passes
by drawing the translucent objects
immediately after the opaque objects.
I can do this because render passes
don't need to be split
when only load and store actions change.
This eliminates
the intermediate loads and stores
and the associated
System Memory bandwidth.
Merging also lets you store
only the final color just once.
We also don't need the depth attachment
outside of this pass,
so I set its store action to DontCare.
And in this case, the depth buffer
isn't used outside the pass either,
so I mark it memoryless
to save on footprint too.
Now let's look at another common pattern
we call attachment ping-ponging.
Apps often need to perform
some intermediate rendering
that is then composited
onto the main scene,
and often have to do so repeatedly.
This looks like a game of ping-pong
where the app switches back and forth
between two sets of attachments.
In this example, we're lighting a scene
with a series of lights.
Each light needs a screen-space
attenuation texture
generated before lighting the scene.
Each light therefore creates
a separate render pass
forcing the main scene attachments
to load and store repeatedly.
This of course is not great
for performance.
To fix this,
let's use multiple render targets.
Metal lets you reference up to
eight color attachments in each pass.
So here I just reference
both the main scene texture
and the light attenuation texture
together.
Draws for the main scene
will target the main scene texture,
and attenuation draws
will target only its texture.
This optimization avoids
all the intermediate memory traffic.
Only the main scene attachment is stored.
The attenuation attachment is set
to the DontCare store action.
The attenuation attachment
isn't referenced outside this pass either,
so I've marked it memoryless too.
Now let's take a quick look at how
to set up the pass for this example.
You start by creating
the main scene attachment.
Then create the attenuation attachment
of the same size.
Notice that I've marked it
memoryless here.
Then you create the render pass by first
describing the attachment configuration.
We want to clear both the scene
and attenuation textures
but only store the scene texture.
And finally, we create our render pass
from our descriptor.
That's it.
Now let's look at an example
of how not to clear attachments in Metal.
Here's another common pattern we see
for apps ported from other graphics APIs
that have a stand-alone clear operation.
In this example, the stand-alone clear
is translated into a separate render pass
that only exists to clear that attachment.
This again generates
wasted System Memory traffic.
The solution is to fold
the clear operation
into the render pass that needs it.
With Apple GPUs, the clear load action
only operates on Tile Memory,
and draws will also target Tile Memory,
either occluding
or overwriting the cleared pixel,
so you don't waste bandwidth storing
cleared pixels that are later overdrawn.
So that's a simple
load action improvement.
For our last tip, let's look at
a similar store action improvement
that you can make
to your multi-sampled apps.
Multi-sample anti-aliasing is a great way
to improve the image quality of your app,
and on Apple GPUs,
it's really efficient when used correctly.
Some apps, however, are choosing to first
store the multi-sampled attachment data,
and then reload it
just to perform the resolve operation.
In this example, we store the sample data
for both color and depth
in the first pass, and then resolve both
in the second pass.
Like the separate clear example,
we often observe this pattern in apps
ported from other graphics APIs
that don't support load actions.
But sample data is rarely needed off-chip,
so the resolve operation should really be
performed as part of the previous pass.
That way, we only consume
System Memory bandwidth
for the pixels that matter
and not the samples.
Also notice in this example that
I've made the MSAA textures memoryless.
MSAA samples are often
only ever needed within a pass,
so that's a great opportunity
to save a lot of memory.
So that's our advice for minimizing
System Memory bandwidth in your apps.
Now let's learn how to maximize
hidden surface removal efficiency
to minimize overdraw.
Remember that Apple GPUs support
hidden surface removal in hardware.
The goal of HSR is to shade
only visible pixels,
and not pixels occluded by later draws.
To do this, HSR categorizes fragments
based on their visibility.
First we have opaque fragments,
which always occlude, or hide,
everything beneath them.
Then we have feedback fragments,
which are generated by fragment functions
containing a discard statement,
or that return a depth value.
Alpha-tested foliage
falls into this category.
And finally we have translucent fragments,
which blend with their background
like a smoke effect would.
To maximize HSR efficiency,
draw each type of fragment together,
and in the order shown.
First opaque, then feedback,
and, finally, translucent objects.
Draw ordering within each category
only matters for feedback
and translucent fragments.
Opaque draws can be in any order,
but are usually sorted
by your app's material system.
Let's focus more on opaque fragments.
Opaque fragments allow HSR
to eliminate the most work
because any pixel beneath them
can be rejected before shading.
For example, when rendering
the opaque triangles on the right,
hidden surface removal will reject
all fragments
belonging to the yellow
and green triangles
that are covered by the blue triangle.
Not all opaque geometry
is treated equally though.
We already know that some Metal features
will make your fragments nonopaque,
like alpha blending and alpha testing,
but some Metal features will also reduce
hidden surface removal efficiency.
It's okay to use those features
when needed,
but you should be aware
of their performance
and how to minimize the efficiency impact.
Let's review them now.
Metal supports writing to buffers
and textures from fragment functions.
These resources are not
your render pass attachments.
By default, Metal is required to execute
all such fragments,
even if they're occluded
by later fragments.
Metal does this to ensure
that memory writes are deterministic,
at the expense of hidden surface removal,
but you often don't need resource writes
to occur for rejected fragments,
and when that's true,
Metal provides the early fragment test
attribute to recover some efficiency.
That attribute tells Metal that it's okay
to not shade the fragment
if it fails the depth test.
You should add the early_fragment_tests
attribute to these fragment functions
wherever possible.
Another feature that reduces
HSR efficiency is write masking.
Write masks allow you to restrict
which color channels
of a render pass attachment are written,
even when the shader
writes all the channels.
In this example,
colorAttachments[0] will only have
its red and green channels written
by the fragment function
bound to this pipeline.
The blue and alpha channels
will not be updated.
Metal must preserve the untouched channels
for correctness, and on Apple GPUs,
that means shading underlapping fragments
to first generate those values.
All channels of the underlapping fragment
are shaded,
even though only some channel values
are actually needed,
so some computation is wasted.
If you need write masking
to express your rendering technique,
then by all means use it,
and you probably intended to use
write masking
when you set it up through the Metal API.
But now let me show you
an example we found
where write masking was not intentional.
Write masks can be set up
in fragment functions too,
and fragment functions that don't
write any channels of an attachment,
are also write masking.
Consider this on-chip
deferred rendering example.
The G-buffer consists
of three render pass attachments:
albedo, normals
and the light accumulation texture.
The fragment function
of the G-buffer generation phase
only writes to two
of those three attachments,
because the last attachment
isn't used in this phase.
This form of write masking
was unintentional.
You didn't intend to reduce
HSR efficiency here.
To fix this, we just need to write
all of the attachments.
And in this case, we can just initialize
the lighting attachment to zeros.
Remember that unless you really need
to preserve the previous values
of an attachment,
you should write to all render pass
attachments to improve HSR efficiency.
To close our discussion
on hidden surface removal best practices,
let's look at the role of depth pre-passes
on Apple GPUs.
Depth pre-pass
is a commonly used technique
in existing Mac games
to minimize overdraw.
You first render the scene into your depth
attachment only to determine visibility.
You then render the scene again
into your color attachments,
testing against that visibility
but without updating it.
This ensures that only fragments
matching the depth test
are shaded in the second pass.
Now, if you need visibility information
before your main scene renders
for a particular technique,
then you don't have to change your app,
but if you only perform
a depth pre-pass for performance,
then hidden surface removal
serves the same purpose on Apple GPUs.
When HSR is maximized,
it can reject hidden fragments
as well as depth pre-passes can,
but without any additional costs.
With HSR, geometry is only processed once.
And HSR doesn't require
the depth attachment to be stored,
or even have memory backing at all.
It also avoids a correctness artifact
called z-fighting,
where the depth calculation of both passes
slightly mismatch.
For more information on z-fighting,
please see this year's
Apple Silicon Mac porting session.
So that concludes our discussion
on how to minimize overdraw
with hidden surface removal.
My colleague Dom will introduce you
to even more
advanced optimization techniques.
Hey, thanks, Mike.
In the first part of this video,
we've seen some performance optimization
techniques for Apple GPUs
that require some relatively small changes
in your use of the Metal API.
In this section, instead,
we're going to discuss about
further optimization opportunities
based on Metal features
that are specific to Apple GPUs,
such as Tile Shaders
and programmable blending.
Let's start talking about how to optimize
deferred shading on Apple GPUs.
Deferred shading is a lighting solution
commonly used in several game engines.
As a quick recap, in deferred shading,
rendering is split in two passes.
First we draw all the scene geometry
to compute some
per-pixel material properties.
In this case, albedo, normals
and surface roughness
are stored in three different attachments.
That's what we call G-buffer.
Then in the second pass,
the G-buffer data is used to compute
the final per-pixel lighting output.
The main idea is that
decoupling geometry from lighting
can keep the shading costs under control.
A common issue of deferred shading
is that G-buffers can have a large
memory footprint and bandwidth costs,
especially in cases
where multiple G-buffers
are used to shade unique materials
such as hair or skin.
However, Apple GPUs
support features designed to reduce
the number of render passes
for deferred shading.
Programmable blending
can reduce the bandwidth cost,
and when combined
with memoryless render targets,
500 Internal Server Error
QTL_Cache/1.2.14
Here, you have a basic example
of a deferred renderer
ported from Intel-based Macs.
The G-buffer attachments are rendered
and stored to System Memory
by the first command encoder.
The attachments are read back immediately
afterwards in the lighting pass,
consuming a significant amount
of memory bandwidth.
Metal on macOS supports the concept
of memory barrier,
and some developers use this construct
in their deferred renderers.
A memory barrier
is a synchronization object
that ensures that all writes to a given
set of resources have completed,
before further commands can be processed.
So in this case, a memory barrier
on the fragment stage
could be used to combine the G-buffer
and lighting passes together.
However, memory barriers
within the fragment stage
are a very expensive operation
on Apple GPUs.
That's because they require to flush
the Tile Memory to System Memory,
which is what we want to avoid
in the first place.
Fortunately, you can use
programmable blending
to optimize this deferred renderer
into a single pass.
Programmable blending allows your shader
to access the current pixel's value
for all color attachments.
The results are accessible
in the on-chip Tile Memory
without needing to go through
System Memory.
One important detail to highlight
is that the Tile Memory
stores color and depth attachments
separately,
so the depth is not directly accessible
to a fragment shader.
To work around this limitation,
you can maintain the current fragment's
depth in a dedicated color attachment
to keep it available
to all your fragment shaders.
Now that we know the basics
of on-chip deferred shading,
let's see some more complex example.
Game engines
can have multiple lighting pipelines
with unique G-buffer layouts.
For instance, hair or skin shading
often add additional material properties
and need custom lighting.
Such configuration would consume
a lot of memory bandwidth on Apple GPUs.
Fortunately, Metal offers
a number of techniques
to optimize these kind of pipelines.
Remember that Metal supports up to
eight color attachments per render pass.
If your G-buffer layout is similar
among all logical passes
of your deferred renderer,
and you use only a few unique attachments
to store
all the intermediate lighting results,
then you can keep everything in one pass
using programmable blending.
In this example,
besides the G-buffer attachments,
you have one attachment
for regular lighting,
and one attachment
for the specialized hair lighting
before compositing them together.
And of course, if you don't
need to reference G-buffer data
outside the render pass, then you can even
make those attachments memoryless,
reducing the memory footprint
of your workload.
To summarize,
we now know that programmable blending
is a simple yet powerful feature
to maximize the use of Tile Memory.
However, there are cases where you
need to repurpose, more drastically,
the structure of your Tile Memory.
Later in this video,
we'll focus again on this topic,
but before, we need to talk about
how to mix render and compute together.
Modern renderers often implement
more sophisticated lighting pipelines
than what we've seen so far.
In many cases, those pipelines
use both render-based techniques
as well as compute dispatches.
A typical example
is tile-based light culling,
which is a rendering technique
where the render target
is split into small tiles,
and a compute shader builds a list
of all lights that affect each tile.
The final lighting pass
uses the per-tile light lists
to shade only the lights
affecting a given tile,
reducing the shading cost dramatically.
Now that we're throwing compute
into the mix,
keeping data on-chip
might require some additional work.
Metal supports render command encoders
for drawing
and compute command encoders
for dispatches.
Starting with A11 Bionic, Apple GPUs also
support tile-based compute dispatches.
With Tile Shaders,
you can dispatch threadgroups
that operate on a per-tile basis
within a render command encoder.
Tile dispatches
introduce implicit barriers
against the fragment shading stage
of the earlier and later draws.
For this reason, a tile dispatch
can use the fragment shading results
of all earlier draws in the tile,
and finish executing before any subsequent
draws start their fragment shading.
Tile Shaders are deeply integrated
in the architecture of modern Apple GPUs,
so they can access Imageblocks,
Threadgroup Memory
and Device Memory as well.
With this in mind, let's go back
to our Tile Deferred Renderer.
Here is a pipeline
that has a G-buffer pass
followed by a light culling compute pass.
To determine whether a light
affects a given tile,
the light culling pass uses the depth
attachment produced by the G-buffer pass.
Finally, the culled light list
is used in the last compute pass
to accumulate the lighting contribution
of all lights in a given tile.
Without Tile Shading,
dispatching threadgroups
with a compute command encoder
would break rendering into three passes,
forcing several flushes
of the Tile Memory to System Memory.
Using Tile Shaders instead,
you can access the whole Imageblock data
in a tile dispatch,
so you can generate per-tile light lists
in the middle of a render command encoder.
With this configuration,
the light list is stored
in a Threadgroup Memory buffer,
which can be read by the fragment shaders
that calculate lighting later on.
And once again,
because most of the intermediate data
stays in the on-chip Tile Memory,
you could use memoryless attachments
to reduce the memory footprint.
Let's look at how to set up the render
pass descriptor for this configuration.
Let's define the dimension
of the on-chip tiles
so that they match
with the light culling scheme.
In this case,
I'm using 32-by-32 pixels for each tile.
One detail to keep in mind
is that Apple GPUs only support
a few different tile dimensions.
Then I allocate
the Threadgroup Memory buffer
used to store the per-tile light list.
I'm assuming that each tile
will contain up to eight unique lights.
Now it's time to set up
the G-buffer attachments.
Notice that I'm using
the dontCare store action,
as I don't want to store the G-buffers
back to System Memory.
And as discussed,
we can use memoryless textures
for those attachments.
The last three lines
configure the lighting attachment
to be cleared
at the beginning of the render pass,
and stored out to System Memory
at the end of the render pass.
And that's it. Our render pass descriptor
is now ready to be used.
Tile Shaders
are a powerful and flexible tool,
and over the last few years,
we at Apple prepared
a lot of material about it.
If you're looking for a deep dive
into Tile Shading,
please, see our Metal 2 for A11 Tech Talk
on "Tile Shading."
And if you want to know more
about tile-based light culling,
please, check our "Modern Rendering
with Metal" talk at WWDC19.
Now that we know about Tile Shaders,
let's go back to our discussion
about how to repurpose Tile Memory.
One more reason to have Tile Shaders
in your toolbox
is when you need to change the layout
of your Imageblock
or Threadgroup Memory.
When you are looking for opportunities
to merge passes,
sometimes you have data stored
in color attachments
or Imageblock fields
that are no longer needed.
A good example would be transitioning
an Imageblock from a G-buffer layout
to a layout suitable to sort
and accumulate
multiple layers of translucent geometry.
To implement this transition,
you need a fragment-based tile pipeline,
which is a Tile Shader dispatch
with a fragment function bound.
Let's look at the source code.
Here is the Imageblock layout
used for deferred shading.
I want to transition to a layout
that is useful for storing multiple layers
of translucent fragments per pixel.
This struct will serve
as the fragment shader output.
It has a single field marked
with the imageblock_data attribute.
The fragment function will read
a DeferredShadingFragment input
and return a FragmentOutput structure,
which will initialize the Imageblock
for multi-layer alpha blending.
The fragment shader will read any values
that need to be processed or preserved
from the input Imageblock,
and return the correct value
to repurpose the Imageblock itself.
So this concludes our discussion
about repurposing Tile Memory.
For further details,
please, see our Metal 2 for A11 Tech Talk
on "Image Blocks."
In the final section of this video,
we'll have a brief architectural overview
of the Apple Shader Core,
which is a key component of our GPUs.
Then we'll focus on
some optimization techniques
for your shaders.
The Apple Shader Core
uses a modern scalar architecture
that is closely aligned
to the Metal Shading Language
programming model.
And even if its math units are scalar,
the Apple Shader Core prefers to load
and store vector types directly.
The Shader Core can hoist execution
of constant code ahead of time,
and prefetch constant data,
once per draw or per dispatch.
This allows each parallel thread
to focus on its own unique work.
The Apple Shader Core contains
both a 16-bit and a 32-bit ALU,
so it can perform math
at different precisions
to reduce power usage
and increase performance.
You get most of these benefits for free,
but optimal performance
may require some tweaking of your shaders.
The next sections
will focus around three important topics.
Let's start talking about
memory address spaces
and how to use them effectively.
GPUs have multiple paths to memory
that are designed
for different access patterns.
For this reason,
the Metal Shading Language
implements the concept of address space.
Every time you declare
a buffer binding in your shaders,
the Metal Shading Language
requires you to tag your data
with a specific address space.
Choosing the right address space
is an important decision
that will directly impact
the performance of your shaders.
We're going to focus our attention
on the device and constant address spaces.
The device address space
is a read-write memory space
with virtually no size restrictions.
On the other hand,
the constant address space is read-only
and can fit only a limited amount of data.
Keep in mind
that this address space is optimized
for reuse of data that is constant across
all threads in the same draw or dispatch.
Picking the correct address space
is usually a matter of asking yourself
two simple questions.
First, how much data are we dealing with?
If the amount of data is not known
at compile time,
and each thread in your draw or dispatch
reads a different number of items,
then the data should be placed
in the device address space.
Second, if the size is fixed,
how many times is each item read?
If it's a few,
then use the device address space.
Otherwise, if the same item is reused
several times by different threads,
use the constant address space.
For instance, if you're indexing some data
via vertex ID or fragment coordinates,
then each thread will likely access
a different item.
In such case,
use the device address space.
Choosing the right address space
can be critical
for achieving the best performance.
Next, let's discuss
about one particular optimization
related to the constant address space.
In some cases, the shader compiler
can preload your buffers
into special registers
dedicated to constant data.
Let's call those registers "uniforms."
The preloading happens
before your shaders run,
so it's a helpful mechanism
to reduce latency.
Buffers tagged with
the constant address space
can likely be preloaded into uniforms.
And preloading is more likely to happen
if the offset of the data
within your buffer
can be determined at compile time.
And if you're indexing into an array,
its size needs to be known
at compile time as well.
Let's see an example.
The fragment shader on the left
reads an array of light structures
from System Memory.
In this example,
constant preloading will not happen.
That's because even if we specified
a const qualifier,
we're actually reading the light array
from the device address space.
But also, the size of the light array
is not determined at compile time.
To help the shader compiler
to preload your constant buffers,
make sure to provide your constants
as a single struct, passed by reference.
And for your constant arrays,
provide a size known at compile time.
The resulting code would look like this.
The light array is now encapsulated
in a struct loaded by reference
from constant address space.
And the maximum number of lights
is known at compile time
with the MAX_LIGHTS constant.
The shader compiler is now able
to preload the light array
into uniform registers.
Let's now talk about ALU data types
and how they can significantly affect
the performance of your shaders.
First, some definitions.
By data types, we mean whatever types
you use throughout your shader code.
Apple GPUs are optimized
for 16-bit data types.
So when you use
a type bigger than 16 bits,
you will allocate
more registers accordingly.
And if you use a smaller type,
you will still consume
a full 16-bit register.
Using 16-bit data types
instead of 32-bit data types,
your shaders will require less registers,
leading to an increase
in Shader Core occupancy.
And higher occupancy means
that more GPU threads
can be in-flight at the same time,
which is great to improve
the latency-hiding capabilities
of the Shader Core.
But also, in most cases, 16-bit data types
use faster arithmetic instructions
than the equivalent 32-bit data types,
leading to a significantly better
ALU utilization.
For all those reasons,
use half and short
instead of float and int when possible.
Don't worry about type conversions.
Those are typically free,
even between single-precision
and half-precision floating-point values.
Let's see some examples.
In this example, consider a kernel using
the thread position within a threadgroup
for some computation.
I'm using 32 bits,
but the maximum threadgroup size
supported by Metal
can easily fit in a 16-bit value.
The threadgroup position
within a dispatch grid, however,
could potentially require
a larger data type,
depending on the grid size.
In this case, for the grid size I'm using,
a 16-bit value is enough.
The resulting code would use
a smaller number of registers
to compute local and global positions
within the dispatch,
potentially increasing
the Shader Core occupancy.
Next, let's talk about another case
where it is possible
to use more registers than expected,
this time through floating-point literals.
The Metal Shading Language specifies
that operations have to happen
at the highest precision
among all operands.
So even if the "a" and "b" arguments
are using half-precision,
the compiler has to promote
the whole expression to single-precision.
That's because of the minus two
and five literals.
So when you're writing
half-precision code,
make sure to use half-precision literals
using the "h" letter suffix.
Finally, let's talk about how to avoid
some common pitfalls
in the memory accesses of your shaders.
In general,
try to avoid stack-allocated arrays,
as sometimes they force the compiler
to generate suboptimal code.
For instance,
the compiler cannot easily optimize away
dynamically indexed arrays
initialized at runtime.
In this case,
if the value of the index argument
is not known at compile time,
the compiler would likely spill
to memory "a," "b" and "c"
and read back the correct value
based on the index argument.
In this other example, instead,
the loop will likely get unrolled,
so the compiler will be able to know
the value of the index variable
at compile time,
optimizing away any spilling.
The best way to know if you have
stack accesses getting spilled to memory
is to use the GPU Frame Debugger in Xcode.
If you see a warning sign
next to one of your draws,
click on the Pipeline Statistics section.
This will open a Remarks panel
containing a message similar to this
if you hit any spilling
due to stack accesses.
Another thing to look out for is the type
of the indices used in memory accesses.
The best practice is to use signed types
wherever you can.
Let's consider the following example.
Here you have a simple loop
accessing a buffer.
The loop index variable uses
an unsigned type.
Unsigned types have
a well-defined wrapping semantic
in the Metal Shading Language.
So, if the index overflows,
the compiler needs to make sure
that it wraps around correctly,
and such behavior comes at a cost.
Let's take a look
at a memory access pattern
involving wrapping.
In this case,
start has a value larger than end.
In the Metal Shading Language,
this is perfectly valid,
and what will happen is that the index
will wrap around when reaching UINT_MAX.
To implement this behavior,
the shader compiler
cannot vectorize the loads together,
potentially affecting
the performance of this shader.
If you need the wrapping behavior,
of course, use an unsigned type.
However, most of the times,
this is not necessary.
Replacing the index with a signed type
will tell the compiler
you don't need a wrapping semantic,
as overflow of signed values
is undefined behavior
in the Metal Shading Language.
With this change,
the shader compiler is now able
to vectorize the four loads together,
likely leading to
a performance improvement.
And once again,
batching your memory accesses together
is generally a good thing for performance.
The compiler will try to do it for you,
but sometimes it needs your help.
Let's consider the following example.
The main loop is accessing fields
"a" and "c" of the foo struct
at the same time.
The problem here is that those fields
are not adjacent,
as "b" is sitting between them.
Therefore, the compiler will not be able
to load them together.
To fix that, you can merge the fields
manually like this.
Using a vector data type directly
forces the compiler
to emit a vectorized load in this case.
You can achieve the same behavior
by simply modifying your structure
so that the fields are next to each other.
And this concludes our discussion
about the Apple Shader Core.
Okay, let's review what we learned today.
In this video, Mike and I showed you
many different optimization techniques
for the Apple GPU architecture.
We discussed about eliminating
unnecessary dependencies
to maximize vertex,
fragment and compute overlap.
Next, we discussed about avoiding
unnecessary pass changes
through pass reordering and merging.
We also talked about how to minimize
memory bandwidth
through proper use of load
and store actions.
We then discussed about how to maximize
the efficiency
of the hidden surface removal hardware
by ordering draws properly
and paying attention to the uses of Metal
that can affect the opaqueness
of your fragments.
We also showed you how to use
Metal's TBDR-specific features
to optimize your apps
for Apple GPUs even further.
We showed you how to optimize
for the Apple Shader Core
by using 16-bit data types where possible,
and using the right address space
to enable constant data prefetch.
And then we discussed about
how to avoid common pitfalls
in the memory accesses of your shaders.
We are now at the end of this road
that started with porting
your native x86 apps
to the new Apple Silicon Macs.
So, what are the next steps?
If you want to profile your apps,
the Metal System Trace instrument
is the best tool at your disposal.
And remember that we at Apple
prepared a lot of material
to help you squeeze
every bit of performance out of your apps.
In particular, check out our new talk
about Metal app profiling
in Xcode 12 from my colleague Sam.
And don't forget to check last year's
WWDC talks
about "Delivering Optimized
Metal Apps and Games,"
as well as
the "Modern Rendering with Metal" talk.
Thank you.