Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Steve Moseley, a UIKit engineer,
and this is "Handle Trackpad
and Mouse Input."
In this video, we're going to talk about
ways to make your app feel responsive
to the indirect input mechanisms
like trackpads and mice
introduced in macOS Catalina
and iPadOS 13.4.
There are some common updates
that apply to every app,
and some advanced updates
for apps that want to go the extra mile.
In common updates,
we'll go over handling pointer movement,
locking the pointer, and handling
scroll input and trackpad gestures.
In advanced updates,
we'll go over handling button mask
and keyboard modifiers,
accepting or rejecting events
with new UIGestureRecognizer
and UIGestureRecognizerDelegate methods,
distinguishing touches
from indirect input devices,
and opting in to some new behavior
with an Info.plist key.
Let's take a look at those common updates.
With a mouse or trackpad,
users expect
to interact with your application
without touching the screen.
Notice how Safari reveals their toolbar
when the pointer moves into that region,
or how they show the tab-close button
when the pointer moves into a tab.
Safari responds to pointer movement
like this with UIHoverGestureRecognizer.
UIHoverGestureRecognizer was introduced
with Mac Catalyst in Catalina
and is now available in iPadOS.
It is a normal gesture recognizer
and works on iPad
just like it does on the Mac.
If you're overriding
UIApplication.sendEvent,
you'll notice it's driven by
a new event type, EventType.hover.
You instantiate a UIHoverGestureRecognizer
with a target and action,
just like you would
any other gesture recognizer.
In your action callback,
you'll switch over the gesture state
and perform appropriate actions.
Note that gesture state "began"
maps to the pointer
entering your gesture view's bounds...
and "ended" maps to the pointer
exiting your gesture view's bounds.
Here,
we're revealing video playback controls
based on whether the pointer
is within our view.
If you inspect touches
in your iPad or Mac Catalyst apps,
you'll see there are a few new phases
to track pointer movement.
These phases map to the overall
pointer movement within your window.
RegionEntered means
the pointer has entered your window.
RegionMoved means
the pointer is within your window
but has not clicked or pressed down yet.
RegionExited means
it has left your window.
Notice that these phases
do not always align
with the gesture states we discussed
for UIHoverGestureRecognizer.
The UIHoverGestureRecognizer states
will only map
to what the pointer is doing
within the bounds of your gesture's view,
whereas these phases pertain to what
the pointer is doing within your window.
Use UIHoverGestureRecognizer
to respond to pointer movement
or for hiding and revealing content,
like we saw in the Safari example earlier.
Don't use it to modify
the appearance of the pointer
or apply a hover effect.
For either of those,
you should use UIPointerInteraction.
For more on UIHoverGestureRecognizer,
see our talk from 2019,
"Taking iPad Apps for the Mac
to the Next Level."
And if you are interested in modifying
the appearance of the pointer,
check out "Build for the iPadOS Pointer."
In addition
to responding to pointer movement,
some apps, like games, would like
to lock the movement of the pointer.
New in iPadOS 14 and Mac Catalyst Big Sur,
we've introduced API
to allow you to do just that.
It's really easy to use.
Set your lock preference
with UIViewController API
and observe the resolved value
with the new UIPointerLockState.
That's it.
The pointer is a shared resource,
so ultimately, the system decides
whether the pointer should be locked.
That means
your preferred pointer lock state
may or may not be honored.
Let's see how these two pieces of API
work together.
Your view controller sets
a prefersPointerLocked value of "true."
As long as some requirements are met,
the system sets the lock value
of your scene to "true" as well.
That status is reflected
in the UIPointerLockState of your scene.
What happens
if you need to present content
and you want to disable the lock?
Let's say your game
experiences a networking error,
and you'd like to present
a UIAlertController.
The user expects to interact
with that content using the pointer
just like they can
throughout the rest of the system.
No problem.
The default value
of prefersPointerLocked is "false."
When UIAlertController is presented,
its value of prefersPointerLocked
is observed by the system
and the pointer lock is disabled.
As view controllers
are presented or dismissed,
your scene's pointer lock value
is automatically updated,
which means you don't need
to keep track of this state.
If you want the pointer to be locked
in your scene,
just override
prefersPointerLocked property
of your view controller to be "true."
If at some point you want to disable
or change this value,
just call setNeedsUpdate
OfPrefersPointerLocked.
If there's a part of your application
that needs to see the current lock status,
you obtain the pointer lock state
from your scene
and look at the isLocked property.
Here, we have an object
that wants to be notified
of changes to the pointer lock state
of its scene.
It obtains the pointerLockState object,
then registers to observe that object.
When UIPointerLockState
.didChangeNotification is posted,
the closure will be executed
and the isLocked value
of UIPointerLockState
will be passed on
to another part of the application.
As mentioned in the diagram,
there are some requirements
your scene needs to fulfill
in order for your preferred
pointer lock value to be considered.
The requirements
are different per platform,
so let's start with iPadOS.
First, your scene must be full screen.
This means your application cannot be
in Split View multitasking or Slide Over.
It also means there can be
no other app in Slide Over.
Full screen here does not mean
using the UIRequiresFullScreen
Info.plist key,
simply that your scene
must occupy the entire screen.
Second, your scene must be
in the foregroundActive activation state.
This means it cannot be deactivated
for any reason,
like Control Center
or Notification Center being presented.
In Mac Catalyst, your application
must be the frontmost application
for your prefersPointerLocked value
to be considered by the system.
And if you have multiple windows,
the window where you'd like the pointer
to be locked
should also be ordered to the front.
If your application
fails to meet these requirements,
the pointer lock is disabled.
On iPadOS,
if a slide-over app is displayed,
or on macOS, if your application
is no longer frontmost,
isLocked will change to "false,"
and you will be notified
through UIPointerLockState
DidChangeNotification.
However, you don't need to do anything
to get the pointer lock back.
The system continuously evaluates
these requirements.
So, as conditions change,
so will the pointer lock status
of your scene.
You don't need to call setNeedsUpdate
OfPrefersPointerLocked.
Remember that it's the system's discretion
to lock the pointer.
These requirements are subject to change
and are informed by user behavior.
So your application should not assume
that your prefersPointerLocked value
will always be honored.
You should always observe changes
to isLocked
and respond
in your application appropriately.
Finally, pointer locking
is not available on all scenes.
For those, the pointerLockState property
on UIScene will return "nil"
to indicate that locking is not available.
When locking the pointer,
you'll also want to look at
relative movement from trackpads and mice.
For more information on that,
see the "Bring Keyboard
and Mouse Gaming to iPad" video.
Let's talk about handling scroll input.
It is important to ensure
that all regions of your app
respond correctly
with connected pointing devices.
If users can pan something
with their finger,
they'll expect to pan the content
with either a two-finger gesture
or a mouse scroll wheel.
Here we see that the custom controls
in Control Center
have been updated to pan
with two-finger swipes on a trackpad.
You handle scroll input in your app
by updating UIPanGestureRecognizer's
allowedScrollTypesMask property.
Simply give it the set of scroll types
you want to handle
and that will enable EventType.scroll
support for your gesture.
UIScrollView's pan gesture recognizer
updates allowedScrollTypesMask
to handle all types of scroll input,
but standard UIPanGestureRecognizers
have no mask by default.
So you'll want to update this property
for all your application's pan gestures.
Let's say you have an app that hides
content on either side of its main view.
The user can reveal this content
with a horizontal swipe,
which is powered by a pan gesture.
Your designer has determined
revealing this content with a scroll wheel
doesn't feel very natural,
so you're going only support
continuous scroll types with this gesture.
Simply update the pan gesture's
allowedScrollTypesMask
to UIScrollTypeMaskContinuous.
Perhaps there's a custom pull-to-refresh
interaction in your application
that's also powered by a pan gesture.
For this gesture,
you might want to respond
to all types of scroll input,
so just update
its allowedScrollTypesMask property
to UIScrollTypeMaskAll.
Handling pinch and rotate
trackpad gestures is even easier.
Just use UIPinchGestureRecognizer
and UIRotationGestureRecognizer.
To ensure every app can handle
these types of indirect gestures,
these recognizers
use a compatibility mode.
By default, they are driven
by gesture-simulating touches.
UIKit creates these touches
a fixed distance apart
and simulates their movement in response
to movement on the touch surface.
Starting in iPadOS 13.4
and macOS Catalina 10.15.4,
applications can move these gestures
out of the compatibility mode
and respond to a new event type,
EventType.transform.
This event type
comes directly from the input device
which enables
precise pinch and rotate gestures
like your users expect.
To get this new event type
and to move these gestures
out of their compatibility mode,
you'll need to add a key
to your application's Info.plist.
We'll talk more about that in a bit.
The good news
is that there is no additional code
required for either of these scenarios.
With or without the key,
UIPinchGestureRecognizer
and UIRotationGestureRecognizer
know how to handle this input.
And when you do add
the Info.plist key to your app,
you don't need to write code
to handle the new event type.
It just works.
Do note, though, that if
you're adopting the Info.plist key,
these gestures will no longer be driven
by touches during trackpad input.
In that case,
numberOfTouches will return zero
and locationOfTouch:inView
may throw an exception.
And those are the common updates
that apply to every app.
Let's move on and talk about
some advanced updates
to surprise and delight your pro users.
Button mask and key modifiers
are a great way
to add advanced functionality
to your application.
Context menus use button mask
to recognize two-finger taps
and secondary clicks
so they can provide a more streamlined UI.
And Numbers uses key modifiers
so I can select multiple rows
with the pointer and Shift key modifier,
just like I can with my finger.
UIEvent.ButtonMask is a new type in iOS,
and it's the set of buttons pressed
while clicking with a pointing device.
It's present on both UIEvent and
UIGestureRecognizer as buttonMask,
giving you a convenient way to respond
to just the primary button of the device,
create features that respond
to two-finger taps
and secondary mouse buttons,
or target high-number mouse buttons.
Note that the button mask
on UIGestureRecognizer
is from the last event processed.
If you want a simple way to require
a specific button mask before firing,
we've updated UITapGestureRecognizer
with buttonMaskRequired.
Just give it a button mask,
and you're done.
There's even a convenience function
on ButtonMask
that returns the appropriate mask value
for high-number buttons.
Together with buttonMaskRequired,
it's really easy to target
high-number mouse buttons
as accelerators for advanced functionality
in your app.
If you've used UICommand
or UIPointerInteraction,
you're familiar with UIKeyModifierFlags.
It's the set of keyboard modifiers
pressed during an event.
We've brought UIKeyModifierFlags
to both UIEvent and UIGestureRecognizer
as modifierFlags.
This property can be used
during gesture callbacks
to alter how you respond to an event.
For instance, clicking on a link in Safari
with the Command key pressed
causes the link to be opened in a new tab.
Like buttonMask,
UIGestureRecognizer's modifierFlags
is populated
from the last event processed.
For more on how to have
a great keyboard experience in your app,
check out the "Support Hardware Keyboards
in Your App" video.
Button mask and key modifiers
are easy to use.
Targeting a third mouse button
is as easy as using buttonMask.button
to get the appropriate mask
and setting the result
on UITapGestureRecognizer.
buttonMaskRequired.
That's it.
Let's go back to our UIHoverGesture
Recognizer example from earlier
to see how modifier flags work.
Previously,
we revealed video playback controls
whenever the pointer entered
our gesture's view.
If we optionally want to show
chapter-selection controls
whenever the UIKeyModifierAlternate
is pressed,
we just need to check
if modifierFlags contains that value.
Button mask and modifier flags
are especially powerful
when combined with new API
for UIGestureRecognizerDelegate
and UIGestureRecognizer subclasses.
These methods are called for
only the events handled by your gesture,
so UIPinchGestureRecognizer
won't be asked about EventType.scroll.
These methods give you an opportunity
to accept or reject those events
based on button mask, modifier flags,
or other properties.
Note that these methods happen
before the event is fully processed
by the gesture,
so UIGestureRecognizer's
buttonMask and modifierFlags properties
will not include the new values
found in the event.
If you're inspecting either of those
properties in these methods,
you should look at the values on UIEvent,
not the ones on UIGestureRecognizer.
As gestures like UIPanGestureRecognizer
and UIPinchGestureRecognizer
respond to multiple
non-touch-based events,
you should move any event-related code
in methods like
gestureRecognizer(shouldReceive touch:)
into either of these two new methods.
Let's look at some examples
for how you can use this in your app.
We have a UIGestureRecognizer subclass
that only wants to receive events
with a buttonMask of secondary.
You might do this for functionality
driven exclusively by two-finger taps
or secondary mouse-button clicks.
Start by overriding the gesture
subclass method shouldReceive(_ event).
In that method, you simply need to check
if the buttonMask on the event
is exactly equal to secondary.
If it is, we receive the event.
If not, we reject it.
As mentioned earlier, while buttonMask
exists on UIGestureRecognizer as well,
we shouldn't look at that property
in this method.
ShouldReceive(_ event)
happens prior to the event
being fully processed by the gesture,
so UIGestureRecognizer's buttonMask
will not be up to date at this point.
It's common to allow click
plus the Control key modifier
to perform the same actions
as a secondary click.
We can update our example
for that as well.
We just need to modify
our shouldReceive method.
First, check if the buttonMask
is exactly primary.
If that's true, we check if modifierFlags
is equal to UIKeyModifierControl.
We'll receive the event
if it's a secondary click or Control click
and reject it if it isn't.
Let's bring back our video example again.
We want to add another hover gesture
over the video
that shows closed-caption controls.
The user can already get to this feature
through a settings menu,
but we'd like to give them
a quick way to do this
with a key modifier and the hover gesture.
We can instantiate
our HoverGestureRecognizer like before.
This time,
we'll set ourselves as the delegate,
and implement the gestureRecognizer
shouldReceive event method.
In that method, we'll receive the event
if UIKeyModifierAlternate is pressed,
and reject the event if it isn't.
As you're considering how to polish
pointer support for your app,
you may want to distinguish touches
originating from a pointing device
from ones originating from a finger.
You especially may want to consider this
if you have a lot custom hit-testing code
in your app.
As the pointer is more precise
than a finger,
you can reduce any expanded
hit-testing regions for those touches,
providing a more precise experience.
Touches from a pointing device
are given the new TouchType
of indirectPointer
if you opt in to the UIApplication
SupportsIndirectInputEvents
Info.plist key.
You can use this touch type
with existing API
like UIGestureRecognizer.
allowedTouchTypes
to have gestures that only respond
to pointer clicks,
or ones that only respond
to finger-based touches.
Let's talk some more about UIApplication
SupportsIndirectInputEvents.
It's a Boolean key you add
to your application's Info.plist.
This key is not required
to enable pointer interactions,
button clicking, scroll input,
or trackpad gestures.
All of those work with or without the key.
It is required in order to get
the new touch type indirect pointer
and EventType.transform.
Existing projects do not have this key set
and will need to add it.
Starting with iOS 14
and macOS Big Sur SDKs,
new UIKit and SwiftUI projects
will have this value set to "true."
In a future release,
the default will change
and we will no longer consult
the value of this key.
Let's see exactly what happens
if this key is or is not present.
It's helpful to think of UIApplication
SupportsIndirectInputEvents
as opting out of a compatibility mode.
We added this compatibility mode
so that users would have
a great initial experience
with indirect input on iPadOS 13.4.
So if the key is not present,
as it is for all existing projects,
your application
is in this compatibility mode.
Clicks from pointing devices
are TouchType.direct,
the same as for finger-based touches,
so you won't be able
to distinguish them apart.
Pinching and rotating on the trackpad
result in gesture-simulating touches
that may incidentally activate
other gestures.
If the key is present and true,
your application
is out of the compatibility mode
and new features are enabled.
Clicks from pointing devices
are TouchType.indirectPointer,
allowing you to target
and modify functionality
for precision pointing devices.
Pinching and rotating on the trackpad
emits a new event type
directly from the input device:
EventType.transform.
This enables
precise pinch and rotate gestures
that won't incidentally activate
other recognizers.
With this key, you are fully entering
the new world of indirect input
on iPadOS and Mac Catalyst.
With that,
there are a few things to be aware of.
New event types like EventType.scroll
or EventType.transform
are not touch-based,
so you'll need to be careful
with touch-related gestureRecognizer API.
When UIPanGestureRecognizer
UIPinchGestureRecognizer
or UIRotationGestureRecognizer
are driven by these new event types,
numberOfTouches will return zero
and locationOfTouch:inView
may throw an exception.
Also be aware that any code you may have
in your shouldReceivetouch
delegate methods for these gestures
will not be run
when they're driven by these events.
After opting in to this key,
UIPinchGestureRecognizer
and UIRotationGestureRecognizer
are removed from their compatibility mode.
So any incidentally activated gestures
from that mode
will no longer be triggered.
In this new world of indirect input,
gestures respond
to multiple types of events.
Because of that, you may find it helpful
to detect which event
your gesture recognizer is responding to.
You can use the shouldReceive methods
we discussed earlier to help with that.
When responding to EventType.touches,
you can use API like numberOfTouches
or locationOfTouch:inView.
If you're responding to other events,
you should avoid those methods.
There are some simple things you can do
to make your app come alive
with trackpad and mouse input.
Enable scroll input for your pan gestures.
Respond to pointer movement
by hiding or revealing content.
Add the Info.plist key to your app
to gain the new TouchType and EventType,
allowing you to customize functionality
for pointer-based touches
and have precise pinch and rotate gestures
in your app.
Use new event properties
and gesture recognizer API
to delight your users
with alternate responses
to button presses and keyboard modifiers.
Thanks for watching this video.
I can't wait to try out your updated apps.