Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone. My name is Shu Gao.
Today I'm going to talk about
HDR video editing
and play back using AVFoundation.
Apple brought HDR play back on iOS
a couple of years back,
and on macOS last year.
This year, we're also adding HDR support
in our framework
to enable HDR for video editing.
In this session, I will show you how
you can take advantage of that,
using AVFoundation.
We will start
with a very quick introduction to HDR
followed by a video of different
video editing workflows.
Then we'll talk about how to enable HDR
on them.
We will also discuss some finer controls
you can have
in configuring the HDR editing,
mainly about the color properties.
At the end, we'll touch upon HDR playback.
Now, what's HDR?
HDR stands for high dynamic range.
It greatly extends the dynamic range
of the video
above and beyond what is capable
by standard dynamic range video.
Because of this,
you can produce more vibrant videos
with brighter whites and deeper blacks,
better contrast
and more details in shadows
and highlights.
To give you a quantitative idea,
SDR video is limited to up to 100 candelas
per square meter, or nits.
HDR video can go 100 times brighter
all the way up to 10,000 nits.
HDR is often implicitly paired
with Wide Color.
The combination of Wide Color
and high dynamic range
can define a much larger color volume.
In other words, it can produce colors
you have never seen in any SDR video.
To accommodate the larger luminance
and color range,
HDR is also typically associated
with higher bit depths,
with 10-bit common for distribution media.
Transfer functions describe
how scene linear lights
is mapped to nonlinear code values
in the video,
and then back to display light.
HDR video comes with either HLG,
or PQ transfer function.
Apple supports both types
of transfer functions.
To get a more detailed introduction
to HDR,
I recommend you check out
the HDR Export session
of this year's WWDC.
With this high-level concept of HDR,
let's move on
to review video editing workflows.
Before I get to the details,
I would like to direct your attention
to the previous WWDC sessions
on video editing.
If you're new to video editing,
I highly recommend
you watch the recordings of these talks.
They will help you
to get a basic understanding
of the important classes
we will discuss here.
Here is a common workflow
for video editing.
You start with an asset,
or a set of assets,
then you build AVComposition
and AVVideoComposition.
These two objects together
specify how to slice, splice,
position and blend tracks in assets
to achieve the artistic intent
of your video editing.
AVComposition specifies
the temporal alignment
of the source tracks.
AVVideoComposition specifies
geometry transformation
and blending of tracks
at any given time point.
We can use these two objects
to construct an AVPlayerItem
and create an AVPlayer from it
to play back the editing effects.
This is the preview pass of our workflow.
We can also use AVComposition
and AVVideoComposition
to provide to an AVAssetExportSession
which can write the editing results
to a movie file.
Here is another workflow
using a lower level API.
This is an export only workflow.
There's no preview path.
We start with an asset,
use an AVAssetReader to read the samples
of the asset.
The editing work is inserted
in the AVAssetReaderVideoComposition
Output object.
This object contains
an AVVideoComposition object
that specifies the details
of the editing intentions.
We can then extract the edited frames
from the AVAssetReaderVideoComposition
Output object,
send it to an AVAssetWriter
to write it out to a movie file.
Now we have reviewed
the video editing workflows.
Next, let's look at how we can enable
HDR on these workflows.
In each of the workflows we just reviewed,
AVVideoComposition is in the center.
Some of the workflows also need
an AVComposition object,
but it is specifying the temporal
alignment of the tracks only,
so it is pretty much HDR agnostic.
The AVVideoComposition, on the other hand,
has to do with blending
and transformations,
which must be HDR aware
to support HDR editing.
When you preview your editing,
you also want to make sure your system
can play back HDR video.
We will touch upon that
toward the end of this session.
If you export your video composition,
you want to make sure you select
the right settings
on your AVAssetExportSession
or AVAssetWriter.
There is a separate session this year
that provides all the details
you need to know on exporting HDR.
Now, assume your display
can display HDR video,
and your export settings are set
to the ones supporting HDR,
let's dig deep into AVVideoComposition
and see what you need to do
to enable HDR supports there.
There are three ways to construct
an AVVideoComposition.
We will discuss them one by one.
The first one is to build it ground up
using AVMutableVideoComposition
but use a built-in compositor.
This is best suited if you want to blend
multiple layers of video,
and/or you want to apply
frame level geometry transformations,
like cropping, scaling,
translation and rotation.
The most common use case
is for transition effects
between two clips of video,
like swipe, fade in, fade out, et cetera.
This method is not good if you want
to apply some filtering effects,
like blurring, color tint
or some fancy artistic effects.
Let's look at a code snippet that
builds AVVideoComposition in this way.
We start with an empty
AVMutableVideoComposition
and build it out.
Note that the video
composition instruction,
contains a complex hierarchy of parameters
to instruct the compositor
precisely how to blend
or transform the layers.
You can also have an array
of composition instructions,
each covers a different segment
in the timeline of your editing.
In our example here,
there's only one element in the array.
If you do have multiple video
composition instructions,
they must not overlap in time
and must have no gaps in between.
We will not expand on that
for the consideration of time.
We left the customVideoCompositor Class
field unset.
This tells the framework that we want
to use the built-in compositor
to carry out the composition instructions.
Note that nothing here
says anything about HDR.
In fact, you may have a piece of code
in your existing video editing app
looking just like this.
Now, let's look at the code
you need to add
to make this AVVideoComposition
HDR capable.
Nothing.
Apple has put in the heavy lifting
in the framework,
especially in the built-in compositor,
to do the right thing
when the video frames are HDR.
If you take your existing
video editing app
using built-in compositor,
without modifying it,
and start to feed HDR video to it,
chances are that you will get
HDR video out
with the same composition instructions
properly applied to the HDR sources.
Now, let's look at the second way
of constructing a AVVideoComposition,
that is to use the
"applyingCIFiltersWithHandler" parameter
in the constructor
of AVMutableVideoComposition.
This is useful when you want to apply
filtering effects
and you are working
on a single layer of video.
This method does not give you the ability
to blend multiple layers.
Let's look at the code.
You can see we are using
a different constructor
of the AVMutableVideoComposition class.
We pass in the asset we want
to apply the composition on,
and a handler that applies CIFilters
to the frames of the first
enabled video track of the asset.
Please note that only the first enabled
video track of the asset gets filtered
and come out of the video composition.
When your handler is invoked,
a AVAsynchronousCIImageFilteringRequest
object is passed in.
You can use this request object to get
the current frame of the input track
as a CIImage object,
suitable to send to a CIFilter
to apply filtering effects.
Once you have a filtered output image,
you can call "request.finish"
to send it out.
This way of building the video composition
frees you up from setting up
the composition instructions
and other churns of constructing
the AVVideoComposition object.
It lets you focus on
and gives you full control on how
you want to filter the source images.
In this example, we pass the sourceImage
to a built-in "CIZoomBlur" CIFilter.
You can do more complicated
filtering effects
by chaining multiple built-in CIFilters,
or apply your own CIFilter
that you can build from your own
CoreImage metal kernel code.
Now, how do we bring up this type
of AVVideoComposition to support HDR?
Again, the answer is mostly
you don't need to do anything.
If your handler is calling
into CoreImage's built-in CIFilters,
all of them can handle HDR sources.
The only thing you need to worry about
is if you are using your own CIFilter
built from your own metal
CoreImage kernel code in your handler.
In the metal CoreImage kernel code,
you need to be aware of the extended
dynamic range that comes with HDR.
Let's look at a couple of examples.
This is a piece
of metal CoreImage kernel code
that is aware
of the extended dynamic range.
The intention of this filter
is to highlight any pixel that exceeds
the normal zero to 1 dynamic range.
If any of the r, g,
or b channel's intensity exceeds 1,
we will paint that pixel
in ultra-bright red.
You may have noticed that we include
CoreImage header here,
and the syntax is a bit different
from your normal metal code.
This type of code is called
the "Metal CoreImage Kernel."
If you want to learn more about it,
you can go to this session
in this year's WWDC.
Here is an example that an existing
SDR metal CoreImage filter
may break down with HDR.
This is a color inverter.
In the SDR world,
you assume the maximum intensity is 1
and you subtract
each channel's intensity from 1.
With HDR frames, your resulted intensity
could go to negative.
Next, let's talk about the third way
of creating an AVVideoComposition,
which is the most flexible way,
using a custom compositor.
It allows you to blend
multiple video layers,
do frame-level geometry transformations
on each layer,
and it also gives you control
to apply filtering effects to each layer.
With this greater flexibility,
you need to do more yourself.
First, you need to define
a custom compositor class.
The framework will use your class
to create and maintain the lifecycle
of a custom compositor object
to do the real composite job.
To construct
the AVVideoComposition object,
just like in the built-in compositor case,
you start with an empty
AVMutableVideoComposition,
and you build it up.
The difference here
is that you tell the framework
about your custom compositor class
by setting the customVideoCompositorClass
field of the video composition.
What do you need to do to enable HDR
on this type of AVVideoComposition?
It's not free
like in the previous two cases.
First obvious thing
is the real work you do
in your custom compositor
needs to be HDR capable.
Most HDR sources come in
with 10-bit pixel formats.
Your custom compositor needs
to be able to handle them.
When you are manipulating pixel values,
you need to be aware of the extended
dynamic range brought by HDR sources.
After you have done all that,
there are two more group of things
you need to set
on the custom compositor class
to inform the framework that
you are capable of doing the HDR work.
This includes, number one,
indicate that you support 10-bit
or higher bit depth pixel formats
for both input and output.
Number two,
indicate that your custom compositor
can accept HDR source frames as its input.
Let's look at the code.
This custom compositor is set up properly
to support HDR.
First, we set both
sourcePixelBufferAttributes
and requiredPixelBufferAttributes-
ForRenderContext
to include 10-bit pixel formats.
Fill in the formats
that you actually support.
The framework will make sure
you get source frames
in one of the listed pixel formats,
and create the render context
for your output frame
in the format you can support.
It will do format conversions
if necessary.
Next is
the supportsHDRSourceFrames field.
This is a new field introduced for HDR.
You must set it to true to welcome HDR
source frames into your custom compositor.
If you don't have this field,
or set it false,
the framework will think
you cannot handle HDR frames
and will convert them to standard
dynamic range before sending it to you.
So don't forget to set this field
after all your hard work
to actually handle HDR
in your custom compositor.
Like I stated in the introduction,
HDR video normally comes with Wide Color.
So you also need to make sure your
custom compositor can handle Wide Color.
Actually, the framework assumes
if you are capable of handling HDR,
you are also capable
of handling Wide Color.
Here I'm setting it to true explicitly.
The startRequest is the function where
you do the real work of the composition.
As mentioned before,
the work you do need to be aware
of the extended dynamic range of HDR.
Next, let's see a demo of HDR
enabled custom compositor in action.
Depending on whether your streaming link
is HDR or not,
you may not be able to see this demo
in HDR,
but the video editing effect
should still be evident.
This is the live preview produced
by a custom compositor
using a custom CIFilter
to add filtering effects.
It is an upgraded version of the HDR
highlighting metal CoreImage kernel code
we saw earlier.
Here, instead of painting the HDR region
to solid color, we use rolling stripes.
The bright stripes you see is our proof
that the source video is actually HDR.
If you download our sample code
and run it on your new macOS,
you will experience the high dynamic range
of the ultra-bright red stripes.
So far, we have talked about
different ways
of constructing AVVideoComposition
for your video editing,
and how to enable HDR support on them.
Next, we will go further to talk about
how you can control some aspect
of the HDR behavior once you enable it,
mainly controlling the color properties
of your video composition.
If you just do the bare minimum
to turn on HDR support
and leave everything else in default,
what will happen
if you get different types of video coming
into your video composition?
This table shows the output format
of the video composition
given different mixture of inputs.
Apple supports two types of HDR video,
categorized by their transfer functions,
namely HLG and PQ.
So you have three possible types
of inputs, HLG, PQ and SDR.
If you don't specify
the composition color properties,
the framework takes a policy,
preferring HLG over PQ, over SDR.
This table shows how the policy
play out for two video inputs.
This can easily expand to multiple inputs.
To change this behavior,
you can specify the color properties
of your video composition
in your AVVideoComposition object.
Namely the colorPrimaries,
the colorTransferFunction
and the colorYCbCrMatrix fields.
If you set these three to color properties
with HLG transfer function,
the output of your composition
will always be HLG
regardless of your input video format.
Likewise, you can set them to PQ
or SDR properties.
Under the hood, the framework converts
the input source frames
to the specified color properties
before it sends them to the compositor,
be it the built-in compositor
or the custom compositor.
Remember I mentioned earlier
in this session that
if you have an existing video editing app
that uses built-in compositor
and start feeding HDR sources to it,
chances are that you will get HDR output
without modifying your code.
Well, I said "chances are" for a reason.
If your app does not explicitly specify
these color properties
in the AVVideoComposition,
the default behavior
of the built-in compositor
will produce HDR video.
If, however, your app is explicitly
setting these properties
to SDR color space,
then the built-in compositor
will respect that setting
and convert the HDR sources
to SDR before compositing.
There are scenarios that this is actually
what you do want.
For example, you want to attach
your edited HDR video to an e-mail
and you know the recipient doesn't have
the system capable
of playing back HDR video.
In this case, you want to produce
an SDR version of your editing.
Let's look at some typical values
for these color properties.
Here is a table showing example values
of the video composition color properties
you can set.
Note that if you want your composition
to be in HLG,
you must set the color transfer function
to "HLG."
If you want your composition to be in PQ,
you must set the transfer function
to "PQ."
For either HLG or PQ,
you normally want to set
the colorPrimaries and YCbCrMatrix
to ITU_R_2020,
which are associated with Wide Color.
We have talked about video compositions.
Now let's look at the playback path.
Like we reviewed earlier,
to playback your editing,
you build your pipeline like this.
After you constructed the AVPlayerItem
from your AVComposition
and AVVideoComposition,
you create an AVPlayer
to play that AVPlayerItem,
just like what you have been doing
for any playback.
There's nothing special here.
You would expect
your HDR video composition
to be displayed in HDR, right?
This is not always the case.
You have to make sure
that you are on a system
that is capable of playing back HDR.
That's obvious, but how do you find out
if you are on such a system?
There is the eligibleForHDRPlayback API
coming to rescue.
Instead of remembering which platform
supports HDR playback,
you can query
this eligibleForHDRPlayback field
on the AVPlayer class to get an answer.
Note this is a class var,
so you don't need to have
an AVPlayer instance to query.
If the property is "true,"
it means, number one, your system
is capable of consuming HDR video,
and number two,
there is at least one display,
built in or external,
that can display HDR video.
I would like to point out here
that HDR playback is not available
on watchOS and macOS Catalyst.
Here is an example code that sets
the video composition color properties
based on the HDR playback eligibility.
If the system is not capable
of playing back HDR,
we don't want to waste
the processing power
to compose in HDR,
so we set the color properties to SDR.
Please note this field is only
a playback statement.
A system that is not capable
of playing back HDR
does not mean it cannot export HDR either.
You can still set your composition
color properties to HDR
for your export path.
You can check out the "HDR Export" session
of this year's WWDC
for information on supported platforms
for HDR export.
Now, let's summarize
what we have discussed today.
First and foremost,
HDR video editing is available.
You have been on the consuming side
of the HDR story,
now you can help your users
to get onto the production side.
You can enable them
to express their creativity
in HDR through HDR video editing.
Through reviewing video editing workflow
we understand that AVVideoComposition
is at the center of video editing.
The good news is that there is
no additional work to enable HDR
if you are using built-in compositor,
or you are using
the applyingCIFiltersWithHandler
with built-in CIFilters
to create your AVVideoComposition.
If you are using custom compositor,
there is some additional work,
that is to indicate you support 10-bit
or higher pixel formats,
and you support HDR
and Wide Color source frames,
aside of making the real work you do
be HDR capable.
Then we talked about how you can control
the composition color properties
and the default behavior
if you leave them to default.
Last, we talked about
the eligibleForHDRPlayback API
you can use to check
if your system supports HDR playback.
Thank you very much for participating
in this session.
We hope you have a great time in WWDC
and look forward to your HDR enabled
video editing apps.