Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome to "Modern Cell Configuration."
I'm Tyler Fox,
an engineer on the UIKit team.
In iOS 14, we're bringing brand-new
features to UICollectionView
by building on top of
foundational technologies,
which can be broadly organized
into three categories:
the way that you populate data,
the way that you define your layout
and the way that you display content.
Check out the "Advances in
Collection View" session from WWDC 20
for an introduction
to all of these new features.
In this session, we're going to be
focusing on View Configuration,
new APIs to configure the content
and styling of your cells.
We'll start by covering the basics
and seeing how easy it is to use these
new configurations to set up your cells.
Next, we'll dive into a new concept
called "configuration state,"
which works together with configurations
to make it easy to get different
appearances for different states.
Finally, we'll take a closer look
at the two configuration types,
background configurations
and content configurations,
and cover using those in more detail.
Before we get into any of these
modern cell configuration APIs,
let's take a quick look at an example
of how you would configure
a table view cell in iOS 13.
If you've ever used UITableView before,
this should look very familiar.
Here, we're using the built-in
imageView and textLabel properties
on UITableViewCell
to display an image and some text.
This is a simple example
of what we mean by cell configuration.
With that in mind, let's take a look
at how you would do the same thing
using the new configuration APIs.
This is how you configure a cell
using a content configuration.
It looks pretty similar to what we had
before, but with two new lines of code.
Let's break it down.
The first thing that we do is ask the cell
for a defaultContentConfiguration.
This always returns a fresh configuration
without any content set on it.
But this configuration
does have default styling,
based on the cell and table view style.
We'll talk more about the styling
and other features
of content configurations shortly.
For now, we'll just set the image and text
on the content configuration.
This part should feel very familiar.
Now that we've set up our content,
there's one final step.
We apply the configuration to the cell
by setting it
to the contentConfiguration property.
As soon as we do this,
the cell is updated to display
the image and text that we specified.
Now, before this line of code,
setting the image and text
only changed our local copy
of the configuration
stored in this "content" variable.
Because we're using
a content configuration,
we never directly touch
a UIImageView or UILabel.
All of the properties
are set on the configuration itself.
So, what have we gained by using a
content configuration to set up our cell?
Well, for one, the code that you see here
to configure a table view cell
is actually the same code you would use
to configure any cell,
such as a collection view cell.
In fact, the same code works for any view
that supports content configurations,
even ones that aren't cells,
such as table view headers and footers.
How is this possible?
This works because
configurations are composable.
Instead of all of the functionality
being baked into the cell class itself,
like it was with UITableViewCell,
these standard cell layouts
and appearances
are now available as independent pieces
that can plug right into any cell
or view that supports them.
Let's run this code to see how it looks
and learn what other benefits we get
from using configurations.
There's our cell,
inside of a collection view list,
using the new sidebar appearance
for multi-column iPad apps.
You can see that the cell has the
star image and text that we configured.
Now, things get more interesting
when we start to interact with this cell.
When I touch down on the cell,
it shows the highlighted appearance.
And when I lift up,
the cell becomes selected.
But these are just a couple of the
different states that the cell can be in,
so let's add some more cells
and manually put them into
a bunch of different states
to see how the cell's appearance changes.
Here's the same content configuration,
but applied to all of these
different cells in different states.
Let me swap out the text in these cells
to indicate which state each cell is in.
As you can see here, the default styling
for a sidebar list cell
varies significantly in different states.
By using configurations
to set up our cell,
we get all of these
different appearances automatically.
We'll talk more about
how this works in a bit.
So, we've gotten a taste
of these new configurations,
but what are they exactly?
A configuration describes the appearance
of a view for a specific state:
things like the content, styling,
metrics and behavior.
By itself, a configuration
is just a bunch of properties.
It doesn't do anything until you apply it
to a view or a cell to render.
And as we've already discussed,
configurations are composable:
they can be used with any type of cell
or view that supports them.
Now, there are two types
of configurations,
background and content configurations.
Let's look at some of the features that
these two system configurations provide.
Background configurations
have a number of properties
to let you quickly specify
common background appearances.
With just a couple lines of code,
you can customize
the background fill color,
set a visual effect to get a nice blur
and add a stroke and some rounded corners.
And if you want to do something
more custom,
you can do that
by providing your own view.
List content configurations
give you the standard layouts
for cells, headers and footers,
much like the familiar UITableViewCell
styles you have today.
But list content configurations
are even more powerful.
They support an image, text
and optional secondary text
and expose many properties
for you to customize for each of those.
They also offer higher-level behaviors,
such as flexible layouts
to display larger amounts of text
and special layout modes
for Accessibility text sizes.
These two configuration types
go hand in hand
and have some common design principles.
One of the most important principles
is that configurations are lightweight
and very inexpensive to create.
They're value types in Swift,
which means whenever you
have a configuration, it's yours alone,
and changes that you make
to your configuration
don't affect anything else until you
set that configuration to the cell.
Because configurations are lightweight,
you should always start
with a fresh configuration,
such as by asking the cell
for its defaultContentConfiguration
as you see here.
This applies not only the first time
you configure the cell,
but also whenever you want to update
a cell that has already been configured.
Each time, just start
with a fresh configuration
and set it up for the new state.
When you're using configurations,
you don't need to think about
the old state at all.
Don't worry about whether
an old configuration was already applied,
and you shouldn't try to get the existing
configuration first to make changes to it.
Just start with a fresh configuration
each time,
set it up the way you want
and then apply it to the cell.
If you've been using UIKit
for a long time,
this might feel a bit different at first.
But once you start thinking this way,
it's incredibly liberating.
When you apply a configuration
to the cell,
UIKit is going to do all
of the heavy lifting for you.
It will figure out what's changed and
efficiently update the views as needed.
As you saw when we ran the code earlier,
configurations give you the default
appearance for many different states.
But configurations are also built
on top of robust infrastructure
that you can use to customize
the appearance for these states,
which we'll talk about
in more detail shortly.
Configurations also give you access
to advanced behaviors
in just a couple lines of code.
Let's say you want to animate
a change to your background appearance.
All you have to do is set a new background
configuration inside an animation.
Configurations aren't just easy to use,
their design actually eliminates
entire classes of bugs,
especially when you're dealing with
complex states and transitions.
You always know that the currently applied
configuration is the truth,
and when you set a new configuration,
that new configuration
is applied all at once.
Finally, configurations are built
from the ground up for performance,
which is especially important
to ensure smooth scrolling.
Because UIKit is responsible
for managing the views and rendering,
we're able to implement
many internal performance optimizations
under the hood, which you get for free.
Now that you're familiar
with the basics of configurations,
let's talk about a new concept
that works together with them,
called configuration state.
Configuration state represents
the various inputs
that you use to configure
your cells and views.
What kind of inputs are we talking about?
One of the most common inputs
that determines how you set up your views
are traits from UITraitCollection.
These are things like the size class,
user interface style
and the content size category.
On top of those traits,
your cells and views exist
in a variety of different states.
Maybe your cell is selected
or is a target for drag and drop
or maybe it's temporarily disabled.
These are just some of the different
states that are common in UIKit.
And on top of these states,
your app has its own custom states.
These are all of the different
pieces of state that you use
which are specific
to your app and its domain.
For example, when configuring cells,
a messaging app might need to know
whether a message is archived or flagged,
and a payment app might show
which transactions are processed.
If you use a view model
to populate your cells with content,
you can also think of that view model
as a custom state as well.
All of these things are what make up
configuration state:
a collection of all the different traits,
states and your own custom states,
wrapped together in one place.
So, where do you find
a configuration state?
Each cell, header and footer
in your collection or table view
has its own configuration state.
There are three cells shown here,
and each one might have different things
in its configuration state.
So, what does a configuration state
look like?
Well, there are two different types,
as you can see here.
There's a configuration state type
for views, like this header,
and there's a different type for cells.
Here's what a view configuration state
looks like.
It starts with a trait collection
and then we have four different states--
highlighted, selected,
disabled and focused.
These are just simple Booleans.
And finally,
we have optional custom states.
This is key-value storage for you
to add any extra states or data
that you want to use
when configuring your view.
So, that's view configuration state.
What about cell configuration state?
Well, cell configuration state just takes
everything from view configuration state
and adds some additional states
that are specific to cells,
whether the cell is editing,
swiped or expanded,
as well as some states
specific to drag and drop.
One of the most important things
you can do with configuration state
is use it to update configurations
for new states.
You can ask any background
or content configuration
to return an updated version of itself
for a different configuration state.
This will return a new copy
of the configuration,
with its properties updated
to reflect the new state.
For example, a background configuration
might change its background color,
and a content configuration might change
the image tint color and text color.
When you ask for an updated configuration,
the original configuration doesn't change.
And if you customized any of the
properties on the original configuration,
those properties will remain the same
on the updated configuration.
You can think of the properties
on a configuration
as becoming "locked" once you've set them.
Recall the demo
from the beginning of this session,
where we saw our content configuration
updating its appearance
for different states.
That worked because
of automatic configuration updates.
By default, when you set a background
or content configuration on the cell,
any time the cell's
configuration state changes,
it will automatically ask
the configuration
to return an updated version of itself
and then reapply that new configuration
back to the cell.
These properties
let you control this behavior.
Now, automatic updates are great
to get the default styling for each state,
but if you want to customize
the appearance for different states,
you can disable automatic updates
and update the configurations yourself
instead.
But where should you put your code
that updates these configurations?
Well, we have a brand-new method
on collection and table view cells,
called updateConfiguration(using state.
This is a method for you to override
in your cell subclass,
where you can put your code
to configure the cell
based on the state that's passed in.
This method is always called
before your cell first displays
and will be called again any time
the configuration state may have changed,
so you can configure yourself
for the new state.
Remember,
when you're using configurations,
you don't need to worry
about the old state.
Just get a fresh configuration each time,
set its properties
and apply it to your cell.
Configurations work best
when there's a single place in your code
that handles setting them up
and applying them to your cell.
If you're using a custom cell subclass,
this new method,
updateConfiguration(using state,
is the best place to do that.
This method is also a great place
to centralize any other setup
or updates to your cell.
For example, if you're using
the new collection view list cell,
you can use this method to update
the tint color of your cell accessories
for different states.
And if you need to reconfigure your cell
for any reason,
just call setNeedsUpdateConfiguration
to request an update.
Let's take a look at an example of how to
use this method to set up our cell
and manually update configurations
for different states.
First, we'll get a fresh configuration
by asking the cell
for its default content configuration.
And we'll immediately update that
for the new state.
This is going to give us a configuration
with the system default styling
for this state.
Next, we'll set
the configuration's image and text,
for the item that our cell is displaying.
And now we're ready to
apply our customizations.
Here, we're checking to see
if the state is highlighted or selected,
and if it is, we're setting the image
and text colors to white.
For any other states,
we don't set the colors at all,
which means we're using
the configuration's default colors.
Finally, we set our new configuration
to the cell.
And that's it.
This method will get called again
any time the state changes
and will apply a new configuration
for the new state each time.
So this is how you customize
the content configuration's appearance
for different states.
We could similarly customize
the background configuration here as well.
Now in this example,
we set different colors
for the image and text in certain states.
But there's another way to change the
appearance of colors in different states
using a new type
called a color transformer.
A color transformer takes in one color
and returns a different color
by modifying the original color
in some way.
For example,
you might have a color transformer
that returns
a grayscale version of a color.
So a color transformer
is just a simple function.
But color transformers are very powerful,
because you can produce
many different variants
from the same input color
with different color transformers.
This is how color transformers can be used
to create different appearances
for different states.
Some of the default configurations
for certain styles and states
will have a preset color transformer,
in order to produce
a specific appearance for that state.
The color transformer
combines with the input color
to produce the resolved color
that you actually see.
Now that you understand
how configurations can produce
updated appearances for different states,
let's cover some of the details
that you need to know
when using background
and content configurations.
Collection view list cells,
table view cells
and table view headers and footers
all set up a default
background configuration automatically,
based on the style of the containing list
or table view.
So typically, you won't need to do
anything at all
to get the background appearance you want.
Now, content configurations
work a little differently.
Instead of the cell
automatically applying one by default,
you can use the defaultContent
Configuration method on the cell
to get a fresh configuration
based on the cell's style,
as you've seen in the earlier examples.
But for both background
and content configurations,
you can easily request
the default configuration
for any style that you'd like
by going directly
to the UIBackgroundConfiguration
and UIListContentConfiguration types.
Here you can see examples
of how to do this
for a sidebar style list cell.
And there are similar methods
for the other different styles
of cells, headers and footers.
How about we take a look at some
of these different styles in action?
Here we have a list of sticker categories.
This list is currently configured
with the sidebar appearance,
so all of our cells have default
background and content configurations
that match that style.
You can see the cells update
their background and content appearance
for different states
as I interact with them.
But the sidebar style is just one
of the appearances that we can use
for our collection view list.
Let's take a look at what happens
if we configure this
with some different appearances.
Here's the same list,
configured with the grouped appearance.
And this is the inset grouped appearance.
And here's the plain appearance.
You probably recognize these styles
from UITableView.
Collection view list
supports some new styles,
such as this sidebar plain appearance
and the original sidebar appearance
that we started with.
All of the visual styling that you see
for these different list appearances
is coming from the default
background and content configurations.
Now let's switch back to the group style,
so we can see the individual cells
more clearly
and take a look at how they respond
to different dynamic type sizes
by changing the system text size setting.
You can see that by default,
everything responds dynamically
to these changes.
As we increase the text size,
the entire layout adjusts
to accommodate that.
And if we switch on
the largest Accessibility text sizes,
you'll see that the cell layouts
use a special mode
where the text wraps around the image
in order to maximize
the space available for the content.
Content configurations are built
from the ground up
to support dynamic layouts like this.
So let's take a quick look under the hood
at how that works.
Content configurations are designed
to be used with self-sizing cells,
where their height can be flexible,
depending on
the exact configuration and environment.
This is important to ensure
that your app looks great
when running on different device sizes,
at different dynamic type sizes
and with different amounts
and types of content.
Content configurations give you control
over the layout margins,
shown in blue here,
and various padding properties,
shown in orange.
Together with the actual content,
these are what determine
the intrinsic height
and affect how the cell self-sizes.
Instead of trying
to enforce a fixed height,
you should use these properties
on the content configuration
to influence the layout and allow
the height to adjust dynamically.
There's one more layout concept
that you should know about.
Let's see how it works in an example.
Here we have three different cells,
each using a content configuration
with an image and some text.
Right now, everything looks pretty good.
But say we want to use
some different images in these cells.
The problem is that
the images aren't exactly the same size.
They have slightly different widths.
So the images and the text
aren't aligned across cells anymore.
The reason that this happened
is because the images are leading aligned,
and the text is positioned
with the same amount of padding
from the trailing edge of each image.
To get the right alignment
across these cells,
we need to specify what we call
a reserved layout size for each image.
If we set the same reserved layout width
for the image
on each content configuration,
what that does
is horizontally center the image
inside that reserved amount of space.
In this illustration, the distance
between the two red-dotted lines
is the reserved layout width
for each image.
The reserved layout size does not affect
the actual size of the image.
And if the image is larger than
the reserved layout size,
it will be allowed to extend
outside of that area.
Using a reserved layout size for the image
also correctly aligns the text,
because the text is positioned relative
to the same reserved layout area
for the image in each cell.
If you're using symbol images,
UIKit applies a standard
reserved layout size automatically,
which you can request manually
for non-symbol images if needed.
So that's what you need to know
about list content configuration layout.
Let's go over a few important details
to keep in mind
as you start adopting configurations.
If you have existing code
that you're updating and migrating over,
keep in mind that configurations
are mutually exclusive
with some existing properties.
Setting a background configuration
always resets the background color
and background view properties to nil.
And the same thing applies
the other way around.
So make sure that you don't mix
a background configuration
with other code still setting
these other background properties
on the same cell.
And specifically for those of you
using UITableView,
content configurations supersede
the built-in subviews of cells,
headers and footers,
like the imageView, textLabel
and detailTextLabel.
These legacy content properties
will be deprecated in a future release,
so we encourage you
to adopt content configurations
to take advantage
of their more powerful features
and enhanced customizability.
The background configuration
and list content configuration types
that we've covered today
are incredibly powerful.
But there are still going to be times
when you need to do something more custom.
With configurations,
you have more options than ever before.
In addition
to the list content configuration,
we're also giving you access
to the associated list content view,
which implements all of the rendering.
You just create or update this view
using the configuration,
and then you can add it as a subview
right alongside your own custom views.
This lets you take advantage
of all the content configuration features
and combine the list content view
with your own additional custom views
next to it,
such as an extra image view or a label.
And because the list content view
is just a regular UIView,
you can actually use it
by itself anywhere,
even outside of a collection
or table view,
such as in a plain UIStackView.
But what about cases
when you aren't building a list at all,
or want to do something completely custom?
Configurations have got you covered.
Even when you're building
a completely custom view hierarchy
inside your cells,
you can still use
the system configurations to help.
Because configurations are so lightweight,
you can use them as a source
of default values
for things like fonts, colors and margins
that you copy over to your custom views,
even if you never apply
the configuration directly itself.
And for more advanced use cases,
you can create a completely custom
content configuration type
with a paired content view class
that renders it,
and then use your custom configuration
with any cell
the same way that you would
use a list content configuration.
With a custom configuration,
you can take advantage of all the features
that we've talked about,
including
allowing your custom configuration
to automatically update itself
for new states.
No matter how complex
or custom your cells are,
you'll be able to take advantage
of the power of configurations.
We've covered all the essentials
of modern cell configuration.
You've seen how easy it is to use
background and content configurations
and how you can use the same code
to configure a collection view cell
or a table view cell.
Configurations let you focus
on what you want to display
without worrying
about how to update all of your views.
You just start
with a fresh configuration each time,
set it up the way you want
and apply it to your cell,
letting UIKit take care of the rest.
You've seen how configurations
can be updated
using configuration state to produce
a wide variety of different appearances
and how you can use configuration state
when setting up your cells.
And everything
that we've talked about today is designed
to be composable and extensible
to meet your needs.
So go download the sample app
and give these new APIs a try,
then start using
content and background configurations
to set up collection
and table view cells in your app.
Be sure to check out
the collection view sessions from WWDC 20
to learn more about building lists
and much, much more.