Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Welcome, everyone.
My name is David Hayward,
and I'll be giving
a short presentation today
that will show how to get
the best performance
when using Core Image to apply effects
to your video app.
With that goal in mind,
I will discuss the following topics:
How best to create a CIContext,
how to write and apply custom CI Kernels,
and how to optimally render to your view.
So, let's dive in
and start with Creating a CIContext.
The first advice when creating your
CIContext is to only create one per view.
Contexts are easy to create,
but they take time
and memory to initialize,
so you don't wanna do it often.
Also, when you create your context,
there are some options
that should be specified.
Most important is to tell the context
not to cache intermediates.
With video, every frame is different
than the one before it,
so disabling this cache
will lower memory usage.
Also, I recommend that you give
your context a name.
This can be useful when using
Core Image debugging techniques.
Under the hood, Core Image uses Metal,
but some applications may want to
combine Core Image with other Metal APIs.
For example, you may want to use a Metal
texture as input or output for Core Image.
In these situations, I recommend
that you create your CIContext
with a Metal-Command-Queue.
A timeline graph
is the best way to explain why.
Consider a situation where an app
first uses its Metal-Command-Queue
to render content into a Metal texture.
This involves enqueueing work on the CPU
which is performed on the GPU.
Next, the app passes that texture
to Core Image
which uses its own internal Metal queue
to render content
into another Metal texture.
This also involves
enqueueing work on the CPU
which is performed on the GPU.
Lastly, the app uses its Metal queue again
to render with the output texture
from Core Image.
Because all this work
is done on different queues,
the app must issue wait commands
to get the correct results.
This causes wasteful bubbles
due to inefficient pipelining.
The solution to this problem
is to create the CIContext
with the same queue
that is used by the other Metal renders.
This allows the app to remove the waits.
And by doing so, the work can be pipelined
efficiently for the best performance.
The next topic to discuss
is writing CIKernels in Metal.
To get the best performance
in your video app,
it is important that the effects
are implemented in Metal.
The easiest way to do this
is to use built-in Core Image filters
wherever possible
because they are all implemented in Metal.
To help you use the built-in filters
we have been upgrading the documentation
to include parameter descriptions,
sample images,
and even sample code is included.
The code to apply a built-in filter
is really simple.
Just import CI-Filters-Built-ins,
create a filter instance,
set the input properties,
and get the output image.
Here are some more reasons why you
want to write custom CIKernels in Metal:
In addition to
the usual features of CIKernels,
such as automatic tiling
and concatenation,
by writing them in Metal,
you will reduce runtime compile time
by shifting that work
to when your app is built.
Also, you'll give your kernels access
to high performance features
such as gather-reads, group-writes,
and half-float math,
and make your life easier as a developer
by syntax highlighting as you type
and syntax checking when you build.
Let's go over an example
of writing CIKernels in Metal.
For today's session,
I will demonstrate this
with a kernel that is shown
in the presentation,
Edit and Playback HDR Video
with AVFoundation.
It is very easy to write
a custom CIKernel for this effect.
First, at the top of the source you will
include the Core-Image-dot-h header
so that you get access to
all the normal Metal classes
as well as the additional classes
that Core Image provides.
Next, you will declare the function
for the kernel which must be extern "C."
This example is a CI-Color-Kernel,
so the function must return a
float4 pixel and take some arguments.
Here, the first argument
is a Core Image sample_t
that represents a pixel
from an input image.
This pixel is a linear
premultiplied RGBA float4,
which is suitable
for either SDR or HDR images.
The last argument
is a Core Image destination
that provides the coordinate
of the pixel to return.
In the implementation of this kernel,
we use the dest-coord x and y values to
determine which diagonal line we are on.
Then we use some simple math to calculate
if we should be on a zebra stripe or not.
If we are on a zebra stripe
and the current pixel sample is brighter
than the normal
Standard Dynamic Range white of one,
then we will return a bright red pixel.
Otherwise, we return
the input sample unchanged.
For more details,
see my presentation on "Build Metal-Based
Core Image Kernels with Xcode."
The last topic to discuss is choosing
the best view class for your video app.
If your app applies effects to video,
it is important to avoid view classes
like UI-Image-View and NS-Image-View
that are designed
for displaying static content.
The easiest view class is AV-Player-View
because it automatically does the work
to display filtered video to the view.
A more flexible option that can also
give great performance is MetalKit View.
I will discuss how to use both
with Core Image in the next few slides.
Using AV-Player-View is really simple.
The key object
is an AV-Mutable-Video-Composition,
which is initialized with a video asset
and a handler block.
This block is called
for every frame in the video,
and it is passed an AV-Synchronous-
CI-Image-Filtering-Request.
When your block is called,
all you need to do is create a CI-Filter,
set its inputs and get its output image.
Then you just need give that image
to the request object.
A great feature in Xcode
is that while debugging,
you can hover over a CI-Image variable
and a small popover will appear
that shows the object's address,
but if you then click on the eye symbol,
a new window will appear
that shows a visual representation
of the recipe that makes up the image.
And if you look at this even closer,
you can see that the input video frame
is a 10-bit HDR surface,
and Core Image
has automatically color managed it
from HLG to the Core Image working space.
Using a MetalKit View
to display your filtered videos
is another option you might consider.
Here's how to get the best performance
with Core Image
when drawing to a MetalKit View.
The first thing you'll want to do
in your MetalKit View class
is override the init
with frame and device.
The init method is the best time
to create a CIContext for the view.
Be sure to set framebuffer-Only to false
so that Core Image can use Metal Compute.
On macOS, if your view supports HDR,
then you should set
the color-Pixel-Format to rgba16Float
and also set the wants-Extended-
Dynamic-Range-Content to true.
The next thing you'll want to do
in your MetalKit View
is implement the draw-in view method.
In this method we create
a CI-Render-Destination in a special way.
We create the destination with the correct
width, height and pixel format,
but instead of passing in a Metal texture,
we pass in a block
that will return the texture.
This allows the CIContext
to start enqueueing Metal work
before waiting on the previous frame
to complete.
Next we tell our CIContext
to start the task
of rendering the image to the destination.
And last step
is to create a command buffer
to present the current drawable
to the view.
So, that concludes
my step-by-step discussion
on how to get great performance
with Core Image in your video app.
We have reviewed
how best to create CIContexts,
apply CIKernels and render to your view.
I hope that this allows you to add
great visual effects to your apps' videos.
Thank you very much,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC 2020.