Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello, everyone!
Thank you for watching our presentation
on "Becoming a Simulator Expert."
I'm Ryan Bowring, an engineer on the
Devices and Simulators team here at Apple.
Today, we are going to talk about
how the Simulator can help you
turbocharge your developer experience
and create great apps.
So let's start with a brief overview
before we dive in.
Just what is Simulator,
and what can it do?
Well, Simulator lets you test your apps
for iOS, iPadOS, tvOS, and watchOS
on your Mac.
No physical device required.
You can prototype your apps faster
and test them on multiple kinds
of simulated devices.
And it exposes
lots of device functionality.
Now, Simulator is built right into Xcode,
and it starts automatically
when you run or test your app
without a physical device.
So many of you have probably seen
the Simulator before.
And you can run the Simulator
as a stand-alone tool
and make use of its powerful features
to help you out on your developer journey.
Here we have two Simulators booted:
an iPhone 11 and an 11-inch iPad Pro,
both running iOS 14.
In the title,
you can see both the device name
and the version of the OS
that it's running.
And the toolbar buttons let you access
some of the most widely used features
of our platforms.
Let's start with screenshots.
In Xcode 12, we've significantly
improved the experience
of taking screenshots in Simulator.
Click on the screenshot button
in the toolbar
and an image of the device
will fly out to the side here.
By Control-clicking
on the screenshot thumbnail,
you can save it
to one of several different locations,
copy it to the clipboard,
or open it in various different apps.
You can drag it onto other apps
to insert it.
And by clicking
on the screenshot button repeatedly,
you can take multiple screenshots,
one after another.
It's a great way to take screenshots
for your apps' App Store page.
If you don't interact with the screenshot,
then it will be saved
to the desktop by default.
You can also drag files onto the Simulator
to cause certain events to happen,
such as adding an image
to the photo library,
triggering a push notification,
or adding a certificate.
For instance, we can drag an APNs file
onto the Simulator window here
to cause a push notification to appear.
We'll talk more about support
for push notifications in a few minutes.
Finally, in Xcode 12, it's now possible
to bring Simulator into full-screen mode,
both on its own,
and tiled with another app.
For example, you can have the Simulator
and Xcode side by side
in full-screen mode.
Let's take a moment to talk about
how Simulator can allow you
to test your apps' support
for certain platform features.
iPadOS supports
mouse pointer interactions,
meaning that if a user connects a mouse
or a trackpad to their iPad,
they can get full pointer
and gesture support.
Watch how we can use the Simulator
to test this support.
With a click of the pointer button
in the toolbar,
you can enter into pointer capture mode
on an iPad Simulator
running a supported version of iPadOS.
Notice that once pointer capture mode
is enabled,
your Mac's mouse or trackpad now controls
the pointer in the iPad Simulator,
so all mouse and trackpad gestures
are processed by iPadOS.
It behaves just like as if it were
connected to a physical iPad.
For example, you can open up the Maps app.
We can do a pinch gesture
to zoom in and zoom out.
All keyboard shortcuts are also captured,
so if we want to go back
to the Home Screen,
we can press Command-H.
To switch apps, we can press Command-Tab
or do a three-finger swipe up
on the trackpad.
And, of course, we can do
a two-finger drag to scroll.
To stop capturing,
and return control to the host Mac,
simply press Escape.
It's also possible to capture
just the keyboard, but not the pointer.
This makes all keyboard input
stay with the Simulator,
but leaves your mouse free
to use with the Mac.
Also, in Xcode 12,
Simulator now keeps track of
which Simulators are currently capturing.
When a Simulator window loses focus,
such as if another window opens up,
then capturing is automatically stopped.
But when you switch back to the Simulator,
capturing starts again.
This is really handy
when you are debugging in Xcode.
Here, I've set a breakpoint
in our demo app's source code.
It will trigger when we load
one of our drinks from the menu.
When the breakpoint triggers,
your mouse pointer
will automatically be released,
allowing you to go into Xcode
and inspect things.
See? Our pointer is now free.
Once you switch back to the Simulator,
capturing starts right back up again,
right where you left off.
And, of course,
you can use Escape to stop capturing.
Now, you may be wondering if you can
change the shortcut to stop capturing.
For instance, maybe you want
to make the Escape key
do something in your app.
Well, the answer is yes,
it is customizable.
Simulator has a preferences window
which allows you to configure
a number of important settings.
At the top here, we can see the option
for the shortcut to stop capturing.
There are three supported options:
Escape, which is the default,
pressing both the left
and the right Command keys,
or pressing Control-Option.
The preferences window also allows you
to customize the lifetime
of booted Simulators.
By default,
when the Simulator is launched,
it boots the most recently used Simulator.
And the running Simulators get shut down
when you close their window
or quit the Simulator application.
Personally, I end up opening
and closing the app frequently,
so I've configured my preferences
to leave Simulators running
after I quit the app.
When I want to shut down a Simulator,
I simply close its window.
To get this result,
I set the preference items accordingly.
Next we have the visual indicator options.
Simulator can draw helpful widgets for you
to show the position
of the simulated fingers
for drag and pinch gestures.
You can also choose whether or not
you want device masks
to appear in screenshots.
If this is enabled, then on
certain devices such as the iPhone 11,
the area with the sensor housing
will be rendered as transparent.
In addition to preferences
which apply to all Simulators,
the menu bar contains a variety of options
for each Simulator.
The Features menu contains
a number of useful options
to toggle features
supported by our platforms.
One such option is Toggle Appearance.
This allows you to toggle between
Light Mode and Dark Mode in iOS.
I personally prefer Dark Mode,
so let's set our Simulator to use it
by clicking on the menu item.
You can also use the keyboard shortcut,
of course.
Under the File menu, you can see
the option to start Simulators.
To keep the clutter down
in Xcode's run destination menu,
Simulator only creates
a few devices by default,
but you can create more.
One feature we are introducing in Xcode 12
is the ability to create a new Simulator
right from within the app.
So you won't need to go
into Xcode as much anymore.
You can bring up the New Simulator window
by clicking on the File menu
and then on New Simulator here.
And as you can see, we can enter a name
for the new Simulator,
as well as choose the device type
and the runtime.
Let's create one now.
I'll just give it a name
and click on Create.
And now you can see it listed
under our list of Simulators
right in the menu.
Once a Simulator is running,
you may want to adjust the window size.
You can click and drag to resize
the corners of the Simulator.
The Window menu also contains
several window scaling options
that can adjust the window size.
Let's go through these options
in more detail.
First, the option for physical size.
This makes the Simulator window on-screen
exactly the same size
as a physical device would be.
This is done by taking the pixels per inch
of your Mac's display,
the pixels per inch
of the device you are simulating,
and then calculating
how big to make the window
so the content matches the size.
This can be used to see
exactly how your app will appear
across multiple simulated devices
with different screen sizes
and pixel densities.
Next, I want to talk about Point Accurate.
Point Accurate mode sizes the window
so that content appears the same size
on devices with different scale factors.
In other words,
it makes all points on all Simulators
the same on your screen,
regardless of the pixel density
of the simulated device.
So a device with a 3x display
will appear the same size as a 2x display.
This will result in the Simulator's
screen content being downscaled
if your Mac's display
has a lower pixel density
than that of the simulated device.
For example, in Point Accurate mode,
a simulated device with a 3x display
will be downscaled
if viewed on a Mac
with a 2x or a 1x display,
and a simulated device with a 2x display
will be downscaled
if viewed on a Mac with a 1x display.
If the simulated device's display
and your Mac's display
have the same pixel density,
then no scaling needs to occur.
It's the same as Pixel Accurate
in this case.
Finally, let's talk about
the Pixel Accurate display mode.
In this mode,
each pixel on the simulated device
is mapped directly to one pixel
on your Mac's display.
This will cause Simulators
to appear larger on-screen
if the Mac's display has a lower
pixel density than the simulated device.
As an example, if we have
a simulated device with a 2x screen
running on a Mac with a 1x screen,
then the Simulator window
will be double the size
of the Point Accurate mode.
Now I want to talk about ways
you can leverage the command line
to access all the power Simulator offers.
You can control Simulator
from the command line
using the simctl tool.
Its name is a portmanteau of the words
"Simulator and "control."
It is an amazing tool
to help boost your productivity.
First, we're going to talk about privacy.
At Apple,
we take our users' privacy seriously.
For so many people,
our devices are often an extension
of our own personal lives.
They contain so much personal data
about ourselves and those we care about.
That's why our platforms don't allow apps
to access your users' personal data
without their permission.
Testing your app's handling
of the user's privacy choices is important
and simctl can help you.
An important part of the privacy features
on our platforms
are various access prompts that appear
when an app wants to access
a protected resource.
You must test your app to see how it works
when permissions are both granted
and withheld.
With simctl, you can grant
and revoke your apps' access
to these protected resources
from the command line.
simctl supports
many of the most important services.
These include access to the calendar,
your user's contacts,
their location, and their photos.
For more information, and to see
the full list of supported services,
don't hesitate to visit
the simctl help pages.
To access it,
just run simctl without any arguments.
To grant your app permission,
you simply specify the action--
here, grant, to grant permissions--
followed by the service name
and your app's bundle ID.
Here I'm using the booted alias to refer
to the currently booted Simulator.
If you have multiple booted Simulators,
you'll want to specify which Simulator
by its name or UDID.
Of course, it's equally possible
to revoke an app's access to a resource.
You just specify the revoke action.
Instead of listing a specific service,
you can instead specify "all"
as the service name.
This applies the specified action
to all services.
Here, we are taking away
all of an app's permissions.
And finally, you can reset all permissions
to restore them to the defaults.
With the reset command,
it can apply either to a specific app,
or system-wide.
Here, we will reset all permissions
to all apps on the system.
Next, let's discuss push notifications.
Push notifications
are a big part of the experience
for users on Apple platforms.
It lets you deliver messages
to your users periodically
to notify them about things
they've asked to be notified about.
Here you can see an example
of a very, very basic push notification
containing a title and a body.
When the push notification is displayed,
the body text appears below the title text
in a different font.
One special additional key
is this "Simulator Target Bundle" key.
This key specifies
the bundle ID of the app
that should receive the notification.
Here, the notification is associated
with our sample app.
Let's dispatch the notification
to our sample app.
Now the push notification command
takes at most two parameters:
the app bundle ID and the payload file,
which I just showed you.
If you drag-and-drop the file
onto the device window,
then the bundle ID must be specified
in the JSON file.
With simctl,
the bundle ID can be specified
as a parameter or in the JSON file.
But it's still useful to include
so that you can omit the bundle ID
from your commands.
Just note that whatever you specify
on the command line
will override anything from the file.
So let's run this command
and see what happens.
Like typical UNIX commands,
simctl prints no output if it succeeds.
You'll see the contents
of the push notification on the screen.
See? It works, just like that.
Next up, let's talk about video recording.
Sometimes, you really need a video
to capture the essence of your app,
whether it's to market your app
on its App Store page,
to send some work in progress UI
to a colleague,
or to give a demo on your website.
Lots of developers use
screen recording software
such as QuickTime to do this,
but you don't need to use any
special software to record the Simulator.
Fortunately, with simctl,
you can capture a video
of your app's functionality
right from the command line.
And Simulator.app
does not even need to be running.
Here's a sample simctl command
to record a video.
It captures a video of the screen
from the running device
and saves it to the output file
named video.mp4.
Note that this file
shouldn't already exist.
If it already exists,
then the recording will fail
unless you use
the "--force" command line flag
to indicate that it is safe
to write over the existing file.
The video recording capabilities of simctl
support several different options
to control the behavior.
Here, we are using the default options.
These options give a video file
the HEVC codec with a black device mask.
If the device mask is set to be black,
then the sensor bar and curves
of certain devices such as the iPhone 11
will be rendered black in the video,
making the items behind them invisible.
It's important to note
that the video recording continues
until you terminate it by pressing
Control-C in the terminal window.
One nice thing
about video recording with simctl
is that it uses your GPU
to accelerate the video encoding.
So, it won't use
too many system resources.
Now, let's record another video,
but this time specifying some options.
We're going to change the video codec
and the device mask.
This time, we will ignore any device mask.
This means that the entire rectangular
frame buffer will be recorded.
We will also use the h264 codec
instead of the HEVC codec.
Lastly, certain devices running iOS
support external displays.
You can choose to capture
the video footage
from either the device's internal display,
or an external display.
Here's how to capture video
from an external display.
On iOS, one app
that supports sending output
to an external display is the Photos app.
Right now, we are flicking through
the Photos app, looking at our photos.
If we want to capture what is displayed
on the external display,
we tell simctl to capture the output
of the external display
with the "--display" flag.
And here is the video that we captured.
You'll notice that it contains the output
of the external display
and not the simulated device's screen.
Now, on to the status bar.
As you know, iOS and iPadOS devices
have a status bar showing the time, date,
cellular and Wi-Fi signal,
and other important information.
You can use simctl
to customize this information
so that it can display
whatever information you want.
For example,
this can be used for screenshots
for your app's App Store page.
Here's our iPhone as it stands now.
Currently the phone is showing
that the current time is 9:41 a.m.
with full cellular and Wi-Fi strength.
The battery is also 100% charged.
Suppose we want to customize
the status bar up top
so we can see what it would look like
under different conditions.
The simctl status_bar command
can override the status bar
to display whatever information you like.
Let's say we want a screenshot
of our app when the user is out and about.
Some time has passed, so it is now 12:01.
Perhaps the user has a low signal
with one cellular bar signal,
3G data network, and no Wi-Fi.
Let's see the result.
After running the command, you can see
that our status bar has changed
to match the settings we have specified.
Of course, at a certain point,
you may want to clear
the overrides you have set.
You can do that with the clear command.
Let's run that now.
And, as you can see, the status bar
has been returned to its default settings.
Now, there are actually more options
that you can override in the status bar
than I've shown here.
To see all the available options,
run the status_bar command
without any arguments.
Finally, let's discuss
the Keychain management.
simctl allows you to add CA certificates
to the device's trusted root store.
This is really useful when you are
developing apps with network capabilities.
Here's how it works.
I have a certificate which I want to add
to the trusted root store
in the Simulator.
I can do this with
the simctl Keychain command.
When you call this command,
you need to it give the path
to a valid CA certificate.
In addition to using simctl,
you can also add the certificate
by dragging it onto the Simulator window,
but here, we're going to stick
with the simctl command.
And after running this command,
your certificate will be added
into the Simulator's trust store.
But you still have to trust it manually.
To do so, go into the Settings app,
then tap on General, About,
Certificate Trust Settings,
and then tap on the switch to activate it.
Be sure to acknowledge
the warning message.
And at this point,
this CA certificate is now trusted.
So now any TLS certificates this CA issues
will work without a problem.
You can do other tasks
with the Keychain command as well,
such as clearing any saved passwords.
For more information,
please check the help pages.
And that's the end of our presentation
on "Becoming a Simulator Expert."
We hope the techniques
we've talked about today
will help you turbocharge
your developer experience
so that you can create better apps
and delight your users.
Thank you for watching,
and we hope you enjoy
the rest of the content for WWDC 2020.