Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. I'm Jenny, and I'm an engineer
on the Pencil and Paper team.
Welcome to "What's New in PencilKit."
In iOS 13, we introduced PencilKit,
a new framework
for easily adding a low-latency
expressive drawing experience to your app.
In iOS 14, we've added some new features
to the out-of-the-box
PencilKit experience.
Next, we'll go over
some of the changes we've made
to the finger versus pencil
drawing policy across the system.
Finally, we'll cover some API changes
that we've made,
in addition to a sneak peek at some
of the new APIs that we're exposing
that will really expand the possibilities
of what you can do with PencilKit.
In iOS 13,
we showed you how you can adopt PencilKit
with only a few lines of code
with PKCanvasView.
It was great to see how you adopted it.
If you haven't adopted PencilKit yet,
check out our talk from 2019
to see just how easy it is.
The Apple Pencil has so much potential,
and it can really unlock the capabilities
of productivity and the iPad.
And so, we can't wait to show you
some of the new enhancements that
we've added to the PencilKit experience,
and the best part is
that they require zero adoption.
PencilKit documents have gotten smarter
as we infuse intelligence
across handwritten notes.
We've provided a rich-selection experience
that mirrors the way
that you select type text.
So you can double-tap for a word,
double-tap again to select a line,
or even use the grab handles
to expand your selection.
We've improvised some enhanced gestures,
like a velocity-sensitive tap-and-pan
so that you can make
noncontiguous selections
by brushing over specific strokes.
We've also introduced an easy way
to insert space
between your handwritten content.
Have you ever written stuff and realized
you've forgotten something right in between?
Instead of having to write super tiny
and squeeze additions in the margins,
you can just tap on the white space,
tap "Insert Space" from the callout bar,
use the grab handle
to adjust the amount of space...
and then easily add the new content
in between.
We also adopted the new UIKit system
standard color picker,
which features rich new ways
to choose more colors for your drawings.
You'll have a rainbow of color options
using the spectrum or sliders,
be able to save your custom colors
for later,
or even use the eye dropper
to sample colors.
For existing PencilKit clients,
there's nothing
that you'll need to add to your app.
You'll get it for free.
For more information
about how to easily adopt this,
check out the UIKit talk,
"Build With iOS Pickers, Menus
and Actions."
We've also made some great
latency optimizations for third parties.
In iOS 13, we recommended techniques
to avoid impacting latency,
such as avoiding any visual effect views
or blur effects.
In iOS 14, that's no longer the case,
and you can use
different visual effect view materials
and bars to your heart's content.
In addition, we've also added
PKCanvasView support for Catalyst.
The tool picker is not supported,
but you can easily set inks on the canvas
through the PKCanvasView APIs.
And, just as a reminder,
for smart selection, insert space,
and the new color picker,
no extra adoption is required.
And that's why we made it
a system-wide experience
so we could keep enhancing it
year after year,
providing a consistent enhanced experience
across the system.
We've also done some work to distinguish
the finger versus Pencil
drawing experience
and how it can be more unified
across the system.
PencilKit is supported
on both phones and iPads.
Drawing with both finger
and Apple Pencil is allowed,
and you have to remember
that not everyone has a Pencil.
In iOS 13, we introduced
the allowsFingerDrawing property,
which meant that if you had it on,
one finger would draw,
while two fingers would scroll.
In iOS 14, we have a new global setting
that can be set from
the new Apple Pencil menu in settings
via the Prefer Only Pencil Drawing toggle.
This is for all third parties
who use Pencil,
both for apps who adopted PencilKit,
and for those
with their own drawing engine.
This setting can be accessed
via UIPencilInteraction in UIKit.
Non-PencilKit clients
that have their own drawing engine
should respect the setting by querying
UIPencilInteraction.prefersPencilOnlyDrawing parameter.
On the phone,
this value is always "false,"
as finger
is your only drawing tool available.
On the other hand,
PencilKit clients get this for free,
as it's surfaced in the tool picker.
This toggles the global setting
that you see in the settings pane.
So when the Draw with Finger switch
is toggled on in Notes,
then that means it will also be turned on
across the system,
such as screenshots, Markup,
other PencilKit clients,
and the new value
will also be reflected in settings.
We've also updated the call
on PKCanvasView
to account for this new
global finger drawing toggle.
We've deprecated allowsFingerDrawing
in favor of setting
the PKCanvasViewDrawingPolicy
on the canvas.
Please do not set the drawing gesture
recognizer allowedTouchTypes,
and instead set the drawing policy
on the canvas
to control Pencil vs finger touches.
There are three different kinds
of drawing policies.
The first,
PKCanvasViewDrawingPolicy.anyInput,
means that you allow any input,
allowing both finger and Pencil drawing.
The second policy, pencilOnly,
means you only allow Pencil,
so finger will scroll
or do smart selection gestures.
The third, which is the default,
is dependent on if the tool picker
is hidden or not.
If the tool picker is visible, it
respects UIPencilInteraction's
prefersPencilOnlyDrawing state,
a.k.a, what the user set in settings
or toggled in the tool picker.
If the tool picker is hidden,
then only Pencil will ever draw.
Whenever finger scrolls, you can
also perform smart selection gestures.
Let me show you.
You don't even have to choose
the lasso tool.
When the pen is selected, you can scroll
and perform smart selection gestures
on your handwritten content
so that you can easily go back and forth
between writing...
and selecting.
If your app is purely a Pencil app,
you might not want to show
the Draw With Finger toggle.
To turn this off in the UI,
you'll need to set PKToolPicker.showsDrawingPolicyControls
to false.
By default, it will always be true
on iPads,
meaning they will always show the Draw
With Finger toggle in the tool picker.
If the canvas drawing policy
is set to Pencil only,
you'll want to set this to false,
so users won't be confused
when they flip the switch
and nothing changes on the canvas.
We've also updated the PKToolPicker
initialization methods.
Instead of having a single
shared tool picker for a UIWindow,
you can now initialize
individual instances of the tool picker.
By doing so, you can now have independent
PKToolPickers with their own state.
Given this state,
it's useful to have multiple tool pickers
for different canvases
or windows in your app.
However, one of the implications of this
is that you must always retain
your own tool picker instance
by having an Ivar reference it.
And so, when should you have a single instance
versus creating a new one?
As a refresher
from our "Introducing PencilKit" talk,
you may have other UI responders
that set visible to "true"
to keep the tool picker visible.
You should always pass
your unique tool picker instance around
to each of these responders.
On the other hand,
when do you need separate tool pickers?
Let's say my app has two modes,
a note-taking mode and a coloring mode.
My note-taking canvas wants
a default drawing policy,
versus I want to allow both finger
and Pencil drawing on my coloring canvas.
In this case, each of the canvases
should have their own unique tool picker
instance with their own unique state,
since I'll want to hide the drawing
policy controls on my coloring canvas.
The tool pickers will also have different
states in terms of their selected tool.
I'll make the selected tool
on my notes canvas a black pen,
while my coloring canvas will have
a purple marker as the default.
The tool pickers in your app
might also have other varying states,
such as different color user
interface styles
if you're drawing versus
marking up an image.
Finally, one of the biggest changes
we made to PencilKit in iOS 14
is providing access to strokes,
letting you peek inside the internals
of PKDrawing.
With the strokes, you'll be able
to access inks, paths, points, and more.
For more information,
check out the "Inspect, Modify
and Construct PencilKit Drawings" talk.
Access to strokes can unlock so many more
interesting custom PencilKit experiences
involving annotations, animations,
recognition, and machine learning.
And that's what's new in PencilKit.
For existing PencilKit clients,
you'll get some new feature enhancements
with zero adoption,
including smart selection, insert space,
and the new color picker.
Move away from the deprecated APIs
to the new APIs
to make sure that you provide the best
finger and Pencil drawing experience.
And, finally, you can introspect
the strokes inside of PKDrawing
with some new PencilKit APIs, taking
your Pencil experience to the next level.
Thanks for watching,
and we're looking forward
to seeing what you will do with PencilKit.