Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hello and welcome. My name is Danny Rust.
I'm an EPM on the Customer Feedback team
here at Apple,
and I'd like to thank you
for tuning in for our session.
I'll be guiding you through
the first portion covering topics
including testing betas,
the AppleSeed for IT program
and filing feedback for your organization,
which include a brief demo
before handing it off to Jared,
who'll talk about the exciting new changes
regarding managing software updates.
Apple makes great tools for business.
Our tools and platforms help employees
solve problems in creative ways,
be productive wherever they are
and collaborate more effectively.
IT departments work incredibly hard
and with some key goals in mind:
Test diligently to stay a step ahead
of emerging security concerns,
ensure devices and apps
operate efficiently,
minimize downtime and compatibility issues
and enable employees to have
the best user experience possible.
To deliver on those goals,
key elements in your environment--
your IT infrastructure,
third-party MDM solution,
Apple devices and business-critical apps--
must be ready when new software versions
are publicly released to your users.
The truth is, we can't possibly replicate
all the various education
and enterprise environments out there,
and we need your help to make sure you're
ready to deploy when the latest OS ships.
Apple has many programs for seeding
pre-release software to developers,
business and education customers
and other audiences.
All these programs help users
provide valuable feedback to Apple.
It's important to note some distinctions.
The Public Beta is available to all users
who sign up at beta.apple.com
and is generally geared towards reporting
livability or general use type issues.
Updates in this program
can be less frequent.
We currently support Public Betas
for iOS, iPadOS, macOS, tvOS
and now this year, watchOS.
The Developer Program's for app developers
to incorporate new features
into their apps,
use new frameworks,
test using simulators and various SDKs
and make sure their apps run
on the new OS when it releases.
And AppleSeed for IT.
It's why you're here
and what I'll be discussing next.
AppleSeed for IT is a seeding program
focused towards IT professionals
in enterprise and education.
In this program,
Apple deploys a variety of software
across all platforms for you to test.
We provide in-depth beta documentation
and release notes
that are focused on IT admin workflows.
Test plans are provided to ensure
the newest features
work in your existing environment.
The surveys are so you can help us
better understand that environment.
We're committed to testing year-round
and we hope you are too.
So, how can you help?
Well, you have specific infrastructures,
mission-critical apps
and services that are important
to your employees, staff and students.
We need you to test against
your unique environments
and provide feedback on what doesn't work
and what you'd like to see next.
We are most interested in feedback
about deployment blockers,
the kind of issues that would prevent you
from deploying the latest OS
when we release it,
and regressions, or things that don't work
in pre-released versions,
but do work in the last public release.
If you're ready to get started,
we've made it even easier to enroll.
Simply use your Managed Apple ID.
If you don't have one,
talk to your Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager administrator
about generating one.
Also, make sure to associate
your e-mail address on the account
to receive important communications
from the program.
Next, log in to appleseed.apple.com
using your Managed Apple ID
and accept the program terms.
If you participated in AppleSeed for IT
last year, you'll do the same flow.
Just sign in using your Managed Apple ID
and accept
the new program terms for this year.
Next, you'll configure your devices
to receive pre-released updates.
You can push the configuration profile
or the macOS Customer Beta Access Utility
to any device you want to use for testing.
Both are available for download
on appleseed.apple.com
under the Downloads tab.
Remember that each participant
that's testing
needs to sign in
and accept the program terms.
Now, once you're started,
we want to encourage collaboration.
You can communicate
with our AppleSeed for IT participants
in the AppleSeed Discussion forums,
and we encourage you to collaborate
with your teammates as well.
This allows you to discuss
pre-release features
with other participants
who have also accepted the program terms.
Many of you likely have
existing contacts within Apple,
either through your account team
or through AppleCare.
It's important that you submit
all issues you encounter
through Feedback Assistant.
These other internal teams
can also assist during your testing.
With an AppleCare for Enterprise
or AppleCare OS Support agreement,
you can request testing assistance
from an AppleCare Account Manager
or an Apple Systems Engineer.
These experienced Apple agents
can quickly guide you through testing,
submitting feedback
and tracking any issues,
and you can also notify them
about any deployment-blocking issues
that you report
through the Feedback Assistant app.
Next, I'd like to talk about how you can
file great feedback for your organization.
These tips will help us
in triaging your issues more efficiently.
Remember to file immediately
after the issue occurs
with the device it occurs on
as this will ensure
the necessary logs are gathered.
When possible, note the time of the issue
and include thorough steps to reproduce,
or if relevant, attach a screen recording
or a screenshot of the issue.
Additionally, we host several profiles
unique to enterprise
and education configurations
to help gather
additional relevant logging.
This year, we have some exciting new
features to share in Feedback Assistant,
our application for filing feedback
on pre-released software.
For that, I'd like to introduce Pete,
who manages our engineers
responsible for Feedback Assistant.
Feedback Assistant is available
on iOS, iPadOS, macOS and the web,
and it helps you send us feedback
on your experiences with our software.
It's designed to provide concise,
yet detailed forms to capture the problem,
to collect system logs and diagnostics
and to be the place for you
to keep track of your bugs
as they work their way through Apple.
One of our biggest feature requests
has been about collaboration.
Organizations have told us how they
want to share information about bugs
that affect more than one person.
And when someone leaves the company,
their feedback goes with them.
So, we're really proud to announce Teams,
new in this year's OS releases.
Teams allows members
within an organization
to work together on feedback with Apple.
Teams are configured
by Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager
for AppleSeed for IT,
and in App Store Connect
for the Developer Program.
Members of a team can see feedback
created by their teammates,
see responses from Apple
and participate in that back-and-forth.
And, when needed,
you can reassign a feedback
so a different teammate gets notified
in case of vacation or departure.
We've also done a lot of work
to help you provide better feedback
in areas like Continuity, AirDrop
and syncing.
Often, we need diagnostics from
both devices to figure out the problem.
So, we've added a feature
we call multi-device diagnostics.
When you start a new feedback
on your iOS device,
Feedback Assistant
can remotely gather diagnostics
from other devices
signed into your iCloud account.
When you submit, the diagnostics upload
from each device directly to Apple,
so you don't have to wait
for them to finish
and sync over to the device you're using.
Like Danny mentioned earlier,
collecting logs right when
you see the problem really helps us,
so now you can get all the logs
from all your devices all at once.
Let's get into a demo
to see how this all works.
Here's the main screen
of Feedback Assistant.
I'm logged in using my Managed Apple ID.
There's some new UI here.
Organizing feedback
that belongs just to me
and feedback that belongs to my team.
Let's start by creating a new feedback.
Here's the form to create a new feedback.
I'm going to make an iOS bug.
I think it's relevant to my organization,
so I want to make it a team feedback.
Choosing my team here makes sure
that the feedback I create
will be visible to other members
of my organization in Feedback Assistant.
Let's add a title.
And this is a Continuity bug.
And it's incorrect behavior.
I had the problem with Safari.
Between my iPhone and my iPad.
On a very busy day.
And I'll attach my screen recording later.
Let's add the description.
Okay. So, now it's time for attachments,
so let's take advantage
of multi-device diagnostics.
A sysdiagnose is already gathering
from this iPad,
but I was using this iPhone
when I encountered the bug,
so I think diagnostics from there
will be useful too.
I can add them
using the Add Attachment button.
I'll chose the iPhone that I was using...
add it to the feedback,
and now it's collecting
a sysdiagnose as well.
I want to move on,
so let's submit the feedback.
Here's another new feature in iOS 14.
You don't have to wait for diagnostics
to complete before sending your feedback.
Feedback Assistant
will let me submit right now,
and as long as my devices stay online,
they'll upload the diagnostics to Apple
when they finish.
Great. So, here's the feedback
in my team's Submitted box.
If you've been
in the AppleSeed for IT program before,
you probably filed some feedback.
All that feedback
lives in your personal space.
To let your teammates
collaborate on that feedback,
you'll need to move it to the team space.
Here's how you do that.
This is the Submitted box
in my personal space.
And here's a Wi-Fi bug
that I filed a few months ago.
Now, I can make it visible
to the rest of my team.
To do that, I use the More Actions button
up here and select Move to Team.
Feedback Assistant will ask
for confirmation, and I'll go ahead.
Now that you can see not just
your feedback but your team's as well,
we've added some new areas to the app
to help you keep track of it all.
We have multiple in-boxes
for organizing content
that belongs just to me
and feedback that belongs to my team.
At the top of the source list,
we've added some smart boxes
to group certain kinds of content.
For example, we have News.
Here are the latest AppleSeed for IT
release notes.
There's also Requests,
where I can see I have a survey to answer.
Now, let's take a look at collaboration.
Here's a bug filed by my colleague, Sean.
You can see at the top,
the enhanced status.
It looks like a lot of other people
had reported this bug,
and it's showing that it's been fixed.
So, a lot of us did see this bug.
I remember it, and it's definitely fixed
in the latest release.
If I look down at the bottom,
here's a request from Apple
to verify that fix,
and I can fill that out right here.
Yes, it's resolved.
So now, here's a feedback
from my teammate Monica, who just retired.
Congratulations to her.
She's not on the team anymore,
so she can't respond or see the feedback.
That's indicated by the icon
to the left of her feedback.
I want to reassign this feedback
to someone else on my team
so they get notified
in case Apple has a response.
Now, because I'm the administrator
for this team,
I have some extra abilities on feedback
in my team space.
I can reassign this feedback
to a different teammate.
I'll assign it to Sean.
Now, if Sean wants to send it
to somebody else,
he can do that too,
as the current assignee.
We have two other abilities
available only to administrators.
Remove from Team moves the feedback
back into a submitter's personal space.
And current assignees already have
the ability to close the feedback.
But as an administrator,
I can also close my teammate's feedback
when we're done with the bug.
Teams functionality is available
in this year's iOS, iPadOS
and macOS releases
and on the web
at feedbackassistant.apple.com.
Now, I'll hand it back to Danny
to talk about configuring team feedback.
Thank you, Pete.
For those of you wondering
how to start using Teams,
there is some configuring available
on Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager to discuss.
Within Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager,
please ensure
that roles you want to participate
have Participate in AppleSeed for IT
privilege enabled.
By default, this privilege is enabled
on all roles in Apple Business Manager.
There must always be an AppleSeed for IT
administrator in your org.
The Administer AppleSeed for IT privilege
is required for administrator roles
and optional for people manager roles.
In Apple School Manager,
the Administer AppleSeed for IT privilege
is also mandatory
for the administrator role
and optional for the site manager
and people manager roles.
Participate in AppleSeed is enabled
by default on all roles except students,
which are excluded from testing.
Let's recap.
Testing keeps us both ahead of the curve.
There are so many incredible ways
to use Apple's technology,
and we need your help
to ensure that your organization isn't
negatively impacted by the next release.
The AppleSeed for IT program
is focused on education and enterprise
IT departments,
and we encourage you
to participate with us.
And with Teams in Feedback Assistant,
you can truly collaborate
on team-owned feedback.
We're excited for you to try it out,
and we can't wait to hear your feedback.
Now, I'd like to introduce Jared
who'll be discussing
the exciting new changes
around managing software updates.
Thanks, Danny. My name is Jared,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Installation Team at Apple.
As my colleagues discussed earlier,
it is critical for IT
and system administrators
to be engaged in the development
of pre-release software.
Your involvement during seeding
ensures that you and your organization
will have a smooth transition
into every update
that Apple ships to its users.
Ideally, organizations should be
deploying updates
as they are released by Apple.
However, sometimes you need
a little extra time
to qualify and deploy updates
throughout your organization.
This is where managing software updates
comes into play.
Managing software updates
puts you in control
over the deployment schedule of updates.
It gives you time to verify
that updates are compatible
with your company's workflow
and existing propriety software.
Although this qualification
should be done during seeding,
sometimes more time is necessary.
Enables IT to have a uniform understanding
of what Apple software
is running on their devices.
By having a deterministic insight
into what software
in your organization is running,
it empowers your team to deal with
the same sets of issues across devices.
It's important to remember
that updates contain critical improvements
in the areas of stability,
performance and security.
Therefore,
organizations should do their best
to deploy updates as swiftly as possible.
Starting the installation
of a software update
via Mobile Device Management,
also known as MDM,
is a great choice for in-place upgrades.
An MDM command can be sent
to supervised devices
to download the latest qualifying version
from Apple.
Administrators can specify
to download and stage the update,
or to install the update as well.
A phased rollout approach can be useful
to reduce network congestion.
It is also advised to implement
content caching servers
for organizations
with constrained Internet resources.
It's important to note that only updates
that are still being signed by Apple
are permitted for installation.
It is also required
for devices to be enrolled in supervision
in order to remotely update the device.
For iPhone and iPad,
if a device has a passcode,
that passcode will need to be
entered first by the user
before the installation begins.
Let's start by talking about iOS,
iPadOS and tvOS.
On these platforms,
Apple supports deferring software updates.
This is controlled by MDM
and can be deployed to supervised devices
or through a profile.
If you choose to enable deferral,
the default behavior
is to defer all updates for 30 days
from the time
that Apple releases the update.
The IT administrator
can also override this default
and specify a value
between one to 90 days,
so that you can pick
whatever schedule works best for you.
Once the deferral window has expired,
the next update is evaluated
and is either presented for installation
or is also deferred.
Deferral windows are determined by date,
not by release version number.
Once an update has been installed,
it is not possible to downgrade
without erasing the device.
Apple only supports updating devices
to newer versions of the OS.
Apple signs its software
for production use,
and older releases may be revoked
to ensure that customers
are not susceptible to downgrade attacks.
Therefore,
if an erase install is performed,
it may be rejected by Apple
if the version being erased
has been revoked by Apple.
Typically, when a user
navigates into the Settings app
and taps on Software Update
in iOS or iPadOS,
they'll be presented with this screen.
As you may note, the user has full control
over their own update experience.
When you implement
the managed software update restriction,
you'll see this screen instead
if an update is presently being deferred.
On macOS, software updates control
more than just operating system updates,
it also controls out-of-band updates
such as Safari.
Therefore, we provide extra options
through the MDM interface.
An administrator can schedule a scan
across their fleet,
fetch the list of available updates
for all Macs,
get the status of all updates in progress
and schedule updates for installation.
The remote management of updates
requires the device to be supervised.
On the Mac,
the automatic checking for updates,
download and installation
is controlled by the settings
that the user has specified
in the Software Update Preference pane
in System Preferences.
These settings can be controlled via MDM
and are fully manageable.
IT Administrators are empowered to make
software update settings a user choice,
or to fully override them.
For macOS, the deferral process
is similar to the iOS process
as we've discussed earlier.
You can deploy a configuration profile
to delay updates for up to 90 days.
But here are some unique things
about the Mac.
Deferred updates are transparent
to the user in System Preferences.
Once an update
has passed its deferral window,
the user
will receive a notification to update
and the update will become visible
in System Preferences.
The Mac does not need to be supervised
in order to defer software updates.
A config profile can be installed
to control these settings.
Updates are automatically deferred
by date, not by their version number.
This allows the deferral
of multiple OS Updates in succession
rather than only deferring
one update at a time.
For example, it is possible to defer
10.16.1 and 10.16.2
while 10.16.3 is currently released.
As long as it has not been
greater than 90 days
since the update was released by Apple.
In prior releases of macOS,
it was not possible
to defer software updates
while an update was in seeding.
Let's take a closer look at how you might
choose to manage software updates.
In this example, macOS 10.16
will be released
for approximately 30 days.
Please note that this is only an example.
Typically, before Apple
chooses to release an update,
it undergoes rigorous beta testing.
This is the time at which you should
start getting involved
in testing the release
against your workflows.
By qualifying your environment
during seeding,
gives you time, and Apple,
to fix any issues that are discovered
before the release ships.
Now, on day 30, Apple has decided
that macOS 10.16.1
is ready to ship to the public.
This is exciting because the bugs that
you've been filing with Feedback Assistant
may now be fixed.
Now it's time to certify the final build
against your environment.
This is the time
to defer the software update.
Preferably for as short of a time
as possible.
The update is then pushed out
to your environment...
and then the cycle continues.
We want IT and enterprises
engaged in testing the features
that they know and love
before they are deployed
to their organization.
Therefore, we are bringing support
for deferring software updates
while macOS Big Sur is undergoing seeding.
Administrators are encouraged to try out
the deferral of software updates
and to file us feedback
using Feedback Assistant
if they find any issues
with the deferral of updates.
In addition, we received tons of feedback
from Mac admins
requesting the ability
to defer major releases of macOS.
As of macOS Catalina 10.15.4,
we introduced the ability
to defer major releases
under the same deferral window
as other software updates.
We plan on improving this in the future,
and we value your feedback.
In macOS Big Sur,
we have some exciting new security changes
that better protect our users.
This year, we have unified
our installation technology
across all of our platforms.
The Mac now uses the same reliable
and secure installation technology as iOS.
In addition, we are snapshotting
the system volume.
This enables
a quicker software update experience
since the system snapshot is patched
while the user is using their Mac.
This is similar to the experience
iOS and iPadOS users
have come to know and love.
We are also
cryptographically sealing those snapshots
using authenticated APFS.
This enables us to verify on boot
that the user's system matches
what was delivered by Apple.
As file system blocks are read from disk,
they are hashed up the file system chain
and compared to the root hash.
If the root hash does not match
what was signed by Apple,
the seal is considered broken
and the device's kernel
will immediately panic.
On macOS, we realize
that there are power users and researchers
that want to be able to modify
the system volume.
Therefore, Apple is permitting
authenticated APFS
to be disabled by modifying
your security settings in the recovery OS,
though this is strongly discouraged.
Lastly, the qualification of OS updates
is now server-driven as it is on iOS.
With these exciting new changes,
we are deprecating some
less commonly used technologies.
In macOS Big Sur,
we have removed the ability
for third-party software update catalogs.
As it is on iOS, the installation catalog
is managed by Apple.
We are also dropping support
for deferring updates indefinitely.
As we have discussed,
updates contain critical reliability,
performance and security updates.
Therefore, we want our users
to be on the latest software possible.
For macOS Catalina and macOS Mojave,
we will be reintroducing support
for ignoring updates
in the 10.15.6 aligned security releases
as long as those devices
are under supervision.
However, in macOS Big Sur,
and moving forward,
ignoring updates indefinitely
is no longer supported.
We are strongly encouraging you
to utilize update deferral
and participate in seeding.
As a reminder,
make sure to actively participate
in pre-release software.
Get your feedback in early
to ensure your organization is ready
for the upcoming release.
Join AppleSeed for IT to gain access
to in-depth documentation and resources.
Work with your extended Apple contacts
such as your account team, sales team
or AppleCare.
Make sure to utilize
Feedback Assistant extensively.
Apple values your feedback,
and by providing feedback early,
we can get your issues resolved
before the release ships.
Take control over the software
that is deployed in your organization
by managing software updates,
and limit the usage of update deferral
by certifying your workflows early
by participating in pre-release software.
Check out these other exciting sessions
for more on managing Apple devices.
Thank you,
and on behalf of everyone at Apple,
we hope that you have a fantastic WWDC.