Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Kyle Piddington.
I'm an engineer in Apple's GPU software
technology group.
In this session,
my colleague Ravi and I are going
to show you some of the new advancements
to ship your new
or existing precompiled GPU code.
This talk will consist of four parts.
First up, I'll provide an overview
of Metal's current shader
compilation model.
Next, I'm going to introduce
Metal Binary Archives,
a new way for you to take control
over shader caching,
and ship precompiled GPU executables
to your users.
I'm excited to share the new support
for dynamic libraries in Metal.
This feature will allow you
to link your compute shaders
against utility libraries dynamically.
And finally, Ravi will present in detail
the set of tools that you have
in your toolchain
to make the most
out of these new features.
Let's get started.
We'll begin with a review of the shader
and pipeline compilation process
on Apple platforms.
As you know, the Metal Shading Language
is our programming language for shaders.
Metal compiles this code
into Apple's Intermediate Representation,
also known as AIR.
This can be done off-line in Xcode,
or at runtime on the target device itself.
Building off-line avoids the runtime cost
of compiling source code to AIR.
In both cases, however,
when creating pipeline state objects,
this intermediate representation
is further compiled on device
to generate machine-specific code
needed for each particular GPU.
This process occurs
for every pipeline state.
To accelerate recompilation
and recreation of pipelines,
we cache the Metal Function variants
produced in this step
for future pipeline creation.
This process is great,
and has served us well for many years.
But for games and apps
that adopt the Metal best practice
of building pipeline objects early on
to provide a hitch-free experience,
this process can potentially result
in long loading screens.
Additionally, under this model,
apps are unable to reuse
any previously-generated machine code
subroutines across pipeline state objects.
We've gathered feedback coming in
from our ecosystem of developers,
and have been able to identify
a concrete set of needs
that will enable you
to address these challenges.
You might want a way to save the entire
time of pipeline state compilation,
from source, to AIR, to a GPU binary.
You might also want a mechanism
that enables sharing common subroutines
and utility functions
without the need of compiling
the same code twice,
or having it loaded in memory
more than once.
Having the ability to ship apps that
already include the final compiled code
for executables as well as libraries
gives you the tools to provide a fantastic
first-time launch experience.
And allowing you to share
these executables and libraries
with other developers
make their development easier.
One of the ways we are addressing these
needs is via the Metal Binary Archives.
Since the beginnings of Metal,
apps have benefited
from a system-wide shader cache
that accelerates creating pipeline objects
that have been created
from previous runs of the application.
With Metal Binary Archives,
explicit control over pipeline state
caching is being provided to you.
This direct control over caching
gives you the opportunity
to manually collect compiled
pipeline state objects,
organize them into different archives
based off of usage or need,
and even harvest them from a device
and distribute them
to other compatible devices.
Binary Archives can be thought of
as any other asset type.
You have full control
over the Binary Archive lifetimes,
and these persist as long as desired.
Binary Archives are a feature
of the Metal GPU Families Apple3 and Mac1.
Creating a Binary Archive is simple.
For this feature, we created
a new descriptor type for Binary Archives.
I use this descriptor to create a new
Metal Binary Archive from the device.
This descriptor contains a URL property.
And this is used to determine
if I want to create a new, empty archive,
or if I want to load one from disk.
When we request a new archive be loaded,
this file will be memory-mapped in.
And we can immediately start
to use these loaded archives
to accelerate our subsequent
pipeline build requests.
The Binary Archive API
allows me to directly add pipelines
I'm interested in to the archive.
I can add Render, Compute,
and TileRender pipelines.
Adding a pipeline to the Binary Archive
causes a back-end compilation
of the shader source,
generating the machine code
to be stored in the archive.
Finally, once I'm done collecting all
the pipeline objects I'm interested in,
I call serializeToURL
to save the archive to disk.
Once I have my Binary Archives on disk,
I can harvest them from device
and deploy them
on other compatible devices
to accelerate their pipeline state builds.
The only requirement is that
these other devices have the same GPU
and are running the same
operating system build.
If there's a mismatch,
the metal framework will fall back
on runtime compilation
of the pipeline functions.
Once I have my Binary Archive populated,
reusing a cached pipeline
is straightforward.
When creating a pipeline,
I set the pipeline descriptor's
binaryArchives property
to an array of archives.
The framework will then search the array
linearly for the function binaries.
If the pipeline is found in any
of the Binary Archives on the list,
it will be returned to you,
avoiding the compilation process entirely
and will not impact
the Metal Shader Cache.
In the case
that the pipeline is not found,
the OS's MTLCompilerService
will kick into gear
and compile my AIR source
to machine code, return the results,
and cache the results
in the Metal Shader Cache.
This process takes time,
but the pipeline will be cached
in the Metal Shader Cache
to accelerate any subsequent
pipeline build requests.
Now that I've gone over the workflow,
let's take a look at the API
to accomplish it.
First, I create
the MTLBinaryArchiveDescriptor.
This is used to determine whether
I want to create a new, empty archive
or to load an existing one.
Creating a Binary Archive is always done
from a descriptor.
In this case, I set the URL to nil.
The device will create a new,
empty archive.
Finally, I call the function
"makeBinaryArchive" to create it.
Next, I'll populate a Binary Archive
using pipeline descriptors.
I can add Render, Compute,
and TileRender descriptors
to the Binary Archive.
Reusing compiled functions
from a Binary Archive
allows me to skip
the back-end function compilation.
I can create my pipeline descriptors
just as I always have
and use the new binaryArchives property
to indicate which archives be searched.
I want to do this
before creating the pipeline.
Once you have collected all the pipelines
you are interested in,
you can serialize the Binary Archive
to a writable file location on disk,
using the method "serialize."
Here, I'm serializing the archive
to my application's "documents" directory.
On the next run of my app,
I can now deserialize the archive
to avoid recompiling the pipelines
that were previously added and serialized.
I simply set the URL
to point to the location
of an existing,
pre-populated cache on disk.
Now, one final note about archive search.
Depending on your use case,
you may find it helpful to be able
to short-circuit the fallback behavior
of compiling a pipeline
when it's not found in the archive.
In this case, you can specify
the pipeline compile option
FailOnBinaryArchiveMiss.
If the pipeline is found
in any of the archives,
it is returned to you as usual.
However, in the case that it is not found,
the device will return nil.
One use case I recommend is using
this workflow for debugging purposes.
Avoiding the compilation process
will let you diagnose any problems
in your app's logic,
or your archive's data.
Let's take a moment to discuss
the memory considerations
of using Binary Archives.
As mentioned before,
it is important to note
that the Binary Archive file
is memory-mapped in.
This means that we need to reserve a range
of virtual memory
in order to access the archive's contents.
This virtual memory range will be released
when you release your cache,
so it's important to close
any Binary Archives
that are no longer needed for optimal use
of the virtual address space.
When collecting new pipelines,
Binary Archives present
a similar memory footprint
to using the system's Metal Shader Cache.
But unlike when using
the Metal Shader Cache,
we have the chance to free up this memory.
Having explicit control
over archive lifetime
allows you to serialize and release
a Metal Binary Archive
when you are done collecting
pipeline state objects.
In addition, when you reuse
an existing archive,
the pipelines in this archive do not count
against your active app memory.
You can serialize,
and then reopen this archive
and only use it
for retrieving cached pipelines,
effectively freeing the memory
that was used in the collection process.
This is not possible when relying
on the system's Metal Shader Cache.
I'd like to wrap up this part
of the session
by discussing some of the best practices
for working with Binary Archives.
Although there is no size limit
for Binary Archives,
I recommend dividing your game assets
into several different caches.
Games are an excellent candidate
for breaking up caches
into frequently used pipelines
and per-level pipelines.
Dividing the cache
gives you the opportunity
to completely release
no-longer-needed caches.
This will free memory
in case we've collected any new pipelines,
as well as
the virtual memory range in use.
When following this guidance,
Binary Archives gives you granular control
and should be favored
over prewarming the Metal Shader Cache.
Modern apps often have too many unique
permutations of shader variants
that are generated based off
of user choices.
With Metal Binary Archives,
you can now capture them all at runtime.
Let's take a look how this all
comes together in practice.
We've partnered with Epic Games
to quantify exactly how reusing
a pre-harvested Binary Archive
can help improve
pipeline state object creation times,
as well as the developer workflow
in the context of Unreal Engine.
For this test,
we used the pipeline state workload
of a AAA title, Fortnite.
Fortnite is a large game.
It's got a big world and many character
and item customization options.
This makes for a large number
of shader function variants
and pipeline state objects,
over 11,000, in fact.
Epic Games follows
the Metal Best Practices
and compiles the needed
pipeline state objects at load time,
which allows minimizing hitching
at runtime
and delivers the smoothest experience
possible to users.
But apps, as we mentioned,
cannot benefit from the Metal Shader Cache
before it's been populated.
So the up-front compilation time adds up,
potentially making the first time launch
experience take longer than desired.
By pre-seeding a harvested
Metal Binary Archive
that had collected function variants
from 1,700 pipeline state objects,
we observed a massive speedup
in the creation times
when we compare against starting
with an empty Metal Shader Cache.
These results were measured on a six-core,
three gigahertz Mac Mini
with 32 gigabytes of RAM.
When we focus on pipeline build times,
we go from spending one minute
and 26 seconds building pipelines
to just three seconds.
Overall, a speedup of over 28 times.
To summarize, Metal Binary Archives allow
you to manually manage pipeline caches.
These can be harvested from a device
and deployed on other compatible devices
to dramatically reduce the pipeline
creation times
the first time a game or app is installed,
and after a device reboots
in the case of iOS.
AAA games and other apps bound by a very
large number of pipeline state objects
can benefit from this feature
to obtain extraordinary gains
in pipeline creation times
under these conditions.
Building and shipping
GPU executable binaries
with your application
allows you to accelerate
your first time launch experience
and cold-boot app experiences.
I hope you take advantage
of this new feature.
And that's it for Metal Binary Archives.
Next, I'm going to talk about
another new feature
we're bringing to the compilation model,
dynamic libraries.
Metal Dynamic Libraries are a new feature
that will allow you
to build well-abstracted
and reusable compute-shared library code
for your applications.
I'll be discussing the concept, execution,
and details of dynamic libraries.
Today, developers may choose to create
utility libraries of Metal functions
to compile with their kernels.
Off-line compilation can save time
while generating these libraries,
but there's still two costs that occur
when using a utility library.
Every app pays the cost
of generating machine code
for the utility library at PSO generation.
In addition, compiling multiple pipelines
with the same utility library
results in duplicated machine code
for subroutines.
This can result in longer
pipeline load times
due to back-end compilation
and increased GPU memory usage.
And this year, we're introducing
a solution to this problem,
the Metal Dynamic Library.
The Metal Dynamic Library enables you
to dynamically link, load
and share utility functions
in the form of machine code.
This code is reusable between multiple
compute pipelines,
eliminating duplicate compilation
and the storing of shared subroutines.
In addition,
much like the Metal Binary Archive,
the Metal Dynamic Library is serializable
and shippable as an asset
in your application.
Before we dive into the API,
let's talk about
what a Metal Dynamic Library is.
A Metal Dynamic Library is a collection
of exported functions
that can be called
from multiple compute pipelines.
Later, we will discuss which functions
in your dylib are exported
and how to manage them.
Unlike an executable Metal Library,
dynamic libraries cannot be used
to create MTLFunctions.
However, standard Metal Libraries
can import functions that are implemented
in a dynamic library.
At pipeline creation time,
the dynamic library is linked
to resolve any imported functions,
much like a dynamic library's used
in a typical application.
So why might you want to use
dynamic libraries?
If your application
can be structured into,
or relies on a shared utility codebase,
dynamic libraries are for you.
Using dynamic libraries in your app
prevents recompiling and duplicating
machine code across pipeline states.
If you are interested in developing
Metal middleware,
dynamic libraries provide you the ability
to ship a utility library to your users.
Unlike before where you would have
to ship sources to developers,
or compile their code
with a static Metal Library,
a dynamic library can be provided
and updated
without requiring users
to rebuild their own metallib files.
Finally, dynamic libraries
give you the power
to expose hooks for your users
to create custom kernels.
The Metal API exposes the ability
to change which libraries
are loaded at pipeline creation time,
allowing you the ability to inject
user-defined behavior
into your shaders
without creating the Metal Library
and MTLFunctions
containing your entry points.
To determine if metal dynamic libraries
are supported for your GPU,
check the feature query
"supportsDynamicLibraries."
In the next few slides,
we'll work through an example
of how to create a dynamic library,
how symbols are resolved,
and some more advanced linking scenarios.
A standard Metal Library is compiled
to AIR through either a makeLibrary
with source call at runtime,
or through compiling your library
with the Metal toolchain.
To create a Metal Dynamic Library,
we begin with a similar workflow.
We start by creating a Metal Library,
but when doing so, we specify
that we'd like this library to be used
as a dynamic library.
Next, we call the function
makeDynamicLibrary,
which will back-end-compile
our metal code to machine code.
This is the only time you will need
to compile the dynamic library.
We need one more bit of information,
a unique install name.
At pipeline creation time,
these names are used by the linker
to load the dynamic library.
The linker supports two relative paths,
@executable_path,
which refers to the metallib
containing an executable kernel,
and @loader_path, which refers
to the metallib containing a load command.
An absolute path can also be used.
With an install name and a library type,
I'm now ready to create a dynamic library.
Once I've set the compile options,
I create a Metal Library which will
compile my library from source to AIR.
Then, I call the API method
makeDynamicLibrary on the Metal device,
which will compile my dynamic library
into machine code.
Now that we've covered how to create
a dynamic library,
let's take a look at how we can use it.
In these next few examples,
I'll be discussing how we can link
dynamic libraries at runtime.
These operations can also be achieved
when compiling Metal libraries off-line.
And we'll discuss our off-line workflow
later in this session.
To link a dynamic library
when compiling a metallib from source,
add the dynamic library
to the "libraries" property
of the MTLCompileOptions
before you compile your library.
The specified library will be linked
at pipeline creation time.
However, symbol resolution will be checked
at compile time
to make sure at least
one implementation of the function exists.
To review these steps,
when creating a metallib from source,
source files should include headers
that define functions available
in your dynamic libraries.
At compile time,
dynamic libraries included
in the "libraries" option
are searched for at least one
matching function signature.
If no signature is found,
compilation will fail,
explaining which symbols are missing.
However, unlike when compiling
with static libraries,
or header-only libraries,
this compilation does not bind
the function call
to the function implementation.
At pipeline creation time,
libraries are linked and loaded,
and a function implementation is chosen.
We'll go over the case
where multiple dynamic libraries export
the same function in just a moment.
In addition to executable Metal Libraries
linking dynamic libraries,
dynamic libraries can also reference
other dynamic libraries.
If all these libraries were created
from source at runtime,
linking Dylib2 and Dylib3 to Dylib1
is as simple as setting
the Metal compiler option
libraries property on creation.
And, to reiterate one more time,
dylibs are shared between kernels.
And although multiple kernels
link the same dylib,
only one instance of the dylib
exists in memory.
Because linking is deferred
to pipeline creation time,
we can replace functions, or even
full libraries with new implementations
by using the insertLibraries property
of the ComputePipelineDescriptor.
Setting this option is comparable
to setting the DYLD_INSERT_LIBRARIES
environment variable.
At pipeline creation time,
the linker will first search
through inserted libraries
to find imported symbols
before looking
through the kernel's linked libraries
for any remaining imported symbols.
In this example, DylibA
exports the function foo.
And when we create
the compute pipeline state,
foo will be linked
to the implementation in DylibA.
When we use insertLibraries,
both DylibA and DylibD
export the function foo.
When we create the pipeline state,
we walk down the list
of imported libraries
to resolve the symbol.
And instead of linking
the implementation of foo in DylibA,
we will instead link from foo and DylibD.
Finally, let's discuss distributing
your dynamic libraries.
Much like Binary Archives,
compiled dynamic libraries
can be serialized out to URL.
Both the precompiled binary
and the generic AIR
for the Metal Library are serialized.
If you end up distributing
the dynamic library
as an asset in your project,
the Metal framework will recompile
the AIR slice into machine code
if the target device cannot use
the precompiled binary.
This would occur when loading your dylib
on a different architecture or OS.
This compilation is not added
to the Metal Shader Cache,
so make sure to serialize
and load your library next time
to save compilation time.
To help you adopt this API
and to work through a small example,
we've provided a sample Xcode project
available on developer.apple.com.
This sample uses a compute shader
to apply a full-screen
postprocessing effect.
The compute shader
calls in to a dynamic library
to determine the pixel color.
And at runtime,
we demonstrate how insertLibraries
can be used to change
which function it's linked against.
If you're interested
in running this code yourself,
head to developer.apple.com
and download
the Metal Dynamic Library sample.
We're really excited
to bring you these features.
Dynamic libraries allow you
to write reusable library code
without paying the cost in time or memory
of recompiling your utilities.
And, like Binary Archives,
dynamic libraries
are serializable and shippable.
In the sample code, we've demonstrated
how you can use dynamic libraries
to allow users to write their own methods
without requiring users to write
their own kernel entry points.
This feature is supported
this year in iOS and macOS.
Check the feature query on your device
to see if your GPU
supports dynamic libraries.
So far, we've talked about some
of the ways we're updating
our shader model in Metal this year.
In the final part of our talk,
we'll be discussing additional updates
to our off-line toolchains.
To help me cover this topic,
I'm going to hand you over
to my colleague, Ravi.
Thank you, Kyle, and hello everyone.
In the previous sections,
we heard about how to create and use
Binary Archives and dynamic libraries
using the Metal API.
I'm Ravi Ramaseshan
from the Metal Front-End Compiler Team,
and in this section
I'm going to talk to you
about how to create
and manipulate these objects
using the Metal Developer Tools.
With a small code base,
you can put all your code
into a couple of Metal files
and build a metallib
using a command line
like the one shown below.
As your code base grows,
you keep adding files
to the same command line.
But it becomes hard to track dependencies
between all your shader sources.
To address this,
we are bringing libraries to Metal.
Libraries come in three flavors.
The kind of metallibs
that you've been building up until now,
the ones you use
to create your Metal functions
are what we call executable metallibs.
For your non-entry point or utility code,
you can now create
static or dynamic libraries.
Along with Metal libraries,
we are also bringing more tools to Metal
which mimic the CPU toolchain.
All these tools together
form the Metal Developer Tools
which can be found
in your Xcode toolchain.
We'll see how to use these tools
to improve your shader
compilation workflows.
To get started,
let's use the Metal compiler
on our Metal sources to get
the corresponding AIR files
using the command line below.
With that out of the way...
let's use a new tool in the toolchain,
metal-libtool,
which like its CPU counterpart
is used to build libraries.
The static option archives
all the AIR files together
to build a static library.
We'll then run the linker
through the Metal compiler
to link the AIR files
with the static library
to create our executable metallibs.
The lowercase "L" option
followed by a name
is how you get the linker
to link against your library.
You can also use the uppercase "L" option
to get the linker to search directories
in addition to the default system paths.
The way to think about static linking
is that each of your executable metallibs
has a copy of the static library.
This has a few implications.
On the bright side, your metallibs
are self-contained and easy to deploy
since they have no runtime dependencies.
Also, the compiler and linker
have access to the concrete
implementations of your library,
so they can perform
link-time-optimizations,
resulting in potentially
smaller and faster code.
On the downside,
you may be duplicating the library
into each of your metallibs,
resulting in a larger app bundle.
Fortunately, dynamic linking
is a powerful mechanism
to address this problem.
To create dynamic libraries,
we'll invoke the linker
by using the dynamiclib option.
The install_name option to the linker
is the toolchain counterpart
of the Metal API you saw earlier.
The install name is recorded
into the metallib
for the loader to find
the library at runtime.
Now, we'll link the utility library
with our AIR files
to get our executable metallibs.
With dynamic linking,
the utility library does not get copied
into the executable metallibs,
but instead has to be deployed
on the target system separately.
Let's see how the loader finds
the dynamic library at runtime.
It starts when you build the library.
The linker uses
the install name of the dylib
to embed a load command
into the resulting metallib.
Think of it as a reference to the dylib
that this metallib depends on.
The load command is how the loader locates
and loads the dylib at runtime.
You can have multiple
of these load commands
if you link with more than one library.
Finally, let's revisit
the install_name option we used
when building our dylib and see
how a couple of special names work.
Let's assume that libUtility
depends on another dylib
and focus on how the loader
resolves these special names
in the load command for libUtility.
At runtime, the loader finds the library
to be loaded using the install name,
but replaces @loader_path
with the path of the metallib
containing the load command.
Metal also supports @executable_path
which the loader resolves
to the path of the executable metallib
containing the entry point function.
You can probably see
that for executable metallibs
both these special names
resolve to the same location.
Through load commands,
each of your metallibs
record only a reference to the dylib.
Binding an implementation
of the symbol to its reference
is done at runtime by the loader.
This, too, has some implications.
On the positive side,
using dynamic libraries
solves the duplication problem
we saw with static libraries.
The downside is that at runtime,
the dylib needs to exist
for your executable metallibs to work
and the loader must be able to find it.
Since libraries can be written
by multiple authors,
you run the risk of name collisions
between the libraries.
Like in this example,
the two libraries unintentionally export
the same symbol calculate.
The expected behavior was for each library
to use its own calculate function.
In fact, with static linking,
you would've gotten
an error at build time.
However, with dynamic linking,
the loader just picks one definition
and binds all references to it.
Because of this,
you may only get an incorrect result
observed at runtime
and can be quite hard to track down.
So, why does the calculate function
participate in dynamic linking?
That's because, just like
with the CPU compiler and linker,
by default, Metal exports
all the symbols in your library.
You can quickly check the symbols
in your library using metal-nm,
which, like its CPU counterpart,
let's you inspect the names of the symbols
that are exported by your metallib.
The question then is, how do we control
what symbols are exported by our library.
Just like on the CPU side,
you can use the static keyword,
anonymous namespaces
and the visibility attributes
to control which symbols
are exported by your library.
It's also a good idea to use namespaces
when defining your interfaces.
And finally, we support
the exported_symbols_list linker option.
For more details,
there's some great documentation
on our developer website
on dynamic libraries.
The other exciting concept
that we introduced to you earlier
was harvesting fully compiled binaries
from the device.
We have harvested such a metallib
for libUtility on an A13 device
using the Metal API that we saw
in the previous section.
To work with such objects,
there's a new tool called metal-lipo.
Let's use it to peek
into what's in the metallib
that we just harvested
using the info option.
The tool reports that this metallib
contains two architectures.
The way to think about that
is it is a fat binary that really contains
two independent metallibs called "slices."
The A13 slice, which is back-end compiled
and the generic AIR slice.
When the harvested metallib
is deployed on non-A13 devices,
Metal will use the AIR slice,
just as it does today.
That means spinning up
the Metal Compiler Service
and invoking the back-end compiler
to build your pipeline.
This allows the metallib
to be used on all iOS devices,
not just A13-based ones.
However, if the same metallib
is downloaded on an A13 device,
Metal will use the A13 slice,
skip back-end compilation completely
and potentially improve
your app-loading performance.
Now, let's say you want to improve
the experience of your app users
that are also on A12 devices.
Besides the A13 device, let's also
harvest a metallib from an A12 device.
To simplify your app deployment,
you might want to bundle
all the slices into a single metallib.
Metal-lipo allows you to do just that
and create an even fatter
universal binary.
This technique can even be used
with Binary Archives.
Obviously, the more slices
that you pack into your binary,
the larger your app bundle becomes.
So keep that in mind when deciding
which slices you want to pack
into your universal binary.
So, let's do a quick recap
of the different workflows
we have seen today.
We started by using the Metal compiler
to turn our Metal sources into AIR files.
We then used metal-libtool
to create static libraries,
a new workflow to replace
your existing Metal AR-based one.
We then built a new kind of metallib,
a dynamic library.
We also saw how to combine
AIR, static and dynamic libraries
to create executable metallibs.
Along the way, we also saw using metal-nm
to inspect the symbols
exported by a metallib.
And finally, we used metal-lipo
to work with slices
in our harvested metallibs.
The last thing we want to show you
is a use case shared to us
by some of our game developers.
Here's a high-level view
of their workflow.
As you can see,
they use a variety of tools,
including the CPU and GPU toolchains,
to build the app bundle.
In some cases,
developers have pooled
their machines together
into a server farm that they use
to build their assets.
This workflow works great
as long as these tools run on macOS.
However, some of these developers
have established game and graphic
asset creation pipelines
that are based
on Microsoft Windows infrastructure.
In order to support these developers,
this year we are introducing
the Metal Developer Tools on Windows.
With this, you will now
have the flexibility
to build your metallibs
targeting Apple platforms
from macOS, Windows
or even a hybrid setup.
The tools are available
as a Windows Installer
and can be downloaded
from the Apple developer website today.
All the workflows that are supported
by the toolchain we release with Xcode
are also supported
by the Windows-hosted tools.
That brings us to the end of this session.
Let's recap what we covered here.
We introduced you to Binary Archives,
a mechanism which you can employ
to avoid spending time
on back-end compilation
for some of your critical pipelines.
We then presented
dynamic libraries in Metal
as an efficient and flexible way
to decouple your library code
from your shaders.
And finally, we went over some new
and important compilation workflows
by directly using
the Metal Developer Tools.
We hope this presentation gets you started
with adopting the new compilation model
for your new and existing workflows.
Thanks for watching this session,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.