Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
Hello. I'm Doug Wyatt
from the Core Audio team,
and today I'd like to introduce you
to audio workgroups.
If you develop an audio application
or plug-in that creates realtime threads,
then this talk is for you.
You're probably using realtime threads
for very low-latency audio synthesis
or signal processing.
It's important that you adopt
new API audio workgroups.
And these new APIs are available in
the fall 2020 releases of macOS and iOS.
Now, if you're wondering if you should
create your own realtime threads,
the answer is probably no.
If you do go down this path, though,
then follow the first rule
of performance tuning: measure everything.
Okay, let's dive in with some background.
Modern CPUs have performance controllers,
which make trade-offs between
power consumption and computing power.
The performance controller
helps assign threads to CPUs.
The CPUs themselves may have
differing power and speed characteristics.
The performance controller
can also dynamically change
the clock frequency of the CPUs.
Up until now, the main input into the
performance controller's decision-making
has been observations about
the running applications and daemons:
how many threads are they using
and how much work they are doing?
Now, because of
the time-critical nature of audio,
we've given it a new input
into the performance controller:
the new workgroup APIs.
Let's look now at audio workgroups.
Later, we'll see how to use them
in your apps and Audio Unit plug-ins.
First, a workgroup consists of
one or more threads.
There is a master thread
which wakes up periodically.
It tells the kernel
when it begins a work cycle,
and what the deadline for that work is.
The master thread might signal and wait
for other threads
that are part of the workgroup
and those threads
might be in other processes.
At the end of each work cycle,
the workgroup, again, notifies the kernel.
This diagram illustrates how Core Audio
runs an I/O thread in the audio server.
This thread wakes up at regular intervals
and has a deadline for each cycle.
Each time it wakes up,
it calls the client to produce output.
When the client is done,
then the output data is written
to the hardware and the I/O thread sleeps.
This is the master thread
of a device workgroup.
It informs the kernel of the
beginning and end of each work cycle.
If the client takes too long
to produce output data,
then the thread misses its deadline
and we get an overload.
The user hears this as a discontinuity,
or a glitch, in the audio.
So, it's important that the performance
controller be aware of the threads
that are producing audio
with that deadline.
For every audio server I/O thread,
there is a second thread
in the client application.
We see here that the audio server
wakes and waits for this thread
on each I/O cycle.
Both threads are colored in green here.
This illustrates that the audio frameworks
join the client-side thread
to the device's workgroup.
So, the kernel knows that both threads
are working together
towards a common deadline.
Here's a more complex situation:
the app is hosting two Audio Units
which are running in other processes.
In each render cycle,
the app renders the two Audio Units
serially, using two inter-process calls.
Here too, all of the realtime rendering
threads are owned by the audio frameworks,
so they are colored in green
to indicate that they are all
part of the device's workgroup.
What we've just seen is the good news.
The audio system's realtime threads
are automatically joined to workgroups.
Now, let's look at apps which have
their own realtime audio threads.
Here we have an app
that's running two auxiliary threads
in parallel with the I/O thread.
For example, it might be rendering
three complex tracks.
It splits the work between
the auxiliary threads and the I/O thread,
and the I/O thread waits for the worker
threads and mixes the final result.
These threads are in shown in gray
to illustrate a problem:
they're not part of the workgroup.
They're running with the same deadline
as the threads in the workgroup,
but the scheduler doesn't know this.
So, the solution is to join these threads
to the workgroup.
And we can see how.
First, obtain the device's
os_workgroup object.
On macOS, you can obtain it directly from
the audio device with the HAL API.
On any platform,
you can obtain it from the input/output
audio unit, AUHAL, or AURemoteIO,
using these properties.
Once you've obtained
the device's workgroup,
then in your realtime thread,
call os_workgroup_join.
This joins the thread to the workgroup
and only has to be done once.
You'll also need to call
os_workgroup_leave
before your thread ends.
The details are in these header files.
After you've done this,
then your app's parallel realtime threads
are part of the device's workgroup.
All the threads are in green.
Let's look at a more complex app.
It is also running two auxiliary threads,
but they are running asynchronously
to the I/O threads,
with different deadlines.
Since they have different deadlines
from the device I/O threads,
these auxiliary threads
need to be in two additional workgroups.
Let's see how.
First, instead of obtaining
the device's workgroup as we saw before,
create your own workgroup
using AudioWorkIntervalCreate.
As before, you need to join
the realtime threads to the workgroup,
using os_workgroup_join.
And again, this only has to be done once.
You might have multiple threads
in your group,
but one is controlling the others.
It's the "master."
In this thread, on each work cycle,
call os_workgroup_interval_start.
The startTime parameter can be "now,"
as reported by mach_absolute_time.
Or it can be in the past,
if you know exactly when your work cycle
was scheduled to start,
presumably in the recent past.
The deadline has to be greater
than the start time.
The units are mach_absolute_time.
Here, be sure not to assume that
mach_absolute_time are nanoseconds
or anything else.
Be sure to use mach_timebase_info to get
the clock frequency of mach_absolute_time.
Then at the end of each work cycle,
call os_workgroup_interval_finish.
After you have joined your asynchronous
auxiliary threads to workgroups,
things look like this.
There are three independent workgroups
working on separate cadences
with separate deadlines
that cover apps
which create realtime threads.
Now, let's look at Audio Units
The vast majority of Audio Units
don't do this,
but there are a few
large and powerful ones
that do create
their own extra rendering threads.
Here's an example.
This Audio Unit is dividing its work
between four threads,
three that it has created,
plus one from the host.
You can see the problem here:
the Audio Unit has realtime threads
that are not part of a workgroup.
It's being called by the host
in some unknown thread context.
That context could be
the device's I/O thread,
or it could be
a non-realtime worker thread.
The Audio Unit doesn't know.
To solve this, we're introducing
the AURenderContextObserver.
This is a block in the audio unit that
gets called before each render request.
As the audio unit developer,
you implement
this render context observer property
to return a block
that receives a context struct.
This struct contains an os_workgroup.
So, at render time, when you see
that the context's workgroup has changed,
you can join your auxiliary
realtime threads to that workgroup,
as we saw earlier,
using os_workgroup_join.
It's important to be aware here
that the workgroup may change
from one render call to the next.
After you implement
the render context observer,
and you join your realtime threads
to the workgroup it observes,
then here too we have all realtime threads
joined to workgroups.
It's very important to note here:
the system informs Audio Units
of the workgroup
using the render context observer.
This happens automatically
when the host renders.
So, the host should not try to call
the render context observer.
Again, the system
handles this automatically.
That brings me
to the main point of this talk:
all audio threads
should be joined to workgroups.
And now we've seen the APIs
you can use to do this.
You might be wondering about
non-realtime audio rendering threads.
They don't have deadlines,
so they can't be joined to workgroups.
If your non-realtime threads
do have deadlines,
that might be a reason
to convert them to realtime.
But again, measure performance
if you start down this path.
If you're creating
parallel worker threads,
there is a new API which will recommend
how many threads to create:
and that's
os_workgroup_max_parallel_threads.
You can't call this
until you know your workgroup,
which, if you're an Audio Unit,
might not be
until you're rendering in realtime.
In that case,
when your Audio Unit is initialized,
then you create as many threads
as there are CPU cores,
but make a render-time decision to use
only the recommended number of threads.
To summarize, here are all the different
kinds of realtime threads we looked at,
and how to make sure
they are joined to workgroups.
The system frameworks
take care of all the threads they manage.
For app threads
that are parallel to the device thread,
join them to the device's workgroup.
For app threads that are
asynchronous to the device thread,
create and manage a workgroup of your own
and join those threads to that workgroup.
For Audio Unit threads that are
parallel to the host's render requests,
implement a render context observer,
and join threads
to the workgroup it observes.
We've seen how to improve the performance
of your app or plug-in's
audio realtime threads
by joining them to audio workgroups.
Thank you for your time and attention,
and I look forward to seeing
your great music and audio apps.