Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Roger Pantos.
And today we are gonna talk about
inserting ads into Low-Latency HLS.
To set the stage for that,
let's start with a quick review
of how regular live HLS works.
Usually, in a live HLS, the server adds
a new segment every target duration,
and the client reloads that Playlist every
Target Duration to see what's changed.
So the timing model for the client is
defined entirely by the current Playlist
and the segments inside it.
The first segment in the current Playlist
defines the earliest seekable point
and the end of the last segment represents
what's currently the live edge
of the presentation.
Now that's important because clients
use the position of that live edge
to make some essential decisions,
such as how close it is safe to play
without stalling.
So let's take a look at Playlists
in a graphical way.
We'll start with a Playlist
that has four six-second segments.
Six seconds later a new segment is added
and the Playlist is updated
to roll the first segment
out of the Playlist.
We're showing it here as gray
because it is no longer part
of the live window.
Now the end of segment five
is the live edge.
Next we'll add a new segment
and the process repeats.
Now one consequence of this is that
if every segment is six seconds,
then each segment
has a six-second publishing delay.
In other words,
you have to wait for six seconds
before any part of that segment
becomes available for playback,
even the first few frames.
That's a long time
if you want to play really close to live.
So enter Low-Latency HLS
and Partial Segments.
Partial Segments
are like looking through a microscope
at the live edge of the presentation.
The way it works
is that every regular segment
at the live edge, called a Parent Segment,
is accompanied
by a series of shorter Partial Segments.
And these offer the same media
just with a lower publishing latency.
So, in this case,
the client can get the first media
from segment five after only two seconds
instead of waiting for six seconds.
Two seconds after that
it can get a little bit more.
And then two seconds after that,
the final part of segment five appears
along with segment five itself.
Now there's nothing magic about
six seconds and two seconds here.
You can use any combination of durations.
Here we've looked at Low-Latency HLS
and how it differs from regular live HLS
for delivering program content.
Let's stick a pin in that
for just a second
and go back to regular live HLS
so we can talk about ad insertion.
Now there are a few different variations,
but the basic idea is that you'll start
with a source feed for your program
that includes markers
for where the ads can be inserted.
Now these markers are often not
on regular segment boundaries.
So your packager may need
to add a short segment
so the ad can start
exactly on a segment boundary.
When it's time to pick an ad,
your decisioning engine will choose
one out of your available inventory.
Then your packager will begin replacing
program segments with the ad segments
separating them with discontinuity tags.
The packager will then continue to spool
out ad segments, one per Target Duration,
until it reaches the end of the ad,
and then it goes back
to regular program segments.
So to go back to our diagram,
it's gonna look like this.
We start with these three program segments
in blue.
When an ad comes up,
we place one last short program segment
to align with the start
of the ad boundary.
Then we wait six seconds
and then we lay down the first ad segment.
Then six seconds after that
we lay down a second ad segment.
At the end of the ad, it might not end
exactly on a segment boundary.
So we might have again a short segment.
This time a short ad segment.
And then we wait six seconds more
and then we lay down
the first program segment after the ad.
This is ad insertion for regular live HLS,
for Low-Latency HLS
you'll do much of the same thing
but with program segments
added to the mix.
So here we have the same stream,
but for Low-Latency
it has Partial Segments as well.
It updates faster. So after two seconds
you get another Partial Segment.
And then you'll get
a short Partial Segment
to line up to the ad boundary
along with the Parent Segment.
At this point,
we'll start spooling out the ad.
The packager needs to maintain
the same Low-Latency timing model.
Which means, every two seconds
it'll add a Partial Segment from the ad.
So then two seconds after that
we'll get another
and two seconds after that
we'll get the last one
along with the Parent Segment from the ad.
This then continues
through the next ad segment.
And then the ad ends
on a short Partial Segment
to line up with the ad boundary
just like the program segments did.
After that the program Partial Segments
and Parent Segments resume,
and you're back to the program.
So inserting ads
into Low-Latency HLS is very similar
to doing it with regular live HLS.
The biggest difference is that
before ads are spooled
out as regular segments
they get doled out
as Partial Segments first,
so the Playlist can update more frequently
at the live edge
and then the Parent Segments follow.
The overall segmentation stays the same
in terms of where the ad boundaries are,
where the discontinuities are placed,
where key rotation happens, et cetera.
And just as when
you're serving program content,
the origin has to implement
Blocking Playlist Reload
for ads as well to preserve
the Low-Latency timing model.
We've got a separate video about
Blocking Playlist Reload.
If you'd like to learn more about it,
it's part of the new HLS Origin API.
And speaking of the Origin API,
another consideration
for ad delivery is Preload Hinting.
Preload Hinting is a technique used
by Low-Latency HLS
to lower segment delivery time.
We also have a video
talking about that this year.
But the basic requirement
is that every Playlist
has to contain the URL
of the next Partial Segment
that we expect to have show up
in the Playlist
carried in a Preload Hint Tag.
Ad content must be hinted,
just like program content.
But it's a little easier to implement
for ads because unlike program content,
where the server has to block
until each Partial Segment
has been completely produced,
with prerecorded content
we don't have to block,
and so you can serve it up
from a regular origin.
Let's take a look at an example of what
Preload Hinting looks like for an ad.
Here's a Low-Latency Playlist,
and segment seven is the last thing
that's currently available.
But we also have a couple
of Preload Hint Tags at the end.
Because we're transitioning to an ad
the first one tells us
that the client should load
a new Media Initialization Section.
The second one gives us the URL
for the first Partial Segment of the ad.
Two seconds later, when the live edge
of the presentation reaches the ad,
the Playlist will update
to look like this.
Now we can see
that there's a discontinuity
following the program segment seven
followed by a map tag for the ad
followed by the first Partial Segment
of the ad.
The Preload Hint Tag has been updated
to hint the second Partial Segment
of the ad
which we expect will show up as its own
part tag two seconds from now
when it goes live.
Then we'll hit the third Partial Segment,
and so on.
Like clockwork, right? Well, not always.
One phenomenon you might be familiar with
is called "early return."
Usually, you see this
when something really exciting happens
in a live broadcast during an ad break
and the producer wants to cut back to the
program right away so you don't miss it.
Just like in regular live HLS,
you'll stop serving ad segments
before you get to the end of the ad.
If you've got an agile packager,
you might be able to end it
at the last published Partial Segment.
In which case, you would conjure up
a short Parent Segment
that ends at the same place.
Then you'd signal a discontinuity
and resume feeding program segments.
In this case, a hint you served earlier
before you knew you were going
to return early might need to change.
So just set it to the next
program Partial Segment instead.
The client will switch back
to loading program content
and you'll have your early return.
So to wrap up our discussion
of inserting ads into Low-Latency HLS,
it's pretty similar to inserting ads into
regular live HLS but with one difference:
ads get spooled out more frequently
as Partial Segments.
Your packager does need
to implement Blocking Playlist Reload
for both ads and program content.
And it has to supply preload hints
for both as well.
Although, your ad origin does not need
to enforce the blocking semantics
because ads themselves are prerecorded.
We know that for many of you
ads are an essential part of your
Low-Latency content delivery strategy.
So we hope that what we've covered here
helps you to deliver them
with Low-Latency HLS.
Thank you.