[chimes]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. Welcome to designing great App Clips.
I'm Grant Paul from the Apple Design Team,
and I'm gonna be joined shortly
by my colleague Heena Ko.
Today we're gonna talk about
all of the pieces that you need
in order to design great App Clips.
I hope you're as excited
about App Clips as we are.
So, let's get started.
First off, we're gonna go into
a little bit more detail
about what exactly App Clips are
and how they relate
to the apps that you already have.
Then we're gonna talk about
how people actually get into App Clips,
since unlike with apps, they don't start
by going to the App Store.
And finally we'll talk about what features
should go into a great App Clip
and what you need to know in order
to design your user interfaces for them.
So, what are App Clips?
App Clips are lightweight
versions of apps.
They offer some of an app's functionality
and they offer it
when and where people need it.
They're fully native experiences
and they use all of the same technologies
that you already know from your apps.
And since App Clips are lightweight,
you can use them instantly.
You don't have to download
or install an app at all.
In fact, App Clips are meant for people
who haven't downloaded your app yet.
They might not even know what it is.
Now, unlike apps, which you usually get
by browsing or searching in the App Store,
App Clips show up
right when you need them.
They're found through codes
and tags out in the world,
including some new codes
that we've designed just for App Clips.
App Clips can also come from
places and apps that are built into iOS.
Things like Maps and Safari.
We're gonna talk more in a little bit
about some best practices
for when your App Clips show up
in each of these places.
Now, last but not least,
App Clips don't stick around
when you're done using them.
Once you swipe an App Clip away,
you're done with it.
You don't need to manage it
or clear it out to save space
or delete it off your device.
It's all gonna be handled for you.
And if you do need an App Clip again,
you can always just get back to it
the same way
that you got there in the first place.
But if you want faster access,
you can download that App Clip's
corresponding app to your Home Screen
and that'll be able to do
everything the App Clip does,
as well as some extra things
that only the app can do.
So, that's what App Clips are.
Let's talk about what they look like.
Of course, this here is an app icon,
which should be pretty familiar by now.
And this is what that app icon looks like
as an App Clip.
And that border is generated automatically
from the icon you provide,
so when you're making your app icon,
there's nothing special at all
that you need to do for App Clips.
So, here's what it looks like
to use an App Clip in practice.
Let's say you tap your phone
to an NFC tag.
You'll instantly get an App Clip card
with information that tells you all about
what the App Clip is and what it can do.
And if you want to use the App Clip,
all you need to do is tap "Open."
And once you tap "Open,"
the App Clip card slides off,
the App Clip finishes loading,
and you're all ready to go.
That's how easy it is
and how fast it is to use an App Clip.
And App Clips can be used for anything.
We're gonna cover
a bunch of ideas in this session
of different categories and different
use cases that you can use App Clips for.
What we're even more excited about
than any of those
are all of the ideas
that we've never thought of,
that developers, that you, are gonna make.
It's just like all of the incredible,
creative, and amazing apps
that we've seen on the App Store.
We hope that App Clips are gonna open up
places that weren't possible before
and spur new ideas, just like apps did.
One of those places that App Clips
can open up is for small businesses.
Now, small businesses often
don't have the resources
to make an entire app by themselves.
So instead,
the small businesses usually show up
as a small part of a bigger app
that's under a different brand.
Think about an app
for delivering ice cream.
So, to order
from an ice cream shop in this app,
you need to go into the delivery app first
and then find the shop that you want.
But what people wanna do is to interact
with the business that they already know.
They don't wanna download
and learn about another app
just in order to order their ice cream.
App Clips can help.
When you have an App Clip, you make a
custom experience for the small business.
An experience that uses
that small business's own branding,
along with some attribution
back to the App Clip.
That lets the experience feel like
it's coming from that small business.
So, we're really excited to see
how this can bring the power of App Clips
and bring the power of apps
to more businesses
where they couldn't work before.
So, that's what App Clips are
and what they're for.
Now I wanna talk about how you find
App Clips and how you get into them.
As I mentioned before, unlike with apps,
you don't find App Clips
by going to the App Store
and searching for them by name
or browsing through categories.
Instead, the way you find App Clips
is in context.
You find them
right when and where you need them.
And one of the ways that you do that
is through physical tags.
Now, App Clips support
many different kinds of physical tags.
They support our new App Clip codes,
they support other kinds of NFC tags,
and they also support
your standard QR codes.
These new App Clip codes
are the most visible way
for people to get into App Clips.
They have a consistent appearance,
so they can become instantly recognizable
as leading to a great App Clip experience
once you scan it.
And when people see one,
because they're instantly recognizable,
they'll know
exactly what to do right away.
Now, these codes are also flexible.
In the middle there's an NFC tag,
which you can use
just by holding your iPhone up to the tag.
And there's a visual code
on the outside around it,
which can be useful
if you can't get up close.
Maybe 'cause the code is on a billboard
or a poster or it's just out of reach.
Something like that.
And this is
what they look like physically.
You can see how the App Clip code
is placed on the table
so it's easy to see and notice
right when you need it.
We're gonna have
some more information available soon
on how you can make and place
your own App Clip codes.
A really important part
of using any kind of physical tag
is to use a different tag
for each way into your App Clip.
So, let's say
a coffee shop has four locations.
If you go to the location in Cupertino,
it should use a different tag
than all of the other locations.
That way the App Clip can know
to show the menu
for the Cupertino location automatically,
rather than making you
have to pick a location first.
You can also use different tags
from within a location.
For example,
each table at the Cupertino shop
could have a different tag on it.
So, the App Clip automatically knows
not just which location you're at,
but also which table
that your order should go to.
It saves a step.
This makes your App Clip faster.
But it also means that there's no chance
that someone's gonna
accidentally pick the wrong location
or pick the wrong table in your App Clip
because it's all handled
for them automatically.
Now, in addition to placing physical tags,
you can also
attach App Clips to locations.
If you do that for your App Clip,
it might start showing up in Maps,
which lets people use the App Clip before
they actually get to the place itself.
For example, a food app
like Panera Bread here,
can let you preorder
or can let you order takeout
before you actually
go over to that location.
And if an App Clip ends up being
especially useful
or popular and relevant
in a specific place,
it can get selected to show up
automatically in Siri Suggestions.
That means both in the widget
on the home screen
and in Siri Suggestions in Spotlight.
That way, people can start
getting into your App Clip
without having to scan anything first
or even find a tag or a code to get in.
So, that's how you can get into App Clips
from physical tags and from locations.
Next, I wanna talk about
getting to App Clips
from different places on your device.
Now, some App Clip experiences
don't have a physical location
that makes sense to put tags or that
they could be associated with in Maps.
And that's totally great too.
App Clips are gonna work just as well
with experiences that are totally virtual
and that take place
entirely on the device.
So, the way that you find
those App Clip experiences
is from the Smart App Banner in Safari.
If you have a website
and you also have an App Clip,
you can add a Smart App Banner
to the top of your page.
And if you do, people can start
going straight into your App Clip
as soon as they press the button.
So, for example, what you see here.
Etsy can put a Smart App Banner
on their detail page
to jump right into their App Clip.
And, of course,
if someone has their app installed,
the banner will take people
to the app instead.
So they can get
all of the features of the app
in addition to what the App Clip can do.
So, when would you show
a Smart App Banner in Safari
versus having people, for example,
just use your website?
Well, there's two main reasons.
One of them is that
when you make an App Clip,
just like when you make an app,
it's often gonna be a better experience
than what you'll find on a website.
App Clips use native system controls,
so people already know how to use them
and they're faster to learn.
And of course, just like apps,
App Clips are really fast and responsive.
It's really the same great user experience
that's why people go to the App Store
to download your apps today.
Now, the second reason is that
App Clips enable new types of experiences
that are either hard or impossible
to make on the Web
but with apps
are really common and easy to do.
For example, think of something
like recording and editing a video.
It's not common on the Web,
but with the power of the iOS frameworks,
it's simple to do in your app.
Similarly, you can do things
like connect to a device with Bluetooth
or show interactive 3D scenes
in augmented reality.
App Clips have all of the power of apps
available to you right away.
And just like with physical tags,
when you use a Smart App Banner,
it's important to launch into the right
part of your App Clip automatically.
So, in this example, Etsy would launch
right into the part of their App Clip
for the product
being shown in Safari below.
That saves people from having to navigate
back to that product
from inside the App Clip.
There's also one last place
that you might see App Clips.
If you have a page with a Smart App Banner
and you share a link
to that page in Messages,
people can go directly from Messages
right into the App Clip.
And what's great about that
is that people can start sharing
your App Clip with the people they know,
which lets people
organically discover your App Clip
and also discover your app through it.
So, that's the Smart App Banner in Safari
and how it ties into Messages.
Now, the next step
after you find an App Clip is to use it.
And every time you use an App Clip,
the first thing you're gonna see
is the App Clip card.
The App Clip card is like
the product page in the App Store.
It's your chance to show off
what it is that your App Clip can do,
to introduce your App Clip to people,
and to let people know
why they should start using it.
So, let's say you tap your phone
on an App Clip code.
As with all of the other ways
that you can get into an App Clip,
the first thing you're gonna see
is the App Clip card.
All App Clip cards
have the same general shape
but they have a few different parts
that you can customize.
Let's look at the different pieces
and how you can customize them.
So, the most important part of your
App Clip card to customize is the title.
The title is what tells people
what your App Clip is.
Now, for most App Clips,
this is gonna be the same as the name
of your app or the name of your brand.
Now, sometimes it can be worth using
a more specific title for your App Clip.
If your App Clip focuses
on a single feature out of your app,
you can use that feature
as part of your title.
For example here,
if you have a music listening app,
but your App Clip for it
is all about radio,
you might put "radio" in as part
of the App Clip experience's title.
Now, if the title
is the brand of your App Clip,
the subtitle is where you get to explain
what it is that your App Clip does.
Remember that when people
are using your App Clip,
it's often gonna be the first time
they're having any interaction
with your app or with your brand,
so they might not know
what your name means.
They're gonna need an explanation
of what it is that your App Clip
is there to do,
and that's what you can put
in the subtitle.
Next up is the header image.
Now, the header image
is your chance to show visually
what it is that you can get
out of your App Clip.
If your App Clip is attached
to something physical,
like a real-world location or a service,
a photo of that location
or of that service
can make for a great header image.
But if it's not attached
to anything physical,
you can always make
a great graphic version
of your logo or some part of your brand.
Either way, you should always stick
to either a photograph
or some kind of custom graphic.
You should never use screenshots
or fill it up with lots of text
since both of those
can be really hard to read
in the small space available
on your App Clip card.
Now, after the header image,
there's one more piece you can customize.
The button on the right
of the App Clip card
represents the action
that people are gonna take
when they open up your App Clip
on their device.
So, right now we have three options
available to you for the action button,
Open, View and Play.
Now, if you're making a general App Clip,
the usual one
that you're gonna pick is Open.
It's the default choice.
But if you have an App Clip
that's all about showing information
or visualizing something,
the View action can be a good one to pick.
And, of course, Play is great
for things like media and games.
Now, beyond these three,
we're looking to hear
what additional action labels
would be useful to you.
So as you come up with ideas
for App Clips,
let us know in Feedback Assistant
what else we could add.
Finally, at the bottom
of the App Clip card
is the attribution back to the App Clip's
corresponding app.
Tapping in here takes you to the App Store
so you can get the app
or you can see more information about it,
like who developed it
or what the privacy policy is.
If you wanna customize this section,
that means changing your app's metadata.
So, that's how people discover App Clips.
It can be from physical tags
like our App Clip codes,
NFC tags and QR codes.
You can use the Smart App Banner in Safari
to offer your App Clip when it has
a new or a better experience
than what you can get from the web page.
You should make sure to launch
into the right part of your App Clip
to skip unnecessary navigation
when the context is already clear
from the specific tag or page
that the App Clip is coming from.
And finally, make sure to be thoughtful
in how you introduce people
to your App Clip on your App Clip card.
You should use clear language
and great imagery.
Now that you have a sense
of what App Clips are
and how you get into them,
I'll hand it over to my colleague Heena
to talk about how to design the content
for inside your App Clips.
Hi, my name is Heena,
and I'll be talking to you today
about designing App Clips.
Let's first talk about what goes into
a great App Clip.
So, the most important thing to remember
is that great App Clips are simple.
Their focused experience
is made for accomplishing a task.
Great App Clips are fast.
Not only are they quick to load,
the flow should be as quick
and streamlined as possible.
So, when you're about
to create an App Clip,
you wanna have three main things in mind.
First, decide what the purpose is.
Whether it's renting a scooter
or buying ice cream,
think about the single task
your App Clip accomplishes.
Second, think about what
the absolute minimum flow is
to accomplish that task.
Remember, App Clips are
in-the-moment experiences,
so the flow should be
focused and efficient.
Consider using technologies
like Apple Pay and Sign in with Apple
for a more seamless experience.
Lastly, you can offer
the full app for more features.
Remember, App Clips
should be useful in isolation,
but if you wanna offer it, we made
something so you can do that easily.
Okay, so let's walk through some examples.
Let's say you're making
an App Clip for a café
where you can order ahead
to get coffee to go.
The minimum flow here could include
the ability to browse the menu and order.
Then pay for your coffee with Apple Pay.
Then after the transaction's complete
and you've demonstrated
the value of your App Clip,
you could offer to download the full app.
It's important here to clearly explain
the additional benefits
that the full app offers.
This next example's a parking app
that allows you to pay for a parking space
in various parking garages.
The minimum flow here could be to provide
the ability to pay for your parking space
for a certain amount of time.
Then you could send a notification
saying that the time is about to expire.
Tapping on that notification
could allow you
to extend your time remotely
so you don't have to walk
back to your car.
Okay, let's move on to this next example.
Let's say you're setting up
an online store, like this one
where you can shop for accessories.
The flow here could include
a simple shopping experience
where you can browse
and add items to a shopping cart.
After the transaction's complete,
you could offer Sign in with Apple
so folks can get notified of sales
and save their favorite items.
This is an example
of a restaurant App Clip
that allows you to order and pay
right from your table.
It's important to note
that this kind of experience
requires that you distribute
unique App Clip codes
to each table for your patrons to scan.
So once the code's been scanned,
the experience here can include
a simple menu to browse the dishes
and the ability to continuously
add items to your order.
Then a checkout experience with Apple Pay.
Lastly, after you've proven how great
of an experience your App Clip is,
offer the full app here
so people could order ahead,
get takeout and delivery.
Has it sunk in yet? Great!
This last example is an AR experience
where you can use the camera to identify
the names of mountains
and peaks around you.
So, here the experience could include
a simple camera view...
and a way to augment that view
with annotations and information
about your surroundings.
And lastly, you might wanna include
a way to share that view with friends.
So, those are the essentials
of what goes into an App Clip.
At this point, you're probably wondering,
"So, I have an app.
How do I turn my app into an App Clip?"
Well, the first step
is to focus on a specific task.
Let's take this coffee shop app.
It's got lots of features.
You can order, save your favorite drinks,
look up stores near you,
you can even create an account.
And the way to focus that experience
is to narrow it down
to just a single feature.
Here we have decided to focus
the experience to only ordering.
The other features,
like saving your favorites
or looking up other store locations,
isn't helpful
to the main task of ordering.
So, really you wanna simplify
the experience and remove elements
unrelated to the single task
of being able to order and pay for coffee.
This means no unnecessary App Clip intros.
Resist the temptation to add instructions,
introductions and tutorials
before getting into the main flow.
Avoid using login or account pages.
If you need some type of registration,
use Sign in with Apple
for speed and privacy.
And with your App Clip
being so streamlined,
you won't need global navigation
or lots of tabs.
And lastly, avoid any type
of settings or management.
Okay, so those are the basics
of how you turn your app into an App Clip.
Now let's talk about designing UI
for App Clips.
More specifically, how to best utilize
system components.
App Clips have the ability
to send notifications.
It's a great way to relay information
that's essential to the experience.
By default, an App Clip
can send notifications
for up to eight hours
after it's first used.
We think this is enough time
to complete most tasks.
However, if your App Clip experience
spans more than a day,
you can request explicit authorization
for an additional week.
For example, a car rental company
could request explicit authorization
for a rental that spans multiple days.
Remember to keep notifications
focused on the task.
Never send any unexpected
or promotional notifications
and only send notifications
in response to an explicit user action.
If the entire experience takes place
within the App Clip itself,
you may not even need
to send notifications at all.
If your App Clip has transactions,
use Apple Pay.
It's the fastest way to take payments
and you don't have to reenter
credit card information or addresses.
And finally, always promote
the full app at the right time,
and the right time
is after the primary task is complete.
That way your app has had a chance
to prove its value.
Remember, App Clips
are not a Trojan horse for your app.
They should have value on their own.
Okay, so to wrap up,
App Clips are native
lightweight experiences
available instantly.
They're in-the-moment experiences
that don't stick around
and live on the device.
Use App Clip codes
in the real world for discovery.
Consider what it means to your app
to create touch points in physical spaces.
And remember to make them highly visible
so people can discover them easily.
Focus your App Clip on a specific task
and remove all unnecessary elements.
And because of all the different ways
App Clips can be discovered,
more people can use your app
in clip form than ever before.
Finally, I recommend checking out
the "Human Interface Guidelines,"
which includes a section
on how to design great App Clips.
I'd also recommend
all the sessions on App Clips,
including the session
"Configure and Link Your App Clips,"
for how to set up
getting into your App Clips.
Thank you so much, and I hope
you go out there and make great App Clips.
[chimes]