Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Wil, and I work on testing
and automation in Xcode.
In this session, we're going to learn
about XCTSkip,
a new API for managing test execution
based on runtime conditions.
Some tests,
particularly integration tests,
have requirements or dependencies
that cannot easily be mocked out.
For example, an app might have
iPad-specific functionality
that can't be tested with an iPhone.
In other cases,
the test may exercise an API
that's not available in devices
running older versions of the OS.
Or a test might require a server that's
periodically off-line for maintenance.
All of these are examples of conditions
that can only be determined at runtime.
To handle cases where the environment
doesn't meet the requirements of the test,
what's needed is a way to make
test execution conditional.
Otherwise, the test author
is left with a choice.
Return early, passing the test,
or report a failure.
There are downsides to both approaches.
Passing the test suggests code is working
when it's not actually been validated.
But failing the test raises a problem
where none has been found,
and may consume triage resources.
Fortunately, you can now use XCTSkip
when you have tests
that require conditional execution.
This API, introduced in Xcode 11.4,
produces a new test result.
Tests can pass or fail, or with XCTSkip,
be marked with an explicit "skip" result.
Xcode uses this icon to highlight tests
which were skipped,
giving you a much clearer picture of
what your test suites actually validated.
Let's get a better understanding
of how this works in practice.
I have here a little project
called Play Garden
that I've been working on
with my 3-year-old daughter.
Play Garden helps us
keep track of all the plants,
toys and furniture in our backyard.
We recently decided to add support
for pointer interactions,
since we love that feature
and mostly use the app on our iPad.
Now, even at age three, my daughter has
fully embraced test-driven development.
So it was a given that we'd be adding
some unit tests for this new feature.
You can see one of these tests
here on the screen now.
As it happens,
this test has two conditions
under which it wouldn't make sense
for it to execute.
First, since pointer interaction
was introduced in iOS 13.4,
we can't run this test on older versions
of the OS.
So I'll add an availability guard
that uses XCTSkip for older iOS versions.
Second, the app only enables
pointer interactions on iPads.
So if we're running on
some other kind of device,
we don't need to execute this test.
I'll use "XCTSkipIf"
to handle this condition.
First, let's run this test
with a destination
where it can execute normally.
I'll use an iPad running iOS 14.
As you can see, it runs and passes
just as we would expect.
Now let's run this on an older device,
an iPhone running iOS 13.0.
I'm going to use my favorite keyboard
shortcut to run the test this time,
"control-option-command-G,"
which just repeats
the previous test action.
This time we can see
that the green "pass" icon
has been replaced
with the gray "skip" icon,
and an annotation in the source editor
shows where and why the test was skipped.
Let's check out the other places in Xcode
where the UI services the skip result.
First, the Test Navigator.
Here we can see the skip indicated
next to the test.
In addition, you can filter the displayed
list to show only skipped tests
using this button
at the bottom of the navigator.
Now let's take a look at the test report.
Here's the run with the skip.
As I expand the test details,
we see the file and line
where the skip occurred,
along with a reason explaining why.
As I hover over this,
perhaps you've noticed
two buttons at the end of the line.
The first is the "jump" button,
which navigates to the location
and source where the skip occurred.
I'll go back
so we can explore the second button.
New in Xcode 12, the "assistant" button
will open a secondary editor
showing the reference source location
for the skip.
This lets us view the test report
and the source code side by side.
Finally, let's take a look at how skip
appears in continuous integration.
I have here the result from my CI system
which ran my test
on three different devices.
I'm going to use the "skipped" filter
so we can focus on just this test.
When I expand the test, we see
a result for each device the test ran on.
A pass for the first iPad,
and a skip for the other devices.
Expanding the device results shows
the location and reason for each skip
putting all of this information
right at my fingertips.
So that's it.
We've seen just how easy it is
to use XCTSkip in your tests
for a variety of conditions
and how Xcode highlights the difference
between tests that were skipped,
versus those that passed or failed
normally.
Now let's take a closer look at the APIs.
As you saw in the demo, there are
a few different ways to use XCTSkip.
There are two throwing functions:
XCTSkipIf and XCTSkipUnless.
Both functions take the same parameters.
XCTSkipIf skips
when the expression is true.
XCTSkipUnless skips
when the expression is false.
The example here shows
how a test might skip
when running on any device
other than iPad.
Tests can also
throw the XCTSkip struct directly.
This is convenient
in combination with guard,
as shown here with an availability check
for iOS 13.4.
So to wrap up, some tests,
particularly integration tests,
may be unable to execute
under certain conditions.
You can use XCTSkip
to respond to those conditions
in a way that most accurately models
the outcome of the test run.
This, in turn,
ensures clearer overall results,
particularly when your test suites execute
in continuous integration systems.
Thanks for watching.