Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi. My name is Adam Humphrey,
and here at Apple,
I'm on a team that works with
enterprise companies all around the world
to help them create great custom apps
for their employees.
And today, I'm happy to share some of
our knowledge to help you do the same.
Apps have changed the way
we live our lives.
People now expect the same change at work.
At Apple, we believe
employees should have access to apps
that allow them to do their best work
and fundamentally improve
how things get done.
So, let's begin.
I'll start by describing some
of the characteristics
that are unique to enterprise apps.
Then, I'll talk about
how to find opportunities
and employee roles
that are best served by custom apps.
And next, I'll talk about the importance
of not just including your employees
in the design and development process,
but enabling them to drive it.
And finally, I'll talk about the tools
Apple has developed
to help you build custom apps quickly,
get them in the hands of your employees,
and continuously improve
with their feedback.
All right. So, let's dive right in.
First, let me talk about some of
the characteristics of an enterprise app.
Simply stated,
enterprise apps are employee-facing
and these apps are as unique
as the employees who use them.
Another characteristic is that
many of them aren't found
in the public App Store.
Enterprise apps
are mostly distributed internally
by the enterprises themselves
using MDM and Apple Business Manager.
Some enterprise apps
are used by a lot of employees.
Like this company directory app,
which allows you
to easily search for your colleagues,
see their availability,
and quickly connect with them.
Or this conference room app that can find
the closest available conference room
and allows you to book it
with just one tap.
And some are role-based.
Tailored to very discreet
groups of employees.
For example, this sales associate app has
specific information and unique workflows
that helps sales associates
with clienteling, task management,
corporate communications,
and other workflows
they need to do their job.
And still,
others are part of a group of apps
that seamlessly work together
to create unique workflows
that best support
many different employee jobs.
For example, our sales associate app
can work with a runner app,
which helps employees
get stock from storage locations
and make sure they get the right item
in the fastest route possible.
And a product catalog app that can be used
by many different employees
to view new product arrivals,
inventory and availability.
And these apps can share data seamlessly
between each other
enabling unique workflows,
and of course, with single sign-on,
app groups and Keychain,
when you sign in to one app,
you're automatically signed in
to the entire group of apps,
reducing time to get things done.
Something that all good enterprise apps
have in common:
they improve an employee's job.
These apps should reduce their workload
and the amount of mental energy
needed to accomplish a task,
rather than only being used
to gather data for a business.
This can be as simple
as replacing a paper-based workflow,
and as complex as helping a pilot
fly a state-of-the-art airplane.
So now, you have a better understanding
of some of the characteristics
of an enterprise app.
I wanna talk to you a little bit about
some of the ways to identify
which employees would be best served
by these types of apps.
As you know, not all employees
are at their desk from nine-to-five.
Some employees do their work on the go
and at many different locations
during the day.
These mobile employees are often helped
by apps that include way-finding,
enabling them to easily navigate
to their next job.
This might even include how long
it will take to get to their next job,
especially when taking into account
traffic and weather conditions.
Most enterprise apps allow people to work
even when there's no network available,
and with location services,
these apps can vastly improve
data accuracy and reporting.
Power line maintenance technicians
who work in very difficult
and remote terrain
have benefited from these apps.
At times, many miles from cell service.
They replaced their heavy,
cumbersome equipment
with iPads, iPhones and Apple Watches,
which reduced the amount of equipment
they had to carry around.
And the Apple Watch app enables them to do
some workflows right from their wrist,
saving a lot of time and effort,
and improving overall work quality
and employee satisfaction.
And what about the parts of your business
that are still run primarily on paper?
Jobs with paper-heavy processes
are often ripe with app opportunities.
One industry that's experienced
this paper-to-digital transformation
was aviation.
For years, airline pilots
carried briefcases
with reams of papers and documents
containing all their flight information.
After the invention of the iPad,
some of the very first pilot apps
enabled pilots to store thousands
of charts and documents on an iPad,
instead of paper
carried in their large briefcase.
These apps had huge impact
on all types of pilots.
From international commercial pilots
all the way to flight instructors.
The positive impacts of these apps
was felt industry-wide.
Now, some employees, they carry around
scanners, cameras, GPS devices,
measuring devices,
audio and video recorders.
These are all often great opportunities
for an enterprise app.
The iPhone and iPad are extremely
sophisticated pieces of hardware.
An insurance claims adjuster
used to carry around a laptop,
a voice recorder,
a tape measure, a digital camera.
With an app
designed specific for their workflow,
now they can do the majority of their work
right on an iPad.
Sometimes it's extremely helpful
for an employee
to action on something right away
without the need to make a phone call,
send an email or even launch an app.
There are incredible opportunities for you
to create simple but powerful workflows
by customizing notifications.
By using notification content extensions,
you can create custom workflows
that an employee can use
right from within the notification,
making some workflows
as easy as a glance and a tap.
When corporate pilots saw this,
they were ecstatic.
This simple rich notification shows
leg information and weather conditions
and with a glance,
the pilots can easily know
if they would be home for dinner
or if they would be gone for a day or two.
Not to mention
what clothes they should pack.
Without the need to launch the app,
they can quickly accept or decline
new trip assignments
right from this rich notification.
And with notification extensions,
the company dispatchers know which pilots
have received these notifications.
This is especially useful
if your workforce
is flying all around the globe
and not always connected to a network.
And speaking of networks
with Wi-Fi, Bluetooth,
and cellular networks,
you can create processes
that allow multiple employees
to collaborate effortlessly.
With iPad, inspectors can seamlessly
work together deep in subway tunnels,
even without cellular connectivity,
using technologies like Bluetooth
and iBeacon.
Teams can streamline inspections quickly,
accessing information required to locate,
identify and complete inspections.
These are just a few of the examples of
great opportunities for enterprise apps.
Start looking for these opportunities
in your own organization
and allow the people doing the actual work
to drive the process of design.
Let's talk about that now.
It's incredibly important
to allow the employees who do the job
to drive the design process.
And that usually starts
with interviewing them
and observing them in their jobs.
Try to understand their pain points,
the blockers that keep them
from doing their best work.
You should seek a diversity of input
by interviewing an employee
who's new to the role,
a veteran employee,
and an employee somewhere in between.
Bring in these employees together
and interview them at the same time.
This way, you give them
the opportunity to dialogue
about their different perspectives
of the work they do.
You then use these rich insights
to inform the app you build.
You'll find that the veteran employee
may have their own workarounds
based on years of experience.
And the new employee, they may have
recently gone through employee training
and they can share how the process
is supposed to be done by the book,
and they'll point out
where processes are difficult to learn
and where an app might make it easier.
You might be encouraged
to involve a manager,
a director or a subject matter expert
instead of the actual employees
who do the job day in and day out.
Instead, prioritize direct experience
and get the details from the people
who actually fly the plane, so to speak,
rather than relying on the input
from employees
who can be more focused
on the ideal or approved process
rather than the realities of the job
that needs to be done.
This even includes those managers
who used to be on the job for many years
before they became a manager.
Stick with the employees who,
if they weren't talking to you,
would be doing the actual work.
It's also very important
to get a holistic understanding
of the employee's role.
Have them talk about
a standard day in their life.
Have them discuss their entire day,
not just the nine-to-five.
Sometimes, you'll find work gets done
over their morning coffee.
Including their entire day
in your discussion
enables you to find blockers that may not
be obvious once they are on the job.
This will help you understand
what features go into this app
and where other opportunities lie.
You may even find you weren't solving
their biggest pain points.
We once started interviewing
a sales associate
for a new mobile point-of-sale app,
and during the course of that interview,
we discovered all their immediate needs
were in clienteling,
not the point-of-sale.
This allowed us to pivot early
and ultimately create an app
with much greater impact.
All right.
So, now you have a holistic understanding
of the employee's work
and have confidence
you've focused on the right problem.
It's time to dive into the details.
Understanding the exact steps
in an employee's workflow
and getting to
the root of their challenges
is key to truly designing an app
that improves their work.
Be sure to qualify the response
with the others who do the same job.
For example, you can say,
"Hey, Dan, what Rebecca just said
about tracking mileage,
is that the same for you
or do you track mileage differently?"
I wanna talk about
a few very important tips
that can really have a positive impact
on the information you get from
your employees during these interviews.
Make sure it's a safe place
for open communication
with no managers
to influence their responses.
You want the unvarnished truth.
When an employee changes their answer
to that of a manager,
or is watching their manager
for validation,
you can be assured
you're not getting the whole truth.
You are there to gain insight
and help improve their lives at work.
Sometimes, you might catch yourself
subconsciously filling in the details
as they tell you their story.
Don't assume anything.
Always ask for clarification
when things seem vague.
Hey, even ask for clarification
if things seem obvious.
You'll be surprised
how much of what you infer
ends up being way off the mark.
And don't forget to constantly ask why.
Continue to ask clarifying questions.
Remember that the majority
of the employees will be stuck
in what they want to fix
in their current workflows today
and it isn't always easy for them
to step back
and look at the larger problem,
or even recognize that there is a problem.
Not to mention, imagine the future state
when they have the app.
For example, think about
how store managers
may not be able to talk about
a future state of shift scheduling
until their sales associates are able to
swap shifts in a sales associate app.
And the final and most important tip,
you must always have empathy
for the employees you interview.
You are there to get all the information
you need to solve their problems
and allow them
to drive the design process.
Put yourself in their shoes
and try your best to feel their pain.
I once interviewed an employee
for a large transportation company
and he was so ecstatic
to have an empathetic ear to talk to.
He said in his 30-plus years of working
at that company,
this was the very first time
he truly felt like
his knowledge and experience
was going to improve the work
of his colleagues all around the world.
That really hit home.
So, what next?
The fastest way to get an app
in the hands of your employees
is to optimize
your design and development time.
Developing and testing in Xcode
is the fastest way to decrease time
to a deployment.
Apple provides you
with very powerful tools in Xcode
to build and test apps.
Use these to streamline
your development and testing activities
and get the app in the hands
of your employees as quickly as possible.
Gone are the days of three-year design
and development cycles
for a single, gigantic app
that tries to be everything to everyone.
Small and focused, and always evolving
is the ticket to creating solutions
that continually improve
and adjust to changing roles.
Using standard views and controls
can save you
a lot of design and development time.
And these design patterns are easily
recognized and understood by Apple users,
so the need for training and support
is greatly reduced.
This doesn't mean your app
can't be beautiful or elegant.
On the contrary.
It just means try to keep custom controls
to a minimum,
so your users don't have to learn
a whole bunch of new interactions
or navigation paradigms
when they first use your app.
Next, keep it focused.
It's perfectly okay to create
a focused app
that delivers
initial value for your employees
and later grows to add
many more features and workflows.
Bottom line, keep your app focused
and always evolving.
This is the best way to make sure your app
is always useful to your employees.
And please, don't forget
to leverage tools like TestFlight.
TestFlight helps you
beta test versions of your app
and get constant feedback
from your employees.
Not only when you're building
the first release,
but also when you start adding
additional features and workflows.
And remember, your employees
should be driving the design process.
So, continue to get feedback from them
as you design and develop your app.
Does this app solve their problems?
If not, continue to iterate until it does.
If it does, what can you do
to make it even better?
You'll quickly learn what features
or apps to build next.
This allows your organization
to organically build product roadmaps
and continually iterate apps to adjust
to changing roles and responsibilities.
Remember my earlier example
about pilots using iPads
to replace their paper charts
and documents?
Those same apps today,
they are very sophisticated
and some even use data
from planes' avionic systems
to create custom real-time procedures
based on that information.
It's amazing
how far these apps have evolved
with constant feedback
from the pilots that use them.
Throughout this session, we've reviewed
employee app characteristics
and how they help your employees
do their best work,
found key areas for app opportunities
such as mobile employees
and paper processes,
walked through the ways you can have
your employees drive the design process
to ensure your apps are impactful...
and finally, how to quickly build
and release your app
and then, keep improving them over time.
These learnings
will help you on your journey
designing and developing
great custom apps for your employees.
We can't wait to see
what you come up with.
And please know the work you do,
these apps you create,
they can fundamentally improve
the lives of your employees at work.
Trust me. I've seen it many times before
and it's always inspiring.
I wish you luck, thank you,
and have a great WWDC.