Hello and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, everyone, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Lizzy, and I'm excited to talk
about how to create awesome content
for Swift Playgrounds on iPad and Mac.
We all know Swift Playgrounds as
the app that brought Swift coding to iPad.
And now, built with Mac Catalyst,
the same app is available on Mac too.
Your users will get the same experience
they've come to know and love
on their iPads,
now customized for the Mac platform.
In this session,
we'd like to share some of the ways
that you can customize your content
so it's a great experience
on both platforms.
After that, we'll show a demo of a book
that behaves differently on Mac and iPad.
First, let's discuss some updates
in the Swift Playgrounds user interface.
There are a few key parts
of the Swift Playgrounds app
that have been adapted
to better fit the Mac platform.
One of these areas is code completion.
On iPad, you'll recognize this
as the area where you can browse
code completion options
for your current state.
On Mac, there's a new,
expandable area for code completion
that can include quick help
for each token.
These descriptions can be localized,
which creates a better code completion
experience
for users in different languages.
To add quick help to your token,
use three forward slashes directly
above your declaration.
You can also add descriptions
to parameters.
Here, we added a description
to the changeTurtleEyes function.
You'll see this turtle again later on in
our demo, and in the Swan's Quest series.
This text will now appear below your token
in the expanded code completion view.
Even if your users won't be on a Mac,
these descriptions
will still be displayed on iPad as well
in the "quick help" popover
in the source editor
and over the original code completion bar.
Next, let's talk about how your content
can be adapted to each platform.
There are two new optional keys
in the PlaygroundBookDocumentFormat:
supportedDevices and requiredCapabilities.
You can use these keys to specify what
your book requires from the device to run.
If the current device doesn't support
a book, it won't show up in the feed.
To specify that your document only runs
on Mac or iPad,
you can use the supportedDevices key.
The valid values for this
are "iPad" and "Mac."
You'll need to add this key
to the book level manifest,
and to the feed.json file.
For example,
if your book supports both platforms,
you'll want to add "iPad" and "Mac"
to the supportedDevices key
in the book level manifest.
Then, add the same values
to the supportedDevices key
in the feed.json file as well.
This book is now available
on both platforms.
If "Mac" is removed
from the supportedDevices keys,
then it will no longer be available
on that platform.
Instead of only supporting
a particular device,
we can require specific capabilities,
which can make your content available
to more users.
The values for the
requiredCapabilities key
can be anything from the
UIRequiredDeviceCapabilities keys
available to look at
on developer.apple.com.
This includes things like ARKit,
microphone and Wi-Fi,
which you can use
to specify what your book requires.
To use this key,
add "requiredCapabilities"
and an array of each capability
to the book level manifest.
Then add "requiredCapabilities"
and the same array
to the feed.json file as well.
In this example, the book requires use
of the microphone and ARKit.
In general, it's best to support
as many configurations as possible,
even if some functionality is different
between platforms.
To do this, we can determine if
the playground is being compiled for Mac
or for iPad
by checking the target environment.
It's a good idea
to go through the language in your book
to make sure it makes sense
for both platforms.
Some things to look out for
are uses of "click" or "touch."
Generic language, like "tap" or "select,"
is recommended instead.
Next, let's talk about how content
can conform to device settings.
When building content, it's important
to respect the device system settings,
such as accent color and Dark Mode.
System-provided colors,
like label or systemBackground,
will automatically respond correctly
to changes in Dark Mode and system accent.
You can also add your own adaptive colors
by adding them
to the book's asset catalog.
It's important to be aware
of the live-view safe area constraints
when developing cross-platform content.
These constraints ensure
that your content won't be hidden
by any controls over the live view.
The constraints are different on Mac,
since there are toolbar buttons
over the top right of the Mac live view.
You may have code that uses
the Live View Safe Area Guide property
of a Playground
Live View Safe Area container.
Now you can just access the safe area
using a standard UI layout guide.
Next I'd like to introduce my teammate,
Grace, who will be showing you a demo.
Thanks, Lizzy. My name is Grace,
and I'll be walking through a demo
of a Playground that we've customized
to work on both iPad and Mac.
I'll open this Playground
in the Mac app first.
You may recognize this turtle
from the Swan's Quest series.
Pretty cute, right?
The goal of this book is to customize
the look of your character.
Once you've done that,
you can save it as an image
and use it in the Swan's Quest book.
The prose here says
to try starting with changeTurtleSkin.
I'll start by typing that.
And code completion shows me quick help
for lots of different
customization methods.
Let's look at how that's implemented.
The customization methods
are in my TurtleEdits file.
The text here,
preceded by three forward slashes,
is what I see in the code completion area
for this method.
I think this is a little vague,
so let's change this to:
"Change the turtle's skin color
to the color provided."
And once we go back to our main page...
that's the text that shows up
in the code completion area.
So let's add some customization
and see what happens.
I'll run my code.
All right,
this is a pretty good-looking turtle.
I can use the UIColor popovers
to quickly change up some of the colors.
I think I want the lighter area
of the shell to be more of a yellow.
I'll run my code again.
Perfect.
I'll go ahead and save this image.
Notice the use in pros of "tap,"
not "click," to use in other books.
I also see in the prose
it looks like we can play with AR
if we're on an iPad that supports it.
I just so happen to have an iPad with me,
so I want to check that out.
Here's my same document on iPad.
I've got Dark Mode on,
so let's make sure it still looks good.
Okay, hmm. When I run my code,
I have a pretty garish white background.
That's because I set the background color
of my drawing to UIColor.white
instead of using a system background.
Let's try fixing that and run again.
Okay, awesome.
So now the background matches my theme.
And if I switch to Light mode,
it'll be white again.
I also notice a new button here.
That's because
in my ColorGridViewController...
I have a target environment check.
If not I'm running on macOS,
then show this button.
Since Mac doesn't have
the required ARKit capabilities,
I won't show it there.
All right, so if I tap this button,
I can check out this turtle in AR.
There's lots of ways to create great
content that works on both iPad and Mac.
When you're creating or updating
your Swift Playgrounds content,
keep these things in mind:
Check out the UI on both iPad and Mac.
You can take advantage of
the updated code completion design on Mac
by providing quick help in your content.
Use #if targetEnvironment checks
to create different experiences
on iPad and Mac.
If your content requires things like AR
or the microphone,
specify these as required capabilities.
If you can only support one device,
use the supportedDevices key.
Lastly, respect the platform's settings,
like Dark Mode, system colors,
and layout guidelines.
And be sure to pay attention
to the accessibility experience
on all devices that you support.
You can download our sample content
along with this video
and reference
the Playground documentation online.
Also make sure to check out
the Swan's Quest.
You don't want to miss it.
Thanks for watching,
and have a great rest of your WWDC.