[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
David Hayward: Hi, my name
is David Hayward,
and I'm an engineer
with the Core Image team.
Today, my colleagues
Tuomas Viitanen,
Matt Dickoff, and I will be
giving a detailed presentation
that will show you
everything you need to know
about the ProRAW image format
and how add support for it
to your application.
Here’s what we will
discuss today.
First, I will describe
what makes up a ProRAW file.
Next, we will discuss
how to capture these files,
how to store them
in a photo library,
and how to edit
and display them.
Let’s start with,
What is a ProRAW?
For some time,
Apple devices have been able
to fully leverage
our Image Signal Processor
to capture beautiful HEIC
or JPEG images
that are ready for display.
Then starting in iOS 10,
we supported capturing
Bayer-pattern RAW sensor data
and storing that in a DNG file.
The differences and advantages
of these two approaches
was well-described
in the WWDC 2016 session
titled
“Advances in iOS photography”.
That presentation
used a great analogy
to describe the two formats.
A processed HEIC or JPEG
is like going to a bakery
and ordering a multilayer cake.
Whereas a Bayer-pattern RAW file
is like going to the grocer
and getting the raw ingredients
to make a cake.
The advantage
of processed HEIC or JPEGs
are that you get a final image
baked by Apple.
It is fast to display
and has great quality
because it is made by fusing
multiple capture frames
using Smart HDR, Deep Fusion,
or Night mode.
Also, it has a small file size
because it uses
advanced lossy compression.
The advantage of Bayer RAW
is that you get an image
that has much greater
flexibility for editing.
It has not been saved
using lossy compression,
and it has more bits
of precision.
Our goal with ProRAW
was to establish an image format
with the best features of both.
The advantage of ProRAW
is that it has a similar look
to HEIC
but uses lossless compression.
Also, depending on the scene,
it is fused
from multiple exposures,
so it has great dynamic range
for editing.
Because they are low noise
and already demosaiced,
they are reasonably fast
to display.
The ProRAW format is designed
to maximize three properties:
compatibility, quality,
and look.
Let's discuss each of these
in some more detail.
In order
to ensure compatibility,
the ProRAW files are contained
in a standard Adobe DNG file.
The linearized DNG file format
is supported by Apple apps
such as Photos,
Adobe apps such Lightroom,
and many others.
Many apps get support
automatically
via the system frameworks,
ImageIO, and Core Image.
Earlier versions of iOS
and macOS
also have basic support
for the format.
And it is also worth mentioning
that the files can contain
full resolution, JPEG-quality
prerendered previews.
All ProRAWs
captured by Camera app
will contain these previews
which will look identical
to the image
if it had been taken
without ProRAW mode enabled.
The quality of a ProRAW file
is quite impressive.
The pixels in the DNG are
scene-referred and linearizable,
may be generated from
multiple demosaiced exposures
combined with image fusion,
losslessly compressed
12-bit RGB;
but we create these bits through
an adaptive companding curve
so we can achieve up to 14 stops
of dynamic range.
The resulting file sizes
can range from 10 megabytes
to 40 megabytes,
but that size will scale
based on the unique scene
of each photo.
Apple goes to great effort
tuning the quality
of our images.
ProRAW images
have a default look
that is consistent with the look
of our HEICs and JPEGs.
This is achieved by embedding
special tags in the DNG file.
These tags are documented
in the DNG spec
and provide the recipe
for how to render
the default look of each image.
The first tag applied
is the LinearizationTable
which decompands
the 12-bit stored data
to linear scene values.
We use the BaselineExposure tag
because ProRAW images adapt
to the dynamic range
of the scene.
The BaselineSharpness tag
allows us to specify
how much edge sharpening
to apply by default.
The ProfileGainTableMap tag --
which is new
in the DNG 1.6 spec --
allows us to describe
how the adjust the bright
and shadow regions.
Lastly, is the ProfileToneCurve
that specifies
the output global tone curve.
All of these tags are unique
to each image.
Because they provide the recipe
and not the cake,
the image remains
highly editable.
For example,
the default sharpness,
or tone curves,
can be altered at any time.
Lastly,
when present in the scene,
we store semantic masks
in the ProRAW
for regions such a people,
skin, and sky.
So now that we know
what makes up a ProRAW,
I would like to introduce Tuomas
who will describe
how to capture them.
Tuomas Viitanen: Thank you,
David.
My name is Tuomas Viitanen.
I'm an engineer
in the Camera Software team,
and I will guide you through how
you can capture Apple ProRAWs
with your application.
AVFoundation Capture APIs
provide you with access
to camera on iOS and MacOS.
They allow you to stream
live preview and video,
capture photos,
and record movies,
among many other things.
And as a recent addition,
we added support
to capture photos in the new
Apple ProRAW DNG format.
A good source of information
on the basic use
of the AVFoundation Capture APIs
are Advances in iOS Photography
talk from WWDC 2016
that explains how to use
the AVCapture photo output
and AVCam sample code
that is an example
of a simple camera capture
application.
Next, we'll look at the
Apple ProRAW capture in detail.
But first, let's take
a quick look
at where Apple ProRAW
is supported.
A good starting point for that
is to do a comparison
with the existing
Bayer RAW support.
Bayer RAW was introduced
in iOS 10
and is supported
on a wide range of devices.
Apple ProRAW was introduced
in iOS 14.3
and is supported on iPhone 12
Pro and iPhone 12 Pro Max.
Apple's own Camera application
supports Apple ProRAW capture
with all fusion captures,
like Deep Fusion and Night mode,
as well as with flash captures.
Apple ProRAW allows
photo-quality prioritization
to be set to .balanced
and .quality,
which allows you
to get the benefit
of Apple image fusion
to your RAW captures.
While Bayer RAW
is only supported
on single-camera
AVCaptureDevices,
like wide and tele.
Apple ProRAW is supported
on all devices,
including dual wide-, dual-,
and triple-camera devices
that seamlessly switch between
cameras when zooming.
Similar to Bayer RAW,
Apple ProRAW does not support
depth data delivery
nor content aware distortion
correction.
Live Photo capture is only
supported with Bayer RAW
but portrait effects matte
and semantic segmentation
skin and sky mattes
are only supported with ProRAW.
So, let's go through how
you can capture Apple ProRAWs.
The items we cover are:
how to set up your capture
device and capture session,
how to set up your photo output,
how to prepare
your photo settings
for the ProRAW capture,
and what options you have after
you capture a ProRAW photo.
Let's start from setting up
the session.
Apple ProRAW is only supported
on the formats
that support
the highest quality photos.
You will get that by setting
the capture sessionPreset
to .photo.
Or if you would like to select
the device format manually,
you can find the formats
that support
the highest quality stills.
Note that this is different
from high quality stills,
which is supported
on a broader set of formats.
And then simply configure
the desired format
to be the activeFormat
of the device.
In this example and later,
I'm simply using the first index
from the list
of supported items,
but you'll want to replace this
with a selection
that's based on criteria that
works best for your application.
Now, let's look how you can
configure the photo output
for the ProRAW capture.
First, you need to enable ProRAW
on the photoOutput.
Be sure to do that already
before starting the session,
as it will otherwise cause
a lengthy pipeline
reconfiguration.
Setting this property to true
prepares the capture pipeline
for ProRAW captures,
and adds
the ProRAW pixel formats
to the list of supported
RAW photo pixel format types.
If you like, you can also
indicate to the capture pipeline
whether you prefer speed
or quality with your captures,
or if you just like a balance
between the two.
More info on the effect
of photo-quality prioritization
to the captured photos
can be found from
the Capture high-quality photos
using video formats talk.
And next, we'll look how you can
prepare for the capture.
To be able to create
photo settings
for your ProRAW capture,
you need to select
a correct RAW pixel format.
You get the supported RAW pixel
formats from the same
availableRawPhoto
PixelFormatTypes
that gives you the supported
Bayer RAW formats.
You can distinguish
the ProRAW formats
from the BayerRAW formats
using the new
isAppleProRAWPixelFormat
class method
on the photoOutput.
An example of a ProRAW
pixel format is l64r
that's a 16-bit full range
RGBA pixel format.
For reference,
you can also query
whether a format
is a Bayer RAW format
using isBayerRAWPixelFormat
class method.
Next, we'll go through some
of the options you have
for capturing Apple ProRAW
and, optionally,
a fully rendered process
photo along with it.
The first and simplest option
of capturing ProRAW
is to request
only the ProRAW photo.
To do that,
you can simply specify
the rawPixelFormatType
when creating the photoSettings.
This gives you a single asset
which is simple to work with
and store to photo library
like Matt will later show you.
It's also possible to capture
a pair of processed photo
and ProRAW similar to what
you can do with Bayer RAW
by providing also
the processedFormat
for the photoSettings.
But this requires you to work
with multiple assets,
and it's also harder
to keep track of them
in the photo library.
Luckily, Apple ProRAW supports
up to a full-resolution
JPEG image as thumbnail,
and in many cases,
this gives you
the best
of the previous two options.
To request a thumbnail,
you can select
the desired format from
availableRawEmbedded
ThumbnailPhotoCodecTypes
and specify the desired
thumbnail dimensions.
Now you're almost ready
to capture a ProRAW photo.
But before that, if you like,
you can specify
the photo-quality prioritization
for this capture.
Note that the value you specify
here must be less than
or equal to the
maxPhotoQualityPrioritization
you specified previously
on the photoOutput.
You can also request up
to a display-sized preview image
if you would like to have
something to show
for the clients
quickly after the capture.
And then you can capture
the ProRAW photo
using the same
capturePhoto method
that's used for all other
still captures as well.
Now that the still capture
is on the way,
let's take a look
what you can do
when the requested photo
is ready.
When the photo
is fully processed,
your didFinishProcessingPhoto
delegate will be invoked
with an AVCapturePhoto
representing the ProRAW photo.
If you requested a preview image
for the capture,
you can now get the pixel buffer
with uncompressed preview image
or a CGImageRepresentation
of that to show on the display.
And in case you requested
a processed photo
along with the ProRAW,
your didFinishProcessingPhoto
delegate will be invoked twice.
You can distinguish the ProRAW
from the processed photo
using isRawPhoto property
on the received AVCapturePhoto.
And then you can simply request
the fileDataRepresentation
for the ProRAW to save the DNG
to the photo library.
Or optionally,
get a pixel buffer
with the RAW pixel data
if you prefer to work with that.
Like David mentioned earlier,
the ProRAW DNG may include
semantic segmentation mattes.
The inclusion of these mattes
is automatic
and scene dependent.
While the mattes are currently
not available through
the AVFoundation Capture APIs,
you can retrieve them through
Core Image and ImageIO APIs
like David will later show you.
And finally, we'll look at some
customization options
you have
with the ProRAW DNG.
You can customize the ProRAW
by implementing
the AVCapturePhotoFileData
RepresentationCustomizer
delegate methods.
By implementing
replacementAppleProRAW
CompressionSettings,
you can change the compression
bit depth and quality
of the ProRAW photo.
The Apple ProRAW is encoded
losslessly by default
using 12 bits
with a companding curve.
You can change the bit depth of
the losslessly compressed ProRAW
by keeping the quality level
at 1
and providing the desired
bit depth with the customizer.
This saves storage space
but still keeps the high quality
of the ProRAW photo.
In case you prefer
a lossy compression,
you can set the quality level
to below 1,
in which case ProRAW
is compressed automatically
using 8-bit lossy compression.
This gives you
a small file size,
but does have a clear impact
on the quality
of the ProRAW photo.
Now that you have implemented
the customizer,
you can request customization
for the captured ProRAW DNG
in your didFinishProcessingPhoto
delegate.
By creating the customizer
and providing that
for fileDataRepresentation,
you will get the customized
ProRAW back
with the compression settings
you just provided.
That was the introduction
to the Apple ProRAW capture
using AVFoundation Capture APIs.
I'll hand it over to Matt
who will tell you more
about Apple ProRAW
and photo library.
Matt?
Matt Dickoff: Thanks, Tuomas!
Hello!
My name's Matt Dickoff,
and I'm an engineer
on the Photos team.
I'll be walking you through
how to first save
the ProRAW file
you've just captured
as a complete asset
in the photo library.
Then, we'll step through
how to fetch RAWs
that already exist
in the photo library.
PhotoKit is a pair of frameworks
used to interact
with the photo library
on Apple Platforms.
It was first introduced
in these releases
and has seen improvements
and additions since then.
Notably, it has support
for RAW image formats
like Apple ProRAW.
Today I'll only be covering
the specific APIs
that deal with RAWs
in the photo library.
If you still have questions
about PhotoKit
after this presentation,
I encourage you to take a look
at the online developer
documentation.
In order to save a new asset,
we'll need to perform changes
on the shared PHPhotoLibrary.
As with saving any asset,
the change we'll be making
is a PHAssetCreationRequest,
and we'll be adding
our Apple ProRAW file
to this asset as the primary
.photo PHAssetResource.
So let's see what the code
for that looks like.
First, we start
by performing changes
on the shared photo library.
We'll simply make
a PHAssetCreationRequest
and then add
the Apple ProRAW file to it
as the primary photo resource.
And that's it!
Just handle the success
and error
as your application sees fit.
Now that we know how to add
assets to the photo library,
let's take a look at how we can
fetch them back,
including RAW assets that
the user may already have
in their library.
I'm happy to say that in iOS 15,
we've provided a new
PHAssetCollectionSubtype,
.smartAlbumRAW.
With this smart album,
you can easily get a collection
that contains all the assets
in the photo library
that have a RAW resource.
This album is the same RAW album
that you see
in the Apple Photos app.
Now that we have some PHAssets
with RAW resources,
let's take a look
at what it takes
to actually get at
those resources.
First, we'll want to get
all the PHAssetResources
for a PHAsset.
Next, we'll be looking for
two different types of resource:
the .photo we talked about
previously,
and additionally,
.alternatePhoto.
I want to take a brief moment
to explain
what .alternatePhoto is.
Some photo libraries
will contain assets
that follow the old RAW plus
JPEG storage model
that some DSLR cameras use.
This requires storing the RAW
and a JPEG
as two distinct resources;
the JPEG as the photo
and the RAW
as the alternate photo.
This leads
to an increased file footprint
in the photo library,
less portability,
and often
a confusing user experience.
This model is not recommended
for Apple ProRAW.
If your intent is to save
a ProRAW file
to the photo library, you should
use the capture settings
to embed a full-size JPEG
preview in the file.
Now, back to our resources.
We'll be checking
the uniformTypeIdentifier
of the resource to see if it
conforms to a RAW type
that we are interested in.
And finally, once we have
a RAW resource,
we'll use
the PHAssetResourceManager
to retrieve the actual data.
Now let's take a look at that
in code.
First, we iterate through all
the PHAssetResources
on an asset,
look for any that are .photo
or .alternatePhoto type,
check that they conform
to the RAW image UTType,
and finally use
the PHAssetResourceManager
to request the data
for that resource.
And that's it!
You now know how to use PhotoKit
to both save and retrieve assets
with RAW resources
from the photo library.
Now I'm going to hand it back
to David who will talk about
how best to edit and display
Apple ProRAW images.
David: Thank you, Matt.
The last section of our talk
today will be about
how to use
the Core Image framework
to edit and display
ProRAW images.
I will describe how to create
CIImages from a ProRAW file;
how to apply the most common
user adjustments;
how you can turn off
the default look to get linear,
scene-referred values;
how to render edits
to output-referred formats
such as HEIC; and finally,
how to display ProRAWs to a Mac
with an Extended Dynamic Range
display.
Getting a preview image
from a ProRAW is possible
using the
CGImageSourceCreateWithURL
and CGImageSourceCreate
ThumbnailAtIndex APIs.
New in iOS 15 and macOS 12,
Core Image has added
a new convenience API
to access the preview.
Getting semantic segmentation
mattes such as person, skin,
and sky is supported by passing
the desired option key
when initializing the CIImage.
This too has a new
and more convenient API
to access
the optional matte images.
Most importantly,
your application will want
to get the primary ProRAW image.
If your application just wants
to show
the default rendering look,
all you need to do is create
an immutable CIImage
from a URL or data.
However, if your application
wants to unlock
the full editability of ProRAWs,
then create a CIFilter
from the URL.
If you just ask
that filter for its outputImage,
you will get a CIImage
with a default look.
The key advantage of this API
is that the filter
can be easily modified.
The RAW CIFilter
has several inputs
that your application can change
to produce new outputImage.
The basic code pattern
is to set a value object
for one of the documented
key strings.
This setValue forKey API
was due for an update though.
So new in iOS 15 and macOS 12,
we have created
a more discoverable
and Swift-friendly API.
To use the new API,
create a CIRAWFilter instance
and then just set the desired
property to a new value.
Next, let’s discuss
what properties
you might want to change.
Given the dynamic range
of ProRAW images,
one of the most important
controls to provide is exposure.
You can set this value
to any float.
For example,
set it to positive 1
to make the image
twice as bright
or negative 1
to make it half as bright.
Because ProRAWs are edited
in a linear
scene-referred space,
adjusting the image
white balance is more effective.
The scene neutral can be
specified as a temperature
in degrees kelvin, or as
an x/y chromaticity coordinate.
The default sharpness
of a ProRAW look
can be adjusted to any value
from zero to one.
And the strength of ProRAW
local tone map can be adjusted
to any value from zero to one.
The local tone map allows
for each region of the image
to have its own
optimized tone curve.
Here is an example
of a ProRAW image
with a local tone map strength
turned to fully off...
and at half strength...
and fully on.
In this image,
the local tone curves
bring up the darker regions
and bring down
the brighter areas
so as to present
the best possible result
on a Standard Dynamic Range
display.
Next, let’s discuss
how your application
can get direct access
to the 14 stops
of linear scene-referred data.
Most users will prefer
the common adjustments
I described earlier,
but access to linear data
can be very useful
for certain application cases.
To get a linear image,
you just need turn off
the filter inputs
that apply the default look
to the image.
Set the baselineExposure,
exposureBias,
boost, and
localToneMapAmount to 0,
and disable gamut mapping
before getting the outputImage.
Once you have
the linearRAWImage,
you can use it as an input
to other Core Image filters
to perform
scene-referred computations.
For example, you could use
the built-in Core Image
histogram filter
to calculate statistics.
Or you may want to render
the linear image
to get its pixel data.
To do this, just create
a CIRenderDestination
for a RGBA-half-float
mutable data,
tell the render destination
to use a linear colorSpace
of your choice,
and then have a CIContext
start a task
to render
the rawFilter’s output image.
Here is an example of ProRAW
with the default look
in comparison to the as-captured
linear scene-referred image.
The linear image will look flat
and underexposed,
but it still contains the full
and unclipped 14 stops of data
from the scene.
This pair of images also
provides a good illustration
of the difference between
an output-referred image
and a scene-referred image.
In the output-referred
default look,
the area of the image
with the maximum luma
is in the sunset on the left.
But this sky area on the right
has a luma that is 80 percent
as bright as that of the sunset.
While the default image
looks great,
the luma values do not represent
the reality of the scene.
For the linear
scene-referred image,
the sky on the right
of the image
has a maximum radiance
of just 12 percent
of the radiance of the sunset,
which is more physically
logical.
This is why the linear
scene-referred image
is so important for
image processing and analysis.
After your application
has made changes
to the ProRAW
CIFilter properties,
you may want to save the image
to an output-referred format
such as HEIC or JPEG.
Here’s an example
of how to save
the rawFilter output image
to an 8-bit deep HEIC file.
With this API, you can specify
the output colorSpace to use,
though we recommend displayP3.
It is also possible to use
the options dictionary
to save the semantic masks
into the HEIC.
Also, because ProRAWs
have extra precision,
you might consider using
this new Core Image API
to save
to 10-bit deep HEIC files.
So far, all of the adjustments
I’ve described
produce an output image
that is tone-mapped
and gamut-mapped
to the Standard Dynamic Range.
This is commonly abbreviated
as “SDR”.
The next topic
I’d like to discuss
is how you can present
the dynamic range
of ProRAW images
in full glory
on an Extended Dynamic Range
display.
Many Mac displays --
ranging from the MacBook Pros
to iMacs
to the Pro Display XDR --
can present EDR content
using a MetalKit View.
To display a ProRAW CIImage,
we recommend using
a MetalKit View subclass
for best performance.
Your MetalKit View subclass
should create a CIContext
and a MTLCommandQueue
for the view.
For important details on how
to get the best performance
with Core Image
in a MetalKit View,
please review our presentation
from last year on the subject.
If your Mac display
supports EDR,
then you can set the view’s
colorPixelFormat to rgba16Float
and set wantsExtendedDynamic
RangeContent to true.
Then, when it is time
for your view subclass to draw,
set the rawFilter.extended
DynamicRangeAmount to 1
and tell the Core Image context
to start a task
to render the outputImage.
Looking at a ProRAW image
on an EDR display
is really something
one needs to see in person
to fully appreciate.
But let me try to approximate
what it looks like.
Here, the SDR image is shown,
while this shows what that same
ProRAW file will feel like
in EDR.
The bright areas
and specular highlights
are no longer restricted
by tone mapping,
so they will be visible
in full glory.
This concludes our presentation
on Apple ProRAW.
Today we have described
in detail
the design and contents
of the file format
as well as how you can capture,
store, and edit these images.
I look forward to seeing
how your applications
can unlock the full potential
of these images.
♪