[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Kate] Hi. I'm Kate.
I'm an engineer
on the Safari and WebKit team,
and today I'm gonna be
telling you
about Privacy-Preserving
Ad Attribution.
I know a lot of you
watching today's session
are probably already experts on
the history of ad attribution,
but to make sure
everyone's on the same page,
I'll start with some background
on cookies, advertising,
and tracking.
Then, I'll introduce
Private Click Measurement,
a tool that allows you
to privately measure
ad campaigns across websites.
Then I'll show you how you can
expand PCM even more,
to measure ad campaigns
that start in apps
and convert on the web.
Finally, I'll talk
about improvements
in privacy-preserving
app-to-App Store ad attribution
using SKAdNetwork.
So, let's start
with the history of cookies
and their role
in web advertising.
Cookies are useful to businesses
because they provide support
for something
called ad attribution.
Ad attribution is the process
of linking an ad-related action,
like a click,
with a desired outcome,
like a purchase.
You'll also hear me refer
to those desired outcomes
as "conversions."
This concept may seem
a little abstract in words,
so let's walk through
an example.
I happen
to really like longboarding.
Say I tap an ad for a longboard
on my favorite search site,
searchforlongboard.biz.
searchforlongboard.biz can store
something called a cookie
in the browser.
Cookies are
useful little bits of text
that help sites remember data
about your previous visits,
like products
in your shopping cart.
The link
on searchforlongboard.biz
might navigate me to a new site,
longboardshop.biz,
where I add the longboard to
my cart.
searchforlongboard.biz
can reference the cookie
that it stored earlier
to link my purchase
with the initial ad tap I made.
This is an example
of ad attribution.
The cookie data allows
searchforlongboard.biz
to measure the effectiveness
of this particular ad campaign,
which is really useful
for its business.
But what if I hadn't made
an initial ad tap earlier?
searchforlongboard.biz
would still get
the cookie data about me,
which can include
clicks I've made,
sites I've visited,
time I've spent on a page,
and other detailed information
about my web history
and behavior.
Companies like
searchforlongboard.biz
can use this information
to follow users across sites
and build detailed profiles
for advertisers,
all without a user's consent.
We call this
cross-site tracking.
Most users don't expect
to have an invasive experience
on the web,
where their interests, behavior,
and personal information
is stored and tracked.
Tracking can break trust
and create a misalignment
between users and businesses.
And now, more and more users
have started turning
to mechanisms,
like ad and content blockers
to limit tracking
on the sites they use.
From a user perspective,
content blockers are great
for preventing tracking,
but can often lead
to compatibility issues.
Additionally, since content
blockers block all ads,
there's clearly no possibility
for any sort of ad attribution.
The disconnect between users
and businesses
around ads and tracking
is hugely damaging
to the web experience,
and we wanted to find ways
to protect user privacy
while maintaining
web compatibility.
So, in 2017, Apple built
Intelligent Tracking Prevention,
or ITP,
which identifies trackers
and protects users
against this sort of profiling
on the web,
without blocking ads.
With ITP, I might tap
the same ad
on searchforlongboard.biz,
which stores
a first-party cookie
and navigates me
to longboardshop.biz,
where I add
the longboard to my cart again.
But now, ITP prevents cookies
and other website data
from being sent
to third parties,
like searchforlongboard.biz.
So, they may know that
I tapped an ad for longboards,
but they won't be able to track
my behavior on any other sites.
ITP specifically mitigates
cross-site tracking
in the browser,
but tracking is not unique
to the web.
The Identifier For Advertisers,
or IDFA, has long been used
to perform similar profiling
of iOS users across apps.
In 2020, Apple launched
SKAdNetwork,
a part
of the StoreKit framework.
It collects and reports data
about ads
that lead to app installs,
and it was designed
to give Ad Networks
privacy-preserving techniques
for ad attribution.
I'll talk later on
about improvements
to SKAdNetwork
over the last year.
Tracking infringes
on a user's privacy
without giving them the ability
to identify, understand,
or consent to what's being
shared about them.
And we aren't the only ones
thinking about this.
Regulations like CCPA and GDPR
are requiring websites
to inform their users
about how their data
is being used.
Other browsers like Brave
and Firefox are also shipping
with built-in
tracking protections.
It's becoming clear
that business models
that rely on tracking
aren't sustainable.
We recognize the importance
of providing a more private way
to measure ads
to help you thrive
in this changing ecosystem.
So the rest of our session
will focus
on some of the exciting new
solutions we've implemented
to help you measure ads
with privacy.
The first case I'm gonna cover
is web-to-web ad attribution,
meaning both
the initial click or tap
and the final conversion event
both occur in the browser.
This year, we're so excited
to introduce
Private Click Measurement,
or PCM,
which brings privacy-preserving
ad attribution to the web.
PCM is a proposed standard
in the W3C
Privacy Community Group.
To be on track
to become a full standard,
it needs an implementation
from another browser.
We're working
with other browsers
to standardize PCM
across the web.
PCM is an entirely on-device
ad-attribution
reporting mechanism.
Limited entropy in the reports
prevents a site
from being able to identify
a specific user.
And when using PCM,
the user isn't being tracked
across sites.
This means App Tracking
Transparency requirements
don't apply for uses of PCM.
Currently, PCM web-to-web
and app-to-web
are fully supported in Safari.
So, throughout
the rest of this presentation,
whenever I refer
to "the browser,"
I mean Safari.
We are working
towards adding support
for other browsers as well,
both those that use
the WebKit engine
and those that don't.
Let's go back to our
original longboard example
to show how PCM works.
Again, I tap an ad
for a longboard
on searchforlongboard.biz.
With PCM, this link specifies
two additional pieces
of information:
a Source ID,
which is 8 bits of entropy
that you can use to specify
the ad campaign,
and the site
that the ad will convert on,
called the attribution
destination site.
These are stored on-device
in the browser.
The ad link then navigates me
to longboardshop.biz.
When I tap Add to Cart,
longboardshop.biz can
specify information
about the conversion event
using an additional value
called the trigger data.
The trigger data is 4 bits,
and it might specify
an action like an Add to Cart
or a purchase.
This is stored on-device,
in the browser, as well.
So, what about reporting?
Note that only the browser
has both the click-side
and the conversion-side
information.
So, if the conversion matches
a stored click,
the browser can format
this information
into a report
that's useful to the advertiser,
while preventing
any identification
of a user across sites.
The browser then schedules
the report
to be sent to both the source
and the destination sites,
randomly 24 to 48 hours later.
The random delay
prevents the reports
from providing
any time-related data
that might link ad-clicks
and conversions together
to identify someone.
As of iOS 15 and macOS 12,
these reports also have
IP address protection,
which is crucial
to prevent fingerprinting.
You can find out more
about IP address protection
in Apple's privacy pillars
in focus WWDC session.
OK, so how do you
actually specify PCM data
when running an ad campaign?
On the source site,
where the ad is being displayed,
you can specify PCM data
using link attributes.
Here we see the Lemon Yellow
Longboard campaign
has an identifier 55,
and converts
on longboardshop.biz.
On the destination site,
you can trigger
an attribution event
by making an HTTP GET request
to the source site,
potentially specifying data
about the conversion event.
The source site gets
this request,
then needs to redirect it
to this well-known location.
Adding the longboard to my cart
has a trigger data value of 15.
And if you later on wanted
to override this conversion
with a more important one,
like a purchase,
you might specify
a higher 6-bit priority.
This design was intended
to support legacy pixels
to make adoption easy.
The last step is reporting.
The report will be sent
in a JSON format
to this well-known location.
The report provides the data
that links an ad click
with a conversion,
but you can see that there's
no identifying information
about the user included.
In this case, what you learn
is that someone, somewhere
added a lemon yellow longboard
to their cart
on longboardshop.biz.
You can use this information
to measure ad campaigns
without needing to track
specific users.
And those are the basics
for implementing
Private Click Measurement
to measure web-to-web
ad campaigns.
Now, I'll show you how you can
expand PCM even more,
to use in your apps.
We've heard lots of feedback
about the importance
of measuring ad taps
that start in apps
and convert on the web.
We realized how crucial it is
that we bridge this gap,
so we're excited
to also be introducing
PCM app-to-web attribution.
Let's go through an example
of how this works.
Now, I open Social App,
which is what I use to catch up
with all
of my longboarding friends.
And I tap an ad for a longboard.
The Source ID
and destination site
are stored on-device.
Then, I'm navigated
to longboardshop.biz in Safari.
The conversion side is exactly
the same as the web-to-web case.
When I tap Add to Cart,
longboardshop.biz can trigger
a conversion
with the trigger data,
which is stored in the browser.
The browser combines
the information into a report,
then sends it to both
the app reporting site
and the destination site
on a random 24 to 48 hour delay.
To use PCM
app-to-web attribution,
you should add
an attribution report
destination site
to the app's info.plist,
with the key NSAdvertising-
AttributionReportEndpoint.
This step is crucial,
because we take
the registrable domain
from the report destination URL
to form a well-known path
for sending reports.
This well-known path is exactly
the same as the web-to-web case.
For PCM app-to-web, you'll also
need to make some changes
in your app's code.
We know that, in order to
measure campaigns effectively,
it's important to know that
an ad tap has actually occurred.
So, we've added
a new data structure
called a UIEventAttributionView.
When you display an ad
in your app,
you'll create a new
UIEventAttributionView.
Then, you'll place it
over your ad.
The UIEventAttributionView
verifies
that a user gesture has happened
before reporting an attribution,
so that you know that
the reported data is accurate.
When the user taps the ad,
you then need to create
a new data structure
called a UIEventAttribution,
which is submitted
when an app opens a URL
to an external website.
This gets populated
with four things:
the source identifier,
which identifies
the ad campaign,
in this case,
for a lemon yellow longboard;
the destinationURL,
where the ad will be converted;
the sourceDescription,
a description
of the content that was tapped;
and the purchaser,
a description of the buyer
of the content.
If you're using a UIScene-based
life cycle management,
you'll create
a OpenExternalURLOptions object.
Then, you should assign
your event attribution object
to the corresponding property
and call the open function.
If you're using
UIApplication-based
life cycle management,
adding support
for app-to-web campaigns
is a bit different.
You'll need to create
a dictionary
that contains
the eventAttribution object.
Then you can call
the open function
with the dictionary as the value
for the options parameter.
And that's pretty much it
for implementing
app-to-web attribution.
Before we move on
to SKAdNetwork improvements,
I want to touch briefly
on PCM fraud prevention.
Since PCM reports carry
no identifying information,
there's no inherent way
for the server to know
if a conversion report
is trustworthy.
So, PCM uses
cryptographic signatures
to prevent fraud.
To explain signatures,
I'm going to use
a popular envelope analogy.
It works like this.
When the ad tap occurs
on searchforlongboard.biz,
the browser fetches
searchforlongboard's public key.
It then creates a message
that searchforlongboard will
validate later on.
However, since we don't want
searchforlongboard.biz
to be able to link
a click and conversion together,
we'll hide this message.
Think of it like putting
the message in an envelope.
The browser will then send
the hidden message
to searchforlongboard.biz.
They sign the hidden message
using an RSA
blind signature scheme
and send it back.
You can think of this
like carbon copy paper.
The signature on the envelope
will also apply to the message.
So, when the browser removes
the message from the envelope,
it will have
searchforlongboard's
signature on it.
When the attribution occurs,
the browser sends
the attribution report
with searchforlongboard's
signature.
Now, the source
and destination site
can validate
that the click was deemed
trustworthy when it happened,
using searchforlongboard's
public key.
Since searchforlongboard.biz
never saw the original message,
it can't link it
with the ad click.
So, that's it
on fraud prevention.
And I also want to talk
about testing
because we know
that it's important
for you all to be able to have
a simple, fast, and easy way
to test and debug.
WebKit has
an experimental feature
called Private Click Measurement
Debug Mode.
You'll find it in the Safari
Develop menu for macOS,
under Experimental Features.
On iOS, you can turn on
Debug Mode
in the WebKit
Experimental Features menu.
Debug Mode has
enhanced Web Inspector logging,
and reports will go out
every 10 seconds,
as opposed to 24
to 48 hours later.
That's it for using PCM
to support your web-to-web
and app-to-web campaigns.
I now want to pivot to talk about
how you can improve
your app-to-App Store
ad campaigns,
with recent updates
to SKAdNetwork.
First, let's start
with a brief overview
of SKAdNetwork up to this point.
Note that the basics
of SKAdNetwork were covered
at WWDC in 2020,
so it would be useful
to reference those presentations
for a more detailed overview
of how it works.
Essentially, SKAdNetwork
involves three parties:
ad networks, publisher apps,
and advertised apps.
Let's say I'm using Social App,
and I'm served an ad
for Longboard App
by SocialAdNet.
In SKAdNetwork terms,
SocialAdNet is the AdNetwork,
Social App is the publisher app,
and Longboard App is
the advertised app.
If I tap the ad
for Longboard App,
this generates a report
with the Ad network ID,
Publisher app ID, Campaign ID,
timestamp,
and additional information
for fraud prevention.
This information is stored
on-device, in the App Store.
Let's say the ad
for Longboard App
takes me to the App Store,
where I install and launch
Longboard App.
Now Longboard App calls one
of two APIs offered by StoreKit:
RegisterApp-
ForAdNetworkAttribution
or updateConversionValue.
Both will trigger
the SKAdNetwork reporting,
and you can check out
the documentation
for more information
on when to use which call.
StoreKit will combine the useful
information into a report
and send it to the ad network.
Now that we have
some background on SKAdNetwork,
I'll talk about
some improvements we've made
over the last year.
Since we launched SKAdNetwork,
we've been listening
to your feedback
and making changes.
Each version
introduced something
to help you better meet
your needs
with ad attribution,
whether that be more security,
more ways to measure ads,
or more attribution reporting.
In this section, we'll talk
about Signing Key improvements,
support for
View-Through Attribution,
Multiple Postback
and IP address Protection,
and Postback to Developer.
Also, note
the minimum iOS version
needed to utilize
each new feature.
First, in version 2.1,
Apple introduced a stronger
and more secure 256-bit
public key.
You should update the Apple
public key you're using
to validate postbacks
in order to utilize this.
Detailed steps on how to verify
Apple's signature
can be found in the link
to SKAdNetwork's documentation
associated with this session.
Next, Version 2.2 added support
for view-through ad campaigns.
This involves creating a new
SKAdImpression instance,
generating a signature,
and calling two new APIs:
startImpression,
when you start to present
your custom ad to the user,
and endImpression,
when you finish
presenting the ad.
With view-through attribution,
StoreKit also introduced
a new parameter
called Fidelity type.
StoreKit-rendered
click-through ads
have a fidelity type of 1,
while custom view-through ads
have a fidelity type of 0.
This gives
view-through impressions
a lower priority
than click-through ones,
and a view-through postback
will only be reported
if there's no
competing impression
with a higher fidelity.
iOS 14.6 introduced
multiple postback
and IP address protection.
Now, SKAdNetwork supports
sending reports
to a winner network
and up to five runner-ups.
The winning network is
determined
by the last impression that
occurred before the conversion.
When a report is generated,
the winner has
the possibility to receive
the crowd anonymity
controlled values,
like the sourceApp
and conversion value.
Runner-ups will not get
this information.
Also new in SKAdNetwork is
the postback to developer,
where the winning postback
gets reported
to the advertised app.
In order to utilize the
postback-to-developer feature,
your app will have to specify
the developer reporting site
in your Info.plist.
This uses the same
NSAdvertising-
AttributionReportEndpoint key
necessary for PCM
app-to-web reporting.
Just like with PCM,
the registrable domain
from the URL specified
in the plist
will be used to form
the well-known location
where the postbacks
will be sent.
Now, I'll give
some best practices
for successfully testing
and debugging
new SKAdNetwork technologies.
First, a reminder that the nonce
for each impression
should be unique.
This is important
for fraud prevention
and maintaining the integrity
of your reports.
Next, the order
of the arguments matters
when creating the signature.
So, if you're encountering
issues at this step,
you can check out
the documentation
to make sure
your argument order is correct.
Next, for testing postbacks,
you should always use
a development-signed source app
with a source app ID of 0.
And lastly, a reminder
that a testing profile
will speed up
postback transmission time
and is available to download
from the link
associated with this session.
So, that's it
for SKAdNetwork improvements,
and that concludes
all of this year's updates
for privacy-preserving
ad attribution.
As you can see,
there's a lot of features
we've implemented and improved
over the last year
to help you adopt
private ad attribution.
So let's review
what I covered today.
First, I introduced PCM,
an ad-attribution mechanism
that brings private ad measuring
to the web.
PCM supports
not only ad campaigns
measured entirely on the web,
but also campaigns that start
in apps and convert on the web.
I also went over all the updates
that have gone into SKAdNetwork
over the last year,
that give you
an even more private,
secure, and useful way
to measure app installs.
And lastly, I want to reiterate
that so much of the design
and improvements
of these technologies has come
from hearing from you all
as developers.
So, thanks. And we ask
that you keep
providing feedback.
We welcome any thoughts
on the PCM proposed standard,
which can be found on the W3C
Privacy Community Group
GitHub page.
If you came into this
with the idea
that privacy and advertising
don't mix,
I hope this session helped you
see a future
where they actually align.
Thanks for watching, and I hope
you enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[upbeat music]