[upbeat music]
[Tori] Hello,
and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Tori, and I'm so excited
to talk to you
about the new features we
have coming for your server
and to help set some guidelines
for running an effective server
to track the status
of all of your in-app purchases.
So, let's dive right in.
This session is part two
of a three-session series
focusing on in-app purchases.
If you've not already watched
"Meet StoreKit 2"
or "Support customers
and handle refunds,"
I recommend you take
a look after this session
so you can get the full story.
For this session,
we're going to focus on
the server and how you
can build your server
to manage your in-app purchases.
To get us started in this
session, let's first talk about
some of the reasons
it's useful to have a server.
Having a server is useful
for several reasons,
and, in the case of in-app
purchase,
most of them revolve
around tracking status.
When you have a server, we're
able to notify you in real time
when the status of one of your
in-app purchases changes
through
App Store server notifications,
and you can call us on-demand
to check status at any time
using server-to-server APIs.
Having a server allows you
to validate
customer access to your content,
even if their device is offline
or if the status changes
outside the app,
so you know if your customer
is still subscribed
after a renewal
or if the coins they bought
in your game have been refunded.
If you already have a server,
you may have set one up
for some of these reasons.
If you don't have a server and
are thinking of building one,
these are strong reasons
to consider,
as they give you more
control of your content.
Even when you have a server,
our story still begins
on an iPhone, iPad,
or other device
with an in-app purchase.
When you send information about
that purchase to your server,
including things like
the transactionId,
originalTransactionId,
and the receipt,
you're now able to track
that purchase from your server
by communicating
directly with our server.
Today, this involves using
APIs like verifyReceipt
or frameworks like App Store
server notifications.
We only want to make
integrating with our server
even better for you,
which brings us
to today's content.
I'll review all of the changes
we have coming
on the server side
and how you can
integrate with these
to build a better,
stronger server.
To start with, I will go through
validating access
with App Store Receipts,
tracking status
with App Store Server APIs,
then I will dive into
how you can track status
passively
with App Store
server notifications.
I will also go over
what this means
for managing family sharing
and how you can
test your server in sandbox.
Let's get started with
validating status
using receipts.
Today, our receipts are in the
unified app receipt format.
To get the JSON version
of the receipt,
you either have to do
an on-device receipt
verification in your app or,
since we're talking about
the server,
call our server-to-server
verifyReceipt endpoint.
When you call us
server-to-server,
you get this decoded receipt,
plus any new transactions
in a latest_receipt_info
section,
upcoming renewal information
in a pending_renewal_info
section,
and a latest_receipt.
This receipt can be huge,
and it contains transaction
from your entire app, whether
they are non-consumables,
consumables, subscriptions,
or non-renewing subscriptions.
This provides you
with a ton of information,
but we wonder if it can be
too much.
Additionally,
with StoreKit 2,
we're introducing new signed
transactions in a JWS,
or JSON web signature,
format on the client side,
and we want to provide
the same thing to you
on the server.
Why did we decide to introduce
signed transactions?
At Apple,
we care about security.
Using JWS to sign these
transactions
will increase security
through signing
and signature verification.
Additionally,
the transactions are easy
to decode and to verify,
so much so that you can do it
on your server
without having to call us.
Let's take a look at these
signed transactions now.
Our signed transactions
consist of three strings
separated by a period.
The first string is
a base64-encoded JSON header,
then a base64-encoded JSON
payload,
followed by a signature.
If you base64 decode the header,
it contains the signing
algorithm we used,
as well as an x5C claim.
This contains
the certificate chain you need
to verify the signature.
We'll get back to verifying
the signature in a bit.
Next, if you base64
decode the payload,
you'll see the receipt JSON.
That means all you need to do
to decode the transaction
is base64 decode the payload,
a simple operation that you
can do on your own
on your server.
Let's take a quick look at
the decoded transaction.
Just glancing at it,
you may notice that some
data types have changed from
strings in the previous receipt
to more appropriate data types,
like numbers or booleans.
Also notice that we have
reduced date formats
to only one,
milliseconds since epoch.
We've also added
a few new fields.
We've added a field
called "type,"
which tells you the content type
the transaction applies to.
We also added a field called
"appAccountToken."
When you provide this value
to StoreKit at buy time
in your StoreKit 2 app,
we persist it on the server
to return it in each
of your transactions.
We will also return this
not only in the new
signed transactions,
but also in our existing
unified app receipt
for each transaction.
The next two fields
I want to call out here
aren't really new,
but rather renamed.
We have renamed
cancellation_date
and cancellation_reason
to revocation_date
and revocation_reason
to make it more clear
that the presence of these
fields indicate that service
should be revoked,
as of the revocation date.
These last two fields
may look new
but are really a simplification
of some information from
our previous receipt.
We've combined isTrialPeriod,
isIntroOfferPeriod,
promotionalOfferIdentifier,
and offerCodeRefName
into offerType
and offerIdentifier.
offerType tells you what
type of offer your customer
has applied to this period,
with 1 for an intro offer,
2 for a subscription offer,
and 3 for an offer code.
If the offer type is 2 or 3,
you'll also see a value
in the offer identifier field
with either
the promotional offer ID
or the offerCodeRefName.
Now, I want to talk about
verifying
the signature portion of
the signed transaction info.
Verifying the signature
is an option for you to validate
that the transaction came from
Apple and is trustworthy.
If you only want to see the
contents of the transaction,
this step is not required.
However,
to verify the signature,
you will need to use
the claims available
in the header portion
of the signed transaction info.
Use the alg claim to know what
signing algorithm we used,
and use the certificate chain
in the array in the x5c claim.
Once you have these two things,
you can use your favorite
cryptographic library
to verify the signature
of the signed transaction info.
So that covers our changes
for App Store Receipts,
or, as we call them now,
signed transactions.
Now, let's move on to how you
can check status with APIs.
So while you don't need an API
like today's verifyReceipt
to verify the validity
of your signed transactions
or to decode the transactions,
we still wanted to build APIs
that would help you
on your server.
That is why we're introducing
a brand-new library
of App Store Server APIs
this year at WWDC
that will provide you
with some new features
previously unavailable
to you on your server
and will also make use of our
new signed transactions.
So we're going to talk
about two brand-new APIs
right now:
the subscription status API,
and the in-app
purchase history API.
First, I wanna talk about
the subscription status API.
The subscription status API
provides the latest status
of your auto-renewable
subscriptions,
indicated by
an originalTransactionId
from your app.
With this API,
you'll get a quick answer
as to your subscriber's status.
You'll quickly know
whether their subscription
is active, expired,
in a grace period,
or other states,
with one simple check.
Let's take a look at it now.
The request to this API
is simple, requiring only
an originalTransactionId
in the URL.
The response from this API
contains a status
for every subscription your
customer is subscribed to
in your app,
grouped by
a subscriptionGroupIdentifier.
For each
subscriptionGroupIdentifier,
we provide a list of the latest
transactions, with an entry
for each originalTransactionId
in the subscription group.
Each entry in this array
contains a status,
the originalTransactionId,
the signedTransactionInfo,
and a signedRenewalInfo,
also signed in a JWS format.
Let's take a closer look
at that status field now.
The status field will give you
a quick answer
as to the status
of your subscription
so you can know whether to
unlock service
for your subscriber.
We're starting with five
possible values for status:
1, meaning that the subscription
is active;
2, meaning that the subscription
is expired;
3, meaning that the subscription
is in a billing retry period;
4, meaning that the subscription
is in a grace period;
and 5, meaning that
the subscription access
has been revoked
due to a cancellation
or some other event.
Looking at the status field
gives you a quick answer
about your subscription.
For more information
on that status,
you can look at the payload
of the signed transaction info
and the payload
of the signed renewal info.
To decode the signedRenewalInfo,
follow the same steps
as you would for
the signed transaction info
by base64 decoding
the payload portion.
You can additionally
verify the signature
of the signedRenewalInfo
in the same manner,
using the header.
Once decoded, you will see
something like this.
The renewal info contains
the same fields we offer
in the pending renewal info
section of verifyReceipt today
with some updates such as
including only one date format
and making some fields booleans
or numbers where applicable.
We will also be adding
our new fields offerType
and offerIdentifier
to the signedRenewalInfo.
This will let you know
if the customer plans to
redeem an offer
at their next renewal.
In addition to the subscription
status API,
we want to provide a way for you
to get all of the transactions
associated with your app,
much like we provide in the
latest_receipt_info section
of verifyReceipt today.
For this reason,
we're also adding
an in-app purchase history API.
The in-app purchase history API
will provide the history of all
transactions for your app,
much like you receive
in the latest_receipt_info
section of verifyReceipt today.
The key difference here
is each transaction
will be in the new signed
transaction info format,
and the API will be paginated
to control the size of
the response you receive
from the App Store.
The initial request for this is,
like the subscription
status API, quite simple.
We require only
an originalTransactionId
from you
to process your request.
In the response
you'll receive app metadata,
like your
app's Apple ID and bundle ID,
and an array of the latest
20 transactions for your app
in our new signed
transaction info format.
We return 20 signed transaction
infos to you per request.
If you have more transactions,
look to the hasMore
and revision values
in the response.
hasMore will be true
if there are more transactions
remaining for your app.
In this case,
make another request,
passing the revision token
as a query parameter,
to get the next 20 transactions.
Repeat this
until hasMore is false.
Now let's pivot and talk about
how all of the App Store
Server APIs
will be consistent
with each other.
They will all be behind JWT — or
JSON web token — authentication,
support our
new signed transactions,
and feature JSON request
and response formats.
And best of all, they all key
off of an originalTransactionId
that you provide in the request,
rather than requiring
a receipt and a shared secret
in the request.
Now, I want to cover
JWT authentication.
All of our
new App Store Server APIs
will make use of JSON Web Token,
or JWT, authentication.
We chose this
to increase the security
of communication between
our server and yours.
To generate this JWT,
you will need to download
a private key
from App Store Connect.
This process
will automatically register
the public key with our server.
Then you must sign the token
using the ES256 algorithm
before calling our server.
To generate your private
key in App Store Connect,
navigate to
the Users and Access page
and visit the Keys tab.
Select the in-app
purchase keys option,
and you'll see a page like this.
Add a key and give it a name.
Save the key in a safe place,
as you can only download
it once,
and take note of the key ID.
Now, let's take a look at what
this JWT actually looks like.
A JWT consists of three parts:
a header,
a payload, and a signature.
In the header,
you should include the key ID
of your private key
and the algorithm
used for signing.
We require an elliptic curve
signature
with a SHA 256 hash, or ES256.
You will also include
the type of the token,
which, in this case,
is always JWT.
The payload should
include your issuer ID.
You can find this value
in App Store Connect.
You will include the time
the token was issued
and the time it should expire,
in seconds since epoch.
The difference between
these two times should be
no more than an hour.
Include the audience, which is
always appstoreconnect-v1.
You'll have to generate a nonce,
or a one-time unique string.
Finally, you'll have
to include the bundle identifier
of your app.
Once you have all of this
information,
you have to implement
the signing of this token
using the ES256 algorithm,
or an elliptic curve signature
with a SHA 256 hash.
Before I move on,
let's review the key takeaways
of our App Store Server APIs.
First, we've separated
determining status
from looking up
the history of transactions,
as these are separate functions.
Next, these APIs require
only the originalTransactionId
in the request,
meaning that you can take the
signed transactions you receive,
either from your app or from
a response from our server,
store the fields
you're interested in,
including originalTransactionId,
and then get rid of the signed
transaction info.
There is no need to store signed
transactions anymore
as we have guided you to do
with receipts in the past.
So that covers how you can
check your customer status
with our new
App Store Server APIs.
Now, I want to go over
how we are making
our App Store server
notifications consistent
and how you can track
status using notifications.
Let's first start
with a quick review
of App Store
server notifications.
We've discussed App Store
server notifications
for a few years now, so
let's review why they're useful.
With App Store server
notifications,
you can receive notifications
when the status of one of your
transactions changes
directly from the App Store.
When you
receive the notification,
you can update
your status immediately,
without your customer having
to open the app on their phone.
With App Store server
notifications,
you also don't need
to call us for status.
We'll just tell you
when something changes.
They are one of the most
powerful tools
your server
can take advantage of.
Our goal for this year
is to make App Store
server notifications
even more powerful
by making use of our new,
easy-to-use signed transactions.
In addition to this,
we will update the notifications
to make sure only one
notification is sent
for one user action,
we will update the payload,
and the entire payload
will be signed
using JWS to enhance security.
We'll also allow you to opt in
to the v2 notifications
when you're ready
and will continue sending
the existing notifications
for some time.
This is our current notification
offering for v1 notifications.
There are 11 total types,
including everything
from INITIAL_BUY to REVOKE.
With v2 notifications,
we're deprecating
four of our notification types:
INITIAL_BUY,
INTERACTIVE_RENEWAL,
CANCEL,
and PRICE_INCREASE_CONSENT.
But we're adding five new types:
SUBSCRIBED, OFFER_REDEEMED,
EXPIRED, GRACE_PERIOD_EXPIRED,
and PRICE_INCREASE.
In addition to the new
notification types,
we're adding a new field called
"substate" to the notification.
This will help you narrow a more
general notification type
to a specific user action.
Currently,
substates apply to
six of our v2 notification
types:
SUBSCRIBED,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_PREFERENCES,
OFFER_REDEEMED, EXPIRED,
and PRICE_INCREASE.
Let's take a look
at some examples
of how substates apply
to these notification types.
First, I want to talk about
the SUBSCRIBED notification
and its substates.
When a customer makes
a first-time purchase,
you will receive SUBSCRIBED
with a substate of INITIAL_BUY.
When a customer resubscribes
to the same SKU
or a different SKU,
you will receive SUBSCRIBED
with a substate of RESUBSCRIBE,
as long as the subscription
is within the same
subscription group.
One of our
new notification types
without an equivalent type
in v1 App Store
server notifications
is the
OFFER_REDEEMED notification.
So I want to take a look
at this example.
OFFER_REDEEMED is received
whenever a customer redeems
a promotional offer.
If the customer redeems an offer
for a first-time purchase,
you'll receive OFFER_REDEEMED
with a substate of INITIAL_BUY.
If the customer redeems
an offer to resubscribe
to the same
inactive subscription,
you'll receive OFFER_REDEEMED
with a substate of RESUBSCRIBE.
If the customer
redeems an offer
to upgrade
their active subscription,
you'll receive OFFER_REDEEMED
with a substate of UPGRADE.
If the customer
redeems an offer
to downgrade
their active subscription,
you'll receive OFFER_REDEEMED
with a substate of DOWNGRADE.
Additionally,
if the customer redeems an offer
to resubscribe to their
active subscription
after canceling within
the same period,
you will receive OFFER_REDEEMED
with a substate
of AUTO_RENEW_ENABLED.
Now, let's look at EXPIRED.
With the new EXPIRED
notification type,
you'll receive EXPIRED
when the subscription expires
after the customer
has disabled auto renew
with a substate of VOLUNTARY.
If a subscription expires
because the billing retry period
has ended without
a successful recovery,
you will receive EXPIRED with
a substate of BILLING_RETRY.
Additionally, if a subscription
expires because the customer
has not consented
to a price increase,
you'll receive EXPIRED with a
substate of PRICE_INCREASE.
So combining the
v2 notification types,
plus their applicable substates,
we now cover over 20 different
customer life cycle events.
Just looking at the notification
type should be enough
to get a general idea of what
has changed in your purchase,
but looking at the substate
will help you get
a more specific state
if you want to go into
more detail.
Now let's take a quick look
at the new payload.
For v2 notifications
we will always include
the same set of fields,
regardless
of the notification type.
The notification type,
the subtype,
the notification version,
which will be 2 if you
subscribed to v2 notifications,
the environment
the notification applies to,
some app metadata
like bundle ID,
the app Apple ID,
and bundle version,
the latest transaction
for the affected in-app
in our new signedTransactionInfo
format,
and the latest renewal info
for the in-app
in our new
signedRenewalInfo format.
These changes will make the
notifications easier to parse
and hopefully easier to adopt
as they make use of our
new signed transactions
and only contain information
about the affected
in-app purchase.
As I mentioned earlier,
the entire payload
will be signed
to increase the security
and trustworthiness
of our notifications.
The payload we just saw is
unsigned for readability,
but the signing
will be similar
to how we are signing
transactions and renewal info
in a JWS format.
We want you to be able
to opt in to v2 notifications
when you're ready.
For this reason,
we're adding an option
to the notification URL
in App Store Connect
to allow you to select
your App Store server
notification version.
To do this,
go to your App's page
and scroll to the new
App Store Server Notifications
section.
If you select the production
server URL,
you now have the option
to choose version 1
or version 2 App Store
server notifications.
When these changes launch
later this year,
you'll be able to opt in
to version 2 App Store
server notifications.
So now, I want to go over
some example scenarios
using our new App Store
server notifications,
starting with the first-time
purchase of a subscription.
For a first-time subscription
purchase in your app,
you'll receive a signed
transaction info
as a result of the purchase.
You can choose to verify
this on your app
and send
the originalTransactionId
and other relevant fields
to your server
or send the signed
transaction info
to your server
for verification
and choose which fields to store
in your database at that time.
Around the same time,
you'll receive
a SUBSCRIBED notification
with a substate of INITIAL_BUY.
Now that the signed transaction
info in the notification
contains the app account token,
you can immediately link
this notification
to your in-app user,
even if communication
is lost between your server
and your app after the purchase.
There's no need to call
our server
to verify
the signed transaction info.
You may call our server
at any time
if you wish to check the status
or in-app purchase history API
by sending us
the originalTransactionId.
Now I've covered
purchasing a subscription.
Let's move onto
subscription renewal.
Now we've reached the renewal
of this subscription.
If this subscription
renews successfully,
you will receive
a notification type DID_RENEW.
You can look at the signed
transaction info
and the signed renewal info
in the payload
to verify the next renewal date
of your subscription
and your customer's
renewal preferences
for their next renewal.
You can also schedule a job
to call our subscription
status API
to check the status
of your subscription
at its renewal time
as a fail-over mechanism.
Once again,
there's no need to call us
to verify the transaction
you receive in the notification.
Of course, auto-renew doesn't
always go according to plan,
especially if there
is a billing issue.
So now, I want to cover grace
period and billing retry.
Now let's suppose
that your subscription
did not renew as expected.
When this happens,
we notify you
with a DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW
notification.
If you have grace period
enabled
and the subscription
exits the grace period
without renewing successfully,
we send you
a GRACE_PERIOD_EXPIRED
notification,
and you can know
that your customer
has entered
the billing retry period.
If the subscription
still is not recovered
during the billing retry period,
we'll send you
an EXPIRED notification
with a substage
of BILLING_RETRY.
If we recover the billing
of the subscription
during the grace period
or the billing retry period,
we'll send you
a DID_RECOVER notification.
No matter
the outcome of the renewal,
we notify you of the result
with a v2 notification,
containing a signed transaction
info and signed renewal info.
You can call the subscription
status or history API
at any point in this process
to double check
your subscription status.
Now, we realize subscriptions
are not the only thing customers
will purchase in your app.
So now let's pivot
and cover what to expect
during a first-time purchase
of a consumable.
For a first-time purchase
for a consumable on your app,
you'll receive a signed
transaction info
as a result of the purchase.
You can choose to verify this
on your app
and send
the originalTransactionId
and other relevant
fields to your server
or send the signed transaction
info to your server
for verification
and choose which fields to store
in your database at that time.
Keep note of the
originalTransactionId always,
as you might need it later.
For consumables
and other content types
like non-consumables
and non-renewing subscriptions,
not much changes over the
life cycle of that purchase
unless the customer
requests a refund.
So I want to cover
that case now.
Now, suppose your customer
requests a refund
for their consumable purchase.
We'll send you
a REFUND notification,
containing the revocation
date and revocation reason
in the signed transaction info.
You can know to stop
providing access
to the consumable purchase
after the revocation date.
Should you be concerned
about the status
of your consumable purchase
at any time,
you can call the in-app
history API
and look for it
in the response.
Canceled consumables
will always be included,
so you will know if the
transaction status has changed.
Now I want to talk about
outages.
Sometimes,
despite best efforts,
you may experience
an outage on your server.
Now I'll cover how you
can help your server
recover from an outage.
If you experience
an outage on your server
and you miss App Store
server notifications,
you'll want to know what
has changed in the interim.
The in-app history API
is your solution here.
Simply call the API
for each customer,
providing
any originalTransactionId
from your app,
and you'll get
the latest history
of transactions for your app
so you can update your server.
You can then call
the subscription status API
to get the latest
subscription status
for each
of your subscriptions.
Now I want to cover
one final case--
migrating to signed
transactions on your server.
This is especially important
if you'll be ready to update
your server before your app
or if you're still receiving
the unified app receipt
from older versions of your app.
Migrating to signed transactions
on your server is easy,
as it only requires
an originalTransactionId.
You can easily convert
the unified app receipts
your server receives
from your app to JWS receipts
so your server can be compatible
with our App Store server APIs
and App Store server
notifications.
To do this,
first call verifyReceipt
with the unified app receipt
and pull all of the unique
originalTransactionIds
from the response.
Call the in-app
purchase history API
for one of these
originalTransactionIds
to get the history for your app
in signed transactions.
Then call
the subscription status API
for a subscription
originalTransactionId
to get signed transactions
and signedRenewalInformation
for all of your customer
subscriptions.
Write down any relevant data
from the payload of
the signed transaction,
and you're all set to continue
using these APIs
and to receive v2 App Store
server notifications.
So now I've covered all of
the changes we have coming
for App Store Server
Notifications
and how you can
use notifications
to check your customer status.
Now I want to talk about
how we are making it
even easier for you
to manage family sharing
for in-app purchases
from your server.
Family sharing for in-app
purchases is currently supported
for auto-renewable subscriptions
and non-consumable purchases,
if you have enabled
family sharing
for that in-app purchase
in App Store Connect.
Right now, we provide a field
called inAppOwnershipType
to indicate if a transaction is
family shared or purchased,
and we support a subset
of notifications
for family members:
REVOKE, DID_RECOVER,
and DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW.
The in-app ownership
type field
and the existing supported
notification types
will remain with our
new signed transactions
and App Store
server notifications v2.
However, coming later this year,
we're adding more support for
App Store server notifications
for family members.
For v1 notifications,
we're adding
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_PREF,
DID_RENEW,
and INTERACTIVE_RENEWAL.
For v2 notifications,
we're adding even more support
for family members.
In addition
to DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_PREF,
and DID_RENEW,
we're adding support for
SUBSCRIBED, EXPIRED,
GRACE_PERIOD_EXPIRED,
and OFFER_REDEEMED
for purchasers
as well as for family members.
This will make it even easier
for you to track the status
of all your customers,
both purchasers
and family members,
through App Store
server notifications.
So with the changes
we have coming for notifications
for family members this year,
this should make managing family
sharing for in-app purchases
even easier for you
when coupled with our existing
family sharing functionality.
Now I want to wrap up
with one more thing:
testing your server in sandbox.
We want you to feel confident
in your app and your server.
So we want you to be able
to integrate with our new
App Store Server APIs
and App Store server
notifications in sandbox
before production.
For the App Store Server APIs
we discussed today,
that means that they
are fully testable in sandbox,
and live, starting now!
This includes
the subscription status API
and the in-app
purchase history API.
In addition to this,
we're adding a few other
new features in sandbox.
Coming later this year,
you will be able to add
a sandbox-specific notification
URL in App Store Connect.
With this addition,
you can keep your production
and sandbox notifications
completely separate.
Additionally,
you'll also be able to choose
your sandbox notification
version
so you can test v2 notifications
in sandbox before production.
Last year, we brought you some
exciting sandbox improvements,
like resetting trial eligibility
and providing a Manage
Subscriptions page in sandbox.
We want to continue making
testing in sandbox easier
and are adding a few new
enhancements this year.
These are clearing purchase
history for a sandbox Apple ID,
changing sandbox account region,
and adjusting subscription
renewal rate in sandbox.
Additionally,
as a security enhancement,
we are returning an error
from verifyReceipt
for TestFlight receipts
when we detect the customer
is no longer a TestFlight user.
These new sandbox enhancements
will be accessible
from the Sandbox Testers page
in App Store Connect.
To clear purchase history,
select edit,
then toggle a tester,
and select the clear
purchase history button.
Once you confirm clearing
purchase history for a tester,
the action cannot be reversed.
So remember the testers
you've selected this option for.
Clearing purchase history
is a powerful new
testing tool for you
that enables you
to purchase something again
without creating a new account.
It also allows you
to have a fresh,
empty receipt for testing.
To change account region
or adjust subscription
renewal rate,
navigate back to
the testers page
and select a tester row.
In the tester settings,
you will see the new options
to change App Store region
and to adjust
subscription renewal rate.
You can change the account
region for a tester
by selecting the desired region.
This makes it possible to test
in 175 storefronts in sandbox,
all with one tester account.
Our final new sandbox feature
is adjusting your subscription
renewal rate in sandbox.
To edit this,
select your desired renewal rate
from the drop-down.
Right now, a month correlates
to 5 minutes in sandbox.
We'll give you
some more options
to adjust the renewal rate
for your testers.
Adjusting the subscription
renewal rate
gives you more time to do things
like cancel, upgrade,
or downgrade a subscription,
and it allows you to rapidly
speed up renewals
to simulate
longer-term customers.
That is everything we have
coming to sandbox this year.
We hope you love testing
with these new features.
So we've covered a lot
of new information today,
and now I want you to be
able to explore all of it.
I hope you take some time
to update your apps
and servers
to adopt our new JWS receipts.
Make use of our new
App Store Server APIs,
especially in sandbox,
where they are live right now.
And enroll in App Store
server notifications
if you haven't already
and get ready for the v2
update coming later this year.
Our new sandbox enhancements
are also coming later this year.
Make use of these to enhance
your sandbox testing experience.
Finally, check out
the other two sessions
from this year in this series,
"Meet StoreKit 2" and "Support
customers and handle refunds."
For more background on App Store
server notifications
and how you can set them up,
check out "What's new with
in-app purchase"
from WWDC 2020
and "In-app purchases and using
server-to-server notifications"
from WWDC 2019.
Our receipts, APIs,
and notifications
are three powerful tools
you have
to manage your in-app purchases
from your server.
By taking advantage of these,
you can make your server
and your app
more powerful than ever.
Please take advantage
of all the new features
we've gone over today,
and we look forward
to hearing your feedback.
Thanks so much
for listening today,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[upbeat music]