[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Thomas Naudet: Hello,
and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Thomas from
the localization team at Apple,
and today I'll be showing you
how to streamline
your localized strings.
You will see the easiest way
to make your app work
in many languages.
We'll start by writing UI code.
Then we'll see how to organize
strings in your targets.
After that we'll let Xcode
do the heavy lifting for us.
Lastly, we'll learn new
techniques for advanced strings.
With all this,
we'll guarantee your app
is prepared
for great translations.
This is super important because
text is everywhere in our lives.
We use text to communicate
and get information
in the real world.
It's obviously all the more true
on our connected devices
with all the apps,
notifications,
and articles we read every day.
More than ever, it's crucial
the text can be read,
be accurate, and be accessible.
Imagine being completely lost
in this street
trying to find a small shop
among all those signs.
It could be the same
for users of your app.
Text is such a core feature --
it guides users
and brings familiarity.
In that way, localizing your app
is an opportunity
to reach all users
around the world,
especially in all the markets
the App Store provides.
As a developer, you are already
familiar with text,
since us developers
enjoy naming things.
We called text "strings."
Strings are everywhere:
titles, buttons, user content,
online content, search queries,
graphics, accessibility labels,
and so on.
Think about all the strings
in your app as movie subtitles.
In the movie you watch,
you want all subtitles
to be in the right language,
at the right time,
with the right context,
and consistent
throughout the movie.
This is the exact same here.
Your strings convey meaning
to your visual content
and help the user navigate
through the streets of your app.
Let's see now,
from a developer perspective,
what the localization
process is.
Your user interface
presents strings in views.
Those strings
live in their own files.
This helps separate the concerns
between your visual content --
which is generic
for all languages --
and your specific translations.
In between,
the Foundation framework
links your user interface
and all your strings.
In this talk
I'll go into details
about each of these components.
That looks like a lot,
but we'll uncover everything
step by step.
Then let's start by defining
strings in your user interface.
Displaying
localized strings is easy
by combining the latest
Apple technologies.
I encourage you to use
these techniques in your app,
so that you never have to think
twice about localization again!
Well, any string you define
in UI needs to be localized.
There are two types
of visible strings.
One is directly defined
as you create your view.
Here, I've defined a label
in SwiftUI and Storyboard.
And yes! Both are localizable.
I told you it was easy!
The second type of strings
is more general
and can be found
in model code in SwiftUI
but also in AppKit or UIKit.
You might need to store a string
in a variable,
or return it from a function.
In all these cases,
you can use NSLocalizedString.
New in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
you can use our refined method
for Swift, String(localized:).
Let's focus on the first method
in SwiftUI for a moment.
Everything you present in
the interface is indeed a view,
whether this a text label
or a button,
it's all localizable by default,
ready to host your future
translated strings.
Since this is enabled
by default,
if you have mock content
such as previews,
make sure you opt out
by using verbatim.
This will avoid unnecessary
work for translators.
You can learn more techniques
in this related session.
Now that we've covered
the basics,
let's learn how to make
this string more dynamic.
I'm currently showing
a localized button
to place an order.
You might not know
I love concerts,
and I love seeing artists live
with friends even more!
In this app, it's not obvious
how many tickets
I'm ordering for all my friends.
So let's improve that button
to include the number
of tickets I've selected.
That was easy.
I just inserted a variable
in the string
like I'm used to in Swift.
Here, count will be replaced
at runtime
by the actual number, 3.
Now that we've seen
all our options,
I want to call out
a common pitfall:
String with (format:).
String with (format:) is great,
but it's not intended to be used
for localized strings.
Let's see why
with an example in Arabic
where the text direction
and the digits can be different.
The good news is both
are managed automatically
when you use
String(localized:).
Now, the number "three"
is correctly written in Arabic
in the button,
according to the user's
preferred digits in Settings.
String(localized:)
also supports plurals,
and isolation of each part
of the string,
meaning words are not shuffled
around in bidirectional text.
Lastly, be careful not
to overuse variables.
Gluing strings together
is handy
but could lead
to translation problems.
Here the word “Order"
could be written differently
in some languages
whether you order now
or order later.
It's safer to use
two separate strings.
All right. There's one major,
final aspect we need to see
that I secretly
kept from you until now.
The strings you've defined
will need to be translated
by somebody other than you.
Translators don't have
the full app UI in front of them
while they translate
string by string,
and they need to stay consistent
in all strings.
So you need to help them,
just like you help your
coworkers understand your code
by adding code comments.
I insist, no matter the string,
you should always
define a comment.
And don't forget
your Storyboard files;
they have a comment field
in the identity inspector.
Let me share some tips
to help translators.
First, comments should explain
where the string is visible.
For instance, is this a button?
A label? Some VoiceOver text?
Knowing if this is an action --
to order --
or a statement --
an order -- is critical.
Second, they should explain
the context.
If I press Order,
am I completing a transaction
or sorting a list?
Lastly, comments
should explain variables.
When localizers
see your strings,
they don't see your code,
so they don't see the name
of your variables to get a clue,
only a generic
placeholder instead.
So for the last example here,
what does the number before
“Ordered" represent?
Is this the number
of past orders?
The number of tickets
I've just ordered?
Yes! Thanks to the comment,
I know it' s the total
number of tickets.
Translators in lots of languages
will be able
to correctly translate
according to the gender
of the word "tickets."
Sometimes the easiest is also
to write an example value
of the variable in the comment.
With that in mind, there it is.
You have your UI code
ready for localization.
Now, we'll learn how you can
maintain your UI code
separately from your strings.
Basically,
you'll be able to organize
where your strings will live.
In order to do this,
let's see how Foundation
will make sure that
your code loads
the correct
localized strings files.
Of course, localization
starts with a language.
You can head into your project
settings to add a new one.
Let's take a look at Xcode.
Select your project
and click the plus(+) button
to add a localization.
You will see the menu
gained lots of new languages
in the latest version.
Let's see... In our app list
of localizations,
it starts with Base at the top.
Indeed, this where
the UI elements live
because they are shared
across languages.
For instance,
a Storyboard file is shared;
a Siri Intents file
is shared too.
Then they need
to be added to Base.
So make sure you click
the Localize button
for all shared assets.
OK but your strings,
on the other hand,
are not shared.
Strings belongs to one language.
So you will have
your strings in English
and all your strings in Arabic.
To test your app with strings
in a certain language,
you can change the preview
environment in SwiftUI
or change the app
scheme settings.
If the device is in a language
your app doesn't support,
Foundation tries to find
the best alternative.
If my phone
is in Mexican Spanish,
Foundation will try to fallback
on Latin American Spanish,
then to Spanish,
then to your app
development language --
for instance, English.
Lastly, when strings
come from a server,
make sure you respect
the user's preferred language.
Great.
We've seen that each language
has a collection of strings.
Those strings can be further
organized into files
called "tables."
You can use this feature
to organize every string
as you'd like.
For instance, you could have
a table for each feature,
or each screen.
Since this is optional
by default,
all strings are put in a table
named Localizable.
Concretely, this means
all strings are stored
in a file named
Localizable.strings.
Let's look at an example
to recap what
we've learned so far.
I have the following code
declaring a string
with a variable,
a customized table name,
and a comment.
Let's say my app
supports French.
In Xcode, you will then need
a UserProfile.strings file
containing the
French translation from English.
It will be stored
in a French resource folder
named by convention, fr.lproj.
The comment was very useful
for the French translator.
They used an "e" to mark
the feminine, as "places;"
French for tickets is feminine.
Let's spice things up a little
bit and talk about bundle.
This parameter allows loading
strings across targets.
The bundle parameter
is main by default.
In your own app,
you don't need it.
Main is that app.
In your app extension,
main refers
to your own extension,
so you don't need it either.
But let's say
you want to share a string
between your app
and its extension.
In your extension,
you will need to provide
the bundle of the main app.
Doing so avoids duplicating
the strings between the two.
You could also get your strings
from a framework.
In that case,
either you tap directly
into the framework's strings
by specifying its bundle
in your app code,
or the framework vends you
variables you can directly use.
Those localized string variables
have been defined
in the framework
by specifying the framework's
own bundle.
Let's look back at our model,
only now we'll update it
to make our app
load the string
provided by the framework.
The framework
defines the string
and informs Foundation
the translation is stored
inside its own bundle
in a strings file.
Without this parameter,
the string would be fetched
from the hosting app instead
and not found.
In practice,
it looks like this.
You supply the bundle
where your text is stored.
The framework will look for
the strings into its own bundle.
Then it's easy for your app.
The string can be used
in a simple line of code.
Moreover, if you implement
localization
in your frameworks this way,
you won't even have to create
the strings file presented here
containing “Complete.”
Let's now see why.
We've seen everything
you can do in code
to declare and organize strings.
But we haven't seen how
to actually create the files
that will hold
your translations.
It turns out you actually
don't need to create
those strings files.
Xcode can take care of creating
all the .strings files
for you.
When you use
Export Localizations
it reads your code
and extracts all your strings.
This is great because you don't
have to maintain strings files.
If you used to forget
to localize the string
you've just coded in your UI,
this is for you.
If you struggle
with ‘genstrings,’
this is for you too.
This year, in Xcode 13,
we've added compiler support
for Swift strings extraction.
Also, workspaces
are now fully supported.
This further separates
the concerns between your logic
and your translations.
Xcode will detect
and extract text from the Swift
and Foundation methods
we've seen earlier.
Please be aware,
if you have custom code
that wraps those APIs,
this will not work by default.
You shouldn't have to use
a method or macro usually,
but if you really need to,
you can add them
to your build settings
under Localized String
Macro Names.
For the rest,
Xcode will extract for
localization your app name
and privacy descriptions
defined in Info.plist,
and in general all assets
marked as Localized
in Xcode's inspector.
If you have existing
localizations,
you can already transition
to Xcode's export
for your new UIs.
The new strings will be
automatically added
to your existing files.
This is great if you want
to convert your project
at your own pace.
As a bonus, screenshots from
your UI tests are now included.
It's great for your localizers
so that they get context
where a string is,
and it's awesome for you to
showcase localized screenshots
of your app on the App Store.
All right, Xcode extracted
all the localization catalogs,
so you'd think it's the
translators' turn to work now.
Actually, you can do it too!
New in Xcode 13,
exported localization catalogs
can be viewed and edited
directly in Xcode.
You can see
each generated file --
so each table --
in their bundles on the left.
And for your selection,
you can see all the contained
strings, images, and files.
You can filter strings,
sort them, see comments,
screenshots,
and even translate!
This is very convenient
if you develop
and translate your own app.
It lets you review and bugfix
strings yourself, too.
When translators send you back
the translated string catalogs,
you can import them
into your project
using the Product menu
in Xcode.
And boom! Your strings files,
stringsdicts,
and other assets will be created
and updated.
Using the command line
equivalents,
you can run an automated
export and import
on a continuous integration
system.
By calling them regularly,
your project gets
the most up-to-date strings,
and a fast turnaround at
getting your new UI translated.
You can see the enhanced
workflow in action
in this year's session,
"Localize your SwiftUI app"
and learn more
in the introductry session.
That's it!
You've witnessed how strings
are born and live in your app.
To conclude,
I'll show you how to deal
with some more complex strings.
And I'm sure you'll love the new
features we have in store.
Let's start with a great one!
We've improved
attributed strings
to have built-in localization.
It's now possible with the
support of the Markdown syntax!
You can now
localize your strings
without losing any formatting.
No more risky
character operations,
just to make one word in bold.
Speaking of which,
here I use asterisks
to put a strong emphasis
on “complete.”
I encourage you to check
"What's new in Foundation"
to learn how you can add a link,
an emphasis, monospace text,
and so on.
We've seen that one string
you define in code
will have one translation
in a strings file.
But sometimes
you need your string
to have multiple
representations.
This is possible
with a stringsdict file,
a collection of strings
adapting to rules you define.
For instance,
remember our example
where we would like
to order several tickets?
In English, we would add
an "s" as a suffix
if there are multiple tickets
and no "s" for one ticket.
To keep your code
simple and correct,
you need to define this
plural rule using a stringsdict.
Because if you localize
your app,
those rules will be
different for each language.
Look at some of the cases
in Russian.
You don't want
to deal with that in code,
it's rather something
localization
should take care of.
Let's see how
we would implement that.
No code change needed;
we will still use our
existing code above.
First, compared to strings files
being made for you,
stringsdict is a manual opt-in.
So create one using
the Xcode template,
and make sure you clicked
Localize in the inspector.
All right, it all starts
with the string
you've defined in code.
If you have multiple
plural strings in code,
you can add this root entry here
for each of them.
Inside, you define
the actual value presented.
This value follows a
search-replace mechanism.
Here in this example
I've defined one token
named "tickets."
It will hold
the fulll final string.
It's best to include most
of the text inside tokens,
but that field will be
localizable
in case translators need
to add a prefix, a suffix,
or move the tokens around
in case you have
multiple variables.
OK, that token will vary
according to your
one variable in code.
Then let's define
that tickets token.
First, we just confirm that
we're doing some pluralization.
Then we indicate
the variable is a number
with the C-style formatter d.
And finally, we can write
the plural rules.
In English, we can just declare
the rule "one" and "other"
and "zero", if you'd like.
For each entry,
we write the actual value
of the tickets token.
Then, if we have three tickets,
in English it will use "other"
and generate
“Order 3 Tickets".
by replacing %d
with the number 3.
If a language needs more cases,
don't worry.
Xcode will add them for you
at export time.
In Russian it will add
“few” and “many”
on top of the existing ones.
That's it!
Our string will be pluralized
at runtime.
Before we move on,
I want to call out one case.
Although stringsdict
should be used for plurals,
it's meant for strings
containing a number.
We've seen earlier the case
"one" for singular in English.
It is indeed for the number one
in Russian as well,
but, it's also used for 21,
31, and so on.
Then in that case, using
stringsdict would not be correct
as you just want
equals to one only.
In this example,
the plural varies on
this, both, or all.
There is no number;
please don't use a stringsdict.
Imagine me booking 21 tickets
for all my friends,
and I would see in Russian,
"Order This Ticket"
instead of "Order All Tickets."
I would ask you,
"Where's my money?"
Instead use this simple
but effective if/else
for correct pluralization
of each of the three strings,
in all languages.
And that was plural support,
but stringsdict can handle many
more variant types of a string.
I invite you to watch the
related sessions to learn more.
This is great, but we wanted
to provide you a simpler way.
Yes, Foundation learned this
year how to do grammar for you!
With Markdown support
added to attributed strings,
use this new format
with the inflect attribute,
and you'll get the right value
computed at runtime,
like on this button.
This is a great new addition
to iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
currently available
in select languages.
If you want more control,
you can use a stringsdict.
We didn't stop at adding
plural support.
We wanted our software strings
to be more inclusive.
For instance,
when an app welcomes users,
it's pretty straightforward
in English.
But it is not in Spanish
because it depends
on the user's term of address.
Up to now, you had to present
a nonpersonalized string,
which is correct but stilted
to most Spanish users.
Literally,
"We give you our welcome."
So what if we could personalize
the string for the user?
With our new Markdown notation,
you can do that now!
The string will now follow
the term of address you select
in the language settings
of your device.
So “Bienvenida" for users
who want to be referred to
in the feminine,
“Bienvenido" in the masculine,
and if we do not know,
we'll use the existing
inflection alternative.
Inline inflections for plural
and term of address
can be defined either
in your code
or your translations.
We are super excited
about this new addition
to select languages,
and we can't wait
to see your app use it.
Finally, we've seen today
all the ways
you can write
localizable strings.
But if you want to present data,
you should actually let the
frameworks write them for you.
Our formatters handle hundreds
of combinations of languages
and regions, and a variety
of types and units.
So don't hardcode;
let us do the hard work.
And this is easier than ever
starting this year
to adopt formatters in Swift.
We made them easy to use
inline in your string
interpolation.
Check this year's
"What's new in Foundation"
to find your new favorite API
and get details about
all those we've seen today.
If you need to deploy
to previous releases
or want details on formatters,
check last year's session.
All right, what I want you
to take away today
is that if you write code
using modern APIs,
Xcode will generate
all the strings for you.
We saw how you can organize
your strings across bundles,
and we discovered new APIs
to make grammar and formatting
easy for you.
If you follow
all these techniques,
adding a new language
won't require any code changes!
Lastly, always test.
No matter how much effort
you put into
localizing your strings,
you should test your app
to make sure it runs great
in all languages.
With that, I can't wait
to book concerts
with your fully localized app.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC,
thank you for watching.
♪