[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Stuart Cheshire: Welcome to
"Reduce network delays
for your app".
My name is Stuart Cheshire.
I'm going to talk
about factors that contribute
to making network apps
feel slow today
and then I'll hand over
to my colleague Vidhi Goel
to tell you about the techniques
and APIs you can use
to make your network app
more responsive.
Let's start by talking about
something you may have already
seen in the WWDC beta of iOS.
If you look
in Developer settings,
you will see a new item
in the Networking section
called Responsiveness.
While upload throughput,
download throughput,
and idle ping time
are all interesting,
the main factor that affects
the responsiveness
of your network app
is the network's responsiveness
under working conditions,
not idle conditions.
The typical internet speed test
idle ping time measurement
tells you how well
your internet connection works
when you're not using it.
What matters is how well
your internet connection works
when you are using it.
Tap on Test.
It will warn you that it will
generate network traffic,
it will measure your network
for a few seconds,
and then it will tell you how
well your network is performing
under working conditions.
The tool reports
network responsiveness
in round trips per minute,
or RPM, instead of milliseconds.
We created this new RPM metric
because milliseconds
are a fairly abstract concept
to a lot of people.
People are also more familiar
with metrics
where higher is better.
The RPM metric produces
numbers in the range
from a few hundred RPM
to a few thousand RPM,
just like the RPM
of your car engine.
There's also a command-line
version of this test tool
on macOS called
NetworkQuality.
You might think that your home
or work network
has a great ping time,
but that's when it's idle.
Run this network quality test
for yourself --
on your iPhone or Mac --
and you might find that when
your network is being used,
its responsiveness
becomes a lot worse.
And I do mean a lot worse.
Your network might have
an idle round-trip time
of 20 milliseconds,
which sounds pretty good,
but you might find
that under working conditions
the round-trip time goes up
to 600 milliseconds or more.
That's 30 times worse.
Network responsiveness
under working conditions
is what matters
for your app's user experience.
We all see this problem
all the time,
but especially with audio
and video
freezes, and dropouts
during video conferencing.
High network delays
hurt all apps,
but we've got used to that,
so we notice it more
when it affects
video conferencing.
When we have problems
with our video conferences,
we think we'll fix it
by upgrading
our internet connection.
People have gone from
a few megabits per second
to gigabit and above,
yet the problems still happen.
A few megabits per second
should be plenty
for video conferencing,
so why do we still have
these problems?
When buffers in the network
are excessively large,
when they fill up,
they don't improve throughput,
but they do add delay.
We normally think of the
internet operating like this,
with packets flowing speedily
through the network.
But if we look inside the cloud,
we'll see that it really works
more like this.
The packet you see
coming out of the network
is not the one
that you saw go in.
Packets spend a lot of time
sitting in excessively large
buffers in the network.
This phenomenon
of excessively large buffers
is called bufferbloat,
and until now it hasn't been
widely measured,
despite the effect it has
on everyday network use.
The good news is that there are
modern queue management
algorithms, like CoDel --
the Controlled Delay
queueing algorithm --
that eliminate bufferbloat.
When the network
keeps queues short,
the time a packet spends
waiting in the network
is dramatically reduced.
It's possible to get
high throughput and low delay
at the same time.
It's not an either/or choice.
It's not a zero-sum game.
We're working with the industry
to deploy smarter
queue management algorithms
and improve
network responsiveness
under working conditions.
But for now, if you want
to give a great user experience,
you will want to make your apps
cope with the internet
as it is today.
Bufferbloat is a large component
of the network delays
your application
will experience,
but it's not the only source
of delay.
There's software and hardware
processing time.
As CPUs get ever faster,
this processing time
continues to shrink.
There's the actual
data transmission time.
As data rates increase
from kilobits to megabits
to gigabits per second,
transmission time
continues to shrink.
Then there's the time delay
due to buffering in the network.
As I said, we're working
with the industry
on reducing these delays.
But there's always going to be
the speed-of-light
signal propagation delay.
Back in the 1990s,
the Stanford-to-MIT ping time,
round-trip, coast-to-coast,
across the United States,
was already under
100 milliseconds.
That's pretty close to the
speed-of-light limit already,
so it's not going to get
much better.
We're working on reducing
the other three delays,
but the speed-of-light delay
will never go away,
so this is why it’s important
to design your apps
taking network round-trip times
into account.
When we're talking about
taking network round-trip times
into account,
what kind of apps
are we talking about?
Everyone knows
that video conferencing
is severely affected
by high network delays.
Everyone knows that online games
are severely affected
by high network delays.
But this affects all apps
that use the network.
I'm talking about
getting weather forecasts,
stock quotes,
driving directions.
This affects web browsing.
It affects skipping ahead while
watching a streaming video.
Think about
how many apps include
some animated
spinning delay indicator
while the app is waiting
for the network.
Maybe your app.
We show
that "please wait" indicator
so that the user doesn't think
the app has hung.
It's great that we put
so much effort
into giving the user something
to look at
while they wait
for the slow network,
but we should also put
equal effort
into reducing the time
they spend waiting.
If you have an app
where you ever show
a delay indicator while waiting
for data from the network,
there are techniques you can use
to reduce those wait times.
The time an app waits
for network data
is a function of
how long it takes
for one network round trip,
and how many network
round trips your app requires.
As an app developer,
there's not a lot you can do
to improve the underlying
network round-trip time,
but you can control how many
round trips your app requires.
Let me introduce my colleague,
Vidhi Goel,
to tell you how you can do that.
Vidhi Goel: Thanks, Stuart.
Hi, I am Vidhi, and today
I'd like to talk to you about
what you can do as a developer
to reduce network delays
in your app.
App responsiveness
is inversely proportional
to the number
of network round trips.
Let me show you how you can
reduce these network round trips
by adopting the modern
networking protocols
and make your apps super snappy.
To speed up your apps,
adopt the modern
networking protocols
such as HTTP/3 & QUIC,
TCP Fast Open,
TLS 1.3, and Multipath TCP.
With these techniques,
your app can potentially achieve
multiple round-trip reductions
in delivering data
to your user.
Server side support is required
for all of these
modern protocols,
so check with your provider
about their readiness.
We are happy to tell you
that all of these technologies
are available on iOS and macOS.
Let's look into each
of these technologies.
First up, we have HTTP/3
and QUIC
which are enabled by default
in iOS 15 and macOS Monterey.
QUIC is a transport protocol
which can set up
a connection much faster
than TCP and TLS.
By reducing
the head-of-line blocking,
QUIC can significantly
reduce delays
in delivering data to your user.
And here is the best part:
if you are already using
URLSession, you’re all set.
If you provide your own
application layer
using the Network framework APIs
and want to take advantage
of QUIC,
simply create an NWConnection
with QUIC parameters
and set a TLS Application-Layer
protocol or ALPN.
Please check out the
"Accelerate networking with
HTTP/3 and QUIC" session
to learn more about how to use
these technologies in your app.
QUIC is useful
in many scenarios.
However, TCP may still be
the right choice
for some applications.
When using TCP, you can
eliminate an entire round trip
by sending the app data
along with the TCP handshake.
TCP Fast Open is supported
in Network framework
and Sockets.
To use it with NWConnections,
there are two options:
the first option is to allow
Fast Open on your connection
and in this case, the app will
provide the initial data
to be sent out
with the handshake.
To enable this,
set the allowFastOpen parameter
to true and create
your connection.
And then, before calling start,
you would call send
with your initial data.
When using TCP Fast Open,
you have to be careful
that you only send
idempotent requests
with the handshake.
Idempotent basically means that
the data is safe to be replayed
over the network.
There is another way
to use TCP Fast Open
that does not require your app
to send its own initial data.
If your app is using TLS
over TCP,
you can choose to send
the TLS handshake message
as the initial data.
To enable this,
go to your TCP-specific options
and set enableFastOpen to true.
The recommended way to use
TCP Fast Open
is via the Network framework
API,
but if your app is built
over Sockets,
then you would call the connectx
API with the respective flags
to specify that you want to send
idempotent data
with the handshake.
I mentioned idempotent
a couple of times.
Let me explain what it means
and why it is important to send
only idempotent requests
with the handshake.
An idempotent
and replay-safe operation
is one that has
no additional effect
if it is performed
more than once.
For example,
when the user goes
to the developer.apple.com
web page,
the HTTP GET request
for this web page is sent out
with the TCP handshake.
If the acknowledgment
for this request
was either delayed
or dropped in the network,
the device will resend
the HTTP GET request
which may get routed
to a different server.
And this time
the acknowledgement arrives
along with the HTTP response.
As the HTTP GET request
does not have
any additional effect
when it is resent
over the network,
it is considered
as an idempotent request.
Now, let's say the user
is trying to buy
a new iPhone 12.
The HTTP request sent
for this operation
is not an idempotent request.
It could result
in multiple transactions
if the request goes
to a different server each time
when the data is replayed
over the network.
Keeping that in mind,
let's talk about TLS 1.3.
TLS 1.3 removes
an entire round trip
from the handshake
as compared to TLS 1.2.
It also provides
stronger security.
It is enabled by default
since iOS 13.4 for URLSession
and NWConnection.
The TLS 1.3 protocol
defines early data support,
which can save yet another
round trip
by sending idempotent requests
along with the TLS handshake
message.
Let's switch gears
and look at Multipath TCP
which works a bit differently
in reducing network delays.
Multipath TCP allows
a single TCP connection
to continue
as the device switches
from one network to another.
To get the low latency feature
of Multipath TCP,
use the interactive mode API.
It will save all
the round trips needed
to establish a new connection,
and the system
will automatically choose
the faster network path
for your data packets.
To opt in from the client,
set the multipathServiceType
property to interactive
on your URLSession
configuration
or on your NWParameters.
To give you an idea of how
many round trips you can save
with these modern technologies,
let's start
with a reference point.
Let's say your app is currently
running TLS 1.2 over TCP.
In this case it will take
four round trips
to get the first byte
to your user.
If your server switches
from TLS 1.2 to TLS 1.3,
your connections will eliminate
an entire round trip.
If you enable TCP Fast Open
on your connection,
you will save
yet another round trip.
In iOS 15, HTTP/3 over QUIC
provides a reduction
to two round trips.
The QUIC protocol
also defines early data support,
which could enable a further
reduction to one round trip.
Based on our measurements
at Apple,
it is common for the users
to see round-trip times
that sometimes spike up
as high as 600 milliseconds.
Let's see what that means
for your app.
Four round trips
at 600 milliseconds
means your user is waiting
almost two and a half seconds
for the data to arrive.
That's a huge amount of time
to wait and stare
at the network spinner.
By adopting the modern
networking protocols,
you can reduce that time
to first byte from 2.4 seconds
to about half a second.
The user will definitively
notice the difference
when the data arrives a whole
second and a half earlier.
Every developer who wants
great network performance
should pay attention
to the number of round trips.
This is where the big wins are.
All the technologies
that I've talked about
help to reduce network delays
in your app
in real-world
network conditions.
If you test your app on 5G,
LTE, or fast Wi-Fi networks,
your app responsiveness
might seem fine to you.
But your users
aren't always using your app
in the best network conditions.
To simulate realistic networks,
Network Link Conditioner tool
is available for iOS
from the Developer settings
menu.
For macOS, you can download it
from the Apple Developer
website.
This tool is a reliable
and repeatable way
to test your app
in different network conditions
that your users may experience
in their day-to-day life.
If you recall, Stuart mentioned
earlier that you can't do much
about reducing
your network round-trip time.
Well, that's not entirely true.
Let me explain how you can
reduce the network
round-trip time when you
correctly inform the system
about your app traffic.
Most apps have a mix of traffic
that they send or receive.
There is a lot of data
that is exchanged
from the user's device
when running a bunch of apps.
In real-world networks,
like a home or office Wi-Fi,
a number of devices
share the same network.
These devices simultaneously
send and receive
significant amount of data
while using a set of apps.
To avoid building up long queues
in this shared network,
it is crucial that you classify
your app data appropriately
so that the system can manage
your traffic efficiently
in order to maintain
low network delays.
And when you allow the system
to maintain low network delays,
it makes your app's
foreground traffic faster
and hence the data
that matters most to the users
is delivered quickly.
Let me illustrate this
with an example.
Many apps prefetch content
like graphics,
audio files, et cetera, to make
it available for later use.
When the app is prefetching
a substantial amount of data,
this is what the network
might look like.
The bottleneck queue
can become full.
If at this point, the user
initiates a network activity --
like viewing
their profile page --
the response for this request
will be queued
at the end of the network queue,
and it may take seconds
before the profile is shown.
This would not be
a good user experience.
Now, let's look at what happens
to the network
when we mark these nonuser
initiated prefetching tasks
as background.
Marking these non user initiated
transfers as background
will dramatically reduce
the size of the network queue
which will then become available
for other foreground data.
Thus, any foreground data --
that is, the green packets --
will be delivered instantly
for a quick,
delightful experience.
In iOS 15 and macOS Monterey,
the background service type
has improved dramatically.
We have added new
congestion control algorithms
for background uploads
and downloads.
These new algorithms not only
reduce network delays
significantly, for better
user experience,
but also ensure that
the background transfers
finish in nearly the same time
as other traffic.
Let's look
at the networking APIs
that you can adopt
to take advantage
of the background service type.
When your app
is in the foreground
and performing
non-user-initiated transfers,
you would use the default
URLSession
and set the network service type
to background
on your URL requests.
Again, this allows the system
to maintain low network delays.
And for NWConnection,
you would set the service class
to background
on your NWParameters.
If your app starts
a long-running transfer,
whether it is user initiated
or not,
you would create
a background URLSession
to continue running
even when your app is suspended.
For time-insensitive tasks,
you can set
the isDiscretionary property
to true.
This will allow the system
to wait for optimal conditions
to perform the transfer.
We've talked about how your app
can help in keeping
the network queues short.
Another source of delay can be
on the sending device itself.
Historically, networking stacks
have used very large
send buffers.
This adds a lot
of unnecessary delay,
sometimes in the order
of seconds,
before the packet
even enters the network.
We fixed this for URLSession
and NWConnection
way back in 2015.
But most servers on the internet
run on Linux
and use BSD Sockets.
Contact your server operators
to ensure that they are using
the TCP not sent low watermark
socket option
to reduce the delays
at the source.
For your next steps,
Adopt the modern
networking protocols
to eliminate
multiple round trips.
Use the background mode
for prefetching assets,
bulk transfers,
and non urgent tasks.
Test your app's performance
in different network conditions.
Network Link Conditioner is an
excellent tool for doing that.
Keeping network delays low
improves the responsiveness
of your app
and enhances
the overall user experience.
Thanks for watching
and have a great WWDC!
♪