[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Adam Sonnanstine:
Hello! my name is Adam,
and I'm here today to show you
what's new in AVFoundation.
We have three new features
to discuss today.
We're going to spend
most of our time talking about
what's new in the world
of AVAsset inspection,
and then we'll give
a quick introduction
to two other features:
video compositing with metadata
and caption file authoring.
So without further ado,
let's jump into our first topic,
which is AVAsset
async Inspection.
But first, a little bit
of background,
starting with a refresher
on AVAsset.
AVAsset is AVFoundation's
core model object
for representing things
like movie files
stored on the user's device;
movie files stored elsewhere,
such as a remote server;
and other forms
of audiovisual content,
such as HTTP Live Streams
and compositions.
And when you have an asset,
you most often want to play it,
but just as often, you're going
to want to inspect it.
You want to ask it questions
like, what's its duration
or what are the formats of audio
and video it contains?
And that's what we're really
going to be talking about
in this topic: asset inspection.
And whenever you're inspecting
an asset,
there are two important things
to keep in mind.
The first is that asset
inspection happens on demand.
This is mainly because
movie files can be quite large.
A feature-length film could be
several gigabytes in size.
You wouldn't want the asset
to eagerly download
the entire file,
just in case you ask
for its duration later.
Instead, the asset waits
until you ask it
to load a property value,
then it downloads
just the information it needs
to give you that value.
The second thing to keep in mind
is that asset inspection
is an asynchronous process.
This is really important because
network I/O can take some time.
If the asset is stored
across the network,
you wouldn't want your app's
main thread to be blocked
while AVAsset issues
a synchronous network request.
Instead, AVAsset
will asynchronously
deliver the result
when it's ready.
With these two things in mind,
we have a new API
for inspecting asset properties,
and it looks a little bit
like this.
The main thing to notice is
this new load method,
which takes in
a property identifier --
in this case .duration --
in order for you to tell it
which property value to load.
Each property identifier
is associated with a result type
at compile time,
which determines the return type
of the load method.
In this case,
the duration is a CMTime,
so the result is a CMTime.
One thing you may not have seen
before is this await keyword.
This is a new feature in Swift,
and it's used to mark,
at the call site, that the load
method is asynchronous.
For all the details
on async/await
and the broader concurrency
effort in Swift,
I encourage you to check out
the session called
"Meet async/await in Swift."
For now, as a quick
way of understanding
how to use our new
property loading method,
I like to think
of the await keyword
as dividing the calling function
into two parts.
First, there's the part
that happens
before the asynchronous
operation begins.
In this case, we create an asset
and ask it to load its duration.
At this point, the asset
goes off and does the I/O
and parsing necessary
to determine its duration
and we await its result.
While we're waiting, the calling
function is suspended,
which means the code
written after the await
doesn't execute right away.
However, the thread we were
running on isn't blocked.
Instead, it's free to do
more work while we're waiting.
Once the asynchronous
duration loading has finished,
then the second half of the
function is scheduled to be run.
In this case, if the duration
loading was successful,
we store the duration
into a local constant
and send it off
to another function.
Or, if the operation failed,
an error will be thrown
once the calling function
resumes.
So that's the basics of loading
a property value asynchronously.
You can also load the values
of multiple properties at once,
and you do this simply
by passing in more
than one property identifier
to the load method.
In this case, we're loading
both the duration and the tracks
at the same time.
This is not only convenient, but
it can also be more efficient.
If the asset knows all the
properties you're interested in,
it can batch up the work
required to load their values.
The result of loading multiple
property values is a tuple,
with the loaded values
in the same order you used
for the property
identifiers.
Just like loading
a single property value,
this is type safe.
In this case, the first element
of the result tuple is a CMTime
and the second element
is an array of AVAssetTracks.
And of course, just like
with loading a single value,
this is an asynchronous
operation.
In addition to asynchronously
loading property values,
you can also check the status
of a property
without waiting
for the value to load
at any time using the new
status(of: ) method.
You pass in the same
property identifier
that you use
for the load method,
and this'll return an enum
with four possible cases.
Each property starts off
as .notYetLoaded.
Remember that asset inspection
happens on demand,
so until you ask to load
a property value,
the asset won't have done
any work to load it.
If you happen
to check the status
while the loading
is in progress,
you'll get the .loading case.
Or, if the property
is already loaded,
you'll get the .loaded case,
which comes bundled
with the value that was loaded
as an associated value.
Finally,
if a failure occurred --
perhaps because
the network went down --
you'll get the .failed case,
which comes bundled
with an error to describe
what went wrong.
Note that this'll be
the same error that was thrown
by the invocation
of the load method
that initiated
the failed loading request.
So that's the new API for
loading asynchronous properties
and checking their status.
AVAsset has quite
a few properties
whose values can be loaded
asynchronously.
Most of these vend
a self-contained value,
but the .tracks
and .metadata properties
vend more complex objects
you can use
to descend into the hierarchical
structure of the asset.
In the case
of the .tracks property,
you'll get an array
of AVAssetTracks.
An AVAssetTrack has
its own collection of properties
whose values can be loaded
asynchronously
using that same load method.
Similarly,
the .metadata property
gives you an array
of AVMetadataItems,
and several AVMetadataItem
properties
can also be loaded
asynchronously
using the load method.
The last bit of new API
in this area
is a collection of asynchronous
methods that you can use
to get at specific subsets
of certain property values.
So instead of loading
all the tracks, for example,
you can use one
of these first three methods
to load just some
of the tracks --
for example,
just the audio tracks.
There are several
new methods like this
on both AVAsset
and AVAssetTrack.
So that's all
the new API we have
for inspecting assets
asynchronously.
But at this point, I have
a small confession to make.
None of this functionality
is actually new.
The APIs are new,
but these classes
have always had the ability
to load their property values
asynchronously.
It's just that,
with the old APIs,
you would've had to write code
more like this.
It was a three-step process.
You first have to call
the loadValuesAsynchronously
method,
giving it strings to tell it
which properties to load.
Then you need to make sure
that each of the properties
actually did successfully load
and didn't fail.
Then, once you've gotten
that far,
you can fetch the loaded value
either by querying
the corresponding synchronous
property
or by calling one of the
synchronous filtering methods.
This is not only verbose
and repetitive,
it's also easy to misuse.
For example,
it's very easy to forget
to do these essential loading
and status-checking steps.
What you're left with are
these synchronous properties
and methods that can be
called at any time,
but if you call them without
first loading
the property values, you'll
end up doing blocking I/O.
If you do this
on your main thread,
this means that your app
can end up hanging
at unpredictable times.
So in addition to the fact
that the new APIs
are simply easier to use,
the fact that they also
eliminate these common misuses
means that we plan to deprecate
the old synchronous APIs
for Swift clients
in a future release.
This is an excellent time
to move
to the new asynchronous
versions of these interfaces,
and to help you do that
we've prepared
a short migration guide.
So, if you're doing that
trifecta of loading the value,
checking its status, and then
grabbing a synchronous property,
now you can simply
call the load method
and do that all
in one asynchronous step.
Similarly, if you're doing
that three-step process
but using a synchronous
filtering method
instead of a property,
you can now call the
asynchronous equivalent
of that filtering method
and do that in one step.
If you're switching over
the status of a property
using the old
statusOfValue(forKey: ) method
and then grabbing the
synchronous property value
when you see
that you're in the .loaded case,
now you can take advantage of
the fact that the .loaded case
of the new status enum
comes bundled
with that .loaded value.
If your app is doing something
a little bit more interesting,
like loading the value of a
property in one part of the code
and then fetching
the loaded value
in a different part of the code,
there are a couple ways
you could do this
with the new interface.
I recommend just calling
the load method again.
This is the easiest
and safest way to do it,
and if the property
has already been loaded,
this won't duplicate the work
that's already been done.
Instead, it'll just return
a cached value.
However, there's one caveat
to this and that is that,
because the load method
is an async method,
it can only be called
from an async context.
So if you really need
to get the value of the property
from a pure synchronous context,
you can do something like
get the status of the property
and assert that it's loaded
in order to grab the value
of the property synchronously.
Still, you have to be careful
doing this,
because it's possible
for a property to become failed
even after
it's already been loaded.
Finally, if you're skipping
the loading
and status-checking steps
and just relying on the current
behavior of the properties
and methods in that they block
until the result is available,
well, we're actually
not providing a replacement
for this.
This has never been the
recommended way to use the API,
and so we've always
discouraged it.
We designed the new
property-loading APIs
to be just about as easy to use
as fetching a simple property,
so migrating to the new APIs
should be straightforward.
And with that,
that's all for our first topic.
I'm really excited about
our new way to inspect assets,
using Swift's
new async features,
and I hope you'll enjoy
using them as much as I have.
Now let's move on to the first
of our two shorter topics:
video compositing with metadata.
Here we're talking
about video compositing,
which is the process
of taking multiple video tracks
and composing them into a
single stream of video frames.
And in particular,
we have an enhancement
for custom video compositors,
which is where
you provide the code
that does the compositing.
New this year, you can
get per-frame metadata
delivered to you
in your custom compositor's
frame composition callback.
As an example, let's say
you have a sequence of GPS data,
and that data is time-stamped
and synchronized
with your video, and you want
to use that GPS data
in order to influence how your
frames are composed together.
You can do that now,
and the first step is to write
the GPS data to a timed metadata
track in your source movie.
In order do to this
with AVAssetWriter,
check out the existing class,
AVAssetWriter
InputMetadataAdaptor.
Now let's take a look
at the new API.
Let's say you're starting
with a source movie
that has a certain collection
of tracks.
Perhaps it has an audio track,
two video tracks,
and three timed metadata tracks.
But let's say that tracks four
and five contain metadata
that's useful
for your video compositing,
but track six is unrelated.
You have two setup steps
to perform, and the first
is to use the new source
SampleDataTrackIDs property
to tell your
video composition object
the IDs of all
the timed metadata tracks
that are relevant for
the entire video composition.
Once you've done that,
the second step
is to take each of your video
composition instructions
and do something similar,
but this time you set
the requiredSourceSampleData
TrackIDs property
to tell it the track ID --
or IDs --
that are relevant
for that particular instruction.
It's important that you do
both of these setup steps
or you simply won't get
any metadata
in your composition
callback.
Now let's move over
to the callback itself.
When you get your asynchronous
video composition request object
in your callback, there are
two new APIs that you use
in order to get the metadata
for your video composition.
The first is the source
SampleDataTrackIDs property,
which replays the track IDs
for the metadata tracks
that are relevant
to that request.
Then for each of the track IDs,
you can use the
sourceTimedMetadata(byTrackID :)
method
in order to get the current
timed metadata group
for that track.
Now, AVTimedMetadataGroup
is a high-level representation
of the metadata,
with the value parsed
into a string, date,
or other high-level object.
If you'd rather work with the
raw bytes of the metadata,
you can use the
sourceSampleBuffer(byTrackID: )
method
to get a CMSampleBuffer
instead of an
AVTimedMetadataGroup.
Once you have
the metadata in hand,
you can use the metadata along
with your source video frames
to generate
your output video frame
and finish off the request.
So that's all it takes
to get metadata
into your custom video
compositor callback
so you can do more
interesting things
with your video compositions.
Now onto our final topic,
which is caption file authoring.
New this year for macOS,
AVFoundation is adding support
for two file formats.
First, we have iTunes Timed
Text, or .itt files,
which contain subtitles.
The other file format
is Scenarist Closed Captions --
or .scc files --
which contain closed captions.
AVFoundation is adding support
for authoring
these two file formats,
ingesting captions
from these types of files,
and also for previewing captions
at runtime
to see what they'll look like
during playback.
On the authoring side,
we have some new APIs,
starting with AVCaption,
which is the model object that
represents a single caption.
It has properties for things
like the text, position,
styling, and other attributes
of a single caption.
You can create
AVCaptions yourself
and use an
AVAssetWriterInputCaptionAdaptor
in order to write them to one
of these two file formats.
In addition, we have
a new validation service
in the AVCaptionConversion
Validator class,
which helps you make sure
the captions you're writing
are actually compatible with
the file format you've chosen.
As an example of why this is
important, consider .scc files.
They contain CEA-608 captions,
which is a format that has
very specific limitations
about how many captions you can
have in a given amount of time,
all the way down
to having a fixed bit budget
for the data representing
the individual characters
and their styling.
So the validator will help you
not only ensure
that your stream of captions is
compatible with the file format,
it'll also suggest tweaks
you can make to your captions,
such as adjusting
their time stamps,
in order to make them
compatible.
The new API
for ingesting captions
is AVAssetReader
OutputCaptionAdaptor
which allows you to take
one of these files
and read in AVCaption objects
from it.
Finally, we have an
AVCaptionRenderer class,
which allows you
to take a single caption
or a group of captions
and render them to a CGContext
in order to get a preview
of what they'll look like
during playback.
So that's just
the tip of the iceberg
for our new caption file
authoring APIs.
If you're interested
in adopting them,
we encourage you
to get in touch with us --
either in the forums
or in the conference labs --
and we can help answer
any questions that you have.
And that was our final topic,
so let's wrap up.
Our big topic for the day was
inspecting AVAsset properties,
the importance of doing so
on demand and asynchronously,
the new APIs in this area,
and some tips for migrating
from the old APIs.
We then talked about
using timed metadata
to further customize
your custom video compositions.
Finally, I gave
a brief introduction
to caption file authoring
and the new APIs in that area.
That's all for today.
Thank you very much for watching
and enjoy WWDC21.
♪