[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Matt Ricketson: Welcome
to “What’s New in SwiftUI.”
I’m Matt, and later on,
I’ll be joined by Taylor.
This session
is all about SwiftUI,
Apple’s declarative
UI framework.
SwiftUI is still young,
but we’ve come so far already.
SwiftUI was first released
in 2019,
introducing a powerful new way
to build user interfaces
in a declarative,
state-driven style.
We took the next big step
with SwiftUI’s second release,
enabling 100 percent
SwiftUI apps
with the new App and Scene APIs.
This year we’re focused
on supporting
even deeper adoption
of SwiftUI in your apps
with a great set
of rich new features.
Now if you haven’t yet
had a chance
to try out SwiftUI yourself,
that’s OK!
Only you know
what’s best for your app.
But here are a few tips
to keep in mind
as you learn about
all the new features
available this year.
A good way to dip your toes
into SwiftUI
is to use it to create
brand-new features
in an existing app,
like how it powers
the new activity stream in Notes
for iOS, iPadOS, and macOS.
Or the new avatar picker
in macOS,
also built with SwiftUI.
Remember, you can mix in SwiftUI
alongside your existing UIKit
or AppKit code.
SwiftUI is also a useful tool
for expanding your app
to new platforms,
like how SwiftUI
was used to build
the new Shortcuts app
on macOS.
With SwiftUI,
you can easily share common code
between platforms
while still crafting a unique
experience for each device.
And when you’re ready
to redesign your app,
that’s the perfect time
to bring in SwiftUI to help.
The all-new
Apple Pay purchase flow
was redesigned using SwiftUI,
which was also used to bring
a fresh coat of paint
to the new Help Viewer on macOS
and the Tips app on watchOS.
And finally, we can’t forget
the gorgeous new Weather app
for iOS,
also rebuilt from the ground up
in SwiftUI.
These are just several examples
of how SwiftUI
is helping build
the next generation of apps.
For this session,
we’d like to share
some of the great new APIs
that made it all possible.
We’ll start by walking through
improvements
to how we build collections
of content with lists and grids.
Next, we’ll go beyond lists,
introducing new features
to take your data-driven apps
to the next level.
Third, we’ll show off some
stunning new tools
for driving graphics
and visual effects.
We’ll talk about enhancements
to text, keyboards,
and focus-based navigation.
And finally,
we’ll give some love to buttons.
So let’s dive in,
beginning with lists and grids,
which are critical features
for organizing
and displaying data
within SwiftUI apps.
This year,
we’re making it even easier
to write rich,
interactive lists and grids.
Let’s start with a fun one.
SwiftUI now has built-in support
for loading images
asynchronously.
SwiftUI makes loading
these images feel easy
with the new AsyncImage view.
Just give it a URL,
and SwiftUI will automatically
fetch and display
the remote image for you,
and even provide
a default placeholder.
AsyncImage
can also be customized.
For example, we can add
modifiers to the loaded image
and also define
custom placeholders,
like I’m doing here
to add some fun colors.
We can even add custom
animations and error handling!
And AsyncImage is available
on all platforms.
We hope you check it out.
AsyncImage loads
its content immediately,
but sometimes your app needs
to load content on-request,
like when showing a feed.
This is a great use case
for supporting pull-to-refresh
on iOS and iPadOS,
using the new refreshable
modifier.
This modifier configures
a refresh action
and passes down
through the environment.
Lists on iOS and iPadOS
use this action
to automatically add
pull-to-refresh,
but you can also use it to build
your own custom
refresh behaviors.
You may have noticed
this new await keyword,
which is one of the new
concurrency language features
in Swift 5.5.
This indicates that
the updateItems method
is an async action,
which lets us refresh our list
without blocking the UI.
Another new concurrency-related
SwiftUI feature
is the task modifier.
This API lets you attach
an async task
to the lifetime of your view.
That means the task will kick off
when the view first loads
and automatically cancel itself
when the view is removed.
This is a great way for us
to load the first batch
of photos automatically.
These new concurrency modifiers
look simple on the surface,
but can be used to build
sophisticated async behaviors
into your app.
For example,
here I’ve set up a task
for loading the newest photos
as they become available.
I’ve written just
a regular for loop,
but you’ll notice the await
keyword used here as well.
That’s because
newestCandidates
is actually an async sequence,
which is another new concurrency
feature in Swift 5.5.
This means we’ll wait for the
newest candidate asynchronously,
iterating the loop only when
the next candidate is available.
That means we’re actually
packing a ton of functionality
into just this single modifier.
The view starts a task
that listens for candidates
asynchronously
as soon as it appears,
updating the list every time
a new candidate
becomes available and then
automatically canceling the task
when the view disappears,
all without blocking
our app’s UI.
There’s a lot more to learn
about Swift concurrency
and how to take advantage of it
in SwiftUI,
so we’ve prepared a few other
talks to dig into the details.
“Discover concurrency
in SwiftUI”
will explain
how concurrency relates
to SwiftUI’s update model
and demo some the new features
we just discussed.
And in “Swift concurrency:
Update a sample app,”
we walk you step by step through
upgrading an existing project
with async model code.
Next up, we’re giving you
new and better ways
to build interactivity
into your list content.
In this example,
I’ve written a simple list
for sharing the directions
to my super secret hideout.
This looks nice,
but the text isn’t editable.
Let’s fix that.
We can make text editable
by swapping it out
for a text field instead.
However, a text field requires
a binding to the text.
Within our list’s
content closure,
we’re only given a plain value
for each element
in our collection,
not a binding.
In situations like this,
it can be tricky to figure out
how to get a binding
to the collection element
for each row.
One common approach
is to iterate
over the indices
of the collection instead,
using a subscript to get
a binding to the element
at that index.
However, this technique
is not recommended,
because SwiftUI will be forced
to reload the entire list
when anything changes.
In fact, we’ve prepared
a whole talk
discussing this topic
in much more detail.
To learn more, I’d recommend
watching “Demystify SwiftUI.”
For now, let’s undo
these changes
and take a look
at a better solution.
This year, SwiftUI is providing
a much easier way
to get access to bindings
for individual elements
within a collection.
Simply pass a binding to
your collection into the list,
using the normal
dollar sign operator,
and SwiftUI will pass back
a binding
to each individual element
within the closure.
Code that only needs to read
the value
can stay exactly the same
as before,
just like you’re used to.
But now we can easily add
interactive controls
like a text field using
the normal binding syntax
that we’re used to,
which means I can finally fill
in the super secret door code
I forgot to include earlier.
This new syntax is part
of the Swift language,
so it works everywhere
you would expect,
not just lists.
For example, we can use
the same technique
in a ForEach view
within our list instead.
And better yet, you can even
back-deploy this code
to any prior release
supported by SwiftUI.
But we’re not just making
your existing code
easier to write.
Lists are gaining some
great new features too!
Let’s start with some new ways
to visually customize
your lists.
With the new
listRowSeparatorTint modifier,
you can change the color
of individual row separators,
like I’ve done here to align
the separator and icon colors
for each row.
SwiftUI also has an equivalent
modifier for section separators.
For this app though,
all those separators
seem a little distracting.
I want my directions to feel
like a single, unified flow.
Maybe we should try
removing them,
which we can now do
with the new listRowSeparator
modifier,
configuring our separators
to be hidden.
Now our directions feel
much less cluttered.
Let’s look at another app
I’m making...
...which helps comic book
authors keep track
of all their superheroes
and villains.
This app uses swipe actions
to quickly and conveniently
pin and delete characters,
but without cluttering up our UI
with extra controls.
New this year,
SwiftUI allows you to define
completely custom swipe actions
using the new swipeActions
modifier.
You configure swipe actions
just like any other
kind of menu in SwiftUI,
defining actions using buttons.
You can also customize
their color
by adding
the new tint modifier,
which I’m using to make
my pin action yellow.
By default, SwiftUI shows
swipe actions
on the trailing edge of the row.
But you can switch them
to the leading side
using modifier’s
edge parameter.
You can even support
both leading and trailing
swipe actions
by adding multiple modifiers
with different
edge configurations.
And lastly,
the swipeActions modifier
is available on every platform
that supports them,
making it easy to share code
within your multiplatform app.
Speaking of other platforms,
let’s check in on the macOS
version of my app.
It shows
a multicolumn interface,
which makes use
of the extra space
available on the Mac.
Instead of cramming
all of my data into the sidebar,
I have an overview tab
that lists all of my characters.
That lets me just keep
my pinned characters
in the sidebar.
This list does feel
a little plain though.
Let’s try to spruce it up a bit.
Here’s my existing code.
I’m currently using
the inset list style
to smoothly fit the list
within my window.
And we’re able to express
this style beautifully in code
using the new
enum-like syntax available
on all view styles this year.
Also new this year,
the inset list style
is gaining a new trick.
It is now able to alternate
the backgrounds of the rows
by just modifying the style
with the
alternatesRowBackgrounds flag.
Our list is looking
a lot better now,
with each row clearly
distinguished from the other.
But for a macOS app,
it still feels like
we’re not taking full advantage
of all that space in our window.
So for the next section,
let’s go beyond lists to get
even more out of your app.
To help us make better use
of all this space,
let’s upgrade our list
to a rich, multicolumn table!
With four columns,
I now get four lists
for the price of one!
But the best part is that
a moderately complex table
like this can be declared
with so little code
it fits on a single slide.
That’s because tables use
the same kind of declarative
construction that you’re used to
throughout SwiftUI.
Just like with lists,
you can create a table
from a single collection
of content.
But unlike a list, a table
is made up of TableColumns
that define content
within each visual column.
Each of these columns
are visually labeled
and use data from the collection
to define their visual content
with some shorthand conveniences
for common cases
like just displaying text.
But tables are also interactive,
supporting row selection
both for single rows
and multiple rows,
just like in regular lists.
Tables also support sorting
with the help of key paths
to sortable values
on the columns.
Now, tables support
several other features,
including multiple different
visual styles
as well as fine-tuning
the appearance of each column.
But let’s talk more about
the data you provide
to a table or list.
This year, we have several
new enhancements
to SwiftUI’s support
for CoreData fetch requests.
FetchRequests now provide
a binding
to their sort descriptors,
which we can pass on
to the Table,
allowing us to write
a fully Core Data-driven table,
complete with selection
and sortable columns,
in just a few lines of code.
SwiftUI now also offers
a sectioned fetch request,
allowing for complex,
multisection lists
like the one on the right to be
driven from a single request.
In this example, we partition
our data into sections
based on whether or not
they're pinned.
We use multiple SortDescriptors
to arrange the data,
first to split it into pinned
and unpinned sections,
and second to order
recently modified characters
last.
Next we specify that any changes
should be animated.
And finally we construct
the sections and rows
of our list dynamically,
based on the results
of the request.
All together,
this single request
is able to drive
the animated list on the right.
For more information
on building apps for macOS,
working with tables,
and integrating Core Data
with SwiftUI,
be sure to check out
these other talks.
The “SwiftUI on the Mac”
two-part series will take you
step-by-step
through building an app
that’s optimized for the Mac.
And “Bring Core Data concurrency
to Swift and SwiftUI”
will cover the new Core Data
fetch request APIs
in much more detail.
Now it’s time to step back
and think about
how we can help users
find what they need
amidst all of this data.
Of course,
I’m talking about search.
Search is a critical part
of all of our platforms.
It helps users find
what they need
exactly when they need it.
You’ll find it on large devices
like the Apple TV,
even all the way down
to the smallest devices,
like the Apple Watch.
So since search
is a multiplatform problem,
it needs
a multiplatform solution
that can scale across
all these devices.
Luckily,
adding search to your app
couldn’t be easier;
just add
the searchable modifier,
like we’ve done here
on our NavigationView.
With this one modifier,
SwiftUI will automatically add
a search field
to the appropriate location
in your app
and optionally show suggestions
in a platform- and
context-appropriate way.
The modifier takes a binding
to the search text,
allowing you to filter your data
based on the current value.
Now, there is a lot more
to say about search in SwiftUI,
but luckily we have
a whole session
to walk you through how to think
about search capabilities
on multiple platforms.
Check out “Craft search
experiences in SwiftUI”
to learn more.
So far we’ve explored
how to load, display, organize,
and search through your app’s
data using lists and grids.
Now let’s talk about
how to share that data
beyond your app.
One of the simplest methods
of sharing data
is by just dragging it
out of your app.
In my Heroes & Villains app,
I’ve configured the character
icon on the detail screen
to be draggable using
the existing onDrag modifier.
New this year,
you can now add custom previews
to your draggable views.
This preview is shown
instead of the view
while it’s being dragged.
Drag and drop is powered
by item providers,
which allow data to be copied
and shared
between different processes.
This year, SwiftUI is providing
several more ways to use
item providers
to integrate with other apps
and services
such as configuring your app
to support
importing item providers
from external services,
using the new
importsItemProviders modifier.
In this example,
we’ve configured our view
to be able to import images,
and add them as attachments
to our story characters.
We can pair this capability
a new macOS feature:
Continuity Camera.
By adding the
“Import from Devices” commands
to our app’s main menu,
we’re now able to use
an iPhone or iPad
to just take photos
to import into our Mac app.
Let’s try it out!
The symbol of the View Builder
superhero is her trusty hammer.
It would be great to attach
a picture of it to her profile.
Luckily, I happen to have it
right here!
[CLATTERING]
From within my app,
I can access
the “Import from devices”
commands in the File menu.
Then, I can choose to take
a picture using my iPhone...
....which automatically opens
the Camera app
so we can quickly
take a picture.
And the new photo is imported
and added to my app,
using the importsItemProviders
modifier we showed earlier.
SwiftUI also supports exporting
data out of our app.
Exporting data allows you
to take advantage
of other services,
such as being able
to trigger shortcuts
from directly within your app.
In SwiftUI, you can export data
using the new
exportsItemProviders modifier.
This exposes your app’s data
to the rest of the system,
for example,
allowing it to be used
by services and shortcuts
on macOS.
Let’s take a look
at how this appears
for people using the app.
I can now see quick actions
show up
in my app’s Services menu
when I’ve selected
one of my pinned characters.
This is a handy shortcut
for adding a title banner
to the most recent photo,
which I can use to share
my latest superhero ideas
with my friends.
I found this great photo to use
for my Stylizer superhero,
who happens to also be
an adorable dog.
My custom shortcut added
this fun banner to the top
and overlaid the hero’s name.
My shortcut also lets me
share the photo.
I’d love to get
Taylor’s feedback,
since he knows a thing or two
about cool graphics.
I can just add Taylor
as a recipient
and type in a quick message
and send it off!
What do you think, Taylor?
Taylor Kelly: Thank you, Matt.
It looks perfect.
And it's definitely going to be
your new contact photo.
This adorable image
is a great segue
to the next section,
Advanced Graphics.
There's a bunch of
exciting enhancements this year:
from symbol updates, materials
and vibrancy,
to a powerful new canvas view.
First up are symbols.
SF Symbols are a great
and easy way of adding
beautiful iconography
throughout your app.
Not only are there
many new ones this year,
but they come with several
new features to make
their use in your app even
easier and more expressive.
There are two
new rendering modes
that give you even more control
over how symbols are styled.
Hierarchical uses
the current foreground style
to color the symbol,
just like monochrome,
but automatically adds
multiple levels of opacity
to really emphasize
the key elements of the symbol.
And palette gives you even more
fine-grained control
over individual layers
of a symbol with custom fills.
Check out
"What's new in SF Symbols"
for more information and design
guidance on these new modes.
Pairing perfectly with these
is an update to the set
of colors available in SwiftUI.
These colors are optimized
for all the different
configurations they appear in:
light and Dark Mode,
specific appearances over blurs,
and even the specific platform
they’re shown on.
In addition to different colors,
symbols come
in many different shapes.
Many symbols have modifiers
to show up as filled,
circled, and more.
Previously you had to hardcode
these variants.
But more than that,
you had to know
which variant was right to use
in which context.
The iOS Human
Interface Guidelines
describes how in tab bars,
filled variants should be
preferred, so you had to
specifically include that .fill
modifier in the name.
This year,
you don’t have to worry that.
SwiftUI will automatically
choose the right variant for you
based on the context
you use it in.
All you have to do is provide
the base symbol
you’d like to use.
And by not over-specifying
the exact configuration
you want,
you also get code
that is more reusable.
For example, if we run
this same code on macOS,
we get the correct variant
for that platform: outlines.
To learn how to take advantage
of this automatic support
in your own custom views,
as well as more symbol
enhancements,
check out
"SF Symbols in SwiftUI."
There are now
a lot of SF Symbols,
so I wanted to build
a cool visualizer
to browse through all of them.
This is a great use
for SwiftUI's new Canvas view.
Canvas supports
immediate-mode drawing
similar to drawRect
from UIKit or AppKit.
When composing lots
of graphical elements
that don't need individual
tracking or invalidation,
this is a great tool.
Here I have a canvas displaying
every single SF Symbol
that comes with the OS.
And for all 3166 of them,
it draws each of them
into their own frame.
Canvas works on every platform.
And since Canvas
is a view like any other,
we can also attach gestures,
accessibility information,
and update it based on state
or the environment
such as adapting to Dark Mode.
Here, I've added a gesture
that lets me set a focalPoint
to zoom in on.
And I'll update the frame
and opacity of each symbol
based on that.
Now I can click and drag around
and every symbol
smoothly updates
as the cursor moves
around the screen.
We can also make sure
this is fully accessible
by taking advantage of a new
accessibilityChildren modifier.
What’s so cool is that
you reuse the same views
you're used to using in SwiftUI
to refine how it comes across
through accessibility features.
In this case, the symbols
can now be enumerated
like someone would otherwise
browse elements in a list,
speaking each element
as they navigate through.
This modifier isn’t restricted
to just Canvas,
but can be used with any view
to really polish
its accessibility experience.
One final thing we can add
to our canvas
is updating over time,
using the new TimelineView.
A refinement to make for tvOS
is to have that focalPoint
animatedly move around
the screen,
acting like a screensaver.
TimelineView is created
with a schedule --
in this case,
the animation schedule --
and it provides the current time
it's rendering for.
And so we can use that time
to update the focalPoint
in the transform,
creating our beautiful
symbol screensaver.
This TimelineView
can do so much more.
A really cool feature
of the Apple Watch
is its Always On display.
Previously your app would be
blurred with the time overlaid
when it enters
the Always On state.
And with watchOS 8 your app
now dims by default,
and you have more control
over how it appears with SwiftUI
giving you the tools you need,
one of which is TimelineView.
Once the watch goes
into its Always On state,
TimelineView can preload
the display of your views
at future dates.
And as we move into the future,
those view will automatically
be displayed onscreen
without ever taking your app
from the background.
A critical part of this
is the TimelineSchedule.
In this example, I'm using
the simple everyMinute schedule
so TimelineView will preload out
the display of each minute
on the minute,
showing me the next symbol
in the browser.
There are several other kinds
of schedules as well
to help suit
the needs of your app,
such as a collection
of explicit of dates,
which works great
for when there will be events
at specific times.
Now, another important aspect
of this mode
is hiding user-sensitive
information
since it could be visible
to others.
I'd really like to keep
my favorite symbol private.
And by simply adding
the privacySensitive modifier,
it will automatically
be redacted
when the watch enters
the Always On state.
Check out
"What's new in watchOS 8"
for more information on
the Always On display and more.
And this privacy-sensitive
modifier
also works in widgets as well.
Widgets that are added
to the Lock screen will use this
to hide sensitive information
while the device
is still locked,
and reveal once the device
is unlocked.
"Principals of great widgets"
will go into more detail on this
and other ways of building
wonderful widgets for your apps.
Materials are used across all of
Apple’s platforms and apps
to create beautiful
visual effects
that really emphasize
their content,
and now you can create them
directly in SwiftUI!
I've been experimenting
with adding color and materials
to my Symbol Browser,
and I'm adding
a material-backed overlay
to display
the number of symbols.
Adding a material is as easy
as adding a background.
I'm using
the ultraThinMaterial,
and can give it
any custom shape to fill.
These materials automatically
come with the expected
vibrant blending of content
on top of them
when using primary,
secondary, tertiary,
and now even quaternary
foreground styles.
And emojis are automatically
excluded from that,
so they look exactly
as they should.
On the Mac, system context
like sidebars and popovers
automatically have blur
material backgrounds
and will also now have that
expected vibrant appearance
for the content within them.
These new materials work great
in conjunction
with the new safeAreaInset
modifier,
which allows you
to place content
on top of a scrollable view
and have the content position
still start and end as expected.
The "rich graphics" session
goes into a lot more detail
on canvas, materials, and more.
And to wrap it up,
complementing new ways to define
these beautiful custom views
are a couple of enhancements
to SwiftUI previews in Xcode.
First is a new preview
orientation modifier
that allows you to specify
the orientation
of the iOS device
in the previews,
and even mix and match previews
across different orientations.
And second is a big improvement
to how you edit and view
your app's accessibility
in previews.
The property editor
now has a curated list
of accessibility modifiers,
making it even easier to polish
views' accessibility behavior.
And there is an entirely new way
of viewing your previews
with a new
Accessibility Preview tab.
You'll be shown a live,
textual representation
of the accessibility elements
and their properties.
This is the same information
that powers
accessibility features,
but is now presented to you
in a format
that might be more familiar
to you.
Check out the
"SwiftUI Accessibility" session
for more information on this
and much more
about how to create an amazing
accessibility experience
for your app!
Now, up next is a range
of enhancements to text,
text-related controls,
and keyboard navigation.
Text is so fundamental
to every app.
It’s one of the main ways
your app communicates to people;
it’s often the very first view
you write.
And this year, its gaining
a lot of new exciting features
from styling to localization,
to interactions and formatting.
First up is Markdown support.
Text can now contain Markdown
formatting directly inline.
This can be used to add
strong emphasis, links --
which can be interacted with --
and even code-style
presentation.
And this is all built on top
of the new, powerful
Swift-based AttributedString
in Foundation.
In addition to Markdown support,
it brings an entire suite
of rich, type-safe attributes,
and the ability to define
your own attributes
and even use them
within Markdown syntax.
For more information on this
and the amazing new
Automatic Grammar agreement,
check out
"What's new in Foundation."
Importantly, text also
localizes its content
so that people across the world
can use your app.
And this is true of the new
Markdown support as well,
allowing language-sensitive
attributes
to be properly localized.
Another great improvement
to localization
comes from Xcode 13.
It now uses the Swift compiler
to generate strings
and localization catalogs from
every use of LocalizedStringKey
and the new localizedString and
attributedString initializers.
To learn more about this
and other localization
tips and tricks,
check out
"Localize Your SwiftUI app."
Now, in addition to these
new ways of displaying text,
there are new ways of making
text even more dynamic.
The first is an important
accessibility feature:
Dynamic Type.
SwiftUI has supported
Dynamic Type
since its inception,
and this year has a new API
to allow restricting
the range of type sizes
a UI supports
to keep it from getting too big
or too small.
This shows
what our header looks like
at the default large size.
I personally use Dynamic Type
to get some extra information
density into my content,
and this shows how the header
stayed the same size
at the small type size,
since it's restricted to be,
at minimum, the large size.
At the other end
of the spectrum,
using the accessibility sizes
does result
in our header growing larger,
but only up to
the extra extra large size.
While macOS doesn't support
Dynamic Type,
it does support another
important text interaction:
selectable text.
This allows people
to take action
on noneditable text from your
app, and that can
now be enabled using
the textSelection modifier.
That modifier can be applied
to any view,
and it applies
to all the text within it --
in this example, now applying to
the text in the header.
And we also introduced
this modifier on iOS and iPadOS
where it enables text to be
copied or shared on long-press.
Finally, Foundation's
new format-style APIs
make formatting text
so much simpler,
yet still allowing
precise presentation.
Here we have a date that
applies the default formatting.
And this is a variant
that displays only the time,
as used in the activity list.
And finally, an expanded format
that allows specifying
the exact components to display.
Our activity list also featured
formatting an array of people
into a properly localized
presentation.
Let's quickly walk through this.
We're mapping our person values
into an array
of PersonNameComponents
and formatting it
using a list format style.
And for each member in the list,
using the PersonNameComponent
format with a short style,
showing just the first name.
And finally, joining it
with an "and" conjunction.
All together,
creating a performant
and type-safe expression
of formatting
that properly handles
any number of people.
TextField has also
gained support
for these new format styles,
allowing you to add editable
formatted text
with a type-safe binding
to some underlying value.
The new attendee field is bound
to a PersonNameComponents value,
and it's formatted using
the standard name format.
This takes care
of parsing the input
and producing
the resulting person name.
"What’s new in Foundation"
also goes into detail
on the power
of these new format styles.
TextField now also supports
adding an explicit prompt,
separate from its label,
to let users know what kind of
content a field is expecting.
And when adding TextField
to forms on macOS,
they’ll align their labels
similar to other controls
and use the prompt
as its placeholder content.
Now, the entire point
of a text field is adding text,
and keyboards are our tool
to do that.
From software keyboards
on iPhone to the iPad,
which supports both software
and hardware keyboards,
and of course,
macOS,
which always has
a hardware keyboard.
This year, there’s several
enhancements
to make the experience of using
a keyboard even better.
With the new onSubmit modifier,
you can easily add
supplementary actions
for when the field’s text
is submitted by the user,
such as by pressing
the Return key.
This modifier provides
some extra flexibility
in that it can even be applied
to an entire form of controls.
And to help give users a hint
of what kind of action
will occur
when submitting a field,
there's the new submitLabel
modifier.
On software keyboards,
this will be used
as the label for the Return key.
And finally, we’ve made it
possible to add accessory views
to the keyboard using the new
keyboard toolbar placement.
These views will be shown
in a toolbar
above the software keyboard
on iOS and iPadOS
or in the Touch Bar on macOS.
This is a great way
to give users quick access
to actions above the keyboard
without dismissing it
to avoid interrupting
your app’s editing experience.
Keyboards also serve
another important role
of navigation and focus,
and this functionality exists
on every platform;
from using focus on watchOS
to direct Digital Crown input,
to using the Siri Remote
to navigate around content
on tvOS.
For most things,
SwiftUI just takes care
of what views are focusable
and how it moves between them.
But sometimes there are
extra refinements you can make
to create even smoother
experiences in your app.
To help with that,
SwiftUI has a new, powerful
tool called FocusState.
This is a property wrapper
that both reflects
the state of focus
and provides precise control
over it.
At its simplest, it can reflect
a Boolean value.
This can be tied to a focusable
view using the focused modifier.
When that view is focused,
the value will be true,
and false when not.
This value can also be
written to, to control focus.
For instance, in response
to someone pressing a button.
This example can act
as an accelerator,
allowing the user
to immediately start typing
after performing
a related action.
This Boolean version is
a convenience for its full form,
which is representing
any hashable type.
This code is functionally
equivalent to the previous slide
but with some
increased flexibility.
Let's walk through it.
First, I've defined a simple
enumeration of the fields
that I might want to know
are focused.
The FocusState property
uses that type
to reflect the current state.
It's optional to indicate
potentially none of those
having focused.
Our focused modifier
is still bound
to that same focus state,
but only when it equals
addAttendee.
And finally, when we want
to focus that field,
we set our focus state value
to addAttendee.
This new flexibility allows
adding additional functionality,
such as building the toolbar
buttons from before,
moving focus
between each of the fields,
and reflecting if focus reaches
the beginning or the end.
Focus state also provides
a great way for iOS apps
to dismiss the software keyboard
by clearing out its value.
If you're interested in learning
more about other ways
to refine the focus experience
in your app,
check out this year’s session,
"Direct and reflect focus
in SwiftUI."
Last, we’re going to focus in
on buttons
because buttons are important.
We all know what
a typical button looks like;
it varies from platform
to platform,
and it is one
of the simplest ways
of allowing people
to interact with your app.
And especially in SwiftUI,
buttons are used
for a lot of things.
Matt discussed earlier
how swipe actions
are composed out of buttons.
And this year,
there is a lot new with buttons.
First, SwiftUI now has standard
bordered buttons on iOS.
You can make a button bordered
just by adding
a buttonStyle modifier,
like I'm doing
with this Add button.
Like other style modifiers,
this can be added
to a group of controls
and applies to all of them.
It supports tinting for cases
where you want a specific
appearance for a given button.
But for this UI,
I like the default appearance
that uses the accent color.
There's more customization
built in as well.
First up is control size
and prominence.
I'm using these to customize
the buttons
representing the tags.
They're using the new standard
small control size
and have a tint
with increased prominence
to really make them stand out.
We can use
these same modifiers
to create another common
kind of button:
these large sized ones
now built in to SwiftUI.
By specifying
the large control size,
you'll automatically get
these beautiful,
rounded rectangle buttons.
And to give them
a sense of hierarchy,
I modified
the most important one
to have increased prominence,
filling it with a high-contrast
accent color.
And the secondary button
can still be tinted
but has a lower contrast.
These buttons have few modifiers
to make them great
on the iPad, too.
The text labels have
a maximum width
so that the overall button
is flexible
but doesn't get comically large.
And the primary button
has a default action
keyboard shortcut,
so when using the app
with a keyboard,
I can quickly hit the Return key
to add this button to my jar.
Now, many of this API
has already existed on macOS,
making it even easier to build
apps for multiple platforms.
The one new addition is adding
increased prominent tint support
to let you tastefully
add these bright buttons
to your apps.
Note that nonprominent buttons,
like these Add buttons,
do not display any tint
since their chrome
is what indicates their
interactivity on macOS.
Having learned about prominence,
I might be tempted to go
and apply that
to all of my Add buttons,
but it can get overwhelming
and confusing
to have so many prominent
buttons onscreen.
It's best to reserve it
for singular primary actions.
The lower prominence tint
is a great alternative
for adding a splash of color
on iOS.
Now, my favorite thing
about these new button styles
is they automatically have
the expected
pressed and disabled states,
Dark Mode support,
and of course are
fully accessible and compatible
with Dynamic Type.
And they help give consistency
between apps.
And buttons' new API
doesn't stop here.
SwiftUI has also added
first-class support for buttons
with additional semantics,
such as marking a button
as destructive,
which will automatically
give them the expected red tint.
One new context
this can also be used in
are confirmation dialogs,
which lets users
confirm actions that have
serious impact to their data.
On iOS, this shows
as an action sheet,
on iPad as a popover,
and on macOS as an alert.
SwiftUI automatically handles
following the design
sensibilities of each platform.
Next, let's talk about buttons
that aren't "capital B" buttons.
Currently, the app's Add buttons
just add to the user's
default jar.
But for avid collectors,
I want to support adding
to specific jars.
This is a perfect use case
for a menu button.
We'll use the same "Add" label,
but present a menu
of all of the possible jars
once the button is clicked.
However, these menu buttons
visually carry
a lot of prominence.
We could hide the indicators
using a new menuIndicator
modifier added this year.
And even without an indicator,
this button still presents
a menu on click.
But for these buttons,
ideally we'd get
the best of both worlds:
with a simple single click
to add to the default jar
and the flexibility of showing
the menu of others.
New this year is the ability
to customize
a menu's primary action
to help with this kind of case.
By default, a menu
with a primary action
has a two-segmented appearance
on macOS.
The main part of the button
triggers the primary action
in the indicator
presenting the menu.
And when the indicator
is hidden,
it again looks visually
just like the button
that I started with but has
a behavioral distinction.
A click triggers
the primary action
and a long-press shows the menu.
And what's great is that this
same thing works on iOS, too!
Now these menus
give a lot of flexibility,
really catering to how your app
needs to use them.
Another new example of a control
gaining a button style
is Toggle.
This creates a button
that when tapped,
visually turns on and off
and can be used just like
any other toggle.
And joining these new
control styles
is a container that groups
related controls;
aptly called ControlGroup.
On iOS, the controls in a group
are organized a little tighter
in the toolbar.
And on macOS,
there are visual affordances
indicating the two grouped
buttons.
And to wrap this all up,
naturally all of these things
can be composed together.
For instance, these standard
back/forward buttons
are a ControlGroup
of two menus.
Each of these menus have
a primaryAction
that is performed when clicked.
And once the menu
is long-pressed,
they'll present their contents.
Now, with just a few additional
customizations on buttons
and these new styles,
a lot of flexibility
has opened up
on how you can use
these controls in your apps.
We ran through a lot
in this session,
and there’s even more that
we didn’t have time to cover.
We’re excited for you to take
advantage of these new features
in your own SwiftUI apps
and adopt SwiftUI
in even more places.
Thank you and have
a great rest of your 2021!
♪