[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Han Ming Ong: Hello,
my name is Han Ming Ong.
I'm an engineer
in the Xcode Debugger UI team.
Today, I want to talk
about the improvements
the team has made to breakpoints
that will make your debugging
more productive.
Let’s start with
some breakpoint basics
to get everyone
on the same page.
When you encounter
a bug in your program,
it means it is not executing
to your expectation,
and you want to check
with the debugger
why reality has diverged.
At this point, there are two
common activities that you do.
One, you inspect
the process state
to further understand
the situation.
Two, you ascertain your logic
by stepping through
the process execution.
Both activities require you
to pause,
ideally just before
the bug happens.
And the best way to pause the
process is to use a breakpoint.
We're going to talk
about three common breakpoints
that you can create in Xcode.
The first is
source file breakpoints.
These are breakpoints
that are set in a single file.
The most common type
is the line breakpoint.
It is the workhorse
of breakpoints
and is excellent for pausing
on a line of code
you want to inspect.
The fastest way to create one
is simply to click
in the gutter,
right next to the line
you want to pause.
Suppose at this point,
I would like to check the logic
of function convertedToVolume
by stepping into it.
But when I step in,
I'm actually stepping
into a different expression.
The compiler has
rightly determined
that adjustedDensity
needs be executed first.
Of course, I can step out
and then step back
into the function,
but this can get laborious
when you have
to repeat it many times.
What we are seeing here is
that sometimes a line breakpoint
is not granular enough.
That's because
the compiler has generated
more than one location
for LLDB to stop at.
What we really want is to pause
just before convertedToVolume
is executed.
In Xcode 13, we are introducing
column breakpoints.
This allows you to avoid the
shortcomings of line breakpoints
when you need to pause
at certain expressions
along a line.
To set a column breakpoint
on convertedToVolume,
you Command-click
on the expression
to bring up the Actions popover
and then select
Set Column Breakpoint.
Just like with
a line breakpoint,
you can click on the icon
to disable or enable.
You can double-click on it
to bring up
the breakpoint editor
if you need to modify
the breakpoint.
Since we don’t need
the line breakpoint anymore,
we can delete it by dragging
away from the gutter.
You can do the same thing
to our column breakpoint,
but I'm just going
to leave it there.
Control or right mouse-click
brings up the contextual menu
which includes
our previous action.
Here I'm going to select
Reveal in Breakpoint Navigator
The subtitle has been amended
to show you the column
of the breakpoint.
When we continue,
we'll iterate through
the next NutritionFact
and hit our newly set
column breakpoint.
When the breakpoint hits,
Xcode uses the line PC
to tell you the paused line.
It draws a light green
highlight over the line.
In Xcode 11.4,
we introduced column PC.
The column PC shows you
the paused column
by drawing a green underscore
under an expression.
So it lets you know
the expression
the debugger is going
to execute next.
Since I'm seeing the column PC
under convertedToVolume,
I can confidently do a one-step
into the function.
Column breakpoints
are particularly useful
for closures in Swift
or blocks in Objective-C.
Sometimes a single Swift line
can have multiple closures,
just like this single line 269.
When a compiler compiles a file
under debug condition,
it creates a map called
a line table
that maps source lines and
columns to compiled addresses.
So for each closure
on this line,
the compiler generates
a line table entry
that the debugger
will use to pause.
Suppose I want to inspect
the anonymous parameter $0
of the last closure,
I can set a line breakpoint
at 269 but after pausing,
to reach the last closure,
I need to do numerous
step-in and step-out
due to the generated
line table entries.
We have seen that with Xcode 13,
we can simply set a column
breakpoint at the last $0
and when paused, we are exactly
where we want to be
and we can inspect $0
to our heart's content.
Hmm, looks having
Fragrant Durian Smoothie --
for breakfast no less --
is a great way to start the day.
Yummy!
Let's move on
to symbolic breakpoints.
These are breakpoints
on function names
that will pause the process when
those functions are executed.
They are very helpful
in situations
where source file breakpoints
cannot be used
or are inconvenient.
For instance, you don’t have
access to the source files
and hence, you can't compile
them with debug info.
Or you have many subclasses that
implement a common function,
and it is cumbersome to set a
file breakpoint in each of them.
Let’s take a look.
We will click on the Add button
at the bottom
of the breakpoint navigator.
This brings up a list
of breakpoints we can create.
We will select
Symbolic Breakpoint
and immediately
the breakpoint editor appears
so that we can enter
the symbol name.
Suppose we are interested in
pausing in the toggle function
that is implemented
in a few classes.
Instead of looking
for each of them,
we can just enter
toggle here.
[KEYSTROKES]
But you need to be careful
about function names
that are common words.
This is because LLDB will match
the name in all the libraries
that are loaded in the process,
including the system libraries.
If unrestricted,
there can be many resolved
breakpoint locations,
sometimes even in the thousands.
This can be annoying if many
of them are constantly hit
by the execution path.
Thankfully, we can restrict the
search to a particular module.
A module is a binary or image
that can be loaded
during execution,
including the main binary.
Here we enter "Fruta,"
which is the binary name
of our app.
And we get three
resolved locations,
which is a lot more manageable.
Since we have selected
a smoothie,
let’s toggle
the favorite button.
We will hit
our symbolic breakpoint
that was just set.
Now, for symbolic breakpoints,
you know it is fairly easy
to make a typographic error.
And then during
program execution,
the breakpoint doesn't hit
and you are left
scratching your head.
Let’s try to create one
called convertToMass.
New in Xcode 13,
if a breakpoint is not resolved
to any location by LLDB,
Xcode will show you
a dashed icon.
There is a myriad of reasons
why a breakpoint is not resolved
but there are some
common explanations.
If you hover over
the unresolved breakpoint icon,
we have a tooltip
that can help you out.
The first couple of reasons
pertain to the kind
of breakpoint.
So for a symbolic breakpoint,
the name has to be
spelled correctly
and the symbol has to exist
in its library.
The next reason is more generic:
the library for the breakpoint
must be loaded.
Sometimes, the library
is only loaded
after you have done
some user action,
like clicking on a button,
and at that point,
LLDB will automatically resolve
the breakpoint for you.
In this case,
I suspect I have a bad spelling.
Let’s figure it out.
One way is to use
the find navigator
and search for "convert."
As you can see,
there are quite a few results
and it will take some time
to analyze them visually.
Instead, let’s use
a different trick through LLDB.
In Xcode console,
we type `image` —
which also means module —
`lookup -r` for regex,
`n` for name, `convert`
[KEYSTROKES]
and we supply the module name,
Fruta to restrict the search.
You can see we only have
four matches
and have certainly misspelled
the function name.
It should be "convertedToMass."
Let’s copy and paste it
into our breakpoint editor.
And this time, LLDB has
resolved it successfully
and given us
location number one.
If you are interested
in other LLDB tips and tricks,
please watch
our previous presentation,
"LLDB: Beyond 'po'."
Let’s bring up a different file.
Unresolved breakpoints
can also be seen
in source file breakpoints.
There are two reasons
that pertain to them.
First,
the line for the breakpoint
must be compiled.
In this case, line 23
was not compiled
because it's in the else part
of the compiler condition.
Also, the compiler must have
generated debug info
for the module.
If not, you need to check
your build settings.
Next is runtime issue
breakpoints.
A runtime issue is an issue
that occurs at runtime —
for example, changing a UI
state in a background thread.
It is not as serious as a crash,
and by default, Xcode
doesn't pause your process,
because it can be too disruptive
when you are focusing
on a different bug.
Instead, when a runtime
issue occurs,
Xcode records the backtrace
and presents it
in the Issue navigator.
But because the issue
happened in the past,
there's no point in inspecting
the current process state.
So sometimes, you do want
to catch it when it happens.
Having a runtime issue
breakpoint
allows you to pause
in the debugger
and poke at the process
there and then.
There are different types
of runtime issue breakpoints.
You can easily select a specific
type by using the type popup.
Bear in mind
that for some of them,
you need to enable
the corresponding feature
in the diagnostics tab
of the scheme editor.
You can go there by simply
clicking on the Go To button.
Since we want to make use
of the main thread checker
runtime issue breakpoint,
we want to enable
Main Thread Checker.
I hope that my session has
shown you the improvements
we have made to breakpoints
in Xcode 13.
Breakpoints can greatly enhance
your debugging prowess
and should definitely
be part of your repertoire.
Thank you and enjoy
the rest of WWDC.
♪