[Tim] Accessibility is more
about including all people
because everyone
has a different way
of accessing the world.
[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[soft acoustic music]
[Ed] In 2009,
I lost my eyesight
and became suddenly
and instantaneously interested
in accessibility.
Since I first started at Avid,
we were trying
to improve accessibility
into our products and services.
[Tim] I was born deaf.
I’ve been deaf my whole life.
My world experience,
my lived experience
has been deaf all the way.
So my world is visual.
There’s no audio in my life.
The way that influences my work
is that it forces me
to look at how apps run
and consider the experience
of running them without audio.
[Saqib] I’m blind,
and, day-to-day,
I develop code
just like anyone else would,
using the same tools
plus a screen reader.
[screen reader
speaking indistinctly]
[Saqib] Each day I’m motivated
by the power of technology
to improve people’s lives,
and for people
with disabilities,
you can really close the gap
between what someone
is capable of doing
and what
their current environment
and situation allows them to do.
[Ed] When you’re developing
and driving accessibility
into products,
attention to accessibility
has more impact and reach
than any of us can imagine.
[Saqib] And with
a billion people in the world
with some form of disability,
it’s not a niche audience.
[Ed] And you want them all
to walk up to the app
and use it the same way.
You don’t want the blind version
of Pro Tools
for these other guys.
You want to have one
universally accessible version
of the tool that everyone
can walk up and use.
[Tim] The biggest misconception
that people have
about making apps accessible
is thinking
that it’s a lot of work
and it’s really difficult,
but it’s not.
[Saqib] Yeah,
I remember once there was
an app that was
completely inaccessible
because there weren’t labels
on any of the graphical buttons.
And I got in touch
with the developer,
and I pointed them
to some resources
and explained
why this was a problem.
And with, you know,
just a day’s work,
he was able to add those labels,
and the app
became mostly accessible.
[Ed] It’s a long-term investment
in good design
for usability and accessibility.
Takes a lot of input
from all over the company
and from external beta testers.
[Saqib] It’s really important
to have your teams
be reflective
of all the different types
of people in the world
because if you have
that diversity on your team,
you’re going
to solve problems in better ways
and create better products.
[Tim] One thing
I’d like to emphasize
is that the tools themselves
need to be accessible.
I can give you an example.
I received a bug report
regarding a problem
with the VoiceOver feature
on our app.
It happened to be the first bug
assigned to me on this job,
and I wondered for a moment--
how can I test this
if I can’t hear it?
So I checked the settings
on the phone
and found that VoiceOver
provides a caption bar.
[VoiceOver]
Tweets and replies, Button.
Media, Button.
Likes, Button.
[Tim] My point is that someone
at Apple
recognized this
and made a decision
to add that caption bar,
which allows me
to do my work, and, in turn,
improve the experience
for more people.
[Saqib] The Seeing AI project,
in many ways,
was born
out of that personal need.
It describes
the world around you
including reading text
and identifying people
and objects around you.
[Seeing AI app audio]
Chair, laptop, table.
Plant, cup, chair, chair, plant.
[Saqib] Early on we realized
that we needed to provide
more audio guidance
on how to point the camera,
and so, one of our team members
came up with the idea,
when scanning a barcode,
to use a kid’s game
of “hot or cold”
so that the beeps
get faster the closer you are.
[phone beeping]
[Seeing AI app audio]
Processing.
Smucker’s
seedless blackberry jam.
[Tim] Back when I was
taking cabs
from wherever I was
to return home,
I’d use the Notes app
to communicate to the driver,
but the text was so tiny,
and the drivers
had a hard time reading it,
and I thought,
"I really need something
that can enlarge the text
and make it easy to read
and speed up our communication."
So I developed an app
called Cardzilla.
[Ed] The thing that makes me
excited is people
using our tools
that have disabilities
but they’re using them
with the same facility
and energy and proficiency
as sighted people.
[Jason Dasent]
So, let’s make some music!
Okay, so here we have the interface.
[energetic drumbeat]
[Saqib] A really nice note
we received is from a father
who took his son to the zoo,
and they were having a nice day,
but the father said
it really became magical
when he could use Seeing AI
to read the signs,
and therefore he was listening
to information
about the orangutans,
and now he could tell
his son about that,
and they could share
that experience together.
Or from parents
who used it to recognize
their children’s
handwritten homework.
And I love this.
It’s one of
the most favorite parts
of my job
is hearing from users.
[Tim] We had a family gathering,
and my grandmother was there.
I had just finished developing
the app at the time
and I showed it to her,
and she was
really excited about it.
She said, "Finally,
I can really talk to you."
She could just hit
the dictate button and speak,
and we could have
an interactive conversation.
[Ed] By making tools
more accessible,
developers are making the world
a more inclusive
and loving place.
[upbeat music]