[music]
[Thalia]
Hello, my name is Thalia,
and I’m a designer
on the Apple Design Team.
Today we will learn
what's new in SF Symbols.
The value of symbols
as one of the elements
of user interface design
cannot be overstated.
They are the simplest form of
communication
between the user and a product
and serve as little pieces
of a puzzle
that aid in usability
and intuitive navigation.
They also make interfaces
faster to use,
helping us navigate quickly,
as most symbols
are language-independent.
They can help
communicate content
or help trigger
a specific action,
and many times,
symbols help solve quite a few
complex or abstract concepts.
SF Symbols
brings this all together
in a library of iconography
designed to integrate seamlessly
with all the San Francisco
font families,
providing a powerful
and flexible designs resource
for creating experiences
on all Apple platforms.
Today, we are going
to have a quick recap
of the SF Symbols basics.
The repertoire keeps growing,
so we will take a look at some
of the new symbols additions.
We have expanded
the localized symbols
by increasing
the script coverage.
We will look at those
in localization.
We will study
the anatomy of a symbol
and learn how its structure
makes color possible.
We will discover the benefits
of adding colors to symbols
in rendering modes.
And finally,
we got some exciting updates
to the SF Symbols app
and the color library,
so let’s get started.
Each symbol comes
in a wide range of weights
that automatically align
with text labels.
In iOS,
SF Symbols supports Dynamic Type
and the Bold Text
accessibility feature.
SF Symbols are also available
in three scales:
small, medium, and large.
These scales maintain
the same point size,
changing only their scales,
with stroke thicknesses
that are optically adjusted
and weight-matched
with the text.
You also need to be aware
of two different alignments.
First is the vertical alignment.
Symbols are automatically
vertically centered
to San Francisco's cap-height
in all the different scales
and weights.
And as you may know,
some symbols
have negative margins.
These margins are there to aid
with horizontal alignments.
That is the case
for most variants with badges,
for example.
When displayed in the UIs,
symbols will be
horizontally centered,
giving a consistent look,
especially when displaying
similar symbol variants.
If you want to learn more about
all the features in SF Symbols,
last year’s session from WWDC20
will get you up to speed.
Now let's talk
about symbol variants.
A symbol is defined
as a representation
of a symbolic value
that is used for the purpose
of communication.
For example, the word "love"
is represented by a heart.
In UIs, a symbol
is part of a visual system
that conveys meaning.
To enrich
this communication system,
a symbol
with the same representation
can come
in many different forms.
In SF Symbols, the default,
or universal variant,
is the outlined version
of a symbol
as it relates to the typography
in the way that we can imagine
the same tool
drawing the symbol and the text.
In the absence of context,
outlined is the default.
And when we want to make
a symbol more prominent,
like when we want it
to have more surface area
to saturate with color
for the purpose of selection,
the filled variant
is a great choice.
In SF Symbols,
a symbol may come
in many different forms.
We have outlined
and filled variants.
We also have slash variants,
which are used to convey
the functions of removing
or displaying an item
as inactive or unavailable.
We have enclosing variants
that are contained
inside a shape
like a circle,
square, or rectangle.
All these variants
help make the UIs richer
and give more flexibility
when setting up
visual hierarchies
with the interface elements
and the content.
A clear visual system
will go to great lengths
in reducing
the appearance of complexity,
even when the actions themselves
are complex.
Consequently,
knowing where to use
a symbol variant is essential.
A filled symbol in swipe actions
and iOS tab bars
give a consistent appearance
and level of emphasis,
giving better control in areas
that indicate selection
when defined
with an accent color.
A symbol inside a circle
with a filled variant
provides better legibility
at small sizes.
And an outlined,
or default variant, of a symbol
is great for Toolbars,
Navigation Bars, Lists
and other places in the UI
where symbols
are presented alongside text
or where symbols need to display
a uniform appearance.
When designing your own symbols,
remember to be consistent
and define a system
that meets the user's needs.
In this way,
you will help perceive
visual metaphors
that are directly related
to the actions
that the symbols initiate
or the content
the symbols represent.
As symbols become available
on all platforms,
the SF Symbols library
keeps growing,
with nearly 600 new symbols
available this year.
We have expanded
the Apple products and devices.
And we have new additions
for video game controllers.
We have
some health-related symbols,
with plenty of new symbols
to represent communication.
And new inset symbols
that are helpful for designs
related to interface layout
and window management.
We also designed
some symbols for watchOS.
And we have many
new objects to choose from,
making SF Symbols a library
with more than 3,000 symbols
to choose from.
Now let's talk
about localization.
At Apple,
we seek to make interfaces
more inclusive and tailored
for international
and multicultural audiences.
This year, we have expanded
the SF Symbols script coverage
with new symbols for Arabic,
Hebrew,
and Devanagari,
and included designs for Thai,
Chinese,
Japanese,
and Korean.
We made it easy
by making
all these localized symbols
and script variants
adapt automatically
based on
the user's device language,
including
right-to-left writing systems.
If you are designing
for left-to-right
and right-to-left
writing systems,
consider the directionality
and overall look
of both localized variants
and be aware that in some cases,
some symbols will not
have the intended look
when mirrored.
In this case,
a new design tailored
to the specific script's needs
will be needed,
like in this example.
If you want to learn more
about designing
for right-to-left
writing systems,
check out
the Human Interface Guidelines.
Now let's study
the anatomy of a symbol.
Every symbol
starts with a vector point.
From there, we can draw
two types of segments:
straight lines and curves,
also known
as Bézier control points.
We define
the design source of a symbol
by drawing a path
as a completely enclosed shape.
Then we get to expand
the stylistic range
by drawing additional sources
and making sure
that the design sources
are point compatible;
that is, each source
has the same number
of vector points.
Next, we interpolate
the design sources,
creating instances that give us
the different weights
and scales.
So as you can see,
drawing with closed paths
is really important
in order to achieve
consistent shapes,
which allow us to have
a lot of flexibility
when creating a symbol.
If you want to learn more
about interpolation
and drawing symbols,
check out this year's session
"Create Custom Symbols."
If you have ever drawn paths
with a pen tool,
you might be familiar
with strokes.
Usually, that is the way
to give thickness to a path,
but for SF Symbols,
we do it a bit differently.
If you look at it closely,
a stroke
is a given thickness value
assigned to precisely
follow a path.
Although a stroke
can have any thickness,
it typically uses
the path as its center.
That means that
the actual vector points
that will define
the thickness of the stroke
are not reliable
for interpolation,
as the strokes
have no vector points
on their borders.
To ensure
that the drawings are reliable,
to facilitate interpolation
and better control the shapes,
the strokes
must be converted to outlines,
which can be achieved
with most vector graphic editors
and design tools.
Now that we know
how SF Symbols are drawn,
let's look at their structure
and shapes.
As you may have noticed,
some symbols combine
two or more objects,
like the share symbol,
which is a combination
of an arrow and a square.
When those objects are combined,
we can emphasize one shape
while de-emphasizing the other.
That way,
we can define design strategies
with badges and overlaps.
We can determine the foreground
and background elements
in just one symbol
and even
create different variants
with its different
container shapes.
There is a lot of versatility.
We can even highlight screens.
And this is all done
with what we call annotations.
We group
the enclosed vectors of a path
like layers inside a symbol.
That way,
we can quickly identify
a primary, secondary,
and even tertiary layer
of a symbol structure,
creating a hierarchy.
So imagine
all the possibilities.
Symbols are getting ready
to be displayed
in all their glory,
but not before we talk
about rendering modes.
Colors can speak in ways
that are as powerful
as language,
plus it is more than just
an aesthetic element,
as it can affect thinking,
help change actions,
and create reactions.
As a form of communication,
color is compelling.
And as you can see,
SF Symbols
become highly versatile
when color is applied to them
making them
an even more powerful tool.
When color is present,
the symbols become
one of the most essential
methods of engaging the user,
helping you create a statement
or draw attention.
This year,
we are happy to announce
that we have new rendering modes
to choose from:
Hierarchical and Palette,
in addition to Multicolor
and Monochrome.
First let's look
at Hierarchical.
Hierarchical rendering mode
uses a single color
with varying opacities
that add
visual hierarchy to a symbol,
creating depth and emphasis
while allowing a single hue
to drive the overall aesthetic.
When multiple symbols
that share common shapes
are presented
alongside one another,
this rendering mode
emphasizes the differences
between them,
intending to make the symbols
more legible and recognizable.
It also attempts to reduce
redundant visual noise
by modulating the opacity
without removing
the essential elements
of the symbol.
We achieve this
by annotating the symbols
with the desired hierarchy,
considering
the primary, secondary,
and in some cases,
the tertiary element
of a symbol.
When a base color
is applied to a symbol,
it is automatically applied
to all the layers
in the hierarchy,
using different opacities
to emphasize
the key characteristics
of the symbol.
Let's analyze
these symbols again,
now with
the Hierarchical rendering mode.
Some symbols
have all the hierarchy levels.
This symbol
with a cloud, sun, and rain
is a good example,
but one important thing to know
is that most symbols
don't have
all these three levels.
This is due to the nature
of their designs.
Let's focus on these symbols.
Shapes that don't touch
or have a gap between the first
and second element of a symbol
are considered secondary,
while shapes that do touch
and are encapsulated
inside one another,
like the filled circle
or the screens
shown in these examples,
become tertiary.
With Hierarchical
rendering mode,
we can achieve
more robust interfaces
with just the emphasis
on hierarchy and color.
We saw what we could do
with Hierarchical.
Now with Palette,
we have even more possibilities.
As we learned,
the Hierarchical rendering mode
uses a single color.
In contrast,
Palette rendering mode
gives the possibility to use
two or more contrasting colors,
each of which
can be controlled independently,
giving elements of a symbol
more prominence,
emphasis, and versatility
when color is applied to them.
Additionally,
Palette rendering mode
has opacity controls
that give us
even more possibilities,
allowing for symbols
to be customized
to better integrate
with the UI's overall look.
This rendering mode
relies on the same layer
annotation data
as Hierarchical.
If only two colors
are applied to it,
the tertiary layer group
replicates
the secondary layer annotation,
so remember this
when annotating
your own symbols.
In Palette rendering mode,
a set of symbols can have
the same defined color palette
applied to them,
helping the user
identify a group of symbols
with the same level
of functionalities.
In contrast,
a similar set of symbols
can each use unique colors
to define
a particular functionality,
reinforcing the actions
of the symbol
and making them more distinct
between one another.
With Palette rendering mode,
you can bring contrast
and versatility to your symbols.
Now let's talk about Multicolor.
Multicolor is a rendering mode
that represents
the intrinsic
or native color of a symbol.
That means it uses
a multitude of different colors
that relate
to the appearance of an object
in the physical world,
or it conveys meaning
between a concept
and an assigned color,
like in this example.
The concept Add
is linked to the color Green,
and the concept Remove
is linked to the color Red.
Many symbols feature
this intrinsic color palette
which is
what's rendered by default.
When customized,
each color can be assigned
an arbitrary one.
With Multicolor symbols,
you can emphasize
the symbol's identity,
creating a stronger
color narrative
that associates
with the symbols' forms.
There are a few ways
in which Multicolor
can affect a symbol.
A symbol can be fully colored.
A symbol
can be partially colored,
which means
that part of a symbol
will have
the Multicolor feature,
while the other will rely
on an accent color.
And finally,
if a symbol does not contain
any Multicolor information,
it will render in Monochrome.
This year, we are introducing
several new symbols
with Multicolor functionality.
The range of colors
from which this draws
is limitless.
And lastly, we have Monochrome.
Monochrome is the rendering mode
that most closely reflects
the typographic nature
of SF Symbols.
Color-wise, it is neutral
as it accommodates for symbols
to commingle with one another
without emphasizing
one over the other.
Monochrome also benefits
from color and opacity controls,
but the difference
with other rendering modes
is that in Monochrome,
the opacity is applied
to all the symbol
without making use
of the layer annotation data.
When uniformity
is of first importance,
Monochrome is ideal,
as it is the most unified
and consistent rendering mode.
Next let's talk about
the SF Symbols app.
This year,
we have made significant changes
to the SF Symbols app.
As we have seen,
we have all the new and improved
rendering modes:
Monochrome,
Hierarchical,
Palette,
and Multicolor.
To access all these colors
for the rendering modes,
we have the color picker.
Here you can choose
from the existing color library,
select the system accent color,
or even define your own
custom colors,
and indeed, all colors shown
in the SF Symbols app
are all available
on all platforms.
We also have some updates
to the color library
in light,
dark,
and increased contrast
appearances
with some colors adapting
depending on the platform.
As a result,
some platforms
will get new colors
that were
previously only available
on other platforms.
For example, Brown--
previously
only available on macOS--
is now available
on all platforms.
We also re-defined Teal
with a greener hue
to reflect
its visual representation
more accurately.
Cyan is a new color name
that will use
the previous Teal color values.
If you were
previously using Teal,
you will need to switch
to the color Cyan
to maintain
the legacy appearance.
Additionally, Indigo and Purple
are available on all platforms
with more consistent
hue definitions.
From rendering mode selection
to color customization,
SF Symbols
is an extremely powerful tool
to use when implementing symbols
in your UIs.
If you want to learn more
about the SF Symbols App,
check out this year's session
"Explore the SF Symbols 3 App."
So, let's recap
what we'e covered.
We have a new version of the app
that is now
available for download.
We have hundreds of new symbols.
You can find
the new beta version
of the SF Symbols app in
developer.apple.com/sf-symbols.
We talked about variants,
and we had a quick recap
of the SF Symbols basics.
We have new script coverage
for localized symbols
and new symbols adapting to
right-to-left writing systems.
We learned about
the anatomy of a symbol
and how drawing
with vector points and paths
can make
layer annotation possible.
We talked about color
with some awesome
new rendering modes:
Hierarchical and Palette.
And we reviewed more in-depth
the Multicolor
and Monochrome modes
with all their amazing features.
Remember that
all rendering modes
adapt dynamically
with Apple platform
system colors.
These automatically
adjust the vibrancy,
accessibility settings,
and appearance modes.
These rendering modes
work with custom colors as well.
And we saw
the new SF Symbols app
and learned about
all the color library updates.
This year,
SF Symbols
becomes more powerful,
flexible, and configurable,
tailored to suit your needs.
One symbol in nine weights
with three scales each
in four rendering modes.
That is amazing.
I hope you enjoyed
learning about
what's new in SF Symbols.
We can't wait to see
what you will do.
[music]