[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Johannes] Hi.
I’m Johannes Fortmann from
the Cloud File Providers team,
and I’m here to show you
file providers on macOS.
If you’re a cloud storage vendor
syncing your users’ files
to macOS,
you’re in the right talk.
After the introduction,
we’re going to talk about
some of the user flows
involved with syncing files.
We’ll then run through
one of the flows in Xcode
and discuss the order
in which you will implement
support for each of them.
We’ll have a quick overview
of additional optional
integration points
and your next steps.
First off, let’s talk about what
file providers can do for you.
The File Provider framework
allows you to integrate
your cloud storage
into the file system on macOS.
It uses new
APFS features to allow
on-demand downloads
of user files and folders.
The API is
entirely in user space.
We’re deprecating kernel
extensions on macOS,
so this is a good alternative
for you
if you were relying on FUSE
or KAUTH
to intercept syscalls
or download files on demand.
All you have to do
is handle uploads,
downloads, and tell us
what changed remotely.
The system will tell you
what changed locally
and handle all the rest.
All of this functionality
is well integrated
with the system
and in particular in Finder.
Your provider will
show up in the sidebar.
File status will be shown
and tracked in Finder,
and there are several
customizable integration points
with the UI.
You implement an app extension
that integrates with the system.
Its life cycle is driven
by user actions.
Initially, you create
a domain which represents
the file tree that the user can
access in your cloud storage.
The system will
expose that domain
in the Finder sidebar
and create a root directory
for the domain
in the file system.
At this point,
no actual data is on the device,
but the user can already
start interacting with the root.
How does this work?
The root is what we call
a dataless directory.
It’s a new kind
of object in APFS,
and there are APIs to recognize
them and interact with them.
But more importantly,
dataless objects are
fully transparent to processes
who happen upon them unprepared.
Reads trigger downloads,
and files lose
their dataless property
before the reads are
allowed to resume.
In this presentation,
we will see how the File Provider
framework allows you
to implement callbacks
that get called when processes
read dataless files.
Let’s have a look
at some user flows
to get sync up and running.
We’re going to look
at four key flows that cover
both sync down and sync up.
In each flow,
you’ll see that the system
calls your extension
whenever it needs new data.
We’ll show you that you can
talk to your cloud server
to pull that data and, finally,
call a completion handler
to reply.
First, we’re going to look
at what happens
when a dataless file is read.
When the kernel detects
a read access
to a dataless file,
that syscall is paused
while your extension is called
to fetch the contents
of the file.
Your extension’s
fetchContents method is called.
Typically, you will implement it
to perform a download.
When the download completes,
it calls a completion handler.
The contents
of the file are handed
to the system which fills in
the formerly dataless file
without invalidating
the open file descriptor.
The system then unpauses
the read access.
Now that the file
is no longer dataless,
subsequent reads won’t
have to involve your extension.
Enumerating a directory
works very similarly.
The kernel detects
a readdir call and pauses it.
It calls
your extension to enumerate
the items in that directory.
You fetch the metadata for these
items from your server.
And you reply
with a number of items.
The enumeration is paginated.
You can return less
than the full set of items,
and the system will
pick up enumerating
from where it left off.
Once all pages
have been enumerated,
the system will allow
the original call to go through.
Like in the file case,
once the directory
has been enumerated,
subsequent readdir calls
will use the contents
from disk and not have
to involve your extension.
But what if those contents
change remotely?
Well, you will have to inform
the system of the remote change.
Let’s look at how that works.
If there’s a remote change,
your server can send
a push notification to the Mac.
In response
to that push notification,
you signal the system
that there are changes
that need to be enumerated
from a special enumerator,
the .workingSet.
The system will turn around
and enumerate
the items that have changed
in the .workingSet.
A continuation token
called the syncAnchor
is used to enumerate
only the new changes.
This token is defined
by your extension.
The system keeps track
of the syncAnchor
it last enumerated to.
It will call your enumerator
with the enumerateChanges(from
syncAnchor:) method.
In response,
you return changed items,
and once you’re done,
give us a new syncAnchor
that we can
use next time around.
The system
will asynchronously go
and update
the user-visible files.
We use an APFS
compare-and-swap feature
which makes sure
that local changes aren’t lost
in the process.
Furthermore,
the system integrates
with file coordination
and other advisory
locking mechanisms
to coordinate with applications.
With these three mechanisms,
we are able to sync files
from the cloud
and keep them in sync
in case of remote changes.
The last flow deals with syncing
up local changes to the cloud.
The system detects
when local items have changed
and calls a modifyItem method
on your extension,
passing in the exact set
of fields that have changed.
It aggregates low-level events
into events
that are meaningful for sync.
For example, the kernel detects
safe saves and remaps
your item identifiers to the new
file IDs transparently.
The system will also zip package
files for you if you request
and present you with consistent
package-level changes.
In response
to the modifyItem call,
you will update the state
of the item server-side.
If the contents
of the file have changed,
the system will hand you a clone
of the changed file so you can
upload a consistent version even
in the event of further changes.
When done,
you call a completion handler.
The completion handler is used
to update the version identifier
of the item
and confirms delivery
of the change to your extension.
The completion handler
also takes the final state
of the item as a parameter.
Updating an item in the cloud
may change its state,
for example, if it conflicts
with a remote change.
Since you pass
the final state back,
the system is able
to update the local state
of the item to match
the truth in the cloud.
There is a fifth flow: eviction.
The system will evict
local files automatically
and without involving
your file provider extension
when there is an urgent need
for disk space.
That might happen, for example,
when the user is
recording a video
or downloading
a software update.
The system will evict
the minimum set
of least recently used files
necessary to free up
the disk space required
to write those new files.
Let’s review the transitions.
Eviction turns a local file
into a dataless file,
and download turns a dataless
file into a local file.
Files can start dataless
if they are created remotely
or not
if they are created locally.
But not all files
can be evicted.
The system will only
evict a file
that you report as uploaded
so that it can be
downloaded again.
So there really are
two sorts of local files:
uploaded and non-uploaded files.
After a local edit,
the new version of the file
needs to be uploaded, so we’re
back in a non-evictable state.
In this presentation so far,
we have seen how your file
provider extension is invoked
by the system to download files
upon access
and to upload files
after local edits.
While you’re not involved
in disk-pressure
triggered eviction,
there are methods to trigger
or prevent eviction
from your extension.
This was a lot of theory.
Let’s have a look at one
of the flows in practice.
We’ve written an app that runs
a small local file server
and embeds
a file provider extension
that operates
against that server.
It’s called FruitBasket.
I’ve already logged in
to that server,
so there’s an entry for the root
folder here in the sidebar.
I’ve also selected the root
folder which caused the system
to make dataless entries
for the items in that folder.
You can tell
that the items are dataless
from the cloud download icon
next to the file name.
We’re going to use
‘cat’ on the command line
to read a file.
Since the file is dataless,
this will cause a content fetch
in our extension.
I’ve already attached
to the extension in Xcode
and set a breakpoint
to intercept this content fetch.
‘cat’ is running,
and our breakpoint has hit.
Since we are blocking
the completion
of the content fetch,
the read in our Terminal window
is also blocked.
Note how in the Finder window,
the cloud icon has been replaced
by a progress indicator.
The system has a consistent view
of the download status.
Of course,
since we are actually blocked
in the debugger
rather than busy downloading,
the progress isn’t updating.
Let’s continue.
I’ve set a second breakpoint
just before we call
the completion handler.
At this time,
our provider has downloaded
the contents of the file
to a local URL on disk.
Once we call
the completion handler,
the system will swap out
the contents
of the user-visible file
with what we’ve downloaded.
Let’s unblock the system
by continuing in Xcode.
The status in Finder updates
to show the file as being local,
and the read that the cat
process was blocked on succeeds.
I’ve still got
the breakpoints set,
but now that the file is local,
I can run ‘cat’ again
without hitting the breakpoint.
Those reads are going
against a regular local file
and don’t involve our extension.
Of course,
this is just a small part
of the feature set
of our sample file provider.
We’ve covered the full
feature set of the API,
and we are publishing the source
code as part of this session.
Let’s talk about how
you can approach implementing
the flows
that we’ve talked about.
First of all,
we’re going to want
to tell the system
that we’re ready to sync.
This will make an entry show up
in the sidebar in Finder.
We call these entries domains,
and they usually correspond
to a login session
on your cloud server.
Each domain
has a unique identifier,
and to make it show up,
you create a new instance
and add it
via the manager object.
You can also remove a domain.
You’d usually do this
when the user logs out,
but it’s also going to be useful
during your initial
development and testing.
With the domain
showing up in Finder,
the system will request
enumeration of items
as soon as you navigate
to the entry.
So let’s implement that next.
Our first step here
is to implement an item class.
Its instances represent
the individual entries
that we’re going to enumerate.
Then we implement an enumerator
that calls the system
with our items
when the system requests it.
At this point,
we can look at directories
by navigating
to our sidebar entry.
Of course, all the files
in those directories
will be dataless.
Let’s change
that by implementing
content fetch.
The fetchContents method
is called by the system
when we open
one of the dataless files.
Our job is to download the file
contents to a location on disk,
then call the completion handler
with that location’s URL.
The system will use the contents
to fill the dataless file
and then clean them up for us.
To allow our directory structure
to stay in sync,
we’ll implement another type
of enumerator.
This one syncs remote changes.
The system calls the
currentSyncAnchor method first
to get a sync anchor.
You return a data object
that describes
a change cursor
for your database.
Whenever you signal
that something has changed,
the system will ask for changes
since the last anchor
you provided.
You can then return the changes
and finally a new anchor.
The last step is to allow
sync up of changes.
If the system detects
changes to the local files,
it will call one
of three methods to create,
modify, or delete
an existing item.
We’ll have a quick look
at the create method.
The system hands you the new
item that it asks you to create.
This is a system item,
although it follows
the same protocol
as your own items.
The system will also
hand you a set of fields
that are of interest
on the item.
For example,
the item may or may not
have extended attributes
attached to it,
and there are fields
to describe that.
If the content field is set,
the system will pass you
a file URL with the contents.
Items that describe folders
or symlinks
will not have contents.
Your job is to upload
the new local item’s data
to the server and then call
the completion handler
with the resulting remote item.
And that’s it.
At this point,
you have a functional
file provider on macOS
providing files on demand,
propagating local changes
to the cloud
and remote changes to the Mac.
There are a lot
of additional optional APIs
in the File Provider framework,
which allow finer integration
with the system.
Let’s have a have a look.
Icon decorations can
be used to visually decorate
items in Finder.
You can badge a file icon,
emboss a folder,
or indicate sharing status.
You provide custom artwork
for the decorations
via a UTType
declared in your app.
Contextual menu actions
allow the user to execute
custom actions on your files
via the contextual menu.
There are UI
and non-UI variants.
You can define which files
these actions apply to
with NSPredicates declared
in your extension’s Info.plist.
Pre-flight alerts allow you
to warn the user
before they take an action
which may have
unintended consequences.
The alert UI and the criteria
to activate the alert
are configured
in the Info.plist as well.
So what are your next steps?
Well, first of all,
you can download
the session’s sample code.
It’s very comprehensive,
and it’ll give you
a lot of pointers.
Add a target to your existing
app for the new extension.
There is an Xcode template
that will help you get going.
From there,
all you have to do is implement
the method stubs
in the order we’ve discussed,
and you’ll be up and running
in no time.
Thank you for watching
this session.
We look forward to seeing
your file provider
extensions on macOS.