[upbeat music]
[Will] Hi, my name is Will,
and I'm a design manager
at Apple.
Today, with my colleague
Hannah,
I'll show you
how you can use DocC
to write interactive
developer tutorials.
Tutorials are a great way
to teach developers the details
of how your swift framework
or package works,
with step-by-step instructions
to build real apps
using your API.
You may be familiar with some
tutorials
we've written at Apple.
We created tutorials
to introduce you
to SwiftUI and Mac Catalyst.
In these introductory tutorials,
you learn the basics
of those frameworks
and build your skills
by following
step-by-step code examples.
We've found that framework
adopters love how quickly
they can get started with new
ideas presented in tutorials.
To make writing these tutorials
possible,
we built a documentation
compiler called DocC.
DocC leverages markdown
to convert plain text
into a rich, interactive system,
and this year,
we've introduced DocC to Xcode,
so you can write tutorials
for your Swift package
or Swift framework, too.
DocC isn't only for developer
tutorials.
DocC can also build
documentation
for the Swift frameworks
and packages
in your project
from source comments,
which means for app developers,
your dependencies
can have documentation
right alongside platform
libraries
in the developer documentation
window.
And if you create Swift
frameworks or Swift packages,
you can write documentation
for your adopters
right in your source,
so it's easy to keep up-to-date
as you create and modify API.
You write documentation comments
with markdown
to preserve readability
in source, while providing
a rich formatting experience
for the documentation window.
You can also write articles
and organize all the API
in your framework or package
by adding a Documentation
Catalog.
You can learn more about
using DocC
and configuring Documentation
Catalogs
in the sessions listed here.
In this session,
I'll focus on writing tutorials.
Tutorials are a
highly-interactive form
of documentation,
and in order to make
authoring them easy,
we've extended markdown
to have directives.
Directives provide structure to
author content-like tutorials
so you can focus on
writing content
with existing markdown syntax
you might already be
familiar with.
Developer tutorials are centered
around building real projects,
ideally apps.
Tutorial apps should use the API
in your framework
in a realistic way.
For example,
in the SwiftUI tutorials,
we show you how to build
an app called Landmarks
that explores the core features
beginners need to understand
to get started with SwiftUI.
With Mac Catalyst, we teach you
to build a Recipes app
that explores the differences
between iPad
and Mac navigation idioms.
And now, my colleagues and I
have been working on
a new framework
for creating, cataloging,
and caring
for cute little digital sloths
right on your iPhone.
My colleagues
have already written
some great reference
documentation and articles,
but I think adopters
of this framework will benefit
from learning to build a real
app so they can quickly see
how the different aspects
of the framework interact.
In this session,
my colleague Hannah and I
will build tutorials to teach
adopters of this framework
the basics they need
to get started with it.
I'll start by giving you
an overview
of the main components
of tutorials.
Then I'll explain how I
approach ideation and planning.
And finally,
I'll hand it off to Hannah,
who will demo creating
a collection of tutorials.
All right.
Let's get started.
As I mentioned earlier,
tutorials are
a highly-interactive
way to learn.
And like article
and reference documentation,
the text of tutorials
is authored in markdown,
but tutorials use
a special syntax
to wrap this markdown
in a directive
that provides structure
so DocC
can build the complex layout
and interactions
featured in the tutorial.
This is a basic directive
that tells DocC
this text is a single step
of a tutorial.
Along with the instructive text,
this example includes a link
to a Swift file that DocC
will display to show readers
exactly what code to write
to accomplish the step.
And DocC directives
can be nested.
In this case, the code directive
contains an image directive
that provides the reader
more context for the step.
Tutorial pages have lots of
individual steps,
like the one we just looked at.
The table of contents
provides organization
and links to the individual
tutorials.
Let's take a look at
the directives
of a table of contents.
The table of contents file
starts with
a Tutorials directive,
which contains all the elements
of the page.
Inside the Tutorials directive,
there is an Intro directive,
which includes a title
and a brief description
of what the framework adopter
will build
throughout the tutorials.
DocC generates some elements
of the introduction,
such as the "Get Started" button
and timing calculation
automatically
when you provide links
to the tutorials
in the Table of Contents page.
The introduction also contains
an image directive.
You can store images
in your documentation catalog
resources folder.
Down the page,
you'll find a Chapter directive.
You use chapters to organize
tutorials
into groups that make sense
together.
Chapters give framework adopters
a clear sense of progress
as they follow your tutorials,
as well as provide context
for what a framework
is all about.
Inside the Chapter,
there are individual links
to tutorials.
With all the context set
by this page,
framework adopters should
have a good understanding
for what the framework is
and what they'll build with it
before navigating
to a Tutorial page.
Much like the table of contents,
the Tutorial page starts
with a single directive
that contains
the contents of the page.
In this case, it's
a single Tutorial directive.
DocC uses some information
from the Table of Contents page
in the tutorial introduction,
letting folks know
what the overall theme
of this tutorial is
by referencing the chapter
it belongs to.
The introduction to the tutorial
includes a title and description
that tell the framework adopter
which part the framework
they'll use
and what they'll build with it.
To provide clarity
along the path of building,
tutorials
are broken up into sections.
Section introductions
are very similar
to tutorial introductions,
but are specific to progress
the framework adopter will make
before moving on
to the next section.
Sections contain steps,
which instruct the adopter
on what exactly they need to do
to move on to the next step.
Steps should be short,
easy to understand,
and easy to follow.
Framework adopters rely on
consistent
and clear tutorial steps
to help them get up-to-speed
on the framework
they're learning about quickly.
It's easier to create
a cohesive set of steps
throughout a collection
of tutorials
if you start with a clear plan.
Let me show you
how I make this plan
by outlining a collection
of developer tutorials
for our new Sloth framework.
In order to understand
how to outline a framework,
it's best to think
about how the framework works
and what the real-world uses
are for it.
Now, the framework my colleagues
and I have been working on
is all about sloths,
and it provides quite a bit
of cool functionality
I'm excited to see people use.
Here's a high-level view
of the main functionality
in the framework.
In order to outline my
tutorials,
I'm going to list the most
important API
so I can get a good idea
of how to explain them
through tutorials.
You can see there's API
like the Sloth type itself,
as well as a Food Generator
and PowerPicker.
If I try to think about these
all at once,
it's going to be tricky
to decide
how I should teach them
in a clear order.
So let me group them
by general functional area.
I know understanding the
Sloth type is really important
for the adopters of this
framework,
so I'll group everything related
to creating
and editing the Sloth type.
APIs used for generating sloths,
giving them names,
editing their powers:
these are the core API used
for creating sloths.
And it turns out, the remaining
API, like food generator,
care schedule, and habitat,
are all related, as well.
These API
about taking care of sloths.
So, it looks like I have two
main API groupings
that make up the framework:
the group of API
that are about creating sloths
and the group of API that
are about caring for sloths.
This is a great start.
I know that adopters will need
to understand these API
to successfully use our
framework.
And grouping them in this way
will make it easy for me
to show them how they function
together.
But I also know that adopters
of this framework are likely
to want to do more complicated
things in their own apps.
So, I'll add another group.
Our new framework is all about
creating and caring for sloths,
but I want to prepare folks
to use it in ways
that go beyond the API
it includes,
so I should include
some information
about interoperability.
I think adopters are likely to
use the framework to help sloths
interact with other animals,
move around different locations,
or hang out in groups of sloths.
I'm not trying to imagine
every use case.
I just want enough variety
to introduce folks
to ways they might use
the framework in their own apps.
With these three groups,
I have a great start
organizing my tutorials.
For now, I'll turn these groups
into chapters,
and I'll use them
to brainstorm app ideas
to let me teach the adopters
of my framework
how to use my API in a real app.
For the tutorials,
I've designed an app
that has features
for each of these three areas.
For creating,
I'll make a simple view
that lets users generate
a new sloth
and assign it a color and power.
For caring, I'll give users
the ability to see
the sloth's general activity
level, appetite, and mood.
And for the interaction section,
I'll make a feature
that lets users
find their sloths
as they move around the world
and interact with other animals.
With my app idea sketched out,
I'm ready to plan
how I'll build it
and how I'll teach people
to build it, too.
I'll write a list of tutorials
for each chapter
that roughly follows how I'd go
about building the app.
First, I'd make the view
for creating sloths.
Then I'd work on
the more complicated
caring-for-sloths features.
Finally,
I'd build the parts of the app
that use other frameworks.
After all this planning,
I have a list of tutorials
that I'm confident will help
adopters of our framework
create and care for sloths.
This plan might change
as I write, but for now,
it'll help me
organize my thoughts
and make sure I've covered
all the important API
in a clear
but not redundant way.
So far, we've explored
the directive syntax
and the components
that make up tutorials.
We've also walked through
the basics
of outlining
a collection of tutorials.
At this point,
we're ready to start writing,
so I'll hand it off to
my colleague Hannah
who will show you how to write
tutorials with DocC in Xcode 13.
[Hannah] Thanks, Will.
My name is Hannah.
I'm a Human Interface designer
here at Apple.
Now that I have an outline
of the SlothCreator Tutorials,
with the all-new DocC feature
in Xcode 13,
let's walk through how
to write a tutorial together.
My colleague, Bea and Jack,
covered how to create
a Documentation Catalog
to organize documentation files
in the session "Elevate Your
DocC Documentation in Xcode."
I'm going to add my tutorials
in the same Documentation
Catalog
they created for SlothCreator.
As Will mentioned,
we need a table of contents file
in order to compile
the tutorials.
So I've already created
a Tutorials folder
and a Table of Contents file
for my SlothCreator Tutorials.
Now, let's start creating
my first tutorial!
First, I'll right click
on the Tutorials folder,
select New File to bring up
the template selector,
then select Tutorial file,
click Next.
I'll name this tutorial
"Creating Custom Sloths."
DocC provides a template
for me to start with.
In the tutorial file template,
there's an intro, a section,
and a set of steps
in the section.
If I want, I can show
the estimated time of completion
for my tutorial.
I'll say it takes about
20 minutes.
Let's continue with the title
of this tutorial.
Here, I'll put in
"Creating Custom Sloths."
Then add my overview of
this tutorial.
I want to make my tutorial
look more engaging,
so I prepared some art files
for the tutorial intro,
section intro, and steps.
Let me open my Art File folder,
select all the images
I prepared,
drag and drop them
into the Resources folder
in the Documentation Catalog.
Let me show you
the intro image I designed.
It visually describes
what our framework adopters
are going to build in this
tutorial.
To add the intro image,
I'll put in the image file name
after "source."
I'm also going to add
an accessible description
for the image.
I want my tutorials
to be accessible to everyone
so that every SlothCreator
adopter
can have a great learning
experience
through both reading
and listening to the tutorials.
An accessible description
describes
what's self-explanatory
to someone
who's looking at the image.
For example,
I'll describe the intro image as
"A wireframe of an app interface
that has an outline of a sloth
and four buttons
below the sloth.
The buttons display
the following symbols,
from left to right:
ice, fire,
wind, and lightning."
Let's add the description
in the code.
Now that I've completed
the intro of this tutorial,
let's move on to
the first section.
This is going to be
a beginner-friendly tutorial.
So in the first section,
our framework adopters
will start with
setting up the basics
for the Slothy app.
I'll put in the section title
and add a description
of the section.
I'm also going to add
the section image I prepared,
which visually represents
the task flow of this section.
Similar to how I added
the intro image,
I'll put in the image file name
and an accessible description.
Next, let's move on to steps.
In the first step
in this section,
our framework adopters
will create
a new Xcode project
using the iOS app template.
I'll put that
in the instruction.
The media of this step
should give adopters
more context
on how to do it,
so I took a screenshot
of Xcode's template selector
and highlighted the areas
they need to interact with.
One thing to keep in mind,
when our framework adopters
are viewing this tutorial,
the background for Sections
and Steps
could be either light or dark
based on their Xcode settings.
So I can either create an image
that is dark-mode compatible
or provide a separate image
for each appearance.
I'll add this image to the step.
Now I have added the first step,
I'll go ahead and add the rest
of the steps in section 1.
Okay.
I've completed the steps
in the first section.
Let's take a look how this
tutorial is coming along.
In Xcode 13,
I can preview my tutorials
in the Developer Documentation
window by navigating
to Product Build documentation,
or use the shortcut by pressing
control+shift+command+D
on the keyboard.
Great! The tutorials
compiled successfully.
And now,
I can preview what I wrote
in the Documentation Window
that just popped up.
Let's take a look
at the Table of Contents page.
On the navigator on the left,
I can see my tutorials
are organized
under the SlothCreator project,
along with other documentation
my colleagues wrote
for SlothCreator.
On the right side, I can see
the Table of Contents page.
There is an overview
for the tutorial collection
and an eye-catching image
in the intro section.
Below the intro,
there's my first chapter
and a link to the tutorial
I just wrote.
Let's take a look.
From the top of
the Tutorial page,
there's the tutorial intro,
which tells our framework
adopters
that they will build
a SlothCreation view,
and it'll take them about
20 minutes.
Below that is the first section.
In this section,
adopters will go through
four simple steps
to set up their project.
We can see the image updates
as we scroll down the steps.
So far, everything looks good.
In the second section,
our framework adopters
will start coding
with SlothCreator.
Let's move on to see how
to guide them with code steps.
I've already completed the intro
of section 2 and the first step.
Let's take a look at
the second step,
where our framework adopters
are importing
the SlothCreator package
in the Swift file
they created
in the previous step.
Before we dive into it,
I want to point out
a couple of things.
A code step shows
the display name on top,
telling adopters which file
they should be working on.
DocC will display the Swift file
I'm adding for this step
on the right side of the screen,
below the display name.
DocC can also automatically
compare
the current code file
with the one from previous step
and highlight the new portion
of the code.
This code file generates
a preview.
I can add a screenshot
of the preview to this step
so that adopters can check
if they have followed
the instruction successfully.
Let's go back to Xcode
and finish this step.
First, add the display name,
then the code file name,
and lastly, the preview image.
Now we've gone over how
to add a code step,
I'll go ahead and add
the rest of the steps
in section 2.
So far, we've walked through
how to write a tutorial intro,
a section,
and different types of steps.
Now, I'm going to
add all the tutorials
I've written for SlothCreator.
Let me open Finder,
select all the tutorial files
I prepared,
drag and drop them
into the Tutorials folder.
Next, I'll open
the Table of Contents file,
link the other two tutorials
in the first chapter,
then add the second
and the third chapter.
Okay, now I have completed
SlothCreator Tutorials.
Let's take a look together.
From the Table of Contents page,
we can see this tutorial
collection includes
eight tutorials organized
into three chapters.
I can also see this structure
from the navigator on the left.
This page is a great way to
provide our framework adopters
a summarized view
of this tutorial collection.
Let's also take a look at
the Tutorial page I just wrote.
We have seen the intro
and the first section,
which guides our framework
adopters
through
how to set up their project.
Below that is the second section
that provides adopters
clear coding instructions
on how to build
a sloth customization view.
Awesome!
The tutorials look really good!
I'm sure our framework adopters
will be excited
to learn about SlothCreator
when they see my tutorials.
In this session,
we went over what tutorials are,
what makes a good tutorial,
how to outline tutorials,
and how to use DocC
to write and preview tutorials.
DocC is a powerful new
documentation feature
in Xcode 13.
With it, you can write
comprehensive documentation
for your framework,
including reference, articles,
and tutorials.
To learn more about how to
write, build,
and organize your documentation
with DocC,
I recommend you check out
other DocC sessions
from WWDC this year.
Thank you for learning with us,
and we are thrilled to see
what you are going to create
with DocC in Xcode 13.
[upbeat music]