[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Rajesh Ambati: Hi,
I am Raj Ambati.
I lead 5G software development
at Apple
and I’m excited
to talk to you about 5G,
so let’s dig in.
Over the course
of this short presentation,
I will cover on three main areas,
beginning with a bit
of background on the path to 5G
and why we think
it’s a big deal.
I will share
how iPadOS and iOS
balance network performance
and battery life
all while preserving
a great user experience,
and leave you with
some practical guidance
you can use to ensure your app
is optimized for 5G.
So let me begin
with the path to 5G.
For me, one of the best ways
to convey the potential
of modern 5G networks
is to take a step back.
Now, I’m guessing
not many of you
owned one of these
sweet portable phones.
But, I think it’s important
to understand
that they were a big deal
in their day.
With this handy device,
you could actually
make a telephone call
while on the go.
And while, of course,
our modern iPhone
still lets you make calls,
so much of the other
amazing things you can do
with your iPhone
is the result of advances
in networking technology.
Each step in network evolution
has brought
dramatically new capabilities
to mobile devices.
2G networks, for example,
were the first networks
to provide data services
for mobile.
So not only could you
make a phone call,
but you could do
dramatically new things
such as having
a voice-free conversation
by sending SMS text messages;
capture pictures and immediately
send them to your friends;
or deliver a variety of media,
including up to multiple images,
video, and audio,
all at the blistering speed of
up to 384 kilobits per second.
And while this is probably
considered slow,
the fact you could do
these amazing new things
with a mobile device meant
the performance of the network
didn’t really matter as much.
But of course,
once we developers
have access to a network,
our goal is to push it
to its limits.
So 2G networks
really were only the beginning
of a continuous strive
to deliver more data, faster.
3G came along with primary focus
on data connectivity
and unlocked new capabilities
such as video calls, mobile TV,
and even internet access.
Imagine what a breakthrough
3G was at the time!
Having a web browser
on your phone was amazing;
it put the entire internet
in your pocket!
4G -- or what’s more commonly
called LTE -- came next,
and with it,
data rates improved even more.
LTE enabled reliable mobile
voice over IP communication,
support for streaming
high-quality video,
and many other data-intensive
user experiences
we’ve come to love
like communicating with
your family using FaceTime video
or exploring shared augmented
reality experiences
or real-time multiplayer
games and more.
Those fantastic new experiences
that we’ve come to rely on
were made possible
by the dramatic increase
in network performance
over the previous generation.
But again, we are always
looking to push the envelope;
to deliver more services
and breakthrough experiences,
and of course, deliver them
at faster speeds.
And that brings us to the latest
technology in networking, 5G.
5G continues the evolution
of our ever-increasing
need for speed.
And if you step back and take
a look at network performance
over these generations,
you can see each new generation
delivered a remarkable
increase in speed
at which the data
can be delivered.
Each jump in speed leads
to a leap in the possibilities
for you to provide richer --
or in many cases,
previously impossible --
experiences in your app.
But while 5G is an incredible
jump in performance
from a network bandwidth
perspective,
5G provides other advances
beyond just more data
at a faster rate.
So not only can you
exchange data faster,
but you’ll have
faster round-trip times
between your app
and your server.
And faster round trips
mean faster
and more synchronized
transactions.
5G’s ability to handle
more devices concurrently
means you can
continue to deliver
data-related services
in your app,
even in congested
public environments
such as sports stadiums,
convention arenas,
and other crowded
public venues --
remember those?
And given that 5G’s performance
is 10 times better
than a typical public Wi-Fi,
this means your customers
won’t have to hop on
potentially insecure
Wi-Fi hotspots
just to quickly exchange
larger files.
So that was a brief review
of the network generations
leading to 5G,
each leap in performance
resulting in increased
opportunities
for app developers like you
to push the envelope
and deliver previously
unheard-of experiences
in your app.
Now, I’d like to transition
from a focus on performance
of the network
to describe the services
we’ve built into iOS
that ensure your app
will perform optimally,
regardless of
the network environment.
Looking back at the major
milestones of networking,
it is easy to think that as each
new network came into being,
the previous network disappeared
into the dustbin of history.
But like any
evolutionary process,
there are always portions of the
past in the next generation.
So the reality is that today’s
modern 5G cellular networks
can be a bit of an amalgam,
but come primarily
in two varieties,
commonly referred to as
Non-Standalone and Standalone --
or even more commonly
referred to as NSA and SA.
Non-Standalone is built
on the existing LTE core
and can use both LTE and 5G
links to schedule traffic,
operates at frequencies
below seven gigahertz,
and includes support
for millimeter wave.
Standalone is built entirely
on the new 5G core,
also operates at frequencies
below seven gigahertz,
and includes support
for millimeter wave,
and delivers improved
latency performance over LTE.
These unique characteristics
of 5G deployments
play a critical role
in determining
the network performance
of your app.
And the upside is huge,
especially with
ideal theoretical speeds
of up to 4 gigabits per second.
And this real-world test
I recently ran at Apple Park
shows me getting close,
clocking in at a wicked fast
3 gigabits per second!
That’s 20 times faster than LTE.
And with a ping latency
of seven milliseconds,
it’s pretty obvious there’s
a lot you can do with 5G.
However, while 5G deployments
provide lower latency
and faster data speeds,
they are inherently
more power hungry.
Sure, the people using your app
want a superfast experience,
but not necessarily
at the expense of battery life.
So we’ve taken this desire
for a balance
between power and performance
into consideration
and made optimizations
at the system level
so you can focus
on user experience.
If we go back to look
at our 5G deployments
and toss public Wi-Fi networks
into the mix,
you can see there’s
a range of network types
with varied performance
characteristics
that we can pick from to provide
the best connection speed
for a given task
in your app.
And we pick the best network
using two techniques
called "Automatic Switch to 5G"
and "Smart Data Mode."
Both technologies look
at a combination of performance,
security,
and power characteristics
to enable the best wireless
connection for your app,
be it Wi-Fi, LTE, or 5G.
In addition
to constantly evaluating
the relative performance of LTE,
5G, and Wi-Fi,
Smart Data Mode
can detect network congestion
on any network
and move your connection
to the wireless interface
with the least resistance.
They also look at the security
of the available
Wi-Fi connection
with the assumption
that public Wi-Fi at airports,
coffee shops, et cetera
are usually less secure
than cellular
and typically provide
very low data speeds.
And battery considerations
also take into account
the most power-efficient network
for a given task
within your app,
such as switching to 5G
knowing it’s more efficient
for large file use cases
like movie downloads,
or switching to LTE
for low data-intensive tasks,
like those typically
run in the background.
So with all the built-in
services
managing the network interface
on your behalf,
it’s easy to ignore
the type of network altogether.
And with that review
of the built-in features,
I have a perfect segue to
provide some practical guidance
for ensuring your app
is optimized for 5G.
And I’ve already hinted
at the first best practice
in the previous section.
With the system choosing
the best network on your behalf,
you should stop even considering
the network type.
Using network type
to drive behavior
is just about guaranteed
to prevent your app
from accessing
the potential 5G benefits.
Also, don’t assume if Wi-Fi
is available, cellular isn’t
because we support
multiple network paths.
My next best practice
is to use our frameworks
to take full advantage of 5G.
For example, you should be
using AVFoundation,
like we do on Apple TV
and in Apple Music,
to stream high-quality
audio and video;
or CallKit to take advantage
of the noticeable
enhancements we’ve added
for VOIP apps on 5G.
Using high-level network APIs
such as URLSession
and the Network framework,
we’ve been able to tune
many of our apps
to take full advantage of 5G.
Apple News will cache articles
over 5G for offline reading.
Now your favorite photos
get synced to iCloud
over the inexpensive 5G link.
And we’ve enabled automatic
backup and restore over 5G
when Wi-Fi isn’t available.
My third best practice
is to tune your application
for constrained
and expensive paths.
In most cases,
expensive and constrained
are automatically
derived by the system
based on
the active cellular plan.
However, the user
can also affect these
by altering the Data Mode
settings on their device.
There are three options:
Allow More Data on 5G,
indicating an inexpensive path,
similar to Wi-Fi;
Standard mode,
which is usually considered as expensive;
and Low Data Mode,
which is considered constrained.
The concept of expensive
and constrained
are surfaced as properties
in all our high-level
networking frameworks.
And the value
of these properties
should be your
only consideration
when determining
the type of network services
available for your app.
For example,
URLSession allows you
to take advantage
of these properties
to manage networking requests.
In order to benefit from
inexpensive networking over 5G,
we recommend you use
allowsExpensiveNetworkAccess
instead of relying
on network type checks.
In addition, if your application
implements policy
based on expensive,
provide a way for users
to influence that policy.
In Network.framework,
you have another option
to check for constrained,
expensive, and inexpensive path.
And finally, if your app
uses AVFoundation,
there are similar case
indicating constrained
and expensive here as well.
So those are my best practices
for ensuring your app
is ready to take advantage
of 5G.
The key takeaway ideally
is to let the operating system
and iOS frameworks
do the heavy lifting.
We’ve covered a fair amount
in this session,
from a bit of a history lesson
to a deep dive
on how the system works,
to some tips to make sure
you are getting the most
out of the network.
But before I sign off,
let me leave you
with a few key takeaways.
First, 5G is here.
While you may not have it
available in your neighborhood,
a good percentage
of your customers do --
or it’s just around
the corner --
so you want to be ready.
Remember that we are
continually working on ways
to leverage
our unique combination
of hardware and software
to ensure a high-performance
user experience
while maintaining the longest
possible battery life.
And by using
our high-level frameworks,
your app can benefit
with minimal effort.
And finally, we’re always
looking for ways
to engage with you.
So please give us feedback
on how our networking tools
are or are not
fitting your needs.
And if you have 5G use cases you
find particularly interesting,
we would love to hear
about that as well.
Thank you!
♪