Hey there, developers!
I'm Serenity Caldwell at Apple.
Did you miss day one at Dub Dub?
Well, let's go back in time.
[WHOOSHING]
[CHEERING]
- Good morning,
and welcome to WWDC.
- iOS 15 is here.
Maps got an intuitive
3D redesign.
Safari looks new
on iPhone, iPad, and Mac,
and we introduced
the amazing Live Text.
- How cool is that?
- We took FaceTime calls
to the next level
with spatial audio
and Portrait mode.
And with SharePlay,
you can now share your screen
or listen to music
or watch a TV show
with your friends all in sync
across your iPhone, iPad,
Mac, and Apple TV.
- This is where you come in.
We're offering new APIs
to start playback
that are designed
to fit right into your app's
existing video experience.
- And speaking of,
now Apple TV sounds even better
with head-tracked
spatial audio support.
And with Find My
separation alerts,
you'll never leave
your AirPods behind.
[FIND MY CHIME]
iCloud+ keeps
your online activity
away from data collectors.
App Library is on iPad now,
and check out
how to place widgets
among apps on your Home screen.
AirPlay is coming to Mac,
and a big round of applause
for Universal Control.
Look how I move
between different devices
as if they were one.
Look how I drag and drop files.
Look how cool I am.
We took a big step
with Walking Steadiness.
You can share your health data
with your family and your
doctors with the Health app,
or try some Tai Chi,
Pilates, and mindfulness
on your Apple Watch.
[EXHALES DEEPLY]
Let's get back on track.
Later this year, we're bringing
ID cards to Wallet,
Home Keys to unlock your home
with just one tap,
and say hello to Siri
on third-party devices.
- We believe
Siri's most powerful
when it's available
throughout your house.
- Then we learned
about Xcode Cloud,
how to stay in the zone
with Focus mode.
- These tools help
reduce distractions
so that people can be
in the moment.
- How to build apps
in Swift Playgrounds,
Swift concurrency, SwiftUI...
That's so many swifts.
Powerful new tools
for developing high-end games.
Object Capture for ARKit
and APIs for SharePlay.
- Now we're all looking at the
same canvas to draw together.
- Wow, that's a lot of stuff.
Not bad for day one, eh?
Now, here's a peek
at what happens tomorrow.
♪ "Better Days (Instrumental)"
by DARKMINDS" ♪
♪
Stay tuned for more
amazing stuff.
It'll be a great week.
♪