[music]
[Justin] Hello,
and welcome to this session
on Xcode Cloud workflows.
My name is Justin,
and I'm an engineer
with the TestFlight team,
and along with my colleagues,
Wesley and Kevin,
we're here to introduce
the ins and outs of creating
your workflows in Xcode Cloud.
Workflows are at the heart
of Xcode Cloud
and drive
the continuous integration
that enables you and your team
to automate building,
analyzing, testing, archiving,
and distributing
your apps and frameworks.
They are
flexible and extensible,
so you can customize workflows
around your team's
existing development
and distribution processes.
And with Xcode Cloud,
workflow management
is integrated
into the Apple developer tools
you already use:
Xcode and App Store Connect.
In this session,
let's break workflows
down into
their specific components.
First, we'll walk through
how to configure the conditions
that automatically
run your workflow.
Then, we'll talk
about the options
for setting up your environment.
We'll also show you how
to create multiple actions
for the tasks you want
to automate,
along with actions
to run afterward,
like sending notifications
about your builds,
or automatically deploying
those builds to TestFlight.
Finally, we have
some strategies for different
workflows you may find
useful and super convenient
to boost your team's
collaboration and productivity.
We have a lot to cover,
so let's get started.
Let me hand it off to Wesley.
[Wesley] Thanks, Justin!
I'm collaborating
on an app called Fruta
with members
of my developer team.
It is already up and running
on Xcode Cloud.
If you haven't
yet seen the session
"Meet Xcode Cloud,"
be sure to check it out to learn
about setting up
your first workflow.
Right here, integrated
in Xcode's Report Navigator,
is a new Cloud tab,
where I see the workflows
and builds from my team.
When I onboarded the Fruta app,
it created a default workflow
for me
that builds the main branch.
This workflow has
been working great for us,
but because we're a team
that also uses pull requests,
I'd like to create
a pull-request-specific workflow
that my team can leverage.
I'd like it to run every time
a pull request is created
by anyone on my team,
analyze, test,
and archive my app,
notify my team when
a pull-request build finishes,
and deliver a version
of my app to members of my team
so they can test out the
features before they're merged
into our main
integration branch.
Creating
a workflow is easy to do.
Under the Product menu,
I can go to Manage Workflows,
click Plus, and select my app.
[trackpad clicking sounds]
This will bring track
a new workflow editor.
A workflow is made up of several
configurable components.
Here's the general section,
where I can name my workflow.
I'm gonna name this
"Pull Requests."
If I were on a team
where only a small number
of individuals
are responsible for making
changes to our workflows,
I can choose to restrict editing
to prevent unintended updates
that might impact our team.
By default,
Xcode Cloud sets the primary
repository
and project information
with the knowledge
of my local settings,
but if I ever decide to move
my primary repository
or migrate from an Xcode project
to a workspace,
I can change
those settings here.
Next, let's take a look
at the Start Condition section.
This is where I can define
when I want my workflow to run.
Xcode Cloud has
a number of condition types.
For this workflow, I want
to set its start condition
to run for all pull requests
that intend to merge
into the main branch.
To do that,
I can select from the Type menu
and choose Every Change
to a Pull Request.
This condition type
allows me to specify the source
and target branch.
I'll set the source branch
to Any Branch
and the target branch to Main.
Now every time a team
member creates a pull request
against Main
and makes changes to it,
Xcode Cloud will
automatically run this workflow.
When building pull requests,
Xcode Cloud will now build
and test the merge of the source
and target branch together,
so my team members
can be confident
and know the real impact
of their changes
with the rest of the team.
I can also narrow
those conditions
to specific files or folders
and choose to set whether or
not I want to auto-cancel
any previously running builds
when the workflow runs.
This is useful
if I push one commit
on top of another
in quick succession.
Every Change to a Pull Request
is just one
of the start conditions that you
can set for a workflow,
and depending on
the needs of your team,
we have other condition types
that you can configure
to meet those needs.
Every Change to a Branch
will always build
the source branch
and will ignore
any pull-request states.
Every Change to a Tag
will build whenever
new tags are created.
On a Schedule
will build a branch
of your choosing on a recurring
schedule that you can choose.
This is great
if you have long-running tests
that you want
to run on occasion.
Now that I have configured
the start condition,
which dictates
when this workflow will run,
let's configure
the Environment section,
which dictates
how the workflow will run.
Xcode Cloud runs
on Apple's Cloud Infrastructure
and makes available various
macOS and Xcode versions.
To choose
your Xcode and macOS version,
you just need
to select it from a menu.
You can also set your workflow
to point to the Latest Release
or Beta version,
so you could always build
or test on the latest software.
As developers,
we all care deeply
about our productivity,
and a large part of that
is the performance
of the tools we use.
Many of you will be working
on large projects
with many files and deal with
potentially long build times.
Just as locally within Xcode,
you have the option to build
your changes incrementally
by just building
the files that have changed.
You also have
this option in Xcode Cloud.
This typically
leads to faster builds.
However,
there are times when you might
wanna perform
a clean build instead.
This is important to make
sure everything is functioning
in your final build,
and is also required to produce
builds that could be deployed
to External Beta Testers
with TestFlight or
to submit to the App Store.
In the environment section,
I have the option to select
Clean.
Since this is a pull-request
workflow,
I'll leave it unchecked
so I can take advantage
of the performance benefits.
Every team works
in its own unique way,
and teams need their tools
to have the flexibility
to be able to work
the way they want to work.
Xcode Cloud provides
options to do what we believe
are the most common development
tasks out of the box.
However,
it also provides a range
of options for extensibility.
This extensibility allows
you to connect Xcode Cloud
with the other tools and systems
your teams use
to get your work done.
Xcode Cloud offers
a comprehensive API
to access your data, configure
workflows, and kick off builds.
In addition to the existing
scripting options
that Xcode provides,
Xcode adds the ability
to create custom scripts
that run on the devices
which are performing
your builds and tests.
In the Environment section,
I can specify environment
variables
that Xcode Cloud makes
available to custom scripts.
This is useful
for configuration and secrets
that I don't want to check
into the source code repository.
I also have the ability
to mark an environment variable
as secret to provide
an extra level of protection.
You can find further
information on this
in the "Customize your Advanced
Xcode Cloud Workflows" session
or in our documentation.
So far, we've shown you how
to configure when your workflows
run and when they run.
What environment
should they run in?
Next, let's talk about actions.
Actions define the work
that you want the workflow to do
for you and your team
every time the workflow runs.
The key actions you could ask
Xcode to perform locally
are now all available to you
within Xcode Cloud:
building,
running static analysis,
testing,
and archiving.
The actions I want
to set up are the Archive,
Test, and Analyze actions.
Let's start by adding
the Archive action
by clicking the plus icon
by Actions
and selecting Archive.
I need to select
the platform and the scheme
I want to create an archive for.
It already
pre-selected the iOS platform
and the iOS scheme,
which is exactly what I wanted.
I also have
the option to register
for TestFlight or make it ready
for App Store distribution,
but more on this later.
You may notice
that I didn't have to manage
provisioning profiles
or code-signing identities.
Xcode Cloud handles
this automatically for you.
To learn more about this,
check out the session
"Distribute Apps in Xcode
with Cloud Signing."
Now that the Archive action
is set up,
let's focus our attention
on the Test action.
Testing
your apps is an incredibly
important part
of the development process.
Not only does it help
ensure your users experience
fewer bugs, but it can speed
up your development process
by giving you confidence
in the changes you are making.
However, sometimes it can
be cumbersome and slow
to run your tests locally,
and sometimes,
you might just forget.
By setting up a workflow
with testing in Xcode Cloud,
tests run in a stable, reliable,
and reproducible environment.
They run in the background
while you are doing other work,
freeing up
your local environment,
and they run automatically,
freeing you up of having to
remember to manually run them.
To add a Test action,
I just need to click on
the Plus button and select Test.
For Test actions,
I can choose to make them
required to pass or not.
Marking the action as required
means that the overall build
will fail if this Test action
fails.
If I were building up
my test suite,
I may choose to set this as
Not Required to Pass
so it doesn't affect
the overall build state.
When it comes to choosing
which tests to run,
I have a couple of options.
I can choose
Use Scheme Settings
to reference the settings
in my Fruta iOS scheme,
or I can
select a particular test plan
if I want to hone in
on a certain set of tests.
Once I have that set,
all that is left to do
is to choose the simulators
I want to run my tests on.
Xcode Cloud provides
a recommended option,
which is a collection
of simulators
with different screen sizes.
The recommended option always
tests against the Xcode
selected
in the Environment section,
but if I choose
specific simulators,
I can also select from a list
of older OS versions.
The last action I want
to run is the Analyze action.
The compiler is capable
of automatically finding
many classes of bugs
and warning us about them.
Heeding and fixing these
can save us a great deal
of development time
compared with tracking down
these issues at run time
and will give our users
a much more stable
and bug-free experience
with our app.
However,
because running static analysis
is not part of our typical local
iterative development workflow,
many of us forget to run it,
only to see the issues mount up
across the team over time.
With Xcode Cloud,
you could make sure that
static analysis runs every time
you make a code change.
To add an Analyze action,
I'll click on the Plus button,
and select Analyze.
Like tests,
I have the option to mark
static analysis issues
as Required to Pass or not.
Right now, I only want
to monitor the results
of static analysis, so I won't
mark it as Required to Pass.
The last action
is the Build action.
On occasion,
you might need to run
a simple Xcode Build action.
This might be useful
to make sure a particular
secondary build configuration
or scheme still compiles,
or perhaps to ensure
that a framework that is part
of your app
can be built on its own.
Now that I've set
up the Archive, Test,
and Analyze actions
for my pull-request workflow,
I'll hand it off to Kevin to add
post-actions to this workflow.
[Kevin] Thanks, Wesley.
With Xcode Cloud workflows,
you have the ability
to configure post-actions.
Post-actions run after
all Build, Analyze, Test,
and Archive actions
have completed.
The post-actions you can
configure with Xcode Cloud
are sending notifications
and deploying with TestFlight.
Let's first talk
about notifications.
There are two types
of notification events
you can send.
The first
is when a build succeeds.
You have the option
to send notifications
for all build successes;
only fixes,
which is when a branch or
pull-request build transitions
from failing to passing;
or don't notify.
The other notification event
is for when a build fails.
You can send a notification
for all build failures;
only breaks, which is when
a branch or pull-request build
transitions from passing
to failing; or don't notify.
For this workflow,
I want to notify my team
when pull-request builds finish.
Below the Actions section
is post-actions.
To add a Notification action,
I'll click the Plus button
and select Notify.
I'll leave All
for Build Success
and Build Failure.
Below the Notification Events,
I have a couple of options
for where to send notifications.
Xcode Cloud integrates
with the popular
collaboration tool Slack.
Once a Slack account
has been authorized,
I can click the Plus button
to bring up a list of channels.
I'll select the "ci-builds"
channel and click OK.
I also have the option
to add email addresses.
By default,
all users automatically
receive notifications
for the builds they kick off,
so you don't have
to add them to this list.
However,
if you have a group email
or if you have users
who want to receive builds
they did not kick off,
you can add their email here.
Finally,
I'd like to share with you
one of my favorite features
of Xcode Cloud Workflows:
the ability to automatically
deploy with TestFlight.
And now,
with TestFlight on Mac,
you can deploy to every platform
Apple has to offer.
There are two
TestFlight deployment options
with Xcode Cloud.
Deploying to internal testers
has been enhanced
to quickly send builds
to members
of your development team.
Because they're members
of your team,
they can receive builds
that were produced
from pull requests
and builds
without Clean selected.
If you use TestFlight today,
External Testing and App Store
is equivalent
to what you already know.
It's recommended for
candidate and release branches
and can be distributed
to external testers
and the App Store,
subject to beta app review.
TestFlight is a great way
to get builds of your app
onto devices
of your teammates
and beta testers
outside of your organization.
You can configure
a workflow to automatically
deploy a build to any
TestFlight group you have.
You manage
your TestFlight groups
the same way you do today,
in App Store Connect
under the TestFlight tab.
Here, I have multiple internal
and external groups,
and each one of them is
available to me in my workflow.
To automatically deploy
with an internal
TestFlight group,
you'll need to do three things.
First, you'll need
to add an Archive action.
Next, you'll need
to set the Deployment option
on the archive to
Internal Testing.
Finally,
you'll need to add a TestFlight
Internal Testing post-action.
Let's configure
our workflow to do just that.
I want this workflow
to automatically
deploy to my QA team.
To do that, first, I'll
click on the Archive iOS action,
and select TestFlight
Internal Testing Only.
Doing this means my builds
will be available in TestFlight.
This is great if I don't want
to automatically send builds
to anyone, but keep
the option to do it later
from the TestFlight section
on App Store Connect.
For this app,
I also want to deploy
to my colleagues automatically
whenever a build is produced.
To do that, I need to add
a TestFlight post-action.
I'll click the Plus button
beside Post-Actions,
and add TestFlight
Internal Testing.
The Archive iOS
artifact is pre-selected,
which is what I want.
I'll hit the Plus button
to add an internal group.
Finally,
I'll select the QA team.
Now members of my QA
team can verify
and test all features
before they're merged
onto the Main branch.
Sending a build to testers
outside of your organization
with TestFlight External Testing
is a great way to get feedback
on your app
and its features before
submitting to the App Store.
This way, you can gain
confidence in your changes
from a wider set of users
and potentially make changes
and fix issues
before it's released
to the App Store.
To deploy with TestFlight
External Testing,
a few more
conditions need to be set.
Select a single branch
in the start condition.
This ensures consistency
in the builds
you intend to send
to your external beta testers.
Next, select Clean
in the Environment section.
This guarantees
your code will be built
from scratch,
without using derived data.
Lastly,
set the Deployment setting
in your Archive action
to TestFlight and App Store.
After all that is set,
configuring the TestFlight
External Testing post-action
is similar to configuring
TestFlight Internal Testing.
You simply add
external groups
that have been created
in TestFlight.
TestFlight External Testing
also has the added ability
to deploy to individual testers.
We've just
created a pull-request workflow
in Xcode,
but you can also create,
edit, and manage workflows
in App Store Connect.
It's a great option
if you're away from Xcode
and need to make changes
to your workflows.
Now back over to Justin
to make a few recommendations
on the types of workflows
you can create for your team.
Justin?
[Justin] Thanks, Kevin.
I think the Fruta QA team
will love accessing builds
faster with
our pull-request workflow.
So as you've seen,
workflows have a lot of power
and flexibility to model
the way your teams work.
You can create
as many workflows as you need
to get your work done.
I know our team
will create several.
Kevin just showed you
a workflow for pull requests,
but here are a couple of ideas
for more workflows
you and your team can try out.
To show your app to users
outside
of your development team,
you might distribute to
an external TestFlight group
or submit
your app to the App Store.
The idea here is that I want to
enforce high quality
so my app's users
have a great experience.
I need to run
a workflow on the branches
designated for releases.
It should execute a
comprehensive battery of tests,
archive the build,
and, finally,
deploy
to an external TestFlight group
and into the hands of users.
To better illustrate, let me
show you my Release Workflow.
To make sure
my workflow will build
all of our future releases
as well,
I set the start condition to
Every Change to a Branch
on my Release branch.
To be thorough,
I want every build
from this workflow
to be generated from scratch,
so I checked Clean
in the Environment section.
Doing so typically increases
build times
since everything
is compiled again,
but it gives us confidence
that there are no issues
caused by caching.
Notice that I also selected
specific versions of Xcode
and macOS for this workflow.
Pinning the tools down
is an important part
of converging
and finalizing a release.
To ensure that our app will work
across the range of users'
iPhones and iPads,
I run our tests on a variety
of simulators
in the Test section.
To distribute the build
of our app via TestFlight,
I included an Archive action
and set the deployment
preparation
to TestFlight and App Store.
To ensure our beta testers
always get the most
up-to-date build,
I set up a post-action
to deploy to our external
TestFlight group.
When new code is merged
into our release branch,
it gets automatically built,
tested,
and deployed
to our beta testers.
Now we can get feedback
quickly on our changes
while maintaining confidence
that the quality remains high.
Here's another workflow
you might want to create
that performs a deeper set
of testing every night.
My Overnight Testing workflow
runs periodically,
testing against
multiple simulators
to cover as many platforms
as I need.
Any test failures get reported
to the QA team,
and since the focus
is entirely on testing,
there's no need
to deploy a build anywhere.
I set my start condition
to run this workflow
every weeknight by choosing
On a Schedule for a Branch
as my start condition type
with weekly frequency.
Then, I selected my days
as Monday through Friday
at 1:00 a.m.
In the Environment section,
I selected the latest
Xcode version to make sure
our app builds successfully
as new tools are released.
I want to thoroughly test
our app,
so I selected a few test plans
and simulators
that are required to pass.
I also want
to run static analysis,
so I added an Analyze action
and also require that to pass.
Should any
of the previous tests fail,
the QA team will find
out with a Notify post-action.
I set Build Success to
Don't Notify,
and Build Failure to All.
My QA team
has their own Slack channel,
but I could also specify
an email address.
Either way,
the QA team will find out
about any build failures
by the following morning.
Running a workflow like this
is a great way to save time
since you and your team can
keep developing during the day
and leave Xcode Cloud
to thoroughly test your app
at night.
And lastly,
under the Product menu in Xcode
is Manage Workflows,
where I can take a look at all
the workflows our team uses.
I see the Overnight Testing
workflow
that I just created
along with the workflows
that Wesley and Kevin
created earlier.
As our project grows,
I can add more, edit,
or remove workflows
to suit the team's needs.
And that's it
for our team's workflows.
We've shown you how to create
workflows for pull requests,
how to configure actions
for different platforms,
how to distribute
releases to TestFlight users,
and how to set
up overnight testing.
But there are so many
more things
you could do with workflows.
On top of that,
you can even create and manage
those workflows
from App Store Connect.
To learn even more
about workflows,
check out "Customize Your
Advanced Xcode Cloud Workflows."
If you haven't had a chance yet,
watch "Meet Xcode Cloud"
to learn how to onboard
your project.
There are also other great
sessions that dive deeper
into cloud signing and Xcode's
new support for pull requests.
Xcode Cloud gives your team
the ability to create flexible,
extensible workflows
that can adapt
to the way you work
and help make sure the team
consistently follows
their development practices.
I hope this session helps
you create workflows
to leverage as you
and your team iterate
development
and deliver a high-quality app.
Thank you for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[music]