[percussive music]
[Manjeet]
Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Manjeet Chawla,
a technical program manager
at the App Store,
and I'm really excited
to talk about some new
features that will help you
support customers
and handle refunds.
This is the third session
of a three-part series
focusing on in-app purchases.
And if you haven't already
watched "Meet StoreKit 2"
or "Manage in-app purchases
on your server,"
I recommend you
take a look after this session
so you get the full story.
In this session, I'll first talk
about customer support
and how you can provide
contextual support
to your customers.
And because refunds are
a critical part of support,
my colleague, Joe,
will talk about handling refunds
and a new server API to inform
and improve the refund process.
Let's start with supporting
customers,
the benefits and the challenges
of providing scalable support
as your business
grows on the App Store.
Whether your app offers
auto-renewing subscriptions
or one-time in-app
purchases like consumables
or non-consumables,
we are introducing new StoreKit
and App Store server APIs
for you to help resolve
customer support issues in
a timely and efficient manner.
And in addition to providing
support,
these APIs will help you manage
your relationships
with existing customers after
you initially acquire them,
increase your overall retention,
improve customer satisfaction,
which can
lead to higher engagement,
and reduce churn that grows
your long-term revenue.
Today, if customers need help
for their in-app purchase,
they may either contact Apple
or you, the developer.
And based on the scenario,
customers can either use
Apple's self-service website,
"Report-A-Problem,"
or contact Apple Support
via phone, email, or chat
to address the issue.
Alternatively,
they may also contact you
via social media, forums,
or live-chat inside the app.
And when they contact you
about an in-app purchase,
the issue may fall into
one of these scenarios.
From identifying customer's
in-app purchases or refunds,
to providing compensation
for a service issue
or an outage,
or helping them manage
their subscription
or request a refund,
these questions cover most
of the support scenarios,
and I'll walk through each
scenario in more detail.
Let's start with the first
scenario,
how do you identify
the purchases made by a customer
when they first contact you
for support?
Now, if you've purchased any
content on the App Store,
you may already have seen
this email.
Today, when customers
make an in-app purchase,
they receive an invoice
for that purchase via email.
This invoice contains
an order ID,
which is unique
for each invoice.
And customers have access
to this via email or by
looking at the purchase history
under account settings.
And now, when a customer
contacts you for support,
you can ask the customer
for the order ID
on their invoice and use a new
server-to-server API
to lookup in-app purchases
for the invoice
presented by the customer.
In addition to validating
the invoice,
this API also helps you identify
any issues
with the in-app purchase.
For example,
if the invoice contains
any purchases that have already
been refunded by the App Store.
Now, let's take a look
at how this API works.
So now, when a customer
contacts your support team,
you can ask the customer
for the invoice order ID,
and your server can call
the invoice lookup API,
and, in response,
the App Store returns a status
and the transactions for that
invoice signed in a JWS format.
And finally,
using this information,
you can provide support
for the correct
in-app purchases.
To implement
this API on your server,
you can call the lookup endpoint
with the invoice order ID
in the URL
and the Apple ID
for the app in the request.
The response includes
a signedTransactions object,
which contains the transactions
for that invoice
signed in a JWS format.
You can decode the payload
for each transaction
to get the details
of the purchase.
Now, let's take a closer look
at the new status field.
This field
identifies the overall
status of the invoice.
The possible values are 0,
meaning the invoice is valid
and contains transactions
for this order ID,
1, meaning the order ID
is invalid,
and 2,
meaning the invoice is valid,
but no matching transactions
were found for this order ID.
Now, let's review an example
of how you can use
the response from this API.
Here's a sample customer
account database
where you might be storing
the originalTransactionId
for each customer's
in-app purchase,
along with the productID
and the purchase date.
Using this API, you can link
the invoice order ID
with the customer's
in-app purchases
when they
contact you about an issue.
For example, if this customer
purchased coins in your app,
and if they contact you
for support,
you can store the invoice order
ID for the purchased coins.
Now, let's take a scenario
where you have
the originalTransactionId
for a customer,
and you want to lookup
their past refunds.
Today, you might be relying
on verifyReceipt API
or App Store server
notifications
to get notified about refunds.
However, if there was an outage,
and your server did not
receive any notifications
from the App Store,
how do you lookup this
customer's past refunds?
We are introducing
a new server-to-server API
to lookup refunded transactions
for a customer
using the original
transaction ID
for any of their in-app
purchases within your app.
This API enables you
to handle an outage
or scheduled maintenance
by looking up refunds
at any time
in a quick and easy manner.
Additionally,
this API can also help you
identify the customer's entire
refund history for your app.
For example,
if your app offers
both subscriptions
and consumables,
this API returns all
the refunded transactions
across all your content types.
To implement this API
on your server,
you create the request
with original transaction ID
in the URL
and the Apple ID for the app
in the request parameters.
The response contains
a list of refunded transactions
signed in a JWS format.
You can get the all
the information needed
about the purchases
by decoding the payload
for each transaction.
So, going back to the sample
customer account database,
you can now use the information
returned by this API
to update
the refunded transactions
for this customer using
the original transaction ID.
Now, after you've identified
there was a service issue,
how do you compensate customers?
Today, there a few different
options to consider.
For games, you might
be providing some form
of in-app compensation
in the form of virtual currency
or content.
Or for subscriptions,
you may want to offer
a discount
on their next renewal.
So, how do you compensate
subscribers for a service issue?
In iOS 14,
we introduced a new feature
called Subscription Offer Codes
to help you acquire,
retain, and win back
subscribers
by providing a subscription
at a discount
or free for a limited time.
You can distribute these unique,
one-time codes
either using online
or offline channels.
And for customer service issues,
you can provide offer codes
as a compensation for the issue,
which helps improve retention.
You may also use this as
an opportunity to suggest
an alternative subscription.
For example,
a longer duration plan
that provides
more value at a lower price.
And customers on iOS
14 and iPadOS 14 and later
can redeem
offer codes on the App Store
through a one-time
code redemption URL
or within your app,
if you've implemented
the presentCodeRedemptionSheet
API in StoreKit.
Now, let's take a look
at a sample
code-redemption flow
within your app.
The only custom UI you
need to create is the one
that initiates
the redemption flow.
There are several natural
places to provide this UI.
For example,
in your app's settings screen
or inside a live-chat
functionality
when the customer is chatting
with your support agent.
After the customer taps
the redeem button,
the system automatically
provides a series
of code-redemption screens,
like the ones shown here,
for the customer to enter
the code and redeem the offer.
Now, let's take a look
at a scenario
where there was an outage
or an event was canceled,
which might be more common
for streaming-based apps,
such as sports, live TV,
or video.
For these
outages or canceled events,
how can you appease customers?
We are introducing a new
server-to-server API
for auto-renewable
subscriptions,
to extend the renewal date
for a paid active subscription.
With this API, you can offer
free service to your customers
for additional time,
which can be used
as an appeasement for temporary
outages or service issues.
You can move the renewal date
for a customer's subscription
twice per calendar year,
each up to 90 days
in the future,
giving you flexibility
to resolve service issues
or outages.
Note that the extension period
does not count towards
the one year of paid service
needed to receive
an 85% proceeds rate.
Now, let's see
how you can implement
this API on your server.
The request for this API
requires an original
transaction ID for the
customer's subscription,
the extension duration, in days,
and a reason code
for the extension.
The response contains
the transaction ID
that was
passed in the request,
the web order line item ID
for the extended renewal,
a success flag to indicate
whether the request succeeded
and an effective date
for the extension
if the request succeeded.
Now, let's take a look
at two different scenarios
where you can use this API.
In the first scenario,
when a customer contacts
your support team for
a service issue or an outage,
you can appease the customer
by calling this API,
and, in response,
the App Store extends
the subscription and notifies
the customer via email.
Or a second scenario,
if there is a cancellation
to a sports match due
to unforeseen situations,
or an interruption
to a live-streamed event,
your support team can
proactively use this API,
and in response,
the App Store extends
the subscription and notifies
the customers via email.
Now, for a scenario where
a customer wants
to manage their subscription,
how can you enable customers
to manage their subscription
right inside the app?
We are introducing
a new StoreKit 2 API
to display
the manage subscriptions page,
which enables you to provide
subscription management
functionality
right within your app,
without redirecting customers
to the App Store.
Optionally, you can also present
a save offer before they see
the manage subscriptions page,
or an exit survey
after they cancel to get
the cancellation reason.
And with this API,
you can also test
managing subscription purchases
in the sandbox environment.
This API is really
simple to implement,
and it takes one line of code.
You simply call the
showManageSubscriptions()
method in StoreKit 2 to display
the manage subscriptions page.
Now, let's take a look at a
sample manage subscription UI
in your app.
Under account settings,
we can add an option
for the user to manage
their subscription.
Once the customer
taps on this button,
the App Store will display
the existing
manage subscriptions page,
with the currently-active
subscription
and the renewal options.
This is the same view
customers are familiar with
with when they visit manage
subscriptions
under account
settings in the App Store,
where they can view,
upgrade, downgrade,
or cancel their subscription.
Now, if the customer selects
to cancel their subscription,
they will
see a confirmation screen
with the cancellation details
and the service expiration date.
And for any action the user
may take on this page,
your server
will receive an App Store
server notification,
and your app will be notified
if you've implemented
the new StoreKit 2 API.
Finally,
if a customer is unhappy
with their purchase and wants
to request a refund,
they shouldn't have to leave
your app to get help.
So, how can you enable
customers to request a refund
inside your app?
We are now introducing a new
StoreKit 2 API called
beginRefundRequest that enables
customers to request a refund
for an in-app purchase
directly from within your app.
And if the refund is approved,
your app will be notified
and your server receives
a REFUND notification
from the App Store.
Or if the refund is denied,
your server receives
a new REFUND-DECLINED
notification.
And for the first time,
using this API,
you can now initiate
and test refunds in sandbox,
right within the app.
To implement this API,
you simply call
the beginRefundRequest method
with the transaction
ID for that purchase.
And after the request
is submitted,
you can handle errors using
the do-catch statement.
For example, if this was
a duplicate request
for a transaction
that was already refunded,
or if the request failed
for some other reason,
the error code reflects the
status of the refund request.
Here's a sample refund
request UI in your app.
In the Help page,
now there's a new option
to "Request a Refund."
Upon selection,
the app displays purchases
for that customer
to request a refund.
And if the power surge purchase
did not work as expected,
the customer can tap on that
purchase to invoke
a refund request sheet, which
contains the purchase details
and a list of reason codes
for the customer to select.
Once the request is submitted,
in addition to
the in-app confirmation screen,
the App Store also sends
the customer an email
with a link
to Apple's "Report a Problem,"
where they can check
the status of their refund.
So, with the new APIs,
you can now provide contextual
and seamless support
for in-app purchases
right within your app and across
other support channels.
Providing good support
increases overall retention,
improves customer satisfaction,
which leads
to higher engagement,
and ultimately, more positive
ratings and reviews.
In other words, it's a better
experience for everyone.
Now, we talked about how you can
offer customers a way
to request refunds using the new
refund request API,
but there is a lot
more to refunds that happens
after initiating a request.
So, I'm going to invite
my colleague, Joe,
to talk more about
handling refunds
and a new opportunity with
regards to refund decisioning.
[Joe] Thanks, Manjeet.
Hello, my name is Joe Mani,
and I'm a program manager
at the App Store.
Refunds are a sensitive topic,
and here at the App Store,
we take it seriously.
It affects a small
percentage of transactions,
but we understand the impact
it has on your apps.
I want to start with a quick
recap on refund notifications,
which was launched at WWDC20.
Then, I will give some insight
into how we handle refunds.
Finally, we will talk
about a new feature,
which will help you inform
and improve the refund process.
In WWDC20, we announced
a new notification type
called REFUND.
After a customer
is issued a refund,
the App Store sends the REFUND
notification to your server.
If you have configured a server
URL in App Store Connect,
you may already be receiving
REFUND notifications.
When your server receives
this notification,
respond with a successful
HTTP status code 200.
Then, you can take
appropriate action
for the refund in response.
Since the launch
of REFUND notifications,
we've had a chance
to hear your feedback,
and I'd like to share some
best practices with you.
Find the best response
strategy that works
for your business model.
For example, if a user purchases
in-game currency,
and then requests a refund,
you can deduct the balance
from their account
after your server receives
the REFUND notification.
While, for a subscription, you
can revoke access to the service
once the subscription has
been refunded and canceled.
Consider the impact
on game design
when identifying
your response strategy.
Use marketing
and promotional tools
to re-engage customers,
and always provide
clear messaging
to your customer across
your communication channels
on any actions you have taken.
Let's look at a sample
refund timeline for an app
that offers coins
as in-game currency.
After a customer purchases
100 coins,
they may immediately spend those
coins within your game.
If the customer then
requests a refund
using the new
request refund API,
or by contacting Apple Support.
And if the refund is approved,
the App Store will
issue a refund, send your server
a refund notification,
and notifies the customer
as well.
And this usually happens
within a 48-hour window.
Now, let's take a look
into what happens
after the refund is requested
and before the App Store
issues a decision.
At a high level, each refund
request will go through
our Refund Decisioning System
to render a decision.
The Refund Decisioning System
includes information
about the transaction
at issue and other factors,
such as the customer's
purchase and refund history.
Now, we've heard from you
that you like to have
a more active role
in refund decisions,
so we're excited to announce
a new feature that will
you improve and inform
the refund process.
With the new Consumption API,
you can share information
about a customer's in-app
purchase with the App Store.
When a customer requests
a refund
for a consumable
in-app purchase,
the App Store will send your
server a new notification
called CONSUMPTION-REQUEST,
for you to respond back
with the consumption data.
In most cases, customers
start consuming content
soon after they purchase it,
and knowing this information
is helpful
in the refund
decision process.
Make sure to send consumption
information to the App Store
with 12 hours of receiving
the CONSUMPTION-REQUEST,
so that it can be used to inform
the refund decision.
Now, let's take a look
at what fields are included
within the consumption data.
The consumption payload contains
the following data points,
each of which helps to inform
the refund decision.
First, you include
the original transaction ID
for the in-app purchase
in the request URL.
Set the customerConsented
field to "true"
if the user has consented
to sending the requested
consumption API data to Apple,
in order for Apple to use that
data in decisioning.
The consumptionStatus
field is important.
Use it to indicate if
the user has consumed
the in-app purchase partially,
fully, or not at all.
For example, if your app has
an exchange platform
that has bartering
or has an in-app purchase
that has been transferred
from one account to another,
it is considered consumed.
The consumption platform
field identifies
if your app is cross platform
and where it was consumed.
Use the sampleContent field
to indicate if you provided
a free sample or trial
to the user,
or if the user was given
a similar in-app purchase
within the app.
Alternatively,
use this field to indicate
if the user
was provided information
about the in-app purchase
and the expected game play
or mechanics
prior to the purchase.
Use the deliveryStatus
field to indicate
the in-app purchase
was successfully delivered
to the customer and that
it functioned properly.
The appAccountToken is a new
field introduced in StoreKit 2.
This will be the UUID
associated with
the app's user account
that you create
that is initiating the purchase
and consuming the content
for the purchase.
The remaining fields include
information about how long
the user has had an account,
how much time they've
played in your app,
their total spend,
and the current status
of their account.
For a refund request, there are
three related App Store
server notifications:
the new CONSUMPTION-REQUEST
notification
to notify you
when a refund request
has been initiated for
a consumable in-app purchase.
For all content types,
the REFUND notification
notifies you when a refund
is issued to a customer.
And for all content types,
the REFUND-DECLINED notification
notifies you
when a refund was declined
for a request that was initiated
using the Store Kit API.
Now let's return
to the refund timeline.
When the customer requests
a refund
for a consumable
in-app purchase,
the App Store server will now
send your server
a consumption request
notification.
Your server responds
back within 12 hours
with the consumption data
back to the App Store server,
which will then be
used for decisioning.
If it is approved,
the App Store will send
the REFUND notification,
and after
your server responds
with an HTTP OK response,
you can take appropriate
action for that refund.
And the consumption API
is available
both in production and to test
in sandbox as of today.
Now let's cover some
of the benefits
of sending
information to Apple
with the new Consumption API.
Obtaining these data points
will help increase transparency
and improve our overall
refund process.
This, in turn, provides
a better overall outcome
to your customers.
Also, with the new
REFUND notification,
you have more opportunities
to reach your customer,
thus increasing
the overall communication.
Now, I'd like to pass it back
to my colleague, Manjeet,
to share some key take-aways
from everything we've covered.
[Manjeet] So, we
covered a lot of topics today.
Let me go through the key
takeaways for this session.
With the new StoreKit APIs,
you can now implement
a custom help UI
in your app
for customers
to request a refund
and for subscriptions,
a way to manage
their subscription
within the app.
Review and optimize your
customer support journeys
by implementing the new
server-to-server APIs.
For example,
use the invoice lookup API
to identify and validate
a customer's in-app purchase.
And if you haven't already,
setup your server
to receive the refund,
consumption request,
and other
status update notifications
from the App Store.
Identify the response strategy
that works best
for your app's business model
to take action upon refunds.
And finally,
you can now inform Apple's
refund decisioning system
by responding to consumption
request notifications
from the App Store by sending
latest consumption data.
So, this was "Support customers
and handle refunds."
For more information on the new
StoreKit 2 APIs,
watch "Meet StoreKit 2,"
and for more information
on building server-side logic
for in-app purchases,
watch "Manage in-app purchases
on your server."
Thanks for listening today,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[percussive music]