[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Mathieu Tozer:
Hi, I'm Mathieu Tozer,
and I'm an engineer
on the macOS SwiftUI team.
SwiftUI is a multiplatform
framework at its core,
with the goal of making it easy
to build great apps everywhere.
When approaching
any new concept or API,
we take a step back and consider
what each platform
expects from that feature.
What's great about SwiftUI
is that its APIs and concepts
apply to all platforms,
and in this talk
we're going to show
how those are fine-tuned
for the Mac.
This is a code-along,
where you'll be downloading
a skeleton project
and writing a Mac app with me.
Before we start, let's look over
some of the key principles
that go into great Mac apps
that we'll refer back to
while working on our app.
These are flexible, familiar,
expansive, and precise.
Mac Apps are flexible,
adjusting to how each of us
individually use them.
This starts with how
we physically use our Macs
from keyboards, mice, trackpads,
switch controls, even iPads --
and then extends
to the software itself.
I can customize my workflow
by adjusting table columns,
sidebars, detail panels,
display modes,
and windows in a way
that suits me best,
and the interface will adapt.
And at the same time,
Mac apps are familiar.
Using controls
and design patterns
consistent with the system
makes an app
immediately approachable, thanks
to a common visual language.
For example, the File menu
is where I always reach
to create new things,
and the search bar
has a consistent look
across all my app toolbars.
You can make your app
more approachable
by zoning out areas of a window,
keeping navigation
and hierarchy in the sidebar,
content in the center,
and user functions along the top
and right-hand side.
But that consistency can still
leave room for apps to be unique
and stand out among others.
You can add customization,
such as the app accent color.
And when you find you need
a custom control,
it should be designed to fit in
with the system controls.
Mac apps are expansive.
Large, often multiple displays
mean more information
can be organized on screen
without being hidden away
in drill-in style
navigation stacks.
Concretely, expansive means
using controls like sidebars
with outline views
and thumbnail previews,
popovers for transient elements,
tabs to toggle between
panes of controls,
and disclosure groups
to display content.
Finally, Mac apps are precise.
They not only have
large windows,
but their views also have
tighter margins and spacing
that results in high densities
of content and controls,
and these controls are designed
to be used with a mouse pointer.
All that said, increased density
doesn't need to result
in increased complexity;
an app that serves a simple,
single purpose
can still be a great Mac app.
You probably recognize
these ideas
from your favorite Mac apps.
We'll next be applying
these ideas in practice.
I'm going to be building
a Mac app with you.
Hit Pause here and
download the project,
which will contain the starting
and end points for this session.
I really like to garden.
I think it would be great
to have a dedicated app
to track my gardens
over the years.
We're going to build this app
for the Mac.
We'll take advantage
of platform features
such as flexible windowing
and high information density,
enabling me to really interact
with my app's data
in a way that feels great
on macOS.
On the left, I have a sidebar
showing an outline view
of all my garden projects.
I can select a garden
and see all the plant details
in a table view,
or as a gallery.
Let's start implementing
this app.
Open up the Session1.workspace
in the starter project.
We have a garden structure that
contains an array of plants,
and we have some views and
helpers to speed us along,
but we'll get started
in the ContentView.
I'm just going
to collapse my sidebar
and make some room
for my Xcode previews.
Our Mac app will have
a two-column layout.
I'm going to embed this text view
in a NavigationView.
I'm going to remove
the padding,
and I'll change the text
to a Sidebar.
The second column
will be for our Plant Table.
This flattened hierarchy
provides a solid foundation
for an expansive
navigation experience
on the Mac's big screens.
Let's get going
on our sidebar.
If I Command-click,
I can extract this view
into its own subview,
and I'll rename it to "Sidebar".
I need access to my store.
And I want to show a list of my
gardens in the current year.
And we'll show each garden's
name in a label
with the leaf systemImage.
I'd like to be able to see
which gardens are current,
put the history
in its own section,
and then control precisely
what I see
by clicking
disclosure triangles.
We'll use a DisclosureGroup,
which flattens our
navigation system out even more
while providing a familiar way
to manage complexity.
I'm going to change
the list to a ForEach,
and if I Command-click,
I can choose
to embed it in a list.
We've already got the content
we iterate over defined,
so we can just clear that out.
Now, this expression
is equivalent
to what we had before,
but now we can embed the
ForEach in a DisclosureGroup.
And for the systemImage,
well, this one's a bit of
a mouthful but here we go.
We'll use the
chart.bar.doc.horizontal image.
OK, great.
I have my gardens
organized in
an outline structure,
giving me the flexibility
to control what I see.
But I'd like the current group
to be open by default,
and for the expansion state
to persist
each time I open the app, which
makes my app more familiar.
To save the expansionState,
we'll add a property
to the Sidebar.
I'll annotate it with the
@SceneStorage property wrapper,
providing a key
of expansionState.
This will tell SwiftUI
to offload this property
when the app quits
and reload it when
the window is restored.
Now I'll pass a binding along
to the DisclosureGroup
for the current year...
...and now the current group
is expanded.
I think my sidebar
is a little tight,
so I'm just going to set
a minimum width.
I'll show the history
in a section,
and I'll use
a GardenHistoryOutline view
I made earlier.
I'll pass that expansionState
along as well.
I'm going to add a badge
to highlight when
my poor plants need water.
OK, in order to see
the details on the right,
I'll need to add selection.
We'll add a binding to the ID
of the selected garden.
And then we can
provide that selection
as a binding to the list.
The Sidebar's parent,
the ContentView,
will hold on to the value,
passing down bindings
to the sidebar and the table.
So I'm going to copy this
up here, too,
and I'm going to pop it into
@SceneStorage
so that it will persist
between runs.
And I'll pass it along
to the Sidebar as well.
I think my sidebar
is looking good.
I can control what I see
with disclosure triangles,
and if my Mac restarts,
things will be restored
to just how I left it.
We can get started on
the GardenDetail view now.
It takes a binding
to the selection as well.
And if I Command-click,
I can jump to
the definition of the view.
This view already contains
properties to our store
and some others
we'll use shortly.
It's also set up to show
the garden's name and year
as the navigationTitle
and Subtitle.
We'll implement the table in its
own variable on the detail view,
and we'll use it here
from the body.
Let's start by simply showing
a list of the garden's plants.
We could display
other plant properties
in a horizontal stack view, but
we have a lot of data to show,
and a lot of it is textual.
Also, we'd like to add
the ability to sort the plants
alphabetically
or in the order we planted.
For these reasons,
we'll display plants in a table.
A table offers
a precise way to view,
filter, sort, and edit our data
in an expansive UI,
making good use
of screen space.
Generally, if you have
visual elements to show
and don't need complex sorting,
use a list.
Otherwise, if you need
multiple columns,
consider a table.
I'm going to replace the list
with a table
and provide some columns
to divide each row by.
And easy as that, I have
a table with a single column!
So let's add
some more columns.
I want to know how long it will
take for each plant to grow,
so I'm going to add
a column for that.
Instead of providing a key path,
I'm going to open up the content
closure for the TableColumn,
and it will be handed a plant.
Now, we can provide
any view we like here,
but the daysToMaturity property
is an integer,
so we'll provide a text view
with a formatted string.
I have a lot of plants,
and I'm always planting more.
Being able to select
and sort the rows
will help keep our plants
organized.
So first we can add a binding
to the selection.
When making the table
sortable,
we need to make sure
we provide a sortOrder binding
and a key path to each column.
So we'll need to add a key path
to the daysToMaturity column.
To really flex the power
of the table,
let's paste in some more columns
from the TableColumns file
in the Views folder.
They'll let us set
some key dates
and flag a plant as a favorite.
I'm going to switch off previews
for now and run the app.
Look at all this plant data!
I can select rows,
and I can click on
column headers to sort them.
This is great, but right now
I don't have a way
to perform many basic actions
needed to manage a garden,
such as adding
a new plant to the table
or marking multiple plants
as watered.
The toolbar is a familiar place
for these kinds of actions --
it's a standard location
that macOS users
can discover ways
to use your app.
We can add a toolbar here,
starting with a button
to add a plant.
We'll give it a label
with the title, "Add Plant"
and the systemImage "plus".
I'm going to build and run,
and now I can add a plant
to my table!
Customization
over our app's interface
can also be surfaced
in the toolbar,
such as how we'd prefer
to view the garden.
We can add the
DisplayModePicker here.
I've got a lot of plants,
and while I can order them,
it would be great to narrow down
the number of rows
quickly and precisely.
We always have immediate access
to a hardware keyboard
on the Mac,
so I'm going to add
the searchable modifier
to the Table, passing in
a binding to the searchText.
The searchText is a property
on the detail view
that we use to filter
the plants array
that gets handed to the table.
And that's all we need to do
to add search filtering!
We've got the structure
of our window set up,
but I'd really like to be able
to see my veggie patch
and my backyard flower bed
at the same time.
Well, it turns out that
we already have this ability.
I can open up a new window
from the File menu,
and each window
has its own selection
and sidebar expansion state.
Each toolbar, of course,
belongs to its own window,
so I can add plants to the
veggie patch or the flower bed.
My plants need watering
regularly.
I'd like to be able
to sort and filter my plants,
select some rows, and mark those
as watered all at once.
We'll add commands to do these
actions to the macOS main menu.
The menu is a familiar piece of
UI that can even be searched,
helping people explore your app.
Before adding
our custom commands,
let's begin by adding
some commands
that the system provides for us.
Move over to the GardenApp file.
I'm going to add
the commands modifier
to the WindowGroup,
and add the SidebarCommands().
Now the sidebar can be toggled
from the View menu
or with a keyboard shortcut.
Now for our custom commands.
Open the PlantCommands file
in the Main Menu folder.
I want to be able
to send actions to the garden
in the front-most window,
so I'll need a garden variable.
We'll use a @FocusedBinding
property wrapper,
passing in a key path
to a custom property
that I've defined in an
extension on FocusedValues.
The plant command menu
items will also need to know
which plants are selected
in the table
so we can check them off
as watered,
so we'll need to pass
the selection up, too.
Moving onto the body,
you'll notice that commands
are declared similarly to views,
meaning you can make your own
and build a custom tree
of commands
to represent your menus.
First up is
the add plant action.
Now, while we can already
add a plant from the toolbar,
the main menu should contain
all the possible actions
your app can perform,
whereas the toolbar,
normally just some subset
as a convenience.
Since this is an action
to create something,
we'll put it
in a familiar place.
Using a CommandGroup,
we'll place it before
the newItem in the File menu.
For my watering action,
I want to put it in
a new CommandMenu
called "Plants".
This will appear next to
the View menu in our app.
These views simply
contain buttons
that mutate the garden,
and modifiers to define
the button behavior.
We have multiple windows,
but only ever one menu bar.
I don't want to put carrots
in my flower bed,
so how can the menu
know which garden
to send the action to?
Back in the GardenDetail view,
I'll add the focusedSceneValue
modifier to the table,
passing in my key path
and a binding.
I'll do the same
for the selection.
This tells the system
to expose these values
for the given key path when
the entire scene is in focus.
Finally, in the GardenApp file,
we need to add our new commands
after the SidebarCommands()
we added earlier.
SwiftUI will then know
to add them to the main menu.
I can now insert a plant
into the garden
in the front-most window
from the main menu.
I can also select plants that
need to be marked as watered,
and do so from the Plants menu.
Adding menus
to all your app's actions
increases the flexibility
of your app
by enabling keyboard shortcuts
and offering different ways
to get things done in your app.
It also aids the discoverability
of actions,
empowering people to explore and
discover your app's features.
Speaking of, in part two,
you'll be adding more features
and polish to your app
with Jeff,
including an accent color,
drag and drop between tables,
and how to take and attach
a photo of a plant
with an iOS device.
We've covered a lot today.
We've built the interface
for a Mac app from the ground up
using SwiftUI, and shown
how each component
contributes to what can
make a great Mac app.
Thanks for watching!
♪