[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Daniel Sykes-Turner: Hi,
my name is Daniel Sykes-Turner
and I'm an accessibility
engineer.
In this talk,
my colleague Virata and I
are going to go over
some of the accessibility
features on watchOS
and how you as a developer
can build your watch apps
to support the people
who use these features.
In today's talk,
you'll first be introduced
to accessibility on watchOS.
Then I'll dive into
the accessibility APIs
and show you
what you can do to support
different types
of visual accessibility.
And finally,
Virata will walk you through
how motor accessibility
works on the watch
and what you can do
to support it.
Let's get started with
accessibility on watchOS.
Accessibility is about people
using their devices
in the way that's best for them.
And that means, to give your app
the best user experience,
accessibility
must be considered.
On the Apple Watch,
we have a large suite
of accessibility features
that can make
using your app easier.
For example, assistive
technologies such as VoiceOver
allow people
with visual impairments
full use of their Apple Watch
by navigating a screen using
a series of gestures and taps
while content
is read back to them.
And brand new on watchOS
this year is AssistiveTouch,
which has been reimagined
specifically
for the Apple Watch.
AssistiveTouch allows
those with motor impairments
to use their Apple Watch
without the need
to touch the screen at all.
Virata will show you
how this works later on
and what you can do
to support it.
watchOS also offers
several display accommodations
such as Reduce Motion,
Bold Text,
and also new this year,
large accessibility text sizes.
Let's talk about visual
accessibility on watchOS.
Supporting accessibility
with the right APIs will ensure
that VoiceOver functions
correctly for your users,
regardless of whether
your app is written
with WatchKit or SwiftUI.
This talk will focus
on accessibility for SwiftUI.
However, know that all
the principles you learn here
will apply to WatchKit as well.
And when making your apps
accessible,
don't forget about complications
and notifications.
Complications
and dynamic notifications
also need to support
our assistive technologies,
as they act as another path
delivering content
from your app.
Now, isn't the best way
to learn something new
to build an app?
Luckily I've become
quite invested
in growing plants at home
so I decided to go ahead
and build an app
to help take care of them.
Now, it's not quite finished,
but on the main screen here
I have all the information
on my plants,
including an upcoming schedule
of plant care tasks:
water in five days,
fertilize in seven days,
and keep in a medium amount
of sunlight.
I have a few other plants
in the list here, too.
Then for each plant, I have
two buttons that I can use
to log a task such
as when I water or fertilize.
And by tapping on the cell,
I can adjust the number of days
between watering
and fertilizing.
Since this is
an informative app,
each cell contains
a fair amount of text.
Here I'm showing you
what the app looks like
when the system text size
is at its default size;
it looks pretty good.
But if I change the system
text size to extra small,
as shown on the left,
you'll notice that
while the buttons
and the task list text resizes,
the plant name title
stays the same size.
Then when I move up
to accessibility extra large
on the right,
the task list text size
has grown so large
that it has truncated
and no longer fits all
the information on the screen.
Let's take a look at how
our app can better support
Dynamic Type.
If I inspect the code
for my PlantView,
I have a VStack with the title
and other content inside.
Notice the font
I've used for my title
is using a fixed font size.
That's definitely going to stop
my title from changing size.
Rather than using
a fixed font size,
I should be using one
of the 11 text styles provided.
The text styles on the left
are displayed
at the default system text size.
And when scaled up
to the largest text size,
they grow to the size
of the text styles on the right.
By using a text style,
the system will automatically
adjust the font size
with the system
text size settings.
So if I take a look
at my PlantView code again,
I can make that change
quickly and easily
by changing my title font
to the title3 text style
for a smaller-sized title.
Next let's fix the truncating
text in the task list.
In the code for
my PlantTaskLabel,
I'm assigning a lineLimit of 1
to everything in the HStack,
which only allows the text
to expand over a single line.
To give your UI
the flexibility to adjust
to as many lines as needed,
set the lineLimit
to the maximum number of lines
you need to support.
Or remove it to allow
an unlimited number of lines.
Now we're making progress.
But while the UI
certainly is larger
and there's no more truncation,
in the process it's become
a lot more crowded.
And it's still not easy to read
the information on the screen.
Sometimes layouts
for larger text styles
just need to be structured
differently.
So when building the layout,
I'll create
an Environment property wrapper
on the sizeCategory
to get updates
whenever this changes.
Next, I just need
to adjust my UI
to depend on the sizeCategory.
In this case,
the text in the task list
starts wrapping somewhere
around extraExtraLarge.
So if the size category
is less than this,
I'll use the PlantView
we've seen before.
But if it's larger, I'll use
this new vertical plant view
that stacks each of my labels
and buttons,
giving them much more
space to grow.
That looks much better.
With the introduction of large
accessibility text styles
on the watch, we expect to see
a lot more people
making use of Dynamic Type --
and so should you!
For people setting up
their Apple Watch,
they will now see the option
to customize the text size
when getting started.
And if they don't
make any changes,
the watch will
automatically pick
the closest size to what is
used on the phone.
So to recap Dynamic Type,
there are three key things
to make sure watch apps
behave great
with larger text sizes.
First, you want to make sure
to always use a text style,
not a fixed font size.
Second, allow your text to wrap
to avoid truncating.
And third,
when necessary,
switch to
a vertically stacked layout
when the content
becomes too crowded.
Since this only scratches
the surface on large text,
I'd strongly recommend
you check out the talk,
"Building apps
with Dynamic Type"
to really step up your game.
And to learn even more about
making great visual experiences,
be sure to check out the talk,
"Make your app
visually accessible."
OK, so visually,
that works great.
But what if I weren't
a visual user?
Let's turn on VoiceOver
and have a listen
to what the experience is like.
VoiceOver: WWDaisy.
Daisy, image.
Drop, image.
Five days.
Leaf, image.
Seven days.
Brightness higher, image.
Medium.
Drop, fill, button.
Leaf, fill, button.
Daniel: OK,
so there are definitely
some improvements we can make.
The first would be to reduce
the number of elements
that can be interacted with.
At the moment,
this is a rather complex view.
Each cell has four labels,
four images, and two buttons.
And currently,
to get to the second plant,
I have to navigate past every
item in the first plant cell.
Also the image icons for water,
fertilize, and sunlight
were read out as
separate elements to the text,
and their labels didn't even
make sense for our context.
Lastly, the two buttons
at the bottom
were using the default labels
provided by the symbols
being used.
So the first issue
we talked about
is that I have to navigate
through too many items
just to move from plant one
to plant two.
When I created
my NavigationLink,
I did this by specifying
accessibilityElement grouping
of the children as .contain,
just to understand
the accessibility state
of each element.
But since this is looking good,
I'll remove this line,
and NavigationLink
will combine all
the accessibility information
from the children automatically.
Now the cell is treated
as a single element
and the content read out is,
"WWDaisy. Five days.
Seven days. Medium. Button."
That task list still needs
some work so next,
let's provide some context
to the upcoming plant-care tasks
by giving each a better label.
The label is determined
by the PlantTask.
So inside
my PlantTaskLabel struct,
I'll just alter
the accessibilityLabel
to return a different string
for each plant task.
This is the same technique
that I'll use
to put labels on my buttons.
Now the content is read out as,
"WWDaisy. Watering in five days.
Fertilizing in seven days.
Keep in medium sunlight.
Button."
And the water and fertilize
buttons will be read out as,
"Log watering, button"
and, "Log fertilizing, button."
So far, a lot of work
is done for us automatically,
with only a few additional
modifiers being needed.
In fact, with SwiftUI,
most of your accessibility
comes for free.
You'll probably just write
a few lines of code.
But every now and then,
you might need
to build a custom control.
I did by building
a custom counter
so that I could adjust
the watering
and fertilizing frequency
for my plants.
Let's take a look.
VoiceOver: Watering frequency
in days, heading.
Remove, button.
Eight.
Add, button.
Add.
Daniel: So while this
technically works,
it's not the ideal experience.
The goal here is
to turn these three items
into a single
accessible element.
To do this,
I'll begin by using
our accessibilityElement
modifier.
This will create
a new higher-level element;
but this time, I will ignore
all the children.
This is actually
the default behavior
for accessibilityElement.
So I can leave
the parameters blank
to get the same behavior.
And because
I'm ignoring the children,
this discards the Add
and Remove button labels
along with
the accessibility actions
that were provided
automatically.
Instead, I'll use
accessibilityAdjustableAction
to allow the user to increment
or decrement the value
by swiping up or down
on the counter.
And now that
I've only got one element,
I'll give it a single label
using the name of the task.
This will end up as
"Watering Frequency"
or "Fertilizing Frequency."
Finally, I'll give it a value.
The accessibilityValue is
read out each time it changes,
while the label
will only be read out
when navigating to the element.
VoiceOver: Watering frequency
in days, heading.
Watering frequency.
Eight days. Adjustable.
Nine days.
Daniel: Great.
That works much better.
As you just saw,
SwiftUI made it easy
to make our watch app accessible
to VoiceOver.
And what's great is that
because this is SwiftUI,
the same code works
on macOS and iOS as well.
To learn more about designing
a fantastic experience
with SwiftUI,
be sure to check out the talk,
"Accessibility in SwiftUI."
And to learn about the brand-new
tools and APIs when working
with SwiftUI accessibility,
check out the talk,
"SwiftUI accessibility:
Beyond the basics."
Now, before we move on
from visual accessibility,
I'd like to highlight
two more things:
complications and notifications.
Complications are a high-traffic
window into your app,
so, of course, they also
need to provide information
in an accessible way.
There are many different
types of complications
but most of them
will be made up
of three different components:
text, images, and symbols.
Text will be picked up
by VoiceOver automatically,
but if your text contains
abbreviations,
make sure to add
accessibility labels
with the nonabbreviated
versions.
Here we expand the abbreviated,
"Wednesday Mar 9"
to its full form of,
"Wednesday, March 9th."
Image-based complications
are also very common.
Be sure to provide
accessibility labels here too;
otherwise, the image name
will be used instead.
"Moon" isn't nearly
as descriptive as,
"A real-time view of the moon.
Third quarter."
Certain iconography
such as SF Symbols
may come with
a default accessibility label
such as "Drop, fill",
but just make sure
that the label
that comes with the symbol
is the one that makes
the most sense for you.
"Water in three days"
makes much more sense for me.
As for notifications,
these are another way your app
may send a lot of information
to your user.
So while some notifications
are fairly straightforward,
others such as
dynamic notifications
can have complex views
and so will need the same
accessibility support
that you've provided
for your app.
And now I'll turn you over
to Virata
to tell you all about
motor accessibility.
Virata Yindeeyoungyeon:
Well, thank you, Daniel.
My name is
Virata Yindeeyoungyeon.
I am an engineer
on the Accessibility team.
Today, I am very excited
to talk about
motor-accessibility support
on Apple Watch.
But before we dive into
the presentation,
let me give you a quick glance
of our new feature.
Without touching the screen
and only using hand gesture,
I am able to navigate
from the watch face
to the Control Center
to the Do Not Disturb button,
and then turn it on.
It is that simple.
This year,
we are very excited
to bring AssistiveTouch
to Apple Watch.
AssistiveTouch allows
full use of your Apple Watch
without touch,
using only the hand
that the Apple Watch is on.
People can use
hand gestures or hand motions
to navigate a cursor
around the screen.
They can bring up a menu to
access additional functionality
based on the screen content.
For some people,
this may be the only way
they can interact
with their Apple Watch.
For people
with motor impairments
such as missing limbs, loss of
functions of hands or arms,
AssistiveTouch
will enable more options
to allow control and performing
actions on Apple Watch.
Now let's see an example
on how people can use
AssistiveTouch.
The primary way
to use AssistiveTouch
is through hand gestures.
People are able
to perform different gesture
such as clench to tap,
double-clench to bring up
the action menu,
pinch to navigate
to the next element,
double-pinch to navigate
back to the previous element.
For those who are not able
to use hand gestures,
an alternative
is using hand motions.
By tilting their wrist,
people are able
to move the onscreen pointer and
interact with the UI elements.
Similar to AssistiveTouch
on iOS,
with Dwell Control
you can perform an action
by resting the pointer
over an element
for a set amount of time.
Now let's get into more detail
on how AssistiveTouch works.
AssistiveTouch is made up
of two main features:
the cursor
and the action menu.
When you turn on AssistiveTouch,
you see a cursor
appear on the screen.
The cursor will focus on
each element on the screen
one at a time, in order
from top left to bottom right.
The cursor
highlights the element
for further interactions.
For more actions
on the focused element,
you can bring up
the action menu
to perform system
or custom actions.
AssistiveTouch action menu
comes with
default system actions
that allow control of the device
such as pressing
on the Digital Crown,
scrolling navigation,
gesture interactions,
and much more.
You can also add custom actions
to this menu as well.
So now we know
how AssistiveTouch works.
Let's take a look at how we can
support it in your application.
We'll go over
these following topics.
First, we'll learn what
focusable elements are
in your view
and how we can modify them.
Then we'll take a look
at the cursor frame
and how we can change
the frame size.
Last, we'll talk more about how
to customize the action menu.
Let's begin with
focusable elements.
This table gives
a general overview
of which elements are focusable
by AssistiveTouch.
Only interactive elements
that respond
to user interaction
are focusable.
SwiftUI provides
built-in control elements
to handle user interactions;
these elements are interactive
and focusable.
In your view,
if you have a button,
a toggle,
or a NavigationLink,
these elements
can be focused by default.
Actionable elements
are focusable by AssistiveTouch
because they have an action or
are defined to be interactive.
A text element can become
interactive and focusable
by attaching
a tap gesture action.
You can also add
an accessibilityAction
to an element as well.
If you define an element
to have an actionable trait,
like a button or adjustable,
then it will be treated
as interactive
and would be focused
by AssistiveTouch.
Some elements
are not focusable.
Static elements
such as a label or a text
that do not respond
to user interaction
will not be focusable
by AssistiveTouch.
Elements with user interaction
disabled are also not focusable.
So let's see an example.
In this view,
we have a label header,
text with drink information,
Accept and Cancel
button elements.
Only the two buttons
are focusable,
while the label and text
are not.
Let's take a look at the code
for this view.
A tap gesture is attached
to the main VStack,
indicating that you can
tap on this view
to show the drink detailed view.
However, the static elements
inside the VStack
do not become focusable
unless explicitly declared.
Here, only the Accept and Cancel
buttons are focusable.
So how would a user know
that they can tap on the view
to show the drink detail view?
To provide
a better user experience,
I would like to highlight the
drink information text element
to show that it is interactable
and a tap can be performed.
This can be done by
setting "true" to
accessibilityRespondsToUser
Interaction modifier.
After applying the modifier,
we now have three focusable
elements in this view:
the drink information text,
Accept and Cancel
button elements.
Now let's learn more about
AssistiveTouch cursor frame.
As you can see,
the focused elements
are important for AssistiveTouch
to highlight if the element
is intractable or an action
can be performed.
The AssistiveTouch cursor frame
is the same as
the element's tappable area;
elements with
small tappable area
will have a small cursor frame
and it might
clip the content inside.
We can make this cleaner
by adding padding
and having the borders
match the shape of the object
to prevent clipping.
In this example,
a NavigationLink
with the ellipsis image
is highlighted
with a small circle
from the AssistiveTouch cursor.
We can improve on this
by increasing the size
of the tappable area,
which also changes the
AssistiveTouch cursor frame.
By providing a path
to the contentShape modifier,
you can change
the tappable area
and the cursor frame
of the element.
For this NavigationLink,
I set the tappable area shape
to be a circle one-and-a-half
times the size of the element.
As a result, the AssistiveTouch
cursor frame is larger
and the element is much easier
to see on the screen.
Now let's take a look at
AssistiveTouch action menu.
AssistiveTouch action menu
surfaces default system actions
and custom actions in your view
to show in
the action menu lists.
If the focus element
has custom actions,
those actions
will be prioritized
and shown at
the beginning of the list
so it's more convenient
to interact.
If the element is adjustable,
the decrement and increment
actions are shown.
If an accessibility group
element contains custom actions,
then those actions
will be surfaced
when focusing
on the group element.
If you have already added
custom actions for VoiceOver
in the element,
that's great!
These actions will
automatically show up
in the AssistiveTouch
action menu as well.
The custom actions
will be shown as an icon.
The default image will be
the first letter of
the custom action name.
If you want to provide an image
for your custom action icon,
you can add a label
with an image
to the accessibilityAction
modifier.
Well, that's the end
of our session.
Now you have
a better understanding
of accessibility features
on Apple Watch.
Remember to add
Dynamic Type, VoiceOver,
and AssistiveTouch support
in your application.
You have the tools
to use these APIs
and make
your watchOS application
accessible for everyone.
Well, thank you for your time
and enjoy the rest of WWDC!
♪