[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Edward: Hi,
and welcome to WWDC!
I'm Edward, an engineer
on the Wallet team,
and later I'll be joined
by my colleague, Russ.
We're very excited
to be here today
to talk to you about what's new
in Wallet and Apple Pay.
Today I'd like to talk
about three main areas.
First, I'd like to share
some Wallet updates
and tell you about
some exciting rollouts
we've had in the last year.
Second, we have made a lot of
exciting updates to Apple Pay.
We've also added
some new functionality,
making payments
even easier to use.
Third, I want to go through
some new API enhancements
that we've made.
So let's get started with
some updates to Wallet.
As you may have heard
in the Keynote,
we're bringing identity cards
to Apple Wallet.
Starting in the US,
with a few select states,
you can just scan
your driver's license
or state ID
and capture a selfie.
Your ID is protected
by the Secure Element.
The TSA is working to enable
airport security checkpoints
as the first place
you can use your digital ID.
For more information on this,
check out the links associated
with this session.
Also new in iOS 15,
we've added support
for HomeKit-connected locks,
so users can now tap to unlock
a door with a home key pass.
When it comes to adding passes,
we know many of your users
install them right from the web.
In iOS 14, if you wanted
to add four movie tickets,
for example,
you would add them individually.
New this year,
we've added multipass downloads
from Safari.
With a straightforward change,
you can bundle passes together,
making the experience smooth
for your users.
To do this,
you'll need to do three things.
First, zip the PkPass files
together.
Second, set the file extension
to .pkpasses.
And, finally,
use the correct mime type.
Now, all the passes
in the bundle will be downloaded
and processed by Wallet
in a single download.
And with all these passes,
it can sometimes be troublesome
for you to keep track
of them all.
We also know that many people
don't like to delete old passes,
preferring instead
to have them as keepsakes,
but that can make Wallet
kind of cluttered.
So new in iOS 15,
Wallet will now automatically
hide your expired passes,
keeping passes organized
and easy to find.
Let me show you an example
of how you can
take advantage of this.
Here we see some JSON
from an example pass.
Wallet looks at three fields
to determine if a pass
should be automatically hidden.
Number one, the pass
has an expiration date
that is older
than the current date.
Two, the relevant date
is older than one day.
Or three,
the pass has been voided.
To ensure a great experience
for your users,
you should ensure these fields
are set correctly
on your passes.
Now let me tell you about some
updates we've made to Apple Pay.
Apple Pay continues to be
the easiest way
to make payments on iPhone,
iPad, Apple Watch, and Mac.
It allows users to make payments
in apps and on the web.
Apple Pay is supported
in iMessage and Business Chat,
and also in App Clips
for streamlined,
in-the-moment experiences.
Apple Pay usage around the world
continues to grow.
We've added support
in Mexico, Israel,
and South Africa this year,
meaning Apple Pay
is now available in 55 countries
and regions across the globe.
We've added support
for Express Transit
in more locations.
And, we've included support for
combined credit and debit cards
in places such as Brazil.
Now, I'd like to show you
a few changes
that you can make
to your apps and websites
to create a great
payment experience.
Last year we added support
for more button types
such as Rent with Apple Pay
and Top Up with Apple Pay.
Today we're introducing
one more:
Continue with Apple Pay.
You should use this button when
offering Apple Pay in a cart
alongside other buttons.
You can use Continue
as a call to action.
We're also introducing a new
JavaScript implementation
for the Apple Pay button.
This new button supports all
current button types and styles.
It's easy to implement,
and can be customized
to match the design
of your sites.
Here is an example
implementation.
As you can see,
the button size and style
can be configured easily.
Note that the styles are
prefixed with "apple-pay".
For more information on this,
check out the documentation
on the Apple Developer Portal.
Next, I'd like to show you
the big changes we've made
to Apple Pay
for iPhone and iPad.
For iOS 15, we're excited
to make payments even better
with a brand-new
Apple Pay experience.
We rebuilt the Apple Pay sheet
from the ground up in SwiftUI
with an all-new design.
It gives users an even clearer
and smoother payment experience
with a great new look.
We also implemented
several new features
to improve conversion.
For users new to Apple Pay,
we simplified the flow
to add a card and addresses
from the payment sheet.
Existing users will be able
to add another card
without leaving
the Apple Pay experience.
We also redesigned
the error handling
for more clarity
when a problem does occur.
Once a user has finished adding
a new payment method,
they seamlessly resume
their transaction.
We also added a new summary view
which shows
more detailed information,
such as payment items,
discounts, and subtotals.
New for iOS 15,
we also display your app's icon
on the summary view.
For payments on the web,
we're now showing
the Web Clip icon
on the payment summary view.
In Apple Pay,
this was previously only visible
when using handoff from a Mac
to complete a transaction.
Now your website icon
is viewable within
the Apple Pay transaction
to provide visual reassurance
for the user
that payment is going
to the right place.
If you accept Apple Pay
on the web
and you haven't already set
a Web Clip icon,
we would strongly recommend you
make your icon visible to users.
To do this, you should provide
a 2x and 3x icon
at the sizes shown
in your root document folder.
Apple Pay will then
automatically retrieve
and display this icon
with the payment request.
Detailed information
on implementing this
is available in the Human
Interface Guidelines section
of the Apple Developer site.
While we're on the subject
of icon sizes,
I wanted to remind you of the
new icon size requirements
for your PKPasses.
Since notifications in iOS 15
now display a bigger icon,
you'll need to update
your PKPass icons
to a minimum of 38x38 at 1x
to ensure that your icons
are displayed without blurring.
We're also pleased
to introduce more flexibility
in the total line.
This will enable you
to add a date
if the payment occurs later;
for example,
if you take pre-orders
or to add the frequency
for a recurring payment.
Many of the new features
we've just observed can be added
to your apps with only
a few straightforward changes.
So we'll now take a closer look
into the API enhancements
we're introducing in iOS 15.
We're pleased to add support
for shipping date ranges.
Now you can present your users
with relevant shipping
or pickup times
within Apple Pay.
These can be used
to set estimated shipping
or delivery dates or time
windows for in-store pickups.
This extra information
is displayed
right on the main
Apple Pay view.
The new shipping date APIs
have built-in support
for calendars and time zones.
This makes the handling
of shipping dates
or pick up times in your app
straightforward
and the relevant information is
displayed clearly to your users.
Now I'll briefly show you
how this works.
We start by defining
a normal shipping method
using the same
PKShippingMethod as before.
Next, we choose a calendar.
In this example, we use
the user's current calendar.
We use today as a reference
and estimate the arrival
between three to seven days
from this date.
We then determine the start
and end date for our date range
using the calendar.
Finally, we convert the dates to
the appropriate date components
and then we add them
to the shipping method.
We use date components
rather than simple dates
so we can take advantage
of the rich calendar
and time zone support
built into iOS.
This enables use cases that
would otherwise not be possible.
For example, we can provide
the correct time zone
for a pickup time regardless
of the user's current time zone.
This level of detail
also allows us to show
the date and time information
most appropriate to the user,
such as displaying
a specific pickup time.
We've included
a JavaScript equivalent
for Apple Pay on the web.
You can see we specify
the date component range
a little differently
than we do in Swift.
Your date components
can be used in conjunction
with any of our supported
pickup types.
For example, you could display
a pickup time in your app.
In addition to date ranges,
you can now declare
a read-only shipping address.
You can use this
to inform the user
of a specific pickup location.
To enable this,
you must provide address details
as an instance of PKContact.
In this example,
we have created a postal address
as a CNMutablePostalAddress
so we can set all the address
components that we need.
You can now add
the shipping contact
to payment request.
Finally we declare
the editing mode
and specify the required
shipping fields.
The address fields
included in the PKContact
will be presented
to the user as read-only.
In this example, we've provided
a pick up postal address,
which the user
won't be able to edit.
And here's the equivalent
in JavaScript
for Apple Pay on the web.
You setup
a shippingContact dictionary,
set the shippingType,
the shippingContactEditingMode,
and the
requiredShippingContactFields,
and then you include
the other fields
for a JavaScript
payment request.
For more information, check out
the documentation available
on the Apple Pay section
of the Developer Portal.
Another great new feature
for iOS 15
is support for coupon codes.
Now your users can enter
promotional codes
once they've initiated
a payment.
This is intended so your users
don't have to cancel
their Apple Pay transaction
if they forgot to apply
a discount code.
You might also consider
implementing this
if you have an express purchase
flow where users can check out
from the product page
or the shopping cart,
but the coupon entry field
is only presented at checkout.
We've provided methods
to update the payment request,
so you can validate
the discount codes
or return error messages
when required.
Let's dive in
and take a look at the code.
You can make changes
using the delegate method
which performs updates
whenever the coupon code
is changed by the user.
For example, you could use this
to validate a code
and then update
any payment totals.
You also use the method
to return customized errors
or update the payment summary
items and shipping methods.
Russ will show you an example
of this in more detail shortly.
We recommend prepopulating
codes whenever possible,
as well as displaying
relevant error messages
for invalid codes.
I hope you've enjoyed these
exciting API enhancements
for iOS 15.
Now that we have talked
all about this in theory,
I'm going to hand you over
to Russ for a demo
so you can see how to implement
all these great new features.
Russ Fenenga: Thanks, Edward.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Russ,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Wallet team.
And I'm thrilled to be able
to demonstrate to you
some of the amazing
new features we have added
to the payment sheet in iOS 15
and how you can integrate them
into your apps.
So let's get started!
Here I have
my ticket purchasing app
for the food festival
I'm planning.
My app has already implemented
the existing protocol methods
from PKPaymentAuthorization
ControllerDelegate
in order to take advantage
of the Apple Pay payment sheet.
With iOS 15, the payment sheet
will automatically be updated
to the new look without
any additional work.
I've decided that
with the update to iOS 15
I want my festival attendees
to finally have the ability
to request their tickets
in multiple ways.
To do this,
I'll need to add support
for multiple shipping methods,
so let's dive in!
I'll head into
our PaymentHandler class
where I build
the PKPaymentRequest
to begin adding support
for multiple PKShippingMethods.
The first thing I'm going to add
is a helper function
that returns me
an array of PKShippingMethods
representing the different
options available to my users.
The first
PKShippingMethod I create
is a standard shipping method,
letting the user know
they can collect their tickets
at the festival.
New to iOS 15,
I want to provide the user
an estimated range
it will take the tickets
to be shipped to them.
To do this I create a Date
and Calendar object,
then define a shippingStart
and shippingEnd date
three to five days from now.
I'm then able to specify
the date components
that I want to display to
the user in the payment sheet.
Then I build my PKShippingMethod
making sure I set the new
property, dateComponentsRange,
and return the array
of the two shipping methods.
The last thing I need to do
is set the shipping methods
on the PKPaymentRequest like so.
With these simple changes,
I can build my app
and check out the new shipping
methods in the payment sheet.
A new row has automatically been
added to the payment sheet
showing the shipping methods.
If I tap the row
I'll see both shipping methods
that were just added,
including the one
that supports date ranges.
I've also decided that
for the festival this year
I want to send out coupon codes
to all my attendees
and add the functionality
to redeem them
directly through
the payment sheet in my app.
To do this, there are two main
changes that I need to make.
Let's head back into the code.
The first is when building
the PKPaymentRequest.
There is a new boolean,
supportsCouponCode,
that needs to be set to true.
There also is a new
optional property, couponCode,
that you can set on
your PKPaymentRequest
to prepopulate the coupon field
with one of your already valid
coupon codes.
Next, let's jump down to my
class extension that conforms
to the PKPaymentAuthorization
ControllerDelegate
and implement
the new protocol method
paymentAuthorizationController
didChangeCouponCode
where I will be able to handle
updating my summary items
and display errors related
to the coupon code entry
when a coupon code is entered.
The first thing I'm going
to need is a helper function
that updates our
PKPaymentSummaryItems
if a valid coupon code
is entered.
I grab a reference
to the first summary item
which is our subtotal item.
From there, I create a new
PKPaymentSummaryItem
that lets the user see
the discount that was applied.
I then create a new summary
item for tax and total,
and then return
the array of them.
Now that I have my discount
application logic written,
I can then write my coupon code
validation logic.
I first check if my coupon code
that the user entered was empty
and if it is,
just call our completion
passing in the unmodified
payment summary items.
If the entered coupon code
matches a valid coupon code,
then I use the just created
applyDiscount function
to return the updated
summary items
into our CouponCodeUpdate
object.
For your apps,
you'll most likely need to be
fetching valid coupon codes
from your server at this point.
Finally, if the entered
coupon code was invalid,
I use the new PKPaymentRequest
convenience initializer,
paymentCouponCodeInvalidError,
and supply it a description
to be shown directly
in the payment sheet.
We also have a second
convenience initializer
for expired coupon codes:
paymentCouponCodeExpired
ErrorWithLocalizedDescription.
I then pass this error into our
coupon code update initializer
as well as the original
SummaryItems.
Just like that,
I've added support
for coupon codes inside my app.
Let's check it out.
To enter a coupon code,
I just need to tap
into the summary view
and enter a coupon code
into the coupon code text field.
If I first enter an invalid
coupon code, Fest,
the error message I supplied
is shown directly below
the text field.
Now if I enter a valid
coupon code, FESTIVAL,
the payment summary items
are immediately updated.
Then I just need to select
the shipping contact
as well as shipping address
and my payment request
is ready to go.
With these simple changes,
you're now ready
to test your updates
to the payment sheet
on a device in our Apple Pay
sandbox environment.
Now, back to Edward.
Edward: Thanks, Russ.
Russ just showed us
how easy it is
to implement multiple
shipping methods,
the new date range,
and coupon code APIs.
This year we've delivered some
exciting new updates to Wallet
such as home key passes,
identification,
hiding expired passes,
and multiple pass ingestion.
We introduced the new
JavaScript payment button
for Apple Pay on the web,
and the new Apple Pay
experience on iOS.
You learned about
the new shipping APIs,
which include support
for date ranges
and read-only addresses,
as well as coupon codes
and how you can implement these
in your own apps.
For more information,
check out the Apple Pay section
of the Developer Portal.
This includes
the Apple Pay sandbox
for testing payment requests
from your apps and websites.
Thank you for watching.
♪