[upbeat music]
[Mike]
Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Mike,
and today
we're going to walk through
how to create
a custom symbol
that takes advantage
of the new features
introduced in SF Symbols 3.
First, we'll recap
what a custom symbol is
and when you may
want to use one.
Custom symbols involve
working with an SVG template.
With SF Symbols 3, we have
an all new template version,
so we'll discuss the changes
from previous versions.
We'll walk through
how to generate templates,
edit your symbols,
and prepare them
for rendering modes
other than monochrome.
We'll cover annotation,
the process of adding
rendering mode data
to your symbols.
We'll discuss some
more advanced techniques
that can drastically
impact your workflows.
And lastly, we'll wrap up
by covering exporting
for Xcode and distributing
your custom symbols.
Let's get started.
So, what is a custom symbol?
Well, SF Symbols
were introduced in 2019.
In the initial release,
there were more
than 1,500 symbols
available to use in your apps.
Since then, the library
of symbols has only grown.
Two years later,
with SF Symbols 3,
it totals over 3,000 symbols.
Now, these symbols
cover a wide variety
of subjects and categories.
But your app may have
a specific need
that isn't fully captured
by an existing SF Symbol
such as a teacup in a circle.
This is where
custom symbols come in.
If you need a custom symbol,
you would draw it as a series
of vector paths and place it
in a custom symbol template.
The template
is in the SVG format,
and includes your designs
and some guides.
This template is the mechanism
for your own symbols
to take advantage
of all the features
that SF Symbols have to offer.
This includes
typographic alignment
to make sure your symbols
look good next to text,
margins for making sure
symbols are optically centered
with one another when used
in lists and table views...
Multiple weights to match text
and adjust to features
such as accessibility bold
on iOS...
And lastly,
three weight-matched scales
to adjust to the context
of different UI elements.
So those are the highlights
of SF Symbols
and custom symbols.
To review the basics
of a custom symbol template,
it's recommended to watch
"Introducing SF Symbols"
from WWDC 2019.
To learn more
about the design details
behind SF Symbols, check out
"What's new in SF Symbols"
from WWDC 2021.
Now that we know
when to use a custom symbol,
let's review the template
that makes them possible.
To go along
with the new features
in SF Symbols 3,
there's a new version
of the template, version 3.0.
This version of the template
has some important
new capabilities
compared to version 2.0,
and it requires Xcode 13
or greater.
In 3.0, the left-margin
and right-margin guidelines
have more explicit names,
indicating the design variant
that they correspond to.
These margins, for example,
have the suffix "Regular-M."
This means
that for additional control
over optical alignment
you can add margins
to any variant in the template,
and as long as they have
a suffix matching one
of the design variants,
they will be respected.
More importantly,
this format of the template
is able to embed information
on how a symbol should look
in different rendering modes.
We can embed data
for existing modes,
such as monochrome
and multicolor,
as well as data used
by the new hierarchical
and palette modes.
On top of all of this,
the 3.0 template
supports
some advanced functionality
that can empower you
to accomplish more
by doing less.
We'll talk about this in detail
in the "advanced techniques"
section.
For the full specification
of the new template,
check out our updated
documentation at
Developer.Apple.com/SF-Symbols.
Now that we're familiar
with the new template,
let's work on a custom symbol.
So I'm working
on a card game app
with some of my colleagues,
and the SF Symbols app
has us covered for a lot
of symbols that we need.
There are four suits
as well as a stack
that we can use to represent
a deck of cards.
The only thing missing
is something we could use
to represent
the Queen of Hearts,
which will play a special role
in our app.
I'm picturing a symbol
of a crown with a heart on top.
I can start by opening
the SF Symbols app
so I can customize
an existing SF Symbol.
This way, I'll have
some point of reference
for stem thickness,
scale, and alignment.
If I search for "crown"
in the SF Symbols app,
I notice that we have
a nice,
unfilled version available.
This will be
a great starting point.
All I need to add
is the heart on top.
I can select "crown,"
and from the contextual menu
select Duplicate
as Custom Symbol.
And under the Custom Symbols
section in the sidebar,
there's now a cell for the crown
I just duplicated.
"Custom.crown" is a bit vague,
so I'll rename it.
"Queen.heart"
is much more descriptive
of what I have in mind.
Now, this is a good way
to start a new custom symbol,
but you may have some symbols
from past years
as 1.0 and 2.0
custom symbol templates.
That's not a problem.
You can drop
the existing symbol on the app,
and it will automatically
get added
to the current collection
and up-converted
to a 3.0 template.
Once the symbol
is in my collection,
whether I copied an SF Symbol,
like "crown,"
or imported a custom symbol
like "Teacup.circle,"
I can export it for editing
in my design app of choice
such as Sketch,
Illustrator, or Figma.
To do so, I can select
File Export Template,
or Command + E.
This will export a 3.0 template
in monochrome
so that I can customize it.
For symbols that originate
in the SF Symbols app,
you have two options
for the initial setup
of your 3.0 template:
static and variable.
Which setup you choose
depends on your design goals.
The static setup
should be familiar,
as it looks similar
to a 2.0 template.
There are 27 sets of paths
and one set
of explicit margins
on regular in the medium scale.
If you are targeting
a particular weight and scale,
or only plan on designing
one or two variants
of your symbol,
this setup will work well.
The variable setup,
on the other hand,
will generate a 3.0 template
that has three sets
of paths
and three sets of margins.
If you plan on supporting
all design variants,
you may be interested
in starting with this setup,
since it gives you
the minimum number
of design variants
needed to generate the other 24.
This requires
that all your paths
have a very high level of
compatibility and consistency.
But don't worry about this now.
We'll revisit these requirements
and this setup
of the template later in detail.
For now,
I'll export a static setup
since I'm only going to draw
one or two variants.
With my template open
in my design application,
I'm ready to begin editing.
Like working
with a 2.0 template,
I can delete design variants
I don't need
and only design a few to start.
For templates that don't
have compatible paths,
Regular-Medium
is still required,
so I'll start with that.
I'll make room for the heart
on the middle spire
of the crown.
And I want this symbol
to look good in multicolor mode,
so I'll adjust the paths
so that I can assign colors
to particular parts
of my symbol later.
With these adjustments,
I now have a single closed shape
for the hollow part
of the crown.
Next, I'll focus on the heart.
Now, as I edit my symbol,
I may use strokes to match
the stem thickness
of Regular-Medium
since I am working
on a stroked symbol.
This gives me flexibility
as I iterate
on the proportions
and size of the heart.
But notice,
I make sure to convert
any live strokes to paths
once I'm happy with the design.
Converting to paths
ensures that the stroked shapes
can be filled with color later.
Another benefit
of converting to paths
is that I can make some
minor optical adjustments
for when a stroke
isn't precise enough.
Like here,
on the top half of the heart,
the stroke is too large
and round on the inside.
Since I converted to paths,
I can fine tune the curve
to look less clunky.
Now that I have
one design variant drawn,
this is a good time to talk
about some items
to keep in mind
if you want your symbol
to support rendering modes
other than monochrome.
Avoid using live strokes
in the final design.
Instead, make sure
to convert any strokes
to paths
so that the resulting shapes
can take on colors
or hierarchy groups.
Avoid using open paths.
These are paths
that have a start point
and an end point
that do not connect.
Since there's
no closed fill area,
these shapes will be unable
to take on any colors.
Instead, make sure
all shapes in your design
are closed
with a defined fill area.
Avoid special fills
involving more than one color
such as gradients
or effects like drop shadows.
If these are present,
they will override
any multicolor
or hierarchical data
you create for your symbol.
Instead,
stick to standard, flat fills
with no additional effects.
Now, if we jump back
to my design tool,
the template is pretty bare.
I may want to add semibold
so that the symbol
responds to
the accessibility bold feature
on iOS.
To do this, it's recommend
to copy an existing drawing
you have to the desired layer
and adjust it from there.
This is a good habit to get into
as it will result
in the same number of paths
being used
across your design variants.
Preserving the number
of paths
across all design variants
is a requirement
if you want to produce
a symbol with multicolor
or hierarchical data.
In this example,
I've colored the paths
to indicate their number
and order.
Both design variants
have four paths.
The first two paths
make up the folder,
then we have a circle
as the third path,
and a plus sign
as the fourth path.
As a result, these two drawings
look great in multicolor.
These drawings
also have four paths present,
but, if you pay close attention,
you'll notice I've shuffled
the order
of the paths on the right.
The main stroke of the folder
is the first path in the drawing
on the left,
but the third path
in the drawing on the right.
When designs have
the same number of paths
but in different orders,
they are likely
to render very differently.
And if we were to render
these drawings
in multicolor,
they don't match up.
The green of the plus badge
is being applied to the folder
in the design variant
on the right.
Back to the Queen.heart symbol.
It looks great so far.
And since I was careful in how
I created my design variants,
I can make it even better
by annotating it
to support multicolor
and hierarchical modes.
Before I can do that,
I'll need to import
my symbol back into the app.
I can simply drop it
on the existing cell
we have to update it
in the SF Symbols app.
Now, you're not required
to annotate your symbols,
but if you want to control
your symbol's appearance
in rendering modes
other than monochrome,
it's a good idea.
To annotate,
you'll use the individual paths
that make up your symbol
as your building blocks.
From these,
you create a set of layers
for each rendering mode.
A layer is simply
a collection of paths
with some
associated rendering data.
Here I have a layer
for the crown with seven paths,
and a layer
for the heart with two paths.
Layers in multicolor mode
get assigned a color,
and layers in hierarchical mode
get assigned a hierarchy group.
Layers have an explicit z-order
where the layers on top
will block out
the layers below.
This is no different
from creating layers
in a design application.
To begin annotating,
I select my symbol
in the app
and enter the gallery view.
In the inspector on the right,
I can select
the rendering mode tab
so I can preview
and annotate my symbol.
I can choose between monochrome,
hierarchical,
palette, and multicolor.
When in a mode
other than monochrome,
you will be able
to add and edit your layers
corresponding
to the active mode.
And in the center
we have our preview.
Here we can interact
with all the paths
we have at our disposal
and assign them to layers.
I'll start with the multicolor
rendering mode first.
I'll create
a new layer for the crown.
Then, I can select
a color for the layer.
For multicolor layers,
I can choose
from various system colors,
or use my own custom color.
It's recommended
to use system-provided colors
whenever possible,
as they will adapt to changes
in the system's appearance
to look great in light mode,
dark mode, high contrast modes,
and different vibrancy contexts.
I'll use system yellow
for the crown.
And that's one layer done.
Now, just for the heart.
I'll add that
on its own layer in red.
I want to add a bit more depth
to my crown in multicolor mode
by setting colors
on the hollow parts
of my symbol.
A path can be used
in any number of layers.
So, to achieve a stroked
and filled effect,
I've added a layer
with the paths
that I want transparent
and set it
to a lower opacity.
I'll do the same
for the heart as well.
That looks great.
Next,
I'll move onto hierarchical.
I can construct
my layers like before,
but instead of colors,
I assign hierarchical groups
ranging from
primary to tertiary.
The hierarchical data
will be used
in the hierarchical
and palette rendering modes.
I'll add a layer
for my crown in secondary.
And the heart in primary.
I can see
in the preview that a bit
of the crown
shows through the heart
where they overlap
because the heart
isn't fully opaque.
This is a common problem
when working
with overlapping shapes.
To control how these overlaps
get rendered,
each layer
has a toggle on the right.
If inactive,
transparent layers will blend
with the layers below,
as shown on the left.
This is the default behavior.
If active,
transparent layers
will clear what's behind them
and render
as if the other layers
don't exist,
as shown on the right.
With the clear behind
toggle set,
now my symbol
behaves as expected.
The hierarchical annotation data
also gets used
by the palette rendering mode,
so I'll make sure
our layer interaction
looks good there as well.
This looks great.
The cyan layer is transparent
but since clear behind
is enabled, we can't see any
of the indigo crown behind it.
In the palette rendering mode,
I can assign two to three colors
to my symbol,
instead of just one
like in hierarchical.
Let's review the difference
in how these two modes interpret
hierarchical annotations
to apply color.
Hierarchical uses one color
and will apply it
to your symbol's layers,
varying the opacity
based on the hierarchy level.
In this case, we have a symbol
with a primary group
and a tertiary group.
Palette takes
two to three colors,
and the behavior
will differ slightly
based on the number
of colors passed.
Passing two colors
will distribute the colors
among the available
hierarchy groups
regardless of their level.
For this symbol,
since we only have two groups,
the first color is applied
to the primary group
and the second color is applied
to the tertiary group.
If you pass three colors,
then each one is applied
to the corresponding
hierarchy group.
The first color
is assigned to primary,
the second to secondary,
and third to tertiary.
If you need
to continue editing a symbol
you've already annotated,
you would export a template
and edit
the monochrome representation
in your design tool.
Then reimport the symbol
and verify
your annotations
still render as expected.
Special care must be taken
when modifying
the paths
of an annotated symbol
if you wish to retain
your annotation data.
Since this data requires
the same number of paths
across designs, you can safely
add, remove, and adjust points.
But removing or reordering
whole paths
will make your design
go out of sync
with its annotation data.
In these cases,
you will need to reannotate
the symbol to account
for its new path structure.
Now, I have my symbol
in two design variants,
and it's annotated
so it will look great
in other rendering modes.
I could stop here,
but what if I need to support
other combinations
of scale and weight?
In this section,
we'll talk about techniques
for working with custom symbols
that can save you time
if you plan on drawing
three or more design variants.
In the past, I would continue
filling out the rest
of the variants
in the template one by one,
adjusting the paths to match
the desired weight and scale.
But now, with SF Symbols 3,
there's a much better way
to do this.
If you provide
just three design variants
with compatible data,
you get the rest
of the template for free.
This is the structure
of the SVG you will get
when asking
for a 3.0 variable template.
Let's dive into the requirements
for producing
compatible designs.
First, we check
for what we refer to
as design sources.
These are Ultralight-Small,
Regular-Small, and Black-Small.
If those are present,
then paths are assessed
across the sources
to see if they match up.
Let's focus
on the Regular-Small source
and the Black-Small source
for a comparison.
Across design variants,
all paths must have
the same number and order
exactly as we discussed earlier
with annotation requirements.
I've colored the paths
of the crown here
to indicate their order.
There are nine paths,
and they all match up.
For example,
the two paths for the heart
are the eighth and ninth path
in both design variants.
So far, so good.
Next, we'll check inside
the corresponding paths
across design variants.
Let's compare the outside path
for the heart
of the regular source
and the black source.
Each path is constructed
from a series of points.
We have 24 points
for the regular source in red,
and 24 points
for the black source in blue.
To be compatible,
points must match one-to-one
between the corresponding paths.
Each pair of matching points
create an imaginary line,
and moving each point
along its respective line
allows us to blend between
the two compatible paths.
Since each point
in the regular source
corresponds to a point
in the black source,
we can do just that.
We'll focus in
on the smaller heart
in red and observe the path
as it blends
with the larger heart in blue.
Blending is what allows
for a new path
to be generated anywhere
between the compatible paths.
This blending is known
as "interpolation."
Now that we know
how interpolation works
at the point level,
let's zoom out
and apply it
to the entire symbol.
You'll notice that any weight
between ultralight,
regular,
and black can be computed.
This is the mechanism
for the weight compensation
necessary to generate
the medium and large scale
design variants
for your symbols.
Let's recap those requirements.
For a symbol to be considered
interpolatable,
it needs three things.
First, the three design sources.
Ultralight-Small,
Regular-Small, and Black-Small.
Second, path compatibility.
All paths must match
between the sources.
And lastly, point compatibility.
All matching paths must have
the same number of points.
So how would I go about
making one of these
interpolatable symbols?
Well, instead of a static setup,
I would start by exporting
a 3.0 template
from the SF Symbols app
with a variable setup.
This way,
I have margins and outlines
for the three source designs.
I would start with Regular-Small
and add my heart on top,
as we did earlier
for Regular-Medium.
This time it is just
for a smaller scale.
Since interpolation
has very strict requirements,
it's recommended to get
the initial
Regular-Small design variant
into good shape before working
on the other sources.
When you do go to work
on the Ultralight-Small
and Black-Small sources,
it is best to copy
and paste
the Regular-Small paths
and only reposition
the points from there.
This is critical to make sure
your custom symbol
is capable of generating
the other design variants.
So let's
review that one more time.
When you want your symbol
to be interpolatable,
avoid adding or removing points,
as this will break
compatibility.
Instead, only adjust
the existing points.
Moving points
and control points is fine,
since this preserves
the compatibility
between designs.
Once ready,
I can drop my updated template
on my custom symbols cell
in the app,
and annotate it
just like I did before.
Since I was careful
in drawing my sources,
I have
all 27 variants covered,
and I'm all set to hand this off
to get implemented.
Now that we've covered
ways to create
your custom symbol,
let's talk about next steps
such as how
to distribute your symbol.
When distributing your symbol,
you have two options.
You can export a 2.0 template
or a 3.0 template.
2.0 templates
should only be used
if you plan on back deploying
to an older OS such as iOS 14.
It only contains monochrome
so make sure
your symbol makes sense
when used in that mode.
Converting to a 2.0 template
is a lossy operation.
Annotation data
and explicit margins are removed
since the older OS
will not understand them.
3.0 can embed all the multicolor
and hierarchical data
you've added,
as well as any custom margins,
but it is
not backwards compatible.
Careful here,
this template is not
a source artifact for editing.
Current design tools
may not be entirely compatible
with the embedded
annotation data.
If you need to make
more edits to your symbol
or share it with a colleague,
it should be imported
back into the SF Symbols app.
From there, you can work
on the monochrome representation
without risk
of dropping your annotations.
The 3.0 template that you export
should go
straight to Xcode
or back to the SF Symbols app.
If your minimum
deployment target is iOS 14,
you will need to export both
a 2.0 and a 3.0 template
and use the appropriate asset
based on a version check.
If your minimum
deployment target
is iOS15 or later,
you only need to export
a 3.0 template.
If you are sharing a symbol
with a colleague,
export a 3.0 template.
They can then import
that into their SF Symbols app
to continue
editing and annotating.
We covered
a lot of content today,
so let's do a quick recap.
We talked about the new
3.0 custom symbol template,
the features it supports,
and how to edit it.
We covered how to prepare
your symbols for annotation
and add multicolor
and hierarchical data.
We explored
a more advanced workflow
that opts into
some stricter requirements
to take advantage
of interpolation.
And we just
finished talking about
how to distribute your symbols.
Once you've delivered
your symbols,
they are ready to be used
by the OS.
There are some new APIs
you can use
for rendering your symbol
in the appropriate mode.
To learn more
about calling SF Symbols
and custom symbols in code,
check out "SF Symbols
in UIKit and AppKit"
and "SF Symbols in SwiftUI,"
both from WWDC 2021.
That's custom symbols
from start to finish.
I hope you enjoy creating
and annotating your own symbols.
[upbeat music]