[music]
[David] Hi, my name is David,
and I'm an engineer
on the Documentation Tools team
here at Apple.
In this session,
you'll learn about
hosting DocC documentation
and automating
documentation builds.
First, I'll talk about
building documentation in Xcode
and how you can host
the built documentation archives
on a server.
Next, I'll go into more detail
of how documentation builds work
and how you can automate
building documentation.
Throughout this talk,
I'll be showing you
SlothCreator,
a project that my colleagues
and I have been working on.
We made a website
to help people get started.
And now, we're really excited
about using
the new documentation features
in Xcode
to build a version
of our documentation
that we can host
right on our website.
That's going
to make it even easier
for people to get started.
So let's look at how
we can accomplish that.
The new documentation features
in Xcode 13 makes it really easy
to build documentation
for your Swift frameworks,
libraries, and packages.
You can start
using it right away
without any setup
and then expand
your documentation
with additional material
over time.
And it's just as easy
to export your documentation
from the Developer
Documentation window.
You can share
the exported documentation
archive with others
so that they can import and read
the documentation in Xcode,
or you can host the
documentation archive online.
If you want to learn more
about documentation in Xcode
and about authoring
documentation for your symbols,
my colleagues Victoria and Ethan
talk about just that in the
"Meet DocC documentation
in Xcode" session.
In the second half
of this presentation,
I'll talk about how you can
automate building documentation
on the command line.
But for now,
I'll use the documentation
archive
that I exported from Xcode
to host on our server.
The documentation archive
itself is a container
that holds all the data
to both
read the documentation in Xcode
and to host it online.
It is structured
as a single page
Vue.js web app
that's used to render
both your reference
documentation and articles
and your rich
and interactive tutorials.
There are
two different types of requests
that the server needs to handle
to host
the documentation archive.
Requests for documentation
and tutorial pages
where the request URL
starts with
/documentation/ or /tutorials/
and requests
for additional files and data
that is loaded by the web app,
where the request URL
matches the relative file path
for one of the files
in the documentation archive.
Let's look at an example
of the requests
that make up a page
and how the server
should respond to them.
When a developer goes to read
your hosted documentation
and the browser requests a page,
if the request starts with
/documentation/ or /tutorials/
then the server should respond
with the index.html file
that's located
in the documentation archive.
That file references
CSS and JavaScript
within
the documentation archive,
which the browser requests
to load the rest of the web app.
Once that is loaded,
the web app requests
the content for that page
and any images or other media
that it references.
Both the files
that is referenced
by the index.html file
and the content and media
that is loaded by the web app
use request URLs that match the
folder structure
of the documentation archive.
Now that you've seen
how the hosting server
needs to respond
to incoming requests,
let's look at that in a demo.
Many of you
may already have a server
that hosts your website.
For our project,
we're using an Apache server,
but you can use any server
that allows for custom routing.
This is our website
about SlothCreator.
We've added this
"Read Documentation" button
below the introductory text
in the center of the page,
but the button
doesn't work just yet.
So let's fix that.
I've already copied
the documentation archive
into the directory
where we're hosting our website
and added
an empty .htaccess file.
But I haven't set up
any of the routing in it.
There are two routing rules
that I need to add:
one for the documentation
and tutorial pages
and one for the additional files
and data.
For the first rule,
the pattern that I want to match
is any URL that starts with
"documentation" or "tutorials"
as its first path component.
Any request
that matches this pattern,
I want to reroute
to the index.html file
within the documentation
archive.
Lastly,
I'll end the rule with a flag
to stop evaluating rules
if the request
matches this rule.
For the second rule,
I'm going to be more explicit
about the pattern.
Since we're also hosting
our website with this server,
we don't want
to reroute requests
for the website to files
in the documentation archive.
If I look inside
of the documentation archive,
you can see
that there are a handful
of top-level files and folders
that I can match in a pattern.
So I'll add a pattern
that matches all of those.
In this case, the request URL
is a relative file path
for one of the files
in the documentation archive,
so I'll reroute the request
to the matched pattern
but prefixed
with SlothCreator.doccarchive.
And just like before,
I added the same flag
to stop evaluating rules.
Now, if I reload the webpage
and click on
the documentation link,
you'll see
that the server now hosts
both our website
and our documentation.
The main SlothCreator page
groups important symbols
into topics
related to higher level tasks.
And each of those
group related symbols
into more specific topics.
DocC comes
with a built-in, clean design
that's made to fit in well
with a variety of projects.
This makes it really easy
to have good-looking,
elegant documentation
for your projects,
like our SlothCreator
documentation here.
Now that we host
a copy of our documentation
on our website,
let's look at how to automate
building and updating
the documentation archive.
To do that,
I'm going to write a script
that calls xcodebuild.
Once I have a script
that does this,
I can run it whenever
new changes are made
so that the hosted documentation
is always up to date.
New in Xcode 13,
you can build documentation
on the command line
with xcodebuild's
new docbuild action.
When you build documentation
in Xcode or xcodebuild,
it works like a standard build
that also builds documentation.
During the build,
the Swift compiler
gathers detailed information
about all the public symbols,
their relationships,
and in-source
documentation comments
and passes this
as a file called a symbol graph
to the documentation compiler
to produce
a documentation archive
with all the necessary data
to both read the documentation
in Xcode
and to host it online.
If the target has an associated
documentation catalog
with additional articles, media,
or tutorials for your project,
then the documentation compiler
is going to combine
all of that content
with the symbol information
when it produces
the documentation archive.
If you want to learn more
about documentation catalogs,
check out
the "Elevate your DocC
documentation in Xcode" session
where my colleagues Bea and Jack
talk about the different types
of documentation
and how you can leverage
each of them
to offer developers a great way
for learning about your project.
Building documentation doesn't
just apply to your targets.
If your target has dependencies
to other Swift frameworks,
libraries, or packages,
then the same process is applied
to all of those as well
so that you get all the relevant
documentation for your project
all in one place.
Since I'm looking to automate
building and updating
our hosted documentation
with a script,
xcodebuild on the command line
is going to be perfect for that.
The new docbuild action
in xcodebuild
works just like
the default build action,
but it also
builds documentation.
Like the build action,
you pass it the scheme
that you want to build
and the project or workspace
that it's a part of.
You can also call xcodebuild
from within the directory
that contains your project,
workspace, or Swift package
and only pass it the scheme.
Depending on your project
and scheme,
you may want to pass other flags
such as sdk, destination,
or configuration
to customize
how your project is built.
It's not required to do so.
But to make
it more easy to follow,
I'll specify a custom
derivedDataPath,
where the build products
and the built documentation
will be written.
After the build has completed,
I can find all of the built
documentation archives
using
the .doccarchive file extension
and copy each of them
to another location
or to another machine.
Let's take a look
at that in a demo.
This is our hosted documentation
from before.
It groups related symbols
into topics
so that it's easy for developers
to find the core types
for a specific task.
In the time since
we built this version,
my colleagues have added
some new articles
and tutorials that appear
in the Essentials section.
So now is a great time for me
to write that automation script
that builds
the latest documentation
and updates our website.
Like you just saw,
we build documentation
by calling xcodebuild's
docbuild action
and update our website
by finding and copying
the documentation archive into
the directory
where we're hosting
our website from.
I already know what scheme
I need to pass
because it's the same as I see
in the scheme selector in Xcode.
If I didn't already
have Xcode open,
I could also run
xcodebuild -list
on the command line to list
all of the available schemes.
Again,
the custom derivedDataPath
is not required,
but it makes it easier to follow
where the built documentation
is written and found.
After the build has completed,
I can find all of the
documentation archives
and copy each of them
into the directory
where we're hosting
our website from.
And with that done,
I'm ready to run the script.
Now, if I refresh,
you can see
the added article and tutorial
in the Essentials section.
With these latest changes,
our documentation
looks more complete.
And people
who are new to SlothCreator
have a great place
to get started,
whether they prefer
the content of an article
or the step-by-step instructions
in one of our tutorials.
Now, updating
our hosted documentation
is as easy as running a script.
And if we run it
as part of a post-merge hook
on our continuous
integration server,
then we can ensure
that our hosted documentation
always stays up to date.
To recap what we talked about
in this session,
you can share
documentation archives
or host them online
to give
a great documentation experience
to consumers of your framework,
even before they've started
using it in Xcode.
And building documentation
on the command line
allows you
to include documentation
in your automation workflows.
If you want to learn more
about DocC documentation,
"Meet DocC documentation
in Xcode"
is a fantastic introduction
to the new documentation
features in Xcode.
"Elevate your DocC documentation
in Xcode"
goes deep into how
you can enhance
your documentation
with DocC catalogs.
And "Build interactive tutorials
using DocC"
details how you can structure
your ideas
and create amazing tutorials
for your project.
Thank you for watching.
[music]