[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Sihui Liu: Hello. Welcome to
“Develop advanced web content.”
I'm Sihui, and I am an engineer
on the Safari and WebKit team.
I am happy to share with you
the important updates
we have made in WebKit
and Safari
for web developers
in the past year.
The things I'm about to share
generally fall
into three categories.
First, I will walk you through
new features and enhancements
in JavaScript.
Then I will give you an overview
of the updates in WebAssembly.
And finally, I will introduce
you to some new web APIs
that can add
additional capabilities
to your web content.
There is a lot to cover,
so let’s begin with our news
in JavaScript.
Each year, there are
hundreds of changes made
in our JavaScript engine.
I will cover some
of the most important ones
you need know if you work
with JavaScript.
They are:
new class field syntax,
weak references that enables
smarter memory management,
new usage of the await keyword,
support for modules in workers,
and interfaces added to
Internationalization API family.
To put you in the picture
of these new features,
I'm going to use a simple
stopwatch as example.
The stopwatch
has only one button.
Click it once,
it begins counting.
Click it again, it will stop
and give you
the duration passed.
Keep this in mind
and we will implement it later
in JavaScript.
Now, let’s take a look
at the new class field syntax.
We have new private class fields
and methods
that let you define
real private members
whose access is protected
by the language.
You will see an error
if you break the access rules.
We also add support
for static fields,
which allows you to declare
a class member
that can be accessed
without creating an instance
of the class.
Now you have the basic idea.
Let’s check how it can be used
with the stopwatch example.
If you are asked to implement
the stopwatch class,
your implementation
may look like this.
StopwatchWithOneButton
has only one method
named click().
It checks startTime variable.
If start time is unset,
the click means to start,
so it will set the start time.
If start time is already set,
the click means to stop,
so it will calculate a duration
and reset the start time.
You can see startTime comes
with an underscore prefix.
This is a naming convention
commonly used to denote
that the variable should only
be used inside of the class.
But that does not actually
prevent the start time
from being accessed publicly.
The new private syntax
can help fix this.
Just replace the underscore
with hash,
and you can declare
a real private instance field.
The encapsulation is enforced
by the language.
There is also support
for private methods.
For example, to make
click() methods more structured,
we can create
two private methods
start() and stop()
to replace the highlighted
content, like this.
By adding the hash prefix
to methods,
we make sure the member
functions can only be accessed
from inside of the class.
The new private syntax
also applies to static fields
like startedStopwatchCount.
Here, startedStopwatchCount
can only be modified
by stopwatch objects
at start or stop times.
Of course, if you want
startedStopwatchCount
to be accessed everywhere,
you can declare it
as public static field,
without the hash prefix.
Public static field
is also available in WebKit now.
Private instance fields,
methods,
private static fields,
and public static fields;
that’s our new
class field support.
And let’s continue
to another feature,
weak references.
Weak references allow you
to hold reference
to a JavaScript object in a way
that does not prevent
garbage collection.
Unlike WeakMap and WeakSet,
you can get
the underlying object
without already having
a reference to it.
The support also includes
notification
on garbage collection,
so you may perform some
cleanup task if you need to.
And let’s see how
it can be used.
We just implemented
the stopwatch class.
Now imagine you have created
multiple stopwatch objects
for different tasks.
For testing, you need to click
all of them at a time.
How would you do that?
An intuitive way is to keep
a set of all
stopwatch instances.
When the stopwatch is created,
add it to the set.
Then in clickAllStopwatches
function,
iterate the set
and click each stopwatch.
But there is an issue
with this approach.
We know JavaScript objects
hold strong reference
by default, so in this case
all stopwatch objects
cannot be garbage collected
because the set still has
reference to them.
Of course, we don’t want to keep
all stopwatch objects around
just for testing.
This is not great
for memory use.
Now, you may suggest
just replacing Set with WeakSet,
but WeakSet is not iterable.
So what would you do?
We can solve it
with the new interface WeakRef,
which holds weak references
to an object.
We still have the set,
but this time we add WeakRef
of stopwatch objects to the set.
In clickAllStopwatches function,
we check if the object
still exists
by dereferencing it
before clicking.
This seems to solve our issue,
but there is another problem:
we don’t remove
garbage-collected stopwatches
from the set in a timely manner,
and the set can grow quite large
before our next click test.
Now what should we do?
Another new interface --
FinalizationRegistry --
may help in this case.
With it, you can specify
a callback to be invoked
at when some object
is garbage collected.
Here we create
a finalizationRegistry object
with removeStopwatch function,
so this function is called
every time an object
is collected.
Then, we register stopwatch
objects to the registry.
Each stopwatch is bound
with an identifier,
so removeStopwatch knows
which stopwatch to remove.
Good, now garbage-collected
stopwatches will be removed
from allStopwatches.
The usage of weak references
sounds not that hard, right?
But be aware that garbage
collection in JavaScript
is very complicated,
and there is
a lot of uncertainty.
For example,
the object you think
should be collected
may not actually be collected
until a long time after,
and you may not get the callback
from FinalizationRegistry
right way because it runs
on event loop.
Therefore, make sure
you fully understand the syntax
and its expected behavior
before use.
Let’s move on
from weak references
to the next feature,
top-level await.
This is a new feature
for modules.
It enables you to use
the await keyword
outside of the async function.
In this case, the module itself
is like a big async function,
so an async module can block
the execution of the module
importing them.
Let me show you an example
with our stopwatch class.
This is the class
we just created.
To illustrate a use
of top-level await,
let’s make it a module
and export the class.
This is an HTML file
that contains an inline module.
It imports the stopwatch module
using dynamic import.
The import function
returns a promise,
so we can use then or catch
methods to perform actions
after import is done.
With top-level await,
you can remove
the chaining methods
and write the code
in a synchronous way.
This can make your code
easier to follow.
Also, because imported modules
are evaluated at load time,
so an async module can block
execution of modules
depending on it.
That means if stopwatch module
runs async operations
and waits for result,
the stopwatch variable here
will be initialized
after stopwatch module
finishes execution.
Top-level await
has made it easier
to do dependency management.
But again, this feature
is only available in modules,
so if the script
is not a module, like this...
...you will see a syntax error
in Web Inspector.
Speaking of modules,
there’s another related feature:
module workers.
Workers has some
well-known benefits.
It can run scripts
in a background thread,
so resources can be utilized
more efficiently.
With this new support,
workers now share the benefits
of modules,
including dynamic import,
optimized loading and execution,
and dependency management.
It is more beneficial and easier
for you to move heavy work
from main thread
to background thread now.
Modules is now available
in different types of workers,
including web worker,
service worker, and worklet.
To create a module worker,
for web workers
and service worker,
you need to specify type
to be module in the options.
For a worklet
like Audio Worklet,
you can use addModule function.
It’s quite easy to create
a module worker
that helps speed up
your application.
Last in JavaScript section
is updates
on the Internationalization API.
This API provides
language-based formatting.
It is useful if your web content
is built for users
in different locales.
To show you how it can be used,
I built this stopwatch records
page because, you know,
stopwatch needs to keep up
with times
and our feature releases.
This page shows us details
about a single use of stopwatch,
including duration,
start time, event, participants,
and the available languages
of the page.
Now, let’s dive into
each section
and take a closer look
of each interface.
First is NumberFormat.
NumberFormat provides
language-sensitive
number formatting,
and it is used to format
the duration.
Constructor of NumberFormat
takes two optional parameters:
language and options.
Here I set the language
to English
and I make two options object,
which specify different
minimum numbers of digits.
After creating
two NumberFormat objects
with language and options,
we can use them to format
the duration numbers.
Here, if number
is not milliseconds,
I use Format1
to keep two digits;
otherwise I use Format2
to keep three digits.
As you can see,
the format method
automatically adds
padding zeroes for us.
There are many different options
you can utilize
to create formats you need,
such as style,
where you can specify value
to be currency or unit.
Next is DateTimeFormat,
which enables language-sensitive
date and time formatting.
The usage is similar
to NumberFormat.
First, set the language.
Then, set the options.
In the options,
I set different styles
for date and time.
The DateTimeFormat object
provides a fine-grained
configuration
that even allows you to specify
style for second or millisecond.
After that, we can create
a DateTimeFormat object
with parameters,
and use it to format
our start time.
The result is represented
in English.
You can see date
is more detailed
because it has the long style.
Next one is Segmenter.
It enables you to do
language-sensitive
string splitting.
I used it to find keywords
in the event sentence.
This is the Chinese version
of the stopwatch records page.
First, I declare a short list
of keywords I want to highlight.
The event string
even includes a Unicode
for the Celsius degree symbol.
Here we specify
Chinese as language.
In options, the granularity
is set to be a word.
The other possible values
are grapheme and sentence.
Then we create a Segmenter
and use it to split the string
with segment method.
We can iterate the result
objects to get all segments.
Check and see if each segment
is contained in
the keyword list to mark it.
Segmenter is quite useful
for interpreting languages,
like Chinese, where the word
boundary is not that obvious.
The next is ListFormat,
which enables language-sensitive
list formatting.
The same as before,
we can specify language
and options.
ListFormat does not have
as many options
as the other interfaces.
The most useful ones I found
are type and style.
With language and options,
we can create a ListFormat
and format the participants list
we have.
As you can see,
because the type is conjunction
and the style is long,
the format method adds a comma
and a word “and” in the result.
The last one is DisplayNames.
It provides consistent
translation of display names
for language, region,
and script.
Here I specify language
to be Japanese.
DisplayNames can take
language code as input.
In the options,
we set type as language.
Then we can create
DisplayNames object.
And here, using of method,
we can get
the translated result.
Even though this page
is built in English,
Japanese users can know
what languages are supported.
And this is how I built
the stopwatch records page
with new internationalization
interfaces.
To refresh your memory,
here is the list of things
we’ve just looked at
in the JavaScript section.
Following that, our next stop
is updates in WebAssembly.
We’ve been shipping
our WebAssembly engine
for a while, but in case you’re
not familiar with it,
let me begin by filling in
with some background
of WebAssembly.
WebAssembly is
a binary instruction format
for a stack-based
virtual machine.
It is a type of a code that can
be run in modern web browsers
with performance
close to native code.
WebAssembly is designed to be
a portable compilation target
for programming languages
like C, C++, or Rust,
so WebAssembly can help us
deploy applications
written in those languages
on the web.
In most use cases
of WebAssembly,
it runs alongside
with JavaScript.
They can communicate
with each other
through the WebAssembly API.
WebAssembly can provide
near-native performance,
and makes powerful frameworks
available on the web.
JavaScript can manipulate
the DOM
and offers powerful web APIs.
They can be good additions
to each other.
A good example of WebAssembly
use is Funky Karts.
It is a game converted from C++
to WebAssembly with Emscripten.
As you can see, it gets to run
very smoothly in Safari.
This year, we’ve upgraded
our WebAssembly engine
with following features:
new memory instructions
that give you better performance
on bulk memory operations,
like copying or initializing
blocks of memory;
new instructions
to tell user process
not to trap on exception,
like positive overflow
when converting
between float and int;
new sign-extension operators
that let you extend
a signed integer;
implementation of the latest
proposal to convert
between WebAssembly
type i64 and JavaScript BigInt,
which is simpler
than previous solutions
and can make your code
run faster;
new reference types that allows
WebAssembly modules
to hold references to JavaScript
and DOM objects,
passing them as arguments
and storing them;
and finally, streaming download
and compilation of WebAssembly
that shortens
overall execution time.
These are the highlights
of our new WebAssembly features.
We hope they will help
your development.
Now, let's move
from powerful low-level code
to some high-level APIs.
In this section,
we are going to explore
the new web APIs.
My goal is to not only
let you know
about the new features
but also make you feel you are
ready to use them,
so you will see
some good examples.
But this will not be
a complete tutorial,
so remember to check official
documentation before use.
This is a preview of features
I will talk about.
Some of them are
completely new
like Speech Recognition
and some of them
are already there,
but we have some updates
we’d like to share,
like Storage Access.
Now, let’s dig into
each of them.
We know to make
the web content attractive,
it’s very important to provide
amazing visual experience.
With WebGL2 being available
in WebKit and Safari,
it’s easier for you to create
beautiful,
interactive web content.
Here is a good example
of what can be done
with WebGL2.
After the Flood
is an interactive demo
developed by PlayCanvas.
You can see the gentle wind
sways the tree.
It looks vivid in Safari.
So what is WebGL2?
WebGL is a very widely used
low-level API
for rendering
2D and 3D graphics.
WebGL2 is an upgrade
of WebGL
that eliminates fallbacks
and introduces
some cool new features.
It adds 3D textures to allow
rendering volumetric effects
like cloud.
It has sampler objects
that give you more flexibility
about how to use textures
in shaders.
It provides transform feedback
that helps you implement
performance particle systems
on the GPU.
There are so many great
new features in WebGL2.
And more importantly,
WebGL2 is now available
in Safari on all Apple devices.
That means you can build
a beautiful site
that looks great everywhere.
And let’s get more familiar with
WebGL2 with an example:
creating an orange square.
And this is the JavaScript code
you need to write for it.
If you have not used
WebGL before,
this may not be as easy
as you would have imagined.
As I mentioned, because WebGL
is a low-level API,
it can be very verbose.
But don’t worry; there are many
great libraries and frameworks
that can help simplify
your development.
With them, it’s not that hard
to create a nice square
or something more complicated
than that.
Now, if you already use WebGL
in you web content,
there is also a good news.
We have improved our support
by migrating backend
from OpenGL to Metal.
That means iOS Simulator
is now able to use the GPU
for web content,
making it a much more accurate
representation
of what your users will see.
Also, you can use Metal tools,
such as the Xcode
Frame Debugger,
to analyze your WebGL code now.
Besides creating content
with WebGL,
another common way to provide
great visual experience
is through video.
Not all browsers have
the same kind of support
for media formats,
so sometimes it might be tricky
for you to decide
which format
you are going to use.
To make things easier for you,
this year,
we have increased our support
for WebM,
a common media format
on the web.
For a start, the support
is only for streaming playback.
In macOS 11.3, we added support
for playing WebM files
containing VP8 or VP9 video
and Vorbis audio.
And in macOS 12,
we add support for files
containing Opus audio.
Last year, we started supporting
WebM played through
Media Source Extensions
on macOS.
Now, we’re bringing that support
to iPadOS 15.
To check if WebM is supported
in your code,
you can use
MediaCapabilities API,
which lets you detect
the exact media configuration
you want to use.
The configuration on the screen
is supported
in the latest Safari,
and that means VP9
is also supported now.
With support
for this video-coding format,
we expect more web content
to be available
in Safari and WebKit apps.
You can use VP9 in both
streaming and WebRTC.
It works on macOS and iPadOS.
Regarding support
on different devices,
it is available
on all Apple silicon Macs.
For the others, you can check
with MediaCapabilities API,
just like what we just saw
for WebM.
Now, if your site has WebM
or VP9 content,
I encourage you to check
how it works
in the latest Safari and WebKit;
but if you are still deciding
which media format to use,
we would recommend H.264
or HEVC.
H.264 is mature
and well-supported
across browsers.
HEVC has great support
for high-quality videos.
They both come with hardware
acceleration that can provide
smoother playback and longer
playback battery life.
Talking about hosting
video content,
a common case is that
we don’t own the content;
instead, we get it
from a third party.
For example, I see
this nice video on video.domain.
To make it appear on my site,
main.domain,
I can load this video source
from video.domain,
or I just create iframes
of video.domain.
For security reasons,
third-party iframes or resources
do not have access to
first-party storage by default.
And that means
if the resource request
for video.domain is initiated
from main.domain,
it will not include the cookies
of video.domain.
This can be a problem when
web servers of video.domain
only want to serve content
to authenticated users.
And no cookies
means no authentication.
The Storage Access API
solves this issue.
It enables third-party iframes
to request permission
to access first-party cookies.
If user grants the permission,
the third-party video.domain
will be able to access
its first-party cookies.
The Storage Access API has been
available in WebKit and Safari
for over three years.
To improve interoperability,
this year we have added
two new features.
First, access is granted
on a per-page scope.
It means once permission
is granted for a third party,
it is extended to all
its subresources
on the same page.
You don't have to make a request
for each iframe.
Second, we allow nested iframes
to make requests.
This means iframes
inside of iframes
can also request access
to first-party cookies,
which was not possible before.
To learn more
about the new usage,
please check our blog post
“Updates to the Storage
Access API” at webkit.org.
Now we know how to load
or import video content
from a third party
with user permission if needed.
How about creating
something on your own?
With the new Media Recorder API,
it’s very easy to do that.
Media Recorder API enables
you to capture data
from media elements,
which includes
HTML media elements
like video tag
or MediaStream objects.
You can use it to record
from user’s input devices.
You can specify desired options,
such as the container's
MIME type
or desired bit rates of tracks.
The API is simple.
It is comprised
of a single major interface,
MediaRecorder,
which does all the work
of collecting the data from
source and delivering it to you.
Let me show you an example.
I used MediaRecorder API
to build this web app
called "Voice Memo."
This is my first voice memo.
Click the button, it starts
recording from microphone.
Click again, it stops recording
and offers playback.
>> This is my first
voice memo.
That is fun.
And now let’s check
the implementation.
We have two major functions:
startRecording
and stopRecording.
In startRecording,
we get the input media stream
for microphone.
Then we create a MediaRecorder
object with that.
We listen to two events
of the media recorder.
And then we can start
the recorder with start method.
To stop recording, we just need
to call stop method
on mediaRecorder object.
Here are the two event handlers.
When some captured data
is available,
we store it in an array.
When the recording is stopped,
we make a blob with
collected data in an array,
and send it to an existing
audio element for playback.
Just like that, you can create
a functional voice recorder.
After you collect
the audio data,
you may want to edit it.
In this case, you can put
the new Audio Worklet API
to good use.
The Audio Worklet interface
is part of Web Audio API,
which you may
already be familiar with
if you have done audio
processing on the web before.
It allows us to run scripts
such as JavaScript
or WebAssembly code
to process audio on
the audio-rendering thread
supporting custom AudioNodes.
Compared with
ScriptProcessorNode
the previous solution
to run custom script
it reduces the hopping
between rendering thread
and main thread
and ensures low latency.
With Audio Worklet,
I added a new capability
to my Voice Memo.
>> This is
my distorted voice.
If Distortion box is checked
for recording,
some distortion effect
will be applied to the audio.
>> [DISTORTED]
This is my distorted voice
That sounds cool,
and let’s take a look
at how it is implemented.
I modified
the startRecording function
to add audio processing.
We still need to get
the MediaStream
for audio input first.
To use Audio Worklet API,
there are four basic steps.
Step one: create a source.
Step two: create
an AudioWorkletNode
and bind it with
an Audio Worklet processor
which performs audio processing.
The processor
is implemented in a module,
and we will look at it later.
Step three:
create a destination.
Step four: connect the path
from source to destination.
This time, MediaRecorder
takes the output
from AudioWorklet as source
and it records
the distorted audio.
This is the audio-processing
module.
We implement the
DistortionProcessor class here.
It must extend the
AudioWorkletProcessor class
and must provide
the implementation
for process function.
The inputs are the audio samples
coming into Audio Worklet,
and outputs are the resulting
samples after processing.
You can use different algorithms
to create output.
Here, I use a custom function
called distort()
to calculate a value
based on input.
Process function returns true,
meaning the processor node
is active.
That’s the basic structure
of the process function.
After creating
the processor class,
we need to globally register it
under a specified name,
so it can be used to construct
AudioWorkletNode.
Just like that, you can apply
sound effects
to your audio data.
So far we have discussed
about producing
and processing audio data.
How about storing it
or sharing it to somewhere else
for your record?
I guess you don’t want to lose
the recording
after you quit the browser.
With updates to Web Share API
this year,
it’s quite easy to do that.
Web Share is not new
in WebKit and Safari.
If you choose to share a link
on a web page in Safari,
a share sheet will show up
with sharing targets
like Messages, Mail, or AirDrop.
The share sheet that matches
well with the system style
is created with Web Share API.
This year, we have added support
for file sharing.
It means you can share image,
video, audio,
or other types of file
with this API now.
Let’s add the sharing capability
to Voice Memo.
If the Save box is checked,
Voice Memo will create
an audio file with captured data
and display a Share button
to let us share the file.
Here, I want to share
the memo file by email.
With just one click,
a nice draft is created
with the memo file attached.
And let’s check the code.
This is the stop event handler
we saw
in the MediaRecorder example.
First, let’s make
the blob variable
in stop event handler global,
so it can be used
by the share function.
The share function
is the click event handler
of the share button.
It converts a blob to a file
and gives it a file name.
The file is put in an array
because that’s the expected
input type.
Then we check if the API
is available
and if the file can be shared
with canShare method.
If check is passed,
we call navigator.share
with the file array.
There are options
you can specify,
like title and description text.
It’s as easy as that to make
your web app to share files
like a native app does.
Well, if you don’t actually want
to interact with audio data,
but just want the text of it
for example, in the case
of voice command
there is also a new API for you.
That’s Speech Recognition.
Like its name suggested,
Speech Recognition API
captures live audio
and transcribes it to text.
It also gives you probabilities
and alternatives of transcript.
It uses the same speech engine
as Siri,
and it gets all the benefits:
multiple languages support
and great accuracy.
That also means your user
will need to turn on Siri
or Dictation in
System Preferences or Settings
to make the API available.
Recognition can be server based,
so we put up a privacy prompt
when recognition service
is used for the first time
in the app.
Users can change the permission
in System Preferences
or Settings.
Now, let’s update Voice Memo
with this new capability.
If the Recognition box is checked,
it means generating a transcript
for the recording.
>> This is
my Voice Memo transcript.
Period.
And let’s check the code.
The usage is a bit like
media recorder.
Here we have
two major functions:
startRecognition
and stopRecognition.
You need to create
a webkitSpeechRecognition
object first.
Yes, we still keep
the WebKit prefix for now
for compatibility,
so don’t forget to add it.
Then you can set some properties
of the recognition,
like continuous, which asks
recognition to keep going
until it is stopped.
We listen to result
and end events.
With recognition object,
we can call start method
to start
and call stop method to stop.
On result event, we collect
finalTranscript to a string.
Here, I only pick the first item
of the results
because the transcription
alternatives are sorted
based on probabilities.
When recognition stops,
I use a custom log function
to print the transcript
to the screen.
Like that, you can
add recognition capability
to your web content
within just a few lines.
It’s been a long journey,
and there’s one last web API
I think worth mentioning.
You may have noticed
that on macOS and iOS,
the Now Playing widget can show
you media states in Safari.
It’s convenient,
but it usually does not contain
much information.
For example, this only shows
the title of web page;
no information about
what audio is being played.
There is a new web API that can
help you improve this situation:
the Media Session API.
Media Session API lets you
communicate media states
between web page
and other platform components.
If you want your user
to view or control media states
outside of the web page,
like in the Now Playing widget,
this is the API
you need to know.
For more details about
Media Session API,
please check our WWDC session
"Coordinate media playback on
the web with GroupActivities."
And these are the new features
we have just explored.
I hope you feel you have learned
something of it.
And your homework today
is to implement
your own Voice Memo
with these new APIs.
I'm just kidding,
but we do have a few things
we hope you can do
to help us bring you
the best development experience
in WebKit and Safari.
Please try out the new features
in the latest WebKit and Safari
and file bug reports
at bugs.webkit.org.
You can take a sneak peek
of new features
or features
under active development
with Safari Technology Preview.
If you are interested
in web technologies
that are used in WebKit
or Safari,
or interested in joining
the WebKit community,
webkit.org is a good source.
If you want to get fresh updates
about WebKit,
or if you have any question
for us,
don’t forget to follow us
or tag us on Twitter.
Thanks for watching
this session,
and I hope you have a great time
at WWDC!
♪