[music]
[Jerry] Hi, everyone.
Thank you for tuning in.
My name is Jerry,
and I'm excited
to present to you
how to bring Object Capture
assets into AR Quick Look.
As a reminder,
AR Quick Look is the built-in,
system-wide AR viewer
for 3D models across iOS,
available in Safari,
Messages, Files, and more.
Apps and websites
can embed 3D models,
allowing people to view
and interact with them
in their own environment.
This can be a great way
to showcase a product,
promote an event,
or provide additional content
in an immersive experience,
such as this interactive demo
for the Apple TV+ show
"For All Mankind"
where you can learn more
about a cosmonaut space suit.
In this presentation,
I'll be talking about how to use
the Object Capture API
to create 3D content
for AR Quick Look,
as well as some
of the best practices
to keep in mind,
depending on your use case.
Then, I'll give a quick recap
on how to integrate
AR Quick Look
in your app or website.
And finally,
I'll show some
exciting applications
that AR Quick Look
and Object Capture
can help create.
Let's get started with
the 3D content creation process
for your AR Quick Look
experience.
Previously,
if you wanted to create
3D content for AR Quick Look,
it required the use
of a 3D-modeling software.
However,
they are usually expensive
and can be difficult
to approach for everyone.
This year,
we've introduced
our new Object Capture API,
built into RealityKit,
as an alternative way
to generate a USDZ file.
It allows you to create
a high-quality 3D model
by using a collection
of still images
of the real-world object.
Object Capture does
the heavy lifting
to create a USDZ file
that can be viewed directly
in AR Quick Look.
You can
also use Reality Composer
if you want to add interactive
custom behaviors to your model.
For example,
you can add tap triggers
and camera actions
to your digital scene.
Together, these technologies
now make it easier than ever
for anyone to create
an immersive AR experience.
Let's see a demo
of this workflow in action.
I've just started an online shop
selling handmade pottery,
and here's one of them.
I'll show you how to create
a 3D model of this pot
and add behaviors
so that customers can preview it
on their own desk
with a variety of succulents
before buying.
But first,
let's see it in action.
Here is the virtual succulent
placed on my desk.
Let me go in for a closer look.
You can see
the geometric spirals
in great detail.
OK, now let's preview
a few other succulents.
I'll tap on the green one...
and it switches to the red one.
Let's check out a few more.
Now I'll tap again.
Oh, I really like this gray one!
It really matches with the pot.
I'm curious how it looks
compared to the real one.
Wow, that looks very convincing,
except the leaves have grown
a lot bigger
since I scanned this
a few weeks ago.
Now, as a friendly reminder,
Object Capture does not make
your virtual plants grow
automatically,
but if you want,
you can simulate that
by changing the scale
using Reality Composer.
I think this would
make a wonderful asset
for my online store.
Now let me walk you through
how I created this from scratch.
The first step for me
was to take photos
of the succulent pot by itself,
from all angles,
on a neutral background.
I then used Object Capture
to generate a USDZ model.
Similarly,
I repeated these steps
for the each
of the succulent plants
to generate
three separate USDZ models.
Now let me show you
how to swap
different succulent plants
in the same pot
by adding behaviors
in Reality Composer.
I've already started a project
where I've added the pot base
and arranged
the three succulents
so it properly rests
inside the pot.
Now let's add the behaviors.
First, I added
a "hide on start" behavior
so initially only
the green succulent is shown.
When someone taps
on the green succulent,
we want it to swap
and show the red one.
For this,
I've added a tap trigger,
along with "hide"
and "show" actions.
I then repeated these steps
so we can swap
from the red to gray
and gray to green.
And that's it!
Now we just need
to export the asset,
and we can view it
in AR Quick Look
like we just saw earlier.
Now that we've just seen
how easy it is to create content
using Object Capture,
let's talk
about the best practices
when exporting models
for viewing in AR Quick Look.
When exporting a USDZ file
using Object Capture,
it is important to determine
which detail setting to use.
Here's a table to illustrate
the different characteristics
of each setting.
There's always a tradeoff
between visual fidelity
and file size.
Exporting a USDZ
with a small file size
is an important consideration
for AR Quick Look
because it results
in a shorter download time
for users.
No matter which detail setting
you choose,
Object Capture will always use
the same underlying algorithms
to generate
a high-quality reconstruction,
but applies varying
levels of mesh decimation
and texture down-sampling,
depending
on the specified detail setting.
The Reduced
and Medium detail settings
offer a great balance
between visual fidelity
and file size.
Therefore, when creating content
for AR Quick Look,
we recommend
that you first export
in both Reduced
and Medium detail settings.
Then you can choose
which to keep
after evaluating
both the visual differences
and other important
considerations,
which I will talk about next.
As we've just seen,
the Reduced detail setting
will generate models
with the smallest file size.
This makes it ideal
for web distribution,
as it reduces the download time
before your model can be viewed.
This is also
the recommended setting
if you plan
on combining multiple assets
in a single scene,
perhaps to showcase
a collection of succulents.
These attributes make
the Reduced detail setting
a great choice
for a majority of use cases.
In certain situations
where you notice
a significant difference
in visual quality
between the Reduced
and Medium settings,
it may be more suitable
to use the Medium detail.
This is usually the case when
you have a very complex object,
and would require you
to take hundreds of images
for reconstructing it
using Object Capture.
Keep in mind, however,
that this will generate
a USDZ with a larger file size,
so it's best not to combine
multiple models together.
For example,
here I've taken photos
of the succulent
and pot base together.
Similarly,
the Medium detail setting
is more suitable for apps
where there is already a local
copy of the asset on the device,
which eliminates download times.
In summary,
we recommend you evaluate
both detail settings
and base your decision depending
on your object and use case.
Be sure to test your asset
on a variety of iOS hardware
to ensure device compatibility
and performance.
With either detail setting,
it's best to ensure quality
at the source.
So always take sharp images
and avoid motion blur
to generate a good,
quality reconstruction.
Also, make sure to provide
sufficient overlap
of at least 70%
between adjacent photos
and fill the frame
with the object.
For more details,
I encourage you to read
the "Capturing Photographs"
article
and check out
the "Object Capture" session.
Now that you know
the best practices,
let's recap how to integrate
AR Quick Look.
As you know, it's possible
to embed AR Quick Look
in your app or website
with just a few lines of code.
Let's go over a quick recap
of the integration.
If you are embedding
AR Quick Look in an app,
you can use
the Quick Look framework.
Here we create a new
QLPreviewController
and assign "self"
as its dataSource.
Then we present it
like a regular view controller.
Of course,
we also have to implement
the QLPreviewController
dataSource protocol,
which tells Quick Look
how many previews to show
and what each is going to be.
Here we create
an ARQL previewItem
with the URL
to a local file on disk.
Then we return it
so the system knows
to present AR Quick Look.
We also provide ways
to customize the experience,
such as disabling
content scaling in AR mode
so that people can always see
the object at its true scale
when placed into the world.
To disable scaling,
set the allowsContentScaling
property to be "false."
If you are integrating
the AR Quick Look experience
on your website,
you can add this a-tag snippet
to your HTML,
replacing the URL
to your own model
and image thumbnail.
And be sure to include
the rel="ar" attribute.
This will add the AR badge icon
to the thumbnail.
Similarly,
it's possible to disable
content scaling in AR
when embedded on web pages too.
To disable content scaling,
set allowsContentScaling
to be 0.
When embedded on websites,
you can also surface Apple Pay
and custom actions,
like preorder,
directly in AR Quick Look
to allow customers
to take the next step
in your order flow.
So that's a quick summary
of just some of the things
you can do with AR Quick Look.
For more details,
I encourage you to check out
our previous sessions.
Now let's talk about
some real-world applications
with AR Quick Look.
With the announcement
of Object Capture,
we've now made
the entire process
of creating
and distributing 3D content
much more accessible
for everyone.
Object Capture
does the heavy lifting
of generating a USDZ file.
Reality Composer makes it easy
to create multi-asset scenes
and add interactivity to models.
AR Quick Look provides
a great viewing experience
for apps and websites on iOS
and is also available on macOS.
Together,
these technologies allow
for the creation
of both improved
and new experiences
in a variety of fields.
Let's take a look at some
examples for inspiration.
E-commerce is one
of the most popular use cases
for AR Quick Look,
and for good reason.
Viewing 3D models
with AR Quick Look
helps customers visualize
products in their own space,
whether it's shoes,
photo frames, or furniture.
Now, with Object Capture,
you, as a retailer,
can easily create 3D models
of your product
without needing to have
prior 3D experience,
like this Fragment Design x
Air Jordan 3 sneaker
that the team behind GOAT app
has created
using Object Capture.
You can also take advantage
of Reality Composer
to add additional behaviors to
enhance the viewing experience.
For example,
similar to the succulent demo,
where I can swap between
different succulent plants,
you can make an app
that allows customers
to preview
different outfits or purses.
Another use case is for museums.
Historical artifacts are often
stored in protective cases,
making it difficult
to view from all angles.
However,
by capturing the object in 3D,
viewers can see and interact
with a detailed virtual
representation of the artifact
on their own device.
Not only does AR Quick Look
allow you to tour museums
remotely,
but it can also enable
new forms of in-person exhibits
that can only be experienced
in a virtual world.
You can also add voiceover audio
to explain the 3D content
or help people
who are hard of seeing,
like this Zemi figure from
the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
Let's have a listen.
[voiceover] It was made
around 1000 AD
by a sculptor
of the Taino civilizations
of the Antilles archipelago
in the Caribbean Sea,
probably in what is now
the Dominican Republic.
[Jerry] Another great use case
of Object Capture
and AR Quick Look
is in the field of education.
Diagrams and videos have
historically been 2D,
which can sometimes
make it challenging
to convey 3D concepts.
Now, with augmented reality,
we can teach in, well, 3D.
Teachers can now create
engaging lessons
by leveraging 3D models
generated with Object Capture.
And technology can provide
immediate feedback
and interactivity
so students can learn
and discover at their own pace.
This doesn't just help teachers
with lesson planning.
Kids can also express
their creativity in AR.
For example,
the Qlone app allows kids
to create 3D models
of their favorite toy
or art project.
It provides
a convenient visual guide
and automatically
takes pictures as appropriate
so kids can scan
objects by themselves.
Qlone is working
on incorporating
the Object Capture technology
with seamless integration
between their iOS and Mac apps,
making it easier for kids
to share their creations
with friends and family.
I've invited the kids
of our Apple colleagues
to share some of the work
that they've done.
After capturing photos
and generating 3D models
with Object Capture,
the kids then added
digital interactions
using Reality Composer.
Let's check it out.
The first is a dinosaur costume
that comes to life with audio.
[dinosaur growling]
We also have a nice set
of plates and cups displayed.
And here's a cool interaction
where the speech bubbles
between the puffer fish
and octopi
are always facing you.
Those are some really cool,
creative art projects.
As you've just seen,
anyone can now develop immersive
AR experiences from scratch
using a combination
of Object Capture,
Reality Composer,
and AR Quick Look.
Object Capture creates
high-quality assets
that are ready to be viewed
in AR Quick Look.
Reality Composer makes it easy
to combine multiple assets
into a single scene
and add interactivity to models.
For more information,
I encourage you to visit
the AR Quick Look Gallery page
for examples
and check out
the "Object Capture" session.
And that's it.
Thank you for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[music]