[music]
[Rini]
Hello. My name is Rini Patel,
and I'm from the GPU software
engineering team.
In this session,
I'll be introducing the new
shader compilation workflows in Metal.
The Metal shading language
is a C++-based language,
and its compilation model closely
resembles the CPU compilation model.
As GPU workloads are increasing
in complexity, Metal has similarly evolved
to address the flexibility and performance
needed to support the modern use cases.
Some common challenges
that you may have already faced
while authoring your shaders can be
sharing utility code across pipelines,
modifying shader behavior at
runtime without recompilation,
or an ability to reuse compiled
GPU binaries between application launches.
So, let's walk through a simple
shader code and discuss the scenarios.
Here, we have a simple fragment
shader that returns the result
of foo() or bar(),
depending on the result of condition.
Now, if those functions are
called by multiple pipelines,
we might want to compile them just once
and link them to each pipeline instead.
We might need to link
a different implementation
of these functions at the runtime,
or we might need a fragment shader
to be extensible
in order to handle
a new case statement for baz().
We may also want to be able
to call a user-provided function bat()
instead of baz()
from our fragment function.
As you can see,
there are many different requirements
that a shader authoring pipeline may have,
and Metal offers
various APIs to support
different implementations.
Each approach will have a different
trade-off between compilation time
and shader performance.
And today, I'd like to talk about
the new compilation workflows that will
help you find the perfect balance
between performance and flexibility.
We are going to start with the new support
for dynamic libraries
for render pipelines,
as well as function pointers
for render pipelines.
We'll talk a bit about
the additions to binaryArchive API.
Then, we will
see private linked functions.
And finally,
we'll introduce a brand-new feature
for stitching visible functions in Metal.
So, let's start with the dynamic
library support in Metal.
Dynamic libraries are a common
tool in software engineering.
They are shared object files
that allow you to compartmentalize
utility code into
a stand-alone compilation unit.
They help reduce
the amount of compiled shader code
and reuse it between multiple pipelines.
Additionally,
they allow you to dynamically link, load,
and share the GPU binary code.
Last year, we introduced dynamic languages
for compute pipelines,
and to get more of an introduction to
dynamic libraries in Metal,
I encourage you to check out
our previous year's presentation,
"Build GPU Binaries with Metal."
This year, we are bringing dynamic
libraries to render and tile pipelines.
With this added support,
you can now share utility libraries
across all
your compute and render workloads.
And now that we know
what dynamic libraries are,
it's time to talk
about some of the use cases.
Helper functions are often
used across general compute,
vertex, fragment, and tile shaders.
With the addition of dynamic
libraries to render pipelines, you can now
manage large amount of utility code
and share it across all of your workloads.
You can precompile the libraries
that may be used at runtime
without experiencing
the compilation slow down,
and even swap out functions of the runtime,
simply by changing the libraries that are
loaded while creating the pipeline.
They also help your users to author
shader code that you can load
as part of your pipeline without
needing to provide the source.
So, we have talked about when
to use dynamic libraries.
Let's now look at
how to build and work with them.
In our example fragment shader,
we call functions foo() and bar(),
but we do not provide the implementation
for either at compile time.
Instead, the implementation for these
functions exist in a Metal library
that we later link when
creating our render pipeline.
And it's also possible
to provide separate libraries
for each of the functions
that you may use.
Let's now discuss the tools
and flexibilities you have
by building dynamic libraries in Metal.
You first need to compile your Metal
shader source to AIR, and you can do that
either by using Xcode's Metal
toolchain as part of your build process,
or by compiling from source by
using newLibraryWithSource API at runtime.
With your compiled Metal shader in AIR,
you can now create a dynamic library
simply by using
the newDynamicLibrary API.
This library is ready to be
used in its GPU binary format.
But what if you want
to reuse it in later runs?
To do that, you can serialize
your dynamic library to disk,
and this can be
done using serializeToURL API.
And later, you can reuse it by
calling the newDynamicLibraryWithURL API.
Let's now go through an example
which calls functions from
dynamic library and fragment shader.
In this example, we declare functions
foo() and bar() using the extern keyword,
but we do not
provide definitions for them.
To use them, we simply call
these functions from our fragment shader.
And you can provide
an implementation for the extern functions
when building your Metal library.
Now, keep in mind that it's
also possible to replace those
implementations with something
different at the runtime.
And to do this, you just need
to add your dynamic libraries
to the appropriate
preloaded libraries array.
In our case, it's fragment,
but a similar property is available
for each stage and pipeline.
And the symbols
will be resolved in the same order
in which the libraries
are added to this array.
This workflow
is well suited for experimenting
with new implementations.
And that's it for the dynamic libraries.
If you are looking to use Metal dynamic
libraries, the support is available
for compute pipelines on Apple GPU
family 7 and above in macOS Monterey.
It's also available for other GPUs,
as well as most Mac family 2 devices,
although you’ll need to call Metal
device supports dynamic libraries.
On iOS 15, this feature is available
on all Apple 6 devices and above.
Render and tile pipeline
support is available on all devices
that support Apple 6 feature set.
Next, let's talk about the improvements
to function pointers coming this year.
Function pointer is a simple construct
for referring to a code that we can call
to make your code extensible by
allowing you to call functions
that we have not seen before.
Last year, we introduced compute
pipeline function pointers, and for that,
I recommend you to check out our previous
year's presentation,
"Get to know Metal function pointers."
This year, we are extending function
pointer support
to the render and tile
pipelines on Apple Silicon.
Similar to dynamic libraries,
function pointers allow
creating customizable pipelines.
With function pointers,
a GPU pipeline can call code
that has not been seen during
the pipeline compilation.
With function pointer tables,
code execution behavior
can change dynamically,
either when you bind the different
function table or when the GPU pipeline
indexes into the function pointer table.
You can also decide
how to balance compilation performance
against the runtime performance
using function pointers.
For fastest compilation,
for example, you can precompile
function pointers to a GPU
binary and quickly deal-in the pipeline.
For the best runtime performance,
on the other hand,
you can have your pipeline reference
AIR representations of functions,
allowing the compiler
to do maximum optimizations.
Let's now see how you can set
the function pointers in your code.
There are three basic building blocks.
We start by instantiating the function,
then configuring a pipeline
with these functions,
and finally, creating function tables.
Once this is done, using a new
render loop doesn't involve much code.
So let's dive in to the details
of each of the steps.
To start using function pointers,
we first declare the function descriptor
and instantiate to compile a GPU
binary version of the function.
This will accelerate pipeline
creation time, and it's as simple as
declaring a descriptor and setting
the option to compile to binary.
When the Metal function foo is created
from library using this descriptor,
the function will be compiled
by the GPU backend compiler.
Next, we need to configure
the render pipeline descriptor.
First, we add the functions
via the pipeline descriptor
to the stage where they'll be used,
which can be vertex,
fragment, or tile stage.
We can choose to add
functions in AIR or binary form.
When adding AIR functions,
the compiler will statically link
the visible functions,
allowing for the backend
compilers to optimize the code.
Adding binary functions,
on the other hand, will inform the driver
which externally-compiled functions
are callable from a given pipeline.
One additional thing to note here
is when you create a pipeline
that uses binary functions
and if the code that you are
calling has a complex call chain,
as illustrated here, it's important to
specify the maximum call stack depth
necessary, as the compiler cannot
do static analysis to determine the depth.
The compiler will default
to maximum depth to be run,
and you may get a stack overflow
if the depth isn't specified correctly.
In contrast,
specifying the depth correctly
leads to a better resource
conception and optimal performance.
So once the descriptor is fully set up,
you can create your pipeline
that's ready to use function pointer.
After creating your pipeline,
the next steps are to create
visible function tables and populate
them with function handles in the API.
First, we create a visible
function table using a descriptor
and specify a render stage.
Then, we create function handles
to reference those functions.
Both the function handles
and table are specific to a given pipeline
and selected stage.
You can then insert the handles into
the function table using setFunction API.
Let's now see how do you use this function
tables after we have done all the set up.
First, as a part
of the command and coding,
we bind the visible function
table to a buffer index.
In the shader itself,
the visible_function_table is passed
as a buffer binding, and we can then
call our functions through this table.
And that was a simple case
of using function pointers.
When using function pointers,
it's not uncommon to create a pipeline
just to find out later that you need to
access one or more additional functions.
Now, if you could achieve that by
creating the second pipeline
from an identical descriptor,
which adds the additional functions,
but that would
trigger a pipeline compilation.
To accelerate this process,
Metal lets you specify if
you plan on extending
the original pipeline.
This way, a new pipeline can be
created faster from an existing pipeline,
and it can use all the function
pointer tables that were
initially created
for the original pipeline.
To do that from code,
when creating the original pipeline,
set supportAddingBinaryFunctions
option to YES,
for all the stages that you wish
to extend.
Then when you need
to create an extended pipeline,
create RenderPipelineFunctionDescriptor
and include new binary function
bat() on the fragment length function list.
Finally, call new RenderPipelineState
with additional binary functions
on renderPipeline1
to create renderPipeline2,
which will be identical, but includes
the additional function pointer bat.
And that's pretty much it.
Now that we have seen how to use function
pointers, here is where you can use them.
Function pointers in compute pipelines are
supported on Apple GPU family 6 and above,
in macOS Big Sur, and iOS 14.
They are also supported
on Mac family 2 devices.
And this year, we are extending
function pointer support for render
and tile pipelines on Apple GPU family 6
and above,
in Mac OS Monterey, and iOS 15.
The next topic I'd like to talk
about is managing binary function
compilation overhead.
Compiling shaders
can be extremely time intensive,
and you may want to control
the overhead it brings to an application.
To help with that, we added
binaryArchives to Metal last year.
BinaryArchives can collect
and store the compiled binary versions
of the pipeline to disk, saving
compilation time and subsequent runs
and reducing the memory
cost associated with the compilation.
This year, we are adding the ability
to store visible and intersection function
to binaryArchives, allowing
you to significantly reduce the overhead.
So, let's take a look at how you store
into and load from binaryArchives.
To add a function to BinaryArchive,
simply call addFunctionWithDescriptor
and pass the function descriptor
and source library as arguments.
To load the binary function
pointer from BinaryArchive,
place the BinaryArchive on the function
descriptor's binaryArchives array,
and then call Metal library
method newFunctionWithDescriptor.
If any of the archives in the array
has the compiled function pointer,
it will be returned immediately,
without having to recompile.
Here are some
of the rules that illustrate how
newFunctionWithDescriptor will
behave with the binaryArchives.
We first search for the binary version
of the function in the BinaryArchive list.
If the function is found,
it will be returned,
and if it's not found,
we'll check the CompileToBinary option
and return AIR version of the function,
if binary compilation wasn't requested.
On the other hand,
if the binary compilation was requested,
then depending on the pipeline option,
FailOnBinaryArchiveMiss
will either compile the function
binary at runtime or return nil.
When you integrate
MTLBinaryArchive into your application,
you can use the same archive
to store all your GPU-compiled code.
Your render, tile, and compute pipelines,
as well as your binary function pointers.
And after your archive has been
prepopulated with the pipeline state
objects and binary functions,
you can serialize it to a disk.
Collecting and storing your GPU
binaries this way will help
accelerate shader compilation
on to subsequent application runs.
When using
a pipeline with function pointers,
you might want to cache
the pipeline state object itself.
But why should you cache when
you have a pipeline that comes
with different
function pointer combinations?
For example, here,
there are three pipeline descriptors
which are identical,
except for their user function pointers.
So, if you are
using AIR function pointers,
you need to cache all
permutations of the pipeline.
However, when using
the binary function pointers,
it's enough to cache a single
variant because the pipeline binary code
doesn't change when a new
function pointer is added to it.
And you can use
that archive to find all other variants
of the pipelines,
independent of which binary
function pointers are used
in the pipeline descriptor.
To wrap it up, you always want
to use binaryArchives in Metal,
as it's a great tool to control
your pipeline compilation cost.
The support for binaryArchives
is available on all devices,
but adding
function pointers to a BinaryArchive
depends on the function pointer ability.
Now, I'd like to briefly
talk about our next addition this year,
which is private linked functions.
So far, we have discussed how
dynamic libraries and function pointers
provide a lot of flexibility
to your shader development pipeline,
but sometimes,
for performance reasons,
you may want to statically link
an external function into your pipeline.
Last year, we added
linkedFunctions API with a support
for statically linking AIR functions.
However, this requires function
pointer support,
as these are usable in a function table.
This year,
we are introducing privateFunctions.
Both functions and privateFunctions
are linked statically at the AIR level,
but since those are private,
no function handling can be made
for a function pointer,
and this allows compiler
to fully optimize your shader code.
So, where are they available?
Because this feature works
with code at the AIR level,
it is available on all devices
in macOS Monterey and iOS 15.
Moving on to the last addition I'd
like to discuss today,
function stitching.
Some applications need to generate
dynamic content at the runtime.
For example, to implement
customizations for the graphic effects
based on user input.
Or, say, complex compute
kernel based on incoming data.
Function stitching is
a great tool to solve this.
Prior to function stitching,
the only way to do this
was by generating Metal source strings.
The string-manipulation technique
can be somewhat inefficient,
and it also implies
that the translation from Metal to AIR
will happen at runtime,
which can be an expensive opration.
So let's take a look at how
function stitching works.
Function stitching provides
a mechanism to generate functions
from computation graphs
and precompiled functions at runtime.
The computation graph is
a Directed Acyclic Graph.
And in a graph,
there are two kind of nodes:
input nodes that represent
the arguments of the generated function,
and function nodes
that represent function calls.
There are also two kind of edges:
data edges that represent how data flows
from one node to another,
and control edges that represent
the order in which function
calls should be executed.
We'll see how function
stitching uses a computation graph
to generate a function.
We'll start with the notion
of stitchable functions.
The function in a graph must
have the stitchable attribute.
Such function is a visible function,
which can be used
with the functionStitching API.
The stitchable functions can
be part of the Metal library
shipped with your application bundle
to avoid Metal to AIR translation cost.
The stitching
process generates the functions
directly in AIR and completely
skipping the Metal frontend.
The generated function is
a regular stitchable function,
so it can be linked into a pipeline,
or used directly as function pointer,
or it can be used
for generating other functions.
So, consider the previous graph,
and let's assume that we have
dual functions A and C from
library as described previously.
Let's now see what happens
when we bind these functions to the graph.
The stitcher here associates
a corresponding function type
to each function node.
N0 and N1 get the type from FunctionA,
and N2 gets the type from FunctionC.
After that, the stitcher infers
the types for the input nodes
by looking at the parameter types
of the functions using them.
For example,
Input0 is inferred to be the type devised
in pointer because it's
the first argument for N0 and N1.
The stitcher then
generates a function equivalent
to the following one described in Metal.
With the functionStitching API,
we can generate a library
containing such
functions directly from AIR.
And now that we have fair
idea on how stitching works,
here is how you can use it in the API.
First, we need to define
the stitched function inputs.
In this case, we simply make enough input
nodes to account for all the arguments.
Next, we create function nodes for each
function we wish to call in our graph.
For each function call,
we define the name, arguments,
and control dependencies if we have
any explicit ordering requirements.
And finally, we create the graph
with the function name,
the function nodes used in a graph,
and any function attribute
we want to apply.
You also assign an outputNode,
which will return the output value
of the resulting stitched function.
So, we have our graph.
Now, we can create a function using it.
The first step is to create
a StitchedLibraryDescriptor.
We add our stitchableFunctions
and functionGraph to this descriptor.
We then create a library
using the descriptor, and now,
we can create our stitched
function out of this library.
This stitched function is now ready to be
used anywhere a stitchable function
is expected, including as
a function in another stitching graph.
And that's it for the function stitching.
This API is also available across all
devices in macOS Monterey and iOS 15.
So, as a quick recap, today,
we looked at dynamic libraries
and function pointers
for render pipelines.
Private linked functions, which can be
used to statically link visible functions.
And how function stitching
can save compilation time
when dynamically creating shaders.
So, when would
you choose one over the other?
Dynamic libraries are an excellent choice
to link helper and utility functions.
And they are best used when
you have a fixed set of utility functions,
and those functions do not
change very frequently.
Function pointers add the ability
for a shader to invoke functions
that it knows nothing about,
other than their signature.
It doesn't need to know how many
functions exist, the names,
or even what speed-flexibility trade-off
the developer has made
using AIR or binaries.
And this year,
you can also cache function pointers.
Private functions offer
you a way to statically link functions
to a pipeline state object by name.
They are internal to the pipeline,
so they cannot be encoded
in a visible function table,
but they allow the compiler
to do maximum optimization,
and they are supported
across all GPU families.
And finally, function stitching
gives you a way to precompile snippets
of your code directly to AIR and perform
function compilation at runtime.
If you are compositing
Metal shader strings today
and have to pay the cost of compiling
from source at runtime,
then function stitching would
greatly accelerate this workflow.
I hope that you can leverage
these compiler features
to develop
new experiences using Metal.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC 2021.
[music]