[percussive music]
[Tanuja] Hi, my name is Tanuja,
and I'm an engineer
on the OS Performance team.
Today Stefan and I are going
to talk about how to detect
and diagnose memory issues
in your applications.
We will start with looking
into the impact
of an application's
memory footprint.
We will then talk about
the tools
to profile your
memory usage
and the types of memory
issues you may encounter.
Let's jump right in.
One question you might
immediately ask is,
why should I care about my
application's memory footprint?
The key reason is that
it improves your app's
user experience tremendously.
There is a finite amount
of memory on the system
and monitoring your app's memory
use can prevent the system
from terminating your app
to reclaim that memory.
This means your app
can preserve its state
when in the background,
which is great,
because loading
into memory takes time,
and keeping your memory
footprint compact
increases the chance
of your application
remaining in memory, leading
to faster app activations.
Reducing your memory use
also results in a dynamic,
responsive experience
which is exactly
what your users want
as they explore
your new features.
By being strategic about
with what your app
has loaded into memory, your app
can avoid the cost of waiting
to reclaim memory as your user
interacts with your app.
Being strategic about
your memory usage
also opens the door to a wider
range of features
you could add to your app,
such as loading videos,
including animations,
and a whole lot more.
Finally, our devices are
constantly evolving over time,
and our newer devices have more
physical memory than before.
By reducing your memory
footprint,
your app will be just as
performant on older devices,
increasing the audience
that can enjoy your app.
By monitoring your app's memory
footprint,
your app will activate faster,
be more responsive,
handle complex features,
and be performant
on a wider range of devices.
Let's now take a look at what
makes up your memory footprint.
There are three categories
we use to break down
your application's
memory profile:
dirty, compressed,
and clean memory.
Let's take a quick look at
what each of these includes.
Dirty memory consists of memory
written by your application.
It also includes
all heap allocations
such as when you use malloc,
decoded image buffers,
and frameworks.
Compressed memory
refers to any dirty pages
that haven't recently
been accessed
that the memory
compressor has compressed.
These pages will be
decompressed on access.
Note that we do not have
the concept of swap on iOS,
which is specific to macOS.
And finally,
we have clean memory.
Clean memory is memory
that has not been written to
or data that can be paged out.
For example,
these can be memory mapped files
such as images that are on disk
but loaded into memory.
Or they can be frameworks.
When we refer your
application's memory footprint,
we're really talking
the your app's dirty memory
and compressed memory together.
Clean memory
does not count here.
This is
a high-level understanding
of your memory footprint.
For a more in-depth,
detailed explanation,
we recommend you check out
the iOS memory deep dive talk
from WWDC 2018.
Let's now take a look at
the tools you can use
to profile your memory
footprint.
Xcode offers a suite
of tools to help monitor
your app's memory
performance throughout
both the development
and production workflows.
The XCTest framework helps you
monitor your memory footprint
directly in your project's unit
and UI tests,
while MetricKit
and the Xcode Organizer
allow you to monitor memory
metrics in production
from your customers.
The continuation of this talk
will be in the context of using
performance XCTests.
But note that these
techniques still apply
to general memory triage
and investigations.
Using performance XCTests,
you can measure system resources
such as memory utilization,
CPU usage, disk writes,
and a whole lot more.
Let's take a look at
an example test together.
Let's say I'm an app
developer at Meal Planner,
an app that helps you organize
what you will eat in a week,
and I want to measure
the memory usage
of this new save meal feature
I've added
that lets user download
the recipe to their device.
In my performance test,
I'm using the
measure(metrics:options:block:) API
and I'm specifying
that I want to measure
the memory use
of my targeted application.
In the body
of the measure block,
I'm launching the application,
manually telling
the measure API
to start measuring,
and then tapping on
the save meal button.
I wait up to 30 seconds
for the recipe download
to complete by checking
for an update in the UI.
Now I can run this test
directly in Xcode's UI
to view my measurements.
I can access my measurements
by clicking on
the gray diamond
next to my test.
The results popover UI
has a drop down
that shows me
which metrics were measured.
The bar graph
on the bottom shows me
the measurements for each
individual iteration.
The average of
all five iterations
is computed and displayed.
I can now decide if I want
to set this run's average
as my baseline for future
tests to be compared against.
A future run of the test
would now fail
if its average is greater
than the set baseline.
We call this deviation from
the set baseline a regression.
A regression indicates that
we should stop, investigate,
and fix our code to make sure
that the test passes.
We are excited to share
that in Xcode 13,
we've added in a new feature
to collect diagnostics
to help triage
these test regressions.
There are two diagnostics
that we find valuable:
ktrace files and memory graphs.
Ktrace files
are powerful and versatile.
They can be used for general
system investigations,
or they can be focused
on specific issues,
such as diving into
the rendering pipeline
when investigating hitches
or looking into reasons
for why your main thread
might be blocked,
resulting in a hang.
These ktrace files can
be opened and analyzed
in Instruments
using your normal workflow.
The second diagnostic
is a memory graph
which are great for
memory-specific investigations.
Memory graphs can be used
with Xcode's visual debugger
as well as a variety
of command line tools,
some of which we'll cover
later in this talk.
A memory graph is essentially
a snapshot
of your process's address space
at an instance in time.
Memgraphs record
the address and size
of each virtual
memory region
and each
allocated malloc block,
as well as pointers between
those regions and blocks.
This allows you to inspect
individual objects
on the heap,
view data regions associated
with linked frameworks,
and more.
XCTest automatically enables
malloc stack logging,
which captures backtraces
for newly allocated objects.
To enable
diagnostic collection,
use the xcodebuild
command line tool
in conjunction with the
enablePerformanceTestsDiagnostics flag.
This flag will enable
ktrace collection
for nonmemory metrics
and memgraphs
for memory metrics.
Once our previously written
performance test
is done running,
we see the following
printed to our console.
This is quite a lot,
but there are a few
key things to look for.
The first thing to look for is
if the test failed or passed.
In this case, the test failed.
The output also calls out
that the test failed
specifically
due to a regression.
Our new average is 12%
worse than our baseline.
Finally, we can find
the path to our xcresult bundle.
When we open the xcresult bundle
in Xcode,
we see the memory
measurements at the top
next to the test name.
We can then expand the test logs
and towards the bottom,
we can find our
attached memgraphs.
Once downloaded and unzipped,
we find 2 memgraphs.
This is because we append
an additional iteration
to your test to enable
malloc stack logging.
We collect an initial memgraph,
prefixed with pre,
at the beginning of
the measured iteration,
and we collect
a second memgraph,
prefixed with post,
at the end of the iteration.
This allows you to analyze
the memory growth
over the period of one single
iteration if needed.
Now with ktrace files
and memory graphs
with malloc stack logging
enabled,
you are ready to not just answer
if a regression occurred
but also why did
the regression occur?
I'll now hand it off
to my colleague, Stefan,
to talk about the types
of memory issues
you may encounter
when looking into your collected
memgraph diagnostics.
[Stefan] Thanks, Tanuja.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Stefan, an engineer
on the OS Performance Team.
I'll be going over some
common memory issues
you might find in your app
as well as how you can diagnose,
fix, and prevent them.
I'll go over two types of memory
issues: leaks and heap issues,
which can be broken down into
heap allocation regressions
and fragmentation issues.
This is not an exhaustive list,
but it does cover some
of the most common issues.
I'll also cover some
command line workflows
that can be used
to diagnose these issues.
For a more in-depth summary
of the command line tools,
check out the iOS memory deep
dive talk from WWDC 2018.
Let's start
by discussing memory leaks.
A leak occurs when the process
allocates an object
and loses all references to it
without ever deallocating it.
Here I have
an example object graph,
where the gray arrows denote
references between objects.
Notice that every object has
at least one reference to it.
Notice the dotted line reference
from object A to object B.
Let's say I set this reference
to nil, removing it.
With that reference gone,
object B has been leaked.
There are
no references to it at all.
It's still dirty,
but the process has no way
to reference it
and no way to free it
until it exits.
For this reason,
you should always fix leaks.
A common way objects leak
in Swift is via retain cycles.
In this diagram, objects A and B
are in a retain cycle.
They reference one another,
but there are no external
references to either of them.
This means the process can't
access or free either of them,
so they're considered leaked.
Fortunately, most objects
in Swift are managed by
Swift's automatic reference
counting system, or ARC,
which prevents a lot of leaks.
If you're working with objects
not managed by ARC,
such as unsafe pointers,
make sure you deallocate them
before you lose
your references to them.
Even ARC managed objects
are susceptible to being
part of a retain cycle.
So avoid creating strong
circular references
in your code.
If a circular reference
is absolutely necessary,
consider a weak reference
instead, because weak references
won't prevent objects
from being deallocated.
Let's look at an example
from the Meal Planner app.
Tanuja has sent me some
pre and post memgraphs
from the failing XCTest.
Right away, I want to check
for leaks in the post memgraph.
To do this,
I run leaks on the memgraph.
This shows me some
helpful information
about any leaks I have.
The output shows I have 4 leaks
for a total of 240 leaked bytes.
Further down, the output
includes a detailed view
of the object graph
for each of the leaks,
which gives me some clues
as to what might be leaking.
The top of the object
graph says ROOT CYCLE,
which means I'm dealing
with a retain cycle.
There are
some useful symbols here.
Looks like this retain cycle
probably includes
meal plan and menu item objects.
Because malloc stack logging
is enabled for XCTests,
the output also includes
an allocation call stack
for each leak.
This is extremely useful
for finding
which objects leaked.
Often, you'll want to find
the section of the call stack
with symbols from your code.
Here's the portion of
the call stack from my code.
The leaking meal plan
object is allocated
in the populateMealData
function.
I'll open up Xcode and see
if I can fix the issue.
Here's the populateMealData
function I saw in leaks.
Here I'm allocating a meal plan
object and a menu item object,
which are the two objects
I saw in my retain cycle.
Hmm, this addMealToMealPlan
function looks a bit suspicious.
I'll take a look.
Hmm, so it looks like I'm
calling addItem on the meal plan,
but I'm also calling
addPlan on the menu item.
This is for a feature
allowing us to see all the items
for a plan but also which
plan an item is associated with.
Here in meal plan,
addItem adds the menu item
to an array,
saving a reference to it.
And here in menu item,
addPlan saves a reference
to the meal plan.
So this is definitely
a retain cycle because
they both hold a strong
reference to each other.
Once populateMealData exits,
both the meal plan
and menu item objects
will be out of scope,
so there will be no external
references to them.
But they still reference
each other, causing a leak.
I should probably try
to find a solution
without a cyclical reference.
But as a quick fix for now,
I'll change menu item
to use a weak reference
for its meal plan object.
This breaks the retain cycle
because we no longer have two
cyclical strong references.
Let's shift gears now to heap
allocation regressions.
The heap is simply a section
of your process's address space
where dynamically allocated
objects are stored.
Heap allocation regressions
are an increase in memory
footprint due to the process
allocating more objects
on the heap than before.
To reduce heap regressions,
look to remove
unused allocations
and shrink unnecessarily
large allocations.
You should also pay attention
to how much memory
you hold at once.
Deallocate memory
you're no longer using
and wait to allocate memory
until you need it.
This will reduce your
app's peak footprint,
making it less likely
to be terminated.
So let's return now
to the failing XCTest
from the MealPlanner app
and check for a heap regression.
To understand
where I should look,
I'll run vmmap -summary
on both the pre
and post memgraphs
to get a nice overview
of where memory is being used.
My footprint
in the pre memgraph
is around 112 megabytes.
And in the post memgraph,
my footprint is 125 megabytes,
so that's about
a 13 megabyte difference.
Further down,
the output shows
my process's memory usage
broken down by region.
Because I suspect this is
a heap allocation issue,
I want to look at the regions
starting with MALLOC_
because those regions contain
all of my heap objects.
Remember Tanuja's equation:
Memory footprint = Dirty memory
+ Compressed Memory.
In this tool, the term
"swapped" means "compressed."
So of these columns,
I only care about
"dirty size" and "swapped size."
And sure enough,
the output shows
that the MALLOC_LARGE region
is holding about
13 megabytes of dirty memory.
That's roughly equivalent
to my regression size,
so I definitely want
to look into that.
The next step is to figure
out what kinds of objects
are contributing to this
13 megabyte regression.
To get that information,
I'll run heap -diffFrom
on my post memgraph.
I pass in my pre and post
memgraphs as arguments.
This shows me
the objects that exist
in the post memgraph heap
but not
in the pre memgraph heap.
Near the top,
the output shows I have around
13 megabytes of new objects
in the post memgraph.
Below, the heap memory is broken
down by object class.
For each object class,
the output shows
the number of objects
and the sum in bytes
of those objects.
Right away,
I notice that I have
about 13 megabytes worth of
this "non-object" type.
In Swift, this usually
indicates raw malloced bytes.
This type of object can be
a bit tricky to track down,
but there are some tools I
can use to get some information.
To start, I want the addresses
of these non-objects.
I'll run heap -addresses
to grab them.
I'll specify that I only
want non-objects
whose size
is at least 500 kilobytes.
Aha.
This non-object
is about 13 megabytes,
so it's a prime suspect
in this investigation.
I'll grab its address
and see if I can
find some clues
about what it is.
I have several options
at this point.
Each has its benefits
depending on the situation,
so I'll walk through
each one briefly.
One option I have is to run
leaks --traceTree
on this address.
This gives me a tree of objects
that reference this address.
This is useful if I have
a specific object
I want to get more information
about
and my memgraph doesn't
have malloc stack logging
or MSL enabled.
Remember
that our XCTest memgraphs
automatically
have MSL enabled,
but if you're ever working
with a memgraph that doesn't,
keep this tool in mind.
I've highlighted the object
in the tree that seems relevant.
My large non-object
probably has something to do
with this meal data object
in MKTCustomMeal
PlannerCollectionViewCell.
I can also run
leaks --referenceTree.
This gives me a top-down
reference tree
of all the memory
in my process
with a best guess
of which objects are the roots.
With this output,
I can get a sense
of where memory is
aggregated in my app.
This tool is extremely helpful
if I know
I have a large regression
but I don't know which specific
objects are responsible.
I can pass the --groupByType
argument
to group like types together,
shrinking the output
and making it a bit easier
to parse.
Oftentimes,
a large chunk of the regression
will be grouped under
a single node in this tree,
making it easier to find
clues about what that memory is.
Again, I've highlighted
the section
showing the relevant objects.
Here's that same
meal data object
I saw in the leaks
-traceTree output.
The output shows that
there's about 13 megabytes
worth of memory allocated
to this meal data object.
I'd love to know how this
object is being allocated.
Because my memgraph
has MSL enabled,
I can use malloc_history
-fullStacks to figure that out.
I pass in the address
of the large non-object
I grabbed from heap
-addresses earlier.
And I get
an allocation call stack
for the object at that address.
This is extremely useful
when I have MSL enabled
and I have the address
of the object I care about.
So looks like my meal data
object was allocated
in the saveMeal function,
shown here on line 3.
I'll head over to Xcode
to see what's going on.
Here's the saveMeal function
inside my custom
cell view controller.
And here's the culprit.
I'm allocating
this raw buffer here
and then wrapping it
with the meal data object.
I'm only allocating this buffer
so that I can populate it
and save the result to disk.
Once I'm done saving to disk,
I don't really need
this buffer anymore.
So why is it sticking around?
Well, meal data
is a class member,
so as long as this
class instance exists,
the reference will stick around.
This means that when I hit
saveMeal on any cell,
that cell allocates
and holds a large buffer
that will stick around until
that cell is destroyed.
That memory could really add
up if I'm saving multiple meals.
So how can I fix this?
One option would be
to just define mealData
in the saveMeal function,
but I know it's used
elsewhere in the class,
so I don't want to do that.
Another way would be
to set mealData to nil
once I'm done writing it
to disk.
The data object in Swift
is smart enough to automatically
deallocate the buffer once I've
lost my final reference to it,
so the buffer won't stick around
past the end of this function.
Lastly, let's talk about
fragmentation.
Let's quickly go over
how pages work in iOS.
A page is a fixed size,
indivisible chunk of memory
that the system
grants to your process.
Because pages are indivisible,
when your process writes
to any part of a page,
the entire page
is considered dirty,
and your process
will be charged for it,
even if most of it is unused.
Fragmentation occurs when
a process has dirty pages
that are not 100% utilized.
To understand how this happens,
let's look at an example.
To start,
I have 3 contiguous clean pages.
As the process runs,
allocations begin
filling up these pages,
dirtying them.
When objects are deallocated,
they create empty slots
where they used to be
marked "free memory"
in the diagram.
However,
these pages are still dirty
because there are still some
allocated objects on them.
The system will attempt
to fill these empty slots
with future allocations.
Here I have a large
incoming allocation
notated by the box on the right.
Unfortunately,
this incoming allocation
is too large to fit
in my free memory slots.
Even though the combined
size of the empty slots
is large enough,
they aren't contiguous
and they can't be used
for a single allocation.
So because it couldn't fit
in any existing free slots,
the system placed my allocation
on a new dirty page
on the right side
of the diagram.
The free memory slots
remain unfilled
and are considered
fragmented memory.
The best way to reduce
fragmentation
is to allocate objects
with similar lifetimes
close to each other in memory.
This helps ensure
that all of those objects
are freed together,
giving the process large chunks
of contiguous memory to work
with for future allocations.
In this example,
I manually allocated
all the objects marked
"my object,"
and I plan to free them
at the same time.
But I wasn't careful in my code,
and the system ended up
interleaving my objects
with other objects.
Now, when I free all my objects,
I have four slots
of free memory,
none of which are contiguous
because they're broken up
by these allocated objects.
This results
in 50% fragmentation
and four dirty pages.
Not great.
What if I instead wrote code
to allocate all
of my objects together?
Now they all end up
together on two pages.
And when I free my objects,
the process frees up two
clean pages for the system,
resulting in only 2 dirty pages
and 0% fragmentation.
Notice how fragmentation
is a footprint multiplier.
50% fragmentation
doubled my footprint
from 2 to 4 dirty pages.
In most real scenarios,
some fragmentation
is inevitable.
So as a rule of thumb,
aim for about
25% fragmentation or less.
One way to reduce fragmentation
is to use autorelease pools.
An autorelease pool
tells the system
to release all objects
allocated inside of it
as soon as it goes out of scope.
This helps ensure
that all objects created
in the autorelease pool
have similar lifetimes.
Although fragmentation can be
an issue for all processes,
long running processes
can be especially prone,
because there are lots
of allocations and deallocations
to potentially fragment
the address space.
If your app uses long running
extensions, for example,
be sure to take a look
at fragmentation
in those processes.
To take a quick look at
my process's fragmentation,
I can run vmmap -summary
and scroll down
to the bottom of the output.
This section is divided
into malloc zones.
Each zone contains different
types of allocations.
Usually I would only care
about the DefaultMallocZone,
because that's where my heap
allocations end up by default.
However, because this
memgraph has MSL enabled,
I actually care about
the MallocStackLoggingLiteZone.
As long as MSL is enabled,
this zone is where all the heap
allocations end up.
The % FRAG column shows me
what percentage of my memory
is wasted due to fragmentation
in each malloc zone.
Some of these numbers
are pretty large,
but I only need to focus on
the MallocStackLoggingLiteZone.
That's because
the MallocStackLoggingLiteZone
has by far the largest
share of dirty memory,
with 4.3 megabytes
out of 5 megabytes total.
So I can ignore the other zones
this time.
The "dirty+swap frag size"
column
shows me exactly how much
memory is wasted
due to fragmentation
in each malloc zone.
In my case, I'm wasting
about 800K due to fragmentation.
This seems like a lot,
but as I mentioned before,
some fragmentation
is inevitable.
So as long as I'm sitting
under 25% fragmentation,
I'll consider
this much waste acceptable.
Looks like I'm sitting
at about 19% fragmentation
in the
MallocStackLoggingLiteZone.
This is comfortably below
the 25% rule of thumb,
so I'm not concerned.
If I did have
fragmentation issues,
I could use the Allocations
track in the Instruments tool.
Specifically,
I'd want to look at
the allocations list view
and see which objects
were persisted and destroyed
in my area of interest.
In the context of fragmentation,
the destroyed objects
create free memory slots,
while the persisted objects
are the remaining objects,
responsible
for keeping the pages dirty.
Both of them
are worth investigating
when you're looking
into fragmentation.
For more information about how
to use the Instruments tool,
check out the Getting started
with Instruments talk
from WWDC 2019.
Now that I've addressed
the leaks and heap regressions
and verified that fragmentation
isn't an issue,
I'll run that XCTest again.
Excellent.
The XCTest now passes
and the regression is resolved.
Now that
you've learned about detecting
and diagnosing memory issues,
let's review the workflow
you can use for your own app.
Anytime you add a new feature,
write a performance
XCTest to monitor memory,
and/or any of the other
provided system metrics.
For each test, set a baseline.
Then use the test
to catch regressions
and investigate
using the collected ktrace
and memgraph files.
Use the memgraphs
from any failing XCTests
to help diagnose
your memory issue.
The first thing you should
do is check for leaks.
Run the leaks tool and use
the MSL backtraces
to help find
and fix any leaks.
If the regression
doesn't include leaks,
then check out the heap.
Start with vmmap -summary
to confirm that the memory
is in the heap.
If so, run heap -diffFrom
to see which object types
are responsible
for the growth.
If the culprits seem obvious,
use heap -addresses
to get their addresses.
If not, look at leaks
-referenceTree for some clues.
Finally, investigate culprit
object addresses
with leaks -traceTree
and/or malloc_history.
Lastly, make sure
you're developing with these
memory best practices in mind.
Strive to have
zero leaks in your app.
If you're working with
unsafe types,
make sure you remember
to free everything you allocate.
And be on the lookout for retain
cycles in your code as well.
Find ways to reduce
your heap allocations,
whether that's shrinking them,
holding them
for a shorter period of time,
or just getting rid of
unnecessary allocations
altogether.
Make sure to keep
fragmentation in mind.
Allocate objects with similar
lifetimes next to each other
to create nice, large chunks
of free memory later on.
With these best practices
and the XCTest workflow,
you'll be equipped to detect,
diagnose,
and fix memory issues
in your app.
On behalf of Tanuja and myself,
thanks so much for tuning in.
[percussive music]