[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Alejandro Segovia Azapian:
Welcome to WWDC!
My name is Ale Segovia Azapian,
and I'm a GPU software engineer
at Apple.
In this session,
we're going to explore
bindless rendering in Metal.
Bindless is a modern
resource binding model
that allows making
groups of resources
available to the GPU
to implement
modern rendering techniques.
First, we'll take a look
at the need
for the concept behind bindless.
Then, we will introduce
the bindless model
and show how it provides
the flexibility needed
to solve the challenges of
the traditional binding model.
We will recap the mechanisms
to encode
and make your scene resources
available to Metal
with argument buffers
and how to navigate your
GPU structures from shaders.
Let's get started!
So bindless rendering allows
making all our scene resources
available to our shaders,
bringing incredible flexibility
to our graphics techniques.
Let's take a look at an example.
Let's imagine we have
a ray tracing kernel
finding intersections against
an acceleration structure.
For some light effects,
such as ray-traced shadows,
the algorithm is very natural.
We want to find any objects
between the intersection point
and the light.
All we need to trace
the shadow ray is a position
and the direction
toward the light.
No object attributes
or Metal resources are needed
beyond the world-space position
of the intersection,
which we can derive from the ray
and the intersection's
parameter.
For other effects however,
such as reflections,
the situation
gets more complicated.
Let's take a look at
a ray tracing reflection shader
in Metal Shading Language.
In this new example,
we've just found
an intersection,
and we're trying
to paint the pixel
with the correct
reflected color.
If we just paint a solid color
after we find an intersection,
the reflection on the ground
will not look accurate.
To produce correct results,
we need to determine
the attributes of each
reflected point found
and calculate the correct
shading for its pixel.
This problem is also present
for other ray-traced effects
such as
diffuse global illumination
and even ambient occlusion
in some cases.
The challenge is that
when we ray trace,
our rays may hit any object
in the acceleration structure.
This means that
from our ray tracing shader,
we potentially need access
to any Metal resources
in our scene,
including vertex data --
associated with
the mesh intersected --
and its material.
It is just not possible
to bind this amount of resources
directly to our pipeline.
This is where the bindless
binding model comes in.
The idea behind bindless
is to aggregate our resources
and link them together.
This allows us to bind
a single buffer to the pipeline
and make all
referenced resources available
via navigation.
In Metal, the construct
that allows us to do this
is argument buffers.
In particular, for bindless,
argument buffers Tier 2
are required.
These are available on the
Apple6 and Mac2 GPU families.
Argument buffers can be used
from all shader types in Metal.
This means that you can use them
for both ray tracing
and rasterization.
As we saw,
for certain ray tracing effects,
using bindless is mandatory
in order to obtain
good visual results.
For rasterization,
the use is optional
but provides advantages
over the direct binding model.
In particular, it virtually
removes the slot limits
for the number of resources
that can be bound
for any given draw call,
and it also provides some
nice optimization opportunities
that we'll explore later
in this session.
We introduced argument buffers
with Metal 2 as a mechanism
to allow you to bind
constant data and resources
all at once in a single call
to the Metal API.
Argument buffers
are very flexible
and can even reference
other buffers.
The idea behind
the bindless model
is to leverage this capability
to link all of our
scene resources together.
This will allow making them
available to the GPU
at the same time.
Let's look at an example
of a way
to link our scene resources
with argument buffers.
Let's say we want to render
a model such as this fire truck.
The model is comprised
of textures,
vertex data, and index data.
These are the typical resources
you would bind one by one
for every draw call in
the traditional binding model.
In our case, however --
because we want to make
all textures, vertex data,
and indices of the scene
available at once --
we need to aggregate these.
Here's a potential way to do so.
We can first create
a meshes argument buffer
to contain all our meshes
or submeshes,
depending on how our assets
are organized.
This argument buffer
will allow referencing
the vertex and index arrays
in our scene.
Similarly, we can do the same
and encode our materials
to an argument buffer.
Each material
can reference its textures
as well as contain
inline constant data.
OK, but now that we have
all our meshes and materials
available to the GPU,
how can we bring them together?
Well, we can, for example,
create an instance object
and also place it
in an argument buffer.
An instance can reference
one mesh
and an associated material.
This is also a great place
to store
a model transformation matrix
as inline constant data.
But we don't have to stop there.
Now that we can store
one instance,
we can take this further
and encode all of our instances
as an array
into this argument buffer.
Let's simplify this diagram
and add a few more
truck instances,
each one with its own material.
As we can see, with this,
we can now have our full scene
and its resources
encoded and linked
with argument buffers.
Later, when we want to reference
any of these resources
from our shaders,
we just need a pointer
to the instances buffer.
We can pass it directly
and interpret this buffer
as an array,
or pass a pointer through
another scene argument buffer.
Now, it's important to note
what happens with the residency
of indirectly accessed
resources.
Since we're only passing
a pointer to the scene
into the pipeline,
Metal will know about
this buffer reference,
but not about resources
accessed indirectly.
The application is responsible
for declaring residency
of all indirectly accessed
resources.
Making a resource resident
means signaling to the driver
to make its memory available
to the GPU.
This is necessary so we can
reference them from our shaders.
We can do this by calling
the useResource:usage: API
for compute encoders and
useResource:usage:stages: API
for render command encoders.
Accessing a nonresident resource
is a common cause
of GPU restarts
and command buffer failures.
This is because its memory pages
may not be present
if we forgot to call this API.
So it's very important
to declare
every indirectly accessed
resource to Metal.
Now, another option,
for convenience,
is that resources allocated
from MTLHeaps
can now be made resident
with a single call
by means of the useHeap API.
This is a great option
if you are already suballocating
or planning to suballocate
resources from heaps.
Now, heaps are a fantastic part
of the Metal API,
and we recommend you use them
for the best resource-creation
performance,
and memory-saving opportunities.
There are, however,
a few considerations
to use them effectively.
The first thing to ask is,
Are all our suballocated
resources only read from?
Examples of where we might need
to write into a resource
include mesh skinning
from a compute shader
and dynamic textures,
amongst others.
In these cases, if the GPU needs
to write into any resources,
they need to be declared
resident individually
with the write usage flag.
Additionally, any resources
that may have been modified
that we now intend to read from
will still need their own
useResource call.
This is so that
the Metal framework
can handle resource transitions
for you, flushing GPU caches
and adjusting
the internal memory layout.
The second consideration is,
Does the heap track suballocate
resource dependencies?
Again, this is
especially important
if we're reading and writing
into resources
coming from the same heap.
Metal is great at avoiding
synchronization problems
through dependency tracking,
and since Metal 2.3,
heaps can be configured
to track hazards in the access
to their resources.
However, since heaps
are a single resource to Metal,
synchronization is handled
at the heap level
not the suballocation level.
This may subject
suballocated resources
to the problem of false sharing.
Let's take a look.
Let's imagine we have
two render passes --
A and B --
accessing resources
from the same heap.
Render pass A is rendering
to a render texture
allocated from a tracked heap.
Render pass B is reading
from an unrelated buffer
that is suballocated
from the same heap.
Depending
on different conditions,
render passes A and B
may qualify to be executed
in parallel by the GPU;
however,
due to the potential hazard
of writing and reading
from the same resource --
the heap --
Metal has to serialize access
to ensure there are
no race conditions.
This can potentially increase
the execution wall-clock time
of our workload by the GPU.
In our case, however,
if we know the individual
resources are independent,
this fence could be avoided.
There are two ways to do this.
One option is to suballocate
resources that are updatable
from heaps separate to the ones
used for our static resources.
The other option, if we desire
to bundle everything together,
is to make sure heaps
are configured
not to track
their suballocated resources.
This is the default behavior
in Metal,
and it means we as programmers
take on the responsibility
of synchronizing hazards
ourselves.
Now, in this diagram
I simplified things a bit
to illustrate the problem
of false sharing.
In practice, overlapping occurs
at the shading stage level,
not at the render pass level.
As a consequence,
Metal allows us
to specify our fences
at the stage granularity.
This is great because
it allows us to still run
parts of our pipeline --
such as vertex stage
and rasterizer --
concurrently,
and only block later
in the fragment stage
if it happens to depend on
a previous pass's
fragment stage output.
We recommend you always do this
for maximum performance,
if possible.
Now, this is a lot to remember,
so if you only get one thing
from this list,
please remember this:
read-only data,
such as static textures
and meshes,
are the easiest to handle.
Determine the total
allocation size
and alignment requirements
upfront
and place these resources
in a heap when the app starts
or during a loading section
in your game.
This way, you can later make it
resident in a single call,
with minimal overhead
in your critical path.
Now that we know about
the bindless binding model,
let's take a look at how we can
encode our resources
and put this in practice
and make our complete scene
available to the GPU
with argument buffers.
Let's say we want to encode
our instances buffer.
Remember, this buffer consists
of an array of instances.
As we saw, instances
reference a mesh, a material,
and contain an inline constant
4x4 matrix
describing the transformation
from local to world space.
Encoding is performed
via an argument buffer encoder,
and there are two distinct ways
to create one in Metal.
You may be familiar
with encoding via reflection.
If the argument buffer
is passed as a direct parameter
to the shader function,
we can ask
the MTLFunction object
to create an encoder for us.
This mechanism works great,
but when we are encoding
the entire scene
into argument buffers, not all
encoders can be reflected.
In particular,
the MTLFunction signature
does not know about the
indirectly referenced buffers.
There might also be
other situations
where creating an encoder
from a MTLFunction
is not convenient;
for example, if your engine
architecture
handles argument-buffer creation
and resource loading
separate from pipeline state
creation.
Additionally, we cannot reflect
an encoder
when the function is expecting
to be passed an array.
So what can we do
in these cases?
For these cases,
Metal provides a convenient
second mechanism
to create an encoder through
a MTLArgumentDescriptor.
MTLArgumentDescriptors allow
describing the struct members
to Metal and subsequently
creating an encoder
without a MTLFunction.
We must first create
a descriptor for each member,
specifying data type
and binding index.
Next, we take our descriptors,
and pass them directly
to the MTLDevice
to create our encoder.
As a result, we obtain
our encoder object back.
So let's explore
what this looks like in code.
For each member,
we needed to create
a MTLArgumentDescriptor;
we specify the binding index,
corresponding
to the ID attribute
for the member in the struct;
we specify the MTLDataType
and potentially access;
and finally, after we've
declared all the members,
we can create the encoder
directly from the device,
passing an array
with all our descriptors.
Once we have an encoder,
it's straightforward to record
our data into a buffer.
We set the argument buffer
on the encoder,
pointing at the beginning
of the buffer.
Then, we simply set the data
we want to store.
Encoding an array
is simple as well.
All we have to do
is offset the encoder's
argument buffer recording point
by the encodedLength,
which we can conveniently
retrieve from the encoder.
For the next instance,
we add the encodedLength
to our offset a second time.
In fact, the offset for each
position we need to record in
is going to be the index
times the encodedLength.
This mechanism
makes it very easy
to encode arrays of structs.
Now, one important point
worth mentioning
is that no special treatment
is needed from shader side
to index into these arrays.
The shader
does not need to know
the length of the buffer
and can freely index
into any location in the array.
It just works!
OK, now that we have encoded
our bindless scene,
let's take a look at navigation.
For the case of ray tracing,
navigation is very natural.
First, we bind the buffer
that contains the root
of our bindless scene
to our ray tracing pipeline.
This is the argument buffer
from where we can access
all the others.
Next, from our kernel,
we proceed with the ray-traced
intersection as usual.
After we discovered
an intersection,
the intersection result object
describes the navigation.
We can query this object
for instance_id,
geometry_id,
and primitive_id.
These members
are designed specifically
for navigating
our acceleration structures.
It is, therefore, important
to build our bindless scene
with a structure that mirrors
our acceleration structures,
such as the one shown earlier.
Let's take a look at it again.
Remember,
this is just an example
of how to organize the scene,
so I'm going to navigate it
according to how I organized it.
The particular details
for your scene may vary,
according to how you decide
to organize
your own argument buffers.
First, we need to find
an intersection.
Once we have it,
because we strategically
organized our bindless scene,
given the instance_id
we can now follow the pointer
to the instances buffer
and determine which one we hit.
Next, as we saw, the instance
knows its mesh and material.
So we can simply use
the geometry_id
to determine
which geometry we hit
within the referenced buffer.
Finally, if we prepared
each mesh
to know its index buffer,
we can use the primitive_id
to determine
the exact primitive that we hit.
In the case of a triangle,
for instance,
we can pull the three indices
from this array
and use them to retrieve
its vertex data.
Here's what this navigation
looks like
in Metal Shading Language.
From the intersection object,
we retrieve the instance_id
and use it to dynamically index
into our instances array
and retrieve
the instance we hit.
Next, having the instance,
we use the geometry_id
to determine which geometry
or submesh was hit.
Once we've determined
the geometry,
we can directly pull the indices
from the index buffer.
In the case of a triangle,
we pull three indices,
one after the other.
We use these indices to access
into the vertex data array
and retrieve any attribute
we need for our technique.
For example, we can retrieve
the normals
corresponding to each vertex.
And finally, using the point's
barycentric coordinates,
we manually interpolate
vertex normals
to arrive at the correct normal
at the intersection point.
With these changes in place,
taking it back
to our teapot example,
now that we have a way
to calculate the normal
at the intersection point,
we can correctly shade
our reflection.
We've updated the code
to find the correct attributes
at the intersection point,
and now the results
are visually correct.
We can now continue
building on this framework
to calculate any other attribute
we want,
such as texture coordinates
to apply a texture
or tangent vectors
to implement normal mapping.
So here we saw how to navigate
our bindless scene
to retrieve vertex data,
manually interpolate it,
and finally, apply it
to correctly shade
all the intersection points
discovered.
To help you bring these concepts
into your own engine,
we're going to be releasing
a companion code sample
that shows a concrete
implementation of all of this.
This is a hybrid rendering
sample
that calculates ray-traced
reflections for a scene
loaded using
the Model I/O framework.
The sample shows how you can
encode a bindless scene
that matches the ray tracing
acceleration structures,
and it also shows
how to find intersections
and correctly shade
their associated pixels
directly from
your ray tracing shaders.
As we can see here,
the sample also allows
directly visualizing
the output of the reflection
ray tracing shader
just at the points where
the rays intersect the trucks.
This is great
for iteratively experimenting
with the reflection algorithm.
Now, we've covered
a lot of ground here,
and so far we've been centering
most of our discussion
in the context of ray tracing.
But as I mentioned earlier,
we can apply the same principles
to properly shade our pixels
in the context of rasterization.
Physically based rendering
is a great candidate for this.
In PBR, our fragment shader
needs information
coming from several textures;
for example, albedo, roughness,
metallic, and ambient occlusion.
In the direct binding model,
we need to bind each slot
individually
before issuing
each one of our draw calls.
The bindless model
vastly simplifies this.
Once we have encoded
our argument buffers,
we can directly bind the scene,
navigate to the material
corresponding to our draw call,
and access all textures
indirectly.
In fact, since we now just need
to bind a single buffer once,
this architecture provides
an excellent opportunity
to optimize our engines further
by reducing the number
of draw calls
and use instanced rendering
instead.
Just remember to make resident
all textures we plan to access.
Here's an example
of a typical PBR shader.
In the traditional model,
each referenced texture
needs to be individually bound
before this draw call.
If the following draw call
requires a different set
of textures,
all these resources need
to be bound one by one as well.
When using a bindless model,
we can now just pass
our root argument buffer
and retrieve our material
directly from its referenced
structures, just like before.
First we retrieve
the instance --
this may be determined
in the vertex shading stage --
then retrieve its material,
and use its referenced textures
and constant data
to calculate
the appropriate shading.
Finally, we just return
the color.
All right!
And that was a tour on how
to effectively implement
bindless rendering in Metal!
To recap, we explored
the Metal bindless model
and saw how extremely flexible
it is,
allowing you to represent
your scene any way you desire.
My recommendation is to design
and build structures
that ease the navigation
for your given renderer.
This way, navigation becomes
very natural,
and you can even use
the same buffers
for both ray tracing
and rasterization.
Bindless completely changes
the game,
giving your GPU
all the data you need
to implement
modern rendering techniques.
You can even take it further
and use this architecture
to put the GPU
in the driver seat
and adopt indirect pipelines
through indirect command buffers
and GPU culling.
We can't wait to see
how you put this in practice
to deliver the next generation
of graphical applications
and games.
Thank you and enjoy
the rest of WWDC 2021!
♪