[music]
[Ken] Hi, I'm Ken Greenebaum,
on the Display and Color
Technologies team.
Thank you for attending this
"High Dynamic Range,
rendering with EDR" talk.
It is a technology I am
thrilled to be sharing with you.
Let's quickly run down
what we'll be covering
and who might best
benefit from attending.
We will start with what
EDR actually is,
describe the four steps
used to add
EDR to your existing app,
discuss the native EDR API
for more control of rendering,
and finally, we will explore
a series of best practices
related to EDR.
Now, what is EDR?
EDR is an acronym
you might not be familiar with.
It stands for
"Extended Dynamic Range."
We use "EDR"
to refer to both
the HDR representation
and the HDR rendering technology
used on our platforms.
It is somewhat akin
to color management,
which you might
already be familiar with.
Developers of many types of apps
will find this talk interesting.
To begin,
any developer interested
in computer graphics technology,
High Dynamic Range displays,
and especially
the new XDR displays
that Apple has been releasing
over the last couple of years.
Next are hardcore
game developers
who want to create
the most realistic
and exciting experience,
unlocking bright details
that might already be present
in their rendering engine.
Critically,
there are the Pro app developers
who are interested in achieving
studio reference response
for HDR video and still images.
Finally, there are
developers of apps
whose emphasis
isn't specific to graphics,
but who would like to embrace
the HDR still image
and video content
now entering the ecosystem.
HDR is here,
and it is enabled
by our EDR technology.
As we will be discussing,
we have displays
with incredible capabilities
already in users' hands.
Stunning HDR content
in the ecosystem
that users are capturing,
streaming, and downloading,
as well as HDR apps,
both games and professional,
available in the App Store.
EDR is an adaptive technology.
As we will discuss,
EDR not only maps HDR content
to displays of wildly
differing capabilities,
but also supports
an even wider range
of viewing conditions.
Have you ever noticed
displays look much different
in a bright environment
versus when viewed in the dark?
The bright, vibrant colors
you experience indoors
likely look dim and muted
with low dynamic range
when viewed outdoors.
The display didn't change.
At a given brightness setting,
it is always making
the same light.
is the environment that changed,
as well as your vision
that rapidly adapted
to the environment.
In a dark environment,
your vision adapts
to the displayed content,
the predominant source of light.
But in a bright environment,
the user's vision largely adapts
to the environment,
over the much dimmer display,
causing the content to look
dim and washed out,
crushing blacks
and shadow detail.
This is why EDR
and the underlying
ambient adaptation technologies
dynamically adapt
display parameters,
such as white point,
black point,
reference white brightness,
and dynamic range,
that we describe
as "EDR headroom,"
to map the display
to the user's adapted vision.
EDR's adaptation provides
a number of benefits.
Perhaps most surprisingly,
this results in EDR creating
a true HDR response,
even on conventional,
standard dynamic range displays.
That is,
when those displays are viewed
in dimmer environments
with correspondingly
dimmer brightness settings.
Similarly, EDR's dynamics
produce a situation-optimized
HDR capability
on bright HDR displays.
This allows HDR content
to look stunning
in HDR reference
dim environments,
while providing a reduced
but optimal dynamic range
in brighter environments,
all while
preserving shadow detail,
such as the patches
on this illustration.
EDR rendering is supported
on most devices
we've shipped for years now.
We described HDR capability
in terms of EDR headroom,
which is how many times brighter
than the conventional
maximum SDR white
the brightest EDR pixels
can be rendered to the display.
EDR headroom varies
based on display capability,
as well as other parameters,
including the current
brightness slider setting.
On conventional
backlit displays,
as found on most
recent Macs and iPads,
up to a very noticeable 2x SDR,
is available.
iPhones with XDR display
provide up to an exciting 8x
SDR EDR headroom.
The new iPad Pro's
Liquid Retina XDR display
has up to an incredible 16x SDR.
Roughly 5x SDR is provided
when driving typical external
HDR 10 displays
via Mac, iPad, and AppleTV.
And the Pro Display XDR
renders to a jaw-dropping
400x SDR
in the default XDR preset,
when brightness is set
to the minimum 4-nit value.
Not only
are HDR-capable displays
already in many users' hands,
but HDR content
is becoming mainstream.
In addition
to commercial HDR content,
users are adding HDR
still and video content,
captured on their own iPhones
and other devices,
to the ecosystem.
An awe-inspiring
list of applications
have already adopted EDR.
Top-tier games
supporting EDR include
"Baldur's Gate 3,"
"Divinity: Original Sin 2,"
and "Shadow of the Tomb Raider."
A growing number
of AppleTV services
provide HDR content,
including TV app,
Netflix, and YouTube.
Finally, an exciting
and growing list of Pro apps
have adopted EDR,
both upping the ante
and increasing
the amount of HDR content
developed on the platform.
Affinity Photo,
DaVinci Resolve,
Cinema 4D,
Final Cut Pro,
Nuke,
and Pixelmator Pro
are just some of the apps.
We chose to name
our technology "EDR"
in part to differentiate
it from "HDR,"
which tends to mean
different things
to different people.
When many think
of High Dynamic Range,
they imagine bright displays
capable of producing
deep blacks.
The production-minded may think
content formats,
perhaps HDR10 or Dolby Vision.
To the technical,
it brings transfer functions,
like PQ or HLG, to mind.
And perhaps to the artistic,
HDR can even suggest
the surrealistic,
painterly tone map
representing bright highlights,
as well as dim shadow detail
as SDR.
Consider this SDR tone map
of an RIT produced,
ultra-High Dynamic Range
OpenEXR image.
In the tone map,
the glowing light bulb
and the shadow detail
are all present.
However,
the dramatic dynamic range
of the original
HDR image is lost.
EDR is not a painterly
HDR-to-SDR conversion,
preserving all details
while losing the intention,
but rather, a true
High Dynamic Range rendering.
The RIT team combined
the 18 bracketed
Digital SLR exposures,
seen here,
to create their HDR image
with its amazing
500,000:1 dynamic range.
EDR fully represents this
in floating point,
with the image's subject,
the Luxo lamp itself,
as pixel values
under reference white's 1.0,
and with brighter details,
such as the emissive orb
of the lightbulb,
represented as values
approaching 500.
That's 500x brighter
than the lamp base.
EDR's implementation
creates a mapping
between the reference whites
of every element of the system.
From the reference white
of the content
to that of the display,
through to that
of the user's adapted vision.
This mapping is fundamental
to providing
many of the benefits of EDR,
including allowing
HDR and SDR content
to co-exist side-by-side,
optimally exposing
an HDR display's dynamic range
across environments,
even allowing
conventional SDR displays
to render true HDR,
while always allowing
EDR to render
as great a dynamic range
as possible.
For instance,
on a Pro Display XDR,
with brightness slider
set to the maximum 500 nits,
EDR values up to 3.2
will be rendered
without clipping.
Brighter elements,
such as the lamp head,
with correspondingly
greater EDR values,
will clamp to the display's
1,600-nit peak.
Lowering the display's
brightness setting
toward its 4-nit minimum,
occurring when in
a dim to dark environment,
either automatically
via auto brightness,
or manually
using the brightness slider,
EDR values up to 400
become renderable,
thereby delivering
most of the dynamic range
of this exceptional image.
The image's brightest elements,
while still rendered
to the display's
1,600-nit peak brightness,
now clearly define
the lightbulb's contour.
Similarly,
other details are revealed,
such as the colors
of the brightly illuminated
color checker.
With the user's vision
now adapting to the image's
4-nit reference white,
the image's brightest elements
are now amazingly rendered
400x brighter
than the lamp base.
Let's explore
the implications of EDR's
floating point
HDR representation
and rendering pipeline.
Being floating point,
EDR can represent every color
that humans can perceive,
as represented
by this completely filled
chromaticity diagram.
Similarly,
EDR can represent brightness
that would be damaging
to eyesight if fully rendered.
As such, EDR's representation
is future-proof.
As mentioned,
EDR is not only
a representation,
but is also
an HDR rendering pipeline.
EDR is an extension
to the color management
technologies
that Apple pioneered,
and has been shipping
for a very long time.
For instance, GPU accelerated
color managed video
first shipped way back
in MacOS 10.4 Tiger.
Conceptually similar
to allowing media
of normal and wide color gamut
to be displayed side by side,
EDR allows HDR and SDR assets
to share the screen
in a harmonious manner,
as well as to be
appropriately rendered
to displays
of differing capabilities.
Among other things,
this means that developers
may continue to use
existing SDR assets,
and selectively add
EDR support as needed.
Let's explore visually
EDR's representation
of HDR pixel values.
EDR is a floating
point representation.
EDR 0.0 represents black,
1.0 represents SDR max,
also known as "reference white"
or "UI white,"
thus EDR 0.0 to 1.0
represent the SDR range,
the same as always.
These values represent
the subject of an image,
and will never be clipped
when rendered.
EDR values beyond 1.0
represent values
exceeding SDR brightness,
such as highlights
and emissive surfaces.
These values might get
extraordinarily bright,
and while representable,
are subject to clipping
when rendered.
EDR is used
to drive the display,
no matter if the display
has a conventional
pure power response
or a newer
HDR transfer function.
Let's consider Pro Display XDR
in the default XDR preset,
which is PQ-based.
EDR 0.0 drives the display
to zero nits,
via the zero nit PQ code.
EDR 1.0,
called "reference white,"
is scaled
by the display brightness slider
or auto brightness,
the same as always.
The XDR preset has the typical,
about 4 to 500 nits reference
white brightness range.
Let's consider the maximum 500
nits setting for this example.
Regardless
of the brightness setting,
the peak white is always
1,600 nits in this preset.
Thus, EDRmax,
the brightest, renderable
EDR value, is 3.2,
as can be calculated by dividing
the 1,600-nit peak white
by the 500-nit reference white.
Correspondingly, we say
there is 3.2x SDR headroom,
as the brightest value
renderable to the display
is 3.2x brighter
than the reference white.
In summary, on Pro Display XDR,
using the default XDR preset,
with display brightness,
also known as "reference white,"
at 500 nits,
EDR values 0.0 to 3.2
are rendered to the display
as 0.0 to 1,600 nits,
with EDR 1.0
displayed as 500 nits.
Finally, EDR values
above EDRmax's 3.2
are clipped to peak white,
1,600 nits.
Amazingly,
as display brightness is reduced
toward the minimum 4 nits,
EDR values up to 400
become renderable,
thus exposing
incredibly bright details
at their true dynamic range.
Now that we have an overview
of how EDR works,
we'll explore adding EDR
to your application.
There are four steps to add EDR
support to most applications.
These steps
are all straightforward,
however,
their effects can be subtle
and you likely won't
reliably have EDR results
until you apply all of them.
First, you have to request EDR
by adding an attribute
to the appropriate context,
layer, or object.
Second, you have to associate
an extended-range colorspace
with your buffer, layer, or app.
Color Management will clip
EDR values beyond 1.0,
if an extended-range
colorspace is not specified.
You should know
that color management
might only engage
when the source and destination
colorspaces don't match,
so this clip
might be intermittent
or content dependent.
Third, you need to select
a pixel buffer format
that can represent
values above 1.0.
This is usually
some form of floating point.
Finally, your application
must generate pixels
that exceed the SDR 0.0 to 1
range,
and thus have sparkly
elements to show off.
Many developers
have existing apps
to which they might
want to add EDR support.
Perhaps the easiest way
to get started with EDR
is to simply substitute
HDR video or still image content
in place of existing
SDR content.
Then follow the four steps
we just outlined.
Some applications, for instance,
the email app shown,
might selectively enable EDR
only when HDR content
is encountered.
AVFoundation's
AVPlayer interface
supports a growing number
of HDR video formats
such as Dolby Vision,
HDR 10, and HLG.
AVPlayer will automatically
render these formats as EDR
when possible
on all platforms,
except for watchOS.
Existing
AVPlayer-based applications
don't require
any changes to render
supported HDR video formats
via EDR.
Let's look at an EDR enabled
AVPlayer code example.
As always, one simply first
creates an AVPlayer instance,
using AVPlayer's playerWithURL.
However, in our example,
we specify HDR video content.
Next, add the player to a layer,
using playerLayerWithPlayer.
Finally, point the controller
to the player
and request the player
to begin playing.
AVFoundation
will automatically perform
what is required
to render the HDR media as EDR,
and will enable and disable EDR
based on the content type.
HDR video playback
is pretty straightforward.
Next, let's consider
HDR still image rendering.
ImageIO has extensive support
for HDR image formats,
and conveniently, will return
the decoded pixels as EDR
in floating point buffers.
While ImageIO is available
on all platforms,
presently, the decoded results
may only be rendered as EDR
on macOS.
We will demonstrate
how to incorporate
ImageIO-based assets into an
application
in the upcoming
CAMetalLayer example.
Now, let's explore
the native EDR API.
As I mentioned,
the native EDR API
was created for applications
like Games and Pro apps,
where the developer may
want to render custom content
and have more control over
how HDR media is rendered.
Presently, this API is available
on macOS via CAMetalLayer,
and NSOpenGLView.
Let's look at an example
using CAMetalLayer,
the preferred
native EDR framework.
To begin, we are going
to look at the first
three of the four-step process,
opting in to EDR,
setting an extended-range
colorspace,
and selecting
an FP16 pixel buffer format.
First, opt-in to EDR
by setting the metalLayer's
"wantsExtended
DynamicRangeContent" attribute
to "yes."
Second,
set the metalLayer's colorspace
to an extended-range colorspace,
such as ExtendedLinearDisplayP3.
Third, set the metalLayer's
pixel format
to a floating point format,
such as RGBA16Float.
Next, we will examine
the fourth EDR opt-in step,
actually generating EDR pixels.
In this case,
we will use ImageIO
to import HDR
still image content,
and render the result
as an EDR texture.
It is a little involved,
so we will walk though it
step by step.
We create the CGImage
from HDR content,
draw the decoded image
into a floating point bitmap,
create a floating point texture,
load the EDR bitmap to texture,
and finally, render the texture
to the EDR enabled
metal pipeline.
First, the CGImage is created
from the source specified
in HDRimageURL,
using CGImageSourceCreateWithURL
and
CGImageSourceCreateImageAtIndex.
Next, create the CGContext
with CGBitmapContextCreate,
using the same colorspace
we set earlier
on the metalLayer,
and draw the EDR image
into the floating point context
using CGContextDrawImage.
Now, we create
a floating point texture
of type RGBA16Float,
using newTextureWithDescriptor.
Load the EDR image data,
using CGBitmapContextGetData
into the EDR texture,
using replaceRegion.
Finally, the developer
is ready to render
the EDR texture
into their EDR enabled
metal pipeline
and enjoy the dynamic results.
For those still supporting
OpenGL-based applications,
we will explore enabling EDR
on NSOpenGLView
using similar steps to those
we have already demonstrated.
Adoption of EDR might also
provide the opportunity
to fully embrace
color management.
However, we will not cover that
in this talk.
We will explore
the following steps:
Opting-in to EDR,
selecting a floating point
pixel buffer format,
and drawing EDR and content
to the NSOpenGLView.
Setting an extended-range
colorspace is not required,
as NSOpenGLView is not
automatically color managed.
First, opt-in to EDR
by setting the NSOpenGLView's
"wantsExtendedDynamicRange
OpenGLSurface" attribute
to "yes."
Second,
set the pixel buffer format
to NSOpenGLPFAColorFloat
with ColorSize, 64.
Finally, draw EDR values
into the OpenGLView,
run your modified application,
and enjoy the results.
Now that we've discussed
enabling basic EDR support
in existing applications,
let's dive a little deeper
and explore
a number of best practices
to get the most from
your EDR enabled application.
Recall EDR opt-in step four
is to set an extended-range
colorspace.
And in our example so far,
we explicitly set an appropriate
extended-range colorspace.
However, many apps don't set
their color space explicitly,
and instead use the default
colorspace
provided by the framework.
This often
corresponds to the display
or composition space,
which are not extended range,
thus breaking EDR
unless something is done.
Let's explore an example
of how to promote
existing colorspace
to extended range.
First,
get the existing colorspace,
in this case,
from your view's window.
Second, promote that colorspace
to extended-range
using
CGcolorspaceCreateExtended.
Finally,
assign the newly generated
extended-range colorspace
to the window, buffer, or layer,
as appropriate,
enabling apps that don't
explicitly set their colorspace
to use EDR.
Next,
we will explore best practices
for generating EDR content.
So far, we've mentioned
EDR content
has values that exceed 1.0,
but not how to actually
synthesize this content,
or convert it from HDR sources.
Please be careful
generating EDR content,
for it is possible to experience
the dreaded
"glowing bunny syndrome,"
where content may have an eerie,
iridescent glow
that makes properly authored
content look dim in comparison.
As has been emphasized,
pixels above EDR 1.0,
should only encode
specular highlights
and emissive surfaces.
This means
that is it inappropriate
to take SDR content and stretch
it to be HDR.
SDR content is compatible
with EDR as-is
in its native 0.0 to 1.0 range.
This aligns
the SDR reference white
to that of HDR contents.
When HDR content is authored
to be too bright,
with what should be
dimmer elements or even shadows
exceeding EDR 1.0,
it will appear unnatural
compared
to well-authored content.
The user's vision
may begin to adapt
to this overly bright content,
making other content appear
dim in comparison.
Please consider this example,
of a girl holding
an 18% gray card,
as used by photographers
and animators to set exposure.
The girl is the subject
of the photograph,
and consequently,
the photographer or animator
will set the exposure
so that she is at or below
reference white,
and thus will not be clipped.
Most user interface elements
shouldn't exceed EDR 1.0
as well.
However,
there may be exceptions,
including EDR color pickers,
or temporarily scaled UI,
brightly illuminated
to capture attention.
Emissive surfaces,
such as the sun or clouds,
as well as specular highlights,
such as the sun reflecting
off a shiny surface,
are potentially far brighter
than reference white,
and consequently,
are expected to exceed EDR 1.0.
A scene's brightest elements
are already clipped
by SDR encoding.
Consequently, SDR content
is correctly represented
as EDR 0.0 to 1.0.
Sometimes a workflow
will require HDR formats
to be converted
to EDR explicitly.
As mentioned, ImageIO decodes
HDR content to EDR,
requiring no further conversion.
For instance,
HLG is decoded
to the 0.0 to 12.0 EDR range,
with EDR 1.0
representing reference white.
ImageIO decodes
other HDR still image formats
to their own particular ranges,
with EDR 1.0
always corresponding
to the source's reference white.
AVFoundation does not presently
decode HDR formats,
such as HDR10, to EDR.
Consequently,
these need to be adapted
for use with EDR rendering.
This conversion
is straightforward
and involves two steps.
First,
converting to linear light
by applying
the inverse transfer function.
And second, dividing by
the medium's reference white.
For example,
100 nits for PQ content,
so that reference white
will be mapped to EDR 1.0,
and the maximum PQ
10,000 nit value
will map to EDR 100.
Consider this photograph
that, like many photos,
both digital and film,
has the sky clipped to white.
While EDR will never clip values
up to EDR 1.0, reference white,
which represent
the subject of the image,
EDR will clip values
above reference white
that are beyond
the current EDRmax,
and thus are not able
to be rendered
on the current system display
and display settings.
These values
above reference white
are highlights
or emissive surfaces,
such as the clouds,
sky, and sun,
that we can't see in this image,
and, as such, are usually
okay to be clipped.
However,
clipping of bright details
is not always acceptable.
For instance,
consider this image
of a sun-lit airplane
flying high above the clouds.
Notice the blue "HDR11" livery?
Brightly illuminated, the
number,
as well as the fuselage
it's painted onto,
might both be rendered
at greater than reference white,
and hence,
potentially be clipped
depending on
the display capabilities
and the current EDRmax.
If this number was a crucial
plot element in a film or game,
then dynamic tone mapping
may be employed
to avoid or manage clipping,
and keep the number visible.
Let's explore
how sophisticated applications
may stay abreast
of the current EDRmax value,
and accordingly,
adapt what they render.
Applications
may want to subscribe
to NSScreen notifications,
perhaps to adjust the brightness
of objects in the scene,
change the scene's exposure,
apply a bloom effect,
or even soft-clip to ensure
critical details are not lost.
Presently, there is only one
dynamic EDR value
accessible
from the NSScreen interface.
It is maximumExtendedDynamic
RangeColorComponentValue,
and represents
the current maximum
renderable linear EDR value.
As we have stated,
EDR values greater than EDRmax
will clip to EDRmax.
And EDRmax
may dynamically change,
since it is dependent
on characteristics,
such as display brightness
or True Tone,
that may themselves
change over time.
The two other EDR values
accessible from NSScreen are
static,
meaning they won't
change over time.
In contrast
to the preceding value,
maximumPotentialExtendedDynamic
RangeColorComponentValue
returns just that,
the maximum EDR
linear pixel value
that might be renderable
without clipping
on this display.
That is,
if the display brightness
and other features
were set appropriately.
Max potential EDR may be used to
guide decisions,
such as if SDR or HDR versions
of content should be used,
or even deciding
if it is worthwhile
to enable EDR at all.
Please remember
that potential is in the name.
The current maximum
renderable value,
EDRmax,
might be below this value.
1.0 is returned for displays,
or display presets,
not supporting EDR.
The final static value,
maximumReferenceExtendedDynamic
RangeColorComponentValue,
is mainly of interest
to Pro application developers
concerned about achieving
the highest fidelity
to a reference standard.
It provides
the maximum EDR value
that is guaranteed to be
rendered without distortion,
such as clipping
or tone mapping,
on a given display.
0.0 is returned on displays
that do not support
reference rendering.
Now, let's explore example code
that reads EDR values
via NSScreen.
Here, we read
the two static EDR values,
maxPotential and maxReference.
EDR values may be
different across displays,
so be sure to make the call
on the screen
your app is actually on.
In this example,
we are using the NSScreen
associated with your window.
The application may keep abreast
of dynamic EDR changes
by subscribing to
"NSWindowDidChangeScreen"
notification,
then query
the current EDR parameters
upon receiving
the screen changed event,
and potentially
altering what is rendered
based on knowledge
of the current EDR headroom.
To complete our discussion
of tone mapping,
we will briefly explore
the CAMetalLayer tone mapper.
This is of interest for Pro apps
that author and render
HDR video,
such as HLG and HDR10,
to project-based HDR
mastering parameters.
System apps, as well as apps
employing AVPlayer,
as we've already described,
use the CAMetalLayer tone mapper
to provide media-specific,
optical-to-optical
transfer function,
and soft clip for HDR values
that would otherwise
not be renderable.
The CAMetalLayer tone mapper
is enabled via
the "CAEDRMetadata" attribute
and is available on macOS.
This example demonstrates
how to enable
the system tone mapper
by setting
the "EDRMetadata" attribute
on your app's CAMetalLayer.
A number of EDRMetadata
constructors are available.
They are specific
to the HDR video standard,
as well as the mastering
information provided.
Here we see
the HLGMetadata constructor,
which takes no parameters.
Next, we demonstrate
one of the HDR10 constructors.
This one takes three parameters:
Explicit minimum
and maximumLuminance,
both in nits,
as well as opticalOutputScale,
which is often set
to HDR10's
100-nit reference white.
Once constructed,
set the resulting object on your
application's CAMetalLayer,
to be processed
by the system tone mapper
based on the provided metadata.
Closely related
to adaptive tone mapping,
an app may want to draw
with the brightest white
currently renderable.
We already understand
how to get the current EDRmax
from NSScreen,
however, EDR headroom
is a linear value
and pixels are most often
nonlinearly encoded.
In this final example,
we will convert EDRmax
into the app's potentially
nonlinear colorspace.
First, we use
CGColorSpaceCreateWithName
to create the linear EDRmax
white pixel we want to render.
And then convert
the linear EDRmax pixel
to the application's colorspace,
using
CGColorCreateCopy
ByMatchingToColorSpace.
The resulting color
may then be used
in any EDR enabled application.
This leaves us
with one last topic to discuss,
the power and performance
implications of EDR.
Similar to all CG rendering,
evaluating EDR's impact
on power and performance
can be complicated,
and often depends on the
specific hardware architecture
and display technology
used on a given device.
While we won't go into details
in this talk,
there are some general points
to consider, such as,
producing brighter pixels
often consumes more power,
floating point buffers
used with EDR may be larger,
and thus consume more bandwidth
than the fixed point buffers
that might otherwise be used.
This, in turn, correlates
to more power consumed.
Even enabling
CAEDRMetadata-based tone mapping
involves
an extra processing pass.
This, in turn, increases
latency and bandwidth.
Simply, EDR, like many features,
isn't free and, as such,
it should be used judiciously.
The best practice
is to enable EDR
when there is both HDR content
and potential EDR headroom
available.
Disable EDR
when this is not the case.
Similarly, choose HDR
or SDR versions of content
to open or stream based on
if the EDR potential headroom,
or even the current
EDRmax headroom,
is significantly
greater than 1.0.
Or, more simply,
only enable EDR
when the user
will see the difference.
We've covered a lot about EDR
in a short period of time.
I hope you are as excited
by EDR as I am,
and are eager to integrate it
into your applications.
To summarize,
EDR is used on macOS,
iOS, iPadOS, and tvOS devices.
EDR is an extension
to the color management
and SDR representations
you are already using.
EDR is easy for applications
to opt-in to.
EDR is compatible
with industry HDR standards,
and provides
a non-modal adaptive experience
across devices and environments.
Please check out the following
talks and resources
for more information
on HDR video playback,
Apple Pro Display XDR,
and metal rendering of EDR.
Thank you!
Hope you enjoy the rest
of your WWDC.
[music]