[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Amanda] Hi there.
I’m Amanda,
and I’ll be joined in a bit
by my colleague, Olivier.
In this talk,
we’ll explore the features
that we’ve added to RealityKit
in 2021.
RealityKit is an augmented
reality authoring framework
introduced in 2019
focused on realistic rendering
and making it easy
to create AR apps.
Leveraging ARKit to read
the device’s sensor data,
RealityKit allows you
to place 3D content
in the real-world environment
and make that content look
as realistic as possible.
Here are some great
examples of RealityKit
experiences in action.
Go on a scavenger hunt
in the real world,
bowl virtually against
your friends, even become
a sculpture in a museum,
and find some colorful bugs.
Over the past couple of years,
we’ve seen some amazing apps
created with RealityKit
and received
really good feedback
to make this framework
even better.
And we’ve listened
to your feedback.
We are happy to share
that RealityKit 2 introduces
a bunch of new features
to help you make
even more immersive
AR apps and games.
In this session, we’ll be
highlighting some of them,
including our
most-requested features,
like custom shaders
and materials,
custom systems,
and our new character
controller concept.
So put on your snorkel mask
and let’s dive in.
When I was growing up
in the Middle East,
I learned to scuba dive
in the Gulf.
Although I didn’t get to wear
one of these super cute
steampunk helmets,
I loved seeing
all the colorful fish schooling.
I thought it might
be fun to re-create
that underwater vibe
right here in my living room.
Olivier and I wrote this demo
using a bunch of the features
that we’ll be showing you
in this session
and in our second RealityKit
session later this week.
We’ve got post processing
to create the depth fog effect
and the water caustics,
a custom geometry modifier
to make the seaweed dance
in the waves, and a bunch more.
Basically,
RealityKit 2 lets you customize
so many things now.
This sample code is
available for you to try out
at developer.apple.com.
There are five main topics
we’ll cover today.
We’ll do a recap of what an ECS
is and how we used
our new custom systems
feature to implement
the fishes’ flocking
behavior in our app.
We’ll show you advancements
in what you can do
with materials
as well as animations,
the new character controller,
which is how we got the diver
to interact so seamlessly
with the AR mesh
of the living room,
and how you can now generate
resources at runtime.
So let’s start with the ECS.
ECS, short for entity
component system,
is a way of structuring
data and behavior,
and it’s commonly used
in games and simulations.
It’s different from
object-oriented programming
in which you tend to model
an item
as an encapsulated bundle
of both
its functionality and the state
associated with that item.
But with ECS,
you have three prongs:
entity, component, and system,
where the functionality goes
in the system, the state
goes in the components,
and the entity is an identifier
for a group of components.
This year,
with RealityKit 2, we’re moving
towards a more pure
ECS implementation,
guiding you to keep more
of your functionality
in the system layer
with our new custom systems.
What does entity mean to us?
An entity represents
one thing in your scene.
Here are entities that represent
the sea creatures in our scene.
An entity can have
child entities,
giving you a graph structure
to work with.
For example,
the transform component uses
the parent entity’s transform
to add its own position onto.
An entity itself doesn’t
render anything on screen.
For that, you need to give it
a model component
or create a model entity,
which’ll do that for you.
To add attributes,
properties, and behaviors,
you add components
to your entity.
Speaking of which,
let’s talk about components.
Components are for storing
state between frames
and for marking an entity’s
participation in a system.
You don’t need to include
any logic for dealing
with that state here, though.
Your logic and behavior go
in your custom system.
There are some components
that will be already present
on any entity you create.
Not shown here are the built-in
components: the transform
and synchronization components.
They’re on all three
of these entities.
There are others that you’ll
often want to add,
like the model component,
which contains the mesh
and materials that make
your entity show up on screen.
You can add
and remove components
from your entities
at runtime too,
if you want to dynamically
change their behavior.
We’ll mark this first
fish as participating
in the Flocking System,
and we’ll tell it
that it likes to eat algae.
This second fish,
it’s also going to flock
with the first fish,
but it prefers
to eat plankton right now.
This third guy is a plankton.
It will be food
for the second fish.
It should watch its back,
because in our app,
we’ve got some hungry creatures.
We know which ones are hungry
because they have the AlgaeEater
or the PlanktonEater
components on them.
Every frame, our Eating System
has its update function called.
In here,
it finds all the entities
in the scene that have
either of these components,
plus all the entities
that are food, so it can
guide the hungry fish toward
the food they prefer to eat.
But what’s a performant way
for the Eating System
to figure out
which entities are hungry,
which ones are the food,
and which ones are neither?
We don’t want to have
to traverse our entity graph
and check each one’s components.
Instead,
we perform an entity query.
Let RealityKit do
the bookkeeping for you.
The Flocking System wants
to find
all entities that have
a FlockingComponent on them.
While the Eating System wants
both kinds of hungry entities,
plus the entity that’s a type
of food.
So let’s take a closer look
at what exactly
is happening when a system
uses an entity query.
Systems have their update
functions called every frame.
Let’s look
at the Flocking System
for our Yellow Tang fish.
We’ll pause at this frame
to see what’s going on.
In the Flocking System’s
update function,
we query for all entities
in the scene that have both
the FlockingComponent
and the MotionComponent on them.
Lots of things have
the MotionComponent,
but we don’t want all of them,
we just want our flock.
Our query returns
our flocking fish,
so now we can drive our custom
game physics by applying
the classic Boids simulation
to each fish in the flock.
We add forces on each fish’s
MotionComponent, where we keep
our state between frames,
forces for sticking together,
for preferring to stay a certain
distance apart, and for trying
to point their noses
in the same direction.
When the Motion System runs,
in the same frame
but after
the Flocking System runs,
it rolls up
all these forces to decide
the fish’s new acceleration,
velocity, and position.
It doesn’t care which other
system added them.
There are others,
like the Eating System
and the Fear System that also
operate on the MotionComponent
to push the fish
in various directions.
So let’s see the code.
Here’s an outline
of our Flocking System.
It’s a class that conforms
to the RealityKit.System
protocol.
When you register your custom
system at app launch time,
you’re telling the engine
that you want it to instantiate
one of this type
per scene in your app.
The init is required,
and you can
also provide a deinit.
We can specify dependencies.
This system should always run
before the MotionSystem,
which is why we’ve used
the enumeration
value.before here.
In our update function,
we’ll be altering the state
stored in the MotionComponent,
and the MotionSystem will be
acting upon the state
we provide, so we need to make
sure the FlockingSystem runs
before the MotionSystem,
sort of like a producer-consumer
relationship.
You can also use
the .after option.
If you don’t
specify dependencies,
your systems’ update
functions will be
executed in the order
you registered them in.
Our EntityQuery says
that we want all entities
that have the Flocking
and Motion Components.
It’s a static let
because it’s not going
to change for the duration
of our simulation.
In a multiplayer AR experience,
components that conform
to codable are automatically
synced over the network.
However, data in systems
are not automatically
synced over the network.
Data should be generally
stored in components.
Now let’s dive in
to our FlockingSystem’s
update function.
It takes a SceneUpdateContext,
which has in it the deltaTime
for that frame and a reference
to the scene itself.
First, we perform
our EntityQuery
on the scene,
which returns a query result
that we can iterate
over for the entities
that have the FlockingComponent
on them.
We get each one’s
MotionComponent,
which we’re going to be
modifying.
Why are we not getting
the FlockingComponent itself?
Because it doesn’t have
any data associated with it.
We use that one like a tag
to signify
membership in the flock.
Then we run our standard
Boids simulation on them
to guide the flock,
modifying the collection
of forces
in the MotionComponent.
At the end, since we’ve added
forces to each fish to push it
in the desired direction,
and because components are Swift
structs which are value types,
we need to store
our MotionComponent back
onto the entity it came from.
Systems don’t have to implement
a custom update function.
It can also be useful to create
a system which only provides
an init, like to register
event handlers for scene events.
So far, we’ve been looking
at the relationships between
entities, components,
and custom systems.
Now let’s zoom out for a second
and talk about some high-level
architecture changes that we’ve
brought in RealityKit 2.
Before, you would subscribe
to the SceneEvents.update event
using a closure that would
be called every frame.
These kind of event handlers
would often live,
or at least be registered in,
your Game Manager-like classes.
Instead of closures like that,
you can now have
your update logic
cleanly separated
and formally ordered
in separate system
update functions.
So that means your Game Managers
can play less of a role.
Instead of doing
all your registrations
for event updates there
and then managing the order
in which you call update
on all the things in your game,
now the Game Managers
only have to add
components to the entities
to signify to your systems
that those entities should be
included in their queries.
Previously, you would declare
protocol conformances
on your entity subclasses
to express
that that entity type
has certain components.
Now you don’t need
to subclass entity anymore,
since it, too, can play
less of a role.
It can be merely
an identifier for an object,
and its attributes can be
modeled as components.
Because when you don’t
subclass entity, you don’t
tie your object to forever
keeping those components.
You’re free to add
and remove components
during the experience.
So with RealityKit 2,
your custom components
are a lot more useful
because you have custom systems.
But you can still
do it either way.
That’s the beauty
of game development.
The world is your oyster.
In our underwater demo,
we’re using both methods.
We’ve also added a new
type of component:
TransientComponent.
Say, for example,
your fish were afraid
of the octopus, but only if
they had ever looked at it.
When you clone up a new fish
entity, you might not want
the clone to inherit that fish’s
fear of the octopus.
You could make
your FearComponent
conform to TransientComponent.
That way, it wouldn’t be
present on the new entity.
The TransientComponent is still
included in a network sync,
though,
if it conforms to codable,
like any other kind
of component that does so.
Another addition is our new
extension on cancellable.
You don’t need
to manually manage
unsubscribing to events
for an entity anymore.
We’ll do it for you when you use
storeWhileEntityActive.
Here, we’re handling collision
events for a fish entity.
We don’t need this subscription
to outlive the fish itself,
so we use
storeWhileEntityActive.
As always, when building a game,
there’s a whole bunch
of settings that you want
to tweak on the fly
without having to recompile.
In our game, we built
a Settings view in SwiftUI,
and we pass its backing model
down into our various
CustomSystems by way of wrapping
them in CustomComponents.
We create our Settings instance
as a @StateObject
and pass it into both
our ARViewContainer
and our SwiftUI view
as an environmentObject.
We wrap the Settings object
in a CustomComponent,
a SettingsComponent.
Then when we create
our fish entity,
we give it a SettingsComponent.
That way, when any CustomSystem
comes along that wants
those settings, it can read them
from there, like take
the “top speed” value and use it
to cap each fish’s velocity.
And now I’ll hand it over
to my colleague,
Olivier,
to tell you about materials.
[Olivier] Thanks, Amanda.
This year,
we added new APIs for materials.
We already had a few types,
such as SimpleMaterial,
with a baseColor, roughness,
and metallic property.
We also had UnlitMaterial,
with just a color
and no lighting.
We had OcclusionMaterials,
which can be used as a mask
to hide virtual objects.
And last year,
we introduced VideoMaterials,
which are UnlitMaterials
using a video as their color.
Note that this year we added
support for transparency.
If the video file
contains transparency,
it will be used
to render the object.
This year, we added new APIs
that give you a more
advanced control over materials,
starting with the type
PhysicallyBasedMaterial,
which is very similar
to the schema
for materials in USD.
It is a superset
of SimpleMaterial and has
most of the standard PBR
properties that you can
find in other renderers.
This is the material
that you will find
on entities that have
been loaded from a USD.
You can,
for example, load the USD
of the clown fish and then
modify individual properties
on its materials
to make it gold or purple.
Among the properties
of the material, you can,
for example,
change the normal map
to add small details
that are not part of the mesh.
You can also assign
a texture defining
the transparency of the model.
By default,
the transparency is using
alpha blending,
but if you also assign
an opacityThreshold,
all the fragments
below that threshold
will be discarded.
You can set the texture
for ambient occlusion,
defining vague shadows
in the model.
And an example of a more
advanced property is clearcoat,
which will simulate
an additional layer
of reflective paint
on the material.
And there’s
many other properties
available on the type
PhysicallyBasedMaterial.
We also added a new type
called custom material
to make materials using
your own metal code.
This is what we used to make
the color transition effect
on this octopus model.
We will explain this shader
and custom materials
in the second talk
about rendering.
In addition to materials,
we also added
more control
over animations in RealityKit.
First, let’s go over
the existing API for animations,
which are mostly about
playback of animations
loaded from a USD.
If you load an animation from
a USD, you can play it once.
You can also repeat it
so that it loops infinitely,
which is what we want
for the Idle animation
of our diver here.
You can also pause, resume,
and stop an animation.
Finally,
when playing a new animation,
you can specify a transition
duration.
If you don’t specify one,
the character will
instantly switch
to the new animation.
If you do specify a transition
duration, RealityKit will blend
between the old and new
animations during that time.
This is useful, for example,
when transitioning
between the Walk
and Idle cycles of the diver.
But we can still improve
the animation of the feet there.
We can use the new API
for blend layers
to make the animations
more realistic.
We play the Walking animation
and the Idle animation
on two separate blend layers,
and since we played the Walking
animation on the top layer,
that’s the only animation
that we currently see.
But we can change the blend
factor of the Walking animation
to reveal the Idle animation
underneath.
Notice how, as the blend factor
gets smaller,
the footsteps also get smaller.
And we can also change
the playback speed
of the animations to make
the diver walk faster or slower.
Here, the diver is
walking at half speed.
Finally, we use the speed
of the character relative
to the ground to control
both of these values.
This way, we can make
the animations smoother
and reduce
the sliding of the feet
compared to the ground.
So far, we have been using
multiple animation clips,
such as the Idle and Walk
cycles.
These are stored
as AnimationResources
in RealityKit.
And there are multiple ways
to load them from USD files.
The first way is to have
one USD file per clip.
We can load
each USD as an entity
and get its animations
as AnimationResources.
The AnimationResource
can then be played
on any entity,
as long as the names
of the joints in its skeleton
match the animation.
Another way to load multiple
animation clips is to have them
in a single USD
on the same timeline
and then use AnimationViews
to slice this timeline
into multiples clips.
This requires knowing
the timecodes between each clip.
Each AnimationView
can then be converted
to an AnimationResource and used
exactly the same way
as the previous method.
Let’s now go over the animations
of the octopus in the app.
The octopus is hiding,
but when the player gets near,
it will be scared and move
to a new hiding spot.
Let’s see how to animate it.
We start with loading
the skeletal animations
of the octopus: jumping,
swimming, and landing.
These animations are loaded
from a USD,
just like what we did
for the diver.
But we also want to animate
the transform of the octopus
to move it from one location
to the next.
To animate the transform, we use
a new API to programmatically
create an animation
of type FromToByAnimation.
This way,
we can animate the position.
Let’s see what it looks like
on the octopus.
To make it more interesting,
let’s also animate the rotation.
The octopus
now rotates while it moves,
but it’s swimming sideways,
which is not very realistic.
We can improve this by making
a sequence of animations.
First, we rotate the octopus
towards the new location.
Then we translate it
to the new location.
And finally,
we rotate the octopus
back towards the camera.
And here is the full animation.
In addition to new
APIs for animations,
we also added a way to manage
the physics of characters.
It’s called
Character controller.
This allows us to create
characters that can
physically interact
with the colliders in the scene.
Here, we see the diver
jumping from the floor
to the couch and walking on it.
This is achieved by adding
a character controller
to the diver.
With that,
the diver will automatically
interact with the mesh
of the environment,
generated from the LiDAR sensor.
Creating a character controller
is simple.
All you need to do is
to define a capsule
that matches the shape
of your character.
On creation,
you have to specify the height
of the capsule and its radius.
After the character controller
has been assigned to the entity,
you can call the move(to:)
function every frame.
It will make the character
move to the desired location,
but without
going through obstacles.
On the other hand, if you do
want to ignore obstacles,
you can use
the teleport function.
Now I will hand it off
to Amanda,
who will take you through
a few more fun features
that we’ve added
to this release of RealityKit.
[Amanda] Great.
Thanks, Olivier.
OK, so I’ll highlight
two new APIs
that are available
for creating resources
on the fly without having
to load them from disk.
First I’ll show you how you can
get the mesh of a person’s face
from SceneUnderstanding,
and then
I’ll take you through
how to generate audio.
There’s a sea of possibilities
that these open up
for procedurally generated art.
First up, the face mesh.
I was so inspired by the look
of the purple and orange octopus
we have in our demo app,
I tried my hand at painting one
on my face, but virtually, using
the new face mesh capability.
SceneUnderstanding can
now give you entities
that represent people’s faces,
and those entities have
ModelComponents on them,
which means you can swap out
the properties of the materials
on the face entity’s mesh.
We had a lot of fun generating
the textures to apply
to the face mesh on the fly
with our live drawings.
Let’s look at the code.
The SceneUnderstandingComponent
now has an enum property
called entityType, which is set
by the SceneUnderstandingSystem
and can take
one of two values: face,
meaning it’s the representation
of a real-world person’s face,
or meshChunk,
meaning it’s some other part
of the reconstructed world mesh.
It can also be nil, meaning
its type is not yet known.
Here’s an EntityQuery again.
You can query for entities
that have
the SceneUnderstandingComponent
and check
their entityType to find faces.
Then, you can get
the ModelComponents
from those entities and do
whatever you want with them.
In our face painting sample,
we’re using PencilKit
to let people draw on the canvas
and then wrapping the resulting
CGImage onto the faceEntity
by creating a TextureResource
from that CGImage.
We’re using
a PhysicallyBasedMaterial
so that we can make
this face paint look
as realistic as possible,
and we’re setting a few
of the properties on it
to dial it in for our look.
To make the glitter paint
effect, we use a normal
map texture which tells
the physically based renderer
how it should reflect the light
differently on this surface
than it would if we had simply
left the material metallic.
We then give the pencil-drawn
TextureResource to the material
and set it on the entity.
So that’s one way
to work with our new
generated resources.
Another type of resource
you can now generate
is the AudioBufferResource.
You can get an AVAudioBuffer
however you like:
by recording microphone input,
procedurally generating it
yourself,
or using an AVSpeechSynthesizer.
Then you can use
the AVAudioBuffer to create
an AudioBufferResource and use
that to play sounds in your app.
Here’s how we turn text
into speech by writing
an AVSpeechUtterance
to an AVSpeechSynthesizer.
We receive
an AVAudioBuffer in a callback.
Here, we’re creating
an AudioBufferResource
and setting its inputMode
to .spatial to make use
of 3D positional audio.
The other available inputModes
are nonSpatial and ambient.
Then we tell an entity
to play that audio.
You could, of course,
process the audio buffer
with fancy tricks to make it
sound like your fish
are blowing bubbles
as they talk under water
or whatever fun things
you can come up with.
So this was an overview
of some of the new features
in RealityKit this year.
We’ve really focused
on giving you more control
over the appearance
and behaviors of your scenes.
We’ve modified our ECS
to provide you
with custom systems,
which gives you
way more flexibility
in structuring
your app’s behaviors.
We’ve added lots of advancements
to our materials
and animation APIs.
We’ve introduced the character
controller to make it easy
for your entities to interact
with the real-world environment.
Finally, we’ve highlighted
a few of the ways
in which you can generate
resources on the fly.
But that’s definitely
not an exhaustive list
of everything that’s new
in RealityKit 2.
In our second RealityKit
session later this week,
you can learn more about
the new rendering capabilities
and see how we implemented
some of the things
in our underwater demo.
A geometry modifier
is what we use
to animate our seaweed.
The octopus uses surface shaders
to transition
beautifully between its colors.
The blue depth fog effect
as well as the water caustics
were created
using post processing.
And in the theme
of generative resources,
you’ll learn
how to use dynamic meshes.
For a refresher,
you might also want to check out
the session “Building Apps
with RealityKit” from 2019.
Thank you,
and we look forward to seeing
the depths of your creativity
with these APIs.
[upbeat music]