[percussive music]
♪ ♪
[Roy] Hi, my name is Roy.
I'm an engineer
on the Camera Software team.
Today I will be walking you
through some exciting
photo quality improvements
we made with our most
popular video formats,
and how your applications
can make use of them
to deliver
an even better experience.
iPhone is the most popular
camera in the world,
and for many years,
developers have been
taking advantage of its
powerful camera systems
to provide a diverse set
of world-class experiences,
from professional photography
apps to video streaming tools.
Different scenarios call for
different levels
of photo quality.
For example, apps dedicated
to taking still photos
will demand
the absolute best quality
that the cameras can provide.
A social app, on the other hand,
might need to apply face effect
overlays
on top of the video
frames being streamed.
And this custom rendering might
be computationally expensive.
In order to avoid frame drops,
the developer might
prefer lower resolution frames
so there are fewer pixels
to process per frame.
This diversity in use cases
calls for an easy way
to specify where you want
to land
on the scale of quality
versus performance.
Before we dive into photo
quality, however,
let's have a brief refresher
on how photos are taken
on iOS in general.
We will start
with an AVCaptureSession object,
around which we can build
our object graph.
Since we are taking photos,
we will use a camera
as our AVCaptureDevice.
Then, an AVCaptureDeviceInput
is instantiated
based on that device,
and it will provide input data
to the session.
An AVCapturePhotoOutput
will then be added to the graph
as the recipients of the photos.
And all these elements
are then connected together
using an AVCaptureConnection.
After the session
started running,
we can capture photos by calling
the capturePhoto method
on the AVCapturePhotoOutput
instance.
Further customization
can be done
using the AVCapturePhotoSettings
object
passed to the capturePhoto
method.
The captured photo will be
represented
as an AVCapturePhoto object
that you will receive
in your delegate method.
We had a very detailed
discussion on these APIs
in the 2016 session,
Advances in iOS Photography.
Please check it out if
you haven't already.
Now that we know how to take
photos on iOS in general,
let's see how high quality
photos can be taken.
Historically,
if you wanted to capture photos
of the best possible quality,
you would set the
isAutoStillImageStabilization
Enabled property
on your
AVCapturePhotoSettings to true,
and that's because still
image stabilization
was the main method for getting
higher quality photos.
But over the years,
we have been continuously
evolving our photo
quality-enhancing algorithms.
In addition to still
image stabilization,
we now have a far richer set
of techniques to draw from,
such as a variety of multi-image
fusion technologies,
including
Smart HDR and Deep Fusion.
Consequently, the name
isAutoStillImageStabilization
Enabled
has become quite obsolete as
a proxy for high photo quality.
To solve this problem,
in iOS 13, we introduced
AVCapturePhotoOutput.QualityPrio
ritization.
It's a very easy way
to tell AVCapturePhotoOutput
how to prioritize quality
in your photo captures.
We haven't had a chance
to talk about this important API
at previous WWDCs,
so let's now take a moment
to see how it works.
There are three quality
prioritization levels
to choose from:
speed, balanced, and quality.
With speed,
you are telling the framework
that the speed of the capture is
what you care about the most,
even at the expense
of photo quality.
If a balance needs
to be struck between
photo quality
and delivery speed,
balanced should be used.
Quality does the opposite
of speed.
It says image quality
should be prioritized
first and foremost,
while the potential
slowness of the capture process
can be tolerated.
Please note that the quality
prioritization specified
only serves as a hint
to the AVCapturePhotoOutput,
and it doesn't dictate
what algorithms to use.
Ultimately,
the AVCapturePhotoOutput
will consider a variety
of constraints
and choose the most appropriate
algorithm for the current scene.
For instance, it might choose
a different method
for a low-light situation
than in a well-lit space.
That being said,
we understand that
based on different capture
durations,
you might want to plan your
user experience differently.
So on the
AVCaptureResolvedPhotoSettings
object passed to some of
the AVCapturePhotoOutputDelegate
methods, we give you
a property called
photoProcessingTimeRange
that indicates how long
it will take to deliver
the photo to your delegate.
This, for instance,
can help you decide whether
you want to put out a spinner if
the capture will take a while.
Let's see how it works in code.
When you are setting up your
AVCapturePhotoOutput,
you can specify a max
quality prioritization
that the particular capture
session will require.
If you choose not to do so,
the default value is balanced.
This only has to be set once.
The importance of doing so
is that depending on
different settings,
we will configure
our capture
pipelines differently.
For instance,
if we know you will not go
beyond speed prioritization,
we can construct
a capture pipeline
that consumes
much less memory and power
than the one for, say,
balanced prioritization.
So we encourage you
to choose responsibly
and only take what you need.
Before you
call the capturePhoto method,
you can customize
the quality prioritization
for this particular capture
by setting the
photoQualityPrioritization
property on your
AVCapturePhotoSettings object.
The default value is balanced.
As demonstrated here,
we are using
two different levels
in two different situations.
Please note that the per-capture
quality prioritization
cannot go beyond your
AVCapturePhotoOutput's
max quality prioritization,
otherwise
you will get an exception.
The performance characteristics
of the three levels
are determined by the underlying
algorithms we use.
The mappings differ based
on the kinds of format you use,
and we will talk some
more on the difference
between photo and video
formats momentarily.
With photo formats, Speed
will get you WYSIWYG photos--
that is What You See is
What You Get photos--
which are lightly processed
only with some noise reduction
applied.
If Balanced is specified,
we will choose from a collection
of fast fusion algorithms
that produce much better
photo quality
than WYSIWYG photos
at a somewhat slower
capture rate.
For Quality, depending
on the current device
and lux level,
the framework will use
some heavy machineries
such as Deep Fusion
in order to provide the best
possible photo quality.
The photos will look great,
but there is no free lunch.
You pay
for it by using more time.
For video formats,
on the other hand,
all levels will use
the lightest processing
to deliver photos
as fast as possible.
We have been talking
about photo and video formats
for a while now.
Let's take a closer look
at the differences between them.
By using photo formats, you are
signaling to the framework
that taking still photos is what
you care about the most.
For example, if you are using
an AVCaptureVideoDataOutput
with a photo format,
the sample buffers you get
by default
will only be
of preview resolutions,
and that's because knowing
that taking photos
is your top priority,
we can assume that these frames
will be used for preview
rather than video recordings.
A good reason to choose photo
formats is that
some photo-centric features
are exclusive for photo formats,
such as Live Photo and ProRAW,
et cetera.
If that's
something you want to do,
then photo format
is the way to go.
Photo formats come with the
highest resolutions available,
but the frame rates are limited
to 30 frames per second.
To choose photo formats,
you can set
your session preset to photo.
Or you can pick a format where
isHighestPhotoQualitySupported
is true.
The usage of video formats,
on the other hand,
indicates that the experiences
will now center around videos.
You will get resolutions
more suitable
for recording and streaming,
and you will be able
to use high frame
rates such as 60 fps.
If a format
is not a photo format,
then it's
considered a video format.
So you can select one by using
a non-photo session preset
or choosing a format where
isHighestPhotoQualitySupported
is false.
You might be wondering
why we are not applying
some of the powerful
algorithms to video formats.
It's not because we're lazy.
We have good reasons for that.
Many apps choose to use video
formats because they need to do
heavy custom processing,
and video formats are
well-suited for this purpose
because of their low overhead.
If we leverage some
of the aforementioned
photo enhancing techniques,
we might introduce degradations
in these apps' experiences.
For instance,
an AR app might allow users
to snap a photo of the 3D scene
that they are interacting with.
Running the existing
fusion algorithms at this point
is likely
to introduce frame drops
in the app's camera feed,
interrupting its core feature.
So we have been very conscious
of this delicate balance between
quality and speed, and we
designed our video formats
to work responsively even under
the most demanding conditions.
But those compromises
stop today with iOS 15.
We are taking a major
leap in photo quality
with our most popular
video formats.
With some improved algorithms,
we are now able to radically
improve photo quality
without impacting other aspects
of your apps' experiences.
With this new feature, your apps
can now take amazing photos,
while retaining
the same flexibility
to perform sophisticated
custom computation.
So how big of a quality leap are
we talking about here?
Let's take a look at some
before-and-after comparisons.
The improvement is quite
substantial.
The little boy's face
on the right
has much less noise,
and thus
looks much more natural.
And we can better perceive
the light coming off his hair.
The catch lights
in your subjects' eyes
are simply
more vibrant and lively.
In this outdoor low-light
situation,
there is superior de-noising
on her face and clothes.
Lastly, the environment
also looks better.
The leather texture on the chair
is much better preserved.
Now that you're enticed,
let's take a look
at the algorithm mappings
for the supported video formats.
Speed will still get you
the lightly processed
WYSIWYG photos.
They are still the fastest
way of getting a photo,
and since speed is now
your top priority,
this fits the bill perfectly,
so we didn't change it.
You will not be getting
any frame drops
in your video recordings
or any disruptions
in your preview feed.
With Balanced, however,
you are now getting
a significant bump in quality,
while only getting
a very slight increase
in the photo's processing time.
And just like in Speed,
your video recording
will not have any frame drops.
Your preview feed will not
get interrupted,
even when
those great-looking photos
are taken and processed.
Finally, for Quality,
we are running more
expensive algorithms
to get even better qualities.
This might drop frames or cause
preview feed interruptions,
depending on how recent
your devices are.
This feature will be
available on all iPhones
with support all the way
back to iPhone XS.
The video formats
that are getting this upgrade
are the most
popular ones:
1280x720
with support for both 30
and 60 frames per second.
1920x1080,
also for both 30 and 60 fps.
1920x1440, for 30 fps.
And we even added support
for 4K, with 30 fps.
So how can you make sure
you are using
the right formats in your code?
It's very simple.
In iOS 15, we are introducing
a new property called
isHighPhotoQualitySupported
on the AVCaptureDevice.Format
type.
For formats
that support this feature,
this property will be true.
Any format with this
property being true
is guaranteed to be a video
format,
so you don't have to worry
about accidentally
picking a photo format.
Let's say you want
to get any such format.
You just need to get
the formats available
on your
AVCaptureDevice instance.
Then just select the one
with isHighPhotoQualitySupported
being true.
We updated our sample code AVCam
to use this feature.
Please check it out if you want
to see a working example.
It's possible to confuse
the new property
isHighPhotoQualitySupported
with the existing
isHighestPhotoQualitySupported.
Like we mentioned earlier,
the latter tells you
whether a format
is a photo format,
and it doesn't tell you
whether a video format
supports high photo quality.
Now, do you need to put
in any work at all
to get this new feature?
The answer is maybe.
If you are already using
AVCapturePhotoOutput,
and the .balanced
prioritization,
then congratulations,
you will automatically
get better-looking photos
on iOS 15.
If your app is using
speed prioritization,
by simply updating it
to balanced,
you will receive better photos
without having to worry
about any frame drops.
If you're
still using the deprecated
AVCaptureStillImageOutput,
then hopefully this
will give you
a big incentive to switch over.
Since now using
the quality prioritization
might introduce
frame drops in your videos,
we don't want to impose
that new behavior on your apps
without you opting in.
So we put in a link time
check to make sure that
if your app is using
quality prioritization
with a video format and was
compiled prior to iOS 15,
then we will automatically
change it to balanced.
If you indeed would like
to get the best quality,
all you need to do is re-compile
your app with the iOS 15 SDK.
There are a few caveats
to be aware of.
This feature currently
only works
with AVCaptureSession,
and not
with AVCaptureMultiCamSession.
The deprecated
AVCaptureStillImageOutput
will not support this feature.
If you are using .balanced
or .quality prioritization,
some of the algorithms we use
might fuse several
differently exposed images
to improve dynamic range.
Photos will have great quality,
but they might look
different from video
being recorded at the same time.
If you need your video and photo
to look exactly the same,
please use .speed instead.
Lastly, let's summarize
what we just covered.
When designing your app's
experience,
be aware
of the decision to choose
between quality and speed.
Once you figured out the role
photo quality will play
in your use cases,
use the appropriate
prioritization levels
to accomplish that.
And with a minimal amount
of work
and sometimes
no work at all,
you will now be getting amazing
photos with video formats.
Thank you very much.
[percussive music]