[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Philippe Hausler: Hi,
my name is Philippe,
and I am really excited
to introduce you
to a cool new feature in Swift,
AsyncSequence.
Today we'll go over
what async sequences are
and the fundamentals
behind them.
Then we'll talk about how
you can use them in your code
and go over a few of the new
AsyncSequence APIs.
And finally,
we'll explore how you can build
your own async sequences.
So let's dive right in.
This is a really simple tool
I wrote to illustrate
some of the cool new stuff
you can do with AsyncSequence.
In this tool, we start off
with a URL to an endpoint.
It lists recent earthquakes.
Now, normally downloading stuff
is really an asynchronous task
that can take some time.
But in this case,
we don't want to wait
for all the things to download;
instead, we want to show things
as they are received.
So I decided
to shake things up a bit
and use the new
async/await features
to get the lines responded
from this endpoint.
The data that we're fetching
is formatted
as comma-separated text,
so each line is
a complete row of data.
Since the async sequence
of lines is emitting each line
as it's received,
that means we can potentially
have a really large download
ahead of us.
But by emitting them
as we get them,
the snippet feels
really responsive,
and the most awesome part
about it is that you can use
the same things
that you're familiar with using
from regular sequences
in this new async context.
That means that you can use
the new for-await-in syntax
to iterate, and functions
like map, filter, and reduce;
or -- like in this sample --
the dropFirst function
to manipulate those values.
So how does this work?
Well, a lot of things that I'm
going to talk about today
have their groundwork
based in the async/await talk.
But let's recap
a few key points.
Async functions let you
write concurrent code
without the need for callbacks,
by using the await keyword.
Calling an async function will
suspend and then be resumed
whenever a value
or error is produced.
AsyncSequence,
on the other hand,
will suspend on each
element and resume
when the underlying iterator
produces a value or throws.
Basically, as the name implies,
they're just like
regular sequences
but with a few key differences.
Namely, each element
is delivered asynchronously.
But because they are
an asynchronous delivery,
that means that failure
is definitely a possibility.
Some async sequences throw,
but if failure is not an option,
others do not.
Just like functions that throw,
the compiler will help make sure
that errors are handled
when iterating or composing.
Generally speaking,
asynchronous sequences
are a description
of how to produce values
over time.
So an async sequence
may be zero or more values
and then signify completion
with returning a nil
from its iterator,
just like sequences.
When an error occurs,
that's also a point
at which the async sequence
is at a terminal state,
and after an error happens,
they'll return nil
for any subsequent calls
to next on their iterator.
So let's take a dive into
how that definition works
by first starting off
with regular iteration.
Here we have
a pretty familiar pattern.
This is a for-in loop.
In this case, it's iterating
quakes from a sequence
and then calling a function
when the magnitude
is above a certain value.
The compiler has knowledge
of how this iteration
should work,
but what it does isn't magic.
The compilation step
really just does some
straightforward transformations.
Let's examine
those transformations
so you can understand what the
asynchronous form of this is.
This is roughly what
the compiler does
when building the previous code.
It first starts off by creating
an iterator variable
and then uses a while loop
to get every quake
produced by the iterator
when next is invoked.
To use the new
async/await functionality,
there is one slight alteration
that can be made.
It's as simple as changing
that next function
to be an asynchronous one.
We can now have the iteration
participate in Swift concurrency
by awaiting the next quake.
Let's rewind back to uncover
what this would have been like
if the loop
was on an async sequence.
As previously mentioned,
we need to await each item
out of the async sequence.
This is reflected
in the new for-await-in syntax.
This all means that if you know
how to use Sequence,
you already have a good idea
on how to use AsyncSequence.
There are a few ways
you can utilize async sequences.
As we just covered,
you can use the new
for-await-in syntax;
or if the async sequence throws,
you can use the new
for-try-await-in syntax.
This lets you easily iterate
the values produced
asynchronously --
without having to muck about
with closures --
and use the syntax
you are already familiar with
to iterate through them.
Even things like break
and continue just work.
Now you have now had
a good introduction
to the theory
of async sequences.
Let's explore that iteration
just a bit further.
Given a source
that is an async sequence,
you can await each value
by using
the for-await-in syntax.
This means that
it will await each item
produced by the iterator,
and when it would hit
a terminal,
it completes the loop.
When iterating async sequences,
breaking is obviously a good way
to terminate iteration early
from inside the loop.
This works just like
regular sequences.
Here we're breaking
when the location data
is not present for the quake.
Or if we have some of value
we want to skip,
we can use continue.
In this case, if the depth
is greater than some value,
we're skipping those
and continuing on
to await the next quake.
This next iteration
from the download
works just like before,
but in this case,
the source that we have
can throw an error.
Just like throwing functions,
try is required
to process each element
when the AsyncSequence
being iterated can throw.
And also just like
throwing functions,
the compiler will detect
when you're missing a try
and offer you a Fix-it
to correct the mistake.
This means that
when an async sequence
can produce errors,
you're always safe,
because the language forces
you to either throw that error
or catch it.
This second iteration
runs sequentially
after the iteration
of the first loop.
Running code sequentially
isn't always what's desired.
If it's useful to run
the iteration
concurrent to other things
going on,
you can create a new async task
that encapsulates the iteration.
This can be useful when you know
the async sequences you're using
might run indefinitely.
Now, even though that sequence
could potentially be indefinite,
it's considerably
less common to occur.
But in the world
of asynchronous behavior,
it is something
much more common
and something that you need
to consider when using them.
Thankfully, the facilities
for concurrency in Swift
make this really easy
and safe to do.
This can be also really helpful
when you want to potentially
cancel the iteration externally.
Here we can run the
two iterations concurrently
and terminate the iteration
later on.
It's pretty easy with tasks
to scope the work
of an iteration
that might be indefinite
to the lifetime
of some container.
Let's next take a tour of some
of the AsyncSequence APIs
that are available
as of macOS Monterey,
iOS 15, tvOS 15,
and watchOS 8.
There are a lot of them,
but I'll show you
some of the highlights.
Reading from files is often
a prime use case
for asynchronous behavior.
FileHandle now has a new bytes
property that gives access
to an asynchronous sequence
of bytes from that FileHandle.
This can be used in conjunction
with the new extension
on AsyncSequence
that converts asynchronous
sequences of bytes into lines.
But dealing with files
is so common
that we decided that URL
should have accessors
for both bytes and lines.
This is that same API
that I used
in the initial example.
It's a convenience property
on URL
to return an AsyncSequence
of lines from the contents,
either from a file
or from the network.
I'm certain this will
make a number
of previously really complicated
tasks easy and safe.
Sometimes getting things
from the network
requires a bit more control
over the responses
and authentication.
So URLSession now
has a bytes function
to fetch an async sequence of
bytes given a URL or URLRequest.
If you want to know more,
you should definitely check out
the session "Use async/
await with URLSession"
for some more details on this
and a whole lot more
new asynchronous capabilities
with URLSession.
But files and networks
are not the only thing
that makes sense
for AsyncSequence.
Notifications can be now awaited
with the new notifications API.
And iteration
is not the only way
to interact with
an AsyncSequence.
In this example, we're awaiting
the first notification
for remote changes that has
a store UUID that matches.
Using methods like firstWhere,
along with the notifications
async sequence,
allows for some really neat
new design patterns
that can make code
that was previously expressing
complicated logic
now compact and easier to read.
And if all of those
weren't cool enough,
there are a whole
lot of new APIs
for asynchronously manipulating
values from async sequences.
These should be pretty familiar,
because they're some
of the same functions
that are available on Sequence.
We've already
covered a few so far,
like dropFirst and firstWhere,
but there are a whole lot more
than just those.
Pretty much anything you can
think of for using on Sequence
now has
an asynchronous counterpart
for working with AsyncSequence.
Now that was a lot to take in,
and you might be thinking,
"Hey, those new APIs
are really cool,
and that syntax is super neat,
but how can I make
my own async sequences?"
Well, let's do exactly that!
There are a few ways of
implementing an async sequence,
but I'm going to focus in on
how to adapt your existing code.
Particularly, there are
a few design patterns
that work really well
with AsyncSequence,
and we have some
fantastic facilities
for making what you already have
interact with this new concept.
Some of those design patterns
are like closures
that are called multiple times,
but also some delegates
can work nicely too.
Pretty much anything that does
not need a response back
and is just informing
of a new value that occurs
can be a prime candidate
for making an async sequence.
These design patterns
are really common
and you likely already have
a few in your apps today.
This is an example
of a common handler pattern.
It's a class that has
a handler property
and a start and stop method.
It seems like a perfect
candidate for AsyncSequence.
Existing usage might be
something like this
where a monitor is created,
and a handler to get values
is assigned,
and then the monitor is started
so that quakes can be sent
to the handler.
Later on, the monitor might
be stopped
to cancel the events
being produced.
We can use the same interface
to adapt the usage
to the new AsyncStream type.
It takes only a small bit
of code to use it
and allows you to build
an async sequence.
When constructing
an async stream,
an element type and construction
closure is specified.
The closure has a continuation
that can yield values
more than once, finish,
or handle termination.
So this means, in this case,
the monitor can be created
inside the construction closure.
And then the handler can be
assigned to yield quakes
to the continuation.
And then the onTermination
can handle the cancellation
and cleanup.
And then we can
start monitoring.
The same monitor code
that we had before
can easily be encapsulated
within the async stream's
construction.
This reduces the need
to replicate the same logic
in every use site.
And this is how the usage
of this async stream would work.
You can use the powerful
transformation functions --
like filter --
and the new
for-await-in syntax.
This lets you focus on
the intent of your code
instead of needing
to worry about
replicating the bookkeeping,
since everything is wrapped up
into one place.
There's a lot of flexibility
with AsyncStream
to create
your own async sequences.
This is really just one example
and there are likely numerous
others that you can adapt
in your own code.
AsyncStream is a great way
to adapt your existing code
to become an async sequence.
It handles all of the things
you would expect
from an async sequence,
like safety, iteration,
and cancellation;
but they also
handle buffering.
AsyncStream is a solid way
of building your own
async sequences
and a suitable return type
from your own APIs,
since the only source
of elements being produced
is from the construction.
And if you need to represent
errors being thrown?
Well, we have a type for that!
AsyncThrowingStream
that is just like AsyncStream
but can handle errors.
It offers the same flexibility
and safety as AsyncStream
but can handle failures
by throwing from its iteration.
AsyncSequence is
a really powerful tool
that is both safe and familiar
for dealing with more
than one asynchronous value.
If you know how to use Sequence,
you already know
how to use AsyncSequence.
We've gone over what
async sequences are,
and how they're used,
and introduced you
to AsyncStream.
We've dived into the theory
and what defines them,
and a few of the newly
introduced async sequences,
and finally,
how to build your own.
I eagerly await
what you do with them next.
♪