[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Kavon] Hi, I’m Kavon,
and I’ll be joined by my colleague,
Joe, later on.
Swift 5.5 introduces a new way
to write concurrent programs,
using a concept
called structured concurrency.
The ideas behind structured concurrency
are based on structured programming,
which so intuitive
that you rarely think about it,
but thinking about it will help you
understand structured concurrency.
So let’s dive in.
In the early days of computing,
programs were hard to read
because they were written
as a sequence of instructions,
where control-flow was allowed
to jump all over the place.
You don’t see that today, because
languages use structured programming
to make control-flow more uniform.
For example, the if-then statement
uses structured control-flow.
It specifies that a nested block of code
is only conditionally executed
while moving from top to bottom.
In Swift, that block also
respects static scoping,
meaning that names are only visible
if they are defined in an enclosing block.
This also means that the lifetime
of any variables defined in a block
will end when leaving the block.
So, structured programming
with static scope
makes control-flow
and variable lifetime easy to understand.
More generally, structured control-flow
can be sequenced
and nested together naturally.
This lets you read
your entire program top to bottom.
So, those are the fundamentals
of structured programming.
As you can imagine,
it is easy to take for granted,
because it is so intuitive for us today.
But today’s programs feature asynchronous
and concurrent code,
and they have not been able
to use structured programming
to make that code easier to write.
First, let’s consider
how structured programming
makes asynchronous code simpler.
Say that you need to fetch
a bunch of images from the internet
and resize them
to be thumbnails sequentially.
This code does that work asynchronously,
taking in a collection of strings
that identify the images.
You’ll notice this function
does not return a value when called.
That’s because the function
passes its result, or an error,
to a completion handler it was given.
This pattern allows the caller
to receive an answer at a later time.
As a consequence of that pattern,
this function cannot use
structured control-flow
for error handling.
That’s because it only makes sense
to handle errors thrown
out of a function, not into one.
Also, this pattern prevents you
from using a loop
to process each thumbnail.
Recursion is required,
because the code that runs
after the function completes
must be nested within the handler.
Now, let’s take a look
at the previous code
but rewritten to use
the new async/await syntax,
which is based on structured programming.
I’ve dropped the completion handler
argument from the function.
Instead, it is annotated with “async”
and “throws” in its type signature.
It also returns a value
instead of nothing.
In the body of the function,
I use “await” to say
that an asynchronous action happens,
and no nesting is required
for the code that runs after that action.
This means that I can now loop
over the thumbnails
to process them sequentially.
I can also throw and catch errors,
and the compiler will check
that I didn’t forget.
For an in-depth look at async/await,
check out the session
“Meet async/await in Swift.”
So, this code is great,
but what if you’re producing thumbnails
for thousands of images?
Processing each thumbnail one
at a time is no longer ideal.
Plus, what if each thumbnail’s
dimensions must be downloaded
from another URL,
instead of being a fixed size?
Now there is an opportunity
to add some concurrency,
so multiple downloads
can happen in parallel.
You can create additional tasks
to add concurrency to a program.
Tasks are a new feature in Swift
that work hand-in-hand
with async functions.
A task provides a fresh execution context
to run asynchronous code.
Each task runs concurrently
with respect to other execution contexts.
They will be automatically scheduled
to run in parallel
when it is safe and efficient to do so.
Because tasks
are deeply integrated into Swift,
the compiler can help prevent
some concurrency bugs.
Also, keep in mind
that calling an async function
does not create a new task for the call.
You create tasks explicitly.
There are a few different flavors
of tasks in Swift,
because structured concurrency
is about the balance
between flexibility and simplicity.
So, for the remainder of this session,
Joe and I will introduce
and discuss each kind of task
to help you understand their trade-offs.
Let’s start with the simplest
of these tasks,
which is created with a new syntactic form
called an async-let binding.
To help you understand
this new syntactic form,
I want to first break down the evaluation
of an ordinary let binding.
There are two parts:
the initializer expression
on the right side of the equals
and the variable’s name on the left.
There may be other statements
before or after the let,
so I’ll include those here too.
Once Swift reaches a let binding,
its initializer will be evaluated
to produce a value.
In this example,
that means downloading data from a URL,
which could take a while.
After the data has been downloaded,
Swift will bind that value
to the variable name
before proceeding
to the statements that follow.
Notice that there is only
one flow of execution here,
as traced by the arrows through each step.
Since the download could take a while,
you want the program
to start downloading the data
and keep doing other work
until the data is actually needed.
To achieve this,
you can just add the word async
in front of an existing let binding.
This turns it into a concurrent binding
called an async-let.
The evaluation of a concurrent binding
is quite different from a sequential one,
so let’s learn how it works.
I will start just at the point
before encountering the binding.
To evaluate a concurrent binding,
Swift will first create a new child task,
which is a subtask of the one
that created it.
Because every task represents
an execution context for your program,
two arrows will simultaneously
come out of this step.
This first arrow is for the child task,
which will immediately
begin downloading the data.
The second arrow is for the parent task,
which will immediately bind
the variable result
to a placeholder value.
This parent task is the same one
that was executing
the preceding statements.
While the data is being downloaded
concurrently by the child,
the parent task continues
to execute the statements
that follow the concurrent binding.
But upon reaching an expression
that needs the actual value of the result,
the parent will await
the completion of the child task,
which will fulfill the placeholder
for result.
In this example, our call to URLSession
could also throw an error.
This means that awaiting
the result might give us an error.
So I need to write “try”
to take care of it.
And don’t worry.
Reading the value of result again
will not recompute its value.
Now that you’ve seen how async-let works,
you can use it to add concurrency
to the thumbnail fetching code.
I have factored a piece
of the previous code
that fetches a single image
into its own function.
This new function here
is also downloading data
from two different URLs:
one for the full-sized image itself
and the other for metadata,
which contains the optimal thumbnail size.
Notice that with a sequential binding,
you write “try await”
on the right side of the let,
because that’s where an error
or suspension would be observed.
To make both downloads
happen concurrently,
you write “async”
in front of both of these lets.
Since the downloads
are now happening in child tasks,
you no longer write “try await”
on the right side
of the concurrent binding.
Those effects are only observed
by the parent task
when using the variables
that are concurrently bound.
So you write “try await”
before the expression’s reading
the metadata and the image data.
Also, notice that using
these concurrently bound variables
does not require a method call
or any other changes.
Those variables have the same type
that they did in a sequential binding.
Now, these child tasks
I’ve been talking about
are actually part of a hierarchy
called a task tree.
This tree is not just
an implementation detail.
It’s an important part
of structured concurrency.
It influences the attributes of your tasks
like cancellation, priority,
and task-local variables.
Whenever you make a call
from one async function to another,
the same task is used to execute the call.
So, the function fetchOneThumbnail
inherits all attributes of that task.
When creating a new structured task
like with async-let,
it becomes the child of the task
that the current function is running on.
Tasks are not the child
of a specific function,
but their lifetime may be scoped to it.
The tree is made up of links
between each parent and its child tasks.
A link enforces a rule
that says a parent task
can only finish its work
if all of its child tasks have finished.
This rule holds even in the face
of abnormal control-flow
which would prevent a child task
from being awaited.
For example, in this code,
I first await the metadata task
before the image data task.
If the first awaited task finishes
by throwing an error,
the fetchOneThumbnail function
must immediately exit
by throwing that error.
But what will happen to the task
performing the second download?
During the abnormal exit,
Swift will automatically mark
the unawaited task as canceled
and then await for it to finish
before exiting the function.
Marking a task as canceled
does not stop the task.
It simply informs the task
that its results are no longer needed.
In fact, when a task is canceled,
all subtasks that are decedents
of that task
will be automatically canceled too.
So if the implementation of URLSession
created its own structured tasks
to download the image,
those tasks will be marked
for cancellation.
The function fetchOneThumbnail
finally exits
by throwing the error once
all of the structured tasks it created
directly or indirectly have finished.
This guarantee is fundamental
to structured concurrency.
It prevents you
from accidentally leaking tasks
by helping you manage their lifetimes,
much like how ARC automatically manages
the lifetime of memory.
So far, I have given you an overview
of how cancellation propagates.
But when does the task finally stop?
If the task is in the middle
of an important transaction
or has open network connections,
it would be incorrect
to just halt the task.
That’s why task cancellation
in Swift is cooperative.
Your code must check
for cancellation explicitly
and wind down execution
in whatever way is appropriate.
You can check the cancellation status
of the current task
from any function,
whether it is async or not.
This means that
you should implement your APIs
with cancellation in mind,
especially if they involve
long-running computations.
Your users may call into your code
from a task that can be canceled,
and they will expect
the computation to stop
as soon as possible.
To see how simple it is
to use cooperative cancellation,
let’s go back
to the thumbnail fetching example.
Here, I have rewritten
the original function
that was given all
of the thumbnails to fetch
so that it uses
the fetchOneThumbnail function instead.
If this function was called
within a task that was canceled,
we don’t want to hold up our application
by creating useless thumbnails.
So I can just add a call
to checkCancellation
at the start of each loop iteration.
This call only throws an error
if the current task has been canceled.
You can also obtain the cancellation
status of the current task
as a Boolean value if that
is more appropriate for your code.
Notice that in this version
of the function,
I’m returning a partial result,
a dictionary with only some
of the thumbnails requested.
When doing this,
you must ensure that your API
clearly states that a partial result
may be returned.
Otherwise, task cancellation
could trigger a fatal error for your users
because their code requires
a complete result
even during cancellation.
So far, you’ve seen
that async-let provides
a lightweight syntax
for adding concurrency to your program
while capturing the essence
of structured programming.
The next kind of task I want
to tell you about is called a group task.
They offer more flexibility than async-let
without giving up all of the nice
properties of structured concurrency.
As we saw earlier,
async-let works well
when there’s a fixed amount
of concurrency available.
Let’s consider both functions
that I discussed earlier.
For each thumbnail ID in the loop,
we call fetchOneThumbnail to process it,
which creates exactly two child tasks.
Even if we in-lined the body
of that function into this loop,
the amount of concurrency will not change.
Async-let is scoped
like a variable binding.
That means the two child tasks
must complete
before the next loop iteration begins.
But what if we want this loop
to kick off tasks to fetch
all of the thumbnails concurrently?
Then, the amount of concurrency
is not known statically
because it depends on the number
of IDs in the array.
The right tool for this situation
is a task group.
A task group is a form
of structured concurrency
that is designed to provide
a dynamic amount of concurrency.
You can introduce a task group
by calling the withThrowingTaskGroup
function.
This function gives you
a scoped group object
to create child tasks
that are allowed to throw errors.
Tasks added to a group
cannot outlive the scope
of the block in which
the group is defined.
Since I have placed
the entire for-loop inside of the block,
I can now create a dynamic number
of tasks using the group.
You create child tasks in a group
by invoking its async method.
Once added to a group,
child tasks begin executing immediately
and in any order.
When the group object goes out of scope,
the completion of all tasks
within it will be implicitly awaited.
This is a consequence
of the task tree rule I described earlier,
because group tasks are structured too.
At this point, we’ve already achieved
the concurrency that we wanted:
one task for each call
to fetchOneThumbnail,
which itself will create
two more tasks using async-let.
That’s another nice property
of structured concurrency.
You can use async-let within group tasks
or create task groups
within async-let tasks,
and the levels of concurrency
in the tree compose naturally.
Now, this code is not quite ready to run.
If we tried to run it,
the compiler would helpfully alert us
to a data race issue.
The problem is that we’re trying
to insert a thumbnail
into a single dictionary
from each child task.
This is a common mistake when increasing
the amount of concurrency in your program.
Data races are accidentally created.
This dictionary cannot handle
more than one access at a time,
and if two child tasks tried
to insert thumbnails simultaneously,
that could cause a crash
or data corruption.
In the past, you had to investigate
those bugs yourself,
but Swift provides static checking
to prevent those bugs
from happening in the first place.
Whenever you create a new task,
the work that the task performs
is within a new closure type
called a @Sendable closure.
The body of a @Sendable closure
is restricted
from capturing mutable variables
in its lexical context,
because those variables could be modified
after the task is launched.
This means that the values you capture
in a task must be safe to share.
For example, because they are value types,
like Int and String,
or because they are objects designed
to be accessed from multiple threads,
like actors, and classes
that implement their own synchronization.
We have a whole session
dedicated to this topic,
called “Protect mutable state
with Swift actors,”
so I encourage you to check it out.
To avoid the data race in our example,
you can have each child task
return a value.
This design gives the parent task
the sole responsibility
of processing the results.
In this case,
I specified that each child task
must return a tuple
containing the String ID
and UIImage for the thumbnail.
Then, inside each child task,
instead of writing
to the dictionary directly,
I have them return the key value tuple
for the parent to process.
The parent task can iterate
through the results
from each child task
using the new for-await loop.
The for-await loop obtains
the results from the child tasks
in order of completion.
Because this loop runs sequentially,
the parent task can safely add
each key value pair to the dictionary.
This is just one example
of using the for-await loop
to access
an asynchronous sequence of values.
If your own type conforms
to the AsyncSequence protocol,
then you can use for-await
to iterate through them too.
You can find out more
in the “Meet AsyncSequence” session.
While task groups are a form
of structured concurrency,
there is a small difference
in how the task tree rule is implemented
for group tasks versus async-let tasks.
Suppose when iterating
through the results of this group,
I encounter a child task
that completed with an error.
Because that error is thrown
out of the group’s block,
all tasks in the group
will then be implicitly canceled
and then awaited.
This works just like async-let.
The difference comes
when your group goes out of scope
through a normal exit from the block.
Then, cancellation is not implicit.
This behavior makes it easier for you
to express the fork-join pattern
using a task group,
because the jobs will only be awaited,
not canceled.
You can also manually cancel all tasks
before exiting the block
using the group’s cancelAll method.
Keep in mind that no matter
how you cancel a task,
cancellation automatically
propagates down the tree.
Async-let and group tasks
are the two kind of tasks
that provide scoped structured tasks
in Swift.
Now, I’ll hand things off to Joe,
who will tell you
about unstructured tasks.
[Joe] Thanks, Kavon.
Hi.
I’m Joe.
Kavon showed you how structured
concurrency simplifies error propagation,
cancellation, and other bookkeeping
when you add concurrency to a program
with a clear hierarchy to the tasks.
But we know that you
don’t always have a hierarchy
when you’re adding tasks to your program.
Swift also provides
unstructured task APIs,
which give you a lot more flexibility
at the expense of needing
a lot more manual management.
There are a lot of situations where a task
might not fall into a clear hierarchy.
Most obviously,
you might not have a parent task at all
if you’re trying to launch a task
to do async computation
from non-async code.
Alternatively,
the lifetime you want for a task
might not fit the confines
of a single scope
or even a single function.
You may, for instance,
want to start a task
in response to a method call
that puts an object into an active state
and then cancel its execution
in response to a different method call
that deactivates the object.
This comes up a lot
when implementing delegate objects
in AppKit and UIKit.
UI work has to happen on the main thread,
and as the Swift actors session discusses,
Swift ensures this by declaring UI classes
that belong to the main actor.
Let’s say we have a collection view,
and we can’t yet use
the collection view data source APIs.
Instead, we want to use
our fetchThumbnails function we just wrote
to grab thumbnails from the network
as the items in the collection view
are displayed.
However, the delegate method is not async,
so we can’t just await a call
to an async function.
We need to start a task for that,
but that task is really an extension
of the work we started
in response to the delegate action.
We want this new task to still run
on the main actor with UI priority.
We just don’t want to bound
the lifetime of the task
to the scope
of this single delegate method.
For situations like this,
Swift allows us to construct
an unstructured task.
Let’s move that asynchronous part
of the code into a closure
and pass that closure
to construct an async task.
Now here’s what happens at runtime.
When we reach the point
of creating the task,
Swift will schedule it to run on the same
actor as the originating scope,
which is the main actor in this case.
Meanwhile, control returns
immediately to the caller.
The thumbnail task will run
on the main thread
when there’s an opening to do so
without immediately blocking
the main thread on the delegate method.
Constructing tasks this way
gives us a halfway point
between structured and unstructured code.
A directly constructed task
still inherits the actor,
if any, of its launched context,
and it also inherits the priority
and other traits of the origin task,
just like a group task
or an async-let would.
However, the new task is unscoped.
Its lifetime is not bound by the scope
of where it was launched.
The origin doesn’t even need to be async.
We can create an unscoped task anywhere.
In trade for all of this flexibility,
we must also manually manage the things
that structured concurrency
would have handled automatically.
Cancellation and errors
won’t automatically propagate,
and the task’s result
will not be implicitly awaited
unless we take explicit action to do so.
So we kicked off a task
to fetch thumbnails
when a collection view item is displayed,
and we should also cancel that task
if the item is scrolled out of view
before the thumbnails are ready.
Since we’re working with an unscoped task,
that cancellation isn’t automatic.
Let’s implement it now.
After we construct the task,
let’s save the value we get.
We can put this value into a dictionary
keyed by the row index
when we create the task
so that we can use it later
to cancel that task.
We should also remove it
from the dictionary once the task finishes
so we don’t try to cancel a task
if it’s already finished.
Note here that we can access
the same dictionary
inside and outside of that async task
without getting a data race flagged
by the compiler.
Our delegate class is bound
to the main actor,
and the new task inherits that,
so they’ll never run together in parallel.
We can safely access the stored properties
of main actor-bound classes
inside this task without worrying
about data races.
Meanwhile, if our delegate is later told
that the same table row
has been removed from the display,
then we can call the cancel method
on the value to cancel the task.
So now we’ve seen
how we can create unstructured tasks
that run independent of a scope
while still inheriting traits
from that task’s originating context.
But sometimes you don’t want
to inherit anything
from your originating context.
For maximum flexibility,
Swift provides detached tasks.
Like the name suggests,
detached tasks are independent
from their context.
They're still unstructured tasks.
Their lifetimes are not bound
to their originating scope.
But detached tasks
don’t pick anything else up
from their originating scope either.
By default,
they aren’t constrained to the same actor
and don’t have to run at the same priority
as where they were launched.
Detached tasks run independently
with generic defaults
for things like priority,
but they can also be launched
with optional parameters
to control how
and where the new task gets executed.
Let’s say that after we fetch
thumbnails from the server,
we want to write them
to a local disk cache
so we don’t hit the network again
if we try to fetch them later.
The caching doesn’t need
to happen on the main actor,
and even if we cancel fetching
all of the thumbnails,
it’s still helpful to cache
any thumbnails we did fetch.
So let’s kick off caching
by using a detached task.
When we detach a task,
we also get a lot more flexibility
in setting up how that new task executes.
Caching should happen at a lower priority
that doesn’t interfere with the main UI,
and we can specify background priority
when we detach this new task.
Let’s plan ahead for a moment now.
What should we do in the future
if we have multiple background tasks
we want to perform on our thumbnails?
We could detach more background tasks,
but we could also utilize
structured concurrency
inside of our detached task.
We can combine all
of the different kinds of tasks together
to exploit each of their strengths.
Instead of detaching an independent task
for every background job,
we can set up a task group
and spawn each background job
as a child task into that group.
There are a number of benefits
of doing so.
If we do need to cancel
the background task in the future,
using a task group means
we can cancel all of the child tasks
just by canceling
that top level detached task.
That cancellation will then propagate
to the child tasks automatically,
and we don’t need to keep track
of an array of handles.
Furthermore, child tasks
automatically inherit
the priority of their parent.
To keep all of this work
in the background,
we only need to background
the detached task,
and that will automatically propagate
to all of its child tasks,
so we don’t need
to worry about forgetting
to transitively set background priority
and accidentally starving UI work.
At this point,
we’ve seen all of the primary forms
of tasks there are in Swift.
Async-let allows
for a fixed number of child tasks
to be spawned as variable bindings,
with automatic management
of cancellation and error propagation
if the binding goes out of scope.
When we need a dynamic number
of child tasks
that are still bounded to a scope,
we can move up to task groups.
If we need to break off some work
that isn’t well scoped
but which is still related
to its originating task,
we can construct unstructured tasks,
but we need to manually manage those.
And for maximum flexibility,
we also have detached tasks,
which are manually managed tasks
that don’t inherit anything
from their origin.
Tasks and structured concurrency
are just one part
of the suite of concurrency features
Swift supports.
Be sure to check out
all these other great talks
to see how it fits in
with the rest of the language.
“Meet async/await in Swift”
gives you more details
about async functions,
which gives us the structured basis
for writing concurrent code.
Actors provide data isolation
to create concurrent systems
that are safe from data races.
See the “Protect mutable state
with Swift actors” session
to learn more about how.
We saw “for await” loops on task groups,
and those are just one example
of AsyncSequence,
which provides a standard interface
for working
with asynchronous streams of data.
The “Meet AsyncSequence” session
goes deeper
into the available APIs
for working with sequences.
Tasks integrate with the core OS
to achieve low overhead
and high scalability,
and the “Swift concurrency:
Behind the scenes” session
gives more technical details
about how that’s accomplished.
All these features come together
to make writing concurrent code
in Swift easy and safe,
letting you write code that gets the most
out of your devices
while still focusing
on the interesting parts of your app,
thinking less about the mechanics
of managing concurrent tasks
or the worries of potential bugs
caused by multithreading.
Thank you for watching.
I hope you enjoy the rest
of the conference.
[upbeat music]