[music]
[Jacob] Hi, I'm Jacob,
and welcome
to "Add Rich Graphics
to Your SwiftUI App."
I'm working on an app
to build gradients
with a few of my colleagues.
This year, colors are
the hot thing on our team.
Most of the implementation
is already done.
Now I just need to finish it
by adding some rich graphics.
As we customize the app,
we're going to see
a few different areas:
working with the safe area,
including customizing it;
new foreground style support;
a rich new set of materials;
and drawing with Canvas,
a powerful new view.
So let's get started.
I'll show you
what's in the app so far.
We have a library of gradients,
and I can view those gradients.
There's something
about this one I really like.
I just can't
put my finger on it.
I can also edit a gradient...
which lets me
change the color stops.
And I can add a new gradient.
I can also use these gradients
in some visualizers...
But one step at a time.
We'll look at those a bit later.
For now,
let's focus
on this gradient detail view.
It's functional,
but our actual content
is pretty small
relative to the chrome
and empty space.
I want the gradient to really
take over for this screen.
So let's
start editing it in Xcode.
This is our main detail view,
and it's used for
our editing mode as well.
Let's start
with isEditing false,
and we'll look
at the editing mode later.
Let's make our gradient use
as much of the space as possible
by deleting this frame.
And now that the gradient
is taking up
all of the height,
we no longer need this spacer.
We can go even further
by putting our controls
on top of this gradient
by changing this to a ZStack.
If you haven't seen
a ZStack before,
it lays elements out
on top of each other
instead of next to each other.
Let's move our editing controls
to the bottom.
And we only need padding
on the controls,
not on our gradient...
so let's move this.
You may be wondering
why there's still empty space
at the top
and bottom of the gradient,
even after
we've removed the padding.
By default,
SwiftUI positions your content
within the safe area,
avoiding anything that would
obscure or clip your view,
like the Home indicator
or any bars
that are being shown.
The safe area is represented
as a region that is inset
from the outermost full area
where a view is shown.
Content in the safe area
is automatically laid out
within the appropriate insets
to avoid those areas
where it would be obscured.
The safe area is also
how SwiftUI helps you avoid
drawing content
under the keyboard.
So in our app,
our controls will
automatically lift
out of the way of the keyboard.
This works the same way,
and if we look
more closely at how,
it's because there are multiple
different safe areas.
The most common one
is the container safe area,
which is driven by the container
a view is shown within
and includes things like bars
and device chrome.
Additionally,
there is a keyboard safe area
for avoiding the keyboard.
And note
that the keyboard safe area
is always a region within
the container safe area.
It keeps content safe
from the same areas
as the container safe area
in addition to the keyboard.
It's possible
to opt out of safe areas.
Usually
you won't need to do this,
since most content should be
within the safe area
so it isn't clipped.
It is safe, after all.
But ignoring the safe area
can make sense
for backgrounds or other content
that you want to go
fully edge to edge.
You can use this code
to opt out of all safe areas
or specify the keyboard region
to just opt out
of the keyboard safe area.
Let's add ignoresSafeArea
to our linear gradient
to get that full-bleed effect.
This Edit button isn't very
visible on top of our gradient,
so let's only ignore the safe
area on the bottom edge.
Now, to make sure we don't
run into the same problem
with this bottom text
being illegible
from the gradient,
let's add
a background behind it.
We'll customize
the background in a minute,
but let's start
with the most simple default,
which gives us
a white background
that automatically changes
in Dark Mode.
And this background
also extends
beyond the safe area
automatically.
This version of background
and its behavior
is new in iOS 15
and aligned OS releases.
Let's look at how it works.
Let's start
with a container view
and its safe area.
Then we have our content view,
which will just be within
the safe area
to keep it legible.
If we naively added a background
with the same bounds
to the view it's applied to,
we'd get this.
But if we apply
the ignoresSafeArea modifier
to just the background view,
then it will expand beyond
the safe area
while keeping the main content
nice and safe.
The new background modifier
gives you this behavior
automatically.
Let's go back to our background
and start customizing it.
We can pass in a specific style,
which could be a color
or any other style,
like a gradient.
It doesn't really make sense
in this app,
but let's look at something
pastel colored.
I can also pass in a shape
to clip this background to...
For example,
a rounded rectangle.
Notice that
when I use a custom shape,
the background no longer extends
out of the safe area
so that the shape matches
your content's bounds.
What I think would fit
our app better
is a blur for our background.
We can use another new API
to do that: Materials.
Materials are a set of standard
blur styles that you can apply.
And let's make
this background go back
to taking up the whole area.
Materials are great for places
where we want to show through
colorful content like this.
There's a set of different
materials you can choose from,
going from Ultra Thin
to Ultra Thick.
And all of these
automatically show
the right design
on every platform.
I'm going to use
a thin material here.
Next, I want to customize
our text.
Let's make
the number of colors
a little less prominent
to show that the name
is the primary information here.
I can do that by setting
a foreground style of secondary.
You may have noticed
that the secondary content
is automatically shown
with an effect called Vibrancy,
which blends
the colors behind it.
In SwiftUI, there's no extra API
for this effect.
It happens automatically
when you use the new Secondary
through Quaternary styles
in a material context.
That can happen when
you explicitly add a background
with a material,
like we just did,
or when your content
is in a system component,
like a sidebar,
that adds the material for you.
And these styles have
a lot of automatic smarts.
They automatically do
the right thing
when used in
a non-blurred context as well,
where they don't use
a vibrant effect.
They also automatically
change their behavior
as you set a color on them,
setting versions
of the color for each level.
And the same support works
for setting
any base foreground style,
even things like gradients.
Please use tastefully.
One thing to note:
Any given text can have a single
foreground style applied to it,
but multiple colors
within its ranges.
So for example,
I could use string interpolation
to embed an inner Text...
And then apply
a foregroundColor of red...
to the word "colors."
And it will show that color,
automatically opting out
of vibrancy for that range.
Even more importantly,
with these foreground styles,
for the first time ever,
you get the right behavior
with embedded emoji,
where they just work.
This is looking good.
Let's run it again
and try out Edit mode
with these changes too.
It mostly works already.
And these colors go under
the blur, which is great.
But if you look closely,
it's not doing
quite the right thing.
When I scroll all the way down,
there's a little bit of the list
that's hidden behind the blur.
Let's look more closely
at what's happening.
Let's take away the chrome
and only look
at the relevant views, here.
If we slide these views apart
a bit horizontally,
we can see
this is because the bar
is just ZStacked
on top of our content.
Now that we want to see
all of the view in the back,
that's not
the right behavior.
We could change
to a VStack here,
but without the list
under the blur,
we wouldn't get any
of the color showing through
when scrolling down.
We want
the background of the list
and its scrollable area
to extend under the bar
but not its main content.
And this is exactly
what the safe area is for.
If we make the safe area
get inset by this bar,
then any important content
will stay unobscured.
To customize the safe area
of our own views,
we can use a new modifier:
safeAreaInset.
This lets us add
auxiliary content,
like our bar,
over the main content.
I'll replace our ZStack...
With a safeAreaInset...
Using an edge of.bottom...
And put our controls into that.
Let's run it again to check.
This view still looks the same,
which is good.
That's because
it's ignoring the safe area.
And in Edit mode...
We can still scroll
under the bar to get that blur.
But when we scroll
to the bottom,
nothing is obscured.
Great.
Next,
let's look at our visualizers.
Let's start
with the Shapes visualizer,
which is already written.
It shows a large number
of random shape symbols,
each drawn with one
of the gradients from the app.
I can tap on a symbol
to zoom it up...
Or tap in the background to
reposition all of the symbols.
And if you've seen our SwiftUI
animation demos before,
you know that it's always
interactive and interruptible.
So I can keep rearranging...
And even tap to select
and deselect shapes
while that's happening.
If I go look at the code...
It's using a common technique
for drawing graphics in SwiftUI.
There's a GeometryReader
so I can read
the view's size
to lay out all of these graphics
and a ZStack
to help me position them.
And at the end of the body,
there's a modifier you may have
seen before: drawingGroup.
A drawingGroup tells SwiftUI
to combine all of the views
it contains
in a single layer to draw.
This works well
for graphical elements
like these
but shouldn't be used
with UI controls
like text fields and lists.
This is a great technique to use
when you want to show a large
number of graphical elements
like we're doing here.
And one of the benefits
of drawingGroup
is that even though these views
are drawn differently,
you can still use the same
functionality from SwiftUI
that you use everywhere else
in your app.
For example, here,
we have a gesture applied
to each symbol
for tapping on them
and also an animation
that applies when we change
selection or reposition them.
The accessibility information
contained in these views
is also passed up normally--
for example, these accessibility
actions on each symbol.
However, to support
all of these features,
there is some bookkeeping
and storage required
for each view.
If you have a high enough
number of elements,
then even that extra overhead
might be too much.
And for those cases,
we've introduced
a new Canvas view.
Our next visualizer
will show
a complex particle system,
and it isn't written yet.
Let's go build it.
Let's start with
our Canvas view to draw it.
This lets us make a closure
that's run every time
the canvas is drawn
and contains
our drawing commands.
If you're familiar
with drawRect in UIKit
or AppKit,
this works pretty similarly.
This closure gives us a context,
which is what we send
drawing commands to,
and a size that we can use
to get the size
of the entire canvas.
Let's start by just
drawing an image.
I can create one
using the same Image type
I use in the rest
of my SwiftUI code.
And let's tell the context
to draw our image.
When we draw it at 0,0,
it's up here,
centered at the origin,
where it's not very visible.
Since we have the size
of the whole canvas available,
let's use that to draw it
in the middle instead.
And one thing you can see
if I change our preview
to be in Dark Mode...
Is that our image automatically
flips to draw in white,
since it's using the same
foreground style
that we saw earlier.
Since we want to build
a particle system,
let's draw this image
a few more times.
Note that this closure
is for imperative code.
It's not a ViewBuilder.
So I can
just use a normal for loop.
And let's shift each image a bit
so we can actually see them.
Now, we're drawing
this image several times,
but each time,
the context needs to resolve it
to evaluate it
based on things
like the current environment,
even though each time,
it's the same image.
We can improve this
by resolving the image ourselves
before drawing it.
Now we have better performance
because we're sharing
the same resolved image,
but the resolved image also
lets us do some other things.
We can now ask
for its size and baseline.
In our case,
we'll use its size to shift
each one by the right amount.
Next, let's add ellipses
behind our sparkles.
I'm going to draw them
in the same region.
So let's pull out a frame
to draw them both in.
I'll create a CGRect
with the same X and Y values
and use our imageSize
for the width and height...
Then draw our image
in that frame.
Because each drawing operation
is done in order,
to put our ellipse
behind the image,
we need to draw it first.
And we can draw it
with context.fill...
Which takes a path
and a shading.
You can construct a path
with standard bezier curves,
but here's a tip:
You can also use shapes
like ellipse
and ask them for their path
in a given rectangle.
The other argument is a shading,
which is what
to fill our path with.
And this can use the same styles
as the rest of our SwiftUI app.
Let's use a cyan color.
And there are the ellipses.
There's not a lot of contrast
with the images, though.
Let's fix that.
Graphics context has many
standard drawing properties,
like opacity, blend modes,
transforms, and more.
Let's set an opacity here.
And we can look at an area
where this context behaves
a little differently
from what you might be used to.
If I just set an opacity
on the context,
then it behaves as you'd expect.
It affects all operations
that happen afterwards.
In the past,
if I wanted to make a change
to a graphics context
only applied to some
of my drawing operations,
I would have to bracket
those operations
in a save and restore call.
But with a SwiftUI context,
all I have to do is make changes
on a copy.
And those changes only affect
drawing done
with the modified context.
Drawing done on the original
context is unaffected.
Let's add some color
to our image too.
One other thing we can do
with a resolved image
is set a shading to control
how symbols are drawn.
Let's set a blue color here.
That looks a little less bright
than I was hoping for.
Sometimes when you're drawing,
the right blend mode
can make a big difference.
Blend modes control
how colors are combined,
especially with partial opacity,
like we have here.
Let's set a screen blend mode.
That combines colors so that
they always get brighter.
That's looks better.
There are many more
drawing operations you can do.
Check out
the GraphicsContext type
to see everything
that's possible.
Now, to make this
like a simulation,
it needs to actually move.
There are a few tools
to make something change
over time in SwiftUI.
Animations are the most common,
and they generally just
happen automatically
when you make a change.
This year,
we're introducing a new
lower-level tool
called TimelineView
for when you want to control
exactly how something changes
over time.
I can use a TimelineView
by just wrapping it
around the view
that I want to change.
And I can configure it
with a schedule,
which tells it
how often to update.
There are schedules
for things like timers,
but we're going to use
an animation schedule
to get updates as quickly
as we can display them.
If you're familiar
with a display link,
this works very similarly.
And if you're not,
that's totally OK.
We get passed
a timeline context
that gives us information
about what we should show.
I can pull out
a time in seconds
that we'll use
to animate our images around.
Let's make our images move
in a rotating oscillation.
So I'll make an angle
from the current time.
Let's have it loop
every three seconds
by using a remainder...
And multiply that by 120
to get 360 degrees.
And we'll get the X value
with cosine.
Or was it sine?
I hope you remember
your trigonometry.
Now let's use that value
to change our offset...
And take our previews live
to see how it looks.
Nice.
See how when they overlap,
they get even brighter?
That's our screen blend mode
at work.
Next,
let's add some interactivity.
Earlier, we looked at some
of the interactions we can do
by adding gestures
to individual views.
Remember that one
of the tradeoffs
of using a canvas
is that the individual elements
within it
are combined
into a single drawing.
So we couldn't,
for example,
attach a gesture
to these individual images.
However, we can still add
a gesture to the entire view.
Let's add the ability
to increase the number
of sparkles shown.
We'll add some state
for how many to show.
And let's have it start
with two.
Let's use the count
to control our loop.
Then we'll add a TapGesture
to increment the count.
Let's update our preview.
And now we can
tap to add sparkles.
One other important aspect
of using a canvas
is that,
since it's a single graphic,
there's not any information
about its contents
available to Accessibility.
To make this accessible,
we'll use the standard
accessibility modifiers
to add information
about our view.
And for more advanced cases,
there's a powerful new
.accessibilityChildren modifier
that lets you specify
an arbitrary SwiftUI
view hierarchy
to use to generate accessibility
information about a view.
See "SwiftUI Accessibility:
Beyond the Basics"
for more information
on how to use that.
We've built up a relatively
simple use of Canvas,
but it's designed to support
much more complex uses,
so let's spice things up a bit.
One of my colleagues wrote
some simulation code for me
that works the same way
as what we have here,
but with a lot more elements
doing more interesting things.
I have the file he sent me here
that I'll just paste
into our view.
This code has the same structure
as what we were just doing.
We now have
a long-lived model object
that we're updating over time
that keeps track
of all of our particles.
We have
the same TimelineView and Canvas
to animate and draw our content.
We're updating our model
with the new date,
setting that screen blend mode,
and telling each active particle
to draw itself
the same way as the ellipse
that we just had.
And finally, we have
the same modifiers applied,
just with a slightly
more complex gesture.
So let's see what it looks like.
It creates a new
fireworks burst periodically,
and we can also tap
to add more bursts.
And they're made
using ellipses
with the colors
from the app's gradients.
One other great thing about
drawing in Canvas
is that it also works on
watchOS,
tvOS, and macOS.
It's available
on all SwiftUI platforms.
All right.
We've finished our app.
And along the way,
we looked at working with
and modifying safe areas,
how to use foreground styles
to control how content is drawn,
how to use materials
to get blurs and vibrancy,
and we used Canvas
and TimelineView
to build complex
animated graphics.
I can't wait to see what amazing
graphics you build in your apps.
[music]