[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Kyle Macomber: Hi, I'm Kyle.
The Swift Standard Library team
maintains a growing roster
of open-source packages
including Swift ArgumentParser,
Swift Numerics,
and Swift System.
Today, we're excited
to introduce
two big new additions
to the family:
Swift Algorithms
and Swift Collections!
is an open-source package
of sequence
and collection algorithms
that augments
the Swift standard library.
One of the most powerful
features of Swift
is the rich taxonomy
of algorithms
that come built in.
It takes a little investment
to learn the vocabulary,
but once you do,
it can be striking to discover
just how many algorithms
are hiding in plain sight
and how much you can improve
the quality of your code
by adopting them.
To see what I mean,
let's take a look at some code
from a messaging application
that I've been working on.
Consider this loop which
iterates over the index paths
for the selected rows
in a table view,
collecting all
the corresponding messages
for forwarding or deletion.
This is just a map.
Using map makes this code
clearer to the reader
because it provides
extra context
that the body of the closure,
regardless of its length
or complexity,
is just transforming the input.
Using map also
makes this code faster
because it avoids
intermediate allocations
due to array resizing
by reserving capacity --
something our raw loop
wasn't bothering to do.
Or consider this loop which,
if the user taps on an image,
iterates the messages
in the transcript,
collecting all the attachments
for display using Quick Look.
This is just a map and a filter!
In fact, this pattern
of filtering out nils
and mapping
to unwrap optionals
is so common that
we have a special name
and algorithm for it:
compactMap.
Next, consider this code.
I have an array of messages,
and I want to transform it
into an array
of transcript items.
The tricky thing is that
any given message
might correspond to multiple
items in the chat transcript.
Using map here produces
an array of arrays.
But that's not what I want;
I just want a flat array.
Does this mean I have to go back
to using a raw for loop?
Of course not; we've got
another algorithm for that.
It's called "joined".
What it does is join together
all the inner arrays
into a single, flat collection
of elements.
This pattern of mapping
and joining is so common
that we define another special
kind of map for it: flatMap.
Of course, map and filter
are just the tip of the iceberg.
Consider this raw loop from the
chat detail screen in my app.
I want to display
the last six photos in a chat,
from newest to oldest.
So I iterate the transcript
in reverse --
from newest to oldest --
and if the item is a photo,
I add it to the array.
And once I have six, I stop.
We can express this
more concisely
by chaining together algorithms
from the standard library --
reversed, compactMap,
and prefix --
to take no more
than the first six.
Chaining together algorithms
also gives us more flexibility
to express this code
more clearly.
For example, I find it
more natural to think about
this operation in terms
of the suffix of the transcript
rather than the prefix
of the reversed transcript.
So the chain of algorithms
is clearer and more concise
than the raw loop,
but how does
the performance compare?
If each step in the chain
allocates an intermediate array,
isn't it going to be slower
than the raw loop?
The answer would be yes
if the standard library
weren't playing
some clever tricks here.
Let's return to the
joined algorithm we saw earlier
to take a closer look
at what's going on.
It turns out joined
doesn't actually allocate
and return a new array here.
Instead, it returns
a FlattenSequence.
FlattenSequence is what
we call a "lazy adapter".
For most purposes,
it works like an array,
but it's just a thin wrapper,
so it's effectively
free to create.
And it's lazy, so it processes
its elements on demand,
rather than doing
all the work up front.
Lazy adapters
like FlattenSequence
are what enable algorithm chains
to have competitive performance
with raw for loops.
Let's return to the detail
screen and take a closer look
at our algorithm to compute
the last six photos in a chat.
We see that suffix actually
just returns an array slice --
that's clever --
and that reversed is also
implemented as a lazy adapter,
one which intercedes
to start at the end
and end at the start.
What about compactMap?
It's still returning an array.
Can that be lazy?
It can.
You just have to add a .lazy
to the start of the chain,
and it makes any of the
algorithms that take a closure,
like map and filter, lazy!
Lazy algorithm chains
are a great fit
for use cases like this one,
where you're only processing
a small number of elements
from a potentially
very large collection.
Of course, sometimes you do need
or want an array.
And in that case, you can always
just wrap your algorithm chain
in an array initializer.
This is one more reason why,
on the Standard Library team,
we're a big fan
of lazy algorithms.
It's really easy to turn a lazy
algorithm into an eager result,
but it's impossible
to go the other way.
So I've been making great
progress on my messaging app,
and my designer approaches me
with a feature request.
They'd like to include
time stamps in the transcript,
if more than an hour has passed
between any two
consecutive messages.
Seems reasonable.
There's got to be another
algorithm I can use for this,
right?
There is.
But to access it,
I'm going to need to import
the Swift Algorithms package.
Every once in a while,
you're going to encounter
use cases like these
that the Swift standard library
doesn't have coverage for yet.
The purpose of the Algorithms
package is to provide
a low-friction venue for us --
with your help --
to incubate new families
of missing algorithms
for eventual inclusion
in the standard library.
We've already added over 40
algorithms to Swift Algorithms.
For things like generating
all the combinations
or permutations
of a collection of elements;
or iterating the elements
of a sequence
by two or three or in groups
determined by a predicate;
or selecting the five smallest
elements in a collection,
the five largest,
or just any five at random.
Let's take a closer look at some
of the powerful iteration tools
that come with Swift Algorithms.
windows(ofCount:)
provides a sliding window,
here of size 3, into the
elements of a collection.
For each turn of the loop,
window is just a subsequence
of the base collection --
here an ArraySlice --
which avoids any intermediate
allocation.
windows(ofCount: 2)
are particularly common
and so we have
a convenience for it.
It's called "adjacentPairs".
adjacentPairs vends a tuple
rather than a subsequence,
allowing for more convenient
element access.
Another powerful iteration tool
is chunks(ofCount:).
Unlike windows,
chunks don't overlap.
If a collection isn't evenly
divisible by the chunk count,
the last chunk in the sequence
will contain the remainder.
And just like windows,
chunks are subsequences
of the base collection,
so they're cheap to create.
Sometimes you want
to chunk a collection
into runs of like-elements.
Here we're chunking
on isPrime.
This means we'll iterate the
chunks of consecutive elements
that return the same value
for isPrime.
For convenience, chunked(on:)
vends a tuple of both the chunk
and the value being chunked on.
Have you ever found yourself
writing a raw loop
like this one
that only does some work
if the previous
and current elements differ?
This is just chunked!
Let's return now to that feature
request from my designer
to include time stamps
in the transcript
whenever more than an hour
has passed between messages.
If you recall,
we create the transcript
by flat mapping
over the messages
to make the transcript items.
Well, every transcript item
has access to its date.
We can chunk on the date
to group transcript items
together
if less than an hour has passed
between them.
We've already seen
how to chunk a collection
into runs of like elements.
Swift Algorithms comes with
another variant of chunked
that allows you to provide
a custom predicate.
It passes you adjacent pairs
of elements,
and you return true if they
belong in the same group.
Here, we return true
if the time interval
between transcript items
is less than an hour.
Next, we need to create
the time stamps
and join everything together
into a single, flat collection.
Earlier, we used joined
to flatten a nested collection.
The standard library comes with
another variant of joined
that can insert a separator.
It's really common to use
this algorithm to join together
strings with, say, a new line
or a comma separator.
However, in this case,
a constant separator
isn't sufficient.
We need access to the first date
in the next chunk
in order to construct
the time stamp.
Well, the Algorithms package
includes another variant
of joined that lets you
compute the separator
from the previous
and next chunks.
We can use that here
to join back together
the chunks of transcript items,
now separated by time stamps.
Pretty satisfying, huh?
Of course, we don't need
to be paying
for any of these
intermediate allocations.
All of this can be computed
on demand
just by adding a .lazy.
Voilà!
I want to caution, though, that
laziness is not a silver bullet.
When you're only iterating
a sequence a single time,
computing on demand can save
work and avoid allocations.
But when you're iterating
a sequence again and again --
like I am with the transcript
in my messaging app --
computing on demand will repeat
the same work over and over --
mapping, chunking, and joining
every time the user
enters edit mode,
taps on an image,
or visits the detail screen.
In cases like this,
you should still use
a lazy algorithm chain.
It's just that as a last step,
it'll be more efficient
if you save your work
by collecting everything
together into an array.
We've looked at over a dozen
different algorithms
from the Swift standard library
and the Algorithms package.
All of them work
not only on array,
but also string,
and every other Swift type
that conforms to the sequence
and collection protocols --
including every data structure
in the new
Swift Collections package.
Chaining together algorithms
makes your code clearer,
faster, and more correct.
And becoming proficient at it
isn't complicated;
it's just about building
your vocabulary.
So next time you find yourself
reading or writing a raw loop,
stop and think about
if it's a map, a filter,
or one of the other algorithms
you've just seen.
If nothing comes to mind,
search the documentation
on the sequence
and collection protocols,
or read the guides in the Swift
Algorithms GitHub repository,
or visit us on the Swift forums
where we can figure it out
together.
Who knows, it might serve
as the inspiration
for a new addition
to the Algorithms package!
Next up, Karoy will teach you
about the versatile
data structures
that come with the new
Swift Collections package.
Karoy?
Karoy Lorentey: Thanks, Kyle!
Let's talk about
data structures.
As it stands today,
the Swift standard library
implements just three major
general-purpose data structures:
it provides arrays,
unordered sets,
and unordered dictionaries.
These have proved great choices
as universal collection types,
and they're especially nice
for transferring data
across module boundaries.
They all implement
copy-on-write value semantics,
providing efficient in-place
mutation operations
while also ensuring that
collection values
are safe to pass around
without these mutations
leading to unexpected changes
in any of the copies created.
However, there are so many more
data structures out there.
It would be useful to have a
larger selection to choose from.
Earlier this year, we released
the Swift Collections package,
with new data structure
implementations.
This package lets
Swift developers
gain real-life production
experience
with new collection types before
we eventually propose them
for inclusion in the Swift
standard library.
By importing the
Swift Collections package,
we get access
to additional types.
The initial version
of the package implements
three of the most frequently
requested data structures.
These happen
to be new variations
of the three
standard collection types.
We have a double-ended queue,
an OrderedSet,
and an OrderedDictionary.
These are similar to array,
set, and dictionary;
they are variants
of the same theme,
adding new features
to the existing constructs.
That said, these new types
aren't replacements
for the existing ones;
they are complementary to them.
For some use cases,
the new types
will be a better fit.
However, for many others,
the existing types continue
to be the right choice.
In order to know which
data structure to reach for,
we need to learn how these
differ from the existing types.
So let's take a brief look
at each of these,
starting with
double-ended queues --
or, rather, queues in general.
Queues pop up everywhere where
an arbitrary number of items
need to be processed
one by one,
from customers waiting in line
in a supermarket
to asynchronous tasks
in an application.
In their most abstract form,
queues provide
two major operations:
we can push items
to the back of the queue,
and we can pop elements
off the front.
A double-ended queue makes these
queue operations symmetric.
It supports efficiently
pushing new items
to the front of the queue...
...as well as popping elements
off the back.
The name "double-ended queue"
is quite a mouthful
for such a useful type,
so we like to shorten
it to "deque".
And to shave off
one more syllable,
this is traditionally
pronounced "deck",
like a deck of cards.
In the Collections package,
deque has roughly the same API
as the familiar array type,
and it implements many
of the same protocols.
For example, we can use an
array literal to create a deque.
Deque conforms to the
RandomAccessCollection protocol.
Like array, deque uses
integer indices that are offsets
measured from the start
of the collection.
This makes it easy to access any
element based on its position.
For example,
the element at index 1
in this deque is the letter E.
Now, I'm sure I'm not
the only one who is bothered
by that lowercase f
at the end of this collection.
Luckily, deque conforms to the
MutableCollection protocol,
so we can fix this by assigning
through the index 2,
replacing the lowercase f
with an uppercase one.
Ah, that looks so much better!
Deque also implements
the RangeReplaceableCollection
protocol,
so it provides all of
the familiar operations
for inserting, removing, or
replacing subranges of elements.
For example,
we can insert a sequence
at the front of our deque
by calling
the insert(contentsOf:) method
with an index of zero.
How it executes this
is where deque starts to differ
from an array.
If we used an array
to store our items,
then inserting new elements
at the front
would need to start by moving
the existing elements
to make room for the new ones.
To make accesses
as simple as possible,
arrays keep their elements
in a single contiguous buffer,
starting at the beginning
of their storage.
If the array is large,
this makes prepending new
elements relatively expensive;
so inserting a new element
at the front takes time
that is roughly proportional
to the number of elements
that are already in the array.
A deque works differently.
It wraps its storage buffer
around its boundaries
so that it can prepend
new elements
without moving
any of the existing ones.
The indices are still offsets
from the logical start
of the collection,
so after the insertion, the
element at index 1 is now B.
This means that deques
need to do some work
to translate between
their logical indices
and their actual
storage positions,
but accessing elements
is still quite efficient.
And because prepending
to a deque doesn't involve
sliding any existing members,
they are able to perform
this operation
radically faster than array.
Inserting a new element
at the front
takes a constant amount of time,
no matter how many elements
are already in the collection.
This is the power
of data structures.
Once we have them
in our toolbox,
we can use them
to solve problems
that were previously
out of reach.
Switching to the right
data structure
can make all the difference.
It can turn an unusably slow app
into a responsive wonder
that is a joy to use.
Of course,
deques can also be clever
about how they perform
operations
in the middle of their storage.
For instance, when removing
a range of elements,
deque has the option of closing
the resulting gap by
moving the preceding elements
rather than the subsequent ones,
and this can reduce
the number of elements
that need to be moved.
This isn't as drastic
an improvement
as prepending an element was,
but when we are removing
elements at random,
it does make things twice
as fast on average.
So, that's deque.
Now, let's take a look
at ordered sets.
The standard, preexisting
set type is a collection
that guarantees that all
of its elements are unique.
However, it doesn't preserve
their original ordering.
In fact, the order of elements
in a set is effectively random.
This means that two instances
of the same set often list them
in two entirely different
permutations.
Despite this, two sets
containing the same elements
are considered equal;
the order is not significant.
This is great when all we want
is to guarantee uniqueness,
but sometimes we
also want to be in control
of how the elements are ordered.
For example, if we are writing
a to-do list app,
we may want to ensure that
it lists each item only once,
but we also need to keep them
in the specific order
set by the user.
So that is what
an ordered set does.
Depending on our viewpoint,
it works either like an array
that keeps its elements unique,
or we can view it as a set
that preserves the order
we establish on its members.
Like arrays and sets,
ordered sets are also
expressible by array literals.
However, unlike a set,
the order of elements is
guaranteed to be preserved.
The order is also significant;
two ordered sets compare equal
if they contain not
just the same members,
but they must
also be in the same order.
If we just need to know
if two ordered sets
contain the same elements,
in any order,
then we can compare them through
the special unordered view.
This lightweight view
ignores element ordering,
so it provides
a more conventional,
set-like interface.
By default, though, ordered sets
resemble how arrays work.
This is reinforced by
the fact that ordered sets
are random access collections
with integer offset indices.
We can use integer subscripts
to access items,
just like in an array
or a deque.
As expected from a set,
we can also add
and remove elements,
although these operations
do need to take the position
into account.
For instance,
we have an append operation
that adds a new element
to the end of the set
if it isn't already a member.
Its return value indicates
whether the element
needed to be added,
and it also reports
the index of the item.
We also have an insert operation
that puts the new element
at the specified location.
In this case, the letter B
already exists,
so the operation
simply returns the index
of the existing member.
Removing an element leaves
a hole in the ordered set,
and the rest of the members
need to be moved to fill it,
just like in an array.
Ordered sets need to keep
their elements unique,
so they can't support arbitrary
item replacements.
This means that unlike arrays,
they can't conform
to the MutableCollection
or RangeReplaceableCollection
protocols.
However, they do support
standard reordering operations
such as sorting or shuffling.
Ordered sets also implement
all high-level set operations
from the SetAlgebra protocol,
in an order-preserving manner.
For example, forming a union
appends any missing elements,
in the order they appear
in the second set.
Subtracting a set keeps
the remaining elements
in their original order.
Even though the ordered sets
implement most
SetAlgebra operations,
they cannot officially conform
to that protocol
because it requires that
the order of elements
must not matter.
However, their unordered view
has an order-insensitive
concept of equality.
So it can and does conform
to SetAlgebra.
We can use it to pass
OrderedSet values
to any function that requires
a SetAlgebra value.
Looking under the hood,
the standard,
unordered set type
stores its elements
directly in a flat hash table
using a randomly seeded
universal hash function.
This provides great lookup
performance for the elements,
but it discards
their original ordering.
To support arbitrary,
user-specified
element orderings,
an ordered set
stores its elements
in a regular array
instance, instead.
Ordered set still uses
the same fast
and secure hash table
implementation,
but in this case,
the table only needs
to store integer indices
into the storage array.
The range of these integers
is bound by the size
of the hash table,
so we can compress the table
by packing the integer values
into as few bits as possible.
This can sometimes save
a considerable amount of memory
compared to a regular set
while still maintaining
competitive performance
for most operations.
Lookup performance is comparable
to the standard set.
Finding a random member
takes roughly constant time,
no matter the size
of the collection.
Array needs to laboriously
look at each element,
which takes longer time
as the collection grows.
Appending a new element
to an ordered set
also performs roughly comparably
to inserting an element
into a standard set.
This still needs to hash
the new item,
and it also includes a check
if the element already exists,
so this is a far
more complicated operation
than directly appending
an element to a simple array.
But these still take
constant time,
no matter how large
the collections become.
However, while OrderedSet
is able to quickly look up
existing elements
and append new ones,
it cannot efficiently implement
removing or inserting an item
at the front or middle
of the set.
Like array, these operations
need to slide elements around
in the storage array,
but they also need to renumber
subsequent indices
in the hash table.
This means that removals
and insertions
turn into operations
with linear complexity,
making these slower
than the regular set.
There is always a trade-off!
But once we get familiar with
how these data structures work,
we will be able to confidently
select the right one
to solve any problem,
based on the requirements
we need to satisfy
and the operations
that are important to optimize.
Selecting the right data
structure can lead
to an algorithmic improvement
that can result in hundreds,
or even thousands,
of times faster code.
Selecting the wrong one
can do the opposite.
So I think it's useful
to learn about these
because, ultimately,
it results in great apps
and happy users.
This new OrderedSet type
is a pure Swift variant
of the existing NSOrderedSet
type in Foundation.
However, because OrderedSet
is implemented in a package,
it doesn't bridge
with NSOrderedSet.
This means existing
Objective-C APIs
won't get automatically imported
to use the new type.
These are separate things.
The third data structure
provided by
the Collections package
is an ordered analogue
of the standard dictionary type.
Like the standard dictionary,
this is a sequence
of key-value pairs
that lets us use
a key as a subscript
to quickly look up
its corresponding value.
Unlike the regular dictionary,
the order of key-value pairs
is well-defined.
By default, it follows the order
in which the keys
were originally inserted.
To append a new element,
we can assign a value
to a new key.
We can remove elements
by assigning nil
to an existing key.
Throughout these operations,
the ordered dictionary
maintains its contents
in a well-defined order.
Ordered dictionaries use
array-like integer indices,
but this introduces
an interesting issue.
In our example dictionary,
the indexing
subscript operation
conflicts with
the key subscript.
When we subscript with zero,
do we mean to access the value
for the key zero
or do we mean to retrieve the
key-value pair at offset zero?
We think that
the key-based subscript
is the primary operation
for a dictionary type,
so to prevent this ambiguity,
subscripting an ordered
dictionary always means
the keying subscript.
OrderedDictionary
doesn't provide
an indexing subscript
operation at all.
This means that
OrderedDictionary
cannot be a collection,
because the collection protocol
requires such a subscript.
Therefore, OrderedDictionary
only conforms
to the sequence protocol.
However, for cases where
a collection conformance
is desirable,
OrderedDictionary provides
the special elements view.
Elements is
a random-access collection
that provides
an indexing subscript
returning a key-value pair.
Looking at the underlying
implementation,
while the regular dictionary
type uses two separate
hash tables for storing keys
and values respectively,
an ordered dictionary uses a
single compressed hash table
and two parallel arrays instead.
This can save even more space
than ordered sets do.
So these are the three
new data structures
available in the
Collections package.
By using these constructs,
we can boost the performance
of our apps,
or reduce memory use or --
just as importantly --
we can express constraints
that we weren't able to easily
satisfy with the standard types,
such as preserving
element ordering in a set.
Because these new types
all conform to some sequence
and collection protocols,
they also interoperate
with the algorithms
provided by the standard library
as well as the new
Algorithms package
that Kyle showed us earlier.
Swift Collections
and Swift Algorithms
are only two of the new members
of our growing list
of open-source packages.
The future of the Swift library
ecosystem is being molded
right now, as we push
onto new platforms
and into new domains.
And this is being done
in plain sight
as we increasingly leverage
open-source packages.
We're deliberately releasing
these packages early,
while they're still pliable,
and we're developing them
as community efforts on GitHub.
So try them out.
File an issue.
Open a pull request.
It's never been a better time,
and it's never been easier
to get involved
and make an impact.
I hope you're as excited about
these new Swift packages
as we are.
We can't wait to see
what you build with these!
Thank you for watching,
and enjoy
the rest of the conference!
♪