[music]
[Christopher]
Welcome to WWDC.
I'm Christopher Skogen,
an engineer
on the Screen Time team,
and I'm here to talk to you
about the new Screen Time API.
It's been three years
since Apple introduced
Screen Time for iOS.
And it has been a giant step
forward
for improving our customers'
and families' relationships
with their devices.
Over the last three years,
Screen Time
brought some great new abilities
to iPhone, iPad, and Mac.
Screen Time helps you
keep track of how often you
and your family
use apps and websites,
manage time by setting limits,
share usage with family members
to provide a view of how
your devices are being used,
and finally, you can also manage
who your children
communicate with and more.
We've also heard from many
of you that you'd like
to leverage some
of these capabilities
in your own
parental controls apps.
So we've created
the Screen Time API.
It brings the core Screen Time
functionality to your apps
so you can create dynamic new
experiences for your customers.
First off, the API will be
available on iOS and iPadOS 15.
It is 100% Swift
and SwiftUI code
for easy integration into
your modern Swift applications.
The Screen Time API
was designed and built
with three guiding principles.
First, provide a modern,
on-device framework
for direct API access
to existing restrictions.
Our second guiding principle
was to protect user privacy.
Since Screen Time handles
some very sensitive personal
information
such as apps you've used
or web sites you've visited,
Screen Time has always taken
a very privacy-centric approach.
For instance,
there is no way for anyone
outside of your family
or even Apple
to know which sites you've
visited or what apps you use.
For the new API,
we continued this approach
to privacy,
and your customers' usage data
will be invisible
outside of their device.
And finally,
our third guiding principle was
to ensure that you,
the developers,
can create fantastic new dynamic
parental controls experiences.
It's no coincidence that
our three guiding principles
led us to create
three new frameworks.
The three frameworks,
taken together,
comprise the Screen Time API.
First, Managed Settings.
Managed Settings gives
your app direct access
to the same restrictions
available in Screen Time.
Second, Family Controls.
Family Controls
drives our privacy policy.
And finally, Device Activity.
Device Activity allows you
to go beyond Screen Time
by giving your app
great new abilities
to run code
without launching your app.
Let's take a closer look
at all three frameworks.
Let's start
with Managed Settings.
Your app needs a better way
to restrict what a child can do
with their devices and ensure
that those restrictions remain
in place
until the parent
or guardian says otherwise.
With Managed Settings,
your app can set a number
of restrictions,
like locking accounts in place,
or preventing a password change,
filter web traffic,
or shield applications,
much like Screen Time does,
but customized with your app's
branding and functionality.
Next is Family Controls.
By leveraging Family Sharing,
Family Controls prevents access
to the Screen Time API
without guardian approval.
Once your app has been approved
by the guardian,
it cannot be removed
from the device
without guardian approval.
Additionally, Family Controls
provides opaque tokens
that represent apps
and websites.
These tokens are used
throughout the Screen Time API
to monitor or restrict usage
and ensure that no one
outside of a single
Family Sharing group
will know what apps
and websites are being used.
And finally, Device Activity.
This framework allows
you to go beyond Screen Time
by giving your app new ways
to monitor web and app usage
and execute your code
when needed.
Because your app is
a parental control app,
it is very unlikely
that a child will have a reason
to run your app on their device.
So how do you execute your code
to set restrictions?
The answer is Device Activity
schedules and events.
Device Activity schedules are
time windows
that call an extension
in your application
at the start and end
of the time window.
Events are usage monitors
that call your extension
when the user on the device
reaches a usage threshold
in a Device Activity schedule.
Your app simply declares
what type of usage
it cares about
and when it cares.
Combining all three frameworks
together looks like this.
After your app is installed
on both the guardian's
and the child's devices,
the guardian opens the app
on the child's device.
Your app authorizes
with Family Controls.
Later, your app
on the guardian's device
chooses settings,
restrictions, and rules.
Your app sends that information
to the child's device.
And then on the child's device,
your app creates Schedules
and Events with Device Activity.
The Device Activity extension
in your app gets called
when the schedule occurs
or the events happen.
From the extension,
set restrictions
with Managed Settings.
This is a good time
to introduce Nolan.
Nolan is working on a great new
demo app, Homework,
and he'll walk you
through how Homework
uses the Screen Time API.
[Nolan]
Hi, I'm Nolan,
an engineer
on the Screen Time team.
I'd like to introduce you
to my demo app, Homework.
Homework encourages good habits
by restricting a child's access
to certain apps
until they accumulate usage
in other apps
the guardian wants them to use.
To make Homework functional,
I'm gonna
use all three frameworks
in the Screen Time API.
First, I'll walk you
through requesting authorization
for Family Controls.
Next up,
I'll shield the discouraged apps
selected by the guardian
on a reoccurring schedule.
Then I'll show you
how to remove those shields
after accumulating enough
encouraged app usage.
Finally, I'll customize
the shields used by Homework
to fit the app's branding
and functionality.
I'll start
with the project setup
and authorizing Family Controls.
In order to set up
my Xcode project
to include
Family Controls capability,
I'll go to the Project editor,
select the app target,
and under
Signing and Capabilities,
click the plus button.
I'll search for Family Controls
to find the capability
and add it to my project.
Now that the capability has
been added, I'm ready to code.
The first thing Homework needs
to do is request authorization
for Family Controls.
I'll use the shared
authorization center
in the Family Controls framework
to make this request
when my app launches.
The request can either result
in success or failure.
Calling this function will
require a guardian
in the family to approve
Family Controls for Homework.
Since my app has never
run on this iPhone before,
requestAuthorization will ask
for a guardian's approval
with an alert.
Tapping on Allow will
then prompt the guardian
to authenticate
with their Apple ID
and password to continue.
Once a guardian has
successfully authenticated,
calling requestAuthorization
will not prompt
with an alert again but instead
silently return success.
To prevent misuse,
requestAuthorization
will return failure
if the signed-in iCloud is
is not a child
using Family Sharing.
It's just that easy
to get your app ready
to use the Screen Time API.
[Christopher]
Thanks, Nolan.
We just saw our demo app,
Homework,
authorizing
with Family Controls.
Authorizing
with Family Controls also
grants other
magic powers to your app.
For instance,
once the device is authorized,
the user can no longer
sign out of iCloud.
Also,
on-device web content filters
built with
the Network Extensions framework
can be included in your app and
will be installed automatically
and cannot be removed.
This gives your app the ability
to filter web traffic
on the device.
One of the challenges in
writing a parental controls app
is getting your code
to run on the child's device
when the child will
likely never run your app.
For the Screen Time API,
we created a new way to perform
background code execution
with Device Activity.
A Device Activity extension
will be your primary way
to interact with the rest
of the Screen Time API.
Let's go back to Nolan to see
how Homework can run code
on a repeating schedule
to restrict a child's device
by placing a Screen Time shield
over some apps.
Nolan.
[Nolan]
Thanks, Chris.
Next up with Homework
is shielding the apps
the guardian has chosen
to discourage
on a reoccurring schedule.
Since I cannot count
on my app to be running
on the child's device,
I will use
a Device Activity Schedule
to set the application shield
restriction every day,
even when Homework hasn't run
since being setup
by the guardian.
When my Device Activity Schedule
fires,
Device Activity will call
into a new extension point.
Homework will
include an extension
for this extension point
where I will set the restriction
to shield apps.
Implementing an extension
for this extension point
requires you to subclass
DeviceActivityMonitor
as the principle class.
Here,
I've overridden two methods
in my extension's
principle class:
intervalDidStart
and intervalDidEnd.
These functions will be
called the first time the device
is used after the start
and end of my schedule.
I'm going to leave
the implementation
of these functions empty
until I've configured
my Device Activity schedule
from Homework's main app.
Now that
my Device Activity monitor
extension is set up
from the main app,
I need to create
a Device Activity name
and a Device Activity schedule.
The Device Activity name
is how I can reference
the activity
from within my extension.
And the Device Activity schedule
represents the time bounds
in which my extension
will monitor for activity.
Here I've set the name
of my activity to "daily,"
and I've set my schedule
to start and end at midnight.
I will also set
this schedule to repeat.
Finally, I can create
a Device Activity center
and call startMonitoring
with the activity name
and schedule I've just defined.
With these few lines of code,
my Device Activity monitor
extension will be called
with the activity name
whenever
the schedule starts and ends.
Another ingredient
to shielding apps
is figuring out what the
guardian wants to discourage.
The Family Controls framework
has a SwiftUI element
just for the job:
The family activity picker.
From the main app's UI,
I can show
the family activity picker
and allow the guardian
to choose from a list of apps,
websites,
and categories
used by the family.
Once the guardian has
made their selection,
Homework can use opaque
tokens returned by the picker
to set restrictions on apps,
websites,
and categories
each token represents.
Here, I've added
the familyActivityPicker
view modifier
to a Button in the app,
and I've bound the picker's
selection parameter
to a property
in the app's model.
This will update my model
whenever the guardian's
selection is updated in the UI.
Now that I have the guardian's
discouraged app selection stored
in my app's model,
I'll jump back
to the Device Activity Monitor
extension.
First, I'll drop in an import
for the Managed Settings module
to get access to the application
shield restriction.
Then in intervalDidStart,
I can pull the selection
out of the app's model
and configure
the application shield
restriction accordingly.
And in intervalDidEnd,
I can remove the restriction
by setting it to nil.
With these simple modifications,
Homework will shield
the guardian selected
discouraged apps every day
from midnight to midnight.
Back to you, Chris.
[Christopher]
Thanks, Nolan.
Shielding is not the only
restriction available
in Managed Settings.
We could also choose to set
any number of restrictions
at the beginning or end
of a Device Activity Schedule.
For instance,
your app could choose
to prevent account creation or
removal, completely block apps
and websites,
or deny media content by age.
Speaking of media restrictions,
Managed Settings also provides
an API that allows any app
to read the restrictions
for Movies and TV content.
No Family Controls
authorization is required.
These functions are ideal
for any media app
to check if a device should
be limiting the content
presented to the user.
In the Homework demo app,
the restrictions were set
at midnight every day,
but what if you want
to change restrictions
based upon app or web usage?
Device Activity has
another feature that will
allow your app to do just that:
Device Activity events.
These events are configured
with the same tokens you saw
from the family activity picker
and allow you to execute code
when the usage limits are
reached.
These events are registered
alongside the schedules
that Nolan showed us
in the last segment.
Now let's go check in with Nolan
and see how these events work.
[Nolan] I want to remove the
application shield restriction
not only when
Homework's schedule ends
but also when the child
accumulates enough usage
for a set of guardian-selected
encouraged apps.
To do that,
I'll need to monitor the usage
of these encouraged apps
by configuring Device Activity
to additionally call
into my Device Activity monitor
extension
when a usage threshold is met.
Here, I'll define
a Device Activity event name
to be "encouraged."
This name is
how I can reference the event
from within my extension.
And then I'll define
my encouraged event
to include the set
of guardian-selected
encouraged apps and
the threshold of usage desired.
Finally, I'll update
the call to startMonitoring
to included
the event I just defined.
Now that I am monitoring
for Device Activity events
from the main app,
my Device Activity monitor
extension is going
to be called whenever any
of those events meet
their usage threshold.
The function
eventDidReachThreshold
will be called with
the Device Activity Event Name
and the DeviceActivityName
to identify which event fired
for which scheduled activity.
In Homework, I want to set the
application shield restriction
to nil when the extension
gets notified for this event.
Setting this restriction
to nil will remove the shield
from any of the
previously shielded apps.
Back to Chris.
[Christopher]
In the previous section,
the discouraged apps were
shielded
with
a default Screen Time shield.
But you'll likely want
to get your own branding
and style in these shields.
You'll also probably
want to have
your own action handlers
for the shield's buttons.
We've got the tools for both.
Custom shields allow you
to create a unique
branded experience.
To customize the shields,
you'll need to implement
two new extension points
defined in Managed Settings.
One extension point
allows you to customize the look
of the shield
by changing background material,
titles, icon,
and appearance of the buttons.
And another extension point
allows you to create
custom button handlers.
Let's go back to Nolan
and see how you would
customize your shields.
[ Nolan] To configure the look
and feel of the custom shields
for Homework,
I need to start
by subclassing
ShieldConfigurationProvider
as the principle
class of the extension.
Configuration
is the only function
you'll need to override here.
This function is passed
a reference to the application
that is currently being
shielded,
and it is expected to return
a ShieldConfiguration struct.
The ShieldConfiguration struct
allows you
to define the background effect,
background color,
icon, title, subtitle,
primary button label,
primary button background color,
and secondary button label.
Wow,
that's a lot of customization.
Once this struct is configured
and returned by my
shield configuration provider
extension,
the operating system
will automatically display
these customizations over any
app shielded by Homework.
Now that we've
styled the shields,
I can use
the second extension point
in Managed Settings
to configure the action handlers
for the primary
and secondary buttons.
In this new extension,
I'll subclass
ShieldActionHandler
as the principle class
and override
the function handle.
The handle function is told
whether
the primary button action
or secondary button action
was pressed
and which application
is currently being shielded.
You are required to call the
function's completion handler
with a sshield action response.
The response can either be to
close the shielded application
or defer action and redraw
the shield configuration.
The ability to defer action
in the shield is very powerful
because it gives the shield
the chance to update
its appearance while it waits
for a signal on how to proceed.
For instance,
it can be used to indicate
that the shield is waiting
for a guardian's action
when the child taps
Ask for Access here.
With the addition
of these custom shields,
my demo app, Homework,
is complete.
The guardian
can choose apps to shield,
such as games or entertainment,
and remove the shield
once the child has done
enough positive screen time,
like reading, learning,
or being creative.
Thanks for joining me
in building
this awesome new demo app.
Now back to Chris.
[Christopher] Today we learned
how our three goals--
to provide restrictions,
protect privacy,
and enable new dynamic
experiences--
were delivered
with the three frameworks
that make up
the Screen Time API.
Managed Settings allows your app
to enforce settings
and restrictions.
Device Activity allows your app
to run code on a schedule
or on usage events even
when your app is not being used.
And finally, Family Controls,
which grants access
to Managed Settings
and Device Activity
and protects the privacy
of your users,
guaranteeing that only
the guardians will know
what the child is doing.
Like all frameworks,
the Screen Time API will
continue to evolve based
on feedback from you.
So give these a try
and let us know how they do
or don't support
your unique use cases.
Thanks for joining us today.
Enjoy WWDC 2021.
[music]