[percussive music]
[Lucy] My name is Lucy Zhang,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Installation
and Software Update team.
I'll be talking about
managed software updates
for macOS,
iOS, and iPadOS today.
Software updates are
critical to everyone
using Apple products.
Updates bring new security
enhancements,
like notarization
and the sealed system volume
in macOS Big Sur.
They enable
all the latest features,
and maybe most importantly,
that's how you get
all the new emojis.
Our platform makes it easy
to update your device.
In fact,
86% of all iPhones introduced
in the last four years
use iOS 14.
However,
in managed environments,
you need more control
over this process.
When managing a fleet
of devices,
you want to keep them
up to date,
but you need time to test
updates before releasing them,
to ensure that the OS is
compatible with your software.
After your testing is complete,
you want to ensure that
updates are installed
as soon as possible,
while minimizing disruption
to the user.
In this session,
we will first explore
the programs and restrictions
that allow you to test
beta and newly released
software updates.
Next, the MDM commands
for deploying updates.
And finally,
I can't wait to tell you about
a new way you can ensure
users get updated
to the latest version
you're ready to support.
Let's get started
with testing updates.
When Apple releases a beta OS,
you have time and tools to test
the OS in your environment
before it's released.
AppleSeed for IT help
you access and test
new Apple software
while it's in beta.
Any non-student Managed Apple ID
from Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager
can participate in the program,
which gives you access
to pre-release Apple software
for testing in your environment,
and includes detailed test plans
and a way to provide feedback.
Once the update
is publicly released,
you may still need time to test,
and you don't want
the update to be available
to all your users yet.
For that, you have deferral.
Deferral prevents
supervised devices
from offering
software updates to users,
until a specified period of time
has expired
since those updates
were published by Apple.
When you
apply a deferral restriction,
the default delay is 30 days
since update publication.
You can also specify a custom
value between 1 and 90 days.
When an update has been
available long enough
for the specified delay
to expire,
that update is offered
to users as part of the standard
software update notifications
and update process.
These restrictions give you
more granular control
over the Software Update
interface in System Preferences.
The deferred updates
restriction only affects
the Software Update interface.
It does not change
the behavior of MDM commands.
Even with a restriction set,
MDM has the ability
to send specific updates
to devices.
For iPhone, iPad, and Apple TV,
deferring software updates
is available
in iOS 11.3 or later,
iPadOS 13.1 or later,
and tvOS 12.2 or later.
When you defer updates,
you set the same deferral window
for major and minor updates.
For Mac computers,
deferring software updates
is available
in macOS 10.13 or later.
In macOS 11.3 or later,
an admin may now choose to delay
major releases for longer
than minor releases.
That way, users can still
benefit from
important security updates,
while the admin works
to approve the latest
major release for production
in their environment.
These are the keys that you
can set in a profile
to install on the Mac computer.
Use the
forceDelayedMajorSoftwareUpdates
key to defer
a major release.
With this key,
you can still receive minor OS
and security updates, while
deferring a major OS update.
There may be times where
you want to separately
defer a minor release,
and you'll use
the forceDelayedSoftwareUpdates
key to do that.
And for separately
deferring
supplemental updates,
you'll use the
forceDelayedAppSoftwareUpdates
key.
If a deferral type is enabled,
but there is no corresponding
deferral period set,
we will fallback to using
the old key,
ManagedDeferredInstallDelay.
When there are deferral
restrictions in place,
this is how the software
update preference pane
appears on macOS.
Let's explore how
deferral might work.
Back to the timeline,
you've now deferred
an update
and continued testing the new OS
for compatibility
in your environment.
Once you've confirmed the OS
and completed testing,
you're ready to push it
to users.
You want devices to update
when users are ready,
and it's not intrusive
to their workflow.
So let's explore
deploying updates.
There are a few steps
to install the right update
on the right device,
and with macOS Monterey,
there's more parity than ever
before between macOS and iOS.
The first step in deploying
updates for all platforms
is to check for updates
and confirm device eligibility.
Here's how that was done for Mac
prior to macOS Monterey.
Available OS updates
were only able to be
evaluated on the user's device.
You used the command
ScheduleOSUpdateScan,
which tells the Mac
to query the server
for available OS updates,
and then evaluates the updates
to determine eligibility.
Once the scan finished and was
sent back to the MDM server,
the MDM could then choose
an update to deploy.
However, Apple provides the
Apple Software Lookup service,
which provides
a list of available OS versions
across platforms.
Here, we are presented
with the iOS devices.
You may already be using
the feed for iPhone
and iPad to reduce
the back-and-forth that comes
with the ScheduleOSUpdateScan
for Mac.
For iOS, MDM solutions
use the
Apple Software Lookup Service
to be aware of available updates
to push the command
directly to the device.
Here's how:
First, the MDM Server
can get a list
of available updates,
such as 12.1 or 12.2,
from the Apple Software
Lookup Service.
When you're ready to deploy
an update, the MDM server
will send the update
version to the device.
Then, the device will reach
the software update server
to verify that
the update is eligible
and begin
to download and install it.
New with macOS Monterey,
we are unifying this process
for macOS and iOS.
We now support a new
DeviceInformation query key
called SoftwareUpdateModelID,
which returns the hardware
model string for iOS
and macOS to MDM.
The Apple Software Lookup
Service will include
the appropriate hardware
identifier for macOS,
allowing MDM servers
to determine the applicability
of an update without
the AvailableOSUpdates command.
Just like on iOS,
the MDM will be able
to determine
update applicability
by comparing the result from
DeviceInformation query
to the device IDs
listed in the JSON feed.
Also, until now, macOS has
ignored the ProductVersion key
and used ProductKey instead.
As of macOS Monterey,
the ProductVersion key
will be supported on macOS.
iOS already uses this
key to specify updates.
For compatibility, if you
specify both ProductVersion
and ProductKey,
then ProductKey will be used.
If the device can't find
an update eligible
for that version, it will send
the appropriate response.
This removes the round
trip for minor OS updates
as long as you have
previously collected
the supported device ID
of the device.
MDM administrators can
automatically install
and authorize software
updates for macOS, iOS,
and iPadOS, as long as
the device is supervised.
In macOS 11 or later,
all Mac computers enrolled
using either Device Enrollment
or Automated Device Enrollment
are supervised.
For iOS and iPadOS,
the user will be required
to enter their passcode
to proceed with the update.
Mac computers with Apple silicon
introduce the concept
of "ownership."
Ownership can
loosely be defined as the user
who has first claimed a Mac
for configuring it for their use
and is not tied to true legal
ownership or chain of custody.
Ownership defines who is
authorized to make changes
to the startup security policy
for a specific install of macOS.
On Apple silicon,
the startup security policy
defines the restrictions
around which versions
of macOS can boot on Mac
computers and permission
to use the bootstrap token
for automated updates.
macOS requires authentication
to perform updates.
For Mac computers
with Apple silicon,
authentication requires
a user password
or an MDM bootstrap token.
A user password is required
for user-initiated,
interactive updates through
System Preferences.
An MDM Bootstrap Token
is used for automated
non-interactive updates,
which requires macOS 11.2
or later,
and the update being installed
must be signed by Apple.
New in macOS Monterey,
we have introduced support
for the bootstrap token
for MDM-initiated
install-later flows.
This means that Apple silicon
devices can schedule
and perform updates
at a later time,
when the device is not in use.
Your users will appreciate
that you're updating
their device while not
disrupting their workflow.
They can just wake up the next
day to an updated machine.
If you're already supporting
the bootstrap token,
this will just start
working when you use
the InstallLater action
in ScheduleOSUpdate.
Once the MDM knows which
update is applicable to devices,
the ScheduleOSUpdate
command is used to deploy
the update to macOS, iOS,
and iPadOS.
Just note,
an MDM command can be used
to install the update during
the deferral window or after.
There are several options
when using
the ScheduleOSUpdate command.
One option that must be set
is the install action,
whose value
significantly affects
the behavior of the update.
The InstallASAP install action
is the primary
update mechanism
for userless macOS devices.
InstallASAP
uses the bootstrap token
for authentication on Mac
computers with Apple silicon.
This action
performs immediately,
with an option for a user
to cancel the update.
Just note that InstallASAP
command does not automatically
close applications that are
actively in use
unless the InstallForceResart
option is used.
DownloadOnly is useful for both
users and userless devices
to download
the update in the background
before the installation time.
NotifyOnly is used to alert
users that there is
an action for installation.
Neither command will
start the install.
InstallLater allows you
to schedule
an Install Tonight update.
The device will choose
a window of time,
usually between
2:00 a.m. to 4:00 a.m.,
based on machine learning,
using conditions such as
when the device is least used,
for the install to occur.
The device then schedules
the update to occur
in that window of time, given
that you are plugged into power.
Let's check
out the notifications.
With the InstallASAP command,
or Default command,
users can get a restart
countdown notification.
The user can choose
to cancel the restart
in the notification options.
And in macOS Monterey,
when you use InstallLater,
the user
will get this notification.
Let's examine this more closely.
This notification shows
that the update
will attempt to install
that night.
The user is reminded that
the device must be connected
to power at the time it
performs the update later.
For iOS or iPadOS devices,
Default
is the primary update mechanism.
DownloadOnly
is useful for both user
and userless devices
to install the download
in the background
before the installation time.
Here is what a user
would be presented with.
Non-passcode-protected
devices install the version
immediately after the command
is sent from the MDM server.
Passcode-protected devices
require
a slightly different flow.
Once the device receives
the install command from MDM,
we will schedule
the installation alert
to show on the next unlock.
This gives the user
the option to Install Now,
or Install Tonight,
or Remind Me Later.
On iOS, this first install alert
shown to the user
allows you to choose Install
Now, Later, or Details.
Subsequent alerts shown
will say that the update
is ready to install.
For example, "iOS 15.0 is ready
to install."
And the provided options
are Install Now or Later.
Tapping Later
in the previous screen
will show the passcode prompt
with the Remind Me Later
option at the bottom.
The MDM server can also
flag an update as required.
This will let the user choose
Remind Me Later
a maximum of three times.
After the third tap
of Remind Me Later,
the installation
notification will be shown
every time the user
hits the Home screen,
and the Remind Me Later
option is removed.
Let's return to the timeline
where we're now ready
to install the update.
For userless devices,
you can use
the InstallForceRestart option
with ScheduleOSUpdate.
Those devices will do a hard
restart to perform the update.
And for user devices, once you
send the install command,
you relied on the user
to perform the update.
That is, until now.
I'm excited to tell you
about a new feature
we are introducing for macOS.
After the admin update
deferral period is over,
you want to ensure that
updates are installed quickly
after you've made
them available to users.
You don't want the user
to continue to cancel
or defer the update.
You need a way to enforce it.
In macOS Monterey,
you now gain more control
over the InstallLater policy
to enforce the update.
You can specify the number
of times the device
should prompt to install
before the update is enforced.
This number is defined by
the MaxUserDeferrals key.
This MaxUserDeferrals key
implies the existing key,
InstallForceRestart,
once the maximum number
of deferrals has been reached.
When you enforce the number
of maximum deferrals,
the user will receive
informative notifications
about the remaining
number of attempts left
before a forced update
will occur.
To change the maximum
number of user deferrals,
you simply need to issue
a new InstallLater command.
Here's what the user
would be presented with.
When you
set the MaxUserDeferrals value,
the notification shows
the remaining number of attempts
before a forced install.
The update
is scheduled for tonight,
but the user is given options.
They can
select Remind Me Tomorrow,
which will defer the update
again and decrement
the count of remaining
number of attempts.
They can install it now,
or they can have it
attempt to update later tonight.
If the user does nothing,
the update
will attempt that night.
When the number of maximum
user deferrals is reached,
the user is notified
that this update will be forced.
This means the machine will
restart to perform the update,
regardless if the user
is still using the device.
With these new changes,
admins gain more control
over enforcing the macOS
update and ensuring that
devices are updated
in a timely manner.
There is one more thing
I want to tell you
about managing software updates.
New this year, iOS and iPadOS
now offer users a choice
between two
software update versions
within the Settings app.
For example, you can update
to the next major OS
as soon as it's released,
for the latest features
and most complete set
of security updates.
Alternatively, continue on
the current major release
and still get important
security updates,
until you're ready to jump to
the next major version
of iOS or iPadOS.
A new option on the Settings
command lets you control
what OS update is
presented to the user.
You specify this by providing
a SoftwareUpdateSettings
dictionary, which has a key
called RecommendationCadence.
This key can have three values.
Here's what's shown if you have
RecommendationCadence set to 0.
This is the default view,
which is what you would get
if no MDM restrictions
are in place.
Both the major and minor
versions
of updates are available.
Here's what's shown if you have
RecommendationCadence set to 1.
If two software update versions
are available,
the device will show the
software update version
with the lower version number.
Here's what's shown if you have
RecommendationCadence set to 2.
If two software update versions
are available,
the device will show
the software update
with the higher version number.
Just note, if a deferral
is set with the existing
enforceSoftwareDelayUpdate key,
the device will take that
into account
and filter by
the RecommendationCadence.
The two update choices
will eventually converge.
To recap, on macOS, we will now
support deploying updates
using an OS version
so MDMs can determine
what updates are needed
for devices
and push them
in a timely manner.
We have also automated
InstallLater flows
on Mac computers
with Apple silicon
using the bootstrap token.
We will allow the MDM to enforce
updates with MaxUserDeferrals,
allowing for users
to stay informed about
when updates occur,
and scheduling updates
at times least likely
to disrupt their workflows.
Finally, on iOS,
we have added support to manage
what versions of updates
are shown in Settings.
We look forward to you
gaining this additional control
and providing
a great update experience
for users in macOS
Monterey and iOS 15.
Thank you,
and have a great WWDC.
[percussive music]