[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Erik Hornberger: Good afternoon,
everyone,
and thank you
for joining us today.
We’ve got some great content
planned out for you.
We’re going to walk through
a code-along
where you and I will build out
a research and care app
together.
ResearchKit is
an open source iOS framework
that Apple maintains
in collaboration
with our GitHub community.
It provides UI elements
for gathering consent,
administering surveys,
and recording sensor data
while participants
perform activities,
such as physical
or cognitive exercises.
CareKit, likewise, is also
a fully open source framework,
and it’s designed to help
with building out
patient-facing care apps.
It excels at scheduling tasks
that you want patients
to perform,
like taking medications
or calling their doctor.
It also provides
a secure persistence layer
for health-related data
and has utilities for charting.
Now, in past WWDC sessions,
we’ve often discussed these two
sibling frameworks in isolation,
but this year we’re going
to show you
how they can be used together
to create
even better experiences
for patients...
[FACETIME RINGING]
Sorry.
Should we just --
I should have had it on silent.
Do we cut?
[RINGING CONTINUES]
Crew: No, just answer it.
[FACETIME PICKUP TONE]
Erik: Yo, Jamie. What's up?
Jamie: Hey, Erik.
I know you’re busy
prepping for WWDC right now,
but I wanted to tell you
that funding just came through
for our physical therapy
study app!
This cutting-edge research
is going to help so many people!
So, do you think we can get
a first rev of the app out,
like, right away?
Erik: Hey, Jamie, that is --
that is awesome news,
and I'm --
I'm really excited about it.
The thing is
we're just very much
in the middle of our-
of our Dub Dub code-along.
Jamie: Oh,
so you're coding already?
That's perfect!
So, the app is going
to be called "Recover."
It’s going to be
a physical therapy app
to help participants strengthen
their knees following surgery,
and it’s going to be
a game changer!
I’ve got tons of great ideas,
but first, it’s really important
that participants consent
to participating in the study
before we let them
start using the app.
We’ve got to explain to them
all the legalese,
but I really want to do it
in a way
that isn’t intimidating,
you know?
We’ll also need to get
a signature from participants
and have them agree
to share data with us as well.
Uh, one sec, Erik.
I’m getting a message
from the clinical team.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
Oh, wow. It looks like
the first participants
will be released from post-op
on Monday.
Erik, can you just get started
with onboarding for now?
I have to catch up
with the rest of team,
but I’ll call you back in a bit!
This is going to be great!
[FACETIME END TONE]
Erik: [LAUGHING] OK.
Uh...
Alrighty then!
I guess this is just going to be
our code-along now!
So let's -- let's see if we can
finish up onboarding
before Jamie gets out
of that meeting!
So, for this session,
let’s focus on onboarding
and consent.
Explaining to the participant
what data we’re going
to collect,
who's going to have access
to it, what it’ll be used for,
how long it will be retained --
and making all of that
easy to understand --
is of paramount importance
to a good study.
We’re going to show you some new
best practices for ResearchKit
that will help you get this
very important part of your app
just right.
And as a bonus,
we’re going to demonstrate
a clever way
to bake that onboarding
and consent flow
right into a CareKit-based app.
Specifically,
we’re going to set up
a standard CareKit app,
but in a way that participants
must complete onboarding
before the care plan’s contents
are revealed.
As part of that consent
and onboarding flow,
we’re going to build out
some instruction steps
telling the participants about
what they’re about
to be asked to do.
We’ve found that orienting
participants like this,
before jumping
into the actual consent parts,
really helps improve
their experience.
We’ll show you how to collect
a signature,
and we’ll also demonstrate
how to use ResearchKit
to ask for authorization
for HealthKit, notifications,
and device motion all up front,
all as part of onboarding.
If you’d like to follow along,
you can find the starter project
in the session resources.
Let’s open Xcode
and get started!
This is where
we’ll be starting from.
We're going to be touching
four files today.
First is the AppDelegate.
This is where
we're going to be interacting
with CareKit’s store.
Over in Surveys.swift,
we’ll be writing out some
surveys using ResearchKit.
Next up, we've got the
CareFeedViewController
and InsightsViewController,
where we’ll be building out
the UI for our app.
Now, if you run the starter app,
you’ll see that there’s actually
not much there right now.
It's just the
OCKDailyPageViewController
with no content.
It allows us to jump around
between days,
but there’s nothing there yet.
It’ll be our job
to fill all of that in.
There’s also the Insights tab
down here in the corner,
and we'll be returning to that
during part three.
Now, what we want to do is make
a consent card show up here
in the participant’s feed.
That consent task will gate
access to the rest of the app.
Nothing else will show up
until it’s been completed,
and once it has been,
all the other tasks
should appear.
Jumping over here
to AppDelegate.swift,
our first step will be
to persist a CareKit task
for onboarding.
Now, whenever we create a task,
we need to define a schedule
that specifies how often
the task will appear
in the participant’s feed.
For onboarding,
we’ll use a daily schedule
so they’ll be prompted
to onboard every day
until they finish consenting.
Next, we’ll create a task.
We give it an ID,
which can be anything we want,
so long as it’s unique.
Random identifiers are fine,
but in this case,
I’ve just got a constant
we’ve defined over here
in another file.
We also need to pass in
the schedule
that we just created.
We’ll also specify
some instructions
and indicate that onboarding
should not impact adherence.
What this means is basically
that onboarding won’t count
toward filling
the completion rings
that you see at the top
of most CareKit apps.
And finally, we can persist
the task into our store.
We’ll just go ahead
and print out a message
to let us know
if it was successful or not.
All right, we’ve got our
onboarding task in the store,
ready to go,
and now, we’re ready
to make it appear
in the participant’s feed.
We’ll hop over
CareViewController.swift
where we’ll tell CareKit
how we want it to be displayed.
Here, we’re subclassing
OCKDailyPageViewController,
which is the calendar and feed
that we saw just a moment ago.
We’re overriding
the prepare listViewController
for date method.
This method will be invoked
each time the user swipes
to a new date,
and it’s our job
to inspect the date,
determine what we want to show
on that date,
and append
the appropriate content
into the listViewController.
Now, the first thing
we want to do
is check if the participant
has finished onboarding or not,
since we’ll display
different content
based on the answer
to that question.
Let’s drop down a bit further
and write out a method
to do just that.
Inside of our
checkIfOnboardingIsComplete
method,
we’ll create an OCKOutomeQuery,
and we’ll query for all outcomes
associated
with the onboarding task.
When our query returns,
we’ll check to see if
any outcomes were found or not.
If there aren’t any, that means
onboarding hasn’t finished yet.
If there is one,
that means that onboarding
is already complete.
We’ll use our new method
right up here,
and based on whether or not
onboarding is complete,
we’ll either show
just the consent task
or all the other tasks.
All right. So far, so good!
We now have
a mechanism in place
for requiring the participant
to onboard
before letting them
into the rest of the app.
The next step is to set up
that onboarding flow.
Right here, we want to create
a CareKit task card
that presents
a ResearchKit survey,
but before we can do that,
we need to actually create
a ResearchKit survey
so that we have something
to display.
We’ll pop over to Surveys.swift
and get that taken care of.
Let’s stub out our function
to start.
Our onboarding survey is going
to consist of five steps:
a welcome step,
an instruction step,
a signature step,
a permissions step,
and finally, a completion step.
The first is going to be
the welcome step,
which will be
an ORKInstructionStep.
We’re going to see a lot of
these instructions steps today.
Whenever we create
a ResearchKit step,
we need to give it
a unique identifier.
You can use any pattern
that you’d like,
including random identifiers.
I’ve found that this
key path-inspired approach
works really well for me.
We’ll also specify a title
and some detailText
as well as a header image.
All right.
So up next: step two is going
to be our informed consent step,
and this will also be
an instruction step.
But this time, we’re going
to add some body items.
Body items are basically
bullet points,
but we have the option
to use an image --
and in this case,
an SF Symbol --
in place of the bullet.
This body item
tells participants
they’re going to be asked
to share some health data.
Let’s create a second body item
to tell them
they’ll be asked
to complete tasks
and a third to inform them
they’ll be asked
to provide their signature.
Let's add one more
to remind them
that their data will be kept
private and secure.
Finally, we’ll insert
these body items
into our instruction step.
And that covers
the instructions.
Next up is gathering
a signature, and fortunately,
ResearchKit makes this part
really easy.
The signature can be collected
with an ORKWebViewStep.
Setting the showSignature
AfterContent property to true
prompts ResearchKit
to show the signature box
at the bottom of the step.
We can supply the actual consent
document as HTML,
and it will be shown right above
the signature box.
There we go; the signature
was pretty quick and easy!
The last bit will be
requesting permissions.
For this fourth step,
we’ll collect permissions with
the HealthKitPermissionType
that my teammate Pariece
introduced at WWDC last year.
It requires that we specify
two sets of HealthKit types:
one that’s we’d like permission
to write to
and one that we’d like
permission to read from.
This year, we’re introducing
two new permission types.
The first is
ORKNotificationPermissionType,
and it allows us to request
permission to show alerts,
badge the app, and play sounds.
We’re also introducing
the ORKMotionActivity
PermissionType,
which will help us ask for
access to device motion data.
We’ll pass all three of these
into a requestPermissionStep,
which wraps up our fourth step.
The fifth and final step is just
going to be a completion step
that thanks the participant
for joining Jamie’s study.
All of these steps will be
chained together
inside of an ORKOrderedTask.
We’ll pass in the steps
in the order
we’d like ResearchKit
to present them
and then return the task
from this method.
All right.
Now that we’ve defined the whole
onboarding and consent flow,
let’s jump back into
CareFeedViewController
and revisit how to display it
from our CareKit-based app.
We’re introducing
a brand-new class,
the OCKSurveyTaskViewController,
and it is specifically built
for this purpose.
Like all other
CareKit view controllers,
we pass in the ID of the task
we’d like to display
along with an eventQuery
and the storeManager.
Additionally, we’ll also need
the survey we just created
and a closure that translates
a ResearchKit result
into an array
of CareKit outcome values.
We’ll revisit this closure
in more detail during part two.
For now, we’ll just say it's
sufficient to persist the date
that the participant
completed onboarding.
We’ll also want to append
this task card into our feed.
Now, there is actually
one more step,
and that is to make sure
that the feed reloads
once the participant
finishes onboarding.
One way we can accomplish that
is by setting ourselves
as the survey task view
controller’s delegate.
Then, down here, we can
implement the delegate method,
survey task view controller
didFinish task with result.
In the body of this method,
we can check that onboarding
was completed successfully,
which is basically just to say
that the participant didn’t
cancel out partway through;
they went all the way to the end
and completed it successfully.
If that’s the case, we can call
reload() to refresh the feed.
All right, so our
onboarding card is set up.
When the participant
completes onboarding,
we’ll save an OCKOutcome
and then reload the feed.
This is looking good!
I think that’s --
that's everything, actually!
Let’s run our app and confirm
that this all works.
You can see that we’re
being asked to consent
before we can begin
using the app.
And that’s exactly what we want!
Let’s tap
on the Begin button here,
and we'll see that we’re greeted
by the welcome step
we created just a moment ago.
The next step
is our instruction step
with the body items
that we defined.
The SF Symbols that we chose
really bring it to life.
Next up is the signature step,
so l’ll just scroll down here
and sign that...
...and then we move on
to the authorization step.
First, we'll authorize
HealthKit.
Just go ahead and allow that.
Next up is notifications,
and then device motion.
The last page
is our completion step
that lets us know
we’re all done
and thanks us for participating.
And now we’re back
in our Care Feed.
Note that we don’t see
the prompt
to complete consent anymore
because we’re done
with that now.
Instead, this is where all
of the true content of our app
is going to appear.
We’re going to get to that
in our next session.
Hey Siri, can you message Jamie
and tell him that we’re done
with the onboarding and consent?
[SIRI TONE]
You can find more info
about our frameworks
on researchandcare.org.
If you’d like to read
the source code --
or contribute --
both frameworks
are available on GitHub.
Please join us again
for our next session.
I’m going to check
with Jamie real quick,
and then I’ll rejoin you
for part two.
See you soon!
♪