[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Holly]
Hi, my name is Holly,
and I’m a manager
on the Continuous Integration
Technologies Team,
and I’ll later be joined
by my teammate Geoff McGinnis.
Today, it’s my pleasure
to introduce Xcode Cloud,
an easy-to-use
continuous integration
and delivery service
designed for developers
just like you,
anyone who’s building
apps and frameworks
for Apple platforms.
In this session,
we’re gonna start
with an introduction
to continuous integration
and meet Xcode Cloud.
Then we’ll setup a project,
make a code change,
and learn how to use Xcode Cloud
to collaborate with your team.
Let’s get started.
Continuous integration or CI
is the practice
of integrating
code changes regularly,
so that issues
are caught and fixed early.
Adopting this practice
allows teams
to work collaboratively
while also creating
high-quality products.
A typical CI workflow
is a set of automated steps
that runs when you
or a team member
push a code change
to your repository.
These steps can do things
like build, run tests,
or any other number of actions
needed to ensure
that the code change
meets your team’s
established level of quality.
With CI,
you can have peace of mind
that integrating a change
is low-risk
and that your next release
is stable.
Now, to think about what CI
might look like for you,
let’s take a look
at the life cycle of an app.
As a developer,
you’re likely working
with feedback
from multiple sources.
You fix bugs
and create features in Xcode,
you receive code review feedback
from your team
on pull requests,
and you distribute
new versions via TestFlight
and integrate tester feedback.
Your team’s ability
to iterate on code
and feedback productively
is essential to creating
a high-quality app or framework.
That’s where Xcode Cloud
comes in.
Xcode Cloud builds upon the idea
of CI while connecting the dots
between Apple developer tools
to provide you
with the complete
development pipeline
to build, test, distribute,
collect feedback,
and quickly iterate
on your projects.
Let’s take a tour
of the features
to learn about what you can do.
You spend most of your time
developing in Xcode,
and Xcode Cloud
is right there in Xcode.
Here, you can see
Xcode Cloud in action.
There are multiple workflows
set up
and builds are running
and catching issues.
You also get a new insight
into all of the work
your team is doing.
A workflow is a configuration
that tells Xcode Cloud
which actions to perform
and when to perform them.
You can breeze through
the easy onboarding
and get your first workflow
up and running quickly.
Then you can come back
and edit it,
or make new workflows
to support different use cases.
The result of running a workflow
is called a build.
Xcode Cloud runs builds
in Apple managed
Cloud infrastructure
that provides
code signing and access
to multiple
operating system versions
and Xcode releases.
When you click on your app
in the Cloud tab
of the report navigator,
you can view the status
of all of your workflows
and the latest builds
in the sidebar.
Clicking your app also opens
the build group overview,
which shows all of your builds
organized by the way
your development team works,
not just by workflow
but also by git branch,
allowing you to use one workflow
for many branches but still see
the results separately.
You can also filter
down the list
to see only builds
started by your code changes,
by clicking the Mine filter
above the overview...
or by selecting the person icon
in the report navigator.
One level down
from the build group overview
is the build report
for a single run of a workflow.
This is where you can deep-dive
into the results
specific to your code change.
You can view test reports,
logs, and jump directly
into the code
that caused an issue.
Geoff will go into more details
of the build report later.
Everything we just saw
is not only available in Xcode,
but it’s also available
in App Store Connect.
This includes starting
and viewing builds,
managing workflows,
viewing
and downloading artifacts,
sharing results with your team,
and managing
notification settings.
And if you’re already
working in TestFlight,
Xcode Cloud
is the tab right next door
in App Store Connect
for quick access.
In App Store Connect,
you can also set up
your personal
notification settings.
I like to set up
Slack notifications
for failing builds
so I can continue working
after pushing my code
but get alerted quickly
if there’s something to fix.
Everyone on your team
can set up notifications
that work best for them.
Whether you’re on the go,
or want visibility into builds
of a project
you don’t have set up in Xcode,
or you’re a member of a team
who isn’t committing code
to a project,
Xcode Cloud in App Store Connect
provides a fully-featured
web-based experience.
When we created Xcode Cloud,
we designed it
for your development process
and for collaboration
with your team,
but it has also been built
with privacy at its core.
Your source code
is the heart of your project.
That’s why all aspects
of Xcode Cloud are designed
to ensure
that your data is protected.
Build environments
are temporary.
Workloads
are completely isolated,
and environments are torn down
and created from scratch
between builds.
Source code is never stored.
Xcode Cloud fetches your code
only within
the temporary build environment.
Build data is encrypted at rest
and stored
in a dedicated
CloudKit database.
And you’re
in control of your data.
You can delete your data
at any time,
and it will be
completely removed
from the system.
Now that I’ve introduced
Xcode Cloud,
I’m gonna hand it over to Geoff
to walk through getting set up.
[Geoff]
Let’s get started onboarding
to Xcode Cloud.
It takes only a few simple steps
to get started
thanks to
the powerful integration
with Xcode.
The process begins
by visiting
the Xcode Cloud section
of the product menu
and selecting Create Workflow.
Next, I select which app
I’d like to onboard
from these options
detected for my local project.
Today, I’ll pick
this new smoothie ordering app
my team is developing
called “Fruta.”
The app supports
both iOS and macOS,
and we’ll onboard both platforms
together at once.
Our app begins
with a default first workflow
created automatically for me.
By inspecting my local project,
Xcode Cloud can tailor
these initial workflow settings
to match my team’s
existing configurations.
Workflows are made up
of a start condition,
an environment,
the set of actions
to be performed,
and post-actions
such as deployments
and notifications.
And I can see Xcode Cloud
selected every push
to the main branch
as the start condition,
the latest released Xcode
for my environment,
and archive actions
for both iOS and macOS.
I have the option
of changing these settings,
but this looks good to me,
so I’ll continue on.
For a deep dive
into workflow editing,
check out the “Explore
Xcode Cloud Workflows” session
later in the conference.
Next, I’ll authorize Xcode Cloud
to access my source code.
This is a one-time action
covering all source repositories
required to build my project
including the primary repo,
any submodules,
and private Swift packages.
For any publicly
accessible repositories,
no additional authorization
is necessary.
Xcode Cloud discovered
the two private repos
within my project,
so, next, we’ll grant
explicit permissions to GitHub
where the source is hosted.
Clicking Grant Access
takes me to App Store Connect
with more details
about the next steps.
It’s important to note
that this process will vary
depending on
the source provider,
and I can revoke access
at any time for any reason.
Granting source code access
to Xcode Cloud
is completed on the web,
and this assistant
guides me through the process.
First, I connect my Apple ID
with my source account,
which is used to enable
a personalized experience
in Xcode Cloud.
This step leverages
the provider’s
native authentication flow
and Xcode Cloud’s
secure encryption,
so I know my code
and personal information
remain protected.
Then I install
the Xcode Cloud application
to my GitHub organization,
enabling access
to the repos I select.
Great!
With those steps complete,
my GitHub account is all set.
Let’s finish the onboarding
in Xcode locally.
Repositories are ready.
I’ll continue.
In the final step,
Xcode Cloud will offer
to register my application
and bundle ID
to App Store Connect.
Our application
is already created,
so I’ll just confirm
the details here.
Everything looks good.
Now that my app is configured
for Xcode Cloud,
I can wrap up
the onboarding process,
which will kick off
my first build.
Looks like
my first build is finished.
Let’s take
a deeper look at the results.
The build group overview
shows my active
and completed builds
at a glance,
and clicking the first entry
opens up
the overview page for our build.
This overview shows me
brief details about the build
such as durations
and environment configurations,
with the lower section
showing me the status
of all actions
and post-actions involved.
Also, the top-right
has helpful buttons
to rebuild the run again,
and check out this revision
in my local environment.
Leaving the overview
and expanding an action node,
such as the passing
“Archive-iOS” one
shows the summary
of this specific action.
And within the view,
I can find logs and artifacts
produced by this run.
The logs page neatly organizes
all the tasks
within this action,
with filters available
at the top to focus
on areas that need attention.
I also have
easy access to binaries,
log files,
and other artifacts produced
by my build
in the artifacts page.
This all makes
for a very convenient way
for my teammates and I
to access our CI content
right here in Xcode.
Now let’s investigate why
the Mac archive action failed
by visiting the action summary.
Similar to the logs view,
I can filter these issues
by type for efficient triage.
Looks like our first CI build
caught an import issue
I previously missed
for our Mac app,
and since I’m triaging
my results in Xcode,
I can use this jump button
within an issue
to navigate directly
to the code I need to fix.
I’ll make a quick code change
to clean things up.
And I want our CI builds
to get off to a good start,
so I’ll go ahead and commit
and push it
to my remote repository.
And right after
I push my change,
I see Xcode Cloud
has started a new build for me.
And I can continue
to follow along
with all my changes live.
I’m pretty excited
with my quick progress.
By running our CI builds
on Apple’s Cloud Infrastructure,
our team will collaborate
on our project
more efficiently than ever.
Now, back to Holly
to join in on the fun.
[Holly]
Thanks, Geoff,
for getting Xcode Cloud set up
and running
for our project Fruta.
As a member of the same team,
I can open
the Fruta Xcode project
on my Mac
and see all of the workflows
and builds that Geoff
and the rest of our team
have been working on.
Here in the report navigator
on the Cloud tab
when I click on my project name,
because workflows
are shared within teams,
I can see the default workflow
that Geoff just created.
It looks like Build 2
that Geoff started
when he fixed the import error
has completed successfully.
Now that we have
a passing build,
let’s edit the workflow
to see what it does,
and find out what improvements
we can make
to get additional coverage
for Fruta.
I can right-click
on the workflow name
and select Edit Workflow.
Let’s start
by giving the workflow
a more descriptive name.
Let’s call this workflow
“Releases”
since we’re gonna be
building and testing
a couple of branches
we use for our releases.
Now,
let’s edit the start condition.
I’ll select
the start condition section
from the sidebar
to bring up the configuration.
Remember, the start condition
defines what needs to happen
to cause the workflow to run.
The default is set
to start when a code change
is pushed
to your main branch.
My team
also uses a release branch,
so let’s go ahead
and add that here too.
I just click on the plus button
in the custom branches section
and type my branch name
in the table row.
That looks good
for the start condition.
Now let’s move on to actions.
The default workflow
automatically creates
archive actions
for all platforms
that my project runs on.
This is a great foundation
to build upon,
but to add
some additional coverage,
I’d like to add some tests here.
I click the plus button
to the right
of the Actions header
in the sidebar
and select the Test action type.
For the Test action,
I can select the platform--
let’s do iOS--
then select the correct scheme,
Fruta iOS in our case.
In the sidebar,
there’s still a red X
next to our new Test action
because we haven’t yet
filled out everything
that’s required.
The last setting
I need to configure
is adding some devices
for these tests to run on.
Clicking the plus button
below the Destination table
automatically adds
recommended iPhone simulators...
And clicking one more time
adds recommended iPads.
I can also change these to pick
a specific device simulator.
Let’s choose the latest iPhone
to make sure my app
works great on iPhone 12.
Notice that all
of the destinations
I’ve added are automatically set
to use the latest OS version.
I can review
my workflow in the sidebar,
and everything looks good to me,
so let’s save the changes
by clicking the Save button
in the bottom right-hand corner.
Now that we’ve made changes
to the workflow,
I want to make sure it works
without having to make
a code change to start it.
I can do that manually
by right-clicking
on the workflow
in the report navigator
and selecting Start Build.
Next, I’m prompted to choose
which branch I want to run.
Let’s try it with “release/v1”
since we’ve just added
that branch to the workflow.
And from here,
I click Start Build
to kick it off.
Great, it looks like
our new build is running.
Now,
in the build group overview,
there’s a new section
for our release/v1 branch,
and the new build
I just started, Build 3,
appears here
with a running status.
After this completes,
I’ll have a good idea
of how our release branch
is doing.
Then I can continue to add
to the release workflow
or create new ones to support
how my team works.
Xcode Cloud
made it really simple
to adopt a continuous
integration practice
for our app.
With just a few clicks,
Geoff got us set up
and fixed an issue
that the workflow found.
Then I was able to easily see
everything he had already done,
and make our workflow
more robust.
Your team’s ability
to iterate on both code
and feedback productively
is essential to creating
a high-quality app or framework.
With Xcode Cloud,
you can easily setup CI,
and whether this
is a totally new practice
or makes your process seamless,
you can be more productive
and feel more confident
that your users
will have a great experience
with your product.
We hope this session
helped you get acquainted
with Xcode Cloud
and Continuous Integration.
From our team
in Vancouver, Canada,
and on behalf of Geoff
and myself,
thank you and enjoy
the rest of WWDC 2021.
[upbeat music]