[music]
[Paul]
[speaking Russian]
Hello, my name is Paul Borokhov, and I'm
an engineer on the SwiftUI Mac team.
I will be joined later by my colleague
Kate Kononenko on the Localization team,
and we will be talking to you about
how to localize your SwiftUI app.
To illustrate this process,
we will be using the Fruta sample app
that you might have seen before.
This application allows
you to browse a menu of smoothies,
order them, and also look at
the recipes to make them at home.
In this talk, we will be adding a Russian
localization to the app, since that's both
my and Kate's first language, and because
it is a good showcase for the different
localization best practices that you will
likely need to use in your own apps.
We'll go over some fundamentals
about how strings are localized
in SwiftUI and how easy it is
to avoid common design pitfalls.
We will discuss techniques
to style and format your strings and data,
and cover some improvements
to keyboard shortcuts localization.
Finally, Kate will give a demo
of the improvements we've made
to the localization workflow
in Xcode to make it easier than ever
to localize your apps.
One of the most critical parts
of localizing your application
is making sure that strings
in various pieces of your UI
are exposed to translators
and render correctly at runtime.
SwiftUI makes this easy for you, because
when you use a Text with a string literal,
it automatically performs a localized
string lookup in the main bundle.
In this example, I have a Done button
that's automatically localized at runtime
based on the translation
in my Russian strings file.
This also works for string interpolation,
so that you can embed variables into
your strings and they are automatically
converted to format specifiers
in the exported localizable
strings files and catalog.
New in Xcode 13, we now infer the format
specifier type automatically
based on the type of the variable
that is passed into the string.
Text accepts additional optional arguments
for table name and bundle,
in case you need more control.
In this example, we have placed
all of our ingredient-related strings
into a separate table called
"Ingredients."
Apart from the actual
ingredients of our smoothies,
we have also placed two variants
of the word "ingredients"
for two different contexts,
in the smoothie view and in
the recipe view, in this strings table.
We did this because Russian
requires these two words to be translated
differently based on the context,
as you can see.
You can learn more about
how to organize your strings
in the "Streamline
your localized strings" talk.
This all works because the first argument
to Text is the LocalizedStringKey type.
If you have custom views and methods
that accept string literals,
you can make them localizable
by using this type in place of String.
This way, literals that are passed as
arguments to these views and functions
are automatically extracted
during the Xcode localization
export process and then loaded
from the bundle at runtime.
An alternative approach, which we saw
earlier in the button example,
is to have your views
accept a Text argument instead.
Using LocalizedStringKey also allows
you to preview multiple locales at once
by specifying the locale of the
environment in your preview provider.
If you want to preview all
localized strings, including those
loaded with NSLocalizedString,
you can change the language
in the scheme editor,
as Kate will show you later.
New in Xcode 13,
exporting your project for localization
can actually build all targets
to find the localizable strings.
What this means in practice is
that Xcode can do a much better job
of finding localizable content
and extracting it for localization.
So imagine we had some code
with a multiline string.
Because the compiler is now
used in extracting the localized content,
this multiline string
literal is parsed correctly.
Now, let's take a look at
how SwiftUI makes it easy
for you to build apps
with localization-friendly layouts.
Just like with string lookup,
the default layout behaviors
provided by SwiftUI have been
designed with localization in mind,
and in most cases, should not require
any additional effort on your part.
For example, when appropriate,
controls with Text will wrap it
so that it does not clip or truncate
in languages with longer labels.
In this case, the smoothie name is wrapped
to a second line in Russian,
because it is longer.
Layouts are automatically flipped
for right-to-left languages, too.
You can see in the screenshot that the
table cell layout has been flipped,
and the symbols in the tab bar have been
mirrored when appropriate as well.
And even when you have to customize
something to deviate from the defaults,
the options we provide guide
you to localization-friendly solutions,
such as providing a leading,
rather than left, alignment in VStacks.
Next, in building your apps,
you might find yourself needing
to style the localized Text
that's displayed in your UI.
To make this easier,
we've introduced the ability
to style localizable strings
using markdown.
This significantly simplifies
applying styling to localized strings
and gives your translators the ability
to apply styling that's
sensible for their language.
For example, Arabic does not have
the concept of italics,
so even if you use
emphasis in your English strings,
your translator is able to use
a different treatment,
such as strong emphasis,
in their translation.
In this case, our Russian translator
was able to apply markup
around the most relevant
words in the string to match
the intent of the original
English description.
And while this
support exists in foundation,
SwiftUI makes it particularly
easy for you to take advantage of
by simply passing the styled
strings directly to texts for display.
You can find out more about
styling Text by checking out
the "What's New in Foundation"
and SwiftUI talks.
Another common scenario you'll
encounter in your apps is the need
to format data in a language
and region-appropriate manner.
New formatting APIs that are
easier to use and integrate
tightly with Text and TextField
will allow you to accomplish this task.
In Fruta, we show the number of calories
in a number of places in the UI.
In the past,
we had to create a measurement formatter
in order to display the formatted values,
similar to what's on the slide here.
Now, we can specify the format
in a declarative manner
directly inline with where
the value is being shown.
Not only is this easier to read,
it can also be more performant
than the code on the previous slide.
You can learn more about
these new formatting APIs
in the "What's New in Foundation" talk.
Finally, let's
consider keyboard shortcuts,
which allow novice and power
users alike to accomplish tasks
more quickly,
both on their Macs and their iPads.
New in macOS and iPadOS,
any keyboard shortcuts you define
in your SwiftUI app will now
be automatically adjusted
so that they can be typed on the user's
currently active keyboard layout.
For example,
if you want to add a smoothie to your list
of favorites,
you can type "Command plus" to do so.
This works great on the US layout,
where the combination requires
exactly two keypresses,
the Command and plus keys.
However, if you're using
a Lithuanian keyboard layout,
reaching the plus key is not so easy.
You must press the backtick key first,
then press "Shift equals."
Worse, this combination is actually
not typeable
while holding down the Command key.
But thanks to the remapping feature
of macOS Monterey and iPadOS 15,
when the Lithuanian keyboard layout
is active,
the shortcut is changed to
"Command ž"
and our users can add smoothies to their
favorites using keyboard shortcuts
no matter which keyboard
layout they are currently using.
And here's the best part,
you as the developer don't need
to do anything, it just works.
And with that,
let me turn it over to Kate,
who will show the improvements we've made
to the localization workflow in Xcode 13,
as well as demo some of the best
practices and new APIs I've just covered.
[Kate] Thanks, Paul.
Hi, I'm Kate,
an engineer on the Localization team.
Let's jump in to see how easy
it is to localize a SwiftUI app.
Here we have the Fruta sample app.
We want to make sure that people
all around the world can order smoothies
in their native language.
Today, I am going
to add a Russian localization.
So, first, I go to the project
in the project navigator,
then choose
"Fruta" in the project editor,
and under the Info tab,
I can add a localization.
All of the localizations
that macOS ships with are listed here
in alphabetical order.
In Xcode 12.5, we added hundreds
of more languages and regional variants
in the "More Languages" submenu
at the bottom of the list.
I'll just select "Russian."
As Paul mentioned,
Xcode 13 greatly simplifies
string extraction from Swift code by using
new technologies in the Swift compiler.
Fruta is written in SwiftUI, so I want to
make sure that the build setting
"Use Compiler to Extract Swift Strings"
is set to "Yes."
This is enabled by default
for new Swift projects,
but you can opt-in to this setting
if your existing project uses SwiftUI.
When I export for localization,
Xcode will build all the targets
in my project and use the compiler
type information to extract
LocalizedStringKeys from my SwiftUI code.
Before exporting,
I can use pseudolanguages
in SwiftUI Previews to see which strings
are localizable and which I've missed.
So, I'll go to the scheme editor,
and under the Options tab,
click App Language.
All of the languages that are supported by
my app are listed here at the top,
but I'll go all the way to the bottom
and choose Accented Pseudolanguage.
The accented pseudolanguage
adds different accent marks
to my source strings in the UI.
Now, I can see that all
of the ingredients are pseudolocalized.
The measurements are not pseudolocalized
because they are formatted,
but the StepperView should
have been pseudolocalized.
Let's make this string localizable.
StepperView is a custom SwiftUI
view that takes in a "label" string
and passes it down to a Text view.
In custom SwiftUI
views that require localization,
we need to use LocalizedStringKey.
Let's make sure it's pseudolocalized now.
Great!
Now that this string is localizable,
we need to make sure
it handles plurals properly.
This code works for pluralizing "smoothie"
in English, but it's not going to work
for all words and it's not
going to work for all languages.
Let's use a stringsdict instead.
A stringsdict file can
provide different translations
for a plural variant in a language.
For more information about how
to use stringsdict, check out
the "Streamline Your Localized Strings"
video.
I have a file prepared right here,
so I'll just drag it into my project...
and mark it for localization.
Now, let's export for localization.
Starting in Xcode 12.5,
you can export and import
localizations for projects
and workspaces in the Product menu.
So I'll just click Export Localizations,
and let's save it to the desktop.
Now, Xcode is building my project and will
create an Xcode Localization Catalog
ready to send to Paul, who has
volunteered to translate it to Russian.
You can learn more about
Xcode Localization Catalogs
in the "New Localization Workflows
in Xcode 10" talk from WWDC 2018.
Let's double-check what was exported
before sending it out for translation.
Starting with Xcode 13,
Xcode Localization Catalogs
are even more convenient to work with.
I can simply double-click on the catalog
in Finder and open it in Xcode.
This is super useful if you're
localizing your own app,
verifying strings or screenshots
before sending content out
for localization, or if fixing
translations for specific languages.
Here in the editor, I can see all
of the files that require localization.
When I select a file, I can see all
of the strings as the translator would.
The key, the source string,
the translation, and a comment.
I'm just going to skim through
here and see if everything looks good.
Right away, I can see a couple of issues.
First, we exported
the "%lf Calories" string.
That string should be formatted
because different regions
use different
units for measuring calories.
I'll need to make
a change in code to fix that.
Here in the NutritionFactView
where the string was extracted from,
instead of a string,
I can use the "formatted" method
in my Measurement type
on my NutritionFacts struct.
I'm going to use wide formatting
and set the usage to "food,"
since we're measuring food calories.
This will take care of formatting
the units for all regions.
That was an easy fix.
Let's go back to reviewing my strings.
Ooh, translators
do not see the variable name,
so a string like "Buy recipe
for %@" could be confusing.
Am I buying a recipe for a certain price,
or am I gifting it to a friend?
Let's see if there are any
other ambiguous strings.
"Favorite" has
a comment saying it's a verb,
but I should add a comment to "Favorites"
so it's clear that it's a noun.
I'll add comments
in code for both of those.
Let's take care of the "Buy
recipe for" string first.
There we go.
The "Favorites" string is in my tab bar
items, so let's add a comment for it, too.
Tab bar items are Label views.
In SwiftUI, to add comments I need
to initialize a Label with a Text view.
Adding comments like this is
really important for ensuring
high-quality localizations.
I don't want my translators to be
confused and have to guess what I meant.
Okay, I think I fixed everything.
Time to export a fresh
catalog and send it to Paul.
[email sent, received]
Wow, that was fast.
Paul is
the Apple Silicon of translators!
Let's take a quick
peek at what he sent back.
Here, I can see all of the translations.
There's the stringsdict for the smoothie
stepper that I've added.
Looks good. Let's import this
and see how the app looks like in Russian.
To import, I just go to the Product menu,
click Import Localizations,
and then choose the Catalog from Paul.
All my strings should be localized now.
Let's build and run
the app in Russian for macOS.
First, I'll change the scheme to macOS,
and then I can
change the language to Russian.
Okay, let's run it.
Wow,
the app looks awesome in Russian,
and all of the smoothies look delicious.
I can see the ingredients and all
of the nutritional value for all of them.
I think I actually will order this one.
Wow, what a great service.
Localization in SwiftUI was designed to be
easy, so you can focus on writing code.
Here are some key points to keep
in mind as you develop your app.
LocalizedStringKey is a special
type that signals SwiftUI
to look up localized strings
in your bundle.
Use it in custom SwiftUI views
to make them ready for localization.
Enable the "Use Compiler
to Extract Swift Strings" build setting
to extract LocalizedStringKeys from code
when exporting for localization in Xcode.
Format your strings to internationalize
your code, and style them with Markdown.
Use Text to add comments
for additional translation context.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC!
[speaking Russian]
[music]