[music]
[Jeremy]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Jeremy Goldman,
an engineer on the XCTest team.
In this session,
we're going to explore
some exciting new ways
to interact with devices
from UI Tests in Xcode 13.
In particular,
we're going to focus
on three new interactions
across three
different platforms:
the iPadOS Pointer,
the watchOS Digital Crown,
and the macOS trackpad.
Let's start with
the iPadOS Pointer.
In iPadOS 13.4,
Apple introduced mouse and
trackpad support,
providing users
with a brand new way
to interact with iPad,
using accessories like
the Magic Keyboard.
Many developers have
taken full advantage of this
by adding pointer-specific
behavior and interactions
to their iPad apps,
like custom hover animations.
In Xcode 13,
we're providing
a powerful new API
for controlling
the iPadOS Pointer in UI Tests.
This API will enable you
to create robust automated tests
for multiple types of pointer
interactions
in your iPad apps
and will be available for use
with devices running
iPadOS 15 and later.
Let's examine this
new API in more detail.
First, we're adding
a new property on XCUIDevice
to indicate whether or not
a device supports
pointer interaction.
Next, we're adding new methods
on XCUIElement
for performing
different pointer interactions,
like hovering,
multiple types of clicking,
and two-finger scrolling.
We're also adding methods
for more advanced click-and-drag
use cases
as well as a class method
for executing blocks of code
with one or more
modifier keys held down.
These methods are also
available on XCUICoordinate,
if additional precision
is required.
Let's explore how these
new APIs work in practice
by creating a new UI Test
for a pointer interaction
in an iOS app.
In this demo,
I'll be using the Fruta app,
which has a sidebar
that's initially hidden
on launch.
I recently added
pointer-specific functionality
on iPad, where a horizontal
two-finger trackpad swipe
opens the sidebar.
Let's add a UI Test for that.
Here I have an empty
UI Test class,
which is where
I'll add my new UI Test.
Let's quickly walk through
what this test is doing.
It starts by launching the app
and then asserting
that the sidebar
is not initially present
on launch.
Then it performs a horizontal
two-finger trackpad swipe
and asserts that the sidebar
is now present.
One other thing
I'd like to point out
is this availability attribute
I've added on the test method.
This is necessary
whenever you're using methods
that are only available starting
with a specific iOS version.
In this case,
the pointer interaction APIs
were introduced in iOS 15.0.
Let's try running the test
on the iPad simulator.
You can follow along
with the cursor indicator,
which is the dark circle
near the bottom left corner
of the screen.
[no audio]
Great! It looks like
our test works on iPad.
However, this app is also
available on iPhone,
which does not support
pointer interaction.
Let's try running this test
on the iPhone simulator.
[no audio]
So it appears the test failed
with an error message that
"Pointer events are
not supported on this device."
To resolve this,
we need to modify our test
so that it only
executes on devices
that do support
pointer interaction.
We can do this by using
XCTSkipUnless with the new
supportsPointerInteraction
property on XCUIDevice
to skip the test on unsupported
devices, instead of failing.
[no audio]
Now let's try running the test
on the iPhone simulator again.
[no audio]
Perfect.
So now this test will be skipped
on devices that don't support
pointer interaction.
Let's talk about some new ways
to interact with devices
on other platforms,
more specifically,
watchOS and the Digital Crown.
As you may already know,
Xcode 12.5 introduced
UI Testing support
for watchOS apps.
This support includes methods
newly available on watchOS
for synthesizing touch events
as well as
hardware button events,
like clicking the crown.
In Xcode 13,
we're expanding this support
with a new method
for synthesizing
Digital Crown rotation.
This method requires
just one parameter,
the number of rotations,
and has an optional
velocity parameter
to specify the speed at which
the crown should be rotated.
This velocity parameter
has type XCUIGestureVelocity,
which means you can either
use one of the preset values,
like slow, fast, and default,
or you can specify
a custom decimal value
in rotations per second.
Let's see how this new
method works in practice.
Say I have a simple
weather app for watchOS
that displays the current
temperature outside.
The app has a feature
where users can scroll
the digital crown forward
to see forecasted temperatures
at future times
or scroll backward
to see the recorded temperature
at past times.
Let's walk through
a basic UI Test
that makes sure this
crown rotation functionality
behaves as expected.
The test starts
by launching the app
and then asserting
that the forecast time label
initially says
Current Temperature.
Then, we rotate the digital crown
one full rotation forward,
and assert the label updated
to say "One hour from now."
After that, we rotate the crown
two full rotations backward,
and the test finishes
by asserting
that the label updated
to say "One hour ago."
Finally, let's talk about
the macOS trackpad.
More specifically,
let's focus on scrolling.
Scrolling can be broken down
into two different categories:
discrete and continuous.
Discrete scrolling has
precise incremental movement.
Think about rotating
the scroll wheel
on a physical mouse.
The on-screen content
moves in uniform increments
for each tick
on the scroll wheel,
and the movement
is non-inertial,
meaning it stops moving
immediately
when you stop
rotating the scroll wheel.
On the other hand, continuous,
or phased scrolling,
has fluid and dynamic movement.
Picture swiping with
two fingers on a trackpad.
The on-screen content
scrolls smoothly
while you're swiping,
and the movement is inertial,
meaning it continues moving
after you lift your fingers off
until it gradually
comes to a stop.
XCTest currently provides
a scroll method on macOS
that enables you to perform
discrete pixel-precise scrolling
in your UI Tests.
This method
requires two parameters
to specify the exact
horizontal and vertical distance
in pixels to scroll.
In Xcode 13,
we're introducing new methods
for synthesizing continuous
or trackpad-like scrolling
on macOS.
These methods accept
an optional velocity parameter
to specify the speed
at which you'd like to scroll.
This velocity parameter
has type XCUIGestureVelocity
which means, just like in
the rotateDigitalCrown method
we explored earlier,
you can either use the presets
or you can specify
a custom decimal value
in pixels per second.
Xcode 13 introduces APIs
across multiple platforms
to enable automation
of new input methods
and provide support
for more specialized use cases.
Use this new functionality
to create UI Tests
for pointer-specific
interactions in your iPad apps,
automate digital crown rotation
in your watchOS UI Tests,
and perform continuous,
trackpad-like scrolling on macOS
with the new swipe methods.
If you're interested
in learning more,
make sure to check out
these related sessions.
Thanks for watching
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[music]