[music]
[Curt] Hi, welcome to "Discover
concurrency in SwiftUI."
I'm Curt Clifton,
an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Later, I'll be joined
by my colleague Jessica.
Swift 5.5 introduces
a variety of new tools
for managing concurrency
in your Swift code.
In this talk, Jessica and I
will help you understand
how these improvements
interact with your SwiftUI apps.
I’ll walk through
how the new tools
can help you make
your data models even better
and show you how SwiftUI works
with the new main actor.
Then Jessica will show you
how to connect
your concurrent data model
to your SwiftUI views
and introduce some
great new APIs
that take advantage of Swift’s
new concurrency tools.
To make the most
of the information
Jessica and I will be sharing,
it’s important to have
some background
on Swift’s new
concurrency support.
We recommend you watch
“Meet async/await in Swift”
and “Explore structured
concurrency in Swift”
before diving into
the rest of this video.
When I was a child,
I always dreamed
of being an astronaut.
I sometimes work in a spaceship,
but otherwise
that particular childhood dream
didn't come true.
Still, I haven't lost
my enthusiasm for space.
So I decided to apply
my actual skills
as a SwiftUI engineer
to build an app
to download
space-related photos.
Let's take a look at
the app I have planned.
The app shows a list
of random space photos.
These colors are just beautiful.
When I see
a photo I really love,
I can save it to view later.
In order to fetch
these beautiful images,
my app is going to interact with
a web service
using a REST API.
This sounds like a perfect use
of the new concurrency features
introduced in Swift.
Let's start with our data model.
I’m using a SpacePhoto struct
to hold the information
for a single image.
The struct has fields
like the title,
a description of the photo,
the date the image was posted,
and a URL pointing
to the actual image.
I made my type Codable
so that I can easily
instantiate instances
from a server response
or save them to disk,
and Identifiable
so I can use them in ForEach
and other data driven views.
Next, I want to display
a list of these entries.
For that, I need a model
that will fetch and hold
a collection of them.
I'm using a Photos class
for this.
By making my Photos class
conform to ObservableObject,
my SwiftUI views
will automatically update
whenever my data updates.
I'm using a published property
to store an array
of SpacePhotos.
To fetch updated items
from the REST endpoint,
I’m using
an Update Items method.
I’ll talk about that
in more detail shortly.
But first I’d like to rough in
a basic user interface.
This is the user interface
I want to build.
So far, I just have
my tab view in place
and a basic PhotoView.
My PhotoView takes a space photo
and displays its title.
That’s enough plumbing
that I’ll be able to see
my data model in action.
Let’s look
at the Catalog view next.
My Catalog view
will show the list of photos.
To do that,
I'll add a State Object
and instantiate it with
my Photos observable object.
In the body of my view,
I'll add a NavigationView.
Using a navigation view here
will let me add
a large
navigation title shortly.
Next, inside my NavigationView,
I’ll add a List.
And inside my List,
I’ll use a ForEach
to map over my photos,
showing a PhotoView
for each of them.
With that,
I can see my sample data.
That’s as far as I need to go
for now,
but let’s add just
a bit more polish here.
First, here’s the promised
navigation title.
Now, the default inset list
style here looks great,
but to really show off
my space photos,
I want to switch
to a plain style
so the photos will really pop
against the black background.
I can make the list style plain
using the new enum-like
static member syntax here.
With this syntax,
SwiftUI’s style modifiers
get a more concise spelling
with better support
for autocompletion in Xcode 13.
Finally,
let me use another feature
new in SwiftUI this year:
control of list separators.
Inside my ForEach,
I can use
the listRowSeparator modifier
to hide the separators.
Sometimes when I’m polishing
a user interface with SwiftUI,
I find it hard to stop.
But I’ll leave the UI for now.
Jessica is planning to finish it
after I’m done
with the data model.
Before I dig into
the data model though,
I’d like to talk just a bit
about how SwiftUI interacts
with your observable objects.
And how
the new concurrency features
in Swift 5.5
make this interaction
easier than ever to get right.
At Dub Dub 2020,
in “Data Essentials in SwiftUI,”
my colleague Raj talked about
the SwiftUI update life cycle.
I’ll refer to the code
that drives this life cycle
as the “run loop.”
With Swift 5.5, the run loop
runs on the main actor.
For more details on actors
in general,
check out the talk,
“Protect mutable state
with Swift actors.”
Jessica and I will focus
on the main actor in this talk.
The SwiftUI run loop
receives events from your user,
lets you update your model,
and then renders your SwiftUI
views to the screen.
I like to call these updates
the “ticks of the run loop.”
Let’s unroll this loop so we can
look at multiple ticks in a row.
In SwiftUI,
ObservableObjects can interact
with the SwiftUI run loop
in some interesting ways.
Let’s go back
to the Photos ObservableObject
and look
at the updateItems method.
I’m going to call updateItems
from my SwiftUI views
and it will run
on the main actor.
Let’s use this blue rectangle
to show the time
when updateItems is running.
I want to focus
on this line of code
where I assign the fetched
photos to my “items” property.
Because “items”
is a Published property,
this assignment triggers
an objectWillChange event,
immediately followed
by writing the fetched photos
to the storage for “items.”
When SwiftUI sees
this objectWillChange,
it takes a snapshot of my items.
On the next tick of the run loop
after the snapshot,
SwiftUI compares the snapshot
to the current value.
Because these
values are different,
SwiftUI knows to update my views
that depend on Photos.
Note that because
objectWillChange,
updating the storage,
and the run loop tick
all happen on the main actor,
they’re guaranteed
to happen in order.
In the 2020
“Data Essentials” talk,
Raj describes slow updates
when your view does
too much work in body.
Slow updates can also happen
if your model code
does too much work
on the main actor.
For example,
suppose my fetchPhotos
function blocks
while waiting
for the download to complete,
and suppose
I’m on a slow connection.
Because I’m blocking
the main actor,
I miss this tick
of the run loop.
This is visible
to my users as a hitch.
In the past,
you might have dispatched
to another queue
to perform the work,
so that
the expensive fetchPhotos
occurs off of the main thread.
This might seem to work fine,
but I have a tricky issue here.
I’m changing my ObservableObject
from off the main actor.
It’s possible for my changes
and the run loop tick
to interleave.
For example,
when I assign to “items,”
and SwiftUI takes
its objectWillChange snapshot,
it’s possible that this happens
immediately before
a tick of the run loop.
The state change
hasn’t happened yet,
so SwiftUI compares the snapshot
to the unchanged value.
The actual state change happens
after the run loop tick,
but SwiftUI
doesn’t see that change,
and so my views aren’t updated.
To update correctly,
SwiftUI needs these events
to happen in order:
objectWillChange,
the ObservableObject’s state
is updated,
and then the run loop
reaches its next tick.
If I can ensure
that these all happen
on the main actor,
I can guarantee this ordering.
Prior to Swift 5.5,
I might have dispatched
back to the main queue
to update my state,
but now it’s much easier.
Just use await!
By using await to make an
async call from the main actor,
I let other work continue
on the main actor
while the async work happens.
This is called “yielding”
the main actor.
In updateItems, I can use await
to yield the main actor
back to SwiftUI
during my long running I/O,
so it can keep
the run loop ticking
and avoid any UI hitches.
When the async work completes,
Swift re-enters my updateItems
method
back on the main actor,
so I can update my state.
Let’s see how this works.
Instead of dispatching
to another queue,
I simply await the result
of the long running operation.
When I write await,
the updateItems function
yields control of the main actor
so that the run loop
can continue.
When the awaited fetch
is complete,
the main actor
re-enters my function,
so that I can safely update
my published property,
triggering objectWillChange,
and making the new value
available to SwiftUI.
Let’s jump into Xcode and see
if I can make fetch happen.
Here’s the updateItems method
that I showed on the slides.
To implement fetchPhotos,
let’s start by adding the code
to fetch a single photo.
I’ll make my fetchPhoto method
take the URL
of a photo
from the rest endpoint,
and return a SpacePhoto.
Next,
I’ll use the new async version
of the data convenience
on URLSession
to fetch the data from the URL.
[no audio]
To stub this in,
I’m using a forced try.
I’ll clean that up shortly.
Ah, the data method is async,
so I need to use await.
And that means I need to make
my fetchPhoto method async.
OK, great.
Now that I have my data,
I’ll use
the Decodable initializer
to instantiate a photo
and return it.
[no audio]
Let’s look at fetchPhotos next.
I’ve stubbed in some code
to get a random selection
of dates
and loop over them.
I want to build up an array,
so I’ll make “downloaded” a var,
and add a date variable
to my loop.
Inside the loop, I’ll call
a helper method I already have
to construct
the rest endpoint URL
for fetching a particular date.
Then, I’ll call
my fetchPhoto method
and append
the results to my array.
[no audio]
And let’s build.
Ah, because fetchPhoto is async,
I need to await the result.
And that means fetchPhotos
needs to be async, too.
I’m making these calls
to fetchPhoto
sequentially for simplicity.
Check out Swift 5.5’s
task groups
for even more powerful options.
Now, I just need
to await fetchPhotos
like I showed in the slides.
And with that,
my update logic is in place.
Now,
maybe you’re as nervous as I am
by these forced tries
to make fetch happen.
Let’s clean that up.
For now, I’ll return nil
when the download fails.
[no audio]
Then in fetchPhotos,
I’ll only add
the non-nil values to my array.
Now that Photos
uses async-await,
I can be sure it won’t run into
any of the tricky
objectWillChange bugs
I discussed,
as long as it runs
on the main actor.
But how can I ensure that?
Luckily, the Swift compiler
can help me here.
By adding the new @MainActor
annotation to Photos,
the compiler will guarantee
that the properties and methods
on Photos
are only ever accessed
from the main actor.
With that done,
the model is in place.
Next, Jessica will connect
our views to the model
and show you
some great new SwiftUI APIs
for leveraging concurrency
in your apps.
Jessica?
[Jessica] Thank you, Curt.
Let’s switch over
to the CatalogView
and use the updateItems method
that Curt just showed us.
I want to call updateItems
whenever my Catalog shows.
In the past, you might have used
onAppear for this,
but starting this year
in SwiftUI,
use the task modifier.
Task lets you associate
an asynchronous task
with your view.
The task starts at the beginning
of the view’s lifetime.
Task is async by default,
so inside its closure,
I can call updateItems
on myPhotos object
and await the results.
This is a great use of task,
but there’s even more
to this new modifier.
A task’s lifetime
is tied to the view’s lifetime,
so you can do things
like waiting on
an async sequence
and responding to its values.
And the task will be
automatically canceled
when the view’s lifetime ends.
For more on view lifetime,
be sure to check out the talk
“Demystify SwiftUI.”
Using live preview, I can see
that the entries are updated.
But we’re still missing
the beautiful images.
I’ve already been
updating the PhotoView
that Curt showed earlier.
I’ll add some background
materials behind the title.
Now, let’s add the images.
Happily,
using the new AsyncImage API,
loading images
from a remote server
is easier than ever.
All I have to do
is get the image URL
I want to fetch
out of our entry,
and pass it to AsyncImage.
[no audio]
Well, this is a little
too big at its full size,
so let’s use the overload
of AsyncImage
that lets me adjust the image
and show a placeholder
so that users know
their image is loading.
[no audio]
Next,
I’ll make the image resizable
and set its aspect ratio
to fill the space.
[no audio]
Finally, I’ll add
a minimum width and height
to make my image flexible.
Using a non-zero minimum
height
will also make sure that the
progress view
peeks out over my title area.
[no audio]
Like the rest of SwiftUI,
AsyncImage comes built with
intelligent defaults,
so even if there are errors
loading your image,
the result will be to continue
showing the placeholder.
You can also choose to customize
the error handling behavior.
To do that, check out
“AsyncImage’s overload
that uses a phase.”
It would also be great
if users could save
their favorite images
to view later.
Let’s add a button
to this title area to do that.
The button will trigger
an async action
to save the image entry to disk.
Saved entries will appear
in the Saved tab in our app.
I’ve already stubbed in
a view to do this.
Let me add it here, then we can
take a look at its code.
[no audio]
Here’s the stubbed-in
version of my Save button.
Let’s add an action
to save the photo.
Button actions in SwiftUI
are synchronous,
but my “save” method
is asynchronous.
To call the method,
I’ll start an async task.
Then, inside the closure,
I’ll call the “save” method on
“photo.”
It’s asynchronous,
so I’ll just use await.
I think it would be nice
to show a progress view
while the save is taking place.
To do that,
I’ll add a State property.
[no audio]
Then, I’ll update the State
around my call to save.
[no audio]
Then, I’ll update the label
on my button
to show a progress view
when the save is happening.
I’m using “opacity”
to hide the Save label
and an overlay
to show the progress view.
This combination ensures that
the button stays the same size,
based on the localization
of the word “save.”
[no audio]
Finally, I’ll disable the button
while the save is happening.
Let’s see how this works
with live preview.
That’s pretty great!
Let’s go back to the Catalog
view to put it all together.
SwiftUI has a great new modifier
this year
that you can use
to give people the ability
to manually refresh their data.
By adding the refreshable
modifier to my List,
I tell SwiftUI that
this content is refreshable.
I can provide an async closure
to refreshable
and call our updateItems method
to update the List.
As I showed earlier with “task,”
I’ll use await
on this async method.
The refreshing indicator
dismisses automatically
when my
asynchronous work is done.
Now, I can pull down
to refresh my images,
tap Save
to save an image I like,
and switch to my Saved tab
to see my saved images.
Swift’s new features
make it easy to work
with concurrent data.
SwiftUI integrates nicely
with Swift’s concurrency
features
to provide you
the best behavior by default.
In many cases,
you just need to use await
to leverage the power
of concurrency.
Mark your ObservableObject
as “@MainActor”
for more robust checking
that your object updates
in ways that work well
with your views.
Take advantage of SwiftUI’s
API additions
to write safe and performant
concurrent apps
with minimal effort.
Use AsyncImage
to concurrently load images.
Add the “refreshable”
modifier to your view hierarchy
to allow users
to manually refresh their data.
Like we saw
with the Save button,
you can use Swift’s
new concurrency features
in your own custom views.
As we all know,
concurrency is tricky.
It’s a hard problem,
but with these
new language features
and SwiftUI APIs,
you now have the tools to manage
that complexity in your apps.
We hope you enjoyed learning
about the great new concurrency
tools
in Swift 5.5 and SwiftUI,
and we look forward to seeing
all the ways you use them
to tackle tricky problems
in your apps.
[music]