[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Preston Lewis: Hi,
my name is Preston,
and today I'm going
to be talking about
how to bring accessibility
to charts in your apps.
Let's go over
what we're going to cover today.
First, we'll talk about
some of the benefits
of making your charts
accessible.
Then, we'll go over
some principles
for making inclusive decisions
for the visual aspects
of your chart.
Next, we'll discuss how to make
your charts
perceivable and navigable
with VoiceOver.
And lastly, we'll talk about
an exciting new feature
called "audio graphs" and how
to support them in your app.
So, let's get started.
Data is so important
in our modern world.
We use data every day to make
decisions about our finances,
our health, our goals,
and so many other things.
But in order to make
any use of data,
we have to be able
to understand it.
Charts are useful because they
allow us to quickly understand
what our data is telling us
without having to get too deep
into the details.
But charts are not
inherently accessible
for blind or low-vision people.
There's no value in a visual
chart if you can't see it.
The accessibility team has been
working hard for years
to make data more accessible
to blind and low-vision people.
This year, you can bring
the full power of your charts
to people with blindness
or low vision
by supporting audio graphs
in your apps.
Let's look at an example.
Here is an example app showing
historical birth rates
from the year 1917 to 1975.
When you look at this chart,
you can immediately see
some interesting features.
You can see that the birth rate
decreased to a minimum
around the year 1935,
and then quickly increased
to about the year 1960
and then decreased again.
We can give blind and low-vision
people the same ability
to quickly get
a sense of the data
using the new audio graph
VoiceOver feature.
Let me show you how it works.
First, I'm going to find
the Audio Graph menu
in the VoiceOver rotor.
VoiceOver: Audio graph.
Preston: Then I'll swipe down
until I hear "Chart Details".
VoiceOver: Play audio graph.
Chart details.
Preston: Then I'll double-tap
to open the audio graph
Explorer view.
VoiceOver: Audio graph. Heading.
Preston: Then I'll navigate
to the Play button
to play the audio graph,
which will play the data series
as a continuous tone.
VoiceOver: Twentieth-century
birth rates.
Play audio graph. Button.
Preston: Let's listen to it now.
[FLUCTUATING TONE]
VoiceOver: Complete.
Preston: Wasn't that exciting?
What you just heard was the same
chart as the one you see,
represented auditorily
instead of visually.
The pitches you heard correspond
to birth rates over time
with lower pitches
meaning lower values
and higher pitches
meaning higher values.
These pitches exactly mirror
the line in the visual chart.
So even without seeing
the chart,
the audio graph allows you to
perceive its important features
in just a few seconds.
Now that we have
a general sense of the data,
let's get more precise
information
about the features
we're interested in.
The next thing
we might want to know
is approximately what
the maximum birth rate was
and what year it occurred.
To do this, audio graphs
provide an interactive mode
where VoiceOver users
can double-tap and hold
and then drag to listen
to the data at their own pace.
If they pause, VoiceOver
will read the data value
corresponding to
the user's current position
in the audio graph.
Let's use this interactive mode
to try to find the maximum birth
rate and what year it occurred.
VoiceOver: Twentieth-century
birth rates.
[FLUCTUATING TONE]
[HIGH PITCHED TONE]
Data point. 1960.
268 births per 10,000 people.
Preston: By scrubbing through
the audio graph
until we heard
the highest pitch,
then pausing to hear
the data value,
we can tell that
the maximum birth rate
was 268 per 10,000 people
around the year 1960.
Because we know the maximum
occurred around 1960,
we might even be able to infer
that this peak corresponds
to the baby boom era.
We can figure all of this out
just from the sonified
representation of the chart.
OK, now let's look at an example
of a different kind of chart.
This chart is a scatter plot
showing the relationship
between vehicle weight
on the X axis
and fuel efficiency
on the Y axis
for several different types
of automobiles.
In the audio graph
for this chart,
each tone you hear
will represent a data point
for one automobile,
just like each visual data point
on the visual chart.
The pitch of each tone
will represent
the automobile's fuel efficiency
in miles per gallon,
so higher pitches signify more
fuel-efficient vehicles.
Take a second to think about
what you expect to hear
when I play this audio graph.
Let's hear what it sounds like.
Try to listen to hear
whether the data is trending
upwards or downwards.
[VARIED INDIVIDUAL
AND OVERLAPPING TONES]
VoiceOver: Complete.
Preston: Hopefully you heard
the downward trend.
This trend means
that bigger automobiles
tend to be less fuel-efficient
in this data set.
Imagine how much longer
it would have taken
to understand this relationship
if we only had the raw
data points available to us
and we had to look at each
data point individually.
Also, if you were
listening closely,
you might have heard
the very high-pitched outlier
in this data set.
It sticks out in the audio graph
just like it sticks out
in the visual chart
and happens to be the only
hybrid vehicle in this data set.
If you wanted to get more
information about the outlier,
you could use
the interactive mode
to navigate through the data
until you hear
the highest pitch,
then pause to hear
the data value,
just like we did
with the birth rate chart.
In addition to the audio graph,
this explorer view
provides summary information
about important
features of the data
like shape, trend, and outliers,
which are inferred from an
automatic statistical analysis
of this chart's data.
Along with the audio graph,
VoiceOver can read
this summary information
to complete our understanding
of the data.
OK, let's quickly recap the
benefits of accessible charts.
Making your charts accessible
allows your data-rich
applications
to reach wider audiences,
including blind
and low-vision people.
It will empower your users
by giving them helpful tools
for understanding
the data in your charts,
which will help them leverage
the incredible power of data
in their personal
and professional lives.
And lastly, with new API
coming this year,
making your charts
is easier than ever before.
I'm really excited to show you
how to support audio graphs
in your apps,
but we need to cover
some general
chart accessibility
topics first,
starting with how
you can make your charts
more visually accessible.
There are a few simple things
you can do
to make your visual charts more
understandable for everybody.
Take this chart as an example.
This is simple line chart that
shows average monthly rainfall
for tropical and arid regions.
Let's apply some
accessibility principles
to improve the visual
accessibility of this chart.
First, it's important to use
high-contrast colors
whenever possible.
High contrast between
foreground and background colors
makes your chart easier
to look at and understand,
especially for people
with low vision.
As you can see,
the lines' contrast
against their background
is pretty low.
The title and label text
also seem a bit dim.
Let's update these colors
to have higher contrast
against the background.
That's much better.
You can check contrast
ratios between colors
to determine whether or not
the contrast is sufficient.
The Accessibility Inspector
that comes bundled with Xcode
has a Color Contrast Calculator
that you can use.
It's good to aim for contrast
ratios of at least 4.5:1.
The next thing you can do
to improve your chart's
visual accessibility
is to avoid problematic
color pairings.
It's generally good practice
to avoid using red and green
together if possible.
Red and green color blindness
is the most common type
and using these colors together
can make your chart difficult
to understand for some people.
So here's the line chart again,
with a green line representing
rainfall in tropical regions
and a red line representing
rainfall in arid regions.
You can probably tell
which data series is which
using the color encoding
in the legend.
But if you have deuteranopia,
a form of red-green
color blindness,
the chart might look something
more like this to you.
It would be hard for you to tell
which line represents
tropical rainfall
and which line represents
arid rainfall with these colors.
Let's improve this by replacing
the red color with blue.
This might not seem
like a huge change,
but to someone with
red-green color blindness,
this chart might now
look like this.
With this small adjustment,
it becomes easy for someone
with red-green colorblindness
to spot the difference
between the series.
It's also good to avoid using
blue and yellow together
because this family
of color blindness
is the second most common.
These are some
good improvements,
but let's take this
one step further
by using symbols
in addition to color
for distinguishing
your data series.
Using data symbols makes it so
that people can understand
your chart without having
to rely on color at all.
So here's our chart again.
And now let's add some symbols
for each data series.
Notice the tropical data series
has circles now,
and the arid data series
has squares.
You can tell which series
is which now
just by looking
at the associated symbols.
This means that even a person
who can't perceive color at all
can now understand your chart.
It's good to do all of
these things by default,
but again, sometimes design
or product constraints
might limit
your choice of colors
or decision to include symbols.
In these cases, you can still
provide an accessible experience
by supporting a few simple
accessibility settings.
If you can't have symbols in
your chart for the default case,
you can still provide
an accessible experience
by adding symbols when the
Differentiate Without Color
system accessibility
setting is enabled.
If you can't easily change your
color set for product reasons,
consider adopting
higher-contrast colors
when the Increase Contrast
accessibility setting is set.
Reducing the use of transparency
can also make your chart
more visually accessible.
If your chart uses
transparency effects,
consider disabling them
when the Reduce Transparency
accessibility setting is on.
If you're building a macOS
rather than an iOS app,
each of these settings
has a counterpart on macOS
that you can support.
You'll find links to developer
documentation for these APIs
in the materials
for this session.
Now let's look at how we can
make your data navigable
for VoiceOver.
Now, I love coffee,
and I love programming.
Let's pretend for a minute
there's a relationship
between the amount
of coffee consumed
and amount of code an engineer
produces as shown in this chart.
Just pretend.
Also, the data goes up
to 12 cups of coffee,
But don't worry,
no engineers were harmed
in the making of this data;
it's all made up.
All right, let's see how we can
make this data navigable
for VoiceOver users.
Here's an example snippet of
code from a chart view class
and its corresponding
model object.
The chart view might have
a reference to its model,
and a function
for drawing itself.
And the model might have the
chart's title and data points
contained in a simple struct.
The first thing
you'll want to do
is make the chart a container.
This will help VoiceOver group
your chart elements correctly
and aid in navigation.
To make your chart a container,
simply override
accessibilityContainerType
on your ChartView
and return the semanticGroup
container type.
Again, this is important
for VoiceOver navigation
and communicating which elements
belong to the chart.
Next, we need to give our chart
an accessibilityLabel.
This tells VoiceOver
what to speak
when it encounters your chart.
Typically, this should
just be your chart's title
or something similar
that VoiceOver can speak
to uniquely identify
your chart in your UI.
Last but not least,
you'll want to provide
an accessibility element
for each data point.
You can provide these elements
by overriding your chart view's
accessibilityElements property.
This will create elements
inside your chart
that VoiceOver can navigate,
so that people
can get information
about individual data points.
To implement this,
you can simply use "map"
to build an array
of accessibility elements
from your list of data points.
For each data point,
we'll create a new
UIAccessibilityElement object,
specifying the ChartView
as its accessibilityContainer.
Then, we'll provide a string
representation of the data point
for the element's
accessibilityValue property.
This string is
what VoiceOver will speak
when it navigates
to these data point elements.
In your code,
you'll probably want
this string to be localized,
and you may want to use
a strings dictionary
to define proper
pluralization rules.
For this example, though,
let's just keep it simple.
Lastly, we need to provide
an accessibility frame
for our element so that
VoiceOver knows where it lives
on the screen.
You'll probably already have
logic for computing the frame
for each data point elsewhere,
since you needed this
to draw the visual chart.
If you have it available,
you can reuse that logic here.
You can now return your finished
accessibility element
for this data point.
All right! Let's see what
we've accomplished so far.
VoiceOver: Cups of coffee
versus lines of code.
Zero cups.
Twenty lines of code.
One cup.
Thirty lines of code.
Two cups.
Thirty-five lines of code.
Three cups.
Thirty-two lines of code.
Preston: Great!
As you heard,
VoiceOver now speaks the title
when it focuses an element
inside the chart
because we made the chart
a semantic group
and gave it
an accessibility label.
We also made it possible to
navigate through each data point
by creating
a UIAccessibilityElement
to represent each one.
There's one more thing I want
to mention before we move on.
Sometimes you might
have hundreds
or even thousands
of data points.
In these cases, you definitely
don't want to make
an accessibility element
for each data point
because there will just be
way too many to navigate.
Instead, we suggest
breaking up your chart
into reasonable intervals and
making an accessibility element
for each interval
rather than each data point.
This will provide
a better navigation experience
as well as improve performance
while still being
understandable.
We're not done yet;
we can do even more.
Making data navigable
is important,
but we're still only presenting
raw data to VoiceOver users
one point at a time.
The value of charts
is their ability to show us
what the data
is really telling us,
and to help us look beyond
individual data points.
This is where audio graphs
come in.
So now -- finally --
let's talk about
how to implement audio graph
support for your chart.
Imagine we have
a ChartModel struct
that contains all the
information we need
to define a particular chart.
In your code,
you probably have a model object
that looks something
like this already.
If you don't, don't worry.
These concepts will
still apply to your code
however it's organized.
For our example, let's say a
chart has a title and a summary,
it has an X and a Y axis,
and each axis has a title
as well as a numeric range
representing the minimum
and maximum displayable values
for the axis.
And lastly, it has
an array of data points
containing our chart's
actual data.
We'll use the information
in this example model object
to enable the audio graph
feature for our chart.
First, import
the Accessibility framework,
then extend your ChartView class
to conform to the AXChart
protocol.
Conforming to the AXChart
protocol is easy
because there's only
one property to support.
You just need to implement
accessibilityChartDescriptor.
The chart descriptor
object you construct
will contain all of
the information VoiceOver needs
to provide
the audio graph experience.
Let's walk through how to build
one of these chart descriptors
step by step.
First, we need to create an axis
descriptor object for each axis.
Each axis descriptor provides
information to VoiceOver
about whether it represents
categorical or numerical data,
the range of displayable
values for the axis,
the positions of grid lines,
and how to format
speakable data values.
Since the X axis is numeric
for our coffee chart,
we'll create a numeric
axis descriptor.
If we had categorical data
on our X axis,
we'd use a categorical
axis descriptor instead.
We'll provide the title
and range for this axis
using our model object.
We can also optionally provide
the positions of grid lines
on this axis if we have them.
When you provide grid lines,
they're represented in the
audio graph as haptic feedback
during playback and interaction.
We'll leave this empty for now
since we don't have any X-axis
grid lines in this chart.
For numeric axes,
we also need to create
a valueDescriptionProvider
closure.
This closure is very important
because it tells VoiceOver
how to speak
the values on this axis,
so it can say "5 cups"
instead of just saying "5".
For this axis, we'll format
the description to speak "cups"
after the value.
Again, in your code,
you would probably want
to localize this string
with proper pluralization rules,
but let's keep this example
simple.
We'll do the same thing
to create an axis descriptor
for our Y axis, except we'll
format our value description
to say "lines of code"
rather than "cups."
Now that we have the basic
structure of our chart defined,
let's add the data.
To do this, you add
a data series descriptor
for each data series.
We only have one data series
in this chart,
so we'll just create
one data series descriptor,
passing in the name
of the series,
whether or not it is continuous,
and the actual data points
for this series.
You should pass "false"
for "isContinuous"
when the series
is visually represented
using discrete marks,
like points or bars,
and you should pass "true"
when the series is visually
represented as a line.
For the series' data,
we need to provide an array
of AXDataPoint objects.
The easiest way to do this
is to just map them
from the data
in the chart model.
We're almost there!
We just have one last
thing to do.
And that's to put
all the pieces together
to build our
AXChartDescriptor object.
We'll give it a title,
which should, again,
be the title of our chart.
Then, if we have one, we can
provide a summary of our chart.
This is kind of like providing
alt text for your chart.
You should use this property
to communicate
the most important insights
from your data
in a sentence or two.
This summary text
will be presented to users
in the audio graph
explorer view.
This can be incredibly helpful
to VoiceOver users
trying to understand your chart.
Lastly, we'll provide the axis
and data series descriptors
we created earlier to complete
our chart descriptor
and then we'll return it.
That's it!
Let's see the final result.
VoiceOver: Audio graph.
Play audio graph.
Chart details.
[BEEP]
Audio graph. Heading: Cups of
coffee versus lines of code.
Play audio graph. Button.
[VARIED INDIVIDUAL TONES]
Complete.
Preston: Let's recap.
Be sure to make
accessible choices
for the visual design
of your chart.
This includes using
good contrast ratios,
using symbols
in addition to color
to differentiate
categories of data,
and avoiding color schemes
that might be problematic
for colorblind users.
Be sure to expose
your data elements
in the accessibility tree
to make them
perceivable and navigable
to VoiceOver users.
And last but not least,
implement the AXChart protocol
and accessibilityChartDescriptor
on your chart view
to allow VoiceOver users
to get the same value out
of your chart as sighted users.
Now you have everything you need
to create rich, accessible
charts for everyone.
We hope you'll use these tools
to empower your users
since data is so incredibly
important in our lives.
Charts are one of our
very best tools
for understanding data
in a data-rich world,
and now you can bring
this benefit to everyone!
♪