[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Sergey Kamensky: Hello,
everybody and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Sergey Kamensky
and I'm a software engineer
in Vision framework team.
The topic of today's session is
to show how Vision framework
can help with people analysis.
Our agenda today
consists of two main items.
First we're going to have
an overview
of people analysis technology
in Vision framework.
While doing that,
we will be specifically
focusing on the new additions.
And second, we're going
to have the in-depth review
of the new person segmentation
feature.
Let's start with people analysis
technology first.
The cornerstone
of people analysis in Vision
is person face analysis.
Since the inception
of Vision framework,
we've been adding
and enhancing
human face analysis
capabilities.
We currently offer
face detection,
face landmarks detection, and
face capture quality detection.
Face detection functionality
in Vision framework
is exposed by the means of
DetectFaceRectanglesRequest.
Our face detector offers high
precision and recall metrics,
it can find faces
with arbitrary orientation,
different sizes,
and also partially occluded.
So far we have
supported occlusions
like glasses and hats.
Now we are upgrading
our face detector
to revision number three which,
in addition to improving
all existing great qualities,
can now also detect faces
covered by masks.
The main function
of our face detector
is of course to find
face bounding box,
but it can also detect
face pose metrics.
Previously, we have provided
roll and yaw metrics only.
Most metrics
are reported in radians
and their values are returned
in discrete bins.
With the new
revision introduction,
we're also adding a pitch metric
and thus completing
the full picture.
But we didn't stop there.
We're also making
all three metrics
reported in continuous space.
All face pose metrics
are returned as property
of our FaceObservation
object,
which is the result of executing
the DetectFaceRectanglesRequest.
Let's look at the demo app
that is designed to show
face pose detection
functionality.
The app processes
camera feed
by running Vision face detector
and presents face pose metrics
to the user
after converting the results
from radians to degrees.
For better tracking
of the metric changes,
the app uses red color gradient
to show when face pose metrics
increase in positive direction
and blue color gradient
to show when the metrics
increase in negative direction.
In both cases,
the lighter the color is,
the closer the metric is
to the zero position.
The zero position for each
metric is what you would call
a neutral position
of a human head,
when the person is looking
straight -- just like this.
As we already discussed,
we have three face pose metrics:
roll, yaw, and pitch.
These terms come
from flight dynamics
and they describe
aircraft principle axes
with respect to the aircraft's
center of gravity.
The same terms have been
adopted to describe
human head pose as well.
When applied to head pose --
or as we also call it,
face pose --
they track human head movement
as following.
Roll is tracking head movement
in this direction.
When I'm going
from the most negative
to the most positive
values of roll,
you can see that
the background color changes
from dark blue to light blue,
neutral, then light red,
and finally dark red.
Similar color changes are
happening with the yaw metric,
which is tracking the angle
when the head
is turning right or left.
And finally, the pitch metric
is tracking my head movement
when my head
is nodding up or down.
Here you can see again
similar color changes
when I'm going
from the most negative
to the most positive
end of the spectrum.
Face landmarks detection
is another important function
of our face analysis
suite.
Face landmarks detection
is offered by means of
DetectFaceLandmarksRequest,
and the latest revision
is revision number three.
This revision offers
76-point constellation
to better represent
major face regions
and also provide
accurate pupil detection.
Face analysis suite
also includes face capture
quality detection.
This holistic measure
takes into account
attributes like human face
expressions, lighting,
occlusions, blur,
focusing, et cetera.
It is exposed via
DetectFaceCaptureQualityRequest API
and the latest revision
of this request
is revision number two.
It is important to remember
that face capture quality
is a comparative measure
of the same subject.
This feature works great,
for example,
to pick the best photo
out of the photo burst series
or to pick the best photo
to represent a person
in the photo library.
This feature is not designed
to compare faces
of different people.
Human body analysis
is another big section of
the people analysis technology
offered by Vision framework.
Vision provides several
functions in this area,
which include
human body detection,
human pose detection,
and last but not least,
human hand pose detection.
First let's take a look
at the human body detection.
This function is offered via
DetectHumanRectanglesRequest,
and it currently detects
human upper body only.
We are adding new functionality
to this request,
and therefore upgrading this
revision to revision number two.
With the new revision,
in addition to
the upper-body detection,
we also offer
a full-body detection.
The choice between
the upper-body
and the full-body detection
is controlled via
the new upperBodyOnly property
of the
DetectHumanRectanglesRequest.
The default value
for this property is set to true
to maintain
backwards compatibility.
Human body pose detection
is offered in Vision framework
via
DetectHumanBodyPoseRequest.
Processing this request provides
a collection of human body
joint locations.
Revision number one
is the latest
and the only available
revision of this request.
Vision framework also offers
human hand pose detection
as DetectHumanHandPoseRequest.
Similar to human body
pose detection,
processing of
the hand pose request
returns a collection
of human hand joint locations.
We're upgrading functionality
of this request
by adding an important property
to the resulting observation,
hand chirality.
The new chirality property
of the HumanHandPoseObservation
will contain information
whether the detected hand
was left or right.
If you want to learn
more details
about hand pose detection,
I recommend watching
the "Classify hand poses and
actions with Create ML" session.
This concludes our overview
of the new upgrades
to the people analysis
technology suite.
It is time now to move to the
second topic of our session,
which is person segmentation.
What is person segmentation?
In very simple terms,
it's the ability to separate
people from the scene.
There are numerous
applications
of the person segmentation
technology nowadays.
You are all familiar,
for example,
with virtual background feature
on video conferencing apps.
It's also used
in live sport analysis,
autonomous driving,
and many more places.
Person segmentation also powers
our famous Portrait mode.
Person segmentation
in Vision framework
is a feature designed
to work with a single frame.
You can use it
in streaming pipeline,
and it's also suitable
for the offline processing.
This feature is supported
on multiple platforms
like macOS, iOS,
iPadOS, and tvOS.
Vision framework implements
semantic person segmentation,
which means that
it will return a single mask
for all people in the frame.
Vision API
for person segmentation
is implemented by means of
GeneratePersonSegmentationRequest,
This is a stateful request.
As opposed to traditional
requests in Vision framework,
the stateful request objects
are reused throughout
the entire sequence of frames.
In our particular case,
using request object
helps with smoothing temporal
changes between the frames
in fast-quality level model.
Let's take a look at
the Person Segmentation API
offered by Vision framework.
This API follows
an already familiar
and established pattern.
Create a request,
create a request handler,
process your request
with the request handler,
and finally,
review the results.
Default initialization of
GeneratePersonSegmentationRequest
object
is equivalent to setting
revision, qualityLevel,
and outputPixelFormat properties
to their default values.
Let's review all properties
one by one.
First is the revision property.
Here we set the revision
to revision number one.
This is the default
and the only available revision,
since we're dealing
with the new request type.
Even though there is technically
no choice here today,
we always recommend
to set explicitly
to guarantee deterministic
behavior in the future.
This is because if new revisions
are introduced,
the default will also
change to represent
the latest available revision.
Second is
the qualityLevel property.
Vision API offers
three different levels:
accurate, which is also
the default one;
balanced; and fast.
As far as the use cases go,
we recommend using
accurate level
for computational photography.
This is the use case where
you would like to achieve
the highest possible quality
and are typically
not limited in time.
Using similar logic,
balanced level is recommended
for video frame-by-frame
segmentation
and fast for streaming
processing.
The third property
is the output mask format.
We are going to review
the resulting mask in details,
but here I would like
to mention that, as a client,
you can specify which format
the resulting mask
will be returned in.
There are three choices here:
unsigned 8-bit integer mask
with a typical 0 to 255
quantization range,
and two floating point
mask formats --
one with 32-bit full precision
and another
with 16-bit half precision.
The 16-bit half precision
is intended to provide you with
a reduced memory
floating point format
that can be inserted directly
into further GPU-based
processing with Metal.
So far we have learned
how to create, configure,
and execute our
person segmentation request.
It is time now
to look at the results.
The result of processing
person segmentation request
come in form of
PixelBufferObservation object.
PixelBufferObservation
derives from observation
and it adds an important
pixelBuffer property.
The actual CVPixelBuffer object
stored in this property
has the same pixel format as our
person segmentation request
was configured with.
Processing of
person segmentation request
will produce
a segmentation mask.
Let's look at the original image
and three different
quality level masks
generated by executing
person segmentation request.
Fast, balanced, and accurate.
Let's zoom in to look
at the details of each mask.
As expected, when we go
from fast to balanced
and eventually to accurate,
the quality of the mask
increases
and we'll start seeing
more and more details.
Now let's examine
the different mask levels
as a function of quality
versus performance.
When we move
from fast to balanced,
and eventually to accurate,
the quality of the mask goes up
but so does the resource usage.
The dynamic range,
mask resolution,
memory consumption,
processing time all go up
when the mask quality
increases.
This represents a trade-off
between the quality
of the segmentation mask
and the resource consumption
needed to compute the mask.
So you already know everything
about mask generation
and their properties.
What can you actually do
with the masks?
Let's start with three images.
The input image,
the segmentation mask
that was obtained by processing
the input image,
and the background image.
What we would like to do
is to replace the background
in the original image in the
area outside of the mask region
with the background
from a different image.
When you execute
such blending operation,
we end up with the young man
in the original image
being transported from the beach
promenade to the forest.
How does this blending sequence
look like in the code?
First let's assume we have done
all relevant processing
and already have
our three images:
the input image, the mask,
and the background.
Now we need to scale both
the mask and the background
to the size
of the original image.
Then we will create
and initialize
the Core Image blending filter.
You probably noticed that
I created my blending filter
with the red mask.
This is because
when CIImage is initialized
with one component
PixelBuffer --
as all our masks are --
it creates an object with
the red channel by default.
Finally, we perform the blending
operation to get our results.
Let's take a look how we can use
person segmentation feature
in Vision framework.
Our second demo app,
which is available
for downloading,
combines face pose
metric detection
with the new person
segmentation capability.
The app processes camera feed
by running face detection
and person segmentation.
Then that takes up
the end segmentation mask
and uses it to replace
the background in the area
outside of the mask pixels
with a different color.
The decision of what
background color to use
comes from the combination
of values
for roll, yaw, and pitch
at any given point in time.
I'm currently located in a room
with a table and chairs,
and the demo app shows
my segmented silhouette
over the new background,
which is the color mix
corresponding to
my head position.
Let's see if it tracks
roll, yaw, and pitch changes.
When I turn my head like this,
roll is a major contributor
to the background
color mix decision.
When I turn my head
left and right,
yaw becomes
the major contributor.
And finally,
nodding my head up and down
makes pitch
the major contributor.
Vision framework
is not the only place
that offers
person segmentation API.
There are several other
frameworks that offer
similar functionality powered
by the same technology.
Let's take a brief look
at each one of them.
First is the AVFoundation.
AVFoundation can return
a person segmentation mask
in some of the newer-generation
devices
during photo capture session.
The segmentation mask
is returned
via PortraitEffectsMatte
property of AVCapturePhoto.
In order to get it,
you will first need to check
if it's supported;
and if it is,
enable the delivery of it.
The second framework that
offers person segmentation API
is ARKit.
This functionality is supported
on A12 Bionic and later devices,
and is generated when processing
camera feed.
The segmentation mask
is returned
via segmentationBuffer property
of ARFrame.
Before attempting
to retrieve it,
you need to check if it's
supported by examining
supportsFrameSemantics
property
of ARWorldTrackingConfiguration
class.
The third framework
is Core Image.
Core Image offers a thin wrapper
on top of Vision person
segmentation API,
so you can perform
the entire use case
within the Core Image domain.
Let's take a look now
at how person segmentation
can be implemented
using Core Image API.
We will start
with logging an image
to perform segmentation on.
Then we will create
a person segmentation CIFilter,
assign an inputImage to it,
and execute the filter
to get our segmentation mask.
We have just reviewed
multiple versions
of person segmentation APIs
and Apple SDKs.
Let's summarize to see
where each one could be used.
AVFoundation is available
on some of iOS devices
with AVCaptureSession.
If you have a capture session
running,
this will be your choice.
If you're developing
an ARKit app,
you should already
have an AR session
where you can get
your segmentation mask from.
In this case, ARKit API is
the recommended one to use.
Vision API is available
on multiple platforms
for online and offline
single-frame processing.
And finally, Core Image
offers a thin wrapper
around Vision API,
which is a convenient option
if you want to stay within
the Core Image domain.
As any algorithm,
person segmentation
has its best practices --
or in other words,
the set of conditions
where it works best.
If you're planning to use
person segmentation feature,
your app will perform better
if you try to follow
these rules.
First, you should try to segment
up to four people in the scene
where all people
are mostly visible,
while maybe
with natural occlusions.
Second, the height
of each person
should be at least
half of the image height,
ideally with good contrast
compared to the background.
And third, we also recommend
you to avoid ambiguities
like statues,
pictures of people,
people at far distance.
This concludes our session.
Let's take a brief look
at what we have learned today.
First, we had an overview
of the person analysis
technology in Vision framework
while focusing on the upgrades
like masked face detection,
adding face pitch metric,
and making all face pose metrics
reported in continuous space.
We also introduced
new hand chirality metric
to the human hand pose
detection.
In the second part,
we took a deep dive into
the new person segmentation API
added to Vision framework.
We also looked into other APIs
offering similar functionality
and provided the guidance
where each one could be used.
I really hope that by watching
this session,
you have learned new tools
for developing your apps
and are really eager
to try them right away.
Before we finish today,
I would like to thank you
for watching,
wish you good luck,
and have a great
rest of the WWDC.
♪