[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Nate] Hi, I’m Nate, an engineer
on the Swift team here at Apple.
Today my colleague Robert
and I will tell you about
async/await in Swift.
Asynchronous programming is
a regular activity
for many of you.
So you know it’s all too easy
to write asynchronous code
that’s verbose,
complex, and even incorrect.
Async/await in Swift
can help out.
Using it,
you can write asynchronous code
just as easily
as you write regular code.
And when you do, your code
will better reflect your ideas.
It’ll be safer too.
On top of that,
the SDK has hundreds
of awaitable methods
available for you to use.
For example,
UIKit provides functionality
to form a thumbnail
from a UIImage.
In fact,
it provides both synchronous
and asynchronous functions
to complete that task.
As a quick reminder,
when you call a function
that is synchronous--
that is,
a regular old function--
your thread is blocked, waiting
for that function to finish.
So if your fetchThumbnail
function
calls preparingThumbnail--
the synchronous function
UIKit provides--
until it finishes,
your thread
can’t do anything else.
In contrast, if you call
prepareThumbnail
(of:completionHandler:)--
the asynchronous version
of that function--
while it runs, your thread
is free to do other work.
When it’s done,
it will notify you by calling
its completion handler.
The SDK provides many
asynchronous functions.
They let you know
that they’ve completed
in a few different ways.
Some use a completion handler
like this.
Others rely
on delegate callbacks.
And many are marked async
and just return a value.
What these asynchronous
functions all have in common
is this: when you call one,
it unblocks your thread quickly,
having kicked off its work.
That allows the thread
to do other things
while that long
running work completes.
To see that difference,
let’s take a look
at an example that may be
familiar to many of you.
In the app Robert
and I are building together,
we have a list of items,
each row of which displays
a thumbnail of an image
stored on a server.
When it’s time to get
a thumbnail ready to be
displayed in that list,
in our view model,
the fetchThumbnail method
is called.
It transforms a string
to a UIImage via a series
of steps.
First, the view model’s
thumbnailURLRequest method
creates a URLRequest
from the string.
Next, URLSession’s
dataTask method gets
the data for that request.
Then UIImage initWithData
creates an image from that data,
and finally,
UIImage’s prepareThumbnail
method renders a thumbnail
from the original image.
Each of these operations depends
on the previous one’s result.
That means they must
be performed in sequence.
Some of these operations
return values quickly--
both constructing a URLRequest
from a string and a UIImage
from data are like this--
so it’s fine to run them
on whatever thread
the function happens to be on
and for these
to be synchronous calls.
However, some of them take time.
It takes awhile to download all
the data that makes up an image.
And rendering a nice-looking
thumbnail from it requires
a device to do
some expensive work.
That’s why the SDK
provides asynchronous functions
to complete those tasks.
So these calls
should be asynchronous.
Before Robert and I took
async/await out for a spin,
we were writing the function
using completion handlers.
The function takes
as its arguments a string,
the input to the first operation
and a completion handler,
used to give the output
back to the caller.
When fetchThumbnail is called,
we first
call thumbnailURLRequest.
This method is synchronous,
so it doesn’t need
a completion handler.
Next we call dataTask
on the shared
URLSession instance,
passing that URLRequest
and a completion handler.
It synchronously produces
a URLSessionDataTask
which must be resumed to kick
off the asynchronous work.
FetchThumbnail then returns,
and the thread is
free to do other work.
That’s really important
because downloading
an image takes time,
and you don’t want
to block a thread waiting
for data to stream in.
Eventually either the image
finishes downloading
or something goes wrong.
Either way,
the request completes
and the completion handler
passed to dataTask is invoked
with several optional values:
the data, a response,
and an error.
If something does go wrong,
then we need to invoke
the completion handler
and pass the error along.
If everything worked out,
then we create an image
from the data using
UIImage’s initWithData.
Because it’s synchronous,
we get to write normal
straight-line code
to handle the results.
If no image is produced,
we’re done.
And if an image was produced,
then finally we call
UIKit’s method prepareThumbnail
on it
and pass a completion handler.
While its work completes,
the thread is unblocked
and freed up to do other work.
After the thumbnail is prepared,
that completion handler is
invoked with an image
if preparing a thumbnail
succeeds or else nil.
If it does succeed, then we call
our completion handler
and pass along the image.
But as Robert pointed out to me,
there’s a problem.
FetchThumbnail’s caller
expects to be notified
when fetchThumbnail finishes
its work, even if it fails.
And currently, we’re leaving
the caller in the lurch.
I’m so used to writing
“guard else return”
that I forgot to invoke
the completion handler twice.
So if creating a UIImage
from data
or preparing a thumbnail fails,
the caller of fetchThumbnail
will never be notified
and the row
will never be updated.
It’ll just show
a spinner forever.
That’s why it’s
so important for us,
the authors of fetchThumbnail,
to notify our callers
no matter what happens.
So every path
through the function
should notify them.
To do that, we need to invoke
our completion handler
if an error occurs
and pass the error along.
A normal function
gives an error back
to its caller by throwing it.
And Swift ensures that
no matter how execution
proceeds through the function,
if a value isn’t returned,
an error is thrown.
But we can’t use Swift’s usual
error handling mechanism here.
We can’t just throw
an error from within
these completion handlers
if we run into a problem.
That’s unfortunate
because it means
Swift can’t check our work.
To Swift, a completion handler
like fetchThumbnails
is just a closure.
While we want to be sure
that it’s always invoked,
in Swift there’s no way
to enforce that it is.
That’s why I didn’t get
a compilation error
when I just returned
from those two guards.
It took Robert
pointing out that there was
a problem for me to fix it.
So it’s up to you to make sure
that your completion handler
eventually gets called.
When the two of us sat down
to write this function,
we just wanted to do a few
operations one after the next.
Two were synchronous
and two were asynchronous,
taking completion handlers.
We succeeded, but we ended up
with around 20 lines of code
containing five opportunities
for subtle bugs to creep in.
What we wanted was to perform
those four operations
in sequence,
but what we got is hard
to follow,
hard to get right,
and obscures our intent.
Now, there are ways we could
have made this a bit safer.
For example, we could’ve used
the standard library’s
result type.
And while this is a little
safer, it also adds ceremony,
making our code uglier
and slightly longer.
People have also used
techniques like futures
to improve asynchronous code
in other ways.
But none
of these approaches give us
code that is simple, easy,
and safe.
With async/await,
we can do better.
Robert and I rewrote
the function
that performs those four steps.
And this time,
we used async/await.
The function still takes
a string as an argument.
But while last time,
a completion handler was passed
as well, this time instead,
the function is async.
When you mark a function async,
the keyword should go just
before “throws” in the function
signature, like this,
or before the arrow
if the function doesn’t throw.
Marking the function
async allows it
and its signature to be simpler.
If an image
is thumbnailed successfully,
that thumbnail is
simply returned.
And if an error is encountered,
it’s just thrown.
When fetchThumbnail is called,
just like before,
it starts off by calling
thumbnailURLRequest.
This function is synchronous,
so the thread
is blocked, doing its work.
Next, it starts downloading data
by calling data(for: request)
on the shared URLSession.
Like dataTask,
this method is also provided
by Foundation
and is also asynchronous.
But unlike dataTask,
the data method is awaitable.
So after it’s called,
it suspends itself quickly,
unblocking the thread.
The thread is then free
to do other work.
“Try” is here because the data
method is marked “throws.”
In the earlier version, remember
how we had to check for an error
and then explicitly call
our completion handler with it?
Here in the awaitable version,
all of that code is
boiled down
to just the try keyword.
Just like “try” is
needed to call functions
that are marked “throws,”
“await” is needed
to call functions
that are marked “async.”
If an expression has multiple
async function calls in it,
you only need
to write “await” once,
just like you only need
one “try”
for an expression with multiple
throwing function calls.
All told, the function call
is marked “try await.”
When dealing with an async
expression that throws,
you’ll need to put try
before await, like this.
Eventually, when the data
finishes downloading,
the data method will resume
and return to fetchThumbnail.
At that point, the values
the data method returns
or error it throws will flow in.
If it threw an error,
then fetchThumbnail
will throw that error
in turn itself.
Otherwise, the data and response
variables will be defined.
This is similar to what happened
in the earlier version
of fetchThumbnail
when the completion handler
passed to URLSession’s
dataTask method was invoked.
In both versions,
values and errors that were
produced by URLSession’s
asynchronous method flowed in.
But the awaitable version
is so much simpler.
It says exactly what we mean.
Make this request
and assign the values
we get back to variables
so we can use them.
And if we happen to run
into a problem, throw an error.
Next, fetchThumbnail
will try to create
a UIImage
from the data it downloaded.
If that succeeds, then
a thumbnail will be rendered
for that image by accessing
its thumbnail property.
While the thumbnail is formed,
the thread is free to do
other things until the thumbnail
property eventually resumes
and returns to fetchThumbnail.
If a thumbnail is rendered,
fetchThumbnail will return it.
Otherwise, it’ll throw an error.
In contrast to the
completion handler version,
if no thumbnail is rendered,
Swift ensures that we throw
an error here or return a value.
But we can’t just silently fail.
And that’s it.
That’s the all code we need.
The function does exactly
what the completion
handler version did before.
But instead of 20 lines of code,
it just has 6.
And it’s all straight-line code.
The four operations
that need to be performed
in sequence are listed
one after the next.
And Swift makes sure
that the function always
notifies its caller
when it’s done,
either by returning or by
throwing if a problem comes up.
This is just one example of how
using async/await can transform
your asynchronous Swift code,
making it safer, shorter,
and making it better reflect
your intent.
Let’s dig in
to some of the details
of how fetchThumbnail
is implemented.
On the second-to-last line,
even though there’s
no function call,
the expression that kicks off
rendering the thumbnail
is marked with “await.”
That’s because
the thumbnail property is async.
Not just functions can be async.
Properties can be too,
so can initializers.
Now, the thumbnail property is
not part of the SDK.
It’s actually one
that Robert added.
Let’s take a look at it.
He defined this property
in an extension on UIImage,
and its implementation is short.
It forms a CGSize
and awaits the result
of passing it along
to byPreparingThumbnail(ofSize).
By the way,
this method on self is
the awaitable version
of the method we used earlier.
There are a couple things
to notice.
First, it has
an explicit getter.
This is required to mark
a property async.
As of Swift 5.5,
property getters can also throw.
And like with async
function signatures,
if a property is both
async and throws,
the async keyword goes
right before throws.
Second, the property has
no setter.
Only read-only properties can
be async.
In functions, properties,
and initializers,
await can be used
on expressions to indicate
where the function might
unblock the thread.
There’s another place that await
can be used as well:
in for loops to iterate
over async sequences.
An async sequence is
just like a normal sequence
except that it vends
its elements asynchronously.
So fetching the next item
must be marked
with the await keyword,
indicating that it’s async.
As the function iterates
over the async sequence,
over and over,
it may unblock the thread
while awaiting the next element
and then resume
either with the next element
into the body of the loop
or, if there are no elements
left, after the loop.
To learn more
about AsyncSequence,
watch the “Meet AsyncSequence”
session.
And if you’re interested
in running
many asynchronous tasks
in parallel,
check out the “Structured
concurrency in Swift” session.
So there are a lot of places
where you can use await.
The keyword indicates
that your async function
might suspend there.
What does it mean for an async
function to suspend?
To answer that,
let’s think about what happens
when you call a function.
When you call any function,
you hand control of the thread
your function’s running on
over to that function.
If it’s a normal function you’re
calling,
like thumbnailURLRequest here,
then the thread will be
fully occupied doing work
on behalf of that one function
until it finishes.
That work might be in the body
of the function itself
or in other functions
that it calls.
Eventually,
that function will finish,
either by returning a value
or throwing an error.
When it does, it hands control
back to your function.
That’s the only way
that a normal function
can give up control
of a thread: by finishing.
And your function is the only
one it can give control to.
If it’s an async function you’re
calling, things are different.
Like a normal function,
when it’s done,
it will finish and return
control to your function.
But unlike a normal function,
it can give up control
of the thread in an entirely
different way: by suspending.
Just like a normal function,
when you call an async function,
you give control
of the thread to it.
Once it’s running,
an async function can suspend.
When it does, it gives up
control of the thread.
But rather than giving control
back to your function,
it instead gives control
of the thread to the system.
When that happens,
your function is suspended too.
Suspending is the function’s way
of telling the system,
“I know you have
a lot of work to do.
You decide
what’s most important.”
How cooperative is that?
So once
the function suspends itself,
the system is free to use
the thread to do other work.
At some point, the system
will decide that the most
important work to be done
is to continue running
the async function that had
suspended itself earlier.
At that point,
the system will resume it.
That async function is
then back in control
of the thread and able to keep
going about its work.
And if it wants,
it can suspend itself again.
In fact, it can suspend itself
as many times as it needs to.
On the other hand, it may not
need to suspend itself at all.
While an async function
may suspend,
just because it’s marked async
doesn’t necessarily mean
that it will suspend.
And by the same token,
just because you see an “await”
doesn’t mean the function
will definitely suspend there.
But eventually,
whether without ever suspending
or after resuming
for the last time,
the function will finish,
handing control of the thread
back to your function,
along with a value or an error.
Let’s take another look
at fetchThumbnail to see
what can happen
when it suspends.
When fetchThumbnail calls
URLSession’s async data method,
the data method stops executing
on the thread in the special way
that only async functions can:
by suspending.
It gives control of the thread
to the system and asks
the system to schedule the work
for URLSession’s data method.
But at this point,
the system is in control,
and that work may not be
started immediately.
The thread can be used
for other things instead.
Let’s see how that might happen.
Suppose that
after fetchThumbnail
has been called,
the user taps a button
which will upload some data.
Say, for example,
that they react to a post.
Then the system is free
to execute the work
to post the user’s reaction
before the previously
queued-up work.
Once that late-breaking
work has completed,
URLSession’s data
method may be resumed.
Or the system might execute
other work instead.
Finally,
once the data method finishes,
it will return
to fetchThumbnail.
The fact that other work
can be performed
while a function is suspended
is why Swift insists
that you mark async calls
with the await keyword.
You need to be aware
that the state of your app
can change dramatically
when your function suspends.
Now, this is also true
when you use
completion handlers.
But because you don’t have
all the ceremony
and indentation they entail
in async/await code,
the await keyword is
how you notice that a block
of code doesn’t execute
as one transaction.
The function may suspend,
and other things may happen
while it’s suspended between
the lines of the function.
More than that,
the function may resume
onto an entirely
different thread.
To learn about these issues,
see the “Protect mutable
state with Swift actors”
session.
Here are a few important things
to remember about async/await.
First, when you mark
a function async,
you’re allowing it to suspend.
And when a function
suspends itself,
it suspends its callers too.
So its callers must be async
as well.
Second, to point out where
in an async function it might
suspend one or many times,
the await keyword is used.
Third, while an async
function is suspended,
the thread is not blocked.
So the system is free
to schedule other work.
Even work that gets kicked off
later can be executed first.
That means your app’s state
can change a great deal
while the function is suspended.
Finally,
when an async function resumes,
the results returned from
the async function it called
flow back
into the original function,
and execution continues
right where it left off.
You’ve seen
how async/await works in Swift.
Now Robert will show you
how to start using it
in your own projects.
[Robert] Thanks, Nate.
Earlier, Nate showed you the app
we’re building together.
The thumbnail function
he converted
to adopt async/await
was called in a few places,
so we’ll need to migrate them
to adopt concurrency as well.
Let’s start
with something critical
to modern software
development: testing.
We wanted testing async code
to be just as easy
as testing synchronous code,
so XCTest supports
async out of the box.
What used to be
a tedious process
of setting up an expectation,
calling the API under test,
fulfilling the expectation,
and then making sure to wait
for an arbitrary amount of time
becomes as easy as adding
the async keyword
to the test function,
removing
the XCTest expectations,
its fulfillment,
and the explicit await,
and instead awaiting the results
of calling the new asynchronous
fetchThumbnail function
that Nate showed you earlier.
Now that our tests are settled,
let’s zoom in
on the application code itself.
In particular,
the SwiftUI code behind
the thumbnail views
in each of row of this list.
An image cell
is created with a post,
and each post has an ID
that we pass to the viewModel
so it can asynchronously
retrieve the thumbnail.
You’ve already seen how
to transform this call
from the testing code,
so let’s give it a shot.
First we remove
the completion handler,
then “try” is added
to handle any errors,
and “await” to complete the call
to an async function.
But when we try to build
this code, something goes wrong.
The Swift compiler is telling us
that we cannot call
async functions
in contexts
that aren’t themselves async.
Here, the onAppear modifier
takes a plain,
non-async closure, so there
needs to be a way to bridge
the gap between the synchronous
and the asynchronous worlds.
The solution is to use
the async task function.
An async task packages up
the work in the closure
and sends it to the system
for immediate execution
on the next available thread,
like the async function
on a global dispatch queue.
Its main benefit here
is that async code can be
called from inside
of sync contexts.
After another rebuild,
the compiler is satisfied.
Async tasks are part
of a family of APIs
that allow you to build
rich concurrent Swift code
in a familiar
and naturally structured style.
To learn more,
See “Explore structured
concurrency in Swift.”
And to learn how you can take
full advantage of async code
in SwiftUI apps, see “Discover
concurrency in SwiftUI.”
We’ve finished up migrating
all the places we were
calling the fetchThumbnail
function.
But our app has
a lot more opportunities
to adopt async/await.
To get up and running quickly,
we recommend starting small
with an async alternative
to an existing API.
The SDK offers hundreds of APIs
that take completion handlers
because they do work
on your behalf
in an asynchronous manner.
When these APIs
are lined up side by side,
patterns begin to emerge.
Even though they may
have different names
and different purposes,
all of these functions
have the same essential
API contract.
You call them, and they call
you back with the provided
completion handlers, passing
the result they obtained.
Earlier, Nate showed you
that you could
await the results
of asynchronous functions
to write
more natural-looking code.
Wouldn’t it be awesome
if we could turn
these callback blocks
into these async functions?
As of Swift 5.5,
this is exactly what happens.
The Swift compiler
automatically takes
a look at completion handler
code imported from Objective-C
and provides
an async alternative.
But we didn’t stop there.
Many delegate APIs
also include methods
that pass
a completion handler to you.
Calling the handler
cooperatively
informs the framework
when an asynchronous task
has completed.
Take this ClockKit
complication data source
that calls fetchThumbnail
to display a timeline entry
for a given post.
Just as before,
we have to make sure
to call the completion handler
on all paths,
and there’s a lot of extra noise
here because of the closure.
With async await, this no longer
needs to be the case.
This delegate method has
an async alternative
we can use instead.
First, the async alternative’s
name is used
which drops the leading “get.”
We recommend
that async functions
omit leading words
like “get” that communicate
when the results of a call
are not directly returned.
After all,
since this is an async
alternative function, it returns
a timeline entry directly.
Now that there is
an async context set up,
we call the async version
of fetchThumbnail.
Finally, we return a timeline
entry from this method
rather than calling the
now-deleted completion block.
The async APIs we’ve highlighted
here barely scratch the surface.
To learn more,
see these sessions
which go into much greater
detail about the APIs themselves
and how you can use them
when adopting async/await.
All of these are examples
of situations
where Swift will create async
alternatives on your behalf.
But there will inevitably be
places in your code
where you will need to create
an async alternative yourself.
Let’s see what this
looks like in practice.
In our app, we use
this getPersistentPosts function
to retrieve any posts
we persisted
to our Core Data store.
This function is called
in a lot more places in our app
than the async thumbnail
function was, so it would be
a really big change to just
use async everywhere.
And since we’re using
NSAsynchronousFetchRequest,
it seems like this function
is a perfect candidate
for an async alternative.
First, we make an async function
and convert the return value.
Since this function
can yield an error,
we mark this function
“throws” as well.
Next, we call
the completion handler version
of getPersistentPosts
and, well, now we’re stuck.
We need to return the result
from the callback back
to the places awaiting
calls to the async
persistentPosts function.
Not only that, those callers
are in a suspended state.
We need to make sure
to resume them
at the right point in time
and with the right data
so that they can get on
with the rest of their work.
Earlier, Nate showed you
how Swift and the system
cooperate to take care
of resuming async code for us.
Let’s dive a little deeper
into how this suspend/resume
process works to see if we can
come up with a similar solution
for our problem.
When the async version
of persistentPosts
is called,
it calls into Core Data.
At some later time, Core Data
calls the completion handler
and passes the result
of the fetch request.
This situation looks
almost identical to the one
Nate showed you earlier
when our fetchThumbnail function
asked the system, not Core Data,
to resume a suspended
async function call.
All that’s missing is a bridge
to await the completion handler
and resume with
the fetch request’s results.
This pattern comes up
all the time,
and it has a name:
a continuation.
Throughout this session,
Nate and I have already
showed you lots of examples
of continuations:
methods that take
completion blocks.
The caller of the method awaits
the result of the function call
and provides a closure
to specify what to do next.
When the function call
completes,
it calls the completion handler
to resume
whatever the caller wanted
to do with the result.
This kind
of cooperative execution
is exactly the way
async functions in Swift work.
To make this explicit,
Swift provides a feature
so that you can create, manage,
and resume continuations
in a high-level and safe way.
Let’s return to our example
to see how continuations
can help us finish
writing our async alternative.
The
withCheckedThrowingContinuation
function lifts completion blocks
with errors
up to throwing
async Swift functions.
It has a counterpart called
withCheckedContinuations
for the situations
where you know a function
will never throw an error.
These functions are the way
to gain access
to a continuation value
you can use to resume
a suspended async function.
This also builds
the first part of the bridge
by allowing us to await calls
to getPersistentPosts.
Let’s finish building
the bridge.
The continuation value provides
a resume function
into which we place the results
from the completion handler.
Not only that,
but resume provides
the missing link we need
to unsuspend any calls
awaiting the result
of the persistentPosts function.
And there, in one neat package,
is our finished bridge
from completion handlers
to async functions.
Continuations provide
a powerful way
to manually take control
over the execution
of an async function,
but there are some things
to keep in mind.
Continuations have a simple
but important contract.
Resume must be called
exactly once on every path.
But don’t worry.
Swift has your back here.
If the continuation is discarded
without resume being called,
the Swift runtime
will log a warning
since this will result in async
calls never unsuspending.
If a continuation is
resumed multiple times
in the same function, however,
this is a more serious error
as it can corrupt program data.
To combat this,
the Swift runtime will detect
attempts to call resume
multiple times and will ensure
a fatal error occurs
at the second resumption point.
With this in mind,
let’s highlight one more
important place you might use
checked continuations.
Many APIs are event driven.
They provide delegate
callbacks to notify
our application
at specific critical points
and allow it
to respond appropriately.
In order to properly adopt
async/await,
we’ll have to store
the continuation
and resume it later.
As before, we create
a checked continuation.
Then we save it
and kick off the work.
To respect the API contract
of checked continuations,
we make sure to resume
the active continuation,
and finally nil it out
so we’re protected from
calling it more than once.
Always remember: the checked
continuation value here
represents the ability
to manually resume
any async calls to this API,
so it must be called
on all paths.
If your delegate API is called
many times or not at all
in certain circumstances,
it is critical to resume
any active continuations
exactly once.
To learn more about
the lower-level details
of Swift concurrency,
including continuations,
see the “Swift concurrency:
Behind the scenes” session.
This has been a whirlwind tour
of async/await in Swift.
We’ve shown you just how
the async and await keywords
work at runtime
and how you can adopt them
in your applications
and frameworks.
To get you started, we gave you
a sampling of the async APIs
available in the SDK
and showed you how to bridge
your existing code
from the synchronous world
to the async world.
Async/await is the foundation
of a whole universe of Swift
concurrency features.
We’re excited to see
what you build with them.
Thank you for watching.