[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Becca Royal-Gordon:
Hi, I’m Becca
from the Swift Compiler team.
I’m going to be talking today
about how you can
implement DSLs in Swift.
If you’ve never heard that term,
a DSL is a domain-specific
language,
and even if
the name is new to you,
you’ve probably used one before.
I’m going to start by explaining
what DSLs actually are
and what they look like
in Swift.
Then I’ll explain
how result builders work.
They’re one of the main features
used to implement Swift DSLs.
After that, I’ll walk you
through designing a simple DSL
for part of our sample app,
Fruta.
And finally, I’ll show you
how to write the implementation
that’s in the Fruta sample code.
But let’s start by explaining
that acronym a little better.
A DSL is a sort of
miniature programming language
that’s designed for programs
that work in a specific area
called a "domain."
Because the language is designed
with a particular kind of work
in mind,
it can have special features
which make that kind of work
easier to do.
So when you write code
for a DSL
instead of
a general-purpose language,
you only have
to write the things
that are specific
to your exact problem.
Many DSLs are declarative.
That is, you’re not really
writing precise instructions
to solve the problem;
it’s more like you’re describing
the problem in the language,
and then it goes
and solves it for you.
The traditional way
you would do this
is called a "standalone DSL."
You would design the entire
language from scratch
and write an interpreter
or compiler for it.
Embedded DSLs
are a more modern alternative.
In an embedded DSL,
you use the built-in features
of a host language like Swift
to add the DSL’s
implicit behavior
to some parts of your code,
effectively modifying
the host language
into one tailored
for your domain.
This is obviously way easier
than designing
the entire language
and writing a compiler for it
because you’re starting
from an existing language
that has already decided
the basics of the syntax
and already has a compiler.
It also makes it easier
to mix the DSL code
together with non-DSL code.
Often you want to use a DSL
to solve a problem
that’s just one part
of a much larger app.
If you’re writing
a standalone DSL,
you have to design a way to call
from one language to the other.
With an embedded DSL,
the parts written in the DSL
look like normal code
to the rest of the app,
so you have a much easier time
interoperating.
An embedded DSL
can also use the tools designed
for the host language.
You already have debuggers
and editors for Swift,
and those work just fine
for a Swift DSL;
if you wanted those
for a standalone DSL,
you’d have to write your own.
And because you’re starting
from the host language,
clients who already
know that language
have a lot less to learn.
They already know
how to declare a variable
or whether there’s
a space in "else if";
all they need to learn is how
you’ve customized the language.
Swift is designed to support
embedded DSLs.
And in fact,
if you’ve used SwiftUI,
you’ve already used one.
The SwiftUI view DSL
assumes you want to describe
the layout of views
on a device’s screen.
So when you’re writing
in the SwiftUI DSL,
your custom code
simply creates the views,
and the DSL is responsible
for building a tree out of them
for SwiftUI to process.
To understand
the value of a DSL,
think about what SwiftUI
might be like
if you wrote views
in ordinary Swift instead.
You’d have to create views,
modify them,
add them to other views,
and return one at the end.
You’d be creating temporary
variables all over the place
to hold individual views,
and the result
wouldn’t really convey
the way the views are nested
in the same way the DSL does.
You’d write more code but
it would convey less meaning.
The SwiftUI DSL,
by contrast,
makes all of those
tedious details implicit.
It’s your job
to describe the views;
it’s the DSL’s job to collect
the views you’re describing
and figure out
how to show them.
But DSLs take extra effort
to implement,
and they take
extra effort to use.
So when do you want
to create one?
Well, there are no
hard-and-fast rules,
but here are some signs
that you might want to use one.
Look for places where the
mechanics of using vanilla Swift
obscure the meaning
of the code.
Where you spend half your time
rearranging commas
and square brackets
and parentheses
every time you change something,
or have to append things
to temporary arrays
to accommodate the control flow.
Look for situations
where the best approach
is to describe something
to another part of your code
instead of directly
writing instructions
about what to do with it.
Like, in a server-side
web framework,
there might be an area
that registers handlers
for the URLs it supports.
Instead of calling an add handler
method over and over,
you could design a DSL
for clients
to declare each URL
and its handler,
and then your framework
can register them automatically.
Look for parts of your code
that will be maintained
by people whose primary job
isn’t programming.
Like, imagine you’re writing
a text adventure game;
only a few developers will work
on most of the code,
but the map of rooms will be
updated by game designers,
and NPC dialog
will be added by writers.
Maybe a DSL would make
their jobs easier.
And look for situations where
you’ll get a lot of mileage
out of the DSL.
Libraries are a good example
because they get used
by many different clients.
But a good DSL could also
handle something in your project
that you define a lot,
or even just something you have
to read or update frequently
and you want to make that
as easy as possible.
Whatever reason you see
to create a DSL,
you need to balance it against
the fact that it will not only
take some effort for you
to design and implement,
it will also take some effort
for its clients to learn.
If methods and array literals
are nearly as good as a DSL,
they’re often the right answer,
because Swift programmers
will already know
exactly how to use them.
But sometimes,
like in SwiftUI,
a DSL is the right answer.
So how do you make one?
Well, let’s break down how
Swift features are used together
to build the SwiftUI DSL.
In addition to Swift’s
generally clean syntax,
the SwiftUI DSL takes advantage
of four things.
Property wrappers.
These let clients
declare variables
that are tied to DSL behavior.
Trailing closure arguments.
These let the DSL provide
functions or initializers
that read almost like
custom syntax
that’s been added
to the language.
Result builders.
These collect the values
computed in your DSL’s code
into a return value
so you can process them.
And finally,
modifier-style methods.
These are basically just methods
that return a wrapped
or modified version
of the value they’re called on;
since result builders
collect the values
computed by your code,
this pattern works really well
with them.
Now, property wrappers
were already covered
in the last half of this session
from 2019,
so I’m not going to talk
much about them today.
But these other three,
and especially result builders,
are going to be
major topics of this session.
Trailing closures and
modifier-style methods
are things a lot of Swift
programmers are familiar with,
but result builders are a more
behind-the-scenes feature.
So let’s talk about
how they work
so we can start
building DSLs with them.
Result builders are used
to gather up the values
created in your DSL
and stitch them together
into whatever data structure
your language wants them in.
They’re a bit like
property wrappers
in that you declare
a special type
and then you can use that type
as an attribute.
Specifically,
you can apply a result builder
to pretty much any function body
with a return value,
like a function or method,
the getter of a computed
property, or a closure.
When you apply a result
builder to a function body,
Swift inserts various calls
to static methods
on the result builder.
These end up capturing
the results of statements
that would otherwise
have been discarded.
So where Swift would normally
ignore a return value,
it instead gets passed
to the result builder.
These calls ultimately
compute a value
which is returned
from the function body.
So when you call the function,
it executes
all of the statements
in that function normally,
gathers up the values
produced by them,
and combines them
into a single value
that becomes
the closure’s result.
Result builders
are a compile-time feature,
so they work on any OS
that your app will run on.
The final version
of the feature,
from open-source
Swift Evolution proposal 289,
was included in Swift 5.4,
so it shipped in Xcode 12.5
back in April.
But prototypes of the feature
were available before that,
so you might see some older
tutorials or libraries
that use the prototype.
Those will say
"function builder"
instead of "result builder,"
and they might not quite
match the final feature.
So I pointed out the features
used in the SwiftUI DSL before,
but now let’s talk about
how they work.
I’ll be simplifying
a few details --
like removing irrelevant parts
of some SwiftUI types
and showing some fake
variable names like v0
for variables generated
by the compiler --
but this should help you
understand the basics.
The first thing to realize
is that, at the top level,
this VStack thing with a block
that looks like new syntax
is actually
a trailing closure argument.
If we look up what VStack is,
we find that
it’s a struct in SwiftUI.
So the trailing closure argument
gets passed to this initializer
on that struct.
Now, when we look
at the parameter
the closure gets passed to,
we notice that it has
a ViewBuilder attribute on it.
That attribute tells
the compiler that it should
apply the result builder
named ViewBuilder
to the closure.
But what is ViewBuilder?
Well, we look for
a type by that name,
and we find this type,
again in SwiftUI.
Note how it has an
@resultBuilder attribute on it
to tell the compiler
that it’s a result builder.
Now that Swift has located
the result builder type,
it starts applying it
to the closure.
The first thing it does
is create variables
for all of the statements
that produce results.
Once it’s created
these variables,
it writes a call to the
buildBlock method in ViewBuilder
and passes all of those
variables to it.
buildBlock’s job is
to process or combine
all of its parameters
into a single value,
which it returns.
Then the compiler
writes a return statement
that returns buildBlock’s result
from the closure.
So basically,
the compiler took your code
and added the code in yellow
so that the ViewBuilder
could assemble all of the values
you created into a single value
that VStack will use
as its content.
Now, I’d like to point out
how modifier-style methods
fit into this.
A modifier-style method returns
either a modified copy of self
or a copy of self
wrapped in a different type
that adds new behavior.
And it does this within
the same statement
that created self
in the first place.
So it ends up changing the value
before the result builder
sees it.
And you can call other
modifier-style methods
on that method’s result,
so you can apply several changes
and compose them together,
all before the result builder
ever sees the value.
Those two things --
the ability to compose modifiers
and the fact that
they modify the value before
the result builder sees it --
are why Swift DSLs
often use modifiers.
The two just work nicely
together.
Now, one thing
we were worried about
when we designed
result builders was that,
if they let you change
Swift’s behavior too radically,
clients wouldn’t be able to
trust that anything in the DSL
worked like normal Swift code.
So when we designed
result builders,
we tried to strike a balance
between having enough power
to make a useful DSL
and making sure
that Swift’s features
still work as clients
expect them to.
Result builders
don’t radically reinterpret
the code a client writes.
Statements still end
with newlines,
calls still use parentheses,
curly brackets
still have to match up;
all of the basics
of Swift syntax
work exactly the way
your clients expect.
They also don’t introduce new
names that wouldn’t be visible
from normal code
written in the same place.
There are some language features
that don’t make much sense
when you’re using
a result builder --
mostly things
like catch or break
that interrupt control flow in
ways that don’t really fit well
into the idea of capturing
and using statement results.
Those features are disabled when
you’re using a result builder.
And there are some features --
like if, switch,
and for-in statements --
that are disabled
unless your result builder
provides extra methods
that are used to implement them.
But if Swift allows you
to use a keyword,
it will work the way
it normally does.
You won’t end up with,
like, if-else statements
that run both
the true and false blocks,
or loops that skip
some of the elements.
Result builders just
capture the statement results
that would otherwise have been
thrown away, nothing more.
So clients can count on them,
you know, making sense.
OK. So now that we have an idea
of what result builders are
and how they work,
we can start designing
a DSL that will use them.
If you’ve never worked
on a language before,
you might find that thought
intimidating,
but designing a Swift DSL
is actually a lot like
designing a Swift API.
Like a Swift API, a Swift DSL
is not starting from scratch;
it uses Swift’s syntax
and capabilities
to express ideas and behavior
relevant to the problem
you’re trying to solve.
A DSL is just using
additional capabilities
that an API usually wouldn’t.
Like a Swift API,
a Swift DSL could be designed
in several different ways that
would all solve the problem,
so your job is
to think of alternatives
and select the one
you think is best;
a DSL just has a much larger
space of potential solutions.
And like a Swift API,
a Swift DSL’s best rule of thumb
is usually to choose the design
that results in
the clearest use sites.
A DSL just assumes
that clients will invest
a little time up front
learning the language,
so it puts less priority
on being crystal clear
to people who’ve never
seen it before.
So if you’ve designed APIs
before,
you’ve got a good starting point
to design DSLs.
And for that matter,
some of the suggestions
and techniques
I’ll be using for DSLs
transfer really well
to API design.
In this talk, we’ll be designing
a DSL for the app Fruta.
You’ll find a working
implementation of this
in the Fruta sample code.
Fruta includes 15 smoothie
recipes in its source code,
and before the DSL,
we simply created each smoothie
by calling
the memberwise initializer
and assigning it
to a static constant.
And then we stored
an array of all the smoothies
into another static constant,
and depending on
whether the particular view
wants to include recipes that
require an in-app purchase,
we either return the entire list
or filter out the paid ones.
Now, this is perfectly shippable
and you could stick with it
if you wanted to.
But the smoothie recipes
get updated pretty often
and, unlike the rest
of the app,
they’re updated by designers
and marketing folks
and [GROANS] managers,
so we might want a DSL
to make that
a little less complicated.
And looking at
the way we’re doing it now,
I can’t help but notice
a few drawbacks.
The need to filter the paid
smoothies out of the list
has contorted this code.
allSmoothies and hasFreeRecipe
are only ever used
in this function;
they otherwise
don’t need to exist.
Yet if you try to imagine
implementing this without them,
you can see
why we didn’t do that.
The mechanics
of creating the array
and appending elements to it
start to obscure the actual list
of smoothies,
which is sort of
the point of this function.
Similarly, the fact that
the list of smoothies
is separate from the smoothie
definitions is a little silly.
A few of these constants
are used by previews,
but most of them appear
only in this list.
And because you
define a smoothie in one place
and add it to the list
in another,
it creates an opportunity
for mistakes.
What if you declare
a new smoothie constant
but forget to add it
to the list?
Or what if you add
a smoothie twice?
If we look back
at the definitions
of individual smoothies,
I also see two other things
that bother me.
One is that the ingredient list
is just incredibly wordy.
Like, each entry repeats
some version of the word
"measure" three times.
In this line, the actual
information we care about
is 1.5 cups of oranges.
The rest of the line
isn’t saying anything useful;
it’s just visual clutter.
There’s inevitably going to be
some supporting syntax
around the information
that matters,
but when there’s this much,
the boilerplate around it
just overwhelms the information
we’re trying to convey.
The other thing I notice
is the sheer number of lines
devoted to each smoothie
compared to
the amount of information
that’s actually present.
I think the culprit here
is the difference
in the length of arguments.
Some of these arguments
are very short
and could fit together
on a single line.
Others are longer and really
need a line of their own.
Now, you could combine
the short arguments
onto a single line
and then use separate lines
for the long ones,
but most style guides
frown on that.
We’d like a syntax
where it’d be natural
to style them differently.
Put these altogether
and we’ve got a bunch of goals
we want our DSL
to accomplish
to make it easier
to maintain the smoothie list.
Now, the next thing to do
is to look at various ways
we could design the DSL
to achieve these goals.
There are a ton
of different designs
that would address
each of these points.
I’m going to quickly explain
what I decided to do
for the first three goals,
and then we can explore
the last goal in more detail.
I decided we’d define the
smoothie list in the all method.
The smoothies will be
defined directly in the body
without using static variables,
so we don’t have to worry about
someone defining a smoothie
and forgetting to list it.
We’ll use a result builder
called "SmoothieArrayBuilder"
to activate our DSL
and collect the smoothies
into an array;
that way we don’t need
to use an array literal
or collect things
into a temporary variable.
And we’ll allow smoothies
to be put in if statements
so we don’t need to filter
the list like we did before.
This is great because
clients who already know Swift
will know how
an if statement is used,
and clients who don’t
will probably understand
"if includingPaid"
with little trouble.
I decided to specify
the ingredient amounts
by using modifier-style
methods.
Ingredient will have a method
called, "measured(with: )"
which takes a unit and
returns a measured ingredient
with one of that unit.
If you want a different
amount of that unit,
the scaled(by: ) modifier
on a measured ingredient
returns it with the quantity
multiplied by
the number you pass.
So one cup of oranges
becomes 1.5 cups of oranges,
and one cup of avocado
becomes 0.2 cups of avocado.
Now, why is scaled(by: )
a separate modifier?
One of the screens in Fruta
has a control
that can be used to scale
the ingredient quantities
in a smoothie recipe.
We previously passed
the multiplier down
to each ingredient row,
which multiplied its quantity.
But I realized
that I could actually use
the scaled(by: ) modifier
to instead scale the ingredients
before they’re passed
to the rows,
which let me
simplify the row views.
So by tweaking
my smoothie DSL design a bit,
I was able to reuse
a piece of it
in another part of the project.
So with the changes to achieve
our first three goals,
we’re starting to see
our new DSL take shape.
Now let’s focus in
on that last goal:
redesigning the individual
smoothie entries
so they’re more compact,
and hopefully so there’s also
less confusing punctuation
our clients could trip over.
Let’s take a look
at a few different ways
we could arrange this
information to help with that.
One thing we could do
is use modifier-style methods
to add the description
and ingredients.
This would work,
but it’s kind of wordy
and it’d be easy for someone
to forget the description
or specify it twice
or something.
Another thing we could do
is give each field a marker type
and put them
in a result builder closure.
But this puts the ID and title
on their own lines,
which we’re trying to avoid.
So maybe we could move
the ID and title
back into the parameter list,
and use marker types
for the other two fields.
But I feel like this is still
maybe a little more ceremony
than we really need.
I realized that when I looked at
the user interface for recipes.
They’re always presented
in a specific order:
title at the top,
description in the middle,
list of ingredients
at the bottom.
And we don’t bother labeling
the title or description.
We let their visual hierarchy --
the fact that the title
is presented more prominently
than the description --
do the talking.
So I drew some inspiration
from that and decided
that our smoothie DSL
should do the same.
It puts the title at the top,
the description in the middle,
and the list of ingredients
at the bottom.
And it lets the fact that
the description is below
and more indented
than the title --
so it’s less
visually prominent --
convey the meaning
of the description string
so there’s no need to label it.
I think the result is
immediately understandable
without unnecessary
complications.
And when we put it into the
context of the DSL as a whole,
I think we have
a pretty comfortable fit.
But you might disagree,
and that’s OK.
DSLs are programming languages,
and personal taste
and subjective trade-offs
are a big part of designing
any programming language.
That doesn’t mean
you shouldn’t be rigorous.
You should start with
a clear idea of what you want
from the language.
You should look into whether
there’s an existing solution --
like the if statement --
that can solve your problem
because if you can
adopt a familiar solution,
people won’t have to learn
a new one.
You should think about
how each part of the language
interacts with the rest of it.
In a Swift DSL,
that also means thinking about
how your DSL interacts with the
ordinary Swift code around it,
like when I picked
the scaled-by modifier
because I could use it
somewhere else.
You should look for solutions
that will make mistakes
either detectable
at compile time
or totally impossible to write.
If you recall,
that’s why we didn’t
make description a modifier;
you could have left it out
by accident.
With all of that in mind,
you should come up with
several different possibilities.
Imagine how each of them
would be used,
write little mock-ups;
you know, weigh them
against each other.
But in the end,
you usually won’t find one
that’s obviously right
where the others
are obviously wrong.
All you can do
is pick something
you feel will be best for
your language’s clients.
If you’re not sure
which is best,
you should probably favor
whichever is most readable.
And if you’re still not sure
after that...
Well, personally,
I like taking bolder options.
I’d rather try something and
walk it back if it doesn’t work
than never try it
and be left wondering.
Now that we’ve decided
what our DSL will look like,
let’s go ahead
and add it to Fruta.
I’ve replaced the previous
smoothie definitions
with the final all method
that uses our DSL,
but I haven’t actually
implemented the DSL yet.
So unsurprisingly,
we’ve got a ton of errors.
But that’s OK.
As we work through this,
I’ll let these errors guide me
to the problems I need to solve,
and by the end
we’ll have something
that builds without any errors.
So let’s just start
at the top of the function
with this first error:
"Unknown attribute
‘SmoothieArrayBuilder’."
The result builder
doesn’t actually exist yet,
so of course
that's not going to work.
Let’s go fix that.
I’ll start by making a type
called "SmoothieArrayBuilder"
that’s marked with
the result builder attribute.
Now, Swift will never actually
make an instance of this type;
it’s just a container
for a bunch of static methods.
So I’ve made it an enum
and I won’t define any cases.
It’s impossible to create
an instance of an enum
which has no cases,
so this keeps people
from using it incorrectly.
If I build just this,
I’ll get an error
saying that the result builder
needs a buildBlock(_:) method.
It has a fix-it
which will insert one,
so I’ll accept that fix-it
and then we’ll figure out
how to implement it.
Now, if you recall
from earlier,
the way buildBlock(_:) works is
that if you have code like this
with a bunch of individual
statements,
each of those statements
gets assigned to a variable,
the variables are all
passed to buildBlock(_:),
and the value
returned by buildBlock(_:)
gets returned by the closure.
So it stands to reason
that our buildBlock(_:) method
needs to accept a bunch
of smoothies as parameters
and return
an array of smoothies.
If we implement that using
a variadic parameter
so that any number
of smoothies
can be passed to the method...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and build...
...well, what we get
is a bit better.
There are still
plenty of errors,
but the one saying
smoothie array builder
was an invalid attribute
is gone
and the attribute
even changed color
to indicate
that it’s a known type.
So let’s move on
to the next errors,
the ones for
the smoothie initializer.
One says that
we’re passing a trailing closure
to a string parameter.
The other says we’re missing the
measuredIngredients argument.
So clearly we’re using
the old initializer,
which expects the description
and ingredients as parameters.
We’ll need to make a new one.
So let’s implement
that initializer
with an ID, a title,
and a trailing closure
that returns the description
and ingredients.
I’m going to tell you
right now,
we’ll have to come back
to this initializer later.
If I build right now, it does
clear away all of the errors
from the smoothie
initializers,
so you might think
this is working perfectly.
But that’s actually
a little misleading.
You see, there’s another
error down here
on the if statement
that’s caused by
the smoothie array builder
not being finished.
And because that error is there,
Swift isn’t checking the insides
of the closures yet.
Like, if I go into this closure
and I just write
some random variable name
that I know doesn’t exist,
and then build it,
Swift doesn’t flag an error.
What’s happening is that Swift
sees that the result builder
didn’t apply correctly,
so it doesn’t really trust
that any errors
it found in these closures
would actually be accurate.
So it’s just not looking
for errors there yet.
Later on, when we finish
the smoothie array builder,
we’ll suddenly start
seeing those errors
and we can fix them
at that point.
But for now it’s easier
to keep working
on the smoothie array builder,
so let’s set
those closures aside
and move on
to the next error.
If we look at this error,
Swift tells us that
we can’t use an if statement
with smoothie array builder,
but there’s a method
we can add to support it.
If statements are one of
a few Swift features like this;
they are disabled
unless your result builder
implements extra methods
to support them.
So to get started
implementing this,
let’s hit the fix-it here
and see what it adds.
So apparently we need
to implement a method
called buildOptional(_:),
which takes an optional
array of smoothies
and returns an array
of smoothies.
So how does this method
get used?
Well, take this simplified
example of the all method,
which has an if statement
with no else.
Like our previous example
without the if statement,
this is going to capture
the result of each statement
into a variable, pass those
variables to buildBlock(_:),
and return the result
of buildBlock(_:) from the closure.
The only question is,
how is it going to capture
the result
of the if statement?
Well, the first thing
it’s going to do
is capture all of the statements
in the if statement’s body
into variables,
and then combine those variables
together using buildBlock(_:),
just like it does
at the top level.
But this is where
buildOptional(_:) comes in.
Instead of returning the result
of that inner buildBlock(_:) call,
Swift will pass it
to buildOptional(_:),
and the value
returned by buildOptional(_:)
becomes the value of
the if statement as a whole.
But this leaves the
variable uninitialized
if the if condition is false.
That’s why
buildOptional’s parameter
is an optional
array of smoothies.
Swift will add an else branch
which sets the value
of the if statement’s result
to the return value
from buildOptional(nil).
For SmoothieArrayBuilder,
the upshot of this is that
we want buildOptional(_:)
to either return
the array that was passed to it
from buildBlock(_:)
or return an empty array
if the parameter is nil.
If we build it now,
we get...
...a really weird-looking error.
Can’t pass array of type
smoothie as variadic arguments?
What?
Well, let’s go back
to our generated code.
The if statement ends up
producing an array of smoothies.
But actually, buildBlock(_:) doesn’t
want arrays of smoothies;
it wants single smoothies.
We’ll need to change that.
So maybe we can make buildBlock(_:)
take arrays of smoothies
as its arguments,
and then use flatMap(_:)
to concatenate
those many arrays of smoothies
together
into a single
array of smoothies.
Great!
Build that, and...
...no.
Now our if statement works,
but all the smoothie lines
broke.
We kind of need those.
Cannot convert value of type
smoothie to array of smoothie.
What happened?
Well, we changed buildBlock(_:)
so that it matches
the array of smoothies
returned by buildOptional(_:).
But we forgot that it also needs
to match the individual
smoothies returned
by the normal statements.
Oops.
Basically,
if you’re going to allow
any sophisticated
control flow,
buildBlock’s return type
needs to be something
that can be passed
as a parameter to buildBlock(_:).
There are two ways
you can accomplish this.
One way is to make sure
that buildBlock(_:)
and the other result builder
methods return types
compatible with the statements
allowed in the result builder.
For example, this is how
SwiftUI’s ViewBuilder works.
In the SwiftUI DSL,
everything conforms
to the View protocol,
including the types
returned by buildBlock(_:)
and other view builder methods.
But that’s not a great fit
for our smoothie DSL
because unlike SwiftUI views,
you don’t nest smoothies
inside of other smoothies.
The other thing you can do
is have the result builder
convert the values
of normal statements
into the same type
returned by buildBlock(_:).
That’s a better fit
for this DSL.
We can do that by adding a
method called buildExpression(_:).
When we add
a buildExpression(_:) method,
Swift passes each bare
expression to that method
before it captures it
into a variable.
That will give us an opportunity
to convert those into arrays.
But values that come from
other result builder methods,
like the ones produced by
buildOptional(_:) and buildBlock(_:),
don’t get wrapped
in these calls,
so they won’t have this
conversion applied to them --
which is good because they’re
already returning arrays.
So what we’re going to do
is implement
a buildExpression(_:) method.
Xcode’s code completion
knows all about
result-builder methods,
so we can ask it to write
the signature for one.
Then we change
the parameter type to Smoothie
and just return
the expression parameter
wrapped in an array literal.
So now our single smoothies
will be turned into
the arrays of smoothies
that buildBlock(_:) needs.
Build that, and...
...fantastic!
Our if statement works
and so do the smoothie
initializers.
However, if we look
in the minimap,
we’ll see that there’s
a second if statement down here
that doesn’t work.
That’s because this one
has an else clause.
buildOptional(_:) actually only
works for plain if statements.
If you have an else statement,
or an else-if, or a switch,
you need to implement
a pair of methods,
called buildEither(first:)
and buildEither(second:).
Let’s create these
using the fix-it
and then talk about
how they work.
So let’s look
at this simplified example
with an if-else statement.
Most of the transform is just
like the one for buildOptional(_:).
Like buildOptional(_:),
the whole if-else statement
will end up filling
a single variable.
And also like buildOptional(_:),
each of the blocks
in the if statement
will have the statements inside
it captured into variables
and then buildBlock
will be used
to combine them together
into one value.
What’s different from
a plain if statement is that
instead of using buildOptional(_:)
to generate the final value,
we use one
of the buildEither methods.
If there are two branches,
like an if and an else,
then the first one
uses buildEither(first:)
and the second
uses buildEither(second:).
That allows result builders
which care about
which branch you took
to distinguish between them.
Now, if you’re
wondering what we do
if there are
three or more cases,
the answer to that
is actually pretty cool.
We build a balanced binary tree
with each branch
as one of the leaves,
and then we treat the nonleaf
nodes as calls we need to make,
with the edge telling us
whether to use buildEither(first:)
or buildEither(second:).
We note which sequence of
calls each branch should use,
then we generate code
that assigns to the variable
with that sequence of calls.
So even though
we only have two methods,
the result builder
can still distinguish
between the three branches.
Not too bad.
Anyway, now that we know how
the buildEither methods work,
we can go ahead and write them.
And since SmoothieArrayBuilder
doesn’t actually care
which branch you took,
there’s not much we need to do;
just return the array argument.
[KEYSTROKES]
So now we build
this thing, and...
it still doesn’t quite work.
But we’re close!
You might remember
this kind of error
from when we had
the array-of-smoothie problem,
only now, it’s not complaining
about type Smoothie,
it’s type '()'.
That’s an empty tuple,
the type you probably
think of as Void.
If we think about
the generated code,
it makes sense
why this is a problem.
We’re calling buildExpression(_:),
but the expression
that's being passed
is calling logger.log,
which returns Void,
not Smoothie.
So we’ll write an overload
of buildExpression(_:)
which takes a Void parameter
and returns an empty array.
Then we rebuild,
and now the log call
works correctly!
We do have
a zillion more errors,
but this is actually good news.
See, the first of these errors
is from that fake variable
I added way back
at the beginning
to show you
that Swift wasn’t finding errors
in the trailing closures.
Now it is, which means
that we’ve finished
the smoothie array builder!
So yay, errors!
Let’s delete that fake variable
and look at what’s left.
If we look closely,
we’ll find that
there’s less to do here
than it looks like.
All of the description lines
have the same warning,
and all of the ingredient lines
have the same two errors.
So even though we have,
like, a hundred errors
and a dozen warnings,
this is actually just
the same couple of problems
happening over and over.
Let’s take a closer look
at the errors
on one of these
ingredient lines.
The compiler has two complaints:
it can’t figure out
what type to look for cups in,
and it doesn’t think Ingredient
has a member called "measured."
Well, that makes sense;
we haven’t implemented
the measured(with:)
or scaled(by:) modifiers,
so it can’t find anything
called "measured."
And it has no idea
what cups are
because it doesn’t know
that measured(with:)
is supposed to take
a volume unit.
So let’s pop over to
MeasuredIngredient.swift
and implement
these two modifiers.
measured(with:)
goes on an Ingredient
and returns a measured ingredient
with one of the unit
the caller passed.
And scaled(by:) goes on
a measured ingredient
and returns a new
measured ingredient
with the measurement multiplied
by the scale the caller passed.
Pop back over to
Smoothie.swift and build...
...and, OK.
We’re seeing a lot more warnings
and only a few errors.
And if we look closely,
we’re seeing
only one kind of warning --
telling us that each
expression in the closures
is being ignored --
and one kind of error --
telling us that the closures
don’t have return statements.
To understand why,
let’s talk about
these trailing closures
and how result builders
interact with them.
In this example,
the SmoothieArrayBuilder
is going to affect
the outer statements
just the way we’ve seen before.
They get passed
to buildExpression(_:),
saved to variables,
and the variables get passed
to buildBlock.
But what about these closures?
What will the result builder
do to them?
Well, it does...
...absolutely nothing
because the closures
are actually separate functions
nested inside the function
we’ve applied
the result builder to.
Result builders
only apply to one function;
they don’t affect the functions
or closures nested inside it.
If you want them to be
affected by the result builder,
then you have to apply it
to them in some other way.
There are three ways
to apply a result builder
to a function body.
The first is
to write the attribute
directly on
the function or property,
like we did for
SmoothieArrayBuilder.
The second way
to apply a result builder
is to write it on a function
or property requirement
in a protocol;
then it will be
automatically applied
to the implementations
on all conforming types.
That’s how the body property
in SwiftUI Views works:
the ViewBuilder attribute
is applied
to the body requirement in View,
so it’s automatically applied
to any View’s body property too.
The third way
to apply a result builder
is to write it
before a closure parameter.
If you do that,
Swift will then infer
that any closure
passed to that parameter
should have the result builder
applied to it.
If Swift has inferred
a result builder
from a protocol or parameter
and you don’t actually
want it to be applied,
you can disable it
by explicitly returning a value
using a return statement.
But in this case,
since we’re using a closure,
we want the last
of those three options:
infer the result builder
from the closure parameter.
We do that by writing
an attribute
before the argument label.
Now, we could write
SmoothieArrayBuilder here,
but that’s probably not
the best way to do this.
SmoothieArrayBuilder
produces an array of smoothies,
but we don’t want this closure
to produce smoothies;
we want it to produce a string
and an array of ingredients.
And we don’t need if statements
or Void-returning calls
in this closure, either.
So really, we’re applying
a separate set
of language rules
to this closure,
and rather than
mixing that second set of rules
into SmoothieArrayBuilder,
it makes more sense
to create a new result builder
that implements
these new rules.
Let’s call it SmoothieBuilder
and create a new type for it,
and start writing
a buildBlock(_:) method.
Now, this one
is a little special.
We want to accept any
number of measured ingredients,
but we also want
to take a string at the front.
So how are we
going to do that?
Well, if you think about
how SmoothieBuilder --
which, remember,
is a simple result builder
with only
a buildBlock method --
is going to be expanded out,
each of those lines
is going to be passed
as a different parameter.
So it seems like maybe you could
just write a string parameter
at the beginning
of buildBlock,
and then the first statement
would have to produce
a string instead of
a MeasuredIngredient.
So let’s try doing that.
Add a string parameter
up front,
and have it return
a tuple of a string
and an array of ingredients.
[KEYSTROKES]
And if we build...
Hey, look at that!
Zero errors!
Our DSL works!
Now, result builders support
a couple more features,
like for-in loops and processing
the final return result.
If you want to use those,
they’re described in the
Swift Programming Language book.
But before we finish,
I want to call attention
to one of the most important
parts of language design:
good error messages.
One of the things you learn
when you’re designing a language
is that there are many more ways
to write invalid code
than valid code,
so you should spend some time
thinking about the errors
you’ll emit for invalid code.
Your behavior
when the code is wrong
is just as important
as when the code is right.
Now, for a Swift DSL,
you’ll get Swift’s
error handling for free.
But the error messages
clients will get
are designed
for general Swift code.
They aren’t phrased in terms of
your language’s rules,
so they may not communicate the
problem clearly to your clients.
For example,
imagine someone forgot
to put a description
in one of these smoothies.
Swift is going to emit
an error message,
but it’s a little unclear.
It complains that
the first ingredient
can’t be converted to a string.
So how does this code
end up producing this error?
Well, the Swift compiler
doesn’t really understand
the semantics
of our Smoothie DSL,
it only understands
the semantics of the Swift code
generated to use
the result builder.
So when it tries
to diagnose this error,
it doesn’t think of this value
as the description
of the Smoothie
or the first ingredient.
It thinks of it as the first
argument to buildBlock.
v0, the first argument
to buildBlock (_:),
is a MeasuredIngredient,
but it’s being passed
to a string parameter.
So Swift
thinks of this error as,
"You’re trying to pass
a MeasuredIngredient
to a string parameter,
but I can’t convert
MeasuredIngredient to a string."
The error message
is not technically wrong
but it’s not really helpful,
either.
Compiler engineers
have a trick for this:
we make the compiler
support the invalid thing
but produce an error
when you do it.
For example, there’s a slot
in Swift’s function grammar
where you can write throws,
rethrows, or nothing.
If you write some other
unsupported word,
the compiler guesses that
it was supposed to be
part of a different statement
and gives you an error
telling you to either add
a semicolon or use a new line.
But, if you write
"try" specifically,
you get a different error.
The compiler suggests
replacing it with throws
and then parses
the rest of the file
as though you’d written throws
there instead.
This is a special case
we added to the Swift parser.
We noticed that
developers sometimes
type other error-handling
keywords here
when they mean to write throws,
so we made a tiny,
undocumented extension
to the formal grammar
of the language.
We parse those
mistaken keywords here
and then diagnose
a different error than usual,
tailored for
that specific mistake.
I point this out because
you can do something similar
in a result builder
to improve its error behavior.
Specifically, if you make
an overload
of a result-builder method
which matches the bad code,
and then you mark
that overload as unavailable,
you can specify an error message
to use when diagnosing it.
And so instead of getting
a generic error
that might not convey
the problem very well,
clients will get a more specific
error message
tailored to that mistake.
What we’ll do
is copy buildBlock(_:),
delete the description parameter
so we’re matching blocks
with only
an ingredient list in them,
and replace the body
with fatalError()
so we don’t have
to fake a return value.
The method will never
be called successfully,
so the body just has to be
something that’s valid.
Then we’ll mark this overload
as unavailable
and give it a message describing
the problem more clearly.
This unavailable annotation
means that the method
can’t actually be used.
If you write a call to it,
that’s an error.
So now, if I pop back up
to the top and rebuild,
I see that I get
a much, much clearer description
of what’s wrong.
Instead of saying that the first
ingredient should be a string,
it says that the
description string is missing.
So the client doesn’t start
thinking that
the ingredient is wrong
or have to wonder
what the string is for;
the error tells them that
right up front.
That’s a much better
experience.
And the most important
thing to remember
about implementing a DSL
is that it’s all about improving
the client’s experience.
A DSL can make some
very complex, repetitive code
much cleaner by allowing clients
to define things
without worrying
about the mechanics
of assembling the definition.
Result builders
are a powerful tool
that allow your DSL to collect
the values being defined.
And modifier-style methods
give you a composable way
to change those values
before the result builder
captures them.
But remember that
if you write a DSL,
clients will have to learn
how to use it.
Provide a DSL only when
it’s going to be worth
their time and effort.
So thanks for your time,
and enjoy building
some little languages.
♪