[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Peikang]
Hi.
My name is Peikang,
and I’m from Video Coding
and the Processing team.
Welcome to “Exploring
low-latency video encoding
with Video Toolbox.”
The low-latency encoding
is very important
for many video applications,
especially real-time
video communication apps.
In this talk,
I’m going to introduce
a new encoding mode
in Video Toolbox
to achieve low-latency encoding.
The goal
of this new mode is to optimize
the existing encoder pipeline
for real-time applications.
So what does a real-time
video application require?
We need to minimize
the end-to-end latency
in the communication
so that people
won’t be talking
over each other.
We need to enhance
the interoperability
by letting
the video apps capable
of communicating
with more devices.
The encoder pipeline
should be efficient
when there are more than one
recipients in the call.
The app
needs to present the video
in its best visual quality.
We need a reliable mechanism
to recover
the communication from errors
introduced by network loss.
The low-latency video encoding
that I’m going
to talk about today
will optimize
in all these aspects.
With this mode,
your real-time application
can achieve
new levels of performance.
In this talk,
first I’m going to give
an overview
of low-latency video encoding.
We can have the basic idea
about how we achieve
low latency in the pipeline.
Then I’m going to show how
to use VTCompressionSession APIs
to build the pipeline and encode
with low-latency mode.
Finally, I will talk
about multiple features
we are introducing
in low-latency mode.
Let me first give an overview
on low-latency video encoding.
Here is a brief diagram
of a video encoder pipeline
on Apple’s platform.
The Video Toolbox
takes the CVImagebuffer
as the input image.
It asks the video encoder
to perform
compression algorithms
such as H.264
to reduce the size of raw data.
The output compressed data
is wrapped
in CMSampleBuffer,
and it can be transmitted
through network
for video communication.
As we may notice
from the previous diagram,
the end-to-end latency
can be affected
by two factors:
the processing time
and the network
transmission time.
To minimize the processing time,
the low-latency mode
eliminates frame reordering.
A one in, one out
encoding pattern is followed.
Also, the rate controller
in this mode
has a faster adaptation
in response
to the network change,
so the delay caused
by network congestion
is minimized as well.
With these two optimizations,
we can already see
obvious performance improvements
compared with the default mode.
The low-latency encoding
can reduce the delay
of up to 100 milliseconds
for a 720p 30fps video.
Such saving can be critical
for video conferencing.
As we reduce the latency,
we can achieve
a more efficient
encoding pipeline
for real-time communications
like video conferencing
and live broadcasting.
Also, the low-latency mode
always uses
a hardware-accelerated
video encoder
in order to save powers.
Note, the supported
video codec type
in this mode is H.264,
and we’re bringing this feature
on both iOS and macOS.
Next, I want to talk about
how to use low-latency mode
with Video Toolbox.
I’m going to first recap the use
of VTCompressionSession
and then show you the step
we need
to enable low-latency encoding.
When we use
VTCompressionSession,
the first thing
is to create the session
with VTCompressionSessionCreate
API.
We can optionally
config the session,
such as target bit rate,
through
VTSessionSetProperty API.
If the configuration
is not provided,
the encoder will operate
with the default behavior.
After the session is created
and properly configured,
we can pass the CVImageBuffer
to the session with
VTCompressionSessionEncodeFrame
call.
The encoded result
can be retrieved
from the output handler
provided during
the session creation.
Enabling low-latency encoding
in the compression session
is easy.
The only change we need
is in the session creation.
Here is a code snippet
showing how to do that.
First we need
a CFMutableDictionary
for the encoderSpecification.
The encoderSpecification
is used to specify
a particular video encoder
that the session must use.
And then we need to set
EnableLowLatencyRateControl flag
in the encoderSpecification.
Finally, we need to give
this encoderSpecification
to VTCompressionSessionCreate,
and the compression session
will be operating
in low-latency mode.
The configuration step
is the same as usual.
For example,
we can set the target bit rate
with AverageBitRate property.
OK, we’ve covered the basics
of the low-latency mode
with Video Toolbox.
I’d like to move on
to the new features
in this mode
that can further help you
develop a real-time
video application.
So far, we’ve talked
about the latency benefit
by using the low-latency mode.
The rest of the benefits
can be achieved
by the features
I’m going introduce.
The first feature
is the new profiles.
We enhanced
the interoperability
by adding two new profiles
to the pipeline.
And we are also excited to talk
about temporal scalability.
This feature can be very helpful
in video conferencing.
You can now have
a fine-grained control
over the image quality
with max frame
quantization parameter.
Last, we want to improve
the error resilience
by adding the support
of long-term reference.
Let’s talk
about the new profile support.
Profile defines a group
of coding algorithms
that the decoder
is capable to support.
In order to communicate
with the receiver side,
the encoded bitstream
should comply
with the specific profile
that the decoder supports.
Here in Video Toolbox,
we support a bunch of profiles,
such as baseline profile,
main profile, and high profile.
Today we added
two new profiles to the family:
constrained baseline profile,
CBP,
and constrained
high profile, CHP.
CBP is primarily used
for low-cost applications
and CHP,
on the other hand,
has more advanced algorithms
for better compression ratio.
You should check
the decoder capabilities
in order to know
which profile should be used.
To request CBP,
simply set ProfileLevel
session property
to ContrainedBaseLine_AutoLevel.
Similarly,
we can set the profile level
to ContrainedHigh_AutoLevel
to use CHP.
Now let’s talk
about temporal scalability.
We can use temporal scalability
to enhance the efficiency
for multi-party video calls.
Let us consider
a simple, three-party
video conferencing scenario.
In this model,
receiver "A" has
a lower bandwidth of 600kbps,
and receiver B
has a higher bandwidth
of 1,000kbps.
Normally, the sender needs
to encode two sets of bitstreams
in order to meet
the downlink bandwidth
of each receiver side.
This may not be optimal.
The model can be more efficient
with temporal scalability,
where the sender only needs
to encode
one single bitstream
but can be later divided
into two layers.
Let me show you
how this process works.
Here is a sequence
of encoded video frames
where each of the frames
uses the previous frame
as predictive reference.
We can pull half of the frames
into another layer,
and we can change the reference
so that only the frames
in the original layer
are used for prediction.
The original layer
is called base layer,
and the new constructed layer
is called enhancement layer.
The enhancement layer
can be used as a supplement
of the base layer in order
to improve the frame rate.
For receiver "A,"
we can send base layer frames
because the base layer
itself is decodable already.
And more importantly,
since the base layer
contains only half
of the frames,
the transmitted data
rate will be low.
On the other hand,
receiver B can enjoy
a smoother video since it has
a sufficient bandwidth
to receive base layer frames
and enhancement layer frames.
Let me show you
the videos encoded
using temporal scalability.
I’m going to play two videos,
one from the base layer,
and the other
from the base layer together
with the enhancement layer.
The base layer itself
can be played normally,
but at the same time,
we may notice the video
is not quite smooth.
We can immediately see
the difference
if we play the second video.
The right video
has a higher frame rate
compared with the left one
because it contains
both base layer
and enhancement layer.
The left video has 50%
of the input frame rate,
and it uses 60%
of the target bit rate.
These two videos
only require the encoder
to encode one single bitstream
at one time.
This will be
much more power efficient
when we are doing
multi-party video conferencing.
Another benefit
of temporal scalability
is error resilience.
As we can see,
the frames
in the enhancement layer
are not used for prediction,
so there is
no dependency on these frames.
This would mean if one
or more enhancement layer frames
are dropped
during network transmission,
other frames won’t be affected.
This makes the whole session
more robust.
The way to enable
temporal scalability
is pretty straightforward.
We created
a new session property
in low-latency mode called
BaseLayerFrameRateFraction.
Simply set this property to 0.5,
meaning half of the input frames
are assigned
to base layer
and the rest are assigned
to enhancement layer.
You can check
the layer information
from the sample
buffer attachment.
For base layer frames,
the CMSampleAttachmentKey_
IsDependedOnByOthers
will be true,
and otherwise it will be false.
We also have the option
to set the target bit rate
for each layer.
Remember that we use
the session property
AverageBitRate to config
the target bit rate.
After the target bit rate
is configured, we can set
the new BaseLayerBitRateFraction
property
to control the percentage
of the target bit rate
needed for the base layer.
If this property is not set,
a default value
of 0.6 will be used.
And we recommend the base layer
bit rate fraction
should range from 0.6 to 0.8.
Now, let’s move to max frame
quantization parameter,
or max frame QP.
Frame QP is used to regulate
image quality and data rate.
We can use low-frame QP
to generate
a high-quality image.
The image size
will be large in this case.
On the other hand,
we can use a high-frame QP
to generate an image
in low quality
but with smaller size.
In low-latency mode,
the encoder adjusts frame QP
using factors
such as image complexity,
input frame rate,
video motion
in order to produce
the best visual quality
under current target
bit rate constraint.
So we encourage to rely
on the encoder’s
default behavior
for adjusting frame QP.
But in some cases
where the client
has a specific requirement
for the video quality,
we now let you
control the max frame QP
that the encoder
is allowed to use.
With the max frame QP,
the encoder will always choose
the frame QP that is smaller
than this limit,
so the client can have
a fine-grained control
over the image quality.
It’s worth mentioning
that the regular rate control
still works even with
the max frame QP specified.
If the encoder hits
the max frame QP cap
but is running
out of bit rate budget,
it will start dropping frames
in order to maintain
the target bit rate.
One example of using
this feature is to transmit
screen content video
over a poor network.
You can make a trade-off
by sacrificing the frame rate
in order to send sharp
screen content images.
Setting max frame QP
can meet this requirement.
Let’s look at the interface.
You can pass
the max frame QP
with the new session property
MaxAllowedFrameQP.
Keep in mind that the value
of max frame QP
must range from 1 to 51
according to the standard.
Let’s talk about
the last feature
we’ve developed
in low-latency mode,
long-term reference.
Long-term reference or LTR
can be used
for error resilience.
Let’s look at this diagram
showing the encoder,
sender client,
and the receiver client
in the pipeline.
Suppose the video communication
goes through a network
with poor connection.
Frame loss can happen
because
of the transmission error.
When the receiver client
detects a frame loss,
it can request a refresh frame
in order to reset the session.
If the encoder gets the request,
normally it will encode
a key frame
for the refresh purpose.
But the key frame
is usually quite large.
A large key frame
takes a longer time
to get to the receiver.
Since the network condition
is already poor,
a large frame could compound
the network congestion issue.
So, can we use
a predictive frame
instead of a key frame
for refresh?
The answer is yes,
if we have
frame acknowledgement.
Let me show you how it works.
First, we need to decide frames
that require acknowledgement.
We call these frames
long-term reference, or LTR.
This is the decision
from the encoder.
When the sender client
transmits an LTR frame,
it also needs to request
acknowledgement
from the receiver client.
If the LTR frame
is successfully received,
an acknowledgement
needs to be sent back.
Once the sender client
gets the acknowledgement
and passes that information
to the encoder,
the encoder knows
which LTR frames
have been received
by the other side.
Let’s look at the bad network
situation again.
When the encoder
gets the refresh request,
since this time,
the encoder has
a bunch of acknowledged LTRs,
it is able
to encode a frame
that is predicted
from one of these
acknowledged LTRs.
A frame that is encoded
in this way is called LTR-P.
Usually an LTR-P is much smaller
in terms of encoded frame size
compared to a key frame,
so it is easier to transmit.
Now, let’s talk about
the APIs for LTR.
Note that
the frame acknowledgement
needs to be handled
by application layer.
It can be done with mechanisms
such as RPSI message
in RTP Control Protocol.
Here we’re only going
to focus on how the encoder
and the sender client
communicate in this process.
Once you have enabled
low-latency encoding,
you can enable this feature
by setting
EnableLTR session property.
When an LTR frame is encoded,
the encoder will signal
a unique frame token
in the sample attachment
RequireLTRAcknowledgementToken.
The sender client
is responsible for reporting
the acknowledged LTR frames
to the encoder
through AcknowledgedLTRTokens
frame property.
Since more than one
acknowledgement can come
at a time,
we need to use an array
to store these frame tokens.
You can request
a refresh frame at any time
through ForceLTRRefresh
frame property.
Once the encoder
receives this request,
an LTR-P will be encoded.
If there is
no acknowledged LTR available,
the encoder will generate
a key frame in this case.
All right.
Now we’ve covered
the new features
in low-latency mode.
We can talk about
using these features together.
For example,
we can use temporal scalability
and max frame
quantization parameter
for a group screen
sharing application.
The temporal scalability
can efficiently
generate output videos
for each recipient,
and we can lower
the max frame QP
for a sharper UI
and text in the screen content.
If the communication
goes through a poor network
and a refresh frame
is needed to recover
from the error,
long-term reference can be used.
And if the receiver can only
decode constrained profiles,
we can encode with
constrained baseline profile
or constrained high profile.
OK.
We’ve covered a few topics here.
We’ve introduced a low-latency
encoding mode in Video Toolbox.
We’ve talked about how
to use VTCompressionSession APIs
to encode videos
in low-latency mode.
Besides the latency benefit,
we also developed
a bunch of new features
to address the requirements
for real-time video application.
With all these improvements,
I hope the low-latency mode
can make your video app
more amazing.
Thanks for watching
and have a great WWDC 2021.
[upbeat music]