[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Eugene Zhidkov:
Hi and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Eugene Zhidkov.
I am from GPU software.
And together, with Harsh Patil
from Mac system architecture,
we'll show you how to create
image-processing applications
powered by Metal
on Apple silicon.
First, I will focus
on the best practices
and lessons learned,
optimizing image-processing
applications for M1
based on developer engagements
we have had over the last year.
And then Harsh will give you
a step-by-step guide
to how you can redesign
your image-processing pipeline
for optimal performance
on Apple silicon.
So let’s jump right in!
To start, let’s briefly revisit
Apple system
on-the-chip architecture
and its benefits.
Many image-processing
and video-editing apps
are designed
with discrete GPUs in mind.
So it’s important to highlight
what’s so different
about Apple GPUs.
First, all Apple chips use
Unified Memory Architecture.
All blocks --
such as CPU, GPU,
Neural and Media engines --
have access to the same
system memory
using unified memory interface.
And second, our GPUs are
Tile Based Deferred Renderers,
or TBDRs.
TBDRs have two main phases:
tiling,
where whole render surfaces
split into tiles
and processed geometry
is then handled independently;
and rendering,
where all of the pixels will be
processed for each tile.
So in order to be most efficient
on Apple silicon,
your image-processing app
should start leveraging
unified memory --
to avoid any copies
your pipeline used to have --
and TBDR architecture
by exploiting tile memory
and local image block.
To learn more about how
Apple TBDR works at low level
and how to target
our shader core,
please watch these sessions
from the last year.
And now, let’s talk about
the exact things
we are going to do to optimize
image-processing
compute workloads
for Apple silicon.
Last year,
we’ve been working closely
with many great developers
on their image pipeline
transitions.
We picked the six most
rewarding tips to share.
First, we’ll discuss
how to avoid
unnecessary memory copies
or blits.
This is really important
given we are now working
with images up to 8K.
Then, we wanted to highlight
the benefits of using
render pipeline and textures
instead of using compute
on buffers
and how you could do that
in your own
image-processing pipeline.
Once we have the render
and textures paths
up and running,
we wanted to show you
the importance of proper
load/store actions
and memoryless attachments.
This will help you getting
the most out of the tile memory.
Then, we’ll talk how to best
approach Uber-shaders
with its dynamic control flow
and also how to leverage
smaller data types --
such as short and half --
to improve performance
and efficiency.
And we’ll finish
with important advice
about texture formats
to get the best throughput.
All right.
So let’s get started with one
of the most rewarding tips:
avoiding unneeded blits
on Apple silicon.
Most image-processing apps are
designed around discrete GPUs.
With discrete GPUs,
you have separate system memory
and video memory.
To make the frame image visible
or resident to the GPU,
explicit copy is required.
Moreover,
it is usually required twice;
to upload the data
for the GPU to process it,
and to pull it back.
Let’s consider we are decoding
an 8K video, processing it,
and saving it to disk.
So this is a CPU thread,
decoding, in this case.
That’s where we need to copy
the decoded frame to GPU VRAM.
And here is GPU timeline,
where all the effects
and filters are applied.
Let’s take it one step further
and let’s recall
we need to save the results
to disk, right?
So we must also consider
bringing the processed frame
back to system memory
and the actual encoding
of the frame.
So, these are known as "copy"
or "blit gaps",
and advanced
image-processing applications
had to do deep pipelining
and other smart things
to fill them in.
Well, the good news
is that on Apple GPUs,
blitting for the sake
of residence
is no longer needed.
Since memory is shared,
both the CPU and GPU
can access it directly.
So please add a simple check
to detect if you are running
on unified memory system
and avoid unnecessary copies.
It will save you memory, time,
and is an absolute first step
to do.
So this is where we land
on Unified Memory Architecture
with the blits removed.
By removing the blits,
we completely avoid copy gaps
and can start processing
immediately.
This also gives better CPU
and GPU pipelining
with less hassle.
Let’s make sure you implement
unified memory path
with no copies involved.
If you just leave blit copies
exactly as it was
on the discrete GPU,
you’ll pay with system
memory bandwidth,
less GPU time
for actual processing,
and potential
scheduling overhead.
Not to mention we no longer need
separate VRAM image allocated.
GPU frame capture can help
you with spotting large blits.
Please inspect
your application blits
and make sure you only do
the copies required.
Now, let’s talk about
how exactly we should start
leveraging Apple GPU
TBDR architecture
for image processing.
Most image-processing
applications operate
on image buffers by dispatching
series of compute kernels.
When you dispatch
a compute kernel
in default serial mode,
Metal guarantees that
all subsequent dispatches
see all the memory writes.
This guarantee implies memory
coherency for all shader cores,
so every memory write is made
visible to all other cores
by the time
the next dispatch starts.
This also means memory traffic
could be really high;
the whole image has to be read
and written to.
With M1, Apple GPUs enable
tile dispatches on MacOS.
In contrast to regular compute,
they operate in tile memory
with tile-only sync points.
Some filters --
like convolutions --
cannot be mapped
to the tile paradigm,
but many other filters can!
Deferring system memory flush
until the encoder end point
provides solid efficiency gains.
You can execute more useful
GPU work
when not limited
by system memory bandwidth.
To take it even further,
let’s notice that many
per-pixel operations
don’t require access
to neighboring pixels,
so tile sync point
is not necessary.
This maps really well
to fragment functions.
Fragment functions
can be executed
without implicit tile sync,
requiring sync
only at the encoder boundary
or when tile kernels
are dispatched serially
after the fragment kernels.
We now learned that Apple GPUs
enable fragment functions
and tile kernels for
more efficient image processing.
Let’s see how we could use that.
We do that by converting
regular compute dispatches
on buffers to render
command encoder on textures.
As we just discussed,
rule of thumb is the following.
Per-pixel operations
with no interpixel dependency
should be implemented
using fragment functions.
Any filter with threadgroup
scoped operations
should be implemented
with tile shading,
since neighbor pixels access
within a tile is required.
Scatter-gather
and convolution filters
cannot be mapped
to tile paradigm
since they require
random access,
so these should still remain
compute dispatches.
Render command encoder
also enables
a unique Apple GPU feature:
lossless bandwidth compression
for textures and render targets.
This is a really great
bandwidth saver,
especially for
an image-processing pipeline,
so let’s see
how we should use it.
Well, speaking of enabling
lossless compression,
it’s actually easier to say
what you should not do.
First, already-compressed
texture formats
cannot benefit from lossless.
Second, there are
three particular texture flags
which cannot work
with this compression,
so make sure you don’t set them
just by an accident.
And third, linear textures --
or backed by an MTLBuffer --
are not allowed as well.
Some special treatment
is also required
for nonprivate textures;
make sure to call
optimizeContentsForGPUAccess
to stay on the fastest path.
GPU frame capture Summary pane
now shows you
lossless compression warnings
and highlights the reasons
why the texture has opted out.
In this example,
PixelFormatView flag was set.
In many cases,
developers are setting
these flags unintentionally.
Don’t set PixelFormatView
if all you need is components
swizzle or sRGB conversion.
All right, we have the render
and textures path
up and running.
Now, let’s make sure
we properly use tile memory.
Tile memory TBDR concepts --
such as load/store actions
and memoryless attachments --
are totally new
to the desktop world.
So let’s make sure
we use them properly.
Let’s start
with load/store actions!
As we already know,
the whole render target
is split into the tiles.
Load/store are per-tile
bulk actions
guaranteed to take
the most optimal path
through memory hierarchy.
They are executed at the
beginning of the render pass --
where we tell the GPU how
to initialize the tile memory --
and at the end of the pass
to inform the GPU
what attachments
need to be written back.
The key thing here is to avoid
loading what we don’t need.
If we are overwriting
the whole image,
or the resource is temporary,
set load action
to LoadActionDontCare.
With render encoder,
you no longer need to clear
your output or temporary data,
as you probably did before
with dedicated compute pass
or fillBuffer call.
By setting LoadActionClear,
you can efficiently specify
the clear value.
And the same goes
for the store action.
Make sure to only store the data
you will later need --
like the main attachment --
and don’t store
anything temporary.
Besides explicit load
and store actions,
Apple GPUs saves
your memory footprint
with memoryless attachments.
We can explicitly define
an attachment
as having memoryless
storage mode.
This enables tile-only
memory allocation,
meaning that your resource
will persist
for each and every tile
only within encoder lifetime.
This can greatly reduce
your memory footprint,
especially for 6K/8K images,
where every frame takes
hundreds of megabytes.
Let’s see how this all
can be done in code.
We start by creating
the textureDescriptor
and then create
the outputTexture.
We then create
a temporary texture.
Notice that I’ve marked it
memoryless,
as we don’t want
any storage here.
Then we create the render pass
by first describing
what the attachments are
and then what are
the load/store actions.
We don’t care about loading
the output
since it is fully overwritten,
but we need to store it.
As for the temporary texture,
we don’t load but clear it,
and we don’t need
to store it either.
Finally, we create our
renderPass from the descriptor.
That’s it.
So we are using unified memory,
moved our image-processing
pipeline
to render command encoder,
and are properly leveraging
tile memory.
Now, let’s talk about
uber-shaders.
Uber-shaders, or uber-kernels,
is a pretty popular way
to make developers' life easier.
Host code sets up
the control structure,
and shader just loops through
a series of if/else statements,
for example,
if tone mapping is enabled
or if the input is in HDR
or SDR formats.
This approach is also known
as "ubers-shader"
and is really good at bringing
total number
of pipeline state objects down.
However, it has drawbacks.
The main one is increased
register pressure
to keep up with more complex
control flow.
Using more registers can easily
limit maximum occupancy
your shader is running at.
Consider a simple kernel where
we pass in the control struct.
We use flags inside the struct
to control what we do.
We have two features here:
if the input is in HDR
and if tonemapping is enabled.
All look good, right?
Well, here is what happens
on the GPU.
Since we cannot deduce anything
at compile time,
we have to assume
we could take both paths --
HDR and non-HDR --
and then combine
based on the flag.
Same goes for tone mapping.
We evaluate it and then mask it
in or out,
based on the input flag.
The problem here is registers.
Every control flow path
needs live registers.
This is where uber-shaders
are not so good.
As you recall,
registers used by the kernel
define maximum occupancy
the shader could run.
That happens because registers
file is shared by all simdlanes
on the shader core.
If we could only run
what’s only needed,
that would enable
higher simdgroup concurrency
and GPU utilization.
Let’s talk how to fix this.
Metal API has the right tool
for the job,
and it's called
"function_constants".
We define
both control parameters
as function_constants,
and we modify the code
accordingly.
Here, we are showing
the modified kernel code.
Host side must be also updated
to provide
function_constant value
at pipeline creation time.
Another great way
to reduce register pressure
is using 16-bit types
in your shaders.
Apple GPUs have native
16-bit type support.
So, when using
smaller data types,
your shaders will require
less registers,
increasing occupancy.
Half and short types
also require less energy
and might achieve
higher peak rates.
So, please use half
and short types
instead of float and int
when possible,
since type conversions
are usually free.
In this example,
consider a kernel
using the thread_position
in threadgroup
for some computations.
We are using unsigned int,
but the maximum threadgroup size
supported by Metal
can easily fit in
unsigned short.
threadgroup_position_in_grid,
however,
could potentially require
a larger data type.
But for the grid sizes we’re
using in image processing --
up to 8K or 16K --
unsigned short is also enough.
If we use 16-bit types instead,
the resulting code
will use a smaller number
of registers,
potentially increasing
the occupancy.
Now, let me show you
where you can have
all the details on registers.
GPU frame debugger in Xcode13
now has advanced pipeline state
object view for render,
tile, and compute PSOs.
You can inspect
detailed pipeline statistics --
now with registers usage --
and fine-tune all your shaders.
With register concerns covered,
let’s talk about
texture formats.
First, we want to note
that different pixel formats
might have
different sampling rates.
Depending on hardware generation
and number of channels,
wider floating-point types
might have
reduced point sampling rate.
Especially floating-point
formats such as RGBA32F
will be slower
than FP16 variants
when sampling filtered values.
Smaller types
reduce memory storage,
bandwidth,
and cache footprint as well.
So we encourage, again,
to use the smallest type
possible,
but in this case,
for the textures storage.
This was actually a common case
for 3D LUTs in image processing;
most applications we worked with
were using float RGBA
for a 3D LUT application phase
with bilinear filtering enabled.
Please consider if your app
can instead use halfs
and the precision
will be enough.
If that’s the case,
switch to FP16 right away
to get peak sampling rates.
If half precision is not enough,
we found out that fixed-point
unsigned short
provides great uniform range
of values,
so encoding your LUTs
in unit scale
and providing LUT range
to the shader
was a great way to get
both peak sampling rate
and sufficient numerical
accuracy.
All right, so we just went over
how we should leverage
Apple GPU architecture to make
your image-processing pipeline
run as efficient as possible.
To apply it all right away,
please meet Harsh!
Harsh Patil: Thanks, Eugene.
Now let’s walk through
redesigning
an image-processing pipeline
for Apple silicon
based on all the best practices
we have learned so far.
To be specific,
we are going to tailor
the image-processing phase
of the video-processing pipeline
for Apple GPUs.
Real-time image processing
is very GPU compute
and memory bandwidth intensive.
We will first understand
how it is usually designed
and then how we can optimize it
for Apple silicon.
We are not going to go
into the details
of video-editing workflow
in this section,
so please refer to our talk
from two years ago.
We will solely focus
on transitioning
the compute part of
image processing to render path.
Before we start,
let's begin quickly take a look
at where image-processing phase
stands in a typical
video-processing pipeline.
We'll take ProRes-encoded
input file as an example.
We first read the ProRes-encoded
frame from the disk
or external storage.
We then decode the frame on CPU,
and now
the image-processing phase
executes on this decoded frame
on the GPU
and renders
the final output frame.
Finally,
we display this output frame.
We could additionally also
encode the final rendered frame
for delivery.
Next, let’s take a look
at what comprises
an image-processing pipeline.
Image processing starts with
unpacking different channels
of the source image
RGB in alpha
into separate buffers
in the beginning.
We will process
each of these channels
in our image-processing
pipeline,
either together or separately.
Next, there might be
color space conversions
to operate in the desired
color-managed environment.
We then apply a 3D LUT;
perform color corrections;
and then apply spatial-temporal
noise reduction, convolutions,
blurs, and other effects.
And finally,
we pack the individually
processed channels together
for final output.
What do these selected steps
have in common?
They are all point filters,
operating only on a single pixel
with no interpixel dependency.
These map well to fragment
shader implementation.
Spatial and convolution-style
operations
require access
to large radius of pixels,
and we have scattered
read-write access patterns
as well.
These are well-suited
for compute kernels.
We’ll use this knowledge later.
For now, let’s see how
these operations are executed.
Applications represent
chain of effects
applied to an image
as a filter graph.
Every filter is its own kernel,
processing the inputs
from the previous stage
and producing outputs
for the next stage.
Every arrow here means a buffer
being written
to/from output of one stage
and read as the input
in the next stage.
Since memory is limited,
applications usually linearize
the graph
by doing a topological sort.
This is done to keep the total
number of intermediate resources
as low as possible while
also avoiding race conditions.
This simple filter graph
in that example
would need two intermediate
buffers to be able to operate
without race conditions
and produce the final output.
The linearized graph here
roughly represents
the GPU command buffer encoding
as well.
Let’s look deeper on why
this filter graph
is very device memory
bandwidth intensive.
Every filter operation
has to load whole image
from device memory
into the registers
and write the result
back to the device memory.
And that’s quite a bit
of memory traffic.
Let’s estimate
the memory footprint
for a 4K-frame image processing
based on our example
image-processing graph.
A 4K decoded frame itself
takes 67 megabytes of memory
for floating-point 16 precision
or 135 megabytes of memory
for floating-point 32 precision,
and professional workflows
absolutely need
floating-point 32 precision.
For processing one 4K frame
in floating-point 32 precision
through this image-processing
graph, we are talking more than
two gigabytes of read-write
traffic to device memory.
Also, writes to buffers holding
the intermediate output
thrashes the cache hierarchy
and impacts other blocks
on the chip as well.
Regular compute kernels
don’t benefit from the on-chip
tile memory implicitly.
Kernels can explicitly allocate
threadgroup-scoped memory,
which will be backed
by the on-chip tile memory.
However, that tile memory
is not persistent
across dispatches
within a compute encoder.
In contrast, the tile memory
is actually persistent
across draw passes within
one render command encoder.
Let’s see how we can redesign
this representative
image-processing pipeline
to leverage the tile memory.
We are going to address this
by following three steps.
We first change the compute pass
to render pass
and all the intermediate
output buffers to textures.
We then encode
per-pixel operations
with no interpixel dependency
as fragment shader invocations
within one render
command encoder,
making sure to account
for all the intermediate results
and setting appropriate
load/store actions.
And finally, we discuss what do
we do in more complex situation
than just point filters.
Our first step
is to use separate
MTLRenderCommandEncoder
to encode eligible shaders.
In this filter graph, unpack,
color space conversion, LUT,
and color-correction filters
are all point per-pixel filters
that we can convert
to fragment shader
and encode them using
one render command encoder.
Similarly, mixer
and pack shaders --
which are towards the end
of this image-processing
pipeline --
can also be converted
to fragment shaders
and encoded using another
MTLRenderCommandEncoder.
Then we can invoke these shaders
within their respective
render passes.
When you create the render pass,
all the resources attached
to the color attachments
in that render pass
are implicitly tiled for you.
A fragment shader can only
update the image block data
associated with
fragment’s position in the tile.
Next shader in the same
render pass
can pick up the output
of the previous shader
directly from the tile memory.
In the next section,
we will take a look
at how we can structure
the fragment shaders
which map to these filters.
We will also take a look
at what constructs
we need to define and use
to enable access
to the underlying tile memory
from within
these fragment shaders.
And finally, we will take a look
at how the output generated
in the tile memory
by one fragment shader
can be consumed
directly from the tile memory
by the next fragment shader
within the same
render command encoder.
This is what you have to do
in your code.
Here I have attached
output image as a texture
attached to color attachment 0
of the render pass descriptor.
I have attached texture
holding intermediate result
to color attachment 1
of the render pass descriptor.
Both of these will be
implicitly tiled for you.
Please set the appropriate
load/store properties
as discussed earlier
in the talk.
Now, set up a structure
to access these textures
in your fragment shader.
In the coming examples,
we will show how to use
this structure
within your fragment shaders.
You simply access the output
and the intermediate textures
within your fragment shader
as highlighted
by using the structure
we defined earlier.
Writes to these textures
are done
to appropriate
tile memory location
corresponding to the fragment.
Output produced by the unpack
shader is consumed as input
by color space conversion shader
using the same structure
that we defined earlier.
This fragment shader can do
its own processing
and update the output
and intermediate textures
which will, once again,
update the corresponding
tile memory location.
You are to continue
the same steps
for all the other
fragment shaders
within the same
render encoder pass.
Next, let's visualize
how this sequence of operations
looks now with these changes.
As you can see,
now you have unpack,
color space conversion,
application of 3D LUT,
and color-correction steps,
all executed on the tile memory
using one render pass
with no device memory passes
in between.
At the end of the render pass,
render targets
that are not memoryless
are flushed
to the device memory.
You can then execute
the next class of filters.
Let’s talk a bit about filters
that have scatter-gather
access patterns.
Kernels representing
such filters
can directly operate on the data
in the device memory.
Convolution filters
are very well-suited
for tile-based operations
in compute kernels.
Here, you can express intent
to use tile memory
by declaring a
threadgroup-scoped memory.
Now, you bring in the block
of pixels into the tile memory
along with all the necessary
halo pixels,
depending upon
the filter radius,
and perform
the convolution operation
directly on the tile memory.
Remember,
tile memory is not persistent
across compute dispatches
within a compute encoder.
So after executing Filter1,
you have to explicitly flush
the tile memory contents
to device memory.
That way, Filter2 can consume
the output of Filter1.
So where do we land once we make
all of these changes?
For processing one 4K frame
in floating-point 32 precision
through our example restructured
image-processing graph,
here’s what we have now.
Bandwidth goes down
from 2.16 gigabytes
to just load and store
worth 810 megabytes,
and that’s 62 percent reduction
in memory traffic
to the device memory.
We don't need two intermediate
device buffers
saving 270 megabytes
of memory per frame.
And finally, we have
reduced cache thrashing,
and that's because
all the fragment shaders
within that render pass
are operating
directly on the tile memory.
One of the key features
of Apple silicon
is its
Unified Memory Architecture.
Let’s see an example
of how to leverage
this Unified Memory Architecture
for interaction
between different blocks
on the Apple silicon.
We will take HEVC encoding
of the final video frame
rendered by GPU
as a case study.
This encoding is done using
dedicated hardware media engines
on Apple silicon.
The final output frame
rendered by the GPU
can be consumed directly
by our media engines
with no extra memory copies.
In the coming section,
we will walk through an example
on how to set up a pipeline
for HEVC encoding
of the final output frame
produced by the GPU
in the most efficient way.
For that, first we will leverage
CoreVideo API
to create a pool
of pixel buffers
backed by IOSurfaces.
Then, using the Metal API,
we render the final frames
into Metal textures
backed by IOSurfaces
from the pool we just created.
And finally, we dispatch
these pixel buffers
directly to the media engine
for encode
without any additional copies
of the output frames
produced by the GPU,
thus leveraging
the Unified Memory Architecture.
Let’s walk through
on how to do this step by step
and covering all the constructs
we need to enable this flow.
First, we create
a CVPixelBufferPool
backed by IOSurface
in the desired pixel format.
Here, we will use the biplanar
chroma-subsampled
pixel format for HEVC encode.
Now, you get a CVPixelBuffer
from this CVPixelBufferPool.
Pass this CVPixelBuffer
to the MetalTextureCache
with the right plane index
to get
the CVMetalTextureReference.
Since we are using
biplanar pixel format,
you need to perform this step
for both planes
of the biplanar pixel buffer.
Next, get the underlying
Metal texture from the
CVMetalTextureReference
object.
Perform this step for both
luma and chroma planes.
Remember that
these Metal textures
are backed by the same
IOSurfaces
which are also backing
the CVPixelBuffer planes.
Using Metal API,
render into the textures
corresponding to luma
and chroma planes.
This will update the IOSurface
which backs these Metal textures
as well.
We highly recommend doing
the chroma subsampling step
on the chroma planes
on the GPU itself
as a shader pass within
your image-processing pipeline.
An important thing to note
is that both CVPixelBuffer
and the Metal textures --
which we just rendered into --
are backed by the same
underlying IOSurface copy
in the system memory.
You can now send
this CVPixelBuffer
directly to the media engine
for encode.
As you can see,
due to the Unified Memory
Architecture,
we can seamlessly move data
between GPU
and media engine block
with no memory copies.
And finally, remember to release
the CVPixelBuffer
and CVMetalTexture reference
after every frame.
Releasing the CVPixelBuffer
enables recycling of this buffer
for future frames.
To wrap up, we encourage
you again to do the following:
leverage Unified Memory
Architecture,
use MTLRenderCommandEncoder
instead of compute
when applicable,
merge all your eligible
render passes
within single render
command encoder,
set appropriate
load/store actions,
use memoryless
for transient resources,
leverage tile shading
when applicable,
and use buffer pools
with other APIs for zero-copy.
We want to thank you
for joining this session today.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC 2021!
[SPEAKS FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
♪