[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Itai Rom: Welcome to
"Customize your advanced
Xcode Cloud workflows."
My name is Itai,
and I'll be joined later
by my colleague, Yan.
This year we're introducing
Xcode Cloud.
Xcode Cloud is a continuous
integration and delivery service
built into Xcode
and designed exclusively
for Apple developers.
In other sessions,
we've shown how you can set up
end-to-end workflows
to continuously build, test,
and distribute your apps.
In this session,
we're going to talk about
some more advanced features
that you can use
to customize Xcode Cloud
to better fit your team's needs.
Xcode Cloud is designed
to integrate
with Apple developer tools
and services --
like the developer website,
TestFlight,
and App Store Connect --
right out of the box.
It also integrates
with your essential,
day-to-day development tools,
like all major Git-based
source control providers,
and even Slack for messaging.
However, you may have
in-house or proprietary tools
and other external services that
are a key part of your pipeline.
In this session,
we'll demonstrate
how you can customize
Xcode Cloud
to integrate well with
these tools and services.
We're going to cover
four customization topics.
First, we'll discuss using
environment variables
to pass extra bits of
information into your builds.
We'll learn how to use scripts
to run custom commands
in the actions
you run in your build.
And also how to add
other source repositories
that you need during a build.
And finally,
how you can use webhooks
to integrate Xcode Cloud with
other systems your team uses.
There's a lot to cover,
so let's get straight into it
with environment variables.
As you plan and configure
workflows for your project,
there may be times when you want
the behavior of your build
to be slightly different
depending on which
workflow is running.
For example, if your app depends
on an API service,
you may want your tests
to use a staging environment
rather than production.
In this case, you'd want to pass
a different URL
for the API service
into your tests.
Environment variables
allow you to do just that.
They're simple key-value pairs
that allow you to define
some information
that you can use
to further control
the behavior of your build.
You can configure any
environment variables you need
right in the Environment section
of your workflow.
Since they're part
of your workflow configuration,
you don't have to commit
any additional information
to your source repository.
Every time your workflow runs,
the variables you've defined
will be set in the environments
that are running the actions.
For sensitive information,
like API keys or access tokens,
you can configure
a secret environment variable.
Secret environment variables
are handled securely.
They're encrypted and stored
securely at all times,
and their decrypted values
are only available
in the temporary environments
that are used
to run your actions.
The values are also
redacted from logs,
and you can't view them
in the workflow editor
like you can for
a nonsecret variable.
Making an environment variable
secret is easy.
Just check the "Secret" checkbox
in the environment variables
table.
The value of your
environment variable
will then be hidden from view
and once you save your change,
will be stored securely
and can no longer be viewed
in the workflow editor.
Environment variables provide
a handy mechanism
to customize behavior
and pass additional information
into your workflows.
They're even more powerful
in conjunction with
our next advanced feature:
custom scripts.
Between Xcode Cloud's workflows
and Xcode's schemes,
you have a lot of flexibility in
how you can set up the actions
that you want to run
in your workflows.
But sometimes you'll need
to run custom logic
or additional commands
during an action,
and custom scripts
provide a powerful
and flexible way
to achieve this.
A custom script is
a shell script that you write
and include in
your source repository.
Your custom scripts are run
in each of the actions
in your workflow.
There are three types
of scripts available:
the post-clone script,
the pre-Xcodebuild script,
and the post-Xcodebuild script.
Each time Xcode Cloud
runs an action
it performs a series of steps
and each of the custom scripts,
as hinted at by its name,
is run as a step at
a particular point in an action.
First, Xcode Cloud sets up
a temporary environment
and clones source code
from your primary repository.
Afterwards, Xcode Cloud
runs the post-clone script.
After resolving all other
source dependencies,
Xcode cloud runs
the pre-Xcodebuild script.
Next, Xcode Cloud
runs the action's
corresponding
Xcodebuild command.
When the Xcodebuild step
finishes,
Xcode Cloud runs
the post-Xcodebuild script
and saves any artifacts
it generated earlier.
If your workflow includes
several actions --
for example,
multiple build actions --
or build, test, analyze,
and archive actions --
Xcode Cloud runs
your custom scripts
at the appropriate times
for each action.
Adding a custom script
to Xcode Cloud is easy.
You simply add a shell script
with the appropriate name
into a folder
called "ci_scripts",
and place this folder at the
same level as the project file
or workspace you're
using in your workflow.
Since custom scripts
are part of your source code,
you can test out script changes
in pull requests
or even customize their behavior
on different branches.
When Xcode Cloud
runs your actions,
it looks for the existence
of each of the scripts
at the appropriate time
and runs them
if they're present.
You don't need to configure
your workflow
to run your custom scripts.
If the scripts are there,
they'll be run.
Do note that the name
of the ci_scripts folder
and the scripts inside
must exactly match
this naming convention
in order for Xcode Cloud to find
and run your scripts.
Environment variables
that you've configured
in your workflow are available
to use in your custom scripts,
including secret
environment variables.
In addition,
Xcode Cloud also provides
a variety of other useful
environment variables.
You can use these variables
to add flow control
to your scripts,
so that you can ensure
the commands you want to run
are run at the correct points
during your workflow.
For example, if you want to
check if your action is running
for iOS, macOS,
tvOS, or watchOS,
you can use the value of the
CI_PRODUCT_PLATFORM variable.
In a more targeted scenario --
perhaps there's a command
you only want to run
during the archive action
of a specific workflow --
you can check that the
CI_XCODEBUILD_ACTION
and CI_WORKFLOW variables
match the archive action
and the specific workflow
before running the command.
Let's see custom scripts
in action.
My team works on a smoothie
ordering app called Fruta.
In the "Explore Xcode Cloud
workflows" session,
you learned how to set up
workflows to build, test,
and distribute apps, like Fruta.
We use Xcode Cloud
to build and test
every time we create
a pull request.
We also distribute builds
from our pull requests
to members of our team
via TestFlight,
allowing them to verify
and sign off on changes
before the code is merged.
Today, I'd like to make it
easier for team members
to tell if the build installed
on their device
is from a pull request.
We can do that by using
a different app icon
when we're building
from a pull request.
As you might've guessed,
using a custom script makes
setting this up a breeze.
Let's see how.
Over in Xcode, I already have
the Fruta project open.
Before I can add
a custom script,
I first need to add a
ci_scripts folder to my project.
I can do this by selecting my
project in the project navigator
and clicking the plus button
at the bottom
and then selecting New Group.
I'll type in the folder
name, ci_scripts.
[KEYSTROKES]
Next, I'll add
the beta app icon set
that our designer created
to the ci_scripts folder,
so that my custom script
can swap it into place
during the build.
To do that, I'll drag it in
to my ci_scripts folder
from Finder.
In the sheet, I'll uncheck
any selected targets
and click Finish.
Finally, let's add
a pre-Xcodebuild script.
This script will run prior
to the Xcodebuild command,
and I'll use it to swap
Fruta's default app icon set
with the beta app icon set
when appropriate.
I've already created
a script to use,
so all I need to do is add it
into the ci_scripts folder.
Again, I'll uncheck
any targets in the sheet
and click Finish.
Now that my script is in place,
let's take a closer look
at what it does.
First, I want to make sure
that the app icon
is only swapped out
when the build is coming
from a pull request.
I can use one of the
environment variables
that Xcode Cloud provides
to check at run time
if the build is
a pull request or not.
There are a variety
of environment variables
related to pull requests
that I could use for this,
but in this case
I'm going to check that
the CI_PULL_REQUEST_NUMBER
environment variable is set.
Also, I only want
the beta app icon to be used
for builds that are distributed
to TestFlight.
Whenever Xcode Cloud distributes
a build to TestFlight,
it always builds an archive
of the project first.
So a good way
to check this is to verify
if the CI_XCODEBUILD_ACTION
environment variable's value
is "archive".
If both of these
environment variables
have the expected values,
then I remove the existing
app icon set
and replace it with
the beta app icon set
using the rm and mv commands.
Also, take note that I'm using
the CI_WORKSPACE
environment variable
to construct the right path
for both the default
and the beta app icon sets.
All that's left to do
is to open up a pull request
with these changes
and wait for Xcode Cloud
to build and distribute
Fruta to TestFlight.
Rather than walk through
that process now,
I've prepared a build
ahead of time.
Here, Xcode Cloud has built
and distributed Fruta
from my pull request branch.
In the TestFlight app
on my phone,
I can verify that my build
is using the new beta app icon
I just added.
Now I can merge my pull request
and everyone on the team
will start seeing the same
beta app icon
in builds of their own
pull requests.
Now that we've seen how to use
custom scripts in Xcode Cloud,
there are a few important things
to note about them.
The standard output and standard
error from your custom scripts
are included in the logs
for the action they ran in,
and they can also be downloaded
from the Artifacts tab.
If your script doesn't appear
to be running
when you expect it to,
double-check that
you've named it correctly
and placed it
in a ci_scripts folder
alongside your project
or workspace.
Make sure to add helpful logging
and resiliency to aid you
in troubleshooting any failures
in your custom scripts.
For example, if your script
makes network requests
to external services,
you may want to include logic
to retry those requests
with verbose logging enabled.
Additionally, Xcode Cloud
respects the exit codes
of your scripts.
So if your script exits
with a nonzero value,
Xcode Cloud will consider
this a failure
and will fail
the overall action.
You can take advantage of this
to ensure that the commands
you need to run
in your script are successful
before Xcode Cloud continues
on with the rest of the action.
Lastly, it should be noted
that in a test action,
multiple environments are used
to build and run your tests.
Only the environment that
is used for building your tests
will have your source code
cloned into it by default.
The environments
that run your tests
won't have source code
cloned into them.
They'll only have the ci_scripts
folder made available on them.
As a result,
the post-clone script
won't run in these environments
and your custom scripts
and any of their dependencies,
such as other shell scripts
and small tools,
must be entirely contained
within the ci_scripts folder.
With custom scripts
and environment variables,
you have two powerful tools
to customize the behavior
of your workflows.
Next, my colleague Yan
will show you
how to use additional
repositories with Xcode Cloud
so that you can make use
of Swift packages
and other dependencies
in your workflows.
Yan Huang: Thanks, Itai.
Many projects are built
using tools,
libraries, and frameworks.
Those dependencies are often
hosted in Git repositories
shared across projects,
and they need to be retrieved
for your project
to build successfully.
Xcode Cloud automatically helps
adding these extra repositories.
For example, we want to add
a new feature to allow users
to invite their friends
and share a drink
to the Fruta app.
Another team has implemented
a similar feature.
So we are going to reuse their
package called "InvitationsKit",
which is hosted
on a private Git repository
shared with my team.
Let's see how to add
this package.
Here am I in Xcode
with the Fruta project.
I can add a package
from the File menu
and select Add Package.
I already have the Nature Labs
shared packages collection,
which contains a list
of packages
within our organization.
I'm going to select
InvitationsKit
and click on Add Package.
Now that the dependency
is added,
I'm going to commit
this new dependency
from the Source Control menu
and push my changes
to my branch.
We setup a workflow
in Xcode Cloud
that will start a new build
when it receives a new commit
from any branch.
So this new commit
should initiate a new build.
Since this is the first time
that we're adding
this dependency,
I expect that the build
is going to fail
because Xcode Cloud
does not have access
to the InvitationsKit
repository.
But Xcode Cloud provides an easy
UI to address this issue.
Let's head to Xcode Cloud
in App Store Connect
and take a look
at this new build.
As expected,
the build has failed.
Xcode Cloud shows
a warning banner
indicating that it has an issue
with accessing the repository
and provides me with the option
to grant access to it.
I go ahead and click on the
Manage Repositories button.
It takes me
to the settings page,
where I can hover over the
invitationsKit repository link
and then click on Grant.
Depending on
your source control service,
you might be directed
to approve Xcode Cloud
to access the repository.
I went ahead and provided access
to InvitationsKit in Github.
Now, when I look back
in Xcode Cloud,
it shows Access Granted.
I can now rerun the build.
We expect this build
to pass this time.
You can go back to the
Additional Repositories section
under Settings to find out
all the repositories
that have been connected.
You can also reject
access from there
if they are no longer
being used.
Xcode Cloud will detect
newly referenced repositories
during a build.
When we add a dependency
that Xcode Cloud
does not have access to,
the UI provides a quick and easy
way to fix this issue.
This is valid
for any Git operations
including cloning a repository
inside a custom script
or referencing a Git submodule.
This also applies
to all the other
dependency management tools.
In this demo,
we used the new Swift Packages
Collection feature
to include
an additional package.
If you want to learn
more about it, check out
"Discover and curate Swift
Packages using Collections."
So far we have demonstrated to
you how to customize your build
within Xcode Cloud.
But sometimes you and your team
may also want to collaborate
through external services.
For example, you may want
to notify the beta testers
when a new build is ready.
This is where webhooks
can come to help.
Webhooks provide
a way for Xcode Cloud
to communicate
with your services.
With its rich payload that
is sent at different stages
of a build lifecycle,
you will be able to further
automate your workflow
and improve your teams'
collaborations.
Let's dive in
to find out more about it.
You can set up webhooks
in Xcode Cloud
to receive
your real-time updates
at three different stages
of your build.
First, when the build
is created,
either because
you pushed some code
or manually started a build;
then, when the build
is starting;
finally, when the build
has completed,
no matter if the build failed
or succeeded.
Let's see how to add
a new webhook to our project
Adding webhooks is easy
in Xcode Cloud.
Click on Settings tab
on the left column.
Click on Webhooks
and then the plus button.
Then it will ask you to enter
the names of your webhook
and the URL
to an app or services
that's capable of receiving
and handling HTTP requests.
Then, click on Save.
Xcode Cloud allows you to create
up to five webhooks per product.
Make sure to provide
a unique name
for each of your webhooks
to ensure you can
easily identify them.
The payload that is sent
to your endpoint is a JSON blob
with information
about your build and product,
such as your App Store Connect
application, your workflow,
your product, your build,
and more.
You need to set up an app
or a service to receive
and handle the payload
that is sent over
via HttpRequest.
Let's take a look
at a sample code
on how to achieve that
using Swift on AWS Lambda.
First, we receive the request.
Then decode its payload
to a JSON object.
Then we check the name
of the workflow
and the build state.
If the workflow
is a release workflow
and the build state
has succeeded,
we'll post a message to Twitter
to let testers
or beta users know
it's available for testing.
Finally, we will return a
200 status code to acknowledge
that the webhook request
has been successfully handled.
If you wish to learn more
about running
Swift serverless functions,
check out this session
in WWDC 2020.
If your endpoint doesn't return
a successful status code,
Xcode Cloud will try to send
the request again.
Xcode Cloud also makes it easy
to inspect the content
of the webhooks
that were delivered
to your endpoint.
You can go to Xcode Cloud
in App Store Connect;
click on your settings
and the webhooks;
select the webhook
you wish to inspect.
Then it shows you
a list of deliveries
at different time stamps,
and select the one
that interests you.
It shows you the request
that was sent to your service
and the response
that was received.
There are so many things you can
do with Xcode Cloud webhooks.
Here are a few
additional examples.
You can automatically create
or resolve issues
from your bug-checking system;
send notifications to a paging
system when a build fails;
initiate downstream builds
as part of a complex
release workflow.
When it comes
to extending your workflow
using the exhaustive content
of the webhook,
the sky is the limit.
Let's recap on what we have
learned in this session.
First, we learned about how to
pass in environment variables
for your build.
Then we demonstrated
how to set up scripts
to customize your build process
and how to work
with additional repositories
in your project.
Finally, we learned
how to set up webhooks
to receive callbacks
from Xcode Cloud
at different stages
of build life cycle.
We hope these features
can enhance your team's
day-to-day workflow.
Thank you for watching.
♪