[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Nat] Hi, my name is Nat.
And I work on Game Technologies at Apple.
Thanks for joining me again this year
to catch up about game input
for iOS, tvOS, and macOS.
Today, I’m going to start with a quick
recap of both the how and the why
for anybody new to game input
on Apple platforms.
Next, I’m going to show you
a new type of virtual game controller,
and we’ll write a little code together.
Finally, I want to talk
about more actual physical controllers
and work through some of our new features.
So let’s start out with our review.
The game controller framework’s goal
is making it easy to add support
for all different kinds
of efficient, low-latency input
across Apple platforms.
By abstracting input hardware
through the common API,
the game controller framework lets you
write your input code once
without having to worry
about how input may have been remapped
or the differences
among specific controllers,
keyboards, or pointing devices.
On iOS, iPadOS, and tvOS,
players can create system-wide
and per-application game controller
input remappings,
which help make your games
more customizable and more accessible.
And on all platforms, you can build
your UI to reflect the symbols
and capabilities of the specific
controllers the player is holding.
So whether your player is
on team circle-square-triangle-cross
or on team A-B-X-Y,
your game UI will look right for them.
The basics of the game controller
framework is reacting to notifications
about different kinds of GCDevice objects
connecting and disconnecting
and either polling active devices
for input state
or setting up value-changed handlers
to be notified about input state changes.
When controllers connect or disconnect
from the system,
GCController objects
are created and removed,
and you are sent
GCControllerDidConnect
and GCControllerDidDisconnect
notifications.
It’s the same pattern
with GCKeyboard objects
when keyboards connect or disconnect,
and with GCMouse objects
when pointing devices connect
or disconnect.
All you need to do is add
an observer to find out when,
for example, a GCController objects
connects or disconnects.
Then it’s up to you whether
to set up those change handlers
to notify you when input state changes,
or to poll the state
of the controller elsewhere.
This is the same pattern you should use
whether it’s a controller, a keyboard,
or a pointing device.
We’ve seen so many great new games
supporting game controllers
and huge customer interest
in games that support controllers well.
That’s why we really want
to help people find games
that support game controllers.
When we know a game
supports game controllers,
we badge it in the App Store
with the Controller Supported badge.
That looks like a little thing, right?
But it’s something players are looking for
if they love using their controllers,
and I know it’s a badge I look for.
And we’re always on the lookout
to curate and promote apps
that work great with game controllers.
There are multiple sections for games
when we discover apps
that make game controllers really shine.
I can’t guarantee that your app
will be chosen for promotion,
but when you do a great job
with controllers,
players will definitely notice.
So here’s all you have to do
to mark your app’s support.
In Xcode, just add
the Game Controllers capability.
This tags your application’s Info.plist
with the game controller capability,
and that’s all you need to do
before submitting it to the App Store.
When your game has this capability,
we also know to include it
in the per-app customization section
of the Game Controller preferences panel.
Players love the ability
to tweak controls to their liking,
and it’s a great way to improve
your game’s accessibility.
You don’t have to do anything
to participate in input remapping,
but when you tag your game,
players can customize it specifically.
Another terrific feature you get for free
when you adopt the game controller
framework is screenshots and video clips.
Players can capture a screenshot
or start and stop video clip recordings
with a quick touch
of the controller’s share button.
Here I am playing Fox2.
[whooshing, exploding]
I can capture a screenshot
by double-tapping on the Share button.
The screenshot lands right
in my Camera Roll,
to my Desktop if I’m on macOS,
or it AirDrops to my phone from AppleTV.
Now here’s what happens if I want
to start and stop a screen recording
using a long press of the Share button.
[chimes]
A little bit later, I’ve got some news
about a new type of game clip recording
we’ve added this year.
My last bit of advice about what gives
a game polished controller support
is the proper use of glyphs in your UI.
Consider this hint to use a button
to display your inventory.
On an MFi or Xbox controller,
we should show the Y button.
On a PlayStation controller,
we instead want to show a triangle.
It may seem like a small thing,
but wow, we really hear feedback
about the wrong button names
showing in your UI.
You might consider
another approach shown here
of optionally representing
positional button locations
if it’s more appropriate for your game.
Some players,
especially new and young players,
may more quickly recognize
the location you’re showing them
and they don’t have to glance down
to try to read the button names.
We made it super easy
to always show the right glyph,
even if the player has remapped a button
in the system remapping UI.
So for example, if we have mapped
the press of the X button to the A action,
as shown here
in the remapping preferences,
and we want to ask the user
to press the A action to continue,
when a developer asks for the glyph
associated with the A action.
To do this, we just query
the sfSymbolsName of the A button,
then use UIImage system image named
to get an image to display.
Now we’ll show the correct glyph
based on the remapping.
So that was my very quick recap.
If you find you need more details,
check out these other talks
about game controllers
from past WWDC conferences.
So over the past few years,
we’ve talked with a lot of developers
bringing games to iOS and iPadOS.
Many are games designed originally
around game controller input,
so they’re expecting two analog sticks,
maybe a d-pad or touchpads,
and digital button input.
What we heard was that some of you
had a hard time building
consistent, great-feeling
and great-looking touch-based input
for these games.
We heard that your touch input
handling code was different
from your keyboard, mouse,
and game controller input code paths.
To address this, I want to tell you
about our new virtual on-screen controller
which is compatible with all your existing
game controller input code.
These new on-screen controls
for iPhone and iPad look amazing,
and they’re carefully tuned
for grip locations across hand sizes
and for a great responsiveness and feel.
They’re easy to add to your application
and act just like a game controller.
Instead of writing
your own on-screen overlay UI
and translating touch inputs
into your game input system,
these on-screen controls appear
to your code
just like game controller framework
GCController objects,
so your input logic can remain
much more consistent.
They’re customizable
with your own symbols,
and they integrate
with your colors and style
while still sharing elements
of the design language
of iOS and iPadOS.
They adjust to a variety of layouts
depending on whether you want
just one button, three buttons,
or a d-pad and multiple buttons.
The core principle
of the on-screen controller
is that the left and the right regions
are independently configured
and that the layout is determined
based on the configuration.
Manual placement of elements
is not supported.
Per side, a configuration can be built
with zero to four buttons
and one of either a thumbstick,
a d-pad, or a touchpad.
There are haptics
on the buttons and the sticks.
And finally, configurations are fixed
at the time of creation.
You can show and hide elements,
but you can’t add or remove them
without creating a new virtual controller.
So let’s take a look at what you do
to choose a layout
and show your on-screen
virtual game controller.
First, you create
a GCControllerConfiguration
identifying all the possible buttons
and joysticks you will want to use.
Then, you create a virtual controller
from that configuration.
Then, you can optionally do
some configuration on the elements,
such as setting custom shapes
or having some elements hidden.
Next, you tell the system
to connect the controller,
and that will trigger the same
GCGameControllerDidConnect
notification that you’re used to handling,
and that gives you a GCController object.
So let’s take a look
at the code we would write
to get a layout like
what I’m showing here:
a thumbstick on the left,
a thumbstick on the right,
and an A and B button on the right.
It’s super easy.
We start by creating a new
GCVirtualControllerConfiguration object.
Then we establish which elements we want.
We want two thumbsticks and two buttons
on the right-hand side,
just like in our previous picture.
Next we’ll create
the GCVirtualController object
using that configuration.
And finally we’ll call connect;
our standard
GCControllerDidConnectNotification
is going to arrive.
So that was easy.
But how do we establish
our own visuals for these buttons,
like what I have in this picture?
This is readily done by adjusting
the GCVirtualController
element configuration.
To create this layout where I’ve changed
the A button to indicate
the spinning attack
and to set the B button
to indicate the jump,
I just adjust the A button’s configuration
to add a BezierPath.
Then I set the B button
to establish its BezierPath.
It’s just as simple to show
and hide different button elements
using the config.hidden property.
So you see, it doesn’t take much
to customize these controls
to just your liking.
Okay, so let’s get back
to the non-virtual world
of physical controllers.
There are so many great controllers
for players to choose from.
There are lots of Made
for iPhone, MFi controllers,
and we see new ones
and improvements all the time.
The standalone SteelSeries Nimbus+,
now with L3/R3 thumbstick triggers
and more system buttons
is really terrific.
I’m also a huge fan of the form-fitting
Razer Kishi and the Backbone One.
These types of form-fitting controllers
are my new favorites
to keep in my backpack.
Of course, besides MFi controllers,
we support the Sony DualShock 4
and Xbox One controllers
on all Apple platforms,
and players love the Xbox Elite V2
and the Xbox Adaptive controller support
we added last year.
We just added support in iOS 14.5
and macOS 11.3 for the latest generation
of console controllers.
The Sony DualSense controller
and the Xbox Series X controllers
are such great-feeling controllers,
and they just work when you’re
using the game controller framework.
The Xbox Series X controller
has a new dedicated Share button,
and the DualSense has cool
adaptive trigger technology.
Let’s take a moment to dig
into the adaptive triggers
and how you can to put them to use.
The DualSense adaptive triggers
really allow you to improve game immersion
through the use of force feedback.
By dynamically applying a varying
resistance to the trigger based
on what the player is doing,
you can emulate the feeling
of pulling a bow string
or a slingshot that’s under tension
and many more sensations.
I hope you get a chance to feel
how great these triggers feel.
The way to support adaptive triggers
in the game controller framework
is really straightforward.
First, you need to verify
that the physical input profile
on the player’s controller is a DualSense.
Next, you simply set
the adaptive trigger effect you’re after
with a method call.
If you want to create
a really dynamic effect,
you can continuously read the state
of the adaptive triggers and the game
and adjust your effect accordingly.
For example, you can apply more resistance
as the trigger is pulled harder
or as the player pulls a rope
into greater tension.
Finally, just like I remind
my kids to turn out the lights
when they leave a room,
you need to make sure you turn off
the adaptive trigger effect
when you’re done.
Let’s jump in to a quick code example
to see how to achieve this in practice.
So let’s say we have a game
where a player can fire a slingshot
to knock out some targets.
The player can start aiming
with the left trigger
and pull back on the slingshot
with the right trigger.
We want to add an adaptive trigger effect
as the player pulls back on the slingshot.
First, we’ll want to make sure that
the player’s controller is a DualSense.
Since our game is a single-player game,
we can just check GCController.current
to get the active controller.
After that, we can grab
the DualSense’s right adaptive trigger.
In this example,
we’ll only want to apply a resistive force
when the player is aiming their slingshot.
We’ll dynamically calculate the strength
of our applied resistance
based on how far
the trigger has been pulled.
If the trigger has not been
pulled all the way back,
we’ll apply a feedback effect
to the adaptive triggers.
The feedback effect provides
a constant resistance to your finger
as you pull the trigger.
Now, otherwise, if the trigger has
been pulled all the way back,
we’ll apply a vibration effect
with a low frequency.
This effect causes the triggers
to vibrate,
emulating the feeling of struggling
to keep that slingshot
pulled back and in tension.
Finally, once the player
fires their slingshot,
we want to turn the adaptive trigger off.
Our final topic of conversation today
is about media capture
through game controller Share buttons.
Last year, we introduced
some media capture gestures
on a controller’s designated Share button.
The Share button is usually mapped
to the upper left-most system button
on a controller,
but some controllers
like the Xbox Series X
have a button labeled Share elsewhere.
As I showed you earlier,
the system gestures for media capture
are a double press to capture
a screenshot to your Camera Roll,
and a long press to start
and stop a ReplayKit recording.
This year, we’re adding
a super cool new type of media capture,
15-second highlights.
So now instead of having to remember
to start and stop your recording,
players can just turn on
automatic background buffering,
which will let them save
the last 15 seconds of gameplay
any time they long press.
ReplayKit clips are an awesome way
to let gamers capture a great boss battle,
an amazing combo move,
or an epic fail.
To choose between our automatic form
of starting and stopping
a longer recording or starting
the background recording
which you can then save
15-second highlights from,
just toggle the global
or per-application setting
in the Game Controller preferences panel.
If you want to trigger your own highlights
for important points in your game,
there’s an API for that.
That will trigger
those 15-second snapshots as well.
Whew.
Okay.
So that wraps up
our game input news for this year.
Before you go, please remember to tag
your app with game controller support
to get per-app customization
and so the App Store
can categorize your app properly.
We really look forward to seeing
how you make use of game controller,
keyboard, and mouse input in your games.
If you’re ready to watch
more presentations
about features for game developers
and for gamers,
check out
“Discover rolling clips with ReplayKit”
and “What’s new in Game Center” as well.
Thanks so much for watching.
We hope to see you in person again soon.
For now, we’re looking forward
to meeting you online
and helping answer your questions.
[upbeat music]