[music]
[Timm] Hi, I'm Timm Hannon,
an engineering manager
in Core OS here at Apple.
In this session, my colleague
Melissa Nierle and I
will cover
User Enrollments for MDM.
User Enrollment
is designed for BYOD,
or Bring Your Own Device
deployments
where the user,
not the organization,
owns the device.
Because the user
owns the device,
User Enrollment
has a limited set
of payloads and restrictions
that can be applied
to the device
by the Mobile Device Management
solution.
And it's available on iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS.
Security and privacy
are at the heart
of everything we do
here at Apple.
User Enrollment is a great
device management option
that incorporates both.
Its design allows the user
to be comfortable
that their privacy and
personal data are protected,
while the organization can be
confident their data is secure.
There are three core components
that form the basis
of User Enrollment.
The first is a Managed Apple ID.
Managed Apple IDs provide access
to Apple Services
such as iCloud.
They are owned and managed
by an organization
and are available through
Apple Business Manager
and Apple School Manager.
They support federation
with Azure Active Directory
so that users can authenticate
with their organization's
existing credentials.
The second is Data Separation.
During enrollment,
a separate APFS volume
with different
cryptographic keys is created.
Data from managed apps
and managed accounts
is kept securely on this volume
away from personal content.
When the device unenrolls
from management,
the volume and the cryptographic
keys are erased.
And finally,
the Management Capabilities
are limited to those
that are appropriate
for controlling
the organization's content
on the device.
The user owns
and has been using the device,
so it's critical
to protect their privacy.
With User Enrollments,
the user maintains control
of their personal data
on the device.
The device is not considered
supervised with User Enrollment.
The management functionality
available to the MDM server
allows it full control
of the managed content
but is limited
from accessing and restricting
personal data and settings.
Access to personal accounts,
apps,
and unique device identifiers
is unavailable
to the MDM server,
as are system-wide operations
like remotely wiping the device.
We've been hard at work
this year
on updates to User Enrollment,
and I'm excited
to discuss them now.
I'll cover Managed Apple IDs
and managed apps.
Then my colleague Melissa
will cover changes
to the onboarding flows
for users,
how to enable
ongoing User Authentication,
and getting started.
Let's start with
Managed Apple IDs.
In iOS 15,
we've improved the experience
of accessing
the Managed Account in Settings.
When a device is user enrolled,
it will now show the account
at the top level of settings.
From there, you can view
details and settings for iCloud.
It is now easier than ever
to manage
the additional account.
With this re-designed
experience,
Settings reflects
the clear separation
of organizational content.
Users are able to see
which parts of the system
are managed by the organization
and which are not.
New in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
Managed Apple IDs
support iCloud Drive.
iCloud Drive is an important
feature of iCloud accounts
and now it will be available
to user-enrolled devices.
On iOS and iPadOS,
it shows up as a new location
in the Files app.
And on macOS, it appears
as an additional location
in Finder.
With iCloud Drive
for Managed Apple IDs,
organizations are now able
to easily provide their users
a built-in
cloud storage solution.
Document browser-based apps
will also have access
to the additional iCloud Drive.
And of course,
iCloud Drive will respect
Managed Open-in restrictions
for managed apps
and data access.
Now let's turn to managed apps.
In macOS Big Sur, we enabled
managed apps on macOS
for the first time.
This allows organizations
to install apps
on a managed device
similar to how they can for iOS,
including with a custom
configuration payload.
It also provides the ability
to remove the app
with an MDM command
or when the device unenrolls.
In macOS Monterey,
we are expanding
the functionality
to user enrollments.
Like on iOS,
the app data is separated
on a different volume.
The app is removed
during unenrollment
or with an MDM command.
When that happens,
the data container
is also erased.
Managed apps that use CloudKit
will now use
the Managed Apple ID
associated with the MDM profile.
You'll need to add
the InstallAsManaged key
to the InstallApplication
command.
And just a quick reminder
that managed apps
need be installed
to the Applications folder
and should only contain
a single app bundle.
We recommend
that you adopt the use
of the Data Protection Keychain
and app sandboxing
to ensure that data
is correctly separated.
We've also added
some enhancements
to managed apps
for all types of enrollment
that are relevant
to user enrollments.
First,
the restriction functionality
for Managed Open-In
has been expanded
to include Copy & Paste.
This will allow organizations
to control data
from being pasted
across the managed boundary
in both directions.
There is also now the ability
to specify
that a required app is installed
when a device
enrolls in management.
The app is approved
for installation
when the device is enrolled,
so it doesn't require
additional user confirmation.
For more information
on managed pasteboard
and the required app
installation,
see "What's new in managing
Apple devices."
Now over to Melissa
to cover enrollment
and ongoing user authentication.
[Melissa] Thanks, Timm.
With all of these enhancements
to User Enrollment,
we updated the onboarding flow
to be a more personalized
and user-driven experience.
The onboarding experience
for User Enrollment
introduced in iOS 13
is initiated and driven
by an MDM Enrollment profile.
This profile has to be
created for each user
and distributed by their admin.
In iOS 15, for a more
streamlined experience
for both users
and administrators,
we've created a new
User Enrollment onboarding flow
that establishes
the user's organization identity
as the entry point.
Users are already familiar with
signing into their
organization identity
to set up services
like Mail and Calendar,
so they'll be familiar
with setting up MDM
on iPhone using their
organization identity.
This onboarding flow
enables new security features
for User Enrollment.
Now there's a layer of security
during the enrollment flow
where your MDM server
can verify the user
before the MDM profile
is even downloaded to the device
and before any organization data
is sent to it.
Let's take a look at how this
new account-based flow works.
There are four components
to the new User Enrollment
onboarding flow.
Service discovery,
where the device identifies
the organization's MDM server.
User authentication,
which is how the MDM server
validates the user.
Issuing the session token,
which is how ongoing
authentication is performed.
And enrollment,
which is the installation
of the MDM payload
to the device.
Let's take a closer look
at each of these.
When the user starts
the onboarding flow,
they are prompted to enter
their organization identifier.
This identifier
has two main pieces,
delineated by the @ sign.
The first piece
will be the User ID,
and the second piece will be
the organization's domain
or a sub-domain.
After the user has entered
their organization ID,
the device takes the domain
portion of the identifier
and turns that into an HTTPS URL
pointing to a well-known
HTTP resource at that domain.
This discovery URL
is where you host
your MDM server document
that tells the device where
the enrollment endpoint is.
The device then performs
a GET request to that URL,
expecting to get back
a JSON document.
The received JSON object
includes a version key to let
the device know
what type of enrollment
the server supports
and a BaseURL key
that specifies the URL
of the MDM server's
enrollment endpoint.
With this information,
the device is now ready
to request the enrollment
profile from the server.
The device POSTs a property list
to the server's
enrollment endpoint
with various device attributes.
If you are familiar with
the over-the-air
profile delivery process,
you will recognize this
as the same request
a device makes
to the profile service endpoint.
But the key difference here
is that the server asks the user
to authenticate themselves
before it hands over
the enrollment profile.
It does this by issuing an HTTP
401 Unauthorized response
to challenge the user
for credentials.
The server must issue
this auth challenge
in order
for enrollment to succeed.
Importantly, this 401 response
includes
a WWW-Authenticate header
with information that the device
uses to authenticate.
This WWW-Authenticate header
uses the Bearer
authentication scheme
and two additional parameters.
The method parameter
tells the device
what type of authentication
is being used.
The value indicates
that the device will use
the AuthenticationServices
web sign-in flow
to authenticate the user.
For now, that value is fixed.
For this method parameter,
a URL is also included.
The value of this key
is an HTTPS URL
that specifies the endpoint
where the authentication
happens.
This URL should be an endpoint
on the MDM server itself.
Receipt of this
authenticate header kicks off
the AuthenticationServices
web sign-in flow.
Let's take a look
at how that works.
The initial content
of the web view displayed by
AuthenticationServices
web sign-in flow
is the result
of a HTTP GET request
to the authentication endpoint
specified by the URL parameter
from the 401 response.
In a simple case,
this web sign-in flow
could display a web form
where the user would enter
their username and password.
In more complex cases,
it could make use
of enterprise single sign-on
or even redirect to
a third-party identity provider
or perform
multi-factor authentication.
Multiple round trips
between the device
and authentication service
can occur.
The AuthenticationServices
web flow completes
when the server returns
an HTTP redirect response
to the device,
like the one seen here.
The response includes
a Location header
with a URL
using a custom fixed scheme.
The URL also includes
an access-token parameter
whose value is an opaque token
that the device will use as a
session token
when making requests
to the MDM server.
With the session token in-hand,
the device re-issues
the original HTTP POST request
to fetch the enrollment profile.
This time, that request includes
an Authorization header
which contains
the session token as the value.
The server validates this token,
and upon success,
returns the enrollment profile
to the device.
The user enrollment profile
contains two new keys
in the MDM payload.
First,
the AssignedManagedAppleID key
is the Managed Apple ID
associated
with the enterprise user.
The user will be required
to authenticate
this Managed Apple ID
to sign into
the iCloud and iTunes accounts
as part of the enrollment flow.
A successful MDM enrollment
guarantees
that the Managed Apple ID
is active on the device.
The device will fail to enroll
if the AssignedManagedAppleID
key is missing
or if the user does not
successfully authenticate it.
And the second new key
is the EnrollmentMode key,
indicating the enrollment
is a BYOD type.
The device verifies
that this value
matches the mode it is in
and will fail the enrollment
if there is a mismatch
or if the key is not present.
Be sure to update
your MDM payloads
with both of these new keys.
With receipt
of the enrollment profile,
the device now sets up
the required
Managed Apple ID account
and enrolls with the MDM server.
All requests to the server
now include the session token
in the Authorization header
for the server to validate.
Let's take a look
at all of the pieces together.
First, the user navigates
to the redesigned VPN
and Device Management
section in Settings
and taps the new Sign In
to Work or School button.
Then they enter
their organization ID,
triggering
the service discovery step.
After discovering
the enrollment endpoint
from the domain,
the Authentication Services
Web UI flow begins.
This is an example
of a simple web form
used for auth.
The user enters
their organization password.
Once the organization's
authentication succeeds,
we are handed the MDM profile.
We take the value of
the AssignedManagedAppleID key
from the profile
and pre-populate it
into the next sign-in screen,
where the user
enters their password.
After this authentication
succeeds,
the user then allows
management of their device.
They enter their device passcode
to create an encrypted
enterprise data partition
and to authorize
the MDM enrollment.
The enrollment
of the user is successful.
And that's the new
account-driven onboarding flow
for User Enrollment.
In the onboarding flow,
we looked at how a server
authenticates a user
before sending enrollment data.
With new
User Enrollments in iOS 15,
we are introducing the ability
for organizations
to reauthenticate the user
at any point in time.
This makes it possible
for your server
and client connection
to be more secure than ever.
MDM servers
can now validate authorization
on every request from the client
and ask the user
to re-authenticate
their identity credentials
at any time.
This functionality is performed
through the use
of the session token.
Here's an example
of an MDM client
checking in with the server
to fetch the next MDM command.
The Authorization header
contains the session token.
This is the staple
for the two elements
of ongoing authentication.
The first element is
persistent authorization,
where the session token is sent
in every client request
to the server.
The second element
is refreshing the session token.
This enables
the organization administrator
to request user
re-authentication at any time.
By implementing your own
server side validation logic
of this session token,
you can add your organization's
security rules
right into your
management solution.
For example,
you can periodically verify
a user's credentials
to ensure sensitive payloads
are only sent to devices
in possession of trusted users.
Let's take a look
at how that works.
When the session token
is invalidated,
re-authentication is triggered.
The next time the device
makes an MDM HTTP request,
the now invalid session token
included in the HTTP PUT
will trigger a 401 response
from the server.
The response
that the server sends
includes the same
WWW-Authenticate header
that we saw earlier in the
initial authentication exchange
during the onboarding flow.
Of course,
because the MDM process
runs in the background
on devices,
this reauthentication request is
surfaced to the user
via NotificationCenter.
By tapping on the notification,
the user continues
the re-authentication flow
in Settings.
The client will start
another AuthenticationServices
Web sign-in flow like the one
during the onboarding process.
The user will need
to authenticate as part of
the AuthenticationServices
web sign-in flow
with either a simple mechanism
or a more complex one
decided by the server's
integration
with their identity provider.
When that authentication
services web flow completes,
the server again sends
a redirect response
with the custom Location header,
containing a new session token.
A successful re-authentication
results in the device
immediately repeating
the MDM request that initially
received the 401 response,
continuing right
from where it left off
without action from the server.
Just like before,
this new session token
is included in all
subsequent MDM HTTP requests.
If, for any reason,
a user's authentication attempt
fails,
the server may no longer
trust the device.
In this case,
the server can remove
any sensitive MDM payloads
or it can completely unenroll
the device.
And when it comes
to unenrolling from MDM,
because ongoing authentication
leverages the HTTP 401 response,
it's important to note
a key difference here
between
profile-based enrollments
and this new User Enrollment.
Before iOS 15,
all MDM-enrolled devices
treated a 401 response
from the server
as an unenroll command.
When this new User Enrollment
style is in effect,
the 401 response triggers
reauthentication instead.
To trigger an unenroll,
you can still use
the existing mechanism
of sending
the RemoveProfile command
for the MDM enrollment profile.
This will result
in a full MDM unenroll
as well as a complete
managed account,
managed data,
and data separated volume
removal from the device.
All unenroll behavior
of profile-based enrollments,
including
the user enrollment flow
from iOS13,
remain unchanged.
So that's a quick look
into Ongoing Authentication.
Now let's help you get started
and wrap up.
You can get started with the new
User Enrollment onboarding
and ongoing authentication
today with iOS 15.
You'll need be sure
to do these five things.
First, set up and publish
an HTTP well-known resource file
for your enterprise domain.
Second, integrate
your MDM server
with your Identity Provider
to perform user authentication
during enrollment
and take advantage
of the ongoing authentication
for added Security benefit.
Third, create Managed Apple IDs
or use already created Managed
Apple IDs
from Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager
to populate
the AssignedManagedAppleID key
in your server's MDM payloads.
Update your MDM payload
to also include
the new EnrollmentMode key.
And lastly, find our new iOS 15
Apple Device Management
documentation
to review our specific updates
along with all the details
that we've gone over today.
And that's all you need to get
started
with Account-Based
User Enrollments.
We covered a lot today,
so let's review.
The new iCloud Drive support
for Managed Apple IDs
brings a built-in
cloud storage option
to your organization.
You can now manage apps
on macOS in User Enrollment.
Build support
for the new onboarding flow
in your MDM solution
or encourage your MDM provider
to support the new
account-driven onboarding
to make user enrollment
easier than ever before.
Incorporate
ongoing authentication
with your accounts throughout
your management workflows.
Take advantage
of these new features
starting in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey
to significantly improve
the Bring Your Own Device
workflow
for both you and your users.
Thanks for joining us today,
and have a great WWDC.
[music]