[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Naiwei Zheng: Hello.
Welcome to WWDC.
My name is Zheng Naiwei.
I'm from Apple's
HLS Streaming Team.
Today I'm going to talk about
a new feature in HLS
called Content Steering,
and how it can improve
global streaming availability.
Today's network connectivity
is at global scale.
Streaming media providers
deliver their contents
all around the world.
However, delivering contents
at the global scale comes with
enormous amount of challenges
the industry has to solve.
We, HLS Streaming Team at Apple,
also recognize
these challenging problems
and are constantly working
to provide solutions.
Today, we will be focusing on
the problem of availability.
Specifically,
network congestion mitigation
and error recovery.
To help us understand
these problems,
let's take a look at an example.
Let's assume a popular
streaming provider in Asia
deploys its CDN infrastructures
in the following
three countries:
China, Japan, and Singapore.
In this graph, we are showing
a state where everything
is working in perfect condition.
We have users in China
streaming from Chinese CDN
and users from Japan
streaming from Japanese CDN,
and both CDN networks
are performing at capable level.
Now, let's introduce
some change.
Let's say a while later,
users in China
streaming from the Chinese CDN
has greatly increased,
to a degree that CDN network
is becoming overloading.
With the HLS technologies
we had,
it's difficult to fully address
this issue
of network congestion.
Even though we could assign
new users to different CDN,
it's, however, difficult
to instruct existing clients
to use a different CDN,
and existing traffic
will continuously overload
the current CDN.
With our new HLS
Content Steering feature,
content providers
can solve this problem
by hosting their own
steering server.
It establishes a side channel
with all latest HLS clients
to update them
with the latest CDN policy.
For example, it can send
a policy update to 30 percent
of the existing clients in China
to switch to Japanese CDN.
And the clients receiving
the policy update
will honor the change and
redirect their network traffics
to the Japanese CDN.
Now the network congestion
in the Chinese CDN is mitigated.
But network congestion
is only one
of the many
availability problems.
What happens when
there's a network outage?
Let's take another example.
Say the network path from users
in Japan to the Japanese CDN
has experienced
a regional outage.
With HLS technologies we had,
content providers can list
our fallback variant streams
in master playlist,
so clients can try
to walk through the list
until it reaches a working CDN.
But this approach
is preliminary in the sense
that content provider
is unable to change
the ordering or priorities
of the CDNs listed
in the master playlist
in real time.
However, with the help
of the steering server,
clients will be updated
with the latest CDN priorities
at near real time.
Let's rewind a bit to see
how it can facilitate the client
with more efficient
error recovery.
Before the network outage,
clients in Japan
periodically pull
for CDN priority list updates
from the steering server.
Let's say in the latest update,
clients in Japan received
the following CDN priority list
where the Japanese CDN
being most preferred,
following Singapore
and then China.
Currently, users in Japan are
streaming from the Japanese CDN.
Now when the network
outage happens,
the Japanese CDN
will be marked as penalized
from the priority list.
The client will move on to the
next CDN in the priority list,
which in this case,
the CDN in Singapore,
and redirect
their network traffics.
Now the users in Japan
will be able to continue
watching their shows
without interrupt.
What our example showed you
is just a high-level overview
of our new HLS feature,
Content Steering.
Now let's dive deeper
to show you how to integrate
this amazing feature
into your streams.
It's just a simple listing
of different CDN URLs
duplicating all
available variants.
As explained before,
a playlist like this
has a constant and final
ordering of CDN priorities.
Content providers
cannot change it later
during the playback.
Now let's see how to add
Content Steering support
to this playlist.
You may be surprised how little
the change introduced.
In fact, the changes
are backward-compatible
with current HLS clients.
Let's walk through
the additions.
Most notably,
we now group variant streams
into different pathways
by the PATHWAY-ID attributes
on each variant stream,
where each pathway typically
corresponds to one CDN.
In this example, we group the
variant streams into pathway CN,
JP, and SG, representing
CDNs in China, Japan,
and Singapore, respectively.
However, a pathway
may contain variant streams
from different CDNs to enable
more advanced use case.
When the client selects
a pathway,
only the variant streams
from that pathway
is eligible
for variant selection.
The PATHWAY-ID attribute on
the new CONTENT-STEERING tag
specifies the initial pathway
to use at playback startup.
So, in this case,
the client will only choose
from variant streams
belonging to the CN pathway
at the initial playback.
The SERVER-URI attribute
specifies where is
the Content Steering server.
Clients will pull for
Content Steering updates
from this URI.
But what if your playlist
contains media groups?
No problem.
It's still very simple
to enable Content Steering.
All you have to do is to
duplicate the media groups
for each pathway and assign them
with unique GROUP-IDs.
For example,
the audio group in this playlist
is being duplicated
for each pathway,
with the GROUP-ID set to
CN-audio for the CN pathway
and et cetera.
When an HLS client
loaded a master playlist
with Content Steering tag,
it triggers a slightly different
startup routine.
First, when it performs initial
variant stream selection,
it will only use variant streams
from the initial pathway.
Then it will load
and start playing
the selected variant stream
and its media segments as usual.
But in parallel to the normal
playback routine,
the client will start making
periodic Steering Manifest
requests in background.
Let's take a look of what
a Steering Manifest request
looks like.
It's just a simple
HTTP GET request
sent to this resolved URI
from the SERVER-URI attribute
based on
the master playlist URL.
The steering server will respond
with a Steering Manifest.
Let's dissect its format
with an example.
The Steering Manifest
is a JSON document.
The steering server can craft
customized Steering Manifests
for each client.
This gives steering server
great potential
in shaping its managed
network traffic.
The most important property
in this Steering Manifest
is the PATHWAY-PRIORITY field.
It's a list of pathway IDs
ordered by their priorities,
with the first being
the most preferred.
Here in this example,
we have a priority of CN pathway
being most preferred,
followed by JP and then SG.
Upon receiving
the Steering Manifest
from the steering server,
the client will perform
Content Steering evaluation
to determine whether
to switch to
a different pathway.
First, the client will exclude
variant streams
ineligible for selection.
This includes
penalized variant streams
due to network errors.
And also, variant streams
with unsupported codecs,
just like usual
variant selection would do.
It will select a pathway
that has at least one
eligible variant streams
and has highest pathway priority
among all eligible pathways.
If the chosen pathway
is different
from the currently
using pathway,
the client will immediately
switch to the new pathway.
If no suitable pathway
is chosen
or is already using
the chosen pathway,
client will do nothing
and keep playing using
the current pathway.
Finally, the client
will schedule
for the next
Steering Manifest request
to pull for latest updates
from the steering server.
So how does
this scheduling work?
Let's review
the Steering Manifest.
Notice that there's a TTL field
which specify
the number of seconds
the client should wait
until sending the next
Steering Manifest request.
In this example,
after the client performed
the Content Steering evaluation
using this Steering Manifest's
pathway priority list,
it will schedule the next
Steering Manifest request
in 300 seconds,
which is five minutes.
It's also worth noting that
steering server is able
to change this TTL value in each
Steering Manifest response,
affecting how long the client
should schedule
the next request.
It's also useful
for steering server
to inject some randomness
to each client's TTL value
to distribute server load.
In addition,
the optional RELOAD-URI field
tells the clients
where to request
the next Steering Manifest.
Steering server can leverage
this field to inject
client-specific state
or session data in the URL
to be echoed back
in the next request.
Now you have seen
the major technical details
of Content Steering.
Let's go back
to one of our early examples
to see how it works
under the hood.
Let's say in this case,
all users in China
have received
a Steering Manifest
with the CN pathway
being most preferred,
and the corresponding Chinese
CDN is being overloaded
because of the increasing
number of users.
So the steering server
came into action,
and sending out a different
Steering Manifest
to 30 percent
of the users in China,
with the most preferred
pathway changed to JP.
After performing
a Content Steering evaluation,
those 30 percent
clients in China
will switch to the JP pathway,
redirecting their network
traffics to the CDN in Japan,
resolving the network congestion
situation in Chinese CDN.
To wrap up, we introduced
the new HLS feature
of Content Steering,
explained how it works,
and how to integrate it
in your streams.
With this amazing feature,
you will be able
to fine-tune your global
streaming availability.
For more technical details,
follow the link below this video
for "HLS Content Steering
Specification".
I'd also like to tell you
that playlists
and Steering Manifest
validation is also supported
in our latest HTTP Live
Streaming Tools.
I'd also like to acknowledge
feedbacks
and helps we received
from industry members
in the HLS Interest IETF forum.
Future feedbacks and suggestions
are also welcomed.
And with all these in place,
the HLS Content Steering
will be available to developers
and users in this year's
WWDC Seed builds.
So, if you want a better
global streaming delivery
with more availability,
act now to integrate
HLS Content Steering
in your streams
and bring your customers
a better streaming experience.
Thank you very much.
♪