[upbeat music]
[Kacper] Welcome!
My name is Kacper.
I'm a Performance Tools Engineer
at Apple, and today,
together with Sergio,
we'll be talking about the new
HTTP Traffic Instrument
available in Instruments 13.
This Instrument, contained
in the Network template,
allows you to inspect
HTTP traffic
coming from your application
through the Apple Networking
stack.
This approach comes
with multiple benefits.
It just works
on all Apple devices.
The entire traffic going through
the URL loading system
is exposed, even the ones sent
with the new HTTP/3 protocol
or over VPN.
Because
of the system integration,
it attributes traffic
to processes running on it,
and since it's instrumenting
Apple Networking frameworks,
it even reveals requests
hitting the on-disk cache
or networking errors.
All of this exposed
in the context
of higher-level API concepts
that you are familiar with,
such as URLSessions
and URLSessionTasks.
This tool
will help you understand
how your usage of the API
translates to the lifetime
of network requests.
In this hands-on session,
we will first get you familiar
with how
the Instruments UI reflects
the API concepts you are using.
After this quick introduction,
we will transition to four demos
that will illustrate
how you can use the tool
to detect both performance
and correctness problems.
And even if your app
seems to work flawlessly,
you will learn how
to verify that it does
what you think by auditing
the traffic coming from it.
Let's get started with how
the Networking API maps
to the Instruments
visualization.
This is how
the HTTP Traffic trace
is displayed in Instruments
when I recorded
my system traffic using
the Network template.
Navigation is structured
around the track hierarchy,
and that's what we will cover
in detail first.
The HTTP Traffic Instrument
located at the top level
shows you an overview
of how many
URLSession tasks were running
in your trace
at any given time,
ideal for detecting spots
with increased HTTP Traffic
activity in your app's lifetime.
The next hierarchy level
shows a breakdown
of activity by process.
In addition to traffic from
all of the debuggable processes,
it allows you to inspect
background traffic
initiated by them.
Contained below each process
are all URLSessions used by it.
And these correspond
to the URLSession objects
you create in code.
The graph at this level
allows you to inspect
all individual task intervals.
To get a better mapping
between your session objects
and the visualization, you can
name them in code by setting
the sessionDescription property
on a session instance.
On the last level,
the traffic is broken down
by requested domains.
Graphs on this level show
more details about tasks,
including individual
transactions that make up
the tasks and their states.
To get a better understanding
of what tasks
and transactions are,
let's analyze an example.
Here are a few tasks
that are loading data
from the selected domain.
Let's focus on one of them
to analyze the structure
of a task.
This single task interval
has a lot of information.
We can represent this in a more
abstract manner to understand
how Instruments visualization
maps to the API being used.
At the top level,
we have a task object.
A task is made up of one
or more transactions.
A transaction is a pair
of an HTTP request
and the corresponding response.
The task level is
the representation of how
your code interacts with the API
of the URL Loading System.
When you create a task
and call resume on it,
the task interval starts.
And it ends
right before
your completion block is called.
Each task can be given
a semantic name using
the taskDescription property,
which will be used
to label
the interval in Instruments.
We also show the task identifier
as part of the task label.
You can use it
to cross-reference
the task with other data.
If your task
finishes with an error,
its description will be
presented
on the interval label
for easier debugging.
As we mentioned before,
a task can be made up
of multiple transactions.
Let's talk about these now.
Here we have a task to load
the start page of apple.com.
However, this URL is
not the canonical URL.
The task requests apple.com,
but the preferred domain
is www.apple.com.
When we create this task,
the URL loading system
initially creates a request
to apple.com.
Shortly after, it receives
a redirect response
from the server,
stating that the preferred URL
is actually www.apple.com.
By default, we follow redirects,
so instead of returning
the 301 response,
the URL loading system
will create a new transaction
to now load the preferred URL.
The response from this second,
successful transaction
is what is returned
back to the task.
As mentioned before,
a transaction represents
the combination of the HTTP
request and response.
It aligns with what URLSession
does under the hood
to handle your task
and contains all of the
information of the HTTP layer,
like the requested URL,
information about
the transferred data,
and much more.
Just like for the task,
the transaction label
gives you an overview
of the transaction.
Mainly,
you get information about
the request and the response.
The track hierarchy
tells you the domain
that is requested,
while you can find
the path and query
on the label itself.
In addition to that,
the interval label
displays the HTTP version,
the HTTP Method,
and whether the request
sent an Authorization
or a Cookie header.
These are often useful
to understand
authentication flows
at a glance.
For the response,
you get the status code,
whether the response
contained a cookie,
and the content type
of the response.
How long the request
and the response took,
as well as more detailed
timing information
about other work that is part
of the transaction
is captured
by the transaction states.
Let's analyze them
in the context
of a containing task.
The start of the transaction
is the point in time
when the URL Loading System
creates the transaction
for making this request.
It first checks whether we have
a valid cached response already.
And if that's not the case,
it will try to schedule
the request on a connection.
Next, the transaction
may have to wait a bit
in the Blocked state, waiting
for an available connection.
The Sending Request state starts
when the transaction
is finally handled
by a connection.
It ends
once we send the last byte
of the request onto the network.
Next, the transaction
goes into an idle
Waiting for Response state,
followed by Receiving Response,
which will track the span
from the first to the last byte
received from the server.
The whole transaction
will complete shortly
after the last byte is received,
once the URL Loading system
has determined whether this was
a successful response.
In practice, the cache lookup
and sending state
for a GET request
are usually much shorter,
so it's more likely
to appear like this.
To show you
some practical examples,
I would like to hand over
to my colleague, Sergio.
He will walk you through an app
he recently started developing
to illustrate how the HTTP
Instrument can help you
with fixing performance
and correctness issues.
[Sergio] Thanks, Kacper.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Sergio Lopez,
and I've been working
on this app for dog lovers.
Think of it like a social media
platform but for dog pictures...
only!
People can post images
of dogs and you get
a stream
of the most recent uploads!
So when I open the app, it loads
several new dog images,
but I noticed that it takes
quite some time for them
to finish loading.
Let's profile the app
with the new HTTP Traffic
instrument to help us
improve this situation.
In the "Product" menu,
I'll choose
the "Profile" option to profile
my app in Instruments.
This will build my app
in the release configuration,
to ensure I'm profiling my app
as it would run for my users,
with all optimizations
turned on.
Once the build is finished,
Instruments will
launch automatically.
Upon starting,
the standard template chooser
of Instruments is displayed.
In our case,
I wanna choose the Network
template on the bottom left,
which gives us more information
about general network
connections my app makes,
but also contains the new
HTTP Tracing functionality.
The track area now contains two
tracks, one for each instrument.
The bottom track is the existing
Network Connections instrument,
and the top track is
the new HTTP Traffic instrument.
We'll focus on this
new instrument today.
All I need to do now
is hit "record."
Instruments will then start
my app and start recording.
Before you can use this tool,
you need to confirm
that you understand
the implications of capturing
the networking traffic.
It's very powerful, especially
if you record all processes.
The data captured includes
everything that is sent,
which may be personal
and sensitive information,
even up to user credentials.
So, you should be very careful
with the resulting trace files,
and we want you to be aware.
So let me confirm this.
The app was launched
and the images were slow
to load.
I will now stop the recording.
Let's zoom in to the data
we recorded
by using Option-click
and dragging
over the area covering
our HTTP traffic.
Clicking on
the disclosure indicator
in the "HTTP Traffic" track
on the top left
will reveal
the full track hierarchy
that Kacper described earlier.
I'll also increase the track
height to show all intervals.
At the top,
there's the first task
that queries the server
for the list of images,
which appear on the "Latest"
section of the app.
When this task completes,
we create a new task to load
a thumbnail for every image
on the list that we received.
I will now click-drag over
the area covering the time frame
it took to fetch
the list of images,
followed by the many requests
to retrieve
each individual image.
By click-dragging
over this area,
a tool tip will be displayed,
showing the duration
of the selected time range.
Overall,
it took more than 7 seconds
to finish
loading the initial screen.
The first few images
load fairly quick.
But as I scroll down,
tasks that were started later
took longer to complete,
as noted by the increasing
blocked states in purple.
Seems like a congestion issue,
where we have too many
requests in parallel.
Let's investigate
one of the later tasks.
By hovering over the task,
the tool tip shows us
the duration of the task
and any of the child intervals
we are hovering over.
This task was blocked
for the majority of the time.
To understand
why it was blocked,
let's switch the track display
to the "HTTP Transactions
by Connection" view.
In the track sidebar
on the left,
under the domain name,
there's a downwards arrow
we can click
to switch the track display.
Currently, we are
drawing "Tasks."
Let's switch to displaying "HTTP
Transactions by Connection."
This view will only
display the transactions,
and instead of grouping
them by task, we can now
find out which connection
they got scheduled on.
The transactions are grouped
by the connection they used.
Overall,
there were six connections
available to handle
these transactions.
Let's analyze the transactions
issued on Connection 1
and investigate
some of the thumbnail loading
transactions further.
From the top down,
it's noticeable
that each transaction is
taking longer to complete.
The purple blocked state
for each
successive transaction
is increasing.
In fact, there's a pretty clear
staircase pattern here.
Each transaction is blocked,
until the previous transaction
on the same connection
has finished.
Only then
can it send its request.
This pattern repeats
for each subsequent transaction.
This is called
"Head of Line Blocking"
and is one of the problems
of using HTTP/1.
The frustrating part
is that these transactions
aren't doing anything
for the majority of the time.
Instead, they spend most
of their time blocked or waiting
for the response
from the server.
We could be sending
another request
for the next transaction in line
while waiting for the response
of a previous transaction
on the same connection,
but that's not supported
by HTTP/1.
Head-of-line blocking
is one of the main limitations
of HTTP/1,
and one of the main improvements
of HTTP/2 is to avoid
that effect by multiplexing
several requests to the same
server onto a single connection.
In HTTP/2,
we can actually start sending
a second request while the first
one is waiting for its response.
Your app does not need to do
anything to support it.
All Apple platforms
support HTTP/2,
and starting in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
HTTP/3 is supported as well.
The client will pick
the most modern HTTP version
the server supports.
If you wanna learn more about
the differences between HTTP/1
and HTTP/2,
and the additional benefits
HTTP/3 provides,
please watch
the "Accelerate networking
with HTTP/3 and QUIC" session.
I've taken this trace,
showed it to our server folks,
and managed to convince them
that we should
really support HTTP/2.
Now, let's run
my app with the new
server enhancements.
Wow, this already feels faster!
Let's confirm this
with Instruments.
So here's a trace I recorded
after we turned on
server support for HTTP/2.
In the domain-specific track,
none of our thumbnail-loading
tasks seem to be blocked anymore
for an extended amount of time.
That's good!
Let's switch
to the "HTTP Transactions
by Connection" view again.
The first thing
we notice is that there is
only one connection.
This is because we no longer
need multiple connections
to send concurrent requests,
which also means we only need
to pay the connection setup
cost once.
Focusing on the individual
thumbnail-loading transactions,
we notice
that they basically spend
no time in the "blocked" state.
In fact,
the amount of time is so small
that it's not visible
at this zoom level.
Eventually
all transactions finish sending
their requests and are left
waiting for a response.
As I scroll down,
we can notice that responses
are making progress
at the same time.
All in all,
we are done with all requests
in under 3 seconds.
This is twice as fast as before.
Now that I've talked
to the server folks
and switched from HTTP/1.1
to HTTP/2,
our images
are loading much faster.
Let me relaunch the app and show
you what else we can do.
When I tap on an image, the app
loads the full-resolution
picture and shows how far away
this photo was taken from me.
There's also a heart icon
at the top right
that allows you to favorite
that specific picture.
To do so, I need an account.
I allow people to use the app
and browse the pictures
without an account,
but to save favorited images,
sync them between devices,
and to upload new pictures,
you need an account.
So let me log in here.
Great.
Let me favorite another picture.
Oh, this dog looks cute!
Let me add it to my favorites.
Wait, why do I have
to log in again if I just did?
This isn't right.
My app should remember
my log-in.
This worked before.
I'm gonna dismiss
the log-in screen,
as I don't want to log in again.
I previously recorded
a trace file
after reproducing the issue.
Let me open it with instruments
to analyze the recording.
On the left, there's the task
that corresponds
to when I pressed the favorite
button for the first time.
To the right of it,
there's the task that was
issued after I returned
to the latest tab,
and the stream of images
were refreshed.
Then, there's the task to load
the full-resolution image
after I tapped
on another dog picture.
And to the far right,
there's the task corresponding
to the second time I tapped
the favorite button.
The first task interval actually
contains two transactions.
The first transaction
received a 401-status code.
This was expected
since we were not logged in.
The transaction is drawn
in orange to indicate
that this is not a success
on the HTTP level.
Then, there's a large,
empty area in the task,
which represents
the time I spent
entering the user name
and password.
As soon as I'm done
entering these credentials,
we retry the transaction.
The green color of the interval
and the 201-status code
indicates it succeeded
this time.
This interaction
of an authentication challenge,
entering a password,
and retrying the transaction
is another case the URL Loading
system handles for us,
so these two transactions belong
to the same task object.
Zooming out,
we find the second attempt
at favoriting
an image on the right.
The task object is displayed
in gray, as my dismissing
of the log-in screen caused
the task to be canceled,
which is also visible
in its label.
The transaction interval is
displayed in orange,
as we got a 401 response
from the server again.
This task occurred
after I attempted to like
another dog picture and was
prompted with the log-in
for a second time.
We use a very basic log-in
system, where the user sends
their credentials the first
time, but once the server
verified the user credentials,
it sets a cookie,
identifying the user,
such that no credentials
need to be provided
on following requests.
So I would've expected this task
to have sent the proper cookie.
Let's determine
whether that happened.
As Kacper explained earlier,
there should be a small
cookie icon here
next to the HTTP method,
had this transaction
sent a Cookie header.
But there's no such icon here,
which means no cookie was sent.
So that part isn't working.
Now the question is,
did the server not
provide us with a cookie,
or is the client not
sending one,
even though it got one?
To find out, we need
to investigate
the previous transaction,
and check
whether we got a cookie
from the server.
Here is
the previous transaction,
the successful one from
the first log-in request.
This one does have a cookie icon
in the response portion
of the transaction label,
so the server did send a cookie.
That's interesting.
So why didn't we send the cookie
in the next transaction?
To get more information
about this transaction
and investigate the cookie
in detail,
I will switch
to the "Transactions" list
in the detail view
at the bottom.
The transaction is
already selected here,
since the time cursor is placed
inside of it in the track view.
The extended detail view
in the bottom right
shows all request
and response headers
of the currently-selected
transaction.
And here is the Set-Cookie
header that we expect.
At first glance,
this cookie seems fine.
But oh, wait,
do you see the expiry date?
It's March 2020.
That's in the past!
So the server did send a cookie,
but it's an expired cookie.
No one likes expired cookies!
This will lead the URLSession
to not send the cookie,
as it will only send cookies
that are still valid.
This is a server-side bug.
I could send the trace file
over to our server folks
for them to investigate
the issue and have it resolved.
Now that we fixed
the cookie issue, I can favorite
a couple more pictures without
being prompted to log in.
In addition to the "Latest" tab,
there's also a "Favorite" tab,
where we display a list
of all the dog images
that the user has favorited.
Let's switch to that tab.
Great, there are a few favorites
here that I added yesterday,
but for some reason, my recent
favorites aren't showing up.
Let's try again.
Let's pick this dog,
who seems to be enjoying a bath,
and let me favorite it.
Let's go back to my favorites
and check if it appears.
Hm, it's still not there.
Let's use Instruments again
to figure out what's going on.
I prepared a trace file
for this already.
I expect to find a task loading
the list of favorites
in the track view, but it's not
visible at first glance.
Let me choose the track
for my server domain,
to display only the requests
issued to that domain.
We could then go to the detail
view at the bottom,
which contains a list
of all tasks for this domain.
There's quite a few
requests here.
Let me use the detail filter
at the bottom left
to search for all requests
related to "Favorites,"
so I can verify whether
we even made a request.
Upon filtering,
the results show we sent
several requests to load
the list of favorites here.
Let's focus on the track view.
The cursor got positioned at
the start of the task I selected
down in the detail view,
so that makes it fairly easy
to find it
in the track view above.
Let's zoom in to double-check.
So this was the first time
we loaded
the list of favorites
on the initial app launch.
This is fine.
Here, I favorited a new image,
and after that,
we loaded the favorites again.
Well, there's a task interval
here, but it's very short.
Yeah, this GET request only took
a couple of milliseconds.
That's too fast to get
a server response.
Let's switch to the "HTTP
transactions
by connection" view again
to get more details.
The first thing we notice
is that this transaction
is not executed on a Connection,
but on "Local Cache."
This shows us that the request
was never sent on the network,
but rather loaded
from the local cache.
This also explains why there is
no "Waiting for Response" state,
since the transaction did
not wait for a server.
So that's the problem:
our request is cached,
so we don't actually ask
the server,
and always get
the cached response back.
One way to fix this would be
to tell the server to set
a cache-control header,
to never cache this response.
What we want is to reload
the images every time the user
goes to the favorites tab
and new images have been added.
What we don't want is
to load the whole list
of images if there was
no such change.
A good trade-off would be
if we could ask the server,
"Hey, did anything change?
If so, please let me know."
That's actually something
we can do
by setting a cache-policy
on the request.
To update the code,
let me go back to the task view
and select the task in question.
For each URLSession Task
that got executed here...
We display
the backtrace on the right,
where "resume" was
called on the task.
It was resumed
in the method sync,
in the ImageCollection type.
Let me open this in Xcode
to make the change here.
Here, I have my URLRequest,
and now I wanna set
my cache policy.
The cache policy I want is
reloadRevalidatingCacheData,
which means that we ignore
the local cache
and will make a request
to the server to check
whether our cache
is still valid.
If so, the server
will send a 304 response code
to let us know
to use the local cache.
If not, it will send
the new data back.
Let's give it a try.
So these are my current
favorited images,
and the dog taking
a bath has been added.
Let's add another one.
Now, let's check
the "Favorite" tab.
The image I just favorited
now properly appears.
OK, great!
That's fixed now as well.
Back to my colleague
Kacper to cover checking
that your app and dependencies
behave like you'd expect.
[Kacper] Just like Sergio
showed before,
when I click
on the "Favorite" tab
without being logged in,
the log-in view is presented.
We already added
Sign In with Apple
to make the log-in
experience seamless.
However, our company has
several pet-themed apps,
and another team is working
on a shared log-in SDK to allow
users to reuse their account
between the applications.
This SDK
is currently in development,
and the other team has
asked us whether it could
replace our classic
log-in screen.
I got the SDK binary,
called Pets,
which is distributed
as an xcframework
so that it can be used
on all platforms.
Integrating it into my Xcode
project is as easy as dragging
and dropping it in the embedded
frameworks section.
Now, all that is left is to add
a button to our existing view.
I will navigate to the source
code of our Log-inView.
I will first import
the framework,
and then add the button
to our SwiftUI VStack,
just below
the Sign In with Apple.
Let's refresh
our Swift UI Preview.
Here it is.
"Sign In with Pets" button
appeared on the preview,
exactly where I want it.
That was, indeed,
a really easy integration.
I am curious to check how quick
this new log-in method will be.
And to measure this,
I'll profile my application
with Instruments by using
Product Profile Action.
I am choosing Network template.
And clicking "record" button
in the toolbar to launch
the app.
My app has now launched.
I can now switch
to the Log-in View.
Instruments is showing
all of the networking traffic
occurring in the meantime.
I will expand it to inspect
my app's URL session.
Here it is.
But wait.
I would expect only my main app
URLSession to be here,
but seems that the Pets
framework we just integrated
is making requests
from its own session,
without me even clicking
on the log-in button.
That's unexpected.
Let's stop the recording right
now to investigate it further.
I will zoom in
to a few first requests,
using option-click and drag.
There's many requests
to some analytics endpoint,
and to get more details,
I can click on this
"Pets Sign On Network" session
and list all of them
in the detail view.
All of them are POST requests,
and when I click on one,
I can see the backtrace
on the right that tells us
which part of the code
the request originated from.
So seems that request is
going through CFNetwork,
invoked by Pets,
just as expected.
But when we navigate deeper,
it seems like CoreLocation
is being involved.
That's really suspicious,
especially because
I didn't perform
any action to trigger it.
I wonder if my location
is being sent back
to the server
and that's why CoreLocation
and CFNetwork
are in the same backtrace.
I will verify that by inspecting
the corresponding HTTP
transactions for these tasks.
To do this, I will switch detail
from the list of tasks
to the list of transactions.
And select one of them.
In the extended detail
on the bottom right,
it's visible that this request
contains some
pretty standard headers,
nothing to worry about.
But wait,
look at the request body.
It's including
my location coordinates,
and that's really bad.
Sending this information
violates users' privacy.
We don't want
to gather their location
without their consent
and without a good reason.
So far, our app only requests
this permission for legitimate
purposes that make
the user experience better.
At this point,
I will not go any further
with this SDK integration.
Instead, I will file
a bug report
on the other team to inform them
about this unacceptable
behavior that I detected.
And I can even use
this Instruments trace
to generate necessary
information for the bug report.
Let's save it
on my desktop first.
I will name it
"PrivacyViolation"
and hit "save."
xctrace, command line tool
bundled with Instruments,
can be used to export this trace
to the HTTP Archive format,
which is an industry standard
for exchange of information
about HTTP Traffic.
To do this, I can simply run
xctrace export command,
with input of my trace,
and HAR export flag.
Let's run it now.
This command generates
a file that I can now attach
in the bug report.
Someone receiving it can inspect
the recorded information
in any tool that supports HAR,
even if they don't have
Instruments installed
on their machine.
HAR itself is
a JSON-based format,
so it can also be opened
in the text editor or easily
processed using scripts.
And even though
it doesn't contain
instruments-specific details,
like URLSessions or backtraces,
that still should be enough
for the other team
to investigate this issue.
And that's how you can use
HTTP Traffic Instrument
to diagnose source and content
of traffic coming from
your application to make sure
that you are in control
of what your app does
at runtime.
Now that you're familiar
with using the new
HTTP Traffic Instrument,
go ahead and target your apps
to detect problems just like
the ones we showed you today.
For easier debugging and having
more context while doing so,
name your URLSession
and task objects.
Always aim for adopting
latest networking protocols.
And even if you don't find
any performance or correctness
issues with your app,
go ahead and verify
by how much data you're sending
to get rid of any
unnecessary traffic.
Thank you for watching today,
and we hope you have
a great time tracing
your app's HTTP traffic.
[upbeat music]