[music]
[Eryn] Hi.
I'm Eryn Wells, an engineer
on the Authentication
Experience Team.
If your app or website ever asks
someone for a password,
then you know
that account security
is critically important.
In this video,
I'm gonna talk about
how to keep your customer's
accounts more secure
and how to make signing in
with verification codes
even easier with the new
verification code generator
built into iCloud Keychain.
This is a big topic,
and I'm gonna break it down
into three important parts.
First, we'll talk
about passwords,
some of the security problems
they have,
and how multistep authentication
helps address
some of those problems.
Second,
I'll talk about time-based
verification codes,
including
a brand-new authenticator
we've built into iCloud Keychain
in iOS 15 and macOS Monterey.
Finally, I'll take a step back
to discuss the beginning
of a big change
happening in the world
of authentication,
as well as
some other opportunities
to improve how people sign in
with verification codes.
OK, let's talk about passwords
and multistep authentication.
Passwords are everywhere,
and people understand
how to use them.
However,
it turns out they're difficult
to use correctly.
In fact,
it's easier to misuse passwords
than to use them correctly.
People frequently
reuse passwords
across multiple websites
or choose passwords
that are easy to guess.
It's also pretty easy
for an attacker
to convince someone
to give up their password.
So services are faced
with a dilemma:
How do we add security
to our users' accounts
while still
making it easy to log in?
Many services add steps
to their log-in flows.
They ask for additional
pieces of information
to confirm someone's identity.
Adding steps like this
reduces the chance
that an attacker
with someone's password
will be able to access
that person's account.
It also means the attacker
won't automatically have access
to any other accounts
where that person used
the same password.
Verification codes
are a common additional step.
Services ask for these codes
after someone has entered
their user name and password.
These codes are either delivered
over SMS, email,
or a push notification,
or they're generated
by an authenticator app
on the person's phone
or with a hardware key fob.
An essential feature
of these codes
is that they're single use.
Since they're not intended
to be memorized or stored,
they're not susceptible to reuse
like passwords are.
Verification codes
do still require a human
to enter the code, though,
so they're still prone
to phishing
in the same way
that passwords are.
The most common way by far
that verification codes
are delivered is with SMS.
Almost everyone
who has a cell phone
can receive a text message,
and people understand
sending and receiving texts.
AutoFill made it even easier
to use these codes.
Just one tap fills a code
into any text field.
But there are still
real problems
with verification codes
delivered over SMS.
For one thing,
they're not very secure.
They're vulnerable to snooping
on carrier networks
and SIM-swapping attacks,
where an attacker
can receive messages
meant for someone else.
People tend to take for granted
that text messages
will come and go without error,
but they do require
network access.
So if someone's on an airplane
or away from strong service,
it might take a long time
for a message to arrive
or it may not arrive at all.
Finally,
SMS messages have a cost,
both to send and to receive.
So sending millions
of these messages
can really add up.
Another way
verification codes are done
is with on-device
code generators.
The algorithm for doing this
is defined in RFC 6238
and is called
"Time-Based One-Time Passwords,"
or "TOTP."
It takes a secret key and a time
and produces
a short numeric code
based on
those bits of information.
Typically,
an authenticator app
or hardware device
generates the codes.
It doesn't require any
communication with the service.
It all happens on the device.
This is a huge benefit in terms
of security and user experience.
Codes are valid
for a short amount of time,
typically 30 seconds or so.
And it results in lower costs
for both services and customers
because no one has to send
or receive SMS messages.
The challenge with TOTP
is that it tends to be a bit
more complicated to set up.
Services have to share
a secret key
with their customers,
along with several
other parameters,
so that the customer's device
can start generating codes.
A typical setup process
involves displaying a QR code
on one device,
downloading an authenticator app
on another device,
and then scanning
the QR code with that app.
This is a cumbersome process,
and it's difficult
to explain to people.
Generating codes on-device
is a better experience
for everyone,
but it does still have
some pesky issues around setup.
We took a careful look
at some of those difficulties
and developed
a new feature of iCloud Keychain
that brings a streamlined
setup experience
together with AutoFill
into something really fantastic.
New in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey,
we've built time-based
verification code generators
into iCloud Keychain
Password Manager,
and I am so excited
to show you how this works.
We started with the basics:
looking up and copying codes
to use on this device
or another device.
These are important features
of any authenticator app.
But AutoFill
really makes this shine.
Just like with codes
delivered over SMS,
AutoFill fills
generated verification codes
with a single tap.
Because codes
are immediately available,
your customers get
a more streamlined,
reliable sign-in experience,
and you get to reduce the costs
of sending SMS messages.
One of my favorite parts
of this feature
is how easy it can be to set up
a new verification code.
When you add
a special link or a button
to your TOTP setup pages,
someone using iOS 15
or macOS Monterey
will be able to set up
a new verification code
on the same device
with just a couple taps.
It's really, really easy.
Finally,
verification codes are synced
across all
of a person's devices,
and they're securely
backed up with iCloud Keychain.
So they don't have
to pull out their iPhone
to fill a verification code
when they're signing in
to an account on their Mac.
This is great
for account recovery too.
When verification codes
are safely backed up in iCloud,
losing a device no longer means
losing access to accounts.
As a reminder,
everything in iCloud Keychain
is end-to-end encrypted,
so no one except
the owner of the account--
not Apple or anyone else--
can access them.
Devices
with iCloud Keychain enabled
are protected by Face ID,
Touch ID, or a passcode.
And every Apple device has
the highest level of security
supported
by the operating system.
So Keychain data is safe,
no matter which device
a person has in the moment.
Apple's Platform Security Guide
describes all of this
and a lot more in great detail.
There are a few
easy things you can do
to ensure your customers have
the best possible experience
setting up and filling codes.
For your setup flows,
there are two things,
and for your log-in flows,
there's just one.
Let's talk a little
about each one.
Being able to set up
a new verification code
with just a few taps
is a big deal.
Hundreds of millions
of iPhone users
are going to be able to do this
as soon as they update
to iOS 15.
You can make it super easy
to set up verification codes
on their devices
by adding a link or a button
that does this
to your setup screens.
If you already
have infrastructure
to support logging in
with TOTP codes,
you might be familiar
with otpauth: URLs.
These URLs contain
all of the information required
to set up a code generator,
including the base32-encoded
secret key,
the number of digits
in each code,
the period of time
that each code is valid for,
and an issuer field
that you should set
to your domain name.
iCloud Keychain uses this field
to suggest an account
to add the verification code to.
This is the same URL that
you encode into the QR codes
that are a common part
of the TOTP setup process.
You can link directly
to the iCloud Keychain
Password Manager
by prefixing the URL
with "apple-".
You can take
this apple otpauth: URL
and put it in an anchor tag
on your web page.
And in apps,
you have two options.
You can create a link
by adding the "link" attribute
to an NSAttributedString
that you assign to a textView's
attributedString property,
or you can open the URL
in response to a button tap
with the open API
on the window scene.
You can check
whether the system can open
apple otpauth: URLs
with an availability check.
On previous versions of iOS,
you should hide setup buttons
and remove setup URLs.
The second thing you can do
during setup
is to use raster images
like JPGs, PNGs, or GIFs
for QR codes intended to be
scanned by other TOTP apps.
Safari uses on-device
image analysis
to detect QR codes
and decode
the information they contain.
If Safari determines
that the QR code contains
an otpauth: URL,
it will offer
to set up the code generator
in the context menu
for the QR code image.
The last thing to do
concerns text fields
for entering generated codes.
To ensure that AutoFill knows
exactly where to fill
user names, passwords,
and verification codes,
annotate those text fields
with content types.
You can do this in SwiftUI
with the textContentType
view modifier,
in UIKit with
the textContentType property
on UITextFields,
in AppKit apps
with the contentType property
on NSTextFields,
and on the web, you can set
the auto-complete attribute
to "one-time-code"
on input elements.
So now,
I wanna take a step back.
Let's look at the big picture
of authentication
and talk a little about
how to make your existing
infrastructure more secure.
Authentication mechanisms
exist on a spectrum,
increasing in strength
and security as you move along.
Passwords are
the traditional baseline
for the industry,
and there are a number of ways
that services reinforce
password-based log-in flows.
Two of the most common
are Passwords + Codes
delivered over SMS
and Passwords + Codes
generated with TOTP.
An additional decision
services make
is whether to use
a federated sign-in provider
that delegates the entire
process of authentication
to another service.
Federated authentication
options are based
on all the same mechanisms
as traditional methods
but require people to keep track
of fewer passwords.
When implemented on robust,
secure infrastructure--
as is the case
with Sign in with Apple--
they can also be more secure
than those traditional
mechanisms.
A step beyond any of these
is to get rid of passwords
altogether.
The WebAuthentication standard,
or "WebAuthn,"
does exactly this.
Instead,
it uses public key cryptography
to keep accounts safe.
iOS 15 and macOS Monterey
contain a preview
of this technology
that offers a usable replacement
for passwords.
My teammate Garrett
has a video about it
that you should definitely
check out.
As our whole industry
continues to work
on building that future
without passwords,
there is still real value
in taking steps
to improve the security
of the infrastructure
you already have
and may continue
to have for a while.
Anything you can do to keep
people safer online is good.
One step you can take
concerns verification codes
delivered over SMS.
As you're evaluating adopting
time-based verification codes,
you might still need
to send codes with SMS.
In iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
we introduced a simple mechanism
for making your SMS codes
more resistant to phishing
by adding domain bindings
to your messages.
A domain binding is a way
of communicating with AutoFill
that the code in this message is
meant for a particular domain.
When the code is bound
in this way,
AutoFill will only offer
the code
if the domain it's bound to
matches the domain
of the web page
or one of your app's
associated domains.
In apps, this works
on the same mechanisms
as associated domains
and universal links.
So if you've already
configured your apps
for those technologies,
you're all set
to add domain bindings.
You can learn more about this
in an article we published
about enhancing the security of
SMS codes with domain bindings.
Now that you know
all about verification codes,
go and do
these two important things.
First,
adopt time-based
verification codes
in your apps and websites.
Add support to your back ends,
and encourage your customers
to use them
instead of getting codes
over SMS.
Second,
if you are continuing to support
SMS verification codes,
add domain bindings
to your messages.
Thank you for watching.
[music]