[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Courtland Idstrom: Hello,
my name is Courtland Idstrom,
and I'm an engineer
on the RealityKit team.
In this video,
I'm going to show you
how to use the new rendering
features in RealityKit 2.
RealityKit is a framework
designed to make building
AR apps simple and intuitive.
Rendering is a key piece
of RealityKit,
centered around
highly realistic,
physically based rendering.
Since our first release in 2019,
we've been working
on your feedback
and we're shipping
a major update to RealityKit.
In the "Dive into Reality Kit 2"
session,
we covered the evolution
of RealityKit,
providing many enhancements --
from updates to the ECS system,
more evolved material
and animation capabilities,
and generating audio and texture
resources at runtime.
To showcase these
improvements,
we built an app
that turns your living room
into an underwater aquarium.
In this talk, we'll show some
of the new rendering features
that went into the app.
RealityKit 2 provides
control and flexibility
with how objects are rendered,
allowing you to create
even better AR experiences.
This year we bring advancements
to our material system,
enabling you
to add your own materials
by authoring
custom Metal shaders.
Custom post effects allow you
to augment RealityKit's
post effects with your own.
New mesh APIs allow
mesh creation, inspection,
and modifications at runtime.
Let's start with
the most requested feature
in RealityKit 2,
support for custom shaders.
RealityKit's rendering
centers around
a physically based
rendering model.
Its built-in shaders
make it easy to create models
that look natural
next to real objects
across a range
of lighting conditions.
This year, we're building on
these physically based shaders
and exposing the ability
for you to customize
the geometry and surface
of models using shaders.
The first of our shader APIs
is geometry modifier.
A geometry modifier
is a program,
written in the Metal Shading
Language,
that gives you the opportunity
to change the vertices
of an object every frame
as it's rendered on the GPU.
This includes moving them and
customizing their attributes,
such as color, normal,
or UVs.
It's run inside of RealityKit's
vertex shader,
and is perfect
for ambient animation,
deformation, particle systems,
and billboards.
Our seaweed is a great example
of ambient animation.
The seaweed is moving slowly
due to the movement
of water around it.
Let's take a closer look.
Here you can see the wireframe
of the seaweed
as created by our artist;
this shows the vertices and
triangles comprising the mesh.
We're going to write
a shader program
that executes on each vertex
to create our motion.
We'll use a sine wave,
a simple periodic function,
to create movement.
We're simulating water currents
so we want nearby vertices
to behave similarly,
regardless of their model's
scale or orientation.
For this reason, we use
the vertex's world position
as an input
to the sine function.
We include a time value as well,
so that it moves over time.
Our first sine wave
is in the Y dimension
to create up-down movement.
To control the period
of the motion,
we'll add a spatial scale.
And we can control the amount of
its movement with an amplitude.
We'll apply the same function
to the X and Z dimensions
so it moves in all three axes.
Now, let's look
at the model as a whole.
One thing we haven't
yet accounted for:
vertices close
to the base of the stalk
have very little room
for movement,
while ones at the top have
the highest freedom to move.
To simulate this, we can use
the vertex's y-coordinate
relative to the object's origin
as a scaling factor
for all three axes,
which gives us
our final formula.
Now that we have
a plan for our shader,
let's take a look at where
to find these parameters.
Geometry parameters are
organized into a few categories.
The first is uniforms,
values that are the same
for every vertex of the object
within one frame.
We need time for our seaweed.
Textures contain all textures
authored as part of the model,
plus an additional custom slot,
which you can use
as you see fit.
Material constants
have any parameters,
such as tint or opacity scale,
authored with the object
or set via code.
Geometry contains
some read-only values,
such as the current vertex's
model position or vertex ID.
We need both model
and world positions
for our seaweed movement.
Geometry also
has read-write values,
including normal, UVs,
and model position offset.
Once we have computed
our offset,
we'll store it here
to move our vertices.
Let's dive into Metal shader.
We start out
by including RealityKit.h.
Now we declare a function with
the visible function attribute.
This instructs the compiler
to make it available
separately from other functions.
The function takes
a single parameter,
which is RealityKit's
geometry_parameters.
We'll retrieve all values
through this object.
Using the geometry member
of params,
we'll ask for both the world
position and model position.
Next we calculate
a phase offset,
based on the world position
at the vertex and time.
Then we apply our formula to
calculate this vertex's offset.
We store the offset
on geometry,
which will get added
to the vertex's model position.
We have our geometry modifier,
but it's not yet hooked up
to our seaweed.
Let's switch to our ARView
subclass, written in Swift.
We start by loading our app's
default Metal library,
which contains our shader.
Next we construct
a geometryModifier
using our shader's
name and library.
For each material
on the seaweed,
we create a new custom material.
We pass the existing material
as the first parameter
to CustomMaterial,
so that it inherits the textures
and material properties
from the base material while
adding our geometry modifier.
It looks pretty nice!
Since we're underwater,
we've kept the animation
pretty slow.
By tweaking amplitude
and phase,
the same effect
can be extended to grass,
trees, or other foliage.
Now that we've shown
how to modify geometry,
let's talk about shading.
This is our octopus
from the underwater scene,
looking great
with our built-in shader.
As they do,
our octopus transitions
between multiple looks.
The second look
has a reddish color.
Our artist has authored
two base color textures,
one for each look.
In addition to the color change,
the red octopus has
a higher roughness value,
making it less reflective.
And, to make our octopus
even more special,
we wanted to create
a nice transition between looks.
Here you can see
the transition in action.
Mesmerizing.
While each look can be described
as a physically based material,
for the transition itself,
we need to write
a surface shader.
So what is a surface shader?
A surface shader
allows you to define
the appearance of an object.
It runs inside
the fragment shader
for every visible pixel
of an object.
In addition to color,
this includes surface properties
such as normal, specular,
and roughness.
You can write shaders that
enhance an object's appearance
or replace it entirely,
creating new effects.
We've seen the two base-color
textures for our octopus.
For the transition effect,
our artist has encoded
a special texture for us.
This texture is actually
a combination
of three different layers.
There's a noise layer on top
creating localized transition
patterns.
We have a transition layer,
which dictates
the overall movement,
starting at the head and
moving towards the tentacles.
And there's a mask layer
for areas that we don't
want to change color,
such as the eye and underside
of the tentacles.
These three layers are combined
into the red, green,
and blue channels
of our texture,
which we assign
to the custom texture slot.
With our textures set up,
let's look at how to access
these from a surface shader.
Similar to
the geometry modifier,
the surface shader
has access to uniforms,
textures,
and material constants.
Time is an input
to our octopus transition.
We'll sample textures
authored with our model
and read material constants,
allowing our artist to make
model-wide adjustments.
Geometry -- such as position,
normal, or UVs --
appear in a geometry structure.
These are the interpolated
outputs from the vertex shader.
We'll use UV0
as our texture coordinate.
A surface shader
writes a surface structure.
Properties start
with default values,
and we're free
to calculate these values
in any way we see fit.
We'll be calculating
base color and normal.
Then, four surface parameters:
roughness, metallic,
ambient occlusion, and specular.
Now that we know
where our values live,
let's start writing our shader.
We'll do this in three steps.
First calculate
the transition value,
where 0 is a fully purple
octopus and 1 is fully red.
Using the transition value,
we'll calculate color and normal
and then fine-tune by assigning
material properties.
Let's get started.
First step: transition.
We're building the octopus
surface function,
which takes a surface_parameters
argument.
Since we're using textures,
we declare a sampler.
On the right, you can see
what our octopus looks like
with an empty surface shader --
it's gray and
a little bit shiny.
RealityKit puts you in complete
control of what does
or does not contribute
to your model's appearance.
In order to compute color,
there's a few things
we need to do first.
We'll store some convenience
variables.
We access our UV0,
which we'll use
as a texture coordinate.
Metal and USD have different
texture coordinate systems,
so we'll invert the y-coordinate
to match the textures
loaded from USD.
Now we'll sample
our transition texture --
the three-layered texture
our artist created.
Our artist set up
a small function
that takes the mask value
plus time,
and returns 0 to 1 values
for blend and colorBlend.
Second step:
color and normal.
With our previously computed
blend variable,
we can now calculate
the octopus's color
and see the transition.
To do this, we sample
two textures:
the base color
and the secondary base color,
which we've stored
in emissive_color.
Then we blend
between the two colors
using the previously computed
colorBlend.
We'll multiply
by base_color_tint --
a value from the material --
and set our base color
on the surface.
Next we'll apply
the normal map,
which adds surface deviations,
most noticeable
on the head and tentacles.
We sample
the normal map texture,
unpack its value, and then
set on the surface object.
Onto material properties.
Here's our octopus so far,
with color and normal.
Let's see how surface properties
affect its look.
Roughness, which you'll see
on the lower body;
ambient occlusion, which will
darken up the lower portions;
and specular, which gives us
a nice reflection on the eye
and some additional definition
on the body.
Let's add these
to our shader.
We sample four textures
on the model,
one for each property.
Next we scale these values
with material settings.
In addition, we're also
increasing the roughness
as we transition
from purple to red.
Then we set our four values
on the surface.
Similar to before, we need to
apply the shader to our model.
We assign this material to our
model in our ARView subclass.
First we load
our two additional textures,
then load our surface shader.
Like before, we're constructing
new materials
from the object's base material,
this time with a surface shader
and our two additional textures.
And we're done.
So to recap, we've shown
the seaweed animation
using geometry modifiers
and how to build
an octopus transition
with surface shaders.
While we've demonstrated
them separately,
you can combine the two for
even more interesting effects.
Moving on to another
highly requested feature,
support for adding custom
post processing effects.
RealityKit comes with
a rich suite
of camera-matched post effects
like motion blur, camera noise,
and depth of field.
These effects are all designed
to make virtual and real objects
feel like they're part
of the same environment.
These are available for you
to customize on ARView.
This year, we're also exposing
the ability for you
to create your own
fullscreen effects.
This allows you to leverage
RealityKit for photo realism,
and add new effects to tailor
the result for your app.
So what is a post process?
A post process is a shader or
series of shaders that execute
after objects have been
rendered and lit.
It also occurs after
any RealityKit post effects.
Its inputs are two textures:
color and a depth buffer.
The depth buffer is displayed
as greyscale here;
it contains a distance value
for each pixel
relative to the camera.
A post process
writes its results
to a target color texture.
The simplest post effect
would copy source color
into target color.
We can build these
in a few ways.
Apple's platforms come
with a number of technologies
that integrate well
with post effects,
such as Core Image,
Metal Performance Shaders,
and SpriteKit.
You can also write your own
with the Metal Shading Language.
Let's start with
some Core Image effects.
Core Image is an Apple framework
for image processing.
It has hundreds of
color-processing,
stylization,
and deformation effects
that you can apply
to images and video.
Thermal is a neat effect --
something you might turn on
for an underwater fish finder.
Let's see how easy it is
to integrate with RealityKit.
All of our post effects
will follow the same pattern.
You set render callbacks,
respond to prepare with device,
and then post process
will be called every frame.
Render callbacks exist
on RealityKit's ARView.
We want both
the prepareWithDevice
and postProcess callbacks.
Prepare with device
will be called once
with the MTLDevice.
This is a good opportunity
to create textures,
load compute
or render pipelines,
and check device capabilities.
This is where we create
our Core Image context.
The postProcess callback
is invoked each frame.
We'll create a CIImage,
referencing our
source color texture.
Next we create
our thermal filter.
If you're using
a different Core Image filter,
this is where you'd configure
its other parameters.
Then we create
a render destination,
which targets
our output color texture
and utilizes the context's
command buffer.
We ask Core Image to preserve
the image's orientation
and start the task.
That's it!
With Core Image, we've unlocked
hundreds of prebuilt effects
that we can use.
Now let's see how we can
use Metal Performance Shaders
to build new effects.
Let's talk about bloom.
Bloom is a screen space
technique that creates a glow
around brightly lit objects,
simulating a real-world
lens effect.
Core Image contains
a bloom effect,
but we're going to build
our own
so we can control
every step of the process.
We'll build the effect
with Metal Performance Shaders,
a collection of highly optimized
compute and graphics shaders.
To build this shader,
we're going to construct
a graph of filters
using color as the source.
We first want to isolate
the areas that are bright.
To do this, we use an operation
called "threshold to zero."
It converts color to luminance
and sets every pixel below
a certain brightness level to 0.
We then blur the result
using a Gaussian blur,
spreading light
onto adjacent areas.
Efficient blurs can be
challenging to implement
and often require
multiple stages.
Metal Performance Shaders
handles this for us.
Then we add this blurred texture
to the original color,
adding a glow
around bright areas.
Let's implement this graph
as a post effect.
We start by creating
an intermediate bloomTexture.
Then execute our
ThresholdToZero operation,
reading from sourceColor
and writing to bloomTexture.
Then we perform
a gaussianBlur in place.
Finally, we add
our original color
and this bloomed color together.
That's it!
Now that we've seen a couple
ways to create post effects,
let's talk about a way
to put effects on top of
our output using SpriteKit.
SpriteKit is Apple's framework
for high performance,
battery-efficient 2D games.
It's perfect for adding some
effects on top of our 3D view.
We'll use it to add
some bubbles on the screen
as a post effect,
using the same prepareWithDevice
and postProcess callbacks.
We have the same two steps
as before.
In prepareWithDevice, we'll
create our SpriteKit renderer
and load the scene
containing our bubbles.
Then in our postProcess
callback,
we'll copy our source color
to target color,
update our SpriteKit scene,
and render on top
of the 3D content.
prepareWithDevice
is pretty straightforward --
we create our renderer
and load our scene from a file.
We'll be drawing this
over our AR scene,
so we need our SpriteKit
background to be transparent.
In postProcess,
we first blit the source color
to the targetColorTexture;
this will be the background that
SpriteKit renders in front of.
Then advance our SpriteKit scene
to the new time
so our bubbles move upward.
Set up a RenderPassDescriptor
and render onto it.
And that's it!
We've shown how
to utilize existing frameworks
to make post effects,
but sometimes you really do
need to make one from scratch.
You can also author
a full-screen effect
by writing a compute shader.
For our underwater demo,
we needed a fog effect
that applies to virtual objects
and camera passthrough.
Fog simulates the scattering
of light through a medium;
its intensity is proportional
to the distance.
To create this effect,
we needed to know
how far each pixel is
from the device.
Fortunately,
ARKit and RealityKit
both provide access
to depth information.
For LiDAR-enabled devices,
ARKit provides
access to sceneDepth,
containing distances in meters
from the camera.
These values
are extremely accurate
at a lower resolution
than the full screen.
We could use this depth directly
but it doesn't include
virtual objects,
so they wouldn't fog correctly.
In our postProcess,
RealityKit provides access
to depth for virtual content
and -- when scene understanding
is enabled --
approximated meshes
for real-world objects.
The mesh builds progressively
as you move,
so it contains some holes where
we haven't currently scanned.
These holes would show fog as if
they were infinitely far away.
We'll combine data from these
two depth textures
to resolve this discrepancy.
ARKit provides depth values
as a texture.
Each pixel is the distance,
in meters,
of the sampled point.
Since the sensor
is at a fixed orientation
on your iPhone or iPad,
we'll ask ARKit
to construct a conversion
from the sensor's orientation to
the current screen orientation,
and then invert the result.
To read virtual content depth,
we need a little bit of info
about how RealityKit
packs depth.
You'll notice that,
unlike ARKit's sceneDepth,
brighter values are nearer
to the camera.
Values are stored
in a 0 to 1 range,
using an Infinite Reverse-Z
Projection.
This just means that 0 means
infinitely far away,
and 1 is at the camera's
near plane.
We can easily reverse
this transform
by dividing the near plane depth
by the sampled depth.
Let's write a helper function
to do this.
We have a Metal function
taking the sample's depth
and projection matrix.
Pixels with no virtual content
are exactly 0.
We'll clamp to a small epsilon
to prevent divide by zero.
To undo the perspective
division,
we take the last column's
z value
and divide by
our sampled depth.
Great!
Now that we have
our two depth values,
we can use the minimum
of the two
as an input to our fog function.
Our fog has a few parameters:
a maximum distance,
a maximum intensity
at that distance,
and a power curve exponent.
The exact values
were chosen experimentally.
They shape our depth value to
achieve our desired fog density.
Now we're ready
to put the pieces together.
We have our depth value
from ARKit,
a linearized depth value
from RealityKit,
and a function for our fog.
Let's write our compute shader.
For each pixel,
we start by sampling
both linear depth values.
Then we apply our fog function
using our tuning parameters,
which turns linear depth
into a 0 to 1 value.
Then we blend between
source color and the fog color,
depending on fogBlend's value,
storing the result in outColor.
To recap, RealityKit's
new post process API
enables a wide range
of post effects.
With Core Image,
we've unlocked hundreds
of ready-built effects.
You can easily build new ones
with Metal Performance Shaders,
add screen overlays
with SpriteKit,
and write your own from scratch
with Metal.
For more information
about Core Image
or Metal Performance Shaders,
see the sessions listed.
Now that we've covered
rendering effects,
let's move onto our next topic,
dynamic meshes.
In RealityKit, mesh resources
store mesh data.
Previously, this opaque type
allowed you to assign meshes
to entities.
This year, we're providing
the ability to inspect meshes,
create, and update meshes
at runtime.
Let's look at how we can add
special effects to the diver.
In this demo, we want
to show a spiral effect
where the spiral contours
around the diver.
You can also see how the spiral
is changing its mesh over time
to animate its movement.
Let's have a look
at how to create this
using our new mesh APIs.
The effect boils down
into three steps.
We use mesh inspection
to measure the model
by examining its vertices.
We then build a spiral, using
the measurements as a guide.
And finally, we can update
the spiral over time.
Starting with mesh inspection.
To explain how meshes
are stored,
let's look at our diver model.
In RealityKit, the Diver's mesh
is represented
as a mesh resource.
With this year's release,
MeshResource now contains
a member called Contents.
There is where all of the
processed mesh geometry lives.
Contents contains a list
of instances and models.
Models contain
the raw vertex data,
while instances reference them
and add a transform.
Instances allow
the same geometry
to be displayed multiple times
without copying the data.
A model can have multiple parts.
A part is a group of geometry
with one material.
Finally, each part contains
the vertex data
we're interested in,
such as positions,
normals,
texture coordinates,
and indices.
Let's first look at how we would
access this data in code.
We'll make an extension
on MeshResource.Contents,
which calls a closure with
the position of each vertex.
We start by going through
all of the instances.
Each of these instances
map to a model.
For each instance,
we find its transform
relative to the entity.
We can then go into
each of the model's parts
and access
the part's attributes.
For this function, we're
only interested in position.
We can then transform the vertex
to the entity space position
and call our callback.
Now that we can
visit the vertices,
let's look at how
we want to use this data.
We'll section our diver
into horizontal slices.
For each slice, we'll find the
bounding radius of our model,
and do this for every slice.
To implement this,
we'll start by creating
a zero-filled array
with numSlices elements.
We then figure out the bounds
of the mesh along the y-axis
to create our slices.
Using the function
we just created,
for each vertex in the model,
we figure out
which slice it goes in
and we update the radius
with the largest radius
for that slice.
Finally, we return
a Slices object
containing the radii and bounds.
Now that we've analyzed
our mesh to know how big it is,
let's look at how to create
the spiral mesh.
The spiral is a dynamically
generated mesh.
To create this mesh,
we need to describe our data
to RealityKit.
We do this
with a mesh descriptor.
The mesh descriptor contains
the positions, normals,
texture coordinates, primitives,
and material indices.
Once you have
a mesh descriptor,
you can generate
a mesh resource.
This invokes RealityKit's
mesh processor,
which optimizes your mesh.
It will merge
duplicate vertices,
triangulate your quads
and polygons,
and represent the mesh
in the most efficient format
for rendering.
The result of this processing
gives us a mesh resource,
which we can assign
to an entity.
Note that normals,
texture coordinates,
and materials are optional.
Our mesh processor
will automatically
generate correct normals
and populate them.
As part of the optimization
process,
RealityKit will regenerate
the topology of the mesh.
If you need a specific topology,
you can use
MeshResource.Contents directly.
Now that we know
how creating a mesh works,
let's look at how to create
the spiral.
To model the spiral, let's take
a closer look at a section.
A spiral is also known
as a helix.
We'll build this
in evenly spaced segments.
We can calculate each point
using the mathematical
definition of a helix
and the radius
from our analyzed mesh.
Using this function for
each segment on the helix,
we can define four vertices.
P0 and P1 are exactly
the values that p() returns.
To calculate P2 and P3, we can
offset P0 and P1 vertically
with our given thickness.
We're creating triangles,
so we need a diagonal.
We'll make two triangles
using these points.
Time to put it all together.
Our generateSpiral function
needs to store
positions and indices.
Indices reference values
in positions.
For each segment,
we'll calculate four positions
and store their indices --
i0 is the index of p0
when it's added to the array.
Then we add the four positions
and six indices --
for two triangles --
to their arrays.
Once you have your geometry,
creating a mesh is simple.
First, create a new
MeshDescriptor.
Then assign positions
and primitives.
We're using triangle primitives,
but we could also choose
quads or polygons.
Once those two fields
are populated,
we have enough
to generate a MeshResource.
You can also provide other
vertex attributes like normals,
textureCoordinates,
or material assignments.
We've covered
how to create the mesh.
The last thing in our spiral
example is mesh updates.
We use mesh updates
to get the spiral
to move around the diver.
To update the mesh,
there's two ways.
We could create a new
MeshResource each frame
using the MeshDescriptors
API.
But this is not
an efficient route,
as it will run through
the mesh optimizer each frame.
A more efficient route
is to update the contents
in the MeshResource.
You can generate
a new MeshContents
and use it to replace the mesh.
There is one caveat, however.
If we created our original mesh
using MeshDescriptor,
RealityKit's mesh processor
will have optimized the data.
Topology is also reduced
to triangles.
As a result, make sure you
know how your mesh is affected
before applying any updates.
Let's have a look at code for
how you can update the spiral.
We start by storing the contents
of the existing spiral.
Create a new model
from the existing model.
Then, for each part,
we replace triangleIndices
with a subset of indices.
Finally, with the new contents,
we can call replace
on the existing MeshResource.
And that's it
for dynamic meshes.
To summarize the key things
about dynamic meshes,
we've introduced a new Contents
field in the MeshResource.
This container allows you
to inspect and modify
a mesh's raw data.
You can create new meshes
using MeshDescriptor.
This flexible route allows you
to use triangles, quads,
or even polygons,
and RealityKit will generate
an optimized mesh
for rendering.
Finally, to update meshes,
we've provided the ability
to update a MeshResource's
contents,
which is ideal
for frequent updates.
To wrap up,
today we've shown off
some of the new rendering
features in RealityKit 2.
Geometry modifiers let you move
and modify vertices.
Surface shaders
allow you to define
your model's surface appearance.
You can use post effects
to apply effects
to the final frame,
and dynamic meshes make it easy
to create and modify meshes
at runtime.
To see more
of this year's features,
don't miss
"Dive into RealityKit 2."
And for more information
about RealityKit,
watch "Building Apps
with RealityKit."
We're very excited
about this year's release,
and can't wait to see the
experiences you build with it.
Thank you.
♪