[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Meghana Gupta: Hi,
my name is Meghana.
Today, I'll be talking to you
about ARC in Swift.
Swift provides powerful value
types like structs and enums.
You should prefer to use
value types when possible
to avoid the dangers
of unintended sharing
that comes with reference types.
Classes are reference types
in Swift,
and if you decide to use them,
Swift manages its memory via
Automatic Reference Counting,
or ARC.
In order to write
effective Swift,
it is important to understand
how ARC works.
In this session,
we’ll do just that.
I’ll start with a review
of object lifetimes
and ARC in Swift.
Then, I’ll describe what
observable object lifetimes are.
I'll explain in detail
what language features make
object lifetimes observable,
consequences of relying
on observed object lifetimes,
and some safe techniques
to fix them.
Let’s begin.
An object’s lifetime in Swift
begins at initialization
and ends at last use.
ARC automatically
manages memory,
by deallocating an object
after its lifetime ends.
It determines
an object’s lifetime
by keeping track
of its reference counts.
ARC is mainly driven
by the Swift compiler
which inserts retain
and release operations.
At runtime, retain increments
the reference count
and release decrements it.
When the reference count
drops to zero,
the object will be deallocated.
Let’s see how it works
with an example.
Imagine we want to build
a travel app.
To represent a traveler,
let’s write a class with name
and an optional
destination property.
In the test() function,
first, a Traveler object
is created,
then its reference is copied,
and finally, its destination
is updated.
In order to automatically manage
the memory
of the Traveler object,
the Swift compiler
inserts a retain operation
when a reference begins
and a release operation
after the last use
of the reference.
traveler1 is the first reference
to the Traveler object,
and its last use is the copy.
Here, the Swift compiler
inserts a release operation
immediately after the last use
of the traveler1 reference.
It does not insert
a retain operation
when the reference begins,
because initialization
sets the reference count to one.
traveler2 is another reference
to the Traveler object,
and its last use
is the destination update.
Here, the Swift compiler
inserts a retain operation
when the reference begins
and a release operation
immediately after the last use
of the reference.
Let's step through the code and
see what happens at runtime.
First, the Traveler object
is created on the heap
and initialized
with a reference count of one.
Then in preparation
of the new reference,
retain operation executes,
incrementing
the reference count to two.
Now traveler2
is also a reference
to the Traveler object.
After the last use
of the traveler1 reference,
the release operation executes,
decrementing the reference count
to one.
Then the destination
of the Traveler object
is updated to Big Sur.
Since that was the last use
of the traveler2 reference,
release operation executes,
decrementing the reference count
to zero.
Once the reference count
drops to zero,
the object can be deallocated.
Object lifetimes in Swift
are use-based.
An object's guaranteed
minimum lifetime
begins at initialization
and ends at last use.
This is different
from languages like C++,
in which an object’s lifetime
is guaranteed to end
at the closing brace.
In this example, we saw
the object was deallocated
immediately
after the last use.
However, in practice,
object lifetimes are determined
by the retain and release
operations
inserted by the Swift compiler.
And depending on the ARC
optimizations that kick in,
the observed object lifetimes
may differ
from their guaranteed minimum,
ending beyond the last use
of the object.
In such cases, the object is
deallocated at a program point
beyond its last use.
In most cases,
it doesn’t really matter
what the exact lifetime
of an object is.
However, with language features
like weak and unowned references
and deinitializer side effects,
it is possible
to observe object lifetimes.
And if you have programs
that rely on observed
object lifetimes
instead of guaranteed
object lifetimes,
you can end up with problems
in the future.
Because relying
on observed object lifetimes
may work today,
but it is only a coincidence.
Observed object lifetimes
are an emergent property
of the Swift compiler
and can change
as implementation
details change.
Such bugs may not be discovered
during development
and may remain hidden
for a long time,
only to be uncovered
by a compiler update
with improved ARC optimizations
or unrelated source changes
that enable a previously limited
ARC optimization.
I’ll go over
the language features
that make object lifetimes
observable,
walk through what can happen
if we rely only
on observed object lifetimes,
and some safe techniques
to fix them.
Unlike default references
that are strong references,
weak and unowned references
do not participate
in reference counting,
and for this reason,
they are commonly used
to break reference cycles.
Before I get into their details,
let’s see
what reference cycles are.
This is an extension
of our Travel app.
We now want to introduce
an optional points system.
A traveler can have an account
and accumulate points in it.
To represent this,
we have a new Account class
with points property.
The Account class refers
to the Traveler class,
and the Traveler class refers
back to the Account class.
In the test() function, we create
Traveler and Account objects,
and then call
the printSummary() function
via the traveler reference.
Let’s step through the code
and see what happens with ARC.
First, Traveler object
is created on the heap
with a reference count of one.
Then Account object
is created on the heap
with a reference count of one.
Since the Account object refers
to the Traveler object,
the reference count of the Traveler
object is incremented to two.
Now the Traveler object starts
referring to the Account object,
so the reference count
of the Account object
is also incremented to two.
This is the last use
of the account reference.
After this, the account
reference goes away
and reference count
of the Account object
is decremented to one.
Then, printSummary() function
is called
to print name and points.
This is the last use
of the Traveler reference.
After this, the Traveler
reference goes away
and the reference count
of the Traveler object
is decremented to one.
Even after all the references
that make the objects reachable
go away, the reference count
of the objects remain one.
This is because
of the reference cycle.
As a result, the objects
are never deallocated,
causing a memory leak.
You may break
the reference cycle
with a weak
or unowned reference.
Because they don’t participate
in reference counting,
the referred object
may be deallocated
while a weak or unowned
reference is in use.
When this happens,
the Swift runtime safely turns
access to weak references
as nil, and access
to unowned references as traps.
Any reference participating
in the reference cycle
can be marked as weak or unowned
to break the reference cycle.
It depends on the application.
In our example, let’s mark
the traveler reference
in the Account class as weak.
Because weak reference
does not participate
in reference counting,
after the last use
of the Traveler object,
its reference count
drops to zero.
Once the reference count
of the Traveler object is zero,
it can be deallocated.
When the Traveler object
goes away,
its reference
to the Account object goes away,
making its reference count zero.
Now the Account object
can be deallocated.
In this example, we used
the weak reference
to only break
the reference cycle.
If a weak reference is used
to access an object
while its guaranteed object
lifetime has ended,
and you are relying
on observed object lifetime
for the object to be available,
you can end up with bugs
in the future
when the observed object
lifetime changes
for unrelated reasons.
Let’s see an example.
Here, the printSummary()
function
is moved from the Traveler class
to the Account class.
And the test() function
now calls
the printSummary() function
via the Account reference.
What exactly happens
when printSummary() function
is called?
It may print the traveler’s name
and points today,
but this is only a coincidence.
This is because the last use
of the Traveler object
is before the call
to the printSummary() function.
After this, the reference count
of the Traveler object
can drop to zero if the compiler
inserted a release
immediately after the last use.
If the reference count
has dropped to zero,
access to the Traveler object
via the weak reference
will be nil,
and the Traveler object
may be deallocated.
So when the printSummary()
function is called,
the force unwrap of the weak
Traveler reference will trap,
causing a crash.
You may be wondering
if the force unwrap is the
reason for the crash here,
and optional binding
may have prevented it.
Optional binding
actually worsens the problem.
Without an obvious crash,
it creates a silent bug
that may go unnoticed when the
observed object lifetime changes
for unrelated reasons.
There are different techniques
to safely handle weak
and unowned references,
each of them
with varying degrees
of upfront implementation cost
versus continuous
maintenance cost.
Let’s explore them one by one
with our example.
Swift provides
withExtendedLifetime() utility
that can explicitly extend
the lifetime of an object.
Using withExtendedLifetime(),
it is possible
to safely extend the lifetime
of the Traveler object,
while the printSummary()
function is being called,
preventing potential bugs.
The same effect can be achieved
by placing an empty call
to withExtendedLifetime() at
the end of the existing scope.
For more complex cases,
we can ask the compiler
to extend the lifetime
of an object
to the end of the current scope
using defer.
withExtendedLifetime() may
look like an easy way out
of object lifetimes bugs.
However, this technique
is fragile,
and transfers the responsibility
of correctness on you.
With this approach,
you should ensure
withExtendedLifetime() is used
every time a weak reference
has a potential to cause bugs.
If not controlled,
withExtendedLifetime() can
creep up all over the codebase,
increasing maintenance cost.
Redesigning classes
with better APIs
is a much more
principled approach.
Object lifetime surprises
can be prevented,
if access to the object
can be limited
to strong references only.
Here, the printSummary()
function is moved back
to the Traveler class,
and the weak reference
in Account class is hidden.
Tests are now forced to call
the printSummary() function
via a strong reference,
eliminating potential bugs.
In addition to carrying
a performance cost,
weak and unowned references
can expose bugs
if you are not careful
with class design.
It is important
to pause and think,
why are weak and unowned
references needed?
Are they used only
to break reference cycles?
What if you avoid
creating reference cycles
in the first place?
Reference cycles can often be
avoided by rethinking algorithms
and transforming cyclic
class relationships
to tree structures.
In our example,
Traveler class needs to refer
to the Account class.
It is not really necessary
for the Account class
to refer to the Traveler class.
Account class only needs access
to the traveler’s
personal information.
We can move the traveler’s
personal information
into a new class
called PersonalInfo.
Both Traveler class
and Account class can refer
to the PersonalInfo class,
avoiding the cycle.
Avoiding the need for weak
and unowned references
may have additional
implementation cost,
but this is a definite way
to eliminate all potential
object lifetime bugs.
Another language feature
that makes object lifetimes
observable
are deinitializer side effects.
A deinitializer runs
before deallocation
and its side effects
can be observed
by external program effects.
If you write code to sequence
deinitializer side effects
with external program effects,
it can lead to hidden bugs,
which are uncovered
only when the observed
object lifetime changes
due to unrelated reasons.
Before I get into how such bugs
can come up,
let’s see
what a deinitializer is.
This is a repeat
of the first example,
now with a deinitializer.
The deinitializer
has a global side effect:
printing a message
on the console.
Today the deinitializer may run
after "Done traveling"
is printed.
But since the last use
of the Traveler object
is the destination update,
the deinitializer can run
before "Done traveling"
is printed,
depending on the ARC
optimizations that kick in.
In this example,
deinitializer side effects were
observable but not relied upon.
Let’s look at a more
complex example,
where deinitializer side effects
are relied upon
by external program effects.
We now introduce travel metrics
to the Traveler class.
Whenever a destination
is updated,
it is recorded
in the TravelMetrics class.
Eventually when deinitializing
the Traveler object,
metrics get published
to a global record.
Metrics published
are the traveler’s anonymous ID,
number of destinations
looked up,
and a computed travel
interest category.
In the test() function,
first, a Traveler object
is created,
then reference
to the travelMetrics
is copied
from the Traveler object.
The traveler’s destination
is updated to Big Sur,
which records Big Sur
in TravelMetrics.
The traveler’s destination
is updated to Catalina,
which records Catalina
in TravelMetrics.
Then the travel interest
category is computed
by looking at
the recorded destinations.
Today the deinitializer
may run
after computing
travel interest,
publishing the interested
category as Nature.
But the last use
of the Traveler object
is the destination update
to Catalina,
immediately after which
the deinitializer can run.
Since the deinitializer runs
before computing the travel
interest, nil gets published,
causing a bug.
Just like weak
and unowned references,
there are different techniques
to safely handle
deinitializer side effects.
Each of them
with varying degrees
of upfront implementation cost
versus continuous
maintenance cost.
Let’s look at them
one by one.
withExtendedLifetime()
can be used
to explicitly extend the
lifetime of the Traveler object
until the travel interest
category is computed,
preventing potential bugs.
As discussed before,
this transfers responsibility
of correctness on you.
With this approach,
you should ensure
withExtendedLifetime
is used every time
there is a potential
of incorrect interaction between
deinitializer side effects
and external program effects,
increasing maintenance cost.
Deinitializer side effects
cannot be observed
if the effects are all local.
Redesigning class API
by limiting the visibility
of internal class details can
prevent object lifetime bugs.
Here, TravelMetrics
is marked private,
hiding it from external access.
The deinitializer now computes
the most interested
travel category
and publishes the metrics.
This works,
but a more principled
approach is to get rid
of the deinitializer
side effects altogether.
Here, defer is used
instead of the deinitializer
to publish metrics,
and the deinitializer
only performs verification.
By removing
deinitializer side effects,
we can eliminate all potential
object lifetime bugs.
We explored our educational
Travel app example
to learn about ARC,
weak and unowned references,
and deinitializer side effects.
It is important to thoroughly
understand the language features
that make object lifetimes
observable
and eliminate potentially
incorrect reliance
on observed object lifetimes,
so that we don’t uncover bugs
at surprising times.
With Xcode 13, a new
experimental build setting
called
"Optimize Object Lifetimes"
is available
for the Swift compiler.
This enables powerful lifetime
shortening ARC optimizations.
With this build setting
turned on,
you may see objects
being deallocated
immediately after last use
much more consistently,
bringing observed
object lifetimes
closer to their
guaranteed minimum.
This may expose
hidden object lifetime bugs,
similar to the examples
discussed.
You can follow
the safe techniques
discussed in this session
to eliminate all such bugs.
I hope you enjoyed this session.
Thanks for watching.
♪