[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Rokhini Prabhu:
Hello, and welcome
to "Swift Concurrency
Behind the Scenes."
My name is Rokhini, and I work
on the Darwin Runtime team.
Today, my colleague Varun and I
are very excited to talk to you
about some of
the underlying nuances
around Swift concurrency.
This is an advanced talk
which builds upon
some of the earlier talks
on Swift concurrency.
If you are unfamiliar with
the concepts of async/await,
structured concurrency,
and actors
I encourage you to watch
these others talks first.
In the previous talks on Swift
concurrency you've learned about
the various language features
available this year
native to Swift
and about how to use them.
In this talk, we will be diving
deeper to understand
why these primitives
are designed the way they are,
not only for language safety
but also for performance
and efficiency.
As you experiment
and adopt Swift concurrency
in your own apps,
we hope this talk will give you
a better mental model of how to
reason about Swift concurrency
as well how it interfaces with
existing threading libraries
like Grand Central Dispatch.
We're going to discuss
a few things today.
First, we'll talk about
the threading model
behind Swift concurrency
and contrast it with
Grand Central Dispatch.
We'll talk about how
we've taken advantage
of concurrency
language features
to build a new
thread pool for Swift,
thereby achieving better
performance and efficiency.
Lastly, in this section,
we'll touch on considerations
you need to keep in mind
when porting your code
to using Swift concurrency.
Varun will then talk
about synchronization
in Swift concurrency via actors.
We'll talk how actors work
under the hood,
how they compare to existing
synchronization primitives
you already may be
familiar with --
like serial dispatch queues --
and finally,
some things to keep in mind
when writing code with actors.
We have a lot of ground to cover
today so let's dive right in.
In our discussion today
about threading models,
we'll start by taking a look
at an example app
written with the technologies
available today
like Grand Central Dispatch.
We will then see how
the same application fares
when rewritten
with Swift concurrency.
Suppose I wanted to write
my own news feed reader app.
Let's talk about what
the high-level components
of my application might be.
My app will have a main thread
that will be driving
the user interface.
I will have a database keeping
track of the news feeds
that the user is subscribed to,
and finally, a subsystem
to handle the networking logic
to fetch the latest contents
from the feeds.
Let's consider how
one might structure this app
with Grand Central Dispatch
queues.
Let's suppose that the user has
asked to see the latest news.
On the main thread, we will
handle the user event gesture.
From here, we will
dispatch async the request
onto a serial queue that handles
the database operations.
The reason for this is twofold.
Firstly, by dispatching the work
onto a different queue,
we ensure that the main thread
can remain responsive
to user input even while waiting
for a potentially large amount
of work to happen.
Secondly, access to
the database is protected,
since a serial queue
guarantees mutual exclusion.
While on the database queue,
we'll iterate through
the news feeds
the user has subscribed to
and for each of them,
schedule a networking request
to our URLSession
to download the contents
of that feed.
As the results of the networking
requests come in,
the URLSession callback will be
called on our delegate queue
which is a concurrent queue.
In the completion handler
for each of the results,
we will synchronously
update the database
with the latest requests
from each of these feeds,
so as to cache it
for future use.
And finally, we'll wake up
the main thread
to refresh the UI.
This seems like
a perfectly reasonable way
to structure such
an application.
We've made sure
not to block the main thread
while working on requests.
And by handling the network
requests concurrently,
we've taken advantage
of the inherent parallelism
in our program.
Let's take a closer look
at a code snippet
that shows how
we process the results
of our networking requests.
First, we have created
a URLSession
for performing downloads
from our news feeds.
As you can see here,
we've set the delegate queue
of this URLSession
to be a concurrent queue.
We then iterate over
all the news feeds
that need to be updated
and for each of them,
schedule a data task
in the URLSession.
In the completion handler
of the data task --
which will be invoked
on the delegate queue --
we deserialize the results
of our download
and format them into articles.
We then dispatch sync
against our database queue
before updating the results
for the feed.
So here you can see
that we've written
some straight-line code to do
something fairly straightforward
but this code has some
hidden performance pitfalls.
To understand more about
these performance problems,
we need to first dig into
how threads are brought up
to handle work on GCD queues.
In Grand Central Dispatch,
when work is enqueued
onto a queue,
the system will
bring up a thread
to service that work item.
Since a concurrent queue
can handle multiple
work items at once,
the system will bring up
several threads
until we have saturated
all the CPU cores.
However, if a thread blocks --
as seen on
the first CPU core here --
and there is more work to be
done on the concurrent queue,
GCD will bring up more threads
to drain the remaining
work items.
The reason for this is twofold.
Firstly, by giving your process
another thread,
we are able to ensure
that each core
continues to have a thread
that executes work
at any given time.
This gives your applications
a good, continuing
level of concurrency.
Secondly the blocked thread
may be waiting on a resource
like a semaphore, before it
can make further progress.
The new thread
that is brought up
to continue working
on the queue
may be able to help
unblock the resource
that is being waited on
by the first thread.
So now that we understand
a bit more
about thread bringups in GCD,
let's go back
and look at the CPU
execution of the code
from our news app.
On a two-core device
like the Apple Watch,
GCD will first bring up
two threads
to process
the feed update results.
As the threads block on
accessing the database queue,
more threads are created
to continue working
on the networking queue.
The CPU then has to context
switch between different threads
processing the
networking results
as indicated by
the white vertical lines
between the various threads.
This means that
in our news application,
we could easily end up with
a very large number of threads.
If the user has a hundred feeds
that need to be updated,
then each of those
URL data tasks
will have a completion block
on the concurrent queue
when the network
requests complete.
GCD will bring up more threads
when each of the callbacks
block on the database queue,
resulting in the application
having lots of threads.
Now you might ask,
what's so bad about having a lot
of threads in our application?
Having a lot of threads
in our applications
means that the system
is overcommitted
with more threads
than we have CPU cores.
Consider an iPhone
with six CPU cores.
If our news application
has a hundred feed updates
that need to be processed,
this means that we have
overcommitted the iPhone
with 16 times more threads
than cores.
This is the phenomenon
we call thread explosion.
Some of our previous WWDC talks
have gone into further detail
on the risks
associated with this,
including the possibility of
deadlocks in your application.
Thread explosion
also comes with memory
and scheduling overhead that
may not be immediately obvious,
so let's look into this further.
Looking back at
our news application,
each of the blocked threads
is holding onto valuable memory
and resources
while waiting to run again.
Each blocked thread has a stack
and associated kernel data
structures to track the thread.
Some of these threads
may be holding onto locks
which other threads
that are running might need.
This is a large number
of resources and memory
to be holding onto for threads
which are not making progress.
There is also greater
scheduling overhead
as a result of thread explosion.
As new threads are brought up,
the CPU need to perform
a full thread context switch
in order to switch away
from the old thread
to start executing
the new thread.
As the blocked threads
become runnable again,
the scheduler will have to
timeshare the threads on the CPU
so that they are all able
to make forward progress.
Now, timesharing of threads
is fine if that happens
a few times --
that is the power
of concurrency.
But when there
is thread explosion,
having to timeshare hundreds
of threads on a device
with limited cores can lead
to excessive context switching.
The scheduling latencies
of these threads
outweigh the amount of useful
work they would do,
therefore, resulting in the CPU
running less efficiently
as well.
As we've seen so far,
it is easy to miss
some of these nuances
about the threading hygiene
when writing applications
with GCD queues
thereby resulting
in poor performance
and greater overhead.
Building on this experience,
Swift has taken
a different approach
when designing concurrency
into the language.
We've built Swift concurrency
with performance
and efficiency in mind as well
so that your apps
can enjoy controlled,
structured,
and safe concurrency.
With Swift, we want to change
the execution model of apps
from the following model,
which has lots of threads
and context switches, to this.
Here you see that we have
just two threads
executing on our two-core system
and there are no thread
context switches.
All of our blocked threads
go away and instead
we have a lightweight object
known as a continuation
to track resumption of work.
When threads execute work
under Swift concurrency
they switch between
continuations
instead of performing
a full thread context switch.
This means that we now only pay
the cost of
a function call instead.
So the runtime behavior that
we want for Swift concurrency
is to create only as many
threads as there are CPU cores,
and for threads to be able
to cheaply and efficiently
switch between work items
when they are blocked.
We want you to be able
to write straight-line code
that is easy to reason about
and also gives you
safe, controlled concurrency.
In order to achieve
this behavior that we are after,
the operating system
needs a runtime contract
that threads will not block,
and that is only possible
if the language is able
to provide us with that.
Swift's concurrency model
and the semantics around it
have therefore been designed
with this goal in mind.
To that end,
I'd like to dive into two
of Swift's language-level
features that enable us
to maintain a contract
with the runtime.
The first comes from
the semantics of await
and the second, from the
tracking of task dependencies
in the Swift runtime.
Let's consider
these language features
in the context of our example
news application.
This is the code snippet
we walked through earlier
that handles the results
of our news feed updates.
Let's see what
this logic looks like
when written with Swift
concurrency primitives instead.
We'd first start with creating
an async implementation
of our helper function.
Then, instead of handling
the results
of our networking requests
on a concurrent dispatch queue,
here we are using
a task group instead
to manage our concurrency.
In the task group,
we will create child tasks
for each feed
that needs to be updated.
Each child task will perform
a download from the feed's URL
using the shared URLSession.
It will then deserialize
the results of the download,
format them into articles
and finally,
we will call an async function
to update our database.
Here, when calling
any async functions,
we annotate it
with an await keyword.
From the "Meet async/await
in Swift" talk,
we learned that an await
is an asynchronous wait.
That is, it does not block
the current thread
while waiting for results
from the async function.
Instead, the function
may be suspended
and the thread will be freed up
to execute other tasks.
How does this happen?
How does one give up a thread?
My colleague Varun
will now shed light
on what is done under the hood
in the Swift runtime
to make this possible.
Varun Gandhi: Thanks, Rokhini.
Before jumping into how async
functions are implemented,
let's do a quick refresher on
how nonasync functions work.
Every thread in a running
program has one stack,
which it uses to store state
for function calls.
Let's focus on one thread
for now.
When the thread executes
a function call,
a new frame is pushed
onto its stack.
This newly created stack frame
can be used by the function
to store local variables,
the return address,
and any other information
that is needed.
Once the function finishes
executing and returns,
its stack frame is popped.
Now let's consider
async functions.
Suppose that a thread called
an add(_:) method on the Feed type
from the updateDatabase
function.
At this stage, the most recent
stack frame will be for add(_:).
The stack frame stores
local variables
that do not need to be available
across a suspension point.
The body of add(_:)
has one suspension point,
marked by await.
The local variables, id
and article, are immediately
used in the body of the for loop
after being defined,
without any suspension
points in-between.
So they will be stored
in the stack frame.
Additionally, there will be two
async frames on the heap,
one for updateDatabase
and one for add.
Async frames store information
that does need to be available
across suspension points.
Notice that the newArticles
argument is defined
before await but needs
to be available after the await.
This means that
the async frame for add
will keep track of newArticles.
Suppose the thread
continues executing.
When the save function
starts executing,
the stack frame for add
is replaced
by a stack frame for save.
Instead of adding
new stack frames,
the top most stack frame
is replaced
since any variables that will
be needed in the future
will already have been stored
in the list of async frames.
The save function also gains
an async frame for its use.
While the articles are being
saved to the database,
it would be better if the thread
could do some useful work
instead of being blocked.
Suppose the execution of the
save function is suspended.
And the thread is reused to do
some other useful work
instead of being blocked.
Since all information
that is maintained
across a suspension point
is stored on the heap,
it can be used to continue
execution at a later stage.
This list of async frames
is the runtime representation
of a continuation.
Say after a little while,
the database request
is complete,
and suppose some thread
is freed up.
This could be
the same thread as before,
or it could be
a different thread.
Suppose the save function
resumes executing
on this thread.
Once it finishes executing
and returns some IDs,
then the stack frame for save
will again be replaced
by a stack frame for add.
After that, the thread can
start executing zip.
Zipping two arrays
is a nonasync operation,
so it will create
a new stack frame.
Since Swift continues to use
the operating system stack,
both async
and nonasync Swift code
can efficiently call
into C and Objective-C.
Moreover, C and Objective-C code
can continue
efficiently calling
nonasync Swift code.
Once the zip function finishes,
its stack frame will be popped
and execution will continue.
So far, I've described how await
is designed to ensure
efficient suspension
and resumption,
while freeing up a thread's
resources to do other work.
Next, Rokhini will describe
the second language feature,
which is the runtime's tracking
of dependencies between tasks.
Rokhini: Thanks, Varun.
As described earlier,
a function can be broken up
into continuations
at an await,
also known as a potential
suspension point.
In this case,
the URLSession data task
is the async function
and the remaining work after it
is the continuation.
The continuation
can only be executed
after the async function
is completed.
This is a dependency tracked by
the Swift concurrency runtime.
Similarly,
within the task group,
a parent task may create
several child tasks
and each of those child tasks
needs to complete
before a parent task
can proceed.
This is a dependency that
is expressed in your code
by the scope of the task group
and therefore explicitly known
to the Swift compiler
and runtime.
In Swift, tasks can only await
other tasks that are known
to the Swift runtime --
be it continuations
or child tasks.
Therefore, code when structured
with Swift's
concurrency primitives
provide the runtime
with a clear understanding
of the dependency
chain between the tasks.
So far, you've learned
how Swift's language features
allow a task to be suspended
during an await.
Instead, the executing thread
is able to reason
about task dependencies
and pick up
a different task instead.
This means that code written
with Swift concurrency
can maintain a runtime contract
that threads are always able
to make forward progress.
We have taken advantage
of this runtime contract
to build integrated OS support
for Swift concurrency.
This is in the form of a new
cooperative thread pool
to back Swift concurrency
as the default executor.
The new thread pool will only
spawn as many threads
as there are CPU cores,
thereby making sure
not to overcommit the system.
Unlike GCD's concurrent queues,
which will spawn more threads
when work items block,
with Swift threads can always
make forward progress.
Therefore, the default runtime
can be judicious
about controlling how many
threads are spawned.
This lets us
give your applications
the concurrency you need
while making sure to avoid
the known pitfalls
of excessive concurrency.
In previous WWDC talks
about concurrency
with Grand Central Dispatch,
we've recommended that
you structure your applications
into distinct subsystems
and maintain one serial dispatch
queue per subsystem
to control the concurrency
of your application.
This meant that it was difficult
for you to get concurrency
greater than one
within a subsystem
without running the risk
of thread explosion.
With Swift, the language
gives us strong invariants
which the runtime has leveraged,
thereby being able
to transparently provide you
with better-controlled
concurrency
in the default runtime.
Now that you understand a bit
more about the threading model
for Swift concurrency,
let's go through some
considerations to keep in mind
while adopting these exciting
new features in your code.
The first consideration that
you need to keep in mind
has to do with performance
when converting synchronous code
into asynchronous code.
Earlier, we talked through
some of the costs
associated with concurrency such
as additional memory allocations
and logic in the Swift runtime.
As such, you need to be careful
to only write new code
with Swift concurrency
when the cost
of introducing concurrency
into your code
outweighs the cost
of managing it.
The code snippet here
might not actually benefit
from the additional concurrency
of spawning a child task
simply to read a value
from the user's defaults.
This is because the useful work
done by the child task
is diminished by the cost of
creating and managing the task.
We therefore recommend
profiling your code
with Instruments system trace
to understand it's
performance characteristics
as you adopt Swift concurrency.
The second thing
to be careful about
is the notion of atomicity
around an await.
Swift makes no guarantee
that the thread
which executed the code before
the await is the same thread
which will pick up
the continuation as well.
In fact, await is an explicit
point in your code
which indicates
that atomicity is broken
since the task may be
voluntarily descheduled.
As such, you should
be careful not to hold locks
across an await.
Similarly, thread-specific data
will not be preserved
across an await either.
Any assumptions in your code
which expect thread locality
should be revisited to account
for the suspending behavior
of await.
And lastly,
the final consideration
has to do with the runtime
contract that is foundational
to the efficient
threading model in Swift.
Recall that with Swift,
the language allows us
to uphold a runtime contract
that threads will always be able
to make forward progress.
It is based on this contract
that we have built
a cooperative thread pool
to be the default
executor for Swift.
As you adopt Swift concurrency,
it is important to ensure that
you continue to maintain
this contract
in your code as well
so that the cooperative thread
pool can function optimally.
It is possible to maintain
this contract
within the cooperative thread
pool by using safe primitives
that make the dependencies
in your code explicit and known.
With Swift concurrency
primitives
like await, actors,
and task groups,
these dependencies
are made known at compile time.
Therefore, the Swift compiler
enforces this
and helps you preserve
the runtime contract.
Primitives like os_unfair_locks
and NSLocks are also safe
but caution is required
when using them.
Using a lock in synchronous
code is safe
when used for
data synchronization
around a tight,
well-known critical section.
This is because
the thread holding the lock
is always able
to make forward progress
towards releasing the lock.
As such, while the primitive
may block a thread
for a short period of time
under contention,
it does not violate
the runtime contract
of forward progress.
It is worth noting that unlike
Swift concurrency primitives,
there is no compiler support to
aid in correct usage of locks,
so it is your responsibility
to use this primitive correctly.
On the other hand,
primitives like semaphores
and condition variables
are unsafe to use
with Swift concurrency.
This is because they hide
dependency information
from the Swift runtime,
but introduce a dependency
in execution in your code.
Since the runtime is unaware
of this dependency,
it cannot make
the right scheduling decisions
and resolve them.
In particular, do not use
primitives that create
unstructured tasks
and then retroactively
introduce a dependency
across task boundaries
by using a semaphore
or an unsafe primitive.
Such a code pattern means that
a thread can block indefinitely
against the semaphore
until another thread
is able to unblock it.
This violates
the runtime contract
of forward progress for threads.
To help you identify uses
of such unsafe primitives
in your codebase,
we recommend testing your apps
with the following
environment variable.
This runs your app under
a modified debug runtime,
which enforces the invariant
of forward progress.
This environment variable
can be set in Xcode
on the Run Arguments pane
of your project scheme
as shown here.
When running your apps
with this environment variable,
if you see a thread
from the cooperative thread pool
that appears to be hung
it indicates the use
of an unsafe blocking primitive.
Now, having learned about
how the threading model
has been designed
for Swift concurrency,
let's discover a little bit more
about the primitives
that are available to us
to synchronize state
in this new world.
Varun: In the Swift concurrency
talk on actors
you've seen how actors
can be used
to protect mutable state
from concurrent access.
Put differently, actors provide
a powerful new synchronization
primitive that you can use.
Recall that actors guarantee
mutual exclusion:
an actor may be executing at
most one method call at a time.
Mutual exclusion means
that the actor's state
is not accessed concurrently,
preventing data races.
Let's see how actors compare
to other forms
of mutual exclusion.
Consider the earlier example
of updating the database
with some articles
by syncing to a serial queue.
If the queue is not
already running
we say that there
is no contention.
In this case, the calling thread
is reused to execute
the new work item on the queue
without any context switch.
Instead, if the serial queue
is already running
the queue is said
to be under contention.
In this situation,
the calling thread is blocked.
This blocking behavior is what
triggered thread explosion
as Rokhini described
earlier in the talk.
Locks have this same behavior.
Because of the problems
associated with blocking,
we have generally advised
that you prefer
using dispatch async.
The primary benefit of dispatch
async is that it is nonblocking.
So even under contention,
it will not lead
to thread explosion.
The downside of using dispatch
async with a serial queue
is that when
there is no contention
Dispatch needs to request
a new thread
to do the async work
while the calling thread
continues to do something else.
Hence, frequent use
of dispatch async can lead
to excess thread wakeups
and context switches.
This brings us to actors.
Swift's actors combine
the best of both worlds
by taking advantage
of the cooperative thread pool
for efficient scheduling.
When you call a method
on an actor that is not running,
the calling thread can be reused
to execute the method call.
In the case where the called
actor is already running,
the calling thread can suspend
the function it is executing
and pick up other work.
Let's look at how
these two properties
work in the context
of the example news app.
Let's focus on the database
and networking subsystems.
When updating the application
to use Swift concurrency,
the serial queue
for the database
would be replaced
by a database actor.
The concurrent queue
for networking
could be replaced by one actor
for each news feed.
For simplicity, I've only shown
three feed actors here --
for the sports feed,
the weather feed
and the health feed --
but in practice,
there will be many more.
These actors would run on
the cooperative thread pool.
The feed actors interact
with the database
to save articles
and perform other actions.
This interaction involves
execution switching
from one actor to another.
We call this process
actor hopping.
Let's discuss
how actor hopping works.
Suppose that the actor
for the sports feed
is running on a thread
from the cooperative pool,
and it decides to save
some articles into the database.
For now, let's consider that
the database is not being used.
This is the uncontended case.
The thread can directly hop
from the sports feed actor
to the database actor.
There are two things
to notice here.
First, the thread did not block
while hopping actors.
Second, hopping did not
require a different thread;
the runtime can directly suspend
the work item
for the sports feed actor
and create a new work item
for the database actor.
Say the database actor
runs for a while
but it has not completed
the first work item.
At this moment, suppose
that the weather feed actor
tries to save some articles
in the database.
This creates a new work item
for the database actor.
An actor ensures safety by
guaranteeing mutual exclusion;
at most, one work item
may be active at a given time.
Since there is already
one active work item, D1,
the new work item, D2,
will be kept pending.
Actors are also nonblocking.
In this situation, the weather
feed actor will be suspended
and the thread it was
executing on is now freed up
to do other work.
After a little while,
the initial database request
is completed,
so the active work item for
the database actor is removed.
At this point, the runtime
may choose to start executing
the pending work item
for the database actor.
Or it may choose to resume
one of the feed actors.
Or it could do some other work
on the freed-up thread.
When there is a lot
of asynchronous work,
and especially
a lot of contention,
the system needs
to make trade-offs
based on what work
is more important.
Ideally, high-priority work
such as that
involving user interaction,
would take precedence
over background work,
such as saving backups.
Actors are designed to allow the
system to prioritize work well
due to the notion of reentrancy.
But to understand why reentrancy
is important here,
let's first take a look
at how GCD handles priorities.
Consider the original
news application
with the serial database queue.
Suppose the database receives
some high-priority work,
such as for fetching
the latest data
to update the UI.
It also receives
low-priority work,
such as for backing up
the database to iCloud.
This needs to be done
at some point,
but not necessarily immediately.
As the code runs,
new work items are created
and added to the database queue
in some interleaved order.
Dispatch queues
execute the items received
in a strict first-in,
first-out order.
Unfortunately, this means that
after item A has executed
five low-priority items
need to execute
before getting to the next
high-priority item.
This is called
a priority inversion.
Serial queues work around
priority inversion
by boosting the priority
of all of the work in the queue
that's ahead
of the high-priority work.
In practice, this means
that the work in the queue
will be done sooner.
However, it does not resolve
the main issue,
which is that items 1 through 5
still needed to complete
before item B
could start executing.
Solving this issue requires
changing the semantic model
away from strict
first-in, first-out.
This brings us
to actor reentrancy.
Let's explore how reentrancy
is connected to ordering
with an example.
Consider the database actor
executing on a thread.
Suppose that it is suspended,
awaiting some work,
and the sports feed actor
starts executing on that thread.
Suppose after a while,
the sports feed actor
calls the database actor
to save some articles.
Since the database actor
is uncontended,
the thread can hop
to the database actor
even though it has
one pending work item.
To perform the save operation,
a new work item will be created
for the database actor.
This is what actor
reentrancy means;
new work items on an actor
can make progress
while one or more older
work items on it are suspended.
The actor still maintains
mutual exclusion:
at most one work item can be
executing at a given time.
After some time,
item D2 will finish executing.
Notice that D2 finished
executing before D1,
even though it was created
after D1.
Hence, support for actor
reentrancy means
that actors can execute
items in an order
that is not strictly
first-in, first-out.
Let's revisit the example
from before
but with a database actor
instead of a serial queue.
First, work item A will execute,
as it has high priority.
Once that's done,
there is the same priority
inversion as before.
Since actors are designed
for reentrancy,
the runtime may choose
to move the higher-priority item
to the front of the queue,
ahead of the
lower-priority items.
This way, higher-priority work
could be executed first,
with lower-priority work
following later.
This directly addresses the
problem of priority inversion,
allowing for more
effective scheduling
and resource utilization.
I've talked a bit
about how actors
using the cooperative pool
are designed to maintain
mutual exclusion
and support effective
prioritization of work.
There is another kind of actor,
the main actor,
and its characteristics
are somewhat different
since it abstracts over an
existing notion in the system:
the main thread.
Consider the example
news app using actors.
When updating
the user interface,
you will need to make calls
to and from MainActor.
Since the main thread
is disjoint from the threads
in the cooperative pool,
this requires a context switch.
Let's look at
the performance implications
of this with a code example.
Consider the following code
where we have a function
updateArticles on MainActor,
which loads articles
out of the database
and updates the UI
for each article.
Each iteration of the loop
requires at least two
context switches:
one to hop from the main actor
to the database actor
and one to hop back.
Let's see how the CPU usage
for such a loop would look like.
Since each loop iteration
requires two context switches,
there is a repeating pattern
where two threads
run one after another
for a short span of time.
If the number of loop
iterations is low,
and substantial work
is being done in each iteration,
that is probably all right.
However,
if execution hops on and off
the main actor frequently,
the overhead of switching
threads can start to add up.
If your application spends
a large fraction of time
in context switching,
you should restructure your code
so that work for the main actor
is batched up.
You can batch work by pushing
the loop into the loadArticles
and updateUI method calls,
making sure they process arrays
instead of one value at a time.
Batching up work reduces
the number of context switches.
While hopping between actors
on the cooperative pool is fast,
you still need to be mindful of
hops to and from the main actor
when writing your app.
Looking back, in this talk
you've learned how we've worked
on making the system
the most efficient it can be,
from the design of the
cooperative thread pool --
the mechanism
for nonblocking suspension --
to how actors are implemented.
At each step, we're using some
aspect of the runtime contract
to improve the performance
of your applications.
We are excited
to see how you use
these incredible new language
features to write clear,
efficient, and delightful
Swift code.
Thank you for watching
and have a great WWDC.
♪