Your daily recap at WWDC
starts in...
three... two... one...
Go!
♪ "Better Days (Instrumental)"
by DARKMINDS ♪
We found out how to easily
extract document data
with the Vision framework.
- So I created a little app
in which I can now scan
our survey cards.
- And we learned how to design
for spatial interaction.
Then app creator Dan Harris,
and his book coauthor,
Jeff Warren,
shared stories and meditation
techniques for fidgety skeptics.
- We've been doing a lot
of talking about meditation.
I do think it would make sense
to just take a quick break
and do five minutes!
You game for that, Jeff?
- Oh, yes I am.
- Oh, and we also learned
about the importance
of protecting
people's privacy online.
- We recognize the importance
of providing a more private way
to measure ads.
- And a big congratulations
to the winners
of the Apple Design Awards.
Your apps and games
are just...
>> [ROARING] <<
Exactly.
Tomorrow will be
the last day at Dub Dub.
Check it out.
♪
So many colors!
Bye-bye!
♪