[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Dean] So our goals
have always been
to build great accessibility
into all of our products
because many of us
navigate our lives
in different ways.
[Chris] At Apple,
we like to think
of accessibility touching four
different broad categories--
vision, cognitive,
motor, and hearing.
And we look
at all those segments
and try to think about
how they impact each product.
Are we doing something
in this area
where we should have
a different accommodation?
Do we have something
that we need
a special assistive technology
to provide a different way
to interact with this device?
How do we make
the whole world accessible?
[Jennifer] Every day,
we're thinking
about accessibility.
We care because they push
the boundaries
of the experience
in a way that we can't imagine.
[Ryan]
If you can create
not just a good
accessibility experience,
but a great
you'll have a fan for life.
[Chris] The Watch is a unique
kind of computing platform.
It's very personal.
It touches your skin.
It also has a long history
of what its use is for,
and what its functions are.
To make it something accessible,
you really wanna look at--
what is the product
supposed to do?
What is its core mission
of what this
is gonna bring value for?
So when you look
at that for the Watch,
that's when we start to realize,
like, all right, how do we make
this more accessible
for someone who's blind?
What do we do for someone
who's low-vision?
[Ryan] And how do we do it
on a CPU
the size of a postage stamp?
[Dean] Apple developed
this product,
and the primary focus was
to be able to read the time,
and so the contrast
with the black background
with the legible letters
was very important.
Well, it turns out
that was also important
for low-vision users,
and it's great for the person
who needs that accessibility,
but it also turns out
to be useful for everyone else.
[Chris] So one
of the great things
about making a product
accessible by design
is that you do things
that you may not think
are necessary,
and I'm reminded of a story
of a woman that I met
who had Usher syndrome.
So she came to us and said,
"You know, what's really great
about the Watch
is that I can read the email
on this really small screen
because all my vision
is focused in this central area.
It's actually better than
having a big screen."
When you sort of invest
in accessibility,
you have to look at things
from a different perspective,
and so that often leads
to features
that become mainstream
over time,
and I think the Apple Watch
is a great example
of showing
a lot of those things,
from the large-type watch face
which was designed
for low-vision users but it's
available for everybody.
Part of the thing about
making the Watch accessible
is what is the primary function?
One of those things
was telling the time quickly,
and sometimes discreetly,
so that's where Taptic Time
came into play,
which is a feature
that we have that allows a user
to feel out the time
using the haptics
played back to them.
[Dean] When we were testing,
one of the things
that I noticed right away
sort of walking around
and using the device,
if I was mobile,
I had to take one hand
off of my cane,
stop,
and then touch my device.
And I thought, "Well, that could
be very dangerous, right?"
So one of the things
I thought is, "Man,
it would be really great
if I could
-just raise my hand..."
-[watch] 1:04 p.m.
- And hear the time,
and then I don't have
to stop or jeopardize my safety.
[watch] 1:09 p.m.
[Dean] That's a very, very
simple solution,
but it solves
a very, very important problem.
[Chris] But we've learned that
there's more to accessibility
than pure technology solutions.
[Ryan]
So the Mickey Mouse watch face,
when it was introduced, I think
it really surprised everybody,
especially because it
even had some
really neat little features
like Mickey's tapping his foot,
but to a low-vision
or blind audience,
if I touched the watch,
all I would get
is a description,
or maybe, perhaps, the time
spoken by
the same text-to-speech
I hear everywhere else
on the watch face,
and that's just not good enough.
[Chris] I remember
I was in a presentation,
and I was sitting
in the back row behind someone,
and they were talking about
the Mickey Mouse watch face,
and I heard a woman
in front of me say,
"Oh, I just really wish
I could hear Mickey speak."
And I turned to the engineer
who was there with me.
I said, "We gotta do something
about this."
[Mickey]
It's 9:41.
[laughs]
[Chris] And we started to look
into this.
Why can't we just ask Disney
to work with us
to make some of these voices?
[Ryan] Disney actually said,
"Yeah, let's work on this."
Well, not only was it going
to be recorded in English,
but it was going to be recorded
in more than 30 languages.
[Mickey]
Buongiorno!
- [Speaking
non-English language]
- [Speaking non-English
language]
- The feedback after we
demonstrated our prototype,
it wasn't about
is this going to be
a great accessibility feature?
What we actually got was
"Can everybody have this?"
[Laughs]
Wow, okay!
[Chris] But the hardest question
was figuring out
how often should Mickey laugh?
[Mickey laughs]
- One.
One is just not enough.
[Mickey laughs]
[Ryan] Three is not enough.
No, we need all the laughs.
[Mickey laughs]
[Chris] But for
a sighted user using it,
they may not want
to hear that as much,
so we ended
with two different standards.
[Ryan] When VoiceOver is on,
Mickey laughs more often.
When VoiceOver is not on,
Mickey doesn't laugh
quite as much.
[Chris] I remember reading
to my kids at night,
and they would reach over
and just tap
on the Mickey watch face
over and over again
to hear him speak.
And those are really fun times.
To work on something
that, you know,
is for one community,
but it's so cool
that it ends up
affecting everybody.
[Ryan] It's about bringing
to light for a character
that people have loved
for nearly a century.
[Mickey laughs]
[Chris] So one of the--
you know,
the jobs of being a developer,
and especially in accessibility,
is to know the landscape
of the technology
so that you can use
these things
and solve the problems
in new, unique ways.
So oftentimes we hear
these stories that people say
they love their Watch,
but it can be awkward to use,
and that's because
I don't have an arm
or another hand
to touch the watch with.
[Jennifer] When we started
trying to meet this need
for our users, we thought,
"Well, we have
this very smart Watch,
and it's on your wrist.
So could we create
a completely gesture-based
human-to-computer interaction?"
And we started off
with these more--
more sort of,
like, gross gestures.
Lift your arm.
Twist your wrist.
And we quickly learned
that we needed the gesture
that would expend
the least amount of energy,
and we started
with just this pinch gesture,
which is pretty low impact.
[Chris] And so we started
to play around and say,
"Well, there's some signal here.
What if we combine
the accelerometer,
the gyroscope,
and some of those health sensors
that detect heart rate,
and use that to detect
subtle muscle movements
in your arm?
Combine that together,
put it into
a machine-learning model
to distinguish just these sort of
very minute differences,
and see
what we got out of that."
- We have a colleague
who has low muscle tone
in his arms,
and so, he was instrumental
in testing and really
narrowing down the gestures.
So we discovered
that we can use,
for simple gestures,
pinch, double pinch, clench,
and double clench
for complete access
to the Apple Watch.
[soaring orchestral music]
♪ ♪
[person]
Hey, I can't talk right now.
[Chris] I mean,
this is the kind of stuff
that you couldn't even imagine
a few years ago.
I mean, we're talking about
real sci-fi kind of things
right now.
[Jennifer] Apple Watch
is uniquely suited
to really meet
this need for our users.
The interface itself is designed
for focused interactions.
We worked really closely
with our font designers
to add a glyph language
to SF Symbols
that basically represents
all of the hardware
and software inputs
of the Apple Watch.
Then, you have an accelerometer.
We can detect your blood flow.
You have a gyroscope.
So all of these sensors
on the Watch allow us
to detect even these
very minuscule gestures.
I can't wait to hear
how this feature
is a game-changer for people.
I can't wait to see
what developers
are going to do
with this new technology.
[Ryan] So accessibility
is incredibly important
because it creates equity
for the world.
It allows people
to be independent,
to have a sense
of control over their life,
their environment,
things they would like to do,
passions they have.
[Chris] Accessibility is really
about allowing more people
to use your thing,
that we're gonna make room
that everybody can use it
to the best of their abilities.
So why wouldn't you want
more people to use your product?
Why wouldn't you want to make it
better for everyone?
To me, that sort of gets
to the heart of why we get
into this from the beginning.
Why do we love programming
so much and developing so much?
It's so people
can use our stuff.
[Dean] I wish developers
knew that doing accessibility
within their apps
really provides a warm,
comforting feeling for users.
It's unexplainable.
You work really hard
on something, on an idea,
on a concept, and then
you see it come into place,
and then, even better, you see
how it impacts someone's life.
And there's just no
feeling like that.
You just feel like the world
is great again
because you've solved
the problem.
[upbeat music]