[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Alejandro Lucena:
Hello, everyone.
Thank you for attending
this session on symbolication.
While symbolication may
seem like a vague term,
we'll see the instrumental role
it plays in helping you
to quickly identify
the root causes of bugs,
crashes, and performance
bottlenecks.
We'll gain a deeper intuition
as to how symbolication works
and cover several tools
that you have at your disposal
to follow along firsthand.
Along the way,
we'll discuss
the various sources
of debug information
that are necessary for a rich
symbolication experience
and how you can
configure your app
to best utilize
this information.
Let's get started
by familiarizing ourselves
with a concrete definition
and example of symbolication.
Fundamentally,
symbolication is a mechanism
to convert or translate
how our devices
see our apps at runtime —
which is in terms of memory
addresses and instructions —
back to how we as developers
see our apps —
which is in terms of functions,
names, and files.
Without this bridging layer,
it vastly complicates
diagnosing a bug
even for a few lines of code.
As an example,
let's consider this Swift code.
Here I have a function,
`generateMagicNumber()`,
that selects
a particular number
from a list
of candidate numbers.
To do this, we first call into
`numberChoices()`
that returns an array of 10
randomly generated numbers.
Then, we pass that array
into `selectMagicNumber(choices:)`,
which returns the number
at a particular index.
This seems like
a reasonable program,
but I encounter a crash
when I first run it.
My first recourse
is to check the crash log,
which is rather unfruitful.
All I can tell from
the thread backtrace
is that my MagicNumbers app
crashed somewhere.
Thanks,
but I already knew that.
I have no idea
what any of the registers
are referring to either.
I can try to step through
the app with the debugger
and identify the crash,
but what if this only happens
in particular circumstances
that I can't reproduce?
Using the debugger
won't necessarily pinpoint
the problem for me
in that case.
Or I can try to look
at the disassembly,
but it's much more difficult
to keep track of things.
This clearly isn't a viable way
to diagnose the problem,
and more importantly,
with the help of symbolication,
we don't have to debug
from this starting point.
The Xcode Organizer tells me
I can download the dSYM
for this app, which will
reprocess the crash log.
In doing so, Xcode applies
the concepts of symbolication
so that I can diagnose the issue
with a much nicer crash log,
where I can not only see
all of my functions
actually being called,
but I can also determine
the file and line number
to refer back to in my code.
This updated crash log
also tells me that we tried
to access an index
out of range.
Alternatively, If I already have
the dSYM,
I can use the `atos` command
to get the same information.
Looking back at my code,
I come to realize
that `MAGIC_CHOICE`
is far outside the bounds
of our 10-element array.
Oops.
In another instance, I'm
interested in profiling my app
to deliver the fastest
user experience.
Here, Instruments shows me
that the app cycles through
periods of high utilization
and low utilization.
If we focus on a period
of low utilization,
Instruments tells us
that the app
was writing some content
to a file.
However, when I inspect
a period of high utilization,
I get the same exact backtrace.
How is this possible?
Isn't this executing
the same exact code?
As we'll see,
this Instruments trace
is only partially symbolicated.
For instance,
I don't see any file names
or line numbers
in the backtrace
as I did with
the updated crash log.
As a result,
it's missing some information.
With that in mind,
I can similarly locate
my dSYM in Instruments.
After doing this,
my new Instruments trace
shows that
the high-utilization regions
were indeed writing to a file,
but they were specifically
within a debug code path
that I left in the program.
The low-utilization areas
avoid this
and represent how my app
behaves in production.
Just as Xcode utilized the dSYM
to symbolicate
a rather uninformative
crash log,
Instruments also used the dSYM
to enrich a partially
symbolicated trace
and tell me the exact cause
of the performance issue.
Now, while it's great that these
tools leverage symbolication
to pinpoint problem areas
in my code,
it naturally begs
a few questions.
How does this all work?
Where else can I apply this?
And is this all about dSYMs?
To answer these questions
and unlock symbolication's
capabilities,
we'll need to take a deeper dive
into the details.
This may seem
a little overwhelming,
but these are important concepts
to understand.
There are many tools to aid
in debugging and profiling
that build upon symbolication.
`atos` alone already gave us
the exact root cause of a crash,
and there are many more tools
built into Xcode.
Further, we specified flags
like `o`, `l`, and `i` to `atos`,
but what do they mean?
Do we always use
the same set of flags?
What if we don't have
one of the values available?
You'll also gain
a good foundation
in understanding when and why
your backtraces
may not be fully symbolicated
and how to fix that,
as we saw
in the Instruments case.
Lastly, there are a number
of build settings
that you're in control of
that influence the richness
of symbolication.
We'll go through
these build settings
so you have a solid intuition
about how they're utilized.
To that end,
I'd like to introduce
the two-step process
for symbolication.
Step number one
is going back to the file,
and step number two is
to consult debug information.
As we'll see,
going back to the file
is all about converting
or translating
runtime memory addresses
into a more stable, usable form.
This allows us to communicate
with our debug information
to make a meaningful connection
between a raw memory address
and the source code.
Let's start off by discussing
step number one,
going back to the file.
The ultimate goal in this step
is to translate
a runtime memory address,
such as those we saw
in the original crash log,
to a corresponding address
in your binary on disk.
Just like we have
runtime addresses,
your apps and frameworks
have an address space
on disk, too!
The on disk address space
differs from the address space
that your app occupies
at runtime,
and we need a mechanism
to figure out those differences.
First, we should understand
exactly what
the on disk addresses are.
These addresses
are assigned by the linker
when you build your app.
Specifically, the linker groups
your binary into segments.
Each segment contains
related data and has properties
such as a name, a size,
and their assigned
addresses.
For example, the `__TEXT`
segment of your binary
contains all of the functions
and methods you've written,
and the `__DATA` segment
contains program-wide state
such as global variables.
Each of these segments gets
assigned a different address
such that they don't overlap.
The linker records
this information
at the very beginning
of your executables
as part of the Mach-O header.
Mach-O is the format used
for all executable binaries
and libraries,
and the system knows that
it needs to read this header
to run your apps.
Looking a little more closely,
the Mach-O header contains
a number of load commands
that hold the segment
properties.
The system uses
these load commands
to load the segments
into memory.
Note that if your apps
are Universal 2,
then the app will have
one header
and a set of segments
for each architecture.
We can see for ourselves
by using the `otool -l` command,
which prints the load commands
for a specified file.
Here, we're looking
a segment load command
identified with `LC_SEGMENT_64`.
This load commands says
that the `__TEXT` segment
starts at the address in `vmaddr`
and is `vmsize` bytes long.
So if the kernel follows
these load commands
to load the segments
into memory,
what exactly
is the difference
between the runtime
and the linker addresses?
Well, before the kernel
actually loads the segments,
it initializes a random value
known as the ASLR slide.
The kernel then
adds the ASLR slide
to the addresses
in the load commands.
So rather than loading
the `__TEXT` segment at address A
and the `__DATA` segment
at address B,
the kernel instead loads them
to A+S and B+S,
where S is the ASLR slide.
Since A+S and B+S are the true
addresses that the system uses,
they're also known
as load addresses.
With that in mind, we now know
that the difference between
a runtime address
and the linker address
is the ASLR slide.
We can calculate the ASLR slide
with the following equation:
S = L-A,
where S is the ASLR slide,
L is the load address,
and A is the linker address.
We'll see examples
of this equation shortly,
but the key point is that
we can always go back
to the file address space
once we know the ASLR slide.
The ASLR slide equation
required two addresses —
the load address
and the linker address —
so where do we get them from?
We already saw how we can
query the load commands
to know the linker address
using `otool`.
To know the runtime address,
the system queries your app
either at the point of a crash
or as its being profiled
by Instruments
for its runtime address space.
This information is reflected
in the Binary Images list
in your crash logs.
You can also see
the load addresses interactively
with the `vmmap` tool,
which enumerates the active
memory regions in your program.
Let's compute the ASLR
slide value ourselves
from the original crash log.
In the Binary Images list,
I have the load address
of the `__TEXT` segment.
I also have the linker address
for the binary on disk
when I looked
at the load commands.
Subtracting these two yields
an ASLR slide value
of 0x45c000.
This means that every address
in my program's
runtime `__TEXT` segment
is 0x45c000 bytes away from the
linker `__TEXT` segment address.
So to see what a backtrace
address from the crash log
corresponds to in the file,
I can subtract 0x45c000
from it
to get the address on disk.
Since this address is now part
of the on-disk address space,
I can inspect my app
to see what resides there.
The crash log tells me
that a thread crashed
while executing
whatever is at this address,
so we can use `otool` again to see
the problematic instruction.
This time, I specified
the `-tV` flags to `otool`,
which will print
the disassembly.
Notice that I'm also specifying
the architecture as arm64.
This is so that otool knows
which Mach-O header
and segments to consider
since the app
is built as Universal 2.
The output of `otool` reveals
a `brk` instruction
at the address.
`brk` signals an exception
or a problem in the app.
Tools such as `atos` also
calculate the ASLR slide
using the same technique
we went through together.
`atos` will read
the load commands for the file
indicated by the `-o` flag,
and we tell it about
the load address
with the `-l` flag.
As I mentioned,
`vmmap` can also tell us
about the load addresses
of a running app.
Let's try
this calculation again,
but this time we'll use `vmmap`
instead of the binary image list
to determine the ASLR slide.
I ran the MagicNumbers
program again
and got the `__TEXT` segment
load address
before the program crashed.
Using the previous formula,
I can determine that this time
the ASLR slide value
was 0x104d14000.
Again, to go back to the file,
I need to subtract
the ASLR slide value.
If I subtract 0x104d14000
from the topmost entry
in the new crash log,
I get the same exact
file address as before.
And this is no coincidence;
the kernel just picked
a different ASLR value
so our load addresses changed
between the crash logs.
However, we can still determine
the file address
that was responsible
for the crash.
The important takeaway here
is that we have a mechanism
to understand exactly
what our app was doing
down to the instruction level,
regardless of
its runtime address.
And with that mapping,
we can then consult
our debug information
for the source code
that was compiled
to those instructions.
Before we move on,
I want to present a summary
of what we covered
and the tools we used.
App binaries and frameworks
are Mach-O files.
This means that
they have related content
in their different segments.
These segments
are created by the linker.
The Mach-O header
load commands
describe the properties of those
segments, including an address.
We used `otool` with the `-l` flag
to print out the load commands.
Next, we learned that the kernel
adds a random value,
known as the ASLR slide,
to the linker addresses.
The addition of the ASLR slide
and the linker address
is known as a load address.
We can check the binary image
list in a crash log
to see the load addresses
in the event of a crash,
or we can use `vmmap`
to see the load addresses
for a running app.
Finally, we walked through
some examples
of calculating the ASLR slide
to get back
to the file address space.
Now we can discuss
debug information,
which contains the crucial links
between the file addresses
and the source code.
Xcode creates
the debug information
when you build your app
and will either embed it
directly into your app binaries
or store it as a separate file,
such as a dSYM.
There are a few categories
or types of debug info.
Each one offers
a different level of detail
for a given file address.
We'll look at three different
types of debug info today.
First, we'll cover
the function starts,
which by itself doesn't add
too much value,
but it is a common
starting point.
Next we'll see
the nlist symbol tables,
which add function
and method names.
Lastly, we'll look at DWARF,
which comes from dSYMs
and static libraries.
DWARF adds the most detail,
including file names,
line numbers,
and optimization records.
Since DWARF
offers the most detail,
we really want to strive
to have this type of debug info
whenever possible.
We'll learn about each of these
and how they can be used
to build up the
fully symbolicated crash log.
Let's begin
with function starts.
As we saw in the table,
function starts offers
the least source code detail.
Also keeping true to its name,
this type of debug information
only tells us about
the first address —
or the literal start —
of our functions.
For example, this would
tell us that a function
begins and exists
at a certain address.
However, it doesn't tell us
which functions
begin at those addresses,
only that they exist.
The function starts debug info
does this by encoding
the list of addresses in your
app's `__LINKEDIT` segment.
Since this is embedded
directly in your app,
the Mach-O header
also has a load command
to inform us
where we can find it,
which is `LC_FUNCTION_STARTS`.
You can see these for yourself
with the `symbols` command
and the
`-onlyFuncStartsData` flag.
Here we get back a list of
addresses and null placeholders.
These placeholders
would ideally have
function and method names
instead of null,
but the function starts data
doesn't provide names.
Again, this isn't
the most descriptive data.
However, it does allow for a
slight update to the crash log.
We can now view
the file addresses
as offsets from a function.
For example,
first we go back to the file
by subtracting
the ASLR slide value.
Then we find
the function starts value
that could contain
the file address.
In this case,
only the first value
could contain the address
because all of the other values
are larger than the address.
Finally we can claim
that our file address
is actually 264 bytes
into this function.
This is primarily useful
for debuggers,
since they can understand
the details of how this function
was set up
and which registers
were modified.
What this means for you,
however,
is that if you ever
encounter a crash log
that lacks function names,
you're probably dealing with
this lowest level
of debug information.
This is good news
because it means there are
plenty of opportunities
to enrich the crash log
with better debug information.
Naturally, the next level
of detail we'd like to see
are function names.
This gives us
our first real opportunity
to take a crash log
or an Instruments trace
and use it to track down
an issue in our source code.
This leads us
to nlist symbol tables.
The symbol tables build on
the idea of function starts
and also encode
a list of information
in the `__LINKEDIT` segment, and
has its own load command too.
However, rather than just
encoding addresses,
they encode C structs.
This lets us add more details
for any given entry
compared to function starts.
Specifically, they encode
the `nlist_64` struct.
Here we have the definition
of that struct.
A cursory glance shows
that we have access
to a name
and several properties.
The values
of these struct fields
are determined
by the nlist's `n_type`.
There are three primary n_types
that we're interested in,
but for now we'll only
focus on two.
The first is known
as a direct symbol.
These are functions and methods
that you have fully defined
within your apps and frameworks.
Direct symbols have
a name and an address
in the `nlist_64` struct.
Additionally,
they're represented
by a particular bit pattern
in the `n_type` field.
Specifically, `n_type` will have
the second, third, and fourth
least significant bits set.
These bits are also known
as `N_SECT`.
We can see these
with `nm` and specifying
the `-defined-only`
and `--numeric-sort` flags.
Here, `nm` walked through
the defined symbols
of the MagicNumbers program
and listed them
in address order.
The names we get back
appear cryptic.
That's because the names
that are actually stored
in the symbol tables
are mangled names.
These mangled names
help the compiler and linker
to uniquely identify a function,
but they aren't
easy to understand
unless they're demangled.
To get a friendlier version
of these names,
I passed the output
to `swift-demangle`.
Now we get some familiar names,
such as `main` and `numberChoices`,
because they're directly
defined in my app.
Similarly, the `symbols` tool
has an option
to show the nlist data,
and it also demangles the names
automatically.
Now that we can associate
a function name to an address,
this lets us update
the crash log once again.
Here we can observe
that our offset expression
that we got
from the function starts data
also matches an entry
from the direct symbols,
and that entry has a name.
Putting these two together,
we can now say
that our crash happened
at 264 bytes into main.
This still leaves some details
to be desired,
since we know for a fact
that main isn't the only
function involved.
And it would also help to have
an exact line number too.
We encountered
something similar to this
in the Instruments trace
example —
we had some function names
available, but it missed others.
One reason for this
is that the symbol table
only has direct symbol entries
for functions that are
involved in linking.
These are functions
that you use across modules
or functions that you export
from your frameworks.
This makes it useful
for identifying API boundaries.
And it also means that
it has the necessary data
to power dynamic loading
with functions such as
`dlsym()` and `dladdr()`.
One downside though is that
local or static functions
aren't represented
in the symbol table
since they aren't referenced
outside of their module.
This ends up omitting
implementation functions
where we may have a significant
portion of the app logic.
Further, it's common for
binaries built in Release mode
to have their symbol table
stripped.
This means that
unnecessary entries
are removed
from the symbol table,
which helps reduce
the size of your app.
If we think about it,
it's rather uncommon
for our app's primary driver to
export functionality anywhere,
so we'd be wasting space
keeping those symbol table
entries around.
For our frameworks
and libraries,
we definitely have
exported functions
that clients should use,
but there's no need
to keep around
the locally shared functions
since they can't be used
anywhere else.
Stripping our primary app
executables will almost always
leave the symbol table
practically empty.
Stripping our frameworks
and libraries
leaves only the exported
functions.
You may have come across
build settings in Xcode
such as Strip Linked Product,
Strip Style,
and Strip Swift Symbols.
These build settings control
how your app is stripped
during the build.
If Strip Linked Product
is enabled,
then the binary is stripped
according to Strip Style.
For example,
All Symbols will perform
the most invasive removal
and leave behind
only the bare essentials.
Non Globals removes
direct symbols
that are used within
different modules of your app
but are not exported for use
in other apps.
Debugging Symbols removes
the third type of nlist type
that we'll discuss later
when we get to DWARF.
However, this strip style does
preserve the direct symbols.
For example,
here I have a framework
that defines
two public interfaces
and one internal shared
implementation function.
Since all of these functions
play a role in linking,
they all have
direct symbol entries.
If I strip non globals,
then I'm only left
with my interfaces.
The shared implementation
function was only used
within my framework,
so it isn't considered global.
Similarly, stripping all symbols
still leaves the interface
since these are required
for other apps
to use the framework.
You can also notice in the
`symbols --onlyNListData` output
that there are function starts
addresses
interspersed between
the direct symbols.
These addresses represent
functions that were either
never in the direct symbols,
or were stripped.
You can tailor
these strip settings
to your desired level
of symbol table visibility.
With this information,
we can determine
when we're working with
direct symbols.
Some telltale signs of this
are having function names
but no line numbers
or file names;
or having a mix
of function names
and function starts addresses,
as we have here
with the framework example.
The second type
of nlist struct we'll analyze
is known as
an indirect symbol,
as opposed to direct symbol.
This is when the `n_type` matches
only the `N_EXT` bit pattern.
These are functions
and methods that you're using
from other frameworks
or libraries, such as `print()`.
You can see these with `nm`,
only this time we'll specify
`--undefined-only` instead of `--defined-only`.
We'll also add the `-m` flag,
which will show you
which frameworks or libraries
the functions
should be found in.
For example,
the MagicNumbers app
depends on a variety
of Swift functions
that are defined
in libswiftCore.
Now that we've covered
two of the three
debug information categories,
let's make sure
we understand their properties.
Function starts
are a list of addresses,
so they lack names,
but do allow us
to determine offsets.
nlist symbol tables encode
entire structs of information
and can associate
a name to an address.
They describe direct symbols —
which are defined in your app —
and indirect symbols,
which are provided
by dependencies.
Direct symbols
are generally reserved
for functions involved
in linking,
and the strip build settings
influence
which direct symbols
are available.
Finally, both
the function starts
and the nlist symbol tables are
embedded directly in your app.
What we haven't seen yet
is the richer levels of detail,
such as file names
and line numbers.
This is provided to us by DWARF.
DWARF takes the concepts
of nlist symbol tables
to a completely different level.
Rather than keeping
only a subset of functions,
DWARF strives
to describe everything.
We saw that nlist symbol tables
added vastly more information
versus the function starts.
It accomplished that
by adding a dimension.
Remember, we started with
just a single dimension,
which were the addresses,
when we looked
at function starts.
Then we upgraded
to two dimensions
by encoding
a struct full of information
in the nlist symbol table.
DWARF adds
a third dimension,
which is about relationships.
DWARF recognizes that
functions aren't isolated.
They call other functions,
they have parameters,
return meaningful data, and are
defined in a particular file.
Encoding these relationships
unlocks the most powerful
aspects of symbolication.
When we're analyzing DWARF,
we're primarily referring
to a dSYM bundle.
In addition to other metadata
such as plists,
the dSYM bundle contains
a binary with DWARF.
What makes this binary
so special?
The binary contains its data
in a special `__DWARF` segment.
The DWARF specification
mentions three streams of data
within the segment
that we'll focus on.
`debug_info`
contains the raw data,
`debug_abbrev` assigns structure
to the data,
and `debug_line` contains the
file names and line numbers.
DWARF also defines
two vocabulary types
that we'll study first:
the compile unit
and the subprogram.
We'll introduce
a third one later.
A compile unit represents
a single source file
that went into
building the product.
For example, we can expect
to have one compile unit
for each Swift file
in our project.
DWARF assigns properties
to a compile unit,
such as the name of the file,
the SDKs,
the portion of the `__TEXT`
segment its functions occupy,
and much more.
The main.swift compile unit
contains these properties
in the `debug_info` stream
on the left,
and it has a corresponding entry
in the `debug _abbrev` stream
on the right which tells us what
the values represent.
Here we see the file name,
the language it's written in,
and a low/high pair representing
the `__TEXT` segment range.
A subprogram represents
a defined function.
We saw defined functions in the
nlist symbol table already,
but the subprogram can describe
static and local functions too.
A subprogram also has a name
and its `__TEXT` segment
address range.
One fundamental relationship
between compile units
and subprograms
is that subprograms
are defined in a compile unit.
DWARF represents this
with a tree.
The compile unit
is at the root of the tree
and it has subprogram entries
as children.
The children are searchable by
following their address ranges.
We can examine these
in more detail
with the `dwarfdump` command.
First we'll look
at a compile unit.
This matches
some of the properties
of a compile unit
I mentioned earlier.
`dwarfdump` helpfully combines
the `debug_ info`
and `debug _abbrev` contents
to show you
the structure and content
of the data in your dSYMs.
And if we scroll down
the output,
we'll encounter one
subprogram child.
The address range it occupies
is within the bounds
of the compile unit
and we can also see
the name of the function.
I mentioned that DWARF describes
its data in extreme detail.
While we won't spend much time
on all of these details,
I think it's fun to see details
such as function parameters.
They have their own
vocabulary type
that describes the name
and type of the parameter.
Following the tree model,
a parameter is a child
of a subprogram.
Here we come across the entry
for the choices parameter
that we supply to a function.
Next, file names
and line numbers
come from the `debug_line` stream.
This stream doesn't have
a tree structure.
Instead, it defines
a line table program
where the individual
file addresses
can be mapped back
to an exact line of code.
This ends up generating
a list of source code details
which we can search
to find the file and line.
If we parse the `debug_info` tree
and generate
the `debug_line` list,
we end up with
a structure like the following.
So if want to match
a file address,
we can traverse the tree.
First, we'll start
at the compile unit
and follow the branches.
Then we'll pick up any of the
`debug_line` entries that matched.
We can automate this again
with `atos`,
only this time I'm specifically
leaving out the `-i` flag.
Notice anything
slightly odd here?
Yes, we have the function name
and line number,
so we're definitely using DWARF.
Other than that though,
this isn't all too different
from the nlist
symbol table update.
In fact, when we compare it
to the first time we used `atos`,
it still looks like
we're missing
so many valuable
functions and details!
What happened here?
The only thing that changed
was that we didn't specify
the `-i` to `atos` this time.
That flag stands for
"inlined functions."
Inlining is a routine
optimization
that compilers perform.
This involves
substituting a function call
with the body of the function
directly.
One cool effect that it has is
making code seemingly disappear.
We can think of it as, rather
than calling `numberChoices()`,
the entirety of the code
for `numberChoices()`
was dropped in place.
Suddenly there's no function
call to `numberChoices()` anymore!
DWARF represents this
with an inlined subroutine.
This is the third and final
vocabulary type for DWARF
that we'll discuss today.
An inlined subroutine
is a subprogram —
so it's a function —
that was inlined
into another subprogram.
Since an inlined function
is completely engulfed
by another node
in the relationship tree,
the inlined subroutine
is a child of that node.
This definition applies
recursively too,
meaning that
an inlined subroutine
can have other inlined children.
Again, with `dwarfdump`,
we can look for
inlined subroutines.
They're listed as children
of other nodes
and have similar properties
to subprograms,
such as names and addresses.
However, in DWARF,
these properties
are frequently accessed
through a common node,
known as the abstract origin.
If there are many inlined copies
of a particular function,
then their common,
shared properties
are kept in the abstract origin
so that they aren't
duplicated everywhere.
One unique property that inlined
subroutines have is a call site.
This is the location
in our source code
where we wrote
the actual function call,
but the optimizer replaced it.
Here for instance, we made
the call to `generateANumber`
on line 36
of the main.swift file.
This lets us update our tree
with new child nodes.
And now this is looking like
a much more comprehensive view
of our program.
The optimization details
for inlined functions
were the key details
in getting us
to the fully symbolicated
crash log.
The `-i` flag for `atos`
instructs the tool
to consider them
during symbolication.
They were also
the missing details
from our Instruments trace.
The reason why
we needed a dSYM
both for Instruments
and for the crash log
was precisely so that we could
extract all of this content.
There is another source
where you'll find DWARF,
and that is from static
libraries and object files.
In the absence of a dSYM,
you can still gather DWARF
for functions that you linked
from a static library
or object file.
In those cases, you'll find the
Debugging Symbols nlist types.
These were one of the symbol
types that could be stripped.
They don't hold the DWARF
themselves though.
Rather, they associate
a function
back to the file they came from.
If the library was built
with debug information,
then the nlist entry
can point us to that DWARF.
These types of nlist entries
can be seen verbosely
with `dsymutil -dump-debug-map`.
Here we have the list
of different functions
and where they were
pulled from.
Those locations can be scanned
and processed for DWARF.
To summarize,
DWARF is a vital source
of in-depth symbolication data.
DWARF exposes
important relationships
between functions and files.
Optimizations such as
function inlining
have an enormous impact
on the quality of symbolication,
and DWARF can express it
very well.
We also saw that dSYMs and
static libraries contain DWARF.
However, please prefer dSYMs
as you can easily transfer them
to others and have built-in
support from several tools.
Finally, I want to share
different tools and tips
you can use
to facilitate symbolication.
For local development builds,
you'll generally have
a great deal
of debug information
if you build in debug mode.
For release mode, you can ensure
that Xcode generates a dSYM by
checking the Debug Information
Format build setting.
Make sure Release
is set to DWARF with dSYM File.
For apps that were submitted
to the App Store,
you can download your dSYMs
through App Store Connect.
This also includes any apps
with bitcode enabled.
If you want to check that
a certain dSYM
is already on your device,
you can use the `mdfind` command.
The alphanumeric string
here is your binary's UUID,
which is a unique identifier
defined in a load command.
You can see the UUID for your
dSYMs with `symbols -uuid`.
Sometimes, a toolchain
could generate invalid DWARF.
You can check this
with `dwarfdump -verify`.
If you see any reported errors,
please file a bug!
DWARF data also has a cap
of four gigabytes per binary.
If you're running into issues
with your dSYMs
and see that they're exceeding
four gigabytes,
consider splitting the project
into separate components
so that each one
has its own smaller dSYM.
You can make sure
that the dSYM you're using
matches the specific build
of your app
that you're interested in
by comparing UUIDs.
The app's UUID is in
the Binary Images list
section of crash reports
and you can also see it
with the `symbols` command.
You should ensure that
both your app and your dSYM
have the same UUIDs.
The `symbols` tool
also lets you check
the types of debug information
your app has available.
We've already seen
examples of this,
but it's a helpful reminder that
these tags in square brackets
tell you the information source.
It's useful if you aren't sure
which debug information
you might be dealing with.
If you're certain that you
have dSYMs available
but still aren't getting names
for your functions
in Instruments traces,
please check your entitlements
and code signing.
Specifically,
with the `codesign` command,
you can verify that you have
a proper code signature.
You should also verify
that locally built apps
for development have
the `get-task-allow` entitlement.
This entitlement grants
permissions to tools
such as Instruments
to symbolicate your app.
Xcode should set this
entitlement automatically
with the Profile action,
but it's helpful to verify.
If you don't have
the `get-task-allow` entitlement
enabled,
you should check
your Code Signing Inject Base
Entitlements build setting
and make sure that it's enabled
as you're developing.
Lastly, for Universal 2 apps,
you should specify
the architecture
that you're interested in
to the tools.
`symbols`, `otool`, and `dwarfdump`
all have an `-arch` flag
to only operate on a particular
architecture slice.
This concludes "Symbolication:
Beyond the basics."
If nothing else,
I want to really emphasize
a few key points.
UUIDs and file addresses
are a consistent
and reliable way to identify
what your app was doing
since they're independent
of the ASLR slide.
They're also our key
to querying the debug info.
You should also use dSYMs
whenever possible.
dSYMs contain
the richest debug information
in the form of DWARF
and are supported
by Xcode and Instruments.
Lastly, we covered
several tools.
These tools are readily
available to you in Xcode
and they offer powerful
diagnostics and insights.
You should strive
to incorporate them
into your workflows
for debugging and optimizing.
If you're interested
in learning more,
I recommend these
two sessions from WWDC18
to learn how your apps spring
to life upon launch:
"Optimizing app startup time"
and "App startup time:
Past, present, and future".
Thank you all very much
for joining me
to learn about symbolication!
Have a wonderful
rest of the week.
♪