[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Xuerui] Hello, and welcome
to "Mitigate fraud
with App Attest
and DeviceCheck."
My name is Xuerui Yan,
and I work
on the App Store Trust
and Safety team.
I'm excited to talk
about protecting your apps
using App Attest
and DeviceCheck.
At Apple,
we're constantly working
to ensure
that the App Store
is a safe and trusted place
for customers and developers.
In this video, we will cover
the engineering specifics.
For business
and conceptual details,
see "Safeguard your accounts,
promotions, and content" video
from WWDC 2021.
In iOS 11, we introduced
the DeviceCheck framework.
DeviceCheck helps mitigate
fraud on promotional offerings.
Suppose you are introducing
a new feature in your app.
To promote the feature,
you offer a free, single-use item.
Someone might abuse
the promotion
by reinstalling the app
over and over again
just to claim the free item.
Likely, you'll want
to limit promotional items
to once per device,
instead of allowing the app
to be installed repeatedly
and having the promotion reused.
Now, DeviceCheck can
help you detect
whether a device has received
a promotion offer,
or if a device has participated
in fraudulent activity.
It allows you to persistently
store two bits of information
and a timestamp associated
with one device on Apple servers.
It is up to you to decide what these bits
mean to your applications.
The state will be
maintained by Apple
for you to update and query.
The bits are shared
by all apps from a developer.
Please keep that in mind when
assigning meanings to the bits
so they are applicable
across all your apps.
The state persists
across app reinstallation,
device transfer between users,
and even "Erase all contents
and settings."
Consider using the timestamp
to reset the bits
on a period of your choosing,
based on your promotional
and business strategies.
To find out more
about DeviceCheck,
see the "Privacy
and Your Apps" video
from WWDC 2017
and the DeviceCheck Framework
documentation.
So that's DeviceCheck.
Next, I'm going to talk
about App Attest,
also available under
the DeviceCheck Framework.
When your service
receives a request,
it can be hard to know whether
it really is from your app.
App Attest allows your app
to attach
a hardware-backed assertion
as a part of the request.
Your server can use assertion
to verify the request came
from your genuine app,
on a genuine Apple device.
Imagine, you designed
a beautiful app
that encourages travel
to discover collectibles,
only to find
that a modified app allowed
collecting everything
without ever leaving home.
Or imagine players' frustration
seeing others
racing up the leaderboards,
by using cheats to get
unlimited boosts
in a competitive multiplayer
racing game.
Or imagine waking up
on a Saturday
and, much to your delight,
seeing a very high
request volume on your server,
but after investigation,
you find the calls aren't
coming from your app at all.
App Attest can help you
identify genuine
and modified versions
of your app,
letting you protect your app
experience and your business.
App Attest provides three
key properties that you can
take advantage of to protect
you and your customers.
App Attest lets your service
verify a request came
from a legitimate instance
of your app
by satisfying three conditions:
the request came
from a genuine Apple device,
running your genuine application,
and that the payload
has not been tampered with.
Let's go through how
App Attest provides
each of these properties.
At the heart of App Attest
is a secure key pair
and an attestation,
signed by Apple,
certifying that
the key pair originates
from a genuine Apple device.
The private key is stored
and accessible
only through the Secure Enclave
using the App Attest API.
Your app can sign requests
to your service with the key,
and your service can then check
the signature to verify
the request was generated
on a genuine Apple device.
For an app to execute
on an Apple device,
it must be signed.
A person making unauthorized
modifications to your app
must re-sign it
with an identity they control.
This unavoidably modifies
the app identity.
We include a hash of the app
identity in the attestation.
By comparing your app identity
with the one included
in the attestation,
you can determine
whether the caller is using
a modified version.
Now that you know
the request came
from a genuine device
and your genuine app,
let's talk about
the request payload.
Before sending
a payload to your server,
you can instruct App Attest
to sign a digest
of the payload
using the attested key.
This creates an assertion
of the payload.
Your app should transmit
the payload
and the assertion
to your service.
By verifying the assertion
against the payload,
you can trust that the payload
was not tampered with in transit.
Those are three key properties.
Now let's talk a bit
about privacy.
Here at Apple,
we care deeply about privacy.
We believe that privacy is
an essential foundation
for a healthy app ecosystem.
Each element of App Attest has
been built with privacy in mind.
The attestations are designed
to provide assurance
of a genuine device,
while protecting
against tracking.
The attestations are anonymous
and include
no hardware identifiers.
App Attest keys are unique
per installation of your app.
This means that an App Attest
key will not survive
app reinstallation,
is not backed up,
and is not synced
across devices.
Keep this in mind
when designing your app.
Now that you understand
the value App Attest provides,
let's dive into the details
of incorporating it
into your app.
There are three basic parts
to incorporate
App Attest into your app.
Creating an App Attest key,
attesting and verifying the key,
and generating
and verifying assertions.
Let's start with creating
an App Attest Key.
All App Attest calls
should be guarded
by the isSupported property.
App Attest is supported
on devices
that have a Secure Enclave,
but there are cases,
such as App Extensions,
where isSupported will
still return false.
Your app must handle
these cases gracefully.
Instead of
immediately blocking access,
use failures as a risk signal.
First, classify
the caller as untrusted.
Then, based on your risk
assessment logic,
evaluate whether to allow
the client
to use sensitive features.
Another approach is to monitor
for a sudden increase in devices
claiming they don't
support App Attest
when calling your service.
If the ratio of devices
supporting App Attest
suddenly decreases, it may be a sign
of modified apps trying
to bypass your checks.
With an App Attest key
successfully generated,
let's go ahead
and attest the key.
To prevent man-in-the-middle
and replay attacks,
we need a one-time server challenge.
Let's have your server
issue the challenge to the app.
To link the attestation
with a user account ID
or other values,
hash those values together
with the challenge
to create the clientDataHash.
Using the clientDataHash,
along with the keyId
from the previous step,
we can now call attestKey API.
attestKey will use
the private key to create
a hardware attestation request
for the device,
and submit the request
to Apple for verification.
Once verified, Apple will return
an anonymous attestation object
to your app.
Send the attestation,
along with any custom payload,
back to your server for verification.
OK, now that your app
has sent the attestation
to your server,
let's try to verify it.
The attestation follows
the Web Authentication standard
and contains three parts:
a list of certificates
signed by Apple,
an Authenticator Data structure,
and a risk metric receipt.
Let's look at the important pieces
that you need to verify.
The certificate section
contains the leaf
and intermediate certificates.
The App Attest root certificate
is available
in the Apple Private PKI
repository.
Validating the full certificate chain
tells you the device is
a genuine Apple device.
When you called attestKey,
a single-use hash,
known as a nonce, was created
from the clientDataHash
and other data.
That nonce is included
in the leaf certificate.
To prevent tampering,
you'll reconstruct the nonce
on your server
and verify it matches.
The authenticator data block
contains multiple properties,
including a hash
of the app identity,
that you can use to verify
it is your app calling you.
The key attestation also
contains a receipt that you can
store and use later to request
a risk metric from Apple.
I will cover more information
about it later in the video.
If everything checks out,
the App Attest Key is genuine.
Store the key
associated with the client data
for use to verify
subsequent requests.
Not all failures are due
to an invalid attestation.
Gracefully handle scenarios,
such as isSupported returning false,
being throttled during ramp up,
or general network failures.
You can then
incorporate failures
as signals
in your overall risk assessment.
For further details
on implementing the verification,
please see the documentation.
Calling the attest-Key API
generates a network call
from your app
to App Attest service.
This only happens
once per app instance.
However, if you have
a large install base,
collectively, your app may send
many requests to App Attest.
In order to manage resources
and avoid being rate limited,
make sure you gradually enable
this feature
across your install base.
For example,
if you have
a million daily active users,
you can probably ramp up
over a day or so.
If you have a billion
daily active users, nice work!
You should ramp up
over a month or more.
Now that you have
the attested key, you can use
the generateAssertion
API call to protect
sensitive communication between
your app and your server.
The assertion flow
is simpler than attestation,
as the Apple servers
are no longer involved.
All assertions using
the key are generated
on-device
and validated on your server.
Start by requesting a unique
challenge from the server,
then generate a digest
of the payload
and call generateAssertion.
generateAssertion will use
the digest to compute
a nonce and sign it
with the App Attest key.
Your app can then
send the payload
and the assertion
to your server.
Finally, your server should
verify the payload.
Assertion payloads contains
this high-level structure.
Signature
and Authenticator Data.
To validate the signature,
reverse the process
to reconstruct the nonce
on your server.
Then use the public key
to verify the signature.
If the signature is valid,
you can trust
the payload is unmodified.
The authenticator data section
contains the app identity hash.
Validate the hash
to ensure the assertion
is from your genuine app.
The authenticator data
also includes
an ever-increasing counter.
To help protect
against replay attacks,
store the counter value
on your server,
and expect it to increase
with each subsequent request.
With the key,
you can now repeat this process
as much as you need.
While generating an assertion
doesn't call Apple servers,
it's a cryptographic operation,
which adds some latency.
You should factor this
into your design
when incorporating
App Attest into your app.
Assertions are
a good fit for important
but infrequent calls,
and the calls that can deal
with the additional latency
and the computation required.
For frequent
real-time network commands,
assertions may not be suitable.
Congratulations!
You have now completed the basic
implementation of App Attest.
With this implementation alone,
you can start classifying
your incoming server requests
as genuine and modified,
and incorporate
this important fraud signal
into your business logic.
But there's more.
An attacker may try
to work around App Attest
by using a single device
to create many App Attest keys,
and use that device
to serve communications
between many modified apps
and your server.
To help detect such behavior,
we offer a service
called the App Attest
Risk Metric Service
that provides
the approximate number of keys
created on a device
for your app.
Recall that attestKey
returns both
the attestation
and a risk metric receipt.
Your server can
submit that receipt
to the service and redeem it
for a new receipt.
The new receipt will
include the risk metric.
Periodically, you can redeem
your latest receipt
for updated metrics
for that app/device pair.
Here is a high-level view
of the receipt structure.
It is a PKCS7 container.
For full details,
see "Assessing Fraud Risk"
in the DeviceCheck Framework
documentation.
App Clips is
an exciting feature in iOS.
We've added App Attest support
to App Clips in iOS 15.
To support a seamless upgrade
from App Clip to full app,
the App Clip and full app
share the same app identity
in the App Attest context.
Make sure to keep this in mind
when you verify the app identity
on your server side.
When App Clips
are manually removed
or expire,
their keys will be invalidated,
just like when your full app
is uninstalled.
OK, that's it for App Clips.
Now, remember these key points
for success with App Attest.
Validate on server,
not on-device.
The app may be modified
to disable your validation code.
Incorporate a one-time
server challenge in your flow
to prevent
network replay attacks.
Handle failure scenarios,
such as isSupported
returning false,
being throttled during ramp up,
or general network failures.
Incorporate failures as signals
in your risk assessment.
App Attest and DeviceCheck
provide the information
that you can integrate into
your overall fraud assessment.
Use DeviceCheck to mitigate
fraud on promotional offerings.
Take advantage
of App Attest to help you
detect modified versions
of your app,
protecting your content
and your user experience.
Thanks for watching!
I'm looking forward
to seeing your apps
protected by App Attest
and DeviceCheck.
Peace!