[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Pierre de Filippis: Hi there.
My name is Pierre.
I’m a manager on our
Communication Applications team,
and I’ll later be joined
by my colleague Bhaskar.
It’s my pleasure to welcome you
to “Meet Group Activities.”
I think we can all recognize
that this past year,
finding ways to stay connected
has felt more essential
than ever.
This is incredibly important
to us at Apple,
and we wanted to give our users
meaningful new ways to connect.
As a result, in iOS 15,
we’re creating a new way
to enjoy activities together
that makes you feel
like you’re in the same room
as the people sharing with you.
And we call it "SharePlay."
SharePlay is powered by
the Group Activities framework,
and in this session,
we’re going to talk about
how you can adopt it
in your application.
Before we get into
some of those details,
let me tell you a bit more about
the key components of SharePlay.
Let’s start with communication.
We think dynamic
and natural communication
is a critically important part
of a meaningful
shared experience,
so we’ve built SharePlay right
into FaceTime and Messages.
We are continually blown away
by how central these apps
have become in people’s lives
and relationships,
especially over the last year.
And people don’t just use
FaceTime and Messages
to connect with that friend
from 30 years ago
once in a while.
Instead, our users spend
a significant amount of time
communicating with the people
that are closest to them;
their closest friends,
and their closest family.
Those are the kind of people
you would invite
into your living room
to watch a movie, for example,
and that’s exactly what we want
to facilitate with SharePlay.
Let me give you an idea
of how this works.
It all starts with the concept
of a session.
Before a group
starts an activity,
they need to join a session
so that everyone is together
and ready to share.
Once users are in a session,
they can communicate via text,
audio, and video in Messages
and FaceTime
just like they are used to.
Switching between these modes
of communication
is dynamic and fluid,
so they can easily choose
a way to communicate
that matches the moment.
We also give users
a consistent system-wide way
to manage their session.
Users can invite new people
on the fly
or leave the session entirely.
Once you are in a session,
users can navigate the entire
system and drop in on any app.
As a developer,
you get it at all for free
with Group Activities.
So that’s communication.
The next area we think is
critical is platform experience.
We want this experience
to be simple, consistent,
and available across our system
and devices.
With Group Activities,
we’re building
a unified experience
that works across iOS,
iPadOS, macOS,
where Group Activities
is available
even for your website
with WebKit.
It also works beautifully
on AppleTV,
so you can enjoy it
on the big screen.
All of your devices are aware
when you are in a session,
so you can join from any device,
and you can use
multiple devices seamlessly.
Finally, we also designed it
to deliver great audio
to Bluetooth devices,
including AirPods.
As part of platform experience,
we’re doing something special
for content playback.
While we’re hoping
you take full advantage
of the expressiveness of the API
to create many different types
of SharePlay activities,
we created some
really cool enhancements
that make shared media
experiences effortless to build.
The core of any media experience
is the play button;
it’s the moment
when your users decide
what content they want
to spend their time on.
Our goal is
for every play button
throughout the system
to work with SharePlay.
We want people to feel that
any piece of media in your app
is ready to kick off
a shared experience
whenever they’re on FaceTime
with their friends,
which is where you come in.
We’re offering new APIs
designed to fit right into
your existing code paths.
By adopting Group Activities,
your play buttons can now start
these shared media experiences
whenever a group conversation
is active.
And we’ll use smarts over time
to adapt to user behaviors,
making shared experiences
effortless.
Next is time-synced playback.
We think it’s super important
that people
are laughing together,
smiling together,
and reacting to content
all at the same time.
SharePlay handles
keeping playback time
synced at the platform level,
so you can simply adopt
and not have to worry about
rolling your own.
Now, this was
a challenging problem to solve
when it came to consuming
content with SharePlay.
We wanted to allow people
to experience
the exact same moments
with one another,
even if they were
halfway across the world.
Imagine seeing and hearing
your friends laugh at something
that hasn’t happened yet.
Spoiler alert!
So we built an entirely new
playback-sync protocol
with deep integration
into the AVFoundation stack
on the device.
That means someone hits play,
and everyone in the group
immediately starts playback
at the same time.
Jump to a favorite scene
and everyone else sees it too,
allowing people to experience
moments together
in perfect sync,
as if they were
in the same room.
The magic behind
this playback synchronization
means we won’t retransmit
your media in any way.
Everyone will get
your full-fidelity video
because it’s playing
right from your app
and streaming from your servers
as it always does.
And by ensuring that all viewers
are watching
the highest-quality video,
they’ll get an immersive
social-viewing experience
that never compromises
the quality of your content.
We’re also doing some
groundbreaking work
to make communication
feel natural during playback.
With smart volume,
when people speak up
during playback,
we’ll automatically duck
the audio of the content
and bring it back up
when appropriate.
So people can communicate
via voice, video,
and text naturally,
just like they would
if they were sitting
in the very same room.
And of course,
it works beautifully
with Picture in Picture,
so the user can take
your content along with them
as they multitask on the device.
So that’s a brief overview
of what we’re doing on platform.
And finally, content.
And that’s where you come in.
We want users to be able
to enjoy the very best content
that you've made available
in your apps.
When people are on
a FaceTime call,
they will expect to be able
to go into your app
and share your content.
SharePlay is going to allow you
to extend the touchpoints
of your product
and increase the times
where your app is relevant
to your users.
And this will happen
very organically.
Existing users will evangelize
for your app
as they are using SharePlay
with other people.
Now that I’ve given you
a brief overview
of some of the key components
of SharePlay,
let’s turn our attention
to Group Activities,
a core concept of the framework.
A Group Activity is an object
representing something
that can be shared and enjoyed
with the people in the FaceTime
call using SharePlay.
Let me walk you through
how a user would start
a Group Activity in your app.
While on a call,
users can navigate to your app,
and if you have adopted
Group Activities,
they will be notified
that the app supports SharePlay.
To configure the activity
you want to share,
you first need to create
an object
that implements the
GroupActivity protocol.
Once you’ve configured
your activity,
you call the
prepareForActivation API
to start sharing that activity.
This API will offer the user
the option
to share that activity with
everyone in the FaceTime call
or just keep it local.
If they decide to share
with the group,
Group Activities will notify you
and let you join
the GroupSession object.
Once users have joined
the Group Session,
their video will be kept in sync
with the group,
even when they play,
pause, or seek.
Whenever those events happen,
Group Activities will
automatically notify the user
as shown here.
And finally,
once users are done,
they can choose to end
the activity for themselves
or for the whole group.
It’s as simple as that!
Now, let me hand it over
to Bhaskar
who's going to walk you through
the rest of this presentation.
Bhaskar Sarma: Thank you,
Pierre.
Hi, my name is Bhaskar,
and I am an engineer
on the FaceTime team.
Now let’s talk about some
of the high-level concepts
and architecture
behind this new framework.
GroupActivities
is a Swift-native framework
that allows you to create
shared experiences
between users
of your application
when they are on
a FaceTime call.
Additionally, the framework
also has a tight integration
with AVFoundation,
which allows you
to easily create
shared video and audio
playback experiences.
Before we go over
the high-level concepts
behind the API,
I would like to talk about
two key parts of the API,
and these are the GroupActivity
and GroupSession.
GroupActivity
is what your app uses
to define the shared experience.
It holds the information
that your application needs
for the shared experience.
For example, if you are doing
a shared audio or video
playback experience,
it might hold the URL of the
content that is being played.
Or your application
might provide
a custom shared experience.
For example,
you could be providing
a draw-together experience.
In that case,
this would hold information
about what the users
are drawing.
GroupSession is basically
a representation of the group
taking part
in the shared experience.
It provides access to things
like the participants
in the group.
And there are additional APIs
in the framework
that you can use along
with the GroupSession
to send and receive data
across devices.
Please note the GroupSession
is not meant to exchange
large amounts of data.
For example, if you are creating
a shared listening experience,
the GroupSession is not used
to exchange the contents
of the song.
Instead, this channel is used
by AVFoundation
to keep content in sync
by exchanging the play,
pause, or seek commands.
Also, the communication medium
provided by GroupSession
is end-to-end encrypted.
This means no one
other than your application
on the device can read the data
that is exchanged
over this channel.
Here I have two phones
on the screen.
The one on the left is my phone,
and the one on the right
is my teammate Pierre’s phone.
And we are on a FaceTime call.
Also, we have
a sample application
called "Awesome App"
on the screen,
and the app is ready to start
a shared experience
between me and Pierre.
So in this case, the application
on the device on the left
is going to initiate
the activity.
The first thing the application
needs to do is create an object
that conforms
to the GroupActivity protocol.
In the example shown here,
it is the AwesomeActivity object
that conforms
to GroupActivity.
As I had mentioned earlier,
this object conforming
to the GroupActivity protocol
contains information
about the shared activity.
For example, if you are creating
a shared playback experience,
it will have information
about what content to play.
Or if you are creating
a custom experience --
like drawing something
together --
it will have information
about what to draw.
Once the app has created
an activity,
the next thing it needs to do
is call prepareForActivation
on the activity.
This causes the user to see
a prompt asking for permission
if they want to start
an activity.
We would like to take
user consent
before starting an activity
as we do not want to cause
surprise to them.
Hence, this step is essential.
And lastly, after the user
has granted permission
to start the activity,
your app needs to call activate
on the activity object.
This tells the system
that your app wants to start
a shared experience.
Next, let’s talk about
observing sessions.
Here we have the same app
that we were looking at earlier.
The application at this point
has called activate
on the activity object.
Your application then needs
to iterate
over incoming sessions
via an AsyncSequence
on the GroupSession class.
And then,
when there is a session,
the application gets handed
the GroupSession object
for the shared experience.
Please note that
this is the same step
your application would take
whether it was
the initiating app
or on the remote device
receiving the session.
To go into more details
about initiating
and observing group sessions,
I would recommend you watch
this WWDC session.
Now that the application
has been handed a session,
it needs to set itself up
before joining the session.
Setting up the application
before joining
could mean different things
based on the specific use case
of the application.
For example, if you are creating
a custom experience --
like drawing something
together --
this could mean loading up
the assets
needed for the shared experience
before your user
can join the experience.
However, if your application
is providing a shared
media-playback experience,
then it would involve
something like this.
Your application
will hook up the
AVPlaybackCoordinator
of your AVPlayer
to the GroupSession
so that its associated AVPlayer
can sync content
over the communication channel
provided by the framework.
Keep in mind,
this syncing support
is not just limited to AVPlayer,
but you can use any other
custom video player
you have today
and still get support
for syncing
via an AVDelegating
PlaybackCoordinator.
And finally, once you are done
setting up your application,
your application calls join
on the GroupSession.
Once join is called,
the system sets up
the end-to-end encrypted
channels between the apps
running across
different devices.
At this point, your application
is ready to sync data
and let your users take part
in the shared experience.
If you're creating
a custom experience,
your application can use
this channel to exchange data
to keep your users in sync.
This channel is also used
by AVFoundation
to keep media playback in sync
by exchanging playback state
when the user hits play, pause,
skip, et cetera.
Note that this channel
is not meant to be used
to exchange
large amounts of data.
Instead, use it to exchange
information
to keep your users in sync.
Now your application
is in a session,
and your users are enjoying
the shared experience.
There is one more thing
you can do
to enrich the experience
for your users,
and that is post events
using the framework.
Events allow your users to know
what is going on
in the shared experience.
For example, you can post events
to let your users know
when someone plays, pauses,
or skips a track.
Posting an event causes
the system to present a notice
telling your users
about the event.
In our current API,
we only let you post events
for media playback experiences.
You get this for free
if you use an AVPlayer
or use an AVDelegating
PlaybackCoordinator.
However, if you are not using
either of these,
your app can still post events
using the framework.
To learn more about providing
your own custom experience
and about posting events,
I would recommend you watch
this WWDC session.
So to wrap up,
Group Activities is a brand new
Swift-native framework
that allows you to create
shared experiences
over FaceTime.
The framework is cross-platform
and is available
on iOS, macOS, iPadOS,
and tvOS.
It has tight integration
with AVFoundation
that allows your app to provide
shared media playback
experiences.
And finally, it also has support
for playback syncing
over the web on macOS.
And with that,
I would like to thank you
for watching our session.
And have a wonderful WWDC21!
♪