[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Jeff Nadeau: Hi, and welcome
to "What's new in AppKit."
I'm Jeff Nadeau.
I work on AppKit,
and I've got some great updates
to share with you.
macOS Monterey includes
some great new features
and enhancements for Mac apps.
There's really something
for everyone in this release,
including updates
to our user interface design,
enhancements to many
of our controls,
a big update to SF Symbols,
an all-new text engine
called TextKit 2,
powerful new
Swift language features,
and automation with Shortcuts,
which is now available
on the Mac.
Let's dive right in,
starting with some updates
on the design of
the macOS user interface.
We're thrilled by the response
to the system-wide redesign
that debuted in macOS Big Sur.
So many of our favorite apps
have updated
to adopt the new design
in only a few short months.
In macOS Monterey,
we've continued to iterate
and refine this new design,
so you'll notice a few new
touches across the system.
Some of them
are big and noticeable,
like popovers that now
appear and recede
with a brand-new animation,
or sliders that now
smoothly glide into position
when you click them.
There are also
much more subtle changes,
like refined metrics
in toolbar controls,
and spring-loading support
on the Search button,
so it's easy to drag in
text and tokens.
And increased spacing
between table sections
to improve clarity.
We've continued to iterate
and enhance the new design
down to the smallest details.
And that leads me
to some control enhancements
that you can use
to refine your own designs.
The first big one
is control tinting.
We've enabled custom tinting
of individual buttons,
segmented controls, and sliders.
Each of these controls accepts
a custom tint color
using one of these APIs:
bezelColor,
selectedSegmentColor,
and trackFillColor.
We introduced these APIs
in macOS Sierra
to allow tinting of individual
controls in the Touch Bar.
And starting in macOS Monterey,
they're functional
for in-window controls as well.
To recap, most controls draw
using the accent color,
which is configurable
in System Preferences.
This allows people
to theme their Mac
to match their favorite color.
The Multicolor option allows
each app to define
its own custom color.
For pervasive theming,
you can define
a custom accent color
in your app's asset catalog.
The new tinting API provides
a way to override the color
for one specific control.
This is great for controls
where you'd like to apply
a semantically meaningful color.
For example, if your app uses
a specific shade of orange
to distinguish a preorder
from a normal purchase,
you can reinforce that design
using a tinted button.
Another example would be
a video conferencing app,
where the Start
and End Call buttons
perform two of the most
meaningful actions in the app.
Tinting them green and red
adds emphasis
and it makes their function
instantly recognizable.
One important note
is that tinted buttons
always show their tint color
in every active state,
unlike ordinary push buttons
which are white or gray.
This puts your tint color
front and center.
However, take care in your
design not to create confusion
with the default button,
which also uses
a colorful appearance.
Finally, it's important
to convey your controls' purpose
using more than just color.
You want to make sure
that people who have difficultly
distinguishing between colors
can still easily identify
the purpose of a given control,
so be sure to provide
a clear label or icon.
Another important
button design change
is that push buttons
no longer highlight
using the accent color on click.
This brings them in line
with other clickable elements,
like segmented control segments,
slider knobs, and steppers.
This is an important change,
because if you're doing
any custom drawing
that assumes a colorful
appearance while highlighted --
say, if you're choosing to draw
white content over top --
it might not look correct
on macOS Monterey.
Instead of checking
for the highlight state,
you can drive your drawing
decisions using
the interiorBackgroundStyle
property.
This property reflects
the underlying style
of the button bezel,
so it'll always return .normal
for colorless states,
and it'll return .emphasized
for those colorful
emphasis states,
like tinted buttons,
default buttons,
and buttons that are toggled
into an "on" state.
Finally, we've updated
the Flexible Push
style of button --
previously known
as Regular Square --
to serve as a variable-height
push button.
It now supports all
of the same configurations
as an ordinary push button,
which means that it can serve
as the default button,
and you can tint it.
The corner radius and content
padding now match those
of a standard push button
at each control size,
so they'll fit in great
with your other controls,
but their vertically resizable
design
means that they can accommodate
larger icons
or text with line breaks.
While the vast majority of
push buttons should continue
to use the standard
fixed-height style,
this newly expanded style
offers some flexibility
for those special cases
when you need to accommodate
taller content.
Another very important
control update comes in the form
of automatic localization
for menu keyboard shortcuts.
There are a lot of keyboard
layouts out there in the world,
and that can make
localizing keyboard shortcuts
fairly complex.
Some key combinations are hard
to reach on some keyboards,
and others can't be typed
at all.
In addition, some directional
keyboard shortcuts
really ought to mirror
in right-to-left languages.
The great news is,
in macOS Monterey,
AppKit can do it for you.
Here's an example of a shortcut
that could benefit from
localization: Command-backslash.
While this works fine
on a US English keyboard,
it's actually impossible to type
on a Japanese keyboard,
which doesn't have
a backslash key at all.
Starting in macOS Monterey,
the system remaps the shortcut
automatically,
providing an equivalent shortcut
that's natural to type.
Another common case
is a keyboard shortcut
that has directional meaning.
For example, Safari uses
Command-square brackets
to go backward
and forward in history.
In a right-to-left language,
using the left bracket to go
backward isn't very intuitive,
so AppKit now automatically
swaps it to the right bracket
when running
in a right-to-left language.
This behavior applies
to brackets, braces,
parentheses, and arrow keys.
In some cases, you might want to
disable this mirroring behavior.
For example, if your menu item
has absolute directionality --
like align left, for example --
you'd want to use
the left bracket
even in
a right-to-left language.
We've provided an opt-out
for cases just like this.
You can control this behavior
using some new properties
on NSMenuItem.
allowsAutomaticKey
EquivalentMirroring
lets you control
the mirroring behavior
for directional keys
like  brackets,
and allowsAutomaticKey
EquivalentLocalization
controls all of
the localization features,
including keyboard mapping
and mirroring.
If you've already
carefully localized
your keyboard shortcuts,
or if your application has
a heavily custom implementation
of keyboard shortcut bindings,
you might want to disable this
feature for your entire app.
To do that,
you can implement this
application delegate method,
applicationShouldAutomatically
LocalizeKeyEquivalents,
and return false.
Most apps won't need
to use this.
The individual menu item APIs
are strongly preferred
for opting out specific items,
and most apps shouldn't need
to opt out at all.
Next up, some big enhancements
to symbol images.
We brought SF Symbols
to macOS in Big Sur,
opening up a massive
repertoire of beautiful,
typographically balanced
symbol images to all Mac apps.
In macOS Monterey, we've built
a new generation of symbol APIs
and tooling that we call
SF Symbols 3.
It's a huge update
that spans every aspect
of the symbol image workflow,
and it's all available
to your AppKit applications.
SF Symbols 3
expands the capabilities
of the SF Symbols app
for previewing, exporting,
and importing symbol images.
It also comes with
an updated format
for annotating custom symbols,
which allows you to define
distinct layers
within a symbol image,
and we've expanded our APIs
in AppKit, UIKit, and SwiftUI
to allow to you to individually
color each layer of a symbol.
In Big Sur, we offered
two distinct rendering modes
for symbols.
First, there was
the traditional Template style,
which draws using a single
tint color or effect
over the entire symbol.
The second is Multicolor,
which draws more
like a full-color image,
drawing each path element
using a color that's defined
in the symbol image itself.
In SF Symbols 3, we've added
two new rendering modes
which take advantage
of the layer information
provided by the new
symbol image format.
The first, Hierarchical,
draws using a single color,
while putting emphasis on
specific parts of the symbol
while deemphasizing others.
And the second, Palette, lets
you assign any color you'd like
to each layer of the symbol.
You can access these rendering
modes using new API
on NSImage.SymbolConfiguration.
I'm representing the
NSColor parameters as dots
to show how they correspond
with the rendered symbol.
The Hierarchical rendering mode
take a single color,
which is applied to the symbol
layers with decreasing opacity.
The Palette mode
accepts an array of colors
which are applied
to the layers verbatim.
You can also create
a configuration
that prefers the Multicolor
rendering mode.
We've also added a new API
that lets you map
from one base symbol
into one of its variants.
For example, you could map
the heart symbol
to its filled variant,
or an inscribed variant
like circle,
or even to the variant
that has a slash through it.
This is really useful
for situations where
you prefer a particular
style of symbol
for a particular context.
For example,
you might have a picker control
where you prefer outlines
for the unselected states,
but a filled style
for your selection.
Normally, this control
would need
two different image properties
to specify the selected
and unselected
versions of the image.
But with the variants API,
it could just accept
a single base symbol and derive
the filled state automatically.
This control could call
image(with: .fill)
to prefer a filled symbol
in its selection state,
and it'll automatically choose
the right version of the symbol
whenever a filled variant
is available.
There are constants
for each type of symbol variant,
and you can combine them
to request
multiple variants together,
like circle and fill.
This was just a brief
introduction to the features
of SF Symbols 3.
There's a new collection
of videos where you can get
the full details
on everything that's new
across the entire
symbols workflow.
Be sure to add them
to your watch list.
macOS Monterey also features
a huge update to the text system
in the form of TextKit 2.
TextKit is the text layout
and rendering engine
for all Apple devices,
and it's a great text engine
with a proven track record.
TextKit is a linear
text layout engine,
which means that it typesets
a block of text
from beginning to end.
As we've evolved our platforms
and technologies,
we've found a lot of cases
where nonlinear text layout
would serve us much better.
So we went back to the basics
and created a new version
of TextKit
and that's TextKit 2.
We had a few key goals
for TextKit 2.
As always, we want to provide
the very best experience
for international text
of every script and layout.
We also want to make it easier
to mix text
with other types of content.
And finally, TextKit 2
is designed to be super fast,
efficiently shaping
and rendering text,
whether it's a short label
or scrolled partway
through a massive document.
TextKit 2 coexists
with TextKit 1,
so you can choose which engine
to use for a given text view.
Now I'm going to let you in
on a secret.
You're already running TextKit 2
on your Mac
because starting in Big Sur,
TextEdit uses it
for plain text documents,
and AppKit text fields
use TextKit 2
for most configurations.
So you've actually been getting
a sneak peek this entire time.
One of the key differences
in TextKit 2
is that it always uses
a nonlinear layout system.
That means that
it can perform text layout
at a more granular level,
which allows it to avoid
unnecessary work.
For example,
if we have a large document
where only a portion of the text
is scrolled to be visible,
a linear system still has to
lay out all of the previous text
in order to show this region.
By comparison, a nonlinear
system like TextKit 2
can start layout at the nearest
paragraph boundary.
For large documents,
this is a huge speedup.
The new layout engine
provides a robust set
of customization points,
making it simple
to extend the layout system
and add your own behaviors.
The nonlinear layout system
also lends itself well
to mixing nontext elements
into your text layout.
And it does all of this
while improving performance
for even the largest documents.
To learn more,
check out "Meet TextKit 2,"
which goes into full detail
about the design of the new API
and how to use it.
Next up, I'd like to share some
updates about AppKit in Swift
starting with concurrency.
Swift 5.5 introduces
some important
language-level features
for managing concurrency.
The first, async/await, allows
for asynchronous method calls
that behave a lot
like coroutines.
The second, actor types, protect
mutable state from data races
by isolating accesses to
a single thread of execution.
AppKit works great
with both of these new features.
For async/await,
many asynchronous methods
in AppKit --
that is, methods
that take a continuation
as a completion handler block --
have been transformed in the SDK
to offer async
variants as well.
One simple example
is NSColorSampler,
which allows the user to pick
a color from anywhere onscreen.
This call is asynchronous
because it waits for the user
to pick the color they'd like,
and then it runs the completion
handler when they're done.
With async/await,
you can express this
as an async function call.
It yields its thread
of execution
while it's waiting for the
asynchronous work to complete,
and then it picks right back up
where it left off.
You can even do it from within
a guard statement.
Now, the continuation --
the work to be done next --
is no longer nested inside
a completion handler block.
Instead, the code reads
naturally in sequence.
Actors work to protect state
from concurrent access
by isolating it to a single
thread of execution.
If that sounds familiar,
it's because most
of AppKit's state,
like the view hierarchy
and responder chain,
should also be accessed from
a single thread of execution,
specifically the main thread.
This restriction fits
the actor model nicely,
so we've introduced the concept
of a MainActor,
which is a type that has to be
accessed from the main thread.
In AppKit,
we've designated NSResponder
including its subclasses
of NSView,
ViewController,
WindowController,
and Application, plus NSCell,
Alert, Document,
and DocumentController
as MainActors.
Code running in a MainActor
can freely call methods
on other MainActor types,
since you know that you're
already on the main thread.
However, code that's not running
in the MainActor
must use the new async/await
features to perform that UI work
in the context
of the MainActor.
By enforcing this
at the compiler level,
Swift can help you avoid
a common source of bugs
when mixing concurrency
with UI code.
The Swift concurrency videos
go into great depth
about this powerful
new language feature.
You don't want to miss them.
Also new in Swift 5.5
is a value-typed version
of AttributedString.
On top of providing
value semantics,
it also has type-safe attributes
and great Swift ergonomics
for enumerating and manipulating
ranges of attributes.
When you're using
AttributedString with AppKit,
you'll automatically get access
to the attributes
that are relevant
to our text drawing system;
things like foreground color,
paragraph style, and so on.
You can convert between
struct AttributedString
and the reference-typed
NSAttributedString,
so you can interoperate
with APIs
that use NSAttributedString.
The "What's new in Foundation"
video goes into more detail
on AttributedString's design
and how to use it.
Our last Swift enhancement
has to do with driving updates
to your NSViews.
It uses Swift's
property wrapper feature
to dramatically reduce
the boilerplate
that's common
in view properties.
Let's go over an example.
Here's a custom view
that's configurable
via a handful of properties.
And while this looks fine,
the reality is that
our view's property declarations
are much more likely to contain
a lot of didSets
and extra side effects,
because it's so common
that you need to redraw,
or layout, or update
your constraints
when something changes.
Now, that's a lot
of boilerplate.
So we made this scenario better
by creating a new Swift property
wrapper just for this case.
It's called Invalidating.
It's nested under NSView,
and it allows you to specify
one or more aspects
of the view to invalidate
when the wrapped property
changes.
All of the didSets
and brackets fall away,
making it easier
to focus on the definition
of the property itself.
AppKit provides several
built-in invalidation cases:
display, layout, constraints,
intrinsic content size,
and restorable state.
Since these invalidations
only make sense on views,
we've constrained
the property wrapper
so that it only works
on subclasses of NSView.
We also require that the value
conforms to Equatable.
We use this conformance
to check for meaningful
changes in value
before performing a potentially
expensive redraw or layout pass.
If you'd like to do
something custom,
you can even define
your own invalidation
by conforming a type to the
NSViewInvalidating protocol.
Finally, Shortcuts.
In macOS Monterey, we're excited
to bring the full power
of Shortcuts to the Mac,
and that includes integrating
Shortcuts with your AppKit apps.
The great news is,
if you app supports Services,
then it already
supports Shortcuts,
and Shortcuts appear
in all of the same places
where you can access
Services today.
If you're new
to this functionality,
it's really easy to adopt.
AppKit decides which shortcuts
are contextually-appropriate
by checking the responder chain.
It asks each responder whether
it can provide or receive
the types of data
expected by each shortcut.
We express this using
a pasteboard type,
which in most cases, corresponds
to a uniform type identifier.
All you have to do is implement
the validRequestor
for sendType
and returnType method.
And if you can accept or provide
the specified types,
return an object conforming to
the NSServicesMenuRequestor
protocol.
In most cases, you'll just
implement that protocol directly
and then return self.
Once a Shortcut is invoked,
you'll get calls to write
and/or read data
from a special pasteboard
that the Shortcut uses
for its input and output.
And that's it!
It's that easy to integrate
your app with Shortcuts.
We've also brought Siri Intents
to macOS.
You can now handle Intents
by creating
an Intents Extension in Xcode.
Or, if you need to handle them
from your main application,
you can return an Intent handler
from your application delegate.
In your app delegate,
implement the
application handlerFor intent:
method,
returning a handler object for
any intent that you can handle.
Every type of intent
has its own handler protocol
that the returned object
must conform to,
so check the Intents framework
documentation
for more details on implementing
a handler object.
Now that you're equipped with
all of this new information,
what's next?
First, think about how features
like control tinting
and SF Symbols 3 can help you
enhance the design of your app.
Next, if your app uses TextKit
to create a custom
text experience,
watch the "Meet TextKit 2" video
and try out the new API.
You're going to love
how easy it is
to express custom layouts
and rich content with TextKit 2.
The that way your app manages
concurrency is a key part
of its architecture,
and Swift's new
concurrency features
will be a huge improvement
in this area.
Now is the time
to start planning
for how features
like async/await will shape
the way your app manages
its concurrent workloads.
Finally, get your app ready
for Shortcuts
by adopting AppKit's
automation features.
Thanks for your time
and attention.
We hope you enjoy all
of these great enhancements
in macOS Monterey.
♪