[upbeat music]
[Shobi] Welcome to the session
"Meet TestFlight on Mac."
I'm Shobi Vijayakumar,
TestFlight Engineering Manager.
I'm really excited
to share with you
about the amazing new
TestFlight features coming soon.
Introducing this year,
one of your most
popular request:
TestFlight on Mac.
TestFlight lets you distribute
beta builds of your app
to testers and collect
valuable feedback.
It's been available
on iOS and tvOS,
and now we are bringing it
to MacOS coming this fall.
TestFlight on Mac provides
all the same capabilities
you have on iOS and tvOS,
and it will be available
to download
on the Mac App Store.
You can install beta apps,
setup automatic updates,
and share feedback.
It supports native Mac apps
and iOS apps
on Apple Silicon Mac.
First let's take a look
at installing beta apps.
You can recruit testers
by sending an email invite
or by sharing a public link.
Once they accept the invite,
they become a tester
for your app.
They can browse through
different builds
grouped by versions
to choose
a specific build to test
and click the install button
to download
and start testing on Mac.
Once a beta app is installed,
it can be launched
from TestFlight anytime.
It can also be launched
by all means
like Dock, Launchpad,
and Finder.
To make it easy
to recognize it as a beta app,
we show a yellow dot
next to the app name
in the Dock, in Launchpad,
and as a Beta Application
in Finder.
Testers can configure
automatic updates
to have
the latest available builds
install automatically.
This will ensure
they are testing
the latest build of your app.
While testing a beta version
of an app,
your testers
can send you feedback
about issues they experience
or make suggestions
for improvements.
They can send feedback
directly from your app
simply by taking a screenshot,
attaching it,
adding in the comments
to describe the issue,
and then submit.
You can view this feedback
in App Store Connect
under the Screenshot Feedback
section.
If the beta app crashes,
then TestFlight automatically
captures the crash logs
and provides a dialog
for testers to enter
additional comments.
You can download the crash logs
and see the feedback
under App Store Connect
crashes feedback section
and in Xcode Organizer.
So that's a brief overview
of the main features
of TestFlight on Mac,
which helps you test the apps
and collect valuable feedback.
Now, let's take a look
at how native Mac apps
and iOS apps
on Apple Silicon Mac
can be set up for TestFlight
followed by improved internal
group management
and built-in
Xcode Cloud features.
OK, let's get into the details
about distributing
native Mac apps with TestFlight.
Native Mac apps
require a provisioning profile
to be distributed
with TestFlight on Mac.
We will create and include
the provisioning profile
for your apps
when you use Xcode
Automatically manage signing.
If your apps manage
signing manually,
you have to add
the profile explicitly.
How to create and upload
a profile manually
is documented
in the Developer portal.
Once uploaded
with a provisioning profile,
the builds will be displayed
under macOS.
You can create groups
to manage testers
and distribute each one,
very similar to iOS or tvOS.
For each build,
you can view
the number of invited testers,
installations on devices,
sessions in the last seven days,
crashes, and feedback count.
These numbers are aggregated
across all of the testers.
When you are looking
at App Store Connect
crashes or screenshots
feedback section,
you can filter by selecting
the platform macOS.
You can further filter
the feedback
by selecting a specific
Mac device or MacOS version.
As you see, native Mac apps
distribution with TestFlight
is very similar to iOS and tvOS.
Let's see how iOS apps
on Apple Silicon Macs
can be distributed
with TestFlight.
For each tester group,
you can control
the TestFlight availability
of iPhone and iPad apps
on Apple Silicon Macs.
When enabled,
the iOS builds in this group
are available to TestFlight
on Apple Silicon Macs.
When this is disabled,
all iOS builds from that group
will stop being available
on Mac.
This provides more flexibility
to control
who can test the iOS apps
on Apple Silicon Macs.
The iOS builds are displayed
similar to today,
but the counts displayed
will include the numbers
from the Apple Silicon Macs
as well.
Similarly, you can see
the crashes and screenshots
feedback
at App Store Connect
under the platform iOS
and will include feedback
submitted
from Apple Silicon Macs.
It's that simple
to make iOS apps
distribute with TestFlight
on Apple Silicon Mac.
Internal testing
has always made testing
with your App Store Connect team
convenient.
This year,
we have made new improvements
to make internal group
management even more flexible.
And it's applicable
for all supported platforms.
You can now create
multiple internal groups
similar to external groups.
You can also configure
distribution of builds
and collection of feedback
per internal group.
For example, let's say you have
a Development Team
and a QA Team.
You can now create
an internal group
for each of them.
You can give
the Development Team
access to all builds as part
of the development life cycle,
while the QA Team
may only require access
to specific stable builds.
For the Development Team,
you would enable the automatic
distribution flag
to make all current
and future builds
available to this group,
whereas for the QA team,
you would choose
to manually add specific builds.
Now that you saw
how internal groups
can be configured per use case,
I want to show you
how to set it up.
You can create the groups
for each team
by clicking on the plus button
next to Internal Testing.
Now give your internal group
a name.
For the Dev Team,
choose
Enable automatic distribution.
While for QA Team,
you can uncheck
Enable automatic distribution
and click Create.
Once the groups are created,
for QA team,
you can click
on the plus button to
manually select the builds
to be added to the group.
Then for each group,
you can click on the plus button
next to Testers
to manually select the ones
applicable for the groups
and add them.
You also have the option
to enable or disable
the feedback per group,
just like external testing.
If you use
the App Store Connect API,
you can manage internal groups
with different configurations
through the BetaGroups Resource.
Similarly if you use
App Store Connect on iOS,
they can also be managed
from there.
Well, these are
the major improvements
to make internal testing
more flexible.
Lastly, we have integrated
exciting Xcode Cloud features
directly into TestFlight.
This week,
Apple introduced Xcode Cloud.
Xcode Cloud integrates
with TestFlight
and provides
a seamless experience
to automatically build, test,
and distribute your apps.
To learn more about Xcode Cloud,
check out the session
"Meet Xcode Cloud."
First, Xcode Cloud
manages beta build distribution
through TestFlight to provide
a seamless experience
by automatically distributing
builds to specific beta groups.
Second, your builds
are organized in the way
your development team works
via Build Groups.
Let me show you
how it looks like
in App Store Connect.
Here is the Builds Groups view,
where you will find builds
grouped by the Xcode Cloud
workflow and GIT branch.
They are supported
in the App Store Connect app
on iOS, too.
For internal testers
on TestFlight,
the Build Groups display
makes it easier
to find builds based on the more
familiar GIT branch names
and Xcode Cloud workflows
for internal testing.
You can also filter feedback
by a specific Build Group
under the Feedback section
in App Store Connect.
Well, these are
the amazing features
of TestFlight
coming soon this year.
TestFlight on Mac supports
both native Mac apps
and iOS apps
on Apple Silicon Macs.
You can start beta testing
on Mac coming fall.
Improve
internal group management
to create multiple groups
as per your needs.
And finally,
Xcode Cloud integrates
with App Store Connect
and TestFlight to manage
build distribution
and organize them
by build groups.
You can sign up
for Xcode Cloud Beta today.
I think you will enjoy
all the new features
added this year
and have an amazing
TestFlight experience.
Try them out
and give us your feedback.
Thank you very much.
[upbeat music]