[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Jeff Robertson: Welcome
to the second part of our talk
on building a great Mac app
in SwiftUI.
I'm Jeff, an engineer
on the SwiftUI team.
I hope you enjoyed
the first part of this talk
by my colleague Mathieu.
If you have not yet watched
part one,
please stop here and do so now,
as we will be building
on top of the changes
that are discussed in that talk.
Our gardening app
has come a long way
since the start
of Mathieu's talk.
SwiftUI enabled us
to build an app
with quite a bit
of functionality
in very little time.
However, users tend to use
our apps in many different ways,
and a particularly great
macOS app will account for this.
With that in mind, let's take
a look at some of the ways
that we can build an app
for everyone
while still maintaining
the principles
Mathieu outlined in part one.
First, we'll take a look
at what it means to be
a fully customizable macOS app,
by handling changes
to the system as a whole
as well as within our own app.
Adding an additional workflow
for our users to manipulate
their data through drag and drop
is another way for us to provide
a flexible user experience.
Then, we'll explore how to work
with the file system,
by allowing our app's data
to be exported.
And finally, we'll add support
for Continuity Camera
to create a seamless workflow
for importing images
into our app.
The first thing
I'd like to talk to you about
isn't any specific API at all,
but more about how an app
built with SwiftUI
fits in with the customizability
of macOS.
Here, I have
our gardening app open
as well as System Preferences.
I'm going to switch
to Dark mode,
and you can see our app updates
its interface automatically.
While I have
the System Preferences open,
I'm also going to update my
sidebar icon size to be large.
Just as with Dark mode,
our app adjusted itself
to what I set
in System Preferences.
I love these little touches,
both as a developer --
since I get them
automatically --
and as a user -- since it means
the apps I'm using
will be taking into account
my own personal tastes.
Before I leave
System Preferences
to focus on our app,
I'd like to point out
that I have my accent color
set to be multicolor.
This feature allows developers
to configure
an app-specific accent color;
and the operating system will
customize your app's buttons,
selection highlighting,
and sidebar glyphs.
I'd like to support
an accent color in my app,
so I'm going to open
the asset catalog in our project
and select the AccentColor.
And I'm going to change its
content to be system green
to match our app's theme.
As you can see,
our sidebar icons and selection
have all picked up the change.
We've seen how our app can
automatically react to changes
which affect
the entire operating system,
but what about
app-specific settings?
Let's walk through
adding an interface
to let users customize
our gardening app.
Here, I've opened
our GardenApp file.
And alongside
the WindowGroup scene
I'm going to add
a Settings scene.
And this scene
will give us a menu item
which, when selected,
will open a window
with our view.
I'm going to use the
SettingsView that I've set up,
and I'm going to pass it
my model as well.
[KEYSTROKES]
Additionally, the Settings scene
will also add
the appropriate menu item
to your app's main menu
and configure it with
the standard keyboard shortcut
of Command-comma.
This gives us a great start.
Now, let's take a look
at the SettingsView,
where I'll define the interface.
On macOS, it's common for apps
to provide a settings interface
with toolbar icons
to allow switching
between the different panes,
particularly if the app
provides a lot of settings
which can be divided up
into different categories.
So for my main view here,
I'm going to use a TabView.
[KEYSTROKES]
And I'm going to give it
two children:
one for GeneralSettings,
and one for ViewingSettings.
And for the content of the tab
in the window toolbar area,
I'm going to use a tabItem.
And the contents of this
can just be a Label.
We'll give it the text
to be displayed --
in this case, "General" --
and a systemImage;
I'm going to use "gear"
for GeneralSettings.
And then let's do the same
for our ViewingSettings.
I'll add a tabItem
and a Label --
we'll call it "Viewing" --
and a systemImage of,
I think, "eyeglasses."
All right. So now we have
the contents of our two tabs.
Let's fill out
the GeneralSettings now.
Something that could be nice
for our users
is the ability to define
a garden to be used
as the default when no garden
is currently selected.
For this, I'm going to add
a Picker...
[KEYSTROKES]
And the first item, I think,
will be the Text("None").
And for the others,
I'm going to add a ForEach
over all the gardens
in our data.
[KEYSTROKES]
And for each garden,
I'm just going to add a Text
and give it the garden's name
as well as its displayYear.
We'll also need to provide a tag
here with the ID of the garden.
So for our "None" value,
we can give it a tag of none.
[KEYSTROKES]
And for our other gardens,
we'll give it a tag
corresponding
to the garden's ID.
[KEYSTROKES]
Lastly, we need to provide
some state
for the Picker's selection.
When providing
a settings interface like this,
it's important
to persist the state
so that your app remembers
the user's selection
across launches and OS updates.
In SwiftUI,
this can be accomplished
by using
the AppStorage property wrapper.
This property wrapper
will persist our value
using the UserDefaults system,
which is exactly
what we want here.
So for our selection binding,
I'm going to add
the AppStorage property wrapper.
This takes a key.
We'll give it "defaultGarden",
and we'll call it "selection".
It is also
an optional Garden.ID.
And what this will do
is persist our selection value
using the user default system.
I'm also going to add
a fixedSize to my Picker
and some padding to the form.
[KEYSTROKES]
I'm going to switch over
to our ContentView here,
and I'll add our AppStorage
and give it that same key
we used.
[KEYSTROKES]
We'll call it "defaultGardenID",
and it's also
an optional Garden.ID.
And then here where I have
this binding for selection,
I'm going to replace this
with a Binding,
and the "get" will be to first
use the selectedGardenID.
And then if that isn't set,
we're going to fall back
to the defaultGardenID.
And then for the setter,
we only want to update
our selectedGardenID.
We don't actually want to update
our defaultGarden.
So I'm just going to say
"selectedGardenID = $0".
All right.
I'm going to run our app.
Open the Preferences
menu item here,
and I'm going to select
Indoor Plants
as my default garden.
And I'll open a new window,
and we see Indoor Plants
is selected.
Providing customization support
via settings is one nice way
of building a flexible
experience for our users.
Another way is providing
alternative workflows
for the same action.
In the first part of our talk,
Mathieu showed you
how to add a main menu item
for adding a plant
to the selected garden.
This is great functionality
for our app,
but let's look at another way
that we can provide
similar functionality via
a common macOS user interaction:
drag and drop.
Since we're using table here,
I'm going to make
a couple of adjustments
to support it being
a drag source
and drop destination.
The first thing I'm going to do
is remove this "plants"
from the initializer.
Then I'm going to go
down at the end
and add a row builder.
For the contents
of this row builder,
I'm going to add a ForEach
and use those plants
that we had from before.
[KEYSTROKES]
And for each plant,
I'm just going to create
a TableRow with it.
So now I'm going to customize
each of our TableRows
by adding
the itemProvider modifier.
And I'm going to return
just plant.itemProvider here,
which is a computed property
I set up on my model.
So now each of these rows
supports being a drag source.
I've made enough changes now
to allow me to drag out
my plants,
but this is not very useful
if nothing will accept it.
Let's fix that by also adding
drop support to our table.
The onInsert modifier
is the other half
of our drag and drop equation.
It takes a list
of content types,
and I'm going to pass
Plant.draggableType here,
which is a custom type
I set up on my model.
It also takes a closure,
which is passed two parameters.
One is the index
where the drop occurred,
and another is the list
of item providers.
We're going to then call
Plant.fromItemProviders
to create our model,
and we'll pass
those item providers here.
This will give us back
a list of plants,
which we can use
to update our model.
I'll call garden.plants.insert
(contentsOf: plants)
at the index where it occurred.
Now, I can open a new window
with my Indoor Plants,
select a few flowers
from my Backyard Flower Bed,
and drag to copy them over.
Drag and drop is a great way
to move data around
inside our app,
but what about moving data
between our app
and the operating system?
Our users would appreciate
being able to export
all this data --
perhaps for backup purposes
or importing into another app.
To facilitate this workflow,
let's add a main menu item
for exporting our database
in a common file format
that can be shared
with other applications.
I've already created a type
to contain my menu item,
which conforms
to the commands protocol.
In our commands here, I'm going
to add an ImportExportCommands
And also pass it our store.
Let's switch over
to that file now.
And for the body,
I'm going to add
a CommandGroup
and I'm going to replace
the system-provided
importExport placement.
And what this will do
is add our menu item
in the expected place
in the File menu.
So for the contents
of our CommandGroup,
I'll add a Section and a Button.
We'll give it a label
of "Export"
followed by the ellipses.
The ellipses indicate to the
user that selecting that item
will open a window
or a save dialog.
And the Button can just modify
some state --
say, "isShowingExport = true" --
and let's add that state
up here as well.
[KEYSTROKES]
So now we have our Button,
which is modifying some state.
I'm also going to add
the fileExporter modifier here.
And I'm going to give it
a binding to our state
in its isPresented parameter.
isShowingExport.
It also takes a document.
This is a type that needs
to conform
to either
the file document protocol
or the reference file document
protocol.
I've already added conformance
to my store,
so we'll just pass that here.
Additionally, it takes
a content type.
We'll give it
Store.readableContentTypes.first
which is just the CSV type.
And lastly, it takes a closure,
which is passed the result
of the operation,
indicating success or failure.
Now, I can select
our Export menu item,
give it a file to save as,
say "plants.csv",
hit Export,
and the file's been saved
to disk.
While we're on the topic
of moving data between our app
and the operating system,
there is one last thing
I'd like to discuss.
Our app has lots of textual data
about our plants,
but it would be great
to add images as well.
Users could take pictures
of their plants over time
to track their progress.
One way to enable
this import flow
is with Continuity Camera.
This feature would allow
our users
to take a picture of their plant
with their iOS device
and have it import directly
into our app.
Let's take a look
at how we can add a menu item
to enable this flow
when a user has selected
a plant in the gallery view.
After my importExportCommands,
I'm going to add
ImportFromDevicesCommands,
and that'll give us
our main menu item.
Additionally, I'm going
to switch over
to our GardenDetail file,
and at the end of our body here,
I'm going to add the
importsItemProviders modifier,
and this takes a list of types
that we want to support
importing.
I'm going to base this off of
whether anything is selected,
so I'm going to use
our selection here.
And if it's empty,
I'm going to return
an empty array.
And if it's not empty,
I'm going to return
Plant.importImageTypes,
which is a list of all
the image types on the system.
And this modifier
takes a closure,
which is passed
a list of item providers.
We'll take those providers
and call
Plant.importImageFromProviders,
pass it the providers,
and this is going to give us
back a URL
where it saved the image
to disk.
We'll then update our model
by looping through all the IDs
that are selected...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and get a reference
to the plant
and update its imageURL.
I'm going to select
my Indoor Plants garden
and switch to Gallery mode.
And I'm going to make things
a little bit bigger.
Select my plant here.
In the main menu item,
choose Import from iPhone >
Take Photo.
[CAMERA SHUTTER]
And you can see
our gallery updated.
I hope this was a nice tour
of some of the various ways
which define a great Mac app.
I'm looking forward
to all the ways your apps
will make the macOS platform
better.
Have a wonderful WWDC 2021.
♪