[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Harry] Hi, I'm Harry,
an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Welcome to "Craft search
experiences in SwiftUI."
Search is all-new
in SwiftUI this year,
and I'm excited to show you
how to start using
these features.
Sometimes,
you want to find something
specific within an app,
but many apps contain
large collections of data,
which can make it difficult
to find exactly what
you're looking for.
Whether it's finding
the latest app trend,
your next favorite song,
or the right podcast
for your morning commute,
implementing search
helps do just that.
The best search experience
will vary
based on the structure
and content of the app.
But, in general,
all experiences will include
a search field
that defines a search query.
Now, you can implement
search directly in SwiftUI.
Let's take a look.
In this talk, I'll introduce
the new searchable modifier
that forms the foundation of all
search features in SwiftUI.
I'll showcase
how a navigation view
integrates with
the searchable modifier.
Finally, I'll cover
extending the functionality
of searchable modifiers
by adding search suggestions.
Searchable is a new
view modifier in SwiftUI
available on all platforms.
It allows you
to mark view content
as being, well, searchable.
The content will define
exactly what that means.
Throughout this talk,
I'll explore examples
of this modifier
on each platform.
Now, to better understand
this modifier,
let's talk about the weather!
A great example of search on iOS
can be found
in the new Weather app.
When viewing
your list of cities,
you can start typing
into the search bar,
which will search for a new city
to add to your list.
To illustrate how Weather uses
a searchable modifier
to power this feature,
let's break down the structure
of their UI.
Weather starts
with a navigation view,
which provides a navigation bar.
Weather adds a custom list
as the navigation view's content.
And inside of that list, it adds
a ForEach over its cells.
Finally, Weather adds
the searchable modifier
to its navigation view.
At the core of all
searchable modifiers
is the configuration
of a search field.
The searchable modifier takes
the configured search field
and passes that down,
through the environment,
for other views to use
in the best way
for each platform.
Here, the navigation view
understands that search field
and will render it
as a search bar.
If no views use
the configured search field,
the searchable modifier provides
a default implementation
of rendering the search field
in the toolbar.
Now, a search field
is often not the only piece
of search-related UI.
Displaying some form
of search results
is a common design pattern.
Weather follows this pattern,
and whenever it sees
a non-empty search query,
it switches its custom list
to display another list
containing the results
of the current query.
Let's see how Weather can
use information vended
by the searchable modifier
to achieve this UI.
Here's Weather's custom list.
Searchable modifiers set up
a new environment property,
called isSearching,
that Weather uses
to dynamically change
the view being displayed,
based on whether a user
is actively searching.
Weather queries the isSearching
environment property
and the text of the search
to conditionally show
its results view.
When rendering your own results,
consider using an overlay
so that the state of your
main UI is unchanged
after a user returns
from their search interaction.
Let's talk a little bit more
about how a navigation view
integrates with the new
searchable modifier.
To do that,
I'd like to introduce
an app I've been
working tirelessly on.
I call it Colors.
This app lets users
manage a library
of their favorite sets
of colors, called Palettes.
Maybe you wanna play
with different paints
for your room,
themes for your app,
or just get help picking
the color of your new M1 iMac.
No matter your desire,
Colors is the app for you.
The basic structure
of Colors is a double-column
navigation view,
where the first column,
the root view, is a sidebar
on iPadOS and macOS,
or the root of a navigation
stack on other platforms.
In the sidebar, you can see
my library of color palettes.
In the detail view, you can see
the currently selected
color palette,
as well as how those colors
might appear to users
with visual differences.
As people started using the app,
I began to notice something.
People love colors.
They're adding colors
to their library constantly,
but as a library gets large,
it becomes difficult to find
a specific color palette,
as people have to scroll
through their whole library
to find it.
At this point,
I've decided it’s time
to add search functionality.
I'd like this feature
to follow platform conventions
so that people using my app
immediately understand it.
Let's take a look
at how I can use
the searchable modifier
to implement this feature.
Here I have
the navigation view I built
as part of the Colors app.
To implement search,
I'll add the searchable modifier
to my navigation view.
Just like before,
I'll provide it with a binding
to the state backing
the search query.
Again, this will be rendered
as a search bar
on iOS and iPadOS.
When a navigation view is
the searchable
modifier's content,
it associates the search field
with one of its columns.
Which column it uses
is dependent on the number
of columns provided
to the navigation view.
Since I have a two-column
navigation view,
the search bar is associated
with the sidebar column
on both iOS and iPadOS.
If you want the search field
associated with a column
other than the default,
you can place
the searchable modifier
on your desired column,
like you would with
the existing toolbar modifier.
For this app,
I'll keep searchable
on the navigation view.
Just like with Weather,
I'll use the isSearching
environment property
to dynamically display
my search results
over the sidebar.
The same placement of
the searchable modifier on macOS
will render
the search field placed
in the most trailing position
of the toolbar,
with behaviors expected
on that platform,
like automatically collapsing
as a window shrinks.
Here, I'll render
my search results
in the detail pane of the app
for a more typical experience
on macOS.
watchOS behaves similarly
to iOS in that it, too,
places a search field at the top
of the view in the toolbar.
Here, SwiftUI chooses
the first column
to associate
the search field with.
Notice how I didn't change where
I placed the searchable modifier
to produce these different
behaviors across the platforms.
The structure of my app didn't
change across these platforms
and remained
a double-column navigation view.
SwiftUI understands
this structure
and the different
platform conventions,
so it handled implementing them
on my behalf.
When I look at tvOS,
I realize that the structure
of my app on the other platforms
could be made more appropriate.
tvOS typically renders search
as a tab in a tab view,
but my app has no tab view.
With just a few tweaks
to my app, I can fix that.
Instead of rendering
a double-column navigation view,
I can make a more typical
tvOS experience
by rendering a single-column
navigation view
with a tab view
as the navigation view’s content.
In my tab view, I'll place
the existing sidebar view
and add a new search tab.
The search tab represents
the placeholder view
that will be visible
when someone first navigates
to that tab.
Finally, instead of wrapping
the navigation view,
I'll move the searchable
modifier to wrap my search tab.
Once a non-empty
search query has been entered,
I'll transition my view
to display my search results.
Now I've added search
functionality to each platform.
Thanks to the declarative nature
of SwiftUI,
where the navigation structure
of my app remained consistent,
I was able to rely on SwiftUI,
and let the implementation
of the searchable modifier
pick the appropriate interface
for that particular
navigation structure.
On tvOS, where the structure
of my app changed,
I took what I learned
about the searchable modifier
and applied that
to the different structure.
Only what I defined
as "searchable" changed
with that structure.
Now that you have
an understanding
of the searchable modifier,
let's move on
to our final topic:
search suggestions.
After using search in my app,
a few users have reported
that while they really like
the new functionality
search provides,
they're sometimes at a loss
for what they're able
to search for.
Many apps use search suggestions
to help guide people
towards the type of search
queries they can provide.
These suggestions represent
completed search queries
that may be presented in a menu,
like on macOS,
in a list, like on iOS,
or as button
that presents a list,
like on watchOS.
Suggestions give people an idea
for the types of things
they can search for.
SwiftUI offers an easy way
to add search suggestions
to your apps.
Let's take a look.
Looking at my app, you can see
that I've configured
a searchable modifier with text.
Searchable modifiers offer
an optional parameter,
called suggestions,
that I can start including.
For the suggestions parameter,
I'll provide a view.
This might just be
a few static buttons
or, more likely, it will be
a ForEach over a dynamic set
of suggestions coming from my
apps database or from a server.
SwiftUI looks at this view
and will present it
based on whether there are
any suggestions to display.
For example, watchOS will render
an icon in its search field
when you provide
non-empty suggestions.
A common pattern here might be
to provide a ForEach of buttons
that, when interacted with,
updates the text binding
provided
to the searchable modifier
with the search suggestion’s
textual value.
In fact, we expect this pattern
to be so common that we've added
a searchCompletion modifier
that does just this.
You can use
the searchCompletion modifier
with non-interactive views.
It will convert that view
into a button
that updates the search text
and dismisses
the currently presented
suggestion.
If you're creating an app
where users first interact
with suggestions to then fetch
a complete set of search results
based on that suggestion,
consider using
the new onSubmit modifier
to know when to fetch
your search results.
Pass in a value of search
to the onSubmit modifier,
and the closure you provide
will be invoked
whenever the user submits
their search query.
This typically occurs
when they select
a search suggestion
or press Enter
on a hardware keyboard.
You can also use
the new onSubmit modifier
in conjunction with text fields
or secure fields
for non-search-related
submissions.
Using the suggestions parameter
along with the search
completion modifier
provides an easy way to add
powerful search-suggestion
functionality to your app.
I hope you've enjoyed
a brief tour
of some
of the search functionality
that SwiftUI now offers.
In summary,
a searchable modifier allows you
to describe view content
as searchable.
Navigation views integrate
with the searchable modifier
to provide
platform-appropriate experiences
based on the content
of the navigation view.
Use the environment's
isSearching property
to dynamically adjust
the UI of your app
when a user is searching.
Use the search
completion modifier
and the suggestions parameter
of the searchable modifier
to add search suggestions
to your app.
Now, go out there
and start adding search
to all your SwiftUI apps,
and have a great WW.
[upbeat music]