[Nicki]
Hi, I'm Nicki Brower.
I'm an engineer
on the Pencil and Paper team.
And today, I'm gonna show
you how to adopt Quick Note.
Quick Note is a brand-new,
system-wide note-taking experience
aimed to not only streamline the ability
to take notes on iOS and macOS,
but to connect content from
multiple apps and the web in one location.
This feature enables people
to easily bring up a Note anywhere,
and the best part is, it uses an API
that already exists:
NSUserActivity.
If that sounds familiar, it's because it's
used for other features, like Handoff.
Today, I'll show you Quick Note
live and in action.
I'll talk about
the how it works on the system
and how to adopt NSUserActivity.
Finally, I'll go over some best practices
so you can create the best experience.
To show you the new Quick Note feature,
I'm going to step through
my plan of action to get into
shape using Apple Fitness+.
I haven't signed up yet, and I don't
want to without an action plan.
Instead of having
to switch to the Notes app,
I'm now able to use my pencil to swipe up
from the bottom right corner of the screen
to create a brand-new Quick Note
to remember that when I'm ready to start,
the Apple website has all
the information I need to know.
There's also a new add link menu at
the top of the Quick Note,
where I'll add a link to the website
to make it easy
to navigate back to this content.
Similar to picture-in-picture,
the Quick Note window
is able to freely move around
to any corner of the device.
I can also pinch to scale
the window from the default size,
to the smallest size,
all the way up the largest size.
If I'm finished with my note,
I can press the Done button
in top left corner.
but I still have some stuff I need to add,
so I'll swipe the UI to the right
to tuck it away on the side of the screen.
In addition to websites,
of course, it also works with apps.
Using Maps, I was able to find
a great spot to practice my HIIT workouts.
I'll pull out my note that I tucked away
and add this location to my note, too.
For more room to draw, tap the Notes icon
from the Quick Note toolbar
to get to the note in the Notes app.
Here, I'll take advantage of the ability
to draw over images and links.
The links I've added here
aren't just any old links.
Sure, tapping on them will take
me to Safari or Maps,
but now I can get back to my note
from these apps
with Quick Note Suggestions.
When I go to the site
about Apple Fitness+,
the Quick Note Suggestions UI will
show up in the bottom right-hand corner.
Tapping on this will bring
me right back to where I was,
and I'll add a note that my goal is
to do a HIIT workout 4 to 5 times a week.
I've created a note here on an iPad,
but it also works
cross-platform with the Mac.
When I visit
the link about Apple Fitness+,
the Quick Note Suggestions UI
will also appear here on my Mac.
When I click on it, I'll be
directed to the note in the Notes app.
Now that you've met Quick Note,
let's talk about how it works.
An NSUserActivity object
provides a way
to capture the state of an app
and put it to use later.
User activity objects are
created about what is happening,
such as viewing a web page
or viewing app content,
and each app will register
its current activity with the system.
The system then gets these activities
and sends them out
out to features like Handoff.
Quick Note linking
piggybacks on this system.
In addition to going to Handoff,
Spotlight, and Reminders,
registered activities are
also sent to Quick Note.
This is how the link shows
up in the add link menu
and what triggers Quick Note Suggestions.
NSUserActivity already has
three properties
that serve as durable identifiers
for linking app content with Quick Note.
To be part of this ecosystem,
you must set one or more
of these properties:
targetContentIdentifier,
persistentIdentifier,
and webpageURL.
Which ones you choose depends on what
other features you want to support.
targetContentIdentifier is also
used during state restoration.
This property creates a great multitasking
experience for apps that run on iPad.
persistentIdentifier is also used
to identify app content
in the system's Spotlight index,
and webpageURL is
also used for web fallback during Handoff.
In order for Quick Note links to work,
there are a few properties
the identifiers need to have.
They should be unique
for that piece of content,
be global so they work across
all devices,
and be stable enough
to work for that content over time.
Having a unique, global, and stable
identifier for an activity
enables Quick Note Suggestions.
When I come back to the website
about Apple Fitness+,
the reason
the Quick Note Suggestions UI shows up
is because the identifier in the link,
created an hour ago or six months ago,
still matches the identifier
on the website.
There are three main steps
to adopt NSUserActivity:
declare supported activities
in your app's Info.plist,
create and register user activities
describing what's on screen
at different points in time,
and handle incoming requests
to continue an activity.
This could be coming from a link
in Quick Note or from another device.
Declare the activity types
that your app supports
under the NSUserActivityTypes
key in its Info.plist file.
The system uses the information
in that key to determine whether
your app is capable of handling
a given user activity object.
To create an NSUserActivity object,
use one of your plist-registered
activity type strings, and set the title.
Set one or more of the three
identifiers mentioned earlier.
Any one of these identifiers
can be used for Quick Note.
For this example,
let's say your app is an iPad app
that is also interested
in supporting state restoration.
Set targetContentIdentifier.
Set the userInfo property
with any app-specific
state information
needed to continue the activity.
Then, attach it to a responder.
Instead of having to register the activity
by manually managing
the current app activity,
let the system take care of it for you.
By setting the activity on a responder,
the object becomes managed
by UIKit and AppKit.
Because NSUserActivity is cross-platform,
this code works on both iOS and macOS.
The final step is to handle
receiving incoming activities
and restoring its state in your app.
When a link is tapped,
Quick Note launches your app
and calls the scene
(willContinueUserActivityWithType) method
of UIWindowSceneDelegate.
This is where you can give some feedback
that your app is receiving the activity.
Quick Note then provides
the activity to your app
in scene(continue userActivity:).
This is where you set up
any view controllers, views,
and use the userInfo dictionary
to restore and continue the activity.
In the case of Handoff,
if devices can't connect,
the system calls scene
(didFailToContinueUserActivityWithType)
where you can present an error message.
This method will
not be invoked for Quick Note,
but is good to implement for a
well-rounded adoption of NSUserActivity.
For macOS apps,
implement the equivalent
application
(willContinueUserActivityWithType),
application(continue userActivity),
and application
(didFailToContinueUserActivityWithType)
in the app delegate.
For more information about
adopting NSUserActivity,
check out the WWDC 2014 video, "Adopting
Handoff on iOS 8 and OS X."
NSUserActivity is a gateway because it's
the foundation for many other features.
By adopting it for Quick Note, this
is everything else that you could get.
Handoff is on by default,
while the others are opt-in.
Your app could be even more powerful
because people could create a reminder
about a document in your app,
or have a blog post from
your app show up in spotlight,
or improved multi-window handling.
Check out the latest
documentation and related WWDC videos
for more information.
Last, but certainly not least,
let's go over some
best practices for adopting
NSUserActivity for Quick Note.
I'm going to go over four behaviors,
and for each of these,
I'll talk about why
and how
to implement them in your app.
The title property is a human-readable
string for the activity.
This is the string that shows
up in the add link menu.
That said,
the title should provide a good,
descriptive representation
of the content.
In general, it's better to use the title
of the document or item directly.
There are a few tips to help
identifiers be unique, global, and stable.
Avoid using device-specific data.
If the identifier for this
photo is its local file path,
the link is only guaranteed
to work on the device it was created on.
Avoid any transient information,
like a session ID
or specific viewing properties.
The title of the photo might be implicitly
unique, but if it can be modified,
there's no guarantee it will exist when
trying to navigate back to this content.
Thinking long term, like using the app's
saved UUID for the photo,
will allow
your app to restore Quick Note links,
even if the content has been moved around.
Although URLs can be unique identifiers
for app content,
they often contain
transient state information,
breaking the identifier guidelines
covered earlier.
Quick Note prefers targetContentIdentifier
or persistentIdentifier
over webpageURL.
webpageURL is perfectly fine to use,
as long as it follows the guidelines.
If your app uses NSUserActivity for both
state restoration and Spotlight,
use the same value
for targetContentIdentifier
and persistentIdentifier.
If you have a website
that compliments your app,
add a URL as a second,
fallback identifier.
This way, if the app isn't installed,
opening a link redirects to your website.
Another important practice
is making sure the app's
current NSUserActivity is up to date.
This means keeping
up with what is happening.
Best practice is to keep the title
and identifier properties accurate
when detecting any activity change,
like selecting to view a different photo.
It's not recommended
to reuse activity instances.
When there's new content,
like the new photo, create a new activity.
Let UIKit and AppKit handle
the current app activity
by attaching activities to responders
like viewControllers or views,
like I showed in the example code.
If attaching to a responder
doesn't work for your app,
the current app activity can
be manually managed by calling
becomeCurrent() and resignCurrent()
at the appropriate times.
For example,
when finished viewing the photo,
the app will call resignCurrent()
on the current activity,
and when a new photo is picked,
the app will call becomeCurrent()
on the new activity.
For better performance, take advantage
of the activity's "needsSave" property.
An activity might need specific
view properties to properly restore
the activity in the app.
For example,
the position and zoom when viewing a map.
These properties can be passed
along with the activity,
but there's overhead when
updating after every gesture.
Instead of updating the activity,
set needsSave to true.
When the system needs to send the activity
out to Quick Note linking or Handoff,
the delegate callback
userActivityWillSave is invoked,
so that the app can update
all the properties on demand.
This callback is where the userInfo
dictionary can be updated to include
any properties that help
with restoring the activity.
There are a couple compatibility
issues to prepare for.
What if the app has been updated?
Take this note with two links from an app.
The links could be from an older or newer
version of the app than is on the device.
Perfectly fine,
but the links still need to work.
To prepare for compatibility handling,
have support to handle receiving
activities
from earlier versions of your app,
and fail gracefully when receiving
activities from newer versions.
This could be supported from
versioning your activities,
or using a dictionary of keys,
and being tolerant of keys being missing
or having some that you don't understand.
What if the content doesn't exist anymore?
The content the activity linked
to could have been deleted or moved.
When navigating back to the app,
show an error message if deleted
or redirect if the content was moved.
Adopting Quick Note plugs your app
into this new system of note taking.
A system designed to improve
the connection between people,
content, and your app.
Make sure you've adopted NSUserActivity.
Now's a great opportunity to revisit
and polish up any existing code.
Have unique,
global, and stable identifiers.
And set your activities
on responders to let the system
manage the app's current NSUserActivity.
Thank you for watching,
and I look forward to seeing your app
in Quick Note and beyond.
[percussive music]