[music]
[Frank]
Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Frank Doepke,
and I'm an Engineer
on the Vision team.
The Vision framework
has grown over the years,
with its focus
on image analysis.
To get a better grasp,
we can look
at Vision's capabilities
in terms of its usage focus.
Sports.
Tracking objects and
the analysis of the human pose
are just some of the requests
that can help you
to create a sports application.
Accessibility.
Visions request like OCR
or image classification
and object detection
are helping
visually-impaired users.
People.
Vision provides a number of face
and body-related requests
that your app can use.
You can find out more about this
in the "Detect people, faces,
and poses using Vision" session.
Health.
From barcode scanning and OCR
to analysis of the human pose,
Vision provides building blocks
to create a smart
Health application.
Computational Photography.
Features like portrait mode
rely on face detection and
segmentation.
Security.
Requests like face
and human detection
are helpful for applications
like motion detection
in security cameras.
And documents.
This is what we want
to focus on in this session.
Vision offers
a number of requests
that help you
with the analysis of documents:
barcode detection,
text recognition,
or commonly known as OCR,
contour detection,
rectangle detection,
and new for this year,
document segmentation detection.
Here's our agenda.
First, we'll talk
about barcode detection.
Then, we'll talk
about text recognition.
And last, we'll talk
about document detection.
Let's look at barcode detection.
This year, we are introducing
a new revision
of the barcode
detection request.
VNDetectBarcodesRequestRevision2
offers support
for new symbologies.
Codabar,
GS1Databar, including
Expanded and Limited,
MicroPDF, and MicroQR,
where the latter is particularly
helpful
if you want to make
a QR code for a URL
and need to place it
on a small label or package,
as it uses a lot less space.
We changed the behavior
for this new revision
to be in line
with the rest of Vision
in respect to how
the resulting bounding boxes
are reported in relation
to the region of interest
that a client has specified.
Let's look at that change
in detail.
Here, we have a document
with a QR code.
When we do not specify
a Region of Interest,
also known as ROI,
the bounding box gets reported
in relation to the full image.
Now, let's specify an ROI,
like we want to only focus on
the center part
of what the camera sees.
Revision 2
now reports the bounding box
in relation to the ROI,
just like other Vision requests.
Unfortunately, Revision 1
always reports
in relation to the full image.
But we don't want
to change that behavior,
as it would potentially
break existing clients.
And just as a reminder,
when you compile
your application
against the latest SDK
and do not specify
a specific revision,
you will always get the latest
revision on your request.
But for applications
that specify Revision 1
or do not re-compile
against a new SDK,
they will still get
the old Revision 1 behavior.
Let me highlight
a few interesting aspects
of the barcode detection
request in Vision.
Vision supports
1D and 2D barcodes.
But what makes
it really interesting
is that within one image,
it can detect multiple codes,
as well as multiple
symbologies, at once.
That means
you don't have to scan
again and again
to get multiple codes.
This is a huge advantage over
most handheld scanners.
Keep in mind that if you scan
for multiple symbologies,
it'll take longer the more
symbologies you have specified.
So you want to setup the request
with only the symbologies
that are relevant
to your use case.
With the expansion
of the new symbologies
for barcode scanning,
Vision can play a particularly
helpful role
in the health sector.
With an iPhone,
you can analyze multiple codes
at once,
and thanks to its connectivity
to the internet,
pull up the information without
needing a separate scanner.
And thanks to the iPhone's
strong low-light capabilities,
you can scan codes,
even in dark scenarios,
without shooting off a laser
or disturbing the patient
while they are resting.
Now, let's look at how Vision
performs barcode detection.
1D codes
will get scanned as lines.
That means you will likely get
multiple detections
for the same code.
It is easy to de-duplicate them
by looking at the payload,
which is the real data
that is included in the barcode.
2D codes get scanned
as a single unit.
That means you get
one bounding box back
for the whole code.
An example for a 2D code
would be a QR code.
Each barcode gets reported
with its own observation.
But as I mentioned before,
1D codes can return
multiple observations,
with the same content, but in
different physical locations.
The payload
is the content of the barcode,
that is, the data
that is included
in this machine-readable code.
In particular
for the payload of QR codes,
you might want to use
data detectors
to analyze the encoded URL.
Now, let's look
at this in a little demo.
Alright, here we have
an Xcode playground,
where you see
that I have an image
with all the barcodes in them.
I use the
VNDetectBarcodesRequest,
and I set the Revision to 2.
Now, as the symbologies,
I just have codabar,
and when we look at this,
we see the codabar
got highlighted in red.
Now, I can change this
to, let's say, QR.
What happens now
is that we run
the request again,
and we see that
the QR code gets highlighted.
But it's an array,
so I can also specify
other requests with it,
let's say ean8.
And when I do that,
we'll now see that we have both,
the ean8 and the QR code.
But what
if I want to get all of them?
I simply pass in an empty array,
and in that moment,
all symbologies get read.
And as you see,
all highlighted right now
with the code on the bottom.
Let's go back to our slides.
From barcodes,
we are now moving on
to look at text recognition.
Vision introduced
text recognition in 2019.
It operates in two modes:
Fast and Accurate.
Since then, Vision has expanded
its language support.
Let's look at how
text recognition works
and where language plays a role.
In the Fast path,
we have
a Latin-character recognizer.
The Accurate path, on the other
hand,
uses a machine-learning-based
recognizer
that operates
on words and lines.
After the recognition is done,
each path goes through
a language correction stage.
And, in the end,
we get back the recognized text.
The language selection
affects the recognition stage.
In the Fast path,
it would mean that the different
Latin character sets
are supported,
like the umlaut for German.
In the Accurate path,
a completely different model
gets used
when we have
to recognize Chinese,
as its structure
is very different
to Latin-based languages.
That means if you need
to read Chinese text,
then it is important
that Chinese
is the primary language
in the request.
The language selection also
influences language correction,
as it picks the correct
dictionary for its work.
So, what are the best practices
when using languages
in text recognition?
Even though it might look
like a fixed set of languages
is supported,
it is always better to query
which languages are supported
for a given request
configuration using
supportedRecognitionLanguages().
You can specify
multiple languages,
and, in that case,
the order matters.
When there is ambiguity,
it gets resolved
in the order of languages.
In particular
for the Accurate path,
the first language decides which
recognition model gets used.
That means
your use case dictates
which languages
you want to use in the request.
Let's look at this
in a little demo.
So, I have here now
a revised version
of our sample code,
and you can see
that I have an image
with different languages
of text in it.
Now, I specified Revision 2,
and I can see
which languages are supported.
We have English,
French, and so on.
Now, if I switch, for instance,
back to Revision 1,
we can see I only have English.
And that is the same
for the Fast
as it is for the Accurate path.
Now, let's go back
to Revision 2.
Notice that when I switch now,
for instance, to German,
I actually
get the umlaut correctly
in Grüsse aus Cupertino.
But I don't have support
in the Fast path for Chinese.
In the Accurate path,
I can now pick Chinese.
And now, we finally get
the correct Chinese letters
for "Hello World."
Let's go back to the slides.
Last but not least,
let's look
at Document Detection.
Vision introduces
a new request called
VNDocumentSegmentationRequest.
It's a machine-learning-based
detector
that we have trained
on various types of documents,
like sheets of paper, signs,
notes, receipts, labels,
et cetera.
The result of the request
is a low resolution segmentation
mask,
where each pixel
represents a confidence
if that pixel is part
of the detected document or not.
In addition it provides
the four corner points
of the quadrilateral.
On devices with a Neural Engine,
the request can run in realtime
on a camera or video feed.
The VNDocumentCamera
in VisionKit
is now using the request instead
of the VNDetectRectanglesRequest
on modern devices
with a Neural Engine.
Speaking of the
VNDetectRectanglesRequest,
how do these
two requests differ,
as they both can be used
to detect a document?
The DetectDocumentsRequest
is, as I mentioned,
machine-learning-based
and performs fastest
on the Neural Engine.
But it can also be used
on the GPU or CPU,
but it is not fast enough there
for realtime performance.
The rectangle detector
is a traditional computer vision
algorithm
that runs only on the CPU
and can keep up
with the realtime performance,
as long as the CPU is not
saturated with other tasks.
The document request is trained
on a variety of documents,
and they don't have
to be all rectangles,
which is one
of its main strengths.
The rectangle detector,
on the other hand,
works by finding edges
and intersections
that form a quadrilateral,
which can be a challenge
with obscured corners
or folds in the document.
The documents requests
provides a segmentation mask
and the corner points,
while the rectangle detector
only provides corner points.
And the document detector
is trained to look
for one document only.
With the rectangle detector
will return multiple rectangles.
These rectangles
can even be nested.
Let's look at this
a little bit more.
As I mentioned,
the document detector
finds one document,
which we see here
with the quadrilateral
of the detected object.
But the rectangle detector
will deliver back
multiple observations
of all the rectangles
it finds in the image,
and I highlighted a few here.
It's up to the app to decide
which rectangle is the document.
How about we try
all this in a demo?
All right, we wanted
to create a little survey,
how well we are doing at WWDC.
Now, unfortunately,
you are not with me,
so I had to ask
the camera team here
to fill out the survey for you.
So, I created a little app
in which I can now
scan our survey cards.
And what do we get?
QuickDraw for beginners
felt outdated.
Well, it is bit old by now.
Let's go for the next one.
Ah, Vision was entertaining
and informative.
And last but not least,
Cobol, just what I needed.
Somebody is in
the wrong session here.
Okay, now let's look
how we did this in the code.
So, I created again
a little playground here
because it's easier
to build this stuff up for us.
What you can already see
is that I loaded up an image,
and I used the CIImage,
because I need to do some
image manipulation on it.
I created a requestHandler,
and I used the new
VNDetectDocument
SegmentationRequest().
Once I perform the request,
I get now the results back,
and I created
a little helper function
that I used core image
to use now
as a perspective
corrected image,
and we get back
just a cropped-out card
in a perspective corrected form.
So, that's easy.
So, what do we have to do next?
We need to detect the bar codes,
detect the rectangles,
and recognize the text.
Once we perform this request,
we then have to scan
the check boxes
to see which ones were ticked.
All right,
I prepared this a little bit,
so let's start
with detecting the bar codes.
And I'm using,
as the symbologies,
just the QR code.
I loaded into the document title
because I know that is--
the content of my QR code
will be the title
of what we get out of it.
Next, we need
to detect the rectangles.
Again, we have a little piece
of code rectangle for that.
So, I create two arrays.
I want to get
all the checkBoxImages,
which is data needed
for the analysis.
And I get
all the rectangles out.
So, I used
the VNDetectRectanglesRequest.
Now, what I do here is
I sort them
in the vertical order
so that I get the results
in the correct order back.
OK, now we need
to recognize our text.
That is simple.
We store
all the resulting textBlocks,
and we use
the VNRecognizeTextRequest.
So now, what we have to do
is simply perform the request.
And as you can see, I used
the documentRequestHandler,
which is the one that used
the cropped-out image,
and performed
the requests on it.
And if I go back up here,
I can already see
that I get my correct QR code,
but something is not quite right
with my rectangles.
I don't get any rectangles.
So, what do I have to do?
Well, by default,
the rectangles detector
only looks for rectangles
that are at least 20%
of the image.
So, we need to correct that.
So, I go in
and set the minimumSize
to, let's say,
something like 10%.
And once we do that,
we get a rectangle.
Okay, well, that's only one.
Well, the other thing
with the rectangle detector is
that I need to tell it
how many it should return.
By default,
the rectangle detection
will only return one,
the most prominent rectangle.
But I want to get all of them.
I do this by setting
the maximumObservations to 0.
And once I have done that,
I now get
all of our checkboxes and the
bar code,
because that looks
like a rectangle.
Okay, so we are good.
Now comes the last part,
and I need to actually
scan the checkboxes.
So, for that,
I actually prepared
a little machine-learning demo.
I have a model here
that I trained earlier
with Create ML.
It's an image classifier,
and all I did was
I used some of these
checkbox images,
which were marked,
and some of them are not marked,
for my "yes" and "no" label.
And I also gathered a few images
that are neither of them.
That's my NotIt.
Again, we can use this
in our code.
So, what do we have?
We create our request
by loading the model
and create
our Create ML request.
And then we iterate,
over all the checkbox images,
create an ImageRequestHandler
from it,
and perform our classification.
Now, I can look
at my top classification.
If that is "Yes,"
then I just find which text line
lines up with the checkbox
that I have,
and what do we get, in the end?
Vision was entertaining
and informative.
Let's go back to the slides.
Let's recap on what we saw.
Document analysis
is a focus in the Vision API.
Barcode detection in Vision
is more versatile
than a scanner,
and we are introducing a new
document segmentation detection.
If you want to learn more
about how to use OCR,
please look at our session
from WWDC 2019.
The "Vision and core image"
session from WWDC 2020
gives you additional insights
in doing your own custom
document analysis
by preprocessing images
and detecting contours.
Thank you,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[music]