[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Tao Jia: Hello, my name is Tao.
Today, my colleague Jack and I
are going to talk about
building dynamic iOS apps
with the Create ML framework.
So what do I mean
by an app being dynamic?
Dynamic apps are those apps
that give their users
the flexibility to customize
certain elements of the app.
Dynamic apps also
tailor their contents
to best suit
different user needs.
These adaptable in-app features
give your users
more intelligent
and personalized experiences
tailored just for them.
You can deliver
certain such experiences
by simple heuristics
and predefined rules.
But often times,
these approaches may not render
the best experience
for all of your app users
as their backgrounds
and preferences can vary.
On the other hand,
machine learning techniques
enable you to create models that
learn directly from user data.
This often is more
generalizable
and likely suit more users than
heuristics and predefined rules.
So what tools can you use
to deliver such experience?
The Create ML app,
available on your Mac,
makes it easy to create models
by simply selecting
some training data
and hitting the train button.
It supports all sorts
of model types
through a rich set of templates.
The app is built on top
of the Create ML framework
which provides
accelerated training
of machine learning models.
The Create ML Framework
was originally introduced
in macOS Mojave
allowing for models
to be trained in Swift code
and from within your macOS app.
And now we're bringing
that framework
to iOS 15 and iPadOS 15.
With it available on device,
your apps can do all sorts
of new and dynamic things.
In other words, you can access
programmatic APIs
directly from your application
for on-device model creation.
It gives your app
the capability to learn from
and thus adapt to your users.
Last but most importantly,
user data never have
to leave their devices;
therefore, user privacy
is preserved.
Now, let's dive in.
There are different tasks
available in Create ML.
Here are all the ones
available on macOS,
and these are now
available on iOS.
Among them are the popular tasks
such as image, sound,
and text classifiers.
More recently added ones
include style transfer
as well as this year's
new addition
of hand pose
and hand action classifiers.
With these tools available,
there are many interesting ideas
and use cases.
Here are a few examples.
With image classification,
an app can learn
what a child's favorite
stuffed animals look like
and then help find
more photos of them
in order to help create a story
about their adventures together.
Text classifier can be used
to help a user
quickly organize
a note they just wrote
with suggested tags and folders
learned from their past actions.
The hand action classifier,
which is new this year,
could give your user the power
to trigger in-app visual effects
with custom hand actions.
There are so many cool things
you can do with Create ML on iOS
but it's better to just show you
what I mean with a demo.
I have an app that looks
a bit like a photo booth app,
but more dynamic
as it allows me to create
a customized photo filter.
Let me show you how that works.
Here on my iPad,
it shows at the top
a list of existing filters
I trained on my Mac
using a Create ML
style transfer task.
Each one of them is represented
by the particular style image
used to create the filter.
On the bottom,
the app is waiting for a photo
to try those filters,
either by taking
or choosing a photo.
Let me take a photo now.
How about a selfie?
[CAMERA SHUTTER]
Let's see how
these filters look.
Let me first click
this first picture of wave form.
Oh, I got all these water drops
on my face and hair;
reminds me of my vacation
in Miami a long time ago.
What about this picture
of birdies?
Look how colorful I am.
How about this third picture
that looks like cracked ice?
Oh, I look cool and icy.
Now these look really fun,
but I feel I am still
missing something.
What if I could
just create a filter
using any photo of my choice?
That would make this app
really fun to use.
Let me give it a shot.
I have this drawing
from my daughter
when she was 3 years old.
I really love
the textures and colors.
I'm curious to see
how I would look
in my daughter's artistic style.
Let me click this
"+ Filter" button,
select Camera,
and take a picture.
[CAMERA SHUTTER]
"Use Photo."
Now the filter is being created.
Under the hood, it is training a
customized style transfer model.
Let me explain how that works.
First, select a single
style image.
The style image I used
is my daughter's drawing.
Next, I need to provide
a set of content images
for the model to learn
how to apply the style onto
while preserving the original
contents of these images.
In this demo, I used a few
tens of photos from my album,
including scenic photos
and selfies.
If you want to apply the style
on other photo types --
for example,
photos of your pet --
you may also include
a few such photos
in your content set as well.
Then, select your filter type
as either image or video,
depending on your application
scenario.
For this demo, I chose image,
as I want to apply the style
on static photos.
You can also experiment
with style strength
and style density, as well as
the number of iterations
to get your favorite
combination of stylization
and original contents.
For details on how to set
these parameters,
please refer to last year's
WWDC session.
Now let's give the newly created
filter a try on my photo.
Wow, that's how I would look
on my daughter's drawing.
It actually picked up
these textures and colors.
How about me trying
a different photo?
I have this bunny
that my daughter
really loves to play with.
How about me taking a selfie
with the bunny
and apply the filter?
[CAMERA SHUTTER]
The bunny has gotten stylized
by her drawing too.
I can't wait to show this to her
and try on her other drawings.
It'll be a lot of fun.
In this demo,
I showed you how to leverage
style transfer model
available in the Create ML
framework on iOS
to create a customized
photo filter.
So what does that
look like in code?
First, define training
data source
that specifies one style image
and a set of content images.
Next, define your
session parameters,
to specify things like
where you want your checkpoints
to be saved.
Next, define your training job
using these parameters.
Finally,
dispatch the training job,
and once a successful
completion is received,
save out the trained model
to stylize images, compile and
instantiate a Core ML model,
start making predictions.
And that's it.
That's what I used to create
a customized photo filter,
using style transfer API
from Create ML framework.
Other tasks follow
a similar API pattern.
So far I've talked about tasks
that enable model creation
from rich media data types,
such as image, text,
audio, and video.
But what if your app does not
interact with such data types?
Let me invite my colleague Jack
to talk about how you can make
your app dynamic in these cases.
Jack Cackler: Thank you, Tao.
In addition to the tasks
we've covered so far,
the Create ML framework on iOS
also supports classifiers
and regressors
for structured tabular data.
Let's walk through an example
of how these could create
a more dynamic app experience.
First, some background
on classifiers and regressors.
A classifier learns to predict
particular classes
from data in a training dataset.
A regressor is similar,
but learns to predict
a numerical value instead
of a discrete class label.
Here are the APIs for training
classifiers and regressors
from general tabular data,
allowing them to be used
in many different scenarios.
In particular,
Create ML on iOS
offers four different algorithms
for each of these.
Working with
general tabular models
can require
a little more work to use,
as you have to decide
which features and target values
you want to use in the model.
However, this can often
be straightforward.
Let's consider an app
using a tabular regressor
to add a personalized
experience.
Here's a simple app for ordering
meals from restaurants.
The app has restaurants
in the area.
Here's a local Thai restaurant
called Amazing Thai.
If I select it,
the app shows dishes I can order
from the restaurant
and information about each dish.
It's a simple app, but what if
I can make it better?
What's really neat
is if over time
my app learned my behavior
and helped surface
intelligent restaurant and dish
suggestions I might like.
This would take this
from a simple app
into a really
dynamic experience.
I can achieve this by training
a tabular regressor
right in the app.
I'm going to take
three kinds of information
and combine them
in a structured table
to train the model and deliver
a new dynamic experience.
The first is the content,
which is data I've loaded
into the app.
In the case of
our restaurant app,
it's information
about the dishes.
The second is the context.
In this case, the time
of the day the user is ordering.
Finally, I add
the user's order history
and create an experience
that's tailored just for them
right on their device.
By combining
the content and the context,
as well as past user
interaction,
I can predict
future interaction;
a great opportunity
for personalization,
in this case
to help predict dishes
a user might like in the future.
Let's go back to the app
with the model added in.
I'm ordering lunch today
and I'm in the mood for pizza.
I set the meal to Lunch
and select the Pizza Parlor,
pick a margherita pizza,
and order it.
There's a few pieces of
information on this window
that are really what's training
our tabular regressor.
The content is the keywords
for this dish;
things like the ingredients --
tomato, mozzarella --
as well as the restaurant
itself  -- Pizza Parlor --
and the genre of food --
pizza.
The context for this model
is the time of day.
This is from lunch,
and now I've taught my model
that these are things
I might like at lunch.
Finally, my interaction is
that I ordered this dish
and not the others.
The regressor I'm training
is predicting a preference score
for each dish
that I might order,
and today it learned
that I did order this dish
and not the others.
Going back to the main screen,
the model has already trained
and there's a new window
that suggests dishes
just for me.
The dish I actually ordered --
the margherita pizza --
is the first recommendation,
but the next recommendation
is a caprese sandwich
from a completely
different restaurant.
Several other pizzas
are also near the top.
Let's try another example.
Say I'm ordering dinner now.
This time I order a yellow curry
from Amazing Thai.
Now the model has updated again.
It's learned my new preference,
contextual on the time of day
I'm ordering.
The yellow curry I just ordered
is now the top recommendation
and a similar curry
is the second recommendation.
The next recommendation
is the vegetarian pizza.
It has mushrooms and peppers
just like the curry
I just ordered,
and the app knows
I might like pizza
even if it might not be
my first choice for dinner.
If I then go to order lunch
the next day,
the model has learned
to distinguish
what I might order for lunch
versus what I might order
for dinner.
This gives a really
personalized experience
that helps me find exactly what
I want at the time I want it,
and that's with just two orders.
There's three real steps
to adding a tabular classifier
or regressor to an app:
setting up the data,
training, and prediction.
The first function here
creates the features
leveraged in this regressor
from the meal and keywords.
I take the keywords
associated with each dish,
combine them with the current
meal (the context)
to create a new keyword
that allows the model
to capture the interaction
between the content (dish)
keywords
and the context (meal) keywords.
We put in the value of 1.0
in the dictionary
to simply indicate that
a particular keyword is present
in the data entry.
First, for each dish
the user ordered,
I add in an entry with the
features generated previously
and a positive target value.
However,
if I just included this,
the model wouldn't learn
to discern what dishes I like
and what dishes I don't.
To do this,
I also add an entry
using all the keywords that
were not present in the dish
with a negative target value
of -1.
This allows the model to learn
which keywords
best fit user preferences.
I convert this combined
information into a DataFrame,
specifying both the keywords
and the target.
Finally, I train the model,
specifying that the column
I'm trying to predict
is the target column
that I had set to 1 or -1.
In this case, the model is
a simple linear regressor
which generates meaningful
results I can use in the app.
At prediction time,
I simply take the data
I want to run an inference on
and call a prediction
from the model I trained.
So far we've shown how to train
a style transfer model
and a tabular regressor
in iPadOS and iOS apps.
Let's talk about
some best practices
to integrate machine learning
training into your app.
Don't forget to follow
best practices
for machine learning in general.
For example, always test
how your model performs
on data not in
the training dataset.
For long-running training tasks,
leverage the asynchronous
training control
and checkpointing mechanism
to customize your
model creation workflow.
Some aspects of model creation
can be computationally
intensive,
consume additional memory,
or require additional assets
to be downloaded.
Do take these into consideration
when integrating into your app.
Please refer to our APIs
and documentation for more info.
If you want to learn more
about best practices,
I highly encourage you to check
our other WWDC sessions
from past years on
"Designing Great ML Experiences"
and "Control training
in Create ML with Swift".
In this session, we have talked
about how you can use
the Create ML framework on iOS.
We gave examples
using style transfer
and a tabular regressor,
and most of the Create ML
templates can now be trained
directly on an iPhone or iPad.
Through training on iOS,
you can create dynamic apps
that give users customized
and personalized experiences
while preserving user privacy.
Because training and inference
are entirely in-app,
there's no model deployment
to worry about either.
We're really looking forward
to seeing what you come up with.
Thank you for listening
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
♪