[upbeat music]
[Nils] Hello, my name is
Nils Beck, and I welcome you
to "Qualities of great iPad and
iPhone apps on Macs with M1."
More than a million
iPad and iPhone apps
are already available
on the Mac App Store.
The experience is great
on macOS Big Sur,
and we've further improved
it in macOS Monterey.
In this video, we'll discuss
how we mapped several iOS APIs
to the corresponding
Mac features, some general
best practices to keep in mind
that will also help
your app shine on Macs with M1,
improvements that we
made in macOS Big Sur
software updates,
as well as in macOS Monterey,
and then we'll finish off with
Mac App Store
deployment considerations.
iPad and iPhone apps on Macs
with M1 are the easiest way
to expand your existing
app's reach to the Mac.
This is your unmodified
iPad or iPhone app,
as submitted and approved
for the iOS App Store,
offered through
the Mac App Store
to anyone with an M1 Mac.
To make this possible, we focus
heavily on compatibility.
System APIs are mapped
to their natural Mac equivalents
wherever possible.
Our aim is to ensure
a smooth app experience
on the Mac without you
making any changes.
And most
existing apps work great!
This includes everything
from small iPhone utilities
to cutting-edge iPad
games and Pro Apps.
A variety of extensions
are also supported.
For example, share extensions,
WidgetKit widgets,
photo editing extensions,
VPN network extensions,
audio units, and more.
So, it's very likely that your
existing iPad or iPhone app
already works well on the Mac,
right out of the box.
Of course, we support all
basic functionality,
such as text interactions,
copy and paste, a Mac menu bar,
and so on, but there is also
a lot of advanced functionality,
like background app refresh,
user notifications,
camera access, Siri intents,
and more.
Many of these topics are
discussed in the video,
"iPad and iPhone apps
on Apple silicon Macs,"
so check that out for more
details.
And when you want your
app to take advantage
of even more of what
the Mac has to offer,
consider building a Mac Catalyst
version of your app.
You can learn more about
that in the videos,
"Qualities of a great
Mac Catalyst app"
and "What's New
in Mac Catalyst."
Now, let's dive into more detail
for some of the APIs
I just mentioned.
You are likely already using
these to make your app great
on iPad and iPhone,
and we've bridged them
to seamlessly give you the same
great features on the Mac.
Naturally,
you can use the Mac keyboard
for text input into text fields,
as well as for UIKeyCommand
keyboard shortcuts.
But if you need more
control and want to write
your own keypress handling,
you can do that
with the UIPress API
on UIResponder.
All Macs have a physical
keyboard, so apps that have
taken the time to add support
for physical keyboards on iPad
and iPhone are greatly improved
on the Mac at the same time.
Next,
let's talk about the menu bar.
As a reminder, the Mac
menu bar is intended to help
with the discoverability of app
features and keyboard shortcuts.
The menu bar structure
is determined at launch,
and should remain more
or less constant after that.
Items are not added or removed,
but rather, they get enabled
or disabled, depending
on whether they currently apply.
We automatically populate
your app's menu bar,
taking into account
your app's features.
For example, we might add
menu items to create
a new window,
to work with rich texts,
or to change the device
orientation.
Note that UIKeyCommands
that are directly attached
to UIResponders through
the keyCommands property
do not appear in the menu bar,
but their keyboard shortcuts
will take priority over
the shortcuts of menu items,
whenever they apply.
You might already be
using the more recent
UIMenuBuilder API that we
introduced in iOS 13.
This adds semantic structure
to your UIKeyCommands.
This structure is visible
in the Keyboard Shortcuts menu
that appears when you
hold down the Command key
on an iPad with a keyboard.
On the Mac, the default
structure that gets passed into
the builder will be different,
but your customizations
to the structure will be
reflected in the main menu.
UIKeyCommands rely
on the responder chain
to find an applicable
target for their action,
and this determines whether
or not a menu item is enabled.
For much more on this,
check out the videos,
"Take your iPad apps
to the next level,"
"Focus on iPad keyboard
navigation,"
and "Qualities of a great
Mac Catalyst app."
For apps that use drag
and drop on iPad and iPhone,
using UIDragInteraction
and UIDropInteraction,
this automatically carries
over to the Mac as well.
This lets people seamlessly
drag content between
your app and others,
like in this example,
where I'm dragging a QR code
from Qrafter to my desktop.
And for apps
that print with
UIPrintInteractionController,
this is automatically
bridged to a Mac print dialog
when printing
is initiated in your code.
Even better, when you adopt
the new Info.plist key
"UIApplicationSupports
PrintCommand"
and implement the corresponding
standard print action,
the Print and Export as PDF
menu items will be added
to your app's menu
bar automatically.
For more details on this
new API,
check out "What's new
in Mac Catalyst."
Many apps use a settings bundle,
and we will automatically
generate a Mac-style
preference panel from this.
It is also common to put
credits in the settings bundle,
and we identify such cases
and move that text
to the About box for you.
But if you want more
control over what is shown
in the About box on the Mac,
you now also have
the option to add a credits
file to your bundle.
You can use RTF,
RTFD, or HTML files,
the same way Mac apps do this.
There are a number
of iPad-centric APIs
that will help make your
app a great iPad app.
These all come across
wonderfully on the Mac.
So, by making a great iPad app,
you're also making your app
better on Macs with M1.
If your app supports
multiple scenes
according to the
UIApplicationSupports
MultipleScenes Info.plist key,
each scene is translated
into a separate window,
and we automatically
add a menu item
to create a new scene.
On the Mac,
a system-wide setting determines
whether all windows are
closed when the app quits,
or whether existing windows
are restored on the next launch.
We respect this setting if your
app supports multiple scenes,
so don't be surprised
if all scenes disconnect,
or if state restoration does not
occur in some cases.
iPad multitasking support,
on the other hand,
automatically translates
to resizable windows on macOS.
Since your app already supports
dynamic layout changes on iPad,
you get live resizing
windows on the Mac.
You can limit the range
of allowable scene sizes using
the minimumSize and maximumSize
API on UIWindowScene.
Note that only the window
scene size will change
when the window is resized.
The UI screen size,
on the other hand, will continue
to report the device size, which
doesn't change in this case.
So, make sure you don't use
the screen size
for your layout calculations,
even on iPad,
or your UI elements will
end up in the wrong place.
If your app expects to be
in control of the entire
screen of the device,
we will use a fixed
scene size and aspect ratio.
But window contents may be
scaled up or down as needed,
in a way that is transparent
to your app.
And if your app supports
multiple
user interface orientations,
the window orientation
can be changed
using the automatically added
menu bar items,
or by dragging the edges
of the window.
Here, I am using the menu bar
items to change the orientation
of the Chess.com app,
and the user interface
adapts to make optimal use
of each device orientation.
These and other mappings
are able to remove
most of the friction
when bringing your iPad
or iPhone app to the Mac,
but let's touch on
some coding practices
that you should follow
to ensure that your app
works well across all platforms,
including the Mac.
When using Apple frameworks,
it is important that you
only use
officially supported APIs,
as undocumented methods
in our frameworks
may not exist on the Mac,
or could change at any time.
Avoid hard-coding paths
to file system locations,
as these
may be different on the Mac.
For example, do not prefix
your paths with "/private,"
or "var mobile."
Instead,
use the appropriate APIs
to determine each path
at runtime.
Similarly, for UI that is not
under your direct control,
it is best not to make
assumptions in your code about
the onscreen positioning
of views and alerts,
or the exact setup
of such view hierarchies,
as these can be drastically
different on the Mac.
Please also be aware
that the available camera
resolutions and orientations
might be quite different
on the Mac.
For example, if your iPhone app
is in portrait orientation
when a picture is taken,
you might expect the resulting
camera picture to be in portrait
orientation as well.
But this is not necessarily
the case
when the app is in portrait
orientation on the Mac.
You might receive images in
landscape orientation instead,
because that's
how the camera is positioned.
We've already included
a number of heuristics
to improve compatibility
with many apps.
For example,
we will give you the picture
of the Mac's front-facing
camera,
even when you asked
for the rear-facing camera.
AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession
and related AVFoundation APIs
to gather information about
the available cameras
and their true properties,
such as the preview dimensions.
And you should aim to handle
all possible configurations
well in your UI.
Also keep in mind
that some hardware features
are unavailable on the Mac.
Your code should be
able to handle such
situations gracefully,
and offer alternatives.
For example,
augmented reality with ARKit
is not supported on the Mac.
If ARKit is the core
functionality of your app,
you have likely made it
a required device capability,
so your app will not appear
on the Mac App Store.
But if the ARKit
is an optional feature,
you should already be checking
the isSupported property
of the appropriate
ARConfiguration subclass.
And for the best experience
on the Mac, and elsewhere,
make sure you only show
augmented reality features
in your UI on devices
that have this capability.
If your app relies on direct
Multi-Touch or on CoreMotion,
consider additionally offering
alternatives that are more
suitable for the Mac
keyboard and trackpad.
That said, Touch Alternatives
may be able to help
in this case.
I'll talk more about
that in a moment.
And if you use CoreLocation,
your app should remain usable
even if no accurate
location data is available.
For example, you can
offer manual location entry
as an alternative,
like the Lowe's app does here.
Next, let's go over some
of the improvements
we've made since we first
started shipping Macs with M1.
In macOS Big Sur 11.3, we made
several improvements to the way
that windows of iPad and iPhone
apps behave on the Mac.
If your app has
a fixed content size
because it does
not support multitasking
but it does support
large device sizes,
at launch we will now pick the
largest supported device size
that fits onto the screen
where the app is launching.
As far as your app is concerned,
the device size
still remains fixed
for the entire session,
but the window makes much better
use of the available space.
There is
also a preference to use
the smallest supported
device size instead.
And as I mentioned earlier,
the window contents
will be scaled
up or down as needed.
For example, when I make the
window full screen,
the window contents are
automatically scaled up
to fit the available space
while maintaining
the original scene aspect ratio.
Or, if the window is
moved to a smaller screen
after launch,
we will automatically reduce
the scale as needed to ensure
that the window still fits.
It is now also possible
to use the Window Zoom feature
to toggle between
two zoom factors,
one prioritizing the natural
size of UI elements,
the other prioritizing
pixel-perfect accuracy.
Here, I am using this
feature to switch between
the two zoom factors
in the Chess.com app.
Game controllers have been
supported from day one through
the GameController.framework,
which is
available on all of our
gaming-capable platforms.
Starting
with macOS Big Sur 11.3,
we've made it possible
to use the Mac's keyboard
and trackpad as
a virtual game controller.
So, even if you don't
have an actual controller handy,
it is easy to use the keyboard
to access all the functionality
that your game maps
to controller buttons.
And in macOS Monterey,
we've further refined this
with the addition
of a sensitivity slider
and pointer hiding,
as shown on this picture
of the corresponding
preference panel.
For more on this framework,
check out "Advancements
in Game Controllers."
Moreover, since day one,
Touch Alternatives
have mapped the keyboard and
trackpad
to several interaction
styles
that would otherwise not
be easy to use on the Mac,
such as Multi-Touch,
drag, tap, and swipe.
And with MacOS 11.3, we've made
a number of improvements.
For example,
you now have the ability
to virtually tilt your device.
This opens the door to a number
of additional games.
Also, the preference panel
now includes a helpful graphical
representation that illustrates
how to access each of the five
interaction styles through
the keyboard and trackpad.
In addition,
we've made it possible for apps
to automatically opt themselves
into Touch Alternatives.
When you opt in,
an onboarding dialog
is shown on first launch,
in order to help with the
discovery of this feature.
The graphics are similar
to those
from the preference panel,
but we only highlight
the interaction styles
that you've selected.
In this example, only Tilt
and Multi-Touch are shown.
If you determine that your
app would benefit from
any of these Touch Alternatives,
here's how you can enable
Touch Alternatives for your app,
right from the start.
All you need to do is
add a new.plist file
to your bundle, named
"com.apple.uikit.inputalternativ
es.plist."
Then, add the keys and values
shown in the snippet.
And for the requiredOnboarding
array,
include only the features that
are useful for your app.
That way,
only those features are
highlighted
in the onboarding dialog.
Let me demonstrate this for you.
Take, for example,
this iPad game called
"Assoluto Racing," running
unmodified on a Mac with M1.
The app enables Touch
Alternatives automatically,
right from the start,
so on first launch,
this onboarding dialog shows
us the keyboard controls.
But first, let's show the
software keyboard
and take the window full screen.
The contents are now scaled
up to fit the screen,
and we maintain the iPad
aspect ratio.
Let's head over to the
"Airport" level
for some freestyle drifting.
This app uses CoreMotion,
so that on iPad,
I can tilt the device to steer.
With Touch Alternatives
enabled on Macs with M1,
the W, A, S, and D
keys simulate tilting.
And here
I control the car that way,
while using my trackpad
to click the accelerator
button on the screen.
And all of this is completely
transparent to the app.
Let's see how I do.
That worked great!
I need to work on my drifting
skills a bit, though.
With macOS Monterey, we have
made even more improvements.
Apple Pay is now available
for iPad and iPhone apps
on M1 Macs using the same
enhanced cross-platform API
we introduced for Mac Catalyst
applications in macOS Big Sur.
This means you can now
accept payments on every
platform
where Apple Pay is available,
using a single implementation.
Just make sure
you've implemented the
"paymentAuthorizationController,
didRequestMerchantSessionUpdate"
delegate call on your
PKPaymentAuthorizationController
Delegate.
For more details,
check out the video,
"What's new
in Wallet and Apple Pay."
We've also made full-screen
video with AVKit even better.
AVPlayerView
and AVPlayerViewController
can now automatically
take a video full screen
using a separate window.
This means that even apps
whose window is otherwise
restricted to the launch-time
resolution and aspect ratio
will make full
use of the Mac display,
as appropriate for the video
content.
And in case you need
more control over
the full screen experience,
we've added new API
to AVPlayerViewDelegate and
AVPlayerViewControllerDelegate.
On top of that,
AVFoundation supports
HDR playback and streaming on
Macs with M1.
No Mac-specific adoption
work is needed in your app.
Finally, AVKit controls
in iPad and iPhone apps now
look the same as they
do in other Mac apps.
We even take full
advantage of the Mac trackpad
with support for new gestures.
For more details,
you can hop over to the video,
"What's new in AVKit."
And if your app uses
the intents framework to offer
custom SiriKit Shortcuts,
on macOS Monterey,
those are now supported for iPad
and iPhone apps on M1 Macs.
For more on Shortcuts,
check out the talks,
"Meet Shortcuts for macOS"
and
"Design great actions
for Shortcuts, Siri,
and Suggestions."
Good news!
It's easy
to be on the Mac App Store.
In fact, most apps are
there automatically.
As I mentioned earlier,
in most cases,
it makes sense to be on the Mac.
After all,
even a Bluetooth door-lock app,
designed to be mobile,
might prove useful
if you've locked yourself out
of your home without your phone,
but you have your
Mac with M1 in hand.
So, if you've previously
opted your app out
of the Mac App Store, now may
be the time to reconsider.
With improvements
such as Touch Alternatives
and enhanced full-screen video
playback,
your app may very well be
a great fit for the Mac.
In that case, simply recheck
the "Make this app available"
checkbox in App Store Connect
to make the app available
on the Mac App Store.
Regardless of whether you
previously opted out,
you will want to confirm
that your app really
works well on Macs with M1.
Once you're confident
that the user experience
is up to your standards,
click the Verify
Compatibility link
in App Store Connect,
shown here.
This removes the "Not
verified for macOS" text,
which is shown next to your
app on the Mac App Store,
and replaces it with
"Designed for iPad."
App shoppers will take
this as a sign that you have
taken the time to make
sure that they will
have a good experience
with your app on the Mac.
You only have to do
this once per app.
Oh, and we've also made
iPad and iPhone apps
much more discoverable
on the Mac App Store.
When customers search
for them by name,
they no longer have to switch
to the iPhone and iPad Apps tab.
Apple will automatically
pick the recommended
minimum macOS version
required for compatibility,
and for most situations,
this is fine.
But in certain rare cases,
you may wish to override this
with a custom
macOS availability.
For example, your video app
may work fine on Big Sur,
but if you want to ensure that
you have access
to the AVKit full
screen improvements,
you may decide that it
should only be available
on Monterey and beyond.
In this case,
you have two options.
Starting shortly,
you will be able to choose
a different minimum macOS
version on the Pricing
and Availability page
of App Store Connect.
This is great for apps that are
already on the store
because you don't have
to resubmit a new version.
Or, you can specify
the LSMinimumSystemVersion
in the Info.plist,
and submit this change
as part of your next update.
This is the recommended
approach for apps
that are
under active development.
Note that this does not replace
the MinimumOSVersion key,
which specifies the iOS
minimum system version.
But really, both options
should rarely be needed.
Finally, let's talk
for a moment about testing.
Testing on macOS is very
similar to testing on iPad.
You can use the same workflows
you are already familiar with.
For local testing in Xcode,
simply select
My Mac (Designed for iPad)
as the run destination,
and debugging, unit testing,
et cetera,
all work just like they
do for other devices.
For beta testing,
we've added TestFlight support
for all apps
in macOS Monterey,
including iPhone and iPad apps,
so you can now distribute
your app to beta testers
who are using Macs with M1.
For more information on this,
head over to the video,
"Meet TestFlight on Mac."
So, welcome to the Mac!
Go verify your app and opt in.
It's easy.
And just remember,
as you continue to improve
your iPad and iPhone apps,
you're also making
those apps better on Macs
with M1.
Thank you very much.
[upbeat music]