[upbeat music]
[Nandini] Hello,
I am Nandini Sundara Raman,
and today,
I will be showing you
how you can tailor
the VoiceOver experience
in your data-rich apps
using AXCustomContent API.
VoiceOver
is Apple's screen reader
that lets you interact
with any Apple device,
even if
you can't see the screen.
You can use VoiceOver
by touching the screen
to listen
to what is under your finger
and then perform
simple gestures like swipe
to navigate the interface.
So, here I have a simple
app that I created
called Woof Woof Kennel
where we have detailed
descriptions of several dogs
listed in a table view,
and VoiceOver user can
swipe through the list
to explore the kennel.
Let's have a quick look
of the VoiceOver experience
of this app.
[VoiceOver] Bailey, beagle,
happy-go-lucky,
excellent hunting dog,
and loyal companion.
Popularity, number one.
Age, three years.
Weight, 25 pounds.
Height, 14 inches.
Winston, pug,
loving, intelligent,
affectionate, loyal, charming,
playful, and mischievous.
Popularity, number two.
Age, three years.
Weight, 14 pounds.
Height, 10 inches.
[Nandini] Whoa!
That was a lot of data
read by VoiceOver
for each dog
where all the contents
of the cell
was read from top left
to bottom right.
While navigating an interface
with VoiceOver,
too much data
can be overwhelming,
with cognitive load on users,
and make your app
hard to navigate.
And too little data
will result in incomplete
experience of your app.
Both extremes are frustrating,
and finding a balance here
might be difficult
because different users might
want different information
when using your app.
To achieve this balance,
we have the Accessibility
Custom Content API.
This class and protocol
in Accessibility framework
is available on all platforms.
A common issue with presenting
complex data with Voiceover
is solved by this API
by delivering accessibility
information to your users
in measured portions.
With this API, you can leverage
assistive technologies
to present only the content
your app users need
when they need it.
Now, let's look at how
AXCustomContent API
can be implemented
in our data-rich apps.
And to do that,
first I would like to show you
how my app looks
with AXCustomContent API
implemented.
[VoiceOver] Bailey, beagle.
More content available.
[Nandini] Yes!
You heard that right.
VoiceOver just announced
that we have more content
available on this cell.
By this, it means that
you can access
additional content on this cell
using the More Content rotor.
Voiceover rotors enable users
to navigate applications
quickly and efficiently.
It has many built-in uses
such as setting
the VoiceOver language,
adjusting the speaking rate,
and also moving between
the links on a web page, etc.
Here, with More Content rotor,
we can navigate
between additional content
of an element
under the VoiceOver cursor.
To get to the More Content
rotor with VoiceOver
in iOS devices,
twist two fingers
on the screen
as if rotating a dial
till you reach
the desired rotor option
that is
the More Content rotor.
[VoiceOver] More content.
[Nandini]
And then, swipe down or up
to navigate to the next
or previous additional content
available
under the VoiceOver cursor.
Now, as I swipe down the cell,
VoiceOver will present
additional content
present on it.
[VoiceOver] Three years, age.
Number one, popularity.
25 pounds, weight.
14 inches, height.
Happy-go-lucky,
excellent hunting dog,
and loyal companion.
Description.
[Nandini] Let's see how the
macOS version of the same app
works after implementing
AXCustomContent API on it.
[VoiceOver] Bailey, beagle.
More content available.
[Nandini]
Once the VoiceOver cursor
is on the element
with more content,
we can bring up the rotor
with VO + command + /
to reveal its custom content.
[VoiceOver] More Content menu.
Five items.
Age, three years.
Popularity, number one.
Weight, 25 pounds.
Height, 14 inches.
Description, happy-go-lucky,
excellent hunting dog,
and loyal companion.
[Nandini]
In iOS, to get notified
when VoiceOver element
has additional content,
go to VoiceOver preferences
and open Verbosity settings.
Under Verbosity settings,
select More Content.
And choose either
to speak hints,
play sound,
or change pitch
to get notified
when additional
content is available.
Similarly,
you can set the verbosity
of more content available
announcement in macOS as well.
You can do this using
VoiceOver Utility preferences.
Now, let's see how we can
make our Woof Woof Kennel app
support Accessibility
Custom Content API.
Here, we have
the DogTableViewCell
with variables for dog photo,
name,
type, description,
popularity, age,
weight, and height.
To implement
AXCustomContent API,
we first import
Accessibility framework.
Then we need to
add and implement
AXCustomContentProvider Protocol
on our TableViewCell.
Before implementing
the protocol methods,
let's override
accessibilityLabel property
and return just the name
and the type of the dog,
as they are the most
relevant details here.
We then implement
AXCustomContentProvider
protocol method
accessibilityCustomContent
with an array of
AXCustomContent objects
where AXCustomContent objects
are a key-value pair
of localized strings.
Here we create AXCustomContent
object for description
with string "Description"
as the label
and description's text value
as the value of
the AXCustomContent object.
We then also create
AXCustomContent objects
for popularity, age,
weight, and height as well.
We then return an array of all
these AXCustomContent objects
in the order
you want VoiceOver
to present them
to your user.
Now, let's see how
the VoiceOver experience
has improved
after implementing
AXCustomContentProvider
protocol
on our TableViewCell.
[VoiceOver] Bailey, beagle.
More content available.
Number one, popularity.
Three years, age.
25 pounds, weight.
14 inches, height.
Happy-go-lucky,
excellent hunting dog,
and loyal companion,
description.
[Nandini] For a user who is
trying to browse this list,
the age of the dog might be
a crucial information for them
if they want to adopt it.
Currently, its value is hidden
behind the More Content rotor.
AXCustomContent object has
a property named "importance"
that can be used
to solve this problem.
We can set this property's
value to "high,"
and the content
will always be presented
when VoiceOver
focuses on the element
without cycling through
the additional elements.
To ensure that the age
of the dog
is always presented
by VoiceOver,
we have set
the importance property
on the age custom content
object to be "high."
Now, here we see
that the age of the dog
is always read by VoiceOver.
[VoiceOver] Bailey, beagle,
three years.
More content available.
[Nandini] This age information
will also be available
in your More Content rotor.
New this year is that
we support the same capability
with SwiftUI as well.
We can set
the accessibilityCustomContent
modifier
on our custom views
in SwiftUI
by passing in localizable
text for both label
and the value parameters
and set the importance
property as needed.
This way works well
in situations
where the custom content value
is added in one place
and not manipulated later
in the hierarchy.
To implement this
in our DogCell View,
we first set the accessibility
hidden modifiers
on description text
and on the HStack
that contains popularity,
age, weight,
and height of the dog
so that these aren't
automatically picked up
for the accessibility
label of the DogCell.
We then set
accessibilityCustomContent
modifiers for age
with importance set
to high, popularity,
weight, height,
and description.
If we want
our custom content value
to be manipulated
in more than one place
in the Swift UI hierarchy,
we can avoid redefinition
of the key
by creating an extension of
AccessibilityCustomContentKey.
This will give the ability
to update
or remove
the value for that key
without recreating
the localizable text string.
In our DogCell example,
we have created
an extension of
AccessibilityCustomContentKey
and added age as one
of the custom keys.
On the DogCell body's VStack,
we have added accessibility
CustomContent modifier
with the
AccessibilityCustomContentKey
"age," instead of using
a string key here.
Finally, here is what
we hope you will do
to tailor
the VoiceOver experience
of our data-rich apps.
First, identify visually
data-rich parts of your app.
Turn on VoiceOver
and determine if the content
under the VoiceOver cursor
is too verbose.
If it is verbose,
implement
AXCustomContentProvider protocol
and consider moving
the supplementary information
to accessibilityCustomContent.
Set the importance property
to "high"
for the information you always
want to present to your user.
For the VoiceOver users,
to have an option
to access their content
in measured portions
and have the content
presented to them
only when they need it
will greatly improve
the Accessibility
experience of your app.
So now, to give
a better experience
to our VoiceOver users,
I really encourage you
to take a look
at how you can incorporate
AXCustomContent APIs
into your data-rich apps!
And thank you so much
for watching this session,
everyone.
Bye-bye!
[percussive music]