[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Brad Ford: Hello and welcome to
"What's new in camera capture."
I'm Brad Ford from
the Camera Software team.
I'll be presenting
a host of new camera features
beginning with minimum
focus distance reporting;
how to capture 10-bit HDR video;
the main course, Video Effects
in Control Center;
and then -- a brief respite
from new features --
I'll review strategies
to get the best performance
out of your camera app.
And lastly, I'll introduce
a brand-new performance trick
for your bag,
IOSurface compression.
All of the features
I'll be describing today
are found in the AVFoundation
framework --
specifically, the classes
prefixed with AVCapture.
To briefly review, the main
objects are AVCaptureDevices,
which represent cameras
or microphones;
AVCaptureDeviceInputs,
which wrap devices,
allowing them to be plugged into
an AVCaptureSession,
which is the central control
object of the AVCapture graph.
AVCaptureOutputs render data
from inputs in various ways.
The MovieFileOutput
records QuickTime movies.
The PhotoOutput
captures high-quality stills
and Live Photos.
Data outputs,
such as the VideoDataOutput
or AudioDataOutput,
deliver video or audio buffers
from the camera or mic
to your app.
There are several other kinds
of data outputs,
such as Metadata and Depth.
For live camera preview,
there's a special
type of output,
the AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer,
which is a subclass of CALayer.
Data flows from
the capture inputs
to compatible capture outputs
through AVCaptureConnections,
represented here
by these arrows.
If you're new to AVFoundation
camera capture,
I invite you to learn more
at the Cameras and Media Capture
start page
on developer.apple.com.
OK, let's dive right into
the first of our new features.
Minimum focus distance
is the distance from the lens
to the closest point where
sharp focus can be attained.
It's an attribute of all lenses,
be they on DSLR cameras
or smartphones.
iPhone cameras have
a minimum focus distance too,
we've just never
published it before...
...until now, that is.
Beginning in iOS 15,
minimum focus distance
is a published property
of iPhone autofocus cameras.
Here's a sampling
of recent iPhones.
The chart illustrates how
the minimum focus distance
of the Wide and telephoto
cameras
varies from model to model.
There's a notable difference
between the iPhone 12 Pro
and 12 Pro Max Wide cameras,
the Pro Max focusing
at a minimum distance
of 15 centimeters
compared to 12 on the Pro.
This is due to the sensor shift
stabilization technology
in the iPhone 12 Pro Max.
Likewise, the minimum focus
distance of the tele
is farther on the 12 Pro Max
than the 12 Pro.
This is due to the longer reach
of the telephoto lens.
It has a 2.5x versus a 2x zoom.
Let me show you a quick demo
of why minimum focus distance
reporting is important.
Here's a sample app
called AVCamBarcode.
It showcases our AVFoundation
barcode detection APIs.
The UI guides the user
to position an object
inside of a rectangle
for scanning.
In this example, I've chosen
a fairly small QR code
on a piece of paper.
The barcode is only
20 millimeters wide.
By tapping on
the Metadata button,
I see a list of all
the various object types
supported by
AVCaptureMetadataOutput.
There are a lot of them.
I'll choose QRCodes
and then position
my iPhone 12 Pro Max camera
to fill the rectangle
with the QRCode.
Unfortunately, it's so small
that I have to get very close
to the page to fill the preview.
That's closer than the camera's
minimum focus distance.
The code is blurry,
so it doesn't scan.
To guide the user
to back away,
I need to apply a zoom factor
to the camera preview...
...like so.
Seeing a zoomed image
on the screen
will prompt them
to physically move the camera
farther away from the paper.
I can do that
with a slider button,
but it would be much better
if the app took care
of the zoom automatically.
That's where the new
minimumFocusDistance property
of AVCaptureDevice comes in.
It's new in iOS 15.
Given the camera's
horizontal field of view,
the minimum barcode size
you'd like to scan --
here I've set it
to 20 millimeters --
and the width of the camera
preview window as a percentage,
we can do a little math
to calculate
the minimum subject
distance needed
to fill that preview width.
Then, using the
new minimumFocusDistance
property of the camera,
we can detect when our camera
can't focus that close
and calculate a zoom factor
large enough
to guide the user to back away.
And finally, we apply it
to the camera by locking it
for configuration,
setting the zoom factor,
and then unlocking it.
After recompiling our demo app,
the UI now automatically
applies the correct zoom amount.
As the app launches,
it's already zoomed
to the correct space.
No more blurry barcodes!
And if I tap on it, we can see
where it takes me.
Ah! "Capturing Depth
in iPhone Photography" --
an oldie but a goodie.
I deeply appreciate
that session.
Please check out the new
AVCamBarcode sample
for best practices
on how to incorporate
minimum focus distance,
as well as a lot of other best
practices for scanning barcodes.
Next up is 10-bit HDR video.
HDR stands for
High Dynamic Range,
and it's been around
as a still image technology
since way back in iOS 4.1.
Preserving High Dynamic Range
is usually accomplished
by taking multiple exposures
of a scene
and then blending them
to preserve
both highlights and shadows.
But what about video HDR?
That's a challenge since
you've got to deliver
30 or 60 frames a second.
Not exactly Video HDR --
but close --
in 2018, Apple introduced EDR,
or Extended Dynamic Range,
to the iPhone XS camera line.
EDR is an HDR-like solution
for video.
It essentially doubles
the capture frame rate,
alternating between standard
exposures and short exposures,
but timed so there's virtually
no vertical blanking
between the captures.
When nominally capturing
30 frames per second,
EDR video is actually
running the camera
at 60 frames a second.
When required by the scene,
the hue map from the EV-
is dynamically applied
to the EV0 image
to recover clipped highlights,
but without sacrificing detail
in the shadow.
It's not a full HDR solution,
as its effectiveness
diminishes in low light,
but it provides amazing results
in medium to good light.
Now here's the confusing part.
EDR was presented as a suite
of AVCaptureDevice properties
under the moniker of videoHDR.
Wherever you see
videoHDRSupported
or videoHDREnabled
in the AVCapture API,
you should mentally
substitute EDR.
That's what it is.
AVCaptureDevice
also has a property
called "automaticallyAdjusts
VideoHDREnabled",
which defaults to true.
So EDR is enabled automatically
whenever it's available.
If for some reason
you wish to disable it,
you need to set
automaticallyAdjustsVideo
HDREnabled to false,
and then set videoHDREnabled
to false as well.
Now the story gets even better.
I needed to tell you about EDR
so I could tell you
about 10-bit HDR Video.
10-bit HDR video
is truly High Dynamic Range
because it's got more bits!
That means increased
editability.
It's got EDR
for highlight recovery,
and it's always on.
It uses hybrid log gamma curves
as well as the BT.2020
color space,
allowing for even greater
contrast of colors --
brighter brights than Rec 709.
And whether you use
AVCaptureMovieFileOutput
or AVCaptureVideoDataOutput
plus AVAssetWriter,
we automatically insert
per-frame Dolby Vision metadata
into your movies,
making them compatible
with Dolby Vision displays.
10-bit HDR video was first
introduced on the iPhone 12.
10-bit HDR video formats
can be identified
by their unique
pixel format type.
On older iPhone models,
cameras have
AVCaptureDeviceFormats
that always come in pairs.
For each resolution
and frame rate range,
there's a 420v
and a 420f format.
These are 8-bit, biplanar,
YUV formats.
The V in 420v stands for
video range -- or 16 to 235 --
and the F in 420f stands for
full range -- or 0 to 255.
On iPhone 12 models,
some formats come in
clusters of three.
After the 420v and 420f formats
comes an x420 format
of the same resolution
and frame rate range.
Like 420v, x420 is a biplanar
420 format in video range,
but the x in x420 stands for
10 bits instead of 8.
To find and select a 10-bit HDR
video format in code,
simply iterate through
the AVCaptureDevice formats
until you find one whose
pixel format matches x420,
or -- deep breath --
420YpCbCr10BiPlanarVideoRange.
You can of course include
other search criteria,
such as width, height,
and max frame rate.
We've updated
our AVCam sample code
to support 10-bit HDR video
when available.
There's a handy utility function
in it
called "tenBitVariantOfFormat"
which can find
the 10-bit HDR variant of
whatever the currently selected
device active format is.
Please take a look.
10-bit HDR video is supported
in all the most popular
video formats,
including 720p, 1080p, and 4K.
And we included
a 4 by 3 format as well --
1920 by 1440 -- which does
support 12 megapixel,
high-resolution photos.
While capturing
10-bit HDR video is simple,
editing and playing it back
properly is tricky.
I invite you to watch
a companion session from 2020
entitled "Edit and play back HDR
video with AVFoundation."
All right, that's it
for HDR video.
Now on to the main event:
Video Effects in Control Center.
Put simply, these are
system-level camera features
that are available in your apps
with no code changes.
And the user is in control.
This is a bit of a departure
for us.
Traditionally, when we introduce
a new camera feature
in iOS or macOS, Apple's apps
adopt it out of the box.
We expose new AVCapture APIs,
you learn about them --
just as you're doing now --
and then you adopt the feature
at your own pace.
This is a safe and conservative
approach,
but often results
in a long lead time
in which users miss out
on a great feature
in their favorite camera apps.
With Video Effects
in Control Center,
we are introducing system-level
prepackaged camera features
that are available
to everyone right away
with no code changes,
and the user is in control.
We do continue to expose
new APIs for these features,
so you can tailor the experience
in your app
as soon as your release
schedule allows.
Let's take a look
at these effects.
The first was announced
at our May
Spring Loaded Apple event
and it's called "Center Stage".
It's available on the recently
released M1 iPad Pro models
and it makes use
of their incredible
12 megapixel Ultra Wide
front-facing cameras.
Center Stage really enhances
the production value
of your FaceTime video calls.
It also works great
out of the box
in every other
video conferencing app.
Here, let me show you.
I've just downloaded Skype
from the App Store;
this is a stock version
of the app.
When I start a Skype call,
you immediately see Center Stage
kick into action.
It's kind of like having your
own personal camera operator.
It frames you as you
move around the scene
to keep you perfectly framed,
whether you come in tight
or you move back
and like to pace.
it can even track you
when you turn your face
away from the camera.
That's because it tracks bodies,
not just faces.
As a user,
I can control Center Stage
by simply swiping down
for Control Center,
tapping on the new
Video Effects module,
and making my selection.
As I turn Center Stage off
and go back to the app,
I no longer get the Center Stage effect.
No changes in the app.
There's a companion new feature
that all video conferencing apps
get as well,
and that's called "Portrait".
Portrait mode offers me
a beautifully rendered
shallow depth-of-field effect.
It's not just a simple
privacy blur;
it uses
Apple's Neural Engine
plus a trained monocular
depth network
to approximate a real camera
with a wide-open lens.
Now let's take a look finally
at the mic modes
by swiping down and picking
the Mic Mode module,
I can make my choice between
Standard, Voice Isolation,
or Wide Spectrum.
Mic modes enhance the audio
quality in your video chats.
More on these in a minute.
While Center Stage,
Portrait, and Mic Modes
share screen real estate
in Control Center,
they differ somewhat
in API treatment.
I'll introduce you
to Center Stage APIs first
and then to Portrait
and Mic Modes.
Center Stage is available
on all the front cameras
of the M1 iPad Pros.
Whether you're using the new
front-facing Ultra Wide camera,
the Virtual Wide camera --
which presents a cropped,
conventional field of view --
or the Virtual TrueDepth camera,
Center Stage is available.
The TrueDepth camera
comes with some conditions,
which I'll cover momentarily.
The Control Center
Video Effects module
presents an on/off toggle
per app.
This allows you to default
Center Stage to on
in a conferencing app,
while defaulting it to off
in a pro photography app
where you want to frame
your shot manually.
There's one state per app,
not one state per camera.
Because the Center Stage
on/off toggle is per app,
not per camera,
it's presented in the API
as a set of class properties
on AVCaptureDevice.
These are readable, writable,
and key-value observable.
centerStageEnabled
matches the on/off state
of the Center Stage UI
in Control Center.
The Center Stage control mode
dictates who is allowed
to toggle the enabled state.
More on that in a minute.
Not all cameras or formats
support Center Stage.
You can iterate through
the formats array of any camera
to find a format
that supports the feature
and set it
as your activeFormat.
Additionally, you can find out
if Center Stage is currently
active for a particular camera
by querying or observing its
Center Stage active property.
You should be aware
of Center Stage's limitations.
Center Stage uses
the full 12-megapixel format
of the Ultra Wide camera,
which is a 30 fps format,
so the max frame rate
is limited to 30.
Center Stage avoids upscaling
to preserve image quality,
so it's limited to a max output
resolution of 1920 by 1440.
Pan and zoom must remain
under Center Stage control,
so video zoom factor
is locked at one.
Geometric distortion correction
is integral to Center Stage's
people framing,
and depth delivery must be off,
since depth generation
requires matching
full field of view images from
the RGB and infrared cameras.
Now let's get into the concept
of control modes.
Center Stage has three
supported modes:
user, app, and cooperative.
User mode is the default
Center Stage control mode
for all apps.
In this mode, only the user
can turn the feature on and off.
If your app tries
to programmatically change
the Center Stage
enabled state,
an exception is thrown.
Next is the app mode,
wherein only your app is allowed
to control the feature.
Users can't use Control Center
because the toggle
is grayed out there.
Use of this mode
is discouraged.
You should only use it
if Center Stage
is incompatible
with your app.
If you do need to opt out,
you can set the control mode
to app,
then set isCenterStageEnabled
to false.
The best possible
user experience for Center Stage
is the cooperative mode,
in which the user can control
the feature in Control Center,
and your app can control it
with your own UI.
You need to do
some extra work, though.
You must observe the
AVCaptureDevice
.isCenterStageEnabled property
and update your UI to make sure
Center Stage is on
when the user wants it on.
After setting the control mode
to cooperative,
you can set center stage
enabled to true or false --
based on a button
in your app, for instance.
The poster child for
cooperative mode is FaceTime.
While I'm in a FaceTime call,
I can use a button
right within the app
to turn Center Stage on
so that it tracks me,
or I can use
the conventional method
of swiping down
in Control Center
and turning Center Stage
on or off.
FaceTime and Control Center
cooperate
on the state of Center Stage
so that it's always matching
user intent.
FaceTime is also
smart enough to know
when features
are mutually incompatible.
So if, for instance,
I tried to turn on Animoji,
which requires depth...
...it knows to turn
Center Stage off,
because those two features
are mutually incompatible.
If I tap to turn Center Stage
back on,
FaceTime knows
to disable Animoji.
That wraps up
Center Stage API.
Let's transition over
to Center Stage's
roommate in Control Center,
Portrait.
Put simply,
it's a beautifully rendered
shallow depth-of-field
effect,
designed to look like
a wide-aperture lens.
On iOS, Portrait is supported
on all devices
with Apple Neural Engine --
that's 2018 and newer
phones and pads.
Only the front-facing camera
is supported.
It's also supported
on all M1 Macs,
which likewise contain
Apple's Neural Engine.
Portrait is a computationally
complex algorithm.
Thus, to keep video rendering
performance responsive,
it's limited to a max resolution
of 1920 by 1440
and a max resolution
of 30 frames per second.
Like Center Stage,
the Portrait effect has
a sticky on/off state per app.
Its API is simpler than
Center Stage's,
the user is always in control
through Control Center,
and it's only available
by default
in certain classes of apps.
On iOS, apps that use
the VoIP UIBackgroundMode
are automatically opted in --
users can turn the effect
on or off in Control Center.
All other iOS apps must opt in
to declare themselves
eligible for the Portrait effect
by adding a new key
to their app's Info.plist:
NSCameraPortraitEffectEnabled.
On macOS, all apps
are automatically opted in,
and can use the effect
out-of-the-box.
The Portrait effect is always
under user control
through Control Center only.
As with Center Stage,
not all cameras or formats
support Portrait.
You can iterate through
the formats array of any camera
to find a format that supports
the feature,
and set it
as your active format.
You can also find out
if Portrait is currently active
for a particular camera
by querying or observing
its isPortraitEffectActive
property.
Mic Mode APIs
are analogous to Portrait.
User selection
is sticky per app.
Users are always in control;
your app can't
set the Mic Mode directly.
Some apps need to opt in
to use the feature.
Mic Modes are presented
in AVFoundation's
AVCaptureDevice interface,
and there are three flavors:
standard, which uses
standard audio DSP;
wide spectrum,
which minimizes processing
to capture all sounds
around the device
but it still includes
echo cancellation;
and voice isolation,
which enhances speech
and removes unwanted
background noise
such as typing on keyboards,
mouse clicks,
or leaf blowers running
somewhere in the neighborhood.
These flavors can only be set
by the user in Control Center,
but you can read and observe
their state
using AVCaptureDevice's
preferredMicrophoneMode --
which is the mode
selected by the user --
and activeMicrophoneMode --
which is the mode now in use,
taking into account
the current audio route,
which may not support
the user's preferred Mic Mode.
In order to use Mic Modes,
your app must adopt the
Core Audio AUVoiceIO audio unit.
This is a popular interface
in video conferencing apps,
since it performs
echo cancellation.
And Mic Mode processing is only
available on 2018 and later
iOS and macOS devices.
With Portrait and Mic Modes,
the user is always in control,
but you can prompt them
to turn the feature off or on
by calling the new
AVCaptureDevice
.showSystemUserInterface
method.
And you can pass it either
videoEffects or microphoneModes.
Calling this API
opens Control Center
and deeplinks to the appropriate
submodule.
Here, we're drilling down
to the Video Effects module,
where the user can choose
to turn Portrait off.
That wraps up Portrait,
and wraps up Video Effects
in Control Center.
I've just shown you examples
of system-level camera features
injected into your app without
you changing a line of code --
a pretty powerful concept!
There's a companion session
to this one
called "Capture high-quality
photos using video formats",
where you'll learn about
improvements we've made
to still image quality
in your apps
without you changing
a line of code.
Please check it out.
We've covered
a lot of new features.
At this point in the session,
I'd like to take a breather
and talk about performance.
Center Stage and Portrait
are great new user features,
but they do carry an added
performance cost.
So let's review
performance best practices
to make sure your camera apps
are ready for new features
like Portrait and Center Stage.
Camera apps
use AVCapture classes
to deliver a wide array
of features.
The most popular interface
is AVCaptureVideoDataOutput,
which allows you to get video
frames direct to your process
for manipulating, displaying,
encoding, recording...
you name it.
When using VideoDataOutput,
it's important
to ensure that your app
is keeping up
with real-time deadlines
so there are no frame drops.
By default, VideoDataOutput
prevents you from getting behind
by setting its
alwaysDiscardsLateVideoFrames
property to true.
This enforces
a buffer queue size of one
at the end of video data
output's processing pipeline
and saves you from periodic
or chronic slow processing
by always giving you
the freshest frame
and dropping frames
you weren't ready to process.
It doesn't help you
if you need to record
the frames you're receiving,
such as with AVAssetWriter.
If you intend to record
your processed results,
you should turn
alwaysDiscardsLateVideoFrames
off and pay close attention
to your processing times.
VideoDataOutput tells you when
frame drops are occurring
by calling your provided
captureOutput didDrop
sampleBuffer delegate callback.
When you receive
a didDrop callback,
you can inspect the included
sampleBuffer's attachments
for a droppedFrameReason.
This can inform what to do
to mitigate further frame drops.
There are three reasons:
FrameWasLate,
which means your processing
is taking too long;
OutOfBuffers, which means
you may be holding on
to too many buffers;
and Discontinuity, which means
there is a system slow down
or hardware failure
that's not your fault.
Now let's talk about
how to react to frame drops.
One of the best ways
is to lower the device
frame rate dynamically.
Doing so incurs no glitches
in preview or output.
You simply set a new
activeMinVideoFrameDuration
on your AVCaptureDevice
at run time.
A second way
is to simplify your workload
so you're not
taking so much time.
Now let's talk about
system pressure,
another performance metric
that's crucially important
to a good user experience
in your camera app.
System pressure
means just that,
the system is subject
to strain or pressure.
AVCaptureDevice has a property
called systemPressureState,
which consists of factors
and an overall level.
The SystemPressureState
contributing factors
are a bit mask of three
possible contributors.
systemTemperature refers to
how hot the device is getting.
peakPower is all about
battery aging,
and whether the battery is
capable of ramping up voltage
quickly enough to meet
peak power demands.
And the depthModuleTemperature,
which refers to how hot
the TrueDepth camera's
infrared sensor is getting.
The SystemPressureState's level
is an indicator
that can help you take action
before your user experience
is compromised.
When it's nominal,
everything is copacetic.
Fair indicates that system
pressure is slightly elevated.
This might happen even if you're
doing very little processing
but the ambient
temperature is high.
At serious, system pressure
is highly elevated;
capture performance
may be impacted.
Frame rate throttling
is advised.
Once you reach critical,
system pressure
is critically elevated;
capture quality and performance
are significantly impacted.
Frame rate throttling
is highly advised.
And you never want to let things
escalate to shutdown,
where system pressure
is beyond critical.
At this level, AVCaptureSession
stops automatically to spare
the device from thermal trap.
You can react to elevated
pressure in a variety of ways.
Lower the capture frame rate;
this will always
help system pressure.
If lowering the frame rate
isn't an option,
consider lessening your
workload on the CPU or GPU,
such as turning off
certain features.
You might also keep features on
but degrade the quality,
perhaps by only processing
a smaller resolution
or less frequently.
AVCaptureSession never
frame rate throttles
on your behalf,
since we don't know
if that's an acceptable
quality degradation strategy
for your app.
That wraps up
performance best practices.
Now onto our dessert course,
IOSurface compression.
I carefully avoided talking
about memory bandwidth
in the performance section,
since there's not much
you can do about the overall
memory bandwidth
requirements of video
flowing through the ISP
and eventually to your photos,
movies, preview, or buffers.
But still, memory bandwidth
can be a crucial limiter
in determining
which camera features
can simultaneously run.
When working with uncompressed
video on iOS and macOS,
there are a lot of layers
involved.
It's a little like
a Russian nesting doll.
At the top level
is a CMSampleBuffer,
which can wrap
all kinds of media data,
as well as timing
and metadata.
Down one level,
there's the CVPixelBuffer,
which specifically
wraps pixel buffer data
along with metadata attachments.
Finally, you get to
that lowest level, IOSurface,
which allows the memory
to be wired to the kernel,
as well as provides an interface
for sharing large video buffers
across processes.
IOSurfaces are huge.
They account for the great
memory bandwidth requirements
of uncompressed video.
Now thankfully,
IOSurface compression
offers a solution for memory
bandwidth problems.
New in iOS 15,
we're introducing support
for a lossless in-memory
video compression format.
It's an optimization to lower
total memory bandwidth
for live video.
It's an interchange format
understood by the major hardware
blocks on iOS devices and Macs.
It's available
on all iPhone 12 variants,
Fall 2020 iPad Airs,
and Spring 2021 M1 iPad Pros.
Which major hardware blocks
deal in compressed IOSurfaces?
Well, there are a lot.
All services listed here
understand
how to read or write
compressed IOSurfaces.
At this point you may be saying,
"Great, how do I sign up?"
Well, good news.
If you're capturing video
on supported hardware
and the AVCaptureSession
doesn't need to deliver
any buffers to your process,
congratulations,
your session is already
taking advantage
of IOSurface compression
whenever it can to reduce
memory bandwidth.
If you want compressed surfaces
delivered to your
video data output,
you need to know about
a few rules.
Physical memory layout
is opaque and may change,
so don't write to disk,
don't assume the same layout
on all platforms,
don't read or write
using the CPU.
AVCaptureVideoDataOutput
supports several flavors
of IOSurface compression.
Earlier in the talk,
you learned that iOS cameras
natively support
420v and 420f --
8-bit YUV formats;
one video and one full range.
And later, you learned about
x420, a 10-bit HDR video format.
Video data output
can also internally expand
to 16-bits-per-pixel BGRA
if requested.
Each of these has an IOSurface
compressed equivalent
which, beginning in iOS 15,
you can request
through
AVCaptureVideoDataOutput.
If you're a fan of ampersands
in your four-character codes,
this is your lucky day.
Here it is again
in eye chart format.
These are the actual constants
you should use in your code.
Two years ago we released
a piece of sample code
called "AVMultiCamPiP".
In this sample,
the front and back cameras
are streamed simultaneously
to VideoDataOutputs
using a multicam session,
then composited
as a Picture in Picture
using a Metal shader, which then
renders the composite to preview
and writes to a movie
using AVAssetWriter.
This is the perfect candidate
for IOSurface compression
as all of these operations
are performed on hardware.
Here's the existing
VideoDataOutput setup code
in AVMultiCamPiP.
It likes to work with BGRA,
so it configures
the VideoDataOutput's
videoSettings
to produce that
pixel format type.
The new code just incorporates
some checks.
First it sees if the IOSurface
compressed version
of BGRA is available.
And if so, it picks that;
the else clause is just there
as a fallback.
And just like that,
we've come to the end.
You learned about minimum
focus distance reporting,
how to capture
10-bit HDR video,
Video Effects and Mic Modes
in Control Center,
performance best practices,
and IOSurface compression.
I hope you enjoyed it!
Thanks for watching.
♪