[percussive music]
[Abhilash] Hello.
Mail is a crucial application,
and Mail app extensions
will let you enhance it
in some incredible new ways.
I'm Abhilash, and along with my
colleague, Seth,
we are going to walk you through
how to build
great Mail app extensions.
In macOS Monterey, we are
shipping a new framework,
MailKit,
for building Mail extensions.
These extensions are built on
the same underlying foundation
as other app extensions
like Safari app extensions
and share sheet extensions.
They are built with user
privacy and security in mind
in mind from the ground up.
MailKit APIs are well
documented and will be supported
across major macOS releases.
Like other app extensions,
they can be in any
properly signed Mac app,
can be bundled in your
existing apps,
and can also be distributed
in the App Store.
Mail extensions are
the future of extending Mail.
Plug-ins will stop functioning
in a future macOS release.
We are introducing four
new ways you can extend
Mail's user experience.
First, compose extensions
will allow new workflows
when composing mail messages.
Action extensions help
people manage their inbox
by providing custom rules
on incoming messages.
Content blocking extensions
provide WebKit content blockers
for Mail messages.
Finally,
message security extensions
can provide further security
by signing, encrypting,
and decrypting messages when
people send and receive mail.
This provides a full
suite of Mail extensions
to help compose messages,
take action
on incoming messages,
block undesired mail content
and provide encryption
and decryption.
They are easy to write.
They are very powerful.
They are stable
and will continue to work
as the OS and Mail app
change over time.
Before we dive in to build
a Mail extension
with these capabilities,
let's go through
an example of one in use.
Imagine I am working for a large
multinational corporation
where all my colleagues
are collaborating
on multiple
highly secretive projects.
To help preserve secrecy
of our projects,
we are using
a Big Secrecy Extension
that validates recipients
of a mail message.
I want to send a message
to my colleague Seth
for an update on our new
remote office on Mars.
The first thing you
notice is a button
for the Big Secrecy Extension
in the Mail compose window.
This extension provides
a list of projects
I'm working on,
and I pick Mars Remote Office.
I type in a subject
and Seth's email.
The extension was able
to validate
that Seth
is disclosed on this project
and annotates his email address
with a blue checkmark.
Of course, for a project of this
importance, we do want to keep
our manager, Mikey, informed,
so I'm going to add him.
Hmm, looks like Mikey
is not disclosed
about our new remote office.
Let me remove him
and send the message.
Oh, I received a reply
from Seth,
and it shows up in red
in the message list.
This is because
the Big Secrecy Extension
performed an action
to color messages
regarding the Mars project
as red.
There is also an icon
indicating that an extension
performed an action
on this message.
When I go to view the message,
there is
an icon in the Message Viewer
indicating that the message
from Seth was encrypted
and successfully decrypted
by the Big Secrecy Extension.
Now let's dive in and learn how
you can leverage MailKit APIs
to build powerful extensions
like the Big Secrecy Extension.
Let's start with compose
extensions which can provide
new features for users
while composing messages.
In macOS Monterey,
there are four ways
your extension can interact
with a Mail compose window.
An extension can validate
recipient email addresses
as the user is editing them,
provide a view controller
with additional context
about the message
being composed,
set additional headers
on outgoing messages,
or alert the user of errors in
the message before it is sent.
Let's walk through how to build
a compose extension.
You start by adding a new target
to an existing macOS App.
In Xcode 13, there is a new
Mail Extension template
that will get you started
on creating
a new Mail Extension target.
During setup,
Xcode will allow you to choose
the type of extension
you want to create.
For a compose extension,
you select
the Include Compose Session
Handler capability.
In the Info.plist
for the extension target,
you must also specify an icon
and a descriptive tooltip
in the MEComposeSession
dictionary.
Mail will
use the icon and tooltip
to display a toolbar button
in the compose window.
Now let's
look at the implementation
for your extension's
principal class.
The principal class
of your extension must conform
to the MEExtension protocol.
MEExtension exposes
optional handler methods
for each of the four
types of extensions.
For a compose extension,
your principal class
must implement the handler
for session method
and return an instance
that conforms
to the MEComposeSessionHandler
protocol.
Methods
in MEComposeSessionHandler
are called by Mail
to inform the extension
about a Compose window's
life cycle.
The first method that
will be called
is ComposeSessionDidBegin,
which happens when a new
compose window is opened.
There are also methods that
are called based on user actions
like editing recipient email
addresses or sending an email.
All the methods
in MEComposeSessionHandler
have a MEComposeSession argument
which provides information
about a compose window.
Mail creates a unique
MEComposeSession instance
for every Mail compose window.
It has a MEMessage property
that exposes various details
of the message being edited.
You can utilize this
information to customize
the responses that you
provide when Mail calls
your extension's
MEComposeSessionHandler methods.
Let's look at an example
of how you can do this
to annotate recipient
email addresses.
Mail will call your
ComposeSessionHandler's
annotateAddressesForSession
whenever recipient
addresses are edited.
In this example, we are
using the allRecipientAddresses
property of MEMessage
to provide an error annotation
for emails that are not
matching seth@example.com.
Compose extensions can also
provide a view controller
that Mail will display
in the compose window.
Your view controller can provide
valuable context to the user
by customizing
the view controller
for each compose window.
Your extension's view
controller must be
a subclass
of MEExtensionViewController.
Mail will request an instance of
this view controller
by calling the
viewControllerForSession method
of MEComposeSessionHandler.
You can learn more about these
compose APIs
in the MailKit documentation
and get started
on building new workflows.
Now let's talk about
Mail action extensions.
Action extensions perform
actions on incoming messages
to help users
manage their inbox.
In macOS Monterey,
we are exposing three types
of actions an extension
can perform on a new message.
An action extension
can modify read status
and flags
of incoming messages,
move messages
to system mailboxes
such as Junk, Trash or Archive,
or apply colors to messages
when they are displayed
in the message list.
You can add support
for message actions
by selecting the Include Message
Action Handler capability
when you are creating
the Mail extension target.
Similar to the compose
extension,
for action extensions,
your principal class
must return
a message action handler
by implementing a handler
for message actions.
In this example,
the principal class
is also acting
as an action handler
by adopting
MEMessageActionHandler.
Your action extension
must implement
MEMessageActionHandler's
decideAction for message method.
DecideAction for message
is called
with a MEMessage argument.
Here, we are coloring
the message red
by checking if the headers
property contains "Mars."
A few things to note
about action handlers.
Mail calls your handler's
decideAction for message
for every new message
that it downloads
before it is even visible
in the inbox.
The first time Mail
calls your extension's
decideAction for message method,
the MEMessage instance
will have only a subset
of the message headers.
You can provide a decision
such as coloring the message
based on the available headers.
Once Mail applies
the action on the message,
it will be visible in the inbox.
In some cases, you will need
the complete body and headers
of the message to return
an appropriate decision.
In this case, your decideAction
for message method
can return
an invokeAgainWithBody decision.
This will cause Mail
to fetch the complete
message body and headers
before invoking your handler's
decideAction
for message method again.
You can
now return a more accurate
decision before it is
visible in the inbox.
Now I am going to turn it over
to Seth, who will to show you
how to build content blocking
and security extensions.
[Seth] Thanks, Abhilash.
First, I am going
to walk you through
how to add
a content blocker extension.
Content blockers hook into
Mail's WebKit configuration
for its message view to allow
extensions to block
loading content based on
triggers in the message's HTML.
This allows extensions
to block loading content
based on criteria
of the HTML such as the URL.
In this example,
the extension was able
to block loading
the remote images
based on the rules in the
extension's content rule list.
You can add support
for content blocking
by selecting
Include Content Blocker
when you are creating
the Mail extension target.
Next, you return a handler
for the content blocker
in your extension's
principal class.
In this example,
the principal class is adopting
the MEContentBlocker protocol
so it returns self.
The content rule lists
are specified
using the same syntax as
Safari content blockers.
So if you already have
a content rule list
for your Safari
content blocker extension,
you can use the same rules for
a Mail app extension as well.
You can get more information
on how to create
a content rule list
by referencing
the "Introduction to Webkit
Content Blockers" documentation.
Once your rule list is complete,
you can provide it to Mail
by returning it
in the contentRulesJSON method.
This method expects
a Data encoding
of the Content Rule List JSON.
And that's it for Mail
content blockers.
Lastly, we're going to go over
Message security extensions.
The Message security
capability gives extensions
the ability to encode
and decode encrypted messages.
They can also sign
messages and provide a way
to view certificates
of signed messages.
You can add support
for message security
by selecting
Include Message Security Handler
when you're creating
the Mail extension target.
Next, you need to return
a handler from your extension
that supports
the MEMessageSecurityHandler
protocol in our extension's
principal class.
In this example, the extension's
principal class is also adopting
the MEMessageSecurityHandler
protocol,
so it returns self.
Now let's take a look
at how to encode messages
that are being composed.
Encoding a message is
broken down into two parts.
The first helps drive the UI
as the message is composed.
This lets the extension show
if it has the ability
to sign and encrypt
the current message.
The next
part is to actually encrypt
and sign the message
as it is being sent.
As a message is composed, Mail
will send the message,
including the sender
and current list of recipients
to the extension.
The extension can then
determine if it has
the ability to sign
and encrypt the message.
Based on what is returned
by the extension,
Mail will highlight the Lock
and Certificate icons,
depending on if the message
can be signed and encrypted.
Each time the sender
or recipients change,
Mail will call
the getEncodingStatus method
on the extension's
message security handler.
The extension will verify
if it can sign
and encrypt the message
and return to Mail
the current encoding status.
The example here is
importing an ExampleEncoder
to do the actual work
of checking the encoding status
of the message.
The Message Security Handler
returns the status
once available.
Next, when the message is sent,
Mail will take
the RFC822 message data
and pass it to the extension.
The extension will sign
and encrypt the message
as needed,
and return the signed
and encrypted RFC822
data back to Mail.
Mail will then send this
data to the outgoing server.
When the message is ready
to send,
Mail passes the current message
using the encodeMessage method
to the extension's
Message Security Handler.
The extension's
Message Security Handler
will return the encoded message.
Again, in this example,
we're using an ExampleEncoder
to do the actual work
of encoding the message.
The Message Security Handler
returns encoded message.
Message decoding works similarly
but in reverse.
When the message is viewed,
Mail will send
the encoded RFC822 message
data to the extension.
The extension will decode
the message into nonencrypted,
or signed, RFC822 data
and return that back to Mail.
Mail will then display
the decoded message.
When Mail is ready
to decode the message,
it will call into
the Extension's Security Handler
calling the decodedMessage
method.
If the extension has the ability
to decode the message,
it will do so and return
the decoded RFC822 message.
If the extension is not
needed for decoding the message,
it should quickly return nil.
When a message is viewed,
it can be determined
if it is signed and encrypted.
For signed messages,
the signer certificate
can be clicked next
to the signer label
to view the sender's
certificate information.
Mail allows extensions to
provide its own view controller
to render this
certificate information.
As part of the decoded Mail
message, the extension has
the ability to return
a set of message signers.
The label provided will
be shown as the signer
in the message view.
The extension can also
populate the context property
with any information
it might need
for displaying
the signing certificate.
When the certificate icon
is clicked,
Mail requests a ViewController
from the extension
and passes it the set of signers
for the current message.
These signers are what
was returned to Mail
by the extension when the
message was originally decoded.
The view controller
must be a subclass
of MEExtensionViewController.
And that's it for message
security extensions.
Mail extensions are
a powerful new way
for you to enhance
the Mail experience.
We're excited to see
how you leverage
these Mail capabilities to build
awesome new products,
and we want to hear
your feedback.
So send us an email
or post a message
on our Developer Forums.
These examples show the power
of Mail app extensions.
We made a compose extension
that verified recipients,
an action extension that
colored incoming messages.
We saw a content blocker
blocking remote images.
Last, we saw
how easy it is to add
custom encryption and decryption
to Mail.
In this video, we covered how
to build Mail app extensions.
We're looking forward
to see how you extend Mail
to do some really cool things.
So get out there and build some
awesome new Mail app extensions.
Thanks for watching.