[music]
[Doug]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Doug,
and today my colleague
Nate and I will take a look
at how Universal Scene
Description, or USD,
can be used for a wide variety
of 3D work flows.
We'll talk a little bit
about what USD is,
take a look
at the exciting developments
n the world of USD,
show some incredible
new features in Preview,
and demonstrate
how USD can be at the center
of a creative 3D workflow.
USD is a set of libraries
and file formats
that allows for assembly,
interchange, and organization
of any number of assets
into scenes, shots,
or virtual objects.
From object capture,
asset creation,
layout and editing
to rendering quick thumbnails
for sharing or feedback
to creating USDZ assets for use
in Augmented Reality, or AR.
The flexibility of USD
can be a core component
of an extensible,
collaborative, 3D pipeline.
USD is a foundational technology
that, with the growing
and deepening integration
into Digital Content
Creation tools,
is enabling more and more ways
of creating assets and content.
Render, collaborate,
for games, AR, film
all with USD at the center.
USD was developed by Pixar to
enable them to create
the enormously complex movies
we love.
We at Apple worked with Pixar
a few years ago
to develop the USDZ format
to utilize USD in a single file
to deliver rich AR content
directly to your devices.
USD-based workflows
are highly collaborative,
enabling you
to work independently
on parts of an asset,
easily incorporating
your changes with others.
It's inherently
extensible by design
and is rapidly emerging
as a key workflow technology.
It's built on
decades and decades
of production experience
in the film industry
and is increasingly
being adopted
for games, simulation, AR,
manufacturing, and e-commerce.
Pixar is using an open
and collaborative model
that the USD project
has been following.
The USD forum is active
and full of core contributors
answering queries,
and the Academy Software
Foundation
has a working group
that meets regularly
to gather input
from interested groups.
Let's take a high level look
at other formats
out there today.
The most basic format is .obj,
which often essentially
contains just a single 3D model.
It has limited support
for materials
and no support for animations.
Then there's a large group
of more modern file formats.
These usually support
multiple models
that can be laid out
in a scene graph
and have varying levels
of support
for material and definitions.
Many are tied
to proprietary tools.
USD supports all of this
and is additionally designed
to be highly scalable.
Pixar developed USD
for its use in films,
so representing millions
of objects is the typical case.
And USD is built
with collaboration
as a core feature,
allowing for many artists
to work on a single scene
without getting
in each other's way.
USDZ is the archive package
for USD
and inherits
most of these features,
is optimized for sharing,
and allows a single file
to contain all the resources
needed for rich AR interchange.
USD naturally allows creation
of USDZ files for AR content.
But it's also the front-end
for a full featured pipeline
that delivers USDZ
for AR and e-commerce
and assets
for offline rendering.
Last year,
we released RealityConverter,
a stand-alone utility
to allow easy creation
of a self-contained USDZ
from collections of USD files,
.obj, alembic,
and a wide variety
of other 3D formats as well.
On the Apple Developer site,
there are command line tools
to allow you to automate
processing of batches of assets.
As the delivery format for AR,
USDZs can be authored to target
a specific Apple device,
letting you tailor
the experience
for your audience.
The USD ecosystem
is growing rapidly.
It's really exciting to see
the things growing
from the roots
of what USD provides.
Multiverse from J-Cube
brings the full power
of non-destructive USD editing
to the Mac,
enabling insanely fast
multi-DCC workflows
as well as editing
in the Multiverse
USD Standalone Editor,
all powered by
the Metal Hydra Storm renderer.
OTOY's Octane renderer
can plug into DCC's like Houdini
and harnesses the blazing-fast
power of the GPU
to render spectrally correct
images directly from USD files.
ZBrush works directly
with USD mesh data
to bring all the power
of sculpting to a USD workflow.
And Maya continues to integrate
USD deeper and deeper,
now using USD Hydra rendering
directly in the VP2 viewport.
Maya 2022 is the first version
to have native seamless
integration of USD.
This means you can load
gigabytes of USD data in seconds
and work directly with that data
using Maya's native tools.
USD data is integrated
right into the Attribute Editor
and the Outliner.
It brings all the USD benefits
right inside the DCC:
nondestructive editing,
variants,
and collaboration to name a few.
Apple worked with Autodesk
to improve the USD
importing and exporting
functionality as well,
including Blendshape support
and using textures
directly in USDZ files.
Of course,
USD isn't a static technology.
Apple is collaborating
with Pixar
and the rest
of the USD community
to extend and improve
USD's support
for the latest features
in 3D content creation.
Last year Apple, Nvidia,
and Pixar
jointly developed a schema
to represent properties
needed for Physics simulation.
It can represent properties
from real-time AR physics
all the way
to offline simulations
for robotics and film.
It's exciting to see
such widespread support
and so many great updates
to the USD ecosystem.
Another key feature
of USD is Hydra.
Hydra is USD's high-performance,
modern rendering architecture
designed specifically
to get millions of objects
to your screen
as fast as possible.
Hydra Storm is one such renderer
that is part of the core
USD open-source distribution.
We're thrilled to share
that Preview and Quick Look
in macOS will include
a Metal-accelerated
Hydra Storm renderer.
This allows anyone
to quickly view USD files
in a way that's consistent
with Hydra Storm
on other platforms
all without
having to open a DCC.
It can handle complex
production-grade assets
and has some 3D scene
exploration tools built in.
Here's a layout asset
from Pixar's "Toy Story 4,"
the antiques mall
rendering in real-time
in Preview.
It has tens of thousands
of individual objects
and about 34 million triangles.
It's a great example
of a production-quality asset,
and it's a real challenge
not only for the renderer
but for also
any scene navigation tools.
To help move around the scene,
any cameras in the USD file
are shown in the thumbnail views
to the left,
letting me click through them.
As well as
the normal camera controls,
I can click on objects
in the view
and lock the camera to them.
To get a more detailed picture
of the composition of the scene,
we added an outliner
that displays
all of the object nodes.
If I select an object
in the view,
then it is highlighted
in the outliner.
But as you can see
from this huge list here,
we needed to provide better
tools
to assist with scenes
of this complexity.
So we've also added the ability
to search for objects by name.
For example, if I search for
all the jukeboxes in the scene,
I'll get a list of them
and can focus on each in turn.
Once I've found
the one I'm interested in,
it can be saved
as a separate USD file.
And then I can view this again
in Preview and Quick Look
and use it in my AR scene
in Reality Composer.
On top of the features
I've just shown you,
Preview also enables you
to render animated USD scenes
to a movie file
or render the current view
to an image,
complete with alpha channel.
For AR,
Preview uses the RealityKit
rendering engine
to view USDZ files.
It's the same renderer
as AR Quick Look on iOS
and is a great way to check
what an on-device view
will look like.
We've worked
with Pixar Animation Studios
to add Metal and M1
acceleration support
to their powerful GPU renderer
for producing 3D movies
like "Soul"
and the upcoming movie "Luca."
Pixar Animation Studios
is making
Metal-accelerated Hydra Storm
available for integration
in your apps through
their USD Open Source project
by the end of 2021.
Now let's see
how all these exciting USD tools
can be used
in a single workflow.
So let's let Nate get to work.
[Nate]Thanks, Doug.
We're going to show you
how you can use USD
to capture a real-world object
and bring it into 3D.
We'll edit it along the way
and then render a gorgeous
photoreal product shot
all with USD.
In a traditional 3D workflow,
sharing data between DCCs
is cumbersome and error-prone.
Lengthy import and export
steps are required
to move data
from one tool to another.
This traditional workflow
is also one-way.
As only the last stages
of the pipeline
can see the overall scene,
earlier stages lack context
on how their contributions
will be used.
In contrast, USD allows us
to work in parallel
using different tools
and to work natively
on the same data.
Crucially, since all of our data
is represented as USD,
the import/export step
is eliminated
and sharing is automatic.
A USD workflow
enables faster iteration,
better collaboration,
and opens up new
and more creative possibilities.
Since it's morning somewhere,
we can assume
that it's time for breakfast.
So let's make some pancakes.
Here's a sketch of how we'd like
our overall scene to look.
We've storyboarded
a few different concepts,
camera angles, and layouts,
and decided
this is our favorite.
Let's see how we can use USD
to turn this sketch
into reality.
Since we're using USD,
we can arrange the scene
into several separate files.
Each file will contribute
to some aspect of the scene,
be it the layout of the models,
sculpting of the geometry,
or any animation or lighting
we might want to add.
These files are all referenced,
or linked, into the main scene.
This is a core feature of USD
which allows any number
of people or tools
to collaborate on the same scene
at the same time.
So first, let's set the table.
We're using Autodesk's Maya
to construct our overall scene.
We need a USD file
to store all of the layout data.
This is where
we assemble all of our assets
and place them into the scene.
We also want a cool camera move,
so we add a USD file
to our scene
for the camera animation.
To create the 3D model
of the pancakes,
we'll use Object Capture
on our real pancakes.
After we've captured the model,
we'll use Pixologic's ZBrush
to do some cleanup
and make some enhancements.
Here we've added a sculpting
USD file to the scene
where this data will live.
Can't have pancakes
without syrup.
We make our virtual syrup
in SideFX Houdini,
using its fluid simulation
capabilities
and native support for USD.
Finally, we'll also use Houdini
to add some virtual lights
to our scene.
Let's see
in a little more detail
how all of this comes together.
First, we use Object Capture
to create a 3D model
from our real,
physical pancakes.
Using a series of photographs
taken from different angles,
we can construct a 3D mesh
and surface material
of the pancakes.
Once we've acquired this model,
we can view it in Preview.
Here's a breakdown
of the captured model
with and without textures.
We'll use this as the basis
of our sculpting USD
that we'll edit later in ZBrush.
While we're capturing
the pancakes,
we can use Maya to construct
the initial set of USD files
where all of our data will live.
As of Maya 2022,
USD is natively supported,
and it's easy
to create a setup like this.
Once we've set up our files
and linked in
our captured pancakes,
we can do the layout.
Here I've assembled
some of the props
that make up the scene.
I just need to make
a few more adjustments.
This is the breakdown
of our scene
after we've done the layout.
While Object Capture
produces excellent results,
we weren't able to capture
all of the angles
of our pancakes
before we ate them,
so let's take them into ZBrush
for some digital enhancement.
Using ZBrush,
we can paint in
the missing geometry
at the bottom
of the stack of pancakes
where they rested on the plate
when we photographed them.
In addition, we can add
even more physical detail
to the model,
as well as make
some improvements
to the surface material.
These edits are being made
in the sculpting.usd file
we created earlier.
Since the main scene
is referencing this file,
everyone on the team
will get these updates
as they are made.
Object Capture looks great,
but you can see the improvement
that ZBrush brings by adding
detail and polish to the model.
While they already
look scrumptious,
they could use just
a little bit more sweetening.
For this task,
we'll take our pancakes into
Houdini
and add our virtual syrup
and lighting.
In Houdini, we can directly load
all of our USD files
as native data.
Houdini has powerful
procedural tools
to generate
all sorts of effects,
and we can use it
to pour virtual syrup
all over our stack of pancakes.
Here's what our scene looks like
with contributions from Maya,
ZBrush, and Houdini.
Everything is brought together,
and now we just
need to share it.
Fortunately, we're using USD,
and we have a lot of options.
We can create a USDZ file
and share our scene
in Augmented Reality
using AR Quick Look on iOS.
On the Mac, we can use
the new built-in features
of Preview that Doug
demonstrated earlier.
Or we can use
a studio-level offline renderer
to produce a photo-real video.
First, we'll bring
our pancakes into AR.
Reality Composer
lets us load our USD scene
and make any final adjustments
before we save it
as an AR-enabled USDZ file.
Let's load this up
on the iPad Pro and have a look.
Just tap on the USDZ file,
and AR Quick Look opens up.
In seconds,
we've created pancakes in AR.
Looks delicious.
Next, let's check out our scene
in Preview on the Mac.
We can navigate the scene,
inspect objects, select assets,
export them, and share.
Everything stays as USD.
Finally, we'll create a video
using OTOY's Octane
to create an offline,
path-traced render of our scene.
Whatever changes we make
to adjust the lighting
or materials
can be shared back
in AR or viewed in Preview.
USD makes this all possible.
From sketch to reality,
thanks to USD
and some great tools,
we've turned real pancakes
into virtual breakfast.
We hope
we've given you a glimpse
of how you can use USD
to create exciting and complex
3D scenes and assets.
All of these software vendors
are actively integrating USD
into their products,
so we encourage you
to get the latest and greatest
and have fun exploring
the universe of USD.
For more info on Object Capture,
check out this session
from this year's WWDC.
We also have several talks
about USD on the Apple platform.
Check out this talk
on "What's new in USD"
from last year's conference.
Thank you.
[music]