[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Dario Rexin: Hi,
my name is Dario Rexin,
and I am an engineer on
the Swift team here at Apple.
Today, my colleague Doug and I
will talk about actors in Swift
and how they are utilized
to protect mutable state
in concurrent
Swift applications.
One of the fundamentally
hard problems
with writing concurrent programs
is avoiding data races.
Data races occur
when two separate threads
concurrently access
the same data
and at least one of those
accesses is a write.
Data races are trivial
to construct
but are notoriously hard
to debug.
Here's a simple counter class
with one operation
that increments the counter
and returns its new value.
Let's say we go ahead
and try to increment
from two concurrent tasks.
This is a bad idea.
Depending on the timing
of the execution,
we might get 1 and then 2,
or 2 and then 1.
This is expected,
and in both cases,
the counter would be left
in a consistent state.
But because we've introduced
a data race,
we could also get 1 and 1
if both tasks read a 0
and write a 1.
Or even 2 and 2 if the return
statements happen
after both increment operations.
Data races are notoriously hard
to avoid and debug.
They require nonlocal reasoning
because the data accesses
causing the race might be in
different parts of the program.
And they are nondeterministic
because the operating system's
scheduler might interleave
the concurrent tasks
in different ways each time
you run your program.
Data races are caused
by shared mutable state.
If your data doesn't change
or it isn't shared across
multiple concurrent tasks,
you can't have
a data race on it.
One way to avoid data races
is to eliminate
shared mutable state
by using value semantics.
With a variable of a value type,
all mutation is local.
Moreover, "let" properties
of value-semantic types
are truly immutable,
so it's safe to access them
from different concurrent tasks.
Swift has been promoting value
semantics since its inception
because they make it easier
to reason about our program
and those same things
also make them safe
to use in concurrent programs.
In this example, we create
an array with some values.
Next, we assign that array
to a second variable.
Now we append a different value
to each copy of the array.
When we print both arrays
at the end,
we see that both copies
contain the values
that the array
was initialized with,
but each appended value
is only present
in the respective copy
we appended them to.
The majority of types
in Swift's standard library
have value semantics,
including collection types
like dictionary,
or as in this example, array.
Now that we have established
that value semantics
solve all of our data races,
let's go ahead and make
our counter a value type
by turning it into a struct.
We also have to mark the
increment function as mutating,
so it can modify
the value property.
When we are now trying
to modify the counter
we will get a compiler error
because the counter is a let,
which prevents us
from mutating it.
Now, it seems very tempting to
just change the counter variable
to a var to make it mutable.
But that would leave us,
again, with a race condition
because the counter
would be referenced
by both concurrent tasks.
Luckily, the compiler
has us covered
and does not allow us
to compile this unsafe code.
We can instead
assign the counter
to a local mutable variable
inside each concurrent task.
When we execute our example now,
it will always print 1
for both concurrent tasks.
But even though our code
is now race-free,
the behavior is not
what we want anymore.
This goes to show
that there are still cases
where shared mutable state
is required.
When we have shared mutable
state in a concurrent program,
we need some form
of synchronization
to ensure that concurrent use
of our shared mutable state
won't cause data races.
There are a number of primitives
for synchronization,
from low-level tools
like atomics and locks
to higher-level constructs
like serial dispatch queues.
Each of these primitives
has its various strengths,
but they all share
the same critical weakness:
they require careful discipline
to use exactly correctly,
every single time,
or we'll end up
with a data race.
This is where actors come in.
Actors are
a synchronization mechanism
for shared mutable state.
An actor has its own state
and that state is isolated
from the rest of the program.
The only way
to access that state
is by going through the actor.
And whenever you go
through the actor,
the actor's synchronization
mechanism ensures
that no other code
is concurrently
accessing the actor's state.
This gives us the same
mutual exclusion property
that we get from
manually using locks
or serial dispatch queues,
but with actors,
it is a fundamental guarantee
provided by Swift.
You can't forget to perform
the synchronization,
because Swift will produce
a compiler error if you try.
Actors are a new
kind of type in Swift.
They provide
the same capabilities
as all of the named types
in Swift.
They can have properties,
methods, initializers,
subscripts, and so on.
They can conform to protocols
and be augmented
with extensions.
Like classes,
they are reference types;
because the purpose of actors is
to express shared mutable state.
In fact, the primary
distinguishing characteristic
of actor types is that they
isolate their instance data
from the rest of the program
and ensure synchronized
access to that data.
All of their special behavior
follows from those core ideas.
Here, we've defined our counter
as an actor type.
We still have the instance
property value
for the counter,
and the increment method
to increment that value
and return the new value.
The difference is that the actor
will ensure the value
isn't accessed concurrently.
In this case, that means
the increment method,
when called,
will run to completion
without any other code
executing on the actor.
That guarantee eliminates
the potential for data races
on the actor's state.
Let's bring back
our data race example.
We again have
two concurrent tasks
attempting to increment
the same counter.
The actor's internal
synchronization mechanism
ensures that one increment
call executes to completion
before the other can start.
So we can get 1 and 2
or 2 and 1
because both are valid
concurrent executions,
but we cannot get
the same count twice
or skip any values because
the internal synchronization
of the actor has eliminated
the potential for data races
on the actor state.
Let's consider
what actually happens
when both concurrent tasks
try to increment the counter
at the same time.
One will get there first,
and the other
will have to wait its turn.
But how can we ensure
that the second task
can patiently await
its turn on the actor?
Swift has a mechanism for that.
Whenever you interact
with an actor from the outside,
you do so asynchronously.
If the actor is busy,
then your code will suspend
so that the CPU you're running
on can do other useful work.
When the actor
becomes free again,
it will wake up your code --
resuming execution --
so the call can run
on the actor.
The await keyword
in this example indicates
that the asynchronous call
to the actor
might involve such a suspension.
Let's stretch our counterexample
just a bit further
by adding an unnecessarily slow
reset operation.
This operation sets the value
back to 0,
then calls increment
an appropriate number of times
to get the counter
to the new value.
This resetSlowly method
is defined in an extension
of the counter actor type
so it is inside the actor.
That means it can directly
access the actor's state,
which it does to reset
the counter value to 0.
It can also synchronously
call other methods on the actor,
such as in the call
to increment.
There's no await required
because we already know
we're running on the actor.
This is an important
property of actors.
Synchronous code on the actor
always runs to completion
without being interrupted.
So we can reason about
synchronous code sequentially,
without needing to consider
the effects of concurrency
on our actor state.
We have stressed
that our synchronous code
runs uninterrupted, but actors
often interact with each other
or with other asynchronous code
in the system.
Let's take a few minutes
to talk about asynchronous code
and actors.
But first,
we need a better example.
Here we are building
an image downloader actor.
It is responsible
for downloading an image
from another service.
It also stores
downloaded images in a cache
to avoid downloading
the same image multiple times.
The logical flow
is straightforward:
check the cache,
download the image,
then record the image
in the cache before returning.
Because we are in an actor,
this code is free
from low-level data races;
any number of images can be
downloaded concurrently.
The actor's synchronization
mechanisms guarantee
that only one task
can execute code
that accesses the cache
instance property at a time,
so there is no way
that the cache can be corrupted.
That said,
the await keyword here
is communicating something
very important.
Whenever an await occurs,
it means that the function
can be suspended at this point.
It gives up its CPU so other
code in the program can execute,
which affects
the overall program state.
At the point where
your function resumes,
the overall program state
will have changed.
It is important to ensure that
you haven't made assumptions
about that state
prior to the await
that may not hold
after the await.
Imagine we have
two different concurrent tasks
trying to fetch the same image
at the same time.
The first sees that
there is no cache entry,
proceeds to start downloading
the image from the server,
and then gets suspended because
the download will take a while.
While the first task
is downloading the image,
a new image might be deployed to
the server under the same URL.
Now, a second concurrent task
tries to fetch the image
under that URL.
It also sees no cache entry
because the first download
has not finished yet,
then starts a second
download of the image.
It also gets suspended
while its download completes.
After a while,
one of the downloads --
let's assume it's the first --
will complete
and its task will resume
execution on the actor.
It populates the cache
and returns the resulting
image of a cat.
Now the second task
has its download complete,
so it wakes up.
It overwrites the same entry
in the cache
with the image
of the sad cat that it got.
So even though the cache was
already populated with an image,
we now get a different image
for the same URL.
That's a bit of a surprise.
We expected that once
we cache an image,
we always get that same
image back for the same URL
so our user interface
remains consistent,
at least until we go and
manually clear out of the cache.
But here, the cached image
changed unexpectedly.
We don't have
any low-level data races,
but because we carried
assumptions about state
across an await,
we ended up with
a potential bug.
The fix here is to check
our assumptions after the await.
If there's already an entry
in the cache when we resume,
we keep that original version
and throw away the new one.
A better solution would be
to avoid redundant
downloads entirely.
We've put that solution
in the code
associated with this video.
Actor reentrancy
prevents deadlocks
and guarantees forward progress,
but it requires you
to check your assumptions
across each await.
To design well for reentrancy,
perform mutation of actor state
within synchronous code.
Ideally, do it within
a synchronous function
so all state changes
are well-encapsulated.
State changes can involve
temporarily putting our actor
into an inconsistent state.
Make sure to restore consistency
before an await.
And remember that await
is a potential suspension point.
If your code gets suspended,
the program and world
will move on
before your code gets resumed.
Any assumptions you've made
about global state,
clocks, timers, or your actor
will need to be checked
after the await.
And now my colleague Doug
will tell you more
about actor isolation.
Doug?
Doug Gregor: Thanks, Dario.
Actor isolation is fundamental
to the behavior of actor types.
Dario discussed how
actor isolation is guaranteed
by the Swift language model,
through asynchronous
interactions
from outside the actor.
In this section, we'll talk
about how actor isolation
interacts with other
language features,
including protocol conformances,
closures, and classes.
Like other types, actors
can conform to protocols
so long as they can satisfy the
requirements of the protocol.
For example, let's make this
LibraryAccount actor
conform to the
Equatable protocol.
The static equality method
compares two library accounts
based on their ID numbers.
Because the method is static,
there is no self instance
and so it is not
isolated to the actor.
Instead, we have two parameters
of actor type,
and this static method
is outside of both of them.
That's OK because the
implementation is only accessing
immutable state on the actor.
Let's extend
our example further
to make our library
account conform
to the Hashable protocol.
Doing so requires implementing
the hash(into) operation,
which we can do like this.
However, the Swift compiler
will complain
that this conformance
isn't allowed.
What happened?
Well, conforming to Hashable
this way means that
this function could be called
from outside the actor,
but hash(into) is not async,
so there is no way
to maintain actor isolation.
To fix this, we can make
this method nonisolated.
Nonisolated means
that this method is treated
as being outside the actor,
even though it is,
syntactically,
described on the actor.
This means that it can satisfy
the synchronous requirement
from the Hashable protocol.
Because nonisolated methods
are treated as being
outside the actor,
they cannot reference
mutable state on the actor.
This method is fine
because it's referring
to the immutable ID number.
If we were to try to hash
based on something else,
such as the array of books
on loan, we will get an error
because access to mutable state
from the outside
would permit data races.
That's enough
of protocol conformances.
Let's talk about closures.
Closures are little functions
that are defined
within one function,
that can then be passed
to another function
to be called some time later.
Like functions, a closure
might be actor-isolated
or it might be nonisolated.
In this example,
we're going to read some
from each book
we have on loan
and return the total number
of pages we've read.
The call to reduce
involves a closure
that performs the reading.
Note that there is no await
in this call to readSome.
That's because this closure,
which is formed within the
actor-isolated function "read",
is itself actor-isolated.
We know this is safe
because the reduce operation
is going to execute
synchronously,
and can't escape the closure
out to some other thread
where it could cause
concurrent access.
Now, let's do something
a little different.
I don't have time to read
just now,
so let's read later.
Here, we create a detached task.
A detached task executes
the closure concurrently
with other work
that the actor is doing.
Therefore, the closure
cannot be on the actor
or we would introduce
data races.
So this closure is not
isolated to the actor.
When it wants to call
the read method,
it must do so asynchronously,
as indicated by the await.
We've talked a bit about
actor isolation of code,
which is whether that code runs
inside the actor or outside it.
Now, let's talk about
actor isolation and data.
In our library account example,
we've studiously avoided saying
what the book type actually is.
I've been assuming
it's a value type,
like a struct.
That's a good choice
because it means that
all the state for an instance
of the library account actor
is self-contained.
If we go ahead
and call this method
to select a random book to read,
we'll get a copy of the book
that we can read.
Changes we make
to our copy of the book
won't affect the actor
and vice versa.
However, if the turn the book
into a class,
things are a little different.
Our library account actor
now references instances
of the book class.
That's not a problem in itself.
However, what happens
when we call the method
to select a random book?
Now we have a reference into
the mutable state of the actor,
which has been shared
outside of the actor.
We've created the potential
for data races.
Now, if we go and update
the title of the book,
the modification happens
in state that is accessible
within the actor.
Because the visit method
is not on the actor,
this modification could end up
being a data race.
Value types and actors are both
safe to use concurrently,
but classes can still
pose problems.
We have a name for types that
are safe to use concurrently:
Sendable.
A Sendable type is one
whose values can be shared
across different actors.
If you copy a value
from one place to another,
and both places can safely
modify their own copies
of that value without
interfering with each other,
the type can be Sendable.
Value types are Sendable because
each copy is independent,
as Dario talked about earlier.
Actor types are Sendable
because they synchronize
access to their mutable state.
Classes can be Sendable,
but only if they are carefully
implemented.
For example, if a class
and all of its subclasses
only hold immutable data,
then it can be called Sendable.
Or if the class internally
performs synchronization,
for example with a lock,
to ensure safe concurrent
access, it can be Sendable.
But most classes
are neither of these,
and cannot be Sendable.
Functions aren't necessarily
Sendable,
so there is a new kind
of function type
for functions that are safe
to pass across actors.
We'll get back to those shortly.
Your actors --
in fact,
all of your concurrent code --
should primarily communicate
in terms of Sendable types.
Sendable types protect code
from data races.
This is a property
that Swift will eventually
start checking statically.
At that point,
it will become an error
to pass a non-Sendable type
across actor boundaries.
How does one know
that a type is Sendable?
Well, Sendable is a protocol,
and you state that your type
conforms to Sendable
the same way you do
with other protocols.
Swift will then check
to make sure your type
makes sense
as a Sendable type.
A Book struct can be Sendable
if all of its stored properties
are of Sendable type.
Let's say Author
is actually a class,
which means it -- and therefore
the array of authors --
are not Sendable.
Swift will produce
a compiler error
indicating that Book
cannot be Sendable.
For generic types,
whether they are Sendable
can depend on
their generic arguments.
We can use
conditional conformance
to propagate Sendable
when it's appropriate.
For example,
a pair type will be Sendable
only when both of its generic
arguments are Sendable.
The same approach is used
to conclude that an array
of Sendable types
is itself Sendable.
We encourage you introduce
Sendable conformances
to the types whose values
are safe to share concurrently.
Use those types
within your actors.
Then when Swift begins
to start enforcing Sendable
across actors,
your code will be ready.
Functions themselves
can be Sendable,
meaning that it is safe
to pass the function value
across actors.
This is particularly important
for closures where it restricts
what the closure can do
to help prevent data races.
For example,
a Sendable closure
cannot capture
a mutable local variable,
because that would allow
data races
on the local variable.
Anything the closure
does capture
needs to be Sendable,
to make sure that
the closure cannot be used
to move non-Sendable types
across actor boundaries.
And finally, a synchronous
Sendable closure
cannot be actor-isolated,
because that would allow code
to be run on the actor
from the outside.
We've actually be relying
on the idea of Sendable closures
in this talk.
The operation that creates
detached tasks
takes a Sendable function,
written here with the @Sendable
in the function type.
Remember our counterexample
from the beginning of the talk?
We were trying to build
a value-typed counter.
Then, we tried to go
and modify it
from two different closures
at the same time.
This would be a data race
on the mutable local variable.
However, because the closure
for a detached task is Sendable,
Swift will produce
an error here.
Sendable function types are used
to indicate where concurrent
execution can occur,
and therefore prevent
data races.
Here's another example
we saw earlier.
Because the closure for
the detached task is Sendable,
we know that it should not
be isolated to the actor.
Therefore, interactions with it
will have to be asynchronous.
Sendable types and closures
help maintain actor isolation
by checking that mutable state
isn't shared across actors,
and cannot be modified
concurrently.
We've been talking primarily
about actor types,
and how they interact
with protocols, closures,
and Sendable types.
There is one more actor
to discuss --
a special one that we call
the main actor.
When you are building an app,
you need to think about
the main thread.
It is where the core user
interface rendering happens,
as well as where
user interaction events
are processed.
Operations that work
with the UI
generally need to be performed
from the main thread.
However, you don't want
to do all of your work
on the main thread.
If you do too much work
on the main thread, say,
because you have some slow
input/output operation
or blocking interaction
with a server,
your UI will freeze.
So, you need to be careful
to do work on the main thread
when it interacts with the UI
but get off
the main thread quickly
for computationally expensive
or long-waiting operations.
So, we do work off the
main thread when we can
and then call
DispatchQueue.main.async
in your code whenever you have
a particular operation
that must be executed
on the main thread.
Stepping back from the details
of the mechanism,
the structure of this code
looks vaguely familiar.
In fact, interacting
with the main thread
is a whole lot like
interacting with an actor.
If you know you're already
running on the main thread,
you can safely access
and update your UI state.
If you aren't running
on the main thread,
you need to interact
with it asynchronously.
This is exactly how actors work.
There's a special actor
to describe the main thread,
which we call the main actor.
The main actor is an actor
that represents
the main thread.
It differs from a normal actor
in two important ways.
First, the main actor performs
all of its synchronization
through the main dispatch queue.
This means that,
from a runtime perspective,
the main actor
is interchangeable
with using DispatchQueue.main.
Second, the code and data that
needs to be on the main thread
is scattered everywhere.
It's in SwiftUI, AppKit, UIKit,
and other system frameworks.
It's spread across your
own views, view controllers,
and the UI-facing parts
of your data model.
With Swift concurrency,
you can mark a declaration
with the main actor attribute
to say that it must be executed
on the main actor.
We've done that with
the checked-out operation here,
so it always runs
on the main actor.
If you call it from outside
the main actor,
you need to await, so that
the call will be performed
asynchronously
on the main thread.
By marking code that must run
on the main thread
as being on the main actor,
there is no more guesswork
about when to use
DispatchQueue.main.
Swift ensures that this code
is always executed
on the main thread.
Types can be placed
on the main actor as well,
which makes all of their members
and subclasses
be on the main actor.
This is useful for the parts
of your code base
that must interact with the UI,
where most everything needs
to run on the main thread.
Individual methods can opt-out
via the nonisolated keyword,
with the same rules
you're familiar with
from normal actors.
By using the main actor
for your UI-facing types
and operations,
and introducing your own actors
for managing
other program state,
you can architect your app
to ensure safe,
correct use of concurrency.
In this session,
we've talked about how actors
protect their mutable state
from concurrent access,
using actor isolation and by
requiring asynchronous access
from outside the actor
to serialize execution.
Use actors to build safe,
concurrent abstractions
in your Swift code.
In implementing your actors,
and in any asynchronous code,
always design for reentrancy;
an await in your code
means the world can move on
and invalidate your assumptions.
Value types and actors
work together
to eliminate data races.
Be aware of classes
that don't handle
their own synchronization,
and other non-Sendable types
that reintroduce
shared mutable state.
Finally, use the main actor
on your code
that interacts with the UI
to ensure that the code
that must be on the main thread
always runs on the main thread.
To learn more about
how to use actors
within your own application,
check out our session
on updating an app
for Swift concurrency.
And to learn more about
the implementation
of Swift's concurrency model,
including actors,
check out our
"Behind the scenes" session.
Actors are a core part
of the Swift concurrency model.
They work together
with async/await
and structured concurrency
to make it easier to build
correct and efficient
concurrent programs.
We can't wait to see
what you build with them.
♪