[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Ravi]
I am Ravi Kandadai Madhavan,
and in this video,
I will show how to use
the static analyzer
in Xcode to find and fix
bugs in your apps.
First, I will demonstrate
how to use
the static analyzer to find bugs
and also understand them.
Then, I will describe
the new checks in Xcode 13,
which can help find more
kinds of issues in your code.
Finally,
I will describe the ways
in which you can
customize the analyzer
to better integrate it
with your development workflow.
Let's now see how to use
the analyzer to find bugs.
The static analyzer is a tool
in Xcode that can discover bugs
by analyzing the source code
without running it,
so it can reveal bugs,
even before you do
testing and quality assurance
of your app.
It can also find problems
in code paths
that are rare
and not covered by tests.
The analyzer finds bugs in C/C++
and Objective-C code,
even in mixed Swift
and Objective-C projects.
Let us see the analyzer
in action
using an app I am developing.
I am trying to improve
an existing app written in Swift
and Objective-C that allows
exploring the solar system.
This is the Xcode project
for the app.
I am going to run
the Static Analyzer to see
if it finds anything wrong
with my code.
It's very easy to run.
Just go to Product
and choose Analyze,
or use the keyboard shortcut
Command-Shift-B.
You can see the analyzer running
in the status bar of Xcode.
Analyzing your project is
very similar to building it.
The analyzer scans all
the sources files in the targets
of the currently-active scheme
looking for bugs.
As you see in the status,
the analyzer has found
an issue in my project.
I can go
to Xcode's issue navigator
to learn more about it.
As I showed you,
all it takes to run
the analyzer on your project
is a single click.
And with this single click,
you can find
several kinds of bugs,
like security issues,
logical bugs, misuse of APIs,
and many more.
The analyzer can not only
find bugs,
but can also explain them.
Let's get back to the bug found
in my app
and try to understand it.
The problem here is
that the Objective-C method
positionAtDate is returning nil
when it is not supposed to.
The method's return value
is declared to be non-null
in the method's definition.
But now,
I want to understand how
this method is returning nil.
You can expand
the analyzer issues
and see the sequence of events
that lead to the bug.
The events are also
shown in the editor,
alongside the statements
where they happen.
The arrows show how
the events are ordered.
I find it easier to read these
reports from bottom to top.
The last event shows
that the returned value,
position, is nil.
The previous events show
that this is because the method
regularPositionAtDate,
meant to initialize position,
is not called because
its receiver object is nil.
Looking at the arrows,
this happens along
the default case of the switch.
Going back to the beginning
of the report reveals
that the receiver object
is initialized to nil
and remains so
along the default case.
Now, I understand that I haven't
handled objects that are not
spherical or irregular
within the switch.
To fix this, I am going to make
the default case identical
to the spherical case.
I will rerun the analyzer
to make sure the issue is fixed.
I am quite relieved
that this bug
is detected while I am
developing the app.
This is because returning nil
from an Objective-C method
annotated as returning
a non-null value
can result in unexpected
runtime behavior when the method
is called from Swift,
which happens in my code.
Thankfully, running
the static analyzer has revealed
this bug before it could
affect the users of my app.
In Xcode 13, we have made
the analyzer even better,
and we have some
brand-new checks for you.
The analyzer can now catch
more logic bugs in your code.
It can detect infinite loops
and redundant code,
such as unnecessary
branch conditions.
It can report side-effects
in asserts, and in C++ code,
it can catch errors in the use
of move and forward operators.
Parts of these new checks
are open-source contributions
made to Apple's Clang compiler.
Let's see some examples of bugs
these new checks can catch.
In general, it's a good practice
to use asserts to validate
your expectations
about your code.
However, you must make sure
that asserts do not have
side effects,
such as writing
to variables or memory.
For example,
consider the code snippet
shown here that traverses
an array
of astronomical objects
and counts the number
of those that have
associated moons.
It has an NSAssert that checks
that the number of objects
with moons is less than or equal
to the number of planets.
But the assert has
a side effect of incrementing
the counter tracking
the objects with moons.
Updates like this can
be lost in the release
build configuration,
where asserts could
be disabled to make
your code run faster.
So this code may not
increment the counter
at all in release builds.
It's easy to miss bugs like
these during development,
as they do not show up
in debug builds.
Starting Xcode 13,
the analyzer can find
such issues in your code
and report it.
This check works
not just for NSAsserts,
but also for asserts in C
and C++.
These bugs are easy to fix,
and you just move
the side effect
outside of the assert,
as shown here.
Infinite loops
are another common bug.
You might have seen it happen
when there are loops
with complex logic.
For instance,
the nested loop shown here tries
to populate a two-dimensional
grid with a value.
It hides a bug where
the variable value
is incremented by the inner loop
instead of column,
which is
the actual loop counter.
The analyzer can now detect such
mistakes and explain it to you.
Once you spot it,
this bug is very easy to fix.
Just replace value
by column.
Though these checks
find simple mistake,
we have found
real bugs with them.
Now you can use them, too,
and find bugs
and fix them as you develop
your app.
Xcode offers many customizations
for fine tuning the analyzer
to fit in
with your development workflow.
You can make the analyzer
run along with every build
of your project from
the project's build settings.
To quickly narrow down
on the relevant settings,
make use
of the search functionality.
For example, using "analysis"
as the search keyword,
I can look at just those options
relevant to the analyzer.
To enable
Analyze During 'Build',
all you need to do is
turn on a build setting.
Like incremental builds,
the analysis runs
only on files that are modified.
This makes running
the analyzer after code changes
both fast and easy.
The analyzer offers two modes
of analysis: shallow and deep.
Shallow mode is faster,
but avoids exploring
bugs spanning
multiple functions.
Use this mode in projects
that are sensitive to build
and analysis times.
As I mentioned earlier,
the analyzer has checks
for finding different kinds
of bugs,
and some of them are opt-in.
You can fine tune the checks
that suit your project
by enabling or disabling them
selectively from
the build settings.
For instance, if your project
has security-critical code,
enable the checks
for security issues.
On the other hand,
if you find that some issues
are not relevant to your code,
you can disable less useful
checks individually and still
benefit from the other checks.
You can also analyze
a single file
instead of the entire project.
Choose the file to analyze from
the Product > Perform Action menu.
Use this to check
your changes quickly,
without even needing
to build your project.
This is particularly useful
when modifying header files.
It would skip reanalyzing
all files importing it.
The static analyzer
in Xcode can reveal bugs
in your code very early
during development.
Run it with a click of a button
and find many kinds of bugs.
And don't forget to customize it
to your workflow.
In Xcode 13, we have
further improved the analyzer
and added many new checks
for finding logical bugs.
Use the analyzer and fix bugs
in your app
before they reach your users.
Thank you,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC!
[upbeat music]