[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Michael] Hello, everybody.
I'm Michael LeHew
from the Core Data team.
And today, I'm really excited
to talk to you
about some of the enhancements
the team has made
to make working
with Core Data and Swift
a truly excellent experience.
I'm going to start with a review
of how Core Data
is a great solution
for your customers’
data persistence needs
across all Apple platforms.
I'll then follow up
with a discussion
on some of the ways
that Core Data has adopted
the new concurrency
opportunities
in the Swift runtime.
Next, I'll cover
some of the enhancements
we've made to Core Data APIs
to make your code
more expressive in Swift.
And then conclude the discussion
with an exploration
of the dynamic capabilities
that Core Data is adding
to our existing SwiftUI support
that we introduced in 2020.
Let's start
at the beginning, though,
where regardless of which Apple
platform you are developing for,
you simply have an application.
At some point, your application
is going to eventually
encounter user data,
and you'll likely need
to store it somewhere.
A great choice for that need
is to use Core Data.
Core Data is Apple's
hallmark framework
for application developers
who desire to persist
their users' data in a robust
and feature-rich way.
The framework takes care
of many of the complexities
of appropriately managing
user data,
from the way it was represented
as an object graph in memory
to how it's modeled in storage.
The framework also goes
through great efforts
to manage important
runtime considerations,
like memory use and latency.
The capabilities provided by
the framework are scalable too.
You can start with a simple,
locally-persisted store
and expand to use
multiple execution contexts
to improve performance,
and even create
powerful shared data experiences
through CloudKit.
Core Data also works across
all Apple-supported platforms.
And I'd really like
to emphasize this last point.
Once you start using Core Data,
everything you learn will work
on each of our platforms,
from your Mac,
to your iPhone,
or even your Apple Watch.
And, of course, Core Data
works great in Swift too.
Over the past few years,
we've been continuing
to enhance Core Data API
to be as expressive
as possible in Swift.
And this is a pretty
exciting year for Swift
with the introduction
of the all-new
concurrency features
in the language and runtime.
Since its inception,
Core Data has always cared
about running code concurrently,
and there's a really
good reason for this.
Persisting data requires
reading and writing
to some external storage media,
and this makes supporting
the new concurrency model
a natural fit.
Let's explore how this works
in the context
of our Earthquakes
sample application.
This application
reads a data feed
from the US Geological Survey
and uses Core Data
to store information
about recent earthquakes,
such as their magnitude,
location,
and the date for which
the event occurred.
Architecturally, Earthquakes
is a Swift application
that has a view context
to drive the UI
and a background context
to ingest the data
provided by the USGS.
Our sample has a local container
for our application
and gathers quake data
from the USGS's JSON feed.
As we download data, we hand
it off to our JSON parser
and then import it
into our background context
to be turned
into managed objects
and saved to our local store.
The view context then
merges the changes
to magically update our UI.
In 2020, we focused on how
to efficiently handle this data
through the use
of batch operations.
Now, however, I'd like to focus
on how we perform
these operations concurrently.
In particular,
I'd like to focus
on the three steps that we take
to import data
into the application.
Step one is
to download the raw data,
and upon successful download,
the application needs
to convert it
to our specific
local representation.
And finally,
save the new objects
into the persistent store.
Let's go ahead and convert this
to high-level code.
I've abstracted each operation
into its own function
or closure.
The app first retrieves
the raw data from the server,
processes it into a convenient
local representation,
and then imports the objects
into Core Data
by making a batch insert request
on the background
managed object context.
Written like this,
it is a bit easier
to visualize
potential bottlenecks.
Loading data over the network
would be a great opportunity
to consider doing
our work asynchronously.
Converting might also be
a place to consider.
Additionally, importing the data
into our persistent store
seems quite opportune.
Historically, though,
in all of these cases,
you would need to implement
any such asynchronous
mechanism yourself
or lean heavily
upon a framework-specific
implementation.
Let's talk about Core Data's
specific abstraction.
In the case of Core Data,
when you call performAndWait,
the managed object context
will execute
the provided closure
within its own protected
execution environment.
This can potentially tie up
the calling thread
until the work is complete.
If we were to visualize this,
we can imagine
three blocks of code
which I've labeled
BEFORE, DURING, and AFTER.
When our code runs,
first the code labeled BEFORE
gets a chance to execute
on the originating thread.
We then call performAndWait,
and the calling thread
will block
until the work that happens
DURING the closure completes.
When that work is done, the code
described AFTER will execute.
Of course,
if you don't need to wait
for the closure to finish,
we've always offered
a fully asynchronous variant.
But new this year,
Swift has gained
powerful concurrency model
with deep language integration
which allows Core Data
to more accurately describe
the intention of our API.
The syntax is a bit different.
You ask to await
the results of the perform,
but the mental model
for using this new API
is exactly the same
that managed object
has always supported.
The benefit, however,
is that the concurrency
is no longer a hidden
implementation detail,
but instead deeply integrated
into the Swift language.
Because of this,
the compiler can
automatically prevent
many common concurrency bugs,
such as data races
and deadlocks,
and even efficiently make use
of resources
when tasks are known
to be awaiting results.
Let's go back to the code
and see what using this
in practice is like.
As we saw, you ask to await
an async-declared function.
This has the potential
to suspend
the calling execution context
until the async function
yields control by returning.
It also seamlessly works
with Swift's existing
structured error handling
by routing any thrown errors
to the calling frame,
just as you would expect.
Now that we've seen an example
of calling
an asynchronous function,
let's take a look
at how they're declared
by looking at Core Data's
brand-new way
to perform asynchronous work
within a managed object context.
There is quite a bit
of functionality packed
into this small stanza
of Swift code,
but I'm only gonna talk
about a few important details,
and then we'll jump into showing
how you can use it in practice.
Starting with the declaration
of the new perform overload.
You can see it's generic
based on the kind of results
that it can return
and is decorated with the new
async keyword,
which opts this function
into the new concurrency
capabilities in Swift.
Perhaps the most significant
facet of this new API
is that the provided closure
now allows you
to throw an error
or return a value,
saving you the effort
of routing these back
to the calling frame by hand.
Let's see how cool this is
by exploring
a few different scenarios.
Historically, since
the concurrency was hiding
inside of our implementation,
one of the only ways
to route errors
outside of a performAndWait
was to close over an optional
and then check it afterwards.
This could be more complicated
if you were using
the fully asynchronous
versions of perform
because you'd need
to do a lot of plumbing
by passing
completion handlers around
and making sure
you used them consistently.
With the new concurrency model
in Swift,
all of that plumbing
is handled for you!
Just try and await
your asynchronous work,
and if an error occurs,
just throw it,
and things will unwind
to the calling frame naturally.
So now, we focused on errors,
but what about results?
Well, everything I've described
works exactly the same.
Let's look
at a concrete example.
Let's sketch out what we wanna
do before jumping into the code.
For this example,
I'd like to configure
a fetch request to identify
the number of earthquakes
that have happened
in the last five hours.
As a sentence,
this is a straightforward task
to describe.
But in code, we're going to need
to reorder things a bit.
We'll first need to figure out
when five hours ago was,
for which we can use
the Calendar APIs
to calculate this
in a robust way.
We'll then configure
a fetch request
with a predicate
in terms of that date
and ask for a count result type.
In code, it looks
pretty much like our plan.
We use Calendar's offset API
to calculate five hours
before now,
and then configure
a Quake FetchRequest
to return a count result
with a predicate
that matches the dates
that we care about.
Historically, returning results
followed a similar pattern
to the way we captured errors.
You would close over any state
that you needed to mutate,
perform your computations
in the managed object context,
and then later, use the result
after regaining control.
Now, we can simply just try
and await the result
of our perform call
and return the result
for perform directly
to our calling frame.
The rest of the code
is exactly the same.
It's only the by-hand
value routing that we avoid
along with any potential bugs
or nuances
that that code may have had.
This new code is quite
succinct and expressive.
It is worth mentioning, however,
that there are times
where you should be cautious.
Let's look at a different
example to see why.
This example attempts to return
the most recent earthquake
as a managed object.
While the new API makes it
really easy to return values,
it is not safe
to return managed objects
that are already registered
to a managed object context.
It is only valid to refer
to such registered objects
within the closure
of a call to perform.
Instead, if you need to refer
to a managed object
between different
execution contexts,
either make use of the object ID
and refetch as needed,
or make use of the dictionary
representation option
of the fetch request.
Now before we look
at one more example,
I'd like to cover a detail
that I haven't talked about yet.
And that detail is
the ScheduledTaskType.
So far, every async perform
that we have seen
has been in terms of the default
value for this option:
.immediate.
There is a second option
called .enqueued,
and to understand the difference
between these two
scheduling approaches,
it helps to think
about what specifically happens
inside a managed object context
when you ask to schedule work.
As we've seen,
.immediate behaves a lot
like a Swift-async-aware
version of performAndWait.
If you're running
on a different execution context
and ask to await work performed
on the background context,
you will wait until it is
scheduled and completed.
If you're already on the same
execution context, however,
the work will be optimistically
scheduled right away.
.enqueued, on the other hand,
is a bit simpler.
It simply always just
appends the requested work
to the end
of the contexts' work set,
regardless of the affinity
of the originating call site.
Let's go ahead and look
at one more example.
All of these async features
can be adopted by you as well.
Here, I factored
the import logic
that we have been talking about
into a new
importQuakes function,
decorated with the new
async keyword.
This function is, in turn,
implemented in terms
of other async functionality.
Now anyone can await
upon this new function
to take advantage of the new
concurrency features in Swift.
Let's summarize
what we've seen so far.
Taken altogether,
this new API brings the support
for Swift's
structured concurrency
right into Core Data.
The new variants
of the perform API
are just Swift
concurrency-aware versions
of the existing Core Data API
you already know and love.
We strongly encourage you
to take advantage
of this new API
in your applications.
Further,
NSManagedObjectContext is not
the only type in Core Data
that supports performing tasks
within its protected
concurrency domain.
We're also adding
similar API to both
NSPersistentContainer and
NSPersistentStoreCoordinator.
The general shape and behavior
of these APIs are quite similar
to what I've already described.
But with all
that concurrent power,
I would be remiss
to not offer the advice
of using existing
debugging tools
available at your disposal.
Of course, the Xcode-provided
address and thread sanitizers
are incredibly helpful
for catching bugs
you might not even know existed.
These can both be found
in the Diagnostics pane
of the scheme editor's
Run settings.
Each sanitizer detects
different kinds of issues,
including validating
safe memory use assumptions
and appropriate use of data
from multiple threads.
It's always a good idea
to qualify your applications
and their associated tests
with both sanitizers
before you release your software
to your community of users.
And while the sanitizers
are useful in all contexts,
I also wanna highlight
that Core Data
provides a special runtime flag
that you can enable to get
more domain-specific help.
By enabling this option,
Core Data will turn on a number
of useful assertions
to validate internal locks
and confirm appropriate use
of various Core Data types.
Adopting Swift
concurrency support
is not the only change made
to Core Data this year.
Every new API
that we are introducing,
from CloudKit sharing
to the new
Spotlight integration,
has been crafted
with its presentation
in Swift in mind.
This year, we have
a separate session
for each of these topics,
and I encourage you
to check them out.
We additionally made a pass
throughout the entire framework
to identify other places
where we can make improvements
in Swift,
and I'd like to show you
a few of these now,
starting with the kinds
of different persistent
stores that we support.
Recall,
persistent stores describe
how you physically want
to store your customers' data.
Core Data currently provides
four such stores:
XML, binary,
in-memory, and SQLite.
And you use these
identifiers all the time.
New this year, we've gone ahead
and gave these
more natural names in Swift.
The existing names
will continue to work,
but the new API
that consumes these
will be a lot more
ergonomic to use
due to the shorter names
and ability to autocomplete
these symbols.
Of course,
persistent stores are not
the only thing in Core Data
that concerns itself with types.
After all, the framework
is all about storing typed data,
and such types are described
with attribute descriptions.
And this year, we're adding
a new extensible enumeration
to attribute description
that provides
a much more natural syntax
for working with their types.
Let's take a look
at these in action
by writing a unit test that can
validate that our runtime model
matches what we designed
in the Xcode model builder.
For simplicity,
we'll just try to validate
a single runtime type defined
by our earthquake object model,
but you can imagine
how this would scale.
This might seem like
a small test to write,
but it's a good thing
to validate
as it could speed up
more interesting diagnoses
in the future.
To write this test,
we'll write a quick
helper function
in terms of
the new attribute type.
Let's go ahead
and describe this function now.
We'll start with the signature,
which expects an attribute name,
the entity description that
we care about, and the type,
described in terms of the new
AttributeType enumeration.
The definition of this utility
is fairly straightforward.
We first validate
that we have an attribute
with the provided name,
failing the test
if we can't find it.
And then we validate
that the type
of the attribute is as expected.
And that's really
all there is to it.
We could repeat this
for each entity and property
and enjoy peace of mind
that our runtime behavior
matches the model we defined.
And this is just a sampling
of some of the ergonomic
improvements that we've made
to Core Data enumerations
in Swift this year.
Up till now, I've been focusing
on a lot of lower-level
framework interactions
and how they manifest in Swift,
but what about presenting
data to your users?
In 2020, we introduced
a number of conveniences
for working with Core Data
in SwiftUI.
And now, my colleague, Scott,
has quite a bit
to share with you
about the new enhancements
we are introducing this year.
Scott?
[Scott] Thanks, Michael!
There are a bunch
of improvements
to the experience
of using Core Data
with SwiftUI this year,
starting with lazy entity
resolution in fetch requests,
which relaxes the requirement
that apps have
their Core Data stacks set up
before they construct
their views.
Also this year,
fetch requests pick up
dynamic configuration for their
sort descriptors and predicates.
And there's a new kind
of fetch request in town
that supports
sectioned fetching.
I'm going to walk
through each of these
using our Earthquakes sample app
that Michael mentioned
earlier in the talk,
starting with
lazy entity resolution.
Probably in your app,
you have some code like this.
This container property here
isn't really necessary
to support the code
in this type,
or even the broader app.
All that stuff
gets what it needs
from the QuakesProvider
type directly.
No, this property exists
to make sure the Core Data stack
has been set up
before any of the views
in the environment try
to refer to any entities
before the model
has been loaded.
See here
that the environment
view modifier is called
after ContentView
has been initialized.
This trick
isn't necessary anymore
when deploying
against this year's SDKs.
The FetchRequest property
wrapper now looks up entities
by name lazily at fetch-time,
at which point
the environment has guaranteed
that the Core Data stack
has been set up,
so it's now safe
to delete this property...
And just refer to...
the QuakesProvider
shared container
directly in
the environment call.
Moving on to some new APIs,
FetchRequest now supports
dynamic configuration.
There are two new properties
on the wrapped value
for directly changing
the request's predicate
as well as its sort descriptors,
which are expressed both
with the NSSortDescriptors
that you're used to
as well as
a new SortDescriptor value type
that provides more convenience
and safety
when fetching entities
with automatically generated
managed object subclasses.
And finally, there's
a configuration binding
with the same set of properties
as the wrapped value
for easier integration
with views.
Before this new API,
I would've had
to design my views
so the sort and predicate
parameters
were passed
through a view's initializer,
but that made it really tricky
to support things like
configuring my fetch request
using controls in a toolbar.
This friction is eliminated
by these new dynamic
configuration properties,
and I'd love to show you
how to use them
by adding sorting
and filtering
to the Earthquakes sample app.
Let's look
at sort descriptors first.
By default, the Earthquakes
app sorts by recency,
but I'd also like
to order them by magnitude,
so I'm going to add a menu
that lets me control
the results' order.
I'll start by adding
a static array of tuples...
containing the sort descriptors
I'd like to support
as well as names for them.
See here that they're also using
the new SortDescriptor type.
I'll also want a bit
of state to track
which sort order
I am currently using.
I've already created
a type for this,
so I'll add it as a property
of the content view.
Now I'll add a toolbar menu
to the list view...
That modifies the selected sort
as well as an onChange modifier
that updates the fetch request's
sort descriptors.
Now in the preview,
we can see the new menu,
and I can use it to sort
the earthquakes by magnitude.
Great!
Now to add filtering.
I'd like to filter based
on the earthquake's place.
The first thing I need
is some state
for the search field's text.
And I'll make
a binding property...
for the search field that
updates the fetch request.
With those in place,
all I need is the UI.
Conveniently...
searchable takes
a binding to a string,
so we can just plop
that right in here.
Now in our preview,
we can narrow down
all the earthquakes near a place
matching a sandwich
by just typing "sandwich"
in this new field here.
And that's dynamic configuration
for FetchRequest.
Another commonly requested piece
of functionality
is support
for sectioned fetching,
which arrives this year
as a new property wrapper type
called SectionedFetchRequest.
This type supports the same
new dynamic configuration
properties as FetchRequest,
but it gets initialized
with an additional parameter,
a key path to a property
that identifies the section,
a lot like
NSFetchedResultsController.
But unlike the fetched
results controller,
the property
that identifies the section
can have any type you like,
so long as it's hashable.
This gets encoded
in the type system
using an additional
generic parameter
on SectionedFetchRequest.
Finally, this new type wraps
a two-dimensional result type.
SectionedFetchResults is
a collection of sections,
each of which is itself
a collection of results.
Each section also has a property
with the section identifier.
This is really easy to adopt,
so I'm going to add
sectioned fetching
to the Earthquakes app.
First, I update
my FetchRequest declaration.
Quake already has
a property for day,
so I'm going to use that
for the sectioning key path.
Next, I need to update
the body property...
To match the new
sectioned results type.
The outer loop here
iterates over the sections,
so I'm emitting
a Section view here,
and each section itself
is a collection of Quakes,
so this inner ForEach
iterates over the section,
just like I was iterating
over the results before.
If we look over at the preview,
I've now got earthquakes
ordered by time
and sectioned by day.
And SwiftUI even gives me
automatic support
for collapsing sections.
This new SectionedFetchRequest
type supports the same
dynamic configuration properties
as FetchRequest
as well as an additional
configuration property
for the section
identifier key path.
This is super important
because it's not actually safe
for us to change
the sorting anymore.
It could cause the sections
to be discontiguous
because time
and earthquake magnitude
aren't perfectly correlated,
which is probably for the best.
To fix this, I need to update
the sorts up top...
so each has a corresponding
section identifier key path.
Next, down in the toolbar...
I need to update
the section identifier key path
each time I update
the sort descriptors.
But here's the important part.
Changes to the request
are committed
whenever the results getter
is called,
so to update both the sorting
and the sectioning safely...
I need to update
the configuration on a reference
to the results that I've pulled
into a local.
Now in the preview,
we can see that
changing the order
also changes the sectioning.
We can flip between earthquakes
ordered by time,
sectioned by day,
and earthquakes ordered
and sectioned by magnitude.
And there we have it:
lazy stack initialization,
dynamic configuration,
and sectioned fetching,
all easily applied
to an existing app
using iOS 15 and macOS Monterey.
So, to recap, Core Data
is your one-stop shop
for managing your app's
data persistence needs
across all of Apple's platforms.
It harnesses the new
concurrency features
available in Swift
through a new perform API,
and still has powerful thread
safety debugging built right in.
It's got new enumeration
interfaces that make store
and attribute types even
more natural to use in Swift,
plus CloudKit sharing
and Spotlight integration.
And it's easier than ever
to connect your data
to your views using SwiftUI
with dynamic configuration
and sectioned fetching.
There's lots more
new stuff to learn
related to these topics.
We suggest checking out
the collections
"Simplify with SwiftUI
and Meet Swift Concurrency."
And that's it!
I'm really looking
forward to seeing
what you all build
with these new APIs.
[upbeat music]