[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Guoye Zhang: Hi, I'm Guoye.
My coworker Zhenchao and I
work on HTTP frameworks.
I'm sure you've heard a lot
about Swift concurrency by now.
If you haven't, check out
"Meet async/await in Swift".
I'm going to jump into
how async/await works
with URLSession.
What I like most
about Swift concurrency
is that it makes your code
linear, concise,
and it supports
native Swift error handling.
Networking is inherently
asynchronous,
and in iOS 15 and macOS Monterey
we introduced a set
of new APIs in URLSession
for you to take advantage
of Swift concurrency features.
To show you our new APIs,
here is an app we are working on
to adopt async/await.
It's a photo-sharing app
just for dog lovers,
and we can favorite
these photos.
Here is our existing code
that fetches a dog photo.
It's using the
completionHandler-based
convenience method
on URLSession.
The code seems straightforward,
and it worked in
my limited testing.
However, it has
at least three mistakes.
Let's dive in.
First, let's follow
the control flow.
We create a data task
and resume it.
Then once the task is done,
we jump into
the completion handler,
we check the response,
create an image,
and that's where
the control flow ends.
Hm, we are jumping
back and forth.
What about threading?
It is surprisingly complex
for this small piece of code.
We have three different
execution contexts in total.
The outmost layer runs on
whatever thread or queue
of the caller,
URLSessionTask
completionHandler
runs on session's
delegate queue,
and the final completion handler
runs on the main queue.
Since the compiler
cannot help us here,
we have to use extreme caution
to avoid any threading issues
such as data races.
Now, I noticed something wrong.
The calls to
the completionHandler
are not consistently dispatched
to the main queue.
This could be a bug.
Also, we are missing
an early return here.
The completionHandler can be
called twice if we got an error.
This could violate assumptions
made by the caller.
Finally, this might
not be very obvious,
but UIImage creation can fail.
If the data is in
an incorrect format,
this UIImage initializer
returns nil,
so we would have called
the completionHandler
with both nil image
and nil error.
This is likely not expected.
Now this is the new version
using async/await.
Wow, it's so much simpler!
The control flow is linear
from top to bottom,
and we know that everything
in this function
runs in the same
concurrency context,
so we no longer need to worry
about threading issues.
Here, we used the new async
data method on URLSession.
It suspends the current
execution context
without blocking,
and it returns data and response
on successful completion,
or throws an error.
We also used the throw keyword
to throw errors
when the response is unexpected.
This allows the caller
to catch and handle the error
using Swift
native error handling.
Lastly, the compiler would bark
if we try to return an optional
UIImage from this function,
so it essentially forces us
to handle nil correctly.
Here are the signatures
of the methods we just used
to fetch data from the network.
URLSession.data methods accept
either a URL or a URLRequest.
They are equivalent to existing
data task convenience methods.
We also provide upload methods
where you can upload data
or upload a file.
They are equivalent to existing
upload task
convenience methods.
Be sure to set
the correct HTTP method
before sending the request
since the default method GET
does not support upload.
Download methods store
the response body as a file
rather than in memory.
Different from download
task convenience methods,
these new methods do not
automatically delete the file,
so don't forget
to do so yourself.
In this example,
we are moving the file
to a different location
for further processing.
Swift concurrency's cancellation
works with URLSession
async methods.
One way to cancel is to use
a concurrency Task.Handle.
Here, we call async to create
a concurrency Task
loading two resources
one by one.
Later, we can use
the Task.Handle
to cancel its current
running operation.
Please note that
concurrency Task
is unrelated to URLSessionTask,
even though they share the name
"Task."
The methods
we just talked about --
data, upload, download --
wait for the entire response
body to arrive before returning.
What if we want to receive
the response body incrementally?
I'm happy to introduce
URLSession.bytes methods.
They return when the response
headers have been received
and deliver the response body
as an AsyncSequence of bytes.
To show you how it works,
my colleague Zhenchao
will demo how he's adopting it
in the Dogs app.
Zhenchao Li: Thanks, Guoye!
Hi, I'm Zhenchao.
I have been working on
a new feature of the Dogs app
that shows how many people
favorited a dog photo.
Right now, I can pull down
the scroll view
to refresh favorite counts.
I would like to update these
favorite counts in real time.
That way, the app feels
much more interactive.
To do that, our back-end
engineers have built
a real-time events endpoint
that gives us live updates
to photos.
I'm going to check out
the endpoint
to examine the response.
Each line of the response body
is a piece of JSON data
that describes updates
to a photo,
such as updated favorite counts.
Let's use the new
async sequence API
to consume the response
of the endpoint
and update the favorite counts
as real-time events are parsed.
We can kick off the live updates
in the onAppearHandler function,
which is an action called
when the photo collection view
appears.
Within the function,
I'm going to call
the new URLSession.bytes API
to fetch data
from our new endpoint.
Note that the bytes
returned here
have a type of
URLSession.AsyncBytes.
This gives us a way
to incrementally consume
response body.
I also added error checking here
to make sure that we did get a
successful response from server.
We want to parse
each line of the response
as a piece of JSON data.
To do that, we can use
the lines method on AsyncBytes.
This enables us to consume
the response line by line
as data is received.
Within the loop,
I can just parse the JSON data
and update my UI by calling
updateFavoriteCount.
Note that the UI updates need
to happen on the main actor,
and that's why I'm using
await syntax
to call updateFavoriteCount,
which is an async function.
Great. Now these favorite counts
are updated in real time.
Back to you, Guoye.
Guoye: Zhenchao
just showed us how to use
an AsyncSequence
built-in transformation --
lines -- to parse response body
line by line.
AsyncSequence supports many
convenience transformations,
and you can also use
AsyncSequence
with other system framework APIs
such as FileHandle.
To learn more
about AsyncSequence,
I encourage you to watch
the video "Meet AsyncSequence".
URLSession is designed
around a delegate model
which provides callbacks
for events such as
authentication challenges,
metrics, and more.
The new async methods no longer
expose the underlying task,
so how do we handle
authentication challenges
specific to a task?
Yes, all of those methods can
take an additional argument --
a task-specific delegate --
allowing you
to provide an object
to handle delegate messages
specific to this data upload,
download, or bytes operation.
We are also introducing
the delegate property
on NSURLSessionTask
in Objective-C
for you to take advantage of
the same capability.
The delegate is
strongly held by a task
until it completes or fails.
It's worth noting
that task-specific delegate
is not supported by
background URLSession.
If a method is implemented
on both session delegate
and task delegate, the one
on task delegate will be called.
Now, Zhenchao will show us
how to use
a task-specific delegate
to handle
authentication challenges.
Zhenchao: Thanks, Guoye!
Our Dogs app has a
simple data-fetching layer
written with the new async APIs.
For some of our
data-fetching tasks,
such as marking a photo
as favorite
or fetching
all favorited photos,
the user needs
to be authenticated.
Right now,
when I tap to favorite a photo,
I get an "Unauthorized" error.
Let's go through how we can add
user authentication
by using
a task-specific delegate.
First, let's write a
URLSessionTaskDelegate.
Let's call it
AuthenticationDelegate.
[KEYSTROKES]
The AuthenticationDelegate
conforms
to the
URLSessionTaskDelegate protocol,
and it accepts an instance of
signInController
in its initializer.
The signInController class
we implemented already contains
some nice helper functions
that we can use
to prompt the user
for credentials.
Next, let's implement
the URLSession
didReceive challenge
delegate method.
Within the delegate method,
we can choose to respond to HTTP
basic authentication challenges
by prompting the user
for credentials.
Of course, we should
not forget about error handling.
Now let's use this
AuthenticationDelegate class
as our task-specific delegate.
To do that, I can just
instantiate an instance of it
and parse it
as the delegate parameter
to the URLSession.data method.
Note that the delegate object
is not an instance variable,
and it's strongly held
by the task
until the task
completes or fails.
What's new here is that
the delegate can be used
to handle events
that are specific
to an instance of
a URLSession task,
which is handy when the logic
inside your delegate methods
only applies to certain
URLSession tasks and not others.
Great. Now when we tap
to favorite the photo...
...it pops up a login form.
Once we log in,
the photo shows as favorited,
and that it has been added to
our favorited-photos collection.
Back to you, Guoye.
Guoye: Thank you, Zhenchao,
for the demo.
We can't wait for you to try out
async/await with URLSession,
and we encourage you to apply
the same async concepts
to improve your code,
including changing functions,
taking a completion handler
to async functions,
and changing repeated events
handlers to AsyncSequences.
To learn more about advancements
in URLSession,
we have a video about
a cool new instrument
inspecting your app's
HTTP traffic
and a video about HTTP/3 support
in URLSession.
Thank you
and have a great WWDC!
♪