[music]
[Kyle] Hi, my name is Kyle Sanner,
from the GPU Software Engineering team.
Together with my colleague Alex Li,
we'll be talking about
how to get optimal frame pacing
in your apps
on variable refresh-rate displays.
We'll be focusing on some new display
technology coming to macOS,
Adaptive-Sync,
and how to drive custom drawing
smoothly on iPad Pro
under all conditions.
We'll start with a quick overview
of the types of displays
now supported on Apple Platforms.
We're going to introduce
you to Adaptive-Sync displays on the Mac,
and the new tools in macOS Monterey
that you can use to deliver
smooth frame rates in full-screen apps
and games on these displays.
Then, we'll dig
deep into ProMotion on iPad Pro,
and look at some CADisplayLink
best practices
that help your apps maintain
correct frame pacing
at different frame rates.
Let's first review the types
of displays Apple's devices can support.
Most displays on Apple systems
work at fixed refresh rates.
That is, they refresh
themselves at a consistent rate
whenever they are powered on.
The exception is
our ProMotion displays on iPad,
and now with Adaptive-Sync
displays on macOS.
Let's start digging in to what's new
with Adaptive-Sync displays on the Mac.
We'll start with what an Adaptive-Sync
display is, and how they work on the Mac.
But first, let's first take a quick
look at how a fixed-rate display works.
Here's a diagram showing frames
being delivered to a 60Hz display.
Each frame is presented to the display,
where it stays for 16ms
before the display is refreshed.
If there's a new frame drawn
by your Mac ready in the Framebuffer,
then that new frame is presented.
Otherwise,
the previous frame is shown again.
Looking at a 120Hz display,
you see that that though we've
doubled the refresh rate,
and thereby halved the interval
each frame can be onscreen,
it behaves the same way, just faster.
Take a look at this Adaptive-Sync display,
on the other hand.
Instead of a static duration,
each frame has a window of time
that it can be onscreen.
This window varies depending
on the attached display.
This display can
operate between 40 and 120Hz,
which means that a frame can be
onscreen anywhere between 8 and 25ms.
Note that once
the maximum time has elapsed,
the system must refresh the panel,
and the display will briefly
be unavailable for new updates
for a short time.
Okay, so what kind of benefits
can your games and apps get
on an Adaptive-Sync Display?
For applications that mostly run at
the maximum refresh rate of the display,
Adaptive-Sync displays provide
a great benefit for free.
Let's first take a look at this scenario,
where your app is mostly able to produce
new frames in under 8ms,
so you're running fairly reliably
at 120Hz.
But due to a momentary increase in scene
complexity,
the finished frame lands
in the Framebuffer
9ms after the previous
frame was first displayed.
On a fixed frame rate display,
the previous frame
is displayed for 16ms,
instead of the 8ms you intended.
This results in a perceptible
hitch in your app.
On an Adaptive-Sync display,
your frame is presented to the display
immediately after it is done,
so your app incurs only a 1ms penalty.
Hitches this small are generally
not perceptible to users.
For workloads that can't reach
the maximum frame rate of the display,
you can provide smooth,
even frames by making
some small changes to how your app
presents its drawables.
Consider this scenario:
a game running a complex scene
can produce updates at around 90Hz.
However, an intermittent effect
causes a large jump in complexity,
but does so inconsistently,
causing sudden spikes down to 66Hz.
By monitoring your app's GPU work,
you can respond to this spike
in complexity by intentionally
presenting your frames later
until your scene's complexity
is consistently lower.
Now, let's talk about some
Adaptive-Sync best practices.
On a fixed rate display, when your app's
GPU work consistently exceeds
the display's on-glass interval,
we've previously recommended
that you slow down your rendering
to hit the next factor
of the display's fastest refresh rate.
Typically, that means lowering your target
frames per second to 30 from 60,
like in this example here.
When presenting
to an Adaptive-Sync display, however,
we're changing that guidance.
You should instead attempt
to present frames at the highest rate
your app can do so evenly.
In addition to presenting frames evenly,
remember that if your frames are presented
at less than the minimum rate
that the display supports,
that the display might become
unavailable for new frames,
which could induce judder in your app.
But so long as
you're in the supported range,
you're free to pick whatever
rate works best for your app.
Now that you've
got a high-level understanding
of the new display support
coming to the Mac this year,
let's talk about how to enable
Adaptive Sync in your games.
First, you'll need a supported Mac.
Any Mac with an Apple Silicon GPU
will work great,
and we also support many of our most
recent Intel-based Macs as well.
Second, you'll need a supported
Adaptive-Sync display,
and to enable Adaptive-Sync mode.
This can be done by selecting
the new variable refresh rate
available in Display System Preferences.
And lastly, your app needs to be
running in full-screen mode.
Let's see what APIs you can
call in your app to detect
whether it should be attempting
to do Adaptive-Sync scheduling.
First, you'll need to determine whether
or not the display you're running on
is capable of Adaptive-Sync scheduling.
For that, there are some new
properties this year on NSScreen,
minimumRefreshInterval
and maximumRefreshInterval.
These values tell you the range
of valid onscreen times
for a frame presented to this display.
On a fixed-frame display,
these values will be the same,
so a simple
not-equal comparison
will tell you whether this screen
is in Adaptive-Sync mode.
Next, you'll need to know if
your window is currently full screen.
You can determine that by
checking your window's styleMask.
And remember, you'll need to combine
both of these checks to ensure your app
is able to take advantage
of Adaptive-Sync scheduling.
Okay, great.
So, now that you've got a handle
on Adaptive-Sync displays and the new APIs
that macOS provides to detect them,
let's see how we can adapt some existing
metal presentation techniques
to present evenly
on an Adaptive-Sync display.
You can use our MetalDrawable APIs
that have built-in frame-pacing,
such as presentAfterMinimumDuration
or presentAtTime,
to great effect
with Adaptive-Sync displays.
Or, you can roll your own
solution with a present now call
and your own custom timers.
Let's take a look at how a few
different implementations will work.
We'll start with a simple example.
Here, we're going to acquire a Drawable,
set up our GPU work,
and present it on the screen.
We're relying on the back
pressure of a Drawable being available
to set our frame rate for us.
On a fixed-rate display, we know that this
isn't the best idea,
since there's no
guarantee that your GPU work
will align to the refresh rate
of the display.
But as you can see from this instruments
capture taken on an Adaptive-Sync display,
when our scene is consistent,
this seems to work out okay.
The problem here is that this
scene is running into periodic hitches.
These hitches will translate
into stutters that are visible to users.
Let's try to fix that by
presenting at a fixed, even rate.
This technique can also be
used if you want to implement
a user-adjustable FPS slider
for the players of your game.
Here, we've set
the frequency we want to 78Hz.
And instead of a plain present call,
we'll use present afterMinimumDuration
for this Drawable, and specify
the interval that we defined above.
And here, you can see smoothly presented
frames at the rate that we requested.
We aren't presenting as quickly
as the previous example,
but your users are far less
likely to encounter stutters,
and your app
will use less CPU and GPU time.
Okay, so here's where things
get a little more interesting.
Let's try an approach that will
produce evenly-paced frames
without having to set a single fixed rate.
One way to do this is to compute
a rolling average of the GPU work
needed to produce each frame,
and feed that time
into our present Drawable call.
For the first frame, we need to load our
average GPU time with a starting value.
I'm going to choose to be optimistic
and target the fastest rate
the display can support here.
This will just be a starting
point for our average,
so any reasonable guess we make is fine.
Now, let's attach a CommandBuffer
completion handler
to measure the amount of time the GPU
spent rendering this frame,
and incorporate that time
into our rolling average.
First, we can acquire the time
the GPU took to complete our work.
Then, we'll incorporate that new time
into our rolling average
that will be used
when we present the next frame.
And here are the results.
As you can see, we're presenting
at a rate similar to the previous example,
but this limit is determined by
the previous frames we've generated,
and will produce even frame
rates across a range of Mac GPUs.
Here, we can see the same
program running smoothly at 48Hz
on a less powerful Mac,
without any additional code changes.
All right, Now you've got some new tools
and techniques
that you can use to optimize your app
for Adaptive-Sync displays.
If you want to learn more about
Adaptive-Sync displays on macOS,
check out the new Metal sample
project on the Apple Developer site.
To learn more about delivering
performant experiences in Metal,
check out these
WWDC talks from previous years.
And now, I'll hand you over to Alex,
where you'll learn more
about frame pacing on iPad Pro.
[Alex] Thank you, Kyle.
Next, let's talk about ProMotion.
Since 2017, every iPad Pro has
been equipped with a ProMotion display
that delivers refresh rates
of up to 120Hz.
However, 120Hz may not be
available in some situations,
including when the user has
switched on Low Power Mode,
which has been brought to the iPad
this year with iPadOS 15.
Proper frame pacing will allow
your app to present motion contents
correctly and smoothly,
regardless of display characteristics,
user preferences, and system states.
We are going to look at the differences
between ProMotion and fixed rate displays,
as well as the situations in which some
frame rates may not be available.
Next, we'll
discuss what is a display link,
and how your app can use
it to drive custom drawing.
And finally, we'll offer some
display link best practices.
Let's dive right in.
As Kyle has briefly presented earlier,
a fixed 60Hz display
refreshes every 16ms, a fixed cadence.
It supports smooth presentation
of contents
whose frame rates are factors of 60.
For example, 60Hz, 30Hz, 20Hz, and so on.
However, when the content is slower
than the display refresh rate, say 30Hz,
the display itself still has to be
refreshed at the same cadence,
hence, every other frame is a repeat
of the previous,
and this consumes some power.
On the other hand,
ProMotion offers great responsiveness
with refresh rates of up to 120Hz.
It also adapts to onscreen content
and so reduces its power consumption.
Let's see how it works.
Of course, at its maximum refresh rate
of 120Hz, the display refreshes every 8ms.
Since 120 is a multiple of 60, ProMotion
supports all existing frame rates.
It offers not just 120Hz,
but some intermediate frame rates
for your apps as well.
Moreover, ProMotion can dynamically
adjust its refresh rate,
so with a smooth 60Hz content,
it can refresh only every 16ms
without repeats, which otherwise would
be required on a fixed 120Hz display.
This is true all the way down to 24Hz.
Now, these frame rates may
not always be available.
The user can
turn on Limit Frame Rate toggle
in Accessibility settings
that caps the maximum frame rate to 60Hz.
Also, when the device gets hot,
the system may
apply restrictions
on the availability of 120Hz.
With iPadOS 15, we'll also
enforce the 60Hz cap in Low Power Mode.
So, how do these
scenarios affect your apps?
The good news is that most apps
will work without any changes.
But if your app performs frame-by-frame
custom drawing,
then you would need to pay attention
to these frame rate changes,
and we will show you how to do that.
The recommended tool to drive
custom drawing is display link,
which is essentially a timer that is
synchronized with display refresh rate.
It helps your app drive any
custom animations or custom render loop.
There are two display links.
One is CVDisplayLink, offered by CoreVideo
on macOS, and the other is CADisplayLink,
offered by CoreAnimation on our other
platforms, as well as Catalyst on macOS,
each with slightly different
characteristics and behavior.
Today, we'll only discuss CADisplayLink,
but on a high level,
these concepts will apply to both.
CADisplayLink wakes up at every
vsync and invokes the callback.
This provides the application
the entire 8ms to complete its work.
A regular timer, such as an NSTimer,
is very unlikely
to be in perfect sync with the display.
It can be out of phase or drifting,
so sometimes the app may not have
enough time to complete its work
and it leads to frame drops.
Now you've seen how CADisplayLink
provides consistent timings,
here are some of its additional benefits.
It can run at a slower rate
than the display refresh rate,
and to do so, your app provides
a hint via preferredFramesPerSecond
and we will choose the nearest
available frame rate for you.
When the frame rate availability changes,
as we have discussed earlier,
CADisplayLink will automatically
adjust its rate under the hood.
Of course, it also provides your app
with the necessary timing information
so that your custom drawing
can be aware of these changes.
We won't go into how to write
a custom animation or custom render loop,
but we will provide you with four
best practices to help your custom drawing
stay in sync with display timings
and avoid some of the common pitfalls.
First, it is important to query
the display refresh rate at runtime
instead of hard-coding it.
Second, it is usually
the case that you should use
the frame rate
of the CADisplayLink itself.
Next, using targetTimestamp to prepare
the drawing will help reduce hitches.
Finally, it is always a good idea
to prepare for the unexpected
by dynamically
computing the time delta.
Let's go through them one by one.
The maximum display refresh rate
can be queried via UIScreen,
which will always return
120Hz on ProMotion displays,
even during situations such
as when Low Power Mode is turned on.
On the other hand,
CADisplayLink will actually
provide the shortest interval
between frames via the duration property,
and it will dynamically update
based on the current device state.
But almost always, you should use
the actual frame information
directly from the CADisplayLink
because the display link can run slower
than the maximum display refresh rate.
Also, frame rate availability
is dependent on the hardware,
and the actual frame rate may be changed
dynamically by the display link itself
in response to system state changes.
Let's look at an example.
Suppose we request a 40Hz display link.
As you see,
on a ProMotion display, 40Hz is supported.
However, on a 60Hz display,
or when ProMotion is capped at 60Hz,
the display link will
automatically adjust itself to 30Hz.
This ensures a good cadence
where each wake-up is on a possible vsync
that tries to give the equal
amount of time for each frame.
If we were to use a plain 40Hz NSTimer,
which is not frame rate aware,
its wake-up could be right in the middle
of the vsync interval,
and of course,
we cannot present a frame there,
so you'll likely observe hitches
in your custom drawing.
So, how does it look in the code?
Well, here is how you would
usually set up a display link.
First, you must
provide a target and a selector,
which is the callback to be invoked.
Next, hint the preferred frame
rate of 40Hz via preferredFramesPerSecond.
You then add the display
link to the current runloop,
from which the callback will be invoked.
So, in the callback,
you can get the expected interval
between display link wake-ups
by subtracting the timestamp
from targetTimestamp.
This interval is not necessarily always
1 over 40 because the display link itself
may be running at a different frequency.
Next, let's talk about these timestamps.
There are primarily two
timestamps on the CADisplayLink,
Timestamp, which denotes when the callback
is scheduled to be invoked,
and targetTimestamp,
which is when the next frame
will be composited by CoreAnimation.
We'll walk through an example
that illustrates why you should use
targetTimestamp to prepare your drawings.
Here's an animation in its normalized
time domain from 0 to 1.
Suppose we are targeting the highest frame
rate possible and currently it is 120Hz.
CADisplayLink wakes up,
and if we were to prepare
our frame presentation using timestamp,
we'll sample directly here,
which gets presented in the next vsync,
and here it is.
The same process continues,
and we see that it has a good cadence
where for each 120Hz frame,
our animation progress increases by 0.05.
Now, suppose the thermal state changes,
and 120Hz is no longer available.
Now the display link wakes up again,
and the app prepares the animation
at progress 0.4, which gets
presented in the next vsync right here.
And the same pattern continues.
Something's not quite right
at the transition here.
We see that the progress increases
by 0.05, but one is over 8ms,
and the other is over 16ms.
It's very clear
if we plot progress versus time,
we'll see a hiccup right at
the transition,
and this will reflect
as a user perceptible hitch,
and that's not desirable.
Now, let's try targetTimestamp.
CADisplayLink wakes up here.
The progress is sampled at
targetTimestamp, which gives 0.15.
The same pattern continues,
and again, we see a good cadence.
At this frame rate transition point,
the display link wakes up,
samples at targetTimestamp,
and we get 0.50.
And it continues in the same way.
If we plot the same progress
versus time graph,
you will see that it is a straight line,
and hence it provides smooth contents
even when the frame rate changes.
So, targetTimestamp should be used rather
than timestamp to prepare your drawings.
In your code,
it should generally be as simple
as replacing any timestamp
usage with targetTimestamp.
Finally, let's talk about
dynamically computing the time delta.
The difference between
targetTimestamp and timestamp
gives you the expected amount
of time between display link callbacks,
but the actual amount
of time is not guaranteed.
A higher priority thread
may be scheduled on the CPU,
or the runloop
is busy with something else.
In the extreme case,
callbacks may be skipped entirely,
so in these situations,
it's especially critical to still maintain
the correct timing in your custom
drawing for the best user experience.
When the CADisplayLink callback
is invoked, the app performs its work
to prepare the updates
or renders necessary for the next frame.
Usually, the callback will be invoked
right at the scheduled wake-up time,
but it's not alays the case.
We expect the next
callback to be invoked here.
However, the display link
doesn't get a chance to run
until a few milliseconds
into the vsync interval.
And hence, you may not get the full 8ms.
In this case,
you can query CACurrentMediaTime
and compare with targetTimestamp to get
a sense of how much time is available.
Now, suppose the work is
taking too long in this frame.
The next callback won't be invoked
until the runloop is free again.
Because this one is delayed,
the following callback will be skipped,
so when you are preparing to advance
the progress of your custom drawing
in this callback, be mindful that the time
delta that you should use is not 8ms,
but rather 16ms, if you were to keep track
of the previous timestamp
at which your custom
drawing state was updated at.
Therefore, if your app uses time delta
to advance the state
of your custom drawing,
this will slow down your custom drawing
by one frame
every time a calback is skipped.
You can instead keep track
of a previous targetTimestamp
so that you can
advance the state correctly.
And if your custom drawing has high
workload, you can look at targetTimestamp
to potentially reduce the workload
to meet the deadline as needed.
To recap the best practices,
don't guess the display refresh rate.
Always query it at runtime.
Your custom drawing should be
flexible in its supported frame rates
and should be ready
to adapt to a different rate.
Use targetTimestamp to ensure a hitch-free
frame rate transition,
and be on the look out
for any unexpected situations,
such as missed display link callback.
So, let's wrap up.
In the first half of this session,
we've discussed how to optimize your app's
frame-pacing when running
on an Adaptive-Sync display on macOS.
In the second half,
we've described the best practices
for your app to drive its custom drawing
and maintain smooth frame-pacing
under all conditions
on a ProMotion display on iPad Pro.
As display technologies continue
to evolve,
we hope this session
has provided you with not only insights,
but also tools and best practices
to support the increasingly dynamic
timings of the displays.
Thank you so much for joining us,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC 2021.
[music]