[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Erik Hornberger: Welcome back to
the third and final installment
of our Research
and Care app code-along!
If you'd like to follow along,
you can find the source code
for this app
in the session resources.
Let's log in and get started.
In our last session, we added
a couple of tasks into the app.
Since then,
I've been getting all kinds
of notifications from Jamie.
I have a feeling
that something's up.
Let's see.
Jamie will arrive at the clinic
in 10 minutes.
Jamie shared
a Motivation Playlist.
Wow! As you can see,
the ever-enthusiastic
Jamie is on his way
to meet with the clinicians
right now.
It looks like Jamie has asked us
to make a couple of changes
and to add two new features.
The first bit is
about enhancing the surveys
that we implemented
in session two.
Jamie says he got some feedback
about them from testers.
He told us the feedback that he got
was that testers
want to be able to tell
what answers they gave
after the fact.
Right now, the card just shows
that the survey has been
completed,
but if you scroll
back in time a couple of days,
there's no way to tell what
answer you gave on that day.
They'd also like us to restrict
editing to the current date.
You shouldn't really be able
to delete survey answers
or redo range of motion tests
in the past.
Similarly, it doesn't
really make sense
that you can scroll out
into the future
and preanswer surveys on days
that haven't come yet.
So we'll start off
by addressing that feedback
and enhancing the surveys a bit.
We've also got this Insights tab
that's still looking
a bit lonely.
Jamie asked that we display
a pair of charts there.
One will capture
the relationship
between sleep and pain,
and the other will show
improvement in range of motion
over time.
Finally, Jamie tells me
that the doctors have asked
we include some
educational content
to help participants understand
what a torn meniscus is,
and ResearchKit will be able
to help us out there.
We're going to begin
by enhancing the surveys.
Let's tackle showing the answers
the patient gave.
We'll go ahead and display
the given answers as text
in the card.
Now, in CareKit, tweaking
the appearance of a task card
is done by passing
a viewSynchronizer
into its initializer.
Let's take a look
at how we can create
a custom View Synchronizer.
We'll subclass the existing
OCKSurveyTaskViewSynchronizer.
This class has two methods
that we can override:
makeView and updateView.
updateView will be called
every time the data
in the store changes,
and it's where we can apply
customizations to our view.
We always start out by calling
the superclass's implementation
and apply our enhancements
on top of that.
We'll check to see
if there is an event
with a completed outcome.
If there is, that means that
the survey has been finished.
We'll snag the pain answer
and the sleep answer
by referencing the kind property
that we set back in part two.
I mentioned that by setting
the kind property,
it would help us out later,
and this is
one of the applications
that I was alluding to.
Now that we have
the answers handy,
we can use string interpolation
to insert the answers
into our card's
instruction label.
And that'll take care
of showing the answers.
Jamie also asked that we disable
editing of past tasks.
One way we can do that
is to first set ourselves
as the delegate
for our survey task cards
and then fill in
this delegate method:
viewController for task
shouldAllowDeleting
OutcomeForEvent.
Our job is to return a boolean
that tells CareKit
if it should allow
a particular event's outcome
to be deleted or not.
We'll look at the date
that the event falls on.
If the date is earlier
than today,
we'll say
that it can't be deleted.
If it is on or after today,
we'll allow deleting it.
And just like that,
we've prevented deletion
of past data.
The third thing Jamie asked
is that we also
prevent participants
from completing surveys
on future dates.
To do that, we'll climb up
a bit higher in the same file
to just before where we create
our task view controllers,
and we'll use
some Calendar utilities
to check if the day
we're populating content for
is in the future or not.
If it is a future date,
we'll disable interaction
with the task card,
and we'll reduce the opacity
to visually indicate
that it's disabled.
All right, nice!
Now we shouldn't be able
to complete future tasks either.
Let's see where we stand.
The first thing
that you'll notice
is that the answers
that were given for surveys
are now displayed
in the survey task cards.
We still have the option
to delete or redo surveys
on the current date,
but if we swipe
back into the past,
we're no longer able
to redo them.
And if we jump forward
into the future,
we can preview what's coming up,
but we can't complete
any of the surveys yet.
Our app is really
coming together now!
The last two things
we need to do
are the charts
and educational content,
and these are both
in the Insights tab.
We're going to start off
with a two-series bar chart
showing the pain rating
and hours of sleep side by side.
We'll need to create two
OCKDataSeriesConfiguration
objects.
The first is
for the pain series.
The ID tells CareKit
which task's data
to plot on the chart.
We'll also pass a legend title,
colors, a marker size --
which determines
how wide the bars will be --
and an event aggregator.
The event aggregator
is responsible
for looking at all the events
that occur on a given day
to determine what Y value
should be used on that day.
For the check-in task,
we know there will only ever be
one event per day,
so we can just take
the first event
and get the answer
to the pain question.
So that's the pain series
configuration.
We'll also need one for sleep.
The sleep series
is almost identical.
We're plotting data from
the exact same check-in task.
The difference is that
we display the sleep answer,
instead of the pain answer.
With both of these in hand,
we can construct
a chart view controller.
We'll choose a bar chart
and set the date to today.
Of course, we also need
to pass in our two series
and a reference
to the store manager,
which is used
to keep the chart up to date
as the content
of the store changes.
Great, so that's
our first chart.
Let's make one more!
This time,
it's going to be a scatter chart
for range of motion.
We'll need to create
a data series configuration
just as we did before,
but this time around,
we'll only need one.
The only difference this time
is that we're plotting data
from the range of motion task
instead of check-in task,
and we're using the range answer
for the Y axis.
Next, we'll create
our view controller.
This time it's going
to be a scatter plot,
and we only have
one data series.
And just like that,
we've got both
of our charts set up.
Let's see how they look.
Jumping over
the Insights tab,
we can see both of our charts
are now rendering.
They look really nice!
If we jump back,
and we add or delete
some outcomes --
here, we'll delete both
outcomes for Tuesday --
and then return
to the Insights tab,
we should see our charts
updated automatically.
And they have!
There's no longer any data
being shown for Tuesday.
Nice!
So charts are looking good.
Jamie also asked
that we give the participants
an option to view a 3D model
of the knee and the meniscus,
along with some explanatory text
he received
from our clinical partners.
ResearchKit can help us out
with that.
I'd like to pause for a second
to note that this time around,
we are not tying the ResearchKit
survey to a CareKit schedule.
There's no particular time
at which we want participants
to look at this content,
so we don't need
the notion of a schedule.
Similarly, there aren't
any results for us
to persist
into CareKit's store,
so we don't need
to create a CareKit task
or use CareKit's
survey task view controller.
That said, we can use
the FeaturedContent view
that my teammate Gavi
introduced at WWDC last year.
We'll need to set ourselves
as the delegate
so that we can be told
when the participant taps
the featured content card.
When they do,
we'll create a kneeModelTask,
wrap it in an
ORKTaskViewController,
and present it
to the participant.
When they're done
viewing the model,
we'll get a callback right here,
and we can use that
as an opportunity
to dismiss the ResearchKit
view controller
and bring the participant back
into the Insights tab.
All right, very nice!
But we are missing
a definition here
for this knee task.
Let's go fill that in
over in Surveys.swift.
It's going to be
just two steps,
where the first is going
to be an instruction step.
I hope these are starting
to feel at least a little bit
familiar to you by now,
since we used them
several times already today.
The second step
is a 3D model step.
Whenever we create
a 3D model step,
we also need to pass in
a modelManager,
so just up above it,
we'll create a USDZ
model manager to pass in.
We're going to start off
by displaying a toy robot
just to make sure
that everything is working.
The last bit is to assemble
an ordered task
with both of our steps
and to return it.
Now, when we run our app,
we'll see the featured content
card in the Insights tab,
and tapping on it will bring up
our instruction step,
followed by our toy robot model.
We can interact with it
by rotating, zooming in on it...
pretty neat!
If you'd like to know more about
how the 3D model manager works,
or how you can implement
your own version of it,
you can check out Pariece's
WWDC session from last year.
To finish up our app,
I'm going to swap out
our toy robot
for BioDigital's model manager.
We'll include some notes on this
in the project's Read Me,
in case you're interested
in knowing the details.
With this version
of the model manager,
we can provide educational text
from the clinicians.
Here you can see some content
provided
by our clinical partners.
We can also highlight
the meniscus
for the participant's reference
to help them understand
more about their injury
and what the path
to recovery will be.
Our app is really
coming together now!
Actually, that's it,
that is everything!
We have checked
all of the boxes!
[FACETIME RINGING]
And just in
the nick of time, too!
It looks like we're getting
another call from Jamie.
Hey Jamie, good timing!
We just wrapped up everything
that you asked us to do.
Jamie: Oh wow, yeah. I'm taking
a look at it right now, Erik.
Let's see...
Yeah, this is really
coming along nicely.
The rest of the team
is going to be thrilled,
and this is going to open up
so many research opportunities!
Quick question for you.
Before I head into this next meeting,
what should I tell
the team to do
if they have any questions
for you?
Erik: Hey, that's a good
question!
So ResearchKit and CareKit
are both open source,
and our team is active
on GitHub.
If they have any questions
about the frameworks,
if they want to request
a new feature,
or if they want to contribute,
tell them to open a new issue
on our GitHub repos.
Jamie: OK yeah,
that's fantastic.
I'll pass that info along
to the team.
Erik: By the way Jamie,
you should consider telling us
more about your study!
If you go to
researchandcare.org,
you'll find a link there
that you can use to tell Apple
the details about
who your study helps.
We love to hear about
how our frameworks
are being used by the community!
We also have
an Investigator Support Program
that offers grants
of Apple Watch
to institutions that propose
novel research studies.
If they want to apply,
they can find the details
on our website as well.
Jamie: Really?
That's fantastic!
I think they'll definitely
want to take advantage of that.
But, Erik, all right I've got
to pop into another meeting.
I've got tons of big ideas
for a second app
that I want to run by you later.
How long do you think an app
for Apple Watch would take?
Erik: All right, but let's
catch up and discuss that later;
like, in a couple of days.
I think I've got enough
to keep me busy for a while!
Jamie: Oh yeah, I heard
you're doing a code-along
this year for WWDC?
Good luck with that!
I'll talk to you later!
[FACETIME END CHIME]
Erik: [LAUGHS]
If you'd like more info,
you can find it on
researchandcare.org.
Source code is available
on GitHub,
and we have two other sessions
this year
that lead up to the one
you just watched.
Well, that's all we've got
for you folks.
Thank you for joining us
for our code-along!
We saw how
our sibling frameworks,
ResearchKit and CareKit,
can be used in tandem
to quickly iterate on an app.
We also covered
some of our new features
and our latest best practices.
I hope you were able to pick up
a few tips and tricks
along the way.
From all of us here on the team,
we hope that you have
a great WWDC!
♪