[etherial percussion music]
♪ ♪
[Kasia] Hi.
My name is Kasia Wawer.
I'm an engineer
on the Keyboards UI team,
and today, I'll be your guide
to the wonderful world
of keyboard layout.
I am incredibly excited
to talk to you today
about bringing the keyboard
from a frame-based past
into an auto-layout future.
We'll start our tour by talking
about the new guide.
Then, we'll go over some of the
new things you'll be able to do
to more fully integrate
the keyboard into your layout.
And finally, we'll talk about
what a keyboard really is--
philosophically speaking,
types of keyboards to consider,
and some of the cases you might
not think about right away.
So, let's get started
with our tour.
As with many things, this one
begins in the ancient past.
If you have worked with
the keyboard in your app before,
you know the way that it's been
handled since time immemorial
is by registering
for notifications,
deriving the appropriate
offsets and animations
from the information
in the notification,
doing some math, and finally,
using that
to adjust your layout.
Now, notifications
are sticking around.
We are not deprecating them.
You can learn more about them,
if you're interested,
in "The Keys to a Better Text
Input Experience" from 2017.
Let's look at a quick example
of how notifications
might be used
with a custom guide.
Now, don't copy
any of this code
because we're
about to replace it.
But here's how you handle
the keyboard before iOS 15.
You'd create
your custom guide and anchors
to respond to notifications.
Then, you'd register for
the appropriate notifications.
Usually, at least
willShow and willHide,
but sometimes
frame changes, etc.
Then, you'd respond
to said notifications
by getting the frame information
from the notification,
making sure that you're
adjusting for your own views
and the safe area guide,
if the keyboard
is leaving the screen.
And you'd get the animation info
from the notification
and, finally,
change your guide to match.
Now, it's not a ton,
but it can get
complicated quickly.
Today, I am happy to announce
a brand-new addition
to the auto layout collection:
UI keyboard layout guide.
Now, try to constrain
your excitement
as we dive into this.
Keyboard layout guide
is brand-new in iOS 15.
It's a layout guide.
You can constrain
the views and guides
in your existing layout to it.
If you're not familiar
with layout guides,
a layout guide is a way
to represent space
in a layout
without using a view.
It has all the same
anchors as a view.
The keyboard layout guide
will represent the space
that the keyboard
occupies in your app
so that your layout
can account for it.
And that's it!
Mostly.
Let's talk about updating
that code we just saw
to use this instead.
Here's that notifications code.
Don't copy it yet,
wait for the green checkmark.
So, now you can go ahead
and remove that anchor
you were tracking.
And change
from your layout guide
to the view's
keyboardLayoutGuide.
And we don't need to register
for notifications anymore.
And we don't need
to respond to them either.
And that's it.
All that code boils down
to this single line.
Ready to see it in action?
Here's what it looks like
to bring up the keyboard
when using
the notifications code.
And here's what it looks like
to bring it up using the guide.
You may have noticed that,
other than their localizations,
those looked
virtually identical,
but that's kinda the point.
You don't have
to do nearly as much,
and you get the same result.
So, let's talk
about updating to the guide.
It's a property on UI view.
And, for most cases,
you'll just update to using
the guide's topAnchor.
The guide matches
keyboard animations,
like bring up and dismiss,
and it follows
height changes too.
Because sometimes
the keyboard is taller,
and sometimes it's shorter.
But the guide will adapt
to fit whatever size appears.
And, when the keyboard
is undocked, by default,
the guide will drop
to the bottom of the screen
and be the width of your window,
and anything you've tied
to the top anchor will follow.
It accounts
for safe-area insets,
so you don't have to worry
about that anymore, either.
For basic uses, that's probably
all you need to know.
But now we get to talk
about the fun stuff.
Why did we choose
to use a new class
and not just
a normal layout guide?
Well, we wanted you
to be able to do more
than you've ever been able
to do with the keyboard.
Our next stop is full keyboard
integration into your app.
Why do I say "integration"?
Well, I have often heard
people talking
about the keyboard
as something they need to avoid,
or as something fighting
with their layout,
but the keyboard is part
of your app.
One of the main motivations
behind UI keyboard layout guide
is to give you, the developer,
the ability to respond
to the many different ways
we have for users
to input text,
and let you really,
fully think of the keyboard
as a part of your layout
in a way that maybe you haven't
been able to before.
I am really excited to see
how you take advantage
of these new features.
So, our next stop,
what makes keyboard layout guide
not just a layout guide?
With UI keyboard layout guide,
you have the ability
to fully follow the keyboard
in all its incarnations,
if you so choose,
by using a new property:
followsUndockedKeyboard.
It's false by default,
but if you set it to true,
the guide will follow
the keyboard
when it's undocked or floating,
giving you a lot of control
over how your layout responds
to wherever the keyboard may be.
No more automatic
drop-to-bottom.
No listening for hide keyboard
notifications when undocking.
The layout guide is
where the keyboard is.
The thing about having
that information, though,
is that it means you have
to be a lot more conscious
of how your layout is responding
to different types of keyboards.
So, UI keyboard layout guide
is a subclass
of another new layout guide:
UI tracking layout guide.
We call it a tracking layout guide
because it tracks the
constraints you want to change
when it moves around the screen.
You can give it an array
of constraints that activate
when near a specific edge,
and deactivate when leaving it,
and/or an array that activates
when specifically
awayFrom an edge,
and deactivates when near it.
Let's look at an example
of what you can do with this,
and the code
you need to achieve it.
Here's a test app.
I have a text field
and some controls
that can sit on the keyboard.
But,  when it gets close
to the top of the screen,
I want them to drop
to the bottom
to avoid going off-screen.
And when the keyboard
moves side to side,
I want the rest
of the UI to shift a bit
to give it a little more space.
So, how is
all this accomplished?
We're gonna look
at some code here.
In the following slides,
the editView is the view with
the text field and controls,
and the imageView
is the image view.
Okay, note that we should be
using identifiers here,
and you will see that
in the sample code,
but this fits better
on a slide.
Let's start
with what's happening
on the vertical axis.
First, we define
an array that ties the bottom
of the editView to
the keyboard layout guide's top.
Then, we set those to be active
only when the guide is
away from the top,
so that they'll be deactivated
when it's near it.
Then, we define a separate array
of constraints that we want
for when the keyboard gets close
to the top of the view.
So, instead of the top
of the keyboard layout guide,
we use the safe area's bottom.
Here's a quick visual to help.
Here's the guide
and the editView.
It's currently away
from the top,
so the awayFromTopConstraints
are active.
But, as you move the guide
closer to the top,
the awayFrom constraints
are deactivated,
and the nearTopConstraints
are activated,
dropping it down
to the bottom of the view.
When we're back away from
the top, the reverse happens.
Now, let's look
at horizontal movement.
When the keyboard is away
from both the leading
and trailing edges,
I want the editView to be
at the center of the keyboard.
I want the imageView to be
centered in the view, as well.
So, I define those constraints
and set them to be active
when I'm away from both
leading and trailing.
Now, let's set up what happens
when we approach an edge.
I want the editView
to move over to trailing
when we're at the trailing edge,
and leading to leading.
So, first,
let's take care of that.
I want the imageView
to move out of the way
of the keyboard a little,
so when we're near either edge,
I move it from the center
to the opposite side
from the keyboard,
leading to leading
when the keyboard is
on the trailing edge,
and vice versa.
Then, I just set these
to be active
when I'm near the proper edge.
They'll be activated
when the keyboard crosses
into that region,
and deactivated when it leaves.
And that's it!
Super advanced
keyboard integration
into your very own layout.
Let's take a look at what
that looks like one more time.
There's my editView.
It stays
with the floating keyboard,
and as we move towards the top,
it drops to the bottom.
And as we move side to side,
the adjustments
we just talked about happen.
Pretty cool!
Next, let's talk
about what "near"
and "awayFrom" mean
for the keyboard.
A docked keyboard is
considered to be
near the bottom
and awayFrom the other edges.
Undocked and split keyboards
can be awayFrom all edges,
or they can get
near the top edge.
When it's the floating keyboard,
it can be near
or awayFrom any edge,
and it can even be near two
adjacent edges at the same time.
This can lead to some
potentially interesting
conflicts that you
should be aware of.
Now, all of this only applies
when you set
followsUndockedKeyboard to true,
and for the rest of the talk,
that's the assumption
we'll be making.
Okay.
Final stretch:
considerations
for full keyboard integration.
A keyboard is a keyboard
is a keyboard--
until it's not.
When you choose to follow
the undocked keyboard,
you have some extra things
to think about.
So, what sorts of things should
you be paying attention to
when designing your layout?
Always remember
that the floating keyboard
can be awayFrom everything.
Do you have sufficient
information to be laid out
correctly if it's awayFrom
all edges?
Also, what should happen
when the keyboard is
awayFrom the bottom edge,
or near the top edge?
You want to be careful
with what's tied
to the topAnchor
of the keyboard, as well.
Because it can get way up there!
So, be careful.
The way to resolve that
is to set constraints
when the keyboard is awayFrom
the bottom edge
that move those views off
of the topAnchor of the keyboard
and down to the bottom
of the safeAreaLayoutGuide.
A user can also move
the keyboard at any time,
so you can't count on it
being any where specific.
You'll wanna keep that in mind,
as well.
Here's a rare specimen:
the split keyboard.
Split and undocked keyboards
are awayFrom all edges,
until it gets too close
to the top.
As with a docked keyboard,
it's always away from leading
and trailing, as well.
Let's talk about some new stuff.
There's a new way
to get text into your app
this year, using the camera.
It's still a keyboard,
so it will still be able
to use the guide.
It's the same
as a regular docked keyboard,
but it's one of a few keyboards
that can be pretty much
full screen.
To learn more about taking
advantage of text input
via camera this year,
tune into "Use the camera
for keyboard input in your app."
Continuing with new things,
what about when there's
a hardware keyboard attached?
Well, new this year,
we have an adaptive
shortcuts bar
that is no longer
always full-width.
It changes width based
on what language you're using
and how many buttons
are in the bar.
Previously, it was always
the full width of the screen,
but now, if you're following
the undocked keyboard,
you can actually use
the real leading
and trailing edges of the bar.
So, what's the story
here with edges?
This is always near the bottom
and, in its normal position,
it's awayFrom
the other three edges.
But it's collapsable!
If you collapse it,
it can also be
near the leading
or trailing edge.
This is one of several reasons
why you might wanna be careful
about using the widthAnchor
of the keyboard, by the way.
It can be very small,
or it can be the full width
of the screen.
Now, let's get into the most
fun part of the tour:
what about if you're not
the only app onscreen,
and you're following
the undocked keyboard?
First, remember
that the keyboard
can leave your app space.
When that happens,
we're going to treat it
as though it's been dismissed.
Second, when your app is
at its narrowest,
the top and bottom edges
are in play,
but leading and trailing
will stay awayFrom,
whether the keyboard
is over your app or not.
Also, the guide is sized
for what part of the keyboard
is over your app's window,
if you're not
the only thing onscreen.
Let's take a look at some
visuals to show you what I mean.
All of this only applies
if you have
followsUndockedKeyboard
set to true.
If you haven't,
the guide is at the bottom
of the screen,
the full width of your window.
When you're full screen
and the keyboard is floating
and in the middle,
you're awayFrom everything.
All of your awayFrom constraints
have been activated,
and all of your near constraints
have been deactivated.
When another app is onscreen,
if you're the wider app,
you're still wide enough
for the keyboard
to be able to be
awayFrom everything.
But it needs to move less
to be near a horizontal edge.
This is similar to being
in portrait, too.
But, at half screen,
the keyboard in the same spot
is now near your leading edge,
and the guide
has gotten sized to match
only the part of the keyboard
that's over your app.
When you're the narrow app,
the guide is always considered
to be awayFrom
the horizontal edges,
the same as an iPhone
or a docked keyboard,
but you can still be
near the top edge.
And notice that, again,
the guide is sized
to account for the portion
over your app only.
And when you dock the keyboard
and it's full sized again,
it's also away from leading,
trailing, and top.
And notice, again,
that the layout guide
is once again sized
for what's over your app.
If you're a slide-over app, it
will resize for that, as well.
With the previous examples
and our demo code,
this should all be well-handled.
You just have to keep
in mind that you might be
to the next level
of keyboard integration.
So, use keyboard layout guide.
If your app can,
take advantage
of the advanced features
of UI tracking layout guide.
And, most importantly,
if you have been thinking
about keyboard layout
as fighting
or avoiding the keyboard,
start thinking about integrating
it into your layout instead.
And if you've already been
thinking about it that way,
now you have even more tools
to realize your full vision.
That brings us
to the end of our tour.
Please make sure you have
all your personal items
before exiting,
don't forget
to visit the gift shop,
and have a great WWDC.
[ethereal percussion music]