[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Marin Eubanks: Hi, everyone.
I’m Marin, an engineer
on the ClassKit team,
and I’m excited to show you
a new API
we’ve added to ClassKit
for file-based apps.
Today, I’ll go over Schoolwork
and how it’s used with ClassKit.
Then, I’ll do an in-depth review
of the new API
for file-based apps.
Next, I’ll walk you through
a sample implementation.
And finally, I’ll show you
how to test the new API
using ClassKit’s developer mode.
Let me start by giving you
a brief overview of Schoolwork.
Schoolwork is an educational app
that enables teachers
to share assignments
in which students use your apps
to learn.
When your app adopts
the ClassKit framework
and advertises assignable
content --
known as CLSContexts --
as well as starts reporting
progress data on activities,
teachers will be able to assign
that content
and view the progress data
reported by your app.
If your app is ClassKit-enabled,
teachers will be more likely
to use your app
in their curriculum.
And coming soon,
Schoolwork will be
even easier to use
and adds many new features
to streamline teacher workflows,
inform instruction,
and provide data from your apps
to teachers.
Now that we’re familiar
with Schoolwork,
let’s see how the data
from your app
flows into Schoolwork.
Your app submits data
to the ClassKit framework.
ClassKit surfaces that data
to the Schoolwork app.
The data is then presented
to the student and teacher.
Here is a view of Schoolwork
with a few assignments
of ClassKit-enabled apps.
If we tap on
one of the assignments,
we can see an example of an app
which has adopted ClassKit
and reported
student-progress data.
We will go through the details
of this use case a bit later.
Now that we have reviewed
Schoolwork,
let’s talk about our new
file-based progress API.
There are more than
190,000 education apps
in the App Store.
And while a lot of you
have adopted
ClassKit’s context-based APIs,
not all of you have.
We received feedback
specifically around apps
that interact with files
and how you wanted
to adopt ClassKit
but contexts didn’t quite fit
your use case.
Well, if you’ve been holding out
on ClassKit adoption
because your app is file-based,
we added a new API just for you.
This new API is for any app
that interacts with files.
If you have an app
that can edit files
or just open and view a file,
then you’ll love our new API
for file-based apps.
Adopting this new API enables
reporting student progress data
on the files used
within your app
when they are assigned
in Schoolwork.
When a teacher assigns content
from a ClassKit-enabled app,
they will be provided
additional insights,
which is a win for them
and a great new use case
for your app.
One important thing to note
is that your app must adopt
Open in Place.
When your app supports
Open in Place,
the exact file shared between
the student and teacher
will open in your app
and not a copy.
Here's the new API for adding
progress data to a file.
It’s called fetchActivity,
and it lives on CLSDataStore.
I have both the async
and async alternative versions
of this API shown here.
You’ll pass in the file URL
of your file to this API,
and it returns a CLSActivity.
Once you have the CLSActivity,
you can add progress data to it.
Now, let’s take a look
at the types of progress data
your app can submit.
If you’ve already adopted
ClassKit,
then this will be a review
of the current progress
data types we have available.
If you’re new to ClassKit,
these classes are currently
being used on CLSContexts,
but the same data types
can also be applied to files.
Here we have a CLSActivity.
This is a class
used to encapsulate
all of the progress data
associated
with a particular file.
We have a few types of data that
can be added to a CLSActivity.
First we have duration.
This is the amount of time
a student spent working
the assigned file.
Time should be reported
on all file types.
To use this API, you simply call
the start and stop methods
that live on CLSActivity.
Next we have progress.
This is some value
between zero and one.
Progress is typically used
when you can determine
a student's progression
through a file.
For example, let’s say you have
an audio or a video file,
and the student got 50 percent
of the way through.
You would report
the playback progress as .5.
To add progress,
you can either set
the progress property directly
or add a range
from some start to an end.
You can add overlapping ranges
or the same range
multiple times.
We’ll handle the logic
to make sure
the correct progress is reported
to students and teachers.
We also have
the primaryActivityItem
which is useful if you have
a file that can be edited.
Setting the primaryActivityItem
indicates that,
this piece of data,
you want to highlight
to students and teachers,
and it shows up in the main part
of the UI in the Schoolwork app.
There's also
an additionalActivityItems
property.
This is an array
of CLSActivityItems
which is useful for adding
additional metadata.
To add a primaryActivityItem,
set the primaryActivityItem
property on CLSActivity.
To add an
additionalActivityItem,
call the
addAdditionalActivityItem
function on CLSActivity
and pass in the activityItem
you want to add.
The primaryActivityItem
and additionalActivityItem
properties hold a reference
to one of our three subclasses
of CLSActivityItem.
You can add any
of the following subclasses:
First, we have CLSBinaryItem.
This is used to represent
any binary data type.
An example usage of this
might be a question on a quiz.
Let's say the student got it
correct or incorrect.
Or you can add CLSQuantityItem.
This is used for any
generic numerical value.
You could use this
for the number of pages,
number of slides,
or total word count
on a document.
And the last is CLSScoreItem.
This class is used for anything
that be represented
as a part out of a total.
For example,
a score on a quiz;
the user got eight out of ten.
You can add any combination
of these subclasses
to an activity, one of them,
or all of them.
Now that we know the types
of data that we can add,
let’s walk through a code sample
of adopting this API
into an app.
Here I have a sample app that
can open and edit a text file.
When the student
opens the text file,
I'll start the timer.
The student will go through,
edit the file.
When the student
is about to close the file,
I’ll record the total word count
and stop the timer.
Let’s navigate
to the part of my code
that gets called
when I open the file
and the student
starts interacting with it.
I have an openFile function.
This is where I will start
tracking time.
In your app, you’ll go
to the part of the code
that you already have
for opening a file,
and this is where you’ll add
a little bit of code
to start the timer.
First, I’ll fetch
the CLS activity
for my file URL.
Once I have the activity,
I will call start
to start tracking time
and then I will call save
on CLSDataStore
to commit the changes I’ve made.
Let’s go ahead and add
a breakpoint here
that we’ll come back to later
when testing our implementation.
Now, I also want
to stop the timer
when the student is done
and add a primaryActivityItem.
So let’s navigate to the part
of my code that gets called
when the student
is about to close the file.
Here I’ll call
CLSDataStore.shared.
fetchActivity,
grab the primaryActivityItem
to update it
if it already exists,
or create a new CLSQuantityItem
if there wasn’t already one.
Once I have the CLSQuantityItem,
I can update its value
and set it
as the primaryActivityItem
on my activity.
I can add
progress to my activity.
And last, call stop
to stop the timer.
Then, I make sure to call save.
If we don’t call save
on CLSDataStore,
then we will not persist
any of the changes we just made.
I’m going to add a breakpoint
here as well.
We’ll use this to help us
debug our submission
of student progress data.
Now that we’ve adopted the API
into our sample app,
let’s see how we can test
our implementation
using Schoolwork
and developer mode.
First, we need to set
the ClassKit
environment entitlement
to development.
This is inside of Xcode.
The default value is production.
We’ll change the value
of the entitlement
to development
so that we can test
using developer mode
and Schoolwork.
The next time we run our code,
it will run in developer mode.
It’s important to make sure
to set this back to production
after you're done testing.
Next, we need to turn
on developer mode on our iPad.
We'll open the Settings app,
navigate to Developer >
ClassKit API.
We’ll select Teacher
to change our role to a teacher
in Schoolwork.
Now, we will we open
the Schoolwork app.
When Schoolwork opens,
we are presented
with the teacher UI.
And if we tap on
the Create Assignment button
in the top right-hand corner,
we can create an assignment
adding a file our app supports
by tapping the Files button.
Then we will select the file
that we want to add,
enter the class and the title
of the assignment.
You can also optionally add
any instructional text
if you’d like.
And then tap the button
in the top right-hand corner
to publish this assignment
to the class.
Now that we've created
the assignment,
we can switch our role
to act as a student
and test our implementation
of submitting progress data.
So let's navigate back
to the Settings app.
In Settings, we’ll select
Developer > ClassKit API,
and tap on Student.
This has now changed my role
in Schoolwork
to act as a student.
We'll go back
to the Schoolwork app.
I can see I am now logged in
as a student
because I no longer have
the Create Assignment button
in the top right-hand corner
of my UI.
In the middle of the screen,
I see the assignment
we just created,
and if I tap on it, I am shown
the details of the assignment.
I can tap on the file icon,
and that will deep-link me
into my app
where I start reporting
progress data.
The file opens up in my app,
and my code gets called
to start the timer.
Here we can see
our breakpoint get hit
after calling save
to start the timer.
And if we hit Play
and then go back to our app,
I see the Student Progress
banner drop down from the top,
which is an indication
that the save was successful
and the timer was started.
Then I'll go through,
add a bunch of text
to complete the essay.
My sample app has a Done button
the student will tap
when they are done
editing the file.
So I’ll tap that Done button
in the top left-hand corner.
At this point, my closeFile
function will get called.
We can see our second breakpoint
was hit
for saving the wordCount
as the primaryActivityItem
and stopping the timer.
Then, we can hit Play
and go back to Schoolwork.
In Schoolwork,
I can see the progress data
submitted by my app.
First, I see the time
as 41 minutes.
This validates
that I'm calling start,
stop, and save correctly.
Next, I see the word count,
which I set
as the primaryActivityItem.
Any CLSActivityItem subclass
I set
as the primaryActivityItem
will show up here
in the main part of the UI.
The fact that I can see
my word count as 558 words
validates that my submission
of CLSQuantityItem
is working correctly.
Now, let’s switch our role back
to a teacher
and see how the data submitted
by my app appears to teachers.
In the center of the screen,
we see I have the average time
and average word count
for all students.
Below that is a row for
every student on the assignment.
In the Student cell,
I see the data
that one student submitted.
And if I tap
on the Student cell,
I can see the progress data
reported by my app.
We have the primaryActivityItem,
time,
and one additionalActivityItem
which is listed as
Readability Grade Level.
And that is how you use
developer mode
to test
your ClassKit integration.
Don’t forget to set the
entitlement back to production.
Well, great!
We covered a lot today,
from the new API
to testing it
with developer mode.
Even if you don’t consider
your app for education,
there’s a good chance
an educator does,
and having it ClassKit-enabled
means your app will be ready
for them to integrate
right into their curriculum.
So make sure to adopt our API.
And thank you.
Thank you
for the feedback reports,
and please submit any other
feedback that you may have.
We love hearing from you.
And if you are interested
in learning more
about our context-based APIs,
take a look
at our previous sessions
on "What’s new in ClassKit"
and our talk
"Introducing ClassKit"
from 2018.
Thanks, and have a great WWDC!
♪