[music]
[Jonathan]
Welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Jonathan Metzgar.
I'm a member
of the Metal Ecosystem team
at Apple.
We get to work with game
developers to help them
get the best graphics
performance on our Apple GPUs.
Dustin and I are going to
show you how
we optimize high-end
games for Apple GPUs.
In this video,
I'm going to cover
the process that we use
to optimize games.
Then, I'm going
to show you the kinds
of optimizations that are used
in the games Baldur's Gate
3 and Metro Exodus.
And lastly,
Dustin is going to do a tools
demonstration featuring the game
Divinity: Original Sin 2,
while he introduces the new
GPU Timeline in Xcode 13.
Let's dive in and talk
about optimization.
So, over the past year,
we collaborated
with Larian Studios and 4A Games
to find ways to tune
the graphics performance
in their games for Apple GPUs.
I am sure you'll be excited
to see the details,
and I want to take a moment
and thank both Larian Studios
and 4A Games for giving
us permission to show
development materials
in this presentation.
Looking back over the course
of the year,
we have analyzed many games and
identified some common scenarios
that affect
graphics performance.
You're probably interested
in finding opportunities
to optimize your own game,
so we have geared this session
to emphasize how our GPU
tools are especially helpful
in pinpointing
these problem areas
and to suggest ways
to solve them.
And, in particular, I'd like
to share some of the principles
our team uses to help developers
optimize their games.
When we optimize a graphics
application, it's important
to have a methodology,
a set of principles
that define how we solve
a particular problem.
So, let me show you
a four-step process.
First, you need to choose
what data to collect,
or measure,
so it will help you understand
what's happening with your game.
Soon after you begin
measuring data,
you will want to choose
some performance targets,
or where you want to be
when you finish.
You may decide
the in-game location
to take your GPU frame captures
and Metal system traces,
the scene complexity,
graphics settings,
and other metrics important
to you, like frame time.
Then, you analyze
the data to learn about
the behavior of your engine.
In-depth analysis
helps you find where
and why the bottlenecks
are occurring.
Once you know
what is causing a bottleneck,
then you can make improvements
to the game,
but normally you pick one or two
at a time,
so you can understand
the impact of each change.
Lastly, you verify
your improvements by comparing
some new measurements
with your original ones.
Since optimization is a process,
you will go back and repeat
until your performance
targets have been met.
For these games,
we use Xcode's Metal Debugger
to give us insights
about their performance
and how their frame
graphs are structured,
and we use Metal System Trace
in Instruments to learn
about a game's performance
over time.
It's a great idea
to save a GPU trace file
and an Instruments trace
file so you can have
your before and after data, both
before and after optimization.
So, I have a little list
of things you could consider,
or look for, in your game.
As I mentioned, Xcode
and Instruments are great tools
to help you understand
your Metal application.
Optimization is about getting
the best out of several areas,
ranging from shader performance
to memory bandwidth.
Another area is getting
good overlap across your vertex,
fragment, and compute workloads.
And while rendering
several frames in flight,
some Apple GPUs can overlap
workloads between them.
I'll show you some pointers
to help you with resource
dependencies, which
might prevent that overlap.
And since some developers
use a custom workflow
for their shaders,
I'll show you how
compiler settings can
affect performance.
Lastly, I'll talk about how
to reduce the impact
of redundant bindings.
Let's start with Baldur's Gate 3
from Larian Studios.
Baldur's Gate 3 is
an RPG building
on a 20-year gaming
legacy and stands out
with its cinematic visual
effects.
Our engagement
with Larian Studios
helped us identify how
they could optimize
their amazing rendering
engine for Apple GPUs.
First, we started
with a GPU frame capture,
like the Ravaged Beach scene
we see here.
Then, we break down the scene
into a frame graph.
The frame graph is a breakdown
of the order and purpose
of each rendering pass.
High-end games have many render
passes specializing in achieving
a certain visual effect,
such as ambient occlusion,
shadow mapping, post processing,
and so on.
Baldur's Gate 3 has
a complex frame graph,
so this is a simplified version.
By using Xcode's Metal Debugger,
we capture a GPU trace
and use it to see all
the render passes in the game.
Clicking
on Show Dependencies brings
up a visualization
that you can pan and zoom.
It shows how your render
passes depend on the results
of previous ones to help
you understand what's going on.
For example,
I am zooming into this deferred
decal render stage
to get more details.
Next, I will show
you the Instruments tools.
We spend time analyzing games
using the Instruments trace,
using the Metal System Trace,
or Game performance templates.
Metal System Trace is ideal if
you wanna focus on GPU execution
and scheduling analysis,
and Game Performance
expands on that to help
you with other issues,
like thread stalls
or thermal notifications.
Let's choose
Metal System Trace to see
the behavior of our engine
from frame to frame.
Instruments allows
you to view several channels
of data along a timeline.
Here, we find our first problem:
An expensive workload
in our render passes.
might mean that we need
to optimize a shader.
For instance,
we see a long compute shader
holding up
the rest of our frame.
We call these gaps "bubbles."
Let's switch back
over to the GPU trace
and investigate this further.
This is the "before" GPU trace.
Let's change the grouping
from API CALL to PIPELINE STATE.
You may
notice the pipeline states
are sorted by execution time.
Let's check the first
compute pipeline.
We can expand
the compute function details
to take a closer look
at its statistics.
Notice here that there are
over four-and-a-half-thousand
instructions.
That's quite a lot.
So, what else?
Let's see what resources
are being used
by this compute function.
Depending on the input data,
this function uses up
to 120 textures to produce
the output.
However,
we discovered that only six
to 12 are actually
used 90% of the time.
So, let's talk about how
this shader could be improved.
Shaders that need to handle many
different conditions can reserve
more registers than necessary,
and this can reduce
the number of threads
that run in parallel.
Splitting your workload
into smaller,
more focused shaders,
which need fewer registers,
can improve the utilization
of the shader cores.
So, instead of selecting
the appropriate algorithm
in the shader, you would
choose the appropriate shader
permutation when you issue
your GPU workload.
Additionally, a shader function
which uses too many registers
can result in register pressure,
when an execution unit runs out
of fast register memory and has
to use device memory instead.
That's one reason to use
16-bit types, like half,
when appropriate,
since they use half the register
space than 32-bit types,
like floats.
In this case, Larian Studios
already optimized their shader
to use half-precision floating
point and decided to create
dedicated shader variants,
instead.
So, let's see what happened.
When comparing the numbers
before, in the box on the left,
with the numbers in the box
on the right, the number
of instructions reduced by 84%,
branches reduced 90%,
registers reduced 25%,
and texture reads reduced 92%.
This shader variant is
used 90% of the time.
We can also see
this in the Metal System Trace.
Notice here,
in the before trace,
the bubbles we saw earlier.
And here, in the after trace,
they have been minimized.
Larian Studios was able
to reduce this shader
by eight milliseconds,
on average.
That is a huge win!
If you look at your most
expensive pipeline state objects
and shaders, you may
find a complicated shader
that could be simplified.
This is especially true
if the results
of that shader
are used by a later pass.
This was a huge improvement
for the game,
but short of the developer's
performance target.
We just mentioned memory
as an issue, and one
of the features of our GPUs
is lossless compression,
which is enabled
in certain conditions.
So, maybe there was a flag
we either accidentally set
or forgot to set.
Lossless compression helps
reduce bandwidth by compressing
textures when they are stored
from tile to device memory.
If you look
at the Bandwidth Insights
on the Summary page,
you may notice
Lossless Compression
warnings for some textures.
They tell you
that these textures
can't be lossless compressed,
and you may pay
a bandwidth penalty.
Metal Debugger will also let you
know why these textures
can't be lossless compressed.
Here we see it's because
of the ShaderWrite usage flag.
We can see all the usage flags
by going to the memory section.
Once in the memory section,
we can filter by render targets.
Then, right click
on the table header,
choose texture, and then usage.
Now, we can sort by usage
and find the textures
using ShaderWrite.
If you set the ShaderWrite
or PixelFormatView flag
when you create your textures,
you will disable
lossless compression.
Let's take a look
at these flags in more detail.
The Unknown, ShaderWrite,
and PixelFormatView flags
prevent your textures
from being lossless compressed.
The general rule of thumb
is to use these flags
only when required.
For example, you would use
the ShaderWrite flag
if you use the write()
method to store values
in a texture from a fragment
or compute function.
Rendering to a texture
bound as a color attachment
doesn't require
the ShaderWrite flag.
And don't
set the PixelFormatView option
if you only need
to read the component values
in a different order.
Instead,
create a texture view using
a swizzle pattern
to specify the new order.
Similarly, don't set
the PixelFormatView option if
your texture view only converts
between linear space and sRGB.
Check the documentation
for more information.
Shader optimization
and lossless compression
are two techniques
that have helped us out,
but another problem area is
getting good overlap
across the vertex, fragment,
and compute channels.
Let's take a look at two ways
to optimize workloads
across channels.
First, we'll start by looking
at our Metal System Trace again.
Here, we can see
that we have low overlap
on our vertex, fragment,
and compute channels.
It would be nice to improve this
to keep the GPU busy.
One way to solve this problem
is to see if we can
restructure the encoding
order in our frame graph.
In other words,
we want to move this work
over to where the vertex
stage has very low occupancy.
We would like to process
those vertices earlier,
along with the fragment
stage of an earlier render pass.
We can think of our frame graph
as a list
of rendering tasks,
like this pseudocode example.
Getting good overlap can
be as simple as changing
the order of your render tasks
in your frame graph.
Some tasks may rely
on results from earlier ones,
but not always.
It turns out that
the CascadedShadowBuffer stage,
which is vertex-shader heavy,
could be moved
a few tasks earlier,
since it has few dependencies.
And now, we see that our region
with low overlap has better
utilization of the vertex
and fragment channels,
giving us another 1 ms win.
But there is
another optimization
that we can try out.
Games often have two
to three frames in flight.
So, a cool feature
in our tile-based
deferred rendering,
or TBDR architecture GPUs,
is to overlap workloads
from two frames
when there are no resource
dependencies between them.
So, I'm going to show you
how to optimize
for this possibility.
Let's have a look at the GPU
track in Instruments once again.
Here, you can see
that these frames
are processed, almost serially.
This is caused by using
a blit encoder to update
constant buffers, like per-frame
animation data, and so on.
To efficiently update constant
buffer data with a discrete GPU,
we blit from shared buffers
on the CPU to a private buffer
on the GPU, which will be
used for rendering the frame.
This strategy is efficient
for GPUs with discrete memory,
so you want to keep this behavior
for that purpose.
If your device has a unified
memory architecture,
then there is no need
to use a blit encoder
to copy your data
to a private buffer.
However, when you use a shared
buffer in a ring-buffer pattern,
you need to watch out
for synchronization issues
because visual corruption
can happen if your CPU
writes to data currently
being read by the GPU.
Let's see this in action.
Here, you can
see in this diagram
the encoding
and rendering of our frames.
We are using colors to represent
the shared buffers,
which are updated
at the beginning of the frame:
blue for buffer one,
green for buffer two,
and yellow for buffer three.
Ring buffers are typically
used to implement queues,
which need to use a compact
amount of memory.
Here, there is no concern
of a data race condition
with this arrangement,
as our writing and reading
of our shared buffers
is mutually exclusive.
It's very common to have
latency between encoding
the frame
and the rendering of a frame.
This causes a shift
of when the rendering
actually begins.
As long as the latency isn't
too long,
you will not have
a data race condition.
However, what happens if latency
continues to increase?
Well, this introduces
a data race condition,
where the main thread is
updating its shared buffers
during the time the GPU is
rendering the frame.
And if that happens,
you could get visual corruption
if elements of your frame
are dependent on this data.
In the case of Baldur's Gate 3,
removing the private buffer
and blit encoder eliminated
the synchronization point,
but introduced a race condition,
which affected their temporal
anti-aliasing render pass.
So, let's see how
to avoid this situation.
To avoid this race condition,
you need to make sure
you are not writing
into the same resource
the GPU is reading from.
For example, you could utilize
a completion handler,
and then wait until it is safe
to update the shared buffer
in your encoding thread.
But let me show you how
we avoided a wait time.
We maintained our completion
handler, but added an extra
buffer to our ring buffer
to avoid the wait.
The extra buffer is colored
purple on the bottom diagram.
The memory consumption remains
the same as with a discrete GPU.
But if you need to save
on memory,
and the CPU wait time doesn't
affect frame rate of your game,
then you can just use
three buffers.
So, let's look at an easy way
to decide how many shared
and private buffers to create
with a pseudocode example.
In this code snippet,
you can see how to choose
the number of shared and private
buffers at initialization time.
Once we have created our device,
we can check
to see if the device has
unified memory or not,
and then ensure that we create
an extra shared buffer,
or to use a private buffer.
This extra
buffer will help reduce
the impact of waiting
for a completion handler,
which we are using to avoid
a data race condition.
And now, we can see how Fragment
workloads from the previous
frame overlaps with Vertex
workloads from the next frame.
Overall, this can give us one
to two milliseconds,
depending on the scene.
And, of course,
this approach can be applied not
only for the constant
buffer data we've
shown in this example,
but for all of the buffer data
you transfer
from the CPU to the GPU.
So, let's review.
Larian Studios was able
to achieve their performance
targets by applying
the following optimizations:
Optimizing their most expensive
shaders to reduce bubbles,
opting in to lossless
compression to improve
bandwidth, overlapping vertex
and fragment workloads
to get better GPU utilization,
and checking
for resource dependencies
that prevent frame overlap.
When they were finished,
Larian Studios not only met
their performance targets,
but got a 33% improvement
in frame time for their game.
And now,
we will look at a different set
of optimizations
with the game Metro Exodus.
Metro Exodus is known
for its epic storyline
and demanding visual effects,
as you can see
in this series
of game-play clips.
After the integration
of our suggested optimizations,
4A Games was able to meet
their performance targets.
So now, let's have a look
at an in-game scene
from Metro Exodus.
Metro Exodus uses
a custom workflow to translate
render commands
into Metal API commands,
which is quite common
for cross-platform games.
The translation layer
they are using is optimized
for Metal,
but some issues can arise
when two complex systems
come together in practice.
So, additional
performance tuning
was required
to meet their project goals.
As in the previous game,
we start
by investigating how
a frame is being rendered.
Modern renderers have a lot
of different techniques involved
so first we try to understand
the high-level frame graph.
Again, we start analysis
by looking at the GPU trace.
It always gives us useful
insights about game performance.
So first,
let's start with the GPU time,
which doesn't meet the developer
performance targets.
So, let's find the shader
or pipeline
which is
the most time-consuming.
To do this, we are going
to group by pipeline state
once again and look
at the most expensive one.
Let's quickly look
at its statistics.
You can see that there is a high
number of ALU instructions
compared to the total, meaning
this is a math-heavy shader.
We also see that the number
of registers being used
by the shader is quite high.
The number of registers used
by a particular shader directly
affects how its workload
will scale during execution.
The higher this number is,
the less work can be done
in parallel by the GPU.
Sometimes it's just a complex
shader, such as SSAO
in this example,
that requires lots
of computations and registers,
but sometimes
the compiler settings can affect
the generated instructions
and register allocation,
as well.
Let's also take a look
at the shader compiler options.
And it turns out,
this shader was compiled
with the fast math flag
disabled.
Fast math allows the shader
compiler to optimize
various instructions,
and it is enabled
for the Metal shader compiler,
by default.
However, there might be
some cases,
for example,
using custom shader workflows,
that can
disable this compilation flag.
In this case, we discovered
that the translation layer,
which 4A Games was using
to invoke the compiler,
had its default behavior
set to not use fast math.
So, what is fast math?
Fast math is
a set of optimizations
for floating-point arithmetic,
that trades
between speed and correctness.
For example, assumptions can be
made that there will be no NANs,
infinity, or signed zeros
as either a result or argument.
Fast math optimizations
can also apply
algebraically-equivalent
transformations,
which may affect the precision
in floating-point results.
However in most scenarios,
fast math is a great choice
for games.
This can significantly
improve performance,
especially in ALU-bound cases.
Our recommendation to you is
to check your compiler options
to verify that you have enabled
fast math, if your shaders do
not depend on the things
that we just mentioned.
The fast math flag
works at the front-
and back-end compiler levels.
When you are building
your shader source,
the front-end shader compiler
will select fast math functions,
which will be used
in intermediate code.
This will hint to the back-end
shader compiler that it can
generate more optimal
GPU machine code.
Here, you can see
how the Instructions
and Register counters
on the left have been improved
in the box on the right
after we recompiled this shader.
So, after changing the behavior
of the translation layer
to enable fast math
for all the shaders,
we got a 21% frame time decrease
in our test workload
using the built-in game
benchmark.
So, the next area I wanna talk
about is redundant bindings.
If we go
back to the summary page,
and look at the API insights,
we can see there are
many redundant bindings
when rendering the frame.
Redundant bindings can be either
resources like textures,
buffers, and samplers;
or render states
like depth stencil state,
viewport configuration, etc.
Repeatedly binding resources
might negatively affect
your encoding time,
but redundant render
state changes may also
affect the GPU time.
Let's have a look
at the encoding
and GPU times
in the Metal System Trace.
For a given frame, it takes
eight-and-a-half milliseconds
for all the commands
to be encoded
and around 22 milliseconds
for the GPU
to render this frame.
When we investigated the cause
of the redundant bindings,
we found
that the translation layer
could be
modified to reduce them.
So, let me show you a pseudocode
example which shows how
to check for and reduce
redundant bindings.
Instead of binding textures
directly to the encoder,
you can pre-cache them and only
bind them if they change.
And to minimize interactions
with the API, you can set all
the textures with one call to
the setFragmentTextures method
instead of setting them
in a loop, one by one.
Additionally,
you can apply a similar approach
to other shader stages
and other binding types,
like buffers and samplers,
as well as render states.
So, let's see what happened
in the Metal System Trace.
4A Games was able
to reduce encoding time
between 30% and 50%,
depending on the scene,
because the translation
layer wasn't repeatedly
binding the same resources
and render states.
However,
GPU time also decreased by up
to three milliseconds and,
overall,
resulted in a 15% speedup
in their in-game benchmark.
If you have a few redundant
binding warnings,
it's not an issue,
but we definitely see an impact
with hundreds or thousands
of redundant bindings.
So, avoiding redundant bindings
gave us a further 15% reduction
in average frame time.
After these two improvements,
4A Games was able to meet
their performance targets.
So now, let's summarize
what we learned
from optimizing Metro Exodus
for Apple GPUs.
First, if you're using
a custom workflow for shaders,
you should check
your compiler settings to ensure
you are using the best options
for your Metal applications.
And if you see a lot
of redundant binding warnings
in the Metal Debugger,
I showed you a technique
to reduce encoding
and GPU time overhead,
which you can apply
either to your engine
or the translation layer
that you are using.
And now, I'd like to hand it
over to Dustin,
who's going to talk to you
about Divinity: Original Sin 2
and demo the new
Xcode GPU timeline features.
[Dustin]
Thanks, Jonathan.
Hi, my name is Dustin,
and I work
on the GPU Software team
here at Apple.
And today, I'm excited
to show you a hands-on demo
optimizing an early build
of Larian Studios hit title,
Divinity: Original Sin 2.
Last year,
Larian announced they were
bringing
their critically-acclaimed
role-playing game Divinity:
Original Sin 2 to the iPad.
And over the last year,
Larian has worked hard
optimizing their game
to run great on Apple GPU's,
and the game is a lot of fun
to play.
Larian was able to achieve these
results with the help of a great
set of tools in Metal Debugger
and Metal System Trace
that are getting even
better this year in Xcode 13
with the addition
of the new GPU Timeline.
Let's get started by taking
a look at a frame
of Divinity: Original Sin 2
I captured earlier.
We are here on the Summary Page,
which contains an overview
of your frame that helps
to guide you along the way
as you debug
and optimize your game.
From the Summary Page,
we can quickly navigate
to all the great tools offered
by the Metal Debugger,
including the new GPU Timeline.
And accessing it is
as easy as clicking
on the new Performance page
here.
So, let me go ahead and do that.
Introducing
the new GPU Timeline.
The Timeline has been designed
around Apple GPU's
unique architecture
that allows each GPU pipeline
stage to run in parallel.
In order to maximize
performance, we need to keep
all pipeline stages as busy as
possible by maximizing overlap,
which the Timeline allows you
to easily see.
The Timeline is composed
of two sections.
On the top,
we have the GPU section,
which is composed
of separate tracks
for each pipeline stage,
making it really easy to see
which stages are active
and running in parallel.
Underneath,
we have the Counters section,
which contains a curated set
of important counters,
such as shader occupancy,
bandwidth,
and performance limiters
that provides us
with deeper insight into how
the GPU's system performance
changes over the course
of your workload.
The encoders in the GPU tracks
provide us with a lot
of useful information, with even
more just a click away.
Selecting a Render Encoder
brings up
the Timeline's sidebar,
which contains
additional information
for the currently-selected item.
In this case,
the sidebar contains
render pass information,
such as texture details,
load/store actions,
and the number of draw calls.
Notice that since
Render Encoders are composed
of two shader stages,
both the vertex
and fragment stages are
highlighted, as well.
If we select the Fragment track
instead,
the sidebar contains all
of the encoders in the Timeline,
which can then be
sorted based on time.
But that's not all because
we can expand the Fragment track
to reveal the Shader Timeline,
which shows all of the shaders
used by the encoders
during their execution.
We can easily identify
long-running shaders, as well
as which shaders are running
in parallel with others.
For the Fragment track,
we also have
two additional tracks
for load/store actions.
This is useful to be able
to see when the GPU
is loading and storing
attachment textures between
local and main memory,
and is an important
consideration in order
to reduce bandwidth usage.
Selecting a shader
will highlight all the regions
on the timeline
where it is active,
and we can learn more about
it from its compiler statistics
and runtime performance metrics
presented in the sidebar.
Expanding the shader timeline
shows each shader
in its own track,
which is useful
for understanding the flow
of your GPU workload
and the order
of shader execution.
Now that you're
a bit more familiar
with the new GPU Timeline
and thinking
of all the ways that you will
be able to use it yourself,
let me show you
just how how easy it is
to find performance bottlenecks
using the GPU Timeline.
Shader performance can suffer
as a result of many factors,
one of which is
register pressure,
and when this happens,
the GPU runs out
of fast register memory and has
to use main memory instead.
A high ALU limiter
alone does not indicate
a performance bottleneck.
It may just be
that your shader is math heavy.
However, when combined with low
shader occupancy, this may be
an indicator of a shader
experiencing register pressure,
which will cause
your shader to run slower.
In order to highlight
this better for today's demo,
let me pin both the ALU track
and the shader occupancy track
to the top of the Timeline
by clicking the "Plus"
button here on the left.
As I scan over these two tracks,
the first thing I notice
is this region here,
where the ALU spikes and,
at the same time,
shader occupancy drops.
I can highlight a region
on the Timeline to see
how long it takes to execute.
Notice as I do this,
the counters in the sidebar
update dynamically based
on the selected region.
This region here is taking about
3.7 milliseconds to execute.
Let's zoom in
and take a closer look.
It looks like our issue
is related
to these first four encoders
of the Ambient Occlusion pass.
Let's see
what shaders are being used
by taking a look
at the shader timeline.
Looks like our issue
is related to this shader here,
as it's the only one being used.
From the sidebar's runtime
performance metrics, not only is
this shader ALU intensive,
it is float heavy, as well,
so let's take a look
at the Floating
Point Utilization track.
Notice as I hover
over this track,
this shader is only using F32.
F16 is at 0%.
From the Timeline,
we can navigate directly
to shader source by right
clicking and opening the shader.
Here in the source editor,
we can see a simplified version
of the shader source
for demo purposes.
Along with source, we can also
see per-line cost information
with the help
of the shader profiler.
Hovering over the shader
profiler pie chart provides us
with confirmation
that this function is
likely causing
register pressure,
as it is both ALU
and float heavy.
Situations like this are
candidates for using F16,
which gives us double the amount
of registers in places
where the full precision
of F32 is not required,
which will help
to reduce register pressure.
Metal Debugger makes it
really convenient
to update source code directly
inside the source editor.
Let me make this change here
that uses an updated version
of the shader that uses
a mixture of F32 and F16.
After making this change,
I can click the "Reload Shaders"
button down here at the bottom,
which will trigger
a shader update that both
recompiles and reprofiles
our shader, as well as updating
the per-line shader costs.
Let's see what effect
this change has made
by going back to the Timeline.
The first thing I'd like
to do is see
how long
those first four encoders
of the Ambient Occlusion pass
are taking.
Looks like this region here
is taking about 2.6 milliseconds
to execute.
The change we just made
has improved
our shader execution time
by over one millisecond, or 30%,
which is a huge improvement.
Taking a look at some
of the counters from earlier,
while ALU is still high,
that is to be expected
for a math-heavy shader.
But notice now,
our shader is experiencing
less register pressure,
as our shader occupancy
has improved by almost double.
This was accomplished by using
a mixture of F32 and F16,
which we can see using
the Floating Point Utilization
track.
The GPU Timeline made
it really easy for me
to identify the issue,
navigate to where
the problem existed,
and get it fixed.
The GPU Timeline is a great tool
for identifying not only
shader performance issues,
but also memory bandwidth
and many other kinds of issues.
I hope you enjoyed this demo
of the brand-new GPU Timeline
and are already thinking
of all the ways
that you're going to use it
to optimize your games
to run even better
on Apple GPUs.
Thank you,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
Back to Jonathan.
[Jonathan] Thank you, Dustin,
for that amazing demo.
And thank you for watching.
It was great to share
with you how we worked
with Larian Studios and 4A Games
to take advantage
of the features
on our Apple GPUs.
They provide many ways
to improve performance, ranging
from lossless compression
to overlapping shader workloads.
And our tools,
like Metal System Trace
and the new GPU timeline
in Xcode,
will really be helpful to you
as you improve your games.
If there's one thing I can leave
you with, a thorough examination
of your rendering is essential
to delivering a highly-optimized
game, and our tools are there
to help you with this.
If you'd like to learn more,
please refer
to the related sessions,
"Discover Metal debugging,
profiling,
and asset creation tools"
in this year's WWDC,
or "Optimize Metal apps
and games with GPU counters"
from WWDC20.
Thank you, and farewell!
[music]