[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Beatriz Magalhães:
Hi, my name is Bea,
and I'm a human
interface designer
on the Documentation team.
My colleague Jack and I
are going to talk about
how to elevate your
DocC documentation in Xcode.
It’s now easier than ever
to write and share
great documentation.
This year, we’ve integrated
documentation
for your Swift frameworks
right into Xcode 13.
of a framework we created:
SlothCreator.
You can use SlothCreator
to catalog sloths
you find in nature
and to create new
adorable virtual sloths.
To make our existing
documentation
for this framework better,
we'll go over what documentation
page types are available
in Xcode 13
and how to choose
what's best for your content,
how to organize
the order of your APIs
to tell a story
about your framework,
and how extensions
can give you flexibility
in how you write
your documentation.
I’ll start with
a new Xcode feature:
documentation page types.
Xcode 13 has a brand-new feature
called "Documentation Catalog,"
which enables you to create
three page types you can view
on the documentation window
or on the web:
reference, articles,
and tutorials.
Each project is unique
and has different needs,
but it’s usually good to have
a diverse set of documentation.
Reference provides concise,
in-depth information
about individual APIs
in your library.
This allows you to add
text descriptions,
code snippets, and relationships
between different symbols.
This is the backbone
of your documentation.
Articles are pages
with free-form content.
They’re great at giving the big
picture of how a framework works
and explaining how to complete
a specific task.
They often connect the dots
between different symbols.
Tutorials are a step-by-step
walk-through of a project
that uses your framework.
It's great to understand
how a combination
of symbols work together
by implementing it in practice.
Framework adopters
of all proficiency levels
can benefit from tutorials,
but it’s worth noting
this is also a very
beginner-friendly format.
In this session,
we’ll focus on articles.
To see information
on reference and tutorials,
check out these other
WWDC sessions.
Before I start enhancing
my SlothCreator documentation,
I’ll check out what’s new
in the documentation window.
Now, you can see
all of the Apple technologies
as well as your own
documentation
right there in the navigator.
Now, I’ll check out
the current state
of my SlothCreator
documentation.
I have my SlothCreator
Swift package open in Xcode.
I'm going to click on Product
and then Build Documentation
to bring up
my documentation window.
Scrolling through
my SlothCreator
framework documentation,
I see that all my symbols
are already covered
by reference here,
which is great.
However, if I approach this page
from the perspective of someone
who's never used
this framework before,
it's not clear at a glance
what it does.
I can use a top-level article
to paint the big picture.
Top-level articles have
a concise summary sentence,
an overview with content
like images and code snippets,
and on the bottom,
a topics section with a few
symbols you want to highlight.
To add an article,
I need to set up my project
with a documentation catalog.
The documentation catalog
is a file in the Xcode navigator
that contains
all my documentation files.
Moreover, it lets me write
new page types.
This makes documentation
quick to access at a glance
and makes it easier for me
to prioritize documentation
in my day-to-day workflow.
To do this,
I can right-click
on the SlothCreator
Sources directory,
which contains the sources
for our SlothCreator target,
and select New File.
Then, I’ll scroll
through the list
until I find
Documentation Catalog.
I’ll name it to match
my framework target:
SlothCreator.
Xcode gives me
a top-level article
when I create
a documentation catalog.
I’ll rename it
to "SlothCreator"
both in the project navigator
and in the markdown.
Now, let’s get started
on our article.
You write articles
using Markdown.
First, I’m going
to add a summary
that describes what my framework
does in one sentence.
Next, I'll add more
in-depth information
under the Overview title
about the main functionalities
of SlothCreator: research,
care, and visualization.
Lastly, I’m going
to add an image
so developers know at a glance
what they’re looking at.
I’d recommend adding images
that are 2x in resolution
and either Dark Mode-compatible
or have a Dark Mode alternative.
Don’t forget to include
the proper naming conventions
for your files.
First, the name of your file:
"sloth."
Then, if your image
is in Dark Mode,
a tilde and the word "dark."
Then, @2x to describe
the scale factor.
And lastly,
your image file format,
which in this case
is .png.
Now that I made sure
my images are the right size
and are named correctly,
I’m going to open Finder
and drag my assets
into the Resources folder
of my documentation catalog.
Next, I’ll add my image
to the article Markdown.
First, I added
an exclamation point,
then a description
between brackets
to make my image accessible,
and lastly, the file name
between parentheses.
You might have noticed
I didn’t type in "@2x"
or "~dark."
That’s because Xcode
automatically selects the image,
so all I have to type in
is the image name itself.
All right, I finished
my top-level article.
Let’s see what it looks like
by building my documentation.
I’ll click on Product and select
Build Documentation again
to bring up
my documentation window.
Awesome, SlothCreator has
a clear high-level summary,
an overview
that gives more context
on what this framework is for,
and an image that illustrates
the core concept
of the framework at a glance.
Now, someone that’s never used
SlothCreator before
can quickly understand
the big picture
of what the framework does.
I can make this documentation
even better
by providing actionable
first steps
on how to get started
with SlothCreator.
A task article
could help with that.
I’ve prepared a task article
ahead of time,
and I’m going to open Finder
and drag it into my SlothCreator
documentation catalog.
This article has the goal
of teaching folks
how to create and care
for a sloth,
the core element
of this framework.
In terms of structure,
it’s very similar
to the top-level article.
Both types can include text,
images, and code snippets.
The biggest difference here
is in the content.
To see those differences, I’ll
build my documentation again
by selecting Product
and Build Documentation.
Then, in my documentation
window navigator,
I’m going to select
Getting Started with Sloths.
Great, this article
provides more context
around how to create a sloth,
by describing its properties
and traits.
It also gives actionable steps
on how to care for the sloth
and form a suitable habitat.
This will help people to adopt
SlothCreator much faster.
To recap,
so far, I talked about all the
different types of documentation
you can author and what you can
use each one for.
I introduced
a new Xcode 13 feature
called "Documentation Catalog,"
which allows you to put all
your documentation files
in the same place
as well as author new types
of documentation.
And I used it
to create two articles
that enhance my documentation
by giving it more context
and diving in a specific task.
To author those articles,
I used Markdown
and the new files that we’re now
supporting for documentation.
Now, I'm going to hand it over
to Jack,
so he can talk about how you can
make your docs even better
by organizing your symbols
and creating documentation
extensions.
Jack Lawrence: Thanks, Bea,
those articles look great.
Now that we’ve added
some new pages,
there’s another way
I can help guide everyone
through the framework.
Earlier, Bea created
a framework page
with an overview
for SlothCreator.
At the bottom of the page,
the DocC compiler automatically
created a topics section
with all of the Sloth
framework’s documentation.
This is a great start,
but I think we can improve it.
So let’s take a step back
and think about the story
we want to tell.
SlothCreator APIs fall
into three main categories:
researching and creating sloths,
caring for the health
and happiness of your sloth,
and viewing your sloth
in its habitat.
I can use these categories
to organize the documentation
pages in SlothCreator.
Here are the top-level pages
for the framework.
First, I’ll put aside all
but the most important pages.
I can organize
supporting types --
like speed and color --
under another page later.
Next, I’ll organize
the remaining pages
into groupings centered around
the features of SlothCreator.
And finally, I’ll sort
the groups and pages
from least to most advanced.
This new organization looks
a lot more approachable,
and framework adopters
interested in specific features
will know right where to look.
Now we’ll update
the documentation
for the framework
to use these themes.
I have the SlothCreator
project open
and the built documentation.
The compiler automatically adds
a topics section to each page
with default groups.
But I can customize it
with some extra Markdown.
Earlier, Bea created
a documentation catalog
with a framework article.
In the project navigator,
I’ll select the SlothCreator
Markdown file
inside
the documentation catalog.
The template already includes
a topics section
for me to fill out.
Starting with "Essentials,"
I’ll update the group title
in the third-level heading.
Then I’ll add a list of links
to include in the group.
I’ll begin with
the "Getting Started" article,
and the sloth type.
To link to an article,
I use the name of the file
without the extension,
using the doc URL scheme.
To link to a symbol,
I surround the name of the
symbol in double back ticks.
Using the categories
I created earlier,
I’ll organize all of the other
documentation pages into groups,
as well.
Now I’ll rebuild and take a look
at the changes.
In the Product menu,
I’ll select Build Documentation
to rebuild.
The documentation built,
but I see a diagnostic
generated by DocC,
And it looks like I mistyped
a link here.
Let’s let autocomplete
take care of it,
so I’m certain it’s correct.
Now I’m going to rebuild
the documentation again
using the Product menu to see
if I resolved all of the issues.
Awesome, no more warnings.
On the framework page
in the documentation window,
our new "Getting Started"
article is the first topic
everyone will see,
followed by the main themes
for SlothCreator
in order of complexity.
The documentation navigator
on the left also updates
to match each page’s
topics section,
so I can quickly find the page
I’m looking for.
Now let’s review how to organize
your documentation.
All of your pages
are organized automatically,
and you can customize
with a topics section.
To create a topics section,
add a second-level
topics heading.
Then, add a group
with a third-level heading,
followed by a list of links
to any other pages
that you want to organize
under the current page.
You can add a topics section
to any article,
along with any container symbol
like a class, structure,
enumeration, or protocol.
When you’re organizing
documentation
for your framework,
consider the most important
features and themes,
and which APIs developers might
use together to create an app.
Move supporting pages under
your primary documentation
to add focus and clarity.
And start with the basics
and then introduce complexity
progressively.
Now that I’ve customized the
groups on the framework page,
I want to organize all of the
documentation in SlothCreator,
including types
and their members.
Documentation extensions
give me the flexibility
to choose how I write
documentation for my APIs.
I could add a custom topics
section right in my source code,
but I think it would be easier
to review and maintain over time
if this additional documentation
was in a separate file.
And I can use a documentation
extension to do just that.
First, I create
a new Markdown file.
I associate it with an API
using link syntax in the title.
Next, to improve the focus
and clarity in my source code,
I’ll leave
the primary content --
like the summary
and discussion --
in the code and extract
the topics section.
When DocC builds, it merges
each source comment
and corresponding
documentation extension
into a single
documentation page.
With extensions,
it’s simple to write
and review the documentation,
improve the framework’s
generated interface,
and provide a better
documentation
reading experience.
Now, I’ll add
a documentation extension
to enhance the documentation
for SlothCreator.
First, I’ll take a look
at the Sloth page
before I make any changes.
I have the documentation
comment for the Sloth type,
and I also have
the built documentation.
The documentation I wrote
in the source code looks great,
but the Topics section
could be improved,
and I can do that in
a documentation extension.
In the project navigator,
I’ll right-click
on the documentation catalog
to add a new file.
In the template chooser,
I’ll select the Extension File
template and name it "Sloth."
Next, I’ll connect the extension
file to the sloth type
using a link in the title.
I need to include the name
of the module in the URL.
This might look familiar,
because earlier my colleague Bea
used this syntax
to create the top-level
framework article.
Then I’ll add some customized
groups in a topics section.
Finally, I’ll rebuild using
Product > Build Documentation
to check out the result.
The content I wrote
in the source code
is still at the top,
and the topics section I created
in the documentation file
is added after it.
When I expand the page
in the navigator,
the navigator's updated as well.
The changes that Bea
and I made are done,
and we’re ready to share them
with the world.
The documentation
looks great in Xcode,
and anyone can build it after
they download the Swift package.
I can also use the Export button
in the navigator
to export an archive
that you can use
to browse the documentation
in Xcode
without downloading or building
the Swift package.
And if I want to make it
accessible to everyone,
I can even publish the
documentation on the web.
And you can check out this
related session to learn more.
Now, let’s review how you can
elevate the documentation
for your Swift framework.
First, create articles
to introduce your framework
and explain how your APIs
work together.
Next,
organize your documentation into
groups to improve navigation.
Finally, add depth and detail
to your API reference
in documentation
extension files.
If you want to go even further,
you can learn
how to publish to the web
and guide readers
step-by-step with tutorials
in these two related sessions.
Xcode 13 is a huge update
for documentation,
and we’re so excited
to see what you publish.
Thanks for watching!
♪