[music]
[David]
Hello.
I’m David,
an engineer from the ARKit team.
Today Christopher and I will be
sharing a broad range
of improvements to ARKit 5.
We’re excited to discuss
the changes coming to iOS 15.
This year, we’ve made many
upgrades across the board,
and we’ll be discussing
multiple features.
Before we do that,
we want to showcase
the experiences you all have
been building with LiDAR.
We’ve seen a variety
of LiDAR-enabled apps using
the scene reconstruction
and depth APIs: productivity,
photo filter effects,
entertainment,
and even games that you can play
in your living room.
We’re really happy
to see the creativity
and resourcefulness shown
by the ARKit community.
While you’re creating
these apps, we’re working hard
on bringing you
the world’s best AR framework
and pushing the boundaries
of what’s possible.
Let’s go over the changes
coming in ARKit 5.
First, we’ll share some updates
and best practices
for location anchors,
which enable AR experiences
in real-world outdoor locations.
Next we’ll cover App Clip Codes,
which are a great way
to discover app clips
and also allow you
to position your content in AR.
We’ll highlight some
improvements to face tracking
using the ultra-wide
front-facing camera
on the new iPad Pro.
And we’ll finish
with some enhancements
to ARKit motion capture.
We’ll begin
with location anchors,
where we’ve worked
to expand region support
and provide some quality
of life improvements.
We’ll also recommend
some best practices
for creating applications.
Location anchors were introduced
last year to allow placement
of AR content at a specific
latitude and longitude.
Their purpose is
to allow creation
of AR experiences tied
to geographic locations.
Let’s take a look at an example.
This is
the New Nature experience
from the ScavengAR application,
built using
the location anchors API.
ScavengAR hosts AR content
at real-world locations
and enables the creation
of virtual public art
installations and activities.
It’s a good example
of how location anchors can
power outdoor experiences
as the world reopens.
The Maps app is also
introducing a new AR feature
that uses the API in iOS 15.
Let’s take a look.
This year Maps is adding
turn-by-turn walking directions
shown in AR,
using the location anchors API.
They incorporate several
practices we recommend.
We’ll cover these later on
to show how you can
build great applications.
Now that we’ve seen a few
samples, let’s recap how
location anchors can
be used to create them, starting
with the steps required to set
up a GeoTrackingConfiguration.
First, verify that the feature
is supported on the device.
Location anchors require
an A12 chip or newer
and cellular and GPS support.
Next, check
that the feature is available
at the location
before launching.
Camera and location permissions
must be approved
by the device owner.
ARKit will prompt
for permissions if needed.
Last year’s presentation
introducing ARKit 4
and the sample project,
“Tracking Geographic Locations
in AR,” cover all these topics
and API usage in greater depth.
We highly recommend
familiarizing yourself
with both of these sources.
This code sample shows how
to perform the checks
from the previous slide.
It queries for device support
and then verifies
if the feature is available
at the current location
before attempting to run
a GeoTrackingConfiguration.
GeoAnchors can then be
added to the ARSession
like other types of anchors.
They’re specified with
latitude-longitude coordinates
and, optionally, altitude.
It’s important to monitor
the GeoTrackingConfiguration’s
status to see if the feature has
localized
and what issues may
remain to be resolved.
The developer sample
contains an example
of how to implement a method
to receive status updates.
Checking availability near
the device location is important
for starting an application
with geo tracking.
We’re constantly working
to support more regions.
Location anchors were
limited to five metro areas
for their initial release
and, since then,
support has expanded to more
than 25 cities across the U.S.
We’re also working hard
to bring location anchors
to cities around the globe.
For the first time,
we’re excited to announce
a market
outside the United States.
Location anchors are
coming to London.
We’ll continue working
to add new regions over time.
If you don’t live
in a supported metro area,
you can also begin to experiment
with location anchors
through the use
of recording and replay,
which we’ll cover later
on in this session.
For the list
of supported regions,
refer
to the online documentation
for ARGeoTrackingConfiguration
at any time.
As location anchors become
available in more regions,
we recognize the need
to have a common visual language
to guide people.
To assist with a consistent
onboarding process, we’re adding
a new .geoTracking goal to use
with the ARCoachingOverlayView.
Similar to the existing overlay
for world tracking, it displays
an animation to help people
achieve a good experience.
Since coaching overlays are used
across many different AR apps,
including Maps,
people will already have
some familiarity with them
and know how to respond.
We encourage you
to include the coaching overlay
to ease the learning curve
for this feature.
Even while using the coaching
overlays, it’s still recommended
to monitor
the .geoTracking status updates,
which contain more detailed
information on tracking state.
Here’s what the .geoTracking
coaching overlay looks like.
The UI shows an instruction
to point the device away
from the ground and then
towards building facades.
After a few seconds,
tracking succeeds,
and your app can place
geo-tracked content.
The code for displaying
this animation is very similar
to that used
for other coaching overlays.
What’s unique
is the introduction
of the .geoTracking
goal for the overlay.
Make sure to set this goal
to display the correct guide.
We’ve seen
how the coaching overlay can
create a uniform onboarding
process.
Now we’ll go over some
other best practices
that will help you create
geo-tracked AR experiences.
Our first recommendation
is to use recording
and replay
for faster development.
ARKit sessions can be recorded
on devices using
Reality Composer, which is
available on the App Store.
This is especially useful
for location anchors
so you don’t have
to go outside as often to test.
It also allows collaboration
with remotely located creators.
The recordings can be replayed
on a device using Xcode.
To avoid incompatibility issues,
it’s recommended
to use the same device
and iOS version.
This also works for other types
of ARKit applications.
Replay is not specific
to location anchors.
Let’s walk through the process
for capturing a recording.
To record, open Reality Composer
and tap for more options
in the upper right.
Then open the Developer pane
and select Record AR Session.
Make sure location services
are enabled.
Tap the red button to start
and stop the recording.
To replay the recording,
connect the device
to a computer running Xcode.
Click Edit Scheme and set
the ARKit Replay data option
for the run configuration.
Then run the application.
While recording and replay can
help speed up development,
there are other practices we
recommend for content placement.
Here’s a video
demonstrating these.
Notice how the AR content is
large and clearly visible,
and information is conveyed
without needing to be overlaid
with a structure
in the environment.
As a trade-off
between development time
and placement precision,
consider creating content
that floats in the air
rather than trying to closely
overlap real-world objects.
We have a few
other recommendations
for placing content.
To obtain latitude and longitude
coordinates to place objects,
use the Apple Maps app
and copy coordinates
with at least six digits
of precision.
The steps for this were shown in
the video introducing ARKit 4,
so please refer there
for more details.
When creating an application,
it’s also important
to adjust the altitude
of the content relative
to the location anchor as needed
to produce a good experience.
If the app requires more precise
content placement,
add the geo anchor
when the device is
within 50 meters
of its location.
If ARKit places the anchor
with precise altitude,
it will update the anchor’s
altitude source field
to indicate this.
The CLLocation class has
a method that can be used
to compute the distances
in meters between two points.
This can
be used to verify that someone
is close to a location
before adding an anchor.
This concludes our session
on location anchors.
There are more ways
to place AR content
in your apps using ARKit 5.
So let me hand it off
to Christopher,
who will tell you more.
[Christopher]
Thank you, David.
Hi, my name is Christopher,
and I’m an engineer
on the ARKit team.
I'm excited to tell you more
about the other great new
features in ARKit 5.
Let me start with App Clip Codes
in ARKit.
You probably remember
that we introduced App Clips
at WWDC last year.
An app clip is a small slice
of an app which takes people
through one contextual workflow
of your app
without having
to install the whole app.
Owing to its small file size,
an app clip saves download time
and instantly
takes people directly
to a specific part of the app
that’s highly relevant
to their context at the moment.
We also
introduced App Clip Codes,
which are a great way
for people to visually discover
and launch your app clips.
No trips
to the App Store necessary.
This is what App Clip Codes
look like.
They can come in a variety
of shapes and colors.
As the developer,
you can create a look
which works
best for your scenario.
You also decide what data
to encode in the App Clip Code
and which app clip is
associated with which code.
All App Clip Codes contain
a visual scannable pattern
and some, like the red, blue
and orange codes shown here,
also contain an NFC tag
for the user’s convenience.
People can scan the code
with their camera
or hold the phone
to the embedded NFC tag
to launch your associated
app clip.
And now, you can also recognize
and track App Clip Codes
in your AR experiences.
We’ll take a look at how that’s
done later in this session.
But first, let’s take
a look at this app clip
developed by Primer,
where they use an App Clip Code
to launch an AR experience.
Primer partnered with Cle Tile
to show
people what their samples
will look like in AR
with the help of App Clip Codes.
Simply place your iPhone
and iPad
over the App Clip Code
to invoke an AR experience.
Now people can preview
the tile swatch on their wall,
all without downloading an app.
That’s pretty cool, right?
So, starting with iOS
and iPad 14.3, you can detect
and track App Clip Codes
in AR experiences.
Note that App Clip Code tracking
requires devices
with an A12 Bionic processor
or later, like the iPhone XS.
Let’s take a closer look at how
to use App Clip Codes in ARKit.
In iOS 14.3,
we introduced a new type
of ARAnchor,
an ARAppClipCodeAnchor.
This anchor has three
new properties: the URL embedded
in the App Clip Code,
a URL decoding state,
and the radius
of the App Clip Code in meters.
Let me explain.
Each App Clip Code
contains a URL
that is decoded
to display the correct content.
Decoding the URL is not instant.
ARKit can detect the presence
of an App Clip Code quickly.
But it can take
a little bit longer for ARKit
to decode the URL,
depending on the user’s distance
to the code
and other factors like lighting.
This is why
the App Clip Code anchor
contains
a .decoding state property,
and it can be
in one of three states.
The initial state .decoding
indicates
that ARKit is still
decoding the URL.
As soon as ARKit has
successfully decoded the URL,
the state will then switch
to .decoded.
When decoding the URL is not
possible,
the state will switch
to .failed instead.
This can, for example,
occur when someone scans
an App Clip Code which is not
associated with the app clip.
To use App Clip Code tracking,
you should first check
if it is supported
on the device.
Remember the App Clip Code
tracking is only supported
on devices with an A12 Bionic
processor or later.
Then set
the appClipCodeTrackingEnabled property
on your configuration
to true and run the session.
To read the URL
of an App Clip Code,
monitor the AR sessions
did update Anchors callback
and check the decoding state
of any detected
App Clip Code anchors.
While ARKit is decoding
the App Clip Code,
you might want to display
a placeholder visualization
on top of the App Clip Code
to give
the user instant feedback
that the App Clip Code
was detected
but still needs to be decoded.
As mentioned before,
decoding App Clip Codes can
also fail. For example,
when someone points the phone
at the App Clip Code which does
not belong to your app clip.
We recommend that you also
give feedback in that case.
Once the App Clip Code
has been decoded,
you can finally access its URL
and start displaying
the right content
for this App Clip Code.
For example,
in case of the Primer app clip
which you saw earlier,
the URL contains information
about which tile swatch
to display.
Once an App Clip Code has been
decoded, the question is, where
should you display the content
associated with this code?
One option is to display it
directly on top
of the App Clip Code anchor.
However, depending on your use
case, the App Clip Code itself
might not be the best place
to display the content.
So, for example,
you could position the content
nearby the App Clip Code
with a fixed relative position.
This works well
when the App Clip Code
is printed on an object,
say, a coffeemaker,
and you want to display
the virtual instructions
on how to operate it on top
of the machine’s buttons.
Or you could combine
the App Clip Code tracking
with other tracking technologies
supported by ARKit.
For example, image tracking.
Let’s take a look
at an implementation of that.
The videos and code
which you see next are based
on the “Interacting
with App Clip Codes in AR”
sample code which you can
download on developer.apple.com.
What you see now is a recording
of the sample’s AR experience.
First, I’m starting
in the Camera app,
scanning
a sunflower seed package.
Maybe I’m shopping
in the gardening store,
trying to decide
what plant seeds to buy.
iOS recognizes the App Clip Code
on the package
and launches the associated
Seed Shop app clip.
Here, I’m scanning
the App Clip Code a second time,
and then the grown sunflower
appears on the seed package.
Note that the app clip
uses image tracking
of the entire seed package
and places the sunflower on it.
This approach makes
sense in this use case,
as the person’s attention is
most likely
on the entire seed package
and not
on the smaller App Clip Code
in the top right.
But what if someone wanted
to see the plant grow
in their garden?
Here is
what that could look like.
Here we see
that when the code is scanned
for the first time,
it invokes an app clip download.
Then when the same code is
scanned again
from within the app clip,
it associates the code
with a sunflower seed box
and then tapping on the lawn
makes a sunflower appear there.
If instead, the app clip saw
the code on the rose seed box,
it would have spawned
a rose plant on the lawn.
Note that app clips are supposed
to contain only one workflow.
But the app clip can
offer a button to download
the full Seed Shop app
to experience other plants
they could preview
in their space.
Remember,
App Clip Code tracking also
works in App Clip’s parent app.
Let’s take a look
at the code which we need
to place sunflowers on the lawn.
First, you add
a tapGestureRecognizer to
the view to detect taps
on the screen.
When the person taps
on the screen
you can cast a ray
into the world
and get back
a resulting location
on the horizontal plane
in front of their device.
In our scenario,
this would be the person’s lawn.
You then grab the last App Clip
Code URL that was decoded
and add a new ARAnchor
on the lawn.
Lastly, you download
the sunflower 3D model
and display it on the lawn.
Now, let’s talk
about some best practices
for App Clip Codes in ARKit.
App clips can be used
in different environments
and for different use cases.
Consider whether it’s an option
for you
to create NFC App Clip Codes.
We recommend NFC App Clip Codes
for environments
where people can physically
access the code.
When using an NFC App Clip Code,
use appropriate call to action
text that guides people
to tap onto the tag
or, alternatively,
offers an explicit affordance
to scan the code.
Last but not least,
you need to make sure
that your App Clip Codes
are printed
on the appropriate size
for the user’s environment.
For example, a restaurant menu
might be printed on A4 paper,
and people will be comfortable
scanning a 2.5-centimeter
App Clip Code on that menu
from a distance of up
to 50 centimeters.
A movie poster, however,
is usually much larger
and might have enough space for
a 12-centimeter App Clip Code
which people would be able
to scan with their phone
from up to 2.5 meters away.
Please check out
our Human Interface Guidelines
on App Clip Codes
for more information
on recommended code sizes.
So that’s how you use
App Clip Codes in ARKit.
If you want to dive deeper into
app clips and App Clip Codes,
be sure to check out
“What’s new in App Clips”
and “Build light and fast
App Clips” sessions.
Now let’s jump over
to face tracking.
Face tracking allows
you to detect faces
in the front-facing camera,
overlay virtual content,
and animate facial
expressions in real time.
Since the launch of iPhone X,
ARKit has seen a ton
of great apps that take
advantage of face tracking.
From tracking multiple faces
to running face tracking
in simultaneous front
and back camera use case,
this API has received a number
of advancements over the years.
Last year, we introduced
face tracking on devices
without a TrueDepth sensor,
as long as they have
an A12 Bionic processor
or later.
And earlier this year,
we launched the new iPad Pro
that provides you
with an ultra wide field
of view front-facing camera
for your AR face tracking
experiences.
Let’s take a look.
Here you see the regular
front-facing camera’s field
of view.
And this is the new
ultra-wide field of view
on the new iPad Pro.
It really makes a difference,
doesn’t it?
Be aware that your existing apps
will keep using
the normal camera
for face tracking.
If you want to upgrade
your user’s experience
to the ultra-wide field of view
on the new iPad Pro,
you have to check
which video formats
are available and opt-in
for the new ultra-wide format.
You can do this by iterating
over all supported video formats
and checking for the
builtInUltraWideCamera option.
You then set this format
on your AR configuration
and run the session.
One thing to note is
that the new iPad Pro’s
ultra-wide camera has
a much larger field of view
than the TrueDepth sensor.
Therefore you will not get
a capturedDepthData buffer
on the ARFrame when using
the ultra-wide video format.
Last but not least,
let’s talk about motion capture.
Since its launch in 2019,
motion capture has enabled
robust integration
of real people in AR scenes,
such as animating virtual
characters
along with being used
in 2D and 3D simulation.
In iOS 15, motion capture is
getting even better.
On devices with
an Apple A14 Bionic processor
like the iPhone 12,
motion capture now supports
a wider range of body poses.
And this requires no
code changes at all.
All motion capture apps on
iOS 15 will benefit from this.
Most notably, rotations
are more accurate than ever,
helping you track sports actions
with much more precision.
Another big improvement is
that your device camera can
now track body joints
from a much further distance.
Also there has been
a significant increase
in tracking the range
of limb movement.
Let’s take a look at an example.
Here is one
of my coworkers, Ejler,
tracking his workouts
with the app Driven2win.
The results on iOS 15
are more precise than ever.
To recap, ARKit 5 brings lots
of new features
and improvements.
Location anchors
are available in new cities
and feature
a new coaching overlay.
App Clip Code tracking assists
in the easy discovery
and use of AR in your app clip,
as well as precise positioning
of your virtual content.
Face tracking works with the new
ultra-wide field of view
on the new iPad Pro,
and motion capture
adds better accuracy
and larger range of motion.
I’m so excited to see
all the amazing experiences
you will create with ARKit 5.
[music]