[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Irida Mance:
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Irida, a scientist
on the Apple software team,
and I will be joined by Sohum,
a Motion engineer.
Today, we'll introduce
two brand-new features
that will enable you to better
understand walking endurance
and quality.
Walking is a vital sign.
The way an individual walks
is highly informative
of their overall health
and well-being.
It can be used to track
recovery from an injury,
assess risk of falling,
monitor the aging process,
and even predict mortality.
At WWDC2020, we introduced
a suite of mobility metrics
that provide a powerful insight
into your walking patterns
throughout the day.
You can learn all about them
in last year's session,
"Beyond counting steps".
Today we're excited
to share an update
to one of these metrics:
the Six-Minute Walk metric,
available for Apple Watch.
Through a new recalibration API,
the metric will enable you
to better capture
acute changes in health.
In addition, we're going to talk
about a brand-new metric:
the Walking Steadiness feature,
available for iPhone.
What do these two metrics
have in common?
They're both great ways
to track important aspects
of walking
and can provide continuous
and objective measures
for monitoring improvements
or catching early warning signs.
But they capture
different things.
The Six-Minute Walk metric
estimates how far you can walk
in six minutes
and is a measure of your walking
capacity and endurance.
Walking steadiness captures
the quality of your walking
and is designed to make it
easy for you
to assess an individual's
risk of falling
based on their mobility.
Whether you are tracking
these metrics week over week --
to measure changes
in response to treatment --
or year over year --
to monitor natural
aging trends --
both metrics can provide
a unique window
into an individual's health.
We'll start by diving deeper
into the Six-Minute Walk
distance metric.
The in-clinic
Six-Minute Walk test
is a staple for clinicians
in many fields
to assess cardiovascular
and musculoskeletal health.
The metric captures
walking endurance
for low-capacity individuals.
It can help identify
which individuals
have a lower endurance relative
to others their age and height,
which is often indicative
of poor health outcomes.
This year,
using a new recalibration API,
the Six-Minute Walk metric
is also a great way
to track changes
to walking capacity
following an intervention --
such as a surgery --
or an acute events,
like an injury.
Let's run through a scenario
where recalibrating
the Six-Minute Walk metric
will be useful.
Imagine that we have
a patient, Jamie,
who just had knee surgery.
We know that Jamie could
barely walk after surgery,
but we only see a small dip
in their Six-Minute Walk
estimate.
Let's look into
what may be causing this.
To build an accurate estimate
of an individual's capacity,
the Six-Minute Walk distance
estimate looks at activity
and motion data across
a historical measurement window.
For example,
this is the measurement window
used for this estimate.
To see how far back
an estimate looked,
you can use a brand-new
metadata field,
which will tell you
the beginning
of the data window used.
We can see
that our example estimate
used data from way
before the surgery.
What we can do now is
recalibrate our estimates
to use data only postsurgery.
With this recalibration,
our estimates now capture
Jamie's true dip in mobility
immediately following
the surgery, which allows
for a way more accurate pre-
and postsurgery comparison.
Now, Sohum can show us
how to use these new features
in your app.
Sohum Thakkar: Thank you, Irida!
The recalibration API
lets you use your knowledge
of Jamie's surgery date
to improve their Six-Minute Walk
distance estimates.
If know you want to recalibrate,
you can use the brand-new
recalibrateEstimates method
in HKHealthStore.
This new method
has a few requirements.
The first thing you need
is a SampleType
that can be recalibrated.
You can check
if a type can be recalibrated
with the .allowsRecalibration
ForEstimates property.
As of iOS 15,
sixMinuteWalkType
is the only sampleType
that can be recalibrated.
The second thing you need
is a new entitlement.
You can add this entitlement
to your Xcode project yourself.
And lastly, your app will need
authorization
for both reading
and sharing the SampleType.
To prompt the user to grant
your app authorization,
simply create a set
with just the Six-Minute Walk
distance type,
and then pass it in
to healthStore.
requestAuthorization.
And with those requirements
out of the way,
let's recalibrate.
Just use HKHealthStore's
recalibrateEstimates method
and pass in the date of surgery.
Since this affects
the patient's health data,
a prompt will pop up on screen
asking them to allow
the recalibration.
And that's it!
For the next few estimates,
you'll see
the recalibration date
reflected in
the Measurement Start Date
in the Health App
and in the EarliestDateUsed
ForEstimate metadata
that will come
with every HealthKit sample.
A few things to consider:
First, this method
does not affect estimates
that are already present
in HealthKit at the time of use,
so it's important to recalibrate
as soon as possible
after a surgery.
Secondly, after recalibration,
it could take up to 14 days
to rebuild enough
activity history
to make a confident estimate.
And thirdly,
the effect is temporary.
Once the recalibration date
is far enough in the past,
the estimates will once again
start using their normal
measurement window.
You might be tempted
to recalibrate every fall
or every surgery
you learn about,
but these often don't result
in reduced mobility or fitness.
There's a trade-off.
In general, a longer data window
will result in more
accurate estimates
but will be less responsive
to acute changes.
In Jamie's case,
we know their surgery will cause
a substantial change
to their mobility and fitness,
and we'd like to monitor
that change closely.
If they're not recovering well,
we can reach out
and provide support.
This new recalibration API
extends the capabilities
of Apple's Six-Minute Walk
distance metric
to a whole new use case
of tracking recovery
from injury or surgery.
We hope you'll find it useful
in better monitoring
your patient's health
and improving outcomes.
Now I'd like to pass it off
to Irida
to tell you about a brand-new
metric, Walking Steadiness,
which measures a different
dimension of your walking.
Irida: Thanks, Sohum.
In addition to being able
to track how much
or how far an individual
is able to walk,
it's also important to monitor
the quality of that movement.
With iOS 15, we've built upon
our foundational understanding
of walking quality and extended
it through a new metric,
the Apple
Walking Steadiness metric.
The metric is designed for you
to better understand
your overall walking quality
and can help assess
your risk of falling
due to a mobility limitation
in the next 12 months.
Your quality of walking
is impacted by many factors,
including
your muscular strength,
your physical endurance,
your balance,
or external factors
like injuries or surgeries,
all of which can alter
your risk of falling.
The Apple Walking Steadiness
metric provides a unified way
to track the mobility components
that contribute to fall risk.
The feature consists
of three elements.
First, we provide a score
that can be used to continuously
monitor changes
in walking steadiness
over time.
A new score will be saved
to HealthKit weekly,
and it will represent the user's
steadiness for that week.
The score provides you
the greatest level of detail;
the higher the score,
the better your walking quality,
and the lower
your predicted risk of falling
because of a mobility
limitation.
Second,
to give a better idea of what
the steadiness scores mean,
we've categorized them
into three classifications:
OK, Low, and Very Low.
These classifications
provide you a simpler way
of identifying who is
at the highest risk of falling.
Lastly,
after individuals onboard onto
the Walking Steadiness feature
in the Health app,
we have enabled
a notification.
The notification
will alert individuals
whenever their steadiness
has dropped
to the Low or Very Low category,
or if they've remained at those
categories for several months.
Now you may be wondering,
What does steadiness look like
for typical healthy individuals
throughout their life?
Let's see what
the Walking Steadiness metric
could look like for two folks.
For this individual,
their walking quality
decreases as they age.
This is fairly typical.
We've all seen
that our elderly relatives
may not walk as well as us.
But we also know
there are behavioral factors
that contribute to steadiness.
For example,
an individual that is able to
maintain a high level of fitness
is likely to preserve
a higher quality of walking
as they age.
But we also know
that age or better fitness
are not the only factors
that impact walking steadiness.
Acute events
like an ankle injury
can drastically change
walking quality
and lead to
heightened fall risk.
So anyone can bounce
between steadiness categories
throughout their life.
And as I mentioned,
the steadiness classification
helps you understand
the significance
of these changes.
Let's dive a little deeper
into what individuals
with these classification levels
may look like.
An OK classification will be
your healthy, confident walker.
They generally will not have
any difficulty
going about their day
and doing many of the tasks
that challenge their strength
and coordination.
Their scores will be high,
and their risk of falling
due to a mobility-related
health issue is low.
A low-classification individual
will have more
compromised mobility.
They may be generally OK;
but in more
challenging situations --
say a difficult hike --
they may need
to take more precautions
to prevent from falling.
They might not have fallen yet,
but this early awareness
will be useful.
Lastly,
a Very Low classification
is indicative
of someone that has noticeably
compromised steadiness.
Based on their mobility,
this individual would be
at high risk of falling.
Again, they might not
have fallen yet,
but their mobility
is compromised,
and they should take
the necessary measures
to avoid situations where
falls are more likely to happen
or, if possible, to improve
their strength and balance
through exercise.
All right.
That's what this metric
is capable of.
Now you might ask,
What is required to get a
Walking Steadiness estimate?
Actually, not much.
the metric is optimized
to measure steadiness
while individuals
are carrying their iPhone
in some of the most
common locations,
for example, a pant pocket,
a jacket pocket,
even a purse held closely;
all will work as long as
the device is held tightly
to the center of your body.
Now back to Sohum
to walk us through
how to leverage
the Walking Steadiness metric
in your apps.
Thanks, Irida
for that introduction
to Walking Steadiness.
Let's put it to use.
Imagine you're building an app
for a physical therapy clinic.
One of the toughest challenges
in physical therapy
and rehabilitation
is tracking progress.
And now that most visits
are virtual,
and telehealth
is gaining popularity,
it can be even tougher.
Let's say your app's purpose
is to keep patients up to date
and identify those
at higher risk of falling
and those who are declining
in steadiness.
That's an incredibly difficult
thing to measure,
but Walking Steadiness can help.
As Irida mentioned,
Walking Steadiness
has three elements:
the score, the classification,
and the notification.
We'll see how each can be
integrated into your app
for physical therapy patients...
starting with the score.
Let's say you want
to display
a patient's
most recent steadiness score.
Let's see how to do that.
The score is
a HealthKit quantityType
with the name
appleWalkingSteadiness.
Since it's an Apple-defined
metric, it's read-only.
Its unit in HealthKit
is percent,
and it ranges
from zero to one.
And it's written weekly,
although estimates
may be delayed
if there isn't enough data
to compute an estimate.
To kick us off,
let's grab an authorization.
We'll construct a set with
the appleWalkingSteadiness type.
Then, we'll call
requestAuthorization.
To get the most recent
steadiness score,
we'll construct a SampleQuery
with a limit of one,
sorted by end date.
If there is a returned sample,
we'll grab the value
with percent units
and update our status
in the app.
This is what it'll look like.
The score is great
for tracking trends,
but is sometimes kind of hard
to interpret on its own.
What does 45 mean?
The classification might be
the more appropriate level
of granularity for most people.
Let's use it to add context.
The classification
comes in the form
of a brand-new HealthKit enum:
HKAppleWalkingSteadiness
Classification.
The enum can take the
values .ok, .low, and .veryLow.
Starting from our previous code
to grab the most recent score,
it only takes a single line
to convert a score
to a classification.
The classification enum
has a convenience constructor
that will translate a score to
the appropriate classification.
And we'll display
the classification
along with the score.
There!
That's far more interpretable.
Now we can tell this individual
is in the Low classification
and may be
at increased risk of falling.
OK, so now let's tackle
the patient-monitoring portion
of this app.
We'd like to be able to identify
and reach out to patients
who are at high risk of falling.
The Walking Steadiness
notification is great for this.
You can register to be notified
when a patient receives
a steadiness notification
and reach out to them
for a check-in.
The notification arrives
in HealthKit
as a CategoryType sample,
and it's called
"appleWalkingSteadinessEvent"
in HealthKit.
It's also a read-only type.
There are four types
of steadinessEvents.
.initialLow and .initialVeryLow
are triggered about a month
after the individual drops
into the Low
or Very Low classifications.
After this initial notification,
.repeatLow
or .repeatVeryLow events
will remind the individual
about once every three months
if they stay
at the same classification.
You can read more
about the notification types
in the developer documentation
in the links associated
with this session.
To read the notifications,
we'll need
another authorization.
This time, we'll construct a set
with only the type
appleWalkingSteadinessEvent
and pass it in to the
requestAuthorization method.
Let's watch for notifications.
Here we're creating
an HKObserverQuery
that will execute a handler
every time a steadiness event
is saved to HealthKit,
meaning the user
got a notification.
In this handler, we'll prompt
the user for a checkup.
We'll also allow HealthKit
to deliver the event to us
in the background
to ensure we can respond
to the notification
within a day.
When we execute the query,
our app will begin listening
for notifications.
And every time the user
receives a notification,
we could trigger a prompt
to schedule a virtual checkup
with the clinic.
Great! Now you can reach out to
patients at increased fall risk.
But there are other users
a physical therapy clinic
might be interested in.
Here's an example of a patient
who showed great progress
at first but is now declining
in steadiness.
They wouldn't have received
a Walking Steadiness
notification
because they aren't yet at a
higher-fall-risk classification.
But a physical therapy clinic
might be concerned
about trends like this.
Are the exercises appropriate?
Are they causing damage?
Is the patient
just not keeping up?
We'd like to schedule
a follow-up,
so let's design
our own notification criteria.
Here are the patient's
steadiness scores over time.
The plan is to query six weeks
of steadiness scores
and calculate
the best-fit slope.
We'll do this every week,
and if a patient's steadiness
is declining more than, say,
five points per week on average,
we should try
to schedule a check-in.
Let's create a predicate
to query in the past six weeks
and execute an HKSampleQuery
for the appleWalkingSteadiness
QuantityType.
In the callback,
we'll pass the results off
to a detectTrends function.
Now, all we need to do
is calculate the best-fit slope,
using a custom function
we have defined,
and check if it's less than -5,
meaning steadiness is declining
at a rate of over five points
per week.
And if it is, we can prompt
the user for a checkup,
just like before.
So now when we detect
their steadiness is declining,
they will receive a prompt!
So that's how to use
all three elements
of Walking Steadiness
and how to design your own
simple notification criteria.
It's never been so easy
to perform passive
mobility monitoring.
But let's not get
ahead of ourselves.
All of this is dependent
on the patient getting
Walking Steadiness scores.
Here are four best practices
to make sure they don't miss
a single sample.
First off, users will only
get steadiness
if they have their height
set in the Health app.
Weight and age are
highly recommended.
So first things first,
let's prompt them for those.
We recommend writing
updated samples directly,
via the HealthKit API.
Secondly, we recommend
prompting the user
to turn on Apple's Walking
Steadiness notifications.
They can do this from the
Health app in the Mobility room.
Third, as Irida mentioned,
for the vast majority
of patients,
keeping their phone
in their pocket
while they go about
their everyday activities
is enough
to get steadiness scores.
Let's just encourage them
to take their phone with them
while they're walking around.
To check if they're meeting
the walking criteria,
we can check
if they're receiving
walking speed estimates
in HealthKit.
Two weeks with consistent
Walking Speed samples
is a good indicator they're
carrying their device enough.
As a reminder,
walking speed requires
an iPhone 8 or above,
and is measured
when the phone is held tightly
to the center of the body
while walking over flat ground.
A quick glance
in the Health app,
or a quick HealthKit query,
can tell us if we need
to prompt them
to walk with their phone more.
So there you have it!
You have all the tools
you need
to build the next-generation
physical therapy app
that can keep track of
your patient's walking quality
without any dedicated
equipment or assessments.
Now, over to Irida to talk about
the many other amazing ways
you can use Walking Steadiness
for health monitoring.
Irida: Thanks, Sohum.
We just saw how
Walking Steadiness
can make a huge difference
to virtual care
for physical therapy,
and it can do so much more.
Consider using
Walking Steadiness
if you want to build an app
that helps families
check up on
an aging grandparent,
or perhaps you can help patients
with neurological diseases
like multiple sclerosis
monitor disease progression.
You could even use it
to recommend workouts
and hikes that are more tailored
to an individual's fall risk.
Walking Steadiness
and the new capabilities
for Six-Minute Walk built
on top of a rich ecosystem
for using motion sensing
to monitor heath.
Given the strong ties
between mobility,
cardiovascular
and respiratory functioning,
we encourage you to explore
how metrics related
to cardiovascular health
on the Apple Watch --
and mobility for the iPhone --
can be used for rehabilitation
or prehabilitation applications,
to best prepare patients
for successful surgery.
Or consider
how Walking Steadiness,
the mobility metrics,
and our Movement Disorder API
can be combined to monitor
the complicated motor symptoms
of Parkinson's Disease.
The combination of these metrics
can unlock a truly powerful
experience for your apps.
To wrap up, we want to provide
some best practices
when collecting this data.
First,
though walking is something we
don't often think a lot about,
as we've just seen, it carries
a powerful health signal.
As with any health information,
make sure that your data
collection has strong privacy
and security safeguards.
Any data you take
outside of HealthKit
should at the very least
be key-coded and encrypted.
Next, you should be transparent
about the information
you are collecting and why.
Anytime you request to read
a certain HealthKit type,
we'll prompt the user
to approve its use.
But beyond this basic measure,
it's our joint responsibility
to collect only
the most meaningful data
and to be transparent
on how that data will be used.
For example,
for Six-Minute Walk estimates,
our users should understand when
the recalibration is appropriate
and how it helps their care.
For the Walking Steadiness metric,
the requirements
to get an estimate
should be clearly communicated.
Working with domain experts,
like physicians
or physical therapists,
will ensure that you collect
the most meaningful data
from these metrics.
Lastly, your customer should
have control of their data.
In HealthKit, an individual
can tap Show All Data
and delete any and all samples
collected from them.
If you take data
outside of HealthKit,
your customer should have
an easy way to view and delete,
turn off data collection,
or have other means
to exercise control
over what is collected
from them.
Whether you are using
Walking Steadiness
to measure quality of movement,
the Six-Minute Walk metric
to assess recovery from injury,
or any other health metric,
following these guidelines will
protect our customers' data
and promote user trust.
A commitment to these principles
is essential
when handling any health data.
OK, that's a wrap for us.
We want to thank you
for watching
and being part of WWDC21.
We cannot wait to see
what you build next.
♪