[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Caroline Cranfill: Hi,
I’m Caroline Cranfill,
a designer on
the Apple Design team.
Later, I’ll be joined
by my colleagues,
Cynthia and Sabrine.
People are both
equally important
and very different
from one another.
Considering each person
can broaden your market,
lead to a more popular app,
and is so much more
than the right thing to do.
Achieving this ambitious goal
will require you to think
from the very beginning
about how to ensure
your app will empower
and delight everyone,
and not just at the beginning.
As with all projects,
designing and developing
for inclusiveness
is an iterative process
that requires you to examine
your assumptions about how
other people think and feel.
Although each person’s
perspective is unique,
inclusive design and development
benefits from focusing hard
on certain axes of diversity.
This can help us think
more broadly
than our own experiences.
Diversity axes
can include class; culture;
ethnicity; language; education;
political, philosophical
and religious beliefs;
race; gender;
sexual orientation;
age; abilities; disabilities;
whether you are right-
or left-handed;
body measurements like height;
and also environmental
conditions like location,
internet connectivity,
or access to technology devices.
Each of these provide
spectrums of perspectives --
and even more
unique experiences --
when you consider
the intersections
of multiple axes
at any given time.
For example,
how will your app perform
if there is no high-speed
Internet or data is limited?
Or, will your app be welcoming
for people across the spectrum
of gender identities
and LGBTQ+ communities?
As you view your app or game
through many
different perspectives,
inclusiveness is about
making people feel welcome
and considered.
People who use it should feel
that you designed with their
life experiences in mind.
Because your app can be used
by people around the world,
it lends to celebrating
humanity and difference.
Today, we will discuss how
creating apps or games
for a diverse set of people
requires inclusivity to be
infused into how you work
just as much
as what you choose to make.
Before we dive into specifics,
I will talk through
some common misconceptions
around inclusive design
and development
and how you can
think differently.
At first, it may feel
like inclusion is hard.
But I would like to reframe this
as, "Inclusion is a journey."
Lots of things are hard,
but we do them anyway
when they’re worthwhile.
Change is an iterative process
and takes time.
Meaningful change requires
planning, persistence,
and patience.
The benefits are high, because
you can improve quality of life,
enable people to achieve
new goals, or try new things.
Another misconception
is that inclusive design
limits creativity.
In truth, inclusive design
and development
stimulates new
creative solutions.
Wider context and awareness
can promote progress in areas
that you may have
never considered before.
You can make breakthroughs
in experiences for everyone
that wouldn’t happen
if you didn’t consider
the diversity
of human experience.
Inclusion doesn’t mean
turning down innovative ideas
or asking all people to accept
a lowest common denominator
experience.
Constraints help your process
by helping you make
the first few early decisions.
This allows you to put
most of your energy
into creating new solutions
in a narrow problem space.
Let me share
an example with you.
A team at Apple figured out how
they can use our Apple products
to add a layer of intelligence
to our physical world.
They first wanted to focus
on recognizing
a few objects and text,
which in itself is a constraint.
But they didn’t just stop there.
They explored ways to surface
buttons to call, message,
add to contacts, or copy
recognized phone numbers.
It’s helpful to me
but essential for people
who are blind or low vision
to interact with printed
materials like signs,
business cards, and envelopes.
Not only can people
who are blind read this text,
they can act on it to make calls
and save contacts.
This brings us to
a misconception about teams.
You may think
that having a diverse team
means your app or game
will be inclusive.
In truth, having an empowered
diverse team
means your app
or game can be inclusive.
We all share
the responsibility to build
an inclusive environment
that enables inclusive actions.
You’re more engaged
when you feel comfortable
voicing your ideas and opinions.
And when those thoughts come
from a diverse group of people,
it fosters more creativity
and innovation.
At Apple, the accessibility
engineers work hand in hand
with a wide array of teams
to help solve unique problems
that affect only
a certain group of people.
For example, a person
who is blind or has low vision
might have difficulty knowing
when to move forward in a line
independently.
A solution started with
the video engineering team
using the technology
called "LiDAR."
It uses a pulsed laser
to ping nearby objects
to generate a 3D model
of the surrounding environment.
The teams were empowered
to work together
to create and release
the People Detection feature
in the Magnifier app.
It allows you to know
the distance between you
and the people around you.
What started as a prototype
to make life more convenient
became a necessity
once COVID-19 hit.
Our team's ongoing conversations
with the blind community
led to a more pressing issue:
How does a blind
or low-vision person
practice social distancing?
One more misconception
is that inclusion
can be done at the very end.
Considering inclusion
and the experience
that each individual person --
or groups of people --
have with your app or game
must be considered upfront
and carried throughout
the design and development.
Waiting until the end
is reactionary,
and there often isn’t
enough time to correct.
More than small changes
become risky.
This doesn’t mean you have
to get it right from the start,
but that it's being considered
from the start.
Now we can build
on these reframings
to empower us to create
more inclusive apps or games.
To start, you can take
a deeper look into how you work.
You can be in a better position
to achieve your inclusion goals
if you first look
at the diversity of your teams
in creating inclusive
working environments.
At Apple, we believe our teams
should reflect the diverse,
ever-evolving world we serve.
People are drawn
to like-mindedness,
consensus, and agreement.
It feels comfortable
and takes less mental energy,
but it doesn’t always
get you the best results.
When you see difference
as an asset,
rather than a challenge,
you open yourself
to new possibilities,
creative thinking, and
productive new relationships
that help you
make better decisions.
In some ways, small companies
are better positioned
to build more inclusive teams
if you commit
to diversity early.
People tend to hire
those they know,
which poses the risk
of them having
very similar perspectives.
If you instead bring on
someone different from you,
you have an easier path
to making diversity a core value
from the get-go rather
than rushing to fix it later on.
And as you grow your teams,
think “culture add,”
rather than “culture fit.”
What perspectives
are you missing
and how could finding
that perspective
change your app for the better?
Your team can be diverse,
but it’s often
that diverse perspectives
are not incorporated
in meaningful ways
that impact decision making.
You want to make sure
you are actively creating space
and asking for perspectives
in a judgment-free way.
To create safe spaces,
teams need time and space
to think inclusively.
Protect this time.
The design and development
process can be rigid
and unwavering,
so much so that you don’t feel
like you can take time
to reflect and think about
what you are making.
Fast development
also doesn’t allow you
to incorporate the diverse
perspectives from your teams.
Now we will look at the design
and development process
more closely, and I will share
tips and pointers
to consider during each phase.
If you were to illustrate
the process,
you may first think of it
as a line
with point A
of formulating the idea
to point B of releasing.
In the middle
are lengths for phases
like design, development,
and testing.
Much like security or privacy,
inclusion cannot be treated
as an afterthought.
Since you don’t want
to release your app or game
and discover that it doesn’t
work well for everyone,
you can dedicate
and reserve time to pause,
think, and pivot throughout
the whole process,
not just at the end.
It really becomes a
rejuvenating, iterative process.
Taking time out of each phase
to reflect,
ask some key questions,
can be helpful to evaluate
what you are making.
It may feel like you are
looping back momentarily,
but the new, more inclusive path
will ultimately
make the app or game
relate to more people.
It will also give you more time
to tackle things
that may be complex
and require longer time
to solve.
Now we will discuss
what you can ask yourself
or do during each phase.
First, we’ll start
when you ideate
on what you are going to make.
Everyone working
on the app or game
should be able
to answer the question:
Why are you making this?
Will everyone relate to it?
Clarify the purpose of the app
or game you are creating.
What human good
are you trying to serve?
How will people be better off?
What does it enable people
to do, be, or feel?
Next, also ask,
who are you making it for?
Don’t just think of people who
use the app or game currently.
Think through the lens
of the different diversity axes.
Which specific dimensions
or intersections
have you considered,
and what will
their experience be?
Next, challenge your assumptions
and listen.
Actively listen and learn about
the experiences and perspectives
very different from your own
and those commonly valued
by your design
and development team.
Your educational journey
will uncover new areas
to concentrate on.
The next phase of the design
and development process
is design.
When ideas are coming to focus,
it’s time to think concretely
about the extremes of how people
will use the app or game,
not just the average person.
It may be that an
unconsidered intersection
is preventing people from
wanting to use your app or game.
Next, consider the emotional,
social, and physical impact
on the people
who use your app or game.
Are some populations
or groups of people
more likely to have
negative experiences?
Are these populations also
vulnerable or disadvantaged?
If so, do you understand why,
and what is being
done about this?
Next, consider the impact
of location and context
on the experience.
Context is about
the circumstances
of the people using your app.
It can span across several
diversity axes like culture,
environment, location,
and connectivity.
You can consider
how in some cultures,
multiple generations of families
may live together
in one household.
People may live in cities
or rural areas,
and both have different needs.
You can consider environments
may be noisy or quiet,
bright or dark,
or small or large.
For example, roommates
or friends using an AppleTV
may have a different experience
and needs
from families with children
who use an AppleTV.
The next phase of the design
and development process
is when you start
to develop your designs.
It’s important
to have inclusive representation
or relevant expertise
throughout development.
As you evaluate
prototypes or designs,
be sure to explicitly include
a diverse group of people
when solutions
are being discussed
and decisions are being made.
Diverse voices can provide
context and strengthen reasons
on why the app or game
is going down a certain path.
Next, start planning
for accessibility
and internationalization
at the beginning of development.
Apple ships products
with lots of built-in
accessibility features
for people with disabilities,
who are 15 percent
of the world’s population.
And the number of people
living with disabilities
is increasing
due to aging populations
and chronic health conditions.
The people who use
your apps or games
need you
to make them accessible.
Take time now to understand
different accessibility
and localization APIs,
so everything is in place
as features are developed.
Standard UIKit, AppKit,
or SwiftUI controls and views
implement the
UIAccessibility methods
and are accessible by default,
but you will need to plan
for more time
to make your apps accessible
if you are using
custom controls or views.
Before wrapping up the design
and development phases,
I’m going to hand it over
to Cynthia to share an example
of considering
intersectionality in innovation.
Cynthia Bennett:
I’m Cynthia Bennett,
and I’m a researcher
on the AI
and Machine Learning team.
Our team designed and developed
one inclusive experience --
powered by machine learning --
which centered a perspective
at the intersection
of two of the diversity axes.
And I’ll explain
how learning from organizations
outside of Apple
helped us to develop
a better feature.
To provide some background,
people who are blind
or low vision
access Apple products
with our advanced screen reader,
VoiceOver.
With VoiceOver, people who use
our devices can navigate apps,
chat with friends,
and do much, much more.
Let me show you
how it sounds.
While using VoiceOver,
you can drag your finger
across the screen
and hear everything you touch.
>> VoiceOver: VoiceOver On.
Calendar, Monday June 7th.
[CLICKING] News. Home.
Camera. Podcasts.
You can also flick left or right
to move from one element
to the next.
>> [CLICKING] VoiceOver: News.
Weather. Photos.
And you can double-tap
to activate items.
>> VoiceOver: Double-tap
to open. [CLICK] [CHIME]
People who are blind
or low vision
may not be able to see
what is in Photos,
but they want to enjoy them
just like everyone else.
Image descriptions --
or textual information
about the most important things
shown in photos --
may accompany photos.
So to create great and
inclusive photos experiences,
Apple has worked on supporting
image descriptions.
In iOS 15, you can use
the Description feature
of Markup
to write your own descriptions
of photos.
These image descriptions
are then sent
whenever you share photos
across Apple products.
The human-written description
for this photo is,
“Side-profile of a giraffe
walking in the savanna
with trees in the distance.”
But there are a lot of photos
out there
and many of them
do not have descriptions.
Machine learning is
a tool that can help.
A machine-learning-trained model
can generate image descriptions
automatically, quickly,
and at scale.
So our team trained a model
to generate detailed natural
language descriptions of images
across iOS, which we call
VoiceOver Recognition
image descriptions.
Let’s listen to the VoiceOver
Recognition image description
of this photo.
>> VoiceOver: A giraffe standing
on a dry, grassy field.
But even state-of-the-art
machine learning is not enough.
Inclusion must be intentional.
So our team needed to understand
how the image descriptions model
described all people,
not just average people.
If you’re working on
machine-learning-powered
features,
one place to start is to learn
how different groups of people
are represented
by machine learning.
And this is a step
everyone can take,
whether you’re working
on your own
or at a large company.
Keep those diversity axes
in mind
when thinking about what groups
you should prioritize.
One aspect of machine learning
representation
that our team learned more about
was how people’s gender
would be described.
We learned that so far,
models tend to represent
two genders: female and male.
But we know that people
may be a variety of genders,
including being non-binary
or transgender.
In this case,
representation did not align
with everyone’s gender.
You might ask,
why does this matter?
What does gender have to do
with making photos inclusive
of one group --
people who are blind
or low vision?
Well, people who are blind
or low vision
have all sorts
of gender identities.
In other words,
these characteristics
will work together
to impact the experiences
people have
while reading
image descriptions.
Intersectionality was developed
by legal and critical race
scholar Kimberlé Crenshaw.
It recognizes
the unique experiences
and needs of people
who have multiple identities
which are systematically
disadvantaged.
In this example, listening
to intersectional perspectives
helped us to develop
great experiences
for people with identities
across groups
in the diversity axes.
Specifically, intersectionality
helped us listen to people
tell us how being both blind
or low vision
and being a minority gender,
like non-binary and transgender,
together impacted
their experiences
reading image descriptions.
To ensure that we learned
perspectives
from people who live at
this very specific intersection,
our team partnered
with outside organizations
with members who are both
blind or low vision
and who are part
of the LGBTQ+ community,
which is inclusive of non-binary
and transgender people.
Our team learned that you can’t
know someone’s gender
by looking at a photo.
We also learned
that gender-neutral
image descriptions
could still provide
helpful details
by focusing on other things,
such as people’s clothes
and hairstyles.
For now, we developed VoiceOver
Recognition image descriptions
to be gender neutral.
As an example, let’s hear
the VoiceOver Recognition image
description of this photo.
>> VoiceOver: A person
with curly black hair
wearing a red and white
striped shirt
and standing in front
of a building.
However, anyone can use
the description feature
to write their own
image descriptions,
which can include
people’s gender
when the person writing
the image description
knows this information.
A human-written description
for the same photo could be,
“Sam stands outside
of a restaurant.
She has curly black hair
and wears a red and white
striped blazer.”
So we just looked at the process
of inclusive development
as it applied
to using machine learning.
But the things I talked about
apply to any app or game.
First, inclusion is innovation
for wider audiences.
For example,
image descriptions enhance
engagement for everyone
by allowing people
who are blind or low vision
to take part in all of the fun
we have
by sharing photos
with one another.
Even if you don’t have
the resources
to train machine learning models
to increase accessibility,
you can still create
great experiences
with features that enable people
to be more inclusive,
like our description feature.
Second, including people
who live at the intersection
of various identities
and experiences
helps you to not just develop
for one group at a time,
but to make sure your products
intended to meet unique needs,
like those of people
who are blind or low vision,
are also respectful
across diversity axes,
which we did by developing
image descriptions
that are inclusive
of all genders.
Our team learned about
this important intersection
by researching how machine
learning represented people.
And this is something
anyone can do,
whether you're working on
your own or at a large company.
Finally, reaching out to experts
when we did not know something,
was a key component
of our inclusive process.
Caroline: As Cynthia discussed,
focusing in on intersections
of diversity axes
is one way to not only
be innovative, but respectful.
To continue discussing
tips for inclusivity
in the design and development
process,
the next phase is
when you test your app or game.
We need to seek out and engage
with a diverse group of people
to use your app or game
to give real-life feedback.
Most of all, you’ll discover
whether the ideas in your mind
hold up in practice
and over time,
as well as gain extra insights.
Having testing teams
with diverse backgrounds
can help find those edge cases.
Diversity will bring
a wider range of experiences
and usability patterns.
Next, testing
with assistive technologies
and various accommodations
will help you uncover issues
before they affect customers.
Learning the basics
of VoiceOver,
increasing your text size
to the maximum level,
or navigating your app
or game with the keyboard
can help you quickly identify
potential problems
and should be incorporated
into test plans.
Next, listen, review,
and prioritize feedback.
Feedback is important
to the final product.
With feedback, you may need
to repeat the design
and development process
with new lenses,
remove features,
or add features.
Advocate in your company
to put inclusive testing goals
as Key Performance Indicators,
or KPIs,
just like any other metric,
to measure inclusion
as a key business objective.
The last phase of the design
and development process
is deciding if you are ready
to release.
At some point,
given time and resources,
you will need to make
tradeoffs to release
if you have a hard date.
It may mean you need
to make hard calls
by cutting back
the release of one feature
so you can make fewer features
great for everyone.
Poor experiences for a
particular group of people
can have severe impact
if it continually happens
over and over.
It can lead them away
from your app or game.
Next, if you can’t have
the best experience
for one of your diversity axes
or intersections,
you need to take time
to know why, how, and when
you can plan
to make the best experience.
Sometimes not enough time
was allotted,
an issue was identified
or escalated too late,
didn’t plan
for additional complexity,
or perhaps the API was novel
and you ran out of time.
But having an informed
and properly scoped plan
and target date to address
improvements is important
to stay on track and to be able
to plan better next time.
Learning how to do better
and how we can do more
is part
of the inclusive journey.
You can also remember
to continue to reevaluate,
strengthen, and grow
with real-life developments,
or as you learn more
about the ways
you can make the experience
better for people.
It also means not just moving on
to the next thing entirely.
Inclusivity allows you to act
towards massive change.
To walk us through an example
of continuing to iterate designs
to be more inclusive,
I’ll hand it over to Sabrine.
Sabrine Rekik:
Hello, I'm Sabrine Rekik,
an inclusion engineer
in the Camera & Photos team.
My multicultural upbringing
taught me that empathy
and curiosity make the world
a better place.
I will share insights
and techniques
on how to continue
your inclusivity journey
after you launch.
To do so, I will use the example
of a feature I worked on,
called photo Memories.
In case you are not familiar
with it,
photo Memories smartly stitches
people's photos and videos
into heartfelt thematic movies
and help them revisit
forgotten moments.
In iOS 15, we wanted to expand
the photo Memories experience
to be even more inclusive
to our global audience.
To guide us,
we paid close attention
to the feedback shared by people
using the Photos app.
Many people said they enjoy
photo Memories
and being reminded of good times
with family and friends,
but others hinted at ways
Memories could be improved.
I will show you two pieces
of feedback we received,
and how we turned them
into inclusion goals.
The first comment is,
"I take a lot of photos at
my daughter’s karate practice.
It would be great to have them
turned into a Memory.”
We turned this feedback
into the following goal:
celebrate diversity.
How? By surfacing memories
people care about,
with themes that match who
they are and what they are into.
To come up with those themes,
we organized brainstorming
sessions with our teammates
throughout the company,
especially those
living outside of the US.
Brainstorming is
my favorite group technique
to quickly and spontaneously
generate ideas
and boost creativity.
We gathered unique ideas
to make Memories more personal;
many of them we would not have
thought of by ourselves.
We were reminded
that even though many of us
love taking photographs,
the content
of our photo libraries
is unique to each of us.
Our photos and videos reflect
our own identity and life story,
including our hobbies
and cultural heritage.
To help people relive
moments they care about,
we had to embrace
the breadth of life experiences
and interests.
Little tip for
your brainstorming session:
identify voices that are very
different from yours.
And if possible, run multiple
sessions with smaller groups
in different time zones
to allow more people
to participate.
Large groups tend
to be intimidating,
and you can miss out
on great suggestions.
Once we gathered
new memories ideas,
we analyzed each one
through the lenses
of the diversity axes.
In our case, we looked
at new Memory themes
through the lenses of:
rural versus urban living,
teenagers versus grandparents,
regional versus global.
And for each of them,
we answered the questions:
Who are we building this for?
Who are excluding?
And how will people feel?
This exercise helped us select
and prioritize
new Memory themes.
People wanted more
of their hobbies to be included,
so we started
representing more of them
such as martial arts,
skateboarding, and soccer.
We chose to prioritize hobbies
around the world,
rather than hobbies
in our areas.
But we didn't stop there,
we also expanded
our international holiday
catalogue
so every person can relive
festivities they cherish,
whether it be Christmas, Diwali,
Lunar New Year, Eïd al-Fitr,
Hanukkah, or all of them.
Since my team didn't have
the expertise required,
we collaborated
with cultural experts
to identify the set of holidays
people living in their regions
love celebrating.
I'm thrilled that the Photos app
can help me revisit
even more aspects of my life,
including my favorite Tunisian,
French, and American holidays.
Now let’s look at the second
feedback we heard.
Someone commented,
“I don’t like when
the Photos app reminds me
of my ex-partner.”
We turned in
into the following goal:
Being mindful of difficult
life experiences,
and design with sensitivity.
To achieve this objective,
we used another technique.
While brainstorming meetings
are great at producing ideas
and increasing creativity,
specific topics require
extra sensitivity
and your undivided attention.
So we leaned towards
individual interviews
to dive deeper
and provide a safe space
for people to share
their stories.
I encourage you to give it a try
and schedule conversations
with people who had concerns
with your app
and didn't feel included.
For Memories,
we hosted several conversations
to unpack the feedback gathered
during our preliminary research.
Several people shared that they
enjoyed revisiting their photos,
except when they featured
a person
they'd rather not
be reminded of.
Before designing solutions,
we carved space to empathize,
listen, and understand
their perspectives.
We gently unpacked the what,
how, when,
and especially the why.
We were interested in what made
a memory enjoyable or not,
but this question
is difficult to answer.
To avoid vague and generic
replies, we asked instead:
What are some
of your favorite Memories?
What Memories did you dislike?
What were you feeling
after seeing it?
How can we make the experience
better for you?
And followed up with things
like, “Why?"
or "Tell me more about that..."
to unpack the answers
even further.
Formulating the right questions
can be challenging,
but it’s a skill
you get better at with practice.
If you can,
favor open-ended questions,
refer to specific moments
in the past
and avoid using language
that can influence the response.
Also restrain from bringing
solutions to their problems
just yet, and take things in.
By having one-on-one
conversations,
we were reminded that photos
and videos have the power
to affect someone's emotions,
both positively and negatively.
It can be difficult
to unexpectedly see photos
of a loved one who passed away
and be reminded
of their absence.
For others, pictures
of their ex-partner
can elicit a myriad of emotions,
from sadness to anger.
And we also learned
that sometimes,
it's not what is in
the frame that hurts,
but the invisible context
that only the owner of
the photo library knows about.
The process of listening
and absorbing other people's
experiences can be humbling.
It was for me and my team.
After being immersed
in real stories,
it is now time to address
the feedback with a new design.
In our case, to help people
revisit photos and videos
that bring joy,
we thought we'd give them
control over who they see,
or not,
in Memories.
In the first iteration,
we added multiple buttons
to feature less of a person
while browsing a Memory,
and we reengineered
our app,
so they’ll immediately
see less of these people
across the Photos app.
For consistency, we looked
at other places in our app
where people would want
to affect the experience.
We added a Feature Less
action from a Featured photo,
from the People albums,
and even from a single asset
while browsing.
The next step is to validate
that a solution
to a problem works.
As designers and developers,
the first design we come up with
is our first response
to the stories we heard
and absorbed.
However, listening to someone
doesn't always mean
we understood them.
To make sure
you are on the right track
and solve real problems,
it is important to circle back
to the people you interviewed,
show them your sketches,
and seek their feedback.
Is your design
addressing their need?
And if not,
try to understand the nuances
you missed the first time.
When we showed
our first solution to people,
we got mixed reactions.
We learned that we all have
different tolerance thresholds
and that the action
of featuring less of a person
wasn't radical enough for some.
We took this insight
into account,
and in the following
design iteration,
left it up to each person
to decide what they would like:
feature a person less,
or never feature it again.
It might feel evident
in hindsight.
However, it happens
to all of us.
When we get too close
to our products,
we develop oversights and fail
at meeting people's needs.
But empathizing with people
can help us course correct
when we didn't get things
right from the first try.
Lastly, even details
like glyphs and icons
can have an impact on people.
During the final phases
of development,
we observed that
the thumbs down icon
could project a feeling
of disliking the person.
This might be the case
in some situations
but not for others,
like when a loved one
has passed away.
So we decided to use
a more neutral glyph instead.
So, we just saw through
the example of photo Memories
that launching a product
is not an end,
it is a new beginning
in your design and
development journey.
By having inclusion in mind,
you will continue to make your
experience better for everyone.
Remember to first,
look at reviews and feedback
people using your app or game
left on the Internet,
and go the extra mile
to seek feedback from people
with experiences different
from yours and your friends.
Second, empathize
and put yourself
in other people's shoes
by using the many techniques
at your disposal
like brainstorming,
working with experts,
and individual interviews.
And finally,
address the feedback
even when it’s not your own
experience with the product.
And remember that sharing back
solutions for validation
can help ensure
the experience has actually made
a more positive impact.
Now back to Caroline.
Caroline: We hope
the diversity axes
and the examples we have
shown you today are useful
as you tailor an inclusive
design and development process
that fits your company
and context.
To conclude,
inclusion is a journey.
Yes, the journey
is sometimes hard,
but we love solving
hard problems, right?
Difficulties should only
drive us to try harder
to make our apps and games
more inclusive.
Inclusive design and development
stimulates new,
creative solutions.
Inclusion does not deliver
subpar experiences,
but instead opens up
opportunities
in areas we may have never
considered,
and offers productive
constraints to narrow our scope
and design with more intention.
Empowered diverse teams can
deliver more inclusive products.
Diverse representation
does not guarantee
inclusivity will come naturally.
Instead, when people are invited
to share their perspectives,
and when perspectives together
impact decisions,
products can be more inclusive.
Finally, inclusion must be
infused into the entire design
and development process --
into empathizing, ideation,
designing, development,
testing, release, and beyond.
The examples we shared
demonstrate that inclusion
is as much of a process as
design and development are,
and the resulting
features are better
because of the attention
given to inclusion.
Listening to the lived
experiences of people
will help you to understand
the impact of your app or game,
and to release both innovative
and respectful products
in response.
Keep the diversity axes
and their intersections in mind
as you choose
who to focus on.
We can practice empathy
and know that inclusive design
is the right thing to do,
but it’s time to just call this
"good design."
We can authentically connect
with our audiences
and learn new perspectives.
We can handle feedback
with grace
and design with them,
rather than for them.
Let this be day one
if you haven’t started
this journey yet.
You just have to start somewhere
and try to do
a little more everyday,
which helps it become habit
and then the new normal.
Be sure to check out
“The practice
of inclusive design”
to learn methods
for designing content
so that your user interface,
language, imagery,
and marketing materials
support the broadest possible
range of people.
♪