[percussive music]
[Selina] Hello, everyone!
Welcome to our WWDC21 session,
"Add support for Matter
in your smart home app."
I'm Selina
from Home Engineering.
Today, my colleague,
Chris, Sagar, and I
will walk you through
the exciting features
we've added this year
for Matter support.
As mentioned in Monday's
keynote,
Matter is a new standard for
smart home accessories
being developed by Apple
and other industry leaders
to ensure that all smart home
accessories work together
seamlessly moving forward.
Its vision is to democratize
home automation worldwide,
making it possible for people
to begin building smart homes,
and then continue adding
to them for years to come.
The Matter protocol is being
developed
as an open source effort
which leverages proven
technologies, including HomeKit,
ensuring that it will support
the broadest amount
of smart home devices,
and then make it easy
for manufacturers to begin
integrating it
into their products.
Using Matter, smart home
accessory manufacturers
no longer need to support multiple
protocols in parallel,
truly simplifying
the development effort
of making a product and supporting it
on an ongoing basis.
It also gives app
developers an opportunity
to focus on developing
the best app experience
for their customers,
without the burden
to create and then maintain
proprietary protocols.
By creating such a unified
protocol for accessories,
customers can easily enjoy
the conveniences of a smart home
and then confidently
bring products into their homes,
knowing they will
all work together.
It will enable more
accessories for people
to choose from in stores,
and then builders everywhere
will be able to install them
as standard into homes.
Motivated by these,
we would love our developers
to be able
to use Matter the soonest
in your accessory
and app development.
We're glad to let you know that
the support for Matter is coming
in iOS, iPadOS, and in tvOS
15 as a developer preview.
There are many great
features that we would
like to introduce to you today.
First and then foremost,
let's talk about how
you can integrate with Matter
accessories via HomeKit.
Today, an accessory implementing
the HomeKit Accessory Protocol
integrates with Apple Home
via the HomeKit framework.
Over the years,
we have built great features
on top of HomeKit that
provides full control
and then management
of HAP accessories.
When we look at integrating
Matter accessories
with Apple Home, we naturally
came to the conclusion that we
could expand the responsibility
of the HomeKit framework
to support Matter as
a parallel protocol.
Architecturally, this means that
a HomeKit calls into
the open source Matter
implementation,
as known as CHIP framework,
in order to communicate
with Matter accessories.
For your context, the earlier
name for the Matter project
was Connected Home over IP,
or, in short, CHIP.
That's why,
throughout today's talk,
you will still see
the reference of CHIP,
both in the open source
project and our APIs.
We expect to have updated naming
for the APIs in a later release.
Back to our main topic,
the encapsulation provided
by HomeKit allows all existing
Apple Home features to begin
working with Matter accessories
seamlessly and immediately.
For example, setting up a Matter
accessory using identical
flows to HAP accessory setup,
controlling Matter accessories
in Control Center
with just one swipe down,
and the great
hands-free integration
with Siri for Matter
accessory status
and then control across
all your Apple devices.
But HomeKit's responsibility
isn't just to support
first-party features.
In fact, since day 1, we
designed HomeKit with the vision
that app developers should
be able to leverage HomeKit
to build creative and then
delightful smart home apps
for their customers,
without the burden
to implement communication
protocols with accessories.
This continues to be true
with Matter accessories.
Keep using existing APIs
as you've been using in HomeKit.
They will all just start
working with Matter accessories,
no code change needed.
Let's take accessory setup
as an example.
This code
shows how you could call
the addAndSetupAccessories API
in your HomeKit app today.
With iOS 15 developer preview,
the QR code scanner you invoke
by this API will not only work
for HAP QR codes,
but also start
recognizing Matter QR codes,
providing your customers
a familiar
and a consistent experience
for accessory setup.
For a bit of fun, those of you
who have been paying
close attention to this year's
Swift updates know that there's
a shift underway in the world
of Swift concurrency.
We are glad to let you know
that the same APIs
you are used to can now be
invoked via the new
Swift async/await paradigm,
as well.
Besides setup,
with iOS 15 developer preview,
you will also be able to use
existing HomeKit APIs
to read and write Matter
accessory states.
Moreover, you will
automatically get remote access
and timely notifications
for Matter accessories,
and then be able to add and edit
Matter accessories
using scene and automation APIs,
all in the same way as what you
do with HAP accessories.
Let's also take a sneak
peak into the future.
As Matter project continues
to develop, we expect it
to provide support for more
and more accessory categories.
We will continue integrating
these new Matter accessory
categories into HomeKit,
making it effortless for our
developers to use them.
Secondly, HAP, as a protocol,
supports custom characteristics.
It allows manufacturers to build
creative custom features
with their accessories
and access them through HomeKit.
Matter, as a protocol,
supports custom features, too.
So, we'd like to connect
the dots here and then
provide you access to Matter
custom features
via HomeKit framework.
This feature will be coming
in the later release,
so stay tuned, and let us
know if you have early thoughts.
In short,
we are committed
to seamlessly integrating Matter
with HomeKit.
Whether you are
an accessory developer,
a HomeKit app developer,
or a HomeKit customer,
rest easy,
as Matter "Just Works."
When you use HomeKit
to integrate
with Matter accessories,
you get features like
secured remote control
and automations for free,
thanks to the power
and intelligence
of Apple smart home hubs,
such as HomePod and Apple TV.
But if you also have
a need to help your customers
to connect Matter accessories
with other smart home hubs
in your homes,
we are making it easy for you
to do so from your iOS app,
as well.
Next, I'm going to pass to Chris
to tell you more about it.
[Chris] Thank you, Selina.
For this year's developer
preview,
we are building a new, yet
conceptually familiar setup API
that enables you to establish
a direct connection
between a Matter accessory
and your home hubs.
Let's start by exploring
the user experience.
As you can see here,
this flow strongly resembles
how we set up
both Apple products
and HomeKit accessories today.
We know our customers are
familiar with this flow,
we know they love it,
and we want you
to benefit from it, too.
It is important to note here
that while this is system UI,
the homes and rooms
the user selects from
are vended from your app.
Your app is responsible for
completing required operations
and providing
requested information
to set up via a new
app extension type.
Let's unpack this
for you step by step.
Before beginning setup, your app
creates a topology object
representing
the homes it manages.
It then passes this topology
object to a new setup API.
At this point,
setup is launched and ready
to scan a Matter QR code.
Here's a code example
for invocation.
As you can see, this API
is conceptually very similar
to the existing HomeKit APIs
for accessory setup.
The major
difference is the addition
of the HMCHIPServiceTopology
object,
which is used to inform setup of
the homes your app manages.
When the user scans a Matter
QR code with the scanner,
setup will automatically
progress to a Detected card
that shows the category
of accessory detected.
The user is now presented
with the option of adding
the accessory to your app,
in this example, Autohome.
Once the user has elected
to connect the accessory
to your home hub,
they may need to specify
which specific home to add to.
We present this screen
in the event you initiated setup
with a topology consisting
of more than one home.
If your topology consisted
of only a single home,
this card is skipped, as the
user's intent is already known.
Once the user selects a home,
iOS sends a request to your
extension asking it
to pair with the scanned
accessory's Matter payload.
Your extension responds to this
request via it's principle
HMCHIPServiceRequestHandler
subclass.
When called, use CHIP framework
APIs to create
a secure pairing
between the Matter accessory
and your home hub.
Next, iOS will request
a list of rooms
from your extension that
corresponds
to the selected home.
These rooms are presented
in UI for user selection.
The code to respond to this
request in your extension
is straightforward.
Just like the pair request,
it revolves
around your extension's
principle
HMCHIPServiceRequestHandler
subclass.
Simply implement this
function and return
the corresponding rooms that
match the user's selected home.
Once the user has
selected a name and room
for their accessory,
we provide that information
to your extension and ask it
to configure the accessory.
Just like the other request
types, your extension
will respond to the
configuration request
by using CHIP
framework APIs
to directly
configure the accessory.
Finally, after the accessory is
fully configured for your app,
the user will also be offered
with the opportunity
to use the Apple Home app,
Control Center, and Siri
to control this accessory.
Collected in its entirety
here again is the code
we expect
your extension to implement.
Three simple functions:
room request,
pair accessory request,
and accessory configuration
request.
Once you have subclassed
HMCHIPServiceRequestHandler
and overridden these methods,
the rest of the setup experience
is essentially free from
a developer perspective.
Things like UI presentation,
transitions between steps,
error handling, etc.,
are all handled for you.
This greatly reduces
the amount of code
you need to write,
while simultaneously
providing your users a truly
first-class experience.
So far, we have talked about
how you can use existing
HomeKit APIs to integrate
with Matter accessories,
as well as a new API
if you need to connect
Matter accessories
with another smart home hub.
If you're a Matter
accessory developer,
you will also need to get
familiar with the protocol
itself for the purposes
of firmware development.
So next, my colleague, Sagar,
will take us
on a tour of the Matter
protocol and show you
the similarities
between Matter and HAP.
[Sagar] Thanks, Chris.
Let's start with the Matter
data model.
Every Matter accessory
exposes its capabilities
via the Matter data model.
We can individually
address these capabilities
starting
from the top with endpoints.
Endpoints can be thought
of as logically separate
features of an accessory.
Most accessories will
only have a couple of these:
one for information,
like name, vendor,
and model; and the other for
the primary function
of the accessory,
for example, a light.
Each endpoint can have
multiple clusters within it.
Each cluster represents
a specific capability
of that endpoint.
For our light example,
its light endpoint
might have
clusters for brightness,
color, and power control.
For those
of us familiar with HomeKit,
clusters can be thought of as
equivalent to HomeKit services.
Next up, we look at what
a cluster has within it.
A cluster can have one
or more attributes.
Each attribute represents
some state of the accessory.
For our light example,
the brightness cluster
on the light will have
an attribute that lets us
read and control
the brightness of the light.
Again, Matter's attributes
can be thought of
as equivalent
to HomeKit characteristics.
Finally, here you can see that
each attribute may support a set
of actions ranging from reading,
writing, and reporting.
In our light example,
we might want reporting enabled
on the on-off cluster
to receive notifications from
the accessory every time
the light turns on or off.
Matter usually offers a broad
selection of APIs to configure
and interact with each attribute
based on its function.
These concepts we just
talked about are being
implemented in the open
source CHIP framework,
with Apple being one
of the key contributors.
As Selina mentioned earlier,
CHIP has been renamed to Matter,
but the framework
and the code will be updated
in a future release.
A fully-certified version
of CHIP framework
will be
distributed in iOS,
which enables HomeKit
integration
with Matter accessories,
and also provides access
to open source APIs
if you need to use them
in your app.
Let's take a look at
an example of using
CHIP framework to interact
with a light accessory.
This exercises
the core concepts
of the Matter data model
we just went over.
We start off by accessing
the shared CHIPController.
This controller is our
primary handle to Matter.
Next, we get a handle
to the light by using
the device ID that we assigned
to it during pairing.
Then, we initialize a handle
to the on-off cluster
on the light endpoint.
And now,
with this on-off cluster,
we can perform reads and writes
on the on-off attribute.
First, we request to toggle
the on-off attribute,
which just toggles
the state of the light.
Then, we request to read the
state of the on-off attribute.
The accessory then sends us
a response with the status
of the attribute, which we can
use to update our application.
So, that's a quick look
into CHIP framework.
Before we
conclude our session today,
we'd like to go over a new
concept introduced in Matter
and show some new features
we've introduced
in the Home app
that leverage it.
As you may already know,
the Matter protocol
allows multiple admins
to connect
to an accessory at
the same time.
This is a great feature for
providing customers choices,
but it also poses challenges
to us
when it comes
to accessory management.
Let's take a look at how
the Home app incorporates this.
The Home app can now
present a list of all
the connected admins
on an accessory under this
new Connected Services
section.
Users are also given the option
to manage connected admins.
And finally,
users have the option
to turn on
pairing mode again to allow
a new admin to connect
with the accessory.
Our goal here is simple:
we want to ensure that
our customers have
the freedom to choose
what's best for them,
and also the confidence to tell
how their smart home
accessories are being managed.
So, Matter support will first be
available in the iOS, iPadOS,
and tvOS 15 developer preview,
and a developer profile must
be installed
on these
platforms to enable it.
You will also need a home
hub to control
Matter accessories via HomeKit.
While we expect Matter
to publish qualified
vendor IDs and certified product
IDs once they become
available for the market,
we will provide a list
of sample vendor IDs
and product IDs
with the developer preview to
facilitate your development.
These IDs are pre-configured
to represent Matter
accessory categories
that are already supported
in the developer preview.
As always,
you can find more information
about our APIs
on developer.apple.com.
And more information about
the Matter open source APIs
and Matter accessory definitions
can be found on Github.
So, in conclusion,
we are bringing seamless
Matter support via HomeKit for
accessory developers,
HomeKit apps,
and HomeKit users.
There will be a new setup API
in an upcoming seed
for developers who need
to connect Matter accessories
with other smart home hubs.
And all of this
will be available
starting with the iOS, iPadOS,
and tvOS 15 developer preview.
Thank you for watching,
and from my team and I, goodbye.
[percussive music]