[music]
- Hi! Welcome to WWDC.
My name is Anne Hitchcock,
and I'm an engineer
on the Watch Frameworks team.
I'm excited to be here today
to talk about data transfer
strategies on Apple Watch.
Since its introduction,
Apple Watch has become
increasingly independent.
Series 3 was the first
Apple Watch available
with cellular capability.
Independent Watch Apps
in watchOS 6
gave you
the ability to write apps
that didn't require
an iOS companion
and could be purchased
from the App Store
on your customers' Watches.
With the introduction of
Family Setup in watchOS 7,
your customers have
more independence than ever,
without having
a companion iPhone.
But these new
capabilities present us,
as developers,
new challenges in the way
we think about communicating
with our Watch apps.
Fortunately,
we have lots of great options.
Today we're going
to talk about those options
and how we pick
the right one for the job.
I'm going to give you
an overview of tools
we have for data communication
in Watch apps
and discuss how to evaluate
which one will be
the right choice for your task.
We can broadly group the tools
into a few categories.
iCloud allows us to
share with all our devices
and gives us server storage.
We can use this in our apps
using Keychain
with iCloud Synchronization
and CoreData with CloudKit.
If we need to transfer data
between paired devices,
we can use Watch Connectivity.
To communicate
directly with servers,
we can use
URL sessions or sockets.
But first, we'll talk about
the questions you can ask
to pick the right one.
When I think about
how I'm going to communicate
from my Watch app,
I think about a few things.
What kind of data is it?
And where is the data now,
and where do I need it to be?
Is the interaction reliant
on a companion iOS app?
Do I want to support
Family Setup?
And when does the data
need to be at its destination?
Can it wait to let the system
optimize performance
and battery usage
for my customer?
How frequently is
the data going to change?
Based on my answers
to these questions,
I can start
going through my toolbox
to evaluate how to craft
the right solution
for my data transfer task.
Let's look at what capabilities
we get from the Keychain
with iCloud Synchronization.
Keychain provides secure
storage for passwords,
keys, and other
sensitive credentials.
And with iCloud
Keychain Synchronization,
introduced in watchOS 6.2,
these keychain items can be
synchronized
to all of a person's devices.
There are two ways
you can benefit
from iCloud Synchronization
in your app:
by using Password autofill with
Associated Domains
and Shared Keychain items.
Password autofill allows you
to use Keychain synchronization
with very little code.
First, add the
Associated Domains capability
to your target.
For your Watch app,
add the capability to the
WatchKit Extension Target.
Add a webcredentials entry
with your domain name.
Add the
apple-app-site-association file
to your web server.
The file must be accessible
via HTTPS without redirects.
The file is JSON format
with no file extension,
and it should be placed in the
./well-known directory
on your server.
Check out
the documentation online
for "Supporting Associated
Domains" for complete details.
Add text content types
to your text fields
and secure fields.
Your options for autofill are
username, email address,
password, and new password.
For new passwords,
the system will prompt the
person to save,
and a record will be
added or updated
in the Keychain for your site.
AutoFill suggestions
have been available
since watchOS 6.2
and are even better
with the new text-editing
experience in watchOS 8.
For more information
about using password autofill,
check out the
"Autofill everywhere" session
in the Developer app or online.
Another way you can share data
using Keychain synchronization
is by sharing Keychain items
among your apps.
As we discussed,
the Keychain is secure storage
for sensitive data,
like passwords, keys,
and credentials.
You can also store
other small bits of shared data
in the Keychain,
such as a person's preference
for a startup screen,
as long as the information
isn't changing frequently.
The data stored in the Keychain
will be synchronized
to all of the person's devices.
Let's look at how
we can store and retrieve
an OAuth 2 token in the Keychain,
and share that
with a group of our apps.
First, we need to add
the Keychain Sharing
or App Groups capability,
all the apps we want to share
these keychain items.
This is required
to share the items,
and helps ensure
the security and privacy
of your customers' information
by preventing access
by other apps.
For your Watch app,
add the capability
to your Watch Extension target.
In this example,
I'm going to add
the Keychain Sharing capability
and add my app
to a Keychain Group.
All of my apps
that are going to share
the Keychain items
need to also share this group.
Now, let's look at the code
to store an OAuth 2 token
in the Keychain.
To store a token,
we'll update the item
if it exists,
and add it if it doesn't.
I've created
an OAuth 2 token struct
to contain the token data,
like the token string,
expiration, and refresh token.
I made the token struct
conform to codable
to make it easy
to store and retrieve.
We create a query dictionary.
This is the set of attributes
that match an existing item
if we already have one saved
for this server and account.
Note the synchronizable
attribute here
that is set to "true."
It's important that we include
this attribute in our query
to indicate that we want
our item to synchronize
to all of our customer's
devices.
We'll encode the token as data,
and set that Data as the value
for our Keychain item
in the attributes dictionary.
Then, update the item
in the Keychain
with the query and attributes.
We always need
to check the result code
returned from the Keychain API.
We'll first check to see
if the Keychain said
that the item was not found.
If so, we'll call
another function we wrote
to add it to the Keychain.
We'll look at that in a moment.
Otherwise, we'll make sure
there was no error.
To do that,
we check for the success result.
If the update function
returned success,
then our token was
updated in the Keychain.
Now, let's look at
the add function.
To add the token
to the Keychain,
we'll set up a dictionary
with all the attributes.
This includes the attributes
we used to find
an existing item,
plus the token data.
Then, we'll call
the Keychain API's
add function
with the attributes.
And check the return code
to make sure it succeeded.
To retrieve the token
information from the Keychain,
we'll set up a query dictionary
to find the item we want.
We'll include the same set
of keys and values we included
to find the item before
in the update function.
Plus, we include some attributes
to tell the Keychain API
whether we want
the item attributes returned
(we don't)
and whether we want
the item data returned
(we do).
The Keychain
"copy matching" function
searches using our query
and populates the reference
we provided as "item."
Before we try to access
the retrieved item,
we'll check the return code
to ensure it was found.
Then, as always,
we check the return code
for success.
Get the dictionary
that was copied for the item,
get the token data we requested
from the dictionary,
and decode the data
as our OAuth 2 token type.
And now, we've successfully
saved, updated,
and retrieved an OAuth 2 token
to the Keychain,
and it's shared with all the
apps
in our Keychain Sharing Group.
There's one more
Keychain storage function
I want to share with you.
Just like anywhere
that you store something
on your customers' devices,
you should remove it
when you're done with it.
We'll set up our query
with our now-familiar attributes
to search.
Call the Keychain API's
delete function with our query.
And, as always,
check for success.
In the case of delete,
not found is successful.
Now, we finish cleaning up
after we're done with the data.
Keychain services with
iCloud Keychain synchronization
are a great way for your app
to share small pieces of data
that don't change frequently,
and that data
will be synchronized
to all of a person's devices.
Use Associated Domains
to easily add
password autofill
functionality to your app.
You can also
store and retrieve values
directly to the Keychain
and share them
with your other apps
using Keychain Sharing
or App Groups.
iCloud Keychain Synchronization
doesn't rely on having
an iOS companion app,
and it supports Family Setup.
The items
are synchronized when possible
based on
network availability, battery,
and other system conditions.
Be aware that customers
can disable
iCloud Keychain synchronization
and that it isn't available
in all regions.
CoreData with CloudKit
synchronizes your local database
to all of your customer's
other devices
that share your app's
CloudKit container.
CoreData integration
with SwiftUI
simplifies accessing
and displaying data
from your database
in your Watch application.
You can quickly
get too much data
on a Watch this way
if you're developing
a multi-platform application.
Think carefully
about what information your
customer
really needs on their Watch.
Consider
using multiple configurations
in your Core Data model
to segment data that makes sense
to have in your Watch app
from data
that is appropriate for your app
running on a device
with more storage
and battery capacity.
CloudKit and Core Data
are powerful tools.
The integration
of Core Data with SwiftUI
makes it easier to use
Core Data features in your apps.
You can provide
the managed object context"
to your Views
with the environment value,
and use the fetch request
property wrapper
to get results
from your database.
Those results can be used
in SwiftUI Lists
and other views.
Core Data with CloudKit
provides us
with a way to share
structured data
that can be synchronized
to all of a person's devices
and backed up on iCloud.
It doesn't rely on having
a companion iPhone app
and does support Family Setup.
Synchronization
of Core Data changes
happens based on
network availability
and system conditions.
Don't expect it
to be instantaneous,
but CloudKit will handle
optimizing performance
of this synchronization
for your app.
To learn more about using
Core Data with CloudKit
in your app, check out
"Build apps that share data
through CloudKit and Core Data"
and "Bring Core Data concurrency
to Swift and SwiftUI"
in the Developer app or online.
You might already be familiar
with Watch Connectivity,
and you might
have used it before.
But I'd like
to give you more details
and some best practices
to help you be successful.
Watch Connectivity
allows you to send data
between your Watch app
and its companion iPhone app
when both devices
are within Bluetooth range
or on the same Wi-Fi network.
It's best used for optimizing
your customer's experience
when they have both your phone
and Watch apps installed,
and for sharing data that is
only available on one device.
For example, if someone
has launched your iPhone app
and has downloaded
the latest data,
you can share that data
with your Watch app
to keep
your complications current
and allow your Watch app
to start
with that same data
the next time it launches.
This will feel more responsive
for your customers
and minimizes
the duplicate data downloads
your apps need to do.
Watch Connectivity
has a diverse set of features,
so it's helpful to know
what's available
and when to use each one.
But first,
I want to share a few tips
to help you succeed
if you decide
that Watch Connectivity
is the right tool for your task.
Since Watch Connectivity
is a tool to communicate
between two devices,
it's going to require us to know
about a few preconditions
and handle some errors.
These are some things
you can do to ensure
your Watch Connectivity
communication works smoothly.
Activate your
watch connectivity session
as early in your app
life cycle as possible,
preferably when
your app finishes launching
in your app
or extension delegate.
This makes your app
available to receive information
from its counterpart app
as soon as possible.
Understand reachability.
None of the background
communication
requires your counterpart app
to be reachable
when you send data.
But interactive messaging
does have reachability
requirements,
and we'll discuss them then.
It will save you time
to understand them.
All of the watch connectivity
session delegate functions
are called
on a non-main serial queue.
If you need to do
any work from these functions
to update your user interface,
make sure you do that
on the main queue.
Now, let's talk about
the different
Watch Connectivity features
and when to use each one.
The application context
is a single property
list dictionary
that is sent
to the counterpart app
in the background,
with the goal of being available
when the app wakes up.
If you update
the application context
before the previous
dictionary is sent,
it is replaced by the new value.
Application context
is useful for keeping content
up to date
on the counterpart app
when you have new data,
and for data
that may update frequently.
User info transfer
also sends
a property list dictionary
to the counterpart app
in the background,
but it's a little different
than application context.
Instead of being
a single dictionary
that is replaced
each time you update it,
each user info
dictionary transfer
is queued and delivered
in the order
that you enqueued it.
You can also access the queue
to cancel a transfer.
File transfer is similar
to user info transfer,
and once you've done one,
the other will feel familiar.
Files are queued to be sent
to the counterpart app,
and sent when power
and other conditions permit.
You can access the queue
to cancel a transfer.
The files are placed
in the document inbox
for the receiving app
when they are transferred.
Each file will be deleted
from the inbox when you return
from the did receive file callback
in your session delegate.
Make sure you move the file
or otherwise quickly process it
before you return
from this method.
One helpful thing
to remember about this:
since this callback is called
on a non-main serial queue,
if you call an async method
to process the file
from the inbox,
you will most likely
run into a problem
because the file will be gone.
The timing of file transfers
is based on system conditions,
and, of course,
larger files may take
longer to transfer.
transferCurrentComplicationUserInfo(_:)
is a special case of the
user info transfer functionality
to send complication-related
data to the Watch.
It's transferred
as soon as possible,
ahead of other user info
transfers,
as long as you have complication
transfers
remaining in your budget.
This immediate transfer
allows you to keep your active
complications current
for your customers when you have
updated data from your phone.
You can check
your remaining budget,
and if you transfer
current complication info
with no remaining budget,
it will still be sent.
It will just use the
normal user info transfer queue.
You can use sendMessage
to send data
to your counterpart app
and get a reply.
This is for
interactive messaging
when your counterpart app
is reachable.
Whether you're sending
a dictionary or data,
keep your messages small.
We also recommend that you
opt to include a reply handler
for your sendMessage calls.
A short reply
allows you to verify
that the counterpart app
did receive the message
and that the data was correct.
When you include
that reply handler
on your sendMessage,
also make sure you implement
the version of the
did receive message
or did receive data
delegate callback function
in the counterpart app
that includes a reply handler.
Otherwise, you'll get an error
when you send the message.
Now that we've heard
about sendMessage,
let's revisit
the concept of reachability.
Both of your apps
need to be reachable
to send messages.
You can check
the isReachable property
on the
Watch Connectivity session
to determine if your
counterpart app is reachable
for live,
non-background messaging.
But what does it mean
to be reachable?
Both devices need to be
within range of each other
via Bluetooth
or on the same Wi-Fi network.
For the WatchKit Extension
to be reachable,
it must be either
running in the foreground
or running in the background
with a high priority,
as it does when performing
long-running
background sessions.
The iOS app doesn't have
this foreground requirement.
If you send a message
from your Watch app
to your iOS app,
and your iOS app
is not in the foreground,
your iOS app will be activated
in the background
to receive the message.
This means that your iOS app
is reachable
from your Watch Extension
far more of the time
than vice versa.
Watch Connectivity is a good way
to provide your customers
with an experience
that feels timely,
responsive, and intuitive
when they have installed both
your iPhone and Watch apps.
Since Watch Connectivity
is specifically communicating
between a phone
and a paired Watch,
don't use it to support apps
for Family Setup.
Data transfer is dependent
on the availability
of the companion device
via Bluetooth or Wi-Fi.
Real-time communication
using sendMessage
requires the counterpart
to be reachable.
Remember that
your counterpart app
won't be reachable a
lot of the time,
especially when
you're trying to communicate
to your Watch app.
Background transfers
aren't delivered immediately.
Think of them
like posting a letter:
you drop it in the box,
but you're not sure exactly
when it's going to be there.
For more information
about Watch Connectivity,
check out
"Introducing Watch Connectivity"
in the Developer app or online.
Now, we're going to talk about
a couple of ways
to communicate
directly with servers.
For most use cases,
the best option is URL sessions.
Depending on the interaction
and type of data,
you might be able to defer
communication
or might need
to do it right away.
So, we have different
configurations for URL sessions
to allow them to be run
in the background or foreground.
Let's look at when you should
use each of these options.
You should use background
sessions wherever possible.
This might not be
our first instinct
as developers,
where we might want
to just go ahead
and get or send data right away.
But really think about it.
Foreground sessions
need to complete
while your app
is in the foreground
or front-most,
and for all
but the shortest tasks,
this isn't enough time.
Think about
your customers' experience
if their communication
task fails.
So, please be considerate
of your customers
and carefully evaluate
each communication task
and ask, "Can I do this
in the background?"
Background URL sessions
are the right choice
for any time communication
can be delayed
and for large data transfers.
You can also send
a push notification
to your app to indicate
that new data is available
and initiate
a background update.
The exact timing of
your background transfer
will depend
on system conditions.
Let's walk through an example
of sending some data
to a server in the background.
For example,
if I have some settings for my
application
that I want to store
through my web server,
when my customer saves those,
I can save them on the Watch
and then send them to the server
in the background.
To do that, I've made
a background URL session class
to handle the work
of the server communication.
Our URL session will
have a background configuration
with a unique identifier
we can use to find it later.
Set the sends launch events
property to true
to indicate that the session
should launch your app
in the background
when tasks on your session
need to be handled.
Note that if you're transferring
a large amount of data,
you should set the
isDiscretionary property
of the URL session configuration
to true
to let the system
schedule the transfer
at an optimal time for
the device for best performance.
In this case,
you should also
let your customers know
that their downloads might not
happen
until they're connected
to Wi-Fi and power.
When we're ready
to send the data,
we need to enqueue the transfer
to schedule
the background session.
We'll create and configure
a URL request
with the contents for our
Settings update to our server.
Then, we'll create a task
for our request on the session.
In this simplified example,
I'm only adding one task
to my session,
but you can add
multiple requests
to your session for efficiency.
Set the earliestBeginDate
to start the download later.
Note that the system
will determine the actual time
our task starts
based on background budget,
network, and system conditions.
Your app can receive
up to four background
refresh tasks per hour,
if you have a complication
on the active watch face,
so schedule your tasks
at least 15 minutes apart
to prevent them from
being delayed by the system.
I'm holding on to this session
in a list
of in-progress sessions.
This will become
important later,
when the system lets me know
that my URL request
has completed.
Calling "resume" on the task
actually starts it,
so it's important
that you call this.
Finally,
I set my status to queued
in case there are
observers for the session.
The system will notify our app
when our background request
has been processed
using a background task sent
to our Extension Delegate.
In order for us
to handle that task,
we need to create
a class that conforms
to WK extension delegate
and implement the
handle(_ backgroundTasks:) function.
For Background URL
Session Refresh tasks,
we'll try to find our session
in our list
of in-progress requests.
If we have it, we'll call
a function on the session
to add
the background refresh task
to the list for the session,
so we can let the system know
we've completed it
as soon as we've finished
processing the data.
I'll show you this in a moment.
If we don't find
the session in our list,
we need to mark
the task as completed.
It is very important that you
always set
your background refresh task
completed
as soon as you're done.
There's one more thing
we need to do
to get
our background task calls:
we need to connect our extension
delegate to our App.
To do this
we're going to use
the WK extension delegate adaptor
property wrapper
with our Extension Delegate
class,
and add a property to our app.
Now, the system will
call our extension delegate
to handle our background tasks.
In our extension delegate,
we called this function
to add our background task
to our existing session.
Add this task
to our list of background tasks
so we can mark it completed
as soon as we're done
processing the URL data.
Now, we've wired up
the whole round trip,
and all we have left
to do is get our data
and let the system know
we're done.
Our URL session
download delegate
will get called when
our request completes.
Process the data received in
the file from the download task.
It's important that
you either move this item
into a directory accessible
to your app
or quickly process
the data from the file.
When this task completes,
the downloaded
file will be deleted.
We're removing this session from
the list of in-process sessions,
since we won't get any more
background tasks for it
from the extension delegate,
and we're setting the status to
completed
in case there are any observers.
Finally, we're setting
our background task completed.
This lets the system know
we've completed
our background processing.
Making sure you do this
isn't just being
a good Watch app citizen.
It prevents the system
from terminating your app
for exceeding
its background limits.
And that's it!
We're all done
sending our settings
in the background and
getting any updates.
Note that in
a full implementation,
you'll want to handle errors
and authentication challenges,
but this gives
you the basic steps.
Use foreground URL sessions
for quick server communication
while a person
is interacting with your app.
A good example of this
is getting
the latest workout list
or the meditation of the day.
Foreground URL sessions
are a less-power-efficient way
to get and send data,
and a two-and-a-half
minute timeout is enforced.
But in practice, you should try
to target foreground sessions
to interactions that are
much quicker than that limit.
URL sessions are the best method
for general purpose
communication
directly with servers.
They don't rely on
a companion iPhone app,
and you can use them with apps
supporting Family Setup.
Use background sessions
for anywhere you can possibly
delay the data transfer,
and always for transferring
larger amounts of data.
To learn more about
URL sessions,
check out "Keep your
complications up to date"
and "Background
execution demystified"
in the Developer app or online.
In addition to URL sessions,
if you're building
a streaming audio app,
sockets are another option
to communicate
directly with servers.
You can use HTTP Live Streaming
or Web Sockets in Watch apps
in the context of your active
streaming audio session.
For more information on
using Sockets, check out
the "Streaming Audio
on watchOS 6" session
in the Developer app or online.
We've covered a lot,
so let's summarize
how we can choose
from among all the options
we've seen.
For small pieces
of sensitive data
that can be synced to
all a person's devices,
choose Keychain with
iCloud Synchronization.
To store databases in iCloud
and share
with all a person's devices,
choose Core Data with CloudKit.
To optimize the experience for
companion iPhone and Watch apps,
or to share data that is
available only on one device
in companion apps,
choose Watch Connectivity.
To communicate
directly with servers,
choose URL sessions.
For streaming audio apps,
you can also use sockets.
To support customers
who are using Family Setup
or to use
cellular data transfer,
make sure you choose Keychain
with iCloud Synchronization,
Core Data with CloudKit,
URL sessions, or sockets.
Think about the type of data,
its source and destination,
and your customer audience
before choosing a solution
to help you pick
the right tool for the job.
And always
test your app on devices,
not connected to the debugger,
before you deploy it
to verify its behavior
in real-world conditions.
Thank you for coming
to learn about
all the great tools
we have for data transfer
in your Watch apps.
We can't wait to see
what you build next.
[music]