[music]
[Tony]
Hello, my name is Tony,
and I'm an engineer
on the Foundation team.
Welcome
to “What’s new in Foundation.”
The Foundation framework
provides base functionality
for all apps and frameworks.
It has plenty of features,
including everything
from file handling to networking
and notifications.
Today I’d like to focus
on something all apps need:
internationalization
and localization.
In this year’s releases,
we have some
of the biggest advancements ever
in this API.
We started at a low level,
rethinking what
an attributed string is in Swift.
We rebuilt our formatters
for Swift, making them faster,
easier to use,
and adding new features.
And finally,
we have a brand new feature
called automatic grammar
agreement.
It dramatically reduces
the number
of localized strings
you need to provide while,
at the same time,
making your code simpler.
Let’s jump right in
to attributed strings.
An attributed string is
a combination of characters,
a set of ranges,
and a dictionary.
Attributed strings allow
you to associate attributes,
which are key-value pairs,
to a specific range of a string.
The most common attributes
are defined by the SDK,
but you can also
create your own.
You’ll often
find attributed strings
in API that supports rich text.
Let’s look at an example.
Here is an app
I’m working on called Caffé.
It’s a simple menu.
I pick the food that I want,
the size, the quantity.
And at the end,
it shows me a receipt
with a list of everything I’ve
ordered.
At the bottom here, I decided
to add a short thank-you note.
This is an attributed string.
Part of the string is in bold
and part is in italics.
The last word has a link
as well.
As you can tell here,
attributes can overlap.
Since the beginning
of Foundation,
we’ve had a reference type
called NSAttributedString.
This year,
we introduce a new struct
AttributedString,
which takes full advantage
of all of the features
that Swift provides us.
First and foremost,
it’s a value type.
It also has the same
character-counting behavior
as Swift String.
As part of our commitment
to making it easy
to write inclusive software,
AttributedString is
now fully localizable.
Finally, it is built with safety
and security in mind.
This includes both compile time
safety by using strong typing
and also safety during
unarchiving using Codable.
Let’s take a brief tour
of what you can do
with the new AttributedString.
We’re going to build
our thank-you message.
First, we create
an attributed string
using a simple initializer.
I want to set an attribute
on this entire string.
That’s as simple
as setting the font property.
In struct AttributedString,
all attributes are available
directly,
and they use the correct types.
This property, for example,
is a SwiftUI Font.
Next, we create another
attributed string.
This one
is a reference to our website,
so we set the link property
to a URL.
Here I’m setting the font
and link on the whole string.
We’ll look at how to change just
part of a string later.
Another useful tool is
an attribute container.
It’s a place you can
hold attributes and values
on their own without the string.
Here, I create a container
and set some attributes on it,
depending
on the importance of my message.
And finally,
I merge those attributes
into both attributed strings.
As I mentioned,
attributed string is
a combination of characters,
ranges, and a dictionary.
The attributed string
itself is not a collection
of any single one
of those things.
Instead, in order to gain access
to these properties,
it has what we call views.
The two most important views
are characters,
which provides access
to the string, and runs,
to the attributes.
These views
are Swift collections,
which means the functions
you are familiar with from types
like Array are available
here too.
Let’s look at another example.
Let’s say our designers told us
to add a little bit
of pizzazz
to our thank-you message
by making all punctuation
a fun orange color.
To do this,
first I need to find
where the punctuation is
in the attributed string.
Like other Swift collections,
attributed string views use
indices,
which are simply a position
for some element
in the collection.
To iterate by index,
I use the standard library
indices function.
Next, I use the function
isPunctuation to check
if this character is one
that we need to change.
Finally, I use another feature
of attributed string, slicing,
to apply an attribute to only
a subrange of the whole string.
The range starts at this index
and continues
until the next index after that,
so one character.
And now the punctuation is
orange.
Let’s look
at another view, runs.
A run is the starting location,
length,
and value
of a particular attribute.
We can start by counting all
the runs in our message.
This will iterate
each contiguous range
of attribute values
in the string.
There are four runs
in this string.
Each run has a value or nil
for each attribute.
The ranges from characters
and runs are interchangeable,
so you can find the string
for an attribute or vice-versa.
Here I use the range
of the attribute in a subscript
for the characters view,
converting the result
into a standalone string.
It’s often most useful
to look at runs by focusing
on a specific attribute.
Here, we use the key path link
to coalesce
for just the link attribute.
Each element of the resulting
collection will give us
the value of the link attribute,
not taking
into account other attributes
which may be set in the string.
If we only look at links,
we have three runs: the first,
where it is not set;
the second,
where it is set to a value;
and the third,
the last period in the sentence,
where it is not set again.
Iterating the runs
gives us a tuple
of the value and the range.
Since the values are type safe,
we can use an API,
like scheme,
which exists on URL,
without casting or worrying
about having the wrong type.
Here I’m checking
that every link
in the attributed string
is https.
Another useful technique
is to look
for a substring
and use that range
to edit the characters
or the attributes.
Let’s say I want to replace
the word "visit'
with something that has
a more throwback vibe.
First, I look for the range
of a substring.
Next, I use that range
to set the attributes
and characters on only
that subrange.
The result
is an attributed string
with six runs, like this.
Next, let’s talk
about localization.
AttributedString is
fully localizable.
We also added localization
support
to NSAttributedString
in Objective-C.
Attributed strings are located
in your app’s strings files,
just like a regular string.
In Swift, we now support
localized formatting of String
and AttributedString
using string interpolation
just like SwiftUI’s text view.
Here’s a simple example.
This function returns
a localized string
which is customized
with a user’s document name.
Instead of using format
specifiers like %@ or %d
and calling a format function,
you can now just
pass the value in directly.
The same approach works
for AttributedString.
Xcode can generate
your strings files
from these new initializers
using the compiler.
To turn it on,
go to your build settings,
look
for the localization settings,
and turn on Use Compiler
to Extract Swift Strings.
You may be wondering how
the localized attributed string
gets its attributes.
I’m excited to tell
you that we’ve added support
for Markdown
to AttributedString.
Here’s an example
of using a localized
attributed string,
right in a SwiftUI Text.
I start off
with just a plain string.
By adding two asterisks
around the text,
I make it strongly emphasized,
which SwiftUI renders as bold.
I can use underscores
to make the text emphasized,
which SwiftUI renders as italic.
We also support links.
This is a great opportunity
for localizers to provide
customized URLs
for different languages.
We also support
other inline styles
like strikethrough
and code voice.
Finally, let’s talk about
archiving attributed strings.
First, we need the ability
to convert to and from
the NSAttributedString
reference type.
Attributed strings can be
part of your data model,
which means we need to be able
to encode and decode them.
Finally, we want a way
to specify custom attributes
in Markdown.
These operations are all related
to each other.
Let’s start by looking
at conversion.
We’ve all written a lot of code
that uses NSAttributedString,
so we’ve made it easy to convert
from the struct
to the class type.
Here’s a view that has
an NSAttributedString property.
To convert, just pass
our struct AttributedString
to the NSAttributedString
initializer.
For attributes that are part
of the SDK,
this is all I need to do.
Now let’s look at encoding
and decoding.
Here is a struct that holds
a receipt from our Caffé app.
Again, I’m using the attributes
provided
by SwiftUI, UIKit, AppKit,
and Foundation.
That means
that AttributedString’s default
Codable implementation is
all I need.
I just add the Codable
conformance to Receipt,
and I’m done.
Let’s go
a bit further and add support
for encoding a custom attribute.
We’ll start by talking
about the attribute itself.
An attribute is two parts:
a key and a value.
The key is a type which conforms
with the new
AttributedStringKey protocol.
That defines what type
of value it requires
and a name for archiving.
This key can also conform
with other protocols
to customize how the value
is encoded or decoded.
Let’s say
we want to define a range
of an attributed string
to have some extra color.
This rainbow effect
comes in three levels:
plain, fun, or extreme.
We’ll use an enum
to represent that value
and set the name to rainbow.
Defining the type and the name
are the only requirements
of this protocol.
Now, let’s say we want to make
this attribute Codable
so that it will be part
of the encoded attributed string.
All I have to do is add
Codable conformance, like this.
Finally, let’s say
we want the rainbow level
to be part
of our localized string.
That means it can be applied
to the right part of the string,
no matter where that is,
in any language.
All we need is one more
protocol conformance to opt in.
When we say that an attribute
is Markdown decodable,
then we can decode it
straight from Markdown
and insert it
into an attributed string.
All that’s required is
that the value is Codable.
Next, let’s take a look
at the custom attribute syntax
for Markdown.
In this first example,
we have a reference to a link.
It uses square brackets
for the link text
and parentheses
for the link destination, a URL.
In this second example,
we have a reference to an image.
It starts
with an exclamation point,
then uses square brackets
for the image description
and parentheses
for the image source.
These first two examples
are common in Markdown.
The third example
shows our syntax
for custom attributes.
It starts with a caret,
then uses square brackets
for the text, and parentheses
for its attributes.
The attributes are represented
with JSON 5.
JSON 5 is compatible with JSON
and allows for unquoted keys,
comments,
and a few other features.
It’s a good match
for a human-friendly string
like this one.
We’ve also added JSON 5 support
to our other JSON API
in Foundation.
Because custom attributes
use JSON, anything that can
be decoded with JSONDecoder
is automatically compatible
with the new
custom Markdown syntax.
Here we have a single attribute,
two attributes,
one string and one number,
and a single attribute
with multiple properties.
There is just one additional
piece here, which is how
we connect these names
in Markdown to a Swift type.
That piece is called
an attribute scope.
Scopes are a group
of attribute keys.
Scopes are useful when decoding
from JSON or Markdown,
because they tell us
which attributes we expect
to find, their names,
and how to decode them.
We define one scope each
for Foundation,
UIKit, AppKit, and SwiftUI.
You can define a scope
of your own attributes as well.
Let’s define a scope
for our Caffé App.
We’ll nest the scope
inside AttributeScopes
and conform it
to the AttributeScope protocol.
Then all we need
to do is list the attributes
inside our scope with “let.”
So far, we have just
our rainbow attribute.
Next, we’ll include the SwiftUI
scope inside of ours.
That allows
all of those attributes
in addition to our own.
Scopes nest recursively,
so this also includes
Foundation attributes.
It’s useful to define a property
for our new scope.
That allows us to use
a key path syntax
in functions which take
the scope as an argument.
Finally,
we can now load our localized
and colorful attributed string
from custom Markdown.
You’ll also find scope-taking
functions for archiving
and conversion to
and from NSAttributedString.
This allows customization
of behavior at every step.
Here’s the first screen
of the Caffé app again,
where you can see our custom
rainbow attribute in the title.
After the localized string
is converted from Markdown
into an attributed string,
the app finds the attribute
and applies a fun effect to just
that range of the string.
Because the attribute comes
from our localized strings file,
this works correctly
for all languages
that Caffé supports,
like Spanish.
We’re just getting started,
though.
We also have
a totally new Formatter API.
Formatters are another
long-time Foundation feature.
They are responsible
for taking data,
like numbers, dates, times,
and more and converting it
into a localized
and user-presentable string.
Formatters are backed by quite
a bit of configuration data,
so it’s a common pattern
to cache and reuse them.
However, apps are composed
of many distinct pieces of code.
It may not always make
sense to share a formatter
between all of them.
Also, because of the large
variety of ways that people
read dates and times,
plus our desire as app authors
to present this data in a way
that fits our design,
there are a lot of opportunities
for edge cases.
This year, we improved both
performance and usability
by rethinking our Formatter API
from the ground up.
In short, our new APIs focus
on the format.
Let’s take a look at this code
from the Earthquakes sample app,
where we can see
the caching pattern in action.
It has a two-step process.
First, create
and configure a formatter.
Next, give the formatter
our date and get a string.
How could it be simpler?
Well, let’s start
by removing the requirement
to create
our own date formatter.
It was really easy to forget
that this needed to be cached,
which would lead to re-creating
the same formatter
for every cell in the table.
Next, the formatting step.
Instead of passing our date
through the formatter,
let’s just use the date itself.
Now it’s just one line of code.
You specify the format you want,
and that’s it.
Let’s talk more
about this number format.
It’s not a lot of code,
but it’s hiding some complexity
and has a few pitfalls
to be aware of.
If the argument is not
a floating point number,
you’ll get entirely
the wrong output here.
Readers have to be aware
of a special case syntax
for formatting
floating point numbers,
along with a set of modifiers
that are just string constants.
We think this code is easier
to understand,
maintain, and read.
It uses regular Swift functions
to specify
exactly how we want our number
to be formatted.
You also get autocompletion
and type safety.
We’ve applied this new approach
to all ten formatters
in Foundation.
We’ve cleaned up
and simplified the interfaces,
made changes
to help avoid common pitfalls,
and added a bunch
of new features along the way.
Let’s take a look in detail
at two
of the most popular
formatted types:
dates and numbers.
Date formatting is
about using a calendar
and time zone to convert
an absolute point in time
into something a human
understands as a date.
And even more than that,
it takes into account
all of the preferences
that humans have
about how they like
their own dates to look.
We call those preferences
locales.
Let’s take a look
at the tiny amount of code
you need in order
to format a date.
First, I’ll get the current
point in time by using Date.now.
Next,
I call the formatted function.
That's it.
Of course,
as we just saw in our example,
date formatting is something
that has a lot of options.
So let’s expand this out a bit.
The formatted function can
be configured
to show only the date
or only the time.
Both of those arguments have
several options to pick from.
An important goal
for this new formatting API is
to provide
as much compile time help
as possible
in creating correct formats.
Formatting using magic
string values is notorious
for creating pitfalls,
where the format looks correct
under normal circumstances
but produces entirely
the wrong value in edge cases,
like at the end of the year.
Here again is
our default format.
This is a short version
of asking
for the date and time style,
like this.
For both the no-argument
and simple style versions,
we pick a default format
for you.
However, if you want
to really customize the date,
you just go from here and add
the fields you care about.
In this example,
I build up a format
by appending fields
to the style.
I want only the year, day,
and month.
Other possibilities
include hours, minutes,
seconds, and so on.
The output format
will automatically adjust
according to the user’s locale.
These fields are
also configurable.
In this case, I change the month
to the wide format,
which means that the full
month name is printed.
Formatting just part of the date
is easy with this API as well.
Here I want
to get just the weekday.
Dates can be formatted
into different styles, too.
Here I choose to use the ISO 8601
format and iso8601, but only
with the year, month, and day,
and separated with a dash.
With these examples,
the formatting pattern
becomes clear.
We start with the value
we want to format.
We call the formatted function
and the argument is the style.
There may be more than one kind
of style for each type.
Date, for example,
has both dateTime and iso8601.
The style can be used
in a default configuration
or customized.
This formatting API works
by specifying a list of fields,
some of which have
additional options.
The order of the fields
you provide does not matter.
Each field just tells
the formatter what values should
be included somewhere
in the final output.
We choose a sensible default
for the shortest versions
of the API, those with no
arguments or just a style name.
Once you begin adding fields
to that, the output becomes
customized and reflects
only what you choose to display,
somewhat like placeholder text
in your UI.
There is also a new API
for formatting two dates
that are relative to each other.
Here are some examples.
First, formatting two dates
in a range.
You can just use
the regular Swift range syntax
with two dates.
Formatting ranges allows
configuration of showing
the date and time, just
as we did with a single date.
You can format this range
as a duration or as components
or a single date relative
to right now.
Another new feature
in formatting
is attributed output.
This allows you to find
the location a formatter
put a particular part
of a formatted value
after it is done rearranging it
to fit the user’s preferences.
This, of course, uses
our new struct AttributedString.
Applying styling
to formatted output shows up
in all kinds of places.
On watchOS,
many of the complications
are formatted strings.
Since Apple Watch is
such a personal device,
it’s important to take into
account the user’s preferences,
but it’s also a place
where we want to apply
a certain kind of
design language,
like giving part of a date
a color of the user’s choosing.
Setting this up is actually
quite a lot of fun in SwiftUI.
Let’s look at it together
in a demo.
Here I have the starting point
for my Caffé companion app,
which shows
when your next free coffee is.
I’ve got a SwiftUI view
which just shows
a formatted date.
I set the locale on the format
so I can control it
with my SwiftUI preview here.
It’s a pretty good start,
but I'd like to customize it
a bit more.
Let’s begin by making this
a little more specific
to my app.
I only care about the minute,
the hour, and the weekday.
OK, looking pretty good.
Now let’s add a splash of color.
First, we’ll change the return
type to AttributedString
and ask
for an attributed output.
Next, we’ll use
an attribute container.
These can hold attributes
without being attached
to any particular
characters in a string.
We’re going to create one
for the weekday attribute
that date formats
put on their output.
It’s set
on the range of the string
that contains the weekday.
Next, we’ll make a container
for the color attribute
we want to set.
And finally, we’ll use
an attributed string function
to replace
the attributes matching those
in the first container
with the values
in the second one
on our attributed string.
Because AttributedString
is a value type and replacing is
a mutating function, we need
to change our “let” to a “var.”
Looks great.
Even better,
it works for all locales.
Let’s add a few more
to our preview to double check.
You can
see here that the weekday
is orange no matter where
it is in the formatted date
for these locales.
Let’s keep learning about even
more new formatter APIs.
Now that we’ve seen how
to turn dates into strings,
let’s talk about how
to strings into dates.
Date now has an initializer
that takes a strategy argument.
The strategy is used
to tell the parser
what fields
to expect in the input.
For dates, the format is
also a kind of strategy.
That’s useful
for round-tripping dates,
like in a text field
that both displays output
and allows the user
to type in a new date.
Here is an example
of a round trip.
You’ll notice
that the parsing can throw.
This is because, depending
on the input, parsing can fail.
Some strategies have more
advanced options for parsing.
Here, we parse a fixed format,
which is useful
when the date format
is something received
from a server.
To use it, initialize a strategy
with a format string.
Instead of using magic
string values, though,
we use string interpolation.
In this case, we expect a string
of the format year-month-day.
Each interpolation is
clearly identified by field,
and each specifies exactly
what format to expect.
One really
nice thing about this is
the autocomplete experience.
If I want
to use a different day format,
autocomplete shows me
the valid options
along with documentation
about what each means.
No, more guessing how many Y
characters you should use
to parse a year.
Let’s move on to numbers.
Number formatting is
about converting an integer
or floating point value
into something a human can read.
Like all formatting, it takes
into account preferences
on how numbers should
be displayed.
This includes everything
from the kind of digit used
to what character is used
to group the digits.
As with date formatting,
getting great output is easy
with no additional parameters
required.
There are many supported kinds
of options and outputs.
Here we show percentage,
scientific notation,
and currency.
Finally, let’s put
a few formats together.
List formatting is now
just formatting an array.
This member style argument
specifies the format style
of each element in the array.
These are numbers,
so I’d like to use a percentage.
The output is correct
for every user’s locale.
So far we’ve focused on
formatting the values directly.
SwiftUI also supports attaching
a format style to a TextField.
Since format styles have
type information about the kinds
of values they format,
we can use a readable
but safe syntax for the tip
percentage on my receipt here.
Let’s look again
at our Caffé app
and see just how many places
formatting shows up.
We use a list format
for the ingredients.
We use a currency format
for the prices.
We use a number format
for the quantity
and also to localize the count
in the order button.
We can’t forget
about the date format
you always see
in the corner up here.
You’ll find formatted output all
over the place, and we think
this new API will make it easy,
even fun, in your app as well.
There are a lot more
resources available
to help with localized
strings and formatters.
We have two more sessions
on this topic,
“Localize your SwiftUI App”
and “Streamline
your localized strings.”
Next, let’s talk
about a new feature called
automatic grammar agreement.
Localizers in languages
like Spanish have been limited
in their ability
to express natural translations,
sometimes leading
to awkward dialog.
These languages require
transformations
to achieve gender
and pluralization agreement
between different parts
of speech
and sometimes even
require knowledge
of the user’s preferred term
of address.
English has this feature too,
with nouns
that have different forms
for singular and plural.
I threw out a lot
of language jargon there,
so let’s go through an example.
In my Caffé app,
I can pick a food item,
a size, and a quantity.
I choose 1 small salad.
Now my friend says
she will join me,
so I increase the count to 2.
In English, the word “salad” has
to change to match the number 2.
This is called agreement.
All that means is that the words
in this sentence have
to match each other.
In English, fixing up words
due to pluralization
is a common kind of agreement.
Now let’s switch our app
to Spanish
and order 1 ensalada pequeña,
or 1 small salad.
When I order for my friend,
this order button needs
the same pluralization
as in English but with a twist.
In Spanish, both the adjective,
pequeña, and the noun,
ensalada, have to agree
with the count, dos.
So instead of ensalada pequeña,
the button says
ensaladas pequeñas.
Next, I move on to drinks.
For this sentence,
the button not only needs
correct pluralization
but also agreement
in the grammatical gender
of these words.
Juice, jugo, is masculine.
The adjective pequeño
has to match as well.
In order to localize text
like this correctly,
we end up
with a combinatorial explosion.
A different localized string
is needed for each combination
of food, size, and count.
In code, it often ends up
looking like this,
where we need
to switch over each item,
then switch over each size,
and so on.
There is also a stringsdict
file, which can pluralize each
of these strings correctly
for counts.
Now, by leveraging the same
technology that powers
suggestions in keyboards,
we’ve created a new API
that can easily handle all
of these cases and more.
We call this feature
automatic grammar agreement,
because the system
automatically fixes up
localized strings so
that they have correct grammar.
Now the code becomes
far simpler.
You can combine the quantity,
size, and food in one string.
Automatic grammar agreement
will fix up the string
for you using a process
called inflection.
Let’s break it down.
In order to inflect,
we need to know which part
of the string needs
to be fixed up.
Luckily, we have a type
in Swift that can do that,
AttributedString, and a custom
attribute in Markdown.
In this string, I use
that syntax to wrap the food,
size, and count
with our inflect attribute.
The value of the attribute
is true.
When we export
this project’s localizations,
we'll get a strings file that
contains our annotated string
as well as other localized
strings in our source code,
like the names of the foods
and sizes.
Here are the strings
for Latin American Spanish.
The localizer has used
the argument reordering syntax
%1, %3, %2,
because an adjective
like "small" or “large” goes
before the noun in Spanish.
They keep
the custom attribute syntax
for inflecting this region
of the string
and supply translations
for the foods and sizes.
The automatic grammar
engine takes care
of fixing up the rest.
Some languages feature
agreement not only
between words
in the localized text itself
but between that text
and the person reading it.
Automatic grammar agreement
can help with that too.
For example, let’s take a look
at this welcome screen
for Notes.
In English,
we say “Welcome to Notes.”
In Spanish, we say “Te damos
la bienvenida a Notas,”
or “We give you our welcome
to Notes.”
We would like to have
the same experience
for Spanish as we do in English.
However, in Spanish,
the word “bienvenido” must
match with the user’s
preferred term of address.
This term could be one
of several choices,
and that choice
changes the text.
Using the correct term
of address results
in a more personal
and inclusive experience.
In this year’s releases, we’ve
made it possible for people
who use Spanish to specify
their term of address.
In the Language & Region
settings,
there is a new Term
of Address option.
When you choose it,
you can pick your preference
and also choose to share it
with all apps.
Here, you see the new
welcome screen in Notes
for a feminine term of address.
And here it is
for a masculine term of address.
If we do not know or the user
prefers not to specify,
we keep our original string
as an alternative.
The same inflection attribute
we saw earlier is also used
in localized strings
which refer to the user.
In our “welcome to” case,
we apply
the inflection attribute
to the word bienvenido.
The English string does
not need to change.
I can also
add an inflection alternative,
which is a replacement string
the engine will use if it has no
information on what the user’s
preferences are.
This year,
we support automatic agreement
for Spanish and English.
We’ve adopted it in several
places across the OS,
like the welcome screen
in Notes.
You can adopt it
in your apps too.
The code changes required
are mostly just deleting a lot
of logic
to pick different strings.
The instructions
on what to inflect are part
of the localized string itself,
allowing localizers more control
over how the string appears
in their language.
Let’s take a look
at automatic grammar agreement
in action for our Caffé app.
Let’s go through the Caffé app
running in English.
I’ll start by adding some pizza
to the order.
I think I’ll have a large one.
And just 1.
Notice how the text
on the button has changed
from 0 large pizzas
to 1 large pizza.
That was done automatically.
If I pick 2,
it fixes it up again.
I’ll just have one.
At the bottom of this screen,
the order button has changed
to say 1 item.
How about something to drink?
Small is fine,
and just 1 of these.
Notice how the button has
changed to say “items”
instead of “item”?
That string
was changed automatically.
Let’s check out.
Here is our receipt.
It lists our pizza and juice,
along with formatted prices.
At the bottom is
our attributed string,
with its custom fonts
and link to the website.
Let’s go back to Xcode
and take a look at the source.
I’ll start
in the food details view.
This is the view that shows
the size selection screen.
Let’s add a new size
so that we can
see how that only requires us
to add one localized string
for Spanish instead
of one for each kind of food,
each size, and each count.
This line shows the list.
The list comes
from our model object.
Let’s go there.
The size enum already
has small and large.
I’m going to add a new size
for our hungriest customers,
called “huge.”
To do that, I’ll add a new case,
along with a localized string.
Now I just need to add prices
for the huge size.
For this demo, I’ve just
put them in the initializers.
Now I just need to add prices
for the huge size.
For this demo, I’ve just
put them in our initializers.
Let’s check out our view again.
Here in the preview
is our new size.
Our source already contains
an English string.
I just need a Spanish one now.
To generate the new strings,
I’ll use the compiler
to find the new localized string
for “huge.”
To do that, I choose
Product > Export Localizations,
and save the Spanish strings.
Now let’s add a translation
for Spanish.
I can filter for our new string
and type in our Spanish word.
Next, I import
these localizations
to put them into my app.
Now I’ll run our app again
but in Spanish.
To do that, I choose
Product > Scheme > Edit Scheme.
In the Options,
I can pick the language
I want to test in.
And run.
You can tell from our header
that we're now running
in Spanish.
Let’s make another order,
starting with salad.
Notice as I change the quantity,
the order button is fixed up.
Our new huge size is correctly
pluralized for 2 salads.
Plus, it matches the grammatical
gender for "ensalada,"
all with just one string.
There are a lot
of great new features
in Foundation this year,
and they are ready
for you to try
in your apps today.
AttributedString provides
a fast,
easy-to-use,
and Swift-first interface
for adding key-value pairs
to ranges of a string.
You can use it with SwiftUI
in text
and start using Markdown
in your localized strings.
Our new Formatter API
puts the focus on the format,
simplifying your code
and improving performance.
Use formats in all of the places
you present data in your app.
Finally,
automatic grammar agreement
will intelligently
fix up localized strings
so that they match
grammatical gender, counts,
and the user’s own term
of address.
I hope you’ll love
these new features.
We’re looking forward
to finding them in your apps.
Thank you.
[music]