[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Russell] Hello!
My name is Russell, and I'm
an engineer on the UIKit team.
In iOS 13, we introduced
a refined appearance for sheets,
bringing them to Phone
and adding a universal
pull-to-dismiss gesture.
To learn more about this,
watch the video
Modernizing Your UI for iOS 13,
specifically the section about
Presentations starting 9 minutes
and 45 seconds in.
In iOS 15,
we've built on that foundation
by adding a bunch of
customization options to sheets,
so you can now use them in
fun new ways like never before.
We've added support
for a medium detent,
which allows you to create
a vertically resizable sheet
that only covers
half the screen.
You can also now remove
the dimming view,
which will allow you to build
a nonmodal UI
where the user can interact
with content behind the sheet
while the sheet is presented.
Next, I'll cover some
new visual options,
including how to get
a non-full-screen appearance
on phones in landscape.
And finally,
I'll show how to set up a UI
that seamlessly adapts
between a popover
in regular size classes
and a customized sheet
in compact size classes.
To explore all of this,
we've made a sample app
for creating digital postcards,
and it's available
with this video.
For each postcard,
I can customize the picture
as well as the text
and the font.
Now, before I can
customize a sheet,
first I have to get one.
A sheet is an instance of a new
UIPresentationController
subclass
called
UISheetPresentationController,
and all of the customization
options are exposed
as properties on this class.
The typical way to get
an instance of this class
is to read
the sheetPresentationController
property
on a view controller
before you present it.
This method returns
a non-nil instance
as long the view controller's
modalPresentationStyle
is form sheet or page sheet,
which it is by default.
From here, you can then set
various properties
on the instance to customize it.
This is the same pattern
as getting a view controller's
popoverPresentationController
and setting its properties.
And with that,
let's jump into detents.
What are detents?
A detent is a height
where a sheet naturally rests,
and these are defined
as a fraction
of the fully expanded
sheet frame.
The fully expanded frame
is visualized
on an iPhone and iPad here,
and it should be familiar
if you've used sheets before.
We've exposed two system-defined
detents in iOS 15:
a medium detent,
which is about half
of a sheet's full height,
and a large detent,
which is the height
of a fully expanded sheet.
To specify which detents
you want a sheet to support,
simply set an array
of the detents you want
on the detents property.
The default value
of this property is an array
of just the large detent,
which is why if you don't
set it at all, you get
a standard full height sheet.
If you set this to an array
of the medium and large detents,
you get a sheet
that is resizable
between medium and large.
But you can also set this
to an array
of just the medium detent,
which gives you a sheet
that presents at medium height
and cannot be resized
to full height.
Let's apply this
to the sample app.
I'm starting with some code
that targets the iOS 14 SDK
to present the system image
picker in a standard sheet.
When a button is tapped,
this first function is called,
which creates an image picker,
sets the picker's delegate
to self,
and then presents the picker.
Then when an image is chosen,
the picker didFinishPicking
delegate method is called,
which then sets the chosen image
on the image view
and dismisses the picker.
Let's run it.
When I tap the photo button,
the photo picker covers
the whole app.
Notice my traveling has
recently been very virtual.
And when I pick a photo,
the photo picker dismisses,
revealing the photo
I picked in the postcard.
But what if I want to pick
a different picture?
I have to go through
this whole flow again.
And it would be really nice
if I could show
my library of photos
and my postcard
at the same time.
And with a medium detent, I can.
Here's the same code as before
but with a few changes.
Before I present the picker,
I access
its sheetPresentationController
and set its detents
to medium and large.
Also in the picker
didFinishPicking
delegate callback,
I removed the line
that dismisses the photo picker,
because now I don't want
the photo picker to dismiss
when selecting a picture.
Now when I run this
and tap the photo button,
my library comes up
at half height,
I can pick a photo, and voila.
I can see it in my postcard
with the library still below.
And if I want to try
a different photo,
it's as simple as one tap.
Also, because my detents array
includes the large detent,
I can drag the bar to resize
this sheet to full height.
In addition,
because the scroll view
is scrolled to top,
scrolling the scroll view
will also expand the sheet.
For a sheet of actions
like the system Share Sheet,
this is a great feature
that progressively discloses
more advanced actions
at the bottom of the list.
But for this
photo library example,
I might prefer that scrolling
not expand the sheet
so the postcard is
always visible
unless I explicitly resize
the sheet
by dragging from the bar.
To get this alternate behavior,
I just have to set
one additional property:
PrefersScrollingExpands-
WhenScrolledToEdge.
By default,
this property is true,
so setting it to false
prevents scrolling
from expanding the sheet.
Now the photo picker
doesn't resize when scrolled,
but I can still drag the bar
to get a better view
of my photo library.
But now when I tap a photo,
it's not obvious
that anything happened.
This is in contrast
to the earlier behavior,
where tapping a photo
dismissed the photo picker,
clearly indicating
my selection was received.
What I'd like is
to have the sheet resize
to the medium detent
when I tap a photo,
both to indicate
my selection was received
and to make my selection
visible in the postcard.
And I can achieve this
by programmatically changing
the selected detent.
So if I go back to the image
picker delegate method
that is called
whenever a photo is tapped,
I can add some code here to get
the sheetPresentationController
and set
the selectedDetentIdentifier
to medium.
Let's try this.
Notice the transition
when I tap a photo.
Whoa!
That transition was so fast,
I almost lost my eyebrows.
It actually didn't
animate at all.
I can easily animate
this transition
by wrapping the setting
of the property
in a sheet.animateChanges block.
This will animate the sheet down
to the medium detent if needed
with a standard animation curve
and animate other sheets
in the stack as well,
such as the root sheet
scaling back up.
Buttery smooth.
One more nice thing would be
to remove the dimming view
to show the selected photo
in full color.
To do that, there's one more
property to look at
called smallestUndimmed-
DetentIdentifier.
By default,
this property is nil,
which means
all of the detents are dimmed,
but if you want
to remove dimming,
set it to the identifier
of the smallest detent
where you don't want dimming.
In this case,
I'll set it to medium.
Notice there's no dimming
at the medium detent
when I bring up the picker.
Ta-da!
But dimming still fades in
if I resize to the large detent.
More than visually removing
the dimming,
this property also allows you
to build advanced
nonmodal experiences,
since I can now interact
not only with the content
in the sheet
but also with the content
outside of the sheet.
This is even more profound
with the font picker,
where I've built a UI
that allows me to select
a range of text
while the font picker is up,
apply a font to just that range,
adjust my selection,
and apply a font again.
Download the sample app for
details on how this is achieved.
It's also worth noting
that medium height sheets
support automatic
keyboard avoidance,
so if I search for a font here,
the sheet grows automatically
to account for the keyboard,
and when the keyboard dismisses,
the sheet automatically
collapses back down.
So that was a lot
of information about detents,
but now I'd like to turn
our attention
to some other new
visual customization options
for sheets,
starting with a new
optional appearance for sheets
on iPhone in landscape.
In iOS 13, we made all sheets
full screen in landscape,
and now we've made available
an alternate appearance
where sheets are only attached
to the screen
at their bottom edge.
To get this new appearance,
simply set
prefersEdgeAttached-
InCompactHeight to true.
Now just setting this
will always give you a sheet
that is as wide
as the safe area.
If you'd like a sheet
whose width follows
the presentedViewControllers
preferredContentSize,
set widthFollows-
PreferredContentSize-
WhenEdgeAttached to true.
This will make the sheet
a narrower default width,
and you can set
preferredContentSize
to further customize this width.
Besides these properties,
there is also a property
to show a grabber if you like.
A grabber often isn't necessary,
but in cases
where it might be less obvious
that a sheet is resizable,
such as when scrolling doesn't
resize the sheet,
displaying the grabber
can be a helpful indicator
of resizability.
Now notice
the corners of the sheet.
Another option we've exposed
is the ability
to customize the corner radius.
If your app has
a more rounded appearance,
you may want
to match that aesthetic.
Note that the system
will keep stacked corners
looking consistent,
so if this photo picker expands
to push back the root sheet,
the root sheet will have
larger corners to match.
Finally, although it's possible
to create a sheet
with detents on iPad,
often a popover is
wanted instead
that adapts
to a sheet in compact,
potentially customized
with things like detents.
Let's take this approach
with the sample app.
To get a popover
for the image picker on iPad,
I need to make
a few small modifications.
First, I'll set
the modalPresentationStyle
of the picker to popover.
Then, instead of grabbing
the sheetPresentationController,
because this
will now return nil,
since the modalPresentationStyle
is not a sheet,
I'll get the
popoverPresentationController.
I'll set the popover's source
to be our barButtonItem,
and then I'll grab
a new property on the popover
called the adaptiveSheet-
PresentationController.
This property returns
an instance of the sheet
that the popover will adapt to
in compact size classes,
and then I'll configure it
just as I did the sheet before.
Now when I tap a photo button,
the photo picker appears
in the popover,
and if I resize the scene,
it adapts
to a medium height sheet.
It works!
And if I expand the picker,
and select a photo--
oh, no!
It didn't automatically resize
to medium height
like we implemented before.
Hmm.
Let's go back to the picker
didFinishPicking
delegate method.
Ah!
To get the adaptive sheet,
I need to read
the adaptiveSheet-
PresentationController
on the
popoverPresentationController
here in the code as well.
Now notice
when I select a photo.
Hooray!
It resizes back to medium again.
Now, I've talked
about a lot of stuff here
that will enable you
to easily build new types of UIs
with sheets that could not be
easily built before.
Review your own apps
for areas that would benefit
from medium height sheets
or nonmodal experiences.
If you have any half height
custom cards in your apps today,
replace them with these
newly enhanced UIKit sheets.
Thank you for watching,
and I look forward to seeing
all of the cool new things
you build with sheets.