[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[person] Design is one of
the most challenging things
that you can do in software.
You have to identify
the problem really well.
♪ ♪
[Arian]
Oh!
[Alan] Design can be certainly
how something looks,
but we are really preoccupied
with how something works.
[Monika] App and game design
enables our device
to be what it is
and what it can become
in your hands.
♪ ♪
[Heena] Designing an app
or a game
is actually
quite an intimate experience.
[Teo]
I need to empathize.
I need to have some--
try and understand
what your experience
might be like using that thing.
[Heena]
The person on the other side
really can feel the attention
and care
that's been put into it,
but the challenge there
is simplifying it
so that somebody can look
at something and just, like,
you know,
understand immediately.
[Mikey] Developers,
the ones that figure out a way
to achieve these things
in their design
are the ones
that usually stand out.
♪ ♪
[Alan] For us to celebrate
the best of the best,
those apps that were designed
in such a way
that are deserving
of an Apple Design Award,
you know, nothing is bigger
in this community,
in our community.
[James]
It's always easy to remember
the really big moments in life,
and winning
an Apple Design Award
was definitely one
of those moments
that I'll never forget.
[Anja] I mean,
I had to pinch myself,
like, really hard to be assured
that I'm not dreaming.
[Jenova] Pretty much everyone
that win Apple Design Award
is somebody
who has made something
that I would use or play.
[Irene] It really gave the team
a chance to pause and reflect
and acknowledge
all that we'd accomplished.
[Quentin] It's elevated it
to this other level
where we've
just got a lot more users,
and we get
a ton of feedback from people
in all different countries.
[Raja] I can't say
it's more like a dream come true
because I--
this was beyond my dream
and really can't express
those things.
[Allan] This year
with the Apple Design Awards,
we're bringing back categories.
[Lauren]
There are six categories
for the Apple Design Awards
this year.
-They're inclusivity.
-[Linda] Delight and fun.
-[Doug] Interaction.
-[Allan] Social impact.
-[Mark] Visuals and graphics.
-[Mike] And innovation.
The thing that I love
about what we're doing this year
is that we're able
to really zero in
on some particular qualities
that are really important
and to talk about them directly.
♪ ♪
[Teo] Apps and games
are hugely powerful
because they can create
environments where, you know,
all are welcome.
♪ ♪
[Linda]
Design is inherently about
understanding and catering
towards people,
so this idea of inclusivity,
it's not anything new,
but it is just making sure
that the goal
is always
to support more people,
to enable more people.
[Aurelio] Well, obviously
ethnicity and age and gender
are some of the big ones,
but all the time,
we're finding more things
that are personally important
to people.
Being inclusive
and being diverse
is being accepting
of those categories
and making sure
that they're represented
in a way that's equitable
to the user.
[Lauren] Apps and games
that excel at inclusivity
include as many people
as possible in the experience.
This can be done
through localization
with a ton of languages.
It can be done
by supporting a wide variety
of accessibility features
like voiceover and dynamic type.
It can be something as simple
as turning on reduced motion
in a game so people
with motion sensitivities
can still have fun
and experience the game fully.
♪ ♪
The winning app
in the Inclusivity category
is Voice Dream Reader.
Voice Dream Reader makes it
so easy to bring text to speech.
[electronic speaker]
Mr. Bennet was so odd.
A mixture of quick parts,
sarcastic humor,
reserve, and caprice...
[Lauren] It has probably one
of the best implementations
of voiceover
that we have ever seen.
It has a lot
of text customization settings,
so it can increase contrast
or decrease contrast,
space out lines, words,
and highlight certain phrases
within a written material
to make it easy for people
who may have low vision
or dyslexia,
and it's also localized
into 26 different languages.
[Linda] This year's winner
in Inclusivity in games
is "HoloVista."
"HoloVista"
is a mixed reality game
where you use the gyroscope
to photograph
these really beautiful
3D spaces.
"HoloVista" has
a pretty thorough set
of accessibility controls
that make it
so that you can control
text legibility,
color legibility,
motion sensitivity,
and the way that you want
to control the camera
as you're panning around
or not.
[Teo] This app has got some
really great visual warnings
about potential sensory
and cognitive needs.
[Linda] It's also very good
at presenting those controls
and those warnings upfront.
♪ ♪
It's easy to know
what it feels like
to be delighted
and to have fun.
Putting it into words
is a lot more difficult.
[chuckles]
[Alan] It's an interesting one
because you can feel delight
having an experience
with a more serious app or game,
or you can have delight and fun
with, obviously, a game
that's just fun to play.
[Andre] Delight and fun
is when you use all of the tools
at your disposal
in an unexpected way.
[Lynne] I think the reason
that it's important
is because it's really memorable
for people.
People understand
that using the app
that time
kind of brightened up your day.
They're gonna return to it
and use it
again and again and again.
[Allan] For a game,
what really stands out
in terms of delight and fun
a lot of the time
are these moments in the game.
Maybe it's something
that catches you by surprise
and just creates
this little moment of,
like, "Oh, I love that."
[Teo] People are
seeking experiences
where they can escape
a lot of the time,
things that might
make you laugh,
make you smile,
and just have fun.
[chuckles]
[Allan] The winner
for Delight and Fun for games
is "Little Orpheus."
[Ivan] My mission was clear,
to find Little Orpheus.
[Allan] "Little Orpheus"
is just such a delight to play.
[Ivan] And deep below
the Earth's surface,
prehistoric monsters
still roam freely.
[Allan] There's these
little moments in the game
that just have to get you.
Everything from the music--
the character's story
is wonderful.
It's like a Jules Verne novel
come to life.
[soaring orchestral music]
[Ivan] Perhaps Little Orpheus
was not lost at all.
[Linda] This year's winner
in the Delight and Fun category
for apps is "Pok Pok."
[upbeat music]
It is just the definition
of a joyful experience.
[warm tones]
The first time I played
with this app,
I honestly spent over an hour
just fiddling
with all of the different
little sandbox toys,
and I know it's meant
to be designed for children,
but it definitely brings out
kind of this childlike wonder.
The thing that I really loved
about it
was that this app came
from a mother and father,
them just wanting
to build something
that was delightful
for their children.
It puts a smile
on everyone's faces
when they use it, and it's
just the clear winner here.
♪ ♪
[Andre] If I poke you,
there is a reaction, right?
There's an action and reaction,
and that dance
is where interaction stands.
[Caroline]
Ooh, look, parallax.
[Alan] Interaction is all about
how an app or a game works,
how the user relates to it,
how they make their way
through the application
and experience it.
In our world,
nothing's more critical.
[Jon] Interaction always has
a result to what you do
even if the result
is letting you know
nothing happened.
[Doug] Apps that stand out
in the Interaction category
are extraordinarily easy to use.
They are kind of using
the right methods of input,
so whether that's keyboard
or jester or pencil.
[Monika] If design can almost--
can get out of the way
of someone's intention
of what they are trying to do,
that's almost
where it's best design.
[Kevin] You don't think
about the app,
or you don't think
about roadblocks in the app,
and you don't think
about anything else really.
It becomes invisible.
[Lauren] When you're interacting
with a game,
and you are just
seamlessly moving,
and you're not thinking,
"I'm moving my left thumb up.
I am moving
my right thumb down."
It's just--it is intuitive.
You just understand
what you're gonna need to do.
You feel like you're at one
with the device
that you're holding,
and it just becomes
second nature.
[Doug] The winner
in the Interaction category
for apps is CARROT Weather.
I think the real magic of it
is in the way that it manifests
in the other places
in my life that I need.
CARROT Weather allows me to put
a widget on the home screen.
I can also go in, add--
oh, there's four faces.
To add any one
of these four faces,
and just add it to my watch,
and there it is.
[person]
Can you show us?
[Doug]
Yeah.
What I love about CARROT Weather
is just how much its personality
infuses every part
of the experience.
Depending on
your outlook on life,
it's either partly cloudy
or partly sunny.
So if you do like
your forecasts snarky,
you can set it for snarky.
If you want them
a bit more professional,
you can dial it down
a little bit.
[person]
And now all the way up.
[Doug]
Okay.
Well, there may be
unprintable words in there,
but we'll see.
[Lauren] The winner
in the games category
for Interaction
is "Bird Alone."
[bird squawking]
"Bird Alone"
won the interaction category
because it is so easy to use.
You instantly know
what you're doing
when you launch the game.
You know where to tap.
You know where to swipe.
[Caroline]
I really like the balance
between a story
that's being told
and then engaging me
and asking me to do a task.
So I just drew a picture
of something
that makes me happy.
[Lauren] You're able
to explore a little bit,
and if you touch onscreen,
you're given visual feedback.
What's really unique
is that it only asks you
to interact with the game
a little bit at a time.
So you can only play
for a little bit per day,
which is such a different spin
on what games
typically are asking you to do.
♪ ♪
[Mikey]
I think being a developer
and being a creator in general,
we have the responsibility
of making sure
that the things that we create,
the tools that we make
are helping
make the world a better place.
[Mike] Social impact to me
represents an awareness
that we have a responsibility
to do things
for others in our community.
I mean, I think a lot of people,
hopefully, share that sense,
[Heena] This is when, like,
technology is at its best--
when it's used
to amplify people's voices
and voices
that are not often heard.
[Caroline] I think there's lots
of ideas still out there
about how technology
can impact social change.
[Mark] A couple ways that we
think about social impact
is does it improve lives
in meaningful ways?
Does it have lasting value
or impact
on the community as a whole?
[Mike] The winning app
in the Social Impact category
is Be My Eyes.
Be My Eyes won
because it's so clear
the benefit
that's being provided,
that you're there
as a volunteer at least.
to help someone who can't see
identify objects around them.
There's just countless stories
of humans helping humans
that I think it just resonates
deeply with us.
[Mark] This year,
we saw several games
take a really active approach
toward social impact,
which is not something
we've seen in previous years,
at least to the degree
we've seen this year.
The winner of the Social Impact
category for games
is "Alba: a Wildlife Adventure."
♪ ♪
"Alba: a Wildlife Adventure"
is just a tremendously
charming game
with incredible personality.
It follows a young girl
who's 11 years old
who's trying to save
this natural preserve
as the city is trying
to build a resort
on top of the natural preserve.
She learns to pick up trash
in the local community,
start a petition
to help out the area.
She takes pictures of wildlife
and then repairs the signs
around the natural preserve
so that people begin
to take interest
in the natural preserve again.
All of these things contribute
to this incredibly charming,
terrific experience.
♪ ♪
[Pablo] The visuals
and the graphics
are the front door
into an experience.
♪ ♪
[Aurelio] Visuals and graphics
are at the core
of design and at the core
of communication,
so as developers
and as we as designers
want to communicate,
we do it through visuals.
♪ ♪
[Mike] You haven't
read anything, done anything,
really interacted with it,
but just through colors
that you're seeing,
the style of the icons,
the choice of typeface,
if it's a game,
the quality of the graphics,
the 3D models,
how they're rendered,
what the frame rate is.
All of these things
tell you so much
about the experience
that you're about to have.
The winning app in the category
of Visuals and Graphics
is Loóna
♪ ♪
[narrator]
Start with its tail
and slowly color
the dragon's body.
[Mike]
Loóna is a app
that helps you slow down,
calm down, forget about things
that are stressing you out,
and just focus
on coloring in a model
while hearing
a really nice story told by
a really talented voice actor,
and it just helps to relax
and maybe help you fall asleep.
[narrator]
Wonderful.
[Allan] The winner for visuals
and graphics for games
is "Genshin Impact."
There's just so many things
to see in this game.
These huge, beautiful vistas
looking out over the terrain
or inside temples
and seeing the special effects
for the magic
and combat encounters.
The look of
the characters themselves
and how they have
this anime quality to them
that really fits the style
of the game.
[game character] Huh?
Look at that!
♪ ♪
[Andre] I've always
seen innovation
as the association
of remote ideas,
and they come together
into something
that is both familiar because
they were already existing ideas
but also something new
because the combination
has never been here before.
[Doug] It's not new
for new's sake.
It's not technology
for technology's sake.
It's a new way
of solving an old problem.
[person] If you can
remove friction
from something and make it
just a little bit easier,
that is really innovative.
[Arian] The trick to, I think,
fostering good ideas
is this state of openness.
[Pablo] Apps are not a monolith.
They keep evolving
with the world and with people.
[Doug] When I use
an innovative app,
my first reaction is
"This can't be possible,"
or, "Why hasn't it always
worked like this?"
The winner in
the innovation category for apps
is NaadSadhana.
[bright music]
What really distinguished it--
it's not only
a music practicing app,
but it's also
a music improvisation app,
and it's
for Indian classical singing.
Giving me real-time feedback
about whether
I'm hitting the notes or not.
♪ This is NaadSadhana ♪
♪ It is the winning app ♪
I'm currently
not hitting the notes.
[Andre]
♪ Hey, yeah, yeah ♪
That's definitely not on pitch.
[Doug] But it's also
using the tone of your voice
and the intensity
of your singing voice
to adapt the rhythm,
so as you sing more intensely,
the rhythm gets more intense.
♪ ♪
[Mark] The winner
in the innovation category
for games is
"League of Legends: Wild Rift."
It's an incredible achievement
to bring the full-fledged
"League of Legends" experience
to Apple's platforms.
[Pablo] Yeah, wow.
[upbeat music]
The motion is very, very fluid.
I love it.
[Mark] MOBAs--multiplayer online
battle arenas--
are incredibly complex,
and "League of Legends"
has a lot of nuance
within that category,
and to be able to bring that
to iOS
and not only fit it
on iPhone and the iPad
but also be able to thrive
on that platform
is a terrific achievement.
[Pablo] Oh, I was slain.
[laughs]
All right, let's do this again.
[Mark] One of
the really challenging things
is bringing the controls
of a multiplayer
online battle arena
like "League of Legends"
to a touchscreen
and a smaller form factor
like an iPhone.
But they do a terrific job
with customized controls.
Really interesting things
like being able
to swipe an ability
up to the corner
to cancel it mid-battle,
and it allows you
to have all the nuanced gameplay
you would expect
from "League of Legends"
on a touchscreen,
which is terrific.
[announcer]
Victory.
[Mikey] To anyone
that's interested
in being a developer,
I would encourage you
to find the things
you're passionate about.
Find a thing
that you want to create.
[Teo] Try things.
Try again.
Have the courage
to go down a path
and turn round
if it's not right.
[Arian]
Being wrong, I think,
is most of the process.
Just accepting that
is kind of hard at first,
but, like, super freeing
once you know that.
[Monika] I wish that somebody
would tell me
that this is gonna be
a life journey.
[laughs]
[Linda] I just wanted
to say congratulations
to all of the winners
and thank you.
[Doug] I just want
to thank you so much.
[Caroline]
Thank you so much.
[person] You know,
when I won many years ago,
it had a huge impact on me
and my career,
so I hope it does
the same for you.
[Andre] Thank you
for being out there
elevating the human experience.
[Alan] And we're so happy
that you put your hard work
into the world.
[Lauren] I'm not sure
what the future holds
for great apps and great games,
but I am positive
there's a developer
who's already building it.
♪ ♪