[ethereal percussion music]
♪ ♪
[Austin]
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
I'm Austin, and I work
on the Apps and Books
Management API.
I'll be sharing with you
improvements we have brought
to a new API version,
enabling your MDM solution
to manage Apps and Books
in a faster and more
scalable way than ever before.
You're likely already using
the Apps and Books
Management API
to enable organizations
using your product
to manage their owned
apps and books.
The organization may have
acquired these assets
through either
Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
And the API allows
for you to assign
these owned apps and books
to the organization's
managed users and devices.
We've introduced a lot
of changes this year
to the new Apps and Books API.
We'll cover many of these
throughout this session
but focus
on the two enhancements
that will most improve
your workflows:
Real-time notifications
and Asynchronous processing.
For an in-depth look
at the other changes,
see the new
developer documentation
within the Device Management
section on developer.apple.com
and in the references
for this session.
Let's get started
with Real-time notifications.
We now support Real-time
notifications for state changes
to assignments, assets,
and registered users.
You need to opt-in
to these notifications,
and you will only
receive notifications
for the types you subscribe
to in client config.
Real-time notifications
finally remove the need
for you
to continually sync state.
Let's discuss the notification
types a little more in-depth.
The first notification type
is for assignments.
An assignment is
when an asset is allocated
to either a user or device
managed by an organization.
If you have to wait
for confirmation
that entire groups
of assignments
have been performed
successfully,
that will lead to delays
in installing the content
that users need.
Now, with assignment
notifications,
you'll know in real-time
exactly what assignments
have successfully been performed
and to which devices.
You subscribe
to the asset management
notification type in client
config to receive these.
Apple will then proceed
to notify you
when assignment states are
altered by either an associate,
disassociate,
or revoke assets event.
You may now rely
on these notifications
to provide users and devices
faster access to content
as they are assigned.
Let's look at an example
of this notification.
When an assignment occurs,
you get this notification.
The example here was triggered
by an associate assets call.
Apple posts these notifications
with a shared secret
in the authorization header
provided by you
in client config.
The notification
contains a payload,
which is specific
to a given notification type.
The type is denoted here,
which for this notification
is asset management.
In our notification payload,
we can see the assignments
whose state has attempted
to be altered,
event ID, the unique identifier
for this MDM-triggered
asynchronous event.
We'll get into
more detail regarding
the asynchronous nature
of our new API in a bit.
Here is the result
of the state change,
whether it succeeded or failed.
And the type of change
to assignment state,
which here is an associate.
The next notification
type is for assets.
Assets are apps and books that
an organization has purchased
in either Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
That organization is not able
to manage and assign the assets
until your MDM knows
that they own the content.
With asset notifications,
you're notified in real-time
when changes to assets
occur from purchases,
transfers, or refunds,
and your MDM can always know
the current available
count of each asset.
You subscribe to the asset count
notification type
in client config
to receive these.
Apple will then proceed
to notify you
when an asset state changes
due to either a buy,
transfer, or refund event.
These notifications
will allow you
to quickly provide users
with their recently
purchased assets.
Let's also take
a look at an example
of this notification
with the context
of what the state of assets
looked like before.
To get the current state
of assets,
we call
the "get assets" endpoint.
This is the new
asset sync endpoint,
which you can note
by both the proper HTTP
request method of GET
and the versioned URI.
Here, we are querying
with the query parameters
of adamId and pricingParam
to receive the state
of a single asset.
We are now requiring
that the server token
or sToken is provided
in the authorization header
of all new API requests
in this bearer token format.
We see in the assets array
of this response
for the asset
we are interested in,
there are 10,000 available
for assignment
and 15,000 in total.
When a buy happens,
you will get this notification.
We see in the payload,
the adamId for the asset
that was purchased.
Then the delta, which in this
case is a positive integer.
This could either denote
a buy or a transfer.
You'd use this delta
to update your counts
without making another call
to the asset sync endpoint.
The last notification types
are for registered users.
Most deployments rely
on device-based assignments,
but when you need
to assign content to users,
creating registered users
is the first step.
Associating these users
to either personal
or managed Apple IDs is then
necessary for deployment.
For a user's personal Apple ID
to be associated
to a registered user
for a given sToken,
the user must accept
an invitation
to associate their Apple ID.
Now, with registered
user notifications,
you'll be updated in real-time
with the latest state of users,
both for their initial creation
and subsequent
invitation acceptance.
You subscribe
to the user management
and user associated
notification types
in client config
to receive these.
Then Apple will notify you
when user states are altered
by either create, associate,
update, or retire user events.
The user associated
notifications
specifically allow you
to better track
when a user has
accepted an invitation
to associate their Apple ID.
Let's take a look at an example
of these notifications
with the context
of what the state of users
looked like prior.
In order to get
the current state of users,
we call the get users endpoint.
This is the new users
sync endpoint.
Here, filtering only for
the user we are interested in
by the clientUserId
query parameter.
This will limit the response
size to only one user.
Here, we have some common
pagination fields found
across our sync API,
indicating the current
page index, size,
or in this context,
the number of user objects
in the current page,
and the total pages
in the provided query.
In our users array,
we can see the only user
we are interested in,
in this case,
with a status of registered,
as opposed to associated,
and an invitation code.
This user has clearly yet
to be associated to an Apple ID.
All our sync API also include
a version identifier,
which will change
whenever a write occurs
to the underlying data.
This can be extremely useful
when traversing large responses
to indicate when data
on prior pages may have changed.
You can associate
a managed Apple ID
to a registered user using
the new update users endpoint.
This results in a registered
user notification as seen here.
In our notification payload,
we see users whose state
has attempted to be altered,
unique identifier for this MDM
triggered asynchronous event,
the result of the state change,
whether it succeeded or failed,
the type of change to user
state, which here is an update.
Looking at the users array,
we see the clientUserId
for the user's state
we are interested in,
containing an idHash
and status of associated,
concluding that the managed
Apple ID association
was successful.
You use this to update
your state of this user
without making another call
to the user sync endpoint.
Instead of you associating,
it is instead possible
that you provide the user
with an invitation link
to associate their own Apple ID
to the registered user.
Here, we are looking at that
associated user notification.
We see in the notification
payload the user object
containing the information
regarding the associated user
including but not limited
to their clientUserId,
an idHash indicating
an associated Apple ID,
the invite code they accepted,
and status denoting associated.
You use this to update
your state of this user
without making another call
to the user sync endpoint.
Let's talk about how you enroll
to receive these notifications.
You must opt in
via client config
for each sToken you manage.
You provide a shared secret
for authentication
with the notificationAuthToken
and the notificationUrl
to post these to.
The token is used to verify
that these notifications
are, in fact, coming from Apple,
and this can be updated anytime
via client config.
Provide an HTTP
200-level response
when you receive notifications
in order to let Apple know
that they've been
delivered successfully.
Apple will attempt
to retry the notification
if a non-200 response
is returned
or a timeout occurs.
Apple will provide
a best-effort delivery.
This attempt to reach you
will be made a few times
before discarding
the notification.
This means if you are unable
to receive notifications
for any period of time,
you will need to poll
for the latest state.
Sync only for what you know
to be in
a potentially stale state
as a result
of the missed notifications.
The second major enhancement
brought to this new API
is asynchronous processing.
In the initial version
of the API,
all management was
performed synchronously.
You make a request
to manage some assets,
and Apple performs
the management
while you wait
for a synchronous response.
This meant you
handled parallelism,
whereas asynchronous processing
enables server-enforced
parallelism on Apple's end.
This results
in processing optimizations,
which leads to larger requests
being fulfilled more quickly.
Ordered processing
reduces the amount
of intermittent failures
and subsequent retries due
to your specific
request patterns.
And this ultimately leads
to stress-free
large deployments,
and, for education,
easier back-to-school seasons.
Apple has already benefited
from asynchronous processing
for Apps and Books,
purchases, and transfers
in both Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager,
allowing organizations
to see inventory on hand
in minutes rather than hours.
Let's look at how
this all comes together
to make for a great new Apps
and Books management experience.
Say there's an organization
that you manage
with 10,000 users,
each with their own device.
And you're asked
to assign 25 apps
that are critical for their
daily tasks to each device.
You're looking at performing
250,000 assignments.
Let's look at how you would
have done this previously.
Your server makes a request
to Apple to manage licenses.
Apple returns a response
to you synchronously.
This response would contain
the licenses assigned
to requested devices.
This single request
manages only one app
up to a maximum of ten devices,
resulting in only
ten assignments.
This requires a minimum
of 25,000 requests
to perform
the 250,000 assignments.
With the new API,
this 25,000 minimum requests
becomes just 10 requests,
all possible by moving
to asynchronous processing.
Let's look at how
you achieve this.
On the left,
we now have the addition
of your notification server.
Process still starts
with you making a request
to Apple to manage assets.
In the request,
you provide the sToken
in the authorization header.
You can now provide us
with multiple assets
in a single request,
up to 25 currently.
This dynamic limit is
exposed in service config
and provide up to 1,000 devices
to perform assignment to,
another dynamic limit
also exposed in service config.
Apple will return a response
synchronously to you.
In this response,
we have the HTTP status code,
which is important
to this new API.
We return appropriate
non-200 status codes for errors,
so you should initially
interrogate the response
to ensure it is a 200
before proceeding.
Then, most importantly,
we have the unique identifier
for this asynchronous event
whose status
can either be gotten
from calling our new
event status endpoint
or by waiting for matching
assignment notifications.
As the assignments complete,
assuming you are subscribed,
Apple will post
notifications to you.
In each of these notifications,
we have a subset
of the requested
assignments listed
in our notification payload,
the metadata
regarding the assignments,
indicating whether it
was a success or a failure,
the type,
and the corresponding event ID.
You should wait for these
successful assignment
notifications
to then proceed
with sending install commands
to the devices listed.
Another advantage
of our new management
endpoints is Ordering.
Let's say you get a request
to reassign some assets
from one group
of users to another.
This can be achieved
by you sequentially firing off
a disassociate followed
by an associate request.
First, you post
the disassociate request.
Apple then responds
with the event ID
for the disassociate.
Then, you post the subsequent
associate request.
Apple responds
with another event ID,
but this time,
for the associate.
Assuming you are subscribed,
Apple will post notifications
to you
as the disassociations complete.
Then, Apple will post
notifications to you
as the associations complete.
Big changes to our API,
like notifications,
allow you to keep your state
in-sync with Apple,
removing the need
to continually make requests
to ensure you have
the latest state.
Asynchronous processing allows
for everyone to have
a better experience,
whether it be employees
or students
getting access
to the content they need,
IT admins performing
large deployments rapidly,
or you effectively managing
an organization's assets.
The legacy API will continue
to be supported at this time.
Note that using the new
and legacy API versions
in conjunction
for the same token
will not be
officially supported.
This new API is the way forward
for Apps and Books Management
and is available today.
We look forward to you testing
and integrating
with this new API
as soon as possible,
providing your users
with the best possible
Apps and Books
Management experience.
For more insight,
please check out
our updated
developer documentation.
Thank you for your time,
and hope you enjoy
the rest of WWDC.
[ethereal percussion music]