[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Ross LeBeau: Hi,
and welcome to WWDC21.
My name is Ross LeBeau,
and I'm an engineer
on the StoreKit team.
Today, we're going to be
talking about StoreKit,
and this is actually
one of three sessions
designed to help you
implement client-side code,
build out your server
for in-app purchase,
and support your customers
and handle refunds.
This session is Meet StoreKit 2,
and you can find the other
two sessions here at WWDC21.
This session will focus on
client-side features
and implementation.
So let's get started!
Since StoreKit was
introduced in iOS 3,
it's created great opportunities
for you and your businesses.
Today, it exists on
four Apple platforms
and supports everything
from games to news apps,
indie titles
to international hits.
Over the years,
we've introduced great features
such as offer codes,
Family Sharing,
and StoreKit testing in Xcode.
But this year, we decided to go
back to the beginning.
Today, I'm excited
to introduce you to StoreKit 2!
StoreKit 2 is a brand new set of
modern and flexible Swift APIs
for working with
In-App Purchase
across iOS, macOS,
tvOS, and watchOS.
We've taken a new look
at StoreKit
with a Swift-first mindset.
We embraced some of
the newest language features,
like Swift concurrency
using the async/await pattern,
to create simple
yet powerful APIs.
We've also made
some huge updates
to the in-app purchase transactions,
making them much easier
to work with,
while also providing more
information and high security.
And we've added
more powerful APIs
specifically for subscriptions
in order to give you
deeper insight that you can use
to grow your business.
StoreKit 2 APIs live inside
the same StoreKit framework
that exists today
and focus on the core in-app
purchase experience
rather than replacing every API.
The new StoreKit 2 APIs are
comprised of five major areas:
Products, Purchases,
Transaction info,
Transaction history,
and subscription status.
Today I'm going to give you an
overview of each of these areas,
and my colleague Jakob
will be showing you how to use
the corresponding
StoreKit 2 APIs in real code.
So first, let's start with
the building blocks of StoreKit:
products and purchases.
The StoreKit 2 product struct
is a supercharged version
of the StoreKit product object
you're used to.
To start, we've added
additional data to it,
such as the product type
and extended
subscription information.
With StoreKit 2, we're making it
easier to do things
like find out
if the customer is eligible
for your introductory offer.
We're also making
StoreKit 2 products
forward-compatible
with new features.
We've accomplished this
by adding a wrapping type
called BackingValue
that allows you to retrieve data
contained in the product
by subscripting the products
directly.
This means that if we add data
to products in the future,
you'll always be able
to access them in StoreKit 2,
even on SDKs and devices
running operating systems
that have older versions
of StoreKit 2.
This means that you can
use the latest features
to provide new functionality
to a larger section
of your customer base.
With StoreKit 2, you request
products by calling
a static function
on the product type itself.
This requests product metadata
from the App Store
just like the existing
SKProductsRequest does.
But thanks to the new Swift
concurrency async/await pattern,
the StoreKit 2 product request
requires just one line of code.
Similarly, purchasing a product
in StoreKit 2
is another simple,
one-line task.
Purchase is now an instance
method on the product type,
meaning you can take those
products you just retrieved
and call purchase
directly on them.
Since the purchase method
also uses async/await,
you get the result of your
purchase inline in your code.
Now we know that not every
purchase is the same.
If you want to modify
purchase behavior
beyond the default settings,
StoreKit 2 has Purchase options.
A Purchase option is an item
that describes a single property
of a purchase.
You can compose Purchase options
into a set
which you pass
into the purchase method.
StoreKit 2 includes
purchase options for things
such as quantity
and promotional offers.
And in StoreKit 2,
we're adding a new option
called App account token.
The App account token
is a way for you to keep track
of which of your app's
user accounts
began and completed
a transaction.
It’s an opaque token
that you generate
which you can link to accounts
that your app owns.
It's easy to generate
an App account token,
because the only requirement
is that it conforms
to the UUID format.
You send up an App account token
on the purchase
as a Purchase option,
and this token is returned
in the transaction info
for that purchase.
The App account token stays in
the transaction info forever,
even across devices.
If your app supports
its own account system,
this can help you keep
track of which purchases
each in-app account has made,
regardless of the Apple ID
or device
that was used to purchase them.
So, we've talked about getting
products from the App Store
and initiating a purchase;
now what happens
when that purchase completes?
As you might expect,
StoreKit is going to return
a successful transaction to you
along with cryptographically
signed information.
Sounds familiar, right?
Well, StoreKit 2 is bringing
the biggest update
to in-app purchase transactions
ever.
To start, StoreKit 2
will be providing
an individually signed object
for every transaction.
Not only that,
but starting in StoreKit 2,
in-app purchase transaction info
will now be provided
in a very common,
easy-to-work-with format: JSON.
And since we know that
secure cryptographic signing
is an important part
of StoreKit purchases,
we're now using a common
standard used across the web
known as JSON Web Signature.
Plus, all the information
contained in the signed object
will now be available
through native StoreKit APIs,
making it easy to work with
this data in your app's code.
In fact, we'll show you
just how easy it is.
Here's Jakob with a
demonstration of these APIs
in real code.
Jakob Swank: Hi, I'm Jakob.
I'm an engineer
on the StoreKit team.
I'm really excited today
to be showing you how easy it is
to get up and running
with StoreKit 2 in your app.
On the right, I have an app
I'm building called Pocket Cars.
You can download
the sample code for this app
in the resources section of
this session and follow along.
The app has two main views.
There's a view for my collected
cars and a view for my store.
Let's go over to the store.
Currently, my store is empty
because I have no products
available for sale.
I'm going to go ahead
and implement those now.
To get up and running quickly,
I'm using StoreKit testing
in Xcode.
This allows me
to build and test my store
before defining products
in App Store Connect.
In my Xcode project,
I've already created
a StoreKit configuration file
defining the products
I want to sell.
This is the same configuration
file I was using for StoreKit;
I don't need to change
or migrate anything.
Here, I also have a plist
containing all
my product identifiers.
It's included as a resource file
built into my app
so I can use it at runtime.
To display these products
in my store,
I first need to make
a product request
using a set of the product
identifiers I want to display.
With StoreKit 2, I can do this
simply by calling a static
method on the Product struct.
[KEYSTROKES]
After I receive the products
from the App Store,
I want to separate them by type.
I can do this easily
with StoreKit 2
since the Product type
now provides a property
for the type as it's defined
on the App Store server.
In my app, I'm selling
three types of products:
fuel, cars,
and a navigation package.
Fuel is a consumable product --
once I use it, it's gone --
so I'll put all the consumables
in to the fuel array.
[KEYSTROKES]
Cars are a non-consumable.
Once I purchase a car,
I own it forever.
So I'll put
all the non-consumables
into the cars array.
[KEYSTROKES]
The navigation package
is a subscription product
with three levels of service.
My customers can subscribe to
one level of service at a time,
and they are billed
periodically.
Also, they can upgrade
or downgrade at any time
if they want to change
their level of service.
The App Store
will return a Product
for each level of service,
so I'll put all the
auto-renewable subscriptions
into the subscriptions array.
[KEYSTROKES]
I also want to sort my products
within each type by price,
lowest to highest.
[KEYSTROKES]
Let's run my app and check out
what I've done so far.
Now I'll navigate to the store.
Wow!
Before, my store was empty,
but now it's looking
pretty great
with all my products displayed.
With just one line of code,
I was able to request my app's
products from the App Store,
then I was able to group
and sort those products
based only on the metadata
I received
which made it easy
to build my store UI.
Now my products
are looking great,
but if I tap a buy button,
nothing happens.
That's because the purchase
method in my store
doesn't do anything.
It should initiate the purchase
with StoreKit.
We can do this simply
by calling the purchase method
on the product.
[KEYSTROKES]
As Ross mentioned,
StoreKit 2 was built
from the ground up
to use the new concurrency
capabilities of Swift.
This allows my app
to keep the code for purchasing
and processing
the result of that purchase
all within the same context
in order to keep my code
easy to read.
When a purchase completes,
a PurchaseResult is returned.
This PurchaseResult
lets me know
whether the purchase
was successful
or if it completed
in some other non-error state,
such as the user
cancelled the purchase
or the purchase needs
some extra bank validation
or approval from a parent.
To handle each case,
I'll just switch over them.
[KEYSTROKES]
If the PurchaseResult
is in the success state,
I also get
a verification result.
A verification result
contains two cases:
verified and unverified.
In StoreKit 2, the transaction
type contains the JWS payload
which represents
the signed transaction.
Every time my app receives
a transaction from StoreKit 2,
the transaction has passed
through a verification process
to confirm whether the payload
is signed by the App Store
for my app for this device.
You heard that right.
StoreKit 2 does transaction
verification for you.
Of course, how I choose to
handle the verification result
is entirely up to me
and the needs of my business.
For my app,
I'm going to make sure
this transaction I received
from StoreKit has been verified.
Here in my store, I'll create
a checkVerified method
I can use for any
VerificationResult.
[KEYSTROKES]
If the result is unverified,
I throw my own
failedVerification error
to alert other parts of my app.
If the result is verified,
I unwrap the transaction
and return it to the caller.
Now I can use
this checkVerified method
on the results of the purchase.
[KEYSTROKES]
Finally,
with my transaction verified,
I deliver the content
to my user.
[KEYSTROKES]
After the user has the content,
I need to make sure
I tell StoreKit
to finish the transaction.
[KEYSTROKES]
Then I need to return it
so my UI can get updated.
[KEYSTROKES]
My app has an account database
I maintain.
I want to include my app's
current logged in user
with the StoreKit purchase
so this information
is always available to my app
when it gets the App Store
signed transaction.
I can do this by creating an
appAccountToken purchase option
using a tokenized version
of my logged-in account
and passing that option
to the purchase method.
[KEYSTROKES]
OK.
We're all set with my
purchase method implementation.
Let's run my app again.
Now we're back in my store,
and I'm feeling
pretty adventurous.
So I'm going to purchase
a motorcycle
because I've always wanted one.
There's the payment sheet
from StoreKit
showing me the purchase
has been initiated properly.
I'll tap to confirm
the purchase.
StoreKit then displays an alert
showing the purchase
was successful.
After I dismiss that alert,
my buy button changes
to a green checkmark
showing my app
trusts the transaction
and my motorcycle
has been delivered.
There's one more important
thing I want to note here.
As I said previously,
sometimes a customer
will have to do
some extra verification
on their account
or they'll need
a parent's approval
before a purchase will complete.
In these cases,
the purchase result I receive
from product.purchase()
will be in a pending state.
This means after
the customer completes
the account verification
or their parent gives approval,
my app should update the UI to
reflect the completed purchase.
To listen for these
transaction updates,
I need to iterate
over a static property
on the transaction type.
[KEYSTROKES]
This property is
an infinite async sequence.
That means
it will continue iterating
over transaction updates
as they come in from StoreKit
until I choose to cancel
or break out of the for loop.
Here I'm creating
a detach task
which will return
a task handle I can use
to explicitly cancel
my update listener
when the store is deallocated.
Just like all transactions
I receive from StoreKit 2,
I want to check if the
verification result is verified
before delivering
content to the user.
I can use my previously
defined checkVerified method.
[KEYSTROKES]
And, just like with
a purchase response,
once I have
my verified transaction,
I need to deliver
the content to my user.
[KEYSTROKES]
And of course, I always need
to finish my transactions.
It's very important I start
my transaction update listener
as soon as my app launches
so I don't miss a single one.
I'm going to do this
as soon as my store is created,
which happens
right around app launch.
[KEYSTROKES]
In order to test
my update listener,
I'm going to enable Ask To Buy
in my Xcode test environment
to simulate a purchase response
in a pending state.
To do this, I select
my StoreKit configuration file
and in the Editor menu,
I select Enable Ask To Buy.
Let's run my app again
and do a purchase.
This time, after I confirm
on the payment sheet,
I see a new alert from StoreKit
saying I need to ask permission
to complete the purchase.
I'll go ahead and tap Ask.
The purchase response
is returned to my app
in a pending state.
To approve the purchase,
I'm going to open
the StoreKit testing in Xcode
transaction manager
and click the Approve button
in the top-right corner.
Great!
Immediately after
I approved the transaction,
my update listener received
the verification result
and the UI immediately changed
to show the approved purchase.
Now I have a brand-new, standard
5-seater to cruise around in.
I just showed you how easy
it is to request products,
start a purchase,
react to different
purchase results,
verify the integrity
of a transaction,
and receive updates from the App
Store for pending transactions,
all using StoreKit 2.
Now let's go back to Ross
for an introduction
on working with your
user's transaction history
and subscription status.
Ross: Wow!  It’s pretty amazing
to see these new APIs in action.
And automatic validation,
what more could you want?
What's that?
You love cryptography
and you still want to validate
the data yourself?
Not to worry.
StoreKit 2's
automatic validation
raises the bar for security,
but it isn't meant to completely
replace your own validation.
As always,
security lies on a spectrum
of strength, time,
and complexity.
I'll give you the scoop
on validation a bit later.
First, if you're as excited
about StoreKit 2 transactions
as I am,
you'll love to hear
that we're giving you lots of
new ways to work with them.
We're adding a new set of APIs
for querying
completed transactions
in the user's
transaction history.
In StoreKit 2, you can access
all of the user's
past transactions
with a single API call.
You can also access the latest
transaction for a product.
So if you want to see
just the most recent renewal
of a subscription, you can.
And we know that the number one
thing you need to know
is what products the user has
paid for access to right now.
So we've distilled
that information
into a single function
called CurrentEntitlements.
Current entitlements contains
all of the non-consumables
in the user's
transaction history,
as well as all of
the subscription transactions
that are currently active.
With this, you have all of
the information you need
to unlock everything the user
has paid for in your app.
And since this represents
only things
that the user should
have access to right now,
any transactions
that have been revoked
are not included
in the response.
Consumables are also
not included,
since they’re not a persistent
part of the transaction history.
Now, you must be thinking,
"I can't wait!
When can I start calling
these in my app?"
Well, with StoreKit 2,
every transaction
a user has ever completed
is available to your app
as soon as you ask for it.
This means that
when a user installs your app
on a new device,
you'll be able to tell
which products they are
entitled to get access to
on the very first time
your app is opened.
Furthermore, transaction history
will automatically update
across users' devices.
When your customer makes
a purchase on one device,
your app will be able
to see the purchase
on every other device
it's installed on.
In fact, if your app is running
when a purchase is made
on another device,
you'll be notified
about the new transaction.
Jakob mentioned
that it's important
to listen for transactions
as soon as your app starts,
and this is just
one more reason that's true.
So, all of this means
that users won't need to restore
completed transactions
when your app is reinstalled
or downloaded on a new device.
Everything should automatically
be fetched by StoreKit
and stay up to date.
But people use their Apple
devices in millions of ways
in millions of places.
In the rare case
that a user thinks
they should have a transaction
but you don't see it,
you can use
the App Store sync API.
This immediately resynchronizes
all StoreKit 2 transactions.
This is a replacement for the
restoreCompletedTransactions
API,
and you should provide UI
in your app
that allows users
to initiate the sync.
However, thanks to StoreKit 2's
automatic synchronization,
it should be very rare
that a user needs to initiate
a sync manually.
Automatic synchronization should
cover the majority of cases.
If a user does need
to initiate a manual sync,
they will be required
to authenticate their account.
For this reason,
you should only use this API
in response to user input.
Finally, all transactions
made using StoreKit 2 APIs
are available
in the original StoreKit APIs,
and vice versa.
So if your app has
existing transactions,
you will be able to see them
in the StoreKit 2 APIs
as soon as you start using them.
New purchases made
with the original StoreKit APIs
will be available via
StoreKit 2 APIs immediately,
and purchases made
with StoreKit 2
will also be available
inside the unified receipt
when it is refreshed.
In addition to
transaction history,
StoreKit 2 is also adding ways
for you to get
detailed information
about a user's
subscription status.
The subscription status
has three parts.
The first is
the latest transaction.
This conveniently lets you
access the last transaction
that occurred
for this subscription,
and it's the same
as if you called
the latest transaction
we talked about at earlier.
The second is the renewal state.
This is an enumeration
that tells you
the current state
of the subscription.
If you just want to know
what's going on
with the subscription right now,
just look at this value.
It'll tell you if it's
currently subscribed,
expired, in the grace period,
and more.
We've designed it to give you
a single place to look
in order to make it easy to base
app logic off this value.
And the final part of the subscription
status is the renewal info.
This is where you can see
all of the details
about a user's subscription.
It contains all kinds
of information
that isn't in
the transaction info
because this data can actually
change without a transaction.
For example,
in the renewal info,
you can find
the auto-renew status,
which tells you if the user has
auto-renew turned on or off
for this subscription.
You can even see the product ID
that their auto-renewal
is set for.
So if a user has recently
downgraded their subscription,
you can see that right here,
and maybe use that as
an opportunity to present them
with a winback offer
to stay at the higher tier.
If the subscription
is already expired,
you can use the renewal info
to see the expiration reason.
And the full renewal info has
all this data and more,
plus another critical feature.
That's right,
all you cryptography buffs,
the renewal info is signed
using JWS!
Just like the transaction info,
the renewal info is a critical
part of unlocking service
and making marketing decisions.
So we're giving you
the confidence to know
that it's valid
and directly from Apple.
And, to answer the question
that I'm sure is running through
your head right now,
yes, StoreKit 2 will
automatically validate
the renewal info for you.
One final thing to know about
the subscription status APIs
is that they return
an array of statuses.
This is because, in some cases,
users can have
multiple subscriptions
to the same product.
For example, a user may have
subscribed to your product,
and then also receive
a subscription
through Family Sharing.
You should check the array
to see what the highest level of
service they're entitled to is.
Now I'll hand it back to Jakob
to show you what it looks like
to work with
these transaction history
and subscription status APIs
in your app code.
Jakob: Thanks, Ross.
Let's go back to the app
I've been working on
and update it to use
the new transaction history
and subscription status APIs
Ross just talked about.
You'll notice the motorcycle
I previously purchased
doesn't have a green check,
and after I navigate away
from my store view, then back,
the standard 5-seater doesn't
have a green check either.
As a user, I can't tell
what I've already purchased.
This is a problem
easily solved with StoreKit 2.
At any time,
my app can query StoreKit
for which products
have been purchased
so I can keep my app's UI
always up to date.
Over in my Store.swift file,
the isPurchased method
currently returns only false.
Let's fix that
with a simple call
to Transaction.latest(for:).
[KEYSTROKES]
Then pass in
my product identifier
to get the most recent
transaction.
This StoreKit method returns
another verification result
telling me the transaction
has passed through
StoreKit 2's verification check.
I'll confirm the transaction
is verified and unwrap it
using the checkVerified method
I wrote previously.
[KEYSTROKES]
Then, I'll make sure my app
doesn't deliver content
for a transaction
that has been refunded
by checking
revocationDate equals nil.
[KEYSTROKES]
Also, subscriptions where
my customer has upgraded
to a higher level of service
in the middle of the period
will have the isUpgraded flag
set to true.
I want to make sure
my app is delivering
the highest level of service
my customer has subscribed to,
so the isPurchased method
should ignore
any upgraded transactions.
[KEYSTROKES]
For a subscription product,
the transaction type
tells only part of the story.
In addition to the date
of the transaction
and the expiration date
of the subscription,
I also want to know
when the next renewal date is,
and whether my customer
has turned off the auto-renewal
for their subscription
or whether their next
renewal period
will change the level of service
they're subscribed to.
To get all this information,
StoreKit 2 offers
a subscription status API.
In my SubscriptionsView.swift
file,
the updateSubscriptionStatus
method
is responsible for getting
the subscription status
from StoreKit
and displaying it to the user.
Because all of
my subscription products
belong to the same group,
I can use any of them
to get the current status
for the group.
I'll just choose
the first subscription product
from the store.
[KEYSTROKES]
Once I have a product,
I can get the status property
from the subscription.
[KEYSTROKES]
It's that easy.
As Ross mentioned,
it's possible for a user
to be paying for their own
personal subscription
while they also have
a subscription being shared
by a family member.
So the status property
will return an array
containing all the statuses
for each subscription.
Now, they could have
a standard tier shared with them
while they've personally
subscribed to the pro tier.
I want to make sure my user
is able to get
the highest level of service
they have access to,
so I'll iterate
through each status.
[KEYSTROKES]
Next, I'll check
whether the status
has a state of expired
or revoked.
I want to ignore these cases
and not display anything
to the user.
For all other cases,
I'll get the renewalInfo
and make sure it's verified
using the checkVerified method
on my store.
[KEYSTROKES]
Once I confirm
the renewalInfo is verified,
I'll compare
the level of service
to the previous products.
This check will get
the corresponding product
for the subscription status,
then it will compare
with any previous product,
and if it's a higher tier,
we set highestStatus
and highestProduct
to the new subscription.
Once I've checked
all my statuses
and I've determined
the highest level of service,
I'll set the status and current
subscription of my view.
[KEYSTROKES]
Let's build and run now.
Over in my store view,
the products
I previously purchased
now show a green checkmark
to indicate I already own them
and I don't need
to buy them again.
Let's see what happens
when I purchase one
of my subscription products.
After I confirm the purchase,
the status is displayed
right in my store.
I can let my user know
what they're subscribed to
and when their subscription
will renew
all using APIs
built into StoreKit 2.
Now how about this
My Cars view?
It should show all
of my purchased products,
but currently it's empty.
To fill this in, I could
iterate through all my products,
then get the latest transaction
for each,
check the transaction's
expiration date
and whether it
has been refunded,
but that sounds like a lot.
Thankfully, I can use
the power of StoreKit 2
and a new, simple,
and convenient API
to get all my user's
valid transactions
called currentEntitlements.
Over in the My Cars view,
I have this method
to refresh my purchased products
when the view is loaded.
Just like with
transaction updates,
I iterate over
the current entitlements.
[KEYSTROKES]
But unlike transaction updates,
the current entitlement's
async sequence is finite,
so it won't wait
in the for loop forever,
delivering new entitlements as
the user makes more purchases.
For each entitlement,
I want to check
the verification result
as I do with every other
transaction.
[KEYSTROKES]
Once I know they're verified,
I'll filter the entitlements
into different arrays
by switching over
the productType property,
just like I did with my original
product request.
[KEYSTROKES]
Current entitlements will
only return transactions
for non-consumable
and auto-renewable products.
I can ignore
any other product type
to complete my switch statement
and keep the Swift compiler
happy.
Once I have the transaction,
I need to get the associated
product to display in my UI.
For non-consumable
transactions,
I'll search the cars product
array for the product identifier
matching this transaction.
And likewise, I'll search
the subscriptions product array
to match any auto-renewable
transactions.
Let's run again
and check out my UI.
Now, when I go into
the My Cars view,
I see everything I've purchased.
All my cars are grouped together
at the top
and my subscription is below.
Now my app has a full working
store and it looks awesome!
And that's how you can use
the transaction history
and subscription status APIs
to make informed decisions
in your app about what UI
your users see.
Now let's go back to Ross
who will talk more in depth
on the JSON Web Signature
object.
Ross: Thanks again
for the fantastic demo, Jakob.
You can really see
how the new transaction
and subscription APIs
come in handy.
Now that we've seen the two ways
that StoreKit 2
uses JWS for security,
I promised we'd take
a closer look at it
and how you can do
your own validation.
JSON Web Signature
is comprised of three parts.
The first is the header,
which contains metadata
about the object.
This contains
crucial information
such as which algorithm
is used for signing
and where to find
the certificate
used to validate
the signature.
StoreKit 2 currently
uses an ECDSA algorithm,
which is supported natively
in Swift with CryptoKit.
For the certificate,
StoreKit 2 uses the x5c header,
which indicates that
the entire certificate chain
is included in the JWS data.
This means that no internet
connection is necessary
in order to validate
these JWS signatures.
The next part of the JWS data
is the payload.
This is the main information
such as transaction ID,
product ID, purchase date,
and so on.
Once you've validated
the signature,
this is where you go to read
all the data you want to know
about the transaction
or subscription.
And the final part of the JWS
data is the signature itself.
This is generated using
both the header and the payload.
Validating the JWS signature
is a well-documented
part of the standard,
so I recommend going
straight to the original source
if you're interested in writing
your own implementation.
I've included a link to this
document in the resources
associated with this session.
Once you've validated
the signature from the JWS data,
there are just a couple more
things you should do
to make sure the signed info
is valid for your app
and the current device.
First, you should make sure
that the bundle ID
present in
the signed info payload
matches the bundle ID
of your app.
We recommend that
for added security,
you embed your app's bundle ID
somewhere in the app,
rather than relying
on an API call,
and use that value to compare it
to the bundle ID in the payload.
And the final thing
you should do
is perform a device validation
check.
This ensures that the signed
info was actually generated
for the device
it currently on.
Use the StoreKit 2 API
AppStore.deviceVerificationID
to retrieve the current device
verification identifier.
Then, take the device
verification nonce
from the signed info
and append the device
verification identifier
you just got from StoreKit.
Perform a SHA384 hash on this
value and compare the result
to the device verification field
from the signed info.
If they match, then the
signed info was generated
for this device and your signed
info validation is complete.
One final thing to note
is that these new JWS objects
are for in-app purchase only.
So if you need to validate
the app receipt,
you should use the existing API
and process for that.
And of course, we are offering
new App Store server APIs
for these new JWS objects,
so you can retrieve and validate
them directly on your server.
Well, I hope you were as excited
to meet StoreKit 2
as we were to introduce it
to you today.
StoreKit 2 is making
in-app purchase even better
with new APIs that
give you more information
and are easier to use than ever.
This includes new
JSON-based info objects
for each transaction,
as well as APIs to give you
transaction details
and historical transaction data
in your native code.
Combine that with the new
subscription status APIs,
and StoreKit 2 unlocks
a wealth of possibilities
for your in-app purchases.
To learn even more
about in-app purchase,
I encourage you to watch
these other sessions
for server-side coding
and supporting customers.
Jakob and I are thrilled
we could introduce you
to StoreKit 2.
Thanks for joining us
at WWDC21!
♪