[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Pranav Sodhani: Hello
and welcome to WWDC!
My name is Pranav,
and I am part of the Display
and Color Technologies team
at Apple.
In this talk, we will introduce
a video quality tool
and show how you can use it
to evaluate perceptual quality
of compressed videos
in your apps or content
creation workflows
All right.
Let's start by looking at a
typical video delivery workflow.
In such a workflow,
the high-quality source video
undergoes video compression
and, optionally,
video downscaling to generate
videos with lower bit rates.
And these low-bit rate videos
can then be easily delivered
over bandwidth-constrained
networks.
A few possible ways
to use such workflows
include AVFoundation APIs
such as AVAssetWriter,
apps such as Compressor,
or it can be one of your own
video compression workflows.
Now, downscaling and compression
can add video coding
and scaling artifacts.
And this will impair
the source video
and create visible artifacts.
One example of such artifact
is blockiness
in the compressed video,
which is shown in the frame
on the right side.
Another example is when
the video appears blurry
and video details
start disappearing.
Such artifacts
can adversely affect
a consumer's
video quality experience.
We know that consumers
are expecting
a high-quality
video experience.
So it's important to deliver
on this expectation.
Now, the first step to do this
is to evaluate the quality
of your delivered content.
And the most accurate
way of doing this
is to have real people
watch the videos
and rate them
on a video quality scale.
But this is very time consuming
and not scalable
if you want to evaluate
a high volume of videos.
Fortunately,
there's another way.
What we need here
is an objective way
to characterize video quality,
so that we can automate
the process for speed
and scalability.
In such a setup, the perceptual
video quality tool
will take the compressed video
and the source video as input
and output
a video quality score.
This score can be
a floating point number
in the range of one to five
and mimic how real people would
have rated the compressed video.
Today, we are very excited
to enable our developers
with such a perceptual
video quality tool.
We are calling it the
Advanced Video Quality Tool
or AVQT in short.
Let's learn more about AVQT.
So what exactly is AVQT?
Well, AVQT comes as a macOS
command line executable.
And it attempts to mimic
how real people
rate quality
of compressed videos.
You can use AVQT
to compute both frame level
and segment level scores,
where a segment is typically
a few seconds long.
And, of course,
we have added support
for all AVFoundation-based
video formats in AVQT.
This includes SDR,
as well as HDR video formats
such as HDR10, HLG,
and Dolby Vision.
Next, we want to discuss
three key attributes of AVQT
that make it very useful
across applications.
First, we will see how well AVQT
aligns with human perception.
Then we will talk about
AVQT's computational speed.
And finally,
we will show why viewing
setup awareness is important
when predicting video quality.
Let's get into details
for each of these.
AVQT correlates well with
human opinions on video quality.
And it works well
across content types,
such as animation,
natural scenes, or sports.
We have found that traditional
video quality metrics
such as PSNR
and structural similarity --
or SSIM in short --
typically do not work very well
across content types.
Let's look at one example.
Now, this is a frame from
a high-quality sports clip,
which is our first source video.
Let's look at the same frame
in the compressed video.
You can see that the frame
does appear to be
of sufficiently high
perceptual quality.
Rightly so, it gets a PSNR score
of around 35
and an AVQT score of 4.4.
Next, we go with
the same exercise
for our second source video.
The compressed video
in this case
seems to have visible artifacts.
In particular,
you can see some artifacts
on the face of the person.
Interestingly, it gets the same
PSNR score of around 35,
but this time AVQT rates it
around 2.5,
implying poor quality.
We think the AVQT score
is the correct prediction here.
Note that this is just one
example we have picked
to illustrate what can go wrong
in cross-content evaluations.
We wanted to test AVQT's
perceptual accuracy
on a diverse set of videos.
So we evaluated it
on publicly available
video quality datasets.
These datasets include
source videos,
compressed videos,
and video quality scores
provided by human subjects.
Here, we will show you
the results on two datasets:
Waterloo IVC 4K
and VQEG HD3.
The Waterloo IVC dataset
includes 20 source videos
and 480 compressed videos,
spanning both coding
and scaling artifacts.
It covers four different
video resolutions
and two different
video standards.
The VQEG HD3 dataset
is relatively smaller.
It has nine source videos
and 72 compressed videos.
And these were generated
using video coding
at 1080p video resolution.
And to measure performance
of a video quality metric
objectively,
we make use of correlation
and distance measures.
Pearson Correlation Coefficient,
or PCC in short,
measures how well
the predicted scores
correlate
with subjective scores.
A higher PCC value
implies better correlation.
And RMSE measures how far off
the predictions are
from subjective scores.
A lower RMSE value would imply
higher prediction accuracy.
Now, we want to evaluate how
well can AVQT predict the scores
given by human subjects.
On the x-axis here,
we have the ground truth
subjective video quality scores.
And on the y-axis, we have
scores predicted by AVQT.
Every point here
represents a compressed video.
As you can see
from the scatter plot,
except for a few outliers,
AVQT does a great job in
predicting the subjective scores
for this dataset.
This is also reflected in the
high PCC and low RMSE scores.
And we see a high performance
on the VQEG HD3 dataset as well.
Let's move on and talk about
AVQT's computational speed.
Note that high computational
speed is quite important
to ensure scalability.
AVQT's algorithm is designed and
optimized to run fast on Metal.
This implies that you can run
through large video files
very quickly.
It also takes care of all
preprocessing natively.
For you, this means you don't
have to decode your videos
and scale them offline.
AVQT does that for you.
You should note that AVQT
runs through a 1080p video
at 175 frames per second.
So if you have a 10-minute long
1080p video at 24 Hz,
AVQT can compute its quality
in under 1.5 minutes.
The final attribute
we want to talk about
is viewing setup awareness.
Your viewing setup can affect
the video quality you perceive
when watching a video.
In particular,
factors such as display size,
display resolution,
and viewing distance
can mask or exaggerate
artifacts in the video.
To address this,
AVQT takes these parameters
as input to the tool
and then attempts
to predict the right trend
as these factors change.
Let's take a look
at one such case.
Consider two scenarios.
In scenario A, you're watching
a 4K video on a 4K display
at a viewing distance of 1.5
times the height of the screen.
In scenario B,
you are watching the same video
on the same display
but now at a viewing distance
which is three times
the height of the screen.
Clearly, in scenario B you will
miss out on some of the artifacts
which were visible when
you were watching it closely.
This implies that your perceived
video quality in scenario B
will be higher
than in scenario A.
And AVQT can capture such trends
at different quality levels.
The chart here shows that
as viewing distance increases
from 1.5H to 3H,
AVQT scores increase as well.
We recommend you go over
the README document
available with the tool
for more information on this.
Well, now that we have
all of you excited about AVQT,
let me show how you can
use the tool the right way.
We will be making AVQT available
to all of you soon
via the Developer
downloads portal.
Let me walk you through a demo.
So I have already
downloaded the tool
and installed AVQT
on this system.
If you look at the output
of "which AVQT",
you can see AVQT is placed
in the usr/local/bin directory.
Now, you can invoke
AVQT help command
to read more about the usage
of different flags
supported by AVQT.
Let's see what I have
in my current directory.
I have a sample reference and
a sample compressed video
that I will use for the demo.
So let me run AVQT through them.
We will provide the reference
and test files as input
and specify an output file.
Let's name the output file
sample_output.csv.
The tool prints the progress
and reports the segment scores
on the screen.
The default segment duration
is six seconds
and since this clip
is five seconds long,
we have only one segment.
Next, let's look
at the output file.
You can see
the frame level scores here.
And, finally, we have
the segment level scores
towards the bottom.
Now, in the demo,
we showed a few options,
but the tool has several other
features built into it as well.
For example, you can use
the segment-duration
and the temporal-pooling flags
to change the way frame level
scores are aggregated.
Similarly, you can specify
the viewing setup
using the viewing-distance
and display-resolution flags.
Please refer to the README
for more details on this.
All right.
So far we have learned about
some of the key attributes
of AVQT.
We have also seen how to use
the command line tool
on a pair of videos to generate
video quality scores.
Now let's take a look at
a specific case
where you can use AVQT
to optimize bit rates for HLS.
HLS tiers are encoded
at different bit rates.
And we know that
choosing these bit rates
is not an easy process always.
To help with this,
we have published
some bit rate guidelines
in the HLS Authoring
Specification document.
Please note that these bit rates
are only initial
encoding targets
for typical content
delivered via HLS.
We also know that
different content
has different
encoding complexity,
which implies that
the optimal bit rate
varies across different content.
So the bit rate that works well
for one type of content --
for example,
an animation movie --
might not work well
for a sporting event.
Here's how you can use AVQT as
feedback to help you determine
optimal bit rate
for your content.
First, we start with
our initial target bit rates.
We use this bit rate to encode
our source video
and create the HLS tier.
We then use the source video
and the encoded HLS tier
to compute video quality
scores using AVQT.
Finally, we can analyze
AVQT scores
to decide if we want to increase
or decrease the target bit rate
for the HLS tier.
To demonstrate
this with an example,
let's pick a specific HLS tier.
Here we are choosing
the 2160p tier
at 11.6 megabits per second.
We will then encode our previous
two sequences --
animation and sports --
with this recommended bit rate.
Once we have
the encoded tiers ready,
we will use AVQT to compute
their video quality scores.
The chart here shows AVQT scores
for the two video sequences.
For this particular tier, we
can expect a high video quality,
so we are setting
the threshold to be 4.5,
indicating close-to-excellent
quality.
You can see that
while this bit rate
is good enough
for this animation clip,
it is not sufficient
for the sports clip.
So we go back
and use this feedback
to adapt our bit rate target.
In particular, we need
to increase our bit rate target
for the sports clip
and recompute its AVQT score.
Let's aim for a 10-percent
increase in bit rate.
Here we have plotted our new
AVQT scores for the sports clip.
The updated scores now lie above
our expected threshold
of four and a half.
And it also resembles video
quality of the animation content
much more closely.
To wrap up, here are a few
important things
that we want you
to take away from this talk.
Video compression
can lead to visible artifacts,
which affects consumers'
video quality experience.
You can evaluate the quality
of your compressed videos
using AVQT.
AVQT comes as a macOS
command line tool,
is quick to compute,
and is viewing setup aware.
It also has support
for all AVFoundation-based
video formats.
Finally, you can use AVQT
to optimize the video quality
of your HLS tiers.
Thank you very much!
♪