[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Jon] Hi.
Welcome to the Sound Analysis
session at WWDC.
My name is Jon Huang.
I'm a researcher
on the audio team.
Today, my colleague,
Kevin, and I
will introduce enhancements
to sound classification
made available through
the SoundAnalysis framework
and CreateML.
In 2019, we made it possible
to train sound classification
models using CreateML.
We showed it was easy to create
sound classification models
and to deploy them
in Apple devices.
When you use this framework,
all of the computations
are optimized
for hardware acceleration
and are done locally on-device.
This helps preserve
your user's privacy
because audio is never sent
to the Cloud.
We leveraged the Sound Analysis
framework to introduce
the Accessibility Feature
called Sound Recognition.
This feature can provide
notifications to the user
when certain sounds are
heard in the environment
like alarms, pets,
and other household sounds.
This is just one application
of sound classification.
Let's see what else
we can do with it.
The demo app is using
my Mac's built-in microphone
to listen to sounds
in the environment.
It's passing audio
through a sound classifier
and displaying
the classification results
in the UI.
So as I'm chatting to you,
speech is detected.
Please sit back with me
for a bit and see what happens.
Make yourself comfortable.
Let's start with some music.
Hey Siri, play "Catch a Vibe"
by Karun and Mombru.
[Siri] Now playing "Catch
a Vibe" by Karun and Mombru.
[Karun and Mombru's
"Catch a Vibe"]
♪ ♪
[Karun and Mombru]
♪ Oh, oh, oh ♪
[Jon] Notice the classifier
is picking up
both music and singing sounds.
[Karun and Mombru]
♪ I don't know anyone ♪
♪ Who feels so right ♪
♪ Don't know anyone
who makes me ♪
♪ Catch a vibe,
feel the frequency...♪
[Jon] Now please join me
for some tea.
[Karun and Mombru]
♪ Feel all right, baby ♪
♪ We could see ♪
♪ If we could be right ♪
♪ See if it's something
about the way you smile ♪
♪ Hold your breath
and, baby, we could ♪
♪ Catch a vibe,
feel the frequency ♪
only you and me ♪
♪ Feel all right, baby,
we could see ♪
♪ If we could be ♪
♪ I've said, I've said ♪
♪ It's part of me ♪
♪ All the part you see ♪
♪ You should be proud of...♪
[Jon sighs]
[Jon whispering]
This is good tea.
[Karun and Mombru]
♪ You're my baby, gee ♪
♪ You a cart, I see... ♪
[phone ringing]
[Karun and Mombru]
♪ How could this be? ♪
♪ How could this be?... ♪
[Jon] Hey, Siri. Stop.
[music ends]
Now it's reasonable to assume
that I collected some data for
each of these sound categories
and trained a custom model
using CreateML.
Yes, I could have done that,
but actually,
the classifier used is built-in.
New to this year,
we have a sound classifier
built right into the Sound
Analysis framework.
It's never been easier to enable
sound classification
in your app.
It's supported on all platforms.
The built-in classifier
is all about simplifying
the developer experience.
It removes the need
for collecting and labeling
massive amount of data,
specialized machine learning
and audio expertise,
and lots of compute power
in order to develop
a high-accuracy model.
The less time you have to worry
about these details,
the more time you can spend
enriching the user experience
in your app.
It only takes
a few lines of code
to enable sound classification.
I'll show you what
this classifier can do.
There's over 300 categories
for you to use.
Let's take a closer look.
We can classify sounds
of domestic animals,
livestock animals,
and wild animals.
For music, many instruments
can be recognized:
keyboard instruments,
percussion,
string instruments,
wind instruments.
We can detect
various human sounds:
group activities,
respiratory sounds,
vocalizations.
Then there's sounds
of things like vehicles,
alarms, tools, liquids,
and so much more.
These ready-to-use categories
are available for you to try.
I'm going to turn it over
to Kevin
to walk you through how to use
this sound classifier.
[Kevin] Thanks, Jon.
Hi, I'm Kevin,
a software engineer
on the Audio team.
I'd like to show you how to use
the new built-in
sound classifier
by taking a look
at a small application I built.
I was hoping Jon would show
how well the classifier works
with cowbell,
but since it didn't fit
in his demo,
I came up with another idea.
I have some media on my Mac
that I collected
while preparing
for this session,
and I'm pretty sure that I have
some old footage
containing cowbell.
I'd love to show it to you,
but first I have to find it.
This means I'll have to find
the right file,
and I'll have to look inside
to find just the right part.
So how will I do this?
I'll write a simple program
that uses the built-in
sound classifier
to read a file and tell me
whether a certain sound
is inside.
If the sound is found,
the program can use
the classifier
to tell me the time
at which it occurred.
I can then use Shortcuts,
now available on macOS,
to create a workflow
that runs my program
over lots of files.
When my program finds a sound,
the workflow can automatically
use the reported detection time
to extract a video clip
containing the sound.
This will work great
for finding a cowbell clip.
So let's see it in action.
Here, I have a folder
full of videos.
I'll select all the files
and kick off my shortcut
using the Quick Actions menu.
I'm asked to select the sound
that I'd like to find,
so from the list of options,
I'll choose Cowbell.
Now, my shortcut is running,
and after just a few moments,
it finds the sound
I'm looking for
and shows it to me
in a Finder window.
Let's take a look.
[cowbell jangling]
Looking good, Jon.
Let's take a closer look
at the shortcut that I used.
When my shortcut starts,
it collects a list
of all the sounds
that it can recognize,
and it asks me to pick one.
Using my choice,
it visits each of the files
that I selected in Finder
and looks for the sound inside.
When my sound is detected,
it extracts a few seconds
from the video
around the time
that the sound occurred
and shows me the resulting clip.
Of these steps,
two of them make use
of the built-in classifier.
These are the steps
that I implemented
in my own custom application
for Shortcuts to use on demand.
Though I won't talk
about Shortcuts in more detail,
if you're curious to learn more,
please refer to the WWDC session
entitled
"Meet Shortcuts for macOS."
Now let's look
at the implementation
for my app's two custom actions.
The first action reports
all of the sounds
that the app can recognize.
Since the app is using
the built-in sound classifier,
it can recognize
a few hundred sounds.
Here's a function I wrote
to get these sounds.
I create
an SNClassifySoundRequest
using a new initializer
that allows me to select
the built-in classifier.
Once I have this request,
I can use it to query
the list of sounds
that the classifier supports.
The app's second action
tells Shortcuts
when a sound is heard
within a file.
To implement this, I'll perform
sound classification
and report back the first time
that the sound is detected,
if it's detected at all.
To perform sound classification,
I'll need to prepare
three objects.
First, I'll need
an SNClassifySoundRequest,
which I can use to configure
sound classification.
Second, I'll need
an SNAudioFileAnalyzer,
which will let me
target classification
toward a particular file.
The third object will require
a little extra attention.
I'll need to define
my own Observer type,
which will handle the results
of classification.
Skipping the Observer for now,
here's some code for preparing
the first two of these objects.
I can create
the SNClassifySoundRequest
using the built-in classifier,
and I can create
an SNAudioFileAnalyzer
using a URL to the file
I want to classify.
If, at this point,
I had an Observer ready to go,
it would be easy to start
sound classification,
but defining that Observer
is the missing piece.
So let's do that.
I'm starting here
with a bare Observer
that inherits from NSObject
and conforms to the
SNResultsObserving protocol.
I'll initialize instances
with the sound label
I want to search for,
and I'll add
a CMTime member variable
to store the time
at which I detect the sound.
I just need
to implement the request:
didProduce result method.
This method will be called
when results are produced
by sound classification,
so I expect to receive instances
of SNClassificationResult.
I can use
the classificationForIdentifier
method of the result
to extract information
about the label
that I'm searching for.
I'll query the confidence score
associated with the label,
and if that score exceeds
a certain threshold,
I'll consider the sound
to be detected.
When I notice the detection
for the first time,
I'll save the time
at which the sound occurred
so that I can provide it
to Shortcuts later.
With that,
my Observer is complete,
and I have all the pieces needed
to determine when a sound occurs
within a file.
This example touches
on two important topics
that I'd like
to discuss further.
First, I'll talk
about time of detection,
and then I'll talk
about detection thresholds.
Let's start
with time of detection.
When you classify audio,
the signal gets broken up
into overlapping windows.
For each of these windows,
you'll get a result
that tells you
what sounds were detected
and how confidently.
You'll also get a time range,
which tells you what part
of the audio was classified.
In my app,
when I detect a sound,
I use the result's time range
to determine
when the sound occurred.
But the time range
can be impacted
when the duration
of a window changes.
You can customize
the window duration
to make it big or small
based on your use case.
Short windows work well
when working with short sounds,
like a drum tap.
This is because you can capture
all the important features
of that sound
within a small window of time.
The small window doesn't cut out
any important information.
The advantage of using
a small window duration
is that it allows you
to more closely pinpoint
the moment at which
a sound occurred.
But small window durations
may not be appropriate
when working with longer sounds.
A siren, for example,
may contain both rising
and falling pitches
over a longer period of time.
Capturing all of these pitches
together in a single window
can help sound classification
correctly detect the sound.
In general, it's good
to use a window duration
long enough to capture
all the important parts
of the sounds
that you're interested in.
If you'd like to edit
the window duration,
you can set
the windowDuration property
of SNClassifySoundRequest.
Note, though,
that not all window durations
are supported.
Different classifiers
might support
different window durations.
You can check what
window durations are supported
by reading
the windowDurationConstraint
property
of SNClassifySoundRequest.
The built-in classifier
supports window durations
between 1/2 second long
and 15 seconds long.
A duration of one second
or longer
is a great starting point
when adopting the classifier
in your app.
Let's talk next
about confidence thresholds.
In my app, I considered
a sound to be detected
any time the confidence
for that sound rose
above a fixed threshold.
I chose a value of 0.5
for my threshold,
but there are some things
to consider
when choosing a threshold
for your own app.
The classifier can detect
multiple sounds
at the same time.
When this happens,
you may notice
that several labels score
with high confidence.
Unlike when using a custom model
trained using CreateML,
label scores do not add up
to a value of one.
The confidences are independent
and shouldn't be compared
against one another.
Because confidence scores
are independent,
you may find it useful to choose
different confidence thresholds
for different sounds.
Choosing a threshold
involves a tradeoff.
A higher confidence threshold
reduces the probability
that a sound will be
falsely detected,
but it also increases
the probability
that a true detection
will be missed
because it wasn't strong enough.
When you select a threshold
for your application,
you'll need to find
a value that achieves
the right balance of these
factors for your use case.
Note that confidence scores
may change
when you set
a custom window duration,
so this can impact
your thresholds as well.
One final thing to keep in mind
when using
the built-in classifier
is that some sounds are similar.
Among the large number of sounds
that the classifier can identify
are several groups of sounds
that can be difficult
to differentiate
using audio alone,
even for a human.
Where possible,
it's best to be selective
about the sounds
that you pay attention to.
You should try to watch
only for sounds
that are likely to occur
in the contexts
where your app will be used.
With that,
let's turn back to Jon
to learn about
what's new in CreateML
regarding sound classification.
[Jon] Thanks, Kevin,
for that great example.
I'm glad you had fun
with that cowbell video.
Now let me show you
what's new in CreateML
or, specifically,
how you can improve
your custom models
by leveraging the power
of the built-in classifier.
The built-in classifier
was trained with a ton of data
across a vast number
of categories.
So the model actually contains
a lot of knowledge
about sound classification.
All this knowledge
can be utilized
for the training of your
custom model using CreateML.
I'll show you how this works.
The sound classifier
can be separated
into two different networks.
The first part is
the feature extractor,
and the second part is
the classifier model.
The feature extractor,
sometimes known
as the embedding model,
is the backbone of the network.
It takes an audio waveform
and transforms it
into a low-dimensional space.
A well-trained feature extractor
organizes acoustically
similar sounds
into nearby locations
in the space.
For example,
sounds of guitar
would cluster together
but are placed away
from drum and car sounds.
Now, the second part
of this pipeline
is the classifier model.
It takes the output
of the feature extractor
and computes
the class probabilities.
The classifier benefits
from being paired
with a good feature extractor,
like the one we have embedded
into the built-in classifier.
We're making
the built-in classifier's
feature extractor
available to you.
It is called
Audio Feature Print.
When you train your own
custom model in CreateML,
your model will be paired
with Audio Feature Print.
With this, your model benefits
from all the knowledge contained
in the built-in classifier.
Compared to the previous
generation feature extractor,
Audio Feature Print has
improvements across the board.
Even though this network
is smaller and faster,
it achieves higher accuracy
on all benchmark data sets
we compared against.
And like
the built-in classifier,
models using
Audio Feature Print support
a flexible window duration.
You can select a long
window duration to optimize
for sounds like sirens
or a short window duration
for sounds like drum taps.
Audio Feature Print is the new
default feature extractor
when you train a custom model
using CreateML.
The Window duration is
the length of audio used
to generate a single
feature while training.
It defaults to three seconds,
but you can adjust it
to suit your needs.
CreateML gives you
the option to select
a window duration between
1/2 second to 15 seconds.
For a more detailed example
of training a custom model,
you can check out
the 2019 session
on "Training Sound
Classification Models
in CreateML."
It also shows you how to use
the Sound Analysis Framework
to run the custom model.
Thanks for joining us
in the session
on Sound Analysis.
Today, we introduced
a powerful new sound classifier
built into the OS.
Along with it,
we've upgraded the feature
extractor in CreateML.
These will unlock
new possibilities,
and we can't wait to see what
you'll do with them in your app.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC.
[upbeat music]