[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Willem Mattelaer: Hi,
my name is Willem
and I'm an engineer
working on Group Activities.
I'll be joined by Angus and Adam
to talk about how you can create
custom experiences
with Group Activities.
To start, I'll introduce the app
we're going to be working on
in this session
and explain why
it's a great candidate
to add Group Activities
support to.
Next, we'll go over
the activity creation
and session management steps
and explain the differences
compared to making
a media experience.
Finally, we'll mention some ways
you could polish the experience
your users have
while using your app.
Group Activities allows you
to build shared experiences
across devices with SharePlay.
Although the focus is on
creating media experiences,
that shouldn't prevent you from
letting your creativity go wild
and see how your app
could be experienced
across multiple devices.
We will be building
on some of the concepts
that were introduced in the
"Coordinate media experiences
with Group Activities" session.
I highly recommend
checking that one out.
In this session,
we'll be working on an app
called DrawTogether
that allows you to --
you guessed it --
draw together
while in FaceTime.
It's a pretty simple app
where almost the entire screen
is the canvas
and everyone gets a random color
they can use to draw with.
But despite being simple,
it's still incredibly fun
to draw with my friends
and admire the great skill
of some of them
or laugh at their poor drawings.
I definitely fall into
the second category myself.
Let me show you a quick demo
of what we're going
to work towards.
Hey guys, what's up?
Adam, I saw you had
a question for me.
Adam Syed: Yeah.
So Angus and I were talking,
and he mentioned that
you're a really good artist --
like a grade A Picasso.
So you got to show us, man!
Angus Burton: I've seen
some of Willem's drawings,
and they're impressive.
Willem: I think, Angus, you're
exaggerating just a tiny bit.
But I'm happy to show you
what I can do.
Let's go to
the DrawTogether app.
Adam: OK.
Can we do, like,
a pastoral landscape?
Willem: Sure, uh... let me start
by drawing a house, maybe.
Adam: [LAUGHS] OK.
Angus: Willem, this house
is looking pretty basic, man.
Maybe I'll help you out
with a sun.
Adam: I'll try a tree.
Willem: That tree
is way too tall. [LAUGHS]
Adam: No, the sun's
too low, man. [LAUGHTER]
Willem: Let me add some grass.
Adam: I'll draw some more trees.
Willem: OK. Um, I think
I'm going to call it.
We are not artists and we should
stop what we're doing right now.
Let's -- [LAUGHTER]
I'll talk to you guys later, OK?
Adam: [LAUGHING] OK
Angus: Bye.
Willem: As you saw,
one of the core experiences
of the Group Activities API
is allowing you
to do things together
while being physically apart.
The real-time interactions
that you can unlock
and the instant reaction
your users will get,
since they can see
and hear everyone else,
can lead to some truly
magical moments.
This is something you should
keep in mind when considering
how to integrate
Group Activities in your app.
There are two steps
to adopt Group Activities:
activity creation
and session management.
We've covered this
in more detail
in the "Coordinate media
experiences" session.
In this session, let's take
a look at how these steps change
when building
a custom experience,
starting with activity creation.
There are two parts
to create a Group Activity.
First you configure
your activity,
and that's followed
by activating the activity.
Compared to
a media Group Activity,
only the configure part is
different for a custom activity.
When configuring the activity,
you have to think about
the specific experience
that you want to share
between all the participants.
The activity should contain
all the information
that remains constant
throughout that experience.
If you've watched the
"Coordinate media experiences
with Group Activities" session,
this should look familiar.
We've defined
a DrawTogether struct
that conforms to
the GroupActivity protocol,
and we've implemented the
metadata property where
we construct the associated
metadata with a title.
Now to make this
a custom activity,
we'll just need to set
the right type on the metadata.
By setting that to generic,
we configure this activity
to be a custom activity.
And that's all you need to do
when configuring
a custom activity
compared to a media one.
Now let's jump right into Xcode
and start creating
our custom Group Activity
in the DrawTogether app.
First, let me quickly
walk you through the code
that we start with.
DrawTogether is a SwiftUI app
using the SwiftUI app lifecycle.
ContentView is the main view
of the app.
At the top of the view,
there is an indicator
that shows the color
that will be used when drawing.
Below that is the CanvasView.
This takes a canvas
and will be responsible
for drawing all the strokes
in the canvas
and updating the canvas
based on any user input.
Finally, at the bottom
there is a ControlBar,
which contains
a couple of controls
that could be useful
while drawing.
Currently we have
a single button there
to clear the canvas
and start from scratch.
The canvas itself
consists of an array of strokes
where each stroke has a color,
an identifier,
and a list of points.
The canvas also has
an activeStroke --
which represents a stroke
that the local user
is currently drawing --
and the stroke color
that will be used by the user.
Let's now start
with configuring our activity.
Before we do that,
I'll have to add the
Group Activities entitlement.
I do that by going
to the project settings,
and in the
Signing & Capabilities tab,
I'll add a new capability.
I'll search for Group Activities
and select it.
Now that we have
the entitlement,
let's finally configure
our activity.
I'll add a new file by going
to File > New > File...
and selecting Swift File.
I'll call it "DrawTogether"...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and click Create.
First, I'll import
our framework.
[KEYSTROKES]
Next, I'll define a new struct
called "DrawTogether"
that conforms to
the GroupActivity protocol.
The GroupActivity protocol
has two properties
that should be implemented:
activityIdentifier and metadata.
For the activityIdentifier,
I will rely on
the default implementation.
The metadata property is,
however, still necessary.
So let's add it.
In this computed property,
I create
a GroupActivityMetadata object,
and I set the title.
I also set the type
to be generic.
This is crucial
for a custom activity.
Finally, I return
the metadata object.
Now that we've configured
the activity,
we still need to activate it
at the appropriate moment.
I'll add a new button
to activate it --
and what better place for that
then our control bar?
I'll add the button
at the start of our HStack.
[KEYSTROKES]
For the label of the button,
we're using an SF Symbol.
And in the action closure,
we'll create a new instance
of our custom Group Activity
and call activate on it.
And that's all that is necessary
to activate our activity.
I just showed how to configure
a custom Group Activity
and how to activate it.
These are the two parts
necessary
for the activity creation step.
Now, I'll hand it off to Angus
who will tell you about
the session management step.
Angus: Thanks, Willem.
Next, we are going to talk about
how you can send and receive
custom data in your application
using Group Activities.
This is at the heart of creating
unique SharePlay experiences
with Group Activities.
From the previous session
titled,
"Coordinate media experiences
with Group Activities,"
you should be familiar
with the three steps
of receiving a session,
preparing for playback,
and joining a session.
Instead of playback
synchronization,
we need to configure a session
for our custom experience.
But before we jump into that,
let's add the code to receive
the Group Session and join in.
Let's go back to Xcode,
and the first thing we'll do
is to navigate to ContentView,
and import GroupActivities.
[KEYSTROKES]
Next, we will create
an async task
to receive our GroupSession.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now that we have a GroupSession,
we need a place to store it.
Let's store it on our Canvas
object using a new method
that we'll call
"configureGroupSession".
[KEYSTROKES]
Now, let's navigate over
to Canvas
and implement the
configureGroupSession method.
We'll start by going to the top
and making sure to import
GroupActivities.
[KEYSTROKES]
Let's go to
the bottom of our file
and implement
our new method next.
[KEYSTROKES]
Here we assigned
the groupSession object
we receive to a new property
on our class.
Also note that
we reset the canvas
before setting
the groupSession property.
Last but not least,
let's add the code
to join the groupSession.
[KEYSTROKES]
At this point,
we should be able to build
and compile our project.
Let's test that now
by going to Product > Build.
Great.
Now that we've set up the code
to receive and join
our Group Session,
let's look at how to configure
the session
for sending and receiving
custom data in our application.
For configuring the session,
we'll be using
GroupSessionMessenger,
which provides a simple API
to send and receive raw data
or structured messages
to and from participants
within the Group Session.
Let's look at how to use
GroupSessionMessenger next.
To start, we will create
a GroupSessionMessenger
from our groupSession.
The first step in using
GroupSessionMessenger
is to define what type of data
needs to be exchanged
between participants
in your application.
In DrawTogether,
the specific data we need
to share with other devices
are the strokes themselves.
We could represent
a stroke with three properties:
an identifier, a color,
and a coordinate point.
Note that we make
our UpsertStrokeMessage
conform to the Codable protocol.
This is because
GroupSessionMessenger
allows us to send and receive
structured messages
and will automatically handle
the serialization
and deserialization for us,
as long as the messages
are codable.
The second step
for configuring the session
is to receive data
using the Messages API
on GroupSessionMessenger.
For DrawTogether,
we will need to handle receiving
the UpsertStrokeMessages.
The messages API shown here is
able to take the codable type
and returns an async sequence --
which hands us a tuple
containing messages
of that type --
and the context
surrounding the message --
which includes information like
which participant
sent that message.
The third step for configuring
the session is to send data
using the send API
on GroupSessionMessenger.
For DrawTogether, we will
send an UpsertStrokeMessage
to all participants
within the group.
Note that the send API
is an async throwing method.
The errors it throws should be
handled appropriately
by your application.
Now, let's go to Xcode and add
our GroupSessionMessenger code.
We'll start by navigating
to the Canvas source file
and creating
a GroupSessionMessenger
from our Group Session.
We'll add the messenger property
to the Canvas
which will hold the messenger
object we just created.
[KEYSTROKES]
Next we need to define
the UpsertStrokeMessage,
which will be sent and received
between participants.
Let's create a new file
for this.
We'll do that by going
to File > New > File...
selecting Swift File...
...and let's stick it
in our Model folder.
And let's call it "Messages".
Now let's add the code to define
the UpsertStrokeMessage.
Now that we've defined the
message to send and receive
with GroupSessionMessenger,
let's write the code
to send and receive it.
We'll navigate back to Canvas
to do this.
Let's go to
the bottom of our file
and add the code
to receive the messages.
Here, we create a detached task
to receive
the UpsertStrokeMessages
from the async sequence
and call a new method, handle,
to process the message.
Let's implement that next.
[KEYSTROKES]
In this code, we check to see
if we already have a stroke
by checking for its identifier,
and if so, add the point to it.
Otherwise, we create a
new stroke, add the point to it,
and append the stroke
to our array of strokes.
Next, we'll write the code
to send the messages.
We'll go up to the method above,
addPointToActiveStroke.
[KEYSTROKES]
Awesome!
Now let's build and run our app
and see a shared DrawTogether
experience in action.
So I'll go over
to my two devices,
and I'm going to start
a FaceTime call with myself.
I'll go to the Phone app
and then call myself.
[FACETIME RINGING]
And then I'm going to answer
on my other device.
[FACETIME RINGING]
Turn off the mics.
Now on this device,
I'm going to start
a shared DrawTogether
experience.
I'll tap the bottom-left icon.
And on the other device,
I'll join the Group Session.
And now I'm going to play
tic-tac-toe with myself.
I'll move first.
[LAUGHS]
Looks like I won.
Cool. Looks like our code works.
[END FACETIME CALL TONE]
Now that we've talked about
how to configure the session
using GroupSessionMessenger
by first defining the messages,
then receiving the messages,
and finally sending
the messages,
let's talk about a few other
things to consider
when using
GroupSessionMessenger.
Under the hood,
GroupSessionMessenger
provides reliable and
FIFO-ordered message delivery
to all active participants
in the group.
The messages you send
do have constraints;
if they are too large,
an error will be thrown
from the send API.
GroupSessionMessenger
is meant for smaller payloads
and should not be used
for streaming large assets
like files, images, or videos.
Another thing to consider
when sending messages
is flow control
and rate limiting.
Sending a burst of messages in
quick succession, like a loop,
could result in an error
being thrown from the send API.
Finally, when defining
the messages to use
with GroupSessionMessenger,
consider adding
versioning support
to your application protocol.
This will allow
your applications
to support inter-op with devices
running an older version
of your software.
Now I'll hand it off to Adam
who will talk to you
about how you can polish
your GroupActivities experience.
Adam: Thanks, Angus!
So now let's talk about
some finishing touches
that your app may need
for its custom experience.
First, let's talk about
late joiners.
Late joiners are devices that
join into an activitySession
after the session is started.
To ensure a proper experience,
late joiners need to be given
the latest information
so that all the devices are
working off of the same data.
Accounting for this scenario
is critical
to ensure a coherent
user experience,
but it isn't
a one-size-fits-all.
The data needed
for this catch-up process
will depend on your app
and experience.
So let's see how it applies
to the DrawTogether app.
Let's say that we have
two devices in a Group Session.
These two devices
have the same information:
a smiley face
drawn on their canvas.
You can see that because
they were both in the session
when the drawing happened,
they have the same data
throughout the experience.
Now, let's add another device.
At this point,
the new device calls join
on their GroupSession, but
there's nothing on the canvas.
So we draw a cloud, and --
Oh, that's -- that's not good!
Because the new device
didn't have prior context,
our smiley face
now has a cloud on it.
Now let's back up
and try that again.
How do we fix this
so that the new device
has a smiley face show
as soon as it joins?
Once the new device calls join
on the Group Session,
every other device joined
into the Group Session
will see the activeParticipants
property on GroupSession fire.
Devices that observe that signal
will then send
its catch-up data --
in this case,
the existing drawing canvas --
to the newly joined device.
Now when the new device joins,
it sees that there was
a smiley face already there
so we can draw around it!
So now, how we do this
in code?
The first thing we need to do
is understand what data
our app needs to transmit
in our catch-up message.
Since we're a DrawTogether
experience
and our goal is to ensure
that the canvas
is the same
on everyone's device,
let's go ahead
and make a new message
in our Message.swift file
called "CanvasMessage".
This struct will contain all
of the strokes that we have
and a variable that we'll call
"pointCount",
which will be used
as a heuristic to calculate
which message
is the most up to date.
Awesome!
Now, how do we handle
receiving this message?
If we go over to our
Canvas model in Canvas.swift,
we're able to set up
a message handler
in configureGroupSession
using the GroupSessionMessenger
like Angus showed us previously.
[KEYSTROKES]
From here, you can see that we
call into our handle function,
so let's go ahead
and implement that.
[KEYSTROKES]
In this code, you can see
that we guard against
our pointCount heuristic to only
accept catch-up messages
that are newer than
what we currently have.
If that passes, then we go ahead
and override our canvas' strokes
with the catchupMessage's
strokes.
Now, like we discussed earlier,
we need to listen
for activeParticipants
to change to figure out
if there's any new participants
that we need to communicate to.
So let's go ahead
and add that to our
configureGroupSession function.
[KEYSTROKES]
In this handler, you can see
that we grab the delta
between our new
activeParticipants
and our old activeParticipants.
This ensures that we only
send our catch-up message
to the newly joined
participants.
Great!
Now we just form and send
our message.
[KEYSTROKES]
This message will contain
our current canvas' state
and will send it only
to the newParticipants.
And that's it!
That's catch-up!
So, now that we have
all the pieces in place
for a Group Session to go on
for a specific activity,
what do we do if we're
changing activities completely?
This could be something like
changing the drawing canvas
or changing movies.
Our API provides two ways
of changing activities:
you can either create
a new Group Session
or update the activity
for everyone
on your existing
Group Session.
So, let's talk about the two.
The first and preferred way
to change content
is through calling the same API
that started the Group Session:
prepareForActivation
on GroupActivity.
This approach makes it easier
to reason about
a consistent state
between participants,
since it provides
a clean barrier
for entrance and exit
of the GroupSession,
so you don't need to worry
about lingering states
or messages that you don't need
from the old GroupSession.
This is incredibly helpful
for when users
back out of the activity
to find the next one,
such as searching
for a new note or movie.
This also gives the system
an indication of a major change,
which will be used
to notify the user.
After this call,
in the same fashion
as starting a Group Session,
you'll receive your new
GroupSession
through the sessions async
sequence on GroupActivity.
Now, what if your application
has a list of activities
that you are going to be
transitioning between,
such as multiple songs
playing after each other?
Our GroupSession API
provides a simple way
for you to trigger
an update for everyone
by simply setting the activity
property on the GroupSession.
From there, you then listen to
the activity property change.
Our API will ensure
that devices
always converge
onto the same activity
so you don't need
to worry about it.
Now that we conceptually
understand the two,
which one should we use
for our DrawTogether app?
Because our app wants
a clean slate
on each new drawing canvas,
the New Session API would
give us exactly what we want.
So now let's hop over to Xcode
to see how to implement it.
The first step here
is to decide
how we want to trigger
a new session.
In our case,
let's make it so when a client
uses our Reset button,
we'll go ahead and create
a new GroupSession.
If we look at
our ControlBar code,
we can see that we already
have a CapsuleButton
that calls into our Canvas model
to reset the local state.
So let's go ahead
and modify that function
to tear down the GroupSession
and create a new one.
[KEYSTROKES]
In this code, we'll go ahead
and cancel any tasks
and cancelables that we have
for our GroupSession.
We'll also check if we
have a GroupSession --
and if we do, leave it and call
into the activate property
on our DrawTogether type.
From there, our normal flow
for receiving a GroupSession
will take place,
and we're good to go!
We now have a clean way
to transition to a new canvas.
Now, what if we want to change
our UI to indicate to users
that they can try our SharePlay
experience with their friends?
For example, in our drawing app,
we want our canvas to change
from this to this
where when we're eligible
for a GroupSession,
you'll notice that we now show
a button to share the canvas.
So how do we do this?
With the GroupStateObserver API,
we're able to listen
to a publisher
to tell us when the device
is eligible for a Group Session.
We can then use this
to dynamically show
and hide our button.
So let's go and implement it!
Like we saw,
we want a small button
in the bottom left
of our application.
Since our application already
has the sharing button
in our ControlBar view,
let's just change the behavior
to show and hide the button
based off of
the GroupStateObserver.
First we go ahead and add
our groupStateObserver
to our view.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now let's surround
our CapsuleButton
to only show if we're eligible
for a groupSession
and we're not in this
groupSession already.
And that's it!
Our button now
dynamically shows
only when it's helpful
to the user.
Now let's go over
what we saw in this session.
We went through the full process
of creating a simple drawing app
that we then changed
to leverage Group Activities
to make it synchronized
and connected like never before.
But more importantly, we went
through all the steps needed
for you to fully unleash
your creativity
and create any custom
SharePlay experience
with Group Activities.
We talked about creating
a custom activity
with a generic type,
configuring and leveraging
GroupSession
and GroupSessionMessenger
for synchronized communication,
and edge cases and APIs
your app should adopt
to make a truly rich
user experience.
I hope you enjoyed creating
this custom experience with us,
and we look forward to seeing
your creativity go wild
with the Group Activities
framework!
Your next step while learning
about GroupActivities
should be the "Design for
Group Activities" session
And if you haven't seen
it already, check out
the "Build media experiences
with Group Activities" session
as well.
If you have any questions,
please find us
at the Group Activities lab.
And finally,
thank you all for tuning in
and have a great WWDC.
We can't wait to see
what you build!
♪