[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
Ally Kazmucha: Hi, I'm Ally,
and I'm the engineering program
manager for Game Center.
I'm really excited to spend
some time walking you through
all the improvements
we're making this year.
We also launched some great
new features this spring
like Friends API,
which we'll be talking
to you about as well.
But before I get into
some of those details,
I'd like to briefly talk about
some of the core features
Game Center offers,
many of which were completely
refreshed last year.
Game Center is Apple's
own social gaming network.
As a developer,
you can take advantage of
whichever Game Center features
make sense in your game
through our GameKit framework.
For players, Game Center
Is a single gaming ID
that allows them to instantly
compete on leaderboards,
track achievement progress,
play multiplayer games together,
and even check out
their friends' profiles.
Helping players find and
discover great new games
is also one of the primary goals
of Game Center.
We added quite a few features
in iOS 14
to help with
game discoverability,
and we're adding
even more this year.
Games are all about community,
and keeping up with
what our friends are playing
is a great way
to discover new titles
we may have otherwise missed.
That's why we integrated
Game Center
directly with the App Store
last year.
We now show more information
on what your Game Center
friends are up to,
through both the Games and
Arcade tabs of the App Store.
Let's take a closer look.
While browsing the Arcade tab,
I can see that several
of my Game Center friends
are playing a few games
that look interesting to me,
including a new game
called "Wonderbox."
Let's check out the product page
to learn more.
Not only can I read more
about the game itself
on the product page,
I can also see a complete list
of my Game Center friends
who are already playing
that particular game.
Tapping on one of them brings up
their Game Center profile.
From here,
I can see even more of the games
they've been playing.
And if I see one I like,
I can download it directly
from their profile.
The Friends Are Playing section
will automatically appear
on the product page for all
Game Center-enabled games.
There are, of course,
opportunities outside
of the App Store
to check out
a friend's profile as well.
For example,
I can tap on a friend
within any leaderboard --
like shown here --
to bring up their profile.
These are all great
opportunities for players
to find new games to play.
And there's nothing
you have to do
to make your game eligible
either.
All Game Center-enabled games
automatically show up
in both Friends Are Playing
and Recently Played.
This fall, we're also adding two
new Game Center-powered widgets.
The first is --
you guessed it --
Friends Are Playing.
We think this is going to be
an even easier way for players
to keep up with and discover
more of the games
their friends are playing,
right from their home screen.
The second widget is called
Continue Playing.
This widget automatically
resurfaces games
you've already launched
and played.
So you can jump right back in
where you left off
with a single tap.
And if you're on an iPad,
both of these Game Center
widgets
support the new larger format
as well.
And just like Friends Are
Playing and Recently Played,
there's no additional code
needed or feature to adopt.
If your game supports
Game Center,
it's automatically included.
And since friends are such an
important part of social play,
we're making some
significant improvements
to both our friending
and multiplayer flows too.
First up, friends.
Game Center friend requests
will continue to be sent
through Messages
just like they are today.
But just in case you miss one,
we've added a brand-new
Friend Requests inbox
to let you manage them
all in one place.
We've also made
some great improvements
to the flow within Messages,
including support to send
and receive friend requests
on MacOS.
But as a developer,
you're probably most interested
in what you can do
with Game Center friends.
And that's where Friends API
comes in.
Friends API gives you
privacy-friendly access
to a player's
Game Center friends,
so you can create all kinds
of unique experiences
within your game.
Whether it's showing
what level my friends are on
in a progression map,
or letting players
launch missions together,
all of these can now
be accomplished
by adopting Friends API.
Chee Han will be walking you
through how to do just that.
So now that you know
about some of the ways
Game Center can help improve
discoverability
and connect players together
outside of your game,
let's look at some of the
benefits Game Center offers
within your game.
In iOS 14, we introduced
a brand-new player dashboard
you can add to your game
through the Access Point API.
We also shipped
an entirely refreshed UI --
virtually no screen
went untouched.
With vibrant colors
that match
the underlying tones
of your game,
this refresh was meant to feel
at home in any game.
You can also choose
to use a combination
of our native Game Center UI
alongside any custom UI
that best fits within your game.
For example, showing
current leaderboard scores
within a level
selection screen --
or even as a live indicator
while playing a level --
are all examples that make sense
to be themed in a UI
that matches your game.
While not in a level,
you can still choose
to give players access
to all their Game Center data
through the access point --
like shown here.
This just gives your players
even more ways to keep up with
and interact with
their Game Center rankings
and achievements.
And if your game
supports multiplayer,
we've got some great updates
here as well.
This year, we continued to focus
on helping people connect
and start playing a game
together as fast as possible.
Now, when you start
a multiplayer match,
our new suggestions section
also surfaces your existing
Messages groups.
Tap a group,
and the invite is sent
within the Messages thread
you already have going.
We also remember the Game Center
friend groups you’ve played with
and suggest them as well.
So one tap gets you back
in the game
with the same friends again.
We're also introducing
a brand-new multiplayer API
called "Fast Start."
Zhehong will be walking you
through some of the benefits
of Fast Start and how you can
implement it within your game.
Finally, we've also added
controller support
for all Game Center UI
on both iPhone and iPad.
The best part:
there's zero new API to adopt
or versioning in Xcode
required on your part.
Just press the Home button
on any supported controller
and the Game Center dashboard
is instantly presented.
Press it again
and you're back in the game.
While the Game Center dashboard
and all the sections within it
will be navigable by default,
you will need to add controller
support for your own UI.
And if you're interested in what
else is new with controllers,
be sure to check out
the session titled
"Tap into virtual and physical
game controllers"
to learn more.
Here's a look
at the rest of the session.
First up, Chee Han is going
to walk you through
our friending improvements,
including a detailed
walk-through of Friends API
and how you can implement it
to leverage Game Center friends
within your game.
And to wrap up the session,
Zhehong will fill you in
on everything multiplayer,
including a walk-through
of how we've streamlined
the invite flow
and how you can implement
our new Fast Start API
to speed up the process
even further.
To get you started on Friends,
here's Chee Han.
Chee Han Lim: Hi, I'm Chee Han.
I'm an engineer on
the Game Center team.
One of the best parts
of playing games
is being able to share
those experiences
with your family and friends.
For some of us,
it's about the competition;
and for others,
it's about the connection.
Game Center friends
allows you to do just that.
So there are two capabilities
that we will be focusing on
today.
First, we have made it easy
to enable players to send friend
requests within your game.
Second, we have introduced
some new APIs
for you to leverage
your player's friends list
through Friends API.
First, let's talk about
sending friend requests.
When your game is better
when played together,
it might make sense
to encourage your player
to make Game Center friends
within your game.
We have introduced a new API
to let you do just that.
In your game, you can have an
Add Friends button on your UI,
where we recommend you to use
SF Symbols as a button image.
When your user presses
on the button,
you can call our friending API
to allow your player to add
friends within your game.
Let's see how we can do that
in code.
When you call
presentFriendRequestCreator
FromViewController API,
a message sheet will be
presented with a real controller
that you have passed in.
After your player finishes
sending the friend request,
we will dismiss the sheet and
return the control to your app
with an optional error.
That's it!
With a few lines of code,
you will be able to provide
your player the opportunity
to send friend requests
without leaving your game.
And now, let's take a look
at what you can do
with all those Games Center
friends.
The second feature
we have added this spring
is privacy-friendly API access
to Game Center friends.
When a player launches your game
and tries to use functionality
for the first time that requires
Game Center friends access,
they will be prompted
to allow or deny
access to their friends list.
If allowed,
we will return you a list of
their bi-directional friends,
which means the list will
only contain their friends
who have also granted access
to your game.
We will also sync
this permission for you
across all their devices,
and the user will only need
to approve your request once.
So what kind of experiences
can you create
if your player allows you access
to their friends list?
Well, this will allow you
to do things like,
show what level my friends
are on within a progression map,
let me launch a mission together
with my friends in the lobby,
show a friends-only
recurring leaderboard
while we are playing
a multiplayer game together,
and much more.
Let us walk through
what Friends API will look like
from your player's perspective.
Your game will call an API
to ask for permission
to access the player's friends.
And the player will see
a familiar system prompt
where they have to decide
to allow or deny your request.
And you will have the option
to explain to the player
why you are requesting
friends access.
Once your player
approves your request,
we will return the list
of friends
who have also granted access
to your game.
In this example, we will use
a leaderboard to keep track
of players' progression with
the score that I have submitted
to this leaderboard.
With the score submitted,
I can utilize Friends API
to show my friends
on a progression map
next to the level corresponding
to their leaderboard scores.
This may look something like
this within your own game UI.
You can see that my friends'
progression is populated
on the map,
where I will know exactly
where they are in my game.
Let's jump into how to create
this UI with code.
We will need to do some setup
before you can call Friends API.
First, you'll need to add
NSGKFriendListUsageDescription
to your info.plist.
This description
will be displayed
as part of the permission
prompt to our player,
as seen in the previous slide.
If the description is missing,
all Friends API calls
will result into an error.
Once the description is set,
you can now call the two new
APIs in GKLocalPlayer class.
To check for friends
list access,
you should call
loadFriendsAuthorizationStatus
in GKLocalPlayer class.
You may want to call this
in your app’s
applicationDidFinishLaunching,
and if the state
is not determined,
you may want to delay
loading players' friends list
until there is a good moment
for you to show
the permission prompt.
This will allow your player
some time to make a decision
once the prompt is presented.
You will receive
GKFriendsAuthorizationStatus
in one of the following
four states
within a completion block.
You can refer
to GKLocalPlayer header
for a detailed explanation
of each state.
When returned state
is denied or restricted,
if you have previously
collected data for this player,
you should delete
the collected data on your end.
If your player chooses
to grant you access
with an authorized state,
you will then be able to proceed
to load their friends list
by calling loadFriends API.
Let's take a look at that now.
In this code, we will leverage
the power of Swift async call,
to simplify our calls
to GameKit framework.
We will start
with an async method
with the name
loadFriendsOnProgressionMap.
First, we will call loadFriends
API in GKLocalPlayer class.
GameKit will return
your player’s friends
as an array of GKPlayer objects.
Next, we will load
our progression leaderboard
from GameKit with the
leaderboard ID "progress."
Once we have
the leaderboard object,
we can then pass in
your player’s friends
to loadEntries method.
You will obtain the score
they have on that leaderboard,
which is used to keep track
of which level they are in now.
With that, we have all
the information we need
to display your player's friends
on the progression map.
And that's it!
You have now
successfully integrated
Friends API in your game
and displayed your player's
friends on a progression map.
We are super excited to see
all the amazing experiences
that our developer community
will come up with
using this new feature.
And with that, I would like
to turn it over to Zhehong.
He will tell you all about
the great changes
we have made to multiplayer
this year.
Zhehong An: Thanks, Chee Han.
Hi everyone, I am Zhehong
from the Game Center team.
I cannot wait to introduce
all the new features
and improvements in Game Center
multiplayer this year.
We have made
significant improvements
to Game Center multiplayer,
as Ally mentioned previously.
The main purpose
behind all of these changes
is to help your players
find people to play with
and get into a game
as fast as possible.
Game Center multiplayer UI
allows many different ways
for players to find people
to connect and play with.
This includes automatching
with other players
or sending invites at once
to multiple friends, contacts,
nearby players, a phone number
or an email address,
Game Center groups,
or Message groups.
It dramatically reduces
your efforts
to show different people
from different sources.
As you might know,
automatching is the mechanism
which helps your players
find each other
from Game Center's
matchmaking pool.
I will walk through
the other new concepts
in the following slides.
To bring better suggestions
to the players,
we have introduced
the Suggestions Shelf
containing a list of people
from within and without
Game Center
that your players
might want to invite.
It contains nearby players,
Game Center groups,
and Message groups.
A Game Center group,
which is a new concept
we have introduced this year,
is a group of players
you recently played with
in real-time
or turn-based matches.
We believe this new feature
will make it fairly easy
for players who want
to play a game repeatedly
with a certain group of people,
because this makes it possible
to select all the players
in that group
with just a single tap.
And we are leveraging
the people you already talk to
on a regular basis over iMessage
with Message Groups.
A single tap will select
an entire Message Group,
and the invitation uses
your existing group chat.
Now, you can not only send
invites faster via Messages,
but also chat
about a game afterwards.
Once you have selected
the people you wish to invite,
tap the Send button
at the top right,
and you will see them
in the lobby.
We now have the capability
for adding or removing players
even after the initial
invitations have gone out.
For example, you may want
to remove some invited players
who are not able to respond,
but you don't want
to remove other players
who have already accepted.
So, we have made it possible
to individually remove
invited players
by tapping on the X button
in their player slot,
as long as they have not
accepted yet,
or they leave the game
after they have accepted.
And players can continue
inviting more people
to your game,
which gives them
a lot of flexibility
to quickly craft the right group
of people to play with.
All of this greatly simplifies
and streamlines the experience
by making it much easier
for players
to play your multiplayer game
faster and easier than ever.
Making it easy for players
to invite people they know
in turn helps increase
your game's discoverability.
As you can see, if you leverage
Game Center multiplayer UI,
you get all these
awesome features for free.
To make it even quicker
to start a multiplayer game,
we added a new API
this year called "Fast Start."
If you adopt Fast Start,
the game initiator
will have the choice
to either wait for everyone
to be connected or begin a game
as soon as the minimum number of
invited players have connected.
It gets players much faster
from Game Center UI
back into your game UI.
Meanwhile in the background,
Game Center will continue
connecting the rest
of the players
and automatching
any unfilled player slots.
All these players will be able
to join your game
when they connect.
If your game can support players
joining a multiplayer session
at different times,
then you can take advantage of
Fast Start via Game Center UI.
You can utilize this feature
to make some warmup
game scenes as well.
The best way to see
this in action
is to show you an example.
Here, we are using a game
called "The Coast,"
which leverages Fast Start.
You will see how powerful it is
to utilize Fast Start
to build your game.
First, I present
GKMatchmakerViewController
with a GKMatchRequest,
configured with 2 minPlayers
and 5 maxPlayers.
In this way, the game can start
as long as two players
are ready,
including the local player.
Then I tap
the Invite Friends button
to launch the player picker.
I pick the players
I want to invite,
and I wait for them
to respond.
As you can see,
once an invitee accepts,
the Start Game button
is highlighted,
so I can either start a game or
wait for other players to join.
I decide to start,
and the gameplay begins
as soon as the matchmaker view
controller is dismissed.
Since this game initially
started with two players,
you can see two boats.
Meanwhile, Game Center is still
connecting in the background.
Once the third player joins,
the game is notified,
and we bring up the third boat.
Because we also had
two automatched slots,
Game Center is still
automatching in the background.
After the matchmaking process
is finished,
two automatched players join.
Now, we have a full set
of five players for this game.
As you can see,
by adopting Fast Start,
different players will be able
to join the same game session
at different times.
Finally, let's look at the code
you need to add
to accomplish what we have
just walked through together.
To construct a
GKMatchmakerViewController
with Fast Start mode
turned on,
simply set its property
canStartWithMinimumPlayers
to "true".
Please note: the minPlayers
of the GKMatchRequest
is the minimum number of players
that the gameplay
in your game needs to start.
Set the delegate after you get
the GKMatch instance,
so that you can know
the connection status
of the players in the match.
And
didChangeConnectionState
is the delegate method
where you can handle players
who join later.
On the invitee side,
just present the
GKMatchmakerViewController
initialized
with the GKInvite instance.
This is probably the same
as what you are doing today.
And don't forget to set
the matchmakerDelegate.
That's pretty much about it.
We are excited to see how you
adopt not only Fast Start,
but all the new features and
improvements we are providing
this year for multiplayer.
To recap,
here is what we covered today.
We introduced
how Game Center helps
increase the discoverability
of your game.
After that, we talked
about Friends API
along with some general
improvements to Friends.
Then all the multiplayer
features and improvements
we just talked through help your
players play multiplayer games
with people they know,
as fast as possible.
And also, we have better support
for controllers this year.
At the bottom, you will see
another two sessions
which you might be
interested in.
They're about
recurring leaderboard
and game controllers.
Thank you all for watching.
Enjoy your week at WWDC.
♪