[music]
[Annie]
Hi.
My name is Annie,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Health Records team.
I'm joined
today by my colleague Cary
to show you
how you can empower people
to share their verifiable
health records using HealthKit.
Before we dive
into verifiable health records,
I want to briefly reintroduce
the Health Records feature
that we launched back
in 2018 for iOS 11.3.
Health Records allows users
to connect to their providers
and securely download
their clinical records
to the Health app
for easy storage
and visualization.
This is all built on top
of industry standards
like HL7's Fast Healthcare
Interoperability Resources,
or FHIR.
With user permission,
your app can
access these health records
that users have downloaded
with HealthKit.
For more details about
the existing Health Records API,
I encourage you to check out
our WWDC 2018 video,
"Accessing Health Records
with HealthKit" to learn more.
For iOS 15, we're leveraging
our Health Records work
to allow for the download,
storage,
and sharing
of verifiable records
in the Health app
implemented based on the SMART
Health Cards specification.
Let's explore what
verifiable health records are
and how they're different
from the health records data
you can currently query for
with HealthKit.
First, a verifiable
health record contains
multiple FHIR resources,
including a patient resource
and one
or more clinical resources.
These resources are bundled
in what we call
a SMART Health Card.
Issuers,
or institutions that create
verifiable health records,
such as a lab
or healthcare provider,
cryptographically sign
this SMART Health Card
as a JSON Web Signature, or JWS.
Finally, issuers generate
verifiable health records
such that they include
only necessary information
about the patient
and their clinical data.
To get a clearer
picture of these points,
let's look at an example.
For this example,
the record contains
two FHIR immunization resources,
one for each dose of a vaccine.
It also includes
a FHIR patient resource
to identify
who received the vaccine.
These resources
are then combined
into a SMART Health Card,
which, in its raw form,
looks like this.
The SMART Health Card payload
includes information
such as the type,
which contains URLs that declare
what types of data
to expect in the health card,
and the credential subject,
which includes the FHIR version
and a Bundle resource
that contains the immunization
and patient resources.
The SMART Health Card
is then signed as a JWS,
which has two components:
A header and a payload.
The JWS header
houses the algorithm used
to sign the JWS;
the public key thumbprint,
which specifies which
of the issuer's public keys was
used to sign; and the algorithm
used to compress the payload.
The compressed JWS payload,
along with
the credential subject,
contains other claims data,
including the issuer URL,
where the issuer's
public keys are located,
the issued date,
and an optional expiration date.
In its raw form,
this is what a Verifiable
Health Record looks like.
For more information,
we encourage you
to visit the SMART
Health Card specification
via the link
associated with this session.
Now that we've reviewed
what a verifiable health record
looks like,
let me show you how you can
import these records
into the Health app.
One option is to use the
existing Health Records feature.
Users can download
verifiable health records
to the Health app by connecting
to a Health Records-enabled
provider.
Note that this option is
only available
where the Health Records feature
is available,
which is currently in the US,
UK, and Canada.
Users also have the options
of downloading a file
with a .smart-health-cards
extension or scanning
a smart-health-card
file-embedded QR code.
This will display
the following sheet
in the Health app,
where users can view details
and choose whether
to download these records.
These two options
are available internationally.
Finally,
how can you request access
to this data with HealthKit?
We are introducing
a new HealthKit query,
HKVerifiableClinicalRecordQuery,
and a new HKSample subclass,
HKVerifiableClinicalRecord
for iOS 15.
Unlike other HKQuery subclasses,
in order to use this query,
you must request for
a HealthKit access entitlement
for Verifiable Health Records.
While you will still have access
to the public headers
in the SDK,
the results handler will return
an authorization denied error
without the entitlement.
Please refer to the links
associated with this session
for information
on how to get started.
Before we dive deeper into
the query and sample classes,
let's look at authorization
for Verifiable Health Records,
which is slightly different
from what you might be used to
with Health Records.
First, Verifiable Health Records
observes a per-sample
authorization pattern,
where the user
selects individual samples,
not types,
to share with your app.
This type of authorization
provides users
with more granular control
over their data
and is important
in protecting their privacy.
The current HealthKit
authorization pattern
consists of two steps:
First requesting
user authorization
for types to read and share,
and then querying for samples
once authorization is granted.
With Verifiable Health Records,
this first step is not needed.
Instead, once an instance of
HKVerifiableClinicalRecordQuery
is created and executed,
an authorization sheet will
be presented,
allowing the user to select
which individual records
to share with your app.
After sharing,
the chosen records are then
returned
to the query's results handler.
Furthermore, authorization
for Verifiable Health Records
is one-time only.
Sharing these records
with a third-party app
does not set up long-term
access authorization.
Each execution of a
HKVerifiableClinicalRecordQuery
will result in the presentation
of the following
authorization sheet
and the return
of user-selected records
to the results handler.
Now that we've gone
over authorization,
let's look at
HKVerifiableClinicalRecordQuery
in more detail.
To initialize the
HKVerifiableClinicalRecordQuery,
you will first have to provide
a string array of record types,
which we defined earlier
as the type of data present
in a verifiable health record.
Only records with all
provided record types present
will be shown
in the authorization sheet.
Like other HealthKit queries,
you also have the option
to add a predicate
to further filter the set
of samples for authorization.
We are providing
a convenience constructor
to create a predicate
for records
with relevant dates
within a date interval.
Once the query is executed
and the user taps "Share Once,"
the authorized
HKVerifiableClinicalRecords
are then returned
in the results handler.
The record includes
basic information
about the subject and issuer,
and, of course,
the JWS property,
which will contain the raw data
that you will verify and decode.
Now that we've gone through
the Verifiable Health Records
feature and
what its API looks like,
I'm going
to hand it off to Cary,
who will walk you
through how to import test data,
use the API to request records,
and verify a record's JWS.
[Cary]
Thanks, Annie.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Cary,
and I'm also an engineer
on the Health Records team.
Today, I'll be walking you
through how to work
with Verifiable Health Records.
So the best way to start working
with this new feature
is to load some test
data into HealthKit.
As Annie mentioned, there are
three different methods
you can use to get started.
If you're in the United States,
Canada, or the United Kingdom,
you can simply connect
to a provider using the existing
Health Records feature
in the Health App.
Another new way we've added
is by downloading
a .smart-health-card file,
an example of which you can find
on the smarthealth.cards
specification website.
The third method
is by scanning a QR code.
So let's go get some data.
For this demo,
you can start by trying out
the new QR code import.
You'll start
with a device running iOS 15
and scanning this QR code.
As soon as you scan it,
you will receive a prompt
to open directly
into the health app.
Once you switch
to the health app,
it will immediately begin
guiding you
through
importing this health card.
After selecting
the "Add to Health" option,
the import process
will complete.
You can scroll over
to the browse tab
and see the imported records
under the immunizations section.
If you go ahead
and tap into this category,
you can now
see that you have a vaccine
and that its signature has
been verified by the Health app.
Now that you have some
signed records imported
into the Health app,
you're ready to go ahead
and request these
records from your own app.
Now, let's look at an example
of how your app can
access this new API.
First, you'll start
by importing HealthKit.
Next,
you'll create a HealthStore,
which you may already
be familiar with doing
if you've used the standard
HealthKit authorization API.
You will also create a list of
record types to specify the type
of data that you would
like the user to share with you.
When authorizing, you will
be presented with a list
of data to share that only
match these record types.
Next, you will create
a predicate specifying
the valid date range
for samples to share.
In this example,
you can see labs conducted
in the past seven days are
being requested.
Then you will create a query
using the constructed
recordTypes and predicate,
using a completion to check
whether the samples presented
were shared with your app.
Finally,
executing the query will
cause an authorization
sheet to be presented
where results may be
selected to share with your app.
This dialogue will be
presented every time
this method is executed.
Now that you have retrieved
a piece of signed clinical data,
you can write some code
to verify its signature
within your app.
To review, digital signatures
are a mathematical way
to verify the authenticity
of digital information.
This process may be
performed by any device,
such as a server
or another mobile device,
but let's go ahead
and take a look at how to do it
from within your app.
You can accomplish this
using four main steps.
First, you will parse the
clinical data using a Codable.
Second,
you will decompress the signed
JSON Web Token payload.
Third,
you will download the issuer's
public key from their website.
And finally,
you will use CryptoKit
to verify the signature.
Let's start by looking
at how to define the data model
for a signed record,
which is formally defined
in the JSON Web Signature
specification.
This struct is defined
in three main parts:
A header, payload,
and signature.
You could use Swift Codable
to do the parsing for you,
and you should keep an original
representation of the header
and payload around for use
during signature verification.
Most importantly,
you'll add an initializer
to parse the JWS from
its compact serialized form.
Next, you'll create a struct
used to represent
the JWS Header.
You will need this
during the initialization
from compact serialization,
as well as during the signature
verification process.
You can see here in the header
that you can expect to find
a specified signature algorithm,
a key-ID field used to hold
a public key thumbprint,
and a compression algorithm.
The public key thumbprint
is used to identify which
of the issuer's keys was
used to sign the JWS.
This process requires
the ES256 Signature Algorithm
and the DEF
compression algorithm,
both of which are supported
by first-party Swift libraries.
Now let's look at the code
needed to parse the JWS
from its compact serialization.
You'll start by splitting
the serialized string
into its constituent pieces,
each of which is
Base64URL encoded.
After creating a JSONDecoder and
Base64URL decoding the header
and payload,
you can check to see
if the header indicates that the
payload is compressed correctly.
After checking the compression,
you will use a utility method
that you can find
in the provided sample project
to decompress the payload.
The next piece you'll
need is a struct
to model
the health card payload.
The two most important pieces
here are the issuer field,
which will hold
the issuer's web identifier
that you can use
to fetch their keys,
and the other is the VC field,
which holds
all the patient data.
For more information
on how to parse the VC field
and analyze its contents,
check out the "Handling FHIR
without getting burned" talk
from WWDC 2020.
Now that you've seen
how to parse a JWS,
you are ready
to verify its authenticity.
Let's look
at creating an extension
that will add a verification
method to your JWS struct.
Since you'll be reaching out
to the issuer's website directly
to retrieve their signing keys,
you can use Combine to help
with the asynchronous aspects
of this process,
and you can use CryptoKit
to help
with the signature verification.
Inside the verification method,
you'll begin by pulling out
the issuer's identifier,
which is always
the issuer's web address.
Here, you can add your own
method to check if the URL
is one that you personally
trust and abort if it's one
that you don't want to
accept results from.
Next, you will create a URL
to retrieve the issuer's keys
by appending the standard
.wellknown/jwks.json URL path.
This path suffix is defined
in the specification
and should be
the same for all issuers.
Now that you have constructed
the well-known URL,
you can connect to the issuer,
download their keys,
and finish
verifying the signature.
You'll finish writing
this method by creating
a URLSession
dataTaskPublisher that will
connect to the issuer's
well-known jwk endpoint.
You can then map it to data,
decode it using a jsonDecoder
to a set of JWKs,
and finally map it to a boolean,
indicating whether
or not the signature is valid.
Inside the final map block
you will select the issuer's key
based on what
the JWS header indicates.
The final piece
involves using CryptoKit
to verify the signature.
According
to the JWS specification,
the signed portion of
data is formed by concatenating
the Base64URL-encoded header
and payload joined by a period.
Next, you'll convert
the downloaded JWK keys
to CryptoKit P256 signing keys,
using a utility method
that you can find in the sample
project accompanying this talk.
Finally, you'll use CryptoKit's
isValidSignature method
to do the verification
of the signature.
Now that your data model
and all logic needed
to verify its authenticity is
defined,
you can put everything together.
Taking a look
at the earlier example
of how to call the new API,
you can replace this comment
with a call to your new
verification method.
Since the API returns
a list of all selected samples,
you can select the first one
from the list.
Next,
parse it from data to a String.
Then parse it using your compact
serialization initializer.
Finally, call your new
verification method,
and listen
for emitted boolean results.
And just like that,
we've seen how to take
a signed piece of clinical data
download the issuer's
signing keys,
and validate the signature
of these records.
Now, I'll hand things
back to Annie to summarize.
[Annie]
Thanks, Cary.
Before we wrap up,
I want to talk
about privacy with respect
to Verifiable Health Records.
Hopefully, I've made it clear
throughout this session
that the Verifiable
Health Records feature
is built with
user privacy in mind.
First of all,
the SMART Health Card
specification uses data profiles
that minimize the information
an issuer should include
in each record.
The Health app is designed to
protect sensitive health data,
so when a phone is locked,
all health and fitness data
in the Health app is encrypted,
which includes
verifiable health records.
Access to verifiable health
records requires an application
to an entitlement that will
come with additional obligations
to ensure that this sensitive
health data is not misused.
And finally, users will
have additional control over how
to share their verifiable
health records with your app.
Let's review what
we've covered today.
In iOS 15, building
on top of Health Records,
we are bringing the capability
to import verifiable records
into the Health app
and for developers
to read this data
with a new API.
To wrap up,
here's what you can do next.
First, to learn more
about the verifiable health data
ecosystem,
check out the SMART Health Cards
specification.
Import test records
into the Health app
to try it out yourself.
Download the sample app,
which shows
how you can query for
and verify those test records.
And finally, when
you're ready to ship your app,
request the HealthKit access
entitlement
for verifiable health records.
Thank you for watching,
and have a great WWDC.
[music]