[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Brett]
Hello, my name is Brett Cato,
and I’m an engineer
on the System Experience team.
Today we’re going to be
talking about principles
of great widgets,
diving into some hot topics
to help you build
the best widgets possible.
In iOS 14,
we introduced WidgetKit.
WidgetKit allows you
to create beautiful,
dynamic, multiplatform widgets
right on the user’s
Home Screen on iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS.
Now, before we get started,
if you missed any of the talks
from WWDC 2020, there are
some really great ones,
like “Meet WidgetKit,”
which provides an introduction
to the WidgetKit framework
and its core concepts.
“Widgets code-along”
is a three-part series
of building a widget
with increasing complexity
from basic to advanced.
“Building SwiftUI views
for widgets” details
how to get the most
out of SwiftUI to build
adaptable views
for your widgets.
Lastly, “Design great widgets”
explores design considerations
from our human interface group
with many, many examples.
Today we’re gonna touch
on two topics for great widgets:
keeping them relevant
and enabling
widget customization.
So let’s get started
with relevance.
There’s three types of relevance
that we’re gonna discuss
in depth
to make sure your widget
is up to date
and can adapt
to its environment.
We’re gonna talk about time,
presentation,
and location relevance.
At the heart
of WidgetKit is the timeline.
This is the core mechanism
of Widgets
to stay relevant
throughout the day.
A timeline is composed
of one or more timeline entries.
In this example,
you can see three such entries,
one at 9:00 AM,
9:30 AM, and 10:00 AM.
Now, when the system asks
your widget for a timeline,
the resulting timeline
will be archived and its entries
rendered at specific times
you specify into the future.
This lets the system have
your user interface ready
at a moment’s notice
to be displayed
right when the user needs it.
Let’s look at some
examples of timelines,
starting from
the most simplistic,
and look at the type of content
that might be in them.
Here’s an example
of the simplest timeline
with just a single entry:
Screen Time.
Now, because Screen Time can’t
predict or forecast data
into the future
and it’s strictly based
on the statistical history
of how the user’s device
has been used,
it really can’t leverage
multiple entries
in its timeline very well,
so it just uses a single entry.
This is the most simplistic
timeline that you can have.
That said, though,
not all widgets need
to be single entry,
and in fact, in most cases,
I’d encourage you to consider
and question why you aren’t
offering multiple entries
in your timeline.
If you have
forward-looking content,
have important dates
or deadlines, or can forecast
your content into the future,
your widget should really be
taking advantage of multiple
entries in your timeline.
Here’s another example
from Weather.
As you can see,
Weather’s timeline provides
multiple entries to last
hours throughout the day.
Now, the first entry here is
the most accurate
because it represents
the current weather,
and all the other
subsequent entries represent
forecast data at times
later in the day.
This extra forecast data
is super useful
as widget reloads aren’t
guaranteed to reload
at the exact time
that you specify.
And if a reload doesn’t hit
that target date
exactly when it’s desired,
then now the system has
additional forecasted content
to tide over
the user experience.
Here’s an example from Photos.
You can see
that the Photos timeline
provides a number
of personal and relevant photos
to appear
at specific times of the day.
For me, these are some really,
really great memories.
And now,
while the widget reloads
only a couple times a day,
it really gives the feeling
of being lively throughout
by presenting
new and fresh content from these
multiple timeline entries.
As you can see here,
even if you don’t have
data that’s forecastable
like weather,
as in this example with Photos,
you can still incorporate
content that’s relevant
to the user in a way
that can surprise and delight
by leveraging
these multiple entries
in your timeline.
Now, because some widgets
are viewed more than others,
we decided to give widgets
a fairness factor for updates.
We call this an update budget.
Budgets are allocated
and accumulated through the day,
and they’re heavily influenced
by user viewing habits.
A frequently viewed widget
can be expected to receive
somewhere in the ballpark
of around 40 to 70
background updates per day,
which translates to an update
roughly every 15 to 30 minutes
if spaced evenly
during the normal hours
that a user is awake.
However, of course
not all reloads have to be
evenly spaced like this,
and our goal was to enable
and support
a varied update cadence
for different requirements.
For example,
maybe you have a sports widget
that’s largely idle
until an upcoming game
for a favorite team,
and then it can receive a burst
of score updates before,
during, and even after the game.
WidgetKit’s smart,
and it may withhold updates
when the user isn’t using
the device
for extended periods of time
like when the user’s sleeping.
Otherwise,
widget updates may be withheld
until budgets become available
for a particular widget.
All that said,
though, reloads are not
an every second operation.
Widgets are not about creating
a live running experience
on the Home Screen.
Now, there’s numerous ways
that your widgets
will refresh throughout the day.
And we’re gonna walk
through each of these briefly
to understand what they are,
how they work,
and how they function
relative to the budget
that we just introduced.
The first is
the TimelineReloadPolicy,
which is API in WidgetKit.
This is the core mechanism
for your reloads
to occur automatically.
When you provide a timeline,
you also provide
a reload policy alongside it.
This reload policy informs
the system when you’d like
to automatically refresh
your widget in the background.
These automatic updates
are budgeted and debited
from your widget’s
current available budget.
Next is the WidgetCenter
reload API.
This is an API to refresh
your widget when events occur
that would invalidate
your widget’s existing data.
Now, normally,
requests using this API would
consume available budget,
meaning that updates
won’t occur
until budget is available.
However, there are a few
situational exceptions that will
make these reloads occur both
immediately and budget-free.
These are when your container
app is foreground to the user
or when your app is
participating in a user session,
like Navigation
or Now Playing audio.
This API is really
supplemental to the automatic
background updates from
the TimelineReloadPolicy API.
Your widgets can also update
when a significant
location change has occurred.
When the system detects
a significant location change
and your widget uses location,
the system will grant you
a budget-free update.
This refresh occurs when
the user next views your widget
so that location can be
resolved appropriately.
Now, note that this is
not guaranteed to happen
right when the location
change occurs
but, rather, the next time
the user views the widget.
We’ll talk a little bit more
on location later.
The system can
refresh your widget, too,
if its presentation
environment changes.
For example,
maybe the user changes
an Accessibility preference
like dynamic text or bold text,
there’s a language
or region change,
an iCloud or App Store
account change,
significant time change,
and more.
Lastly, due to budgeting,
if a user has a widget
that’s rarely seen,
it may not receive
as many updates as you,
the developer, may prefer.
The system knows
what dates are in your timeline,
what your preferred
refresh time is,
and general view history
from the user.
The system may grant
a budget-free reload
if it thinks the data
may be stale
when it’s viewed by the user.
Of course, all these
system-initiated updates
are always budget-free.
As we learned just a moment ago,
each timeline comes paired
with a reload policy
that describes
when it should automatically
update in the background.
WidgetKit offers
three choices here: atEnd,
afterDate, and never.
Which of these
three reload policies
are appropriate for your widget?
Let’s dive in
to talk about each one,
with some examples for context,
and we’ll talk about gotchas
on what to be mindful about
with each one.
The first policy we’ll discuss
is the atEnd reload policy.
This policy will mark
your widget eligible
to be refreshed when
the timeline comes to an end,
that is, of course, when
the last entry becomes relevant.
In this case, it’s at 10:30 AM.
Note, too,
that this time is simply
the time that the widget becomes
eligible for refreshing,
and it doesn’t guarantee
that it’ll refresh
exactly at this time.
Further, if using atEnd
with widgets that have
single-entry timelines,
like the Screen Time example
we talked about before,
the system will choose
an appropriate time
for your widget.
atEnd is recommended if
your widget already has content
that extends beyond the life
of its current timeline.
I kind of like to think about it
like viewing windows
into your content.
Let’s look at an example.
Outlined here
is the current timeline
for the Calendar widget
on June 7th.
It has four entries.
I’ve included its past
and future content to help
showcase the windows.
And as we change
the timeline for June 8th,
you can see what I mean
by viewing a window
into its content.
And again
for the timeline for June 9th.
We’re just changing
the perspective on the data
that’s already available
and provided by the user.
This type of content
is really where using
the atEnd policy shines.
Now, some examples of widgets
that use the atEnd policy
include Reminders, Calendar,
Photos, Tips, and more.
Again, these are all widgets
with endless content well known
into the future where you can
simply view a window into it.
It’s not really a great fit
for single-entry timelines
because the system’s gonna
choose a reload time for you,
and it’s probably not
what you want.
AtEnd is also not recommended
if your timeline has
projected content that loses
relevance or accuracy over time.
We simply want
your content to be
the most relevant
that it can be,
and if we wait
until the end of the timeline
when things are
the least relevant
to become eligible for updating,
then it just doesn’t lead
to the best user experience.
So that’s atEnd.
Now, let’s talk about afterDate.
The afterDate reload policy
makes your widget
eligible for reloading
after the date that’s specified.
With afterDate,
you’re really in full control
of the eligibility time.
In this example,
let’s pretend the timeline
is valid from 9:00 AM
to roughly 11:00 AM.
A widget reload policy date
of 9:30 AM was chosen
because the widget’s
forecast data
starts to lose accuracy
around 9:45 or so.
This gives the widget
plenty of runway after 9:30
to still show its forecast data,
even if it’s not reloaded
immediately at 9:30.
afterDate is most appropriate
for content that can change
unpredictably or unexpectedly
throughout the day
as well as for data
whose accuracy or relevance
changes periodically.
Some examples of widgets
that use afterDate
include Stocks, Weather,
News, Mail, and more.
These are all widgets
with content that can
change unpredictably
or unexpectedly through the day.
Now, with afterDate,
you have to really be careful
of a few potential issues.
Be cautious
of near-immediate reloads.
It can be valid to specify
a date a minute or so away
but usually only
for very narrow windows of time.
Asking for too many refreshes
at this level of resolution
can starve yourself
of reloads later.
Also be careful if you align
widgets refresh dates
across devices.
For example,
the U.S. Stock Market opens
at 9:30 AM on the East Coast
and you schedule a refresh
at exactly 9:30 AM
to fetch that initial data
for the day from servers.
Remember, your widget
could be on thousands
or even many millions
of devices,
potentially even multiple times
on each of those devices
as well.
And if you have to have
time-aligned data pulls
like this,
you really should consider
adding some level
of random jitter to these dates
in addition to hitting
caching servers.
These are especially important
to consider
to avoid any potentially
unplanned or unnecessary costs.
Lastly, let’s talk about
my favorite reload policy,
which is never.
The never reload policy
is the simplest policy
because it never
automatically reloads.
If your widget’s content
can only change
through its container
application being foreground
or through discrete events
like push notifications,
then never is a great choice
for your widget.
When using the never policy,
you can keep your widget
up to date solely with
the WidgetCenter reload API
from your container
or other accessory extensions.
This really minimizes
reloads to happen
only when necessary
and it keeps minimal impact
to your budget
and to the user’s battery life.
Never is also appropriate
if your widget requires
an explicit user condition
in your app
that hasn’t yet been satisfied.
For example,
maybe logging in to a service
or purchasing
some specific content.
Consider never if your widget
can’t produce meaningful content
before these types of conditions
are met in your app.
Good examples of widgets
that use the never policy
include TV, Notes, Music,
Podcasts, Contacts, and more.
These are all widgets
and apps that require
user interaction in the app
to drive content changes
or they receive pushes
for those content updates.
In summary, leverage timeline
entries to your advantage.
Choose the correct
reload policy for your widget,
and use WidgetCenter’s
reload API
to reload timeline events
on discrete events.
All right, let’s move on
to presentation relevance.
Your widget may be presented
in specific contexts
on iOS or macOS
that could result
in your widget
changing appearance.
The widget may sometimes
be rerendered
without any timeline updates.
And great widgets
will always adapt
to these presentation
environments appropriately.
So we’re gonna talk
about color schemes,
Dark and Light Mode,
partial privacy redactions,
which are new in iOS 15,
and full-on privacy redactions.
WidgetKit will automatically
handle shifting your content
between Light and Dark Mode
as the system settings change.
This is because we use
the power of SwiftUI.
Now think about
how you want your widget
to look in these
respective contexts.
Here you can see examples
of Notes and Calendar
in both the light
and dark schemes.
Remember, though,
that not all widgets necessarily
have to conform to Light
and Dark Mode by changing
their background
and text colors.
There are a few widgets,
like Music and Stocks,
for example,
that don’t change their colors.
If your application design
is agnostic
of this high contrast content
of dark and light styles,
then feel free to continue
whatever color scheme
makes sense for your widget.
You can also preview
color scheme changes
to your widget in Xcode
through Xcode Previews.
Here’s a quick example
of previewing
a systemSmall widget
in Light Mode.
And now in Dark Mode.
All we had to do was
add the colorScheme
environment override to preview
how our widget would look
in this environment.
And if you want the system
standard background color
for Light and Dark Mode
as shown here,
then use BackgroundStyle
for your fill.
Widgets are also subjected
to presentation environments
that can be privacy sensitive,
like the Lock Screen on iOS.
New in iOS 15,
widgets can now redact
partial content
in these situations.
Now, that may sound
really confusing,
so let’s give an example to see
what the heck
I’m talking about here.
Let’s pretend we had
a banking widget
where I’m showing the balance
available in a specific account.
In this case, I have $128.45
available in my account.
Now, when we go to the Lock
Screen and lock the device,
this account balance still
appears in iOS 14
because WidgetKit really had
no way to dynamically redact
the balance information
when the device became locked.
However,
that’s now changed in iOS 15,
and you may now
contextually mark
specific views to be redacted
in these situations.
Now, to show you how to do that,
all we do is, we simply insert
the .privacySensitive
view modifier
on the text representing
the balance amount.
So when not passcode locked,
as you can see here,
the view still renders
the balance amount
as you’d expect.
But when we now lock the device,
the balance amount becomes
masked, or redacted.
Be aware, too,
that this modifier can be
applied to any view,
including container views
like hstacks and vstacks.
And if applied to a container,
the entire container
will be redacted.
If your app leverages complete
data protection that can’t be
touched while an iOS device
is passcode locked, for example,
maybe your app is using
Health data and you skipped
building a widget
or were scared to include it
because you thought it had to be
shown on the Lock Screen,
then this feature
is really for you.
WidgetKit can
automatically replace
your active timeline content
with your placeholder content
when the device is
passcode locked
for a full redaction of content.
And it can even withhold
updates for the duration
while the device is
passcode locked.
This is all possible
when you adopt
the default-data-protection
entitlement listed here.
Your timeline data will be
stored per your wishes
in that data class
on the device.
We really take your data
privacy seriously here.
Lastly, I want to talk
about location relevancy.
Widgets, like your app,
can also provide
contextual information
for our current
physical location
or just simply locations
that are relevant
to the user
in one way or another.
If your application uses
location normally,
then it’s likely
that your widget should too.
Because widgets can have
multiple instances
on the Home screen
and in Notification Center
on the Mac,
consider offering pre-selected
and even searchable locations
for your widgets
in addition to using
the current location
just like we do
with the Weather widget
through the power of Intents.
Now, to fetch current location
in your widget,
there’s only
a few steps required.
First, you need to specify
the NSWidgetUsesLocation
key in your Info.plist.
This lets the system know
that you’ll be
using location
from your widget extension.
Secondly,
use the CLLocationManager
as you would normally,
except this time
from your TimelineProvider
in your widget extension.
Consider the resolution
your widget requires,
as it’s faster
to resolve coarse location,
and it can result
in a better user experience
if you don’t need
super precise location.
In general, the more precise
the location requested,
the longer it’s gonna take
to resolve.
Lastly, you can check
whether the widget is authorized
for location updates by using
the isAuthorizedForWidgetUpdates
API on the CLLocationManager.
This’ll tell you
whether the user has granted
your widget permission
to use location or not.
Speaking of permissions,
let’s look
at location permissions
for widgets in more detail
to see how they work.
Permissions for the widget
are generally shared
with its app container.
Here, you can see a list
of the available location
permissions available
from the Settings app.
If the user selects
“While using app,”
the user’s location is available
to the widget
only when the widget’s
container app
is foreground to the user
or other situations that would
consider the app to be in-use,
like being in a nav session.
If the user selects
“While using app or widgets,”
then location is available
just the same as before
with “While using app,”
but with an additional allowance
specific to the widget.
This allows the widget
permissions to receive location
up to 15 minutes
after a widget was last viewed.
And when location can’t be
resolved with either of these
two permissions set,
consider alternate content,
potentially even prior content
if it’s available,
or simply indicating
that the location
couldn’t be resolved.
If the user selects “Always”
for the permission,
the widget will always have
available permission
to access location.
Finally, let’s talk about
building customizable widgets.
We’re gonna talk about size,
kind, and configuration
as a means for users
to personalize
their widget experience.
Now, widgets come
in all different sizes.
And it’s recommended to support
as many sizes as you can
so that users have choice
when placing their widgets.
Remember that small variances do
exist in sizing between devices,
and it’s best to use
system standard padding,
margins, text styles,
and text sizes when possible.
Now, if you look at this iPad,
it’s really transformed
into a content showcase.
If it’s not obvious, a new size
has been added in iOS 15
specifically for the iPad,
and we call it Extra Large.
Here it is
so you can see it better.
It’s the same height
as the large widget but wider
to showcase even more content
that’s available on the iPad.
And here’s how you add it
to your widget.
Here I’ve added it
to an existing widget config
that already supports
the systemLarge family.
By default, if you don’t specify
supported families
on your widget configuration,
then the new size will be
supported automatically
if you build with the iOS 15 SDK,
or later.
The next axis
for personalization
is the widget kind.
Kinds of widgets offer
different perspectives
into your data or content.
So think about
what kinds of widgets
might make the most sense
in your app.
The best way to describe these
is really by example.
Here’s an example from Clock.
On the left,
we have a City widget
that tracks the time
of a single city,
and on the right,
a World Clock widget
that can accommodate
many different cities
in the same view.
Here’s another example
from Stocks.
On the left,
there’s a stock Symbol widget
that shows the stock price
for a given stock--
in this case, Apple--
and on the right,
an Overview widget.
The Overview widget
will show a series of stocks
reflected in the user’s
Stocks app.
So how do you publish these
different kinds of widgets?
Well, to publish multiple kinds
of widgets is super trivial.
Using that Stocks example
from before,
here I have a Symbol widget
and an Overview widget
in the top left.
To publish these,
you just return the different
widget configurations
in a WidgetBundle object
and include the @main attribute
to the WidgetBundle.
It’s that easy.
Note that the order
that widgets are defined
in the bundle
is also very important.
This order reflects
how your widgets
will appear
in the widget gallery.
So make sure
that the first widget listed
is your hero use case.
Lastly, it’s not possible
to dynamically publish
or dynamically retract
the availability of a widget
once your app is installed.
So some care and thought
should be applied
around the support
of your widgets over time.
The last axis
for customizability
is through configuration.
And widgets support two types:
static and Intent-based
configurations.
Static widget
configurations deliver
the same content
for each widget instance.
Remember that Stocks Overview
example from before?
Well, each one’s gonna show
the exact same content
even if they’re in different
locations on the user’s device.
Static widgets are super simple,
and they’re elegant widget
definitions because they take
no configuration
or setup from the user.
On the other hand,
Intent widget configurations
deliver user-configured content
for each instance.
Check out these Stock Symbol
widgets on the right.
This user has configured
many different instances,
each showcasing
a different stock.
Now, this is
some pretty sweet stuff.
And a user could even combine
these all into a stack
of widgets on their Home Screen
to flip through to save space.
So how are these configured
by the user, you might ask.
Well, from a user’s perspective,
the system will provide
all the surrounding UI pieces.
And after tapping on a widget
in Edit mode
that supports Intents,
the configuration platter
is shown.
It presents a list
of parameters from the Intent
that the user can configure.
And in this example,
there’s a single parameter
for the Symbol to track
and its value
is currently the string AAPL
for the Apple stock.
Now, once a user taps
on a parameter,
an input controller appears
to collect the input
from the user.
And once completed, the widget
will update automatically.
Now, there’s a ton
of customization that you can do
with an Intent,
and there’s a great talk
from WWDC 2020 that I’ll share
in a moment to help you
get started if you want
an Intent configuration.
In the meantime,
let’s just quickly highlight
what the differences are
between coding a widget
based on Intents
versus a static configuration.
The static configuration’s
really simple.
You just instantiate
a StaticConfiguration object
with the standard
TimelineProvider.
Let’s contrast that
with an Intent configuration.
All that’s different here
is that the StaticConfiguration
is replaced
by an IntentConfiguration,
and the TimelineProvider
is replaced
by an IntentTimelineProvider.
Each of these has
a slightly modified interface
to support Intents,
and this is so you can receive
the user-configured Intent
when populating your timeline.
For a more detailed look
at creating and configuring
Intents for widgets,
including an overview
on the various
data types supported
and what they look like
from the config UI,
check out the “Add configuration
and intelligence
to your widgets” talk
from WWDC 2020.
To wrap up,
we’ve reviewed how great widgets
make use
of their timeline entries,
master their reload policy,
and adapt to their presentation
and potentially
physical environments.
Plan to offer
different sizes, kinds,
and configurations
to give a dynamic
and personalizable experience
to your users.
Thank you.