[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Jen] Hi, I’m Jen Simmons.
And I’m here to talk about how the new
Safari impacts web design and development.
If you’re a web designer, a web developer,
or have any role involved
in making a website or a web app,
this session is for you.
This is a huge year for Safari.
In this session,
we’re going to focus on the visual
or interaction design impact
of the changes in Safari.
Safari has an all-new design.
By default,
your website’s gonna look great,
but if you wanna go the extra mile,
this session will empower you
to make your work really shine
in the new Safari.
We’ll talk about a few of the great
new features in macOS, iOS,
and iPadOS and how they’ll impact the web.
We’ll cover what’s new in CSS,
including my favorite,
the new aspect-ratio property.
And we’ll take a look at form controls,
controls we’ve newly implemented
and a whole new look for forms
on iOS and iPadOS.
Let’s start with the design
of the browser itself.
Since very early
in the evolution of the web browser,
most of the browsers we’ve used have had
a few fundamental things in common.
There’s a very tall toolbar
at the top with a slot
for the URL that’s on its own line.
And the website stays inside this space,
this portal to the web, the viewport.
Of course, as users,
we’ve trained ourselves
to put all of our focus on the website
that we’re using,
but for years, the browser itself
has maintained a strong visual presence.
No, matter how a website
is designed to look and feel,
the browser interface framed that design
and dominated it.
What if we could get rid of that frame
and extend the design of the website
to every edge of the window?
Well, that’s what we’ve done in Safari 15.
This year, we’ve reimagined
the browsing experience as we know it.
We’re putting all the focus
on the web content.
The new Safari blends the tab bar
into each website
by changing its background color.
The entire interface is on one line,
and things naturally appear when needed.
This makes your content
feel more expansive.
Each web page or web app takes over,
extending to all four edges of the window.
The browser interface yields
to the content.
So what determines which color is used
for the background of the toolbar?
As a web designer or developer,
you can choose the color
and code that choice into your HTML.
For sites that don’t provide a color,
Safari will figure out a color to use.
Sometimes Safari matches
the background color of the web page.
Other times,
it matches the header background.
To provide your choice
for the toolbar color,
put it in the HTML head using a meta tag
with name=“theme-color,”
and use the content attribute
to specify the color.
By providing this information
in the HTML head,
Safari will get it immediately
on page load.
It’s also declarative code.
It’s very simple to use.
You can support both Light and Dark Mode
by setting two colors.
Yes, now you can add
media attributes to meta tags.
In this case,
media=“(prefers-color-scheme: light)”
in the first meta tag
and “(prefers-color-scheme: dark)”
in the second.
This is a new addition
to the HTML specification
that we proposed this spring.
It gives us a simple,
robust way to hook
into which color scheme
the user has asked for.
In browsers that do support
name=“theme-color”
but don’t yet support using
the media attribute on meta tags,
those browsers will use
the first theme-color declaration
and ignore the rest.
So put your fallback first,
not last, the way you do in CSS.
Even if your site doesn’t have
a whole design for Dark Mode,
you might want to set your own color
for the tab bar
when the device is in Dark Mode.
If the one color you’ve specified
is too light,
Safari will make adjustments
in order to give the user
the Dark Mode experience
that they’ve asked for.
Instead of defining the theme color
on the HTML head,
you can define it in a web manifest file.
If you specify it in both places,
the color in the HTML head
is the one that’s used.
And right now in June of 2021,
there’s not yet a way
to define multiple colors
for Light and Dark Modes
in a web manifest file.
There’s discussion happening
in the working group
right now to figure that out.
There’s also a very narrow
range of colors
that Safari isn’t going to apply -
colors, really,
that would totally get in the way
of the user’s experience,
maybe making it inaccessible.
For these, Safari will do
something else, like here,
changing this site’s tab bar to white.
If the color that you’ve chosen
doesn’t seem to be working,
just try adjusting it a bit.
If you’d like,
you can set the theme color
to be different
on different parts of your website.
Each separate HTML page has its own head.
Or you can use JavaScript
to swap out the theme color dynamically
in reaction to a user’s behavior.
Think through ways that your design
can blend the tab bar seamlessly
into your site.
That’s how you can create a feeling
of your website or web app
filling the whole window
in Safari 15 on macOS
and Safari for iPadOS and iOS 15.
Next, let’s look
at two other small adjustments
that you can do
to really take your website
to the next level.
Many of us have a lot of tabs open
in our web browsers as we work.
The new Safari provides an intuitive way
to organize those tabs into groups.
I really like this.
I’ve organized my work projects
into separate groups
and named each whatever I want,
and then I can put them away.
Put way the things
that I’m not working on,
knowing that I can reload those tabs
later on any device,
since Tab Groups are synced
across macOS, iOS and iPadOS.
While Tab Groups give us the ability
to declutter the tab bar,
it still is possible to have
a lot of tabs open
in any one window.
When there are a lot of tabs,
the favicon becomes pretty important
for easily identifying which tab is which.
You’ll want to make sure you provide
a great icon for your site,
one that supports high-resolution devices.
A favicon with a transparent background
can look especially great.
By the way, a lot of teams
use automated tooling
to generate the different sizes
and formats of icons
to support a wide range of devices.
Often, such tooling generates code
that specifies a theme color
along with the icon code
for the HTML head.
Or perhaps your CMS
or your front-end framework
is defining a theme color,
and you didn’t realize it.
Check and see.
Test that color and see if it’s a good one
for the design of your site,
perhaps changing it to a better one.
When most people look at the new tab bar,
they’ll just see all their tabs
on one line.
As someone who makes websites,
you’ll probably notice
that when the site is loaded
into a browser window,
the tab for that site
shows its domain name.
And when a site is in a background tab,
the web page title is what’s displayed,
the text in the title tag
in the HTML head.
The space for the page title
can be limited,
so crafting a thoughtful pattern
for your web page title is important.
The quicker the title gets to the point,
the easier it is
for users to find the tab that they want.
Some sites put the name
of the website first
and the name of the page second.
Instead, put the content title first.
That way, if someone has
your site open in multiple tabs,
it’s easier to tell which tab is which.
The color of the tab bar,
the favicon, and the page title
are all parts of a site
to design with intention.
They don’t show up on the web page itself,
but they deeply impact
someone’s experience
of your website or web app.
To show you more
on how to leverage the power
of the theme-color meta tag, here’s Myles.
[Myles] Hi, I’m Myles.
And I’m working on Dog Dog DC,
which is a website
where people can stream videos
of their dogs during WWDC.
Here, you can see
Maggie’s stream in Safari.
She looks so happy!
I’ve started the stream
out paused for now,
but I’ll unpause it for just a little.
Good catch.
And on the right side of Dog Dog DC,
you can comment in real time
to express just how good Maggie is.
Now, at the top of the Safari window,
Safari 15 colors the tab bar black,
which is actually
the background color of my page.
You can see the black color is used
as the background
of the center content area at the bottom.
And that black color looks good
up there in the tab bar.
The whole window looks like it has
a holistic, coherent design.
You can also see in the tab bar
that Safari is mentioning
my page is Not Secure,
which I expect because this is
my development environment.
Now, we’ve also got a floating blue bar
at the top of the website
that would look really great
extended up into the tab bar.
So if I go into my source code
in the Editor over here...
I can override the black color
that Safari automatically discovered
to match this beautiful blue color.
I’ll add this one meta tag,
which will extend that blue color
up into the tab bar.
Then I’ll reload
and see what it looks like.
That looks pretty good,
but we’ve designed Dog Dog DC
to contain a gray newsletter bar
at the top that’s horizontal,
which actually interrupts
the flow of color a little bit
into the top tab bar.
In order to get an uninterrupted canvas,
let’s denote the newsletter bar
another way rather than background color.
Hmm.
I’ll keep playing around with it later.
For now, I’ll just remove
the newsletter bar.
Wow, that now looks great.
The color is uninterrupted
and really shines in Safari 15.
And of course, the same effect
works great on iPadOS too.
All right.
Now, I could sit here
and watch Maggie all day,
but what I really want to do
is bring her front and center
and dim out everything except her
and the chat area,
because I take
those doggo comments seriously.
So of course, I’m going to tap
this Theater Mode button.
But wait.
When I enter Theater Mode,
the tab bar is still colorful.
Theater Mode would be a little bit
better if we updated the theme color
when entering Theater Mode.
Well, we can fix that over here
in my JavaScript.
Earlier, Jen showed you how to use
a media query in the meta element itself
to automatically react to changes
in the environment, like Dark Mode.
However, for changes initiated
by my page itself,
I can do this in a more proactive way
using JavaScript
to simply modify the meta element itself
using standard JavaScript
when entering Theater Mode.
And, of course, I can’t forget to reset
the element when exiting Theater Mode.
Let’s see what it looks like now.
Perfect.
And there we go.
That looks so much better.
Now I can really focus on Maggie.
Back to you, Jen.
Dog Dog DC.
I’m gonna make sure to visit that site
once it’s online, Myles.
Thanks.
I really love how this
opens up another way
for web designers to impact
people’s visceral experience of the web.
Now let’s dive a bit deeper
into what’s happening on iOS.
You’ll notice the theme color
is used here, too, at the top,
wrapping around the sensor housing
so the web page or web app
fills the whole screen.
You’ll also notice that we’ve moved
the tab bar to the bottom of the screen.
This puts it directly
under the user’s thumb,
making it easier for them to reach,
especially if they’re using
their phone one-handed.
Swipe sideways on the tab bar
to switch between the tabs.
And swipe up to see
a grid of all the tabs
and to access Tab Groups.
When a user scrolls the web page,
the tab bar minimizes down
to just the domain name at the very bottom
to ensure people know where they are.
When they pull the page back down,
the expanded tab bar reappears.
All of this means that the websites
and web apps that you make
are the shining star of the show.
But what if you’ve built
something important
at the bottom of the page
and now that gets covered up
by the new tab bar?
This is where you want to use
environment variables in your CSS
to ensure there’s enough padding
or margin or a grid track
or however you write your layout code.
You can use an environment variable
to make sure any UI or content
that would be affected by the tab bar
scoots out of the way.
So what is an environment variable?
It’s a dynamic measurement
that’s provided by the browser.
You can see here,
the green is what’s called the safe area.
When the tab bar is expanded
at the bottom,
the safe area starts above it.
As the tab bar minimizes,
the dimensions of the safe area change.
env(safe-area-inset-bottom)
is a measurement
of however many pixels it is
from the safe area
to the bottom of the viewport.
It’s a lot like the var function
in CSS custom properties.
Maybe you’ve used custom properties
to turn all your colors
into variables, for instance.
Only instead of you
defining this variable,
the browser defines it.
It’s providing information
about the environment.
And you can use that length measurement
any place in your code,
including inside a calc.
Here, my footer is position: sticky
with some padding to push
my two links away
from the edges of the footer.
I defined a padding bottom
of 1rem + env(safe-area-inset-bottom).
In many contexts, that’ll be 1rem + 0.
On iOS, it will be 1rem plus the distance
that’s needed to clear the tab bar.
There are four environment variables
that provide a measurement
from the edge of the safe area
to the edge of the viewport:
env(safe-area-inset-top),
-right, -bottom, and -left.
These environment variables
don’t just work in Safari.
They’re defined in a CSS specification
and work across different browsers,
devices,
and operating systems.
If you want to make vertical adjustments,
you do need to take the action
of using an environment variable.
Safari won’t try to move
content around by default.
When an iPhone is rotated sideways,
however,
it works a bit differently.
There’s also a safe area
defined to avoid the sensor housing
and the round edges of the screen.
By default, Safari will
automatically move web content in
from the left and right edge
and put it into the safe area.
You might wonder why.
Well, if instead,
Safari extended every site
to the left and right edge,
content could be lost.
Here, the text is covered up.
And that’s--that’s bad for usability.
To prevent data loss,
Safari will scoot content
into the safe area,
including when a site is using
a meta viewport tag
with width=device-width,
which is the meta tag that’s commonly used
in responsive web design.
But of course I’d like
this design to look better.
I’d like for my purple header
and the photo
to extend to the edges of the screen.
I can signal to Safari that I want
the browser to extend the content
to the left and right edges
by changing the meta viewport tag
to viewport-fit=cover.
Now I’m responsible to make sure
that the layout works.
I’ll use environment variables
to ensure the content is fully visible.
I can define a left margin
of env(safe-area-inset-left)
on the header text
and on the paragraph text.
For more information about safe area
insets and environment variables,
check out the article “Designing Websites
for iPhone X” on the WebKit Blog,
linked in the notes for this session.
Let’s go out to Myles
and see how
environment variables work in action.
Now let’s see what Dog Dog DC
looks like in Safari on iPhone.
Over here on my iPhone,
we can see Maggie the same way
we were seeing her before,
but this time on a smaller device.
But wait.
It looks like there’s a problem.
When the user scrolls the chat area,
the input area overlaps the tab bar.
Dog Dog DC is explicitly using vh units
to size itself from top to bottom,
explicitly taking exactly
the size of the whole viewport,
which it’s now sharing with the tab bar.
As a user, I can scroll
to minimize the tab bar,
and that’s pretty easy.
But as a developer,
I want to make sure that my users
have the best experience possible
even when they scroll.
Luckily, I can use safe area insets
to move the input area up
by the appropriate amount.
All I have to do is add bottom padding
and set it to safe-area-inset-bottom.
Then I just reload my web page.
I actually just used one
of my favorite new features of Safari 15:
pull to refresh.
Hmm.
That’s pretty close to what I want,
but it looks like now
it’s a little too high.
Oh, I see the problem.
I’ve given the input area bottom padding
when it already has a bottom margin,
and those two things stack vertically.
So it looks like I should just
update the existing margin
to use the safe area inset instead.
Let’s adjust these styles again
and see what it looks like now.
Perfect.
This actually shows the power
of environment variables.
They can be applied
to any length in your style.
You can use them in borders, margin,
padding, line-height, anything.
As the tab bar is minimized and expanded,
the value of the environment variable
will automatically update,
and Safari will automatically
re-layout the page
with the new value when they do.
You can also see in Dog Dog DC
how the chat area is the area that resizes
when the tab bar is expanded.
Everything above it stays the same size,
while everything below it
hugs the tab bar.
This is because
we’re using Flexbox layout,
where this kind of behavior is very
natural and straightforward to create.
If you haven’t already started using
these more modern layout modes
like Flexbox or grid,
now would be a great time
to give them another look.
Next, let’s hear from Jen
about some more great features
in Safari 15.
Thanks, Myles.
Environment variables are
another powerful tool for creating layouts
that dynamically respond
to whichever device someone is using.
Let’s also see how a website looks
when someone saves it
as a Home screen app.
I can save this site
to my Home screen with a tap.
Now my site’s icon is on my Home screen.
If I tap on it, I can see the site opened
as a Home screen app.
It looks fantastic.
The theme color fills the top
of the screen, just like in Safari.
I get an app-like experience.
You’ll notice there’s no tab bar
at the bottom.
We aren’t in the Safari app.
We are in the Resilient web design app.
So that’s the new Safari
and how you can make sure
your website looks fantastic.
Next, let’s talk about several
of the amazing new features
of macOS, iOS, and iPadOS
and how they’ll impact the web.
Often, the very first experience
people will have of your website
is when someone else tells them about it,
like when one person sends a link
to another in Messages.
Anytime this happens,
the site appears as a simple rich link.
The way these rich links work
is consistent
across iOS, iPad OS, and macOS.
And this year, with Shared with You,
we’ve added many new places
and many new ways for people
to share web content with each other.
These are just two.
You’ll want to take the time
to ensure your site looks fantastic
when it’s presented in rich links.
By default, if nothing else, rich links
will pick up the web page title,
the site URL, and the favicon
and display them in a simple fashion.
We can improve on this
by adding to our metadata
in our HTML head through meta tags
with names defined
in the open graph protocol.
Let’s specify a title
that’s a bit better for this context
than the web page title.
And we’ll specify a graphic to display.
We want this image to be something
for this particular web page,
like the hero image
from the content of this page.
If we’d like, we can also provide a video.
The video will autoplay silently
if the user allows,
and they can tap on it to hear the sound.
You can learn more about the details
in “Ensuring beautiful rich links,”
a short video on developer.apple.com.
Customizing your rich links
is another detail that ensures people
have a fantastic experience
with your website or web app.
Next up, let’s take a look
at visual intelligence and the web.
So much text on the web
is stuck inside images.
Starting in Safari 15,
we’re using visual intelligence
to free that text.
Now people can interact with it directly,
just as they would
with any other text on a web page.
Here’s an image on Twitter
that’s full of text.
When we hover over it,
see the mouse pointer change
into a cursor?
Now we can drag over this text
and copy it,
just like any other text.
Anytime you hover over an image
on macOS Monterey
or touch the image on iOS or iPadOS 15,
visual intelligence quickly finds
and recognizes
all the text in that image.
Once visual intelligence finds text,
not only can you select and copy it,
you can look it up it, translate it,
search the web with that phrase,
share the text,
listen to it, just like any other text.
The text that visual intelligence finds,
it sort of becomes part of the web page,
and it sort of doesn’t become part
of the web page.
The text is injected into the Shadow DOM
inside the image,
which means it’s not affected
by JavaScript.
But it is affected by z-order.
So, if there’s something
overlaying your image,
like a transparent box,
visual intelligence won’t be able
to find any text in the image underneath.
The layer on top gets in the way.
We’ve integrated visual intelligence
into assistive technologies like VoiceOver
to make text that’s been trapped in images
available to many more people.
But that does not mean
that this feature changes
current accessibility best practices.
Of course, content on the web
that consists mostly of text
really should be put
on the web as text in HTML,
styled with a web font to give it
the look and feel if you want,
but as text content.
This is still the best practice.
For content that is a photo,
an illustration, or other image,
the best practice is still
to include alt text
as an attribute on the image element.
Great alt text provides
the kind of meaning and context
that only a human can explain.
Plus, not all browsers
have visual intelligence,
so continue to make sure that the images
on your website have useful alt text.
That said, it is pretty great to be able
to access text that, until now,
you had to be able to see to read
or to retype
in order to quote somewhere else.
Next, let’s take a look at the CSS
that’s been implemented
in WebKit over the last year.
First up, aspect ratio.
Aspect ratio is a new CSS property
that allows you to set
a preferred aspect ratio
for any element.
But what does that mean,
“set a preferred aspect ratio”?
Well, let’s first look at the kinds
of content on the web
that has a natural aspect ratio.
Images are a good example.
Let’s say we have an image of Maggie
that’s twice as wide as it is high.
That image has a 2:1 aspect ratio.
We’ll put this image on a web page
and make it flexible
by adding width: 100% and height: auto,
a classic responsive web design technique.
Because images have
a natural aspect ratio,
the height automatically changes
in direct relationship with the width.
This photo is always twice
as wide as it is tall,
and Maggie always looks really good.
This kind of behavior is so expected,
we almost don’t even see it anymore.
This is just how images work.
Video works the same way
when you put it in your page’s HTML
by using a video element.
Video files also have
a natural aspect ratio.
And the video element conveys
that aspect ratio to the browser
as it’s calculating the page layout.
But not all content has
a natural aspect ratio.
Here, I’ve got an article element.
Inside, there’s a headline
and a paragraph.
By default, the article element has
a width of auto and a height of auto.
In this writing mode, width of auto means
please stretch the article out
so it takes up 100%
of the space that’s available.
Height auto means be tall enough
to fit all of the content
that’s inside a view
and don’t be any taller.
We can see how when the column
of text gets narrower,
the text wraps more often
and takes up more
and more vertical space.
When the column gets wider,
the text reflows
and takes up less and less vertical space.
The height of my box is adjusting
to fit the text content -
not too short and not too tall -
without any regard
for any sort of aspect ratio.
For most of the history of the web,
this is just how layout has worked.
Any graphic design ideas
about using squares
or making boxes be a consistent shape,
those design ideas, well,
they were tossed into the bucket
of “Nope! The web doesn’t work that way!”
Until now.
Now we can write CSS
to define a preferred aspect ratio
on elements that otherwise
wouldn’t have one.
Let’s add aspect-ratio: 1 / 1 to our code,
which says whatever width
this ends up with,
think of that as one unit,
and then make the height
also be one unit,
which translates
to please make this a square.
The height grows bigger than it did before
in order to maintain that square.
But what happens when there’s too much
content to fit inside that square?
By default,
the box will automatically grow
to be taller.
With one line of code,
we can create a set of squares
or any shape box
with any certain aspect ratio,
knowing that if the content is longer
in one of the boxes,
that box will grow to prevent overflow.
If we want the aspect ratio
to always be obeyed,
even if that does cause overflow,
we can add min-height of 0 to our code.
Perhaps we want
to handle overflow another way,
like by adding overflow: scroll.
Now, I’ve been writing the value
to make this square as 1 / 1.
But I can instead just write this
as aspect-ratio: 1.
If there’s only one number, the browser
will assume that it’s “over one.”
In fact, there are a lot of ways
I can express the same aspect ratio,
including by using decimal numbers.
This gives us the freedom
to write aspect ratios
in ways that you might be familiar with
from other industries
like film and television
or art and design.
For the last decade,
it’s been pretty impossible
to use these ratios on the web,
even though they’ve had a deep
and meaningful place
throughout human culture
in architecture, painting,
book design, modern print design.
Now we can build our layouts
using these ratios.
Especially when you combine
aspect-ratio with CSS grid,
all kinds of new
design possibilities open up.
Speaking of film and video,
one very common use case
for aspect ratio
will be embedded video
from third-party services.
If you use YouTube, Vimeo, Wistia,
or any of the many
video hosting providers,
those give you an iFrame
to embed your video.
The iFrame element is not an element
that has a natural aspect ratio.
When responsive web design came along,
we wanted to make
our embedded videos flexible,
but we ran into trouble.
We’ve been stuck either using
a confusing padding hack in CSS
or using JavaScript to resize the video.
Now we can add one line of CSS
to give that iFrame
a preferred aspect ratio.
It’s a very elegant solution
to a very common problem.
Aspect ratio: it gives us
another powerful tool
to create the layout that we want.
Next up, flex gaps.
This year in Safari 14.1,
we shipped support for gaps
in Flexbox containers.
Flex gaps gives you a way
to define a minimum space between items
to make sure that there’s always a gap.
Here, I’ve got a navigation bar
that I’ve laid out in Flexbox.
I don’t want these menu bar items
to ever touch each other.
If I add a gap property,
with a 1rem value,
now there’s always a space
between the items.
No left or right margins are needed.
I don’t have to figure out how to remove
those margins on the outside edge.
This is much simpler.
There are many other features in CSS
that were implemented in WebKit this year,
including additional logical properties,
so important for supporting
international audiences.
The individual transform properties:
rotate, translate, and scale.
Updates and improvements
to scroll margin and scroll snap.
Support for new color spaces.
And the animation of pseudo elements
and discrete properties.
Many of these features
shipped this past spring
in Safari 14.1 on macOS
and Safari for iOS
and iPadOS 14.5.
And the rest will ship this fall
in Safari 15.
Next, let’s take a look at form controls.
In Safari 14.1, we shipped support
for the Date and Time inputs on macOS.
Now on Mac, users can fill out Date fields
by interacting with a Calendar control
or fill out the time with a Time control.
And client-side validation
is built right in.
For iOS and iPadOS 15,
we’ve completely redesigned
the form controls.
They’ll better match
the overall experience
and fit in much better with UIKit.
And they look great in Dark Mode too.
These are the new defaults
for form controls.
If you’ve overridden any of these styles,
then of course,
your styles will be applied.
We’ve also implemented a new color picker
for input type=“color”
on iOS and iPadOS
with three panels
for choosing or adjusting a color,
plus an eyedropper.
That’s our tour of Safari 15
and some of the highlights
of what landed in WebKit this year.
But before I go,
I want to make sure that you know
where to find important resources
for learning more
about Safari and WebKit
and where you can submit feedback
on what you’d like to see next.
The links to all these resources
are in the notes for this session.
If you’re interested in learning
about new JavaScript,
DOM APIs, and media format support,
check out “Develop advanced web content”
here at WWDC21.
Definitely watch
“Discover Web inspector improvements,”
and learn about the new
web developer tools coming to Safari,
including our own CSS Grid inspector.
To keep up with what’s coming
in the future,
download Safari Technology Preview,
the one with the purple logo.
It updates about every two weeks.
It’s an especially great way
to test against the latest bug fixes
and to use the most recent advancements
in Web inspector.
Webkit.org is the place
for WebKit release notes,
articles detailing new web technologies,
and the documentation for Web inspector.
And we want to hear from you.
If you have a suggestion
for the Web inspector
or for the interface of Safari,
file feedback
in Apple’s Feedback Assistant.
If you come across a bug in WebKit,
something about HTML, CSS, JavaScript,
or DOM APIs
that seems broken or missing,
please file a ticket at bugs.webkit.org.
And you can find and follow us
on Twitter @webkit.
I hope you’re as excited
about the new design
of Safari 15 as we are,
the way the new tab bar gives you
a new dimension for your design,
new possibilities for layout
with aspect ratio,
all-new form controls on iOS and iPad OS,
and so much more.
I can’t wait to see what innovations
in web design this brings.
Thanks for joining me and enjoy WWDC.
[upbeat music]