[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Ryan Chapman: Hello
and welcome to WWDC.
Hi, I'm Ryan Chapman,
and I work on
the Proactive Intelligence team.
Today I'll be talking to you
about how you can expand
your app's presence
with intent donations.
Our device's operating systems
have become
increasingly integrated with
the apps people use day to day.
This collaboration between
the system and apps
is at the heart of an
intelligent system experience
that gives our users
superpowers.
One of the primary ways
your apps can participate
in this collaboration
and expand your app's presence
and capabilities
throughout the system
is by donating intents.
In this session, I'll define
what intent donations are,
walk you through
the life of an intent donation,
and then talk to you
about how you can
structure your donations
for success
and ultimately expand your app's
presence across the system.
Let's go ahead and start out
with understanding
what intent donations are.
Three years ago in iOS 12,
we introduced Shortcuts.
Shortcuts let you expose
the capabilities of your app
as actions.
They enable people
to use your app's features
in new ways and places
across the operating system.
It's a really powerful way
to engage your users
and expand your presence
beyond the confines of your app.
Every action that you expose
should be accelerative,
by performing a key function
of your app.
That means it should
take something
that the user already
wanted to do with your app
and help them do it
even faster.
And next, every action
that you expose
should be repeatable and of
persistent interest to the user.
That means it should
be something
that the user
might want to do multiple times.
It's not a good idea
to expose an action
for something that someone
might only want to do
once or twice.
And you should also
only expose actions
that are stateless
and executable at any time,
because you can't
rely on someone
being in a particular state
before your action
will be ready for use.
To learn more about
what makes a great action,
be sure to check out
the session called,
"Design great actions
for Shortcuts,
Siri, and Suggestions"
from WWDC 2021.
So once you've decided
what actions to expose,
you're ready to check out
the Shortcuts APIs.
There are two APIS
that you can use
to adopt shortcuts for your app.
The first is NSUserActivity.
NSUserActivity
is a lightweight way
to represent
the state of your app,
and it integrates with
other Apple features
like Spotlight and Handoff.
And the second is intents.
Intents are a way
of representing, in detail,
a type of action that your app
can perform,
and Siri includes a bunch
of great built-in intents
that support
a range of capabilities
that you can use
to integrate with the system.
Intents also supports
the ability for you to define
your own custom intents
for use with Shortcuts.
To learn more about both APIs
and how to adopt shortcuts
for your app,
be sure to watch the
"Introduction to Siri Shortcuts"
session at WWDC 2018.
For this session,
I'll be focusing on Intents,
going over new and existing
opportunities for you
to offer your app's capabilities
throughout the system.
The first step toward
making an intent donation
is to decide what type
of intent you'd like to adopt.
Siri includes many great
built-in intents,
like for messaging,
reservations, media, and more.
There is also the ability
to define custom intents
in Xcode for Shortcuts.
So if the action that you want
to build corresponds
to one of the default
built-in SiriKit intents,
then you should adopt that.
But, otherwise,
you can define your own
using an intent
definition file in Xcode.
Once you've decided which
intent you'd like to adopt
and defined it in your app,
you can start
making intent donations.
An intent donation
is the act of telling the system
when a person performs
an action in your app.
The system will store
these donations
and use them to expand
your app's capabilities
and presence
throughout the system.
Apps that donate intents
show up in places
throughout the system
like Suggestions, Shortcuts,
Focus, Smart Stack,
and Siri.
Now that you understand
at a high level
what an intent donation is,
let's make this more concrete
by going through the life
of an intent donation
using an example.
Let's use the example
of checking the weather
in the Weather app.
For this app, checking the
weather at a particular location
is the key capability of the app
that I'd like to expose
an action for.
This app already
has an existing widget
that I'd like to make
configurable using my intent,
so someone can select the city
they'd like to see
the weather for in the widget.
Let's go ahead and learn how to
define a check weather intent,
how to donate it to the system,
and how the system
uses the donation.
The first step to defining
an intent in Xcode
is to create
an intent definition file.
To do this,
I'll add a new file...
...and select the SiriKit
Intent Definition File.
Then I'll select any targets
that I want to use
the custom intent in,
and confirm that
I'd like to create
the intent definition file.
Once the intent
definition file is created,
I can define the intent.
There wasn't an existing
built-in system intent
to check the weather,
so I can go ahead
and add a new intent.
I'll call the intent
"Check Weather."
From here, I can begin
defining the intent.
I'll start by checking
the "Intent is eligible
for widgets" option
because I'd like
to allow this intent
to work as a configuration
for my app's existing widget.
The system will also be able
to use my intent donations
to power Smart Stack
widget intelligence.
If you want your intent to also
support the Shortcuts app,
check the "Intent is
user-configurable
in the Shortcuts app
and Add to Siri" option.
I'll uncheck this option
for this demo
and just focus on
widgets and Suggestions.
I'll also leave the
"Intent is eligible for Siri
Suggestions" option checked
because I'd like the system
to use my donations
to surface Siri Suggestions
for my intent.
Next I need to define
the parameters of my intent.
I can define just one parameter
for the location
to check the weather in.
Next I need to select
the parameter's type.
This location represents
an object in my app
corresponding to the city
the app has the weather for,
so I'm going to use
a custom type
to represent this parameter.
I can go ahead and create
a custom type for a city
that has an identifier
and displayString.
Let's go back
to our location parameter.
You can see that
the type of the location
is the new custom City type.
I'll keep the option
for allowing users
to edit the value in widgets,
because I'd like this intent
to be used for widget
configuration.
Since this intent won't support
running in Siri for this demo,
I'll uncheck the "Siri can ask
for value when run" option.
When people configure
the widget,
the list of weather locations
will need to be provided
by the app and will change
depending on which cities
that person has saved
so I will check the "Options are
provided dynamically" checkbox.
Finally, I just need to define
the supported parameter
combinations for Suggestions.
The system reads
the intent definition file
to determine the intent
and parameter combinations
that an app supports
for prediction.
In this case,
the app supports an intent
with a location parameter set.
I'll go ahead
and add that parameter
as a supported combination.
Then I'll define the summary
that is shown in Suggestions.
And that's it.
I've defined the custom intent
to check the weather
that can be used
by widgets and Suggestions.
With the intent defined,
I just need to donate the intent
to the system whenever someone
checks the weather
for a specific location
in the app.
To donate the intent,
I create an instance
of the intent class
and set its parameter values.
After creating the intent,
I create an instance
of an INInteraction object,
passing in the intent,
then call the interaction
object's donate method
to donate the intent
to the system.
Behind the scenes, the system
stores these donations over time
along with the context
the person was in
when the intent was donated.
As they continue to check
the weather in the Weather app,
the app continues
to make intent donations.
In this case, they have been
checking the weather
in Cupertino and in San Diego.
The system uses the intent
parameters to determine
whether the intents
are equivalent or not.
As shown by the color
of the donations,
the two Cupertino donations
are equivalent
and are different from
the two San Diego donations.
In practice, the system
also receives donations
from many other apps
on the person's device.
If at any time
you'd like to delete donations,
you can delete a single donation
or a group of donations
using our deletion APIs.
If someone has,
for example,
removed the San Diego
weather location
from their stored
weather locations,
then you can delete intents
associated with
the San Diego location.
It's important
to delete donations
so people don't get suggestions
for actions in your app
that are no longer relevant.
When donating the intent,
the INInteraction identifier
and group identifier
can be used to later delete
one or more INInteractions
that you've donated.
You can either pass in
an array of identifiers
to delete individual
interactions,
or you can pass in
the group identifier
to delete a group
of interactions.
So how are all of these intent
donations used by the system?
Let's take a high level view
of the donation history
the system sees
across multiple days.
Here you can see three days
of donations for a person
and the donations that occurred
throughout the day,
starting with when they woke up.
The system uses machine learning
and on-device intelligence
to find patterns in the data
and predict what intent
is relevant
given a person's current context
and past behavioral patterns.
In this case, you can see that
this person has a pattern
associated with checking
the weather after they wake up.
The on-device intelligence
integrates with
user-facing features to expose
your app's capabilities
and presence to the user.
Let's look at some examples of
where this exposure takes place.
Before we do that,
it's worth noting
that all of the machine learning
and intelligence
is performed on-device
in a privacy-preserving manner,
meaning Apple does not
collect any data
that can be used
to personally identify a user.
With that said, let's return
to our weather example.
I can use the intent I defined
to make the app's
existing widget configurable.
After configuring the widget
to use the intent,
people will be able
to select the location
they'd like to see
the weather for in the widget.
With the app donating intents
that match the widget's
configuration intent,
the system is now
able to provide people
with Smart Stack widget
intelligence for the app.
Let's say there is a person who
has a Home screen configuration
with a Smart Stack.
New in iOS 15, the Smart Stack
supports Widget Suggestions,
which allow the system
to suggest widgets
the user doesn't have
in their stack
by placing them on top of the
stack at just the right time.
To determine whether a widget
should be suggested
and the correct time
to make the suggestion,
the system leverages
the intent donations
that match your widget
configuration intent.
In the weather example,
after the person woke up,
the Smart Stack placed
the Weather widget
on the top of the stack
at just the right time.
This is a great way for people
to discover your widget
and to deliver glanceable
information.
If they already had the Weather
widget in their stack,
then it would have rotated
to the Weather widget instead.
To learn more about
how to add configuration
and intelligence
to your widgets,
watch the WWDC session
from 2020.
Your intent donations also
power the on-device intelligence
behind Siri Suggestions
that are shown in Lock screen,
in Spotlight search,
and in the Siri Suggestions
widget.
These suggestions allow people
to perform the key capabilities
of your app with one tap.
Your intents can also be used
in the built-in Shortcuts app
as a part of a simple or complex
multi-step shortcut
across macOS, iOS,
and watchOS.
And donations are also used
to determine what actions
get suggested to people
in the Shortcuts App Gallery.
People can also set up
a voice shortcut
to execute your custom intents
just by asking Siri.
If you chose to use the
built-in INSendMessageIntent,
your intent donations are used
by sharing suggestions
to make it really easy for users
to get content to the people and
groups that matter most to them.
New in iOS 15, when you donate
INSendMessageIntents,
the system uses
the people in your donations
to determine who is
strongly associated
with the user's current Focus.
These strong associations
can be used to make suggestions
to add certain people to their
allowed notifications list
when they receive messages
from them.
In this case, you can see
that Aga is suggested
as a person who this user
should consider adding
to their allowed notifications
list for Work Focus
based on that person's
past interactions with Aga.
If you choose
to use the built-in
INGetReservationDetailsIntent,
your intent donations
will be used to notify users
when it's time to leave
for their restaurant reservation
based on current
traffic conditions
and when it's time
to check in for their flight.
People will also see
Siri Suggestions
when they open Maps,
which makes it super convenient
to get directions to the airport
with just one tap.
New in iOS 15, if you choose
to use the built-in
INPlayMediaIntent,
your intent donations
will be shown in the new
Now Playing UI in Lock screen,
Control Center,
and in the Home app.
This is a fantastic way
for users to start listening to
or watching their favorite
content from your app.
People may consume periodical
media content like podcasts,
TV shows, or movies in your app.
In these cases, you can use
the INUpcomingMediaManager API
to provide the system
a list of media intents
for content that the user
hasn't listened to or watched,
so might be interested in.
The system combines
the past media donations
with your app's upcoming media
to make better
media suggestions.
Your intents can also be
surfaced on the Siri Watch Face
using the
INRelevantShortcut API.
The INRelevantShortcut API
enables you to expose
relevance information
to the system
such as a time or a location
for when your shortcut should be
shown on the watch face.
To learn more about
how to expose your shortcuts
on the Siri Watch Face,
watch the "Siri Shortcuts
on the Siri Watch Face"
WWDC session from 2018.
New in iOS 15,
the widgetKind property
was added to the
INRelevantShortcut object
so you can hint to the system
when to show
the corresponding widget
in a Smart Stack.
To learn more about this
property and how to use it,
watch the "Add intelligence
to your widgets" session
from WWDC 2021.
To summarize,
we've taken a look
at the life of intent donations
and seen how they are used
to expand your app's presence
and capabilities
throughout the system
to an increasing number of
places like the Smart Stack,
Focus, Suggestions,
Shortcuts, and Siri.
Now that we've looked at
the life of an intent donation,
let's talk in more detail about
how you can structure
your donations for success
and ultimately expand your app's
presence across the system.
Let's use a new example of
ordering coffee in a coffee app.
So far I've defined
an order coffee intent
and exposed two parameters:
the size of the coffee
and the coffee item.
In this case,
we have a large iced latte.
Let's take a look
at what could go wrong
if I include the order date
in my intent donation.
It starts off OK,
with a donation coming in
for a large iced latte
on June 7, 2021.
But once the date changes,
the intent's date parameter
has a new value,
and the system
treats the second donation
as a completely different
intent,
despite both donations having
the same item and size.
The system continues
to treat the donations
differently over time
and you can see
that they're not equivalent
across the days,
based on the donation's colors.
If you look at a high-level view
of the donation history
the system sees
across multiple days,
you can see that there's
no meaningful pattern
the system can find for
ordering a large iced latte.
Let's take a look
at how I filled out
the intent definition file to
understand what went wrong.
I defined the three parameters
for item, size, and date.
And I added a supported
parameter combination
with all three parameters.
This tells the system that it
should use all three parameters
to determine
how to find patterns
across intent donations
for prediction.
In this case, including the date
in the supported combination
with the item and size
prevented the system
from properly finding a pattern
across the donations.
To resolve this issue,
I can instead define a supported
combination that includes
only the size and item
parameters.
By doing this, the system knows
that it should only use
the item and size parameters
when comparing intent donations
to find patterns over time.
Now, the system will see a
donation for a large iced latte,
not including the date anymore.
Then on the second day,
the system sees
an equivalent donation
for a large iced latte.
And same on the third day.
If you look at a high-level view
of the donation history again,
you can see that
there is now a pattern
associated with ordering
a large iced latte
just after waking up.
To maximize the benefit
of your donations,
please ensure
your intent donations
are likely to be repeated
and the intent payload
you're donating
is consistent across donations.
That means
don't include timestamps.
In summary, the system has
become increasingly integrated
with the apps we use
day to day
and intent donations
are a key integration point.
Benefit from donating intents
by expanding your app's
capabilities and presence
across the system.
Thank you for listening
and I hope you have
a great rest of your WWDC 2021.
♪