[upbeat music]
♪ ♪
[Aditya] Hello, I'm Aditya Krishnadevan,
an engineer on the UIKit team.
At the core of many apps
are lists or collection views.
Having super-smooth scrolling
is a big part
of making those apps feel great.
This video will set you up for success
when making blazing-fast lists
and collection views.
We'll build this app here
that uses collection views
to display a list of image posts
of some great travel destinations.
It's fairly simple at first glance,
with a photo of the destination
and a couple of text labels.
Throughout this video,
we'll talk about how it's set up
and how it achieves
the performance that people expect.
First, we'll learn how to start
from a strong foundation when using APIs,
like diffable data source
and cell registrations.
We'll refresh our understanding
of the life cycle
of a collection view cell.
We'll then talk about why you might
not see perfectly-smooth scrolling,
and some advances
in prefetching that can help.
Finally, Patrick will explain
how to correctly update cells
when their content
comes in asynchronously,
and how to use new UIImage API
to get the absolute best scrolling
performance on all devices.
Okay.
Let's begin by talking
about how the app structures its data.
The sample app retrieves
a list of posts for display,
where each post is represented
by this DestinationPost struct.
DestinationPost conforms to identifiable,
which means it has this ID property
that stores its identifier.
This is a unique identifier
for each DestinationPost
that remains stable even
if other properties change.
Diffable data source is built to store
identifiers of items in your model,
and not the model objects themselves.
So, in the sample app,
the diffable data source is populated
using the ID property here,
and not the DestinationPost itself.
Here's the diffable data source
used in the app.
Like we just discussed,
it uses the DestinationPost.ID type
for its item identifiers.
The Section type here is an enum
with one case,
as the app has only one section.
To populate the data source,
the app first creates an empty snapshot
and appends the main section.
Then, it fetches all the posts
from its backing store
and appends their identifiers.
This way, if one of the other properties
of a DestinationPost changes,
its representation
in diffable data source remains stable,
as the identifier does not change.
The final step is to apply
the snapshot to the data source.
Before iOS 15,
applying a snapshot without animation
would be translated
to a reloadData internally.
That wasn't great for performance,
as the collection view had to discard
and recreate all the cells on screen.
From iOS 15 onwards,
applying a snapshot without animation
will only apply the differences
and not perform any extra work.
With iOS 15,
diffable data source also gains
a new reconfigureItems method
that makes it very easy
to update the contents of visible cells.
We'll go through how it works
later in this video.
First, let's get the data
from our data source
into cells and onto the screen.
Cell registrations are a great way
to keep all the configuration
for each type of cell in one place,
and they give us convenient access
to the identifiers
from diffable data source.
UICollectionView maintains a reuse queue
for each of instance of a registration,
so ensure that you create registrations
only once for each type of cell.
Here's a simplified registration
for cells in the app.
The postID that's passed in
is used to retrieve
a DestinationPost
and an asset object containing the image.
The properties from
the DestinationPost are used
to set the title and image in the cell.
To use a registration,
call dequeueConfiguredReusableCell
inside the data source's cell provider.
Note how the registration
is created outside the cell provider
and then used inside.
This is important for performance,
as creating a registration
inside the provider would mean
that the collection view would
never reuse any of its cells.
Now that we understand
how to configure a cell,
we'll move on to when a cell is configured
and what its life cycle is like.
The life of a cell is composed
of two phases:
preparation and display.
The first step for preparation
is fetching the cell to work on.
Whenever UICollectionView needs a cell,
it asks for one from its data source.
If this is a diffable data source,
it runs the cell provider
and returns the result.
When the cell provider runs,
the collection view is asked
to dequeue a new cell
using a registration.
If a cell exists in the reuse pool,
UICollectionView will call
prepareForReuse on it,
and then dequeue the cell.
If the reuse pool is empty,
it will initialize a new cell.
That cell is then passed in
to the configuration handler
from the registration.
This is where apps set up
the cell for display
for a given item identifier
and index path.
The configured cell is returned
to the collection view for the next step.
The collection view queries the cell
for its preferred layout attributes
and sizes the cell appropriately.
At this point, the cell is fully prepared
and ready for phase two: display.
willDisplayCell is called on the delegate,
and the cell is made visible
inside the UICollectionView.
The cell is now on screen.
There are no more changes
to its life cycle
while it remains visible.
When it is scrolled off screen,
didEndDisplaying is called for the cell,
and it ends up right back
in the reuse pool.
From the reuse pool,
a cell can be dequeued again,
repeating this process.
Let's now check what the app feels like
with these basics in place.
The app is featuring Cusco in Peru,
and Saint Lucia in the Caribbean.
Let's scroll through the app
and see some other destinations,
but notice how it doesn't scroll smoothly.
These interruptions during scrolling
are called "hitches."
To understand what causes a hitch,
let's first learn how an app
updates the display.
For each frame,
events such as touches
are delivered to an app.
In response, it updates the properties
of its views and layers.
For example, a scroll view's contentOffset
will change during a pan gesture,
changing the on-screen location
of all the views it contains.
As a result of those changes,
the app's views and layers perform layout.
This process is called a "commit."
Then, the layer tree is sent
to the render server.
Each frame has a commit deadline.
This is the time by which all commits
for that frame need to finish.
The amount of time an app has
to commit for each frame
depends on the refresh rate
of the display.
For example, on an iPad Pro running
at a higher refresh rate of 120 Hz,
apps have less time
to finish work for each frame
compared to an iPhone running at 60 Hz.
Here's a typical example
of scrolling a list of cells
in a collection or table view.
When a new cell becomes visible,
there's a longer commit,
during which the new cell is configured
and performs layout.
Then, there's a couple frames
where it's just the existing cells
being moved around on screen.
The commits for these frames are quick
because no new cells are needed.
Eventually,
the scroll position changes enough
to cause a new cell to become visible,
and this pattern repeats.
So what causes hitches
like in the demo earlier?
When the commit for a frame takes
too long and misses the deadline,
those updates don't get incorporated
into the intended frame.
The display keeps
the previous frame on screen
until the commit finishes,
and this delayed frame can render.
This is a commit hitch
and is perceived as a momentary
interruption when scrolling.
To learn more about this
and other types of hitches,
watch the "Explore UI
animation hitches" video.
To help avoid these hitches,
UICollectionView and UITableView
both have a brand-new cell
prefetching mechanism in iOS 15.
We're back here to the example
of an expensive cell
causing a hitch during scrolling.
A key takeaway from this is
that you typically don't need
a cell every frame.
We have a couple of frames
with very short commits
doing minimal work.
Cell prefetching in iOS 15
takes advantage of this spare time
by preparing the next cell right
after finishing a short commit.
Then, when the cell is eventually needed,
it's just a matter of making it visible.
That's why the commit for the frame
where the prefetched cell
becomes visible is very quick,
because all of the work was done earlier.
The amount of time spent
prefetching the cell is the same
as when it causing a hitch.
But because we're able
to get a head-start,
we're able to avoid a hitch.
Let's understand why this works
by stepping through each commit.
Before the prefetching happened,
we performed the commit for this frame.
Since no cells were needed,
it was a quick commit,
and it finished with lots of time left
before the deadline.
Instead of just waiting around
until the next frame,
in iOS 15,
the system recognizes the situation
and uses the spare time
to start prefetching the next cell.
Now, the following frame is
where things get interesting.
Because the cell being prefetched
is expensive,
it actually causes
the commit for that frame
to start later than normal.
However, even though
that commit starts late,
it still finishes well before its deadline
because it's quick.
Compare this
to the illustration we saw earlier
without prefetching.
Notice how there are no longer
any commits missing deadlines,
and so, there are no more hitches
with cell prefetching.
This means that your apps get up
to twice the amount of time
to prepare each cell,
without causing any hitches.
What's more, all you need to do
to get this great new functionality is
to build your app with the iOS 15 SDK.
When I last ran the demo,
the app was built with the iOS 14 SDK.
Let's check out scrolling in the app
when built with the iOS 15 SDK.
This is great!
Looks like prefetching is doing
exactly what we'd want.
Scrolling is now perfectly smooth,
and we didn't have to change
a single line of code.
Remember, all you need to do is
to build your app using the iOS 15 SDK.
For UICollectionView,
this new prefetching expands
on what was introduced in iOS 10.
Cell prefetching
is now supported for lists,
as well as all other
compositional layouts.
This great new prefetching is now
even enabled in UITableView.
Prefetching can improve scrolling
performance by eliminating hitches,
but it will also reduce power usage
and increase battery life.
If your cells are quick to prepare,
the system can use the extra time to run
in a more energy-efficient state
and still avoid hitches.
So, even if you don't notice any hitches,
it's still very important to make
your cell configuration
and layout implementations
as efficient as possible.
Let's now talk about how prefetching
affects cell life cycle.
This is the life cycle
we talked about earlier,
without prefetching,
with the two distinct phases.
When a cell is prefetched,
it is the preparation phase
that is executed ahead of the cell
being required on-screen.
To take full advantage of prefetching,
a cell must be fully configured
in this phase.
Don't wait until a cell is visible
to perform any heavy work.
When a cell returns
to the collection view,
it is sized to get
its preferred layout attributes,
also as part of the prefetch.
After being prefetched,
there is now this in-between state,
where a cell is waiting to be displayed.
Given this new phase,
there are two important
considerations for apps.
It is possible for a prepared cell
to never be displayed,
which could happen if the user
suddenly changed the scroll direction.
Then, once a cell is displayed,
it can go right back
into the waiting state
after it goes off screen.
The same cell can be displayed
more than once for the same index path.
It's no longer the case
that a cell will be immediately added
to the reuse pool when it ends displaying.
Prefetching helps us achieve
smooth scrolling,
but only because it gives us more time.
On other devices with a higher frame rate,
it's still possible that the app is going
to have hitches during scrolling.
Patrick will now give you more detail
about how the app configures its cells,
and also talk about strategies
to reduce the amount of time per commit
when displaying images.
[Patrick] Thanks, Adi.
Hi, I'm Patrick from
the High-Level Performance team.
Now, I'll guide us through
updating existing cells in the sample app,
and then how to display images
with the best-possible performance,
utilizing some new APIs in iOS 15.
The sample app was built
with local image files on disk.
As we scroll the app,
the cells are prepared off screen,
and the images within them are loaded
from the file system immediately.
Now, we wan display images
stored on a remote server.
So, when cells scroll in,
we may not have the image
to show in the image view.
When the image view is first visible,
it will be blank
and only filled in
once the server request completes.
Let's take a look at extending
our registration's configuration handler
to support this new approach.
Here in the registration's
configuration handler,
we already fetched the asset
from the asset store.
The store will always return an image,
but it may not be the full asset.
It might need to be downloaded.
The asset object indicates this
with the isPlaceholder property.
When this is true,
we will ask the asset store
to download the full image.
When the load operation completes,
it's time to update the cell's image view.
Here, we take the existing cell object
and set the asset on its image view.
This is a mistake.
Cells are reused
for different destinations,
and by the time the asset store
loads the final asset,
the cell object we have captured
could be configured for a different post.
Instead of updating the cell directly,
we must inform
the collection view's data source
of the needed update.
iOS 15 introduces
the reconfigureItems snapshot method.
Calling reconfigureItems
on a prepared cell
will rerun its registration's
configuration handler.
Use this instead of reloadItems
because it reuses
the item's existing cell,
rather than dequeuing
and configuring a new cell.
In our sample app,
we'll declare a setPostNeedsUpdate method,
which calls reconfigureItems
on the ID passed in.
Now, back in our registration's
configuration handler,
when the image is a placeholder,
we will download the full-size asset
and call the new method.
reconfigureItems
will then call this handler again,
but now, fetchByID
will return the full asset
and not the placeholder.
This allows us to keep all
our view-updating code
in one place
and asynchronously update our cells
once we have data.
To maximize prepare time,
we can also use our downloadAsset method
inside our prefetchingDataSource.
Data-source prefetching is a great place
to kick off network downloads
for a collection-view item.
It gives more time to download the asset
and have it ready
before the cell is visible,
reducing the time users
see placeholder content.
Let's take a look
at how this looks in our app.
It looks fine,
but there are visible hitches
while scrolling.
They also appear to coincide
with when new images are displayed.
When a new cell is prepared,
there is no hitching.
It's only when an image is updated
with the full-resolution image
that we hitch.
That's because all images
take time to decode for display,
and some images,
like the larger non-placeholder assets,
are too large to be decoded
in time for display.
When the cell registration's
configuration handler
is first called
and the asset is a placeholder,
the code begins an async request
for the full-size image
and completes its configuration.
When the asset
is finally downloaded later,
the cell configuration handler is rerun
with the final image.
When an image view tries
to commit a new image,
it must first prepare the image
for display
on the main thread.
This can take a long time,
and there's a hitch
when the app missed its commit deadline.
Image preparation is a mandatory process
that all images must undergo
to be displayed.
The render server
can only display images that are bitmaps,
which means they are raw pixel data.
Images come in many different formats,
like PNG, HEIC, and JPEG,
which are compressed and must be processed
and unpacked to be displayed.
Image views do this processing
when it commits a new image,
and it happens on the main thread.
Ideally, we could prepare
the image in advance
and only update the UI
when it's finally completed.
That way, we never block the main thread
and do not hitch.
iOS 15 introduces
the image preparation APIs,
giving you control over where
and when image preparation happens.
These APIs produce a new UIImage,
which only contains the pixel data
that the renderer needs.
There is no additional work needed
once it's set on an image view.
It comes in two forms: a synchronous one,
which you can run on any thread,
and asynchronous ones,
which run on an internal
UIKit serial queue.
To use it, we take a UIImage we've created
and set a placeholder image
on our image view.
Then, calling the new API
kicks off the preparation
in the background on the larger image.
When it completes,
we can just set it on the image view.
Prepared images solve a large problem
in any image-heavy app,
but they also come
with some considerations.
The prepared images contain
the raw pixel data
from the original image.
It will remain free to display
in an image view
as long as it's retained in memory.
But this also means
it takes up a lot of memory,
and they should be cached sparingly.
Finally, because of their format,
they are not ideal for disk storage.
Instead, save the original asset to disk.
One last consideration is how
image preparation can utilize prefetching.
Prefetching gives extra time
for the image to be downloaded
and prepared.
Giving the process more time
means the users will not see
the placeholder for long,
and probably not at all.
In the sample app,
we already have an asynchronous path
for image retrieval.
After the download completes,
we can then prepare the asset
before calling the completion handler.
These assets are large,
but also valuable,
so once the image is prepared,
we want to cache it.
Our image cache uses the image's size
to estimate the memory use
of the prepared image.
Now, when a cell asks for an asset,
we check that cache
before fetching it from our server.
If we had smaller images,
we would be able to cache more.
Images can be large,
and iOS 15 introduces a similar API
for preparing thumbnails of images.
These can scale and prepare an image
to a smaller size.
It ensures that the image
is read and processed
with its destination size in mind,
saving a lot of CPU time and memory.
You use it just like
the Image Preparation APIs.
First, take a UIImage
and set a placeholder image
on the image view.
Then, call the new resizing API,
with the view's size
as the target size for the thumbnail.
When its prepared,
just update the image view
with the new thumbnail.
Along with the Image Preparation APIs,
it's much easier to accelerate images
and avoid hitches
in any app with iOS 15.
When working with images,
focus on having an asynchronous API
that can update the UI
when an image is ready.
In the meantime, use a placeholder image,
which is small or cheap enough
to display synchronously.
When used with prefetching
and reconfigureItems,
showing asynchronous content
in collection and list views
has never been easier or more performant.
To get started
with fast collection and table views,
first, build your app with the iOS 15 SDK
to unlock many new optimizations.
Particularly, ensure you
validate the behavior
of your collection and table views
with the new prefetching.
All the new APIs demonstrated here
can be found in the sample code
for this talk.
Check it out and make sure
to adopt the image preparation
and resizing APIs across your app.
This will ensure your collection
and table views are blazing fast.
Thanks for watching.
[upbeat music]