[MAC STARTUP CHIME]
♪ Bass music playing ♪
[KEYSTROKES]
♪
Pradhap Natarajan: Hello,
and welcome to
"Manage Devices
with Apple Configurator."
I am Pradhap Natarajan,
an engineer
on the Device Management team
here at Apple.
Today, I am going to walk you
through some exciting updates
to Apple Configurator.
Configurator makes it easy
to deploy iPad, iPhone,
and Apple TV devices
in your school or business.
It features a flexible
device-centric design
that enables you to configure
one or dozens of devices
quickly and easily.
You can inspect any device
to see details
like the serial number
and hardware addresses,
installed apps, and profiles.
In addition to apps
and profiles,
Configurator can also install
books and software updates.
Blueprints provide a great way
to apply the same configuration
to large numbers of devices
with a single click.
Configurator also provides
a rich set of automation tools,
including a command line tool,
an AppleScript library,
and a suite
of Automator actions.
Initially, Configurator
supported iOS and tvOS devices.
But recently,
it has learned some new tricks
for managing Mac computers
as well.
We introduced the ability
to restore and revive a Mac,
beginning with models
with the Apple T2 Security Chip.
And last year,
we brought those features
to each Mac with Apple silicon.
There are two ways to use
Configurator with a Mac.
First, Restore is a great way
to return a Mac
with Apple silicon to service
by reinstalling
the latest macOS version.
On a Mac with the T2 chip,
this action restores
the firmware,
after which macOS
can be reinstalled
using internet recovery.
The second is Revive.
Revive helps you recover a
Mac while preserving user data.
Occasionally,
things can go wrong.
For example, a MacBook Pro
could run out of battery
during a software update.
In these situations,
a Mac with Apple silicon
or a T2 chip can be revived
which updates the firmware
while preserving user data.
To return this Mac to service,
select it in Configurator
and choose Revive from
the Advanced Actions menu.
This will bring the Mac
back to life.
It is important to use
the correct port
on your MacBook Air
with Apple silicon,
or a Mac Mini,
or a MacBook Pro.
And note
that the port is different
on your MacBook Pro
with the T2 Chip.
Let’s recap Restore and Revive.
To prepare a Mac for a new user,
use Restore.
This action restores
the firmware
and updates recoveryOS
to the latest version
and erases all user data.
On Apple silicon,
this also reinstalls
the latest version of macOS.
If you have a Mac that is unable
to boot, use Revive.
Revive updates the firmware
and the recoveryOS
to the latest version
while preserving user data.
And remember, it’s essential to
use the correct port on your Mac
when restoring or reviving it.
For more information
on restoring a Mac,
please refer
to the Configurator user guide.
Configurator has served us well
in helping to erase and restore
iPhone, iPad, and Apple TV
devices quickly.
Now it can do the same
for a Mac with Apple silicon
or T2 chip.
Let’s look at another way
Configurator can be a lifesaver
for organizations that need
to manage lots of Mac computers.
A Mac purchased
directly from Apple,
participating Apple authorized
resellers, and cellular carriers
can be assigned
to your organization
in Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager.
And having the Mac assigned
to your organization
provides access to some key
device management features.
For example, automated device
enrollment enables your users
to enroll in your organization’s
MDM solution
with the flow integrated right
into Setup Assistant in macOS.
Also Automated Device Enrollment
paired with AutoAdvance
enables a completely touch-free
configuration solution
for Mac computers
by just connecting
to power and ethernet.
The Mac is enrolled
in your MDM Server,
automatically configured
to your specifications,
and left ready for use
in your organization.
But if the Mac wasn’t purchased
through one of Apple’s
supported channels
and not assigned
to your organization,
you cannot take advantage
of these great features.
Configurator has long provided
a way to assign iPhone,
iPad, and Apple TV devices
to your organization
in Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager,
even if they were not purchased
through an official channel.
Yet, Configurator
hasn’t provided a way
to assign a Mac purchased
outside an official channel,
until now.
Today,
I am very excited to introduce
Apple Configurator for iPhone.
This new app makes it easy
to assign a Mac
to your organization.
It works like magic!
Assign one Mac -- or 100 --
without a cable,
using your iPhone’s camera.
All you need to do
to perform this critical task
is sign in with
a Managed Apple ID
and point your iPhone’s camera
at an image
in Setup Assistant on a Mac.
The Managed Apple ID
must have at least
the device enrollment manager
role in your organization.
Let me walk you through
how it works.
The app has just
two main buttons.
The first button is Settings.
It allows you to choose
the network configuration
the Mac should use
to connect to Wi-Fi,
if it is not already connected
over Ethernet.
The easiest option is to share
the current Wi-Fi network
that your iPhone
is connected to.
However, not all networks
are shareable.
If you need the Mac
to connect to a network
that is not shareable,
you can choose
a configuration profile
with the Wi-Fi payload
that the Mac should use.
To assign a Mac
to your organization,
simply start up the Mac
and select the language.
When the Mac asks you to select
your country or region,
bring the iPhone running
Configurator near the Mac,
wait for the animation
to appear on the Mac,
then center the animation in the
viewfinder of iPhone’s camera.
Wait for the message that says
“Paired Successfully”.
[PAIRING CHIME]
Boom! That’s it.
Once paired, Configurator sends
all the required information
to the Mac to assign itself
to your organization.
The other button allows you
to view the status
of each assigned Mac.
Status provides a report
of nearby Mac computers
that you can assign
to your organization
and the ones
that have already been assigned.
Once the Mac is assigned
to your organization,
the next step
is to configure automated
device enrollment settings.
To do this, sign into
Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager,
move the newly assigned Mac
from the Apple Configurator 2
MDM server
to the MDM server
that will deliver
the correct automated
device enrollment settings.
The next time the Mac restarts,
it will download its new
enrollment settings
and enroll itself
into the selected MDM server,
configuring itself according
to the settings you specified.
Now, it is ready for use
by an employee or a student
in your organization.
Note that a Mac assigned
using this feature
will be released
from your organization
if the user unenrolls from MDM
during a 30-day provisional
period, just like iOS.
Configurator for iPhone
makes it easy to assign any Mac
to your organization
in Apple Business Manager
or Apple School Manager
so that you can take advantage
of all the great device
management features
that automated device
enrollment enables.
As a program member,
you'll be able to download
the app at AppleSeed for IT.
Alternatively, you will be able
to request access via TestFlight
on the Apple Developer website.
Apple Configurator
for iPhone beta requires iOS 15
and can assign Mac computers
running macOS Monterey.
Make sure to file your feedback
using Feedback Assistant.
Apple Configurator for iPhone
will be available
in the App Store this fall.
Enjoy WWDC 2021.
Thank you.