♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Well, greetings and welcome to "Get more
mileage out of your app with CarPlay."
My name is André, and I'll be
driving you through the session today.
As you know, CarPlay is the smarter,
safer way to use your iPhone in the car.
Today's session is all about your
apps and how to enable them in CarPlay.
We'll start with a quick refresher
on the types of apps that are supported,
then talk about some new app types
we are enabling this year,
and finally go over
a new tool we have made available
to support the development of your apps.
We'll finish today with an important
new feature specific to navigation apps.
Without further ado,
let's get right into it!
One of the most fundamental things about
CarPlay is that it is built for drivers.
People who are actively driving
are the primary users you should consider
when building your app.
As a result, you should only enable use
cases that are relevant while driving,
and you should omit any use cases
that people shouldn't do while driving.
Things like one time configuration,
signing in to your app,
or reading terms and conditions,
are things that are better to do before
or after driving, so they shouldn't
appear in your app's CarPlay UI.
Note that an entitlement is needed
for your app to appear in CarPlay.
You can request the entitlement
on the Apple CarPlay developer website
based on the type of app
you'd like to make available.
Here are the types of apps
we support in CarPlay today.
These cover a wide number of tasks
drivers may want to do while driving,
but we've heard from many of
you that there are even more
driving-relevant apps
you'd like to enable.
I'm happy to announce we are adding
two new types to our list this year,
Fueling and Driving Task apps.
We'll go over
these in more detail shortly,
but first, let's take a quick pit stop
and talk a bit about Templates.
Templates are how apps in
CarPlay present their UI.
Your app supplies the data,
and the system draws the UI
onto the vehicle's display on your behalf.
This system of templates is
simple for your app to adopt
and has several benefits,
including helping steer your app
towards making it
appropriate for the road.
You don't have to worry
about things like font sizes,
the templates help you ensure
your UI is of low complexity,
and finally, the UI of your app is
consistent with other apps in CarPlay,
making it easier for your users
to quickly take actions in it as needed.
Just as important, the templates take
care of making sure your app's UI
works great in any car that supports
CarPlay, regardless of the size of
the screen or the type of
input device used in the car.
You may still want to test
your app in different configurations,
and we'll talk more about
testing later on in the session,
but suffice it to say, the templates
take care of most of the work for you.
You have several templates to choose
from when building your app.
From the grid template showing
an array of buttons,
to the list template showing a table,
these templates should be familiar to
you, both as a developer, and an iOS user.
Most importantly,
they will be familiar to your users
driving with CarPlay as
they appear all throughout CarPlay.
We spoke just before about the different
types of apps we support in CarPlay.
Some of these templates are more relevant
to some of those types than others.
This chart helps you understand
which templates your app can use,
depending on which type it is.
I realize trying to read this is a bit
like taking a DMV eye exam, but fear not,
you'll find this exact chart in
our developer documentation online.
The thing to take away here now
is that the templates your app can use
depend on its type.
Only templates that are
relevant and appropriate
for a particular app type are permitted.
Now that we've talked about templates,
let's take a closer look at the
new app types
we are launching with iOS 16.
First let's talk about
the new Fueling app type.
As you may remember, in iOS 14 we
launched support for EV Charging apps.
These apps aren't just for
finding locations of EV chargers,
they do more than that - for example,
they may help the user connect to
the right
charging station and start it up.
We've heard from many developers
that this type of functionality
would be great for more
than just electric vehicles.
Whether it is traditional gasoline-enabled
cars or alternative fuel vehicles,
this new category enables you to
support CarPlay in your fueling app.
Note that many users use
navigation apps to find and drive
to particular locations,
so your fueling app should enable
more functionality in its CarPlay UI
than simply finding a location.
A great example
of what your app could enable is,
for instance, starting up a gas pump.
Now, let's talk about Driving Task
applications.
Driving Task is a new type
of CarPlay app
designed to enable
a wider variety of very simple apps.
Keep in mind the primary purpose
of these apps must be to enable tasks
people need to do while driving--
it's for tasks that actually help with
the drive, not just a task
to be done while you drive.
Some examples of apps that
would fall under this type include apps
to help control car accessories,
apps that provide driving or road status
and information, and apps to help with
tasks at the start and end of a drive.
Let's take a look at some more
concrete examples of these.
First, here we have a road
status app that can inform users
about important road information.
This app was built using the
CPPointOfInterestTemplate.
Keep in mind,
a user using this app is driving,
so an app like this should provide
a very short list of important items
near where the user is located.
This is not intended for apps helping users
do full route planning
ahead of a drive.
In this app, here's what a user
sees when they select a location.
Note that the amount of space for text
is intentionally limited to keep this
information glanceable, so you should be
concise in the language you choose here.
Next, let's look at an application
designed to control a car accessory--
in this case a trailer controller.
This app uses the CPInformationTemplate
to provide basic information on a
connected accessory, as well as a couple
of buttons for the user to take actions.
Note that in this example,
this is the app's entire UI in CarPlay.
There are no other screens!
Of course, the app has plenty
of other functionality,
for instance, the ability to
manage paired accessories,
but any functionality that
isn't needed for driving is simply
not included
in the CarPlay UI for that app.
Users are best served doing
non-driving tasks using the
app's primary UI on iPhone
when they're out of the vehicle.
Finally, let's look at a couple
examples using the CPGridTemplate.
This is an extremely simple
app that has two buttons - that's it!
And lets the users keep track
of their miles
as either personal or business miles.
This app fits the new
Driving Task app type perfectly,
as it enables a very simple task
that users need to do while driving,
without enabling
any other non-critical tasks.
Simple, and to the point.
Just to show you that this style
of UI can serve multiple types of apps,
here's another example
with a near identical UI.
This is an express lane toll transponder
app that uses the CPGridTemplate
to let users choose
how many occupants are in the car.
It meets the exact same goals
as the previous example and is
another perfect Driving Task app.
To recap, when designing
your Driving Task app,
definitely consider making a
single screen app that provides
the minimum functionality
your users need while driving
and only enable tasks that can
be accomplished in a few seconds.
You should avoid enabling complex
or infrequent use cases.
A great example of this is first time
set up or detailed configuration.
And finally, you should not
add functionality to your app
that isn't needed while driving,
even if it's car-related.
The kitchen sink, this is not.
And that's it on Driving Task apps.
Now let's shift gears a bit and
talk about how to test your CarPlay app.
We'll review the different ways
in which you can go about this,
and I'll introduce a new tool
called CarPlay Simulator.
As a developer, you have a few
different tools at your disposal
to test your CarPlay-enabled app.
First, you can use the Xcode simulator,
which has a built-in CarPlay window.
If you're already using the Xcode
simulator to test the rest of your app,
this is a great way to quickly
test your CarPlay UI, too.
Second,
for testing your app on a real iPhone,
you can, of course, connect your phone
to a real CarPlay-enabled vehicle,
or an aftermarket head unit.
Until recently,
this was the only way to test your app's
CarPlay UI running on a real iPhone,
but I'm happy to report
we have a third option for you now
that may just become your favorite--
the CarPlay Simulator!
Let's look at this in more detail.
So what is it?
CarPlay Simulator is a
stand-alone Mac application that
replicates a CarPlay environment.
You simply download the
"Additional Tools for Xcode" package
on the Apple developer website,
run the app,
and connect your iPhone
to your Mac using a cable.
CarPlay will start on the phone
and run just the same
as if you had it connected to a real car.
So what's the big deal,
and why would you want to use this?
Well, there are several benefits.
First of all, when you are using
CarPlay Simulator,
CarPlay is actually
running on your iPhone
the same way it would be in a real car.
This means you can test your
app running on your phone without
constantly having to run back
and forth to your parking spot
or having to buy an aftermarket head unit.
Another huge benefit is that because
your phone is connected to your Mac
when you're using CarPlay Simulator,
you can use all of the other
fantastic developer tools
on your Mac simultaneously,
whether it is debugging in Xcode
or tuning performance in Instruments.
Similarly on the iOS side of things,
because your app is running
on an actual iPhone, you have access to
complete iPhone functionality.
Some scenarios cannot be tested
without either a real CarPlay system,
or now, CarPlay Simulator.
A great example is testing that
your navigation app's voice instructions
correctly mix with a car's
native audio source, like FM radio.
You can now test this
at the convenience of your desk.
Last but not least,
you can use CarPlay Simulator
to test multiple different
configurations of cars, too,
for example,
cars with different display sizes.
Let's see what CarPlay Simulator
looks like in action.
So here it is.
As you can see, the CarPlay
display from the connected iPhone
appears right in the app,
alongside several controls.
Let's go through what some of these do.
At the bottom of the screen
are buttons that simulate
various different hard keys
and knob controls in a car.
You can also click directly in
the CarPlay view to simulate a touch
in touchscreen vehicles.
At the top of the window
we have some quick controls.
The limit UI button allows you
to simulate when a car in motion
requests for CarPlay
to limit certain content on screen,
which, for example, could shorten
the contents of lists in an audio app.
The next two buttons are to
simulate when a car requests dark
or light appearance for UI and map
content, respectively.
The last button lets you quickly
simulate disconnecting
and reconnecting your phone to CarPlay.
Because your phone will still
remain connected to your Mac
when you use this button,
you can use it to debug CarPlay
reconnection scenarios
in your app using Xcode.
But what about
that first button that I skipped?
As you might have guessed,
this will pop up a secondary window
with more advanced functionality.
Let's take a look
at those advanced features now.
In the General tab,
you're able to choose the display size
for the main CarPlay display.
If your application UI is composed
only of templates,
you can try different sizes
to see what your UI will look like
in different cars, but as we talked
about before,
the system will make sure
everything works great regardless.
If your app is a navigation app, however,
it's critically important that you
try different sizes and aspect ratios
to ensure your map drawing code
works correctly.
Here are some recommended display
sizes to test with your app.
Let's take
a look at the Cluster Display tab.
As you will see here,
you are able to simulate cars
with a second display
in the instrument cluster!
Simply check the box to enable it,
restart the session,
and a second window will appear
for the instrument cluster
alongside the primary display.
Again,
this is most relevant to navigation apps.
The instrument cluster display is used
to display either a map or turn card
for the driver right in their field of
view in the car's instrument cluster.
We'll chat more about the
instrument cluster in a second,
but that's a quick tour of
the new CarPlay Simulator app.
We hope you find it as useful as we do!
We just saw how CarPlay can now draw
a live map in the instrument cluster.
But what about your navigation app?
How can you add - and test -
instrument cluster support in your app?
Let's take a look.
You may remember that back in iOS 13,
we added APIs
to enable navigation apps to
appear in the CarPlay Dashboard.
To do this, you edited your app's
Info.plist
to declare support for Dashboard
and implemented the required delegates.
The delegates notify your app when it is
appearing and disappearing in Dashboard,
and also pass over a UIWindow to your
app in which to draw your map content.
It's easy.
If you've already done this,
then the great news is
adding instrument cluster support
will be a piece of cake,
as it follows the exact same pattern.
Let's look at how I did this in my
own navigation test app, Space Roads.
I edited my Info.plist to declare support
for the instrument cluster
navigation scene
and added the required
Scene Session Role.
Then, I implemented my
CPTemplateApplicationInstrumentCluster
Scene delegate
as well as my
CPInstrumentClusterControllerDelegate.
These will both give you a window
in which to draw your content
as well as notify you when the
instrument cluster starts and finishes,
making your instrument cluster view
visible.
That's all it takes to have
your map appear live
in the car's instrument cluster!
While this is all very similar to
implementing Dashboard support,
there are a few more considerations
specific to the instrument cluster.
First of all, the instrument cluster may
allow users to zoom the map in and out.
It's your responsibility to
implement this in your app using the
CPInstrumentClusterControllerDelegate.
Similarly, if your app includes
a compass or speed limit,
the corresponding delegates
will tell your app
when it is appropriate
to draw them or not.
Finally, note that your instrument
cluster view may be partially obscured
by other elements
in the car's instrument cluster.
Of course, iOS already has a first class
mechanism for dealing with such a thing,
safe areas!
You can override
viewSafeAreaInsetsDidChange
on your view controller to
know when the safe area changes,
and use the safeAreaLayoutGuide
on your cluster view
to keep critical content in the area of
the view guaranteed to be visible.
If you have a blue route line
showing the user's location,
for instance,
you'd want to ensure the critical parts
are contained within the safe area.
We just saw some new features for you
as a developer building CarPlay apps,
and we saw a
new tool for you to test your apps.
Let's take a look at it in action.
First, I'm going to start here on my Mac,
showing you CarPlay Simulator.
I have the app running,
and I'll simply connect my phone.
And voilà, here it is running CarPlay.
Let's see how CarPlay Simulator
can help you when testing your apps.
Even if your app is primarily template
based, you can use it to make sure
the artwork in your app works great
in both light and dark appearances.
Let me run the Express Lane app...
And I can use the button in the toolbar
to toggle between light and dark
appearances.
Notice how my app has provided
different artwork for both styles.
Looks great.
Now let's switch over to Space Roads,
a navigation test app I've written.
I'll use the main configuration panel
to try my map drawing code
at a different screen size.
And finally, I will enable
the instrument cluster display
to test the instrument cluster support.
Here it is. It works great!
Earlier, I fully tested my apps
in CarPlay Simulator, so now,
I have full confidence
they will work great in a real car.
Let's give it a try!
Alright, here we are in my car,
and as you can see,
I have my phone connected to the
vehicle and running CarPlay.
First, let's try running my
connected trailer controller app
so I can show you how templates have
taken care of making the app work great
in a knob enabled vehicle.
This particular vehicle has both a touch
screen and a knob controller,
but many users like to use
the knob controller while driving,
so it's important for apps
to work great using the knob.
As you can see,
I have full access to the buttons
in my app here,
and the best part is, I didn't have to do
anything special - the
templates did all the work for me!
Next, let's switch over to my
navigation app, Space Roads.
We'll launch the app...
and we'll start navigation...
and then I press go.
Boom!
My app now shows a live map view
on both the center console
and in the instrument cluster!
It's great having the live map
right in my line of sight as a driver.
I'm certain drivers using
your navigation app will love it, too.
Well, that's all I have for you today.
For more information, be sure to check out
the CarPlay developer portal
at developer.apple.com/carplay
Thank you, and happy roads, everyone!   ♪♪