Sam Lazarus: Hi my name is Sam,
and I'm an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
When designing SwiftUI,
we've always strived to make decisions
based on clearly defined principles,
and today, we're going to highlight
one of them: progressive disclosure.
On the SwiftUI team,
we spend a lot of time thinking about
and building new API,
but what you might not have realized
is that the moment
you build a reusable component
or abstraction,
you, too, are an API designer.
In this talk, we wanted to peel back
the curtains on our design process
and share what we've learned
about progressive disclosure,
so the next time you're building
a reusable component, or abstraction,
you have a new tool in your tool belt.
Let's start by talking
about what progressive disclosure
actually means.
As it turns out,
it's not unique to the design of APIs!
In fact, you can see it in action
in one of the most common macOS UIs:
the save dialog.
When you're first shown a save dialog,
there's a default location
already populated for you.
Additionally, the dialog shows you
a drop-down with some common locations,
so locations you're likely to select
are easy to reach.
And finally, if you need to browse
the filesystem to find the right path,
you can expand the dialog to reveal
a more complex but more powerful UI.
There are different layers of complexity
here that can be revealed when needed.
This is the same experience that we want
to provide with our APIs.
The code equivalent
to providing a nice UI experience
is making your APIs feel great to use.
As developers,
we're used to looking at our code
from the perspective of where
we write it: the declaration site.
But to make code feel great to use,
we have to look at it
from a different perspective:
where the code actually gets used,
or what we refer to as the call site.
Progressive disclosure, then,
is designing APIs
so that the complexity of the call site
grows with the complexity of the use case.
An ideal API is both simple
and approachable
but also be able to accommodate
powerful use cases.
This has real benefits for developers.
First, it minimizes the time
to the the first build and run,
letting you make use of your API quickly.
It also lowers the learning curve
of your code, preventing APIs
from getting bogged down by concepts
that aren't relevant in all use cases.
Finally, it creates a tight feedback loop.
With APIs that embrace
progressive disclosure,
you can add pieces bit by bit,
seeing what you've created at each step.
All of these things together make
building apps a cycle of quick refinements
rather than a single, large,
up-front investment.
So progressive disclosure
is a useful guiding light,
but how can we design specific API
so they embrace that principle?
On the SwiftUI team, we start
by considering common use cases.
In order to progressively disclose
functionality,
we need to identify
what the simple cases should be.
We also strive
to provide intelligent defaults,
so those common cases
can specify only what they need to.
Next, we aim to optimize the call site,
ensuring every character
of your call site has a purpose.
And finally, we design our APIs
so they compose pieces
rather than enumerating possibilities.
Let's dive right in and take a look
at some examples from SwiftUI,
starting with how we consider
common use cases.
One place where SwiftUI does this
particularly well is with labels.
When you create a button, for example,
we require that you provide
a label for the button.
Most of the time,
that label will just be some text,
describing the purpose of the button,
and SwiftUI provides you
a concise way to spell that.
But if you want to customize
the button further,
SwiftUI provides another overload.
which takes an arbitrary view as a label.
This allows you to build
complex functionality
out of this simple control.
But because this API carefully considers
its common use cases,
99% percent of the time,
you only need the simple version.
This label pattern
shows up everywhere in SwiftUI.
And when I say everywhere,
I really mean it.
So considering common use cases
is something we do
across the entire framework.
Next, let's look
at providing intelligent defaults.
In order to streamline
our common use cases,
we have to provide intelligent defaults
for all the things
we don't specify explicitly.
And there's no better example of this
than one of the most commonly used APIs
in all of SwiftUI:
Text.
Text is such a great example
of intelligent defaults
that you've probably written code
like this hundreds of times
without thinking about everything
you don't have to specify.
Just with this code,
SwiftUI will localize your text
by looking up the localized string
in your app bundle
with the environment locale.
It will automatically adapt
to the current color scheme,
supporting dark mode right out of the box.
And it will automatically scale
the text up or down
depending on the current
accessibility dynamic type size.
We've talked about these behaviors before,
but text is doing even more
behind the scenes than that.
When you put two texts
next to each other into a stack,
for example, the space between the texts
is automatically adjusted
to the correct line spacing
for text in the current context.
All that behavior
can be manually specified,
but SwiftUI's intelligent defaults
mean that when they aren't relevant
to your use case,
they don't appear at the call site.
Text is an example of an API where
the simplest case is extremely minimal,
but intelligent defaults apply
to all sorts of call sites.
Take toolbar, for example.
Here, we have a toolbar
with a bunch of buttons.
Without having to explicitly specify
their position,
the toolbar buttons are placed
according to platform convention.
On macOS, they'll appear
in the leading edge of the toolbar,
but on iOS, they'll appear
in the navigation bar,
starting from the trailing edge.
And finally, on watchOS,
only the first item appears,
pinned under the navigation bar.
This works great for the large majority
of cases,
but if you do need more control,
we provide additional API
to explicitly specify
the placement of items.
Again, the customization
is there if you need it,
but intelligent defaults
handle the majority of cases.
Considering common use cases
and providing intelligent defaults
create some really great experiences,
but if using those APIs feels clunky,
or unrefined,
it can ruin the whole effect.
That brings us to our last strategy:
optimize the call site.
And for that, let's look
at another API: Table.
Multi-column tables
are a very feature-rich control.
There's lots to configure
and lots of functionality.
But the large majority
of tables are much simpler
and don't need all those features.
We want table to be capable
of this more complex behavior,
and in its most verbose format,
it has that.
It has support for sorting,
multiple columns with rich cell content,
sectioned rows, and much, much more.
But we also want to provide
a great experience
in the more common cases,
so let's take a look
at the fully specified code
for this simpler table
and see how we can optimize its call site.
First, let's break down this example.
Table starts by specifying
how it generates the data for each row.
Here, I'm iterating over each book
we're currently reading
and creating a table row
for each of those books.
Next, it specifies how to populate
the columns from the data for each row.
Here, I create a Title column
and an Author column.
It also takes a binding to the sort order
to allow table to change the sort
when users click
on the table column headers.
Finally, I've added some code
which re-sorts the table's data
whenever the sort order changes.
That's a lot of information,
so let's take a look
at how to optimize this call site
to really embrace progressive disclosure.
One common use case that stands out
right away has to do with rows.
Most of the time, the rows field will look
just like it does in this example:
a ForEach over a collection,
providing a table row for each item.
The developer doesn't need to loop
through all of this themselves,
so SwiftUI provides a convenience
that handles this under the hood.
By passing the collection
directly to table,
the ForEach behavior can be provided
behind the scenes,
drastically simplifying our call site,
but this can still be simplified further.
What are other common use cases?
Well, most of the time,
when one of the values
I want to show in a table
is a string, I'll just use
a text to display it in the column.
We optimize the call site
for this case too.
Whenever the value keypath
points to a string,
we allow the view associated
with the TableColumn to be omitted.
That's another significant simplification,
but there's still more to optimize!
There's information in the call site
which not all tables need
to concern themselves with:
the sort order.
The simplest use case for table
doesn't care about sorting at all!
So we provide a version of table
which doesn't concern itself
with sorting either.
And this brings us to our final iteration.
Much simpler!
Every character of this call site
serves a clear purpose,
and we got here by asking ourselves
two key questions at every step:
"What are the most common use cases
that we should build conveniences for?"
and "What is the essential information
that should always be required?"
These guiding questions are
great for helping you optimize
your call sites, but they need
to be applied carefully.
If you don't think through
their implications for your API,
they can lead you astray.
That brings us to our final strategy:
Compose, don't enumerate.
And to illustrate this,
let's talk about the design
of a part of SwiftUI's layout system:
stacks,
in particular, HStack.
First, let's think about what
the essential information is
for an HStack.
Well, it needs to know
what content should be in the stack
and how that content
should be arranged within the stack.
We already have view builders
to specify the content of the HStack,
so let's focus on the arrangement.
Going back to the guiding questions
we highlighted,
what are the most common use cases
when arranging elements in an Hstack?
Well, sometimes I want to show a stack
like this one
that shows the boxes one after another,
starting from the leading edge.
Another common case is
wanting to center the elements.
And finally, I might want
to align the elements
against the trailing edge.
VStack already has an API
with similar cases to this, alignment,
so it might seem tempting
to create a similar enum
for the arrangement
of elements within the stack.
This supports all the cases we mentioned!
By specifying the arrangement
of an HStack, I could select a leading,
trailing, or centered arrangement,
depending on which I wanted.
But now what if I want to space
the elements out evenly
or put spacing only between the elements
or put space
only before the last element?
This is getting really messy!
But more importantly, it's unsustainable.
I have to add an enum case
for every behavior we want,
and we might not think
of all the useful cases!
When you find yourself
enumerating common cases
rather than providing conveniences
for them,
try breaking your API apart into
composable pieces
that can build a solution:
Compose, don't enumerate.
In the case of stacks, SwiftUI
provides Spacer and lets you compose it
with the elements of your stack to build
all of the spacing schemes we enumerated,
and many, many more, which is
how we arrived at the API we have today.
Designing the best experience
for progressive disclosure here
wasn't just
about minimizing the call site,
but also involved careful thought
about how that call site should scale
to handle all its cases: in this case,
through composition.
When writing code yourself,
it can be incredibly helpful to apply
the same kind of careful consideration
for the components you create.
And to recap, that starts
by considering common use cases.
By applying progressive disclosure,
the code you write
will save you time
in the most common use cases.
Intelligent defaults will mean
you won't have to think about the details
in those common cases.
Working to optimize the call sites
you build
will allow you to iterate quickly.
And finally, utilizing composition
will let you build APIs that are flexible
enough to accommodate all their use cases.
And because you are an API designer,
you can apply these lessons
to the code you write every day,
whether it's
being designed for someone else,
or just for you to use.
Thank you for watching.
[spacey music]