[upbeat music]
- Hello, I am Michael Ilseman
and I'm an engineer
on the Swift standard library team.
Join me as we meet
and get to know Regex in Swift.
There's a lot to Swift Regex,
and we'll be getting just a taste
of everything it has to offer.
Let's say we're developers collaborating
with some financial investigators
on a tool to analyze
transactions for irregularities.
Now, you'd think that for
a task this important
we'd be processing well-structured data.
But instead, we have a bunch of strings.
Here the first field
has the transaction kind,
the second the transaction date,
the third field
the individual or institution,
the fourth and final field
the amount in US dollars.
Fields are separated
by either 2-or-more spaces or a tab
for a very important technical reason
that no one involved can remember.
And, yes,
that date field is totally ambiguous.
We're just going to hope that it's
month/day/year and see what happens.
Processing these transactions
involves processing strings,
and string is a collection,
which means we get access
to generic collection algorithms.
These algorithms
basically come in two kinds,
those that operate over elements,
and those that operate over indices.
We can try to use
the element-based algorithms
by splitting out the transaction fields,
but the field separator being either tab
or 2-or-more spaces
makes this difficult.
Splitting on whitespace alone
doesn't cut it.
Another approach is to drop down
to low-level index manipulation code.
But it's hard to do right,
and even if you know what you're doing,
it still takes a lot of code.
Let's come back to split.
The reason this approach doesn't work
is because it is element-based
while the field separator
is a more complex pattern.
A solution found in a wide variety
of languages
is to write a regular expression.
Regular expressions emerged
from formal language theory
where they define a regular language.
They entered practical application for
search in editors and command-line tools
as well as lexical analysis in compilers.
These applications
take regular expressions
beyond their theoretical roots,
as they need to extract
portions of the input,
control and direct execution,
and add expressive power.
And Swift is taking them further.
We call this derivative Regex.
Regex is a struct generic
over its Output,
which is the result of applying it,
including captures.
You can create one using a literal
containing regex syntax
in between slash delimiters.
Swift's regex syntax is compatible
with Perl, Python, Ruby, Java,
NSRegularExpression,
and many, many others.
This regex matches one or more digits.
The compiler knows regex syntax,
so you'll get syntax highlighting,
compile-time errors,
and even strongly-typed captures,
which we'll be meeting later.
A regex can be created at run-time
from a string containing
the same regex syntax.
This is useful for search fields
in editors or command-line tools.
This will throw an error at run-time
if the input contains invalid syntax.
The output type
is an existential AnyRegexOutput,
because the types and number of
captures won't be known until run-time.
And the same regex can be
written using a declarative
and well-structured,
albeit more verbose, regex builder.
Let's adapt our split approach
from earlier to use a regex literal.
The first portion matches 2-or-more
occurrences of any whitespace character.
The second portion
matches a single horizontal tab.
And the pipe character
denotes a choice between alternatives,
giving us a field separator of either
2-or-more-spaces or a single tab.
Now that our fields are split,
let's make a contribution
to civilization itself
and normalize that field separator
to a single tab and be done with it.
We could call 'join'
on the result after splitting,
but there's a better algorithm
for that:
'replacing' lets us replace
all field separators with a single tab.
So we go out and evangelize
our clearly superior approach
to anyone who will listen.
Adoption is...slow but promising.
If you are familiar
with regular expressions,
you may also know
of their mixed reputation.
As the old saying goes, "I had a problem,
so I wrote a regular expression.
Now I have two problems."
But Swift regex is different.
Swift advances the art
in four key areas.
Regex syntax is concise and expressive,
but it can become terse
and difficult to read.
And newer features have to use
increasingly cryptic syntax.
Swift regexes can be structured
and organized
the way we structure and organize
source code through Regex builders.
Literals are concise,
builders give structure,
and literals can be used within builders
to find that perfect balance.
Textual representations for data
have become a lot more complicated,
and handling them correctly requires
a standards-conforming parser.
Swift regex lets you
interweave industrial-strength parsers
as individual components of a regex.
This is done
in a library-extensible fashion,
meaning any parsers can participate.
Much of the history of applied
regular expressions
took place in a world
where the entire computer system
only supported
a single language and encoding,
most notably ASCII.
But the modern world is Unicode.
Swift regex does the Unicode
without compromising expressivity.
And finally,
the power of regular expressions
can open up a broad search space
that must be exhaustively explored.
This makes their execution
difficult to reason about.
Some languages support controls,
but because
they're behind cryptic syntax,
they tend to be obscure.
Swift regex provides predictable execution
and surfaces controls prominently.
Let's go back to the financial statements
we've been working with
and fully parse each transaction
using Regex builders,
a declarative approach
to string processing in Swift.
We'll import the RegexBuilder module
to get started.
We can re-use the field separator
regex that we just defined.
The first field is simple;
it's either a CREDIT or a DEBIT.
We can use the regex literal syntax
we've already seen to write that.
After that comes a field separator,
and then the date.
Parsing dates by hand is a bad idea.
Foundation has really good parsers
for types like dates,
numbers, and URLs, and we can
use them directly in a Regex Builder.
We supply an explicit locale which is
our best guess at the author's intent.
We do this instead of implicitly
using the system's current locale.
We can always change it later,
and it's easy to do
because we made our
assumptions _explicit_ in code.
The third field can be "anything,"
so it's tempting to just write
"one or more of anything."
And while
that will give us the right answer,
it does a lot of unnecessary work first,
because it starts off by matching
anything else that comes after it.
The regex will back up one character
at a time and try the rest of the pattern.
We want to tell the regex to stop when
it sees the terminating field separator.
There are a quite a few ways
that we could accomplish this.
One good way to do this
is to use NegativeLookahead
which peeks at the next part of the input
without actually consuming it.
Here we peek at the input to make sure
a field separator isn't coming up
before matching any character.
NegativeLookahead
is one of a family of tools
that let you precisely control
how a Regex matches its components.
Finally, we match the amount,
again using one of Foundation's parsers,
this time for currency.
We've been assuming that comma
is a thousands separator
while period is a decimal separator,
and we make this assumption explicit.
We've built a regex that lets us parse
a line from the transaction ledger.
We don't just want to recognize the lines.
We want to extract some of this data out.
To do this, we use captures,
which extract portions
of our input for later processing.
By convention,
the '0th' capture is the part of the input
that the entire regex matched,
and each explicit capture follows.
Our transaction kind is captured as
a Substring that is a slice of our input.
For dates, we actually capture
the strongly-typed value
that was parsed out
without needing to post-process the text.
The individual or institution is again
captured as a portion of our input,
and the decimal capture
is another strongly-typed value.
To use it, we extract date and decimal
values from the match result,
and the investigators take it from here.
It's at this point that we recommend
they dump the data into a real database
for obvious benefits
like structured queries.
They have a...different opinion.
They want to
keep everything as strings.
Which is good news for this talk because
we get to see even more of Swift Regex.
Everything's going well
until suddenly it's not.
We just learned that the date order
in the transaction text,
which we told everyone was
totally ambiguous, is in fact ambiguous.
It's not always the same,
and the leading theory is that it depends
on the currency used in the transaction.
Because of course it does.
This means that US dollars
is month/day/year
and British pounds is day/month/year.
So let's write a sed-like script
to disambiguate this.
For our regex, we're going to use
an extended delimiter.
This allows us to have slashes inside
without having to escape them.
This also gives us access
to an extended syntax mode
where whitespace is ignored,
which means we can use whitespace
for readability, just like in normal code.
We used named captures, which show up
in the Regex's output as tuple labels.
And we use a Unicode Property
to recognize currency symbols.
This makes our regex more adaptable;
we will handle the specific symbols
in application logic.
Rather than try
to cut and splice text manually,
we're going to yet again use
Foundation's date parser.
pickStrategy receives the currency symbol
and will determine
a parse strategy based on it.
All of our assumptions
are explicit in code,
which makes it easier to adapt
and evolve,
something we almost
certainly will end up needing.
Let's use our regex and helper function
with a find-and-replace algorithm
by supplying a closure which uses
the match result, including captures,
to construct the replacement string.
We pick a strategy based on the captured
currency and parse the captured date.
We can access the captures by name,
instead of only by position.
For our output,
we'll format the new date using ISO-8601,
an unambiguous industry standard.
Our tool transforms this ledger Into
an unambiguous one.
Because we're using
a real date parser and formatter,
we're far more adaptable
to changing requirements.
And using a Unicode property
to recognize currency symbols
helps us evolve that much quicker.
A regex declares an algorithm
over some model of String.
Swift's String presents multiple models
for working with Unicode.
This string, representing a love story
for the ages, contains 3 characters.
These characters are complex entities
formally called Unicode
extended grapheme clusters.
A single Character is composed
of one or more Unicode scalar values.
String provides a UnicodeScalarView
to access this lower-level
representation of its contents.
This enables advanced usage as well
as compatibility with other systems.
Our first Character,
who is our story's protagonist,
is composed of 4 Unicode scalars:
ZOMBIE,
Zero Width Joiner, FEMALE SIGN, and uh...
VARIATION SELECTOR-16,
which in this context signals
a preference to be rendered as emoji.
Of course!
These scalars produce
the single emoji we see visually.
When strings are stored in memory,
they are encoded as UTF-8 bytes.
We can view these bytes
using the UTF-8 view.
UTF-8 is a variable-width encoding,
meaning multiple bytes may be needed
for a single scalar, and as we saw,
multiple scalars may be needed
for a single character.
Our story's protagonist,
represented by 4 Unicode scalars,
is encoded using 13 UTF-8 bytes.
In addition
to being composed of multiple scalars,
the same exact character can sometimes be
represented by different sets of scalars.
This comes up a lot when handling
languages other than English.
In this example,
the 'e' with an acute accent
can be represented as either a single
scalar, precomposed ‘e’ with acute accent,
or as an ASCII 'e' followed
by a combining acute accent.
These are the same characters,
so String comparison will return true.
This is because String obeys
what is formally called
Unicode Canonical Equivalence.
From the perspective
of the UnicodeScalarView,
or the UTF-8 view,
the contents are different,
and we see this difference when we
compare within these lower-level views.
Just like String, Swift regex is
obsessively Unicode correct by default.
But it does this without
compromising expressivity.
Let's switch over a pair of strings.
For the first string, we'll match the
named Unicode Scalar SPARKLING HEART
surrounded by
any characters denoted by dot (.).
The any character class
will match any Swift character;
that is, any Unicode extended
grapheme cluster.
For the second string, characters
that are equal compare as equals...
and we can ignore case.
And now our simple love story
has become a lot more complicated.
Sometimes life, or in this case un-life,
has complexities that we need to process.
Just like String, if you do need to
process Unicode scalar values yourself,
either for compatibility or sub-grapheme
cluster precision,
you can by matching with
'unicodeScalar' semantics.
When we match at the Unicode Scalar level,
the dot matches
a single Unicode Scalar value
instead of a full Swift Character.
Which means we get to see our
friend again: VARIATION-SELECTOR 16.
This friendly little selector gets
matched by the dot, and you can't see it
because when it's all alone,
it renders as empty whitespace.
So helpful.
Now that we've worked with
precision and correctness,
let's do something a little different,
and get back to finance.
The investigators have returned,
and this time they have
an interesting request.
They modified our transaction
matching tool to sniff transactions
live off the wire instead of
processing ledgers after the fact.
Looking at their code,
they actually did a reasonably good job,
but they're facing scaling issues
and need our help.
The transactions they are processing are
very similar, but with minor differences.
Instead of a date,
they have a precise time stamp instead.
This is represented in a clear,
unambiguous,
and shockingly proprietary format.
They have a regular expression
written in a prior century
that matches this just fine.
It's fine.
Next they have a details field
which includes individuals
and identification codes.
They filter transactions
against this field
by using a run-time compiled regex
derived from input.
Because this is live,
and there are more fields later on,
they like to bail early on
any uninteresting transactions.
Then comes an amount
and other fields like checksums,
which they handle just fine on their own.
And of course, fields are still separated
by 2-or-more spaces or a tab.
Their transaction matcher
looks a lot like ours.
They have their own regex
for the timestamp,
their details regex
is compiled from input,
and they handle the rest of the fields.
They did a reasonably good job.
Everything technically works.
It just isn't scaling well.
They notice that their timestamp
and details regexes
often match much more
of the input than their fields.
Ideally, these regexes
would be constrained
to only run over a single field.
We handled a similar issue in
our project by using negative lookahead,
so let's pull that regex in.
'field' will efficiently match
any character
until it encounters a field separator,
and we'd like to use it
to contain their regexes.
We could do this as a post-processing
step, but because this is running live,
we want to bail early if these
regexes don't match their fields.
We can do this using TryCapture.
TryCapture passes the matched field
to our closure,
where we test against the investigator's
timestamp and details regexes.
If they match,
we return the field's value,
meaning that matching succeeded
and the field is captured.
Otherwise we return nil,
which signals that matching failed.
TryCapture's closure
actively participates in matching,
which is exactly what we need.
And with this,
we've solved a major scaling issue.
But there's still one more problem:
when something later on
in the transaction matcher fails,
it can take a long time to exit.
Our fieldSeparator regex
we defined at the very beginning
matches 2-or-more whitespaces or a tab,
which is what we want.
If there are 8 whitespace characters,
it will match all of them
before trying the rest of the regex.
But if the regex later fails,
it will back up
and only match 7 whitespace characters
before trying again.
And if that fails, it will match
only 6 whitespace characters, and so on.
Only after trying all alternatives
does matching fail.
This backing up in order to try
alternatives is called global backtracking
or, in formal logics, the Kleene closure.
It's what gives regular expressions
their characteristic power.
But it opens up
a broad search space to explore,
and here we want
a more linear search space.
We want to match all of the whitespace
and never give any up.
There are a couple tools
that we could use;
the more general tool
is to put fieldSeparator
in a local backtracking scope
instead of a global one.
The Local builder creates a scope where,
if the contained regex
ever successfully matches,
any untried alternatives are discarded.
Even if our transaction matcher
fails later on,
we don't go back
to try consuming fewer spaces.
Global backtracking,
the default for regex,
is great for search and fuzzy matching.
Local is useful for matching
precisely specified tokens.
The field separator,
as vexing as it may be, is precise.
Local is known elsewhere as
an atomic non-capturing group,
which can be a… frightening name.
Makes it seem like
your regex might blow up.
But it actually does the opposite--
it contains the search space.
And with this, we've helped them
solve their scaling issues.
Today we got to meet Swift Regex,
but there's so much more
that we weren't able to cover.
Be sure to check out Swift Regex: Beyond
the Basics by my colleague Richard.
Before we leave,
I want to highlight a few points.
Regex builders give structure.
Regex literals are concise.
The choice between when to use one
over the other
will ultimately be subjective.
Make sure to use real parsers
whenever possible.
This will save you massive
amounts of time and avoid headaches.
Just by using Swift's defaults,
you're going to get
far more Unicode support
and goodness than anywhere else.
Look for ways to use things
like character properties effectively,
such as when we
matched the currency symbols.
And finally, simplify
your search and processing algorithms
by using controls such as lookahead
and local backtracking scopes.
Thank you for watching.