♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello,
I am Dominik
and I am thrilled to
introduce you to Swift Charts,
Apple's new framework
for making informative
and delightful charts
in SwiftUI.
Data surrounds us and provides
an unprecedented resource
for understanding the world
and making better decisions.
Yet, data alone
is of little use.
To make data useful,
we must make sense of it.
A well-designed and accessible
data visualization
can clearly communicate
complex data
and turn data into understanding
and knowledge.
At Apple, we spent years
studying the best practices
for visualizations.
We learned that charts work best
when they show additional
useful context around data
like the trends and fluctuations
of stock prices
over some time range,
your heart rate
during the last workout,
and when the day
will cool off in the evening.
And these are just some
of the many examples
across all our platforms
where we use charts.
Today, I'm excited to introduce
you to a new framework
so you can make informative and
delightful charts in your apps.
Say hello to Swift Charts.
Swift Charts is
a flexible framework
for making
Apple-designed charts.
It uses the same
declarative syntax as SwiftUI,
so you already know
the language of Swift Charts.
So today, let's make
some informative, accessible,
and delightful visualizations
with Swift Charts.
In the team,
we've been helping
a pop-up pancake food truck
track its sales with an app.
The truck serves
an international variety
of sweet and savory pancakes
like cachapa, injera, crêpe,
jian bing, dosa,
or American pancakes.
The food truck served
more than 4500 pancakes
across these styles
in the last 30 days.
Cachapa were the most popular
and the app already shows
the most important
information in the title.
Let's add a chart to show
a detailed breakdown
for the six pancakes.
To make this visualization
in Swift Charts,
we can use the same
declarative syntax as SwiftUI.
In Swift Charts,
you build charts by composition.
The main components
of a bar chart are the bars,
which are visual elements
for each item in your data.
Swift Charts calls
these visual elements "marks."
Let's jump into Xcode
to make this chart.
We start with adding a chart.
To make a bar, I add a BarMark
inside the Chart.
To show a bar
for the number of cachapas,
we have to set
the name and the sales.
We set the x-position of the bar
to be derived from the value
of the name of pancake --
in this case "Cachapa."
The first argument
to the .value factory method
is the description of the value,
and the second
is the value itself.
And now we get a single bar
in the preview.
The height of each bar
described by the y attribute
should be set by the number of
cachapas sold, which were 916.
To indicate that we're not
setting the position
or height of the bar directly,
we use .value.
Swift Charts automatically
creates not only the bar
but also a label
for the bars on the x-axis
and a y-axis that shows
what the length of a bar means.
Let's add a second bar
for injera,
of which the truck sold 850.
Now, it's cool to build
individual marks
and see them appear in the app.
However, we usually want
to create a chart
driven by a collection
such as an array of structs.
I'll start by adding a struct
for my pancake sales.
It has a name --
which is a string --
and how many pancakes
the truck sold --
which is an int.
Because we want
to use it to repeat,
we make it identifiable...
...and define an ID-computed
property that returns the name.
Now we can create our data set
as an array of pancakes.
We could load this
from an external data source
but here we'll define it
in the code.
Besides cachapa and injera,
we also add crêpe.
We can make the bar chart
data driven with ForEach.
First, remove the second bar.
And all we need to do now
is to repeat the BarMark
with a ForEach.
I pick "element" as the name
of the variable in the loop.
Then we can use
element.name for x...
...and element.sales for y.
If ForEach is the only
content in the chart,
we can also put
the data directly
into the chart initializer.
We can now add the
remaining three entries
for the jian bing, dosa,
and american pancakes.
As we add more entries
to the array,
we add new bar marks
to the chart.
Lastly, we see that the labels
are becoming close
to each other.
By swapping x and y,
we transpose the chart
and give the labels
for each bar more space.
The Swift Charts framework
automatically chooses
an appropriate axis style
to make your chart beautiful.
And with that, we made
our first data visualization
in Swift Charts.
And using the new
variant feature in Xcode,
we can see that this chart
looks beautiful in Dark Mode,
adapts to different
font sizes,
device sizes and orientations,
and supports accessibility.
To access the data
in a visual representation,
you need to be able to see.
Swift Charts exposes the data
in a visualization to VoiceOver
so that everyone can explore the
details of the popular pancakes.
When I navigate the chart
in VoiceOver,
it speaks the name and
number of pancakes sold.
VoiceOver: Cachapa, 916.
Injera, 850. Crêpes, 802.
Jian Ping, 753. Dosa, 654.
American, 618.
Dominik: And of course,
the chart supports
the Audio Graphs feature
Apple presented in 2021,
including the sonifications.
VoiceOver: Describe chart.
Chart Details.
Play Audio Graph.
[DESCENDING BEEPS]
Complete.
Dominik: We just used
Swift Charts to add
an informative and accessible
chart to the food truck app.
The chart shows
how many pancakes
the truck sold of each style.
Besides the summaries
for each style of pancake,
the food truck also
has per-day sales data.
The truck can park in Cupertino
and San Francisco.
We want to help the food truck
know where to park
on different days of the week.
To answer this question,
let's visualize the data
as a time series
for our two cities.
To see how easy it is
to explore different designs,
we will make three iterations
of the chart.
We will start by making
a bar graph for Cupertino.
Then, we will add the data for
San Francisco and add a picker.
And finally,
we will combine the data
into one multiseries line chart.
Let's start with the bar chart
showing the average number
of pancakes sold
per day of the week.
The sales data has the weekday
stored as a date
and how many pancakes
the truck sold as an integer.
The data for Cupertino is
in a variable, cupertinoData.
As before, we start making
a chart with a BarMark.
We set the x-position of the bar
to be derived from
the day of the date...
...and the height to be derived
from the sales.
And this gives us
a first iteration of a chart
that shows the sales data per
day of the week for Cupertino.
For the second iteration, let's
add the data for San Francisco.
Using this chart, we want
to help the pancake truck
decide where to park
during the week.
The sales data for San Francisco
is in the sfData variable.
We want to toggle
between the two cities
and see the bar chart
for each city.
We start with adding
a state variable, city.
And then we add a SwiftUI
picker for the city to the View.
To toggle between the sales
summaries for the two cities
via the city variable,
we add a switch statement
for the data variable.
And all we have to do now is to
replace the data for Cupertino
with the one that toggles
between the two --
Cupertino and San Francisco.
If I switch the toggle,
the charts toggles
between the two cities.
Swift Charts works
with SwiftUI animations,
so if we specify that the
transition should be animated
with easeInOut,
the bars animate as I toggle
between the two cities
and also only shows
one location at a time.
This gives our app
the right look and feel.
As our final iteration,
we will show both series
in a line chart.
To make this line chart,
we start with the bar chart
from Cupertino from before.
The data for Cupertino
and San Francisco
is in an array of series.
Series structs have
the city and sales data.
Before we show both series,
let's focus on
the Cupertino data.
In the chart, we can loop
over the series data.
Remember,
the chart initializer
acts just like a ForEach.
Then we can replace
the specific data for Cupertino
with the sales data
from the series.
To distinguish the data
for the two cities,
I want the color of the bars
to be derived from the city.
For this, we set
the foregroundStyle
to be derived from
the city in the series.
To show what city
a color represents,
Swift Charts creates
a legend below the chart.
Now, I add the data
for the second location.
As you can see in the preview,
Swift Charts
automatically chooses
a color for San Francisco,
and it shows the bars
for both cities in the chart.
Charts show data
for a particular context
and a visualization
may need to change
as our data
or questions change.
Swift Charts makes it easy
to quickly change your chart
to explore different designs.
The stacked bar chart is great
for showing the total
average sales per day;
but what if I wanted
to do a comparison
between the two cities?
Maybe a point or line chart
would be better.
We change the mark type
from a BarMark to a PointMark
to display the pancakes
sold as points,
or to a LineMark to show
the data as a line chart.
A line chart is a good fit
for the sales data
since it lets us compare the two
cities in each day of the week.
Charts can combine
multiple marks.
For example,
I can add a PointMark.
To make the series
differentiable without color,
we set the symbol
to be derived from the city.
Now each point indicates the
city by its color and symbol.
Because it is common
to show points on a line,
Swift Charts has
a shorthand for this
where we apply the symbol
modifier to the LineMark.
The style of the points
adapts to the line.
This chart is great.
We can easily compare the sales
trends throughout the week.
We observe that the sales
are especially high
in San Francisco on Sundays.
Swift Charts made it
very easy for us
to iterate through many designs
in just a few minutes.
So to wrap up, let's look at
how Swift Charts makes it easy
to iterate quickly and at the
same time be flexible enough
to seamlessly integrate charts
into your app's unique style.
In Swift Charts,
you build charts
by composition of marks
with mark properties.
In the Pancake app,
we composed charts
with three different marks
and four mark properties.
For example,
we made a simple bar chart
as a bar mark
with x and y properties.
We also changed the mark
to quickly explore designs,
like charts with points,
or line charts where
we used the line mark
with x and y properties.
We also saw
that we can add properties,
like Foreground Style, to show
multiple series in a line chart.
And a chart doesn't have
to have just one mark.
We combined points and lines,
and showed the same value
with two mark properties.
Swift Charts supports even more
marks and mark properties
than we used today.
It's also extensible
and you can add custom marks.
Marks and mark properties
is what allows Swift Charts
to express a wide range
of chart designs
with a small number
of declarative building blocks.
There are many ways
in which you can combine
these building block to create
great data visualizations
for your apps.
Together with what you can
already do in SwiftUI,
the possibilities
are truly endless.
And as I've showed you today,
you get support for Dark Mode,
different device screen sizes,
Dynamic Type, VoiceOver,
and Audio Graphs for free.
In addition, Swift Charts
supports High-Contrast mode.
And finally, Swift Charts
works across locales
and is multiplatform.
The chart with the same code
works across all
Apple platforms.
And the same customizations
work everywhere
so you can tailor the chart
to each platform.
Today, I showed you
how Swift Charts
uses SwiftUI's powerful
compositional syntax
so you can make more charts
with less code.
Swift Charts also provides
a rich set of
customization options,
so you can style the chart
to match your application.
And now that you know
how to chart new territory
and make a chart, you can learn
how to customize it in the docs
and in our follow-up talk
where you'll raise the bar.
♪