♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Devin Clary: Hi. I'm Devin, an
engineer on the Messages team.
Lance Parker: And I'm Lance,
also a Messages engineer.
Devin: Welcome to "Integrate
your custom collaboration app
with Messages."
Collaboration starts
with a conversation,
and in iOS 16
and macOS Ventura,
you can bring your app's
custom collaboration experience
right into the fabric
of the conversation.
In this video, we'll go over the
life cycle of a collaboration.
Then, we'll show you
how to prepare
your app's collaborative content
to be shared through Messages.
Next, we'll give you everything
you need to instantly verify
recipient access, and respond
to participant changes,
all without
compromising privacy.
Finally, we'll show you
how your app can post notices
about the content right
to the Messages conversation.
This video assumes your app
has existing collaboration
infrastructure,
and has already adopted
universal links.
We'll also build on some
concepts introduced in
"Add Shared with You
to your app"
and "Enhance collaboration
experiences with Messages."
First up,
I'll go over the life cycle
of a custom
collaboration message
to illustrate how this API
allows your users
to start collaborating
faster than ever.
When a user decides
to share a collaboration
from your app through Messages,
you first create metadata
to represent the content.
The metadata includes share
options the user can configure
prior to sending the message,
and a number of other properties
you can customize.
Next, you provide that metadata
to the share sheet,
or to drag and drop.
This allows a draft
of the content to be staged
in the Messages compose field.
The collaboration needs to be
represented by a universal link.
That can be created immediately,
but it's best deferred
until right before
the message is sent.
This is useful
if your app's link creation
depends on the selected
share options, or recipients,
as configured in
the Messages compose field.
The user chooses the recipients
and share options
and taps the send button.
Before the message is sent,
Messages asks your app
for the universal link
and a device independent
identifier for the content.
Using that identifier,
Messages provides a set of
cryptographic identities
representing the recipients
of that specific
collaboration message.
Your app will
use these identities later
to allow the recipients
to immediately open the link
on any of their devices.
Your app stores those
identities on its servers
and associates them
with the shared content.
Once your app
finishes this step,
the message is sent
to the recipients.
Now, here's what happens
on the receiving device.
The goal is to instantly
verify access,
pairing a recipient identity
with an account on your server.
When the recipient
opens the link,
your app receives
a call to open the URL,
just like it does
for any other link.
When your app detects
that a user account
doesn't yet have access
to the document,
it queries the system
for a proof of user identity
cryptographically signed
by the recipient device.
Your app sends
that signed identity proof
to your server for validation.
If the signature is valid,
the server compares the proof
against the identities
previously provided
by the sending device.
If there's a match,
your server grants access
to the user's account.
And with that,
the recipient has gained
instant and secure access
to the content,
all without exchanging
account information!
And that's the life cycle
of a collaboration message!
Next,
let's look more closely
at the API
for starting a collaboration.
The system needs some metadata
about the collaboration.
And for that,
you use a new class
in the Shared with You framework
called SWCollaborationMetadata.
This class has a few properties
for you to configure:
the content's title,
a local identifier
to reference the content
before its been shared;
the initiator name
and account handle,
to provide transparency
to the user
about the account
they're sharing from;
and the default share options,
for the user to configure.
Here's how to create
a metadata object
and configure its properties.
Create a local identifier using
SWLocalCollaborationIdentifier
initialized with a string.
The string only needs
to be sufficient for your app
to identify the content locally,
not across devices.
Initialize
a new metadata instance
using the local identifier.
Set the content title,
the initiator's account handle,
and their name
using PersonNameComponents
from the foundation framework.
The handle and name
are only displayed locally
so the user can confirm the
account they're sharing from.
Next,
set the defaultShareOptions.
Before I show you
how to do that,
I'll first describe
how options work.
Share options are
the settings a user configures
on the collaboration
in Messages or the share sheet.
The options selected by the user
are provided to you
before the message is sent.
Share options
might include settings like
who can make edits
to a collaboration
or who should have access
to the content.
You use a few classes
to define options,
starting with
SWCollaborationOption.
Depending on how
they're grouped,
options represent
individual switches,
or mutually exclusive values
for a setting.
Options have a title
and an identifier,
and they are either
selected or unselected.
There are two classes
to represent a group of options:
SWCollaborationOptionsGroup
and SWCollaborationOptions
PickerGroup.
You use
SWCollaborationOptionsGroup
to represent
a collection of switches,
while SWCollaborationOptions
PickerGroup
represents mutually exclusive
values for a setting.
Finally,
SWCollaborationShareOptions
defines the full set
of option groups,
to be set on the metadata's
defaultShareOptions property.
You can also provide a summary
string to describe the options.
Now that I've described
the option classes,
here's an example
showing how to use them.
This code defines
two option groups.
The first group is initialized
with an identifier
and two possible options.
The identifier is
an arbitrary string
you later use to identify which
option was selected by the user.
Since this is a picker group,
the options are
mutually exclusive.
This group represents
the permission settings
for the content:
readwrite or readonly.
Then, the first option in that
group is selected by default.
And the title is set to a string
describing this group.
The second option group
is initialized the same way,
and also contains two options.
But since this is
a generic option group,
the user will be able
to configure
whether to allow mentions
and comments independently.
Finally, the two option groups
are used to initialize
an instance of
SWCollaborationShareOptions,
which is then set
on the metadata.
Next, the metadata is provided
to the share sheet
or drag and drop,
depending on how the user
decides to share the content.
If your app uses SwiftUI,
SWCollaborationMetadata
is compatible
with the new ShareLink API.
Watch "Meet Transferable"
and "What's new in SwiftUI"
to learn more about
Transferable and ShareLink.
Here's how easy it is
to support collaboration
on a proxy representation
in SwiftUI!
From within
a Transferable model object,
set up a ProxyRepresentation
to return a collaboration
metadata instance.
Then, from a view,
initialize ShareLink
with that model object.
For UIKit and AppKit apps,
you use NSItemProvider
to support sharing.
And SWCollaborationMetadata
conforms to
NSItemProviderReading
and writing.
So you simply register
a metadata instance
with an item provider,
to support collaboration.
It's also good practice
to register multiple
representations of the content
to support sharing through
as many channels as possible.
For example,
Messages automatically
offers an option to send
the content as a copy
if you provide
a file representation.
You'll use
the NSItemProvider API with
UIActivityViewController and
UIDragItem on iOS and iPadOS
and NSSharingServicePicker
on macOS.
Here's how to set that up
with the share sheet on iOS.
Create an NSItemProvider
instance.
Register
the collaboration metadata
created in the previous example,
with visibility set
to all processes on the system.
Initialize
UIActivityItemsConfiguration
with the item provider,
then initialize
UIActivityViewController
with that configuration.
And finally,
present the view controller.
It's just as easy
to support drag and drop.
Initialize NSItemProvider
and register the metadata
the same way,
then create a UIDragItem
with the item provider
to use
with the drag and drop APIs.
The API is similar on macOS
for the sharing popover.
Again, set up the item provider.
And this time,
use it to initialize
NSSharingServicePicker.
And then show the picker
relative to a target view.
Drag and drop on macOS
utilizes NSPasteboardItem
rather than NSItemProvider.
To support this,
SharedWithYou exports
an NSPasteboardItem extension.
Using that extension,
set the collaboration metadata
directly on a new
NSPasteboardItem instance
in order to support
drag and drop.
And that's all you need
for a draft
of your collaborative content
to be staged in Messages!
Next, when the user
taps the send button,
the system coordinates with
your app to set up the share.
It does this through
a new class called
SWCollaborationCoordinator.
SWCollaborationCoordinator
is a singleton,
meaning there is
a global shared instance.
That shared instance
coordinates the collaboration
through a delegate you define
called an actionHandler.
To ensure your app
is always available
to coordinate collaborations,
it will be launched
in the background when needed.
So you should register
the delegate soon after launch
and handle actions
immediately to avoid timeouts.
Here's how to set up
the collaboration coordinator
after your app
finishes launching.
Access the singleton
coordinator instance
through the shared property.
Then, in the app delegate's
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions
method,
set the actionHandler property
to an object
that conforms to the
SWCollaborationActionHandler
protocol.
The action handler
protocol uses a new class
called SWAction.
SWActions represent work
your app is expected to perform.
You fulfill actions
to mark them as complete,
and fail them otherwise.
The first action your app
needs to handle
is the start collaboration
action.
SWStartCollaborationAction
contains the collaboration
metadata you set up earlier,
updated with the user's
selected share options.
Once you've performed
the necessary setup,
you fulfill the start action
with the universal link
and a device-independent
identifier
for the collaboration.
If you explicitly
fail the start action,
the message is canceled.
Here's an implementation
to handle the start action
using an example
server request.
First,
retrieve the local identifier,
and user-selected share options
from the action's
metadata property.
Set up a server request
to prepare the collaboration
using the identifier
and options.
Then, send the request
to the server.
This example uses async await.
Finally, fulfill the action
with the universal link
and the device independent
identifier from the response.
Or, if there was an error,
fail the action
to cancel the message.
If the start action
was successful,
the system sends your app
a second action
to update
the collaboration participants.
The SWUpdateCollaboration
ParticipantsAction
contains
the cryptographic identities
for the participants.
The identities are derived from
the collaboration identifier
fulfilled by the start action
in the previous step.
Store the identities
on your server
associated with the content.
You'll use this data
for verifying access
on the recipient devices.
Finally,
fulfilling this action
will send the universal link
in Messages.
This example shows
how to handle
the update participants action.
Retrieve
the collaboration identifier
from the action's metadata.
This is the identifier
you fulfilled
while handling the start action.
Next, retrieve the participant
data to store on your servers
using the action's
addedIdentities property.
Each identity has a Data
property called a root hash.
This is the data you should
store on your server
for later use.
Lance will go over
more of the details
about this property in
the Verifying Access section.
Set up another server
request, this time to add
the participants
to the collaboration
with the target identifier.
And just like before,
send the request to your server,
and fulfill or fail the action.
This time, the fulfill method
does not take any parameters.
Now that you've set up
the collaboration,
your app has everything it needs
to grant immediate access
to the recipients
of the message.
I'll hand it over to Lance
to show you how to do that!
Lance: Thanks, Devin.
In this section,
I'll show how to provide
immediate access
to the recipients using
the identity data
you stored on your server
in the previous step.
The rootHash property
on SWPersonIdentity
is used to do this verification.
A rootHash is a secure value
used to uniquely identify
a participant on their devices.
In order to perform
verification,
you'll need to understand
how to compute a root hash.
I'll take you through that now.
When a collaboration
message is sent,
it's actually sent individually
to each of a person's devices.
Messages identifies each device
using a cryptographic
public key.
Since the goal
is to allow access
only on this set of devices,
the root hash is derived
from the set of public keys
registered to each recipient.
The root hash is the root node
of a data structure
called a Merkle tree.
A Merkle tree is
a binary tree that is built
by performing a sequence
of hashing operations.
In order to derive an identity
for the user based on their
public keys, the keys are used
as the leaves of this tree.
The hashing algorithm used
in the Merkle tree ensures
that the root node can only be
computed from that set of keys.
In this example,
this user has three devices
and three public keys.
The keys will be unique for
each collaboration identifier
provided by your app,
using a process called
key diversification.
To prevent tracking the number
of devices registered to a user,
the set is padded with
random keys up to a fixed size.
The leaf nodes of the tree
are created by hashing
the padded set
of diversified keys.
The SHA256 algorithm is used
for the hashing operations
in this tree.
Then, each pair of leaf nodes
are concatenated
and then hashed to derive
their parent nodes.
This process is repeated
with the parent nodes
and repeated again until
a single root node remains.
This is the root hash
used to uniquely represent
this recipient's identity
across their devices.
Notice that it's possible
to generate a root hash
using a subset of the nodes
from a complete Merkle tree.
The root hash in this tree
can be reproduced using just
the hashes H4, 7, and 11,
along with the diversified
public key P3.
First, hash the public key
to get the missing leaf node H3.
Use H3 and H4 to generate H8.
Use the given H7 node
with H8 to generate H10.
And finally, H10 and H11
produce the root hash.
It's important to note that you
can prove the public key P3
was used to generate
a given root hash,
without needing
to reconstruct the entire tree.
The subset of nodes
needed to do this is called
a proof of inclusion.
Verification begins
when a universal link
is opened in your app.
To do this,
you first need to check
that the link is collaborative.
SWCollaborationHighlight
represents a collaborative link
and is retrieved
from SWHighlightCenter.
Use that collaboration highlight
to generate
the proof of inclusion.
To represent
a proof of inclusion,
use a class called
SWPersonIdentityProof.
To perform verification,
you'll first generate
this object along
with a cryptographic signature
to send to your server.
Retrieve the proof using the
getSignedIdentityProof method
on SWHighlightCenter.
It takes an
SWCollaborationHighlight
and some arbitrary data
to be signed by the device.
Use the signature to ensure
the request cannot be replayed
by a bad actor to gain access
to your collaboration.
The data could be a challenge
you request from your server,
or a nonce generated
on the device.
This example uses
the challenge approach.
The URL is passed
to this method on your app's
UIApplicationDelegate.
This URL is the universal link
associated
with the collaboration.
The URL is used
to fetch the associated
SWCollaborationHighlight
from the SWHighlightCenter.
Next, I'll request the challenge
from my server,
and pass the data I get back
to the getSignedIdentityProof
method on SWHighlightCenter,
along with the highlight.
This method returns
a signed identity proof.
I'll discuss
what your server should do
to validate this data later on.
Now I can send the signed proof
to my server for verification.
Finally, I update my user
interface with the result.
The app sends
the proof to the server,
along with the public key
and the signed data.
The data is signed
using the elliptic curve
digital signature algorithm
over the P-256 elliptic curve,
using SHA256
as a hash function.
Verify the signature on the data
using the public key
in the identity proof.
You can do this
with most commonly used
encryption libraries.
Once you have verified
the signature,
you can trust
that the identity proof was sent
from the device associated
with that public key.
Next, you use the identity proof
to recompute the root hash.
Here is an example of what
an SWPersonIdentityProof
would contain using the example
tree we looked at before.
Use it to reconstruct
the root hash of a Merkle tree.
The public key is P3.
The inclusion hashes are
H4, 7, and 11.
A local key index of 2
indicates the position
of the public key in the tree.
Here is an example
implementation that reconstructs
a root hash from the properties
on the proof.
A recursive algorithm
works nicely when working
with tree data structures,
so that's what I've done here.
On the initial invocation, pass
in the hash of the public key,
the set of inclusion hashes,
and the public key index.
Next, the first inclusion hash
is pulled out.
The public key index
is checked to see if the key
is on the left or the right
of its sibling.
The selected hashes
are concatenated
in the correct order,
and then hashed.
Next, the consumed node
in the inclusionHashes array
is removed,
and the rest are passed
to a recursive call
to this same function.
The public key index
is also updated
so that it's ready
for the next node in the tree.
With this simple function,
you can quickly compute
a root hash given
an identity proof.
The server can now check
that this generated root hash
is in the list of root hashes
the owner of the document
uploaded during sending.
The hash is present
in the list of known hashes,
so the server can grant access
to the document.
Now you can grant access
to the document with confidence!
To recap the steps you'll follow
to verify an identity:
first, look up
the collaboration highlight
for your content while handling
its universal link.
Next, sign some data and
retrieve the proof of inclusion.
Send the signed data
and proof to your server.
Verify the signature
on the data.
Using the proof of inclusion,
generate the root hash.
Finally, compare the root hash
to the list of known identities
associated with that content.
Now that you know
all about verifying access
to your collaboration links,
I'll talk about
how to coordinate participant
changes with Messages.
When the participants
in a Messages group change,
and that group
is collaborating together,
a user can choose to propagate
those changes to your app,
right from a banner
in the Messages thread.
In this scenario,
your app receives another
SWUpdateCollaboration
ParticipantsAction
containing the added
and removed identities.
You'll use the same code
you wrote to handle this action
when setting up
a collaboration,
but you'll also need
to handle removed participants.
For removal, simply look up
any account associated
with a removed identity
and revoke their access.
If no account is yet associated,
simply delete the root hash
from your database.
Here's
the implementation for
the update participants action
that Devin went over earlier.
This example uses
the removed identities property
on the action
and passes them to
a similar removal API request.
Note that this code only shows
handling removed identities,
but a complete implementation
should handle
both added
and removed identities.
And that's all you need
to handle participant changes!
Lastly, when changes
are made to a collaboration,
your app posts notices
about those changes
to be shown
directly in Messages.
There are a few types
of supported notices
I'll go over in this section.
Notices are displayed
as a banner
right in the conversation
where the link was shared.
The banner includes
a description of what changed,
as well as who made the change.
In this conversation,
Charlie made edits
to the Baking Recipes document.
Tapping the show button
connects them
right back to the content.
To represent a notice,
the SharedWithYou framework
has a protocol named
SWHighlightEvent.
Highlight events are
initialized with SWHighlights
retrieved
from the SWHighlightCenter API.
Messages supports
several categories of events.
A change event
for content updates or comments,
a membership event when
a participant joins or leaves,
a mention event when a user
is mentioned in a collaboration,
and a persistence event when
content is moved or deleted.
Here's an example showing
how to post a change event
for an edit to a collaboration.
Using the highlight center API,
retrieve
a collaboration highlight
for the target identifier.
Remember, this identifier
is one you defined during
the collaboration initiation,
so your app should have this
available for use when
a content change is made.
Next, create a highlight change
event instance.
The initializer
takes a highlight,
and a trigger enum value;
in this case,
set it to the edit type.
Finally, again using
the highlight center,
post the notice for that event.
Similarly,
for membership changes,
post a membership event,
this time passing
the addedCollaborator
or removedCollaborator
trigger type.
Next, if your app
supports user mentions,
you can post a mention event.
Initialize a person identity
with the root hash
of the mentioned user.
Recall that you associated
a person identity
with a user account in your app
while verifying access.
Then, post the mention event
in the same way,
this time passing the mentioned
identity as a parameter.
This notice will only be shown
in Messages
to the mentioned user.
Finally,
use the persistence event type
when content is moved,
renamed, or deleted.
Here, the renamed
trigger type is used,
to signify that the user
changed the name of the content.
And that is how your app
can notify collaborators,
and they will get those
updates right in Messages.
Devin: And with that,
you're ready to integrate
your app's collaboration
experience with messages
by following a few steps.
Set up your content
to be shared collaboratively,
cryptographically verify
participant access,
keep track
of participant changes,
and post notices in Messages
to connect your users
right back to the content.
Be sure to check out
the "Enhance collaboration
experiences with Messages" video
to learn more about
the new UI elements
you can display
for collaborations.
Lance: We can't wait to get
collaborating with your apps!
Devin and Lance,
cryptographically signing off.
Devin: Thanks for watching!
♪