[upbeat music]
Benjamin Poulain: Hi everyone, and welcome
to our session about virtualization.
This is what we are going
to do together today.
We'll see how you can run macOS
and Linux inside virtual machines,
on Apple silicon.
By the end of this session, you will
be able to do the same on your own Mac.
This may seem a little ambitious,
but stick with us,
and we'll do it together.
Here is our agenda for today.
We will start with an overview
of virtualization technologies,
and we'll see how to use Virtualization
framework to build virtual machines.
Then we'll do a deep dive into macOS.
We'll see how we can set up a virtual Mac
and install macOS into it.
And finally, we'll do a second deep dive,
this time into Linux.
We'll see how
to run full Linux distributions
and some cool new features.
Let’s get started with the overview.
We'll first look into the stack
that enables virtualization.
It all starts with hardware.
Apple silicon has special hardware
that enables the virtualization
of CPUs and memory.
This means you can run multiple
operating systems on top of a single SoC.
Next, we need software
to take advantage of this hardware.
And this is built right
into the macOS kernel.
You no longer need to write
kernel extensions, or KEXTs.
It's all built in.
To use those capabilities
from your application,
you can use Hypervisor framework.
Hypervisor framework is a low-level API
that lets you virtualize CPUs and memory.
But, because it's
a low-level framework,
you need to write every single detail
of the virtual environment.
Oftentimes,
we want to run full operating systems.
For this, there is a higher-level API,
which is Virtualization framework.
Virtualization framework enables
the creation of virtual machines
running macOS on Apple silicon
or Linux on both Apple silicon and Intel.
Today, our session will focus
on Virtualization framework.
When using Virtualization framework,
we'll deal with two kinds of objects.
The first kind are configuration objects.
They define all the properties
of our virtual machines.
The second kind
are virtual machine objects.
Those objects abstract virtual machines
and how to interact with them.
We'll start
with looking at the configuration.
The configuration defines the hardware.
Creating a configuration is
like configuring a Mac on the Apple Store.
We define how many CPUs we want,
how much memory, what kind of devices.
We can start from a simple configuration.
We can add a display,
and we get to see the content.
We can add a keyboard, and we can type.
We can add a trackpad,
and we can interact with the UI.
Configuring a virtual machine
is just like that.
But since we are dealing
with virtual machines,
we'll do this in code.
Let’s see how we can write
the configuration in Swift.
Defining the hardware is very simple.
We start with an object of type
VZVirtualMachineConfiguration.
This is the root object
of all configurations.
Next, we define how many CPUs
our machine should have.
Here we give four CPUs.
Then, we set how much memory we want.
In this case,
we give four gigabytes of memory.
Finally, we define the devices
our machine will have.
In this example,
we set a single storage device,
the disk to boot from,
and a pointing device, like a mouse.
There are many devices available.
The ones you set up depend
on the problem you want to solve.
Now we've seen the configuration.
It starts
with VZVirtualMachineConfiguration,
on which we add the CPUs,
the memory, and the devices.
Next, we'll look
into the virtual machine objects.
After we have configured our Mac,
we get it by the mail.
It's time to unbox it and start it.
But since we are dealing
with virtual machine,
we need to do that in code.
Let’s see how we can do it in Swift.
First, we'll create an instance
of VZVirtualMachine
from our configuration.
A VZVirtualMachine abstracts
an instance of the virtual hardware.
Now that we have the virtual machine,
we can operate on it.
For example, in this case,
we call start() to start it.
We'll often want to interact
with our virtual machines.
For this,
we have other objects to help us.
For example,
if we want to show our virtual display,
we can use an object
of type VZVirtualMachineView.
We start by creating a view.
Then we set our virtual machine as
the virtualMachine property on the view,
and it's ready.
Now we can use this VZVirtualMachineView
object like any NSView.
We can integrate it in our app
to see the content of the virtual machine.
To wrap up,
we've seen the configuration.
The configuration starts
with VZVirtualMachineConfiguration,
from which we define the CPUs,
memory, and our devices.
From the configuration,
we will create a virtual machine,
and we will use virtual machine objects.
We've seen VZVirtualMachine
to abstract the VM itself,
VZVirtualMachineView to display content,
and there are other objects
that can help us use the VM.
We have seen that the configuration
gives a lot of flexibility
in how we define virtual machines.
Unfortunately, there are
too many features to cover in one session.
In this session, we will look
into some of the core capabilities.
For everything else,
we have documentation,
and I invite you to check it out.
In the overview,
we just saw how to build virtual machines.
Now it is time to look into how we can
run a full operating system in them.
And we will start with macOS.
Virtualization framework supports macOS
on Apple silicon.
When we built Virtualization framework
on Apple silicon,
we've developed macOS
and Virtualization framework together.
What this gives us
is incredible efficiency
when running macOS
inside virtual machines.
Here is what we are going to see:
First, we will look into what we need
to turn a virtual machine
into a virtual Mac.
Then we'll look into the steps
to install macOS on our virtual Mac.
Next, we'll see some
of the special devices we have for macOS.
And finally, we will look
into a very important use case,
which is sharing files between
the host system and the virtual Mac.
Let’s start with the configuration.
We have seen before how
to build a generic virtual machine.
Now we want to add the special properties
that will make a virtual machine a Mac.
So how do we make a virtual Mac?
First, we will define a special platform.
A platform is an object
that holds all the properties
of a particular type of virtual machine.
There are three properties that are unique
to the virtual Mac hardware.
First, we have the hardware model.
The hardware model specifies
which version of the virtual Mac we want.
Second, there is the auxiliary storage.
The auxiliary storage is a form
of non-volatile memory used by the system.
And third,
there is the machine identifier.
The machine identifier is
a unique number representing the machine,
just like a physical Mac
has a unique serial number.
Once we have the platform, we have
all the pieces to describe the hardware,
but we need one more piece,
which is a way to boot macOS.
For this, we will use
a special boot loader,
the macOS boot loader.
Let’s see how to do all of this in Swift.
We start from the same base as before.
This code is what
we have seen in the overview.
Then we create
a VZMacPlatformConfiguration.
This is our platform object
for virtual Macs.
We need a hardware model for this Mac.
Here we use one we previously saved.
In virtual machines,
the auxiliary storage is backed
by a file on the local filesystem.
Here, we initialize our auxiliary storage
from a file URL.
For the unique identifier,
we initialize a VZMacMachineIdentifier
from one we previously saved.
For a new install,
we can also create a new identifier.
We have set all three properties.
Our platform is ready.
All we have to do is set it
on the configuration object.
This gives us the hardware.
Next we need a way to boot it.
To do that, we set up the boot loader
with VZMacBootLoader.
Now our machine is ready to boot.
What we have done so far is define
the virtual Mac and how to start it.
But we still need to get software on it,
which brings us to the installation.
Installing macOS is done in three steps.
First, we need to download
a restore image with the version
of macOS we want to install.
Then we need to create a configuration
that is compatible
with that version of macOS.
And finally,
we’ll install our restore image
in the compatible virtual machine.
So first,
we need to download a restore image.
You can download restore images
from the developer website,
but Virtualization can also help us.
You can call
VZMacOSRestoreImage.latestSupported
to get a restore image object
for the latest stable version of macOS.
This object has a URL property
that we can use to download the file.
Then we want to create a virtual machine
that is compatible
with the version of macOS we downloaded.
Virtualization can also help us here.
We can ask the restore image object
for the configuration requirements.
If the restore image can be run
on the current system,
we get an object listing the requirements.
From the requirements,
we can obtain the hardware model needed
needed to run this version of macOS.
We have seen previously how
to restore a hardware model.
This is how we obtain a new one.
The requirements
also contain two useful properties.
The object can tell us how many CPUs
and how much memory is required
to run this version of macOS.
Finally, we are ready
to start installation.
We start by creating a new virtual machine
from our configuration.
Then we create an installer.
The installer takes two arguments,
the compatible virtual machine we created
and the path
to the restore image we downloaded.
Now we can just call install(),
and voilà, we are ready to run macOS.
Now that we can set up a virtual Mac
and install macOS,
let’s see some
of the special devices for the Mac.
A first cool capability
is GPU acceleration.
We have built a graphic device
that exposes the GPU capabilities
to the virtual Mac.
This means you can run Metal
in the virtual machine,
and get great graphics performance
in macOS.
Let’s see how to set it up.
We start by creating
the graphics device configuration.
Here, we will use
the VZMacGraphicsDeviceConfiguration.
Next, we want to give it a display.
We set up the display
by defining its size and pixel density.
Now our device configuration is ready.
As usual, we set it
on the main configuration object.
We set it as the graphics device
for our virtual machine.
Next, we have a new device
for interacting with the Mac.
In macOS Ventura,
we are adding the Mac trackpad support
to the virtual Mac.
With the new trackpad,
it is possible to use gestures
like rotation, pinch to zoom, and so on.
This new device uses new drivers in macOS.
So to use it,
you will need macOS 13
both on the host system
and in the virtual machine.
Let’s see how to set it up.
It’s very easy.
We create a new object
of type VZMacTrackpadConfiguration.
Then we set it as the pointing device
on the virtual machine.
Now when we’ll use the view
with our virtual Mac, we can use gestures.
Finally, let’s look into a common use case
for many of us,
sharing files between the host system
and the virtual machine.
In macOS 12,
we introduced the Virtio file-system device
to share files on Linux.
In macOS Ventura,
we are adding support for macOS.
You can now pick folders that you want
to share with the virtual machine.
Any change you make from the host system
is instantly reflected
within the virtual machine
and vice versa.
Let’s see how to set it up.
First, we create a VZShareDirectory
with a directory we want to share.
Then we create a share object.
Here we'll use VZSingleDirectoryShare
to share a single directory.
You can also share multiple directories
by using VZMultipleDirectoryShare.
Now that we have the share,
we need to create a device.
But we will start we something special.
File system devices
are identified by a tag.
In macOS Ventura,
we have added a special tag
to tell the virtual machine
to automount this device.
Here, we take this special tag,
macOSGuestAutomountTag.
Then we create the device
and use our special tag.
We set the share
from the single directory we configured.
And finally, we add the device
to the configuration as usual.
Finally, let’s look
at everything together in a demo.
We start from a basic configuration.
We have a VZVirtualMachineConfiguration
with just CPU,
memory, a keyboard, and a disk.
We want a virtual Mac.
To do that, we need to start
by setting up the platform.
We'll use createMacPlatform
that is defined above to do that.
The second piece
of a virtual Mac is the boot loader.
We need a boot loader
that knows how to boot macOS.
To get that,
we set the platform's boot loader
to VZMacOSBootLoader().
Next, we want to set up the devices.
We want accelerated graphics.
To get it, we will set up
a VZMacGraphicsConfiguration.
We create the object,
define the display size and pixel density,
and we add it to the configuration.
Next, we want to use the new trackpad.
All we need to do
is set the pointing device
to VZMacTrackpadConfiguration.
That's it.
Now, we could start the VM,
but let's add the cherry on top.
We have seen how we can share directories.
Let's do it here.
We start by creating
the filesystem device configuration.
Here, notice we use the special tag
to automount it into macOS.
Then we define our share.
Here we use a single directory share
from a path on the file system.
Here, we will share this project
we are editing right now.
We add the device to our configuration,
and we are done.
Everything is ready.
We launch our app.
Since we configured
the Mac graphics device,
the VZVirtualMachineView
can show the content.
This is what you see here in the window.
And here it is.
We have configured macOS from scratch.
We can see the shared directory
and the project we were editing right now.
Finally, we will turn our eyes onto Linux.
Virtualization framework has
supported Linux
since the very beginning in macOS Big Sur.
In macOS Ventura, we have
added some pretty cool new features,
and we want
to share some of them with you.
First, we will see how we can
install full Linux distributions,
completely unmodified,
in virtual machines.
Then we will look at a new device
we are adding to show UI from Linux.
And finally, we will look at how
we can take advantage of Rosetta 2
to run Linux binaries in virtual machines.
Let’s start with installation.
If we wanted to install Linux
on a physical machine,
we'd start by downloading an ISO file
with the installer.
Then we'd erase a flash drive
with the ISO.
And finally, we'd plug the drive
in the computer and boot from it.
When dealing with virtual machines,
we will go through the same flow.
But instead of using a physical USB drive,
we will use a virtual one.
Let’s see how it works.
We start by creating an URL from the path
to the ISO file we downloaded.
Then we create a disk image attachment
from the file.
A disk image attachment represents a piece
of storage that we can attach to a device.
Next, we configure
a virtual storage device.
In this case, we want USB storage,
so we use
VZUSBMassStorageDeviceConfiguration.
Finally, as always,
we add our device
in the main configuration.
Here, the USB device appears
next to another storage device,
the main disk
on which we will install Linux.
Now we have a USB drive,
but we need a way to boot from it.
In macOS Ventura,
we have added support for EFI.
EFI is an industry standard
for booting both ARM and Intel hardware.
We are bringing the same support
to virtual machines.
EFI has a boot discovery mechanism.
What this will allow is discovering
the installer on our USB drive.
EFI looks at each drive
for one that can be booted.
It will find the installer
and start from there.
The installer itself will
tell EFI what drive to use next.
After the installation,
EFI can then start the Linux distribution.
Let’s see how to set up EFI in code.
First, we create a boot loader
of type VZEFIBootLoader.
EFI requires non-volatile memory
to store information between boots.
This is called the EFI variable store.
With virtual machines,
we can back such storage
by a file on the filesystem.
Here, we create
a new variable store from scratch.
Now EFI is ready.
We just need to set it
as the boot loader on the configuration.
Next, we will look into a new capability
for Linux VMs, graphics.
In macOS Ventura,
we have added support for Virtio GPU 2D.
Virtio GPU 2D is a paravirtualized device
that allows Linux
to provide surfaces to the host macOS.
Linux renders the content,
gives the rendered frame
to Virtualization framework,
which can then display it.
You can now show this content
in your app with VZVirtualMachineView
just like on macOS.
Let’s see how to set it up.
Setting up the device is similar
to what we did for macOS.
We start by creating
a VZVirtioGraphicsDeviceConfiguration.
We need to define the size
of our virtual display.
In Virtio terminology,
a virtual display is a "scanout."
So we create one scanout
with the size of the display.
Finally, we set the new device
as the graphics device
of our configuration.
Now our VM is ready to display content
with VZVirtualMachineView.
Next, let’s see everything
together in a demo.
We start from where we left off.
Let's delete the code
that is specific to the Mac.
Then let's change the disk
we are booting from.
We'll swap the path
from our Mac drive to our Linux drive.
Next, we need a boot loader.
We set up EFI with VZEFIBootLoader.
We first create
the EFI boot loader object.
Then we load
the variable store from its file.
And finally, we set EFI
as the boot loader on our configuration.
Now we can boot,
but it'd be nice to show the UI.
Let's add Virtio GPU to our configuration.
We simply create a graphics device
of type
VZVirtioGraphicsDeviceConfiguration.
Then we define a scanout
with the size of the virtual display.
And we set the Virtio GPU as
a graphics device on our configuration.
The last touch
is getting the mouse to work.
We just use a virtual
USB screen coordinate pointer device,
and we'll have a mouse in Linux.
That's it.
We can run the project.
EFI looks at the disk
and finds it bootable.
Then Linux shows the content of the UI
through the Virtio GPU device.
And we can use the mouse
to interact with Linux.
Last but not least,
we'll see how we can take advantage
of the Rosetta 2 technology inside Linux.
For many of us,
we love developing services on our Mac,
but once our work is ready,
the binaries we create may need
to run on x86 servers.
x86 instruction emulation
has been great for this,
but we can do better.
In macOS Ventura,
we are bringing the power
of Rosetta 2 to Linux binaries.
What Rosetta 2 does is translate
the Linux x86-64 binaries
inside your virtual machine.
This means you can run
your favorite ARM Linux distribution,
and its x86-64 apps can run with Rosetta.
And it's fast.
It's the same technology
we have been using on the Mac,
which means
we have incredible performance.
Let’s see how to use it.
First, we need
to give Linux access to Rosetta.
To do this, we use the same file sharing
technology we have seen on macOS.
Instead of sharing a folder,
we use a special kind of object,
a VZLinuxRosettaDirectoryShare.
Then we create a sharing device
and set up Rosetta directory share.
Finally, we set up our device
on the configuration as usual.
Now our virtual machine
is ready to use Rosetta.
Next, let’s see how Linux
can take advantage of it.
In Linux, we start by mounting
the shared directory in the file system.
What we see from Linux is a Rosetta binary
that can translate applications.
Then we can use update-binfmts
to tell the system to use Rosetta
to handle any x86-64 binary.
Don’t worry
about remembering this command.
It's all in the documentation.
Now Linux is ready.
Every x86-64 binary launched
will be translated by Rosetta.
Before we end our Linux section,
let’s see everything together.
Here, we have a full Linux
distribution installed from scratch.
We can show its UI with Virtio GPU 2D.
From within the VM,
we run a PHP server with Rosetta.
And we can just connect
to it from macOS host.
We've seen that creating
virtual machines has never been simpler.
With Virtualization framework,
you can get virtual machines running
with just a few lines of code.
We have also seen that virtual machines
are ridiculously fast on macOS.
To learn more about Virtualization,
I invite you to check out
the code samples and documentation.
And on behalf of the team,
we cannot wait
to see what you will do next
with this technology.
[upbeat music]