♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello.
I'm Doug from the Swift team,
and I'm here to talk about
Swift Concurrency's approach
to eliminating data races.
We introduced Swift Concurrency
as a set of language features
that make it easier to write
concurrent programs.
For the mechanics of these
individual language features,
we refer you to the 2021 WWDC
talks covering each of them.
This talk takes a different,
more holistic view
of Swift Concurrency
as a way of structuring
your program to make
efficient use of concurrency
without introducing data races.
But to do so,
we need a great analogy,
so we invite you to sail with us
on the high seas of concurrency.
The sea of concurrency
is unpredictable,
with many things
going on at once,
but with you at the helm
and Swift helping you navigate
the waters,
it can produce amazing things.
Let's dive in!
We'll start
by talking about isolation,
which is one of the key ideas
of Swift's concurrency model,
ensuring that data
is not shared in a manner
that can introduce data races.
Let's start with task isolation.
In our sea of concurrency,
tasks are represented by boats.
Boats are our main workers --
they have a job to do,
which they perform sequentially
from start to finish.
They are asynchronous,
and their work can be suspended
any number of times at
"await" operations in the code.
Finally,
they are self-contained:
each task has its own resources,
so it can operate by itself,
independently of all
of the other boats in the sea.
If our boats are
completely independent,
we have concurrency
without data races,
but it's not very useful
without some way to communicate.
Let's add some communication!
For example, one boat might have
a pineapple that it wants
to share with another boat.
So the boats meet
on the open sea,
and we transfer the pineapple
from one boat to the other.
Now, this is where
the physical analogy
breaks down a little bit,
because this pineapple
is not a physical item that
moves from one boat to the next.
It's data, and in Swift we have
a couple of different ways
we could represent that data.
How do we define
our pineapple type?
We like value types in Swift,
so let's make the pineapple
a struct that's defined
by its weight and ripeness.
Let's see how this works.
When the boats meet
on the open sea,
we're really passing a copy
of the pineapple instance
from one boat to the next,
and each boat goes away
with its own copy.
If you were to
mutate the copies,
such as by calling
the slice() and ripen() methods,
it won't have any effect
on the other one.
Swift has always
preferred value types
for exactly this reason --
mutations have
only local effects.
That principle helps
value types maintain isolation.
Now, let's extend our data model
a bit and add chickens!
Unlike pineapples,
which are pretty much
only good for eating,
chickens are beautiful creatures
with their own
unique personalities.
So, we're going to model
them with a class, like this.
Let's have our intrepid
seafarers exchange a chicken.
When our boats meet,
we share the chicken,
except that copying
a reference type like chicken
doesn't give you another
full copy of the chicken,
it gives you a reference
to that specific object.
So once our boats have
gone their separate ways,
we can see
that we have a problem:
both boats are doing
their work concurrently,
but they are not independent
because they both reference
the same chicken object.
That shared mutable data
is prone to data races,
such as when one boat
is trying to feed the chicken
and the other
wants to play with it,
leading to one
very confused chicken.
We need a way to know that it
was safe to share pineapples
amongst boats, but not chickens.
And then we need some checking
in place in the Swift compiler
to ensure that chickens
aren't accidentally passed
from one boat to another.
Swift protocols are a great way
of categorizing types
so you can reason
about their behavior.
The Sendable protocol
is used to describe types
that can safely be shared across
different isolation domains,
without creating data races.
A type can be made Sendable
by writing a conformance.
The Pineapple struct
conforms to Sendable
because it's a value type,
but the Chicken class cannot
because it's an unsynchronized
reference type.
Modeling Sendable as a protocol
allows us to describe
the places where data
is going to be shared
across isolation domains.
For example,
when a task returns a value,
this value is provided
to any of the tasks
that are waiting for that value.
Here, we are trying to return
a Chicken from our Task,
and we get an error
stating that this is unsafe
because Chicken is not Sendable.
The actual Sendable constraint
comes from the definition
of the Task struct itself,
which specifies that
the result type of a Task,
called Success,
must conform
to the Sendable protocol.
You should use
Sendable constraints
where you have
generic parameters whose values
will be passed across
different isolation domains.
Now, let's revisit the idea
of sharing data among boats.
When two boats meet on the high
seas and want to share data,
we need someone to consistently
check all of the goods
to make sure
they're safe to share.
That's the role of our friendly
customs inspector --
played here
by the Swift compiler --
to make sure that only
Sendable types are exchanged.
The pineapple is fine
and can be exchanged freely,
because it's Sendable.
However, the chicken
cannot be exchanged,
and our friendly customs
inspector will prevent us
from making that mistake.
The compiler is involved
in checking Sendable correctness
at many different points.
Sendable types must be
correct by construction,
and cannot allow any shared data
to be smuggled through them.
Enums and structs
generally define value types,
which copy all of their
instance data along with them
to produce independent values.
Therefore, they can be Sendable
so long as all of their
instance data is also Sendable.
Sendable can be propagated
through collections
and other generic types
using conditional conformance.
An array of Sendable types
is Sendable,
so a Crate full of pineapples
is also Sendable.
All of these Sendable
conformances can even be
inferred by the Swift compiler
for non-public types,
so Ripeness,
Pineapple, and Crate
are all implicitly Sendable.
But let's say we create a coop
to house our flock of chickens.
This type cannot
be marked as Sendable,
because it contains
non-Sendable state:
Chicken isn't Sendable,
so the array of chickens
isn't Sendable.
We'll get an error message
from our compiler to indicate
that this type
cannot safely be shared.
Classes are reference types,
so they can only be
made Sendable under
very narrow circumstances,
such as when a final class
only has immutable storage.
Our attempt to make
the Chicken class Sendable
will produce an error because
it contains mutable state.
Now, it is possible
to implement reference types
that do their own internal
synchronization, for example,
by using a lock consistently.
These types are
conceptually Sendable,
but there is no way for Swift
to reason about that.
Use unchecked Sendable to
disable the compiler's checking.
Be careful with this,
because smuggling mutable state
through @unchecked Sendable
undermines the data race safety
guarantees Swift is providing.
Task creation involves
executing a closure in a new,
independent task, like sending
off a rowboat from your boat.
When we do this, we can capture
values from the original task
and pass them
into the new task,
so we need Sendable checking
to ensure we don't
introduce data races.
If we do try to share
a non-Sendable type
across this boundary, the
Swift compiler has us covered,
producing an error message
like this one.
This isn't magic
for task creation.
The closure is being inferred
to be a Sendable closure,
which could have been written
explicitly with At-Sendable.
Sendable closures are values
of Sendable function type.
At-Sendable can be written
on a function type to indicate
that the function type conforms
to the Sendable protocol.
That implies that values
of that function type
can be passed to other isolation
domains and called there
without introducing data races
on their captured state.
Normally, function types
cannot conform to protocols,
but Sendable is special
because the compiler validates
the semantic requirements
for it.
There is similar support
for tuples of Sendable types
conforming to the
Sendable protocol,
which allows Sendable
to be used
throughout the entire language.
The system we've described
has many concurrently executing
tasks that are isolated
from each other.
The Sendable protocol
describes types
that can be safely shared
among tasks,
and the Swift compiler
checks Sendable conformances
at every level to maintain
isolation of the tasks.
However, without any notion
of shared mutable data anywhere,
it's hard for the tasks
to coordinate
in a meaningful manner.
So we need some way
to share data amongst our tasks
that doesn't re-introduce
data races.
This is where actors come in.
Actors provide a way
to isolate state
that can be accessed
by different tasks,
but in a coordinated manner
that eliminates data races.
Actors are the islands
in our sea of concurrency.
Like boats,
each island is self-contained,
with its own state
that is isolated
from everything else in the sea.
To access that state,
your code needs to be running
on the island.
For example,
the advanceTime method
is isolated to this island.
It lives on the island
and has access
to all of the island's state.
To actually run code
on an island, you need a boat.
A boat can visit the island
to run code on the island,
at which point it has
access to that state.
Only one boat can visit the
island to run code at a time,
which ensures that
there is no concurrent access
to the island's state.
If other boats show up,
they must await their turn
to visit the island.
And because it might be
a long time before a given boat
gets a chance to visit the
island, entering into an actor
is a potential suspension point
marked by the “await” keyword.
Once the island frees up --
again, at a suspension point --
another boat can visit.
Just like with two boats
meeting on the open sea,
interactions between a boat
and an island need to maintain
isolation of both,
by making sure
that non-Sendable types
don't pass between the two.
For example, perhaps we try
to add a chicken from our boat
to the flock on the island.
This would create two references
to the same chicken object
from different
isolation domains,
so the Swift compiler
rejects it.
Similarly, if we try to adopt
a pet chicken from the island
and take it away on our boat,
Sendable checking ensures
that we cannot create
this data race.
Actors are reference types,
but unlike classes, they isolate
all of their properties and code
to prevent concurrent access.
Therefore,
having a reference to an actor
from a different
isolation domain is safe.
It's like having a map
to an island:
you can use the map
to go visit the island,
but you still need to go
through the docking procedure
to access its state.
Therefore, all actor types
are implicitly Sendable.
You might be wondering
how to know
what code is isolated to
the actor and what code isn't.
Actor isolation is determined
by the context you're in.
The instance properties
of an actor
are isolated to that actor.
Instance methods on the actor
or an extension of the actor
are also isolated by default,
like this advanceTime method.
Closures that are not Sendable,
such as the closure passed
to the reduce algorithm,
stay on the actor and are
actor-isolated when they are
in an actor-isolated context.
The task initializer
also inherits actor isolation
from its context,
so the created task will be
scheduled on the same actor
as it was initiated from.
Here, that grants
access to the flock.
On the other hand,
a detached task
does not inherit actor isolation
from its context,
because it is completely
independent of the context
where it was created.
We can see that the code
in the closure here
is considered to be outside
the actor because it needs
to use “await” to refer
to the isolated “food” property.
We have a term for this closure:
it's non-isolated code.
No-isolated code is code
that does not run
on any actor at all.
You can explicitly make
a function that's within
an actor non-isolated by using
the non-isolated keyword,
putting it outside of the actor.
Just like what happened
implicitly with the closure used
for the detached task.
That means if we want to read
some of the state
that's isolated to the actor,
we'll need to use “await”
to visit the island and grab
a copy of the state we need.
Non-isolated async code
always runs
on the global cooperative pool.
Think of it as only running when
a boat is out on the open sea,
so you have to leave the island
you're visiting to do the work.
That means checking to ensure
that you aren't taking any
non-Sendable data with you!
Here, the compiler detects
the potential data race,
where an instance
of the non-Sendable Chicken
is trying to leave the island.
Let's consider one more case
of non-isolated code.
The “greet” operation is
non-isolated, synchronous code.
It knows nothing
about boats or islands
or concurrency in general.
And here, we're calling it
from the actor-isolated
greetOne function,
and that's okay!
This synchronous code,
when called from the island,
will stay on the island,
so it's free to operate
on the chicken from the flock.
If instead we had a non-isolated
async operation
that calls “greet,”
then “greet” will run there,
on a boat, in the open sea.
Most Swift code is like this:
synchronous,
non-isolated to any actor,
and only operates on
the parameters it's been given,
so it stays in the isolation
domain where it is called.
Actors hold state
that is isolated
from the rest of the program.
Only one task can run
on an actor at a time,
so there is no concurrent
access to that state.
Sendable checking
applies any time
a task enters or exits
an actor to ensure
that no unsynchronized
mutable state escapes.
Altogether, this makes actors
one of the building blocks
for a concurrent program
in Swift.
There's another special actor
we often talk about
called the main actor.
Think of the main actor
as a big island
in the middle of the sea.
It represents the main thread,
where all of the drawing
and interaction for
your user interface occurs.
So if you want to draw
something,
you need to run the code
on the main actor's island.
It's so important for your UI,
that maybe we should even
call it the “U-I-land."
When we say
that the main actor is “big,”
what we mean is that
it contains a lot of state
related to the program's
user interface.
There's a lot of code,
both in the UI frameworks
and in your apps,
that needs to run on it.
However, it's still an actor,
so it only runs one job
at a time.
So you have to be careful
not to put too much
or long-running work
on the main actor,
because it can make
your UI unresponsive.
Isolation to the main actor
is expressed with
the MainActor attribute.
This attribute can be applied
to a function or closure
to indicate that the code
must run on the main actor.
Then, we say that this code
is isolated to the main actor.
The Swift compiler
will guarantee
that main-actor-isolated code
will only be executed
on the main thread,
using the same mechanism
that ensures mutually exclusive
access to other actors.
If one calls updateView
from a context that isn't
isolated to the main actor,
it will need to introduce
an “await”
to account for the switch
over to the main actor.
The main actor attribute
can also be applied to types,
in which case the instances
of those types
will be isolated
to the main actor.
Again, this is just like
any other actor --
the properties
are only accessible
while on the main actor,
and the methods are isolated
to the main actor
unless they explicitly opt out.
Like normal actors,
references to main-actor classes
are themselves Sendable,
because their data is isolated.
This makes the main actor
annotation suitable
for your UI views
and view controllers,
which are necessarily
tied to the main thread
by the frameworks themselves.
You can share a reference
to your view controller
with other tasks
and actors in your program,
and they can asynchronously call
back into the view controller
to post results.
This has a direct effect
on your app's architecture.
In your app,
your views and view controllers
will be on the main actor.
Other program logic should be
separated from that main actor,
using other actors
to safely model shared state
and tasks to describe
independent work.
And those tasks can shuttle
between the main actor
and other actors as necessary.
There's a lot going on
in a concurrent app,
so we've built some great tools
to help you make sense of it.
I invite you to check out
the "Visualize and Optimize
Swift Concurrency" talk
to learn more.
Let's dive into some deeper
waters to talk about atomicity.
The goal of the
Swift Concurrency model
is to eliminate data races.
What that really means
is that it eliminates
low-level data races,
which involve data corruption.
You still need to reason about
atomicity at a high level.
As we've talked about before,
actors only run
one task at a time.
However, when you stop
running on an actor,
the actor can run other tasks.
This ensures that the program
makes progress,
eliminating the potential
for deadlocks.
However, it requires you to
consider your actor's invariants
carefully around
await statements.
Otherwise, you can end up
with a high-level data race
where the program
is in an unexpected state,
even though no data
is actually corrupted.
Let's break down
an example of this.
Here we have a function
that intends to deposit
some additional pineapples
on an island.
It's outside of an actor,
so it's non-isolated async code.
That means it runs out here
in the open sea.
It's been given some pineapples
and a map to the island
where it should deposit
those pineapples.
The first interesting
operation here
gets a copy of the food array
from the island.
To do that, the boat needs
to visit the island,
signaled by the “await” keyword.
As soon as it has a copy
of the food,
the boat heads back out
to the open sea
to continue its work.
That means adding the pineapple
from the pineapples parameter
to the two it got
from the island.
Now, we can move along to the last line
of the function.
Our boat now needs
to visit the island again
to set the island's food array
to those three pineapples.
Here, everything
worked out fine,
and we have the three pineapples
on the island!
But things could
have gone a bit differently.
Let's say a pirate ship snuck in
and stole all of the pineapples
while our first boat was waiting
its turn to visit the island.
Now, our original ship
deposits its three pineapples
on the island,
and we notice a problem.
The three pineapples
have suddenly turned
into five pineapples!
What happened here?
Well, notice that we have
two awaits
for access to state
on the same actor,
and we're making
an assumption here
that the food array
on the island
doesn't change
between those two awaits.
But these are awaits,
meaning that our task
could get suspended here
and the actor could do other
higher-priority work,
like battling pirates.
In this specific case,
the Swift compiler will reject
an attempt to outright modify
the state on another actor.
However, we should really
rewrite our deposit operation
as synchronous code
on the actor, like this.
Because this
is synchronous code,
it will run on the actor
without interruption.
So we can be sure
that the state of the island
will be unchanged by anyone else
throughout the entire function.
When you are writing your actor,
think in terms of synchronous,
transactional operations
that can be interleaved
in any way.
Every one of them
should ensure that the actor
is in a good state
when it exits.
For async actor operations,
keep them simple,
forming them primarily
from your synchronous,
transactional operations,
and take care that your actor
is in a good state
at each await operation.
This way, you can make full use
of actors to eliminate
both low-level
and high-level data races.
In a concurrent program,
many things
are happening at once,
so the order in which
those things happen
can vary from one execution
to the next.
And yet programs often rely
on handling events
in a consistent order.
For example,
the stream of events
that come in from user input
or messages from a server.
When these
event streams come in,
we expect their effects
to happen in order.
Swift Concurrency provides tools
for ordering operations,
however, actors are not
the tool for doing so.
Actors execute the
highest-priority work first,
to help the overall system
stay responsive.
This eliminates
priority inversions
where lower-priority work
ends up happening
before higher-priority work
on the same actor.
Note that this
is a significant difference
from serial Dispatch queues,
which execute in a strictly
First-In, First-Out order.
Swift Concurrency has several
tools for ordering work.
The first we've been talking
about a lot already -- tasks.
Tasks execute
from beginning to end,
with the normal control flow
you're used to,
so they naturally order work.
AsyncStream can be used to model
an actual stream of events.
One task can iterate
over the stream of events
with a for-await-in loop,
processing each event in turn.
An AsyncStream can be shared
with any number
of event producers,
which can add elements
to the stream
while maintaining order.
We've talked a lot about
how Swift's concurrency model
is designed to eliminate
data races
using the notion of isolation,
which is maintained
by Sendable checking
at task and actor boundaries.
However, we cannot all
just stop what we are doing
to go mark all of the
Sendable types everywhere.
Instead, we need
an incremental approach.
Swift 5.7 introduces
a build setting to specify
how strictly the Swift compiler
should check for Sendability.
The default setting is Minimal
meaning that the compiler
will only diagnose places
where one has explicitly tried
to mark something as Sendable.
This is similar to how Swift 5.5
and 5.6 behaved,
and for the above, there won't
be any warnings or errors.
Now, if you add
a Sendable conformance,
the compiler will complain
that the Coop type
cannot be Sendable because
Chicken isn't Sendable.
However, this -- and other
Sendable-related problems --
will be presented as warnings
in Swift 5, not errors,
to make it easier to work
through the problems one by one.
To move further
toward data race safety,
enable the “targeted”
strict concurrency setting.
This setting enables Sendable
checking for code
that has already adopted
Swift Concurrency features
like async/await, tasks,
or actors.
This will identify, for example,
attempts to capture values
of non-Sendable type
in a newly created task.
Sometimes the non-Sendable types
come from another module.
Perhaps it's some package
that hasn't been updated
for Sendable yet,
or even your own module
that you just haven't
gotten around to.
For those, you can temporarily
disable the Sendable warnings
for types that come
from that module
using the @preconcurrency
attribute.
This will silence Sendable
warnings for the Chicken type
within this source file.
At some point,
the FarmAnimals module
will get updated
with Sendable conformances.
Then, one of two things
will happen:
either Chicken
becomes Sendable somehow,
in which case the preconcurrency
attribute can be removed
from the import.
Or Chicken will be known
to be non-Sendable,
in which case the warning
will come back,
indicating that your assumptions
about Chicken being Sendable
are, in fact, not correct.
The targeted strictness setting
tries to strike a balance
between compatibility
with existing code
and identifying potential
data races.
However, if you'd like to see
everywhere that races
could occur,
there is one more option:
complete checking.
Complete checking approximates
the intended Swift 6 semantics
to completely eliminate
data races.
It checks everything
that the earlier two modes check
but does so for all code
in the module.
Here, we're not
actually making use
of Swift's concurrency
features at all.
Rather, it's performing work
on a dispatch queue,
which will execute
that code concurrently.
The async operation
on a dispatch queue
is actually known to take
a Sendable closure,
so the compiler produces
a warning indicating
that there is a data race
when the non-Sendable body
is captured by the code
running on the dispatch queue.
We can fix this by making
the body parameter Sendable.
That change eliminates
this warning,
and now all of the callers
of doWork know
that they need to provide
a Sendable closure.
That means we get better
checking for data races,
and we can see
that the visit function now
is the source of a data race.
Complete checking
will help flush out
the potential data races
in your program.
To achieve Swift's goal
of eliminating data races,
we'll eventually need to get
to complete checking.
We encourage you to work
incrementally toward that goal:
adopt Swift's concurrency model
to architect your app
for data race safety,
then enable progressively
stricter concurrency checking
to eliminate classes
of errors from your code.
And don't fret over marking your
imports with @preconcurrency
to suppress warnings
for imported types.
As those modules adopt
stricter concurrency checking,
the compiler will recheck
your assumptions.
At the end of this road,
your code will benefit
from both memory safety
and data race safety,
helping you focus
on building great apps.
And thank you for sailing with me
on the sea of concurrency.
♪