♪ ♪
Zheng Naiwei:
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Zheng Naiwei
from Apple's AVFoundation Team.
In this session we are going to talk about
how to improve
streaming delivery reliability with new
features we added to HLS Content Steering.
We will cover three topics today.
If you haven't heard of Content Steering,
don't worry.
It's a piece of HLS technology
that can dynamically steer
streaming traffic,
to improve streaming service quality.
I will give you a short review
to help you get on track.
Then I will present
the new Pathway cloning feature,
which can bring
dynamic steering ability beyond limits,
to further improve the reliability
of your streaming service.
Finally, I will use concrete examples
to guide you through how to influence
server-side logic for steering traffic.
Let's wait no more and get started.
Back in the time we don't have
Content Steering,
variant selection in case of error
fallback wasn't standardized
in the HLS specification.
And different client implementations
can behave differently
in choosing the next fallback variant.
But a typical way to do this
is to follow the variant ordering
in the multivariant playlist.
If a streaming provider wants to specify
a set of fallback CDNs,
they need to list every variant
from every CDN
and properly order them
in the multivariant playlist.
This way, in case the client player
encountered a failure
in the first variant,
it can move on to the next variant
in the playlist with the failed variant
penalized from selection.
In this case, we see that the client
player had trouble with the 6 Mbps variant
from CDN1 and thus moved on
to the next 3 Mbps variant from CDN1,
following the order
in the multivariant playlist.
If unfortunately the 3 Mbps variant
from CDN1 also failed,
the client player would be left
with no variants from CDN1,
and move on to
the 6 Mbps variant from CDN2.
It can do this on and on
until no variant to fallback to.
However, even though the playlist
authoring server can control the ordering
of the fallback variants,
such control only happens
at the point of client
requesting the multivariant playlist,
and once the playlist was handed out,
there's no way
to change the fallback ordering.
This is where Content Steering
comes into the picture.
With Content Steering,
the streaming provider
can now group variants into Pathways
with different CDN hosts.
The error fallback behavior is
now standardized for Content Steering.
Pathways are ordered by preference.
In this example,
the CDN1 Pathway at the top
is most preferred,
following CDN2 and CDN3.
The streaming provider also hosts
a Steering Server,
generating Steering Manifests
for each client player.
A Steering Manifest defines rules
of Pathway priorities,
so the player can follow the rules
in selecting and fallback between
variant streams.
Let's say for example the streaming
provider is trying to offload
some of the traffic from CDN1 to CND2.
It would generate a Steering Manifest
with the new Pathway priority rules,
and when a client player playing from CDN1
requests for a Steering Manifest update,
the Steering Server can send
the prepared Steering Manifest
with the rule changes to the client.
The client will parse and see
the new Pathway Priority rules,
and apply it to its playback session.
In this case the rule change
switched preference order
between Pathway CDN1 and CDN2
so that the client player will switch
and play from CDN2 immediately.
Then, in case of failures,
the client will first exhaust fallback
variants within the current Pathway,
and fallback to the most preferred Pathway
according to its current Pathway Priority.
In this case, if all variants
from CDN2 were errored out,
the client player can start to choose
from variants from CDN1,
which is the next preferred Pathway.
When we apply Content Steering
to the global scale,
it can solve bigger regional
load balancing problems.
Let's say our streaming service provider
operates all around the world,
with two main CDN providers.
To assign these CDNs
to client players globally,
the Steering Server prepared two
different Steering Manifests,
one prefers CDN1,
and the other prefers CDN2.
Then it distributes
these Steering Manifests
based on the client player's region
so that the North and South America
utilizes CDN1
and the rest of the world utilizes CDN2.
At the top of the world map
we show a horizontal stacked bar
representing the distribution of traffic
between CDN1 and CDN2.
As of right now, both CDNs are serving
half of the worldwide traffic.
However, over time the streaming
service provider observed
a significant increase of traffic
towards CDN2
because of global daylight shift.
At the same time,
the traffics toward CDN1 is decreasing.
So the streaming provider decided
to steer the Europe region to use CDN1.
It does so by preparing
a Steering Manifest that prefers CDN1,
and sends it to clients
from the Europe region.
Now those client players in that region
will steer traffic to CDN1,
offloading from CDN2.
And the global traffic
became more balanced.
Now let's take a look at
an HLS multivariant playlist
with Content Steering support.
First we see
the EXT-X-CONTENT-STEERING tag
that indicates this multivariant playlist
uses Content Steering.
Then we have a SERVER-URI attribute
specifying where the client should request
Steering Manifest updates from.
Then the next PATHWAY-ID attribute
specifies the initial pathway to choose
for playback at startup.
Then we can see that each variant stream
were given an PATHWAY-ID attribute
to group them into Pathways.
Each Pathway should have
the same set of variant streams,
with only difference being their URIs
and media group names.
In this example, we have two Pathways,
namely CDN1 and CDN2.
Both contains two variant streams,
one 6 Mbps high resolution video
and one 3 Mbps lower resolution video.
With the only difference
being their URI hostname.
There are also two distinct audio groups
for each Pathway
where they have different URI hostnames.
Here is an example Steering Manifest,
which is a JSON document.
The PATHWAY-PRIORITY field is a list
of Pathway IDs in the preference order.
So in this case, the receiving
client player would prefer CDN1 over CDN2.
This is the Steering Manifest
the Steering Server would provide
to the European clients,
to let them prefer CDN1.
By altering the PATHWAY-PRIORITY field
in a Steering Manifest,
a Steering Server can control
the steering policy for every client.
That's it for a quick overview
of Content Steering.
If you want a more in-depth explanation,
feel free to check out my WWDC21 talk,
Improve global streaming availability
with HLS Content Steering.
However, our journey for
supporting a more scalable
and more reliable streaming service
doesn't stop here.
Nowadays companies can access
more versatile cloud infrastructures
and tools to achieve things
unimaginable in the past,
and we have to catch up
in the leap in technology.
Let's say our streaming service provider
has grown larger this year,
and they are experimenting with a new way
to satisfy the dynamic traffic demands
of its growing user base.
They are doing it by dynamically spawning
fleets of CDN servers in real-time
to alleviate temporal traffics stresses.
For example,
it can spawn a new fleet of CDN3
and want to advertise it
to existing clients.
However the challenge here
is that the dynamically spawned CDN info
is not included
in the multivariant playlists
when existing client requested it,
because it just didn't exist.
So what can we do to tell our client
players of the emergence of a new CDN?
This is where our new Pathway Cloning
feature comes in handy.
It's a new feature
with backward compatibility
with Content Steering 1.2
introduced in WWDC21.
With Pathway Cloning,
the Steering Server can announce new CDNs
to existing clients
using a compact manifest definition.
By assuming Pathways
are structure-identical,
new Pathways can be created by copying
and modifying existing Pathways.
Let's take a look
at the structure of a Pathway.
A Pathway consists of one
or many variant streams.
Each variant stream can only be
in one and only one Pathway.
If not specified
the PATHWAY-ID attribute,
it implicitly belongs
to the default “dot” Pathway.
Each variant stream may refer to zero
or one media group for each media type,
out of audio, subtitle,
and closed-caption.
Each media group may be referenced
by multiple variant streams,
even from different Pathways.
When we clone a new Pathway
out of an existing one,
we should not only clone
its variant streams,
but also the referenced media groups,
if any.
Then, to make it a new Pathway,
we need to modify the URIs
of the variant and rendition streams
of the newly cloned Pathway.
Let's take the 6 Mbps variant stream
from the cloned Pathway for example.
Let's say this particular variant stream
has the URI as shown.
To modify it to become the URI
for the new Pathway,
the most flexible way
is to replace the full URI line in whole.
This means we need to store a full set
of URIs in the Steering Manifest
for each cloned Pathway.
However, in practice
we can usually do better than that.
It is common in the industry
to deploy streaming assets
across multiple CDNs
retaining the same URI path structure.
And assets served from the same
URI share the same URI hostname
and query parameters.
If it's the case,
we only need to store the replacement
of host and query parameters
in the manifest,
and replace the components of all cloned
URIs and we got the new Pathway.
Let's take a look at how we can define
the Pathway Clone in a Manifest object.
We added the PATHWAY-CLONES field
with an array of Pathway Clone objects.
Each Pathway Clone object defines a new
Pathway cloned from an existing Pathway.
In this example,
we have one Pathway Clone object.
The BASE-ID field specifies CDN1
to be the original Pathway to clone from.
The ID field specifies
the new Pathway ID to be CDN3.
Next, we have the URI-REPLACEMENT field
with an object of URI replacement rules.
In this example, we are using the HOST
and query parameters replacement rules,
which should replace the host part,
and insert or replace query parameters
of the stream URIs respectively.
In this case,
we are replacing the host part
to be cdn3.example.com,
and adding or setting query parameter
“foo” with value xyz,
and query parameter “bar” with value 123.
Let's try to apply the host
and parameter URI replacement
on our previous example URI.
First we have the resolved
variant stream URI
based on the multivariant playlist's URI.
In the Steering Manifest
we used HOST URI replacement rule.
So for the host part of the URI,
we replace it with cdn3.example.com,
and got the new host part for the new URI.
Then we retain the URI path component
from the cloned URI.
Finally, we apply the URI query
parameter replacement rule.
Here we replace the “foo” parameter
because it exists on the original URI.
Then we append the “bar” parameter
because it's a new parameter.
Then we have the replaced
query parameter part of the new URI.
The final result URI would be the URI
for the 6 Mbps variant stream
from the new Pathway CDN3.
We apply the same URI replacement rule
to the rest of the variants
and renditions in the cloned Pathway.
For the 3 Mbps variant stream,
we have the original URI,
and apply the host and parameter
replacement rule to get the new URI.
We do the same for the audio
and subtitle renditions.
After we apply the URI replacement rule
to all cloned variants and renditions,
we have a new Pathway
that serves from the new CDN host.
Let's take another example
and let's say the streaming provider
wants to serve their highest bandwidth
video and audio streams
from a specially tuned, fastest CDN host,
different from the rest of
the lower bitrate streams.
This is where per-stable-ID
URI replacement rule comes in handy.
In HLS, STABLE-VARIANT-ID
and STABLE-RENDITION-ID attributes
were introduced to identify
variant and rendition streams.
By setting them
in the multivariant playlist,
we can later reference each variant
or rendition stream,
by their stable ID
in the Pathway Clone object,
in the Steering Manifest,
and assign per-stream
URI replacement rules.
To define these particular special URI
replacement rules,
we need to assign stable IDs
to all the variant and rendition streams
in the multivariant playlist.
For example we assign STABLE-RENDITION-ID
"audio-en-ac3"
to the AC3 English audio,
and STABLE-VARIANT-ID "video-4k-dv"
to the 25 Mbps 4K variant stream.
Then, in the Steering Manifest,
we can add the two
flexible replacement rules
by referencing their stable IDs.
For variant streams,
we added "PER-VARIANT-URIS" field
to the "URI-REPLACEMENT" object,
with a dictionary
of STABLE-VARIANT-ID to URI records.
Here we specify to replace the URI
of the variant stream
with STABLE-VARIANT-ID
"video-4k-dv" with the following URI.
For the rendition stream,
we added "PER-RENDITION-URIS" field
to the "URI-REPLACEMENT" object,
with a dictionary of
STABLE-RENDITION-ID to URI records.
Here we specify to replace
the URI of rendition stream
with STABLE-RENDITION-ID
"audio-en-ac3" with the following URI.
Here we see that
after applying the URI replacement,
all streams are serving from the new
cdn3.exmaple.com host
except the 4K video variant
and AC3 English audio rendition,
where they have
special URI replacement rules
pointing them
to the faster.example.com host,
and with different URI path
and query components.
With Pathway Cloning, when the
streaming provider dynamically spawn
new CDN fleet, in this example, CDN3,
the steering server can add CDN3
as a Pathway Clone for existing clients
in their Steering Manifest.
It can also choose a region,
for example Europe,
to prioritize CDN3 as the primary Pathway.
When clients in Europe got
the Steering Manifest update,
they will steer their traffics
toward CDN3.
For the final part of this talk,
let's switch our focus
to the details of Steering Server,
to explain how to implement
the server logic,
with concrete examples, to steer client
player traffics for load balancing.
One way to manage and orchestrate
a swamp of client players
and apply partitioned rules
is to put every client into a bucket,
and apply the rules at the buckets level.
It's simple to implement
the bucketing at the Steering Server
without maintaining
any client session states.
When a client player requests
for the initial Steering Manifest,
it makes an HTTP GET request
at the Steering Server URI.
The server then generates a uniform random
number out of 12 possible buckets.
When returning the Steering Manifest,
the server adds the bucket number,
in this case, 7,
to the RELOAD-URI attribute,
which will be the Steering Manifest URI
for the next request
from the client player.
So that the next time the client player
request for Steering Manifest,
it will carry the bucket number
in its request parameter,
and the server can extract it and apply
steering rules based on the bucket number.
Now let's take a look
at a simple bipartition steering rule.
In this case,
we want to steer 50% traffic
to prefer CDN1
and the other 50% of the traffic to prefer CDN2.
We can write such rule
in terms of the bucket number.
If the client player's bucket number
falls in the first 6 buckets,
we return Steering Manifest
with PATHWAY-PRIORITY prefers CDN1,
and otherwise return that
with PATHWAY-PRIORITY prefers CDN2.
Since clients are assigned
to buckets uniformly,
dividing the 12 buckets into 6 buckets
can bipartition the traffics evenly.
Now let's say a new Pathway
called CDN3 is dynamically spawned.
The Steering Server can advertise it
using Pathway cloning
to clients that don’t know it from
their multivariant playlists.
One common question when
constructing a Steering Manifest
with Pathway Cloning,
is to determine the set of Pathways
that need to be included
in the PATHWAY-CLONES array.
The rule is to clone Pathways that are
not in the client's multivariant playlist.
However, without maintaining
any server side states
about the client session,
how can the Steering Server
know the set of Pathways
in the client's multivariant playlist?
One way to do it
is to include the set of Pathways
in the initial steering server URI
as a query parameter,
during the generation of
the multivariant playlist.
In this case, the multivariant playlist
contains two pathways,
CDN1 and CDN2.
Therefore, it includes them
in the SERVER-URI attribute
as a query parameter.
Then the client player
would send request to the URI,
carrying the parameters
to the steering server.
Then the steering server
can extract the parameter
as the set of Pathways
in the client's multivariant playlist.
Then it can calculate the set
of Pathways to be cloned,
by subtracting the set
of available Pathways
with the set of Pathways
in the client's multivariant playlist.
In this case,
the available Pathways are CDN1, 2, and 3,
and the Pathways in the client's
multivariant playlist are CDN1 and CDN2,
therefore,
the Pathway that needs to be included
in the PATHWAY-CLONES array is CDN3.
Let's also take a look
how the Steering Server
can change its steering rules
when there are three available Pathways.
In this case,
the server wants to partition
the client traffics evenly
across CDN1, 2, and 3.
We write this rule by returning
PATHWAY-PRIORITY that prefers CDN1
if the client's bucket number falls in
the first third of the 12 buckets,
returning PATHWAY-PRIORITY
that prefers CDN2
if the client's bucket number falls
in the second third range,
and otherwise returning
PATHWAY-PRIORITY that prefers CDN3.
This way each Pathway would serve
a third of the client traffics.
With everything we covered,
you are now fully equipped
to build your Steering Server
with your own dynamic steering rules.
Doing so can further improve
the reliability of your streaming service.
That's it for our updates
in Content Steering this year.
If you haven't done it yet,
try adopting Content Steering
as your HLS CDN fallback mechanism
as it's more versatile
and provides dynamic traffic steering.
Please also take advantage of
the new Pathway Cloning feature
to improve your service's reliability.
As usual, check out the latest IETF HLS
specification for more technical details.
And remember to utilize
our HTTP Live Streaming Tools
to validate your playlists
as you make changes.
Finally, if you have more questions
or suggestion,
feel free to reach out
at hls-interest@ietf.org.
Thank you for joining,
and have a great day.