♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello and welcome to the session
"Meet Transferable."
My name is Julia.
I am a SwiftUI engineer,
and I am excited to introduce
Transferable,
a declarative way
to support drag and drop,
copy/paste, and other
functionality in your app.
Apart from SwiftUI and
developing applications for Mac,
I'm also interested
in the story of women
in computer science.
I think it's important
that we know our heroes.
So I decided to create
a catalog application
where I can view, add, and edit
a list of the female inventors',
engineers',
and scientists' profiles.
I want this application to
seamlessly support drag and drop
of the scientists' portraits
to and from the app,
being able to use
the clipboard content
to paste interesting facts.
And for the first time,
my app can support sharing
on watchOS!
My potential users say
that they would love
to be able to share
a personality profile
from their watch.
Also, via SwiftUI, sharing is
now available on iOS and Mac,
which also got this brand-new
design for ShareSheet this year.
Under the hood,
enabling all these features
require the models
that we already have
to support being sent over
to a receiver inside our app
or even in other applications.
The profile structure
contains all the information
that we have
about a single personality.
All the profiles
packed in an archive
can be shared among friends.
We store fun facts
about the personality in strings
and even can attach videos.
And there's a great new easy way
to make all these model types
to be shared.
Meet Transferable!
It is a Swift-first declarative
way to describe how your models
can be serialized
and deserialized
for sharing and data transfer.
Today, we are going
to be talking about
what Transferable is
and what is going on behind
the scenes when we use it;
how to conform custom types;
and at the end,
I'll share some
advanced tips and tricks
that can help
to customize Transferable
to do exactly what you need.
Let's start!
Say there are
two applications running,
and the user wants to pass
some information from one app
to another via copy/paste,
ShareSheet, just drag,
or use some other app feature.
When you send something
between two different apps,
there's all this binary data
that goes across.
An important part
of sending this data
is determining
what it corresponds to.
It could be text, a video,
my favorite female engineer
profile, or whole archive.
And there's the UTType that
describes what the data is for.
Let's take a closer look at how
apps generate this binary data.
All the types that can be
shared with other apps,
or even within
a single application,
have to provide
two pieces of information:
ways to convert them
to and from binary data,
and the content type that
corresponds to the structure
of the binary data and tells the
receiver what they actually got.
The content type --
otherwise known as
uniform type identifiers --
is an Apple-specific technology
that describes identifiers
for different binary structures
as well as abstract concepts.
The identifiers form a tree,
and we can also define
custom identifiers.
For example, one for the binary
structure used by our profiles.
In order to declare
a custom identifier,
first, add its declaration
to the Info.plist file.
It is also a good idea
to add a file extension.
If the data is saved on disk,
the system will know that
your app can open that file.
Secondly, declare it in code.
To learn more about
content types,
I invite you to watch a video:
"Uniform Type Identifiers
-- A reintroduction."
Personally, I love it,
and it gives a clear idea
what are uniform type
identifiers and how to use them.
Good news is that
many standard types
already conform to Transferable;
for example, string, data, URL,
attributed string, image.
You need only a couple of lines
of code to paste fun facts
to a profile with the new
SwiftUI paste button interface,
support dragging images
from a view,
or receiving a dropped image
from Finder or other apps.
Using the br and-new ShareLink,
we can now implement sharing
experience from the watch.
We covered the basics,
and now you have an idea
how to use Transferable
and what it is.
Let's see how to add
Transferable conformance
to the models
in our application.
As I mentioned earlier, there
are four model types in our app
that are going to be shared.
One of them -- string -- already
conforms to Transferable;
we don't need to do
anything more.
But what about the single
profile, ProfilesArchive,
and the video that
I want to share as well?
To conform a type
to Transferable,
there's only one property
to implement:
TransferRepresentation.
It describes how the model
is going to get transferred.
There are three important
representations to be aware of:
CodableRepresentation,
DataRepresentation,
and FileRepresentation.
We'll talk about each of them.
But first, meet our central
model, Profile structure.
It has an id, a name, a bio,
maybe some fun facts,
a portrait, and a video.
It already conforms to Codable.
Because of that, we can include
CodableRepresentation
in our Transferable conformance.
Codable representation
uses an encoder
to convert the profile
into binary data,
and a decoder
to convert it back.
By default, it uses JSON,
but you can also provide
your own encoder/decoder pair.
To learn more
about the Codable protocol
and how encoders
and decoders work,
I invite you to watch a WWDC
session where this protocol
was first introduced:
"Data you can trust."
Back to our profile.
The only thing Codable requires
is knowing
the desired content type.
Since this is going to be
a custom format,
we will use a custom declared
uniform type identifier.
After adding the profile
content type, we're good to go.
Profile now conforms
to Transferable!
Now, let's take look at another
case: ProfilesArchive.
It already supports
converting to CSV data.
I can export the list of
the women profiles in CSV files
and then share with friends or
import it on another computer.
The archive can be converted
to and from data,
and it means that we can use
the DataRepresentation.
If we peek inside, we'll see
that DataRepresentation uses
the conversion functions
to directly create
binary representation
and to reconstruct
the value for the receiver.
This is how easy it is
to conform to Transferable
using the DataRepresentation.
All it takes is calling the two
functions that we already have:
the initializer
and the converter to CSV.
If a personality profile
has a video attached,
I want to be able to drag
or share it as well.
But videos can be large;
I don't want to load it
into memory.
This is where
FileRepresentation comes in.
And again,
if we lift the curtain,
we'll see that
FileRepresentation
passes the provided URL
to the receiver
and uses it to reconstruct
the Transferable item for them.
FileRepresentation
allows us to share items
backed by a binary
representation written to disk:
file.
Let's summarize.
If you want to pick just
a single representation
for a simple use case,
first check if the model
has the Codable conformance
and doesn't have any specific
binary format requirements.
Use CodableRepresentation
if it is the case.
If not, check if it is stored
in memory or on disk.
DataRepresentation
works best for the former,
and FileRepresetnation
for the latter.
Transferable is meant to cover
not only simple use cases,
but also complex ones.
And most of the time,
with just a few lines of code.
See it for yourself!
Previously, we have added
Transferable conformance
to the profile,
but let's go further.
When the profile is copied
to the pasteboard
and pasted into any text field,
I want to paste
the profile's name.
This means we need to add
another representation.
ProxyRepresentation allows
other Transferable types
to represent our model.
One line, and Profile can be
pasted as text.
Notice that I added
the ProxyRepresentation
after Codable;
the order is important.
The receiver will use
the first representation
with the content type
they support.
If the receiver is aware of
our custom content type Profile,
they should use it.
If not, but they support text,
let them use the
ProxyRepresentation instead.
Now, Profile supports both
encoder/decoder conversions
and a conversion to text.
The ProxyRepresentation
in this case
describes only
exporting to text,
but not reconstructing
the profile from it.
Any representation can describe
both conversions, or just one.
Now, when we know about
ProxyRepresentations,
do we really need
the FileRepresentation
for the video?
We could have proxy with a URL.
The difference is subtle.
FileRepresentation is intended
to work with the URLs
written to disk,
and ensure receivers'
access to this file or its copy
by granting a temporary
sandbox extension.
ProxyRepresentation
treats URLs the same way
as any other Transferable items,
like strings.
It doesn't have any
of these additional capabilities
that we need for files.
It means that we can have both.
The first one,
FileRepresentation,
allows the receiver
to access the movie file
with its contents.
The second one will work
when I paste the copied video
in a text field.
So the URL is treated
very differently
by file and proxy
representations.
In the first case, the actual
payload is the asset on disk,
and in the second, the payload
is the URL structure itself
that can point
to a remote website.
Another model that I'd like to
upgrade is the ProfilesArchive.
There are cases when it doesn't
support converting to CSV,
and I'd like to reflect that
in code.
Let's see.
We add a Boolean property that
tells us if we can export to CSV
and conversion functions
to and from data.
To express this idea in code,
we can use .exportingCondition.
If given archive
doesn't support CSV,
it won't be exported
in this format.
With this API,
you can even build
custom TransferRepresentation,
just like custom Views
in SwiftUI.
The only requirement is
to provide the body property
where you can have
other representations
configured the way you need.
It is useful
if you want to reuse
a combination of
representations,
or you have some
private data representation
that you don't want
to expose publicly.
Transferable helped me to
quickly build this application
with all the functionality
that I wanted to have.
I hope it is going to help you
building feature-rich apps
in less time than ever before.
Thank you for joining me
for this session
and keep building amazing apps!
♪