♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hao Tang: Hi, my name is Hao.
I'm an engineer
on the Object Capture team.
Today, my colleague Risa and I
will be showing you how to use
the Object Capture API
and RealityKit
to create 3D models
of real-world objects
and bring them into AR.
Let's get started.
First, I'll give you a recap
of Object Capture,
which we launched
as a RealityKit API
on macOS last year.
Then, I'll introduce you
to a couple of camera
enhancements in ARKit,
which allow you to capture
high-res photos of your object
and can help you
better integrate
Object Capture
into your AR applications.
After that, I will go through
the best practice guidelines
of Object Capture
so you can continue
to make the best
out of this technology.
In the last section,
Risa will take you through
an end-to-end workflow with
Object Capture in RealityKit
and demonstrate how
you can bring real-world objects
into an AR experience.
Let's start with a quick recap
of Object Capture.
Object Capture
is a computer vision technology
that you can leverage
to easily turn images
of real-world objects
into detailed 3D models.
You begin by taking photos
of your object
from various angles
with an iPhone, iPad, or DSLR.
Then, you copy
those photos to a Mac
which supports Object Capture.
Using the Photogrammetry API,
RealityKit can transform
your photos into a 3D model
in just a few minutes.
The output model includes both
a geometric mesh
as well as various material
maps, including textures,
that are automatically applied
to your model.
For more details
of the Object Capture API,
I would highly recommend
that you watch
last year's WWDC session
on Object Capture.
Many developers have created
amazing 3D capture apps
using Object Capture:
Unity, Cinema4D, Qlone,
PolyCam, PhotoCatch,
just to name a few.
In addition to this,
we have beautiful-looking models
that were created
using this API.
Here's a few models that
were created by Ethan Saadia
using the power
of Object Capture
within the PhotoCatch app.
And our friend Mikko Haapoja
from Shopify also generated
a bunch of great-looking
3D models using this API.
The detailed quality
of the output 3D models
you get with Object Capture is
highly beneficial in e-commerce.
Here's the GOAT app,
for example,
that lets you try on a variety
of shoes on your feet.
All of these shoe models
have been created
with the Object Capture API
which has been designed
to capture the finest level
of detail on them.
This can go a long way
in helping you
with your purchase decision
on a product,
or even try out an accurate fit
for an object in your space.
For example, the Plant Story app
lets you preview
real-looking 3D models
of various plants in your space,
all of which have been created
with Object Capture.
This can help you get a sense
of how much space
you may need for a plant,
or simply see them in your space
in realistic detail.
Speaking about realism,
were you able to spot
the real plant in this video?
Yes, it's the one
in the white planter
on the left-most corner
of the table.
We are very thrilled
to see such a stunning
and widespread use
of the Object Capture API
since its launch in 2021.
Now, let's talk about some
camera enhancements in ARKit,
which will greatly help
the quality of reconstruction
with Object Capture.
A great Object Capture
experience starts
with taking good photos
of objects from all sides.
To this end, you can use
any high-resolution camera,
like the iPhone or iPad,
or even a DSLR
or mirrorless camera.
If you use the Camera app
on your iPhone or iPad,
you can take high-quality
photos with depth
and gravity information which
lets the Object Capture API
automatically recover
the real-world scale
and orientation of the object.
In addition to that,
if you use an iPhone or iPad,
you can take advantage
of ARKit's tracking capabilities
to overlay a 3D guidance UI
on top of the model
to get good coverage
of the object from all sides.
Another important thing to note
is that the higher the image
resolution from your capture,
the better the quality
of the 3D model
that Object Capture can produce.
To that end,
with this year's ARKit release
we are introducing a brand-new
high-resolution
background photos API.
This API lets you capture photos
at native camera resolution
while you are still running
an ARSession.
It allows you to use your 3D
UI overlays on top of the object
while taking full advantage
of the camera sensor on device.
On an iPhone 13, that means
the full 12 megapixels
native resolution
of the Wide camera.
This API is nonintrusive.
It does not interrupt
the continuous video stream
of the current ARSession,
so your app will continue
to provide a smooth
AR experience for your users.
In addition, ARKit makes
EXIF metadata available
in the photos,
which allows your app
to read useful information
about white balance, exposure,
and other settings that can be
valuable for post-processing.
ARKit makes it extremely easy
to use this new API in your app.
You can simply query
a video format
that supports high-resolution
frame capturing
on ARWorldTrackingConfguration,
and if successful,
set the new video format
and run the ARSession.
When it comes to capturing
a high-res photo,
simply call ARSession's new
captureHighResolutionFrame API
function,
which will return to you
a high-res photo
via a completion handler
asynchronously.
It is that simple.
We have also recognized
that there are use cases
where you may prefer manual
control over the camera settings
such as focus, exposure,
or white balance.
So we are providing you
with a convenient way
to access the underlying
AVCaptureDevice directly
and change its properties
for fine-grained camera control.
As shown in this code example,
simply call
configurableCaptureDevice
ForPrimaryCamera
on your
ARWorldTrackingConfiguration
to get access to the underlying
AVCaptureDevice.
For more details
on these enhancements,
I highly recommend
you to check out
the "Discover ARKit 6 session"
from this year's WWDC.
Now, let's go through
some best practice guidelines
with Object Capture.
First things first;
we need to choose an object
with the right characteristics
for Object Capture.
A good object has
adequate texture on its surface.
If some regions of the object
are textureless or transparent,
the details in those regions
may not be reconstructed well.
A good object should also be
free of glare and reflections.
If the object does not have
a matte surface,
you can try to reduce
the specular on it
using diffuse lighting.
If you would like
to flip over the object
to capture its bottom,
please ensure
that your object stays rigid.
In other words, it should not
change its shape when flipped.
And lastly, a good object
can contain fine structure
to some degree,
but you will need to use
a high-resolution camera
and take close-up photos
to recover the fine detail
of the object.
The next important thing
is setting up an ideal
capture environment.
You will want to make sure
that your capture environment
has good, even,
and diffuse lighting.
It is important to ensure
a stable background
and have sufficient space
around the object.
If your room is dark,
you can make use
of a well-lit turntable.
Next, we'll look
at some guidelines
for capturing good photos
of your object, which in turn,
will ensure that you get
a good quality 3D model
from Object Capture.
As an example, I'll show you
how my colleague Maunesh
used his iPhone
to capture the images
of a beautiful pirate ship
that was created
by our beloved ARKit engineer,
Christian Lipski.
Maunesh begins
by placing the pirate ship
in the middle of a clean table.
This makes the ship
clearly stand out in the photos.
He holds his iPhone steadily
with two hands.
As he circles
around the ship slowly,
he captures photos
at various heights.
He makes sure that the ship
is large enough in the center
of the camera's field of view
so that he can capture
the maximum amount of detail.
He also makes sure
that he always maintains
a high degree of overlap
between any two adjacent photos.
After he takes
a good number of photos --
about 80 in this case --
he flips the ship on its side,
so that he can also
reconstruct its bottom.
He continues to capture
about 20 more photos of the ship
in a flipped orientation.
One thing to note is that
he is holding the iPhone
in landscape mode.
This is because
he is capturing a long object,
and in this case,
the landscape mode helps him
capture maximum amount of detail
of the object.
However, he may need to use
the iPhone in portrait mode
if he were to capture
a tall object instead.
That's it!
The final step in the process
is to copy those photos
onto a Mac and process them
using the Object Capture API.
You can choose from
four different detail levels,
which are optimized
for different use cases.
The reduced and medium detail
levels are optimized
for use in web-based
and mobile experiences,
such as viewing 3D content
in AR QuickLook.
The reconstructed models
for those detail levels
have fewer triangles
and material channels,
thereby consuming
less memory.
The full and raw detail levels
are intended for high-end
interactive use cases,
such as in computer games
or post-production workflows.
These models contain
the highest geometric detail
and give you the flexibility
to choose between baked
and unbaked materials,
but they require more memory
to reconstruct.
It is important to select
the right output level
depending on your use case.
For our pirate ship, we chose
the medium detail level,
which only took a few minutes
to process it on an M1 Mac.
The output 3D model
looked so stunning
that we actually put together
an animated clip
of the pirate ship
sailing in high seas.
And that's the power
of Object Capture for you!
Ahoy!
Now I'll hand it off to Risa,
who will be walking you through
an end-to-end workflow
with Object Capture
in RealityKit.
Risa Yoneyama: Thanks, Hao.
Now that we have gone over
the Object Capture API,
I am excited to go over an
end-to-end developer workflow,
to bring your real-life object
into AR using RealityKit.
We'll walk through
each step in detail
with an example workflow,
so let's dive
straight into a demo.
My colleague Zach
is an occasional woodworker
and recently built six oversized
wooden chess pieces --
one for each unique piece.
Looking at these chess pieces,
I'm inspired to create
an interactive AR chess game.
Previously,
you'd need a 3D modeler
and material specialist
to create high-quality 3D models
of real-world objects.
Now, with the
Object Capture API,
we can simply capture
these chess pieces directly
and bring them
into augmented reality.
Let's start off
by capturing the rook.
My colleague Bryan will be using
this professional setup,
keeping in mind
the best practices we covered
in the previous section.
In this case, Bryan is placing
the rook on this turntable
with some professional lighting
to help avoid harsh shadows
in the final output.
You can also use the iPhone
camera with a turntable,
which provides you with
automatic scale estimation
and gravity vector information
in your output USDZ.
Please refer to the
Object Capture session from 2021
for more details on this.
Of course, if you do not have
an elaborate setup
like Bryan does here, you can
also simply hold your iOS device
and walk around your object
to capture the images.
Now that we have all the photos
of our rook piece,
I'm going to transfer these
over to the Mac.
I'll process these photos
using the
PhotogrammetrySession API
that was introduced in 2021.
Per the best practice
guidelines,
I'll use the reduced detail
level to reconstruct,
as we want to make sure
our AR app performs well.
The final output of the API
will be a USDZ file type model.
Here is our final output
of the rook chess piece
I just reconstructed.
To save us some time,
I've gone ahead and captured
the other five pieces
ahead of time.
You may be wondering
how we will create a chess game
with only one color scheme
for the chess pieces.
Let's duplicate
our six unique pieces
and drag them
into Reality Converter.
I have inverted the colors
in the original texture
and replaced the duplicated set
with this new inverted texture.
This way, we can have
a lighter version
and a darker version
of the chess pieces,
one for each player.
I'll be exporting the models
with the compressed textures
option turned on
in the Export menu.
This will help decrease
the memory footprint
of the textures.
Now that we have
our full set of chess pieces,
we are ready to bring the models
into our Xcode project.
I've created a chessboard
using RealityKit
by scaling down
primitive cubes on the y-axis
and alternating the colors
between black and white.
Here are all the chess pieces
I reconstructed,
laid out on the chessboard.
This is already exciting to see
our real-life objects
in our application,
but let's start adding
some features
to make it an actual
interactive game.
Throughout
this part of the demo,
I would like to showcase several
different existing technologies,
so we can provide examples
of how you might want
to combine the technologies to
accomplish your desired output.
As we'll be going over
some practical use cases
of advanced topics
in RealityKit,
I would recommend checking out
the RealityKit sessions
from 2021
if you are not already
familiar with the APIs.
I want to start by adding
a start-up animation
when we first launch
the application.
I am imagining an animation
where the checker tiles
slowly fall into place
from slightly above
its final position,
all while the chess pieces
also translate in together.
To replicate
this effect in code,
all it takes is two steps.
The first step is to translate
both our entities
up along the y-axis,
while also uniformly
scaling down the chess piece.
The second step and final step
is to animate both entities
back to its original transform.
The code for this
is quite simple.
I'll start by iterating through
the checker tile entities.
For each entity,
I'll save the current transform
of the checker tile
as this will be the final
position it lands on.
Then, I'll move each square up
10 cm on the y-axis.
We can now take advantage
of the move function
to animate this back
to our original transform.
I also happen to know
that this border USDZ
that outlines the checkerboard
has a built-in animation.
We can use the playAnimation API
to start the animation
simultaneously.
I've added the exact same
animation to the chess pieces
but also modifying the scale
as they translate.
And here we have it:
a simple startup animation
with just a few lines of code.
However, we won't actually
be able to play chess
without the ability
to move the chess pieces.
Let's work on that next.
Before we can start moving
the chess pieces,
we'll need to be able
to select one.
I've already added
a UITapGestureRecognizer
to my ARView.
When the users taps
a specific location,
we will define a ray that starts
from the camera origin
and goes through that 2D point.
We can then perform a raycast
with that ray into the 3D scene
to see if we hit any entities.
I've specified my chess piece
collision group as a mask
as I know I only want to be able
to select the chess pieces
in my scene.
Be mindful that
the raycast function
will ignore all entities
that do not have
a CollisionComponent.
If we do find a chess piece,
we can finally select it.
Now that we know
which piece is selected,
I want to add an effect
that will make the piece
look like it is glowing.
We can leverage custom materials
to achieve this;
more specifically,
surface shaders.
Surface shaders allow you
to calculate
or specify material parameters
through Metal,
which then gets called by
RealityKit's fragment shader
once per each pixel.
We can write a surface shader
that looks like
this fire effect in Metal.
Then apply a custom material,
with this surface shader
to our rectangular prism
to have the shader affect
how our entity looks.
Let's write some code
to achieve our desired effect.
I've already added
a noise texture to the project
to use in this surface shader.
We'll sample the texture twice,
once for the overall
shape of the effect
and another for detail.
We then take the RGB value
and remap it to look
just the way we want.
Then, with the processed value
we just extracted,
we'll calculate the opacity
of the sample point
by comparing its y-position
with the image value.
To give the effect
some movement,
we'll be moving through
the y-axis of the texture
as a function of time.
Additionally, we will also
use the facing angle
of each sample point
in conjunction
with the viewing direction
of the camera
to fade the effect at the sides.
This will soften the edges
and hide the regular nature
of the underlying model.
Finally, we'll set the color
and opacity we just calculated
using the surface
parameter functions.
And here are the chess pieces
with the selection shader
applied to it.
They really do look like they
are glowing from the inside.
Now, if we combine that
with three separate
translation animations,
that will result in something
that looks like this.
With the functionality to move
chess pieces implemented,
we'll also be able to capture
the opponent's pieces.
Just like surface shaders,
geometry modifiers
can be implemented
using custom materials.
They are a very powerful tool,
as you can change vertex data
such as position, normals,
texture coordinates, and more.
Each of these Metal functions
will be called once per vertex
by RealityKit's vertex shader.
These modifications
are purely transient
and do not affect
the vertex information
of the actual entity.
I'm thinking we could add
a fun geometry modifier
to squash the pieces
when they are captured.
I have this property
on my chess piece
called capturedProgress
to represent the progress
of the capturing animation
from 0 to 1.
Since capturing
is a user-initiated action,
we somehow need to tell
the geometry modifier
when to start its animation.
The good thing is
you can do this
by setting the custom property
on a customMaterial.
This allows data to be shared
between the CPU and the GPU.
We will specifically use
the custom value property here
and pass the animation progress
to the geometry modifier.
To extract the animation
progress from the Metal side,
we can use the custom parameter
on uniforms.
Since I want to scale
the object vertically,
as if it is being squashed
by another piece,
we will set the scale axis
as the y-direction.
To add some complexity
to the animation,
we will also change
the geometry in the x-axis
to create a wave effect.
The offset of the vertex
can be set using the
set_model_position_ offset
function.
Here is the final product
of our geometry modifier.
You can see that it scales up
a bit before collapsing down,
while being stretched vertically
along the x-axis.
As a chess novice myself,
I thought it might be helpful
to add a feature
to indicate where
your selected piece can move to
to help me learn the game.
Since the checker pieces
are each individual entities
with their own Model Component,
I can apply a pulsing effect
using a surface shader
to potential moves
to distinguish them from others.
Next, I'll add a post-processing
effect called "bloom"
to accentuate
the effect even more.
Again, we're using
the custom parameter here
we used in the surface shader
for the glow effect.
In this case, we are passing in
a Boolean from the CPU side
to our Metal surface shader.
If this checker
is a possible move,
I want to add a pulsing effect
by changing the color.
We'll specifically add the pulse
to the emissive color here.
Lastly, I'll add the bloom
effect to the entire view.
Bloom is a post-processing
effect that produces
feathers of light from
the borders of bright areas.
We can accomplish this effect
by taking advantage
of the render callbacks property
on ARView.
We will write the bloom effect
using the already built-in
Metal performance shader
functions.
Next, we'll simply set the
renderCallbacks.postProcess
closure as our bloom function
we just defined.
When we pulse our checkers,
we are pulsing to a white color
which will now be
further emphasized
with the bloom effect.
With the surface shader
and bloom effect together,
we can see exactly where
we can move our pieces to.
Finally, let's combine
everything we have together
to see our real-life
chess pieces come to life
in our AR app.
We can see how
all the features we added
look in our environment.
For your convenience
we have linked
the Capture Chess sample project
to the session resources.
Please download it
and try it out for yourself
to see it in your environment.
And it's that simple.
From capture to reconstruction
of the oversized chess pieces,
then into
our augmented reality app.
We've covered a lot
in this session today
so let's summarize
some of the key points.
We first started off by
recapping the Object Capture API
that we announced in 2021.
We then went over
a new API in ARKit
that enables
capturing photos on-demand
at native camera resolution
during an active ARSession.
To help you get the most out of
the Object Capture technology,
we listed types of objects that
are suited for reconstruction,
ideal environments
to get high-quality images,
and the recommended
flow to follow
while capturing your object.
For the latter part
of this session,
we walked through an example
end-to-end developer workflow.
We captured photos
of the oversized chess pieces
and used the images as input
to the PhotogrammetrySession API
to create 3D models of them.
Then, we imported the models
into Reality Converter
to replace some textures.
And finally, we slowly
built up our chess game
to see our chess pieces
in action in AR.
And that's it
for our session today.
Thank you so much for watching.
Ahoy!
♪