♪ ♪
Brady Eidson: Hello.
My name is Brady Eidson.
I'm an engineer
on the WebKit Architecture team.
I am thrilled to introduce you
to Web Push in Safari.
Web Push lets you
remotely send notifications
to your web application's users.
Here, a notification displays
from webkit.org
in the upper-right of the screen.
Clicking the notification opens
a WebKit blog post in a new window.
Before I get into other details
on how this works,
I want to answer a few questions
up front I know many of you will have.
Web Push is supported in Mac Safari
beginning with macOS Ventura.
And Web Push will be coming
to iOS and iPadOS next year.
Apple's Safari Push Notifications
have been an option
for reaching Mac Safari users
for quite a while.
While it will continue to work,
today I'm happy to announce
that we have added support for Web Push,
and this really is Web Push!
The same combination
of various web standards
as implemented in other browsers.
We'll go over those standards
more later, but…
the most important takeaway
is that if you've coded
your application to web standards,
you won't need to make any changes
for it to work in Safari.
Of course, if you exclude Safari
through browser detection,
then you have some work ahead of you.
Now would be a great time to switch from
browser detection to feature detection,
which has always been the best practice.
We're using the same
Apple Push Notification service
that powers native push
on all Macs and iOS devices,
but no Apple Developer account
is required to reach Safari users.
We are using new
end point URLs for Web Push,
which brings up another thing you might be
doing to unintentionally exclude Safari.
If you tightly manage
push end points on your server,
make sure you allow URLs
from any subdomain of push.apple.com.
Moving beyond answers
to those important questions,
let's get into more detail.
First, we'll look at
the Web Push experience in Safari
from a user's perspective.
Then we'll cover the entire Web Push flow,
from asking for permission
to handling a click on an entry
in Notification Center.
Finally, we'll see what it takes to add
Web Push to an existing web app.
But first, the Mac Safari user experience.
And I can think of no better way
to cover that than with a demo.
Here's Safari on macOS Ventura.
I have webkit.org
open in this browser tab.
I need to keep up-to-date
with the WebKit open source project,
and Web Push is a great way to do that.
webkit.org is not allowed
to request permission to push
without the user asking
with a user gesture.
So I'll click this bell-shaped button here
to subscribe for notifications.
What you see here is
the system notifications prompt–
the same one you'd see for
any other application.
In this case,
it's on behalf of webkit.org.
I will click "allow," and I'm all set.
webkit.org is giving me the option
to be notified about new blog posts
as well as new commits
to the source code repository.
I know being notified for every commit
will distract me from important work,
but I absolutely want to be
notified about new blog posts.
So I'll check that box now.
Coincidentally, somebody must've
just published the WebKit blog post
about Web Push.
This notification looks
just like any other
and is attributed to webkit.org.
I can click it to activate,
and there is the blog post,
open in Safari.
Once a user has
granted permissions to a website,
they maintain control
over that permission.
As a macOS user, I'm used
to managing Notification preferences
inside System Settings,
and that's where I can go
to configure webkit.org's notifications.
The same rich configuration
as I'd find for any other app or service.
As a Safari user,
I'm used to managing website settings
from inside Safari preferences.
I can also go there to turn
webkit.org's permissions on or off.
And that's how Web Push works
for users in Mac Safari.
Before we move on, I want to reiterate
a few things covered in that demo.
First, we don't want users
to be spammed by subscription requests
they haven't asked for.
So a website may only request
a push subscription
in response to a mouse click
or a keystroke.
Once a website has permission
to show notifications to the user,
the user controls that permission.
They can choose to manage it in
Safari's preferences or System Settings.
And the setting will stay in sync
if they happen to manage it in both.
Finally, if you provide notifications
for different types of events,
it is a best practice to provide
fine-grained controls
for notification types
within your web app,
just like other apps do.
Now that you've seen Web Push in action,
let's dig in to what's happening
at each step.
Some of you are already
intimately familiar with this.
But for those of you new to Web Push,
I'll go step by step,
referring you to the relevant standards
and documentation along the way.
The first thing that happens is a user
visits your website in a browser tab.
Here's webkit.org open in Safari.
Since it is open in a tab,
it can install a Service Worker.
A Service Worker is
a unit of JavaScript that operates
on behalf of an entire domain, separate
from a currently open browser tab.
Once the Service Worker script
is installed,
your web app is eligible
to request a push subscription.
As already mentioned, this request
must be tied to a user gesture.
webkit.org requests permission
when clicking this bell-shaped button,
which fulfills
the user gesture requirement.
When your site asks
for a push subscription,
the user sees this system prompt.
Here is where they can make the final call
on granting your website
this powerful ability.
It is possible
the user might deny the request.
Your JavaScript should be
prepared to handle that.
But assuming the user grants permission,
your JavaScript gets back
a PushSubscription object.
This includes everything your server needs
to send a push message
to this user in this browser.
Information like
the exact URL end point to use.
You send this PushSubscription
payload back to your server
in whatever manner
works best for your web app.
Many popular server packages have
Web Push support to manage subscriptions,
or you can roll your own.
The same pertains to how and when
to actually send a push message
to the URL end points
your server knows about.
I can't tell you when to do so.
That's up to you and your website.
But once you've decided
to send that push message,
I can help with what happens next.
Remember how push requires
an installed Service Worker?
Once your server has sent
a push message and Safari receives it,
Safari wakes up your Service Worker
and sends it a JavaScript push event.
Showing a notification to the user
in Notification Center
is a requirement
while handling the push event.
Receiving the push event
and displaying the notification happens
if your website is currently open
in a browser tab.
It also happens if your website is
not currently open in a browser tab.
In the case of Safari on macOS Ventura,
this happens even if Safari
is not currently running.
The final step: If your user clicks
on that notification,
a notificationclick event is sent
to your Service Worker
so it can respond appropriately.
For example, by opening a new window
to the URL associated
with that notification.
With that understanding
of the Web Push flow under our belt,
it's time to get into even more detail
by actually adding Web Push support
to an existing web app.
Besides webkit.org,
Browser Pets is the most
mission critical internal tool
for the Safari and WebKit teams.
Keeping everyone in the department
up-to-date on their favorite WebKittens
and Pups on Safari has always been
the mission statement of Browser Pets,
and Web Push has made that
easier than ever.
Our internal BrowserPets domain
already had a ServiceWorker script
registered to speed up page loads
and synchronize between multiple tabs.
At a high level, a ServiceWorker script
looks a lot like this.
When an engineer visits
the Browser Pets page in a tab,
this JavaScript excerpt either determines
if the Service Worker script
has already been registered,
or registers it if necessary.
Notice we're practicing
feature detection here,
previously mentioned as a best practice.
With the Service Worker prerequisite
taken care of,
we're ready to subscribe for push.
Remember, you cannot request
a push subscription
without an explicit user gesture.
Running this script in response
to a button's onclick handler
is one of many ways
to satisfy that requirement.
Once the user clicks that button,
here's code to request
a push subscription.
I'll go into each of these points
in more detail.
First, we need to configure
the request for a push subscription.
An important bit for that is
the public key our server uses
to identify themselves
to Apple's push servers.
Here we use the standard technology
called VAPID, the same as other browsers.
I won't go over the sometimes
complex details of VAPID here,
but there are resources on the web
to help you
with the best solution
for your server's setup.
With the VAPID key set, we're ready
to configure the subscription request.
Notice we are explicitly stating
that we promise to always
make pushes user visible.
While the standard
for the JavaScript Push API
optionally accommodates
silent JavaScript runtime
in response to a push,
most browsers do not support that.
Safari does not support that.
And like most websites,
Browser Pets does not need that.
Then we request permission to push.
This line of JavaScript results
in the permission prompt
for the user to either approve or reject.
Assuming the user grants permission–
which all Safari team members do
for Browser Pets–
this gives us a PushSubscription object
with the details on how to reach
this user in their browser.
Things like the URL end point
and the key used to encrypt
the push message for transit.
Finally, we need to send
all of those details to our server.
As mentioned before,
the specifics of this will vary
based on your exact application.
Our BrowserPets server uses WordPress,
which already has
a few plugins to support
standard Web Push.
It's likely you'll find the same is true
for your backend,
and there are resources on the web
to help find the right solution
for just about any setup.
Now we need to go back
to our Service Worker JavaScript code.
It will need to handle a few new events,
starting with the push event.
When a push message makes its way from
the Browser Pets server to this browser,
this Service Worker has
a push event sent to it.
That event contains
a PushMessageData object
which has multiple ways of accessing
the data sent by your server.
We use the JSON accessor here.
Remember how when we subscribed for push,
our JavaScript promised
they would always be user visible?
That means we must always
show a platform native notification
in response to each push.
It is best to do this as early as possible
in your push event handler.
We're pulling everything
we need out of that JSON blob
to configure the notification,
including setting up an action with a URL.
That will come in handy in just a moment.
After the notification is shown,
we need to handle the user clicking on it.
One more event
for our Service Worker script to handle.
In this notificationclick handler,
BrowserPets will take the URL
from the notification that was clicked
to open a new window.
Take note: This is a very common pattern.
That's all the JavaScript
we need to write to support Web Push.
Of course, it's best to have
some help while developing.
As usual,
that's where Web Inspector comes in.
In addition to helping debug
your website open in a browser tab,
Web Inspector can also inspect
Service Worker instances
and set breakpoints on event handlers.
All of this together will let you
inspect and debug the JavaScript
that subscribes for push
as well as the service worker code
that handles the push event
and notification events.
Additionally,
the Apple Push Notification servers
will give you human readable errors
if something goes wrong
when you attempt
to publish a push message.
Check out the links associated with
this session for further documentation.
I'd also like to get into more detail
on a few points that came up
while writing that code,
with direct regards
to user privacy and power usage.
Importantly–and this is
not the first time I've said this–
subscribing for push requires
a user gesture.
As with other privileged features
of the web platform,
it's the right thing for user trust
to require that the user actually asked
to enable Web Push.
As mentioned when I showed you the code
on how to request a push subscription,
you must promise
that pushes will be user visible.
Handling a push event is not
an invitation for your JavaScript
to get silent background runtime.
Doing so would violate both a user's trust
and a user's battery life.
When handling a push event,
you are in fact required
to post a notification
to Notification Center.
Other browsers all have countermeasures
against violating the promise
to make pushes user visible,
and so does Safari.
In the beta build of macOS Ventura,
after three push events
where you fail to post a notification
in a timely manner,
your site's push subscription
will be revoked.
You will need to go through
the permission workflow again.
That's all.
We're genuinely proud to support Web Push
and excited that any site can use it,
no Apple Developer account required.
As long as you've coded to the standards
and use feature detection,
so you don't unwittingly exclude Safari,
your users will already get
the benefit of Web Push
in Safari 16 on macOS Ventura.
As usual, we've added tons of other
new stuff to Safari and WebKit this year,
and I hope you'll check out
that session to learn more.
Thank you for watching.
I hope you have a great rest of WWDC 2022.