[spacey music]
Conrad: I'm Conrad Carlen, and today,
I'll be talking about what's new
in PDFKit.
Here's our agenda.
First a quick review of PDFKit,
and then, look at what's new,
including Live text and forms,
a new way to make PDF pages from images,
and, finally, overlay views.
Let's start with a quick refresher
on how PDFKit works.
PDFKit is a full-featured framework
that helps your app view,
edit, and write PDF files.
It's available on iOS, macOS,
and Mac Catalyst,
and it can also be used in SwiftUI
by way of UIViewRepresentable,
a wrapper that lets you integrate
UI views into your app.
PDFKit consists of 4 core classes
that cover most of the functionality
you'll need in your app.
PDFView is the widget
that you include in your layout
using SwiftUI or Interface Builder.
It displays the content of a PDF document
and lets people navigate,
set zoom level,
and copy text to the Pasteboard.
PDFDocument represents a PDF file.
It's not common to subclass PDFDocument,
but you will always use one.
It's the root of the PDF object graph,
or the trunk of the tree.
You can't have a tree
without one of these.
Each document contains one
or more PDFPage objects.
Pages render content and store resources
like fonts and images
that are unique to that page.
At the leaves of our object graph
are PDFAnnotations.
These are optional.
Whereas the content of a PDFPage
is not intended to be edited,
annotations are interactive
by nature and often editable.
Each of these objects will play a role
in what I'll cover today.
To learn more about the fundamentals
of PDFKit,
check out the great presentation
"Introducing PDFKit" in the link below.
Now, let's talk about new features
introduced in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura.
PDFKit now supports Live Text.
It's different than in Photos,
where the text
is often a small amount
that you can tap to copy.
Unlike with photos, with a PDF,
if you see text, it generally is text,
and people expect it to behave as such
without doing anything special.
Now, with Live Text,
you can select and search
text in a PDF document like this one.
It's just a scanned bitmap,
with no text at all.
Of course, PDFs can have many pages.
You wouldn't want to grind through OCR
on all the pages of a PDF document
when you open it,
so PDFKit does it on demand,
as you interact with each page,
if you interact with it.
OCR is done in place, so there's no need
to make a copy of the document.
And, if you choose to save text
for the whole document,
there's an option to do so when saving.
In addition to live text,
PDFKit has improved form handling.
Documents that contain form fields
are automatically recognized,
even if they don't contain
built-in text fields.
You can tab through these text fields
and enter text,
just like you would expect.
Next, let's talk about a new API
for creating PDF pages from images.
In iOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
there's a new, flexible API
that lets your app create PDF pages
using images as inputs.
Your app supplies images using CGImageRef.
PDFKit takes the CGImageRef
that you provide and compresses it
using high-quality JPEG encoding.
Because CGImageRef is
a native data type in CoreGraphics,
additional conversions are unnecessary.
There are several options that help you
handle the most common cases.
MediaBox specifies the size of the page.
You can choose to fit the image exactly,
or choose a paper size, like Letter.
Rotation lets you specify
portrait or landscape orientation.
UpscaleIfSmaller.
By default,
if the image is larger than the MediaBox,
the image is downscaled to fit.
If UpscaleIfSmaller is specified,
that still applies,
but, if the image is small,
it will be upscaled to fill the page.
And now, to answer a question
that many of you have asked--
"How can I draw on PDF pages
using PencilKit?"--
the answer is to use an overlay view.
In the past, the only way to do
additional drawing on PDFs
was to subclass PDFPage
and override the drawing method,
or by using custom PDF annotations.
But starting in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
it's now possible
to overlay your own view
on top of each PDF page.
This allows your app to create
live, fully interactive views
that appear on top of PDF pages.
Here are the 3 things you need
to know about overlaying views.
First, you'll use a new protocol
to install your overlay view
on a PDF page.
When it comes time to save, you'll need
to incorporate your content into the PDF.
And, speaking of saving, we'll cover
some best practices
when saving a PDF document.
Installing overlay views
on PDF Pages is straightforward.
Because PDFs can contain hundreds,
if not thousands, of pages,
there's no way you want to create views
for all of those pages when opening a PDF.
And what if the user scrolls
back and forth rapidly?
How do you know when to create your views?
Fortunately, PDFKit is already designed
to intelligently prepare content
before people scroll pages into view.
So it knows best
when to ask for an overlay view.
Your app just needs to respond
to its requests
that are made through the new protocol.
PDFPageOverlayViewProvider
is the new protocol.
By the way, PDFKitPlatformView is just
a define of UIView or NSView,
depending on the platform.
The most important method you need
to implement is overlayViewForPage.
Simply provide an instance
of your view, and PDFKit will size it
by applying the appropriate constraints.
It will also rotate it
if the page has a non-zero rotation.
The next 2 methods are optional.
willDisplayOverlayView can be used
to install your own gesture handlers,
or to set up failure relationships
with those of PDFKit.
willEndDisplayingOverlayView is called
when PDFKit is done with your view,
likely because
the page scrolled out of view.
You can release your view here, but there
is another important use for this method.
Assuming your view has some data
to represent what it's drawing,
you can use this method
to get that data and set it aside.
We'll do that in
our example with PencilKit,
but, if your view data lives
somewhere else,
you won't need to implement this.
In the example, this is the class
we're using as the provider.
It implements
the PDFPageOverlayViewProvider protocol.
This is iOS, so the PDFKitPlatformView
is a UIView.
It uses a map
to go from a PDFPage to a UIView.
Here are the placeholder protocol methods.
Next, lets look at the implementations.
overlayViewForPage checks
its pageToView map
to see if it's already made a view
for the given page.
If not, it creates a new view.
In either case, we get the drawing
from the page
and set that on the canvas view.
In these examples,
I'm using a subclass of PDFPage.
All it does is
to add a "drawing" property.
And now, let's focus on the next method:
WillEndDisplayingOverlay.
willEndDisplayingOverlayView is simple.
It gets the drawing from the view
and stores it on our custom page class.
Now that we've done that,
let's see it in action.
Normally, around this time off the year,
I would be in Maine, fishing,
but instead, I'm here at WWDC,
so another person is taking my place
on the trip,
and I'm going to show him
some of my favorite spots.
I'll be doing that with this app,
which uses PencilKit in an overlay view.
This app consists of the code we just saw
and little else.
The entirety of the code to get
overlay views onscreen is about 30 lines!
So, Grand Lake Stream.
This is the dam pool.
There are always lots of fish in there.
It's where most of the action is.
You can get to the dam pool
by taking this trail down
through the woods and then fishing.
You can fish all of that stuff,
or you can take this road,
go over the dam,
and down around through here.
From there, you can fish up into here,
go around the island, down into here,
but whatever you do,
don't go past here.
The water gets deep and fast.
Avoid that and come down here,
to the hatchery.
Walk down beside the hatchery
and enter this pool here.
You can cast all around through here
This is a great spot.
I always catch fish here.
All right, now that we have some marks
on the page,
let's exercise zooming and scrolling.
See how responsive it is?
And there we have it.
Overlay views in PDFKit.
So, now that you have these sketches,
how do you save them?
We'll use the PDFAnnotation class
to do this.
There are 2 things we want to achieve when
saving:
We want to match the onscreen appearance
with high fidelity,
and we want to do round-trip editing.
PDF annotations have some features
that will facilitate this.
PDF annotations can have an
"appearance stream,"
which is a stream of PDF drawing commands.
Nearly anything that you can draw
using Quartz2D
can be recorded in an appearance stream.
Anything else can be rendered
into an image, and that can be recorded.
That's how we do it if we're using Metal.
And, since it's recorded as PDF drawing,
it will look identical in Adobe Reader,
Chrome, etc.
PDF annotations are stored
as dictionaries in a PDF document.
That means we can also store custom data
in private key/value pairs.
So let's see what the code looks like.
Start by creating a subclass
of PDFAnnotation.
We do this in order to override
the draw() method.
PDFKit will call this method when it saves
the appearance stream
that I mentioned on the last slide.
To save our document, we override
UIDocument's contents().
Here is an overview of the function,
for context later.
We loop through all pages
of the PDFDocument.
We'll flesh out the loop next.
We do the following for each page:
create an annotation of our custom class;
encode our drawing into data;
add the data to our annotation.
Next time, when we open this document,
we can use value:forAnnotationKey
to read back the stored drawing data
and put that into our overlay view.
Finally, add the annotation to the page.
Back to our contents() override.
Now that we have added annotations
to our pages,
We use PDFDocument's dataRepresentation()
and return the result.
When your content
is saved as an annotation,
a recipient of the document can move it,
resize it, or delete it.
Often, that's what you want.
But sometimes, you want your annotations
to be "burned in," as part of the page.
There is a new PDFDocumentWriteOption
in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura
that makes this easy.
Just add burnInAnnotationsOption = true
to the save options, and that does it.
Speaking of PDF writing options,
there are a few
that have been made available
in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura.
Let's look at them.
CoreGraphics has always strived
to save images in PDFs
with maximum fidelity,
so images are saved at full resolution,
with lossless compression.
That's great if the PDF will be printed
on a large-format printer.
More likely, though,
it will be displayed on screen,
and all of that high-fidelity image data
will result in a file that's very large.
To address that, I introduce
the next two options.
saveAllImagesAsJPEG
does just what it says.
No matter how the image was created,
it will be saved
with JPEG encoding in the PDF.
optimizeImagesForScreen
will downsample images
to a maximum of HiDPI screen resolution.
These two options may be used together.
createLinearizedPDF will create
a special kind of PDF
that's optimized for the internet.
The PDF format, as originally designed
right before the Internet came along,
is read from the end of the file.
That means the entirety of it needs
to be downloaded first
before anything is displayed.
A linearized PDF has everything
needed to display the first page
at the beginning of the file,
so a web browser can show that quickly
while the rest of it is loaded.
You can pass these options
to PDFDocument's dataRepresentation
or writeToURL methods.
And there we have it.
PDFKit is powerful, yet easy to use,
used by many of your apps today on iOS
and macOS,
and now with new features for iOS 16 and
macOS Ventura.
I'm stoked to see what you do with them!
To learn more,
check out the sessions below
for additional information.
Thank you for watching!
[spacey music]