♪ ♪
Jeff Nadeau: Hello, and welcome
to What's new in AppKit.
I'm Jeff Nadeau,
an engineer on the AppKit team,
and I'm here to share the latest
and greatest in building apps
for macOS Ventura.
It's never been a more exciting time
for the Mac,
between the performance
and efficiency of Apple Silicon,
the power of macOS,
and an app ecosystem
that's richer than ever.
Your apps are an important part of
that story,
and we're continuing
to push AppKit forward
so that you can keep building
the very best apps.
I'll be covering a wide variety of topics,
starting with Stage Manager,
moving on to Preferences,
followed by controls,
SF Symbols,
and sharing.
I'll start off with Stage Manager.
Stage Manager cleans up inactive windows
in your workspace
while your active window
takes center stage.
For a more advanced workflow,
you can also pull windows together
into sets
which swap in and out as a group.
This has an impact on how
your app windows present themselves.
Stage Manager is trying to keep
the working space tidy,
so when a new window is presented,
existing windows will exit the stage
to make room.
That's what you want for
"primary" windows, like your documents.
Auxiliary windows like panels,
popovers, settings, and others
should continue to appear
above the existing windows.
NSWindow already has a lot of APIs
that can help you define the behavior
you'd like for a particular window.
By default,
Stage Manager won't swap out other windows
if you present a floating panel,
a modal window,
or a window with
a preference-style toolbar.
Stage Manager also respects
your window's collectionBehavior.
This OptionSet defines how
your window behaves
in spaces and full screen,
and it now also helps Stage Manager
understand
that a window is considered
to be auxiliary or floating.
If a window's collectionBehavior
includes the auxiliary, moveToActiveSpace,
stationary, or transient options,
then it won't displace
the active window in center stage.
By setting up your windows
with the right collection behaviors,
you can make sure
that they work great in every context,
whether it's a desktop space,
full screen, or now in Stage Manager.
Next, I'd like to cover some
important changes to Preferences.
In macOS Ventura,
the System Preferences app
has taken on a whole new look,
with a refreshed navigation scheme
and all-new visual design.
To align with the settings experience
on our other operating systems,
we've also renamed the app
to System Settings.
These changes extend
to your application too.
For example,
you might have a preference pane bundle
that appears in
the System Preferences app today.
You might also have
a settings area inside of your app.
There's also a new design system
for control-rich forms
that may be the perfect fit
for settings interfaces or inspectors.
If you ship a custom prefpane bundle,
it'll continue to work
with the new Settings app.
Your custom pane will appear
in the sidebar,
and the app will load up your bundle
and present your settings UI
just like it did in Monterey and earlier.
To match the newly-renamed
System Settings app,
we've renamed in-app preferences
to "settings" as well.
To help get you started,
once you build against the newest SDK,
AppKit will automatically update
the name of the "Preferences," menu item
in your app menu.
However, you might be using the word
"Preferences" in a number of other places,
like window titles, descriptive labels,
or other controls around your app.
Search through your localized text
to find places that also need updating.
For example, TextEdit's settings window
used to be called "preferences"
and we chose to rename that window to
Settings to match the rest of the system.
The System Settings app also uses
a new interface style
for presenting
all of its configuration options.
Settings interfaces
are often control-heavy,
so this style is designed to present forms
containing many controls
in a clear and well-organized fashion.
Since the form itself provides a lot
of visual structure,
many system controls adapt to this context
by drawing with a lower visual weight,
while revealing more prominent
control backings on rollover.
If you want to write interfaces
that use this new design,
SwiftUI makes it super easy.
Place your controls into a Form view,
and then apply
the "insetGrouped" form style.
SwiftUI takes care of the rest:
the visual style, scrolling behavior,
and layout of the form
are all applied automatically.
If you haven't gotten started
with SwiftUI yet,
this is a great opportunity
to give it a try.
A Settings window is often
a standalone area of your app's interface,
so it's the perfect place
to do some incremental adoption.
We've even created a video
about using SwiftUI and AppKit together,
which is a great place to learn more.
Next, I'd like to share some updates
to our controls.
We've got a lot of exciting
control enhancements to share,
starting with a new control
called NSComboButton.
We've also updated NSColorWell,
made some enhancements
to the NSToolbar API,
adjusted the design of NSAlert,
and improved the performance
of NSTableView.
First, NSComboButton.
NSComboButton is all about
combining an immediate button action,
and a menu for additional options.
In today's control landscape,
you'd traditionally use
a button to perform some immediate action,
or you would use a pull-down button
to show a menu with many options.
NSComboButton combines both elements
into a single control,
which joins a primary action
and a pull-down menu together.
This design is commonly used
for use cases like this one in Mail,
where the predicted folder
is a single click away,
but you can still access a menu
to file your messages anywhere.
Previously,
you might've assembled something like this
using the segmented control API,
but now there's
a dedicated control for it.
NSComboButton comes in two styles,
which dictate both the appearance
and the behavior of the button.
The default style is called "split,"
and it includes a separate arrow portion
just for the menu.
The second style, "unified,"
looks much more like an ordinary button.
This style performs
its primary action on click,
and it presents its menu
if you click-and-hold.
And that's NSComboButton.
We've also got some great new updates
to NSColorWell,
starting with a brand-new look.
In place of the classic square
gradient appearance,
the color well has adopted a new style
reminiscent of other button bezels
across the system.
This change is completely automatic,
so you don't need to do any adoption
to get this modern appearance.
However, we know that color picking
is an important part
of creative and professional applications,
so we've gone a step further
and introduced two new styles
for NSColorWell.
The first is a minimal style,
which shows a disclosure
arrow on rollover,
and provides a quick
color picking experience
by showing a popover to immediately
select from a palette of colors,
with the option to break out
into the full NSColorPanel.
By default,
it uses a system standard grid of colors,
but you can customize what appears here
if you've got a different UI
or palette in mind.
The second is an expanded style,
which you might recognize
from the iWork apps.
This style combines both
interaction models:
the well on the left has
the same disclosure arrow
and popover for quick picking,
while the button on the right
pulls up the full panel
for more detailed color picking.
And with that, NSColorWell now offers
three different ways to pick colors.
You can access these styles using the new
colorWellStyle property on NSColorWell,
which has cases for each style:
default, expanded, and minimal.
NSColorWell has also gained
a new target-and-action pair
for its "pulldown action."
This action determines what happens
when you click the pulldown portion
of a minimal or expanded color well.
By default,
these properties are nil,
which signifies that NSColorWell
should use the system-standard popover.
However, you can customize this action
and use it to present
your own custom popover,
Or you could even present a different
picking interface, like a menu.
And that's the new NSColorWell.
It's got a brand new look
and two new ways to quickly pick colors.
Next up, some news on NSToolbar,
where we've made a variety
of API enhancements
to give you better control
over customization
and increased flexibility for your layout.
On the customization front,
we've added two new delegate methods
to give you better control over
the customizability of your toolbar.
The first is
"toolbarImmovableItemIdentifiers".
If you implement this method
to return a set of item identifiers,
those items won't be movable
or removable by the user,
and they won't animate
when you enter customization mode.
For example,
the Mail app wants the Filter button
to always appear here,
above the message list.
Using this API, they can prevent it
from being moved away from this spot.
The second method is called "toolbar
itemIdentifier canBeInsertedAt."
This delegate method gives you veto power
over any particular reordering,
insertion, or removal from the toolbar.
You can use it to implement
your own set of customization rules –
for example,
you could create a toolbar item that's
allowed within one section of the toolbar,
but it's disallowed
within another section.
You can now specify multiple
centered items for your toolbar
using the new
centeredItemIdentifiers property.
If your toolbar is customizable,
items in this set
can still be added or removed
from the toolbar,
but they can only be reordered
within the centered group.
In this example,
the photo editing tools
all stick together in the center
of the toolbar
regardless of how many items are placed
in the leading and trailing sections.
Once your toolbar is customized
the way you like it,
you don't want the items to shift around,
and that can be difficult
for toolbar items that change meaning
based on some other state,
like the Mute and Unmute button in Mail,
which toggles when you click it.
Since the labels have different sizes,
the other items in the toolbar have to
shift around to accommodate the change.
In a scenario like this, you can
use the new possibleLabels property
on NSToolbarItem to provide a set
of the localized strings
that you'll use for the item.
NSToolbar will automatically size the item
to fit the longest label,
so your layout stays the same
even when the item is reconfigured.
Next, a design update for alerts.
Alerts on macOS use a compact layout,
which is optimized
for a small amount of text
accompanied by a few clear choices.
And in general, that's a great way
to put together an alert.
Alerts work best with shorter text:
you can communicate your message
more directly,
and people are more likely to read
what you've written
before pushing their way
through the alert.
However, sometimes you really can't
shorten your description,
especially if you need to communicate
something complex and subtle,
like this Disk Utility alert,
which conveys a really important choice
about your filesystem data.
The compact layout just isn't optimal
for this situation.
For these cases, we've adapted NSAlert
to provide a wider layout
that's suitable for longer text.
This adaptation happens automatically
for alerts where the informative text
is too long to fit comfortably
in the compact size.
We'll also use this style
if you have an accessory view
that's too large to fit
in a compact alert window.
There's no need for your app
to opt in to this behavior –
it's applied automatically system-wide.
It's important to note
that the layout is determined
at the time you present the alert,
so an alert won't swap styles
if you modify it
while it's already on screen.
You should still aim to reduce the length
of your alert text wherever possible,
but this design update
will improve the user experience
for those cases where you can't.
Next, an important new feature
of NSTableView.
NSTableView is designed to efficiently
handle a very large number of rows,
by lazily populating
and reusing the views as you scroll.
However, for tables where each row
can have a different height,
that can be a challenge,
because in order to provide
a good scrolling experience
the table needs to know its total height
and the location of each row
in the scrolling region.
Historically, NSTableView does this by
sizing all of the rows in the table,
which can have an impact
on initial load times.
In macOS Ventura,
NSTableView achieves those goals
while providing much better performance.
Instead of eagerly calculating
the height for each row,
NSTableView now lazily calculates
row heights
based on which rows are within
or near the scrolling viewport.
For the rows that haven't
been measured yet,
NSTableView uses
a running estimated height
based on the row heights
that it's already measured.
As you scroll through the table,
NSTableView requests row heights
as needed,
replacing the estimated heights
with real measurements,
while taking care to maintain
the correct scrolling position.
This optimization significantly improves
the load times for very large tables.
The change does alter the timing
of delegate calls
like "table view: height of row",
so you shouldn't make assumptions
about when NSTableView
will request row heights from you.
This optimization applies to both
NSTableView and SwiftUI's List view,
and it's automatically used for all apps
on macOS Ventura
with no adoption required.
And that's NSTableView performance.
Next, some updates on SF Symbols.
macOS Ventura includes SF Symbols 4,
which adds more than 450 new symbol images
covering all kinds of subjects.
These new symbols include laurels,
all kinds of household objects,
currency symbols from around the world,
and even a variety
of sports-related symbols.
With a catalog of thousands of symbols,
it's likely that SF Symbols includes
a professionally-designed icon
for any idea that you want to represent.
But we haven't stopped there.
SF Symbols 4 also includes
some new features
to further enhance your iconography.
To recap, symbol images support
a number of rendering modes
that you can choose from
depending on your design.
There's monochrome,
which uses a single color;
hierarchical,
which uses different opacities of a color
to emphasize certain portions
of a symbol;
palette,
which allows you to specify
distinct colors
for each part of a symbol;
and multicolor, which uses colors
designed directly into the symbol artwork.
These choices give you the flexibility
to realize a wide variety of designs,
but we also want symbol images
to look their best right out of the box,
without the need
to apply any configuration.
That's why we've introduced
a new feature to symbols
in macOS Ventura:
preferred rendering mode.
With preferred rendering mode,
symbols can specify the style of rendering
that they prefer,
and at runtime
AppKit will use that style automatically.
This is great for symbols
like AirPods Pro,
which prefers a hierarchical style
to increase the clarity
of those fine details.
Of course, if you have
a different design in mind,
you can always use an
NSImageSymbolConfiguration object
to choose your preferred style.
Some symbols
don't just represent a concept,
they're also meant to communicate
some value or quantity,
like your Wi-Fi signal strength,
or audio volume.
For cases like these,
we've introduced a new type of symbol
that we call a "variable symbol."
With a variable symbol,
you supply a floating point value
directly to NSImage,
and the symbol embeds numeric thresholds
to decide how each path should vary
based on that value.
Here's the API.
Variable symbols are created
using a new initializer.
It's similar to the existing
symbol image initializer,
with the addition of a value parameter,
which is a floating point number
between zero and one.
If the symbol image doesn't define
any variable thresholds,
this value is ignored
and the symbol draws as it normally would.
If it does, you'll see
the symbol paths drawing differently
based on the value you supplied.
Each variable symbol can represent
a value in its own unique way,
and by providing that value
at the API level,
you get access to all of those variations
without having to know the fine details
of how the symbol is composed.
Variable symbols work great
in combination with rendering styles
like palette color and multicolor,
so you can adapt them
to almost any design.
Finally, I'd like to cover
some big updates to Sharing
macOS Ventura elevates
the sharing experience on the Mac,
introducing features like suggested people
and new ways to invite and manage
the people that you're collaborating with.
There are some new APIs that you can adopt
so that your app gets the most
out of these enhancements.
The most prominent update to the sharing
experience is the new sharing popover.
This replaces the existing share menu
with a rich interface
that includes more information
about the document you're sharing
and familiar features
like suggested people.
It supports all of the same APIs and
delegate methods as the previous picker,
so you can still do things like
filter the list of sharing services,
or insert your own custom
services into the picker.
If you're sharing a file URL,
NSSharingServicePicker can automatically
populate the header with an icon,
name, and other metadata about the file.
But if you're sharing
a custom type instead,
you can conform your items
to a new protocol
that NSSharingServicePicker will use
to request that information.
The protocol is called
NSPreviewRepresentableActivityItem.
Conforming types must be able to return
the underlying item to share,
like an NSItemProvider,
and they can optionally return a title,
an image provider, and an icon provider.
For convenience,
there's a conforming class in AppKit
called NSPreviewRepresentingActivityItem
which you can use to bundle up an existing
sharing item with its metadata.
You can provide each image parameter
directly as an NSImage,
or you can use NSItemProvider
if it's too performance-intensive
to generate those images up front.
The new sharing picker is great for
kicking off sharing from somewhere
like a toolbar button,
but sometimes you want to start sharing
from a menu,
like the main menu bar or the context menu
for a selected view inside your app.
Previously, you might've constructed
your own menu to handle this,
by enumerating sharing services
and then building menu items for each one.
Although that does work,
it bypasses the standard picker,
so now you're missing out
on all of those new features.
In macOS Ventura,
NSSharingServicePicker
can create
a "standardShareMenuItem" for you.
You can add the standard item
to any menu to easily kick off sharing.
Once selected,
the menu item summons the sharing popover,
and for context menus,
it'll even anchor the popover
to the same view that produced the menu.
There's a lot of new support for
managing collaboration in macOS Ventura.
With some extra adoption,
your shareable items can also become
invitations to collaborate,
which users can initiate
via the sharing picker,
drag-and-drop into Messages,
or even via FaceTime.
You can share content
using CloudKit or iCloud Drive,
or you can connect the invitation flow
with your own collaboration server.
Now this is a really big topic,
so we've made a few videos
to explain it in much greater depth.
They're a must-see
if your app supports collaboration,
or if you'd like
to get started with adding it.
As you get started with macOS Ventura,
make sure you're setting up your windows
to work best with Stage Manager.
Then, consider how your design
might benefit from control enhancements
like NSComboButton
and NSColorWell.
Improve your iconography using the newest
symbols and features of SF Symbols.
And finally, for collaboration,
adopt the latest APIs
so that you get the most
out of macOS Ventura's
new sharing experience.
Thanks so much for watching,
and thanks for continuing
to build great Mac applications.