♪ Bass-heavy electronic music ♪
Ready for your day two briefing?
Let's jump right in, shall we?
First, we cooked up new ways
to navigate within
your SwiftUI apps.
- This recipe is our
pièce de résistance.
Then we learned more about
the new features in Xcode 14.
- You can choose
the level of detail
that's right for you.
And Jared showed us
new plug-ins
for adding Apple frameworks
to your Unity game projects.
- The Core Haptics Unity plug-in
gives you the tools you need
to add an entirely new level
of immersion into your games.
- And there's a brand-new
way to do 3D scans
with RoomPlan.
- Apple has enabled
powerful new ways
for people to bring the world
into their apps.
And then Paul showed
developers how they can
use color to make SF Symbols
even more expressive.
And we introduced the new
Push to Talk framework for iOS.
[CHIME]
- Hey Trevor.
Are you ready to cover
your WWDC slides? [CHIME]
- Hey Kevin.
I'll be ready in a few minutes.
[CHIME]
Can you hear me?
Over.
Here's some intel for tomorrow.
♪
Developers, we'll be in contact.