♪ ♪
Hello, I'm Devin Rousso,
an engineer on the WebKit team,
and I'm here today to share with you
the exciting new opportunity
to create extensions
for Safari's Web Inspector.
Web Inspector is the primary
developer tool for debugging web content
on all of Apple's platforms.
It already has a ton of built-in
functionality for debugging websites,
but there are often areas
of web development
that are difficult to build into
a generalized developer tool.
Maybe you're debugging
a popular JavaScript library,
or you just need something more specific
to what you're working on.
Web Inspector extensions
are a fantastic solution
for these personal workflow scenarios.
By utilizing cross-browser web extensions
and the DevTools APIs,
you can now add your own tabs
in Web Inspector in Safari 16.
Let's take a quick look
at a Web Inspector extension in action,
and then I'll show you
how you can build your own.
First I'll open Safari's
extension preferences.
And enable a Web Inspector extension.
Then I'll close Safari's extension
preferences and inspect the page.
I'll do that from the Develop menu,
Show Web Inspector.
In Web Inspector,
not only can I see the many built-in tabs
like the Elements Tab,
but also the tab for the Web Inspector
extension I just enabled.
Because we've just enabled
this extension, however,
we first have to give it permission
to work with the currently inspected page.
I have the same permission
duration options as other extensions
outside of Web Inspector,
so for now
let's give it access for one day.
This Open Graph extension is
what I'll be building in this session.
It displays the common social media
metadata that most websites put
on their pages
for use by link previews
in Messages and other social media sites.
Now that we've gotten a quick look
at what a Web Inspector extension can do,
let's talk about how they're built.
Like other Safari Web Extensions,
Web Inspector extensions
are distributed via an app
in the App Store.
To build your own Web Inspector extension,
you will need to have Xcode,
Apple's app creation tool
for building Mac and iOS apps.
Xcode also comes with project templates
to help jumpstart
making a new Safari extension app.
If you already have
an existing web extension
you've created for another browser,
you can also use
Xcode's bundled conversion tool.
Simply run safari-web-extension-converter
from the Terminal,
passing a path
to your extension's directory
that contains the manifest.json file.
A full app project will then be created
for your extension
that is ready to build and run.
For more information on this tool,
check out Meet Safari Web Extensions
from WWDC 2020,
as well as the online documentation.
So today I'm going to go over the basic
structure of a Web Inspector extension,
cover how to best evaluate code
in that extension,
and discuss some good
best practices for your users.
Let's get started.
Web Inspector extensions are structured
just like other Safari Web Extensions,
with a toolbar icon, background page,
content scripts, and more,
but they also have
a dedicated devtools background page.
Let's take a look at how that works
in practice.
The structure
of a typical Safari Web Extension
begins with a manifest file
that declares the basic details
about the extension, like the name,
icons, descriptions, and more.
It can declare a background page
to handle all the behind-the-scenes logic
of your extension,
and can also declare any content scripts
used to inject functionality
into web pages visited by the user.
For Web Inspector extensions,
a couple other pages enter the mix.
First there is a required
devtools background page
for the behind-the-scenes logic
of your Web Inspector extension.
This page has access
to the unique devtools APIs
and only a limited set
of content script APIs.
From this devtools background page
you can create devtools tab pages
that will be shown in Web Inspector.
But all of that is just for
a single Web Inspector.
If there are multiple Web Inspectors,
each has its own instance
of this same devtools background page,
staying alive for the duration
that the related Web Inspector is open.
As such,
you might also have multiple instances
of each devtools tab page as well.
Let's take a look
at how this structure looks in practice,
and start building my Open Graph
Web Inspector extension.
I'll start by creating a new project
in Xcode.
The project type I'm going to create
is a Safari Extension App.
I only really need macOS,
but I'm going to leave it as is,
in multiplatform, in case I want to add
iOS functionality in the future.
I'm going to name this "Open Graph",
and keep the rest of the defaults.
Note that you need to pick a team
and bundle identifier
based on the Apple developer account
you're using.
And finally,
I'm going to save this on the Desktop.
Now I have a generic Safari Web Extension
project, ready for me to modify.
I am first taken
to the manifest.json file,
which is the root configuration file
for every web extension.
The manifest file references the other
resources that make up your extension–
localizations, images,
pages, scripts, styles, and more.
For my Web Inspector extension,
I won't need some of these files,
like the background page,
content scripts, or popup,
so I'm going to delete them from
the manifest
and from the entire project.
Okay, let's start making this
a Web Inspector extension.
To do that I need to add
a devtools background page to the manifest
and create a corresponding file for it,
as well as a JavaScript file
I'm going to use inside it.
I'm going to go to File - New - File...
And scroll down
to find the Empty file template.
I'm going to call this file
"devtools_background.html"
to match the name I used in the manifest.
The location is already set
to be right next to my other resources
and part of the correct targets,
so I don't need to change anything here.
I'll repeat the same steps again
with the JavaScript file...
…which I'll call "devtools_background.js".
Finally, I need to include the JavaScript
file in my devtools background page.
Remember, this page gets created
when Web Inspector opens,
and is responsible for creating the custom
tabs that appear in Web Inspector.
I almost always want to create a tab
so that, if needed,
the permissions I saw earlier
will be displayed to my users
right there in-line,
instead of in some other place.
This devtools panels create API
takes three simple arguments.
The first is the name of the tab.
For that,
I am using the localization method
to look up the localized name
of my extension.
The next argument is the icon path to use.
Note that this should be a vector image
to smoothly scale to any size
if the user chooses
to zoom their user interface.
But in order to use this icon, I need to
make sure it's part of my project,
along with all of the other icons
I need for my extension.
The icons in the "images" folder are still
the defaults from the project template.
So let's delete these from the project.
And replace them with some icons
I created earlier...
…including the "logo.svg" I am trying to
use when creating the devtools tab.
Now that this is here, I'll go back
to the devtools background script.
The third argument is the HTML used
by the tab in Web Inspector.
And just like
with the images a moment ago,
I need to create this page
before I can use it.
I'll name this "devtools_tab.html"
to match the name I gave the API.
Unlike the devtools background page,
however,
this devtools tab page
will actually be shown to the user,
so this time I'll create both
a JavaScript and CSS file.
I'll name the JavaScript file
"devtools_tab.js"...
…and the CSS file "devtools_tab.css".
It's great that I've already set up
this structure,
but for now I'll just add the usual
"Hello World"
to make sure that things
are working correctly.
But don't worry, we'll dive deeper
into this a little bit later,
because first,
we still have a few more icons to replace
to make sure this extension
has a consistent look.
First we need to replace
the default large icon...
…by deleting it...
…and dragging my large icon in its place.
Since this large icon
is part of the app, however,
I need to add it to the right target.
The remaining icons are all part
of the Assets catalog,
specifically the AppIcon set.
I've already prepared these icons,
so I'll just paste them in.
And with that, I think we've replaced
all of the default icons,
so I'm now going to run my extension.
Note that this may take a few seconds
the first time the project is built.
And there it is!
Most of this UI
is from the Xcode template,
but I do correctly see
my icon instead of the default one.
Once we've launched
the Safari extension app at least once,
we can close it,
as the app doesn't need to be running
anymore for Safari to pick it up.
But before I can see it in Safari,
however,
I have to Allow Unsigned Extensions
in the Develop menu
as this is a locally built unsigned app.
Now, in Safari's Extensions preferences,
I can see Open Graph.
I'll turn it on.
I'm going to open a Safari tab
and browse to apple.com
so that I can try my extension.
And already we can see
that my icon is in the toolbar.
And my extension tab
is now in the tab bar.
Switching to it,
we can see the same permission prompt we
saw earlier.
This permission prompt
is automatically shown
if permissions are needed
by the extension.
Just like earlier,
I'll allow it for one day.
And there's the "Hello World"
I added to the devtools tab page earlier.
Those are the basics of how to create
a Web Inspector extension for Safari 16.
Let's recap.
I declared the devtools background page
and added it to my Xcode project.
From there, I was able to create
a new tab in Web Inspector
to show my custom tooling.
And finally, I've started considering
the permissions my extension needs.
For a Web Inspector extension,
this often boils down to evaluating code
in the inspected page,
usually to extract some data
for display inside of Web Inspector.
Web Extensions already have
a number of ways to evaluate code.
For Web Inspector extensions,
there is another API
that is the preferred method
of evaluating scripts
inside the inspected page.
Let's take a look at this API and see how
I can use it for my OpenGraph extension.
This devtools extension API to evaluate
JavaScript in the inspected window
is the best way to get quick results.
It will automatically target the page
associated with the Web Inspector
your extension is running in.
Remember, the user could be inspecting
multiple pages at the same time.
There are also some useful options
for this API
that can help you get the right results.
By default the expression given
to this API is evaluated
in the context of the main frame
of the inspected page.
But you can use the frameURL option
to specify evaluation
inside a different frame.
This is needed when your extension
needs to extract data
from one of many possible sub-frames
in the page.
For my OpenGraph extension,
I only need to worry about the main frame,
but I recommend you keep this in mind
when evaluating scripts
for your Web Inspector extensions.
Let's take a look at how I can use
this function in my extension
to get and display data
from the inspected page.
I'll start by replacing the placeholder
"Hello World" I added earlier
with HTML that actually loads
my CSS and JavaScript files.
Then I'll add some basic CSS
to give my devtools tab a nice style.
I want to make sure that my devtools tab
fits in with the rest of Web Inspector,
so I've declared
a root `color-scheme` property
that will make my devtools tab match the
appearance of the rest of Web Inspector.
I am using a system font family
and inheriting the font size,
and matching the colors
of more important text.
As far as functionality,
I'll start by adding some text
in case the page doesn't have
any opengraph metadata.
Note that I can use web extension
localized strings in Web Inspector
just like I can anywhere else
in a web extension.
But in order to do so, I need to add
that same localized string identifier
to the localized strings file.
Next,
I'll create the JavaScript
I'll provide to the powerful devtools
inspectedWindow eval API,
which lets me evaluate it
in the inspected page.
In this case,
I want to query the inspected page's DOM
for some common opengraph metadata,
specifically the title, description...
…and image,
as well as the current ready state
of the inspected page's document,
bundling it all together to send back
to the devtools page via the return value.
Once that's done,
I can grab the HTML element
that corresponds
to each of these properties
and configure them so that they show
the data that was gathered.
And if the document isn't quite ready yet,
I can try again after a short delay.
I also want to redo all of this
every time the inspected page navigates,
so I'll add a listener
for devtools network onNavigated.
This all looks great,
so I'll build again to test it.
Now, whenever I open Web Inspector or
navigate with Web Inspector already open,
I can see the opengraph title,
description, and image of every page.
And that's a simple example of
how to use some of the many new
and powerful Web Inspector extension APIs.
My OpenGraph extension
is coming along very nicely.
My Web Inspector extension's
devtools tab page
is now able to evaluate
in the inspected page.
I'm able to take the result data
and process it
to display it in a user friendly format
for quick access.
So what are some great ways to make
great user experiences
when creating a Web Inspector extension?
Always create devtools tab pages
from the devtools background page.
This way, the user can see where
these tabs will appear in Web Inspector,
and any appropriate permission prompting
will be shown in-line.
Instead of asking
for specific host permissions,
try to use the activeTab permission
to keep Web Inspector extensions
as targeted as possible.
And make sure to use
the CSS color-scheme property
or the web extension devtools theme APIs
to match the overall theme
of Web Inspector.
So today I showed you at how to create
entirely new debugging tools
with Web Inspector extensions
and covered some great best practices
to keep in mind while doing so.
You're welcome to download
the OpenGraph Web Inspector extension
in this session's related resources
if you want to take a closer look
for yourself.
We're super interested
in hearing your thoughts,
so please file bugs and feature requests
using the Feedback Assistant,
or come chat with us
on the Safari developer forums.
And even consider joining
the WebExtensions community group
to help shape the future
of web extensions.
And also, make sure to check out
What's new in Safari Web Extensions,
and the documentation online,
to learn more about what's new this year.
I really hope you've enjoyed learning
about the amazing new ability
to create custom tooling
within Web Inspector.
We can't wait to see what awesome
Web Inspector extensions you'll create,
and look forward to all the ways
you'll push the bounds of what's possible.
Thank you so much for listening,
and I hope you have
a fantastic rest of your WWDC.  ♪ ♪