[upbeat music]
Rich Gillam: Hi, I'm Rich,
and I'm here to help you get it right
to left.
So you’ve already localized
your application for a bunch of languages,
including the most common
European languages,
the most common Asian languages.
And now you want to localize it
for Arabic and Hebrew.
This is a good choice;
Arabic is one of the ten most used
languages on our platform,
but it brings
with it some challenges you don’t face
when developing for other languages.
That’s what this talk is about,
how to develop your application
so that it can be localized into languages
such as Arabic and Hebrew.
Arabic and Hebrew are
the most commonly used
of the so-called
“right-to-left languages.”
Why are they called this?
English, French, Chinese, Thai,
and many other languages are written
so that their characters run
from left to right like this.
In Hebrew, the characters run
from right to left like this.
They do the same thing in Arabic,
and in Arabic,
the characters are also cursively joined.
The four letters in “salaam” look
like this when they're written separately.
It’s not just Arabic and Hebrew,
by the way.
Apple actually has font
and keyboard support
for 15 right-to-left languages.
Here’s a paragraph of Hebrew text.
This one is from the Hebrew version
of the “Formulas & Functions Help”
page for Numbers.
Notice that the text is aligned
on the right and ragged on the left,
and that many lines,
including the last one,
have punctuation on the left-hand side.
There’s also a number in this paragraph.
The number still goes from left to right.
This one is telling us
that Numbers supports over 250 functions.
If we widen our view
to include another paragraph,
we see that this one
has some English words,
the names of iWork
and its constituent applications,
Pages, Numbers, and Keynote.
These are also written from left to right,
even in a Hebrew paragraph.
So for many paragraphs,
the text is bidirectional.
This is an inherent property
of Arabic and Hebrew,
and it’s why they’re also often referred
to as the “bidi” languages.
If we widen our view even further,
we see the entire page is
laid out from right to left.
We have a table here,
and the text is to the right
of the images instead of to their left.
And if we widen it even further
to see Safari’s window frame,
we see that it doesn’t stop
with the content.
Lines of Arabic and Hebrew text begin
on the right and progress to the left,
so it’s natural to expect
other UI elements to do the same.
Just as readers expect things to start
on the left and progress to the right,
Arabic and Hebrew readers
expect the opposite.
So here,
Safari’s toolbar runs from right to left
with the traffic light buttons
in the upper right corner
and the buttons progressing to the left.
And if we widen our focus
to include the entire screen,
we see that it extends everywhere.
This is Numbers’ help screen,
and we see that all
of the elements
in Numbers have also flipped.
The sidebar is on the left.
The tab bar runs from right to left.
Even the document itself is flipped.
And the Mac menu bar and dock run
from right to left as well.
Getting all of this right
can be complicated,
but the great news is that we do most
of the heavy lifting for you.
Most support
for right to left comes for free.
But there are things to keep in mind.
So that’s what we’re gonna talk about,
what the system does for you,
when you need to opt in or out,
and what to think about when implementing
your own right to left support.
We’ll talk about text, images,
control orientation, and UI layout.
We'll also cover
displaying numbers in Arabic.
And finally,
we’ll talk a little about how to test
that your app is
handling right to left correctly.
So let’s dive in.
First, we’ll talk a little bit more
about how text works
and introduce some terminology.
Let’s start with the concept
of writing direction.
As we’ve already seen,
English is written from left to right,
and Hebrew is written from right to left.
But what happens if we mix them?
If you’ve got
a multilingual sentence like these,
the individual components
still keep their writing direction,
but this means that each
of these sentences now consists
of three components:
Two separate snippets
of text in the native language
sandwiching one snippet
in a different language.
When we talk about the writing direction
of a paragraph,
we’re talking about the order
of these individual snippets.
When we say the English sentence
has left to right writing direction,
it's because these three boxes
run from left to right,
and when we say the Hebrew sentence
has right to left writing direction,
it’s because those three boxes
run from right to left.
A different but related concept
is text alignment.
If you read a left to right language,
your eye goes to the left-hand side
of the page and progresses to the right.
If you read a right to left language,
it’s the opposite.
So text gets aligned on the right-hand
side in right to left languages.
The good news is that most of the time,
you don’t have to worry
about either of these things.
Not only does CoreText take care
of arranging all
of the characters properly
on a line or paragraph of text,
including when text of different
directions is mixed on one line,
but all of our UI frameworks
automatically set the writing direction
and alignment as well.
All UI widgets default to something
called “natural writing direction"
and “natural alignment."
The writing direction
of a text widget defaults to match
the normal writing direction
for the user’s UI language.
That is,
if your UI is in Hebrew or Arabic,
the writing direction of your text widgets
defaults to right to left.
Natural alignment
follows the writing direction.
That is, if the writing direction
of a text widget is right to left,
it’ll also be right-aligned.
Most of the time, this is what you want,
but you can override the defaults.
We’ll talk more about this
in the section on control orientation.
Now seems like a good time to start
a little chart of terms you’ll run across.
What we’re saying here is
that natural alignment corresponds
to left alignment
in left to right languages
and to right alignment
in right to left languages.
We’ll add to this chart as we go.
But of course, it’s not just text
you have to worry about.
Having text that’s read
in the opposite direction has
a profound effect on elements
of your application other than text.
Let’s talk about how it can affect icons
and other pictorial elements.
This is the Pages toolbar
in English and in Arabic.
Let’s take a closer look at some
of the icons in the toolbar.
Many, such as the “Add page”
and “Media” buttons,
look the same in both languages.
This is either because they’re symmetrical
or because their directionality isn't tied
to the language,
and they look fine in both languages.
Other buttons,
such as the “View” and “Document” buttons,
flip to their mirror images in Arabic.
The “View” button
brings up the Pages sidebar,
which appears on the opposite side
of the window in Arabic,
so the icon has to change to reflect that.
The “Document” button changes to show
that if the user is writing in Arabic,
the pages turn in the opposite direction.
And you can have situations
where the icon changes completely.
The letter on the “Insert text box” button
changes to a different letter
to reflect the user’s language.
Once again, the great news is
that a lot of this gets handled for you.
You have to think about image orientation
a little more than you generally have
to think about text writing direction,
but getting things right is fairly simple.
This is the “View” menu in Mac Pages
in English and Arabic.
Notice that the “Show Ruler” icon
reverses itself.
In right to left languages,
the vertical ruler is
on the right-hand side.
For a custom image like the ruler icon,
right to left behavior is controlled
in the Xcode imageset editor.
If your image is the same
in left to right and right to left,
you don’t have
to do anything special.
The system can also
algorithmically mirror your image for you
when your app is running in a language
with the opposite writing direction
from your development language.
You can ask for this feature
in Xcode’s imageset editor.
In the sidebar,
you’ll find a control marked “Direction.”
If you click on this,
you get a menu with four choices.
If your image is the same regardless
of the UI language, you pick “Fixed.”
If you want algorithmic mirroring,
you opt in by picking one
of the “Mirrors” options.
Which one depends on the writing direction
of your development language.
If you have an image
you can’t mirror algorithmically,
either it has multiple elements
that behave differently
when the UI changes direction,
or you’ve got shading
you don’t want to move, you pick “Both,"
and three new wells get added
to the image set editor,
allowing you to create separate images
to use for left to right
and right to left contexts.
But if you use images from SF Symbols,
as the Pages toolbar did,
things are even easier.
Almost all
of the work has been done for you.
The symbols that need to change
for right to left languages
do so automatically.
Consider this bulleted list icon
for example.
For many images,
SF Symbols’ sidebar has
a "localization" section
that shows localized versions
of the image you chose.
In this case,
the bulleted-list icon has
different left to right
and right to left versions.
It mirrors automatically.
The localization feature can
go beyond just mirroring
for right to left languages.
Here’s the localization tab
for the “insert text box” icon.
It has localized versions
not just for the Latin and Arabic scripts,
but for a variety of others as well.
One case that’s specifically important
for Arabic support is the question mark,
which is often used as a “help” icon.
In Arabic,
the question mark is the reverse
of the Latin question mark.
Using icons from SF Symbols for help icons
gets you this version
without any extra work.
One class of images you have
to think about carefully
is arrows
and other directional indicators.
Here we have four arrow-in-a-circle icons.
You’ll notice they’re in two pairs.
You have two pointing to the left
and two pointing to the right.
If we look at just the two
that point to the left,
you’ll see that one is called
“arrow.backward.circle.”
This one flips
to point to the right in right to left.
The other one
is called “arrow.left..circle”
and does NOT flip for right to left.
SF Symbols follows
this naming convention throughout
with icons that you may or may not want
to have flip for right to left.
The “forward” and “backward” ones flip,
and the “left” and “right” ones don’t.
If you’re using an arrow or other shape
to convey the idea
of “forward” or "backward,"
you want to use the flipping versions,
and if you’re using the arrow
to convey an absolute direction,
you want to use the non-flipping versions.
And let’s add a row
to our “Terminology” chart.
When choosing images in SF Symbols,
remember that “left” and “right”
always point those directions
and “forward” and "backward" point
in different directions
depending on the UI language.
Now let’s talk about how controls
and other UI widgets
are handled in right to left.
This is the Mac Keynote sidebar
in English and Arabic
showing the format inspector for a shape.
Notice that everything has
flipped its appearance for right to left.
We have lots of pop-up menu buttons
where the menu indicator moves
to the left-hand side for right to left.
We have a couple of checkboxes,
where in Arabic,
the checkbox is to the right of the label.
The opacity slider has changed for Arabic
so that the minimum is on the right
and the maximum on the left.
And so on throughout all
the other controls in this inspector.
The great news
is that you get this behavior for free.
All of the standard UI controls
in all our UI frameworks
automatically reverse their appearance
for right to left languages.
There are, however,
situations where you may not want this
or where you need to have some control
over how it happens.
Let’s take a look at a few
of the interesting cases.
Let’s talk about buttons with both
a textual label and an icon on them.
This is the Keynote animation
inspector showing the controls
for the “Move In” animation.
This inspector has two buttons
with both a label and an icon.
Notice that the arrow
on the Preview button flips
with the change in UI direction,
but the arrow
on the animation direction menu doesn’t.
Both flip sides with the UI direction,
but if the direction control was a group
of buttons instead of a menu,
you can image maybe
not wanting it to change sides.
To show how to control this,
I've isolated those two examples
out into a small toy application.
Here’s the code
to build that UI in SwiftUI.
There are a few interesting things
to note here.
We’ll look at them one at a time.
Let’s start with the image names.
As we saw before,
for images from SF Symbols,
you choose either an icon
that reverses or one that doesn’t.
Here we’ve used
“arrowtriangle.forward.fill”
for the “Preview” button.
The “forward” in the name tells you
that it flips for right to left.
We’ve used “arrow.left” and “arrow.right”
for the direction buttons.
The “left” and “right”
in the name tell you
that they don’t flip for right to left.
If you’re working in AppKit or UIKit,
this works the same way.
Here’s my app in Xcode’s storyboard editor
with the “Preview” button selected.
You control the button’s icon
with the “Image” control
in the Attributes inspector.
And in code, you set this
with the button’s “image” property,
and it works basically the same way
in both AppKit and UIKit.
Coming back to our SwiftUI example,
the next question is how
you control which side
of the label the icon goes on.
You do this by setting a label style.
The built-in TitleAndIconLabelStyle
puts the icon before the label
in the user’s reading direction.
We can use this for the “Left” button.
For the other two buttons,
we want the icon to go after the label
in the user’s reading direction.
To do this, you need a custom label style,
but that’s pretty easy to do.
Your label style’s makeBody()
method just has to make an HStack
and add the title and icon into it.
As with any HStack, the order you add them
determines the order they display,
and the order automatically reverses
when appropriate for the UI direction.
This technique works on any view
that can take a Label, not just buttons.
Of course, you don’t want the icon
to change sides on the “Right” button.
You want it to always be on the right
regardless of the UI direction.
That brings us to the last
interesting thing in this code snippet.
Views in SwiftUI
pick up their directionality
from the SwiftUI environment,
which you can modify.
You do this by adding
an “environment” modifier to a view
and giving it the key and new value
for the property you want to change.
Here we’re overriding the environment’s
layoutDirection property
to always be left to right
regardless of what value
we might be inheriting from our parent.
Changing the environment
in this way works on all SwiftUI views
that respond to the user’s UI direction.
Notice we applied the modifier
to the HStack
that contains the “Left”
and “Right” buttons.
Any changes you make
to a view’s environment are inherited
by its child views,
so putting it here not only
keeps the HStack
from reversing the order of the buttons,
but it keeps both buttons
from reversing the layout of their labels.
And of course,
we didn’t apply our environment modifier
modifier to anything in the parent chain
for the “Preview” button,
so it still reverses when appropriate,
just as we want it to.
So to recap,
the “Left” button has its icon
on the left because we used
the built-in TitleAndIconLabelStyle,
and the “Preview” and “Right” buttons
have their icons on the right
because we used a custom label style
we called IconOnRightLabelStyle.
The “Left” and “Right” buttons
don’t change their order
or the internal arrangement
of their labels
because we added
an environment modifier
to the HStack that contains them,
setting the layout direction
to left to right.
The “Preview” button reverses
the internal arrangement of its label
because it doesn’t have that modifier.
This works differently
in AppKit and UIKit.
In both of those frameworks,
the position of the icon relative
to the label is controlled
with the “Position” control
in Xcode’s Attributes inspector.
If you click on this control,
you’ll see that the menu has,
among other options,
two pairs of options that align the label
and icon horizontally.
You have “Leading” and “Left,”
and you have “Trailing” and “Right.”
“Leading” and “Trailing” change
their meanings based on the UI direction,
and “Left” and “Right” don’t.
In AppKit, you control this
with the button’s imagePosition property.
In UIKit, it’s the imagePlacement property
on the button’s configuration,
which might mean you need
to set your button’s configuration first.
The icon
on the “Preview” button changes sides
because we set its position to “Trailing,"
and the icon on the “Right” button
doesn't change sides
because we set its position to “Right.”
This also lets us fill in the last row
in our “terminology” chart.
The terms “leading” and “trailing”
will come up a lot
when discussing UI layout.
Like “forward” and “backward,”
you’ll often see them used
in contrast to “left” and “right.”
The “leading” edge of something is
the edge closest to beginning of the line
or to the side of the screen or window
where the reader would begin reading,
left for left to right
and right for right to left.
The trailing edge is the opposite side,
closest to the end of the line,
right for left to right
and left for right to left.
Most of the time, you want to use these
instead of “left” and “right,”
saving “left” and “right” only for things
that are tied to an absolute direction.
Let’s look at another interesting case.
This is part of the text format inspector
in Keynote on the iPhone,
in English and in Arabic.
This particular screenshot
has four segmented controls.
The top two,
the page selector for the inspector
and the standard
“bold/italic/underline” style buttons,
reverse the order of their segments
depending on the UI language.
If you don’t read Arabic, you’ll have
to trust me on the page selector.
As with the other
controls we’ve looked at,
this is the default;
you get this behavior for free.
The other two segmented controls,
the alignment controls,
don’t reverse the order of their segments.
This is because they move things
in absolute directions.
Left alignment is left alignment
regardless of whether
that’s the beginning or the end of a line.
Let’s look at how we keep
these controls from reversing.
We already know how to do this in SwiftUI.
You just apply an “environment” modifier
that changes the environment’s
layoutDirection property to left to right.
Here, we’re using this technique
to keep the alignment control
from reversing itself,
but letting the style control
reverse itself as it normally does.
In UIKit, this works differently.
Here’s a toy application
in Xcode designed to simulate
that segmented control behavior.
I have two segmented controls,
one that mimics
the bold/italic/underline behavior
and a second one
that mimics the alignment control.
The alignment control is selected.
In the attribute inspector,
you’ll find a menu labeled “Semantic.”
If you click on that menu,
you get five choices.
This menu controls something called
the semantic content attribute.
You use this to say what kind
of control this is,
and the system uses that to determine
if it reverses its appearance
based on the UI direction.
The default is “Unspecified,"
which causes the control
to reverse its appearance.
"Playback" says the control is
a media playback control
or part of a group of playback controls.
"Spatial" says the control is a spatial
control or a part of a group of them.
Spatial controls move things around
in space in absolute directions.
And finally, you can force the control
to always lay itself out left to right
or right to left.
So the bold/italic/underline control
reverses its segments for right to left
because its semantic content attribute
is set to “Unspecified,”
and the alignment control
doesn’t reverse its segments
because its semantic content attribute
is set to “Spatial.”
The great thing about this
is that it doesn’t just work
for UISegmentedControl.
All UIViews have
a semantic content attribute,
and it controls all
of that control’s right to left behavior.
For any standard UIKit view
that has subcomponents,
the semantic content attribute
will determine whether the positioning
of that view’s subcomponents reverses
based on the UI language.
In AppKit,
you do this kind of thing differently.
For all NSControls,
the Xcode attributes inspector
contains two menus
marked “Layout” and “Mirror.”
The “Layout” menu corresponds
to the control’s
userInterfaceLayoutDirection property,
which says whether the control should
use left to right or right to left layout.
You don’t normally change this
when working in Interface Builder.
Instead, you use the “Mirror” menu.
Setting it to “Always” causes
the userInterfaceLayoutDirection,
and thus the control’s layout,
to be flipped when the nib is loaded
when the user’s UI language
is right to left,
and setting it to “Never”
defeats this behavior,
keeping the layout the same.
You keep the layout
of the alignment control the same
by setting this value to “Never”.
If you’re not working
in Interface Builder,
you accomplish the same thing in code
by setting the control’s
userInterfaceLayoutDirection
back to left to right directly.
userInterfaceLayoutDirection,
by the way, is a property on NSView,
but appears in Interface Builder
only on instances of NSControl,
so if you want to reverse something
that’s not an NSControl,
you need code like we’re showing here.
Before we move on,
I want to talk about text a little more.
This is the “Set document password” dialog
in iWork for the Mac.
In the Arabic version,
you’ll see everything has reversed.
But notice what’s happened to the labels.
In English, they were right-aligned
so that they’d be close
to the edit-text fields.
In Arabic, they’re left-aligned.
In other words, you have
the opposite of natural alignment,
trailing-edge alignment, if you will.
Getting this layout in SwiftUI
on the Mac is trivially easy.
Just use a Form
to gather the text fields together.
But this can get interesting if,
as in our example,
one of the labels is multiple lines.
If we expand that last label out
to be two lines, we get this.
The two one-line labels
are correctly right-aligned,
but the two-line label isn’t.
The thing is,
the bottom label really is right-aligned.
It’s just that its bounding box
is right-aligned,
not the individual lines of text
within that bounding box.
You fix this by adding
a multilineTextAlignment modifier
to the last label.
Text alignment in SwiftUI only comes
into play on text objects
that are more than one line long.
For single-line text objects,
their bounding box
tightly encloses the text itself,
and you align it
by aligning the entire text object.
Also notice that whether you’re aligning
the text’s bounding box or multiple lines
of text inside the bounding box,
you have a choice of leading
and trailing alignment,
which change meaning based
on the user’s UI direction.
To keep the alignment the same
regardless of UI direction,
you use an environment modifier
to change the environment’s
layout direction as we saw earlier.
In UIKit,
text is naturally aligned by default,
but you can change it to one
of the absolute directions when necessary.
In Interface Builder,
the control looks like this
and corresponds
to the textAlignment property
on UILabel and UITextView.
The button on the far right
with the dotted line
gives you natural,
or leading-edge, alignment.
The alignment of the label
will follow
the label’s semantic content attribute.
The other buttons give you fixed left,
right, or center alignment
regardless of the UI direction
or the label’s semantic content attribute.
There’s no built-in setting
for trailing-edge alignment.
You have to do that in code.
In AppKit, it’s a little different.
You still have the alignment control,
and it works
basically the same as in UIKit,
but the way it interacts with
userInterfaceLayoutDirection is different.
If you have “Mirror” set
to “Automatically,”
and the system sets
userInterfaceLayoutDirection
to right to left,
the meanings
of all the alignment settings reverse.
So if “Mirror” is set to “Automatically,”
left alignment is
really leading-edge alignment,
and right alignment is
really trailing-edge alignment.
So we’ve talked about how all
of the standard UI widgets
automatically reverse their layouts
to match the user’s writing direction,
but it’s fairly easy
to prevent that when necessary.
This extends to arranging
individual UI widgets on the screen.
If you’re using one
of the standard views or view controllers
that handles the positioning
of their subviews,
all of them
automatically reverse their layouts
when necessary
without you having to do anything.
Table views and collection views
handle scrolling correctly
in right to left languages too.
UINavigationController
automatically changes the directions
of its segue animations
to reflect the user’s writing direction,
and changes the “back” button
to match it as well.
And UIPageViewController automatically
reverses the paging direction
and the meanings of the swipe gestures
automatically as well.
You generally won’t want
to override these things,
except for when you’re using a stack view
to position child views,
but all of the views honor
their semantic content attribute
and use it to tell them how
to lay out their subviews.
The same goes for the standard
AppKit views, and again,
table and collection views
handle right to left scrolling as well.
The views all honor their
userInterfaceLayoutDirection property
in determining how
to lay out their subviews,
although Interface Builder
doesn’t let you set it.
You have to do that in code.
The standard SwiftUI views also reflect
the environment’s
layoutDirection property.
If you’re using Auto Layout
instead of stack and grid views
to lay out your view,
Auto Layout also
automatically reverses things
to account for the UI direction.
If you have horizontal constraints,
you’ll see that they
automatically connect things
to the leading and trailing edges,
and as we’ve seen,
"leading" and “trailing” have different
meanings depending on the UI direction.
You can set Auto Layout constraints
to absolute left and right directions,
though, if you need to.
You do this by clicking on the direction
for one side of the constraint
and turning off
“Respect language direction”
in the menu that pops up.
That’ll change the direction
of both ends of the constraint
from “leading” and “trailing”
to “left” and “right.”
There are a lot of different ways
to set up Auto Layout constraints in code.
Here is one of them.
Pretty much however you do it,
the thing to remember is
is to use "leading" and “trailing”
instead of “left” and “right,”
except in the comparatively
rare situations where you really want
the same layout orientation regardless
of the UI language’s writing direction.
Okay, that was a lot to take in,
so let's take a breath.
The main takeaway is
that we do most of the work
of handling
right to left languages for you
and that when you need to override it,
there are ways to do that.
Let's take one more look
at our terminology slide.
Remember that "left" and "right"
are always left and right
and that the other terms
reverse their meanings
depending on the overall UI direction.
Before we wrap up, let’s take a look
at one more important issue,
and that’s how to display numbers.
It’s not strictly a right to left issue,
but for many developers,
Arabic is the first language
they’ll localize for
that uses different digit characters
than the ones used in English.
Here’s what those digits look like.
There are lots of different
naming conventions for the digits,
but I'll call the ones used with most
European languages “Latin” digits
and the ones used
with Arabic “Arabic-Indic” digits.
There are other languages
that have their own digits.
These are the Devanagari digits
used with Hindi;
Hindi is the other common language
that uses different digits.
One important thing to keep
in mind is that neither Arabic
nor Hindi always uses their native digits.
For Arabic, it depends on the country,
with some, such as Saudi Arabia,
using native digits and others,
such as the United Arab Emirates,
using Latin digits.
Individual users can also
choose their preferred digits.
For Hindi,
we use Latin digits by default,
but users can elect
to use native digits instead.
You already know that constructing
UI strings like this is a bad idea.
The string is hard-coded
and can’t be translated,
the message doesn’t
change to handle plurals, and so forth.
But another reason
this isn’t good is that the value
of “peopleInChat” will always
get rendered with Latin digits.
You probably also already know
that the solution to that is
to use the “localized” init method
on String,
which will look up the actual string
in your application’s bundle
and handle plurals properly
if you have a stringsdict file.
The great news is
that it also handles numbers correctly.
The value of the “peopleInChat”
interpolation here will be rendered
with the correct localized digits
for the user’s locale and preferences.
This also works right
with text views in SwiftUI.
The text views initializer will also
render any string interpolations
with properly localized digits.
Always use String(localized:)
when constructing user-visible strings.
Many of the other APIs on String
that can format numbers,
including +stringWithFormat:
and the String init function
that takes a number,
always use Latin digits.
One wrinkle to be aware of is
static strings that contain numerals,
such as this one.
What’s the big deal?
You send it off to the translators,
they translate it, and you get this.
This is correct in a lot of places,
but in Saudi Arabia
and some other countries,
you want to see this
. The text is the same except
for the character used for the 3.
You could, of course,
have separate localizations
for the Arabic-speaking locales
that use Arabic-Indic digits
and the ones that use Latin digits,
but nobody does that,
and it’d be wasteful.
Worse, in both Arabic and Hindi,
the user can choose the digits
they want to use,
so you’d be having
to choose a localization
based on the user’s preferences,
not just on their locale.
The solution is to still just
have one Arabic or Hindi localization,
but to substitute
the number in at run time,
even though you know the value
at compile time.
In Swift, you can just use
a string interpolation to do this.
If you’ve got other elements
that travel with a number,
their placement relative
to the number can also be challenging.
It isn’t even the same
for all right to left languages.
Notice that the minus sign
and the percent sign are
on different sides
of the number in Arabic and Hebrew.
In fact, it doesn’t have to be
a right to left language at all.
Notice that in Turkish,
which is a left to right language,
the percent sign also goes on the left.
And, of course, keep in mind
that if you’re using native Arabic digits,
they use
a completely different percent symbol.
In other words, you really don’t want
to do this kind of thing,
where you’re appending the percent sign,
or currency sign,
unit abbreviation, or whatever yourself.
Instead, use a number formatter
to add the percent sign,
or currency symbol, or whatever.
In Swift, this is easy
to do with the formatted() method
on all the numeric types.
If it’s part of a larger string,
as in this example,
String(localized:) will also make sure
that the formatted number--
or anything else substituted
into the string at runtime,
including other strings,
is surrounded with markup
that’ll keep the writing directions
of the formatted number
and the surrounding message
from messing each other up.
Finally, I want to leave you with one tip
for testing your app to make sure
that you’re doing the right thing
for right to left.
You don’t have to have
Arabic or Hebrew localizations
in your executable
to test your app in right to left.
You can actually test
right to left behavior
in your development language.
To do this,
bring up the scheme editor in Xcode.
Now go to the Options tab
and look for the “App Language” menu.
At the bottom of this menu are a bunch
of “pseudolanguage” options.
These are fake languages
that transform your UI in various ways
to allow you to check
for localization problems
without actual localizations.
Pick the “Right-to-Left Pseudolanguage”
option and click Run,
and your app will still be in English
or whatever your development language is,
but the UI will
all have been flipped for right to left.
And that’s all I have.
Localizing for right-to-left languages
involves attention
to some issues relating
to the change in writing direction,
but the system does most
of the heavy lifting for you.
There are cases,
usually around absolute directions,
where you may want
to opt of this behavior,
and that’s always possible.
And remember that not all languages
use Latin digits to render numbers.
Keep these things in mind,
and it shouldn’t be hard
to get things right
to left.
[upbeat music]