♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi! My name is Jared,
and I'm a software engineer
here at Apple.
Today I'd like to talk you
about a new framework
we are introducing this year
to iOS, iPadOS, and macOS.
This new framework is called
Background Assets,
and we believe it will greatly
enrich the user experience
of the apps that we all
know and love,
and more importantly,
that you develop.
To get started,
I'll be introducing you
to the new
Background Assets framework.
Afterwards, I'll show you
how to adopt the new framework
into your app.
This will be followed by a quick
overview of the extension
and what new capabilities
it provides.
Then we'll finish
with some best practices
and everything we've learned.
Before we begin,
let's talk about
what we're trying to solve here.
The truth is,
waiting is not fun.
Anytime we find ourselves asking
those that use our software
to wait, we're increasing
frustration and taking away
from the experience
we want our apps to provide.
For instance, how often
have you found yourself
browsing endlessly
through the App Store
looking for that perfect app?
You finally find it,
and oh does it look so perfect!
You then tap that GET button.
With every moment, your level
of excitement increases.
Then you shortly realize
that depending
on your network connection
or the size of the app,
you may find yourself having
to wait as the app downloads.
Then after a few seconds
of waiting,
you find yourself
putting your phone down,
grabbing a cup of coffee,
reading your favorite book
about the benefits
of practicing mindfulness
and mastering patience.
Then a few hours pass, and you
finally pick up your phone.
Your excitement levels rise
as you're ready to dive into
the perfect app that you've been
waiting to use all day.
Just to launch the app and be
immediately greeted with this:
more downloading.
It's confusing.
You've been away
from your phone all day.
Why is this app now
making you wait even longer?
Couldn't this app have
downloaded this content
automatically after the app
was installed?
For anyone on a slower
internet connection,
this might frustrate them
to close and remove the app.
The truth is,
this is not the experience
any of us want to have.
We know this isn't your fault,
and we believe we can make
this experience so much better!
This is why we're proud
to introduce to you this year,
Background Assets.
This framework was developed
to help you enrich the user
experience of your apps.
So that the moment
your app is launched,
it is providing a phenomenal
first impression!
Background Assets
is designed to be flexible
with your existing workflows.
A lot of you
have already developed
complex asset management
systems,
and we wanted this new framework
to easily fit into the solutions
that you have already developed.
We also know that you want to
be able to push updated content
to your apps without having to
require an additional submission
to the App Store.
It's not uncommon
for games or other apps
to need additional content after
the app has already shipped.
Think updated art textures
or a bug fix in game-level data.
Background Assets provides you
with the ability to schedule
and update your assets
outside of your app's lifecycle.
We believe it's important
that assets are present
before first app launch,
or whenever the app
is updated overnight.
So we've worked to create
a mechanism to help ensure
that your content is present by
the time your app is launched.
And finally, the easier
a framework is to adopt,
the more we can encourage you
to use it in your apps.
We want Background Assets
to be used in any place
where large assets
need to be predownloaded.
That way, we can minimize
the time your app is waiting
and showing a progress bar
before its content is available.
So you may be wondering,
how is this new framework
helping you solve this problem?
Well, in order to be
as extensible as possible,
we've created
a new app extension
for downloading content
in the background.
This new extension is built
on top of the powerful
app extension technology
that other extensions
on our platforms use.
This provides an opportunity
to run code
outside of the app's lifecycle.
For instance, the extension
will run whenever the user
first installs your app
but has yet to launch it.
The extension will also run
whenever the app is updated
automatically in the background.
This helps to ensure that
your content can be scheduled
and downloaded before the user
opens the application
after it has been updated.
Finally, the extension will run
periodically in the background,
allowing you to check
for updated assets
and schedule them
periodically over time.
Though it is important to note,
that extension runtime
is short-lived,
so all work will need to be
scheduled by your extension
with haste.
If downloads are not
scheduled quickly,
the system may terminate
the extension.
It's also important to be aware
that the frequency
of the extension's
ability to run periodically
will back off
based on app usage.
If your app isn't being used
very much,
then the extension will receive
less frequent runtime.
So that's an overview of the
new Background Assets framework.
It provides you with the tools
you need to ensure that
your assets are available by
the time your app is launched.
This is done
with an extension that runs
whenever your app
is installed or updated,
but before the user
has launched your app.
Now, let's take a look
at adopting
the Background Assets framework
into your project
and getting started!
The download manager
within the framework
is the primary vehicle
used to communicate
with the Background Assets
system service.
The manager
is a singleton object
that can be used
throughout your app.
Using the manager, you can
schedule the download
of your assets in either
the foreground or background.
You can also retrieve downloads
that are currently in flight,
which might have started
before your application
was ever launched.
Downloads can also be canceled.
This is useful if they were
already scheduled
or are in the middle of being
downloaded and you no longer
need that asset that you
originally requested.
We've also introduced
a synchronization mechanism
for managing exclusive access
between your app
and the extension
so that both the extension
and application do not end up
scheduling or modifying existing
downloads at the same time.
I have an example to show you,
but for now, more on this later!
Let's take a look at just
how easy it is to start using
Background Assets.
I'm going to begin
by walking you through
some of the basics of the API.
I'll then follow that up later
by showing you how to tie
all of this together
into an app extension.
To get started, you'll import
the Background Assets
framework module.
Then, it's as easy
as defining a URL that points
to the location of where
your remote asset is located.
We then follow that up by
defining an app group container
that your extension
and app are both members of.
Having your app and extension
in the same group
allows them to manage
your assets during the download
and after completion.
If you're not already
familiar with app groups,
you can easily add one from
the Signing & Capability section
of Xcode 14.
They're a powerful feature that
allows two or more applications
to access the same resources,
or in this case,
your app and its extension.
The next thing to do is create
your download object.
The Background Assets framework
is designed to support
multiple different types
of download objects.
However, in this example,
we'll be focusing on the most
common one: BAURLDownload.
Immediately, you'll notice that
the initializer takes in the URL
and the app group identifier.
This information
tells the system
both what we're downloading
and where the resulting file
will end up.
It also takes an identifier.
You'll use this identifier
to track your download
across multiple launches of your
app, and within the extension.
The engine will not allow
more than one download
to be scheduled
with the same identifier.
Therefore, you should make
these identifiers unique.
Next, we'll grab a reference
to the BADownloaderManager
shared object.
The download manager
is your single interface
into Background Assets.
It's what allows you to observe,
cancel, and schedule downloads.
We'll then pass it a weak
reference to a delegate
that conforms to the
BADownloadManagerDelegate
protocol.
I'll go more into
this protocol shortly,
but the most important part
to know now is that it receives
messages about downloads
that have been scheduled.
The only thing left to do
is to ask the download manager
to schedule the download.
If for any reason the download
cannot be scheduled,
then an error is thrown.
In addition to scheduling
downloads in the background,
we also provide API for doing
foreground downloads.
Running in the foreground
not only gives you
increased priority,
but it also enables your
download to begin immediately.
This is similar to using the
default session configuration
within URLSession.
We provide this API
so that your app can promote
any downloads scheduled by your
extension in the background
to the foreground.
One thing to keep in mind:
performing a foreground
download is not available
from within the extension;
it can only be initiated
from the app.
Since extensions
never present UI,
and the user doesn't notice
that they are running,
extensions may only schedule
downloads in the background.
If your app
would like to promote
existing background downloads
to the foreground,
this can easily be accomplished
by fetching the list
of currently active downloads
from the manager.
The list that is returned
contains all downloads
the are currently scheduled,
which may include downloads
in flight or queued up
in the scheduler.
Next, your app can begin
the promotion process
by calling
startForegroundDownload.
If a download is already
in the foreground,
calling this method
will effectively do nothing.
However, if the download
was backgrounded,
it will first be paused,
then resumed in the foreground
without requiring any content
that was already downloaded
up until this point
to be redownloaded.
Together,
this provides an effective
and simple illustration
for how easy it is
to use Background Assets to
promote downloads
scheduled in the background
to the foreground.
It really is as simple as that!
The download manager is your
primary interface that is used
to schedule and monitor
background downloads.
As these download objects
are processed by the system,
you'll receive messages
in your delegate object.
Let's walk through
the delegate now.
The delegate receives messages
for all downloads
that have been scheduled
by either the extension
or your app.
If there are numerous downloads
that were scheduled,
callbacks will be received
for all of them.
This is where you use
the download object's
unique identifier
to distinguish between them.
Your app will begin
to receive callbacks
the moment the delegate
is established
on BADownloadManager.
Callbacks are not enqueued
by the system.
If your app does not handle
one of the delegate methods
or your delegate
is not established,
then your extension will wake
to process the message.
This means that you should
fully expect your extension
to be sent messages if you have
not established a delegate
onto BADownloadManager
within your app.
If your app is currently
in the foreground
being presented to the user
and its delegate
has been established,
then callbacks will be sent
to your app
and the extension
will not be woken.
The extension will only wake
if your app does not handle
its delegate callback.
If a download finishes,
or fails,
and the app does not
process this message,
then the extension will wake.
Keep in mind,
the extension is not woken
for all types of callbacks.
Only callbacks that share
common interfaces
between
BADownloadManagerDelegate
and the BADownloaderExtension
protocol.
A download succeeding or failing
is an example
of a common interface between
the delegate and the protocol.
Although your app extension
has its own entry points
that cause it to wake,
if the extension
is currently running,
it can use BADownloadManager
and establish a delegate.
This will allow both
the app and extension
to receive duplicate messages
to their delegates.
Keep in mind
that extensions do not wake
to process delegate messages.
They only wake at extension
entry points defined in the
BADownloaderExtension protocol.
Let's take a look
at the protocol
for the download manager's
delegate.
The first function
is for receiving messages
whenever a download starts.
This is useful for tracking when
the device has finally chosen
to schedule a specific download.
You may also be notified
if a download pauses.
An example of
a pause occurring would be
if the extension starts
a download in the background
and then your app asks us
to promote it to the foreground.
During this promotion
there will be a small window
where the download pauses
before it is resumed.
The download manager
also allows you to monitor
active progress of your download
as it is being downloaded
in the foreground.
We also provide a mechanism
to answer a challenge request,
which is useful for validating
the authenticity of a connection
or for providing credentials
to authorize a connection.
The most important functions
are for dealing with a failed
or finished download.
If a download fails,
you may need to reschedule it
or determine the cause.
For a successful download,
the system has placed
the file in a location
that is managed
by the operating system.
If the device ends up
low on space,
then the system
will delete the file for you.
We strongly recommend that you
leave the file at the location
that the system has provided.
Only move the file
if you absolutely must
and please do not duplicate it
unless you delete
the originating file afterwards.
As a reminder, the protocol for
the download manager's delegate
is for receiving messages
related to downloads
that your app or extension
has scheduled.
It is not the entry point
for your extension,
which brings us
to our next topic.
Now we'll be taking a look
at the most exciting part
of Background Assets,
the extension!
The extension enables you
to schedule the downloads
of your assets before the user
has launched your app.
This enables you to ensure
that your assets are in place
and ready to go
in order to provide
the best possible experience in
your app with minimal wait time.
As discussed earlier, we're
introducing a new app extension.
This extension can be created
from within Xcode
inside of your existing project.
As a quick reminder,
the extension runs
whenever your app
is installed or updated.
Giving you the flexibility
to make sure changes to your app
always has its latest assets.
The extension
also runs periodically
based on how often
a user uses your app.
If someone uses your app
everyday,
then the system
learns this behavior
and your extension
will run more frequently.
However, if the app
is never launched,
then the frequency of this
periodic check will subside.
The new extension
also has a short lifecycle
and a tight sandbox to ensure
that its usage is limited
to just downloading assets.
You are encouraged to make
quick decisions in the extension
and to limit the extension to
the Background Assets framework.
Before we start navigating
through the extension,
there are a couple of
configurations
that you need to make
before the extension can launch.
These changes are
also a requirement
for your app to be approved for
distribution on the App Store.
In your app's
information property list,
you'll need to define
a couple of additional keys.
These keys should not be placed
in the extension's Info.plist,
only the app's.
The first key is
BAInitialDownloadRestrictions.
This is a dictionary where you
will be specifying restrictions
that will be placed
upon your extension.
These restrictions are reviewed
by App Review,
so try to be as accurate
as possible.
Now, let's dig into
each individual key
inside the dictionary.
The first restriction
is the download allowance.
This is represented in bytes
and is the maximum download size
you're requesting to make
within the extension
during an initial app install.
This size pertains to the sum
of all files combined
that you are requesting
to download,
not the size
of each individual file.
The next item is
the domain AllowList,
which takes an array of domains
represented as strings.
The domain AllowList supports
prefix wildcards and takes in
a list of host names
that your extension
is permitted to download from.
It's important to note
that the keys in the
BAInitialDownloadRestrictions,
such as the DownloadAllowance
and AllowList are only enforced
after first app install.
Whenever your app is launched,
these restrictions
are no longer enforced.
The last required key,
which sits at the root
of your Info.plist
is the maximum size
that your app will require
in additional storage
for these assets.
We expect that you might want
to download compressed assets,
so this value should be
the final extracted
uncompressed size.
The number that is placed here
will be presented
on the App Store
before the app is downloaded.
Now that we've gone over
some housekeeping,
let's talk about the entry
points into your extension
in more detail.
The functions that you define
from the protocol
will be called by the system
and not by your app.
Unlike other app extensions,
where the application
is responsible
for talking to the extension,
the background
download extension
is brokered by the system.
Since the system is maintaining
the lifecycle of the extension,
it should be viewed
as an ephemeral service.
Whenever any of the functions
inside of the protocol
are invoked,
it's important to keep
the work that is done there
to a minimum.
The extension will be terminated
rather quickly
after it is launched.
This is not the place
to kick off decompression
or other complex operations
that may take a while.
One of the great parts
of working in the extension
is that all of the
BackgroundAssets APIs
available to your app are also
available within the extension.
With the only exception being
the ForegroundDownload API.
This means that you'll use
BADownloadManager
just like you would in your app.
As a matter of fact,
it's entirely likely
that you'll discover
the ability to create something
that uses the same code to
schedule and manage your assets
in both your app
and its extension.
Also, when creating
your extension,
it's important to ensure that
both are in a common app group.
You'll want to use
the same group identifier
so that content can be read
and written by your app
and its extension.
Now let's take a look at the
downloader extension protocol
that you will be conforming
your extension to.
The first thing you'll notice
is how similar it looks
to the download manager
delegate protocol.
As I stated earlier,
you can use BADownloadManager
and construct a delegate
from within the extension.
However, only these entry points
can actually wake the extension.
The first function is invoked
whenever your application
is first installed.
The app hasn't launched yet,
but your extension has.
This is the perfect opportunity
to start scheduling downloads
that your app needs
to provide the best experience
once your app has been launched.
It's also important to recall
that during initial app install,
download restrictions
are in effect.
You'll want to consult
the BADownloadRestrictions key
that you defined
in your Info.plist
to know what your maximum
permitted download size
and allowed domains are.
This next function is invoked
whenever the App Store
updates your app.
As long as the user hasn't quit
your app in the app switcher,
your newly updated
extension will wake
and you can begin
scheduling work.
The checkForUpdates function
provides support
for your extension being
periodically awoken
by the system, so that you
can check for any updates
that need to be background
downloaded.
This function is invoked
by the system based on
how often a user uses your app.
We also have support
for responding
to an authentication
challenge request.
So that you can better
restrict and ensure
that the files
you are downloading
have come from a trusted source.
Finally, just like the delegate,
you'll be informed if the
download failed or succeeded.
You'll notice that in the
backgroundDownloadDidFail
function,
there is no error returned.
The error can be retrieved
along with its state
in a variable inside of
the returned BADownload object.
It's also important to note
that the last three functions
can be invoked
even if your extension
isn't what scheduled
the download.
If your app scheduled
a download,
but hasn’t become backgrounded,
then the extension
will be expected
to service the download.
Now that we understand
how to use BADownloaderManager
from our app and its extension,
we have to start thinking about
what it means if both the app
and its extension
are running simultaneously.
For instance, let's say
the system has decided
that it's time
to wake the extension
to have it periodically
check for updates.
And of course, since the
extension needs to access
the network to do this check,
it's going to use
BADownloaderManager to schedule
the download of a catalog
or some other type of metadata
that provides a list
of updated assets
that are available.
For instance, let's say the file
is a small 100KB catalog
that contains a list
of large multi-gigabyte assets
that we need to download.
Since the extension
needs to know
when the download it has
scheduled finished, or failed,
it's going to attach a delegate
onto the download manager.
The download manager's
delegate is used
over its extension entry points
since its downloading
a small file to determine
what larger assets it
will be scheduling,
and extension entry points
are not guaranteed
to be invoked immediately.
After the download
has finished,
the extension receives this
message through its delegate.
Your extension now has access
to the catalog file
and has to make a choice
with what it plans to do
with the downloaded file.
You could imagine that the
extension will read the file
to determine which of the assets
in the catalog
need to be downloaded
to the device.
Then the extension could
schedule background downloads
of those larger assets.
Now that the downloaded file
is no longer necessary,
the extension should delete
the file.
While this seems appropriate,
what happens if your app
launches while your extension
is running and creates its own
BADownloadManager?
Well, let's take a look!
The app launches
and immediately wants to know
if it has updated content.
Perhaps a version number
is stored in the app group
that both consult to determine
if their assets are up to date.
Since the app was launched
before the newer catalog
finished downloading,
it's going to fetch
the current downloads
from the manager
and realize that a download
of the catalog
is currently in flight
and wait for it to be finished
in its delegate.
But we have a problem.
Both the extension
and the app will receive
a download finished message
in their respective delegates
that were hooked into
the download manager.
This means we have a data race
on the file being downloaded.
Both the app and extension will
try to read and delete the file
at the same time;
this is not good.
This means that either
your app or extension
could try to read the file
and it might be missing.
This means that you will need
think about your app
and extension in a similar way
that you would think about
two threads within your app.
Luckily, Background Assets
provides a way to synchronize
between your app
and its extension.
Let's talk about that now!
Synchronizing between
your app and its extension
is extremely simple
with Background Assets.
What we're currently looking at
is the download manager's
delegate function for when
a download has completed.
A URL is provided that contains
a local path to the file
that your app or extension
has access to.
In this example, we'll be
ensuring mutual exclusion
of this file.
Next, we grab a reference
to the download manager
and use the
withExclusiveControl function,
which takes
a completion handler.
All code that is executed within
the completion handler scope
is guaranteed to be mutually
exclusive with other calls
that require exclusive control.
Meaning if your extension calls
withExclusiveControl
while you app has not returned
from its completion handler,
then the extension will wait.
This applies in the other
direction as well.
If the extension acquires
exclusive control first,
then the app will wait until
the extension is terminated
or releases control
by exiting scope.
An important thing
to keep in mind
is that acquiring exclusive
control can fail.
It is extremely unlikely
that this will occur,
but in the event it does,
your code should handle it.
You can detect if exclusive
control could not be acquired
by checking if the error
provided by the function
is not nil.
From this point on,
you are guaranteed that your app
or extension has exclusive
access within its context.
So based on our
earlier example,
it is now perfectly valid to
read the contents of the file
and then clean it up,
if you so choose.
Just make sure to be aware that
when your other app or extension
gets its opportunity
to enter exclusive control
that it knows that you have
already processed the file.
One way this can be accomplished
is by first checking
if the file exists or writing
to a database or plist.
As a reminder, the background
downloader extension
is for collecting and scheduling
the downloads of large assets
for your app.
Its runtime is short lived,
so please keep
the work that is done
within the extension
to a minimum.
You should also place
your extension and app
within a shared app group
so that both can access files
that are downloaded
by one another.
And finally, the extension
is brokered by the system
and not your app.
Now that you know
how to develop
a basic background
download extension,
you have everything you need
to start implementing
Background Assets into your app.
Now, let's go over
what we've learned.
The download manager is used
to coordinate and schedule
downloads between your app
and its extension,
therefore you should be using
the download manager
in both places.
Your extension runs even if your
app is not in the foreground.
This can occur during
app installation, update,
or periodically at an interval
determined by the system.
If your app is launched
and content that was being
downloaded in the background
is now be waited on,
please immediately promote those
downloads to the foreground.
The extension can only schedule
downloads in the background.
By having your app promote them
to the foreground,
ensures that your content will
arrive as quickly as possible.
If you ever find yourself
needing exclusive access
to the download manager, please
use the exclusive control APIs.
This will ensure that only
your app or extension
will have runtime
within that window.
This is extremely useful so that
you don't have to think about
your extension racing your app
when accessing its container
or managing downloads.
If there is anything you should
take from this presentation,
it's that waiting results
in a poor app experience.
Minimize waiting
by making your app usable
while the task
you are waiting on is underway.
One of the ways you can
minimize waiting in your app
is to adopt the new
Background Assets framework
along with the underlying
background download extension.
This helps to ensure
that your app will have
all of its content ready
before the app is launched.
Make sure to also check out
the documentation,
which includes extra information
that may not have been
incorporated into
this presentation;
including how to test
your extension
and to simulate
its entry points.
We're really excited
to get to share
Background Assets with you,
and we value your feedback.
Please use Feedback Assistant
to let us know
what is working for you
and what you'd like us improve.
This is a new framework
and we have the opportunity
to make adjustments
during seeding.
We have
some additional sessions
that we think you might
find interesting
and we encourage you
to check them out.
"Accelerating networking with
HTTP3" is a fantastic session
that pairs well with
Background Assets.
Also, I encourage you
to check out another session:
the "Introducing on demand
resources" presentation
covers an alternative
to Background Assets
where your content
is hosted by Apple
and files are downloaded
at your request.
Both of these sessions
are really engaging
and have a lot to offer.
Thank you for spending
your time with me,
and on behalf of everyone
at Apple,
we hope you have
a fantastic WWDC!
♪