♪ ♪
Hello, everyone,
my name is MaryAshley Etefia,
and I'm a software engineer
for Screen Time.
The COVID-19 pandemic put
a lot of pressure on our industry
to respond to the growing demand for
digital health and productivity resources.
The pandemic reinforced
society's need for balance
and has put everyone's ability
to successfully manage their own space
to the test.
Last year, we introduced to you all
the Screen Time API,
which allowed you to build
new apps to help your users
manage their child's relationship
with their device.
We were very pleased to see
the creative and productive ways
that you all have made use of our product.
It excites us to see you embracing
our culture of thinking differently.
We are also very thankful for the feedback
we have received in the past year.
Before I introduce to you all
what's new in iOS 16's ScreenTime API,
I would first like to recap
some highlights from our iOS 15 release.
Last year's Screen Time API
introduced three new frameworks:
Family Controls,
Managed Settings, and Device Activity.
In iOS 15, these frameworks
brought new capabilities
to your parental control apps.
To jog your memory,
let's take quick look at all three.
Family Controls is essentially a gateway
since it authorizes access
to the Screen Time API.
This framework allowed you
to prevent removal
of your parental control app,
and it protected user privacy
by providing opaque tokens
used to identify apps and websites.
With ManagedSettings,
your app could apply restrictions,
filter web traffic, and shield activity,
much like Screen Time does,
but customized with your app's
branding and functionality.
The Device Activity framework
allowed you to execute code on the start
and end of timing windows,
as well as whenever usage
of an app or website exceeded a threshold.
Each of these three frameworks have had
some exciting new updates in iOS 16.
These updates are not only going to make
our API easier for you to use
but are also going to enhance
the experience of our users.
I'll walk you through the details
using our demo application, Worklog.
Worklog encourages good habits
for new professionals by restricting
access to certain apps
until a certain usage metric is met.
I would like to show you how Aniyah,
the owner of this iPhone,
can impose these restrictions on herself
using iOS 16's ScreenTime API.
Lets start with Family Controls.
If you remember from iOS 15,
Family Controls was only capable
of authorizing child devices
via iCloud authentication.
We are happy to inform you that in iOS 16,
Family Controls is now capable
of authorizing independent users
from their own device.
This new authorization method
means the Screen Time API can be
used to build more than
just parental controls apps.
Unlike the existing
parental control authorization,
individual authorization can be
used by any number of apps per device.
Also, since individual authorization
is not for parental control use cases,
implicit restrictions for iCloud sign-out
and deletion of an app do not apply.
Let's look at how to use
the new authorization.
The first thing your app needs to do
on launch is request authorization
for FamilyControls.
I will use a shared Authorization Center
to make this request
when Worklog first launches.
The request can either result
in updating the authorization status
or throwing an error.
Since this app has never been
run on this iPhone before,
requestAuthorization will ask
for Aniyah's approval with an alert.
Tapping on Allow will then prompt
the user to authenticate
with Face ID, Touch ID,
or device passcode to continue.
Once the user
has successfully authenticated,
calling requestAuthorization again
will not prompt with an alert again,
but instead silently succeed.
Once an app has
authorized with Family Controls,
two switches are added
in Settings for the app.
One in Screen Time, under
the Apps with Screen Time Access List
and one in per app settings,
labeled as Screen Time Restrictions.
Parents and individual users can
choose to deauthorize the app
from Family Controls
via either of these switches.
As you can see,
using the new individual authorization
is just as simple as using
the parental controls authorization,
and we've made some nice improvements
to both with our use of async.
Now, lets look at the new changes
to Managed Settings.
Managed Settings has been revamped
to make developer use a lot more easy,
particularly in the use
of Managed Settings Store.
For those of you who are unfamiliar,
a Managed Settings Store is a data store
that applies settings
to the current user or device.
In iOS 15, you could only have
one Managed Settings Store per process.
Also, your app
and device activity extensions
had to have
different Managed Settings Stores.
This made it difficult to change settings
in response to device activity.
Now, in iOS 16, you can create
up to 50 Managed Settings Stores
per process,
each with their own unique name.
These named stores are also
automatically shared between
your app and all your app extensions.
Also, you can now remove all the settings
in any given named store all at once.
I'd like to show you
how Worklog uses named stores.
When Worklog launches for the first time
and Aniyah's device has
been successfully authorized,
we create a Gaming ManagedSettingsStore.
This store will contain
our gaming restrictions,
which, in Worklog's case, includes
shielding for all gaming websites.
Worklog also has a store named "Social"
which shields social media
apps and websites as soon as
the app is launched for the first time.
However, when using Worklog,
Aniyah can click
the Allow for Evenings button,
which will create
a Device Activity Schedule
that only allows social media
between 5:00 and 8:00 p.m.
Once it's 5:00 p.m.,
our Device Activity Monitor un-restricts
the corresponding named store.
When the timing window ends at 8:00 p.m.,
we re-apply restrictions
to social media apps and websites
on Aniyah's device.
Now, some of you may be wondering,
"Didn't our Gaming store
restrict gaming websites?"
"Won't clearing all the settings
in our Social store
conflict with our settings
from our Gaming store?"
The answer is no.
The most restrictive setting always wins,
therefore Gaming websites will
still remain restricted
on Aniyah's device.
We feel that these new named stores
are extremely powerful
and will make it a lot simpler for you
to develop apps using Managed Settings.
But we're not done yet.
We've also added a very exciting feature
to the Device Activity framework.
In iOS 15,
Device Activity allowed your app
to respond to the start and end
of timing windows,
as well as usage thresholds
for apps and websites.
In iOS 16, Device Activity has
a new reporting service which enables
your app to create completely custom
usage reports using SwiftUI.
The usage data is provided to a new
extension point where you can customize
which data is shown to the user,
as well as how it's rendered on screen.
These device activity reports
allow for you to completely
customize your user's experience,
whilst providing the end user
with complete privacy.
In Worklog, you can see us establish
a DeviceActivityReport.Context
and a DeviceActivityFilter.
You can think
of a DeviceActivityReport.Context
as a customizable type
that tells your report
what type of view to draw
based on DeviceActivity Data.
You can customize the timing windows
of whichever report context
by specifying a DeviceActivityFilter.
We will then set the definition
of our device activity report context
inside of our DeviceActivityReportScene
in order to tell the scene
what to represent.
Our content defines our custom
configuration, PieChartView.Configuration,
as well as the resulting
SwiftUI view for this report.
Then, inside of makeConfiguration, we will
map over Aniyah's DeviceActivity Data,
in order to hydrate
our pie chart view's configuration.
The framework will invoke
makeConfiguration
whenever new usage data is fetched
so you do not need to invoke it yourself.
Here, you can see
how PieChartView.Configuration
serves as a view model
for our pie chart view
by providing the view
with Aniyah's device activity data.
Finally, we are able to render
our custom SwiftUI report
by defining it in the body
of our DeviceActivityReport extension.
The pie chart report that we created
for Worklog is just one
of the exciting ways that you can
customize device activity reports.
That concludes our briefing
of what's new to iOS 16's Screen Time API.
As you can see,
the Screen Time API continues to support
features like core restrictions
and device activity monitoring
in the same secure yet privacy-preserving
way that we first launched it.
To recap,
independent users can now authorize
with Family Controls with the option
of authorizing multiple third party
applications per device,
Managed Settings Stores now
locally share settings between apps
and their app extensions,
and as a result,
you are now allowed to manage
multiple named stores in your application,
and finally, the Device Activity framework
is introducing a new privacy-preserving UI
that reveals usage data to users
and is customizable.
We believe that these new enhancements
and additions will broaden
the amount of users capable
of engaging with your application.
Thank you for inspiring this new release
and thank you
for your future contributions
to the digital health
and productivity space.
We cannot wait to see the new
and exciting ways that you make use
of the Screen Time API.
We welcome any feedback that you have
and we will continue working to make this
technology more accessible
for you as well as our users.
Thank you.