♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hello, my name is John, and I'm
an engineer on the Xcode Cloud team.
And I'm Jo Lynn,
a designer on the Xcode Cloud team.
Today we're going to take a look
at some of the features of Xcode Cloud
that are super helpful when
you're using Xcode Cloud
as part of a team,
whether that's a team of 5 or 500.
And I'm going to share
some other features and best practices
that work well when you use
Xcode Cloud as part of a team.
In our session today,
we're going to go into detail
on some topics which are also covered
in some other sessions.
If you want to learn more about webhooks
and other advanced workflow topics,
check out the "Customize your advanced
Xcode Cloud workflows" session.
In this session, we're going to look
at how we can integrate Xcode Cloud
into your existing tools and technologies
that you use every day,
easily manage your code dependencies,
and showcase Xcode Cloud best practices
to help you set up workflows
to continuously build, test,
and distribute your apps effectively.
Let's get started.
When it comes to integrating Xcode Cloud
into your existing tools,
we have a couple of options.
Webhooks allow easy integration with tools
and services that support them.
You can connect a webhook
in App Store Connect
by telling Xcode Cloud what URL to send
the webhook to,
and you should start
to see those webhooks come in right away.
Our API also allows a great amount
of visibility into your builds,
allowing you to do things
like easily create build dashboards,
extract your build artifacts,
or, in our example today,
integrate build information
into your existing software.
We've been building out a bunch
of new features for our food truck app,
but we've also been finding new bugs,
and now that we have a team of people
working on the app together,
we've found it difficult
to understand who is working on what.
To solve this problem,
we've decided to use an issue tracker
to track all of the work
going on in our app.
If you're using an issue tracker,
you often have a view like this.
A common workflow with issue trackers
is to create a ticket,
have designers and developers
work on that ticket,
and finally, close it once the feature
or bug is complete.
Having the actual build information
shown in our issue tracker
would be a big help in connecting
all the dots together.
Let's take a look
at how we might do that now.
Our plan here is to create a very simple
Swift On Server-based service
that will handle everything we need
to integrate our issue tracker
with Xcode Cloud.
To speed up development,
we'll use the Vapor web framework,
which will let us focus on writing
the webhook handling code.
The basic flow will look something
like this.
A webhook will come
from Xcode Cloud to our server.
We will read that webhook
and check if the commit message
written by the committer
has a certain string in it
which maps to an issue in our tracker.
If it does, we'll hit the Xcode Cloud API
to gather more information
about the build.
Then we'll construct a comment we
can post onto our issue tracker
that contains the information
we're interested in.
We'll then call an API
on our issue tracker,
which will save the message
against our issue.
First, let's take a look
at the Xcode Cloud API documentation.
All of the Xcode Cloud API
lives under the App Store Connect API.
If we have already set up
authentication tokens
for the App Store Connect API,
we already have everything we need
to also access our Xcode Cloud data.
Opening up the Build Runs collection,
we can see some endpoints
that let us interact with our builds.
You can call an endpoint
to create a build,
cancel a build, or get more information
about a particular build.
For example, if you wanted to build
a dashboard
to show the status of your builds,
the Ci_Build_Runs endpoint
should be all we would need to call.
Next, let's look at the Artifacts
collection in the documentation.
For our workflow,
we want to keep our build artifacts
outside of Xcode Cloud, and the API
should have everything we need to do that.
First, we can get the artifact ID
from the build action endpoint,
which will return all the artifacts
produced for a given action.
Then we can call ci_artifact,
which will give us the URL we need
to download our artifact
in the downloadUrl attribute.
Let's start by downloading
the openAPI spec
from the App Store Connect documentation,
and go through what we need
to create our client for the API.
Let's create a new directory
where we can create our client code.
I'm going to call this xcodecloud-client.
Now we need to download
the command line tool for our generator.
There's lots of ways to do this on
the openAPI website, and for our session,
I've already set it up
Let's copy the openAPI spec
that we just got
from the app_store_connect_API
into our directory.
Great, now we can call
the openAPI generator
and tell it to create a swift client
for our API.
While the generator is running,
we can quickly talk about what it's doing.
An openAPI specification
is made up of information
about all the paths and models
that make up our API.
The generator is going
through each of the API paths
and generating Swift code that
can talk to that particular path,
with a strongly typed swift object.
In most cases,
this means you don't have to do
any JSON encoding or decoding.
Great, our generator is finished,
so let's take a quick look
at the files it created.
Conveniently,
the client code is a Swift package.
This makes it really easy to include
in our webhook server
that will update our issue tracker.
Now we can commit our code
to a new git repository,
and we can then reference this
as a Swift package.
Now that we've got everything
we need to talk with our API,
let's set up our webhook.
in App Store Connect,
we can register our webhook
that will let our server know
every time a build completes.
To do that, go to your product
in App Store Connect,
go to settings,
and navigate to webhooks.
And I'll paste in the URL for our server.
This will let Xcode Cloud know
where to send the webhooks.
With our web hook set up,
the only thing left to do
is write the code to process them,
so let's get started on that.
First we have to define a struct
which matches to the fields
we're interested in from our webhook.
The webhook will contain information
about the specific build being executed,
as well as each actions being performed,
so let's keep those
in our webhook payload struct.
Next, we have to create
the code to have Vapor correctly route
incoming webhooks to our function.
We'll define a function that runs
on a post request to the webhook path.
Inside this function, all we need to do
to convert the incoming JSON payload
into a strongly typed Swift object
is to decode it,
so we'll also add that code as well.
Great, now all we need to do is call
the Xcode Cloud API
to get a little bit more information
about the build which just completed
so that we can include it
on our issue tracker page.
The webhook payload contains
a lot of information
about the build which just ran,
and what actions succeeded or failed.
We could probably stop there,
but let's take it to the next level.
I think it would be amazing
if we also include information
about which issues were found
in each action.
We can write an extension function
to CiBuildActionsAPI
that gives us the ability to easily return
the issues we're interested in
for a particular action.
In this extension, we'll write a function
that takes the build action ID
as a parameter
and returns all the issues found
for a particular action.
I already have this in my project,
but let's fill in the rest of our code.
We only want our webhook handler
to run if the build is complete,
so let's guard against that.
Next we can start working
on our comment string.
I think it would be great to have
the build number, commit hash,
as well as the author in this string.
Now let's go through each action and call
our extension function
to get the issues for each action.
Let's pass this all on
to our issue tracker now.
With all of this information,
I think this will help us keep
our issue tracker
up to date with our builds.
And we're done!
At this point,
we want to host our server code
at the URL we provided
to Xcode Cloud for the webhooks,
and we should start to see Xcode Cloud
build information in our issue tracker.
Let's have a quick summary
about what we've learned so far.
Xcode Cloud has a great API you can use
to get an even deeper integration
with your existing development workflows.
You can use that API along with webhooks
to connect all the dots together
and integrate your existing tools
and technologies with Xcode Cloud.
Next, here's Jo to talk
about other features and best practices.
Jo: Thanks, John!
Xcode Cloud is designed to integrate
with Apple developer tools and services
that you use
to create apps and frameworks.
However, your Xcode project
may require additional dependencies
or external tools to compile your code.
Xcode Cloud works great
with Swift Package Manager.
It supports Swift package dependencies
without requiring
any additional configuration,
if the package's repository
is publicly accessible.
You can also make Xcode Cloud work
with third-party dependency managers
like Cocoapods and Carthage,
but you'll have to do a little extra work
by using custom build scripts.
You can refer to the Xcode documentation
for instructions
on how to make dependencies
available to Xcode Cloud.
Once we've added our Swift package
and pushed changes
to kick off the workflow,
we can go to the cloud tab
of the Report Navigator,
and view the status of our latest build.
Select Logs to view
the detailed build logs.
We'll see that Xcode Cloud has
automagically resolved the dependencies.
After Xcode Cloud has
successfully completed the first build,
you should plan next steps
for refining your continuous integration
and delivery practice
to make sure that your app or framework
is always in a shippable state.
In this section, I'm going to talk
about how you can use
Xcode Cloud with SwiftLint
for static code analysis,
how to restrict editing on your workflows,
and the value of configuring
multiple start conditions.
SwiftLint is an open source linter tool
that enforces
style guide rules and conventions
generally accepted by the Swift community.
It performs static code analysis
to improve your code quality
and prevent bad practices.
We have found that SwiftLint
is a great way
to keep your team's codebase consistent,
especially when working with larger teams.
What we're going to show now
is how to integrate SwiftLint
with Xcode Cloud
using a custom build script.
We want Xcode Cloud to run
the SwiftLint tool
after it clones our source code
from the team's primary repository.
In the Project navigator,
I've already added a post_clone script
in my ci_scripts folder
to my Food Truck project.
The Xcode Cloud build environment
includes Homebrew,
and that's what we're using
here to install SwiftLint.
On this line, we are executing SwiftLint.
One thing to remember is that the script
executes within the ci_scripts directory,
so we have to tell SwiftLint
to run within the ci_workspace
environment variable,
which points to our repository.
Let's check out
the result of the code analysis.
Looks like SwiftLint found
a bunch of violations,
15 of them serious.
Since this is the first time
we're integrating our tools,
I'm going to temporarily deactivate
this workflow
so that we can have a discussion
with the rest of our team first,
come up with an agreement
about coding styles and conventions,
and then decide as a team
which issues we want to fix.
You can deactivate a workflow in Xcode
from the Manage Workflows menu.
Doing so will stop the start conditions
from working,
and only manual builds can be started.
Now that our static code analysis workflow
has been deactivated,
we can focus on fixing the issues
we want to fix.
Then we can come back
and enable this workflow.
Our team has been growing rapidly,
and we want to make conscious choices
about workflow configurations.
Because I'm responsible
for maintaining and managing
all of our team's workflows,
I don't want team members to make
unintentional changes to a workflow.
That takes a lot of time to undo.
To prevent unintentional changes,
you can restrict who can make edits
to your workflow.
Select the workflow, then choose
Restrict Editing from the context menu.
Anyone in the team
can use or run this workflow,
but only administrators,
account holders, and app managers
can enforce a restriction,
which makes it editable only by them.
A workflow where editing is
restricted will have a 'key' symbol.
This means that it is locked
and can only be edited by you
and other administrative users.
If you see a 'lock' symbol instead,
this means that it has been locked
by an administrator
and cannot be edited by you.
This feature makes it easy
to manage access for complex workflows,
especially if you're part of a large team.
We've just learned how easy it is
to pause or lock down our workflows.
Now let's talk about workflow management
and maintenance.
I want to run the same tests
and archive actions
whenever I make a pull request
or when I merge my branch.
The best way to do so is
through multiple start conditions.
This improves the maintenance of workflows
because it reduces the number of workflows
that you'll need to create and manage.
To illustrate, in this example,
I want to kick off a build
given the following conditions:
if there are changes in the main branch
or the release branch,
or if there's a scheduled build
for the main branch, then,
run the same set
of archive and test actions
as well as deploy
to TestFlight for internal testing.
Instead of creating 3 workflows,
then managing them
and keeping them in sync,
I'd create a single workflow specifying
all the start conditions in one go.
This improves manageability,
especially when the team has
many workflows to maintain.
Configuring start conditions
in Xcode is easy.
From the workflow editor, pick the type
of start conditions
from the + button menu.
Xcode Cloud in App Store Connect
provides a fully featured
web-based experience.
Everything that I just did
in Xcode to configure our workflow,
from deactivating it and locking it down,
to setting up multiple start conditions,
are also available from AppStoreConnect.
Xcode Cloud is a powerful,
continuous integration & delivery service
built right into Xcode that helps
development teams of any size
and can easily be integrated
with your existing tools and processes
to help you deliver high-quality apps
for your users.
To the Xcode Cloud beta participants,
we really appreciate your feedback
and look forward to hearing more.
We hope these features
can help you refine
your team's continuous integration
& delivery practice.
Thank you for watching,
and have a great WWDC!
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪