♪ ♪
Hi, my name is Brett Keating,
and it's my pleasure to be introducing you
to what is new in the Vision framework.
You may be new to Vision.
Perhaps this is the first session
you've seen about the Vision framework.
If so, welcome.
For your benefit, let's briefly recap some
highlights about the Vision framework.
Some Vision framework facts for you.
Vision was first introduced in 2017,
and since then, many thousands
of great apps have been developed
with the technology Vision provides.
Vision is a collection
of computer vision algorithms
that continues to grow over time
and includes such things
as face detection,
image classification,
and contour detection to name a few.
Each of these algorithms is made available
through an easy-to-use, consistent API.
If you know how to run one algorithm
in the Vision framework,
you know how to run them all.
And Vision takes full advantage
of Apple Silicon
on all of the platforms it supports,
to power the machine learning at the core
of many of Vision's algorithms.
Vision is available on tvOS,
iOS, and macOS;
and will fully leverage
Apple Silicon on the Mac.
Some recent additions to the Vision
framework include Person segmentation,
shown here.
Also hand pose estimation,
shown in this demo.
And here is our
Action and Vision sample app,
which uses body pose estimation
and trajectory analysis.
Our agenda today begins
with an overview of some new revisions,
which are updates to existing requests
that may provide increased functionality,
improve performance, or improve accuracy.
First, we have a new revision
for text recognition.
This is the third revision,
given by VNRecognizeTextRequestRevision3.
This is the text recognizer
that powers the amazing Live Text feature.
The text recognizer supports
several languages,
and you may discover
which languages are supported
by calling supportedRecognitionLanguages.
We have now added a few new languages,
and I'll show you a couple examples.
We are now supporting
the Korean language in Vision.
Here is an example of Vision at work
transcribing a Korean receipt.
And here is a corresponding example
for Japanese,
also showing the results
of Vision's text recognition
on this now-supported language.
For text recognition, we have
a new automatic language identification.
You may still specify
the recognition languages to use
using the recognitionLanguages property.
But suppose you don't know
ahead of time which languages
your app user might be trying
to recognize.
Now, but only
for accurate recognition mode,
you may ask the text recognizer
to automatically detect the language
by setting
automaticallyDetectsLanguage to true.
It's best to use this
just for such a situation
where you don't know
which language to recognize,
because the language detection
can occasionally get this wrong.
If you have the prior knowledge
about which language to recognize,
it's still best to specify
these languages to Vision
and leave automaticallyDetectsLanguage
turned off.
Next, we have a new third revision
for our barcode detection,
called VNDetectBarcodesRequestRevision3.
This revision leverages
modern machine learning under the hood,
which is a departure from prior revisions.
Barcodes come in a variety of symbologies,
from barcodes often seen on products
in stores, to QR codes,
to specialty codes
used in healthcare applications.
In order to know
which symbologies Vision supports,
you may call supportedSymbologies.
Let's talk about performance.
Partly because we are using ML,
we are detecting multiple codes
in one shot rather than one at a time,
so the request will be faster
for images containing multiple codes.
Also, more codes are detected
in a given image containing many codes,
due to increased accuracy.
And furthermore, there are few,
if any, duplicate detections.
The bounding boxes are
improved for some codes,
particularly linear codes such as ean13,
for which a line was formerly returned.
Now, the bounding box surrounds
the entire visible code.
Finally, the ML model is more able
to ignore such things as curved surfaces,
reflections, and other artifacts that have
hindered detection accuracy in the past.
Both of these new revisions,
for text recognition
and for barcode detection,
form the technological foundations
for the VisionKit Data Scanner API,
which is a drop-in UI element
that sets up the camera stream
to scan and return barcodes and text.
It's really a fantastic addition
to our SDK,
and I highly recommend you check out
the session about it to learn more.
The final new revision I'll tell you
about today is a new revision
for our optical flow request called
VNGenerateOpticalFlowRequestRevision2.
Like the barcode detector,
this new revision also uses
modern machine learning under the hood.
Although optical flow is one of the
longest studied computer vision problems,
you might not be aware of what it does,
compared to detection of things
which form part of all of our daily lives,
like text and barcodes.
Optical flow analyzes
two consecutive images,
typically frames from a video.
Depending on your use case,
you might look at motion
between two adjacent frames,
or skip a few frames in between,
but in any case, the two images
should be in chronological order.
The analysis provides an estimate of
the direction and magnitude of the motion,
or by how much parts of the first image
need to "move," so to speak,
to be positioned correctly
in the second image.
A VNPixelBufferObservation is the result,
which represents this motion
at all places in the image.
It is a two-channel image.
One channel contains the X magnitude,
and the other contains the Y magnitude.
Together, these form 2D vectors
at each pixel
arranged in this 2D image
so that their locations map
to corresponding locations in the images
that were provided as input.
Let's have a look at this visually.
Suppose you have an incoming video
and several frames are coming in,
but let's look
at these two images in particular.
Here we have a dog running on the beach.
From the left image to the right image,
it appears the dog has moved
a bit to the left.
How would you estimate
and represent this motion?
Well, you would run optical flow
and arrive at something
akin to the image below.
The darker areas are
where motion has been found,
and notice that it does indeed
look just like the shape of the dog.
That's because only the dog
is really moving in this scene.
We are showing the motion vectors
in this image by using "false color,"
which maps the x,y
from the vectors into a color palette.
In this false color representation,
"red" hues happen to indicate
movement primarily to the left.
Now that you've seen
an example from one frame,
let's see how it looks
for a whole video clip.
Here we compute optical flow
for a short clip of this dog
fetching a water bottle on a beach.
On the left is the result from revision 1.
On the right is the result
from our new ML-based revision 2.
Hopefully some of the improvements
in revision 2 are clear to see.
For one thing, perhaps most obviously,
the water bottle's motion is captured
much more accurately.
You might also notice improvements in
some of the estimated motion of the dog.
I notice improvements
in the tail most clearly
but also can see the motion of his ears
flapping in the new revision.
The first revision also contains
a bit of background noise motions,
while the second revision more coherently
represents the backgrounds as not moving.
Hopefully that example gave you
a good idea what this technology does.
Now let's dive in a bit
on how you might use it in your app.
Clearly the primary use case is
to discover local motion in a video.
This feeds directly
into security video use cases,
where it's most important to identify
and localize motions
that deviate from the background,
and it should be mentioned
that optical flow does work best
for stationary cameras,
such as most security cameras.
You might want to use
Vision's object tracker
to track objects
that are moving in a video,
but need to know
where to initialize a tracker.
Optical flow can help you there as well.
If you have some computer vision
or image processing savvy of your own,
you might leverage
our optical flow results
to enable further video processing.
Video interpolation,
or video action analysis,
can greatly benefit from
the information optical flow provides.
Let's now dig into some
important additional differences
between revision 1 and revision 2.
Revision 1 always returns
optical flow fields
that have the same resolution
as the input.
Revision 2 will also do this by default.
However, there is a tiny wrinkle:
partially due to the fact
that revision 2 is ML-based,
the output of the underlying model
is relatively low resolution
compared to most input image resolutions.
Therefore, to match
revision 1 default behavior,
some upsampling must be done,
and we are using
bilinear upsampling to do this.
Here is a visual example
explaining what upsampling does.
On the left, we have a zoomed-in portion
of the network output,
which is low resolution
and therefore appears pixelated.
The overall flow field might have
an aspect ratio of 7:5.
On the right, we have a similar region
taken from the same field,
upsampled to the original
image resolution.
Perhaps that image also has
a different aspect ratio, let's say 16:9.
You will notice that the edges
of the flow field are smoothed out
by the bilinear upsampling.
Due to the potential
for the aspect ratios to differ,
keep in mind that as part
of the upsampling process,
the flow image will be stretched
in order to properly correspond
the flow field
to what is happening in the image.
When working
with the network output directly,
you should account for resolution
and aspect ratio in a similar fashion
when mapping flow results
to the original images.
You have the option to skip the upsampling
by turning on keepNetworkOutput
on the request.
This will give you the raw model output.
There are four computationAccuracy
settings you may apply to the request
in order to choose
an available output resolution.
You can see the resolutions
for each accuracy setting in this table,
but be sure to always check
the width and height of the pixel buffer
contained in the observation.
When should you use network output,
and when should you allow Vision
to upsample?
The default behavior is best
if you already are using optical flow
and want the behavior
to remain backward compatible.
It's also a good option
if you want upsampled output,
and bilinear is acceptable to you and
worth the additional memory and latency.
Network output is best
if you don't need full resolution
and can form correspondences on the fly
or just want to initialize a tracker.
Network output may also be
the right choice
if you do need a full resolution flow,
but would prefer to use
your own upsampling methods.
That covers the new algorithm revisions
for this session.
Let's move on to discuss
some spring cleaning we are doing
in the Vision framework
and how it might impact you.
We first introduced face detection
and face landmarks
when Vision was initially released
five years ago,
as "revision 1" for each algorithm.
Since that time
we've released two newer revisions,
which use more efficient
and more accurate technologies.
Therefore, we are removing
the first revisions of these algorithms
from Vision framework, while keeping
the second and third revisions only.
However, if you use revision 1,
never fear.
We will continue to support code
that specifies revision 1
or code that has been compiled against
SDKs which only contained revision 1.
How is that possible, you may ask?
Revision 1 executes an algorithm
under the hood
that I have called
"the revision 1 detector" in this diagram.
In the same way, revision 2 uses
the revision 2 detector.
What we have done
for this release of Vision
is to satisfy revision 1 requests
with the output
of the revision 2 detector.
Additionally, the revision 1 request
will be marked as deprecated.
This allows us to remove
the old revision 1 detector completely,
allowing the Vision framework
to remain streamlined.
This has several benefits,
not the least of which
is to save space on disk,
which makes our OS releases and SDKs
less expensive to download and install.
All you Vision experts out there might be
saying to yourselves, "But wait a minute,
"revision 2 returns upside down faces
while revision 1 does not.
Couldn't this behavior difference
have an impact on some apps?"
It certainly would,
except we will be taking precautions
to preserve revision 1 behavior.
We will not be returning upside-down faces
from the revision 2 detector.
Similarly,
the revision 2 landmark detector
will return results that match
the revision 1 landmark constellation.
The execution time is on par,
and you ought to experience
a boost in accuracy.
In any case,
this change will not require any apps
to make any modifications to their code,
and things will continue to work.
Still, we have a call to action for you.
You shouldn't be satisfied
with using revision 1
when we have
much better options available.
We always recommend
using the latest revisions,
and for these requests,
that would be revision 3.
Of course the main reason
for this recommendation
is to use the latest technology,
which provides the highest level
of accuracy and performance available,
and who doesn't want that?
Furthermore, we have established
and communicated several times,
and we reiterate again here,
the best practice of always
explicitly specifying your revisions,
rather than relying
upon default behaviors.
And that's what we've done
for our spring cleaning.
Now let's talk about how we've made it
easier to debug apps
that use the Vision framework.
We've added
Quick Look Preview support to Vision.
What does this mean
for Vision in particular?
Well, now you can mouse over
VNObservations in the debugger,
and with one click, you can visualize
the result on your input image.
We've also made this available
in Xcode Playgrounds.
I think the only way to really explain
how this can benefit your debugging
is to show you.
Let's move to an Xcode demo.
Here we have a simple routine
that will detect face landmarks
and return the face observations.
First, we set up a face landmarks request.
Then, if we have an image
ready to go in our class, we display it.
Then, we declare an array
to hold our results.
Inside the autoreleasepool,
we instantiate a request handler
with that image,
and then perform our request.
Assuming all went well, we can retrieve
the results from the request.
I will run it and get to a breakpoint
after we retrieve the results.
So now I'm in the debugger.
When I mouse over the results,
the overlay shows
I've detected three faces.
That's great.
I do have three faces in my input image.
But how do I know
which observation is which face?
That's where
the Quick Look Preview support comes in.
As I go into this request,
I can click on each "eye" icon
in order to visualize the result.
The image appears with overlays drawn
for the landmarks constellation
and for the face bounding box.
Now you know where the first
observation is in the image.
I can click on the next one to draw
overlays for the second observation
and for the third observation.
Continuing to the next breakpoint,
we run some code
that prints the face observations
to the debug console.
As you can imagine,
here in the debug console
where the face information is printed,
it's pretty hard
to immediately visualize in your mind
which face is which
or whether the results look correct
just from these printed coordinates.
But there is one more thing
to point out here.
Notice that I've somewhat artificially
forced the request handler
out of scope by introducing
an autoreleasepool.
Now that the request handler
is out of scope,
let's use the Quick Look Preview
support again on the results.
Well, what do you know,
the overlays are still drawn,
but the image is not available.
This is something to keep in mind:
the image request handler that was used
to generate the observations
must still be in scope somewhere
in order for Quick Look Preview support
to use the original image for display.
That is because the image request handler
is where your input image resides.
Things will continue to work,
but the image will not be available.
This Quick Look preview support
can be especially useful
in an Xcode Playgrounds session,
while doing quick experiments
to see how things work.
Let's have a look at that now.
Here we have a simple Playground set up
to analyze images for barcodes.
Rather than go through this code,
let's just make a couple modifications
and check out how it impacts the results.
We'll start off by using revision 2
on an image with two barcodes
of different symbologies.
All the results at once are displayed
if we ask for all the results,
and just the first result
is also displayed at the end.
Notice that revision 2 has
a couple issues.
First, it missed the first barcode.
Also, it detected
the second barcode twice.
And it gives you a line
through the barcode
rather than a complete bounding box.
What happens if we change
to revision 3 now, instead of revision 2?
First of all, we detect both barcodes.
And, instead of a line,
we are given complete bounding boxes.
What is great about this
Quick Look Preview support
is that we've removed the need for you
to write a variety of utility functions
to visualize the results.
They can be overlaid directly
on your images in the debugger
or in an Xcode Playground.
So that is Quick Look
Preview support in Vision.
Now you can more easily know
which observation is which.
Just be sure to keep
the image request handler in scope
in order to use it with your input image,
and hopefully the Xcode Playground support
will make live tuning
of your Vision framework code much easier.
We've covered some important updates
to Vision today.
To quickly review, we've added
some great new revisions
to text recognition,
barcode detection, and optical flow.
As we continue to add updated revisions,
we will also be removing older ones,
so keep your revisions up-to-date
and use the latest
and greatest technology.
We've also made debugging
Vision applications much easier this year
with Quick Look Preview support.
I hope you enjoyed this session,
and have a wonderful WWDC.  ♪ ♪