♪ ♪
Hello. My name is Jaewoo.
I'm a designer on the Apple Design team.
Whether preparing Keynote presentations
with colleagues
or collecting ideas with friends,
people collaborate
on all types of things everyday.
To create a first-class
collaboration experience,
we made a handful of changes
to iOS 16 and macOS Ventura.
Today, I'm going to talk about
why we put Messages
in the center of our
collaboration experience
and walk you through an end-to-end
collaboration flow,
showcasing all the new changes we've made.
I'll also share a few considerations
to help you design a great
collaboration experience in your app
using Messages.
Without further ado, let's get started.
Email is one of the great communication
tools that people use every day.
Many collaborative apps use email
as a primary way of connecting people.
However, chatting over email during
collaboration doesn't feel responsive.
That's because email was designed
as an asynchronous communication tool.
So, we brought Messages
into collaboration to supplement email.
Messages allows people
to send collaboration invitations
using existing conversations.
No need to ask for email addresses.
Effective communication is a key
to successful collaboration.
Messages already has many
great features to facilitate that.
Messages conversations can
also easily turn into FaceTime calls.
Talking over FaceTime and using
screen sharing can make collaboration
far more productive.
Let's take a look at how Messages
and collaborative apps work together.
My friends and I love baking,
and we often share recipes
with each other.
I'm working on a Pages document
with some recipes,
and I'd like to share it with my friends.
I'll start by tapping
on the share button in the toolbar.
The new system share popover allows me
to share this document
in two different ways.
I can either start a new collaboration
or send a copy.
With the collaboration option,
I can send invitations using Messages,
Mail, or other communication apps.
My baking friends and I have
a chat group called Cupcake Designers.
The system share popover knows
I talk to them quite often
and show them as a conversation suggestion
in here.
I'll select the group
to start a collaboration.
The collaboration invitation is
now in the Messages input field
and is ready to be sent.
Send button kicks off
collaboration immediately.
If you look at the toolbar, you can see
the Cupcake Designers photo appeared.
The conversation is now linked
with this document.
Looks like my friends
Lauren and Chris just joined.
Tapping on the group conversation photo
brings up the collaboration popover.
This collaboration popover was added
for easy access to communication tools
and is also
a quick collaboration overview.
Pages displays
who's currently in the document.
Tapping on the Messages button
in the popover
brings the Messages conversation
over the shared document.
I can quickly go back
to the group conversation
and talk about this document.
If I need to talk to people over FaceTime,
I can simply tap on the audio
or video button in this popover.
Now, my friends and I can
make edits in real-time.
Tight integration with Messages
unlocks more superpowers.
Now Messages can display notifications
from collaborative apps.
Looks like Chris just made edits
to the Baking Recipes document.
This Messages banner allows me to directly
open the document and see the new updates.
Collaborative apps and Messages
now have a strong connection
to make collaboration workflows
more streamlined.
Okay, we looked at an example
of the new collaboration experience.
Starting a collaboration is simple
using the share button
and the system share popover.
People can easily drop invitations
in existing conversations.
And the collaboration popover
allows people to easily go back
to Messages conversations
or start FaceTime calls.
Edit notifications from collaborative apps
let people stay up-to-date.
Now that we've seen how Messages
and collaborative apps work together,
let's switch gears
and look at some practical tips
for how to design collaboration
into your app.
Starting with the system share sheet.
The people who use your app are
very familiar with the system share sheet.
They use it for all kinds of things,
including sharing websites,
songs and albums, photos,
and other types of content.
And conversation suggestions help people
quickly find destinations
of the content they are sharing.
The system share sheet gives people
an easy way to begin a collaboration.
It will help make collaboration
in your app more consistent and familiar.
If you do decide to take advantage
of the system share sheet,
the next step is to place
a share button in your app.
Put the button in a place
where people can easily access.
Toolbars are a good candidate.
Now let's look more closely
at how you can customize
the share sheet for your needs.
The popup button in the header allows
people to choose how they share files.
If your app
doesn't support sending a copy,
then the popup button will be hidden.
"Everyone can make changes"
text below the popup button
is an entry point
to the collaboration permission settings.
You need to provide a descriptive copy
of default settings your app supports.
To avoid truncation,
be as concise as possible.
The permission settings screen
will be presented
when tapping on
"Everyone can make changes" text.
When customizing the screen,
keep the structure of choices simple
so people can easily skim the options
and make quick decisions.
The share popover
in macOS has been redesigned
to reflect the changes in iOS and iPadOS,
including the conversation suggestions.
The dropdown menu lets people choose
how they wish to share their files.
Permission settings are also
accessible within this popover.
Again, use a concise
permission summary string
and keep the settings simple.
Next, let's talk about
how to optimize the experience
of initiating collaboration in Messages.
People can choose not only how they share,
but also customize collaboration settings
from the Messages input field.
People don't need to go back to
the share sheet to change those options.
Using drag and drop to add a file
into a Messages conversation
is another convenient way
of starting a collaboration.
So help people easily set the permissions
from the Messages input field
and let them start a collaboration
with the send button.
And it's really important
to put the collaboration button
where people can easily find it.
Once people have begun collaborating,
the collaboration button
will appear in your app.
This collaboration button is one
of the most important UI elements
of the entire collaboration experience.
Find a place where it can stand out
and draw people's attention.
It's best to place the collaboration
button right next to the share button.
The appearance of the collaboration
button will be slightly different
depending on
how people started collaboration.
If people sent an invitation
to a one-on-one Messages conversation,
the recipient's picture
will appear as the button.
If collaboration started
with a group conversation,
and the conversation has a photo,
the system will show
the photo in your app.
If a group conversation photo
is not available,
a system provided symbol
will be used instead.
Once you decide where to put
the collaboration button,
it's time to customize
the collaboration popover for your app.
The collaboration popover
consists of three separate sections.
The top section shows
who you are collaborating with.
The system will find corresponding
profile pictures from the Contacts app
and display them here.
There are also buttons for communication.
If there is no Messages conversation
linked with the document,
the message button
will let you connect one.
The middle section is for you,
and it's fully customizable.
Think about what information
or functions will be essential
for people using your app.
Pages shows the active participant list
with a display setting.
In contrast,
the Notes app shows the latest activities
along with two action buttons.
Try not to overload
this collaboration popover
with too much information
or too many buttons.
Keep it glanceable.
Also make sure everything
you are adding here is visually consistent
with other elements in the popover.
If your app doesn't have
anything to show in this popover,
it's okay to leave
the middle section empty,
like Reminders and Files.
At the bottom of the popover,
there is the "Manage Shared File" button.
You can customize
the button label if needed.
This button opens
the collaboration management screen.
People can add and remove participants
and also change other settings
from this screen.
If your app is using CloudKit sharing,
the management screen will be
provided by the system.
If you're not using CloudKit sharing,
you can have your own
management screen for your app.
The collaboration popover on macOS
has the same structure as iOS.
Use macOS UI components
and design patterns
when customizing the middle section.
Lastly, you will want to give
special consideration
to the appearance of the banners
in Messages.
The banners in Messages are
how your app can notify collaborators
of important changes.
These banners allow people
to stay informed about new updates
without having to open the document.
Messages offers banner templates
for you to choose from.
Edits made, comments added,
you were mentioned,
and also files modified.
Tell Messages what type of updates
you want to display.
Those updates will end up
in the right conversations.
You might ask,
what if multiple people made
multiple edits
in many different documents?
How will Messages handle multiple banners?
To not clutter conversation
with too many banners,
Messages will consolidate
those banners into one.
When people tap
on the view button in this banner,
Messages will show all the updates
in one place
and let people choose
which one they want to open.
Okay, we've taken a look
at all the details
to design the best collaboration
experience using Messages.
Adopt the new system share sheet
for better collaboration initiation,
and customize the collaboration popover
to provide communication tools
and a good collaboration overview.
Let people enjoy a productive
and successful collaboration
with the Messages integration.
I hope all these updates help you
design a better experience for your app.
Thank you for watching.  ♪ ♪