♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hi, I’m David Wendland,
a Commerce Technical Advocate
for the App Store.
Today, I’ll show you how your app
can deliver a first class experience
by proactively identifying
a customer's new, current,
and past purchases,
without the customer taking any action.
I’ll cover how to do this with StoreKit 2
and the original StoreKit,
so you can optimize
your app's onboarding experience
for all your customers.
Let me start by defining
proactive in-app purchase restore.
This means that when
a customer launches your app,
you use the data readily available,
on device,
to proactively check for the transactions
in order to determine
if they are a new or existing customer
and doing so
without requiring any customer action,
not even tapping a "Restore Purchases"
button or entering a password.
This enables you
to tailor your app experience
to your customer's purchase history
and state
so your app unlocks products or services
for your current customers,
or your app merchandises your latest
product offering to new customers,
or for those past subscribers,
you present them subscription offers
to win them back.
This is what proactive restore is about,
using StoreKit to optimize
your app's experience
for new, existing, and past customers,
on all of their devices, automatically.
Let’s look at this example.
Here we have our Ocean Journal app.
This is a common merchandising experience,
where the customer has a few different
calls to action to choose from.
Either I can attempt
to buy the in-app purchase
and authenticate with biometrics,
such as FaceID,
or if I’ve created an app account,
I could sign in and possibly use Keychain
to enter my password,
or if I believe I’m an active subscriber,
I could use the "Restore Purchases"
button.
For your active subscribers
on a new device,
knowing which option to choose
isn’t always clear to them.
And with the data readily available
to your app,
this experience can be streamlined
with our proactive in-app
purchase restore best practice.
So, if I launched this app on a new device
but was already an active subscriber,
upon launch, the app would proactively
restore my service, automatically,
without requiring any action from me.
So here the app recognized
my Pro subscription
and loaded my favorite beach,
complete with surf conditions
and enabled the live cam feature.
This experience differentiates
your app from the others
and I will cover how to do this
with StoreKit 2 on iOS 15 and newer.
Additionally, if your app supports
previous versions of iOS,
I will cover how to create this same
great experience
with original StoreKit
and the verifyReceipt endpoint.
With that background,
here’s what I’ll cover.
First, I’ll describe in detail
the core customer product states
that your app uses
to generate personalized experiences
based on the customer's in-app purchases
with StoreKit.
Then I'll review the steps to implement,
using StoreKit 2,
complete with sample code
using the SK Demo app.
Let’s look at each in-app purchase type,
their core customer product states,
and review a few examples of
a personalized onboarding experience.
To start,
the in-app purchase types that apply
to proactive restore are non-consumables,
non-renewing subscriptions,
and auto-renewable subscriptions,
as they are all persistent
in the customer's transaction history
and will always be available
with StoreKit.
Therefore your app can identify
per customer their purchase state
for each product or subscription group.
For non-renewing and auto-renewable
subscriptions,
I will use the term "subscriptions"
to reference them both
as we review the customer product states.
Here are the three core states your app
can personalize against.
Let’s review in-depth new customers.
This state represents
a signed in App Store Apple ID
that does not have any current
or past in-app purchase transactions.
This state is typically used as the app’s
default merchandising experience.
Our Ocean Journal app is merchandising
its monthly and annual subscription
with a one month free trial.
Looking at our second core state,
we have Purchased and Active Subscriber.
In this state,
a customer has an active transaction
and your app is obligated
to grant the customer access
to the purchased product or service.
Here, our Ocean Journal app
immediately presents the customer
their preferred beach
with the premium live beach cam.
No buy buttons are visible,
as service was proactively restored.
For each purchased product
or active subscription,
the transaction has a static
and unique original transaction ID,
which persists for the customer's
Apple ID and storefront.
To maintain status
of the customer's transactions,
associate the original transaction IDs
with an account on your system.
It can be either an anonymous account,
or an account that the user created
with your system.
Knowing the original transaction ID
is critical
when leveraging the power
of App Store Server Notifications,
allowing your server to remain current
on the transaction status.
One scenario to highlight
is when a customer's subscription
failed to auto-renew,
therefore it falls into
what we call the billing retry state,
where we attempt to recover
the subscription for up to 60 days.
If you have opted in to the Billing
grace period feature in App Store Connect,
then subscribers in billing retry
with grace period
would continue to have access
to their subscription service,
while we attempt to recover
their subscription.
And while they have still access
to your service,
be sure to present them
a simple call to action
to resolve their payment issue.
To learn more about Billing retry and
Billing grace period,
check out our sessions links and resources
about reducing involuntary
subscriber loss.
The final core state is the inactive
purchase or inactive subscriber.
This state represents customers
who previously made in-app purchases,
but are no longer entitled
to that product or service,
due to expiry or if revoked.
These transactions are persistent
and contain an original transaction ID,
which allows you to maintain status
across devices and platforms.
For Subscriptions, inactive is determined
by the expires date.
And for all in-app purchase types,
they can be inactive
if there is a revocation date.
This occurs when a transaction
has been refunded
or if access granted through
Family Sharing has been revoked.
For your inactive subscribers,
due to expiration or revoked,
consider presenting
subscription offers to win them back.
And for those in the billing retry state,
don’t forget to present them
that same call to action
to resolve their payment details.
In review, here are the three core
customer product states your app will use
to proactively restore in-app purchases
and tailor your app's experience
to your customers.
Let's see how these experiences look
side-by-side with our Ocean Journal app.
New customers will see your latest
product offering and introductory offers.
Your current active customers
will have the feeling it just works,
as your app has streamlined access
to your products and services
on all of their devices.
And for your inactive subscribers,
you can present them
your latest win-back offers
using offer codes or promotional offers.
Okay, we’ve covered
the three core customer product states,
and how supporting these states alone
is a huge win for your customers.
But of course, there are opportunities
to take the experience further.
Your app could expand
or refine the customer experience
to fit your product offering,
business model,
policies, and prioritizations.
But here are few things to consider
when preparing to implement
proactive restore into your app.
If you support multiple products
or subscription groups,
the customer's state is determined for
each product and each subscription group.
Therefore, you may need
to account for hybrid states
or any other dependencies.
Consider any off-platform activity
and how that factors into
your customer's product state.
And be sure to check out
App Store Server Notifications,
as these are critical to maintaining
status, server-to-server,
for all in-app purchase types.
And with Version
2, the new notification types and subtypes
support 28 unique events,
sent securely to your server
in near real time.
Learn more about integrating
or migrating to Version 2
in the session, "Explore in-app purchase
integration and migration."
Alex and Gabriel also cover compatibility
with StoreKit 2
and the original StoreKit framework,
and best practices.
We’ve talked through
the customer product states to support
and what that experience can be
for your customers.
Now let’s walk through
the implementation details.
I’ll be using our SK Demo App
that we’ve updated with proactive restore
using StoreKit 2.
Note that the SK Demo app will be
available for download with this session.
Let's review the SK Demo’s
default experience for new customers,
those without any active in-app purchases.
To view our products,
tap the “Shop” button,
where up top we have our inventory
of available cars
as non-consumable in-app purchases.
And then we have our navigation service
as a monthly auto-renewable subscription,
which offers three different levels
of service for customers to choose from.
And down below, we have
a non-renewing subscription option,
providing one-time access.
This covers our app's
new customer experience,
when no products have been purchased.
Now let's look at
how our app is able to determine
if the customer has current
or past purchases.
It requires your app
to execute three steps
immediately upon app launch.
What is most important
is that these steps are completed
before a "Buy" button is merchandised
to the customer.
The first step is your app
will need to begin listening
for transactions from the App Store.
This is an App Store best practice,
as transactions can show up at any time
from features such as
Family Sharing Ask to Buy,
code redemptions,
subscription auto-renewals,
or when a purchase gets interrupted.
In addition, your app can receive revoked
transactions,
where access is lost due to a refund
or is no longer shared via Family sharing.
This will apply more
in subsequent app launches,
when access has already been granted
and their state is moving
from active to inactive.
If transactions are found, they are
considered unfinished transactions,
and need to be validated,
delivered to the customer,
and marked as finished.
This ensures your app
won’t miss any transactions
and delivers a great customer experience.
Now let’s look at how our SK Demo app
listens for transactions in StoreKit 2.
Here I’m using the function
listenForTransactions.
It will return any unfinished transactions
or updates to a transaction
for the signed-in App Store customer.
For any transactions found,
here, StoreKit 2 will verify
the authenticity of these transactions.
And then,
after my app delivers the content,
grants access,
or updates the customer product status,
I will then finish the transaction
to indicate to the App Store
that the purchase has been delivered.
Once a transaction is finished,
it will no longer be returned to your app,
on any device, via StoreKit.
That first step is critical for all apps
and will occur on every app launch
going forward.
Step 2 is determining
that customer product state,
and this is done by proactively requesting
the customer's active transactions
using currentEntitlements.
And specifically for auto-renewable
subscriptions,
to account for
the customer's renewal state,
such as cancelled,
billing retry, or pending downgrades,
you will additionally use
Product.SubscriptionInfo.RenewalState.
Let’s look at the SK Demo app
and see how we accomplish this.
This starts with the function,
updateCustomerProductStatus,
which keeps track
of the customer's product states
for each of our persistent
in-app purchase types.
I then loop through
each of the purchase types
using StoreKit 2’s
currentEntitlements method.
This returns transactions for products
that the customer may be entitled to.
And we record these transactions
per product type.
Here, for our non-consumables products,
and here for our non-renewing
subscription product.
In order to determine if they are
an active, or inactive subscriber,
I’ve added additional logic
to calculate an expiration date
for our non-renewing subscription.
And lastly, I will check for
an active auto-renewable subscription,
and apply that state to
the subscription group.
To account for inactive states such as
billing retry, expired, and revoked,
our variable subscription
group status uses
Product.SubscriptionInfo.RenewalState
Now that we've retrieved
the user's transactions
and determined the customer status
for each product or subscription group,
our app has logic
to personalize the app experience
for the various use cases.
Let’s take a look at
the SK Demo app source code.
If no active transactions are determined
for all three in-app purchase
product types,
the customer will then see
the default new customer experience
that we reviewed earlier,
where they will have a simple
call to action to our "Shop" page.
If the customer has any active purchases,
then upon app launch,
they will see their purchases
and update "Buy" buttons
on all products accordingly.
So here for non-consumables,
we present what they’ve purchased
and the app either shows
their purchased non-consumables,
or the app provides a call to action
for the customer to visit
the shop experience.
For active products,
here we handle if the customer is
an active subscriber
of the navigation service
for non-renewable subscriptions
and auto-renewable subscriptions.
And in our last portion,
we account for inactive subscribers.
Those with subscriptions
that have expired, been revoked,
or are in the billing retry state.
Okay, let's now go to the SK Demo app.
We want to simulate an active customer
for both a non-consumable
and auto-renewable subscription.
So if I purchase the race car
and subscribe to the pro navigation,
the demo app will apply green checkmarks
to indicate the app has confirmed
those purchases were successful, verified,
and has enabled them.
With these purchases,
my customer product state
for the non-consumable is purchased.
And for our subscription,
I’m an active subscriber.
Now, if I install the app on a new device,
when I launch the SK Demo app
for the first time,
it will proactively perform
steps one, two, and three.
Here you see our demo app has proactively
restored access to both of my purchases,
without any action from me.
As this is a demo app,
that is the extent of products
being delivered.
But in your app, this process would ensure
these active customers
are not offered products to purchase
that they already own,
and that those products and services
are enabled for them automatically.
For your current customers, this is great.
No need to require customers to sign-in
or tap "Restore Purchases."
It just worked.
Your app can use
the APIs and data readily available.
So we’ve covered the three steps
to do this with StoreKit 2.
Now I want to discuss how to implement
this same experience for your customers
on previous versions of iOS
where you cannot leverage
the power of StoreKit 2.
With original StoreKit, you will perform
the same steps as StoreKit 2
to determine the customer product state
by proactively restoring in-app purchases
on iOS 7 or later.
To do this, it will require your server
to use the verifyReceipt endpoint
to validate and retrieve
the latest transactions
in order to determine
customer's product state.
The app receipt is present on-device
when an app is installed from App Store.
But keep in mind,
when testing with Sandbox or TestFlight,
the app receipt is only present
after an in-app purchase
has been completed or restored.
If your app finds no app receipt present,
this should only occur in Sandbox
and your app can consider this scenario
the same as a new customer
where no in-app purchases are found.
An app receipt
created in the past is sufficient
to retrieve the latest transactions
from the App Store.
Therefore, no customer actions
like a "Restore Purchase,"
or receiptRefresh are necessary.
Just include the shared secret
with your request to verifyReceipt
in order to receive
transactions
for non-consumables,
non-renewing subscriptions,
and auto-renewable subscriptions.
Let’s look back at the three
implementation steps we reviewed earlier.
The difference lies within Step 2,
where you identify
the customer's product state.
How we determine customer product state
starts with the app receipt on device,
that, in turn, your server validates
with the App Store verifyReceipt endpoint.
Let’s look at this process.
First, we need to retrieve
the App Receipt,
and be sure you are using
the appStoreReceiptURL property,
as you can see in this sample
from our developer documentation.
With the app receipt,
let’s see how this is sent from the device
to your server and the App Store.
Your app on a device is here on the left.
it will first, retrieve the app receipt,
and send it to your server,
then validate it with
the App Store verifyReceipt endpoint.
From that response,
you will determine customer product state,
and send those states to your app.
To determine customer product state,
we used the Entitlement Engine
from WWDC2020.
It’s updated to support non-consumables
and non-renewing subscriptions,
and now handles the new customer state
when there are no in-app purchases.
To learn more about
using our Entitlement Engine,
I encourage you to check out the
"Architecting for subscriptions" session
and download the sample project.
You can find links to this session
and more with this video’s resources.
That completes Step 2,
where your app will receive the customer
product state from your server.
Now your app will personalize
the app experience immediately on launch
using the StoreKit 2
and original StoreKit frameworks.
I want to share some final best practices.
First, continue providing a "Restore
Purchases" button within your app.
While not used often,
it does give customers an opportunity to
force an app
to restore their Apple ID’s transactions
in case of an issue
or if the customer uses
a different Apple ID.
When your app first proactively restores
a customer's in-app purchases on a device,
it’s recommended to optimize your app
and store data securely
to assist in determining
customer product state.
CloudKit is a feature to consider
with its flexibility, security,
and ability to sync
across a customer's devices.
Testing your implementation
is critical when using StoreKit.
And with StoreKit 2, you can test
your proactive restore implementation
with Sandbox, TestFlight
and Xcode StoreKit testing.
And if you are using original StoreKit,
it’s important to remember an app receipt
may not be present
when testing in Sandbox and TestFlight,
while it is always present when the app
is installed from the App Store.
If an app receipt isn’t present,
it is suggested your app uses
its default new customer experience,
and ensure you have a Restore Purchases
button readily available.
In conclusion, update your app
to proactively check for purchases
without any customer action,
no taps or authentication.
Allow your app to tailor the customer's
experience immediately at launch
to fit your new, active,
and inactive customers' product states.
Maintain status on
all your customer's transactions,
server to server,
for all in-app purchase types,
by implementing App Store
Server Notifications Version 2.
This enables your backend
to know in near real-time
any change that has occurred
with a transaction,
such as refunds, or revoked transactions,
or subscription renewals,
billing retry, and expirations.
Thank you for watching,
and be sure to check out
this additional session,
"What's new with in-app purchases”,
where Dani and Ian will tell you
about all the great updates
to StoreKit, the Server API,
and Server Notifications Version 2.
Thank you. Take care.
♪ ♪