[spacey music]
Ram: Hi.
My name is Ram.
I'm an engineer
on the account experiences team.
I'll be joined by my colleague Patrick
to talk about how you can enhance
your Sign in with Apple experience
for your app.
Since Sign in with Apple was introduced
in iOS 13,
people love the fast, easy account setup
and sign-in.
With just a few lines of code,
you can enable
quick, one-tap account setup
with no forms or passwords.
Every Sign in with Apple account
is protected
by a strong two-factor authentication
that is already used to secure
the user's Apple ID.
If you need to communicate
with your users,
Sign in with Apple provides you
with an email address
that just works.
There is no additional verification
required.
Sign in with Apple also provides
an indicator
for how likely the user is indeed real.
This can help you combat fraud.
And Sign in with Apple works everywhere,
including your managed Apple IDs
that you use for work and school.
To learn more about how you can integrate
your app with work and school accounts,
check out the session "Discover Sign in
with Apple at Work & School."
In this session, we are going to talk
about how you can enhance and streamline
your Sign in with Apple experience.
First, I will discuss how you can prevent
account duplication
by checking for existing credentials
in your app.
Next, I'll take a deep dive
into the Apple ID credential,
and then, I'll talk about some of the ways
you can monitor credential changes
and discuss how to handle scenarios
like account deletion.
And finally, Patrick will discuss
how to integrate Sign in with Apple
on the web and other platforms.
Let's get started.
Sign in with Apple is
a convenient and secure alternative
to traditional username-
and-password-based authentication,
but your users could still have accounts
that are unlocked with passwords.
So if your user already has an account
that works for them,
it is important not to create
a second account for your app.
I'll explore how you can guide someone
to make the right decision
while signing in.
This is Juice, a sample app
that uses Sign in with Apple.
You can find its source code
in the related links for this video.
You can sign in to Juice either using
traditional email and password
or using Sign in with Apple.
If your user has either
of these credentials already,
it is in your hands to help them
sign into the right account.
To start with, be sure to implement
password autofill
so that existing password credentials
are displayed on the keyboard
for your login screen.
This way, the user can autofill
the credential with just one tap.
Also, you should provide your users
to upgrade their password-based accounts
to Sign in with Apple.
Once upgraded, your users
will get an account
that has security built in,
and they have one less password
to remember.
This is implemented
using the Account Authentication
Modification Extension.
The extension-based API provides
seamless experience for your users
to upgrade the way they sign in
using Sign in with Apple.
For more information
on providing security upgrades
for your users' accounts,
check out the docs
"Get the most out of Sign in with Apple"
and "One-tap account security upgrades."
Apart from providing password autofill,
you can go a step further
by presenting existing credentials
as soon as your app launches.
This way, your users can sign in
using the right account
even before they reach the login screen.
The Authentication Services API
is really flexible this way.
Besides allowing a user to create
a Sign in with Apple credential,
the API can also present
existing credentials,
including password-based credentials.
Adopting this is really easy.
Let me take you through some code
on how to achieve this.
If you're already using
the Authentication Services API,
this code should be very familiar.
You start by creating an instance
of ASAuthorizationController
and include both
ASAuthorizationAppleIDProvider
as well as
an ASAuthorizationPasswordProvider
in the authorization request array.
Then you'll need to set up a delegate
and an object
to help with presenting the interface.
And finally, you'll need to call
performRequests
with the option
preferImmediatelyAvailableCredentials
on your authorization controller.
This option is new on iOS 16.
It tells the system
that you only want credentials
that are immediately available
on the device.
It is intended specifically to be called
on app launch.
If you want to support
previous iOS versions,
you can use performRequests.
When you do this,
you will be presented with a list
of existing credentials.
Your user can now select
either an existing
Sign in with Apple credential
or an existing password credential.
After the user has selected a credential,
the system will call
didCompleteWithAuthorization
on the ASAuthorizationController delegate.
If the user chose
a Sign in with Apple account,
you continue with the appleIDCredential.
If the user chose
a password-based account,
you sign in with the passwordCredential
returned.
If the user has no existing credential,
the API will not present the user
to create a Sign in with Apple account.
Instead, the system will call
didCompleteWithError.
You should fall back to showing
standard login flows in such scenarios.
By the way, the same
Authentication Services API
also works seamlessly for passkeys.
To learn more about passkeys,
a next-generation authentication
technology to replace passwords,
check out the session "Meet passkeys."
With just a few lines of code,
you can take full advantage
of the sign-in experience.
You can now help your users
select the right account,
and hopefully, this prevents
duplicate accounts
from being created in your system.
Next, I'd like to take you on a deep dive
on Apple ID credential.
As you know, the response you get
after a successful authorization
using Sign in with Apple
is an ASAuthorizationAppleIDCredential
object.
It contains values like user,
fullName, email, realUserStatus,
identityToken, and authorizationCode.
I'll cover each of them briefly.
User is a unique and stable identifier.
It is the same identifier
across all the apps
in your developer team.
Use this to uniquely identify
users in your system.
You should ask for fullName
only if you need it.
If requested, your users can share
any name they want.
If you want to communicate
with your users,
you should ask for the email.
When requested, your users
have two options
to share their email address.
One option is to share the email
associated with their Apple ID.
The other option is to use
the "hide my email" feature.
This creates a hidden email address
that routes to their inbox.
It is a two-way relay,
so it can handle replies, too.
Regardless of which option is chosen,
the email address
has been previously verified by Apple,
and it is ready to use.
Also, not all accounts have
an associated email,
so be prepared to handle scenarios
where there is no value for email,
even if you requested it.
RealUserStatus is
a high-confidence indicator
on how likely the user is real.
It is calculated
using on-device machine learning,
account history, and hardware attestation
whilst preserving the user's privacy.
There's three types for realUserStatus.
"Likely real" means the user appears
to be a real person.
Provide this user
with the best experience,
such as skipping
additional fraud verification checks
like CAPTCHAs.
"Unknown" is when the system
hasn't determined
whether the user is a real person.
Trust this user as you would
for any account with limited information
that requires
additional verification steps.
The user could still be real,
so do not block them
from using your app.
And finally, "unsupported"
means the system is not capable
of this determination.
I should take a moment to call out
that the properties
like fullName, email,
and realUserStatus
are only returned when an account
is created for the very first time.
They're not returned
upon subsequent sign-ins,
so make sure to securely cache
properties like fullName and email
until you can verify that an account
has been created in your system.
The identityToken is a JSON web token
that contains most of the data
that the app server needs,
including the user information.
This is an industry-standard approach
to authentication.
The JSON web token, or JWT,
consists of three parts:
a base-64 URL encoded header,
a base-64 URL encoded payload,
and a signature signed by Apple.
You should verify the signature
with Apple's public key
to ensure that the response
has not been tampered with
and is indeed from Apple ID servers.
It is also equally important
that your app server checks
the validity of the token.
Once you decode the payload,
you should verify the issuer is
appleid.apple.com,
verify the audience field
is your app's bundle identifier,
then make sure the expiry timestamp
is greater than the current time
so that you know the token is valid.
Subject will be your user identifier.
If you requested
for the user's email address,
it will also be included.
You can also find the realUserStatus.
The value will be 0 for "unsupported,"
1 for "unknown," 2 for "likely real."
And finally, verify that the nonce
is the same
as the one generated prior to the creation
of the authorization request.
For more information on nonce
and how to secure
your authorization process
to mitigate replay attacks,
check out the session "Get the most
out of Sign in with Apple."
AuthorizationCode is
a short-lived, single-use token
that you can provide Apple ID servers
in exchange for refresh tokens.
If your systems already use open standards
like OAuth 2.0,
this might be familiar for you.
To generate a refresh token,
you should send a post request
to the auth/token endpoint.
You pass on the client ID
and the client secret
along with the authorization code
that you just received.
A detailed description on how to create
the client secret
is available
in the Apple Developer documentation.
In the response,
you will get a refresh token,
an access token,
and a new identity token
similar to the one you received earlier.
If you have an expired access token,
you can use the refresh token
to obtain a new access token
using the same endpoint.
You can also continue to use
the same refresh token
until it gets invalidated.
The refresh token could get invalidated
if the token verification fails
or if there are changes
around your user's session.
Speaking of user session,
next, I’ll talk about handling
and monitoring changes
around the credential state.
After verifying the identity token,
your app is responsible for managing
the user session.
There are various scenarios
that can trigger user session changes.
For example, a user could stop using
Apple ID with your app from Settings,
or they could have been signed out
of the device.
To handle session changes gracefully,
call the getCredentialState(forUserID:)
on the ASAuthorizationAppleIDProvider.
This API is recommended to be called
as soon as your app launches
or at any point where you wish to check
the state.
You should also observe
for credentialRevokedNotification
so that your app is notified
when the credential is revoked.
If you observe any change in the state,
you should assume that a different user
has signed in
and sign the current user out of the app.
If you have an app server,
you should subscribe
to server-to-server notifications.
Your server will receive important updates
about your users and their accounts.
Notifications are sent to each group
of apps
for the following scenarios:
when the user disables or enables
their mail forwarding preference;
when the user stops using their Apple ID
with your app;
or when the user permanently deletes
their Apple ID.
To start receiving notifications,
you should first register an endpoint URL
in the Apple Developer portal.
All events arrive
at the same endpoint URL.
The events are sent as JSON web tokens
signed by Apple.
If mail forwarding is disabled,
in the payload of the JWT,
you will receive an email-disabled event.
When the user stops using
their Apple ID with your app,
you will get a consent-revoked event.
It is important to invalidate
any active user session
when you get this event.
And if the user deletes their Apple ID,
you will get an account-delete event.
Again, be sure to invalidate
any active user session
and update their accounts
according to your process.
Now I'd like to focus on account deletion.
Accounts are part of our identities,
and we use them to manage some
of our most personal and private data.
Someone might want to delete
their account,
and you need to support this
in your app.
You should provide a way
to initiate account deletion
from your app,
and it is your responsibility
to manage the entire deletion process.
If you have an app server
that stores user information,
typically, the app notifies the server
to delete user accounts.
Now, you can include Sign in with Apple as
part of your deletion process.
This is done using a new REST endpoint
that your server can use
to delete an account associated
with your app.
Let me briefly take you through this API.
In order to delete an account,
you must have either a valid refresh token
or a valid access token for the user.
If you don't have either of the tokens,
you can generate using
the auth/token endpoint.
Once you have either of the tokens,
you can use the auth/revoke endpoint
with the required parameters.
When using the refresh token,
set the token type to REFRESH_TOKEN.
If you want to delete
using the access token,
set the token type to ACCESS_TOKEN.
If you get a successful response,
the tokens and the user's active sessions
will be instantly invalidated.
Once deleted,
the user returning to your app
and using Sign in with Apple
will have an experience similar
to when they first created the account
with the app.
With that, I will sign out
and pass it on to my colleague Patrick
to discuss how you can use
Sign in with Apple
on the web and other platforms.
Patrick: Thank you, Ram!
People love how Sign in with Apple
works seamlessly
across all of Apple's platforms.
But it doesn’t stop there.
Sign in with Apple also works seamlessly
on the web and other platforms.
Let’s discuss how you can enhance
your Sign in with Apple experience
to support the web and other platforms.
We have an existing iOS app that Ram
introduced to you earlier, called Juice.
We’d like to bring Juice
to even more users
by expanding to the web.
Let’s begin by discussing how to group
our similar apps together.
It is recommended that you group
related apps together
to streamline the user experience.
By grouping related apps together,
your users only need to provide
their consent once
to share their information with your app.
For example, your app may be available
on iOS and macOS
but use different bundle identifiers
for each platform.
It’s recommended that you group
these apps together.
When using Sign in with Apple, your users
will see the App Icon for the app you set
as the primary app.
Let’s discover how you can configure
a Services ID
to support Sign in with Apple
on your website.
To begin, log into the Apple Developer Portal
and navigate to "Certificates,
Identifiers & Profiles."
Select the radio button
next to Services IDs
and then click "Continue."
Enter a description for your Service.
Enter a unique identifier for your Service
and click Continue.
Click on the checkbox
next to Sign in with Apple
and then click the Configure button.
On the Web Authentication Configuration
screen,
select a Primary App ID
from the drop-down menu.
Next, input the domains and subdomains
your website will use to support
Sign in with Apple.
Last, enter a redirect URL for Apple
to redirect your user back to your app
or website
after a successful authorization.
That’s it!
You’ve configured a Services ID
to support Sign in with Apple
on your website.
You’ll need a button to show users
your website supports Sign in with Apple.
Apple provides
a highly configurable button API
to generate Sign in with Apple
button images.
Use this to customize
and embed your button of choice
in your app or website.
Sign in with Apple JS
is a simple Javascript framework
that makes integrating Sign in with Apple
even easier on the web.
In your application or website,
start by including the Sign in with Apple
JavaScript framework.
This simple API will allow you
to authenticate your users
and obtain different assets,
like the Sign in with Apple button
that you can create
with just one simple DIV.
You can also customize the button to fit
your app or website
by modifying the properties of the button.
For example, with the current properties,
you’ll get a white
"Sign in with Apple" button
with a border and a default corner radius.
By changing the data-color property,
we can choose a different background color
for the button.
If we change the data type to "continue",
the button text will update to show
"Continue with Apple."
Alternatively, you can create
a logo-only button
by setting the data mode property
to logo-only.
The Sign in with Apple Javascript
Button API
provides even more customizable
properties.
You can refer
to the Sign in with Apple button resource
to easily configure these many options.
If you’d prefer to use a REST API
to generate
your Sign in with Apple button,
you can use one
of the Apple ID button endpoints
to generate a button.
There are separate endpoints
for center-aligned,
left-aligned, and logo buttons.
You can customize the button by using
query parameters.
In this example request,
I customize
a white Sign in with Apple button
with a border.
I receive a response
with the customized button as a PNG image.
Now that you have personalized
your Sign in with Apple button,
it's time to authenticate your user.
You’ll need to send
an authorization request
with the required parameters to Apple.
These are the parameters you need
in order to successfully log in a user.
Since you have already implemented
Sign in with Apple on an Apple platform,
these parameters are very familiar.
First, we’ll need to set the “clientID”.
This will be the Services ID
that you created
on the Apple Developer Portal
for your app or website.
Next, if your app or website requires
email or name,
fill in the "scope" parameter.
If you are requesting multiple scopes,
use a space to separate each scope.
It is important that you only request
the data you need.
The “redirectURI” parameter
is where you will add
the URL you registered previously
on the Apple Developer Portal
and informs Apple where to direct the user
to on your website.
You can also add a “state”
and “nonce” to secure your request.
And finally,
with the "usePopup" parameter,
you can choose to display the login screen
in a separate pop-up window
or have the existing window
redirect to the Apple Sign in website.
If someone is using Safari,
they’ll see a native screen like this one
providing them
a first-class experience to sign into
your website.
After the Apple ID server
processes the authorization request,
you’ll receive a DOM event
containing the results
of the authorization.
To handle a success response,
add an event listener
for "AppleIDSignInOnSuccess."
To handle a failure response,
add an event listener
for "AppleIDSignInOnFailure."
If the authorization was a success,
you’ll receive a response that contains
the authorization code,
the identity token,
and the user information if requested.
This is similar to the response
you are already used to
on Apple platforms.
If you’d prefer to use a REST API
to integrate directly
with Apple ID servers,
direct the authorization request
to the authorize endpoint
with the required parameters.
If the authorization is successful,
you’ll get a response that contains
the authorization code,
the identity token,
and the user information.
This is very similar
to the response you're already used to
on Apple platforms.
That’s it!
You’ve successfully adopted
Sign in with Apple on your website!
To wrap up, I’d like to highlight
some important things to keep in mind
while implementing Sign in with Apple.
Unless your app requires
significant account-based features,
let people use your app without a login.
For example, you may allow a user
to purchase an item using Apple Pay
and then optionally offer them to tie
their purchase to an account
after the purchase is complete.
Offer existing users the ability
to upgrade the security of their account
by switching away from username
and password authentication
to Sign in with Apple.
If you just need a unique identifier
to identify the user,
don't collect name or email.
And if you do collect email
through Sign In with Apple,
make sure that you respect
the user's choice.
You should not prompt
for an additional email.
It’s important to implement
Sign in with Apple
across all of the platforms your app
or website is available.
Your users may use multiple platforms,
and they will expect to use
Sign in with Apple everywhere.
We’re really excited to see what you do
with Sign in with Apple in your apps,
and we look forward to your feedback.
Thank you for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC!
[music]