♪ ♪
Vaibhav Gautam:
Hi, I am Vaibhav Gautam,
and I am an engineer
on the Software Power team.
Apps enrich people's lives,
as they provide various critical
functionalities throughout a day of use.
But this use can come with a cost:
battery drain.
Therefore, it is important
that you take special attention
to improve your app's battery life
so that your users can use their devices
and your apps longer.
We deeply study
different system components
to understand power consumption,
and in this session,
I will go over four key actions
we have identified that you can take
to significantly improve
your app's battery life.
These are Dark Mode in your app,
auditing frame rates,
limiting background time,,
and deferring work in your app.
First, I'll talk about Dark Mode.
Dark Mode was introduced in iOS 13,
and allows someone to configure
their devices in a darker presentation.
You may be familiar with
the personalization benefits of Dark Mode,
but it can also
dramatically affect battery life.
This is because
on devices with OLED displays,
like iPhone 13 and 13 Pro,
darker content consumes
less power than lighter content.
On an OLED screen
each pixel requires individual power,
and for darker colors less power
is required to light up the pixels.
Among all the components in the system,
display is one of the major sources
of power consumption.
In fact, in typical use cases,
the display can be the leading contributor
to battery drain.
You have a way to influence
the power consumption of the display.
And one way is by adopting Dark Mode.
I'll use the Food Truck app
my team has been working on
as an example.
This app has a very prominent
background color
that takes up most of the screen.
When presenting in Dark Mode,
this background color becomes much darker
than its Light Mode version,
contributing heavily to battery savings.
In fact, for cases like this,
we expect up
to a 70% display power savings
as a result.
This is a huge savings!
And when screen brightness is high,
the battery savings are even higher.
For users who prefer Dark Mode,
this is a tremendous opportunity
to save them some battery drain
and it can reduce thermal load too.
To adopt Dark Mode, start by reviewing
how your app currently appears
when Dark Mode is enabled.
Figure out what components
of your app you should update
to fit in better with system UI.
Xcode makes this easy by using the
appearance feature when building your app.
Your app may have hard coded colors
because it only supports Light Mode.
Use dynamic colors in Xcode
to support background color,
images, and text
in Light and Dark Mode.
The system will automatically use
the correct color values,
and will update when the mode changes.
Your app should also support
alternate images for Light Mode
and Dark Mode.
To learn more about
customizing your app for Dark Mode,
check out "Implementing Dark Mode on iOS"
from WWDC 2019.
Now that you know
how to adopt Dark Mode in your app,
you should also think about how to adopt
Dark Mode for your web content.
Safari does not auto-darken
any web content,
so make sure you adopt Dark Mode
for your web content too.
To do so, implement the color-scheme
property in your website's stylesheet.
This enables the default text
and background colors of the web page
to match the current system appearance,
standard form controls, and scrollbars.
Other named system colors
change their look,
switching between Light and Dark Mode.
Start using stylesheet variables
wherever colors are referenced
in your stylesheet.
This allows your web content
to update its colors
as the device switches
between Light and Dark.
Apply the same logic to images
and other media assets on your web pages,
with different variants
for different modes.
To learn more about implementing Dark Mode
for web content,
refer to "Supporting Dark Mode
in Your Web Content"
from WWDC 2019.
Another way to reduce your app's
power usage is to audit your frame rates.
On devices with ProMotion displays,
the refresh rate
can affect power consumption.
Higher refresh rates use higher power.
The frame rates
of animations in your app
determine the display's refresh rate.
Be considerate
of the primary content in your app
and what frame rate it requires,
as not all content in your app
may require a high frame rate.
The display's refresh rate is determined
by the animation
with the highest frame rate in your app.
Your app may have secondary elements
refreshing at a higher rate
than necessary,
causing the app as a whole
to consume more battery than expected.
Here we have the food truck app again.
The primary truck scene at the top
is rendering at 30 frames per second.
Below the truck,
there is a text overlay "Food Truck,"
which is horizontally scrolling.
This secondary text is rendering
at 60 frames per second.
As a result, the whole screen is
now rendering at 60 frames per second.
If we change the text animation to 30fps,
then the entire screen can render
at 30fps,
and we could save
up to 20% of the battery drain.
Amazing!
To debug and get more information
about the frame rates in your app,
use Instruments.
Use the CoreAnimation FPS instrument
to see a timeline showing the frame rate
of your app over time.
Start by auditing main user scenarios.
To identify if frames are being rendered
at the rate you expect,
determine if secondary elements
on the screen
have a higher frame rate
than your primary content.
Your app may be using CADisplayLink
offered by CoreAnimation on iOS
to drive custom animations
and custom render loop.
CADisplayLink is a timer synchronized
with the display refresh rate.
It provides necessary timing information
to your app
so that your custom drawing
can be aware of refresh events.
Your app can give hints
to a CADisplayLink object
about the desired screen refresh rate.
Set the preferredFrameRateRange
of a CADisplayLink
and specify your minimum,
maximum, and preferred frame rates.
Display link will then choose
the nearest available frame rate
to your preferred rate,
based on what the system can handle.
If it cannot provide that rate,
it will try to stay
within your specified range.
To configure your display link,
initialize it with a target and selector.
The provided selector is used
to perform custom animation
and calculate which video frame
to display next.
Once your display link is initialized,
set the preferred frame rate range.
In this example,
the preferred rate is 30,
but the range can handle
anything between 10 and 60.
Finally, add the display link
to the current run loop.
Keep refresh rates in mind when thinking
about your app's battery consumption.
This is especially important
for devices with ProMotion displays
that support very dynamic refresh rates.
Monitor your app's frame rates
with Instruments
to discover issues
before you release your app.
Lastly, provide information to the system,
using CADisplayLink
to limit refresh rate
for your app's content.
To learn more
about frame rate optimizations,
refer to "Optimize for variable refresh
rate displays"
from WWDC 2021.
Now, let's talk about
how you can power down your app
when it's running in the background.
When someone switches from your app
to a different app,
your app may rely
on background execution APIs
to continue to run in the background.
While running in the background,
your app may continue to use
common services like location and audio.
Running these services for long durations
will cause battery drain,
so when your app is using
these services in background,
you need to be especially careful!
So let's talk about how to avoid
excess drain when using these modes
Location services keep the device awake
to continuously stream location.
Even though the app is invisible
to the user,
it could be continuously streaming
location in the background,
and cause excess battery drain.
It is important to make sure, that you
are on top of background location session
runtime in your app.
When you no longer need the session,
make sure your app calls
stopUpdatingLocation()
to stop the session.
During different stages
of app development,
you can use different tools
to find out background location usage,
which may not be expected.
While building and testing the app,
Xcode gauges can be used
to find out system energy usage,
as well as background location usage.
When testing your app before release,
you can use MetricKit to collect
diagnostic information for a day of use.
New in iOS 16 is the location usage
in Control Center.
Xcode gauges provide information
about system usage
such as CPU, Network, and Location usage.
Xcode gauges will show a timeline
of the location usage
and energy impact of your app.
Looking at this timeline view
can be a great way to verify
that your location runtime stops
when you expect it to stop.
Another tool is to use Metric Kit
when testing your apps.
Use the
cumulativeBackgroundLocationTime property
to find out how long your app was actively
using location services in background.
New in iOS 16,
users can monitor apps
which are currently using location
services by navigating to Control Center.
They can tap the text at the top
for a detailed view
of apps using location.
Use this to get
an away-from-your-desk insight
into your location runtime.
If you see your app here
and you don't expect to,
it is an indicator that your app has
an active location streaming session.
We can apply the same principles
to audio sessions.
Let's say we have a music app
that is using the audio player
for playing back some file,
and the user stops playback.
The app should not only
pause or stop the sound,
but it should also pause or stop
the Audio Engine
in order to prevent it from running idle.
We recommend using auto shutdown mode
which can be enabled by setting
the autoShutdownEnabled property
of AVAudioEngine class.
In this mode, the audio engine
continuously monitors and detects
if it is idle for a certain duration.
When idle, the engine will shut down
the audio hardware.
And later on,
if any of the sources become active again,
it will start the audio hardware
dynamically.
And all of this happens under the hood.
On watchOS auto shutdown mode
is the enforced behavior.
Make sure to stop
the Audio Engine when not in use
in order to conserve power.
The key to limiting background runtime
is to remember to tell the system
when you are done.
The last action you can take
to improve battery life is to defer work.
Over the course of the day,
your app may process
lots of different tasks and data.
Some of this work needs to occur
immediately to service user actions,
like rendering content on the screen
or playing audio
or a video the user taps on.
Other work like machine learning tasks,
uploading analytics,
or backups is not as time-sensitive.
If we defer this time insensitive work
to a better time–
when the device is charging–
we can save battery
and avoid contending with
the user initiated and interactive work.
Let's talk about three APIs
you can use to accomplish this.
BGProcessingTask is a good choice to
defer tasks which run for long durations.
Discretionary URLSession
is the perfect choice
to schedule deferrable networking.
And leveraging the right push priority
can help servers
deliver pushes at the right time.
Let's go into detail for each.
First is BGProcessingTask.
BGProcessingTask lets you defer
long-running processing tasks
to a better time,
such as when the device is charging.
It's great for tasks
like database cleanup,
creating backups,
and running machine learning training.
To use it, you simply create a request by
using BGProcessingTaskRequest API,
and provide an application identifier.
Then provide more information,
such as if your task needs
external power or network.
Providing more information
will help the system schedule the task
at a better time window.
The system will then launch your app
in the background at an opportune time
and grant several minutes of runtime
to complete the deferrable work.
Next is discretionary URLSession.
Your app may already be using
Background URLSessions
for general networking.
Background URLSessions get even better
when you use the discretionary flag.
URLSessions with discretionary flag
are networking transactions
offloaded to the system
to perform networking
at a more optimal time,
such as when the device is plugged in
and connected to Wi-Fi.
The discretionary flag
is great for non-user initiated
long-running networking,
such as telemetry collection
or downloading
the next episode of a TV show.
And because the networking was offloaded,
it means
your app does not need to be running
while the network transaction completes.
To use discretionary URL sessions,
you simply set up a background URL
session
and set isDiscretionary to true.
You can provide additional information
to help the system schedule the download
at the right time.
Pass in timeout intervals
so that the system does not attempt
to download forever,
causing battery drain.
If you don't want to upload
or download data
until some point later in the future,
pass in an earliest begin date.
Finally, pass in an expected workload size
so that the system
can intelligently load balance
between your various download tasks.
Similar to how you can control
the immediacy of certain operations
with BGProcessingTask
and discretionary URL sessions,
you can influence the immediacy
of push delivery
by using different push priorities.
Push priority determines how urgently
a push needs to be delivered
to the device.
For a high priority push,
the server will send the push immediately
to the device,
potentially waking the device
and causing battery drain.
For low priority pushes,
the server will delay sending the push
until an opportune time,
such as when the device is awake
or a high priority push comes through.
High priority pushes are great for urgent
messages like a severe weather warning.
Low priority pushes are great
for more passive notifications
that aren't urgent and can be deferred.
Leveraging low priority push to delay
the delivery of deferrable messages
will save battery as the device will not
have to wake as frequently from sleep.
To configure low priority pushes,
simply set apns-priority to 5
in the push payload.
The server will take care of the rest,
and your users will appreciate
the battery life savings.
So let's wrap it up
with some final thoughts and next steps.
Provide an option
of Dark Mode in your app.
If a user chooses Dark Mode,
respecting their intent can save battery.
Review your animations
and hunt for opportunities
to reduce frame rates to what's necessary.
One small animation can have a big impact.
Keep a close eye
on your background runtime
by letting the system know
when you are done.
Finally, consider deferring
long-running background work
to a better time, such as
when the device is connected to a charger.
If you do all this,
then you will have
truly powered down your app.
Thank you so much.