♪ ♪
Harry: Hi, I'm Harry,
an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Welcome to the second part
of the SwiftUI on iPad series.
In the first part of this series,
my colleague Raj dove deep
into how you can use lists, tables,
selection, and split views
to really make your apps shine
using the iPad's larger screens
and various input devices.
If you haven't seen that session,
I highly recommend starting with that.
I really enjoyed seeing Raj build out
the Places app
and I wanted to add some features
of my own.
So in this session
I'll be looking at something
near and dear to my heart, toolbars!
In SwiftUI, the toolbar API
configures many system bars
like the navigation bar
or bottom bar on iOS
or the window toolbar on macOS.
Toolbars provide quick actions
to a lot of your most common features.
Creating a good toolbar can really improve
the productivity of people using your app.
I've been spending a lot of time
thinking about toolbars
and how Places could use some of
the new toolbar features in iOS 16.
I'd like to start by briefly showing you
what I've built
to give you a taste
of what is now possible on iPad.
After all my changes,
here is the updated Places app.
You might notice some new features,
like leading aligned navigation titles,
title menus, title menu headers,
and centered aligned toolbar items.
If you've used a Mac, you might
also be familiar with features
like Toolbar customization,
which allows people to make toolbars
uniquely their own.
These powerful Mac features
are making their debut on the iPad.
To start this session,
I'll show some enhancements
to the toolbar API.
Then I'll walk you through
some new APIs for titles and documents.
So let's dive right in with toolbars.
Now, many of you have already configured
toolbars in your own iOS app
and to optimize for a smaller screen,
you might've added a menu like I did
when I first looked at Places.
My menu looked like this in code.
You can see I have a toolbar item
with a primary action placement.
Inside, I have a more menu,
with a few controls as the menu's content.
Let's see what this looks like on iPad.
As you might have guessed,
it doesn't really take advantage
of the space available there.
What's great, though, is that in iOS 16,
toolbars can implement these kind of menus
on your behalf.
We call these overflow menus
and to make best use of them,
I'll want to restructure
the content of my toolbar.
I'll start by converting the toolbar item
into a toolbar item group.
I'll then remove the menu
and make its content
the content of the toolbar item group.
This group inserts individual toolbar
items for each view in the group.
On iPad and Mac,
this is all that's needed
to automatically move items into
an overflow menu when needed.
There's more I can do here,
but before I can get to that,
I'll need to think about the placement
of my toolbar items.
Placements define the area
in which a toolbar item is rendered.
Different placements
can resolve to the same area.
You can think of a navigation bar
as having three distinct areas:
the leading, the center,
and the trailing area.
The leading and trailing areas
typically contain controls.
While the center contains
your app's navigation title.
Let's look at this
in the context of Places.
In Places
my primary action toolbar item group
resolves to the trailing area
on iPad or Mac.
Primary actions represent
the most common action available
to the user for a particular screen.
In iOS 16, there's a new placement
called secondary action.
These items represent controls
that are not the most used controls,
but still warrant their own toolbar items.
Actions like favoriting and editing
aren't the most important in Places,
so I'll make them secondary actions.
By default, secondary actions
will not be visible in the toolbar.
Instead, they live in the overflow menu.
You can change that behavior
by using the new toolbarRole modifier.
This modifier influences the behavior of
a toolbar by assigning it a semantic role.
Here I pass an editor role
which tells the navigation bar
that it should be optimized
for editing content.
The navigation bar interprets this
as a desire to have more space
to render toolbar items
and so it moves the navigation title
from the center area to the leading area.
This makes room for secondary actions
to be placed in the center
before moving to the overflow menu.
In compact size classes,
the navigation bar doesn't change
and continues to render the title
in the center.
Using the secondary action
and toolbar role API
really lets Places start to take advantage
of the iPad's size.
With the center available to me,
I can add more items to my toolbar,
like a noise button,
or a comfort level button,
or a trash button.
But if I start adding a lot of items,
my toolbar might become unwieldy
for some users.
MacOS has long supported
customizable toolbars
which lets each person choose the toolbar
best for them
and I'm excited to say that now iPadOS
also supports user customization.
You can use the existing toolbar
customization API
that's worked on macOS
to adopt this feature.
Let's look at that now.
Only toolbar items are customizable
so I'll first split up my toolbar item
group into individual toolbar items.
Note that there is no functional
difference after this change.
Customization also requires
every item in the toolbar
to be associated with a unique identifier
so I'll add IDs to each of my items.
It's important for these IDs to be unique
and consistent across app launches.
When a user customizes their toolbar,
SwiftUI persists these IDs
and uses them to look up
the associated view to render.
Finally, I'll add an ID
to the toolbar modifier as a whole.
Altogether, this opts the toolbar
into supporting customization.
Unique to customizable toolbars,
toolbar items have the ability to not be
initially present in the toolbar.
These items start their life
in the customization popover
and can be added to the toolbar later.
Because these items
aren't initially present,
this is a good option for actions that are
more useful to specific workflows.
Let's check them out.
I want to hide some of my current toolbar
items to make my new items easier to see.
Now let's add a toolbar item
that contains a share link.
Share links are new in SwiftUI and rely on
a new protocol called transferable.
For more information
on Transferable and ShareLink,
be sure to check out
the Meet Transferable session.
With my toolbar item in place,
I'll provide a value of false to the shows
by default parameter
which makes this item
not be initially present in the bar.
Now you can see my share link
living its best life
in the customization popover.
And I'm able to drag it from
the customization popover into the bar.
People are going to love that.
With my share link in place,
I started to think about
the relationship between my toolbar items.
After moving the share link into the bar,
I noticed that my image
and map adjustment items are separated,
but I think of these items
as a group of quick editing control,
and I'd like to model that relationship
in the toolbar itself.
iOS 16 and macOS Ventura support
modeling this relationship
by using ControlGroup.
I'll show you how.
You can see
I have two individual toolbar items
for my image and map adjustment actions.
To group them together,
I'll first move them to the same item.
Then I'll wrap them in a control group.
A user can now add or remove them
from the toolbar as a unit.
That's pretty cool,
but I can take this even further
using a new API available on ControlGroup.
By providing a label to the control group,
this group of items can collapse
into its own smaller menu
before moving into the overflow menu.
The toolbar is really
starting to come together.
There's one last change I'd like to make.
Adding a new place
is a common and important action,
so I'd like to add a toolbar item
for that.
To do that,
I'll add a new button to my toolbar,
but this time
I'll use the primary action placement
as I consider the new button
to be the most common action.
This placement highlights an important
distinction between iOS and macOS.
All items within a customizable toolbar
modifier support customization on macOS,
but on iPadOS,
only secondary actions do.
So my new button here renders
in the trailing area of the bar
and is not customizable by the user.
Wow!
That was a lot about toolbars
and those aren't the only improvements.
Navigation titles gained
some new features as well
around menus, documents, and more.
Let's take documents as an example.
There are lot of kinds of documents.
You might be familiar with documents
that are managed
by the document group API.
Document groups come with
a lot of built-in functionality
for representing
and managing their documents.
All of what I'm about to talk about
comes for free when using document groups.
In Places, though, an individual place
can be considered a document
even though Places
isn't using a document group.
It has properties that you can edit,
you can add or remove them
to the Places app,
and you can share
a place with your friends.
Let's look at how
we can show off this relationship
in a non-document group based app.
I already associate the name of the place
as the navigation title of the view.
So I'm already associating a piece
of the place to the title of my toolbar.
In iOS 16, I can take that even further
by using new navigation title modifiers.
Navigation titles now support
presenting a menu.
You can kind of think of this
like the File menu on macOS.
To create one of these menus,
provide a set of actions
to the navigation title,
just like you would a normal menu.
Notice that the title now has
a menu indicator attached to it
that presents a menu
populated with your actions.
And that's not all
navigation titles can do.
One of my favorite parts is its
new ability to support editable titles.
You can pass a binding
to your navigation title
and this tells the toolbar
that you support editing the title.
All you're missing is a way
to actually start editing.
You can use the new RenameButton
inside your titles menus actions
to accomplish this.
Tapping on the rename button
allows you to start renaming the title.
Just like you can associate
a navigation title to your view,
you can now also associate a document,
like my place.
When provided a document,
the title menu renders
a specialized header that shows
a preview of that document.
The preview can be dragged and there's
quick access to share the document.
To get one of these headers,
associate your navigation document
to your view using the new
navigation document modifier.
You can do this by providing a type
that conforms to transferable,
or by providing a URL directly.
Here I'll provide a URL that will open
the Maps app to the place I'm viewing.
The navigation document modifier
will also configure the proxy icon
of the window toolbar on macOS
when providing a URL.
After all that, I think I'll take a break
from updating my app's toolbars.
Can you believe all the features
I've added in this time?
I can't wait to start using them.
I covered a lot in my journey
to improve the Places experience on iPad.
Toolbars on iPad have gained
a lot of new features
like overflow menus
and user customization.
Use the secondary action placement
and customization APIs
to really make the most of the larger
space available on iPad and Mac.
Titles have gained some new ways
to represent themselves in the toolbar.
Use a navigation title or create
a title menu or support title renaming.
And remember to use the navigation
document modifier when appropriate.
I hope you've enjoyed
the SwiftUI on iPad series.
With all the improvements in tables,
selection, toolbars, and more,
go out and take your iPad apps
to the next level.
Thank you, and have a great WW.