♪ Bass-heavy electronic music ♪
It's time for your final report.
♪
First, we covered how to improve
battery consumption
for your apps.
- Display is one
of the major sources
of power consumption.
- We learned how to make
a Swift Server app
alongside an iOS app
in Xcode.
- Using Swift for building
server components
helps bridge
this technology gap.
- Then Neil showed us
how to match audio catalogs
with video
using ShazamKit.
- Now we have some
important updates
that streamline working
with custom catalogs at scale.
- We discovered how
to create multiple windows
for our iPad apps.
- Here's an app I've built
to keep track of the books
I'm reading.
- And we closed out the week
with a friendly device-to-device
game of tic-tac-toe.
- And that's how easy it is
to connect devices to Apple TV.
- Our training is complete,
developers.
You're ready for your mission.
This message will self-destruct
in 3... 2...
Ah, just kidding!
See you next year!
♪