♪ ♪
Raj Ramamurthy: Hello,
and welcome to "SwiftUI on iPad:
Organize your interface."
I'm Raj, and I work on SwiftUI.
iPadOS 16 has a number of updates
to allow building more productive,
professional-grade apps
with rich features.
In this session,
I'm going to discuss a few of them
and talk about organizing the interface
of your SwiftUI apps to shine on iPad.
To start, I'll take you on a tour
of lists and tables.
Then, I'll talk about
the SwiftUI selection model
and how to integrate selection with menus.
Finally, I'll discuss how to structure
your app's navigation
for iPad by using split views.
But wait, there's more.
This is actually the first session
of a two-part series.
In the second part,
my colleague Harry takes a tour
through toolbars, titles, and more.
Harry covers
some really important additions
that take SwiftUI iPad apps
to the next level,
so please make sure
to watch both sessions.
Let's get started with lists and tables.
I recently joined a few book clubs,
but I'm running pretty behind.
It's so hard to find
a quiet place to read.
So to help me focus on my reading,
I've started working on an app
to find these mythical quiet places.
A quiet place is like a reading oasis,
where the pages just fly.
And this app helps me track
all the quiet places that I've found.
I've built the app for iPhone,
but I think it'd be a fun exercise
to update it for iPad to really
take advantage of the larger display.
By making the app better for iPad,
I'll also be further along
when I eventually bring it
to the Mac as well.
I won't be covering the Mac
explicitly in this session,
but many of the APIs shown
also apply on macOS.
Here is a list of all the quiet places
that I've found so far.
This list is a great place
to start with updating the app.
I've started working on the iPad version.
It's not terrible, but it doesn't
take advantage of the bigger screen.
There's quite a bit of wasted space,
and the information density is low.
Thankfully, in iPadOS 16,
there's a great solution
for these sorts
of information dense scenarios:
multi-column tables.
Let me show you what they look like.
Here's the “All Places" view
after adopting the SwiftUI API
for multi-column tables.
I'll work up towards this screenshot
over the next few minutes.
Multi-column tables in SwiftUI
were first introduced in macOS Monterey,
and starting in iPadOS 16, the same
table API is now available for iPad.
Just like on the Mac, tables on iPad
support multiple columns and sorting.
Along with the introduction
of tables on iPad,
SwiftUI now supports sections
in tables on iPad and the Mac.
The general guidance around tables
from the previous session
"SwiftUI on the Mac: Build
the fundamentals" still applies on iPad,
so I invite you to watch that session
if you haven't already.
Let's build up the table shown earlier,
starting from the iPhone list.
Here's the code
for the places list from earlier.
First, I'll switch from a list to a table.
Tables have
a different construction from lists.
Instead of a view builder,
tables accept a column builder.
The first column I'll add
is for the place's name.
The column requires a name
for its header and a view builder
to produce the view
for each element in the collection.
I've also specified a value key path,
which will be important later
when I add sorting to the table.
Notice how similar the view builder is
to the list-based construction.
In fact, I can even reuse
the PlaceCell type from before.
In compact size classes,
tables only show their first column,
which means my table still looks great
on iPhone and in slide over on iPad.
You might notice that this is similar
to a list in appearance.
But I didn't just replace
the table with a list,
because reusing the table allows
for scroll position and selection
to be preserved when transitioning
between size classes.
In general,
make sure to use the first column
for compact-specific appearance,
and always make sure you're testing
your iPad apps in a variety
of environments, like slide over.
Okay, moving on.
I'll add columns
for the comfort and noise levels.
For columns with just textual content,
TableColumn offers a convenience API
that lets me omit the view builder
when my value points to a string.
And in this case,
I know the comfort level isn't
going to need much room,
so I've applied a fixed width.
I can also add sorting to the table
by using comparators.
I'll create some state
to store the comparators in.
The state here is an array
because it represents
all of the comparators for the table.
And setting the initial value
to the name comparator
allows the table to appear sorted
when it's first displayed.
Next, I'll pass a binding to my state
into the table to wire everything up.
Because the columns each specify
their value as a key path
to a comparable field,
they are sortable by default.
And now the table is fully sortable
by name, comfort level, and noise.
Note that table doesn't handle
the sorting on its own.
That's up to me.
I can use the onChange modifier to sort
the data when the sort order changes.
All right, let's take it for a spin.
The table looks great,
showing all the places data
and really taking advantage
of the larger screen.
Unlike on the Mac,
tables on iPad don't scroll horizontally,
so it's important to limit
the number of columns.
This ensures that all of the columns
can be shown at once.
Each column shows its label in the header.
And tapping on the label
sorts that column.
I can even sort by noise level.
And in slide over,
the table collapses into a single column
that represents all of the information
in a more condensed format.
Now that I've updated the list
into a table, let's dive into selection.
In this section,
I'll review the SwiftUI selection model
and discuss
integrating selection with menus.
Along the way, I'm going to supercharge
the places table with rich functionality.
But first, I'll talk about
how selection works in SwiftUI.
SwiftUI includes a robust API
for managing list and table selection.
Here's a diagram with a list
containing a few rows.
Each row has a tag.
These tags are unique values for each row
that help the list manage selection.
In this diagram,
the tags are shown in green circles.
Along with the tag, there's also
some state that holds the selection.
This is the type
that holds the tag values.
For example, with multiple selection,
this is a set that holds the tags
for each selected row.
The job of the list is to coordinate
between the tag in each row
and the selection state.
And it does this
via its selection binding.
So when a row is selected,
such as row number two here,
the list adds it to the set
via the selection binding.
And similarly,
if some other part of the app
programmatically changes the set,
say to add three like shown here,
the list selects it
because the selection binding changes.
This general model is the same
across iOS and macOS.
So there are two parts to selection:
a tag and some state.
Next, I'd like to talk
about where tags come from.
A tag is just a value for a view
in a selectable container
that is used to track
whether that view is selected.
In many cases, SwiftUI can automatically
synthesize tags on your behalf.
Tags are similar to identifiers,
but not quite the same.
When using ForEach,
SwiftUI will automatically derive the tag
for a view from its explicit identity.
And tables will use their row value's
identifier as the selection tag.
In the places app, that means the place
struct's identifier type will be used.
For more information
about explicit identity,
check out "Demystify SwiftUI."
To manually tag views,
use the tag modifier.
This is what ForEach does under the hood.
The tag modifier takes a Hashable value.
However, when using the tag modifier,
be careful–
it's important that all of the views
in a selectable container
share the same tag type.
Otherwise, SwiftUI might not know
how to select the view.
Note that if you use the ID modifier,
it doesn't set the tag.
So that's an overview of tags.
Let's bring back the diagram from earlier.
Now that I've explained the tag part
of this diagram,
I'd like to focus on the other half
of the selection equation:
the selection state.
In the previous example, I used a set,
but there are other options too.
You can use these data structures
to represent selection.
SwiftUI supports single selection,
new in macOS Ventura,
required selection for macOS sidebars,
and multiple selection.
iPadOS 16 also introduces
lightweight multiple selection.
Now, with a keyboard attached,
you don't need to enter edit mode
to select multiple rows,
which helps avoid modality.
When using a keyboard,
you can use common shortcuts
like shift and command
to extend and modify the selection.
And this works great with the pointer.
Here's what the places table looks like
after adopting selection.
In this example,
I have an attached keyboard and trackpad,
so the rows aren't indented,
but they're still selected.
However, when using touch,
I'll still need to enter edit mode,
which is accelerated
by using a two-finger pan.
SwiftUI supports
this gesture automatically.
Speaking of edit mode,
there are some updates
with single selection
and edit mode as well.
In iOS 16,
list selection on iPhone and iPad
no longer requires edit mode
when selecting a single row.
And this is super useful for coordinating
with the updated navigation APIs.
With all of these updates,
that brings us to this table,
which builds upon the previous table
by adding a new column for edit mode.
Edit mode is only required when using
multiple selection without a keyboard.
So with that, I'll update the places table
to support selection.
I can easily add selection
to the places table
by adding some state
to store the selection.
After creating the state,
I'll pass a binding
to the table's initializer.
Table enforces that its selection type
matches its row identifier,
so I've used the place ID type
as the selection type.
Since I want multiple selection,
I've used a set for the selection state.
Table tags its rows automatically,
so I don't need to tag anything myself.
And now I can select rows in the table.
But I haven't really done
anything with the selection.
I think it'd be great to add a button
that allows me to add the selected places
to a guide that I can share
with others in my book club.
This is the code
to add the toolbar button.
If there is a non-empty selection,
the button will now show up.
I've also added an edit button,
which complements the existing
lightweight selection support,
but it provides an affordance
to enter and exit edit mode
when there is no keyboard.
A good iPad app shines both with
and without the keyboard,
so it's important to offer controls
to enter and exit edit mode.
We're getting there.
Now we have a button that shows up
when we select rows
as well as a button
to enter and exit edit mode.
Please make sure to watch
the second session in this series
for more information about toolbars.
I'm pretty happy
with the toolbar button here,
but we can do more.
For actions on selection,
it's a great practice to keep them
as easy to access as possible.
That's why in iOS 16,
iPadOS 16, and macOS Ventura,
SwiftUI adds support
for multi-select context menus.
Multi-select context menus allow
for a context menu to be presented
that operates on a set
of selected identifiers.
Let's examine the anatomy of this table
to understand more.
Item-based context menus
have three variations.
First, you can show a menu
on multiple items,
such as the selection at the top.
You can also show a context menu
on an individual item.
And lastly, you can show a context menu
on an empty area,
where there is no content.
Let's add support for this
into our places table.
I've omitted some details
from the previous code examples
so we can focus on the context menu.
I've added the new contextMenu modifier
that takes a selection type.
This needs to match the selection type
of the list or table,
so since I'm using a table,
I'll use the PlaceID type.
The closure is passed
a set of the items to act on,
so if it's empty,
I know the menu is for the empty area.
I think a button to add a new place
would work great for the empty area.
That way, when I'm on the go
and find a new quiet place to read,
I can add it quickly.
Note that if the view builder
for the empty set of items
doesn't resolve to a view,
SwiftUI won't show a menu
on the empty area.
Next, let's handle a single selection.
If the set has only a single item,
I know the menu is being shown
for a single place.
And for both single
and multiple selections,
I want to be able to add
these places to a guide,
so I'll add another view to the menu.
Let's check out our progress.
Here's the new
context menu support in action.
Clicking on the empty area shows
a menu item to add a new place.
Selecting a single row shows
a context menu for just that row.
And I can extend the selection
with the keyboard,
creating this blue highlight.
I can then activate a context menu
over multiple rows,
allowing me to easily add places
to a guide.
This table is looking pretty snazzy now,
so I think it's time to add
some structure around it.
To do that, I'll need a split view.
Navigation is a fundamental part
of the iPad experience.
And split views are a great way
to avoid modality on iPad's larger display
by showing more information at once
without the need to drill in.
In this section, I'm going to cover
some updates to SwiftUI
around navigation and split views.
In the previous sections,
I created the places table
and added rich features
like selection and edit mode.
But I think the places app
is lacking some structure.
So in this section, I'll build
the foundation of our app's structure
by leveraging a navigation split view.
New in iPadOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
SwiftUI has improved support
for split views
with the NavigationSplitView type.
SwiftUI supports two
or three column split views
and has multiple styles
for complex control
over how the columns are displayed.
I'm not going to fully cover
how to present navigation content
in this session,
so for that, I invite you to check out
the SwiftUI cookbook for navigation.
Curt has quite a few recipes
for cooking up some really tasty
navigation experiences.
Instead, I'm going to focus
more on split views.
Here's a diagram showing
a two column split view on iPad.
In SwiftUI, the leading column
is called the sidebar column
and the trailing column is called
the detail column.
Notice how the columns are balanced
next to each other here.
In landscape,
SwiftUI offers this by default.
In portrait, however,
the sidebar hides out of the way,
showing only the detail column.
Tapping on the sidebar button
shows the sidebar,
which appears over the detail column,
dimming it underneath.
Generally, a two column split view
will prefer to show
only the detail column
when space constrained,
because the detail column often shows
more important information
than the sidebar column.
If you'd like to customize this behavior,
you can either always prefer
the detail column
with the prominentDetail navigation
split view style
or balance the weighting
with the balanced
NavigationSplitView style.
NavigationSplitView also supports
three column layouts.
With three columns,
there is an additional column
between the sidebar and detail
called the content column.
If you're coming from UIKit, you may
know this as the supplementary column.
In landscape,
the content and detail column are shown,
and the sidebar can be toggled.
After tapping on the toolbar button,
the detail column slides out of the way,
making room for the sidebar and content.
In portrait,
only the detail column is shown,
and tapping on the toolbar button
shows the content.
From there,
tapping again shows the sidebar.
The sidebar and content
both overlay the detail.
In general, I recommend
sticking with the automatic style
for three column split views
because it makes the best use
of the available space
and is specialized for larger displays.
Just like the two column split view,
the three column split view collapses
to a stack in compact size classes.
Now that I've covered
the basics of split views,
it's time to add one to the places app.
Here is the content view.
I've created a NavigationSplitView
with two columns here.
The first column is the sidebar column
and the second column
is the detail column.
The detail column is populated
by links from the sidebar column,
but if nothing is presented,
the placeholder with "select a place"
will be shown instead.
Here's a screenshot of the placeholder.
It's pretty great.
This is using the automatic style,
which shows the sidebar in landscape,
hiding it out of the way in portrait.
Tapping on a row in the sidebar
presents that row in the detail column.
And when using slide over,
the columns collapse automatically.
This is just the tip of the iceberg–
there are so many
exciting navigation additions,
including better support
for state restoration,
deep linking,
and even richer programmatic control.
Again, I encourage you to check out
the navigation cookbook session for more.
I've built some awesome iPad features
into the app,
and I'm excited to go find
some peaceful places to read.
Hopefully I'll be caught up
with my book club soon.
In this session,
I've covered how to leverage tables
for rich display of data,
how to manage
sophisticated selection interactions,
and how to avoid modality
with split views.
Make sure to check out
the related sessions
and refine your SwiftUI apps
to leverage the power of iPad.
Thank you.
♪ ♪