♪ ♪
Kiara Rose: Hi, my name is Kiara Rose,
and I work as a Safari Extensions
Engineer.
Today I'm very excited to be speaking
to you all about what's new
in Safari Web Extensions this year.
Before we dive into today's presentation,
I'd like to take a moment
to thank all of you
for submitting your iOS, iPadOS,
and macOS extensions to the App Store.
Moving forward, our goal is to continue
to implement new features and APIs
so that you can deliver
even better experiences for your users.
And today, I'm going to highlight
some of the exciting new features
that we've implemented over the past year,
such as a new Manifest version
for extensions,
updated APIs,
and syncing extensions
across multiple devices.
Let's get started with Manifest version 3.
Manifest version 3 is the next iteration
of the web extension platform.
It introduces performance
and security improvements
and consolidates popular extension APIs.
For those of who have already updated
your extension to use version 3,
your extension
will now work in Safari 15.4 and onwards.
For those of you who haven't,
there's no need to worry,
because we will continue
to support extensions
using Manifest version 2 in Safari.
One of the key new features
in Manifest version 3
is that your extension can use a service
worker instead of a background page.
If you're a web developer, you're likely
familiar with service workers.
These are event driven pages
where you can register listeners
using the addEventListener API.
These pages are also compatible
with other browsers
that support Manifest version 3.
If you prefer to keep using
background pages for your extension,
you're more than welcome to do so,
but they must be non-persistent.
Another improvement in version 3 is
that the APIs for executing JavaScript
and styling on a web page have moved from
the tabs API to the new scripting API.
Most of the functionality of these methods
remain the same,
but there are some new, additional
features that scripting provides,
such as new ways to inject code
on a webpage,
more options for which frames on the page
the code should be executed in,
and the ability to decide which execution
environment the code should run in.
Let's take a look at how the code
for the new scripting API
differs from the tabs API.
In this code snippet,
I'm using the tabs.executeScript API
to change the background color
of a webpage to blue.
And with this API, I can only
inject code that's contained in a string,
by passing along the "code" property,
But now, with the new scripting API,
I can pass along a function object
containing this code.
And like any other function,
it can contain arguments
that can be passed in.
This is a much more improved way
of executing a script
because you're not confined
to writing code in a string.
And note that with scripting,
there's a new property called target.
This property is used to specify
where the script should run.
In order to execute a script,
you have to specify the ID of the tab
you want to script to execute in.
This API will return an error
if the tab ID isn't specified.
Then, if you'd like to select which frames
of the webpage
to inject the code,
you can specify the frame IDs.
Note that with the tabs API,
you can only specify one ID.
But with scripting, you can specify
multiple IDs.
But let's say I have a lot more code
and it would look much cleaner
if I could contain it in multiple files.
In the tabs.executeScript API,
I can only specify one file,
but in scripting.executeScript,
I can specify multiple files.
Similarly, the same can be done
for insertCSS,
where you can inject styling
on a webpage,
and the same for removeCSS
where you can remove injected styling
from a webpage.
These APIs are available to use
in both Manifest versions 2 and 3.
However, the tabs.executeScript APIs
are not available in version 3.
In addition to the new scripting API,
there have been some slight modifications
to a few other APIs as well.
One of these modifications
is for web_accessible_resources.
In Manifest version 2,
if you want to include resources,
you'd do so by passing along
an array of files
you'd like a webpage to have access to.
But this can be problematic
since it'd give any webpage access
to all the resources
you specify in the Manifest.
With the new format in version 3,
you're in control of which resources
are available on any given site.
Let's take a look at an example.
Previously,
the cookie and pie images were available
on every site the extension had access to.
But now, with version 3,
I can make the pie image available
only on apple.com URLs,
and the cookie image
just on webkit.org pages.
Now let's take a look
at the modifications
to the browser_action and page_action
APIs.
In Manifest version 2, the actions
were specified distinctly like this.
But since these
APIs fulfill similar roles,
they've been consolidated to use just
one API in version 3, which is action.
We've also made updates to how
you declare content security policies
for your extension.
In version 2, an extension's policy
was defined using a string.
However, in version 3,
the policy is defined
using an object
with the key "extension_pages".
It's important to note
that remote sources for scripts
are no longer allowed for version 3.
The final API change has been
to the deprecated
browser.extension.getURL API.
This API is no longer supported
in version 3.
Instead, use the equivalent API
in browser.runtime.
So I've talked about the new features
introduced in Manifest version 3,
now let's step through the process
of updating your extensions
so that you can use these new features.
I'll update the Sea Creator extension
from last year's presentation
to use Manifest version 3.
This extension replaces all occurrences
of the word fish with an emoji.
The first thing I'll do is change
the version number from 2 to 3.
And even though I can still use
a non-persistent background page
for version 3,
I'll update this to use a service worker
so that my extension
will be compatible with Chrome.
Lastly,
I'll change browser_action to action.
And in terms of the structure
of the Manifest,
these are the key changes I'll need to
make to have this extension
be compatible with the new
specifications in version 3.
So to test this out,
I'll build the extension,
and enable it in Safari.
Then I'll navigate to a webkit.org
blog page
where I'll use this extension to replace
every instance of the word fish
with a fish emoji.
But it looks like something went wrong.
As you can see, none of the words on this
page have been replaced with an emoji.
Let's inspect the popover
to see if there are any error messages.
In the console tab,
I see that there is an error message
stating that browser.tabs.executeScript
is undefined.
That's because this API
is no longer available in version 3,
so I should update my extension
to use the new scripting API instead.
In Xcode, I'll go back
to the popup.js file,
and then I'll change this line
to use scripting instead.
I'll add the target property,
which is used to specify
where the script should be injected into.
And with the new scripting API,
I'll have to specify the ID of the tab.
I can do this by using
the tabs.getCurrent API
to get an object containing
the information of the current tab.
Then I can use that object
to retrieve the tab ID.
Next, I'll add the file
containing the script to run.
Finally, the last change I'll make
is to add the scripting permission
in the Manifest.
I'll go ahead and build the extension
and use these changes in Safari.
And as you can see,
this extension now works in Safari,
using the new features
in Manifest version 3.
So that's how simple it is
to upgrade your extension.
But if you're not yet comfortable
with these new changes,
a lot of the features
such as scripting and services workers
are also available to use in version 2.
Now let's take a look at some of the APIs
we've updated this year,
starting with declarative net request.
Declarative net request is
a content blocking API
that provides web extensions with a fast
and privacy preserving way
to block or modify network requests
using rulesets.
This API allows you to delegate
all the work of intercepting
and modifying requests off to Safari
and all you have to do
is specify the content blocking rules
that should be applied.
You can specify a ruleset in the Manifest.
Here I've added the declarative
net request permission,
and I've used
the declarative_net_request key
to add one ruleset that should applied
to all pages.
Previously, I could only declare
up to 10 rulesets in the Manifest.
But now with the new updates
to this feature,
you can declare up to 50 rulesets,
which means your extension
can be more customizable.
But keep in mind that only 10 of these
rulesets can be enabled at once.
For more information
on how to create rulesets,
check out last year's presentation
on Safari Web Extensions,
where we go into more depth on this API.
Let's move on to some of the new features
for declarative net request.
Previously, you could only declare
rulesets in the Manifest,
but now we've implemented
the following two APIs
that will allow you
to update your rules dynamically.
The first API is updateSessionRules,
which will allow you to add or remove
rules for your extension.
But it's important to note
that these rules will not persist
across browser sessions
or extension updates.
If you would like to update rules
that will persist,
use the updateDynamicRules API instead.
This will allow you to update
your blocking rules
without updating your entire extension.
Let's take a look
at how we can use one of these APIs
to make modifications to our rulesets.
I'm going to block some content on
webpages using the sea creator extension,
and then, I'll use the new APIs
to unblock content on select pages.
In the extensions Manifest,
the first thing I'll do
is add the declarative net request
permission.
Then, I'll use the declarative net request
key to add a ruleset.
The rule that's being applied
is located in the rules.json file.
In this file, I've declared one rule
which blocks all images on all URLs.
Let's build the extension and
see how this rule is applied in Safari.
As you can see,
the image on this page has disappeared.
Which is exactly what we expected.
This shows that Safari has successfully
applied our content blocking rule.
And if I navigate
to this Wikipedia page on fish,
I'll see that the image on this site
has been blocked as well.
But let's say we want to update
our rules to block images on all pages
expect webkit.org blog pages.
Using one of the updated APIs
for declarative net request,
we can do just that.
Let's go back to Xcode
and make some changes.
In the popup.js file,
I'll declare a function
to update our content blocking rules.
I'll set the rule to allow images
on webkit.org/blog-files pages.
Then, I'll use the updateSessionRules API
to add this rule to our ruleset.
Lastly, I'll build the extension
and test our changes in Safari.
As you can see,
the image on this blog post has loaded,
showing that our new rule to allow images
on this site has worked.
And if I go to the Wikipedia site,
we'll see that the images on this page
are still blocked,
showing that the new rule
wasn't applied to this page.
So that's how you can use the new
declarative net request APIs
to update your content blocking rules.
Now, let's take a look at how your
extension can communicate with a webpage.
This awesome feature allows websites
to create custom behavior
if the user has your extension enabled.
The API is called externally_connectable.
To use it, you declare match patterns
in the Manifest.
These match patterns determine which pages
can communicate with your extension.
And an important thing to note
is that this feature only works
using the browser namespace.
And lastly, the user has to grant
your extension access to the page
before it can send or receive messages.
Let's take a look at the code you'd add
in the web page to use this feature.
First, you'll need to get the extensionID.
It's the bundle identifier
of the extension
and the team identifier in this format.
You can find your team identifier
on developer.apple.com,
in the membership tab
in your account settings.
Then you'll use the send message API
to post a message to the extension.
You can handle the response
you'll receive from the extension
by passing along a function.
Now let's take a look at the code
your extension will have
to receive messages.
Your extension can receive messages
from the webpage
by listening to the event
called onMessageExternal.
The extension can send a message
back to the web page
using the method passed
to the event listener.
Because there are different extension
web stores for different browsers,
extensions can have
many different identifiers.
So you'll need to determine
the correct one to use
to make sure you're messaging
a Safari web extension,
and not a Chrome or Edge extension.
To do this, you can use
the browser.runtime.sendMessage API
with a call to Promise.all.
Next, let's look at some example code
that will help you do this.
From the webpage,
you can broadcast multiple messages
using multiple extension IDs.
You'll get exactly one response
from an extension
and that'll let you know which extension
ID to use for further communication.
Here, I have a function
called determineExtensionID.
This function sends a message
to the extension
using the browser.runtime.sendMessage API.
If you have multiple IDs
and you want to determine
the correct one to use,
then you can use Promise.all
to make multiple calls
using the determineExtensionID function.
Promise.all takes an array of promises
and then returns a single promise
with an array
of all of the resolved values.
You can use this array to find
the extension that the user has installed.
In the extension's background page,
you'll need to listen for a message
from the web page.
When you receive the message,
you'll need to send one back
to tell the web page
that your extension is installed.
So that's how you can use
the new externally_connectable API
to allow your extension
to communicate with a web page.
The next feature we've updated
is a personal favorite of mine,
and that is unlimitedStorage.
And I'm so happy to announce that
unlimitedStorage is actually unlimited!
Given that this feature
was so highly requested by you,
we're excited to share that your extension
will no longer have a 10 MB quota.
You are free to use
as much data as you see fit.
Although, it's important to note
that users have the ability
to clear the data being used
by your extension at any given time.
So be sure to only store data
that's strictly necessary
so users don't feel inclined
to clear your data.
To use this feature, simply claim the
storage and unlimitedStorage permission
in the Manifest, and you're good to go.
So those were all of the APIs we've
updated for web extensions this past year.
Lastly, let's talk about a new feature
that will easily allow your users
to get your extension
on all of their devices.
In Safari 16, we've made the experience
of using extensions more seamless.
If a user turns on your extension
on one of their devices,
it'll be turned on
on all of their devices.
On top of this, we've made the process of
downloading your extension much simpler.
Let's take a look at how this works.
Let's say a user has one of
your extensions enabled on their Mac.
In Extension Settings
on any of their other devices,
they'll be given the option
to download your extension.
Once it's downloaded,
it'll automatically be enabled
on their device,
improving their user experience.
Now, let's dive into
how you can set this up
for web extensions and content blockers.
First, we recommend that you list
your extension for iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS
when submitting to the App Store.
This way, your extension will be available
across all of your users' devices.
Then, to allow your extension
to sync across their devices,
you'll need to use one of
the following two methods.
The simplest and recommended way,
is to adopt universal purchase.
Universal purchase allows your users to
enjoy your extension across all platforms,
by only purchasing it once.
If you use this method, you're all set.
Your users will get all of the features
I've shown
after they download your extension once.
To set up universal purchase,
you'll need to use
a single bundle identifier
across your extensions so that it can be
associated with the same app record
in App Store Connect.
For more information on how to do this,
check out our documentation
on how to set up universal purchase
for your extensions.
But if you choose not to set up
universal purchase,
you can manually link your apps.
To do this, you'll use Xcode to add
bundle identifiers in the info plist
for the apps
and extensions you'd like to sync.
To sync your iOS app
and extension with the macOS ones,
you'll need to use specific keys
in the info plist.
You'll put this key
in your macOS app plist,
and this key in
the macOS extension plist.
Similarly, you'll follow the same process
for syncing your macOS app.
By adding this key to the iOS app plist
and this key to the iOS extension plist.
Let's see how this works in Xcode.
In Xcode, the first thing we'll need to do
is update the settings for each target
to include the bundle identifiers of
the extensions and apps we want to sync.
I'll start by adding the bundle identifier
for the corresponding macOS app
in the info plist for the iOS app.
And as you can see, I've done the same
process for the macOS app
by adding the iOS app bundle identifier.
And similarly for iOS extension by adding
the macOS extension bundle identifier.
And lastly, for the macOS extension
by adding the iOS extension
bundle identifier.
And that's how simple it is
to link your apps and extensions
so that your users
can use them everywhere.
To recap, you can make
this feature available for your users
by either setting up universal purchase
or by adding bundle identifiers for each
iOS and macOS app and extension in Xcode.
Today we discussed Manifest version 3,
the APIs we've updated,
and syncing extensions
across multiple devices.
I hope you're as excited as I am
about these all these new features
for Safari Web Extensions.
Feel free to download the sample project
containing the code from today's session
and to play around
with some of the APIs we featured.
Next, we'd love to know what you think.
Use Feedback Assistant to file bugs
or chat with us
on the Safari Developer Forums
to provide feedback
on how we can make developing extensions
better for you.
No, really.
We want to know what you think!
Consider joining
the WebExtensions community group
to shape the future of web extensions.
Finally, check out our WWDC presentation
on creating web inspector extensions.
Thanks for tuning in to this session,
and have a great rest of your WWDC.