[upbeat music]
Hey there,
I'm Justin from Privacy Engineering,
and welcome to
"What's new in privacy."
At Apple, we believe
that privacy is a fundamental human right,
and protecting people's privacy
is at the center of everything we do.
You want people to love your app
and make it part of their life.
Building a great feature
is how you get their attention,
and building with privacy
is how you maintain their trust
and your place in their life.
When people understand what data is
collected about them and how it's used,
they're more likely to fully engage
with your app or service
instead of choosing an alternative.
At Apple, we've prioritized
great features and great privacy
for the people who use our products,
and we want to help you deliver
this to your customers too.
At Apple, we approach this goal
of great features and great privacy
with a set of actionable patterns,
the privacy pillars.
These are a great guide for you as well
on how build privacy into your app.
The first is data minimization.
Use only the data needed
to build the feature.
Next is on-device processing.
If the feature requires sensitive data,
use the power of the device
to avoid sharing it with the server.
Third is transparency and control.
If sensitive data is sent off device,
make sure people understand what is sent,
how it's used,
and give them control.
Finally, security protections.
Protect sensitive data
in transit and at rest,
both on and off the device.
In this video, I'll talk about some
platform changes that will impact you,
some new privacy-enhancing features
that you should adopt,
and an important new feature
with privacy impact.
First, I'll talk about some changes coming
to the platform that will impact your app.
iOS 16 and macOS Ventura
include several important changes:
a new device name entitlement
that restricts access to the device name;
the location indicator now
shows app attribution in Control Center;
improvements to Gatekeeper
that verify the integrity
of notarized apps in more places;
launching Mac apps at login
now notifies people of additions
and has a simplified API;
legacy Pasteboard access
now requires permission.
I'll start with changes
to device name access.
To make it easier to identify devices,
the user's name
from their Apple ID account
is included by default as part
of the device name on iOS.
Before iOS 16,
the UIDevice API allowed apps
to access the user-assigned device name.
To better align app access
of this value with user expectations,
the UIDevice.name API will
return the model of the device
rather than the user-assigned name,
regardless of how people customize it.
We understand that some apps
have multi-device experiences
that utilize the device name,
like making it clear to people
where a document was last edited.
If your app uses multi-device features
and makes this visible in your app's UI,
you can request the entitlement
to access the device name.
Even with this entitlement,
sharing the device name with third parties
other than cloud-hosting service providers
is not permitted.
Next is updates
to attribution for location use.
When apps use location,
iOS displays an arrow in the status bar.
In iOS 16,
swiping down from the Control Center
indicates which app is using location.
Make sure that your app
only uses location when expected
to avoid surprising people.
Now I'd like to talk about the Mac.
Gatekeeper checks the integrity
of newly-downloaded apps.
In macOS Ventura,
Gatekeeper will now check
the integrity of all notarized apps,
not just quarantined apps.
First, apps need to be properly signed.
Starting with macOS Ventura,
if your notarized app is
no longer validly signed,
it will be blocked
by Gatekeeper on first launch.
You should sign
all your executables and bundles
and ensure that their signatures stay
valid when you make changes to your apps.
In addition to an integrity check,
Gatekeeper will also prevent
your app from being modified
in certain ways.
The most common way
apps are modified is for updates.
Apps validly signed by the same
developer account or team will continue
to be able to update each other.
This will just work.
To allow another development team
to update your app
or restrict updates to only your updater,
you can update your info-plist.
For example, here,
Unrelated App can allow Pal About
to update it with just a plist change.
Simply add the NSUpdateSecurityPolicy
you want to allow.
Within NSUpdateSecurityPolicy,
add “AllowProcesses”, a dictionary
mapping team identifiers
to an array of signing identifiers.
In this example,
the policy allows any process
with the signing identifier
com.example.pal.about
signed by Pal About's team identifier
to update your app.
If an app is modified
by something that isn't signed
by the same development team
and isn't allowed
by an NSUpdateSecurityPolicy,
macOS will block the modification
and notify the user that an app wants
to manage other apps.
Clicking on the notification
sends people to System Settings,
where they can allow an app
to update and modify other apps.
To prepare for macOS Ventura,
you should sign the executables
and bundles for your app and make sure
those signatures remain valid
after updates.
Enumerate any updaters you use
and adopt an NSUpdateSecurityPolicy.
Remember that if your app tries
to modify other apps outside the policy,
users will need to allow this.
Next, I'll talk about launching apps
at login on the Mac.
In macOS Monterey and earlier,
when someone logs into their Mac,
apps can run at login
using launch agents or daemons.
This is convenient as it allows apps
to run menu helpers,
check for software updates
in the background
or synchronize data across multiple apps.
Sometimes when a user logs into their Mac,
apps that aren't relevant open
and may be in their way.
In addition, apps or other software
can access sensors or data like location.
It is not always clear to people
that this is happening,
as what's running may not be visible.
And for developers,
it's not always clear which mechanism
to use to launch at login:
daemons, agents, service management…?
With macOS Ventura, this is much simpler.
In macOS Ventura, you can use
a new, single API to launch your app,
launch agent or daemon at login.
Your app will be allowed
to launch at login by default,
and users will be notified.
If your app requires a daemon
with elevated permissions,
it will require admin approval to enable.
Clicking on the notification
opens the Login Items pane
in System Settings, where people can
manage apps that launch on their system.
The top portion
controls apps that run at login,
and the bottom portion controls
other items that run at login.
This pane now controls different ways
apps can run at login,
including agents,
daemons, SMLoginItems,
and apps that add themselves
to open at login.
Here's how you can use this new API.
The service management framework
makes it easy for you
to launch resources at login.
Since all agents and daemons
live inside your app bundle,
you don't need to use an installer
to write launch agents
or create cleanup scripts anymore,
and this works in Mac App Store apps too.
Call the SMAppService API
from your app to control when people
get the notification and what
your app icon looks like in Settings.
Next is pasteboard access.
Previously, a transparency notice
let people know when apps accessed
the pasteboard when they had
not pressed paste in the edit options.
In iOS 16, the system confirms intent
for all access to pasteboard items
written by other apps.
If your app continues
to access values for pasteboard items
using the UIPasteboard API,
the system will display a modal prompt.
There are three ways to avoid
this prompt appearing in your app.
The first is to use the edit options menu.
The second is
to use the keyboard shortcut.
In the “Features to adopt” section,
I'll talk about the third option,
the new UIKit paste controls.
Those are the privacy changes
coming to the platform
that you need to know about.
In addition, there are a few new
privacy-enhancing technologies
that make it easier for you
to build seamless experiences
with privacy into your app.
I'll start by talking
about UIKit paste controls.
Add UIKit paste controls
to your app experience
so people can intuitively provide access
to their pasteboard by pressing a button.
Adopting UIKit paste controls
allows pasting without an edit menu,
keyboard shortcut or system prompt.
The system confirms intent
by verifying the button was
visibly displayed and tapped.
Customize these buttons
to fit with your app's interface.
Change the rounded corners
or change the color of the text,
icon or background.
Just be sure
the button has enough contrast
and isn't hidden behind other elements
or it won't work.
Make sure to test that your paste buttons
work as you expect.
Another tool to create
a seamless experience
while minimizing data access
is media device discovery.
Apps today use a wide range
of streaming protocols,
with custom discovery
and communication logic.
To stream media using one
of those protocols before,
apps needed permission
to access the local network,
and often Bluetooth.
This permission is needed
because knowledge of all devices
is required to manage device selection
but this provides access
to more information than is necessary
and poses a fingerprinting risk.
Media device discovery lets
your app stream to selected devices
without having to present network
or Bluetooth access prompts.
Streaming devices appear right
in the same picker as AirPlay,
and apps only see
the device picked to stream to.
This works thanks
to DeviceDiscovery extensions.
This extension can search
for local network and Bluetooth devices
but is sandboxed separately from the app,
so it can't send scan results back.
This means no broad permission is needed
for the app to access the local network
or Bluetooth since the app
doesn't see the whole network.
Instead, the extension can
only send the discovered accessories
to the DeviceDiscoveryExtension framework.
The DeviceDiscoveryExtension
framework presents the list
of discovered devices in the picker,
and after a selection is made,
the system enables communication
with the selected device.
No other permissions are needed.
Protocol providers should
create an app extension
with DeviceDiscoveryExtension,
extend AVRoutePickerView
to handle user selection callbacks,
handle user-selected networking devices
in your protocol,
download the sample
app and extension to learn more.
App developers should contact
their streaming protocol provider
to implement a DeviceDiscoveryExtension.
Media device discovery is
an opportunity to build great features
with great privacy.
Your app gets to access exactly
the data it needs to stream -
discovery is simple and prompt-free,
and people get great network privacy.
This is a win for everyone.
Just like media device discovery
provides permission to access only
the devices needed without prompts,
the PHPicker API provides permission
to access only the photos needed
without prompts.
PHPicker is on the Mac now
with macOS Ventura
and the watch with watchOS 9.
Update your Mac and watch apps
to access photos without prompting users
for access to all photos.
Next is private access tokens,
which are a powerful tool to prevent fraud
without CAPTCHAs getting in the way.
Private Access Tokens replace CAPTCHAs
and are built using blinded tokens
that allow website
or API developers to recognize
legitimate devices without being able
to track those devices.
Apple doesn't know what websites
a device fetches tokens for,
and the servers receiving the tokens
don't learn the identity
of the device sending the token.
Private Access Tokens are part
of the Privacy Pass IETF open standard
and are the same technology we use
to verify the authenticity
of Private Relay users.
To learn more, check out the video,
"Replace CAPTCHAs
with Private Access Tokens."
Now I'll go over Passkeys.
Passwords are at the center
of authenticating accounts
and keeping personal data secure
but they have serious issues.
They're hard to remember,
so people make them simpler
or reuse them across multiple sites.
And they can be phished.
Passkeys enable
a more robust authentication solution
and use the same
instantly familiar UI style
and biometric verification
as password autofill.
Passkeys are
built on public key cryptography,
so the value the server stores
can't be weak,
and if it's revealed,
it doesn't matter
because it's truly public.
Because passkeys are inherently linked
to the website they correspond to,
they can't be phished.
For more information
on implementing passkeys,
there's a full video, "Meet Passkeys.”
Those are the exciting and important
privacy updates for you to adopt!
One more important thing I want
to talk about is a new privacy tool
in iOS 16 called Safety Check.
Safety Check is designed
to help people in domestic
or intimate partner violence situations
review and reset access
they may have granted
to others previously.
Safety Check helps in the following ways:
It stops sharing data with people by
turning off location sharing in FindMy
and stopping sharing in Photos,
Notes and Calendar.
It stops sharing data with apps
by resetting system privacy permission
for all third-party apps.
It helps you sign out of FaceTime
and iMessage on your other iCloud devices
to ensure Messages and calls are
sent only to the device in your hand.
It walks you through signing
out of other iCloud devices to ensure
other devices can't receive updates
on location from FindMy, Photos,
calendars, etc.
It helps you change passwords
for both the device
and iCloud account.
And trusted phone numbers
for iCloud two-factor auth.
And it helps you manage emergency contacts
to make any changes as needed.
All these things together help people
with threats to their personal safety
control access to their data.
There are two ways to use Safety Check.
The first is Emergency Reset,
for crisis situations when you need
to immediately reset access
across people and apps.
The second is Manage Sharing & Access,
which provides more fine-grained control
over each capability of Safety Check.
Emergency Reset lets you quickly
take action across all people and all apps
and disables access to FaceTime
and iMessage on your other devices.
Then you are walked through securing
your iCloud account to the device
in your hand
and reviewing your emergency contacts
and trusted devices.
Manage Sharing & Access
lets you review person by person
and app by app
to review who you're sharing with.
You can sort this by name or the type
of information you're sharing.
This is a great tool
to understand and control your sharing
with a particular person.
It also can help you find an app
with sensitive permissions
installed by someone
with access to your device.
Quick Exit is available
in all Safety Check flows
and quickly lets people exit the flow
if they're concerned
someone might see what they're doing.
Pressing it returns them
to the home screen,
and the next time they enter settings,
they'll be back
on the main settings page,
not in Safety Check.
Safety Check helps people in domestic
or intimate partner violence situations
take back control of their private data.
Privacy isn't just about making a decision
in the moment you share data,
but also being able to understand
and change that decision at any time.
This is just one example
of how Apple designs for privacy.
Designing for privacy in your app
will help you build and maintain trust
with your users.
iOS 16 and macOS Ventura bring many new
technologies to help you on this journey.
Prepare for new platform updates
like UI device name changes
and Gatekeeper improvements.
Adopt media device discovery extensions,
UIKit paste controls,
Private Access Tokens,
and Passkeys.
Thanks for joining me today.
We can't wait to see how
you build great features
and great privacy into your app.
[upbeat music]