♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hi, my name is Adam,
and I'm a Manager with the Developer
Experience Team.
And I'm Sasan,
an Engineer with the Xcode Cloud Team.
In this session,
we're gonna show you
how to get the most out of Xcode Cloud
by reviewing an existing workflow
and highlighting the brand-new
Xcode Cloud Usage dashboard.
Then, we'll take a look at how we can use
what we've learned
from viewing our existing projects usage,
to optimize it further,
and begin developing
a new Watch OS App version of our project
Before we get to that,
let's do a quick overview of Xcode Cloud.
At WWDC 2021,
we announced Xcode Cloud,
a continuous integration
and delivery service built into Xcode
and designed expressly
for Apple developers.
Xcode Cloud lets you adopt
continuous integration and delivery,
a standard software development practice
that helps you develop
and maintain your code,
and deliver apps to testers and users.
Xcode Cloud accelerates the development
and delivery of high-quality apps
by bringing together cloud-based tools
that help you build apps,
run automated tests in parallel,
deliver apps to testers, and view.
and manage user feedback,
all while protecting user privacy.
If you'd like to learn more about
setting up Xcode Cloud for the first time,
check out "Meet Xcode Cloud"
from WWDC 2021,
where Holly and Geoff go into more detail
in setting up your first workflow.
Now, let's take a look
at an existing workflow and build
for our Food Truck app in Xcode Cloud.
This is the Xcode Cloud dashboard
in App Store Connect,
it gives us an overview of a recent build
of our Food Truck project.
We recently made the decision
to add a companion watchOS app,
so a food truck operator can accept
incoming orders from their watch quickly,
without having to reach for their phone
every time a new order comes in.
Before we get started building
the new watchOS app in Xcode Cloud,
we'd like to make sure our current
workflows and project are fully optimized,
getting us the build and test results
we want, as quickly as possible.
We think there may be some ways
in which we can save some time
and resources here.
To better understand
where we might be able to start
making some of these optimizations,
let's take a closer look
at the build details overview.
First, we notice that we started the build
at 9:15 a.m.
and that it took 14 minutes to complete
and present us with results.
We also see there is a time
associated with usage,
which in this case is 32 minutes.
This is the total time it took
for all the actions
in our 14 minute build to complete.
Next to the usage,
you'll see an option
to view the distribution of actions
for this build.
Each action is broken out,
along with its respective usage,
with the 32-minute total
indicated at the bottom.
This Usage distribution gives us an idea
of some places
we could possibly make some
optimizations.
But before we get to that,
let's take a moment to look more closely
at how Xcode Cloud performs these actions,
and the difference between
a build duration and usage.
Each build is broken out into
a series of actions
depending on the setup of your workflow.
You'll see how Xcode Cloud breaks each
action out into multiple parallel actions
like Analyze, Archive, Build, and Test.
Because these actions are performed
in parallel,
the duration of the build
is equal to the longest running action;
in this case, the tests
we've configured in our workflow
that took 14 minutes to complete.
Now, when calculating usage,
each one of these actions,
when observed in sequence,
give us the total compute usage
of the build–in this case, 32 minutes.
And that's how Xcode Cloud calculates
the build duration,
and usage for a given build.
Now, let's take a look
at the Xcode Cloud Usage dashboard
in App Store Connect!
At the top is the usage overview,
since the beginning of our monthly cycle
for the Truck to Table Team,
including a total percentage used.
Additionally, we see
total usage expressed in minutes,
along with the remaining compute
available on our team's current cycle.
Beneath this, we see an area
dedicated to usage trends for our team,
broken out by builds
created and overall usage,
along with percentage increases
or decreases during the last 30 days.
If we'd like to see the usage
over a different time period,
we can do so by changing the time period
in the top, right-hand corner
of the trends section.
A little further down the page,
we see the total usage of each one
of our products currently
using Xcode Cloud,
again, during the time period
that we selected above.
All right, let's select Food Truck
so we can see its total usage breakdown.
Here we start by seeing the same trends
from our team view,
but now specific
to our Food Truck project.
A little further down the page,
we see the usage stats
for each one of our workflows.
At a quick glance, I can see
from the Release workflow
this is going to be an excellent place to
start making a couple of optimizations.
Now, I'm gonna hand it over to Sasan
who, after observing some of the build
details and compute usage,
is gonna show us a couple of ways
we can optimize our project.
Show them how it's done, Sasan.
Sasan: Thanks, Adam.
Let's use the Food Truck project
to cover some of the best practices
when using Xcode Cloud.
This should allow us to start iterating
quickly on our new watchOS app.
Workflows define when to start a build
through the use of Start Conditions.
It is important to configure
your Start Conditions
so that builds only start for changes
that are intended for the Workflow.
Let's see how we can apply
this practice to the Release workflow
of the Food Truck project.
But first, I recommend checking out
"Explore Xcode Cloud Workflows"
for more detailed information.
I have the same build
that Adam showed us earlier open in Xcode.
To start, let me open the Release workflow
in the editor window.
I right-click on the Workflow
in the Navigation Panel
and select Edit Workflow.
In the editor window,
I can see all of the configurable sections
that make up a Workflow,
including a section for Start Conditions.
We've discovered
that sometimes the scheduled build
doesn't contain any new changes.
To address that,
let's add a new start condition
for branch changes to replace
the existing scheduled start condition.
This will ensure that we don't
build duplicate commits.
I on the Plus button
and select Branch Changes.
Now to delete
the scheduled start condition,
I will select it
and click on the trash icon.
The Branch Changes Start Condition
will run
whenever a new commit
is pushed to a remote branch.
By default, the Source Branch
is configured to be Any Branch.
This means that any change
made to any branch of your repo
will cause this workflow
to start a build.
Since our release workflow
is configured to be thorough,
I want to restrict this to ensure we only
start builds for our release branches.
I click on Custom Branches,
and I can immediately see
that I need to specify the custom branch.
I click on the Plus button
and enter the branch name.
The editor will allow me to choose from
either the exact branch name or a prefix.
In this case,
we know we have multiple release branches
so I'll select
branches beginning with "release".
Next, I want to specify which files
and folders from the release branch
can start a build.
My goal is to not start builds
when the docs folder is modified.
This folder contains only our development
documentation so it's safe to skip.
For the Files and Folders option,
I select Custom Conditions.
I select the Start a Build dropdown
and select Don't start a build.
I click on the Plus button
to add a new condition.
I will specify which folder to exclude
by selecting Any Folder
and selecting Choose.
Finally, this will open a file picker.
Now I can select the docs folder
and click Open.
To finish up,
I'll click Save to persist my changes.
I have now configured
the Start Condition to be more selective
when starting
by restricting to only branches
with the release prefix
and to ignore changes to the docs folder.
Workflows also define
how to run your builds
through the use of pre-defined Actions.
Actions allow you to analyze,
archive, build, and test your changes.
One important component of the test action
is the selection of test destinations.
To make sure
that results are delivered fast,
each destination will run in parallel
once the test products are built.
I want to make sure that I'm selecting
a concise set of simulator destinations
for my tests.
In addition to speeding up my builds,
this also helps reduce noise
from the tests
that might fail on similar devices.
Xcode Cloud provides an alias
for recommended destinations.
These are curated lists of simulators
that represent a cross section
of screen sizes.
Let's visit the Release workflow again
to see how we can select a reasonable set
of simulator destinations
for the iOS test action.
After selecting the Test iOS action,
we can see there are a wide range
of selected test destinations.
To remove test destinations,
I'll select each one
and click the Minus button.
Then I'll click on the dropdown menu
of the last item
and select Recommended iPhones.
Again, I'll click Save to persist
my changes.
I now have a set of test destinations
that will help provide a clear signal
if we introduce a regression.
As we discussed earlier,
Xcode Cloud will run your workflow
when you push new changes
to your repository.
Sometimes, you may want to skip
building in CI
depending on the type of change
being committed.
We've added in
the ability to do just that.
Let's take a look in Xcode.
To skip your commit in Xcode Cloud,
simply append "ci skip"
to the end of the commit message.
Now, when you push to remote, Xcode Cloud
will know to ignore this event.
Make sure you're using the exact format
of the ci skip tag shown here.
For each action, custom scripts
are executed at multiple points.
Tidying up unused dependencies
and resiliently retrying API requests
that are known to be unreliable
will ensure builds complete fast
and consistently.
For more information on custom scripts
and other advanced customizations,
check out "Customize your advanced
Xcode Cloud workflows".
For testing, you should ensure
that flakey and unreliable tests
are corrected quickly.
When a flakey test fails, the instinct
is to immediately retry the build.
Depending on the reliability
of your test suite,
this can result in many retried builds.
Make sure to spend more time
writing reliable tests.
For more information on
how to do that effectively,
check out our other session "Author fast
and reliable tests for Xcode Cloud".
So far we've discussed some best practices
and applied them
to the Food Truck project.
Let's see what sort of impact
those changes had
by comparing the build from earlier
with one from our updated workflow.
This is a build that was started
after applying the best practices.
Compared to the previous build
that Adam showed us,
the duration decreased by a minute
but the usage reduced by four minutes.
It looks like we've made
some good improvements overall.
Let's return to the usage dashboard
to better understand the impact.
Since it might be difficult to see
the impact from a single build right away,
we've applied the best practices
to another one of our workflows,
the Integration Workflow.
We've been running builds for a while
with best practices applied.
We can tell that our changes
were effective
because usage is trending downward.
This means we're now capable of adding
more workflows
and starting more builds to start
development of the watchOS app.
Using the usage dashboard,
you can continue to apply
the same best practices
to your existing projects and workflows
to get the most out of Xcode Cloud.
For more information on how to manage
Xcode Cloud for large teams,
check out Deep Dive
into Xcode Cloud for teams.
We hope you enjoyed our session.
Adam: Thank you for watching.
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪