♪ ♪
August Joki: Hello, I'm August Joki,
a software engineer on watchOS,
and I'm here to show you how to go further
with WidgetKit complications.
I hope you've seen the wonderful
Complications and Widgets: Reloaded talk
first, covering the basics
of complications in WidgetKit.
This talk expands
on the concepts covered there
as they relate to complications
on the watch faces.
And my WWDC 2020 talk:
Build complications in SwiftUI
covers more specifics about tinting
and SwiftUI drawing in complications.
In this talk,
I'll be discussing the WidgetKit features
unique to watchOS,
as well as how to migrate your,
and your users',
existing ClockKit complications
to WidgetKit.
I've taken inspiration from
the Coffee Tracker sample app
to use as an example
throughout this talk.
The app records the number of coffees,
teas, and sodas
you drink throughout the day
and tracks the amount of caffeine
in your body over time.
Let's start with what's unique to watchOS.
In iOS 16
we brought complication style widgets
to the phone's lock screen
and in watchOS 9 we brought WidgetKit
to the watch's complications.
On the watch faces we have
a unique complication presentation
for the corners of the watch screen.
And it requires a unique WidgetKit family
called accessoryCorner, to describe it.
Part of that unique presentation
is auxiliary content
specified by your SwiftUI view,
but not rendered as part of your content.
Instead, it is rendered by the watch face.
The circular part of the corner
is standard SwiftUI rendering
and the auxiliary content
is the curved part in the corners.
Or in the dial on the Infograph face.
The accessoryInline family
has a unique behavior on watch faces.
It has multiple ways of being rendered
depending on the face.
Sometimes flat,
sometimes curved to match the dial.
Let's talk about how to support
these unique features
by looking at how the coffee tracker app
might be updated to use WidgetKit.
In addition to the three new
complication-styled widget families
on iOS 16:
AccessoryRectangular,
accessoryCircular,
and accessoryInline,
we have a fourth family on watchOS 9
called accessoryCorner.
accessoryCorner can either be shown
as a large circular content,
like the maps and heart rate
complications shown in the lower corners,
or as smaller circular content
with a curved label or gauge
like the coffee tracker and moonphase
complications shown in the upper corners.
To control whether
the inner auxiliary content is shown,
watchOS 9 has added a new view modifier
you can use, which I'll show you now.
Let's look at building a corner
complication for my coffee tracker app.
Starting with the larger
circular content style,
I have a ZStack
with an SF Symbol and a background.
The SwiftUI content is
automatically clipped to a circle
to keep in line with the design
of the other corner complications.
To add the inner curved content,
we use the new to watchOS 9
widgetLabel view modifier.
The watch face extracts the contents
of the modifier to draw the control
appropriate for the family
and the style of the watch face.
And the circular content
automatically scales down to make room.
For accessoryCorner
you can specify a SwiftUI text, gauge,
or progressView in your widget's label.
AccessoryCorner isn't the only family
that supports widgetLabel.
Let's look at how it is used
on the accessoryCircular family.
On the Infograph watch face,
in addition to the corner complications,
there are four circular complications
inside the dial.
My coffee tracker circular complication,
in the middle top,
looks very similar to the corner
complication we just saw,
but with text in the dial.
I'll show you how to add that text now.
For my circular complication design,
I thought it more appropriate
to move the gauge
that was in the widgetLabel
in my corner complication,
to be front and center.
To take advantage of the top
middle position on Infograph,
I add a widgetLabel to the gauge
in order to display additional text
in the longer bezel area that wouldn't
otherwise fit in the circular content.
But now I have redundant information
between the main view
and the text above it.
I can clean that up
by switching the circular content
to that good looking coffee cup SF Symbol
from my corner complication
But when I switch to a face
showing my circular complication
that does not have the bezel,
then I've lost all of my caffeine info.
Luckily, there's a piece of API I can add
to make my complication work
in both cases.
I update my complication
to add the Environment property
called showsWidgetLabel to my view.
This will be true whenever
the complication is in a position
on the watch face that shows
the content in the widget's label.
And then I can change the content
to depend on the value of showsWidgetLabel
so I am able to have the appropriate level
of information in each complication spot.
I just demonstrated two different ways
that the accessoryCircular family
can show up on watch faces,
and there is one more way
you need to be aware of.
The Extra Large watch face has long been
a great way for people to see the time
in an extra large format.
And it supports a single,
large circular complication.
The Extra Large face uses
the accessoryCircular family
and automatically scales up the content
to match the style of the face.
Please note:
as this face is designed
to have a single, large complication,
do not use the increased canvas size
as an opportunity
to densely pack your complication.
The content should be identical to
the normal circular family, only larger.
As I mentioned earlier,
there are two more widget families used
on watch faces:
accessoryRectangular and accessoryInline.
There are no faces with rectangular
complications that show the widgetLabel.
And the accessoryInline family acts,
already, as a widgetLabel.
The watch face extracts Images
and Texts from your inline content
and renders them itself
to match the look of the face.
Next up is Migration.
There are two parts to migration:
rewriting your existing ClockKit
complication code in WidgetKit;
and providing a mapping
to let the system know how to upgrade
your complications people have set
on their watch faces.
When you adopt WidgetKit the system
will stop asking your ClockKit data source
for new content and show only your new
complications in the face editing picker.
As well as bringing
WidgetKit to the watch,
watchOS 9 has updated every face
to support rich complications,
which allowed us to dramatically reduce
the number of complication families
from 12 to only 4.
Rectangular and Corner
map directly across
to accessoryRectangular
and accessoryCorner.
All three graphic Circular
styled ClockKit families
are now a single
accessoryCircular WidgetKit family.
And the accessoryInline family
is used where the old utilitarianSmallFlat
or utilitarianLarge used to be.
And many places that used to be
utilitarianSmall
have been updated
to use the accessoryCorner family.
With WidgetKit, SwiftUI views
and their state driven layout
have replaced ClockKit's templates.
WidgetKit still has
familiar timelines and entries.
In fact, they were originally inspired
by ClockKit itself,
which means that your complication
data source will nicely migrate
to one of either a static or intent based
WidgetKit configuration.
Please see the original WidgetKit talk
for more details
about the types of configurations
WidgetKit supports
as well as general family support.
We've added one last API to ClockKit
to allow a person's complications
to be migrated by
the system automatically.
This allows for your existing
complications that are already
on watch faces to automatically be
upgraded to your new WidgetKit based
complications
without any user interaction.
When your app gets updated on a watch,
the Watch Faces will check
for the presence of widgets
in your app's bundle.
If it finds any, it will then launch
your ClockKit complication data source
to generate the migrations
for the existing complications.
From this point forward,
your CLKComplicationDataSource
will only be run to ask for migrations
when a person receives a shared face
with your ClockKit complications on it.
The system will ask for your migrations
every time a new face is shared,
so for a consistent experience you should
keep your migrations consistent.
Once you've finished creating
your beautiful WidgetKit complications,
you can add the new property,
widgetMigrator,
to provide the object that conforms
to the new Migrator protocol.
Be that your complication data source
itself or some other type you provide.
The CLKComplication WidgetMigrator
protocol has a single function
to provide to the watch faces
widget migration configurations
from existing CLKComplicationDescriptors.
The most straightforward way
to adopt the new API
is to have your data source conform
to the new Migrator protocol.
If your WidgetKit complication
uses the static configuration,
you provide a static migration
configuration.
And there's an equivalent
migration configuration
if you use intents
in your widget complication.
Note that if you provide intent based
migration configurations,
you will need to also include your intent
definitions in your watch app
as well as your widget extensions,
so you can create your intent objects
in both places.
WidgetKit enables new and creative ways
to make complications for the watch,
while dramatically simplifying
the experience.
Thanks for watching.