♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, folks.
My name is Michael Gorbach
from Shortcuts Engineering.
Thanks for tuning in for this
deep dive into App Intents,
our new framework
for exposing your app's
functionality to the system.
Here's the plan for our dive.
After a quick introduction,
I'll talk about intents
and their parameters,
and how to define entities.
I'll go over some powerful
finding and filtering features
you can build,
and how your intents
can interact with the user.
Lastly, I'll cover App Intents
architecture and lifecycle.
Let's start at the beginning.
In iOS 10, we introduced
the SiriKit Intents framework,
which lets you hook up
your app's functionality
to Siri domains like messaging,
workouts, and payments.
Now we're introducing
a new framework
called App Intents.
It has three key components.
Intents are actions
built into your app
that can be used
throughout the system.
Intents use entities to
represent your app's concepts.
App Shortcuts wrap your intents
to make them automatic
and discoverable.
Let's talk about
a couple of the ways
that App Intents can make your
app's functionality available
in more places,
and benefit your customers.
With App Shortcuts,
everyone can use
your app's features
with their voice through Siri,
without needing
to set anything up first.
The same adoption also makes
your intents appear in Spotlight
when people search for your app
and when your app's suggested.
This will put your work
front and center.
Using App Intents, you can also
build Focus Filters,
letting customers customize
your app for a specific Focus.
For example, they might
set up their Calendar app
to only show their work calendar
while they're actually at work.
Check out this session
to learn more about
how to adopt Focus Filters.
With App Shortcuts,
your intents show up in the
Shortcuts app automatically,
without needing
to be added manually.
Integrating your actions
into Shortcuts
is incredibly valuable
for customers
because they can run shortcuts,
and take advantage
of your app's features,
from so many places
throughout the system.
They can run shortcuts with
a single tap on the Home Screen,
from the menu bar on macOS,
and in many other ways.
They can even set shortcuts up
to run automatically
with automations.
Supporting shortcuts
multiplies the power
and capability of your app
by connecting it
to the entire
Shortcuts ecosystem,
harnessing the power
of an array of apps from Apple
and other developers.
That's because a shortcut
can combine actions
from multiple apps,
letting users invent entirely
new features and capabilities
without you needing
to do any work.
If you want to learn
how to make your actions
work well with others and fit
seamlessly into this ecosystem,
check out our design talk.
Our goal in building App Intents
was to make it a joy
to develop for.
App Intents is concise.
Writing a simple intent can take
only a few lines of code,
but the API also scales
to deeper and more
customizable actions.
App Intents is modern.
We've gone all in on Swift,
leveraging result builders,
property wrappers,
protocol-oriented programming,
and generics.
These APIs just couldn't exist
without cutting-edge
language features.
Adopting App Intents
is also easy,
because it doesn't require
re-architecting
your products and targets
or creating a framework.
It doesn't require an extension
and can be adopted
right in your app.
And App Intents code
is maintainable.
Like SwiftUI,
App Intents uses your code
as the fundamental
source of truth,
avoiding the need for separate
editors or definition files.
This lets you rapidly build
and iterate on your adoption,
and simplifies maintenance
because everything
lives in one place.
With that said,
let's explore these new APIs,
starting with the intent,
the central building block
of our new framework.
An app intent --
or "intent" for short --
is a single, isolated unit
of functionality
that your app
exposes to the system.
For example, an intent
could make a new calendar event,
open a particular screen,
or place an order.
An intent can be run
by the user on request --
like by running a shortcut
or asking Siri --
or automatically --
like using Focus filters
or a Shortcuts automation.
When an intent is run,
it will either return a result
or throw an error.
An intent includes
three key pieces:
metadata,
or information about the intent,
including a localized title;
parameters, which are inputs
that the intent can use
when it's run;
and a perform method,
which does the actual work
when the intent is executed.
Our starting point today
is this Library app.
Since I'm a huge bookworm,
it's all about tracking
books I've read,
want to read,
or am currently reading.
Each category is shown
in separate tab of the app
that I call a Shelf.
My users visit
the Currently Reading shelf
all the time,
so I'm going expose
an app intent
to make opening it quicker
and more convenient.
I'll create an
OpenCurrentlyReading intent here
by defining a Swift struct
that conforms to
the AppIntent protocol.
I need to implement
only one method, called perform.
In my app, I've already got
a navigator that can open tabs,
so implementing
the intent for me
is only a few lines of code.
I'll annotate the perform method
with @MainActor,
since my Navigator
expects the main thread.
My intent also needs a title.
Like all the other strings
I'll be showing you today,
this will get localized
automatically
if I add the key
to my strings files.
This is all I need to do to get
a basic app intent working.
Now that it's defined
in my code,
it will automatically appear
in the Shortcuts editor,
where my user
can add it to a shortcut.
Just exposing this intent
provides huge leverage,
because once customers turn
this intent into a shortcut,
it can be used from
a ton of places in the system,
including all of these.
To make my new intent
easy to use and discover,
I'll also add support
for App Shortcuts.
With a little bit of code,
I can make my intent show up
automatically in Spotlight
and the Shortcuts app,
and I can define a phrase
that people can say to Siri
to use this intent
with their voice.
Check out the "Implement App
Shortcuts with App Intents"
session to get all the details.
So far, I've exposed an intent
to open the Currently Reading
shelf.
Next, let's generalize it,
adding a parameter so it can
open any of the shelves.
I have an enum
that represents shelves.
In order for it to be used
as an intent parameter,
I need to conform it
to the AppEnum protocol.
AppEnum requires
a String raw value,
so I'll add that first.
It also requires
that I provide localizable,
human-readable titles
for each of my enum cases.
These must be provided
as a dictionary literal,
since the compiler will
read this code at build time.
Finally, I'll add
a typeDisplayName:
a user-visible, localizable name
for this enum type
as a whole.
I'll use "Shelf."
In an intent,
each parameter is declared
using an @Parameter
property wrapper,
which is initialized with
information about the parameter,
like the title.
Here, I define
a new shelf parameter,
which I read
in my perform method.
Parameters support
all of these types,
including numbers, strings,
files, and more,
as well as entities and enums
from your app.
Here's how this intent looks
in the Shortcuts editor.
Note that the shelf parameter
appears in a table row.
I can make the UI
more streamlined,
and make it fit better
into Shortcuts,
by using the
ParameterSummary API.
The Parameter Summary
is a sentence
that represents your intent
and its parameters
in the editor,
like "Open [Shelf]."
For best results in Shortcuts,
you should always provide
a Parameter Summary
for every intent you create.
You can also define
which parameters
show up below the fold
and which are hidden.
These APIs can
do some pretty cool stuff,
like varying the summary
based on the actual values
of any parameter of your intent,
using the When
and Otherwise APIs,
or the Switch, Case,
and Default APIs.
To add a parameter summary,
I implement
this static property.
Here I'll return the string
"Open",
and interpolate
the shelf parameter.
The last thing I need to do
to get Open Shelf working
is make sure that the intent
opens the Library app
when it's run,
like this.
Opening the app by is controlled
by the static property,
openAppWhenRun.
It defaults to false,
which is great for most intents.
But for intents that open
something in the UI
like this one,
I'll need to set it to true.
I just created an intent
to open shelves.
This is super simple because
the set of shelves is fixed.
But what if I wanted to build
an intent that opens Books,
the set of which is dynamic,
not fixed?
For that, I'll need entities.
An entity is a concept that
your app exposes to App Intents.
You should use an entity
instead of an enum
when the values are dynamic,
or user-defined,
like a note in Notes
or a photo or album in Photos.
To provide instances
of entities,
your app can implement queries,
and return entities
as results from intents.
I'll start by making an intent
to open a book in the app.
In the Shortcuts editor,
it should look like this.
When people tap
on the Book parameter,
they'll get a picker
to choose a book,
including a set
of suggested entities
that my app has provided.
They can also find
any book in their library
with this search field
at the top of the picker.
Before I build
the intent itself,
I'll need to create
a book entity
and the corresponding query.
An entity contains
at least three things:
an identifier,
a display representation,
and an entity type name.
To add an entity,
start by conforming a struct
to the AppEntity protocol.
Here, I'll define a new struct
for the BookEntity,
but I could also conform
an existing type from my model.
You provide an identifier
by conforming your entity
to the Identifiable protocol.
App Intents uses this identifier
to refer to your entity
as it's passed between your app
and other parts of the system.
The identifier should be
stable and persistent,
since it might be saved
in a shortcut
created by your customers.
The display representation
is used
to show this entity to the user.
This can be as simple
as a string of text,
like a book title.
You could also provide
a subtitle and an image.
The typeDisplayName
is a human-readable string
representing
the type of an entity.
In this example,
it's "Book."
Now, to round out
the book entity,
I need to add a query.
A query gives the system
an interface
for retrieving entities
from your app.
Queries can look up entities
in a few ways.
All queries need to be able
to look up entities
based on an identifier.
String queries support search.
And later, you'll run into
property queries,
which are more flexible.
All queries can also provide
suggested entities,
which allow the users
to pick from a list.
Every entity should be
associated with a query
so the system can look up
instances of that entity.
You provide a query
by making a Swift struct
that conforms to
the EntityQuery protocol.
The basic query has only
one required method,
which you implement
to resolve entities
given an array of identifiers.
I've implemented this
by going to my model database
and finding any books
matching those identifiers.
Now, I need to hook up
the query to the entity.
I do this by implementing
the defaultQuery static property
on the BookEntity type
and returning an instance
of my BookQuery.
When the user picks a book,
its identifier will be saved
into the shortcut.
When the shortcut is run,
App Intents will pass
the identifier to my query
to retrieve
the BookEntity instance.
Now that the BookEntity type
conforms to
the AppEntity protocol,
I can use it as a parameter
in my OpenBook intent.
The perform method
uses my Navigator
to navigate to the book.
In order to support
the book picker,
my query also needs
to provide suggested results.
To do that, I need to implement
one more method on query,
returning all the books
added to my Library app.
Shortcuts will fill the picker
with these results.
Notice that the Shortcuts UI
has a search field on top.
My app could have
a lot of book entities,
so I should really run
the search in my app process,
against my database directly.
The StringQuery API
lets me do that.
Adopting the StringQuery
subprotocol gives me
one more method to implement,
called
entities (matching string:),
to return results
given a string.
Here, I've implemented it as
a simple case-insensitive match
against the title of the book,
but I could have done
fancier stuff
like searching through
the author or series name,
for example.
If I have a huge list of books,
and a smaller list of favorites,
I could return just the
favorites in suggestedEntities,
and rely on
entities (matching string:)
to allow my users to search
across the longer list.
Now I've exposed a way
to open books in my app,
and built a book entity
and book query in the process.
I can use the same entity and
query to create more intents.
My next task
is to build an intent
to add books to the library.
Customers can quickly add books
while browsing online
using a share sheet shortcut,
or they can tell Siri on HomePod
to add a book
without even looking
at a screen.
Building intents like this that
manipulate your model directly
without showing your UI
can really empower your users.
Here's the implementation
of my AddBook intent,
taking as parameters
the title of the book
and an optional
name of the author.
It also includes
an optional note
to record which friend
recommended the book.
The perform method
will add the book to the library
by looking it up with
an API call using async/await.
It will throw an error
if it can't find a match.
To localize this error,
I conform my error type to
the CustomLocalizedString
ResourceConvertible protocol.
I'll return a localized
string key from this property,
and add the key
to my strings files.
This Add Book intent
is incredibly useful as is,
with Siri, widgets,
and more.
But it gets even more flexible
if it can be combined
with other intents.
With a little bit of work,
I can allow combining
my Add Book intent
with the Open Book intent
I built earlier,
passing the result
from one to the other.
To do so, I'll have
the Add Book intent
return a value
as part of its result.
Notice that my perform method's
return type
has picked up a new protocol
to represent the value
I'm returning.
Now, users can connect
the result value of this intent
to other intents that take
a book entity as a parameter.
The Add Book intent
and the Open Book intent
pair quite naturally together,
so you can make a shortcut
that adds a book
and then immediately
opens it in the library.
It's a common pattern to return
a result from an intent
and open it in the app.
App intents have a built-in way
to express this
called the openIntent.
If I add an openIntent,
customers will get
a new switch in Shortcuts
called "Open When Run."
If they turn the switch off,
they'll be able
to use this intent
as part of a shortcut in the
background without interruption.
If they leave the switch on,
the newly added book
will be immediately opened
in my Library app.
Adopting openIntent
is as easy
as creating an instance
of the Open Book intent
and returning it
as part of the result.
When this intent is run,
if the Open When Run switch
is on,
the Open Book intent
will automatically be performed
after the Add Book intent
finishes.
There's a lot more you can do
with entities and queries.
With the next set of APIs,
AppIntents opens up
some powerful abilities
you never had before with
the SiriKit Intents framework.
Let's take a look at how
you can expose more information
from your entities,
and allow customers to find
and filter based on that.
So far, I've added
all the basic requirements
to my book entity.
But to let people
integrate books
more deeply
into their shortcuts,
I'm going to need to expose
a bit more about my books.
Entities support properties,
which hold additional
information on the entity
that you want to expose
to users.
In this case,
I'll add the book's author,
publishing date, read date,
and who recommended it,
so that people can use those
properties in their shortcuts.
I add properties
to my BookEntity
using a property wrapper
called @Property.
Properties support all the same
types that parameters do,
and each one
takes a localized title.
With these new properties,
my customers can now use
magic variables in Shortcuts
to pull out each new
piece of information
when working with
a book entity
When using
the earlier Add Book intent,
they can use the author
or publishing date
of a newly added book
in their shortcuts.
When you combine properties
with queries,
your app automatically
gets these incredibly powerful
Find and Filter actions
in Shortcuts,
with this flexible
predicate editor UI.
Now, my customers will be
able to find and filter books
based on date read, title,
author, and more.
It's a piece of cake to find
all the books by Delia Owens,
for example.
Using the Sort by
and Limit options,
you can support even more
advanced queries,
like find the three
most recently published books
by Delia Owens.
A customer can use
these building blocks
to do some pretty cool stuff,
like finding
the three most common authors
in their collection.
To enable all this,
I'll need to adopt
another kind of query
called a property query.
Property queries find entities
not based on a string,
or an identifier, but on the
properties within the entity.
There are three steps to
implementing property queries.
First, you declare
query properties,
which specify how your entity
can be searched
using its properties.
Then, you add sorting options,
which define how query results
can be sorted.
And finally, you implement
entities(matching:)
to run the search.
The query properties
declare every way
AppIntents can search
on the entity associated
with this query.
Each one lists
a property of my entity,
and the comparison operators --
like contains, equal to,
or less than --
that are available for it.
Here, I list "less than"
and "greater than" comparators
for my date properties,
and "contains" and "equal to"
for my title property.
Query properties
map each combination
of property and comparator
into a type of your choice,
called
the comparator mapping type.
Here, I am using CoreData,
so I'll use an NSPredicate.
If I was using a custom database
or a REST API,
I could design
my own comparator type
and use that instead.
Here's the code to set up the
query properties for my books.
I conform BooksQuery to the
EntityPropertyQuery protocol.
Then I implement
static var properties
using the QueryProperties
result builder.
Each entry specifies
a keyPath of a Property
that can be queried,
and within it,
each comparator that is
applicable to that property.
For each comparator,
I provide an NSPredicate,
because I've chosen NSPredicate
as my comparator mapping type.
When the system asks my app
to return results for the query,
it will provide back
the NSPredicates
that I'm constructing here.
There's a similar definition
for sorting.
This is a list
of all the properties
my model can sort books by.
In this case,
I allow sorting by title,
date read,
and date published.
Finally, I implement
entities(matching:),
which queries my database
and returns matching entities.
This method takes an array
of the comparator mapping type
I used in the previously defined
query parameters --
in this case,
NSPredicate.
These predicates
are describing what criteria
on the properties of my entity
I want to query by.
It also takes a mode,
indicating whether
to combine the predicates
with "and" or with "or,"
key paths to sort by,
and an optional limit
for the number of results.
My implementation
uses these parameters
to perform a query against
my CoreData database.
What can customers do
with this property query?
They can pick a random book
from their library to read.
They can find all their books
published in the early part
of the twentieth century.
They can leverage
the Shortcuts ecosystem
and make my app more useful
by connecting it to others.
For example, they can use
a spreadsheet app
to export all the books they
read this year to a CSV file.
Or, they can use a graphing app
to make a chart
of how many books they've read
every year over the last 10.
And that's just the beginning.
This kind of deep
App Intents adoption
really lets customers
use your app
to do what they need it to do,
making it a critical part
of their workflow.
Each of these integrations --
like making graphs,
for example --
is a feature
you don't have to build.
When your intents
are performed,
your app may need
to interact with the user
to show or speak a result,
or to resolve ambiguity,
whether it's a Siri request
or a shortcut.
App Intents supports
a number of these interactions:
dialog for giving text
and voice feedback
to your users
when an intent has completed,
and snippets
for giving visual feedback.
Request value and disambiguation
for asking the user to clarify
values for intent parameters,
and confirmation for verifying
parameter values
or checking with the user
on intents that are
transactional or destructive.
Dialog provides
a spoken or textual response
to the person
running an intent.
It's really important
to provide dialog
for intents to work well
in a voice experience.
In my Add Book intent
from earlier,
I'll add a needsValueDialog
that's spoken
when asking for a book title
and a result dialog returned
from my perform method.
These will be read or shown
by Shortcuts or Siri
across our many platforms.
You can think of snippets as
the visual equivalent of dialog,
letting you add
a visual representation
to the result of your intent.
To use a snippet, just add
the SwiftUI view of your choice
as a trailing closure
to your intent result.
Like with a widget, your SwiftUI
view will be archived
and sent over
to Shortcuts or Siri.
App Intents also supports
asking the user for a value
by throwing requestValue.
For example, this comes in handy
when you need a value
for a parameter
that is sometimes optional.
Here, requestValue helps me
when my string search
returns more than one book.
In this case,
I prompt and ask for an author
to narrow the book search down.
requestValue gives me
an error I can throw,
which will prompt the user,
and rerun the action
with the updated author name.
Disambiguation,
meanwhile,
is great when you need
the user to choose
between a set of values
for a parameter.
This gives me an even better
way to handle
multiple possible results
in my Add Book action.
Here, I get a list of author
names from the generated books,
and request disambiguation
with those possible values.
The user will be asked
to pick between them,
and I'll get the result back.
Lastly, App Intents supports two
different kinds of confirmation.
The first kind is confirmation
of a parameter value.
You might use this
when you have a guess
at what that value should be
but you want to confirm,
just to make sure.
When adding a book,
sometimes the web service I call
to look up books by title
returns a couple matches,
but one of them is by far
the more popular.
In these cases,
I'm going to assume
that the user meant
to add that popular book,
but I'll add confirmation
to make sure I got it right.
To do that,
I'll call requestConfirmation
on the title parameter.
The second kind
is a confirmation
of the result of an intent.
This is great for placing
orders, for example.
If I wanted to monetize
my Library app
and add ordering
through a bookstore,
I'd want to make sure
that I have the order right.
To do this, I could call
requestConfirmation
on my intent, passing in
the order to be placed.
I'll specify a snippet here too,
showing a preview of the order.
I prefix the call with "try"
because requestConfirmation
will throw an error
if the user cancels
instead of confirming.
Before I leave you,
there are a couple aspects
of the App Intents
architecture I want to cover,
which you should know
as you adopt the framework.
There are actually two ways
to build your App Intents:
within your app
or in a separate extension.
Of these, implementing intents
directly in your app
is the simplest.
This is great because
you don't need a framework
or to duplicate your code,
and you don't need to coordinate
across processes.
Using your app also gives
some higher memory limits,
and it gives you the ability
to do some kinds of work
that are harder
from an extension,
like playing audio.
Your app can be run
in the foreground
if you implement openAppWhenRun
on your intent to return true.
Otherwise, it will be run
in the background.
When running in the background,
your app will launch
in a special mode
without scenes being brought up
to maximize performance.
In fact, if you implement
background app intents
in your app,
we strongly encourage you
to also implement scene support.
Or, you can build your
app intents in an extension.
This has a couple advantages.
It's lighter weight,
because the extension process
only handles app intents
and doesn't require
spinning up your app.
If you are handling
Focus intents,
using an extension also means
that you'll immediately
get intents performed
on your extension
when Focus changes,
without the requirement
that your app is running
in the foreground first.
An extension is a bit more work,
since you'll need
to add a new target,
move some code
into a framework,
and handle coordination
between your app
and the extension.
To create an App Intents
extension,
go to File > New Target
in Xcode
and choose
App Intents Extension.
With App Intents, your code
is the only source of truth.
App Intents achieves this
elegant developer experience
by statically extracting
information about your intents,
entities, queries,
and parameters at build time.
Xcode will generate
a metadata file inside your app
or extension bundle
during your build process,
containing information received
from the Swift compiler
as it runs on your code.
To make sure all of this works,
keep your App Intents types
directly in the target or
extension, not in a framework.
Similarly,
your localized strings
should be found
in a strings file
within the same bundle where
your App Intents types live.
For those of you
who have existing apps
with SiriKit Intents
that you want to upgrade,
if you adopt intents
to integrate with widgets,
or domains like messaging
or media,
you should keep using
the SiriKit Intents framework.
But if you add custom intents
for Siri and Shortcuts,
you should go ahead and upgrade
to App Intents.
You can start
the upgrade process by clicking
the Convert to App Intent
button
in your SiriKit Intents
definition file.
Integrating your app into
Shortcuts with App Intents
is a great way to maximize
your leverage as a developer,
because by doing a small amount
of work to adopt App Intents,
you create a large amount
of value for customers.
Thank you for joining!
I really hope that you'll
try out App Intents today
and give us your feedback.
I'm excited about
how this new framework
can help you surprise,
delight, and empower folks
using your apps!
Happy reading and
hope your WWDC is epic!
♪