♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi everyone,
my name is John Crowson,
and I'm a software engineer
on the Performance Tools team
here at Apple.
In this talk,
I'm excited to introduce you
to several new tools
to track down hangs in your app
with Xcode
and on-device hang detection.
I'll be your guide
as we visit different phases
of your app development process,
and consider which tools
are best suited
to help during each phase.
This talk is broken
into four sections:
First, I will cover,
What are hangs?
Then, I will present tooling
to help you discover
and diagnose hangs
while developing your app,
while beta testing your app,
and after releasing your app.
Let's get started!
I want to tell you about
a new app my team is developing:
Food Truck, which will help
manage food trucks
that specifically sell donuts.
Let me introduce you to some of
the donut types I've created.
Huh, that took
a really long time
to scroll through
my list of donuts.
The app was laggy and would not
respond to any of my touches.
At Apple, we call this period
of unresponsiveness a "hang."
An app's main thread is
responsible for processing
user interactions
and updating the view content.
A hang is reported when the main
thread is busy doing work
or waiting on another
thread or system resource,
causing a delay
in updating the view content
by at least 250 milliseconds.
The main thread
is also unavailable
to process new user interactions
until the hang is resolved.
To the user, it appears
the app is completely stuck.
Creating a responsive app
is critical to providing
a positive user experience.
Consistently unresponsive apps
may result in users
force quitting the app,
switching to a different app,
and in some cases,
even deleting your app
and writing a negative review.
Because of this,
tracking down hangs in your app
is critical to gaining
and maintaining your user base.
Providing a responsive
experience ensures people
will enjoy using your app.
For more information on hangs
and what causes them,
as well as strategies to
eliminate them from your code,
checkout the "Understand and
eliminate hangs from your app"
talk from 2021.
The app-development process
can be broken down
into three phases.
First, developing the latest
app version at desk using Xcode.
Then, testing the app
and collecting feedback
in a beta environment
without Xcode.
For example,
you may have an app version
that's development-signed
on your device
or distributed
through TestFlight.
Finally, releasing the latest
app version on the App Store.
Even for the most
proactive developers,
new hang issues
can arise at any phase,
so it's important that you
know the tools to resolve them
during each one.
Before iOS 16 and Xcode 14,
we offered two tools
that assisted with discovering
and diagnosing
the hangs in your app.
MetricKit is a framework
that supports collecting
nonaggregated hang rate metrics
and diagnostic reports
from individual users on your
beta or public release app.
The Xcode Organizer provides
an aggregated hang rate metric
from users on your
public release app.
There are gaps here,
specifically when developing
your app or when trying
to understand what source code
has caused the public release
hang-rate metric to rise.
In iOS 16 and Xcode 14,
we've been busy introducing
several new tools to help.
Let's introduce
each of them briefly
before we cover them
in more detail.
The Thread Performance
Checker in Xcode
alerts you to hang-causing
threading issues
while debugging your app
without actively tracing it.
Instruments in Xcode
now detects and labels hangs
while tracing your app.
On-device hang detection
provides hang detection
without using Xcode or tracing,
providing real-time
hang notifications
and supporting diagnostics
while using
your development-signed
or TestFlight app.
And finally,
the organizer in Xcode
now supports hang reports,
which provides
aggregated hang diagnostics
from users in the field.
Now that you know
what hangs are
and the different phases
they can arise,
I will cover
how to track down hangs
while developing
an app with Xcode.
In Xcode 14, the new
Thread Performance Checker tool
notifies you in the Xcode
Issue Navigator when it detects
priority inversions
and non-UI work
on the main thread of your app,
both of which
are common causes of hangs.
I have now returned to Xcode
to diagnose the hang I observed
earlier in the Food Truck app
when I was scrolling through
the donuts I've created.
When I built and ran the app,
and repeated
the user interaction,
the Thread Performance Checker
tool alerted me to a hang risk
caused by a priority inversion.
This means a higher priority
thread was attempting
to be synchronized
with a lower priority thread.
This may indicate the hang
we are noticing
is caused by the main thread
waiting on different
lower-priority threads.
To detect priority inversions
and non-UI work
on the main thread of your app,
enable the Thread Performance
Checker tool
from the Diagnostics section
of the appropriate scheme.
The Thread Performance Checker
alert has helped me discover
the potential culprit
of my hang,
but in order to triage further,
I will want to know
what the other thread was doing
during the hang duration.
Let's use another tool
to dive deeper.
The Time Profiler instrument
gives you the ability to know
what each thread
in your app was doing over time
by providing call stacks.
New in Xcode 14, the Time
Profiler also detects hangs
and labels them directly in
the corresponding process track.
In the Food Truck app,
I'll use the Time Profiler
to confirm a hang is occurring
when scrolling through
my donuts,
that it was caused by a priority
inversion on the main thread,
and figure out
what the lower priority threads
were busy doing that caused
the main thread to wait.
I start from the
Product > Profile menu in Xcode.
This builds the app for release
and launches Instruments
already setup to target the app.
I launch
the Time Profiler template
and begin recording a trace of
the problematic user interaction
in the Food Truck app.
I see there is a hang
being detected
and labeled in the timeline.
The hang duration
is also specified
to help evaluate
the severity of the issue.
Next, I can triple-click
the hang interval
which creates a time filter
for the duration of the hang
and filters the information
in the detail views
at the bottom
to only events occurring
in this selected time interval.
It also makes it easier
to see what was happening
during this time period
in other tracks.
The first thing I notice
is that the main thread
has barely any CPU usage
during the hang interval,
meaning the main thread
was unresponsive
because it was waiting
on another thread,
not because it was doing
too much work itself.
This aligns with
the Thread Performance Checker's
priority inversion alert
from earlier.
Next, I see a worker thread
that has lots of CPU usage
during the hang.
This is likely the thread that
the main thread is waiting for.
The next step
would be to examine
what the worker thread
was doing during the hang
and resolve
the priority inversion.
Hang detection
and labeling in Instruments
is a great way to surface
any hangs that are encountered
while profiling your app.
It is available by default
in the Time Profiler
and CPU Profiler instruments.
There is also a new standalone
hang tracing instrument
that you can add
to any trace documents
to surface hangs in combination
with other instruments.
In addition to hang detection
and labeling,
it allows you to configure
a hang duration threshold
to find specific periods
of unresponsiveness.
You have now learned
how to use Xcode
to discover
and diagnose hangs at desk.
Even with great testing
coverage during development,
beta and public release
environments are likely
to uncover hangs in code paths
you hadn't considered.
Next, I will introduce
how to track down hangs
once the app is deployed
in a beta environment.
I've now deployed
a build of the Food Truck app
to TestFlight through
App Store Connect
and it is downloaded
on my personal device.
I'll test the app when
selling donuts around town,
including in places where
I don't always have
a strong network connection.
But how do I discover
and diagnose hangs
if my device
is not connected to Xcode?
To continue to monitor for hangs
under these conditions,
iOS 16 introduces on-device hang
detection in Developer settings,
which provides real-time
hang notifications
and supporting diagnostics.
This is available
for development-signed
or TestFlight apps.
It's time to start
selling orders.
When I attempt to open
my current orders,
I receive an on-device
hang detection notification
that my app is hanging,
this time for over
three seconds.
I wonder why
I didn't notice this hang
when I was developing
with Xcode?
I will need to use
the diagnostic information
provided by the on-device hang
detection tool to learn more.
Once your app is setup
for development,
this feature can be
enabled by opening
Settings > Developer >
Hang Detection,
and toggling the switch.
The Hang Threshold setting
allows you to configure
the minimum duration
of hangs to detect.
The shortest hang threshold
is 250 milliseconds
and can be bumped
to 500 milliseconds or higher.
Long hangs tend to have
a higher user-impact,
but even shorter ones can be
disruptive to the experience,
depending on the context,
especially if they happen
consecutively.
After installing your app,
it will appear in the list
of monitored apps.
The final section
shows a chronological list
of available logs for the hangs
you were alerted to.
Note that these diagnostics
are best-effort
and processed in the background
at a low priority
to minimize
performance overhead.
This means the processing
can take longer,
especially if the system
is busy.
Fortunately, a passive
notification is displayed
when new diagnostics
become available.
Let's examine the diagnostics
for the hang that was detected
when I was opening
the orders in the app
while selling donuts
around town.
I am given both
a text-based hang log
and a tailspin
for the detected hang.
A text-based hang log
has less information,
but can give us
an understanding of the hang
at a glance.
For a deeper investigation,
open the tailspin
in Instruments for viewing
the thread interaction within
your process or identifying
the usage of system resources,
for example.
To start, I'll use
the Share button
to send the text-based hang log
to a Mac,
where I can symbolicate it
and view it on a larger screen.
From viewing an excerpt
of the text-based hang log
I transferred and symbolicated,
I see that during the hang,
I am calling a method
on the main thread
that I know performs synchronous
requests to the network.
When I am testing
the application at my desk
with Xcode and a strong
network connection,
there may not be any delay
when requesting data
from the network.
However, when testing
the app in places
with a limited
network connection,
the request takes longer
and results in a hang.
It is important to test
the beta version of your app
under these different,
real-world conditions,
and on-device hang detection
allows you to monitor for hangs
using just your device.
At this point, I have discovered
and diagnosed hangs
using the available tooling in
the development and beta phases,
and I am ready to make
the Food Truck app available
to customers in the App Store.
I'll now present how to track
down hangs once your app
is in the hands
of your customers,
on various OS versions,
devices, and in other
real-world conditions
you may not have been able to
replicate in your prior testing.
New in Xcode 14,
the Xcode Organizer
supports hang reports to deliver
aggregated hang diagnostics
from customer devices.
The collected data is from
customers which have consented
to share app analytics,
and they contain information
about the main thread stack
trace that led to the hangs.
Hang reports are available
from the left-side navigation
of the Xcode Organizer.
When similar stack traces
are collected,
they are grouped together
to form a single signature.
In the list,
the signatures are shown sorted
based on the user impact.
For each signature, you can
find a few sample hang logs.
Each hang log contains
the main thread stack trace
containing the code responsible
for the hang, the hang duration,
and the device and OS version
from which the log originated.
Each signature also provides
aggregate statistics about
how many hang logs the signature
was responsible for
and a breakdown of those logs
by OS Version and device.
To identify the hangs
most affecting your customers,
pay close attention
to your top signatures.
In this case, the top signature
is responsible for 21 percent
of the hang time
in this release.
Since I've submitted
the app to the App Store
with symbol information,
the hangs report shows me
all of the functions named just
as they are in the source code.
By examining the functions in
this main thread's call stack,
I can infer that this hang was
caused by synchronously reading
a file from disk
on the main thread,
which is known to block
for significant periods of time.
It is important to tackle
the performance problems
that are most affecting
your customers,
and the Organizer is
a great tool to identify them.
Check this data after
each app release
to validate the previous hangs
have been resolved,
and to address new hangs
that may appear.
You can also retrieve
the same hang report data
through the App Store
Connect REST APIs.
This can help you integrate
performance data
with your own systems,
or run additional analysis.
I highly recommend you check out
the "Identify trends with the
Power and Performance API" video
to learn more about using
the Power and Performance APIs.
Added in Xcode 13.2, you can
now receive notifications
when monitoring power and
performance metrics in your app.
I recommend
you enable notifications
by clicking the Notifications
button in the top right
of the Xcode Organizer's
Regressions view.
This will alert you to sudden
rises in your app's hang rate.
Find out more about performance
regressions in the
"Diagnose Power and Performance
Regressions in your app" talk
from 2021.
To improve your experience
in the Xcode Organizer,
I strongly recommend
you build and submit your app
to the App Store
with symbol information.
This symbol information is used
to add function names
from your app to reports
in the Xcode Organizer.
This makes stack traces
significantly easier
to understand.
It also enables
one-click navigation
from a function name
in a stack trace
to the function definition
in the Xcode source editor.
The information extracted
is limited to function
and methods,
names and paths
of source code files,
and line number information.
It is important to note that
the limited symbol information
will be securely stored
and will never be shared.
Fantastic!
You now know how to discover
and diagnose hangs
at each phase
in the development process.
Going forward,
discover, diagnose,
and fix hangs
in the earliest possible phase
of the development process.
Use the tools available to help,
including proactively profiling
new features using Instruments.
Be sure to enable
the Thread Performance Checker
and on-device hang detection.
After each release,
use the Xcode Organizer
to tackle hangs that are most
affecting your customers
and to validate that hangs
from previous app versions
have been resolved.
Enable regression notifications
to be proactively alerted
to regressed
performance metrics,
which can be the first sign of
power and performance problems.
And finally, build and submit
your app to the App Store
with symbol information
to improve the usefulness
of the Xcode Organizer.
By following these steps,
your apps will have
even better performance
to provide the best possible
user experience.
Thanks for hanging out at WWDC!
♪