♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hip music ♪
♪
Hello, and welcome to "What's
New in App Store Connect."
My name's Will Averill,
and I'm an engineering manager
on the App Store Connect team.
App Store Connect has grown
considerably over the years.
You use it to create,
manage, and grow your apps
on the App Store
across all of our platforms.
And we continue to bring new
features to App Store Connect
on web, our iOS and iPadOS app,
and the App Store Connect API.
Just last year, we launched
a bunch of great new features.
You've probably heard all about
things like in-app events,
custom product pages,
and TestFlight for Mac.
So instead,
let me quickly highlight
a couple recent updates
you might have missed.
In TestFlight, we made
managing your build's
associated tester groups easier.
With just one click, you can
now quickly add or remove
a tester group to a build
directly from the Versions
or Build Groups tab.
We also heard your feedback
loud and clear,
so we made an update
allowing you to transfer apps
that use Apple Wallet.
And finally, to facilitate
the submission process
for in-app events,
custom product pages,
and product page optimization,
we launched the enhanced
App Store submission experience.
This is one the biggest
enhancements we've made
to the submission workflow,
so let's explore this together
in a bit more detail.
First, you're now able
to group multiple items
into a single submission.
Additionally --
in most cases --
you can choose to submit
without a new app version.
And we introduced
a dedicated App Review page
where you can manage
in-progress submissions,
communicate with App Review,
and even view recently
completed submissions.
Let's start by talking
about what it means
to group items
in a review submission.
Say we have a number
of custom product pages
or any other review items
we want to publish to the store.
Since review items
can only be submitted
as part of a review submission,
the first step is
to add them to one.
Think of a review submission
as the vehicle
that carries review items
to and from App Review.
Now, a review submission only
needs one item to be submitted,
but the advantage
to grouping several items
is they are all reviewed
in context together.
This helps ensure a consistent
and efficient review.
In fact, all review submissions
are typically reviewed
within 24 hours,
regardless of the number
or type of review items.
After review,
each item in the submission
will be marked as
accepted or rejected.
It's very important
to understand
that no review
items are approved
until all items in the review
submission are accepted.
So let's look at two ways
to move forward
with a review submission
that has rejected items.
The first option is to edit any
of these rejected review items
and then resubmit.
If those items
now come back accepted,
the review submission
is complete
and every item is approved
and able to be published
to the App Store.
The other option
is to simply remove
any rejected items
from the submission.
This leaves
the review submission
with only approved items,
once again completing
the review process.
However, keep in mind
that any removed items
will need to be resubmitted
as a part of a new submission
in order to become approved.
And before I move on,
let me specify that
review submission items
can be app versions,
in-app events,
custom product pages, or
product page optimization tests.
Now, let's take a look
at how you're able to submit
without a new app version.
To understand how this works,
let's discuss
a few more specifics
about review submissions.
First, each submission
has an associated platform.
In addition,
each platform supports
a specific set of review items.
Although, as you can see,
most items are reviewed
and grouped as part
of an iOS submission.
And lastly, you can have one
in-progress review submission
per platform.
In this example,
you can see we're working
towards submitting all three
versions of our app.
But, let's go ahead
and take a closer look
at the iOS review submission.
App Review reviews
all items in a submission
against an app version to ensure
everything is consistent.
If there's an app version
in the submission,
that becomes the version
used for review.
But like I mentioned earlier,
you can submit without adding a
new version to your submission.
To do this requires
a previously approved version
of your app.
Of course,
once submitted,
items will be reviewed
against this version.
This means you're able
to submit in-app events,
custom product pages and
product page optimization tests
anytime after your first
iOS version is approved,
without needing
a new app binary.
So now that I've explained
how this experience works,
let me show you
where the dedicated
App Review submission page
lives in App Store Connect.
Once you've logged in
and selected an app,
click the App Review link
on the left nav menu.
This is the App Review page
where you can manage
your entire review workflow.
Here, you can see an overview
of your submissions
and click into any of them
for a more detailed look.
Now obviously,
using the web UI is great,
but wouldn't it be nice
to submit and track
submission status on the go?
That's why we're excited
to share
that we've brought the
enhanced submission experience
to App Store Connect on iPadOS
and iOS with this week's update.
You'll now be able to submit
any of your Ready for Review
submissions to App Review
from anywhere,
with just one tap.
Once submitted,
you can track the progress
of your review submissions.
And you can opt in
to receive timely notifications
about status updates
as well as manage your
submission by removing items,
viewing rejection reasons,
and replying to App Review.
So that's the enhanced
App Store submission experience,
available now
on App Store Connect
for iPadOS and iOS.
Let's shift gears a bit
and focus on
the App Store Connect API
which represents a great way
for you to customize
and automate your app workflows.
Best of all, we're always
working to add new capabilities
to the API.
Last year, we added support
for App Clips, Xcode Cloud,
in-app events,
custom product pages,
product page optimization,
and even the enhanced App Store
submission experience
I just described.
And this year is no different.
With our huge 2.0 release
coming this summer,
we're expanding the number
of resources in the API
by 60 percent.
In this summer's release,
we're adding some
great new functionality
that has been heavily requested.
Beginning with
a comprehensive set of APIs
to manage your entire
in-app purchase
and subscription lifecycle.
We started by breaking
subscriptions
into their own resource
and giving you full control
to create, edit, or delete
any of your in-app purchases
or subscriptions.
You'll also be able to manage
pricing, submit for review,
and create special offers
and promo codes.
We can't wait to see
how you take advantage
of this new opportunity
to automate your in-app purchase
and subscription workflows.
We're also adding the ability
to fetch and respond
to your app's customer reviews.
The goal here
is to allow you to build
some great custom workflows
around customer interaction.
And lastly, we're adding
additional reporting data
to the power and performance
metrics and diagnostics APIs
for app hangs.
Identifying and eliminating
hangs in your app
is a great way
to increase performance
and improve user experience.
But until now,
you could only view metrics
like your app's hang rate
through the API.
That changes this summer
as we're adding
a new diagnostic type
for app hangs.
You'll be able use this type
with the existing
diagnostic signatures resource
to discover the places
in your app
that contribute most to hangs.
Not only that,
but you'll also be able to see
detailed stack traces
for these hang signatures
through the diagnostic logs
relationship.
I've just barely scratched
the surface here,
so if you'd like to learn more
about how these APIs work
or how to use this data
to discover additional insights
into your app's behavior,
definitely check out
these two related sessions.
Overall, the App Store Connect
API 2.0 release
represents a major milestone.
After four years of development,
we've fully embraced REST APIs
as the future of
App Store Connect automation.
As a result,
we'll begin to decommission
the XML feed this fall.
Therefore, we highly encourage
you to align your integration
with the App Store Connect API
moving forward.
In summary, we recommend
taking full advantage
of the enhanced App Store
submission experience
in order streamline
your review process.
Also, be sure to download
the latest release
of App Store Connect
for iOS and iPadOS,
which adds support for the
enhanced submission experience
and several other updates.
And finally, we're adding
a bunch of new capabilities
to the App Store Connect API
with the 2.0 release
this summer.
We strongly suggest working
to integrate with our API,
especially as we begin
to decommission the XML feed
later this fall.
As always, we look forward
to hearing your feedback
and hope you have a great WWDC!
Thanks for watching.
♪