[spacey music]
Hi, I'm Nick Gillett, an engineer
here at Apple on the Core Data team.
In this session, I'll show you how
to use our developer tools to learn more
about your applications that use
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
We'll begin with a detailed look
at how to explore applications
in a productive and educational way.
Then, we'll use some of my favorite tools
to analyze how applications behave.
And finally, we'll look
at how you can provide detailed,
actionable feedback about your experiences
with NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
I like to think of engineering
a bit like the water cycle.
Typically, I begin working on a feature
by exploring the space
that feature exists in.
Then, based on the things I learn,
I use a combination of tools and tests
to analyze my work
in a reproducible environment.
Finally, I review the results
with my peers and coworkers
and collect their feedback.
The goal of this cycle
is to durably capture the things I learn
as I work.
Apple platforms include a great selection
of tools like Xcode,
Instruments, and XCTest
that I use to capture what I learn.
Those tools also make it possible
to collect a wealth
of diagnostic information I can use
to provide actionable feedback.
This session references a lot of knowledge
from years past.
I've discussed
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
and the Core Data CloudKit Sample
application I'll be showing today
in detail in the sessions "Build Apps that
share data through CloudKit and Core Data"
and in the session
"Using Core Data with CloudKit."
I'll also demonstrate how to use
Xcode and Instruments to run tests
and the Device organizer
to capture data from devices.
If you need to,
I recommend you review the sessions
"Getting Started With Instruments"
and "Diagnose performance issues
with the Xcode Organizer"
to learn more about these two important
pieces of the toolchain.
All right, let's get started with
the first part of the cycle, exploration.
For me, the primary goal
of exploration is to learn.
I want to challenge and verify
all of the assumptions I have
about how an application will work.
I might ask:
What happens if I tap this button?
Does NSPersistentCloudKitContainer sync
when I save data to a persistent store?
Does an application run out of memory
when working with a large data set?
From Core Data's perspective,
all of these questions are influenced
by the data an application works with.
For example, the Core Data CloudKit
sample application uses this data model.
It manages a set of posts which have
some text fields for a title and content.
Posts can be related to attachments,
generally images,
which can be quite large.
The ImageData is therefore stored
across a to-one relationship
so that it can be loaded on demand.
And I'm going to focus
my exploration on that data set,
specifically what happens
to the sample application
as I change the shape,
structure, and variance of that data.
Since its release, the sample application
has included a built-in way to explore it.
The Generate 1000 Posts button
does exactly what it says on the label.
When tapped, it generates
a sample data set
of 1,000 posts with a short title.
The Posts table view easily handles
this level of data.
So the next question I would ask is,
how can I explore a data set
of a different shape or size
in this application?
The Generate 1000 Posts button
runs what I like to call
an algorithmic data generator.
Algorithmic data generators
follow a set of predetermined rules
like "insert 1000 objects"
or "make sure that every field has
a value, or that no fields have values."
We, as it turns out,
are also data generators.
We can hand-craft
specific data sets in code, in SQL,
or by interacting
directly with an application,
and these generated data sets
can be preserved
for later use or analysis.
To explore a larger data set,
I can define a new data generator,
the LargeDataGenerator,
and give it a single method,
generateData, to build my new data set.
With just two for loops,
I can generate a set of 60 posts
that each have 11 image attachments
associated with them.
That's 660 images in total.
At an average size
of 10-20 megabytes per image,
the generated data set
consumes almost 10GB of data.
With such a simple interface,
data generators are easily invoked
in tests like this one.
This single line of code generates
over 10GB of representative data
for this test to use.
Additionally, we can build
validation methods in the tests
that verify the data generator
behaves correctly,
like asserting that each post
does indeed get 11 image attachments.
Of course, this wouldn't be a talk
about NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
if we didn't sync this data.
So let's craft a new test to do just that.
The first thing I'll need is an instance
of NSPersistentCloudKitContainer to use.
I've created a helper method
to make that easy.
Next, I use the LargeDataGenerator
to populate the container
with my desired data set.
And finally, I wait for the container
to finish exporting the data.
In this specific test,
I wait for up to 20 minutes
to give the large data set time to upload.
The eagle eyed among you may have noticed
that this test appears
to be doing a lot of waiting
for different types of events.
Here, when I create the container,
I wait for the container
to finish setting up.
And here, I use a helper method
I wrote to create XCTestExpectations
for an export event from the container.
Let's look at that in detail.
This method takes a desired event type
and an instance
of NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
as an argument.
It creates one expectation
for each persistent store in the container
using XCTestCase's
expectationForNotification method
to observe NSPersistentCloudKitContainer's
eventChanged notification.
In the notification handler block,
I verify that the incoming event
is of the correct type
for the specific store
this expectation is for,
and that it's finished
by checking endDate
is not equal to nil.
By using this technique,
we can strongly associate
points of control in our tests
with events
from NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
Back in my test, I add a new container
to import the data that was just exported.
This technique uses a trick.
It creates a new instance
of NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
with empty store files.
This allows the test to take advantage
of NSPersistentCloudKitContainer's
first-time import
to explore what happens when all
of this data is downloaded by a device.
Now, tests are great,
but sometimes I want to feel
how a data set behaves in an application.
To do that, I can bind data generators
to a user interface,
as we have done in the sample application.
When I tap the Generate Large Data
button, I can watch
the data generator populate the data set.
On a second device, I can watch
the table view populate
as NSPersistentCloudKitContainer makes
progress downloading the generated data.
Tapping on an individual post
allows me to see the attachments download
and populate incrementally,
just as they would
for a user of this application.
This specific user interface
is driven by an alert controller.
The LargeDataGenerator's simple
interface makes it easy
to add a new alert action
with just these two lines of code.
It's clear, concise,
and easily understood.
In this section, we've explored
the behavior of an application
using the concept of a data generator.
Data generators can be driven in
our applications any way we choose,
whether that be by tests
or custom UI, as I've demonstrated,
or by something
like a command line argument,
or anything else that happens to work
for your specific use case.
Now that we know how to populate
an application with data,
we're ready to analyze how
that changes application behavior.
In this section, we'll learn
about some tools and techniques
to analyze how an application behaves
with a large data set.
Specifically, we'll use Instruments
to analyze the time and memory complexity
of the data set
created by the LargeDataGenerator.
Then, we'll look at the wealth
of information available to us
in the system logs.
There we can find a record of activity
from NSPersistentCloudKitContainer,
CloudKit, the system scheduler,
and from push notifications.
Let's get stared with Instruments.
One reason I love tests is
that Xcode makes it easy
to analyze the behavior of a test.
In my test case, I can right-click
on the test disclosure
in the gutter and select Profile.
Xcode will build the tests
and then automatically launch instruments.
I can double-click
the Time Profiler instrument
to examine where my test spends time
doing work.
When I click the record button,
Instruments will launch the application
and execute the selected test.
This test appears to be taking
quite a while to run.
Let's skip ahead and see why.
Instruments has already selected
the main thread,
and on the right side, I can see
the heaviest stack trace of the test run.
Let's make that a little easier to read.
There we go.
Now, if I scroll to the bottom,
I can see the LargeDataGenerator is
spending a lot of time
generating thumbnails.
How would we decide
if this is a bug or a feature?
In the LargeDataGenerator,
I have this line of code that generates
a new thumbnail for each attachment.
However, I know from the application's
data model that thumbnails are special.
They're computed on demand
from the related imageData.
That means this line is unnecessary,
and my data generator is wasting
a lot of time on them.
So I can just remove it.
Let's see how that changes
the performance of the test.
After rebuilding the app
with the updated data generator,
I can rerun the test in Instruments.
And honestly I don't see much of change,
but after a few more seconds,
the test completes.
That's a lot faster than the previous run.
Let's see
where the test spent most of its time.
In the right drawer, I now see
that the heaviest stack trace
is saving images to the persistent store,
and that's exactly what I would expect
for a test that manages this much data.
That one change reduced the runtime
of the generateData test
from this to this.
It executes in one tenth the time.
Analyzing tests in this way
doesn't always uncover bugs,
Sometimes we just learn more
about where an application
is spending time
when working with a specific data set.
But either way, though,
it's valuable learning.
So that's how the Time Profiler instrument
can help explore
where an application
spends time with a data set.
Now, because of the size of this data set,
I'm also curious how much memory
the test uses.
So let's give it a run
using the Allocations instrument.
I'll use Xcode to launch
Instruments to profile my test.
Instead of selecting
the Time Profiler instrument,
I'll double-click Allocations...
And then click Record.
Even though
this test is executing quickly,
it’s using a lot of memory,
over 10GB, in fact.
This tells me that nearly
the entire data set
is being kept in memory
during the test run.
Let's find out why.
I can select
a range of allocations to look at.
In the bottom pane, I can see that
there are a number of large allocations.
I can dig into those
by clicking this disclosure,
and then click
on one of the large data blobs
that's been allocated for the test.
This specific blob was allocated
but not freed for almost two seconds.
That's an eternity in test time.
Why was it alive so long?
I can explore that by expanding
the stack trace on the right.
From experience, the allocation
and deallocation stack trace
tell me that this object
was faulted by CoreData
and then released when the managed object
context finished its work.
That's usually an indication that
the object was retained by a fetch,
an autoreleasepool,
or an object in the test.
The problematic section of code
is here in my verifier.
I load an image
from an attachment and verify it.
However, this keeps the attachment
and the associated image data
registered
with the managed object context.
There are a number of ways
we could try to resolve this.
For example, in a table view,
we could use a batched fetch
to free the images
as the table scrolls over the posts.
However, this test is executing
far too quickly for that to be effective.
I need to change my approach.
Instead of verifying by fetching posts,
I can fetch attachments instead.
If I also fetch only the objectIDs,
the managed object context
won't capture any
of the loaded objects until I ask it to.
I can use NSManagedObjectContext's
objectWithID method
to fetch the attachments
as I go for validation.
Finally, for every 10 attachments
I validate, I reset the context,
freeing all of the cached state
and the associated memory.
If I rerun the test with this change,
I can see that it results
in a much more predictable and tunable
level of memory consumption.
In fact, the verifier
uses even less memory
than the LargeDataGenerator does
when it inserts these objects.
Let's drill down
into a specific allocation
to learn how the fix works.
First, I'll select a range
of allocations to work with.
Then, I'll select
a specific size to examine,
I need to enable destroyed objects to find
the ones that were freed during this time,
and then I can select
a specific allocation to examine.
On the right side, Instruments
shows me an allocation stack trace,
but I want to know where it was freed,
so I'll select the deallocation event.
I happen to know
that this stack trace means
that NSManagedObjectContext
is asynchronously deallocating
the object that retained this blob,
freeing the consumed memory.
This technique allows me to establish
a high water mark for the test,
enabling it
to run on systems with less memory.
By combining tests with Instruments,
I've been able to discover
that this specific test had
some less-than-desirable behavior.
I made targeted changes to address
that behavior directly
and then verify the results.
Additionally, the system logs also contain
a wealth of information
about an application
and the system services it depends on,
like CloudKit,
scheduling, and push notifications.
I'm going to sync a single post
between my MacBook Pro and my iPhone.
When I insert a new post on my Mac,
give a short title,
and let it upload to iCloud,
the system logs capture
a number of events.
When it syncs to my iPhone,
sometimes even capturing
intermediate state,
the system logs capture
a corresponding set of events.
On the MacBook Pro,
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer does work
inside of the application process,
in this case, CoreDataCloudKitDemo.
When data is written
to a persistent store,
it asks a system service called DASD
if now is a good time
to export that data to CloudKit.
If it is, DASD will tell
NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
to run an activity.
will then schedule work
with a process called cloudd
to export the changed objects to CloudKit.
We can observe logs from each
of these processes using the Console app.
For application logs, we simply look
for the application process,
CoreDataCloudKitDemo.
Here, I've selected one
that shows an export completing.
For scheduling logs, we want
to look at logs from the process dasd
and from the application's specific store.
Here, I've selected the start
of an export activity
for the application's private store.
Let's examine
this log in a bit more detail.
Activities created
by NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
with dasd follow a specific format.
The activity identifier
is composed of a specific prefix
that NSPersistentCloudKitContainer uses
along with the store identifier
for the store the activity belongs to.
The dasd logs include information
about how the service decides
if an activity can run.
Policies that affect
the application's ability to do work
will be listed in the log
along with a final decision.
Finally, the process cloudd
logs information from CloudKit,
and I like to filter these logs
by the container identifier
I'm working with.
Here I've selected
the corresponding modify records operation
for the export I mentioned earlier.
When changes are imported
on a receiving device,
there is one additional process
to observe.
The process apsd is responsible
for receiving push notifications
and forwarding them to the application.
That causes NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
to initiate a series of activities
similar to the export process.
It asks dasd for time to perform an import
and then works with cloudd to fetch
all of the updated objects from CloudKit
and import them
into the local store.
Apsd logs when it receives
a push notification for an application,
and this log captures
a number of important details.
The log message includes
the container identifier here
as well as the subscription name
and zone identifier
that triggered the push notification.
These are managed
by NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
and will always start with the
prefix com.apple.coredata.cloudkit.
Now the console app is great.
But when I'm developing on my Mac,
I like to use the log stream command
in Terminal to display
these logs alongside my app.
I open one terminal window or tab
for each of the following predicates,
first the application.
Next, the logs from cloudd so I can see
what's happening with the CloudKit server.
Next, apsd for push notification logs.
And finally, dasd so I can see
what's happening with activities
that NSPersistentCloudKitContainer
schedules on my behalf.
These predicates can also be used
to guide your queries in the console app.
There's so much information
available to us on the devices we use.
The challenge, really, is knowing
what tools to use to find and analyze it.
With just Instruments, we can learn
about a host of topics like runtime
and memory performance and so much more.
The system logs capture events
that describe the work an application does
and what the system is doing
for it behind the scenes.
The last phase of my development cycle
is collecting and providing
actionable feedback.
In this section, I'll demonstrate
how to collect diagnostic information
from devices.
Our goal is to use
this information
to generate feedback that's actionable
and aligned with a specific goal.
These techniques can help
you collect feedback
from any device, whether it's one you own
or a customer device.
There are three steps to gathering
diagnostic information from a device.
First, we'll need to install
the CloudKit logging profile,
which enables logs that can be used
to identify issues
and triage them effectively.
Next, we'll collect a sysdiagnose
from the affected device.
And finally, if we have physical access
to the device,
we can also collect
the persistent store files from Xcode.
To install the the logging profile,
we simply visit the Profile and Logs page
on the developer portal.
I can search for the CloudKit profile
and tap the profile link to download it.
On some devices, a notification
will appear to install the profile.
However, here on iOS,
we'll need to install it manually
via the Settings app.
In Settings, I can navigate to tap
on the Profile Downloaded cell.
Then I can tap on the downloaded profile
to install it.
Follow the steps to complete
the installation.
After the profile is installed,
the device can be rebooted,
and it will take effect.
Once the device has rebooted,
we can reproduce the behavior
we want to capture
and then take a sysdiagnose.
Taking a sysdiagnose is done using
a keychord, a special series of buttons.
These are described
in the instructions page for the profile.
I happen to know that for an iPhone,
we hold the volume buttons
and the side button
for a couple of seconds
and then release it.
After a short while, a sysdiagnose
will be available in Settings.
The instructions for finding it
are included in the instructions file
for a profile.
In Settings I navigate
to Privacy & Security,
Analytics and Improvements,
then choose Analytics Data,
and scroll through the logs
until I find the sysdiagnose.
If I tap on the sysdiagnose
and then tap the Share button,
I can choose a number of ways to share it.
For example, I like to AirDrop them
to my Mac for analysis.
Finally, if possible,
I can collect the store files
from Xcode using the Device Organizer.
I can collect the files from this iPhone
by clicking on the Sample Application
in the installed apps list,
clicking on the disclosure button,
choosing Download Container,
and saving that to my Downloads directory.
With all of that done,
both the system logs and the store files
are now available for analysis.
We already talked
about the log stream command,
but with a sysdiagnose,
I can use the log show command
to print out logs from the sysdiagnose.
Here, I've copied the predicate
for the apsd logs we talked about earlier.
The final argument to the log show command
is the logarchive to use.
If nothing is specified,
it will display the system logs
from the machine its running on.
Here, I have specified
system_logs.logarchive
so that it reads the logs
I took from the sysdiagnose.
For example, I can specify
a precise time range
to focus on the time
when an event I'm interested in occurred.
I can also combine many of the predicates
we discussed earlier
to form a unified log of all the activity
relevant to an application,
beginning with the application logs here,
the cloudd logs here, apsd logs here,
and finally dasd logs here.
This powerful command can be included
in feedback reports
or shared with teammates
to allow everyone to focus
on a specific set of logs for analysis.
In this session, we talked about
how you can explore application behavior
with data generators,
analyze applications with instruments
and the system logs,
and provide or collect actionable feedback
from applications
that use NSPersistentCloudKitContainer.
I'm Nick Gillett,
and it's been my pleasure to bring you
this presentation.
Thanks for watching, stay active,
close your rings, and have a great WWDC.
[spacey music]