♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Julia
from Privacy Engineering,
and welcome to "Explore
App Tracking Transparency."
At Apple, we believe privacy
is a fundamental human right.
Part of engineering
great privacy
is giving people
choices and control
over how their data is used.
When people have these choices
and understand how their data
will be linked or shared,
they are more likely to trust
and engage with your app.
That's why,
beginning last year,
App Store policy requires apps
to receive users' permission
before tracking users
across apps and websites
owned by other companies
by adopting
the AppTrackingTransparency
framework.
Today, I'm going to talk to you
about when and how to adopt
App Tracking Transparency.
First, I'll start with some
background on tracking
to help you understand if
and when your app needs to adopt
the AppTrackingTransparency
framework.
Then, I'll highlight some
key things to keep in mind
when adopting the framework
in practice.
Let's get started with some
background on tracking.
So, how is tracking defined
for App Tracking Transparency?
Tracking refers to linking
user or device data
collected from your app
with user or device data
collected from other
companies' apps, websites,
or offline properties
for targeted advertising
or advertising-measurement
purposes.
Tracking also refers
to sharing user or device data
with data brokers.
Let's talk through
some example scenarios
to better understand
how tracking is defined.
First, let's look
at an advertising scenario
that doesn't involve tracking.
Suppose I download
an app called Pal About,
and the Pal About app
has a feature
that lets me search
for places and events
that are happening nearby.
Now suppose I use Pal About
to search for places
that serve waffles near me,
which results in Pal About
storing waffles
as an interest of mine.
Pal About later wants to show
an ad for breakfast places
targeting people
who like breakfast foods.
Using the data Pal About stores
about me from my searches,
Pal About shows me
the breakfast ad.
In this example,
Pal About doesn't link my data
with any data
from an app or website
owned by another company
to show me the breakfast ad,
so this scenario would
not be considered tracking.
For another example that
wouldn't be considered tracking,
suppose the company that owns
Pal About -- Pal About Inc. --
has another app that I use
called Pal About Plus.
And Pal About's server links
together data collected about me
in Pal About Plus,
like my interest in tacos,
with data collected about me
in Pal About.
After linking this data,
Pal About shows me an ad
for a taco truck using
the fact I like tacos
collected from Pal About Plus.
In this example,
the Pal About app doesn't need
to get my permission to track
because it isn't tracking.
Pal About doesn't link
my data from Pal About
with any data
from an app or website
owned by another company.
Let's now consider a scenario
that would require Pal About
to get permission to track.
Suppose there's
a food delivery app I use
that's owned by a different
company than Pal About.
And I've used
the food delivery app
to place orders late at night.
When I signed up for
the food delivery app,
I gave the app
my email address --
the same email address I used
to sign up for Pal About
and that Pal About stores
for my account.
The food delivery app
includes code
that shares my email address
and the fact I often order
at night with Pal About.
The Pal About server uses my
email address to link together
my interest in waffles,
collected by the Pal About app,
to the fact I order at night,
collected in
the food delivery app.
Finally, Pal About
uses the combination
of my ordering habits
and my interest in waffles
to show me
an ad for a restaurant
that serves all-day breakfast.
This scenario
would require Pal About
to request permission to track
because it linked user data
from Pal About --
my email address --
with another company's
user data --
my email and habit
of ordering at night --
for advertising purposes.
In this example, data is
linked together across apps
with an email address.
Even if the email address
or another user identifier
is hashed before it is used
to link data,
it would still require
permission to track
because it would still be
linking data about a user
from the app with another
company's data about that user.
The type of identifier
and whether or not it is hashed
doesn't change the fact
it is being used for tracking,
which is what
requires permission.
Another thing
you'll need to consider
to determine if your app needs
to request permission to track
is how third-party SDKs use
and share data from your app.
As a developer,
you're responsible for
the behavior of your whole app.
Returning to our example,
suppose the Pal About developer
hasn't written
any code themselves
that would require
permission to track,
but would like to include
a third-party SDK in their app
for advertising-measurement
purposes.
Whether Pal About
needs permission to track
in order to include the SDK
depends on whether or not
the SDK combines
user data from Pal About
with user data from other
companies' apps or websites.
For example, if the SDK
shares user data from Pal About
to provide analytics
about ads in Pal About,
but doesn't link the user data
it collects from Pal About
with user data
from other companies,
it doesn't require
permission to track.
Now suppose instead,
the SDK shares user data from
Pal About with an ad network,
and the ad network
links the data it receives
about how I use Pal About
with data about ads I saw
in other companies' apps
to compare the impact
of ad campaigns in those apps.
This requires Pal About
to request users' permission
to track because this SDK
is tracking.
This is considered tracking
regardless of whether Pal About
uses the SDK
for those purposes,
or even if Pal About
only gets aggregate reporting
after Pal About
users' data is linked
with other companies'
users' data.
If you're unsure about
whether an SDK you want to use
would contain code
that would require
App Tracking Transparency,
you should ask the developer
of that SDK.
This responsibility applies
not just to SDKs,
but to any libraries or
third-party code your app uses.
So far, we've looked at examples
that involve linking user data.
Now let's look
at another scenario
that's considered tracking:
sharing user or device data
with data brokers.
First, how are data brokers
defined?
Data brokers are defined by law
in some jurisdictions.
But in general,
a data broker is a company
that regularly collects
and sells, licenses,
or otherwise discloses
to third parties
the personal information
of particular end users
with whom the business does
not have a direct relationship.
Let's look at sharing data with
a data broker in an example.
Suppose the Pal About app
includes client code
that sends my interest
in waffles
and an account identifier
to a data broker.
This scenario counts as tracking
whether or not
the data that is shared
is linked with data
from other companies
for advertising
or advertising measurement.
Sharing of user data
with a data broker
requires permission to track.
And even if
Pal About client code
doesn't directly send
my account identifier
and my interest in waffles
to the data broker,
but instead this interest
is sent to Pal About's server
and the server
later shares accounts
interested in waffles
with the data broker,
this would require
getting permission to track
even though my device
isn't communicating
with the data broker directly.
We've now talked through
how the definition of tracking
applies to some
example scenarios.
For more information about
how App Tracking Transparency
defines tracking,
you can visit
the User Privacy
and Data Use page.
Now, if you've determined
that your app
would like to track users,
you'll need to ask for
and obtain the user's permission
before you do so.
Here's how.
To ask for permission
for your app to track,
you'll need to present
the app tracking authorization
request prompt by calling
the requestTrackingAuthorization
method.
Calling this method will cause
a system permission alert --
like this one for Pal About --
to appear over your app.
This is a one-time prompt.
The system will remember
the user's choice
and won't prompt again
unless the app is uninstalled
and reinstalled.
The next thing you'll
need to do is provide
a NSUserTrackingUsageDescription
key in your app's info.plist.
The string provided here will
be shown in the system prompt
and informs the user why
the app is requesting permission
to use data for tracking
the user or the device.
A great purpose string is clear,
concise, and helps users
understand why they are
being asked to allow tracking.
This string doesn't need
to include the app's name,
because the system
will automatically identify
the requesting app
and display the app name
in the system prompt.
If you don't include
a usage-description string,
your app will crash
when the system prompt is shown.
Finally, use
trackingAuthorizationStatus
to determine the user's
app-tracking permission status
for your app.
If a user has selected
Allow for this app,
then you have their permission
to link their activity
in that app across
other apps and websites
as long as their
tracking authorization status
remains authorized.
Users can change
and grant or revoke
their tracking authorization
at any time,
so make sure your app checks the
tracking authorization status
each time it is launched
and only continues to track
when the value of the
tracking authorization status
is authorized.
Users can control whether apps
have their permission to track
on a per-app basis.
Just because a user
has given one of your apps
permission to track doesn't mean
you have their permission
to track in another app
owned by the same company.
Different apps must each
individually request permission
from the user
for that particular app
before data from
that app can be linked
to apps or websites
owned by other companies
for marketing or advertising.
If your app doesn't have
tracking authorization
for a user,
there are a couple things
to keep in mind.
First, per the App Store
review guidelines,
your app must not gate
any of its functionality
on whether the user agrees
to allow tracking.
Second, the IDFA API
will return all zeros
if the user has asked your app
not to track.
If a user has opted
out of tracking,
there are nontracking
alternatives for advertising
or advertising measurement
for your app.
For example, your app could
choose to serve first-party ads
or contextual ads.
And for advertising measurement,
we continue to build and improve
privacy preserving
ad-attribution technologies
that ad networks can adopt.
For more information
about recent improvements
to SKAdNetwork and private click
measurement, you can refer to
"Meet privacy preserving
ad attribution"
and "What's new in SKAdNetwork."
You'll also need to declare
what data your app uses
to track for display in your
app's privacy nutrition label.
Filling out your
privacy nutrition label
when submitting your app
to the App Store
and getting permission
to track using
the AppTrackingTransparency
framework
are two separate steps
that are both required
if your app would like to use
data for tracking.
For more information
about nutrition labels
and how to fill them out
for your app,
see "Create your
Privacy Nutrition Label."
Finally, let's talk
about fingerprinting.
With permission,
tracking is allowed.
But fingerprinting
is never allowed.
Regardless of whether
a user gives your app
permission to track,
fingerprinting --
or using signals
from the device
to try to identify
the device or user --
is not allowed
per the Apple Developer Program
License Agreement.
Some examples of user or device
data used for fingerprinting
include properties
of a user's web browser
and its configuration,
the user's device
the user's location, or
the user's network connection.
Collecting any data
solely for the purpose
of generating a fingerprint
is also not allowed.
It's important people
have transparency and control
over how their data
is used for tracking.
We hope that by tuning in
to this session,
you now have the tools
you need to determine
when and how to give people
that control by adopting
the AppTrackingTransparency
framework.
Thanks for watching.
♪