♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Jared Marsau and I work
on Game Technologies at Apple.
Today, I'll be talking to you
about how you can use
select Apple frameworks
to add new features
to your Unity-based games.
We know that many of you
are using tools, such as Unity,
to build your games.
Our goal is to bring you
the latest features,
no matter what tool
you're using.
Starting today,
enhance your games
with a new set
of Unity plug-ins.
Use the Game Center plug-in
to add GameKit features like
player authentication,
leaderboards, and matchmaking.
Use the Game Controller plug-in
for input customizations and
glyphs, along with support for
MFi and third-party controllers.
Use the Accessibility plug-in
to improve accessibility
through system features,
like VoiceOver and Dynamic Type.
Integrate Apple's data-driven
rich haptic feedback system
with the Core Haptics plug-in.
Add advanced geometry-aware
spatial audio
with the PHASE plug-in.
Finally, use the Apple.Core
plug-in to manage build settings
and simplify the build process.
This initial set of plug-ins
will let you add
new gameplay mechanics,
make your games more accessible,
and help you more rapidly tap
into the latest features
and services.
I am extremely excited
to see the amazing games
you create with this new set
of Unity plug-ins.
Now, I'll get into the details
of the project.
First, I'll discuss the design
principles of the project.
Then, I'll cover project
concepts and organization.
Next, I'll offer
some key pointers
on interacting
with the project repository.
And finally, I'll go into detail
for each plug-in.
As you may know,
Apple frameworks encapsulate
functionality in a modular way.
This lets you pick and choose
the right technologies
for your apps while maintaining
compact, efficient code.
With the Unity plug-ins,
a similar pattern is followed;
each plug-in maps to a single
underlying framework.
This lets you pick and choose
the set of plug-ins
you want to use based upon
your game's needs.
Each plug-in exposes
C#-based Unity script,
which maps as directly
as possible
to the underlying framework.
Doing this means that any
familiarity that you might have
with the underlying framework
carries over to the plug-in.
Concepts, and in many cases
the framework API,
carry directly over.
Conversely, this also means
that by learning the plug-in,
you'll be implicitly learning
the underlying framework.
Another important detail
is that these plug-ins
are built as Apple platform
native libraries.
These libraries act as
the glue between the C# script
and the underlying
framework API.
Apple Unity plug-ins are
organized as Unity packages,
so managing their integration
to your project can be done
with the Unity Editor's
built-in Package Manager.
In some cases, plug-ins also
include additional Editor
functionality that makes working
with the plug-in even easier
and aligns with the Unity
inspector-driven workflows
that you're already
familiar with.
Of course, each plug-in
is paired with detailed readmes,
samples, and links
to additional resources,
such as associated Apple
Developer documentation.
Next, I'll briefly examine
some key workflow concepts
to help you get started.
The first step is to clone
the source from GitHub.
You can find all of the project
source and documentation there.
This is the starting point
for everyone who will be using
the Apple Unity plug-ins.
Once you've cloned
the repository,
building the plug-ins will be
one of your first tasks.
To simplify this process,
the repository includes
a Python script at
the repository root: build.py.
This script handles
building native libraries,
copying them
to the correct locations,
updating Unity meta files,
packing the plug-ins,
and building plug-in tests.
The script is organized such
that the simplest invocation
builds all of the plug-ins,
packages them into tarballs,
and saves them
to a build folder
ready for integration
into your Unity projects.
It's important to note
that fully building and packing
the plug-ins will require Xcode,
Python3, npm, and Unity.
Finally,
we have detailed documentation
for using build.py
in the project repository.
Now it's time
to dive into details
with each of the plug-ins.
For each plug-in,
I'll cover how to add them
to your Unity projects, a brief
overview of included features,
key scripting concepts,
and some code snippets
or examples
in the Unity Editor
highlighting how to integrate
them into your projects.
Let's start
with the foundational plug-in,
Apple.Core.
Apple.Core unifies build
settings for each plug-in into
a single preference pane within
Unity's Project Settings window.
Because you compile each
plug-in's native libraries,
Apple.Core also includes
an asset processor,
which ensures that each
plug-in library is configured
for the appropriate platform
on import.
When building your projects,
Apple.Core also contains
scripts that run as
a post-process to your build
to ensure that native libraries
are referenced correctly
in your intermediate
Xcode projects.
Because each plug-in interacts
with an underlying framework,
Apple.Core also defines
a handful of runtime inter-op
types, which ease data passing
between the C# script
and native code layers.
Finally,
Apple.Core is a dependency
for all other
Apple Unity plug-ins.
This means that Apple.Core
should be imported
into your projects before
any of the other plug-ins.
In this demo,
I'll show you how to import
the Apple.Core plug-in
into a new project
and briefly explore the Apple
Build Settings preferences.
Once the plug-ins
are built and packed,
Apple.Core can be imported
with the Unity Package Manager.
Just choose the option
to add package from tarball
and browse
to the packaged plug-in.
The Editor will then load the
package and compile the scripts.
Once complete,
Apple.Core is ready to use.
Apple.Core's primary
user-facing feature
is the addition
of the Apple Build Settings tab
in the Editor's
Project Settings window.
When you import
an Apple Unity plug-in,
all of it's available build
options will be visible here.
Out of the box,
Apple.Core comes with some
default configuration options,
such as minimum
supported OS version.
It's also useful to note
that you can disable
the post-process
build steps for any plug-in.
Finally, you can configure
common security settings,
which will propagate to your
intermediate Xcode projects.
Use the Game Center plug-in
to bring even more fun
and connection to your games
with Game Center,
Apple's social gaming network.
Game Center lets players
build an identity across
Apple platforms and enables
features like safe,
secure player authentication,
in-game achievements,
shared leaderboards,
challenges sent between players,
and multiplayer matchmaking.
You can pick and choose
which Game Center features
to integrate into your games,
but everything starts
with player authentication.
Add Game Center player
authentication to your game
and the Game Center widget
can feature your game
on the player's Home Screen
or within the App Store.
It also requires
very little code
to add player authentication.
The first step
is to add the Apple.Core
and GameKit plug-ins
to your project.
The GameKit plug-in connects
the Game Center service.
When authenticating, connect
with the Game Center service
and initialize
a GKLocalPlayer object.
Once initialized,
query for player restrictions
based upon
the local player's profile.
These restrictions include
limiting access to adult
or explicit content
for underage players,
limiting access
to multiplayer features,
or disabling
in-game communication.
A simple way to manage
a GKLocalPlayer
and it's interactions
with the Game Center service
is to define a component
within Unity.
Here, for example,
is a simple Game Manager
component definition.
This component holds
a reference to a GKLocalPlayer.
It also handles both
authentication and query
for player restrictions
in its start method;
player authentication
only needs to happen once
during the lifetime of the game.
This is the GameManager
component's script.
Here's the field for caching
a GKLocalPlayer.
Within the component's
start method
is the one-time call to
GKLocalPlayer.Authenticate,
a static method that returns
the GKLocalPlayer instance.
Once the local player
is successfully authenticated,
it's time to check
their player restrictions.
Checking player restrictions
in code
resolves to a series of
Boolean checks and can be added
to the try block in the
GameManager component's script.
True here means
your local player should have
limited access
to explicit content.
True here means
that your local player
should have a restricted
multiplayer experience.
And finally, true here means
that in-game communication
should be disabled.
And that's all
the code changes necessary
to add player authentication
to your game.
From here, there are two
additional steps necessary
to fully prepare your game to
take advantage of Game Center.
First, you'll need to add
the Game Center capability
to your intermediate
Xcode projects.
This is done from within
the Xcode project UI.
More information can be found
in the Apple Developer
documentation article
"Enabling and Configuring
Game Center."
Next, you'll need to add
Game Center features to your app
using App Store Connect.
Check out the App Store Connect
portal for more information.
With these steps complete,
you're ready to authenticate
players and ensure
a safe gaming environment.
Player authentication
only scratches the surface
of the features made available
by the Game Center Unity
plug-in.
To learn more about improving
discoverability of your game,
check out the session
"Reach new players
with Game Center dashboard."
To learn more about multiplayer
and matchmaking,
watch the "What's new in Game
Center" session from last year.
Controllers are the primary way
for players to interact
with the worlds
that you'll create.
Easily bring reliable and
flexible game controller support
to your games with
the Game Controller plug-in.
The Game Controller plug-in
brings a handful of features,
like support for game controller
customizations,
which allow players
to remap buttons
in one place for all games.
Button glyphs, to ensure
consistent user experience.
And support for all
MFi controllers,
as well as
third-party controllers
like select Sony
and Microsoft controllers.
Just as with the other plug-ins,
use the Package Manager
to add the Apple.Core
and Game Controller plug-ins
to your project.
With the Game Controller
plug-in loaded,
the first step is to initialize
the GCControllerService.
As we'll see shortly,
this service is how controllers
and their connection events
are accessed.
Once initialized,
query GCControllerService
for all controllers currently
connected to the system.
Connected controllers
are represented
by GCController objects
in the Game Controller plug-in.
For each GCController
that's connected,
poll for updated
controller state.
Polling can happen as little
or as often as is needed
by your game,
but a good place to start
is in Unity's
regular update loop.
Once controller state
is updated,
test for input
on each of the controller's
individual elements,
such as buttons, thumb sticks,
and so on.
Not to be forgotten,
controllers may come and go
during your game's lifecycle --
register callbacks
to handle controller connect
and disconnect events.
A quick way to get
the Game Controller plug-in
integrated is to create a simple
input manager component.
This component
has three key elements:
a container which holds
all of the currently
connected controllers,
a start method
for initialization,
and an update method
for handling polling
and testing for input.
First, let's take a closer look
at the start method.
This is a great place
to do all of the necessary
one-time setup tasks.
Initialization of
the game controller service
should happen here,
along with the initial check
for connected controllers
and registration of callbacks
for connection
and disconnection events.
Here's the input manager
component's script.
All of the one-time setup code
goes in the component's
start method, including a call
to GCControllerService.
Initialize().
Calling GetConnectedControllers
gets an enumerable container
of all the currently connected
controllers.
The final initialization step
is to register callbacks
for controller connect
and disconnect events.
Now that initialization
is complete,
the input manager also needs
an update method
in order to poll
each connected controller
to update input state,
and to handle input state
for each of the controller's
inputs.
To poll for input,
start by iterating
through the set
of connected controllers.
Call the
GCController's Poll method
to gather the latest state.
Then check each button state
and respond accordingly.
And that's a quick look at how to
use the Game Controller plug-in
to access connected controllers
and get controller input.
To get into more detail about
the Game Controller framework
and learn about topics
like third-party controllers
and nonstandard inputs,
check out prior years' sessions:
"Supporting New
Game Controllers"
and "Advancements
in Game Controllers."
Accessibility is about
making technologies available
for everyone.
Use the Accessibility plug-in
to integrate a wide range
of Apple's assistive
technologies
into your Unity-based games.
The Accessibility plug-in
gives you the ability
to add key features,
such as VoiceOver,
which can read programmatically
tagged content to your users;
Switch Control,
allowing for a wide range
of assistive input devices;
Dynamic Type,
to easily scale in-game text
and UI based upon
user preferences;
and UI accommodation
settings in order to adhere
to system-wide
accessibility preferences.
There's a lot to cover
with the Accessibility plug-in,
so I encourage you to check out
the session
"Add accessibility
to Unity games"
for a deep dive into the
Accessibility Unity plug-in.
In that session you'll not only
get examples and use cases,
but you'll also build
an understanding
of what's possible
with accessibility
on Apple platforms.
Be sure to check it out as soon
as you have the opportunity.
Adding haptic feedback
to your games is a great way
to increase immersion and
enhance the gameplay experience.
Integrate Apple's advanced
haptic capabilities
with the Core Haptics plug-in.
Use the Core Haptics plug-in
to build custom haptic patterns
from a set of haptic
and audio events.
Play back synchronized
custom audio and haptics.
Programmatically define
or update haptic feedback
by adjusting parameters
in real time.
Use the Apple Haptic and Audio
Pattern file format, or AHAP,
for a file-based approach
to designing and storing
your patterns as assets.
Tune your Core Haptics patterns
in the Unity Editor
with inspector support.
To get the most out of
the Core Haptics plug-in,
you'll need to understand
four fundamental elements
of Core Haptics and their
relationship to one another.
The highest-level element
is the CHHapticEngine.
The haptic engine represents
the link to the haptic server
on the device and is required
to play any haptic patterns.
The CHHapticEngine creates
CHHapticPatternPlayers.
Pattern players are used
for playback of CHHapticPatterns
with controls like start,
stop, pause, and resume.
A CHHapticPattern
is a logical grouping
of one or more haptic
and audio events.
The CHHapticEngine uses patterns
to create players.
CHHapticEvents
are the building blocks
used to define
a haptic experience.
Core Haptics
is a data-driven API,
which allows for haptic patterns
to be defined programmatically,
directly in your scripts,
or by leveraging AHAP files.
One easy way
to add Core Haptics support
to your projects is to create
a Haptics component
that manages each of the
necessary Core Haptics objects.
Here is an example
Haptics component
that contains a CHHapticEngine,
a CHHapticPatternPlayer,
and an AHAP Asset.
The AHAP asset
is a custom Unity asset
defined by
the Core Haptics plug-in.
This allows for easy import
and export to AHAP files,
as well as
a custom editor extension
to manage pattern creation
and customization.
Let's take a closer look.
I'll begin by ensuring
that both Apple.Core
and the Core Haptics plug-ins
are installed in my project.
With those added,
I can start enhancing my game
with haptics.
Here's the haptics component
that I've created
based upon the previous diagram.
We'll check out the
implementation in just a moment,
but for now,
I'll attach it to my airplane.
Once attached,
I now see that the component
requires an AHAP asset,
but my AHAP Assets folder
is empty.
I'll create a new one by going
to Assets > Create > Apple >
CoreHaptics > AHAP.
Once created,
I'll give it a fantastic
and original name:
MyHapticPattern.
The Core Haptics plug-in
comes with editor extensions
that let me tune my new pattern
right in the inspector window.
This is where I define
the CHHapticEvents
that are part of
the CHHapticPattern
that can be played.
By default,
there's a transient event,
but I can easily add
a continuous event as well.
There are also Import, Export,
and Reset buttons in the UI.
Reset clears any events
that I've added
and returns the pattern
to its default state.
Import and Export
are great features.
These allow your project to load
and save AHAP files.
Here I've imported a predefined
AHAP called Rumble,
which triggers
a nice vibration effect,
but I think it needs
to be tweaked just a little.
Now that I've updated
the pattern,
I can export it
to a new AHAP file
in order to share
this improved haptic pattern
with the rest of my team.
Now that my asset
is created and tuned,
I'll go back to my airplane
and point it to MyHapticPattern.
Great! Everything is wired up.
With the haptic pattern defined
and properly referenced,
all that remains
is to add some logic
to the Haptics component
so it can play a haptic pattern.
This can be divided
into two methods:
PrepareHaptics and Play.
PrepareHaptics is where the
haptic engine is initialized,
and the haptic pattern
player is created.
Play will simply call
the CHHapticPatternPlayer's
start method to begin playback.
And here's
the Haptics component script.
Fields are defined
for a haptic engine
and a haptic player.
Importantly,
add a serializeField attribute
to allow the AHAP asset
to be set in the editor UI.
Next, add the code to create
a CHHapticEngine, start it,
and create
a haptic pattern player
by accessing the AHAP directly
from the referenced asset.
Of course,
calling Start on the player
will play the haptic pattern.
The Core Haptics Unity plug-in
gives you the tools you need
to add an entirely new level
of immersion into your games.
Use the Core Haptics plug-in
to create magical game moments
that look, sound, and feel real.
For a deep dive
into Core Haptics,
check out the session
"Introducing Core Haptics."
For details on designing
engaging haptics experiences
be sure to watch "Designing
Audio-Haptic Experiences"
and "Practice audio
haptic design."
Immersive audio is an incredibly
important aspect
of great game experiences.
Use the PHASE Unity plug-in to
unlock your creative potential
and build lush soundscapes
into your game worlds.
With PHASE,
you can provide complex
and dynamic audio experiences
to your games.
Geometry-aware audio means
that sounds emanate from
and interact with
meshes in the scene.
Environments in your game
will sound more realistic
through reverberation
and reflection.
You can build hierarchical
audio graphs
that allow for dynamic audio
control during gameplay
The PHASE plug-in includes
a set of predefined components
that are game-ready.
Simply attach them
to your game objects
and you can start using PHASE
without writing
a single line of code.
The first component is the
PHASEListener component.
It acts as the "ears"
of your game scene
and processes audio based
upon its position, orientation,
and reverb preset.
Next is the
PHASEOccluder component.
PHASEOccluders
attach to game objects
with geometry data
and dampen audio
when they come between sources
and the listener in the scene.
Next is the
PHASESource component.
These are attached
to game objects
and use the object's transform
to position sounds
in your game world.
In addition to
the built-in components,
the PHASE plug-in also defines
a custom asset,
the SoundEvent asset.
Sound events are objects which
describe audio playback events
and define the audio played
by sources in the scene.
To start using
the PHASE plug-in,
the first step is to make sure
that both the Apple.Core
and PHASE plug-ins
are added to the project.
Once installed, I can start
adding the included components
to the scene.
In this example project,
I have three game objects
of interest:
an airplane, a building,
and then the camera.
First, I'll attach
the PHASEListener component
to the camera.
By doing that, I've added
the "ears" to the scene.
Next, I'll make
the building an occluder
by attaching
the PHASEOccluder component.
Finally, I'll add a source
to the scene by adding
the PHASESource component
to the airplane.
Now that I've added a source
it needs some audio to play,
so I need to attach
a sound event,
but the Sound Events folder
is empty.
I can create one by going to
Assets > Create > Apple >
PHASE > SoundEvent.
After creating a sound event,
the PHASE plug-in
will immediately open
the PHASE sound event
composer window.
This is the canvas
used to build sound events.
I start by right-clicking
anywhere in the window.
This shows a pop-up that allows
me to add a node to the event.
Because I want to play back
a clip I’ll create a sampler node.
I've already added an audio clip
of an idling airplane
to the project,
so I can reference that here.
I'll keep looping enabled
so that the airplane
keeps humming along.
To hear the airplane,
I need to route it to a mixer.
I can create a mixer
by dragging the output line onto
the event composer's canvas,
where it will show me
the option to create a mixer.
My sound event is now
complete and ready to use.
By clicking on the sound event,
I can see its settings
directly in the inspector.
This allows me to adjust values
without having to go back
into the sound event composer.
With the sound event created,
I can now reference it
in the PHASESource component
I attached
to the airplane earlier.
And with that,
audio in the scene is routed
and configured for playback.
The PHASE Unity plug-in
opens totally new possibilities
for in-game audio design.
To learn more about PHASE
and to dive deeper
into the concepts
I've introduced today,
be sure to check out the Apple
Developer documentation site
and last year's introductory
WWDC session video.
And that concludes our overview
of the new Apple Unity plug-ins.
I've covered a lot today,
but if you would like
to know more about any
of the Apple Unity plug-ins,
the repository on GitHub
is the best place to start.
That's where you'll find
the source,
detailed documentation,
and samples for each of the plug-ins.
Find out more
about integrating accessibility
into your Unity games with the
"Add accessibility
to Unity games" session
and be sure to check out
"Reach new players
with Game Center dashboard"
to learn how to boost
your game's visibility.
Thank you for watching.
♪