♪ ♪
Felix Acero: Hi, my name is Felix Acero,
and I am a Software Engineer
with the Security Engineering
and Architecture team.
In this video, I am going to show you
how you can use
the LocalAuthentication framework
to improve the authentication
and authorization flows of your app.
We will start by taking a look
at the generic concepts
of authentication and authorization
and how they apply to your application.
Then we will review
how the existing LocalAuthentication API,
and in particular the LAContext,
can help you implement a wide range
of authorization schemes.
And finally we will see how the new APIs
we are adding to LocalAuthentication
this year
can help you further streamline
your authorization code.
So let's start by talking
about authentication and authorization.
Authentication and authorization
are distinct
yet closely related security concepts.
On the one hand, authentication is the act
of verifying the identity of the user.
On the other hand, authorization is
the act of verifying whether a given user
is allowed to perform a specific operation
on a concrete resource.
Put together, we can see that,
since we first need to verify
that the user is who they claim to be
before we can evaluate
what resources and operations
are available to them,
we can say that authentication
in fact enables authorization.
To help illustrate these concepts,
let's look at a concrete example
involving a common security resource
managed by your applications,
such as Secure Enclave keys.
Secure Enclave keys are special types
of asymmetric keys
that are bound to a specific device
and which are protected
by a hardware-based key manager
that is isolated from the main processor.
What makes these keys special
is that when you store a private key
in the Secure Enclave,
you never actually handle the key
but instead instruct the Secure Enclave
to perform operations with it.
Secure Enclave keys can be associated
with access control lists
or ACLs for short.
An access control list specifies
the requirements that need to be satisfied
in order to perform specific operations
such as signing or decrypting a blob.
They can specify
when a given item is available,
for example after device unlock,
as well as the authentication requirements
needed to allow the execution
of certain operations.
For this example,
let's say that your app wants to protect
the sign and decrypt operations
of its key with biometric authentication,
while also ensuring
that the key is only available
after the device has been unlocked.
Now let's see how an authorization flow
would look like
for a sign operation involving this key.
First, your application issues a request
to sign a blob using the private key.
Then, after verifying
that your application can access the key,
the system proceeds to identify
the authorization requirements
for the sign operation.
In this case, the sign operation requires
a successful biometric authentication
from any of the currently enrolled users.
The system will then walk the user
through the biometric authentication
process via the standard UI.
Upon a successful authentication,
the system verifies
that all the remaining authorization
requirements have been satisfied
before finally performing
the sign operation
and returning a signed blob to your app.
Let's break down the main components
involved in this flow
to see how they fit
into our initial definitions.
First, we have a resource:
the Secure Enclave key.
Second, we have an operation
that can be performed with the key.
And third, we have a set of requirements
that, among other things,
specify who is allowed to perform
the operation
as well as the means of authentication
that should be used
to verify their identity.
Plugging the parameters of this example
into our definitions, we can see that
for authentication, the question
of whether this is the right user
is answered by means
of a biometric authentication;
while for authorization, the question
of whether the user is allowed
to perform a signature operation
using the private key
is answered by verifying the requirements
specified in the access control list.
Now that we have seen how this works
at a high level,
we can take a look at the way
a flow like this can be implemented
using the current API
of LocalAuthentication.
Let's start by quickly reviewing
the features offered by the LAContext,
which is one of the core components
of the framework.
An LAContext can be used to evaluate
the user's identity.
It handles user interaction when biometric
or passcode authentication is required.
And it also interfaces
with the Secure Enclave
to enable the secure management
of biometric data.
From this perspective,
the LAContext can be used
to support your authentication use cases.
The LAContext can also be used
in association with other frameworks
to support authorization flows.
For instance, you could use it
to evaluate access control lists
like the one we saw
in our previous example.
Let's take a closer look.
The first thing we need to do
is to get access the ACL
associated with our private key.
We can do this with the help
of the SecItemCopyMatching API
offered by the Security framework,
making sure that we provide the
return-attributes key inside of our query.
Once we obtain access
to the access control list,
we can evaluate it directly
using the LAContext
and the evaluateAccessControl API.
The biggest advantage that this approach
gives you is that it lets you decide
the right moment and the right place
in your application
to prompt the user for this authorization.
In this case,
since the access control list requires
biometric authentication
for the signature operation,
the LAContext will present
the familiar Face ID or Touch ID UI.
Once the ACL has been authorized
inside our LAContext,
we will be able to use it
as part of our query
for obtaining a reference to our key.
We do this by appending
the LAContext to our SecItem query
under the use-authentication-context key.
By binding the LAContext
to our private key reference,
we ensure that executing
the signature operation
will not trigger another authentication,
while allowing the operation to continue
without unnecessary prompts.
These binding also means
that no additional user interactions
will be required for future signatures
until the LAContext is invalidated.
The LAContext offers
a great deal of flexibility
and it lets you control
each of the steps and parameters
involved in your authorization flows.
It can be used in combination with other
frameworks such as the Security framework,
which in turn unlocks
a wide range of use cases.
This versatility, however, comes
at the cost of higher code complexity,
requiring you to carefully orchestrate
the APIs offered by several frameworks.
Depending on your use case,
the LAContext might be
the right tool for you,
especially if the main value proposition
of your app
requires low-level access
to keys, secrets,
contexts, and access control lists.
However, if all you need for your app is
a way of authorizing access to content
or a sensitive resource, then you may want
to trade off some of this flexibility
for a simpler API.
This brings us
to our last topic, streamline your app.
New to iOS 16 and macOS 13,
LocalAuthentication is introducing
a higher level, authorization focused API.
The new API builds on top of existing
concepts in LocalAuthentication
such as the LAContext and is geared
towards simplifying the implementation
of common authorization flows,
allowing you to focus all your energy
in the core value proposition
of your apps.
The most important abstraction introduced
by the new API is the LARight.
The simplest use case
you can give a LARight
is to help you authorize operations
on application defined resources.
For instance, you could use a right
to help you gate access
to the user profile section
of your application
by first requiring a successful
biometric authentication from your user.
By default, rights are protected by a set
of authentication requirements
that allow your users to authenticate
using Touch ID,
Face ID, Apple Watch,
or their device passcode
depending on the device they are using.
You can also choose
to associate your rights
with more granular requirements,
which allow you to further constrain
the means of authentication.
Let's have a look
at how we can use LARights in code.
The first thing that we need to do
is to instantiate our right.
We do this by specifying its requirements.
In this case, our login right will
require users to authenticate
using biometry
or providing the device passcode.
We then proceed to verify that the current
user can obtain the login right.
We use this information to determine
whether we can continue
with the login operation
or if instead we need to redirect
the user to the public section of our app.
Finally, we can proceed
with the actual authorize operation
providing a localized reason
that will be visible to the user
in the authorization UI.
When authorizing a right in this way,
a brand-new,
system-driven UI is presented.
The UI is rendered
inside your application window
and provides users
with relevant information
to help them understand
the origin and purpose of the operation.
We believe that the new look will
allow you to craft authorization flows
that integrate more seamlessly
with your application
and that provide more context
and information for your users.
Now that we have seen how to create
and authorize a right,
let's take a closer look at its lifecycle.
Rights start their lifecycle
in an unknown state.
As soon as your application issues
the authorize request,
the state of the right changes
to authorizing.
It is at this point that the user will be
presented with the authorization UI
that we saw in the previous slide.
Depending on the success or failure
of the operation,
the right may transition
to authorized or notAuthorized state.
This is the most important
state transition for your application.
Finally, the right can also move
from the authorized
to the notAuthorized state.
This occurs
when your application explicitly issues
a deauthorize request on the right,
or when the right instance is deallocated.
Be sure to keep
a strong reference to your right
in order to preserve its authorized state.
After a right has been deauthorized,
your application can continue
to issue authorization requests
to restart the cycle.
All the previous state transitions
can be queried and observed.
If you have access
to the LARight instance,
you can query its state property directly.
You can also observe all state transitions
using KVO or Combine.
Additionally, if your application
handles several rights,
you can observe the state of all them
from a single place
by listening to the didBecomeAuthorized
and the didBecomeUnauthorized
notifications,
which are published
to the default NotificationCenter
after a change
in the authorization state is detected.
Before we move on,
let's jump back to our example
and add a logout operation
to deauthorize our login right.
By doing this, we guarantee
that a new authorization will be required
the next time the user wants to log in.
So far, we have seen
how to use right instances
to authorize operations
on application-defined resources.
We have also seen how the lifecycle
and state of these rights
is ultimately tied to the runtime,
which means that on every session
of your application,
you need to instantiate
and configure these rights correctly.
So let's take a look
at how rights can be persisted
and what sort of possibilities
this enables for your app.
LARights can be persisted
with the help of the right store.
When persisted, rights are backed
by a unique Secure Enclave key
that is protected
with an access control list or ACL
that matches the authorization
requirements of the right.
This approach helps us ensure
that the authorization requirements
will remain immutable
after the right has been persisted.
You can also access the private key
that backs your right
and use it to perform
protected cryptographic operations
such as decryption, signature,
and key exchanges.
The corresponding public key
is also accessible
and can be used to perform operations
such as encryption
and signature verification.
Because this is a public key, you can
also export the bytes associated with it.
Private key operations are only allowed
after the right has been
successfully authorized.
In contrast,
public key operations are always allowed.
When persisting your right,
you also have a chance of storing
a single, immutable secret along with it.
The secret is also associated
with an access control list
that matches the authorization
requirements of your right
and it only becomes accessible
after the right has been authorized.
To summarize,
LAPersistedRights are created
with the help of the right store.
They are configured only once
and their authorization requirements
are immutable.
Because they are stored, they can be used
across different sessions
of your application.
Internally,
they are bound to a specific device
and are backed by a unique
Secure Enclave key
which can be used to perform
different cryptographic operations,
depending on the authorization status
of the right.
Finally, they can be used to protect
a single, immutable secret
that only becomes available
after the right has been authorized.
Now that we understand some of
the features offered by persisted rights,
let's see how they can help us implement
the scenario we discussed
at the beginning of the presentation,
where we wanted to authorize
a signature operation.
We start by instantiating a regular right
specifying its authorization requirements.
In this case, we want to ensure
that the right would only be granted
to users that have biometric enrollments
in the device
at the moment of the creation
of our right.
Therefore, we use
the biometryCurrentSet requirement.
We can then persist the right
with the help of the right store,
providing a unique identifier.
This identifier will be useful
the next time we need to fetch the right
in future sessions of our application.
Once the right is persisted,
we get immediate access to its public key
and can start performing
unprotected operations with it,
without the need
for an explicit authorization.
In this example, we are simply
exporting its public bytes.
Later on, when it's time to perform
a signature operation,
we can retrieve our right from the store
using the unique identifier we provided
during creation.
We can then proceed to authorize
the current user
through the authorize operation
on our right.
At this point, the system will walk the
user through the authentication process
and will verify that all the authorization
requirements are satisfied.
After the right has been authorized,
we can use its private key
to perform
protected cryptographic operations.
In this case, we are using the private key
to sign a challenge
issued by the backend server
of our application.
To wrap up, we talked about
the relationship that exists
between the generic concepts
of authentication and authorization,
and particularly how authentication
enables authorization.
We went over some of the features
offered by the LAContext
and how it can be combined
with frameworks such as Security
to unlock very powerful
and extensible authorization flows.
And finally, we looked into how
the newly added LARight
could help you streamline the code
to implement
certain authorization use cases.
We invite you take a look
at existing usages of LocalAuthentication
in your app and consider whether
some of the features we discussed today
can help you simplify your code
while still protecting
the privacy and security of your users.
Thanks.