♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, my name
is Karen Xing.
I'm an engineer
in the Camera Software team.
Welcome to
"Bring Continuity Camera support
to your macOS app"
To start this session
I will talk about,
what is Continuity Camera?
Next, I will discuss
how your application
can build an automatic
camera selection experience
with Continuity Camera.
And finally,
I will walk through the APIs
that are new in macOS 13
for Continuity Camera.
With Continuity Camera,
you can now use iPhone
as your webcam.
Setup is seamless;
just bring your iPhone
close to your Mac.
And it works wirelessly
so you can quickly join a call.
Your iPhone
will appear on your Mac
as an external camera
and microphone
under several conditions.
First, you must be running
macOS 13 and iOS 16.
Both Mac and iPhone must be
signed into the same Apple ID
using two-factor authentication.
For wired connection,
the phone needs to be
connected to Mac over USB.
Or for wireless connection,
the two devices need to be
in proximity
and have both Bluetooth
and Wi-Fi turned on.
Rather than talking through it,
let me show you right away
how magical Continuity Camera
looks on devices.
Here I have a MacBook Pro
and iPhone 13 Pro.
Both devices are signed in
to the same Apple ID.
The phone is placed on a stand
attached to my MacBook.
I will be joining
a video conferencing call
with my colleague Eric today
and show you how we can use
Continuity Camera in Zoom.
The app is launched using
the built-in camera first,
and then an onboarding dialogue
shows up
describing what you can do
with the new camera.
The dialogue shows up one time
after your Mac is upgraded
to macOS 13
when you open a camera
application for the first time
and there's an iPhone eligible
for Continuity Camera.
Hi, Eric!
Eric: Oh, Karen! Hi!
Karen: After the onboarding
dialogue is shown on the system,
Continuity Camera
and microphone devices
will become available
in all applications.
Let's switch to use this camera
and see how it looks.
Continuity Camera uses the rear
camera system on the iPhone,
so you get the same
great video quality
that you expect from iPhone.
And it works with all four
orientations of the phone.
The portrait orientation
gives you a more zoomed in
field of view compared
to landscape orientation.
Continuity Camera
also lets you do things
that were never before
possible with a webcam,
including several new
video effects.
You're probably already familiar
with Center Stage
and Portrait video effects
introduced in iOS 14.5
and macOS 12.3.
If not, I highly recommend
watching the
"What's new in Camera Capture"
session from WWDC 2021
to learn more about
system video effects
and how to interact with them
in applications.
Let's go to Control Center
and enable system video effects
on Continuity Camera.
Center Stage keeps you in frame
as you move around in the scene.
Portrait blurs the background
and naturally
puts the focus on you.
Portrait is only supported
on Apple silicon Macs,
but with Continuity Camera,
it is now available on all
Intel and Apple silicon Macs.
Studio Light
is a new system video effect
available on macOS 13.
It is supported
by Continuity Camera
when using iPhone 12 or newer.
Enable this when you want
to look your best on screen.
It provides a stunning
lighting effect
that dims the background
and illuminates your face.
Studio Light is perfect
for tough lighting situations,
like when you're
in front of a window.
Even though I'm showing you
each video effect separately
for a clear comparison,
all of them work well together.
And any combination
of the effects
can be applied at the same time.
Here's another exciting feature
I really want to show you
for Continuity Camera.
When you want to work together
and share what's on your desk,
you can now use Desk View.
The Desk View app
comes with macOS 13
and can be launched right here
in Control Center.
It works like an overhead
camera setup,
without needing
all the complicated equipment.
iPhone will split the Ultra Wide
camera feed in two,
showing off your desk and face
both at the same time,
so you can collaborate
on a school project
or teach a friend
a knitting stitch.
It leverages the extended
vertical field of view
of our Ultra Wide angle
camera,
applies perspective distortion
correction onto cropped frames,
and then rotates the frames
to create this Desk View.
You can use the share window
function available
in most video conferencing apps
to share this Desk View feed,
running in parallel with
the main video camera feed.
Desk View can also
be used alone
without streaming from the main
camera at the same time.
But when you do stream
from both Desk View
and the main camera,
we recommend enabling
Center Stage on the main camera
for a better framing
to capture face and body there.
The feature is supported
when the phone is placed
in either landscape
or portrait orientation.
The portrait orientation
provides the most versatility,
as there's a larger
vertical field of view.
There's also
a Desk View camera API
to provide customized
integration
suitable for your application.
I will talk about the API
in a moment.
During a video conferencing call
on your Mac,
we want you
to focus on the session
but we also want to make sure
you are not missing
anything important.
When Continuity Camera
is in use,
all notifications on your phone
will be silenced
and important call notifications
will be forwarded on your Mac.
Bye, Eric!
Eric: Bye, Karen!
Karen: We've just talked about
all the great experiences
available to users
without writing a single line
of new code in your application.
But with some adoption
of new APIs,
you can make
the Continuity Camera experience
even more magical and polished
in your app.
Now that most users will get
at least two camera devices
on the Mac,
we've thought more on how
cameras should be managed.
Prior to macOS 13, when a device
is either unplugged
or a better camera becomes
available on the system,
a manual selection step
is usually required
in applications.
We'd like to offer customers
a magical experience by
switching cameras automatically
in applications.
We've added two new APIs
in the AVFoundation framework
to help you build this function
in your app:
the class properties
userPreferredCamera
and systemPreferredCamera
on AVCaptureDevice.
userPreferredCamera
is a read/write property.
You will need
to set this property
whenever a user picks a camera
in the application.
This allows
the AVCaptureDevice class
to learn users' preference,
store a list of cameras
for each application
across app launches and reboots,
and use that information
to suggest a camera.
It also takes into account
whether any camera
becomes connected
or disconnected.
This property
is key-value observable
and intelligently returns
the best selection
based on user preference.
When the most recent preferred
device becomes disconnected,
it spontaneously changes
to the next available camera
in the list.
Even when there's
no user selection history
or none of the preferred devices
are connected,
the property will always
try to return
a camera device
that's ready to use
and prioritize cameras that have
been previously streamed.
It only returns nil
when there's no camera available
on the system.
systemPreferredCamera
is a read-only property.
It incorporates
userPreferredCamera
as well as a few other factors
to suggest the best choice of
cameras present on the system.
For example, this property
will return a different value
than userPreferredCamera when
a Continuity Camera shows up
signaling that it should be
automatically chosen.
The property also tracks
device suspensions internally
so it prioritizes unsuspended
devices over suspended ones.
This is helpful for building
automatic switching behavior
to change to another camera
if the built-in camera
gets suspended
from closing the MacBook lid.
Continuity Camera signals itself
to be automatically chosen
when the phone is placed
on a stationary stand
in landscape orientation,
the screen is off,
and either connected over USB
to the Mac
or within a close range
of the Mac.
In this scenario,
the user's intention is clear
that the device should be used
as Continuity Camera.
When adopting
systemPreferredCamera API,
you should always
key-value observe this property
and update your
AVCaptureSession's
video input device accordingly
to offer a magic
camera selection experience.
userPreferredCamera
and systemPreferredCamera
are already adopted
by first-party applications.
With more and more applications
adopting these APIs,
we will be able to provide
customers
a universal and consistent
method of camera selection
on Apple devices.
Let me show you a demo
to illustrate
how automatic switching
with Continuity Camera
looks like in FaceTime.
Here in FaceTime,
I'm in the
Automatic Camera Selection mode.
For applications
that want to offer both
manual and automatic behavior,
we recommend adding a new UI
for enabling and disabling
auto mode.
FaceTime is currently streaming
from the built-in camera.
When I pick up the phone
from the desk
and place it on a stand
behind the MacBook...
...FaceTime switches to stream
from the Continuity Camera
seamlessly.
That is where
the new class property
systemPreferredCamera
comes in:
the property value
changes to Continuity Camera
when the phone is in a position
ready to stream.
You might want to build your
application in a similar way.
Here's my recipe
for how to implement
Automatic Camera Selection
and manual selection mode.
When Automatic Camera Selection
is on,
start key-value observing the
systemPreferredCamera property.
Follow the systemPreferredCamera
whenever it changes
by updating your session's
input device.
In auto mode,
we highly recommend
still providing options
to let users pick a camera
by themselves.
When a different camera
gets picked,
set the userPreferredCamera
to that device,
which then gets reflected
in systemPreferredCamera
property value.
When Automatic Camera
Selection is off,
stop key-value observing the
systemPreferredCamera property.
Instead of following
systemPreferredCamera,
you will need to update
session's input device
with the user-picked camera
in manual mode.
But same as auto mode,
you still need to set
the userPreferredCamera
property
every time a user
picks a different camera,
so we maintain the user's
history of preferred cameras
and suggest the right camera
when getting back
to Automatic Camera Selection
mode.
For best practices on how to
incorporate userPreferredCamera
and systemPreferredCamera APIs,
please check out
the new sample app,
"Continuity Camera Sample."
Besides bringing a magical
webcam experience to the Mac,
Continuity Camera also presents
you with new opportunities
to harness the power of
iPhone-specific camera features
in your Mac app.
We've added a few
AVCapture APIs on macOS 13
to help applications
better utilize
Continuity Camera devices.
We're bringing the amazing
quality of iPhone photo captures
to macOS,
thanks to Continuity Camera.
First off, we support capturing
high-resolution photos.
Previously, macOS has only
supported photo captures
at video resolution.
Starting with macOS 13,
you will be able to capture
up to 12 megapixel photos
with Continuity Camera.
This can be enabled
by first setting
highResolutionCaptureEnabled
to true
on AVCapturePhotoOutput
object before starting
a capture session,
and then setting the
highResolutionPhotoEnabled
property to true
on your photoSettings object
for each capture.
In addition to capturing
high-res photos,
Continuity Camera supports
controlling how photo quality
should be prioritized
against speed
by first setting the maximum
photo quality prioritization
on the photoOutput object,
then choosing the prioritization
for each capture by setting
photoQualityPrioritization
property
on the AVCapturePhotoSettings
object.
To learn more about choosing
the right prioritization
for your application,
please check out
"Capture high-quality photos
using video formats"
in WWDC2021.
Another photo-related feature
is flash capture.
You can now set flashMode
on your photoSettings object
to control whether flash
should be on, off,
or automatically chosen
based on the scene
and lighting conditions.
We are also making
AVCaptureMetadataOutput
available on macOS to allow
processing timed metadata
produced by a capture session.
You can now stream
face metadata objects
and human body metadata
objects from iPhone.
Let's go through
how to setup a session
to receive
face metadata objects.
After setting up the session
with proper video
input and output,
you will need to create
an AVCaptureMetadataOutput
and call addOutput
to add it to the session.
To receive face metadata
in particular,
set your object types array
on the output
to include the face object type.
Make sure the metadata types
requested are supported
by checking
availableMetadataObjectTypes
property.
Then setup the delegate
to receive metadata callbacks.
After the session
starts running,
you will get callbacks
with face metadata objects
produced in real time.
Besides AVCapturePhotoOutput
and AVCaptureMetadataOutput
we just talked about,
Continuity Camera also
supports video data output,
movie file output,
and AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer.
Here's a list of video formats
supported by Continuity Camera
that you'll want to be aware of
when integrating this camera
into your application.
It supports three
16 by 9 formats --
from 640 by 480 to 1080p --
and one 4 by 3 format:
1920 by 1440.
You can choose between formats
supporting up to
30 frames per second
or 60 frames per second,
based on the need.
Another major addition
is Desk View device API.
Desk View camera is exposed
as a separate AVCaptureDevice.
There are two ways
you can find this device.
First one is by looking up
AVCaptureDeviceType
DeskViewCamera
in device discovery session.
Alternatively,
if you already know
the AVCaptureDevice object
of the main video camera,
you can use
the companionDeskViewCamera
property on that device
to access a Desk View device.
This API will be helpful
to pair main camera
and Desk View device
when there are
multiple Continuity Camera
devices around.
Once you have
the AVCaptureDevice object
of the desired
Desk View camera,
you can use it with an AVCapture
video data output,
movie file output,
or video preview layer
in the capture session
just as you can
with other camera devices.
Desk View device currently
supports one streaming format
in 420v pixel format.
The resolution of the format
is 1920 by 1440,
and the maximum frame rate
supported is 30 fps.
This is the end
of the session.
You learned about
Continuity Camera,
how to build a magical camera
selection on macOS,
and a handful of new APIs
to integrate Continuity Camera
in your Mac application.
I'm excited to see you
adopting all these APIs,
and have a great rest of WWDC.
♪