♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
♪ Suspenseful
classical music ♪
[FACETIME RINGING]
Ryan Williams: One call
can change everything.
>> Priya Shah: OK,
are you sure you have
everything you need
for this demo?
Because after I drop this
call, you're on your own.
Ryan: I’ve got this!
It's going to be a breeze.
It should have been a breeze.
I just had to choose one great
SharePlay experience
to kick off our talk
while my partner
got some well-deserved
shut-eye.
I narrowed the list of suspects
down but I couldn't choose.
I'd have to call in
my whole team
to help me make a break
in this switch case.
First up,
[SHAREPLAY NOTIFICATION CHIME]
a test run
with Adam in the gym.
>> [CLATTERING]
Adam: I'm so excited!
We're always so down
between the lines.
Siri: Burpee.
Adam: Calling functions,
[HEAVY BREATHING]
refactoring code.
[CLATTERING]
Siri: Butt kicks.
Adam: It's nice to hit Run
and check out
what people are building.
Siri: Rest.
[HEAVY BREATHING]
Ryan: Adam left me
inspired and perspired,
but I still had a few more
if checks to evaluate.
So I called Agnes
and Gav to shop around.
[SHAREPLAY NOTIFICATION CHIME]
But much as I like browsing
the toy market,
I wasn't ready
to make a bid just yet.
Maybe a piano break with Justin
would be the subroutine
I needed.
[SHAREPLAY NOTIFICATION CHIME]
♪ Somber piano music ♪
My thoughts were starting
to compile.
But first, I had one last
spy game to play.
>> Gav: Wow, here he is.
Olivia: We thought...
Adam: ...you thought...
Olivia: ...you might be
too overloaded.
[SHAREPLAY NOTIFICATION CHIME]
Ryan: My mother didn't
instantiate a quitter.
Let's go.
As we played, somewhere --
somewhere deep, a synapse fired.
The case was
a simple one after all.
I'd been looking for one
great app, but the truth is,
I learned something
from them all.
Not our usual demo, I know,
but forgive a man
a little virtualization
now and again.
Now if you'll excuse me,
I'm off to my next case.
All the great experiences
still waiting to be found.
♪ Suspenseful
classical music ♪
Hi. I'm Ryan, an engineer
on the SharePlay team.
Our team has had
a lot of fun exploring
all the incredible SharePlay
experiences you've made.
Your work has brought people
together like never before,
and we've also learned
a lot over the past year
about how you can give people
the best SharePlay experience
possible.
So today, we're going to take
you through how to design
and build a great SharePlay
experience in your app.
We'll talk about using SharePlay
as a new way to connect people.
Then we'll go over how to foster
a sense of presence,
breaking down the digital
barriers between people
and making them feel
like they're together
in the same space.
We'll go over the different
types of SharePlay experiences
you can design in your app,
and then finally, we'll tell you
some tips and tricks
we've learned along the way
for how to make it
a seamless experience
for people using your app.
More people than ever
are relying on FaceTime
and iMessage in order
to stay connected.
With iMessage, we connect by
sharing text or sharing images,
and with FaceTime, we connect
by sharing audio and video.
However, some of the most
meaningful moments
people have together
are about more
than just sharing
a conversation.
When we're together, we connect
most by sharing experiences.
So to foster that sense
of closeness,
we built SharePlay,
and by adopting the
Group Activities framework,
you can connect people
in this entirely new way
by allowing them to participate
in SharePlay activities
in your app.
It all comes down
to this concept of activities.
When someone in a FaceTime call
starts an activity,
SharePlay brings the
group directly into your app,
where you can create
almost any type of experience.
And an activity can
really be anything;
from cooking together,
to playing piano together.
We've seen a lot of
creative examples of activities
from you already.
And this year,
we focused on elevating
the core SharePlay experience,
making it even easier
for people to share experiences
in your app.
Now, people can start SharePlay
directly from your app.
When someone finds that perfect
piece of content in your app
that they want to share
with their friends,
they can choose who they want
to experience that content with
and invite them to SharePlay
directly from your app.
This way, people can jump
into a shared experience
with their friends whenever
it feels most natural for them,
without having
to plan in advance.
They'll even get the option to
start SharePlay from Messages,
letting them share an experience
with their friends
without needing to be
on a FaceTime call.
We think people are going
to love all the new ways
they can start SharePlay
from your app.
We'll go over how to adopt
all of these new features
in the session
"What's new in SharePlay."
And that just scratches
the surface
of what SharePlay can do
but we think the real potential
of SharePlay is unlocked
when you unleash your creativity
to build experiences
that bring people
closer together.
And a big part of that is
fostering a sense of presence.
So before we go into how
to build these experiences,
we first have to understand
what it means
to be present with others
and how to take aspects
of a great in-person
experience
and bring them into your apps.
Typically, digital communication
tools are designed to bridge
the gaps in presence,
but in order for SharePlay
to create meaningful moments
between people,
we need to find ways to actually
make people feel present
with each other, as if they were
in the same physical space.
Now, knowing how to foster
this sense of presence
can be different
for every experience
but one trick we can do
is to think about your app
being used
in the physical world.
So, here's an exercise
we recommend doing:
think of SharePlay like
a portal transporting people
through their phones
and into the same space.
What would they do with your app
if they were actually present
with each other?
If that sounds impossible,
don't worry.
We'll go over some ways
that you can foster
this sense of presence
in your own apps.
Let's do this exercise together.
Imagine you're transported
to a room
with a physical record player.
Everyone can go up to it
and interact with it.
They can put on
their favorite song
and once it's playing,
anyone else in the room
can also go up to the record
player and interact with it.
They can skip forward
in the song
or they can skip
the song entirely.
From this, we found
that we needed
to offer shared playback
controls in our app.
And in fact, it's critical that
we don't put any limitations
on who can interact
with these controls.
We want to create
an engaging experience
where everyone feels like
they're able to walk up
and control
that same music player.
OK, now someone has started
playing some music.
The next thing they might
do is look around
and see who's there
listening with them.
Now this may seem obvious,
but that person may be playing
their favorite song for someone
and probably wants
to be reminded of their friend
there listening with them.
When people are doing
these experiences
through their phones,
we need to find ways
to offer reminders
that there are others there
doing that experience
with them.
This exercise is a great way
to start thinking
about the design considerations
that will help
to foster presence in almost
any kind of experience.
Now, I'm going to hand it over
to Priya to talk through
some things to keep in mind
when designing your experience.
Priya: Thank you, Ryan.
When designing
an experience for groups,
the first thing to think about
is what shared activities
your app will support.
It might be challenging at first
since many apps
have been designed
with a single person in mind.
Apps have been personalized
to build engaging experiences
for individual people
but a great personalized
experience
might not always translate
to a great group experience.
Here is an opportunity for you
to think of your app
from a different perspective --
to think of an experience
designed specifically
for groups.
When designing your activity,
think about what people like
to do when they're together.
From cooking together
with your friends,
to breathing
through a yoga flow,
watching your favorite team
win the finals
or gasping at every
"Severance" cliffhanger.
All of these are good candidates
for SharePlay
because they're activities that
people love to do together --
in person!
SharePlay provides
the ability to create
rich coordinated experiences
for groups where everyone
has control and shares
the same experience in sync,
to help foster
a sense of presence
when people are apart.
For example, when using
SharePlay with Apple TV+,
pressing play on a video
enables everyone
to watch together.
Everyone's playhead is in sync,
and pause, play, seek commands
are all coordinated.
So when Ryan pauses
or Adam resumes,
the video pauses and plays
for everyone at the same time.
Apple TV+ is a great example
of a single-view
coordinated experience,
where everyone can watch
and listen to the same thing.
If you're building
a coordinated media experience
like this for your app, you can
add shared playback controls
by adopting
AVPlaybackCoordinator
and using the
coordinateWithSession method.
The system will keep everyone
in perfect sync
as if they were all in the same
room sharing one remote.
But sometimes,
we share activities
that participants
experience differently.
Some participants
might have different views
of the same coordinated
experience.
For example, when playing
a game of Heads Up!,
one person has to guess
the words on the screen
while their friends shout out
or act out clues.
Now, it wouldn't be
a very difficult game
if the guessers could see
the answers…
so there are two views
in this game,
and not all participants
see the same view.
If you're building a multiview
coordinated experience
like this, you can use
the send method
of the GroupSessionMessenger
class and specify the subsets
of the participants that should
receive the message.
So once you've decided on
the activity you are designing
and the views needed
to support it,
the next step is to build a
great experience for the people
interacting with your app.
Let's discuss some
of the factors
that can make your app's
SharePlay experience
intuitive and easy to use.
In order to build a great
SharePlay experience,
it is important to think
through the different stages
of a shared activity --
starting, during, and ending.
We've added the ability
to start a SharePlay session
without the need
for an active FaceTime call.
So people can start a SharePlay
session directly from your app
when they come
across content or an activity
that they want to share
with their friends.
This helps bring everyone
directly to the experience
you've created in your app.
When people browse your app
and come across something
they want to share
with their friends,
they might tap the Share button
to present the Share Sheet.
In order to surface the ability
to SharePlay here,
you can register your app's
group activity by using
the registerGroupActivity(_:)
method.
People will see the option
to SharePlay the activity
from your app directly
from the Share Sheet.
In order to make
group activities in your app
even more discoverable,
you can support the ability
to SharePlay directly
in your app's UI
with the SharePlay button.
To do this, you can adopt the
GroupActivitySharingContoller.
This allows people to start
a SharePlay session,
select the friends they want
to SharePlay with,
and whether they want
to SharePlay over messages
or FaceTime.
I'm going to go ahead
and SharePlay some music
with Adam and Ryan.
The system will
display information
about the group activity
to them, including the title,
an optional subtitle and image.
It's important that this
information is descriptive
so that Ryan and Adam
know what to expect
when they join
the SharePlay session.
So be sure to implement
the metadata property
for your group activity
with meaningful information
and return a
GroupActivityMetadata instance.
Also consider including
a web-based URL
for participants who might not
have your app installed
on their device already.
This will make it quick
and easy for them
to download your app and join
their friends in the activity.
It's important to remember
that just because someone's
on a Messages group
or FaceTime call
doesn't mean that they have
joined the group activity.
To find out who else
is participating
in the SharePlay session,
people can navigate
to the details view.
Looks like Ryan's
listening with me,
but Adam, who's on
the FaceTime call,
hasn't joined
the SharePlay activity yet.
When possible, you can also
show similar information
in your app's UI.
This is a great way to know
everyone is on
the same page as you.
It also helps maintain a sense
of presence with the group.
If you were all
in the same room,
you would know
how many people
were enjoying the activity
with you just by looking around.
Now we all have some friends
who are always fashionably late
to a party; so, depending on
your app's experience,
you might want to consider
supporting a lobby
where people can wait
for people to join
before beginning
the experience.
For example with Heads Up!,
once everyone has joined
the SharePlay session,
you can tap Let's Play!
to start the game.
OK, so we've covered
how to make starting
and joining a SharePlay
activity seamless.
Now let's consider how to create
an intuitive experience
during an activity.
As part of the ongoing activity,
everyone will be interacting
with your app
at the same time.
We have built a relationship
with our devices
that changes occur
as a result
of us directly
touching something.
But when you build
a shared experience
across different devices,
it's possible that things would
change on someone's screen
due to someone else's
interaction.
So when things change
during a SharePlay session,
it is important to let
everyone know why.
For example,
Ryan might pause the movie
the group is watching
on his device.
When Ryan pauses the video,
it pauses
for everyone else as well,
without any interaction
with their devices.
The system already handles
communicating changes
like these to the rest
of the group with notices
but, for some activities,
people may benefit
from in-app
contextual information
about what's going on
during the activity as well.
For example,
when using SharePlay
with the Flow app by Moleskin,
multiple people might be
drawing on the same page.
When someone draws something,
the app shows the initials
of who drew it,
and this makes for
a much more intuitive experience
for the entire group.
It also helps reinforce
the feeling of presence
with the rest of the group.
This is even more important
now that you can SharePlay
over Messages, where you may not
have continuous feedback
from your friends
over audio or video.
All right, so we've started
a SharePlay activity
with our friends.
We've made sure
everyone has joined.
Now, the focus is on
the activity itself.
You might have a fully-immersive
experience that supports
full-screen viewing and might be
hiding the status bar.
For example, the Apple TV app
hides the status bar
and other interface elements
when people are
watching a video
but…  it is important to remember
that the pill in the status bar
gives people access
to important controls.
So, let people redisplay
a hidden status bar
using a simple, discoverable
gesture to give them access
to these types of controls
during the ongoing activity.
In the Apple TV app, a single
tap shows the status bar again
and reveals important
experience controls in the UI.
It is also important to remember
that the activity
in your app's interface
is only one part
of the whole experience.
Think about how the people
using your app
will engage with
the rest of the group
during the SharePlay
experience you've built.
Whether they are on a FaceTime
call or texting over Messages,
people are multitasking
so there may be instances
when someone navigates away
from your app
while in a group activity.
For cases like this, remember
to support Picture in Picture
for coordinated
media experiences.
This will allow everyone
to continue watching
with their friends,
maintaining a sense of presence
with the rest of the group.
Whether someone is
responding to a message
or connecting with the group
over FaceTime,
the video doesn't have
to pause every single time.
Considerations like these
when building group activities
for your app
will help make
the end-to-end SharePlay
experience seamless,
breaking down
the digital barriers
to create meaningful moments
where people feel present
with each other.
So make sure to register
your group activity
so people can start to SharePlay
directly from your app;
configure descriptive metadata
so people know what to expect
when they join the activity;
have an experience
for late joiners,
and provide contextual
information
about why the UI
might be changing;
make sure controls
are easy to access;
and support Picture in Picture
for media.
We've talked about a lot today,
so let's do a quick recap.
Now, you can start a SharePlay
session directly from your app
without the need
for an ongoing FaceTime call.
This expands the opportunities
for building a variety
of group activities.
So we recommend
that you do the portal exercise
to start thinking about
how to design an experience
for your app
that helps people feel
like they're in
the same space together;
reimagine your app's
content and activities
to create great experiences
for groups;
and use best practices
when building your experience
to prevent digital barriers
from getting in the way.
We cannot wait to see
the creative uses of SharePlay
that you all come up with.
We hope you enjoyed the session.
Adam and Priya:
Thanks for watching!
♪