♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello, everyone.
I'm Jonathon Mah.
And I'm Lisa Xiao.
And we'd love
to introduce you
to what's new in Xcode 14.
Today, we'll look
at new features
and enhancements
throughout Xcode,
including source editing
and SwiftUI previews,
multiplatform applications,
TestFlight feedback,
and performance improvements.
There's a lot to cover,
so let's get to it.
The first thing you'll notice
is how much faster it is
just getting started.
Xcode 14 is 30 percent smaller.
It downloads and installs
significantly faster.
You can download additional
platforms and simulators
on demand.
If you need them immediately,
you can get them here --
or later, when you first
try to use them.
We're building Food Truck,
a food-delivery application.
SwiftUI with live previews
is a great workflow,
and it's getting even better.
Now the preview canvas
is interactive by default,
so your changes
are immediately live
as you make them.
The canvas has a new control
to create additional variants
of each preview
without writing any code.
You can vary the color scheme,
text size,
or device orientation,
and then immediately
see your interface
rendered in each scenario.
Let's see how our view looks
with different
Dynamic Type sizes.
With these previews
side by side,
it's easy to validate
your interface
and make sure
things look just right.
Let's check the larger sizes.
The first icon is very wide
and causes the text
to wrap awkwardly.
Luckily, my designer has
just asked me to change it,
but only in the header.
Our CardView doesn't support
a different icon
for the header yet,
so let's start by adding
that functionality.
I'll switch over
to the implementation.
The header and content elements
are both using the same image.
Let's add another image property
specifically for the header.
In most of the cards,
using the same image
in both places looks great.
We can save ourselves the time
of updating each existing call
by adding a custom initializer
with a default value.
When I start to type
the initializer,
Xcode 14 now offers to complete
the whole thing!
I can accept the default value
as a starting point
for my customizations,
saving a ton of time.
This also works
for the codable methods.
Let's give the headerIcon
parameter a default value.
Now, we'll return
to the CardStack view
and use this new functionality.
My designer asked me to use
the calendar symbol here.
The library now includes
all of the SF Symbols,
so it's easy to make sure
I'm using the right one.
I can press Return
to insert the right code
to use the symbol.
This symbol looks great.
The new side-by-side comparisons
we get from preview variants
make it easy to ensure
your app looks good
with all the settings
your users have chosen.
In addition to initializer
and codable definitions,
Xcode 14 provides more
intelligent recommendations
so you can write your ideas
more quickly and easily.
Let me show you some more.
When I start to add
another CardView,
the initializers now appear
directly in the completion list.
The headerIcon parameter
is in italic.
That's because
it has a default value.
If I accept the completion now,
it won't include
the headerIcon label,
it will use the default value
we just added.
Here, I want to specialize
the icon again,
so I can type part of the name
to opt in.
I'll give my new card
some values.
I'd like a divider
before my new card.
Adding a Divider to the VStack
gives a line across
the entire width.
To make it more subtle,
I'll use frame
to set a maximum width.
The frame modifier has
a lot of optional arguments.
The new completion features
make it a snap
to get just the arguments
I need.
That's code completion
in Xcode 14.
This first card's title
comes from a method.
I've heard it isn't handling
all numbers correctly,
so let's see
how it's implemented.
I'll Command-click and choose
Jump to Definition.
The redesigned definition list
highlights what's different
about each of the results
so that you can quickly
choose the one you want.
Since our text(for:) method
is from a protocol,
there are multiple options.
The list shows the specific
types that define the method:
we have the declaration
from the protocol
and two implementations.
I'll navigate to the
server-backed implementation.
This class implements parsing
using a regular expression
literal,
which is new in Swift 5.7.
My coworker told me
the problem is being caught
by our unit tests.
Let's run them now.
Yep, we have some failures.
Let's take a look.
Something seems wrong
with extracting the event count.
Let's check how this function
is called.
I can see that directly
by opening the callers
of this method
by Command-clicking.
Just like the definition list,
the callers list
shows the different files
and functions
that contain calls
to this method,
along with a preview
of each call site.
Here's a call
from the failing test method.
The preview shows me
the test is passing
the string "0 records",
which gives me a hint
about the problem.
And now I can spot the bug:
the regular expression is
matching against the digits 1-9,
but I forgot to include zero!
I could fix this by updating
the character range to use 0-9,
or switch
to the more descriptive
digit character class.
Something's still not right,
but now the compiler
is telling me why.
Regular expressions
are a first-class feature
in Swift 5.7.
The compiler checks
my regular expression
like it does with other code,
and Xcode highlights my typo
immediately.
Notice that when I correct
the expression,
two things happen:
syntax highlighting
in the regular expression
confirms my edit,
and the errors dim gray.
This new dimming
shows that Xcode
is reevaluating
the diagnostics.
When I pause for a moment,
the file is reprocessed
and Xcode confirms
the errors are resolved.
This dimming happens
during long builds as well,
so you can easily tell
which problems
are from the latest build
and which are from
a previous build.
Let's go over to the test.
This jumped me
straight to the call,
which is in the middle
of a test method.
Take a look
at the top of the editor.
Xcode 14 shows the definitions
containing the visible code,
even when they're
scrolled out of view.
I can use the test diamonds
at the top to rerun the tests.
Fantastic,
the fix passes all the tests.
With Xcode 14,
you can write code faster
with new code completions,
design fluidly with
SwiftUI preview variants,
be more informed with improved
error presentation,
and navigate confidently
with jump to definition.
And there's even more.
Here's Lisa.
Thank you, Jonathon.
Let's take a look at the build
performance improvements.
When Xcode
builds multiple targets,
like a framework
and application,
first it compiles
the framework sources.
Then it generates a module.
That enables linking
and compiling
the application sources.
And then it links
the application,
completing the build.
Xcode 14 rearranges your build
for improved parallelism.
By eagerly producing
Swift modules,
Xcode unblocks build tasks
and increases parallelism.
It shortens all the critical
paths of your builds,
all while being more respectful
of your simultaneous
use of the machine.
But we didn't stop there.
We also made the linker
up to two times faster
through increased parallelism.
All together,
Xcode 14 builds projects
up to 25 percent faster,
with machines
with the most cores
seeing the biggest
improvements.
Even with the improvements
to build scheduling,
sometimes your project can have
internal dependencies
on long synchronous tasks.
It can be hard to tell
this is happening
without a visualization.
Good news, we've included that
in Xcode 14!
You can open
the new build timeline
on any build log
or result bundle.
It will help you identify
unexpectedly long tasks
and bottlenecks.
Here's the build timeline
for Food Truck.
I can see a script phase
constraining the build
to a single core.
You can get critical insights
and identify performance
opportunities in your build
with the new build timeline.
You can learn all about
parallelizing builds,
the new build timeline.
and linking
in "Demystify parallelization
in Xcode builds"
and "Link Fast:
Improve build and launch."
Parallel testing in Xcode
has been a great way
to run your tests faster.
In Xcode 14,
it's even better.
We used the same techniques
to improve build performance
that I just showed you.
Xcode 14 eliminates
scheduling dependencies
between targets
and test classes
to increase parallelism
during testing even more.
If you have long-running tests
in different test classes
and targets,
this feature could improve
your test execution time
by up to 30 percent.
To learn about how to improve
test speed and reliability,
please check out
"Author fast and reliable tests
for Xcode Cloud."
Building is faster,
testing is faster,
and preparing your macOS app
for distribution is faster too.
We have sped up notarization
by four times in Xcode 14.
For projects using
Interface Builder,
I have more good news!
Document loading
is up to 50 percent faster,
and switching between
iPhones and iPads
in the device bar
is up to 30 percent faster.
Canvas editing operations
are incremental
and prioritize the scenes
you're looking at
so that it gives you
immediate feedback,
even in large storyboards.
Xcode 14 is faster,
and it's easier to use, too.
Let me show you how.
Xcode 14 makes it easy
to bring your app
to different platforms.
You can use a single target
to define your app,
and list what platforms
you support.
This eliminates the need to keep
settings and files in sync,
so you only have to describe
what's unique on each platform.
Check out "Use Xcode
to build a multiplatform app"
to take advantage of this
feature in your project.
Xcode also has great tools
for making your app smaller.
The memory debugger
has always been great
for exploring leaks
in your application.
It zeros in
on the shortest paths
from root objects
to unexpectedly live objects
so that you can investigate
why they've leaked.
Xcode 14 expands
these capabilities
so that you can see
all reference paths
in and out of an object.
In addition to a more
thorough explanation of leaks,
now you can gauge the total
weight of your objects.
In Xcode 14, you can also
extend Xcode itself
with Swift Package plugins.
Now packages
can integrate plugins
that process your code
in place,
like linters and formatters,
and you can invoke them
directly from
the project navigator.
You can also integrate
build tools that generate code
or process resources
while building.
For example, you could translate
a high-level description
of a remote procedure call
interface
into low-level glue code
during the build.
You could also compress
or optimize resources
while building.
For an in-depth look
at package plugins,
check out
"Meet Swift Package plugins"
and
"Create Swift Package plugins."
You can also localize
package resources
just like applications.
Now you can set your package's
default localization,
export the localization catalog,
translate it, and reimport it.
To learn more
about localization,
check out "Building global apps:
Localization by example."
Next, let's move on
to the run destination chooser.
Switching between devices
is something I do all the time,
and now it's even easier
to get the device you need
with the updated
run destination chooser.
Let's take a look.
When you open
the run destination chooser,
it shows all the available
run destinations
for the selected scheme.
I often switch between
an iPhone and an iPad.
The new run destination chooser
prioritizes recent choices,
which makes this
really convenient.
It's also easy
to select other devices
that I haven't used lately.
I can filter the list here,
and type "max" to bring
all the Max devices together
and easily pick the one I want.
These same features
are all available
in the Scheme chooser, too.
Next, let's take a look
at the Organizer window.
We've made some great
improvements to the Organizer
to help you identify new issues
and improve your apps.
There are two new reports
in the Organizer
to help you understand
how your app is doing
on your users' devices:
Feedback and Hangs.
Let's dive in.
The Feedback organizer shows
all of your TestFlight feedback
directly in Xcode.
Our TestFlight users sent
great comments and screenshots
for our recent builds.
The inspector shows
additional details --
like tester information
and the device configuration --
that can help to identify
the underlying problems.
If I need a bit more context,
I can email my tester
directly with this button.
TestFlight feedback
is from beta users,
but there are some issues
that can slip past testing
and make it into
the App Store.
One of the most common types
of bugs like this are hangs.
Your app hangs
when it uses the main thread
without taking a break
to process user input.
Your code might be doing
important work,
but the user experiences
an unresponsive app.
This new Hangs report shows
the highest-impact hangs
from App Store users
so that you know
which code to restructure
to have the biggest impact.
On the left,
there's a list of hangs
ordered by severity.
Each one has
a weighted backtrace
showing the problematic code.
Our app supports
many devices and OS versions.
Some hangs impact certain
configurations more than others.
In the inspector,
it is helpful
to find that this hang
happens mainly on iOS 15.3.
When I'm ready to work on this,
I can jump
straight into the code
with this Open in Project
button.
The new Hangs
and Feedback reports
help you triage issues
and get the right fixes
to users quickly.
To learn more about
fixing hangs,
check out "Track down hangs with
Xcode and on-device detection."
Next, let's take a look
at icons.
Our app icon
looks great at every size,
because we've taken the time
to pixel hint
and to choose the right number
of stripes for every resolution
so that it always looks crisp.
All of this pixel hinting
can be totally essential
for some icons
and unnecessary for others.
Now we have a new icon.
Let's take a look at it.
These simpler textures
don't need any hinting,
and will look great
drawn at any size.
With a double click,
I can select the new image.
In Xcode 14,
you can choose
the level of detail
that's right for you.
For this icon,
our single image looks great.
I'll use the new
Single Size feature
to tell Xcode
to automatically create
all of our different sizes
from this one.
To do that, I can select
Single Size in the inspector.
And that's it!
That was a brief overview
of what's new in Xcode 14.
It is faster and easier
to help you develop.
Thank you for watching!
Jonathan: Go download it
and get started today!
♪