♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Nadia Hussein: Welcome to WWDC!
I'm Nadia, and my colleague
Graham and I are so thrilled
to tell you about all the new
device management features
we have for macOS Ventura
and iOS and iPadOS 16.
In the world
of device management,
it's our shared responsibility
to enable employees
to thrive in the workforce
and increase
student-teacher productivity.
We're continuously developing
the tools and technology
to help foster
this collaboration.
And with macOS Ventura
and iOS and iPadOS 16,
there are many great
enhancements and features,
some of which
we'll cover in this session.
But first, I'd like
to briefly highlight
a few of the additional sessions
where you can discover
even more about the enterprise
and education space.
During WWDC 2021,
we introduced declarative
device management,
a new paradigm
for device management
that makes devices
more autonomous and proactive,
while allowing servers
to be lightweight and reactive.
This year we are expanding
declarative device management
with new platform support
and new features.
Be sure to watch the session,
"Adopt declarative
device management."
Apple Business Essentials
is one complete subscription
that seamlessly brings together
device management,
24/7 support,
and cloud storage.
With Apple Business Essentials,
small businesses can easily
manage every iPhone, iPad,
Mac, and Apple TV
every step of the way.
Check out the session, "Explore
Apple Business Essentials"
to learn more.
Managed device attestation
is a new security feature
that uses the Secure Enclave
to provide strong assurances
about a client device,
such as its identity
and software version.
Attend the session, "Discover
Managed Device Attestation"
for additional information.
In this session,
we're going to discuss
new capabilities
with Apple Configurator;
identity technologies
across platforms;
protocol modifications
to macOS Ventura,
iOS and iPadOS 16;
and an exciting change
to how we provide documentation.
Let's start with
Apple Configurator.
At WWDC 2021, we announced
Apple Configurator for iPhone.
Education and enterprise
customers
love having this solution
to take advantage
of automated device enrollment
for all of their Macs.
Apple Configurator for iPhone
makes it easy to add a Mac
purchased outside
of the normal channel
to their organization
in Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
In Setup Assistant on a Mac,
simply hold your iPhone
running Configurator
[CHIME]
over the animation.
The Mac will then
connect to the internet
and add itself
to your organization.
Version 1.0.1 brought new,
explicit support
for taking advantage
of existing network connectivity
if available on the Mac.
And we are excited to announce
that with iOS and iPadOS 16,
Apple Configurator for iPhone
can now also add
iPhone and iPad devices
to your organization.
This works just as you expect,
just like adding a Mac.
It's a great new alternative
to the version of this feature
in Configurator for Mac,
which requires connecting
each device via USB
to the Mac running Configurator.
A key difference
for iOS and iPadOS
is which pane in Setup Assistant
you scan.
On iOS and iPadOS,
that's Wi-Fi,
but on macOS,
it's country or region.
And remember, any device that
requires interactive activation,
such as activation lock
or cellular carrier activation,
must be handled manually
before adding it
to your organization,
just like Configurator for Mac.
Devices running iOS
or iPadOS 16
can be added using the version
of Apple Configurator for iPhone
currently in the App Store.
Now, lets cover
identity management
for business and education.
We know identity management
is important for the industry
and it's a key priority
for Apple as well.
It enables our users
to have a cohesive experience,
while ensuring
security of their data.
Our goal for identity
is for users to sign in once,
and from then on,
use that identity consistently
across the operating system.
We're working towards that goal,
and there's a lot of technology
that supports that,
including the new features
in macOS Ventura
and iOS and iPadOS 16.
For Federated Authentication,
Apple Business Manager
now integrates
with Google Workspace
as an Identity Provider.
This allows users to leverage
their work credentials
as Managed Apple IDs
for authentication to services
on iOS, iPadOS, and macOS.
And remember,
use Directory Sync --
which we've formerly
referred to as SCIM --
to create the user accounts as
Managed Apple IDs automatically.
Sign in with Apple can now
be used at work and school
with Managed Apple IDs.
In apps that support
Sign in with Apple,
this will just work!
If you want to control
where users can sign in,
you can choose to allow all apps
or add apps
to an explicit allow list
in Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
Learn more in the session,
"Discover Sign in with Apple
at Work & School."
Another notable
identity management update
is OAuth support.
In iOS and iPadOS 15,
we used a simple access token
authorization mechanism
to allow the MDM server
to verify the identity of users.
In iOS and iPadOS 16,
we are adding OAuth 2
as another authorization
mechanism.
OAuth opens the door
for MDM servers
to support a wide variety
of identity providers
already using OAuth today.
It also improves security
via its refresh token mechanism,
which allows a short-lived
access token to be used
in conjunction
with a silent refresh
that won't prompt the user
for credentials.
OAuth can be used
with the existing
account-driven
user enrollment flow,
but it provides an even better
user experience
when combined
with a cool new feature.
We call it
Enrollment Single Sign-on,
or Enrollment SSO.
It's a new, faster method
for personal devices
to complete an MDM enrollment
and access your organization's
apps and websites
with a single authentication.
This builds upon
a few existing technologies.
iOS 13 introduced extensible SSO
as a new way to configure SSO
for an organization's
apps and websites.
And iOS and iPadOS 15
introduced Account-Driven
User Enrollment,
which allows users
to enroll in MDM
by just entering their email
address in Settings.
To make enrollment even better,
we combined these
two technologies together
because we know BYOD devices
are an important part
of your deployment.
Users start out by entering
their email address in Settings.
They are then prompted
to download an app
from the App Store.
This app,
which contains
an Enrollment Single Sign-on
extension,
provides a native UI to perform
the authentication steps.
Because this is
an app-based model,
you can use any authentication
technology you choose.
As a user, sign in once.
The app will then sign in to get
you through the enrollment flow
without having to sign in again.
There are four main pieces
required to bring
Enrollment Single Sign-on
to life.
First, the app developer
updates their app
to support enrollment SSO.
Next, MDM vendors
federate MDM protocol
client authentication
with an identity provider.
Then administrators set up
Managed Apple IDs
using Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager
and finally, configure
the MDM Server to return a URL
to the JSON document
in the authentication response
headers.
Now that we've talked
about what this feature does
and who needs to do what,
let's dive into the details.
When the initial authentication
challenge from the server
is received, there will be
an HTTP header present
indicating that Enrollment
Single Sign-on is available
and should be used.
That header's value will be
a URL that the client will use
to download a JSON document.
The JSON document
contains all the details
the client needs
to continue the enrollment.
The value for
the iTunesStoreID key
must refer to the
Enrollment Single Sign-on app
to be used during enrollment.
The AssociatedDomains keys
are the same keys available
in ApplicationAttributes and can
be configured here as well.
Finally,
the ConfigurationProfile
should be a
Base64EncodedProfile
that contains at least
one Extensible SSO payload
and may contain certificate
payloads if needed.
And we'll be shipping
this feature for customers
in a later release of iOS
and iPadOS 16.
If you are interested
in developing an app
that supports this feature,
you'll need to apply
for a new entitlement
though the Apple
Developer Program.
However, you can start
developing for this now
using test mode.
This is a special version
of the Enrollment
Single Sign-on process
that allows you to test your app
before it's even offered
on the App Store.
To get started with test mode,
head to the Developer section
of Settings
and enable Enrollment
Single Sign-on test mode.
You'll then need to configure
your authentication response
with the new HTTP header
and the corresponding
JSON document.
Then, in VPN
and Device Management,
start the enrollment process.
During the enrollment,
you'll be prompted to install
the Single Sign-on app.
You can install the app
using any method available
from Xcode to TestFlight or even
Enterprise app distribution.
After that, return to Settings
and complete the enrollment.
To use test mode, there is
a different header required
in the response
and a modified JSON document.
Here's an example of the JSON
document for test mode.
You'll notice
the iTunesStoreID key
has been replaced
by the AppIDs key
and the value of this key
is an array of strings
containing the App IDs
that can be used for enrollment.
Everything else
remains the same.
Next, let's explore
Single Sign-on extensions.
In 2019, we added
Single Sign-On extensions
to iOS 13 and macOS Catalina
to enable identity providers
to use SSO authentication
for all the apps and websites
for their users.
When using SSO extensions,
the user is prompted
to sign in to the extension
after they've unlocked
the device,
which means entering
credentials twice.
If an organization also uses
the built-in Kerberos extension,
the user may have
to sign in again.
In many cases, these are all
identical credentials.
Well, in macOS Ventura,
we're introducing
Platform Single Sign-On --
or Platform SSO --
to enable users to sign in once
at the login window
and then automatically
sign in to apps and websites.
Platform SSO makes
tokens from the login
available to third-party
SSO extensions
and also works with the built-in
Kerberos extension.
The first login authenticates
with a local account password,
which also unlocks FileVault
encryption on the device.
This enables the user
to login when offline
or when connected
to captive networks.
From then on,
their identity provider password
can be used for unlock.
Additionally, Platform SSO
supports the use of a password
or a Secure Enclave backed key
to authenticate
with the identity provider.
And regardless of
the authentication method,
the SSO tokens are retrieved
from the identity provider,
stored in the keychain,
and made available
to the SSO extension.
Kerberos TGTs
can also be retrieved,
imported to a credential cache,
and optionally shared
with the Kerberos extension.
If the identity provider
password changes,
Platform SSO will validate
that new password
with the identity provider
on unlock.
Platform SSO is
a fully integrated protocol
that is built using OAuth
and OpenID
and does not use web views
for authentication.
Platform SSO is the modern
replacement for AD binding
and mobile accounts.
Note, it does not directly use
directory services,
or check with
the identity provider
for each unlock attempt.
Instead, the identity provider
is only called
when the user is attempting
to use a new password at unlock
or to retrieve SSO tokens.
Platform SSO also does not
prevent logging in to the Mac
based on the response
from the identity provider.
For that purpose,
leverage MDM
or alternative strategies
to disable access.
To take advantage
of this feature,
the identity provider needs
to implement the SSO protocol
and update their SSO extension,
then ensure the extensible SSO
profile is updated
to support the new keys
on managed devices.
Find more implementation
details
in the Apple Platform
Deployment guide.
To recap,
we've introduced integration
with Google Workspace,
Enrollment SSO,
OAuth support,
and Platform SSO,
to contribute to
a simplified sign-in experience.
Identity management is
an ever-evolving technology
and we are just getting started.
macOS Ventura brings many
enhancements across OS updates,
enrollment, and security.
Let's start
with software updates.
macOS Monterey introduced
fundamental changes
to Managed Software Updates.
My colleague Lucy
covered this in the session,
"Manage software updates
in your organization,"
where we break down
OS updates into three areas:
test, deploy, and enforce.
This year, we focus
on even more additions
to deploy and enforce.
Historically, all OS Update
commands would return a NotNow
when sent while in
Power Nap mode.
To ensure a more consistent
and robust
OS Update deployment process,
the device will now acknowledge
and respond to ScheduleOSUpdate,
OSUpdateStatus,
and AvailableOSUpdate
commands
even when the device is asleep
or in Power Nap mode.
Since we also understand
that sometimes administrators
want an OS update
as soon as possible,
we've introduced
a new key called "priority"
sent via the ScheduleOSUpdate
command.
Accepting a string value
of High or Low,
it controls
the scheduling priority
for downloading and preparing
the requested update.
Sending the command
with a High priority
will mimic as if the user had
requested the update themselves
in system settings.
Note that this key is only
supported for minor OS updates.
In macOS 12.3, we added
even more admin visibility
into the logs and reporting
with the OSUpdateStatus command.
DeferralsRemaining indicates
how many notifications are left
to prompt the user to update.
MaxDeferrals reveals
the total number of times
a user is allowed to defer
the OS update notifications.
NextScheduledInstall
is the date that the OS
will attempt to install
the update next.
And finally, PastNotifications
is the exact dates and times
when the notification
was posted to the user.
All of these updates
to the OSUpdateStatus command
will be useful
for administrators
to have further clarity into
the compliance of their users.
macOS Ventura
and iOS and iPadOS 16
are introducing a new mechanism
to ship critical security fixes
to users more quickly.
It does not modify the firmware,
and the user can also remove
the Rapid Security Response
if necessary.
We are introducing
two restriction keys for this.
Use allowRapidSecurity
ResponseInstallation
to disable this new
security response mechanism,
and use allowRapidSecurity
ResponseRemoval
to block the end user
from being able to remove
a Rapid Security Response.
Now, let's cover a couple
enrollment changes.
Automated device enrollment
provides a streamlined process
for the device to be
unboxed, activated,
and enrolled in the
organization's MDM solution.
In an upcoming release,
after erasing
or restoring a Mac,
an internet connection
will be required
to go through Setup Assistant
for devices registered
to your organization
in Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
Once the Mac is set up
for the first time
and connected to a network,
the Mac is acknowledged
as owned by an organization.
If later on, for example,
MDM initiates
an Erase All Content
and Settings
or the device is restored
with Configurator,
then the network --
and therefore,
device enrollment --
cannot be bypassed
in Setup Assistant.
Stay tuned with
the AppleSeed for IT
release notes for timing.
The profiles command line tool
has been a staple
for MDM deployments,
migrations, and reporting
in admins' tool kits
for many years now,
and we have an update to how
it works as of macOS Ventura.
Profiles tool will start
enforcing rate limiting
on macOS.
This will only be for
organization-owned
enrollment types
and to the show, renew,
and validate commands.
Each command has a maximum
of 10 requests per day
from the server,
and if that number is exceeded,
the results will return
cached information.
When you don't want to use
one of the 10 requests,
the show command
has a new, optional flag
to return cached information.
Refer to the profiles
manual page
for more detailed information.
In each release of macOS,
we continue to improve
protection capabilities
for our users.
Here are a few upcoming
security changes to be aware of.
In iOS 10.3,
we introduced a change
in the default TLS trust policy
for certificate payloads
to enhance overall protection
for our users.
In a future release,
we'll be bringing it to macOS,
meaning manually-installed
certificate payloads
will no longer be trusted
for TLS purposes,
unless the user grants them that
trust using Keychain Access.
Note, we will still continue
full certificate trust
if it's a certificate embedded
in an MDM profile,
but be sure to update
any workflows
if it involves interactive
certificate installation.
Next, "Allow accessories
to connect" on macOS
aims to protect our customers
from close-access attacks.
Supported on portable Macs
with Apple silicon,
the initial configuration
is to ask the user
to allow new Thunderbolt
or USB accessories,
even when unlocked.
Approved accessories
can connect to a locked Mac
for up to three days.
If you attach an unknown
accessory to a locked Mac,
you will be prompted
to unlock the Mac.
From an MDM perspective,
we understand this may
impact enterprise
and education workflows
such as bulk provisioning
or test taking.
To address this, we are
leveraging the same restriction
offered on iOS and iPadOS
for macOS.
The existing allowUSBRestrictedMode restriction
will allow wired accessories
to always connect
without any limitation.
It provides authorization
to bypass the requirement
of user consent.
Also remember,
this inherently makes
your user's system less secure,
so please only use
this restriction if you have
a legitimate business need
to do so.
For other restrictions
and payload modifications,
such as the new
allowUniversalControl
and UIConfigurationProfileInstallation,
be sure to check out
the documentation.
Thanks for listening
to the exciting changes
coming to macOS Ventura.
Now I'm going to hand it over
to Graham to talk about iOS.
Graham McLuhan: Thank you,
Nadia!
I'm really excited to be here
today to tell you about
a ton of great new
device management features
in iOS and iPadOS 16.
We know managing
network traffic on devices
is an important way to improve
the security of your data.
There are three main ways
that you can manage traffic
on Apple devices:
VPN, DNS Proxy,
and Web Content Filter.
For many years now,
we've offered per-app VPN --
and in fact,
for user-enrolled devices,
this is the only type of VPN
available to MDM.
In iOS and iPadOS 16,
we're expanding
our per-app offerings
to include DNS Proxy
and Web Content Filter.
These features will be available
on all enrollment types
but we think they'll be
particularly useful
for user enrollment
since this is
the first time organizations
can secure their app traffic
in this way for BYOD.
Configuring these new features
is a two-step process
that will feel very similar
to Per-App VPN.
Let's take a quick look
at how it's done.
First you'll need to add
a new key value pair
to each payload.
In the Web Content Filter
payload,
ContentFilterUUID.
And for DNS Proxy,
DNSProxyUUID.
There are a few things
to be aware of with these keys.
First, the values for these keys
can be any arbitrary string.
And second, when this key
is added to the payload,
it can only be installed
via MDM.
Now, we need to configure the
apps to use these new features.
Using either the
InstallApplication command
or the Settings command,
add the same UUID
to the attributes of the app
that will use
the per-app feature.
In this example,
we included both keys,
but you can just include
one or the other.
A few additional details
I'd like to point out.
First, app developers
don't need to do anything new!
All existing DNS Proxy
and Web Content Filter apps
will just work.
Second, you can have
multiple DNS Proxies
but you cannot mix system-wide
and per-app proxies.
And finally,
for Web Content Filters,
you can have up to seven
per-app filters
and one system-wide filter.
Next, I'd like to talk about
managing eSIMs.
eSIM has become
the new standard
for carriers around the world,
and over the last few years,
we've added
a number of MDM features
to make managing eSIM
easier than ever.
We wanted to take a moment
to talk about how MDM vendors
can bring all these features
together
to make for a better experience.
When we talk to organizations
using eSIM,
some of the primary tasks
they are doing
are provisioning new devices,
migrating devices
between carriers,
and supporting users
with requirements
such as multiple carriers
or traveling and roaming.
To accomplish these goals,
they need to query data
from enrolled devices
and provide that data
to carriers.
And second,
they need the ability
to install an eSIM on a device.
Let's begin by discussing
the device query
and carrier data requirements.
The DeviceInformation query
is the easiest way
to collect data from a device.
And in iOS 12,
the ServiceSubscriptions key
became the one stop shop
for collecting all data
relating to cellular
on iPhone and iPad.
A few points you may find useful
when looking at these responses.
Devices that return two items
in the ServiceSubscriptions
support two active
cellular plans.
If the response contains an EID,
it's an eSIM.
Newer devices like iPhone 13
and iPhone SE (3rd generation)
support dual active carrier
eSIM profiles
so it's possible to have
more than one eSIM
returned in the
ServiceSubscriptions response.
Note that the EID
is unique per device.
Starting with iOS
and iPadOS 16,
otherDeviceInformation
queries that return data
which also appear in the
ServiceSubscriptions response
are deprecated
and will no longer be returned
in a future version
of the operating system.
Now that we know
how to get data from the device,
let's take a look at what
we need to give to the carrier.
In general, they require
four pieces of data
to get an eSIM
set up for a device:
IMEI, EID, serial number,
and phone number.
Giving your admins
the ability to generate reports
containing all this data
will make it easier for them
to get up and running
with eSIM.
Let's pull this all together
and review
how eSIMs get provisioned.
First, the MDM server uses
the ServiceSubscriptions query
to collect the required data
from the device.
Then, the admin will send
that data to the carrier.
And finally, the carrier will
provision eSIMs for the device
on their eSIM server.
We can now shift our focus
to getting the eSIM
installed on the device.
The carrier will provide
the customer with a server URL
where devices
can fetch an eSIM
using the RefreshCellularPlans
command.
The MDM server will send
the RefreshCellularPlans
command to the device
which will initiate a request
to the carrier's eSIM server
and check if an eSIM
is available.
If it is, it will automatically
download and install it
without requiring
any user interaction.
The MDM server can then use
the ServiceSubscriptions query
to confirm that the eSIM
has successfully been installed
when the query returns
a nonempty phone number.
Now let's talk about
a few key points
that you should keep in mind.
eSIM installation
is a one-time operation
and future requests to install
an eSIM on the same device
require the carrier
to provision a new eSIM.
To prevent users
from accidentally
removing their eSIM,
use the allowESIMModification
restriction.
Also note that the
RefreshCellularPlans command
can install an eSIM when
the restriction is installed.
And finally, MDM could also
remove the eSIM
when erasing a device.
To avoid this, be sure to set
the PreserveDataPlan key to True
when sending
an EraseDevice command.
We hope this information
provides a more complete picture
on how to manage
and deploy eSIM.
Now let's talk about some
updates to Shared iPad.
Shared iPad is a great way for
education and business customers
to use iPad
in a one-to-many environment
while still giving users
a personalized experience.
This year we've made
a few changes
that will make Shared iPad
even better.
First, we added
ManagedAppleIDDefaultDomains
to the SharedDeviceConfiguration
Settings command.
With this command, you'll be
able to save users time
entering their Managed Apple ID
using the QuickType keyboard.
Once the user starts to enter
their Managed Apple ID,
a typing suggestion
for your domain name
will automatically appear
for the user to tap.
The Settings command
will accept a list of any size
but only three will be displayed
to the user.
Next, we've made
some changes
to the requirements
for remote authentication.
Currently, Shared iPad
requires remote authentication
approximately every seven days.
In iPadOS 16, Shared iPad
will only use local verification
for existing users
on the device.
If admins want to enforce
remote authentication,
they can set the
OnlineAuthenticationGracePeriod
key
in the SharedDeviceConfiguration
Settings command.
This key will be
an integer value that represents
the number of days
between remote authentications;
a value of zero
will require all logins
to be remotely authenticated.
Both the
ManagedAppleIDDefaultDomains
and OnlineAuthentication
GracePeriod values
can be retrieved via
the DeviceInformation query.
Finally, I wanted to help
provide some clarity
around Shared iPad quotas.
The SharedDeviceConfiguration
command
is the best way to manage quotas
on Shared iPad.
There are two relevant keys
that you can use to set quotas:
QuotaSize and ResidentUsers.
Regardless of which key
you choose to set,
ultimately the operating system
is computing a storage quota.
Let's take a look at an example.
This iPad has 35 gigabytes
of free space for user data.
If I send the SharedDevice
ConfigurationSettings command
asking the device
to set ResidentUsers to three,
it will compute each user's
quota to 11.67 gigabytes.
Alternatively,
if I ask the device
for a quota size
of 10 gigabytes,
each user will have
a quota of 10 gigabytes.
If we have three existing
users on the device
and a fourth user
tries to log in,
one of the existing user's data
will be removed from the device
to create enough space
for the new user.
In the QuotaSize example,
even though there was
five gigabytes of free space
still available,
that would not meet
the requirement
for the fourth user,
and therefore,
one user still needs
to be removed.
Let's look at one more scenario
where we see
how the number of users
can be adjusted on the device
without changing the quota.
When we started the scenario,
we had 35 gigabytes
of free space.
Well, it turns out that
25 gigabytes
of the total space on the iPad
was taken up by apps and books.
After doing a little research,
I realized that there's
a few apps on this device
that aren't being used
anymore.
Now that I've trimmed down
my app library,
my device has an additional
10 gigabytes of free space --
meaning when our fourth user
comes to log in,
it no longer requires
another user to be removed.
Also, remember that
as of iOS 13.4,
as long as there are no
cached users on the device,
quota sizes can be adjusted
at any time.
Keeping these points in mind
should allow you to ensure
the best possible experience for
your Shared iPad deployments.
Let's wrap up our iOS and iPadOS
updates with some MDM protocol
and behavior changes
that you should be aware of.
Apple devices come standard with
built-in accessibility features
that let people
experience everything
that their device has to offer.
Traditionally, each user
needed to enable
accessibility settings
themselves.
But in iOS and iPadOS 16,
we're adding the ability for MDM
to manage many of the most
popular accessibility settings.
These features include
Text Size, VoiceOver, Zoom,
Touch Accommodations,
Bold Text,
Reduce Motion,
Increase Contrast,
and Reduce Transparency.
With all these options
available,
we believe admins
can make devices in schools,
restaurants, and hospitals
more accessible for all users.
Be aware that these settings
are not locked after being set
and a user is free
to modify them
to match their own
unique preferences.
The MDM server
can also query these settings
with the DeviceInformation
query.
Next, starting in
iOS and iPadOS 16,
you'll now be able
to install applications
during the
AwaitDeviceConfigured state
during Automated
Device Enrollment.
A few things to keep in mind.
Is it is very likely
at this stage
no user will be signed in
to the App Store,
so we recommend using
device-based app licenses.
Unsupervised devices in Setup
will still return a NotNow
until they reach
the Home screen.
With this feature,
you can now ensure
a device has everything a user
needs to get started
before exiting Setup Assistant.
As we continue to improve
the security of our devices,
certain data types
become inaccessible
before first unlock.
Because of this,
the CertificateList query
will start returning a NotNow
before first unlock.
Once the user
unlocks the device,
the query will respond as normal
until the device is rebooted.
MDM developers,
please ensure that your servers
are able to handle a NotNow
response for this query.
And finally, we have an
exciting update for Apple TV.
Starting in tvOS 16,
when you erase an Apple TV --
either from Settings
or via MDM --
the remote will now
remained paired.
Combined with Auto Advance,
this ensures that your Apple TVs
are always refreshed
and ready to go.
In addition to everything
that we've discussed today,
there are even more changes
that you can check out
in our documentation
at developer.apple.com.
Speaking of documentation,
at a previous WWDC,
we brought the MDM documentation
to its new home.
This change brought
more accurate
and up-to-date documentation
but also gave you the ability
to highlight changes
in a particular OS release.
The reception to this
documentation has been amazing
and today I'm excited
to tell you that
we are making the source code
that backs this documentation
publicly available under
the MIT Open Source License
in the new device
management project
on Apple's GitHub page.
Let's take a look at what
you'll find when you arrive.
There will be two folders:
one containing all
of the MDM documentation
and one containing the new
declarative device
management documentation,
as well as a README file
and our license information.
Inside the MDM folder,
you'll find folders
for checkin, commands,
and profiles.
And for declarative management,
declarations, protocol,
and status.
When you dive
into these folders,
you'll find YAML files
for each command,
profile,
or declaration.
I'd like to highlight
a few items
to get you familiar
with these files.
First is the payload key.
This key shows the request type
for the MDM command.
In this example,
that's ProfileList,
which returns
a list of all profiles
installed on the device.
Next, supportedOS key
gives you platform-specific
information
like operating system
and version support,
as well as things like
if it requires supervision
or if it works
with user enrollment.
Here we find the ProfileList key
was introduced in iOS 4.
The payloadkeys
give you information
about additional features
the query offers.
Each sub-key may include
an additional supportedOS key
that will override the values
from the payload above.
The ProfileList query
was introduced in iOS 4,
but the ManagedOnly feature
wasn't added until iOS 13.
The rest of the supportedOS
information remains the same,
meaning supervision
is not required
and the query works
for user enrollment.
In the case of
the ProfileList query,
it returns a response
to the MDM server.
The response keys
detail this information.
In our example, we can expect
an array of dictionaries
that describe
each profile installed.
Inside that dictionary,
you will see key value pairs
including things
like PayloadUUID
and PayloadIdentifier.
This is just a quick example
and you will find
comprehensive details
about the schema and the
structure of the repository
in the README.
Now let's talk about
some details.
You will find data published
back to the initial release
of iOS 15 and macOS Monterey.
From there, we publish
new branches for each release
and seed as needed,
meaning that the iOS 16
and macOS Ventura
documentation
is up for you to check out
right now.
We think that there are
a lot of exciting use cases
for this new data
and we can't wait to see
what new tools or integrations
you come up with!
As you start to work
with this data,
please use Feedback Assistant
to let us know how it's going.
We've covered a ton
of information today,
so let's take a moment to recap.
Apple Configurator for iPhone
now adds iPhone and iPad
to your organization,
allowing you to more easily
manage and deploy devices.
For identity,
Google Workspace integration,
Enrollment SSO,
and Platform SSO
bring a more cohesive
authentication experience.
From there, Nadia told us about
how macOS Ventura
gives you more information
to help you
manage software updates
for your fleet.
Automated Device Enrollment
gets better by
requiring a network connection
during Setup Assistant
after erasing
or restoring a Mac.
And we wrapped up with
some important security changes
that will impact
your deployments.
In iOS and iPadOS 16,
you can now manage DNS Proxy
and Web Content Filter
on a per-app basis.
We explored the tools used to
manage eSIM on iPhone and iPad.
We discussed enhancements
to Shared iPad,
and finally,
changes to the MDM protocol
including the ability to install
apps during Setup Assistant.
Last, we hope that our new
machine-readable documentation
enables you to build new and
exciting tools and integrations.
Thank you for joining us
and I hope you have
a great WWDC!
♪