♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi everyone, I'm Holly
from the Swift Compiler team.
Welcome
to "Embrace Swift generics."
Generics are a fundamental tool
for writing abstract code
in Swift,
which is crucial for managing
complexity as your code evolves.
Abstraction separates ideas
from specific details.
In code, there are
a lot of different ways
abstraction is useful.
One form of abstraction
that you likely use all the time
is factoring code out into
a function or a local variable.
This can be really useful
if you need to use
the same functionality
or value multiple times.
When you extract the
functionality into a function,
the details are abstracted away,
and the code
that uses the abstraction
can express
the idea of what's happening
without repeating the details.
In Swift, you can also
abstract away concrete types.
If you have a set of types
that are all the same idea
with different details,
you can write abstract code
to work with all
of those concrete types.
Today, we'll walk through
the workflow
of modeling code
with concrete types,
identifying common capabilities
of a set of concrete types,
building an interface
to represent those capabilities,
and finally,
we'll dive into writing generic
code using that interface.
We'll dig into Swift's
abstraction tools
while building up some code
to simulate a farm.
So, let's start by writing
some concrete types.
We'll start with one struct
called "Cow."
Cow has a method called "eat,"
which accepts
a parameter of type Hay.
Hay is another struct.
It has a static method
called "grow"
to grow the crop
that produces Hay,
which is Alfalfa.
The Alfalfa struct
has a method to harvest Hay
from an instance of Alfalfa.
Finally,
we'll add a struct called "Farm"
that has a method
for feeding a cow.
The feed method
can be implemented
by first growing some
alfalfa to produce hay,
then harvesting the hay,
and finally,
feeding the hay to the cow.
And now, I can feed cows
on my farm.
But I want to add
more kinds of animals.
I can add more structs
to represent other animals,
like Horse and Chicken.
And I want to be able to feed
cows, horses, and chickens
on the farm.
I could overload the feed method
to accept each type
of parameter separately,
but each overload will have
a really similar implementation.
This will become
extra boilerplate
as I add more types of animals,
and it's mostly
repeated code anyway.
If you find yourself
writing overloads
with repetitive implementations,
it might be a sign
to generalize.
Fundamentally, these
implementations are so similar
because different types
of animals
are similar in functionality.
The next step is to identify
the common capabilities
between the animal types.
We've built a set
of animal types
that all have the ability
to eat some type of food.
Each type of animal will have
a different way of eating,
so each implementation
of the eat method
will have differences
in behavior.
What we want to do
is allow abstract code
to call the eat method
and have that abstract code
behave differently
depending on the concrete type
it's operating on.
The ability of abstract code
to behave differently
for different concrete types
is called "polymorphism."
Polymorphism allows one piece
of code to have many behaviors
depending on how
the code is used.
Appropriately, polymorphism
itself comes in different forms.
The first is
function overloading,
where the same function call
can mean different things
depending on the argument type.
Overloading is called
"ad-hoc polymorphism"
because it isn't really
a general solution.
We just saw how overloading
can lead to repetitive code.
Next is subtype polymorphism,
where code
operating on a supertype
can have different behavior
based on the specific subtype
the code is using at runtime.
Finally, we have
parametric polymorphism,
which is achieved
using generics.
Generic code uses
type parameters to allow writing
one piece of code
that works with different types,
and concrete types themselves
are used as arguments.
We've already
ruled out overloading,
so let's try to use
subtype polymorphism.
One way to represent
subtype relationships
is with a class hierarchy.
We could introduce
a class called "Animal."
Next, we'd change each animal
type from a struct to a class.
Each specific animal class
will inherit
from the Animal superclass,
and override the eat method.
Now, we have
an abstract base-class Animal
that can represent all
of our specific animal types.
Code that calls eat
on the Animal class
will use subtype polymorphism
to call the subclass
implementation.
But we're not done.
We still haven't filled
in a parameter type
for the eat method on Animal,
and there are a few other
red flags in this code.
First, using classes forced us
into reference semantics,
even though we don't need
or want any state to be shared
between different
animal instances.
This strategy
also requires subclasses
to override methods
in the base class,
but forgetting to do this
wouldn't be caught
until runtime.
But the bigger problem
with this model of abstraction
is that each animal subtype
eats a different type of food,
and this dependency
is really difficult to express
with a class hierarchy.
One approach we could take
is to have the method accept
a less specific type,
such as Any.
But this strategy relies
on subclass implementations
to make sure the correct type
was passed at runtime.
So, we've imposed
extra boilerplate
in each overridden method,
but more importantly,
it allows you to accidentally
pass the wrong type of food,
leaving you with another bug
that could only be caught
at runtime.
So, let's try something else.
We could instead express
the animal's feed type
in a type-safe way
by introducing a type parameter
on the Animal superclass.
This type parameter serves
as a placeholder
for the specific feed type
for each subclass.
With this approach,
the Food type parameter
must be elevated to the
declaration of the Animal class.
This seems a little unnatural
because though animals
need food to operate,
eating food isn't
the core purpose of an animal,
and a lot of code
that works with animals
probably won't care
about food at all.
Despite that, all references
to the Animal class
need to specify the food type.
For example,
each Animal subclass
needs to explicitly specify
its food type in angle brackets
in the inheritance clause.
This boilerplate at each
use site of the Animal class
could become onerous
if we added more types
that are specific
to each animal.
So, none of our approaches here
have good ergonomics
or the right semantics.
The fundamental problem
is that a class is a data type,
and we're trying
to convolute a superclass
to make it represent abstract
ideas about concrete types.
Instead, we want
a language construct
that was designed to represent
capabilities of types
without the details
of how the capability works.
Animals have
two common capabilities.
Each animal has
a specific type of food,
along with an operation
for consuming some of that food.
We can build an interface that
represents those capabilities.
In Swift, this is done
using a protocol.
A protocol
is an abstraction tool
that describes the functionality
of conforming types.
Using a protocol,
you can separate the ideas
about what a type does
from the implementation details.
The ideas about
what a type does
are expressed
through an interface.
Let's translate
the capabilities of an animal
to a protocol interface.
The name of the protocol
represents the category of types
we're describing,
so I called
this protocol "Animal."
Each capability will map
to a protocol requirement.
The specific type
of food will map
to an associated type
of the Animal protocol.
Just like a type parameter,
an associated type
serves as a placeholder
for a concrete type.
What makes
associated types special
is that they depend
on the specific type
that conforms
to the protocol.
This relationship
is guaranteed,
so each instance
of a specific type of animal
always has
the same type of food.
Next, the operation to consume
food will map to a method.
This method is called "eat,"
and it accepts a parameter
of the animal's feed type.
The protocol does not have an
implementation of this method,
and concrete animal types
are required to implement it.
Now that we have
the Animal protocol,
we can make each concrete
animal type conform to it.
You can annotate a concrete type
with a protocol conformance
at the declaration
or in an extension.
Protocols are not limited
to classes,
so we can use protocols with
structs, enums, and actors, too.
Once you write
this conformance annotation,
the compiler will check
that the concrete type
implements each
of the protocol requirements.
Each animal type must
implement the eat method,
and the compiler can infer
what the feed type is,
because it's used
in the parameter list.
The feed type can also
be written explicitly
using a type alias.
We've successfully identified
the common capabilities
of an animal and expressed
those capabilities,
using a protocol interface.
Now, we can start
to write generic code.
We can use
the Animal protocol
to implement
the feed method on Farm.
We want to write
one implementation
that works for all
concrete animal types.
We'll use
parametric polymorphism
and introduce a type parameter
that will be replaced
with a concrete type
when the method is called.
A type parameter is written
after the function name
in angle brackets.
Just like regular variables
and function parameters,
you can name a type
parameter whatever you like.
And just like
any other type,
you can reference
the type parameter
throughout the function
signature, using its name.
Here, I declared
a type parameter called “A”,
and I used A as the type of
the animal function parameter.
We always want
the concrete animal type
to conform
to the Animal protocol,
so we annotate
the type parameter
with a protocol conformance.
Protocol conformances can be
written in angle brackets,
or they can be written
in a trailing "where" clause,
where you can also
specify relationships
between different
type parameters.
Named type parameters
and trailing "where" clauses
are really powerful,
because they allow you to write
sophisticated requirements
and type relationships.
But most generic functions
don't need this generality.
Let's focus on
the feed method.
The type parameter A appears
once in the parameter list,
and the "where" clause lists
a conformance requirement
on the type parameter.
In this case,
naming the type parameter
and using the "where" clause
make the method look more
complicated than it really is.
This generic pattern
is really common,
so there's a simpler way
to express it.
Instead of writing
a type parameter explicitly,
we can express
this abstract type
in terms of the
protocol conformance
by writing "some Animal”.
This declaration is identical
to the previous one,
but the unnecessary
type parameter list
and "where" clause are gone,
because we didn't need the
expressiveness they provide.
Writing "some Animal"
is more straightforward,
because it reduces
syntactic noise,
and it includes
the semantic information
about the animal parameter
right in the parameter
declaration.
Let's break down
the some Animal syntax.
The "some" in "some Animal"
indicates that there is
a specific type
that you're working with.
The "some" keyword
is always followed
by a conformance
requirement.
In this case,
the specific type must conform
to the Animal protocol,
which will allow us
to use requirements
from the Animal protocol
on the parameter value.
The "some" keyword can be used
in parameter and result types.
If you've written
SwiftUI code before,
you've already used "some"
in result position
using "some View."
A result type of "some View"
is exactly the same concept.
In a SwiftUI view,
the body property
returns some specific
type of view,
but code that uses
the body property
doesn't need to know
what the specific type is.
Let's take a step back
to better understand
the concept
of a specific abstract type.
An abstract type
that represents a placeholder
for a specific concrete type
is called an opaque type.
The specific concrete type
that is substituted in
is called
the underlying type.
For values with opaque type,
the underlying type is fixed
for the scope of the value.
This way, generic code
using the value is guaranteed
to get the same underlying type
each time the value is accessed.
A type using the "some" keyword
and a named type parameter
in angle brackets
both declare an opaque type.
Opaque types can be used
for both inputs and outputs,
so they can be declared
in parameter position
or in result position.
The function arrow
is the dividing line
between these positions.
The position of
an opaque type determines
which part of the program
sees the abstract type
and which part of the program
determines the concrete type.
Named type parameters are always
declared on the input side,
so the caller decides
the underlying type,
and the implementation
uses the abstract type.
In general, the part of the
program supplying the value
for an opaque parameter
or result type
decides the underlying type,
and the part of the program
using the value
sees the abstract type.
Let's dig into
how this works,
following our intuition about
parameter and result values.
Because the underlying type
is inferred from a value,
the underlying type always
comes from the same place
as the value.
For a local variable,
the underlying type is inferred
from the value on the
right-hand side of assignment.
This means local variables
with opaque type
must always have
an initial value;
and if you don't
provide one,
the compiler will
report an error.
The underlying type
must be fixed
for the scope
of the variable,
so attempting to change
the underlying type
will also result
in an error.
For parameters with opaque type,
the underlying type is inferred
from the argument value
at the call site.
Using "some" in parameter
position is new in Swift 5.7.
The underlying type
only needs to be fixed
for the scope
of the parameter,
so each call can provide
a different argument type.
For an opaque result type,
the underlying type is inferred
from the return value
in the implementation.
A method or computed property
with an opaque result type
can be called from anywhere
in the program,
so the scope of
this named value is global.
This means the underlying
return type has to be the same
across all
return statements;
and if it isn't, the compiler
will report an error
that the underlying return
values have mismatched types.
For an opaque SwiftUI view,
the ViewBuilder DSL
can transform
control-flow statements
to have the same underlying
return type for each branch.
So in this case,
we can fix the issue
by using
the ViewBuilder DSL.
Writing an @ViewBuilder
annotation on the method
and removing return statements
will enable the result
to be built for us
by the ViewBuilder type.
Let's go back
to the feedAnimal method.
I can use "some"
in the parameter list
because I don't need
to reference
the opaque type
anywhere else.
When you need to refer to
the opaque type multiple times
in the function signature,
that's when a name type
parameter comes in handy.
For example, if we add
another associated type
to the animal protocol
called "Habitat,"
we might want to be able
to build a habitat
on the farm
for a given animal.
In this case,
the result type depends
on the specific animal type,
so we need to use
the type parameter A
in the parameter type
and the return type.
Another common place
where you need to refer
to an opaque type multiple
times is in generic types.
Code often declares a type
parameter on a generic type,
uses the type parameter
for a stored property,
and again
in a memberwise initializer.
Referencing a generic type
in a different context
also requires you to explicitly
specify the type parameter
in angle brackets.
The angle brackets
at the declaration
can help clarify
how to use a generic type,
so opaque types must always
be named for generic types.
Now, let's build out
the implementation
of the feed method.
We can use the type
of the animal parameter
to access the crop type
to grow
through the
Feed-associated type.
We'll call Feed.grow() to
get an instance of the crop
that produces
this type of feed.
Next, we need to harvest
the produce from the crop,
which we can do
by calling a method
provided by the crop type
called "harvest."
And finally, we can feed
this produce to the animal.
Because the underlying
animal type is fixed,
the compiler knows
the relationship
between the plant type,
the produce type,
and the animal type across
the various method calls.
These static relationships
prevent us from making
the mistake of feeding the
animal the wrong type of food.
If we attempt to use a type
that is not guaranteed
to be the correct food type
for this animal,
the compiler will tell us.
To learn how
the other farm protocols
were crafted to express
the relationship
between the animal-feed type
and its plant,
check out "Design protocol
interfaces in Swift."
Lastly, let's add a method
for feeding all the animals.
I'll add a method called
feedAll that accepts an array.
I know the element type
needs to conform
to the Animal protocol,
but I want the array
to be able to store
different types of animals.
Let's see if some Animal
can help us here.
With "some" there is
a specific underlying type
that cannot vary.
Because the underlying type
is fixed,
all of the elements in the array
need to have the same type.
So, an array of some Animal
doesn't express the right thing,
because I want an array that
can hold different animal types.
Here, we really
need a supertype
that can represent
any type of animal.
We can express
an arbitrary type of animal
by writing "any Animal."
The "any" keyword indicates
that this type can store
any arbitrary
type of animal,
and the underlying type of
animal can vary at runtime.
Just like with
the "some" keyword,
the "any" keyword
is always followed
by a conformance
requirement.
any Animal is a single static
type that has the capability
to store any concrete
animal type dynamically,
which allows us to use
subtype polymorphism
with value types.
To allow for
this flexible storage,
the any Animal type has
a special representation
in memory.
You can think of this
representation like a box.
Sometimes,
a value is small enough
to fit inside
the box directly.
And other values
are too large for the box,
so the value has to be
allocated elsewhere,
and the box stores
a pointer to that value.
The static type any Animal
that can dynamically store
any concrete animal type
is formally called
an existential type.
And the strategy of using
the same representation
for different concrete types
is called "type erasure."
The concrete type is said
to be erased at compile time,
and the concrete type
is only known at runtime.
These two instances of the
existential type any Animal
have the same static type,
but different dynamic types.
Type erasure eliminates
the type-level distinction
between different animal values,
which allows us to use values
with different dynamic types
interchangeably
as the same static type.
We can use type erasure
to write a heterogeneous array
of value types,
which is exactly what we want
for the feedAll method.
So we'll use an array
of any Animal
as the parameter type.
Using the "any" keyword
for protocols
with associated types
is new in Swift 5.7.
To implement
the feedAll method,
we'll first iterate
over the animal's array.
For each animal, we want
to call the eat method
from the Animal protocol.
To call this method,
we need to get
the specific feed type
for the underlying animal
at this iteration.
But as soon as we try
to call eat on any Animal,
we'll get a compiler error.
Because we've eliminated
the type-level distinction
between specific
animal types,
we've also eliminated
all type relationships
that depend on
the specific animal type,
including associated types.
So, we can't know what type
of feed this animal expects.
To rely on type
relationships,
we need to get back
into a context
where the specific type
of animal is fixed.
Instead of calling eat
directly on any Animal,
we need to call the feed method
that accepts some Animal.
Now, any Animal is a different
type from some Animal,
but the compiler can convert
an instance of any Animal
to some Animal by unboxing
the underlying value
and passing it directly
to the some Animal parameter.
This capability of unboxing
arguments is new in Swift 5.7.
You can think of unboxing as
the compiler opening the box
and taking out the value
stored inside.
For the scope
of the some Animal parameter,
the value has
a fixed underlying type,
so we have access
to all of the operations
on the underlying type,
including access
to associated types.
This is really cool
because it allows us to opt
for flexible storage
when we need it,
while still allowing us
to get back to a context
where we have
the full expressivity
of the static type system
by fixing the underlying type
for the scope of a function.
And most of the time,
you don't have to think
about the unboxing
because it just works
in the way you'd expect,
similar to how calling
a protocol method on any Animal
really calls the method
on the underlying type.
So, we can pass each animal
to the feed method,
where we can grow and
harvest the appropriate crop
to feed to the specific
animal at each iteration.
Throughout this process, we've
seen that "some" and "any"
have different capabilities.
With "some,"
the underlying type is fixed.
This allows you to rely
on type relationships
to the underlying type
in your generic code,
so you'll have full access
to the API and associated types
on the protocol
you're working with.
Use "any" when you need to store
arbitrary concrete types.
"any" provides type erasure,
which allows you represent
heterogeneous collections,
represent the absence
of an underlying type,
using optionals,
and make the abstraction
an implementation detail.
In general,
write "some" by default,
and change "some" to "any"
when you know you need
to store arbitrary values.
With this approach,
you'll only pay the cost
of type erasure
and its semantic limitations
when you need the storage
flexibility it provides.
This workflow is similar
to writing let-constants
by default, until you know
you need mutation.
In this session,
we walked through
the workflow
of generalizing code
as it evolves and gains
more functionality.
We started by writing
concrete types.
As the code gained
more functionality,
we noticed repetition between
different concrete types.
From there, we identified
common capabilities
and generalized them
using a protocol.
Finally, we wrote abstract
code using "some" and "any”,
and we discussed preferring
"some" for more expressive code.
To dig deeper
into crafting protocols
and understanding
type erasure,
check out "Design protocol
interfaces in Swift."
Thank you joining me
and have a great WWDC.
♪