♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
- Welcome to
"What's New in UIKit" in iOS 16.
I'm Dima, and I'm an engineering
manager on the UIKit team.
UIKit is the powerful framework
at the core of your apps.
It has been updated to support
new features in iOS 16.
In this video, I will cover
UI improvements for productivity,
Control enhancements,
API refinements,
and I will talk about exciting new ways
to use UIKit and SwiftUI together.
We made it even easier in UIKit to develop
streamlined, discoverable user interfaces
with improved navigation bars
that feature a new title menu,
find and replace,
and reimagined editing interactions
for cut, copy, and paste.
You will be able to enhance
your document-based applications.
I'll start by taking a closer look
at navigation bars,
updated to support desktop class
toolbar capabilities.
In iOS 16, UIKit introduces
two new navigation styles
to better support the needs
of document based apps:
browser and editor.
The browser style is designed for apps
that use history or folder structure
for navigation,
like web and document browsers.
The editor is intended for interfaces
centered around editing documents.
in iOS 16, you can add a variety
of bar button items to your app,
a subset of which will be displayed
in the center of the navigation bar.
By tapping the "customize toolbar" entry
in the menu,
items can be rearranged
by dragging to and from the items popup.
The resulting new configuration
persists across app launch.
To accommodate a size change,
for example,
when entering side-by-side mode
with another app,
the system automatically provides
an overflow menu
to access any items that don't fit.
We have added a title menu that works
with the new navigation styles
and supports a few standard functions:
duplicate, move, rename,
export, and print.
These are displayed in the menu
automatically
when the corresponding delegate methods
are implemented.
It's also possible to add
completely custom items to the title menu.
Additionally,
apps built with Mac Catalyst
take advantage
of the improved navigation bars
by seamlessly integrating with NSToolbar
with no additional code required.
iOS 16 introduces
new ways to manipulate text
consistently across various apps.
The first one is the new find and replace.
Conceptually, it is different
from the more high-level in-app search
that operates on data model objects
such as photos or calendar events.
Instead, find and replace
is purposefully built to work with text.
It only takes setting a flag
to activate the feature
for built-in UIKit views
such as UITextView and WKWebView.
Additionally, it seamlessly works
across multiple views and documents
that opted into this system.
Next, the edit menu
has received a major upgrade.
It now looks different depending
on the input method used.
On touch interaction,
you get a redesigned menu
that is more interactive.
When using a pointer,
you get a more full-featured context menu.
To provide both of these experiences
in a seamless way,
we've introduced UIEditMenuInteraction
as a full replacement for
the now-deprecated UIMenuController.
There is also new API
to insert actions into a text view's menu.
Watch "Adopt desktop class
editing interactions"
to learn all the details
on the new edit menu,
and learn how to adopt find interaction
for custom views.
There is one visual UI update
I'd like to cover.
In iOS 16, the sidebar in slide over mode
automatically becomes vibrant
without any additional code.
To achieve this, UIKit manages a set
of private views on your behalf.
Those are the new
productivity features in UIKit:
the new customizable navigation bars,
find and replace, editing interactions,
as well as the powerful title menu.
I am just scratching the surface here.
To learn a lot more, check
the "Meet desktop class iPad" session,
as well as a more in depth
"Build a desktop class iPad app,"
where you'll be walked through
improving a sample app
with new advanced
UIKit features in iOS 16.
Now I'm going to introduce
two new controls we've added
and discuss some enhancements
to UIPageControl.
The inline calendar style
of UIDatePicker is now available
as a standalone fully-featured component,
in the form of UICalendarView.
UICalendarView supports different types
of selection behaviors,
like optional single dates,
as well as selecting multiple dates.
On top of the available date range,
it also supports
disabling individual dates from selection.
Moreover, you can annotate
individual dates with decorations.
One major difference
between UICalendarView
and UIDatePicker is that
UICalendarView represents dates
as NSDateComponents,
rather than NSDate.
Unlike NSDate,
date components are a better,
and a more correct representation
of a date
whereas NSDate is a representation
of a point in time.
Because NSDateComponents
offer many flexibilities,
you should be very explicit
about which NSCalendar
the components are represented by.
Note that you should not make assumptions
about the type of the current calendar.
If you need the calendar to be Gregorian,
explicitly specify the Gregorian calendar.
To configure a Calendar view
like the one shown earlier,
first, create the Calendar view
and set its delegate.
To ensure that the Calendar is backed
by the Gregorian NSCalendar,
set the calendar property
on the calendarView
to a Gregorian NSCalendar.
Next, to configure
the multi-date selection.
Create
a UICalendarSelectionMultiDate object,
and set the selected dates property
on the selection object to existing dates
you have from your data model
to show in the Calendar view.
Then, set the selection object
to the calendar view's selection behavior.
To prevent the selection of individual
dates in the Calendar,
implement the
multiDateSelection:canSelectDate: method
from the calendar's selection's delegate
to control which dates can be selected.
Dates that cannot be selected will appear
greyed out in the calendar view.
To annotate individual dates
with decorations,
implement the calendar delegate's
calendarView:decorationForDateComponents:
Method.
For no decorations, simply return nil.
For a default grey circle,
return the default decoration.
You can also create image decorations
with options to customize its color.
And if you need more,
use the customView decoration
and return your view in the view provider.
Please note that the custom view
decorations do not allow interaction
and are clipped to the available space.
The page control is also improved.
We added the support for custom
indicator images for the current page,
so you can now choose different images
depending on whether the page
is selected or not.
Now you can also fully customize
both the orientation
and the direction of the page control.
Here is an example of configuring
a vertical page control
whose indicators change between
the current versus the non-current pages.
I set the page control's direction
to top-to-bottom
and set preferred indicator image
and preferred current indicator image
and that's it!
Apple is committed to protecting
user privacy and security.
In iOS 15,
when an application programmatically
accessed the pasteboard without
using system provided Paste interfaces,
a banner would appear to indicate
that the pasteboard was accessed.
New to iOS 16,
the system behavior has changed.
Now, instead of a banner,
we will display an alert that asks
for permission to use the pasteboard.
System paste interfaces
that the users interact with
provide implicit access to the pasteboard
and will avoid the alert.
If you have custom paste controls,
you can replace them
with the new UIPasteControl
that looks and behaves
like a filled UIButton.
It is enabled whenever the pasteboard
gets content compatible
with the control's paste target.
So those are
the new powerful UICalendarView,
the improved UIPageControl,
as well as
the security-oriented UIPasteControl.
Go ahead and try them out.
Now I'll walk you through some
API refinements we've made.
In iOS 15,
detents were added to sheets
which enabled building flexible
and dynamic UIs.
In iOS 16, we added support
for custom detents
so you can make sheets any size.
To take advantage of this feature,
use the new ".custom" detent
and specify the sheet's height
in points in an associated block.
You can return a constant value,
or a percentage of
the maximum detent height.
And you can also give your custom detent
an identifier
if you need to refer to it
from other APIs,
for example, to disable dimming
above your custom detent.
Note that the value you return
from the custom block
shouldn't account for
the bottom safe area inset.
This is so the same calculation works for
both floating and edge-attached sheets.
To learn more about customizing sheets
with system detents and other options,
watch the Customize
and resize sheets in UIKit video.
The sample code for that video
has also been updated
to show these new custom detent APIs.
There are new features
for SF Symbols in UIKit.
Symbols support four rendering modes:
monochrome, multicolor,
hierarchical, and palette.
UIKit would use monochrome rendering
by default
unless the symbol was configured
with a different rendering mode.
In iOS 16,
UIKit may render individual symbols
with a mode other than monochrome
if no rendering mode is specified.
Take these device symbols, for example.
In iOS 15 and earlier,
these symbols use monochrome rendering
if no rendering mode is specified.
In iOS 16, these symbols instead default
to hierarchical rendering.
Generally,
a symbol's default rendering mode
is the preferred way
to display the symbol.
So in this case, you should allow
the default hierarchical rendering
to take effect.
However, monochrome rendering
can be explicitly requested
with the new UIImage.SymbolConfiguration.
preferringMonochrome() API.
UIKit added support for variable symbols,
which allows apps to display
variations of a symbol
based on a value from 0 to 1.
Suppose an app wants to depict
the current volume level with a symbol.
The app can use
the speaker.3.wave.fill symbol,
which has been updated
to support variable rendering.
At a value of 0,
the speaker waves are faded out,
indicating the lowest volume level.
As the value increases up to 1,
the speaker waves progressively fill in,
indicating higher volume levels.
If a symbol supports variable rendering,
then apps can request
a version of the symbol
reflecting a value between 0 and 1.
Using variable symbols is straightforward.
You can get the regular
non-variable version of a symbol
with the standard SF Symbols API
on UIImage.
To get a version of that symbol
with a particular variable value,
simply add the variableValue parameter.
You can even mix variable rendering
with other rendering modes,
such as palette,
to further style the symbol.
Many system symbols now
support variable rendering,
and apps can update their custom symbols
to support variability as well.
To learn how to create
custom variable symbols,
check out the sessions
"Adopt variable color in SF Symbols"
and "What's new in SF Symbols 4”.
We've modernized UIKit to work
with new Swift Concurrency features,
including making immutable types
such as UIImage and UIColor
conform to Sendable,
so you can send them between the MainActor
and custom actors
without compiler warning.
For example, here we have
a custom actor called Processor,
and a view controller called ImageViewer
which is bound to the MainActor.
In the method sendImageForProcessing,
the ImageViewer sends an image
to the Processor actor for processing,
to make it fancy like adding glitter
and rainbows to it.
This is safe because UIImage is immutable,
so Processor has to make new copy
to add the rainbows and glitter.
Any code that has a reference
to the original image
doesn't show these modifications,
and a shared state
is not unsafely mutated.
Contrast this with UIBezierPath,
which is not Sendable
because it is mutable.
How cool is it that something
that could previously only be expressed
in documentation
can now be checked by the compiler?
To learn more about
Sendable and Swift Concurrency,
check out "Eliminate data races
using Swift Concurrency"
and "Visualize and optimize
Swift Concurrency" videos.
iOS 16 features new powerful support
for external displays.
The great news is that you don't have to
update your app to take advantage of this,
unless you are using old UIScreen APIs.
You can no longer assume
your app is on the main screen.
Instead, defer to more specific APIs,
like trait collection and UIScene APIs,
to get the information you need.
If your app is still not using UIScene,
there's now even more reason to upgrade
and to support multiple windows.
Self-sizing cells in UICollectionView
and UITableView got a major upgrade.
Now cells are also self-resizing!
In iOS 16, when the content
inside a visible cell changes,
the cell will automatically be resized
to fit the new content.
This new behavior is enabled by default,
and UICollectionView and UITableView
each have a new selfSizingInvalidation
property
that gives you control
over this new functionality.
Here is how it works:
When selfSizingInvalidation is enabled,
cells can request to be resized
by their containing collection
or table view.
If you're using UIListContentConfiguration
to configure cells,
the invalidation happens automatically
whenever the cell's configuration changes.
For any other cases,
you can call
the invalidateIntrinsicContentSize method
on the cell
or its contentView to resize the cell.
By default,
cells will be resized with animation,
but you can wrap the call
to invalidateIntrinsicContentSize
inside performWithoutAnimation
to resize without animation.
UICollectionView and UITableView
intelligently coalesce
size invalidation from cells
into a single update
performed at the optimal time.
If you're using Auto Layout in your cells,
you can opt-in to an even more
comprehensive behavior
by choosing enabledIncludingConstraints.
This means when a cell detects any auto
layout changes inside its contentView,
it will automatically call
invalidateIntrinsicContentSize on itself
so that the containing collection
or table view can resize it if necessary.
This makes it incredibly easy
to have cells
that automatically adjust their size
in response to content
or layout updates.
UIKit is powerful and flexible.
You can also take advantage
of the expressiveness
of implementing UIs using SwiftUI.
We've made it much easier to incorporate
both frameworks in the same app.
In iOS 16, there is an entirely new way
to build cells for your collection
and table views using SwiftUI.
This is made possible
by a new content configuration type
named UIHostingConfiguration.
With just one line of code,
you can start writing SwiftUI
right inside your cells--
no extra views
or view controllers needed at all.
Here is a simple custom cell
written in SwiftUI
using UIHostingConfiguration.
It is extremely easily
to build this cell.
Not only is this a great way to start
integrating SwiftUI into your app,
the expressive nature of SwiftUI means
there's never been a more powerful way
to build custom cells in UIKit.
There is a lot more to this topic,
so be sure to check out the video
"Use SwiftUI with UIKit" to learn more.
There are a couple of small but important
changes that you should be aware of.
To prevent users from being fingerprinted,
UIDevice.name now reports the model name
rather than the user's custom device name.
Using the customized name
now requires getting an entitlement.
Setting UIDevice.orientation
is no longer supported.
Instead, use UIViewController APIs
such as preferredInterfaceOrientation
to express the intended orientation
of your interface.
What's next?
Compile your app using iOS 16 SDK.
Test out the new features
such as text edit menus
and find and replace.
Adopt the new UIKit APIs
to use new enhanced controls
and productivity features.
And experiment with the new exciting ways
to incorporate SwiftUI in your UIKit app.
Thank you. ♪ ♪