[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
[ iPhone Silent Buzzes ]
>> I'm sure you're familiar with
that sound.
It's been part of our life for
years.
In 2019 though, I think we can
do better.
I'm Camille Moussette,
interaction designer on the
Apple design team.
>> And, I'm Hugo Verweij, sound
designer on the design team.
This session is about designing
great audio-haptic experiences.
Our goal, with this talk, is for
you to be inspired, and leave
you with practical ideas about
how to design great sound and
haptics when used together in
the right way, can bring a new
dimension to your app.
>> During the next 30 minutes,
we'll talk about three things.
First we'll introduce what is an
audio-haptic experience?
Then we'll look at three guiding
principles to help you design
those great experiences.
Lastly, we'll look at different
techniques, and practical tips,
to make those experiences great
and truly compelling.
>> So, what is an audio-haptic
experience?
Well, let's start by listening
to a sound.
[ High-pitched Sound Plays ]
OK, now let's lower the sound.
[ Sound Plays ]
What happens if I lower it even
further?
[ Sound Plays ]
Whoa.
It's so low I can't hear it any
more.
You know, our ears just don't
register it any more.
But, if you would put your
finger on the speaker, you could
still feel it move back and
forth.
We designed the Taptic Engine
specifically to play these low
frequencies that you can only
feel.
Here it is in the iPhone.
And, next to it, the speaker
module.
The haptic sensations from the
Taptic Engine are synchronized
to the sounds coming from the
speaker.
And, the result is what we call
an audio-haptic experience.
But, haptic sensations are meant
to be felt, so because we are
presenting this on stage, and on
screen, we need your help in
imaging what this would feel
like.
We'll do our best to help you by
visualizing the haptics like
this.
Or, by playing a sound that
resembles the haptic, like this.
[ Low Knocking Sound ]
We will also visualize these
experiences on the timeline, and
Camille will tell you some more
about how that's done in a quick
haptics design primer.
>> iOS 13 introduced a new API
for designing your own custom
haptics.
It's called Core Haptics.
This new API allows you
developers to use the Taptic
Engine fully in iPhone.
The Taptic Engine is capable of
rendering a wide range of
experiences.
It can generate a custom
vibration, like this.
Looks like this, and it should
sound and feel like this.
[ Humming Sound ]
So, as you've seen, we're using
a waveform and sound to
represent haptics.
As Hugo said, you need to
imagine this in your hand as a
silent experience.
This should be felt and not
heard.
So, we can play these continuous
experiences.
We can also have something
that's more shorter and compact.
It's a single cycle, and we call
this experience a transient.
It's much more momentary, and it
feels like an impact, or a
strike, or a tap.
[ Microphone Bump Noise ]
Very momentary.
And then we actually can refine
it further.
Moving forward, we'll use basic
shapes to represent haptics in
different patterns.
So, our transient becomes our
simple rectangle.
And, because our Taptic Engine
is an exceptional piece of
haptic engineering, we can
modulate the experience in
different ways.
First, we can modulate the
intensity or the amplitude.
We can also make it feel more
round, or soft.
At the other extreme, we can
make it more precise and crisp.
So, this experience is possible
with the Taptic Engine.
So, in the end, this completes
our quick introduction to haptic
design, and what the Core
Haptics API is all about.
We have one intensity you can
modulate, and another design
dimension, haptic sharpness,
that you are in control for two
types of event, continuous and
transient.
Now, let's look at the three
guiding principle that we want
to share with you today.
First is causality.
Then, we have harmony.
And, lastly we have utility.
These concept or approaches are
used throughout the work that we
do at Apple, and we think they
can help you as well in your own
app experience.
For each of them, we'll look at
the concept and explain through
a few examples.
Let's get started.
Causality: Causality is about,
for feedback to be useful; it
must be obvious what caused it.
>> So, imagine being a soccer
player, kicking this ball.
What would the experience feel
like?
[ Sharp Noise ]
There is a clear relationship,
an obvious relationship between
the cause-- the foot colliding
with the ball-- and the effect--
the sound of the impact and the
feel of the impact.
Now, what this experience sounds
and feels like is determined by
the qualities of the interacting
objects.
The material of the shoe, the
material of the ball, and then,
the dynamics of the action.
Is it a hard kick or a soft
kick?
And, the environment.
The acoustics of the stadium, or
the soccer field.
Because we are so familiar with
these things, it would not make
sense at all to use a sound that
is very different.
Let's try it out, and take it
way over the top.
[ Glass Shattering Noise ]
Very strange.
That doesn't really work.
Now, when designing sounds for
your experiences, think about
what would it feel and sound
like, if what you interact with
would be a physical object.
As an example, let's look at the
Apple Pay confirmation.
We wanted the sound and the
haptics to perfectly match the
animation on screen, the check
mark.
So, where do we start?
Well, what sounds do you
associate with making a payment?
What does money sound like?
And, what is the interaction of
making a payment, using Apple
Pay?
And, of course we have to look
at that animation of the check
mark on screen.
It should feel positive, like
confirming a successful
transaction.
Here are a few examples of
sounds that were candidates for
this confirmation.
This the first one.
[ High-pitched Noise ]
This one is very pleasant.
But, it sounded a bit too happy
and frivolous.
The next one worked really well
with the check mark of the
animation.
[ Bell-like Ding ]
But, we felt that its character
wasn't really right.
It was a little too harsh.
And then, there's this one, the
one that we chose in the end.
And, that you all know.
It's not too serious, and it's
clearly a confirmation.
[ Glassy Ding ]
OK.
So, we've got our sound.
Now, on to the haptics.
Our first idea was to mimic the
waveform of the sound because it
matches perfectly, but after
some experimentation, we found
that two simple taps actually
did a better job.
I like to see these as little
mini-compositions, where we have
two instruments; one that you
can hear and one that you can
feel, the haptics.
They don't always necessarily
have to play the same thing, but
they do have to play in the same
tempo.
Here they are together.
Notice the lower sound
indicating the haptics.
[ Glassy Ding ]
OK.
And, this is then the final
experience with the animation.
Again, imagine feeling the taps
in your hand when you pay.
[ Glassy Ding ]
>> Next, let's look at our
second guiding principle,
harmony.
Harmony is about things should
feel the way they look, the way
they sound.
In the real world, audio,
haptics, and visuals are
naturally in harmony because of
the clear cause and effect
relationship.
In the digital world, though, we
have to do this work manually.
New experiences are created in
an additive process.
The input and output need to be
specifically designed by you,
the developer.
Let's start with creating a
simple interface with the
visual.
We have a simple sphere dropping
and colliding with the bottom of
the screen.
Let's add audio feedback.
[ Hollow Bouncing Sounds ]
Now, we choose a sound that
corresponds to a physical
impact, or the bounce of the
sphere.
It needs to be short and precise
and clear, but we also modulate
the amplitude based on the
velocity of the hit.
Now, let's do additional work,
and introduce the third sense,
haptic feedback.
[ Hollow Bouncing Sounds ]
So, imagine feeling that hit in
your hand.
Again, we're trying to design in
harmony the sphere hitting the
bottom of the screen, so we
choose a transient event with
high sharpness.
We also modulate the intensity
to match the velocity of the
bounce.
We're not done yet.
Because it's really important to
think about synchronization
between the three senses.
That's where the magic happens.
That's where the illusion of a
real ball colliding with the
wall takes shape.
So, here's an example where we
broke the rules, and we
introduced latency between the
visual and the rest of the
feedback.
[ Hollow Bouncing Sounds ]
It's clearly broken, and the
illusion of a real bouncing ball
is completely not there.
So, harmony requires great care
and attention from you, but when
done well, can create very
delightful and magical
experiences.
Let's look at the different
harmony in terms of the notion
between interaction, visuals,
audio, and haptics.
In terms of qualities and
overall behaviors.
We'll look at a simple green dot
on screen that we'll animate,
and think through what kind of
audio, what kind of haptics,
make sense with that green dot.
So, if we add a snappy pop, or a
different pulse, what kind of
audio, or what kind of haptics
work with these visuals?
What if we have a large object
on screen?
Does it sound different?
Does it feel different than a
tiny little dot?
If we have different dynamic
behavior, different energy
level, a pressing, pulsating dot
that really calls for attention
might want different sound,
different haptics.
And, lastly, something that
feels calm, or like a heartbeat,
warrant different type of
feedback.
So, think about the pace, the
energy level, and the different
quality that you're trying to
convey in your app.
Design feedback that tells a
consistent and unified story.
>> I'll illustrate how the
harmony principle helps us with
designing sound and haptics for
the Apple Watch crown.
We were all used to our phones,
and their old-school vibes
coming from them, when the Apple
Watch came out as the first
device with a Taptic Engine.
It was the first device that
could precisely synchronize
sound and haptics.
For Series 4, haptics and a very
subtle sound were added to the
rotation of the crown.
Remember the sharp and precise
haptic that Camille described
earlier?
That was the one that we used
for the crown.
But, it was scaled down to match
the small size of the crown.
And so, the haptics are felt in
the finger touching the crown,
rather than on the wrist.
For sounds, we looked at the
world of traditional watch
making for inspiration.
We listened to and recorded all
kinds of different watches, some
of which sounded quite
remarkable, like this one.
[ Fast Ticking Sound ]
And then, there are other
physical-- mechanical objects in
the real world, with a similar
sound, like bicycle hubs.
[ Fast Clicking Sound ]
We wanted to find a sound that
would feel natural coming from a
device like this.
We took these sounds as
inspiration before we started
crafting our own.
And, this is the result.
On your wrist, it sounds very
quiet, just like you would
expect coming from a watch.
[ Regular Clicking Sound ]
The perfect coordination between
sound and haptics creates the
illusion of a mechanical crown.
And then, to match this
mechanical sensation, our motion
team changed the animation so it
snaps to the sound and the
haptics when using the crown.
Let's look at that.
[ Fast Clicking Sound ]
And, I'll play it again.
Look at the crown, visualizing
the haptics.
[ Fast Clicking Sound ]
The result is a precise
mechanical feel, which is in
perfect harmony with what you
see and what you hear.
>> Next, let's look at our third
guiding principle, utility.
Utility is about adding audio
and haptic feedback only when
you can provide clear value and
benefit to your app experience.
Use moderation.
Don't add sound and haptics just
because you can.
Let's look at a simple ARKit app
that we made to illustrate this
point.
In this app, we place a virtual
timer in the environment, and
the interaction is dependent on
the distance to that virtual
timer.
Let's look at the video first.
[ Fast Ticking Sound ]
So, in this app, we purposely
designed audio-haptic feedback
to complement the AR interaction
and the most significant part of
the user experience.
Meaning moving closer to the
timer, or moving away from the
timer, modulate the audio-haptic
experience.
The three senses are coherent
and unified.
We refrain from adding other
sound effects, or haptic
feedback, to interacting with
the different elements, or other
minor interaction in the app.
>> It is often a good idea not
to add sound in haptics.
So, start by identifying
possible locations in your app
for audio-haptic feedback, and
then focus only on the elements
where it can enhance the
experience, or communicate
something important.
And then, are you tempted to add
more?
Well, maybe don't.
It will overwhelm people, and it
will diminish the value of
what's really important.
So, to recap, here are the
guiding principles one more
time.
We spoke about causality.
How it can help to think about
what makes the sound, and what
causes the haptics.
About harmony.
How sound, haptics, and visuals
work together in creating a
great experience.
And, utility.
How looking at the experience
from the point of view of the
human using your app.
>> Next, let's look at the
techniques that-- and, practical
tips, that we can use with these
three guiding principle to
create great audio-haptic
experience.
First, a small recap about the
primitive available in Core
Haptics.
We have two building blocks that
you can work with.
The first one is called
transient, and is a sharp,
compact haptic experience that
you can feel, like a tap or a
strike.
The second one is a continuous
haptic experience that extend
over time.
You can specify the duration.
How long it should last.
For transient, there are two
design dimensions that is
available and under your
control.
We have haptic intensity, and we
have haptic sharpness, to create
something more round or soft at
the lower value.
And, something more precise,
mechanical, and crisp at the
upper bound.
Intensity changes the amplitude
of the experience as expected.
For continuous, we have the two
similar design dimensions.
We have sharpness and intensity,
and we're able to create more
organic, or rumble-like
experience that extends over
time, or something that is more
precise, and more mechanical at
the upper values of sharpness.
But, there are more many more
details and capabilities in the
Core Haptics API.
Be sure to check out the online
documentation.
>> Now, when designing sounds,
keep in mind what will work best
with these haptics.
For a sharp transient, a chime
with a sharp attack will
probably work really well.
[ Chime Sound ]
But, if we have a sound that's
much smoother, using those same
haptics is probably not such a
good idea.
[ Slow Chord Plays ]
So, for something like this, a
continuous haptic, ramping up
and down probably works better.
[ Slow Chord Plays ]
But, these are not hard rules.
There's a lot of room to
experiment.
And, sometimes, you may find out
that the opposite of what you
thought would work is actually
better.
And, this was the case for the
Apple Watch alarm that sounds
like this.
[ Bell Alarm Plays ]
For a sound like this, you may
want to add a haptic like this,
because it pairs together
perfectly.
[ Bell Alarm Plays ]
But, can we make it better?
Can we keep experimenting?
Maybe flip it around and change
the timing?
[ Bell Alarm Plays ]
This creates anticipation by
ramping up the haptics and then
quickly cutting it off and
playing the sound.
There's a clear action-reaction,
and the sound plays as an answer
to the haptic.
This works really well for the
Apple Watch alarm.
>> Next, it's pretty common to
have a number of events
back-to-back to convey different
type of experience.
In this case, we have four
transient event.
And, we notice that when we
present this to different
people, they don't necessarily
feel the first one.
We have the first ghost haptics.
[ Four Haptic Beats Play ]
So, the sequence of four taps is
actually reported as a triple
tap only.
This could be a problem, or an
opportunity.
We could use this effect of
ghost, or not perceiving the
first one completely, as a
priming effect.
Let's look at the example of a
third-party alert on watchOS.
This is the sound and the
haptics of that third-party
notification.
[ Alarm Plays ]
So, this is a really important
notification that we want to
make sure the user perceive and
acknowledge clearly.
So, in this case, we use our
ghost effect, or our primer in
this case, to wake up the skin,
and make sure that it's
completely ready to feel what's
to come.
Let's listen and feel it.
[ Alarm Plays With Haptic Beat ]
So, in this case, we have a
clear presentation and
recognition of our main
notification experience.
Next, we can also create
contrast between very similar
experiences.
Here is the sound for the left
navigation cue on watchOS.
It sounds like this.
[ Wooden Chimes Sound Plays ]
With our harmony guiding
principle, we end up with really
nice haptic that pairs really
well with that sound.
So, we have a series of double
strike, that sound and feels
like this.
[ Wooden Chimes Sound Plays ]
Now, if we look at the right
cue, we have a similar sound,
but slightly different.
[ Wooden Chimes Sound Plays ]
So we can notice the little
difference between the left and
the right on the audio, but if
we continue to follow our
harmony principle, with the
haptics we end up with the
identical pattern between the
left and the right experience.
In this case, we want to add
haptics-- we double up haptics
from the double strikes.
And then, we have true contrast
between left and right.
Let's listen and feel what--
this experience.
[ Wooden Chimes Sound Plays ]
Again, we have contrast between
the left and the right for very
similar audio experience.
>> So, by now, you have quite a
few tools to create your own
experiences.
We would like to show you one
more example to illustrate the
points we made.
This is a full-screen effect in
Messages.
[ Swooping Sound Plays ]
[ Fireworks Sound Effects ]
The sound and haptics are
perfectly synchronized to the
animation.
And, it's a delightful moment
for a special occasion.
Let's look at it one more time.
[ Swooping Sound Plays ]
[ Fireworks Sound Effects ]
Now, if you haven't yet, I
encourage you to try this out on
your own iPhone, to experience
the haptics yourself.
And now, a few more thoughts to
consider in addition to the
guiding principles that we
shared.
The best results come when
sound, haptics, and visuals are
designed hand-in-hand.
Are you an animator?
Collaborate with a sound or
interaction designer and vice
versa.
It's the best way to come to a
unified experience.
Imagine using your own app for
the very first time.
What would you like it to sound
like, or feel like?
And, then imagine using it 100
times more.
Does it still help you to hear
and feel these things?
Or, are you overwhelmed?
Experience it, and take away all
the things that don't feel
compelling, or that are not
useful.
And, don't be afraid to
experiment.
Try things out.
Prototype.
We've seen that you may just
come across something amazing,
by trying something new.
We're looking forward to seeing,
hearing, and feeling what you
will come up with in your own
apps.
See this URL for more
information.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]