♪ ♪
Hemant: Hi, I am Hemant,
a Commerce Developer Advocate
for the App Store.
I'm excited to discuss
App Store's tools to help you test
and validate
your in-app purchase experience.
I'll cover benefits
for each of these tools
and when it's best to use which.
I will also cover
all the great new features
we are introducing this year
for testing in-app purchases.
So let's get started.
App Store offers three tools
to help you test in-app purchases.
There is StoreKit Testing in Xcode,
where you can test in-app purchases
locally,
and then there's sandbox,
which uses products you have set up
in App Store Connect, and TestFlight
for performing end-to-end beta testing
and to gather feedback from testers.
These tools are available
to help you build,
test, and optimize
your app's in-app purchase experience.
I'll briefly describe each of these tools
to help you determine
the appropriate tool
for your in-app purchase testing.
Starting with StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
We introduced StoreKit Testing in Xcode
at WWDC20.
It enables you to test in-app purchases
without setting up your products
in App Store Connect.
You can test your in-app purchases
fully offline,
without requiring a server.
It provides you with the ability to create
and manage your in-app purchases
in the StoreKit configuration file.
So you can test your code changes
locally and in real-time.
As you began your StoreKit integration,
you can test
your in-app purchase experience
using simulator or a device.
You can build automations
to continuously test your in-app purchases
by using a dedicated
StoreKitTest framework.
In addition, you can sync
your in-app purchase products
from App Store Connect to Xcode.
This alleviates the need to set up
a StoreKit configuration file manually.
And you have ability to test
advanced subscription use cases,
such as offer code redemptions,
price increase sheet,
and subscriptions entering
and exiting billing retry,
all locally
without having any dependency on a server.
And one unique capability is
the flexible subscription renewal rates,
where you have option
to choose a rate that fits your needs,
from real-time to every two seconds.
And now we have new options available
with Xcode 15,
giving you a set of renewal rates
that are static
and independent
of the subscription duration.
So a monthly product or annual product
would renew at that same rate.
You can simulate StoreKit errors
that your app may encounter,
which will help you build
error handling into your app,
errors such as if a product
is not available for sale
or if a user cancels the purchase.
And now, if you are running
multiple instances of your app,
the transaction manager will display
transactions for each app instance,
allowing you to test on multiple devices.
Transaction manager has added the ability
to buy in-app purchases directly,
all without opening your app,
so you can test how your app handles
external transactions.
These new capabilities are available
with Xcode 15.
For more details,
please see WWDC23 session
"What's new in StoreKit 2
and StoreKit Testing in Xcode."
Now, let's take a look
at App Store sandbox.
The App Store sandbox enables you
to test and validate
your end-to-end
in-app purchase implementation
on both client and server.
This is important when building
and qualifying
your complete app experience
and ensuring you are successfully
delivering content to your users.
To test in-app purchases in sandbox,
your developer account needs to have
a paid application agreement.
You can test the app and in-app purchases
on a registered device
with your developer account.
To make a purchase in sandbox,
you'll first need to create
a sandbox Apple ID
in the Users and Access section
of App Store Connect.
To run your app on an iOS device
running iOS 16 or greater,
you will need to enable developer mode
in Privacy Settings.
The installed app is intended to be used
for development and testing.
Sandbox helps you validate your logic
to handle production-like scenarios
such as purchases, restores,
and subscription offer
and provides you confidence
to launch your app in production.
To test your app in sandbox,
you need a device,
and you can distribute your app
using two options,
such as you can tether
your device to your Mac
and download the app on the device
or using either of the distribution method
like Release Testing,
Debugging, and Custom
to generate an IPA file.
These methods help you deliver the app
for testing purposes
to your teams
without a need to provide source code.
We have been listening to your feedback
and we understand
sandbox is important to you
for testing the customer experience.
We continue to improve sandbox
and add new testing features,
and this year, we added support
to simulate scenarios
around involuntary churn
such as subscription billing
problem messaging
and billing grace period.
Later this year, we are releasing support
for testing Family Sharing
in-app purchases,
and we have added new options
to the iOS sandbox Account Settings page.
Let's deep-dive
into all of these features.
Billing problem message simulation
is available to you in sandbox,
and later this year, it will be presented
to customers in production
when they enter billing retry.
Billing problem messaging helps customers
to resolve the payment issue
without leaving your app
and stay subscribed
to your content and service.
The billing problem sheet uses
StoreKit 2 message API
with reason billingIssue.
The StoreKit message API
is displayed by default
when the customer launches your app
or brings it to the foreground.
Your can choose to defer
or suppress the message
by implementing a message listener
in views,
where a billing problem sheet presentation
might confuse the customer.
You can simulate the message API reason
billingIssue in sandbox
to test how your app handles
the message presentation.
To learn more about implementing
StoreKit 2 Message API,
please see WWDC22 session
"What's new with in-app purchase."
Now, let's review the steps for simulating
a billing problem message in sandbox.
To test billing problem message,
your sandbox Apple ID needs to be
subscribed to an auto-renewable
subscription with status active.
Then you can simulate billing issue
by navigating
to your sandbox account settings page
on device in App Store settings
and disable the switch
"Allow Purchases & Renewals."
Disabling the switch will simulate
billing issue for the Sandbox Apple ID,
and the existing auto-renewable
subscriptions will fail to renew
as per the configured
subscription renewal rate
and will go into billing retry state.
And when you navigate back to your app,
App Store will send
the billingIssue message
once the subscription fails to renew,
and the billing problem message
will appear.
When you tap the Continue button,
it will open the iOS sandbox
Account Settings page,
and you can now toggle ON
the "Allow Purchases & Renewals" switch
to successfully renew the subscription.
Once the subscription renews successfully,
you will no longer get
the billing problem message.
This helps you simulate a customer
recovering from billing issue
without leaving your app when they update
their payment method for their Apple ID.
Enabling grace period allows customers
to retain full access
to your app's paid content and service
while Apple attempts
to collect the payment.
This also helps you as a developer
to avoid interruption
to your paid days of service
if an auto-renewable subscription
is recovered within the grace period.
To enable and simulate
billing grace period in sandbox,
navigate to your App Subscriptions section
in App Store Connect.
In the Billing Grace Period section,
click "Set Up Billing Grace Period."
This will open a dialog,
which will allow you to configure
billing grace period for your app.
You can than select
from available grace period durations.
Remember, these durations apply
to production only,
so when testing in sandbox,
the duration of billing retry
and billing grace period are pre-set
according to your sandbox account's
renewal rate.
You can also select
the eligible subscriber
for billing grace period
and select the environment.
You can choose to enable it
first in sandbox
or choose to enable
in both sandbox and production,
then click Confirm.
You'll see your selection visible
in App Store Connect.
And now let's discuss Family Sharing.
Family Sharing is a powerful tool
that makes it easy for customers
to share their digital purchases
with their family members.
Enabling Family Sharing
for your auto-renewable subscriptions
and non-consumable products
can help you attract new customers,
increase user engagement,
and improve retention.
We wanted to provide you
with an ability to test
Family Sharing in-app purchases
in sandbox.
To test Family Sharing in sandbox,
you will need to log in
to App Store Connect
and navigate to the subscription
or non-consumable products
for which you need to enable
Family Sharing.
Then you will need to organize
sandbox Family Sharing Members
in App Store Connect.
And lastly, make a purchase
with your sandbox Apple ID
which is enabled for Family Sharing.
Let's walk through the testing details.
Once you have enabled
your in-app purchase product
to be family-sharable,
you can now navigate
to "User and Access" section
of App Store Connect,
and there, you will see a new section
labelled "Family Sharing."
In that section, you will be able
to organize and view
your sandbox family members
for a storefront.
Let's illustrate what the in-app purchase
experience looks like in sandbox.
Here, you initiate a purchase on device,
just like any other
normal sandbox purchase.
As Family Sharing is enabled,
transactions will be created
for each family member.
Your app will now see
these new transactions upon launch
or in real-time from StoreKit.
At this point, you can test your app logic
to make sure it validates
and entitles service for the transaction.
Additionally, you can also simulate
a family member
losing access to the service.
For that, on iOS sandbox Account Settings,
tap Family Sharing.
This will present you a view
of all the family members in sandbox,
and you can choose to stop Family Sharing.
The Family Sharing in sandbox
will allow you to verify
and validate use cases such as:
merchandising family-sharable products
using isFamilySharable property
of StoreKit.
Validate your app logic
to entitle service to a family member,
for a new or existing purchase.
Each family member can turn off sharing,
enabling you to
test when family members lose access
to a previously shared purchase.
For a scenario
when a purchaser stops Family Sharing,
you will be able to validate
revoking access to services
by using revocationDate
available in JWSTransactions.
And lastly, you will receive
App Store Server Notifications
for family members.
To learn more
about implementing Family Sharing,
please see Tech Talk session "Explore
Family Sharing for in-app purchases."
Later this year, we are adding options
to iOS sandbox Account Settings.
The iOS sandbox Account Settings
is available
once you have made an initial
in-app purchase in your sandbox app.
Your signed-in sandbox account
is visible in App Store settings.
Scroll down this page
to view your Sandbox Apple ID.
When you tap on Sandbox Apple ID,
a dialog appears.
Tap the Manage button,
and you'll navigate
to your sandbox Account Settings.
Later this year, you'll see three options,
which were earlier available
in App Store Connect
and are now available to you
on-device for testing.
Now through the Account Settings page,
you'll be to adjust
subscription renewal rate,
test interrupted purchases,
and clear purchase history.
When you tap on Renewal Rate,
you can adjust
the subscription renewal rate
for your sandbox account.
And you'll also be able to clear
purchase history of the sandbox Apple ID,
to refresh your sandbox Apple ID
and re-test your use cases.
Lastly, let's take a look at TestFlight.
TestFlight helps you to test
your app's end-to-end experience,
distribute your apps, and gather feedback
from a wider tester audience.
This helps you to validate and improve
your app experience
before releasing it on the App Store.
TestFlight allows you to distribute
your app across all Apple platforms.
You can add both internal
and external testers,
create multiple groups of testers,
and add different builds to each group
depending on the features
you want each group to test.
Testers can allow latest builds
to be installed automatically,
and each build remains available
for 90 days after upload.
For more information,
please watch the Tech Talks session
"Get started with TestFlight."
When testing in-app purchases,
testers need to download
your app builds using the TestFlight app.
When buying an in-app purchase
for an app downloaded through TestFlight,
it uses your Apple ID, which is signed in
to Media & Purchases settings
of the device.
Similar to sandbox,
you won't be charged for testing
in-app purchases for an app
downloaded through TestFlight.
For testing auto-renewable subscriptions,
the renewal rates
in TestFlight are equivalent
to default renewal rate of sandbox.
And if your app has implemented
showManageSubscription API
of the StoreKit, it gives you the ability
to test subscription cancellation
or change subscription.
This year, we are making it easier
to manage testers in TestFlight.
You can filter by tester data
like status, sessions,
and bulk select group of testers
to add or remove from a group.
And to streamline
your TestFlight app distribution,
a new method is added for you
to distribute the build, Internal Only.
Using this method ensures
the build can be available
to internal testers
and cannot be submitted
for the App Store review.
To learn more, please see session
"What's new in App Store Connect"
and "Simplify distribution
in Xcode and Xcode Cloud."
Now that I have reviewed
the tools available
for testing in-app purchases,
it's important for you to know
that these tools have
their own benefits and differences
but also have a lot in common,
such as they support testing
all in-app purchase types,
and the subscriptions renew
at an accelerated rate.
However, some of these tools may be ideal
for specific feature implementations
or use cases.
For example,
subscription offer code redemption
and price increase sheet
can be tested using StoreKit Testing
in Xcode.
Billing retry and grace period
can be tested
using both StoreKit Testing in Xcode
and sandbox.
To validate
your server side implementation,
both sandbox and TestFlight support
App Store Server Notifications
and App Store Server API,
while TestFlight provides you
with a streamlined process
to receive feedback
from internal and external testers
about your app's performance
and overall experience.
Consider leveraging these tools
for testing in-app purchases
depending upon your use cases,
feature implementation,
and your organization's team structure.
We have covered a lot today,
and I hope this session helped you
better understand all the available tools
for you to test in-app purchases.
To learn more,
please see available documentation
on developer.apple.com.
And we would love to hear your feedback
on how we can improve
your in-app purchase testing experience.
Please let us know
through Feedback Assistant.
Thank you for taking time
to watch this session.