♪ ♪
Taylor: Hello, my name is Taylor,
and I'm a designer
on the Apple Design Team.
We are so excited to introduce watchOS 10,
the most significant change
to Apple Watch since its introduction
over eight years ago.
In this session, you'll learn
about what's new in watchOS 10,
how the Apple Design Team approaches
the design of our own apps and the system,
and how you can apply
these design patterns
to make great Apple Watch apps
of your own.
Let's get started.
In 2014, we introduced Apple Watch,
the most personal product
we've ever created together.
It's always with you
and is worn on your body.
In acknowledgement of this,
we designed Apple Watch
to offer a wide range
of stylistic personalization
in case materials, bands, and watch faces.
And with the introduction
of Apple Watch Ultra,
Apple Watch can be your companion in some
of the most extreme conditions on Earth.
The unique constraints
of a device worn on the wrist,
a comparatively small display,
limited input capabilities,
and generally short interaction times,
required us create new methods
of interacting,
like the Digital Crown,
and to focus the design of apps to be
glanceable, actionable, and responsive.
Since then, Apple Watch has evolved a lot.
Its displays are larger, brighter,
and seamlessly integrated
into the curvature of the casing.
Apple Watch is also more capable
than ever with cellular connectivity,
new Health sensors,
a display that's always on,
and apps that are
increasingly full-featured.
With watchOS 10, we are introducing
an entirely new user interface
for Apple Watch that takes
full advantage of these modern,
bright displays and more capable,
connected hardware.
watchOS 10 intelligently surfaces timely,
relevant widgets right on your watch face
that you can access
by turning the Digital Crown.
The Home Screen is easier to navigate.
Rotate the Digital Crown
to move vertically
through a consistent organization of apps.
And you can click the Side Button once
to open Control Center
from anywhere you are,
or twice to open Wallet.
And we've redesigned every app
with a focus on glanceability,
clarity, and consistent placement
of controls and navigation.
We designed watchOS 10 by following
a rigorous and methodical design process
centered around clear design principles
that you can apply
to the design of your apps.
Apple Watch apps should be
focused and highly-specialized
in the utility they provide users.
The design of each screen should optimize
for glanceability
and short interaction time.
And controls and navigation
should be clear and consistent.
Compared to the original Apple Watch,
Apple Watch Series 8
and Apple Watch Ultra have much larger,
more rounded displays.
To bring more navigational consistency
to our app designs
and increase their glanceability,
we established a new approach to layout
that informed the design
of individual apps.
This new system is based on the shape
of the display and defines the size
and placement of controls,
labels, and content,
making apps more consistent in layout
and controls more clear and ergonomic.
To accommodate different types of content,
we designed three foundational layouts:
Dial, Infographic, and List.
All of these layouts are designed
to adapt automatically
to the different Apple Watch sizes
supported by watchOS 10 .
Apps in watchOS 10 also make
considerate use of background content
to convey additional information,
like the time of day in World Clock,
the current conditions in Weather,
or whether a company's stock price
is trending up or down.
For instance, in Activity,
each Infographic view
for the Move, Exercise,
and Stand Activity Rings
has a background that matches the color
of the ring you're focused on.
Use background colors
to help users navigate
or to aid in recognition
of what app they're using.
Background content in watchOS 10
should play a supporting role
that provides additional utility,
not merely be a visual flourish.
Background content can be
as simple as a color, gradient,
or as sophisticated as an animation
that communicates additional information.
Consider using color
to help people who use your app
understand their sense of place.
In addition to background content,
watchOS 10 introduces new applications
of materials across the system.
Distinct, functional layers utilize
translucency to establish hierarchy
and help users understand where they are
in the system or inside an app.
These new materials maximize
the amount of space for content,
while allowing system elements
like the Status Bar to remain legible
when content is scrolled underneath them.
Additionally, elements using
semantic system colors automatically adapt
their contrast when placed
on top of vibrant background materials.
watchOS 10 also introduces
new navigation patterns:
Vertical pagination, source list,
and refined hierarchical navigation
designed to help make apps easier
and more consistent to navigate.
The Digital Crown is a unique
input mechanism we designed
to address the needs
of a product this small,
having a way navigate without occluding
the display with your finger.
In watchOS 10, the Digital Crown
is used to navigate to apps,
and also navigate within apps.
In List-based views, like Mail,
you can rotate the Digital Crown
to scroll vertically through the list
of inboxes or mail messages.
For apps with multiple tabs,
watchOS 10 introduces
a new navigation pattern,
vertical pagination.
In Activity,
we use the Digital Crown to navigate
between the Activity Rings overview
and the individual infographic views
for the Move, Exercise, and Stand rings.
Vertical pagination is a great way
to separate multiple views of information
inside your app into distinct,
purposeful screens.
The page indicator is aligned
to the Digital Crown and is designed
to adapt and remain visible
on any background.
Sometimes, an element in your design
exists in multiple pages of your app,
like the Activity Rings in Activity
or Dials in Stopwatch.
Smoothly animate elements between pages
by manipulating their scale,
position, and information density,
instead of introducing additional
instances of that element on each page.
This object permanence helps
provide a visual anchor for users
as they navigate
through full-screen pages of content.
Generally, we advise limiting the content
of an individual page
to a single screen height.
Embracing this constraint
encourages each page to serve
a clear and distinct purpose
and results in a more glanceable design.
However, we know there a certain cases
where it's necessary for content
to extend
beyond the height of the display.
One example of this is Messages,
which contains two pages,
one for your pinned conversations
and another containing conversations
with other people or groups.
This first page is a fixed height and can
contain up to nine pinned conversations.
The second page is a scroll view
that scrolls vertically
after it becomes the active page.
In Contacts,
the first page of a contact card
provides a detailed photo
and frequently used actions.
The second page is a scroll view
and contains
less frequently used contact details.
We recommend using scroll views
inside pages judiciously and,
if possible, placing them only after
fixed height pages in your app design.
Use Vertical Pagination
in place of horizontal pagination,
which is more difficult
to navigate on Apple Watch.
In contexts
where the Digital Crown does not need
to navigate lists or between pages,
it is a fantastic tool
to inspect data in your app.
In World Clock,
rotating the Digital Crown advances
the time of day at a selected location,
allowing users to compare various times
of day to their current time.
World Clock also makes use
of Split Views in watchOS 10
to introduce a new navigation pattern,
Source Lists.
In source list based apps,
users navigate between detail views
for multiple entities
containing the same type of information.
These apps open to the detail view,
and users can tap the Source List Button
in the upper left
to switch between entities,
such as multiple locations in World Clock.
Traditional hierarchical navigation
is still supported,
but it should be used considerately,
and only when your app
cannot more succinctly
represent its content
in a two-level, Source List based design
or as distinct vertical pages.
Settings and Mail are good examples
of where deeper hierarchical navigation
is appropriate.
watchOS 10 introduces a new animation
for hierarchical navigation
that makes it clear
which view users are navigating into
as they traverse the hierarchy
of your app.
Great watchOS 10 apps are focused,
they convey information succinctly,
and are optimized for glanceability
and brief interactions.
To design a great watchOS 10 app:
Focus what your app does
and make it highly specialized,
Keep navigation shallow
and use standard navigation patterns.
Convey information in the most
succinct number of screens possible.
And use standard layouts, controls,
label sizes, semantic colors,
and materials.
If you'd like to go deeper and learn more
about how to design for watchOS 10,
check out "Design and Build Your App
for watchOS 10"
and "Update your app for watchOS 10."
We also have great sessions dedicated
to widgets and the new Smart Stack.
watchOS 10 was a massive effort,
requiring collaboration
from many different people and disciplines
across the Design Team and Engineering,
but this is just the beginning.
We cannot wait to see what innovations you
bring to Apple Watch with your own apps.
♪ ♪