♪ ♪
person: Hello, and welcome
to "Demystify SwiftUI Performance."
SwiftUI makes it easy
to build complex, powerful apps,
offering a large set of features and
complex controls like lists and tables.
When you're just starting out
and your app isn't very complex,
performance issues aren't as obvious.
but as your app's complexity grows,
performance becomes more important.
Small issues can get amplified,
and code that works well for a prototype
might not work as well in production.
This session is all
about building a mental model
for performance in SwiftUI
because if you understand how
to write fast code from the beginning
of the development process,
you'll run into fewer issues
as your app becomes more complex.
Let's examine the feedback loop involved
in addressing a performance problem.
Performance problems start with a symptom.
Perhaps there's a slow navigation push,
a broken animation,
or you're seeing
the spinning wait cursor on macOS.
When you identify a performance problem,
the first step
towards addressing it is to measure.
Once you have measured
and verified that the symptom exists,
work on identifying its cause.
This can often be one
of the trickier phases of this loop
because it requires an intuition
about how things are supposed to work.
Bugs arise when your app
has an incorrect assumption.
This session is about helping
you identify the mismatch
between your app's assumptions
and reality.
After identifying the root cause,
fix the issue through optimization.
But performance problems don't end
after you've found a root cause
and optimized your code.
You need to re-measure and re-verify
any fix you make to ensure
that it addresses the issue.
This is a good practice for all bugs,
but it's especially important
for performance.
After you've verified that the problem
is resolved, you break the loop.
This diagram puts this session in context.
Ideally, you never end up in this cycle,
and you can avoid many performance issues
by writing fast code when prototyping.
However, it's inevitable that,
as your app gets more complex,
you end up with performance bugs.
It happens to the best of us.
And when you do encounter
performance issues,
it's good to have as many tools
at your disposal to triage and fix them.
This session aims to make it easier
to get through the loop.
This is an advanced session,
and there are some prerequisites.
You should have a cursory understanding
of SwiftUI identity,
including the difference
between implicit and explicit identity.
It's also important
to know the distinction
between view lifetime and view identity.
If you don't have these prerequisites,
don't fret.
The "Demystify SwiftUI" session
from WWDC21 has you covered.
Today's session picks up
where that session left off.
Let's go over the agenda.
We'll begin with an in-depth discussion
of dependencies
and explore the SwiftUI
update process in detail.
Next, we'll move on to a discussion
of updates and how to improve the speed
with which SwiftUI updates your interface.
And last, but definitely not least,
we'll discuss identity in list and table.
Along the way,
we'll take a peek under the hood
of SwiftUI and check out several tips
and tricks to use when developing.
This session is primarily concerned
with slow updates
to the view hierarchy,
but is by no means an exhaustive look
at all the performance problems that you
might encounter when developing an app.
Let's get started with Dependencies.
It's been a few years since
the last "Demystify SwiftUI" session,
and I've missed working
on dog-themed apps.
So continuing the theme from that session,
I've been working on a new app
that lets me keep track
of my favorite furry friends
and set up some time to play with them.
Here's one of the views,
a table showing all of the dogs.
The app also has a detail view,
shown here on iPhone,
that shows a bigger picture of each dog,
the dog's preferences,
and offers a button
to set up some time to play.
Here's the code for that same view.
The view takes in a dog as a parameter
and also has an environment property
for knowing whether it's play time.
As mentioned
in the previous Demystify session,
this means the dog and the play time
variables are dependencies of the view,
and another way
to show this view is as a graph.
Here is a basic graph representing
approximately the same view.
Each arrow represents a view's body.
The dog view produces a stack.
And the stack has multiple children,
like some text,
the scalable dog image,
the detail view, and the button.
Continuing on,
each of those views has children,
and the graph continues
until it reaches a leaf view,
like an image, text, or color.
All views ultimately resolve
to a leaf view.
There are many leaf views in SwiftUI,
so I won't be covering all of them here.
Check out the documentation
for more information.
Let's go back to the app.
Whenever I'm using the app, I can log
whenever I play with one of my friends.
I just finished playing fetch
with Rocky here,
so I've noted that in the app,
which updates the button and the image.
Rocky's looking pretty happy,
but he's definitely too tired to play now.
When this data changes in the model,
SwiftUI updates this view.
Let's explore the update process in depth
by returning to the graph
and looking at what happens
when this change occurs.
Here's our graph again.
This is where the previous
Demystify session left off,
explaining that views form a graph
and SwiftUI looks at dependencies
when evaluating your code.
Let's zoom in
and provide a more in-depth look
at where those dependencies come from
and how you can control them.
Each child view is dependent
on the view value that gets produced
by its ancestor.
But there are other forms
of dependencies too.
Dynamic properties are a common source
of dependencies as well.
For example,
the DogView reads whether it's play time
from environment by using
the @Environment property wrapper.
Therefore,
it is dependent both on the value
produced by its parent
and the value from the environment.
If we visualize time on the X axis,
the first step in the update process
is to produce a new value for the view.
This value encompasses
all the stored properties of the view,
like the dog value and the initial value
of the dynamic property.
Next, SwiftUI updates all
of the dynamic properties of the view,
replacing their values
with the current ones from the graph.
Finally, with the updated value,
body runs to produce the view's children.
Let's bring in the graph again.
This process recurses
to update the interface,
only updating those views that have
new values or other changed dependencies.
When we mark Rocky as tired,
we get a new dog--
sorry, a new dog struct value,
but it's still the same Rocky.
Because our data is a value type,
a new copy of it
is created when it's mutated.
And that results in DogView
producing new content for the stack,
Which updates the stack's children.
I'm only focusing
on the ScalableDogImage here,
but other views may update
if they depend on the dog value.
ScalableDogImage
ends up producing a new image.
Images are leaf views, so the rest
of the work is done by SwiftUI from here.
The process then finishes,
and a new rendering is produced.
That's how
to look at the dependency graph.
Let's go over some tips
to improve this process.
It's important to reduce the updates
to only those that are necessary.
To understand when a view is updated,
SwiftUI has the printChanges method.
This lets you print out
why the SwiftUI graph evaluator
called into a view's body.
Let's walk through
an example of how to use it.
Here we have our scalable dog image,
which contains a piece of state.
When we tap on the image,
the state changes like so.
Focusing on just the image view,
if we set a breakpoint
in our view's body,
from the LLDB console,
we can call Self._printChanges
by using the "expression" LLDB command.
printChanges is a debugging-only facility
that gives a best-effort explanation
of why SwiftUI requested a view's body.
In this case,
it's because scaleToFill changed.
You can use printChanges
to understand whether a view
might have extra dependencies.
For example, I'm currently
running my app and debugging
and want to see
if this view has an extra dependency.
I can add a call to printChanges
to this view's body to print every time
the view's body is accessed.
However, note that printChanges
is prefixed with an underscore.
In this case, that means,
it is never guaranteed to always exist
and may even be removed
in a future release,
so never submit a call
to this method to the app store.
I'll need to remove this call later.
It's only meant for debugging
and has a runtime performance impact.
If I re-run my app
and change Rocky's favorite treat,
say, from a biscuit to something else,
like a cucumber,
I notice a log
in the console from our image.
It says that "self" changed.
This means that the view value changed,
so the scalable image view must have
some dependency on the treat,
but it doesn't actually need to.
Focusing on the code,
the view's value only has
the scaleToFill member
and the dog property.
Since scaleToFill
is a SwiftUI dynamic property,
it would have shown up
in the change log if it had changed,
so "@Self" here means
that the dog value changed.
But looking at this view,
we only care about the image.
So we can eliminate this dependency
by instead using just the image.
And now,
when I change a property of the dog
that isn't related to the image,
I don't see a log.
The view's dependencies
are tightly scoped.
If you follow this technique, don't forget
to remove the call to printChanges.
Let's update the parent view to match.
Here's the code for the parent dog view.
I need to update the initializer
for ScalableDogImage to take in an image,
like so.
By extracting the ScalableDogImage out,
I've reduced the dependencies
to only those that matter.
I can do the same with the header too
and extract it to its own view.
This has a number of benefits.
This code is now easier to read,
and the dependencies of the DogHeader
are apparent at its use site.
This technique works great
for smaller views,
but just be careful
with very large structs.
Not every dependency deserves
to be scoped like this.
You'll need to use your best judgement.
Fewer updates means better performance
when data changes in your app.
As we just explored, one way
to do this is by reducing dependencies.
Try reducing view values
to only the data they actually depend on.
Another tip is to extract views
to reduce dependencies.
And finally, the new Observable protocol
can also help with dependency scoping
by automatically limiting the dependencies
to only that which is read.
Check out the "Discover Observation
in SwiftUI" session for more information.
That was just a quick tour
of how to look at dependencies.
Let's move on
to talk about faster updates.
In this section, we'll discuss how
to reduce the cost of each SwiftUI update.
Slow SwiftUI updates can have a number
of negative effects on your app,
including reduced responsiveness,
such as hangs and hitches.
A hang is a delay
in responding to user interaction,
like a view taking a long time
to initially appear.
The "Analyze Hangs in Instruments" session
from WWDC2023 goes into detail
about how to use Instruments
to analyze hangs,
including how to identify whether the hang
may be caused by SwiftUI-related work.
A hitch is a user-perceivable
animation issue,
such as a pause during scrolling
or skipped frames of an animation.
The root causes of hangs and hitches,
especially in SwiftUI, are often related.
For more information on hitches, including
how the system render loop works,
check out the "Explore UI animation
hitches and the render loop"
tech talk video.
Both hangs and hitches in SwiftUI
often originate from a slow update.
These slow updates have
a number of common causes.
The first is expensive
Dynamic Property instantiation,
such as allocating and initializing
a state object or initializing state.
Another source is work done in body.
Make sure to check for expensive
string interpolation or operations
like data filtering
and other work inside of body.
It's important that body itself
is as cheap as possible.
These are all inter-related.
For example,
a dynamic property could be computed
from a view's body,
making the view expensive to evaluate.
Slow identification also
frequently happens in a view's body.
Let's start by looking
at an example from the fetch app.
In this example, I've been working
on the root view of the app,
which has an object
that I use to create the dog list.
Following the code highlight
on this slide,
accessing model.dogs in the body
lazily instantiates the object,
which brings us to the initializer,
which fetches the list of dogs.
As the code comment says,
this could take a long time.
This is synchronous work.
One way to fix this
is by using the task modifier.
We'll first make the fetching async.
I'm only showing the addition
of the async keyword here.
Next, in the task modifier,
we'll asynchronously fetch the dog list
by awaiting it.
That way, the app is responsive
when the expensive data
loading operation occurs.
There are other sources of work
that you might not realize
are affecting your app.
For example, string interpolation
can often be expensive,
so make sure to cache any strings
you might need to frequently use.
Similarly, looking up values
from bundles can be expensive.
And of course, any heap allocation,
such as for a class-bound type,
can add up.
Let's move on to lists and tables.
List and Table support rich features
beyond a simple layout,
adding selection, swipe actions,
reordering support, and more.
These are complex, advanced controls,
and understanding identity
is critical to ensuring
they perform well in your app.
In this section,
I'll discuss identity in list and table
and demystify how to maximize update
performance for these built-in components.
Before we dive into this subject,
I'd like to touch on some improvements.
In macOS Sonoma and iOS 17,
SwiftUI has a number of optimizations
under the hood for cases
like filtering and scrolling.
These improvements can be had
with minimal effort on your part,
and in many cases, can result
in drastically more responsive load
and update times
for bigger lists and tables.
However, there are certain ways
to construct lists and tables
that result in better performance.
List and Table use identifiers
to know what changes occurred to the data.
For consistency, all the IDs
of List and Table are gathered eagerly.
Therefore, being able to quickly
generate identifiers for your list
and table contents directly translates
to faster load and update times.
Identity helps
SwiftUI manage view lifetime,
which is crucial for incremental
updates to your hierarchy.
A change to the identity
means the view changed.
This is important
for animations and performance.
For more information on animations,
check out the "Fundamentals
of SwiftUI Animations" session.
Identification performance is important
because identifiers are gathered often,
especially for lists and tables.
Let's walk through
the list identification model.
I've been hard at work
on the list of dogs in the app.
I've started with just a single row.
Here's the code for the list,
with a single DogCell inside.
The next step is to use ForEach
to iterate over all the dogs.
This example is simple,
but it's directly related to identity,
and adding a ForEach in a List is
an important time to evaluate performance.
To understand why, let's look
at the generic signature of ForEach next.
This is the signature
for ForEach from SwiftUI.
ForEach maps a collection of data
onto a resulting sequence of views,
producing explicit identity
for each of its views.
When you use List, it needs
to figure out how many rows to display,
as well as what the identifier
for each row is.
Therefore, it visits
the data collection up front,
determining each element's ID.
The content closure is called
to produce each view.
Rows are created on-demand.
List uses a composite of the identity
and the content to produce a list row.
The rows created on-demand
correlate to the visible region,
plus some system-determined buffer
for prefetching or accessibility.
As the view is scrolled,
more views become extant.
Here's the code snippet
producing this ForEach.
Note here that the content
is just DogCell,
which is itself single view,
because it uses an HStack inside.
ForEach is critical in determining
the ultimate row ID used by the List.
And List needs
to know all of its IDs up front.
But it can only do this efficiently
without visiting all the content
if the content resolves
to a constant number of rows.
As an example,
let's say we want to refactor our list
to only show those dogs
that like to fetch a ball.
It might be tempting to add a filter
using a conditional view, like this.
Here, the number of views is variable.
It's either one or zero.
This is bad
because it results in list needing
to build all the views
to retrieve the row identifiers
because it doesn't know how
many views each element resolves to.
The same is true if you use AnyView.
Here, the number of views
is now completely unknown.
So we have the same problem as before:
All rows must be created.
What if we move the filter
into the data collection itself?
Now we're back to a constant number
of views per element,
and only those that are needed
have their row contents constructed,
but be careful: The inline filter here
is linear over the collection.
This might work in a prototype,
but when the collection scales,
this operation
can quickly become expensive,
leading to a slow update.
It's better to move it out to the model.
Now we have the best of both worlds:
The filter is cached,
so it won't run every
time this list is constructed,
and the number of views
per element is constant.
Here are a few tips for how to ensure
your view counts are constant.
Note that this approach to view counts
is only relevant in the context
of ForEach within List and Table
because those components
gather their identifiers up front.
As I just mentioned,
avoid using AnyView
and lopsided conditions.
You can also use an explicit stack
where appropriate,
but note that certain modifiers
like listRowBackground need
to go after the stack and not within it.
Finally, try to flatten nested
ForEach constructions if you can.
However, there is one place where nested
ForEach can be valuable, sectioned lists.
Let's take a look at an example.
In this example,
I have a list of dogs that's sectioned
by the favorite toy of each dog.
I'm using ForEach to create
a dynamic number of sections.
and each section has a dynamic number
of rows within it by nesting a ForEach.
List will need
to retrieve all of the identifiers,
but because we're using sections here,
SwiftUI understands this construction
and ensures the list
is still fast to render.
Dynamic sections are a good example of
when using nested ForEach is recommended.
The basic equation to think about
is that the row count resulting
from a ForEach in a List
is equal to the number of elements
multiplied by the number
of views produced for each element.
You need to ensure the number
of views per element is a constant,
or SwiftUI has to build the views
in addition to the identifiers
in order to identify the rows.
So far we've talked about List,
but these rules
generally apply to Table too.
Table uses TableRow instead of views,
and TableRow always resolves
to a single row.
Let's look at a Table example.
Here I have the dog table,
which has a ForEach inside.
Because TableRow is always a single row,
the number of total rows here
is just the number of elements
in the dogs collection.
This construction is so common that,
new in iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma,
SwiftUI provides a streamlined initializer
that lets you simply write ForEach
of your data collection
and creates the table rows on your behalf.
While this initializer is new,
it back deploys to all previous
operating system versions
where Table is available.
Not only is this construction simpler,
it also enforces a constant number
of rows for the ForEach content,
which helps
with identification performance.
However, there is a semantic change
I'd like to call out that's new.
If you have code like this,
it could behave differently
in the newest OS versions.
In this example,
we have a ForEach over dog,
which also creates a row of dog.
However, the dogs here don't match.
The values are the dog's best friend.
In iOS 16,
each row became identified by its value.
In iOS 17, this behavior has changed
to improve performance.
The reason is, now we don't need
to identify each table row
by looking into the ForEach.
So this example now has the IDs
of each of the dogs,
instead of the TableRow's value.
If you need to back deploy,
you can get the old behavior
by either mapping over your collection
or by explicitly specifying
an ID key path.
The basic equation to think about
is that the row count resulting
from a ForEach in a List
is equal to the number of elements
multiplied by the number
of views produced for each element.
In Table, this is similar, but it's
the number of TableRows per element.
We've covered a few tips and tricks
for faster lists and tables here,
namely that you should ensure
identifiers are cheap to create
and that the number of views
in ForEach content is constant.
We've covered a lot today.
We started with exploring the graph to
understand dependencies and optimize them.
Then, we looked at slow updates
and how to improve responsiveness.
And finally, we discussed the importance
of identity with Lists and Tables.
With the right mental models,
you can easily have great performance
from the beginning
of the development process,
which lets you focus more
on the details of your app.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪