♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
John Calsbeek: Welcome!
I'm John, and I work
on RealityKit.
Vladimir Vukićević:
And I'm Vlad, from Unity.
John: I'm thrilled
to introduce Unity support
for immersive apps.
Unity has worked
with Apple to bring
the full Unity experience
to this new platform.
Unity is used
by tens of thousands of apps,
and now you can use Unity
to build immersive apps.
Triband brought their Apple
Arcade title What The Golf?,
which is built in Unity,
to this platform.
It's really fun to play
on an iPhone,
and it feels great
to play it this way.
There are two main approaches
for creating
immersive experiences
on this platform with Unity.
You can create experiences
which mix your content
with real-world objects
using passthrough,
either as
an immersive experience
or in the Shared Space
alongside other apps.
You can also bring a fully
immersive Unity experience
to the platform.
If you're interested
in this approach,
I recommend you check out
"Bring your Unity VR app
to a fully immersive space."
Creating experiences
for the shared space with Unity
opens up exciting opportunities
for your apps.
Here's Vlad to tell you more.
Vladimir: Thanks, John.
Unity and Apple have been
working together
for the past two years
to make sure
your Unity content looks great
on the platform.
Whether you're starting
with an existing project,
or building something
completely new,
Unity is a great tool for
creating immersive experiences
using familiar tools
and some new capabilities.
On this platform, you can
achieve the visual look you want
using Unity's
shaders and materials.
We're introducing the ability
to enter play mode
directly to device,
improving your iteration time.
There's also a new concept
called the volume camera,
which controls how content
from your Unity scene
is brought into the real world.
Input on this new device
can be as simple
as a look-and-tap gesture
or involve more
complex interactions.
And there are a few things
you can do today
to prepare your Unity content
for spatial computing.
Here's an example of some of
these elements working together.
This scene uses materials built
with Unity's Shader Graph,
and it's being displayed
in the shared space
in the Simulator
with passthrough.
There are fully rigged
and animated characters,
like the ogre in the back.
Physics interactions work
just like you're used to.
All of the residents
of this town
are using character navigation
to move around,
and custom dynamic
scripted behaviors
are used to make
this scene feel alive.
We put this together
in two weeks with the help
of the Asset Store,
and it looks great
when viewed in your space,
where you can get up close
and look at a scene
from any angle.
All content in the shared space
is rendered using RealityKit.
Your Unity materials and shaders
need to be translated
to this new environment.
Unity has created PolySpatial,
which takes care
of this translation for you
and brings many Unity features
over to this environment.
PolySpatial translates
materials,
regular and skinned
mesh rendering,
as well as particle effects
and sprites.
Unity simulation features
are supported,
and you continue to use
MonoBehaviours,
scriptable objects,
and other standard tools.
Three categories of materials
are translated.
They are the physically based
materials, custom materials,
and some special effect
materials.
Materials based on Unity's
physically based shaders
translate directly
to RealityKit.
If you're using the
Universal Render Pipeline,
you can use any of the Lit,
Simple Lit,
or Complex Lit Shaders
in your materials.
With the built-in pipeline,
you can use the Standard Shader.
All of these are translated
to a RealityKit
PhysicallyBasedMaterial.
Custom shader and material types
are supported
through Unity Shader Graph.
Unity Shader Graphs
are converted to MaterialX,
a standard interchange format
for complex materials.
MaterialX shaders become
a ShaderGraphMaterial
in RealityKit.
Many Unity Shader Graph nodes
are supported,
so you can create complex
and interesting effects.
Handwritten shaders
are not supported
for rendering
through RealityKit,
but you can use them
with RenderTextures in Unity.
You can then use
that RenderTexture
as a texture input
to a Shader Graph
for displaying
through RealityKit.
Two additional material
shader types are supported.
First is the Unlit Shader,
which lets you create objects
that take on a solid
color or texture,
unaffected by lighting.
The second is
the Occlusion Shader,
which lets passthrough
show through the object.
You can use the Occlusion Shader
with world mesh data
to help your content feel more
integrated with the real world.
Unity MeshRenderers
and SkinnedMeshRenderers
are supported
and are the primary way
of bringing visual content
into real space.
Rigged characters
and animation are available.
You can use either the Universal
or the Built-in Render Pipeline,
and your content will be
translated to RealityKit
via Unity PolySpatial.
Rendering features,
such as postprocessing effects
and custom pipeline stages,
are not available,
as RealityKit performs
the final rendering.
Particle effects using
Unity's Shuriken system
are either translated
to RealityKit's particle system,
if they are compatible,
or are translated
to baked meshes.
Sprites become 3D meshes,
though you should consider
how you're using them
in a spatial context.
PolySpatial works to optimize
and translate rendering
between Unity and RealityKit.
Simulation features in Unity
work just like you're used to,
such as Physics,
Animation and Timeline,
Pathfinding and NavMesh,
your custom MonoBehaviours,
and other
non-rendering features.
To help you fine-tune your look
and to speed up iteration,
Unity PolySpatial
enables "Play to device."
It can take time to go
through the build process
to see what your content
looks like on your device.
With PolySpatial, you have
access to Play to device
for the first time.
Play to device lets you see
an instant preview
of your scene and make
live changes to it.
It works in the simulator and
works great on device as well.
You can use Play to device
to rapidly explore
the placement and size
of your content,
including adding
and removing elements.
You can change materials,
textures,
and even Shader Graphs
to fine-tune your look
while seeing your content
in place with passthrough.
You can test out interaction
because events
are sent back to the editor.
Your simulation
continues to run,
so it's easy to debug just
by attaching to the editor.
Here's the same castle scene
you saw earlier.
I have it open in Unity
on the left,
and with Play to device,
I can see it running
in the simulator on the right.
I can add more ogres just
by dragging them into my scene.
They're instantly visible
in the simulator or device.
If I want to see how pink
or neon green ogres look, I can.
Play to device is a really
efficient workflow
for iterating on your content,
and it's currently available
in Unity
only for creating content
in the shared space.
Because you're using Unity
to create volumetric content
that participates
in the shared space,
a new concept called
a volume camera lets you control
how your scene is brought
into the real world.
A volume camera can create
two types of volumes,
bounded and unbounded, each with
different characteristics.
Your application can switch
between the two at any time.
Bounded volumes exist
in the shared space
as volumes, alongside
other apps and games.
They have dimensions
and a transform in Unity,
as well as a specific
real-world size.
They can be repositioned,
but people cannot resize them.
The dimensions and the transform
of the volume camera
define the region of your scene
that your app will display
in a volume.
They're specified
in scene units.
You can see a preview
of the volume in green
in Unity's scene view.
By manipulating the dimensions
and the transform
of the volume camera,
different parts of the scene
can be brought into the volume.
If I move or rotate the camera,
new objects become visible
in my space.
If I scale up its size, more
of the scene comes into view.
In both cases, the volume
remains the same size.
Only the content visible
inside of it changes.
Notice that in the initial
placement of the volume camera,
the spring intersects
the side of the volume;
content is clipped
by RealityKit.
If you will have content
intersecting the edges
of your volume,
consider placing the same mesh
in your scene a second time
with a back-facing material
to fill in the clipped sections.
Your unbounded volume displays
in a full space on this platform
and allows your content
to fully blend with passthrough
for a more immersive
experience.
It has no dimensions because
it selects your entire scene,
and its transform specifies
how your scene units
are mapped to real-world units.
There can only be one unbounded
volume camera active at a time.
You'll see an example
of an unbounded volume
when we talk about interaction.
Unity supports multiple input
types for apps on this platform.
On this platform, people use
their eyes and hands
to look at content and tap their
fingers together to select it.
Full hand tracking
as well as head pose data
lets you create
realistic interactions.
Augmented reality data
from ARKit is available,
as are Bluetooth devices
such as keyboards
and game controllers.
The tap gesture
is the most common way
of interacting with content
on this platform.
In order for your objects
to receive these events,
they must have
input colliders configured.
You can look and tap to select
an object from a distance,
or you can reach out
and directly touch an object
with a finger.
Up to two simultaneous tap
actions can be in progress.
In Unity, taps are available
as WorldTouch events.
They are similar
to 2D tap events,
but have a full 3D position.
Hand and head pose tracking
gives your application
precise information
about each hand joint
and the viewer's head position
relative to the global
tracking origin.
Low-level hand data is provided
via Unity's Hands package,
and head pose is provided
through the Input System.
Both of these are available
in unbounded volumes only,
and accessing hand tracking
requires your application
to request permission
to receive the data.
Augmented reality data
such as detected planes,
the world mesh,
and image markers
are available through ARKit
and Unity's AR Foundation.
Like hands and head pose,
AR data is only available
in unbounded volumes
and requires extra permissions.
Finally, Bluetooth devices
such as keyboards, controllers,
and other supported devices
are available
for you to access through
Unity's Input System.
Because some types of input
are only available
in unbounded volumes,
you'll need to decide
what type of interaction
you would like to build.
Using look and tap will allow
your content to work
in a bounded volume
that can live
alongside other applications,
but if you need access
to hand tracking
or augmented reality data,
you'll need to use
an unbounded volume
and request permissions.
Each of these is delivered
to your Unity application
via an appropriate mechanism.
This sample uses tapping,
hand tracking,
and plane detection
in an unbounded volume scene.
You can look at a surface found
via ARKit plane detection
and create flowers by dragging
your finger along it.
The flowers are painted
using hand tracking,
and you can tap to grow flowers.
Flowers that you grow react
to hand movement
using Unity's physics system.
By incorporating the real world
into your content in this way,
you can create a much
deeper sense of immersion.
The best way to adapt
your existing interactions
depends on the type.
If you are already
working with touch,
such as on an iPhone,
you can add appropriate
input colliders
and continue to use tap as
your primary input mechanism.
If you are using VR controllers,
you will have to redefine
your interactions in terms of
either tap or hand-based input,
depending on how complex
they are.
Existing hand-based input
should work without changes.
And if you have
existing UI panels
using one of Unity's UI systems,
you can bring them
to this platform.
User interface elements
built using uGUI,
as well as UI Toolkit,
are supported.
If you are using
other UI systems,
they will work as long
as they use meshes
and MeshRenderers
or draw to a RenderTexture,
which is then placed
on a mesh.
Support for spatial computing
on Apple platforms
will be coming soon in beta
based on Unity 2022.
However, you can start getting
your content ready today.
If you're starting
a new project,
use Unity 2022 or later.
If you have an existing project,
start upgrading to 2022.
If you have handwritten shaders
in your project,
start converting them
to Shader Graph.
Consider adopting
the Universal Render Pipeline.
While the built-in graphics
pipeline is supported,
all future improvements will be
on the Universal pipeline.
If you haven't yet, start using
the Input System package.
Mixed-mode input is supported,
but platform events
are only delivered
through the Input System.
Finally, start thinking about
how you can bring
an existing app or game
to spatial computing,
or what new experience
you'd like to create.
Consider whether your idea
fits in the shared space
to give people more flexibility,
or if your app needs the power
of a full space.
To get more information
about Unity's support
for this platform,
and to sign up
for early beta access,
please visit unity.com/spatial.
I'm excited to see
all the amazing things
that you'll create with Unity
and this new device.
John: Unity is an amazing way
to hit the ground running
and build immersive apps.
And it works great with
RealityKit on this new platform.
You can get started today
preparing your projects.
If you want to create
a fully immersive experience
with Unity,
I recommend the session
"Bring your Unity VR app
to a fully immersive space."
And don't miss "Build great
games for spatial computing"
to get an overview
of game development technologies
for this platform.
We can't wait to see
what you create.
Vladimir: Thanks for watching.
♪