♪ ♪
Jonathan: Hi, I'm Jonathan,
and I'm an engineer
on the Internet Technologies team.
Today we'll explore how to build
robust and resumable file transfers
using URLSession.
Large file transfers can be
a huge challenge
because even a tiny interruption
can throw away all your user's progress
and force them to start
from the very beginning.
Plus, the larger the transfer,
the longer it takes,
and the longer it takes,
the more opportunity there is
for something to go wrong.
In that time, your user might
navigate away from your app,
leave the range of Wi-Fi,
or experience one of so many
network problems outside of their control.
In this session, we'll explore
how to solve these challenges
and provide a robust
networking experience for your users.
Our first stop
is resumable HTTP protocols,
which allow your user
to keep their progress
when a connection is interrupted.
This prevents wasted time and bandwidth,
making these protocols a powerful tool
when transferring large amounts of data.
I'll demonstrate how to resume both
downloads and uploads in URLSession,
including brand new APIs
for resumable upload tasks.
Understanding the mechanism
behind these APIs can be really helpful
for debugging your app,
or even building your own server support.
That's why we'll also cover
the resumable protocols themselves,
so you know exactly how your app
and server achieve this over HTTP.
Next up, speaking of servers,
you'll learn how to bring resumable upload
support to any server that uses SwiftNIO.
And lastly,
we'll review how background URLSessions
can gracefully handle
user and network interruptions,
while making efficient use
of system resources.
Let's learn more about download
and upload resumption in URLSession.
So I'm downloading the latest Xcode,
and the 7 gigabyte download
is almost finished.
Right at the end, my Wi-Fi goes out.
But wait, the download is paused,
and when the Wi-Fi comes back online,
I can resume my download
from where it left off.
I just saved lots of time
and several gigs of bandwidth.
Resumable downloads are amazing.
But how do they work?
First, the client sends a GET request
to retrieve the download from the server.
In the response,
the server advertises its support
for resumable downloads
using the Accept-Ranges header.
Accept-Ranges: bytes means
the server supports range requests
for specific bytes of this resource.
The server response also contains
what's called an ETag,
which uniquely identifies the resource
at this moment in time.
If the content on the server changes,
the ETag does, too.
So what happens
if this download is interrupted?
The client has stored
the partial download data,
so it only needs the last part.
To accomplish this,
it can send a range request
to retrieve the missing bytes
of the download.
The request indicates which bytes
using the Range field.
But the client also needs to make sure
the resource hasn't changed,
or else it would be appending data
from the new resource
onto the older resource that's stored.
To prevent this, the If-Range field
contains the ETag received
from the previous response,
telling the server to only send
the partial data if the ETag is the same.
If the ETag is the same,
then the server responds
with 206 Partial Content.
The Content-Range field here
denotes the range of bytes
included in this response,
completing the download.
Since the beginning,
URLSession has offered API
to pause and resume download tasks
using Range requests.
Now,
you can pause and resume uploads, too.
Not only does this allow you
to manually pause an ongoing task,
but you can also perform error handling to
recover from unexpected connection issues
and resume your transfer
right where it left off.
Let's review how this works
for downloads first.
Imagine you're creating a UI
that allow users to manually pause
and resume their downloads.
Like the Safari example,
your app owns this UI, but under the hood,
you can use URLSession
to handle all the details,
like keeping track of the partial download
data, ETag, and request headers.
To begin a download,
you create a download task like usual,
and start it by calling resume.
To pause the download,
such as when a user taps a pause button,
you can call cancelByProducingResumeData.
In order to resume this download later,
URLSession will need information
about the partial download,
like its ETag, current size,
and location on disk.
This, and other metadata,
are conveniently stored in the resume
data object returned from this function.
Again, it's important to note
that this resume data
is not the partial download data.
If the resume data is nil,
this means that one or more requirements
for resumable downloads are not met,
which we'll cover soon.
On the other hand,
if the resume data is not nil,
you should store it for later use.
That's because to resume the download,
like when a user taps a resume button,
you pass this stored data to
the downloadTask withResumeData method.
It's as simple as that!
This pattern is great
for manually pausing a download,
but URLSession also offers ways to recover
from unpredicted connection interruptions.
If your download task fails
due to a network problem,
you can check for resume data
in the error itself.
If the download can be resumed,
the error's userInfo dictionary
will contain that resume data.
You can conveniently access this data
using the downloadTaskResumeData
property of URLError.
There are a few requirements for
resumable downloads in URLSession.
Downloads inherently fetch data,
and should be safe to repeat,
so URLSession requires the download task
to have an HTTP GET request.
Other schemes or methods
are not supported.
Next, the server must support
byte-range requests
and advertise this
using the Accept-Ranges header.
The server must provide an ETag,
or Last-Modified field,
for the resource in the response,
but ETag is preferred.
And lastly, the temporary download file
must not have been deleted by the system
in response to disk space pressure.
With these requirements in place,
you can manually pause
and resume a download,
or even recover
from connection interruption.
Without a resumption protocol,
even a small interruption
forces you to restart your transfer
from the very beginning.
This is an even bigger problem
for uploads.
Upload speeds are often much slower
than download speeds,
so restarting means even more lost time
and resources.
iOS 17 introduces brand new support
for resumable upload tasks.
I'm super excited for these.
Now, upload tasks
are automatically resumable
if the server supports
the latest protocol draft.
Let's explore the new API first,
then dive-in to the details
of the resumable upload protocol.
Just like download tasks,
simply create an upload task
and start it by calling resume.
To pause,
upload tasks now support
the same cancelByProducingResumeData
method as download tasks.
The task automatically detects
if the server supports
the latest resumable upload protocol.
If the server does support it,
then you can store the resume data
for later use.
And finally, to resume your paused upload,
use the new
uploadTask withResumeData method.
You'll notice the pattern shown here
is identical to download tasks.
That means if you've already
created a great experience
for pausing and resuming downloads
in your app,
you can easily implement resumable uploads
for your users, too.
If there's just
a momentary network interruption,
but the server is still reachable,
URLSession will automatically try
to resume your upload.
No extra code is needed.
But in case of other,
broader connection issues,
like if your network or server
goes down entirely,
you can check the error for resume data,
just like download tasks.
I'm extremely happy to see
resumable uploads in URLSession,
and I hope you love them, too.
But in order for you to take advantage
of this feature,
your server must also support
the latest resumable upload protocol.
This protocol
is currently being developed,
and there are efforts across the industry
to standardize it in the IETF.
In the protocol, the client is able
to automatically discover server support.
This means URLSession can attempt
to make ALL uploads resumable
on the very first request.
If the server does not support
resumable uploads,
the request simply continues
as a regular upload.
Let's see how it works on the wire.
The client first sends a request
to an upload endpoint.
The Upload-Incomplete field
indicates that this client
supports resumable uploads.
The question mark zero is what's known
as a structured field boolean,
and it represents the value false.
This means that all of the upload data
is included in the body of this request.
If the server supports resumable uploads,
it detects the client's header
and advertises its own support
using a 104 informational response.
The 104 response contains
a location field with a resume URL.
This resume URL is used
to uniquely identify the upload,
so the client knows where to resume the
upload if the connection is interrupted.
The server associates the upload data
it receives with this unique resume URL.
If the upload finishes
without interruption, then great.
The server sends a 201 and it's done.
However, if the upload is interrupted,
the client and server perform
the resumable upload procedures.
The server has stored the partial upload
for the resume URL,
but the client needs a way to determine
how much data the server actually got.
To do this, the client sends
a HEAD request to the resume URL,
asking the server for the upload offset.
This offset is the true number of bytes
the server has received.
The server then responds with the upload
offset for the client's specific upload.
And lastly,
the client needs to acknowledge
the server's offset
and send the remaining data.
To do this,
the client sends a PATCH request
to the resume URL
with a matching upload offset.
The body of this request
contains the upload data
starting from the given offset.
With that, the client has finally sent
all the data to the server,
completing the upload.
Your app gets all this for free
using upload tasks in URLSession.
Now, let's take a quick trip
to the server side
and explore how you can build your very
own resumable upload server with SwiftNIO.
For those of you already using SwiftNIO
on your server,
this section is for you.
Resumable uploads can be implemented
in any server,
but if your server already uses SwiftNIO,
there's a new package that makes it
really easy to add support.
Let's go over a quick example.
If you're not familiar, SwiftNIO is an
asynchronous network application framework
that works in your app and server.
In this sample code,
we're setting up an HTTP/2, server.
We've added two handlers to our server.
The codec translates HTTP/2 frames
into requests
our example handler can understand.
In the other direction, it takes
responses from the example handler
and codes them into HTTP/2 frames.
The ExampleChannelHandler
performs the basic routing
and logic for our server.
At first, we only support regular uploads.
Let's find out how easy it is to transform
our server to support resumable uploads.
First, we download
the NIOResumableUpload project,
add it as a dependency,
and import it in our code.
Then, we define
a resumable upload context.
This tells the handler
which upload endpoint to use
when generating resume URLs.
And lastly, we wrap our current handler
in the HTTPResumableUploadHandler.
This performs the resumable upload
procedures on top of our current logic.
For each upload, it generates a random
and secure resume URL
and associates this with the upload data.
If a connection is interrupted,
the handler holds on to any partial data
and responds to all
the resumable upload procedures for us.
Wow!
With just a few lines of code,
we've supercharged our server
to support resumable uploads.
For those of you using Swift on Server
already, try this out!
And for everybody regardless,
be sure to check out
the open-source sample code
from the link in the description.
The sample code also uses new HTTP types,
which allow you to use the same types
across your app
and your Swift on Server projects.
These data types were released
as an open-source package
in collaboration with SwiftNIO,
so check out the Swift blog to learn more
and provide your feedback.
You might have noticed
the resumable upload protocol
makes use of informational responses
using the 104 status code.
The new HTTP Types make it easy to support
these responses on the server side.
In your app, URLSession handles
the 104 response automatically
for resumable uploads.
But on top of that, URLSession now
provides a delegate method
didReceiveInformationalResponse.
This allows your app to handle
other intermediate responses
such as 102 Processing or 103 Early Hints.
Resumable protocols are a great way
to alleviate network interruptions
and save bandwidth.
Background URLSession can also be useful
when handling large file transfers.
Imagine your user wants to upload a huge
4K video from their latest ski trip.
If their connection gets interrupted,
you want to make sure to resume
the upload if possible.
You could do
all the error handling yourself.
Or, you can let background session
do it for you.
In fact, background session will handle
resumption automatically
for both download and upload tasks,
if the server supports it.
If a task is interrupted,
the system will try to resume the task
at increasing time intervals.
If the task cannot be resumed,
the system will automatically retry
the task from the beginning.
Maybe your user loses cell coverage
on the ski mountain,
or a snowstorm took out their Wi-Fi.
Background session always waits
for connectivity,
so tasks will be scheduled at some point
after the device connects
to the internet again.
While your user is uploading their video,
they might leave your app
or put their device away.
Maybe they're getting ready
to shred more some powder,
and they still expect
their upload to continue.
This specifically calls
for a background session.
Background tasks are scheduled
by the system,
so they run outside your app's process.
This means even if your app is suspended
or terminated by the system,
your network tasks continue reliably.
Use a background session for large
file transfers that might take a long time
and need to persist
when a user leaves your app.
Lastly, your user deserves the best
experience when they're in your app,
and that might mean scheduling less urgent
tasks to happen at a later time.
By using a background session,
you have several ways
to efficiently schedule network activity
and save resources for your user.
For tasks that don't need
to happen immediately,
consider setting the isDiscretionary
property to true
on your background configuration.
This allows the system
to intelligently schedule your tasks,
taking into account factors like
"Is the user on Wi-Fi",
"is their device connected to power",
and "is the network constrained"?
This can be a great option
when downloading assets for later use,
or uploading a nightly backup,
or analytics.
To prevent using too much bandwidth
on Low Data Mode,
consider setting
the allowsConstrainedNetworkAccess
property to false.
Check out the Advances
in Networking session
for more tips on supporting
Low Data Mode in your app.
You can also schedule the background task
itself to begin at a later time,
when a person is less likely
to be using system resources.
Late at night is often a great time
for scheduling tasks like large backups.
To further assist the system scheduling,
we can set the
countOfBytesClientExpectsToSend
and Receive properties.
By utilizing these properties,
you're empowering the system
to best allocate resources
and passing those benefits on
to your users.
Background session is a great tool
for large file transfers
that don't need to happen immediately
or transfers that should continue
when your app is suspended.
For smaller tasks, or tasks
that need to happen as soon as possible,
you can use a standard URLSession.
Make networking reliable for your users
by bringing the power of resumption
to your app.
Check out SwiftNIO and HTTP Types,
and let's work together to create
the best HTTP experience in Swift.
And lastly, try using background session
for large or discretionary file transfers.
You'll find lots of ways to save resources
for when your user needs it most.
Thanks for watching,
and be sure to check out
these other
great networking sessions below.
And that's a wrap!
♪ ♪