♪ ♪
David: Hi, and welcome to
"What's new in Wallet and Apple Pay."
My name is David.
Jon: And I'm Jon.
David: Today,
we'll talk through all the new features
and enhancements
we're introducing this year
to the Wallet
and Apple Pay experience.
Wallet and Apple Pay encompasses a wide
range of features and functionality,
barcode passes,
transit cards, car keys, and more.
These are all important parts
of our ecosystem,
but today's focus will be on three areas:
Payments, Order Tracking, and Identity.
Let's start with Payments.
We'll first talk about Apple Pay Later
and how you can integrate
merchandising support
for it within your platform.
We'll talk about some enhancements
to preauthorized payments
and then walk through a brand-new API
to support transferring funds
with Apple Pay.
Apple Pay Later
was introduced earlier this year
to customers in the United States
and allows users to split purchases
into four separate payments.
Users can then conveniently track
and manage these purchases
within Wallet.
While Apple Pay Later
does not require any integration,
we're introducing a new API that provides
a dedicated merchandising view
for inclusion within your UI.
Using this view indicates support
for Apple Pay Later,
and details
the experience a customer can expect.
You'll have the ability
to customize the style of the view
to better suit it
for the context it's displayed in.
When a user
selects this view to learn more,
you have a choice of how
Apple Pay Later is explained.
And this view will be available to
developers for both apps and on the web.
The merchandising view can be rendered
in four different display styles,
depending on context:
The standard style,
which briefly describes how
Apple Pay Later can be used to split
a purchase into multiple repayments.
A badge style,
indicating support in a concise way.
A checkout style,
designed to be placed alongside
other payment options
in your checkout flow.
And a price style, for use
alongside the total purchase price.
When a user interacts with this view,
they will be presented
with more information.
As a merchant, you have the ability
to choose between two different actions.
The "Learn More" action will present
an overview of Apple Pay Later
and explains the experience
a user would go through
if they select it as a payment method.
The "Calculator" action will still present
an explanation of Apple Pay Later,
but with a focus on the repayment
schedule the user would need to follow.
Let's take a look at incorporating
this view within your app.
Firstly, you'll want to check
whether the user is eligible
to use Apple Pay Later.
You can use the validate function
within PKPayLaterUtilities to do this.
You'll need to provide the amount
for the transaction,
as well as the locale required.
Once you've determined whether the user
is eligible to use Apple Pay Later,
you instantiate a PKPayLaterView,
with the same details provided
for the eligibility check.
If you wish to customize the style
and action of the view,
you can do so by changing
their respective properties.
We also provide a convenient SwiftUI view,
that allows you
to express Apple Pay Later acceptance
within your SwiftUI apps.
To use it,
you instantiate a PayLaterView,
and provide it
with the same information as before.
To customize the display style and action,
use the appropriate
view modifiers to do so.
And it's as simple as that.
If you want to support
the merchandising view on the web,
there are a few setup steps
you will need to perform first.
The API for displaying the view
is provided within the existing
Apple Pay JavaScript SDK,
but there are some new attributes
you may need to set when including it.
It's important to set
the crossorigin attribute
if you're required to support
Cross Origin Resource sharing requests.
Use the async attribute
to ensure the script loads
and executes independently
from your page's loading progress.
And lastly, a JWT is required
to authenticate requests to the API.
This token can be generated
on the Apple Developer portal.
Using the JavaScript SDK
couldn't be simpler.
Use the apple-pay-merchandising
element to represent the view.
The amount, country code, currency code,
and locale are required fields.
Just like the native API,
you can also customize other aspects
of the view as required.
Here are some best practices to follow
if you're incorporating
the Apple Pay Later merchandising view.
For apps, an entitlement
is required to use this view.
This can be obtained
on the Apple Developer portal.
For websites,
remember to register your domains
and obtain a JWT
for use when including the SDK.
This can also be done
on the Apple Developer portal.
Where possible, try to import
the SDK within the head element.
This will allow it
to run as soon as possible,
so the merchandising view is ready
for when your page has fully loaded.
The size of the view can be
customized for your needs,
but ensure that you follow
the sizing requirements.
And lastly, if your website
has a restrictive content security policy,
follow the recommended guidelines
to ensure the SDK can
be loaded across domains.
And that's a look at Apple Pay Later.
Next up, we'll talk
about preauthorized payments.
In iOS 16,
we introduced preauthorized payments.
Users are able to view and manage payments
they've preauthorized in Wallet,
and merchants are able to charge
the user according to the agreed terms.
We initially provided support
for recurring payments
and automatic reload payments.
We now also support deferred payments.
All three preauthorized payment types
are available for use in apps,
as well as on the web.
Deferred payments allow you
to charge either a fixed
or variable amount
at a particular date in the future.
If you have
a free cancellation cut off date,
you can specify this as part
of the request as well.
Examples where deferred payments
may be suitable include
when a customer
is booking a hotel reservation
or when they are pre-ordering an item.
Preauthorized payments take advantage
of Apple Pay merchant tokens.
They are tied to a user's Apple ID,
rather than an individual device.
This means for example,
if a user were to upgrade their device,
the token would still be valid for use.
Because of this, you will still be able
to use the token to charge their account,
making receiving payments
at a later date more reliable.
When performing a preauthorized payment,
merchant tokens are automatically issued
if the customer's payment card
supports them.
If the payment card doesn't
support merchant tokens,
the transaction will still go through
but will use
the traditional Apple Pay token
that is tied to an individual device.
To learn more
about Apple Pay merchant tokens,
check out last year's
What's new in Wallet and Apple Pay.
So let's take a look
at how to incorporate deferred payments
within your app.
First, we create
a PKDeferredPaymentSummaryItem,
which outlines a description of the charge
and the amount that will be taken.
You also set the date
for when the payment will be taken.
Next, we create
a PKDeferredPaymentRequest.
We provide it
with the summary item we just created,
along with other information
regarding the management of the payment.
If we have a billing agreement
we need to display to the user,
this can also be set
on the deferred payment request.
Once we have
the request created and configured,
we can then attach it
to our PKPaymentRequest.
For the payment summary items
on our request, we create another
PKDeferredPaymentSummaryItem
with the same amount and date as before.
But this time with a label
representing the name of the merchant.
We set this on the request,
and we're ready to present for payment.
As can be seen in this example,
the Apple Pay payment sheet will present
the deferred payment to the user
with information on the billing agreement
and when they can expect to be charged.
Now, there are
some important considerations to make
if you specify a free cancellation date.
When you provide a free cancellation date,
you are stating that any cancellations
before that point in time will be done
with no charge to the user.
Because of this, both the date and time
are important pieces of information.
You need to explicitly state the time zone
the cancellation policy applies in.
We have provided a separate property
to support this.
In the example below,
we have specified that the time zone
is Pacific Standard Time.
This is important
because your customer's time zone
might not match the cancellation policy's
time zone.
For example, when someone
is based in the United Kingdom,
booking a hotel in the United States.
When working with deferred payments,
here are some best practices to follow.
As mentioned previously, if you need
to describe a free cancellation policy,
carefully consider the date,
time, and time zone provided
to the deferred payment request.
Remember to include the deferred payment
within your summary items,
and ensure you set
the appropriate merchant name.
This is not done for you automatically.
When providing a billing agreement,
remember to keep it short.
The billing agreement text should only act
as a summary of key facts to consider
and should not replace any normal billing
or legal agreements in place.
Lastly, specify a token notification URL,
so you can be kept up to date
with lifecycle events
of the Apple Pay merchant token
if one has been issued.
And that's deferred payments.
Next, let's take a look at a brand-new way
to transfer funds with Apple Pay.
Traditionally with Apple Pay,
the payment sheet has always
been available for users
to add funds to an account.
New in iOS 17, we're introducing
Transfer Funds with Apple Pay.
This offers the ability for users
to transfer from an account
to a card in their Wallet, completing
the lifecycle for money movement.
This uses the same secure and private
Apple Pay infrastructure as payments,
meaning customers will already
be very familiar with the process.
An example
where transferring funds makes sense
would be allowing a customer
to withdraw funds from a bank account
or a stored value account.
To support Transfer Funds with Apple Pay,
we have created a new request type
that focuses on just the information
required for a funds transfer.
To use it,
you simply define an amount you wish
to be transferred
to a user's payment card.
If you require the contact details
of the recipient,
you are also able to request these.
If you've used PKPaymentRequest before,
this new API will feel
very familiar to you.
Because Transfer Funds
with Apple Pay works
on the same infrastructure as payments,
you will need to register as a merchant
within the Apple Developer portal.
To learn more
on how to register as a merchant
and get set up to use Apple Pay,
check out our "Implement Apple Pay
and order management" Tech Talk.
To give you an illustration of how
Transfer Funds with Apple Pay works,
let's take a look at an example.
Say we have a customer, Andrew, who wishes
to withdraw money from their account.
Using Transfer Funds with Apple Pay,
they would trigger a transfer
from within your app.
Your app then creates a request,
outlining the amount to be transferred.
Andrew will then be presented
with the Apple Pay sheet
detailing the transfer,
allowing them to select the card
they with to receive funds to.
Once Andrew
securely authenticates the transfer,
an encrypted payload is generated
and returned to your app,
ready for processing
with your payment provider.
Once the transfer has been processed,
your app will then return
the result to Apple Pay.
If the transfer is successful, that's it.
If an error has occurred,
Andrew would be informed and may be able
to take corrective action
to fix the issue.
Now that we've seen an overview
of how a funds transfer works,
lets take a look at how
to implement it within your app.
We first need to determine which networks
and card capabilities we wish to support.
Next, we'll check to see
whether the user has an eligible card
to initiate a funds transfer.
This is done through
PKPaymentAuthorizationController.
Using the supportsDisbursements method,
we provide the networks
and card capabilities defined earlier.
You can use the result of this check to
adjust your user interface as appropriate.
Now that we've checked for eligibility,
we can start
building our transfer request.
Similar to payment requests, the amounts
are defined through summary items.
In this case,
we create two different summary items.
The first is a PKPaymentSummaryItem.
This represents the amount
being withdrawn from the user's account.
It's important to note that the label
associated with the item,
should be the name of your business.
The second item is a new type
of summary item,
a PKDisbursementSummaryItem.
You must include one of these,
and it should always represent
the final amount received
onto the recipient's payment card,
net of any fees, charges, or adjustments.
Whereas for payments,
we have PKPaymentRequest,
we have a new request type
for Transfer Funds with Apple Pay,
PKDisbursementRequest.
In order to construct
a PKDisbursementRequest,
you need to specify certain details.
It requires the merchant identifier
you set when registering
for Apple Pay,
the currency of the transaction,
the region of your business,
as well as the networks
and capabilities defined earlier.
You also provide
the summary items you just created.
If you require the contact details
of the transfer recipient,
you can request those here as well.
You can also limit
which regions the recipient's payment card
has been issued in.
Once the request has been built,
we can now present it to the user.
We do this by initializing an instance
of PKPaymentAuthorizationController
with our disbursement request.
We set ourselves as a delegate,
and then present.
As can be seen here,
the user is presented with the option
to select the payment card
they wish to receive the transfer to
and the amount
they will receive to that card.
Now, once the user securely authorizes
the transfer to take place,
there are some delegate callbacks
that will need to be implemented
to process the transfer.
There are only two delegate methods
that are required
to be implemented to handle
Transfer Funds with Apple Pay.
The first is
paymentAuthorizationControllerDidFinish.
This will be called
when the sheet is ready to dismiss.
The responsibility is
on the calling app to dismiss it.
You can also use this method
to change your own app's UI accordingly.
Secondly, is the didAuthorizePayment
delegate method.
Because Transfer Funds with Apple Pay
uses the same infrastructure as payments,
you'll receive the same type
of PKPayment object to use for processing.
Here we've abstracted the processing
of the token away
into our own processFundsTransfer method.
Depending on the result of processing,
you would either return a success
or failure.
If during the processing stage
there are errors encountered,
we have provided a set
of convenience methods to represent these.
You can use
disbursementContactInvalidError
for when there are issues relating
to the contact information provided.
If your payment processor determines
that the user's payment card is unable
to accept fund transfers, you can use
disbursementCardUnsupportedError.
Some financial institutions
support instant funds transfers,
where funds can be sent
to the recipient more quickly.
These can also be represented
with Transfer Funds with Apple Pay.
Depending on the service,
these instant transfers can sometimes
include fees,
which can also be represented.
Typically, a user will be given a choice
of transfer speed within your app.
When a user chooses
to transfer funds instantly,
provide the capability
to require support for them.
When doing so,
the user's choice of cards will be limited
to those that are known
to support instant transfers.
And this is what an instant transfer
would look like.
The sheet looks very similar to before,
but now we highlight the fact
the transfer is instant, as well
as any fee the user will be paying.
The transfer amount has also been
adjusted to take into account the fee.
Let's see how to make the previous
transfer request an instant one.
Firstly, we add instantFundsOut,
to our list of supported capabilities.
We can then check
within supportsDisbursements
whether the user has any cards
that support instant transfers.
You can then adjust your transfer method
options and user interface accordingly.
As for summary items,
we have a dedicated item
to represent instant transfer fees,
PKInstantFundsOutFeeSummaryItem.
With this item, you specify
the amount that will be charged
for the purposes
of performing an instant transfer.
Even if you don't charge a fee,
this summary item is still required.
In this case,
you would set an amount of zero.
Because in this example,
we are charging a fee,
we need to update
the disbursement amount accordingly.
This won't be done automatically for you.
Creating the PKDisbursementRequest
isn't too different from before.
The only difference is
to ensure you provide the capabilities
and summary items defined earlier.
And that's all that's required
to represent an instant transfer.
Here are some best practices
to keep in mind
when implementing
Transfer Funds with Apple Pay.
Note that Transfer Funds with Apple Pay
is only available for iOS and iPadOS,
and is unavailable
for use on macOS or the web.
If an error were to occur
during the processing of a funds transfer,
use one
of the dedicated disbursement errors
in order to communicate this
to the user effectively.
It's important to note
that the first summary item should
represent the amount that will
be withdrawn from the user's account.
The label of the first summary item
should match that of your business.
And the last summary item must represent
the amount that will be received
by the user's payment card,
net of any fees, charges, or adjustments.
And that's everything
we have today regarding payments.
To change tracks a little bit,
let's talk about Order Tracking.
Order Tracking was introduced in iOS 16
as a way for users to track orders
placed with participating merchants.
The response
from users has been fantastic,
and we have been hard at work
making Order Tracking even better.
We'll talk about how we've improved
integration within the operating system
to better represent
and communicate orders.
We'll then go through some enhancements
we've made to Order Tracking.
And lastly, we are introducing
new ways to add Orders to Wallet.
In iOS 16.4,
we added support for sharing orders
through Messages,
providing an inline preview of the order,
and the ability for the recipient
to track it within Wallet.
We also introduced
an Order Tracking widget,
where users can keep a track
of orders at a glance.
Users can already benefit
from these new features
without any additional work needed.
We are continuing
with system integration in iOS 17
with support for Maps.
If a user is tracking an order with
a specified pick up time and location,
Maps will proactively suggest it
through Siri Suggestions.
Now let's take a look at some
of the enhancements we've made
to Order Tracking in iOS 17.
To better support courier
and food delivery use cases,
you can now indicate the type
of shipping being used.
Through the new shippingType property,
you can declare whether an order
is being shipped or delivered.
We now have better support
for associated applications,
including enterprise apps.
By declaring your associated application identifiers,
you can improve the management
of order notifications
between your app and Order Tracking.
In addition, we support
custom product page identifiers,
enabling a deep-link
to your App Store product page
most relevant for Wallet traffic.
Lastly, we are introducing new ways
to represent payment information.
Order packages now support an array
of transactions associated with it,
with each having
its own detailed information,
such as payment method and amount.
You can also attach receipt files
to transactions,
so your customer has a record of payment.
This receipt file can either be a PDF
or an image such as JPEG or PNG.
Keep in mind that order packages
are limited in size,
so be considerate for the size
of the receipt files you include.
You can now also describe
whether a transaction is for a purchase
or a refund.
With iOS 17, adding Orders
into Wallet has never been simpler.
You can now attach
order packages to emails,
such as the order confirmation email.
The user will then be able to add
the order to Wallet right then and there.
In addition, you can also
add a “Track with Apple Wallet” button
within your apps and websites.
Let's take a look
at the new Order Tracking API
that supports adding orders to Wallet.
This API is included within two new
frameworks, FinanceKit and FinanceKitUI.
These two Swift exclusive frameworks
will allow developers
to handle order data within Wallet.
Access to order information is achieved
through a shared instance of FinanceStore,
providing a central resource
for handling order tracking queries.
With this API, you will be able to check
for the existence of an order,
as well as a way
to add or update an order.
Let's take a look
at how you check for an existing order.
You first query the FinanceStore
to check whether it contains an order
with a fully qualified order identifier.
You will then receive one
of two responses,
either it exists,
or it has not been found.
You can then respond in your app
as appropriate.
It's as simple as that.
If you want to add or update an order,
you can do this in one of two ways.
We'll first show
how you use FinanceKit to do this.
You will first need a Data serialization
of the signed order package
you wish to add to Wallet.
You then provide this
to FinanceStore's save order method.
When you do this,
a screen is presented to the user
to verify the order's contents and whether
they wish to track it within Wallet.
Once a user has either confirmed
or denied the request,
you will receive
the result asynchronously,
and it can take three forms.
Either they've added the order to Wallet,
they cancelled the request,
or a newer order already exists.
If your app is written with SwiftUI,
you can use FinanceKitUI.
This provides a dedicated
"Track with Apple Wallet" button
and allows you to process
the result of adding the order.
Like with FinanceKit,
you will first need a serialized instance
of your signed order package.
You then include
AddOrderToWalletButton within your view.
When a user selects this button,
they will be offered the ability
to add the order to their Wallet.
You are then able to respond to the three
results states, just like before.
For merchants who want to support
customers tracking an order on the web,
we offer a version of this button
in the JavaScript SDK.
To use this,
you insert an apple-wallet-button
and configure it using attributes.
The type of button should
be set to track-order.
When using this button,
it's important to set the onClick callback
to point to the location of
the signed order package you wish to add.
And that's what we have for you
today on Order Tracking.
We can't wait for you to adopt
these new APIs in your apps and services.
And now
for something completely different,
we have some exciting updates
to share regarding Identity,
and for that, I'll hand over to Jon.
Jon: Thanks, David.
Hello again.
I'm Jon, an engineer
on the Apple Pay and Wallet team.
I'm so excited to talk
about the new functionality
we've added for Identity in iOS 17.
We introduced IDs
in Wallet back in iOS 15.4,
enabling users in supported U.S. states
to add their driver's license
or state ID to Wallet.
Last year,
we introduced Verify with Wallet.
With this API,
businesses can streamline their onboarding
and account verification flows
by requesting information
from a user's ID stored in Apple Wallet.
This year, in iOS 17, we're introducing
Tap to Present ID on iPhone.
With this API, your apps
can seamlessly and securely verify IDs
in Wallet or other mobile
driver's licenses using just your iPhone.
This builds on top
of the Tap to Pay on iPhone API,
which we added to the ProximityReader
framework in iOS 15.4.
Tap to Pay on iPhone provides a secure,
private, and easy way
to accept contactless payments
without the need
for additional hardware
or payment terminals.
Now, let's take a look
at Tap to Present ID in action.
Suppose I work for Spaceship Rentals
and that David would like
to rent a spaceship from us.
He needs to be
at least 21 years old to do this,
so I'm going to perform an age
verification using Tap to Present ID.
First, the Spaceship Rentals app
invokes Tap to Present ID.
My iPhone will show the business' name,
logo, and the type of request
being performed,
in this case, proof of age.
I'll now invite David
to hold his iPhone near mine.
[phone chimes]
David: My iPhone now displays
a consent sheet that I can review.
I can see that I'm presenting
my ID to Spaceship Rentals,
and they are requesting my ID photo
and whether I'm over 21.
I'm willing to present this information,
so I'll double click
and confirm with Face ID.
[phone clicks]
Jon: My iPhone now shows
the information David presented.
I see that he matches his ID photo
and that he's over 21.
So now he's ready for takeoff.
I've just successfully verified David's ID
using the Tap to Present ID API.
This experience offered some key benefits
compared to checking a physical ID.
First, the ID information
itself is verified.
Unlike physical IDs,
which are susceptible to tampering,
mobile driver's licenses
are cryptographically signed
by the issuing authority,
and iOS verifies the signature,
so you can trust the response.
Second, the experience
was wireless and secure.
At no point did David need
to hand over his iPhone to me
or even unlock it,
and the data was sent securely
using NFC and Bluetooth.
Finally, this is a more private way
to verify an ID.
David only needed to share the information
necessary to verify his age,
unlike with a physical ID,
where everything is shared.
Let's talk about the types of requests
you can perform with this API.
We just demoed the display request.
This is suitable for when you need
to verify a person's name or age.
The result is shown in the system UI,
and no ID information
is returned to your app.
The API also supports data requests.
These can request a wider set
of document elements,
such as address, date of birth,
and driving privileges,
and the result is returned to your app
to process.
To perform data requests,
your app will need
an additional entitlement.
Check the documentation
for more information.
Now, let's have a look
at how to implement this in code,
starting with a display request.
First, use the isSupported class property
on MobileDocumentReader
to check whether the current device
supports this API.
If it does, instantiate a reader object
and call its prepare method.
This will return
a MobileDocumentReaderSession object.
Next,
create a driver's license display request
with the elements you want to verify.
Here, I'm verifying whether
the holder of the driver's license
is at least 21 years old.
Then call requestDocument on the session,
passing in the request.
The reader UI will then be shown,
first prompting the ID holder
to present their device, and then
displaying the result of the request.
Keep in mind,
as this is a display request,
nothing is returned
from the requestDocument method.
And with just a few lines of code,
you've added mobile document
reading capability to your app.
By default,
the name and logo of your brand
isn't displayed on either
the reader iPhone or ID holder's device.
However, if you wish
to display your brand information
during a document request, you can.
This can be configured
through Apple Business Register
and with a few more lines of code.
To show your brand information
during document requests,
you'll need to pass in a reader token
when preparing your device.
You'll need
to create this token on your server.
A reader token is a JWT,
signed with a key pair you've configured
through Apple Business Register.
Your server will create the reader token
with your brand ID, key ID,
and a reader instance identifier.
The brand and key IDs can be obtained
through Apple Business Register
and are the same
across all instances of your app.
Your app will provide the reader
instance identifier to your server.
Back in the code, your app
will fetch the reader instance identifier
from MobileDocumentReader's
configuration object
and send it to your server
in exchange for a reader token.
Pass this token into the prepare method
to obtain a reader session.
Then create a request
and call requestDocument just as before.
And now your brand's name and logo
will be displayed
on both the reader iPhone
and ID holder's device.
And that covers the display request.
So far, we've looked at how
to prepare a session, request a document,
and how to use a reader token
to show your branding information.
Now let's look at how
to perform a data request.
These requests support a wider range
of document elements,
and the API returns the result
to your app,
instead of just displaying it.
To use this request type,
you'll first need to prepare your device
with a reader token, just like before.
Then create
a driver's license data request,
specifying the document elements
to be requested
and whether
you intend to retain the information.
Calling requestDocument
will show the reader UI
just like with the display request,
but once the read has completed,
the UI is automatically dismissed.
The response is then returned
to your app to process.
And that's Tap to Present ID on iPhone,
an exciting new API we've added
to the ProximityReader framework.
And now, back over to David.
David: Thanks Jon!
So what have we learned today?
We've taken a look
at enhancements to payments
with support for Apple Pay Later
and new use cases.
Order Tracking's new APIs allow you
to add Orders to Wallet
from within your apps and services,
and there's a new way
to verify mobile driver's licenses
with Tap to Present ID on iPhone.
To wrap up, if you're a business,
consider enrolling
on Apple Business Register.
This will help enrich the Wallet and
Apple Pay experience for your customers.
You can visit the Apple Developer forums,
where you can ask questions
and get help all year round.
And lastly, if you have any feedback,
we'd love to hear from you.
You can do this
by using Feedback Assistant.
And that's it.
We hope you've enjoyed this session.
both: Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪