♪ ♪
James: Hello.
I'm James Magahern from UIKit,
and I'll be your guide through what's new
with text and text interactions.
Text plays a crucial role
in every application.
It's the primary way
to consume information and communicate.
Now we're giving you even more tools
to create a powerful
text experience in your app,
whether you're starting from scratch
or from high-level abstractions.
I'll be going over a bunch of great
improvements to crafting text experiences
and how to take advantage of them
in your apps,
including some changes
to system selection UI,
adding text item actions and menus
to UITextViews,
lists and bullets in TextKit 2,
dictation UI on macOS,
and some important updates
for internationalization.
We'll begin by talking
about some changes to selection UI.
New on all our platforms
is a completely redesigned text cursor.
We now display an inline,
interactive switcher
when changing input languages,
more ergonomic selection handles
when doing range selection,
and we also have a completely new loupe
to make it easier to place the cursor
in large bodies of text.
If your app is using UITextViews
or UITextFields,
then you'll get
all this new UI automatically.
Additionally, we made sure
that clients of UITextInteraction
also get the new selection UI.
However, if you have a highly customized
UI for displaying text,
it can be challenging to keep up with
these changes in your own implementation,
especially if you aren't able
to adopt UITextInteraction.
That's why in iOS 17, we've added
UITextSelectionDisplayInteraction,
which just provides the selection UI
without the gestures included
with UITextInteraction.
UITextSelectionDisplayInteraction is a new
type of UIInteraction
that can be installed on any UIView.
You must also provide an object
that implements the UITextInput protocol,
which defines various methods
for the interaction
to obtain selection state from your view.
UITextSelectionDisplayInteraction will
then do all the heavy lifting for you,
providing the cursor view
and cursor accessories,
as well as the range highlight
and selection handles.
All of these views are replaceable too,
so you can customize the behavior
if you need to.
Here's a quick look at an example
of how to do this in code.
First, create a selection display
interaction
and provide it with your document object
that implements the UITextInput protocol.
This can be the same as your view,
if applicable.
Next, simply add the interaction
to the view you want to display
the selection UI inside of.
This can be a container view
or the view that renders your document.
Whenever the selection state changes,
just make sure
to call setNeedsSelectionUpdate
on the interaction,
and the interaction will take care
of updating all the views
to reflect your new selection state.
In addition
to UITextSelectionDisplayInteraction,
we've also added a new API
for displaying a loupe.
It can be used on any view,
and UITextSelectionDisplayInteraction
or UITextInput isn't required to use it.
It's recommended to use
a gesture recognizer,
such as UIPanGestureRecognizer,
to drive the loupe's updates.
Here's how to manage
a loupe session in code.
When using a pan gesture recognizer,
in the callback, grab the gesture's
location and selection widget,
in this case, the cursor view.
Next, if the gesture is beginning,
create a new UITextLoupeSession
by calling begin(at:),
providing the loupe's starting location,
selection widget, and coordinate space.
Then when the gesture moves around,
call move(to:) on the existing
loupe session to update its location.
Lastly, when the gesture recognizer ends,
make sure to call invalidate
on the loupe session to dismiss it.
Next I'd like to go over text item actions
and how you can use them
to display menus inside of text views.
Text item interactions in UITextView
are now much more customizable
using new APIs on UITextViewDelegate.
These new additions make it possible to
modify the primary action for text items
or present a menu like the candidate menu
shown here in the Translate app.
Previously, UITextView allows developers
to disable item interactions
through the shouldInteractWith APIs
on UITextViewDelegate
for links and attachments.
In iOS 17, you now have the ability
to customize item interactions
for text items in text views.
UITextViewDelegate has gained new methods
to customize both the primary action,
or provide a menu for specific text items.
Here's a quick review
of what text items actually are
and how they integrate with your app.
Text items represent the content
that support item interactions.
This includes text attachments,
represented by NSTextAttachment,
and links,
represented by NSLinkAttributeName.
UITextItem now also supports tagging
custom ranges of text for interaction.
To tag a range for interaction,
use the UITextItemTagAttributeName
on the attributed string
representing the range of text
you wish to make interactive.
With these new APIs,
it is now possible to change
the default tap or menu behavior
when a text item is interacted with.
For instance, you might want
to redirect known links
to existing views within the app
or add custom menus to parts of the text.
To continue to suppress or disable
the primary action or menu,
simply return nil
for the menuConfiguration
or primaryAction delegate methods.
Here's a small code example
demonstrating how to show a menu
in response to the user tapping on a link
inside of your UITextView.
Just implement the
menuConfigurationFor:defaultMenu: method
from UITextViewDelegate
and return a menu configuration
containing the menu you wish to display.
You may also provide a preview
as part of the menu configuration
to show inline
with the rest of the context menu.
List and bullet support have also been
added to TextKit 2.
I'll go over how you can take advantage
of this in your application.
In addition to supporting multiple
different kinds of bulleted items,
roman numeral, alphabetical,
and decimal ordering is also supported.
Each one will automatically be localized
based on the device
or app's configured locale,
so worldwide internationalization
is built right in.
Here's a quick example
of how you can get started with text lists
using attributed strings.
Use the textLists property
on NSParagraphStyle
to define which paragraph
has an ordered list applied to it.
The system will automatically
number the items
based on line terminating characters
like newlines,
and UITextView will automatically
propagate the paragraph style
based on typing attributes.
There are some big changes in the way
dictation works on macOS Sonoma.
We have some new APIs
to help you make sure
your custom text elements work well
with the new design.
This is how the new dictation indicator
behaves on macOS 14.
Like on iOS, dictation has a trailing
glow effect while speaking,
and a microphone indicator appears
when at rest.
Notice that after scrolling, the indicator
next to the cursor will stick
to the edge of the scroll view,
and offer a button
to return to the current position
in the document.
If you're using a standard text control
in AppKit like NSTextView,
you'll get this behavior
right out of the box.
If your app offers
a customized implementation
for showing the insertion point,
there's a little bit of work
you'll need to do
to support this new behavior.
Similar to
UITextSelectionDisplayInteraction for iOS,
there's now a new API for macOS
that also allows you to remain consistent
with the system's selection UI.
Instead of drawing your own cursor,
adopt NSTextInsertionIndicator,
which is a customizable NSView subclass
that you can place
inside of your document's view
to indicate the cursor position.
Its appearance is customizable.
You can change the color and size.
By default, it will follow
the current accent color.
It makes supporting the dictation effects
really easy.
There's just a little bit
of configuration required
to allow the system to insert
the appropriate views into your hierarchy.
Here's how to get started
using NSTextInsertionIndicator on macOS.
Simply create an NSTextInsertionIndicator
view and add it as a subview
to whatever view is displaying
the contents of your document.
Once you've done that,
set effectsViewInserter to a block
that inserts views provided by your system
into your document's view hierarchy.
The system will automatically take care
of positioning the effect views
and making sure they get updated
as the insertion indicator moves around.
When your custom text view resigns
responder status,
make sure to hide the cursor
by setting displayMode to hidden.
As text is inserted, updates to the frame
will automatically be animated
with a glow effect if dictation is used
as the input source.
If you need to disable the glow effect,
remove the showEffectsView option
from automaticModeOptions.
When the user changes input modes,
an effect view is displayed
beneath the cursor in horizontal text
to show the language selection UI.
If you need to override
the placement of this UI,
you can specify
preferredTextAccessoryPlacement
in your implementation
of NSTextInputClient.
The system checks
the value of this property
to determine
where to draw the accessories.
When the text cursor is scrolled offscreen
during dictation,
the system will also display
a scroll-away indicator
to indicate the relative position
of the cursor
and offer an affordance
to get back to the dictation point.
To make sure this behavior is supported
in your custom text view,
make sure to adopt NSTextInputClient
and implement the selectionRect
and documentVisibleRect properties.
Notify the system
about scrolling beginning and ending
by calling
textInputClientWillStartScrollingOrZooming
and willEndScrollingOrZooming.
Making sure your app works well
in every language is crucial
to providing
an outstanding text experience.
We've made some important changes
to standard text controls,
enhancing their readability and ergonomics
across a broader range of languages.
Supporting dynamic type in your apps
goes a long way
towards improving the layout of your UI
in every language.
Something important to consider
when laying out text elements in your app
is the fact that many languages can have
variable line heights
in addition to layout direction
and font styles.
A common issue encountered
when dealing with variable line heights
between languages is the problem
of clipped text.
Not only does this look bad, but it can
also drastically impact readability
and significantly hinder
the overall user experience of your app.
These issues may be difficult to notice,
especially if you aren't able
to test your app in every language.
We've made some improvements
to standard text elements,
like UITextField and UILabel,
to address this problem automatically
in most cases.
However, there are some best practices
that you should still make sure to follow
to ensure the system can prevent
clipping of these elements.
To prevent these common clipping issues,
all our platforms will now automatically
adjust the line height
in UILabel or UITextField
to accommodate languages
with highly dynamic line heights.
This new behavior takes place
only in specific cases.
First, keep in mind
that line heights are now dependent
on the device's configured
preferred languages.
Second, this adjustment affects
the entire user interface,
increasing line heights
for all text elements,
even those that display scripts
with fixed line heights, like English,
which wouldn't normally require
the extra space.
This is intentional
to ensure visual consistency
across all text elements.
Lastly, this automatic adjustment
only applies
to text elements that use text styles.
Custom fonts will continue
to use their fixed line heights.
This behavior isn't entirely new,
as it has been in effect
for several releases.
However, in iOS 17 it's much more dynamic,
and the exact adjustment depends
on both the text style and language used.
To take advantage of this behavior,
adopt Text Styles
by creating a UIFont explicitly with
the preferredFont(forTextStyle:) method
and assign it to a text element,
like UILabel.
Next, avoid setting clipsToBounds
on text elements.
Ascenders and descenders for languages
like Thai and Hindi will often protrude
beyond the line height bounds.
This is generally acceptable
in most layouts,
since there's usually extra space
around neighboring elements,
but it does mean
that setting clipsToBounds will result
in those text elements being clipped.
UIKit has also been updated
to prevent unnecessary use of this setting
where it was previously enabled
by default.
Lastly, ensure that your UIs
are responsive to changes in height
and that all other controls
remain aligned,
as text elements can now grow vertically.
We also made substantial enhancements
to line-breaking behavior
for languages such as Chinese,
German, Japanese, and Korean.
These improvements apply different rules
based on what kind of text style
you're using in your UI
and which language is being displayed.
For instance, previously,
a word within Korean text
might have been split between lines.
Now UIKit prevents such splitting
for title text styles,
ensuring a more seamless
reading experience.
To benefit from this new behavior
in your app,
similarly adopt Text Styles.
So that's everything you need to know
to create a powerful text experience
in your app on iOS 17.
If you're using a custom text view
in your app,
make sure to use the system selection UI
to take advantage
of all the new features in the OS.
Use text items
to create better interactions
with links in your text views.
Leverage the powerful new features
of TextKit 2
to provide a more rich
text editing experience.
And adopt Text Styles
in common text elements
to ensure a great user experience
for everyone,
regardless of what language
or preferred text size.
That's all for now.
Thanks for watching.
Be sure to rate five stars
and leave a comment down below.
♪ ♪