♪ ♪
Pawel Szczerbuk:
Hello, my name is Pawel Szczerbuk,
and I'm a GPU Software Engineer.
Metal can help you scale
your ray tracing applications
to complex and detailed scenes.
Ray tracing is fundamental to image
fidelity in production rendering
while ray tracing in games
focuses on high frame rates
while improving visual quality.
This image of Disney's Moana Island Scene
was rendered with Metal ray tracing.
Today I am going to talk about
how to use Metal ray tracing.
I will highlight some exciting
new features you can use
to accelerate ray tracing in games
and production renderers.
Ray tracing applications
simulate individual rays of light
bouncing around a scene
To render with Metal ray tracing,
the first step is to define
your scene geometry.
Then Metal builds
an Acceleration Structure
that contains your geometry
and can be efficiently queried
for intersections using GPU acceleration.
In a GPU function,
create a ray to intersect with your scene.
Make an intersector object in your shader
and provide it
with both your ray
and the acceleration structure.
This returns an intersection result,
with all the information you may need
to either shade the pixel,
or process it further.
Each of these pieces work together
to enable you to build your scene,
use instancing to add visual complexity,
and perform ray intersection.
And there are some amazing tools
at your disposal
to help you work
with ray tracing applications.
It all starts with building your scene.
The Metal ray tracing API supports
a few different types of geometry.
All of this geometry is stored
in an acceleration structure.
An acceleration structure speeds up
the ray tracing process
by recursively partitioning the geometry.
This allows for quick elimination
of any geometry
that does not intersect with the ray.
You can set up an acceleration structure
in three steps.
Create an acceleration structure
descriptor,
where you will provide
your actual geometry.
Once you have the descriptor,
you can allocate
the acceleration structure,
and then build it.
An acceleration structure descriptor
contains one or more geometry descriptors.
There are three types of geometry
descriptors available in Metal.
Triangles are the primitives
we all know and love,
used to model almost everything
in computer graphics.
Bounding box primitives
are entirely defined
by your custom intersection function
that Metal will call when a ray hits
an enclosing bounding box.
And new this year, curves.
These are great
for rendering hair and fur.
To create an acceleration
structure using triangles,
create a triangle geometry descriptor
for an individual piece of geometry.
You'll provide a vertex buffer,
index buffer, and triangle count.
Bounding box geometry
works in a similar way,
except instead of vertices,
you provide the bounding boxes
that enclose your geometry.
Additionally,
you provide an intersection function
which Metal will invoke when
a ray hits your bounding box primitive.
For more details about how
to set up the intersection function,
see the 2020
"Discover ray tracing with Metal" talk.
Geometry such as hair, fur, and vegetation
can have thousands
or even millions of primitives.
These are typically modeled
as fine, smooth curves.
Instead of using triangles
to approximate these curves,
you can use Metal's new curve primitives.
These curves will remain smooth
even as the camera zooms in.
And compared to triangles,
curves have a more compact
memory footprint
and allow faster
acceleration structure builds.
A full curve is made of a series
of connected curve segments.
Every segment on a curve
is its own primitive,
and Metal assigns each segment
a unique primitive ID.
Each of these segments
is defined by a series of control points,
which control the shape of the curve.
These control points are interpolated
using a set of basis functions.
Depending on the basis function,
each curve segment can have
2, 3, or 4 control points.
Metal offers four
different curve basis functions:
Bezier,
Catmull-Rom,
B-Spline,
and Linear.
Each of these basis functions
has their own benefits,
so choose the best one for your use case.
Metal also requires
a control point index buffer.
Each curve segment has one index
in this buffer
representing the first control point
for the segment.
For example,
say you have four control points.
You define a curve segment using the index
of its first control point,
so add a zero to the index buffer.
This example is using
Catmull-Rom basis function,
so the actual curve segment is only
defined between control points 1 and 2.
All you need to do to connect
another curve segment
is add one more control point.
This additional curve segment
uses control points 1 through 4,
so add a 1 to the index buffer.
These two curve segments share 3 control
points because of the index buffer,
which is one reason
curves are able to save memory.
Repeat this as many times as needed
to finish the curve.
To start a new curve,
simply add additional control points
which don't overlap
the previous control points
and add the corresponding index
to the index buffer.
So far the curves I've described
have been abstract mathematical objects.
In order to render them,
they need to have some kind of 3D shape.
Each control point also has a radius
which is interpolated
along the length of the curve.
By default, curves are rendered
with a 3D cylindrical cross section.
This is great for curves
that will be seen from close-up.
For curves
that will only be seen from far away,
Metal also supports flat curves.
This can improve performance
whenever you don't need full 3D geometry.
Similar to triangles and bounding boxes,
curve geometry is represented
with a curve geometry descriptor.
Attach the buffers
containing your control points,
the corresponding radii,
and control point indices.
Set the number of control points
in the control point buffer,
as well as the number
of actual curve segments.
This should be the same as the number
of indices in the index buffer.
Specify what kind of curves you are using.
This example uses round Bezier curves
with 4 control points per curve segment.
That's all you need to do
to set up a curve geometry descriptor.
Now that you've created
your geometry descriptors,
you can set up
the acceleration structure descriptor.
Use the primitive acceleration
structure descriptor
for primitive geometry like triangles,
bounding boxes, and curves.
Add the geometry descriptor
to the acceleration structure descriptor.
Multiple geometry descriptors can be added
to a single acceleration structure
to combine the geometry.
When you have your acceleration structure
descriptor ready,
you can allocate memory
for the acceleration structure.
Metal gives you full control over when
and where this memory is allocated.
This is a two-part operation.
First calculate the size of the objects
needed for the build.
The Metal device provides a method
to calculate the required allocation size
for an acceleration structure.
Although it's possible to allocate storage
for acceleration structures
directly from the Metal device,
allocating them from a heap
will allow you to reduce resource
management overhead later.
The heap may have additional size
and alignment requirements,
which you can query using another method
on the Metal device.
With these sizes
you can now allocate memory
to store the acceleration structure.
This storage is represented by
an MTL Acceleration Structure object.
To allocate one of these objects,
call the make Acceleration Structure
method
on a heap or Metal device,
passing the size.
You will also allocate some scratch memory
which Metal will use
while building the acceleration structure.
Since this memory only needs
to be accessed by the GPU,
you can do this by allocating a private
storage mode buffer from the Metal device.
Now you're ready to actually build
the acceleration structure.
Schedule the build operation,
and then Metal will build the acceleration
for you on the GPU.
You do this using an acceleration
structure command encoder.
This encoder has several methods
that you can use
to build and modify
acceleration structures.
In this case, call the build method with
the destination acceleration structure,
the descriptor, and the scratch buffer.
Metal will build the primitive
acceleration structure for your geometry,
and it will be available for use
in subsequent GPU commands.
That's how you can represent
the geometry in your scene
with a primitive acceleration structure.
To help you scale to larger scenes,
Metal also supports
instance acceleration structures.
It would take an enormous amount
of memory to store a complex,
detailed environment
like the Moana island scene
in a single primitive
acceleration structure.
But this intricate scene
has a repetitive structure
in the thousands of trees,
millions of leaves, and other objects,
which can be exploited
to render the scene efficiently.
All unique objects in the scene,
including the mountains, corals,
and trees,
can be represented
as primitive acceleration structures.
These can be combined into an instance
acceleration structure
representing the whole scene.
So while a primitive acceleration
structure contains geometry,
an instance acceleration structure
contains references
to other acceleration structures,
transformed to different positions, sizes,
and orientations to compose a full scene.
Each instance has a transformation matrix
to place the acceleration structure
that it references in the scene.
Building an instance acceleration
structure is similar
to building
a primitive acceleration structure.
You will start by creating a descriptor.
This time, instead of geometry,
you provide a buffer containing
information about each instance,
like the acceleration structure
it references,
and the transformation matrix
that places it in the scene.
Then build the acceleration structure
on the GPU
in the same way that you build
a primitive acceleration structure.
To create the descriptor, construct an MTL
Instance Acceleration Structure Descriptor
and set the number of instances
it will contain.
Then provide an array
of the primitive acceleration structures,
which can be referenced by instances,
and specify
which type of instance descriptor
will be contained in the instance buffer.
Metal offers several instance descriptor
types which you can choose from,
depending on your use-case.
You will configure the instances in
the acceleration structure in two steps.
First, allocate a buffer
to store the per-instance data.
The size of this buffer
depends on the number of instances
and the size of each instance descriptor,
but it's allocated
just like any other Metal buffer.
Once you've allocated the buffer,
assign it to the instance
acceleration structure descriptor.
Next you will fill the instance buffer
with information
about all of the instances
in the acceleration structure.
For each instance, create a descriptor
and specify the acceleration structure
that this instance refers to.
You will identify the acceleration
structure with an index into the array
that you set on the instance
acceleration structure descriptor.
Each instance
also has a transformation matrix,
visibility mask, and other properties
depending on which type
of instance descriptor you are using.
The last step is to build
the actual acceleration structure,
which is the same process as for
a primitive acceleration structure.
All of the steps before the build
can run on the CPU.
But if the number of instances is large,
the process of filling out the instance
buffer can become compute intensive.
Since instance descriptors are stored
in a normal Metal buffer,
you can accelerate this step by filling
out these descriptors from the GPU.
This is a great opportunity
for GPU acceleration,
as long as you know how many instances
your acceleration structure will contain
before you hand off the work to the GPU.
But if you want to do something
like instance culling,
you would have to cull instances
on the CPU
so you can set the final instance count
on the descriptor.
New this year,
you can drive this process on the GPU
with the new indirect instance
acceleration structure descriptor.
With this indirect descriptor,
you can cull instances,
fill the instance buffer,
and set the final instance count
entirely on the GPU.
To perform a GPU-driven
acceleration structure build,
create an indirect instance
acceleration structure descriptor.
Set the maximum instance count
on the descriptor,
and the buffer where you will write
the final instance count from the GPU.
Then simply set
the instance descriptor buffer,
and you're ready to start
configuring instances on the GPU.
You will use a different type
of descriptor in the instance buffer.
The indirect instance descriptor is
similar to the direct instance descriptor,
except that you can identify
the acceleration structure
being instanced by simply assigning it
to the descriptor.
That's how you build
an instance acceleration structure.
So far, I've talked about
two-level model of instancing.
In this model,
a forest in the Moana island scene
is composed of thousands of instances
of different trees.
But if we dig deeper, a tree itself is
a trunk with many copies of the same leaf.
You can take advantage of this structure
using the new multi-level
instancing feature.
With multi-level instancing,
an instance acceleration structure
can contain
not just primitive
acceleration structures,
but also other
instance acceleration structures.
For example, in this scene a palm tree
can be expressed
as an instance acceleration structure
containing a trunk
and instances of a leaf,
while the scene as a whole
can contain instances of the palm tree.
The Moana island scene is a great example
of the power of multi-level instancing.
When using two levels of instancing,
adding one type of tree to a scene
could mean adding hundreds or even
thousands of copies of parts of the tree.
But with multi-level instancing,
you can add instances of a complex tree,
defined with repeated instances
of its parts.
This saves millions of instances
across the Moana island scene.
But multi-level instancing isn't just
for production renderers.
It is also valuable
for real time apps like games.
Games also use the two-level
acceleration structure pattern,
building worlds
from instances of game objects.
However, games are different
from production renderers.
Production renderers use deep hierarchies
to reuse objects,
but games use long lists of instances
for game objects.
Games also rebuild their instance
acceleration structure each frame
for their dynamic content,
and high instance count
mean a lot of GPU time for the rebuild.
However in a game,
a lot of the content is static
and doesn't need to be updated
every frame.
You can split the world into static
and dynamic acceleration structures
to limit acceleration structure updates
to only the content that changes.
This means only rebuilding
the dynamic content,
which is typically much less
than the static content.
When applying this split of static
and dynamic content,
it is important to balance
the depth of the hierarchy
with the additional cost of ray traversal.
In a frame with acceleration structure
building and ray tracing,
using 3 levels of instancing allows you
to reduce build time
with only minor impact on trace time,
overall reducing the frame time.
Multi-level instancing is a great tool
to reduce memory usage
and speed up rebuilds.
You also have other ways you can optimize
your Metal ray tracing apps.
One of them is Build parallelization.
A typical application
will need to build or update
many acceleration structures
representing different scenes
and different parts of a scene.
You can greatly reduce your start-up time
by running these builds in parallel.
Whenever you can,
be sure to batch your builds
by encoding multiple builds
to the same command encoder
so they can run in parallel.
You will want to parallelize
as many builds as you can
while ensuring
that the working set fits in memory.
Also remember that after
an acceleration structure build completes,
the scratch buffer is no longer needed.
This means that you can re-use
the scratch buffers from one batch
of acceleration structure builds
to the next.
Sometimes the best way to reduce
the time spent
rebuilding acceleration structures
is to avoid rebuilding altogether.
This is where
acceleration structure refitting comes in.
When Metal builds
an acceleration structure,
it groups nearby primitives
into a hierarchy of boxes.
If your primitives move,
those boxes no longer
accurately represent the scene,
and the acceleration structure
needs to be updated.
But if the geometry only changes slightly,
then the hierarchy
may still be reasonable.
Instead of building
a new acceleration structure from scratch,
Metal can refit the existing
acceleration structure
to reflect the new positions
of primitives in your geometry.
This is cheaper than rebuilding
the acceleration structure from scratch.
Refit requires a scratch buffer
like a build operation.
The size of the refit scratch buffer
is in the same struct you used earlier
to allocate the acceleration structure.
The refit operation runs on the GPU
and is encoded with an acceleration
structure command encoder.
The refit can operate in-place or into
a different acceleration structure.
Finally, compaction is a great way
to reduce the size
of your acceleration structures in memory.
When you first build
an acceleration structure,
Metal can't know
exactly how much memory it needs,
so it has to make a conservative estimate.
Once you've built
the acceleration structure,
Metal can calculate the minimum size
needed to represent it.
With compaction, you can allocate
a new acceleration structure
with the minimal size,
and then use the GPU
to copy from the current
acceleration structure to the new one.
This is especially valuable
for primitive acceleration structures.
To use compaction, encode a command
to calculate the compacted size
of your acceleration structure on the GPU.
When you execute the command,
Metal will write the compacted size
to a buffer that you provide.
Once you've read the compacted size,
you can allocate a new
acceleration structure with that size
and then encode
a "copy and compact" operation
from the old
to the new acceleration structure.
After this command buffer has completed,
you can release
the original acceleration structure.
To learn more about optimizing
your Metal ray tracing apps,
check out the 2022 "Maximizing your Metal
ray tracing performance" session.
In this section,
I have discussed how to set up instancing,
leverage the new
multi-level instancing feature,
and handle instancing at scale.
Now it's time to intersect rays
with the scene.
In Metal, you intersect rays
in a GPU function
that executes as part of a command.
On Apple Silicon you can intersect rays
in both compute and render commands,
and on AMD and Intel you can intersect
rays in compute commands.
To get ready to intersect rays,
bind your acceleration structure
on the command encoder.
Now you can intersect rays
with this acceleration structure
in your GPU function.
Declare the function with
an acceleration structure parameter,
and create an intersector object.
You can set properties on this intersector
to configure ray intersection
for the best performance.
To intersect a ray with your scene,
simply create a ray
and call the intersect method
on the intersector object,
passing the ray and the acceleration
structure as parameters.
This returns everything you need to know
about the intersection,
like the kind of primitive
the ray intersected,
the distance to the intersection,
the ID of the primitive, and more.
To get more information about
the triangle intersection point,
add the "triangle data" tag
to the intersector
and "intersection result" types.
This makes the triangle
barycentric coordinates available
in the intersection result.
That covers intersecting rays
with a primitive acceleration structure.
Intersecting rays with an instance
acceleration structure is very similar.
Bind your instance acceleration structure
the same way
you bind a primitive acceleration
structure,
and be sure to call useResource or useHeap
to make the acceleration structures
referenced
in your instance acceleration structure
available on the GPU.
You only need to make a couple of changes
to your GPU function
to intersect rays with
an instance acceleration structure.
First add the instancing tag
to the acceleration structure type.
Then add the instancing
and "max levels" tags
to your intersector
and "intersection result".
The "max levels" tag specifies
the number of levels of instancing
in your acceleration structure.
For example, the acceleration structure
representing the Moana island scene
is a three-level acceleration structure.
The first level
is the instance acceleration structure
containing the whole scene.
The second level has instances of corals,
trees, and the terrain.
The third level has instances
of the parts of the trees,
like leaves, flowers, and trunks.
When a ray intersects this scene,
it doesn't just intersect a primitive,
but also the instances
that contain the primitive.
If a ray intersects a leaf of this tree,
it also intersects
an instance of the tree,
and an instance of the leaf in the tree.
Metal keeps track of this for you
by recording the ID
of each intersected instance.
In this case, the first intersected
instance is the tree with an ID of 6,
and the second intersected instance
is the leaf with an ID of 1.
The ray could also intersect
just one instance.
For example,
if the ray intersects the terrain,
then Metal will only record the ID
of the terrain instance.
You can find the number of instances
that were intersected
and IDs of the intersected instances
in the intersection result.
That's how you can intersect rays
with primitive acceleration structures
and instance acceleration structures.
There are a few things to keep in mind
when using curve primitives.
By default, Metal assumes
you are not using curve primitives
when you perform ray intersection.
You can tell Metal
that you are using curves
by setting the geometry type
on the intersector object.
Once you've set the geometry type,
you're ready to intersect curves.
As before, find information
about the intersection
on the intersection result.
If you use the "curve data" tag,
then the intersection result
also contains the curve parameter.
This is the value you can plug into
the curve's basis function
to compute the point along the curve
where it intersected the ray.
These functions are implemented for you
in the Metal Shading Language.
You can learn more in
the Metal Shading Language specification.
In many applications, curve geometry is
represented with just one kind of curve.
For example,
all the curves in your scene
might be expressed as cubic bezier curves,
with circular cross sections.
In this case, you can tell Metal
what kind of curves your scene uses
by setting the properties of your curves
on the intersector object.
This allows you to get the best
performance when using curve primitives.
That is how you can intersect rays
with your scene.
And you can use Xcode to debug
and profile your raytracing workloads.
One of the tools at your disposal when
dealing with difficult to debug problems
is Shader Validation.
It performs runtime checks in your shaders
and catches issues
which may lead to crashes or corruptions.
Shader Validation now covers
all of the Metal API,
including the latest ray tracing features.
In addition, Shader Validation has greatly
reduced impact on shader compilation time.
This is extremely helpful when you are
working with long and complex shaders,
like those commonly found
in ray tracing applications.
Another tool that can help you
is the state of the art
Acceleration Structure viewer.
It enables you to inspect the scene
which you use for intersection testing.
When I open
the Acceleration Structure viewer,
I get an outline on the left for
navigating the individual building blocks
in the acceleration structure
down to the geometry primitives.
Here, it lists the individual triangles
that make up the triangle geometry.
On the right, I have a viewport,
where I can inspect the acceleration
structure in various highlighting modes.
For example, the "Axis-Aligned Bounding
Box Traversals" highlighting mode
can visualize areas
with deeper levels of traversals,
which correspond to
more expensive intersection testing.
As I move the pointer over the scene,
the inspector updates
with the number of intersections
which a ray would
hit in the pointed direction.
Another example is
the Acceleration Structure highlight mode.
This visualizes the acceleration
structures in different colors.
The Acceleration Structure viewer supports
the new multi-level instancing feature
and curve geometries.
When I move the camera in the viewport,
I can find instance acceleration
structures for some trees
and curves for some foliage.
To identify an acceleration structure,
I can click in the viewport
to reveal it in the outline.
Now, take a closer look
at the acceleration structure
for these palm leaves.
In this acceleration structure,
the palm leaves consist of curves.
I can change the viewport to the
Primitive highlight mode
to visualize the curve segments.
To better inspect the curve segments,
I'll zoom in a little bit.
Similar to selecting acceleration
structures in the scene earlier,
here, I can click to select each segment.
Another useful tool at your disposal
when examining a ray tracing workload
is Shader Debugger.
This can help you with troubleshooting
issues in your shader code.
Here, I'm at a compute dispatch
which performs intersection testing
in the shader.
To begin debugging my shader,
I can the Shader Debugging button,
choose a thread in the popover,
and then click the Debug button.
After it finishes gathering data,
I can examine the value for each variable
at any point during shader execution.
Take a closer look at the value
for primitive ID.
To provide more debugging context,
Shader Debugger also gives me data
from the neighboring threads.
Here, I can hover the pointer
over the value view
to inspect the primitive IDs
from the same thread group.
Performance is another important aspect
of any app.
The Profiling timeline gives an overview
of the ray tracing workload performance,
allowing you to inspect and correlate
various performance metrics side by side.
In addition,
I can change the Debug navigator
to view all the pipeline states
in the workload.
And with the shader profiling data,
the navigator lists the most expensive
pipeline states at the top.
Further expanding a pipeline state
reveals the shader code.
After opening a shader, I can get
the per-line shader profiling insights
about where and how each individual shader
spends its execution time.
When I move the pointer over the pie-chart
in the sidebar,
it shows a popover
with more detailed breakdown
of the cost at that line of code.
These tools support
all of Metal's new ray tracing features,
and can offer great debugging
and profiling aids
when you're working on your Metal apps.
Metal ray tracing also supports
many more features such as:
Primitive and instance motion for
animating scenes in production renderers,
custom intersection functions,
for customizing ray intersection
with enhancements like alpha testing,
and intersection query,
for portability from query-based APIs.
The Metal Ray Tracing API,
Language and Tools
support real time rendering apps like
games, and production renderers.
You can use the latest
Metal Ray Tracing API to build your scenes
using primitive acceleration structures,
including geometry like curves.
Instancing and especially
the new multi-level instancing feature
enables you to scale to larger,
more complex scenes.
Your GPU functions can call
the Metal Ray Tracing APIs directly.
And finally, Xcode can help you
in debugging and profiling your app.
Be sure to check out
the previous ray tracing talks
where we have covered many of these topics
in more detail,
as well as our sample code
and documentation.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪