♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Eric Chiu: Hi there.
My name is Eric,
and today I'll be giving
a walkthrough
of Reality Composer Pro.
You might remember in 2019,
we introduced
Reality Composer
to get your feet wet
with augmented reality.
Now, with
the release of xrOS,
we're introducing
Reality Composer Pro,
a pro developer tool
to help you compose, edit,
and preview 3D content.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
Using Reality Composer Pro,
we can create immersive
3D experiences.
Let's take this interactive
Dioramas app as an example.
We can check out fantastic
national parks at room scale,
along with some points
of interest.
In this session,
we'll go through
various features
in Reality Composer Pro
that we can leverage
to build this scene.
We'll begin
with a fresh project,
then go through the general UI
of Reality Composer Pro,
compose our main scene
using a 3D terrain
and location pins,
add some clouds
on top of our terrain,
and a few birds with audio.
We'll take advantage
of statistics
to optimize the performance,
and finally check out
an on-device preview
of our scene.
Let's get started.
First, setting up our project.
There are two ways to set up.
One way is to go to
Xcode > Open Developer Tool
and open Reality Composer Pro
from there.
This is recommended
if we want to create
a standalone
Reality Composer Pro project.
The other way is to create
a new Xcode project
using the xrOS app template.
The template automatically
generates and links
a Reality Composer Pro project
to the Xcode project.
This is recommended
if we want to use
a Reality Composer Pro project
in an Xcode app.
We'll build our Dioramas
app this way.
The Reality Composer Pro
project is this Swift package.
Swift packages
not only make it easy
to work with
Reality Composer Pro,
but also during
the build process,
it packages the content
into a framework
for our Xcode app to use.
Let's take a look
at the structure
of our Reality Composer Pro
project in Finder.
Notice here, the files we use
to edit 3D content are USDs,
otherwise known as
Universal Scene Descriptions.
This is Apple's preferred
file format for 3D content.
To learn more, check out
the WWDC sessions
on the USD file format,
listed below.
When organizing files, any USD
placed in the .rkassets folder
will be compiled
into a framework,
ready to use
in our Xcode project.
Going back to Xcode,
if we select the package,
a 3D preview
of the default scene appears.
If we want to investigate
or edit the scene further,
all we need to do is click
Open in Reality Composer Pro.
Now let's go over
how to navigate
around Reality Composer Pro
and get a sense of the UI.
In the center,
we have the viewport.
The viewport allows us
to visualize, navigate through,
and preview the 3D objects
in the scene.
We support moving through the
viewport using W, A, S, D keys
as well as the arrow keys.
If we want even more control
of the viewport,
we can plug in
a Mac-compatible game controller
and fly through the viewport
that way.
On the leading side,
we have the hierarchy panel.
The hierarchy panel provides
an easy way to search, select,
and organize the 3D objects
in the scene.
On the trailing side,
we have the inspector panel.
The inspector panel provides an
easy way to edit the properties
of selected objects
such as the position,
rotation, and scale.
The Add Component button
on the bottom
of the inspector panel
also lets us view
the built-in
RealityKit Components
that we can configure
on our objects.
Below we have the editor panel.
The first tab on the editor
panel is the Project Browser.
The Project Browser
is a user-friendly way
to navigate through the files
included in the
Reality Composer Pro project.
This panel also contains
other tabs for advanced editing:
Shader Graph, Audio Mixer,
and Statistics.
Now that we have the
Reality Composer Pro project
set up and know how to navigate
around the UI,
let's start
composing a scene.
There's three ways to add assets
into a Reality Composer Pro
project.
The first is importing assets
into the Project Browser
that already exist
on your computer.
Let's import the assets we plan
to use for our Dioramas app.
We can do this by pressing
the import button
in the Project Browser.
Great! We have all our assets
in the Project Browser now.
The second
is the Content Library,
which is a curated
library of assets
provided by
Reality Composer Pro.
The third is Object Capture,
which turns photos of real-world
objects into 3D models.
To learn more, check out
the "Meet Object Capture
for iOS" WWDC se  ssion.
Now that we have our assets
imported into our project,
let's get started
on building our scene.
First let's delete the sphere
created by the template
by selecting the object
in the viewport
and hitting Delete.
In the Project Browser,
we have a 3D model of Yosemite
and a nice diorama base
to hold it.
We'll drag these two assets
into the hierarchy panel,
which adds references
to those assets in the scene.
The diorama base doesn't
seem to have a material.
Let's check out
the Content Library
and see if there's any materials
we would like to use.
Let's click the plus button
in the toolbar
to open up the Content Library
and look for a possible
material to use.
This concrete material
looks promising,
so we'll drag it into our scene.
The asset is automatically
imported into our project
and referenced in the scene.
Now let's select the diorama
base's material in the hierarchy
and update it
to use the concrete material.
Great! Next, placing
some location pins.
We'll drag and drop a
location pin into the viewport
and place it on El Capitan.
Then duplicate the location pin
two more times,
using Command-D,
and rename the three pins
to El Capitan, Cathedral Rocks,
and Merced River.
[KEYSTROKES]
Let's move the Cathedral Rocks
and Merced River location pins
to the right spots.
Now that we have
the location pins
in the right spots,
let's group the location pins
for organizational purposes
and rename the group,
"Yosemite_Location_Pins."
What if we want to update
the location pins
to a newer version?
Well, all these location pins
are referencing
the location pin file
we previously imported.
Leveraging the power of USD,
if we ever wanted to update
the Location_Pin asset,
we can import a new Location_Pin
asset into our project
and replace the existing one.
Now let's go over
particle emitters.
Particle emitters allows us
to create effects
such as this flame in our scene.
A particle emitter
is composed of two parts:
particles and an emitter.
Both the particle and emitter
have multiple sections
of variables
to tweak and modify.
On the particle,
there's the color, properties,
force fields,
and rendering sections.
On the emitter,
there's the timing, shape,
and spawning sections.
Now let's add some clouds
using particle emitters
to make our scene
more interesting and dynamic.
How do we do that?
Well, our Reality Composer Pro
project
can contain an arbitrary
amount of scenes.
Scenes can represent
either a finished piece
ready to use in our Xcode app,
or a reusable piece of content.
In this case, clouds are made up
of smaller clouds.
We'll first build a reusable
cloud chunk scene.
Then we'll create a complete
cloud scene
that combines multiple
cloud chunks
placed at different positions
in 3D space.
We'll make three
different variations
of the complete clouds
and finally,
put those three clouds
into our main scene.
Jumping back into
Reality Composer Pro,
let's create a new scene by
going to File > New > Scene.
We'll name the scene
"Cloud_Chunk".
When a new scene is created,
it appears as a new tab
in the window.
There's two ways to add
particle emitters to the scene.
The first is through
the plus button
at the bottom
of the hierarchy panel.
The second is adding
a Particle Emitter Component
to any object in the scene
by clicking
the Add Component button
at the bottom
of the inspector panel.
We can preview
the particle emitter
by using the playback controls
near the top
of the inspector panel.
It's a little hard to see
so let's go to Settings
and change
the viewport background
to make the particle emitters
more visible.
That's a lot better.
Particles are really fun
to play with.
I often get the results
I'm looking for
just by experimenting with
properties here and there.
There's no right
or wrong approach
to making particle emitters,
as long as you get them
to a state that pleases you.
One thing to consider though
is that a high count
of particles in a scene
may have performance
implications,
so I would recommend
paying close attention
to the number of particles
being used.
Now the particle emitter
component has two sections:
particles and emitters.
In the particles section,
we control the appearance
of the individual particles.
In the emitters section,
we control how the particles
come out of the origin location.
There are also some presets
for us to build on top of.
so we don't have to start
from scratch.
The cloud is closest
to the Impact preset
so let's select
the Impact preset to start.
My typical workflow
is first focusing
on the Emitters tab,
and then moving on
to the Particles tab.
Looking at the Emitter tab,
Timing is the first section.
There's a slight pause
in between every emission
of particles.
This is due to the
idle duration variable.
Setting this to zero should give
a constant emission
of particles.
Moving on to the Shape section,
clouds are more of a sphere
shape than a cylinder shape,
so let's switch the emitter
shape to Sphere.
Next, clouds should have
particles within its volume,
so let's change
the birth location
from Surface to Volume.
Clouds also tend to be
more flat than tall,
so let's adjust
the x- and z-axis scale
to be greater
than the y-axis scale.
That's looking great.
Finally we should check
isLocalSpace
so that future translating,
rotating, and scaling
on the particle emitter's parent
will also apply
to the particle emitter itself.
Moving on to the Particles tab,
we'll adjust the looks
of the individual particles.
The birth rate defines
the number of particles
that exist at once.
Being wary of performance,
let's crank this down
from 2000 to 500
and see if it
makes a difference.
There's a slight change
in appearance,
but it still looks pretty good,
so let's keep it at 500.
Thanks to using
the Impact preset,
the color and texture
of the particles
are already what we want,
so we can skip modifying
variables in those sections
and move on
to the Properties section.
The particles seem to exist
for too short of a time.
Let's increase the life span
from two to five seconds
and see what happens.
This looks great.
There are more variables
we can play with
in the Motion, Force Fields,
and Rendering sections,
but the effect we have so far
is close to what we want,
so let's not modify
those sections for now.
We'll save the scene using
the shortcut Command-S
and move on to the next step.
Cool! We just built
our cloud chunk
that we're going to reuse.
Now let's create a new scene
that combines
multiple cloud chunks
to make a complete cloud.
We'll create a new scene
using the shortcut Command-N.
Let's name this scene "Cloud_A."
[KEYSTROKES]
I'll reference
the cloud chunk three times
by dragging the Cloud_Chunk
asset from the Project Browser
into the hierarchy panel.
We can select the parent
of these three cloud chunks
and press play
in the playback controls
at the top of the
inspector panel
to preview the cloud.
Now let's use the manipulator
to move these three cloud chunks
to different positions
in 3D space.
[CLICKING]
Amazing.
This looks like one cohesive
and complete cloud.
We can save the scene
using Command-S again.
In order to get
a nice variety of clouds,
I made two more clouds
using a similar process
to making Cloud_A but positioned
the cloud chunks differently.
I named these scenes
Cloud_B and Cloud_C.
Now let's jump back
into our main scene.
I made a group called "Clouds"
and imported Cloud_A,
Cloud_B, and Cloud_C
underneath this group.
I also arranged them nicely
on top of our terrain.
To preview
the particle emitters at once,
all I have to do is click
the group "Clouds"
and press play
on its playback controls
at the top of the
inspector panel.
Awesome,
things are coming together.
Next, let's go over
how to incorporate audio
into our scenes.
We can add audio
using audio files,
audio file groups,
and audio sources.
Audio files imported into
a scene from the Project Browser
can be configured
in various ways,
such as if they should loop.
An audio file can be played
on one or more objects,
and an object can play
one or more audio files.
An audio file group
can be constructed
from audio files in a scene.
Each time an object plays
an audio file group,
a random audio file from the
group is selected for playback.
An audio source defines
the way audio files
and audio file groups
are emitted into a scene.
There are three kinds
of audio sources:
spatial, ambient, and channel.
Spatial audio sources provide
a position and a direction
in 3D space
for the audio playing.
Imagine using spatial audio
for a radio asset
sitting on a table.
Ambient audio sources
provide no position
but a direction in 3D space
for the audio playing.
Imagine using ambient audio
for wind sounds
coming from the east,
and no matter how far
we walk toward the east,
the wind sounds will always
be coming from that direction.
Finally, channel audio sources
provide neither a position
nor a direction in 3D space
for the audio playing.
Imagine using channel audio
for background music
in an environment.
Now that we've covered
the audio authoring concepts,
let's see it in action
in our Dioramas project.
We'll create a new scene
as a reusable asset
that combines
a 3D model of a bird
with audio files
and an audio source.
Command-N, and name this scene
"Bird_With_Audio."
[KEYSTROKES]
We previously imported
a bird with animation
and two bird call audio files
into our Project Browser.
Let's add those assets
as references into this scene
by dragging them
into the hierarchy panel.
Now any audio source
in the scene
can utilize these two
bird call audio files.
Next let's add
a spatial audio source
by using the plus button at the
bottom of the hierarchy panel.
We can also add
a spatial audio source
to any object in the scene
by clicking
the Add Component button
at the bottom
of the inspector panel,
and selecting Spatial Audio
in the menu.
Again, the Spatial Audio source
has a position and a direction,
so we should place it near
the beak of the bird
so it sounds more realistic.
We can preview
the Spatial Audio source
with the playback controls at
the top of the inspector panel.
There's additional properties
on the spatial audio component
we can adjust,
such as the focus
and which bird call
audio file to preview.
[BIRDS CALLS]
Now what if we want
to randomly select
one of these two bird calls
every time
the spatial audio source
is told to play?
Well, that's what
audio file groups are for.
We can create
audio file groups
using the same plus button
at the bottom
of the hierarchy panel.
Let's drag in these audio files
into the audio file group
and name the group "Bird_Calls."
[KEYSTROKES]
Now every time we preview
the Spatial Audio source,
one of the bird calls within
the audio file group
is randomly selected to play.
[BIRD CALLS]
Now that we've finished making
our reusable asset,
let's save and close
this Bird_With_Audio scene
and open back up our main scene.
I arranged five references
of Birds_With_Audio
in a V-shaped pattern
under a group called "Birds."
We can select the group "Birds"
and press the playback controls
in the inspector panel
to preview the animation
and audio for all the birds
at the same time.
[LAYERED BIRD CALLS]
Now that looks and sounds
pretty nice!
Using this same procedure,
I added the Forest_Sounds
audio file into our main scene,
along with
an ambient audio source
named "Nature _Ambience."
To play audio in an Xcode app,
some additional code is needed,
which will be covered in the
"Work with Reality Composer Pro
content in Xcode" WWDC session.
Now that we have the content
in our main scene set up,
let's go over
how to use statistics.
Statistics is a dedicated editor
for helping us optimize
the performance of a scene.
The categories are split into
general, physics,
animation, particle emitters,
audio, materials,
geometry, and textures.
Let's try out statistics
in our main scene.
If we click on the Statistics
tab in the editor panel,
the collection
of categories appears.
The expand button
on the top-right corner
of every category
opens the category up
to a more detailed view.
Clicking on the expand button
for Geometry,
we see that there are roughly
464,000 triangles
used in the scene,
and the Diorama_Base
uses the most amount
of triangles -- 256,000.
We caught something here.
The diorama base has a lot more
triangles than our 3D terrain,
even though its visual shape is
less complex than our terrains.
This is a great time
to simplify the geometry
of our diorama base
in a 3D modeling software.
Luckily, my colleague
Scott Wade,
who has created the assets
for our Dioramas app,
has helped me with that.
We can import the new simplified
version of our diorama's base
into our project using the
Project Browser's import button.
Select our new Diorama_Base,
and replace the existing one.
Now let's go back
to Statistics
and take a look
at the Geometry category.
The Diorama_Base now only
uses 2,500 triangles.
We reduced the number
of triangles in the scene
from 464,000 to 210,000—that's more than half!
And our scene maintains
the same look
prior to our change.
As we just saw,
Statistics is a great tool
to help optimize
the performance of a scene.
There's one more thing.
Let's take a look at how we can
preview our scene on device.
When we connect
our headset to the computer,
select it in the dropdown
next to the on-device preview
button in the toolbar,
then toggle the
on-device preview button.
We should see our scene appear
before our very eyes in AR.
We can pinch and drag
to rotate the scene,
and zoom to scale the scene.
This makes it very easy
to get a sense
of what our 3D content
looks like
in the intended xrOS platform.
In interest of time,
I performed similar steps
of what we went through
in this session
for another national park,
Catalina Island.
Using this same workflow,
I added an additional 3D terrain
of Catalina Island
to our main scene.
I also added a few location
pins to mark Two Harbors,
Parsons Landing, and
Ribbon Beach on Catalina Island.
Finally, I added an
Ocean_Sounds audio file
for the Nature_Ambience
audio source to use.
What you saw today
is a walkthrough
of Reality Composer Pro,
a powerful tool to help you
assemble 3D scenes.
You can add interesting
RealityKit Components,
such as particle emitters
and audio sources.
It also helps you
optimize your scene
and preview it on headset.
To learn more about how
you can use the Shader Graph
to transition between
the Yosemite
and Catalina Island terrains,
watch Neil's session,
"Explore materials
in Reality Composer Pro."
You can also learn how to make
this experience interactive
in Amanda's session,
"Work with Reality Composer Pro
content in Xcode".
I'm excited to see what you
build with Reality Composer Pro.
Hope you enjoyed this session
and thanks for watching!
♪