♪ ♪
Doug: Welcome, everyone.
I’m Doug Davidson,
and I’m here to talk to you
about Natural Language Processing.
Now, there have been a number of sessions
on Natural Language Processing
in past years.
What we’re going to talk about today
builds on all of that,
with the addition
of some exciting new functionality.
First I’m going to give some background
on NLP and NLP models.
Then I’ll summarize
the existing functionality.
Then I’ll talk about what’s new this year.
I’ll discuss some advanced applications.
And then I’ll wrap it up.
Let’s start with some background.
Schematically,
NLP models generally have a similar flow.
They start off with text data,
then have an input layer that converts it
to a numerical feature representation,
upon which
a machine learning model can act,
and that produces some output.
The most obvious examples of this
from previous years
are the Create ML models
that are supported
for text classification and word tagging.
The development of NLP as a field
can be traced fairly closely
just by the development
of increasingly sophisticated
versions of the input layers.
Ten or twenty years ago,
these were simple orthographic features.
Then about a decade ago,
things moved to the use
of static word embeddings,
such as Word2Vec and GloVe.
Then to contextual word embeddings
based on neural network models,
such as CNNs and LSTMs.
And more recently,
transformer-based language models.
I should say a few words
about what an embedding is.
In the simplest form,
it’s just a map from words in a language
to vectors in some abstract vector space,
but trained as a machine learning model
such that words with similar meaning
are close together in vector space.
This allows it to incorporate
linguistic knowledge.
Static embeddings are just a simple map
from words to vectors.
Pass in a word, the model looks it up
in a table and provides a vector.
These are trained such that words
with similar meaning
are close together in vector space.
This is quite useful
for understanding individual words.
More sophisticated embeddings
are dynamic and contextual
such that each word in a sentence
is mapped to a different vector
depending on its use in the sentence.
For example, “food” in “fast food joint”
has a different meaning
than “food” in “food for thought,”
so they will get different
embedding vectors.
Now, the point of having
a powerful embedding as an input layer
is to allow for transfer learning.
The embedding is trained
on large amounts of data
and encapsulates general knowledge
of the language,
which can be transferred
to your specific task
without requiring huge amounts
of task-specific training data.
Currently, Create ML supports embeddings
of this sort using ELMo models.
These models are based on LSTMs
whose outputs are combined
to produce the embedding vector.
These can be used via Create ML
for training classification
and tagging models.
Now, let me discuss the models
that have been supported so far.
These were discussed in great detail
in previous sessions in 2019 and 2020,
so I’ll just describe them briefly here.
Natural Language supports model training
using Create ML
that generally follows the pattern
we’ve seen for NLP models.
This involves models
for two different tasks:
text classification and word tagging.
In text classification,
the output describes the input text
using one of a set of classes.
For example,
it might be a topic or a sentiment.
And in word tagging, the output puts
a label on each word in the input text,
for example,
a part of speech or a role label.
And the supported Create ML models
have generally followed
the evolution of the NLP field,
starting with maxent and CRF-based models,
then adding support
for static word embeddings,
and then dynamic word embeddings
for Create ML models
using ELMo embeddings.
And you can view the detail on this
in previous sessions,
“Advances in Natural Language Framework”
from 2019
and “Make Apps Smarter
with Natural Language” from 2020.
Now let me turn to what's new this year
in Natural Language.
I’m happy to say that we now provide
transformer-based contextual embeddings.
Specifically, these are BERT embeddings.
That just stands for Bidirectional Encoder
Representations from Transformers.
These are embedding models
that are trained on large amounts of text
using a masked language model
style of training.
This means that the model is given
a sentence with one word masked out
and asked to suggest the word,
for example, “food” in “food for thought,”
and trained to do better and better
at this.
Transformers at their heart are based
on what’s called an attention mechanism,
specifically, multi-headed self-attention,
which allows the model
to take into account
different portions of the text
with different weights,
in multiple different ways at once.
The multi-headed self-attention mechanism
is wrapped up with multiple other layers,
then repeated several times,
which altogether provides a powerful
and flexible model that can take advantage
of large amounts of textual data.
So much so in fact that it can be trained
on multiple languages at once,
leading to a multilingual model.
This has several advantages.
It makes it possible to support
many languages immediately
and even multiple languages at once.
But even more than that,
because of similarities between languages,
there's some synergy such that data
for one language helps with others.
So we’ve gone immediately
to supporting 27 different languages
across a wide variety
of language families.
This is done with three separate models,
one each for groups of languages
that share related writing systems.
So there's one model
for Latin-script languages,
one for languages that use Cyrillic,
and one for Chinese, Japanese, and Korean.
These embedding models fit right in
with the Create ML training
we discussed earlier,
serving as an input encoding layer.
This is a powerful encoding
for many different models.
In addition though,
the data that you use for training
doesn’t have to all be
in a single language.
Let me show you how this works
with an example.
Suppose you're writing a messaging app
and want to aid users
by automatically classifying
the messages that they receive.
Suppose you want to divide them
into three categories:
personal messages, such as you might
receive from your friends,
business messages, such as you might
receive from your colleagues,
and commercial messages, such as you might
receive from businesses you interact with.
But users might receive messages
in many different languages,
and you want to handle that.
For this example, I’ve assembled
some training data in multiple languages,
English, Italian, German, and Spanish.
I used json format,
but you could also use directories or CSV.
To train our model, we go into
the Create ML app and create a project.
Then we need to select our training data.
I’ve also prepared validation data
and test data to go along with it.
Then we need to choose our algorithm,
and we have a new choice here:
the BERT embeddings.
Once we’ve chosen those,
we can choose the script.
Since these are Latin-script languages,
I’ll leave it on Latin.
If we were using a single language,
we would have the option
of specifying it here,
but this is multilingual,
so we’ll just leave it on automatic.
Then all we need to do is press Train,
and model training will start.
The most time-consuming part
of the training
is applying these powerful embeddings
to the text.
Then the model trains fairly quickly
to a high degree of accuracy.
At that point, we can try it out
on some example messages.
In English…
Or Spanish.
And the model is pretty confident
that these are commercial messages.
As an example of the synergies
that are possible,
this model hasn’t been trained on French,
but it can still classify
some French text as well.
I do recommend though
that you use training data
for each of the languages
you are interested in.
Now, so far we’ve just been working
with Create ML,
but it’s also possible
to work with these embeddings
using the Natural Language framework
with a new class called
NLContextualEmbedding.
This allows you to identify
the embedding model you want
and find out some of its properties.
You can look for an embedding model
in a number of different ways,
for example, by language or by script.
Once you have such a model,
you can get properties
such as the dimensionality of the vectors.
Also, each model has an identifier,
which is just a string
that uniquely identifies the model.
For example,
when you start working with a model,
you might locate it by language,
but later on you would want to make sure
that you're using the exact same model,
and the identifier will allow you
to do this.
One thing to keep in mind is that,
like many other Natural Language features,
these embedding models rely on assets
that are downloaded as needed.
NLContextualEmbedding provides some APIs
to give you additional control over this,
for example,
to request download before use.
You can ask
whether a given embedding model
currently has assets available on device,
and if not put in a request,
which will result
in their being downloaded.
Now, some of you may be saying,
I have some models
that I don’t train using Create ML,
but instead I train
using PyTorch or TensorFlow.
Can I still use these new BERT embeddings?
Yes, you can.
We provide these pre-trained
multilingual embedding models
that are available to you,
that you can use as an input layer
to just about any model you want to train.
Here’s how that would work.
On your macOS device,
you would use NLContextualEmbedding
to get the embedding vectors
for your training data.
You would then feed these
as input to your training
using PyTorch or TensorFlow
and convert the result to a Core ML model
using Core ML tools.
Then at inference time on device,
you would use NLContextualEmbedding
to get the embedding vectors
for your input data,
pass them into your Core ML model
to get the output.
To support this, there are additional
NLContextualEmbedding APIs
that allow you to load a model,
apply it to a piece of text,
and get the resulting embedding vectors.
If you remember
the model identifier from earlier,
you can use that to retrieve
the same model that you used for training.
You can then apply the model
to a piece of text,
giving
an NLContextualEmbeddingResult object.
Once you have this object,
you can then use it
to iterate over the embedding vectors.
Now, to give you just a taste
of what's possible with this,
we prepared a simple example model.
We started with an existing
English-language Stable Diffusion model,
then used some multilingual data
to fine-tune it
to use the new BERT embeddings
as an input layer, taking those as fixed,
and also training
a simple linear projection layer
to convert dimensionalities.
The result then is a Stable Diffusion
model that takes multilingual input.
Here are some examples
of output from the model.
If I pass in some English text,
for example,
“A path through a garden
full of pink flowers,”
the model leads us down a path
into a garden full of pink flowers.
But also, if I translate the same sentence
into French, Spanish, Italian, and German,
the model produces images of paths and
gardens full of pink flowers for each one.
Let me take a slightly more complicated
example.
“A road in front of trees and mountains
under a cloudy sky.”
Here’s some output from the model,
with road, trees, mountains, and clouds.
But likewise,
I can translate the same sentence
into French, Spanish, Italian, and German,
or any of a number of other languages,
and for each one get an image
of road, trees, mountains, and clouds.
Now let me sum up the lessons
from this session.
You can use Create ML
to easily train models
for text classification
or word tagging tasks,
and the new multilingual
BERT embedding models provide
a powerful input encoding layer
for this purpose.
These models can be single-language
or multilingual.
You can also use the BERT embeddings
as input layers
for whatever model you want to train
with PyTorch or TensorFlow.
Thank you.
Now go out and start training some models.
♪ ♪