♪ ♪
Hi everyone, I am Gauri Jog,
and I work on the Metal Ecosystem team
here at Apple.
I'm excited to talk to you about
optimizing GPU renderers using Metal.
Modern digital content creation
applications and game-engines
empower content creators to interactively
create and modify materials
for their 3D assets.
There are several common techniques
for handling
these complex and dynamic materials
at runtime.
Some applications compile materials
into individual shaders
and others use data-driven solutions
such as uber shaders
or shader virtual machines.
These material-centric workflows
have two main performance goals.
Authoring of materials should be
responsive for fast iteration
and the best experience.
Rendering performance
should be as good as possible
for real-time interactivity
and efficient final-frame rendering.
In this demonstration of Blender 3D,
material editing is responsive.
When you modify a material slider
in the user interface,
the results are shown instantly
in the viewport
without any stutters
due to shader re-compilation.
Once the material is modified,
the resulting rendering performance
is fast and interactive,
giving content creators the ability
to efficiently view
the results of their work.
To achieve a responsive and
performant workflow in your application,
you can leverage key Metal features
and implement Metal best practices.
Metal can help you maximize
complex shaders' performance
leverage asynchronous compilation
to keep the application responsive,
compile faster with dynamic linking
and tune your compute shaders
with new Metal compiler options.
Optimizing your shaders
is the key to performance.
An uber shader is an example
of a long and complex shader
that can be used
to render any possible material.
These types of shaders have lots of
branches for any possible combination.
When artists create material,
the material parameters are stored
in a Metal buffer,
used by the material shader.
This buffer gets updated
when you change the parameters,
but there is no recompilation required.
This approach provides a great
responsive authoring experience.
However, uber shaders are not optimal
since they have to account for
all the possible options.
To make the most optimal shader variant,
you should use Metal specialization
with function constants.
Simply declare function constants
in your Metal shader
and set their values at runtime
when they are changed.
The material buffer contents
simply become constants
in your shader pipeline states,
dynamic branching is eliminated.
Specialized materials give you
the most performance.
This is a comparison
of real-time performance data
from two common test assets in Blender 3D,
Wanderer and Tree Creature.
First is the baseline performance
in frames per second
of the scenes using an uber shader.
Second is the specialized shader approach
with function constants
that performs much faster.
In order to make the fastest
specialized shader variant,
use function constants to disable
unused features and eliminate branching.
An uber shader would query
material parameters from a buffer
doing conditional branches at runtime
to enable and disable features.
With function constants you declare
one constant per material feature.
Now the dynamic branch
for the feature codepath
is replaced with the function constant,
eliminating all unused code.
Here is the same uber shader
now using function constants.
The Metal compiler can fold these
as constant booleans
and remove unused code.
Branch expressions that resolve
to false will be optimized out,
leaving only the true branches.
All the unused control flow
is optimized out.
Specialized shader now does not need
to query material data,
having a much simpler control flow.
Memory loads and branches
have been removed
resulting in faster runtime performance.
Function specialization
also helps with constants folding.
Material parameters that don't change
are replaced with constants.
This example material uses a collection
of input parameters from a Metal buffer.
The parameters could be color,
weight, sheen color, and many more.
At material creation time,
these static parameters can be replaced
with function constants.
Function constants produce
the most optimal code
with no buffer reads required.
On the host side,
function constant values are provided
when creating
a specialized pipeline state.
MaterialParameter structure can
be used to represent all parameters
that are constant for a material.
IsGlossy is an example
of a boolean material feature flag
controlling glossiness.
MaterialColor is an example of a vector
parameter used to describe color.
To create a specialized
Pipeline State Object,
iterate over
a MetalFunctionConstantValues set
and insert
the values using setConstantValue.
Then just create
a Render Pipeline as usual.
The only difference is when
creating the fragment function,
you'd use the variant of
newFunctionWithName with constantValues.
Finally,
create your Pipeline State Object.
The resulting shader is the most optimal
performing variant of this material.
Always use Xcode's
GPU Debugger Performance section
to confirm the impact
of using function constants.
The original uber shader shows
a high number of ALU instructions
and a large amount of spill.
The number of memory waits is also large.
Specialized approach gives
immediate relief on the ALU and spill.
This is due to dead code elimination
and constants folding.
Also, the number of memory waits
is significantly smaller.
Observing the original uber shader
in runtime shader execution costs,
the GPU is spending significant time
on memory waits.
Specialized approach, in contrast,
spends far less time on memory waits,
enabling more productive ALU utilization,
along with other efficiency benefits.
In the GPU Debugger timeline view,
it takes 58 milliseconds
to render the material pass
using the uber shader.
And only 12.5 milliseconds
to render with specialized versions.
It's a pretty dramatic improvement.
Material specialization requires
runtime shader compilation
and this will often result in hitching
if you block and wait
for these specialized materials
to be created.
The Metal asynchronous compilation APIs
allow you to use generic uber shaders
and keep user experience
interactive and responsive
while generating specialized versions
in the background.
To opt in to the asynchronous pipeline
state creation,
provide a completion handler.
These calls will return immediately
allowing you to keep the user experience
interactive and responsive.
Completion handler will be called
when specialized pipeline state is ready,
and you can switch
to the optimal shader right away.
This is a diagram of an asynchronous
material workflow.
By default, when the material
has not yet been specialized,
you use your uber shader.
At the same time,
Metal compiles the specialized shader
in the background.
Once this is done,
you can switch out the uber shader
for the fast specialized material.
Runtime Metal shaders compilation
is designed
to provide a balanced level
of parallelism.
However,
modern content creation applications
need to provide multi-material
editing workflows,
resulting in many shader re-compilations.
To help such heavy authoring needs,
you may want to ask Metal
to maximize
shader compilation parallelism.
Metal device has
a new property in macOS13.3
called
should-Maximize-Concurrent-Compilation.
When you set it to Yes,
Metal compiler will make the best use
of your CPU cores.
Maximizing concurrent compilation
is really great
for multi-material authoring workflows.
With additional compiler jobs available,
specialized material variants
are available much sooner.
Here is how it all works in practice.
When material parameters are changed,
the current specialized variants
of the material are invalidated,
there is a switch back to using
the uber shader to keep authoring fluid.
A new async job is queued
and once it completes,
you can observe
a substantial performance improvement
once the specialized material is engaged.
Most modern apps have extremely
complex materials,
so it can take
a significant amount of time
for a specialized variant to be ready.
Dynamic libraries in Metal can be used
to pre-compile the utility functions
and reduce overall material compile time.
You do this
by splitting up groups of functionality
into separate dynamic libraries.
For even faster runtime compilation,
utility libraries
could be precompiled offline.
And you end up compiling
much less code at runtime.
If I were to take the previous uber shader
and split it into dylibs.
one approach is to split it
by common groups of functionality.
In this case, one math utility library
and another for lighting functions.
To make function symbols visible
for linking,
you assign "default” visibility.
Symbols can also be hidden
from external programs
by assigning visibility to "hidden".
There are two properties to check
if your Metal device
supports dynamic libraries.
For render pipelines you should use the
supportsRenderDynamicLibraries property
of the Metal device.
This is currently available on devices
with Apple6 and above GPU families.
For compute pipelines you should query
the supportsDynamicLibraries property.
This is available on Apple6 and above
and for most of the Mac2 GPU families.
To create a dynamic library
from an existing Metal library,
simply call newDynamicLibrary
and pass it a Metal library.
To create from the URL,
call the newDynamicLibraryWithURL method
and provide the path
to the stored dynamic library.
You can precompile
dynamic libraries offline
using the metal compiler tool chain.
When loading precompiled
dynamic libraries at runtime,
compilation is completely avoided.
To specify dylibs in the linking phase:
pass an array
of Metal Dynamic Library Objects
into the preloadedLibraries parameters
on the pipeline descriptor.
There is also the option
to provide this array of dynamic libraries
via Metal Compile Options
when compiling other shader libraries.
Moving large parts of utility code
into dynamic libraries
greatly shortens runtime compilation.
And finally, compiler options tuning
is really important for compute cases
like path tracing
in the final production quality renders.
and there is one additional Metal feature
to get the most performance
out of your final rendering.
Metal compiler options
and occupancy hints,
enable you to tune the performance
of any of these compute kernels
specifically when working
with dynamic linking.
Every GPU workload
has a performance sweet spot
that needs analysis and evaluation.
There is a Metal API
to target desired GPU occupancy,
that is also available
for dynamic libraries now.
This can unlock performance
for an existing workload
without changing
original code or algorithm.
It's worth noting that any tuning
needs to be performed per-device
as performance characteristics can vary
depending on the GPU architecture.
The Metal compute pipeline
descriptor property allows you
to express the desired occupancy level
by specifying the
Max-Total-Threads-Per-Threadgroup value.
The higher the value,
the higher occupancy
you hint the compiler to aim for.
Now, using this new Metal-Compile-Options
property for dynamic libraries,
you can match the pipeline state object
desired occupancy level.
Max-Total-Threads-Per-Threadgroup
is available for MetalCompileOptions
in iOS 16.4 and macOS 13.3.
Now you can simply match the
Pipeline State Object desired occupancy
while tuning Metal dynamic libraries
for the optimal performance.
This graph of the Blender Cycles shading
and intersection compute
kernels performance
shows the impact of changing
Max-Total-Threads-Per-Threadgroup.
That was the only variable changed for
the pipeline state object and the dylibs.
In this case, there is a sweet spot
where kernels perform at their best.
Each workload and device is unique
and the optimal value of
Max-Total-Threads-Per-Threadgroup differs
depending on the nature of the kernel.
The optimal value is not always
necessarily the maximum number of threads
per threadgroup a GPU supports.
Experiment with your kernels
to find the optimal value
you want to use and bake in the code.
Here is a Blender Cycles shading kernel,
The compiler statistics demonstrate
that the kernel is very complex.
There are several parameters
that affect the actual runtime.
The amount of spill,
the number of registers used,
and other operations like memory loads.
By tuning
the Max-Total-Threads-Per-Threadgroup,
you can change target occupancy
and find that performance sweet spot.
After finding the sweet spot,
the spill increases a little,
but increased overall occupancy has led to
significantly better kernel performance.
The Cycles path tracer
within Blender 3D 3.5
is now well-optimized for Metal,
and it uses all the best practices
I covered today.
Remember to maximize shader performance
of large and complex shaders
using function specialization,
use asynchronous compilation
to keep the application responsive
while generating optimized shaders
in the background,
enable dynamic linking
for faster compilation at runtime,
and tune your compute kernels
with new Metal compiler options
to get the optimal performance.
Be sure to check out previous sessions
where you can learn how to scale
compute workloads for Apple GPUs
and discover
more compilation workflows in Metal.
Thank you for watching.
♪ ♪