♪ ♪
Hello, and welcome.
I'm Varun Subramanian, an Engineer in GPU,
Graphics, and Display Software group
at Apple.
This session is the second part
of a 3-part series
on bringing your high-end games to Mac.
The first session, covers how you can
evaluate your game and "make a game plan".
This session focuses on your shaders
and how to improve their flexibility
and speed
with some of the new Metal compiler tools,
including new ways to convert your shaders
to Metal intermediate representation
and how to avoid on-device compilation
by finalizing GPU binaries
during your games' build time.
The Metal compiler toolchain
helps you compile the shaders
that power your game
and Metal now makes that easier than ever.
Creating the Metal IR on device
is suboptimal
because it adds compilation overhead
before the GPU can do the work
you need it to do.
Metal provides you with tools necessary
to generate Metal IR
from your Metal Shading Language
ahead of time.
That Metal IR is stored
as a part of a Metal library.
You should always aim to generate
your Metal libraries
using the Metal compiler toolchain
ahead of time.
However, when coming from another API
and shading language,
you need a way to get them to Metal.
If you are a new comer to the Mac,
you now have Metal Shader Converter.
This simplifies your shader pipelines
and allows you to package the generated
Metal libraries directly in your bundle,
avoiding on-device generation of Metal IR.
The Metal libraries generated are the same
as those generated from the Metal compiler
allowing your converted shaders
to natively integrate with the Metal API.
Use the new tool to convert
your existing shaders to Metal libraries
that you then ship with your game.
Metal Shader Converter
provides a robust feature set
to improve the experience
of converting your shaders to Metal.
It consumes DXIL to produce Metal IR.
You use it alongside
the open source DXC compiler tool
to build an end-to-end shader pipeline.
Converting from DXIL to Metal IR
is very fast
because Metal shader converter performs
the conversion at the binary level.
As a result you will have reduced
shader asset build times.
It also enables you to leverage
advanced features of Apple GPUs.
You can do this because of the rich
feature set of Metal shader converter,
which supports all the traditional
and modern shader stages
of your existing DXIL shaders.
Using Metal shader converter,
you can convert your shaders
for the traditional graphics pipeline
including tessellation
and geometry shaders to Metal libraries.
It also supports compute shaders,
as well as more recently introduced
ray tracing stages and shaders
and amplification and mesh shaders.
Now, I'll walk you through
how to use the Metal shader converter.
There are two scenarios where you may want
to convert your shaders via command line.
Using the command line tool
via terminal is a good mechanism
to convert one shader at a time.
If you have multiple shaders,
you can create a shell script
that calls Metal shader converter
to transform multiple shaders
for you automatically.
Converting your shader using
the command line tool is very easy.
After you set up DXC and shader converter,
start by compiling
your HLSL shader to DXIL.
DXC requires you to specify
the entry point to compile,
the type of shader, and the output file.
Next, call shader converter
on the DXIL file just created
and specify the output
Metal library to create.
By default,
shader converter generates a Metal library
for the latest version of macOS,
as well as JSON file
with useful reflection data.
At runtime, you pass this Metal library
to the Metal device
to load it
and build pipeline state objects.
There are two other scenarios
where the command line interface
may not be the best choice
for your workflow.
Some game engines have custom
asset build programs
that compile and package shaders
into game-specific formats.
Also, in some situations,
as you bootstrap your game for Metal,
you may also want to see how well
your shaders are working on the platform
before you fully turn them
into Metal libraries ahead of time.
For these last two cases,
you need a way to better integrate
Metal shader converter into your workflow.
To accomplish this, use the Metal
shader converter dynamic library.
It exposes all the same functionality
as the CLI tool
to help you generate Metal libraries.
The library offers a pure C interface
and just like the CLI,
it is available on both macOS and Windows,
so it's easy to integrate
into your existing workflows.
After you've converted your shaders
to Metal IR,
to integrate them into your game
you create pipeline states
and bind resources to them.
In your shaders,
you typically define resources
as global variables and assign
"register" declarations to them.
From the API side, your game either
binds resources directly to these slots,
or defines an explicit memory layout
via "root signatures".
Shader converter can help you
bring this model over,
because Metal
has a very flexible binding model.
The tool lays out these resources
into Argument buffers.
In this model,
you bind one argument buffer
directly to your pipeline
and reference your resources through it.
There are two layout modes
for this "top level" Argument buffer
that you can choose from,
to best suit your game.
The simplest layout you can create
is an automatic one,
where shader converter places
your resources one after the other.
Once you create a pipeline state
containing your shader,
you bind a single argument buffer,
and through it
you reference all your resources.
Alternatively, shader converter supports
explicitly defining a layout
that matches your root signature.
Use this mode when your game needs
to specify separate textures and samplers
into their own resource tables
or if your game uses bindless resources.
You may also embed raw buffers
and 32-bit constants
directly into the top-level
argument buffer,
shown as 0's and 1's in this diagram.
Now, the top-level Argument Buffer
is a resource shared
between the CPU and the GPU,
so as you write into it,
you need to coordinate access
to its memory
to avoid a race condition
that may cause visual corruption.
You don't need to serialize CPU
and GPU work to avoid this race condition.
One way to avoid this
is to use a bump allocator.
This can be a large Metal buffer
from which you sub-allocate
different resources each frame.
You then shadow the backing buffer
for each frame in flight
that your game handles.
For more details on bump allocator
implementation, check out our sample code.
For best Argument
buffer management practices,
check out the bindless session
from last year and Metal documentation.
The binding model is not the only place
where Metal shader converter
can help you
bring your shaders to the Mac.
Mapping certain shader stages
can be challenging
due to differences in graphics APIs.
For example, you may have pipelines
that leverage traditional geometry
and tessellation stages.
Metal is a modern API,
and it offers features
such as viewport ID and amplification
that makes older, less efficient stages
from other graphics APIs unnecessary.
However, when your game relies
on these pipelines for traditional effects
that enhance some surfaces,
like the grass rendered in this image,
converting them by hand is costly.
Metal shader converter helps you
bring these pipelines to Metal,
by mapping them to Mesh Shaders,
a modern and more efficient
graphics API construct.
The tool does the heavy lifting
to bring these complex pipelines
over to Metal easily,
by mapping each stage
to a Metal IR representation.
This includes the tessellator, which is
traditionally a fixed function operation.
To support this workflow,
this year Metal adds the capability
of linking visible functions to the
"object and mesh" stages of Mesh shaders.
After you've compiled your shaders,
you use them to build
a "Metal Mesh RenderPipeline Descriptor"
and compile it into
a "Metal Render Pipeline state".
When Metal receives the request
to build this pipeline state,
it compiles and links all the Metal IR,
baking all functions into
a single pipeline,
completely avoiding function call overhead
and maximizing performance during runtime.
Notice the power and flexibility
of Metal visible functions
that allows you to build this elaborate
render pipeline
containing these shading stages
with their supplemental functions.
While building these mesh pipelines
is straightforward,
every pipeline has to follow
a series of steps in precise order.
The shader converter runtime
helps you build these complex pipelines.
It even emulates draw calls
by dispatching mesh shading work.
For more information, please consult
the Metal Shader Converter documentation.
Now that your shaders are on Metal
and you are running your pipeline states,
here are some tips to help you get
great performance and visual correctness.
Shaders compiled with shader converter
reference Metal resources indirectly.
To flag resource residency to Metal,
you would call "useResource".
However, useResource is an expensive call
when used in excess.
Use the plural useResources
to provide several resources at once,
or consider using Metal heaps
via useHeap to flag residency
of several resources in a single call.
The pipeline objects are cached when
Metal compiles them for the first time,
automatically reducing compilation-based
hitching on subsequent runs of your game.
Binary archives can also help you here.
To get more out of the GPU
and customize the Metal IR
for higher performance,
shader converter provides you options.
There are customizations on compatibility,
GPU family,
vertex fetch behavior,
entry point naming, reflection, and more.
Here's one
additional optimization opportunity.
I mentioned earlier that shader converter
joins the Metal compiler
as another mechanism to produce
"Metal Libraries"
from your existing shader IR.
Metal uses these
to feed various graphics pipeline stages.
Since everything is Metal IR,
you can mix and match "Metal Libraries"
coming from Metal shader converter
and from the Metal Compiler in a single
app and even in a single pipeline.
Metal shading language also enables you
to access unique features
like programmable blending.
Use this approach to make the most
out of Apple's GPUs.
You can even take advantage
of unique shading functionality
such as tile shading.
This grants you tremendous flexibility
in how you bring your game to Metal.
Performance is important but visual
correctness of your game is paramount.
HLSL allows seamlessly treating textures
as arrays of one element.
To bring over shaders
that rely on this behavior,
create your textures as texture arrays,
or create "texture array views"
on your textures.
If you are using
"MetalKit Texture Loader",
it can also help you load files
as texture arrays.
To set up your sampler objects
and read from these textures,
make sure to let Metal know in advance
that you intend to reference samplers
in argument buffers by using the property
supportsArgumentBuffers
in the MTL Sampler Descriptor.
Now that you are familiar with Integrating
shader converter in your workflows,
here's how to get it.
You can download Metal shader converter
from developer.apple.com.
If you are working on your Mac,
get the Metal shader converter
for Mac package.
If you are working on Windows,
it is part of the Metal Developer Tools
for Windows package.
The beta version of the tool
is available now.
Both packages
contain Metal shader converter,
in standalone and library form,
as well as the runtime companion header.
Full documentation as well as
a Metal C++ code sample are available now.
Use the sample code to explore geometry
and tessellation emulation,
instanced drawing, and compute shaders.
Converting your shaders to Metal libraries
that you ship with your game
helps you avoid generating those libraries
at game run-time.
There is one additional optimization
you may be able to perform,
which is to compile your GPU binaries
ahead of time as well.
When you build your game,
you compile your shaders
into Metal libraries which still need to
be finalized into GPU binaries.
Usually your game does this at launch,
resulting in longer loading screens.
If you defer finalizing
GPU binaries at runtime,
it may result in frame drops as
the game compiles new pipelines on demand.
The Metal GPU Binary compiler
can help you solve this
by allowing you to generate
your shader binaries at game build time.
By removing the need to generate
shader binaries during gameplay,
your players benefit
from reduced app load time
without incurring
in additional GPU hitches.
To take advantage of this,
you can add another step to your workflow
to finalize your Metal libraries
into Metal binary archives at build time.
On device GPU Binary compilation
happens when you create a pipeline state
from a descriptor.
This descriptor not only references
functions from a Metal library,
but it also provides other critical
information to Metal
such as the color format
of its render attachments
and the vertex layout descriptor.
The GPU binaries are generated
just-in-time as part of the PSO creation.
Binary archives allow you to take control
of when that compilation occurs.
In order to produce
GPU binaries ahead of time,
you provide both
your existing Metal Library
as well as a pipeline configuration script
referencing those libraries.
You then provide both of them to metal-tt,
producing a binary archive
with GPU binaries.
To develop the pipeline script,
you produce a JSON script
with pipeline configurations
similar to the Metal API.
This Metal code generates
a render pipeline descriptor
and alongside is its JSON
equivalent representation.
For your pipeline script,
add the Metal library path
as well as its fragment
and vertex function names.
You also specify
any other pipeline state configuration.
That's it, you now have
a Metal script that you can use.
You can find additional info
about the JSON schema
in Metal's developer documentation.
Your ahead-of-time
shader compilation workflow
may not be geared to generate
pipeline script files.
For these cases, there's
an alternative way to produce them.
You can record Metal binary archives
while running your game on device.
These archives include
the corresponding pipeline scripts.
If you harvest these archives from device,
you can then use "metal-source"
to extract
their embedded pipeline scripts.
You then update the paths to your Metal
libraries in the extracted scripts.
For more information,
please refer to our talks
on how you can "Build GPU binaries"
as well as "Discover compilation
workflows".
Because GPU binaries are tailored
to each GPU,
"metal-tt" produces different versions
of the binaries
for you to distribute to your players,
based on their device.
Metal-tt helps you manage this complexity
by encapsulating
all the different GPU binaries
neatly into Metal binary archives.
This way,
when your app loads that binary archive,
Metal automatically picks
the appropriate binary for your players.
You can also encapsulate multiple sets
of binaries into a single binary archive.
Now that you are able to produce
binary archives ahead of time,
here are some best practices.
When your players run a Metal app
with pre-compiled GPU Binaries,
Metal searches the packaged binary archive
for the necessary GPU binary.
If Metal finds no match in the archive,
it automatically falls back
to on-device compilation.
Your app will still look correct, but this
may delay your submissions to the GPU.
You can test if your binary archives
contain the pipelines you expect,
using the option
"FailOnBinaryArchiveMiss".
You can easily specify
the FailOnBinaryArchiveMiss option
when creating
a Metal pipeline state object.
In case of a binary archive miss,
when you have this option set,
Metal skips the on-device compilation
and returns a nil pipeline state.
Once your binary archives are ready
with support for all target devices,
you're ready for deployment.
Not all of your players
may be on the latest OS.
To ensure all users
benefit from binary archives,
generate an archive for each major
OS version and store it into your app.
To accomplish this, check the OS version
of your player's device
and select the appropriate binary archive
to associate
with your Pipeline Descriptors.
When your players update their OS,
their binary archives may require
recompilation
for forward compatibility,
but Metal has you covered.
Metal identifies
the unpackaged binary archives
in app bundle on your player's device
and upgrades them automatically
in the background
after an OS update or game install.
In summary, "metal" compiler
and "metal-shaderconverter"
are your go-to tools,
to produce Metal libraries ahead of time
that you can then ship with your game.
Use the "metal compiler"
when compiling MSL source,
and "metal-shaderconverter"
when your shaders are in HLSL.
metal-tt enables you to finalize
Metal libraries into GPU binaries,
tailored to the various GPUs
in the Metal ecosystem.
Finally, metal-source helps you
harvest pipeline scripts
from your existing MacOS games.
The vast majority of these tools,
as well as the rest
of the GPU binary compiler toolchain,
now support Windows, in addition to macOS,
making it easier than ever to integrate
them into your existing workflows.
To wrap up:
Metal Shader Converter is a new tool
to help you bring your shaders that were
developed in another shading language
to Metal.
The GPU binary compiler and its toolchain,
which is now available on Windows,
can finalize your Metal libraries
into GPU binaries.
With these tools,
you now have everything you need
to bring your shaders to Metal.
There's still more to share with you.
Part 3 of the series focuses on
optimizing a high-end Metal application.
Be sure to check it out.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪