♪ ♪
Dave: Hi, I'm Dave Wendland,
a developer advocate
for our App Store Commerce team.
My colleague Alex and I will discuss
the new App Store Server Library
and how its set of functions
will enable your server
to utilize an array of capabilities
from generating a JWT
for the App Store Server API
to migrating away from the verifyReceipt
endpoint for purchase validation.
When we look back,
the App Store launched in 2008
when apps were either free or paid.
Soon, we added in-app purchases,
and ever since then,
the developer community has grown
in size and complexity across the globe.
The App Store continues to roll out
updates for developers and customers
to support the global
and dynamic mobile app ecosystem.
In 2021,
we released the next era of StoreKit tools
with the revamped StoreKit Framework,
App Store Server API,
and App Store Server Notifications v2.
With more updates in 2022
and again this year at WWDC 2023.
These tools provide transactions
and status in a signed JWS format.
And they are designed
to provide developers robust information,
client side and server side.
This set of APIs inspired
the App Store Server Library.
We are proud to share that this
library provides a set of functions,
which will make it easier
for our developer community to adopt
and integrate the latest APIs
available today and in the future.
The library beta launch
supports four languages:
Swift, Java, Node, and Python,
giving you the flexibility
to choose the language
that best supports
your backend and expertise.
The App Store server library
for each language is available on GitHub,
and we look forward to your feedback
and contributions.
I've broken down
what the library has to offer
into four key capabilities.
The first and most robust capability
is with the App Store Server API.
By streamlining the JWT creation,
you can use any
of the dozen different endpoints
the App Store Server API offers.
Next is a core capability
to verify JWS signed data,
so you can ensure your transactions
and server notifications
have been generated and signed by Apple.
Next is the extract
receipt transaction utility.
This simple tool extracts a transaction
identifier from an app receipt.
Doing this can alleviate your need
to use the verifyReceipt endpoint
and enable you to migrate
to the App Store Server API
for your purchase validation
and additional capabilities.
This provides a clear path to support
your current and legacy app versions.
Lastly, is the utility to generate
subscription promotional offer signatures.
This utility does the heavy lifting
of signing and generating your offers
using your in-app purchase private key.
If you are not familiar
with the subscription promotional offers,
learn more in our session titled
"Subscription Offers Best Practices."
Now lets deep dive into three
of those core library functions.
App Store Server API,
signed data verification,
and moving to the App Store Server API.
Let's get started
with the App Store Server API.
The foundation to the Server API
is the Get Transaction History endpoint.
By simply using a transaction ID,
this API provides a customer's
complete in-app purchase
transaction history.
And it has even more capabilities
beyond this endpoint.
This API has a dozen endpoints,
all of which require a form
of authentication,
a JSON Web Token.
Generating your JWT is a critical step,
and if you aren't familiar
with this process,
that is where the library comes in.
Over to Alex to demonstrate
getting the library setup for use
with the App Store Server API.
Alex: Hello, I'm Alex Baker,
an App Store Server Engineer.
I'll demonstrate how to get started
with the App Store Server Library
and how you can use it
to call the App Store Server API.
This demo will walk through collecting
the necessary pieces of information
to configure the App Store Server Library,
then show an example of creating
an API client and calling the API.
I am starting in App Store Connect
to get information I'll need
to use the App Store Server API
with the library.
Go to the Users and Access module...
Then the Keys tab,
then the In-App Purchase option.
There are a few pieces
of useful information here.
First, the issuer ID.
Next,
I am going to generate a new private key.
I'll give it a name, then click Generate.
Generating the key
provides two pieces of information:
The key ID and the option
to download the private key.
Downloading is only possible once.
Switching to the Apple Public Key
infrastructure website,
focus on the Apple Root Certificates
section in the upper left.
Download the root certificates.
Here is a simple Java project
using the Gradle build system.
First, add a dependency
on the App Store Server Library.
Moving to the ExampleApp class,
here are the pieces
of information I obtained earlier,
the issuerId,
the keyId, and the private key.
Additionally,
store the bundleId of the app--
in this demonstration,
I am using sandbox--
and store the appropriate enum value.
Using these pieces of information,
instantiate an AppStoreServerAPIClient.
With this client, call the Request
a Test Notification endpoint,
which requests the App Store server
send a notification with type TEST
to the URL you configured
in App Store Connect.
Last, print the testNotificationToken.
Running this, we will see
the testNotificationToken printed,
and, as expected, we see this token.
This demonstrated how
to use the App Store Server library
to simplify using the App Store Server API
and the information you need
from App Store Connect.
Now back to Dave.
Dave: Thank you, Alex.
That demo really illustrates
how quickly this library gets you set up
and generating a JWT
for use with the Server API.
This library will have a meaningful impact
in reducing your implementation timelines
when adopting our APIs.
While using the library
is helpful and simple,
there is nothing more critical
than storing
your in-app purchase private key securely.
And if you ever think
your key has been compromised,
generate a new key
in App Store Connect anytime.
As you begin your development,
we do recommend starting
with sandbox
and TestFlight transactions.
And lastly, be sure to check regularly
for updated Apple root
certificate authorities.
Now lets discuss
why signed data verification
is a foundational action
to your business with in-app purchases.
First let's discuss what signed
data contains and why it is important.
StoreKit Signed data means
it was generated and signed
by the App Store
in a JSON Web Signature format
and contains data about the app purchases,
in-app purchases,
customer events,
and customer subscription status.
The two most common signed data payloads
are the JWS Transaction
and JWS Renewal Info.
Then the appTransaction contains details
on the app version originally purchased
and the version currently installed
on device.
And then we have
the App Store Server Notifications V2,
the notification itself is signed data
and additionally may contain
a JWS Transaction and JWS Renewal Info.
And as a reminder,
you will only find this JWS signed data
in StoreKit 2 on iOS 15 and later
and in the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications v2.
It's recommended that you verify
the JWS signed data after any
of the following events:
When delivering or unlocking content
on device
or when your server
has received signed data,
whether that be from your own app,
another server,
or App Store server notifications.
And lastly, when you receive a response
from the App Store server API.
Here's Alex to demo
how to verify JWS signed data
and how the library handles this for you.
Alex: In this section,
I'll show how to verify signed data
from the App Store.
I'll describe the verification process
you would need to perform.
Then, we'll walk through how
the App Store Server Library's
SignedDataVerifier class
can perform this process for you.
I would like to stress that using tools
like the App Store Server Library
is highly advisable when you are
not familiar with the RFCs and protocols
behind the operations
I am about to describe.
Here is some signed data
from the App Store.
It looks like
there is a lot going on here.
Color coding reveals
there are three sections.
Each section is separated by a period
and is Base64 URL encoded.
The first and largest section
is the header.
Once decoded,
the header is a JSON structure
with fields defined
by the JWS specification.
In this case,
our header only has two fields:
First, the algorithm,
which is always ES256.
Next a field called x5c.
This is an array of certificates
that are used to calculate
the expected public key
that signed the JWS.
Let's review the certificate
chain construction process.
The first certificate
in the array is the leaf certificate.
This certificate's public key
signed the JWS.
To verify this certificate is from Apple,
construct a chain of trust
back to a known trusted source,
in this case,
an Apple root certificate authority.
The next certificate in the array
is the Apple Worldwide Developer Relations
intermediate certificate authority.
Think of this
as a more specialized version
of the Apple Root Certificate Authority
focused on developers.
The last certificate in the chain
is an Apple root certificate authority
so that we understand which Apple
authority originated this chain.
Reminder, it is important to verify
the certificate exactly matches
a root certificate we previously obtained
from Apple's
Public Key Infrastructure website.
The first step is to verify
that each certificate is signed
by the previous certificate in the chain.
Then perform additional
verification steps,
like making sure each certificate has
valid dates, is properly formatted, etc.
Next, validate that these certificates
are from Apple and that their purpose
is to sign App Store data,
as opposed to an unrelated use case,
which would not be valid
to sign App Store data.
To verify the leaf certificate,
confirm its purpose by checking
the presence of the object identifier,
or OID, for Mac App Store Receipt Signing.
For the intermediate certificate,
check that the intermediate authority OID
for Apple Worldwide Developer Relations.
Last, as stated before,
make sure the root certificate authority
is one of the certificates you stored
as an Apple Root Certificate Authority.
Now let's actually decode
a leaf certificate and observe how
to check these values.
Here is the X.509 v3 extensions section
of a certificate as produced
by the OpenSSL x509 command.
At the bottom is the OID listed
on the previous slide,
indicating the certificate's purpose
is App Store receipt signing.
However, there are some additional fields
that are important to check.
Here we see
the authority information access section,
which provides information
about the issuer and, importantly,
provides information for checking
if the certificate was revoked.
Using the Online Certificate
Status Protocol, or OCSP.
check if a certificate has been revoked
before proceeding
with the verification process.
The process and cryptographic procedures
for doing so are defined in RFC 6960.
After verifying the certificate chain,
check the JWS is signed
by the leaf certificate's public key.
Take the leaf certificate from before,
extract the public key
of the leaf certificate,
take the key and original JWS,
and pass them
to a JWS signature verification function.
The verification function checks
that the data is signed
by the public key and decodes the payload.
The process is almost complete,
but there is
one additional verification step.
Here is a decoded
App Store Server TEST Notification.
The previous steps verified
the data came from the App Store.
However, also check
that the notification is targeted
at your correct application
and environment.
Check the appAppleId and bundleId
to confirm the notification
is targeted for your correct application.
Check the environment
matches the expected environment.
Just like the other steps
in the verification process,
the App Store Server library also checks
these when it performs the verification.
That completes the process
to verify signed data from the App Store.
Next, I'll expand my project from earlier
to verify signed data
using the SignedDataVerifier class
included in the App Store Server Library.
The SignedDataVerifier class performs
the verification steps previously covered.
In this demo, I'll get the test
notification that I requested earlier,
and then validate
and decode the signed notification.
There is a small delay
between requesting the test notification
and the notification
being received on my server.
Therefore, add a five-second delay.
Next, call
the Get Test Notification Status endpoint
using the testNotificationToken
obtained earlier.
Last, print the first few characters
of the notification to confirm success.
The Get Test Notification Status
endpoint returns the result
of the send attempt,
as well as the notification payload.
The beginning of that payload
is what we should see.
As expected, I see the first few
characters of the notification.
Moving on,
creating a signed data verifier.
This requires three pieces of information,
starting with the list
of Apple Root certificate authorities.
The certificates I downloaded earlier
are now in the resources folder.
Import the root certificates into a Set.
Since I am using sandbox,
I don't require an app Apple ID.
Pass null instead in sandbox.
Last,
whether to perform revocation checking.
Because the notification
was just received,
onlineChecks should be true.
For notifications
received months or years ago,
this should be false
because the certificates may have expired.
Pass these fields
into a new SignedDataVerifier.
Then, pass in the notification
received earlier,
print the result,
and then run the program.
Once the program is complete,
the program will display
a verified and decoded notification.
Since this is a test notification,
this will have a type
of TEST and the app's bundle identifier
in the payload,
along with a few other fields.
As expected,
I see a decoded notification of type TEST.
I expanded on our previous demo to
demonstrate the SignedDataVerifier object.
Here’s Dave to review some best practices.
Dave: Wow, that really illustrates
all the steps required
to verifying signed data
and how the library can handle
that complexity for you,
so be sure
to utilize the SignedDataVerifier
for your server-side validation.
An important reminder:
when you verify data,
you still need to confirm
the app and product identifiers
to ensure you are granting
or revoking purchases
for the correct app or service.
Lastly, as certificates expire
and can be revoked,
don't hardcode any certificates,
client side or server side,
and always validate that they are active.
Now we'll review
another App Store server utility to assist
with moving
your server-side app receipt validation
off the verifyReceipt endpoint
and over to the App Store Server API.
The App Store Server library
offers a utility
to help specifically with this migration
and ensures no app is left behind.
When considering moving
to the App Store Server API,
there are many reasons
to prioritize this work in your roadmap.
The API supports purchase validation
and contains additional endpoints
useful for customer support, appeasement,
and testing App Store
Server Notifications V2.
As we continue to make updates
and release new properties,
these will be released
only with the JWS signed data,
which is supported by StoreKit 2,
App Store Server API,
and App Store Server Notifications V2.
An additional benefit,
the only data you need to record,
is an original transaction ID
or transaction ID.
You no longer need to save base64
encoded receipts in your account system.
And with our continued investment
in the latest APIs,
we have announced that verifyReceipt
endpoint is now deprecated.
To learn more, check out the session
"What's new in App Store server APIs"
for a detailed update and guidance.
Now here's Alex
to share how the App Store server library
will assist in your migration.
Alex?
Alex: Thanks, Dave.
Now let's walk
through a flow diagram for App Receipts.
While StoreKit 2
and the App Store Server API
are great tools to use,
it is important
to support clients on older devices
or users that have not updated recently,
and for which only App Receipts
may be provided to your server.
I'll show how these devices
were supported previously,
and then how you can continue
to support these clients
following verifyReceipt's deprecation.
First, the device sends
a receipt to your server.
In the old model,
your server passes this receipt
to verifyReceipt,
and then receives the decoded receipt.
The response contains
an originalTransactionId,
which is passed
to the Get Transaction History endpoint
in the App Store Server API.
The App Store Server returns
signed transactions you use
to provide service to the customer.
Now that verifyReceipt is deprecated,
let's replace this section.
The receipt utility
in the App Store Server Library
directly extracts a transaction ID
from a receipt.
You pass the transaction ID
to the App Store Server API,
removing the need to make two round trips.
After this,
store the revision from the endpoint.
This removes the need
to re-parse the entire history each time.
Because the value extracted
from the app receipt
may or may not be
an original transaction ID,
we are excited to announce
that many of our endpoints,
including the Get Transaction History
endpoint,
now support any transaction ID
as a parameter,
not just an original transaction ID.
Now I'll demonstrate
extracting transaction IDs for use
with the Get Transaction History endpoint
using the App Store Server Library.
Here I will take an app receipt,
extract a transaction ID,
and call the Get Transaction History
endpoint using the ID.
First, the App Receipt.
You can get an App Receipt from a device
or an App Store Server Notification V1.
I have one here already.
Next, create an instance
of the ReceiptUtility class.
To extract the transaction ID,
call the extract transaction ID
from app receipt method.
Not all receipts
will have a transaction ID.
It is possible
the user doesn't have any purchases.
Therefore, add a null check.
To provide some more depth
to this problem,
imagine we want to get information
about the most recent consumables
for this user
and exclude revoked consumables.
Create a Transaction History
Request object,
specify that only wanted are products
of type CONSUMABLE
to exclude revoked transactions
and that the data should be returned
in descending order.
We need two helper objects,
a response variable,
and a list of transactions.
A do while loop pages
through the responses
from the transaction history endpoint.
If this isn't the first request,
fetch the revision token
from the previous response
to keep paging through the data.
Then, call the Get Transaction History
endpoint with the transaction ID
from the app receipt, the request object,
and the revision.
Finally, add all the transactions
from the response to the transaction list.
Repeat this process until the hasMore
field is false in the response.
Print out the transactions
to see the result.
Here I see a list
of transactions returned from the API.
The could be decoded
using the SignedDataVerifier
from the previous demo.
Thanks for joining our final demonstration
that showed how you can use App Receipts
with the App Store Server API.
Back to Dave to wrap us up.
Dave: I'm really excited
about the new App Store Server library,
and I see these capabilities
easing your adoption of our APIs
and transitioning
to the App Store Server API.
Here's a screenshot
of the App Store Server API
Java repository on Github.
On this page,
you can find links to our documentation,
submit pull requests, and find examples
of how to use the library.
You can download
the App Store Server library BETA soon
and start planning your adoption
of the App Store Server API.
We look forward
to your feedback and feature requests.
Please contact us
at Feedback Assistant and on Github.
Thank you.
♪ ♪