♪ ♪
Jennifer: Hi, I’m Jennifer Patton,
a designer on the Apple Design Team.
Matthew: And I’m Matthew Koonce,
the engineering manager
of the SwiftUI team for watchOS.
Jennifer: For the tenth major release
of watchOS,
we have redesigned the user interface
to surface timely information,
communicate focused content at a glance,
celebrate the shape and fidelity of the
display
with full screen color and imagery,
and make navigation consistent
and predictable.
Matthew: And we've also evolved our APIs.
SwiftUI is at the very heart
of watchOS 10.
In this session, we'd like
to walk you through the details
of the watchOS 10 redesign.
We’ll start with some key
design principles.
Then, we’ll look at some new ways
to structure navigation in your app.
After that, we’ll talk about
the evolution of our layout system,
and some updated APIs
that help make use of every pixel.
And lastly, we’ll see how color
and materials
can bring a whole new dimension to apps.
Sound like a plan?
Jennifer: Yeah!
Let's get right into it.
Let’s start with some Design Principles.
The first thing you’ll want to think about
when designing for Apple Watch is
“What is the most relevant information
or experience
my app can offer to people in the moment?”
Let’s look at the Weather app
as an example.
Because Apple Watch
is a timekeeping device
best suited for quick
and focused interactions,
the first thing you’ll see when opening
the app is your local weather for today.
With a simple rotation
of the digital crown,
you’ll get local weather
for the rest of the day,
and then for the rest of the week.
And if I’m looking for the weather
in New York, for example,
my list of cities is just a single tap
away from any of these detail views.
Weather achieves what I like to think of
as an “Apple Watch Moment.”
When you’re designing your app,
try to narrow the focus of the experience
to just what’s relevant
at the time the wearer raises their wrist.
Watch experiences should be
highly specialized for brief interactions.
If you had ten seconds
of someone’s attention,
which information would you surface?
On iPhone, News is a multi-tab,
multi-level app rich with content.
And on Apple Watch,
News is focused on five top stories.
The content is stacked vertically in
the feed and expands inline when tapped.
Brief interactions are one of the things
that I love about designing
for Apple Watch.
When you only get a few seconds
of people's attention,
you need to be concise,
like how News focuses the experience
on just today's headlines.
And Heart Rate displays finite data first,
so it can devote most of the view
to a full screen animation.
And Activity simplifies a broad experience
into single focused views.
So when designing your app,
keep it brief and keep it focused.
When we announced Apple Watch in 2014,
we also introduced the Digital Crown
as being a unique and precise input device
that could be used
without obscuring the display.
In watchOS 10,
we are emphasizing the Digital Crown
as the way you get to and navigate
through apps, to scroll,
paginate, and make precise adjustments.
While interactions
should be anchored to the crown,
they should also always
be backed up by touch.
You can use the design goal
of tying interactions to the digital crown
to shape your app’s navigation structure
and experience.
When designing for watchOS,
consider the journey people will take
from the moment they raise their wrist.
A great new feature in watchOS 10
is the Smart Stack.
With a turn of the digital crown,
glanceable widgets spring onto the screen
in an intelligently ordered stack.
When you design your app,
you can begin by thinking about
which information would make
the best Smart Stack widget
and then design around those relevant and
timely experiences to architect your app.
And definitely check out design widgets
for the Smart Stack on Apple Watch
by my colleague, Ed.
Once you have narrowed the focus
of your watch app
to bite-sized pieces of information
that are relevant in the present moment,
your next step will be
to stitch those moments together
into an easily navigable structure.
Matthew and his team
have been hard at work
developing some incredible new APIs
for you to use.
Take it away, Matthew.
Matthew: Thanks, Jenn.
Let’s take a look at how navigation
within apps has been updated with SwiftUI.
First, we’ll look at NavigationSplitView,
which provides
detailed content at a glance.
Then, some updates to TabView
that allow you to tie more interactions
to the Digital Crown.
These both sit alongside
the NavigationStack
as our core navigation paradigms.
Picking the right way to structure
your app is a fundamental decision,
and each has its strengths.
Let’s start with NavigationSplitView.
The concept of NavigationSplitView
on watchOS
is borrowed from a two column layout,
like you have in Weather on iPadOS.
On watchOS, the source list
and detail view are separated
and then recombined,
with the source list
tucked just beneath the detail view.
Now that source list
is just a tap away.
Jennifer: Navigation Split View is a
perfect option if you have a source list,
like a list of cities in Weather
or a list of stocks
and detailed views
of the items in that source list.
Land people directly in the detail view
when they launch your app.
Use location, recency, frequency,
or some other indication
of user intent to inform
which detail to surface first.
Strive to make your detail view
so unmistakable at a glance
that it doesn’t need a title.
Matthew: One really slick feature
of Navigation Split View that we built
right into SwiftUI is the transition
between the detail view
and the source list.
You can, of course, tap the list icon,
or even better, interact with your finger.
Jennifer: And the source list
is an excellent tool
for showing comparative data.
It’s 10:09 a.m. in Cupertino
and it’s 7:09 p.m. in Budapest.
There is no need to title the source list
and no need for a close button
or navigation controls.
This allows the source list
to use a shorter navigation bar,
showing more comparative data
on screen at a glance.
Matthew: The API for NavigationSplitView
is the same on watchOS
as it as on other platforms.
You can set up a source list
and initialize it with a selection.
Always initialize the selection to a value
so SwiftUI can automatically launch
to the detail view.
Next, let’s talk about TabView, which has
received some really fantastic updates
and is my new favorite way
to navigate apps on my Apple Watch.
Tab view can scroll between views,
and new in watchOS 10,
a single tab can expand
and resize as needed.
Jennifer: Aside from allowing content
to expand in-line,
this also allows a design
that fits on a single screen by default
to support localized text
and large type if needed.
Matthew: Let’s take a closer look
at how we’re using TabView in Activity.
Activity has a tab
for each of the ring detail views,
and it’s using
the new “vertical page” style.
Activity also features this
new blur transition between each tab.
Combine this transition
with the container background modifier
for a seamless blend between views.
The last page in Activity is a scrolling
list of recently completed exercises.
Adding that list is as easy
as, well, adding a list!
TabView will automatically detect
any scrolling content,
and will expand to accommodate it.
So that’s how we can quickly build
a layout similar to Activity,
but TabView has one more trick
up its sleeve.
Jenn: Have you noticed
the cool animation that occurs
when you scroll to the move tab?
Watch the Activity Rings
as they scale up into the top left corner.
This achieves our design goal of
tying interactions to the digital crown,
while also keeping
the Activity Rings permanently in view.
Matthew: Now you may be wondering,
“Can I do that, too?”
And the answer is, you can!
Let’s take a look.
In watchOS 10,
you can now drive animations
based on the selection value
of the TabView.
One really neat trick is to hook this up
to a matched geometry effect.
The Activity Rings appear in both
the TabView and in the toolbar.
By adding the matched geometry effect
to each of these two views,
SwiftUI will automatically animate
from one position to another.
Jennifer: Navigation Split View
and Tab View are really capable,
but they’re not necessarily right
for every app.
If your app can’t do what it needs to do
by pivoting between a detail
and source list,
or in a few vertically paginated tabs,
consider using a NavigationStack.
Matthew: Yep, that’s totally right.
We’re using NavigationStack in many apps
like Workout, Calendar, and Music.
We’ve even refreshed
the navigation push animation!
It now highlights
and moves the view you selected.
Jennifer: The NavigationStack is still
the clearest way to lead people
into and back out of a hierarchy of views.
Use a large title on the first view,
but not on any of the subviews
where a back button is present.
When designing your app,
choose a navigation structure that
accomplishes your “Apple Watch Moment”
in as few interactions as possible.
Matthew:
So that’s navigation on watchOS 10.
NavigationSplitView, TabView,
and NavigationStack
make the experience consistent
and predictable across all apps.
Jennifer: Now that you have chosen the
best navigation structure for your app,
let’s talk about the resources
you can use to build each view.
As the Apple Watch display and hardware
have evolved,
the display has gotten consistently
larger and more rounded.
While designing for an increasingly
rounded display over the years,
we have developed a flexible
grid system that defines the size
and placement of controls, labels,
and content.
To accommodate different types of content,
we designed three foundational layouts.
Dial-based Views,
Infographic Views,
and Lists.
All of these layouts are designed
to adapt automatically
to the different Apple Watch sizes
supported by watchOS 10.
Dial-based views are great for dense
information delivered at a glance.
The use of full screen color and imagery,
like weather conditions,
can help to add additional context.
Dials also allow you to add up
to four different corner controls
without obscuring content.
The infographic view
is ideal for charts, graphs,
and other data visualizations that are
paired with a block of text and metrics.
And Lists makes it easy
to scroll through content
and find exactly what you need.
The grids are based on the shape
of the active display area.
We start with the curvature
of the display,
and use that to mathematically inform
the sizing and position
of the elements in the view.
These layout grids are available
in the Apple Design Resources.
I hope you’ll find them useful
in designing your app.
Matthew: The layout grids
created by Jenn and the Design team
form the foundations of watchOS 10,
and they provide
the underpinnings of many of our APIs.
For example, use scene padding to get
the insets you need to build a dial view.
Or use the new “top bar trailing”
placement to add a button
to the toolbar at the top right
of the screen.
When you use this placement,
the time moves out of the way
and centers on screen.
The now playing view really makes
use of the updated toolbar
In addition to using
the “top bar leading”
and “trailing” placements,
Now Playing adds its control buttons
to the bottom bar.
SwiftUI is using the same layout grids
that Jenn just described
to align these buttons.
No need to add any additional padding.
Also in the bottom bar
is the pause button.
You can use the control size modifier
to make this button larger
and more prominent.
It’s never been easier
to build a Now Playing screen!
These toolbar placements
unlock new opportunities
for focused interactions by allowing
more controls on screen at a time.
Jennifer: We developed the layout
grids to utilize every pixel
and make the experience
of using Apple Watch more consistent
and predictable across apps.
I also hope they’ll inspire you to
design great apps for many years to come.
Matthew: Next, let’s talk about how color
and a full suite of materials,
give the people a sense of place
inside the hierarchy of views.
Jennifer: One of our design goals
for watchOS 10
is to emphasize the shape
and fidelity of the display
with full screen color and images.
To that end, we added four vibrant
full-screen background materials
that affect background content
at different blur levels,
like Ultra Thin, Thin,
Regular, and Thick.
Matthew: And you can use
the same SwiftUI APIs on watchOS
as you might already do
on other platforms.
Jennifer: We also added
a full screen background gradient
that you can tint
with your own accent colors.
In Activity,
we use the accent colors for Move,
Exercise, and Stand
to differentiate three consecutive tabs
that have similar layouts at a glance.
Another great use of full screen color
is to set tone,
like this calming blue background
in Sleep.
You can use color to convey information
at a glance,
like in World Clock where we use
solar gradients to show the time of day.
You can also use full screen color
to convey a state change.
In Timers, the background is black
when the timer is counting down,
and then, bright orange
declares that my egg timer is done.
To make sure foreground elements
look great over all of these backgrounds,
we added vibrant fill materials
to controls and platter cells,
and vibrant text labels,
in Primary, Secondary, Tertiary,
and Quaternary prominence levels
for creating information hierarchy
in typography.
We also added vibrant versions
of all the system colors
that ensure legibility
over full screen backgrounds.
Matthew: It’s so cool to have all of
those new materials available on watchOS!
So how does it come together in an app?
Let’s use the Noise app as an example.
We’ll start with the full screen
background gradient.
This comes from the “container background”
modifier, which is new in watchOS 10.
Noise passes the color green
with a gradient applied.
The unfilled bars of the chart
and the X-axis labels,
are using the secondary foreground style.
The secondary style
provides some vibrancy
and allows the background color
to come through.
The filled bars
and the rest of the text labels
are using the primary style.
With that, the view is complete!
When you update your app for watchOS 10,
you’ll notice a few other changes.
Presentations throughout the system
now use a full screen thin material.
This give the wearer additional context
about where they are in the app.
You can see a hint of green
just beneath this view.
In fact, all of SwiftUI’s controls,
labels, and List content
have been updated to look amazing
when placed over a material background.
Jennifer: And the navigation bar
has a beautiful new variable blur.
This provides a gentle transition
as content scrolls
underneath the navigation items.
That was a lot to cover!
We walked through our design principles,
entirely new ways to navigate in apps,
brand-new layouts,
and how to use color and materials.
watchOS 10 is a major leap forward
for the design of Apple Watch apps.
Matthew: And we have so much more
to talk about with all of the changes!
Jennifer: Check out “Meet watchOS 10”
for an overview of everything that is new,
as well as “Design Widgets
for the Smart Stack on Apple Watch”
to learn how to design beautiful widgets.
Matthew:
If you already have a watchOS app,
“Update your app for watchOS 10”
is for you!
We’ll walk through
updating an existing app
with all the SwiftUI APIs we showed here.
watchOS 10 was only possible
because of deep collaboration
between design and engineering.
And this is just the start!
Jennifer: That’s so true.
watchOS has
never been a more vibrant platform,
and there’s never been a better time
to design and build your Apple Watch app.
♪ ♪