♪ ♪
Hello, I'm Rachel.
I'm an engineer on the Safari team.
Today, I'm excited to share
what's new in web apps.
We've been on a journey with web apps
since the release
of the very first iPhone,
and they just keep getting better.
In iOS and iPadOS 16.4,
we added notifications
to Home Screen web apps,
using the Web Push standard
with support for badging.
We also added API for iOS and iPadOS
browsers to adopt Add to Home Screen.
New in iOS and iPadOS 17,
Add to Home Screen is now available
in Safari View Controller.
So now users can add Home Screen web apps
in iOS browsers and many in-app browsers.
New in macOS Sonoma,
we now have web apps on Mac.
Web apps on Mac let me focus
on websites that I use all the time
in a dedicated way that's separate
from the rest of my browsing.
Similar to iOS,
the way I can create a web app
is by adding a website to the Dock.
I'm browsing Wikipedia,
and I'd like to add it to the Dock.
I'm going to open the File menu
and select "Add to Dock..."
Now I can see the icon,
name and URL of this site.
I'm going to simplify the name.
I could also modify the icon if wanted to,
but this one looks good.
I'll press “Add”,
and now there's a new icon in my Dock.
I'm going to close Safari for now
and open the Wikipedia web app.
Now once I've launched this web app,
I can use this site in a way
that feels more like an app.
I'm still logged into my account.
That's because Safari copies website
cookies when it is added to the Dock.
There is a simplified toolbar
with navigation buttons.
and the theme color for the site
blends into the toolbar.
As a developer, you can control
whether the navigation buttons are shown.
Today, we're going to first cover
how web apps on Mac work out of the box
for all websites.
Then I'll tell you about how you can
customize the behavior of your web app
to create the best experience
for your users.
Finally, I'll discuss notifications,
including sounds and badging,
giving you a way to reach your users
even when they're not actively
using your web app.
Let's start with how web apps work
out of the box.
Web apps on Mac work great
with no adoption required by developers.
Any website can become a web app.
Web apps on Mac are fully integrated
with many of the features
that you would expect
from a native app on macOS.
Let's take a look at the web app
that I already added to my Dock.
This site doesn't have
any web app-specific features,
such as a web app manifest,
and it looks great and functions
as a standalone web app.
Like all Mac apps,
web apps work great with Stage Manager,
Mission Control, and keyboard shortcuts,
such as command + tab.
Web apps can be opened from the Dock,
Launchpad, and Spotlight Search.
Web apps work with AutoFill credentials
from iCloud Keychain
and from third-party apps
that have adopted
the Credential Provider
Extension API.
We put people in control of their privacy,
so they can grant camera, microphone,
and location access to your web app
in the same ways as native apps,
through system permission prompts
and in the Privacy & Security
section of System Settings.
That was the default behavior,
but you may want to customize
the experience
for people who use your website.
When a webpage is added
to the Dock on macOS,
it is always treated as a web app.
As a developer, you can control
the initial behavior of the toolbar
for the web app's window.
The default behavior shows a toolbar
with navigation controls.
This is helpful
for navigating around sites
that don't have
their own navigation controls.
You may not want to show the toolbar if
your site has its own navigation controls
or navigation controls aren't necessary
in the context of your site.
This is called
the standalone display mode.
The default behavior on iOS
is different from macOS.
A website that has been added to the
Home Screen opens in the default browser.
This provides a quick way
for users to access a commonly-used site
right from the Home Screen.
Websites that have been added
to the Home Screen on iOS and iPadOS,
with the standalone display mode,
will become a Home Screen web app.
Home Screen web apps have a standalone,
app-like experience on iOS,
with separate cookies and storage
from the browser.
There's no browser-provided UI,
such as a toolbar,
and all the content is from the web page.
If you want your site to be able
to use Web Push and badging on iOS,
then you should use
the standalone display mode.
To set the display mode.
I'll add a web app manifest to my site.
The web app manifest is a way
for a website to communicate
its intended behavior for web app-related features with the system.
To add a web app manifest to your website,
simply add a link with rel="manifest"
to a JSON file in the head of your HTML.
I called mine “manifest.json”.
In the corresponding manifest file,
add the keys and values
that apply to your website.
First I'll set the name
since this is what I want to be used
as the web app name,
not the website title,
since mine is pretty long.
To change the display mode,
I'll set display to “standalone”.
On macOS,
the web app will not have a toolbar.
On iOS and iPadOS,
the site will open
in a Home Screen web app,
instead of in the default browser.
Now, let's cover where links clicked
within the web app open.
All web apps have an associated scope.
Links within the scope
open within the web app.
The default scope is the host of
the webpage used to create the web app.
You can further refine the scope
using the web app manifest
to limit it to a specific path
on your site.
For example, when I click on this link
in the Browser Pets web app
to go to another page “webkittens”,
you'll notice that we stay
within the web app
since Web Kittens is just another page
on our site under example.com.
Now when I click on a link to apple.com
that will open in my default browser,
since that is outside the scope
of example.com.
If I wanted links to Web Kittens
to open in the default browser,
like that link to apple.com,
then I can adjust the scope
in the web app manifest.
To adjust the scope, I'll first start
by adding the "start_url".
The start_url is the URL that is loaded
when the web app is first opened.
This will open the home page
for Browser Pets.
Now I'll add the scope.
Suppose I want to separate Browser Pets
and Web Kittens into different web apps,
then I could limit the scope
to just Browser Pets.
The scope is a subdirectory
of the manifest URL.
In this case,
the scope will be example.com/browserpets.
Any links within the scope
will stay within the web app
and any links outside the scope
will open in the default browser.
In Home Screen web apps on iOS,
links outside the scope
will open in Safari View Controller.
So when I tap this link
in this Home Screen web app,
it opens in Safari View Controller.
We need to log in to get the most
out of many of the websites
that we use on a daily basis.
As I mentioned earlier, to make web apps
work great out of the box for most users,
we copy website cookies when
a web app on Mac is added to the Dock.
In many cases, users stay logged in
when the web app is opened
for a seamless experience.
From that point on, cookies are separate
between Safari and the web app.
If the authentication state
is solely stored in cookies for your site,
then your users should be
automatically logged into the web app
when they add it to their Dock
since Safari copies the website's cookies
to the web app
when it is added to the Dock.
Some websites split authentication state
between cookies and local storage.
Since local storage is not copied
when a web app is created,
users would have
to re-authenticate to continue
using your site as a web app.
To create a smooth experience
for your users,
keep authentication state
saved within cookies.
As I mentioned before,
links that go beyond
the scope of the web app
will open in the default browser.
If the user logs into your web page
in their default browser,
they will not be logged into the web app
that has already been added to the Dock,
since cookies and storage are separate
after the web app is added.
Authentication through OAuth
on a third-party domain
will still open in your web app.
This is done through heuristics.
If you test and find that your OAuth flow
opens the authentication experience
in the user's default browser,
please send us feedback
using apple.com/feedback.
If you want to ensure your OAuth flows
do not open in the user's default browser,
you can use window.open.
Links loaded through window.open
will always open in the web app
regardless of scope.
Apple is engaging with standards bodies
to offer developers a way to indicate
that links to authentication domains
should stay within
the context of the web app.
Some websites use email links to
automatically sign in users
by opening the link.
Since links from email will open
in the default browser,
this will not automatically sign users in
to the web app that they already have.
You may want to provide an alternative
one-time code in the email
that your user can easily enter
into the sign-in flow on your site.
For a more convenient and
more secure authentication experience,
consider adopting passkeys
for authentication on your site.
Check out "Meet passkeys"
from WWDC22 for more information.
Notifications in web apps on Mac
is an exciting addition
to our existing standards-based
Web Push support
for Safari in macOS Ventura
and in Home Screen web apps in iOS 16.4.
Now I'll tell you
how you can integrate notifications,
including badging and sounds,
into your web apps.
If you have already implemented
Web Push according to web standards,
then push notifications should work
for your web page
as a web app on Mac
with no additional work.
Notifications for web apps on Mac
use the web app's application icon
in the notification.
Web Push notifications originating
from Safari show the Safari icon,
while notifications from web apps on Mac
use the web app's icon
in the notification,
providing context to users.
You may want a sound to play
on the user's device
when they receive a notification
to get their attention,
so now I'll tell you how that works
on macOS, iOS, and iPadOS.
Using the Notification API,
you can specify if your notification
should have sound or not.
Following platform conventions,
sound is on by default on iOS and iPadOS,
and sound is off by default on macOS.
To override the platform default,
explicitly specify a silent value.
If the notification should be silent,
set silent to true in the options
when requesting your notification.
If the notification should make a sound,
then set silent to false.
Just like for native app notifications,
users can control notification sounds
using notifications settings.
Badging is useful to alert users
that there is something to address
in the web app.
Just like for Home Screen web apps
in iOS 16.4,
web apps on Mac support badging.
Since badging and push notifications
are so closely associated
on macOS, iOS, and iPadOS,
when users allow a web app
to send notifications,
that includes permissions
for the web app to use badging.
Badges can be updated
when the web app is open
and when push events are being handled
in the background.
Users can always configure badges
in Settings.
For more information
on adopting the Badging API,
check out "Badging for Home Screen
Web Apps" on webkit.org.
For more information on adopting
standards-based Web Push,
check out "Meet Web Push for Safari"
from WWDC22.
Home Screen web apps on iOS
and web apps on Mac integrate with Focus
to give users control
over their notifications.
Users can set which notifications
they want to see in different Focus modes
and have their preferences applied
to Focus modes across all their devices.
Let's take a look back
at our web app manifest.
The "id" manifest key defines
unique web apps within the same domain.
This is used for syncing Focus modes and
can be useful if you have multiple parts
of your website that should be treated as
distinct web apps under the same domain.
If you only have one web app
for a given domain,
then you don't need to set the id.
The fallback if there is no
id provided is the start_url.
One of the great parts of Focus
is how Focus modes sync
across all of a user's devices.
Both you and your users control
how Focus mode settings are synced.
You as a developer may have distinct web
apps for different parts of your site.
For example, you may have one web app
for your shop and one web app for forums.
Here, the “Name" column is the name of
your web app on the user's iPhone or Mac.
The id key of the web app manifest
can be used to indicate
that a web app created
with the id "shop" is for your shop
and the web app created
with the id "forums" is for the forums
for your community.
This way, your users can set
different notification preferences
for your Shop and Forums web apps.
Focus modes sync across a user's device
when the name and id align.
Users can create multiple instances
of a web app for a given site
on their device.
This can be useful for separating
work and personal accounts.
The user can choose different names
for each instance.
In this example
"Forums" and "Forums - Work".
This way users can set different
notification and Focus settings
for each of their Forums web apps
that sync across all their devices.
There are several APIs
that we added to WebKit this year
that may be helpful to you
when creating your website.
We have support for
the User Activation API,
which tells the website when a transient
or sticky user activation has occurred.
This is helpful for you to determine
if it is okay to call a function
that depends on user activation,
such as requesting permission
to send notifications.
We shipped the updated
and un-prefixed Fullscreen API
in Safari 16.4 for macOS and iPadOS.
We also added preliminary support
for the Screen Orientation API,
including the type and angle properties
and the onChange event handler.
For more information,
check out "WebKit Features in Safari 16.4"
on webkit.org.
Web apps on Mac
work out of the box for all websites.
You can use the web app manifest
to customize the behavior
for when your website
is added to the Dock.
You can implement features
that are tailored for web apps,
such as Web Push and badging.
For more information on developing
and debugging your website in Safari,
check out "Rediscover Safari
developer features"
and "What's new in Web Inspector"
from WWDC23.
Thank you for watching.
Enjoy WWDC23.
♪ ♪