♪ ♪
Luca: Hi! My name is Luca and
I’m an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Today we are going to discuss
how you can bring widgets to life
with some new, exciting capabilities.
Widgets are a beloved part
of the iOS and macOS experience
and now, with interactivity
and animations,
they are even more powerful.
Interactivity allows your user to directly
manipulate the data in your widget,
creating powerful interaction to execute
the most important actions in your app.
And animations bring widgets to life
by helping users get a sense
of how the content has changed
and what’s the result of their actions.
I’m super excited about all of these new
capabilities, so let’s get started.
First, we are going to cover animations
and how easy it is
to make your widget look great.
After that, I’m going to walk you through
how to add interactivity to your widgets.
Let’s start with animations.
Throughout this talk,
we are going to use an app
that my friend Nils
has been working on
to keep track of the caffeine intake
during the day.
It already has a widget that shows
the total amount of caffeine
and the last drink I had today.
If I recompile my widget
with the latest SDK,
every time the content
of the widget changes,
the system is going
to animate the transition
between the entries
with a default animation.
We are going to add some tweaks here
to make it look even better,
but before we jump into Xcode,
let me briefly talk
about how animations work with widgets.
In a regular SwiftUI app,
you use state
to drive changes to your view.
And animations are driven
by state mutations
using modifiers like withAnimation.
But Widgets work slightly differently.
Widget don't have state.
Instead, they create a timeline
made of entries,
which correspond to different views
rendered at specific times.
SwiftUI determines what is the same
and what is different
between the entries,
and animates the parts that have changed.
By default, widgets
get an implicit spring animation
and various implicit content transitions,
but you can use
all the transition, animation,
and content transition APIs
that SwiftUI provides out of the box
to customize how your widget animates.
I won’t go into more details about how all
the animation primitives of SwiftUI work.
For that, there is a fantastic talk
called “Explore SwiftUI Animation.”
Okay, time to open up Xcode
and show you how, with a few tweaks,
your widget can be as fancy as latte art
on your morning cappuccino
and how the new Xcode Preview API
can help you iterate quickly
on these animations.
Here we have all the views
that comprised my widget.
The main view has a VStack with two views,
the first showing the total amount
of caffeine
and the second,
the last drink I had today, if present.
Note how I am using the
containerBackground modifier here
to define the background for my widget.
This allows it to show up in all the new
supported locations on the Mac and iPad.
Normally, to be able to see
your widget animating,
you would need to have a bunch of entries
and wait for their moment
to appear on screen,
but that can be tedious
and would slow you down,
but luckily we have a great solution
with the new Preview API
we are introducing this year.
I can define a new preview
for a widget in systemSmall
and pass the type defining my widget.
and now I can specify
how to render a timeline
with some entries I've defined earlier.
When I do that in the canvas,
I can now see a preview of my timeline
and how every entry would look like.
But check this out!
When I click through the preview,
I can see how my widget will animate
when transitioning between entries.
This is pretty cool!
And this is only scratching the surface
of what this new Preview API
is capable of.
Make sure to check out the session
"Build programmatic UI
with Xcode Previews"
to learn more about this new powerful API.
Okay, time to start
tweaking these animations.
The first thing I want to do is start
with the text for the caffeine amount.
Right now it is just cross-fading
with the next value,
but I really want to add some drama
to the value going up.
In this case, the view is not changing,
but only the text content is,
and to animated that,
we can use a content transition.
And I'm going to choose add a numeric text
with the value of my caffeine.
This is a content transition that is made
specifically for important numeric value
that we want to give prominence
when they change.
I think its looking great!
Now, I want to focus on the view
showing the last drink.
I want to add a transition to emphasize
that a new drink is coming in.
The first thing I want to do
is to use the ID modifier
to associate the identity of this view
with specific log it is rendering.
This will inform SwiftUI
that whenever this log changes,
this is a new view and we need
to transition to the new one.
And now I can specify a transition.
I think a push will be good.
From which edge?
I think from bottom is a good choice.
Okay, you already know what to do now.
Back to the preview canvas.
And yeah, I like this transition
from the bottom.
One last tweak.
I get a little jittery
when I drink that much coffee,
and I want that reflected with
the animation curve for this transition.
What's great is that,
like in a regular SwiftUI app,
I can use the animation modifier
and choose a smooth spring
with a shorter duration
and bind that animation to my log value.
And now, the animation
would match my caffeination.
I feel pretty good about
what we have now,
so let's switch our attention
to interactivity.
With interactivity, you can
execute actions right from the widget!
Before we jump into Xcode,
I want to take a moment
to discuss the architecture
of how widgets work.
This will allow you to create a better
mental model for how interactivity works.
When you create a widget,
you define a widget extension,
which is discovered by the system
and run as an independent process.
Widgets define a timeline provider
that returns a series of entries,
which are effectively the widget’s model.
If a widget is visible,
the system launches
the widget extension process
and asks its timeline provider
for entries.
These entries are fed back
into the view builder
that is part of your widget configuration
and used to generate a series of views
based on these entries.
After that, the system generates
a representation of these views
and archives it on disk.
When its time to display a specific entry,
the system decodes and renders
the archived representation of your widget
in its process.
Let me pause for a second
and reiterate this last point.
Your view code only runs during archiving.
A separate representation of that view
is rendered by the system process.
But if your data is not static,
you might want to update those entries.
You can do that by calling the
reloadTimelines function in your app
whenever you are updating data
that is displayed by your widget.
This will repeat the process
I've just described,
regenerate new entries, and archive
new copies of the views on disk.
There are three important takeaways
with this architecture.
First, when your widget is visible,
your code is not running.
You drive changes to the widget content
by updating its timeline entries,
and this is also true
of interactive widgets.
Typically, updates to widgets are done
on a best effort basis,
but importantly, reloads
initiated from an interaction
are always guaranteed to occur.
With this out of the way,
let’s look at how to add interactivity.
What’s great is that you can use controls
that you are already familiar with,
like Button and Toggle,
to make part of your widget interactive.
But remember, since widgets
are rendered in a different process,
SwiftUI won’t execute your closure,
nor mutate your bindings,
in your process space.
So we need a way to represent actions
that can be executed
by the widget extension
and be invoked by the system.
Thankfully, there is already
a solution to this problem: App Intents.
You might have used app intents to expose
actions for your app to Shortcuts or Siri.
And now, the same intents can be used
to represent the actions in your widget.
At its very core, AppIntent is a protocol
that allows you to define, in code,
actions that can be executed
by the system.
For example, here,
I’m defining an app intent
to toggle a todo item in a todo app.
An intent defines a number
of parameters as inputs
and an async function called perform,
where you will have the business logic
to run your intent.
App Intents are very powerful, and there
is a lot more to know about them,
so be sure to checkout
the “Dive into App Intents”
and "Explore enhancements
to App Intents” sessions
from WWDC22 and 23.
And to support the ability
to execute App Intent right from the UI,
when you import both SwiftUI
and AppIntents,
There is a new family of initializers
on Button and Toggle
that accept an AppIntent as an argument
and will execute that intent
when these controls are interacted with.
Note that only Button and Toggle
using AppIntent
are supported in interactive widgets.
Other controls won’t work.
And of course,
those initializers work in apps as well,
which is cool because
you can share the app intent logic
between your widget and your app.
Let’s go back to Xcode
and our coffee tracker app
and add some interactivity.
Currently, the user can log a new drink
only by opening the app,
but where interactive widget shines
is as accelerator to surface
the most important actions in your app,
and for my app, this is definitely
the logging of a new drink.
So lets add that to a file
I've already created.
The first thing I want to do
is to define a type
that conforms to AppIntent
to log a new drink.
We'll give it a human-readable title
that can be used by the system,
and then implement the perform
requirements by logging an espresso
to our store and returning
an empty intent result.
Something that
I want to call your attention to
is that perform is an async function
and you should take full advantage of it
if you are doing any asynchronous work,
such as writing to a database
exactly like I'm doing here when
I'm awaiting the log writing operation.
As soon as your perform returns,
the system will immediately
initiate a reload of your widget timeline,
giving you the opportunity
to update the content of your widget.
So again, make sure to have persisted
all the information necessary
to reload your updated widget
before returning from perform.
I've hard coded the drink
to be an espresso,
but, of course, we want to be able
to pass the specific drink to log.
To do that we can add a stored property
with the @Parameter property wrapper
and an initializer
that populates the all parameters.
It is important
that I use this property wrapper
because only the stored properties
that are annotated with it
are going to be persisted
and will be available
when the intent is performed
in your widget extension.
Before we add the button
to invoke this intent,
I want to highlight an important ecosystem
benefit of using App Intents here.
This app intent I've just defined is going
to be available in Shortcut and Siri,
so the investment in defining it here
will pay dividend to your user experience
beyond widgets.
And now we are ready to add
the button to the widget.
Let's create
a new view holding our buttons.
In this view
I'm using this button initializer
that take an app intent,
so we can pass the one we just defined.
And let's add this view to the rest
of the widget with some spacers.
Now we have everything in place,
let's see how this is working out
on the widget by building and running.
A little tip here: you can
actually have directly build the target
for the widget extension
and Xcode will install the widget
right on the home screen for you.
My widget now has the button
I've just defined.
If I tap on it,
I can log this last cup of espresso.
But there is also one additional change
I want to make
so that my widget provides
the best user experience possible.
When your app intent finishes to perform,
it will cause a widget
to reload its timeline.
This can introduce
a small latency from the action,
to the resulting change in the UI.
But this latency can become more
pronounced with iPhone widget on Mac
so we are providing
a solution out of the box for it.
For example, in my widget,
the value showing
the total amount of caffeine won't update
until an updated entry arrived.
We can annotate this view
with the invalidatableContent modifier.
I've added this widget
from my iPhone to my Mac.
Let's tap on the button.
The view showing the caffeine amount
shows a system effect
to indicate that its value is invalidated
until an update comes in.
We just saw Button in action and how
with the invalidatableContent modifier,
you can help users
improve the perception of latency.
Use this modifier judiciously.
You don't need to annotate
every single view that might change.
You should use this modifier
with views that are meaningful
to set the right expectation
with your users.
Toggle goes one step further
and will optimistically update its
presentation when interacted with
without having to wait for a roundtrip
to the widget extension and back.
This is done automatically,
on your behalf, at archive time,
by pre-rendering the toggle style
in both configurations.
Make sure,
if you define your own toggle style,
to check the configuration isOn
property from the style
and use that to switch the appearance.
This concludes our overview
for interactivity and animations.
With animations and interactivity,
you have the opportunity
to infuse new life into your widgets
and with widgets now
in all these new locations,
you can bring these little,
delightful interactions
to your users wherever they are.
So make sure to fine tune
the animations for your widgets
with the help of the new Xcode
Preview APIs
and look out
for the most important actions in your app
and surface them in your widget,
giving your user powerful interactions
whenever and wherever they need them.
Thanks you!
♪ ♪