♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi, my name's Roy,
and I'm an engineer
on the Performance team.
Today, we'll learn
how you can optimize
your app for spatial computing.
We'll first look at
the unique aspects
of this new platform
for performance and power.
We'll then go over building
a performance plan,
starting with
profiling your app.
And finally, we'll take a tour
of the best ways
to optimize performance issues
for this platform.
So what makes
spatial computing different
for power and performance?
For one,
the content on the display
is always being updated,
regardless of app updates.
Whenever people move
their body, hands, or eyes,
content needs to be updated.
This means the system
is always rendering
every frame at all times.
The platform is also always
running spatial algorithms
to create visuals and
interactions across every app,
and can run multiple apps
at the same time.
People will use your app
with other apps.
To handle multitasking
and the additional system work,
optimize your own app's resource
usage as much as you can.
To deliver a great
user experience,
performance in your app
is essential.
People want apps to be
immediately responsive to input
and to provide
smooth visual updates
for a sense of immersion
and comfort.
Let's talk about how to
profile and analyze your app
for performance issues.
You may already be familiar
with performance metrics
from other Apple platforms.
On any platform, people want
apps that launch quickly,
avoid disk wear,
and don't use too much battery.
They also want apps
that avoid terminations
from inefficient memory use.
With spatial computing,
some of these metrics
take on new meaning.
Take power.
Users want apps
optimized for power,
not for battery life,
but because of thermal pressure.
To sustain great performance,
apps need to be optimized
for system power use,
to reduce the likelihood of
encountering thermal pressure.
Hangs are another example.
They occur when an app's
main thread is stalled
on doing work
for a period of time.
But on this platform,
even small, momentary stalls
are disruptive
to responsiveness.
Now consider rendering.
On other platforms,
you may be optimizing
for render performance
primarily to provide
smooth UI and 3D animations.
But here,
render performance is essential
for static content as well, since
the system is always rendering.
All Apple platforms provide
tools to profile these metrics.
Today, we'll cover finding
performance issues
specifically for
spatial computing apps.
But to learn more about
optimizing for these metrics
on any Apple platform, check out
the "Ultimate Application
Performance Survival Guide"
session.
To optimize your app,
profile during development
using tools like Instruments
and Xcode Gauges.
Once your app is released,
gather more data from the field
to help you further optimize
your app.
Let's talk more about
profiling during development.
RealityKit Trace is a brand-new
template in Instruments
to help profile any
spatial computing app
for performance and power.
It is an incredible tool
that can help identify
when your app has
poor rendering performance
or when it is causing
high system power use.
There are many more instrument
templates you can use as well.
To learn more and explore
this new template in action,
watch the session
"Meet RealityKit Trace."
Your app's performance
and power depends on
how someone interacts with it.
The simulator doesn't perform
the same work as a real device,
so its performance data
might not be accurate.
Profile in the device.
Profile using various
interactions in your app
when playing audio or video,
or when using technologies
like FaceTime and Personas.
Make sure to check for good
performance and low system power
over minutes of use.
Lastly, try profiling while
other apps are also running
and using resources.
If you are bringing over
compatible iPad and iPhone apps,
make sure to profile them
on device
to identify further
optimizations needed.
After development,
people may run your app
in a wide variety of conditions.
Data from the field
is a great way to find issues
that people are actually
running into.
When your app is in beta
or publicly released,
use MetricKit to get
diagnostic reports from users.
Xcode Organizer provides
aggregated performance data
from consenting users' devices,
including energy diagnostics
to help find any power issues.
All of this data you collect
helps you find bottlenecks
and prioritize
performance work for your app.
Now, let's talk about optimizing
your spatial computing app.
Performance issues can arise
from many areas.
Today, we'll cover strategies
for optimizing
several core areas:
rendering, user input, ARKit,
audio and video playback,
SharePlay,
and app terminations
from system pressure.
Great rendering performance
is one of the top priorities
for a great user experience.
Let's dive in.
In this platform, the rendering
pipeline starts with your app,
which is responsible for
updating your app's content.
Like all Apple platforms,
your app's interface is updated
on the main thread and
must provide updates promptly.
Since your app is rendered in
a 3D space alongside other apps,
its updates get sent
to the system render server.
The render server
is continuously running
to process updates from apps,
users' inputs,
and from their space
and surroundings.
It renders a new frame
with all these updates
and sends it
to the compositor.
The compositor
is always rendering.
It supplies new frames
to the display
at a rate matching
the display's refresh rate.
This helps provide
a comfortable experience.
This rate is usually 90 frames
a second, but can be higher.
While the compositor updates
the display consistently,
a great user experience
still needs fast visual updates
from your app.
If your app has content
or updates that take
too long to render,
the render server can miss
its rendering deadline
for optimal rendering latency.
This means the app visuals
could have made it
to the compositor
on frame Y,
but made it on
frame Y+1 instead.
This delays the visual updates
the people see on display
and makes your app
feel less responsive.
Especially severe rendering
stalls can even cause
your app to be terminated.
Whether your app
is built on SwiftUI, UIKit,
RealityKit, or Metal,
you want to optimize its content
and updates
to reduce frame drops
and work done
in the render server.
Let's start with optimizing
SwiftUI and UIKit usage.
On this platform,
the system does render work
for static UI content,
even with no app updates.
This rendering work can increase
from overdraw.
Overdraw occurs when
you have translucent content
in front of other
virtual content.
The GPU has to do work
to render both content,
but if that translucent content
was fully opaque,
the GPU wouldn't need to render
any UI behind it.
If you have any overlapping
UI views with Z offsets,
avoid adding translucency
to them.
Also, the more pixels
on the display
that your app's UI takes up,
the more work is done
to render the window.
Consider reducing
their default sizes.
UI redraws in the render server
are usually triggered
by app updates,
but on this platform,
they are also triggered
by dynamic content scaling
of core animation layers.
With this behavior,
the resolution of text,
or vector-based UI content
changes based on
where the user is looking
to allow for sharper visuals.
This can also lead to more
frequent redrawing of UI content
at potentially higher scales,
even with no app updates.
SwiftUI and UIKit
enable this behavior by default,
but apps doing
custom Core Animation
or Core Graphics rendering
can opt in to this behavior.
To learn more about its visual
benefits and trade-offs,
watch the session
"Explore rendering
for spatial computing."
The cost of these redraws
is heavily impacted
by offscreen render passes.
This can be caused
by visual effects
like shadows, blur, and masking.
Reduce these effects
to make your app
easier for the system to render.
To minimize re-draws in your app,
avoid unnecessary view updates
whenever possible.
For example, with SwiftUI,
use @Observable.
@Observable provides
more granular change tracking
and reduces unneeded
layout updates.
Next, let's talk about
optimizing 3D rendering
with RealityKit.
SwiftUI has added
RealityView this year
for spatial computing.
It can natively display
RealityKit 3D scenes
within a SwiftUI hierarchy.
Your app should be
a good citizen on the platform
by optimizing your 3D scenes
for all of these
RealityKit features.
In these 3D scenes,
the complexity
of the assets they contain
can greatly increase the amount
of render server work
done each frame.
So let's start
by optimizing these assets.
Reality Composer Pro
helps you create
RealityKit scenes from assets.
From mesh rendering,
particles, animations,
physics, and audio work,
this tool provides statistics
about the entire scene
that can help you
understand
its performance impact.
When examining these statistics,
lower numbers usually mean
less work, which can improve
render performance.
Watch the session
"Create 3D models for Quick Look
spatial experiences"
to learn more around
best practices
for visuals and power use
of 3D assets.
Mesh rendering in particular
is a core part of 3D rendering.
Complex meshes and materials
can quickly become
performance bottlenecks.
Optimize the geometry
of your mesh assets.
Reduce the amount
of separate mesh parts
by combining parts
that share a material.
Mesh geometries with
high triangle and vertex counts
can also be costly.
Use assets with smaller counts
as needed.
Minimize the impact of overdraw
with your 3D meshes.
To do this,
use transparency sparingly
just like with UI content.
The “Physically Based” material
in Reality Composer Pro
has environment lighting,
is well optimized,
and works best for meshes
with minimal transparency.
But for translucent
or very large content,
consider using a Custom
material with an unlit surface,
Use baked lighting textures
or other cheaper visuals.
This helps avoid
potential bottlenecks
with more expensive
lighting calculations.
For further guidance on
building and using materials
in RealityKit,
watch these two sessions.
Having optimized content
for runtime rendering
is a great start.
But there's even more
you can do
to optimize your app
with RealityKit.
When your app updates
its RealityKit content,
updates get sent
to the render server,
which applies and renders them.
But too many updates
in a short period of time
can become a bottleneck
for the render server.
For example, your app may be
rapidly creating and destroying
RealityKit entities.
It may have too many
complex animations,
be updating too many
SwiftUI views,
or it may be loading
many assets in a single frame.
Create entities in advance,
and hide or show them as needed.
You could remove and add them
to the scene hierarchy,
or use the isEnabled flag.
Minimize the amount of entities
that are updated
by flattening your mesh
entity hierarchies.
For code-based animations,
consider lower update rates
or reducing the number of
entities the animations update.
And when updating
RealityKit entities,
avoid triggering excessive
SwiftUI redrawing accidentally.
When using attachments,
make sure to optimize
their rendering
in the same way
you optimize
for all SwiftUI content.
Loading complex assets
can also trigger
expensive render updates.
Complex assets
can also contribute
to high app launch
and content loading times.
Use asynchronous
loading APIs at runtime
to avoid blocking
the main thread
and load assets well before
they are needed.
Entities that use
the same assets
can also share that asset
and only load it once.
Use exported files
from Reality Composer Pro
as these files are optimized
for loading times
and memory costs.
You also get texture
compression for free.
Reducing asset sizes
usually speeds up loading,
but remember that texture
compression already happens
with Reality Composer Pro files,
so you may not
need to do it yourself.
Finally, let's talk about
immersive experiences
with RealityKit.
When your app requests to move
to a dedicated full space,
it becomes the only
foreground experience running.
When using a portal or moving
to a fully immersive experience,
the system also hides
part or all of the person's
surroundings.
Your app can create
an environment
with RealityKit content
to fill their space.
Your fully immersive content
needs to be rendered
to a lot more pixels
on the display
than scenes in a shared space
or a full space.
This means that more work
can be done on the GPU
to render that content.
Optimize this type of content
for GPU power use.
Start with a “Custom” material
with an unlit surface
in Reality Composer Pro
for optimal power use.
Consider adding
baked lighting textures
or using time-based animations
to get a feel
of dynamic lighting instead.
Profile your material for system
power and render performance.
You can also create
fully immersive experiences
with Metal.
For those of you building
3D engines or experiences
using Metal, let's talk about
some things to optimize.
You can use Metal with the
CompositorServices framework
to bypass the render server
and send a rendered surface
directly to the compositor.
Watch the session "Discover
Metal for immersive apps"
to learn how
to do this properly.
When using CompositorServices,
pace your Metal frame
submissions so the compositor
receives a new frame
on each of its updates.
Make sure to query
a new foviation map
and post prediction each frame.
And query this input data
at the last moment
before you start using it
to encode GPU work.
Doing all three of these things
helps ensure
responsive virtual content
relative to user motion
and input.
If the app takes too long
to submit a new frame,
the system terminates it.
Avoid any long frame stalls.
Make sure to profile
GPU performance
using the Metal System Trace
Instruments template
while running your app.
Long-running fragment
and vertex shader executions
from your Metal app
or from custom materials
with Reality Composer Pro
can impact
system rendering times heavily.
To reduce fragment
and vertex times,
start by reducing
ALU instructions
and texture accesses by shaders.
For Metal, use compute shaders
instead wherever possible.
Review these talks
to learn more
about optimizing
your GPU performance.
Remember, optimizing your app
for UI and 3D rendering
performance benefits
the overall user experience.
Let's now move on
to input performance.
People can use their eyes,
hands, voice,
and hardware inputs
on this platform.
App updates to inputs are
processed on the main thread.
If these take too long,
it makes your app
feel slow and unresponsive.
Input updates on the main
thread need to complete
within certain deadlines based
on the display refresh rate.
Hardware for this platform
usually has a refresh rate
of 90 hertz or higher.
For 90 hertz refresh
rates, keep input updates
below eight milliseconds
for optimal latency.
When interacting
with spatial content,
the system does hit testing
work to check
which UI or 3D objects the user
is trying to interact with.
For RealityKit content,
you will add physics colliders
to interact with them.
When adding these colliders,
use static colliders
over dynamic colliders
whenever possible,
as static ones are cheaper.
To reduce redundant hit
testing work in your app,
minimize overlapping
any interactive content.
Now, let's move on to ARKit.
On this platform,
ARKit algorithms
are always running to create
visuals and interactions
across every app.
Your app can impact system
power and visual smoothness
based on how it uses ARKit data
and anchors virtual content.
For example, your app
can use ARKit or RealityKit
to place an anchor content
in the user's surroundings,
head, or hands.
Every anchor adds additional
work for the system.
When anchoring content,
consider whether the anchors
need to be tracked
continuously in a user's space.
When using AnchorComponent
in RealityKit,
use the “once” tracking mode to
avoid continuous tracking costs.
Minimize the total amount
of persistent
and transient anchors
from your app.
For persistent anchors
especially,
every app can add them,
so try not to add too many
from your own app.
There's even more
optimizations you can do
while using ARKit data.
If you apply ARKit data
that is too old to app content,
app visuals can look
out of sync with input.
Query ARKit data right before
it needs to be used
and apply it
to updates promptly.
Post predictions
are expensive to compute.
Generally, only custom
Metal rendering engines
need this data.
If you just want to place
app content in the scene,
RealityKit is
a great choice instead.
Generating collision data
for scene understanding meshes
is also expensive.
If you do use this data,
turn it off
when your app doesn't
need it anymore.
Now, let's talk about optimizing
audio and video playback
for spatial computing.
Spatial audio is used by default
on this platform.
The system processes
information in real time
about the user's position,
their surroundings,
and audio sources
to output audio.
If your app causes too much
spatial audio work,
it can cause problems
with system power use
or lead to delays
in audio output.
If you see these issues,
there are three main things
to look at
for reducing spatial audio work:
concurrently playing
audio sources,
the number of moving
and the size of the soundstage.
All of these are variables
that can increase
the computational work.
Now, let's consider video.
In a shared space, people can
play multiple videos at once.
For each video,
the system needs to decode it
and render it
in the render server.
Each new rendered video frame
needs to make it to the display
at consistent intervals
for a great video
watching experience.
To give the render server
as much power and time
to meet its rendering deadlines,
your app should minimize
updates to UI or 3D content
during video playback.
The video frame rate
also impacts the work done.
Consider using 24 or 30 hertz
videos
for optimal performance
and power.
Finally, reduce the number
of concurrent videos
that need to be played
and rendered on the device
from your app at any given time.
When choosing between
video presentation methods,
consider how you would
like to optimize
for different features
and performance.
Watch the session
"Create a great spatial playback
experience" to learn more.
Now, let's talk about SharePlay.
This platform opens up
a whole new set of experiences
to collaborate
and connect with people.
To create a truly great
SharePlay group experience,
you'll want to ensure your app
can sustain great performance
over long periods of time.
And great spatial computing
performance with SharePlay
starts with the basics.
Profile and optimize your app
for local performance first.
Then examine your app's
performance during SharePlay
to avoid expensive
render updates
being synced across devices.
Profile your app for power
to ensure system power needs
doesn't create
thermal pressure,
which can prevent your app
from sustaining
its great performance.
To help with this,
carefully consider
what work and
features in your app
are essential for your app's
SharePlay experience,
and turn off anything
it doesn't need.
Lastly,
let's look at app terminations
from thermal or memory pressure.
People may use this device
in a warm place.
Like all Apple platforms,
the system manages
computational resources
available under thermal pressure
in order to keep the device cool
and comfortable when in use.
Having lower
computational resources
can impact
your app's performance.
The system may even
terminate your app
due to critical
thermal pressure,
or because render deadlines
were no longer being met.
When under thermal pressure,
do less work in your app
to maintain good performance
and to keep thermal pressure
from increasing further.
Do this by subscribing to the
thermalStateDidChange
Notification.
When the pressure gets higher,
adapt your app's content
and updates in response to it.
To see how your app performs
under a thermal pressure,
use thermal inducers
in Xcode to simulate
higher thermal states
for your device.
To learn even more
about thermal pressure,
check out the session
"Designing for Adverse Network
and Temperature Conditions."
Next, let's talk about
memory pressure.
Devices have a limited
amount of memory
that is shared between
the system and all apps running.
When the device gets
close to this limit,
the system begins
to terminate apps,
starting with apps that are
not being actively used.
A single app using
too much memory
can also get terminated,
even if it is being used.
You don't want this
to happen for your app.
You can avoid this by reducing
your app's memory usage
as much as possible.
On this platform,
apps are more likely
to have large amounts
of memory allocated
for UI and 3D rendering,
and audio and video playback.
If your app has UI content,
reduce rendering
memory allocations by minimizing
offscreen render passes,
the total amount of windows,
and media content.
For 3D memory with RealityKit,
the resolution
of your textures and geometry
sizers for meshes and particles
can contribute
significantly to memory use.
Reduce them wherever you can.
When playing audio and video,
evaluate the total memory load
from all audio
and video files in your app.
When changing resolutions,
bitrates, file formats,
and durations,
consider the trade-offs
for the user experience
and performance
against any memory savings.
Review these talks to learn
more tips for reducing
your memory footprint
across all Apple platforms.
Remember,
performance is essential
for a great user experience
on this platform.
To get started,
profile your apps
actively during development
to find performance
and power issues.
Build a performance plan
around important metrics
for spatial computing.
And optimize your app
for rendering, power,
and all of the other areas
we covered today.
And finally,
collect performance field data
with tools like MetricKit
and Xcode Organizer.
I can't wait to see all
the great apps and experiences
you come up with
on this platform.
Thanks for watching.
♪