[upbeat music]
Rob: Hi.
I'm Rob Simutis from the Camera
software team, with Sebastian Medina
from the Photos team,
and welcome to our session,
"Create a more
responsive camera experience."
We'll be presenting a slew of
new powerful APIs in the AVFoundation
capture classes,
and in the PhotoKit framework.
First, we'll talk about
deferred photo processing.
Then, I'll show how
you can really "capture the moment"
with zero shutter lag.
Third, I'll cover our new
Responsive Capture APIs.
And finally, I'll go over a different way
to be responsive
with updated video effects.
Starting with iOS 13,
you could use AVCapturePhotoSetting's
photo Quality Prioritization enum
value to change the responsiveness,
or how quickly you could capture
and get a processed photo back,
and then be able take the next photo.
Your app could choose
among different enum values
to achieve the right responsiveness,
but it impacted image quality.
Or if you always wanted
to use the quality value,
you could impact shot-to-shot time.
In iOS 17,
you can still use this API,
but we're bringing you new,
complementary APIs
so you can improve the chances
of getting the shot you wanted
while also getting
higher-quality photos.
I'm going to walk you through this app
my team built for our session.
By flipping each toggle switch to "on,"
we can enable
the new features this year,
and we'll build on the concepts
one by one to make a more
responsive photography experience.
So let's get moving,
starting with deferred photo processing.
Today, to get the highest quality
photos out of the AVCapturePhotoOutput,
you use a photo quality
prioritization enum value of "quality"
on the settings
when you capture a photo.
For our "balanced"
and "quality" values,
this typically involves some type of
multiple-frame fusion and noise reduction.
On iPhone 11 Pro and newer models,
one of our most advanced
techniques is called "Deep Fusion."
This gives amazing, crisp detail
in high resolution photos.
In this Deep Fusion shot,
the parrot's feathers are super-sharp,
and really stand out.
But it comes at a cost.
This processing must complete before
the next capture request will start,
and it may take some time to finish.
Let's look at a real-life example.
I'm putting together
a presentation about how
the camera software team gets
to the office to get its work done.
Here's my colleague Devin using the latest
bike technology to get around Apple Park.
As I tap,
I'm waiting for the shutter button
to finish spinning from
one shot before I can take the next one.
The end results are
great Deep Fusion photos.
Just check out that beard detail!
But while I was tapping,
the processing runs synchronously,
and the shot to shot
time feels a bit sluggish.
So I might have gotten a good
photo with crisp detail,
but maybe not exactly
the shot I was looking for.
Let's check out a diagram of events.
you call AVCapturePhotoOutput's
capturePhoto method with your settings
and your delegate receives callbacks
at various points in the process...
such as willBeginCapture
for resolvedSettings.
The camera software stack grabs
the frames from the sensor,
and uses our processing techniques
to fuse them into a Deep Fusion image...
Then it sends the photo back to you via
the didFinishProcessingPhoto
delegate callback.
This processing must complete
before the next capture happens,
and that might take some time.
You can even call capturePhoto before
the didFinishProcessingPhoto
callback fires,
but it won't start until the previous
photo's processing is complete.
With deferred photo processing,
this timeline shrinks.
You request a photo, and,
when suitable,
the camera pipeline will deliver
a lightly-processed "proxy" photo via
a new didFinishCapturingDeferredPhotoProxy
delegate callback.
You store this proxy photo
into the library as a placeholder.
And the next photo
can be immediately captured.
The system will run the processing
later to get the final photo
once the camera session
has been dismissed.
So now if I turn on deferred
photo processing in my app's settings,
the capture session will
reconfigure itself to deliver
me proxy photos at the time
of capture when appropriate.
And I can get the same sharp,
highly-detailed photos as before,
but I can take more of them while
I'm in the moment by deferring
the final processing to a later time.
Nice wheelie.
Those bikes are solid.
There we go. That's a great photo
for my presentation, beard and all.
So let's look at all
the parts that interact
to give you a deferred-processed photo.
As a brief refresher course
from earlier WW presentations,
when configuring an AVCaptureSession
to capture photos,
you add an AVCaptureDeviceInput
with an AVCaptureDevice
that is, the camera, to the session.
Then, you add
an AVCapturePhotoOutput
to your session,
and you select a particular
format or session preset,
typically the "Photo" session preset
when your app calls capturePhoto
on the photoOutput.
If it's a type of photo that is better
suited to deferred photo processing,
we'll call you back with
didFinishCapturing Deferred Photo Proxy.
From there, you send
the proxy data to the photo library.
So what you've got now
in your library is a proxy photo,
but you'll eventually want
to use or share the final image.
Final photo processing happens
either on-demand when you request
the image data back from the library,
or in the background when the system
determines that conditions are good
to do so, such as the device being idle.
And now I'll let my colleague Sebastian
show you how to code this up.
Over to you, Sebastian.
Sebastian: Thanks, Rob.
Hi, my name's Sebastian Medina
and I'm an engineer on the Photos team.
Today I'll go over
taking a recently captured image
through PhotoKit
to trigger deferred processing.
Then I’ll be requesting that same
image to show what’s new in receiving
images from a PHImageManager request.
Although, before I get into
processing the asset through PhotoKit,
I need to make sure the new Camera API
for deferred processing is set up.
This will allow my app
to accept deferred photo proxy images,
which we can send through PhotoKit.
Now, I’ll go ahead and write
the code to take advantage of this.
Here, I've set up the AVCapturePhotoOutput
and AVCaptureSession objects.
Now, I can begin configuring our session.
In this case, I want the session to have
a preset of type photo
so we can take advantage
of deferred processing.
Now I’ll grab the capture device
to then setup the device input.
Then, if possible,
I'll add the device input.
Next, I’ll want to check
if photoOutput can be added.
And if so, add it.
Now for the new stuff.
I’ll check if the new
autoDeferredPhotoDeliverySupported value
is true to make sure I can send captured
photos through deferred processing.
If this passes,
then I can go ahead and opt into
the new deferred photo delivery
with the property
autoDeferredPhotoDeliveryEnabled.
This deferred photo delivery check
and enablement are all you would need
to add to your Camera code
to enable deferred photos.
Lastly, I'll commit
our session configuration.
So now when a call is made
to the capturePhoto method,
the delegate callback we receive will hold
a deferred proxy object.
Let's check out an example
of one of these callbacks.
In this photo capture callback
I'm receiving the AVCapturePhotoOutput
and AVCaptureDeferredPhotoProxy
objects from Camera,
which are related
to an image I recently captured.
First, it's good practice to make sure
we're receiving
suitable photo output values,
so I'll check the value
of error parameter.
Now, we'll start getting into
saving our image
to the photolibrary using PhotoKit.
I'll be performing changes
on the shared PHPhotoLibrary.
Although, just note, it's only required
to have write-access to a photo library.
Then I'll capture the photo data from the
AVCaptureDeferredPhotoProxy object.
Since I'll be performing changes
to the photo library,
I'll need to set up the related
performChanges instance method.
Like with saving any asset,
I'll use a PHAssetCreationRequest.
Then I'll call the 'addResource' method
on a request.
For the parameters, I'll to use the new
PHAssetResourceType '.photoProxy'.
This is what tells PhotoKit to trigger
deferred processing on the image.
Then I can add the previously captured
proxy image data.
And in this case I won't be using
any options.
Here, it's important to know that using
this new resource type on image data
that doesn't require deferred processing
will result in an error.
And speaking of errors,
I'll go ahead and check for them
within the completion handler.
And it's as easy as that.
Go ahead and handle the success
and error within the completion handler
as your application sees fit.
Now, say I want to retrieve our Asset.
I can achieve that through
a PHImageManager request,
so I'll go through the code
to do just that.
For parameters I have
a PHAsset object for the image
I just sent through PhotoKit,
the target size of the image
to be returned, and the content mode.
I'll grab a default PHImageManager object.
then, I can call the request image asset
for the requestImageForAsset method
using our imageManager object.
For the parameters,
I'll use the asset I previously fetched,
the target size, content mode,
and in this case,
I will not be using any options.
Now I can handle the callbacks
through the resultHandler
where the resultImage is a UIImage and
info is a dictionary related to the image.
Today, the first callback will hold
a lower resolution image
with the info dicitionary key
PHImageResultIsDegradedKey
while the final image callback will not.
So, I can make a check for those here.
The addition of creating processed images
through PhotoKit
gives a good opportunity
to bring up our new API which will allow
developers to receive a secondary image
from the requestImageForAsset method.
Since it may take longer
for an image going through
deferred processing to finalize,
this new secondary image
can be shown in the meantime.
To receive this new image,
you would use the new
allowSecondaryDegradedImage
in PHImageRequestOptions.
This new image will be nestled
between the current two callbacks
from the requestImageForAsset method.
And the information dictionary
related to the image
will have an entry for
PHImageResultIsDegradedKey,
which is used today
in the first image callback.
To better illustrate what’s going on,
today, the requestImageForAsset method
provides two images.
The first is a low-quality image
suitable for displaying temporarily
while it prepares
the final high-quality image.
With this new option,
between the current two,
you will be provided a new,
higher resolution image
to display while
the final is being processed.
Displaying this new image will give your
user a more pleasant visual experience
while waiting for the final image
to finish processing.
Now, let's write the code
to take advantage of this.
Although, this time, I'll be creating
a PHImageRequestOptions object.
I will then set the new
allowSecondaryDegradedImage option
to be true.
This way the request knows to send back
the new secondary image callback.
Here, I can go ahead and reuse
the requestImageForAsset method
I wrote before,
although now I'll be adding the image
request options object I just created.
Since the new secondary
image info dictionary will hold
a true value for
PHImageResultIsDegradedKey,
just like the first callback,
I'll check for that here.
And that's it for receiving
the new secondary image representation.
Remember to handle the images
within the result handler
to best support your app.
Now you know how to add images
to your photo library
with deferred processing and how to
receive a secondary higher quality image
from an image request
to display in your app
while waiting for the final image
to finish processing.
These changes will be available
starting with iOS 17, tvOS 17,
and macOS Sonoma alongside the new
deferred processing PhotoKit changes.
Now, I’ll hand it back to Rob
for more on the new tools
to create a more responsive Camera.
Rob: Awesome. Thanks, Sebastian!
Let's get into the fine details
to ensure you have a great experience
with deferred photo processing.
We'll start with the photo library.
To use deferred photo processing,
you'll need to have write permission
to the photo library
to store the proxy photo,
and read permission if your app needs
to show the final photo
or wants to modify it in any way.
But remember,
you should only request the smallest
amount of access to the library
as needed from your customers
to maintain the most privacy
and trust on their behalf.
And, we strongly recommend
that once you receive the proxy,
you get its fileDataRepresentation
into the library as quickly as possible.
When your app is backgrounded,
you have a limited amount
of time to run
before the system suspends it.
If memory pressure becomes too great,
your app may be automatically force-quit
by the system during
that window of backgrounding.
Getting the proxy into the library
as quickly as possible
ensures minimal chance
of data loss for your customers.
Next, if you normally make changes to
a photo's pixel buffer
like applying a filter,
or if you make changes to metadata
or other properties of AVCapturePhoto
using AVCapturePhoto File Data
Representation Customizer,
these won't take effect for
the finalized photo in the library
once processing is complete.
You'll need to do this later
as adjustments to the photo
using the PhotoKit APIs.
Also, your code needs
to be able to handle
both deferred proxies and non-deferred
photos in the same session.
This is because not all
photos make sense to handle
with the extra steps necessary.
For example, flash captures
taken under the "quality"
photo quality prioritization enum value
aren't processed in a way that benefits
from the shot-to-shot savings
like a Deep Fusion photo does.
You also might notice
that there's no opt-in or opt-out property
on the AVCapturePhotoSettings.
That's because deferred photo
processing is automatic.
If you opt in
and the camera pipeline will take a photo
that requires longer processing time,
it will send you a proxy back.
If it's not suitable,
it will send you the final photo,
so there's no need to
opt-in or opt-out on a per shot basis.
You just need to tell
the AVCapturePhotoOutput that you want
isAutoDeferredPhotoProcessingEnabled as
true before you start the capture session.
Finally, let's talk about user experience.
Deferred photo processing provides
our best image quality
with rapid shot-to-shot times,
but that just delays the final processing
until a later point.
If your app is one where the user
may want the image right away
for sharing or editing
and they're not as interested in the
highest quality photos we provide,
then it may make sense to avoid using
deferred photo processing.
This feature is available
starting with iPhone 11 Pro and 11 Pro Max
and newer iPhones.
And here are some great related videos
on working with AVCapturePhotoOutput
and handling library permissions.
And now, let's turn to Zero Shutter Lag
and talk about skateboarding.
For my upcoming presentation about the
camera software team's modes of transport,
we went to a skate park
to grab some footage.
I'm filming my coworker with
Action Mode on my iPhone 14 Pro
and I also want to get some high-quality
hero action shots for my slides.
But, spoiler alert,
I will not be skateboarding.
I tap the shutter button to grab a photo
of my colleague, Tomo, catching air.
When I go to
the camera roll to inspect the photo ,
this was what I got.
I tapped the shutter button
when he was at the height of his jump,
but the photo is of his landing.
It's not exactly what I wanted.
So what happened?
Shutter lag.
Shutter lag happened.
You can think of "shutter lag"
as the delay
from when you request a capture
to reading out one or more frames
from the sensor to fuse into a photo
and deliver it to you.
Here, time is going from left to right,
left being older frames,
and the right being newer frames.
Say frame five is
what's in your camera viewfinder.
Today, when
you call capturePhoto:with settings
on an AVCapturePhotoOutput,
the camera pipeline starts grabbing
frames from the sensor and
applies our processing techniques.
But the bracket of frames captured
starts after touch-down, after frame five.
What you get is a photo based
on frames six through nine, or even later.
At 30 frames per second, each frame
is in the viewfinder for 33 milliseconds.
It doesn't sound like much,
but it really doesn't take long
for the action to be over with.
That's long enough for Tomo
to have landed,
and I've missed getting that hero shot.
With Zero Shutter Lag enabled,
the camera pipeline
keeps a rolling ring buffer
of frames from the past.
Now, frame five is what you see
in the viewfinder,
you tap to capture,
and the camera pipeline does
a little bit of time travel,
grabs frames from the ring buffer,
and fuses them together
and you get the photo you wanted.
So now if I use the second toggle
in my app's settings pane
to enable Zero Shutter Lag,
as Tomo catches air,
when I tap the shutter button
I got one of the "hero" shots
I wanted for my presentation.
Let's talk about what you need
to do to get Zero Shutter Lag in your app.
Absolutely nothing!
We've enabled Zero Shutter Lag
on apps that link on or after iOS 17
for AVCaptureSessionPresets
and AVCaptureDeviceFormats
where isHighest
Photo Quality Supported is true.
But, should you find during
testing that you're
not getting the results you want,
you can set
AVCapturePhotoOutput.isZeroShutter
LagEnabled to false to opt out.
And you can verify if
the photoOutput supports zero shutter lag
for the configured preset or format
by checking if isZeroShutterLagSupported
is true once the output is connected
to your session.
Certain types of still image captures
such as flash captures,
configuring the AVCaptureDevice
for a manual exposure, bracketed captures,
and constituent photo delivery, which is
synchronized frames from multiple cameras,
don't get Zero Shutter Lag.
Because the camera pipeline
is traveling back in time
to grab frames from the ring buffer,
users could induce camera shake
into the photo if there's
a long delay between the gesture
to start the capture and when
you send photo output the photoSettings.
So you'll want to minimize any
work you do between the tap event
and the capturePhoto API call
on the photo output.
Rounding out our features for making a
more responsive photography experience,
I'll now cover
the Responsive Capture APIs.
This is a group of APIs
to allow your customers
to take overlapping captures,
prioritize shot-to-shot time
by adapting photo quality,
and also give great UI feedback
for when they can take their next photo.
First, the main API, responsive capture.
Back at the skate park,
with the two features enabled earlier,
I can capture about two photos per second.
We've slowed down
the footage to help make it clear.
At two frames per second,
you can't see as much of the action
of Tomo in the air
and this was the best photo
I ended up with.
Pretty good,
but let's see if we can do better.
I'll now turn on the 3rd and 4th switches
to enable Responsive Capture features.
I'll go over Fast Capture Prioritization
in a little bit.
But first, back to the park!
And let's try that again.
With responsive capture,
I can take more photos
in the same amount of time, increasing
the chance of catching just the right one.
And there's the "hero" shot
for the start of my presentation.
The team's really gonna love it!
You can think of a call to
the AVCapturePhotoOutput.capturePhoto
with settings method as going
through three distinct phases:
capturing frames from the sensor,
processing those frames
to the final uncompressed image,
and then encoding the photo
into a HEIC or JPEG.
After the encoding is finished,
the photo output will call your delegate's
didFinishProcessingPhoto callback,
or if you've opted in
to the deferred photo processing API,
perhaps didFinishCapturing
Deferred Photo Proxy,
if it's a suitable shot.
But once the "capture"
phase is done and the "processing" starts,
the photo output could,
in theory, start another capture.
And now, that theory is reality,
and is available to your app.
By opting in to
the main Responsive Capture API,
the photo output will overlap
these phases so that a new photo capture
request can start while another
request is in the processing phase,
giving your customers faster
and more consistent back-to-back shots.
Note that this will increase peak memory
used by the photo output,
so if your app is also using a lot of
memory it will put pressure on the system,
in which case you may
prefer or need to opt out.
Back to our timeline diagram, here,
you take two photos in rapid succession.
Your delegate will be called back for
the willBeginCaptureFor resolvedSettings,
and didFinishCaptureFor resolvedSettings
for photo A.
But then instead of getting a didFinish
Processing Photo callback for Photo A,
which is the photo is encoded
and delivered to you,
you could get the first willBeginCapture
For resolvedSettings for photo B.
There are now two in-flight
photo requests,
so you'll have to make sure
your code properly handles
callbacks for interleaved photos.
To get those overlapping,
responsive captures,
first enable Zero Shutter Lag
when it is supported.
it must be on in order
to get responsive capture support.
Then use the AVCapturePhotoOutput
isResponsiveCaptureSupported API
to ensure the photo output supports it
for the preset or format,
and then turn it on
by setting AVCapturePhotoOutput.
.isResponsiveCaptureEnabled to true.
Earlier,
we enabled "fast capture prioritization,"
so I'll go over that, briefly, now.
When it's turned on for the photo output,
it will detect when multiple captures are
being taken over a short period of time,
and in response,
will adapt the photo quality
from the highest quality setting
to more of a "balanced" quality setting
to maintain shot-to-shot time.
But, since this can impact photo quality,
it's off by default.
In Camera.app's Settings pane,
this is called
"Prioritize Faster Shooting."
We've chosen to have it on by default
for Camera.app because we think that
consistent shot-to-shot times
are more important by default,
but you might choose differently
for your app and your customers.
As you might expect by now,
you can check
the "is fast capture prioritization
supported" property on the photo output
for when it's supported,
and when it is,
you can set "is fast capture
prioritization enabled" to true
if you or your customers
want to use the feature.
Now, let's chat about
managing button states and appearance.
The photo output can give
indicators of when it's ready
to start the next capture,
or when it's processing,
and you can update your photo
capture button appropriately.
This is done via an enum of values called
AVCapturePhotoOutput CaptureReadiness.
The photo output can be
in a "notRunning," "ready,"
and three "not ready" states:
"Momentarily," "waiting for capture,"
or "waiting for processing."
The "not ready" enums indicate that
if you call capturePhoto with settings,
you'll incur a longer wait time between
the capture and the photo delivery,
increasing that shutter lag
I talked about previously.
Your app can listen for this state change
by using a new class,
AVCapturePhotoOutputReadinessCoordinator.
This makes callbacks
to a delegate object you provide
when the Photo Output's readiness changes.
You can use this class even
if you don't use the Responsive Capture
or Fast Capture Prioritization APIs.
Here's how you can convey shutter
availability
and modify button appearance
using the Readiness Coordinator
and the Readiness enum.
The app for our session turns off user
interaction events on the capture button
when handling a "not ready" enum value
to prevent additional requests
from getting enqueued inadvertently
with multiple taps,
resulting in long shutter lag.
After a tap,
and a capturePhoto with settings request
has been enqueued,
the captureReadiness state goes
between .ready and the
.notReadyMomentarily enum value.
Flash captures hit the
.notReadyWaitingForCapture state.
Until the flash fires,
the photo output hasn't even
gotten frames from the sensor,
so the button is dimmed.
Finally, if you only use zero shutter lag
and none of the other features this year,
You might show a spinner while the
.notReadyWaitingForProcessing
enum value is the current readiness,
as each photo's capture
and processing is completing.
So here's how you make use
of the readiness coordinator in code.
First, create a readiness coordinator
for the photo output,
and set an appropriate
delegate object to receive
callbacks about the readiness state.
Then, at the time of each capture,
set up your photo settings
as you normally would.
Then, tell the readiness coordinator
to start tracking the capture request's
readiness state for those settings.
And then call capturePhoto
on the photo output.
The readiness coordinator will then call
the captureReadinessDidChange
delegate callback.
You update your capture button's state
and appearance
based on the readiness enum value received
to give your customers
the best feedback
on when they can capture next.
Responsive Capture
and Fast Capture Prioritization APIs
are available on iPhones with
A12 Bionic chip and newer,
and the Readiness Coordinator
is available wherever
AVCapturePhotoOutput is supported.
And now I've got all of
the new features enabled in our app,
with the most responsive camera experience
possible that also gives super-sharp,
high-quality photos.
But, you don't have to use
them all to get an improved experience.
You can use just the ones
that are appropriate for your app.
We'll finish up our session today with
updated video effects.
Previously, Control Center on macOS
provided options for camera
streaming features
such as Center Stage, Portrait,
and Studio Light.
With macOS Sonoma,
we've moved video effects out
of Control Center and into its own menu.
You'll see a preview
of your camera or screen share,
and can enable Video Effects
like Portrait mode and Studio Light.
The Portrait and Studio Light effects
are now adjustable in their intensity,
and Studio Light
is available on more devices.
And we have a new effect
type called "Reactions."
When you're on a video call,
you might want
to express that you love an idea,
or give a thumbs up about good news,
all while letting the speaker
continue without interruption.
Reactions seamlessly blends
your video with balloons,
confetti, and more.
Reactions follow the template
of portrait and studio light effects,
where they're a system-level
camera feature,
available out of the box,
without any code changes needed
in your app.
For more detail
on Portrait and Studio Light effects,
check out the 2021 session,
"What's new in camera capture."
We have three ways to
show reactions in the video stream
First, you can click
on a reaction effect
in the bottom pane in
the new Video Effects menu on macOS .
Second, your app can call
AVCaptureDevice.performEffect
for: a reaction type.
For example, maybe you have
a set of reaction buttons
in one of your app's views
that participants can click on
to perform a reaction.
And third, when reactions are enabled,
they can be sent by making a gesture.
Let's check this out.
You can do thumbs up,
thumbs down,
fireworks with two thumbs up,
heart,
balloons with one victory sign,
rain with two thumbs down,
confetti with two victory signs,
and my personal favorite,
lasers, using two signs of the horns.
Hey, that's a nice bunch of effects.
You can check
for reaction effects support by looking
at the reactionEffectsSupported
property on
the AVCaptureDeviceFormat you want
to use in your capture session.
There are properties
on AVCaptureDevice that you can
read or key-value observe for
knowing when gesture recognition is on
and when reaction
effects have been enabled.
Remember, because these are under
the control of the user,
your app can't turn them on or off.
On iOS, it's the same idea.
The participant goes to Control Center
to turn gesture recognition on or off,
and you can key value observe
when this happens.
However, to trigger effects
in your app on iOS,
you’ll need to do it programmatically.
So let's go
through how you can do that, now.
When the "canPerformReactionEffects"
property is true,
calling the performEffect
for reactionType method will render
the reactions into the video feed.
Your app should provide buttons
to trigger the effects.
Reactions coming in via gestures
may be rendered in a different location
in the video than they would
be when you call performEffect\
depending on what cues
are used for the detection.
We have a new enum
called AVCaptureReactionType
for all of the different reaction effects,
such as thumbs-up or balloons
that AVCaptureDevice will recognize
in a capture session
and can render into the video content.
And the
"AVCaptureDevice.availableReactionTypes"
property returns a set
of AVCaptureReactionTypes
based on the configured format
or session preset.
These effects also
have built-in system UIImages
available that you can place
in your own views.
You can get the systemName
for a reaction from a new function
AVCaptureReactionType.systemImageName
that takes in an AVCaptureReactionType
and returns the appropriate string to use
with the UIImage systemName constructor.
And we have API to tell
you when reaction effects are in progress,
the aptly-named
AVCaptureDevice.reactionEffectsInProgress.
When the user performs
multiple reaction effects in sequence,
they may overlap briefly, so
this returns an array of status objects.
You can use Key-value observing
to know when these begin and end.
If you're a voice-over-IP conferencing
app, you can also use this
information to send the metadata
about the effects to remote views,
particularly when those callers have
video turned off for bandwidth reasons.
For example,
you might to show an effect icon
in their UI on behalf of another caller.
Rendering effect animations
to the video stream may be
challenging to a video encoder.
They increase the complexity
of the content,
and it may require a larger
bitrate budget to encode it.
By Key-Value observing
reactionEffectsInProgress,
you can make encoder adjustments
while the rendering is happening.
If it's feasible for your app,
you can increase the bitrate
of the encoder
while effects are rendering.
Or if you're using the low-latency video
encoder through VideoToolbox
and setting the MaxAllowedFrameQP
VTCompressionPropertyKey,
then we encourage you to run tests in your
app using the various video configurations
including resolutions, framerates,
and bitrate tier supported and adjust the
max allowed FrameQP accordingly
while the effects are in progress.
Note that with a low MaxAllowedFrameQP
value, the framerate of effects
can be compromised and you'll end up
with a low video framerate.
The 2021 session
"Explore low-latency video encoding
with VideoToolbox" has more great
information on working with this feature.
You should also know
that the video frame rate
may change when effects are in progress.
For example,
if you've configured your AVCaptureSession
to run at 60 frames per second,
you'll get 60 frames per second
while effects aren't running.
But while effects are in progress,
you may get a different frame rate,
such as 30 frames per second.
This follows the model of
Portrait and Studio Light effects
where the end frame rate
may be lower than you specified.
To see what that frame rate will be,
check out
AVCaptureDeviceFormat.videoFrameRateRange
ForReactionEffectsInProgress
for the format you're configuring
on the device.
As with other
AVCaptureDeviceFormat properties,
this is informational to your app,
rather than something you can control.
On macOS and with tvOS apps using
Continuity Camera,
reaction effects are always enabled.
On iOS and iPad OS, applications can
opt-in via changes to their Info.plist.
You opt in either by advertising
that you're a VoIP application category
in your UIBackgroundModes array,
or by adding
NSCameraReactionEffectsEnabled
with a value of YES.
Reaction effects and gesture recognition
are available on iPhones
and iPads with the A14 chip or newer,
such as iPhone 12,
Apple Silicon Macs
and Intel Macs and Apple TVs
using Continuity Camera devices,
Apple Studio display attached
to a USB-C iPad or Apple Silicon Mac,
and third party cameras attached
to a USB-C iPad or Apple Silicon Mac.
And that wraps up
our session about responsive
camera experiences
with new APIs this year.
We talked about deferred photo processing,
zero shutter lag,
and responsive capture APIs
to give you new possibilities for making
the most responsive photography
app with improved image quality
and we also covered how
your users can really express themselves
with updated video effects,
including new "reactions."
I can't wait to see how you respond
to all the great new features.
Thanks for watching.
[upbeat music]