♪ ♪
Jean-Yves: Welcome to
"Explore media formats for the web."
I'm Jean-Yves Avenard, a WebKit engineer,
and today I will go over media formats
supported in Safari,
focusing on images and video,
and introduce you to some new technologies
we made available in Safari 17.
We are adding support
for some new image formats,
and I'm going to help you choose
the right one for your site
after a little presentation
on the most commonly found ones.
Then I'll guide you on optimizing MSE
with a brand-new technology
we've implemented in Safari 17.
Finally I will present how you
can add AirPlay support to your videos
using Media Source Extension
Over the years, three formats
have been the most widely used.
They are supported by all browsers
and are easily created and deployed,
but technology has made
tremendous progress over the last decade,
and new great formats are now available.
The incumbent formats are GIF,
JPEG, and PNG.
Let's look at them in more details.
GIF, or as we properly say
in my country of birth, "jeef,"
a format introduced 36 years ago
that is best suited for simple animations,
memes, and social media content.
It does not support a full color palette
being limited to 8 bits color at a time.
Since it's a lossless format,
file sizes can be quite large,
making it less suitable
for larger animations.
Then we have JPEG,
introduced over 30 years ago.
A great feature is progressive loading,
where you can see some
of the image before it's fully loaded,
particularly convenient at a time where
network speeds weren't particularly fast.
It is best suited
for photographs and other images
with a lot of color and details.
It's a lossy format.
That means that some image data
is lost during the compression process.
The compression also allowed for smaller
file sizes and faster loading times.
With GIF having so many limitations,
PNG was created 26 years ago.
PNG supports transparency,
which makes them useful
for overlaying images
on top of each other.
It's great for images
with large areas of solid color,
or sharp text such as logos,
or illustrations like
the WebKit Javascript's squirrel fish.
It's lossless and doesn't compress
as well as JPEG,
so it's not very suitable
for big images with lots of color.
Like GIF, it was designed to replace,
it supports animations,
though I've rarely seen those in the wild.
By using these formats,
you can reach all your users,
regardless
of what web browser they are using.
Safari 17 supports
an additional four extra modern formats,
which you will want
to use in addition to the legacy ones,
and that I think makes the most sense.
While they are great
and pretty much all interchangeable,
they each have their key
advantages over the others.
WebP was added to Safari 14
and macOS Big Sur.
This is a modern image format
that uses advanced compression algorithms
to achieve smaller file sizes
without sacrificing image quality.
WebP files are typically smaller
than those earlier image formats,
which can help improve
website performance and loading times.
WebP lets you do animations
with video-like quality,
and so use it
where it's a bad idea to use GIF
due to their size or lack of colors.
One exciting addition to
Safari 17 is JPEG-XL,
a new image format that's designed
to offer high compression rates
and image quality.
JPEG-XL uses a new compression algorithm
called "Modular Entropy Coding"
that allows for greater flexibility
in adjusting the compression ratio.
It is well suited for images that
may be served over slow connections,
like JPEG, so users can see something
before the whole image is fully loaded.
A key feature of JPEG-XL is
that you can losslessly convert,
that is, not occur any data loss going
from your existing JPEG files to JPEG-XL,
all while significantly reducing
their size by up to 60%.
It's a relatively new format,
and so may not be widely supported
by all devices and browsers.
AVIF is another modern image format
that uses the AV1 video codec
to achieve high compression rates
without sacrificing image quality.
Widely supported across all browsers,
it is well suited for live photos
and supports up to 12 bits color depth.
It also has the broadest support,
and you should include it as fallback.
AVIF can be
up to ten times smaller than JPEG.
In Safari 17, we added support for HEIC,
also known as HEIF.
It's an image format that uses the HEVC
video codec compression algorithm
to achieve small file sizes.
But since it's not widely supported
on other platforms,
you will probably only want
to use it as an alternative format.
This is the format used
by iPhones and iPad to save photos,
so you can directly handle photo uploaded
from your iPhone with no conversion.
If you intend to display images
using a WKWebView inside your app,
this is the format you should be using,
as it's hardware accelerated
and can be rendered quickly
and efficiently.
One of the key advantages of JPEG-XL,
AVIF and HEIC, however,
is that they support
both wide color gamut and HDR.
Supporting billions of colors,
the large color gamut
allows more colors to be preserved
on file and represented on screen.
HDR let you better define
how dark the darks can be,
and how bright the brightness can be,
and how much light can be taken in.
Together, you get more vibrancy
to outdoor landscapes,
or very bright scenes
with lots of contrasts,
or have perfect rendering
of those beautiful, complex skin tones.
As you want your website
to continue supporting
all widely deployed web browsers,
you will likely still need to provide GIF,
JPEG, and PNG for the years to come.
However, by offering these extra formats,
you can make your site quicker to load
and using less bandwidth,
while still being compatible.
You really don't need to choose.
Let me show you how.
Declaring an image element
with a JPEG-XL image means
older browsers and browsers that
don't support it will get a broken image.
The picture element in HTML allows you
to specify alternative sources,
allowing the browser
to choose a format that it supports.
You can even provide
multiple alternative sources,
prioritizing the format
that gives the best performance.
The browser will look over the list
of available format from top to bottom.
So here,
it will use HEIC first if supported.
If no matches are found
or if decoding failed along the way,
the URL of the image element's
source is selected.
That's how easy it is
to provide the right format for people
regardless of device support
without the need for looking
at the User-Agent string
or worry about the browser
the user will use.
You don't need to choose.
Let the browser do it for you.
Now that we know
the modern image formats we can use
and when to use them,
let's take a look at video,
and specifically,
let's dive into adaptive streaming video.
The evolution of video presentation
on websites has been a fascinating one,
and it has come a long way
since the early days of the web.
Here are some
of the key milestones in the evolution
of video presentation on websites.
In the early days of the web,
video was not commonly used
on websites due to technical limitations.
Websites were primarily made up
of text and static images.
In the early 2000s,
browser plugins like Flash and QuickTime
emerged as a popular way
to add video to websites.
And in 2010, HTML5 was introduced,
which made it possible to embed video
directly into webpages
without the need for those plugins.
This made it easier
to add video to websites,
and also allowed
for greater flexibility and control
over how video content
was displayed and played.
And WebKit was
at the forefront of this revolution.
With the rise of mobile devices,
it became increasingly important
for websites to be able to display
video content on smaller screens.
This led to the development
of new techniques to allow websites
to adapt to different screen sizes
and orientations.
HTTP Live Streaming
was introduced by Apple in 2009.
One of the key features of HLS is its
support for adaptive bitrate streaming,
which allows for the delivery
of the best possible video quality
based on the user's internet
connection speed and device capabilities.
Adaptive streaming in HLS
works by dividing the video content
into small chunks or segments,
typically between two and ten seconds
in length.
Each segment is encoded
at multiple bitrates,
and these different bitrate versions
are made available to the client
via a manifest file in the form
of an M3U8 multi-variant playlist.
HLS does a brilliant job
at selecting the best suitable variant.
It's very simple to use and is
the best solution for the end users.
Unfortunately, on desktop,
not all browsers included support for HLS,
and even today, only Safari supports it.
Web developers wanted
more control and more flexibility,
such as the selection
and transfer of media data,
or the ability
to play DRMed content on desktop.
And so in 2013,
the Media Source Extension
was published by the W3C body.
Safari 8 along with other browsers
quickly added support for it
Media Source Extension, or MSE,
is a low-level toolkit that allows
for adaptive streaming
by giving the webpage more control
and responsibilities
for managing buffering and resolution.
Overall, MSE has been a game changer
for web developers.
It has enabled the development
of high-quality streaming experiences
on the web and is now
the most used web video technology.
MSE has some drawbacks.
It isn't particularly good
at managing of buffer levels,
the timing and amount of network access,
and media variant selection.
These inefficiencies have largely been
immaterial on relatively powerful devices
like modern general purpose computers.
Power usage on mobile devices was much
higher than with the HLS native player,
and so MSE was never made available
on iPhones because we couldn't achieve
with MSE the required battery savings.
All our testing of various sites
proved that enabling MSE
would have lead
to a regression in battery life.
On devices with narrower capabilities
or where the connectivity
is spotty at best,
it can also be difficult
to achieve the same quality
of playback with the MediaSource API
than is possible with HLS.
One of the reason for this is
that MSE transferred most control
over the streaming of media data
from the User Agent
to the application running in the page.
This transfer of control
added points of inefficiencies,
the page does not have
the same level of knowledge
or even goals as the User Agent,
like they may seek
the cheapest networking connection path,
and this typically led
to much higher power usage.
And this year,
we wanted to address those drawbacks,
and we worked hard to find a way
to combine the flexibility provided by MSE
with the efficiency of HLS.
And so I am super pleased
to introduce this new technology
that combines the best of MSE
with the elements that makes HLS awesome,
the Managed Media Source API.
A "managed" MediaSource is one
where more control over the MediaSource
and its associated objects
has been given over to the browser.
It makes it easier
for media website authors to support
streaming media playback
on constrained capability devices,
all while allowing User Agents
to react to changes
in available memory
and networking capabilities.
Let’s go over some
of the differences over the old MSE.
Managed Media Source can reduce
power usage by telling the webpage
when it's a good time
to buffer more media data.
When not buffering,
it allows the cellular modem to go
into a low power state
for longer periods of time,
increasing battery life.
When the system gets
into a low memory state,
Managed Media Source
will intelligently clear out unused
or abandoned buffered memory,
making pages more efficient.
Because Managed Media Source tracks
when buffering should start and stop,
the page's job of detecting
low buffer and full buffer states
becomes much easier.
The browser does it for you.
With these improvements in place,
Safari can send media requests
over the 5G modem.
This allows your site
to use the blazingly fast 5G network
to load media data incredibly quickly,
while having a minimum impact
on power use.
And if you need to play a live show,
Managed Media Source
will automatically detect it
and switch to LTE or 4G, where available,
to extend your battery life.
You are still in the driver seat.
You are still in control
on which resolution to fetch,
how you download each segment
and from where.
Managed Media Source only
provides hints and gives you
a more efficient version of MSE.
By using ManagedMediaSource,
you will save bandwidth and battery life,
allowing your user
to watch your video for longer,
not only on their iPhones,
but also their iPads and Macs.
Let me show you how easy it is migrate
from MSE to Managed Media Source.
Transitioning your video player
from MSE to Managed Media Source
is easy and only requires a few steps.
Here, I will open a very simple HTML page
I had used multiple times
in the past to test MSE development.
It creates a video element and loads
12 seconds of data, and then plays it.
All the logic actually occurs
in a utility file mediasource.js
that is included.
Let's look at it, and in particular,
the method runWithMSE.
RunwithMSE waits for the page to load,
create a video element,
and attach it to a MediaSource object,
and append it to our HTML's body.
First, you need ensure
that Managed Media Source is available.
This is easily done
by checking the document
that ManagedMediaSource object is defined,
and if not, fall back to using MSE.
Then replace any call to MediaSource
by ManagedMediaSource itself.
Another way, and in my opinion easier,
is to override MediaSource itself like so:
You define a method getMediaSource()
and set a MediaSource shim.
And now, whenever you are
referring to MediaSource,
you will actually be using
ManagedMediaSource instead.
Managed Media Source should always be
your first choice over the older MSE.
Now, back to my HTML page.
After creating SourceBuffer,
now ManagedSourceBuffer,
you add two event handlers.
Startstreaming will notify the player
when it should start fetching new content
and add it to the managed sourceBuffer.
And one to handle the "endstreaming"
event to tell when the player needs
to stop fetching new data.
The user-agent now has determined
that it has enough data,
and it can now enter low power mode.
For this demonstration,
the endstreaming event handler
is just a placeholder.
Unlike with MSE,
your sourceBuffer may evict content
at any time,
and not just when appending data.
With MSE it was never a good idea
to assume your buffered range
only increased when appending new data,
which would have caused playback to stall
and the MSE specification
encouraged you to regularly check.
So you also need to add an event handler
for the bufferedchange event
where you will need
to check which data was evicted.
If you follow the guidance
of the Managed Media Source events
and only append data
when the element asks you to do so,
you will get access to 5G speed
on iPhone and iPad,
giving your users access
to higher resolutions,
shorter rebuffering time,
and best possible battery life.
You are now ready
to handle adaptive streaming
using the new ManagedMediaSource
available in Safari 17.
Though if all you care about
are Apple devices,
using HLS instead
will likely make more sense.
There's one more thing your users
will want to continue doing:
The ability to AirPlay
to their favorite TVs.
One of the great benefit
of using native HLS
was the automatic support for AirPlay.
With AirPlay, while sitting on your couch,
you can move the video
from your phone
to your big AirPlay device.
Airplay requires a URL that you can send,
which doesn't exist in MSE,
and this created a problem
we also wanted to resolve.
In the choosing
the right image format earlier,
I showed you with the picture element
how you could add alternative sources.
The video element
offers the same mechanism.
Simply add
your HTTP Live Streaming playlist
to a child source element for the video,
and when the user AirPlays your content,
Safari will switch away
from your Managed Media Source
and play the HLS stream
on the AirPlay device.
Safari will automatically add an AirPlay
icon to the video player controls
and let the user AirPlay the video.
If this all sounded too complicated,
you can use frameworks, such as HLS.js,
that will support Managed Media Source
automatically when available
and will do all the hard work for you.
Making use of HLS.js
for handling your video is fairly easy
and usable on all web browsers,
even those not natively supporting HLS.
First, you will need to create a video
element in your HTML file like usual.
We first check if HLS
is natively supported by the browser.
If it is, we can directly set the video
source attribute to the manifest URL.
If not, we check if HLS.js can run,
and if so,
create a new instance
of the HLS.js library
and attach it to the video element
with ID "my-video."
We then load the HLS playlist file,
in this case, my-video.m3u8.
That's it.
With these steps, you should be able
to play HLS videos on most browsers.
When designing Managed MSE,
we wanted to make sure that nothing
was left out by accident and that users
continue to get the same level
of features as they did in the past.
So to activate Managed MSE
on Mac, iPad, and iPhone,
your player must provide
an AirPlay source alternative.
You can still have access
to Managed MSE without it,
but you must explicitly disable AirPlay
by calling disableRemotePlayback
on your media element
from the Remote Playback API.
And that's it.
Managed MSE supports all the same
great technology we added last year,
such as SharePlay,
spatialized audio, or HDR.
Managed MSE is available in Safari 17
on macOS and iPad OS
and behind an experimental flag on iPhone.
We are so excited for this
to finally be coming to iPhone.
I hope you'll try the new image formats
and experiment with Managed Media Source.
Please make sure
to test your site with Safari.
Also, we release
Safari Technology Preview fortnightly,
where you can test the latest new features
as they come available
and before it reaches end users.
Like all actively developed programs,
glitches and bugs happen
from time to time,
and we would be immensely grateful
if you reported those
to bugs.webkit.org
should you encounter them.
You can also submit
comments or suggestions.
We are always listening.
You can learn about new CSS features
in Safari in "What's new in CSS."
And check out
"Rediscover Safari developer features"
to learn about turning on feature flags
to try out Managed Media Source.
Thank you for watching.
♪ ♪