♪ ♪
Justin: Hello!
My name's Justin,
and I'm part of the Photos team.
Today I'm going to take you through
new improvements
to the system Photos picker
and all the great new APIs
you can use in your app.
We introduced
the redesigned picker UI in iOS 14.
It has many great features
like search and a zoomable grid.
Even better, you don't need to request
any photo library access to use it.
We really recommend you
to replace your custom picker
with the system one whenever possible.
The API is really easy to use as well.
With only a few lines of code,
you can present the picker
and receive user selected images.
"What's new in the Photos picker"
session last year
talked about the new API in depth.
In this session, I'm going to focus
on new APIs you can leverage
to embed the system picker in your app,
making the photo picking experience
more seamless.
Later, I will also discuss
the new Options menu,
as well as best practices
if you want to support HDR photos,
HDR videos, and Cinematic mode videos.
But before we dive in,
let's quickly recap
the picker's access model.
This is the picker you saw a moment ago.
Even though it looks like
it is running in your app,
it is really running
in a separate process,
rendered on top of your app.
Your app can't access
the picker directly
and not even take screenshots
of the picker content.
Only what the user actually selected
is passed back to your app.
This year, we are bringing
more configuration options
to the out-of-process picker.
A new ".photosPickerDisabledCapabilities"
modifier
allows you to disable
certain picker capabilities,
so you can implement
your own version of it.
For example, the "Cancel" button
and the "Add" button
can be hidden
if you disable selection actions.
A new ".photosPickerAccessoryVisibility"
modifier allows you to hide accessory UI
around the picker content,
like the navigation bar and the toolbar.
You can even specify the size
and position of the picker
using standard SwiftUI modifiers
like ".frame" and ".padding".
You may be wondering:
"If the "Add" button is hidden,
how can my app receive user selected
assets in multiple selection mode?"
You can now set selection behavior
to ".continuous"
to receive live selection updates.
And finally, you can use the new
".photosPickerStyle(.inline)" modifier
to embed the picker in your app,
instead of having it presented
as a separate sheet.
Even though the picker is embedded,
it is still rendered
in a separate process.
Some users might be worried
when they see your app displaying
all of their photos
without prompting for library access.
We want to help users to feel safe
when using your app,
so the first time
an embedded picker is displayed,
an onboarding UI will automatically appear
explaining that your app
can only access selected photos.
The Photos privacy badge
indicates that the picker is private
and out of process.
If your app already presents
the full size picker,
a dismissible banner will appear
when users upgrade to iOS 17.
The Privacy Settings UI is also updated
with more detailed explanation.
In addition, we made some changes
to the library access permission prompt.
To learn more about those changes,
you can watch
the "What's new in privacy" session.
All right, let's go back
to the actual API.
I will go though their use cases first,
and then I'll explain each API in detail.
If you want to embed
the out-of-process picker,
use the ".photosPickerStyle" modifier.
To place your own UI around the picker,
".photosPickerAccessoryVisibility"
is the one to use.
It also has an optional argument
allowing you to control accessories
around specified edges.
The default value is all edges.
If you want to implement
your own replacement
for some picker features,
use the ".photosPicker
DisabledCapabilities" modifier.
And lastly, if you need to adjust
or respond to selection updates
in real time,
make sure "selectionBehavior"
is set to ".continuous".
So what exactly are considered
as accessories?
On iOS, the top accessory
is the navigation bar
and the bottom accessory is the toolbar.
On iPadOS and macOS,
the leading accessory is the sidebar
when it is visible.
The top and bottom accessories
are similar to what iOS has.
Next, I will walk you through
picker capabilities
that can be disabled
and how they will affect the picker UI.
The search bar will be hidden
if the search capability is disabled.
If collection navigation is disabled,
the albums tab will be hidden.
On iPadOS and macOS,
the sidebar will be hidden as well.
If the staging area is disabled,
the toolbar button will be replaced
with the status label.
If you disabled selection actions
without continuous selection,
only the "Cancel" button will be hidden
and the "Add" button
will still be visible.
Otherwise, your app won't be able
to receive any user selection.
Both buttons will be hidden
if you also set the selection behavior
to ".continuous".
Let's look at new picker styles now.
In addition to the ".presentation" style
and the ".inline" style,
the picker also supports
another ".compact" style.
This is the default ".presentation" style.
This is the ".inline" style
with all accessories hidden.
And this is the ".compact" style.
The single row picker allows you
to embed it in more places
where the available vertical space
is seriously constrained.
It's time for a demo
to connect everything together.
I already made a simple app allowing me
to annotate images with text descriptions.
Let me show you what it can do right now.
I can present the picker as a modal sheet,
select some images,
and add some descriptions.
For the demo, I want to replace
the "Select Photos" button
with the embedded picker.
Let me add the
".photosPickerStyle(.inline)" modifier
and try it out.
[no audio]
It works, but it doesn't look good yet.
I still need to tap the "Add" button
to update the list,
and if the picker resizes,
the toolbar is not extended
to the bottom edge of the device.
But don't worry.
With only a few tweaks,
it can look a lot better.
First, because the picker can handle
safe area insets gracefully,
I can use the ".ignoresSafeArea" modifier
so the picker can expand
to the bottom edge of the screen.
Next, I'm going to make sure
the list can be updated
as soon as I select a photo in the picker.
Actually, it's super easy to change.
Setting the selection behavior
to ".continuous" is all I need to do.
Since the list is now live updated,
I don't really need to keep
the navigation bar buttons anymore.
I can remove them
using the ".photosPicker
DisabledCapabilities" modifier.
The picker is now fully functional.
But I want to make sure
the picker looks nice as well.
I think I should hide the navigation bar
and the toolbar.
I also want to give the picker
a fixed height.
I can use the ".photosPicker
AccessoryVisibility" modifier
to hide the bars,
and adjust the height of the picker
like any other SwiftUI views.
[no audio]
Now it looks great.
Within just a few minutes,
I updated my app
to display the new embedded picker.
I'll build and run so we can test it
on a real device.
I can use the zoomable grid to quickly
navigate to the photo I want to pick.
Selected photos
automatically appear in my app.
My app's photo picking experience
is greatly improved
with the new embedded picker.
That's it for the demo.
I was using an iPhone in the demo,
but the same API is available on iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS.
In addition to SwiftUI,
the same API is available
to UIKit and AppKit apps as well.
Let's take a look
at the UIKit and AppKit API.
The embedded picker is available
via the same PHPickerConfiguration API.
You can now set "selection"
to ".continuous"
to opt in the continuous selection
behavior.
You can also set "mode" to ".compact"
to configure the picker
to the single row layout.
You can use "edgesWithoutContentMargins"
to hide accessories
like the navigation bar,
and "disabledCapabilities"
to disable certain picker capability.
Unlike the SwiftUI API
where you can use
the ".photosPickerStyle(.inline)" modifier
to embed the picker,
you will need to add it
as a child view controller
to your container controller.
You can set the frame
of the picker manually
or use Auto Layout constraints
to size and position the picker view.
After adding the subview,
you just need to notify the picker
that it has been added.
A new "PHPickerConfiguration.Update" API
allows you to update the picker
while it is shown to the user.
You can also deselect
or reorder selected assets
using the existing "deselectAsset"
and "moveAsset" APIs.
Next, I will talk about
the new Options menu
and how it will affect your app.
The new Options menu gives users
more control over what they can share
with your app.
By default,
all image metadata are included,
but users can now choose
to remove sensitive metadata,
like location, from selected photos.
If you are using the "PhotosPicker"
and "Transferable" API,
you don't need to do any adoption work
to support the new Options menu.
Similarly, no adoption work is needed
if you are using
the "PHPickerViewController" API.
The Options menu will not be supported
for apps that use
the legacy "UIImagePickerController" API
or have full library access.
Okay, that's the Options menu.
Now I will talk about how you can
support HDR images,
HDR videos, and Cinematic mode videos
if you use the system picker.
The picker may automatically
transcode assets to compatible formats,
like JPEG, by default.
However, the transcoded asset
may not contain all information
included in the original asset.
So if you want to receive HDR content,
it's best to avoid automatic transcoding.
You can get photos and videos
in their original formats
by using the ".current" encoding policy
and requesting a generic content type,
like ".image" or ".movie".
Requesting specific content types,
like ".jpeg", may still transcode assets
even if the encoding policy
is set to ".current".
For more information
about adding support for HDR,
you can watch the "Support HDR images
in your app" session this year.
Here is a code example that receives
images in their original formats.
You can see that "preferredItemEncoding"
is set to ".current"
and "importedContentType" is ".image".
If a Cinematic mode video is selected,
the picker will give you
its rendered version,
with all the depth effect baked in.
If you want to get all decision points,
you need to request photo library access
and use PhotoKit
to fetch the video instead.
To learn more about Cinematic mode videos,
you can check out the "Support Cinematic
mode videos in your app" session.
To wrap up, the new embedded picker
brings a lot of flexibility
and I can't wait to see
what you can do with it.
The Options menu gives users more control
over what to share,
so please avoid requesting photo library
access unless it's really necessary.
Thank you, and happy coding!
♪ ♪