♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
David Johnson:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to "What's New
in Safari Extensions."
My name is David Johnson,
and I'm a Safari extensions
engineer here at Apple.
Today, I'm excited to tell you
about some recent developments
in Safari extensions,
highlighting improvements
to the user experience
and new features.
First, we want to thank you
for creating
and sharing the over
2000 Safari extensions
available on
the App Store today.
Demand for
Safari extensions on iOS
has been especially impressive.
They're often among the top
categories on the App Store
since their introduction
at WWDC21.
Your extensions empower
users to customize
their browsing experience
across macOS, iOS, and iPadOS.
There are four ways
to build Safari extensions:
content blockers,
share extensions,
app extensions,
and web extensions.
Safari 17 continues to support
all of these types,
but the future
of browser customization
lies in web extensions.
Apple is dedicated
to standardizing web extensions
alongside the other
major browser vendors.
This collaboration aims
to improve compatibility,
streamline development,
and ensure a familiar experience
across all browsers.
We're working together
in the W3C WebExtensions
Community Group,
where Apple proudly serves
as a cochair.
By connecting with other browser
and extension developers
to drive this
standardization effort,
we're building a stronger
and more unified
web extension ecosystem.
Before jumping
into today's topics,
I'd like to share
two key details
about Safari web extensions.
First, Safari 17 will continue
to support both Manifest v2
and v3 web extensions.
We'll continue to add
new features to Manifest v3,
so update when it makes sense
for your extension.
Second, web extensions
are the best way
to build extensions for Safari
across platforms.
With a single shared codebase,
web extensions allow you
to customize the capabilities
of Safari on iOS,
iPadOS, macOS, and now xrOS.
That's right, web extension
available on iOS and iPadOS
will also be available on xrOS.
Web extensions on xrOS
work just like you'd expect
and have the same capabilities
as extensions on iOS,
including the ability
to inject scripts,
run background content,
and display popovers.
We're excited to see
how your extensions
enhance the browsing
experience on xrOS.
To learn more about
Safari on xrOS,
check out
"Meet Safari for xrOS."
With those announcements
out of the way,
here's what we'll cover
in the rest of today's session.
First, we'll delve into some
new and updated extension APIs
and how they enhance
the capabilities
of Safari extensions.
Then we'll cover
per-site permissions
for Safari app extensions,
offering users more control
over their browsing experience.
And finally, we'll take a look
at how to ensure compatibility
with both Safari Profiles
and Private Browsing.
Up first,
new extension APIs.
Content blockers are a great way
to clean up web pages,
remove annoyances,
and block loading of scripts.
Content blockers use rules
defined in JSON to block or hide
content without needing
access to any information
about what websites are visited.
Declaratively hiding content
on web pages can be tricky.
That's why content blockers
now support :has() selectors.
:has() selectors are great
because they allow
your content blocker to
precisely target parent elements
based on their children.
In this rule example,
we're hiding any elements
with the class .post that
also have a child element
with the class .paid-promo.
Extensions that hide
webpage content,
or block network requests,
are some of the most popular
types of extensions.
That's why Safari continues
to support you
in creating innovative
and effective extensions
that offer a secure and private
browsing experience
for your users.
If you're looking to block
or modify network requests
with a web extension,
you should check out
these updates
to Declarative Net Request.
Declarative Net Request
is a powerful API
that provides a way
for your web extension
to block and modify
network requests.
Like content blockers,
your extension provides rules
in a JSON format
and Safari handles the rest.
This means enhanced
power efficiency,
especially on
battery-powered devices.
Since these rules
are declarative,
your extension
doesn't need access
to webpages the user visits,
increasing their privacy
and security.
One big update
to Declarative Net Request
in Safari 16.4
is that your extension
can now modify request headers.
In this example,
I've defined an action
that sets a custom
User-Agent header
for all requests made
to example.com.
Beyond setting headers, this
action type can modify headers
by adding new values,
removing existing values,
or even removing
headers entirely
from HTTP requests.
Modifying network requests
is a powerful tool,
and there are some key points
to keep in mind.
First, you must declare
the declarativeNetRequestWithHostAccess permission
in the manifest.
In Safari 16.4, this permission
is now also required
for redirect actions.
Your extension must also
be granted per-site permissions
for any modify headers or
redirect actions to be applied.
This ensures that the user
has control over their data
on a site-by-site basis.
By keeping these
considerations in mind,
you can create powerful
and privacy-friendly
content-blocking extensions
that provide a tailored
experience for your users.
If you're building an extension
that uses
Declarative Net Request,
you may want
to let your users know
just how many requests
it has blocked.
Using the new
declarativeNetRequest.setExtensionActionOptions API,
you can configure the badge text
to display action counts,
such as the number
of blocked loads.
In this example, we set the
displayActionCountAsBadgeText
option to true,
which is currently
the only option for this API.
Your extension badge
will update automatically
based on the actions taken.
This allows your users
to easily monitor
the extension's activity
and effectiveness,
all while keeping
their browsing history private.
Now I'll cover an update
to the scripting API
that gives you more control over
the behavior of your extension.
With the registerContentScript
set of APIs,
you can create content scripts
that can be registered,
updated, or removed
programmatically.
This means that you can target
specific pages or conditions
to apply to content scripts.
In this example,
I'm registering a script
to be injected onto pages
that match webkit.org.
This script registration will
also persist across sessions.
This new API complements
the static content scripts
defined in
the extension manifest,
giving you greater flexibility
in managing content scripts
and enabling you
to create more advanced features
for your extensions.
Safari 16.4 also brings
a new storage area
to web extensions:
the session storage area.
Storing and retrieving data
from session storage
uses the same familiar functions
as other storage areas.
This API allows you
to store data in memory
for the duration
of your browser session,
providing a fast and efficient
way to access data
between nonpersistent
background page loads.
Unlike local storage,
session storage is not
persisted to disk
and it's cleared
when Safari quits.
This makes session storage
particularly useful
for storing sensitive
or security-related data,
such as decryption keys
or authentication tokens,
that should not be stored
in local storage.
Finally, we know that
making sure your extension
has all the right icon sizes
for different UI elements
is a chore.
That's why starting
in Safari 16.4,
you can now create
a single SVG icon
that looks beautiful
at any size.
Safari will take care of scaling
your extension's icon sharply,
letting you focus
on everything else.
Those API updates are just
some of the improvements
to Safari extensions this year.
Now let's talk about
Safari app extensions
and per-site permissions.
If you're already familiar
with per-site permissions
from web extensions,
they work the same way
for app extensions.
Users are able to grant
extensions access
to websites as they browse,
providing for better
privacy and control.
When an extension
is first turned on,
it won't have access to any
sites that the user visits.
The first time an extension
tries to access the page,
Safari will badge
the extension's toolbar item
alerting the user
that the extension wants access
to the current page.
When the user clicks
on that toolbar item,
they'll be shown information
about what access
the extension will have,
and be given the option
to Allow for One Day,
or Always Allow.
When granted permission,
the extension's toolbar item
will be tinted to show
that the extension
has access to the current page.
Anyone that upgrades
to Safari 17
and already has
Safari app extensions turned on
will have all permissions
migrated for those extensions.
They'll also be shown a banner
giving them the option
to increase their privacy.
If Ask for Each Website
is chosen,
all Safari app extension
permissions will be reset,
and your users will be able
to grant your extension access
to each site as they visit.
There are no new APIs to adopt
to support this change
in Safari 17; however,
take some time to review
your extension's assumptions
and test how your extensions
behave in Safari 17.
Your users will have full
control over the websites
every Safari app extension
can access.
Your extension will
automatically have access
to sites when permission
is granted by the user.
However, permissions can be
granted or revoked at any time.
Toolbar items are now shown
by default for all extensions.
Take a look at how your
extension icon appears in Safari
and supply a PDF vector icon
that can be
tinted appropriately.
Finally, let's talk about
updates to how extensions work
in both Profiles
and Private Browsing.
In Safari 17, users will be able
to control which extensions
have access to their Private
Browsing windows and tabs
without needing to turn off
the extension
in other browsing contexts.
Extensions that inject scripts,
or can read information
about the pages a user visits,
are turned off by default.
However, extensions
that don't access content,
like content blockers,
are automatically allowed
in Private Browsing
because there aren't any
additional privacy concerns.
Here's the updated Extensions
pane in Safari settings on macOS
and there are
similar updates on iOS.
There's a new option
to allow this extension
in Private Browsing.
For extensions
that are turned on,
it's one click
in Safari settings
to allow that extension access
to Private Browsing as well.
Profiles are new
in Safari this year.
They're a way to keep
browsing data separated.
Profiles contain separate
history, cookies,
and website data.
Users can also choose
which extensions
they want to turn on
per profile.
This includes new
tab page extensions.
And of course,
all these settings sync
across all of a user's iPhone,
iPad, and Macs through iCloud.
The Extensions pane
in Safari settings
has also been updated
to list the profiles
where an extension is active.
Here you can see that
the Sea Creator extension
is active in both
Work and School profiles.
When an extension
is turned on in a profile,
it is an entirely new instance
of that extension.
This means each instance
will have a different UUID,
background page,
and storage.
However, per-site permissions
are shared across profiles.
That means your users only need
to grant your extension
access once.
When running in a profile,
an extension only has access
to the windows, tabs,
and other data related
to that profile.
If your extension communicates
with a native host app,
make sure that your app expects
to receive messages
from multiple profiles
and respects the separation
of data across those profiles.
When your app receives a call
to beginRequest(with context:),
decode the userInfo dictionary.
If your extension
is active in a profile,
there will be
a profileIdentifier value
for the key
SFExtensionProfileKey.
Since extensions have
unique instances per profile,
it's possible to inspect their
background content separately.
From the Develop menu
in Safari 17,
you can dive into
the Web Extension
Background Content menu item
and see the background pages
and service workers
grouped by extension.
Each extension will list its
inspectable content per profile.
To learn more about
the improvements
to Safari developer
features this year,
check out
"What's new in Web Inspector"
and "Rediscover Safari
developer features."
In summary, Safari is committed
to standardizing web extensions
and providing you with new APIs
to create innovative
and effective extensions.
We'd love for you to join
in the discussion
and help shape the future
of web extensions
by participating in the WECG.
With per-site permissions
for app extensions
and support for new features
like :has() selectors,
you can create extensions
that offer a secure
and private browsing experience
for your users.
Don't forget to update
your extensions
to take advantage
of these new capabilities
and ensure they work well
with both Profiles
and Private Browsing.
And finally, provide feedback
through Feedback Assistant
as you test your extensions
in Safari 17.
Thank you for listening,
and have a great rest of WWDC.
♪