♪ ♪
David: Hi, I'm David Ilenwabor,
an Engineer on the ShazamKit team.
ShazamKit is a framework that allows you
to bring audio recognition to your apps.
You can match audio against
Shazam's vast music catalog
or match against your own prerecorded
audio using custom catalogs.
2022 saw some great updates to ShazamKit
which improved working
with custom catalogs at scale.
There was the introduction of
the Shazam CLI
to handle heavy workflow
when using custom catalogs,
time restricted media items
for better syncing,
and frequency skewing
to differentiate between
two similar sounding bits of audio.
If you're not already familiar
with how these work,
check out the Create Custom catalogs
at scale with ShazamKit video.
But to give a quick overview,
ShazamKit lets you perform a match
by converting audio
into a special format called Signatures.
You can pass in a stream of audio buffers
or the signature data
into a ShazamKit session.
The session then uses the signature
to find a match
in the Shazam Catalog or a Custom catalog.
If there's a match,
the session returns a match object
with media items that represent
the metadata of the match.
You can then display the media items
in your app.
ShazamKit can perform a match
by generating a signature
from a stream of audio buffers
or using a signature file
which can be stored on disk.
Signatures are irreversible
which means it is not possible
to reconstruct the original recording
from a signature.
This protects the privacy
of our customers.
A catalog is a group of signatures
with their associated media items
and a match occurs when a query signature
sufficiently matches part of
a reference signature in a catalog.
Matches can occur even when
the query signature is noisy,
such as music playing in a restaurant.
Now that I've covered that,
I'll move on to the exciting new updates
in ShazamKit this year.
In this session,
I'll go through new changes
for recognizing audio with ShazamKit,
then I'll talk about
the Shazam Library API,
which has been redefined
with exciting new functionality.
Finally, I'll take you through
some best practices
for creating better app experiences
with ShazamKit.
Before I get started,
I suggest you download
the attached sample code project
on the developer portal.
I will be making use
of this project throughout this video.
There's a lot to cover,
so I'll get started.
First off, Audio recognition.
The process of using ShazamKit
to recognize audio from the microphone
can be summarized in the following steps.
First, ask for microphone permissions
from the user.
Then, start recording
after permissions have been granted.
Next, pass in the recorded audio buffers
to ShazamKit,
and finally, handle the result.
To demonstrate this, I've built a demo app
which you can find in the sample project.
I love dancing,
and to keep up with the latest trends,
I built an app to help me discover
trending dance moves to a song.
The app works by listening
to audio using the microphone,
and proceeds to find a dance video.
So for example,
I can ask Siri to help me find a song.
Hey, Siri, play "Push It" by Dukes.
Siri: Now playing "Push It" by Dukes.
David: Then, I can tap the Learn The Dance
button to start recording.
♪ ♪
ShazamKit recognizes the song
and the app searches for
an appropriate dance video to go with it.
Seems like I got one. Hmm!
Looks like my twin Dancing Dave is showing
me some moves.
This looks exciting.
So how was this implemented?
Let me take you through the code.
Here I have the sample project
opened in Xcode.
I have added the microphone usage
description in my info.plist file
which is used
to request microphone access.
I also have a host of SwiftUI views
for the home screen
and the dance video screen.
However, this Matcher class is where all
the magic of audio recognition happens.
On initialization, I have a method
to configure and set up the audio engine.
In this method,
I install a tap to receive PCMbuffers
and prepare the audio engine.
Also, I have a match method which is called
when I tap on the Learn The Dance button.
I request for recording permission,
and if this is granted, I call start
on the audio engine to begin recording.
Next, I tell the UI matching has started,
then I call session.results
and wait for an async sequence
of match results.
After receiving a result,
I set the match object if it was a match,
and I handle the no match and error cases.
This class also has a stopRecording
Function in which I stop the audio engine.
This works great,
but notice how I have a lot of setup code
to configure the audio engine
before I can receive audio buffers.
This can be challenging to get right,
especially if you aren't familiar
with audio programming.
And so, to make recording
and matching easier,
we've introduced a new API
called SHManagedSession.
Managed Session automatically takes care
of starting the recording for you
without the hassle
of setting up audio buffers.
This makes it very easy to set up and use.
Microphone permission is required
to use Managed Session.
Without this permission,
the session cannot start recording.
Therefore, it is important you add
the Microphone usage description entry
to the info.plist file of your app.
Managed Session will use this description
when asking for microphone access
from the user.
So how can I use this API in code?
First, I'll create an instance
of SHManagedSession,
then I can wait on a result
by calling the result method.
This method returns an enum which has
three states that can either be a match,
NoMatch, or an error.
Next, I can switch over the result,
using the returned media items
in the case of a match,
and handling the no match and error cases.
And what if I want to have
a longer recording session
that can return many results over time?
Well, I can do this by using
the async sequence results property
on managedSession.
I can use each result that's received
from the sequence just as before.
This ensures I can keep recording audio
for long periods.
Finally, I can stop matching
by calling cancel on managedSession.
This cancels any currently running
match attempt and stops recording.
And that's it.
With Managed Session,
it's just a few lines of code
to start recording
and receive a result after matching.
Going back to my app, I'm going to update
the Matcher implementation
to use managedSession.
I can replace all instances of
SHSession with SHManagedSession.
Then, I can delete the configure
audio engine method and its usage.
And in the match method,
I can delete the calls to request
recording permission
and to start the audio engine.
Finally, in the stopRecording method,
I can replace the existing code
to stop the audio engine
with just a call
to managedSession's cancel method.
Now, I'll run the app to make sure
everything is still working as expected.
Hey, Siri, play "Push It" by Dukes.
Siri: Here's "Push It" by Dukes.
♪ ♪
Exciting!
Everything is still working fine,
but this time, the code is even better
and cleaner with Managed Session.
That's not all.
There's even more
to Managed Session to talk about.
Depending on your use case,
you may want managedSession
to prepare for a match attempt
ahead of time.
Preparing a Managed Session makes
the session more responsive when matching.
It also preallocates the necessary
resources needed for a match
and, it starts prerecording
in anticipation of a match attempt.
To give you an idea of the benefits
of using prepare,
here's a timeline representing
the behavior of the session
without calling prepare.
When you ask for a result,
the session allocates the resources
for the match attempt,
then starts recording,
finally, it returns a match.
However, when you call prepare,
the session immediately preallocates
the resources and starts prerecording.
Then, when you ask for a result,
the session returns a match
faster than before.
To do this in code,
I can simply call the prepare method
before I ask for a result.
Calling this method is entirely up to you
and ShazamKit will call it
on your behalf if necessary.
Now, you might be wondering,
"How do I track
the current behavior of the session?
"For example, in a long running session,
"how do I know it's recording or matching
or doing something else?"
To help with this, Managed Session has
a property called state
which represents
the current state of the session.
The three states are
idle,
prerecording, and matching.
In the idle state, the session is neither
recording nor making a match attempt.
This is the case if the session
just completed a single match attempt
or you call cancel,
or the session terminates
the async sequence of results
when carrying out multiple matches.
Prerecording represents the state
after the session has been prepared.
In this state, all the necessary resources
for matching are ready
and the session is prerecording
for a match attempt.
You can then proceed with matching
or cancel prerecording.
Matching is the third possible state
which indicates the session is making
at least one match attempt.
Calling prepare in this state
will be ignored by the session.
Here's an example of how
the managedSession state
could be used in SwiftUI
to drive view behavior.
Here, I have the sample implementation
of a subview from the demo app.
I have implemented different behaviors
for this view
if the state is idle or matching.
Currently,
the state of the session is idle
and the text view is set to Hear Music.
Also, I have a conditional that checks
if the state is matching or not.
If it is,
I display a progress view,
and if it's not,
I display the Learn the Dance button.
Since the state is currently idle,
the Learn the Dance button is displayed.
When I tap on the button,
the state changes to matching
and my UI automatically refreshes.
This time the text is set to Matching
and the progress view replaces the button
since matching has commenced.
Whenever the state of the session changes,
SwiftUI will automatically
refresh your views
to respond to those changes
without any extra work.
And this is because managedSession
conforms to Observable,
which is a new Swift type that
makes objects automatically communicate
their changes to observers.
Therefore, SwiftUI can easily respond
to any state changes of managedSession.
To learn more about Observable,
check out the Discover Observation
of SwiftUI video.
Now that I've covered audio recognition,
I'll talk about the Shazam library.
In 2021, ShazamKit provided an API
to allow developers
to write a match result
to the Shazam Library,
provided it has a valid Shazam ID.
This means that it corresponds to a song
in the Shazam Catalog.
The added item is visible in the Control
Center Music Recognition module
and the Shazam app if installed.
It is also synced across devices.
There is no special permission required
to write to the Shazam library,
but I recommend you avoid storing content
in it without making customers aware,
as all songs saved in the library will
be attributed to the app that added them.
Here, the second song in the list
is attributed
to the ShazamKit Dance Finder app.
Over the years, usage of this API
presented different use cases
and led to some drawbacks.
For example, what if you wanted to
view items you've added in your own app?
The go-to solution would be managing
your own local storage
which can be tedious to handle
and prone to bugs.
Because of these drawbacks,
a new class has been introduced
called SHLibrary.
I recommend adopting SHLibrary,
as it offers more extensive features
compared to
the previous SHMediaLibrary class.
Some of the core features
of SHLibrary include
adding media items to the Shazam Library,
which works the same way as the
corresponding method in SHMediaLibrary;
reading media items;
and deleting media items from the library.
Note that your app can only read and
delete what it has added to the library.
Items returned when you read
are specific to your app
and do not represent the entire library.
Also, attempting to delete a media item
your app hasn't added will throw an error.
Next, I'm going to explain
how to use SHLibrary.
Adding with SHLibrary is as simple
as calling the addItems method
of the default library object.
This method takes in an array
of media items to be added.
Reading from the library
is equally simple.
As an example,
here's how you can read items
from the library
and populate a List view in SwiftUI.
You simply pass in the items property
of the library object
into the list initializer.
SHLibrary also conforms to
the new Swift Observable type,
therefore, your SwiftUI views
will automatically reload
when there's a change.
You can also read from the library
in a non-UI context.
For example, if I want to retrieve
the most popular genre of a user
from their synced Shazams,
I can ask for the current items
of the library.
Then, once I have this,
I can filter through the array of items
to get all the returned genres,
and count the genre
with the highest frequency.
Finally, I can remove items from
the library by calling removeItems
on the library object,
passing in the array of media items
to be removed.
Going back to my app,
since I've added recognized songs
to my library,
I can use the new SHLibrary
to read these songs.
In the RecentDancesView,
I have a List which contains
an empty array of mediaItems
in the initializer.
I'll replace the empty array with items
from SHLibrary
to automatically read my library items.
I'll run the app with these changes.
As soon as the app loads,
I receive a list of songs which the app
has added to the Shazam Library.
With SHLibrary,
I get this functionality for free,
and I don't need to maintain a database
of matched songs.
Next up, I'll add a Swipe to delete action
on each row,
so I can delete a song from the library.
I can add a swipeAction on the row view.
Then when the swiped button is tapped,
I can call the removeItems method
of SHLibrary,
passing in the media item
that is to be deleted.
Now that's done,
I'll run the app with these changes.
I've got the app open on my iPad as well.
I can swipe on an item on my iPhone,
and tap the delete button.
The changes are synced
and the deleted item
is also removed from the list on the iPad.
This is amazing.
Now that you've learned
how to use the new library APIs
and how you can make use
of Managed Session to handle recording,
I'll take you through some best practices
and offer some tips when using some of
the new features introduced this year.
SHManagedSession and SHSession
are closely related.
They can achieve almost the same thing,
albeit in different ways.
Use managedSession when you want to let
ShazamKit handle the recording for you.
Use SHSession when you are generating
the audio buffers
and passing them into the framework.
Use managedSession to recognize audio
coming from the microphone or an AirPod.
Use SHSession when you want to only
recognize audio
streaming from the microphone.
Matching arbitrary signatures
with managedSession is not supported.
Therefore,
if you have a signature file
or loaded signature data in memory,
use SHSession to match it.
Finally, managedSsession automatically
handles audio formats for the matching,
while SHSession allows matching
with multiple PCM audio formats.
Speaking of audio formats in SHSession,
previously, the matchStreamingBuffer
method only allowed
matching PCM audio buffers
with specific format settings
at these sample rates.
Audio buffers with unsupported
settings resulted in a NoMatch.
With this release,
SHSession now supports PCM buffers
with most format settings,
sampled at a range of rates.
You can pass in these buffers
and SHSession will handle
the format conversion for you.
Finally,
if you have two or more bits of audio
that sound similar in a custom catalog,
ShazamKit can now return all the matches
from the custom catalog
when you pass in a query signature that
matches multiple reference signatures.
The matches are returned,
sorted by the best match quality
and you can filter for
the appropriate match result you want.
As a tip, properly annotate
the reference signatures
that sound similar
in their respective metadata,
so you can distinguish
between which result you want.
Here's an example
of how you can achieve this.
Say I have a television show where
every episode has the same intro sound.
I can generate a televisionShowCatalog
with reference signatures
representing each episode.
I can create a session using this catalog,
and when matching the intro section,
ShazamKit will return a match result
with mediaItems of each episode.
I can then filter through the mediaItems
and only return mediaItems
for a particular episode,
say Episode 2, for example.
This is how proper annotation helps.
Now that I've gone through
all the exciting updates this year,
I'll conclude by switching back
to my wonderful app
and attempt to learn one more dance.
I'll switch to my AirPods and play a song.
Since I am using Managed Session
in the app,
it can listen to the audio
playing in the AirPod
and find a dance video for me.
I'm going to press on the touch control
of my AirPods to play a song
and wait for the app to detect the audio.
Sweet!
Looks like Dancing Dave is showing off
a couple of Afrobeat moves,
which I'll try my best to learn
after this talk.
I hope you're as excited as we are
with these new updates.
Thank you for joining,
and have a great WWDC.
♪ ♪