♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi! I am Tricia Gray,
and I work on
the RealityKit Tools team.
Welcome to "Build great games
for spatial computing."
I am really excited
to talk to you today
about making games
for this new device.
Spatial computing
makes all sorts
of new game types possible.
It has unique rendering, audio,
and input characteristics.
You have several choices when
it comes to which frameworks
and tools you can use
to build games on it,
and that includes RealityKit.
But first, I'll give you an idea
of what types of games
are possible
on this new platform.
This is a standalone
spatial computing device.
It has high-resolution screens,
a wide field of view,
and a great refresh rate.
The Spatial Audio is amazing.
And there's LiDAR that tracks
both hand movements
and the shape of the room
around the player.
And players can stay connected
to their surroundings
using the device's
high-quality passthrough.
This has exciting possibilities
and lets you create
a wide variety
of different game types.
You can build games that span
a spectrum of immersion,
all depending on how much
of the player's attention
you want to capture.
All apps and games
start in the Shared Space.
This means that your game
can live in space together
with other games and apps
and the player's surroundings.
There might be a virtual
chessboard on the player's
actual desktop representing
an active game of chess,
or a virtual pet
sitting on the floor.
All of these apps live together,
and the player can interact
with whichever one they want.
You can put all attention
on your game
when you move into Full Space.
This closes all other
windows and volumes,
focusing the experience
on your content,
while still keeping the player
connected to their surroundings
through passthrough.
This might be suitable
for an action game --
something you're
actively playing
but that still interacts
with the real world.
You can have spaceships coming
through a hole in the wall,
for example.
A fully immersive experience
is when the game
takes over the whole view.
Instead of your room,
there's an environment
and you can no longer see
the real world.
Of course, you can also make
traditional 2D games.
They run in a virtual window,
and the player
can make that window
as big or as small as they want.
It doesn't even have to be
a vertical window,
it could be a flat surface
laying on the ground.
They could hang it on the wall
or put it on a desk,
or have it as the largest screen
they've ever had
right in front of their face.
Players can interact with your
game just as they would on iOS,
but instead of touching
the screen,
they'll look at an object
and tap their fingers together
to select it.
You can also connect
a Bluetooth controller
or a keyboard,
just as you can on iOS,
and the passthrough is helpful
here because you can look down
and see the controller
you are using.
You can also spice up a 2D game
by adding
some 3D elements to it.
For example,
your window has real depth,
so you can render your objects
in separate layers
and get a real parallax effect.
You can also have elements
that come out of the plane,
such as smoke or sparks.
Or you can add support
for custom hand gestures.
With all these options,
you have a lot to think about.
As you design your game,
think about
how you can take advantage
of these new opportunities
for gameplay experiences,
from having a giant
high-resolution screen
to having something personal
that you can play
in your own room.
Your game can appear
on the player's desk.
They can place it on the wall.
Something can fly out
and land in the player's hands.
You can make use
of the real world around them
or transport them into
an entirely different place.
Rendering, audio, and input
work differently on this device
than you might be used to
on other platforms.
When you're running
in a Shared Space,
the content from your game
is drawn together
with content from other apps,
system UI, and passthrough.
Since the rendering is shared,
the frameworks ensure that
all apps are good citizens
and their rendering doesn't
interfere with other apps.
In this mode,
you can use surface shaders
and geometry shaders
through MaterialX.
Rendering on xrOS
works a little differently
than you are used to.
Instead of rendering
every pixel,
you describe
what should be rendered --
all the models,
textures, and shaders --
and then the device renders it
automatically for each eye.
Another benefit of the platform
rendering for your game is that
it can apply dynamic foveation
to increase the resolution.
Dynamic foveation is
a technique where the renderer
uses higher resolution
at the part of the display
where the player's eyes
are looking.
This means you get crisper
resolution in those spots
without paying the cost
of rendering the whole scene,
all without having to do
any of the hard work.
By default, RealityKit renders
your objects in such a way
that they blend in realistically
with the real-world objects
around them.
RealityKit will sample
the actual lighting
in the player's room
and apply that same lighting
to the objects you render.
For materials,
RealityKit uses
a physically based lighting
model with typical parameters
such as roughness,
specular, and metallic.
This, together with
the sampled lighting,
gives you a realistic look.
But you can choose
where you want to be
on the scale
from realistic to fantastical.
Instead of using
the built-in PBR shader,
you can create customized
shader content using MaterialX
and edit the shader graph
in Reality Composer Pro
or other graphic packages.
You can also assign
custom IBLs to your object
for custom lighting effects.
Another consideration
is that there are
some systemwide effects that
get applied to rendered content.
The purpose of this is to make
your game work better
with other apps
and protect the player.
Depth mitigation makes your
content slightly transparent
when it's hidden behind objects
in a player's surroundings.
This gets rid of the feeling
that objects are floating
in the room.
Near-field vignetting
fades your content
when the player
gets too close to it.
This prevents issues
with your content
clipping against the near plane.
Breakthrough allows someone
who is approaching you
to break through
the rendered view,
so they don't run into you
without you noticing.
Finally, grounding shadows
are added to rendered objects
when they are placed
near real-world objects
to make them feel
more integrated into the scene.
Fully immersive rendering works
similar to shared rendering,
but in this case,
instead of sharing the screen
with passthrough and other apps,
your app
is the only thing visible.
In this mode,
you render an environment
that replaces the real-world
view around the player.
Rendering in this mode
works similar to rendering
in the shared mode.
You still describe the scene
and the device renders it.
But since you control
everything the player sees,
you have more freedom.
For example,
you don't have to use
the same lighting environment
as the room the player is in.
You can make the world as bright
or as dark as you want.
The strength of the device
lies in the shared mode,
but the fully immersive
experience is there
when you want to transport
the player to a different place.
If you'd like to write
your own engine,
the CompositorServices API
gives you access
to Metal rendering on xrOS.
You can combine it with ARKit,
which adds world tracking
and hand tracking to create
a fully immersive experience.
In this mode, you have
full access to the screen
and render the scene
for each eye.
You can use fully custom Metal
shaders and post processors.
This enables you to completely
replace real-world content
with your own virtual content.
Passthrough and other apps
are hidden.
For more information on this,
check out
"Discover Metal
for immersive apps."
Audio can be immersive too.
xrOS uses Spatial Audio
to bring objects to life
in the player's space,
automatically matching
the reverb and the real room
acoustics.
If you play audio using
standard iOS audio APIs
such as AVAudioEngine,
the audio will be positioned
relative to the app window.
If you want sound to come from
different objects in the scene
in the player's space,
you should play the audio
through RealityKit on
specific entities in your scene.
You also have the option
of doing your own audio
using any Apple or external API.
If you want the audio
to be head tracked,
you need to use ARKit to get
the player's head position.
In addition
to graphics and audio,
interaction is another key part
of an immersive experience.
After all,
every game needs input,
and this platform
offers multiple ways
to interact with the device.
You can get input events
on the objects in your scene
through SwiftUI as well as
other standard system gestures
such as dragging and magnifying.
This is based on
the physics collision.
To make the gestures
work on your objects,
they need to have both
a CollisionComponent,
which provides
the collision shape,
as well as an
InputTargetComponent,
which marks them
as interactable.
Spatial input can feel
pretty magical for players,
but you have other options
for game input too.
Even game controllers!
While system Look & Tap
gestures feel natural,
you only have one set of eyes
to look with
and only two hands
that can tap, pinch, or grab.
Some games
need more points of input.
One possibility is to use
a standard Bluetooth controller.
xrOS supports trackpads,
mice, and keyboards,
as well as Bluetooth-based
game controllers.
This can be a good option
for traditional games.
And xrOS also allows
for more unconventional input,
such as using your own body
as a controller.
You can use hand tracking
to let the player grab
virtual objects
or implement custom gestures,
such as pointing at an object
or karate chopping them.
You access hand tracking
through ARKit,
and the device will ask
the player for permission,
same as when an app
wants to use your location
or microphone.
There are some things
to consider
when designing this input.
Hands can only be tracked when
they are visible to the camera.
Really fast hand movements
can be hard to track.
Take that into account.
When you are working
in a Full Space,
you can request
scene understanding.
Scene understanding
provides a virtual mesh
representing the room
around the player.
It can also do plane detection
to find horizontal
and vertical surfaces.
You can also get the materials
of those surfaces,
whether it's carpet or wood.
This lets you use
the room itself
as part of the input
to your game.
Just as with hand tracking,
this requires permission
from the player.
With all the input options,
you have to figure out
what is right for your game.
Using the player's body
for direct input
is a great way of engaging them.
But holding your hands up
and doing gestures
is also something
that can get tiring over time.
If your game will be played
for long stretches of time
or require a lot
of quick actions,
think about how you can make use
of indirect gestures and gaze.
That way players
can rest their hands
comfortably on their lap,
and Look & Tap
instead of moving their hands.
The device is meant to be
something you use every day,
so comfort is important.
And if it makes sense,
you can also go
to a more traditional
game controller.
This platform supports all
the multiplayer and networking
capabilities you are familiar
with from other platforms.
Web-based networking, low-level
socket-based networking,
and Multipeer Connectivity
are all available to you.
SharePlay also makes it easy
for the player to socialize
in a more intimate way.
You can even build games
using networking
that allows some players
to play on iPhones or iPads
and still connect
to this great device.
Imagine a dominos game
with your friend
that has an iPad,
and they have a 2D experience
while you have a rich,
immersive 3D experience.
Now that you know
a little bit more about this
as a gaming device,
here are the frameworks
you can use to create games.
Depending on whether
you want to make a 2D game,
a game that lives in Volume,
or a fully immersive game,
there are different options
available to you,
such as using RealityKit,
our immersive framework,
or writing something directly
on top of Metal,
or even using Unity.
If you have already made
a game for iPhone or iPad,
in most cases, your game will
automatically run on the device
in a virtual window,
using Look & Tap to interact.
Note that this applies
to compatible 3D games too.
They will run in a flat window
on the device.
If you want your game
to be stereoscopic,
you must use
the spatial computing APIs.
Being able to run
compatible games is great,
but if you want to take full
advantage of the device,
build your game to target it.
That way you can use gestures
for input,
or add 2.5D elements such as
perspective or volumetric smoke.
You can build 2D games
for the device
using a 2D framework
such as SwiftUI or SpriteKit.
You can use Unity
to build games for xrOS.
This is a great option if you
already have a Unity game
that you want to port,
or if you are a Unity developer.
If you want to learn more about
using Unity, go to the sessions
"Bring your Unity VR app
to a fully immersive space"
or "Create immersive
Unity apps."
Finally,
there is RealityKit,
Apple's real-time
rendering framework
for building immersive
spatial experiences.
The API has
a lot of new features
to make it a great way
of creating 3D games for xrOS.
RealityKit supports
all the features you need
to make great games.
There is an entity component
system for custom behaviors,
and an extensibility
along with physics,
animation, particles,
and audio support.
On the rendering side,
RealityKit supports
both USD models
as well as custom meshes.
For grounding your objects
in the world,
there are MaterialX
and IBL lighting.
Attachments, a new feature
which allows you to connect
rich SwiftUI directly
to your RealityKit objects.
Using SwiftUI, you can mix
passthrough and rendered content
in various ways using features
such as Windows, Volumes,
Spaces, Anchors,
and Portals.
You can use system gestures
for input,
or you can use ARKit
to access hand tracking
and scene understanding.
To start building your game
for xrOS,
you create a new Xcode project
from the xrOS template.
This gives you a SwiftUI window
with a RealityView inside of it.
The RealityView
in the SwiftUI hierarchy
holds the 3D rendering
and simulation for your game.
If you're not familiar
with SwiftUI yet,
it is worth it to learn
a little bit about it.
By default, your 3D content
appears in a volumetric box
formed by the window.
Your content is confined
to that window
and will follow along
as it moves.
RealityKit is a Swift API.
Swift can be a great language
for building games,
but if you want to use
another language, you can.
You just create a bridge
between that language
and the Swift API.
Xcode comes with a Simulator.
You can start developing
your games right away
without having a device.
Of course, testing it
on a real device is always best.
Your 3D content will by default
be displayed
in a SwiftUI window.
One of the first things
you will want to do
as a game developer
is to break out of that window
and draw content
in the player's surroundings.
You have some different options
for doing that.
You can use a volume.
Volumes are similar to windows,
with one important difference.
With windows,
the player controls the size.
They can drag the corner
and make it as big
or as small as they like,
and your content has to adapt.
If the window is too small
for your content,
your content will be clipped.
With Volumes,
it's the other way around.
With Volumes, you say,
"I want the box to be this big,
this high, and this deep."
The player can
still put that box
wherever they want
in the world,
but the box will always
be the same size.
So you can make sure
that the box is big enough
to fit your entire experience,
and you can be sure
that the content doesn't clip.
If you don't want to use a box
at all, you can use a space.
This allows you to render
content all around the player
in the real world.
For example, you can surround
the player with buzzing bees.
There are different
kinds of spaces
corresponding
to the different game types.
You can use a Shared Space
to run together with other apps,
or a Full Space
if you want your game
to be the only thing running.
Anchors let you anchor
your scene to an object
in the real world and
follow it around as it moves.
You can use a horizontal
or a vertical surface anchor
to anchor the entity
to a desk or a wall.
There are also hand anchors
that let you anchor content
to the player's hands.
Portals allow you to punch
a hole in the player's reality
to create your own
fantastic reality.
You can anchor a portal
to a real wall
and have that portal
cut a hole in the wall
that lets you peek into a
rendered world inside the hole.
You can render whatever you want
inside that portal,
and the objects
inside the portal
can emerge
into the real world too.
RealityKit can load and render
USD files.
One of the easiest ways to get
started with volumetric content
is to assemble scenes
out of premade objects,
but for that, you need
some kind of visual tool.
Reality Composer Pro is a tool
that comes bundled with Xcode.
It lets you load USD models
and preview how they will look
on the device.
When you build your project
with Reality Composer Pro,
your assets are automatically
optimized for use on the device.
You can learn more about
Reality Composer Pro
in these sessions.
I hope this session
was a helpful
game-development roadmap
for spatial computing.
Be sure to take a deeper dive
in the multiple framework
sessions available.
This is a great platform
to socialize
and play games with others.
I can't wait to see
what you develop for it.
♪