♪ ♪
Aiswariya: Hello and welcome.
My name is Aiswariya,
and I'm very excited to talk to you
about bringing your game to the Mac.
This session is the first
in a three-part series
about how to bring
your high-end game to Mac.
In the second and third sessions,
my colleagues will focus on tools
and techniques for compiling your shaders
and best practices when rendering natively
with Metal.
You have everything you need
to deliver an amazing gaming experience
with Apple Silicon Mac’s
advanced graphics, fantastic performance,
immersive audio, stunning displays,
and feature-rich software.
With Macs more popular than ever before,
there’s never been a better time to bring
your games to millions of new players.
Porting your Windows game to the Mac
is now faster than ever.
This year, the new Game Porting Toolkit
provides an emulation environment
to run your existing,
unmodified Windows game,
and you can use it to quickly understand
the graphics feature usage
and performance potential of your game
when running on a Mac.
It doesn't take months to get a sense
of how your game looks, sounds, and plays.
You see your game’s potential right away.
Porting your Windows game to a whole new
platform typically involves many steps
before you even see
your first scene running,
including recompiling your source code;
converting thousands of custom shaders
from HLSL;
re-implementing your graphics subsystem;
and converting your use of audio,
input, display, and HDR rendering–
all before you can even see
your first scene running natively–
and then finally debugging and optimizing
for performance before you release it.
With the help of the Game Porting Toolkit,
you can now see your game's first scene
running on the platform much earlier.
The Game Porting Toolkit includes
a new Metal Shader Converter,
which you can use to automatically convert
all of your existing HLSL GPU shaders
to Metal.
With the Metal Shader Converter,
bringing your shaders and graphics
to Mac takes a lot less time too.
You can ship sooner
and still have more time
to take advantage of the unique features
of Mac and Apple silicon.
Seeing your game running right away
can even help you
when you use a cross-platform engine
to take care of most of your porting.
You can see your game's potential ahead
of porting any platform-specific code
or plug-ins that your Windows game added
over the cross-platform engine.
Porting your game to the Mac starts
with evaluating your game,
followed by compiling your shaders,
rendering with Metal,
converting your game’s use of input,
audio, and display and HDR rendering.
The first step is to use
the Game Porting Toolkit
to evaluate your game.
The environment
of the Game Porting Toolkit translates
your game’s Intel instructions
and its use of Windows APIs
for keyboard, mouse, and controller input;
for audio playback;
for networking and file system use;
and of course, for graphics.
All modern graphics features, such as
GPU-driven pipelines and SIMD operations,
and even older features,
such as tessellation and geometry shaders,
are translated.
Take a look at this in action.
Here’s how a developer like Bloober
might use the Game Porting Toolkit
to examine their Windows DirectX 12 build
of "The Medium."
"The Medium" is a recent game developed
and published by Bloober.
Their native Apple Silicon
and Metal release is an amazing,
beautiful, super fun game to play.
It’s also just a little bit scary,
delivering a highly immersive graphics
and audio experience for the player.
After installing the tool kit,
they copy a Windows build of "The Medium"
to their Mac
and launch it from a terminal.
As it launches in the Game Porting
Toolkit’s translation environment,
logging and debug information appears
in the terminal.
When you launch your game,
this logging may include
potential issues for you to address,
but things look clear here
for Bloober’s developers.
Take a look
in the Game Porting Toolkit documentation
to find details on what you might find
in the logging for your game.
Here the developer sees
that the gaming is running well
with all of its graphics features enabled,
and it's working as expected.
They’ll notice that features
like transparency,
reflection, geometry shaders,
tessellation,
and their unique and moody
global illumination approach to lighting
have all been translated into Metal 3
and look crisp and pixel-perfect.
The next step is to play for a little bit
to get a sense of baseline performance.
It’s worth noting that the baseline
performance you will observe
running your Windows game includes all
the overhead of the Game Porting Toolkit
as well as API
and instruction set translation.
In Bloober’s case, the Windows version
is of course not making use
of performance-enhancing features
like MetalFX upscaling.
When a non-native game runs
through these layers of translation,
its performance
and power efficiency may be affected.
Bringing your game natively to the Mac
will increase its performance
and allow you to take advantage
of many advanced features
of Apple silicon and Mac hardware,
including features like MetalFX
and extended dynamic range features
of Apple’s built-in displays.
A great workflow
for evaluating a game is to play it
with the Metal Performance HUD enabled
and to look for specific spots
that might warrant a deeper look.
The developers found a spot where the HUD
is showing occasional dropped frames
as well as much lower average frame rate.
They are then able to use Instruments
to capture a Metal System Trace.
This is a great way to investigate
performance issues.
The Metal Performance HUD
has been enhanced
when you are running
in the Game Porting Toolkit.
The standard portion
of the HUD is still at the top.
It shows information about the GPU
and resolution being rendered,
the instantaneous frame rate,
present-to-present interval,
and an approximation
of the amount of GPU time being used.
It highlights high and low values
of these statistics,
shows memory usage, and provides
a graph of the last few seconds of data.
Below, the HUD now shows deeper details
about instruction set translation
and which Direct3D API version
is being used,
how many render encoders are in use,
how many command buffers
and dispatches are happening,
and how many of each type of features,
such as geometry shaders
and tessellation shaders,
are being used each frame.
Additionally, resource copies
and clears are captured.
Here they open the trace file
in Instruments
and then browse to quickly find
where we see frame drops.
Here it is, an area where the GPU timeline
has huge gaps and little utilization
and there were several frames
where no work was scheduled at all.
After studying this,
it looks very likely to be caused
by the overhead of instruction translation
or differences caused by API translation.
These are just the kinds of problems
that will go away
when you bring your game to Mac natively.
You can be sure your game will have better
performance and run more efficiently.
Additionally, using best practices
for rendering in Metal
and adopting MetalFX upscaling will boost
your game’s performance even further.
Here is "The Medium’s" native version
running side by side
with the translated version, making more
optimal use of Metal 3 and Apple Silicon
for a dramatic improvement
in frame rate in this scene.
To get started
using the Game Porting Toolkit,
just head to developer.apple.com.
You’ll find a package
containing instructions
for building and configuring the tool kit
so you can begin evaluating your game.
You can provide your feedback,
questions, and suggestions
about the Game Porting Toolkit
and bringing your game to Mac
using Feedback Assistant.
Now that you’ve evaluated
your graphics features and performance
by running your existing Windows game,
take that knowledge
to port your shader pipeline.
You can use Metal Shader Converter tool
to convert all your game’s
advanced shading pipelines,
including geometry, tessellation,
mesh, and ray tracing stages.
Compiling your shaders is a deep topic
on its own, so when you’re ready,
watch the second talk in this series,
“Compile Your Shaders.”
It’s time to take a look
at rendering with Metal.
Metal 3 provides all of the advanced
graphics and compute features,
including MetalFX, fast resource loading,
offline compilation, mesh shaders,
and ray tracing,
used by modern high-end games,
which makes converting your graphics code
incredibly straightforward.
The third session in the series,
“Render with Metal,”
is about how to port your renderer
to Metal
and get great performance
out of Apple Silicon.
You evaluated your game’s basic input
features through the Game Porting Toolkit.
Now it's time to port it natively
and take advantage of advanced features
like rumble and haptics.
Your Windows game is either already built
over a cross-platform game engine
and making use of common input plug-ins,
or it’s making direct use of low-level
Windows APIs like XInput and GameInput,
or it may bundle a custom SDK
for game peripherals.
On Apple platforms, the Game Controller
framework provides your game
with thread-safe and low latency support
for game input across a wide variety
of peripherals,
such as game pads, keyboards, mice,
racing wheels, and arcade sticks.
You also have access to additional
capabilities of game controllers,
including haptics and motion.
Apple platforms provides
system-level user preferences support
for per-app input remapping,
as well as automatic support
for screenshots,
capturing video recordings,
and 15-second highlights of gameplay
right from a controller in any game.
It is easy to port
your game’s input logic.
When you’re ready to learn more,
these two prior talks,
“Tap into Virtual and Physical
Game Controllers”
and “Advancements in Game Controllers,”
are great places
to find details and sample code.
Audio is another key part
of a captivating game experience.
Bringing your existing game’s
audio workflow and features natively
to the Mac is quite straightforward.
Apple devices have state-of-the-art
built-in speakers
that your players can hear loud and clear
because there are no loud fans
drowning them out.
There are also many excellent wired
and wireless audio peripherals
compatible with Apple devices
which support low latency spatial audio.
Your existing game likely already uses
cross-platform audio middleware solutions
like Wwise, Unity, and FMOD.
These middleware products generally
abstract system audio APIs and frameworks.
On Windows, you may be using
middleware layers over lower-level APIs
like DirectSound, XAudio2, and WASAPI.
Those same middleware products exist
on Apple platforms.
These make use of a rich set of high
and low-level Apple audio frameworks
including Spatial Mixer Audio Unit,
PHASE, and AVAudioEngine.
Great news: you’ll find that all these
middleware products are well supported
with native Apple Silicon SDKs.
There is little or nothing
you will need to do.
But if you’re not using middleware,
of course you can use
the platform-provided audio frameworks
and APIs directly,
just like the middleware does.
In particular, to achieve
great spatial audio at this level,
check out the PHASE documentation
as well as the sample code
which demonstrates creating spatial audio
from a 12-channel, 7.1.4 PCM data
using AUSpatialMixer.
These previous talks about CoreAudio,
AudioUnits, and PHASE
are also great sessions to learn
about using low-level system frameworks
if your game is not based
on audio middleware.
Apple’s displays are an integral part
of providing your players
with a stunning and immersive
gaming experience.
With the Game Porting Toolkit, you can see
your game's rendering code running
over the basic standard dynamic range
and frame pacing APIs
of its translated environment.
On Windows, your game might be making use
of color management and tone mapping APIs
to achieve high dynamic range, such as
AdvancedColorInfo color space APIs.
And you might be using the timing
and feedback available in IDXGISwapChain
to pace your SDR and HDR content.
CAMetalLayer’s extended dynamic range
support gives you access
to even more advanced display features.
You can easily move your HDR
and tone mapping logic,
whether it’s based on floating-point
or 10-bit integer range,
or HDR10 or PQ10 shaders.
The CAMetalDisplayLink API gives you
fine-grained control
to achieve lowest input
and display latency for your game.
Check out these talks about adding
EDR support to your Metal rendering.
“Explore EDR on iOS” is a great talk
which recaps the pixel formats
and Metal APIs to use which are consistent
between macOS and iOS.
The “Explore HDR Rendering with EDR”
presentation offers a great foundation
for understanding how to make most
of EDR APIs and capabilities.
Apple Silicon Mac platforms have
all the software and hardware features
you need to bring your game to the Mac.
With the Game Porting Toolkit
and Metal Shader Converter,
bringing your game to the Mac
is easier than ever.
Be sure to keep going with part two,
“Compile Your Shaders,”
and part three, “Render with Metal.”
I can’t wait to play your games
on the Mac.
♪ ♪