♪ ♪
Grant: Hi, my name is Grant.
I’m an Engineer on the Accessibility Team.
Many people use speech synthesis
across Apple platforms
and some people rely on
synthesizer voices.
These voices are
a window into their devices.
Therefore, the voices they choose
are often a very personal choice.
People using speech synthesis on iOS can
already choose from many different voices.
Let’s take a look at how
you can provide even more.
First, we’ll talk about what
Speech Synthesis Markup Language is,
how it can bring immersive
speech output to your custom voices,
and why your speech provider
should adopt it.
Next, we’ll walk through how you can
implement a speech synthesis provider
to bring your synthesizer
and voice experiences across the device.
And finally,
we’ll dive into Personal Voice.
This is a new feature.
Now, people can record their voice
and then generate a synthesized voice
from those recordings.
So now, you can synthesize speech with
the user's own personal voice.
Let’s start by taking a look at SSML.
SSML is a W3C standard for
representing spoken text.
SSML Speech is represented declaratively
using XML format with various tags
and attributes.
You can use these tags to control
speech properties like rate and pitch.
SSML is used in first-party synthesizers.
This includes WebSpeech in WebKit
and is the standard input for
speech synthesizers.
Let’s take a look at how you can use SSML.
Take this example phrase
that has a pause in it.
We can represent this pause in SSML.
We’ll start with our "hello" string,
add our one second pause using an SSML
break tag,
and finish by speeding up
"nice to meet you!"
We do this by adding an SSML prosody tag
and setting the rate attribute to 200%.
Now we can take this SSML and create
an AVSpeechUtterance to speak with.
Next, let’s take a look at
how you can implement
your own speech synthesizer voices.
So what is a speech synthesizer?
A speech synthesizer receives some text
and information
about desired speech properties in
the form of SSML
and provides an audio representation of
that text.
Suppose you have a synthesizer with
great new voices
and you want to bring it to
iOS, macOS, and iPadOS.
Speech synthesis providers allow you
to implement
your own speech synthesizers and voices
into our platforms
to give even more personalization
to users beyond system voices.
Let’s see how this works.
Speech Synthesis provider audio unit
extensions will be embedded in a host app
and will receive speech requests
in the form of SSML.
The extension will be responsible for
rendering audio for the SSML input
and optionally returning markers
indicating where words occur
within those audio buffers.
The system will then manage
all playback for that speech request.
You don't need to handle
any audio session management;
it's managed internally by
the Speech Synthesis Provider framework.
Now that we understand
what a synthesizer is,
we can start to build
a speech synthesizer extension.
Let’s start by creating a new
Audio Unit Extension app project in Xcode,
then select the "Speech Synthesizer"
Audio Unit Type
and provide a four character subtype
identifier for your synthesizer,
as well as a four character identifier
for you as a manufacturer.
Audio unit extensions are
the core architecture
upon which speech synthesizer extensions
have been built.
They allow your synthesizer to run
in an extension process
instead of in your host app process.
Our app is going to provide
a simple interface
for buying and selecting a voice that
our extension will synthesize speech for.
We’ll start by creating a list view that
shows our available voices for purchase.
Each voice cell will show
the voice name and a buy button.
Next, I will populate my list
with some voices.
Here, WWDCVoice is a simple struct
holding the voice name and identifier.
We also need a state variable
for keeping track of purchased voices
and a new section to display them.
Next, let’s create a function
for purchasing a voice.
Here we can add the newly purchased voice
to our list
and update our UI accordingly.
Take note of
the AVSpeechSynthesisProviderVoice method
updateSpeechVoices.
That is how your app can signal that
the set of available voices
for your synthesizer has changed
and the system voice list
should be rebuilt.
In our example, we can make this call
after completing an in-app purchase
for a voice.
We also need a way to keep tabs
on which voices are available
in our speech synthesizer extension.
This can be done by creating
an instance of UserDefaults
that will be shared through an app group.
An app group will allow us to share
this voice list
between our host app and our extension.
We are explicitly specifying a suite name
that we provided when creating
the app group.
This ensures the host app and extension
read from the same domain.
Taking a look back at
the purchase function,
I have implemented a method to update
my user defaults
when a new voice is purchased.
AVSpeechSynthesizer also has new API
to listen for a change in
available system voices.
The set of system voices can change
when a user deletes a voice
or downloads a new one.
You can subscribe to
the availableVoicesDidChangeNotification
to update your list of voices
based on these changes.
Now that our host app is done,
let's fill in the audio unit,
which consists of four key components.
The first thing we’ll need to add is
some way to inform the system of
what voices our synthesizer will provide.
This is accomplished by overriding
the speechVoices getter
to provide a list of voices
and reading from our app group
UserDefaults domain we specified earlier.
For each item in our voice list,
we’ll construct a US English
AVSpeechSynthesisProviderVoice.
Next, we need some way for
the system to tell the synthesizer
what text to synthesize.
The synthesizeSpeechRequest method
will be called
when the system wants to signal to
an extension
that it should start synthesizing
some text.
The argument to this method will be
an instance of
AVSpeechSynthesisProviderRequest
containing SSML
and which voice to speak with.
Next, I’ll call a helper method
I’ve created
in my speech engine implementation.
In this example, my getAudioBuffer method
will generate audio data
based on the voice specified in
the request and the SSML input.
We’ll also set an instance variable,
called framePosition, to 0
in order to keep track of how many frames
we’ve rendered
as the render block is called
and we copy frames out of the buffer.
The system also needs a way to signal to
a synthesizer to stop synthesizing audio
and discard the current speech request.
This is accomplished with
cancelSpeechRequest,
where we will simply discard
the current buffer.
Finally, we need to implement
the render block.
The render block is called by the system
with a desired frameCount.
The audio unit is then responsible for
filling the requested number of frames
into the outputAudioBuffer.
Next, we will set ourselves up
with a reference to the target buffer
and the buffer we generated
and stored earlier
during the synthesizeSpeechRequest call.
Then, we’ll copy the frames
into the target buffer.
And then finally, once the audio unit has
exhausted all the buffers
for the current speech request,
the actionFlags argument should be set to
offlineUnitRenderAction_Complete
to signal to the system that rendering has
completed
and there are no more audio buffers
to be rendered.
Let's see it in action!
This is my speech synthesizer app.
I will purchase a voice and navigate to
a view where I can synthesize speech
using my new voice and speech engine.
First, I will give the synthesizer
an input of "hello."
Synthesized voice: Hello.
Grant: Then I’ll give the input "goodbye."
Synthesized voice: Goodbye.
Grant: We’ve now implemented
a synthesis provider
and created a hosting app that provides
voices you can use across the system,
from VoiceOver to your own apps!
We can't wait to see what new voices
and text-to-speech experiences you craft
using these APIs.
Let’s move on and talk about
a new feature called Personal Voice.
People can now record and
recreate their voice on iOS and macOS
using the power of their device.
Your Personal Voice is generated
on the device and not on a server.
This voice will appear amongst
the rest of the System voices
and can be used with
a new feature called Live Speech.
Live Speech is a type-to-speak feature
on iOS, iPadOS, macOS, and watchOS
that lets a person synthesize speech with
their own voice on the fly.
You can request access to synthesize
speech with these voices
using a new request authorization API
for Personal Voice.
Keep in mind that usage of
Personal Voice is sensitive
and should be primarily used
for augmentative
or alternative communication apps.
Let’s checkout an AAC app
I’ve made to use Personal Voice.
My app has two buttons
that will speak common phrases
I find myself saying at WWDC
and a button for requesting access
to use Personal Voice.
Authorization can be requested
with a new API
called requestPersonalVoiceAuthorization
on AVSpeechSynthesizer.
Once authorized, Personal Voices will
appear alongside System voices
in the AVSpeechSynthesisVoice API
speechVoices
and will be denoted with a new voiceTrait
called isPersonalVoice.
Now that I have access to Personal Voice,
I can use it to speak with.
Let’s check out a demo of
Personal Voice in action.
First, I’ll tap the “Use Personal Voice”
button to request authorization,
and once authorized,
I can tap a symbol to hear my voice.
Personal voice: Hi, my name is Grant.
Welcome to WWDC23.
Grant: Isn’t that amazing?
And now you can use these voices
in your apps, too.
Now that we discussed SSML,
you should use it to
standardize speech input
and build a rich speech experience
in your apps.
We also walked through
how to implement your Speech Synthesizer
into Apple platforms, so now you can
provide great new speech voices
that people can use across the system.
And finally, with Personal Voice,
you can bring even more of a personal
touch to synthesis in your apps,
especially for people who may be
at risk of losing their own voice.
We are super excited to see what
experiences you create using these APIs.
Thanks for watching.