♪ ♪
Nivash: Hello, everyone.
I’m Nivash Raaja Karukankaatur Murugasamy,
an Engineer in
Core Location Frameworks team.
Welcome to my talk on
Core Location Monitor.
I’m really excited to talk about
our new CLMonitor API.
It enables you to write simple
yet powerful monitoring logic
with just few lines of code in Swift.
You just create a monitor,
add conditions, and await events.
There it is.
Hello, CLMonitor!
Let’s go into the details of
CLMonitor API.
I will begin with an overview
of the CLMonitor API,
our new simple yet powerful way to
monitor for user’s location or beacons.
Then, I’ll tell you about the types
of conditions you can monitor
and how you can add or remove them.
Then, I will go over monitoring records,
what they contain, and how you can
access them during your app’s lifecycle.
Followed by the steps you will need to
take in your app
if any of the monitored conditions
encounter an event.
And finally, I’ll wrap up with
some requirements and recommendations
that will help you when using CLMonitor.
First, let’s take a look at
what a monitor is
and how you can create one for monitoring.
CLMonitor is a top level Swift actor
and each CLMonitor instance acts as
a gateway to monitoring.
As it is an actor, it relieves you from
the overhead of thread
and task synchronization.
So accessing the contents of CLMonitor or
adding or removing a condition at any time
just needs to be awaited.
To create a monitor,
you call the monitor’s init method
with an alpha-numeric string.
If there is no prior monitor existing with
that name, a new one will be created.
Otherwise, the existing one
will be opened.
Either way, the monitor instance
will be returned.
Note that only one instance with
a given name can be open at any moment.
The entity that is being monitored is
called a condition.
You can add a condition to
a CLMonitor instance for monitoring
and associate it with an identifier
using the add method.
The identifier is an alphanumeric string.
For instance, "Work" in this example
uniquely identifies
the record of a condition that is
satisfied when the user is at work.
The record object and its contents
will be accessible by this identifier
and the condition will be monitored
until it is removed.
You can remove the condition
from monitoring by calling remove
with the same identifier.
Removing a condition
removes the corresponding record as well.
Now that you know
how to create a monitor instance
and how it relates to conditions,
let’s take a look at the types of
conditions available,
and how you can create one
and add it for monitoring.
There are two types of conditions
supported in iOS.
First, CircularGeographicCondition.
A circular geographic condition is defined
by a center and a radius.
The center defines the geographical
location of the condition.
The radius defines the area
under which the condition
will be considered satisfied.
Anywhere outside of that area,
we will report the condition
as unsatisfied.
This is similar to CLCircularRegion in
iOS 16 and prior releases.
You define a center by constructing
a CLLocationCoordinate2D
with the latitude
and longitude of interest.
Then you create
the CircularGeographicCondition
with that center
and the radius of interest.
The other type of condition supported
in iOS is BeaconIdentityCondition.
BeaconIdentityCondition is similar to
CLBeaconIdentityConstraint
or CLBeaconRegion that you may have used
in iOS 16 and earlier releases.
If your company has multiple sites
at different locations,
you can deploy beacons to detect
in your app
if the user is at any one of your sites, or
at a specific site,
or even at a specific section of
a specific site.
Consider Apple’s cafeterias as
a simple example,
available in offices at multiple sites.
Let's see how beacons could be
deployed effectively
to enable location based behavior in
an associated app.
And as we go, I will talk about how that
app can monitor for these beacons
by using different flavors of
BeaconIdentityCondition
under different situations.
Let's take a brief look at
what defines a beacon.
It contains a UUID string,
a major number, and a minor number.
With BeaconIdentityCondition,
you can monitor for a specific beacon
by specifying all three:
UUID, major, and minor.
Or you can wildcard to match
any single beacon
from a group of beacons by specifying
just UUID and major, or just UUID alone.
When you leave the minor
or the major and minor unspecified,
a beacon with any values for
those properties could match.
Let see how we can use this
in our example.
We could deploy beacons at these cafeteria
sites with all having the same UUID.
And, in the app,
a BeaconIdentityCondition could be created
to monitor for this UUID.
Then, if a user nears
one of these beacons,
the condition will become satisfied.
Otherwise,
it will be determined as unsatisfied.
In code, you can do this
by calling the init method
that specifies only the UUID.
Now that we have deployed beacons
at the required locations,
you might be interested to detect
if a user is at one of the specific sites.
In this case, let's see how to monitor
whether a user is at the Apple Park site.
To achieve this, the beacons deployed at
each site
will have to share a unique major number.
Then, in your app, you can monitor for
a BeaconIdentityCondition
with that major and the overall UUID.
The condition’s state will be determined
as satisfied
only when the device is at that site
where the beacons match both UUID
and major values.
It will remain unsatisfied at other sites.
In code, you can create
a BeaconIdentityCondition
by calling the init method that specifies
only UUID and major.
Now you know how to monitor for all sites
or a specific site.
But you can also monitor for a specific
section within a specific site as well.
This can be achieved by deploying beacons
at different locations--
say, cuisine stations--
within each site with
corresponding minor values.
In your app, you can monitor for
a BeaconIdentityCondition
for a specific minor value
along with UUID and major.
Such a condition would become satisfied
only when the beacon with that minor
as well as the overall UUID
and major is detected.
In code, this means
creating a BeaconIdentityCondition
by passing in the UUID, major, and minor.
When creating a BeaconIdentityCondition,
use the init method that suits your need.
OK, now that you know how to create
different types and flavors of condition,
let’s take a look at how you can add them
for monitoring.
You can add a condition for monitoring by
calling the add method
with an alphanumeric string called
identifier on your CLMonitor instance.
The condition would be associated with
the identifier.
If a condition is already being monitored
with the given identifier,
it will be replaced with the new condition
that is passed in.
When you add a condition,
it's initial state will be unknown
until determined by Core Location.
There might be instances where
you are aware of the current state of
the condition before you add it.
In those cases, you can override
the default initial state
by passing the state
when adding for monitoring.
In this example, let’s assume that
your app deduces that
you’re not at Apple Park site and so
expects the condition to be unsatisfied.
You can add "assuming: .unsatisfied"
to your call.
Then, monitoring will begin with state
set to unsatisfied.
But not to worry.
If your assumption of the state is wrong,
Core Location will give you
the correct state once it is determined.
To remove a condition from monitoring, you
can call the remove method
with the identifier that was passed
when the condition was added.
Now you know what a condition is,
what types are supported,
and how to add or remove one
from monitoring.
Let’s take a detailed look at
the contents of a record
and how you can get a record
or all the records in a monitor
to inspect at any time.
If you can recall from the earlier slide,
when you add a condition for monitoring,
Core Location creates a record
and adds the condition in that record.
In addition to the condition, a record
contains another object called event.
The event contains the state
representing the current observed state
of the condition,
whether satisfied, unsatisfied,
or unknown,
and the date and time at which
the condition encountered the state.
now you might wonder why there is another
instance of condition in the event.
This is called the refinement.
What is it for?
If you can recall from
BeaconIdentityCondition,
your app can monitor just for UUID ,
or UUID and major,
or UUID along with major and minor.
If a condition with major and minor
wildcarded becomes satisfied,
that event will be delivered with
the refinement populated.
That refinement condition will carry
the UUID
but also the major and minor information
of the observed beacon.
Then, once the condition becomes
unsatisfied,
the refinement will be reset to nil.
There can be multiple instance of record
with each record uniquely addressed
by the identifier passed in
when the condition was added.
All the records of your monitors,
associating conditions with
lastEvents and identifiers,
are stored with your app.
This enables you to query conditions and
their corresponding states
as last observed at any time.
Let’s see what that looks like in code.
To retrieve a record associated with
a condition,
you can call the record method
with its identifier.
If no condition is being monitored with
the identifier you passed,
nil will be returned.
You can then get the underlying
monitored condition
by accessing the condition property.
And you can get the lastEvent delivered
to your app for that condition
by accessing the lastEvent property.
Then, from the event, you can get
the most recently observed state,
date, and refinement.
Now you know how to retrieve one record.
How do you get all the monitoring records?
Do you need to keep track of
all the identifiers?
Well, you don’t have to.
We maintain the list for you in
the identifiers property on your monitor.
You can easily iterate over it
to retrieve each record and its contents.
Now that you know how to access
the contents of a record,
let’s see how to consume events
as changes occur.
The code to receive an event
can be implemented
using a simple loop wrapped in a Task.
When Core Location observes a state
for a monitored condition
which differs from the state reported in
the lastEvent,
then Core Location will deliver a new
event
through the events async sequence property
on your monitor
which resumes the awaiting loop.
The event object delivered brings you
the new state
and the identifier of
the condition affected.
Or, while processing the new event,
you can also use the identifier
to get the record and
the lastEvent for that condition.
We can use that information to get more
context on what has happened now.
There it is!
Our simple greeter program is complete.
Now that you know how CLMonitor works,
I have some advice on how to use it best.
Let's begin with three key requirements.
First, you can have multiple monitors
with different names
to separate handling of
different conditions,
but you must instantiate only one at time
for a given name.
Because CLMonitor maintains the state of
the conditions that it is monitoring,
trying to initialize another one
with the same name
could result in undesired behavior.
Second, because events can arrive
unpredictably,
it's best to always have a Task awaiting
on your monitor’s events sequence.
An event can only become the lastEvent
of some record after you have handled it.
So, if a condition changes state
while you’re not awaiting events,
your monitor will not reflect
the new state until you do.
Finally, if your app has been terminated,
when any monitored conditions encounter
an event,
Core Location will launch your app in the
background
as long as it is authorized
to receive user location.
That means your app needs to
reinit monitor
and await events whenever it is launched
if it remains interested in the state
of conditions it is monitoring.
One way to do this is by listening to
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions
app delegate callback.
As the new API results in
launching behavior,
I strongly recommend using CLMonitor
only from your app.
Using it in widgets or plug-ins
will launch your app instead,
and complicate ensuring that only one
monitor exists for a given name at a time.
Finally, I mentioned this earlier:
conditions and their states persist,
and events are generated when
CLMonitor observes a change of state
in one of the conditions it is monitoring,
so I strongly recommend looking at those
states as CLMonitor represents them
rather than maintaining them
in your own table
then get out of sync with arriving events.
That said, some applications,
such as SwiftUI visualization,
may require a separate representation
be kept.
If you need to do that,
reserve that representation for SwiftUI
and don’t use it to reason about
expected events.
So that’s CLMonitor!
I’m really excited about our new API.
Try it out!
We hope it will greatly improve
your monitoring experience.
We would love to hear your feedback.
We also have a sample app
that demonstrates CLMonitor in action.
It is available in the resources section
of this video.
Download it and give it a try.
Finally, checkout the session by
my colleague Siraj on location updates.
Thanks for watching!