♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Jeremy,
and I'm a media experience
software engineer.
This talk will explain
how to create
a great spatial experience
for video playback in your app.
A great experience
is optimized for the platform,
takes advantage of its powerful
media capabilities,
and integrates
with the whole system.
First, we'll explore
the media experience
with a minimal app.
Next, I'll go over some more
advanced UI features.
Then, I'll go over some other
methods of displaying video.
Finally, I'll compare
the options.
If you have used
the media APIs on iOS or tvOS,
then this may feel familiar.
This platform builds
on those same APIs
and extends them
for its unique capabilities.
AVFoundation handles
all the work of playing movies:
streaming, parsing,
decoding, synchronizing.
And AVKit builds on AVFoundation
and UI Frameworks,
to create a playback experience
that's customized
and integrated
for each platform.
On this platform,
AVFoundation has been enhanced
to support new media formats
that take advantage
of its unique capabilities,
such as 3D video.
Refer to this session for more
details about these formats.
AVFoundation has also been
enhanced to render performantly
and with high quality
using RealityKit,
so that video can be
composited seamlessly
into the world around you,
and so that audio also responds
to the world around you.
And AVKit's
AVPlayerViewController
has been extended to make use
of the power of RealityKit
and the unique capabilities
of the platform
to create a highly refined
experience.
This includes all the playback
controls you expect,
but also has many
unique capabilities.
What's required to take
advantage of this in your app?
First, the Xcode target must
build with this platform's SDK.
Compatible iOS apps
built with the iOS SDK
will get an iOS compatible
experience.
Use AVPlayerViewController
just like you do
on iOS or tvOS.
And finally,
present the view controller
so it fills the window.
Let's demonstrate this
with some code.
First, we'll import
AVFoundation and AVKit.
Next, create an
AVPlayerViewController
and connect an AVPlayer to it.
Then, create a new player item
with the content URL
and set it on the player.
Adding the item
after setting the player
on the view controller
can improve performance
because the player
will understand
how it will be displayed before
it starts loading the media.
Then, to use it in SwiftUI,
wrap that code in a
UIViewControllerRepresentable.
We'll call this one PlayerView.
Then, we'll create our app,
which we'll call
MoviePlayingApp.
Add the view controller,
which we just defined,
so it fills the window.
Just like that,
you've got a movie playing app.
If you're thinking this code
looks very similar
to what you would write
on other Apple platforms,
that's because it is.
AVPlayerViewController
and AVPlayer are doing
a lot of the heavy lifting
so you don't have to.
Let me show you
the media experience
a simple app like this has.
Before the app is launched,
just the room is visible.
When the app launches,
a large screen appears
right in front
and the room darkens,
creating a nice ambiance.
When moving,
the screen stays in place,
and the audio stays
anchored to the screen.
To show playback controls,
look at the screen and tap.
The controls float
just in front of the video.
While playing,
do nothing and they will
disappear on their own.
Or make them disappear
by looking at the screen
and tapping again.
Grab the window bar
below the screen
to reposition it.
Grab the corner of the screen
to resize.
Notice that
as the screen resizes,
it animates smoothly and matches
the aspect ratio of the video.
Adjust the volume
by turning the Digital Crown.
Or use the Digital Crown to
open an environment, like this.
I love watching movies this way.
You've got to experience
this for yourself.
Now, let's examine the playback
controls more closely
to see the features
they provide.
Here is our player interface.
At the top right
is the volume control
to make quick adjustments
or to mute.
As I mentioned,
volume can also be adjusted
with the Digital Crown.
At the bottom left
are the familiar play/pause
and back/forward buttons.
In the bottom middle
is the scrubber
to jump to a different time
in the movie.
And in the bottom right
is this button
with more options.
Here are options to adjust
the playback speed.
When movies contain multiple
audio tracks or caption tracks,
use these options
to choose the language
for the audio track,
or to enable captions
in the preferred language.
This last option
is Dimming Effect.
I love watching movies
in the dark
to really focus on them,
but sometimes a video
isn't my only focus.
Here, I can turn off
Dimming Effect
to better see what's around me.
We've covered the basics
that are built in.
Now, let's explore some more
advanced features.
Thumbnail scrubbing
shows a small image
of the video while scrubbing,
allowing seamless navigation
of the content.
The controls will automatically
display a thumbnail
when scrubbing for HLS streams
that have an I-frame only
playlist,
also known as
a Trick Play track.
Small Trick Play tracks
with a width of 145 pixels
are preferred.
Refer to this document
for more details.
Sometimes media needs to be
inserted into the timeline
for a logo, a recap, or an ad.
Interstitials support
enables this ability.
When interstitials are present,
the controls will automatically
reflect them
with an indicator
in the timeline.
These interstitials can be
configured programmatically
with an AVPlayerInterstital
EventController,
or they can be described
within the HLS stream.
Refer to this session
for more details.
There are some
additional UI options
commonly used
by video playing apps.
Contextual actions allow you
to add buttons like
Skip intro
or Play next episode.
They can have a title
and an optional image.
Custom info view controllers
can be used
to show metadata
about the content
or to suggest related content.
These APIs work the same
as on other Apple platforms.
Refer to this session
for more details.
Your app can also transport you
to another place
with a feature called
Immersive Spaces.
When your app creates
an Immersive Space,
you get to decide
what that space looks like.
And even better,
your video screen
will automatically
move into that space
and anchor itself at
a predictable size and position
to guarantee an excellent
viewing angle every time.
And the controls detach
and move closer
to make them easier
to interact with.
Let's check out some code.
Here is our MoviePlayingApp
from earlier.
First, we'll add
an Immersive Space.
The 3D content
will be described
by RealityKit entities.
Then we'll use onAppear
on our PlayerView
to open the space.
Make sure your Immersive Space
is designed to accommodate
the movie player
when it's docked.
For more information
about how to build
and present spaces,
refer to this session.
AVPlayerViewController
has been thoroughly refined
and designed for a great
experience on this platform.
We really want
AVPlayerViewController
to work for you.
So, if there are features or
behaviors you'd like to suggest,
please provide feedback
so we can continue
to improve it
for your use cases.
Now, there could still be
rare situations
where someone needs to build
custom playback controls.
In that case,
please provide feedback.
And we recommend
you use AVPlayerViewController.
You can hide the controls
and supply an overlay
for your custom UI.
This is preferred over using
a lower-level API because,
as we've demonstrated,
AVPlayerViewController
provides a lot
of system integration features
beyond just playback controls.
And you'll continue to get great
system integration features.
We've explored
AVPlayerViewController's
fullscreen experience.
Now let's look at some other
use cases for video playback.
Sometimes you want a movie
to play inline in a window.
It could be part of a document
or to play a preview.
AVPlayerViewController inline
is great for this situation too.
How do you get the inline view?
It will automatically
use this mode
whenever it's displayed
without filling the window.
Its inline controls are also
redesigned for the OS.
Note, because video is
composited within the window
using AVPlayerLayer,
it won't be able to display
3D video.
Sometimes your app
may want to play video
as an entity of a 3D scene.
It could be a splash screen
or a video transition.
In these cases, you don't want
playback controls
and you also don't want
system integration like docking.
For those cases,
use RealityKit's
VideoPlayerComponent.
VideoPlayerComponent
connects a RealityKit Entity
to an AVPlayer.
You can position it
in your RealityKit scene
just like any other entity.
It creates an aspect ratio
correct mesh for the video,
and it supports
displaying captions.
Whenever possible,
prefer it over AVPlayerLayer.
Because it takes advantage
of RealityKit's optimizations
for video, it gets better
performance than AVPlayerLayer,
and it supports
new 3D video formats.
Refer to this session
for more details.
Sometimes you may want
to use video in a 3D scene
where the video
is used as an effect.
In this case, you may want
to create your own geometry
and have more control
over how the video is displayed.
VideoMaterial
is a lower-level API
that will display video
on arbitrary geometry.
This means it can't ensure
the original aspect ratio
and it doesn't have the ability
to display captions.
Check out this related talk
for more details.
We've talked about some
additional UI features
and some other use cases.
The DestinationVideo sample app
demonstrates
some of these features.
It has a video browser
for choosing videos
and plays them
in an Immersive Space.
Here it is.
Choose a video
to show the info page
and an Immersive Space opens.
Notice the use of an inline
player with custom UI controls
for the preview.
Then, play the movie.
The player UI appears
and immediately docks
into the Immersive Space
at a fixed size and location
for optimal viewing.
Another nice detail is that
when the screen is docked
in an Immersive Space like this,
the playback controls detach
and come a little closer
to make them more convenient
to interact with.
Tap the list button.
The app has supplied
custom info view controllers
to display more info
about the content
and related content
while watching the video.
Near the end of the video,
a contextual action button
labeled Play Next
appears in the
bottom-right corner.
We've covered the spatial
experience for video playback.
It has a large screen floating
in space in front of you
with beautiful visuals
and great spatial audio.
It includes playback controls
for everything you need to do,
and we've talked about some
other playback use cases.
There are several ways
to display video in your app.
Let's compare them.
These are the APIs
to show video.
Each has different
capabilities.
Use the correct API for
the media experience you need.
Make sure your media
is displayed accurately
and is accessible.
Make sure it's optimized
for the platform
and enables 3D video formats
by rendering with RealityKit.
And make sure it has
powerful playback controls
tuned for the platform.
And make sure it's integrated
with the whole system
to get a great experience.
AVPlayerViewController
will allow your app
to take full advantage
of features you've been using
in other Apple platforms
and the new, unique features
of this platform.
You can deliver a great
movie playback experience
for your users.
Spatial media capabilities
represent an opportunity
for people to experience video
in a whole new way.
To get started, check out
DestinationVideo Sample Project.
It demonstrates many of
the features discussed here.
And check out these
related talks.
I can't wait for people
to see what you make
with these powerful tools.
But now, I've got to get back
to watching a show.
Enjoy!
[CRUNCHING]
♪