♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi, and welcome to "What's new
in App Store Connect."
I'm Laurel McAndrews from
App Store Connect Engineering.
Today, I'll walk through
the developer lifecycle
in App Store Connect,
and I'll call out
some enhancements
we're making this year.
I'll begin with some ways to
think about monetizing your app,
implementing in-app purchases,
and how to set prices
internationally.
Then, I'll review
how to manage testers
and some of the improvements
we've made
to managing builds and testers.
I'll cover getting ready
for going live on the App Store,
and ways to build excitement
for your app.
Last, I'll walk through ways
to use the App Store Connect API
to speed up your release cycle
and customize workflows.
First, let's talk about
monetizing your app.
As you're working on your app,
you'll consider
whether to include in-app
purchases and how to set prices.
Whether you're a solo developer
doing everything yourself,
or a large company
with a dedicated pricing team,
there are features this year
to help you run your business
on the App Store.
For example, StoreKit
for SwiftUI is a new capability
that allows you to quickly and
easily offer in-app purchases
and subscriptions in your app.
After you set up products
in App Store Connect,
you can go into Xcode and add
a few lines of code
to generate views in your app
to offer in-app purchases.
These pages are fully accessible
and localize
your project strings
into all App Store languages.
You can choose
the simplest implementation
of StoreKit for SwiftUI.
Or you can customize elements
like backgrounds, buttons,
and styles to achieve a design
that is seamless with your app.
If you promote your in-app
purchases on the App Store,
you even have the option to use
the App Store promotion image
in the product view in your app.
This icon will appear alongside
the in-app purchase in your app.
If you offer in-app purchases
or if you choose to offer
a paid app, you will need
to consider how to set prices
and how they will translate
to international markets.
This spring, we upgraded
our pricing capabilities,
making it easier
to manage the prices of apps,
in-app purchases,
and subscriptions.
This update allows you
to choose from 900 price points
to give you flexibility
on the pricing of your app;
set a base region,
which is the ability to choose
one region to automatically
generate prices
across other regions
and currencies;
manage international pricing,
which allows the App Store
to adjust your prices
as currencies or taxes change
or manage them manually
on your own;
and set the availability
of in-app purchases
and subscriptions by region.
To begin implementing
StoreKit for SwiftUI,
visit
"Meet StoreKit for SwiftUI."
To go in-depth
on this year's pricing changes
as well as
the new pricing endpoints
in the App Store Connect API,
visit "What's new
in App Store pricing."
Next up, let's talk about ways
to manage testers for your app.
Once you have an idea
of how to monetize your app,
you'll start thinking about
who your testers will be
and how you'll test changes
before releasing.
TestFlight makes it easy
to test your prerelease builds
on iOS, watchOS, tvOS,
macOS, and now xrOS.
This year, we're making it
easier to manage testers,
builds, and test different
use cases in your app.
We want to help you
get the right builds
to the right testers and ensure
you can test scenarios
that users will encounter when
you release on the App Store.
TestFlight provides data
about your testers
to help you understand
how engaged they are.
This data includes a status,
which tells whether a tester
has been invited,
if they've accepted,
or if they've installed a build,
the number of sessions
the tester has had,
the number of crashes,
and amount of TestFlight
feedback they have provided.
We're adding an additional
column for devices
which will show the most recent
device and OS
on which the beta app
was installed.
We're also adding the ability
to filter by tester data
in order to view and manage
segments of testers.
You will be able to bulk select
groups of testers
in order to resend invitations,
add to a group,
or remove testers altogether.
And all of this data
will be available
through
the App Store Connect API.
Once you're able to easily
manage your testers,
you may want to put release
controls in place to make sure
you're sending the right builds
to the right people.
When distributing a build
from Xcode,
you may have a build
like a prototype
that you never want to go
outside of your internal team.
For this, we're adding
a TestFlight Internal Only
selection to the new
distribution workflow in Xcode.
When you make this selection,
it will ensure that these builds
can't be released
for External TestFlight
and can't be submitted
for App Store review.
In App Store Connect, these
builds will be clearly marked
so you can easily see which
builds can be distributed where.
If you have
a good group of testers
and the right builds
going to the right places,
you also need to tell testers
what you want them to check out
in your app.
Xcode Cloud will make
this process even easier
with the ability to upload
TestFlight What to Test
information alongside a build.
To do this,
you have a few options.
You can add a plain text file
to a TestFlight folder
located in the same folder as
your Xcode project or workspace.
This file will itemize
the things
you want testers to check out.
Or you pull from commit messages
with a custom build script.
This information will be passed
to App Store Connect
and will be distributed
to your testers
when you're ready
to start testing your build.
Now that you've optimized
your build and tester management
in TestFlight,
let's talk about
some new features
in sandbox testing.
Family Sharing allows
your customers to share
your subscriptions
and in-app purchases
with their Family Group.
To enable you to test
this feature before you release,
we are adding the ability
to combine sandbox test accounts
into a Family Group.
Just like Family Sharing
in the App Store,
you can group up to six
test accounts into a family.
You will be able to configure
these accounts
in App Store Connect.
This year, we're adding
the following sandbox
on-device enhancements on iOS.
View Family Group members
and select to stop sharing
an autorenewable subscription
or nonconsumable with a family.
Modify the renewal rate
of a subscription.
Test interrupted purchases,
and clear purchase history
right on the test device.
To expand on
these testing topics,
discover the new streamlined
distribution in Xcode as well as
new support for notarization
in Xcode Cloud in the session
"Simplify distribution
in Xcode and Xcode Cloud."
Explore how to use
StoreKit testing in Xcode,
sandbox testing,
and TestFlight in the session
"Explore testing
in-app purchases."
After you have your app tested,
you'll think about
how to represent your app
on the App Store.
Let's cover some ways
to build your store presence.
Your product page
is where you tell customers
about the features in your app.
App Store Connect helps you
configure your product page,
get customers excited,
and acquire customers.
App Store privacy
nutrition labels
summarize your data practices
in a simple, easy-to-read label
so that customers
can make an informed decision
when downloading your app.
When answering app privacy
questions in App Store Connect,
you need to indicate
in the data collection section
the types of data
you collect from customers.
With the introduction of xrOS,
we are adding
a few new data types.
You should select
Environment Scanning
if you collect data on a user's
surroundings,
Hands if collect hand structure
or movements,
or Head if you collect
head movement.
For example, if your app
teaches users how to play piano
and collects data
on the movement of their hands
in order to instruct them,
you should select
the Hands data type
for data collection.
These new data types
will be especially relevant
for xrOS apps, but could apply
on other platforms.
For example,
these would apply to you
if you use ARKit on iOS
and collect these types of data.
These new data types will appear
on the xrOS App Store
and all other platforms
where your app is released.
After you've inputted your
answers to privacy questions,
you can start thinking
of when you'll release your app
and how you'll present yourself
to customers.
Now let's talk about pre-orders.
Releasing your app for pre-order
can be a powerful way
to build awareness
and excitement
for your upcoming app release.
This year, we're giving you
the flexibility
to use pre-orders
on a regional basis.
This means you can start
by launching your app
to a limited set of regions,
often referred to
as a soft launch,
and also offer your app
for pre-order in other regions.
We're making this possible with
a redesigned availability page,
where you can manage your app's
state across regions.
You'll be able to launch
your app and tune your design
and functionality before using
pre-order in new markets.
Whether your app is available
for pre-order or download,
you might want to think about
which metadata is right
to display
on your product page.
For this you can use
product page optimization.
Product page optimization
gives you insight
into which product pages
your users like best.
This year, we're making
a change so that tests
will continue to run until
you choose to stop them,
and won't be affected
by new versions.
You will be able to view and
monitor a currently running test
while pushing updates
to your app as needed.
Keep in mind that a test
is meant to compare treatments
against your control,
so any changes to a product page
with a new version could impact
the results of a running test.
To continue building
your store presence,
here are some other sessions.
To get your app ready for xrOS
outside of our new
data collection options,
visit "Explore App Store Connect
for spatial computing."
To go deeper on privacy,
including our new features
for third party SDKs,
visit "What's new in privacy."
To better understand pre-order
by region,
including our redesigned
availability tab,
visit "What's new
in App pre-order."
Once you have your app
in the hands of customers,
you can explore how to automate
with the App Store Connect API.
The App Store Connect API
provides options
for customizing workflows,
staying in sync
with your internal systems,
and automating processes
to save time.
Our API collections allow you
to automate many areas
of the App Store.
This year, we launched in-app
purchases and subscriptions,
customer reviews and responses,
and the ability to manage
sandbox testers.
We have some great releases
coming this year,
including support
for Game Center.
These APIs will make it
easier and faster
to set up Game Center features
and build consistent experiences
across all platforms
of your game.
Let's go into detail
about what these APIs entail.
You can create, configure,
and even archive leaderboards
and achievements just as
you would in App Store Connect.
Archiving is a new feature
to remove leaderboards
and achievements from your game.
Submit scores
and achievement unlock events
via a server-to-server API.
This is great if you are
a cross-platform game
that manages data
across many platforms.
Remove scores and players
from your leaderboards
to automate management
of fraudulent activity.
Last, match players
using custom rules
like skill level or region,
an upgrade to our matchmaking
capabilities.
In addition to bringing
Game Center to the API,
we also have some updates
to API authentication.
This year,
you can generate
marketing and customer service
API keys
if you'd like to limit keys to
manage your marketing metadata
or respond to App Store reviews.
You can also create
a user-based key,
which is an API key that has
the same permissions as you do,
regardless of what role
you have.
You'll be able to do this
from your user profile
in App Store Connect.
We covered a lot
in this session,
and these new features are just
a subset of the developer tools
for the App Store.
Whether you're building
an app for the first time,
you're an experienced
developer,
you're building by yourself,
or you're part of a team,
App Store Connect can help you
put the best version of your app
on the App Store.
To wrap up, I encourage you
to try out
some of these new capabilities
and tell us what you think.
If you run into issues,
you can contact us
through
the Apple developer website
for unlimited support
via phone and email.
We provide support in nine
languages, 24 hours a day.
I encourage you
to submit feedback
with the Feedback Assistant.
Whether it's for App Store
Connect, TestFlight,
or the App Store Connect API,
our team reviews
every piece of feedback
that comes in.
Thanks for watching.
I'm excited to see
what you build next.
♪