♪ ♪
Allison: Hello, everyone.
My name is Allison,
and I am an accessibility engineer.
Today we are going to be talking
about some of the exciting new ways
you can make your app more accessible.
At Apple, accessibility is an essential
piece of everything that we build
because we believe
everyone deserves access to technology.
We want it to be extremely easy
for you to make your apps accessible.
Over the past year, we have been working
on a number of enhancements
to ensure that everyone has
the best possible experience in your app.
In this session, we will explore API
that lets people interact with your app
in new, exciting ways.
Next, we will discuss how to improve
the accessibility visuals
for your content in your SwiftUI app.
Finally, we will learn a better way
to keep your accessibility attributes
up-to-date in UIKit.
Let's start by talking about
accessibility enhancements.
I have been working
on a photo editing app.
My app lets me add
cool image modifications
to photos from my library or camera.
I can apply different filters,
change the photo tint color,
or create custom sounds
to pair with my images
using the piano keyboard in my app.
Let's discuss a few
accessibility enhancements
that we can integrate into the app.
In the filter page of my photo app,
there is a custom button
that has an on and off state.
The "Filter" switch button lets us
toggle on and off the image filter.
The system does not know
the correct accessibility hint
and title for this custom UI,
and we want to make sure that we provide
an accessibility experience
that matches that of other system toggles.
This is where the new accessibility trait,
isToggle, helps out.
We have a struct
representing the filter button.
In the body of the struct,
we create a button
that toggles the filter when pressed.
The button's color updates
based on the filter state variable.
We will add the isToggle trait
to the filter button
in the accessibilityAddTraits modifier.
isToggle provides the proper
accessibility hint
and "switch button" description.
VoiceOver: Filter, switch button.
Double-tap to toggle setting.
Allison: The new toggle trait
is also available in UIKit.
In the viewDidLoad method,
we set up the button view.
Then, we set the accessibilityTraits
property on the button
to contain .toggleButton.
In the photo filter app,
I want to add a new announcement
to the photos navigation bar button
to let people know
the photos view is loading.
Accessibility Notifications are
a new API that can help us do this.
Accessibility notifications provide
a unified, multi-platform way
to create announcements
to convey information
to someone using
an assistive technology in your app.
Accessibility notifications can be
created for apps running SwiftUI,
UIKit, and AppKit.
With AccessibilityNotification,
you can send announcement,
layout change, screen change,
and page scroll notifications
in a way that is native to Swift.
When the photos tool bar button
is pressed,
I want to post an announcement.
VoiceOver: Photos, button.
Photos. Loading photos view.
Allison: We can post the announcement
in the action for the toolbar button.
To create the announcement, we can use
AccessibilityNotification.Announcement
with "Loading Photos View"
as the string parameter.
In the app,
I also want to create three announcements
when the camera navigation
bar button is pressed.
The first announcement, "Opening Camera,"
and third announcement,
"Camera Active," are the most important.
Let's look at VoiceOver's current
speech pattern for the announcements.
Notice how the second announcement,
"Camera Loading,"
interrupts "Opening Camera".
VoiceOver: Camera, button.
Done. Open--camera--camera active.
Allison: Now, in SwiftUI and UIKit,
you can also set
an announcement's priority,
which lets you set the importance
of an announcement queued to be spoken
by assistive technologies.
This gives you more control over
which announcements people need to hear,
versus announcements that can be ignored
if not spoken in time.
You can specify
the importance of this information
using one of three
announcement priorities:
high, default, and low.
High priority announcements
can interrupt other speech
and cannot be interrupted once started.
Default priority announcements
can interrupt existing speech
but are interruptible if a new
speech utterance is started.
Low priority announcements are queued
and spoken
when other speech utterances
have completed,
if no new announcements have started.
In the photos app,
we can use announcement priority
to fix the interrupting strings.
We have three announcements
made from attributed strings.
In SwiftUI, we will set the priority
on the
accessibilitySpeechAnnouncementPriority
string property.
Our second announcement, "Camera Loading,"
is the least important,
so we give it a low priority.
The last announcement, "Camera Active,"
is the most important,
so we want it to have a high priority.
Next, we will pass the attributed strings
to the AccessibilityNotification.
First, we will dispatch
the default priority announcement,
then the low priority,
then the high priority.
Now note how the low priority announcement
does not interrupt
the default priority announcement,
while the high priority announcement
does interrupt
the default and low announcements.
VoiceOver: Camera, button.
Done. Opening camera--camera active.
Allison: We can achieve
the same announcement order in UIKit.
We set the announcement priorities
as NSAttributedString key value pairs.
We use the key
UIAccessibilitySpeechAttribute
AnnouncementPriority
and set the value
to the proper UIAccessibilityPriority.
Then we pass the attributes
to the attributed string initializer.
Back in the app, there is an image view
that people can physically touch
or pinch to zoom in and out.
With an assistive technology turned on,
this physical touch or pinch gesture
can be hard to accomplish.
Now, with the accessibility zoom action,
people can zoom in and out
on UI elements
when assistive technologies are enabled.
We will add the zoom action on the image.
The image is in the body
of the ZoomingImageView struct.
We first add
the accessibilityZoomAction modifier.
Then, based on the direction
of the zoom action,
we will zoom the content in or out
and post an accessibility notification
announcement.
Now let's explore VoiceOver's
zoom capabilities with these changes.
VoiceOver: Zooming image view, image.
Zoom.
2x zoom. 3x zoom.
4x zoom. 3x zoom.
Allison: We can also add
the zoom trait and action in UIKit.
We will first create a zoom view
which will contain the image view.
Next, we will add the supportsZoom trait
to the zoom view
alongside the image trait.
We then implement
accessibilityZoomInAtPoint
and accessibilityZoomOutAtPoint,
each of which return a boolean
to indicate zooming success or failure.
In each of these methods,
we update the zoom scale
and post an announcement
to indicate the zoom change.
In our image filter app,
we can also create a short sound
to add to the image
by playing the small piano keys.
People can create custom tones
for the image using the keys.
[piano notes play]
Let's examine the current
VoiceOver experience with these sounds
as I try to create a tone.
[VoiceOver reading, piano keys playing]
VoiceOver speaks the key label
and plays the VoiceOver activation sound
every time the element is touched,
which makes it difficult
to quickly press the keys in succession.
Typically, VoiceOver provides
a safe exploration experience,
but sometimes, people need
to directly interact with your app
to use it properly.
For our app, it would be much better
if people could directly touch
the piano keys
without extra speech and sounds.
This is a great time to adopt
the direct touch trait,
named allowsDirectInteraction,
on our view.
Accessibility direct touch areas
will let you specify
a region of the screen
where VoiceOver gestures pass
directly through to the app.
In the default state,
VoiceOver both speaks
and activates the content
of the direct touch element.
For our app, though, it would be great
if VoiceOver would be silent
when someone touches a piano key
so they can immediately hear the tone
without having to activate
the piano key element first.
In addition
to the allowsDirectInteraction trait,
there are now two new direct
touch options that will be supported.
First, you can specify silentOnTouch
to ensure VoiceOver is silent
when touching the direct touch area,
so that your app can make
its own audio feedback.
Second, you can specify requiresActivation
to make the direct touch area
require VoiceOver
to activate the element
before touch passthrough happens.
This is the code snippet
for the KeyboardKeyView.
Each key is a rectangle
that plays a specified sound.
To fix the issue with VoiceOver
speaking over the tone every time,
we have set the direct touch option
for the button to silent on touch.
Now, the correct tone plays
once VoiceOver reaches the key button
without interference
from VoiceOver's speech.
[keys playing]
We can also add
the new direct touch options in UIKit.
We can create the key button
as a UIButton.
Next, we will add
the allowsDirectInteraction
accessibility trait.
This trait is required when setting
accessibility direct touch options
in UIKit.
Finally, we will add
the silentOnTouch option
for accessibilityDirectTouchOptions.
With the accessibility toggle trait,
announcement priority, zoom trait,
and direct touch options,
you have more control
over the ways assistive technologies
interact with your SwiftUI and UIKit apps.
Next, let's talk about the accessibility
content Shape kind in SwiftUI.
This kind sets
an accessibility element's path
and controls the appearance
of accessibility elements on the screen.
Previously,
the interaction content shape kind
changed the accessibility shape
and hit testing shape.
Now there is an accessibility
content shape kind
which will not impact
the hit testing shape
and only impact the shape
of accessibility content.
When an element needs a custom shape,
such as a circle,
the computed accessibility cursor visuals
may obstruct other items on the screen.
In this example,
the accessibility path is a square,
which does not match
the red circular content.
When the Accessibility Content Shape kind
is applied to a view,
it will update the underlying
accessibility geometry
for the element
with the shape provided by the modifier.
This lets you quickly update
an element's path
with an existing SwiftUI Shape.
I have created the circle button
using a circle image.
We can set the frame
and the accessibility label
to match the color, red.
Finally, we can add
the content shape modifier to my view
with the accessibility type
and Circle as the shape.
Now the accessibility path
correctly matches
the circular shape
of the red color button.
Finally, let's discuss an addition
coming to UIKit accessibility,
block based attribute setters.
In the photo editing app,
I want the accessibility value
for the image view to represent whether
the photo is filtered or not filtered.
Now there is an easy way
to keep the underlying
accessibility attributes
for my views always in line
with the presented UI.
I can do this
with accessibility block based setters.
The new accessibility block API lets you
provide a closure that is evaluated
whenever the attribute is needed
rather than storing the value directly.
The closure is re-evaluated
every time a view is referenced
or accessed by an assistive technology.
We can simplify things with a closure,
created in the viewDidLoad method
for my view controller.
We set the accessibilityValueBlock
property on the zoomView
to keep the value updated based on
whether or not the image is filtered.
The closure must return
the correct type for this attribute,
which is an optional String.
Notice that we are using
a weak reference to self
to avoid a retain cycle.
Blocks are great to add
at the beginning of a class life cycle,
to start up a class with the proper
accessibility attribute information.
Now accessibility attributes
are much easier to maintain.
Every time someone moves
the VoiceOver cursor to a new element,
VoiceOver first looks for attributes
set with a closure
and re-evaluates the closure.
[VoiceOver reading]
When you are building custom UI,
consider integrating accessibility traits
like toggle
and features like direct touch interaction
to increase usability for everyone.
Second, think about your views
with custom shapes in SwiftUI.
If the accessibility shapes
do not match the UI,
consider introducing
a custom accessibility shape.
And finally, I encourage you to evaluate
how you are setting
your accessibility attributes
and identify if block based setters
make more sense in your app.
At Apple, we believe
accessibility is a human right.
With your help, we can create technology
that enhances and empowers
everyone's lives.
These new API additions are a great way
to increase the usability of your app
for people who rely
on assistive technologies,
and I encourage you to use all of them
to build amazing, accessible apps.
Thanks for watching.