♪ ♪
Georgi: Hello and welcome!
I’m Georgi Rakidov,
Software Engineer in GPU,
Graphics, and Display Software.
This session is the third
of a three-part series
that helps you bring your game to Mac.
The first session covers how
you can use the new Game Porting Toolkit
to run your umodified Windows game
on the Mac
to evaluate your graphics, audio,
and display features
the second session shows how much
development time you can save
by compiling your existing HLSL shaders
to Metal
using the new Metal Shader Converter tool.
This session completes the process
of bringing your game to Mac
by giving you detailed insights about
how to port your renderer to Metal
and get great performance
out of Apple Silicon.
As you port your renderer to Metal,
you’ll notice your engine requires mapping
the concepts from other platform graphics
APIs to Metal.
To help you with that, this session covers
four topics, with Metal best practices,
so you can leverage the
powerful architecture of Apple GPUs.
Each game is responsible
for making GPU resources,
including textures and data buffers,
available to the GPU,
and configuring how your shaders
can access them.
Your game can leverage
the powerful graphics architecture
of Apple processors by optimizing
how it submits commands to the GPU.
Games typically implement modern rendering
techniques by using indirect rendering.
MetalFX helps games save time
for each frame
by rendering to a lower resolution
and then upscaling with MetalFX
to the final resolution.
When it comes to managing resources,
each engine has to decide
how the GPU accesses each texture,
data buffer, and so on.
On Metal, it's important to think about
providing shaders access to resources
with bindings,
and Making resources resident
into GPU-accessible memory
and keeping access to them synchronized.
Resource bindings and shaders go together.
Start by translating your existing shaders
with the Metal Shader Converter,
which is a new tool this year,
that can save you a lot of time
porting your shaders to Metal.
You can learn more from the
"Compile your Shaders" session
in this series.
Metal Shader Converter gives
you two binding models to choose from.
With "Automatic layout,"
the converter generates
the binding information automatically,
or you can pass binding information
to Metal Shader Converter
with "Explicit Layout."
Explicit layout is very flexible
and can be helpful
when you need to implement binding models
from other platforms.
For example, some API designs
use a shader root signature,
and here is a typical one
with four entries:
a descriptor table
that points to a series of textures,
a buffer root parameter,
a 32-bit constant,
and another descriptor table
that points to a series of samplers.
Each descriptor table is a resource array
that contains elements
of the same type,
such as all textures, all samplers,
or all buffers.
Metal's argument buffers are more flexible
in that elements can be of multiple types.
But if your engine expects
a homogenous array,
you can easily encode them
with an argument buffer.
This example encodes the equivalent
of a texture descriptor table.
It starts by allocating a Metal buffer
that serves as a texture descriptor table
by storing the Metal resource ID
for each texture.
As it creates each texture,
the code stores its resourceID
directly into the table.
The nice part is
you can run code like this up front
and outside of your rendering loop!
The process for encoding a sampler
descriptor table is almost the same.
Just like with textures,
the code starts by creating a Metal buffer
that serves
as the sampler descriptor table.
As the code configures
each sampler's descriptor,
it sets the supportArgumentBuffers
property to yes.
After the code creates the sampler
with the descriptor,
it saves the sampler's resourceID
in the table.
You can also use an argument buffer
to represent the top-level
root signature itself.
This example defines
a structure for the root signature
and creates a Metal buffer
that can store one instance of it.
The code assigns each field
of the structure's fields
with appropriate values,
including GPU addresses
for the texture and sampler tables.
That’s all it takes
to convert a root signature.
Argument buffers
are super-efficient in Metal 3!
Now you can just bind the top-level
argument buffer to a shader.
This part is done in the render loop,
but you can create the descriptor tables
and root structure beforehand
outside the render loop.
Metal 3 argument buffers
provide a flexible,
performant way
to translate other binding models,
including root signatures
and descriptor tables.
Resources need to be resident
during the execution of a given pass
or render stage in order
for shaders to access them.
And if a resource
is shared between passes,
the order of execution of those passes
has to be synchronized.
The usage of bindless resources
with Metal argument buffers
requires explicit residency management
on all GPU architectures,
and Metal provides efficient ways
to control residency.
The recommendation is to group
all read-only resources in big heaps.
That way, you can just call useHeap
once per encoder
and all your read-only resources
will be made resident
for the duration of that pass
or render stage,
ready to be accessed by the shaders.
This is how you can do it.
Create a heap with the necessary size
to allocate all your read-only resources,
then allocate each resource
out of this heap.
And at render time, just call useHeap
to make all these resources resident.
For writable resources,
the story is a bit different.
Consider allocating writable resources
individually and calling useResource
with the right usage flags.
In this case, Metal will handle
synchronization for you
and optimize for performance.
This will help you avoid the burden
to manually synchronize resources
across Metal encoders.
Similar to before,
you start by allocating the resources,
this time not backed by a heap.
Then, only for the encoders
that are going to access these resources,
call useResource
with the right usage flags.
In this example,
the encoder is writing to the texture
and reading from the buffer.
Here is a table with this recommendation.
Both, read-only and writable resources,
are accessed
from a top-level argument buffer.
In the ideal case,
set just once per encoder.
Read-only resources, grouped in heaps,
hazard tracking mode set to Untracked.
To make all resources
in the heap resident,
call useHeap once per encoder.
Writable resources,
allocated individually,
leave hazard tracking
and synchronization to Metal.
And for each resource call,
useResource once per encoder.
This is an efficient approach!
It implements a bindless model
with low CPU overhead,
and the Application doesn't have to worry
about hazard tracking and synchronization,
complicated tasks that require
serious effort, and development time.
For more details in bindless,
residency, and synchronization,
refer to the session
“Go bindless with Metal 3.”
Once you have resource bindings,
residency,
and synchronization
implemented in the code,
to render anything on screen,
the engine will have to send commands
to the renderer.
The Apple Processor has many features
to optimize command execution.
The GPU is a Tile-Based Deferred Renderer,
or TBDR,
with a unified memory architecture
where the CPU and the GPU
are sharing system memory.
Also, the GPU has a fast, on-chip memory
called Tile Memory.
To leverage this architecture,
Metal has a notion of passes,
and your goal is to group
rendering commands into passes
and properly configure those passes.
For a deeper dive into TBDR architecture,
please refer to the related presentations
“Bring your Metal app
to Apple Silicon Macs”
and "Harness AppleGPUs with Metal."
Other APIs can have a continuous stream
mixing GPU commands of different types,
and your engine might assume this.
Translating commands to Metal,
you first create a command buffer.
Then, depending on the type of commands,
Graphics, Compute, or Blit,
you group them into passes.
You write the commands for each pass
into the command buffer
using a command encoder.
At the end,
when all the commands are encoded,
submit the command buffer
to the command queue
for execution by the GPU.
Your engine can consider
four best practices
to efficiently translate
rendering commands to Metal.
Start by batching copies up front
before rendering starts,
group commands of the same type,
and avoid having empty encoders
to clear render targets.
And finally,
optimize your Metal Load and Store actions
to minimize memory bandwidth.
These best practices are easy to explain
by using an example.
Say you have the following sequence:
a render target clear, a draw, a copy,
a dispatch, and another draw.
In particular,
look at all the memory traffic
between system and tile memory
generated in this sequence.
This is not ideal!
The copy in the middle of the stream
copies uniform data for subsequent draws,
in this case, Draw 1.
The recommendation is, if possible,
to move and batch these copies
before rendering to avoid
interrupting the rendering pass.
After the change,
the copy is now first,
then the clear, draw 0,
dispatch, and draw 1.
If there is no dependency between
the two draw calls and the dispatch,
you should reorder them
so you can batch draws
and dispatches together.
In this example, after switching the order
of the draw and the dispatch calls,
you now have two render passes
after each other.
This scenario is perfect for merging them
into a single render pass
if they share the same render targets,
saving significant memory bandwidth.
That way, you remove
some unnecessary memory traffic,
as data doesn't need to go
from tile memory to system memory
and back between the two draws.
This is already better,
but could be optimized further.
The clear is an empty encoder,
with only one purpose:
to clear the render targets
used by the next draws.
In Metal, there is a very efficient way
to do this.
Just use LoadActionClear
for the first render pass
that uses the render targets.
This is much better,
but there is one more recommendation
You can optimize load and store actions.
You only have to store
in the system memory
the content of the render targets
that will be used in the next passes.
From this example, assume after draw 1,
only the first render target will be used.
All other render targets are intermediate
and the content doesn’t need
to be preserved.
Metal allows control of the store action
for each render target.
In this case,
you can use StoreActionStore
for the first render target
and StoreActionDontCare
for the other ones.
And that's it!
This is the initial commands sequence.
There are five round trips between
tile memory and system memory.
And this is how
the commands sequence looks
after a few easy optimizations.
Only one final flush from tile memory
to system memory.
The memory bandwidth is greatly reduced!
And that has been achieved
by moving copies before rendering,
grouping commands of the same type,
avoid clearing render targets
with empty encoders,
and optimizing load and store actions.
The GPU tools
can help you identify these issues.
Metal Debugger in Xcode automatically
finds optimization opportunities,
so you can get the best performance
in your game.
It allows you to inspect and understand
the dependencies of your Metal passes,
and comes with a full-featured suite
of debugging and profiling tools.
It's easy to use Metal Debugger to
identify the issues that were mentioned.
When I capture a Metal workload,
Metal Debugger shows the Summary viewer.
The Insights section at the bottom
shows me optimization opportunities
that come grouped into four categories:
Memory, Bandwidth, Performance,
and API Usage.
There are two bandwidth insights
I’d like to highlight in this workload.
The first one is for unused resources.
When I select an Insight,
I can find a summary
and some actionable advice to address it
in the right panel.
The GBuffer pass is storing
more attachments than it needs to.
In this case, the GBuffer pass loads
the albedo/alpha texture
and stores it.
However, since the albedo texture
isn’t used later in this frame,
the store is redundant, so we can fix this
by setting the store action to DontCare.
Let’s check the next Insight.
Combining render passes can help
with reducing bandwidth,
and here, the insight suggests
that I can combine GBuffer
and Forward passes into a single pass.
I can also learn more about
what these passes are reading and writing
by clicking the Reveal in Dependencies
button on the right
to find this render pass
in the Dependencies viewer.
The Dependencies viewer is a great tool
to inspect dependencies between passes!
Here, I can see at a glance
the load and store actions,
shown above and below
the render attachments.
All the attachments in this pass
have store action store,
but only the color 0 and the depth
attachment are used in the future pass.
The previous insight revealed this.
Zoom out a little,
and the data edges are shown
flowing from the GBuffer pass
to the Forward pass.
As the insight indicated,
the GBuffer and Forward passes
can be merged to save bandwidth,
as they’re storing and loading
from the same attachments.
Merging these two passes will
save bandwidth and improve performance.
That was just one example of
how you can use Metal Debugger
to find optimization opportunities
in your game.
To learn more about Metal Debugger,
please check out the related sessions
“Gain insights into your Metal app
with Xcode 12”
and "Discover Metal debugging, profiling,
and asset creation tools."
Indirect rendering
is an important functionality
that high-end games use to
implement advanced rendering techniques.
This topic will review
how ExecuteIndirect works
and how to translate
this particular command to Metal.
With indirect rendering,
instead of encoding
multiple draw commands,
their arguments are stored
in a regular buffer in memory
and only one ExecuteIndirect command
is encoded referencing the buffer
and specifying how many draw calls
the GPU has to execute
by fetching arguments for each one of them
from the buffer.
The main idea of this approach is
to be able to populate content
of the indirect buffer
by a compute shader
scheduled for execution before
the ExecuteIndirect command.
This way,
the GPU prepares work for itself
and decides what to render.
Execution of commands
with indirect arguments is
a key feature
to implement advanced techniques
such as a GPU-driven rendering loop.
There are two ways
to translate this command to Metal,
by using Draw Indirect and
Metal Indirect Command Buffers, or ICBs.
In Metal, the renderer has
to translate each ExecuteIndirect
to a series
of API calls to DrawIndirect.
Each one references the buffer
and provides an offset
for the draw arguments.
Here is the code.
Look through the maximum number of draw
calls this ExecuteIndirect might have.
For each one, encode a separate draw
specifying the indirect arguments buffer
and offset in that buffer.
At the end of iteration,
move the offset to point
to the next set of indirect arguments.
This approach is very easy to implement
and will work in almost all situations.
However, if you have scenes
with thousands of draw calls
and performance in your game
is limited by the CPU encoding time,
you should consider
Indirect Command Buffers in Metal.
ICBs are a superset of buffers
with indirect draw arguments.
In addition to draw arguments,
you can also set buffer bindings
and render Pipeline State Objects
from the GPU.
To schedule commands from an ICB
for execution on the GPU,
you have to encode
executeCommandsInBuffer command.
Usually with ExecuteIndirect,
all draw calls
share the same Pipeline State Object.
And each time the PSO changes,
you have to encode
a new ExecuteIndirect command.
If you are using ICBs, it is not required
to split the indirect execution commands
by state changes that often.
All PSOs and buffer bindings
could be set from the ICB,
so you don’t have to encode them.
Depending on the structure of the scene,
this might significantly
reduce the encoding time.
To leverage ICBs, it’s not necessary
to modify existing shaders
that populate indirect arguments.
You can share the same shaders
with other platforms
and compile them
with the Metal Shader Converter
then translate draw arguments to ICBs
by adding a small compute kernel
after indirect argument generation
and before the indirect rendering pass.
To encode the ICB in your compute kernel,
write it in the Metal Shading Language.
As input to the shader,
there is a pointer to the indirect
arguments you want to translate.
Next, check if the arguments are valid,
and only then
will you encode the command.
In the encodeCommand function,
set the render pipeline state,
buffer bindings, and the draw call.
This translates the draw arguments
to a render command
in the indirect command buffer.
And that’s how to translate
Indirect rendering to Metal.
You can use a series
of draw indirect commands
or Metal Indirect command buffers.
If you want to learn how
to use indirect rendering
to implement
advanced rendering techniques,
check out the “Modern Rendering
with Metal” Sample Code.
Once your game is producing correct images
by binding resources to its pipelines
and properly encoding commands
into command buffers,
you can leverage upscaling to get more
performance out of your players' devices.
Upscaling via MetalFX
helps games save time for each frame
by reducing the amount of GPU work.
MetalFX is a turnkey solution
to implement your upscaling pipeline.
It works by scaling
a lower resolution image
up to the target output resolution
in less time than it takes
to render at the output resolution
directly.
MetalFX was introduced
last year for the Mac,
and it offers high performance upscaling!
MetalFX supports two upscaling algorithms,
"Spatial" for the best performance
and "Temporal" for quality
approaching native rendering
on the output resolution.
Integrating MetalFX in the engine
will improve the player's experience
by rendering in higher resolutions
with better performance.
New features this year include
support for iOS,
up to 3X upscaling,
and support in Metal-cpp.
If your engine already supports
an existing upscaling solution
on other platforms, MetalFX integration
won’t require much coding
and modification on the engine side.
To support MetalFX,
you need upscaling support in the engine.
Another requirement is the renderer
to manually control the level of detail
for texture sampling in materials shaders.
Temporal upscaling requires
jitter sequence and motion vectors.
You probably already have those
if your engine supports
temporal anti-aliasing.
MetalFX’s temporal upscaling can take
rendering’s exposure into account,
and you have two options.
If your renderer supports a 1 by 1
exposure texture, then use that.
Otherwise, you can enable
the autoexposure feature
and see if it improves the quality.
Don’t forget to reset the history
on camera cuts
and extreme camera movements.
For more details on how to integrate
MetalFX in your applications,
refer to the Documentation
and “Boost performance
with MetalFX upscaling” from last year.
Metal gives some powerful options
to make the most
of your app's rendering time.
You can manage resources
and bind them as efficiently as possible.
Based on how your shaders access them,
ensure the passes that share resources
run in the right order,
and make resources resident
and available for the GPU.
Your app can leverage the full potential
of Apple’s powerful graphics architecture
by locating and applying
optimization opportunities
with Metal Debugger in Xcode
and optimizing your command submission.
Let the GPU decide for itself what work
to do by implementing indirect rendering,
which can be the key for many
modern rendering techniques.
Up your rendering game
by upscaling your renderings with MetalFX,
which can save your app valuable time
in the render loop.
For more rendering tips and guidelines,
check out "Optimize Metal Performance
for Apple silicon Macs."
Thank you for watching!
♪ ♪