♪ ♪
Ben: Hi, and welcome
to "What's New in Swift 5.9."
I'm Ben,
and together with my colleague Doug,
we'll take you through some
of the improvements
to the Swift language this year.
We'll talk about some ways
it's easier to express what you mean
using Swift's clean syntax,
some powerful new features
that help framework authors
make their new APIs more natural to use,
and we'll look at some new ways
to get more control over performance
and safety in low-level code.
But let's start by talking
about the Swift open source project.
This is a great update for Swift,
and it couldn't have happened
without the Swift community,
the contributors
and users of the language
who gather at swift.org,
working together to evolve the language
and support new initiatives.
Swift follows an open process
for language evolution.
New features or significant
behavior changes are proposed
and reviewed
in the open on the Swift forums.
If you want to follow along,
you can find a dashboard
of all the language proposals
on the Swift website.
A year ago,
we saw a significant restructuring
of the Swift Project governance.
The core team announced the formation
of the Language Steering Group,
which took on primary responsibility
for oversight of the Swift language
and standard library evolution.
Since then,
the language group has overseen
40 new language proposals,
and we're going to talk
about several of them today.
But sometimes,
individual language proposals
come together as part of a wider theme,
like the addition of Swift concurrency,
which was introduced
through ten separate proposals.
For cases like this,
the language steering group
has introduced a new way
of tying together these proposals,
through vision documents.
These documents lay out a proposal
for larger changes to the language.
The first one to be accepted
by the language steering group
was a vision of Swift macros,
a new feature in Swift 5.9
that we'll be covering later in this talk.
Of course,
evolution of the language is only part
of the work of the Swift community.
A successful language
needs much more than this.
It needs great tooling,
robust support for multiple platforms,
and rich documentation.
To oversee progress in this area,
the core team is creating
an ecosystem steering group
parallel to the language steering group.
This new structure was recently laid out
in a blog post on Swift.org,
a look out for further announcements
about the formation
of this new group soon.
Now let's talk about changes
to the Swift language this year,
starting with better ways
to express yourself in your code.
Swift 5.9 includes what
is probably our most commonly
requested language enhancement,
allowing if/else and switch statements
to be used as expressions,
providing a nice way
to clean up your code.
For example,
if you wanted to initialize a let variable
based on some complex condition,
you had to resort to tricks,
like this hard-to-read
compound ternary expression.
If expressions let you
instead use a much more familiar
and readable chain of if statements.
Another place where this helps
is if you're initializing
a global variable or a stored property.
Single expressions work fine here,
but if you wanted a condition,
you had to use the trick
of wrapping it in a closure
that you then immediately executed.
Now that an if statement
can be an expression,
you can just drop that clutter,
leaving you with neater code.
Result builders, the declarative syntax
that drives features like SwiftUI,
have seen
significant improvements this year,
including optimized
type checking performance,
code completion,
and improved error messages.
This improvement
was particularly focused on invalid code.
Previously, result builder code with
errors would take a long time to fail,
as the type checker explored
the many possible invalid paths.
As of Swift 5.8,
invalid code type checks much faster,
and error messages on invalid code
are now more precise.
For example, previously,
some invalid code could lead
to misleading errors in a completely
different part of the result builder.
In Swift 5.7,
you'd receive an error like this,
when the mistake actually lies up here.
In the latest release, you now receive
a more accurate compiler diagnostic
identifying the real issue.
Next, let's talk about how
an addition to the generics system
will allow for some great improvements
to frameworks you use every day.
Almost all the Swift you write
is using generics in some way.
Type inference enables
using these types without needing
to understand the advanced capabilities
they're built with.
For example, the standard library
Array type uses generics
to provide an array
that works with any type of data
that you might want to store.
When you use an array, all you need
to do is provide the elements.
There's no need to specify
an explicit argument for the element type
because it can be inferred
from the element values.
Swift's generics system
enables natural APIs
that preserve type information
so that your code operates seamlessly
on the concrete types that you provide.
Here's an example inspired
by the Swift compiler's own codebase:
An API that takes a request type
and evaluates it
to produce a strongly typed value.
So you can make a request
for a Boolean value
and get back a Boolean result.
Now, some APIs want to abstract
not only over concrete types,
but also the number
of arguments that you pass in.
So a function might take one request
and return one result
or two requests and return two results,
or three and return three results.
To support this,
the generics system has to be used
together with a mechanism
to handle multiple argument lengths
so that all of the types that you pass in
are linked to the types that you get out.
Before Swift 5.9,
the only way to accomplish this pattern
was by adding an overload
for each specific argument length
the API supported.
But this approach has limitations.
It forces an artificial upper bound
on the number of arguments you can pass,
resulting in compiler errors
if you pass too many.
In this case,
there isn't an overload that can handle
more than six arguments,
but we've passed seven.
This overloading pattern
and its limitations are pervasive
across APIs that conceptually handle
arbitrary argument length.
In Swift 5.9, the generics system
is gaining first-class support
for this API pattern by enabling
generic abstraction over argument length.
This is done with a new language concept
that can represent multiple
individual type parameters
that are "packed" together.
This new concept is called
a type parameter pack.
Using parameter packs,
APIs that currently
have individual overloads
for each fixed argument length
can be collapsed down
into a single function.
Instead of accepting
a single type parameter, Result,
representing the result type
of a single request,
the evaluate function now accepts
a separate request over each Result type.
The function returns each
result instance in parenthesis,
which will either be a single value
or a tuple containing each value.
The evaluate function now handles all
argument lengths with no artificial limit.
Type inference makes APIs
using parameter packs natural to use
without needing to know
that the API is using them.
Calling our new evaluate function
that can now
handle any number of arguments,
looks just like calling
the fixed-length overloads.
Swift infers the type of each argument
along with the total number
based on how you're calling the function.
To learn about how to write
generic library APIs like these,
check out Generalize APIs
using parameter packs.
Calling generic APIs
in a natural way demonstrates one
of Swift's fundamental design goals,
clear expression through concise code.
Swift's advanced language features
enable beautiful APIs
that make it easier to say what you mean.
You benefit
from these advanced language features
from the very first lines
of Swift that you ever write,
whether it's using generics
through arrays or dictionaries
or designing a UI in SwiftUI.
Swift's embrace of progressive
disclosure means that you can learn
about the more advanced features
when you're ready to.
Swift 5.9 takes this design approach
to the next level
by providing library authors
with a new toolbox
for expressive API design
using a new macro system.
Here's Doug to tell you more.
Doug: With macros, you can extend
the capabilities of the language itself,
eliminating boilerplate and unlocking more
of Swift's expressive power.
Let's consider
the ever-present assert function,
which checks whether a condition is true.
Assert will stop the program
if the condition is false,
but when that happens,
you get very little information
about what went wrong,
just the file and line number.
You'll need to add some logging or trap
the program in the debugger to learn more.
There have been attempts
to improve on this.
XCTest provides an assert-equal operation
that takes the two values separately,
so when things fail, you can at least see
the two values that aren't equal.
But we still don't know
which value is wrong here.
Was it a, b, or the result of max?
And this approach really doesn't scale
for all of the kinds of checks
we perform in asserts.
If we go back to the original assertion,
there is so much information here
in the source code that we'd like to see
in the log when our assertion fails.
What was the code?
What are the values of a, and b, and c?
What did max produce?
We couldn't improve this in Swift before
without some custom feature,
but macros make it possible.
In this example, the "hash-assert" syntax
is expanding the macro called "assert."
The hash syntax might look familiar
because Swift already has a few things
with this same spelling,
like hash-file,
hash-selector, and hash-warning.
The assert macro looks and feels
like the function version,
but because it's a macro,
it can provide a richer experience
when the assertion fails.
Now the program is showing the code
for the failing assertion,
along with each of the values
that contributed to the result.
In Swift, macros are APIs,
just like types or functions,
so you access them by importing
the module that defines them.
Like many other APIs,
macros are distributed as packages.
The assert macro here comes
from the power asserts library,
an open-source Swift package
available on GitHub.
If you were to look
into the macro package,
you would find
a macro declaration for assert.
It is introduced with the "macro" keyword,
but otherwise,
it looks a lot like a function.
There's a single unlabeled Bool parameter
for the condition to be checked.
If this macro produced a value,
that result type would be written
with the usual arrow syntax.
Uses of the macro will be type checked
against the parameters.
That means, if you were to make a mistake
in using the macro,
such as forgetting to compare
the maximum value against something,
you'll get a useful error message
immediately,
before the macro is ever expanded.
This allows Swift to provide
a great development experience
when using macros because macros operate
on well-typed inputs and produce code
that augments your program
in predictable ways.
Most macros are defined
as "external macros,"
specifying the module and type
for a macro implementation via strings.
The external macro types
are defined in separate programs
that act as compiler plugins.
The Swift compiler passes the source code
for the use of the macro to the plugin.
The plugin produces new source code,
which is then integrated back
into the Swift program.
Here, the macro is expanding the assertion
into code
that captures the individual values
and where they should be displayed
in the source code.
You wouldn't want
to write the boilerplate yourself,
but the macro does it for you.
Macro declarations have one additional
piece of information, their role.
The assert macro here
is a freestanding expression macro.
It is called freestanding
because it uses the "hash" syntax
and operates directly
on that syntax to produce new code.
It is an expression macro
because it can be used anywhere
that one can produce a value.
The new Foundation Predicate APIs provide
a great example of an expression macro.
The predicate macro allows one
to write predicates
in a type-safe manner using closures.
The resulting predicate values can then
be used with a number of other APIs,
including the Swift collection operations
SwiftUI and SwiftData.
The macro itself is generic
over the set of input types.
It accepts a closure argument
that's a function operating on values
of those input types and produces
a Boolean result,
does the set of inputs match or not?
And the macro returns an instance
of the new Predicate type,
which can be used elsewhere
in the program.
But there is more to macros
because a lot of the boilerplate
we end up writing
is because we need to augment code
we have written
with something else derived from it.
Let's take an example.
I find that I use enums a lot
in my own code,
like this Path enum that captures
either relative or absolute paths.
But I'll often find myself needing
to check for a specific case,
say, by filtering all absolute paths
from a collection.
I can write this isAbsolute check
as a computed property, of course.
But sooner or later,
I'm going to have to write another one.
This is getting a bit tedious.
Macros can help here
by generating the boilerplate for us.
Case detection is an attached macro,
written using the same custom-attribute
syntax as property wrappers.
Attached macros take as input the syntax
of the declaration they apply to--
here it's the enum declaration itself--
and will generate new code.
This macro-expanded code
is normal Swift code,
which the compiler integrates
into your program.
You can inspect the macro-generated
code in your editor, debug into it,
copy it out if you want
to customize it further, and so on.
Attached macros are classified
into five different roles
based on how they augment
the declaration they are attached to.
The case detection macro we just discussed
is a "member" attached macro,
meaning that it creates new members
in a type or extension.
Peer macros add new declarations alongside
the declaration they're attached to,
for example,
to create a completion-handler version
of an async method or vice-versa.
Accessor macros can turn a stored property
into a computed property,
which can be used to perform
specific actions on property access
or abstract the actual storage
in a manner similar to,
but more flexible than property wrappers.
And attached macros
can introduce attributes
onto specific members of a type,
as well as add new protocol conformances.
Several attached macro roles
can be composed together
to achieve useful effects.
One important example
of this is with observation.
Observation has
always been a part of SwiftUI.
To be able to observe changes
to the properties of a class,
one need only make the type
conform to ObservableObject,
and mark every property at-Published,
and use the ObservedObject
property wrapper in your view.
That's a bunch of steps,
and missing a step can mean
that the UI doesn't update as expected.
We can do better
with macro-based observation.
Attaching the Observable macro
to a class provides observation
for all of its stored properties.
There is no need
to annotate each stored property
or worry about what happens if you don't
because the Observable macro
handles it all.
The Observable macro works
through composition of three macro roles.
Let's dive
into how these roles work together.
Each macro role corresponds
to a specific way
in which the Person class
is augmented by the Observable macro.
The member role introduces
new properties and methods.
The member attribute role
will add the @ObservationTracked macro
to the stored properties
of the observed class,
which in turn expands to getters
and setters to trigger observation events.
Finally, the conformance role
introduces the conformance
to the Observable protocol.
This may look like a lot of code,
but it's all just normal Swift code,
and it's neatly folded away
behind the Observable macro.
Whenever you need
to see how any macro expands
to better understand
its effect on your program,
it's right there
at your fingertips in Xcode.
Use the "Expand Macro" action
to see the macro-expanded source code
in your editor.
Any error messages
within macro-generated code
will automatically show the expanded code,
and you can step into and out of it
with your debugger.
Swift macros provide a new tool
for enabling more expressive APIs
and eliminating boilerplate
from your Swift code,
helping unlock Swift's expressive power.
Macros type-check their inputs,
produce normal Swift code,
and integrate
at defined points in your program,
so their effects are easy to reason about.
And any time you need
to understand what a macro did,
its expanded source code
is right there in your editor.
We've just scratched
the surface of macros.
"Expand on Swift macros" will go deep
into the design of Swift macros
to answer all of those questions
you must have.
And you can get hands-on
implementing your own macros
with "Write Swift macros."
I can't wait to see what new macros
the Swift community will build.
Ben: From the start, Swift was designed
to be a scalable language.
Swift's design emphasizes expressivity
with clear and concise code
that is low on ceremony
and easy to read and write.
By leveraging Swift's powerful features,
like generics
and native concurrency support,
frameworks like SwiftUI or SwiftData
let you quickly achieve
the results you want,
leaving you more time
to focus on what matters.
Despite these high-level
capabilities though,
Swift is also efficient.
It compiles natively,
and its use of value types
and of reference counting
instead of garbage collection means
it's able to achieve
a low memory footprint.
This scalability means we're able
to push Swift to more places
than was previously possible
with Objective-C,
to low-level systems,
where previously you might expect
to have to use C or C++.
This means bringing Swift's clearer code
and critical safety guarantees
to more places.
We recently open sourced
the start of a rewrite
of the Foundation framework in Swift.
This initiative will lead
to a single shared implementation
of Foundation on both Apple
and non-Apple platforms.
But it also meant rewriting large amounts
of Objective-C and C code in Swift.
As of MacOS Sonoma and iOS 17,
there are new Swift-backed implementations
of essential types like Date and Calendar,
of formatting
and internationalization essentials
like Locale and AttributedString,
and a new Swift implementation
of JSON encoding and decoding.
And the performance wins
have been significant.
Calendar's ability to calculate
important dates can take better advantage
of Swift's value semantics
to avoid intermediate allocations,
resulting in over a 20% improvement
in some benchmarks.
Date formatting
using FormatStyle also gained
some major performance upgrades,
showing a massive 150% improvement
in a benchmark of formatting
with a standard date and time template.
Even more exciting are the improvements
to JSON decoding in the new package.
Foundation has
a brand-new Swift implementation
for JSONDecoder and JSONEncoder,
eliminating costly roundtrips
to and from the Objective-C
collection types.
The tight integration of parsing JSON
in Swift for initializing Codable types
improves performance too.
In benchmarks parsing test data,
the new implementation
is between two and five times faster.
These improvements came from both
reducing the bridging cost
from the old Objective-C
implementation to Swift,
but also by the new Swift-based
implementations being faster.
Let's look at one benchmark as an example.
In Ventura, calling enumerateDates
from Objective-C was slightly faster
than calling it from Swift
because of bridging costs.
In MacOS Sonoma,
calling that same functionality
from Swift is 20% faster.
Some of that speed up comes
from eliminating bridging costs,
but the new function implementation itself
is also faster,
as seen when calling it from Objective-C.
This particular date calculation
is not overly complex,
so this is a great way
of seeing the reduction
in overhead between the two languages.
Now, sometimes,
when you're operating at lower levels
of the system,
you need more fine-grained control
to achieve a necessary level
of performance.
Swift 5.9 introduces
some new opt-in capabilities
that help you
achieve this level of control.
These capabilities focus
on the concept of ownership, that is,
what part of the code "owns" a value
as it passes around your application.
To see when you might want
to use these features,
let's first look at some example code.
Here we have a very simple wrapper
for a file descriptor
that would allow us to give low-level
system calls a nicer Swift interface.
But there’s still some easy ways
to make mistakes with this API.
For example, you might try to write
to the file after you’ve called close.
And you have to be careful
to always close it manually
by calling the close method
before the type goes out of scope.
Otherwise, you would get a resource leak.
One solution would be to make it a class
with a deinit that closes it automatically
when the type goes out of scope.
But that has different downsides,
like making an additional
memory allocation,
which is usually not a big problem,
except in some very constrained
systems contexts.
Classes also have reference semantics.
You might unintentionally end up sharing
a file descriptor type across threads,
leading to race conditions,
or store it unintentionally.
But let's go back
and look at the struct version.
Really, this struct also behaves
like a reference type.
It holds an integer
that references the true value,
which is an open file.
Making a copy of this type could
also lead to unintentional sharing
of mutable state across your app
in ways that could lead to bugs.
What you want is to suppress
the ability to make a copy of this struct.
Swift types, whether structs or classes,
are copyable by default.
This is the right choice most of the time.
While excessive unnecessary copies can
sometimes be a bottleneck in your code,
it's better to spend the time
finding those bottlenecks
in instruments occasionally
than to be constantly bothered
by the compiler requiring you
to be explicit about those copies.
But sometimes that implicit copy
isn't what you want--in particular,
when making copies of a value
might lead to correctness issues,
like with our file descriptor wrapper.
In Swift 5.9, you can do that
with this new syntax that can be applied
to struct and enum declarations
and that suppresses the implicit ability
to copy a type.
Once a type is non-copyable,
you can give it a deinit,
like you can a class,
that will run when a value
of the type goes out of scope.
Non-copyable types can also be used
to solve the problem of calling close,
and then using other methods.
The close operation
can be marked as consuming.
Calling a consuming method
or argument gives up ownership
of a value to the method you called.
Since our type is not copyable,
giving up ownership means
you can no longer use the value.
By default, methods in Swift
borrow their arguments, including self.
So you can call the write method,
which borrows the file descriptor,
uses it to write out to the buffer,
and after that,
ownership
of the value returns to the caller,
and you can call another method,
like close.
But since close
has been marked as consuming,
not the default of borrowing,
it must be its final use.
This means, if you close the file first
and then attempt to call another method,
like write, you'll get an error message
at compile time,
rather than a runtime failure.
The compiler will also indicate
where the consuming use occurred.
Non-copyable types
are a powerful new feature
for systems level programming in Swift.
They're still
at an early point in their evolution.
Later versions of Swift will expand
on non-copyable types in generic code.
If you're interested
in following along with this work,
it's being actively discussed
on the Swift forums.
Doug: A key to Swift's success has been
its interoperability with Objective-C.
From the start, developers have been able
to take incremental steps towards Swift
adoption in their existing code bases,
mixing in Swift a single file
or module at a time.
But we know a lot of you don't
just have code written in Objective-C.
Many apps also have
core business logic implemented in C++,
and interfacing
to that has not been so easy.
Often it meant adding an extra
manual bridging layer, going from Swift,
through Objective-C,
and then into C++, and all the way back.
Swift 5.9 introduces the ability
to interact with C++ types
and functions directly from Swift.
C++ interoperability works just like
Objective-C interoperability always has,
mapping C++ APIs
into their Swift equivalents
that you can use directly from Swift code.
C++ is a large language
with its own notions of ideas
like classes,
methods, containers, and so on.
The Swift compiler
understands common C++ idioms,
so many types can be used directly.
For example, this Person type
defines the five special member functions
expected of a C++ value type:
Copy and move constructors,
assignment operators, and a destructor.
The Swift compiler
treats this as a value type
and will automatically call the right
special member function at the right time.
Additionally,
C++ containers like vectors and maps
are accessible as Swift collections.
The result of all of this is that we
can write straightforward Swift code
that makes direct use
of C++ functions and types.
We can filter over the vector
of Person instances,
calling C++ member functions
and accessing data members directly.
In the other direction,
using Swift code from C++
is based on the same mechanism
as with Objective-C.
The Swift compiler
will produce a "generated header"
that contains a C++ view
on the Swift APIs.
However, unlike with Objective-C,
you don't need to restrict yourself
to only using Swift classes
annotated with the objc attribute.
C++ can directly use most Swift types
and their full APIs,
including properties,
methods, and initializers,
without any bridging overhead.
Here we can see how C++
can make use of our Point struct.
After including the generated header,
C++ can call Swift initializers
to create Point instances,
invoke mutating methods,
and access both stored
and computed properties,
all without any change
to the Swift code itself.
Swift's C++ interoperability
makes it easier than ever
to integrate Swift
with existing C++ code bases.
Many C++ idioms can be
directly expressed in Swift,
often automatically, but occasionally
requiring some annotations
to indicate the desired semantics.
And Swift APIs
can be directly accessed from C++,
no annotation or code changes required,
making it possible to incrementally adopt
Swift throughout a code base
using any mix of C, C++, and Objective-C.
C++ interoperability is an evolving story,
guided by the C++
interoperability workgroup.
For more information,
please see the "Mix Swift and C++" talk,
or join us in the discussion
on the Swift forums.
Interoperability
at the language level is really important,
but you also have
to be able to build your code.
And having to replace your existing
build system with Xcode
or the Swift Package Manager
to even get started with Swift
can be just as big a barrier
as rewriting a large amount of code.
That's why we worked
with the CMake community
to improve Swift support in CMake.
You can integrate Swift code
into your CMake build by declaring Swift
as one of the languages for the project
and putting Swift files into a target.
More importantly, you can mix C++
and Swift within a single target,
and CMake will be sure
to compile each separately
and link all of the appropriate
supporting libraries and runtimes
for both languages.
This means you can start adopting Swift
in your cross-platform C++ projects today,
file by file or target by target.
We're also providing a sample repository
with CMake projects containing Swift
and mixed C++/Swift targets,
including using
the bridging and generated headers,
to help you get started.
A few years ago,
we introduced a new concurrency model
into Swift based
on the building blocks of async/await,
structured concurrency, and actors.
Swift's concurrency model
is an abstract model,
which can be adapted
to different environments and libraries.
The abstract model has two main pieces:
Tasks and actors.
Tasks represent a sequential unit of work
that can conceptually run anywhere.
Tasks can be suspended whenever
there's an "await" in the program,
and then resume
once the task can continue.
Actors are a synchronization mechanism
that provide mutually-exclusive access
to isolated state.
Entering an actor
from the outside requires an "await"
because it may suspend the task.
Tasks and actors are integrated
into the abstract language model,
but within that model,
they can be implemented in different ways
to fit different environments.
Tasks are executed
on the global concurrent pool.
How that global concurrent pool decides
to schedule work is up to the environment.
For Apple's platforms,
the Dispatch library provides
optimized scheduling
for the whole operating system,
and has been extensively tuned
for each platform.
In more restrictive environments,
the overhead of a multithreaded
scheduler may not be acceptable.
There Swift's concurrency model
is implemented
with a single-threaded cooperative queue.
The same Swift code works
in both environments
because the abstract model
is flexible enough to map
to diverse runtime environments.
Additionally, interoperability
with callback-based libraries
was built into Swift's async/await support
from the beginning.
The withCheckedContinuation operations
allow one to suspend a task,
and then resume it later
in response to a callback.
This enables integration
with existing libraries
that manage tasks themselves.
The standard implementation of actors
in the Swift concurrency runtime
is a lock-free queue of tasks
to execute on the actor,
but it's not the only possible
implementation.
In a more restricted environment,
one might not have atomics,
and instead could use another
concurrency primitive such as spinlocks.
If that environment were single-threaded,
no synchronization is needed,
but the actor model maintains
the abstract concurrency model
for the program regardless.
You could still take that same code
to another environment
that is multi-threaded.
With Swift 5.9,
custom actor executors allow
a particular actor to implement
its own synchronization mechanism.
This makes actors more flexible
and adaptable to existing environments.
Let's take an example.
Here we consider an actor
that manages a database connection.
Swift ensures mutually-exclusive access
to the storage of this actor,
so there won't be any concurrent access
to the database.
However, what if you need more control
over the specific way
in which synchronization is done?
For example, what if you want
to use a specific dispatch queue
for your database connection,
perhaps because that queue is shared
with other code
that hasn't adopted actors?
With custom actor executors, you can.
Here we've added
a serial dispatch queue to our actor
and an implementation
of the unowned executor property
that produces the executor
corresponding to that dispatch queue.
With this change,
all of the synchronization
for our actor instances
will happen through that queue.
When you "await" on the call
to pruneOldEntries from outside the actor,
this will now perform a dispatch-async
on the corresponding queue.
This gives you more control
over how individual actors
provide synchronization,
and even lets you synchronize an actor
with other code
that isn't using actors yet,
perhaps because it's written
in Objective-C or C++.
The synchronization of actors
via dispatch queues is made possible
because dispatch queue conforms
to the new SerialExecutor protocol.
You can provide your own synchronization
mechanism to use with actors
by defining a new type
that conforms to this protocol
which has only few core operations:
Checking whether the code is already
executing in the context of the executor.
For example,
are we running on the main thread?
Extracting an unowned reference
to the executor to allow access to it
without excess reference-counting traffic.
And the most core operation, enqueue,
which takes ownership
of an executor "job."
A job is part
of an asynchronous task that needs
to run synchronously on the executor.
At the point where enqueue is called,
it's the responsibility
of the executor
to run that job at some point
when there's no other code running
on the serial executor.
For example, enqueue for a dispatch queue
would call dispatch async on that queue.
Swift Concurrency has been in use
for a few years now,
and its abstract model
consisting of tasks and actors
covers a large range
of concurrent programming tasks.
The abstract model itself
is quite flexible,
making it adaptable
to different execution environments,
from iPhones to Apple Watches,
to servers and beyond.
It also allowed customization
at key points to enable it to interoperate
with code that hasn't fully adopted
Swift Concurrency yet.
For more information,
please see our "Behind the Scenes" talk,
as well as "Beyond the basics
of Structured Concurrency."
I want to wrap up with a bit
of a case study of Swift operating
in an environment very different
from the iOS or MacOS apps
where we are used to seeing it.
FoundationDB is a distributed database,
providing a scalable solution
for very large key-value stores
running on commodity hardware
and supporting a variety of platforms,
including MacOS, Linux, and Windows.
FoundationDB is an open-source project
with a large code base written in C++.
The code is heavily asynchronous,
with its own form
of distributed actors and runtime
that provides a critically important
deterministic simulation environment
for testing purposes.
FoundationDB was looking
to modernize their code base
and found Swift to be a good match
for its performance,
safety, and code clarity.
A complete rewrite would be a big,
risky endeavor.
Instead,
we leveraged Swift's interoperability
to integrate into the existing code base.
For example,
here's a part of the C++ implementation
of FoundationDB's "master data" actor.
There's a lot going on here,
and you don't need
to understand all of this C++.
However, I'd like to point out
a few key aspects of the code.
First, C++ doesn't have async/await,
so FoundationDB has
their own preprocessor-like approach
to emulate it.
Like many C++ code bases,
they've implemented
their own C++ Future type
to manage asynchronous tasks.
These pair with explicit messaging
to send responses to the requests.
Note the careful pairing of sending
a reply with returning from the function.
Finally, FoundationDB has
its own reference-counted smart pointers
to help manage memory automatically.
We can implement this whole thing
much more cleanly in Swift.
[breathes deeply]
That's better.
This function can be directly implemented
as an async function in Swift.
We have a normal return type
and normal return statements
to provide the response to this request,
so you can't ever be out of sync.
We have an "await"
to indicate the suspension point
in the same manner
as all other Swift async code.
And this Swift code ties in
with the C++ Future type
adapted using continuations.
We're using a number of C++ types here.
The MasterData type in C++ was
using a reference-counted smart pointer.
By annotating the type in C++,
the Swift compiler can use
this type like any other class,
automatically managing
reference counts for us.
Other types,
such as the request and reply types,
are C++ value types
being used directly in Swift.
And the interoperability goes both ways.
This asynchronous function,
and indeed, all the work introduced
by the Swift concurrency model,
run on FoundationDB's
existing deterministic runtime.
So we can get the benefits
of Swift where we want it,
interfacing with the existing C++
to enable gradual adoption throughout.
In this session,
we've covered a lot of ground.
We described features like parameter packs
and macros
that enable more expressive APIs
and can help you write better code faster.
We talked about the use of Swift
in performance-sensitive code
and the introduction of non-copyable types
to provide resource management
without reference-counting overhead.
Then we dove into C++ interoperability,
which provides support for using C++ APIs
in Swift and vice-versa,
making it easier to bring the benefits
of Swift to more of your code.
Finally, we talked about how
Swift's flexible concurrency model
can adapt to myriad environments
across devices and languages
to make concurrency easier and safer.
Parameter packs,
macros, non-copyable types,
and all of the other language enhancements
in Swift 5.9 were designed
and developed openly
through the Swift Evolution process,
and community feedback
was crucial in shaping these features.
Swift 5.9 is the culmination
of countless contributions
from members across the Swift community,
including active design discussions,
bug reports, pull requests,
educational content, and more.
Thank you for making Swift 5.9
the great release it is.
♪ ♪