♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Miquel Estany Rodriguez:
Hi, I'm Miquel Estany Rodriguez.
Lorena Pazmino:
And I'm Lorena Pazmino,
and we're from
the Apple Design team.
Today, we're going to talk
about how to design
spatial user interfaces.
To help you get started
on this platform,
we've built a visual language
that maintains consistency
and familiarity
with our existing platforms,
while also evolving
certain elements to adapt
to immersive
and spatial experiences.
Miquel: We'll start by talking
about the UI foundations
and design principles
to consider
when creating app icons
and interfaces
that are legible and usable
in an environment.
Then we'll go over key concepts
and best practices
to create layouts that are both
ergonomic and easy to target.
And finally, we'll conclude
by showing how this platform
can bring your app
from a screen to spatial,
walking you through
all our system components,
most of which you are
already familiar with
and some that are
completely new.
Let's dive deep
into UI foundation.
These are the core
design principles
we will cover on this section.
Let's start talking
about app icons.
We wanted to keep
home view familiar
and we've gone one step further,
making app icons
three-dimensional
and realistic in your space.
When people look at them,
they expand.
And the system enhance
this visual effect
by adding specular
highlights and shadows
to reinforce the subtle depth
between layers.
So how can you design
a great icon?
First of all,
use multiple layers.
Other platform use layers
to create a parallax effect.
Here, just by using flat layers,
the system can create
this truly 3D effect.
All app icons can have
up to three layers,
a background layer and up to
two foreground layers on top.
Each layer
is a square image,
and their size is
1024 by 1024 pixels.
Both foreground layers should
have a transparent background.
Design your background layer
as an edge to edge square image.
Then all layers will get
cropped by a circular mask.
And finally, when layers
match together,
a glass layer is applied
automatically, adding depth,
specular highlights,
and shadows to them.
Try to keep graphics centered.
If they are too close
to the edge,
they could look
off-center when expanded.
Avoid using large regions
of semitransparent pixels.
Layers with reduced opacity
will blend with the shadow
cast behind it.
And that's how
you can easily create
three-dimensional app icons.
Next,
let's talk about materials.
When people tap your app icon,
apps will launch
in many different places
like this one,
a broad daylight room,
or in a small space
like an airplane,
or at nighttime.
Apps need to adapt
to the lighting conditions
in your surroundings.
They should be easy to place
in the space around you,
easy to use at any distance,
and easy to view
with any lighting conditions.
And that's why we've designed
a new visual language,
the glass material.
This system-defined beautiful
glass window
feels part of
your physical world.
And its unique properties
allow light
from people's surroundings and
virtual content to show through.
In addition, specular
highlights and shadows
reinforce its scale
and position in your space.
And it works as a canvas
for your contained UI,
making it feel lighter
and adding a sense
of physicality to it.
This lightweight material
also gives people a sense of
what might be behind a window,
like other apps or people.
To deliver great
spatial experiences,
it's important to be aware
of your surroundings.
Avoid using solid colors
on windows.
Too many opaque windows
can feel constricting
and make the interface
feel heavy.
Glass responds
dynamically to lighting,
adjusting the contrast
and color balance
to feel part of your space,
like in this transition
from day to night.
Unlike iOS and macOS,
this platform does not have
a distinct light
or dark appearance.
Instead, glass and UI
naturally adapt
when placed in front
of light and dark backgrounds.
System-defined vibrant materials
take great advantage
of this feature,
ensuring your app looks great
across different scenarios
and lighting conditions,
Let's take a look at them.
First, we start
with a glass window.
If you want to separate
sections of your app,
like a sidebar,
use a darker material.
Or a lighter material
to bring attention
to interactive elements,
like buttons.
Or you might even consider
using darker materials
to increase contrast
for standard components,
like input fields.
Here is how Music app looks
with all the UI elements.
As you can see,
text defaults to white.
So, imagine that you want to
design a lock-up like this one,
and you want to add
a lighter button.
It is great to place it
on top of the glass material.
Or if you want
to get more contrast,
use a darker cell behind it.
Try to not stack lighter
materials on top of each other,
as it impacts legibility
and reduces contrast.
Now, I'll show you
how typography
has been precisely adapted
to this platform.
To keep things familiar,
all font styles
use semantic names that work
on all platforms.
They have been tuned
on our point-based unit system,
ensuring they are legible
at any distance.
To learn more,
check out the session
"Principles of spatial design."
We've also modified
some of the font weights
to improve legibility.
Let's take a closer look.
To improve the contrast of text
against vibrant materials,
font weight has been modified
to be slightly heavier.
For example, on iOS,
we use regular weight
for the body text style.
On this platform, we use medium.
And for titles,
instead of semibold,
we use bold,
keeping text clear all the time.
Consequently, the tracking
has been slightly increased
to help with legibility.
In addition to
the well-known font styles
we share across platforms,
we've added two brand-new
font styles that take advantage
of the wide, editorial-style
layouts you can use.
Here is an example of the
Extra Large Title 1 on Arcade.
Cool, right?
Even though windows can scale up
to incredible large sizes,
custom smaller
or lightweight fonts
can still be difficult to read.
To improve that,
consider increasing the weight
or using a typeface designed
for optimized legibility,
like system fonts.
Next, let's talk about
vibrancy.
This is one
of the most important details
to maintain legibility
across the system.
Vibrancy brightens
foreground content
that displays on top
of a material and works
by pulling light and color
forward from what's behind it.
On this platform,
since the background
can be constantly changing,
vibrancy updates in real time
to make sure your text
is always legible.
To show what I mean,
let's look at an example.
Vibrancy works on top
of the glass material,
enhancing legibility
and making system materials
feel richer and sophisticated.
Make sure to use the system
components when possible.
By default, they take advantage
of this vibrancy effect.
Let's pause for a second
and turn vibrancy off.
As we just saw,
vibrancy improves legibility
and how materials look.
Let me turn it on and off
to show you the difference.
Now let's see how
you can take advantage of it.
Use vibrancy
to indicate hierarchy for text,
symbols, and fills.
There are three modes: primary,
secondary, and tertiary.
Use primary for standard text.
Or use secondary for description
text, footnotes, and subtitles.
You've seen the glass material
can be many different colors,
since it shows the color
of what's behind it.
Colorful elements on top
of the glass may be hard to see
if the color
of the glass is similar.
Most of the time, consider using
white text or symbols
so they are always
clearly visible.
If you need to use color,
use it in a background layer
or an entire button
so people can see it.
When possible, use system
color instead of custom color,
as they have been
calibrated for legibility
and dynamically adapt
to maintain hue and contrast
on the glass.
So those are the design
principles and the updates
we've made
to the core components,
like materials, typography,
and vibrancy,
to make sure your app gets
elevated on this platform.
Now I'm going to hand it off
to Lorena who will show you
how to create ergonomic layouts
that are easy to target
as you take your app
from screen to spatial.
Lorena: Thanks, Miquel.
Let's start by exploring
some of the best ways
to position content
so that it feels comfortable.
Then show you
how to properly size content
so that it's easy to target.
And lastly, show you
how to create layouts that work
with our new and beautiful
eye focus feedback.
Because people
primarily interact
with their eyes and hands
on this platform,
it's important
to create experiences
that prioritize people's
physical comfort and safety.
More than ever,
you need to consider
the ergonomics of your design,
ensuring that the placement
of content is intentional
and doesn't cause
eye or neck fatigue.
For example, because of
the neck's range of motion,
it's easier for most people
to turn their head
farther to the right and to the
left rather than up and down.
So keep your UI in people's
field of view and be careful
about placing anything
too high up or too far down.
If you need a large canvas
for your app,
go with a wider aspect ratio
than taller.
For example, in Freeform,
the canvas extends horizontally
and not vertically.
Prioritize having
the most important information
centered in your app
so people can comfortably
view your content.
Now that we've covered best
practices for content placement,
let's talk about content size.
Each person is unique and
our eyes have slight variations
from one person to another,
which is why
elements should use sizes
that are easy to target.
Let's get into the details.
Interactive elements
must have a tap target area
with at least
60 points of space,
so they can be easily selected.
This means that your UI element
can be visually smaller,
like the standard button,
which is 44 points,
as long as you add
enough space around it.
So for this button,
it always needs
to have at least eight points
of empty space around it
so it meets the minimum
of having a target area
of 60 points.
As an easy thing to remember,
if you need to have
several buttons in a stack,
use standard system buttons
with at least 16 points
of spacing in between them.
Now, let's say you needed to use
a visually smaller element,
like a disclosure control.
You can use a mini button,
which is 28 points,
in an area like
the section header.
Even though this button
might look small,
because it has 60 points
of space around it,
it's easy to select.
Let's look at another example.
Here, this button
still has enough space
because the text next to it,
it's not interactive.
Similarly, using large
and extra large buttons
requires less spacing
around them.
So, always remember
to give all interactive elements
at least 60 points of space.
Now that we've talked about
how to size elements
in your layouts,
let's talk about focus feedback.
Focus feedback
is a powerful tool
built into every interactive
element in this platform.
When people look at
system-provided components,
they automatically display
a subtle visual brightening
or hover effect.
This hover effect
allows people to understand
which parts of an interface
are interactive
just by looking at them.
When an item becomes inactive,
like the Share button,
it no longer gives
focus feedback.
This gives people confidence
that they are focused
on the intended element,
which means that they can tap
their fingers to select it.
As you go creating layouts,
it's important to take
the hover effect into account.
For example, if you're creating
a list or a menu,
you need to account for
a small amount of padding
in between each item to avoid
having the hover effect overlap.
Four points is recommended.
As you're designing a lock-up,
include a shape
that will allow the system
to display the hover effect
as people focus on it.
Here, we have some images
with text below them.
Each lock-up is a single
interactive element.
You need to define
a custom region
so it can brighten
as people look at it.
This helps them understand
the entire area
is a single element
that can be selected.
And remember to keep
that small space
in between each
containing shape.
Another thing to keep in mind
is to ensure nested elements
have relative corner radii
and padding
that keeps them concentric
with each other.
To help you figure out
how to size your corners,
you can use this simple formula.
Corner radius
of the nested element,
plus the padding in between it
and the outer container,
gets you
the outer corner radius.
And remember, in order
to keep your corners smooth,
be sure to set them
to be continuous corners.
Throughout the system,
every element is concentric
to one another,
starting from the relationship
of the window to the elements
in the corners.
So remember to keep
nested elements
concentric with each other,
as this will help them feel
like they belong together.
Now that we've covered best
practices to create layouts,
let's take a closer look
at the components
that you'll be using.
In this section,
we'll show you
how to take your knowledge
from existing platforms
and apply it
to spatial computing.
We'll start with a brief
overview of our input model,
then dive deep into how
to set up the core structure
of an app with a window,
tab bar, and sidebar.
Then we'll talk about
a new way of presenting content.
And last,
we'll explore modalities.
Let's get started with inputs.
As we've mentioned earlier,
people interact with a device
with their eyes, hands,
and voice.
They do this
by looking at elements
and tapping their fingers,
primarily from a distance.
However, people can also select
an element directly
by touching it.
Additionally, people can also
connect a keyboard
or a trackpad,
allowing them to interact
with the system
with a wide array of inputs.
Interacting with
the system feels magical,
but it means elements
have to provide
the appropriate feedback
for each of those models.
All of our system components
have been built
to support each input.
So, use system components.
They help you create interfaces
quickly so you can spend time
finding what makes your app
unique in this new medium.
To learn more about inputs,
be sure to check out
the session
"Design for spatial input."
Now, let's walk through
some examples.
If you're familiar with iOS,
many of the components
in this platform
will look familiar to you.
Let's begin with a window,
tab bar, and sidebar.
Let's start with the core
structure of an iOS app.
You need a window,
which has an opaque material
and provides the canvas
for all elements to sit on top.
As Miquel said, the window
is made of the glass material
with a window bar below
that allows people
to move your app fluidly
in their space.
Similarly, on top of it,
you'll have your content.
On iPhone at the bottom
of the window,
laid out horizontally,
you have a tab bar controller
for your main navigation,
giving people quick access
to the top-level sections
of your app
with just a single tap.
Here, the tab bar is vertical,
floating in a fixed position
on the left side of the window.
Designed to be out of the way
and easy to access,
it's there where you need it,
allowing people to see
where they are in your app
without taking away
from your main content.
In general, you want
to keep those feeling light,
so avoid having
more than six items.
When people look at the tab bar,
they can quickly select an item.
And if they look at it
for a little longer,
It automatically expands,
showing labels for each section.
When people look away,
it automatically closes again,
allowing people to focus
on the content.
If you need to provide
sub navigation,
like with an album
in this example,
sidebars live in the window
alongside the tab bar.
This gives people a clear sense
of where they are in that tab.
Now that we've covered
the core structure of an app,
let's get into
a new presentation style
we've added, ornaments.
In the Photos app, we have
a floating accessory element
at the top center to navigate
between years, months, and days.
On this platform, since we're
not bounded by a screen,
that accessory is placed
as an ornament at the bottom,
slightly in front of the window.
This gives people
additional persistent controls
that are easy to access
using depth to create hierarchy.
Ornaments are a great way
to present toolbars.
They allow people
to perform quick actions
related to the content
in a convenient location.
And they add a bit of depth
to your app.
Since ornaments are usually
a collection of buttons
and sit on their own
glass container,
this is a perfect place
to use borderless buttons.
In this case, it's clear that
these are interactive elements,
and they'll still get the hover
effect as people look at them.
Here's another great use of
an ornament in the Music app.
The Now Playing controls are
presented as an ornament
that persists no matter
where you are in the app.
This allows people to search
for their next song
while being able to control
their music.
When ornaments sit at
the bottom edge of the window,
place them so they overlap
the bottom edge by 20 points.
This helps ornaments
to feel like they're integrated
with the main window without
blocking too much content.
And they look really nice,
pulling colors from the content
through the glass as you scroll.
Ornaments can appear
and disappear entirely.
However, it is only recommended
while focusing on a single
piece of content.
For example, looking at
a photo or watching a movie.
Like in this example,
with just a tap,
we give people quick access
to important controls
without distracting them
from the main experience.
Additionally,
ornaments can expand,
presenting additional content,
or even have their own
navigation hierarchy.
So find where ornaments
fit in your app.
They are flexible
and give your app depth
without occluding content.
Now that we've
covered ornaments,
let's get into menus,
popovers, and sheets.
On iPad, menus align
to the leading edge
of the invoking button,
and the button dims
as the menu opens.
Popovers point to
the invoking element
and the navbar becomes inactive.
On this platform,
menus and popovers
can expand outside the window.
They appear centered
by default,
ensuring that
the content always appears
right where the user is looking.
One thing
to always keep in mind
is to change the button
that invokes them
to its selected state.
On this platform,
we always use black labels
on a white background
to show buttons are selected.
This helps people
have clear feedback
of which button
invoked the popover
without the need of arrows.
As a general rule
on this platform,
avoid using buttons
with white backgrounds
unless they are selected.
Finally,
let's talk about sheets.
On this system, sheets
are presented as modal views,
and they appear
at the center of the app.
Modals contain the same
Z position as the parent window.
The parent window
pushes back and dims.
This helps focus the experience
and prevents people
from interacting
with the parent view
until the sheet is dismissed.
If you need to present
another sheet, a secondary modal
can appear in front
with an additional layer
of dimming
pushing everything back.
So let's look at it again
from the side.
Because we're stacking
all these elements in Z,
consider using push navigation
for nested views.
Here's a quick example
of push navigation in a modal.
The secondary view will present
a back button instead of close.
Also, notice how
the close and back buttons
are in the top-left corner.
As a system pattern,
always place close buttons
on the top-left corner.
Miquel: Now that you understand
the fundamentals
of building an app
and using system components,
think about
what makes your app special
and how to take advantage
of the space outside windows
to create rich spatial moments.
For example, in Photos,
we kept the browsing
experience familiar
and focused on creating new ways
to experience your images,
like Spatial Captures,
which give you an immersive way
to relive your moments
and experience content
in a unique and special way.
We've covered how to design
and develop accessible,
familiar, and intuitive apps,
using materials that blend
with your surrounding.
Interfaces that take advantage
of different layers of depth
and endless components that are
not only visually appealing,
but also familiar and easy
to use in this new platform.
All our system components
have been designed to support
our wide array of inputs,
while maintaining consistency
with the rest of the Apple
ecosystem so you,
as a designer or developer,
can focus on generating
groundbreaking immersive
and spatial experiences.
Thanks for watching.
Both: Ciao!
♪