♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hey, I'm Pau Sastre Miguel,
a Software Engineer at Apple.
Today I'm going to talk
about how to create
immersive experiences
with Metal on xrOS.
This year,
with the launch of xrOS,
you will be able to create
immersive experiences
with familiar technologies
in the Apple ecosystem.
With RealityKit you will be able
to create experiences
that blend your virtual content
with the real world.
On the other hand,
if your application
will take the user
into a fully immersive
experience,
xrOS also enables you
to completely replace
the real world content
with your own virtual content.
When creating fully
immersive experiences,
you have a few choices when it
comes to your rendering method.
You can still use RealityKit,
or if you prefer, you can choose
Metal and ARKit APIs.
RecRoom is a great example
of an application
that provides a fully
immersive experience
using CompositorServices
to create a rendering session,
Metal APIs to render frames,
and ARKit to get
world and hand tracking.
They were able to bring support
to all these technologies
thanks to the Unity editor.
If you'd like to write
your own engine,
the CompositorServices API
gives you access
to Metal rendering on xrOS.
You can combine it with ARKit,
which adds world tracking
and hand tracking,
to create a fully
immersive experience.
CompositorServices is the key
to configure your engine
to work on xrOS.
I'll show you how to setup
the render loop
and then how to render
one frame.
Finally, I'll show you
how to use ARKit
to make your experience
interactive.
Start with the architecture
of an xrOS app.
You'll get the most
out of today's session
if you have previous experience
with Metal APIs
and Metal rendering techniques.
If you haven't
used Metal before,
check out the code samples
and documentation
over in
developer.apple.com/Metal.
When you create immersive
experiences on xrOS with Metal,
you'll start with SwiftUI
to create the application
and the rendering session.
After creating
the rendering session,
you can switch to a language
you might be more familiar with,
like C or C++, to define
the inner parts of the engine.
You start by creating
a type that conforms
to the SwiftUI app protocol.
To conform to this protocol,
you will define the list
of scenes in your app.
On xrOS, there are three main
scenes types.
The window type provides
an experience similar
to 2D platforms like macOS.
The volume type renders content
within its bounds
and it coexists in the Shared
Space with other applications.
And ImmersiveSpace allows you
to render content anywhere.
Whenever you render
fully immersive experiences
with Metal, you will choose
the ImmersiveSpace type.
ImmersiveSpace is a new
SwiftUI Scene type
available on xrOS.
It serves as the container
for fully immersive experiences.
To learn how to use
ImmersiveSpace,
check out the session "Go beyond
the window with SwiftUI."
When you create an
ImmersiveSpace scene,
your application provides
the content by using a type
that conforms to the
ImmersiveSpaceContent protocol.
Often, when creating content
for an ImmersiveSpace Scene,
applications
will use RealityKit.
It uses CoreAnimation
and MaterialX under the hood.
But if instead, you'd like
to use the power of Metal
to render the content
of your application,
you've got another option.
The CompositorServices API
uses Metal and ARKit
to provide immersive
rendering capabilities
to your application.
The new CompositorServices API,
introduced in xrOS,
provides a Metal
rendering interface
to be able to render the
contents of an ImmersiveSpace.
With CompositorServices,
applications can render
directly into
the compositor server.
It has a low IPC overhead
to minimize latency,
and it is built from
the ground up
to support both
C and Swift APIs.
When using CompositorServices,
the ImmersiveSpaceContent
is called CompositorLayer.
To create a CompositorLayer
you will need to provide
two parameters.
The first one is the
CompositorLayerConfiguration
protocol.
This protocol defines
the behavior and capabilities
of your rendering session.
The second
is the LayerRenderer.
This is the interface
to the layer rendering session.
Your application
will use this object
to schedule and render
new frames.
When writing an immersive
experience with Metal,
start by defining the app type.
As the scene type,
use ImmersiveSpace.
For the content type,
use a CompositorLayer.
Once the CompositorLayer
is ready to render content,
the system will call
the application
with the instance
of the rendering session.
Here is a good place
to create the instance
of your custom engine.
Now that you have
the engine instance,
you can create the render thread
and run the render loop
by calling start.
One thing to take into account
when defining the scene list
in your application,
is that by default
SwiftUI creates a window scene,
even if the first scene in
your app is an ImmersiveSpace.
To change that default behavior,
you can modify the info plist
of your app.
You can add the key
UIApplicationPreferred
DefaultSceneSessionRole
to your
application scene manifest
to change the default
scene type of your application.
If you are using a space
with a Compositor SpaceContent,
you will use
CPSceneSessionRole
ImmersiveSpaceApplication.
After setting up
the application,
and before getting
in the render loop,
you'll tell CompositorServices
how to configure
the LayerRenderer.
To provide a configuration
to the CompositorLayer,
you will create a new type
that conforms to the
CompositorLayerConfiguration
protocol.
This protocol allows you
to modify the setup
and some of the behavior
of the rendering session.
The CompositorLayerConfiguration
provides you two parameters.
The first one
is the layer capabilities.
It enables you to query
what features are available
on the device.
Use the capabilities to create
a valid configuration.
And the second parameter is the
LayerRenderer Configuration.
This type defines
the configuration
of your rendering session.
With the configuration,
you can define
how your engine maps
its content into the layer,
enable foveated rendering,
and define the color management
of your pipeline.
Now, I'll talk about how
each of these properties
will affect your engine.
The first one
is foveated rendering.
The main goal of this feature is
to allow you to render content
at a higher
pixel-per-degree density
without using
a bigger texture size.
In a regular display pipeline,
the pixels are distributed
linearly in a texture.
xrOS optimizes this workflow
by creating a map
that defines what regions
in a display
can use a lower sampling rate.
This helps reduce the power
required to render your frame
while maintaining the visual
fidelity of the display.
Using foveation whenever
possible is important,
as it will result
in a better visual experience.
A great way to visualize
how foveation affects
your rendering pipeline
is using Xcode's Metal Debugger.
With Metal Debugger, you can
inspect the target textures
and rasterization rate maps
being used
in the render pipeline.
This capture shows
the contents of the texture
without scaling for
the rasterization rate map.
You can notice the different
sample rates by focusing
in the regions of the texture
that are more compressed.
With the attachment viewer
options in Metal Debugger,
you can scale the image
to visualize the final result
that the display will show.
Compositor provides
the foveation map
using an MTLRasterizationRateMap
for each frame.
It is a good practice
to always check
if foveation is supported.
This will change depending
on the platform.
For example,
in the xrOS simulator,
foveation is not available.
To enable foveation,
you can set isFoveationEnabled
on the configuration.
The second property
is LayerRenderer layout.
This property is one of the most
important configurations
for your engine.
It defines how each display
from the headset
gets mapped into the rendered
content of your application.
Each eye first maps
into a Metal texture
provided by Compositor.
Then Compositor provides
the index of which slice
to use within that texture.
And finally, Compositor provides
the viewport to use
within that texture slice.
The LayerRenderer layout lets
you choose different mappings
between the texture slice
and viewport.
With layered,
Compositor will use one texture
with two slices
and two viewports.
With dedicated, Compositor
will use two textures
with one slice
and one viewport each.
And finally with shared,
Compositor will use one texture,
one slice, and two different
viewports for that slice.
Choosing which layout
to use will depend
on how you set up
your rendering pipeline.
For example, with layered
and shared, you will be able
to perform your rendering
in one single pass,
so you can optimize
your rendering pipeline.
With shared layout,
it might be easier
to port existing code bases
where foveated rendering
is not an option.
Layered layout
is the optimal layout
since it allows you to render
your scene in a single pass
while still maintaining
foveated rendering.
The last configuration property
to discuss is color management.
Compositor expects the content
to be rendered
with extended linear display
P3 color space.
xrOS supports
an EDR headroom of 2.0.
That is two times the SDR range.
By default, Compositor does not
use a pixel format
that is HDR renderable,
but if your application
supports HDR,
you can specify rgba16Float
in the layer configuration.
If you want to know more about
how to render HDR with EDR,
checkout the session "Explore
HDR rendering with EDR."
To create a custom configuration
in your application,
start by defining a new type
that conforms to the
CompositorLayerConfiguration
protocol.
To conform to this protocol,
add the makeConfiguration
method.
This method provides
the layer capabilities
and a configuration
you can modify.
To enable the three properties
I mentioned before,
first check if foveation
is supported.
Then check what layouts
are supported in this device.
With this information,
you can set a valid layout
in the configuration.
In some devices
like the simulator,
where the Compositor
only renders one view,
layered won't be available.
For foveation, set it to true
if the device supports it.
And finally, set the colorFormat
to rgba16Float
to be able to render
HDR content.
Returning to the code that
created the Compositor layer,
you can now add
the configuration type
you just created.
Now that the rendering session
is configured,
you can set up the render loop.
You'll start by using
the LayerRenderer object
from the CompositorLayer.
First, you'll load the resources
and initialize any objects
that your engine will need
to render frames.
Then check the state
of the layer.
If the layer is paused,
wait until the layer is running.
Once the layer is unblocked
from the wait,
check the layer state again.
If the layer is running,
you'll be able to render
a frame.
And once that frame
is rendered,
check the layer state again
before rendering the next frame.
If the layer state
is invalidated,
free the resources
you created for the render loop.
Now, it's time to define
the main function
of the render_loop.
Until now I've been using Swift
since the ImmersiveSpace API
is only available in Swift.
But from here I will switch
to C to write the render loop.
As I mentioned, the first step
in the render loop
is to allocate and initialize
all the objects you'll need
to render frames.
You'll do this by calling
the setup function
in your custom engine.
Next, is the main section
of the loop.
The first step is to check
the layerRenderer state.
If the state is paused,
the thread will sleep until
the layerRenderer is running.
If the layer state is running,
the engine will render
one frame.
And finally, if the layer
has been invalidated,
the render loop will finish.
The last step of the
render_loop function
will be to clear any
used resources.
Now that the app is going
through the render loop,
I'll explain how to render
one frame.
Rendering content
in xrOS is always
from the point of view
of the device.
You can use ARKit to obtain
the device orientation
and translation.
ARKit is already
available on iOS,
and now xrOS is introducing
a whole new API,
which has additional features
that can help you create
immersive experiences.
With ARKit, you can add
world tracking, hand tracking,
and other world sensing
capabilities
to your application.
The new ARKit API is also built
from the ground up
to support C and Swift APIs,
which will allow
for an easier integration
with existing rendering engines.
To learn more about ARKit
on xrOS,
check out "Meet ARKit
for spatial computing."
Within the render loop,
it's time to render one frame.
When rendering a frame,
Compositor defines
two main sections.
The first one is the update.
Here's where you will do
any work that is not
input-latency critical.
This can be things like updating
the animations in your scene,
updating your characters,
or gathering inputs
in your system
like hand skeleton poses.
The second section of the frame
is the submission section.
Here's where you will perform
any latency-critical work.
You'll also render any content
that is headset-pose
dependent here.
In order to define the timing
for each of those sections,
Compositor provides
a timing object.
This diagram defines
how the timing affects
the different frame sections.
The CPU and GPU tracks represent
the work that is being done
by your application.
And the Compositor track
represents the work done
by the Compositor server
to display your frame.
The timing type
from Compositor Services
defines three main time values.
First is the optimal input time.
That is the best time to query
the latency-critical input
and start rendering your frame.
Second is
the rendering deadline.
That is the time by when
your CPU and GPU work
to render a frame
should be finished.
And third is presentation time.
That is the time when your frame
will be presented on display.
In the two sections
of your frame,
The update section should happen
before the optimal input time.
After the update, you will wait
for the optimal input time
before starting
the frame submission.
Then you will perform
the frame submission,
which will submit
the render work to the GPU.
It is important to notice
that the CPU and GPU work
needs to finish before
the rendering deadline,
otherwise the Compositor server
won't be able to use this frame
and will use a previous
one instead.
Finally, on the
rendering deadline,
the Compositor server
will composite this frame
with the other layers
in the system.
Back to the render loop code,
it's time to define
the render_new_frame function.
In your engine's
render_new_frame function,
you will first query a frame
from the layerRenderer.
With the frame object,
you will be able to predict
the timing information.
Use that timing information
to scope the update
and submit intervals.
Next, implement
the update section.
Define this section by calling
the start and end update
on the frame.
Inside, you will gather
the device inputs
and update the contents
of the frame.
Once the update is finished,
wait for the optimal input time
before starting the submission.
After the wait,
define the submission section
by calling start
and end submission.
Inside this section,
first query the drawable object.
Similar to CAMetalLayer,
the drawable object
contains the target texture
and the information
that you will need to set up
the render pipeline.
Now that you have your drawable,
you can get the final timing
information
that Compositor will use
to render this frame.
With the final timing,
you can query the ar_pose.
It is important to set the pose
in the drawable
since it will be used
by the Compositor
to perform reprojection
on the frame.
Here I'm getting the pose
by calling the get_ar_pose
function in my engine object.
But you will need to implement
the contents of this function
using the ARKit
world tracking APIs.
The last step of the function
will be to encode
all the GPU work
and submit the frame.
Inside the submit_frame,
use the drawable
to render the contents
of the frame as usual.
Now that the render loop
is rendering frames,
it's time to make your immersive
experience interactive.
This video shows how
RecRoom using Unity
is already taking advantage
of the ARKit and Compositor APIs
to add interactivity
to their application.
There are two main input sources
driving this interaction.
ARKit's HandTracking
is providing the hand skeleton
to render virtual hands.
And pinch events
from the LayerRenderer
are driving
the user interactions.
In order to make
the experience interactive,
you'll first gather
the user input
and then apply it to
the contents of your scene.
All this work will happen in
the update section of the frame.
There are two main
input sources,
the LayerRenderer and
the ARKit HandTracking provider.
With the LayerRenderer,
you will get updates every time
the application receives
a pinch event.
These updates are exposed
in the form of spatial events.
These events contains
three main properties.
The phase will tell
you if the event is active,
if it finished,
or if it got canceled.
The selection ray
will allow you to determine
the content of the scene
that had the attention
when the event began.
And the last event property
is the manipulator pose.
This is the pose of the pinch
and gets updated every frame
for the duration of the event.
From the HandTracking API,
you will be able to get skeleton
for both the left
and right hands.
Now, it's time to add
input support in the code.
Before gathering the input,
you will decide
if your application is rendering
virtual hands
or if it uses passthrough hands.
Add the upperLimbVisibility
scene modifier
to the ImmersiveSpace to make
the passthrough hands
visible or hidden.
To access the spatial events,
go back to where you defined
the CompositorLayer
render handler.
Here, register a block
in the layerRenderer
to get updates every time
there is a new spatial event.
If you are writing
your engine code in C,
you'll map the SwiftUI
spatial event to a C type.
Inside the C code,
you can now receive
the C event collection.
One thing to keep in mind
when handling
the spatial event updates
is that the updates get
delivered in the main thread.
This means that you will use
some synchronization mechanism
when reading and writing
the events in your engine.
Now that the events
are stored in the engine,
it's time to implement
the gather input function.
The first step
is to create an object
to store the current
input state for this frame.
This input state will store
the events that you received
from the LayerRenderer.
Make sure that you are
accessing your internal storage
in a safe way.
As for the hand skeleton,
you can use the hand tracking
provider API from ARKit
to get the latest hand anchors.
And now that your application
has input support,
you have all the tools
at your disposal
to create fully immersive
experiences on xrOS.
To recap, with SwiftUI,
you will define the application.
With CompositorServices
and Metal, you will set up
the render loop
and display 3D content.
And finally, with ARKit,
you will be able to make
your experience interactive.
Thank you for watching!
♪