♪ ♪
Kay: Hey, this is Kay
from Privacy Engineering.
I'm here to introduce a new and exciting
Privacy and Security feature in Xcode
that will help you automatically verify
the integrity of your dependencies.
At Apple,
we believe that privacy should be
at the core of everyone's
development process,
as much as it is
at the core of our products.
Dependency signature verification
within Xcode
will help app developers
protect their apps
and dependency authors
protect the SDKs they distribute.
Apps are developed using a range of SDKs.
For example, the iOS SDK.
Some are made by Apple,
some by app developers
to use across all of their apps,
and some that app developers obtain
from other sources.
These form the app's supply chain
and can include frameworks,
Swift source files,
and other types of dependencies.
Using third party SDKs can make
app development significantly easier
and can provide extended functionality.
However, this does introduce risks.
Supply chain security is the process
of mitigating these risks.
You have the responsibility
of protecting your users
by being selective
of what dependencies you include
and to ensure that you don't
accidentally use a version
that has been maliciously modified.
This responsibility also extends
to SDK authors
who include other SDKs
as part of their development.
The processes and tools available
to mitigate these risks
can be burdensome or complex
to do manually.
Dependency signature verification
is a new Xcode feature
that can make this task easy
and automatic.
Now that you know
what supply chain security is,
I will talk about the role
that digital signatures play
in protecting developers
and in helping reduce this burden.
To begin, I will give you an overview
on how Apple's code signing
technology works
and what Xcode now does
to verify the signatures
of your dependencies.
And then I will talk about
how app developers can use this feature
to ensure that their dependencies
haven't been compromised.
And finally,
I will discuss what SDK authors can do
to improve the security of the ecosystem.
I'll get started with how Apple's
code signing technology works.
When you are developing an SDK
for app developers to use,
you want to ensure that no one can modify
or tamper with it
during its distribution
to your SDK clients.
Code signing is a mechanism
to cryptographically link
the final complied binary
and the associated metadata
such as the Info.plist
or the privacy manifest for your framework
or, for certain types of distribution,
the source code itself,
with your developer identity.
At a high level, code signing works
by first generating a Code Directory hash,
also known as the CDHash,
of your compiled binary.
To then sign this hash,
you use your developer identity.
This identity is represented
by your developer certificate.
It is made up of a private key
that is used for code signing
and a public key that is distributed
as part of the signature.
This signature can be
tied back to your identity.
This identity is then used
to sign the hash
and can be combined
with a secure timestamp
that is used to validate
that the signature was generated
at a specific point in time.
This ensures that if anyone tampers
with your SDK,
the signature will no longer be valid.
It also allows app developers to verify
that it was you who signed it,
using the certificate that is
embedded into the signature.
A common type of dependency
that you may use in your app
is the xcframework.
With xcframeworks, the signature resides
within the _CodeSignature directory.
The code signature protects
the integrity of all the files
inside your final xcframework,
including the privacy manifest files
that are mentioned in the WWDC23 video
"Get started with privacy manifests."
It's possible for you to manually verify
these code signatures
for every version of every xcframework
you include within your app,
but this is a time-consuming process
and places a burden on you
in order to get the security benefits.
Signature verification is
a new feature in Xcode
that automatically handles
the verification
of your app's dependencies
and protects your supply chain integrity
by alerting you if an issue is detected.
Xcode 15 now has tools to help you
automatically track the identities
used to sign any xcframeworks
that you include in your project.
Xcode now shows a new section
in the Inspector
that displays the signature status
for the xcframeworks
you include within your app.
This section includes information
about the signature,
such as the author's identity.
It will show
whether the xcframework is signed
by an Apple Developer Program identity,
signed by a self-signed certificate,
or currently unsigned at all.
In addition,
Xcode will record the identity
the first time you use the xcframework
and verify that it does not change
during later builds.
For different developer identities,
Xcode provides
differing levels of features
based on the trust in the identity
that was used
for a particular xcframework.
For Apple Developer Program identities,
Apple is able to check the validity
of the certificate used,
including if it's been revoked,
and ensure that multiple developers
can't register with the same name.
If the certificate used is self-signed,
app developers should confirm
its validity and authenticity
directly with the dependency author.
When the xcframework author's
signing certificate expires,
Xcode is able to automatically validate
that a new certificate
for Apple Developer Program identities
is from the same developer.
For self-signed certificates,
you will need to manually verify
that this change was legitimate,
as there is no attestation
of the certificate by a trusted party,
like Apple.
When the dependency is signed
by an Apple Developer Program identity,
Xcode will verify it on build
and show you an alert
if the signature is not valid,
the identity has changed,
or the xcframework was signed
after the certificate had expired.
Xcode will also alert you
if the Apple Developer Program certificate
has been revoked by Apple.
This can happen if Apple determines
that the developer account is malicious.
These alerts will be rare
and will automatically ensure
you don't build your app
until you've resolved the issue.
If this does happen, Xcode will offer
to let you remove the xcframework
from the project.
For self-signed identities,
Xcode will still compare
the certificate's SHA-256 fingerprint
with the one that was previously added
to the project.
It will show you an alert
if the identity has changed
or if the contents of the dependency
have been modified.
You may need to contact
the xcframework author
to ensure the fingerprint matches
what they have used,
or an xcframework author
can publish this information.
And that's how digital signatures work
on xcframeworks.
Next, let me show you
how an app developer can
use this feature in Xcode.
To demonstrate, I'm going to use
the Backyard Birds sample app.
It provides a digital birding experience
where you own multiple backyards,
are able to put bird food and water out,
and see when bird visitors show up.
I plan on using an xcframework
called BirdFeeder
to automate the food and water
refilling process.
The author of the BirdFeeder xcframework
has signed the most recent release.
Here, I've added the BirdFeeder
into my project.
For xcframeworks, Xcode 15 will have
a "Signature" view in the Inspector.
This displays
the certificate signing information,
showing the team details.
The xcframework developer's identity
will be stored in the project
the first time it is seen.
During the build,
Xcode will validate that the identity used
to sign the BirdFeeder xcframework matches
the expected identity in the project.
It built successfully.
To simulate a supply chain attack,
I'll pretend that someone gave me
an updated version
of the BirdFeeder xcframework
that they said added
many new exciting features
and gave better performance.
This could also happen to you
when you download an xcframework
from a website
that you do not fully trust.
Here, I replaced my previous version
with this updated one.
When I build my app,
Xcode verifies the signatures
of all the xcframeworks within the app.
The build failed, pointing out
that BirdFeeder developer's identity
does not match what was
previously recorded in the project.
Selecting the error offers an alert
explaining that the developer's identity
has changed,
showing how the expected identity compares
to what is present in the new version.
In this case,
it shows that the expected certificate was
an Apple Developer Program Certificate,
but the one in the project
uses a self-signed certificate.
This could mean
that the xcframework has been compromised
or the change was legitimate.
For example,
they might have transferred ownership
of the xcframework to another developer.
It's always safe to cancel
if you're unsure.
This gives you time to investigate
if the change was genuine.
Xcode protects you and your apps
by ensuring that if this change happens,
you will be notified automatically.
In this case, the change wasn't expected,
so I will move this new version to trash
in Xcode.
However, if you know
the change is legitimate–
for example,
the developer has communicated this to you
via a verified public channel–
then you could accept the change.
Finally, I will talk about
what this feature means to SDK authors.
It is important for SDK authors
to cryptographically sign SDKs
because it allows an app developer
to confirm the identity
and guarantees that the code has not been
altered or tampered with
after it was signed.
Both of these properties are
extremely important
for building trust
and safely distributing SDKs.
As discussed earlier,
there are two types of identity
that you can use:
Apple Developer Program and self-signed.
Members of the Apple Developer Program
should use the certificates included
as part of this program
to ensure the trust of your SDK clients.
You should use
the Apple Distribution certificate
if you publish your SDK
or the Apple Development certificate
if you are distributing test versions.
Enterprise Program members
should use their iOS Distribution
or App Development certificates.
When Apple issues a certificate to you,
Apple is attesting to the fact
that you are a legitimate member
of the Apple Developer Program
and have met
all the necessary requirements
to obtain the certificate.
This includes verifying your identity
and adherence to Apple's policies
and guidelines
around privacy and security.
If you manually revoke
the certificate used to sign an SDK,
you will need to release
an updated version
signed using a valid certificate,
as Xcode will no longer be able
to verify the signature
when a developer attempts
to build their app.
An SDK that has been signed
with an Apple Developer Program
certificate
has a baseline level of trust
and ensures that the SDK
has not been tampered with.
On top of that,
because Apple is the trusted authority,
certificate validation is
automatically handled
when a new certificate is generated.
At the start of this video,
I discussed how code signing works
and how it includes a signature
within your SDK
using your developer identity.
Let's now go through how you can do this
using the codesign tool.
You can sign your xcframeworks
using the command here
and your Apple Developer Program identity.
The timestamp flag is included
to ensure that the signature contains
a secure timestamp
that is attested to by Apple.
However, if you aren't a member
of the Apple Developer Program,
you can generate a self-signed certificate
and use it with the codesign command.
You are responsible for sharing
with your SDK clients
the fingerprint of this certificate
so that you can verify
the xcframework was signed by you.
Developers including your SDK in their app
will be able to confirm
that the xcframework was signed by you
by using the new feature
included in Xcode.
If you always sign
the SDKs you distribute,
this new feature in Xcode
will help your SDK clients
get more confidence in their supply chain.
Doing this is simple.
You can start straight away
with versions of your frameworks
that you've already published
with no new build required.
This even works
using a self-signed certificate
if you are not currently a member
of the Apple Developer Program.
You can then do this for all new versions
of your xcframeworks
by including the codesign command
in a build script,
so that you no longer need to worry.
For app developers,
Xcode 15 will automatically help you
ensure the integrity and security
of your apps' underlying SDKs.
Making sure
that all SDK signatures are verified
is an important aspect
of responsible app development
and protecting your users.
You can help by encouraging
the developers in your supply chain
to start signing the SDKs they publish.
For SDK authors, start signing your SDKs
to ensure their security and authenticity.
By signing your code,
you establish trust with your SDK clients,
showing them that you take
their security and privacy seriously.
Happy app development!
This is Kay, signing off.
♪ ♪