Julia: Hello!
My name is Julia.
I'm a SwiftUI Engineer.
Recently, we've introduced SwiftData,
a new way to persist your model layer
in Swift.
In today's session,
let's see how to seamlessly
integrate SwiftData in a SwiftUI app. We
will discuss the new SwiftUI features
that allow for smooth integration
with SwiftData models.
To cover your basics,
watch the "Meet SwiftData"
session first if you haven’t already.
To see how SwiftData
and SwiftUI play together,
let’s build a flashcards app.
For some time,
I’ve wanted to make a tool that can
help me remember dates
and authors of great inventions,
and SwiftData is perfect for this task.
It will help to persist
the flashcard decks,
so I can open and click through them
whenever I got a minute.
I want this app to work everywhere:
on Mac, iPhone, Watch,
and TV, and SwiftData has my back.
It is available across all the platforms.
This is a code-along.
During this session,
I will be building an app with you.
Hit pause now,
and download the companion Xcode projects:
an archive with the prepared
starting point, and the finished one.
Open the starter project,
and go to the ContentView file.
Throughout this session,
we will leverage a new Xcode feature,
embedded interactive live Previews
for Mac.
In the Previews section,
there's a grid with some flash cards.
A click on any card
transitions into a view
where we can scroll the cards one by one.
Do you remember who invented the compiler?
Click the card.
It flips and gives an answer!
The app is populated with
sample cards stored in memory,
and if we run the app and add new ones,
they will disappear when we close the app.
This is where SwiftData comes in.
We will use it
to persist the flashcards we create.
Today, we will talk about
everything you need to know
to start using SwiftData,
checking off one item after another
in this to-do list
that I put together for us.
You have just met the app we will build.
Next, we’ll take a look at
the starter project and its model class.
Then, step by step,
we will convert and amend it
to use SwiftData as its storage.
We’ll learn how to expand the model class
to become SwiftData model,
how to query the data and update the view
on every change in the model layer,
create and save models,
and conveniently bind UI elements to them.
And at the end, as a bonus,
we’ll see how easy it is
to create a document-based app
when SwiftData takes care of the storage.
In the starter project,
I defined a Card model
that represents a single flash card,
some views,
and supporting files to save us time.
Every card stores the text for the front
and back sides and the creation date.
It is a pretty typical model.
Let’s update it so
that SwiftData can store it for us.
First, import SwiftData into this file.
And next, the main change
that we need to make
is adding the @Model macro
to the definition.
And now, the class is fully persistable
with SwiftData.
No more typing.
That’s it!
And even more: with @Model,
the Card gets conformance
to the Observable protocol, and we will
use it instead of ObservableObject.
Remove the conformance
to the Observable object
as well as @Published property wrappers.
We previously used
the ObservedObject conformance
to edit the card directly from the UI
in the CardEditorView file.
To adopt Observable here,
we replace the "ObservedObject" property
wrapper with "Bindable."
It allows the text fields to bind directly
to the card's front...
and back text.
Done!
New Observable macro
and Bindable property wrapper
allow to effortlessly set up the data flow
in an application
with even less code than before.
When a View uses a property
of an Observable type in its body,
it will be updated automatically
when the given property changes.
And it has never been that easy
to bind a model's mutable state
to UI elements!
I encourage you to watch
the WWDC23 session,
"Discover Observation with SwiftUI."
You'll be surprised how Observable
simplifies the data flow code
with or without SwiftData.
And that’s all you need to know
about the models.
Nothing more.
How cool is that?
Next, to query models from SwiftData
and display them in the UI,
let’s switch to ContentView.
Instead of the SampleDeck.contents,
we will display
the cards that SwiftData has.
And there’s a single change
that I need to make
to bind the cards array
to SwiftData storage:
replace @State property wrapper
with @Query.
That’s it!
As we can see in the preview,
there are no more cards to display,
probably because we haven’t saved any.
Use @Query whenever you want
to display models,
managed by SwiftData, in the UI.
@Query is a new property wrapper
that queries the models from SwiftData.
It also triggers the view updated
on every change of the models,
similarly to how @State would do that.
Every view can have
as many queried properties as it needs.
Query offers lightweight syntax
to configure sorting,
ordering, filtering,
and even animating changes.
Under the hood, it uses a model context
of the view as the data source.
How do we provide @Query
with a model context?
We'll get one from a model container.
SwiftUI vends a new view
and scene modifier
for a convenient setup
of the view’s ModelContainer.
To use SwiftData, any application
has to set up at least one ModelContainer.
It creates the whole storage stack,
including the context
that @Query will use.
A View has a single model container, but
an application can create and use
as many containers as it needs
for different view hierarchies.
If the application does not set up
its modelContainer,
its windows and the views it creates can
not save or query models via SwiftData.
Many applications
need a single model container.
In this case, you can set it up
for the whole window group scene.
The window and its views
will inherit the container,
as well as any other windows created
from the same group.
All of these views will write
and read from a single container.
Some apps need a few storage stacks,
and they can set up several
model containers for different windows.
SwiftUI also allows for a granular setup
on a view level.
Different views in the same window
can have separate containers,
and saving in one container
won’t affect another.
Now, let's set up the modelContainer to
provide the Query with a source of data.
I open the app definition...
And set a model container
for app's windows.
Note that the subviews can create,
read, update,
and delete only the model types
listed in the view modifier.
And we are done with the setup!
Although, I want to take one extra step:
provide my previews with sample data.
In the app, I have defined
an in-memory container with sample cards.
Let's open the "PreviewSampleData" file
and include it in the target.
This file contains the definition
of a container with the sample data.
I will use it in the ContentView
to fill my preview with sample cards.
[no audio]
Now that @Query has a source of data,
the preview displays the cards!
And this is all the setup that’s required
to have SwiftData stack ready
and generate a preview.
Next, I want to make sure
that SwiftData tracks and saves
the new cards that I create, as well as
the changes made to the existing ones.
To do that,
I will use the model context of the view.
To access the model context,
SwiftUI offers a new environment variable.
Similarly to model container,
each view has a single context,
but an application, in general,
can have as many as it needs.
In our app,
the context is already configured.
This environment variable
was populated automatically
when we set the model container earlier.
Let’s switch back to Xcode.
We will need to access the modelContext
to save and update the cards.
[no audio]
We insert the newly created card
in the model context
to make SwiftData aware
of the model we want to store.
You might think that
after inserting the model,
you need to save the context,
calling "modelContext.save(),"
but you don't need to do that.
A nice detail about SwiftData is
that it autosaves the model context.
The autosaves are triggered
by UI-related events and user input.
We don’t need to worry about saving
because SwiftData does it for us.
There are only a few cases
when you want to make sure
that all the changes
are persisted immediately,
for example, before sharing the SwiftData
storage or sending it over.
In these cases, call "save()" explicitly.
Now that our app can save
and query the cards,
let’s create one!
I run the app...
and press plus button to create a card.
Let's add that Compiler card
that we saw before.
[no audio]
Now, let’s quit the app, launch it again,
and see if our new card is there.
And here it is!
Now you know how to access the model
context of the view and add cards.
Done!
Let’s open a new window.
It displays the same deck
as the first one, which makes sense,
since both windows use the same model
container and access the same data.
It would be nice, though,
if the app could open different
flash card decks in different windows.
Essentially, it means that I want to treat
every deck as a separate document.
Then, I can share
these documents with friends.
Document-based apps is a concept
used on macOS, iOS, and iPadOS.
It describes the certain types of
applications that allow users to create,
open, view, or edit
different types of documents.
Every document is a file,
and users can store, copy, and share them.
And I am excited
to let you know that SwiftUI
supports SwiftData-backed document apps.
Let’s try this approach.
I open the FlashCardApp file.
Document-based apps exist
on iOS and macOS,
and on these platforms, we'll switch
to using the DocumentGroup initializer.
[no audio]
I will be passing in
the model type Card.self,
content type, and a view builder.
Let's take a short detour and talk
about the second parameter,
content type, in more detail!
SwiftData Document-based apps
need to declare custom content types.
Each SwiftData document
is built from a unique set of models
and so has a unique representation
on disk.
In the context of documents,
you can think of a content type
as of a binary file format, like JPEG.
Another type of documents, a package,
is a directory with a fixed structure
on disk, like an Xcode project.
For example, all the JPEG images
have the same binary structure.
Otherwise, photo editors
wouldn’t know how to read them.
Similarly, all the Xcode projects
contain certain directories and files.
When the user opens the deck,
we need the operating system
to associate the deck format
and file extension with our app.
That’s why we need
to declare the content type.
SwiftData documents are packages:
if you mark some properties
of a SwiftData model
with the “externalStorage” attribute,
all the externally stored items
will be a part of the document package.
In the UTType+FlashCards file,
I have a definition
of the new content type,
so we can conveniently use it in code.
We'll put the same definition
in the Info.plist.
We are about to declare a new content type
in the operating system.
We need to specify the file extension
to help to distinguish
the card decks created by our app
from any other documents.
For this sample app,
we’ll use “sampledeck” as an extension.
I will also add a short description,
like Flash Cards Deck.
The identifier should be exactly the same
as the one in the code.
Because SwiftData documents are packages,
we have to make sure our type conforms to
com.apple.package.
And now, let’s use
the content type that we declared.
I am returning to the app definition
and passing the content type
to the DocumentGroup.
The view builder looks identical.
Notably, we don’t set up
the model container.
The document infrastructure
will set up one for each document.
Let's run the application
and see how it looks now!
The app launches
with the open panel.
Standard behavior for Document-based
applications.
I'll create a new document
and add a card there.
The document now has a toolbar subtitle
indicating that it has unsaved changes.
I press Command+S,
and the save dialog appears.
Note that the deck will be saved
with the same file extension
that we put in the Info.plist earlier.
I'll save the new deck,
and here it is, my first flashcards deck,
on the Desktop.
I can also press Command+N
to create a new deck,
or Command+O to open one.
These shortcuts,
as well as many other features,
Document-based applications
get automatically.
Just to recap, today, we’ve learned how
to use SwiftData storage in SwiftUI apps.
We talked about the new @Model macro,
@Query property wrapper,
and the new Environment variable
for model context,
and saw how easy it is to use SwiftData
as a storage for your documents.
Thanks for joining me today,
and have fun building apps!
♪ ♪