♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Nathan Gitter: Welcome
to our session
on the principles
of spatial design.
I'm Nathan Gitter.
Amy DeDonato: And I'm
Amy DeDonato,
and we're designers
on the Apple Design team.
Today, you'll learn
how to design
for a spatial operating system.
Here, the world around you
is an infinite canvas
for amazing new apps and games.
Nathan: With depth, scale,
natural inputs,
and Spatial Audio,
you can create experiences
that were
never possible before.
You can enhance an existing
app with key moments,
or create something
entirely new.
You can go to a new place
or share an experience
with someone special.
Amy: There's a lot to learn,
and we're here to help you
get started.
Nathan: We'll help you
make your ideas a reality
and create experiences
people will love.
Today, we'll talk about
how to make great spatial apps.
We'll start with the basics,
learning how to keep
your apps familiar.
Next, we'll talk about what
it means to be human-centered.
Then we'll learn how to use
dimension to take advantage
of the space and push apps
even further with immersion.
Last, we'll learn how to make
apps that feel authentic
to the platform.
Let's jump right in.
With so many new possibilities,
strike a balance
with what's familiar.
Common elements like sidebars,
tabs, and search fields
help people find the music
they're looking for.
On a spatial platform,
people should be able to find
their music just as reliably,
using elements they recognize
and know how to use.
We place interfaces
within windows
so people can comfortably
see them and use them.
People are familiar
with app windows,
but on this platform,
windows live in your space
and feel like part
of your surroundings.
In this first section,
we'll talk about windows,
learn how to find
the right size for them,
and discuss the points system.
Let's start with windows.
We've designed windows
with a new visual language.
The glass material provides
contrast with the world,
gives people more awareness
of their surroundings,
and adapts to different
lighting conditions.
The system provides controls to
move, close, and resize windows.
People can grab the window bar
to move windows anywhere
around them.
Notice how they always turn
to face someone when moving.
This keeps interfaces
easy to read and easy to use.
When they release, the window
stays in its final position.
Next, let's talk about how to
choose a size for your windows.
Windows are designed to fit
comfortably within people's view
but they are super flexible,
stretching to fit any size.
Choose a comfortable window size
based on your content.
For example, Safari is tall
so people can see
more of the web page,
and Keynote is wide
to fit full-size presentations.
Windows can have
flexible shapes too.
Use tab bars and toolbars
to push outside the window,
like here in the Music app.
These controls are layered
above the main window,
so they're always accessible
and provide more room
for the content.
Or use multiple sections to
separate controls from content.
Here in Safari,
the navigation bar is set apart
from the web page
to let the page take the focus.
And windows can change size too.
When the sidebar
is opened in Safari,
the window grows,
showing more controls
without covering the web page.
Windows aren't
bound by a screen,
so they should remain
smaller when possible
to avoid blocking
too much of people's view.
Think about how your app
can be flexible and dynamic,
changing its shape and size
based on the context.
Designing apps for this platform
is a ton of fun.
If you need a larger canvas,
you can give yourself
a larger canvas.
And like other platforms,
apps can have multiple windows,
which are useful
in certain cases.
They can display content
side by side,
like viewing multiple
web pages at once,
or show distinct actions
meant to be used together.
Here in Keynote,
when playing a presentation,
the slides are in one window,
large and far away,
while the presenter display
is in a smaller window nearby.
This lets people place
the presenter display
where they want while keeping
the slides nice and large.
Ideally, keep your app's
interface in a single window.
Multiple windows
can quickly become a lot
for people to manage.
Next, let's talk about points.
To make sure our
interfaces scale well,
we design with points.
This is a concept you're
probably already familiar with.
Points are the way
we specify the size
of interface elements,
describing our interfaces
in a way that adapts
to other screens.
On this platform,
as people move windows,
they scale larger
as they move away
and scale smaller
as they move closer to them.
This keeps interfaces
legible and usable.
And if you're used to points
on other platforms,
they're a familiar way
to set the size
of interface elements
like buttons
with the same units
you already know.
Design your interface
with points
and it will work
at any distance.
Learn more about designing
interfaces in the session
"Design Spatial
User Interfaces".
Next, let's talk about
how we can design apps
that are human-centered.
Good design is always
human-centered,
but now this takes on
a whole new meaning.
People wear the device,
use their eyes and hands
to interact,
and experience apps
through their own view
in their own space.
When designing spatial apps,
think about what someone can see
and how they might need to move.
Let's start with
what people can see.
When people wear the device,
they see the world
in front of them.
This is their field of view.
It's easiest to see things
in the center,
so place the most
important content there.
And the field of view is wide,
so use landscape layouts.
Here's an example.
In Safari, when people want
to see all their tabs at once,
we spread them out in a grid.
This layout is wide to match
people's field of view.
The tabs scale down so they're
not too far from the center,
and the tabs on the sides
turn inward
so they're easier to read.
But people don't keep
their head perfectly still,
they look around.
This means we can
extend content further
for immersive experiences,
but in general,
keep your main content
within the field of view,
or else it's difficult to read
or comprehend all at once.
Designing with
people at the center
also means to design
with ergonomics in mind.
The placement of your content
has a big effect
on how people react physically.
So place objects comfortably
in all dimensions.
By default, windows are placed
along a natural line of sight
to encourage a healthy
and comfortable posture.
When placing your own content,
place it relative
to the person's head
in the direction they're facing.
This helps people see
and interact with your content
and accounts for people
of different heights
and in different positions,
like laying back on a couch.
Most of the time,
place content away from people,
a bit further than arm's reach,
to encourage people
to interact at a distance.
Avoid placing content behind
people or extremely high or low
unless it's part of
an immersive experience.
Not everyone
will be seated in a way
where they can move around
to use your app.
And avoid anchoring content
to people's view.
This makes things feel stuck
and can be disorienting.
Instead, anchor content
in people's space.
This gives them the freedom
to look around naturally.
While wearing the device, people
can also get up and walk around.
But we recommend creating
stationary experiences
that require minimal movement.
This makes your apps
easier to use for everyone.
Unless it's a core part
of your experience,
people should be able
to use your app
without needing to move at all.
Sometimes people do move
to a new seat in their room
or to face
a different direction.
When they settle, they can
press and hold the Digital Crown
to recenter.
This moves content
back in front of them.
Your app doesn't need
to provide a special way
to bring back windows
or reset the scene.
Instead, rely on this system
as a way to reposition
your app's content.
Next, let's talk about
giving your app dimension.
We'll discuss the space
that's available for your app,
and after that,
how to use depth and scale.
Let's start with space.
Great apps take advantage
of the space around people.
And while the canvas
is infinite,
people's physical space
may be limited.
Design your app to work well
in any amount of space,
because you don't know where
someone might be using it.
Also be careful not
to constrain your app
by the physical space available.
Let's see how this works
with the TV app.
Here, a window is moved
through a chair in the room.
The chair is still visible
while the window is moving
to make it easy to place.
When the window is released,
the content becomes visible
so people can see
and use the app.
With windows,
you don't need to worry
about how they fit
into someone's space
since the system
handles this for you.
When it's time to watch a movie,
the video takes over
the entire window
and passthrough is darkened.
Dimming is a simple yet
powerful way to maximize space.
Even though the movie might
overlap the physical room,
dimming helps people
focus on the content.
This is a great balance.
People are still aware
of their surroundings
without being limited by them.
And at any time,
people might open an Environment
extending beyond the dimensions
of their physical room.
And if your app needs
more space to fit big content,
you can create your own
larger-than-life experience.
Here, we created
an immersive cinema
to fit a huge movie theater.
We'll talk more later about Full
Space experiences like these.
Giving apps dimension
means using depth.
On this spatial platform,
depth is a new variable.
It's a powerful tool
for hierarchy and focus.
Let's look at some examples.
Depth affects how we relate
to objects in space.
Content far away
can be nice and large
and encourages people
to interact at a distance.
Nearby objects
invite interaction
and are easier to inspect
at different angles.
A small movement allows us to
see the object from all sides.
A great use of depth
is to create hierarchy.
Let's take another look
at the TV app.
In the immersive cinema,
the playback controls
are placed small and nearby.
Even though they're small,
it's still clear that
they control the movie.
If they were placed
on the movie screen,
they would look too large
and out of place.
Nearby elements like these
can remain small
but still take visual precedence
over large objects far away.
Depth needs to be reinforced
with visual cues
like light and shadow.
Some objects emit light, like
the movie screen we just saw.
The light shines
onto the floor and ceiling,
highlighting its position
in the room.
Any object that appears
to emit light
should shine color
onto nearby objects.
And most other objects
should cast a shadow,
like this window over the table.
This grounds them
and makes them look
more integrated into the space.
Any custom objects in your app
should cast shadows too.
In most cases,
prefer subtle depth.
It's easy to overdo,
making things look
distracting or unrealistic.
Subtle depth between
elements is often enough
to direct people's attention.
Notice how when
a modal appears,
the window pushes back slightly
to bring attention to it.
The depth is subtle,
but effective.
And not everything needs depth.
Text, for example,
can be distracting and difficult
to read when it's 3D,
especially at an angle.
Keep text flat when used
as an interface element.
Like depth, scale is a new way
to emphasize your content.
Small objects feel personal
and lightweight.
Large objects feel impressive,
like a giant movie
playing over a lake.
Increasing the scale
completely changes
the feeling of the movie.
Some objects are best viewed
at their real-life scale.
For example, a shopping app
may want to display products
as they appear in real life.
Explore different scales
for your content.
Try making things really big
or try them really small,
and see how scale makes it feel.
To push your app even further,
it's time to leverage immersion.
To tell you more, here's Amy.
Amy: Thanks, Nathan.
Now let's talk about
how to make your app immersive.
Immersive experiences
extend beyond a window
and transform
the world around you.
We'll explore
the immersion spectrum,
essential tips for creating
great immersive apps,
and how to keep people
comfortable.
First, the immersion spectrum.
On this platform,
an app can be dynamic.
It can fluidly transition
between different
states of immersion,
depending on where people
are in your experience.
This spectrum offers
so much flexibility.
You can enhance someone's view
or bring them to a new place
and everything in between.
Your app can be within
a window in the Shared Space
alongside other apps.
Or if it needs more room,
it could run in a Full Space,
where other apps are hidden.
Try to start your app in
a window in the Shared Space.
This will give people control
over how immersed
they want to be.
Let's look at an example.
In Keynote,
the app opens in a window.
But when it's time
to play the slideshow,
we use dimming to bring focus
to this presentation.
Dimming is a simple way
to create contrast
between your content
and people's surroundings
without taking them
out of their space.
When it's time to rehearse
the presentation,
we can bring people
onto the big stage
fully immersing them
within the theater.
Life-size experiences like these
require more room,
so Keynote is now in a Full
Space and other apps are hidden.
Here the app takes someone
to a new place
that they can see
all around them.
But Full Space moments might
not take someone to a new place.
They can exist within
their own space as well.
Here it feels like you're
looking out over the ocean
while you still see
your surrounding room.
You can design rich,
immersive experiences
without taking over
someone's entire view.
This is also helpful
if they need to see their hands
to use a keyboard or controller.
Immersive apps
can also feel connected
to people's
physical surroundings.
Here, a big welcome moment
casts a shadow across the table,
making "hello" feel like
it's really there.
If your experience relates to
someone's physical surroundings,
remember to keep
your design flexible.
Not everyone's space
is the same,
and spaces tend to change
over time,
so make sure your experience
can adapt to work well anywhere.
Now, some essential tips for
creating great immersive apps.
When designing
immersive experiences,
there's a new consideration.
People can look around and pay
attention to different things,
but if too much is happening
all at once,
they might feel overwhelmed
or unsure of what to do.
Which is why it's important
to guide people's focus
toward parts of your experience
that matter the most.
In the Mindfulness app,
your focus is guided toward
a single object in space.
While you could look
in any direction,
your attention is drawn here,
through motion,
spatialized audio,
and colorful materials.
When it's time
for deeper reflection,
we gently expand the flower
to fully surround you.
Remember to design smooth,
predictable transitions
like these
to create continuity
between different states
of your experience.
This will keep people
feeling comfortable
and aware of what's happening.
Another important tip is to
blend thoughtfully with reality.
If your app's in a Full Space,
you can use the shape of a room
to anchor content or create
physical interactions.
An awareness
of someone's surroundings
allows you to blend your content
meaningfully within it.
When you're blending entire
scenes into someone's space,
make sure to use soft edges
to smoothly integrate your app.
This avoids abrupt transitions
and keeps people focused
on your content.
The most inspiring experiences
make things feel alive.
Subtle animation can bring
liveliness to a scene,
like water rippling on a lake
or clouds floating
through the sky.
Subtle motion can transform
a static experience
into something alive
and dynamic.
And to enhance things
even further,
create atmosphere with sound.
With Spatial Audio,
you can anchor sound
to objects in space...
[STARTUP CHIME]
...or create soundscapes
that fully surround people.
[RESONANT SYNTH CHORDS]
To learn more,
check out the session
"Explore Immersive
Sound Design".
One last tip: do more with less.
You can create big impact
with small effects.
In the cinema, a subtle light
reflecting on the floor
and ceiling gives a convincing
sense of space.
You don't need to render all
the details of a real theater
to convey the feeling
of being in one.
Last, let's talk about keeping
people comfortable
and in control.
If you need to move
your immersive app
or someone's position within it,
make sure to avoid large,
fast movement.
This could feel disorienting.
Instead, we recommend fading
out content while it's in motion
and fading it back in
once it's settled.
This will keep people
feeling steady.
If people physically move
in their space,
immersive experiences
will also fade out.
This shows people
their physical surroundings
while they're in motion.
And make sure
to provide a clear way
in and out of
your immersive experience.
Guide people with short,
helpful labels
and recognizable symbols,
like expand and collapse arrows.
Our last principle.
Let's talk about
how to make your app
authentic to the platform.
When creating
any great app experience,
it's important to take advantage
of the unique capabilities
of the device.
On this platform, the best apps
are rich, immersive experiences
that make use of people's space.
Apps shouldn't be quick things
you jump into for a minute.
Freeform, for example,
puts you in a big creative space
where you can see
all of your content at once
to focus on your project.
Think about how you can make
your app worthwhile, engaging,
and distinct enough that people
will welcome your experience
into their space.
Before we wrap up, let's
apply the things we covered
to your own app.
You might be starting
with a new idea
or extending an existing one
to the platform.
With so many possibilities,
start by focusing on one unique
aspect of your app or game
that can be spatial
or immersive.
To do that, find a key moment
that can only
be experienced spatially.
Let's look at how we did this
in the Photos app.
We looked at core features
of the Photos app
people were already familiar
with on existing platforms.
Browsing your Photos library,
rediscovering special memories,
and reliving a place
through panoramas.
We thought finding your favorite
photos should be easy.
A window interface
and familiar navigation
help you get to what
you're looking for quickly.
But when you find
that special shot,
the photo grows big
in your space
and dims your surroundings.
These are the same great
memories on your iPhone,
but seeing them at a lifelike
scale is truly magical.
And when it's time
to view a panorama,
we have a key moment,
taking you back
to a special place to feel like
you're really there.
Here, panoramas transport you
in a way that's only possible
with infinite space.
Think about a key moment
in your own app.
By focusing on
one special feature,
you can make your experience
unique and memorable
with the content
you already have.
Could you enhance a moment
with depth and scale
or transform someone's space?
Help people focus on a task
or evoke a feeling?
You can create
memorable experiences
like reliving a moment
in the past
or seeing from someone
else's perspective.
Rich visuals and high-fidelity
audio make things feel real.
We covered a lot of new things.
We learned how to use
the space around people
to create immersive experiences
that are authentic yet familiar.
To learn more
about spatial design,
other sessions dive deeper
into topics like input,
user interfaces,
SharePlay, and sound.
Nathan: There's a whole new
universe of possibilities,
and we hope these principles
will guide you on your journey.
Amy: Thanks for joining us.
♪