♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello!
I'm Kellie, and I'm a Platform
Compatibility Engineer.
iPadOS and iOS
are powerful platforms.
You already have
a great app built for them,
maybe you even have multiple.
Now you can easily run
those same apps
on Apple's latest platform.
The majority of iOS apps
look and feel great
right out of the box.
For example, check out
the iPad Calendar app
running unmodified
in the simulator.
It looks and feels
just like iPad
and everything works
exactly as I would expect.
I can see different timelines,
zoom into details
about specific events,
and add new ones.
And Maps, which runs
in its iPad version
following the recommendations
I'm about to cover.
I can spin the globe
beautifully.
I can also look up
specific destinations...
...and visit famous landmarks.
In this video, I'll introduce
iPad and iPhone apps
on this new platform.
I'll start by covering
the built-in behaviors
your app gets for free.
Next, I'll talk about
the functional differences
your app should be aware of and
what you should do about them.
Finally, I'll explain
how to decide
whether the Designed for iPad
experience
is best suited
to your app's needs.
This new platform is built
on the foundations of iOS.
We enhance that shared bedrock
with additional system support.
The combination of the two
makes it more than likely
that your app
will run beautifully
without changing anything!
iPad and iPhone apps
are displayed as windows
on this device,
in their light mode style.
The system prefers
the iPad variant of your app
in landscape orientation,
but if your app
only supports iPhone,
the system displays it
with an iPhone aspect ratio
in portrait orientation.
If your app supports
multiple orientations,
a rotation button is provided
above the top-right corner
of your window,
so people can rotate each scene
to their preference.
When you grab
the corners of your app,
the system scales its window,
preserving the aspect ratio.
When you reach the minimum
or maximum size,
the corners bounce
to reflect that.
The scaling is managed
by the system
so your app gets
all of this support for free.
People interact with content on
this device via natural input.
They look at something
and tap their fingers together
to select it or reach out
and touch content directly.
They may also use a Bluetooth
trackpad or game controller.
All of these system-defined
interaction methods
send events that your app
is already familiar with
so you can continue to leverage
the same event-handling
techniques that you already use.
System views like the document
manager and photo picker
match the system appearance
to help your app fit
into the look and feel
of the platform.
If your app supports
Touch ID or Face ID,
LocalAuthentication
automatically forwards
those implementations
through Optic ID
so your app supports the latest
authentication technology
without any additional work
on your part.
Now, there are a few things
that are different
about this platform
compared to iOS.
Apps on this device can be
viewed in portrait or landscape.
That's nothing new
compared to iPad.
But unlike iPad,
there's no notion of rotating
the entire device.
Because the device's orientation
doesn't inform
your app's orientation,
you may want to specify
which orientation
your app prefers for new scenes.
People can still
rotate scenes later
via the system rotation button.
You can express a preference
by adding the new
UIPreferredDefaultInterface
Orientation key
to your app's Info.plist.
If you don't provide one,
the system will use
its default orientation.
This key is unique
to this platform
and will not affect
other platforms.
There are a couple
other plist keys
that also have special meaning
on this device,
even though they're not new.
The system uses
UISupportedInterfaceOrientations
to decide if your app's windows
need a rotation button,
and App Store Connect relies
on UIRequiredDeviceCapabilities
to determine if your app is
compatible with this new device.
All suitable apps are
automatically made available
on the App Store.
If your app relies
on specific features
which are not available
on this device
or if there's a reason your app
doesn't make sense
on this platform,
you can manage availability
in App Store Connect.
For more information,
watch "Explore App Store Connect
for spatial computing."
Take a moment to add those keys
to your Info.plist if necessary
or confirm the existing values
are still accurate
and up to date.
Gestures on this device
work differently
since folks use their eyes and
hands to interact with content.
There are a maximum
of two simultaneous inputs
as each hand
is a distinct touch.
All system gestures that expect
two touches or fewer
work seamlessly.
Custom gesture recognizers
are also supported,
but you may need to update them
to run smoothly
with the natural
input expectations.
One of the most updated
frameworks is ARKit
which has evolved significantly
to be more powerful than ever.
We've designed new APIs and
experiences from the ground up
to account
for fundamental differences
in platform architecture
and privacy needs.
That means your existing
ARViews and ARSessions
won't work on this device
as they do on iPad and iPhone.
Check out
the "Re-imagine your ARKit app
for spatial experiences" video
to learn about all the new ARKit
capabilities you can leverage
by rebuilding your app
for this platform.
Location support for this device
is a lot like iPad:
location can be approximated
via Wi-Fi or shared via iPhone.
More details are provided
in the "Meet Core Location
for spatial computing" video.
Look to Dictate is a convenient
new input technique
that allows people to quickly
navigate through an app
using only their eyes and voice.
When enabled,
a microphone icon
replaces the magnifying glass
in search fields,
and you can look at the
microphone and speak to search.
This API is offered
on search bars.
It's disabled by default
for iPad and iPhone apps
running on this platform to
allow you to verify the behavior
and decide where
you want to enable it.
And it's a no-op
on iOS and iPadOS,
so there's no need
to conditionalize your support
by platform.
You can enable Look to Dictate
in SwiftUI by adding
the .searchDictationBehavior()
modifier
to your searchable view.
For UIKit search bars, set
isLookToDictateEnabled to true.
The best way to handle
all of these changes
is the same way you always have:
use availability checks.
Make sure that a framework
is supported
before calling into it.
Many frameworks even
have those functions built in
for your convenience.
Don't forget to do
the same thing
when accessing configurations
that rely on the presence
of specific hardware.
For example, the headset
has many more cameras
than just the front and back
cameras on iOS devices,
but not all of those
are available for apps to use.
Verify that a camera is present
and supported before you use it.
These practices make your app
more robust on every device,
not just this one.
That's only a sampling
of the framework evolution
on this platform.
Some frameworks have grown a lot
and have videos specifically
dedicated to this device,
like SwiftUI, ARKit,
and RealityKit.
Most of the remaining frameworks
work as they always have
with a few tweaks
to how you adopt them.
Detailed information about
all of the modified frameworks
is available in
the developer documentation.
Now that you have a sense
of what code changes
are necessary for your app,
you're ready for action.
When the xrOS SDK is installed,
Xcode automatically adds
xrOS Device (Designed for iPad)
to the Supported Destinations
for projects that use
the iOS SDK.
If your scheme sets a different
platform or auto for the SDK,
you can add the Designed
for iPad target manually.
Once that's set up,
a run destination
with the matching name
will appear
in the destination picker.
Select that target,
build, and run.
That's all there is to it!
iPad and iPhone apps provide
a fantastic experience
on this device.
Most apps don't need
any changes at all,
thanks to extensive
system support.
Whether you want to stick
with building your app
against the iOS SDK or rebuild
against the xrOS SDK
depends on your goals.
Like I discussed earlier,
there are differences
in which frameworks
are available for each SDK,
as well as differences
in supported features
within each framework.
There are two big things
I want to call out
that are only available
in the iOS SDK:
SpriteKit and storyboards.
If either of these technologies
is integral to your app,
you need to stick
with designing for iPad.
iPad and iPhone apps
are displayed in windows
that feel just like iPad
in their light mode style.
Here's what Maps looks like
when zoomed into
the Sydney Opera House.
Notice how the content
fills all the way
to the edges of the window
but doesn't extend past it,
and all of the colors match
the same light mode style
that Maps uses
on iPad and iPhone.
Apps designed for xrOS
unlock another level
of immersive,
spatial experiences.
Several frameworks,
like ARKit and RealityKit,
have evolved functionality
that's only available
in apps designed
for this platform.
Refer to the other videos
or the documentation
to learn about
all the new experiences
that are possible
thanks to these updates.
In addition to windows,
apps designed for this device
also support volumes
to display 3D objects
in containers
that grow to fit their contents,
as well as Immersive Spaces
for immersive experiences.
Here's what the Keynote
rehearsal space looks like
in headset.
By hiding passthrough
and other apps,
Keynote keeps you fully
immersed and focused
on your presentation.
In both the headset
and the simulator,
apps designed for this platform
use the system look and feel.
Their backgrounds
are a glass material
that grounds people
in their surroundings
and dynamically adjusts
color balance and contrast
to promote legibility.
They can also take advantage
of the new Ornament API.
Like the tab bar on the left and
buttons at the bottom of Photos,
ornaments anchor
to the sides of a window
to enhance its functionality.
And they leave the app more room
to draw within the window.
Most frequently, ornaments are
used for navigation or toolbars.
Designing for xrOS is perfect
for apps that want to create
immersive experiences, adopt
new framework functionality,
or match the system
look and feel.
If you would rather preserve
your app's existing experience,
designing for iPad
is the road for you.
This platform shares a common
foundation with iOS and iPadOS,
so no matter which SDK
you choose,
the work you do
for those platforms
will continue to benefit
your experience on this one.
If you decide that designing
for this new platform
is the best fit for your app,
the "Meet SwiftUI
for spatial computing"
and "Meet UIKit
for spatial computing" videos
are great places to start.
Your next step
is to try your app
on this exciting new platform!
The vast majority of apps work
without any code changes at all.
Pay special attention to the
compatibility areas I covered:
ensure your Info.plist keys
are up to date,
opt into new platform
experiences
you're interested in,
and verify that
your framework dependencies
are available
before you use them.
Once you've done all that, watch
"Enhance your iPad and iPhone
apps for the Shared Space"
to learn how
to make your iOS app
feel right at home
on this device.
Thanks for watching,
and I look forward to trying
your app on this new platform.
♪