♪ ♪
Sophia: Hello, and welcome
to "Generalize APIs with parameter packs."
My name is Sophia,
and I work on the Swift compiler team.
Today I will be talking to you
about Swift parameter packs
and how they provide a new dimension
of flexibility with generic programming.
This is an advanced talk, and it builds
upon the existing generics system.
If you are unfamiliar with the topic,
I encourage you to watch
"Embrace Swift generics" from WWDC22.
Today, I will walk you through
the types of problems
that parameter packs can solve,
how to think about parameter packs
when you encounter them in libraries,
and finally,
I will dive into how to implement
your own code
that utilizes parameter packs.
Before I jump into parameter packs,
it is important to know why they exist.
So I will begin by talking a little bit
about generics and then variadics.
The code you write is
fundamentally composed of two categories:
values and types.
You can abstract over values
by writing functions
that accept different values
as parameters.
An example could be
a radians(from:) function
that as input will accept
any Double value representing degrees
and for output will return
a new Double value representing radians.
You can abstract over types
by writing generic code
that accepts varying types
for its parameters.
For example,
the standard library Array type
is designed to hold any form of data
that you might wish to fill it with.
It has an Element type parameter
which is a placeholder
for the concrete type that you will use
for a given instance of an Array.
In both cases,
concrete values or concrete types
are passed as arguments
to the abstraction.
Most generic code abstracts
over both types and values.
To explore this, I am going to write
some code to send queries to a server.
Its basic implementation will receive
a Request of some Payload type,
then it will pass that
as a query to the server,
and finally return a server response
of type Payload.
The function has one parameter,
but I want to support querying
multiple requests in the same call.
For the ability to have a variable number
of arguments, we have variadic parameters.
Variadic parameters allow
for a function to flexibly accept
any number of arguments of a single type.
But variadic parameters have limitations.
For example,
you might want to map the given arguments
to a tuple whose length is the same
as the number of arguments.
However, with variadic parameters,
there is no way to declare
a return type that is based
on the argument length.
There also is no way for variadic
parameters to accept varying types
without using type erasure,
and therefore no way to preserve
the specific static type information
of each argument.
What we lack with the generics system
and variadic parameters is the ability
to both preserve type information
and vary the number of arguments.
Today, the only way to do this
is with overloading,
which forces you to choose an upper bound
of the number of arguments you support.
I wonder, will two parameters be enough?
Probably not.
Handling up to three parameters is better.
But what if we want four?
This overloading pattern,
as well as its limitations, are pervasive
across APIs that conceptually handle
varying numbers of type parameters.
This approach has
the downside of redundancy,
but more importantly, it forces
choosing an arbitrary upper limit
to the number of arguments
that will be supported.
Exceeding whatever limit was chosen
will result in a compiler error
about extra arguments.
This is the kind of problem
that parameter packs solve.
If you find yourself
falling into this overloading pattern,
then that is a strong sign
that you want to use parameter packs.
In Swift 5.9, the generics system
is gaining first class support
for abstraction over argument length
with a new construct
called "parameter packs."
I'm now going to talk
about what parameter packs mean
when you see them in APIs.
In code, most of the time,
you work with a single type or value.
A parameter pack can hold
any quantity of types or values
and pack them together to pass them
as an argument to a function.
A pack that holds individual types
is called a type pack.
For example,
you could have a type pack that holds
three individual types:
Bool, Int, and String.
A pack that holds individual values
is called a value pack.
For example,
you could have a value pack that holds
three individual values: true,
the number 10, and an empty string.
Type packs and value packs
are used together.
A type pack provides each individual type
for each individual value in a value pack.
The corresponding type and value
are at the same position
in their respective packs.
At position 0,
the type of the value true is Bool.
At position 1, the type
of the integer literal 10 is Int.
And at position 2, the type
of the empty string literal is String.
Parameter packs allow you
to write one piece of generic code
that works with every individual element
in a pack.
This concept might sound familiar
because you're already used
to writing one piece of code that works
with different, individual elements
when you use Collections in Swift.
The way that you write such code
is through iteration.
For example, the body of a for-in loop
operates on each individual element
of an array.
What makes parameter packs different
from collections is that each element
in the pack has a different static type,
and you can work with packs
at the type-level.
Normally,
you write generic code that works
with different concrete types by declaring
a type parameter inside angle brackets.
In Swift 5.9, you can declare a pack
of type parameters
with the keyword "each".
Instead of having a single type parameter,
the function accepts each Payload type
that you want to query.
This is called a type parameter pack.
In order for the names of type packs
and value packs to read naturally,
use a singular naming convention,
such as "each Payload"
rather than "each Payloads".
Generic code that uses parameter packs
can operate on each Payload individually
using repetition patterns.
A repetition pattern is expressed
using the 'repeat' keyword,
followed by a type
called the pattern type.
with individual pack elements
at every iteration.
Let's see how this replacement works
with a concrete type pack
containing Bool, Int, and String.
The pattern will be repeated three times
and the placeholder 'each Payload'
is replaced with the concrete type
in the pack during each repetition.
The result is
a comma-separated list of types:
Request of Bool, Request of Int,
and Request of String.
Because repetition patterns produce
comma-separated lists of types,
they can only be used in positions that
naturally accept comma-separated lists.
This includes types
wrapped in parentheses,
which are either a tuple type
or a single type.
Additionally, they can be used
in function parameter lists,
and repetition patterns can be used
in generic argument lists.
Using a repetition pattern
as the type of a function parameter
turns that function parameter
into a value parameter pack.
This enables the caller to pass in
an arbitrary number of Request instances,
and the argument values will be collected
into a pack and passed to the function.
That covers the fundamental concept
of parameter packs
and the syntax that is used.
Next, to demonstrate
how they can simplify as well as extend
the functionality of APIs,
let's return to our query API.
Each overload has 1, 2, 3,
and 4 type parameters, respectively.
Each overload maps each type parameter
to a Request
over that type in the parameter list.
And each overload contains a list
of each type parameter in the return type.
Using parameter packs,
these 4 overloads can be collapsed
down into a single function.
Let's first consider
the type parameter declarations,
then the function parameter list,
and finally the return type.
Each type parameter can be collapsed down
into a type parameter pack.
Each individual Request parameter can be
collapsed down to a value parameter pack.
And the return type can be collapsed down
into a tuple
constructed by repeating
each Payload type.
Now you have one query function
that can handle
any number of request arguments.
Because the function parameter
and return type are both dependent types
of the type parameter pack 'each Payload,'
you know that the length
of the function's value parameter pack
will always match the number of elements
in the tuple that is returned.
Now that I have adopted
parameter packs in this API,
you can call this single query function
with one argument
or with three arguments
or any amount you wish.
Parameter packs handle
all argument lengths the same way.
Let's focus on the call
with three arguments.
The concrete argument pack is inferred
from the arguments at the call-site.
Every concrete type
for the placeholders 'each Payload'
is collected from the argument list
into a type pack.
And the concrete type pack is
substituted in to produce the return type.
'each Payload' appears
in the parameter list and the return type.
In the end, the code that is run
is equivalent to an iteration
over all three types of the type pack.
Suppose that our query payloads
should be Equatable.
By adding a colon
and the protocol name Equatable
following the type parameter pack,
every element in the Payload pack is
required to conform to Equatable.
More general requirements can be
declared with a 'where' clause,
just like ordinary generics.
Remembering that parameter packs
can contain zero or more arguments,
you may be thinking
that this server query API
has no particular reason
to accept zero arguments.
Fortunately, there is a simple technique
to require a minimum argument length.
In this case,
I want to require at least one argument,
to give the function something to do.
To achieve this,
I add a regular type parameter
preceding the type parameter pack
and a corresponding value parameter
preceding the value parameter pack.
Any constraints on the type parameter pack
should be applied
to the new type parameter as well,
which, in this example,
is conformance to Equatable.
Now callers to your function
must provide at least one argument.
At this point,
we have covered the foundation
of what parameter packs solve
and how to read them in an API.
Next, let's go over how to implement code
that uses parameter packs.
We're going to build out
the implementation of the server query
using parameter packs.
The query function accepts a value pack
where every individual element
is a Request
over every element in the type pack.
for every item in the value pack.
You can express this
using repetition patterns.
Repetition patterns are expressed
using the same syntax
at the type-level and at the value-level.
At the value level, the 'repeat' keyword
is followed by the pattern expression.
The pattern expression will contain
one or more value packs.
The pack is iterated
through every value it contains,
and the expression is evaluated
once per value.
To produce a list of all evaluation
results contained within a tuple,
you can wrap the pattern expression
in parentheses.
If the value pack that is passed
to the function is empty,
the result will be the empty tuple.
If the value pack has a single element,
the result will be another single value.
If the value pack has multiple elements,
the result will be a tuple.
And that's it.
Now, we have a query function
that accepts a value pack of results,
evaluates every individual request,
and returns the result
of every request together in a tuple.
This is the foundation of how you make use
of parameter packs in your code.
This continues to be far less code
than the earlier example
that used multiple overloads
rather than parameter packs,
and that version didn't even have
an implementation.
Maintenance is easier,
and errors that often arise
from repetitive code patterns are gone.
Now let's add a little more flexibility.
I'm going to refactor my example
to: enable the query API to store state,
and lift the type parameter pack
from the query method
to the Evaluator type.
The Evaluator struct can store
the request pack in a stored property
by wrapping it in parentheses
to make it a tuple value.
Given a concrete Payload type
argument pack,
the 'item' variable will either be
a single request
or a tuple of every request.
Next, I'll change Request
from a struct to a protocol
that has an associated type named Output.
And I will add another associated type
to the Request protocol named Input.
I will then update
the evaluate method in Request
to make its argument
the protocol's Input type.
This enables the method's return type
to differ from that
of the argument's type.
After this,
I update the Evaluator to require
all Payload types to conform to Request
and correspondingly update
the 'item' stored property
to now be simply of type 'each Payload.'
However, at this point, the name "Payload"
for Evaluator's type parameter pack
doesn't really fit.
Payload is no longer
what is contained within a Request
but instead conforms
to the entirety of Request.
Therefore, we will change
the name of Payload to be Request
and the name of the protocol
to be RequestProtocol.
The query method can now accept
a pack of each Request's Input type,
and it will return a list
of each Request's Output type.
Finally, the new parameter 'input'
to the query method
simply needs to be passed along
to the calls
to every item's evaluate method.
Now we are able to have
a different type returned
from the server's response
than the type of data
that we include inside our query.
You can know that the length
of the method's value argument pack
will match the length of the value pack
that is returned
if you were to want to exit early
from the iteration.
Perhaps it is the case
that the consequences
of a collection of queries
should only take effect
if every query is successful.
Throwing errors can be used for this.
In our example, you could update
RequestProtocol's evaluate method
to be a throwing function
and modify the return type
of Evaluator's query method
to be optional.
You can move the body of the query method
into a do-catch statement,
placing the return statement
within the do clause
and returning nil from the catch clause.
Now any individual query's evaluation
is able to halt iteration
over all of the queries,
if that might be needed.
In this session, we have talked
about how parameter packs allow you
to abstract over types as well as
the number of arguments in generic code.
We walked through
how you can use parameter packs
to both simplify and remove limitations
in your code
by writing a single generic implementation
that previously would have required
numerous overloads.
Finally, we wrote code
to implement sending queries
to a server
while utilizing parameter packs.
To learn more about generics,
check out the session
"Embrace Swift generics" from WWDC22.
And to learn more about protocols
and type erasure,
check out the session
"Design protocol interfaces in Swift"
from WWDC22.
Swift parameter packs are a powerful tool
to expand what is possible
in your generic code
while also enabling you
to simplify common generic patterns.
We can't wait to see
what you build with them.
Thank you for watching.