♪ ♪
Adam: Welcome, I'm Adam,
an engineer for VisionKit.
It is my pleasure to spend time
with you today to talk about new features
and API the team
has been working on for this year.
To recap, last year Live Text support
was added in VisionKit,
enabling interactions such as
text selection, translation,
QR support,
and more for images in your apps.
VisionKit also introduced
the DataScannerViewController,
The Data scanner uses a live camera feed
provide a simple and full featured way
to capture specific text types,
as well as many variants
of machine readable codes.
Information on those APIs are included
in these WWDC22 sessions.
The response from developers
has been amazing,
and this year I'm happy to announce
VisionKit is adding support
for both Subject Lifting
and Visual Look Up.
There's also new Live Text API
for text selection,
expanded platform support for Catalyst,
and context menu integration
for native macOS apps.
And now I'm going to get started
with Subject Lifting.
With a simple long press
on the subject of an image,
it lifts it from its surroundings
and becomes highlighted
with this beautiful animated glow,
and then I am presented
with several options to share it,
or invoke Visual Look Up.
New for iOS 17, you can now use
any lifted subject
to create a sticker, with fun effects such
as shiny, puffy, and more
to share with your friends and family.
Now the good news is, integrating
Subject Lifting is very simple.
In fact, there is a good chance
you are already finished.
Here is the same code snippet
from the last year's video
where I analyze an image
and set it on the interaction.
But now, it supports Subject Lifting,
without any code changed.
Let's explore further.
Notice that I'm not passing anything
special into the analyzer configuration.
This is because in order to preserve
power and performance,
Subject Lifting analysis is handled
separately by the interaction
after the initial analysis is complete.
For iOS this process occurs after
it's been on screen for a few seconds,
and for macOS it will occur
the first time the menu appears.
This means you don't need to handle
the case
of the user swiping though many photos.
The interaction will handle this for you.
All you need to do is ensure you have
an appropriate interaction type set--
in this case, automatic--
and the rest is handled
by the interaction.
Let's examine Subject Lifting compatible
interaction types
a bit closer.
Automatic gives the default
out of the box experience,
combining text interaction,
Subject Lifting, and more.
If you only want Subject Lifting,
and not text selection or data detectors,
you can set the interaction type to
.imageSegmentation,
or combine it with other types.
And finally, if Subject Lifting
just does not make sense for your app,
but you want the previous
automatic behavior from iOS 16,
no problem, you can use a new type,
.automaticTextOnly.
This provides features such as
text selection and data detectors,
but not Subject Lifting.
We have a detailed session
specifically on Subject Lifting available
if you would like to learn advanced topics
about this amazing new technology
in both VisionKit, and Vision.
This year VisionKit also supports
Visual Look Up.
Visual Look Up allows users to
easily identify and learn about pets,
nature, landmarks, art, and media.
And In iOS 17, Visual Look Up
will support additional domains,
including food, products,
and signs and symbols.
Now, finally, it's easy to look up what
those symbols on your laundry tags mean.
I mean, that's pretty cool if you ask me.
Visual Look Up availability
is based on language,
and is available for these languages.
Let's take a quick peek under the hood,
and explore how Visual Look Up works.
It's actually a two-part process.
Initial processing is accomplished
entirely on device at analysis time.
If the .visualLookUp type is present
in the analyzer configuration,
Visual Look Up will locate
the bounding box of the results,
and their top level domain.
For example, if it's a cat, book,
or plant.
This step also includes
feature extraction.
Once the user requests
to look up an object,
then, and only then,
are the domain and image embeddings
from feature extraction sent to the server
for additional processing.
Now you know how Visual Look Up works,
let's quickly explore how to use it,
and what actions you need to take
to add it to your app.
Visual Look Up can be invoked
in two different ways.
The first is in conjunction
with Subject Lifting,
if the current lifted subject
contains one,
and only one,
correlated Visual Look Up result,
the Look Up option will be offered
in the menu,
and selecting it will show
the full Look Up result.
VisionKit handles this interaction
for you automatically.
As an adopter all you need to do
is have .visualLookUp added to your
analyzer configuration at analysis time.
Second,
there is a modal interaction available
where badges are placed over each
of the visual search results.
Notice how the badges move to
the corner if they leave the viewport,
Users can tap on these badges
to show the Look Up result.
This is the same interaction as clicking
on the info button in the Photos app,
or Quick Look, for example.
This mode is invoked by setting
.visualLookUp
as the preferredInteractionType
on your interaction.
Please note:
this type will have precedence
over the other interaction types.
For example,
you cannot select text or data detectors
at the same time
that the visualLookup Mode is set.
As such, this is normally used
in conjunction with a button,
or some other bespoke way
to get in and out of this mode.
For example,
Quick Look uses the info button
to enter Visual Look Up mode.
Now let's shift gears and discuss
new API and features for the Data Scanner
as well as Live Text.
Introduced In iOS 16,
the DataScannerViewController
was designed to be the easiest way
to use OCR
with a live camera viewfinder.
In iOS 17, it's been enhanced with optical
flow tracking as well as currency support.
Optical flow tracking can enhance text
tracking for live-camera experiences.
Here is what we have in iOS 16.
I'm scanning for text
with highFrameRateTracking enabled.
And this what you'll get
with optical flow tracking.
Now the highlights feel much more stable
and grounded than before.
Optical flow tracking comes for free
whenever you use the
DataScannerViewController,
however, it is only available
when recognizing text,
and not machine readable codes.
And you're also required to scan for text
without a specific text content type set.
And finally, once again, ensure
high frame-rate tracking is enabled.
Which is, conveniently, the default.
No matter how you configure it,
the data scanner provides
great text tracking;
but if your use case
allows for this configuration,
the new optical flow tracking
can enhance it even further.
Next, the data scanner has a new option
allowing users to find and interact
with monetary values.
It's incredibly simple to enable.
Just set the text content type to currency
when specifying text recognition
in the data scanner's initializer,
just as you would other content types
like email addresses
or telephone numbers.
Now I'm going to explore this new type
in more detail with a quick example.
When the data scanner recognizes
currency in text,
It contains both
a bounds and a transcript.
The transcript has both
the currency symbol and the amount.
Here's an example where I find
the total of all the values
on something like a receipt.
First, I get the currency symbol
using the current locale.
While awaiting the data scanner's results
in the recognizedItems stream,
I can loop through each of
the recognized items
and grab its transcript.
If the transcript contains
the currency symbol I'm interested in,
I'll go ahead and update the total value.
And just like that,
now you'll have the sum of all values.
This is just a simple example,
but this can very powerful,
I'm excited to see
what you can build with this.
And now I'm going to talk about
enhancements to Live Text.
First off,
Live Text is coming to more regions
by expanding our supported languages
to include Thai and Vietnamese.
Live Text includes enhancements
for document structure detection
as well this year.
Document structure detection?
What does that even mean?
Well, as an example,
in iOS 16
Live Text supported list detection.
This allows you to easily copy and paste
a list into an app that understands lists,
such as Notes, and the list formatting
will be maintained.
Live Text handles several list styles,
such as numbers or bullets.
And now, Live Text is offering
the same support for Tables,
making it far easier
to get structured table data from an image
into applications like Notes or Numbers.
Now I can select, copy, and paste
this table into Numbers,
and the structure is maintained.
Notice how it merges cells automatically
if necessary.
And just like that,
I'm now just a few clicks away
from visualizing this information
in a graph.
Nice.
And that's not all.
We are also adding
Context Aware Data Detectors in Live Text.
For this feature, data detectors
and their visual relationships
are used when adding contacts.
Notice how when I add this contact
from an email address,
additional information from surrounding
data detectors are now included,
allowing me to easily add
all this information at once.
Adding a contact from a business card
or flyer has never been easier.
In addition to these great features
you are also getting for free,
VisionKit also has some new APIs
specifically for text.
Last year,
you could get the entire text contents
by accessing the transcript property
on the image analysis.
Based on your feedback,
you now have full access
to plain and attributed text,
selected ranges,
and easy access to selected text.
There is also a new delegate method
so you can be aware
when the text selection changes
and update your UI as appropriate.
It is now easy to add features
that rely on what the user has selected.
For example, using the menu builder API,
you could insert a menu item
that creates a reminder
based on the current text selection.
Start in the view controller that owns
your image analysis interaction.
First grab the selected text,
and ensure it isn't empty.
Then create a command
that calls our handler when chosen,
Now create a menu object
that holds the command.
And finally, insert that menu as a sibling
after the share menu option.
Now you have a custom menu
alongside system items
like copy and share.
Now I'm going to talk about
our expanded platform support.
And this year, it's all about the Mac.
We are rolling out Catalyst support
to easily bring Live Text
from your iOS apps over to the Mac.
And if you're new to the native macOS API
and the ImageAnalysisOverlayView,
stay tuned, because I'm going to go over
some specifics,
as well as some tips on adopting them.
Finally, I am going to talk about
a new system for menus,
offering simple and seamless integration
of VisionKit into your contextual menus.
Catalyst adoption is very straightforward.
It should be a simple recompile
to get the image analysis interaction
working in Catalyst.
We support, Live Text,
Subject Lifting and Visual Look Up,
but unfortunately QR code support
is unavailable
in either the Catalyst environment
or native macOS API for VisionKit.
However, I wanted to let you know
that if you have a shared implementation,
leaving the .machineReadableCodes in
your analyzer configuration for Catalyst
is perfectly safe,
and just becomes a no-op.
Also, please note
that QR detection support
is available in the Vision Framework
if you need this functionality on the Mac.
Now I'm gong to transition
to the native macOS API.
As with iOS, there are two major classes
you need to be aware of
when adopting VisionKit:
the ImageAnalyzer
and the ImageAnalysisOverlayView.
First, the easy part.
The Image Analyzer and analysis process
for the Mac is identical to iOS.
With the exception of machine readable
codes being a no-op,
as I mentioned earlier,
everything is the same
and is used in the same way.
The main difference between
the iOS ImageAnalysisInteraction,
and macOS's ImageAnalysisOverlayView
is how the interaction
is added to your application.
For iOS, the ImageAnalysisInteraction is
a UIInteraction that is added to a view,
already existing
in your apps view hierarchy.
But UIInteraction does not exist
on the Mac.
So what do you do?
In this case, as the name suggests,
the image analysis overlay view
is a subclass of NSView.
I simply need to add the overlay view in
my view hierarchy above my image content.
I can add it, for example, here.
Or even here.
But the simplest way is to add it
as a sub view of my content view.
Any way you choose is perfectly fine,
but I've found adding it as a subView
is generally simpler,
and easier to manage as you don't have to
handle repositioning the overlay view
when the contents view position changes.
And now you know how
and where to add it to your app,
Let's talk rectangles.
Since the OverlayView doesn't host
or render your content,
it needs to know exactly where the
content exists in relation to its bounds.
This is described by the contentsRect,
which is in unit coordinate space
with the origin at the top left.
Wow, that was a mouthful.
A quick example should help clarify this.
Since the overlay view is placed
directly over the imageView,
they have same bounds.
I'll show the bounds with this rectangle.
And I'll also add
its matching contents rect.
Easiest case is if
the content matches the bounds.
Here it's simply the unit rectangle.
Now, here is an aspect fit.
Notice this portion of the imageView
now has no content underneath it.
And is reflected in the contents rect.
And here is an aspect fill.
This portion of the image
is no longer visible to the user,
Notice how the contents rect
changes here.
Now, some good news.
Just as with UIImageView on iOS,
if you are using NSImageView,
you can simply set the trackingImageView property on the overlay view,
and it will calculate
all of this for you automatically.
If you are not using NSImageView,
no worries.
You can provide the contents rect
by implementing the delegate method
contentsRect(for overlayView:)
The overlay view will ask for this
during layout when its bounds change.
However, you can manually request
this be updated
by calling setContentsRectNeedsUpdate
on the overlayView.
All righty,
let's move on to contextual menus.
As I'm sure you are all aware,
contextual menus are a huge part
of the Mac experience.
Now Its now easy to add
VisionKit provided functionality
directly into your menus,
for features such as Live Text,
Look Up, and Subject Lifting, and more.
One question you may have is, why?
Let's examine the macOS Photos app.
If I were to right click
on the text for this iconic road sign,
I would just be presented
with only the VisionKit text menu.
If it were not over text,
I would be offered the app menu instead,
without any text items.
This is not ideal.
Now in macOS Sonoma,
items can be combined into the same menu.
You can easily get to both text
and image functionality,
no matter where the menu event
was initiated.
This is a far better experience
for the user,
and is simple to implement.
Let's explore how this can be accomplished
in your own app.
You now have a new delegate method
available,
overlayview:updatedmenu:forevent:atpoint.
The arguments include
the event that triggered the menu,
and the point in the overlay view
bounds coordinate space,
so you can create any menus you need.
From there, you simply need to return
the menu that you would like to display.
The default implementation
returns the VisionKit menu.
However, you may wish to add
your own items to that menu,
or take items from that menu
and add it to yours.
VisionKit menu items
are identified by tags,
and there is a struct available
that contains these tags.
We have several items available
for copying and sharing
the image and subjects,
and one for Look Up.
We also have a special item you can use
to find the suggested index
to add items
to the VisionKit provided menu,
but more on that later.
Here are some examples
of how this is used.
If I had an existing menu
and all I were interested in was adding
the copySubject item,
it could be easily added like this.
First, get your apps menu.
Then get the item you are interested in.
In this case, copySubject.
And insert it in your menu.
Now, it's important to remember
that Items will only be available
if they are actually valid.
For example, if there's no
subject interaction capable type present,
the copySubject item
will not be in the menu.
Also, for system provided text items,
they are included if applicable,
but not all are identifiable by tag.
You can even customize these items
however you would wish.
For example, I've changed the item
from copy image to copy photo.
And worry not
about changing these properties.
These items are re-created each time
and you can change them
however you'd like.
Now that I've covered adding items
to your existing menu,
I'm going to explore an example
of how to add items to the VisionKit menu.
As mentioned earlier,
the overlayView will provide an item
with a tag at the recommended index
to insert your items
called recommendedAppItems.
You simply ask for the index of this item
and insert your items at that index.
Using this index is optional
and not required.
However, it is a good way
to keep things consistent for your users.
You will notice that some of these
menu items have special properties.
For example, when the subject related
menu item are highlighted,
the area surrounding my cat KiKi here dims
and the glow animation begins,
indicating the subject to the user
before it is copied or shared.
VisionKit uses the menu appearing
as a trigger to begin subject analysis,
if it hasn't began already.
This is all handled for you automatically.
In order to provide these features,
VisionKit will set itself as a delegate
for any menu you return
from the update menu method.
If you were previously relying
on these NSMenuDelegate callbacks,
VisionKit now provides
its own Delegate callbacks
allowing you to retain functionality
with your menu items
if you were using that previously.
And here's a quick tip.
If you are in this situation,
depending on where
the menu was initiated from,
it may not come from VisionKit.
So you'll likely want to keep
your existing implementation around.
Generally, the simplest way
to keep this all in sync
is to have your OverlayViewDelegate
implementation
call your matching
NSMenuDelegate implementation,
adjusting as necessary.
Of course,
ensure this makes sense for your app,
but in general,
this usually does the trick.
And that's a quick overview
of what's new in VisionKit.
It has been my pleasure to spend time
with you today discussing Subject Lifting
and Visual Look Up,
as well as of our new macOS APIs
and related information.
I'm looking forward to hear
how you use these new capabilities
to delight and surprise your customers.
And seriously, as always,
please have fun!
Thank you!