♪ ♪
Ethan: Hi, I'm Ethan.
I'm from the Siri Understanding team
and here to talk to you
about some exciting developments
in speech recognition.
In iOS 10,
we introduced the Speech framework.
It allowed you to leverage the same
technology
that powers Siri and keyboard dictation
to create voice enabled apps
by using a simple, intuitive interface.
However, the speech recognizer class,
out of the box,
isn't suitable for all apps.
To explain why, let's talk
about how speech recognition works.
A speech recognition system
first feeds audio data
into an Acoustic Model,
which produces a phonetic representation.
Then the phonetic representation
is converted into a written form,
or transcription.
Sometimes, multiple phonetic
representations fit the audio data,
or a single phonetic representation
may correspond to multiple transcriptions.
In these cases, we end up
with multiple candidate transcriptions,
and we need a way to disambiguate.
To do this, we employ something
called a language model.
A language model predicts
the likelihood that a given word
will come next in a sequence of words.
Applied to a whole sentence,
it can give us a feel for whether
the sentence is probably nonsense.
The language model helps us
reject candidates which are unlikely,
based on patterns of usage that the model
was exposed to during training.
Since iOS 10,
the Speech framework has encapsulated
this entire process in order to present
an interface that is easy to use.
To understand why that might not be ideal,
let's consider an example.
I love to play chess,
and I've been working on a chess app
that will let users dictate
individual moves,
as well as common openings and defenses.
Here, my opponent has played
the classic Queen's Gambit.
I've been studying,
and I like the response E5,
the Albin counter gambit.
Play the Albin counter gambit.
Uh oh, there's a problem.
The recognizer is misrecognizing
my chess move as a music request.
The language model
that the recognizer uses was exposed
to a lot of music requests
during its training process,
so it is prepared for queries like,
“Play the album,”
followed by an album name.
Conversely, it's probably never
encountered my preferred transcription.
By abstracting away the behavior
of the language model,
the Speech framework forces
all apps to use the same model,
even though different domains
call for different behavior.
Beginning in iOS 17,
you'll be able to customize the behavior
of the SFSpeechRecognizer's
language model,
tailor it to your application,
and improve its accuracy.
To get started
with language model customization,
first create a collection
of training data.
You can do this
during your development process.
Then, in your app,
you'll prepare the data,
configure a recognition request,
and then run it.
Let's talk about the process of building
your collection of training data.
At a high level,
training data will consist of bits
of text that represent phrases
your app's users are likely to speak.
These will teach the model
to expect those phrases
and boost the likelihood
that they'll be recognized correctly.
Experiment often,
as it's surprising to see how
capable the recognizer is,
and how much it improves over time.
The speech framework introduces
a new class that acts
as a container for training data.
It's built using the result builder DSL.
You can provide an exact phrase or part
of a phrase using a PhraseCount object.
A PhraseCount will also describe
how many times the sample should be
represented in the final data set.
This can be used to weight
certain phrases more heavily than others.
Only so much data can
be accepted by the system,
so balance your need to boost phrases
against your overall training data budget.
You can also leverage templates
to generate a large number
of samples that fit a regular pattern.
Here, I've defined three classes of words
that together make up a chess move.
The piece to move, which doubles
as the file that I'm targeting,
the royal piece that defines
which side of the board to play on,
and the rank to move to.
By putting them together into a pattern,
I can easily generate data samples
representing every possible move.
Here, the count applies
to the entire template,
so I'll get 10,000 samples
representing chess moves,
divided evenly among all
of the resulting data samples.
When I'm done building up the data object,
I export it to a file
and deploy into my app
like any other asset.
If your app makes use
of specialized terminology,
for example, a medical app that
includes the names of pharmaceuticals,
you can define both the spelling
and pronunciations of those terms,
and provide phrase counts
that demonstrates their usage.
Pronunciations are accepted
in the form of X-SAMPA strings.
Each locale supports a unique subset
of pronunciation symbols.
Refer to the documentation
for the full set of locales
and supported symbols.
For my app,
I want to make sure the recognizer can
understand the Winawer variation,
a common variant of the French defense.
I describe the pronunciation
using the subset of X-SAMPA symbols
that are supported by this locale.
You can use the same API to train on data
that your app can access at runtime.
You might do this to support
usage patterns that are specific
to your users,
such as focusing on the chess openings
and defenses
that your user is trying to learn.
You might also want
to train on named entities.
Maybe your app supports network play
against your user's contacts.
And as always, respecting
the user's privacy is paramount.
For example, a communication app may want
to boost commands to call contacts
based on the frequency with which
those contacts appear in the call history.
This kind of information should always
stay on device.
You simply call into the same methods from
within your app to generate a data object,
write it to a file,
and ingest it as shown earlier.
Once training data is generated,
it is bound to a single locale.
If you want to support multiple locales
within a single script,
you can use
standard localization facilities
like NSLocalizedString to do so.
Now, let's talk about deploying
your model in your app.
First, you need to call a new method,
prepareCustomLanguageModel,
that accepts the file
we generated in the previous step
and produces
two new files that we'll use later.
This method call can have
a large amount of associated latency,
so it's best to call it
off the main thread,
and hide the latency behind some UI,
such as a loading screen.
Sometimes,
you need to keep data on the device
where it's generated
in order to respect the user's privacy.
LM customization supports this
by never sending customization data
over the network.
All customized requests
are serviced strictly on device.
When your app constructs
the speech recognition request,
you first enforce
that the recognition is run on device.
Failing to do so will cause requests
to be serviced without customization.
Then you attach the language model
to your request object.
Now, with LM customization
turned on in my app...
Play the Albin counter gambit.
My custom terms work as well.
Play the Winawer variation.
By customizing the language model,
I've tuned the recognizer
to my application's domain,
and I've gained some control
over how it behaves.
Most importantly,
I've improved
speech recognition accuracy for my app.
Now that the Speech framework can
be adapted to more apps and more users,
it's even more powerful and can be used
to create even better experiences.
Language model customization
provides you a way
to enhance the speech recognizer
and customize it for your apps.
I'm super excited
to see all of the amazing things
you'll accomplish with it.
Thank you,
and remember to play for the center.
♪ ♪