♪ ♪
Christopher: Hello and welcome!
My name is Christopher,
and I am a software engineer
on the ScreenCaptureKit team.
I'll be joined by my colleague
Natalie Lindsay,
and together we'll introduce new features
that are going to enhance
screen capture capabilities
in your applications.
ScreenCaptureKit was introduced
in macOS 12.3
to help you create your application's
screen sharing experience.
ScreenCaptureKit provides APIs that will
let you customize the content
you want to share, with controls that fit
your application's needs,
all of which can be applied
dynamically to your streams.
The framework delivers high quality
content with a focus on performance
that goes up to the native resolution
and frame rate of your display,
all while having privacy in mind
with global safeguards.
This year, ScreenCaptureKit provides
several developer APIs
that integrate with new macOS features.
Presenter Overlay is a feature
that allows people
to make their screen shares
and presentations more personal
by embedding themselves
into the captured content.
With the new screen sharing picker,
you'll be able to integrate
a system-wide experience for
what you capture in your screen share.
Finally, screen capture isn't just for
live streams,
and this year, there's a brand-new API
that allows you to capture
high definition screenshots
of any content you choose.
People interact with each other every day,
all across the world.
These interactions are where
we share our thoughts and ideas
and solve important issues.
They are both professional and personal.
To this end,
your apps can work seamlessly with
a new video effect
called Presenter Overlay.
When sharing content, Presenter Overlay
elevates the presenter's presence
by including the presenter
on top of the shared content,
adding a personal touch
for more productive remote calls.
Small overlay places
the presenter in a movable window,
thanks to advanced segmentation algorithm,
while large overlay separates
the presenter's face and body
from the background
and then layers the screen content
between them for a more immersive effect.
Presenter Overlay is available with every
application that uses ScreenCaptureKit.
For every SCStream that is created,
ScreenCaptureKit will notify
the screen sharing picker,
and a live preview with controls
for the stream will be displayed
in a new Video menu bar item.
The Video menu bar will show every
application that has an active stream,
and will show a live preview of the
streams associated with any application.
From this menu bar, one will be able
to control the stream content by presenting
the stream-wide screen sharing picker.
This is also where
Presenter Overlay is enabled,
embedding the camera frame
into the content stream.
And one can also use this
to control the stream,
like replacing or ending the screen share.
There are other useful features here for
customizing camera and microphone effects.
Every application that uses
ScreenCaptureKit and camera together
will automatically have
these features working.
Currently, a stream has content frames
sent to its process
from ScreenCaptureKit.
Now, when an application starts using
the camera during an active stream,
Presenter Overlay is made available
in the video menu item.
Once enabled,
ScreenCaptureKit will take the camera
and apply the rendering
to the selected stream
that your application is already running.
You will get the composited frames
automatically from the active stream.
So what if I wanted to know explicitly
when Presenter Overlay has been applied?
Let's start with creating a new stream
and adding self as delegate.
Then you'll implement the new
delegate callback on SCStream,
outputEffectDidStart.
This is how you'll be notified
when Presenter Overlay has been applied.
When notified, you want to check
if the effect's started or stopped.
Presenter Overlay is
a new macOS system feature,
and there are some considerations
your application might want to take
when an overlay is applied.
When Presenter Overlay is turned on,
the AVCaptureSession will not send
the typical live camera stream.
That is because your camera
will be used directly in the overlay.
This would be a great time to update
the application UI
to account for this change.
For example,
video conferencing applications
might want to adjust your audio
and video synchronization
to account for the shared content
being mixed with the camera.
You may also want to hide the presenter's
camera tile for a more optimized look.
Presenter Overlay is
a camera and video feature,
so your application should optimize
for higher frame rates.
In addition to Presenter Overlay,
you can also take advantage
of a new systemwide screen sharing picker,
that allows your application to fully
integrate with several features
centered around how people will
pick the content they wish to share.
These are the general constructs
that you use to create a stream.
Currently, you call into SCSharableContent
to get all of the available
screen content that you could share.
You'll use that
to create an SCContentFilter.
The SCContentFilter is what you'll use
to determine what you're going to capture.
Currently, you build that
from SCSharableContent
but, new this year, you'll be able to get
a content filter through the picker.
There are two ways the picker
will generate SCContentFilters.
First, the desired content can be
shared through the system picker.
Secondly, the content can be selected
right from the window that's open.
In both cases, the system shares
an SCContentFilter with your application.
But how do you get the new
content filters into your application?
By using the new API,
SCContentSharingPicker.
SCContentSharingPicker acts
as the interface between
your application and the OS,
providing delegate callbacks
to your application
with new stream requests,
new content filters,
and updates to current streams
and content filters.
SCContentSharingPicker has a built-in
system level content picker
that enables one to pick content based on
windows, apps, or even displays.
Whether one initiates
the selection of content
through a button in your application,
the new Video menu bar,
or directly from a window,
your application can take advantage
of SCContentSharingPicker
to add, remove, or replace the active
selection for any of your ongoing streams.
It also has a built-in
stream request callback
that allows your application to know
when a new stream is being requested.
And finally,
it comes with per-stream customization,
where you can define how the system
experience is applied to each stream.
The constructs for getting the filter
for an SCStream
now goes from using SCSharableContent
to using the system picker interface
with the SCContentSharingPicker singleton
to pass back SCContentFilter.
Let me show you how easy it is
for your application to take advantage
of this new screen sharing picker.
You'll start with the shared instance
for SCContentSharingPicker
and add self as an observer so you can
get all the appropriate class callbacks.
In order for the system to recognize
my picker instance, set it as active.
Once active,
the system will know about your picker,
and your application will be included
in the System UI
and people will be able
to interact with it.
You want to make a stream where
people are allowed to choose windows
through the picker, so you'll call
the singleton method picker.present
and pass in nil and a style of picker
you want to present.
Once people press your UI button,
the picker will be presented,
allowing them to choose
the windows they wish to capture.
After that content has been selected,
you will be notified via the observer
callback of a new filter.
And you are now free
to either create a new stream
or update an existing stream
using this filter.
The remaining observer callbacks are
equally important.
Set up the picker again
by making it active and presenting it.
You'll also want to know if the picker
failed when you asked to present it.
If it did fail,
you'll want to post a notification
in your application to notify people.
Also,
if the picker was presented but canceled,
meaning no content was picked,
you want to make sure you set the state
for your stream accordingly.
SCContentSharingPicker also comes
with methods that allow you to customize
how the system is going to behave
on a per-stream level.
The SCContentSharingPickerConfiguration
allows for several customizations.
AllowedPickingModes tells the system
which of the picking modes are allowed
between windows, applications,
and display selection for content filters.
It also allows for the explicit
declaration of excludedWindowIDs
and bundleIDs that are not allowed
to be picked by the system experience.
If you have a stream
that you don't want people to change,
SCContentSharingPickerConfiguration has
a property that can enforce that feature.
First, you'll get
a shared picker instance.
Start with adding self as the observer
and setting the picker active.
Now, set up the appropriate
configuration settings.
For this stream,
perhaps you want to exclude
a selection of two specific applications
and don't want to allow repicking.
Once the configuration is set up,
call set configuration on the picker,
passing in the configuration
and applicative stream.
Now the picker will know exactly
how to behave for a given stream.
Also note that each stream could have
different picker configuration
to best suit the application's needs.
To recap, all ScreenCaptureKit streams are
now integrated into the macOS experience,
allowing any application to take advantage
of new features like Presenter Overlay.
And I introduced you
to SCContentSharingPicker,
the new API for integrating your
application into the new system picker UI.
But screen capturing in your application
isn't just about live streams,
so I'd like to pass it off
to my colleague, Natalie,
to talk more about
this new screenshot API.
Natalie: Thanks, Christopher.
This year,
there's a new API in ScreenCaptureKit
designed to make it easy for you to grab
a still image right off your screen.
The new screenshot API brings the benefits
of ScreenCaptureKit streaming
to screenshots.
Features like advanced filtering
by app or window,
multiple pixel formats and color spaces,
and other options like cursor visibility
are available to you.
Now you'll be able to efficiently grab an
image of the exact screen content you want
using familiar
ScreenCaptureKit constructs.
The new API is asynchronous.
For your output image,
you can choose between
a CMSampleBuffer or a CGImage format.
The CMSampleBuffer option has
additional pixel formats available,
which is great if you're interested
in specific formats.
If you already use CGImage in your code,
then using this format will be easier
to integrate.
In either format, your screenshot will use
almost all of the same configuration
options as ScreenCaptureKit streaming
and will follow a similar setup flow.
If you're using CGWindowListCreateImage,
there are a couple things that will make
the transition to ScreenCaptureKit easier.
All the window image options that you have
available for the CGWindowList API
can be found inside
the SCStreamConfiguration class
in ScreenCaptureKit.
The window list options, like getting
all windows above a certain window ID,
are provided inside SCShareableContent.
And if you're used to working
with CGImage output,
the new screenshot API provides a CGImage
output format
that's easy to integrate
into your existing code.
Taking a screenshot follows a similar flow
to ScreenCaptureKit streaming,
but in place of creating an SCStream,
you'll call the screenshot API.
To start, just like for creating a stream,
use SCShareableContent to get
your desired content
and create your SCContentFilter.
Don't forget to set up
your SCStreamConfiguration
with all the options you want
for your screenshot.
Once you have the content filter
and stream configuration,
call the screenshot API and pass them in.
The API is a class method
on the SCScreenshotManager class,
so you won't need to create
an SCScreenshotManager object
to take a screenshot.
When the screenshot image is ready,
it'll be returned to you asynchronously
in whichever format you chose.
You can also use the new system picker
to create your content filter,
and then use that
to call the screenshot API.
This would be a great way to allow people
to pick the content they want
in an intuitive way.
When it's time to take the screenshot,
there are two versions of the API to
choose from, depending on what you need:
one for the CMSampleBuffer output type
and one for the CGImage output type.
Other than that,
the two versions work the same way
and will return your screenshot
asynchronously.
Here's a code example
of how you can use the screenshot API.
Start by setting up your SCContentFilter
and SCStreamConfiguration.
Once you have those ready,
you can call the screenshot API,
wait for it to return,
and you'll get your screenshot.
And that's everything that's new
in ScreenCaptureKit.
To recap, there's a new API to create
SCContentFilters that uses system level UI
to create a fully integrated
screen sharing experience
with your application.
A New Presenter Overlay video effect
offers a more dynamic
screen sharing experience,
and a new screenshot API allows you
to grab one-off screen captures
with the power of ScreenCaptureKit.
For more information
about ScreenCaptureKit,
be sure to check out the sessions
from last year,
"Meet ScreenCaptureKit" and
"Take ScreenCaptureKit to the next level."
Thanks for watching.