♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Sarina Wu: Hello!
My name is Sarina,
and I'm a Software Engineer
on the RealityKit Tools team.
Harjas Monga: And I am Harjas,
a Profiling Tools Engineer.
Sarina: Today, Harjas
and I will be introducing
the RealityKit Trace
template in Instruments.
We'll show you how this template
can help you optimize
the performance
of your spatial experiences.
Performance is essential
to the user experience
in spatial computing.
To learn how to optimize
spatial experiences,
we will briefly cover
how rendering works
on this platform,
show you how to profile using
the RealityKit Trace template
in Instruments,
and briefly cover
the other great tools
available to optimize
your content.
This platform has unique
performance constraints.
To understand them,
you first need to understand
how rendering works.
Rendering includes
your app process,
the render server,
and the compositor.
How your app interacts
with these components
will depend on the types
of experiences you create.
Let's take a look at the types
of experiences you can create
for your spatial apps
and how they are rendered.
Apps on the platform can enter
either the Shared Space
or a Full Space.
These have different
performance implications
to consider based
on how they render.
When multiple apps
run side by side,
they are all rendered
in the same space,
which is one of the reasons
we call it the Shared Space.
This means that the performance
of your app
can be affected by the work that
the render server is doing
to render the other apps.
Then the render server works
with the compositor
to generate the final frames.
When your app
enters a Full Space,
all other visible apps
are hidden.
This means that
the performance of your app
is no longer affected
by the rendering work
for the apps
that are now hidden.
To learn more about
how to enter a Full Space,
check out the session "Go
beyond the window with SwiftUI."
Based on what was just covered,
we have two recommended ways
to profile your app.
Whenever you are investigating
performance issues
or analyzing
system power impact,
you should profile your app
in isolation
to understand your app's impact
on system performance.
When you expect your app
to work alongside other apps,
you should profile your app
with those other apps.
This is important to understand
how the user would
experience your app.
Let's profile a spatial app
to show you
how you can optimize your app's
performance in isolation
using the RealityKit
Trace template.
We've been working
on Hello World,
and we want to make sure that
there are no performance issues.
Sarina: This is
the Start screen of the app,
which is a SwiftUI View.
This view has
an Objects in Orbit button.
We can tap on that button
to learn more
about objects orbiting Earth.
The button opens a new view
that lists examples
of different objects
that are orbiting Earth.
This view has 3D models
of these objects,
including a satellite,
the Moon,
and a telescope.
In this view, there is also
a View Orbits button.
We can explore this
by tapping the button,
which will open an immersive
experience showing Earth
and a satellite
orbiting around it.
We've used detailed assets
for these models,
and I suspect that they're
affecting the performance
of this app.
In the immersive experience,
we can see the path
of the satellite animate
as it orbits Earth.
We can even scale the Earth up
to see it in more detail.
This interaction
is incredibly choppy,
so I think there's
a performance issue here.
Harjas and I profiled
that experience
using the RealityKit
Trace template.
Harjas, could you
walk us through it?
Harjas: Of course,
let's walk through
all the features available
in RealityKit Trace.
RealityKit Trace is available
as a new template
in Instruments 15.
It can be used to profile both
a real device and a simulator.
To get the most accurate
and actionable information,
you should profile
a real device.
When profiling
against the simulator
not all the timing
information will be accurate
because of the hardware
and software differences
between your Mac and on-device.
But you could still use it
for quick iteration
and improving
some of the statistics
that are not based on time.
The RealityKit Trace template
contains several instruments.
The first instrument
you will want to look at
is the RealityKit Frames
instrument.
This instrument
tracks each frame
being rendered by the device.
You can zoom in
on these frames to check
how long each frame
took to render.
With this, you can check
how long each stage
of the frame took to render.
This gives you a high-level idea
of what portion
of the render pipeline could be
causing performance problems.
In order to achieve
a smooth user experience,
your application should be able
to achieve 90 frames per second.
However, the OS may not
always be targeting 90 fps.
It will render at the frame rate
most appropriate for the content
being displayed and the
environment the device is in.
Because the frame rate
can change,
every frame has a deadline
in which it has
to complete rendering
so that the device
can hit whatever the current
target frame rate is.
The frames are classified
into three groups:
frames that are completing
well within their deadline,
frames that are just barely
finishing within their deadline,
and frames than run
past their deadline
and result in frame drops.
These classifications
are color coded
green, orange, and red,
respectively.
Frames that are running
past the deadline
will negatively impact
the user experience.
If you zoom out and check
the frames from a high level,
the color coding allows you
to quickly find
the problematic parts
of the trace.
So, you can narrow down
any performance investigations
to the areas where there are
the most frame drops.
In addition to
the individual frames,
the instrument also visualizes
the average amount of time
the system spent on CPU or GPU
work to render each frame.
The next instrument
you will want to check
is the RealityKit Metrics
instrument.
At a top level,
the instrument draws
all the bottlenecks
that it detected.
These bottlenecks
are generated by looking at
comprehensive timing information
from the entire render pipeline.
Prioritize the bottlenecks
that occur during the same time
that frames exceed
their deadline.
In the detail view below,
you will find
that these RealityKit
bottlenecks
are summarized
by severity and type.
You can dig in further to see
exactly what kind of bottleneck
the instrument found
and how much it affected
your overall performance.
In the extended detail view,
the instrument provides
recommendations
on how to diagnose
these bottlenecks further
and what steps you can take
to mitigate them.
By expanding
the RealityKit Metrics track,
you will be presented
with several types of metrics
from different components
of the render pipeline.
These statistics can help
you understand
the full complexity of the scene
your app is presenting.
Some of the key metrics will
have associated thresholds
to help inform you on reasonable
expectations for those metrics.
Use the metrics
to help guide you further
in diagnosing a bottleneck
or why a frame
is not hitting its deadline.
RealityKit Metrics
will visualize
how much time is being
spent in each frame
to run the application's
RealityKit systems.
This includes all
the built-in systems
and all the custom systems
your application may implement.
This information is best
combined with Time Profiler
so you can optimize
your RealityKit system code.
Lastly, review
the System Power Impact lane
shown in RealityKit Metrics
to understand
the power envelope
your application needs
to work within
to provide a great
and consistent user experience.
Now let's take a look
at some traces we took
while we were stepping
through the world experience.
The first scene in the app
was the Start screen,
which is implemented in SwiftUI.
In the frames instrument,
there are quite a few
dropped frames
throughout this trace.
These dropped frames
may not seem significant,
but they can really damage
the user experience.
I can use Option-drag to zoom in
on one of the more
problematic areas.
And by adjusting the time range,
I can check what bottlenecks
the RealityKit Metrics
instrument found
during these
long-running frames.
The Instrument found
that the largest bottleneck
in this time was
Core Animation Encoding.
So I'm going to check
the Core Animation statistics,
which can be found by clicking
on the disclosure triangle
next to RealityKit Metrics
Instrument
and selecting the track
labeled Core Animation.
These Core Animation metrics
can help inform us
on what might have caused
these frame drops.
When investigating
these metrics,
you will notice
that some of them
have context of how severe
the metric is.
In the timeline, this is
reflected in the color coding.
This is to guide you on what
are reasonable thresholds
for these key metrics.
Based on the timeline
visualization,
it is clear that the application
is exceeding
the recommended threshold
for the number
of offscreen prepares.
The summary at the bottom
shows that the average number
of offscreen prepares
here are 180,
which is quite a high average.
When considering
the Core Animation statistics,
there are three types of work
you want to keep in mind.
Firstly, transparency
and blur effects
are very expensive operations
for the system.
Use these effects
when they deliver
most impact to the user,
otherwise use them sparingly.
The number of render passes is
determined by how many layers
Core Animation
has to render individually
for the entire image.
And finally,
there are offscreen passes.
So as the name implies,
an offscreen pass
is a render pass that
is rendered offscreen
and not to the display.
An offscreen pass requires
the rendering pass
to pause what it's
currently doing
and do some work that won't be
shown to the user.
However, the output
of the offscreen pass
is needed to continue
the regular rendering pass.
Offscreen passes are
particularly impactful
for spatial apps.
Unlike other app platforms,
this platform continuously
renders spatial apps
because every single frame
needs to account
for environment factors,
such as the user's
head movements.
Therefore, your static UI
needs to be efficient enough
that it can be rendered at
the system's target frame rate.
There are four
main types of work
that can cause
an offscreen pass:
shadows,
masking,
rounded rectangles,
and visual effects.
To learn more about
offscreen passes,
watch our tech talk
on "Demystify and eliminate
hitches in the render phase."
Since there were a lot
of offscreen passes,
I am going to check
the SwiftUI code for this view
to find what could
have caused them.
In the SwiftUI code,
this view is not doing
any masking or visual effects.
But there are instances
of shadows being applied.
For example,
in the SwiftUI View item,
shadows are being applied
to several buttons.
Shadows are a particularly
expensive operation,
especially when combined
with transparency.
While shadows
are a useful UI idiom,
for spatial apps,
you should use them
when they deliver a significant
effect to the user.
I'm going to disable
these shadows
and take look at a new trace.
With the shadows disabled,
in the RealityKit
Frames Instrument,
there are few frame issues
and RealityKit Metrics reports
that offscreen passes
have reduced by four times.
Now, the next scene that we saw
in the World app
was the objects in orbit view.
I am going to open up
a trace from that scene
to see if there is anything
that can be optimized.
In the Frames Instrument,
there are a scattering
of dropped frames
throughout the trace
with lots of bottlenecks.
The detail view
for RealityKit Metrics
provides a summary
of those bottlenecks.
In the summary,
most of these bottlenecks
are related to GPU Work Stalls.
Because the bottleneck type
reported most frequently
are GPU stalls,
I am again going to expand
RealityKit Metrics.
But this time, I'll investigate
using the 3D Render track.
I'm going to select
the area of the trace
that has a high number
of frame drops.
In this time selection,
the 3D Render metrics
reports that the triangle
and vertex counts
are far exceeding
the recommended thresholds.
Next, I am going to highlight
the area of the trace
where there aren't nearly
as many frame drops.
And according
to the rendering metrics,
the triangle and vertex counts
are within the recommended
thresholds.
This means you should really
be evaluating the number
and quality of the assets
the app is using in the scene.
When optimizing asset rendering,
first check the triangles,
vertices, and draw calls
from the 3D Rendering group
in RealityKit Metrics.
To optimize these metrics,
use simple shape meshes
when possible.
Take advantage of instancing
when utilizing assets
with the same mesh.
Check the complexity of assets
using the statistics
in Reality Composer Pro,
which is a new developer tool
that allows you to assemble,
edit, and preview 3D content.
That content could later
be accessed through code
directly in your Xcode project.
To learn more about this tool
and how to create great assets,
check out the session
"Meet Reality Composer Pro."
I went ahead and swapped out
the assets I was using
with those that used
fewer polygons
and captured a new trace.
In this trace,
the Frames Instrument reports
that all the frames
are hitting their deadlines.
And if I check the 3D rendering
statistics again,
it reports that the triangle
and vertex counts
are reduced substantially.
While these assets
did use fewer polygons,
there was no loss in quality
of the experience.
The next trace is for
when we were interacting
with the Earth model.
During this scene,
resizing the globe
was actually quite jittery.
RealityKit Metrics reports that
the System Power Impact lane
was very high for
a substantial amount of time.
This is indicating that
some part of your application
is being very inefficient
and the user experience
could be impacted.
You should target for
your application to work well
while keeping the device's
system power impact
in the nominal state
for as much time as possible.
When profiling to reduce
system power impact,
always profile with
your application in isolation
to ensure you get the most
actionable information.
You can lower the system power
impact using several approaches.
First, make sure
that the statistics
from RealityKit Metrics
are within expectations.
If these are exceeding
expectations,
the device could be operating
at higher power states
for long stretches of time
to deliver a smooth experience.
Next, check what work
the CPU and GPU are doing.
For the CPU, check if Time
Profiler reports high CPU usage
during your high-power
draw regions.
And if it does,
optimize your CPU-bound code
using Time Profiler.
For the GPU,
we have performance states.
When the GPU is
in the maximum stage,
it draws a considerable
amount of power.
In that case, we should use
the Metal System Trace template
in Instruments to see what work
is being done on the GPU.
That way, we can understand
what could be optimized.
Going back to the trace,
Time Profiler tells us
that the CPU usage
was averaging 100 percent
in this region,
and the GPU performance states
were minimum
during most of this time.
Using Time Profiler, I can check
what caused the high CPU usage.
The heaviest stack trace
is in the extended detail view.
This is a very useful feature
of the Time Profiler,
as it allows you to quickly find
the most expensive parts
of your code in the call tree.
Looking at these frames,
it appears that Entity.makeModel
is using a lot of CPU time.
The next frame down is calling
Entity.generateCollisionShapes.
Therefore, the performance issue
appears to being caused
by constantly generating models
and collision shapes,
which is an expensive operation.
I'm going to open Xcode to see
what I can do about this.
This is the Entity.makeModel
function call
that the call tree showed
was taking a lot of CPU time.
This is getting invoked
within the makeGlobe function.
I can Control-click
on the makeGlobe function
to see who is invoking it.
It's getting invoked from
the Orbit SwiftUI view body.
This is antipattern
that should be avoided
because the view body needs
to be computed very quickly.
You should avoid
doing model loading
or any other
expensive operations
in the body
of your SwiftUI views
because any time the state
of the view changes,
all those expensive operations
need to be recomputed.
So, what I am going to do
is remove this call
from the view body.
Next, in the ViewModel,
I will add a reusable version
of the Earth entity.
And finally, I am going to use
that reusable Earth entity
in the Orbit View.
Now, when the view body
is recomputed,
the app is not wasting time
reloading the same model.
Looking at the trace
after our fix,
the power impact is brought
back down to the nominal state.
And Time Profiler reports
that the CPU usage
has dropped from
100 percent to 10 percent.
After all these optimizations,
there are few
reported bottlenecks,
almost every frame
is hitting its deadline,
and power is
within expectations.
Now, the World app
is a well-optimized app
for this platform.
Now that we've reduced
the number of offscreen passes,
replaced the high-polygon assets
with reasonable ones,
and lowered CPU and power usage,
we're going to step through the
optimized version of this app.
The start screen looks great,
and since the shadows
weren't adding much
to the user experience,
this was a good optimization.
Next, let's open up
the Objects in Orbit.
These models look great,
even though we are using assets
with fewer polygons.
So that extra detail was
just wasting resources.
And finally, we're going to
open up the Earth model again
and try resizing.
Now this interaction
is as smooth as butter.
That was a brief overview
of how to use RealityKit Trace
to optimize your apps
for this new platform.
Hey, Sarina, what other tools
are available for developers?
Sarina: There are
several tools available
to help you optimize your apps
for spatial computing.
For optimizing SwiftUI content,
there are domain-specific
instruments
in the Instruments app
for analyzing SwiftUI,
Core Animation, and hangs.
You can learn more about the
Hangs instrument in the session
"Analyze hangs
with Instruments."
There are also
several tools available
to optimize your 3D
asset-based content.
The Time Profiler Instrument
can help you find areas
where your app
is taking the most time,
such as when a large amount
of time is spent loading assets.
The RealityKit Metrics
Instrument
can help you diagnose when
scenes have too many assets
or assets that are too complex.
Finally, you can also check
the complexity of your assets
as you're assembling a scene
using Reality Composer Pro.
To learn more about
Reality Composer Pro,
watch the session
"Meet Reality Composer Pro."
If you are using Metal
in your app,
the most useful tool will be
the Metal System Trace template
in Instruments.
This template has key metrics,
such as the GPU timeline,
GPU counters,
and GPU performance state.
To learn more about
this template and other tools
for profiling Metal content,
check out the session
"Discover Metal debugging,
profiling,
and asset creation tools."
To recap, performance
is essential for this platform.
Apps need to be well optimized
to deliver the best possible
user experience.
You can use
the RealityKit Trace template
to find performance bottlenecks
in your app.
Profiling proactively
with other instruments
and checking your content
in Reality Composer Pro
can also help you find
and resolve performance issues.
To learn more about how to use
the RealityKit Trace template
to optimize your apps,
please check out
the developer documentation.
And to get a better
understanding of performance
for this platform,
watch the session
"Optimize app power
and performance
for spatial computing."
Enjoy optimizing
your spatial computing apps,
whatever the trace may be.
Harjas: Thank you for watching.
♪