♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Curt Clifton: Hello and thanks
for joining us.
I'm Curt and I'm an engineer
on the SwiftUI team.
Jeff Robertson: And I'm Jeff.
I'm also an engineer
on the SwiftUI team.
We're happy to have the chance
to share what's new in SwiftUI.
Curt: You can now use SwiftUI
in even more places,
including a brand-new platform!
New data flow types dramatically
simplify modeling your domain,
providing more power
than ever before.
The Inspector,
plus Table improvements,
provide great ways
to display your data.
The team amped up
our animation APIs,
letting you create even more
beautiful experiences
for the people using your apps.
Across the framework,
we've enhanced your ability
to provide great interactions,
with powerful scroll view
improvements,
refinements to Focus
and keyboard input,
and deeper customization of
controls like buttons and menus.
I'm excited to tell you
about some great new places
to use SwiftUI.
From the headset and watchOS 10
to new widgets
and cross-framework integration,
SwiftUI can help you
create experiences
that delight the people
who use your apps.
Spatial computing brings SwiftUI
into a bold new future
with all-new 3D capabilities
like volumes;
rich experiences
with immersive spaces;
new 3D gestures,
effects, and layout;
and deep integration
with RealityKit.
From core pieces like the
Home View in Control Center
to familiar apps like TV,
Safari,
and Freeform;
to all-new environments like
immersive rehearsals in Keynote;
SwiftUI is at the heart
of these user experiences.
On this new platform,
construct windows
using familiar scene types
like WindowGroup.
WindowGroup scenes
render as 2D windows,
with delightful
depth-sensitive 3D controls.
Within a window, choose one
of the usual SwiftUI containers,
like NavigationSplitView
or TabView.
Within these containers,
you can use all
the usual SwiftUI controls just
like on the other platforms.
For even more depth,
apply the volumetric style
to your scene.
Volumes display
3D experiences --
like board games
or architectural models --
in a bounded space.
They display
alongside other apps.
People can use your content
while they jot down thoughts
in Notes or update slides
in Keynote.
Fill a volume with
a static model using Model3D.
For dynamic, interactive models
with lighting effects and more,
use the new RealityView.
To go truly all in, add
ImmersiveSpaces to your app.
The new ImmersiveSpace scene
type lets you define immersive,
spatial experiences,
whether embedded
in your surroundings
or with full immersion.
The system whisks
other apps away
letting people dive into
the world you've created.
Use an ImmersiveSpace
with the mixed immersion style
to connect your app
to the real world,
combining your content
with people's surroundings.
Anchor elements of your app
to tables and surfaces,
and augment and enrich
the real world
with virtual objects
and effects.
Go further with
the full immersion style.
Your app takes
complete control.
Build these connected
and immersive experiences
using the same Model3D
and RealityView
that work in volumes.
SwiftUI on this new platform
lets you create
magical experiences.
Watch "Meet SwiftUI
for spatial computing"
to continue exploring
this great combination.
SwiftUI is at home building
a room-filling experience,
but it can also
build experiences
for Apple's most
portable displays.
watchOS 10 delivers
a redesigned user experience
that surfaces
timely information,
conveys focused content
at a glance,
and celebrates the shape
and fidelity of the display.
We've updated apps across
the platform to take advantage
of this beautiful full-screen
color and imagery.
At the root of these designs are
several existing SwiftUI views,
newly empowered
for watchOS 10.
NavigationSplitView
and NavigationStack
get beautiful new transitions.
TabView gets a new
vertical paging style
driven by the Digital Crown.
SwiftUI introduces
some new API to help you
bring this full-color flair
to your Apple Watch apps too.
The new containerBackground
modifier
lets you configure
these subtle background washes
that animate when you push
and pop content.
You can also configure
backgrounds for tab views
on watchOS.
And new multiplatform
toolbar placements --
topBarLeading
and topBarTrailing,
along with the
existing bottomBar --
let you perfectly place
these small detail views
in your Apple Watch apps.
Besides these new additions,
we're pleased
to bring some existing API
to watchOS for the first time,
including DatePicker
and selection in Lists.
Now is a great time to polish
your Apple Watch apps
with these new capabilities.
And if you don't have
an Apple Watch app yet,
it's a great time to begin.
Learn how design and engineering
come together to create
these experiences in "Design
and build apps for watchOS 10."
Then apply these ideas
to your work
with "Update your app
for watchOS 10."
Widgets for the Smart Stack
on watchOS 10 let the people
using your app see
their information on the go.
SwiftUI is core to widgets
wherever they appear,
like these other new places.
Widgets on the Lock Screen
on iPadOS 17
are a great complement
to widgets on the Home Screen.
Big, bold widgets shine on
the iPhone Always-On display
with Standby Mode.
And desktop widgets
on macOS Sonoma
keep people up to date
during their day-to-day.
Widgets have found
their way to new places,
and the team has also
taught them another trick.
I'm thrilled to share
that widgets
now support
interactive controls.
Toggle and Button in Widgets
can now activate code
defined in your own app bundle
using App Intents.
And you can animate
your widgets
using SwiftUI transition
and animation modifiers.
To get started with these great
new capabilities, check out
"Bring widgets to new places"
and "Bring widgets to life."
To develop and refine your new
interactive animated widgets,
you'll love the power
of Xcode Previews.
Previews leverage macros
in Swift 5.9
to provide
an elegant new syntax.
Declare and configure a Preview,
add a widget type,
and define a timeline
for testing.
Xcode Previews shows
the current widget state
and a timeline that lets you see
the animations between states.
Of course, the new previews work
with regular SwiftUI views
and apps as well.
And you can now interact
with previews of Mac apps
right inside Xcode.
Check out the talk
"Build programmatic UI
with Xcode Previews"
to learn how to leverage these
terrific new tools
to accelerate your app
and widget development.
Besides the macros
that power previews,
Swift 5.9 also brings a host
of other improvements.
Get an overview of all
that's fresh in Swift
by queueing up
"What's new in Swift."
Another way SwiftUI
comes to new places
is through SwiftUI-specific
extensions
to other Apple frameworks.
Several frameworks bring
new or improved support,
and I'd like to highlight a few
that I think are
particularly exciting.
MapKit delivers a massive update
that gives you
the power of Apple's marvelous
mapping framework
right in your SwiftUI code.
Simply import SwiftUI and MapKit
to use these great features.
Put a map in your view.
Add custom markers, polylines,
and the user's location.
Configure
the available controls.
To learn all about
adding amazing maps
to your SwiftUI app,
check out the talk
"Meet MapKit for SwiftUI."
In its sophomore season,
Swift Charts brings a slew
of great improvements,
including scrolling charts,
built-in support for selection,
and something I know
folks have been hungry for:
donut and pie charts
with the new SectorMark.
To dig into these new features,
check out the talk
"Explore pie charts and
interactivity in Swift Charts."
For building
experiences that attract
and retain loyal customers,
you'll love the ease and power
of the new in-app purchase
and subscription stores.
Present a
subscription store view
with your custom
marketing content.
Configure a full-bleed
background
to match your branding
and choose from
a variety of control options.
Watch "Meet StoreKit
for SwiftUI"
to power up your in-app
marketing game.
From new platforms and widgets,
to cross-framework integration
and the beauty of watchOS,
SwiftUI continues to push
the Apple developer
experience forward.
It's exciting to see
all the new places
to use SwiftUI, Jeff.
Jeff: Certainly!
And we also have a lot
of great improvements
that work across
all our platforms.
Curt: Indeed!
Jeff: We should work on an app
that uses these improvements.
Curt: Oh, agreed!
Have you thought any more
about my idea?
Jeff: The one about dogs?
Curt: Yeah!
It's like bird-watching
but for dogs!
Jeff: Do you really think people
want a dog-watching app?
Curt: Oh, certainly! The pitch
deck practically writes itself.
Jeff: With our million-dollar
idea in place,
it's time to start
building out our app.
Since every great app begins
with a great data model,
let's start by looking at
the pack of great new features
SwiftUI has for working
with our app's data.
One of my favorite things
about SwiftUI is how it lets me
define my UI as a function
of my app's state.
I'm happy to share
the biggest upgrade
to how you define your model
types with SwiftUI:
the new Observable macro.
Observable models let you use
familiar SwiftUI patterns
for data flow,
while also making your code
more concise and performant.
Here's the model class
I've set up to store data
representing dogs I've met
while out and about.
To make this type an Observable,
I'll add the macro to my type.
That's all I need to do.
Unlike ObservableObject,
there's no need to mark
properties as Published.
Observable models
easily integrate
into the existing SwiftUI
mechanisms for data flow.
Let's use my DogCard view
as an example.
When using an Observable
in your View,
SwiftUI will automatically
establish dependencies
on properties you read.
There's also no need to use a
property wrapper when reading,
so your view code is cleaner.
And this view is reading
the isFavorite property,
so when that changes,
it will get reevaluated.
Invalidation only happens
for properties which are read,
so you can pass your model
through intermediate views
without triggering
any unnecessary updates.
SwiftUI includes several tools
for defining your state
and its relationship
to your views,
several of which are designed
for use with ObservableObject.
When using Observable,
this is becomes even simpler
since it's designed
to work directly
with the State and Environment
dynamic properties.
In addition to modeling
read-only values,
Observables are also a natural
fit to represent mutable state,
like on this form
for a new dog sighting.
The model is defined using
the State dynamic property,
and I'm passing bindings to its
properties to the form elements
responsible for editing
that property.
Lastly, Observable types
integrate seamlessly
into the environment.
Since views throughout
our app want a way
to fetch the current user,
I've added it to the environment
of my root view.
The user profile view
then reads the value
using the Environment
dynamic property.
I'm using the type
as the environment key here,
but custom keys
are also supported.
Be sure to catch "Discover
Observation with SwiftUI"
to learn more on how you can
take advantage
of this powerful new tool.
I love how Observable lets me
write clear and concise code.
It's given me a great start
to my app,
but I'd really like
to make sure any changes
to my data model are persisted,
so that I never lose track
of all my favorite pups.
SwiftData is an all-new
framework for data modeling
and management.
It's fast and scalable
and works great with SwiftUI.
SwiftData models are represented
entirely by their code,
making them a natural fit
for any SwiftUI app.
To set up my Dog model type
for SwiftData,
I'll switch from using
Observable to the Model macro.
This is the only change
I need to make.
In addition to the persistence
provided by SwiftData,
models also receive all the
benefits of using Observable.
It's really powerful.
Our dog-watching app's
main screen
shows a scrolling stack
of recently met doggos.
Let's take a walk
through the changes needed
to use SwiftData here.
First, I'll add
a model container
to my app's definition
and provide it my model type.
Then, in my view code,
I'll switch my array of dogs
to use the new
Query dynamic property.
Using Query will tell SwiftData
to fetch the model values
from the underlying database.
When the data changes,
like when I spot a new dog,
my view will be invalidated.
Query is incredibly efficient
for large data sets
and allows for customization
in how the data is returned,
such as changing
the sort order
to use the date
I spotted the dog,
which makes for a better
experience in the app.
SwiftData also works great
for storing a document's data
on macOS and iOS.
I decided I wanted a quick way
to prototype
some dog tag visual treatments
for our app,
so I built this little
document-based app
for collaborating with Curt
and our designers.
Document-based apps
can take advantage
of all the functionality
of SwiftData
using a new initializer.
SwiftUI will then use SwiftData
for the underlying storage
of each document,
as well as automatically set up
a model container.
To learn more about SwiftData
and how it integrates
with SwiftUI,
please watch "Meet SwiftData"
and "Build an app
with SwiftData."
In addition
to SwiftData support,
DocumentGroup
also gains a number
of new platform affordances when
running on iOS 17 or iPadOS 17,
such as automatic sharing
and document renaming support,
as well as undo controls
in the toolbar.
Inspector is a new modifier
for displaying details
about the current
selection or context.
It's presented as a distinct
section in your interface.
On macOS,
Inspector presents
as a trailing sidebar.
as well as on iPadOS
in a regular size class.
In compact size classes, it will
present itself as a sheet.
To uncover all the details
on Inspector,
watch "Inspectors in SwiftUI:
discover the details."
Dialogs have been given several
new customization APIs
in iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma.
I'm using some
of the new modifiers
to give my image export dialog
some useful information,
like adjusting
the confirmation button's label.
An increased severity
helps draw attention
to important
confirmation dialogs,
and including a suppression
toggle indicates a preference
that the dialog should
not present itself
for subsequent interactions.
Lastly, adding a HelpLink
can be a guide
to further information about
the purpose of the dialog.
Lists and tables are
a key part of most apps,
and SwiftUI has brought
some new features and APIs
for fine-tuning them in iOS 17
and macOS Sonoma.
Tables support customization
of their column ordering
and visibility.
When coupled with the
SceneStorage dynamic property,
these preferences
can be persisted
across runs of your app.
You provide the table
with a value
representing
the customization state
and give each column
a unique stable identifier.
Tables now also have all the
power of OutlineGroup built in.
This is great for large data
sets that lend themselves
to a hierarchical structure,
like this one which groups
some of my favorite dogs
with their proud parents.
Simply use the new
DisclosureTableRow
to represent rows
that contain other rows,
and build the rest of your table
as you would normally.
Sections within a list
or table have gained support
for programmatic expansion.
I've used it here
in my app's sidebar
to show the location section
as collapsed initially,
but while still allowing
for expansion.
The new initializer takes
a binding to a value
which reflects
the current expansion state
of the section.
For smaller data sets,
tables have also gained a few
new styling affordances,
such as how row backgrounds and
column headers are displayed.
And lastly, custom controls like
my star rating will also benefit
from the new background
prominence environment property.
Using a less prominent
foreground style
when the background is prominent
lets my custom control
feel right at home in a list.
In addition to these and other
APIs that let you fine-tune
the look and feel
of lists and tables,
we've also made big improvements
to the performance,
particularly when dealing
with large data sets.
To learn more about this
and the ways you can optimize
your own SwiftUI views,
check out
"Demystify SwiftUI performance."
From Observable
to SwiftData to Inspector
and table customizations,
working with data in your apps
feels like a whole
new experience.
Curt: With the data model
and tables
that Jeff has put together,
we have the bones
of a great app.
I'd like to add some pizazz
using the extraordinary
new animation APIs.
I think it would be great
to have an Apple TV app
for viewing a gallery
of dog photos.
Here's an animation
I've been working on
for choosing the current viewer.
I built this with the new
Keyframe Animator API.
Keyframe animators let me
animate multiple properties
in parallel.
I give the animator
a value containing
animatable properties
and a piece of equatable state.
Changes to the state
trigger my animation.
In the first closure,
I build a view,
modified by
my animatable properties,
like the vertical offset
of my logo.
In the second closure,
I define how these properties
change over time.
For example, the first track
defines the animation
of my verticalTranslation
property.
I pull my logo down 30 points
over the first quarter second
using a spring animation.
Then I make my Beagle leap
and land using a cubic curve.
Finally, I bring this dog home
with a natural spring animation.
I define additional tracks for
my other animated properties.
All these tracks run in parallel
to create this cool animation.
To learn how to leverage
keyframe animators in your apps,
check out "Wind your way through
advanced animations in SwiftUI."
I've also been working
on an Apple Watch app
to record dog sightings
when I'm out on a run.
It's pretty simple so far,
just our happy icon
and a button
to register a sighting.
I'd like to animate this icon
when I tap the button.
This is a good place
for a phase animator.
A phase animator is simpler
than a keyframe animator.
Instead of parallel tracks,
it steps through a single
sequence of phases.
This lets me start one animation
when the previous
animation finishes.
I give the animator a sequence
of phases and tell it
to run my animation whenever
my sightingCount changes.
Then in this first closure,
I set the rotation and scale
of my happy dog
based on the current phase.
The second closure tells SwiftUI
how to animate
into each phase.
I'm using some of the cool
new spring animations here.
I just love these names.
Who doesn't want a snappy
or bouncy animation?
And for my grow phase,
I'm using an entirely
custom spring.
Springs now take
a duration and bounce,
making them easier to describe.
You can use all
these new springs
everywhere that takes
a SwiftUI animation.
Spring animations
have a nice, natural feel.
They match the velocity
of any previous animation
and settle to their final value
with realistic friction.
They're now
the default animation
for apps built on or after
iOS 17 and aligned releases.
I'm pleased with
my animation now,
but when I'm out on a run,
it would be great
to also get some
haptic feedback.
Haptic feedback provides
a tactile response,
such as a tap,
to draw attention and reinforce
actions and events.
I think a tap on the wrist would
give me more confidence
that I didn't miss a dog.
Haptic feedback is easy with
the new sensory feedback API.
To play haptic feedback,
I just attach
the sensoryFeedback modifier,
specify what sort of feedback I
want and when it should happen.
The sensoryFeedback modifier
works on all platforms
that support haptic feedback.
Different platforms support
different kinds of feedback,
so check out
the Human Interface Guidelines
to learn what sorts of feedback
will be best in your apps.
I've also been working
on an animation
for the welcome screen, using
the new visual effects modifier.
The visual effects modifier
lets me
update these dog photos
based on their position.
And I don't need
a GeometryReader to do it.
I've got a little simulation
that moves a focal point
around the screen.
This red dot shows
what I mean by focal point.
I associate a coordinate space
with this grid
that shows all the dogs.
Then inside my DogCircle view,
I add a visual effect.
The closure gets my content
to modify and a geometry proxy.
I'm passing the geometry proxy
to a helper method
to compute the scale.
I can use the geometry proxy
to get the size of my grid view
and the frame of a single dog
circle relative to my grid view.
That lets me compute
how far any dog is
from the focal point
of the simulation,
so I can scale up
the focused doggos.
With visual effects,
I can do all of this
without using a GeometryReader.
And it automatically adapts
to different sizes.
I'd like to share
one more example.
I've been playing
with a feature
to send good-dog messages to
the people of the dogs I've met.
I thought it would be fun
to style the dog's name
to make it stand out.
This is easy now that
I can interpolate text
with a foreground style
right inside another text view.
And check it out!
I can adjust the styling
using these sliders.
Now how does that work?
Here's how I'm
defining the style.
I'm passing my stripeSpacing
and angle,
along with a color
from my asset catalog,
to a custom Metal shader.
Using SwiftUI's
new ShaderLibrary,
I can turn
Metal shader functions
directly into SwiftUI
shape styles,
like this one that renders
the stripes in Furdinand's name.
If you'd like to take Metal
shaders out for a spin,
just add a new Metal file
to your project
and call your shader function
using ShaderLibrary in SwiftUI.
There's another thing
in this example
that I want to point out.
Notice when I hit the end
of the tracks on the sliders,
the symbol gives
this satisfying bounce.
That effect is built in
to Slider on macOS and iOS.
You can also add it
to your own symbols
with the new symbol
effect modifier.
Just apply this modifier
to animate an SF Symbol,
or all the symbols
in a view hierarchy.
Symbols support
a variety of effects,
including continuous animations
with pulse and variable color.
State changes with scale,
appear and disappear,
and replace,
and event notifications
with bounce.
Watch
"Animate symbols in your app"
to learn about the best
people-pleasing practices
for using symbol effects.
Before leaving this example,
I want to point out
one last feature.
Notice the units
on the text here.
In the past I might have used
small caps for this effect,
but now I can get
this appearance
by applying the new
textScale modifier to my units.
If Jeff and I bring our app
to the Chinese market,
the units will be
sized correctly,
even though the concept
of small caps
isn't part of the typography
in Chinese.
We have another tool
to help apps work great
in multiple locales.
Some languages, like Thai,
use taller letter forms.
When text from one
of these languages
is embedded in text
localized in a language
with shorter letter forms,
like English,
the taller text can
be crowded or clipped.
When we know that
this might be an issue --
for example, if our dog names
were globally crowd-sourced --
we can apply the
typesettingLanguage modifier.
This lets SwiftUI know that
the text might need more space.
I'm having so much fun
using these new APIs,
but it's important to tastefully
choose animations
to avoid overwhelming people.
To learn about the fundamentals
of animation in SwiftUI,
check out
"Explore SwiftUI animation."
Then in "Animate with springs,"
Jacob will help you build
animations that feel at home
on everyone's devices.
The breadth of new animation
APIs in SwiftUI is amazing.
I've only scratched
the surface here.
There's even more to discover,
from animation
completion handlers
to building entirely
custom animations.
I hope you enjoy these APIs
as much as I do.
Jeff: I love how all these new
animations and effects
really bring our app to life.
Now, let's take a look at some
of the new interaction APIs
for the final touches.
Interactions are at the heart
of any great app experience,
and these are just a few
of the updated APIs
coming to iOS 17
and aligned releases.
My screen of recently met dogs
could use a little extra flair
to give it that final bit
of polish.
I'd like to add some
visual effects to my dog cards
as they transition in and out
of the visible area
of my scroll view.
The scroll transition modifier
is very similar
to the visual effect modifier
Curt used earlier
for the welcome screen.
It lets you apply effects
to items in your scroll view.
Using the scale
and opacity effects
gave me just that little bit
of polish I wanted,
with only a few
extra lines of code.
I'd also like to add
a side-scrolling list
of my favorite dog parks
to this screen.
SwiftUI has added some great
features to let me build this.
Above my vertical stack of dogs,
I'll drop in a horizontal stack
for the park cards.
I'm using the new
containerRelativeFrame
modifier
to size these park cards
relative to the visible size
of the horizontal scroll view.
The count specifies
how many chunks
to divide the screen into.
The span says how many of those
chunks each view should take.
This is pretty great,
but I'd like my park cards
to snap into place.
The new scrollTargetLayout
modifier makes that easy.
I'll add it to the LazyHStack
and modify the scroll view
to align to views
in the targeted layout.
In addition to view alignment,
scroll views can also be defined
to use a paging behavior.
And for a truly
custom experience,
you can define your own behavior
using the scrollTargetBehavior
protocol.
I also thought my mutts
would deserve a little accolade
when they're at the top
of the scroll view.
The new scrollPosition
modifier takes a binding
to the topmost item's ID,
and it's updated as I scroll.
This way,
I always know who's top dog.
To learn more about all these
and the other great improvements
to Scroll View,
be sure to watch
"Beyond scroll views."
Image now supports rendering
content with high dynamic range.
By applying the
allowedDynamicRange modifier,
the beautiful images
in our app's gallery screen
can be shown
with their full fidelity.
It's best to use this
sparingly, though,
and usually when
the image stands alone.
Apps written with SwiftUI
work great
with accessibility features
out of the box,
but you can make them
even better
with some of the new
accessibility APIs
we're introducing.
The adventurous dog
in this photo
is a bit too far away to see,
so I've applied
a magnification gesture
to allow zooming in.
I'm also going to add the new
accessibilityZoomAction
modifier to my view.
This allows assistive
technologies like VoiceOver
to access the same functionality
without using the gesture.
I'll just update the zoom level
depending on
the action's direction,
and I can see what mischief
she's been up to now.
VoiceOver: Zooming image view.
Image.
Jeff: To learn more
about all the new
accessibility functionality
across Apple's platforms,
be sure to check out
"Build accessible apps
with SwiftUI and UIKit."
Color now supports
using static member syntax
to look up custom colors defined
in your app's asset catalog.
This gives compile-time safety
when using them,
so you'll never
lose time to a typo.
For the document app
I showed earlier,
I've added a menu containing
several useful actions
to the toolbar.
The top section of the menu
is a ControlGroup
with the new compactMenu style,
which shows its items
as icons in a horizontal stack.
The tag color selector
is defined as a picker
with the new palette style.
Using this style in concert
with symbol images
gives a great visual
representation in menus,
especially one like this
where I can use the label's tint
to differentiate them.
Lastly, the
paletteSelectionEffect modifier
lets me use a symbol variant
to represent the selected item
in the picker.
With my menu in place,
Buddy's dog tag can
now be his favorite color,
tennis-ball yellow.
Bordered buttons can now
be defined
with new built-in shapes,
such as circle
and rounded rectangle.
These new border shape styles
work on iOS, watchOS, and macOS.
Buttons on macOS and iOS
can now react to drag actions,
like this button in my editor
that opens a popover.
The new springLoadingBehavior
modifier
indicates that a button
should trigger its action
when a drag pauses over it, or
when force-clicking it on macOS.
Buttons on tvOS
can make great use
of the new highlight
hover effect.
I've used it
on our gallery images
and applied it just
to the image portion
of my button's label,
to create an effect
which feels right at home
on the platform.
These buttons also use
the borderless style,
which is now available on tvOS.
Hardware keyboards are great
for providing an accelerant
for common interactions
in your app.
Focusable views on platforms
with hardware keyboard support
can use
the onKeyPress modifier
to directly react
to any keyboard input.
The modifier takes a set of keys
to match against
and an action to perform
for the event.
To get your fill
of focus-related recipes,
be sure to watch "The SwiftUI
cookbook for focus."
From the scroll transitions
and behaviors,
to button styles
and focus interactions,
these new APIs
can help you build apps
with rich functionality
and outstanding style.
Curt: I think we've made
great progress on our app!
Jeff: It's certainly something.
Curt: It was fun
using all these new APIs.
Jeff: That much is true.
Curt: It's an exciting time
for SwiftUI.
There's a brand-new platform!
Jeff: And the elegance
of Observable and SwiftData
work so well with SwiftUI.
Curt: The animation improvements
are amazing.
Jeff: And don't forget
scroll views!
Curt: It's always
a thrill to see
what our amazing
developer community
can do with these new APIs.
Jeff: Thanks for watching,
everyone.
Say hi to your dog for me!
Curt: Keep doing great work!
♪