♪ ♪
Tyler: Welcome
to "Unleash the UIKit Trait System."
I’m Tyler Fox, a UI frameworks engineer,
and I’m excited to tell you
about some incredible new UIKit features
that you can take advantage of in iOS 17.
To start, I’ll review fundamentals
about the trait system in UIKit.
Then I’ll guide you
through the new features and capabilities,
which include the ability
to define custom traits
to add your own data to UITraitCollection,
easier ways to apply trait overrides
in your app’s hierarchy,
and more flexible ways
to handle when traits change.
Finally, I’ll explain how you can bridge
UIKit traits with SwiftUI environment keys
to seamlessly pass data between UIKit
and SwiftUI components in your app.
It's time to review some fundamentals.
Traits are independent pieces of data
that the system automatically propagates
to every view controller and view
in your app.
UIKit provides
many built-in system traits,
such as user interface style,
horizontal size class,
and preferred content size category.
In iOS 17, you can define
your own custom traits as well.
This unlocks a powerful new way
for you to provide data
to your app's view controllers and views.
I'll tell you all about custom traits
a little bit later.
The main way that you work with traits
in UIKit is using trait collections.
A trait collection contains traits
and their associated values.
There are some new APIs in iOS 17
that make it easier
to work with trait collections.
First, there is a new initializer
that takes a closure.
Inside that closure,
you receive a mutable traits container
that you can set values to.
This mutable container conforms
to a new protocol named UIMutableTraits.
Inside the closure,
I set the user interface idiom to phone
and the horizontal size class to regular.
When the closure finishes executing,
the initializer returns
an immutable UITraitCollection instance
that contains all of the trait values
I set inside the closure.
There’s also a new modifyingTraits method
that allows you to create a new instance
by modifying values from the original
trait collection inside the closure.
Here I’ve changed
the horizontal size class to compact,
and I've populated a dark value
for the user interface style.
Since I haven't changed
the user interface idiom,
it remains equal to phone
from my original trait collection.
While you can create
your own trait collections like this,
most of the time you obtain
trait collections from trait environments.
Trait environments
in your app are window scenes,
windows, presentation controllers,
view controllers, and views.
Every one of these trait environments has
its own trait collection,
and each trait collection may contain
different values.
Trait environments are connected
in the trait hierarchy,
which is how traits flow through your app.
Here's an example
of the trait hierarchy’s tree structure,
from each window scene all the way down
to the individual view controllers
and views.
Each trait environment inherits
trait values from its parent environment.
Always use the trait collection
of the most specific
trait environment possible.
I'll dive deeper into the way that traits
flow through view controllers and views.
Here is an example
of a parent view controller,
which contains a child view controller.
The dashed line represents
the view controller hierarchy.
The parent controller owns a view,
and the solid line connecting them
represents their relationship.
The parent view has one subview,
and the dashed line through the views
represents the view hierarchy.
Finally, the view of the child controller
is a subview of that middle view.
First I’ll explain how traits flowed
through view controllers and views
prior to iOS 17.
View controllers inherited traits directly
from their parent view controller.
And views owned by a view controller
inherited their traits
directly from their view controller.
Finally, views without a view controller
inherited traits
directly from their superview.
This behavior meant that the flow
of traits in the view hierarchy stopped
at each view owned by a view controller.
For example, a trait value from the view
of the parent controller
would only be inherited
by its direct subview.
The view of the child controller wouldn’t
receive that value,
even though it is a subview
in the view hierarchy below those views.
This behavior could be surprising.
In iOS 17, we’ve eliminated this issue
by unifying the trait hierarchy
for view controllers and views.
View controllers now inherit their trait
collection from their view’s superview,
instead of directly
from their parent view controller.
This creates a simple linear flow
of traits
through view controllers and views.
Note how view controllers still inherit
traits from their parent view controller,
it just happens indirectly
via the views in between them.
Because view controllers now inherit
their traits from the view hierarchy,
a view controller’s view must be
in the hierarchy
for the view controller
to receive updated traits.
As a result, if you access
a view controller’s trait collection
before its view has been added
to the hierarchy,
the view controller won’t have
up-to-date values for its traits.
The most common place you might find code
that is affected is inside viewWillAppear,
as that is always called before
the view has been added to the hierarchy.
There's a new callback named
viewIsAppearing that you can use instead.
viewIsAppearing is called
after viewWillAppear
once the view has been added
to the hierarchy
and both the view controller and view have
up-to-date trait collections.
viewIsAppearing is a drop-in replacement
for nearly all cases
where you’re using viewWillAppear today.
And the best part is that this new method
back-deploys all the way to iOS 13.
Watch "What’s New In UIKit"
to learn more about this new callback
and how it fits
into the view controller life cycle.
iOS 17 also improves the consistency
and performance for view trait updates.
Views only update their trait collection
when they are in the hierarchy.
And once in the hierarchy, each view only
updates its trait collection
immediately before it performs layout.
The best practice is to use traits
during layout.
For views,
that means using the traitCollection
from inside the layoutSubviews method.
Remember that layoutSubviews runs again
any time setNeedsLayout is called
on the view,
so your implementation should avoid
duplicating work if called multiple times.
Custom traits are a powerful new feature
in iOS 17.
They open up an entirely new way
for you to provide data
to your view controllers and views.
As you work with data in your app,
consider the following things
to help you decide
when to define a new custom trait.
Traits are a great choice when you need
to propagate data to many children,
such as from a parent view controller
to multiple child view controllers
or from a superview
to all of its subviews.
You can also use traits to pass data
to other components
that may be nested many layers deep,
where you don’t have
a direct connection to them.
Because traits are inherited
through the hierarchy,
they can provide context
to your views and view controllers
about their environment,
such as providing information
about a containing view controller.
While the trait system is powerful,
using it to propagate data is not free.
For best performance,
use traits when they add value,
but avoid using traits
when you can easily pass data directly.
Now you're ready to define
your first custom trait.
Imagine that I have a Settings screen
in my app,
and I want to implement a trait
that indicates whether a view is contained
inside my Settings view controller.
I can define a custom trait
with just a few lines of code.
To start, I declare a new struct
and conform
to the UITraitDefinition protocol.
I implement the one required
static property, defaultValue.
This is the default value for the trait
when no value has been set.
Each trait definition has
an associated value type,
which is inferred from the defaultValue.
In this case, since I am assigning
a defaultValue of false,
the type of this trait's values
is inferred to be Bool.
If you’ve ever defined a custom
environment key in SwiftUI before,
this should feel very familiar.
Once you’ve defined a trait,
you can immediately use it with new APIs
on UITraitCollection and UIMutableTraits.
You can think of the trait as a key
that you use to get and set values.
Inside the new
UITraitCollection initializer,
I can set a value for my trait by using
the subscript operator on UIMutableTraits.
And then I can read back
the value for the trait
by using the subscript operator
on UITraitCollection.
Adding two simple extensions will
let me access this trait
using standard property syntax,
just like all of the system traits.
Here I’ve declared a read-only property
in an extension
of the immutable UITraitCollection class.
And then I’ve declared
a read-write property
in an extension
of the UIMutableTraits protocol.
Now that I’ve added
these very simple extensions,
I can use standard property syntax
to access my trait everywhere.
Always write these extensions
when you define your own custom traits.
I have an idea for another custom trait.
Imagine I'm building support
for custom color themes in my app.
I have an enum named MyAppTheme
that represents the four different
color themes my app supports.
The first thing I’ll do is declare
a new struct
which conforms
to the UITraitDefinition protocol.
I’ll use the standard theme
as the default value for this trait.
Since I plan to use this new theme trait
in my app’s custom dynamic colors,
I indicate that this trait affects
color appearance,
and the system will automatically
redraw views when this trait changes.
Traits that affect color appearance
are much more expensive,
so use this sparingly and only for traits
that change infrequently.
Traits also have a name,
which is used for things
like printing the trait in the debugger.
By default, it will use the name
of the trait type itself,
but I can give it a shorter name,
like “Theme.”
And finally,
I can provide an identifier string.
The identifier makes the trait eligible
for additional features such as encoding.
Use reverse-DNS format
to ensure each trait's identifier
is globally unique in your app.
I want to be able to use regular
property syntax to set and get this trait,
so I’ll extend UITraitCollection
and UIMutableTraits to declare a property,
just as I did before
in the previous example.
And that’s all I need to do
to implement a custom theme trait.
Now I can start using this new trait.
For example, here is how to define
a custom dynamic color
that changes its appearance
based on the theme.
I create a new UIColor
using the dynamic provider initializer.
Inside the closure,
I use the theme of the trait collection
that gets passed in
to determine which color to return.
Now I can set this custom background color
to a view.
Because I indicated
that this trait affects color appearance
when I defined it, any views using
this custom background color
will automatically update
when the theme changes.
When defining a trait,
the most important thing to consider
is the associated data type
of the trait’s values.
The best traits are built
around value types,
including simple structs and enums.
Avoid traits that are based
around classes in Swift.
The most efficient data types
for traits are Bool, Int, and Double,
or an enum that uses an Int raw value.
Enums are one of the most useful
data types for traits.
Just make sure to explicitly specify Int
as the enum's raw data type
for maximum efficiency.
Any custom struct data types
that you use as trait values should have
an efficient implementation
of the Equatable protocol.
The system will compare trait values
frequently
to determine when traits have changed,
so your equal-to function should be
as fast as possible.
For those of you with apps
that use Objective-C,
the new trait system functionality
is available there as well.
The API for custom traits is different
in Swift and Objective-C.
However, you can define one custom trait
in Swift and one in Objective-C,
and have both point
to the same underlying data.
Refer to the documentation for more
details and special considerations.
Once you’ve defined a custom trait,
the next step is to populate some data
for it in your app's trait hierarchy.
Trait overrides are the mechanism you use
to modify data within the trait hierarchy.
In iOS 17, it’s easier than ever
to apply trait overrides.
There’s a new traitOverrides property
on each of the trait environment classes,
including window scenes, windows, views,
view controllers,
and presentation controllers.
Going back to the illustration
of the trait hierarchy,
trait overrides change the value
for traits at any location in this tree.
When you apply a trait override to one of
the trait environments in this hierarchy,
it modifies the value for that trait
in the trait collection of that object
and all of its descendants.
Taking a parent and child trait
environment from the trait hierarchy,
here’s how trait overrides affect both.
Trait overrides applied to the parent
affect the parent’s own trait collection.
And then the values
from the parent’s trait collection
are inherited to the child.
Finally, the child's trait overrides
are applied to the values it inherited
to produce its own trait collection.
Think of trait overrides
as optional inputs,
and the trait collection as the output.
Any traits without overrides will inherit
from the parent.
I’ll go through an example
of using trait overrides
to change the color theme
for specific parts of my app.
On the right, I have an illustration
of my app’s trait hierarchy.
Initially, I haven’t applied any overrides
to populate the value for my theme trait,
so all of these trait collections have
the default value,
which is the standard theme.
I’ll start by applying a trait override
to the root of this hierarchy
on the window scene.
The traitOverrides property leverages
the UIMutableTraits protocol
to allow you to easily set trait values.
Therefore, you can set override values
for custom traits
with standard property syntax
using the extension to UIMutableTraits
I explained earlier.
By setting the theme to pastel on
the trait overrides of the window scene,
all of the windows, view controllers,
and views inside of that window scene
now inherit the pastel value
in their trait collections.
So by setting the theme in one place
at the root of the hierarchy,
I’ve changed the base value
that gets propagated
to everything in that hierarchy.
For example, I can read the theme
from the trait collection
of any view controller
inside that window scene
and get back pastel.
Then I can use the traitOverrides property
on a view deeper in the hierarchy
to modify the theme for that view
and anything below it.
Here I’m setting a monochrome theme
trait override for this view.
So this monochrome value is what
is inherited by its subview,
overriding the pastel value
from higher up in the hierarchy.
You may not see changes
to trait overrides reflected immediately
in the trait collection.
For example, because views update their
trait collection right before layout,
modifications to a view’s trait overrides
aren't reflected in its trait collection
until just before it runs layoutSubviews.
The traitOverrides property
also allows you to check
whether overrides are applied
and remove overrides altogether.
Here is an example of toggling an override
by using the contains method
to check if an override exists,
and the remove method
to remove the override entirely.
Each time this method is called,
it will either remove
the existing override
or apply a new theme override
when there wasn't one already.
Trait overrides are an input mechanism
to set values.
To read trait values,
always use the traitCollection property.
Reading from traitOverrides
when no override has been set
will raise an exception.
Here are some performance considerations
to keep in mind
as you use trait overrides.
First, each trait override
has a small cost,
so only set trait overrides
on the places you need them
and avoid setting trait overrides
that aren’t used.
And every time you change
a trait override,
the system needs
to update the trait collection
of any descendants in the hierarchy.
Therefore, minimize the number of times
that you change trait overrides.
Finally, trait overrides applied
near the root of the hierarchy,
such as on the window scene or window,
affect everything beneath them.
This is very useful,
and there are many great use cases
for applying trait overrides
to the window scene or window.
However, when a trait only affects
a few views deep in the hierarchy,
then apply the trait override
to the nearest common ancestor
of those views instead, such as
a common superview or a view controller.
That way, you aren’t paying the cost
of propagating the trait
to your entire hierarchy
when only a small portion
of the hierarchy uses that data.
Now that you know how to define traits
and populate data for them
in the hierarchy,
you need to handle when they change value.
traitCollectionDidChange is deprecated
in iOS 17.
When you implement
traitCollectionDidChange,
the system doesn’t know
which traits you actually care about,
so it has to call that method
every time that any trait changes value.
However, most classes only use
a handful of traits
and don’t care about changes
to any others.
This is why
traitCollectionDidChange doesn’t scale
as you add more and more custom traits.
In its place,
there are new trait registration APIs
that are more flexible
and improve performance.
By registering for changes
to specific traits,
the system knows exactly
which traits you depend on.
The new APIs allow you
to receive callbacks
using the target-action pattern
or a closure.
And because you no longer need
to override a method in your subclass,
it’s now easy to observe trait changes
from anywhere.
I'll start by explaining how to update
an existing implementation
of traitCollectionDidChange.
Here’s my existing implementation.
Note how I check whether
the horizontalSizeClass trait changed
before calling updateViews,
as that method only relies
on this one trait.
If you need to keep using
traitCollectionDidChange
because you are deploying your app
to older iOS versions,
make sure that your implementation checks
whether the specific traits
that you care about have changed.
Now I'll replace this implementation
with the new trait registration methods
in iOS 17.
I'll start with the closure-based method.
I call registerForTraitChanges and pass
an array of traits to register for.
There are new UITrait symbols
for all of the system traits,
such as this one
for horizontal size class.
Then I pass a closure that is called
when those specific traits change.
The closure is not called
for changes to any other traits,
so there's no need to compare old
and new trait values here.
The object whose traits have changed
is passed
as the first parameter to the closure.
Use this parameter
so you don’t have to capture
a weak reference to that object.
When you're registering
for trait changes on self,
always write "self: Self" here.
You can also observe trait changes
for a different trait environment.
Here I'm registering for changes
to two traits,
the horizontal size class
and the ContainedInSettings custom trait
I defined earlier.
The closure executes when either
of these traits change on this other view.
I write the type of the view
I'm registering on
as the first parameter of the closure.
Here's an example of the new
target-action-based method.
Call registerForTraitChanges and pass
an array of traits to register for
as well as the target and action method
to call on changes.
The target parameter is optional.
If you omit it,
the target will be the same object
that registerForTraitChanges is called on.
In this case, that's self.
As with the closure method,
you can also register for changes
on other trait environments.
Here I’m registering for trait changes
on another view,
but setting up a call to a method on self
named handleTraitChange.
When registering for trait changes
using a target-action,
your action method can have zero,
one, or two parameters.
The first parameter is always the object
whose traits are changing.
Use this parameter
to get the new traitCollection.
The second parameter will always be
the previous trait collection
for that object before the change.
In addition to registering
for individual traits,
you can also register
using new semantic sets of system traits.
For example, there is
systemTraitsAffectingColorAppearance,
which returns any system traits
that may affect
the way system dynamic colors resolve.
There’s also
systemTraitsAffectingImageLookup,
which returns the subset of system traits
that are considered
when you load an image using
UIImage(named:).
Pass either of these sets directly
to registerForTraitChanges
to perform custom invalidation.
Registrations are cleaned up automatically
when you use the new methods
to register for trait changes.
If you have an advanced use case,
you can manually unregister
using a token that is returned
by each of the registration methods.
But these cases are very rare,
so generally you should just ignore
the return value
when you call registerForTraitChanges.
As you adopt the new
trait registration APIs,
there are two best practices
to keep in mind.
First, register only for the traits
that you actually depend on
so you don't perform work
when unrelated traits change value.
Finally, try to invalidate
in response to trait changes
without updating immediately.
For example, if you use traits
inside of the layoutSubviews method
of a view subclass, call setNeedsLayout
to invalidate for a trait change.
This schedules the view
to receive layoutSubviews,
but doesn’t perform the update
immediately.
Now that you can propagate your own data
using the trait system in UIKit,
it unlocks an entirely new way
for you to seamlessly pass data
between UIKit and SwiftUI components
in your app.
Custom traits in UIKit are very similar
to custom environment keys in SwiftUI.
You can bridge them to access
the same data from both UIKit and SwiftUI.
Whether you’re embedding
SwiftUI components inside of UIKit,
or UIKit components inside of SwiftUI,
bridged data passes seamlessly
between them.
You can read and write
to the same underlying data
using the trait APIs in your UIKit code
and the environment APIs
in your SwiftUI code.
It’s incredibly easy to take
the new color theme trait
I defined for my app’s UIKit code
and bridge it to a corresponding
environment key in SwiftUI.
Assuming I have a custom trait in UIKit
and a custom environment key in SwiftUI
that represent the same data,
all I need to do to bridge them
is add a conformance
to the UITraitBridgedEnvironmentKey
protocol.
To do this, I implement one method
to read the trait from UIKit
and return the value to SwiftUI,
and one method to write the SwiftUI
environment value to the UIKit trait.
And now both the UIKit trait and SwiftUI
environment key access unified storage,
so I can read or write to the same data
from components written
using either framework.
Here is an example of how I can use
the bridged trait and environment key.
At the root of my app, I apply
a trait override for the theme trait
onto the UIKit window scene.
This propagates the monochrome theme value
to everything contained
inside that window scene.
Then, deeper down inside of a window
in that window scene,
I have a UIKit collection view.
This collection view contains cells,
which are configured
using UIHostingConfiguration,
to display a SwiftUI view in each cell.
Inside the SwiftUI CellView,
I have a property named "theme,"
which uses
the Environment property wrapper
to read the value
from the SwiftUI environment.
The value in the environment corresponds
to the same value
for the bridged trait in UIKit.
And finally, I use the theme property
to control the color of text
inside this SwiftUI view.
Because SwiftUI automatically tracks
data dependencies,
if the theme trait override all the way up
on the UIKit window scene changes
to a different value, my SwiftUI cell view
will automatically update
to reflect the new theme.
The bridging also works
in the other direction.
Here I have a SwiftUI view
that displays my app’s settings.
I use the environment modifier
to set the standard theme,
which will apply to everything
in the settings controller.
This is conceptually equivalent
to applying a trait override in UIKit.
Then, in the UIKit-based
Settings view controller
contained inside
the UIViewControllerRepresentable,
I read the theme value
from the bridged trait
and use it to update the title displayed
for this view controller.
This is how easy it is
to seamlessly access data
using bridged UIKit traits
and SwiftUI environment keys.
Now that you've learned
about these powerful new features,
go and find places in your app
where you can leverage the trait system
to automatically propagate data
by defining your own custom traits.
Next, adopt the new
traitOverrides property
to easily modify data
in the trait hierarchy.
And then use the more flexible
trait registration APIs
to create precise dependencies
on the exact traits you use.
Finally, bridge your custom UIKit traits
with custom SwiftUI environment keys
so that your data flows seamlessly between
UIKit and SwiftUI components in your app.
Now it’s up to you
to unleash the power of traits.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪