♪ ♪
Artem: Hi, my name is Artem.
I’m an engineer
on the Apple Push Notifications team.
I'm excited to introduce you
to Push Notifications Console.
It is a brand-new tool
which combines a few features
that will help you integrate
push notifications into your app.
I’ll start by sending some
notifications from the console,
which can be helpful
for end to end testing.
Next, I’ll use the delivery log feature
to analyze some common problems.
And finally, I’ll introduce you
to some additional tools
that you can leverage to work
with authentication and device tokens.
To begin, I’m going to cover
some Push Notifications basics.
Push notifications are short messages
that are sent to a user's device
from an application or website.
They are an incredibly powerful tool
to expand the capabilities of your app.
There are millions
of push notifications delivered
to Apple devices each second,
enriching user experience.
These notifications are delivered
in real time and are designed
to provide users with timely
and relevant information.
This allows for a more dynamic
experience when it comes
to updating your application.
Push notifications can help
to increase user engagement,
and allow them to always stay
up-to-date with your app.
Here’s a brief overview of how it works.
The backend that enables the delivery
of push notifications is called
Apple Push Notification service,
or APNs for short.
The story of a notification begins
when you prompt the user
to allow notifications from your app.
If the user agrees,
a Device Token is generated
by APNs and then sent to the device.
That token uniquely identifies
your app on that particular device.
Usually the token is then forwarded
to your application server
which stores it for future use.
When the server wants
to send a push notification,
it uses the stored device token
to address the notification through APNs.
APNs then delivers
the notification to the app
on the device
with the corresponding token.
Note that device tokens can change,
so it's essential to keep them
up-to-date on the server side
for accurate and reliable delivery.
The Push Notifications console
is a brand-new tool
that provides a variety of instruments
for interacting with APNs.
If you're developing an app
and adding push notifications to it,
you might want to have
a quick way of testing it end-to-end.
That’s where
the send feature comes in handy.
I’m developing the Backyard Birds app.
It's now spring,
and some birds are returning
from their wintering grounds,
so I want to let users know about that.
I’m going to create a new notification.
Give it a name,
provide the device token
of the app on the phone,
and then fill some payload attributes.
I’ll use the name
of the app for the title.
The subtitle will say “Important Update.”
And the body will be
the “Robins are back” message.
Now that it's ready,
I’m going to click send.
When a device receives a push,
it displays a notification.
The history of the notifications
sent from this page is preserved
for your convenience
in the sidebar on the left.
I want to reuse the last notification,
but slightly change the message.
I’m going to copy the message that was
just sent and create a new notification.
Here, give it a name.
And then toggle this switch
which allows me to enter
the payload in raw JSON format.
I’m going to insert the payload
I just copied and only change
the message to a different one.
Supply the same Device token,
and then send it.
And the device
receives an updated notification.
The Console allows you
to test many types of notifications
and different attributes.
You can specify the environment...
Try different push types...
Set the exact expiration...
Try different priorities...
And send any type of payload.
Next up,
I’ll cover the Delivery Log feature.
Sometimes there are situations where
a notification you send is not received,
leaving you uncertain
about what happened to it.
Using this tool might
help you analyze such cases.
As a notification travels
through the APNs stack
the events that reflect
its delivery process are recorded.
And now you can retrieve that information,
using the new header that APNs
returns when the notification is sent.
Here’s how it works.
The device can emulate a situation
where a notification is not received
by enabling Low Power mode.
Then, I go to the Send tab
and resend one of the notifications.
I’ll give it a name,
paste the payload,
supply the device token,
and set the expiration date
sometime into the future.
But this time, after clicking “send”
the notification
will not show up on the device.
To find out what happened,
I’m going to copy the new type of ID
that APNs returns in HTTP response,
“apns-unique-id”.
After switching to the “Delivery Log” tab,
I'm presented with a search field
where I can put the ID I just copied.
Once I run the search,
I can see the history of the notification
as it traveled through the APNs stack.
Here the last event is
"stored for device power considerations,"
which explains
why the message was not delivered.
In this case,
the phone was in Low Power Mode,
so it deferred receiving
some notifications to conserve battery.
When Low Power mode is disabled,
the notification is received
and displayed on the device.
After it's delivered,
the corresponding update can also
be seen in the delivery log.
With this tool, you can analyze
a variety of situations.
Each history event not only
describes what happened, but also why
in corresponding tooltips.
For example, a notification can go
to APNs storage if the device is offline
or can be discarded if the app
was removed from the device.
You’ll find more examples
when you start working with the tool.
This feature is available
for notifications sent
through regular APNs API as well.
You need to record “apns-unique-id”
from APNs response to be able
to query this information.
And for the notifications
sent from the Console,
there’s no need
to switch to the “delivery log” tab,
the same information is available
on the Send page itself.
As you integrate your app with APNs,
you’ll work with different types
of tokens used for authentication
and sending notifications,
and the console also provides
a variety of handy tools
to help you work with them.
Let’s cover authentication first.
There are two types
of authentication with APNs:
Certificate-based and token-based.
Certificate-based authentication relies
on SSL certificates
to establish a trusted connection
between your server and APNs.
You need to create and manage
certificates for each app and environment
within the Apple Developer portal.
Keep in mind that certificates expire
and need to be renewed periodically.
Token-based authentication uses
JSON Web Tokens for secure
and efficient authentication
between your provider server and APNs.
It requires generating a token
signed with a private key associated
with your Apple Developer account.
Private keys don't expire
like certificates.
As part of Push Notifications Console,
there's now a tool that can generate
an authentication token for you.
All you need
to do is supply a private key,
obtained from the developer portal...
And associated key ID.
After supplying these pieces,
a new token will be generated.
You can then use it to authenticate
your requests against APNs.
Keep in mind that the validity period
of these tokens can not exceed one hour,
so they need to be rotated periodically.
And when you generate a token,
your key is not uploaded anywhere.
It is only used in your browser,
so your private information is preserved.
If you already have a token,
but think it might not be working,
you can leverage another tool,
authentication token validator.
I’m going to take
the token I just generated,
and then paste it
into the validation tool.
Here, I get back the validation result,
which will either confirm that the token
is valid, like in this case,
or provide you the reason why it’s not.
For example,
when I supply a token I used a while ago,
the validation result is telling me
that the “issued at” claim is too old,
which effectively means
that the token has expired.
And lastly,
there’s the Device Token validator.
As you remember,
these tokens are used to specify
the recipient
when you send a notification.
They are tied to a concrete
environment and push type.
When you enter a token,
you will get a response that will tell you
which environment and push type
the token is valid for, if any.
For example,
when I supply the token that was used
used in the demonstration before,
we can see that it is valid
for Alert & Background push types
and Development environment.
Hopefully you’ll enjoy using
these features and find it easier
to integrate Push Notifications
into your app,
providing people
with new exciting functionality.
Get started today.
Send push notifications
to test integration end-to-end.
Examine delivery logs and get better
insight into the delivery process.
Validate your tokens and generate
new ones, all from the console.
For more information on implementing
push notifications on the client,
check out “The Push Notifications primer”
video from WWDC20.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪