♪ ♪
Michael: Hello and welcome.
I'm Michael Ochs and in this video
I'm going to talk about
how to build better document-centric apps.
Document-centric apps are
a big part of productivity tools,
especially on the iPad.
There are three types
of document-centric apps.
Those that allow browsing documents,
such as the Files app;
those that allow viewing content,
for example Quick Look;
and those that also allow editing
or creating content,
like Pages, Keynote, or Numbers.
This video focuses on improvements
to viewer and editor apps,
but some of the content discussed
also applies to browser apps.
iPadOS 17 introduces a new view controller
that automatically enables
a large number of features in your app.
It works nicely together
with the desktop-class iPad APIs
introduced in iPadOS 16,
and the existing document-centric APIs.
This new view controller
is built in a modular way.
You get great system defaults,
but can customize any individual behavior.
To catch up on desktop-class iPad APIs,
check out 'Meet desktop-class iPad'
and 'Build a desktop-class iPad app'
from WWDC22.
For SwiftUI development,
DocumentGroup now has support
for all these features
with no additional code.
To learn more
about the SwiftUI side of this,
check out 'Build document-based apps
in SwiftUI' from WWDC20
and 'SwiftUI on iPad: Add toolbars,
titles, and more' from WWDC22.
In UIKit the functionality is opt-in.
UIDocumentViewController is a new
base class for content view controllers.
It works together with UIDocument
to automatically configure
the navigation bar.
This enables features like sharing,
dragging the document,
undo and redo support, and more.
It also supports automatic renaming.
In this video,
you will learn how to use UIDocument
and how to present documents
with UIDocumentViewController.
I'll then explain
which features are built-in,
and how to customize them further.
At the end I explore some best practices
to migrate your existing apps
to take advantage of UIDocument.
First up, creating a document.
The core of every document based app
is UIDocument.
It's an abstract base class
that is meant to be subclassed
for each file-type that your app supports.
All UIDocuments are backed by a URL.
Files on disk are the most common,
but you can also save and load
your documents using a database
and a custom URL scheme.
UIDocument's load and save operations
are asynchronous,
which allows for lengthy
read and write operations, if necessary.
For this reason,
UIDocument is thread safe
and takes care of coordinating access
through locks and queues.
When implementing a UIDocument subclass,
there are two main responsibilities
to take care of:
loading and saving of the document,
and providing access
to the content of the document.
Loading and saving is very similar
across all documents.
Accessing the content is more specific
to the type of document
and how it is used in your app.
For example,
a document model for a markdown editor
might only have a single text property;
or it could expose
a more complex interface
that allows updating individual parts
of the document.
Before we talk more
about accessing the content,
let's talk about loading and saving.
For simple, file based documents,
there are two convenience methods
you can override.
When a document gets opened,
'loadFromContents:ofType:'
will be called
with the contents of the file.
When the document is being saved,
'contentsForType:' is called to get
the current content of the document.
The content of the document
is a Data object for regular files,
or a FileWrapper for everything else.
To learn more about file types
and how they work,
check out the Tech Talk
'Uniform Type Identifiers --
a reintroduction'.
For example here, the document
deals with regular markdown files,
so we expect a data object.
Now, if you want total control,
overriding 'saveToURL:forSaveOperation:'
and 'readFromURL:' instead
gives you full access to the URL
and leaves all reading and writing to you.
This is great if you want to store
your documents in a database
or have special requirements
for reading and writing your document.
Note that while the save operation
is asynchronous,
reading is expected to complete
by the time the method returns.
And this is all there is
to loading and saving a document.
Now let's make sure we have a way
to access the content of the document.
An easy way to provide access
to the document's content
is by adding properties for that content.
In this example,
I add a single text property
that contains the full markdown string.
This property will be set
when loading the document initially,
as discussed on the previous slides.
The app can then update this text
whenever the user edits the document.
For UIDocument to know
when it requires saving,
call 'updateChangeCount:'
every time a property updates.
Calling 'updateChangeCount:' allows
UIDocument to mark the document
as needs-saving and automatically
save at appropriate times.
Next, presenting a document
with the new UIDocumentViewController.
Similar to UIDocument,
UIDocumentViewController
also is an abstract base class
that is meant to be subclassed.
It manages opening,
saving, and closing the document
and populates its navigation item with
information from its associated document.
This includes the title,
the navigation item's title menu,
its UIDocumentProperties object,
and the rename delegate.
UIDocumentViewController also provides
key-commands for common actions
like undo and redo.
Let's check out how to implement
a UIDocumentViewController subclass.
There are two methods that are designed
to be overridden by your subclass.
When the document associated
with the view controller gets opened,
or when an already opened document
gets assigned to the view controller,
'documentDidOpen' is called.
Populate the view controller's views
to display the content of the document
in this method.
Note that there's no timing guarantee
between when 'documentDidOpen' is called
and when the view controller's view
gets loaded.
A good approach to write robust code
is to move the view configuration
in its own method and call it from both,
'documentDidOpen'
as well as 'viewDidLoad'.
Check if the view is loaded
and the document is opened,
before configuring your views.
The second method to override
is 'navigationItemDidUpdate'.
Whenever UIDocumentViewController
makes changes to the navigation item,
it will call this method.
Add your navigation item customization
in there.
'UIDocumentViewController'
will make a best effort
to keep changes to a minimum to persist
your changes as best as possible.
UIDocumentViewController also offers
a 'undoRedoItemGroup'.
Put this group in the navigation bar if
you want undo and redo buttons to appear,
and make sure that your document
has an undo manager assigned to it.
UIDocumentViewController will change
the 'hidden' property of this group
depending on the availability
of an undo manager
and enable or disable the buttons
inside the group as necessary.
UIDocumentViewController automatically
opens and closes the document.
However if you need access to the document
from outside the view controller,
call 'openDocumentWithCompletionHandler'.
UIDocumentViewController will make
all the necessary callbacks,
such as calling 'documentDidOpen'
and call your completion handler
when ready.
Last but not least,
UIDocumentViewController
provides a document property.
This property always refers to
the document associated
with the view controller.
While you can provide a document
during initialization,
it is entirely optional.
When there is no document
associated with the view controller,
it will automatically show an empty state.
To learn more
about configuring empty states,
check out "What's new in UIKit".
Furthermore, UIDocumentViewController can
be used as your app’s root view controller.
If there is no browser view controller
in the hierarchy,
UIDocumentViewController puts
a document button in the navigation bar
that opens a document picker.
This requires declaring the key
'UIDocumentClass'
for the relevant file type
in your app's info.plist
and setting it to the UIDocument subclass
matching that file type.
In iPadOS 17, UIDocument conforms
to 'UINavigationItemRenameDelegate'
and will handle
the underlying file changes by itself
when the user invokes renaming
from the title menu.
If you are using UIDocumentViewController,
it will automatically
configure renaming for you,
otherwise you can set the document
as the navigation item's
rename delegate manually.
These are all the pieces you need
to create a great document-centric app
in iPadOS 17.
Next, how to migrate your existing apps.
Migrating your app to make use of
the new UIDocumentViewController is easy
and only requires three steps.
First, update the base class
of your content view controller.
Second,
move existing code to the new callbacks.
And third,
delete code that is no longer necessary.
Let's check out how to convert
the markdown editor example
we use
in the desktop-class iPad app videos.
If you are not familiar with it,
don't worry.
I'll walk you through the relevant parts
of the existing code first.
So here we have the definition
of the view controller at the top,
the document property it defines,
and an init method
that sets the initial document
and then adds a callback to our document.
First we change the base class
to UIDocumentViewController.
Now that this class inherits
from UIDocumentViewController,
we will get a compiler error
because the property 'document'
already exists in the superclass
with a different type.
We change the name of that property
to a more specific one,
like 'markdownDocument'.
Then we make it a computed property
that casts the generic document property
to the specific document class
used in this view controller.
The last bit in this code to take care of
is the initializer.
The only code in there that we still need
is assigning a callback to our document.
Since the document can change during
the lifetime of this view controller,
we move this to execute every time
the document changes.
An easy way to do this
is to override the document property
and add a didSet callback.
Great,
now that the base class is up to date,
we need to take care of the new callbacks.
In 'viewDidLoad' we add buttons
to our navigation bar
and configure it
to allow toolbar customization.
For UIDocumentViewController
we move this to the new callback
'navigationItemDidUpdate'.
Next, our class already has a method
'didOpenDocument'.
This is almost what
UIDocumentViewController has as well.
We just need to rename the method,
and adjust for the fact
that the document is now optional.
All right,
next the part that we all enjoy most:
deleting code.
Editor view controller conforms
to 'UINavigationItemRenameDelegate',
but we no longer need that.
UIDocument does all renaming for us
automatically.
So we remove the delegate definition,
the delegate method with all its code,
and also the 'renameDelegate' assignment.
Next we can remove a few more
navigationItem customizations.
Both 'style' and 'backAction'
are configured
by the document view controller
automatically,
so we can get rid of this completely.
There is also
a 'updateDocumentProperties' method
that is used to create
a UIDocumentProperties object.
This method is called from various places.
However, we don't need it anymore.
UIDocumentViewController
is doing all of this for us,
so we can remove it
and all its call sites.
And that's all there is to do.
The editor view controller is now
only taking care of the features
that are unique to the app.
It no longer has to manage basic tasks
of document management
or default configuration
of the navigation bar.
Instead you can focus on the pieces
that are unique, key elements of your app.
This is all you need to know
to take your document-centric apps
to the next level and provide your users
with a great experience.
Convert your data models
to use UIDocument.
Then convert your content view controller
to use the new
UIDocumentViewController base class.
After that,
go through your view controller
and remove all the code
that's no longer needed.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪