♪ ♪
Tony:
Hi, I'm Tony from Privacy Engineering.
Welcome to
"Get started with Privacy Manifests."
At Apple, we believe privacy
is a fundamental human right.
In addition to techniques
like data minimization,
a key part to bring this value to life
is to make sure
people have transparency and control.
To support this, we now provide new tools
to make it even easier for you
to provide accurate
Privacy Nutrition Labels
and integrate App Tracking Transparency.
This is because the apps you build
are integral parts of people's lives.
There are many apps to choose from,
and as a refresher,
Privacy Nutrition Labels help people
learn more about how your apps
collect and use their data.
People often want to know:
What are the categories of data
that apps collect about them?
Is data used to track them?
Is data linked to them?
Privacy Nutrition Labels
demonstrate the great privacy work
that you've done in your apps,
and they give people the information
they need to make great choices.
For all new and updated apps
on the App Store,
developers like you have been
providing Privacy Nutrition Labels.
And you've been using
App Tracking Transparency
to give people control over
when their data is used to track them.
It's now easier for you
to provide accurate Nutrition Labels
and integrate App Tracking Transparency.
You are responsible for all code
included in your apps,
per the App Store Review Guidelines.
This includes any data collection
and tracking practices.
A large part of your app's privacy story
often depends on third-party SDKs.
We have heard from developers like you
that it can be challenging
to get all the information you need
from the great third-party SDKs
that your apps depend on.
Privacy manifests are a new way
for third-party SDK developers
to provide information
about their privacy practices.
This information helps you
accurately represent privacy in your app.
Third-party SDK developers can
include a privacy manifest in their SDK.
They can create a new privacy manifest
right from the Xcode navigator,
by creating a file named
"PrivacyInfo.xcprivacy".
This file is a property list that declares
what data types the SDK collects,
how each data type is used,
whether they are linked to the user,
and whether they're used for tracking
as defined by
the App Tracking Transparency policy.
Taking a closer look at this manifest,
the Example Sharing SDK is listed
as not tracking.
It collects name and user ID,
linked to the user,
for both app functionality
and product personalization.
It also collects photos or videos,
linked to the user,
for just app functionality.
Check that the privacy manifest
matches your understanding
of the third-party SDK's functionality.
The definitions for types of data
and data use for privacy manifests
are the same as for the Nutrition Label,
so refer to the Apple developer
documentation on app privacy details.
And the new privacy report
brings all this information to one place.
Let me show you how that works.
When you're building your app
to submit to the App Store,
Xcode 15 can aggregate all the privacy
manifests in your app's project,
and produce a privacy report
that summarizes the declared data uses.
To view this, go to Xcode Organizer,
show the context menu for an archive,
and select "Generate Privacy Report."
The privacy report is a PDF
and easy to use.
It is organized in a similar way
to Privacy Nutrition Labels.
So you can easily reference this report
when you provide your app's privacy
details in App Store Connect.
This helps you review, understand,
and describe the privacy practices
of your app and its dependencies.
To learn more about Nutrition Labels,
watch the WWDC22 video:
Create your Privacy Nutrition Label.
Another feature of privacy manifests
is helping you manage tracking domains,
by making it easier for you to understand
and control network connections
from your app.
While you don't intend
to track people without their permission,
there may be edge cases that create
un-intended network connections
to domains that are used for tracking.
For example, many third-party SDKs
check tracking permission status
before tracking people.
However, some third-party SDKs rely on you
to manually disable tracking
when the user has not granted permission.
The third-party SDK might default
to tracking
unless you specify otherwise,
either through a function
in their library,
or some configuration change.
This could lead to edge cases.
To make it easier for you
and third-party SDK developers
to avoid tracking people
without their permission,
privacy manifests that declare tracking
include tracking domains.
In cases when a user has not provided
tracking permission,
iOS 17 automatically blocks connections
to tracking domains
that have been specified in any privacy
manifest included in your app.
This helps you eliminate those edge cases.
In addition to the privacy
manifests included in third-party SDKs,
you can also choose to create
a privacy manifest for your app,
which may also include tracking domains.
By preventing accidental connections,
this feature helps to preserve
your intention to not track users
without their permission.
Tell iOS your tracking domains,
and the system will help.
For more information about tracking,
visit the Apple Developer website,
or watch the WWDC22 video,
Explore App Tracking Transparency.
In some cases,
domains may be used for both tracking
and non-tracking functionality.
An approach that you or a third-party SDK
developer could take
is to separate the functionality
into different host names.
For example, you can host tracking
functionality at tracking.example.com,
and non-tracking functionality
at non-tracking.example.com.
Then, declare tracking.example.com
as a tracking domain
in the privacy manifest.
You may not always realize if your app,
or a third-party SDK,
is connecting to a tracking domain.
In Xcode 15,
the Points of Interest instrument
can help you with this
during your testing.
It now shows connections to domains
that may be following people
across multiple apps and websites
to combine their activity into a profile.
This puts you in the driver's seat,
and you can assess whether a domain is
used for tracking
under the App Tracking
Transparency policy.
If it is, then you or your SDK developer
should declare the domain as a tracking
domain in the privacy manifest.
With the user's permission,
tracking is allowed.
However, fingerprinting is never allowed.
Fingerprinting is using signals
from the device
to try to identify the device or user.
Regardless of whether a user
gives your app permission to track,
fingerprinting is not allowed.
There are existing APIs
in our platforms
that have the potential
of being mis-used for fingerprinting.
However, these APIs also provide
powerful user experiences
when accessed appropriately.
To support important use cases
that benefit the user
while avoiding fingerprinting,
there is a new category of APIs
called Required reason APIs.
We have begun
by grouping these APIs into categories,
taking into consideration
their functionality
and the information they provide.
For each category,
there is a list of approved reasons
to access these APIs,
based on their use cases.
For example, one Required reason API
is NSFileSystemFreeSize,
which indicates the amount of free space
on the file system.
One of its approved reasons
supports using this API
to check whether there is sufficient
disk space before writing files to disk.
The list of Required reason APIs
and approved reasons,
including any future updates,
is published in the Apple
developer documentation.
The total number
of Required reason APIs is small,
but it is likely
that you use one or more of them.
If you have a use case for an API category
that is not already covered
by an approved reason,
and the use case directly benefits
the user,
the documentation will link to a feedback
form where you can let us know.
To protect users
from possible fingerprinting,
apps and SDKs are allowed to access
the Required reason APIs
only for the approved reasons.
Data returned from these APIs
may not be used for other purposes.
To help you clearly state
why you use Required reason APIs,
and to make it easy for third-party
SDK developers to do the same,
privacy manifests
include this information.
An app or third-party SDK
that accesses a Required reason API
declares the API category,
and all of its reasons for using the API.
These must be selected from the list
of approved reasons for that category.
Just like Nutrition Labels
in the App Store,
which help people
make choices about your app,
privacy manifests help you make decisions
about your dependencies.
Each privacy manifest also gives you
a better picture
of your app's privacy story by making
the Xcode privacy report more complete.
It's a great idea to leverage third-party
SDKs that provide privacy manifests,
and SDK authors can add manifests
to existing versions of their SDKs.
Looking at the app ecosystem,
we have identified some third-party SDKs
that have particularly high impact
on user privacy.
These are called privacy-impacting SDKs.
A list of these third-party SDKs,
and any future updates,
is published
in the Apple developer documentation.
Because it is especially important
for you to get information
from privacy-impacting SDKs,
apps that include a privacy-impacting SDK
will be required to include a copy
of that SDK with a privacy manifest.
Xcode 15 also supports SDK signatures,
which help you protect your app
and verify the integrity
of third-party SDKs.
Including a signature is a best practice
for all third-party SDKs.
To help you confirm that the developer
you expect provided the privacy manifest
for privacy-impacting SDKs,
apps that include a privacy-impacting SDK
will also be required to ensure
that the SDK is signed.
For more information about SDK signatures,
watch "Verify app dependencies
with digital signatures."
Starting in Fall 2023,
App Store will check
if new and updated apps
include a library
from a privacy-impacting SDK.
If the privacy-impacting SDK does not
include a signature and privacy manifest,
Apple will send an informational email
to the app developer.
Apple will also send
informational emails for apps
that access Required Reason APIs
without declaring approved reasons.
Starting in Spring 2024, these will be
expected and become part of App Review.
You'll need to address any issues
before you can submit
new and updated apps to the App Store.
Okay, here's what's next.
App developers:
Ask for SDK privacy manifests
from your third-party SDK developers.
Always refer to the Xcode privacy report
when you are submitting your app
to keep your Nutrition Label up to date.
SDK developers:
Adopt signatures and manifests.
These are super helpful to your customers.
All developers:
Document and declare tracking domains
and Required Reason API usage
in your app or SDK's privacy manifest.
With the new privacy manifests,
providing accurate, complete,
and clear privacy information
to your users will be easier than ever.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪