♪ ♪
Darin Adler: Welcome to
Platforms State of the Union 2023!
We're excited to share more
about how you can take advantage
of what's coming in our new releases.
Like interactive widgets
on iOS and iPadOS,
which give you more ways
to surface your apps across the system,
a new widget experience on macOS,
the beautiful design of watchOS 10,
Continuity Camera on tvOS,
and, of course,
an entirely new platform with visionOS.
Platforms State of the Union is a chance
to learn about some of the most exciting,
impactful, and important developments
from this year's releases.
And what we have for you
delivers on all those fronts.
Before we dive in,
I want to talk for a moment
about what makes a great platform
and great apps.
A great platform is more than a collection
of frameworks and technologies.
It's key ingredients that come together
to make something truly special.
It's the combination of a language,
frameworks,
tools, and services created
to work seamlessly together,
so the most natural way
to write your code is also the best.
A rich set of APIs to help you
create amazing experiences
that deeply integrate with the system,
whether your app is open or not.
Thoughtful ways for you
to safely take advantage
of cutting-edge hardware technologies
across a wide range of products.
And finally, a great platform evolves
to meet new challenges
so you're able to meet the needs of users
right when they emerge.
The more than 300 frameworks
on our platforms are building blocks,
enabling you to get right to
what's innovative, creative,
and different about your app.
They go further than just
saving you some time
or helping you add a specific feature.
When you use these platform foundations
with purpose,
your app fits in beautifully
and extends the system itself.
And that's the path to a great app.
A great app elevates the right information
to the user
at the right time in the right place.
That place could be the Share Sheet,
right on the Lock Screen,
Spotlight, Siri,
or any number of other places.
A great app takes advantage of hardware
like a new sensor or a powerful chip
with help from frameworks that put
those capabilities at your fingertips.
And a great app does things
that are so important to get right,
like creating safe, accessible products
that respect a user's privacy.
Our platforms and your apps come together
to deliver all of this
with the consistency and reliability
that people value and expect.
And this is a big deal.
We're incredibly passionate
about great platforms and great apps.
Users can tell the difference they make.
The shared foundations of iOS,
iPadOS, macOS,
tvOS, watchOS, and now visionOS
form a cohesive ecosystem
that allow you to deliver your apps
across the full range
of Apple platforms and products.
Your apps are key to this ecosystem.
They empower people
as they go about their day
with easy-to-use experiences that move
seamlessly from one device to another.
At Apple, we often talk about building
the things we want to use ourselves
and it couldn't be more true
than with our approach to our platforms.
Because we're developers too!
We use the same language, tools,
and frameworks here at Apple.
So today, we have a lot to cover.
We'll start with the latest developments
in Swift and SwiftUI,
and how you can use them
across all of our platforms
to create amazing experiences.
We'll talk about how you can
leverage hardware features,
and also how you can prioritize values
in the experiences you build.
And we'll walk you through
the improvements
to the powerful tools
we all use every day.
Finally, we'll take a deep dive
into the technologies
of our latest platform, visionOS,
and show you how you can build
the next generation of apps
for Apple Vision Pro.
To kick things off,
I'll turn it over to Holly
to talk about what's new in Swift.
Holly Borla: The foundation for so many of
the APIs that you use every day is Swift.
It's fast, modern, and safe,
guiding you toward code that's efficient,
expressive, and correct.
APIs allow you to take advantage
of libraries and platform features,
and create experiences
that are unique to your app.
But some APIs can be hard to use,
requiring you to write a lot
of boilerplate code just to get started.
That's why Swift is unlocking
a new kind of API
that's easier to use
and easier to get right
with the introduction of macros.
And these macros are done the Swift way.
A macro is an annotation
that uses the structure of your code
to generate new code
that's built with your project.
Macros can either be attached
as attributes to your code,
or they can be freestanding,
spelled with the hash sign.
Macros make APIs feel
like they're part of the language,
and there are so many ways to start
using a new API with just an annotation.
Macros come to life in Xcode,
where the generated code
feels like it's part of your project.
Let me show you.
I created a URL macro
that checks for valid URL strings.
Because macros
generate regular Swift code,
I can use the "Expand Macro" feature
in Xcode to see exactly what they do.
This macro looks really simple.
It calls the URL initializer
and force-unwraps the result.
But the URL macro does more than that.
It checks that the string is a valid URL
at compile-time.
For example,
URLs can't have spaces,
so if I add one,
the macro provides a custom error message
and a fix-it to automatically remove
the space from the string.
This moves what would have been an error
when my app is running,
into feedback while I'm writing my code,
so I can fix mistakes right away.
All macros have the ability
to provide custom feedback
to help you write correct code.
Attached macros go even further,
because they can add new functionality
to code you already wrote.
Let's take a look
at what attached macros can do.
I have a function called fetchContent
that performs asynchronous work,
and uses completion handlers,
but I want to use async/await.
Instead of implementing
another fetchContent function,
I can attach the AddAsync macro.
And that's it!
Now, instead of passing in
a completion handler
when I call fetchContent,
I can simply await the result.
Just like any other API,
I can use quick-help on the macro
to see its documentation.
But if I want to understand
how this works under the hood,
I can set a breakpoint, run my code,
step into the async function,
and Xcode will expand the macro
right in my source editor.
This is really cool,
because there are no secrets.
Stepping into an expanded macro
while debugging
is a natural way to peek behind the scenes
and help me understand
what's happening in my code.
You can write your own macros,
so you can extend the language in ways
that were previously only possible
by implementing features
in the Swift compiler.
Because Swift is developed in open source,
developers are already using macros
to build some of the most commonly
requested language features,
including automatically generating
rich descriptions of assertion failures,
providing customizable
default protocol conformances,
and the list continues to grow.
You'll also see macros used
throughout many of this year's new APIs.
You can benefit
from community-authored macros,
or share your own macros with others,
through Swift packages.
Language advancements, like macros,
enable Swift to be adopted
in more projects than ever before.
Let's talk about all of your code
that isn't written in Swift.
Since its inception, Swift has provided
bi-directional interoperability
with C and Objective-C.
You can introduce Swift into your projects
a single file or module at a time,
without having to rewrite
entire codebases.
Swift is extending that interoperability
to C++.
Swift-C++ interoperability allows you to
use both languages in the same project
without an intermediate bridging layer.
You can share your classes, functions,
and even template specializations
like vector
across both languages
by setting a compiler flag.
Using C++ from Swift will eliminate
many sources of undefined behavior
in your code,
such as using variables
before they're initialized.
And bridging is efficient:
calls are made natively
between your Swift and C++ code,
with minimal overhead.
Swift-C++ interoperability
is already in use in open source,
helping to transition the Swift compiler
itself from C++ to Swift,
and I am so excited to use Swift
to implement Swift.
Swift's fundamental goals
of safe and expressive code
are ingrained in the libraries
that are built with it.
And nowhere is that more apparent
than with SwiftUI.
Here's Josh to tell you more.
Josh Shaffer: The best way
to build modern user interfaces
across all Apple platforms
is with SwiftUI.
SwiftUI lets you write better apps
with less code
so you can focus on
what's unique to your app.
It also maximizes your ability
to reuse interface code.
The healthy habits app Streaks
by Crunchy Bagel is a great example.
They first started using SwiftUI
when building widgets for iOS.
Then they shared that code
with their watchOS app,
and augmented it
with beautiful animations.
And now,
they've incorporated the same code
back into their original iOS app.
Incremental adoption enabled them
to share UI code at their own pace,
and see benefits from SwiftUI
in their existing apps.
SwiftUI is also incredibly capable,
helping to power sophisticated interfaces
in apps like the new Logic Pro
and Final Cut Pro for iPad.
Adopting SwiftUI in your apps
prepares you to build
the next generation of user interfaces.
And what you can build with SwiftUI
continues to expand.
As always, its new capabilities
in this year's releases
focus on areas of high impact
and top developer requests,
like new support for Pie Charts
and selection in Swift Charts,
a brand new inspector API,
expanded MapKit support,
including Overlays, Look Around, and more.
These improvements cover
a wide range of functionality,
but many of them are focused
on improving animations.
This is a key area,
because well-designed animations
make your interface easy to use.
They can provide feedback
so your users know
that something is happening.
Or they can confirm that a task
has completed successfully.
And that's why SwiftUI has had
advanced features like reversible,
interruptible, and cancelable animations
from the beginning.
This year,
SwiftUI is taking animations even further.
It starts with the way that they move.
Animations are often triggered
by a user's gesture.
So now, SwiftUI can automatically transfer
the velocity of your gesture
into your animation,
providing a smooth transition.
And animations now default
to a spring-based motion
that can be configured
with just two simple parameters:
duration and bounce.
SwiftUI can also take advantage
of new animated effects in SF Symbols,
bringing the iconography
in your apps to life.
Finally, when you need to build
multi-part animations,
SwiftUI has a new API
called AnimationPhase
that helps you build
sophisticated animations
with just a few lines of code.
I've created a sample app to illustrate
new APIs like AnimationPhase,
inspired by the beautiful landscape
of Apple Park.
It provides a calming experience
where users can create outdoor spaces
and provide food and drink
for visiting birds.
To make sure that I never miss a new bird,
I've added a reminder
to the top of the list.
Let's switch over to a preview
focused on just that view.
I really want to make this SF Symbol
stand out by adding some animation.
First, I'll add an enum
to define the different states
in a custom animation.
Next, I'll wrap my view
in a 'PhaseAnimator'.
This is a new view that automatically
animates between a set of states.
And finally,
I'll scale and rotate the icon
in the '.highlighted' animation phase.
This is looking good,
but I think it would look even better
if the background animated
along with the icon,
so I'll add a couple more modifiers.
Now, for even more advanced animations,
this year SwiftUI adds full support
for keyframing.
This powerful API
lets me animate anything,
including the properties
of the new SwiftUI-based MapKit API.
Keyframes let you define the values
of multiple properties
at specific times within an animation,
and then let SwiftUI interpolate
the intermediate values.
Here, I've used keyframes
to animate the map camera
visiting different landmarks in Cupertino.
Because keyframes let you define
the motion for different properties,
we're able to independently animate
the pitch, heading,
and position of the camera
to achieve this smooth, continuous motion
across Cupertino, and over to Apple Park.
Crafting the feel of your app
using animations in SwiftUI
has never been easier.
Next, let's talk about data flow.
When building an app with SwiftUI,
you have a few choices
to bring data into your views.
SwiftUI offers a set of property wrappers
for managing data local to your view
and for referencing data owned elsewhere.
This year data flow is getting simpler,
letting you focus on
just State and Environment.
You may have written code like this
when exposing your model to SwiftUI,
conforming to ObservableObject
and adding the Published property wrapper
to each property.
Swift's new Macro support
makes this much simpler,
with a new Observable macro
taking its place.
Just annotate a class with @Observable,
and you're done.
All publicly visible properties
are published automatically.
And when using an Observable
in your SwiftUI views,
there's no need to use a property wrapper
to trigger view updates.
You just reference
your variables directly.
You'll write less code,
and get fast and correct behavior
by default.
Observable lets SwiftUI track access
at a per-field level,
so your view's body is only re-evaluated
when the specific properties
used by your view change.
If you modify a field
not used by your view,
no invalidation will happen at all.
So now when you connect your model
to your views,
just like with the rest of SwiftUI,
the most natural code to write
is also the correct code to write.
SwiftUI was the start of a new generation
of frameworks designed for Swift.
But the benefits of a Swift-native
framework don't stop with your UI code.
Core Data has long provided tools
for data management,
but its design was born
of the era of Objective-C,
and it doesn't take full advantage
of everything that Swift has to offer.
Many of you have been asking
for a Swift-native solution
to data management,
designed with first-class support
for all of Swift's features.
Let me introduce you to SwiftData.
SwiftData is a framework
for data modeling and management.
It's built on top of Core Data's
proven persistence layer,
but with an API completely redesigned
and reimagined for Swift.
Like SwiftUI, it focuses entirely on code,
with no external file formats.
Instead it uses Swift's new macro system
to offer a streamlined API.
If you were defining a model in Swift,
you might write code like this,
using regular Swift types.
To manage this with Core Data,
you'd then need to redefine the same model
using the model editor built into Xcode.
But with SwiftData,
you just annotate your class
with the @Model macro.
This single line of code
packs a lot of functionality,
like automatically enabling persistence,
iCloud synchronization,
undo and redo, and more.
You can then refine
these automatic behaviors
by annotating properties
with additional attributes,
like indicating the value
must be unique across all instances.
And SwiftData uses the Codable protocol
to understand structs and enums,
so you can model your data
with the tools that you already know.
These types are fully modeled
in the underlying data store,
enabling you to perform
fast and efficient queries,
even on complex structured data.
And of course, it's simple
to integrate SwiftData with SwiftUI.
Now, we started to build our demo app
using the new Observable macro
to drive SwiftUI view updates.
So my interface updates
as I see new birds,
but my edits aren't saved across runs.
By importing SwiftData, I'll be able to
add support for persistence really easily.
I'll just replace the two
Observable macros on my existing classes
with SwiftData's Model macro,
and my model's ready.
At the root of my app, I'll add a modifier
to set up the SwiftData container.
And when I create a new backyard,
I'll insert it into the model context
so that it gets persisted.
And finally, I'll hook up my BackyardList
view to the persisted data.
That's really easy to do
with the new @Query property wrapper.
Because we're now loading saved data,
I can remove the default sample data
that I used when I was prototyping.
Before we test it out, let's also update
a widget that I've been working on.
I'll just set up the container
and query the same way.
With the app's shared container enabled,
SwiftData automatically makes
my data directly accessible
by the widget using the same API.
Backyards are now persisted by SwiftData,
and delivered to the view by @Query.
Before we started, I filled the database
with some initial data,
so you can already see some bird visitors.
And if I add a new backyard object,
when I return to the list
it will appear with no additional work.
And SwiftData provides more
than just persistence,
including things like support
for undo and redo,
which just works automatically.
And as you can see, my widget is already
showing the backyard that we just created.
And that's a look at how easy it is
to save and restore data using SwiftData.
SwiftUI and SwiftData work hand-in-hand
to help you
build engaging and powerful apps.
They form a foundation of a new approach
to development enabled by Swift
that helps you spend less time
on boilerplate,
and more time building your ideas.
Next, Jonathan is going to show you
how to apply these technologies
to elevate your app in new ways
across the system.
Jonathan Thomassian: I'm really excited to
tell you about four new app experiences.
With WidgetKit,
you can surface your content
in many places across the system.
With App Intents, your app's functionality
is integrated into the system
even more seamlessly.
With TipKit, you can surface
beautiful tips directly in your app.
And with AirDrop, you can make it
even more convenient for your users
to share content with those nearby.
Let's start with WidgetKit.
Widgets elevate important information
from your apps,
making your app experience
more glanceable and available
to your users as they go about their day.
Widgets started on the Home Screen,
but now they're in many more places
to bring your experiences to users
right where and when they need them.
And this year,
widgets are becoming even more powerful.
Once you rebuild for iOS 17,
with just a few simple changes,
your existing widgets will look gorgeous
in StandBy on iPhone.
They'll appear scaled up
and drawn out to the edges,
with the backgrounds removed,
so they look stunning side by side.
They'll also be available
on the Lock Screen on iPad,
again drawn to their edges
and with their backgrounds removed.
Here, they'll have a uniform
visual appearance
so they blend perfectly
with the Lock Screen.
And on macOS Sonoma they'll be available
on the Desktop in full color,
and then recede into the background
when a window has focus.
And you can now make your widgets more
useful with new support for interactivity.
Simple actions that can be accomplished
with a tap, like checking off a reminder,
can now be handled
directly from your widget.
All of these new widget updates
were enabled
by their SwiftUI-based architecture.
Your widget's code is run asynchronously
to generate content,
and the SwiftUI views it builds
are then saved to an archive.
Later, when the widget needs to be drawn,
the archive can be loaded,
rendered in the background, and then
displayed as part of the system UI.
When a user taps a button,
its extension is run again
to handle the action and update the UI.
This architecture also enables
iPhone widgets
to be seamlessly displayed on your Mac.
Thanks to the magic of Continuity,
the widget archive can be sent
across the network to your Mac,
and user interactions can be sent back
to be handled on iPhone.
Getting your existing widgets ready
couldn't be easier.
Just identify your widget's background
and update its padding to use the default
provided by WidgetKit.
SwiftUI's stack-based layouts
let the system adapt your widget's color
and spacing based on context.
Interactivity is also easy to adopt
by adding SwiftUI Buttons
or Toggles to your widget.
New support for triggering an App Intent
from these controls
launches your extension on demand.
When your widget's content updates,
the system triggers a transition animation
that works just like
a Magic Move in Keynote.
Moved elements slide
to their new locations,
and added or removed elements
fade and blur softly in and out.
You can use standard SwiftUI
transition APIs
to further customize
and get exactly the effects you want.
Let's take a look at how easy it is
to include these new features
in an existing widget.
Our sample app has a widget that tracks
notable events in our backyard.
The first thing I need to do
is identify its background.
Here's our widget view
and we can see our background
is right here in the ZStack.
All I need to do is move it into the new
container background view modifier.
And starting in iOS 17,
widget padding is provided for me,
so I'll go ahead and remove the padding
I was adding before.
Now, thanks to Swift Macros,
I can see my entire widget timeline
directly in Xcode previews.
Here, at the bottom of the preview canvas,
are all of my timeline entries.
And clicking through them shows how
my widget will animate when it updates.
This transition is great,
but let's see if we can do something
that feels a bit more
like a bird arriving.
Just like in my app, I can make use
of standard SwiftUI transitions.
Here in the editor, I'll add
a transition modifier to my BirdView.
Let's try a leading edge push.
That looks great.
The updated preview canvas
also makes it easy to see
how my widget looks in different contexts,
like the new iPad Lock Screen
or StandBy on iPhone.
Let's look at StandBy.
When the background is removed,
I want my bird to stand out.
And its feet are a bit lost here,
so let's add a birdbath.
SwiftUI provides a new
showsWidgetContainerBackground variable
that lets me customize how my widget looks
when the background is removed.
Nice!
Many of you have asked for the ability
to interact with your app from your widget
and now, you can.
Let's add a button
to refill my bird's water.
I've already defined an App Intent
for this action,
so all I have to do is associate it
with a button in my widget.
Let's try it out in the simulator.
And just like that,
I've refilled my bird's water.
And that's WidgetKit.
It's never been easier
to surface your content
in so many places across the system.
We're excited about all the ways
you can use interactivity
and animated transitions
to enhance your widgets.
Now, App Intents are about more
than just interactivity in widgets.
They elevate your app's functionality
across the system,
in Spotlight, Shortcuts, and Siri.
Now, when you wrap your intent
in an App Shortcut,
it will appear right next to your app icon
in Spotlight results,
with a richer,
more interactive presentation.
You just need to provide a few things.
In your App Shortcut,
a short title and an image or symbol.
And in your app's Info.plist,
a background color that's complementary
to your app icon.
And your app shortcuts will be surfaced
in the updated Shortcuts app,
where users can set them up
to run automatically,
add them to their Home Screen,
or use them to create their own shortcuts.
Siri has gotten even better too.
Users have more natural language
flexibility to invoke a shortcut.
With WidgetKit and App Intents,
users can access features of your app
in whole new ways.
Next, let's talk about feature discovery
in your app.
Every year,
we developers spend time building features
that we think users will love,
but sometimes the users
who would benefit most
don't know the feature exists!
A new framework called TipKit
helps address this
by intelligently educating users about
the right features at the right time.
TipKit includes templates to match
what users are accustomed to seeing
in system apps,
and are easily customizable
to match the look and feel of your app.
The power of TipKit is its turnkey nature.
Simply customize a template
and add targeting to educate users
on functionality
related to their current context.
You can also manage the overall frequency
to avoid showing tips
users have already seen,
even if they saw them on another device.
Lastly, we have a fun new way
to help users share content from your app
with AirDrop.
On iOS 17,
your users can skip the share sheet
and quickly send content
to another device nearby.
You can use ShareLink in SwiftUI,
or adopt activityItemsConfiguration
on your app's UIKit view controller.
And system-provided ViewControllers
like ShareSheet and QuickLook
already work by default.
WidgetKit, App Intents,
TipKit, and AirDrop
will help you build experiences that make
your app's content available to your users
in the right place and at the right time.
We're looking forward to seeing how you'll
use these to take your apps even further.
And now, back to Darin.
Darin: Our platforms are built to give you
access to the unique hardware capabilities
of our products right out of the gate.
Whether you're tapping into
a Neural Engine to process a photograph
or using an accelerometer
to measure sleep movements,
our APIs give you the ability
to harness the power
of hardware technologies with ease.
Next,
we'll look at this year's improvements
for Gaming, Cameras, Displays,
and Apple Watch.
Here's Brandon to tell us
how this all plays out.
Brandon Corey: The blazing performance,
long battery life,
and stunning graphics
of Apple silicon Macs
make them the perfect platform
for running high-end games.
And now, Game Mode in macOS Sonoma
makes gaming on Mac even better.
With Macs more popular than ever before,
there's never been a better time to bring
your games to millions of new players.
If you're a developer who builds games
for Windows or gaming consoles,
you'll find it is now easier than ever
to bring your games to Mac
by using the new Game Porting Toolkit,
which significantly accelerates your
development using three simple steps.
First, you can evaluate just how well your
existing Windows game could run on Mac
using the provided emulation environment.
This lets you analyze your game's
potential performance immediately,
eliminating months of upfront work.
In the second step,
you'll convert and compile your shaders.
The Game Porting Toolkit includes
a new Metal Shader Converter,
which you can use to automatically convert
all of your existing HLSL GPU shaders
to Metal,
including all of your game's
advanced shading pipelines like geometry,
tessellation, mesh,
and ray tracing stages.
You can use this tool while
you're building your game in Xcode,
or in a custom Windows-based toolchain
for shader compilation.
Which brings us to step three:
converting your graphics code
and optimizing your game.
Metal provides all of the advanced
graphics and compute features
used by modern high-end games,
which makes converting your graphics code
incredibly straightforward.
And the powerful graphics performance
and debugging tools
integrated right into Xcode
give you all the guidance you need
to fully optimize your game.
We can't wait to see you
make use of these tools
to take advantage of the incredible
performance of Apple silicon,
and powerful graphics, display, audio,
input, and gaming technologies,
to bring your games to Mac
dramatically faster than ever before.
Speaking of faster performance,
we also have news to share about Camera.
Apple continues to push
mobile photography forward
and expand APIs
that let you do incredible things
with the world's most popular camera.
AVCapture is used by over a third
of iOS apps across all categories:
from creativity to productivity,
social media, and even health,
and it's getting some powerful
performance improvements this year.
With Zero Shutter Lag,
you capture the exact moment
when the shutter is pressed.
With overlapping captures, the camera
will dynamically adjust image quality
when the shutter is pressed rapidly.
And with deferred processing,
high-quality images including Deep Fusion
can be processed in the background.
These improvements will make
shot-to-shot time
up to three time faster between shutter
presses in your iOS or iPadOS app,
even while capturing high-quality images.
And later this year,
you'll also be able to use
the volume and up and down buttons
to trigger the camera shutter.
There is also big news
on displaying photos in your apps.
In recent years HDR-capable displays
have become widely available,
including on iPhone, iPad, and Mac.
HDR photography takes advantage
by capturing additional dynamic range
to display bright highlights
and dark shadows with more fidelity
and realism than ever before,
just like you experienced
the scene in real life.
Apple has been the leader in bringing
HDR photography to the mainstream,
with trillions of HDR photos captured
on iPhone 12 and later.
To do this, the Camera app
intelligently analyzes the scene
and stores additional highlight
and shadow data at capture time.
But while there are industry standards
for HDR video,
there has been no standard
for storing and displaying HDR photos,
which has made them
difficult to work with.
But that's all changing this year.
Apple has driven an industry-wide effort
resulting in a specification
for encoding and displaying HDR photos,
recently ratified by
the International Standards Organization.
It's now available as an API in iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS,
so that you can display compatible photos
in your apps
with just a couple of lines of code.
This is great news for all apps
that display images,
and not just for photos.
Generative content apps can use it to make
images pop with extra dynamic range.
So now a complete HDR workflow
will be possible:
from capture to edit to sharing,
and everyone will be able to enjoy
its full HDR glory,
just like the photographer experienced it.
Next, let's talk about video.
We all spend a lot of time
with our cameras on these days,
whether for video conferencing
or in creative apps.
We've continued to invest
in video lighting and effects,
like these new reactions,
gestures, and presenter overlay effects.
They're built into the camera feed
you receive,
so they'll just work in your app.
Your app can observe
when these effects are invoked
and you can perform additional actions,
like promoting that user's tile
so everyone can see that they reacted.
If you have a video conferencing app,
there are a number of improvements
to screen sharing
and camera functionality
in ScreenCaptureKit.
The new ScreenCaptureKit picker makes it
simpler for users to start screen sharing,
in a more private and secure way.
The picker also makes it simple
for your app to capture multiple windows
or even multiple apps all at once.
Your users can start sharing
right from the app they're in
and they'll appreciate
that they see a preview
of what's being shared
in the new Video Effects menu.
Another benefit of ScreenCaptureKit
is higher resolution content
for better-looking screen shares
when sharing a single window.
We've also brought
external camera support to iPad.
Any USB camera can now be connected
and used within your iPad app.
And we are thrilled to add camera
and microphone capabilities
to an entirely new platform:
tvOS.
With Continuity Camera on tvOS,
you can take advantage of iPhone
and even iPad
to integrate video and audio
in tvOS apps for the first time.
And with the living room as your stage,
there's so much potential
to do amazing things with your apps.
For example,
conferencing apps can use Center Stage,
which makes group video calls more dynamic
on the biggest screen in the home.
Games can incorporate camera
and audio feeds directly into the action.
And creative apps
can stream or record video,
while applying Portrait mode
and other fun effects.
If you already have an app on Apple TV,
you can make the experience
even more connected and social
by leveraging frameworks
you're likely already familiar with.
And for those that want to take advantage
of Continuity Camera
but haven't yet developed for tvOS,
it's super easy to get started
with SwiftUI.
Let me show you how it works.
So here's my example iPad app, PartyCam,
that takes selfies with fun filters.
First, we'll add Apple TV
as a destination.
Next, we need to add the picker so
the user knows which phone to choose from.
Then we'll add the code
to present the picker.
And then we run.
And now, I just pick up the remote
and snap a photo.
Hey, it's Susan and Serenity!
Awesome!
We can't wait to see how you make
the living room even more entertaining.
Now, over to Lori
with what's new on watchOS.
Lori Hylan-Cho:
As our first wearable device,
Apple Watch opened up new possibilities
for developers
to bring timely notifications,
health and fitness insights,
and handy app experiences
to people's wrists.
This year, watchOS 10 is getting
a huge design refresh
that takes advantage
of the larger, brighter displays,
and more capable, connected hardware
of modern Apple Watch models.
SwiftUI is at the very heart
of this redesign.
We employed it across the system
to update virtually every app
to be more dynamic, more colorful,
and more glanceable.
Let me show you a few examples.
There's a renewed focus on pagination
in watchOS 10,
and Vertical TabViews
allow for variable page sizes,
making better use of the crown
for scrolling within apps
without sacrificing space
for all your valuable content.
The new containerBackground modifier
lets you use color,
with gradient fills for readability,
to help users understand where they are
within your app
or make data more glanceable.
For app designs that fill the screen,
new ToolbarItem placements
make better use of the corners
and allow the time to automatically shift
to the center if necessary.
And for layouts with a strong source
list/detail view association,
NavigationSplitView is more compelling
than ever on Apple Watch
using the same code
you'd use on other platforms.
And the pivot in and out
of the detail view on Apple Watch
even uses SwiftUI's
new interactive spring animation.
This animation is composed of
12 separate tracks
for an animation plan that animates
both the size and position of the views,
driven by the velocity
of the user's finger.
And of course, all the major
UI components have been updated
with material treatments
to be legible on any background,
and they size automatically
for the hardware.
If you've already adopted SwiftUI
in your app,
you'll get these updates automatically
when you build with the watchOS 10 SDK.
Let me show you what I mean
with the Backyard Birds app
that I originally designed for watchOS 9.
It's a list/detail app
built using a NavigationStack,
and even without any code changes,
it already works well
when recompiled with watchOS 10.
The views automatically adjust to
accommodate the new navigation bar height,
and the large title shrinks and animates
to a position under the time as I scroll.
Now let's make some edits to make the app
feel even more at home on watchOS 10.
I'd like to see the current status of
my primary yard whenever I launch the app,
rather than always having to choose it
from the list.
NavigationSplitView
is designed specifically for apps
with a strong source list/detail
relationship,
so I'll swap out my NavigationStack
for a NavigationSplitView.
I'll remove the navigation title
from the Source List,
since it's no longer
the entry point for the app,
and indicate the detail view
that should open by default.
The source list is now tucked away
behind the detail view,
and I'm focused on the details.
But my detail view's pretty long.
It's a scrolling List
with three clear sections,
so I'll break up the content by converting
the List to a vertical TabView
with a separate page for each section.
Each of these pages will be
the height of the screen by default
and because that final section contained
a ForEach loop,
each bird's getting its own page.
I'd rather have a list of all the birds
on a single tab that scrolls
if it exceeds the height of the screen,
so I'll change this ForEach to a List,
which will make it a scrollable view.
Next I'd like to add some color
to differentiate between the tabs,
so I'll add a .containerBackground
modifier to each tab.
And to quickly spot when food
or water are running low,
I'll make
the Sustenance background dynamic.
It'll be green, yellow, or red
based on the supply levels.
Looking at the changes in Live Previews,
you can see how the background color
gives a sense of place within the app
and makes it easier to spot
when I need to refill food or water.
The final tab lets content scroll
beyond the bounds of the screen,
and I can still reach
the list of backyards
by tapping the Source List button.
It took just a few changes
to make my app fit right in on watchOS 10.
SwiftUI made our lives easier
as we worked to make every app
on the system look amazing,
and as we just saw,
it'll make updating your apps
for these new design paradigms easy too.
If you haven't moved to SwiftUI
in your app yet, now is the time.
In addition to these
SwiftUI-based app updates,
watchOS 10 also has a brand new
system space
where AppIntents relevance helps
your widgets move up the Smart Stack
at just the right time.
And you can use the same
.containerBackground modifier
mentioned earlier
to make those widgets really shine
with beautiful custom backgrounds.
For those of you building workout apps,
you can help your users take advantage
of the fitness tracking capabilities
of Apple Watch
with the new Custom Workout API,
which lets you share fitness plans
from your app,
and a new CoreMotion API that will enable
higher-fidelity capture of motion
and accelerometer data
to help improve swing analysis
for sports like golf and tennis.
And because we know how creative
you all can be,
this data is available
when running any kind of workout.
We can't wait to see what kinds
of experiences you'll build with it.
And that's a glimpse of some of the
big changes coming to watchOS this year.
And now, back to Darin.
Darin: A platform is also about
the people who use it,
and the values that are built into it
from the ground up.
These core values mean a lot
to us at Apple,
and we know they mean a lot to you too.
Together we can make your app
adapt to people's needs
so anyone can use it
and create apps that show respect
for each user's need to protect themselves
and protect their data.
Starting with what our platforms provide
can make this important work
easier for you.
To tell you more, here's Chris.
Chris: We believe that everyone
should be able to use our devices
to do what they love.
That's why making our products accessible
is a core value at Apple.
According to
the World Health Organization,
there are over one billion people
around the world with disabilities.
Building accessible technology means
giving more people the best tools
to create, learn, stay connected,
and live on their terms.
That's why Apple products
have accessibility features
available out of the box for users
who are blind or low vision,
Deaf or hard of hearing,
non-speaking or at risk of speech loss,
those with physical or motor disabilities,
and those with cognitive disabilities.
Our frameworks come with built-in support
for these accessibility features,
along with tools and APIs
to help you ensure
that your apps are accessible to everyone.
Often, accessibility comes down to taking
small steps that have a big impact.
As an example,
last year we added the ability
to detect and describe doors
in the Magnifier app,
helping people independently navigate
their environment.
This year, we're expanding our support
for users who are sensitive to animations
and flashing lights.
These users often face a difficult choice
between avoiding
potentially risky content,
such as movies that begin
with a flashing lights warning,
or consuming it
without enough information,
which can mean exposing themselves
to health risks, like seizures.
Our frameworks now include APIs
for two features
that can make content in your apps
more accessible to these users.
The first feature
is Pause Animated Images,
which will stop the motion
in animated GIFs
in Safari, Messages, and more.
And it's easy
for you to add it to your app.
Suppose you are animating a sequence
of images with TimelineView in SwiftUI.
You can use a new environment property
to understand
if the user prefers to pause
animated images,
and if they do, replace animated images
with a static image
to respect their choice.
The second feature is Dim Flashing Lights,
which automatically darkens
the display of video
during sequences
of bright, flashing lights.
There's a new phase
in AVFoundation's video rendering pipeline
to identify and dim flashing elements.
If you use AVFoundation
to play media in your app,
there's no extra work
to support this feature.
However, if your app uses
a custom media player,
you can use a new API to identify
video content with flashing lights,
and automatically darken it.
We've even open-sourced the algorithm,
so you can understand the science
behind this feature.
Our commitment to building accessibility
into each product and framework
extends to our newest platform: visionOS.
Because we believe
the world's best technology
should adapt to everyone's needs,
visionOS comes with dozens
of accessibility features
built into its foundation
from the very start.
And you, as a developer,
will play a critical role
by making your visionOS apps
accessible for everyone,
using the same tools and APIs
that you use on iPadOS and iOS today.
We are thrilled to work with you
to bring spatial computing
to diverse sets of users,
and you'll hear more about accessibility
on Vision Pro in a bit.
Now, over to Katie to talk about privacy.
Katie Skinner: At Apple, we believe
privacy is a fundamental human right.
We hear from our users
how much they care about it,
and we're here to help you deliver
great privacy along with your features.
Over the years we've built many ways
to help you build privacy into your apps.
This year we're making it even easier
for you to offer
robust privacy experiences
to your users in a number of areas,
starting with improvements
to privacy prompts.
Let's start with Calendar permissions.
We know that in many cases, your apps
don't need read access to Calendar–
they just need to write new events.
For these cases,
we've created a new add-only permission.
This will help you
get the access that you need,
and the user will get a prompt
that makes sense to them.
And in Photos, we've offered two choices
for users to provide photos to your app;
they can select which photos to share,
or they can provide access
to their full library.
We wanted to make it even easier
to help users select photos
to share with your app,
so you get exactly what you need
and users share only what they intend.
So we're adding a new photo picker
that you can embed into your app,
so users can easily select photos to share
from inside your experience.
Next, app privacy.
It's important to help users understand
how you protect their data,
so we've built features
to help you do just that.
For example, Privacy Nutrition Labels
help users understand
what data you collect and how you use it.
Many of you include third-party SDKs
in your apps,
which can offer great functionality.
But including them can make it harder
to get your labels right,
because you might not understand
how they handle user data.
And they can introduce security challenges
to your software supply chain.
So this year,
we're introducing two updates.
First, to help you understand
how third-party SDKs use data,
we've introduced privacy manifests.
These are files that outline
the privacy practices
of the third-party code in your app,
in a standard format.
When you prepare to distribute your app,
Xcode will combine all the manifests
across all the third-party SDKs
you're using into a single,
easy-to-use report.
With one summary report
for all of your third-party SDKs,
it has never been easier to create
accurate labels in App Store Connect.
We also want to help you improve the
integrity of your software supply chain.
When using third-party SDKs, it can be
hard to know the code you've downloaded
was written by the developer you expect.
To address that, we're introducing
signatures for third-party SDKs.
Now when you adopt a new version
of a third-party SDK in your app,
Xcode will validate that it was signed
by the same developer,
to give you more peace of mind.
With privacy manifests
and signatures for third-party SDKs,
we're making it even easier
for you to protect users
and help them understand
how their data will be used.
And finally, Communication Safety,
which uses privacy-preserving technology
to protect children on our platforms.
Our platforms and the apps you build
play an important role
in the lives of many families
across the world,
especially in how they communicate.
In iOS 15 we introduced the
Communication Safety feature in Messages
to offer more protections
for children using Apple devices.
Many of you build apps
where users share content
and also want to protect children
in vulnerable situations.
We know that training and implementing
a model to classify unsafe content
can be a difficult problem to solve
and a lot of work to undertake.
And so we're bringing Communication Safety
to the entire platform
with the Sensitive Content Analysis
framework.
With just a few lines of code,
the framework helps you detect images
and videos that contain nudity,
and this happens entirely on-device.
So you can build positive experiences
in your app
for children who have
Communication Safety enabled.
The Sensitive Content Analysis framework
uses the same technology
that underpins Communication Safety.
The framework protects users' privacy
by processing images
and videos entirely on-device.
In addition, we wanted to give everyone
the ability to blur sensitive content
with Sensitive Content Warning.
The sensitive content analysis framework
will let you know
if a user has enabled Communication Safety
or Sensitive Content Warning,
so you can tailor your app experiences
based on which feature is enabled.
These new features
make it easier than ever
to offer privacy and peace of mind
to your users.
Next, Chris will tell us
what's new in the App Store.
Chris Markiewicz:
There is a trusted place
for users to discover apps
that meet our high standards
for safety, privacy, and performance,
and that's the App Store.
The App Store empowers you
to scale your app distribution worldwide
using a variety of business models,
like in-app purchase.
StoreKit is foundational
for safe and trusted in-app purchase.
We provide a robust data model
to connect your products to your app's UI.
If you offer in-app purchase,
you know the importance
of presenting key details,
like price and subscription duration,
so users can make an informed purchase.
And we know many developers struggle
to get this right.
This year, we're taking StoreKit further
with a new collection of views
to power your app's merchandising UI
across all platforms,
using the best practices
from the Human Interface Guidelines.
Using the declarative syntax of SwiftUI,
you can craft
your merchandising experience
and StoreKit takes care of the rest.
Let's view some examples.
The ProductView enables you
to display your products
using data you defined
in App Store Connect.
You can easily customize it
to match the look and feel of your app.
The SubscriptionStoreView is
a purpose-built view for subscriptions.
With as little as one line of code,
the description, price, and duration
for each level of service
are clearly presented to the user.
These views aren't just for iPhone.
The same code creates a view to match
the platform experience
across all Apple devices.
And it even scales to fit
the compact display of Apple Watch.
And of course, they were created with
accessibility and localization in mind
for all users.
Integrating the SubscriptionStoreView
into my app is super easy.
Let's work on the Backyard Birds Pass
subscription offering.
I'll go into Xcode to add some
declarations to my SubscriptionStoreView
to match the look and feel
of Backyard Birds.
I'll customize the marketing content
with a view,
add a container background,
and change the style
of the subscription options.
Now we have something that looks great
and matches the app's branding.
Let's also take a quick look
at the simulator
where I can get the same full experience
that my users would.
Here I can select an offer,
click Subscribe,
and complete the purchase.
That's all it takes to build
a customized purchase experience
to show users all the information
they need to make an informed decision.
We also know how hard it can be
to customize the offers you present,
based on the user's purchase history
or subscription status.
That's why the SubscriptionStoreView
will automatically determine
user eligibility
and display the right offer.
The new StoreKit views are the best way
to merchandise your in-app purchases.
Another important aspect
of growing your business
is understanding how advertising
helps users discover your app.
That's why SKAdNetwork helps ad networks
measure how successfully
ad campaigns drive downloads of your app,
all while preserving user privacy.
In addition to measuring downloads,
we know it's important to understand
how advertising can bring users
back into your app.
SKAdNetwork 5 will support
measuring re-engagement.
In addition to measuring conversions
after a user downloads your app,
you'll also be able to measure conversions
after a user opens your app
by tapping on an ad.
Version 5 will be available
in an iOS release coming later this year.
Our new features for in-app purchase
and SKAdNetwork
will help you grow your business
responsibly while respecting user privacy,
giving users transparency
and peace of mind.
Now, back to Darin.
Darin: Like our programming language
and frameworks,
our tools were made for each other.
Xcode brings together everything you need
to develop, test, and distribute apps
across all our platforms.
TestFlight and Xcode Cloud
make the experience seamless,
from your first line of code
to the first download in the App Store.
Now Ken will take us through a look
at the latest developments.
Ken Orr: For all Apple platforms,
one tool is at the center
of your developer experience,
helping you build all your great apps:
Xcode.
It brings together powerful features,
like an editor that blends crafting code
and designing user interfaces
with interactive previews
and live animations,
and built-in source control for making,
reviewing,
and sharing changes with your team.
Debugging, profiling, and testing tools
to help you evaluate and refine your app,
all of it is connected in Xcode Cloud,
a continuous integration
and delivery service
that simplifies distribution
to TestFlight and the App Store.
For Xcode 15, there are some big updates.
Let's start where you spend
most of your time: the source editor.
Code completion helps you get the code
you want faster and with fewer mistakes.
With Xcode 15, you'll start
with the most relevant completions
with the editor using the surrounding code
for prioritization.
Whether that's
the most appropriate modifier
for a specific view you're using
or when you're chaining modifiers
as you customize a view.
And Xcode will automatically generate
symbols for your asset catalog resources,
which means they show up
in code completion
and are easy to use in your code.
This gives you type safety
and peace of mind
that your assets are available at runtime.
A great place to use those assets
is in your SwiftUI views.
Xcode's previews are a seamless way
to iterate on your UI,
with nearly instant feedback
as you design
right alongside your app's code.
In Xcode 15, previews are easier to use
and available in even more places.
It starts with a new syntax,
built using Swift Macros,
that is simple to write
and easy to remember.
Working with different platforms
and devices is now easier.
You can choose them right in the canvas
to make sure
your views look great everywhere.
And you can now use Previews
across all UI frameworks!
Wherever you're using SwiftUI,
UIKIt, or AppKit,
you can iterate on your UI
with a consistent experience
from anywhere in your code.
Now, to keep pace with quickly making
and previewing changes,
Xcode streamlines how you review
and commit those changes.
Many of you use git staging
in your workflows,
and now,
it's integrated directly into Xcode!
You can stage or un-stage any change
with just a click,
crafting your next commit
without leaving your code.
From the Source Control navigator,
you can review all your changes
in a single view,
helping you put the finishing touches
on your commit.
And Xcode shows un-pushed commits too,
so you can perfectly time getting all your
commits together into a pull request.
Let's talk about testing.
It's an essential part
of creating a high-quality app.
As your code grows
across many platforms, devices,
languages, and user features,
navigating your test results
and knowing where to focus–
that can be challenging.
Xcode 15 includes a complete redesign
of the test report,
giving you new tools to better understand
your results and take action.
And it starts with
a beautiful results overview.
It shows me Top Insights
including common failure patterns,
like those
with the same assertion message.
I also get a comprehensive summary
of how my tests ran across configurations,
like device and language,
and that helps me spot patterns.
And there's a heat map
to quickly show me where to focus.
Now, I've been working on a feature
in the Backyard Birds app.
And looking at my latest test run,
I see I've got some issues.
I'll start by clicking on this insight.
It looks like a tap gesture
is failing across my new test.
I'll click this test that failed,
which gives me a detailed view
of the test activities
here on the left,
along with a full recording
of the app's UI over on the right.
I can select a specific activity.
Or I can use the new timeline
to jump to any moment.
I can see marks for interesting points,
like when the test scrolled
this view here,
or over here
where it tapped the search field.
And this is a full video recording
that gives me much more detail,
showing me exactly what happened
before the test failed.
I'll play it to see what happened.
Here, the test is selecting some food
to feed the bird.
The bird starts flying around,
and then it disappears
before my action is complete,
which is what caused my test to fail.
This new test detail with a timeline
and video recording
makes reviewing tests for animations,
gestures,
and other UI experiences so much faster.
And when I need more than video,
I can also see accessibility frames,
giving me even more insight into my views.
All combined, the new report experience
gives you deep insights,
finer details, and more interaction
to get the most out of your testing.
And it works seamlessly in Xcode
and Xcode Cloud.
Xcode Cloud is a continuous integration
and delivery service
that helps you build, test,
and share your app
across all Apple platforms.
It's deeply integrated into Xcode,
saving you time
by keeping you focused in one place.
It leverages Apple's cloud infrastructure
to offload your builds, tests,
and even code signing for distribution.
It connects with Apple services
like TestFlight and App Store Connect.
And it's built with advanced security
to protect you and your projects.
Last year, we made Xcode Cloud available
to every member
of the Apple Developer Program.
Tens of thousands of teams onboarded
their projects directly from Xcode
and the feedback has been great!
And we continue
to make Xcode Cloud even better.
We really care about performance.
Since last year,
we've made significant investments
so you can do even more
with your compute time.
We've also added
your most important requests.
When distributing to TestFlight,
you can now create and share tester notes,
helping keep all your users up to date
on your latest improvements.
Xcode Cloud also supports
macOS notarization
when distributing with DeveloperID,
so you can automatically check your app
for malicious components
before sharing it with your users.
With just a few minutes
to set up your workflows,
you can take advantage
of hours of compute time
to build, test, and deploy your apps.
We are excited
about the future of Xcode Cloud,
as we continue to make it faster,
safer, and more flexible.
Over the last year,
we've optimized the compiler
for the multi-core architecture
of Apple silicon
to make all of your builds faster
and more scalable.
The linker has been redesigned
from the ground up,
bringing massive improvements
in link speed.
Linking is up to five times faster!
The new linker also reduces
the size of debug binaries by up to 30%.
And for apps
that embed a lot of frameworks,
there's a new framework type
that delivers faster builds
during development
and reduced app size
and faster launch time for production.
Finally, we continue to make Xcode faster
and easier to just get started.
On the Mac App Store,
Xcode is now 50% smaller,
and all simulators
are downloadable on demand.
That means you can get started quickly
and install the platforms you need
at just the right time.
And now, back to Darin.
Darin: Our singular approach
of building a language,
frameworks, tools, and services
that all work together
truly comes to life
when we introduce a new platform.
The use of shared foundations
help make the platform seem familiar
while ensuring
its individual strengths shine.
visionOS takes advantage
of the investments we've been making
in our platforms for many years
and showcases the benefits
of this approach.
Here's Mike to tell you all about it.
Mike Rockwell:
The launch of Apple Vision Pro
marks the beginning of a journey together
in spatial computing.
You can now push beyond what
you previously understood to be possible
and reimagine what it means
to be connected,
productive, and entertained.
Vision Pro has many
groundbreaking technologies.
Your apps will make use of new elements
to interact with the user's space
and blend seamlessly with their room.
This is all possible using powerful
technologies you already know:
SwiftUI, RealityKit, and ARKit–
now extended for visionOS.
With this solid foundation
and an updated set of developer tools,
you're going to feel right at home
creating an entirely new universe of apps
for Apple Vision Pro.
Today we're going to cover everything
you need to get started with visionOS,
from the fundamental building blocks
to critical frameworks, tools,
and technologies.
You'll learn about the activities and
programs we are launching to support you
as you bring your apps to life
on Vision Pro;
apps that take advantage of
the infinite canvas of Vision Pro,
or that turn a room
into an immersive media environment.
So let's roll our sleeves up.
Vision Pro allows you to rethink
what is possible for your app experience.
Regardless of the kind of app
you're building,
you need to understand
how it will exist in 3D,
in your user's space.
This will inform the decisions you make
as a developer.
That understanding will help you
take advantage
of the capabilities of Vision Pro,
bringing focus and immersion to your apps
in ways that, until now,
were just not possible.
By default,
apps launch into the Shared Space.
The Shared Space is where
apps exist side by side,
much like multiple apps on a Mac desktop.
The user has full agency to reposition
apps wherever they would like.
Let's talk about the elements
you can use inside a space,
starting with the familiar window.
On visionOS,
your app can open one or more windows,
which are SwiftUI scenes
and behave just as you would expect,
as planes in space.
They can contain
traditional views and controls,
and they even support 3D objects
and RealityViews,
allowing 3D content
to sit alongside 2D content.
Additionally, your app can create
three-dimensional volumes,
which are also SwiftUI scenes,
and showcase 3D objects,
like a game board or a globe.
Volumes can be moved around this space
and viewed from all angles.
In some cases, you may want more control
over the level of immersion in your app–
maybe for the user to watch a video,
play a game, or rehearse a presentation.
You can do this by opening
a dedicated Full Space,
in which only your apps, windows,
volumes, and 3D objects appear
across the user's view.
So those are the foundational elements
of spatial computing:
windows, volumes, and spaces.
They give you a flexible toolset
to build apps
that can span the continuum of immersion.
Now, to tell you more
about how to get started building apps,
here's Geoff.
Geoff Stahl: Vision Pro supports
several different kinds of apps.
Existing iPad
and iPhone apps are supported,
each as a single scalable 2D window
with their original look and feel.
But that's only the beginning
of what's possible.
At its core,
visionOS is similar to iPadOS and iOS,
and includes many
of the same foundational frameworks.
You use SwiftUI and UIKit
to build your user interface,
RealityKit to present 3D content,
animations, and visual effects,
and ARKit to understand the space
around the user.
These are all part of the visionOS SDK.
So what does it take
to bring your app to Vision Pro?
First, in Xcode,
add the visionOS destination
to your project.
Now, when you rebuild,
your app automatically gets
some really cool improvements.
Materials with the visionOS look and feel,
fully-resizable windows with spacing tuned
for eyes and hands input,
and access to highlighting adjustments
for your custom controls.
Then, you can add visionOS-specific code
to expand your app
into a collection of windows,
volumes, or spaces.
From here, you can begin to take advantage
of the extended capabilities of SwiftUI,
RealityKit, and ARKit.
Here's Enrica to tell you how.
Enrica Casucci: On visionOS,
many of our frameworks
have been extended
to support spatial experiences.
With SwiftUI, you can now add depth
or add a 3D object inside a window.
On iOS and MacOS, a ZStack
is typically used for layering views.
visionOS goes further,
and you can separate them with depth.
This gives your two-dimensional apps
a three-dimensional feel.
You can add subtle changes in depth
to your UI elements
by using the new z-offset view modifier.
A higher offset value presents the view
in front of views with lower values.
And you can use this to show emphasis
or to indicate a change in modality,
for example
when showing details for a selection.
And with additional view modifiers,
you can have more control
over width, height, and depth.
On Vision Pro, even gestures
are aware of the additional space.
We are all used to dragging objects
around the screen.
Now, people will be able to move or rotate
objects anywhere in their physical space.
You can also create a volume with SwiftUI.
It can exist alongside your app windows,
and when running in the Shared Space,
sits side by side with other apps.
And SwiftUI windows and volumes
can also be inside a Full Space,
where you can place 3D objects
and SwiftUI elements
anywhere in the user's room.
Not only can SwiftUI quickly and easily
bring your apps onto visionOS,
it can also render
fully immersive experiences.
And SwiftUI now renders
through RealityKit,
so you can easily mix
SwiftUI and RealityKit APIs.
You can utilize UI enhancements
like ornaments,
materials, and hover effects.
Ornaments allow you to affix UI components
to the edges of your windows and volumes.
They're great for things like toolbars
and menus.
Hover effects highlight UI elements
in response to where a user looks.
While system controls
automatically get these effects,
you have options to decide whether your
custom control shows a highlight or glow.
And materials adapt to the world
around your user.
Dynamic blurs and vibrancy
make your app readable,
no matter the conditions.
Just like on our other platforms,
we recommend you use SwiftUI
to build your visionOS apps.
Your existing apps built with UIKit
can also be recompiled for visionOS,
and will get access to ornaments,
hover effects, materials,
and the native look and feel.
SwiftUI is just one of the frameworks
you'll use
to build spatial experiences on visionOS.
Edwin will walk you through a few more
that will help you on your journey.
Edwin Iskandar:
When you're ready to extend your apps
with full scenes of dynamic 3D models,
animations, and visual effects,
you'll want to use RealityKit–
Apple's 3D rendering engine
built from the ground up
for rendering spatial experiences.
We introduced RealityKit and SwiftUI
together in 2019
as independent frameworks.
On Apple Vision Pro,
they are deeply integrated
so you can build sharp, responsive,
and volumetric interfaces.
3D content can bind to SwiftUI views
and states,
seamlessly coupling 2D
and 3D visual elements together.
RealityKit automatically adjusts
to physical lighting conditions
and grounds the experience in reality
by casting shadows on floors and tables.
This makes your app look like
it belongs in the room.
RealityKit also has significant
new capabilities,
including the ability to create portals
into 3D scenes–
like the dinosaur we saw in the Keynote–
to render incredibly sharp text,
so you can read comfortably,
and a customizable material system
to create stunning visual effects.
Additionally,
rendering is even more efficient
on Apple Vision Pro by using a technique
called Dynamic foveation.
RealityKit leverages eye tracking
to selectively render
regions the user is focusing on
at very high fidelity,
reducing the rendering cost
of content in the periphery,
and enabling your apps to maximize
the processing power of the device.
RealityKit renders your 3D models
with stunning photorealistic results
by allowing you to specify
its physical properties,
such as how reflective or metallic it is.
By default,
RealityKit renders virtual content
so its lighting is connected to the
lighting conditions of the physical room.
If you want to customize
or even extend the realism
based on your creative intent,
you can provide
an image based lighting asset, or IBL,
to individualize the look.
For authoring your materials,
RealityKit has adopted MaterialX,
an open standard for specifying surface
and geometry shaders
used by leading film, visual effects,
entertainment, and gaming companies.
The broad support for MaterialX
across a variety
of industry leading creation tools
makes it much easier to write shaders.
MaterialX lets you design
and rapidly iterate on the look
of individual materials,
by allowing you to define
its shading properties.
There are repositories of materials
you can choose from,
and helpful tools like Houdini and Maya
that can be used
to author your own custom shaders.
RealityKit provides a new SwiftUI view
called RealityView.
RealityView can be used
within windows, volumes, and spaces,
letting you place 3D content
anywhere you want
within the scenes that you control.
It also supports Attachments,
which allow you to embed 2D SwiftUI views
with your 3D content.
Alongside SwiftUI and RealityKit,
a third powerful framework enables you
to take full advantage
of the user's surroundings: ARKit.
ARKit understands the space
around the user,
allowing app content to interact
with the room,
whether it's a ball bouncing off the floor
or water splashing on the wall.
ARKit hosts the real-time algorithms
on visionOS
that power a host
of core system capabilities.
These algorithms are always running,
which means your apps automatically
benefit from ARKit in the Shared Space,
no matter how they are built.
Persistence and world mapping
are handled by the system.
Segmentation, matting,
and environment lighting
are automatically applied
to the entire space.
And with the user's permission,
ARKit features can be made directly
available to your Full Space apps.
Inside a Full Space, your apps
can interact realistically with the room
by leveraging ARKit's Plane Estimation,
Scene Reconstruction,
Image Anchoring,
and World Tracking,
which uses the same Anchor concepts
as ARKit on iOS.
This makes migrating
your existing ARKit app to visionOS easy.
And on visionOS, you now also get access
to Skeletal Hand Tracking.
You can use hand tracking to create
custom gestures for your app experience
or even augment the user's hands
with digital information.
ARKit provides positioning
and orientation of joints
in the same skeletal model
introduced on iOS.
With the integrated approach
across SwiftUI, RealityKit, and ARKit,
you can leverage
the learning and investment
you've already put into Apple platforms
over the years.
And that includes efforts you have put
into making your apps accessible.
This is especially meaningful
because spatial computing opens up
great new opportunities for accessibility.
On Apple Vision Pro,
users with physical and motor disabilities
can interact with their device
entirely with their eyes,
or their voice, or a combination of both.
Users can also select with their
index finger, their wrist, or their head
as an alternative pointer
for navigating Vision Pro.
You'll make your apps accessible
on visionOS
with the same techniques you've used
for years on our other platforms.
Accessibility Inspector analyzes
and reports accessibility issues
in your visionOS apps,
and gives you suggestions
on how to make them more accessible.
And with the accessibility support
built into our frameworks,
it's easy to bring your visionOS apps
and experiences
to users with disabilities.
For example, you can help VoiceOver
describe objects in your apps
to users who are blind or have low vision
by adding labels and descriptions
that convey information,
like an object's physical appearance.
You can also incorporate user preferences
to make your apps more accessible
by design,
such as Dynamic Type
for larger text sizes,
Reduced Transparency
for better legibility,
and alternatives to head locked content.
By making use
of these familiar APIs and tools,
your apps will play a huge role
in making spatial computing accessible
to users around the world.
So that's an introduction
to the powerful frameworks you can use
to build amazing visionOS apps.
Now here's Thessa to talk about
all the tools available to you.
Thessa Buscar-Alegria:
As you start building apps for Vision Pro,
you'll recognize more
than just the frameworks.
Our developer tools have also been updated
to support visionOS.
Just like for all our other platforms,
Xcode is at the center of your development
experience for Vision Pro.
You can add a visionOS destination
to your existing projects,
or you can build an entirely new app
dedicated to the unique capabilities
of this platform.
The first step in building your app
is getting the look right
across both 2D and 3D content.
Xcode Previews lets you rapidly iterate
on appearance without leaving the editor.
When it's time to start testing
your entire app,
you can move to the simulator,
which provides a powerful environment
to run and debug your app.
You can move and look around the scene
using a keyboard,
trackpad, or a compatible game controller.
And you can interact with your app
by simulating the system gestures.
The simulator also provides
three different simulated scenes
with day and nighttime lighting conditions
to help you visualize your app.
When it comes to developing
with your Vision Pro,
you'll be building and running your app
on the device to make sure it's working.
I'm super excited
to share this additional feature
that will change the way you work.
Mac Virtual Display lets you bring
a high-fidelity 4K virtual monitor
of your Mac
right into your Vision Pro
just by looking at it.
You can use the full capabilities
of your Mac
from within your device,
and that includes Xcode.
This is an incredible
end-to-end development experience:
coding, testing, and debugging your app
on your Vision Pro the entire time,
without any interruptions
or loss of context.
Sometimes,
you need to dig into the details
of how your app's content
relates to the real world.
When your app interacts
with the user's room,
it can present unique challenges,
such as 3D content
visually clipping through walls.
Xcode features
practical debug visualizations
to help you explore collisions,
occlusions,
and scene understanding
as it relates to your 3D content.
These visualizations work both
in the simulator and on Vision Pro.
As you evolve your visionOS apps,
they will become more spatial,
breaking outside the boundaries
of flat windows
and bringing 3D experiences to users
unlike ever before.
Doing this right
requires a new visual tool.
That's why we made Reality Composer Pro.
Reality Composer Pro is an application
that lets you preview and prepare
3D content for your visionOS apps.
You can import and organize assets such as
3D models, animations, images, and sounds.
It integrates tightly
with the Xcode build process
to optimize your assets
for use on Vision Pro.
You can easily send your content
to Vision Pro
to preview, size, and rotate it.
Push new changes at any time,
and see how your content looks
before ever typing a line of code.
Here's Jason to give you a tour.
Jason Cahill: I've been working
on one of our sample projects
that takes you through the Solar System.
I want to make sure
my 3D content looks great Vision Pro,
and I'm going to use Reality Composer Pro
to update it now.
I'll start by importing
the satellite model and images
that I made in my 3D modeling application.
This model has a lot of details,
but presently no materials.
I'll create a custom material
in Reality Composer Pro,
and then I'll jump to the Shader Graph
where we can customize it.
It's easy and fun
to add some simple images
and function nodes
to change the look of an object,
all without needing to get into code.
You can try things
and see the results instantly,
and you'll never get compiler errors
from having to hand-type shaders.
I'll repeat this for the other nodes too.
At any time, I can preview my work
right on my Vision Pro.
I can scale it,
move it,
or rotate it, and make sure
it looks and feels how I want.
I like these changes.
And then jump back into Xcode,
where my changes have been reflected
in my project
and are ready for use in Xcode Previews,
or the Simulator.
Just like that, ready for me
to load in code and use in my app!
With Reality Composer Pro,
your visionOS development process
has a powerful new tool
that works side by side with Xcode,
making previewing and preparing 3D content
as easy as building and running your code.
Thessa:
When you're ready to beta test your app,
TestFlight will be available to use
on Vision Pro from the start.
Submit new builds to TestFlight
just as you would expect
through App Store Connect,
Xcode, or Xcode Cloud,
and testers can install them
and provide valuable feedback
right from the native TestFlight app.
They can also access beta builds
of your compatible iPad and iPhone apps
on Vision Pro.
With this family of development tools
and services, from Xcode to TestFlight,
and now Reality Composer Pro,
you'll be well on your way
to making amazing apps for Vision Pro.
And now, back to Mike.
Mike: Many of you have invested years
building 3D apps and games with Unity.
To make it easy to bring your apps
to Vision Pro,
Apple and Unity
have been deeply collaborating
to layer Unity's real-time engine
on top of RealityKit
and enable their development tools
to target visionOS.
This means that Unity-created apps
can coexist with other visionOS apps
in the Shared Space,
and take full advantage of
the unique benefits of Apple Vision Pro.
To tell you more,
I'd like to introduce Ralph from Unity.
Ralph Hauwert: Thank you, Mike.
It's been truly exciting
to collaborate with Apple
on our deep integration for visionOS.
Now, you can use Unity's robust
and familiar authoring tools
to create new visionOS games and apps.
And you can bring your existing
Unity-created projects to Vision Pro
to reimagine your experiences
for this new platform.
Your apps get access
to all the benefits of visionOS,
such as high-resolution pass-through
and Dynamic Foveated Rendering,
in addition to familiar Unity features
like AR Foundation.
And with this deep integration
between Unity and visionOS,
your apps can even appear
alongside other apps in the Shared Space.
By combining Unity's authoring
and simulation capabilities
with RealityKit's managed app rendering,
content created with Unity
looks and feels at home on visionOS.
With Unity, you'll be able
to get started quickly with our community,
our tutorials, and templates.
We believe
that Apple Vision Pro has launched
the new frontier of spatial computing,
and we are really excited
to see the brand new apps and games
that you will create.
Mike: Thank you so much, Ralph.
It's been amazing working with you.
There are a few more
fundamental features of visionOS
that you should know
when you're planning your next steps.
Here's Jeff to give you all the details.
Jeff Norris: The frameworks you use
to create apps for Vision Pro
were designed with two goals in mind:
to enable you to leverage
the platform's powerful hardware
and software with minimal effort,
and to preserve user privacy.
You can see these principles at work
throughout the system,
from the way apps blend in
with their surroundings
to the natural user interactions
to the new possibilities
for collaboration.
visionOS builds a 3D model
of the user's surroundings
to enable realistic lighting and shadows.
As a result, apps can naturally blend in
with the world around them
without needing access to camera data.
visionOS uses the same 3D model
to enable the next generation
of spatial audio for your apps.
In the real world, sound reverberates
through and around a space,
bouncing off walls and furniture
before arriving at a person's ears.
Your app's virtual sounds
should behave the same way.
This requires a sophisticated
understanding of the user's surroundings.
The PHASE spatial audio engine in visionOS
fuses acoustic sensing
with 3D scene understanding
to create a detailed model
of the sonic characteristics of the space.
As sound sources and the user
move around the environment,
PHASE updates its audio ray traced
simulation in real time.
This model combines with Apple's
Personalized Spatial Audio technology
to tailor the experience
to each individual
and their surroundings, automatically.
All of this incredible complexity
is managed for you,
and you don't need access to any details
of the user's physical space.
Using RealityKit, you simply decide
where you want sounds to come from,
and visionOS naturally mixes them
into the real world.
Just like the algorithms that power
realistic lighting and audio in your apps,
user input on visionOS works automatically
and is private by design.
Hover effects render automatically
for any UI elements
built using SwiftUI or RealityKit.
If a user looks a button,
it highlights before they tap on it.
And just like a click of a mouse,
or a tap on an iPhone,
your app is notified of a selection
when a user taps their fingers.
The user gets the visual feedback
they need,
and you receive
the interactions you expect
without needing to know
where the user looks before they tap.
Sharing and collaboration are a central
part of the Vision Pro experience.
Just like on macOS,
Vision Pro users can share any app window
with others on a FaceTime call.
And with SharePlay, next-generation
shared experiences become possible.
When your app adopts SharePlay
with the GroupActivities API,
the sharing control over each window
adds an option
that launches your app for everyone
on the call.
This allows them to participate
in a truly shared experience,
together, in real time.
You decide how your app
can be used collaboratively,
just as you have for SharePlay
on our other platforms.
A Vision Pro user on a FaceTime call
appears to other participants
as a Persona–
a natural representation created
with advanced machine learning techniques,
that dynamically matches
their facial and hand movements.
Personas appear to other Vision Pro users
with three-dimensional volume and depth.
But we want to take FaceTime
to the next level on Vision Pro
and empower users anywhere to interact
like they are actually in a room together.
This experience
is still in its early form,
and we're excited to share it
with you here for the first time.
Spatial Personas allow Vision Pro users
to break out of the familiar FaceTime tile
and feel more present, like they are
gathered in the same physical space.
visionOS ensures that users and apps have
a shared and consistent spatial context.
Your apps can take advantage
of this new context with SharePlay.
Now, beyond just synchronizing changes
in your app between users,
you can respond
to a user's physical actions,
so that standing together
at a Freeform board
or moving pieces in a tabletop game
feels natural.
We want your apps to be a part
of this incredible new experience,
and your feedback will be important
as it continues to develop.
That's why we're making
a developer preview of Spatial Personas
available to you later this year.
These are just a few more examples
of the rich, extensive technologies
you can take advantage of on visionOS.
Now, here's Linda
to talk about where you'll go from here.
Linda Dong:
Now that you've been introduced
to Apple Vision Pro and visionOS,
what's next?
Your development journey starts today.
We encourage you to dive in
and learn as much as you can
as you begin designing, developing,
and testing for Vision Pro.
The visionOS SDK,
along with an updated Xcode and Simulator,
and Reality Composer Pro,
will be available later this month,
so you can start working on your ideas.
You'll also have access
to extensive technical documentation,
new design kits and tools,
and an updated Human Interface Guidelines
for visionOS.
In addition to the Vision Pro Simulator,
we also have options for you to see
how your app works on Vision Pro.
This summer we're launching
the Apple Vision Pro Developer Labs,
where you can test your app
on Vision Pro hardware.
You'll have hands-on support
and an ability to preview your experience
before Vision Pro is released
to customers.
These labs will be located in
several locations around the world,
including our Developer Center
here in Cupertino.
And no matter where you are,
you'll be able to submit a request
for us to evaluate your app's
compatibility with Vision Pro.
We'll install your app
and share any issues we may find.
To get further updates
on these exciting opportunities,
visit the Developer Website.
And of course, Vision Pro will launch
with a brand new App Store,
so people can discover and download
the incredible apps you create.
We invite you to share your ideas
for this platform
and we'll continue to support you
as you bring them to life!
Now, back to Darin.
Darin: What an exciting year!
An incredible opportunity with visionOS,
so many thoughtful additions
to each platform,
like more places to surface your app
with WidgetKit,
an expansion of Continuity Camera,
and a new design for watchOS.
Plus major enhancements to Swift
with Macros and Swift Data,
and a big upgrade to Xcode Previews.
This year's developments across languages,
frameworks,
tools, and services
represent our deep commitment
to helping you create unique experiences
for billions of devices
across our platforms.
These platforms span an increasingly
diverse range of products
with a level of consistency
and integration
that make a difference to you
as a developer and to users.
We successfully scratched the surface
of what's new in our platforms.
But to go further,
we have 175 in-depth video sessions–
40 for visionOS alone–
along with over 200 labs
staffed by Apple experts
to answer your burning questions
as you build great apps.
There's never been a better time
to be an Apple developer,
and I have no doubt what you create
will astound and delight your users.
Have a fantastic WWDC!
♪ ♪