♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello and welcome.
My name is Sirisha,
and I'm an engineer
on the HealthKit team.
Today, there are hundreds
of health and fitness apps
in the App Store that help users
get healthy and stay healthy.
And for them all,
HealthKit provides a centralized
encrypted database,
so your amazing apps can show
your users a cohesive view
of their health data.
Now, the Workout APIs
are some of the most powerful
that HealthKit provides,
and I love them.
For today's video, I've created
a sample cycling app
for Apple Watch to track
my cycling workouts.
And for easier access, I would
love to mount my iPhone
on the handlebars to use
as a cycling computer.
That way, I can get
a quick and easy view
of the live metrics displayed
on my Apple Watch
without having to take my hands
off the handlebars.
HealthKit is introducing
new Workout APIs
to control and mirror
active workout sessions
between Apple Watch and iPhone.
Updating support
for cycling workouts
with the addition
of new data types
for tracking cycling speed,
power, cadence,
and functional threshold power,
or FTP.
And if that wasn't enough,
HealthKit along with
the Health app is now on iPad.
Now, your customers signed into
their iCloud account on iPad
will see their health data
synced through HealthKit
to their iPad.
Just imagine the richer health
and post-workout experience
you can provide.
Today, I'll use my sample app
to demonstrate
how to mirror a workout
running on Apple Watch
with a paired iPhone.
Then, I'll add some code
to show you
how to collect
new cycling metrics
and sync them across devices.
And I'll wrap up with
the authorization details
required to display
workouts on iPad.
So let's check out how
Apple Watch, iPhone, and iPad
can work together to provide
a great workout experience.
In my example, I'm running
the workout on Apple Watch.
I'm using a workout session
as a centralized object
to manage its life cycle,
starting, pausing, and stopping.
If you're not already familiar
with workout sessions,
you might want to watch
previous talks,
"New ways
'to work with Workouts,"
and "Build a workout app
for Apple Watch."
Now, for me to control
the workout from my iPhone,
I need to get
this workout session
from my Apple Watch
to my iPhone.
And to do so,
I'll use HealthKit's
new mirrored session APIs.
When a mirrored session
starts on my Apple Watch,
if my iPhone app is not running,
it will be launched
in the background
and handed over
the workout session.
To receive the session,
my iPhone app needs to be ready.
So, first I'll set up a handler
in the iPhone app launch
sequence using the HealthStore.
That way, it will be ready
to receive the session
from my Apple Watch.
Every time my iPhone app
is launched
in the foreground
or the background,
I'll implement
the mirroring start handler
in order to receive
the active workout session
passed from my Apple Watch.
Next, I'll create
a workout configuration
with an activity type
of cycling.
Then I'll call the existing
Start Watch App API
in my iPhone app to launch
the app on my paired Apple Watch
and pass the workout
configuration.
When I receive the configuration
from my iPhone,
I can create a workout
session in my Apple Watch app.
The workout session
on my Apple Watch
is called the primary session.
And the workout session
on my iPhone
is called the mirrored session.
So here's how it looks.
When I start a workout
in my iPhone app,
my app on my Apple Watch
gets launched
with the configuration
sent from my iPhone.
So far, so good.
Now the thing that makes
this API so convenient
is that HealthKit
takes care of keeping
both the primary and the
mirrored session states in sync.
For example, when the primary
session is paused
on my Apple Watch,
the mirrored session
on my iPhone is paused as well.
In addition to getting a copy
of the active workout session
to my iPhone, HealthKit also
provides a new API
to exchange relevant workout
data between both devices,
and provides the ability
to begin and end activities
as well as generate events.
OK, now that I have
my primary session ready
and my iPhone ready
to receive the handler,
I'll start mirroring
from my Apple Watch
by calling
startMirroringToCompanionDevice
and start the primary session.
Once I call startMirroring
on Apple Watch,
HealthKit launches my companion
iPhone app in the background,
gives my app 10 seconds
to start a live activity
and call a handler
to start mirroring.
Great, so we have started
the session on the Apple Watch
and got the copy on iPhone.
Now, let me show you
how the session state
is communicated
between the devices.
In my example app,
I want to show my users
the state of
the workout session,
like whether the session
is running, paused, et cetera.
So I'll set up the session
delegate on Apple Watch
and iPhone to monitor
the session state updates
and the events generated.
Keep in mind that it is
important to keep a reference
to the retrieved mirrored
session on the iPhone app.
Calling startActivity
on my Apple Watch
starts the primary session
and changes the session
state to running.
This state update is delivered
to my Apple Watch app
since it's set as session
delegate of the primary session.
My app on my iPhone
also gets the state update
through the mirrored
session delegate.
It's that easy to bring an
active workout session to iPhone
and monitor the changes
on a session.
So here's what it looks like.
When a workout session
is started on my Apple Watch,
the pause button on my iPhone
and my Apple Watch
is activated to indicate that
the workout session is running.
In addition to syncing
session states
between the primary
and the mirrored session,
I can also generate and send
events like pause and resume.
When I pause the workout
session on my Apple Watch,
both my Apple Watch app
and the mirrored session
on my iPhone
get notified about
the pause event
through their session delegate.
And that looks like this.
When I pause a workout
session on my Apple Watch,
the resume button on both
my devices becomes active.
Now that I have a workout
session on my iPhone,
I can control the workout
from iPhone as well.
When I resume the mirrored
session on my iPhone,
the primary session delegate
on my Apple Watch
gets notified about
the state change
and the mirrored session
delegate gets a resume event.
Next, I would like to show
you how to take advantage
of the new cycling features
HealthKit is introducing
this year,
including new data types such as
cycling speed, power, cadence;
a new ability to directly
connect to Bluetooth devices
designed to provide
these data types,
similar to how a heart rate
monitor collects and writes
heart rate data
to the health database;
and finally, the ability
for HealthKit on Apple Watch
to automatically
calculate and save FTP
based on the data collected
from these Bluetooth devices.
My bike has a power meter
that collects power and cadence,
which I paired
with my Apple Watch.
The sensor writes the data
to my Apple Watch,
and I would like to extend
my app to send that data
to my iPhone
for display as I ride.
To do this, I'll first start
collecting cycling metrics
using the recommended workout builder API beginCollection.
And then I'll send the data
using the sendData(toRemoteWorkoutSession) API.
To send the cycling metrics,
I'll package the speed,
cadence, and power data received
from Bluetooth sensors
on my Apple Watch and call
sendData(toRemoteWorkoutSession)
on the primary session.
As a result, the mirrored
session delegate on my iPhone
will receive the
didReceiveDataFromRemoteDevice
call with the package data,
which I can unpack
and display on my iPhone.
Here is how it looks like
with my example app
sending cycling metrics
from my Apple Watch
and how they are displayed
in my iPhone app.
Using
sendData(toRemoteWorkoutSession)
I can also send data
in the opposite direction
from my iPhone
to my Apple Watch.
In my example, I want
to keep track of my water intake
during a workout
so I can analyze it afterwards
in the hopes of creating
a better hydration plan
for my next ride.
To do this,
I'll package and send
the amount of water I consume
on the mirrored session
from my iPhone to Apple Watch.
The primary session's delegate
method
didReceiveDataFromRemoteDevice
is called with the packaged data
which I'll unpack
and save on my Apple Watch.
So here's how it looks
in my example app.
When I tap the button to count
each ounce of water I take,
it sends it to my Apple Watch,
where it displays the total
amount of water consumed.
Now I can stop mirroring
the session anytime
during the workout by calling
stopMirroringToCompanionDevice
API.
Calling this method
will stop sending data
to the companion device
and the mirrored session's
didDisconnectFromRemoteDevice
WithError delegate method
will be called.
And when I'm done cycling,
I'll end the primary session
and save it on the Apple Watch
by finishing the builder.
After saving the workout sample
on Apple Watch,
it syncs to my other devices,
and I can now show
the post-workout summary
with more detailed charts
and visualizations.
Great! My next step is to
present the post-workout summary
in my app running on my iPad.
Since the workout
I just saved on Apple Watch
automatically syncs to iPad,
I only need to make
a few changes
to visualize my workout data.
Like any app
accessing HealthKit data,
my app on iPad will will first
need to get user authorization.
When an app requests
authorization,
the authorization sheet
is shown if needed.
On iPad, your app might
have multiple window scenes,
so it's important to ensure
that the authorization sheet
is shown over
the appropriate scene.
To do this in my app,
I'll first import
HealthKitUI framework.
I'll specify the data types
I'm interested in reading,
specifically active energy,
cycling speed, power, cadence,
heart rate, and workout samples.
Then, since I built
a SwiftUI app,
I'll use the new
healthDataAccessRequest
view modifier from
the HealthKitUI framework
and pass the data types
I want to share and read,
as well as a trigger.
Setting the trigger to true
will present the authorization
sheet in my app.
For a UIKit app,
you would set the
healthStores.authorizationView
ControllerPresenter property,
and then request authorization
with the types to share
and read.
Now, with the authorization
taken care of,
let's check out
my workout on iPad.
Amazing!
Now I can access my workout data
and take advantage
of the iPad's screen size
to create a richer experience
for my app.
Isn't it super easy?
Now you can start and control
a workout from your iPhone,
collect and sync rich cycling
data from your Apple Watch,
and finally, view the workout
details on your iPad.
To wrap up,
be sure to update your app
to support authorization
on iPad.
If your Fitness app
involves cycling,
you can add support
for new data types.
If you build workout apps
on iPhone and Apple Watch,
check out the new
mirrored session APIs
to start mirroring data
and controlling state
between both devices.
If your app needs it, use sync
identifiers and version numbers
to keep the data consistent
across your server
and users' devices.
And finally,
give us your feedback.
We want to support
the features you need
to keep building those amazing
apps to keep the world healthy.
Thank you for watching.
♪