♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Manda Paul:
Hi, my name is Manda.
I'm on the Apple Vision
Science team
Herman Damveld: And I am Herman,
and I'm a research scientist
here at Apple.
Creating experiences
in three dimensions makes use
of unique modalities such
as depth and full field of view.
We will introduce you to how
a person may experience
this new level of immersion
through visual cues
and motion information
from 3D content,
and where human limitations
may interfere
with comfort of people
experiencing your apps.
Manda: Our guidelines are
to help you create experiences
that are comfortable
and enjoyable.
We'll talk through
visual depth cues,
content parameters,
eye effort,
motion of virtual objects,
head-locked content,
motion in windows,
and oscillating motion.
To begin, it's important
that your content
provides correct
visual depth cues to the viewer.
This matters because
well-designed 3D content
enables the brain
to perceive depth.
First, a bit of science.
We have multiple sensory systems
with which we experience
the real
and virtual world.
At the very high level,
the visual system is responsible
for taking in light
from the content you create
and interpreting it
into what is perceived.
That is to say,
your design decisions
have a significant impact on
vision comfort for your viewers.
Agreement between
the depth intended by you
and the depth
perceived by the viewer
is necessary for vision comfort.
As an image moves in depth,
the brain enlists
the eye muscles to converge
the line of sight and fixate
the eyes at the image depth.
This enables a single image
to be perceived.
To converge the eyes correctly,
the brain needs correct
visual depth cues.
Vision comfort might be affected
when depth cues are missing,
conflicting, or misleading.
The viewer might
experience discomforts
such as double vision
or eye fatigue.
Let's see how we can use image
cues to maintain vision comfort.
When working with scenes
that are very sparse,
as in this image of a citrus,
many visual cues are missing
that might have conveyed
depth information.
The brain might be unable
to reconcile what depth
to converge the eyes to,
hence causing discomfort.
Seeing the color of the citrus
enables the familiar size cue.
If the slice looks green, the
brain uses the prior knowledge
of the size of a lime
to inform what depth
this slice might be floating at
and converges the eyes
at that correct depth.
Using blur is another way
to convey depth information.
Relative size can also be used
to add depth cues
to a sparse image.
The larger of the two slices
from the lime
is perceived to be
closer to the viewer.
Gentle motion can also
provide a reference
for what depth the line of sight
should point to.
My colleague Herman,
will elaborate on the nuances
of using motion in your content.
For now, let's add just a few
more cues to direct the eyes.
An added background,
light and shadow, occlusion,
and texture density
are some more methods
to add in the missing
visual depth cues.
Conflicting cues
are also troublesome.
As mentioned, the bottom slice
appears closer
since it looks larger.
We expect it to be in front
and occlude
the smaller looking slice.
However here, relative size cue
conflicts with occlusion cue,
telling the brain the opposite
of what we expect.
The conflict between
the depth cues
might lead to vision discomfort.
Conflicting cues are not unique
to sparse scenes.
The more conflict there is,
the more challenging
for vision comfort.
So, ensure all of the depth cues
from your content
give the brain
correct information
so to align the viewer's eyes
to the depth you intended.
One more thought about depth
is correcting the visual cues
that are misleading,
such as repeating patterns.
Here, both eyes are pointed
to the same object
in the repeating pattern.
That's great!
However here, each eye
locks onto a different object
from the repeating pattern
and when the brain tries
to combine the images
from each eye into one,
it's perceived
at a different depth
than the repeating pattern
is intended to be.
To mitigate this conflict
and to avoid double vision,
use smaller portions
of the pattern
or break up the pattern
with another design.
A final note about
depth perception.
The 3D content, along with
your visual depth cues
will automatically be rendered
on each display
per eye appropriately
to enable someone to see
the depth you intended.
If you choose to manually
render stereo content
for stereo video, for example,
it is extremely important to not
only have correct depth cues
but also have correct
disparity for each eye
so to avoid extremely
conflicting visual cues
which could lead
to severe vision discomfort.
All right!
Let's move on
to content parameters
such as size and contrast.
Visually comfortable content
have parameters suited
for each specific
visual experience.
Choose parameters
that reduce visual effort.
Here are some scenarios.
Content requiring fixating
the eyes for an extended time,
such as for reading,
is most visually comfortable
when placed farther
than arm's-length distance.
In addition, enable a person
to adjust content depth
so they may choose a depth
that's most comfortable for them
in the experience.
Reserve content
closest to the viewer
for experiences demanding
only momentary visual effort
or for experiences
inviting direct interaction
which occurs when someone's hand
actually intersects an item
in 3D space.
Otherwise,
you may use visual cues,
such as transparency or blur,
to redirect eyes
to a farther depth
to increase visual comfort.
Similar to depth,
content size and contrast
should match the particular
visual experience
you are designing
to allow for vision comfort.
For example, utilize higher
contrast for reading text
and lower contrast,
transparency, or blur
to redirect visual attention
elsewhere.
Choose text size
and window size and depth
for extended reading
such that text is legible
with comfortable eye scanning,
without the need
to rotate the head or body.
One more parameter to be mindful
of is content brightness.
When a large portion
of the field of view is dark
as in this image,
slow down the transition
to a bright scene
to give time to the eye
for brightness adaptation
and ensure vision comfort.
One last thing to be mindful of
for vision comfort
is the effort required
from the eyes.
For a more comfortable
visual experience,
minimize eye effort
demanded from your viewers.
Here is how.
When choosing content location,
keep in mind
it's most comfortable for people
to turn their eyes downwards
or left and right.
So choose those positions
for your content when possible.
Upward and diagonal eye rotation
requires most eye-muscle effort.
Holding the eyes at those
positions can be fatiguing.
Content requiring
extended reading
or elongated target fixations
should be placed
towards the center
and slightly below line of sight
to provide a comfortable
visual experience.
If extreme eye-rotation angles
are necessary
for your experience,
design for brief interactions,
or else move them
to the center of field of view
to reduce eye-rotation effort.
It is also important to consider
that a person might prefer
to take a break
to rest their eyes.
To enable this,
design for natural break points
in your experience
to allow for
the person's eyes to rest.
That's it for vision comfort!
Next, my colleague Herman
will walk you through
how to design apps
for motion comfort.
Herman: Thanks, Manda!
Next, we are going
to have a look
at how the motion information
from content
in your immersive apps
can affect a person's experience
and where human limitations
may interfere with comfort.
Let's start with digging a
little further into the science.
We, human beings,
use multiple sensory systems
to experience the real
and virtual world.
We already saw that
the visual system is responsible
for taking in light and
interpreting what is perceived.
Part of that perception
is your own motion.
The vestibular system
in your inner ear
also measures
your own movements.
Normally, the visual motion
information
and the motion that you perceive
with your vestibular system
are always in agreement.
But when the visual motion
information is missing
or conflicting with
the vestibular information,
you can experience
motion discomfort,
such as dizziness
or an upset stomach.
Well-designed content
enables the brain
to perceive the world
as stationary.
This provides
a sense of stability
and is necessary
for motion comfort.
Let's go over
some scenarios with motion
and see how we can
maintain motion comfort.
The first scenario deals
with motion of virtual objects.
When one or more
virtual objects,
like these blue
polyhedrons here,
cover a large part
of the field of view
and move,
the viewer's brain might
interpret the visual motion
of the objects as if the viewer
themself is moving.
This upsets
the sense of stability
and can cause motion discomfort.
As a designer,
you can mitigate this
by making objects
semitransparent when they move,
so the passthrough content
is clearly visible
during the motion.
Whenever possible,
avoid using head-locked content.
That is content that is
anchored to the user's head.
Head-locked content will be,
always, in the same position
in the field of view.
If head-locked views
are necessary,
use a smaller window size
placed near the center
of the line of sight
and farther away
from the viewer.
Whenever possible,
use world-locked views
to prevent content
from feeling stuck.
Another alternative is to use
a lazy-follow animation.
This moves content slowly
towards a destination over time.
You also want to be mindful
of the motion of the content
that will be visible
in a virtual window.
When the content in a window,
such as this virtual landscape,
moves...
...the viewer's brain might
interpret the visual motion
as if the viewer themself
is moving.
To provide optimal
motion comfort,
you want to be mindful
about camera motions.
For starters, keep the horizon
of the content in the window
aligned with the real horizon.
The point where all the pixels
appear to be coming from
is called
the focus of expansion.
That's where you're going,
and people have a natural
tendency to look at that point.
You want to move the camera
in such a way
that the motion
of the focus of expansion
is slow and predictable,
and you want to keep
the focus of expansion
within the field of view.
That means that you want
to avoid fast turns
or pure rotational motion.
The focus of expansion shifts
out of the field of view
in those cases.
As an alternative
to fast rotations,
you can use instantaneous
directional changes
during a quick fade-out.
To optimize for motion comfort,
you also want to avoid
that large objects shoot by
at close range,
as seen here on the right.
Best keep objects small
and at a larger distance,
as on the left.
And if possible,
use plain textures
with low luminance contrast,
which makes the motion
less perceivable by your eyes.
The last type of motion
scenario to be mindful of
deals with sustained
oscillations of objects
and animations.
To ensure a comfortable
experience,
try to avoid oscillations
in general,
and in particular those
with frequencies around 0.2 Hz.
That is one oscillation
per 5 seconds.
And if you really cannot avoid
showing oscillating motions,
try to keep the amplitude
of the motion low
and make the content
semitransparent.
This makes the motion much
less perceivable by your eyes,
as seen on the left.
And it's always a good idea
to provide
an oscillation-free alternative
through the Reduce Motion
accessibility setting.
To wrap it up, here's a summary
of the things to keep in mind
when designing
for motion comfort.
Try to provide
a sense of stability,
avoid head-locked content,
be gentle with camera motion,
and avoid oscillations
if you can.
To learn more about principles
of spatial design
and see many of our vision
and motion guidelines in action,
I can recommend visiting
the sessions listed here.
Manda: That's it for us.
We can't wait to see
what amazing experiences
you will create!
Herman: Thank you for watching!
♪