♪ ♪
Kathryn: Hi! I'm Kathryn, and I'm an
engineer working on System Experience.
Today I'm going to talk about
the new locations for widgets,
and how you can easily optimize
your widget to look great everywhere.
First, let's go over
a quick history of widgets.
iOS 14 introduced widgets
on the Home screen,
and iOS 16 brought widgets
to the Lock screen,
using the same easy WidgetKit API.
This year, the widget ecosystem
is expanding to four new locations:
the desktop on Mac,
the Lock screen on iPad,
the new StandBy mode on iPhone,
and the new Smart Stack on Apple Watch.
This means that people will be able
to see all of their favorite widgets
in even more places.
Your widget will be able to appear
in all of these locations automatically,
so it's important to make sure that it
looks great no matter where it's shown.
Thanks to iPhone Widgets On Mac,
people will be able
to use your widget on Mac
even if you don't currently have
a macOS app.
My friends Devon and Graham
have asked me to help them update
their Emoji Rangers widget
to get it ready for these new places.
You might remember this project
from WWDC20's "Widgets code-along",
and WWDC22's
"Complications and widgets: Reloaded".
We'll start by going over
the new content margins for widgets,
and how to transition to them
on Apple Watch.
Next, we'll add an automatically
removable background to our widget.
Then, we'll modify our widget so that
it can dynamically expand its layout
to fit its environment.
Finally, we'll make sure the elements
in our widget
are ready for vibrant rendering.
Let’s get started.
New for widgets this year
are content margins.
Content margins are padding
which is automatically applied
to your widget's body,
preventing your content from getting to
close to the edge of the widget container.
These margins may be larger or smaller,
depending on the environment
where your widget is being shown.
On watchOS 9 and below,
widgets use the system-defined safe area
to keep content from getting
too close to the edge.
Widgets could add modifiers like
ignoresSafeArea to views
to allow them to extend
outside of the safe area.
On watchOS 10 and above,
safe areas in widgets
have been replaced
by the use of content margins.
This means that modifiers like
ignoresSafeArea
no longer have any effect in widgets.
For most widgets, this change
won't affect how your widget looks.
However, if your widget has content
which used to ignore the safe area,
you can still achieve this same effect
by adding the contentMarginsDisabled
modifier to your widget configuration.
Then, for any content which should
remain within the default content margins,
simply add padding back in.
You can use the widgetContentMargins
environment variable
to get the default margins
for the current environment.
Content margins, along with
these new modifiers and variables,
are available on every platform
where widgets are shown.
Now, let's add a removable background
to our Emoji Rangers widget.
Our existing accessory family of widgets
automatically work on iPad Lock screen,
just like on iPhone.
iPad can also show system small widgets
right alongside them.
Here's what ours looks like
on the Lock screen right now.
We need to remove its background
in this environment
so that it matches
the other widgets better.
Luckily, doing this is super simple.
Here I have the code for
our systemSmall widget's view.
Right now, it consists of an AvatarView
layered on top of our gameBackground color
using a ZStack.
To make the background color removable,
all we need to change
is to add a containerBackground modifier
to our View,
and move our gameBackground color inside.
Once we do that,
the system can automatically take out
our widget's background
depending on where it's being shown.
The Smart Stack on Apple Watch can also
utilize this new containerBackground.
By default,
your accessoryRectangular widget
will receive a dark material background
in this environment.
By adding that same
containerBackground modifier to our view,
the widget is placed on the same
background as our other widgets,
linking it with our app's visual identity.
For a deeper dive on this new environment,
check out "Design widgets for
the Smart Stack on Apple Watch".
Some widgets,
like the Photos and Maps widgets,
don't really have
distinct foreground content,
so there's no background
which makes sense to remove.
In this case, you can add
the containerBackgroundRemovable modifier
to your WidgetConfiguration,
and set it to false.
Now, let's make some optimizations
to our layout
for when we're on iPad Lock screen
and StandBy mode.
The Weather widget is a great example
of how to change your layout
when the widget background is removed.
Notice how the widget still contains
the same information,
but it's been optimized
to take advantage of the space.
The content is pushed
all the way to the edges,
and important elements are enlarged.
These tweaks make the widget
easier to read from far away,
and integrate it more seamlessly
into StandBy mode.
These layout changes also help the widget
to blend in with accessory family
widgets on iPad Lock screen,
maintaining a more consistent look
across every family.
Let's move to Xcode to implement
these changes in our own widget.
Here I have the code for our AvatarView,
which is what we use
for our systemSmall widget.
On the right, I can see a live preview
of what our widget looks like
in Xcode Previews.
When shown in contexts where
the container background is removed,
the widgetContentMargins automatically
shrink to bring our content edge-to-edge.
We can detect whether the widget
background has been removed
using the showsWidgetContainerBackground
environment variable.
When it is, let's omit the details
about our hero's level and XP
from our HeroNameView,
and instead show those details below.
This will also make our hero's name larger
when in this environment.
Now when we toggle between these contexts,
our layout changes automatically
from our original view
to our new enlarged view.
Just like with accessory family widgets,
our system family widgets are shown
in the vibrant rendering mode
on iPad Lock screen.
This means that your widget
will be desaturated,
then colored appropriately
for the Lock screen background.
When rendered like this,
issues with contrast
can impact our widget's legibility.
For example, our hero's avatar
becomes difficult to distinguish
from its circular backdrop.
Let's hop back to Xcode,
and modify our widget
to remove that backdrop
when in the vibrant rendering mode.
Let’s check this out
in StandBy Night mode.
We can use the widgetRenderingMode
environment variable
to detect which rendering mode we're in.
Let's change
our Avatar's includesBackground parameter
to check if we're in
the vibrant rendering mode.
StandBy Night mode
also uses vibrant rendering,
so our avatar is clearly visible
in this context as well.
To learn more about
widget rendering modes,
watch "Complications and widgets:
Reloaded" from WWDC22.
And for more about
what's new with widgets,
check out "Bring widgets to life".
I'm super excited about all the changes
that are coming to widgets,
and I can't wait to see what ideas
you come up with to enhance your widgets
with these new features.
Thanks, and enjoy!
♪ ♪