♪ ♪
Melissa: Hi, I’m Melissa Nierle.
I’m a software engineer
on the Enterprise and Education
Technologies team,
and today I’m excited to introduce you
to device management for Apple Watch.
Apple Watch has become
an indispensable daily companion for users
by helping us stay connected,
active, and healthy.
Hands-free communication,
responding to notifications on the go,
and safety features like fall detection
make Apple Watch the perfect addition
for enterprise customers.
From small businesses and public utilities
to large enterprises
and healthcare systems,
there’s no limit to the places
where you’ll find Apple Watch at work.
Companies like Volvo
already use Apple Watch
to enhance their employee workflow
by using it to log jobs and streamline
communication with customers.
We want to enable organizations to create
solutions that improve productivity,
support wellness,
and provide additional safety
by deploying Apple Watch
to their employees.
That’s why this year, we’re introducing
Device Management for watchOS.
Organizations can now deploy
and configure Apple Watches
along with all their other Apple devices.
We’re excited to see all the ways
Apple Watch will impact
both users and their organizations
when deployed at scale.
Let’s get started with how it works.
First, we’ll discuss the new enrollment
flow for Apple Watch, and then later,
we’ll talk about what you need
to know when managing Apple Watch.
There are a few things we should consider
when Apple Watch enrolls into MDM.
First, just like how we use
Apple Watch and iPhone together as a pair,
they are managed together
as a pair as well.
The devices share functionality between
them like apps and restrictions,
as well as hand off information
to each other
to perform tasks in one seamless flow.
We’ve leveraged this to create
the Apple Watch enrollment flow.
The enrollment flow
actually begins on iPhone
for both the organization administrator
and the end user.
The host iPhone will need
to already be enrolled with MDM,
and supervised in order to perform
the watch enrollment flow.
MDM enrollment happens
during the watch pairing flow,
so you will need to begin
with a new or reset Apple Watch.
Existing paired Apple Watches will need
to be reset in order to be enrolled.
The Apple Watch enrollment flow
utilizes declarative device management
so your server will need
to support both Apple Watch
and Declarative Device Management
to enroll Apple Watch.
Check out what’s new this year
in declarative device management
by checking out its session.
Now that we know the prerequisites,
let's dive into the enrollment flow
step by step.
We start with a managed
and supervised iPhone.
First, the organization administrator
will send a new declaration to the phone.
This is the new
Watch Enrollment configuration.
It signifies to the iPhone
that any Apple Watch that pairs to it
should be enrolled into MDM.
Here is the content of that configuration.
Let's take a look at the payload keys.
First is the key
for the enrollment URL endpoint.
This endpoint delivers the MDM profile
that the Apple Watch will download
and install.
The MDM profile for Apple Watch
is just like the MDM profiles already used
for iOS and macOS devices.
The next key,
AnchorCertificateAssetReferences,
is an optional item and specifies
an array of anchor certificates.
These anchor certs will
be used to evaluate the trust
of the enrollment profile server.
Each anchor certificate used
in this flow must be included
in an asset declaration
already present on the iPhone.
Now that the configuration is installed,
let’s bring in Apple Watch.
Like I mentioned, the Apple Watch
will be in its pairing state,
and once
the user initiates pairing from the phone,
they will be prompted
to accept Remote Management.
Here. the user will need
to allow remote management
for their Watch to continue.
If they don’t accept remote management,
the pairing flow will end
without the Watch getting set up.
The enrollment flow for Apple Watch
is designed with security in mind
to address the need to manage iPhone
and Apple Watch together as a pair.
There are two key pieces
to ensure security.
First, the administrator needs
to verify that the host iPhone
is enrolled into an MDM server
managed by their organization.
Secondly, they need to be able to identity
which iPhones and Apple Watches
are paired together.
Let’s see how we accomplish
that with this new enrollment flow.
During Watch pairing,
the iPhone sends information
from its Watch enrollment configuration
to the Apple Watch.
The Apple Watch uses the URL
and any provided anchor certificates
to make initial contact with the server.
Within this request,
it will provide signed machine info.
Upon receiving the enrollment request
from the Apple Watch,
the server will inspect
the machine info data
and look for a new "pairing token" key.
Because the pairing token key
will not be present on this first attempt,
the server will issue
an HTTP 403 response.
Here’s what that 403 response
will look like.
First, the error code tells us
that the Watch pairing token is missing
from the request.
Then, within the details dictionary,
you will provide a security-token.
This random UUID string
will be used by the Watch
to kick off the pairing token
retrieval flow.
The Watch sends
this security-token to the iPhone.
The iPhone performs
a GetToken checkIn request,
which includes
both the phone and Watch UDID,
as well as the security token received
from the Watch’s MDM server.
Here’s what this
new checkin request looks like.
We’ve added a new CheckIn message type
this year called the “get token”
check in request.
This new message type allows
the device to request secure tokens
for various services
the MDM server supports.
The TokenServiceType key indicates
which service
we are requesting a token for.
Here, the value indicates
it needs a Watch pairing token.
Next, the TokenParameters key
is a dictionary
containing parameters specific
to the token service type.
For the Watch pairing token,
the phone includes the security token
from the Watch, its own UDID,
and the Apple Watch’s UDID.
The MDM server takes this information
and uses it to generate
a secure pairing token
that can be verified by the Apple Watch’s
MDM server upon receipt.
Here, the MDM server can create
the correct relationship
between the iPhone and Apple Watch
based on the received UDIDs.
The server finishes by sending
its generated pairing token to the iPhone.
Here’s an example of what that token
response from the server will look like.
The token is in
the form of base64 encoded data.
Upon receipt, the phone sends
the pairing token to the Apple Watch.
The pairing token is then added
into the Watch’s Machine Info,
and sent back to the MDM server
in a new enrollment request.
Here’s an example of
the Apple Watch machine info
sent to the server with
the secure pairing token included.
The MDM server securely verifies
the pairing token it received
with the machine info,
and can therefore confirm the identity
of the iPhone’s MDM server
and the paired relationship
between the iPhone and Apple Watch.
Now the server returns the MDM
enrollment profile to the Apple Watch.
The user will finish the steps on
the phone to complete Apple Watch setup,
and the Enrollment profile
will be installed on the Apple Watch
at the end of the pairing flow.
Just like on iOS,
enrollment is officially complete
when the Apple Watch sends a CheckIn
request with the Authenticate messageType.
And now Apple Watch
is enrolled and supervised!
With this specialized enrollment flow,
you will want to keep a few things in mind
for Apple Watch.
First, when building
your device management solution,
utilize the data sent
to the server during enrollment
to detect which Apple Watch
is paired to which iPhone.
Use this information
to create an intuitive UI
for IT administrators
who will need to identify the pairs.
Keep in mind that once
the Watch Enrollment configuration
is applied to the phone,
all Apple Watches that begin to pair
with the phone will be prompted
to enroll into management.
However, any Apple Watches
already paired to the phone
will not be affected
and would need to be wiped
and paired again in order to be enrolled.
And lastly, remember that Apple Watch
is supervised once its enrolled,
so you can add it to all of your workflows
for organization owned devices.
And just like with iOS,
health information and fitness activity
is never sent to the MDM server.
Now that we know
how to enroll Apple Watch,
let’s talk about how you’ll manage it.
We are starting right out of the gate
with declarative device management support
for watchOS.
In watchOS 10, all declaration types
are supported on watchOS.
Predicates in activation declarations
are supported as well,
so you can build custom multi-step
management workflows right on the Watch.
The status channel has also
made its way to Apple Watch,
so you will be able to receive proactive
updates from all of your Apple devices.
Here’s a look at the declarative
device management features in watchOS 10.
Find the full list of support
in our open source schema
and developer documentation
that has been updated
to reflect availability on watchOS.
Of course, the MDM protocol
is also supported on managed watches.
Payloads, restrictions, and MDM commands
and queries
can all be sent to the Apple Watch,
just as you do today
for your other Apple devices.
There’s a wide range of supported
MDM features for watchOS this year.
Let’s talk about a few of
the available configuration payloads.
First we have our suite
of networking capabilities.
New this year in watchOS 10
is the ability to have a dedicated VPN
installed on Apple Watch.
In addition to our existing
networking payloads,
Wi-Fi and Cellular,
we’ve also brought support
for the per-app VPN payload to watchOS.
Now you can equip all your Apple devices
with access to your secure enterprise VPN.
Next, let's talk about the payloads
you can use to ensure security on watchOS.
The same payloads you already use
to install SCEP and ACME certificates,
enforce passcode rules, and
apply restrictions on your Apple devices
are now all supported for watchOS.
The password policy
and restrictions payloads
both share unique behavior on watchOS.
Let’s cover that now.
Restrictions and passcode rules
that are applied to iPhone
will be synced to the paired Apple Watch.
For example, if you apply a passcode
enforcement policy to the iPhone,
the paired managed Watch
will prompt the user
to create a passcode for it as well.
If an alphanumeric password
is required by the iPhone’s policy,
the user will need to use their iPhone
in order to unlock their Apple Watch,
Like, for instance,
when it's taken off their wrist.
However, both Restriction payloads
and password payloads applied
directly to Apple Watch will
not be synced back to iPhone.
Use this detail in the directionality
of the rules
to customize your restrictions
and password policy payloads
for each platform.
MDM queries are helpful
to learn the current status
of the device and its content.
These queries, of course,
operate in a polling manner,
from the server to the device.
Instead of constantly
polling the Apple Watch with queries,
you should instead use the status channel
of declarative device management.
This way, the Apple Watch
proactively tells the server
whenever a change occurs
to a status item the server subscribes to.
Now, let's turn to commands that
you'll want to consider for watchOS.
The same commands from iOS
are supported on watchOS
to ensure the integrity of the enterprise
data on your Apple Watch.
You can remotely clear the passcode,
lock and erase the device as needed.
Un-enrolling from MDM by removing
the profile is also supported
for watchOS,
but it has different on-device behavior.
Let’s look at that now.
Removing the MDM profile from Apple Watch,
whether by a user or via MDM command,
causes it to be unenrolled
from the server.
When Apple Watch is unenrolled,
it is unpaired from its host iPhone
and its content and settings
are all erased.
Un-enrolling Apple Watch will not effect
the enrollment status of its host iPhone.
Now, if the host iPhone
becomes unenrolled,
whether by the user or the organization,
it will trigger the Watch
to be unenrolled as well.
Therefore, removing management
from the host iPhone
will ultimately result in the managed
Apple Watch being unpaired and reset.
The last piece of the MDM protocol
we will want to discuss is app deployment.
On watchOS, there are
three different kinds of apps.
First, there are Paired apps,
which are watch apps
that share data between itself
and its complementary iPhone app,
but the Watch app can function on its own
in the absence of the iPhone app.
Next, there are dependent watchOS apps.
These Apple Watch apps require
a companion iPhone app to be functional.
And lastly,
there are Standalone watchOS apps.
These apps exist only on the watchOS
platform and have no iOS companion app.
For both the Paired
and Dependent watchOS app types,
administrators will need to manage these
apps together across the two devices.
Standalone watchOS apps
are also supported.
These apps will only need the App Install
command sent to the Apple Watch.
When installing paired and dependent apps
to iPhone and Apple Watch,
the app should
be installed to the iPhone first.
Then, once you ensure
the app installed on iPhone,
send the install app command
to Apple Watch.
When updating Paired
or Dependent watchOS app types,
both the phone and the Watch app will need
to be sent commands to update their apps.
Similarly,
when deleting paired or dependent apps,
the remove command will need
to be sent to both Apple Watch
and iPhone in order
to ensure correct behavior.
Managing paired and dependent iPhone
and Apple Watch apps in tandem like this
will make for the best user experience and
the smoothest workflow for administrators
because it ensures apps are
available and properly managed.
That’s just a small glimpse
of all the things you can do
with managing Apple Watch.
Understanding these best practices
we’ve gone over is the best way to ensure
a smooth adoption and ramp up
of your watchOS management.
Let's summarize some of the key points
now.
Administrators will need to manage iPhones
and watchOS together as a pair,
so make sure your MDM products
are built with this relationship in mind.
Creating combined workflows and exposing
the device relationships in your UI
will help admins keep
the two platforms in sync with each other.
Take advantage
of the proactive status channel
built into Declarative Device Management
to avoid constantly polling the device
for information,
which could be a drain on power.
The Declarative Device Management
status channel will update the server
whenever a meaningful change occurs.
Although there are new considerations
for managing Apple Watch,
the MDM protocol together with the
Declarative Device Management features
are all the same tools
you’re familiar with using already,
so you’ll be able to get started
with managing Apple Watch today.
Let's wrap up what we’ve
discussed today about Apple Watch.
Apple Watch is
now manageable in watchOS 10,
paired to
a supervised iPhone running iOS 17.
Begin implementing your Apple Watch
enrollment and management support
for your MDM solutions today to empower
IT admins and their organizations
to make their enterprise Apple Watch
workflows as easy as possible.
Admins, start planning
how managed Apple Watch
will optimize
your organization’s productivity
and end user’s connectivity
and well-being.
We’re excited to learn about
the Apple Watch workflows
you plan to implement
and how it will improve
your organization's digital ecosystem.
And whether you are the MDM developer
or admin looking to deploy Apple Watch,
we want to hear from you.
Be sure to file feedback requests
at feedback.apple.com.
And finally, check out
our other sessions this week
on declarative device management
as well as everything else that’s new
in managing Apple Devices.
That’s Device Management for Apple Watch.
Thanks for being here today,
and have a great week!