♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Raffael Hannemann:
Hello, and welcome to
Go Beyond the Window
with SwiftUI.
I'm Raffa,
and I'm an engineer at Apple,
and I'm later joined
by my colleague Mark.
Today, we're going to show you
how easy it is to leverage
the full power of xrOS to create
truly immersive experiences
with the tools and frameworks
you already know.
You may already be familiar
with augmented reality
from developing AR apps for iOS.
In the past few years,
we've introduced and extended a
number of tools and frameworks,
including ARKit and RealityKit,
for creating rich AR apps
for iPhone and iPad.
These apps allow you to blur
the line between the real world
and your imagination by
augmenting the user surroundings
with interactive user interfaces
and virtual objects.
This year,
with the launch of xrOS,
we are bringing AR
to a whole new level,
starting with
immersive experiences.
In these experiences,
your application displays UI,
including windows and
three-dimensional content
anywhere around you.
The surroundings remain visible
and, in fact, even become
part of the experience.
You can anchor elements
of your app to surfaces
and augment and enrich
the real world
with virtual objects
and effects.
And then there are fully
immersive experiences,
which go one step further
and cover your entire space.
Your app takes complete control
over what you see.
Think about all the
possibilities this will unlock.
And the best of all,
all of this is possible
with the tools, frameworks,
and patterns
that you are already
familiar with.
And at the core of this
is SwiftUI's Immersive Space.
Let's get started.
In the other sessions,
you've learned that this year,
we are adding the third
dimension to SwiftUI.
You can present windows
and volumes on xrOS
and display three-dimensional
user interface elements
with the easy-to-use
declarative patterns of SwiftUI.
Both windows and volumes
let you display content
within their bounds.
So what if you want to make
the most of the infinite space
that xrOS offers and create
a truly immersive experience?
You may want to place your items
beyond the window's bounds
all around your head and be
right in the middle of it.
And this is what
we've designed Space for.
Next to windows and volumes,
spaces are a kind of container
to present your
user interface on xrOS.
In this session,
we'll focus on Spaces
and how you can use them
to create immersive experiences.
Let's first get started
with Space
and learn how to display
your content.
Mark will then show you
how you manage your Space,
launch directly into a Space,
and explain
all the customizations
that Spaces allow.
So let's get started
and check out some code.
I am really excited
about space exploration.
To continue the World app
that we've been working on
in the other sessions,
we're going to extend
the app step-by-step
with a space that lets us
explore our solar system.
Spaces are a new scene type in
SwiftUI called Immersive Space.
As you would do
with other scene types,
you define an Immersive Space
in your app
and can then open
and dismiss it at any time.
You can make your whole app
consist of only one single
Space,
but you can also extend
your existing app
by adding one or more Spaces
next to your windows
and volumes.
Your app can have one Space
open at the time.
Before opening another Space,
you first dismiss
the current one.
And again, similarly
to other scene types,
you place your view hierarchy
in the body of the scene.
By placing our SolarSystem
in the ImmersiveSpace,
it will be rendered without
any clipping boundaries.
Let's just take a moment
and point out how easy this is.
With just these three lines,
we've brought
our solar system view
into a rich,
immersive experience.
Let's dive into the details.
Having a Space open enables
a couple of special behaviors
that make this scene stand out
from the other scene types.
When multiple apps
are running side by side,
they are all displayed
together in the same space,
which is why we are calling
this the shared space.
Once your app displays
an Immersive Space scene,
your app enters
what we call a Full Space.
Your app will then be the
only one visible to the user.
All other applications
will go away
to make room
for your content to appear
without any distractions.
Later, once you dismiss
your space,
the other apps will reappear.
Since Immersive Space
is a scene,
it implicitly defines
its own coordinate system.
So everything that
you place in a Space
is positioned relatively
to the space's own origin.
And the origin of a Space
is below the user,
close to the user's feet
when the Space is first opened.
So now you know the basics.
Let's move on
and talk about how you display
the content of your Space.
ImmersiveSpace is a scene type,
so you place your
view hierarchy right in it.
An ImmersiveSpace
can take any Swift UI view,
and while it doesn't have
any clipping bounds,
a Space still lays out
its content
within its layout bounds.
Anything you place
in the Space
uses the same layout system that
you are already familiar with.
But since the origin of your
Space is near the user's feet,
you probably don't just want
to put your content down there.
Let's talk about RealityView.
If you want to make the most of
SwiftUI, ARKit, and RealityKit,
we encourage you
to use ImmersiveSpace
together with
the powerful features
of the new RealityView.
ImmersiveSpace and RealityView
go hand-in-hand,
and were specifically
designed together
to provide all the features
you need
for building great
immersive experiences.
For example, RealityView
comes with built-in support
for asynchronous
loading of assets,
as shown here, for loading
and displaying a star field.
But next to
asynchronous loading,
putting a RealityView
in an Immersive Space scene
allows a lot more.
Place elements within your
RealityView on ARKit anchors.
And since your app gains access
to hands and head-pose data,
while a Space is open,
you can use that data
to position your entities
within a RealityView.
Mark will show you
something cool later.
A note about coordinate Spaces.
RealityView uses RealityKit
for displaying its content.
So when positioning entities
within a RealityView,
keep in mind that the coordinate
Space orientation
is different than
in SwiftUI's layout system.
In SwiftUI,
the y-axis points downwards
and the z-axis
points towards you.
This applies to windows,
volumes,
and to Immersive Spaces,
whereas in RealityKit,
the y-axis points upwards.
There is a lot to cover
about RealityView.
Make sure you add "Build spatial
experiences with RealityKit"
to your watchlist
for all the details.
Now let's write some code.
We're going to use the WorldApp,
or at least
a simplified version of it,
and add an immersive
solar system to it step by step.
We start by defining
an ImmersiveSpace.
Similarly to WindowGroup,
you can assign an identifier,
a value type, or both.
In this case, we assign
the solar identifier.
We will use this identifier
later to open the Space.
We then place a SolarSystem view
into the Space.
Let's also define a simple
standard window for our app,
which we want to show up
when the app launches
with a control to view
our solar system.
This is similar
to what the World app does.
So we define a new launch window
using a WindowGroup,
and we add some information
together with a control that
will allow us to open our Space.
That control is just a button.
When clicking it,
we want to change its title
and open our Space.
For controlling windows,
SwiftUI provides the openWindow
and dismissWindow
environment actions.
And for Immersive Space,
we are adding the new
openImmersiveSpace
and dismissImmersiveSpace
actions.
We obtain the two actions
from the environment.
We can then use these actions
when the button is invoked.
When opening the Space,
we pass in the identifier
we defined earlier.
Since only one Space
can be open at a time,
the dismissImmersiveSpace action
doesn't need any argument.
The system animates
your Space in and out
with a certain duration.
These environment actions
are async
so that you can react to the
completion of the animation.
Opening an Immersive Space
may fail,
and openImmersiveSpace
will tell you via its result
whether the call failed
or succeeded.
Make sure to have
proper error handling.
Coming back to our app that
we defined at the beginning,
we can now just add
our LaunchWindow right here.
Notice the order
of our two scenes.
The LaunchWindow is the first
in our list of scenes,
so SwiftUI will display
the launch window
when the app starts.
The Immersive Space
won't be visible at launch,
but will only show up once
the user clicks on our button.
Let's run this on the simulator.
When our app launches,
we get to see the launch window.
And then with just a click
on our button,
the solar system appears
right in our living room.
So now we've defined
a multiscene app
consisting of a standard window
and a Space displaying
our solar system.
You've seen the models
used in the World app.
When building
your immersive app,
you're surely going to want
to display some 3D assets
with a lot of detail
in your Space.
Keep in mind that
it may take some time
for your assets
to be fully loaded
and ready to be rendered
by your app.
For the best user experience,
make sure to leverage the new
Model3D and RealityView APIs,
which load your 3D assets
asynchronously.
In this code here,
we display a text
while the model is still loading
and an error in case
something went wrong.
And now, Mark is going to tell
you how to manage your Space
and even better,
how to launch into Space.
Mark Ma: Thanks, Raffa.
As we just demonstrated,
it was incredibly easy
to integrate Immersive Spaces
into our World app
with just a couple lines
of code.
Transforming your app
into an immersive experience
also involves managing
your Space alongside the system
with scene phases,
coordinate convergence
between your Space
and other scenes,
and presenting it
with different styles.
Similar to other
SwiftUI scene types,
Immersive Space supports
the same scene phases
which are handled by the system.
This also means
your Space is always
in one of SwiftUI's
scene phases.
By opening the Space,
it moves it to the active phase.
And at any point in time,
it may change it
to the inactive phase.
For example, if we step out
of the system-defined boundary
or a system alert shows,
your Space and windows
are hidden temporarily, moving
them to the inactive phase.
Once the user re-enters
the experience,
your Space and windows
will be made visible,
updating their scene phase
to be active again.
For our World app, we can add
a few quick lines of code
to handle the
inactive scene phase.
Let's scale down
our Earth model to half size
to help indicate that the state
of the Space has changed.
Let's also make sure that
we handle the active phase
to restore the contents.
And keep in mind, the Space
can be dismissed at any time
by using hardware
or software means.
So let's check this out
in the Simulator.
We'll open up our Space
and demonstrate how our app
handles the inactive phase.
For example,
this might be triggered
when an alert shows up.
When the alert pops up,
note that the Space content
changed in scale
as a result of our
previous sample code.
And when we dismissed the alert,
the Space scaled back,
reacting to
the now active phase.
SwiftUI makes handling
and animating these transitions
really easy and convenient.
Another great way to manage your
Space is by integrating content
from your other windows
with your Space.
For example, if you want
to reposition the earth model
next to the main window,
we'll need to know
the position of the window
in our Immersive Space
coordinate system,
but both objects define
their own coordinate systems.
So to help resolve this,
SwiftUI provides
a new coordinate Space
named Immersive Space.
And that represents a coordinate
system of an Immersive Space.
To access this
coordinate system,
we encapsulate the window inside
a geometry reader to 3D context.
Then by using the existing API
that takes in a coordinate
space, like transform,
and passing in the
Immersive Space type,
we can get the proxy.transform
in the new coordinate system.
Using this transform,
we'll update the Earth's
position on tap.
Let's run this on the simulator.
We'll reopen our Space
so we'll have our earth
and the main window visible.
We've slightly shifted
the window
and we want to reposition earth
right in front of it.
Now when the earth
gets tapped,
it'll get positioned
to where we expected.
And with coordinate conversions,
it's that easy to position our
content exactly where we want it
and move assets between
the Space and the window.
Other times to
use coordinate conversions
would include Immersive Spaces
in SharePlay,
where we can manage
our content's  position
across not only
a private Immersive Space,
but also a group
Immersive Space.
If your app supports SharePlay
and group Immersive Spaces,
when other participants join,
the system may move
the origin of the space
to a shared location
defined by spatial templates.
For more information,
please check out the session,
"Build spatial SharePlay
experiences."
Our World app
now handles scene phases
and can combine content
from other windows,
but we still have yet to use
the full capabilities
that Space offers.
We'll explore
immersion styles next
to have them become
even more amazing.
Immersion styles offers
different presentations
of how your space content can
take over your surroundings.
You can present your content
alongside a mixed style,
a progressive style
online in front of you,
or a full style that surrounds
you in all directions.
Let's update our app to take
advantage of all these styles.
Let's reopen our app again
and go back to where we defined
an Immersive Space.
Right now, the space presents
the solar system
in a mixed immersion style,
which is the default one.
It's easy to change the style
and also have it be dynamic.
First, let's add
a new state variable
of type ImmersionStyle
and assign a default value
we want the Space to begin with.
Let's keep the mixed style here.
We then use the immersionStyle
scene modifier
and define the list of styles
we want our Space to support.
In order to have a reference
to the current style,
we pass in our state variable
as a binding.
If we pass the binding
to our solar system,
we can also read
the current style
and control it to transition
to any of the map styles.
In this sample, we'll transition
on a magnification gesture
so that as we scale up
the solar system,
we'll go to a different style.
So far, we've been running
our World app on the simulator
to show you how easy it was
to bring an
Immersive Space into it.
But to get a really great sense
of how these styles work
with our surroundings,
let's run our experience
on a device.
And later, we'll show you
even more customizations
that really enhance
your on-device experience.
You open the Space
in the default style,
which results in the
mixed immersion style.
This style is great,
but you might want
to become a bit more
immersed in the content
and maybe see some stars.
So you can perform
the magnification gesture.
And as the content grows bigger,
eventually the Space transitions
into the progressive style.
This style is the bridge between
a passthrough
and fully immersive experience.
It allows you to see the
Immersive Space content
within the portal
that's in front of you,
along with your surroundings.
This style feels
pretty immersive,
but also lets you be aware
of what surrounds you.
This also means you can chat
with people nearby,
know where to sit
to be comfortable,
and even interact
with the surroundings.
And once you're comfortable,
by turning the Digital Crown,
you increase the immersion
of the style.
Isn't that really cool?
Now you're floating like
an astronaut in the galaxy.
And if you want to see more
of your surroundings again,
just turn the Digital Crown back
to decrease the immersion.
This lets you quickly and easily
be in control
of how immersive
the content will be
within the progressive style.
But perhaps you like to be
in full immersion all the time.
This is great for experiences
that surround you
or instantly transport you
to a whole different world.
So far, you've learned
how easy it is
to transition to different
styles based on gestures.
Going to full immersion
is no different,
and you'll experience that
as you scale up the Earth again
to update the style binding.
Notice how easy
and seemless it was
to transition between
the different styles.
Now the Space has
become fully immersive.
And with SwiftUI, it only took
a couple lines of code.
And by pressing
the Digital Crown,
you can go back to passthrough
whenever you're ready
to leave the experience.
We've just demonstrated
different ways
to manage your Space by reacting
to scene phase changes
and controlling the style.
Now let's add some
final enhancements
to take our Space
to the next level.
The spatial computing
capabilities on the device
allows for your Space
to be easily enhanced
to make it feel
even more exciting.
So let's go over
a couple options,
like launching
directly into a Space,
adding effects
to the surroundings,
and virtual hands.
So far, our app allows us
to open a Space
with a click of a button.
But what if you want to launch
an immersive experience
right when your app starts,
like if you have
a fully immersive game?
In order to launch directly
into an Immersive Space,
you'll need to configure
the scene manifest for your app.
Just set the ImmersiveSpace
application role
and the immersion style.
Attach your Space content
as you normally would,
and it'll open right away.
You can also have your app
go back to a window
if the user chooses
to dismiss the Space.
Next, the surrounding effects
preferences allows me
to dim the passthrough
to have the Space content
be in focus even more.
We'd like to have our
surroundings be dimmed
when the Space transitions
to the progressive style.
We set the
preferredSurroundingEffects
modifier to be dark, so when
the solar system appears,
our surroundings will
automatically be dimmed.
The upperLimbVisibility modifier
allows us to hide our hands
while in a Space
that's fully immersive
since no passthrough
is available.
For our world experience,
we'll simply set our preference
to be false when we open
our Space.
And just like that,
we can change the
upperLimbVisibility preference.
Hiding your hands while
in the full emergence style
means we can show
virtual hands instead,
and we'll show some space gloves
in our World app.
Let's start by creating
a new view called SpaceGloves.
Next, we'll add a RealityView
so we can have our gloves
render in our Space.
Then we'll create a root entity
in our RealityView
to add entities to
so they can also be rendered.
Then we'll load
an asset onto an entity
and add it as a child
of our root.
To correctly place the entities,
we'll need to use ARKit
and its hand tracking API,
and we'll also need to start the
hand tracking system as well.
Our next step is making sure
the assets correctly
anchor to our hands.
We'll need to check for
hand tracking anchor updates.
And next,
checking for the hand chirality.
We'll then make sure
the hand asset's transform
is the same as the anchors.
In this example, we also
made sure our assets
have the same joint names
as the one ARKit provides.
This way, we can map the anchor
skeleton joint names correctly
and the glove entity
will automatically
be anchored for us.
So let's go back to where
our Space is defined
and make sure to include
the SpaceGloves view.
That's all we need
for virtual hands.
For more ARKit customization
and in-depth details,
check out the "Evolve your ARKit
app for spatial experiences."
Now let's try these
customizations out on device.
The World experience
starts again,
and the Space will reopen
in the default immersion style.
By using the magnify
gesture on the earth,
the app will transition
into the progressive style.
When the Space opens,
the code will modify
the surroundings to be dark.
You made yourself feel
even more immersed
by utilizing the
Surrounding Effects API
to dim the passthrough.
It was easy to apply
and it's a great way
to focus on the experience.
This is pretty immersive
right now,
but you can take it
a step further
with our next customization.
As our previous
code demonstrated,
when you transition
to full immersion,
your hands will disappear
and the virtual space gloves
will appear
where your hands would be
thanks to hand tracking.
By using RealityView with ARKit
and enabling hand tracking,
you were able to launch into
space like a virtual astronaut,
and it feels really awesome.
With just a couple enhancements
and customizations,
we were able
to turn our World app
into a fully immersive
experience
that took us beyond
the Shared Space.
And now it's up to you to use
the new Immersive Space API
to create experiences
effortlessly,
show them off
with different styles,
and be creative with
the possible customizations.
It's a powerful and easy to use
API that gives you
all the tools necessary
to transform your surroundings
and create new and immersive
experiences.
Thank you for joining us.
♪