♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Dan Golden: Hi, I'm Dan
from the Accessibility team.
I am thrilled
to talk about accessibility
in spatial computing,
alongside my colleague Drew.
In this talk, I'll give you
an overview
of some of
the accessibility features
available on this platform.
Next, I'll dive into
some of the specifics
of what you can do in your apps
to support people
who are blind or low vision.
Then, I'll hand it off to Drew
to discuss motor, cognitive,
and hearing accessibility
in spatial computing.
Let's get started!
We've designed this immersive
platform for everyone.
While spatial computing
experiences are often built
with stunning visual features
and a variety of hand inputs,
that doesn't mean that vision
or physical movement
are required to engage
with them.
In fact, these experiences
have the potential to be
incredibly impactful to people
who are blind or low vision,
have limited mobility,
or limb differences.
For example,
someone who is blind
could interact
with the real world
without having to see
what's on the displays.
Therefore, it's important
to keep people of all abilities
in mind when you're
building out your app,
so that everyone can enjoy
and benefit from them.
At Apple, we recognize
that access to technology
is a fundamental human right,
and this platform
contains the largest list
of accessibility features
we've ever included in the
first generation of a product.
You'll recognize many features
you already know and love,
like Dynamic Type support,
Increase Contrast,
and Spoken Content features.
And we've reimagined our
flagship assistive technologies
specifically for
spatial computing.
We are so excited
about these features,
and as a developer, you can help
by making sure the experiences
that you're building
include everyone.
Let's start by talking about
the ways you can support people
who are blind or low vision
in your apps.
There are a few things
to consider
when discussing
vision accessibility:
VoiceOver support,
visual design, and motion.
Let's start by talking
about VoiceOver support.
VoiceOver is
the built-in screen reader
available on
all Apple platforms,
and I'm excited to say we've
brought it to this one as well.
Drew and I have been working
on a really fun app
called Happy Beam that
utilizes ARKit and RealityKit.
In the app, you make
heart gestures with your hands
to turn grumpy clouds happy.
Let's take a look
at some of the ways
we can improve the VoiceOver
experience in this app.
We've gone ahead
and added VoiceOver
to the Accessibility Shortcut
in Settings > Accessibility >
Accessibility Shortcut,
so that whenever we triple-press
the Digital Crown,
VoiceOver will toggle on or off.
This is a great tool
when we're testing
the accessibility of our app.
Let's open the app
and toggle VoiceOver on
with a triple-press
of the Digital Crown.
♪ Ethereal instrumental music ♪
VoiceOver: Happy Beam.
Choose how you will cheer up
grumpy clouds.
Dan: On this platform, VoiceOver
uses different finger pinches
on different hands
to perform different actions.
By default, you can move focus
to the next item
by pinching
your right index finger.
♪
VoiceOver: Make a heart
with two hands, button.
Use a pinch gesture
or a compatible device, button.
Dan: To move focus
to the previous item,
pinch your right middle finger.
VoiceOver: Make a heart
with two hands, button.
Dan: To activate an item,
pinch your right ring finger
or your left index finger.
[ACTIVATION CHIRP]
Now that we're familiar
with some of
VoiceOver's basic controls,
let's explore
the rest of the app.
VoiceOver: Three, two, one.
[HAPPY BEAM GAME START TONE]
Happy beam. Back button.
Score zero.
Stop music, button.
Twenty-nine seconds remaining.
Pause, button.
Dan: Things are looking
pretty good here.
This app is built using SwiftUI,
so a lot of the standard
controls we're using
are already accessible,
and we've taken care
to adopt SwiftUI's
accessibility modifiers
on the rest of the views
to ensure appropriate
accessibility information
is being provided to VoiceOver.
To learn more, check out our
talks on SwiftUI Accessibility.
Let's take a look
at the rest of the app
and see how we can interact
with the clouds.
VoiceOver: Close, button.
Pop-up. App placement bar.
[DEEP TONE] App placement --
[DEEP TONE]
App placement bar.
Dan: That sound that you hear
indicates that VoiceOver
can't find any other items
to interact with,
so the clouds are
inaccessible to VoiceOver.
The clouds are generated
using RealityKit,
so we can fix this using
the new accessibility component
available in RealityKit.
The accessibility component
allows you to specify
accessibility properties
on RealityKit entities.
You can configure accessibility
labels, values, and traits,
as well as custom rotors,
custom content,
and custom actions.
You can also configure
system accessibility actions,
such as the activate
and adjustable actions.
To make the clouds accessible,
let's start by creating
a new accessibility component,
and then set
isAccessibilityElement to true
to indicate
to assistive technologies
that the cloud
should be navigable.
Next, we'll give the cloud
the button trait,
so that technologies
like Switch Control
and Voice Control
understand that this cloud
is a user-interactive item.
We'll also give it
the playsSound trait,
since the clouds play a sound
when they turn happy.
Next, we can give the cloud
a name via the label property,
and a value describing
its grumpy or happy state.
Any time the state
in your app is updated,
make sure you update
the relevant property
on the accessibility component.
Here, in the didSet handler
of our isHappy variable,
we're using one
of the convenience properties
to update the accessibilityValue
on the cloud.
Any time you use
a convenience property,
the cooresponding property
on the accessibility component
is updated accordingly.
Labels and values are stored
as LocalizedStringResources,
which can be created
using string literals,
but automatically resolve
to a localized value
that you've provided at runtime.
Lastly, we'll set the component
on the entities component list.
Let's take a look at our app
now that the cloud
should be accessible.
♪
VoiceOver: App pl--
Cloud, grumpy. Button.
Dan: Great! We can
navigate to the clouds
and their state
is communicated to us.
VoiceOver uses Spatial Audio
to provide cues
as to where objects are located.
So let's try to make a heart
gesture at one of our clouds
to turn it happy.
♪
What's going on?
We just showed that cloud
so much love,
but it still didn't turn happy.
That's because when
VoiceOver is enabled,
your app won't receive
hand input by default.
This is to ensure that your app
won't inadvertently
perform an action
while someone is performing
VoiceOver gestures,
enabling them to explore safely.
On this platform,
VoiceOver includes
a new Direct Gesture Mode,
and when it's enabled,
VoiceOver won't process
its standard gestures
and instead allow your app
to directly process hand input.
People can choose
to run your app
both in Direct Gesture Mode
and in VoiceOver's
default interaction mode,
and there are accessibility
considerations
to keep in mind in each case.
Let's start by talking about
VoiceOver's
Default Interaction Mode.
Let's add an activate action
so that we can turn the clouds
happy using VoiceOver.
To do this, we'll add
the activate action
to the systemActions property
on the accessibilityComponent.
Then, we'll subscribe
to the activate event
on the content inside
our RealityView.
Any time we receive an activate
event in the callback,
we'll update the game model
so that the state
of the relevant cloud
is updated accordingly.
Let's take a look at our app
again with actions added.
VoiceOver: App placement --
Close --
Cloud, grumpy.
[CLOUD COOS]
Dan: Awesome!
Now we can turn the clouds happy
using VoiceOver.
The AccessibilityComponent
also offers additional APIs
such as custom actions,
custom rotors,
and custom content.
These are great tools
for improving
the accessibility experience
in your app.
To learn more about,
check out our talks
on the corresponding topics.
Next, let's talk about
Direct Gesture Mode.
This is a new way
to interact with apps
while using VoiceOver
on this platform.
VoiceOver's activate action
isn't available
in Direct Gesture Mode, so we'll
need to provide feedback
to the hand-input interactions
that we'll be using instead.
Let's start by posting
an announcement
when the clouds appear,
describing them and
their placement in the world.
To do this, we'll create
a new AccessibilityNotification
with an Announcement type,
pass in the string
we'd like to have spoken,
and then call the post function
on the announcement.
In spatial experiences, it's
critical to provide information
about what items are available
and where they are located,
so this will be a crucial
announcement in our app.
Let's also post an announcement
any time a heart gesture
is recognized
or when a cloud changes
from grumpy to happy.
Always announce any
meaningful event to VoiceOver,
so that it's clear
what is happening,
and what interactions
are being performed.
For example,
in a fully immersive app,
any time you enter a new room
or environment,
make sure to announce that
change in context to VoiceOver,
and describe any new items
that are available in the world.
Also consider utilizing sounds
when actions are performed.
The sounds that play
in Happy Beam
when a cloud turns happy
are a great way
to keep the app feeling
fun and spatial,
even if we can't see the visual
transformation of the cloud.
Let's take a look at our app
one last time
with some announcements added.
When the game starts,
we'll enable Direct Gesture Mode
with a left index finger
triple-pinch and hold.
Then, we can make heart gestures
to turn the clouds happy
and get feedback about
all of the interactions.
VoiceOver: Three, two, one.
Happy Beam.
Three clouds above and in front
of you to the right.
Direct Gestures enabled.
Press the crown to ac--
Casting beam.
♪
[WINNING CHIME]
Grumpy cloud hit.
Hiding beam.
Dan: Awesome!
We received some
great feedback there
about all of the interactions
as they were being performed.
Our app is shaping up to have
some great VoiceOver support.
But there's still
a lot you can do
to support people
with low vision
who aren't using your app
with VoiceOver,
especially if you're building
any custom components
or controls.
Just like on all
other Apple platforms,
make sure your app responds
to changes in Dynamic Type,
especially at the largest
sizes available
in accessibility settings.
Audit your app for any UI
that might benefit
from being laid out vertically
instead of horizontally
at these larger sizes.
Also ensure you're using
at least
a four-to-one contrast ratio
between foreground
and background colors.
To learn more, check out "Make
your apps visually accessible."
In spatial experiences,
anchors can be used
to place content relative
to different anchor points,
such as a hand or a specific
position in the world.
You can also configure content
to be anchored
to the virtual camera,
so that it appears
on the same spot
on the displays.
While you may be familiar
with camera anchors
in Reality Kit on other
Apple platforms,
on this platform,
the content follows your head
as you look around,
which has the potential
to impact people
with low vision differently.
Head anchors should be
avoided and used sparingly,
so that people with low vision
can get closer to content
to read it or view its details.
Additionally, people using
the accessibility Zoom feature
won't be able to easily
position head-anchored content
inside of the Zoom lens,
since the Zoom lens
is also head anchored.
Instead, consider
using a world anchor
or lazily move your content
after a delay.
In the rare cases where
it's absolutely necessary
to use head anchors,
keep the content decorative.
Critical information should
not only be accessible
through head-anchored content.
Always provide alternatives
for head anchors,
even when they might be
the best mainstream experience
in your app.
The new accessibilityPrefers
HeadAnchorAlternative
Environment variable in SwiftUI,
and the AX PrefersHeadAnchor
Alternative API
in the Accessibility framework,
let you know when you should
use alternate anchors.
Observe these APIs anywhere
your app employs head anchors.
We've taken care to adopt this
API in the system ourselves.
By default, Control Center
is head anchored
in its collapsed state.
You can see here that,
as you look around,
Control Center follows you.
While this design makes it easy
to access Control Center
from anywhere,
we knew it might be challenging
for some people.
I mentioned earlier that
Zoom is also head anchored.
This is a feature
that magnifies content
for people with low vision.
When Zoom is enabled or someone
has otherwise indicated
that they prefer alternatives
to head anchors,
Control Center moves
freely about the Y axis.
Here, you can see that,
as you tilt your head up,
the Zoom lens follows your head,
but Control Center does not.
Enabling you
to position Control Center
inside of the Zoom lens
and interact with it.
It's also important
to be mindful
of the usage of motion
in your app.
Motion can be dizzying
for some people,
and wearing a headset can be an
especially jarring experience,
even when subtle
motion effects are used.
Avoid the use of motion
that move a person rapidly
through your app,
or involve a bouncing
or wave-like movement.
Zooming animations,
animations that involve movement
along more than one axis,
spinning or rotating effects,
and persistent
background effects
should all also be avoided.
Always provide alternatives
for these types of animations
when Reduce Motion is enabled.
You can check whether
Reduce Motion is active with the
accessibilityReduceMotion
Environment variable in SwiftUI.
In UIKit, you can query
UIAccessibility.
isReduceMotionEnabled,
and observe changes
to the preference
with the corresponding
notification.
If you're having trouble
finding a suitable replacement
for the motion in your app,
consider utilizing a crossfade.
Here's an example of how
we've adopted Reduce Motion
in the system.
Check out the water here
in the Mount Hood Environment,
as the water persistently
ripples in the background.
When we toggle Reduce Motion on,
the water is changed
to statically show
a ripple effect,
which achieves
a similar visual effect
without requiring
the usage of motion.
That's an overview of some
of the ways you can improve
the vision accessibility
in your apps,
but there's still a lot
to consider when discussing
motor, cognitive,
and hearing accessibility.
And for that, here's Drew
to tell you more.
Drew Haas: Thanks, Dan.
Really great work!
My name is Drew Haas
and I'm an engineer
on the Accessibility team.
Now that we've learned
about meaningful ways
to improve the visual
accessibility
of your spatial experiences,
there is so much I want to share
about how to create your apps
to be inclusive
to people with disabilities
which affect
physical and motor function,
cognition, and hearing.
Let's start first with motor!
The default input system
is driven
by a combination
of eyes and hands.
For example, looking at
a button with your eyes,
and pinching with your hand
sends a selection event
to activate the button.
However, not everyone can
perform these physical actions.
Our accessibility features
provide alternate input methods
for people with disabilities
which impact their use of eyes,
hands, or both.
The Dwell Control accessibility
feature allows people
to select and interact with the
UI without using their hands.
Dwell Control supports gestures
like tap, scroll,
long press,
and drag.
You should design your app
to have full functionality
with this gesture set
so people using Dwell Control
aren't excluded.
It's a breeze to switch
gesture modes
by using the Dwell Control menu,
allowing people to operate
their device
using accommodations
without sacrificing efficiency.
This is by design: giving people
a frictionless experience
even if they're using
nondefault inputs.
Let's see how
our Happy Beam app
is designed to support
a variety of inputs,
which makes it fully playable
using Dwell Control.
When Happy Beam is launched,
the player will first choose
how they'll cheer up
those grumpy clouds.
You saw the first option
earlier in this session:
using two hands
in the shape of a heart
and aiming it at the clouds.
The second option supports
Bluetooth accessories
like keyboards
and game controllers.
When playing with these inputs,
the happy beam is fired
using this heart turret.
The turret also responds
to tap-and-drag gestures,
which means you can play
with one hand.
And, people playing
with Dwell Control
have full functionality
over the turret.
So plan and design for your app
to support different inputs
like Happy Beam does.
This is the best way to ensure
you don't accidentally
exclude people.
There is another
accessibility feature
that works really well
with Dwell.
Enter Pointer Control,
one of my favorite
accessibility features.
This feature transforms
the input experience,
allowing people to use
different input sources
to control the system focus
instead of using their eyes.
Eyes is the default,
but here people can change
the system focus
to be driven by head position,
wrist position, or index finger.
Since Pointer Control
can change the input signal
to follow head position,
remember to use camera-anchored
content sparingly.
This is another reason
you should prefer
to use world anchors
or provide alternatives
to camera-anchored content.
Both Dwell Control
and Pointer Control --
either on their own or utilizing
their feature sets combined --
provide tons of flexibility
with how people
interact with their device.
These features accommodate
the physical requirements
to use the system.
Allow multiple avenues
for physical interaction,
because you never know
what kind of disabilities
someone using your app may have.
Spatial experiences enable new,
dimensional ways
to interact with content.
Switch Control has
new menu options
for adjusting the camera's
position in world space.
Here we're using a keyboard
with Switch Control
to activate the new camera
position modifiers.
This moves your spatial position
downward
without you physically
moving your body.
Not everyone will be able
to move comfortably or freely
in their environment.
While these camera position
options are available
for Switch Control,
if you have experiences
that require people
to position themselves
in certain ways,
provide options to bypass them.
Next, I want to talk about
Cognitive accessibility,
and how you can support people
with disabilities that affect
the way they learn, remember,
and process information.
Guided Access is a cognitive
accessibility feature
that promotes focus
by restricting the system
to a single app.
It aims to minimize distractions
by backgrounding other apps,
removing ornamental UI
which may be distracting,
and by suppressing
hardware button events
that could take someone
out of their experience.
Being able to adjust the system
in this way can make it easier
for someone to stay focused
on their current task,
without distractions or easy
ways to get sidetracked.
To learn more about
how to use Guided Access
and implement the custom
restrictions APIs,
check out my talk
from last year,
"Create accessible
Single App Mode experiences."
By following just a few
best practices
for cognitive accessibility,
you make your app easier
to use for everyone,
but especially people
with disabilities.
Some people need
a little more help
breaking down the complexity
of your app.
Interactions which require
complex hand gestures
can be hard for people
to pick up on and retain.
You can help create a consistent
and familiar visual experience
by using Apple's UI frameworks
like SwiftUI.
This reduces the amount of time
someone may need
to feel comfortable
using your app,
because it's likely
they've used other apps
built using the same
UI framework.
And finally, allow people
to take their time
immersing themselves
and experiencing all
that you have to offer.
There is no need to rush people
through an experience.
Immersive content can promote
focus and attention,
which is a fantastic way to
create a comfortable environment
for someone with
sensory processing disorders.
Remember that not everyone
processes information
at the same speed,
so some people may prefer
or need a little extra time
to work through an experience.
Finally, I want to share
some of the best ways
to provide access
and accommodation
to people that are deaf
or hard of hearing.
It's common to use
audio and speech
as a way to immerse people
in a spatial experience.
For people with hearing loss or
auditory processing disorders,
one of the most impactful things
you can do
is provide quality captions
so they can access your content.
A comfortable reading experience
is easy to create
by using pop-on captions --
which render the phrase all at
once and are easy to read --
instead of using
roll-up captions,
which appear word-by-word
and can cause reading fatigue
and nausea when reading
for a long duration.
Did you know that people
can customize
the visual appearance
of captions on their device?
Captions can be
widely customized,
modifying things
like text size, font, and color,
as well as stroke outlines
or backgrounds.
These options allow people
to customize their captions
so they're easy to see and read.
AVKit and AVFoundation
provide built-in support
for supplying captions
in your app.
These frameworks
automatically handle
the caption appearance
and visual style.
If you are not
using AVFoundation
because you're implementing
your own captions system,
there are two APIs
that you should know about.
First, the
isClosedCaptioningEnabled API.
Use this to check whether
someone already has
Closed Captions turned on
in Accessibility settings.
If you have separate
caption settings in your app,
you should use this API
to inform the default state
of captioning.
This way, people who rely
on captions
get access to them right away.
The second can be found in the
Media Accessibility framework,
which has APIs to access each
style attribute individually.
You should check these styles
and apply them to your captions
to keep a consistent
reading experience
across the entire system.
No matter which way you choose
to provide captions,
you should have a high standard
for their quality.
Captions should represent
all audio content,
including music
and sound effects.
It's also helpful to indicate
where in space
the audio is coming from
if directionality
is important to your experience,
basically telling the user
to "keep in mind, the nearest
audio source may be behind you."
An impressive
accessibility experience
comes from considering
all people and their needs.
Provide rich RealityKit
experiences
by setting accessibility
properties on your entities.
This is the foundation
for your app's accessibility
for technologies like VoiceOver,
Voice Control,
and Switch Control.
Be flexible and provide options
for physical interaction
like we saw in Happy Beam
to include all players
and their play styles.
Strive to remove ambiguity
and provide clarity
and focus for people
with cognitive disabilities,
and spend time and care
on captioned content
for audio experiences
so that people that are deaf
or hard of hearing
can enjoy your creation.
If you're not sure
where to start,
turn on some of these
accessibility features
and open up your app!
Trying out these features
for yourself
is a great way to dive right in.
This platform is designed
for everyone,
and with all
of the considerations
Dan and I have shared today,
you are equipped
to create accessible and
inclusive spatial experiences.
Thank you!
♪