♪ ♪
Razvan: Hello!
I'm Razvan, an engineer
on the WebKit Developer Experience team,
and I'm here to tell you
about some of the new features
and improvements we've made
to Web Inspector this year.
Web Inspector is part of Safari on macOS,
and it provides a powerful set of tools
that allow you to inspect
all the resources and activities
of a website, web app,
web extension, or home screen web app.
I'm excited to show you
some of the new features and improvements
we've added since last year,
like new typography inspection tools,
a way to emulate user preferences,
new badges for elements with
event listeners and scroll containers,
and we've improved
the JavaScript debugging experience
with enhancements to breakpoints.
If you haven't used Web Inspector before,
you'll have to enable it.
Open the Settings window of Safari
and switch to the Advanced tab.
At the bottom, you'll find the setting
to "Show features for web developers."
Click the checkbox to enable this.
The Develop menu
is now available in the menu bar.
You can open Web Inspector using
the menu item called Show Web Inspector
or by pressing the keyboard shortcut
Option+Command+I on any web page.
This year, we've made many improvements
to all of the developer features
in Safari,
including a streamlined way to pair
and inspect web content on devices,
a quick way to open
a web page in a Simulator,
a refreshed Responsive Design Mode,
and many others.
To learn more, watch this session titled
"Rediscover Safari developer features"
from this year's WWDC.
Now that Web Inspector is enabled,
let's start by looking at the new tools
for typography inspection.
Web developers use custom fonts
to create beautiful content
with type that is both legible
and makes it stand out.
But getting typography on the web
just right is not always easy.
First, the right font file
needs to be loaded.
It must be in a format
supported by the browser
and with the right features.
And it should include the right glyphs
for the characters
of the written language
it's going to represent.
Then, there are many CSS properties
that influence the way
a font renders on screen.
And most of them are inheritable
through the cascade,
sometimes leading to confusion,
like, "Which font face was actually used?"
Or "Why is this bold?"
Or "Is this style really italic?"
Web Inspector can help with a host
of typography inspection tools.
You can find them in the Details sidebar
of the Elements tab, in the Font panel.
It shows properties and capabilities
of the font used on the selected element,
such as the name of the primary font used.
You can reference this to quickly check
if the font you expected was indeed used.
Keep in mind that this only identifies
the primary font.
If the selected node includes characters
for which the primary font
does not have glyphs,
a fallback font will be used for those.
Next, the Font panel shows
a summary of the basic font properties,
like font size, style,
weight, and stretch.
There's also a section that shows
the supported font feature properties
and their used values.
These toggle special aspects
of a typeface such as ligatures,
small caps
instead of lowercase characters,
special numeric styles, and many others,
depending on what the font supports.
New this year,
the Font panel shows warnings
for synthetic bold or oblique styles.
What's a synthetic style?
Let's take italic as an example.
Italic styles are often supplied
in their own font files,
separate from the ones
for the regular upright styles.
When a suitable italic style is missing,
WebKit generates
an artificial representation for that.
It runs an algorithm
over the regular upright font style
and skews the individual glyphs
to produce an oblique style.
This is called a synthetic oblique.
Font designers pay a lot of attention
when crafting italic styles.
Often, these aren't slanted versions
of the upright style,
but instead they're cursive,
specially designed
to convey a particular aesthetic.
Something similar happens
for synthetic bold,
where the stroke of the glyphs
is made artificially thicker.
Keep in mind
that not all fonts support this.
Web Inspector now displays a warning
when a synthetic bold or oblique is used.
It shows up
next to the synthesized weight or style
in the basic properties section
of the Font panel.
This warning can be a hint
that the expected font file
was not loaded.
But sometimes, it may be
that the font file just doesn't support
the exact values you asked for.
That's where variable fonts can help.
What's a variable font?
Put simply,
it's a font format that can include,
in a single file,
all the information needed to generate
multiple style variations for a font,
such as weight, width, slant, and others.
And for each supported style,
variable fonts provide
a spectrum of values
compared to just a few discrete values
in static font files.
This gives you a lot more flexibility
to choose the exact style
that's right for your content.
Variable fonts are even more capable.
A font designer can make almost
every aspect of a font configurable,
from the thickness of the stroke,
the curves of the glyphs,
the width of the characters,
and many others.
The possibilities really are vast.
All aspects of a variable font
that can be configured
are expressed as variation axes.
To know which are available,
you'd either have to read
the font's documentation
or use a special tool
that reveals this information.
Web Inspector can help here.
When you inspect an element
that uses a variable font,
the Font panel shows you a list
of the supported variation axes.
For each, it shows its axis tag--
a four-character identifier--
an optional axis label,
the supported minimum and maximum values,
as well as the current value,
or the default value
if one is not specified in CSS.
This year, we added interactive controls
to edit the values of variation axes
and see the results
live on the inspected page.
This gives you a great way to tweak
the font styles until they're just right.
Let me show you.
Here's a web page I'm building
for a travel photography blog.
I have the layout just as I want,
with a photo gallery
and navigation by labels,
but I'm still not sure
about the look of the title.
I'll right-click
to inspect the heading element.
In the Font panel, I can see
this is using a variable font.
I can tell because I have these controls
for the available variation axes
that I can play around with.
For example,
I can drag the slider for the Weight axis.
This immediately changes the font weight
of the title live on the inspected page.
Notice how the corresponding
CSS font weight property is written
to the Styles panel.
A static font would have
just a few font faces for weight
in increments of 100.
But with a variable font,
I can chose any value
within the range of the variation axis.
Let's also try the variation axis
for Width
to see how this looks wider or narrower.
I can also type
in the axis value input field
or I can hold the ArrowUp
or ArrowDown keys
to change the value in precise increments.
I like this slightly condensed version.
I'd like it a bit bolder,
but I want it to keep this width.
This variable font also provides
a custom variation axis
to change the Grade of the font.
When I drag the slider for this,
notice that the individual characters
get thicker in-place
without shifting position like they did
when I changed the Weight axis.
This looks nice.
To integrate these changes
back into my project,
I can copy the new CSS properties
from the Styles panel
or from the Changes panel.
We've seen how to inspect typography
and how to tweak font styles
with variable fonts.
Now, let's move on
to another new feature in Web Inspector
that allows you to
emulate user preferences
so you can make sure
the content you're building
adapts to user needs.
All Apple products offer
a variety of settings that allow people
to configure their devices to adapt
to their needs and preferences,
like the Accessibility settings on macOS
which control things
like the built-in screen reader,
VoiceOver, or Display preferences,
which control reduced motion,
increased color contrast,
color filters, and many more.
One of the most popular things people do
on their devices is to browse the web.
So it makes sense
to build websites and web apps
that strive to welcome everyone.
To do that,
you sometimes need to experience the web
the same way other people do
when they set user preferences.
To test your website with, say,
the preference for reduced motion,
you could go to the Accessibility Settings
on macOS and set it there.
But that will influence the entire system,
not just Safari and your website.
What you often want is to set it
just for the page you're testing.
To help you with that,
we've introduced a new tool
in Web Inspector
to emulate user preferences.
Click the new icon in the Elements tab
to reveal the User Preference Overrides
popover.
Here, you'll find a set of toggles
to override user preferences
just for the inspected page
while Web Inspector is open.
These preferences map
to CSS media features
which you can use to adapt the style
and behavior of your web page.
For example,
the preference for color scheme
maps to the prefers-color-scheme
media feature in CSS.
Here's how to use it:
you can set an element's styles
for the default light color scheme.
Then, use the prefers-color-scheme
media feature
to check
if a dark color scheme is preferred
and update the styles.
Check how the page adapts by using
the User Preference Overrides popover.
In the Appearance section, override
the color scheme preference to Dark.
The icon changes color
to indicate an override is applied.
The styles for the dark color scheme
will be applied
while the override is active
and Web Inspector is open.
This control for color scheme
used to be a standalone button.
It now joins the other controls
for preference overrides in the popover.
Next, I'm going to show you
how to override the preference
for reduced motion.
This next section displays
an animation with a lot of motion.
If you are sensitive to this,
you may want to skip
the next three minutes of this video.
Back on my page, these animations that run
when I click on a photo to enlarge it
are perhaps a bit too much.
Some people can get disoriented by
animations with quick and sudden motion,
particularly when it happens
on the z-axis.
It can cause discomfort,
like nausea or headaches.
This is definitely not
a welcoming experience for them.
People can set the preference
for reduced motion on their devices
to signal that they want
websites and web apps to adapt.
Us web developers should respect that.
This is where the prefers-reduced-motion
CSS media feature is useful.
If the animation is just for decoration,
you can remove it.
But remember, some animations are useful
to convey meaning in an interface.
Removing them can affect usability.
A slower and more subtle fade animation
may still work well
to communicate change
and also satisfy people's needs.
Let's try that change on my web page.
First, I'll inspect the photo
and select the figure element
in the Elements tab of Web Inspector.
This reveals all its matching CSS rules
in the Styles panel.
Here's the CSS property that sets
the animation with a lot of motion.
It runs for everyone now.
Next, I'll click on the source code
location of this CSS rule
to jump to where it's defined
in the stylesheet.
This opens the Sources panel
and puts me right next to that CSS Rule
which has the animation I want to change.
I'll uncomment this block of code
I prepared earlier.
It's guarded by a prefers-reduced-motion
CSS media feature.
Here, I change the animation to a fade,
instead of the one that zooms the photo,
and I also increase the animation duration
so it doesn't feel as sudden.
Now I'll click again on an image
on the page to see how that looks.
Oh! It still runs the same animation.
That's happening
because I defined the new animation
guarded by the prefers-reduced-motion
media feature.
But the page still respects the default
system value for this preference,
which is set to Off.
Let's adjust that.
I'll click back to the Elements tab.
Here, I'll open
the User Preference Overrides popover.
In the Accessibility section,
I'll open the popup menu
to override the user preference
for "Reduce motion."
I'll change it from the default value
on my system and set it to On.
Now, I'll click again
on a photo on my page.
And look.
The photo now slowly fades into view.
No more disorienting movement.
This is a better experience
for those who prefer reduced motion.
I'll remember to integrate these changes
back into my project.
The last item
in the User Preference Overrides popover,
"Increase contrast," maps to the
prefers-contrast CSS media feature.
Ideally, you want to build content
that has a high level of color contrast
for everyone.
But if your design system constrains you,
use this media feature
to adapt your styles for people
who benefit from increased contrast.
Then, check that the styles
on the inspected page adapt accordingly.
Override the preference
for "Increase contrast" to On.
We hope you use these features
to build content
that even more people can enjoy using.
Next, I want to tell you
about the new element badges
in the Elements tab of Web Inspector.
In the node tree view of the Elements tab,
you can already see badges
next to elements that act
as CSS Flex or CSS Grid containers.
Element badges provide a quick way
to identify at a glance
nodes of particular interest.
In this case, nodes that create
a CSS Grid or Flex layout context.
You can click on the grid
and flex element badges
to toggle the specialized page overlay
for that node.
The highlight color of the badge
matches the color of the page overlay.
The CSS Grid and Flexbox page overlays
show guides that reveal the lines,
gaps, and the available space
which determine the layout.
To learn more about how to debug
CSS Grid and Flexbox layout
with page overlays,
watch these sessions from previous years.
One of the trickiest CSS layout issues
to debug is unwanted scroll,
like a container that scrolls horizontally
because the content inside it
doesn't fit the available width.
This type of issue can lurk undetected
for a long time
when scroll bars are not visible
by default.
To help you identify unwanted scroll,
we've added a new element badge
that shows up next to scroll containers.
It provides a quick visual hint
in the node tree
when an element's content
overflows its bounds
and a scroll bar is applied.
Let's look at a common example
of unwanted scroll and how to fix it.
Back on my page, I see these labels
at the top of the photo gallery
appear be nicely laid out
to use all available horizontal space.
But when I try to swipe,
I notice there's a short horizontal scroll
in this container.
This is something I don't want.
And the last label is slightly cut off.
It gets even worse
when I resize the window.
In the node tree in the Elements tab,
I notice there's a "scroll" badge
next to the container for the labels.
I'll click this element to reveal
its matching CSS Rules
in the Styles panel.
This Flexbox container looks right.
How about its flex items,
the labels themselves?
This overly precise value for
the minimum-width property looks strange.
It was probably my naïve attempt
to tell the browser exactly what to do
instead of telling the browser what I want
and letting it do the math.
To fix this, I'll comment out
this minimum-width declaration.
Now, each label takes up
as much space as it needs.
But there's a lot of unused space left.
To fix this, I'll add a flex property
with a value of 1.
This distributes the unused space
to each of the labels
so they fill up the container.
And there's no more
unwanted horizontal scroll,
as confirmed
by the now missing "Scroll" badge
next to the container in the node tree.
Next, I'd like to tell you
about the new Event badge.
It appears next to elements
which have JavaScript event listeners
attached to them.
It works both for built-in events,
like pointer or UI events,
as well as custom JavaScript events
that you dispatch in your code.
Look for elements with the Event badge
next to them in the node tree
and click on the badge to show a popover
with all the event listeners
attached to that element.
Here, you can get an overview
for each event listener:
the event type,
the name of the JavaScript function
which handles the event,
and the location in the source code
where that function is defined.
The various configuration options
for the event listener,
like whether it bubbles
through the DOM tree
or if it's automatically removed
after running just once.
Then, there's the option
to disable the event listener
so you can debug your code
without it running.
Or if you want to debug it step-by-step,
you can set an event breakpoint for it.
This will pause JavaScript execution
next time the handler is invoked.
This is a good time to talk
about the improvements we've made
to the debugging experience
with breakpoints.
When debugging JavaScript,
you may be used to adding
console.log() statements to your code.
Breakpoints, on the other hand,
are a powerful way to debug
by pausing and stepping through JavaScript
without having to make changes
to your source.
If you haven't used breakpoints before,
the easiest way to start
is by clicking on a line number
on a script file
in the gutter of the Sources tab.
This sets a JavaScript breakpoint
on that line of the script.
Next time that line is about to run,
Web Inspector will instead pause
JavaScript execution at that point.
While paused,
you can observe the call stack,
inspect the state
of objects and variables in scope,
and even make changes to them
through the Console.
You can resume JavaScript execution,
or you can step through the code
one expression at a time,
using the stepping controls at the top.
You can configure a breakpoint
by right clicking on it
and selecting Edit Breakpoint.
Here, there are many options you can set
to control when the breakpoint is hit
and even run actions when it does.
Let's look at a few of them.
You can control when a breakpoint is hit
by setting a condition for it.
This evaluates as JavaScript
in the same scope
where your breakpoint is set.
When the condition is true,
the breakpoint will hit.
Sometimes, you may find it easier to skip
the breakpoint for a number of times.
For example, while inside a loop
where you're not interested in stopping
for the first few iterations.
Here, you can set the number of times
to ignore the breakpoint.
You can also run actions
when a breakpoint is hit,
like evaluating a piece of JavaScript.
This runs in the same scope
where the breakpoint is set.
You can use this to modify the state
of your script before continuing.
You can also log messages to the console
with expressions that have access
to the state of variables and objects
at the moment when JavaScript was paused.
This is similar to adding
a console.log() statement to your code,
but without having to modify your source.
Instead of logging variables
and objects to the console,
you can also use
the Probe Expression action.
This allows you to inspect
the state of the given expression
in the details sidebar panel
of the Sources tab.
Of course, these actions are very useful,
but sometimes you just want to run them
without actually stopping
at the breakpoint
and having to resume manually.
In those cases,
use the option to automatically continue
after evaluating expressions.
This option makes the Log messages action
behave like a console.log() statement:
it logs, but it doesn't pause.
Likewise, you can evaluate
some JavaScript at the breakpoint location
and continue as if it were
already in your source code.
There are many other types
of breakpoints you can set.
Click the Plus button
in the Breakpoints section
to show a list
of all the breakpoints you can set,
such as URL Breakpoints that trigger
when a network request is about to be made
via methods like fetch()
or XMLHTTPRequest,
event breakpoints like the one we saw
earlier from the Event badge for "click,"
breakpoints that trigger when micro tasks,
animation frames,
timeouts, or intervals are handled,
and new this year,
we've added Symbolic breakpoints
to pause before
a function is about to be invoked.
Symbolic breakpoints are helpful
to debug calls
to built-in JavaScript functions
or to pause in multiple functions
with the same name.
When adding a Symbolic breakpoint, you can
be as specific or as generic as you want.
Either match the function name exactly,
including case sensitivity,
or use a regular expression
if you want to break at multiple functions
that match the pattern,
or if you don't quite remember
the complete function name.
Let's see how Symbolic breakpoints
help debug a problem I have in my code.
Each photo on my page has
a share button that lets me share
a link to it with friends.
But I've received a bug report
that the URL they get
doesn't point to the photo page.
Let's investigate.
It's been a while since I worked on this,
and I don't quite remember how it's built.
There are multiple ways to debug this,
but I'm going to try
a Symbolic breakpoint.
I'll switch to the Sources tab
and click to add
a new Symbolic breakpoint.
Whatever code runs on my end,
it has to eventually call
the navigator.share() browser API
which shows the system popover.
Let's set a breakpoint
before the share() function is invoked.
I'll click away
to set my Symbolic breakpoint.
And now I'll click the share button
on a photo on my page.
And look, Web Inspector has paused
before navigator.share() is invoked.
I'll hover over the data object
passed to this method.
Here, I can see
the contents of the object.
It seems the value for the URL key
that gets shared is indeed wrong.
Where does this come from?
In the Call Stack section
of the Sources tab,
I can see the chain of functions
that were called to get to this point.
Looks like the click event handler
was called before.
I'll select its entry in the Call Stack
to jump to that function.
Here, I can see the code
that builds the data object
which gets passed
to the sharePhoto() function.
And by the look of the code comment here,
I meant to implement this, but I forgot.
Let's fix that now.
I'll click to set a breakpoint
on this line.
Then, I'll right-click
and select Edit Breakpoint.
I don't need to set a condition,
but I'll configure it
to run a JavaScript action.
Inside the expression field,
I'll modify the data object
to fix the url property before it gets
passed along to the share function.
I don't need this breakpoint to stop here,
so I'll click the option
to automatically continue
after evaluating this expression.
Next, I'll click the button
to resume JavaScript execution.
Now, when I click the share button,
the Symbolic breakpoint I set earlier
is reached again.
But now the data object it gets
has the right URL value.
The JavaScript action
from the other breakpoint
modified the value and sent it along
to this function without pausing.
This confirms that the change I made there
does indeed fix the issue.
This was just one example
of the many great debugging workflows
enabled by breakpoints.
There are so many more,
and I encourage you
to try them out in your projects.
We've covered a lot in this session,
from the new typography inspection tools,
to overriding user preferences,
using the new element badges,
and we looked at breakpoint enhancements.
And that's just scratching the surface.
There are many other new features
and improvements
in Web Inspector this year
that we didn't have time to cover
in this session.
And there's so much more
that Web Inspector can do.
If you want to learn more about these
and the many other features you can use,
go to webkit.org to find
in-depth blog posts and documentation.
We'd also like to hear from you.
If you encounter an issue or have ideas
for how we can improve Web Inspector,
please let us know
by filing an issue on WebKit's bug tracker
for the Inspector product.
I'd also like to encourage you
to download Safari Technology Preview.
It is released every few weeks
and contains the latest tools
and technology in WebKit,
as well as bug fixes and improvements,
before these reach
the next version of Safari.
Before I go,
if you want to learn more about what's new
for developers in Safari this year,
check out these great sessions:
"Rediscover Safari developer features"
and "What's new in CSS."
Thanks for watching.