♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello!
I'm Harlan,
and I work on SwiftUI.
I'm thrilled to help you
make your windowed app
truly spectacular
on this new spatial platform.
With spatial computing,
your apps exist
within your physical
surroundings,
which enables whole new classes
of stunning three-dimensional
experiences.
And as with every
Apple platform,
the best way to build
an app is with SwiftUI.
SwiftUI has added a suite
of APIs and behaviors
that take advantage
of everything
this new platform has to offer.
If you haven't already,
watch "Meet SwiftUI
for spatial computing"
for an overview
of all the new ways
you can use SwiftUI
on this device.
I'll be focusing on SwiftUI but
if you're working with UIKit,
there's a lot you can
take advantage of too.
Check out "Meet UIKit
for spatial computing"
to learn how to make the best
UIKit experience possible.
If you have an existing
iPhone or iPad app
and you'd prefer to retain
your iOS experience, check out
"Run your iPad and iPhone apps
in the Shared Space."
Whether you're bringing an app
from another Apple platform
or making something brand-new,
SwiftUI is the best way
to make your app feel at home
wherever it runs.
In this session, we'll update
a SwiftUI app for this platform.
We'll begin by exploring
how the built-in controls
automatically adapt themselves
for legibility and interaction;
we'll talk about how to ensure
your custom views and controls
take advantage of the new
visuals and input techniques
on this device;
and we'll adopt
some brand-new features
that are only possible
with this device.
This platform was built
from the ground up
with SwiftUI in mind.
In fact, most of the system
applications
are written with SwiftUI,
like Keynote,
Freeform,
and TV,
which all bring
their familiar interfaces
right into your surroundings.
Even though these apps
look similar
to their iPad counterparts,
they take full advantage
of the new design language
and interaction methods
on this platform.
Let's explore how you can do
the same with your apps
by updating
an iPad app together.
This is Backyard Birds, and it's
like a virtual birdwatching app,
where you can feed
and record all the birds
that visit your yard.
As a Swift developer,
I love birds.
This is my kind of app.
Backyard Birds
is written in SwiftUI.
It's a great example
of a multiplatform SwiftUI app.
It supports iPhone, iPad,
Mac, and Apple Watch.
I'd like to add one more
platform to that list.
Let's make Backyard Birds
really sing in the Shared Space.
First, make sure your app
supports this new platform
by adding it in the Supported
Platforms menu in Xcode.
This will add a new
run destination,
so let's choose that and run
our app in the simulator.
Here in the simulator,
when I move my cursor around,
the app responds as if I was
looking around with my eyes.
When we run Backyard Birds,
we immediately find
that it has the same
basic layout as on iPad,
but some things
appear a little different.
The first difference
I notice is that the app
now has a glass background.
Glass is a standard background
provided to windows by default.
It adjusts its contrast
and color balance
based on lighting conditions and
the colors of objects behind it.
Because of that, this platform
does not make a distinction
between light
and dark appearances.
Glass automatically ensures
your app stays legible
no matter where you're using it.
Let's explore Backyard Birds
some more.
Backyard Birds has a navigation
split view at the top level,
which provides this sidebar
for switching between
top-level views.
The sidebar automatically
darkens its background on top
of glass to visually separate
itself from the detail view.
When I hover the cursor
over these list rows,
they highlight subtly.
I can tap on these rows
to switch between views,
just like on iPad.
On the right side of the split
view is a navigation stack.
When I tap on one
of the backyards,
it navigates
to its details view.
From here I can see
how much seed and water
is left for the birds
in this yard.
I can scroll down to see
a list of all the birds
that have recently visited.
The navigation bar has
these circular buttons
that also highlight
when I look at them.
When I press
the Favorite button,
it scales down and then
toggles the favorited state.
These are just a few of
the things that SwiftUI has done
to enhance every app
for the Shared Space.
Now that we've taken a stroll
around Backyard Birds
and found some of the new,
automatic behaviors
that the built-in
controls offer,
let's investigate how we can
make our custom views
and controls feel at home.
I spotted something subtle
while we toured
the Backyards list.
If I get really close
to the app,
the bird and plants
remain crisp,
but the fountain
becomes a little blurry.
I suspect the fountain is being
drawn at a fixed resolution.
Apps on this device are placed
in your physical surroundings.
And unlike other platforms,
there's no screen
with physical pixels
that defines the quality
at which your content can draw.
Apps could be
positioned anywhere.
They might be pushed
far away from you,
or brought right up close,
or even viewed at an angle.
The system ensures
that apps look great
in all these situations by
scaling content dynamically.
For the system to do that,
you must provide vector assets
because bitmaps cannot be
scaled without reducing quality.
Text and SF Symbols
are already vectors,
but if you're using
custom icons or graphics,
use vectors to take advantage
of dynamic content scaling.
Let's check if that fountain
is a bitmap image.
Ah, if I look at
the scales option,
it's specified in
individual scales.
Thankfully, I have a vector
for this asset already,
so I'll switch it
to a single scale,
remove the existing assets,
and replace it with my vector.
Then I'll check
the Preserve Vector Data box,
which allows the contents
to scale to any size.
This setting is supported
on all Apple platforms.
That's better.
Now the fountain is sharp,
and if I move closer
or further away,
it stays at high quality.
Let's poke around
some of the other tabs.
The Plants tab shows
a grid of all the plants,
and these circles
behind the plants
look bright and out of place.
If we inspect the code,
we find our answer:
the background is a solid color.
Solid colors like this one have
a fixed contrast against glass
and can't adjust
to your surroundings.
There's a check here to use
a slightly darker color
in Dark Mode, which is
a common practice on iOS.
This platform reports
its color scheme as dark,
so this is the color
we see behind the plants.
But remember, this platform
doesn't distinguish
between light and dark
color schemes.
Instead, the best way to make
sure your content is legible,
regardless of what's coming
through glass,
is to adopt vibrancy.
Vibrant materials introduce
additional contrast
and brightness to ensure
that content on top of glass
remains legible no matter
what's shining through.
All of the built-in controls
and containers
use these vibrant materials
by default,
so if you're using
standard controls,
there's no extra work
for you here.
SwiftUI's semantic styles
automatically adopt
an appropriate appearance
on each platform.
On this device,
they look vibrant
when placed on top of glass.
If you're building your own
custom views or containers,
use these semantic styles
to make your content legible
no matter how glass adapts
to your surroundings.
Let's change these plant icons
to use a semantic fill color
rather than a solid color.
Since we're using
semantic materials,
we can remove the color
scheme check altogether.
Now the code is simpler and
more correct on all platforms.
Wow, these icons
are much better.
They pop beautifully
against the glass
in every lighting condition.
Now that we've spent some time
improving the visuals
in the app,
let's make sure all
the interactive components
are clear and easy to target.
As you learned in "Meet SwiftUI
for spatial computing,"
there are four ways you can
interact with your apps.
The most common interaction
is an indirect pinch gesture,
where you look at a control
and pinch your fingers together
to perform a tap.
If an app is close to you, you
can directly interact with it
just by reaching out
and touching it.
If you've paired a trackpad,
you can use it as a pointer
for precise input.
And the world-class
accessibility technologies
that you're already familiar
with on Apple platforms
are also available
on this device.
Tools like VoiceOver and
Switch Control enable everyone
to have the same great
experience using your apps.
On this platform,
interactable content
is highlighted
using hover effects.
For example,
when you look at a control
like a button or a list,
a subtle highlight effect
over the view's bounds
makes it clear
that you can interact with it.
These hover effects are crucial
to making your app
feel responsive.
They give people confidence
that the view they're looking at
or reaching for is the view
that they'll interact with.
Hover effects are
added automatically
to all system controls.
If you use the built-in controls
provided by SwiftUI,
you'll get these effects
in your app for free.
I noticed a missing hover
effect on the Birds tab
of our app.
I can tap on one of these birds,
but there's no visual indication
that I can do that
because there's no hover effect.
Whenever you make a control that
responds to gestures like taps,
it should probably
have a hover effect.
You can add one using
the hoverEffect() modifier.
By default, the hover effect
is a highlight,
meaning it will brighten
when you look at the control.
With our new hover effect,
it's clear that I can interact
with these controls,
but the hover effect
has these sharp corners,
and I think they'd look
a little better rounded.
I can provide a custom shape
using the contentShape()
modifier,
with hoverEffect as the kind.
The hoverEffect() modifier
reads this content shape
out of the view
that it modifies.
There, that feels much better.
The hover effect is clear
and has a bit of padding
and nice rounded corners.
However, I think there's
more that we can do.
In SwiftUI, if a control
performs an action
in response to a tap,
it's likely that the control
should just be a button.
Let's change the bird view
to a button.
Buttons are bordered
by default on this platform,
but I don't want these buttons
to have a background
when I'm not looking at them.
I'll make this a plain button,
so it gets
a standard hover effect but no
background or internal padding.
Perfect!
These buttons have
a standard hover effect,
and they scale down
when they're tapped.
Hover effects were built
to preserve privacy.
These effects are performed
by the system
outside of your app's process.
System hover effects are
the only way to make your app
react to where
people are looking.
Your app is only told when
someone pinches their fingers,
directly touches your app,
or hovers their finger
or pointer over your controls.
After all these changes,
I'd say Backyard Birds
is looking pretty good.
But by making some small
changes to our layout
and adopting some features
unique to this platform,
we can really take to the skies.
Let's talk about some
of the top-level layout.
On iPad, when a window's
horizontal size class
is regular,
a sidebar is preferred
over a tab view
because it makes better use
of the increased width.
On this device, however,
your windows are not tied
to the size of a screen,
and controls are not required
to live inside your window.
Consider using a tab view to
switch between top-level views.
When using a tab view,
the tab bar is attached
to the left side of your app,
like the one here in Photos.
When you look at
one of the icons,
it automatically expands
to show each tab's label.
Let's go ahead and switch
from a navigation split view
to a tab view.
[KEYSTROKES]
I'll make a view
for each screen in the app...
[KEYSTROKES]
...and give it a tab item
with a title and icon.
[KEYSTROKES]
Nice!
The tab bar is collapsed
when you're not
interacting with it,
and the app now has much
more room for its content.
Notice how the tab bar
sits outside of the window
instead of within it.
This kind of attachment
is called an ornament.
Ornaments are positioned
outside the boundaries
at the edges of your windows
and are a great place
to put additional controls
that you want
alongside your main content.
In addition to the tab bar,
Photos has a toolbar
at the bottom that lets you
control the time ranges
shown in your library.
These kinds of ornaments
are so common,
you can add one automatically
with the .toolbar modifier
using the bottomOrnament
placement.
Toolbar ornaments provide
a glass capsule background
automatically.
I have an idea for an ornament
to add to Backyard Birds.
I try to keep an eye on how
much water and seed
I've left out,
but if I'm running low,
I'd like to be told that
a feeder needs a refill.
You can build this kind
of custom ornament
using the ornament() modifier.
The attachmentAnchor
determines where in your app
the ornament will be attached.
I could put my notification
on any edge of my app window,
but I want to align it
to the bottom.
The contentAlignment
parameter lets you choose
what part of your ornament is
aligned to the attachmentAnchor.
I'd like to put the center
of my ornament
at the bottom of my app.
Because you have more control
over the contents
of a custom ornament,
SwiftUI does not give them
a glass background by default.
If you do want one,
you can use
the .glassBackgroundEffect()
modifier
on the ornament's contents.
Now when there's not
enough water or seeds
in any of my yards,
I'll get this message
at the bottom of my app,
and I can tap on it
to navigate to that yard.
I love it!
Because SwiftUI automatically
adapts to the platform
it's running on,
it was simple to make
Backyard Birds
feel at home
in the Shared Space.
You can follow
the same steps in your apps.
Add hover effects
to interactive controls,
use vector assets
and vibrancy for legibility,
and make ornaments
for auxiliary controls.
There's still so much more
that you can explore
that's only possible
on this platform,
like volumes for 3D content
and Immersive Spaces
for spatial experiences.
Check out "Take SwiftUI
to the next dimension"
and "Go beyond the window
with SwiftUI"
to learn how to expand your app
beyond its window.
Thanks and happy coding!
♪