[dreamy upbeat music]
♪ ♪
Roman Efimov: Hello, everyone.
My name is Roman Efimov,
and I’m an Engineer on the Shortcuts team.
Today, I'll be covering some exciting new
features and enhancements in App Intents,
helping you create even better apps.
First, I'm going to start with widgets.
As you know, widgets have become
an increasingly important part
of the iOS user experience.
And now, App Intents and widgets
work seamlessly together
to provide new experiences
through interactivity and configuration.
Next, I'll move on to
the improvements in developer experience
that we made this year.
I will cover some quality improvements,
such as framework support,
as well as some recent enhancements
to static extraction.
And finally, I’ll dive into updates to
the Shortcuts app integration
with App Intents.
We have a pretty packed agenda,
so let’s get started with a couple of
exciting updates to widgets.
First, let's talk about
widget configuration.
When you create a configurable widget,
you can specify the options you want
the person to be able to select
on the backside of the widget.
These options are called parameters,
and you can define them using
the same system that you use
to add support for Siri and Shortcuts
to your app: Intents.
The configuration UI of a widget
displays an ordered list of parameters
that are included in
the corresponding Intent.
Each parameter added to the Intent
is presented as a row in
the widget configuration interface.
In the past, you had to declare
your Intents in Xcode
using an Intent Definition File.
Now in iOS 17,
we have made it even simpler
to define the schema of
your widget's configuration
using App Intents
right in your Widget extension code.
To do that, first, you will need to start
using the AppIntentConfiguration
WidgetConfiguration type
instead of the IntentConfiguration
that you may have used previously
to configure your widget.
Next, define a new type that conforms
to the WidgetConfigurationIntent protocol.
WidgetConfigurationIntent is
a sub-protocol of App Intent,
and you can conform to it directly in
your Widget Extension code.
I've been working on a widget
for my bus schedule app
that displays the time and route of the
next scheduled bus for a particular stop.
This would allow people to quickly check
when the next bus is arriving
without having to open the full app.
I will be using App Intents to provide
the configuration Intent for my widget.
To let users configure
my Next Bus widget,
I'm going to start by defining a struct
that conforms to the
WidgetConfigurationIntent protocol
and includes the following parameters:
a Bus Stop, chosen from the list of saved
stops or by searching for a new stop,
a specific bus Route,
and a Direction of travel
for the selected route.
Once I finish defining the parameters
required to configure my widget,
I'll need to provide dynamic options
for each of the parameter types.
In the past,
providing dynamic options for a parameter
required creating
a separate Intents extension.
With App Intents, I can implement queries
and dynamic option providers
directly within my widget extension,
leading to a cleaner
and more efficient project.
To learn more about
dynamic options providers and queries,
I would suggest checking out
the “Dive into App Intents” video.
Now, let's talk about migrating
your existing widgets
from SiriKit to App Intents.
Migrating your existing widget
configuration to App Intents is easy.
In fact, it can be done with
a single click in Xcode.
Migrating your widget lets you support
both the latest OS version,
and previous versions before you were able
to convert your Widget to App Intents.
Existing configured widgets can
continue working.
Once you no longer need to support
previous OS versions,
you can remove your SiriKit Intent
definition file.
To migrate, navigate to
your SiriKit widget configuration Intent
within your Intent definition file
and click
the Convert to App Intent button.
Xcode will produce App Intents code
that is equivalent to
your old Intent definition.
You will need to ensure that
the schema stays the same,
meaning that all App Intent
parameter names and types
should match what you had
in your Intent definition.
Feel free to add new parameters
to your App Intent.
You can add an optional parameter or even
a required one that has a default value.
Existing widgets,
created before the parameter was added,
will pick up an empty value
for that parameter
or a default value if you've provided one.
If you do plan to support
people on previous iOS versions
and let them use that new parameter,
then you will need to maintain
your SiriKit Intent definition file
and add that new parameter in there,
as well.
Whenever a customer updates your app,
their widget
will get automatically migrated.
It is crucial to test that
the migration goes smoothly,
as your app will only have
one opportunity to do so.
To learn more about migration,
I encourage you to watch
the “Migrate custom Intents
to App Intents” video.
Moving on to interactivity in widgets.
Widgets can now react to
button taps and toggles,
allowing people to adjust settings,
play media,
or access any other
important functionality from your app
right from their homescreen.
In my Next Bus widget, I would like to
make the time buttons tappable.
When people tap one of these buttons,
I want to set an alarm in my app,
ensuring that they know
exactly when to leave,
so they don't miss their bus!
How can I do that?
SwiftUI Buttons and Toggles have been
updated to support App Intents,
making it easy to add
interactivity to widgets.
If you implemented an App Intent before,
you should be instantly familiar with it.
First, I would need to define a struct
that conforms to the App Intent protocol.
Then, annotate any key properties with
the Parameter property wrapper
to let the system know
I need the associated information
to perform the action.
After that, I need to implement
the perform method
that would actually execute the action.
Finally, in my Widget view,
I simply associate my SetAlarm
App Intent with a Button.
SwiftUI integration with App Intents is
not only available for interactive widgets
but also for regular SwiftUI apps.
By consolidating the code
into App Intents,
you can reduce redundancy and ensure
consistent behavior across your app.
Since App Intents serve both
as a configuration
and as providers of interactive actions,
it is quite easy to reuse
the Intent code for Shortcuts.
For example, my ShowNextBus
widget configuration Intent
can be used as both a widget configuration
and a Shortcuts action
that can provide me with
up-to-date information when I need it.
In addition, the App Intent I used
to add interactivity to my widget
also serves as a great Shortcuts action,
allowing people to set the alarm
for their preferred bus arrival time.
To learn more about Widget Interactivity,
check out “Bring your widget to life”.
Let’s move on
to several advanced techniques
that can enhance the functionality and
design of your Widget configuration.
First, let’s talk about enhancements to
Dynamic options and queries.
Dynamic options is an interface
for providing the available values
for a parameter of your App Intent,
and it can be implemented by conforming to
DynamicOptionsProvider
or EntityQuery family of protocols.
In some cases, you may want to
show options that are only available
when a certain condition based on
the value of another parameter is met.
For example, in my widget configuration,
I want to display only the route options
that are available
based on the Bus Stop parameter.
To do that, I can use a new API in iOS 17
called IntentParameterDependency.
It is a property wrapper that lets you
access parameters from your Intents,
within a DynamicOptionsProvider or Query.
You can read these parameters
and use them to create
more dynamic and context-aware options.
In my example,
I return the available bus routes
filtered by the user's selected bus stop.
IntentParameterDependency works in
all environments,
such as Widgets, Shortcuts,
and Focus Filters.
In my example,
I have a struct called BusRouteQuery
that conforms to the EntityQuery protocol.
This struct has a property called
ShowNextBus, which is wrapped with
the IntentParameterDependency
property wrapper.
This means that the Bus Route query
has a dependency
on the showNextBus App Intent,
specifically on the bus stop parameter.
Notice the suggestedEntities method.
It returns an array of
suggested Route objects.
It first checks if the showNextBus
Intent property is non-nil.
If so, it filters the available routes
so that the person will only see routes
that match their specified bus stop.
IntentParameterDependency can
also depend on multiple parameters.
For example, in my direction query,
I want to rely on
both the bus stop and route parameters
to provide the direction options.
You can also depend on multiple
App Intents within the same query
or dynamic options provider.
My direction query reads parameters
from two Intents:
ShowNextBus and ShowFavoriteRoute.
The IntentParameterDependency
property wrapper is used to
specify the dependencies on the busStop
and route parameters
for ShowNextBus Intent,
and the route parameter for
ShowFavoriteRoute Intent.
The route computed property
returns the value from
either showNextBus or showFavoriteRoute,
depending on which one is available.
Widget Configurations
often have array parameters.
For instance, my Favorite Routes widget
can display the bus schedules for
a person's favorite routes.
However, due to limited screen space,
a person should be able to select
only up to three routes.
So how can I declare that?
New in iOS 17, you can now declare
the size when defining an Array parameter.
The size here can also accept a mapping
from the widget family to the array size
since sometimes larger widgets can
accommodate more items than smaller ones.
Once I have defined
my Widget Configuration App Intent
and its parameters,
I might want to define which of these
parameters are shown to the user and when.
ParameterSummary defines
the visual representation
of an App Intent’s parameters.
It powers the appearance of
your App Intent in the Shortcuts editor,
Focus Filters,
and now in Widget Configuration.
You can use parameter summaries
to define which parameters are shown
and in what conditions.
For Widgets, the UI will first show
the parameters in the Summary sentence
and then any additional parameters
listed in the closure.
Here, the sentence contains
the routes parameter,
and the closure has includeWeatherInfo,
so they're displayed in that order
in the configuration UI.
New in iOS 17, you can now use
the When statement with the widget family,
allowing your widget configuration
to change based on widget size.
For example, I want to display the toggle
that shows weather information
only in large widgets, while other sizes
will not have this capability.
So I add the includeWeatherInfo parameter
to the Parameter Summary,
only for large widgets.
Otherwise, for small widgets, I won't
add it, so the parameter is hidden.
Now that I've implemented configuration
for my widget using App Intents,
how do I determine what happens
when the person taps on it?
The person is taken to my app
whenever they tap anywhere in my widget.
I would like to take them directly to
the screen that shows information
about the specific route that they
selected in their widget configuration.
When a person taps your widget
and your app is launched,
you can get the associated
configuration Intent
by calling the widgetConfigurationIntent
method on the user activity.
Once you have the App Intent, you can use
it to update your app's UI accordingly.
Here, I extract the content from
my Configuration Intent
and use it to navigate my app
to the specific bus stop view
for the corresponding stop and route.
When you build a widget,
you'll want to make sure
people see it at just the right time
in their Smart Stacks.
To do that, you can use
the new RelevantContext APIs
for Widget suggestions on iOS and watchOS.
Drawing inspiration from
the previous INInteraction,
INDailyRoutine,
and INRelevantShortcut APIs,
we have designed the new
RelevantIntentManager and RelevantIntent,
to be more Swift-friendly and
work seamlessly with App Intents.
Imagine a sports app that wants to
surface its widget during games.
With the new RelevantContext API,
you can specify this Intent
and its relevant date range.
By providing
this relevant date information,
the sports app widget will automatically
be suggested within the Smart Stack,
ensuring that people have easy access
to the game information
when it's most important.
Relevance APIs are also great for
surfacing your watch complications.
To learn more about
the watchOS side of relevance,
check out "Build widgets for
the Smart Stack on Apple Watch."
Now that we've covered Widgets,
let’s dive into
the developer experience improvements
that we’ve made in iOS 17 and Xcode 15.
We’ll start with Framework Support.
If your app requires the ability
to perform App Intents
from both the main app
and an App Intents extension,
you currently need to compile
your App Intent code into both targets.
Unfortunately,
this approach leads to code duplication,
which can introduce maintenance issues
and increase the likelihood of errors
or inconsistencies.
This also bloats the binary size,
which can negatively impact
the app's performance
and download times for people.
In iOS 17 and Xcode 15,
frameworks can now expose
App Intents directly,
so there's no more need to
compile your code twice.
You can now use the AppIntentsPackage APIs
to recursively import dependencies
in your app.
By conforming types to
the AppIntentsPackage protocol,
both your app and frameworks can
re-export metadata from other frameworks.
I'm going to use framework support
to simplify
the implementation of my Bus Schedule app.
I have a framework called
BusScheduleIntents
that provides various App Intents
for viewing bus schedules.
It makes itself available for re-exporting
without any dependencies.
I have another framework
called BusScheduleUI
that provides custom interface elements
for the Bus Schedule app.
This framework depends on and re-exports
the BusScheduleIntents framework.
Finally, I import the BusScheduleUI
framework from my Bus Schedule app.
Since the AppIntentsPackage is a protocol,
I can make my SwiftUI App struct
conform to it.
The Bus Schedule app only needs to mention
its direct dependency
on the BusScheduleUI framework.
I can now create a SwiftUI button
within my Bus Schedule app
that displays my favorite bus route
by performing the ShowSchedule App Intent.
The same App Intent, ShowSchedule,
is also available to Shortcuts users,
which means that
they can create custom Shortcuts
to quickly access their favorite bus route
schedules without even opening the app.
Moving your App Intents into Frameworks
helps make your codebase simpler
and more streamlined.
The new framework support is
especially great
when building Widgets with App Intents,
since you might need to access
the same Intents
from both your app,
and your Widget extension.
One more tip on keeping
your App Intents code more modular:
you can now create
an AppShortcutsProvider
and define App Shortcuts in
your App Intents extensions.
Previously, you had to define
your App Shortcuts
entirely in your main app bundle.
This would mean that your app is
always launched in the background
when an App Shortcut is run.
Now you can define your App Shortcuts
in an App Intents extension.
This is great for performance because you
can optimize your App Intents extension
to come up faster than
your entire main app
and avoid bringing up UI, analytics,
or other non-critical code.
All these features rely on
static metadata extraction enhancements
that we've made in Xcode 15.
So let's talk about how
App Intents content
is statically extracted
while your code is built.
The Swift compiler outputs information
about the types available in your code,
as well as type-level
and some value-level information
from your App Intents implementations.
Another tool then parses this information
to generate a Metadata.appIntents
directory in your built product,
which contains files describing
your App Intents, parameters,
entities, queries, and more.
In Xcode 15, the static extraction process
has been significantly improved.
It is now faster, more reliable,
and works in more cases than ever before.
When building your apps with Xcode 15,
if Xcode is unable to statically extract
something it expects,
you will now see error messages
directly in the Xcode editor,
along with line numbers, so you know
where to go and fix the problem.
Before we talk about
Shortcuts integration,
there are two more great abilities
we've added to App Intents this year
which are worth mentioning.
First up, is the ability to continue
the execution of an Intent in your app,
even if that Intent was previously
running in the background.
We call this the
ForegroundContinuableIntent protocol.
For example, if my App Intent
that fetches the next bus
fails to retrieve the bus schedule due to
invalid parameters or connectivity issues,
I could ask the person to continue in
the app to resolve the issue.
To do that, first, I conform my App Intent
to the ForegroundContinuableIntent
protocol.
The ForegroundContinuableIntent protocol
is designed for Intents that
initially start their work
in the background
but may need to request continuation
in the foreground.
Next, I call the
needsToContinueInForegroundError method,
which returns an error to me.
When I throw that error, the system stops
performing the App Intent
and asks the user to continue execution
in the foreground.
I can also provide
an optional continuation closure
that will be executed on the main thread
to update my app's state
after it comes into the foreground.
Here, I'm using this closure
to navigate my app to an error screen.
Use needsToContinueInForegroundError
when you want to stop the Intent execution
and require action to continue,
like in the previous example.
We have another API you can use if you
want to continue executing the App Intent,
instead of stopping it entirely.
For that case, call
the requestToContinueInForeground method.
I might use this when
the bus app detects that
a bus route is having a maintenance issue,
and I want to present a custom UI in
my app to choose an alternate route.
Once the person has chosen the route,
I can return that updated route from my
app and continue the App Intent execution.
This time, instead of throwing an error,
I'm simply calling a method
with try and await.
The closure passed in can return a value,
which I can get back within my perform.
That allows me to continue executing
the App Intent
after getting input from the user.
Here, I take the alternate route
the user has chosen
and return a snippet
showing the next bus for that route.
In summary, use the throwing method
when you want to completely stop
the execution of App Intent.
Otherwise, if you want to get a result
from the person
and use it to complete
the App Intent's perform,
use requestToContinueInForeground
and await its result.
This year, we've also added support
for Apple Pay to App Intents.
You can now initiate
an Apple Pay transaction
directly within your perform method.
Using Apple Pay in your perform is simple.
I'm going to create
a PKPaymentRequest instance
and configure it
with the necessary information.
Next, I use
PKPaymentAuthorizationController
to present the Apple Pay payment sheet
and handle authorization.
A guard statement checks if
the controller is presented successfully.
If not, I return a dialog with
"Unable to process payment."
Otherwise,
the payment is processed successfully.
Finally, let's dig into
a couple of updates to integration
between App Intents and the Shortcuts app.
Let's start with all the different places
in the system
where App Intents is integrated.
App Intents is a modern way
to build Shortcuts actions,
and App Shortcuts make it easier
to discover and use
your app's functionality with Siri
and the Shortcuts app.
There's also integration
with Focus Filters
and the Action button
on Apple Watch Ultra.
In iOS 17, App Intents have become
even more widely accessible
thanks to the integration with
Interactive Live Activities,
Widget Configuration and Interactivity,
and SwiftUI.
App Shortcuts have grown too,
to include support for
Spotlight Top Hits and Automations.
All these integrations mean that
the same App Intents code
can be reused in lots of different ways.
Since App Intents are now deeply
integrated into key system components,
it's very important to ensure that
the App Intents you create
are being good citizens.
Providing a good parameter summary is
crucial to ensure that
your App Intents look great
when they are surfaced across the system.
Write your parameter summaries
so that they read like a sentence,
with optional parameters
tucked beneath the fold.
The system will then determine
the optimal visual representation
for your parameter summary
based on the context.
While it's desirable for your App Intents
to work well everywhere,
there might be cases where
you need to make App Intents
for use within your app
or in an interactive widget,
and you want to hide them from
other parts of the system.
For example, when an App Intent invokes
a local function in your app
that would not make
a useful Shortcut action.
In that case, you can set
the isDiscoverable property
on your App Intent to false.
I am going to add a refresh button
to my Next Bus widget
that will retrieve the latest data
from the server.
While it serves a purpose in my widget,
it doesn't make a useful Shortcuts action.
Since I only want this App Intent
to be used from my interactive widget,
I will set isDiscoverable to false for it.
Note that App Intents marked as
undiscoverable
cannot participate
in App Shortcuts either.
The Intents in my app perform
pretty quickly,
but not all Intents do.
This year, we introduced a new way for you
to provide progress for
long-running Intents.
To report progress,
simply make your App Intents
conform to
the ProgressReportingIntent protocol.
Inside the perform() method, you can
access the provided progress object.
Update the progress by
setting the totalUnitCount
and incrementing the completedUnitCount
as your Intent execution advances.
The Shortcuts app will now
automatically display
the progress of your App Intent execution.
Implementing progress reporting is
particularly important for
long-running Intents.
It is really valuable for people to have
that feedback,
so they know the perform of the Intent
is moving forward,
and when it might complete.
This year, we've also improved how
your app can integrate with Find actions.
Shortcuts users love being able
to find content within your app
by specific criteria,
with actions like Find Notes.
The outputs of these actions can be
sent on to other Shortcuts actions,
like sending an email,
enabling lots of powerful workflows.
In iOS 16, you could automatically
get a Find action for your app
by implementing an EntityPropertyQuery,
declaring the criteria you want users
to be able to specify.
Starting with iOS 17,
you can now also use
the EnumerableEntityQuery protocol
instead.
It's really simple and easy to adopt.
Implementing EnumerableEntityQuery
is as simple as returning
all the possible values for your entity
in the allEntities() method.
Shortcuts and App Intents
take it from there,
automatically generating find actions.
The difference between
EnumerableEntityQuery
and EntityPropertyQuery
is that with EntityPropertyQuery,
we send you, the developer, the criteria,
and you run the search
on behalf of the user.
That means you will often return
a limited set of results.
With EnumerableEntityQuery,
you give the framework
all the possible entities,
and Shortcuts does the filtering.
Because it returns all the entities,
EnumerableEntityQuery is
really simple to use,
but it's also optimized for
a small number of entities.
It works well for cases,
such as Safari's Tab Groups,
but is not suitable for
a large number of entities,
which would be typical for the Notes app.
It is also not suitable for very large
entities that take up a lot of memory.
In this case, use EntityPropertyQuery
so you can run the search on your end,
instead of returning
all the possible entities at once.
Lastly, I want to tell you about
some updates to IntentDescription.
This is the type you use to fill out
the Shortcuts UI
people see when tapping the details button
to get more information on your action.
IntentDescription includes description
text, category name, and search keywords.
In iOS 17 the Intent Description type
has been updated
with a new property
called resultValueName,
so you can provide a more descriptive name
for the output of your action.
Here, "Add Reminder" provides
a resultValueName of "New Reminder"
for the reminder that it has created
and returned.
When the "Add Reminder" action here
is connected to the Show Result Action,
the parameter in the Show Result action
shows that name: "New Reminder."
To provide a resultValueName, just use
the new initializer on IntentDescription.
Starting with iOS 17, you can also include
an Intent description
for your Find actions that are generated
using the EntityPropertyQuery or
EnumerableEntityQuery protocols.
To do this, simply adopt
the findIntentDescription property
within your query types.
If you categorize your actions
with categoryName,
this will let you display
the generated Find actions
under your desired category in
the list of actions supported by your app.
To summarize, App Intents
are a great way to expose functionality
of your app to the system
and to your users.
To learn even more about how
you can turn your App Intents
into App Shortcuts
so people can use them right away,
I suggest you check out the "Spotlight
your app with App Shortcuts" session.
This year, App Intents enable you to build
configurable, interactive widgets
and live activities,
and provide an even smoother
developer experience,
with deeper integration
into the Shortcuts app.
I'm truly excited to see
how your apps can leverage
the new App Intents technologies
to surprise and delight.
Thanks for joining me.
[upbeat dreamy music]